<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069011eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
N° 6
1955
(8th year)
Price : 7d (U. K.)
30 francs (France)
TWISTED
IMAGES
How nations see each other
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
As others see the European
1 m
r-
Mum*
;Sv
/
Two recent exhibitionsin the Berkeley Galleries, London, and in the Rijksmuseum Voor Volkenkunde,
Leiden, Hollandbrought together remarkable displays of sculptures of European subjects as seen
through the eyesand in the artof artists in Africa, Asia and America. The exhibits ranged from a
30 feet high wooden carving of a man dressed in cloth and hide hat from the African Ivory Coast, to an
eight-inch high figure of Queen Victoria. Photos on this page show: (I) Britain's Field Marshall Lord
Kitchener, a stately, aloof and elegant figure from Africa. (2) European with telescope, a I 9th century
Japanese ivory carving. (3) Englishman on horseback, a wooden carving from East Africa. (4) Naval
Officer and Boat Crew, West African carving. (For photos of other sculptures, see pages I 4 and 15.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
* KO Courier
4 wiNjow grin ON ml igiu
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
Number 6 - 1955
8th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 TAKE OFF ON INDIAN STEREOTYPES
5 PICTURES IN OUR HEADS
Twisted ¡mages of foreign nations
By Otto Klineberg
10 AS OTHERS SEE THEM
An Englishman takes a closer look at Americans
By D.W.Brogan
14 BETTER UNDERSTANDING THROUGH FOREIGN
LANGUAGES
By Henri Kerst
16 WHAT A FRENCH VILLAGE THINKS OF THE
FOREIGNER
A Unesco-sponsored survey
By Lucien Bernot and René Blancart
20 MORE HARM THAN A THOUSAND WORDS
Stereotyped national images in cartoons
By Gilbert Gadoffre
OTHER ARTICLES AND FEATURES
23 THE SUDAN
A land changing faster than the people
By Alexander Shaw
27 I95S : BIG YEAR OF DECISION FOR TV
By Henry Casslrer
30 ART RENAISSANCE FOR ECUADOR'S INDIANS
By Lilo Linke
32 YOUTH VOLUNTEERS ACROSS THE FACE OF
INDIA
By Hans Peter Müller
26 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris I 6, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
Circulation Manager
Jean Greffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted maybe reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-; $ 1.50 or 300 French fri
or equivalent (U.S. edition $ 2.50)
MC. 55.1 92. A
COVER PHOTO
The picture or the image that one nation
makes of another necessarily recalls the dis¬
torting mirrors in a fun house at best.
(USIS photo taken In the Musée Grévin, Paris)
Nothing could be more evident than the fact explicit in
the columns of every popular newspaper that if the
peoples of the world are to learn to live together in
peace they need to know one another better. As matters stand,
each of us has oversimplified, stereotyped concepts of other
peoples. These concepts are usually erroneous, out of date
and, all too frequently, negative in character. This is not
the kind of material with which to build mutual understand¬
ing and tolerance If people are to get along together in
peaceful co-operation, our stale, distorted images of others
need to be replaced by more accurate views. Progress from
national stereotypes to international understanding is one of
the fundamental conditions of modern life.
Children in particular need to be the focus of attention;
their education and personal development should be free of
prejudiced mis-information about their fellows in other parts
of the world. A hundred years ago it was relatively unimpor¬
tant (though never negligible) that dietary quaintnesses the
French living chiefly on frogs,* the Chinese on birds' nests, the
British on beef, the Germans on beer and similar mistaken
irrelevancies formed a large part of a child's knowledge of
other countries. At that time the was wide, and rela¬
tively safe. It has now become a small, and more dangerous
neighbourhood. If the children of the future are to become
citizens in the best sense, they have to know other peoples not
as creatures of a different species but as they really are.
The question has often been raised as to whether national
stereotypes play any important part in international relations.
For example, the American stereotype of the Germans before
World War I, and even between the two world wars, was a
relatively favourable one and yet this fact did not prevent
the outbreak of hostilities between Germany and the United
States. On the other hand, the American stereotype of the
Turks was for many years rather unfavourable and unflatter¬
ing, yet the relations between these two countries since World
War I have remained free of hostility. Granting all this, we
still have no right to draw the inference that stereotypes are
unimportant.
At the most, we can say that they do not by themselves
alone determine whether or not war will occur. It is not only
possible, but even highly probable, that unfavourable stereo¬
types concerning a particular nation constitute a fertile soil in
which hostility may be more easily developed, although the
specific outbreaks may be precipitated by other factors.
It might be argued with considerable plausibility that the
opinions held by Hitler concerning the fighting qualities and
the powers of resistance of the Russians and the British were
in part responsible for his decision to run the risk of fighting
on two fronts.
A good case might be made for the view that if Hitler had
recognized the real qualities of his enemies, instead of being
misled by false and inadequate stereotypes, he might have
made very different decisions, and the whole course of history
might have been affected thereby. This analysis is admittedly
speculative but it is sufficiently plausible to be used as an
argument in favour of the notion that the existence of such
stereotypes may play an important part in determining acts
which lead to, or away from war.
Demagogues and dictators have shown their awareness of
this fact. As a consequence they have manipulated existing
stereotypes in order to whip up war fever, or they have used
oratory and the mass media to develop stereotypes which
would facilitate warlike preparations against an alleged
enemy.
Unesco recognizes the fundamental importance of stereo¬
types in international relations. Since 1949 it has undertaken
a series of investigations and studies as part of a direct attack
on the problems of both national and racial stereotypes. It
is hoped that this issue of the unesco courier will contribute
in the same direction.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FAITH PATIENCE
SYMPATHY
'Take off on
Indian stereotypes
It is only lately that cartoonists in
India have begun to use the rich
raw material in the life that goes
on immediately around them as the
basis for humorous cartoons. Uni¬
versal subjects like the unmana¬
geable wife and the impatient suitor
are popular in India. These cartoon¬
ists use another well-worn gag
Indian lovers employing the "rope
trick" to reach the balconies of
their Juliets. Western humorous
cartoonists use the same rope and
the same fakir to poke gentle fun
at Indians or to represent their
national stereotype. Various ways
in which they do so are shown in
the drawings on this page by the
Indian cartoonist, A.M. Abraham,
who has neatly " turned the
tables" on his Western colleagues.
CHARITY
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955'
Pic
our
by
Otto
Klineberg
Like certain stero-
type pictures In our
heads, this photo,
printed upside
down, offers a de¬
formed ¡mage not
immediately discer¬
nable.
(Photo Luc/en Hervé, Paris)
About a year ago I was in London at the invitation of
British psychologists and sociologists in order to lecture
on "National Stereotypes". Throughout the preceding
day, during which I was undoubtedly made more sensitive by
my preoccupation with this topic, I kept running into exam¬
ples of such stereotyped thinking.
In my hotel, I heard someone say, "Oh, she has that
Scottish stubbornness, you know". A book review in a
newspaper used the phrase, "With true Gallic wit". At the
theatre that evening, during the interval, I caught part of a
conversation in which a pretty girl said to her escort, "I know
that all Americans have a 'line' " ; and in a mystery story
that I read before retiring, there was a reference to "typical
German thoroughness".
These are all instances of those "pictures in our heads"
to which Walter Lippman gave the name of stereotypes.
They are typical of the ease with which most of us generalize
about national or ethnic groups, usually without even stop¬
ping to think where such "information" comes from, and
whether it represents the truth, the whole truth, or anything
like the truth.
There are certainly very few, if any, among us who have
not succumbed to the temptation to stereotype nations. One
might almost describe the tendency as inevitable, or at least
very nearly so. We know that Englishmen are reserved, and
Irishmen pugnacious ; we have heard it all our lives ; be¬
sides most people agree with us. If we are asked, however,
how we know, we would not easily find a suitable answer.
One of the earliest careful studies of this tendency was
made by Katz and Braly, in 1932, in connexion with the
stereotypes held by Princeton University students. The
technique was simple.
Each student was given a list of traits, and a list of
nationalities ; from the first list he chose the five traits
which he regarded as characteristic of each national or
racial group.
The results showed a fair degree of unanimity, e. g. out of
100 students, 78 described the Germans as "scientifically
minded", and 65 described them as "industrious"; 53 students
used the adjective "artistic" for the Italians ; the same per¬
centage described the English as "sportsmanlike" ; 79 agreed
that the Jews were "shrewd" and 54 stated that the
Turks were "cruel"; 84 regarded Negroes as
erstitious", and 75 described them as "lazy".
sup
(Cont'd on
next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PICTURES IN
OUR HEADS
(Cont'd;
W I s ted i m ages of nations
We may summarize the results in a
slightly different manner by indicating
the three or four characteristics most
commonly ascribed to each nationality.
These included, for the Germans: scien¬
tifically-minded, industrious, stolid ;
the Italians, impulsive, artistic, passion¬
ate ; Negroes, superstitious, lazy,
happy-go-lucky, ignorant ; the Irish,
pugnacious, quick-tempered, witty; the
English, sportsmanlike, intelligent, con¬
ventional ; the Jews, shrewd, mercen¬
ary, industrious ; the Americans, in¬
dustrious, intelligent, materialistic, am¬
bitious ; the Chinese, superstitious,
sly, conservative ; the Japanese, intelli¬
gent, industrious, progressive ; the
Turks, cruel, religious, treacherous.
A recent study of the stereotypes of
German students
at the Free Uni¬
versity of Berlin
by Sodhi and
Bergius showed a
similar willing¬
ness to stereotype
nations and, on
the whole, com¬
parable results.
Americans, for
example, were
described as
sportsmanlike,
democratic, ma¬
terialistic; the Italians as warmblooded,
musical, light-hearted; the Chinese as
poor, inscrutable, modest; the Germans
as conscious of duty, loving their
homeland, intelligent; the English as
proud of their nation, bound by tradi¬
tions, sportsmanlike. There were some
variations between the German and
the American stereotypes, but on the
whole the overlapping is considerable.
On a more extensive scale, a study
conducted in 9 countries under the aus¬
pices of Unesco in 1948 and 1949, show¬
ed that such stereotyped thinking
could easily be elicited almost any¬
where. In each country approximately
1,000 respondents, representing a cross-
section of the population, were given a
list of 12 traits, and asked to choose
those which they thought were most
applicable to themselves, to Americans,
to Russians, and in some cases, to two
or three other national groups as well.
They could choose as many of the
traits as they wished.
The British, for example, thought of
Americans as primarily progressive,
conceited, generous, peace-loving, in¬
telligent, practical. The Americans re¬
garded the British as intelligent, hard¬
working, brave, peace-loving, conceited
and self-controlled. The Norwegians
described the Russians as hardworking,
domineering, backward, brave, cruel
and practical. The full results can be
found in the volume by Buchanan and
Cantril, "How Nations See Each Other".
(1).
The "self-image" is also revealing.
The British saw themselves as peace-
loving, brave, hard-working, intelligent;
the French saw themselves as intelli¬
gent, peace-loving, generous, and brave;
the Americans saw themselves as peace-
loving, generous, intelligent and pro¬
gressive. All the groups agreed on one
item: their own nation was the most
peace-loving of all!
The most peace-
loving nation?
Our own, of course
(11 See
page 8.
"Books for understanding other peoples".
Few people realize how much the
existence of stereotypes may colour our
relations with other people, even to the
extent of seeing them differently as a
result. Psychologists have long known
that our perceptions of the external
world, and particularly of human
beings, are determined not only by what
is out there , but also by what is in
ourselves. What we see is determined
in part by what we expect to see. If
we believe, for example, that Italians
are noisy, we will have a tendency to
notice those Italians who are indeed
noisy; if we are in the presence of some
who do not fit the stereotype, we may
not even realize that they, too, are Ita¬
lian. If someone points that fact out
to us and says: "Look, those people are
Italians, and they
are not noisy",
we can always
dismiss them as
exceptions.
Since there is
no limit to the
number of cases
that can be so
dismissed, we may
continue to cling
to the pictures in
our heads, in
spite of all the
facts to the con¬
trary. This does not always happen.
Stereotypes do sometimes change in
the light of new experience, and evi¬
dence for this is presented later. If we
have had them for a long time,
however, we surrender them with great
reluctance.
A number of significant investigations
have shown in a very dramatic manner
how our stereotypes may determine our
perceptions. Some years ago Allport
and Postman, psychologists at Harvard
University (Cambridge, USA) studied
some of the phe¬
nomena associat-
ed with the-
spread of ru¬
mours, making
use of a tech¬
nique known as
"serial reproduc¬
tion", a very sim¬
ple device which
anyone can use
with a group of
friends in his own
home. They
showed a picture
to one student, and he described to
a second student what he saw in the
picture. The second then told a third
what the first had told him; the third
told the fourth, and so on, through a
series of 8 to 10 reproductions. Then a
comparison was made between the final
result and the original presentation.
One of the pictures used in this
investigation showed a scene in a
subway in which, in addition to a
number of people seated, there were two
men standing, one a white man, the
other a Negro. The white man was
dressed in working clothes, with an
open razor stuck in his belt. It so
happens that the stereotype of the
Negro held by some people in the USA
includes the notion that Negroes carry
with them an open razor, of which they
make ready use in an argument.
The psychologists were able to de¬
monstrate that in half of the groups
The razor 'moves'
from the white
man to the Negro
who served as subjects in these experi¬
ments, before the end of the series of
reproductions had been reached, the
razor had "moved" from the white man
to the Negro. In some instances, the
Negrq was even represented as bran¬
dishing the razor violently in the face
of the white man. This does not mean
that half of the subjects in the experi¬
ment saw the Negro with the razor,
since if only one person in the chain
made this error, it would be repeated
by those that followed. Interestingly
enough, this did not occur when the
subjects were Negroes (who rejected the
stereotype), or young children (who
had not yet "learned" it).
Another study conducted by Razran
in New York points in the same direc¬
tion. A group of college students in
the USA were shown photographs of
30 girls, and asked to judge each pho¬
tograph on a 5-point scale, indicating
their general liking of the girl, her
beauty, her intelligence, her character,
her ambition, and her "entertaining-
ness". Two months later, the same
students were again shown the same
photographs, but with surnames added.
For some of the photographs Jewish
surnames were given, such as Rabino-
witz, Finkelstein, etc; a second group
received Italian names, such as Sca-
rano, Grisolia, etc; a third group
Irish surnames,, such as McGillicuddy,
O'Shaughnessy, etc; a fourth, "old
American" names like Adams and
Clark.
The investigator was able to demon¬
strate that the mere labelling of these
photographs with such surnames defi¬
nitely affected the manner in which
the girls were perceived. The addition
of Jewish and Italian names, for
example, resulted in a substantial drop
in general liking, and a similar drop for
judgments of beauty and character.
The addition' of
the same names
resulted in a rise
in the ratings for
ambition, parti¬
cularly marked in
the case of the.
Jewish surnames.
It seems clear
that the same
photographs Zoofc-
ed different just
because they
could now be as¬
sociated with the
stereotype held by these students.
If a great many, people agree that a
particular trait is associated with a
particular nation, does that make it
true? There is a fairly widespread
theory to the effect that "where there's
smoke there's Are"; or, in other words,
that the very existence of a stereotype
is, to some extent at least, an argument
in favour of its truth. Otherwise, the
argument runs, where does the stereo¬
type come from? How would it come
into existence?
There is, however, a good deal of
evidence as to the possibility that
stereotypes may develop without any
kernel of truth whatsoever. We all
know how widespread is the notion
that intelligent people have high fore¬
heads, yet scientific investigation in
this field has failed to reveal any such
relationship. The stereotype of the cri¬
minal as bearing in his features the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
mark of his criminality is widely
accepted, but it is equally without foun¬
dation; the famous British criminolo¬
gist, Sir Charles Goring, was able to
demonstrate that a composite photo¬
graph, representing criminals in British
gaols, bore no resemblance to the ac¬
cepted stereotype of the criminal.
Stereotypes frequently change. In
some cases it may be argued that this
corresponds to a real change in the
characteristics of the people; in others,
however, it seems much more likely to
be due to external circumstances which
have little or nothing to do with the
group concerned. The Dutch sociolo¬
gist, Shrieke, has, for example, made a
collection of some of the descriptive
phrases applied to the Chinese during
the course of their residence in the
state of California, U.S.A.
When the Chinese were needed in
California, in order to carry on certain
types of occupation, they were welcome
there; during
that period,
newspapers and I
ioumthemerrä Richard :
among "the most
worthy of our
newly adopted ci¬
tizens"; "the best
immigrants i n
California";- they
were spoken of as
thrifty, sober,
tractable, inof¬
fensive law-abi¬
ding. This flat¬
tering picture prevailed over a consi¬
derable period of time, but around 1860,
presumably because economic competi¬
tion has grown much more severe, there
was a marked change in the stereotype
of the Chinese. The phrases now
applied to them included: "a distinct -
people", "unassimilable", "their pre¬
sence lowered the plane of living", etc.
They were spoken of .as clannish, cri¬
minal, debased, servile, deceitful, and
vicious.
This startling change can hardly be
.accounted for by any real modification
of the characteristics of the Chinese
population of California. The most
acceptable explanation is that when it
became advantageous to reduce the
competition from the Chinese, the
stereotype was altered ' in a direction
which would help to justify such action.
In this historical case it seems reason¬
able to conclude that the change in
the characteristics ascribed to the
Chinese throws doubt on the notion
that stereotypes must necessarily
contain some truth.
Another Dutch sociologist, Den Hol¬
lander, has studied the historical
changes in the stereotype of the
Hungarians in Europe. He points out
that for centuries after the migration
of Hungarians to Central Europe, they
had a bad reputation, and were regard¬
ed as culturally different, and therefore
inferior, to Europeans generally. Dur¬
ing the 15th and 16th centuries, how¬
ever, when they joined in the war
against the Turks, they were pictured
as a brave, devout, and chivalrous'
people.
By the second half of the 18th century
their popularity had again declined,
and they were described as savage,
lazy, egotistical, unreliable, and tyran¬
nous. This picture changed again a
little later, when the Hungarians be¬
came romanticized and idealized. Den
Hollander believes that the image fol¬
lowed the pattern of political inter-
Herman : Stupid
Cuthbert: Sissy
relationships; it seems unlikely that
there was sufficient transformation in
the character of the people to justify
the change in the national image.
One of the most amusing examples
of a stereotype which has apparently
developed without any kernel of truth
emerges from an investigation by
Schoenfeld on stereotypes associated
with proper names. Here again the
technique used was a simple one. The
American students who served as sub¬
jects in this study were given a list of
eight proper names, and a list of eight
adjectives; their task was to "match"
or pair each name with the adjective
regarded as most appropriate.
Since there were 120 students, and
eight names, the results to be expected
by chance alone, that is to say, if no
stereotype existed, would be 120 divid¬
ed by eight, or 15 for each name. The
actual results showed that 63 out of the
120 judges matched Richard with "good
looking"; 58 judg¬
ed Herman to be
"stupid"; 59
HnnHqomp judged Rex as
nUIIUbUlllt: "athletic"; 71 as
sociated Adrian
with "artistic";
and 104 agreed
that Cuthbert
was "a sissy". In
a similar experi¬
ment with Ame¬
rican girls judg¬
ing feminine
names, 54 re¬
garded Minnie as
stupid; 60 saw Linda as sophisticated;
69 said that Mary was religious; 58 that
Maisie was talkative; and 73 that Aga¬
tha was middle-aged.
Although this study was done with
American students, it seems quite cer¬
tain that comparable stereotypes would
be found in languages other than
English.
In any case, it can hardly be
argued that Ri¬
chard is really
better looking
than John, or JLA m m a
Herman more " I
stupid than
Cuthbert. To
return to ethnic
stereotypes, one
significant study
may be cited
which demon- jyt « »
strates the man- JVtOISie
ner in which
stereotypes may
-ievelop without
any basis in truth. The Ame¬
rican sociologist, La Piere, studied the
attitudes of residents of California
towards first and second generation
Armenian immigrants in Fresno County
in that State. There was almost com¬
plete agreement that these Armenians
had more than their share of faults,
and the general attitude toward them
was relatively unfriendly.
La Piere proceeded to question non-
Armenians as to the reasons for their
antipathies, and he was able to classify
the answers into three stereotypes. In
the first place, it was stated that Arme¬
nians were treacherous, lying, deceitful.
In actual fact, when measured by the
criterion of business integrity, the Ar¬
menian merchants turned out to be
equal and frequently superior to others.
In the second place, they were alleged
to be parasites, making excessive de¬
mands upon charitable organizations,
free clinics, etc. Actually, such de
mands by them were less than half of
what would be expected in terms of
their proportion of the population.
Finally, it was said that they had an
inferior code of morality, and they were
always getting into trouble with the
law. In fact, police records showed
that they appeared in only 1.5% of
Police Court cases, although they
constituted approximately 6% of the
population. La Piere concludes that
all of these stereotypes have one factor
in common, viz. that they are definitely
false. This does not mean that stereo¬
types never contain any truth. It does
mean that they can develop without
any truth whatsoever.
There is, however, the possibility that
a little truth may enter into a stereo¬
type through the back door, so to
speak. A Frenchman, with consider¬
able experience of international meet¬
ings, once said that when he had occa¬
sion to address such a meeting he
usually did so in a rather oratorical,
flowery, "Latin" style. He said that
otherwise his Anglo-Saxon colleagues
would be disappointed! When he was
with other Frenchmen, he reverted to
a quieter, more matter-of-fact, "un-
Latin" manner, which really suited him
personally much better.
In this case, the stereotype itself
determined his behaviour under certain
circumstances, and undoubtedly' rein¬
forced the conviction of the Anglo-
Saxons that they really knew what
Frenchmen were like. More rarely, the
stereotype may operate in reverse. A
member of a group with the reputation
for frugality, may go out of his way to
spend freely, and tip lavishly; if the
stereotype calls for lack of punctuality,
he may make it a point to arrive at his
destination well before the hour speci¬
fied. Since, in that case, as was indi¬
cated above, he will probably be re¬
garded as an exception, the stereotype
will still prevail.
Stereotyped thinking may be almost
inevitable, but
there is good evi¬
dence that it can
. C 4- i « r-v j-l at least be redu-
-JlUpiU ced, if not elimi
nated. Eighteen
years after the
Katz and Braly
study, another
psychologist (Gil¬
bert) applied the
T || ¿ I same technique
lalkatlVe to a new gene
ration of Prince¬
ton students. He
found that there
was some persistence of stereotypes,
but also a very important change
which he describes as "a fading effect".
There is much less agreement among
the students in 1950 than in 1932; any
specific trait is usually checked by a
much smaller proportion of students In
the later study. In 1932, for example,
84% of the students described the
Negroes as lazy; in 1950 the percentage
had dropped to 31. The description of
Italians as artistic drops from 83 to 28.
In London, a Unesco study conducted
by H.E.O. James and Cora Tenen,
showed how specific personal expe¬
riences might affect the nature and
content of stereotypes. (1) What they
did was to obtain from schoolchildren
their opinions of other ethnic groups,
particularly of African Negroes, and
then bring them into contact with two
able African women teachers ,r ,.
who spent a few weeks l " 1 *"!
in the schools. next W)
Linda : Snob
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
PICTURES IN OUR HEADS
(Continued)
The "before and after" picture is very
striking. As an example, a child before
the experience stated that "I do not
like black people; it's the colour; it
makes me nervous; they might be sa¬
vage... they are different in nature to
us, more savage and cruel sometimes,
so you don't trust them ever". The
same child after the- experience said:
"Miss V. and Miss W. were nice people-
there does not seem any difference
between them and us except the colour.
Ithink that Negroes are like thaWjust
like us, except for the colour. I like
them. They are nice people".
The authors give many examples of
f-ir-nilar changes that occurred. Stereo¬
types cannot always be modified so
¿ nor so fast, but the fact that
they can be changed at all as a result
of experience is itself encouraging.
Growing older helps
Sometimes just growing older helps.
In a study sponsored by Unesco,
Piaget and Weil report the results
of a series of interviews with Swiss
children of different ages. One inter¬
view with a little girl aged eight years
ran as follows:
"Have you heard of foreigners?
Yes, there are Germans and French.
Are there any differences between
these foreigners?Yes, the Ger¬
mans are bad, they are always
making war. The French are poor
and everything is dirty there.
Then I have heard of Russians, but
they are not at all nice^Do you
have any personal knowledge of
the French, German, or Russians,
or have you read something about
them?' No*Then how do you
know? Everyone says so."
On the other hand, a boy aged
thirteen years, after having mentioned
a large number of foreign countries of
which he had heard, was asked,
"Are there any differences between all
those countries?", and his answer was,
in part, "you find all types of people
evert/where". We are not all as "ma¬
ture" as this 13-year-old boy, but per¬
haps we can move in that direction.
Or is it possible that the Swiss are...?
Oh no! No stereotypes!
Peoples are different
The understanding of national char¬
acteristics represents an impor¬
tant task for all of us, and it is
certain that the following articles will
contribute to that end. The difficulties
in the way are great: nations are made
up of many different kinds of indivi¬
duals, and generalizations are danger¬
ous if they do not give adequate
consideration to the range of individual
variations.
An important first step will be taken
if we treat "the pictures in our heads"
with a strong dose of scepticism, and if
we keep our minds closed to stereotypes
and open only to facts. No one is
denying the existence of national char¬
acteristics.
A knowledge of them can aid our
understanding of people, as well as our
enjoyment of the varieties of behaviour
and personality that are found in dif¬
ferent parts of the world. We need to
make sure, however, that the "pictures
in our heads" correspond as closely as
possible to reality.
Books for understanding other peoples
TODAY the press, the cinema,
the radio and television are
playing an ever-increasing
role in presenting the ways of life
and the inhabitants of one country
to those of another. But a great
many people still turn to books for
detailed information on other na¬
tions. The way in which books on
foreign countries are written, the
information they give and the way
it is presented are therefore still
important factors despite the
growth of other sources from
which the public gets its know¬
ledge and impressions of foreign
countries.
Books and studies which give a
well-balanced picture of different
countries and peoples can contri¬
bute greatly towards better inter¬
national understanding, for an ob¬
jective knowledge of national cha¬
racteristics and their origin can
help to remove misunderstandings
that arise between nations.
Generally speaking there are
three main types of readers whose
needs must be met: the "general
public" whose interest in another
country may be a casual one, for
example, because they intend to
visit it; "officials" (diplomats, in¬
ternational civil servants and tech¬
nical assistance experts) and in¬
dustrialists and businessmen who
need to understand the customs
and outlook of people with whom
they will be in contact; and "tea¬
chers" who want their pupils to
whom they are teaching a foreign
language to know more about the
particular country or countries
where that language is spoken.
Unesco is helping to meet the
needs of all these types of readers
by publishing or sponsoring the
publication of books and studies,
explaining the causes of both in¬
ternational and internal national
tensions, studies on "-ways of life"
in different countries and in urban
and rural communities in a parti¬
cular country. Material in many
cases has been obtained through
Unesco by institutes and univer¬
sities.
The list of books which follows
covers Unesco or Unesco-sponsored
works which help to improve
knowledge about other countries
and peoples. In certain cases the
volume has been published under
Unesco auspices by a private pub¬
lisher whose name is listed.
INTERNATIONAL
TENSIONS
How Nations See Each Other, by
Hadley Cantril and William
Buchanan. University of Illinois
Press, U.S.A.
Tensions That Cause Wars, Hadley
Cantril (editor). University of
Illinois Press, U.S.A.
Democracy in a World of Tensions,
R. McKeon (editor). Unesco pub¬
lication.
National Images : National Types
as Hollywood Presents Them, by
Siegfried Kracauer. Published
in Public Opinion Quarterly, 1949
(13,53-72).
Tensions Affecting International
Understanding1, by Otto Kline-
berg. Social Science Research
Council, 230, Park Avenue, New
York.
Content Analysis of the Mass Me¬
dia of Communication, by D.V.
McGranahan. Chapter 16, Vol. 2
of "Research Methods in Social
Relations", edited by Jahoda,
Deutsch and Cook, the Dryden
Press, New York, 1951.
The Modification of International
Attitudes : A New Zealand
Study, by J. R. McCreary. Dept.
of Psychology, Victoria Univer¬
sity College Wellington, New
Zealand, 1952.
The Teacher Was Black, by H.E.O.
James and Cora Tenen. William
Heinemann Ltd., London.
International Social Sciences Bul¬
letin, Autumn, 1951 issue. Pub¬
lished in English and French,
by Unesco and devoted to Na¬
tional Stereotypes.
INTERNAL TENSIONS
In the Minds of Men ' a general
report on studies of social ten¬
sions in India, by Gardner Mur¬
phy. Basic Books Inc., New
York.
Without the Chrysanthemum and
the Sword, by Jean Stoetzel.
Columbia University Press, New
York, and William Heinemann
Ltd., London. (A special issue of
the Unesco Courier, No. 4/5, 1954,
was based on this study).
COMMUNITY STUDIES
Nouville, un village français, by L.
Bernot and R. Blancard. . "Tra¬
vaux et Mémoires de l'Institut
d'Ethnologie", LVII, 1953, Paris.
Vienne sur le Rhone . Sociologie
d'une ville française, by Pierre
Clement and Nelly Xydias. Ar¬
mand Colin, Series des cahiers
de la Fondation Nationale des
Sciences Politiques.
Social Structure and Personality
in an Australian Rural Commu¬
nity, by O.A. Oeser and F.E.
Emery. Routledge and Kegan
Paul, London, 1954.
WAYS OF LIFE SERIES
(Heinemahn Ltd, London.)
Australia (Edited by George Cai-
ger) ¡-Canada (Miss True David¬
son) ; England (K.B. Smellie) ;
France (Gabriel Le Bras) ; Italy
(Umberto Morra di Lavriano);
Norway (Frede Castberg); Paki¬
stan (Ishtaig Hussain Qure-
shi); South Africa (Edited by
C.H. Calpin).
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
CAN YOU IDENTIFY THEIR NATIONALITIES?
After you have tried, turn to page 26.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Englishman's
'GADGET MINDED' is a description often applied by Englishmen to Ameri¬
cans. In Britain people go to films and read magazines, especially the adver¬
tisements, to see what the ingenious "Yankees" (for all Americans, even Texans,
are Yankees) are up to now. British people expect most American mechanical
gadgets, such as those above, to be newer and more ingenious than others.
close-up view
of the 'Yanks'
by D. W. Brogan
Progressive, conceited, generous, peace-loving, intelligent,
practical these were the six adjectives most frequently
used by people in Great Britain to describe Americans in
1 948, in a survey carried out by the British Institute of Public
Opinion as part of a Unesco-sponsored international enquiry
on "the conceptions which the people of one nation enter¬
tain of their own and other nations". The Unesco Courier
asked Professor D.W. Brogan,- well-known for his long
personal observations in the United States, to comment
on whether those characteristics apply equally today.
The picture or the image that one nation makes of another
necessarily recalls the distorting mirrors in a fun
house at best. It may, of course, be totally unlike
the involuntary sitter ; it may be a caricature so moved by
malice or so remote from factual knowledge that it casts a
great deal of light on the observer but none on the society
observed. Or the foreign viewpoint may have the penetrat¬
ing novelty of the innocent eye. Just as the child in Hans
Andersen's fable saw that the Emperor has no clothes, the
innocent observer may see a lot that the less innocent
observer misses.
I remember being struck by the convincing originality of
the portraits of officials in the East India Company in some
Indian paintings of the eighteenth century that I once saw
in a London exhibition. They were not, from a western
point of view, good portraits, but they not only told us a good
deal about the Indian view of the newcomers, they told us
a good deal about the newcomers that their fellow-coun¬
trymen would not have noticed. In the same way, the
drawings made by the early Japanese missions in the United
States not only illustrate Japanese art techniques or Japanese
reactions to what was then a novel technological world in
which Japanese had not begun to live, but they did and do
illustrate The United States of President Grant as well as
the Japan of the Meiji restoration.
No such freshness of vision can be expected from British
views of the United States or the American people. While
it is absurd to think of the United States as simply a
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
THE BRITISH CONCEPT of the " American people " is influenced far more by the press, films and books than through the contacts people in Britain have
had with GIs, business friends or tourists. A British public opinion survey showed that opinions on Americans as individuals were strongly coloured by
personal associations with Americans, and that on the whole they were favourable. But once questions were related to the American " type ", personal
attributes became more blurred, generalizations became more sweeping and considerations of American national and international policy began to affect
the replies. American domestic affairs drew more contradictory replies than any other subject. Above, US farmers attending a political rally. (USIS photos)
"child" of Great Britain, it is equally absurd not to notice
the important and special bonds that exist between the two
societies, bonds which make understanding both easier and
more difficult. An old daguerrotype may be a good family
portrait. It may, on the other hand, be a misleading
reminder of what Uncle Alec looked like, if attention is
concentrated on his resemblance to Aunt Emma.
There is some truth in the epigram attributed to Oscar
Wilde "nothing divides us but the language", for an almost
common tongue is bound to be full of what the French call
"faux amis", words formally identical but, in fact, meaning
different things. And British criticism, or even appreciation,
of American ways often springs from misunderstandings bred
by words.
Then, common institutions, common cultural traditions
often mislead ; they are almost identical but not quite and
we expect them to be quite identical and feel betrayed when
they are not. Then there is a last link that both helps and
hinders. The number of people in Britain with first-hand
knowledge of the United States is very large. It was
discovered during the last war that 8 % of the population
of Great Britain had some knowledge of America at first
hand. There were, that is to say, very few families in which
there was no direct knowledge of the United States for, of
course, the 8 % did not cover the large number of people of
British birth, who had gone to the United States and stayed
there. The British unlike the French or the Indians, were
not mainly dependent on films, books, radio, the press, all
the mass media, for the knowledge they had of America.
On the whole, this was and is a good thing. But, some¬
times, the returned emigrant had returned simply because
he did not like, say Nashville, Tennessee, and saw and report¬
ed all America in terms of this unfortunate experience. On
the other hand, he might have returned with every intention
of exploiting the fact that he had been to the land of
wonders and, by his pride in his experience, build up resent¬
ment against the American society that allowed the boaster
to boast.
The adjectives most frequently used by the guinea pigs of
the British Institute of Public Opinion's poll illustrate the
special character of British reactions. And one special cha¬
racter can be illustrated by the fact that adjectives, one
friendly, one critical, even hostile, can be used to describe
America and American society by the same people.
Take, for example, the not obviously related characteristics
of being "progressive" and being "conceited". There is no
doubt that the first adjective is meant in a complimentary
sense, for few people in Britain are converts to the fashion¬
able pessimism that makes of "progress" an idol to be over¬
thrown. On the other hand, in no culture known to me, is
"conceit" considered a virtue or an asset. It is not only
offensive to others, it is crippling to the conceited person
who not only doesn't make friends or influ¬
ence people, but is rendered incapable of learn¬
ing. And Americans notoriously want to be
liked and to learn. Yet it is, I think, true
(Continued
on
next page)
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
An Englishman's
close-up view
oí the 'Yanks'
(Continued)
FRIENDLINESS is per¬
haps the most striking
American quality. At home
or abroad the American
is far more willing to
"strike up a friendship"
than the average European.
That friendship may not
go down to the roots of
his being, but it Is a plea¬
sant reality. (USIS photo)
that "progressive" and "conceited" are adjectives that a
great many people, not in the least moved by idealogical bias,
use of Americans and, this is important, have used for a
long time.
"Progressive" is an attribute that we, in Britain, willingly
allow to Americans. On the material plane, we expect
Americans to be ready to "try everything once". We expect
their attitude to be unlike that of the English academic rule:
"nothing should ever be done for the first time". People
go to films, go to shows, read magazines, especially the ad¬
vertising, to see what the ingenious Yankees are up to now.
(For, for us, all Americans, even Texans, are Yankees)
Owning American gadgets is a sign of beings "progressive"
yourself and it is a real blow, a "deception d'amour" when an
American gadget doesn't work (sometimes they don't) or
proves to be meaninglessly complicated to no visibly good end.
We expect most American mechanical things to be more
ingenious, newer, more "cunning" (in the English not the
American sense, for here we have a real "faux ami"). Ships
are an exception ; no true Briton, goes on an American ship
without a vague feeling (it may not even be vague), that he
is taking a serious if indefinable risk. And since, despite the
highbrows, Britain belongs to the gadget-minded western
world, "progressive" is here a word of praise. It is a "boost
not a knock".
But, and this is to be noted, it is often connected with
conceit. It is one thing to be full of ingenious ideas about
how to make two blades of grass grow where none grew
before or how to shave in the open at the top of Mount
Everest, and another to be continually telling people these
secrets of well being, people who may think there is enough
grass anyway, or that you can do without a shave on Mount
Everest, that five o'clock shadow is more than compensated
for by being on top and finding no Americans there.
This may be a churlish attitude but it is common enough.
There is a great mass of unreported folklore of which the
point is the discomfiture of a boasting American who be¬
lieves that New York is bigger than London, who does not
know that no American football field holds as many people
as Hampden Park, Glasgow, or who is simply outboasted by
a local wit with more taste for fancy than for fact.
The dislike of American "boasting" is often based on a
misunderstanding of the American temperament, the
American passion for optimistic figures, the American belief
that figures always prove something. Often they do ; some¬
times they don't. An American, making a plain and truthful
statement about his home town, may make the impression
of conceit on an Englishman who doesn't know the popula¬
tion of his home town or care whether it has grown faster
than its neighbours or not.
Traditionally, the American is always saying "I guess"
meaning he is affirming. To the Englishman he is merely
guessing, or boasting, for we don't distinguish enough
between boosting and boasting. And English or British
conceit, just because it does not take the American form,
resents the American form as is natural in a country which
does not even put its name on its postage stamps.
It may seem, at first sight, odd to link conceit with gene¬
rosity. But, alas, they are linked. This is partly due to
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
the disagreeable human trait which has found proverbial
expression in many languages. "Do a man a good turn and
he will never forgive you." This human trait has its
exemplars in Britain, and American "generosity" is often
sneered at. But it is also admired, if silently. Here the gene¬
rosity of the G.I. has helped a lot. This is not the gene¬
rosity of the G.I. paying too much, being an "easy mark",
but the G.I. subscribing to local charities, putting on a party
for the children, taking it as axiomatic that he has a duty
of generosity and kindness to his neighbours, even those in
a foreign land in which he is, as a general rule, an un¬
willing sojourner.
What is a little surprising is that no mention was made
of what I think, after many years of experience, is the most
striking American quality, friendliness. The American, at
home or. abroad, is far more willing to "strike up a friend¬
ship" than is any European known to me. That friendship
may not go down to the roots of his being but it is a reality
and a pleasant reality.
If the British have not noted it more, it may be because
they themselves, though a kindly people, are not, in this
sense, a friendly people. And few things would make British
and especially English life more agreeable than more of the
open American willingness to be friendly, even at a super¬
ficial level. American is, I think, the only language in which
the word "stranger" is not automatically a term of hostility
or at any rate of suspicion. "Howdy stranger" is the most
intrinsically American greeting I know.
That the Americans are a peace-loving people is true ;
that they are believed to be so by the mass of the British
people is a tribute to their good sense. It is also a tribute
to an American attitude to which I have already referred, to
the fact that the American soldier or airman, stationed
abroad, is so obviously homesick. "Home Sweet Home" is,
after all, an American song even if written by an American
who spent many years abroad and died in Tripoli.
The whole world has had proof of American skill in the
arts of war, but the deeply unmilitary attitude of the
Americans, as revealed in their exiled servicemen, offsets
any belief that because Americans are good at war, they like
war. Few indeed, if any, were the armies at the end of the
late war which had so few deserters, so few soldiers anxious
to stay away from home. The very boasting of American
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
superiority revealed this homesickness felt by servicemen.
That the Americans are "intelligent" is a folk belief closely
connected with the belief that they are "progressive". But
it might be noted, that in English speech, "intelligent" like
"clever" is not a term of unmixed praise. It is often,
consciously or unconsciously, contrasted with being "wise"
and wisdom is perhaps a quality that the British find it har¬
der to notice in the Americans.
Here the belief, only partly true, that the Americans are
young members of the family, nephews if not sons, leads
to the adoption of a semi-parental attitude. Few fathers
spontaneously come to accept the fact that their sons are
now old enough to be let loose on the world and buried not
very deep in the British psyche is the belief that Americans
are not quite mature enough to be given the key of the door.
They are smart ; that is admitted ; but then being smart is
not a totally good thing the British think. (But it was the
Americans who opened the phrase, "smart Alec".)
Then the Americans are "practical". This can be both
praise and blame. Normally, it is praise ; it belongs to the
same group as "progressive". The Americans will find a way
to do things a new way, but in any case they won't sit down
and say "It can't be done" because it hasn't been done before
or because the old way of doing it is palpably impracticable.
That is the good side of American practicality. But it
would be dishonest not to point out that there is another
side to the attribution of "practicality" to Americans. It is
often used, more or less innocently, to suggest that the
Americans are only practical, only interested in material
things. This belief is, of course, reinforced by the American
habit of statistical terms. Thus Americans are wrongly
accused of caring for nothing but money when they are not
merely generous, but less money conscious than Europeans,
using money as a method of ranking, as a proof of achie¬
vement, not, as we are inclined to do, as an intrinsic good.
And because American reverence (which exists) is a rever¬
ence for traditions, historical achievements, social conven¬
tions that necessarily differ from ours, if only because
American history has been not only shorter but so much
happier than ours, we underestimate the degree to which
Americans are unpractical, passionate, sentimental, moralistic
in fact, for all their gadgets are human beings, not supermen
caring nothing for our standards, but in fact almost British!
4s ^ ^¿ x
ri
	a
SYMBOLS OF AMERICA fixed in the minds of people in Britain vary greatly. During a public opinion survey, replies to "What do you usually
think of first when you hear the word 'American'?" related in 50 per cent of cases to acquaintances, about 35 per cent to the U.S.A. as a world power,
and the remaining 15 per cent to various items of interest such as skyscrapers, automobiles, cowboys and Indians. Phrases used to describe Americans
ranged from "friendly", "generous" and "industrious" to "they mechanize everything" and "they boast and brag a lot." Above, left, service
station on a new American continental highway and, right, mealtime for crew of mechanized harvesting combine which travels from farm to farm.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
BETTER UNDERSTANDING THROUGH
FOREIGN LANGUAGES
ON SAFARI, a European is transported in a hammock. Nineteenth century carving from the Upper Congo. Figures
on these pages form part of exhibitions held recently in London and Leiden, Holland. They comprised sculptures of Euro¬
peans as depicted by artists in Africa, Asia and North America. Many reveal humorous comment on European attitudes
and general behaviour. (Photos W. Ohly, Berkeley Galleries, London, and Rijksmuseum voor Volkenkunde, Leiden, Holland.)
A nation may be likened to a real
person, with its own heredity and
traditions, all the complexities of
daily life, and racial and linguistic
"relations" sometimes scattered
throughout the world. The study of
its physiognomy and character is what
we understand by the term "study of
civilization".
This subject therefore covers part of
By Henri Kerst
the same field as the syllabuses for
which our history colleagues are res¬
ponsible. The past helps us to under¬
stand the present; it is often, indeed,
still present. What would Italy be
without the Roman world ? Or Spain
without Arab civilization? Or Germany
without the shades of the Hercynian
Forest ?
The personality of each country has
slowly developed through the centu¬
ries. Wars, often episodic and acci¬
dental in themselves, have marked
important stages and must be taken
into account. The United States of
America today owe much of what
they now are to the War of Indepen-
SHIP'S CAPTAIN of 1830's was carved in
shale, a black stone of cheesy softness, but which
hardens after use, by a Haida Indian of Queen
Charlotte Island, British Columbia, Canada.
14
THE MISSIONARY, a curiously moving
sculpture of a Livingstone-like missionary dres¬
sed in austere clothes, and reading his Bible.
Work in painted wood from the Belgian Congo.
COURTING COUPLE seen with a dispassion¬
ate eye by an artist from Yoruba in Nigeria.
These two painted wooden figures, eight and a
half inches high, probably date from the 1920V
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
dence and to the Civil War. Nor can
political evolution and the institutions
marking its successive stages be
neglected; the soul of Russia has
developed along a clearly marked line
from the time of the Czars to the
present-day regime.
Geography also explains many na¬
tional characteristics. Even without
reference to Hippolyte Taine's theories,
it is tempting to consider that climate
may have an effect on temperament,
that the Italian landscape seems
destined to be the home of the most
brilliant, schools of painting; that the
harshness of the Spanish mountains,
beneath a blazing sun, was bound to
produce a literature of action and
heroism, blended with passionate love;
that England, because of her position,
must eternally waver between German¬
ic austerity and the volatile charm of
France; and that France herself, as
Madame de Stael said, should be the
meeting-place of the literature- of
north and south.
The modern language teacher must
also be familiar with various current
activities, which are largely determin¬
ed by geographical factors. The char¬
acteristics of a country's economic
life explain its customs, the standards
of living of different social classes at
different times, its everyday habits,
and the blossoming, according to the
alternating seasons of tension and
confidence produced by the cycle of
struggle and success, of those flowers
of a richer life, science and religion,
literature and art. The cultural life
of a country depends on its physical
life.
Going beyond the facts of history
and geography, due account should be
taken of certain more elusive factors,
difficult to translate into statistics or
dates. I have in mind the influences
which seem to radiate naturally from
certain countries at a given time,
sometimes peaceful, as in the case of
Italy at the time of the Renaissance,
France under Louis XIV, or the United
States of America at the present day,
and sometimes taking the form of a
"racial dynamism" such as carried
Philip IPs' Spain to the North Sea and
the Pacific, nineteenth-century Eng
land all around the world and Ger¬
many in the last fifty years from one
end of Europe to the other.
To sum up, the traditional field of
history and geography is the objective
study of ' foreign countries, based on
documentary materials, from the stand¬
point of an observer looking on from
outside or above, a study for which
some degree of detachment and syste¬
matic synthesis is necessary. The
teacher responsible for the study of
civilization will aim at making a sub¬
jective study of a nation's history by
actual experience. He will delve into
its subconscious and seek to depict its
heart and soul. He will lay hold on
what is vital and present, what repre¬
sents the nation's potentialities and
nature as a group. We do not get to
know a person by reading his biogra¬
phy but by sharing his life.
We can see immediately where the
study of civilization comes in relation
to its two cousins, the study of lan¬
guage and the study of literature; its
place is of the utmost importance. It
DISTRICT OFFICER sitting at his desk and
dispensing justice, has been depicted with a parti¬
cularly aristocratic nose by a Yoruba artist and
wearing a collar and tie and prominent shirt cuffs.
THE CYCLIST pedalling along with purposeful
air. A modern wood carving touched with
colour, from the Yoruba. Shoes, bicycles and
books are things which impress the artists.
is unthinkable that the language
should be taught alone, in the "pure"
state, as it were. Language is a
scheme, a mould, whose substance is
either literature or civilization.
Now literature is "difficult" and can
hardly be used in the early years of
the study of a foreign language. Liter¬
ature also presupposes a knowledge of
the civilization if it is to be fully
understood and explained. How, for
instance, can Goethe be studied without
reference to that decisive turn in
human history between the eighteenth
and the nineteenth centuries? Shake¬
speare and the Elizabethan court,
Tolstoy and the Russia of the barins,
Dickens and the poverty of the lower
classes in England, provide other
examples.
A country's civilization includes cer¬
tain simple factors suitable for study
even by beginners. When we talk about
the "home", the "town" or the
"family", we are surely simply conjur¬
ing up for our pupils the English house
in the little town where we ourselves
once lived in a British family. Clothes,
QUEEN VICTORIA portr^yad with great
majesty and motherliness. A favourite subject
in West Africa. Beneath the skirts are high-
heeled bootsa mark of high social standing.
meals, motor drives or visits to the
theatre are all features of civilization,
parallel to, but different from our own
and those of our children, with which
an increasingly complex picture can
gradually be built up from the first
year of secondary schooling to the last.
This is of the utmost importance
from the educational point of view.
So far as these features resemble those
familiar to the pupils, they are bound
to seem "easy" to them and should be
of interest to the whole class. , Not all
minds, it must be admitted, can appre¬
ciate literature; it is the prerogative
of the more intelligentthe future
specialists. In its higher forms, such
as lyric poetry, relatively few are cap¬
able of truly "feeling" it. A country's
civilization, on the other hand, can
to some extent be understood by every¬
body.
This leads to a second important
consequence, this time psychological.
The difference between civilizations
will arouse curiosity and thus produce
a desire to know more about them,
which is seldom the case with a purely
literary text, the subject matter of
which is already complete in itself and
often above the standard of mental
development normally attained by
children.
More than ever in the modern world
"civilizations" must overstep political
boundaries. We affect and are affect¬
ed by the form of civilization found
among other peoples, even when they
are not our neighbours, so that this
study, which is calculated to interest
all pupils, will also be the most useful
to them, leaving them long after the
literature or the language have been
forgotten, for lack of the opportunity
of continuing their stud y a real,
practical knowledge of the foreign
country which may one day perhaps
be our ally or our enemy but, in any
case, must be our travelling companion
on this small planet.
This article is reprinted from "The Teaching of
Modern Languages", ¡ust published by Unesco (Price :
$ 1.75 ; 10/6 ; 500 fr.). It was originally published
In unabridged form by the French National Commission
for Unesco in "L'Enseinnement des langues vivantes et
la compréhension internationale", 1953. M. Kerst ¡s
Professor of English at the Lycée Henri-IV, Paris.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
What a French
village thinks
of the
foreigner
by Lucien Bernot
and René Blancard
N
ouville is* a real French village, but you won't
find it marked on any map of France. The name
was used to hide the identity of a typical French
village where experts from Unesco and from the
Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes, in Paris, made
a detailed study of its people and their opinions.
While the complete report««Nouville, un village
français," by Lucien Bernot and René Blancard (I)
covered a great deal of ground, the following article
is taken from one of the chapters, entitled : "What
do the people of Nouville think about foreigners?"
Who do these villagers regard as "foreigners" ?
For them, the foreigner is not only someone who
lives outside the borders of France. It is anyone
who does not belong to the family, the village or
the region. It is ««he" as opposed to ««we". It
(I) Published in co-operation with Unesco by the Ethnological Institute
of the University of Paris, 1953. Price $ 7; 2,000 Fr. frs. (French only).
16
(Unesco photo)
can apply both to the far-off Chinaman and the
close-at-hand Parisian. Recalling childhood mem¬
ories, one villager told an investigator: ««When I
went to fetch the milk in the evening I was uneasy ;
I wasn't afraid of the French people, but of the
Bretons."
Foreigners, then, are the people of whom the vil¬
lagers say: "We don't visit one another. It's not
that we are on bad terms with them ; we simply ex¬
change a «good day' or a «good evening'nothing
more."
Yet not all the distinctions made by the "Nouvil-
lois" are black or white. ««Of course they are not
foreigners", they say of some people, «'they live in
France, don't they?"
Here, directly, sometimes awkwardly and often
bluntly, but always with a ring of sincerity, which
marks a simplicity of ideas, is what the people of
Nouville think about foreigners.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
When the Municipal Council of Nouville heard that two
investigators were being sent to the village by Unesco,
several Councillors asked "What's Unesco?". The
general concensus of opinion was "It's one of those U.N.
thingumajigs; an international organization run by the
Americans."
When we did arrive one of the villagers told us: "We
expected to see two dark-suited officials ride up in a magni¬
ficent American car complete with chauffeur. We were
surprised when you came by train." The school-teacher's
comment, on hearing that one of us had paid a visit to the
village by bicycle a few days earlier, was: "Good, that shows
they are the athletic type."
The one idea that everyone had of us at first was that we
must have plenty of money. People we met asked: "Who's
paying you ? The Government? The
Americans?" One Councillor later
admitted to us: "At first, I was
suspicious. I thought you had been
sent down by some Conservatives. Then
I saw you weren't dealing with politics
and you were talking with the working
people; you weren't stand-offish."
We ran into sharper, more intense
opposition in a hamlet which we visited
later than the rest of the commune.
When some of the inhabitants found
we were there, they asked their coun¬
cillor what we were up to and his reply
was: "They are here as representatives
of some international affair." This cau¬
sed some people to remark "The inter¬
national people are the Russians.
We'd better be careful. These fellows
are the eye of Moscow".
. When one of us asked a workman in
this hamlet for some information, he
replied: "You're not pumping me for
any information. I almost got stood
up against a wall in the last war. And
if I wasn't it was only because I kept
my mouth shut."
Others were more polite, but still
refused to give any information: "I've
got nothing against you; you go ahead
and do your job, but I've nothing to
tell you.""Why?""Because the whole
thing's anti..""Anti what?""Anti...
'. it's not pro anything..."
As a whole, the first reaction of the
people of Nouville was that we might
be spies.
"In 1940 people like that came round
asking questions. And then we had
the war a little later on." They still
tell the story of the butcher from Sou-
zoir who used to make deliveries before
1939 and who turned out to be a Nazi
spy; he was seen during the war in German uniform.
Eventually, this suspicion around us died away; the inha¬
bitants of Nouville were reassured by articles in the press.
"They're in the newspapers", they told one another, "so they
can't be spies."
A Councillor's wife remarked to me: "Unesco is the same
as the U.N., and all that sort of thing's tied up with
foreigners... We've got too many foreigners in France,
that's why you get so many spies."
Someone else from the same hamlet said: "Don't you pay
any attention to what people here think; they're stupid;
you're talking to somebody now who really knows what
Unesco is. It's an American outfit." (sic)
We explained that he was wrong, that Unesco was an inter¬
national organization, and that in any case we were working
under the direction of the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes,
of Paris. This person was quite ready to believe us, and the
continued: "During the war I sheltered an
American airman. We hid him for several months and then
he managed to escape. After the Liberation we got a short
letter of thanks. I don't want to make anything of it, but do
you think they sent us any parcels? Not even one... You
can tell them so when you see them."
On the whole, the people received us in a friendly way, but
no one would ever admit that Unesco could be anything but
an American organization. Several Councillors asked us if it
would be possible to get some assistance for the commune
through Unesco. One of the Nouville representatives, intro¬
ducing us to a glass manufacturer, said to him, "Here are
two gentlemen from Unesco. It's an honour for us to have
them here... and maybe they'll be able to be of use to you in
your business."
It is possible to distinguish several categories of foreigners
within the commune, but the "conscious" meaning which
both adults and children give to the word "foreigner" is:
someone who is not French. A test made on second year and
(Photo Christian Baugey)
final year secondary school pupils bore this out for the majo¬
rity of the boys and girls. In a few isolated cases, it is also
used to indicate someone from outside the village.
An analysis of the answers gave the following definitions
of the term "foreigner": First, someone speaking another
language than French; secondly, someone wearing different
clothes; and finally someone who does not know the district.
We found that the idea which people.form of foreigners is
determined more by what is known about them, through the
press and radio, than by any fears or hopes they may inspire.
Not all foreigners are thought of in the same way or seen
in the same perspective. When people speak (well) of the
British or (ill) of the Germans, they do so by evoking the
past. But Americans and Russians are considered in the
light of current events. People speak of them in the present
tense, calculate the chances of their "leaving us in peace or
not", and think of the future. Their views of these two
foreign peoples depend on public opinion, that
is, on the degree of fear which either of these (Cont'd on
countries happens to arouse at the time. next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Villagers' likes and dislikes (Cont'd;
A second group of nations, such as the Belgians, the
Luxemburgers and the Swiss, are regarded favourably. They
are spoken of as peaceful countries to be imitated; looking
for trouble with no one, and clearly in no way to be feared.
*
(Unesco photos)
J_ iNALLY there is a third
type of foreigner, the attitude
towards him being quite
distinct. It includes the
Chinese, the Japanese, the Indians who live in far-off, di¬
stant lands and whom no one fears. The people of Nouville
have no strong feelings about them either way, yet at the
same time they regard them as backward, and also cruel
views based on what they have read. Opinions about these
countries may therefore be favourable or unfavourable. In
either case, though, no strong emotional feelings are involv¬
ed, and the inhabitants readily admit that they may be
mistaken, that they "'saw it in a book".
*
<-c¿- N Y I,: :
cribed. The first was:
T
	 wo questions were put
to the people of Nouville. The
replies reflect the three cate¬
gories of foreigners just des-
"Of the following peoples, underline the names of those
you like most and strike out those you like least: Americans,
Belgians, Chinese, English, Germans, Jews, Russians, Spa¬
niards, Swiss, Jugoslavs, Israelites."
The answers (shown at the top of the next column) reveal
no great differences of opinion between farmers and
workers. Some, however, simply underlined the names of
peoples for whom they had the most friendly feelings, or
underlined or crossed out only a few names:
This question listed the two names, Jews and Israelites.
Some of the inhabitants of Nouville did not know the second
term, but this hardly changed the result at all.
In the second question, the inhabitants were given 14 brief
sentences containing descriptive adjectives or phrases, such
as "the... are trustworthy", "the... are untrustworthy", "the...
want war", etc. They were asked to write in the name of the
foreigners they considered most fitting in each case. The
replies are shown in columns two and three of these pages.
FOREIGNERS MOST LIKED
AND DISLIKED BY NOUVILLE
Peoples
Americans .
Belgians ..,
Chinese ...
English 	
Germans ..
Jews	
Russians ..
Spaniards .
Swiss 	
Jugoslavs .
Israelites ..
Workers Farmers
Mos't liked
9
20
5
15
0
2
14
4
12
7
2
Disliked
15
3
20
10
21
24
11.
19
9
13
22
Most liked
9
17
4
14
2
2
6
11
15
8
2
Disliked
11
4
14
5
19
16
12
11
5
9
13
No great advantage can be gained from considering all
these replies globally as they indicate no valid conclusion.
This system was unsuited to the people of Nouville. Some
used their children's geography books to refresh their memo¬
ries and to obtain the names of 14 different peoples so as to
complete the questionnaire!*
jflhftt *
w e shall therefore li¬
mit our comments to .those
results borne out by our
personal experience, noting
those peoples whose names recurred most frequently in
conversation during our stay with the villagers.
There is very little spontaneous discussion about Jews, but
when the villagers were asked to strike out from a list of
peoples those they liked least, a large number struck out the
word "Jew". Yet, no active or systematic antisemitism was
involved. Several men from Nouville had Jewish friends in
the army and still spoke of them: "They were just like
everybody else." In our opinion, if Jews were to settle in the
community, they would not be regarded any differently from
the other inhabitants. The opinions about Jews reflect ste¬
reotype thinking.
Trustworthy :
DESCRIPTIONS GIVEN TO
DIFFERENT PEOPLES
Untrustworthy:
	 i 	 19
	 6 7
6
	 5
7
	 5
4
	 2
British 	 3
2
Rich:
	 32
	 1
1
Poor:
	 8
4 6
	 3 6
1 	 4
	 1 3
1 1
	 1
1
1
Serbs 		 1
1
I8
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Intelligent:
Americans	 8
French 8
English 5
Swiss 3
Jews	 2
Germans
Belgians
Dutch
Spaniards	
Norwegians
Japanese
Swedes
Friendly:
Belgians	 23
English 19
Poles 2
Americans	
Canadians
Chinese
Russians
Jugoslavs	
Civilized:
French	 13
Swiss 8
English 3
Belgians	, 	 2
Swedes 1
Jews 1
Americans	 1
Spaniards 1
Want peace:
French	 18
Russians 11
Americans 5
Swiss 3
All peoples	 2
Poles 2
Workers 2
Belgians 1
Kindhearted:
Swiss	 12
Belgians 12
English 5
Canadians	 2
French 2
Luxemburgers
Dutch
Portuguese	
Russians
Jugoslavs
Stupid:
Spaniards	 6
Chinese 5
Italians 4
Russians 3
Jews	 2
Japanese 2
Indians 1
French 1
Serbs	 1
Unfriendly:
Germans '.	 32
Spaniards 5
Russians 4
Japanese 2
Americans	 1
Backward:
Chinese	 13
Russians 12
Spaniards 2
Germans 1
Jews	 1
Turks 1
Vietnamese 1
1 Want war:
Americans	 18
Russians 12
Germans 5
Capitalists	 2
Buddhists 1
English 1
Spaniards	 1
Cruel:
Germans	 22
Russians 7
Turks 3
Chinese 2
Mongols	 2
Japanese 2
A young woman who
had recently arrived in Nou¬
ville attracted attention be¬
cause of her olive complexion
and black hair. These were regarded as odd characteristics
and caused much speculation. Many people queried us
about her: "You are invited to her house, do you know where
she' comes from? What race, is she? What country does
she come from? I'll bet it's Indochina." Someone else
insisted that she came from North Africa. A third spe¬
culated: "She must be Jewish. They say she wore a yellow
star at Amiens during the occupation... But she's a
good Jew."
As a matter of fact, the woman's ancestors had been
citizens of Amiens for generations and never, so far as is
known, had any Indochinese, African or Jewish origins.
We asked someone who was criticizing the Jews, "Do you
know any?" He replied that he did not, apart from this
woman, "who must be Jewish but who is a nice person".
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
It is only through news sources that people can have any
knowledge of the Chinese. The opinions expressed about
them fall into the third category of "distant" foreigners,
already described. A few favourable answers were given
concerning them. These came from local communists or
communist sympathisers who were happy "to see a new
friendly nation". But, apart from these few cases, the
general opinion held of the Chinese is unfavourable, not
from a political point of view but because people have read
stories and articles about "those lands of mystery". We
heard people remark: "These Chinese must be a queer lot;
I shouldn't like to live with them." The idea most frequently
expressed is that the Chinese are "backward".
II. s for the views held of
the Americans and the Rus¬
sians, it was interesting to see
the extent to which an unfa¬
vourable opinion of one of those countries corresponded to
favourable opinion of the other.
Favourable to the Americans and unfavourable to
the Russians	34 %
Unfavourable both to the Americans and to the
Russians 34 %
Favourable both to the Americans and to the
Russians 7 %
Unfavourable to the Americans and favourable to
the Russians	25 %
The results thus obtained reflect three attitudes among
the people of Nouville and are in many cases dictated by fear
of a future war. We thus have:
Those friendly to the U.S.A.;
Those friendly to the U.S.S.R.;
Those who consider both countries equally responsible
for any future conflict.
*
R
EGARDiNG this third
attitude, the percentage indi¬
cated above simply covers
those persons who replied to
However, the fact of not replying itself
We also noted (but the fact cannot be
expressed in terms of statistics) that among the persons
who did not reply were a large number who showed indiffe¬
rence to this subject or refused to co;umit them¬
selves. This would perhaps tend to increase the (Cont'd on
relative importance of this third group. page 34)
the questionnaire,
reveals an attitude.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Images that do
more harm than
a thousand words
by
Gilbert Gadoffre
Symbols used by people for project¬
ing their own image abroad or
for representing foreign countries
to themselves usually have two things
in common a strong tendency to
persist once they take hold and a
faculty for crystallizing certain emo¬
tional reactions, such as hatred and
scorn, which it would be dangerous to
underrate.
The term "national images" covers
a whole set of images of different type
and origin superimposed one on the
other. First there are the earliest
images, which though limited in num¬
ber, occur in almost all the civilizations
in various forms. The Ceres-Bellona
combination, for example (goddesses
of fertility and of war) occurs in diffe¬
rent forms all over the ancient Italo-
Greek world, from Mesopotamia to
pre-Aryan India.
Then there are the national figures
such as Joan of Arc, William Tell and
Andreas Hofer whose character and
legends are based on or influenced by
the original images, and which have
finally become symbols in the life of
national communities.
There are also abstract symbols such
as Liberty (the first incarnation of
France's Marianne), Germania or Bri¬
tannia. Finally, symbolic images exist
such as the Marianne of the French
Third Republic, John Bull and Uncle
Sam. These come midway between
the abstract symbols on which they are
sometimes based (as in the case of
Marianne) and the stereotype-proper.
Borrowed from antiquity
Although these images can be
separated into the above categ¬
ories, the categories are by no
means watertight; each symbol merges
with those of preceding categories, of
which it frequently bears recognizable
traces. Such intermingling does indeed
occur; but it should not cause us to
forget that, as we move further away
from the prototype and the images be¬
come progressively more heterogeneous,
confusion more easily arises, and tran¬
sition from one category of images to
another becomes more difficult.
One point in this process of transition
from the three first categories of
images to the fourth still remains
obscure: how is it that primordial
images, of religious origin, and still
retaining much of their emotional
fascination, finally acquire an almost
burlesque character? Here again, no
answer can be given without analysis
of a specific case. We have to make
an excursion into political history.
We meet the first republican symbols
during the Great Revolution, i.e., at a
critical period, amongst grim men,
lacking both humour and self-criti¬
cism, and obsessed by all that recalled
Greco-Latin antiquity. The original
effigies were borrowed from Roman
coins reproducing, in stylized sil¬
houette, the statue of Liberty from the
temple of Jupiter on the Aventine hill,
with the classical attributes; the stola,
the spear and the Phrygian helmet.
Then, by a decree passed in 1792, to
the effect that the royal statues were
to be replaced by representations of
the figure of Liberty, the Convention
imparted an official character to this
symbol. The motive is clear: to replace
the paternal image of the sovereign by
a feminine image symbolizing both the
death of the authoritarian paternalism
of the monarchs, and the new affilia¬
tion . with the great democracies of
ancient times.'
Unlike the abstract symbols, the
symbolic images affect people emotion¬
ally in two distinct ways; they exercise
a strong fascination in their country,
but beyond the national frontier, the
same symbolic image rapidly deterior¬
ates into over-simplified and male¬
volent stereotypes.
As long as a symbolic image remains
in its country of origin, it retains some
links with the original images from
which it stems. In France the man in
the street knows nothing of the mythi¬
cal, historical or sociological origins of
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
Marianne. In most cases he knows
that she represents the French Repub¬
lic, and not the French people, but
he has a vague feeling that behind the
conventional abstraction portrayed by
the political cartoonist there is a con¬
nexion between the lovely feminine
face of Marianne and the "fair
France" he has heard so much about
since his childhood, whose presence he
has actually felt and which undoubt¬
edly is something quite real in French
mentality.
In its turn this attitude is linked to
the very nature of French patriotism
which is not so much the collective
solidarity of a group of men who feel
themselves to be a single people as
the common love felt by different
people for a mother country and a way
of life.
A flighty scatterbrain
Once transplanted, Marianne loses
both her mythical aura and her
emotional overtones, retaining
merely her shell as depicted in French
cartoons and other drawings. Demo¬
cratic nations like to poke fun at
themselves and to criticize good-natur¬
edly but the symbolic figures used soon
take on undue importance and help to
change the image into a hostile stereo¬
type.
In Germany, John Bull becomes a
caddish, insolent ogrelike figure; in
Europe, Uncle Sam is seen as a dessi-
cated, heartless Shy lock; and for
France, the German Michel is regarded
as a sly double-crossing fool; in the
same way Marianne is all too easily
transformed into a flighty scatterbrain.
On careful examination such inter¬
pretations often prove to have a social
origin, in that the ruling classes can
project their particular obsessions and
phobias more easily on to foreigners
than on to their own compatriots. A
Dutch historian, Dr. de Vries, has
shown very clearly that, in the eyes of
the Frenchman of the grand siècle,
the stereotyped caricature of the
Dutchman in clogs was closely linked
with the social problems of Louis XIV's
contemporaries.
Though already ruined for more
than a century and economically un¬
productive, the French nobility still
occupied all the great posts, set the
tone of the country and thanks to
their power of persuasion, backed by
their prestige, imposed their own scale
of values. All the aristocratic quali¬
ties^ gallantry, generosity, elegance
were extolled, whereas the bourgeois
virtues of thriftiness, forethought and
a serious attitude towards business
and intellectual pursuits, were given
minor importance.
During the same period, there deve¬
loped in Holland a type of society bas
ed entirely on varying degrees of
wealth: the middle class, possessing
both power and wealth, had no diffi¬
culty in building a civilization uphold¬
ing the bourgeois values. The scorn
with which Frenchmen at that time
regarded the Dutch an attitude
expressed in the stereotype used is
essentially a projection, on the inter¬
national level, of a specifically French
class conflict.
This feeling of scorn arose from the
negation of bourgeois values "and the
affirmation of a set of aristocratic
values unknown to the Dutch people
who, as Louis XTV said, lived "on trade
and fish". It equally expressed the
then growing fear that the political
of the aristocratic caste
were about to collapse and that the
rich bourgeoisie would gradually seize
power with the help of royalty.
Less than 100 years later the picture
has succeeded in imposing its own
values: Monsieur Jourdain no longer
has to play at being a gentleman;
instead queens now play at being
shepherdesses and princesses admire
the furnishings and decorations of
bourgeois homes, and the pictures and
books extol virtues ridiculed only a
century before.
Thus the image of the Dutchman is
transformed: he becomes the model of
the worthy, resourceful citizen. Vol¬
taire sees in Amsterdam a paradise on
earth. Nothing, he writes, is sweeter
than the fortune you have made your¬
self.
This example of Franco-Dutch rela¬
tions throws some light on the nature
of certain transformations undergone
by Marianne. But to obtain precise
results would require country-by-coun¬
try enquiries and above all a careful
study of thousands of drawings and
cartoons. From the very limited mate¬
rial available it would seem that cer¬
tain sentiments and attitudes strongly
censured in Protestant, industrial and
bourgeois countries were often thrown
into the stereotype of Marianne. Thus,
anything in these countries which
seemed to threaten life based on the
glorification of hard work (such as the
idea that elegant living was superior
to work, the assertion of the right to
fantasy, opposition to sexual taboos)
was projected outwards on to a femi¬
nine figure displaying all the seductive
appeal of sin.
The confusion is further increased
because the various symbolic images
do not have the same meaning; and
any comparison between them is diffi¬
cult. John Bull represents a sovereign
people which is master of its own
destiny; Michel, the German, is not a
citizen but a subject: Marianne stands
for a political regime. But in the past
60 years journalists and caricaturists
have got into the habit of depicting
international debates as a kind of
puppet show in which the symbolic
figures have only one purposeto
represent their people.
An unwelcome marriage
The levelling down of these different
symbols has distorted both the
images themselves and the relat¬
ions between them. The simple art of
portraying Marianne and John Bull in
conversation introduces an ambiguous
note: the régime of one country cannot
be placed on the same footing as the
people of another country. And, since
it is always tempting to compare rela¬
tions between countries with relations
between individuals, it is very easy to
talk of friendship, hostility and mar¬
riage, even between puppets, particu¬
larly when there are differences of sex.
Several years ago, German news¬
papers favouring the Schumann plan
hailed the prospects of Franco-Ger¬
man reconciliation with headlines and
variations on the theme of the mar¬
riage of Michel and Marianne. The
German public took this as a token of
purely peaceful intention, but the
reaction of the French was entirely
different.
To the French the (Cont'd
feminine symbol of their on next
government was an -page)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
More harm than
a thousand words
(Continued^
affirmation of virility and masculinity
which had liberated them from tyranny.
They refused to see France represent¬
ed by Marianne and could not admit
or conceive a marriage between Ma¬
rianne and Michel since, this seemed
to them adultery or a denial of their
virility. Their refusal to assume the
feminine role was strengthened by the
suspicion that they had before them
a partner who was trying to trick
them by taking the better share. Thus,
the introduction of national images
had the effect of distorting the friend¬
ly and conciliatory spirit in which the
plan was conceived, with the result
that problems were further confused,
and fresh tensions artificially created.
The harm such national images can
do when used in this way can hardly
be emphasized too strongly. Inevitably
deteriorating into stereotypes as soon
as they cross their own frontiers, they
breed misunderstanding, create deep-
rooted associations of ideas from early
childhood, caricature national temper¬
aments and nourish the spreading of
internal conflicts abroad.
In their own country of origin the
effect is almost equally deplorable; they
crystallize the most obsolete nationalist
prejudices with amazing potency. One
could be fooled. Because the demo¬
cracies introduce a certain note of lev¬
ity, as if to narrow the gap between
the symbols and their images and
allow a certain latitude for self-criti
cism and decorous mockery, it might
be imagined that the slightly burlesque
silhouette of Uncle Sam, Marianne and
John Bull are perfectly harmless.
But in these three cases the criticism
expressed within the countries is really
a kind of affectionate jibe at their own
faults which are merely seen as slight
shortcomings.
The sudden changes of public opi¬
nion, the scandalous instability of a
Parliament or a Ministry are easily
attributed to the light-hearted femi¬
nine flavour which gives Marianne all
her charm; the most cynical acts of na¬
tional egoism are admired as proofs of
the "strong character" of John Bull;
and as for Michel, in Germany, it is
taken for granted that he is eternally
exploited, always ridiculed, because he
is too goodhearted and too . credulous.
In this way, the worst faults of na¬
tions, those which in fact present the
greatest obstacles to international co¬
operation, receive compassionate abso¬
lution, supported and reinforced by
what passes as self-criticism. National
stereotypes thus lead to stagnation and
discord in every way. But can the
damage they cause at least be limited?
From kings to sportsmen
We must not forget that behind
these figures and the compar¬
isons made with others lies the
need sometimes felt by nations to assert
their own personality, and to show
themselves in a negative light against a
foreign background. This is a vital
factor which it would be dangerous to
underestimate. It should be noted,
however, that the image of a group is
not always identified with nationality:
'it has successfully advanced from the
tribe, through the city and the pro¬
vince before reaching the present stage.
It is perhaps not impossible to stimu¬
late this process of evolution, until the
image merges with certain universal
images which contain, yet transcend,
several other images.
But treaties, laws or political institu¬
tions could not by themselves acceler¬
ate such a movement unless certain
focal points of popular sentiment also
existed. In ancient Europe, where the
family constituted the basic unit it was
the monarchy (a sublimated image of
the family) which provided this focal
point, and in military states, the figure
of the King was replaced by that of the
Chief. In both cases, popular attach¬
ment to an individual was diverted to
the larger unit of which he was the
living representative.
With the disappearance of kings and
military chiefs, what new objects re¬
ceived the fund of emotion thus re¬
leased? To what extent have the
symbolic images in question inherited
the prestige formerly enjoyed by na¬
tional figures? How far have they
been robbed of their prestige by such
new objects of popular affection as film
stars, great sportsmen and heroes of
war or crime, all of whom are no longer
symbols of group-dignity, but of the
unfulfilled aspirations of the individ¬
ual?
These are questions to which no
reply can be given at present since no
studies have 'been made of the objects
of popular affection in the various
countries ; or of the genealogy of na¬
tional images; and of the projection
and exchange of images between one
country and another. Until it has been
done, certain factors of mass psycholo¬
gy will remain obscure ; the abrupt
switches of public opinion will remain
a mystery, and statesmen will continue
to be confounded, and their calcula¬
tions upset, by such phenomena as the
Hitlerian landslide in 1933.
The above text is an abridged version
of the study "French National Images
and the Problem of National Stereo¬
types" by Gilbert Gadoffre, originally
published in Unesco's "International
Social Science Bulletin," Vol. Ill, No. 3.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N- 6. 1955
*«£
.:. ~*J *4i^ --. -
SUDAN : a land
changing faster
than the people
TENANT FARMERS of the Sudan are now part of one of the world's great agricultural projectsthe
Sudan Government's Gezireh Scheme which has brought them prosperity by using the waters of
the Blue Nile to irrigate farmlands. But old traditions of work and life still block new ideas.
Farmers welcome progress, but are slow to accept changes in their own daily lives. (Unesco photos)
There is something excessively ord¬
erly about cotton. Field after
field of it; every plant exactly
the same height and at exactly the
same stage of development. As I drove
through it the other morning at dawn
the fields were all deserted except for
the grey herons along the irrigation
channels and the flashing scarlet and
blue bee-eaters. They almost succeed¬
ed in making the scene look untidy.
Fallow, cotton, maize; a pattern end¬
lessly repeated over the five million
acres of the Sudan Government's
Gezireh scheme.
Order is the keynote of the whole
scheme; control of the waters of the
Blue Nile at the Sennar dam; control
of the waters as they flow through
channels of decreasing size until they
gush into the cotton fields; control
again of the tenants and their times
of planting and cultivating and har¬
vesting. The scheme is much too
important for the economic life of the
country, and water is far too precious,
for anything to be left to chance.
The Board can control the water; it
can control what is planted and it can
control when it is planted, but the
tenants of the scheme are another
matter. People do not change fun¬
damentally in one generation (the
scheme has been running for thirty
years) even when the circumstances of
their lives have altered completely.
Just as the water has been guided into
the channels now the minds 'of the
	 by 	
Alexander Sha w
Unesco Technical Assistance Specialist
people must be guided into new ways
of thinking.
The first years of the scheme were
naturally devoted to making it an
economic success and the peasants
were used as pawns in carrying out
this objective. But now there is money
and time, and a Social Development
department has been set up. With this
department the Ministry of Education
co-operates by sending a team of Adult
Education Officers to work in the area.
I, and the men whom I am training,
are working to provide the team with
Visual Aids mainly film strips. so
that they can use them in their talks
in the villages.
When you talk to the villagers they
sit and nod their heads and say:
"Certainly, that is true." They thank
you for coming and give you fizzy
drinks. And then they forget every¬
thing that you have said, possibly
almost before you have gone. But if
you show them pictures at the same
time they say: "That must be true
because we can see it." And they
discuss the pictures and argue and re¬
member what it was all about.
A film strip was shown about the
daily life of a French small-holder and
his family. The Adult Education
Officer was able to talk about a man
who did his own work (which the Gezi¬
reh tenants on the whole don't do)
without offending his audience who are
apt to be rather sensitive.
However, next evening íContínue<í
we showed them a strip on page 25)
about the Gezireh, and
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
MEN OF THE SUDAN who once tended their flocks wherever there was pasture and grew crops when the rains came have been tenant farmers for a
generation thanks to the Nile irrigation scheme. Though successful cultivators, they are still inclined to rely too much on their leaders to wait to be told
what to do. Their womenfolk, as yet, play little or no part in everyday life and affairs. If the young Sudanese girl (above) had been a year or two older no
photograph could have been taken. Women soon respond when someone takes the lead, but there are few emancipated women as leaders. (Unesco photos)
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N° 6. 1955
It's a man's world in the Sudan c°^
talked to them directly about working
themselves and they were extremely
offended. "I have been a tenant for
twenty-five years", said one, "and no
one has ever insulted me before by
suggesting that I should do the work
myself." Because of this we intend to
show them strips about their own lives.
We already have evidence that the
results will be dramatic.
"Thus the villagers of Abdul Hafiz are
going to help us make a film strip
which will be used all over the Gezireh.
It is one of a programme of twenty-
five that we have planned with the
Government and local authorities.
The village looks very pretty from
across the canal. Trees are reflected
in the water, brightly clad women from
West Africa are cleaning the grain
which they have taken out from its
store in the ground, and a herd of post¬
card conscious camels are single-filing
against the early sun. A villager has
just had a bath in the canal and his
white nightgown-like garment is flut¬
tering in the cool breeze. A group of
villagers all men of coursaare
waiting for .us. (We hide our surprise
that they should be ready in a land
where time is usually kept in its place)
Even the. truck is there from the
nearby market town. Peace be upon
you, God preserve you, welcome, how
are you? This is an Arab world and
the formalities are important. These
villagers are some of the half million
people who live on the scheme and it
is for them that the Government has
asked the help of Unesco Technical
Assistance.
Village film actors
All the villagers like being photo¬
graphed and once we have per¬
suaded them not to puff out their
chests and look the camera straight in
the lens, all goes well. Shots are taken
for the first scene of "Safeguard Your'
.Future", a strip about a scheme which
sets out to make the tenants into farm¬
ers instead of people who just do what
they are told. They are to be encour¬
aged to make themselves reasonably
self-supporting so that if cotton prices
fall they will survive the bad times.
Having waited for a few hundred
goats to cross, held up a troop of camels
and allowed the dust to subside we
move on to the offices of the Alternat¬
ive Husbandry scheme and start on
our carefully prepared schedule. We
will do this and that in a certain or¬
der will we? The tenants take
charge. They want to see everything
and in their own way.
. They break away from us and rush
about asking questions and arguing.
We get photographs as best we can,
occasionally getting lost in the prob¬
lem of whether lentils should be
picked and dried or threshed after
drying on the plant itself. But the sun
is rising high and one way or another
we have all the pictures we need. Still
the tenants are looking at the baler,
asking questions about profits or
looking at the milk yield. Breakfast
saves us, with some wonderful coffee.
It takes rather a time because it must
be roasted on charcoal in a wooden
platter just before it is served. 'Only
women can make it and this ,is the
first time in the day that even the
idea of -a woman has appeared.
Women in the Sudan are very remote
from everyday life when it is not con¬
cerned with children and food. Al¬
though, in the towns, you may see a few
white-draped figures, the village
women do not go out very much. Nei¬
ther do they eat with the men. In
fact they are expected to follow a line
of speak when you are spoken to, come
when I call. This is. a delicate matter
as it is connected with all kinds of
everyday things.
It is difficult, for example, for a
mother to take her child to a clinic
because she cannot go alone and the
husband says "tomorrow". She and
the children have to eat what is left
over after the men and if, as is very
common, there have been guests they
may only get bread; since she never
hears about anything she appears apa¬
thetic. There is no incentive to change
and indeed it would be difficult for her
to achieve it even if she did consider it.
Custom and tradition are strong and
the old women rule supreme. However,
they will respond as soon as someone
takes the lead: they were delighted to
help in the making of four film strips
and worked far harder than the men.
Unfortunately there are practically no
emancipated women in the country to
lead their sisters gently. The men
know that change must come. As one
old chaikh (headman) said "I know
that my family ought to eat with me,
they would get better food but it would
be impossible."
Omdah asks the questions
We talk to the omdah (chief). He
is a shrewd, successful man,
the sort of man all the tenants
would like to be. Until recently he
could not read or write but that
has not stopped him taking full
advantage of the Alternative Hus¬
bandry Scheme and its free advice. He
is of course a tenant of the Gezireh
Scheme but he runs a good dairy herd,
a fruit orchard and is always trying
out* new crops.
We ask him a lot of questions about
the changes he has seen and what
he thinks of them. (We do not ask
these questions of the ordinary villagers
ours is a stratified society and at
the moment only the top counts, the
others will wait for a lead from the
omdahs and the chaikhs.) We ask him
what he thinks about the village
councils, the rural councils, how his
village has changed. After two or three
such questions he stops us. What is
Unesco, what does it do, what is
United Nations, how does it affect the
Sudan? We explain as best we can to
someone who still thinks of the Sudan
as a place called the Gezireh with some
other areas tacked on.
Apparently satisfied he allows us
to continue. He finds his people greatly
changed. Once upon a time he told
them to do something and they did it.
Now they want to know why. He does
not seem to resent this; changing times
have brought him success and perhaps
because of this he is tolerant. But he
feels that teaching must be slow.
Like many other success- (Continued
ful men he is inclined on neJtt
to look up on the peo-
pie as a bit silly. But his v '
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
SUDAN (continued)
comments are a useful corrective to
any ideas we may have of immediate
change. Slow and steady is his
motto. He feels that the rest of
the Sudan is rather remote but realizes
that all must stand together. Although
of course he thinks that the Gezireh
must stand in the lead.
He refuses to be drawn on the subject
of women. Since we know him well we
ask him how a country can really pro¬
gress while women occupy such an
inferior position. This is an important
question as the country faces a crisis.
There are so few teachers and social
workers and they are so hemmed about
with restrictions that it is very diffi¬
cult to make any progress at all. There
are of course practically no women
doctors, officials, or nurses or typists
or in fact any women doing the
jobs which are essential.
Between two worlds
Before we leave the village, almost
deserted in the intense heat, we
call in at a village council meeting
and discuss the disease of bilharzia
with the tenants. It is possible that
there will be no one there; it is hot,
perhaps someone has died, the headman
may have wanted to go to town. The
tenants swing between two worlds.
They have certain advantages; some
economic security and a comparatively
high income; plenty of space in which
to live so that the villages are not hud¬
dled and can be replanned; the possi¬
bilities of greater economic expansion
when the Roseires dam is built; more
social services than is normal.
On the other hand they are pulled
back by traditions and customs that
once did service, but now with changed
conditions are no longer of such value.
The women have but little idea of
looking after their children, and
dysentries and eye diseases are com¬
mon.
The men want everything to change
except their own daily lives, but they
are not yet ready to work for the chan¬
ges they desire. Through their tenants'
union they press for a bigger share
than their present forty per cent of
the revenue (forty to the Government
and twenty to the Board) without
wondering whether more money for
simply supervising under supervision is
justifiable or even sensible. They live
in a dream world of progress in the
shape of hospitals and schools and
clean water and other services but all
these things must be given to them.
Not a backward people
Fundamental education has rather a
strange job in a peculiar situation.
Here are no backward poverty
stricken people asking for help but the
people of an established society with a
certain economic level who need, per¬
haps in spite of themselves, to change
if they are not to be a hindrance to the
progress of their country. And in this
change they must be guided and
encouraged. It is not so very long ago
that they tended their flocks wherever
there was pasture and grew their crops
when the rains came or when they
could use the river for irrigation. Now
they find themselves part of one of the
world's great agricultural schemes
with all that such schemes entail of
progress and upheaval and they think
that everything can change except
their own private lives.
From the Unesco Newsroom
B OOKS FOR ALL: A new
Unesco documentary film, "Books for
All" is helping the development of
public libraries, by showing how the
Delhi Public Library organized jointly
by the Government of India and
Unesco is filling a vital need and
how it shares in programmes of popu¬
lar education. In its first three years
of operation, the Delhi Public Library
has already served over two million
persons. It now ttands as a model for
similar libraries in India and other
countries. The new Unesco film has
been produced in English, French and
Spanish versions.
* UNESCO'S EXPANDING FAM¬
ILY : Paraguay became Unesco's
73rd Member State on June 20
the Paraguayan Ambassador
to the United Kingdom deposited
his country's instrument of accep¬
tance of the Unesco Constitution
at the British Foreign Office.
Paraguay's entry completes mem¬
bership of Unesco by all the sta¬
tes of North and South America.
Ei_LdUCATION AROUND THE
WORLD : For the first time a truly
comprehensive picture is now available
of the state of education in the world.
Unesco's newly-published "World Sur¬
vey of Education" provides an amazing
array of statistical data and informa¬
tion, covering educational systems and
achievements in two hundred coun¬
tries and territories. Almost every
country in the world is represented.
Details are given on everything from
domestic science schools in Ruanda-
Urundi, Africa, to the syllabus of
primary schools in the Soviet Union.
While recording educational progress,
the book also points out that five out
of every ten children in the world
still do not attend schools at all.
COST OF NEWS : The flow
of news around the world is
hampered by the high cost of
press cables according to a report,
"The Problem of Transmitting
Press Messages", prepared jointly
by Unesco and the International
Telecommunication Union.
Charges made by different coun¬
tries for similar press communi¬
cation services may vary by over
300 %. Often, it costs twice as
much to cable news in one direc¬
tion as in the reverse. The
Unesco-ITU report is an overall
survey of press rates and facilities
throughout the world. It includes
Unesco recommendations to Mem¬
ber States for cutting rates and
favouring a freer flow of press
messages.
It»ETTER COPYRIGHT PRO¬
TECTION : The Universal Copyright
Convention, sponsored by Unesco and
now signed by forty States, will come
into force on September 16th. Twelve
of the signatory states have already
ratified it. The Convention will give
increased protection to authors, artists,
composers and other creative workers
and will also help encourage transla¬
tions. Until now, the world has been
divided into various groups of multi¬
lateral conventions, none of them
world-wide in scope.
BIGGER ALL THE TIME :
Fewer infants are dying and life
expectancy is going up in many
nations, reports the current U. N.
Demographic Yearbook. Al¬
though the birthrate is gradually
declining in many areas after a
postwar 1946-47 peak it still re¬
mains on a generally high level
in most of the world. The U. N.
numbers the world's population at
2,547,000,000 as of mid-1953. This
comprehensive collection of popu¬
lation statistics provides figures
for 183 countries and territories,
including statistics on population
density, mortality, migration, mar¬
riage and divorce.
It ADIO - ISOTOPE PROB¬
LEMS : An international group of
nuclear scientists meeting in Paris
recently urged Unesco to take steps
which would encourage the wider use
of radio- isotopes. Radio-isotopes are
the by-products of atomic reactors and
are now used extensively in industry,
medicine and research by physicists,
chemists and biologists. Since the
"life" that is, the radio-active period
of certain isotopes is very short,
delays in transport or in customs may
render them useless. Recommenda¬
tions made by the scientists for Unesco
action included : the drafting of in¬
ternational regulations to cover safety
measures needed in transport of iso¬
topes, proposal of a system to speed
customs clearance, action to reduce
allocation and sales formalities so that
isotopes will be more readily available
to qualified institutions and persons,
and the possible creation of an inter¬
national bulletin to supply information
on new uses of radio-isotopes.
PRESERVING THE PAST :
A centre is to be set up to collect
all available information on the
history of art and civilization in
ancient Egypt. Unesco will aid
the new centre in Egypt finan¬
cially, and the Egyptian Govern¬
ment will admmister it. Research
facilities will be offered to stu¬
dents and scholars of any natio¬
nality. A complete record is to
be kept of all remaining relics of
Egyptian life and art at the time
of the Pharaohs, thus preserving
for future generations invaluable
knowledge of man's cultural his¬
tory.
E DUCATIONAL LEADERS
MEET : Ministers of Education from
the countries of Central America and
Panama have just met for the first
time to discuss common educational
problems, and find ways to increase
educational and cultural cooperation.
The conference took place in Guate¬
mala City. Unesco, the United Na¬
tions and the International Labour
Organization all collaborated in the
work of the Conference.
CAN YOU IDENTIFY
THEIR NATIONALITIES?
The people shown in the photo¬
graphs on page 9 are all from Great
Britain.
(Photos C.O.I. , London.)
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 195S
1955 : BIG YEAR OF DECISION FOR TV
by Henry Cassirer
The spread of television throughout the world has been
phenomenal. Today there are some 60 "television
countries". Of these no fewer than 38 are operating
regular or experimental television services, and another
20 are planning to introduce them, or taking practical steps
toward that end.
Television can carry
a visual image across
the North American
continent and can
bring programmes
from London to Rome
or from Copenhagen
to Paris. The viewer
can be "on the spot"
for an event taking
place hundreds of mi¬
les away. In Morocco
and the Philippines,
in Japan and the
Soviet Union, on the
American continent
from Alaska in the.
far north to Argen¬
tina in the south,
television is opening
up new fields.
In what directions
is this enormous ex¬
pansion of television
leading? A survey
made by Unesco in
February 1955 (1)
shows that the power
of attraction intrinsic
in TV is so great that
sooner or later every
modern State con¬
templates its intro-
d u c t i o n. Although
obstacles may exist,
such as lack of eco¬
nomic resources, in¬
dustrial under-deve-
1 o p m e n t, mountain
ranges, vast distances
and dispersed popula¬
tions, nevertheless the
slogan "we must have
television ! " can be
heard from the Chi¬
lean Andes to the
deserts of Iraq, and
from the mountains
of Yugoslavia to the
plains of India. If
in Costa Rica or
Egypt, or in Portugal
or Australia, television may not yet be here today, present
plans indicate that it will certainly come tomorrow.
Television is part and parcel of the modern world and those
who still believe that they can close their eyes to it are liable
to find themselves overtaken by developments. They may
ignore television but it is sure that television will not ignore
their countries. This is not to say that television must ne¬
cessarily be welcomed. Its influence can be beneficial and it
can be the reverse. The pertinent question in most coun¬
tries today is not whether to have television, but to what
purpose and to what extent. The issue is, therefore: on
what lines will television develop and what will be its impact.
Closer examination of today's world television picture
suggests that 1955 will be the "year of television" for many
countries hitherto on the fringe of its development. To use
a military term for a
medium which can
vitally contribute to
peace, the "'infra¬
structure", that is
the network of trans¬
mitters and relay
systems, has made
great strides during
1954.
In Europe, the
number of stations
increased from 25 in
1953 to 76 in January
1955, while for the
first time eight Euro¬
pean countries (2)
were joined by tem¬
porary relay facilities
which are now gra¬
dually being turned
into permanent links.
The German Federal
Republic is covered by
a network from Ham¬
burg to Munich; Ita¬
ly's television extends
from the northern
frontier to south of
Rome at present, and
it will cover the entire
country, including
Sardinia and Sicily,
by the end of 1956;
France, which for
years had been mark¬
ing time with trans¬
mitters at Paris and
Lille, now has its
entire eastern region
covered, from Metz
through Strasbourg
and Lyons right
down to Marseilles in
the south. Many
smaller countries are
similarly caught up
in the race to expand
the scope of televi¬
sion by building new
transmitters and
relay links.
The result of this
expansion is reflected
in the sale and production of television receivers. Monthly
production in Germany was four times as large at the end of
1954 as at the beginning; in Italy, the advance of television
is no longer marked in tens but in hundreds of thousands of
receivers. This development, of course, falls far short of the
United States or the United Kingdom, with their 35 million
and 4 million receivers respectively. But the important point
is that in many countries, where in 1954 it was still regarded
as a questionable novelty, television has "caught on" in 1955,
and is now ready to go forward in '"snowballing dimensions"
within the limitations of national powers of production and
consumption.
(Photo N.K.H.. Tokyo)
(1) "Television, a world survey, supplement 1955". Unesco publication. Price :
Î.50; 3./; 750 Fr fr.
(2) Belgium, Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, Netherlands, Switzerland and
the United Kingdom.
In 1954 receivers in Canada exceeded
the million mark, and it thus became
the third country to reach this figure
(Continued on
next page.)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
1955 : TV YEAR
OF DECISION
(Continued)
after the United States and Great Britain. In 1955 a fourth
countrythe Soviet Union will be added to this list accord¬
ing to present plans for receiver output.
This year will also be significant in another way as it will
bring to an end the monopoly of non-commercial television
in Europe, and of commercial television in the United States.
The first commercial European television station went on the
air in 1954 in the Saar, quickly followed by stations in Monte-
Carlo and Luxembourg. This commercial development will
reach its apex in September 1955 with the inauguration of
telecasting by the Independent Television Authority in
England. In the United States educational television has to
struggle against great financial, political and organizational
odds. Nevertheless there are today already 14 educational
stations on the air serving a potential audience of 20 million
people, and many more are under construction.
The stakes in the future of television are so high that
questions of ownership and organization have given rise to
bitter controversy. Television was the subject of some of
the most animated sessions in the British and French par¬
liaments. It has led to rivalry between Swiss cities and in
Belgium between regions. Educational television is a poli¬
tical factor in Washington and in every state of the Union.
Practically every other country touched by television has
had its share of conflict.
Why all this heat? Because the pattern which is adopted
today will undoubtedly shape the future. Far-sighted men
are aware that a control on stations today may mean a hold
on the eye of the public tomorrow, and that the purposes of
television programmes which are now better developed will
determine the character of telecasting for a long time to
AROUND THE WORLD, television is finding its way into the homes of
all classes of people, helped by a decrease in the price of sets and the
availability of credit purchase facilities. Often replacing other forms of
distraction for those with moderate means, it has also changed the
skyline in hundreds of cities. (Photo taken by Henry Cassirer in Lens, France)
28
ASIA'S leading TV
country is Japan
where over 33,000
receivers were func¬
tioning towards the
end of 1 954. Japan
has both public and
private TV stations.
Here.achildren's pro¬
gramme is rehearsed
in Tokyo studios of
the Japanese Broad¬
casting Corporation.
come. A race is on, and it is open to question how the sup¬
porters of educational and cultural television will fare.
If television programming is examined, the first impression
gained is that television- can accomplish everything! from
spectacular variety shows in the United States, priced at
over $100,000, to simple but effective telecasts for school
children in Japan; from full length drama in the United
Kingdom to instructional broadcasts to French farmers;
from classical ballet in the Soviet Union to songs and folk¬
lore in Venezuela.
Uncanny power of pursuasion
There can be no doubt that the social and cultural condi¬
tions in each nation impress themselves upon its televi¬
sion system. In the United States a competitive eco¬
nomic system and the federal state structure have contri¬
buted to the rise of hundreds of television stations, with
different patterns of programmes and of ownership, which
give viewers in many cities a choice between more than seven
different stations.
In the Soviet Union, where not only television but all
entertainment media are functions of the state, it can bring
to the viewer the latest films, theatre and opera performan¬
ces, or any public sports event, without regard to legal or
contractual restrictions. In Germany, television faithfully
reflects the federal structure of the Federal Republic. ' Here,
programmes are originated from a greater number of places
than in any other country in the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
EUROPE'S contri¬
bution to use of TV
as a link between
nations began in 1952
when programmes
were first exchanged.
Last year, eight coun¬
tries used relay
networks to transmit
programmes giving a
picture of each coun¬
try. Left, base of
link aerials near Do¬
ver, England part
of this network. (BBC
Copyright photo.)
In France and Britain, on the other hand, television
expresses the centralization of much of the cultural life in
the capitals, though the provinces constantly seek to assert
themselves. While television is mass education in Colombia,
it's mainly middle class entertainment in Mexico. There Is
no rigid and immutable structure and it can and must be
adapted to national needs and traditions.
With due regard to national differences and the efforts
made to enhance educational programming, it remains true
to say that television is being developed primarily as a source
of mass entertainment. There is no doubt that this will
always remain a fruitful field as much of this entertainment
can make a cultural contribution and bring joy and relaxa¬
tion to working people caught in the monotony of modern
life. But there is more to television than mere entertain¬
ment. Its use for education of children and of adults alike,
its power to make knowledge of science or geography, his¬
tory or economics visually accessible to the many. Here is a
field for fruitful exploitation and development.
Television is taking root today in countries where illiteracy
and utter poverty, ignorance of healthy living and of modern
methods of production, are widespread among large sections
of the people. Advertisers have long realized television's
uncanny power of persuasion and demonstration. Cannot
these same powers serve fundamental education and change
our entire approach to the problem of informing people in
less developed countries on ways to improve their conditions
of life? This is a subject, rich in promise, to which Unesco is
now giving particular attention. Here is a challenge for
constructive forces to bring their influence to bear upon the
future shape of television.
Another trend which has shown significant advance in
1954, is the use of television as a link between all nations.
International co-operation .between stations, by relay, film,
or adaptation of programmes, is gradually becoming normal
practice. In Europe, individual countries frequently find
themselves unable to cope with the vast demand for pro¬
grammes, because television devours money, talent and faci¬
lities. Through international exchange by direct relay, these
countries increase their resources - and enrich their pro¬
grammes* Film telecasts flow out from the United States or
reach viewers there from foreign countries.
Danger of standardized ideas
Herein lies both danger and opportunity. The danger is
that this most centralized and costly of all communi¬
cation media will further subject national and regional
cultures to the standardization of ideas and tastes of a few
world production centres. The opportunity lies in the possi¬
bility of hearing and seeing on television the people of ano¬
ther nation and another culture. Here television may serve
peace by narrowing the gap between man's public life, whose
fate is in the hands of world-wide forces, and the circle of
his personal experience, which is confined to the narrow
range of the individual. World Television in 1955 stands
at the threshold.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ART REVIVAL
for Ecuador's Indians
by Lilo Linke
Creative Indian art in Ecuador was supposed to
have ceased with the Spanish conquest, after
which Indian artisans and craftsmen chiefly
worked under European guidance on magnificent
baroque churches like " La Compañía " (right)
In Quito. Today, helped by a special art education
centre, Indian artists are once more showing
the traditional talents and skills of their ancestors.
The people of Quito's most elegant district have got used
to the sight of groups of Indians walking into a large
modern house as if it were their home. "'That crazy
artist Jan Schreuder is giving them their painting lesson",
they remark.
Jan Schreuder is neither crazy nor does he pretend to
teach the Indians how to paint. All he does is to provide
encouragement and the material facilities so that the
Indians may follow their own inspiration.
Until recently, Indian art in Ecuador was considered to be
something of the past. Creativeness was supposed to have
come to an end with the Spanish conquest, about four
hundred years ago. The only thing generally admitted was
that the Indians had shown amazing ability as artisans
working under Spanish guidance. Stone cutters and wood
carvers above all had transformed the many colonial
churches into admirable examples of Spanish baroque art.
Thanks to these buildings, Quito is today the delight of
tourists from all over the world.
Among the many foreigners who established themselves
in Ecuador during recent decades were several artists. They
were enthralled by the grandeur of the Andean landscape
and the picturesque costumes and customs of the natives.
Using the Indians at first simply as models, they gradually
arrived at a deeper appreciation of their personality and
capacities.
Already a number of Ecuadorian anthropologists and
similar experts had worked on behalf of the Indians. They
were now joined by Jan Schreuder and other artists in an
endeavour to provide an outlet for Indian creativeness.
Jan Schreuder, a Dutchman by birth, first came to Ecuador
fifteen years ago. For many years, he painted on his own,
then, in 1952, he opened a centre of art education for
children and adults (Centro Ecuatoriano de Arte) in the
capital. The very building which he designed for it indica-
30
ted his intentions. Its windows frame part of the town and
the ever-green mountains behind it, with here and there a
glimpse of eternal snow. The entire second floor is occupied
by a huge studio which is also a museum of Indian art and
folklore from various Latin American countries.
For all foreigners who arrive in Quito with an interest in
the colourful aspects of native Andean culture, a visit to Jan
Schreuder's studio has therefore become one of the highlights
of their stay. They will find small clay figures excavated
on the coast and more than a thousand years old, as well
as pottery-cows baked only recently in some primitive kiln
. in a lonely Andean village ; ancient jewellery and modern
"mates", the gourds which Peruvian Indians decorate with
whirling processions of figures that tell the story of some
historic event or of a native fiesta ; textiles from Guatemala
and Peru, and masks from Mexico.
4 Rondador ' and ' Pingullo ' music
They will hear records of Indian music played on the
traditional instruments, the "rondador" (pipes of Pan),
the drum and the little flute known as '"pingullo".
But, more exciting, they will see the Indians of today
painting at the easel or bent over the long table busy at
some intricate design.
Matilde, for instance, is a little girl of twelve. She belongs
to the tribe of Otavalo Indians, famous for its weaving. Two
years ago, Matilde came to Quito with her whole family
because Jan Schreuder had offered to help her father
improve his weaving technique. One day, while they were
all visiting Jan's studio, she timidly picked up a brush and
was so thrilled by the splashes of colour she could produce
with it that Jan allowed her to come regularly and paint.
She always brings her little brother Segundo, now ten, and
her little sister Luchita.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
Like fine embroidery
Reflowering of Indian art has
been largely stimulated in Ecua¬
dor by a Dutchman, Jan Schreu¬
der, seen with Otavalo Indians
(left). He has helped them adapt
traditional art and handicrafts
to modern needs. Right, pupils
painting in Schreuder's studio.
Above, lino cuts of people and
animals made bySalasaca Indians.
(Photos Jan Schreuder)
What did these children want to express ? Matilde's first
painting was a group of Indians with their animals, in vivid
colours against the background of Imbabura, their sacred
mountain. Her work, like that of the other Indians, is
constantly concerned with their agricultural life : ploughing
the fields, planting the seeds, harvest and fiestas.
Among the other Indians who come regularly to Jan's
studio are two Salasaca youths of 19 and 21. The Salasaca
Indians come from an arid region some 80 miles south of
the capital. Unlike the Otavalo Indians, they are still
opposed to contact with the whites. Catholic and Protestant
missionaries have been working among them, trying to break
down the barriers, but of equal importance have been the
efforts of such people as Jan Schreuder to make the
Salasacas renounce their hostility.
The Otavaleño men dress in large blue ponchos that cover
the whole figure, and wear their smooth black hair in a
thick braid plaited at the nape. The Salasacas wear black
ponchos not much wider than a towel, and cut their hair
page-boy fashion.
Their style of painting is strongly influenced by the
embroidery a combination of cross and chain stitches
which has always been a pastime of the Salasaca men. They
handle the brush as delicately as if it were a needle and
obtain with gouache and water-colours a similar effect to
that produced by their yarns. Their motifs are scenes from
their own life, but one of the characteristics of their art is
the apparently unconnected juxtaposition of people and
animals.
The artistic expressions of all Indians are particularly
valuable since they offer the white man a chance to get to
know the inner life of an otherwise extremely reserved and
even hostile people. No verbal intimacy has ever been
established. Now the paintings can serve as a vital link in
human communications.
But Jan Schreuder has done more. At first under the
auspices of the Ecuadorian Institute of Anthropology and
Geography and of late under those of the International
Labour Office, one of the specialized organizations of the
United Nations, he has been teaching a group of Indians to
improve their weaving techniques and to make use of tra¬
ditional patterns for purposes of decoration.
The idea originated from Schreuder's experiences in
Guatemala where native handicrafts not only added the
colourful touch necessary to attract foreign tourists, but
also provided the Indians with an important source of
income. Guatemaltecan textiles have found their way even
beyond the western hemisphere. Jan Schreuder wanted to
guide the Ecuadorian Indians along the same lines not by
copying anything foreign, but by giving free play to native
creativeness and native patterns of Ecuador.
Traditional arts for modern living
So far, a great variety of wall-hangings, table covers and
mats, napkins and other textiles have been woven on
improved looms. At the same time the women learned
to perfect the handspun yarn by better methods of cleaning
and dyeing the raw wool and by the use of the spinning
wheel, not hitherto known among the Salasacas.
Thus, far from attempting to make the Indians renounce
their traditional ways, Jan Schreuder has insisted on their
purposely adapting traditional art and handicrafts to
modern living.
A further value derives from the fact that each object is
hand-produced. Do we not all try to escape the soul-killing
machine and encourage creativeness wherever we find it?
And who is more creative than the Indian, whose work starts
already with the careful selection of the raw materials he
himself produces, and who puts into every object he manu¬
factures a whole world of imagination?
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The traveller arriving for the first
time in Bombay is struck by an
impression of lavish luxury side
by side with the poorest kind of slums.
And he will probably ask himself how
many of the people in the well-to-do
neighbourhoods know or care about the
uprooted masses living nearby. For
my part, I thought of the week-end
work camps organized in the Paris
suburbs by the Service Civil Interna¬
tional, and of the many American
Friends Service Committee camps in
the poorer quarters of New York and
Chicago.
But it was not long before I learned
that in Bombay, as
in other big cities,
there are groups of
people who do know
and who do care.
They are doing
something about it,
too, and on a much
larger scale than
any work camps in
Europe or in the
United States. They
belong to Rashtra
3eva Dal, and their
work squads known
as Sane Guruji Sevf.
Patak go into the
slums, in teams some
10 to 30 strong,
to launch clean-up
campaigns and ini¬
tiate people into
the fundamentals of
health, sanitation
and child care.
Followers of Gandhi,
they use drama and
music to get their
points across, and
their shows draw
thousands on public
squares.
But Rashtra Seva
Dai's main task is
the improvement of
conditions in rural
areas where 80 %
of India's popula¬
tion live. I got my
first glimpse of this
work at Hadaspar,
not far from Poona,
where 3,000 volun¬
teers (550 of them .
women), were "bunding" on a co¬
operative farm formed by small land¬
holders whose plots are too minute to
be worked individually.
Bunding, I learned, means digging
the earth and heaping it into long
dikes to protect the crops from the sun
and wind. The volunteers in the camp
came from all walks of life students,
farmers, engineers, architects, doctors,
teachers, craftsmen and shop-keepers.
Not many Indian work camps,
however, are as large as this. Usually,
they consist of 20 to 30 selected
volunteers, as in the case of Taranagar,
near Hyderabad. There, I joined a
group of students working with the
villagers to lay the ' foundations of a
library and to rebuild the local
teacher's living quarters. When the
students first came to Taranagar, three
years ago, the villagers asked them to
repair a ruined temple, inhabited by a
huge cobra. The students and the
peasants cleared the underbrush from
the temple, killed the snake and
converted the ruined building into a
community centre.
Since then, every year, Hyderabad
students spend their vacations carrying
out projects suggested by the villagers.
A school has been opened and a teacher
found for it, a market built, and a
major road repaired. Hyderabad's
Health Department helped to spray
mud huts with DDT and to distribute
anti-malaria pills. Soakage pits, com¬
post heaps and smokeless cholas
(stoves) were built. A co-operative
was opened in 1954, and this year,
chapaties (India's wheat pancake
bread), vegetables, curry and curds in
a bamboo hut covered with mats and
plastered with mud and cow-dung.
During the meal, dozens of villagers on
their way to a nearby temple, stopped
in and said "hello". They all glanced
at our plates and probably were pleased
to note that the international cuisine
was no different from their own.
Ingrid, the camp housemother, who
is a trained nurse, knew many of these
people. Their wives often came to look
at her kitchen with its stove burning
waste wood instead of cow-dung. Any
new "home appliance" always drew a
crowd. Besides, it was Ingrid who kept
YOUTH VOLUNTEERS
across the face of India
by
Hans Peter
Müller
Hans Peter Müller is Secretary of the Coordination
Committee for International Voluntary Work Camps.
With the aid of Unesco, he recently spent three
months In India to promote the development of
international voluntary work camps and to help link
local groups with similar organizations in other coun¬
tries.
Taranagar plans to build an adult
education centre.
It is a long trek from Hyderabad to
the Service Civil International camp at
Matras in the State of Bihar which
had suffered terribly during the floods
of August 1954. Many villages were
still isolated from the outside world
and when I left the railway station at
Dharbanga, I had to wade over paddy
fields for nearly three-quarters of an
hour, with water up to my knees and a
heavy suitcase on my shoulders, heart¬
ily wishing I had carried a rucksack
instead.
At Matras, a village of 1,100 inhabi¬
tants, the project consisted of re¬
building the school which had been
washed away, and also of constructing
a "Govardham" or earth platform to
shelter the villagers and their cattle
in the event of another flood. The
villagers were giving one day a week
of voluntary labour to work with the
international team consisting of two
Indians, a Pakistani, a Swiss, a French¬
man and a German girl.
After hauling baskets of earth all
the morning, we had our lunch of
C L E A RING
FLOOD DEBRIS,
is a job at which even
youngsters can lend
a hand. Here, school¬
children in Himalayan
village of Kajjiar give
up their recreation
time to aid Swiss
work camp volunteers.
the team's first-aid kit and, as time
went by, she had to institute visiting
hours for her dispensary so as not to
he "invaded" at all hours. The inter¬
national team had become a demons¬
tration in fundamental education.
As we finished our meal, we were
startled by an unusual uproar outside
the hut. The mud platform at the
back was swarming with teen-agers in
"dhotis" and shorts. More than two
hundred of them had come with their
teacher to help.
Soon the schoolboys were digging
lumps of earth with whatever they
could find and, forming a human
chain, passing the big chunks up to the
platform. By the end of the afternoon
the results of their work were very
visible they had not lost a minute
and they returned to Dharbanga,
walking and wading all over again.
This example is a good illustration
of the great possibilities of small work
camp groups in India. They can
induce thousands of young people to
work on community service projects in
a country where manual labour is still
regarded in many circles as degrading.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N" 6. 1955
In India, a tradition going back to
the Vedic age, once made it a duty for
every individual to give certain services
to his community: "Gyandan" the
gift of knowledge; "Dhanda" the gift
of wealth; and "Shramdan" the gift
of labour. Every physically fit man
had to make this gift of labour at least
once in his lifetime.
Gandhi, who coined the phrase
"work is worship", revived these
ancient traditions, and, more recently,
Vinoba Bhave initiated a new move-
. ment the "Bhoodan" or land gift
which may set off an economic revo¬
lution.
Many who have studied these
movements believe that Shramdan and
Bhoodan herald a renaissance that
will not halt at India's borders, but
will spread to all South-East Asia. In
any event, Shramdan and Bhoodan
have become magic words in India.
When on leaving Matras I took the
train at Dharbanga, one of my fellow
passengers stared at me and said to his
neighbour in Hindi: "He's one of the
Shramdan wallahs. I saw him working
with the others." A hush came over
the carriage, but it was soon broken by
questions about the work, the volun¬
teers and the camp. Several young¬
sters announced that they would go to
Matras with their friends to work. A
little later, I changed trains, but my
new fellow travellers were equally
interested, and two men told me: "We
want to devote a year to this work."
Last December, the Kosi Area Bharat
Seva Samaj (a voluntary service asso-
HELP1NG THE COOK, members of an international team in the Himalayas prepare
vegetables for Sunday lunch (top photo). This team has helped to lay one and a half miles
of wooden channels (hewn from tree trunks) to bring water over steep hillside terraces
to a village. Village teacher with some of his pupils and students from Calcutta and South
India (bottom photo) lift a heavy beam as they construct the roof of a new school.
(Service Civil Intl. photos}
ciation) wired India's Ministry of
Irrigation and Power in Delhi that
local citizens had decided to begin work
on eight miles oí the eastern Kosi
embankment.
This telegram may mark the
beginning of a new phase of local
participation in India's development
programme. The Kosi Valley Project
is a multi-purpose dam on the lines of
Tennessee Valley Authority. It will
not only control floods on the wild
Kosi river racing from its source in
Nepal to the Ganges valley, but will
also furnish irrigation water and elec¬
tric power.
In India, where power machinery is
often not available, the speed with
which large-scale projects are complet¬
ed depends on public co-operation.
And this is where work camps have an
important part to play. If the millions
who live in the valleys of the Kosi and
the Ganges can be awakened and
encouraged to co-operate, they will do
the job of a thousand bull-dozers and
they will know that they are working
for themselves.
The Kosi project was worked out by
the Indian Planning Commission in
co-operation with the Nepalese Govern¬
ment. Thus, Indian voluntary work
camps will have their first chance of
action on an international scale.
In India itself, the scope of their
work is ever increasing. Last year,
the Co-ordination * Committee for
International Voluntary Work Camps
estimated the total number of camps
in India to be nearly 450. In 1955, the
number of camps will be at least 1,000
with a total of some 50,000 volunteers.
To staff these camps, a training centre
for leaders was started near Delhi
early "in 1955, while other leader
training courses have been organized
in Hyderabad and Bangalore.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A French village's views on foreigners
(Cont'd {rom page 19)
It has already been suggested that most of the time people's
ideas of foreigners come from daily news and from sources of
political information. It seemed of interest to correlate the
answers to the question "Are you interested in politics?"
with those to the two questions on foreigners. The answers
were:
Did not answer
either question
on foreigners
3
22
9
Answered only Answered only
the first the second
Answered
both
Yes 	
No	,
No
Indication.
1
5 4
1
15
15
1
This table does not take into account a few answers that
could not be fitted into this framework; e.g., to the question
"Are you interested in politics?", the reply "A little at election
time"; or, to the question about foreigners: "One people is as
good as another."
This table makes it clear that those who are interested in
politics replied, for the most part, to the two questions
concerning foreigners, while those who claim not to be
interested in politics fell into two groups those who replied
and those who did not.
*
O'pinions in respect of
foreigners spring from three
different ways of looking at
things. Yet, even though these
opinions may vary, behaviour is identical in the case of
most people in Nouville. Little aggressiveness is displayed
towards the foreigner; when it does appear, it is merely in
verbal terms and as a reaction to some unpleasant event; it
is not systematic.
The wealth of information from outside of Nouville
compared with the meagre information available within the
village, here assumes its full importance.
In practice, the news which comes to hand about foreign
countries, with little if anything in the way of explanation,
is passed around at Nouville in the form of gloomy remarks:
"Did you see what it said in the paper? Things don't look too
good !" . And so the question of foreigners imperceptibly be¬
comes the question of the difficulties between foreign coun¬
tries.
*
F or the inhabitants of
Nouville, the people in all
foreign countries are "'always
human beings", and, while
these countries are seen in an abstract way, they evoke a
concrete picture in the minds of these French villagers.
Their standard of reference is France, which also is a con¬
crete country made up of people, of Frenchmen, and the
feeling is that "these people are just the same as we are."
Thus, for the inhabitant of Nouville, the term "foreigner"
brings to mind above all someone who speaks a different lan¬
guage.
For those foreigners who come from a country other than.
France, either contacts have been established with them over
a sufficiently long period and they are then "people like
ourselves" (for example, the foreigners who live in Nouville
or the German soldiers who were stationed there for a long
time), or no contact has been made, in which case they re¬
main unknown, "foreigners" in the full sense of the word.
The villagers have no personal experience of these people ;
they live far away in "'mysterious", "exotic" lands. "Beyond
the forest," said a very old lady of Nouville, speaking of the
Chinese. What is known about them inspires wonder or
"makes one shudder". Even in this case, the people of Nou¬
ville know nothing of their history nor their legends, and
have nothing to turn to except stereotyped memories of
school lessons and the clichés of the modern town criers, the
broadcaster and the journalist.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER con be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors ore listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
55I-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ej'nar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O.B. 1 20, Addis-Ababa.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Kcs-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, 1 9, Avenue
Kléber, Paris- 1 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Librairie H. Kauffman, 28, Rue
du Stade, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iran : Iranian National Commission for
.Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P.O. Box 5 1 54. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings,
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori -N¡chôme,
Nihonbashï, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea : Korean National Commission for
Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : J. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
and Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore i
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 1 35,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N V. Martinus Nij'hoff,
Lange Voorhout 9. The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre
1 00, Hackthorne Rd., Christchurch.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokhande', Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475
5th Ave., New York 17, N.Y.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Courier
* WINDOW OPEN ON TMK WORLD
PHOTOGRAPHY, INTERNATIONAL LANGUAGE
Its role in modern civilization. A new art form. Its use in the preservation
of old paintings and in detecting fakes.
MAMMOTH SCHOOL VENTURE -
Schools in the desert for Palestine
Arab refugees. The story of one of
the biggest educational ventures in¬
ternational organizations have attemp¬
ted to tackle anywhere in the world.
MAN AND THE DESERT. An exciting
60-page issue on the latest world-wide efforts
to make the desert bloom. Developments in
solar energy, wind energy, fresh water from
sea, soilless cultivation, artificial rain-making,
myths about the tropics, old rain gods of
primitive peoples.
ARE WOMEN INFERIOR BEINGS?
Advances in women's status in recent
years in education, politics, society.
WHAT'S WRONG WITH OUR
TEXTBOOKS? Distortion of his¬
tory in school books. Textbook
publishinga great unknown indus¬
try.
SUBSCRIBE TO THE UNESCO COURIER TODAY. - English, French, Spanish, U.S. editions
ONE FULL YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION AT THE AMAZINGLY LOW PRICE OF :
300 French francs; 6/-; $1.50 or equivalent in local currency (U.S. edition $2.50).
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Courier
HANDS BREAK DOWN
A LANGUAGE BARRIER
They can't speak each other's language. And so this Japanese expert in ceramics, weaving
and bamboo handicrafts (top photo) uses sign talk to converse with his Thai trainee.
He was sent by the International Labour Organization to help the Unesco Fundamental
Education Centre at Chachangsao, Thailand, in the training of adults, teachers and pupils.
It is hoped to start a modern handicrafts programme in primary and secondary schools.
Each morning the flag is raised outside the school (bottom photo) while students sing the
national anthema ceremony repeated in schools throughout Thailand. (ILO Newsphotos.)
]]>
</page>
</document>
