<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069416eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A selection from the
Unesco 40th anniversary issue
0
<a
**> ,
Trvasurtw
Hnr/a
gano»*
/.//< Wir/».
tCM>*
OCtASS
Un00**
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A message
to world youth
YOUNG people form a considerable and ever-increasing proportion
of the world population. Inevitably they are concerned by all the
problems arising from the present and future of humanity. None of
the major questions of our time can be answered without the active
involvement of young people.
Young people constitute 45 per cent of the world's population today and
their numbers are continuing to grow. There were 730 million fifteen- to
twenty-four-year-olds in 1975, and this figure should rise to 1,180 million by
the year 2000 an increase of 60 per cent in twenty-five years.
If the role and impact of youth in national life vary from country to
country, young people in many cases share a number of common preoccu¬
pations, fears and aspirations.
In many countries young people are particularly exposed to such prob¬
lems as unemployment, hunger, delinquency, drugs, violence and racism,
all of which are rooted in the tensions and uncertainties of today. But young
people are also endowed with imagination, enthusiasm, and courage,
qualities which may contribute to the changes which prove necessary; they
stand at the meeting-point of continuity and change, tradition and progress.
The different groups of young people must have the opportunity to
participate fully in all aspects of the economic, political, educational,
cultural, and scientific life of the society in which they live, and to exercise
freely in it the qualities which are theirs.
Unesco, which places action in favour of young people at the heart of its
programmes, notably those concerned with education and training, is
making its contribution to the achievement of this goal.
Unesco's efforts in this field are focused on three main objectives:
stimulating research on young people in the different world regions;
promoting the diffusion and exchange of information about and for young
people; contributing to the formulation of policies and the application of
programmes which will encourage the participation of young people in all
aspects of the life of societies .
January 1985
TU'*' böty
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
LE COURRIER
~* " * '
Le programme de l'Unesco
pour 1948
it cMritiict ifiiir i aturi
ni miHif n Mimt, nn
Wwjidblf ffmiij
fi» Wi
Le 1,11,(2.-1 défia
rix. .. »:.!«.«
.
.
__
AS a contribution to the celebrations
marking Unesco's 40th anniversary,
the Editors of the Unesco Courier
have compiled for readers an anthology of
articles and illustrations which have
appeared in the magazine since it began
publication almost 39 years ago. All the
articles have been shortened. (Above, cover
of the first number, published in February
1948.) Although any such selection is bound
to be to some extent arbitrary, we have been
guided by a number of criteria. Firstly, we
have given coverage to major Unesco preoc¬
cupations and spheres of activity such as
hunger and world peace, racism and human
rights, the environment and the cultural
heritage, science and technology, education
and literacy, youth and the condition of
women. Secondly, we have tried to reflect
the magazine's aspiration to be a "window
open on the world", through which peoples
and countries can be viewed on equal terms,
irrespective of geographical position or de¬
mographic, economic or political weight,
with the main focus on their cultural riches
and their human and ecological problems.
Thirdly, we have included a selection of
work by writers occupying a leading posi¬
tion in their own culture or internationally,
and who by virtue of their contributions to
the Courier have also signalled their attach¬
ment to the ideals of Unesco.
Cover: Marking the Unesco Courier's 39 years of
publication, a display of 39 issues in many
languages. Photo Princelle, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
The Courier
A window open on the world
May-June 1986
39th year
A message to world youth
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
The roots of a growing world crisis
My lastest work a wall
by Joan Miró
PEACE
Nuclear weapons and world sanity
by Linus Pauling
WORLD HUNGER
Food for a hungry world
by Antoine Dakouré
11
RACISM
Apartheid: the shameful record
by Basil Davidson 12
Racism today: 'Us' and 'Them'
by Albert Memmi 14
The forbidden dialogue by Lewis Nkosi 15
Pictures in our heads by Otto Klineberg 16
THE ENVIRONMENT
The menace of 'extinct' volcanoes
by Haroun Tazieff 17
The shocking slaughter of Africa's wild life
by Sir Julian Huxley 18
Will deserts drink icebergs?
by Paul-Emile Victor 19
LANDS AND CULTURES
Fifty years of literary life
by Ba Jin 20
Night thoughts, November 1926
by Lu Xun 21
The angry young men of Oceania
by Albert Wendt 22
The Afro-Brazilian experiment
by Gilberto Freyre 24
Where gods and men have mingled
by Jorge Amado 25
'I was born 1,000 years ago'
by Dan George 26
Ishi the last of the Yana Indians
by Alfred Métruux 27
The blacks in Latin America
by Alejo Carpentier 28
The land-locked island of Paraguay
by Augusto Roa Bastos 30
The Chronicle of Michoacán,
by J. M. G. Le Clézio 31
EDUCATION
An illiterate in Paris
Interview by Marguerite Duras 32
A 21-point programme
for a global strategy in education 33
SCIENCE
Science, technology and man
Nobel Prize-Winners' Round Table 36
The truth behind the veil of facts
by José Ortega y Gasset 38
The candle of learning
by Abdus Salam 38
TECHNOLOGY
My first steps in space
by Aleksei Leonov 39
CHILDHOOD
African childhood by Cámara Laye 40
The sting in the fairy tale
by Jorge Enrique Adoum 42
Disabled characters in search of an author
by Tordis Orjasaeler 43
All about Alice by Anthony Burgess 44
HUMAN RIGHTS
A Third World view of human rights
by Radhika Coomaraswamy 45
WOMEN
Women of the Mediterranean:
tradition and change by Niliifer Gale 46
Self-portrait of a woman writer
by Ding Ling 47
THE SPOKEN AND THE WRITTEN WORD
The image and the word
by Alberto Moravia 48
The yestermorrow of the book
by Marshall McLuhan 50
COMMUNICATION
Man, the first walkie-talkie by Victor Bunak 51
Tongues that span the centuries
by Amadou Hampâlé Bâ 52
The non-aligned countries pool their news
by Pero ¡vacie 53
THE BOOK
On translation by Octavio Paz
Painted manuscripts
of pre-Columbian America
by Miguel Angel Asturias
54
55
CULTURAL IDENT1
Today's crisis in anthropology
by Claude Lévi-Strauss
The building blocks of culture
by Cheikh Anta Diop
The writer between two worlds
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
TY
56
58
59
THE CULTURAL HERITAGE
'The action of a man who snatches
something from death' by André Malraux 60
GREAT MEN
Miniature anthology of works by Al-Biruni 61
Lenin and the physical sciences
by Mstislav Keldysh 62
Portrait of Rabindranath Tagore
by Satyajit Ray 63
Leonardo da Vinci, or the glory of painting
by Carlo Pedretti 64
Year of peace: 5
Letter from Nagasaki by Takashi Nagai 66
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Slnhala
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 5/6 - 1986 - CPD - 86 - 1 - 434 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The roots of a
Extracts from a collective text by:
YOSHIO ABE, Professor, University of Tokyo;
SAMIR AMIN, Director, African Institute for Eco¬
nomic Development and Planning, Dakar;
MARGARET J. ANSTEE, Deputy Regional
Director, Bureau for Latin America, United Na¬
tions Development Programme, New York;
BECHIR BENYAHMED, Director of Jeune
Afrique magazine, Paris;
WILBERT CHAGULA, Minister for Economic
Affairs and Development Planning, United Re¬
public of Tanzania;
JEAN-MARIE DOMENACH, Director of Esprit
magazine, Paris;
MARION DÖNHOFF, Chief Editor of the weekly
Die Zeit, Hamburg;
ABDUL-RAZZAK KADDOURA, former Rector,
University of Damascus; Assistant Director-
General, Science Sector, Unesco, April 1976- );
ALFRED KASTLER, Member of the French
Academy of Sciences, Nobel Prize for Physics;
M.G.K. MENON, Secretary, Department of Elec¬
tronics, Government of India;
YEHUDI MENUHIN, Former President, Interna¬
tional Music Council, Unesco, Paris;
CHARLES MORAZE, Director, Institute of Stu¬
dies for Social and Economic Development, Uni¬
versity of Paris;
AURELIO PECCEI, Chairman of the Club of
Rome, Italy;
RAUL PREBISCH, Former Special Representa¬
tive of the Secretary General, United Nations
Emergency Operation, New York;
RADOVAN RICHTA, Director, Institute of Phi¬
losophy and Sociology of the Czechoslovak
Academy of Sciences, Prague;
JOAQUIN RUIZ-JIMENEZ, Professor, Universi¬
ty of Madrid;
ABDUL AZIZ EL SAYED, Former Director-
General, The Arab Educational, Cultural and
Scientific Organization, Paris;
VADIM SOBAKIN, Professor of International
Law, Moscow.
WE are now undergoing a period of
profound and rapid, though uneven,
and not infrequently crisis-ridden,
change. This change is largely connected
with the ever-increasing power available to
man through the development of science and
technology.
Technology is ambivalent. On the one hand
it has brought immense benefits to mankind.
On the other, it has resulted in an incredible
accumulation of destructive devices. Fur¬
thermore, the contradictions inherent in the
transfer of technology from the industrial cen¬
tres to the developing areas of the world have
brought very serious maladjustments and dis¬
ruptions. Inequalities have been accentuated
and an extraordinary demographic growth is
taking place.
One thing is beyond doubt: none of the
urgent problems facing mankind today and
tomorrow can be solved successfully if the
conditions of peace are not ensured, if the
relaxation of international tension is not trans¬
formed into an irreversible process and if the
enormous resources today still tied up with
armaments are not gradually released for hu¬
man development.
Photo Dominique Roger - Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
growing world crisis
Efforts for the consolidation of peace, which
is to be understood as a just and democratic
system of international relations based on the
principles of peaceful coexistence and not
simply as the absence of war, should be ex¬
panded in all spheres, from economics to
science, from diplomacy to culture.
Annual expenditure on the arms race is
probably around 200 to 250 billion dollars a
sum equal to the total national income of
those countries in which the majority of man¬
kind is living. At the same time 2,500 million
men and women live a largely precarious
existence at levels of nutrition below the
acceptable minimum.
The present growth-rate of these popula¬
tions is such that their number is expected to
double in 25 years.
The currently accessible resources of the
earth have their limits. Within the space of a
few generations we are frittering away re¬
serves of energy below the ground which
nature has taken thousands of millions of
years to accumulate. In the immediate future
there is a danger that we shall destroy, without
a thought for future generations, the plants ^
Illustrations to this article symbolize the
evolution of the human outlook from that
of the small community and the region to a
trulyglobalperspective. Photo far left Is of
a statue by the Swiss sculptor Alberto
Giacometti which stands in a patio at Un¬
esco's headquarters in Paris.
», ' *A -^r
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
and trees produced over the ages. In the last
fifty years, nine-tenths of the forests of some
tropical islands have disappeared.
Under the pressure of either justified or
artificial imperatives designed to maintain
economic growth, increase consumption or
satisfy it without heeding the consequences,
today's generations are plundering and pollut¬
ing nature.
Thus the very fact that our resources
(whether renewable or not) are limited would
indicate that the "Western model" of develop¬
ment cannot be applied everywhere or at all
times.
In some societies where they are firmly
established, industrialization and technology
deprive individuals and groups of the possibil¬
ity of influencing their living conditions, and
hence their own destiny.
Human rights and freedoms are threatened
by multiple intrusions into private life. As a
result of the spread of computer science and
communication techniques, life is being con¬
ditioned on the basis of surveys whose aims in
some cases are to a certain extent inquisitor¬
ial. Thus some of the industrialized countries
must undertake a new kind of struggle to
defend human rights, the very notion of which
is an empty promise for the masses of the
developing countries who are deprived of the
most elementary means of satisfying their
needs.
These considerations emphasize the close
interdependence of the problems facing the
modern world. We are not faced with distinct
problems, each of which we may try to solve
separately and in isolation. A global view must
therefore be a prerequisite to any attempt to
solve the different problems of today. The
United Nations declaration on a New Interna¬
tional Economic Order can be regarded as an
event of world-wide significance.
We must give up thinking of the centres of
economic power as the sole repositories of
truth, civilization and universality. It has been
held in certain quarters that industrial growth,
modelled on that of certain European or North
American centres, would itself bring about a
general improvement in human conditions,
each nation being free to reproduce the pro¬
posed pattern for itself. We must face the fact
that this is not so.
Once it is seen as global, development can
no longer be the direct extension to the whole
world of the knowledge, ways of thought, life
styles or experiences specific to a single re¬
gion of the world; each local development
must be related to its own values and culture.
It is not enough to transfer the sum total of
the knowledge available in developed coun¬
tries to the developing countries; to do this
excludes the possibility of any genuine im¬
plantation of science and technology in the
countries at the receiving end. It favours the
"brain drain" and even slows down the gener¬
al advancement of knowledge.
The immediate problem facing the develop¬
ing countries is that of establishing an infra¬
structure for science. As long as this does not
exist, there can be no authentic scientific de¬
velopment, but only transplantation of im¬
ported science, which does not correspond to
the true needs of the country.
The kind of scientific development which
does correspond to the needs of a country can
only be based on an awareness of its civiliza¬
tion, traditions and values.
Whilst science has been concerned with
discovering knowledge and understanding
nature, its applications have been largely gov¬
erned by the profit motive to the benefit of
small sections of human society groups or
countries.
We should also like to draw attention to the
huge sums spent on scientific research, half
of which at least are spent on armaments. In
actual fact, science is one of the great creative
manifestations of human genius. What is
needed is a new concept and long-range in¬
ternational strategy for the development of
science and technology which reflects overall
global social needs.
With the headlong progress of science and
technology, there are new developments in
the offing whose implications are of a global
nature for human society as a whole such as
interference with the genetic code, deliberate
efforts to modify climate, mass employment of
information systems and storage devices with
permanent memories, industrial utilization of
micro-organisms, creation of closed man-
nature metabolism cycles, and so on. Con¬
cerning questions of so far-reaching a charac¬
ter, there is need for a widely based discus¬
sion leading to a global concept and in this
Unesco should play an important role.
Culture is not a luxury reserved for those
whose elementary needs are satisfied; it is
linked with the organization of society, and to it
society owes its dynamic force. It is made up
of the wisdom of the illiterate or the experience
handed down through generations of manual
workers as well as of the highest scholarship.
Traditions which have been forgotten or des¬
troyed by inconsiderate modernization are
irreparable losses to the understanding of our
destiny.
-
Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
To over-assert cultural particularities is just
as dangerous as to underrate them. It is
another way of running the same risks. We
must maintain a constant equilibrium between
sciences and cultures, although this is not
enough. It must be matched by an equilibrium
in mutual efforts at comprehension, and by
incessant adjustments between what different
cultures have to learn from one another.
It is not to be taken for granted that men will
escape the course of events which has led
them to the present dangers; the survival of
the planet is at stake. Is it not high time to
display a certain modesty, a wisdom which at
times our ancestors possessed and which
could constitute the basis of a new morality?
What is at stake, indeed, is not merely the
survival of the human race, but the survival of
all living things. If man really wants to live in
harmony with the natural environment, as he
claims he does today, he must show respect
not only for human rights but also for the rights
of life in its widest sense.
March 1976
H
KflB :-V..-.. (¿SR.
TAB HI ¡"^«S
[H i^HH ml w MÊ
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
My latest work-
a wall by Joan Miró
IN 1955 Unesco asked me to take part in
the decoration of its new headquarters
buildings, then under construction in
the Place de Fontenoy, Paris. Two perpen¬
dicular walls one fifteen metres long, the
other seven and a half metres long near
the Conference building were put at my
disposal. My idea was to decorate them with
ceramics, in collaboration with José
Llorens-Artigas.
The design and colouring for the walls I
was to decorate were suggested by the
shapes of the buildings themselves, their
Miró andArtigas set up full-sizedpaintings
of the ceramics in a dell beneath an im¬
mense circle of rocks and trees near Galli-
fa. Towering background enabled them to
visualize how works would look against
the great walls of the Unesco buildings.
spatial structure, and the play of light. As a
reaction to the huge concrete surfaces
around the larger wall came the idea of a
large, vivid red disc. Its counterpart on the
smaller wall would be a blue crescent to
accord with the more confined area it was to
occupy. ... I aimed at a crude and forceful
expression in the large wall and at some¬
thing more poetic in the smaller one. I also
wanted to provide an element of contrast
within each composition itself, and for this
reason I conceived harsh, dynamic outlines
side by side with restful coloured shapes, in
flat-tinted or in check design.
The second stage in the task was to study
with Artigas how my plan in ceramics was to
be carried out. No ceramist had ever before
been faced with an undertaking of this
scope. Besides this, as both walls were to be
in the open air and unprotected, we had to
keep in mind the extent to which the mate¬
rials used would resist differences in tem
perature, humidity, and the sun's rays.
There is no doubt that Artigas was the only
person capable of solving these extremely
difficult problems.
He sought, like an alchemist of old, the
type of earth, the sandstone enamels and
the colours that he would use. It was true
creative work.
It was then that we suddenly decided to
visit Santillana del Mar to have another
look at the famous cave paintings of Alta-
mira and gain inspiration from the world's
earliest mural art. While we were in the
"Collegiata", the old Romanesque church
at Santillana, we were deeply moved by the
extraordinary beauty of the material used
on an old wall, rotten with damp. Artigas
made notes about it for the purpose of his
backgrounds.
Having made our journey to the foun¬
tain-head, we thought we should also go
where we could feel the influence of the
Catalan Romanesque artists and of Gaudi.
The Barcelona Museum has wonderful
Romanesque frescoes, which have inspired
me since I first began to paint. Finally, we
visited Gaudi's work in the Guell park; and
here I was struck by the sight of an enor¬
mous disc set into the wall. It bore a strong
resemblance to the disc which I had in¬
tended to carve and paint on the larger wall
in Paris, and this coincidence I took both as
confirmation and as encouragement of my
purpose.
Artigas was not satisfied with the basic
material we were using and he feared that
the geometrical regularity of the tiles might
harm the feeling and "life" of the work.
Then he remembered the wall of the Col¬
legiata, and succeeded in reproducing in his
tests the wonderful depth of feeling we had
found there. In much the same way, the
sight of the walls of the old chapel at Gallifa
was a revelation to us. We saw that, in
deciding how to divide up the surface we
were to cover, we should think of "the
"throbbing" irregularity of the stones at
Gallifa. We had to begin again, using slabs
of different sizes.
Now that we had discovered how to
arrange the slabs and the base, the first
firing gave no trouble whatever. No matter
what precautions are taken, the firing is the
decisive factor; its action is unpredictable,
its decision final.
One more difficulty lay ahead the large
size of the surface I was to paint. If some of
the shapes and lines were to retain their
original form and spontaneity, they would
have to be made with single brush strokes.
For this purpose I used a long-handled
brush made of palm fibres. Artigas held his
breath when he saw me take the brush and
paint in shapes of five or six metres. One
mistake could have ruined the work of
several months.
November 1958
Reproduced from Derrière le Miroir, numbers 107, 108
and 109. © Maeght, Paris, 1958.
JOAN MIRO (1893-1983), Spanish painter, was
one of the great artists of the 20th century. As a
young man he took part in the Surrealist move¬
ment in Paris, where he lived for many years. He
was commissioned to create for Unesco's Paris
headquarters the two ceramics which he de¬
scribes in his article and which he named The
Wall of the Sun and The Wall of the Moon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Food for a hungry world
by Antoine Dakouré
©
s
I
FOR years, the vast problem of world
hunger has been the focus of lengthy
debate in various organizations at the
governmental, non-governmental and in¬
ternational levels.
In a noteworthy study entitled Agricul¬
ture: Toward 2000 the Food and Agricul¬
ture Organization of the United Nations
(FAO) warned all nations of the deteriorat-
"Even the best rural developmentprojects
designed by experts and backed with all
the material, technical and financial re¬
sources needed, are destined to fail if the
farmers in whose interest they are pur¬
ported to be carried out do not feel suffi¬
cientlyconcerned to offer theirunreserved
participation and if they lack the assur¬
ance that the projects are for their own
benefit." Below, Egyptian farmers hard at
work.
ing situation and offered concrete sugges¬
tions for controlling hunger effectively.
Today, however, it must be admitted that
the plight of the world's underprivileged is
steadily worsening. Nearly 500 million hu¬
man beings, stagnating in poverty, are
under daily threat of famine. The popula¬
tion of the most vulnerable countries in¬
creases by 2.5 per cent a year, whereas the
annual increase in cereal production has
levelled out at 1 per cent. If current trends
continue, requirements for cereal aid,
which totalled 7.6 million tonnes in 1979,
will reach some 21 million tonnes by 1990.
Land resources are very seriously de¬
pleted in many regions. Demographic
pressure, which is responsible for the in¬
creasing over-exploitation of arable land,
the destruction of plant cover and the
damaging effects of extensive grazing, is the
ultimate cause of accelerated desertifica-
> >*i .
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
V M
tion, whose consequences in the medium
term are just as harmful as a nuclear holo¬
caust. Our planet is threatened by famine
and yet, at the same time, we continue to
exhaust almost 20 million hectares of land
every year.
Why does the problem seem insoluble
despite all indications that it has been care¬
fully and perspicaciously analysed? There
are undoubtedly many reasons, the most
serious of which , it would seem , is that both
the developing and the industrialized na¬
tions lack the political courage needed to
implement the measures recommended.
It is important to seek methods of
approach that involve farmers as much as
possible rather than insisting on taking deci¬
sions for them and imposing solutions on
them without taking the precaution of soli¬
citing their opinion. This is an essential
prerequisite to obtaining their collabor¬
ation. Without the farmers' wholehearted
involvement no profound changes can take
place. Their participation cannot be
obtained by presidential decree or ministe¬
rial decision. Tangible, co-ordinated mea¬
sures are required which will progressively
create a favourable environment, working
at a pace acceptable to the farmers and not
racing ahead at the speed of technicians and
politicians. The farmer must be assured that
the land he needs, as well as seeds, equip¬
ment and other inputs, of adequate quality,
will be made available to him at the right
time and in sufficient quantity. Furth¬
ermore, he must have some guarantee that,
when production begins, he will not be
despoiled of the fruits of his labour.
As stressed in the study Agriculture: To¬
ward 2000, it should be possible to solve the
problem of hunger by the year 2000. Gener¬
ally speaking, however, while considerable
emphasis has been placed on all the sectoral
areas that influence programme success, I
feel that the vital question has yet to be
answered: "What concrete measures can be
taken to create the motivation essential to
progress in the field of agricultural produc¬
tion?" Unesco and the FAO could under¬
take joint initiatives in order to make a
detailed examination of this question with
the appropriate organizations in the coun¬
tries concerned.
As a first step, food aid, which enables us
to attend to the most urgent cases rapidly, is
a highly positive factor. It can help stabilize
food prices and encourage efforts to in¬
crease the quantity and improve the quality
of agricultural production.
Beneficiaries and donors of food aid must
ensure that it does not become self-perpe¬
tuating. A prolonged commitment would
constitute a long-term hindrance to the de¬
velopment of local agricultural production.
This reservation aside, nobody can deny
that well organized food aid is precious. It
could, however, become a formidable
weapon and a serious threat to peace if the
donor countries were to succumb to the
temptation to use it as a lever in internation¬
al relations.
April 1984
ANTOINE DAKOURE, a former Minister ofPlan-
ning and Rural Development of his country, Bur¬
kina Faso, was President of the Governing
Council of the United Nations Development
Programme (UNDP) in 1973. His country's
ambassador to the European Economic Com¬
munity from 1981 to 1983, he also served as a
memberof the independent Brandt Commission.
10
- i'h.-ra' a
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
R«
Nuclear weapons
and world sanity
by Linus Pauling
fpi
DURING the Second World War there
were some massive bombing raids on
German cities. In one such raid, on
one night, one thousand aeroplanes each
carrying four tremendous one-ton blockbus¬
ters destroyed much of the city of Hamburg
and killed an estimated 75,000 people. If there
were to be such a raid on, say, Paris today,
and another such 1 ,000-plane raid tomorrow,
and then another the next day and so on day
after day for fourteen years, the explosives
delivered would have the power of one 20-
megaton bomb. (One megaton equals a mil¬
lion tons.)
Now, one 20-megaton bomb test in the
atmosphere or at the surface of the earth
liberates radioactive materials into the atmos¬
phere which will, according to the best esti¬
mates that we can make, cause gross dam¬
age or death to 550,000 unborn children. This
is the probable sacrifice of the testing of a
single H-bomb by any one nation. Everyone
must understand this.
The standard nuclear bomb today is the
20-megaton bomb. The Soviet Union has de¬
tonated a 60-megaton bomb, which was
apparently only the first two stages of a 1 00-
megaton bomb. A 100-megaton bomb in¬
volves only about three and a half tons of
explosive material and probably can be car¬
ried in a single large rocket from one continent
to another. But 100-megaton bombs don't
make.very much sense because a 20-mega¬
ton bomb can destroy any city on earth.
My estimate is that the stockpiles of the
world comprise about 16,000 of these 20-
megaton bombs or the equivalent of them.
Now, there aren't 16,000 large cities in the
world and one might well ask why this irra-
Of what was once a man, only a sha¬
dow on the wall Is left. For a single In¬
stant, on 6 August 1945 at Hiroshima,
the man's body absorbed the radiation
and heat from the atomic blast and
traced the outline on the building be¬
hind. The man vanished. The ladder re¬
mained.
tionally great amount of explosive material
has been produced.
If 10 per cent of the stockpiles were to be
used in a nuclear war with the bombs ex¬
ploded on the average within 150 kilometres
of the targets (you don't have to hit the target
in order to get the result) then 60 days after the
day on which the war was fought and we
assume that it would cover Europe as a
whole, all the Soviet Union and the United
States of the 800 million people living in
these regions, 720 million would be dead, 60
million severely injured, and there would be 20
million survivors with only minor injuries.
But these survivors would have to cope with
the problems of complete destruction of all
cities, metropolitan districts, and means of
communication and transportation, complete
disruption of society, death of all livestock,
and gross radioactive contamination of all
growing foods. This would be the end of this
part of the world, and how great the damage
would be to the rest of the world no one has
been able to estimate in a reliable way.
The partial test ban treaty signed at Mos¬
cow in 1 963 was a great step forward. I regret
very much that this treaty was not made three
years earlier.
I should like to see some action taken in the
meantime that would decrease the chance of
outbreak of a devastating nuclear war,
perhaps through some psychological or tech¬
nological accident or through some combina¬
tion of circumstances such that even the
wisest of national leaders could not prevent
catastrophe.
November 1964
LINUS PAULING, US chemist, achieved re¬
nown through his contributions to the under¬
standing of molecular structures, particularly
with regard to chemical bonding. In the late
1940s he discovered, with other scientists, a
"molecular defect" associated with haemoglo¬
bin formation. His most influential work is The
Nature of the Chemical Bond, and the Struc¬
ture of Molecules and Crystals (1939). He
was awarded the Nobel Prize for Chemistry
in 1954 and the Nobel Peace Prize in 1962.
r**r:
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Apartheid: the shameful
record
by Basil Davidson
THE history of apartheid is the record
of a racism conceived and used by
small white minorities in South Afri¬
ca in order to dominate a large black ma¬
jority, deprive this majority of its land, and
maximize the exploitation of its labour for
the benefit of the whites and their foreign
partners. Apartheid is colonial racism car¬
ried to an extreme.
Up to 1899 the white politics of all the
lands south of the Limpopo river the
lands that form modern South Africa
were largely those of military power used to
defeat black resistance. Broadly, those poli¬
tics were contained within two areas of com¬
petition. As soon as the British were estab¬
lished securely at the Cape of Good Hope,
following victory over the French fleet at
Trafalgar in 1805, they embarked on a long
scries of what were euphemistically called
"frontier wars". Against continuous black
resistance, not always defeated, British
forces pushed east and northeastward from
their little colony at the Cape, invading and
dispossessing one African community after
another until their final conquest of the
Zulu kingdom in 1879.
The descendants of the Dutch settlers
(enlarged by immigration from Holland but
still more by unadmitted unions with black
women) had meanwhile gone some way
towards forming themselves into a distinc¬
tive nation, the Afrikaner volk, and by this
time spoke a variant of Dutch which was
already beginning to be a distinctive lan¬
guage, Afrikaans. They were far too weak
in numbers and technology to tackle strong
African communities such as the Xhosa and
the Zulu, whose destruction as independent
entities was left to the British, but were
strong enough to dispossess a wide range of
small African communities. These lived to
the west of the areas of British conquest,
and were duly enclosed in the Afrikaner (or
Boer, a term meaning simply "farmer")
republics of the Orange Free State and the
Transvaal.
By the 1880s there were four white poli¬
tical units: the two British colonics of the
Cape and of Natal, and the two Afrikaner
republics in the north and west. Diamonds
had been discovered in quantity at Kimbcr-
ley as early as 1867, and in 1871 the British
duly annexed these diamond fields which
became, a little later, the scene of a verit¬
able "diamond rush", with a railway com¬
pleted from the Cape to Kimberley in 1885.
But even this new source of wealth could
change little in the general picture. What
changed everything, with violent drama,
was the proving in 1884-18S6 of the great
goldfields of the Witwatersrand in the
Transvaal Republic.
For reasons imperialist and narrowly eco¬
nomic, major British interests now saw that
they must secure political control of a
Transvaal governed by farmers who had
little or no interest in large-scale capitalist
development. After many skirmishes there
followed the Anglo-Afrikaner war of 1899,
provoked by the British and won by the
British, though at a sorry cost in lives, two
years later.
Having won the war, the British were
quick to reassure their Afrikaner opponents
that systematic discrimination against the
black majority would be written into the
foundation of the Union of South Africa
(that is, the union of Cape Colony, Natal,
Transvaal, and the Orange Free State)
which followed in 1910. For thirty-eight
years after that, the English-speaking
minority generally dominated the all-white
parliament of a now-independent Union,
but invariably on apartheid lines.
This new parliament lost no time in
guaranteeing a systematic racism. In 1911, a
Native Labour Regulation Act provided for
the legalization much elaborated and
tightened up in later years of an all-
embracing discrimination against black
wage-earners. In 1913 the parliament went
much further. It passed a Land Act which
reserved some 90 per cent of the total land
surface of the Union for white ownership,
and reduced the area available for black
ownership to the remaining 10 per cent (less
at the beginning, today about 13 per cent).
These small areas where Africans could
own land were named Native Reserves, and
rapidly became what they were intended to
be: destitute reservoirs of black labour for
the "white areas".
In 1923 came the Natives (Urban Areas)
Act which was to remain, with the Land Act
of 1913, the foundation of all white policy
towards blacks, and so remains to this day.
Essentially, it was a weapon of physical
segregation with the "white areas"; and the
policy which was held to justify it was called
"separate development".
In 1948 the English-speaking minority
lost control of parliament, and were never
to regain it. That control passed to the
Purified Afrikaner National Party; and
"separate development" was followed by
apartheid.
Meanwhile the Second World War had
done much to exacerbate English-Afrikan¬
er hostility. Nearly all the leaders of the
Purified National Party had openly hoped
and worked for a Nazi victory; and some of
The face of hunger
/ counted ribs on his concertina chest
bones protruding as if chiselled
by a sculptor's hand of famine.
He looked with glazed pupils
seeing only a bun on some sky-high shelf.
The skin was pale and taut
like a glove on a doctor's hand.
His tongue darted in and out
like a chameleon's
snatching a confetti of flies.
Ol child,
your stomach is a den of lions
roaring day and night.
Oswald Mbuyiseni Mtshali
them had been gaoled for pro-Nazi sabo¬
tage. Their electoral triumph of 1948 was
therefore accompanied by a determination
to succeed where Hitler had failed: and put
an end, once and for all, to English-speak¬
ing supremacy.
The system in no way changed in sub¬
stance. Laws were passed to identify any
black protest, however peaceful or other¬
wise legal in nature, with a "Communism"
which was equated, however ludicrously,
with some kind of foreign-promoted
attempt to overturn the State.
In this Republic of South Africa, all
"safety valves" were now scaled off, so that
explosion had become the only possible
alternative to continued submission. And in
1980, through its action-wing, Umkonto wa
Sizwe, the African National Congress of
South Africa duly embarked on the begin¬
nings of a war of resistance.
By 1981 the South African régime was
virtually at war with Angola and Mozam¬
bique as well as in its colony of Namibia,
and was threatening invasive action against
the newly-independent Republic of Zim¬
babwe. But this régime was also at war, in
save the name of war and its
formal declaration, within its own frontiers.
Today that war continues.
November 1983
BASIL DAVIDSON, British writer and historian,
is an authority on African history and current
affairs. His many books on Africa include Libera¬
tion of Guiñé (1969) and In the Eye of the Storm:
Angola's People (1972).
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
~ '
^
,
, *« '
- u * » * s r i.
V
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
*w
&
C^-£~> S "3 # C f
Racism today:
Z>3> Albert Memmi 'Us' and 'Them'
AFTER twenty years of observation,
reflection, research and studies "in
the field", I am convinced that rac¬
ism is a rotten plank. I am not speaking only
of its moral aspect, but of its very logic.
Man's present biological nature de¬
veloped, and is still developing, in the
course of continuous cross-breeding proces¬
ses. In this context, therefore, the concept
of purity is no more than a metaphor, wish¬
ful thinking, fantasy. This is not to say that
men do not differ from each other. They do,
both culturally and even biologically. But,
surprisingly, the most recent scientific re¬
search reveals on the contrary that the dif¬
ferences are so fragmented that it is im¬
possible to make a given social group co¬
incide with any one biological profile. Nor is
the concept of superiority any more sustain¬
able on a functional level. There is nothing
to prove that biological superiority, assum¬
ing that it exists, leads to psychological or
cultural superiority. Finally, it is difficult to
see why any form of natural superiority
should involve economic or social advan¬
tages.
In order to survive, man seeks to defend
his integrity and his possessions and, on
occasions, to appropriate those of his neigh¬
bour, whether they be movable or immov¬
able property, food, raw materials, terri¬
tory, women, real or imaginary religious,
cultural or symbolic assets. Man is both
aggressor and the object of aggression, both
terrifying and terrified.
However, this aggressive rejection of
another is not yet exactly racism. The racist
way of thinking is based on this rejection,
and on pre-existing cultural and social facts.
It is evident that racism or, in other
words, alleged racial superiority based on
alleged biological purity, is no more than an
ideological apparatus, one among many ali¬
bis for domination and expropriation. For
this reason, I think it is necessary to point
out both this general character of a form of
human behaviour which is unfortunately
only too common, and the specific charac¬
ter of racism. Otherwise the false problems
associated with racism will continue to
obscure the permanent drama represented
by the aggressive rejection of others. To
make the distinction more clear, I have
proposed that this terrified, aggressive re¬
jection be designated by a new word, heter-
ophobia, and that the term racism be hence¬
forth reserved for that variety of heteropho-
bia which exploits the fear engendered by
biological and racial difference in order to
justify aggression and privilege. ... I there¬
fore suggested the following formulation,
which has been adopted by the Encyclo¬
paedia Universalis and which Unesco has
done me the honour of using as a basis for
its own definition: Racism is the gener¬
alized, permanent' exploitation of real or
imaginary biological differences, to the
advantage of the accuser and to the detriment
of his victim, for the purpose of justifying
aggression.
We can perceive what could constitute a
single criterion for replying to those closely
related questions which embarrass contem¬
porary consciences what connexion is
there between anti-semitism and the slave
trade? Can one speak of prejudice against
women or young people as forms of racism?
Is there also a form of racism affecting the
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Dr. Martin Luther King, winner of the
1964 Nobel Peace Prize, addresses par¬
ticipants in a "Prayer Pilgrimage for
Freedom" in front of the Lincoln Memo¬
rial in Washington, D.C., in May 1957.
King was assassinated on 4 April 1968,
a victim of racism.
poor and oppressed? etc. To establish the
connexion between these forms of be¬
haviour, one has only to ask oneself what
advantage a particular aggressor could de¬
rive from them at the expense of a particular
victim.
There is an obvious correlation between
the black slave trade, which reached its
climax in the seventeenth century, and the
first arguments used in support of biological
racism. True, the first element of such a
demonstration can be found in certain
ancient writers. But these are isolated
cases, and where it was present at all, biolo¬
gical stigmatization played only a very
secondary role. This latter system of
argument, which obviously had mercantile
advantages, came into its own with the
growth of the slave trade.
Anti-semitism is of course very ancient,
but it was originally a religious or national
issue. It appeared as a racist doctrine only
much later, simultaneously with the relative
social emancipation of the Jews and their
consequent emergence as economic com¬
petitors.
In short, then, it is only relatively recently
that attempts have been made to provide a
systematic explanation of racism based on
an alleged science. At the end of the
nineteenth century educated Europe was
convinced that the human species was di¬
vided into superior and inferior races /see
Ernest Renan and the anthropologist Paul
Broca).
A comparison of these various doc¬
trines social and cultural as well as biolo¬
gical clearly reveals a constant factor,
irrespective of their specific characteristics
or local circumstances: in the name of a
biological or other form of superiority, one
human group believes itself entitled to
assert itself over another and to have re¬
course for that purpose even to violence and
murder.
Thus we find at the same time the answer
to the most recent questions with which
people are concerned. Racism was a conve¬
nient ideology for rising colonialism, for the
black slave trade and for anti-semitism. It
can still be useful on a wide scale. The
Algerian war, followed by the presence of
millions of immigrant workers in France
and throughout Europe, provided and still
provides favourable ground for "arabopho-
bia", renewed "negrophobia" and, more
generally, the aggressive rejection of im¬
migrants, which I also suggest be included
in the general concept of heterophobia
the complex of fear of others and aggres¬
siveness towards them .
November 1983
ALBERT MEMMI, Tunisian-born French writer,
is well qualified to describe the different man¬
ifestations of racism. Notable among his works
published in English are The Colonizer and the
Colonized (Souvenir Press, London, 1974) with
a preface by Jean-Paul Sanre, and The Pillar of
Salt (1955) with a preface by Albert Camus.
The forbidden
dialogue
by Lewis Nkosi
EVEN the proponents of apartheid
cannot deny that the blacks suffer
untold hardships as a price for the
maintenance of the policy of apartheid.
What is not always noted is that, though
economically exploitative as a ruling class,
the whites are also subject to certain very
real deprivations as a result of their deter¬
mination to live by a policy which would
seem to all reasonable men not only un¬
realistic but insane.
To say the very least, South African
whites are the most culturally deprived
community in Africa. Emotionally they are
just as stunted.
They not only grow up denying their in¬
nermost dreams, they also learn to do with¬
out some of the best works of modern world
culture (in literature, music, painting and
intellectual discourse) either because such
works are considered subversive, or be¬
cause traffic in culture with the outside
world is rendered almost impossible by the
maintenance of the policy of apartheid.
We all know what happens to people who
cannot face up to the reality of their lives,
who must live by evasions and fantasies; a
greater burden is placed on writers or any
other kind of artist who belongs to such a
community. Before they go on to create
anything of value they must make an ex¬
traordinary effort to unlearn everything
they have been taught.
In South Africa they must, for instance,
unlearn what they are taught in schools:
that the whites, from their forefathers to the
present generation, are all heroes; that the
whites have the monopoly on moral wisdom
and intellectual enterprise; the pain and the
anguish which attend the creative efforts of
Afrikaans writers at the moment is not a
matter for cynical amusement. It is the
agony of creative artists who must break
through a sealed cocoon in order to see the
world in its variousness or even to say some¬
thing remotely relevant to their country.
Black writers do not have to make any
comparable moral choice; they do not have
to choose to oppose a system which is
patently contrary to all observable reality;
their colour makes the choice for them;
what they have to do is learn to survive the
system.
There are times when an affirmation of
certain traditional African values proves
exasperatingly difficult for black writers
since most of them are reacting to an ideolo
gy which asserts again and again that black
and white people are irreconcilably dif¬
ferent; that the African mind cannot grasp
certain nuances of European thought; and,
concluding from the foregoing, that apar¬
theid is justifiable, indeed the only realistic
policy to follow.
The result has been that black intellec¬
tuals in South Africa have had to bend over
backwards to prove that they can not only
master the modes of European thought but
that they can beat the South African whites
at their own game.
Urban African music seems to me to have
provided the only example of what South
Africa can offer culturally if she were left to
develop in a natural direction.
Music, because it is non-literal, is not
subject to the same limitations as literature;
it is hardly banned; also it is less self-con¬
scious in the modes it adopts to express the
agony of the South African situation. The
result has been that popular urban African
music has provided a glaring paradigm of
what is happening to the underground life
of the nation.
The music is predominantly African,
which is as it should be, considering the
dominant number of Africans in the coun¬
try; but it is also eclectic; it provides a
moving illustration of cultural diffusion in
that part of the continent which offers us the
best laboratory for the marriage of African
and European techniques and for the com¬
ing together of European and African
modes of expression.
While black literature from the Republic
offers us glimpses into an appalling situa¬
tion of rare brutality and anguish, the music
not only shows us this but goes further to
affirm what we should have known all
along; that the oppressed in South Africa
also display an amazing form of resilience,
emotional certitude and optimism. On the
other hand, apartheid deprives white South
Africans of any real participation in such
robust forms of cultural expression.
March 1967
LEWIS NKOSI, South African writer, was exiled
from his country in 1960, and later lived in Lon¬
don. He is the author of a play about racial
tensions in Johannesburg, The Rhythm of
Violence, and of an essay on contemporary
Black American and South African literature en¬
titled Home and Exile.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Pictures in our heads
o
©
by Otto Klineberg
THERE are very few, if any, among
us who have not succumbed to the
temptation to stereotype nations.
One might almost describe the tendency as
inevitable, or at least very nearly so. But if
we are asked how it originates, we would
not easily find a suitable answer.
One of the earliest careful studies of this
tendency was made by Katz and Braly, in
1932, in connexion with the stereotypes
held by Princeton University students.
We may summarize the results by indicat¬
ing the three or four characteristics most
commonly ascribed to each nationality.
These included, for the Germans: scientifi¬
cally-minded, industrious, stolid; the Ita¬
lians, impulsive, artistic, passionate; Neg¬
roes, superstitious, lazy, happy-go-lucky,
ignorant; the Irish, pugnacious, quick-tem¬
pered, witty; the English, sportsmanlike,
intelligent, conventional; the Jews, shrewd,
mercenary, industrious; the Americans, in¬
dustrious, intelligent, materialistic, ambi¬
tious; the Chinese, superstitious, sly, con¬
servative; the Japanese, intelligent, indus¬
trious, progressive; the Turks, cruel, re¬
ligious, treacherous.
A study conducted in nine countries
under the auspices of Unesco in 1948 and
1949, showed that such stereotyped think¬
ing could easily be elicited almost any¬
where. In each country approximately
1,000 respondents, representing a cross-
section of the population, were given a list
of twelve traits, and asked to choose those
which they thought were most applicable to
themselves, to Americans, to Russians, and
in some cases, to two'or three other national
groups as well.
The British, for example, thought of
Americans as primarily progressive, con¬
ceited, generous, peace-loving, intelligent,
practical. The Americans regarded the
British as intelligent, hard-working, brave,
peace-loving, conceited and self -
controlled.
The "self-image" is also revealing. The
British saw themselves as peace-loving,
brave, hard-working, intelligent; the
French saw themselves as intelligent,
peace-loving, generous, and brave; the
Americans saw themselves as peace-loving,
generous, intelligent and progressive. All
the groups agreed on one item: their own
nation was the most peace-loving of them
all.
There is a good deal of evidence that
stereotypes may develop without any ker¬
nel of truth whatsoever. We all know how
widespread is the notion that intelligent
people have high foreheads, yet scientific
investigation in this field has failed to reveal
any such relationship. The stereotype of the
criminal as bearing in his features the mark
of his criminality is widely accepted, but it is
equally without foundation.
The American sociologist La Piere stu¬
died the attitudes of residents of California
towards first and second generation Arme¬
nian immigrants in Fresno County in that
State. There was almost complete agree¬
ment that these Armenians had more than
their share of faults, and the general atti¬
tude toward them was relatively unfriendly.
La Piere proceeded to question non-
Armenians as to the reasons for their anti¬
pathies, and he was able to classify the
answers into three stereotypes. In the first
place, it was stated that Armenians were
treacherous, lying, deceitful. In actual fact,
when measured by the criterion of business
integrity, the Armenian merchants turned
out to be equal and frequently superior to
others.
In the second place, they were alleged to
be parasites, making excessive demands
upon charitable organizations, free clinics,
etc. Actually, such demands by them were
less than half of what would be expected in
terms of their proportion of the population.
Finally, it was said that they had an in¬
ferior code of morality, and they were al¬
ways getting into trouble with the law. In
fact, police records showed that they
appeared in only 1.5 per cent of Police
Court cases, although they were about 6 per
cent of the population.
La Piere concludes that all of these
stereotypes have one factor in common,
namely, that they are definitely false.
June 1955
OTTO KLINEBERG, Canadian psychologist
and anthropologist, is one of the world's leading
authorities on questions of race and psychology
and on race relations. Among his many pub¬
lished works are Race Differences and The
Human Dimension in International Relations.
Cartoon specially drawn for the Unesco
Courier in 1955 by an Indian artist, A.M.
Abraham.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The menace of 'extinct' volcanoes
by Haroun Tazieff
One of history's most famous volcanoes,
Vesuvius on the bay of Naples, is still
active. Its eruption of AD 79 buried Pom¬
peii, Herculaneum and Stabiae.
I
have gradually become convinced of
something that laymen and even pro¬
fessional geologists and volcanologists
usually ignore and it fills me with dread
the prospect, some day soon, of unheard-
of volcanic catastrophes. Geological evi¬
dence has finally convinced me that
humanity has so far been fantastically
lucky, and the catastrophes of Pompeii and
St. Pierre de la Martinique are nothing to
what awaits us. These were small towns
compared with the enormous modern cities
threatened at closer or longer range by a
volcanic outburst Naples and Rome,
Portland and Seattle, Mexico City, Ban¬
dung, Sapporo, Oakland, Catania, Cler¬
mont-Ferrand! ... Volcanoes regarded as
totally extinct near these cities are dead
only to eyes that cannot or will not see. A
volcano may be less than a century dor¬
mant and people almost forget that it exists.
But volcanoes are geologically live; time for
them is counted not in years or even in
centuries, but in millennia and tens of mil¬
lennia. Centuries might pass and Clermont-
Ferrand, Rome or Seattle not be wiped out.
Butthe interval might be much less.
October 1967
HAROUN TAZIEFF, French geologist and vol-
canologist, has combined scientific research
with the authorship of many popular scientific
books and documentary films.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The shocking slaughter
ofAfrica's wild life by Paul-Emile Victor
by Sir Julian Huxley
THE wild life of eastern Africa is the
wonder and envy of the rest of the
world. Unique in abundance and
variety, it has been gravely diminished in the
past and is seriously threatened in the im¬
mediate future. Its natural habitats and wild
lands cover more than half of its immense
area, and are of tremendous potential import¬
ance if properly used. But they too have been
reduced in extent, their value has been sadly
reduced by improper use and they are
threatened with drastic misdevelopment in
the immediate future.
The future of African wild life is bound up
with that of the conservation of natural re¬
sources. Both are now in the balance. The
next five or at most ten years will be decisive in
determining whether they are headed down¬
hill towards a point of no return, or set on the
upward path of beneficial development.
Let me state the African situation in ecolo¬
gical terms. The ecological problem is fun¬
damentally one of balancing resources
against human needs, both in the short and in
the long term. It thus must be related to a
proper evaluation of human needs, and it
must be based on resource conservation/and
resource use, including optimum land use and
conservation of the habitat.
Over the whole of south-eastern Africa, the
wild life resource has been shockingly re¬
duced from its astonishing past abundance. In
spite of this, the wild life of this region is still a
resource of unique value. It must be pre¬
served both as an object of study and as a
spectacle to be enjoyed. Its scientific study is
a necessary basis for proper land use policies,
and an increasing number of people from all
over the world are finding unique satisfaction
and interest in it as a spectacle.
Proper management of wild lands can yield
a large crop of meat as well as numerous
ancillary animal and plant products. The
meat-crop could in particular areas be com¬
mercially profitable, but of more general im¬
portance is the fact that it would go a long way
to satisfying the Africans' meat-hunger, which
springs from the region's marked protein de¬
ficiency.
This in turn would help in reducing the threat
of poaching to African wild life. "Poaching"
today is in reality a large-scale illegal trade in
slaughtered wild animals. It is by no means
confined to killing for meat; all too often it
takes the horrible and wasteful form of merely
taking the valuable trophies, such as rhino
horn, wildebeest tails, or elephant ivory, and
leaving the slaughtered carcasses to rot.
The poacher's methods are not only waste¬
ful, but extremely cruel. It is bad enough when
gangs of bowmen with poisoned arrows wait
near a waterhole or at a gap in a prepared
barrier, and shoot large numbers of animals,
which then die an agonizing death. However,
pitfalls are worse; in the Serengeti, for instan¬
ce, whole series of carefully-sited pitfalls have
been laboriously dug, providing proof of the
value of the proceeds.
What is needed is a comprehensive and
conservationist land use policy for the region,
based on a proper survey, to decide which
land should be allocated primarily for agricul¬
ture and for commercial or industrial develop¬
ment; which allocated for game-cropping,
watershed protection, forests, National Parks
and Nature Reserves, or merely kept unde¬
veloped in reserve until its best use can be
determined; and which could be best de¬
veloped by establishing a fruitful symbiosis
between wild life and domestic stock.
Wild life in Africa as a resource may be
summed up in the phrase Profit, Protein, Pride
and Prestige, with enjoyment and scientific
interest thrown in. It can yield Profit from
tourist revenue, sales of meat and trophies,
and Protein from game-cropping schemes; it
can be a source of local Pride and internation¬
al Prestige; while its importance as a source of
scientific knowledge is very great.
To let the wild life die or be destroyed would
be to allow a precious element in that rich
variety to be submerged forever in the drab
monotonous flood of uniformity that is
threatening to engulf our mass-produced
technological civilization. Unesco has roused
world opinion to save the threatened monu¬
ments of Nubia: it should take on the responsi¬
bility of rousing world opinion for the equally
worthy task of saving the threatened wild life
of Africa.
September 1961
JULIAN HUXLEY (1887-1975), British zoologist
and biologist who won a worldwide reputation for
his work in embryology, was Unesco's first Direc¬
tor-General, from 1946 to 1948. The author of
some 40 books on science, travel, religion, poli¬
tics and natural history, he was awarded the
Unesco Kalinga Prize for the popularization of
science in 1953.
*
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Will deserts drink icebergs?
EVERY attempt has to be made to find
further supplies of fresh water. There
are two viable methods of doing this,
and two only: the desalination of sea water,
and the tapping of the only existing reserves
of fresh water the ice of the polar regions,
formed by the accumulation and compression
of snowfall over many thousands of years.
The desalination of sea water is expensive,
whereas the production of fresh water by the
transportation of icebergs is both economical¬
ly competitive and feasible.
Icebergs are composed of fresh water so
pure that it often approaches the characteris¬
tics of distilled water.
It has been estimated that the Antarctic
icecap loses more than 1 0 million million cubic
metres of ice every year in the form of
icebergs, which eventually melt and dis¬
appear.
Why go to the South Pole to get icebergs?
Why not the North Pole?
There are two reasons for this. First, most
Arctic icebergs are irregularly shaped and
dangerously unstable. Secondly, Arctic bergs
come from mountain glaciers (from Green¬
land, for example) which precludes their ever
being large enough. The "tabular" icebergs
from Antarctica, on the other hand, are often
big and regular in shape.
A "suitable" iceberg should be large
enough (100 million tonnes) to provide the
required amount of water by the time it arrives
at its destination. It should be tabular, as
regularly shaped as possible, and, to make
towing easier, much longer than it is wide.
Icebergs of this type, always supposing that
no internal or invisible cracks and stresses are
subsequently detected, are formed in the
Pacific sector, in the Atlantic sector, and in the
Indian sector.
The most important problem will be to pro¬
tect the icebergs against all types of erosion,
such as melting, evaporation, mechanical
erosion by waves, and friction caused by
movement through the sea.
It would, for instance, take eight to nine
months to cover 6,000 nautical miles at opti¬
mum towing speed (about one knot or roughly
two kilometres per hour).
Various solutions have been suggested.
One of them involves the protection of the
sides of the icebergs by strips (similar to those
of a Venetian blind) made of a reflective
material.
The submerged portion of the sides would
be protected by a similar curtain (or skirt)
made of insulating material, while the insula¬
tion itself would be provided by a pool of cold
fresh water between the skirt and the sides of
the iceberg. The underside of the berg would
also be protected by a kind of wrap held
against the bottom by inflatable floats.
The manufacture and assembling of such
units in Antarctic waters will involve various
problems that are not yet solved.
The actual towing operation should, in
theory, cause no problems at all, as the
largest modern tugs have a tractive force of
125 tonnes. The tractive force needed to shift
an iceberg of 100 million tonnes is in the
region of 600 to 700 tonnes, so five or six large
tugs could do the job.
Once the iceberg arrived at its destination it
might have to remain a certain distance
offshore, depending on the shallowness of the
continental shelf. Melting water would then
have to be pumped by pipeline to the coast.
The production of fresh water by the trans¬
portation of icebergs is undoubtedly one of the
most original and exciting ventures of our
time. It is also one of the most useful: the most
urgent problem soon to face mankind will be
how to obtain fresh water.
February 1978
PAUL-EMILE VICTOR is a noted French explor¬
er who has organized and led many French
expeditions to the Arctic and Antarctic. He was
headof the international glaciological expedition
to Greenland from 1967 to 1970. His achieve¬
ments as an explorer and scientist have brought
him international recognition, including the
award of the gold medal of the Royal Geog¬
raphical Society, London.
W
r.
h*w«».--
hi
^K.:
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Fifty years of literary life
by Ba Jin
WHEN the Chinese people
were liberated and the Peo¬
ple's Republic of China was
founded, I wanted to use my pen,
which had been used to writing about
darkness and misery, to write about
new people and new deeds, to cele¬
brate the people's victory and joy. But
I had not the time to familiarize my¬
self with these subjects. I also took
part in non-literary activities.
I wrote widely in praise of our new
society and our new life. These writ¬
ings were used as evidence of my
"crime" and were condemned as
"poisonous weeds" during the ten
years of the "Great Cultural Revolu¬
tion". I myself was illegally detained
and suffered from all kinds of mental
torture and humiliation. During these
ten years I was deprived of all my
civic rights and denied the freedom to
publish.
These ten unforgettable years consti¬
tute an important episode in the his¬
tory of humanity. Few writers in the
world experienced such dreadful, ridi¬
culous, strange, painful events. We
were all involved, we all played a
part, and today when we look back at
what we did during those years we
find our behaviour ridiculous but it
didn't seem like that at the time. I
often say to myself that if I don't sum
up those ten hard years and analyse
myself sincerely, I may one day again
regard cruelty, savagery and stupidity
as part of the normal order of things.
I have never thought about writing
technique or ways of expression when
writing my stories. What I care about
is how to help people lead a better
life, a worthy life, and how to help my
readers contribute to society and to
the people. All my writings have this
aim.
When I met a group of Sinologists
in Paris in September 1981 someone
asked how I had survived the "Cultu¬
ral Revolution". Their sincere desire
to understand something which seemed
quite ordinary to us set my mind
working. Those ten dreadful years had
taught me something. At last I came
to realize what I have learned- from
those long years of disaster.
Gradually things became clearer in
my mind. It must be love, fire, hope,
something positive. Many people had
survived because they had these qual¬
ities. But many had been destroyed
and left to us their love, fire and hope
to be transmitted to posterity. No, I
shall never lay down my pen.
December 1982
BA JIN, born 1904, is a celebrated modern
Chinese novelist. His major works include
Trilogy of Love (The Mist, The Rain, The
Lightning), Trilogy of the Torrent (The Family,
Spring, Autumn), and Reminiscences of my
Writing Life.
Ba Jin at his Shanghai home in 1982,
aged seventy-seven
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
READERS who claim me for their
favourite writer often say that I
express the truth. This is exces¬
sive praise induced, no doubt, by their
very partiality. It is true that I do not
seek to deceive, but neither do I try to
recount all that is within me. What I ex¬
press is merely a few odds and ends, just
enough to hand in to the printer. It is
true that I often try to dissect other peo¬
ple, but I apply the scalpel even more
frequently to myself, and with far less
pity. When I lift only a corner of the
veil, sensitive spirits quail. What if I
were to reveal myself entirely, exactly as
I am?
It occurs to me from time to time to
use this method to drive people away, so
that those who even then did not aban¬
don me, "snakes and odious monsters"'1'
though they might be, would show them¬
selves to be my friends, true friends af¬
ter all. And if even they left me in the
lurch, then too bad, I'd walk alone. But
for the time being I refrain from putting
this idea into practice, partly because I
lack the courage to do so, and partly be¬
cause I want to go on living in this
society. But there is another reason, too,
which I have mentioned several times: it
gives me a certain satisfaction to create
for as long as I can a feeling of unease
among our "respectable and right-think¬
ing" fellow-citizens. This is why I shall
continue to gird myself with a few pieces
of armour and stand before them, dis¬
turbing their orderly world with my pre¬
sence, until I become tired of the whole
business and take off this armour.
To serve as a guide to others is all the
more difficult for me, since I myself do
not know which path to follow. There is
certainly no lack of "masters" and
"guides" in China, but I am not among
them and they do not inspire my con¬
fidence. There is only one outcome of
which I myself am certain, and that is
the tomb. But this is something every¬
body knows, without having to consult a
guide. The problem is that more than
one way leads to that ultimate destina¬
tion, and up to now I have been unable
to determine which of them to take. I
am still trying to find out, and I am very
much afraid that my still-gréen fruit
should poison those who appreciate me,
while those who detest me the "respec¬
table" and "right-thinking", for exam¬
ple all live to a ripe old age. It is thus
inevitable for me to clothe my words in
ambiguity, since it often occurs to me
that the best gift I can offer to readers
who are fond of me might well be "in¬
consistency".
Some people imagine that I write
spontaneously, that the words pour out
in total freedom. Nothing could be furth¬
er from the truth: I am inhibited by a
host of scruples and uncertainties, I have
known for a long time that I am not the
stuff that warriors and pioneers are
made of. Three or four years ago, I re¬
member, a student arrived to buy one of
my books. The money which he took
out of his pocket and pressed into my
hand was warm with the heat of his
Night thoughts,
November 1926
by Lu Xun
(1) In the original: "Xiao, snakes and revenants".
Xiao was an unpleasant mythical bird whose repel¬
lent attributes included devouring its own mother.
Lu Xun at the age of fifty
body. And that warmth penetrated me,
so much so that ever since then,
whenever I take up my pen, I am afraid
of poisoning people like that student; I
hesitate for a long time before putting a
single word on paper. I fear that the
time will never come again when I speak
without such reserve, and although I
sometimes think that in order to respond
to the expectations of the young genera¬
tion one should sweep every scruple
aside, I have not, as yet, managed to
bring myself to do so.
That is all I intended to say today, and it
may be taken as relatively sincere.
December 1982
This text, an extract from the afterword to "The Tomb",
the first compilation of Lu Xun's collected works, was
written in November 1926, shortly after the author had
left Beijing, where he faced the threat of imprisonment,
to teach at the University of Xiamen (Amoy). This
English version is based on the French translation from
the Chinese, carried out under the direction of Michelle
Loi and the Lu Xun Research Centre of the People's
Republic of China. This translation, La Tombe, was
published by Editions Acropole in 1981, and forms part
of the Unesco Collection of Representative Works.
French translation © Unesco, 1981
LU XUN (pseudonym of Zhou Shuren, 1881-
1936) is a major figure in Chinese literature.
He exercised considerable influence on his
times through his many essays, stories and
poems. Among his works translated into En¬
glish is "The True Story of Ah Q" (Chinese,
1921; Eng. trans. 1926).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
OK
The angry young men
of Oceania
by Albert Wendt
These bird of paradise feathers form part
ofan intricate headdress worn by the peo¬
ple of the New Guinea highlands. The rela¬
tionship between birds and men is strong¬
ly expressed in the oral literature andart of
the Oceanian peoples.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
IN our various groping ways we are all in
search of that haven, that Hawaiki
(mythical homeland of the Maori peo¬
ple) where our hearts will find meaning.
Our dead are woven into our souls like
the hypnotic music of bone flutes; we can
never escape them. If we let them they can
help illuminate us to ourselves and to one
another. They can be the source of new¬
found pride, self-respect and wisdom. Con¬
versely, they can be the aitu (evil spirit or
ghost) that will continue to destroy us by
blinding us to the beauty we are so capable
of becoming as individuals, cultures,
nations. We must try to exorcise these aitu
both old and modern.
Photo © Camera Press, London
There is no state of cultural purity (or
perfect state of cultural "goodness") from
which there is decline; usage determines
authenticity. There was no Fall, no sun¬
tanned Noble Savages existing in South Sea
paradises, no Golden Age, except in Holly¬
wood films, in the insanely romantic litera¬
ture and art produced by outsiders about
the Pacific, in the breathless sermons of our
self-styled romantic revolutionaries.
Our quest should not be for a revival of
our past cultures but for the creation of new
cultures which are free of the taint of col¬
onialism and based firmly on our own pasts.
The quest should be for a new Oceania.
Many of us are guilty whether we are
aware of it or not of perpetuating the
destructive colonial chill, and are doing so
in the avowed interest of "preserving our
racial and cultural purity" (whatever that
means).
To advocate that in order to be a "true
Samoan", for example, one must be a "full-
blooded Samoan" and behave, think,
dance, talk, dress and believe in a certain
prescribed way (and that the prescribed way
has not changed since time immemorial) is
being racist, callously totalitarian, and stu¬
pid. This is a prescription for cultural stag¬
nation, an invitation for a culture to choke
in its own body odour, juices, and excreta.
There are no "true interpreters" or
"sacred guardians" of any culture. We are
all entitled to our truths, insights, and intu¬
itions into an interpretation of our cultures.
To varying degrees, we as individuals all
live in limbo within our cultures: there are
many aspects of our ways of life that we
cannot subscribe to or live comfortably
with. We all conform to some extent, but
the life-blood of any culture is the diverse
contributions of its varied sub-cultures.
The population of our region is only just
over five million but we possess a cultural
diversity as varied as any other in the world.
There is also a multiplicity of social, econo¬
mic and political systems all undergoing
different stages of decolonization, ranging
from politically independent nations (West¬
ern Samoa, Fiji, Papua New Guinea,
Tonga, Nauru) through self-governing ones
(the Solomons, the Gilberts, Tuvalu) and
colonies (mainly French and American) to
our oppressed aboriginal brothers in
Australia.
If as yet we may not be the most artistical¬
ly creative region in our spaceship, we pos¬
sess the potential to become so. There are
more than 1,200 indigenous languages plus
English, French, Hindi, Spanish, and va¬
rious forms of pidgin to catch and interpret
the void with, reinterpret our past with,
create new sociological visions of Oceania
with, compose songs and poems and plays
and other oral and written literature with.
We also possess numerous other forms of
artistic expression: hundreds of dance
styles; wood and stone sculpture and carv¬
ings; artifacts as various as our cultures;
pottery, painting and tattooing. We have a
fabulous treasure house of traditional
motifs, themes, styles, material which we
can use in contemporary forms to express
our uniqueness, identity, pain, joy and our
own visions of Oceania and the earth .
February 1976
ALBERT WENDT, of Western Samoa, is a
writer, poet, and specialist in Oceanian literature.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Afro-Brazilian experiment
by Gilberto Freyre
BRAZIL'S experience can be useful to
new nations in Africa, Asia and else¬
where for, after four centuries of
pre-national and national development and
more than a century of independence, Bra¬
zil is now emerging as a civilization in search
of forms of expression suited to a tropical
environment. This civilization does not,
however, repudiate the European values
which are so basic to Brazil's national
heritage.
Brazil now boasts its own types of
architecture, music, painting, cooking,
Christianity, social life, attitudes towards
health and hygiene, and football a more
dionysiac Brazilian kind of football than the
apollonian English one. All of these express
a new type of civilization whose novelty
derives as much from racial intermingling as
from an intermixing of cultures.
The cult of the Virgin Mary is an exam¬
ple: elements have been assimilated from
the Yemanja cult (the female counterpart
of Orixa, a secondary divinity in the African
jeje-nago cult). Brazil has black Virgins like
the Virgin of Rosario and mestizo Virgins
like Our Lady of Guadalupe, whose de¬
votees pledge themselves by offering ex¬
votos wood and clay sculptures whose ex¬
pression and colour symbolism are more
African than European.
Brazilians do not consider themselves
less Catholic because elements of African
rites or beliefs have been incorporated into
their religious worship. Though their
Catholicism is more tropical and less
European, believers do not feel it has been
corrupted or de-Christianized. The same
holds true for Brazilian cookery, music,
sculpture and painting of European origin:
African penetration represents not a cor¬
ruption of values but an enrichment.
The process of "tropicalization" of the
Portuguese language in Brazil stems pri¬
marily from African influence, and only
secondarily from Amerindian influence. As
a literary language, it is no longer con¬
sidered as inferior to the academic language
of Portuguese purists. Less and less
academic, the Brazilian language is daily
acquiring new rhythms and expressions
whose musicality and forcefulness are deep¬
ly marked by their African origins.
More has been written about the African
influence on Brazilian music than on any
other Brazilian art form. It is apparent not
only in popular music but also in some of the
country's most serious music. The compos-
GILBERTO FREYRE, of Brazil, is an interna¬
tionally known authority on sociology and on
social and cultural anthropology. His works
translated into English include: The Masters and
the Slaves, New World in the Tropics, and The
Mansions and the Shanties.
er Heitor Villa-Lobos (1887-1959) was in- must not forget that another factor, besides
fluenced both by American and even more the historical one, has contributed to these
by Amerindian musical themes, which he similarities: a common tropical environ-
considered basically Brazilian. ment undergoing the process of moderniza-
The cultural affinities between Brazil and tion.
Africa are, as we have seen, strong. But we August-September 1977
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Where gods
and men
have mingled
T
by Jorge Amado
HE culture of Brazil was formed in
the struggle against racism and was
born of the mingling of whites,
blacks and Amerindians. The black ele¬
ment in Brazilian society is inextricably
mingled with the white, and Africa is a
maternal presence in our midst.
Our outlook on life is fundamentally anti-
racist, based as it is on intermingling. The
vigorous "negro" art of the sculptor Agnal-
Photo René Bum © Magnum, Paris
do da Silva, without equal in Brazil today, is
not exclusively black. It bears traces of
white and Iberian influences in both form
and subject: Agnaldo's Oxossi is also St.
George.
It is all the more unfortunate, then, that a
distorted image of our way of life is some¬
times presented abroad. The African con¬
tribution, which is of fundamental import¬
ance to Brazilian culture, is glossed over or
pushed into the background.
This is a totally false approach. Through a
curious reversal of the colonial mentality,
there is a tendency to put the spotlight on
painters, writers and singers with the black¬
est possible skins. This attempt to prove the
absence of racial-prej udice in Brazil actually
indicates a preoccupation which is totally
alien to the Brazilian philosophy of life.
The blackest girls are chosen to sing, but
no attention is paid to the fact that they sing
songs more strongly marked by Iberian than
black influence, although Brazilian music
derives primarily from the atabiques of
Africa.
The paintings shown tend to be typical
examples of the Paris School the impor¬
tant thing is that the artists' skins are black.
Brazilian painters like Tarsila and Di Caval-
canti are neglected, although their work
displays the black African influences which,
along with white, Amerindian and Japanese
elements, have produced an art which is
uniquely Brazilian.
We must proclaim to the world at large
the tremendous importance of the African
presence in Brazil, in our life, culture and in
the faces of our people.
The black African has contributed to all
the great achievements of Brazil. The pre¬
sence of Africa with its sunlight and shadow
can be felt in the prophets, saints and angels
which the mestizo sculptor Aleijadinho
(1730-1814) carved in the mining region of
Minas Gerais.
Africa is present in the music of Villa-
Lobos and Dorival Caymi, in the Orixas
and Madonnas of Agnaldo, in the poetry of
Gregorio de Matos, Castro Alves and Vini-
cius de Moraes. It is present in the dancing,
and the singing, the gentleness, the friendli¬
ness and the expansive imagination of
everything great in Brazil.
For here in Brazil gods and men have,
happily , become inextricably mingled .
August-September 1977
JORGE AMADO, of Brazil, is one of Latin Amer¬
ica's most widely read novelists. Since the
appearance of his novel Mar Morto (Dead Sea,
1936), which won him a reputation throughout
Latin America, he has published many books
that have been translated into over 30 lan¬
guages. Among his works published in English
are Gabriela (1963) and Doña Flor and Her Two
Husbands (1970).
For four centuries, black Africa has exer¬
cised a strong influence in Brazil, along¬
side the Amerindians and the European
colonizers. Black African cultures and
peoplesplayeda majorpart In the develop¬
ment ofa new type of civilization, which is
neither European nor African, but distinc¬
tively Brazilian. Left, an Afro-Brazilian
family out for a stroll in Salvador de Bahía.
On the wall in background, scenes from
the conquest and colonization of Brazil.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Open letter from a Capilano Indian:
1 was born 1,000 years ago'
This letterfrom Dan George, chief of the Capilano Indians of
British Columbia, Canada, was read at a symposium on the
economic development of the Arctic and the future of Eskimo
societies, by Father André-Pierre Steinmann, of Puvirnituq,
New Quebec.
My very good dear friends,
I was born a thousand years ago, born in a culture of bows
and arrows. But within the span of half a lifetime I was flung
across the ages to the culture of the atom bomb.
I was born when people loved nature and spoke to it as
though it has a soul: I can remember going up Indian River
with my father when I was very young. I can remember him
watching the sunlight fires on Mount Pé-Né-Né. I can remem¬
ber him singing his thanks to it as he often did, singing the
Indian word "thanks" very very softly.
And the new people came, more and more people came,
like a crushing rushing wave they came, hurling the years
aside, and suddenly I found myself a young man in the midst
of the twentieth century.
I found myself and my people adrift in this new age but not
a part of it, engulfed by its rushing tide but only as a captive
eddy going round and round. On little reserves and plots of
land, we floated in a kind of grey unreality, ashamed of our
culture which you ridiculed, unsure of who we were and
where we were going, uncertain of our grip on the present,
weak in our hope of the future.
We did not have time to adjust to the startling upheaval
around us; we seem to have lost what we had without finding a
replacement.
Do you know what it is like to be without moorings? Do you
know what it is like to live in surroundings that are ugly? It
depresses man, for man must be surrounded by the beautiful
if his soul is to grow.
Do you know what it is like to have your race belittled, and
have you been made aware of the fact that you are only a
burden to the country? Maybe we did not have the skills to
make a meaningful contribution, but no one would wait for us
to catch up. We were shrugged aside because we were dumb
and could never learn.
What is it like to be without pride in your race? Pride in
your family? Pride and confidence in yourself?
And now, you hold out your hand and you beckon to me to
come over: "Come and integrate," you say, but how can I
come? I am naked and ashamed; how can I come in dignity? I
have no presents, I have no gifts. What is there in my culture
you value? My poor treasure you can only scorn. Am I then to
come as a beggar and receive all from your omnipotent hand?
Somehow, I must wait. I must find myself. I must wait until
you need something that is me.
Pity I can do without. My manhood, I cannot do without.
Can we talk of integration until there is social integration?
Until there is integration of hearts and minds you have only a
physical presence and the walls are high as the mountain
range.
Come with me to the playground of an integrated school.
Look, it is recess time, the students pour through the doors.
Soon , over there, is a group of white students, and over there,
near the fence, a group of native students.
What do we want? We want first of all to be respected and
to feel we are people of worth; we want an equal opportunity
to succeed in life.
Let no one forget it: we are a people with special rights
guaranteed to us by promises and treaties. We do not beg for
these rights, nor do we thank you for them because, God help
us, the price we paid was exorbitant. We paid for them with
our culture, our dignity and our self-respect.
I know that in your heart you wish you could help. I wonder
if there is much you can do, and yet there is a lot you can do.
When you meet my children, respect each one for what he is: a
child and your brother.
Dan George
January 1975
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Ishi
the last of the Yana Indians
by Alfred Métraux
ONE night in the summer of
1911, a butcher in a small town
in California was woken up by
the furious barking of his dogs. He
went outside and found near his house
a "wild man" leaning against a wall,
quite clearly in the last stages of ex¬
haustion. The sheriff was called, and
after handcuffing the strange creature,
he took him off to the county gaol
where, as an extra precaution, he lock¬
ed him up in the cell reserved for
dangerous lunatics. Ishi, the Indian,
had made a lonely and painful entry
into civilization.
It is curious to note that Ishi did not
retain any unpleasant memories of his
first contact with white men. The pris¬
on had impressed him as a fine house
and he was grateful for the food he had
been given and the way in which he had
been treated. Ishi had, in fact, been
expecting to be killed. He could not
imagine any other fate at the hands of
the white men who had massacred his
own people. Towards 1872, when Ishi
must have been about ten years old, the
small tribe of the Yahis, belonging to
the Yana group of Indians, had been
virtually wiped off the ethnic map of
America. There was barely a handful of
them left.
It is difficult to imagine the existence
of a dozen Indians who have chosen to
live like hunted animals rather than
give themselves up to subjection. They
were forever on the move, taking the
utmost precautions to conceal every
trace of their passage and living only on
the animals they managed to kill or the
fruit and herbs they gathered. Gradual¬
ly, fatigue, age and illness took their
toll of the fugitives.
By 1906, Ishi was alone. For five
years he lived a solitary life in the
forests of his territory. When he was
discovered on the outskirts of one of
the white men's villages, he had made
up his mind to return to the community
of men, even though they might be his
worst enemies.
The American anthropologist Pro¬
fessor Alfred L. Kroeber had made a
life study of the Californian Indians, (1)
and his attention was attracted by the
newspaper reports of the capture of a
"wild man". He telegraphed the sher¬
iff, asking him to receive his colleague,
Professor Waterman. The latter went
to the prison equipped with vocabular¬
ies of the Indian languages of the Cali¬
fornian district, and read lists of these
words to Ishi. He listened patiently, but
his face did not betray the slightest sign
of comprehension.
Waterman was beginning to be dis¬
couraged and was about to give up his
attempt to communicate with the "sa¬
vage" when he pronounced the word
"siwini", at the same time touching the
wood of the bed on which the Indian
was sitting. Ishi's face suddenly lit up.
He repeated the word. The two men,
realizing the importance of the in¬
cident, went on striking the wood as
hard as they could, shouting "Siwini!
Siwini!" The mystery had, to some ex¬
tent, been solved. Ishi could now com¬
municate, after a fashion, with a white
man. He was no longer alone, and his
"hunted animal" look disappeared.
What was to be done with this "sa¬
vage" who could no longer be kept in
gaol? The sheriff consented to his pris¬
oner's transfer to the University of
California. ... Ishi had come out of the
prehistoric past. He seemed to be just
over fifty years old. Would he be able
to adapt himself to the industrial civi¬
lization of the twentieth century?
He showed no emotion or fear when
confronted with the novelties of San
Francisco. The strict Indian etiquette
which he invariably observed forbade
him to do so. He quickly adapted him¬
self to the white man's way of living.
Either out of natural kindness, or
gratitude, or even perhaps because he
realized that he was helping to perpetu¬
ate the memory of his people, Ishi
tried, as far as he could, to pass on his
knowledge to the ethnographers and
linguists who questioned him.
His greatest exploit was the expedi¬
tion on which he took his friends
through the valleys in which he had
lived with the last of the Yahis and
where he had eventually spent years of
wandering on his own.
It was a unique experience for the
ethnologists, and they learnt to see na¬
ture through the eyes of a Neolithic
hunter. As Ishi went further and furth¬
er into the woods which he knew so
well, old memories came surging into
his mind. ... But gradually, the plea¬
sure of finding himself back in his famil¬
iar surroundings gave way to a strange
impatience to be gone. It was with an
eager step that he climbed up into the
train which was to carry him away from
the lands of his ancestors.
Ishi had an iron constitution, but he
had not been immunized against the
white man's illnesses. In spite of the
best medical care, it proved impossible
to rid him of the devastating effects of
tuberculosis, which he contracted dur¬
ing the fourth year of his stay among
the white people. When his friends
judged that his end was near, respect¬
ing the Indian tradition according to
which a man should die in his own
house, they had him taken to the
Ethnological Museum, his "home".
Ishi died stoically, without a word of
complaint, like the members of his
race. His friends, the ethnologists, felt
that it was their duty to deal with his
body as his family would have done,
and accordingly burnt it, together with
his bow, his arrows and his shells. In¬
scribed on the urn which contains his
ashes are the words: "Ishi, the last
Yana Indian, 1916".
February 1963
(1) Ishi in Two Worlds was published by Theodora
Kroeber, widow of Alfred L. Kroeber (University of
California Press, 1961).
ALFRED METRAUX (1902-1963), French
anthropologist of Swiss origin, specialized in
the study of South American Indians. As a
member of the Bureau of American Ethnology
of the Smithsonian Institution, Washington,
D.C., he contributed extensively to the Hand¬
book of South American Indians (1946-1959).
From 1946 to 1962, he held posts with the
United Nations and Unesco. Notable among
his works translated into English are, Ethnolo¬
gy of Easter Island (1940), Myths of the Toba
and Pilagá Indians of the Gran Chaco (1946),
and Voodoo in Haiti (1959).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The blacks in Latin America
by Alejo Carpentier
THE apparent loss of feeling for
their original plastic arts among
displaced Africans transported to
the Americas can be explained by the fact
that sculpture, carving and decorative
painting required free time, which the
slave-holder was not prepared to grant.
He was not going to place workshops
and tools at the disposal of men who were
there to increase his wealth, simply so
that they could have the pleasure of carv¬
ing figures that he considered barbaric
idols and repositories of ancestral beliefs.
On the contrary, any such recollections
had to be wiped from the black man's
memory with the help of the overseer's
lash. "Civilized man" in the West did not
yet have the slightest interest in what he
would later come to value as "folk art".
While the black man's paintings or
carvings were considered works of the
Devil, music, on the other hand, did not
cause much inconvenience. The planta¬
tion owners in Cuba, for example,
allowed their slaves to beat their drums
and dance every evening because this
showed that they were in good health and
that their "ebony flesh" was fit for hard
labour.
Meanwhile, the slaves listened to what
they heard around them. During the six¬
teenth century, when they were first
taken to America, they assimilated Span¬
ish ballads, songs from Portugal and even
French square dancing. They discovered
musical instruments unknown in their
own lands and learned to play them.
If one of them succeeded in being freed
by a master who was more benevolent
than others, he might well turn to music
as a way of earning his living, mingling
with white people in an occupational
freemasonry.
Far removed from his African roots,
the black man in Latin America became a
basic constituent, together with the Indi¬
an, of the creóle class that was to affect
the destiny of a whole continent with its
aspirations, its struggles and its protest.
As the centuries went by, the blacks were
slowly incorporated into the society of
their new homelands and, little by little,
they recovered their poetic sense and the
feeling for the plastic arts which they
seemed to have lost.
Observing ancestral traditions that no
longer bore any relation to their sur¬
roundings was now out of the question.
The black peoples had forgotten their
African dialects by this time and spoke
only the major languages of the New
World. They felt no need to revive old
Yoruba tales, to recall ancient legends or
return to the sources of an oral culture
they were alienated from, but rather to
"make poetry" in the full sense of the
term.
The same thing happened in painting.
Black artists in the New World were com¬
pletely out of touch with art forms that in
Africa were related to religious cults now
left far behind (even though some ves¬
tiges can still be found on altars ostensibly
consecrated to Christian saints).
On the contrary, they had to solve the
same technical problems that face artists
everywhere in any period. It is obvious
then that the work of the black and mesti¬
zo painters and sculptors active in Latin
America in the nineteenth century bore
no resemblance whatsoever to the forms
and stylizations of African art.
This was also true of poetry at that
time. And one may add that there were
many "white" writers the word "white"
has always been quite relative in Latin
America who published novels with
"negro" settings, denouncing the loath¬
some aspects of slavery in the Americas.
It is only in the last fifty years that a
new generation of poets and painters has
appeared, whose works are marked by
the symbiosis of cultures fostered by the
New World. There has been much talk,
for example, of "black poetry", referring
to a resonant, percussive, onomatopoeic
type of poetry which, despite a prevalent
assumption, has often been written by
perfectly "white" poets.
In point of fact, this is an exotic view of
"négritude". The truth is that if "black
poetry" as such ever existed, it would
have had to be a protest on behalf of the
black people oppressed by centuries of
slavery and racial discrimination.
First and foremost, it would have had
to be a revolutionary cry because, since
the sixteenth century, the blacks have
always been in revolt against their over¬
lords in some part of the hemisphere, and
even formed small independent States in
Brazil, the Guyanas and Jamaica States
that sometimes survived for many years.
Never during their long history in the
New World did the blacks give up their
quest for freedom, a quest furthered by
the creóles of all classes and stations who,
after much struggling, finally threw off
the yoke of Spanish, Portuguese, French
and English colonialism.
In short, there exists in the Antilles,
where Spanish, English and French are
spoken, literature and painting with a
markedly creóle character, and it would
be difficult to say just what can be attri¬
buted to their various ethnic com¬
ponents.
August-September 1977
ALEJO CARPENTIER (1904-1980), of Cuba,
was one ofLatin America 's leading novelists. His
many books have been translated into 22 lan¬
guages and include, in English editions: The
Kingdom of this World (1957), The Lost Steps
(1957) published by Knopf, New York, Explosion
in a Cathedral (Gollancz, London, 1963) and
Reasons of State (Partridge, London, 1976). A
musicologist, Carpentier wrote A History of
Cuban Music (1949).
African slaves and the caravels that trans¬
ported them to the New World dominate a
huge mural in an office in Bahia (Brazil).
Along with the Iberian conquistadors, the
blacks were to create a new form ofculture
in the Caribbean, Brazil and other parts of
Latin America. Black artists in the New
World lost touch with purely African art
forms, but family resemblances to the Afri¬
can tradition have survived.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
t
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The land-locked island
of Paraguay
by Augusto Roa Bastos
ONE cannot hope to understand Pa¬
raguay without taking into account
its linguistic problem. For four hun¬
dred years now, two languages have coex¬
isted in the country: Spanish and Guarani
the language of the conquerors and the
language of the conquered. These two lan¬
guages are used as parallel, though not com¬
plementary, means of expression for a
whole society. In this, Paraguay is unique in
Latin America.
For the child with a European father and
an Indian mother, the natural mother
tongue was Guarani, and Spanish was a
language imposed as a symbol of authority.
It was the " language which the mestizo
would in turn use to impose his own author¬
ity on the Indians.
Mestizos and Indians felt that the lan¬
guage of their father or master, as the case
happened to be, was a more integral part of
his dominance than the arms, tools, food,
houses and customs which were the trap¬
pings of his power.
Paraguay has a large rural population,
amounting to some 70per cent of the total.
Almost all are Indians, who communicate
among themselves in Guarani, a language
which is spoken in Paraguay's towns and
cities as well as in rural areas.
In the missionary settlements of the
Jesuits, however, sermons and prayers were
in Guarani. There, the Indian was not
forced to change his language. He did,
however, have to change his rituals, his
liturgy, his gods, and his conception of
nature, of the world and of the universe
although the embers of all these still glow
brightly today in Indian myths about the
universe.
Governor Lázaro de Ribera was mis¬
taken when he complained, at the end of the
eighteenth century, that the language of the
conquered peoples had become dominant.
Guarani was not, and could not be, the
dominant language. It retreated into the
depths of the collective memory, settled
there like a sediment, and came to domin¬
ate/row within the self-expression of Para¬
guay, whether it be bilingual or not.
The use of Guarani or Spanish in Para¬
guay is governed by social and regional
factors. Even people who think of them¬
selves as bilingual will never discuss certain
topics in the indigenous language: it would
be simply impossible because social cir¬
cumstances do not allow it. The Guarani
speaker thus finds in fact that he is excluded
from a whole range of fields because he
cannot make himself heard in them. Worse
still, he cannot even conceptualize them
because he lacks adequate linguistic means
of self-expression.
If, for example, someone speaking
Guarani had access to the world of ad¬
vanced technology, he would find that he
would have to use so many neologisms that
his language would be practically
annihilated.
It is clear that the future of Guarani like
that of Spanish is closely linked to the
historical destiny of the country itself.
Although Guarani has been relegated to
the status of a vehicle for communicating
emotions, it will continue to modulate the
expression of a whole people's deepest and
most vital feelings. Herein lies its strength.
Linked to the mysteries of blood, instinct
and collective memory, the survival of
Guarani is guaranteed by the density of the
linguistic sediment that forms the founda¬
tions of the bilingual island of Paraguay.
August-September 1977
AUGUSTO ROA BASTOS, ofParaguay, won an
international reputation with his book Hijo de
hombre, published in English as Son of Man by
Victor Gollancz, London, 1965. His novel Yo el
supremo is required reading for students ofLatin
American literature in a number of European
universities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Arrival of the first Spaniards in
Michoacán. In his residence at Tzint-
zuntzán, the Cazonci (sovereign) orders
gifts to be taken to the strangers who
were thought to be gods.
The Chronicle
of Michoacán
by J.M.G. Le Clézio
In the sixteenth century, Michoacán, which in the Náhuatl
language means "the place of fish", was the name of the
Indian town of Tzintzuntzán, the capital of the
Porhepecha. We should know nothing about this vanished
civilization of Central America were it not for the Chroni¬
cle of Michoacán, which can rightly be said to be its tes¬
tament. The book was written in Spanish around 1540; it
describes the history of the Porhepecha people, their beliefs
and their faith, and gives the names of their gods and
heroes. The French writer J.M.G. Le Clézio has published
a French translation of the Chronicle of Michoacán (La
Relation de Michoacán, Gallimard, Paris, 1984). In the
following text he evokes this legendary tale of the one-time
glory of the Indians.
THE great stories of history tell us
about beginnings: the creation of
the earth, its first inhabitants, and
the coming of the gods and of the beings
they created.
The Chronicle of Michoacán is one of
the few texts the books of the Chilam
Balam of the Mayas of Yucután and the
Popol Vuh of the Quiche Mayas are
others which tell us about these begin¬
nings. Thanks to the Western system of
writing, it catches the verbal magic of
the fabled past of the people of
Michoacán when, after centuries of
wandering amid tribal warfare, there
came the first signs of the destiny of a
nation which played a vital part in the
civilizations of Central America.
Stricken in its vitals, with its temples
in ruins, its gods overthrown and, worst
of all, the one incarnation of the god
Curicaueri, the Cazonci Tangaxoan
Tzintzicha, fallen and enslaved by the
Conquistador Ñuño de Guzman, the
Porhepecha Kingdom was unable to put
up a fight. The men of this warlike peo¬
ple were struck motionless by a holy
dread, and fighting was out of the ques¬
tion.
The Indians sent these new gods offer¬
ings by way of greeting. But they were
soon to realize that these terrifying mes¬
sengers from the other world had not
come to bring the answer to their
prayers and receive their offerings; they
had come to fulfil the doom-laden
sayings of the oracles.
The news of the destruction of the
opposing empire of Tenochtitlán brought
no solace to the Cazonci; it perturbed
him even more. "Who are you?" he
asked Montano, the first Spaniard to set
foot on his territory. "Where are you
from? What are you seeking? For we
have never heard tell of men such as
you, nor seen such men. Why have you
come from such distant lands? Is there
neither food nor drink in your native
land, that you have come to make the
acquaintance of peoples unknown to
you? And what had the Mexicans done
to you, that you annihilated them when
you were in their city?"
The apprehensive questions of the
Porhepecha people were soon to be
answered. ... The newcomers wanted
gold, the "excrement of the sun", the
symbol of divine power. Their lust for
gold was not sated by the spoils of war
handed over to them by the Cazonci;
they wanted more and more, so they
sacked the temples and profaned the
tombs of the most illustrious kings.
Everything vanished when these con¬
querors approached, everything grew
silent, as the soothsayers had prophesied.
On the banks of a river, at the ford of
Nuestra Señora de la Purificación in the
year 1530, the last Cazonci was tortured and
slain by Ñuño de Guzman, after a parody of
a trial. So ended the glorious line of the
Uacusecha, the Eagles, who had built up
the empire, and also the reign of the god
Curicaueri, whose last incarnation on earth
the Cazonci had been. Another form of
speech, another conquest, were about to
begin, covering over the silence of the
Indians.
All that is left today as a legacy, thanks to
the anonymous Chronicle, is the memory of
that greatness, the legend, both touching
and true, of a past era, when poetry and
history were one, and when the kingdom of
men was like the dwelling place of the gods.
August 1985
JEAN MARIE G. LE CLEZIO is an essayist
and novelist of Franco-Mauritian origin. In
addition to his translation from Spanish into
French of the Relación de Michoacán (The
Chronicle of Michoacán, 1984), his many
published works include French translations
of Mayan texts, such as The Prophecies of
Chilam Balam (1976), and novels such as Le
chercheur d'or (The Gold-seeker, 1985).
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
An illiterate
in Paris
An interview by
Marguerite Duras
Text © Reproduction prohibited.
In countries where free and compulsory education has been applied for gener¬
ations, illiteracy is no national problem. Yet in all countries, even the most ad¬
vanced, a small residue remains of adults who, for one reason or another, have
never learned to read or write. What is the position of the few who have somehow
slipped through the network of compulsory education? What does it mean to be an
adult illiterate in a society where life is organized on the assumption that everybody
can read and write? The French writer Marguerite Duras decided to find out and
managed to discover a middle-aged woman factory worker living at Romainville, a
suburb of Paris, who could neither read nor write. The answers she gives in the
interview published below reveal the poignant drama of an illiterate person living in
a modern capital and the tragedy of being cut off from written communication.
Are there any words which you can recognize
even though you cannot read them?
Yes, three words. The names of the two
Underground stations on the line I take every
day: 'Lilas' and 'Chatelet' and my maiden
name.
Could you pick them out from a group of
other words?
I could recognize them from about a dozen
others, I think.
What do they look like to you ... like
drawings?
Yes, like pictures, if you want. 'Lilas' is a tall
word it's almost as tall as it is wide and it's
pretty. The word 'Chatelet' is too long, and it's
not so pretty. When you see it, you know it's
not the same as the word 'Lilas'.
When you tried to learn to read, did it seem
difficult to you?
You can't imagine what it's like. It's terrible.
Can you give me an idea of what you mean
exactly?
I don't really know. Maybe because every¬
thing is so ... so small. I'm sorry, I'm not very
good at explaining things.
It must be quite a difficult thing foryou to live
in a city like Paris and to get around from one
place to another without being able to read.
Oh, if you've got a tongue in your head you
can get anywhere you want.
How do you manage exactly?
Well, I do a lot of asking. And then I use my
head. It's funny how quick you pick up things
and remember what you see. Much quicker
than other people. It's like a blind person.
There are places where you know where you
are. Then, I ask people.
Do you have to stop and ask your way
often?
Oh, about ten times when I come into Paris
from Romainville on an errand or something.
There are all those Underground station
names. They mix you up. You have to take
another train back, ask again ... and then
there are the names of the streets, the shop
names and the numbers.
The numbers?
I can't read them. When I get my pay or go
shopping, I can count the figures in my head,
but I can't read them.
Don't you ever tell people that you can't
read?
No, never! I always say that I forgot my
glasses.
But there must be times when you can't
avoid it?
Yes, sometimes. When they ask me to sign
my name at the factory or in the Town Hall. But
I go red when I have to say it. If you were in my
shoes you'd know what I mean.
How do you manage in your job?
When I'm being hired, I keep it to myself.
And I always hope to get away with it. It works
most of the time, except when there are time-
slips to fill in. The rest of the time I make
believe I can read.
Everywhere?
Yes, everywhere. In the factory, in the
shops, I look at the labels and the scales and
make believe that I'm reading them. I'm so
afraid that peopple are cheating me, too. I'm
always suspicious.
Does it bother you in your work?
No, I'm a good worker. I've got to be more
careful than the others. I use my head and I'm
careful. I don't have any trouble there.
What about your shopping for food and
things?
I know all the colours of all the brands I use.
When I want to change a brand I ask one of my
friends to come with me. After that I remember
the colours of the new brand. You've got to
have a good memory if you're like me.
What do you do for amusement? Do you
like the cinema?
No, I don't. It's too fast and I don't under¬
stand the way they talk. The pictures always
start with a lot of writing. People read letters
and you see it on the screen. Then they look
sad or happy and I don't understand why. But I
do go to the theatre.
Why the theatre?
You've got time to listen. They tell you
everything they're doing. There's no writing.
They talk slow. I understand better.
Any other amusements?
I like to go to the country and I like to watch
sports. You know I'm no more stupid than
anybody else, but when you can't read you're
like a child.
Do you ever forget that you can't read?
No, I can't. As soon as I walk out of the
house I think about it all the time. It tires you
out and makes you waste time. You never
want people to notice it ... that's what you think
about all the time. You're always afraid.
March 1958
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
"Education", says the report of the Inter¬
national Commission on the Development
of Education, "has the power to cultivate
or stifle creativity." This is what a young
Spanish artist and teacherattempted to do
in his art class at the High School of
Lugones, near Oviedo (Asturias) : his
pupils listened to a piece of classical
music after which, with no further guid¬
ance, they drew images and impressions
evoked by the music. Their drawings often
surprisedby theirquality, considering that
they were the work of culturally underpri¬
vileged children of 10 to 12, whose first
experience of art was acquired in these
classes. Above, "The Rite of Spring" by
Stravinsky as seen by 11-year-old Maria
Paz Martinez. Right, the same composer's
"Fireworks" as interpreted by Leonor
Huerta Rodriguez, aged 10.
A 21-point programme
for a global strategy
in education
In 1971, Unesco set up an International Commission on the Develop¬
ment of Education to carry out an unparalleled world-wide inquiry. The
Commission's purpose was to devise a global approach to educational
problems; to rethink the objectives and methodology of education in
the light of development needs and of individual aspirations; and to
provide ideas for national educational strategies and for international
co-operation. The members of the Commission were Messrs. Edgar
Faure (Chairman), Felipe Herrera, Abdul-Razzak Kaddoura, Henri
Lopes, Arthur Vladimirovitch Petrovsky, Majid Rahnema and Frederick
Champion Ward. Summarized below in 21 points are the conclusions
of the Commission's report.
Lifelong education should be the key¬
stone of all educational policies in the
years ahead, in industrially-developed as
well as developing countries.
O
Artificial or outdated barriers between
different branches and levels of educa¬
tion and between formal and non-formal
education should be abolished.
Lifelong education presupposes a
complete restructuration of education.
Education must cease being confined
within school walls. Education should
become a true mass movement.
Education for pre-school-age children
should be a major objective for educa¬
tional strategies in the 1970s.
O
©
Education should be provided in many
ways. What counts is not how a person
has been educated, but what real know¬
ledge he or she has gained.
Millions of children and young persons
are still deprived of education. Universal
basic education, geared to national
needs and resources, should be a prim¬
ary objective of educational policies for
the 1 970s.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Rigid distinctions between different
branches of education should be re¬
moved. Education, from primary and
secondary levels, should have a com¬
bined theoretical, technological, practical
and manual character.
O
Education should aim not only to train
young people for specific jobs, but also
equip them to adapt to a variety of
occupations.
Responsibility for technical training
should not fall exclusively on the school
system. It should be shared by schools,
business, industry and out-of-school
education.
©
Higher education should be expanded
and made varied enough to meet indi¬
vidual and community needs. Traditional
attitudes towards the university must
change.
34
O
Access to different types of education
and employment should depend only on
a person's knowledge, capacities and
aptitudes.
©
Development of adult education, in
and out of school, should be a priority
objective of educational strategies during
the next ten years.
©
All literacy teaching should be geared
to a country's objectives in social and
economic development.
©
Aids to self-education, including lan¬
guage laboratories, libraries, data banks
and audio-visual equipment, should be
integrated into all education systems.
©
Education systems should be conceived
and planned in terms of possibilities offered
by new educational techniques.
Giving free rein to their imagination, pupils
of the High SchoolatLugones (see caption
previous page) express on paper the im¬
pressions evoked for them by (above)
Johann Sebastian Bach's "Air on the G
String" (Miguel Cortina Garcia, aged 11);
"Spring" (above right) from Vivaldi's "The
Four Seasons" (Maria Pilar Sanjosé Cal¬
derón, aged 11); and, (right) "The New
World Symphony" by Dvorak (Emilio Pra¬
do Sanchez, aged 12).
©
Teacher training programmes should
make full use of the latest teaching aids
and methods.
©
All hierarchical differences between
teachers in primary schools, technical
colleges, secondary schools and univer¬
sities should be abolished.
©
Teachers should be trained to be edu¬
cators rather than specialists in the
transmission of knowledge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
©
Skilled auxiliaries from the trades and
professions (workers, technicians and
executives) should be brought in to
teach in schools. Students should also
participate, educating themselves while
teaching others.
©
Contrary to traditional practice, teaching
should adapt itself to the learner. The stu¬
dent should have greater freedom to decide
for himself what he wants to learn and how
and where to learn it.
©
Students and the public as a whole
should be given a greater say in deci¬
sions affecting education.
November 1972
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Science,
technology
and man
Nobel
Prize¬
winners'
Round
Table
Seated at a "Round Table" set up
under the immense shell of reinforced
concrete housing Unesco's
Conference Hall, eight world-famous
scientists, five of them Nobel Prize
winners, took part in a succession of
scientific and cultural events
organized in November 1958 on the
occasion of the inauguration of
Unesco's new Headquarters and its
Tenth General Conference. Vital
questions arising from the impact of
science and technology on human life
were discussed by members of the
Round Table. We present here
significant passages from these
debates.
Bernardo Alberto Houssay (Argentina)
Nobel Prize for Physiology and Medicine,
1947
IT is a mistake to talk of pure and applied
science. There are not two kinds of science
but only one, and there are the applications
of that science. The public in general and
governments, too, think that only applied sci¬
ence is useful. They are very much mistaken.
People should realize that all the knowledge
on which applied science is based comes
from theoretical or pure science. If theoretical
or pure science is brought to a halt or loses its
impetus, then application, too, becomes slug¬
gish or stops. So we should make no distinc¬
tion between these two aspects of science.
Pasteur said: "It is not the long and involved
political discussions we may read about in the
newspapers that help mankind to progress,
but only the great discoveries of science, of
human thought, and the uses to which they
are put."
P.M.S. Blackett (United Kingdom)
Nobel Prize for Physics, 1948
IT is very important to realize that science,
although it has achieved marvellous
things, is not a magic wand to wave over a
poor country and make it into a rich one.
Science textbooks are cheap; it is reasonably
cheap to train scientists; but it is extremely
expensive to embody the science in the fac¬
tories, the steel works, the transport systems,
the power stations, the mines and the chemic¬
al plants. They all cost an enormous amount
of capital, and the poor countries are very
hard put to find capital. And that simple econo¬
mic reason is why science is so very unevenly
applied over the world today.
I agree that the most important thing for
mankind is not to blow itself up. But I am,
curiously, an optimist about this matter. ... And
assuming that we won't blow ourselves up,
what is the next main problem?
I think the next main problem is to do some¬
thing about the widening gap between the rich
and the poor parts of the world, the rich coun¬
tries which have successfully used science
and obtained all the benefits, and the poor
ones which have not. Now, if we don't do
something about this widening gap, in a few
decades, if the standard of life in the West
goes up at the present rate, we may end up
with a large part of the world poverty-stricken,
as for centuries past, while the advanced
countries of the West are enjoying (if "en¬
joying" is the right term) what has been called
a "five-day weekend".
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
John Boyd Orr (United Kingdom)
Nobel Peace Prize, 1949
IT is the advance of science, leading to
technology and to the birth of new ideas,
which has guided the full evolution of our
civilization.
The problem of the present day, however, is
that in our generation science has advanced
at an accelerating rate. In the last fifty years
science has advanced more than in the 2,000
previous years and in this advance has given
man enormous new powers.
In the past, hunger and disease limited the
growth of population. Today hunger can be
abolished, disease is rapidly being defeated
and we are undergoing an explosive rise in
population. This is one of the problems we
shall need to deal with. Thus, you see, the
advance of science has driven us into an
entirely new age an age where war is impos¬
sible. That is the biggest revolution which has
ever taken place since the beginning of civi¬
lization.
Can we adjust human society to these great
changes? Some people think we cannot. I
believe we can. But it depends upon whether
the people of the world realize what it is we
have to face up to, and make it possible for our
governments to lead us to a new golden age.
Nikolai Semenov (USSR)
Nobel Prize for Chemistry, 1956
WHAT is the situation facing us today?
Science has the means to bring
happiness and contentment to the
world. But should a new war break out (it
would inevitably be an atomic one) then man¬
kind would experience the most dreadful fate
it has ever known.
Which road will humanity take? The deci¬
sion rests with us, on our goodwill, our efforts
and our determination. What we can and must
do is to put an end, once and for all, to the
testing of nuclear weapons. Though this is
perhaps not the main problem it is of primary
importance, for the first effect of prohibiting
nuclear tests would be to prevent any further
development of devastating nuclear
weapons, and would help to re-establish inter¬
national confidence.
This would do much to dispel the present
worldwide fears and depression caused by
the "cold war". It would hasten the next and
most decisive action a banning of the pro¬
duction and use of nuclear weapons, the des¬
truction of all existing stocks of such weapons,
general disarmament, and the renunciation of
war as a means of settling international
disputes.
Daniel Bovet (Italy)
Nobel Prize for Physiology and
Medicine, 1957
WE must see to it that university
teaching is not impoverished; that
humanistic teaching is not impover¬
ished. We must see to it that, where science is
concerned, authority is not transferred from
the university to politics. We must do every¬
thing to avoid the militarization of our en¬
deavours and our culture.
The question of the degree of responsibility
of the scientist, and particularly the physicist,
for all our weapons, all our wars, has some¬
times been raised. Let me take up his de-
fen' a task which is easier for me as I am
not a physicist.
Science is innocent of the crimes of which it
is accused. The only guilty party is society a
society insufficiently permeated with the sci¬
entific spirit.
l--> 0~rv\*_4«. O v¿«-*
-Af ^fy / ¿W^ S^t Oc*¿*~*^*J
February 1959
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The truth behind the veil of facts
Text © Reproduction prohibited by José Ortega y Gasset
FOR centuries the sidereal facts of this
world were set clear before the eyes of
humans; yet what those facts meant,
what they presented to man, what they made
evident to him, was by no means a reality, but
quite the opposite an enigma, a profound
secret, a problem before which man trembled
in terror.
Facts, then, come to be like the figures in
hieroglyphic writing. Have you ever noted the
paradoxical character of such figures? There
they are, holding up their clean profiles to us
so ostentatiously; but that very appearance of
clarity is there for the purpose of presenting us
with an enigma, of producing in us not clarity,
but confusion. The hieroglyphic figure says to
us: "You see me clearly? Good now what
you see of me is not my true being. I am here
to warn you that I am not my own essential
reality. My reality, my meaning, lies behind me
and is hidden by me. In order to arrive at it, you
must not fix your attention on me, nor take me
for reality; on the contrary, you will have to
interpret me, and this means that in order to
arrive at the true and inward meaning of this
hieroglyph, you must search for something
very different from the aspect which its figures
offer."
Science is the interpretation of facts. By
themselves, facts do not give us reality; on the
contrary, they hide it, which is to say that they
present us with the problem of reality. If there
were no facts, there would be no problem,
there would be no enigma, there would be
nothing hidden which it is necessary to de-
hide, to dis-cover. The word which the Greeks
used for truth is aletheia, which means dis¬
covery, taking away the veil that covers and
hides a thing. Facts cover up reality; while we
are in the midst of their innumerable swarm-
ings we are in chaos and confusion. In order to
discover reality we must for a moment lay
aside the facts that surge about us, and re¬
main alone with our minds. Then, on our own
risk and account, we imagine a reality, or to
put it another way, we construct an imaginary
reality, a pure invention of our own; then,
following in solitude the guidance of our own
personal imagining, we find what aspect, what
visible shapes, in short, what facts would be
produced by that imaginary reality. It is then
that we come out of our imaginative solitude,
out from our pure and isolated mental state,
and compare those facts which the imagined
reality would produce with the actual facts that
surround us. If they mate happily one with
another, this means that we have deciphered
the hieroglyph, that we have discovered the
reality which the facts covered and kept
secret.
That labour is what science is. As you see, it
consists of two different operations: one pure¬
ly imaginative and creative, which man pro¬
duces out of his own most free substance; the
other a confronting of that which is not man, of
that which surrounds him, the facts, the data.
Reality is not a datum, not something given or
bestowed, but a construction which man
makes out of the given material.
May 1964
JOSE ORTEGA Y GASSET (1883-1953), inter¬
nationally known Spanish philosopher and
essayist, exercised a strong intellectual influ¬
ence throughout Europe and the Spanish-speak¬
ing world. Among his many works translated into
English are La Rebelión de las masas (The
Revolt of the Masses) and España invertebrada
(Invertebrate Spain). The text on this page is
taken from Man and Crisis (published by W. W.
Nonon and Company, Inc., New York, 1958).
The candle of learning by Abdus Salam
Pakistaniphysicist Abdus Salam, founder
and director of the Unesco-sponsored In¬
ternational Centre for Theoretical Physics,
Trieste, and professor of theoretical phy¬
sics at the Imperial College ofScience and
Technology, London, was awarded the
1979 Nobel Prize for Physics. The prize,
which he shared with two American physi¬
cists, Sheldon Glashow and Steven Wein¬
berg of Harvard University, was awarded
for work in electromagnetic interaction be¬
tween elementary particles. Shortly after
the announcement of the award, Professor
Salam, who has had a long and fruitful
association with Unesco, was Invited to
the Organization's headquarters in Paris
to receive the congratulations of the Un¬
esco Executive Board. The article below
consists of extracts from his address.
THE question which I wish to lead up
to is, are we in the developing world
today firmly on the road to a re¬
naissance in the sciences, just as the
West was in the twelfth century at the time
of Michael the Scot?
For this renaissance to happen, there
are two prerequisites: one, the availability
of places like Toledo where international
concourse can take place, where one can
light a candle from a candle; secondly,
there has to be an interest in developing
societies to give the topmost priority to the
acquisition of knowledge, just as, for ex¬
ample, the Japanese did after the Meiji re¬
volution by enshrining the acquiring of
knowledge in their constitution.
Regretfully, if I may speak the truth and
if I look at the world of developing coun¬
tries as it is today, I see that neither of
these requirements is being met. The
opportunities for international concourse
are fast shrinking, with greater and greater
restrictions on acceptance of overseas
scholars from developing countries. It is
becoming increasingly clear that soon the
developing world will need internationally-
run, United Nations-run, Unesco-run, insti¬
tutions, universities of science, not just for
research as at the United Nations Universi¬
ty in Tokyo, but for high-level teaching of
traditional technology and science, both
pure and applied. The second prerequisite
which I mentioned, a passionate desire on
the part of the developing countries for sci¬
entific knowledge and the removal of all
barriers to its acquisition, is unfortunately
non-existent.
I would like to appeal, first, to the dele¬
gates from the developing countries, of
which I am one. I wish to make a personal
appeal. Science and technology are your
responsibility. Your men of science are
precious assets. Prize them; give them
opportunities to participate in the scientific
and technological development of your
countries. Do not leave them out. The goal
of increasing the 2 billion dollars which the
poorer countries currently spend on non-
military science and research, to the 20
billion they should be spending on the
basis of the norm established by the richer
countries, is ultimately your responsibility.
But having said this, I would also wish to
appeal to the international community, both
to governments and to scientists. A world
so divided where science and technology
are concerned cannot endure. What is one
to think when one sees that an internation¬
al centre for theoretical physics has a
budget of 1.5 million dollars to spend on
100 developing countries, while the great
organization CERN (European Organization
for Nuclear Research), at Geneva, which is
a joint organization of European nations,
has a budget of one-third of a billion dol¬
lars? That is the scale on which scientific
research has to be conducted in order to
be effective.
November 1979
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
y firs
s e s
•
I space
b lek ei Leono
On 18March 1965, AlekseiLeonovbecame the first man to leave a
space vehicle and walk about in outer space. He described his
extraordinary adventure in this article specially written for the
Unesco Courier.
ONLY the unforgettable moments at
the take-off and the recollection of
the long months of flight training
forced me to believe in the reality of the
scene that unfolded before my eyes as I
viewed the spaceship while I floated
through the vacuum of space. Voskhod 11
sailed with an awesome majesty.
Before me, blackness-an inky-black sky
studded with stars that glowed but did not
twinkle; they seemed immobilized. Nor did
the sun look the same as when seen from
Earth. It had no aureole or corona; it re-
sembled a huge incandescent disc that
seemed embedded in the velvet black of
the sky of outer space. Space itself
appeared as a bottomless pit. It will never
be possible to see the cosmos the same
way on Earth.
Below me our blue planet drifted by. It
did not look round but completely flat, like
a giant physical map. Only the curvature of
the horizon showed that it was round.
Two minutes after the ship had been
placed in orbit, Pavel Belyayev, Comman-
der of Voskhod 11, and I began making
preparations for my exit into space.
When we were over Kamchatka, Com-
mander Belyayev helped me to put on the
cylinder containing my air supply. I check-
ed the connexions linking my breathing
mixture to the spacesuit. Belyayev opened
the inner door of the air lock. Together we
fastened to my spacesuit the tether cable
that would keep me attached to the ship.
Built into the tether was the telephone
cable that would be my link with the ship
and Earth. I unstrapped myself from the
seat and floated into the chamber of the
air lock.
I gave a hand signal to the Commander.
The inner door closed behind me. Be-
Iyayev at once began to empty the cham-
ber of air in order to equalize the pressure
with that outside the ship. I could feel this
happening from the way my spacesuit be-
came inflated. Suddenly the outer door of
the air lock opened into space. A blinding
burst of sunlight poured into the chamber. I
made my way forward in the lock towards
the exit and poked my head out. We were
over the Mediterranean.
I found myself spinning and was power-
less to control it. I had had the same ex-
perience when Belyayev and I were prac-
tising in the aeroplane-laboratory the tech-
nique of exit and re-entry under conditions
of weightlessness. So I did nothing about
it. I merely waited for the twisting of the
tether to slow down the rotations. I could
have checked this by grabbing hold of the
tether, but I preferred to keep on rolling
because this enabled me to see better.
While I was drifting in space, I was al-
ways in telephone contact with Pavel Be-
Iyayev and with Earth. I spoke to Yuri
Gagarin who was on duty in the control
room of the spaceport. I heard Radio Mos-
cow announce the launching of our craft.
While over the Yenisei, Commander Be-
Iyayev gave me the signal to re-enter the
ship. I was feeling wonderful, in excellent
spirits, and was in no hurry to leave open
space.
I tried to enter the air lock directly, but
this proved anything but easy. The .inflated
spacel?uit constricted my movements. I had
to use all my strength to re-enter, but be-
fore long I was back in the cabin alongside
Pavel Belyayev.
So ended the experiment in which a
man climbed out of a capsule into space. I
had spent twenty minutes outside the
cabin. During this time, Voskhod 11 had
gone far from the Mediterranean, over
which we had been travelling when I first
went into the air lock-we were now
approaching the Pacific. •
June 1965
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
African
childhood
by Cámara Laye
KOUROUSSA in Guinea, West
Africa, my birthplace and the
traditional home of my fore¬
bears, is a typical Malinke village; the
Djeliba River which flows past it domin¬
ates the life of its mainly agricultural
population. Kouroussa is situated some
700 kilometres from the coast and is
reached by train or automobile.
In my childhood, Kouroussa was a
cluster of round banco (clay-walled) huts
topped by conical thatched roofs. The
village housed various kapila, or ex¬
tended families, bound together by a love
that welded them into united, close-knit
groups.
From my studies of the oral tradition of
West Africa, undertaken over the past
twenty years, I know today that Tabon
Wana Fran Cámara was an ancestor of
mine. He was a contemporary of the
great kings and leaders of the Mandingo,
a people formed of a confederation of
tribes which constituted the basis of the
Malian empire.
According to our elders, the snake
spirit of our race belonged first to Fran
Cámara and made him a skilled and re¬
spected craftsman. As a child I was taken
by my father to see the snake spirit whom
I got to know very well. The source of my
father's skill in the shaping of wood and
the working of metal, the snake spirit was
also his trusted adviser in the art of con¬
trolling his colleagues.
In those days men protected them¬
selves with all manner of greegrees
(charms); it was a time of revealers of
things hidden, and of healers, some of
whom could really heal.
A child in Kouroussa did not belong to
his parents but to his lineage group which
was responsible for him and took care of
his education. The individual remained
linked to the group which was held to
have given him life, and it was within the
group that he continued to live.
This solidarity, or rather this source of
life, made itself felt on important occa¬
sions.
Should a villager fall ill, the men and
women would visit the sufferer on the
way to work in the fields in the morning
and again on their return in the evening.
But it was above all at the time of a death
that the solidarity of Kouroussa was seen
at its best. Work was abandoned so that
everyone could lavish attention on the
one who was dying and on his or her
family.
Today, many of the ancient customs
are unsuited to the modern age and have
had to be abandoned. But the solidarity
arising from these exchanges created a
current of sympathy and was a positive
aspect of traditional society. Solidarity
was a vital force that existed in all African
villages.
In the past, the face, the figure or the
animal that took shape from the wood in
our sculptor's hands and the varied out¬
put of our sculptor-ironsmiths were im¬
bued with mystery and were designed for
use in worship and magic. It was a time
when the sculptor-ironsmith was not
merely a craftsman, but a sorcerer, a
priest in constant contact with fire, which
he used first to melt the ore and then to
breathe shape into the metal. It was a
time when the hoe was not merely a tool
for turning the soil, but an instrument
which controlled the earth and the har¬
vest.
And though these skills have never
been completely lost, they have, inevi¬
tably, become rarer in a society whose
ancient animism has been confronted
with new ideas.
March 1979
CÁMARA LAYE (1928-1980), Guiñean writer,
attended the Qur'anic school and the French
primary school at Kouroussa in northern Guinea,
and later continued his studies in Paris. He told
the story of his childhood in Africa in L'Enfant
Noir (The Black Child).
Evoking the harmony of traditional ways
oflife in Africa, the Togolese sociologistF.
N'Sougan Agblemagnon wrote that "All
form part of a single whole which is
Nature. ... People must live in the world of
Nature, co-ordinating their rhythms with
those of Nature. This is a form of happi¬
ness which African children learn In their
earliestyears." Right, musician of the Bas-
sari people (Republic of Guinea).
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The sting
in the
fairy
tale
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
'A1
T one time or another," says
Bruno Bettelheim, "every child
dreams of being a prince or a
princess." Yet what child of the tropical
plains or plateaux of Latin America would
ever have dreamed of such a thing if these
(fairy tale) images had not been imposed
upon him, images made much more con¬
crete by Gustave Doré's at times gruesome
engravings and Walt Disney's cloying car¬
toons, and made superficially more real by
the stage versions of these tales in which
schoolchildren are obliged to take part?
Given the authors and the immediate
audience for whom they were writing, the
kings and queens, princes and princesses
who figure in these tales were inevitably
generous and charitable, beloved of their
subjects and respected by their peers. They
had neither armies nor police forces (at
most a few kind-hearted gamekeepers) and
they never declared war. Only rarely were
their subjects sent to prison or to the execu¬
tioner's block, and then only through the
spiteful machinations of a wicked step¬
mother. The queens and princesses,
moreover, were all remarkable for their
beauty. The young Latin American was not
slow in recognizing that, in comparison with
the realities of his life, all this was nothing
more than a huge adult lie.
In European fairy tales, which draw on
Scandinavian, German and Slav traditions,
the characters are naturally white-skinned,
blue-eyed and fair-haired (with the sole ex¬
ception of Snow White whose hair was "as
black as ebony"). Yet in Latin American
society, where economic discrimination
almost always goes hand in hand with discri¬
mination of a racial nature, the tacit identi¬
fication of this type of beauty with goodness
may have undesirable repercussions.
Young indigenous and mixed-race Latin
Americans who, quite naturally, reject this
discrimination may tend to develop a sense
of inferiority, especially since at school and
in daily life they are already set apart by the
more or less white children whose servants
they often are.
In the Grimm brothers' version of Cin¬
derella this identification is quite deliber¬
ate: "This woman (the stepmother) had
brought with her two daughters who,
though beautiful and fair of complexion,
were nevertheless evil and black-hearted."
In establishing the exceptional nature of
this case, the "nevertheless" betrays the
ideological content of the sentence. If we
were to turn the sentence round and say that
"the daughters, though ugly and black-
skinned, were nevertheless good and pure
in heart", the racist implication, however
involuntary it may be, would become bru¬
tally apparent. It is easy to see why, for
Latin American children, the most comfort¬
ing, or at any rate the least cruel, of these
stories is Hans Andersen's Ugly Duckling.
A vital element in this literature, this
ideology, is the solution of problems not by
human endeavour but by providential
means which constitute, moreover, the re¬
ward for submission. A king's son trans¬
forms Cinderella's life, other princes do the
same for Snow White and Sleeping Beauty,
and a dragon and a soldier arrive'in the nick
of time to save Bluebeard's third wife. Two
centuries later the situation is brought up to
date. At closing time, a humble washer-up
in a bar sings at her work and a film director
seated in a corner "discovers" her and
makes her a film star. Unfortunately there
are very few Marilyn Monroes; millions of
young Latin American match-sellers,
goose-girls and Cinderellas are destined
only to become adult Cinderellas. They
have no fairy godmother with a magic wand
to free them from their toil and change their
rags into silken robes and their sandals into
glass slippers. They have no prince to come
to their rescue, not even a more prosaic
modern equivalent the son of a president,
of an industrial magnate or of a banker. For
most women the dream of Cinderella be¬
comes the harsh reality of Snow White; if
she wants a roof over her head she can stay
and be provided for so long as she is pre¬
pared to "make the beds, cook, wash, sew,
spin and keep everything clean and tidy" for
the dwarfs.
January 1979
JORGE ENRIQUE ADOUM, Ecuadorian writer,
has published several volumes ofpoetry, includ¬
ing an anthology, No son todos los que están -
Poemas (1949-1979), a novel, Entre Marx y una
mujer desnuda, and two plays, La subida a los
infiernos and El sol bajo las patas de los cabal¬
los, the latter of which has been published in
English as The Sun Trampled Beneath the
Horses' Hooves.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Disabled characters
in search of an author
by Tordis Orjasaeter
IT is important for handicapped chil¬
dren to meet themselves in chil¬
dren's books, to see pictures and
read about children like themselves,
their lives, problems, feelings, circum¬
stances. And it is important for other
children to get acquainted with handicap¬
ped children.
Mentally retarded, physically handicap¬
ped or other disabled children almost never
see children like themselves on television or
in films, unless the programme specifically
concerns handicapped children. They
almost never belong to their environments
in the mass media as naturally as other
children do.
During the last decade quite a few
books have appeared about handicapped
children, but many of them are not good
enough. They often activate our mechan¬
isms of rejection and make integration
even more difficult. Because literature
influences us for better or for worse,
especially when we are children, it is im¬
portant to evaluate it critically.
There is the hidden rejection found in
many well-intentioned books where heal¬
thy young people who meet handicapped
persons are filled with gratitude for their
own good health. The underlying atti¬
tude is that the normal thing is to be
healthy, beautiful and charming and the
handicap somehow is a kind of punish¬
ment for our sins.
The blind characters in children's
books are mostly girls it seems so suit¬
able that girls should be sweet and gen¬
tle and play the piano. The characters in
wheelchairs are mostly boys, extraordi¬
narily clever boys, the best companions
anyone can think of and such excellent
referees in a football or baseball game.
The handicap is compensated far beyond
reasonable limits.
There are so many misleading books
about mentally handicapped children.
Some typical examples: many authors
use the description ill when they write
about mentally retarded children. They
are not ill, no more than other children,
unless they have measles or colds or
something like that. They are not ill,
they are retarded in their mental de¬
velopment.
We need books containing good
psychological descriptions of the hand¬
icapped person as one of the main char¬
acters, and books where handicapped
children belong to their environment as
naturally as do other people. Happily,
books exist in which the author shows
both insight and poetic power.
Most children's books about the hand¬
icapped tell us about children with
physical or sensory handicaps, and the
authors' intention is quite obviously to
make the readers identify themselves
with these children. Books about mental¬
ly handicapped children ¡ire fewer in
number and mostly written from the
point of view of a sister or brother.
During the last decade we have seen a
number of photographic picture books
about handicapped children. Children
who read them are usually as fascinated
by this documentary material as by fic¬
tion. It acquaints them with handicapped
children in their daily life. Such books
are often excellent for handicapped chil¬
dren as well; they can look at pictures of
and read about children who look like
themselves and have to struggle with
some of the same frustrations.
Especially interesting are picture books
made by authors or artists who are
themselves parents or siblings of hand¬
icapped children, using their personal ex¬
perience and love, trying to tell other
children how it can be for a family to
have a handicapped son or daughter, sis¬
ter or brother.
June 1981
TORDIS ORJASAETER, of Norway, associate
professor at the Norwegian Advanced College
for Special Education, is the author of several
books on children's literature. This article has
been extracted from a background paper pre¬
pared for a Seminar on Books and Disabled
Children, organized by Unesco in co-operation
with the Bologna Children's Book Fair in April
1981.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
All about Alice
by Anthony Burgess
Copyright © Anthony Burgess, 1982.
Reproduction prohibited
LEWIS Carroll, who wrote Alice's
Adventures in Wonderland (1865)
and Through the Looking-Glass
(1872), was, in private life, a professor of
mathematics at the University of Oxford
named Charles Lutwidge Dodgson.
He produced other books as well most¬
ly on difficult mathematical subjects.
Lewis Carroll was also the first of the
great photographers, and his studies of chil¬
dren especially of little Alice Liddell , who
was both the heroine and the first reader of
the two great books have a charm and a
mastery of technique envied by the snap¬
pers of today.
His love of girls, which he was too inno¬
cent to interpret sexually, had perhaps
something to do with his desire to remain a
child himself.
He never married, he was deeply and
innocently religious, he liked to be cut off
from the dangerous outside world. But the
publication of the two Alice books brought
him fame.
Both the Alice books are fantasies,
aspects of the love of nonsense which was
prevalent in England in the Victorian age.
There was no nonsense in the rest of the
world.
Alice's adventures take the form of
dreams in which bizarre things happen, but
these things are based on a more serious
approach to language than we can permit
ourselves in waking life. By language I
mean, of course, the English language in
which Carroll wrote; many of his dream-
jokes are impossible to render into other
tongues.
There is a strange poem which one of the
characters, Humpty Dumpty, kindly ex¬
plains to Alice, that sums up the possibili¬
ties of the dreaming world. It is called "Jab-
berwocky" and it begins:
Twas brillig, and the slithy toyes
Did gyre and gimble in the wabe.
All mimsy were the borogroves,
And the mome raths outgrabe.
"Slithy" is both slimy and lithe, to "gyre"
is to girate, to "gimble" is both to gambol
like a lamb and to turn like a gimlet or
corkscrew. Humpty Dumpty calls these
"portmanteau words", because, like port¬
manteaux, several things can be crammed
into them. James Joyce saw the possibilities
of this Jabberwocky language and, in his
great novel Finnegans Wake, which pre¬
sents an adult, not a child's, dream, he used
the technique. What, with Carroll, began as
a joke ends, in Joyce, as the most serious
attempt ever made to show how the dream¬
ing mind operates.
To be honest, Alice is not a very nice little
girl. She is far too sharp and bossy and
proud. She lacks humility, but and this is
an aspect of the British imperialist spirit
she also lacks fear. It requires great
44
courage, at the trial of the Knave of Hearts,
with the Queen shouting "Off with her
head!", for her to cry: "You're nothing but
a pack of cards!" and to see the chaos of the
mass of pasteboard that, a minute ago, was
an imperialist society whirling about her
head. She is transported to mad colonial
territories and retains something of her
sanity. She is very British and very Victor¬
ian, but she is also admirably and universal¬
ly human.
June 1982
ANTHONY BURGESS, prolific British novelist,
critic and man of letters, has published most
recently Flame into Being, a study of D.H. Law¬
rence (1985) and Homage to Qwertyuiop ( 1986),
a collection of essays.
"Off with her head!" the Queen shouted at
the top other voice. Nobody moved. "Who
cares for you?" said Alice (she had grown
to her full size by this time). "You're no¬
thing but a pack of cards!" At this the
whole pack rose up into the air and came
flying down upon her. ...
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
A Third World view of human rights
by Radhika Coomaraswamy
TO a great extent, the Third World has
not played a creative part in the for¬
mulation and implementation of human
rights. Though human rights embody many
tenets found in all the world's cultures, the
theoretical origins of the human rights move¬
ment are distinctively Western. The pillar con¬
cepts of the movement liberty, equality,
material welfare and self-determination are
formulated in the manner envisioned by the
modern movements of nationalism, liberalism
and socialism. These movements originated
in the West but have influenced political,
values throughout the world.
These historical origins alone have made
many cultural nationalists advocate the rejec¬
tion of the human rights movement as a uni¬
versal norm. Violations of human rights are
justified in terms of the illegitimacy of certain
human rights values in the Third World con¬
text. This remains a major crisis for the human
rights movement in the latter half of the twen¬
tieth century.
What approach should be adopted to re¬
concile the tension between the inherited
tradition of human rights and major develop¬
ments in the non-Western world? It is inevit¬
able that any such reappraisal must begin
with a view of history as a collective ex¬
perience, a synthetic process of human rights
learning and growth. At present there is a
need for Third World insights into human
rights protection, but the process must be a
creative one and not a denial of the very
concept of human rights; a process of supple¬
mentation and not of derogation.
The problem posed by this polemic be¬
tween North and South has two aspects. The
first is the reconciliation of non-Western cultu¬
ral values with the basic concepts of human
rights. The second is the integration of the
"development" experience into the norms and
structures of human rights protection. One
method of moving towards resolution of these
problems would be to regard human rights not
as ends in themselves but as a process which
implies a certain approach to law, politics and
economics. It should be seen as an approach
which accentuates the human dilemma above
other considerations.
The human rights movement cannot im¬
mediately be removed from the context of its
own history and structures. To do so would be
to deny it content and increase ambiguity.
The success, of the human rights movement
in the future of developing societies is greatly
dependent on its ability to convince the youth
of these nations that human rights must be an
important, if not primary, concern of any poli¬
tical ideology. It is therefore imperative that
teaching human rights be considered a fun¬
damental aspect of the school curriculum.
RADHIKA COOMARASWAMY is a Sri Lank¬
an lawyer who has specialized in human
rights research and education.
Though women's rights have received
much attention in the Western world, the
dilemma is more fundamental and complex in
developing societies. On the one hand, the
problem is political, legal and economic, espe¬
cially in relation to the so-called "modern"
sector. The human rights approach to
women's rights has most relevance to this
sector where the structure and style of the
industrial establishment are based on those
either in Western Europe or the Communist
countries of Eastern Europe.
The "techno-rational" principles of man¬
agement and policy-making are especially re¬
levant to the structures of protection formu¬
lated and implemented by the human rights
Resting in the shade, India.
movement. As the organizations in the mod¬
ern sector are prototypes of their European
counterparts, the human rights issues greatly
resemble those which are present in the de¬
veloped societies. The issues are, never¬
theless, accentuated because of a limited
sharing of resources.
On another level, the problem of women's
rights in developing societies has enormous
social and psychological dimensions. In many
ways, the issues of women's rights have ac¬
centuated the constant tension between tradi¬
tion and modernity. There is an important and
fundamental need to extricate women's rights
from the constraint of traditional ideas and
institutions, while acknowledging the creative
role that such concepts may play in other
areas of social and political life.
August-September 1982
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
by Niliifer Gole
Women of the Mediterranean:
tradition and change
P
46
"It is up to us to dismantle themechanisms
of invisibility, all those processes which
impoverish our relationship with the
world, impose silence on the majority of
women, and bring to the fore a few of us,
under certain conditions, to legitimize the
exclusion process as a whole. n
Fatma Oussedik (Algeria)
RUNNING in filigree through studies
on the situation of women in various
Mediterranean countries is a com-
mon thread: a desire to seek out the femi-
nine presence wherever it lies hidden, in the
political and cultural as well as the religious
and urban context.
The two dominant aspirations offeminist
movements in the industrialized coun-
tries-the equality of the sexes and the
search for a specifically feminine identity-
find an echo in the perceptions of women of
the Mediterranean countries.
In the industrialized countries these two
themes made headway only with difficulty.
... Does not the demand for both equality
and recognition of a specific identity leave
women in a "Catch 22" situation?
This thorny problem also faces the
women of the Mediterranean. The societies
in which they live are exposed to the
onslaught of the hegemonic cultural model
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
of the industrialized countries, a
homogenizing model conceived in terms of
the Universal, of History, of Progress, as
opposed to regional, national and cultural
specificities.
Mediterranean societies are not, by
nature, modern societies in the individualis¬
tic, egalitarian, liberal sense. Liberal ideol¬
ogy situates and defines Western society
both in the "public" area (social relation¬
ships) and in the "private area" (the rela¬
tionship between the sexes); when it in¬
trudes on Mediterranean societies, it not
only meets strong resistance with regard to
matters concerning the "private" area but
also creates a duality in the social sphere.
Italy is an example of a Mediterranean
country in which these two influences co¬
habit and even create a geographical dicho¬
tomy between the North and the South,
with the northern influence more and more
gaining the upper hand.
The complexity of the situation in which
Mediterranean women find themselves re¬
sults from the specificity of their cultural
heritage, the impact of a hegemonic cultural
model and the claims of the feminist
movement. The conflict between the sexes
thus takes on a particular coloration in each
country as a result of the interaction and the
opposition between these elements in the
religious, political and cultural fields.
In the political and religious context of
the Arab Mediterranean the question arises
as to whether or not the Islamic cultural
heritage constitutes an obstacle to equality
of the sexes. Must the Arab-Islamic past be
"mutilated" in order to enable equality of
the sexes to be established, or should this
past be sifted and analysed, in which case
might not a measure of hidden political
power of women stand revealed?
In Morocco, women who have exercised
direct power have been given a dehuman¬
ized image, being represented either as
something "monstrous" or as pertaining to
the "sacred". However, the exercise of in¬
direct power via a husband or a son seems to
have been more acceptable to the extent
that it conjured up the image of the devoted
wife or mother.
Examination of the specific form domina¬
tion of women takes in Algeria comes down
to an examination of the various aspects of
Algerian women's "invisibility", that is to
say, the various forms of social rejection to
which they are subject as being "Other". It
also involves study of the struggle of those
women who have attempted to escape from
this cloak of "invisibility" by acquiring a
certain autonomy in their private lives or by
outright militancy.
One aspect at least of the condition of
Mediterranean women can be defined.
From the situation of Algerian women to
that of Italian women there is a progression
from "silent" action towards conscious, col¬
lective action by women. The "silent" way
is perhaps peculiar to Muslim societies;
nevertheless, outspoken, independent ex¬
pression by women is possible only within
the context of a lay society.
April 1985
NILUFER GOLE is a Turkish sociologist and the
author of many articles and studies on women 's
participation in public affairs, the discrimination
from which they suffer and the solutions pro¬
posed by feminist movements.
Self-portrait
of a woman writer
by Ding Ling
I am a Chinese writer, and for the
first sixty years of my life I lived,
worked and wrote in the wake of
the Chinese people, by whose difficulties
I have been guided and inspired. In this
way I came to know the world and its
contradictions,^ but at the cost of many
trials and tribulations. Today, at the age
of seventy-seven, one hope remains to
be able to serve my fellow countrymen
until I die.
I was born in 1904, at a time when
the Manchu Empire was in its death
throes, into a family of notables, a
breeding-ground of mandarins such as
described in those great classic Chinese
novels Dream of the Red Chamber, by
Cao Xueqin, and The Scholars, by Wu
Jingzi.
My family was a replica in miniature
of feudal society in decline and its his¬
tory was a chequered one. The branch
of the family to which my father be¬
longed was impoverished and going
rapidly downhill, and when I was four
years old my father died completely
ruined. My lonely childhood gave me an
insight into the miserable lot of the peo¬
ple in Chinese society at the beginning
of the twentieth century and opened my
eyes to the selfish attitudes which gov¬
erned relationships between one man
and another. I found comfort in, and
learned much from, reading the great
Chinese classic novels. European Re¬
naissance literature and foreign literature
of the nineteenth century was also grist
to my mill. And it was this reading that
sowed in me the seed of my vocation as
a writer.
Ding Ling during a visit to a farm co¬
operative in 1955
I became a writer, not out of personal
vanity or out of a love of art for art's
sake, but to defend my fellow country¬
men and help them to achieve liberty.
The same objectives motivated other
writers, both my contemporaries and
those of the following generation, to en¬
gage in a literature of combat.
I wanted to give myself up totally to
the cause of the people, to share their
destiny, their cares and their sufferings,
to live and die with them. During the
1920s my female characters had been
petty bourgeois intellectuals in revolt;
from the 1930s onwards they were based
on working women and peasants.
I took part in the agrarian reform
which abolished the feudal land system
and redistributed the land. In the new
China that had just been established I
was given the task of helping in the
reorganization of literary life. So
absorbed was I in this task that I almost
forgot that I too was a writer. It was
only when this practical work was com¬
pleted that I began once again to be
haunted by the characters buried deep
within my soul. I became eager to reveal
their existence by writing them into my
novels, stories and essays.
When I write, my pen follows the
thread of my imagination and I stick to
my first impulses, not trying to refashion
the characters I have known and loved
in my life and who become the heroes
and heroines of my books.
December 1982
DING LING (1904-1986) is one of the most
popular figures in modern Chinese literature.
Among her novels translated into English is
The Sun Shines over the Sangkan River.
L*4
J^M ^Bk ^m - - ^^fe M
-
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The following two articles, in which the Italian writer Alberto
Moravia and the Canadian thinker Marshall McLuhan set forth their
reflections on the future of the book in the modern world, were
specially written for the January 1972 issue of the Unesco Courier,
devoted to International Book Year.
K¿ * m :
The image
and the word
by Alberto Moravia
<J>
v
FEW persons appear to have given
much thought to the fact that the
image owes its success to the entry
into history's arena of large masses of
humanity, including their new literates and
total illiterates.
The illiterate person undeniably has a
distinctive visual awareness. For him the
whole world is a vast system of visual signs
and symbols waiting to be interpreted and
translated.
So in the first place, what we are dealing
with is not so much a decline of the book as a
triumph of the image, a triumph due in far
smaller measure to those who have always
been readers than to those who only yester¬
day did not know how to read.
If this is so, as I myself believe, we can
expect at any time to see a sfeady decline in
the influence of the image and a corres¬
ponding resurgence of the book. In other
words, as millions upon millions of illiterate
men and women learn to read and write,
they are likely to abandon the primitive,
direct language of the image in favour of the
more elaborate, more indirect language of
the printed word.
That this hypothesis is plausible is borne
out by the huge circulation of paperbacks.
The paperback scatters the seeds of the
culture of all ages and all regions wholesale
upon completely virgin soil. In the space of
a few years, the entire population of our
planet, only now barely emerging from
illiteracy, has been inundated, without any
preparation, with the culture of thirty
centuries.
The danger is that this culture will not be
assimilated, but thrown together, con¬
densed and reduced to mere formulas and
synthetic aggregation in a vast grinding op¬
eration of destruction. After which the
masses would apparently be free to revert
to the image, thenceforward the sole
medium of communication.
Besides, the image itself has recently
appeared to be reaching its limits. The fact
that the spectator takes in the picture pas¬
sively, without any attempt at interpreta¬
tion, ultimately results in the picture itself
losing its full force and becoming a victim of
this passivity.
The decline of the book is by no manner
of means, then, a certainty. Even if we
ignore the fundamental fact that the book
springs from nature, that is from the faculty
natural to all human beings to utter words
and shape them into organized speech, we
should not overlook the fact that the book is
made up of words which are "also", under
certain conditions of poetic creativity, im¬
ages. Thus there is no substantial difference
between the image suggested by the book
and the image that appears on the screen. In
fact there is only one difference, though an
important one: the image on the screen
allows for no play of imagination; it is what
it is.
Nevertheless, we must distinguish be¬
tween one type of reading and another type
of reading, between one book and another
book. Reading some books is no more than
a simple physical exercise. For a book to be
properly "read" it must first be really
"written".
A book, then, must be thought out and
created or it is not a book. Indeed, the
future of the book is bound up with the
poetry, creativeness, descriptive power and
imagery of the writing. The future of the
book will be assured if we succeed in
"writing" books; it will perish if we content
ourselves with merely printing them.
January 1972
+2
t
48
ALBERTO MORAVIA, Italian writer, is one of the
great names of contemporary world literature.
He has published some 15 novels, from Gli
Indiferenti (1929, The Time of Indifference) to
1 934 (1982) as well as volumes of short stories,
five plays and many articles on social and politi¬
cal subjects.
It will take until the year 2000 for the pre¬
cious book collections of the libraries of
Florence, ravaged by the floods of 1966, to
be fully restored. Right, a cleaning and
drying centre set up in a former tobacco-
curing shop.
*
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
1 1 . gi
\«Uli
^ jO > .« 4*
j«fi
__ - TT
*TW»*f
^
»
V#i
Ü¿ar
SB«:
Zp- *
_« %
fTt'
;3 *-:
¡p
!fe3
.
h
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
ü
>
i-
©
The yestermorrow
of the book
by Marshall McLuhan
Text©McLuhan Associates Limited, 1972
Reproduction prohibited w
rHEN Gutenberg transformed the
European manuscript into a new
uniform and repeatable package,
he ended the regime of oral scholastic phil¬
osophy and provided the means of retriev¬
ing the world of pagan authors.
At the same time that the new intensity of
words as visual objects came into play
against the old oral ground, words became
visual counters in a new "objective" sense.
The world of resonance and multi-levelled
50
depth of verbal structures which had been
the basis of the exegesis both of the sacred
page and the Book of Nature, was suddenly
muted by high visual stress.
New kinds of rational authority were sub¬
stituted for the old resonance with its affin¬
ity for magic and metamorphosis.
Clearly, scholastic philosophy was a form
of discourse that would not do in the new
era. It was doomed, not because of its con¬
tent or meaning, but because it was chatty,
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
"The new electronic interdependence,"
wrote Marshall McLuhan, "recreates the
world in the image of a global village, " an
aphorism aptly portrayed by the optical
trickery of this Salvador Dali painting, Vis¬
age paranoïaque (vertically a face, hori¬
zontally a group of villagers).
conversational discussion that took all man¬
ner of things into account at any given
moment.
With the coming of print, specialism de¬
veloped because the individual reader, by
solitary effort, could speed over the super¬
highways of assembly-line printing without
the company or comment of a group of
fellow learners and disputants.
With the advent of telegraph and tele¬
phone and radio and TV as service environ¬
ments, totally new figure-ground rela¬
tionships have come into play. In science
and in fiction, in art and in politics, the fact
of audience involvement in all aspects of the
social process has become an irresistible
datum.
So far as the book is concerned, the mode
and means of involvement of reader as co¬
author and of audiences as actors has been
the symbolic or discontinuous form in poet¬
ry and painting, and music, in press and
novel, and in drama.
Print made handwriting "obsolete", but
there is more handwriting in the present day
than there ever was before printing.
Obsolescence is not extinction but the
necessary matrix of innovation. Therefore
handwriting has blossomed out in many
new forms, including that of the typescript.
In the same way as the information
offered by the printed book is outstripped
by photo and film and TV, the book has
steadily hybridized with other forms of
visual image giving us many new art forms.
There is a sense in which it is possible to
speak of the book as "hardware" tech¬
nology.
The paradox is, oral culture is stable and
conservative, whereas the written word is
fashionable and fluctuating. There is a good
deal on this subject in The Gutenberg
Galaxy. For example, "correct" grammar
begins with the written word. Nobody ever
committed a grammatical error in an oral
culture.
Alexander Pope felt that an inky smog
had settled over all human consciousness in
the age of Newton. What lay ahead now
seems, in retrospect, to have been a con¬
siderable advance over the world that Pope
saw in dissolution. In the age of video cas¬
settes, when it will be possible to dial a book
as easily as an acquaintance, totally new
forms of literary experience are at hand. It
is our literate job to be ready to cope with
these innovations.
January 1972
HERBERT MARSHALL McLUHAN (1911-
1980), Canadian sociologist, was founder-direc¬
tor of the Centre for Culture and Technology of
the University of Toronto (1963-1980). In addi¬
tion to his celebrated work The Gutenberg
Galaxy (1962), he was also the author of Under¬
standing Media (1964) and The Medium is the
Massage (with Quentin Fiore, 1967).
Man, by Victor Bunak
the first walkie-talkie
SCIENTISTS have long speculated
about the origins of speech, and a
great many theories have been ad¬
vanced.
One of the earliest, already current in
Ancient Greece, held that the first words
were onomatopoeias imitations of the
sounds prehistoric man associated with
various activities. Another maintained that
words developed from inarticulate cries of
fear, alarm, delight and so on.
But none of these theories explains how
shouts or onomatopoeias could turn into
articulate syllables and words, or what fac¬
tors determined the development of mental
activity along with the faculty of speech so
closely connected with it. For it is man's
ability to speak that above all distinguishes
him from the animal.
Man finally left the animal world when he
was at last able to reproduce in his mind
coherent images of different objects and
actions, to distinguish between them and to
combine some with others. The mental im¬
ages of these linked percepts are what we
call concepts, and the capacity to form con¬
cepts was the first main feature distin¬
guishing Homo sapiens from the earlier
hominids.
The next stage in man's evolution was the
ability to combine and diversify these con¬
cepts, a process representing a considerable
development of the intellectual faculty.
The combination of percepts in a single
mental operation or concept becomes possi¬
ble because of its association with vocal
stimulations. The sound of the voice and
the corresponding movements in the mouth
and throat become, as it were, symbols of
concepts, a different set of vocal move¬
ments being associated with each one.
The vocal organs can produce a great
many sounds, but in each language only
some thirty, known as phonemes, are used.
There are, however, hundreds of phoneme-
combinations or syllables, and many
thousands of syllable combinations.
Modern man can produce hundreds of
syllables a minute, each of which requires a
different use of the vocal chords, a different
direction of air expelled from the lungs and
a different positioning of the tongue and the
mouth cavity. The whole system of articula¬
tion can switch from one position to the next
in a fraction of a second.
This mobility of the speech organs and
the extremely flexible link-up of concepts
are the result of a long evolution.
The first words, still few and mainly
monosyllabic, related to material objects
and basic facts in the lives of primitive peo¬
ples, particularly their food-gathering, and
perhaps some percepts with a magical
meaning. New words were formed by
doubling or inverting syllables or by
changes in the pitch of some sounds. First
mastered by one or several members of a
group, they were adopted by the group as a
whole if they supplied a need, and then
modified by practical use.
A major change took place at the end of
the Stone Age, at the time of the fourth and
final glacial period, when the direct ances¬
tors of modern man, (Homo sapiens)
appeared, some 50,000 to 30,000 years ago.
So far as their technology, economy and
arts were concerned, the Neolithic people
of the last glacial period in Europe had a
standard of living and way of life that were
by no means inferior to those of certain
hunting and food-gathering tribes still ex¬
isting today. There is no doubt that they
were able to form paired combinations of
concepts and words. In other words, they
had fully mastered articulate speech.
The periods that followed saw the ela¬
boration of different speech systems or lan¬
guages with their own phonetic, lexical and
grammatical structures.
According to historical, archaeological
and linguistic research, the great basic lan¬
guage systems emerged in the early Age of
Metals some 6,000 to 9,000 years ago, while
the formation of many contemporary lan¬
guages dates from historical times.
August-September 1972
VICTOR BUNAK of the USSR is one of the
world's leading authorities on the early develop¬
ment of speech.
©
"He said his first word today, 'pterodactyl'!" u
51
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
Tongues
that span
the centuries
by Amadou Hampâté Bâ THE Bambara tradition of the Komo
(one of the great initiation schools of
the Mande group of peoples of Mali)
teaches that the Word, Kuma, is a fun¬
damental force emanating from the Sup¬
reme Being himself Maa Ngala, creator of
all things. It is the instrument of creation:
"That which Maa Ngala says, is!" proclaims
the cantor, the singing priest of the god
Komo.
The story of Genesis used to be taught
during the sixty-three-day retreat imposed
on the circumcised in their twenty-first
year, and then twenty-one years were spent
in deeper and deeper study of it.
After the initiation, the recital of the
primordial genesis would begin:
"There was nothing except a Being,
That Being was a living Emptiness,
Brooding potentially over contingent
existences.
Infinite Time was the Abode of that One
Being.
The One Being gave himself the name
Maa Ngala.
Maa Ngala wished to be known.
52
]]>
</page>
<page number="53">
<![CDATA[
It would be virtually impossible to over¬
emphasize the importance of the oral
tradition in Africa where, it has been said,
whenever an old man dies a whole library
disappears with him. In societies that have
oral rather than written records, it is by
word of mouth that the guardians of the
collective memory hand down from one
generation to the nextstories, legends and
poetry, society's moral values and re¬
ligion, the mastery of occult forces, the
secrets of initiation into different crafts, as
well as detailed accounts of actual events
of yesterday or today. Left, an African
griot, or musician-entertainer. Griots are
leading transmitters of the African oral
tradition.
So he created Fan,
A wondrous Egg with nine divisions,
And into it he introduced the nine
fundamental
States of existence.
"When this primordial Egg came to
hatch, it gave birth to twenty marvellous
beings that made up the whole of the uni¬
verse, the sum total of existing forces and
possible knowledge.
"But alas! None of those first twenty
creatures proved fit to become the inter¬
locutor (Kuma-nyon) that Maa Ngala had
craved.
"So he took a bit of each of these twenty
existing creatures and mixed them; and
then, blowing a spark of his own fiery
breath into the mixture, he created a new
Being, Man, to whom he gave a part of his
own name: Maa. And so this new being,
through his name and through the divine
spark introduced into him, contained some¬
thing of Maa Ngala himself."
Synthesis of all that exists, pre-eminent
receptacle of the supreme Force and conflu¬
ence of all existing forces, Maa, Man, re¬
ceived as his legacy a part of the divine
creative power, the gift of Mind and the
Word.
Maa Ngala taught Maa, his interlocutor,
the laws according to which all the elements
of the cosmos were formed and continue to
exist. He installed him as guardian of his
universe and charged him with watching
over the maintenance of universal Har¬
mony. That is why it weighs heavy, being
Maa.
Initiated by his creator, Maa later passed
all that he had learned on to his descen¬
dants; and that was the beginning of the
great chain of initiatory oral transmission of
which the order of Komo (unlike the orders
of Nama, Kore, and so on in Mali) claims to
beacontinuator.
August-September 1979
AMADOU HAMPATE BA, Malian writer, is a
specialist in African history, cosmogony and liter¬
ature. He is the author of many articles and
books, including L'Empire peul du Macina (The
Peul Empire ofMacina), Les Religions africaines
traditionnelles (Traditional African Religions)
and L'Etrange destin de Wangrin (Wangrin's
Strange Destiny), a work which won the Grand
Prix of Black African Literature in 1974.
The non-aligned countries
pool their news
by Pero Ivacic
NEWS exchange, the basis of relations
among news agencies, is more impor¬
tant today than ever before.
In recent years, news exchange has be¬
come accepted practice for most news agen¬
cies in the non-aligned world. January 1977
marked the second anniversary of the cre¬
ation of the system known as the "Pool" a
multichannel flow of news reports and in¬
formation between these agencies.
Current efforts to build a new international
economic order inevitably stimulated initia¬
tives for change in the structure of informa¬
tion, which for decades had been based on a
one-way flow of news from the developed to
the developing countries under the influence
of a small number of news agency giants in
the developed world.
On the basis of recommendations adopted
at the Fourth Summit Conference of Non-
Aligned Countries held in Algiers in 1973,
bilateral exchanges of views took place be¬
tween the news agencies of some ten non-
aligned countries concerning possibilities of
joint action to change the existing situation.
The Pool was officially constituted at the
meeting of information ministers and news
agency directors of sixty-two non-aligned
countries held in New Delhi in July 1976. All
the resolutions of the meeting were endorsed
a month later at the Non-Aligned Summit in
Colombo (Sri Lanka).
The first meeting of the Pool co-ordination
committee, held in Cairo in January 1977,
noted that more than forty news agencies in
Africa, Asia, Latin America and Europe were
already contributing actively to the news flow
of the Pool. Five news agencies were already
functioning as regional or multilateral collec-
Over 40 news agencies in non-aligned
countries of Africa, Asia, Latin America
and Europe have pooled their resources
for the exchange of news reports and in¬
formation. The recommendations which
led to the creation of this news agency
"Pool" were adopted at the Fourth Summit
Conference of Non-Aligned Countries,
held in Algiers in 1973. Below, the Confer¬
ence Centre where this historic step was
taken.
tors and redistributors of news reports and
information from other agencies participating
in the Pool.
The Pool is a tangible example of co-opera¬
tion among equals on a voluntary and demo¬
cratic basis. The manner in which it functions
is the best proof of this. A news agency is
considered as a participant if it transmits its
selection of news reports to one or more of the
Pool's collector-redistributor news agencies.
The process involved is simple. Each parti¬
cipant agency transmits by the means at its
disposal teleprinter, telex, airmail one or
more of its news reports daily to a Pool redis¬
tribution centre.
Each agency selects which reports it will
send to the Pool. A redistributing news agency
translates the reports it receives into the lan¬
guages it usually transmits abroad, scrupu¬
lously respecting the substance of the news
received.
This concrete form of co-operation among
the non-aligned countries is in no way viewed
as a challenge to or competition with existing
news reporting systems. The Pool's function
is to fill the previously existing vacuum in the
international information system.
Interest in the Pool has been shown by
several news agencies outside the non-
aligned world, where the Pool is increasingly
making its presence felt in the mass media.
It is obvious that a new dialogue has begun
in international communication, and that the
process of building a new international in¬
formation system is under way. Difficulties
clearly lie ahead and change will not be rapid,
but the process which has been initiated can¬
not be arrested or reversed.
The best contribution to the quest for the
most widely acceptable solutions will be to
continue the dialogue among all those who
have an interest in the world of information a
dialogue which must take place between
equals.
April 1977
PERO IVACIC, Yugoslav journalist, was, when
he wrote this article, Director-General of the
Yugoslav national news agency Tanjug, which
played an active role in the setting up of the
non-aligned countries' news pool.
£
E
TO
O
©
; » ' ,«i \ 2
53
]]>
</page>
<page number="54">
<![CDATA[
On translation
Text © Reproduction prohibited
by Octavio Paz
EACH text is unique, yet at the same
time it is the translation of another
text. No text is entirely original, be¬
cause language itself is essentially a trans¬
lation. In the first place, it translates from
the non-verbal world. Then, too, each sign,
each sentence, is the translation of another
sign, another sentence. This reasoning may
even be reversed without losing any of its
force and we may assert that all texts are
original because every translation is dif¬
ferent. To a certain extent every translation
is an original invention and thus constitutes
a unique text.
The original text never reappears in the
other language: this would be impossible.
Nevertheless, it is always present because,
although the translation does not explicitly
state as much, it refers to the original text
constantly, or else converts it into a verbal
object that differs from it, yet reproduces it
by metonymy or metaphor. Both of these,
as distinct from explanatory or free trans¬
lations, are strict forms that are not incom¬
patible with exactness. Metonymy is an in¬
direct description; metaphor is a verbal
equation.
Poetry has always been considered the
form- of writing that lends itself least to
translation. This prejudice is surprising
when we stop to think that many of the best
poems in every Western language are trans¬
lations, and that many of these translations
have been made by outstanding poets.
The reason why many poets are unable to
translate poetry is not purely psychological
in nature though the cult of self does enter
into it but functional. Poetic translation is
an operation similar to poetic creation, ex¬
cept that it is executed in reverse.
Meaning tends to be univocal in prose,
whereas one of the characteristics of poetry ,
as has often been noted, and possibly its
chief quality, is that it retains the several
meanings of a word. In reality, this is a
property of language in general. Poetry ac¬
centuates it, but it is also to be found in
everyday speech and even in prose.
The poet, caught up in the whirl of lan¬
guage which is a constant verbal coming
and going selects a few words, or is
selected by them. He fashions his poem by
combining them and it then becomes a ver¬
bal object made up of irreplaceable and
irremovable signs. The translator's starting
point is not language in motion, which is the
poet's raw material, but the fixed language
of the poem. It is a frozen language, and yet
it is quite alive. His operation is the oppo¬
site of the poet's. He is not called upon to
forge an unchangeable text with changing
signs, but to take that text apart, set the
signs in motion again and return them to the
language. Up to this point the translator's
work is similar to that of a reader or critic,
since every reading is a translation, and
every criticism is, or begins by being, an
interpretation.
Reading, however, is a translation within
the same language and criticism is a free
version, or more exactly a transposition, of
the poem. For the critic a poem is the
jumping-off place towards another text, his
own, whereas the translator, using another
language and different signs, must compose
a poem similar to the original.
Thus at the second stage the translator's
activity is comparable to that of the poet,
but with this important difference: when the
poet writes, he does not know what his
poem is going to be like; when the translator
translates, he knows that his poem must
reproduce the poem he has before him.
Translation and creation are twin oper¬
ations. As the cases of Baudelaire and
Pound show, it is often impossible to dis¬
tinguish translation from creation.
Below, detail of Metamorphosis II. 1940, a
work by the well-known Netherlands artist
M.C. Escher. In this masterly feat of
graphic transformation, the artist imper¬
ceptibly changes bees into birds by way of
fish. Above, the same engraving reversed.
Moreover, there is a constant give and take
between them, a continual and mutual cre¬
ative influence. The great ages of poetry in
the West have been preceded or accompa¬
nied by the interweaving of various poetic
traditions. These cross-currents have some¬
times taken the form of imitation and at
other times that of translation.
Critics study "influences", but this term is
equivocal. All styles have been trans-
linguistic.
Styles are collective and pass from one
language to another; written works, rooted
in their verbal soil, are unique. They are
unique but not isolated, for each of them is
born and lives in relation to other works in
different languages.
In every period European poets and
now those of the two Americas as well
write the same poem in their several lan¬
guages, and each of these versions is like¬
wise an original and different poem.
The synchronization may not be perfect,
but if we withdraw a certain distance, we
find that we are listening to a concert in
which the musicians, playing different in¬
struments and without following any
orchestra leader or score, are composing a
collective work in which improvisation is
inseparable from translation, and invention
is closely bound up with imitation. Occa¬
sionally one of the musicians launches into
an inspired solo. The others soon take their
cue from him and then go on to introduce
variations, while the original motif becomes
lost in the new creation .
February 1975
OCTAVIO PAZ, Mexican poet, essayist and
translator, is one of the outstanding writers in the
Spanish language. He has published several
volumes ofpoetry such as Libertad bajo palabra
(Liberty on Parole). English translations of his
essays include Labyrinth of Solitude (1961),
Claude Lévi-Strauss: An Introduction (1972),
and Alternating Current (1973).
]]>
</page>
<page number="55">
<![CDATA[
Painted manuscripts
ofpre-Columbian America
by Miguel Angel Asturias
THE Mexican, Maya and Peruvian In¬
dians discovered and cultivated
different "modes" of transmitting
their culture and ethics. Some of them still
amaze us with their plastic beauty and their
esoteric ingenuity, and in them all we dis¬
cern a fundamental and even obsessive urge
to preserve and transmit through original
forms of writing the profound meaning of
man and the universe.
For this reason writing became some¬
thing sacred and esoteric for the pre-Hispa-
nic peoples. Written signs, writing materials
and those who could handle them were
considered by the people as being con¬
nected with the divine. The writings them¬
selves, in their creation and their appear¬
ance, had a magical character, closely
linked to cosmogonie conceptions.
A page from the Codex Borbonicus
(named from the Palais Bourbon, seat of
the French National Assembly in Paris,
where it is preserved). It depicts children
dancing around a "maypole" decorated
with paper clothes on the occasion of an*
Aztec festival.
That is why the various systems of writing
that evolved among people with such a high
level of technical expertise bore no relation
to practical needs; they were symbols for
the sacred message concealed within.
We know that writing, its preservation
and interpretation, were the responsibility
of a special class of dignitaries with priest¬
like functions sometimes they even were
priests who used language, materials, col¬
ours and contents indissolubly related to the
archetypal situations of the Indian deities.
The pre-Columbian peoples possessed
several systems of writing (ideographic, |
tj , / ""V-r.-.V.Yv'V, -T/
i v. . /Jet, 'i".t .v/
E
o
Q
©
55
]]>
</page>
<page number="56">
<![CDATA[
^ calendric, pictographic, numeral, phonetic)
with which they wrote on deerskins, stones
and strips of amatl paper. In their eyes,
however, the very fact of recording and of
keeping these records was of such vital im¬
portance that their loss or preservation was
identified with the destruction or continuity
cf the universe.
In fact, in order to make sure that the
world will continue to exist and that the loss
of the instruments of transmission does not
bring about the end of their lives and the
destruction of the universe, the ancient
Nahuas meet to reinvent or rediscover the
old knowledge and the old form of preserv¬
ing the past, the life and essence of their
people.
They are not concerned with the form
and various ways of recording the past
hence their infinite variety but with the
act of recording it so that its remembrance
may illuminate and give coherence to a
world filled with gods, conflicts and doubts.
Then they invented the count of the fates,
The annals and the count of the years,
The book of dreams;
They recorded the sequence and course of
events,
The time that passed
Under the lordship of the Toltecas,
The lordship of the Tepanecas,
The lordship of the Mexicas,
And all the lordships of the Chichimecas.
This is one reason not the most improb¬
able for the dearth of Maya texts and the
abundance of Náhuatl writings. The Span¬
ish conquest and the destruction that en¬
sued ... put an end to the various systems of
transmitting Indian culture.
In the final phase of the Mexican tragedy,
the missionaries attack the Indian religion
and way of thought and at this point one of
the Chiefs rises to express "with courtesy
and urbanity" his displeasure at this attack
on the customs and beliefs so dear to his
ancestors. It is not for him to defend them
since there are still some survivors of
Those who turn the rustling leaves of the
codices,
Those who have in their power the black
and red inks and the painting.
They lead us, guide us, show us the way.
They order how a year passes,
How it follows its course,
The account of the days
And each of the twenty-day months,
That is their business,
It is for them to speak of the gods.
There could be no more concise descrip¬
tion of the old Indian conception nor any
better expression of the loneliness, sadness
and helplessness of a bewildered, leaderless
people.
December 1972
MIGUEL ANGEL ASTURIAS (1899-1974), of
Guatemala, was one of the greatest modern
novelists in the Spanish language. In 1967, he
was awarded the Nobel Prize for Literature.
Three of his most important novels have been
translated into English: The President (1963),
The Mulatta and Mister Fly (1970) and The
Green Pope (7977;.
Today's crisis in
THE important place social anthropology
holds in contemporary thinking may
seem paradoxical to many people. It is
a science very much in vogue: witness not
only the fashion for films and books about
travel, but also the interest of the educated
public in books on anthropology.
Today there is no fraction of the human
race, no matter how remote and retarded it
may still appear, which is not directly or in¬
directly in contact with others, and whose
feelings, ambitions, desires and fears do not
affect the security and prosperity and the very
existence of those to whom material progress
may once have given a feeling of ascendancy.
Even if we wanted to, we could no longer
ignore or shrug off with indifference, say, the
last head-hunters of New Guinea, for the sim¬
ple reason that they ate interested in us. And
surprising though it may be, the result of our
contacts with them means that both they and
we are now part of the same world, and it will
not be long before we are all part of the same
civilization.
As they spread throughout the world, the
civilizations which (rightly or wrongly) felt that
they had reached the height of development,
such as Christianity, Islamism, Buddhism,
and on a different level the technological civi¬
lization which is now bringing them together,
are all tinged with "primitive" ways of life,
"primitive" thinking and "primitive" behaviour
which have always been the subject of anthro¬
pological research. Without our realizing it the
"primitive" ways are transforming these civi¬
lizations from within.
For the so-called primitive or archaic peo¬
ples do not simply vanish into a vacuum. They
dissolve and are incorporated with greater or
lesser speed into the civilization surrounding
them. At the same time the latter acquires a
universal character.
Thus, far from diminishing in importance,
primitive peoples concern us more with each
passing day. To take only one example, the
great civilization the West is justly proud of
and which has spread its roots across the
inhabited globe, is everywhere emerging as a
"hybrid". Many foreign elements, both spir¬
itual and material, are being absorbed into its
stream.
As a result, the problems of anthropology
have ceased to be a matter for specialists,
limited to scholars and explorers, they have
become the direct and immediate concern of
every one of us.
Where, then, lies the paradox? In reality
there are two insofar as anthropology is
chiefly concerned with the study of "primitive"
peoples. At the moment when the public has
come to recognize its true value, we may well
ask whether it has not reached the point
where it has nothing more left to study.
For the very transformations which are
spurring a growing theoretical interest in "pri¬
mitives" are in fact bringing about their extinc¬
tion. This is not really a new phenomenon.
Let me cite a few examples. Protected by its
exceptionally hostile environment, New
Guinea, with its several million tribesmen,
may well be the last great sanctuary of primi
tive society on earth. But civilization is making
such rapid inroads that the 600,000 inhabi¬
tants of the central mountains, who were total¬
ly unknown a mere twenty years ago, are now
providing labour contingents for the building
of roads. And it is no rarity today to see road
signs and milestones parachuted into the un¬
explored jungle!
As Western civilization becomes more
complex with each passing day and spreads
across the whole of the earth, it is already
beginning to show signs of the sharp differ-
In a shrinking world, from the tributaries of
the Amazon to the mountain fastnesses of
New Guinea, traditional ways of life are
being transformed.
56
]]>
</page>
<page number="57">
<![CDATA[
anthropology by Claude Lévi-Strauss
enees which anthropology has made it its
business to study but which it could formerly
do only by comparing dissimilar and widely
separated cultures.
Here, no doubt, lies the permanent function
of anthropology. For if there exists, as anthro¬
pologists have always affirmed, a certain "op¬
timum diversity" which they see as a perma¬
nent condition of human development then
we may be sure that divergencies between
societies and groups within societies will dis¬
appear only to spring up again in other forms.
Who knows if the conflict between the old
and new generations, which so many coun¬
tries are now experiencing, may not be the
ransom that must be paid for the growing
homogenization of our social and material
culture? Such phenomena seem to me patho¬
logical but anthropology has always been
characterized by its ability to explain and jus¬
tify forms of human behaviour which men
found strange and could not understand.
In this way anthropology at every phase has
helped to enlarge the currently held and al¬
ways too constricting view of humanity. To
picture the disappearance of anthropology,
one would have to conjure up a civilization
where all men no matter what corner of the
globe they inhabited, and whatever their way
of life, their education, their professional acti¬
vities, their age, beliefs, sympathies and aver¬
sions were, to the very roots of their con¬
sciousness, totally intelligible to all other men.
Whether one deplores it, approves it, or
merely states it as a fact, technical progress
and the development of communications
hardly seem to be leading us to this end. And
as long as the ways of thinking or of acting of
some men perplex other men, there will be
scope for meditation on these differences;
and this, in a constantly renewing form, will be
the abiding province of anthropology.
November 1961
CLAUDE LEVI-STRAUSS, one of the world's
greatest living anthropologists, has been profes¬
sor of social anthropology at the famed College
de France, Paris, since 1959. Between 1935 and
1939, he was professor of sociology at the Uni¬
versity of Sao Paulo, and led many scientific
expeditions in central Brazil. He has written
many authoritative works including A World on
the Wane (Hutchinson, London) also published
by USA Criterion Books, New York, under its
French title, Tristes Tropiques.
Ä<C >**""
]]>
</page>
<page number="58">
<![CDATA[
The building blocks of culture
by Cheikh Anta Diop
A people's cultural identity is related to
three major factors historical, ling¬
uistic and psychological (the last of
which may include the people's specific forms
of religious observance). These factors vary
in importance in different historical and social
situations; when they are not fully present in a
people or an individual, the cultural identity is
flawed.
Can these factors be classed in a hierarchy
of importance, or does each one play an equal
part in the constitution of the cultural
personality?
Awareness of a common history is the most
solid rampart a people can build against cultu¬
ral or any other form of aggression from out¬
side. Thus in contacts between civilizations
during the colonization process, for exam¬
ple the colonizer tries to weaken if not des¬
troy the historical consciousness of the colo¬
nized people.
The exercise of national sovereignty is by
far the best school for a people's mind and
soul, and the only way to keep alive its
greatest virtues.
It is hard to say whether or not the historical
factor is more important than language. For
the French philosopher Montesquieu lan¬
guage was the only common denominator,
the supreme mark of cultural identity. "As long
as a vanquished people has not lost its lan¬
guage," he wrote, "it still has hope."
But nowhere in the world does the phe¬
nomenon of linguistic unity exist on a con¬
tinental scale. Fragmentation and diversity
prevail until an official effort is made or a
Anthropomorphic Head Sections, a work
by the British sculptor Roy Adzak
Photo © Gérard Dufresne, Paris. Xavier Jeupitre Collection
political decision is taken to extend the use of
one language, if necessary by force.
This process, nevertheless, at first only
affects the vocabulary of a language, not its
grammar, i.e. its morphology and syntax.
The civilization with the most advanced
technology usually exercises a one-way influ¬
ence on the civilizations or societies with
which it comes into contact.
Creolization is a linguistic process which
began in a specific historical situation. Iso¬
lated individuals, deprived of their freedom,
were taken from their original environment
and cast brutally into another environment to
which they adapted as best they could. The
illiterate Africans thus deported to the West
Indies deformed the European languages
spoken there, creating new forms of speech in
which specialists have found distant echoes
of the syntactical and morphological struc¬
tures of African languages.
Finally, the psychological factor presup¬
poses a certain permanence within a diversity
of structures. A thorough analysis of this fac¬
tor would call for study of what might be called
cultural invariables.
The cultural environment may be regarded
as an assimilating structure which absorbs
material from outside and evolves while re¬
maining aware of its own identity. Assimilation
enriches it without affecting its destiny. Only
destruction by some external agency, disin¬
tegration (whatever the reason), or hardening
of the arteries because of excessive autarky
can be fatal to it.
Each civilization has two ways or levels of
handling concepts. The first is concerned with
all that is specific, with an area that is, so to
speak, protected by the people's unique
psychological barrier, an area which can only
be understood from within. This is also the
level of poetic expression; it is the core of all
living culture, of all civilization. The second
way or level is concerned with the universal,
with general ideas that everyone can grasp,
with the area in which one civilization can
influence another.
When the core perishes, the life of societies
and civilizations comes to an end. Hence the
widespread efforts today to safeguard this
productive uniqueness which is not isolation
nor withdrawal but the fundamental condition
of universality.
August-September 1982
CHEIKH ANTA DIOP (1923-1986) was a Sene¬
galese anthropologist and physicist who played
a leading role in inspiring the revival of interest in
African history. Professor of Egyptology at the
University of Dakar and director of the Radiocar¬
bon Laboratory at the University's Institut Fon¬
damental d'Afrique Noire (IFAN), he was also
one of the most active members of the Interna¬
tional Scientific Committee for the Drafting of a
General History of Africa, an 8-volume work
sponsored by Unesco and now in course of
publication.
58
]]>
</page>
<page number="59">
<![CDATA[
The writer
between two worlds
Two young pupils in a Mexican school
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
THE Third World intellectual must live
with a terrible fact: over 80 per cent of
people in the Third World can neither
read nor write. No magic wand can be waved
to change their plight; it will be a long, hard
struggle which will call on men and women
with a real determination for change.
Is it not a paradox to write in a continent of
illiterates? "No," says the Mexican writer
Carlos Fuentes, "it is not as paradoxical as it
may seem. Perhaps the writer knows that he
is working to keep alive a relationship with a
past which has rarely found its political
equivalent."
A literature in which many poor and domin¬
ated peoples find a recognizable picture of
themselves has come from a single fissure
etched in the warm and human earth of Latin
America. The waifs and strays of Bogotá are
part of the same wound as the urchins of Cairo
and the shayatin ("little devils") of Casablan¬
ca. A peasant dispossessed of his land has
the same dreams whether he lives in north
Africa or northeast Brazil; the same imagina¬
tion broken by injustice, forbidden to express
itself, thwarted by a tragic fate.
Once he has resisted blandishments and
pressures, the writer born of this reality cannot
accept that a dispossessed peasant should
be left to live what political and military author¬
ities call a reasonable life.
"A continent of illiterates" has a greater
need of writers than a continent sated with
knowledge. Writing here is a refusal to accept
defeat.
And so we have this gamble on liberty and
on the future, for this continent will not always
be afflicted by the inevitability of illiteracy.
Those who come later, perhaps the children of
this period, will be entitled to call us to
account. The writer will have to declare his
books or his silence.
The commitment of the artist implies solv¬
ing his country's problems at the same time as
creating a work of art. This still has a meaning
in countries which are confronted with life-
and-death problems, not intellectual fads. In
this respect the Peruvian writer Mario Vargas
Llosa has noted something which is valid not
only for Latin America but for the Third World
as a whole. "Elsewhere, to be a writer means,
primarily and often exclusively, assuming a
personal responsibility for a body of work
which, if artistically valid, will enrich the culture
of the country in which it is created. In Peru
and in other Latin American countries, to be a
writer means primarily, and often exclusively,
assuming a social responsibility." There is
virtually no escape from assuming that re¬
sponsibility.
If this conception of literary activity relates
to reality by making the writer a repository of
information with his eyes fixed on the outside
world, then it causes a major misunderstand¬
ing. For the main thing is forgotten, namely
how to write, how to create.
Should we then go far in the other direction
and regard literature as a pure stylistic exer¬
cise or a lifeless tour de force?
There is a widespread misunderstanding
about where the writer's commitment lies. To
militate in a political party or organization is
one thing; to write while taking part in politics
as well is another. The one does not exclude
the other. But it is rare that the two combine in
such a way as not to be mutually harmful and
do not create confusion and misunder¬
standings.
As for the writer who deliberately chooses
to live in exile, he leaves far behind him the
prevailing stagnation, the temptation to bitter¬
ness and inactivity. Whatever he does is
bound to be wrong! If exile leads to nothing, he
is wrong. If exile brings him success, he is
wrong. The child who leaves his family con¬
nexions by the wayside is not forgiven.
But to be far away does not necessarily
mean to be absent. To go away is another way
of establishing links with one's land and peo¬
ple. Wherever it is produced, the work of a
writer or an artist returns in one way or another
to the land of its origin.
But when exile becomes a way of thinking
and of becoming ensnared in the toils of an
unhappy conscience, when it severs a man
from his deepest roots, when it becomes an
end in itself and submerges the individual in a
set of problems which ought not really to
concern him, then exile becomes alienation. It
returns to the mother country another person,
often a stranger who has lost the capacity for
wonder: a wreck apparently in good health.
duly 1982
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN, Moroccan writer and
journalist, has divided his time between France
and Morocco since 1971. Among his recent
works is L'écrivain public, published in 1983.
59
]]>
</page>
<page number="60">
<![CDATA[
'The action of a man who
snatches something from death'
by André Malraux
André Malraux, French Minister ofState for CulturalAffairs, was one of the speakers
at a ceremony held at Unesco 's Paris Headquarters on 8 March 1960 to launch the
International Campaign for the Preservation of the Monuments of Nubia. Below,
extracts from André Malraux's address.
ON 8 March 1960, for the first time,
all nations, though many of them
even now are engaged in covert or
open conflict, have been summoned to
save by a united effort the fruits of a civi¬
lization on which none has a pre-emptive
claim.
Such an appeal, in the last century,
would have seemed fanciful. With our own
century, however, has come one of the
greatest developments in man's spiritual
history. These temples which had been
looked on only as records have again be¬
come living witnesses; these statues have
acquired a soul.
The only ancient Egypt which can come
alive for us is the one conveyed by its
art and this is an Egypt that never ex¬
isted at all, any more than the kind of
Christianity which would be inferred from
Romanesque art if that were our only wit¬
ness to it. Yet Egypt has survived in her
art, not through famous names or lists of
victories. ... Despite Kadesh, one of his¬
tory's decisive battles, despite the car¬
touches carved and recarved at the behest
of the bold pharaoh seeking to force his
lineage upon the gods, Sesostris has less
meaning for us than the unfortunate Akhe-
naton. The face of Queen Nefertiti haunts
our painters as Cleopatra has inspired our
poets; but whereas Cleopatra is a queen
without a face, Nefertiti, for us, is a face
without a kingdom.
At their highest expression, Egyptian
conventions were designed to mediate be¬
tween ephemeral men and the controlling
stars. It is an art that consecrates night. ...
In such a way, during three thousand
years, Egyptian art translated the temporal
into the eternal.
Let there be no misapprehension about
this today: it is not as a witness to the
past that it moves us, nor as what used to
be called beauty. "Beauty" has become
one of our age's most potent mysteries,
the inexplicable quality which brings the
Egyptian masterpieces into communion
with the statues of our own cathedrals, or
the Aztec temples, or the Indian and
Chinese grottos; with the paintings of
Cézanne and Van Gogh, with the greatest
dead and the greatest living artists; with, in
short, the whole treasury of the first world
civilization. For the first time, men have
discovered a universal language of art.
The emotion we share with the creators
of these granite statues is not even one of
love, nor a common feeling for death nor
even, perhaps, a similar way of looking at
their work; yet before their work, the ac¬
cents of anonymous sculptors forgotten
during two thousand years seem to us as
much untouched by the succession of
empires as the accents of mother love.
If Unesco is trying to rescue the monu¬
ments of Nubia, it is because these are in
imminent danger. Yours is the first attempt
to deploy, in a rescue operation, on behalf
of statues, the immense resources usually
harnessed for the service of men. And this
is perhaps because for us the survival of
statues has become an expression of life.
At the moment when our civilization di¬
vines a mysterious transcendence in art
and one of the still obscure sources of its
unity, at the moment when we are bringing
into a single, family relationship the mas¬
terpieces of so many civilizations which
knew nothing of or even hated each other,
you are proposing an action which brings
all men together to defy the forces of dis¬
solution. Your appeal is historic, not be¬
cause it proposes to save the temples of
Nubia, but because through it the first
world civilization publicly proclaims the
world's art as its indivisible heritage.
The slow flood of the Nile has reflected
the melancholy caravans of the Bible, the
armies of Cambyses and Alexander, the
knights of Byzantium and Islam, the sol¬
diers of Napoleon. No doubt when the
sandstorm blows across it, its ancient
memory no longer distinguishes the bril¬
liant notes of Rameses' triumph from the
pathetic dust that settles again in the wake
of defeated armies. And when the sand is
scattered again, the Nile is once more
alone with its sculpted mountains, its col¬
ossal effigies whose motionless reflection
has for so long been part of its echo of
eternity.
But see, old river, whose floods allowed
astrologers to fix the most ancient date in
history, men are coming now, from all
parts of the world, who will carry these
giants far away from your life-giving, des¬
tructive waters. Let the night fall, and you
will reflect again the stars under which Isis
accomplished her funeral rites, the star of
Rameses. But the humblest worker come
to rescue the statues of Isis and Rameses
will tell you something you have always
known but never heard from men before:
that there is only one action over which in¬
different stars and unchanging, murmurous
rivers have no sway it is the action of a
man who snatches something from
death.
May 1960
ANDRE MALRAUX (1901-1976), French writer
and politician, was the author of a wealth of
literature covering the fields of art, civilization,
war and autobiography. Among his best-known
works translated into English are La condition
humaine (Man's Fate, 1934), L'espoir (Man's
Hope, 1938), Le musée imaginaire (Museum
without Walls, 1967), and his autobiography,
Antimémoires (Antimemoirs, 7967/ He fought
with the French Resistance during the Second
World War, and was Minister ofState for Cultural
Affairs from 1958 to 1969.
60
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="61">
<![CDATA[
Miniature anthology of works by
Al-Biruni
Selections from works written a thousand years ago
Intelligence and reasoning
Some believe that science is of recent ori¬
gin, others that it is as old as the world. The
former affirm that its techniques were
taught by "initiation" and go so far as to
maintain that every technique was revealed
and implanted by a particular prophet. But
there are others who think that man discov¬
ers techniques with the help of intelligence
and that it is reasoning which enables the
mind to acquire understanding.
When one discovers, by reasoning, a law
or principle, one must proceed from the
general to the particular. At the same time,
experiment and reflection allow us to com¬
pare one thing with another and so obtain
knowledge in detail.
Time is limitless and successive genera¬
tions traverse only stages. Each passes on its
heritage to the next, which develops and
enriches it.
Bibliography of the Works of al-Razi
Smart scholars
Once a sage was asked why scholars always
flock to the doors of the rich, whilst the rich
are not inclined to call at the doors of
scholars. "The scholars," he answered, "are
well aware of the use of money, but the rich
are ignorant of the nobility of science."
India
Why the Earth is round
As concerns the curvature of the Earth in
the directions between longitude and lati¬
tude, it may be ascertained by means of the
longest days in the towns we have men¬
tioned. Let us consider, for instance, the
town of Bulgar, in the far north, and the
town of Aden, lying far to the south of it. In
and around Aden, the length of the longest
day is little more than twelve hours, whilst
in Bulgar it is little less than seventeen
hours. There is a difference of two hours
between the hours of sunrise and sunset in
those two towns. Consequently, at the time
of sunrise over Aden, the Sun has already
risen to a height of two hours' travel in the
sky over Bulgar.
This being the case, we may assert that a
line traced on the Earth in the direction of
latitude, that is to say a meridian, must of
necessity be either straight, or a concave or
convex curve.
The Mas'udic Canon on Astronomy
Astronomer, mathematician, physicist,
geographer, historian, linguist, ethnolo¬
gist, pharmacologist as well as poet,
novelist, philosopher, and humanist,
Abu al-Rayhan Mohammed ibn Ahmad
al-Biruni was born just over a thousand
years ago near Kath in what is today
Soviet Uzbekistan. He was one of the
most outstanding scholars of the Isla¬
mic world and many specialists rank
him even higher than Avicenna (Ibn
Sina). An early proponent of fruitful
cultural and scientific exchange be¬
tween the East and the West, al-Biruni
had a spirit of tolerance and open-
mindedness rare for his time. Above,
portrait of al-Biruni executed by Iranian
artist Azarguin to mark the thousandth
anniversary of the great thinker's birth.
'Speak the truth'
That man only is praiseworthy who shrinks
from a lie and always adheres to the truth,
enjoying credit even among liars, not to
mention others.
It has been said in the Qur'an, "Speak the
truth, even if it were against yourselves"
(Sura 4, 134); and the Messiah expresses
himself in the Gospel to this effect: "Do not
mind the fury of kings in speaking the truth
before them. They only possess your body,
but they have no power over your soul." In
these words the Messiah orders us to exer¬
cise moral courage.
India
On Hindu religions
I have written this book on the doctrines of
the Hindus, never making any unfounded
imputations against those, our religious
antagonists, and at the same time not con¬
sidering it inconsistent with my duties as a
Muslim to quote their own words at full
length when I thought they would contri¬
bute to elucidate a subject. If the contents
of these quotations happen to be utterly
heathenish, and the followers of the truth,
i.e. the Muslims, find them objectionable,
we can only say that such is the belief of the
Hindus, and that they themselves are best
qualified to defend it.
India
Witchcraft and science
We understand by witchcraft, making by
some kind of delusion a thing appear to the
senses as something different from what it is
in reality. Taken in this sense , it is far spread
among people. Understood, however, as
common people understand it, as the pro¬
ducing of something which is impossible, it
is a thing which does not lie within the limits
of reality. For as that which is impossible
cannot be produced, the whole affair is
nothing but a gross deception. Therefore
witchcraft in this sense has nothing what¬
ever to do with science.
One of the species of witchcraft is
alchemy, though it is generally not called by
this name. But if a man takes a bit of cotton
and makes it appear as a piece of gold, what
would you call this but a piece of witchcraft?
India
June 1974
61
]]>
</page>
<page number="62">
<![CDATA[
Lenin
and the physical sciences
by Mstislav Keldysh
ALL of Lenin's work as a politician,
statesman and public figure is in¬
separable from science.
The turn of the century, as we know,
was marked by a series of discoveries
which were to lead to a complete revolu¬
tion in physics, and eventually to the de¬
velopment of the physics of today. Thus,
the advances in electrodynamics opened
the way to the theory of relativity and
the discovery of new and more precise
space-time relationships. Research into
the theory of opaque bodies and the
photo-electric effect made possible the
formation of the quantum theory.
These new ideas and theories, to
which were soon to be added the discov¬
ery of radioactivity and radium, could no
longer be fitted into the nineteenth -
Lenin, photographed in Paris in 1910.
century concept of physics or into the
electromagnetic concept of the universe
that had succeeded the mechanical con¬
cept.
Serious difficulties arose. In particular,
the conclusion of the classic electron
theory, according to which electrons had
mass and electromagnetic characteristics,
was interpreted by many mechanistic and
positivist physicists of the time as a verit¬
able "disappearance of matter". Re
search scientists spoke heatedly of "the
big crisis in physics".
In 1909, Lenin entered the scene with
his work Materialism and Empirio-Criti-
cism. This was his reply to the philo¬
sophical problems raised by the latest
scientific discoveries. Lenin pointed out
that the crisis in physics perceptible at
the beginning of the century was just the
first step challenging "the old laws and
basic principles", and that the change
affected the postulates of physics that
had been thought unalterable. The crisis,
Lenin said, marked the beginning of a
complete revolution in physics.
"To say that matter has disappeared,"
Lenin wrote, "is merely to state that the
limits of our knowledge of matter have
disappeared and that our understanding
has deepened. The properties of matter
that formerly appeared absolute, unalter¬
able and immutable ... have disappeared
and are now recognized as being relative
and inherent only in certain states of
matter."
He stressed that "the one and only
property of matter that philosophical
materialism recognized is that it is an
objective reality, existing apart from our
consciousness". Here he pronounced his
famous philosophical dictum: "the elec¬
tron is as inexhaustible as the atom; na¬
ture is infinite ..."
The discovery that electrons were cap¬
able of behaving as waves opened up a
fantastic new world to physicists. In the
1930s the positron was identified. The
electron revealed a new property: united
with a positron, it was transformed into
a photon. There followed the discovery
that the electron is an active protagonist
in the phenomenon known as weak in¬
teractions and so is also a bearer of a
specific charge of these interactions.
Thus Lenin's thesis has shown itself to
be a great deal more than a mere
prophecy. It has become a philosophical
postulate of the investigation of the in¬
finitely small. All the later developments
of physics have corroborated the validity
of this principle, confirming the "inex¬
haustibility" of the electron, and, more
generally, the inexhaustible physical
properties of matter itself.
June 1970
MSTISLAV KELDYSH was President of the
Academy of Sciences of the USSR in 1970.
Portrait
62
]]>
</page>
<page number="63">
<![CDATA[
Rabindranath Tagore with a group of
students in the school he founded at
Santiniketan in 1901.
Photo © Rabindra-Sadana, Vlsva Bharati
of a man
by Satyajit Ray
WITH a wordly wisdom unusual in a
poet but characteristic of the
Tagores, Rabindranath set out in
a practical way to improve the lot of the
poor peasants of his estates. But his own
gain from this intimate contact with the
fundamental aspects of life and nature, and
the influence of this contact on his own life
and work, are beyond measure.
Living mostly in his boat and watching
life through the window, a whole new world
of sights and sounds and feelings opened up
before him. It was a world in which the
moods of people and the moods of nature
were inextricably interwoven. The people
found room in a succession of great short
stories, and nature, in an outpouring of
exquisite songs and poems. Dominant was
the mood of the rains, exultant and terrible.
Rabindranath Tagore received the Nobel
Prize in 1913, and a knighthood in 1915,
while war was raging in Europe. Touring
the United States and Japan in 1916, the
poet made eloquent appeals for peace. He
felt that world peace could be achieved only
through intellectual co-operation between
nations. He said, "The call has come to
every individual in the present age to pre¬
pare himself for the dawn of a new era,
when man shall discover his soul in the
spiritual unity of all human beings."
While peace had been restored in
Europe, in India there was unrest. The
occasion was the Rowlatt Bill, designed to
suppress all political movements. It dashed
India's hopes of gaining the self-govern¬
ment that the British rulers had kept prom¬
ising through the war years.
Dominating the Indian political scene at
this time was Gandhi. As a protest against
the Rowlatt Bill, Gandhi launched a move¬
ment of passive resistance. But the masses
misinterpreted the movement and, follow¬
ing a rumour of Gandhi's arrest, violence
broke out in many parts of the country.
In the Punjab, martial law was declared.
In charge of the troops at Amritsar was
Brigadier General Dyer. On the first day of
the month of Vaisakh, a crowd gathered in
Jallianwallabagh, as it had done every other
year. It was a peaceful crowd . But Dyer was
taking no chances. Machine guns rattled.
Rabindranath wrote to the Viceroy, Lord
Chelmsford, and the letter was published in
the newspapers. Condemning the Govern¬
ment for the killing at Jallianwallabagh, he
concluded: "And I for my part wish to
stand, shorn of all special distinctions, by
the side of my countrymen who for their
so-called insignificance are liable to suffer
degradation not fit for human beings. And
these are the reasons which have painfully
compelled me to ask your Excellency to
relieve me of my title of knighthood."
The next ten years of Rabindranath's life
were filled with ceaseless activity. The ne¬
cessity to collect funds for his university
took him to all parts of the world, and the
West as much as the East welcomed him
with open arms.
Wherever he went, he spread the mes¬
sage of peace and stressed the importance
of intellectual co-operation between
nations. He said: "We ought to know that
isolation of life and culture is not a thing of
which any nation can be proud. In the hu¬
man world, giving is exchanging, it is not
one-sided."
On 7 May 1941 , Rabindranath was eighty
years old. For the occasion, he had com¬
posed a message his last message to the
world which concerned itself with the
state of so-called modern civilization, a civi¬
lization that was being shaken to its very
roots by barbaric wars of aggression:
"I had at one time believed that the
springs of civilization could issue out of the
heart of Europe. But today, when I am
about to leave the world, that faith has
deserted me. I look around and see the
crumbling ruins of a proud civilization
strewn like a vast heap of futility. And yet, I
shall not commit the previous sin of losing
faith in man. I shall await for the day when
the holocaust will end and the air will be
rendered clean with the spirit of service and
sacrifice. Perhaps that dawn will come from
this horizon, from the East, where the sun
rises. On that day will unvanquished man
retrench his path of conquest, surmounting
all barriers, to win back his lost human
heritage."
December 1961
To commemorate the centenary of the birth of Rabin¬
dranath Tagore, the Indian Government asked one of
the country's leading film directors, Satyajit Ray, to
produce a documentary film on the poet. In December
1961 the Unesco Courier reproduced the text of Ray's
commentary, from which these extracts are taken.
63
]]>
</page>
<page number="64">
<![CDATA[
An eye of the angel in The Virgin of the
Rocks, executed by Leonardo in Milan
about 1483 (Louvre Museum, Paris)
An eye of Mona Lisa. Leonardo began work on the painting
about 1501 and finished it more than fouryears later (Louvre
Museum, Paris)
Leonardo da Vinci, or
by Carlo Pedreta
L
IMBS which are not in exercise
must be drawn without showing
the play of muscles. And if you
do otherwise, you will have imitated a
sack of nuts rather than a human
figure."
This is one of the notes on painting found
in the second of the recently discovered
Madrid Manuscripts of Leonardo da Vinci,
dating from the first years of the sixteenth
century.
All the elements of Leonardo's paint¬
ing are present in the theories expressed
in this manuscript. Another series of
notes, in addition to those on form and
colour, deals with light and shadow and
the smooth transition from light to sha¬
dow, which is the true essence of the
famous Leonardo sfumato.
When in the first period of his activity
Leonardo was dealing with the problem
of light and shadow he conceived of ob¬
jects in terms of geometrical entities and
was mainly concerned with the study of
the gradations and degrees of intensity
of the shadows.
After 1500 his main concern becomes
the study of light and shadow on objects
placed in the open air, thus taking into
account colour and reflections. Light be¬
comes the vehicle that blends the ele¬
ments of landscape into a harmony of
transitions from colour to colour, and
this Leonardo calls "grace".
The human figure, too, becomes part
of the landscape (one thinks of the
Mona Lisa, The Virgin and St. Anne,
Leda) and thus participates in the phe¬
nomena of reflection, refraction and in¬
terplay of coloured shadows, as is the
case with every other object placed
under the light of the sky. What can be
seen under the projection of a roof is
also to be seen under the chin of a hu¬
man face.
One of Leonardo's most beautiful
observations pertains to the way a hu¬
man face should be represented. He
advises the painter to arrange the setting
so as to achieve the most delicate sfuma¬
to effects in the shadows, what he calls
"the gracefulness of shadows, smoothly
deprived of every sharp contour".
The setting is provided by the walls of
the houses flanking the street, through
which the light penetrates light made of
air without brightness, a golden, diffuse
light such as that of Giorgione.
Now, says Leonardo, "light ends upon
the pavement of the street and rebounds
with reflected motion at the shadowy
parts of the faces, brightening them con¬
siderably. And the length of the
aforementioned light of the sky created
by the boundaries of the roofs hanging
over the street illuminates almost as far
as the beginning of the shadows which
are underneath the projections of the
face, and so it is gradually changed into
The smile of the angel in The Virgin of the Rocks The smile of Mona Lisa
]]>
</page>
<page number="65">
<![CDATA[
An eye of St. John the Baptist, painted by Leonardo about
1509 (Louvre Museum, Paris)
An eye of the lady In the portrait known as the Belle
Ferronnière (Louvre Museum, Paris)
he glory of painting
brightness, until it ends under the chin
with imperceptible shadows all over."
Most interesting is the "unpredictable
Leonardo", the Leonardo who cannot be
anticipated, because the notes he writes
are nothing but the record of the move¬
ments of his mind, so that his precepts
to the painter do not have the stiffness
of academic teaching but the freshness of
a revelation, evocative of the space that
opens up in the background of his paint¬
ings:
"What I would remind you of, con¬
cerning faces, is that you should consider
how, at varying distances, different qual¬
ities of the shadows are lost and that
only the main spots are left, that is, the
pits of the eye and the like: and finally
the face remains dark, because the
lights, which are small compared with
the medium shadows, are absorbed by
darkness. For this reason, at a distance,
the qualities and quantities of the main
lights and shadows are consumed, and
everything blends into a medium sha¬
dow. And this is why trees and all ob¬
jects appear darker at a distance than if
the same objects were near the eye.
From this obscurity on, the air which is
between the eye and the object causes
the object to become brighter and to
turn towards blue. But it turns bluish
rather in the shadows than in the lumi¬
nous parts, where one can see better the
true quality of the colours."
October 1974
CARLO PEDRETTI is the author of many
books on Leonardo. This article is inspired by
a chapter on the "Notes on Painting in the
Madrid Manuscripts", published in his book
Leonardo da Vinci Inédito (Leonardo da Vin¬
ci's unpublished works), published in Italian
by Barbera Editore, Florence, 1968.
In the manuscript known as Codex Madrid
II, Leonardo states that the human face
and body are defined by the light sur¬
rounding them. He notes that reflectedand
refracted light as well as coloured sha¬
dows are all what he calls "the truth of
colours". This may explain the affinity be¬
tween the many faces hepainted which the
photographic enlargements on this dou¬
ble page clearly reveal, especially Leonar¬
do's rendering of the eyes and the smile.
The enlargements show how skilfully
Leonardo played with light and shadow in
order to achieve his enigmatic smile and
beautifully expressive eyes (thousands of
pages have been written about Mona
Lisa's smile). In Codex Madrid II, Leonardo
advises the painter to strive for a subtle
blend of shadows which he describes as
"the gracefulness of shadows, smoothly
deprived of every sharp contour". By so
doing he has given us his secret ofhow he
achieved such delicately nuanced forms
in his models.
The smile of St. John the Baptist The smile of the Belle Ferronnière Photos Louvre Museum, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="66">
<![CDATA[
Year of peace: 5
Takashi Nagai, professor at the
Nagasaki Faculty of Medicine,
died in 1951 at the age of 43 from
the effects of the atom bomb ex¬
plosion which destroyed his town
in 1945. His eyewitness account
is extracted from a book pub¬
lished in the Federal Republic of
Germany in 1961. Entitled Die
Stimme des Menschen (The Voice
of Mankind) by Hans Walter Bahr
(R. Piper and Co. publishers,
Munich), it is an anthology of let¬
ters from all parts of the world
written between 1939 and 1945 by
men and women who lost their
lives as a result of the Second
World War.
by Takashi Nagai
Letter from Nagasaki
Text © Reproduction prohibited
DIRECTLY after the bomb exploded, the
reaction of those who could still move
was either to remain where they had
been at the time of the explosion or to flee
immediately. Those who stayed where they
were either to help injured friends or to try to
save their apartment, office or factory were
quickly hemmed in by the flames and
perished along with those they had wanted to
save. When the fire came closer, we took
refuge on the hill near our hospital. In this way
my neighbours and I escaped death by a
hair's-breadth.
Here and there we came across medical
students and nurses lying on the ground. We
picked them up and carried them a little further
up the hill, out of reach of the fire. All the time I
was urging those around me to move faster.
I had a gash on the right temple and was
losing a lot of blood. Eventually I collapsed.
When I came to, I found that I was lying in the
grass beneath the billowing eddies of the
atomic cloud. I was suffering terribly from my
wound and had to grit my teeth to overcome
the pain. Then I began to think about my wife.
If she were still alive, I told myself, she would
have already joined me.
Next day, looking down from the hill behind
the clinic, I could see the ruins of my house.
Nothing remained of Urakami but a great pile
of white ashes. Nothing moved, wherever one
looked, in the clear morning light.
I had seen my beloved faculty and all the
students to whom I was so attached engulfed
in a flash by the flames. My wife was now
nothing but a little heap of charred bones
which I collected one by one in the ruins of our
house. Her remains weighed no heavier than
a parcel you might send through the post. She
had died in the kitchen.
As for me, "atomic sickness" in its most
acute form now added its effects to those of
the long-standing illness caused by my re¬
search into X-rays. This, along with the injury
to my right side, completely disabled me. By
an extraordinary piece of luck, three days
earlier our two children had been sent to their
grandmother in the mountains and were thus
safe and sound.
Never before had I found my work as a
scientist such a painful burden. Leaning on a
stick, my body covered with wounds which
hampered my movements, I began with great
effort to climb mountains and cross rivers in
order to visit my patients. I kept this up for two
months. Then I was struck down by a violent
attack of atomic sickness and had to give up
my medical work altogether.
Those of us who suffered the bombing had
no idea at all of what an atomic bomb could
be. I myself never thought for a moment that
the bomb meant anything so cataclysmic,
even though I was right underneath the
mushroom cloud. I thought it was just a super¬
bomb, or something similar. It was only when
the cloud began to spread out and disperse
and the sunlight (which it had completely blot¬
ted out) began to filter through again until it
was bright enough for me to see something,
that I looked around and said to myself: "It's
the end of the world."
The rest of the world cried out in horror:
"The atomic bomb must never be used
again."
And yet I hear that some people do not think
the bomb is as terrible as all that, or that it
must never be used in any circumstances: "A
city is never entirely destroyed...," they say.
"There are always some survivors. ... Radio¬
activity disappears in time. ... It's only a new
weapon, more effective than any used before.
..." More effective! ... What do they know
about it, the people who talk like this?
November 1975
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs. 2 years (valid only in France):
1 44 French francs. Binder for a year's issues: 56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed ar¬
ticles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo capitions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produ¬
ced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University Microfilms (Xe¬
rox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (30 N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-ln-chlef: Olga Rodel
Managing Edltor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English:
Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille: Frederick Potter
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-
Chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian:
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras I Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic(Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
66
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) Dépôt légal : C 1 - Mai - Juin 1986
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de IUNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION ; MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A.. Z.I. route dEtampes. 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="67">
<![CDATA[
Four Unesco
international quarterlies
resources
F Prospect!
Prospects
A quarterly review of education which
benefits from the direct collaboration of
institutions and academics from more than
150 countries. Intended not only for
specialists, it considers education in all its
socio-economic and cultural contexts.
Annual subscription 86 French francs
Single issue 27 FF
Nature and resources
Provides international news and informa¬
tion about Unesco programmes concerning
environmental activities, natural resources
research and conservation. Issues soon to
be published include such topics as: water
resources and energy; environmental
geology; land development in the tropics.
Annual subscription 48 FF
Single issue 15 FF
Museum
The sole international journal that presents
museological evolution and its multiple
facets around the world, from security to
cultural policies and curating.
Annual subscription 138 FF
Single issue 43 FF
Copyright bulletin
A quarterly to meet the needs not only of
specialists in the field, but authors, librar¬
ians, publishers, editors, record producers,
broadcasters, film makers, scientific re¬
searchers and lawyers.
Annual subscription 48 FF
Single issue 15 FF
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collmgwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications : Educational Supplies Pty Ltd , P.O. Box 33. Brookvale 2100.
NSW; Periodicals : Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33. Brookvale
2100. NSW. Sub-agent : United Nations Association of Australia. P.O. Box
175, 5th lloor. Ana House. 28 Elizabeth St , Melbourne, Victoria 3000. AU¬
STRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31. A-1 011, Vienna BAHA¬
MAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd.. P.O. Box N-3138. Nassau. BAHRAIN. The
Arabian Agencies and Distributing Co.. AI Mutanabi St.. P.O. Box 156,
Manama. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd.. Ittefaq Build¬
ing. 1. R K. Mission Rd.. Hatkhola. Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the
West Indies Bookshop. Cave Hill Campus. P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Couner" Dutch edition only: N,V. Handelmaatschappq
Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18. 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen French edition and
general Unesco publications agent : Jean de Lannoy. 202 Ave du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91. Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552 Merchant
Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
St. West, Montreal. Quo. H3H 1M7. CHINA. China National Publications
Import and Export Corporation. P O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O Box 1 722, Nicosia CZECHOSLOVA¬
KIA. SNT.L, Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B.
790-111-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Souke-
nicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only : Arfa Verlag -Publishers, Hurtanovo nam
. 6,893 31 Brat islava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tidssknft-
service, 35 None Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUB¬
LIC OF). National Centre lor Unesco Publications, No. 1 Taiaat Harb St..
Cairo ETHIOPIA. National Agency (or Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10;
Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64 FRAN¬
CE. Ubraine de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. CCP 1 2598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBUC. Buchhaus Leipzig. Postfach 1 40, 71 0
Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the GOR. FED, REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Couner (German. English. French and Spanish
edrbons) : Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basartstrasse 57.
D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Presbylenan Bookshop Depot Ltd.. P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana. Accra. The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The
University Bookshop of Logon, P O. Box 1, Logon. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat St., Abderdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock
Rd., Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Sen/ices. Publication Centre,
Baskerville House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kuftura- Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B
149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson and Co.. H F.
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Onent Longman Ltd.. Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate. Bombay 400038: 17 Chrtaranjan Ave , Calcutta 13; 36a. Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2, 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP), 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd.. Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-
500001. Sub-depots : Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St.. Calcutta
70016; Sandia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit. Ministry ot Education and
Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Rd New Delhi, 110001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardmata
111, Jakarta; Indira P.T.. Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37. Jakarta Pusat, (RAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 28 Vessal Shirazi St . Enghelab
Ave., P.O. Box 314/1486. Teheran; Iranian Nat Comm. for Unesco. 1188
Englab Ave.. Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P O Box 11365-4498.
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzies Bookshop, AI Rasbid St . Baghdad. IRELAND.
The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Rd . Walkinstown,
Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd.. P.O Box 1283. 71 Allenby Rd , Tel
Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librena Commissionaria Sansoni, S p A ). Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence JAMAICA. Sangster's
Bookstores Ltd.. P O. Box 366. 101 Water Lane, Kingston; University of the
West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P O. Box 30571, Nairobi, Afnca Book Services Ltd , Quran House.
Mlangano St.. P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi KOREA. Korean National Commis¬
sion lor Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop
Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwart. for the Unesco Courier : Farafalla Press Agency,
P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O.
Mazenod. Lesotho. Southern Africa. UBFRIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd , P.O. Box 286. Monrovia. LIECHTENSTEIN. Eurocan Trust Reg P.O B.
5-9494 Schaan. UBYAN ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. Agency tor Development of
Publication and Distnbution, P O. Box 34-35, Tnpoli. LUXEMBOURG. Líb¬
rame Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxembourg MALAWI. Malawi Book
Service. Head Office. P.O. Box 30044 Chichin. Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Co-operatrve Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur 22- 1 1 . MALTA.
Sapienzas. 26 Republic St , Valletta MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd , 30
Bourbon St . Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd des Moulins. Monte
Cario. NEPAL Sajha Prakashan Poichowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS.
Keesing Boeken B V. Joan Muyskenweg. 22, Postbus 1118. 1000 BC Am¬
sterdam. NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O Box 200,
Willemstad. Curacao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government PubJisino, P.O Box
14277-Kilbirnie Wellington. 1 30. Oxford Terrace, P O Box 1721 Chnstchurch;
Alma St.. P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Pnnces St.. P O. Box 1104. Dunedm.
NIGERIA. The Unrversity Bookshop of Ife: The University Bookshop of
Ibadan, P.O. 286. The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The Universrty Book¬
shop of Lagos: The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop ol Zana. NORWAY.
Johan Grundt Tanum. P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum - Oslo 1 . Narvesen A/S. Subscnp-
bon and Trade Book Service. POB. 6125 Etterstad. Oslo 6; Universrtets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret. Postboks 307 Blindem. Oslo 3 PAKIS¬
TAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam. P O Box No. 729,
Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book Development
in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P O Box 8950, Karachi 29.
PHILIPPINES. National Book Store, Inc. 701. Rizal Ave., Manila D-404
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury 1 Nauki, Warsaw: Ars Polona-Ruch.
Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda Lrvrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon
F007SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box 48. Mahé; New Sarvice
Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131. Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay,
Njala Unrversrty and Siena Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SING¬
APORE. Fedeml Publications (S) Pts Ltd. Tim*» Jurong, 2 Jurong Port
Rd.. Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modem Book¬
shop and General. P.O. Box 951. Mogadiscio SOUTH AFRICA. For the
Unesco Couner (single copies) only : Central News Agency. P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. F007SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chrttampa-
lam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2 SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1 1 1 8, Khartoum, SWEDEN. All publications A/B C E. Frrtzes Kungel,
Hovtookhandel. Regenngsgatan 1 2. Box 1 6356. 1 0327 Stockholm 1 6. For the
Unesco Couner : Svenska FN Fôrbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65
StockhcHm; Wennergren-Williams, Box 30O04-S-104, 25 Stockholm, Esselte
TidsknttscentraJen. Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20 Stockholm. SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications : Europa Verlag. 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairie
Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11. CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also
in Lausanne. Basle, Berne. Vevey, Montreux, Neuchatei and Zurich. TANZA-
NUL Dar-es- Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es- Salaam. THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O.
Box 402. Bangkok: Suksapan Panrt, Mansion 9. Rajdamnem Ave.. Bangkok;
Suksrt Siam Company. 1715 Rama IV Road. Bangkok. TRINIDAD ANO
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Tnnidad W 1 . TURKEY. Hasel Kitapevi A.S.. Istiklal Caddesi. No 469. Posta
Kutusu 219. Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 7145.
Kampala. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O.. P.O. Box
278, London SWS 5DT. and Govt. Bookshops in London. Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bnstol; for scientific maps only : McCarta Ltd., 122
King's Cross Rd London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd St.. New York, N.Y. 10O17. Orders for books and periodicals : P.O. Box
1 222. Ann Artxx, Ml 461 06. USSR. V/O Mezhduna/odnaya Krwga, Ul Dimrtro-
va39, Moskva 113095. YEMEN. 1 4th October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227.
Aden. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Ilea 30/11, Zagreb; Cankaneva ZaJozba,
Zoprtaneva 2. Lub^ana; Nott. Terazije 27/11. Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Dtstnbuton Co of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka ZIMBAB¬
WE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Ave.. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="68">
<![CDATA[
Jorge Enrique Adoum - Al-Biruni - Jorge
Amado - Samir Amin - Miguel Angel
Asturias - Ba Jin - Tahar Ben Jelloun -
P.M.S. Blackett - Vietor Bunak - Daniel
Bovet - John Boyd Orr - Anthony Burgess
Alejo Carpentier - Radhika
Coomaraswamy - Antoine Dakouré - Basil
Davidson - Ding Ling - Cheikh Anta Diop
- Jean-Marie Domenach - Marguerite
Duras - Gilberto Freyre - Dan George -
Nilüfer Göle - Amadou Hampâté Bâ -
Bernardo Alberto Houssay - Julian Huxley
- Pero Ivacic - Alfred Kastler - Mstislav
Keldysh - Otto Klineberg - Cámara Laye -
J.M.G. Le Clézio - Aleksei Leonov
Claude Lévi-Strauss - Lu Xun - Marshall
McLuhan - André Malraux - Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow - Albert Memmi - Yehudi
Menuhin - Alfred Métraux - Joan Miró -
Alberto Moravia - Charles Morazé
Takashi Nagai - Lewis NKosi Tordis
Orjasaeter - José Ortega y Gasset - Linus
Pauline - Oetavio Paz - Carlo Pedretti -
Satyajit Ray - Augusto Roa Bastos - Abdus
Salam - Nikolai Semenov - Haroun Tazieff
- Paul -Emile Vietor - Albert Wendt
]]>
</page>
</document>
