<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069653eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
JULY 1986 B French Irancs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live . . .
45 Mexico
To the rescue
Earthquakes are a grim fact of life for the
people of Mexico. Mexico City, one of the
world's largest and oldest capital cities, is
situated on the southern Mexican plateau in
an area of volcanic activity and faulting of
the Earth's crust related to the shaping of
the continental areas to the north and south.
In September 1985, Mexico City was shaken
by a powerful earthquake which caused se¬
vere damage in the heart of the metropolis.
In an unprecedented effort of international
solidarity, rescue teams from many coun¬
tries came to Mexico City to help in the w ork
of rescuing and caring for the many victims.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
A window open on the world
Editorial
SEEN against the immensity of the Universe, the Earth
we live on is a tiny speck of rock and metal. The third
planet of the Solar System, counting outward from the
Sun round which it orbits at a speed of 29.8 kilometres per
second , the Earth is located between Venus and Mars , at just
the right distance from the Sun (149,573,000 kilometres) to
avoid being baked in perpetual heat or frozen in unending
cold.
In this issue of the Unesco Courier our purpose is to offer
our readers a simple description of the genesis of our planet
and of the major geological mechanisms that regulate its
restless churning. For though we call the land surface we live
on "terra firma", the great continental plates are in constant
motion. Sometimes these plates collide, buckling at the
point of impact into mighty mountain ranges; at times they
are shaken by violent, shuddering earthquakes; at times the
internal furnaces spew out molten rock in awesome volcanic
eruptions. And all the while new crust is forming on the
ocean floor and old crust is being sucked down to be recycled
in the banked fires of the mantle.
In terms of geological time, man is a newcomer to this
planet. If we imagine the 3,900 million years since the
Earth's crust solidified as one calendar year, then Homo
sapiens only appeared on the scene on 31 December at about
_^¿ eight and a half minutes to midnight (100,000 years ago).
' In the very last half second of our condensed time scale,
man has himself become a major geological force capable of
deteriorating or even destroying the environment in which
he lives. The damage that human beings inflict upon the
environment is mainly due to ignorance. We still do not
know enough, for example, about the long-term effects of
the widespread use of chemical fertilizers and pesticides,
how to prevent the spread of man-induced desertification, or
how best to handle our newest energy source nuclear
power.
With its major international science programmes Unesco
is in the forefront of the battle to keep our planet habitable.
Although there may well be other Earths in the vast ex¬
panses of the Universe, if they exist they are well beyond our
reach. We must look after planet Earth; we have nowhere
else to go.
N. B. We suggest that this issue be read in conjunction with two other recent issues of the
Unesco Courier: "The Story of the Universe" (September 1984), and "The New World
of the Ocean" (February 1986).
' Several of the photographs and diagrams in this issue of the Unesco Courier are
reproduced by courtesy of the Geological Museum, London, to whom we express our
grateful thanks.
Cover: Océane Pyrénées, 1985, acrylic on canvas (116 x 73 cm), by
Georges Servat. Galerie jean-pierre lavignes, Paris.
Editor-in-chief : Edouard Glissant
July 1986
39th year
4 The genesis of the Earth
by John Gribbin
6 Vital statistics
8 Inside the Earth
9 Our place in the Solar System
10 Wandering continents
12 Rocks around the clock
The concept of geological time
12 Shaping the land
15 A trilogy of rocks
16 Drilling into the unknown
by Yevgeni Kozlovski
23 The restless Earth
The uncertain art of earthquake prediction
by E.M. Foumier d'Albe
27 Volcanoes
by Haroun Tazieff
32 The evolution of life
33 Life from Space
Does life on Earth have its origins in comets?
by Chandra Wickramasinghe
35 The hand of man
by Stephen Boyden and Malcolm Hadley
38 1986: Year of Peace/ 7
2 A time to live...
MEXICO: To the rescue
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 7 - 1986 - CPD - 86 - 1 - 435 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The genesis
IN the beginning there was nothing at
all. Space, time and the matter of the
Universe we live in were created
together in a superdense fireball, some
15,000 million years ago, a fireball which
we call the "Big Bang". As the Universe
expanded and cooled, matter became
spread more thinly until huge clouds of
hydrogen gas began to clump together,
breaking up and collapsing inwards to
form stars and galaxies. By about 10,000
million years ago, galaxies like our own
Milky Way system, each containing up to
a few thousand million stars, were estab¬
lished as the basic units of the Universe.
Within each galaxy stars are born, live
and die, wheeling their long orbits
around the galaxy's centre, while the
galaxies themselves are carried ever
farther apart as the Universe continues to
expand.
Our Sun and Solar System are typical
products of the galactic environment, but
our Sun was not one of the first stars to
shine in the cosmic night. Those earliest
stars contained only hydrogen and a little
helium; all the other elements have been
created by nuclear reactions inside stars
and scattered through space when those
first stars exploded. So when our Sun
formed, only a little over 4,500 million
years ago, it formed out of a cloud of
hydrogen gas well laced with other mate¬
rials such as iron, carbon, oxygen and
nitrogen materials that settled out of
the collapsing gas cloud to form the
planets.
The planets of the Solar System differ
from one another chiefly because of their
distances from the Sun. Those closest to
the forming young Sun were subjected to
the greatest heat, and this drove off into
space many light materials. This is why
Mercury, Venus, Earth and Mars are
small, rocky objects. Far out from the
Sun's furnace, however, even light gases
such as methane and ammonia could be
trapped and held by a forming planet. So
the giant planets, Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus
and Neptune, probably contain the same
amount of rocky material as the Earth,
but this is buried deep beneath the vast
layers of their gaseous atmospheres.
They need not concern us here, but it is
interesting and informative to make some
comparisons between our own home in
space, Planet Earth, and our nearest
neighbours, Venus and Mars.
The small cloud of material that col¬
lapsed to form our planet, within the
greater cloud that was collapsing to form
the Solar System, was probably made up
chiefly of silicon compounds, iron oxides
and magnesium oxides, with just a small
trace of all the other elements, including
those that are so important to life.
As the Earth formed, it grew hot. First,
gravitational energy was turned to heat as
particles rained down and smashed into
the proto-planet. In addition, radioactive
elements inside the core of the growing
planet contributed their share of warmth
as they decayed into stable elements a
process which continues at a slower rate
today.
The young, iron-rich planet must have
been largely molten in the first tens or
hundreds of millions of years after it
formed, and as a result molten globules of
iron forced their way downwards to the
core of the Earth through the lighter,
rocky material, which was left to float on
top and provide a solid skin as the crust
cooled. The material of the crust on
which we live is not typical of the material
that makes up the bulk of the Earth and
the material of the atmosphere that we
breathe is even less representative of the
whole planet.
The crust of the Earth contains 6 per
cent iron, but the planet as a whole con¬
tains 35 per cent; silicon, which makes up
only 15 per cent of the mass of the planet,
forms 28 per cent of the crust, combined
with oxygen to make silicate rocks. The
lightest rocks, chiefly granite, make up
the bulk of the continents, but the ocean
floor consists of basalt, which is rather
heavier.
From the surface to the centre, the
Earth is layered like an onion, with the
lightest material on the outside and the
most dense material at the core. And this
process of segregation was more or less
completed by 3,900 million years ago,
just 600 million years after the planet
formed. Geophysicists know this because
they have been able to date the oldest
rocks of the Earth's crust, using measure¬
ments of their residual radioactivity; and
they know about the layered structure of
the planet from studies of earthquake
waves, which are bent and distorted by
the different layers.
However, no more than the broad out¬
lines of the picture of the Earth's interior
can be determined in this way. The
pioneering geophysicist Sir Edward Bul-
lard once told me that "determining the
structure of the Earth by studying earth¬
quakes is like a blind man trying to deter¬
mine the structure of a grand piano solely
by listening to the sound it makes when
pushed down a flight of stairs". And it is ''^,.
true that scientists know more about the '^
composition of distant stars than about
the Earth deep below our feet after all,
we can actually see the stars!
But we do at least have the broad out¬
lines of a picture of the Earth's interior.
Starting from the surface, we live on a
rocky ball with an average radius of 6,372
kilometres, slightly flattened at the poles.
The outer skin, or the crust, represents
only 0.6 per cent of the volume of the
planet. Below the crust, which varies in
thickness from 5 to 35 kilometres, there is
a sharp boundary called the Mohorovicic
Discontinuity, or Moho.
This marks the top of the mantle, a
layer which goes down to a depth of 2,900
kilometres and takes up 82 per cent of the
volume of the Earth. Near the top, the
mantle is partly molten, with a consisten¬
cy like thick porridge, or slushy, melting
ice. This region of weakness, called the
asthenosphere, is of great importance be¬
cause the crust above can move over it,
leaving the continents free to wander
around the globe (see page 10). On a
broader scale, the mantle seems to be
made up of three zones , the upper mantle
being about 370 kilometres thick and
separated by a transition zone about 600
kilometres thick from the lower mantle,
which is itself 1,900 kilometres in thick-
ness.
Evolution of the Earth from a cloud ofgas
and dust to a rocky planet
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
of the Earth by John Gribbin
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ Below the mantle lies the core an
outer core 2,100 kilometres thick and the
inner core itself, with a radius of just
1,370 kilometres, at the centre of the
Earth. The outer core is the region of
liquid iron, where the Earth's magnetic
field is generated.
Venus and Mars are rocky planets like
the Earth and formed in much the same
way. But our planet is covered by oceans
of water, whereas Mars is a cold, dry
planet with a thin atmosphere and Venus
has a superdense atmosphere covering a
baking hot surface. These differences
seem to be a direct result of the differ¬
ences in the distance of the planets from
the Sun.
All three planets, astronomers and
geophysicists now believe, had no atmos¬
phere immediately after they cooled.
Any gases that were present as they
formed were driven off by the heat of the
Sun. Simple physics tells us the tempera¬
ture of the surface of each of the three
rocky balls, at their different distances
from the Sun, once the Sun had settled
down to a steady brightness. For Venus,
the stable temperature, where incoming
heat from the Sun is exactly balanced by
outgoing radiation, is 87 degrees Centi¬
grade, and for Mars the figure is -30
degrees Centigrade. These figures, re¬
member, are for airless planets. ^
Vital statistics
Source: National Geographic Society, Washington, D.C
THE EARTH
Weight: 5,973,502,000,000,000,000,000 tonnes
Circumference at the Equator: 40,075 km
Area: 510,074,600 km2
Land: 148,940,540 km2
Water: 391,134,060 km2
THE CONTINENTS
Area JL Highest point V7 Lowest point
v (metres)
Population
(km2) (metres)
Asia 43,998,920 1 Everest
8,848
1 Dead Sea
-396
2,048,898,000
Africa 29,800,540 2 Kibo
(Kilimanjaro)
5,895
2 Lake Assal
-156
344,000,000
North 24,320,100 3 McKinley 3 Death 314,970,000
America 6,194 Valley
-86
South 17,599,050 4 Aconcagua 4 Valdés 186,013,000
America 6,960 Peninsula
-40
Europe 9,699,550 5 El'bruz
5,642
5 Caspian Sea
-28
637,943,000
Australia 7,687,120 6 Kosciusko
2,228
6 Lake Eyre
-16
12,200,000
Antarctica 14,245,000 7 Vinson
Massif
5,139
Not known
MAJOR WATERFALLS
Height
(metres)
1 Angel 979
2 Tugela 948
3 Yosemite 739
4 Cuquenán 610
5 Sutherland 580
6 Mardalsfossen 517
7 Ribbon 491
8 King George VI 488
9 Gavarnie 422
10 Victoria 108
1 1 Iguazú 72
12 Niagara 59
LONGEST RIVERS
Length
(kilometres)
1 Nile 6,669
2 Amazon 6,436
3 Mississippi-Missouri 5,969
4 Ob'lrtysh 5,567
5 Yangtze 5,471
6 Huang 4,827
7 Congo 4,373
8 Amur 4,344
9 Lena 4,312
10 Mackenzie-Peace 4,240
1 1 Mekong 4,183
12 Niger 4,183
13 Paraná 4,023
14 Murray-Darling 3,717
15 Volga 3,685
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A highest points
^7 lowest points
^¡¡f Earth's extremes
^ deepest points
A major seas
O largest lakes
| | longest rivers
major waterfalls
A
LARGEST LAKES O THE OCEANS
Area Greatest depth Area tar Deepest Point
(metres)(km2) (metres) (km2)
1 Caspian Sea 371,795 995 Pacific 166,242,517 1 Mariana Trench 1 1 ,033
2 Superior 82,362 406 Atlantic 86,557,800 2 Puerto Rico Trench 8,648
3 Victoria 69,485 81 Indian 73,427,795 3 Java Trench 7,725
4 Aral Sea 65,527 68 Arctic 13,223,763 4 Eurasia Basin 5,450
5 Huron 59,570 229
6 Michigan 58,016 282
7 Tanganyika 32,893 1,417
8 Great Bear 31,792 413
9 Baikal 30,510 1,620
10 Nyasa 29,604 678
MAJOR SEAS #
Area
(km2)
Average depth
(metres)
EARTH'S EXTREMES ft
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10
11
12
13
South China Sea
Caribbean Sea
Mediterranean Sea
Bering Sea
Gulf of Mexico
Sea of Okhotsk
Sea of Japan
Hudson Bay
Andaman Sea
Black Sea
Red Sea
North Sea
Baltic Sea
2,974,615
2,515,926
2,509,969
2,261 ,070
1,507,639
1,392,125
1,012,949
730,121
564,879
507,899
452,991
427,091
382,025
1,464
2,575
1,501
1,491
1,615
973
1,667
93
1,118
1,191
538
308
55
1. Rainiest spot: Mount Waialeale, Hawaii: average annual rainfall: 11,680 mm.
2. Driest spot: Atacama Desert, Chile: rainfall barely measurable. (At Calama,
no rain has ever been recorded.)
3. Coldest spot: Vostok, Antarctica: -88°C (recorded in August 1960).
4. Hottest spot: AI'Aziziyah, Libya: 56°C (recorded in September 1922).
5. Northernmost town: Ny Alesund, Spitsbergen, Norway.
6. Southernmost town: Puerto Williams, Chile.
7. Highest town: Aucanquilcha, Chile: 5,334 m
8. Lowest town: Villages along the Dead Sea: -396 m
9. Largest gorge: Grand Canyon, Colorado River, Arizona: 349 km long,
6 to 21 km wide, 1.6 km deep.
10. Deepest gorge: Hells Canyon, Snake River, Idaho: 2,408 m deep.
11. Strongest surface wind: 372 km/h (recorded in 1934).
12. Greatest tides: Bay of Fundy, Nova Scotia: 16 m
13. Biggest meteor crater: New Quebec, Canada: 3 km wide.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
1. crust granite (continents)
basalt (oceans)
2. mantle peridotite (and denser forms)
3. outer core iron (liquid)
4. Inner core iron (solid)
Inside the Earth
The Earth's interior has a layered struc¬
ture. The outermost layer is the crust;
beneath this is the mantle; and in the
centre is the core. Temperatures and
pressures inside the Earth are very
high at the core the temperature is
thought to be about 3,500 degrees Cen¬
tigrade and the pressure nearly 3,750
tonnes per square centimetre.
The Crust: In relation to the Earth as a whole,
the crust is as thin as a postage stamp stuck
on a football. It consists of a thin skin of rock
which is less dense than the underlying man¬
tle from which it has been derived by complex
processes over many millions of years. There
are two kinds of crust: continental crust,
which makes up the continents, and oceanic
crust, which forms the ocean floors. Con¬
tinental crust is lighter In weight and much
thicker than oceanic crust. It is also very
much olderparts of the continental crust
are over 3,500 million years old, whereas
oceanic crust is nowhere more than 200 mil¬
lion years old.
The Mohoroviclc Discontinuity: The sharp
boundary that marks the junction between
the crust and the mantle.
The Asthenosphere:Th\s Is a hotter, weaker,
partly molten section of the top of the upper
mantle with a consistency like thick porridge.
It Is of great Importance because it enables
the rigid plates of the crust above to move
about.
The Upper Mantle: scientists believe that the
upper mantle consists of dense, dark-col¬
oured rocks, probably peridotite and perhaps
also dunite and ecloglte, composed of Iron
and magnesium-rich silicate minerals. Frag¬
ments of these rocks are found In volcanoes
fed by magma (molten rock) that originates In
the mantle.
The Transition Zone: In this region, where the
upper mantle grades into the lower mantle,
higher pressures force the minerals to
change their structure.
The Lower Mantle: The minerals composing
the lower mantle are probably simple oxides
with very compact structures produced by
high pressures.
The Core: Almost twice as dense as the man¬
tle, the core is probably composed of Iron
with some dissolved sulphur and silicon. The
Earth's magnetic field is generated In the
outer core, which Is molten. The Inner core is
thought to be solid.
On each planet an atmosphere began
to form when carbon dioxide and water
vapour were produced by volcanic activ¬
ity (it may seem surprising, but one of the
main things that emerges from the fiery
furnace of a volcano is water vapour).
Although 87 degrees Centigrade is still
below the boiling point of water, the
temperature on Venus was already high
enough for a great deal of water vapour
from volcanic outgassing to stay in the
atmosphere with carbon dioxide.
Both water vapour and carbon dioxide
are very efficient at trapping infra-red
radiation the process is called the
"greenhouse effect". So less heat could
escape from the planet into space and as a
result its temperature quickly rose above
the boiling point of water, and then still
higher as still more water vapour joined
the atmosphere. From then on, all pro¬
duction of volcanic gases thickened the
atmosphere and strengthened this green¬
house effect. On Mars the opposite hap¬
pened. Water may have flowed briefly on
the planet, but it soon froze. Venus is a
hot desert; Mars is a cold desert. But
Earth is different.
On our planet the temperature was
high enough for liquid water to flow, but
not so high that water vapour could cause
a runaway greenhouse effect. Quite the
reverse the warm waters of the young
oceans dissolved carbon dioxide out of
the air, leaving a much thinner atmos¬
phere than on Venus, while white clouds
in the sky reflected away some of the
incoming solar heat and let the planet
cool. It is no coincidence, astronomers
believe, that the mass of all the carbon
dioxide in the atmosphere of Venus today
is roughly the same as the mass of carbon
dioxide locked up in carbonate rocks,
such as limestone, laid down from the
oceans around the Earth.
If our Sun had been a little warmer,
Earth too might have been a superhot
desert with a thick, carbon dioxide
atmosphere but if that were so, then
Mars would be warm enough for water to
flow and life to flourish. Or suppose the
Sun were a little cooler; our Earth might
have ended up like Mars but Venus
could have become a pleasant planet of
oceans and cloudy blue skies. If you are
not fussy about exactly which planet you
settle on, the implication seems to be that
an Earth-like planet is an almost inevit¬
able counterpart of every Sun-like star.
In the case of our Solar System, it just
happens to have been the third planet out
from the Sun that was, by about 3,500
million years ago, already in possession
of oceans of water, continents, a carbon
dioxide atmosphere and a comfortable
temperature. The scene was set for the
emergence of life, and for life itself to
begin to change the environment of the
planet but that is another story.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
What of the future? Our Sun has ex¬
isted in a more or less steady state for
4,000 million years, keeping hot as it
burns hydrogen fuel into helium in its
interior. Eventually the supply of hyd¬
rogen will be exhausted. When it is, the
inner part of the Sun will collapse slightly
and become still hotter as helium is fused
by nuclear reactions into carbon. This
greater internal heat will cause the outer
layers of the Sun to expand and it will
become a red giant star, engulfing the
inner planets and burning them to cin¬
ders. But there is no need to panic. Our
Sun is only halfway through its life-cycle,
scarcely into middle-age, and "eventual¬
ly", in this case, means not for another
4,000 million years or more. The fate of
mankind lies in its own hands, not in the
stars.
JOHN GRIBBIN, British astrophys,cist and sci¬
ence writer, former member of the Science Poli¬
cy Research Unit of the University of Sussex,
England, is physics consultant to the magazine
New Scientist. He has written many books on
astronomy, geophysics and climatic change, as
well as two novels, and in 1974 he received the
United Kingdom's premier science-writing
award. His books on astrophysics include White
Holes (1977), Timewarps (1979), Genesis: The
Origins of Man and the Universe (1981), and
Spacewarps (1983).
Our place in the Solar System
Sun
A nuclear furnace that converts hydrogen
into helium, releasing an enormous amount
of energy. Central star of the Solar System,
making up 99 per cent of its mass. Mean
surface temperature: 5,500 degrees Centi¬
grade. Core temperature: 17 million degrees
Centigrade. Diameter: 1.39 million
kilometres. Distance from Earth: 150 million
kilometres.
Mercury
Dense, probably partly metallic. May have a
thin atmosphere. Average midday temper¬
ature: 350 degrees Centigrade. Diameter:
4,840 kilometres. Distance from Sun: 57.9
million kilometres.
Venus
Similar in composition to Earth. Shrouded in
a dense atmosphere of carbon dioxide. Sur¬
face temperature: 300 degrees Centigrade.
Diameter: 12,104 kilometres. Distance from
Sun: 108.2 million kilometres.
Earth
Silicate layers surround dense metallic core.
Water, and an atmosphere of nitrogen and
oxygen, support life. Surface temperature:
Between 60 degrees Centigrade and -90
degrees Centigrade. Diameter: 12,756
kilometres. Distance from Sun: 150 million
kilometres.
Mars
Surface has Moon-like craters but also such
Earth-like features as canyons and volca¬
noes. Atmosphere is carbon dioxide with a
little nitrogen and water. No evidence of life.
Surface temperature: (?) 20 degrees Centig¬
rade at Equator. Diameter: 6,760 kilometres.
Distance from Sun: 227.9 million kilometres.
Asteroids
Small bodies revolving in paths between
Mars and Jupiter. Mostly less than one
kilometre across. Mean distance from Sun:
414.4 million kilometres.
Jupiter
Giant frozen planet enveloped in a thick
atmosphere of hydrogen and helium. Strong
energy source. Diameter: 142,700 kilometres.
Distance from Sun: 778.3 million kilometres.
Saturn
Least dense of planets. Mainly hydrogen and
helium. Orbited by ice-covered fragments
(rings). Diameter: 120,800 kilometres. Dis¬
tance from Sun: 1,427 million kilometres.
Uranus
Probably ice with some solid ammonia, hyd¬
rogen and helium. Owes its green appear¬
ance to a methane-rich atmosphere. Di¬
ameter: 47,600 kilometres. Distance from
Sun: 2,869 million kilometres.
Neptune
Probably frozen methane, water and ammo¬
nia. Diameter: 44,400 kilometres. Distance
from Sun: 4,498 million kilometres.
Pluto
Most distant planet yet discovered. Composi¬
tion unknown. Diameter: (?) 3,000 kilometres.
Distance from Sun: 5,900 million kilometres.
The Moon
Its composition shows small but significant
differences from that of Earth. Analysis of
Moon rocks reveals a far greater proportion
of titanium, chromium and zirconium than is
found in the Earth's crust, suggesting that
the Moon formed separately probably by an
agglomeration of pre-existing solid particles.
The surface is marked by countless craters
formed by falling meteorites. Bright areas
(uplands) represent primeval crust. Dark
areas are basins formed 3,600 million years
ago by impact and flooded by lava eruptions.
Meteorites
Stony and metallic debris, seared by heat,
that falls to the Earth from outer space. They
are probably fragments of colliding aster¬
oids. They range in composition from Iron-
magnesium silicate rock to nickel-iron. They
have a maximum age about the same as that
of the Earth.
A speck in space
The Earth and the Solar System are ex¬
tremely small in relation to distances in
space. These are measured in light-
years one light-year is the distance light
travels in one year about 10 million mil¬
lion kilometres.
The nearest of the 100,000 million stars in
our Galaxy is four light-years away, and
the Galaxy itself is 80,000 light-years
across. Yet it is only one of millions of
galaxies in the Universe.
The Solar System consists of the Sun and
the material revolving around it planets,
moons, asteroids, comets, meteorites,
dust and gas. Most of this material circles
the Sun in the same direction and in the
same plane.
o
©
Sun Mercury Venus Earth Mars Asteroids Jupiter Saturn Uranus Neptune Pluto
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Wandering
ANYONE who has looked at a world map must have noticed
how snugly the coastlines of Africa and the Americas
could be made to fit together, if the intervening ocean were
removed. Modern geophysics has established that all of the
Earth's landmasses were indeed joined together in one super-
continent, Pangaea, hundreds of millions of years ago, and that
this supercontinent was broken apart, with the land masses
drifting to their present positions on the globe.
This idea took many years to become established. Specula¬
tions about the fit of the continents go back to Francis Bacon
(1561-1626), but the acknowledged "father" of the idea of con¬
tinental drift was the German astronomer and meteorologist
Alfred Wegener, who published the first comprehensive state¬
ment of the theory in 1 91 2. Wegener thought that the continents
might move through the thinner crust of the ocean floor, like
icebergs ploughing through the sea, and he gathered a wealth of
evidence showing how well the continents could be fitted
together like some global jigsaw puzzle. But the idea of conti¬
nents moving through the rocks of the sea floor did not seem
feasible, and found little favour until the 1 950s, when the develop¬
ment of new geological techniques provided conclusive evidence
that the continents do move.
The key evidence came from magnetic studies of the ocean
floors. These showed that the crust of the Atlantic Ocean floor is
arranged symmetrically on either side of a great ridge of volcanic
activity which runs roughly down the centre of the ocean bed. The
interpretation of this discovery is that new oceanic crust is being
created at the mid-ocean ridge, where it wells up through a crack
in the Earth's crust and is pushing out on either side, steadily
widening the Atlantic.
Maps © Oxford University Press, Oxford
200 million years ago Present
135 million years ago In 50 million years' time
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
continents
Ocean spreading ridge. Plates are separating; molten rock rises,
adding new material to each plate.
In other parts of the world the reverse happens. The North
Pacific, for example, has no oceanic ridge, but there is a deep
trench running down the west of the ocean floor, next to the
Eurasian landmass. There the thin crust of the ocean floor is
being pushed under the continent, back down into the mantle
where It melts and is ultimately recycled. The net effect is that
there is no change in the surface area of the Earthspreading in
the Atlantic and at other sites is balanced by contraction of the
Pacific. A piece of the Earth's crust that is bounded by spreading
ridges and subduction zones is called a "plate", which gives the
concept of continental drift its modern name, "plate tectonics". In
some places, two pieces of crusttwo platesrub side by side,
with no net creation or destruction of sea floor. This happens
today along the notorious San Andreas fault in California.
The whole process of break-up and re-arrangement of the
continents may have happened several times in the Earth's his¬
tory, and is responsible for building mountain ranges, where
continents collide. India, moving northward into Eurasia, has
forced up the Himalayas, which are still growing. By contrast, the
line of the Red Sea marks a new (by geological standards) crack in
the Earth's crust, a spreading ridge which is splitting Africa off
from Arabia, and which may eventually cause this narrow sea to
expand into an ocean as large as the Atlantic is today.
Overwhelming evidence for the reality of continental drift, or
plate tectonics, was collected during the 1 960s and 1 970s. But the
"icing on the cake" has been provided only in the past few years.
Using laser beams bounced off artificial satellites in orbit around
the Earth, it is now possible to measure directly the steady
widening of the Atlantic, calculated at a couple of centimetres
every year.
Ocean subduction zone. One plate underthrusts another. The
edge of one plate is pushed down into the mantle where it melts
and is recycled. Some of the molten rock rises to form an island
arc.
Collision zone. An underthrusting plate rams two continents
together, forming a high mountain belt.
J
é
Transform fault. Two plates slide past one another with no addi¬
tion or destruction of plate material.
Illustration © The Sunday Times with the Geological Museum, London
Eurasian Plate
continental crust
volcanoes
earthquake zone
subduction zone
. uncertain plate boundary
, movement of plate
	" spreading ridge offset by transform faults
	 collision zone
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Rocks around the clock
The concept of geological time
GEOLOGY is the science which
deals with the condition and the
structure of the Earth and the evi¬
dence afforded of ancient forms of life. It
includes the description of landforms, but it
is much more concerned with the processes
and forces responsible for the landscape we
see today.
These processes generally operate ex¬
tremely slowly. Huge periods of time are
involved in the crumpling of the Earth's
crust into mountain ranges, in the wearing
down of other mountains into plains, in the
advance and retreat of sheet ice and in the
relentless movement of vast sections of the
crust itself.
The concept of the enormity of geological
time is a relatively recent one in Western
thought. In AD 1656, James Ussher,
Archbishop of Armagh in Northern Ire¬
land, after careful study of the genealogies
recorded in the Bible, calculated that the
Creation occurred at 8 pm on the 22nd of
October of the year 4004 BC, an estimate
which was widely accepted even as late as
the eighteenth century.
In 1785, however, the Scottish naturalist
James Hutton published his Theory of the
Earth in which he suggested that the natural
processes such as mountain building and
erosion were so slow that the Earth must
have been in existence for many millions of
years. His views were generally discounted
until the early 1830s, when another Scots¬
man, the geologist Charles Lyell, gave them
his backing in his famous three-volume
work The Principles of Geology, which laid
the foundations for evolutionary biology as
well as for an understanding of the develop¬
ment of the Earth.
With the emergence of geology as a sci¬
ence in its own right, people at last became
aware of the huge length of time nature
took to achieve the changes they recognized
as having occurred.
The Earth is a rocky planet and its his¬
tory, virtually from its origin up to the
present, can be elucidated from the study of
rocks exposed on its surface or attainable by
drilling.
Rocks can be grouped into three major
categories: igneous rocks, formed from the
molten material that rises from the Earth's
interior; metamorphic rocks, that have
been transformed and crystallized by heat
and pressure; and sedimentary rocks, which
have a layered structure and are formed
from fragments worn away from existing
rocks and deposited elsewhere as sediment
(see page 15).
Ancient igneous and metamorphic rocks
provide clues as to the origin and early
history of the Earth's crust; younger de¬
formed and igneous rock formations help us
to understand how mountain chains were
formed; and sedimentary rocks, deposited
in layers or strata over millions of years,
provide the major evidence on which the
standard geological time-scale is based.
Sedimentary rocks contain fossils, the re¬
mains of once-living organisms. Because
living things are continuously changing
4-71III ted
The land surface is shaped by erosion
and deformation. Erosion by water,
wind and ice wears away the rocks of
the continental crust. Deformation
occurs where the crust is unstable,
rocks fracture, shear, crush, fold or flow
plastically.
Erosion Deformation
U-shaped valleys like this one
in Alaska are formed by the
gouging action of a glacier mov¬
ing down a river valley. The
moving ice and the rocks it car¬
ries abrade and carve out the
valley's steep sides.
Canyons are formed when uplift of the
land increases the speed and cutting
power of a river flowing through a plain.
The most spectacular example is the
Grand Canyon of the Colorado River, in
places over 1.5 km deep (see colour
page 20).
Rift valleys, often called
Graben (the German for
"trenches"), are the results
of blocks of land sinking be¬
tween parallel faults. The
East African Rift Valley, the
world's largest, is nearly
5,000 kilometres long.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
through evolution, fossils found in
sedimentary rock provide the principal
means of establishing the relative age of
rocks found in different geographical areas.
In combination, therefore, stratigraphy
(the study of the sequences of rock strata)
and palaeontology (the study of fossils in
relation to the evolution of the Earth's
crust) might be described as the study of
"history in layers".
With the development of radiometry in
the 1950s, it became possible for scientists
to supplement the relative age dating
obtained from the fossil record with abso¬
lute age data (that is to say, age in years).
The age in years of some types of rock can
be calculated from the amounts of radio¬
active elements and their decay products in
the minerals of which the rock is composed.
Radioactive isotopes of uranium, potas¬
sium and rubidium decay at known rates
into stable isotopes of lead, argon and
strontium respectively. The decay products
begin to accumulate in a mineral after it has
crystallized and cooled, thus, as it were,
setting a "radioactive clock" running.
Just as "clock" time is divided into hours,
minutes and seconds, so geological time
(see table page 14) is divided into Eras,
Periods or Systems, and Epochs or Series.
The first era, known as the Precambrian,
covers the span of time from the formation
of the Earth's crust, about 4,600 million
years ago, until the time, about 570 million
years ago, when, for the first time in the
history of the Earth, evidence of varied
forms of life preserved as fossil remains
becomes plentiful. The Precambrian era,
which some geologists also divide into two
sub-divisions, the Archaeozoic and the Pro-
terozoic, thus comprises nearly 90 per cent
of geological time.
Three eras span the period from the end
of Precambrian time to the present the
Palaeozoic ("ancient life") era, from 570
million to 225 million years ago, the Meso-
zoic ("middle life") era, from 225 million to
65 million years ago, and the Cenozoic
"modern life") era, from 65 million years
ago to the present. Broadly speaking, in¬
vertebrates and relatively simple verte¬
brates, such as fish, amphibians and primi¬
tive reptiles were in the ascendant during
the Palaeozoic era, the Mesozoic era saw
the rise to domination of the larger reptiles,
such as the dinosaur, and the Cenozoic, the
contemporary era, is the time of the domi¬
nance of mammals.
The eras are divided into smaller units
called periods or systems. Most of them are
named after geographical regions where
rocks containing fossils characteristic of
their segments of geological time have been
found. Thus the Cambrian period is so
called after the ancient name for Wales and
the Permian period is named after the
ancient Russian kingdom of Permia.
Some periods are named, not after their
geographical location, but after the physical
characteristics of their rocks. Thus the
name of the Cretaceous period is derived
from the Latin word for chalk, creta, while
the Triassic period is so named because, in
Germany, rocks of this period are divided
into three distinct layers consisting of red
sandstones, limestone and shales.
In some cases, both types of nomencla¬
ture are used for the same period by geolog¬
ists in different parts of the world. Thus,
two periods which North Americans call the
Pennsylvanian period and the Mississippian
period (geographical names) are grouped
together in Europe as the Carboniferous
period (from the coal-bearing nature of its
strata).
Periods are divided into epochs or series,
which are in turn sub-divided into ages or
stages, and at this point wide divergences
appear in the nomenclature used by geolog¬
ists in different parts of the world.
This is basically because the relationship
between geological time and sequences of
rock strata has usually been modelled on
national or regional traditional thinking,
and standards, terminology and classifica¬
tion differ from country to country. Neither
the names nor the dates shown, even on a
simplified table of geological time such as
that published on page 14, will be accepted
by all geologists.
The solution of many basic geological
problems would, therefore, be greatly
facilitated if, through the adoption of com¬
mon standards and terminology, data from
different areas could be made intelligible to
geologists the world over. Achieving this
aim is one of the major aims of the Interna¬
tional Geological Correlation Programme, a
co-operative undertaking by the Interna¬
tional Union of Geological Sciences and
Unesco (see page 14).
Of particular importance are projects
aimed at progressively refining geological
time-scales. Geologists need accurate time-
determination methods not only as a basis
for research on the evolution of the Earth's
crust, but also for identifying and assessing
energy and mineral resources.
An understanding of the natural pro¬
cesses which have led to the accumulation
of mineral deposits or fossil fuels depends
on the geologist's ability to understand the
sequence of stages responsible for the
formation of deposits and to make accurate
correlations between sequences concerned
with the formation of similar deposits in
widely separated areas. To paraphrase the
old saying: "Geological time is money".
Drawing © The Sunday Times, Geological Museum, London
Detachment, or décollement, is a common mechanism
of folding in many lesser foothill ranges like the Jura
(above). It occurs in flat sedimentary layers alongside
rising fold-mountains, in this case, the Alps. As the
young fold-mountains rise, they push the sedimentary
layers sideways until they are detached from the under¬
lying rocks and are rucked up like a carpet on a slippery
floor. The "polish" or lubrication is a soft layer of rock
salt or clay underlying the sedimentary layers.
Overfolds form in fold-mountains when rucked-up rock
layers topple over. In Scotland, erosion has exposed the
underside of such a fold, a wide belt from Aberdeen to
Antrim that is upside down.
Nappes are masses of rock that have
been driven over younger rocks for long
distances until they cover them like a
cloth. The Matterhorn (above right) was
carved by glaciers out of a nappe of
pre-Alpine granite driven over Switzer¬
land from the south.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Geological time scale
Era Period / System Epoch / Series Duration
millions of years
CENOZOIC
Quaternary Holocene 0.01
Pleistocene 2.5
Tertiary Pliocene 4.5
Miocene 19
Oligocène
Eocene
12
16
Palaeocene 11
MESOZOIC
Cretaceous
Names based on
geographical
location and
vary widely
71
Jurassic 54
Triassic 35
PALAEOZOIC
Permian 55
Carboniferous
Pennsylvanian
Mississippian
45
20
Devonian 50
Silurian 35
Ordovician 70
Cambrian 70
Proterozoic
or
Algonkian
PRFHAMRRIAN Not divided into periods 4030
Archaeozoic
or
Archaean
A geologist's hammer has been adopted as the "trademark"
of the International Geological Correlation Programme
(IGCP), a major scientific venture, jointly undertaken by
Unesco and the International Union of Geological Sciences
(IUGS), devoted to the study of the earth's crust and its
mineral and energy resources. The Programme involves
some 4,000 geologists In more than 110 countries, working on
about fifty research projects. It combines the advantages of
non-governmental participation and guidance through Its sci¬
entific partner, the IUGS, with the benefits of governmental
support through Unesco. Projects undertaken by the IGCP
range from study of geochronology to prospecting for eco¬
nomic mineral deposits and processing of geological data.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A trilogy
of rocks
Igneous rocks
Igneous rocks form from molten material
(magma) that rises from the Earth's in¬
terior. Magma that solidifies before
reaching the surface forms intrusive rocks
like dolerite, gabbro and granite. Magma
that solidifies after reaching the surface
forms volcanic rocks like basalt (the most
common), obsidian and pumice. As it
cools and crystallizes, the magma's com¬
position changes, producing hundreds of
different types of igneous rock from re¬
latively few types of mineral. Rapid cool¬
ing may trap minerals formed at higher
temperatures.
Metamorphic rocks
"4 Metamorphic rocks are rocks that have
been transformed (metamorphosed) and
crystallized by heat and pressure. In this
process, the minerals of the original rock
either reform into larger crystals or react
together to form new minerals. The rocks
produced have a layered texture called
foliation, familiar to us in slate. Meta-
morphism occurs in two types of
situation: (i) around plumes of molten rock
that have risen in cool rock ("contact meta-
morphism"); and (ii) in the interiors of fold-
mountains where the heat flow is high, and
beneath ocean trenches where there are
high pressures ("regional metamor-
phism"). Metamorphic rocks include slate,
produced from clays at low temperatures
and pressures; schist and gneiss, formed
at higher temperatures and pressures;
and marble, formed from sandstone.
Sedimentary rocks
^ Sedimentary rocks have a layered struc¬
ture. They contain all the world's oil and
coal and all its fossils. The first step in their
formation is the weathering of existing
rock. The products are carried away as
fragments or in solution and deposited
elsewhere as layers of sediment. These
layers, subjected to pressure or cemented
together by other minerals, harden into
sedimentary rock. There are three main
types: (i) Fragmental. Made of pebbles
(breccia, conglomerates), sand (grits,
sandstones, siltstones), or mud (clays,
mudstones, shales), (ii) Organic. Consist¬
ing mainly of the fossil remains of plants
and animals (coal, fossil-bearing lime¬
stones), (iii) Chemically formed by pre¬
cipitation from salt water or hot springs
(rock salt, gypsum, ironstone, some lime¬
stones and siliceous cherts).
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Drilling
into the unknown
by Yevgeni Kozlovski
1
THE structure of the Earth reflects the
long history of its evolution. By re¬
constructing this history scientists
hope to find the key to such processes as the
formation of the Earth's crust, volcanism,
and the upheavals, subsidences and foldings
which led to the development, on the
Earth's surface and in its sub-stratum, of
conditions which favoured the formation,
accumulation and preservation of useful
minerals.
In the Soviet Union, study of the complex
physical and physico-chemical processes
which take place within the Earth's hard
crust and the upper layers of the mantle is
undertaken within the framework of a vast,
integrated programme for the exploration
of the "basement" of the country using
geological, geophysical and geochemical
methods as well as deep and very deep
drilling.
The particularity of this programme is
that it focuses on the study of the Earth's
crust within the limits of the continental
zone where most of the planet's useful
minerals are concentrated. Geophysical ex¬
plorations are being conducted along the
system of profiles traversing the entire terri¬
tory of the USSR, and deep and very deep
drilling is being undertaken at their points
of intersection.
In this way it has been possible to explore
the Mohorovicic Discontinuity (the bound¬
ary between the Earth's crust and the man¬
tle) and to obtain new data on the structure
and physical properties of the upper man-
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
tie, to identify zones where important frac¬
tures occur in the Earth's crust and deter¬
mine their extent, and to pinpoint the
boundaries and structure in depth of major
tectonic elements which may be the site of
concentrations of mineral ores, oil or gas.
At the heart of the programme is the
exploration of the deep structure of the
continental crust, on whose layers is im¬
printed, as on the pages of a book, the
whole story of its formation. The first drill¬
ing was made in the Kola Peninsula, on the
fringe of the Baltic Shield, which is com¬
posed of ancient crystalline rock dating
back to Precambrian time. The Kola drill¬
ing has thrown some new light on the evolu¬
tion and structure of the early continental
crust of the Earth as a whole, since similar
formations are widely distributed in other
parts of the globe in India, North Amer¬
ica, South Africa, Western Australia,
Antarctica and Greenland. Very deep drill¬
ing explorations being carried out in the
USA, Canada and the Federal Republic of
Germany are also contributing to our know¬
ledge of the deep horizons of the Earth in
areas potentially rich in mineral raw
materials.
The direct observations made possible by
these drillings have provided the founda¬
tions of the first factually-based model of
the continental crust and have led to a
The Kola Peninsula in the far north of
the USSR Is the site of the first very
deep drilling made as part of an ambi¬
tious programme aimed at exploring the
deep structure of the continental crust
and seeking areas potentially rich in
mineral, oil or gas deposits. Left, the
drilling rig and the accompanying build¬
ings and workshops which house the
industrial and technical services. The
drilling rig is clad with corrugated iron
sheeting to maintain a constant positive
temperature in this bleak Arctic environ¬
ment.
Right, the new sophisticated and fully
automated URALMACH 15000 drilling
plant, which incorporates the very latest
technology, is capable of drilling down
to a depth of 15 kilometres. The derrick
is 86 metres high and has a hoisting
capacity of 400 tons.
revision of earlier notions about the evolu¬
tion and structure of the Earth's depths.
The Kola drillings have resulted in a
series of unexpected and very interesting
discoveries.
One of our objectives was to bore
through the so-called granitic layer (the
upper part of the consolidated crust) to
reach a basaltic layer whose existence had
been deduced from geophysical data. Geo-
physicists had observed sharp variations in
the speed of seismic waves at great depths,
and, since these waves travel faster through
granite than through basalt, these varia¬
tions were thought to indicate a transition in
the Earth's crust from a granitic to a basaltic
layer. But this was no more than conjecture
because, unlike the granitic layer, identified
with the Archaean granitoid gneiss which is
widely distributed over the surface of the
continents, the basaltic layer does not
emerge on the surface.
The Kola drilling was the first ever to
bore through the line where the seismic
waves undergo a sharp change of speed. But
contrary to expectations, no basaltic layer ^
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
^ was discovered. It became apparent that the
variations in the speed of diffusion of the
seismic waves was related, not to a transi¬
tion from a granitic to a basaltic layer, but to
the decompaction of the rock which occurs
at great depths.
This phenomenon is due to the fact that,
under the effect of the high pressure and
temperatures existing at great depths, water
is released from the crystalline network of
minerals and, because of the enclosed
space, exerts pressure on the rock, leading
to Assuring and consequently decompac¬
tion. It turned out that the decompacted
zone had subsisted over a long period.
The discovery of the phenomenon of
"hydrogenous decompaction" not only
makes it possible to explain the geological
character of certain boundary zones which
reflect seismic waves at great depths, the
nature of hydrothermal fluids, and the
mechanism of tectonic deformations, it also
radically alters our ideas about the hydro-
logical cycle in continental conditions and
of the structure of the underground hydro¬
sphere,
The drilling provided extremely interest¬
ing information not only for geologists but
also for biologists. It was discovered that
. the deep horizons which had been thought
to be "dead" since the beginning of time
had actively participated at some stage in
the biological processes which took place in
the depths of the Earth.
Isotopic carbon analysis revealed two
sources of carbonic gas the first connected
with the mantle and found mainly in
Archaean rocks, the second of biogenic
origin and found predominantly in Protero¬
zoic rock, in which petrified remains of
micro-organisms (micro-fossils) estimated
to be thousands of millions of years old,
were also found.
This was not an isolated discovery.
Seventeen species of micro-organisms were
found, bearing witness to an extensive de¬
velopment of biogenic processes on our
planet in earliest times. Thus biological life
started on Earth much earlier than had
previously been estimated.
Data supplied by direct measurement of
temperatures at great depths have obliged
us to revise our concepts regarding present
and geohistorical variations of temperature
in the bowels of the Earth. It was previously
thought that in regions of slight tectonic
activity temperature rise in relation to
depth increase was insignificant. However,
although it was expected during the Kola
drilling that the temperature at a depth of
ten kilometres would be about 100 degrees
Centigrade, it turned out in fact to be
almost double this estimate, at 180 degrees
Centigrade. It was established that during
the Proterozoic era the géothermie gradient
(the temperature increase per 100 metres of
depth) was five times higher than it is today.
Study of the thermic regime in the bowels
of the Earth also provided an answer to a
question that has long preoccupied scien¬
tists what is the contribution of the mantle
and of radioactive decay of elements in
rocks to the overall heat flow in the interior
of the Earth? It was established that the
mantle was the chief source of ascending
heat.
Finally, the existence of underground wa¬
ter inside the old crystalline massifs at prac¬
tically all the levels reached was proved for
the first time. Inflows of highly mineralized
water saturated with bromine, iodine and
heavy metals were discovered, as well as
gases circulating through the crystalline
rocks in the zones of tectonic deformation.
At depths of 6.5 to 9.5 kilometres, zones of
low temperature hydrothermal mineraliza¬
tion (copper, lead, zinc, nickel, silver), pre¬
viously considered to be primarily near-
surface formations, were discovered.
The large number of mineral associations
discovered in the rock strata traversed dur¬
ing the drilling confirms the possibility that
mineral deposits may be present in indus¬
trially viable accumulations.
We were also led to revise our ideas
about the physical state and properties of
rocks at great depths. It emerged that rock
fissures do not disappear as depth increases.
This journey towards the centre of the
Earth the first to such a great depth (15
kilometres) was made possible by the em¬
ployment of radically new types of drilling
technology and equipment. This vast
undertaking necessitated the creation of a
unique type of drilling installation the
URALMACH 15000.
Drilling was effected by the open-shaft
(untubed) method. This considerably im¬
proved the quality and accuracy of geo¬
physical measurements. The reconnaiss¬
ance operations were conducted, not with
steel tubes, but with extra-strong heat-resis¬
tant tubes made from specially-developed
light alloys capable of withstanding temper¬
atures of 230 to 250 degrees Centigrade.
The specially-designed, highly efficient
rock-blasting and turbo-drills were pow¬
ered by the energy of the drilling liquid
pumped into the well. A completely new
type of apparatus was built to draw rock
samples from great depths intact and pre¬
served in their original orientation.
The programme for the study of the sub¬
terranean structure in depth provides for
exploration throughout the territory of the
Soviet Union. Drillings at very great depth
are at present being conducted in the Trans-
caucasus, the Urals, the Krivoi'-Rog Basin
and the Muruntauski region of Central
Asia. A drilling is being set up in the Tiu-
men district of Western Siberia.
The data provided by them will make it
possible, firstly, to assess the oil, gas and
ore-bearing potential of deep horizons and,
secondly, to elucidate the essential ques¬
tions relating to the tectonic evolution of
the Earth in the light of the continental drift
hypothesis. The programme provides for
special experimental and theoretical studies
concerning the elaboration of a general
theory of the evolution and structure of the
Earth's tectonosphere. The journey into
the Earth's past, undertaken by scientists to
decipher its evolution, will continue.
YEVGENI KOZLOVSKI, of the Soviet Union, is
head of the interdepartmental council of the
USSR State Committee ofScience and Technol¬
ogy for the study of the deep layers of the Earth
and for very deep drilling. Holder of the Lenin
Prize, he is the chief editor of a monograph on
deep drilling in the Kola Peninsula, and of the
world's first Encyclopaedia of Mining.
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page
Top photo: (a) This pebble of volcanic ash,
found near ¡sua in west Greenland, has
been shown to have an age of3,824 million
(plus or minus 12 million) years and is the
oldest known rock in the world. Other
rocks close to this age in the same area are
the Amitsoq Gneiss (b) and a banded iron
formation (c), whilst the fourth rock (d) is
an ancient Antarctic rock.
Bottom left: A stony meteorite from Bar-
well, England. Meteorites have been dated
back to about 4,600 million years.
Bottom right: A rock from the Moon. The
oldest rocks brought back from the Moon
have been dated at about 4,600 million
years.
Photos © British Museum (Natural History) Geological Museum,
London
Page 20
Above: One of the geological and scenic
wonders of the Earth, the Grand Canyon is
an immense gorge (in places over 1.5
kilometres deep) cutby the Colorado River
into the high plateaux of northwest Arizo¬
na, USA. Its rocks, including granite and
schist some 4,000 million years old, con¬
stitute a unique record of geological
events. Over 300 kilometres long, the
Canyon is at some points more than 20
kilometres wide.
Photo Alan Keler © Sygma, Paris
Below: Irazu, a volcano in the Cordillera
Central, Costa Rica, erupts in an inferno of
flame and lava.
Photo Ernst Haas © Magnum, Paris
Page 21
Above: Gases, ash and incandescent,
semi-solid lumps of lava are hurled up¬
wards during a volcanic eruption.
Photo Ernst Haas © Magnum, Paris
Below: The Hawaiian volcano Mauna Loa
during an eruption in 1984. Rising to 4, 169
metres above sea level, Mauna Loa (mean¬
ing "long mountain") has a dome 120
kilometres long and 102kilometres wide. It
has averaged one eruption every three and
a half years since 1832.
Photo Krafft © Explorer, Paris
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
V
f
im
ífW
êr
-, i*i
.-
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
J; ni V Se
m
Wí wff?-
M,
¿SS:
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
TT**
'.3Ç«fi i'".n
*¿*z
*&»*
¡r ^srm
-
*marj*-l
' J
>**J&
W"N^J
i**^.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
^r"*
^Êto te J^H -^ -
******** '
ET.' v
[A^^
^JÊ
S*:
>f*
y
* ;95f
-v
-- *e
\t¿
1
.
w* -**
<
- .
;,' ' i.. i
G
y»&r&«8
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The restless
Earth
The uncertain art
of earthquake prediction
by EM. Fournier d'Albe
Colour page left
Above: Photo taken in 1965 shows the
boiling crater ofSurtsey, a volcanic island
formed off southern Iceland after a sub¬
marine eruption on 14 November 1963.
(See picture story page 29.)
Photo Ernst Haas © Magnum. Paris
Below: Air view of the church of the village
of San Juan and another edifice partially
burled in lava flows from the eruption of
Paricutin, in West Central Mexico. One of
the Earth's youngest volcanoes, Paricutin
began to erupt on 20 February 1943. When
the eruption ended in 1952, the peak was
2,800 metres high.
Photo Kraift © Explorer, Paris
IT is often said that one cannot claim to
understand a natural phenomenon un¬
less one can accurately predict its
occurrence. If this is true, then the ability to
predict earthquakes must be one of the
principal goals of the science of seismology.
The scientist who ventures into this field,
however, incurs an unusual degree of per¬
sonal and social responsibility. Prediction
of a potentially destructive earthquake may
have serious disruptive effects on the social
and economic life of a community, whether
or not it eventually proves to be correct.
Many lives were saved, for example, by the
correct prediction of the Haicheng earth¬
quake in China in 1975, but against this
must be set many cases of erroneous predic¬
tions which have not only damaged the
reputations of the scientists concerned but
have also had considerable economic and
even political consequences.
In the present state of knowledge it is not
possible to determine, by observation and
calculation, precisely where and when an
earthquake will take place. This is because,
in order to make a prediction with the re¬
quired pinpoint accuracy, detailed informa¬
tion is needed on the stress fields and the
mechanical properties of the Earth's crust
over wide areas and down to depths of
several tens of kilometres. Even if it were to
become technically possible to obtain such
information, the cost of doing so would
probably remain prohibitive, and might in¬
deed be greater than that of repairing the
damage caused by the earthquake itself.
The few successful predictions that have
been made were based on the observation
of precursory phenomena of various kinds
generated by the same deep-seated process
which leads to earthquakes yet not causally
related to the earthquakes themselves.
Such phenomena might include sudden
changes in the level of minor seismic ac¬
tivity, slight deformations of the Earth's
surface, changes in magnetic or electrical
fields, unusual rise or fall of water levels in
wells, changes in the gravity field or abnor¬
mal behaviourof animals. Howevernoneof
these precursory . phenomena has yet
proved to be a reliable indicator of a forth¬
coming earthquake. The methods so suc- ^
Thousands of lives were saved when
Chinese experts successfully predicted
the Haicheng earthquake of 1975 (see
map). Following a severe earthquake at
Xingtai, in 1966, scientists noted that the
epicentres of subsequent tremors and
shocks, including that of the earthquake in
the Bo Hai gulf in 1969, seemed to be
moving in a north-easterly direction to¬
wards the heavilypopulated Liaoning Pro¬
vince. By June 1974, scientists were pre¬
dicting that there would be a major earth¬
quake to the north of Bo Hai within one or
two years. On 1 February 1975, a series of
minor tremors was correctly identified as
the foreshock heralding a major shock in
the area of the city ofHaicheng, and on the
following day more than a million people
were evacuated to temporary outdoor
shelter. Early in the evening of 4 February
the main shock (magnitude 7.3) occurred.
Although 90 per cent of the houses in the
area were damaged or destroyed, there
was very little loss of life.
©
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
^ cessfully employed at Haicheng failed to
predict the terrible Tangshan earthquake in
the following year.
New data are constantly being accumu¬
lated and there is hope that the accuracy of
predictions will gradually improve,
although they will of necessity remain prob¬
abilistic in nature. They will not state, for
instance, that "an earthquake of magnitude
X will take place in area Y on a certain
date"; rather they will take the form of a
statement on the probability of an earth¬
quake of a certain magnitude occurring in a
given area during a specified period of time.
So much for the scientific side of the
problem. The next question is: What will be
the effects of the predicted earthquake, if it
actually occurs? How many buildings will
be damaged or destroyed, and how many
people will be killed, injured or rendered
homeless? Will telephone networks con¬
tinue to function? Will streets be blocked by
debris?
In preparing to face an impending earth¬
quake emergency, civil defence services
need answers to these questions. They need
information on the expected strength of the
seismic ground motion and on the vulner¬
ability of buildings and urban lifelines to
this motion. They will need to prepare
"scenarios" of the probable effects of the
predicted earthquake.
For this to be done, seismologists and
geologists have first to estimate what will be
the intensity of the ground motion caused
by the expected earthquake and how this
intensity will vary from one part to another
of the area round the earthquake focus.
This they do on the basis of previous experi¬
ence and of knowledge of the local charac¬
teristics of the soil and sub-soil.
Then an inventory of buildings in the area
has to be compiled and an assessment made
of how each building is likely to react to the
expected ground motion, according to its
structural type and to the materials of which
it is built. This is where the greatest difficul¬
ty lies, since it is almost impossible to pre¬
dict exactly how any individual building will
behave in an earthquake. The best one can
do is to base the assessment on information
as to how similar buildings have behaved in
recent earthquakes elsewhere. Hence the
importance of carrying out detailed studies
of the damage caused each time an earth¬
quake occurs. Already some extremely
valuable information has come from the
studies made in Romania and Yugoslavia of
the damage caused in those countries by the
earthquakes of 1977 and 1979.
Clearly, all this work takes time and
should preferably not be left until an earth¬
quake is impending. For this reason civil
defence services in many earthquake-prone
countries are already collecting such in¬
formation and preparing scenarios, so as to
be ready to deal more effectively with poss¬
ible earthquake disasters, whether or not
they are predicted in advance.
Earthquake scenarios are invaluable not
only for planning the mobilization of rescue
teams, medical and fire-fighting services,
and the stockpiling of emergency supplies
of food and shelter against a possible earth¬
quake, but also for planning the various
temporary measures of protection that can
be taken in response to a prediction. For
instance, inflammable or toxic substances
can be moved into safe storage, vulnerable
systems in chemical plants can be shut down
for a time, water levels in reservoirs can be
lowered and schools and theatres can be
temporarily closed. In the final stage of an
alert, people can be evacuated from their
homes or places of work in vulnerable
buildings.
Such measures are costly and disruptive
of individual and social life. They may be
resisted and cannot be prolonged for more
than a few days, and they will probably be
abandoned after one or more false alarms.
They are therefore likely to be applied in
response to an earthquake prediction only
if the responsible authorities are convinced
that the prediction satisfies certain criteria
of accuracy and reliability.
As we have seen, scientific predictions
are likely to be expressed in terms of prob¬
ability. Public authorities, on the other
The world's first seismometer
The first known instrument capable of
sensing earth motion was invented in AD
132 by the Chinese philosopher Chang
Heng. It consistedofa large bronze vessel,
some two metres In diameter, around
which were spaced eight dragon heads
with pivotingjaws In which were held eight
balls. Inside the vessel was a pendulum
with eight arms each of which was con¬
nected to one of the dragon heads. When
an earthquake shock caused the pendu¬
lum to vibrate, the arm connected to the
dragon head facing the direction of the
shock caused its jaws to open allowing the
ball they held to fall into the open mouth of
one of the eight toads positioned around
the base of the vessel. The Instrument was
sensitive enough to detect an earthquake
whose epicentre was over 600 kilometres
away. It was not until 1856 that a seismo¬
graph capable of recording the passage of
seismic waves and giving their amplitude,
time ofonsetanddirection was installedat
the observatory at Vesuvius. Opposite
page, a modern reconstruction of Chang
Heng's apparatus and, above left, Its mode
of operation. Since the founding, In the
early 1960s, of the Worldwide Standar¬
dized Seismograph Network (WWSSN),
seismic observatories with standard
equipment and synchronized time-keep¬
ing have been established virtually
throughout the world. Map above shows
distribution of the WWSSNandassociated
observatories.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
hand, have to make decisions on a "yes or
no" basis. It is therefore of crucial import¬
ance to develop an effective dialogue be¬
tween scientists and public authorities. The
latter need to acquire, through discussions
with the scientists, insight into the reason¬
ing that leads to the formulation of predic¬
tions in a particular form. For their part,
scientists need to familiarize themselves
with the problems faced by public author¬
ities, so that they will understand the
responses of the latter to predictions and
the reasons behind those responses.
It is essential that any earthquake predic¬
tion that is communicated to the public
should be accompanied by a verifiable esti¬
mate of the probability of occurrence of the
predicted event within the specified limits
of time and space. If it is to be useful in
practice, the prediction must also meet the
following criteria:
(a) its lead time (the interval between the
issue of the prediction and the expected
occurrence of the event) should be longer
than the time required for putting into
effect the appropriate protective measures
and for mobilizing the resources needed to
deal with the emergency;
(b) its time window (the duration of the
period during which the event is predicted
to occur) should be shorter than the max¬
imum acceptable duration of protective
measures such as the evacuation of build
ings, the temporary closure of plants and
the mobilization of rescue services.
The above criteria are, of course, very
difficult to satisfy given the present state of
scientific knowledge, but experience has
shown that predictions that fail to meet
them can cause severe social and economic
disturbance without being of any great use
to the community concerned. Earthquake
prediction is not only a scientific problem
but one which concerns the community as a
whole.
The development of techniques of earth¬
quake-resistant design and construction
offers the hope that in the course of time
death and destruction in earthquakes will
become a thing of the past. The phenomena
accompanying some volcanic eruptions,
however, are of such violence that there are
no means of protection against them. The
only hope of survival lies in flight from the
threatened area. Accurate prediction of
eruptions is therefore of vital importance
for the safety of people living on or near
active volcanoes.
Fortunately, the problem of predicting
eruptions is slightly less difficult than that of
predicting earthquakes. This is because the
possible sites of volcanic eruptions are
usually known. It is rare for an eruption to
occur anywhere but from an existing volca¬
nic structure, although eruptions do some¬
times occur at volcanoes that have been
dormant for so long that they are thought to
be extinct. By careful geological study it is
possible to identify and map the areas
around a volcano that have been affected in
the past by one or more of the destructive
phenomena that accompany eruptions
glowing avalanches, mudflows, lava flows,
heavy ash falls, and so on.
A census can be made of the people who
live or work in these hazardous areas,
together with an inventory of movable
property and livestock. Evacuation routes
to safe refuge zones can be identified and
plans made for rapid evacuation in the
event of an eruption. Arrangements can be
planned for the emergency shelter and
housing of evacuees in the refuge zones. If
worked out in detail beforehand, such plans
can be instrumental in saving many lives
when an eruption occurs.
As in the case of earthquakes, predic¬
tions based on the observation of precur¬
sory phenomena are necessarily expressed
in terms of probabilities of eruption. There
will always remain, therefore, the problem
of making "yes or no" decisions in situations
of uncertainty. The risk of a possible catas¬
trophe has to be weighed against the cer¬
tainty of the inconvenience, hardship and
cost of removing people from their homes,
perhaps for periods as long as weeks or
months.
Here again it is of crucial importance that ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
^ an effective dialogue be developed between
scientists, civil authorities, the news media
and the public before any emergency arises.
The threat of an imminent earthquake or
volcanic eruption is a great revealer of the
strengths and weaknesses of any com¬
munity.
"Success stories" in dealing with such
threats are still few, but they do demon¬
strate that, if scientific predictions are pre¬
cise and reliable, if the civil authorities are
prepared and have the means to take
appropriate protective action, and if the
public is kept fully informed of the situation
and of the action being taken to meet it, the
losses inflicted by these violent manifesta¬
tions of nature can be reduced and may in
time become a thing of the past.
E.M. FOURNIER D'ALBE, of the United King¬
dom, is a specialist on earthquake risk man¬
agement. Until 1979 he was head of Unesco's
Division of Earth Sciences and was responsible
for the initiation and development of the Organi¬
zation's programme related to natural disasters
and their prevention.
//
Mechanism of earthquakes
Fault stuck after
last movement
Stress builds up
rocks bend
like a bow
Focus
Earthquake! Rocks
spring back
and vibrate
When the Earth shakes
ALTHOUGH some minor earthquakes
have been triggered by human acti¬
vities, such as underground nuc¬
lear testing and the construction of reser¬
voirs and dams, the principal cause of all
major earthquakes and most minor ones Is
the fracturing of rocks following the gra¬
dual accumulation of stress during geolo¬
gical processes.
The Earth's surface Is made up of a
series of plates (see page 10) and the
severest earthquakes tend to occur at the
plate margins, where plates slide past
each other as, for example, along the San
Andreas "fault" region of California. Dia¬
gram above offers a simplified illustration
of the mechanism of an earthquake. Rock
has a certain elasticity and where adjacent
areas of rock are subjected to the push/
pull forces of plate movement stress gra¬
dually accumulates. When the strain be
comes too great, the rock ruptures and
tension is released as the rocks on either
side of the fault spring back violently. The
point at which the rupture originates is
called the focus and the point on the
Earth's surface directly above the focus is
called the epicentre.
The energy released is emitted in waves
which cause the ground to oscillate. It is
these seismic waves that are picked up
and recorded by seismographs, instru¬
ments which enable scientists to pinpoint
the epicentre of an earthquake and to mea¬
sure Its magnitude.
Two scales are commonly used to mea¬
sure the size of an earthquake. The magni¬
tude of an earthquakethe total amount of
energy released or dissipatedis ex¬
pressed In terms of the Richter Scale and
is based on seismograph recordings of
the amplitude of seismic waves. To cover
the huge size range of earthquakes, the
Richter scale of magnitude is logarithmic
rather than arithmetic, that is to say, the
scale is so arranged that each increase in
magnitude of one unit represents a thirty-
fold increase in earthquake size. Thus an
earthquake of magnitude 8 on the Richter
scale is 810,000 times as large as one of
magnitude 4.
The intensity of an earthquake classifies
the degree of shaking and is based on
inspection of damage and on information
supplied by people involved in the earth¬
quake. The scale most commonly used is
called the Modified Mercalli Intensity Scale
(see below). Since this scale is based pure¬
ly on observation of earthquake effects,
the points on the scale are stated in Roman
numerals, from I to XII, rather than in ordin¬
ary numbers, which might be interpreted
as indicating some kind of measurement.
Modified Mercalli Intensity Scale
I Not felt by people.
II Felt by people at rest on upper floors of buildings.
III Felt indoors; vibrations like a light truck passing outside. Hanging
objects swing.
IV Vibration like passing of heavy truck; windows, dishes and doors rattle.
V Felt outdoors; sleepers wakened and liquids spilt.
VI Felt by all; many frightened and run outdoors; plaster and masonry
cracked; furniture moved or overturned; windows, glassware and
dishes broken.
VII Difficult to stand up; noticed by drivers of moving vehicles; plaster,
loose bricks, tiles, etc. fall; large bells ring; waves on ponds.
VIII Difficult to steer vehicles; fall of stucco and some masonry walls; fall of
chimney stacks, towers, monuments; branches broken from trees;
cracks to be seen in wet ground.
IX General panic; frame structures cracked and underground pipes
broken; conspicuous cracks in ground; sand craters.
X Most masonry and frame structures and foundations destroyed; se¬
rious damage to dams and embankments; some bridges destroyed;
large landslides.
XI Railway lines badly bent; underground pipes completely out of service.
XII Damage nearly total; lines of sight and level distorted; objects thrown
up into the air.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Volcanoes
by Haroun Tazieff
VOLCANISM plays a fundamental
role in the story of the Earth. The
crust we live on, the water in
oceans, rivers and lakes and most of the
atmosphere we breathe are derived ulti¬
mately from volcanic eruptions. Without
volcanism there would be no creation of
new oceanic crust through sea-floor
spreading, no subduction (the dragging
down of older crust into the mantle where
it is melted and recycled), no orogenesis
(mountain-building) and therefore no
erosion and no sedimentation.
Without volcanism the Earth would
lack the colossal, continual flow of sul¬
phides, oxides, halogens, hydroxides of
all existing metals, emitted in the form of
gases at high temperature by fumaroles
(volcanic vents) from the thousands of
active craters, whether dormant or in
eruption, whether submarine or on land,
scattered the length of the 100,000
kilometres of the belts that mark the fron¬
tiers between the Earth's tectonic plates
(see page 10) and the fractures occurring
within those plates.
Without the contribution of submarine
fumaroles there would be no mineral sul¬
phide deposits; without fumaroles the
marine environment, whose chemical
make-up made possible the emergence of
life and conditioned its evolution, would
not have existed; without fumaroles the
Earth would have lacked the elements to
form the atmosphere whose composition
made it possible for life forms emerging
from the ocean to colonize the land and
then to evolve to give rise to human
beings.
Like everyone else at that time, I was
unaware of all this when, in 1948, chance
brought me face to face for the first time
with the strange phenomenon of a volca¬
nic eruption. Like all my fellow geologists
of that generation, especially my Euro¬
pean colleagues, I had received from my
teachers, among whom were some of in¬
ternational renown, a course of instruc¬
tion in which volcanism was barely men¬
tioned, since, in their view, it represented
no more than "a skin disease of the
planet".
At all events, I knew practically no¬
thing at all about volcanism when, one
day in March 1948, to the north of Lake
Kivu in the Belgian Congo (now Zaire),
the first eruption I was privileged to see
not only opened the eyes of the naive
geologist I then was to the magnificence
of the spectacle but also to a phenomenon
which, because of my lack of knowledge,
raised more questions than it provided
answers.
In the forty or so years that have passed
since then, volcanology, moribund at the
close of the Second World War (barely
surviving in the United States and in New
Zealand, but extinct everywhere else),
gradually revived and finally, in parallel
with oceanography, came into full blos¬
som. The new knowledge these two disci¬
plines enabled us to garner soon revealed
the fundamental role played by volcan¬
ism both in the phenomenon of sea-floor
spreading and the genesis of life and its
evolution over the past 3,000 million
years.
More than a third of a century spent in
observing eruptions from as close as
possible and in measuring everything
there was to measure among other
things energy flows (mainly thermal) and
the flow of matter (mainly in the form of
gases) has enabled me to establish that,
rather than the liquid or lava phase, as
most people seem implicitly or explicitly
to imagine, it is the gaseous phase that
plays the active role in volcanism. Lava is
totally passive and, without its eruptive
gases, volcanism would simply not exist.
Furthermore, eruptions always involve
the emission of gas, but not always of
lava.
These considerations led me to the
conviction that, in order to understand
the mechanism of eruptions, it was essen¬
tial to know the chemical composition
and thermodynamic evolution of their
gaseous phase. It would seem that the
chemical composition of these gases
varies from one kind of eruption to
another and from one type of magma to
another, but in our present state of know¬
ledge it has not been possible to establish
a correlation between the chemical varia¬
tions detected and the variations in activ¬
ity observed.
It must be admitted that, up to now,
only an insignificant amount of data has
been acquired on the physico-chemical
composition of eruptive gases. By erup¬
tive gases I mean those that have not been
subject to much cooling, oxidation by the
air or hydration by groundwater, all of
which processes transform the gases to a
lesser or, more often, a greater extent.
Obviously, to measure the chemical
and physical properties of the eruptive
gases before they degrade into fumarole
gases, it is necessary to get close to the
vents from which they are being emitted.
This usually demands some physical
effort and, at times, a certain amount of
courage. What too many volcanologists
lack is not courage but a taste for muscu¬
lar effort. Between the ages of twenty and
thirty, some seem to possess it, but I have
noticed that, once they have attained a
certain academic standing, they usually
appear to lose it.
This would not be too serious were it
not for the fact that, in addition to the raw
data which will continue to be provided
by the young and still enthusiastic volca¬
nologists, a sine qua non of progress in
this field is experience of the actual event
of eruption, the complexity of which is
matched by its variability. This can only
be acquired by direct observation of the
phenomenon of eruption in all its succes¬
sive forms.
The competence of the volcanologist in
this respect, like that of a physician, de¬
pends both on proper knowledge of im¬
portant publications and on experience
gained through the examination of a max¬
imum number of subjects patients for
the doctor, volcanoes in eruption for the
volcanologist.
My first ten years of volcanological
research in the field were devoted exclu¬
sively to seeking an explanation of the
various aspects of the phenomenon of
eruption. I soon became convinced that
the maturation of dormant magma re¬
sulted from the release of the gases
formerly dissolved within it. The chemic¬
al properties, size and distribution of gas
bubbles within the viscous mass, their
growth in size either by two or more
bubbles joining up or by expansion dur¬
ing their ascension through the magma
and of the magma itself, all these factors
play their part in the maturation of the
magma before the eruption and in its
evolution during the eruption itself.
Whether they can be measured or
merely observed, when correctly inter-
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
^ preted the parameters of an eruption en¬
able us more or less to understand the
eruptive process and, consequently,
sometimes to predict it.
This understanding enabled me, from
1958 on, to answer accurately questions
put to me by the administrative or politic¬
al authorities of a number of cities, pro¬
vinces, even countries, where a volcano
appeared to pose a threat to public safety.
Thus I found myself gradually moving
from fundamental research to research
applied to the forecasting of possible
eruptions. Since 1981, when the French
Government decided to take an official
stand on the mitigation of catastrophic
events, my work in volcanology has been
limited to this area.
Over nearly thirty years I have found
myself in the position of having to answer
questions from the authorities in a dozen
or so different countries. And if my re¬
plies have not once been mistaken, this is
because, like a good doctor, I have based
my diagnosis on the information avail¬
able interpreted in the light of my ex¬
perience. Out of fifteen cases which I
recall, I was able to give nine reassuring
replies, to confirm the threat of danger
three times and, on three occasions, was
obliged to admit that I did not know.
Over this period, the questions put to
me were seldom in the form "Is there
going to be an eruption or not?" Usually I
was asked whether there was or was not
any danger from an eruption actually tak¬
ing place. While, under such circum¬
stances, the latter question is clearly the
most important, it is also the most diffi¬
cult one to answer.
It is, in fact, relatively easy to predict
an eruption when the volcano in question
is being properly watched over by
genuine experts with adequate equip¬
ment. With the exception of eruptions
resulting from a build-up of steam press¬
ure caused by overheating of under¬
ground water beneath a blocked vent
hole eruptions which emit no magma or
lava, but only steam, some fumarole
gases and fragments of the rock blocking
the vent all volcanic eruptions are the
result of the ascent to the surface of the
globe of a certain volume of magma.
This ascension of magma cannot occur
without some movement of the Earth's
crust in response to the pressure of the
magma; either the crust stretches and
becomes deformed, or it fractures. Sur¬
face deformations can be detected and
measured by such instruments as tilt-
meters, extensometers and geodimeters.
The opening of fractures, through which
magma can infiltrate into the crust and
rise to the surface, causes tremors which
can be recorded by seismometers.
These geophysical observations and
measurements, which can give warning of
an eruption, often several months but
sometimes only days or hours in advance
(depending, among other things, on the
depth at which the magma is situated
before it begins its ascension), are sup¬
plemented by other observations which
may help the volcanologist in making a
forecast. These include the temperature,
composition and pressure of fumarolic
gases, and changes in the magnetic field
of the Earth's crust. All these indications
enable experienced volcanologists to de¬
tect a coming eruption and to give a date
for its arrival, sometimes with very great
precision.
Unfortunately, from the point of view
of saving lives, such predictions are of
little importance. Magmatic eruptions,
whether they be explosive or effusive,
never start in disastrous fashion. The first
phase of an eruption is always (to my
knowledge no exception to this rule has
ever been observed) relatively moderate,
allowing inhabitants time to leave the
threatened area.
Evacuation, the only way to protect
people from major volcanic risk, is rarely
necessary, since it is quite exceptional for
an eruption, after its initial phase, to
deteriorate into a paroxysmal phase or to
become even slightly more dangerous.
Out of the average hundred eruptions
that occur year after year throughout the
world, scarcely one will develop in this
way and so justify special precautions.
The major problem that faces the vol¬
canologist is to forecast the evolution of
eruption while it is taking place a task
infinitely more difficult than predicting
an imminent eruption. Once an eruption
has begun, all the mechanical indica¬
tions deformation or fracturing of the
surface connected with the rise of the
magma through the Earth's crust will
have disappeared and the flow of magma
will be "fluid", that is, it will no longer
have to fracture the rock in the depths or
lift the flanks of the volcano to force its
way to the surface.
Deprived of these two indicators that
are fundamental to the forecasting of a
coming eruption (tremors and deforma¬
tion of the surface), the volcanologist is
obliged to establish his diagnosis on the
basis of his interpretation of the other
physical and chemical indications men¬
tioned above. Correlation of the various
factors involved and their interpretation ^
CONTINUED PAGE 31
Waves of destruction
At one o'clock in the afternoon of 26 August 1883 the first of
a series of increasingly violent explosions occurred on the
volcanic island of Krakatoa, in the Sunda Strait between Java
and Sumatra, Indonesia. An hour later, a black cloud of ash
rose 27 kilometres into the air above the island.
The eruptions continued, reaching a climax with a
tremendous explosion at ten o'clock in the morning of the
following day which sent ash billowing 80 kilometres into the
air and which was heard in Australia over 4,000 kilometres
away. All but a fragment of Krakatoa, the cone of a huge
underwater volcano, disappeared beneath the waves.
On the neighbouring islands of Lang and Verlaten, volcanic
ash and debris lay 60 metres deep. Vivid sunsets caused by
fine ash particles in the air were seen as far away as Europe
and rafts of pumice (lava filled with gas bubbles) floated on
the surrounding ocean for many months.
Worse was to come; the collapse of the volcano triggered a
series of tsunamis, or seismic sea waves (often called tidal
waves, a misnomer since they have no connection with
tides). The biggest wave, which attained a height of some 35
metres, devastated some 300 towns and villages on the
shores of Java and Sumatra, taking 36,000 lives.
Almost all tsunamis occur in the Pacific. They are caused
by a sudden vertical movement of the sea bed resulting from
a submarine volcanic eruption or an earthquake. Following a
disastrous tsunami in 1946, a warning system was estab¬
lished covering the entire Pacific Ocean. Tsunami detectors
and seismic recording apparatus at seismic observatories
around the Pacific sound the alarm whenever a likely event is
detected. The information recorded is transmitted to the Hon¬
olulu Observatory which is responsible for assessing the risk
and issuing warnings if this is considered necessary.
Sumatra
VKrakatoa o -
>. tth-ftll 4
Rodriguu Island ' , \
"*"*** ¿Alte« Springt
'-. art* ovtf which txplotlont wtrt httrd ..'
30004HTT
	i
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Birth of an island
On 14 November 1963, a fiery eruption in
the Atlantic Ocean off the southern coast
of Iceland heralded the birth of a new
island. Named Surtsey, after Surtur, the
fire god of Icelandic myth, the new island
rose from the water in a convulsion of
flame and steam. A weekafter the eruption
Surtsey had a surface area of 70 square
metres and within three and a half years
had grown to its present size of two and a
half square kilometres with elevations of
up to 173 metres. When scientists visited
the island after it had cooled, they were
astonished to find that plant life had
alreadyestablisheda footing. Constituting
as it does the first "virgin" ecosystem
known to man, Surtsey is now the site
of a long-term ecological research pro¬
gramme.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Photo Jacques Huttin © Gamma, Paris
Cry havoc!
Although prediction of volcanic eruptions
can reduce orprevent loss of life, little can
be done to control damage to crops or
property once an eruption is under way.
The three major dangers arise from mud-
flow, lava-flow and ash.
Over the last few centuries mud-flows
(sometimes known as lahars^ have proved
to be the most dangerous, killing more
people and destroying more property than
any other type of volcanic activity. Mud-
flows often result from the rapidmelting of
ice or snow on the slope of a volcano or
maybe due to heavy rain orsnow falls after
an eruption on new volcanic ash. Mud-
flows have been known to attain speeds of
up to 70 kilometres an hourand to travelas
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
3fr
rar as Í80 kilometres. Left, the town of
Armero, Colombia, swallowed up by mud
following the eruption of the Nevado del
Ruiz volcano, in November 1985.
Thin lava-flows cool fairly quickly, but
thicker flows may take years to cool com¬
pletely. Various methods have been
attempted to check or divert lava-flows,
including the use of water hoses to create
a solid wall ofcooled lava andbombing the
sides of a flow to split it into many smaller
flows. Above left, lava-flow blocks a road
following the eruption of La Fournaise vol¬
cano on the French island of Réunion in
the Indian Ocean, on 18 March this year.
Despite its name, volcanic ash is not the
product of burning; it consists of pulver
ized lava and fragments of rock thrown
into the air by the sudden explosive
escape of volcanicgas. The eruption of the
Tambora volcano on the northern coast of
the island ofSumbawa, Indonesia, in 1815,
which killed 50,000 ¡slanders, is estimated
to have had an explosive force equivalent
to 16,000 megatons. The very fine ash from
such an eruption may travel huge dis¬
tances andaffect weatherpatterns. Above,
the village of Parentas, Indonesia, en¬
veloped in volcanic ash following the erup¬
tion, in 1982, of the Galunggung volcano.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 28
^ is extremely difficult in view of our pre¬
sent lack of sufficient research data and
experience in this field. And without cor¬
relation to enable him to establish links of
cause and effect between what he has
been able to measure and observe, it is
virtually impossible for the volcanologist
to establish a serious diagnosis.
Finally, I would like to remind readers
of an article by me which appeared in the
October 1967 issue of the Unesco
Courier. In it I drew the attention both of
politicians and of the inhabitants of the
regions involved to the great danger of
so-called "extinct" volcanoes. These vol¬
canoes are often, in fact, only dormant,
which implies that they will one day be¬
come active again. This is a risk which
should be taken seriously and construc¬
tion should be avoided within the danger
zone surrounding such volcanoes.
The extent of the danger zone will de¬
pend on the nature of the volcanic activity
(whether it is effusive or explosive), the
size and altitude of the volcano con¬
cerned, and even the climate of the re¬
gion in which it is situated.
The importance of climate and altitude
was demonstrated in dramatic fashion on
13 November 1985 with the eruption of
the Nevado del Ruiz volcano in Col¬
ombia. Had it not been for the height of
the volcano and the climate of the region,
which made possible the formation of a
thick icecap on its summit, the upsurge of
lava at a temperature of 1,000 degrees
Centigrade would not have provoked the
melting of hundreds of thousands of cubic
metres of ice and the formation of "la-
hars", those terrible torrents of volcanic
mud which swallowed up the town of
Armero, claiming the lives of 23,000
victims.
What I wrote almost twenty years ago
about the danger represented by Vesu¬
vius (Italy) or the Campi Flegrei (the
Phlegraean Fields, Naples, Italy), Mount
Fuji (Japan) or Mount Rainier (USA),
remains true today, as witness what hap¬
pened at Mount St. Helens, a close neigh¬
bour of Mount Rainier, and at Helgafell
in Iceland. The authorities of countries
within whose borders potentially danger¬
ous volcanoes are situated those
thought to be extinct as well as those
known to be active, such as Merapi (In¬
donesia) or Etna (Italy), Sakurajima
(Japan), Vulcano (Italy) or Pichincha
(Ecuador), to name but a few should
take advantage of the "days of peace" to
consider the problems that will arise and
prepare' the action they will take when
these sleeping giants reawaken.
HAROUN TAZIEFF, eminent French volcanolo¬
gist, was formerly Director of Research at the
Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique.
Until recently Secretary of State for the Preven¬
tion of Major Disasters, he is the author of many
books and studies on volcanology. He has also
produced a number of films and documentaries
including Les Rendez-vous du Diable (The De¬
vil's Rendezvous, 1958) which achieved world¬
wide acclaim.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Quaternary. Large mammals like mastodons (A), sabre-tooth cats (B), and blue
whales (C) are at first dominant. For the last million years, ice intermittently covers
most of the northern hemisphere. Some animals migrate; some, like woolly
rhinoceroses (D), adapt to the cold. Early man (E), using stone tools and making fire,
is succeeded by modern man.
m
Tertiary. Mammals evolve rapidly, producing such specialized types as the lemur
Plesiadapis (A), ancestor of the primates, five-toed Phenacodus (B) and horned
Titanotherium (C). Birds evolve, including giant flightless forms like Diatryma (D).
Fish, reptiles and invertebrates now resemble those of today; for example, the sand
shark (E) has hardly changed.
Cretaceous. On land, flowering plants like magnolia (A) appear. In the sea, modern
bony fishes evolve alongside sea-urchins (B) and bivalve molluscs (C). At the end of
the period, giant dinosaurs, like Stegosaurus (D), and large flying pterodactyls (E)
suddenly die out. New types of small mammal, such as the shrew-like Phascolother-
ium (F), evolve.
Jurassic. The sea shelters brachiopods, cephalods called ammonites (A), belem-
nites (B) and fossil oysters such as Gryphaea (C). There are bony fishes, sharks and
two groups of marine reptiles: ichthyosaurs (D) and plesiosaurs. Great dinosaurs like
Brontosaurus (E) share the land with small mammals. Archaeopteryx (F), the ances¬
tral bird, takes wing.
Triassic. Such mammal-like reptiles as Cynognathus (A), ancestors of the mammals,
are succeeded by small animals, dinosaur-ancestors like Omothosuchus (B). Club-
mosses, horsetails and seed ferns become rarer; they are replaced by cycads,
ginkgoes (C) and conifers. In the sea, new invertebrate groups evolve. Sea-lilies (D)
and reef-building corals are numerous.
Permian. Mammal-like reptiles like Dimetrodon (A) rule the land. Large amphibians
are scarce. In the sea, cephalods (B), two-valved molluscs (C) and primitive bony fish
(D) continue to thrive; corals and sea-urchins grow scarcer, and most of the sharks die
out. A forest of seed ferns covers the southern land mass. More varied plant life
flourishes in the north.
°Y'
.MM
Carboniferous. The amphibians (A) become a large and important group; they
eventually give rise to the reptiles, the first full-time land vertebrates. Conifers and tree
ferns (B) evolve, and dragonflies (C) and other insects appear. Sharks (D) dominate
the sea. In shallow water, brachiopods (E), corals (F), cephalopods, sponges and
sea-lilies are common.
-
II
Devonian. Armoured fish (A) and bony and scaly fish (B) flourish in fresh water.
Sharks and spiny fish colonize the sea. Brachiopods (C) and molluscs called cephalo¬
pods (D) continue to evolve; trilobites grow scarce and graptolites die out. On land,
simple vascular plants (E) are followed by clubmosses, horsetails and ferns. The first
amphibians evolve from scaly fish.
Silurian. The land is conquered, first by colonies of seedless vascular plants and later
by scorpion-like arthropods. In fresh water, small fish and large eurypterids or
water-scorpions abound. The sea ¡s teeming with invertebrates, especially trilobites
(A), crinoids or sea-lilies (B), corals (C), horny-coated eurypterids (D), brachiopods (E)
and graptolites (F).
Ordovician. Shelly invertebrates flourish, especially trilobites (A), brachiopods (B),
cephalopods (C) and gastropods or sea-snails (D). Corals, two-valved molluscs and
branchy or mossy colonies of bryozoans appear. Graptolites (E, F), some looking like
hard spider webs, spread. In fresh water the first fish (known only from scale
fragments) evolve.
Cambrian. At the dawn of this period a number of animal groups develop shells and
hard parts of calcite and horn. These include trilobites (A, B), brachiopods (C, D),
sponges (E) and crustaceans. The trilobites, so called from their three-lobed bodies,
evolve into a large and varied group of crawlers and swimmers that dominates the sea
for the next 100 million years.
U
Precambrian. During this period, which goes back to the beginning of geological time,
complex organic compounds evolve from simple inorganic chemical substances.
Bacteria (A, B) and algae (C, D) appear early in the period. By its close, soft-bodied
marine and freshwater animals like worms (E, F), jellyfish and sponges have evolved. Oil
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Life from space
Does life on Earth have its origins in comets?
by Chandra Wickramasinghe
Since 1962, astronomers Professor Chandra Wickrama¬
singhe and Sir Fred Hoyle have been studying the nature of
interstellar dust and have concluded that terrestrial life had
its origins in the gas and dust clouds of space. Life, they
believe, in direct contradiction to Darwinian theory, was
derived from and continues to be driven by sources outside
the Earth (see the Unesco Courier, May 1982). Although their
conclusions are strongly contested by other scientists, initial
appraisal of data obtained from the study of Halley's comet
appears to lend support to at least some aspects of their
viewpoint.
COMETS are inextricably linked with
the history of the Earth. Cometary
bodies, as well as debris from them
in the form of fine dust particles, have been
colliding with the Earth from the very ear¬
liest days of its existence as a planet some
4,600 million years ago. It is now clear that
volatile materials from comets, including
water, contributed in significant measure to
the primordial oceans and atmosphere.
Cometary impacts and the acquisition of
cometary material did not, however, stop in
distant geological time. As recently as 1908,
a comet, or part of a comet, collided with
the Earth in the Tunguska Valley of Siberia,
exploding at a height of 8.5 kilometres in
the atmosphere and devastating hundreds
of square kilometres of taiga forest.
The entire Solar System today is sur¬
rounded by a spherical halo of some
thousands of millions of comets located at a
distance of about a tenth of a light-year (a
light-year is the distance light travels in a
year about 10 million million kilometres).
Passing stars cause cometary objects from
this halo to become deflected into orbits
that bring them to the inner regions of the
Solar System at the rate of about one or two
a year. The Earth is well and truly entwined
within these orbits so material shed from
these comets must be reaching us quite
plentifully. This material becomes trapped
in the Earth's upper atmosphere, adding
steadily to the store of terrestrial volatile
materials. Fluctuations must occur in the
rate of in-fall of cometary debris over long
periods of geological time. It is now widely
believed that significant increases in this
rate would trigger the onset of episodes of
global glaciations (ice ages) such as are
known to have occurred.
A typical comet, such as Halley's comet,
has a mass of some 100,000 million tons and
a direct hit from such an object would have
dramatic consequences for our planet. For¬
tunately, such collisions are exceedingly
rare, occurring at intervals averaging about
300 million years, coinciding approximately
with the time intervals between successive
bursts in the evolution of terrestrial life.
Smaller comets are more numerous and
could collide more frequently.
This much is more or less agreed upon by
most scientists. A less popular view, advo¬
cated by the British astronomer Sir Fred
Hoyle and myself, is that comets were also
responsible for the importation of organic
molecules that contributed to the origin of
life on our planet. We have further sug¬
gested that the Earth continues to receive
ready-formed living structures such as bac¬
teria and viruses even at the present time.
From 1975 onwards, we have accumu¬
lated evidence to support our view that
organic dust grains, including organic po¬
lymers (large chains of carbon-based orga¬
nic molecules), exist on a vast cosmic scale.
These dust grains populate the clouds of gas
that exist between stars and give rise to the
visual effect of dark patches and striations
(1) The adjective "organic" is often commonly used to
mean "living", in the sense that a plant, a tree or a human
being is "living"; chemists employ it in a restricted sense to
describe compounds containing carbon combined with
hydrogen. All living things contain carbon and hydrogen
and thus are organic, but not all things that contain
carbon and hydrogen are living. "Biological" means "of
or relating to life or living things".
seen against the diffuse light of the Milky
Way. In 1981, through a combination of
laboratory studies, mathematical computa¬
tions and astronomical observation, we ar¬
rived at the conclusion that the bulk of
cosmic dust was not merely organic but
distinctly biological in character ^.
In a series of publications we have pre¬
sented arguments to support the theory that
life on Earth had its origins in comets and
that evolution is controlled by the con¬
tinuing input ofcometary material. Because
the injection of comets from the outer Solar
System is sporadic, this input of cometary
material is not expected to be uniform and
regular in time, and so the effect on evolu¬
tion will also be sporadic. This sporadic
characteristic clearly shows up in the fossil
record which traces the evolution of terrest¬
rial life.
A dramatic example is provided by the
extinction of the dinosaurs 65 million years
ago. It has recently been argued by many
scientists that this event was caused by a
comet which shrouded the Earth in a halo of
fine particles. These particles acted like a
smog that darkened the skies for decades
and caused withering of plankton and plants
and the demise of all large creatures that fed
on plants.
Sir Fred Hoyle and I believe that such a
purely physical cause is unlikely in view of
the fact that the extinction of the dinosaurs
also coincided with an extinction of a large
fraction of the genera of all plants, animals
and micro-organisms and the emergence of
several brand new orders of living forms.
We identify this extinction/speciation event
of 65 million years ago with a genetic storm
that resulted from an exceptionally large
new crop of comets that were injected into
the inner regions of the Solar System.
The first clear-cut detections of organic
molecules hydrogen cyanide (HCN) and
methyl cyanide (CH3CN) came from
observations of comet Kohoutek, in 1973
and 1974. But cometary theories came
under very much closer scrutiny in March
this year when, as the culminating point of
the International Halley Watch, the Euro¬
pean space satellite Giotto penetrated to
within a few hundred kilometres of the
nucleus of Halley's comet (see the Unesco
Courier, March 1986).
The payload of Giotto included a variety
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
^ of scientific experiments and a video
camera that was intended to send back col¬
our pictures of the comet's nucleus. Earlier
in March, the Soviet space satellite Vega 2
successfully accomplished a similar mission.
Pictures of the comet's nucleus, taken by
Vega 2 from a distance of several thousand
kilometres, showed tentative indications
that it may be split into at least two frag¬
ments. Giotto might have been able to settle
this matter but for an unfortunate hitch in
communications that occurred seconds be¬
fore the moment of closest approach. In the
event, the best pictures we have is of the
nucleus surrounded by a peanut-shaped
shroud of obscuring dust.
What is to be learned from the first
appraisals of the data sent back by the va¬
rious missions to comet Halley?
Our organic theory of comets predicts
that cometary nuclei must develop a highly
porous mesh-like surface layer of polymeric
particles. Evaporation of material on a
large scale can only occur from places on the
surface where this surface layer becomes
abraded or broken. A consequence is that
cometary nuclei must have exceedingly
black, non-reflective surfaces, a property
we predicted only weeks before the Giotto
encounter.
The Giotto pictures showed a few places
where the nucleus could be seen through
"holes" in the dust halo, and the surface
showed up as amazingly black Giotto in¬
vestigators described it as being "blacker
than the blackest coal". This was indeed a
triumph for the organic model.
More triumphs were to follow. Giotto's
particle impact analyser was equipped to
determine the chemical make-up of the
cometary dust particles by measuring the
distribution of the masses of atoms within
them. J. Kissel, the principal investigator
on this experiment, reported on 17 March
that analysis of one per cent of the total data
record indicated that the dust was made up .
of the elements carbon, oxygen, nitrogen
and hydrogen with very much smaller
amounts of other chemical elements. Two
logical possibilities follow from this data.
These atoms can exist in the form of volatile
ices such as water, carbon dioxide and
ammonia together with simple hydrocar¬
bons such as methane, or they could occur
in the form of highly stable organic
polymers. Since, in other experiments, the
temperature of these particles was mea¬
sured at 125 degrees Celsius, well above the
boiling points of ices and simple hydrocar¬
bons, it follows that the cometary particles
could only be made of organic polymers.
Both Vega 2 and Giotto experiments indi¬
cated that hydrogen atoms, hydroxyl radic¬
als and water molecules were also released
quite liberally from the comet. However,
the amounts of these substances were not
inconsistent with the water associated with
living cells (60 per cent by volume of such
cells is water). Significantly there was no
evidence whatever for a halo of icy particles
around the nucleus which is predicted by
the widely accepted "dirty snowball" com¬
etary theory first propounded by US astro¬
nomer Fred Whipple.
On the morning of 30 June 1908, a huge
aerial explosion with an energy equivalent
to that of 10 to 15 megatons of TNT devas¬
tated some 2,000 square kilometres of
pine forest (left) near the Tunguska River
In central Siberia. The explosion Is
thought to have been caused by a comet,
ora fragment ofa comet, colliding with the
Earth. An object such as this would have
disintegrated in the Earth's atmosphere
creating a fireball and a powerful blast
wave but no crater.
Scarcely two weeks after the Giotto ren¬
dezvous an important observation of the
comet in the infra-red region of the spec¬
trum was made by astronomers Dayal
Wickramasinghe and David Allen, using
the 154-inch Anglo-Australian telescope at
Siding Springs, New South Wales. They
discovered remarkably strong signals due to
emission from heated organic dust over the
wavelength range from 2 to 4 micrometres.
Basic structures of organic molecules in¬
volving linkages between carbon and hyd¬
rogen atoms (CH bonds) absorb and emit
radiation at wavelengths near 3.4 mic¬
rometres; for any assembly of complex
organic molecules such as bacterium this
absorption band is in general very broad
and takes on a highly distinctive profile.
The most remarkable fact that emerged was
that the profile of this emission from Hal¬
ley's comet matched precisely the be¬
haviour of a dried-out bacterium as mea¬
sured in the laboratory.
Although a full appraisal of the recent
observations of comet Halley cannot yet be
offered, it is already clear that a few quite
remarkable facts have emerged. The comet
is clearly not an inorganic dirty snowball as
most astronomers had previously held. It is
organic. Within a mammoth chunk of orga¬
nic matter, some 8 kilometres long and 4
kilometres wide, a large proportion of wa¬
ter molecules and traces of other materials
are also trapped. Whether one likes it or
not, the organic material of the comet
occurs predominantly in the form of parti¬
cles whose absorption properties, sizes and
densities are identical to the predictions of a
bacterial model.
Interpreted in the most conservative
possible way, the latest discoveries indicate
at the very least that comets could have
provided the raw materials, the organic
building blocks from which life emerged on
the Earth. More realistically, in my view,
the data point in a decisive way to life in the
form of bacteria and viruses being con¬
tained in comets and brought by them to the
Earth.
NALIN CHANDRA WICKRAMASINGHE is pro¬
fessor of applied matriematics and astronomy at
University College, Cardiff, Wales, and Director
of the Institute of Fundamental Studies, Sri
Lanka. In 1962, while at Cambridge University,
Professor Wickramasinghe, who is ofSri Lankan
origin, was awarded the Powell Prize for English
poetry. His views on the space origins of terrest¬
rial life are fully developed in two books, Space
Travellers: the Bringers of Life and Evolution
from Space, of which he is the co-author with Sir
Fred Hoyle.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The hand of man
by Stephen Boyden and Malcolm Hadley
THE human species evolved late, very
late, in the history of our planet; but
during man's short time on Earth,
his hand has wrought pervasive change in
air, water and soils, in other living
creatures, in the whole tightly connected
system of interacting parts of which the
environment consists and this in but the
last instant of geological time.
The history of man's changing rela¬
tionship with his habitat in terms of both
the impact of human society on the natural
environment and the conditions of life of
human beings can, at the risk of over¬
simplification, be divided into four distinct
but overlapping ecological phases: the
Primeval Phase, the Early Farming Phase,
the Early Urban Phase and, finally, the
Modern Industrial Phase.
During the Primeval Phase sometimes
also called the pre-domestic or hunter-
gatherer phase human populations prob¬
ably differed little from those of other
omnivorous mammals in the extent and na¬
ture of their interaction with the ecosystems
of which they were a part. As hunter-
gatherers they had their natural place in the
food cycle, deriving their energy, in chemi¬
cal form, from natural foodstuffs of animal
and plant origin. They in turn provided food
for other predators and their remains were
returned to the soil through the processes of
decomposition. The amount of energy used
by an early hominid group in its natural
habitat would have been more or less
equivalent to the energy value of the food¬
stuffs consumed by members of the group.
In short, our ancestors fitted into their en¬
vironment in much the same way as any
other animal species.
Then, probably about half a million years
ago, in the volcanic lands of the East Afri¬
can rift valleys, man began to use fire,
deliberately and regularly, both for protec¬
tion and as a means of obtaining and cook¬
ing food. Fire was used to drive game out of
the undergrowth and to attract animals to
the fresh herbaceous growth that sprang up
on ground cleared by fire.
This was a highly significant development
with considerable ecological impact. Forest
and grass fires became much more frequent
events, bringing about important changes in
the plant cover of certain areas of the
Earth's surface. Suddenly, human societies
were using considerably more energy than
previously, since the flow of "somatic"
energy (the energy that flows through the
bodies of human beings for metabolism,
physical work and growth) was now sup¬
plemented by "extra-somatic" energy
(energy such as that derived from fuel,
which does not flow through living orga¬
nisms).
The use of fire thus brought about a
qualitative change in the relationship be¬
tween the human species and its environ¬
ment. The ecological consequences were
restricted to the destructive effects of fire
itself, and the chemical products of the
combustion of wood (mainly carbon diox
ide) were easily absorbed into the system as
a whole with negligible repercussions.
Nevertheless, the use of fire is an early and
clear example of man's potential as a modi¬
fier of the environment. Man had already
become a significant ecological force, and
human groups no longer fitted into their
local ecosystems in quite the same way as
other animals.
In addition to fire, the most significant
ecological effect of man on the environment
during the primeval phase was probably the
spread of the human species itself. Man
appears to have roamed the open African
savannah until about one million years ago,
when he fanned out into a great variety of
other habitatsarid steppes, high altitude
grasslands (in Ethiopia) and forest grass¬
lands. Following these initial excursions,
man ventured further out into a wide range
of different climatic and ecological settings
in all five continents of the world. ^
Rock painting dating from about 2000 BC,
from the Rusape area of Zimbabwe. The
way of life represented is that of Late
Stone Age hunters. Bushmen were still
making paintings like this in the 19th cen¬
tury, but some of the surviving examples
mayhave been the workofsouthern Bantu
peoples.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Engraving by the Swiss artist Aloys Fell-
mann (1855-1892) depicts men at work in a
typical 19th-century factory at a time when
the industrial revolution was gathering
momentum in Europe.
The Early Farming Phase began , in some
regions of the world, about 12,000 years
ago. With the domestication of animals and
plants, for the first time in the story of the
Earth, a living creature came, quite con¬
sciously and deliberately, to manipulate the
biological processes of nature for his own
purposes.
As domestication spread and farming
techniques advanced, the total impact of
human society on the environment in- .
creased significantly. The face of the Earth
was beginning to be changed by the hand of
man, to the extent that, in the northern
hemisphere, vast areas of forest land dis¬
appeared, to be replaced in some instances
by farming land and in others by less lux¬
uriant and more open vegetation. In some
cases, man's agricultural activities triggered
massive erosion. In eastern Fiji, for exam¬
ple, where man arrived some 3,000 years
ago, at least 50 centimetres of soil was lost in
a period of 150 years, from between 1,900
and 1,750 years ago.
Among other important implications of
farming practices was the introduction of
monoculture food crops, on which many
populations came to be almost entirely de¬
pendent for sustenance. This development
clearly had some practical advantages, but
it also involved serious risk, since, if the
monoculture crop failed for any reason,
then widespread starvation was virtually
inevitable.
One further consequence of mankind's
deliberate manipulation of biotic processes
is worthy of mention. Selective breeding of
animals and cultivation of plants for desir¬
able qualities relating to food production
brought into existence a range of forms of
life which would otherwise never have seen
the light of day.
Fire, of course, remained in use during
this second ecological phase and it came to
play an important role in the manufacture
of metal implements. With the invention of
such devices as watermills, windmills and
sailing ships, extra-somatic energy came to
be used for performing work of various
kinds. Compared with what was to happen
later, however, the ecological impact of
these machines was relatively slight, being
restricted mainly to the role that ships
played in the migratory movements of the
human species, the geographical spread of
technologies and the re-distribution of
some animal and plant species.
Human groups became much less no¬
madic than in the primeval phase, although
the length of time they remained in one
. place depended to some extent on the kind
of farming they practised. The new lifestyle
had significant consequences for the inter¬
relationships between human populations
and microbial and other parasites and
pathogens. In some areas, for example,
malaria and schistosomiasis became impor¬
tant causes of ill-health and death, partly
counteracting the reduced mortality result¬
ing from the protection which the new living
conditions gave against some of the hazards
of life experienced in the primeval phase.
Despite all the changes that agriculture
produced, the early farming phase shared
two important ecological characteristics
with the primeval phase which are not fea¬
tures of modern societies. First, the rate of
use of extra-somatic energy (mainly fire)
paralleled the rate of increase in the human
population. Second, man's activities did not
interfere significantly with the natural
biogeochemical cycles of the biosphere,
such as the carbon, nitrogen and phosphor¬
us cycles.
The Early Urban Phase started about
5,000 years ago, with the establishment of
the first cities in Mesopotamia and, not long
after, in China and India. These early cities
ushered in the third ecological phase of
human existence, which was marked by a
series of fundamental changes affecting the
organization of human society and the life
experience of its members. Some, but not
all, of these changes have persisted and
remain features of many urban settlements
in the modern world.
The most obvious changes were simply
the huge increase in the number of people
gathered together in one place and the fact
that the majority of their inhabitants were
not directly involved in such subsistence
activities as farming, fishing and hunting.
The urban populations were supported by
food surpluses produced by nearby farmers
who lived and worked beyond the city walls.
Because many urban populations came to
rely for their sustenance on a single staple
food, such as rice, maize, a cereal grain or
potatoes, there was a narrowing of the
range of foods consumed by individuals.
Specific deficiency diseases, including rick¬
ets, scurvy, beri-beri and pellagra, were
common in different parts of the world.
There was a constant threat and repeated
occurrence of famine, since urban popula¬
tions did not have a wide range of alterna¬
tive sources of food to turn to when one
supply failed.
Increased population density had a
marked effect on the interrelations between
human populations and potential parasitic
or pathogenic organisms. Pestilence be¬
came one of the major facts of life. Typhus,
cholera, typhoid, the plague, smallpox,
malaria, infant diarrhoea and many other
infectious diseases were a constant cause of
fear and alarm and were among the main
causes of death.
One of the most significant biosocial de¬
velopments which accompanied early urba¬
nization was the advent of job specializa¬
tion. Some degree of specialization existed
in the early farming and even in the hunter-
gatherer societies, but, apart from the sex-
based division of labour, most people were
jacks-of-all-trades. It was during the early
urban phase that specialization really came
into its own.
Part of the ecological importance of this
development lies in the fact that, for the
first time in human history, different groups
within a single society experienced quite
different conditions of life. Job specializa¬
tion led in turn to a reinforcement of the
tendency of human societies to establish
hierarchies. Instead of being relatively
spontaneous, transient and dependent
upon the nature of the task in hand, the
hierarchical structure of society became
much more rigid, more extreme and more
permanent. It frequently came to be deter¬
mined by heredity rather than by common
consent based on ability and personality.
Urbanization also introduced entirely
new concepts of ownership. In primeval
times, an individual "owned" only those
possessions he had made himself and no
more than could be easily carried when he
moved from one camp site to another. In
the early farming phase, animals, crops and
stored grain became the objects of own¬
ership, but, at least in the early stages, this
was usually communal ownership. In early
cities, individual and family ownership be-
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Highway intersection at Villefranche, near
Lyon, France a typical construction of
our modern, energy-hungry, industrial
society.
came very important and has remained so
ever since in many parts of the world.
As in the preceding phases, the natural
biogeochemical cycles were still intact, and
the rate of energy use by society still par¬
alleled changes in population size. The bio¬
sphere as a whole and most of the eco¬
systems to which human populations be¬
longed were, despite some short-term fluc¬
tuations, still essentially in a state of dyna¬
mic equilibrium. The existence of cities did
not, of course, mean an end to self-suffi¬
cient subsistence agricultural societies,
which indeed continue to exist in some
areas of the world today.
Until very late in this period, few cities
contained many more than 100,000 inhabi¬
tants. One notable exception was Rome,
which, around the time of Jesus Christ, had
a population of about one million.
However, although cities have until very
recently contained only a very small percen¬
tage of the total human population, they
have had an ecological impact out of all
proportion to the number of people living in
them.
The Modern Industrial or Technological
Phase began with the so-called industrial
revolution. This industrial transition, as we
prefer to call it, started in Europe and in
North America some 150 to 200 years ago
and is still taking place in many parts of the
world. Though it began only seven or eight
generations ago, this phase has had an im¬
pact on the Earth and its workings quite
disproportionate to its duration. Its ecolo¬
gical characteristics are not shared with any
of the preceding phases of human existence.
This is most strikingly illustrated by the
present situation regarding population,
energy and the biogeochemical cycles.
While the early farming and early urban
stages provided protection from some of the
causes of death that characterized the
primeval stage, they were associated with
new causes of mortality in the form of mal¬
nutrition and pestilence. In the modern in¬
dustrial phase, greatly improved knowledge
of the nutritional requirements of our spe¬
cies, and new practices in public health and
medicine, including the pharmaceutical re¬
volution, have resulted in a remarkable
change in population dynamics. As a conse¬
quence, the human population is now
doubling at the rate of once every thirty-five
to forty years, in contrast to the overall rate
of once in 1 ,500 years during the early farm¬
ing and early urban phases.
Another outstanding feature of the mod¬
ern industrial phase, and one which deter¬
mines many of its other characteristics, has
been the massive introduction of machines
and manufacturing processes powered by
extra-somatic energy. The chief sources of
this energy have been the fossil fuels, begin¬
ning with coal, but with petroleum products
and natural gas now more important. In
some places, hydroelectric power makes a
significant contribution and nuclear power
is rapidly coming to the fore. In highly
industrialized countries like the United
States, the amount of power used on a per
capita basis is now thirty times greater than
it was prior to the industrial transition.
Thus, unlike the situation in the earlier
phases, the rate of increase in energy use in
the modern industrial phase no longer
matches the rate of increase in population,
and the ratio of extra-somatic energy used
by society is continually increasing. Global¬
ly, the amount of energy flowing through
human society is doubling about twice as
fast as the population.
In many areas the natural biogeochemic¬
al cycles are no longer intact. Interference
with the carbon and phosphorus cycles, for
example, may well give rise to very serious
ecological problems in the future. In the
case of the nitrogen cycle, vast amounts of
nitrogenous waste products of human com¬
munities, which in previous eras were re¬
turned to the soil, are now lost to rivers and
oceans, and industrial processes are dis¬
charging substantial quantities of nitrogen
oxide into the atmosphere.
A significant change of a qualitative na¬
ture has been the synthesis, often in very
large amounts, of thousands of new chemi¬
cal compounds, many of which have potent
effects in biotic systems. Vast quantities of
these synthetic chemical substances are
finding their way into the oceans, the soil
and the atmosphere and, of course, into
living organisms.
Complexity and unpredictability are two
other characteristics of the present phase of
human existence. Modern technology and
the economic web of interdependence of
countries are making problems of land use
and resource management much more com¬
plex than they were even a generation ago.
Machines are now available, for example,
for clearing large areas of forest in a very
short space of time. With modern com¬
munications technology, a decision taken
now in a financial centre in a temperate
zone can lead to the felling, within a week,
of a tropical forest tree 10,000 kilometres
away which has taken one hundred years to
grow.
If certain widely accepted predictions
about future increases in the level of energy
use turn out to be correct, by the year 2050
mankind will be using about as much energy
as is used by all other animals and plants put
together. One does not have to be a special¬
ist to see that this kind of growth in energy
use, and the concomitant increase in the use
of resources and the outpouring of wastes,
cannot go on indefinitely.
Opinions differ as to how much longer
the biosphere is likely to be able to tolerate
the ever-increasing load which human soci¬
ety is placing on it. There are some who
believe that mankind is incapable of bring¬
ing under control the accelerating processes
which threaten the collapse of the biosphere
and civilization and that the collapse of the
system will be total and will involve the
extinction of the human species. Others are
more optimistic, believing that man, with
his great ingenuity, will succeed in reaching
a new ecological equilibrium before it is too
late.
STEPHEN BOYDEN, ofAustralia, is a specialist
at the Centre for Resource and Environment
Studies, Australian National University, Canber¬
ra, and leader of the integrative research study
on the ecology of Hong Kong undertaken within
the framework of Unesco's Man and the Bio¬
sphere (MAB) Programme. The theme of this
article is treated in greater depth in a book to be
published later this year.
MALCOLM HADLEY is a staff member of Un¬
esco's Division of Ecological Sciences. A zoolo¬
gist, he is responsible for the co-ordination of
activities in the humid tropics within Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
1986: Year of Peace/ 7
Over 400 representatives of 1 1 5 interna¬
tional non-governmental organizations
and 71 national organizations from 36
countries attended "Together for
Peace", a Conference held in Geneva
from 20 to 24 January 1986 to mark the
International Year of Peace. Topics dis¬
cussed at the Conference, held under
the auspices of the Board of the Confer¬
ence of Non-Governmental Organiza¬
tions in Consultative Status with the
Economic and Social Council of the Un¬
ited Nations, included questions of dis¬
armament, development, social prog¬
ress, justice, human rights, satisfaction
of basic human needs, and preparation
of societies for life in peace. At the end
of the Conference, the following appeal
was adopted by acclamation.
We appeal to all people of the world to join in a
common pursuit of peace.
With just a decade and a half for this century
to come to a close, we are convinced of the
duty and obligation of all people to make
concerted efforts to usher in a world of peace
as the new century opens. We are convinced
that it can be done, that the present danger¬
ous trends in world affairs can be stopped and
reversed. We see signs of hope in the new
spirit of dialogue and openness among lead¬
ers of nations and in the determination of the
people to attain peace.
We do not have to recount the threats to
peace. The race towards nuclear catastrophe
is keeping up its momentum. As if the earth
and the oceans can no longer bear the weight
of weapons outer space is explored for sta¬
tioning of arms. Hundreds are killed every day
by non-nuclear weapons. Hunger takes its
daily toll of thousands. Millions are deprived of
basic human needs and fundamental human
rights. Millions still groan under domination
and exploitation. Apartheid continues, de¬
nying justice, destroying people and destabi¬
lizing nations.
We appeal therefore to work together for a
world of peace, not where war is merely
absent, not where human survival is just pos¬
sible, but where justice prevails and human
dignity is upheld.
We reiterate that the nuclear arms race
constitutes the greatest threat to peace and
survival. Our appeal therefore assumes a
special urgency in this regard. ...
As we pledge to work together for disarma¬
ment we appeal to all to join in and support
efforts for an immediate end to all nuclear
weapon tests, a comprehensive test ban
treaty, the prevention of an arms race in outer
space, elimination of chemical weapons and
all other weapons of mass destruction, and
substantial reduction in conventional
weaponry. We believe that it is possible to
implement a systematic and credible pro¬
gramme for the elimination of nuclear
weapons by the end of the century.
We believe that peace is inextricably inter¬
linked with development and social progress
and that its foundation is justice. Deprivation
and disparity are threats to peace. We there¬
fore call for a strategic development initiative
for a new international economic order that
ensures just economic relations between and
within nations. We further appeal for genuine
respect of the rights of people to decide their
own destiny, their rights to self-determination
and interdependent development, non-in¬
terference in their internal affairs, in conditions
of security and social progress.
We emphasize that the exercise of human
rights and freedoms is an essential element of
peace. Violations of them are a major cause of
armed conflicts. The fuller the rights that every
person enjoys in society, the more stable that
society will be; the fullerthe implementation of
human rights globally, the more stable inter¬
national relations will be. ...
We recognize that peace is an essential
requirement for the satisfaction of basic hu¬
man needs such as food, shelter, health, edu¬
cation, labour and environment. As we com¬
mend recent co-operative actions across con¬
tinents to meet emergency needs for food, we
appeal for more systematic and concerted
attempts to prevent death by starvation and
for the adoption of long-term policies national¬
ly and internationally to ensure food for all.
We call for joint actions to promote substan¬
tial reduction of military expenditures with a
view to rectifying the current distortion in the
use of resources. We agree that every gun
that is made, every warship launched, every
rocket fired, signifies in the final sense a theft
from those who hunger and are not fed, those
who are cold and are not clothed.
Recognizing the importance of preparation
of societies for life in peace we call for a new
orientation in education, science, culture, reli¬
gion and mass media towards peace-making.
The resources available in these areas can
be more constructively utilized for peace. ...
Nations must seek peace together. We can
only create a common future if we can cope
with the common crisis we face and build
peace on the basis of the concept of common
security. We appeal for a greater commitment
to international co-operation for which the uni¬
versal instrument is the United Nations. We
pledge our continued support to the United
Nations and its agencies. ...
We realize that the odds are tremendous.
But we are confident that the determination of
the people to achieve peace will prevail. We
have optimism and hope because we are
together for peace. It is in that spirit that we
renew our commitment to peace and invite
you all, all peoples of the world, to join in the
challenging tasks ahead.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office :
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs. 2 years (valid only in France):
144 French trancs. Binder for a year's issues : 56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER ¡s published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by : Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans; (2) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (30 N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief : Olga Rodel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors :
English : Roy Malkin
French : Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish : Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian : Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic : Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille : Frederick Potter
Research : Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations : Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion : Fernando Ainsa
Special projects : Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-
Chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German : Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese : Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian : Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi : Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil : M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew : Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian :
Dutch : Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese : Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish : Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu : Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan : Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian : Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean : Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili : Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene :
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese : Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian : Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek : Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala : S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish : Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish : Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque : Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai : Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
38 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Juillet 1986 -
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de l'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.l. route d'Ëtampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
co»«P« »"/.ïe imp»« °* of se*"«»1;
«öS- -fi0fsuoUence £*$} .
^b°tSeo-atnematS and* geoto&5ts.
studentsing totogists
p\otaUon p* teaChers.
dusive^esnS h ttancs
D.
598 pa&cS
-$^^
ä sW ^su^1 nc t ancS
A«»*««380" , ,aV. KJu*«
«d edition (USA Dclby *
Havdbound ^ ( 190 u
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collmgwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications : Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P 0. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals : Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O, Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent : United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne. Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerald and Co., Graben 31, A-1011. Vienna.
BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box N-3138, Nassau. BAHRAIN.
The Arabian Agencies and Distributing Co.. AI Mutanabi St.. P.O. Box 156,
Manama. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq Build¬
ing, 1 , R.K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the
West Indies Bookshop. Cave Hill Campus, P O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only : N V. Handelmaatschappij
Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18. 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition and
general Unesco publications agent : Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Boo* Centre, P.O.
Box 91. Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552 Merchant
Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd.. 2182 St. Catherine
St. West, Montreal, Qué. H3H 1M7. CHINA. China National Publications
Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P O. Box 1 722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve Smeckach
30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1
Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only : Alfa Verlag. -Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG. Tids-
sknftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
St., Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Hel¬
sinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01 640 Vantaa 64.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP
12598-48 GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Post¬
fach 140, 71 0 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G. D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German, English. French
and Spanish editions) : Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb.
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd..
P.O. Box 1 95, Accra; Ghana Book Supptiers Ud., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana. Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bcûkshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón. GREAT
BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK)
Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat St.. Aberdeen. Swindon
Book Co., 13-15, LockRd., Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services,
Publication Centre. Baskerville House. 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-
Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjórn
Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman
Ltd., Kamam Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave.,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh.
Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001;
3-5-020 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-depots : Oxford Book and Sta¬
tionery Co., 1 7 Park St.. Calcutta 7001 6; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publica¬
tion Unit, Ministry ol Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra
Prasad Rd.. New Delhi, 1 10001 . INDONESIA, Bhratara Publishers and Book¬
sellers. 29 Jl. Oto Iskandardinata 111, Jakarta; Indira P.T.. Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusal. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co.. 28 Vessal Shirazi St., Enghélab Ave.. P O. Box 314/1486, Teheran;
Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, 1 1 88 Englab Ave . Rostam Give Building, Zip
Code 13158. P.O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzies Bookshop,
AI Rashid St., Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Rd., Walkinstown, Dublin 12 ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd . Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librena
Commissionaria Sansoni, S p A ), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552,
50121 Florence. JAMAICA. Sangster's Bookstores Ltd.. P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston: University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kings¬
ton. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku,
Tokyo 1 1 3. KENYA. East African Publishing House, P O. Box 30571 . Nairobi;
Africa Book Services Ltd.. Quran House, Mfangano St., P.O. Box 45245,
Nairobi KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central
64. Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait:(or the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN. Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5-9494 Schaan. LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. Agency lor Development of Publication and Distribu¬
tion. P.O. Box 34-35. Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22.
Grande-Rue. Luxembourg MALAWI. Malawi Book Service, Head Office, P.O.
Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-opera¬
tive Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St..
Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd , 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha
Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Keesing Boeken B.V.,
Joan Muyskenweg, 22, Poslbus 1118. 1000 BC Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V.. P.O. Box 200. Willem-
stad. Curaçao, N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirnie, Wellington; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christ-
church; Alma St.. P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Princes St.. P.O. Box 1104,
Dunedin NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of He; The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P.O. 286: The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop ol Zana
NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O B. 1 177 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen
A/S; Subscription and Trade Book Service. POB. 6125 Etterstad. Oslo 6:
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindern, Oslo
3. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam. P.O Box No.
729. Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store, Inc., 701. Rizal Ave.. Manila
D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kuttury 1 Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-
Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiesae No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
National Bookshop. P.O. Box 48, Mahé. New Service Ltd . Kmgsgate House.
P.O. Box 131, Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops. Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal Pub¬
lications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Bookshop and General, P.O.
Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single
copies) only: Central News Agency, P O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI
LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chiftampalam Gardiner Mawata,
P.OB. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fntzes Kungel, Hovbokhan-
del, Regen ngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier : Svenska FN Forbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stock¬
holm; Wennergren-Williams, Box 30004-S-104. 25 Stockholm: Esselte Tids-
knftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20 Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zürich;
Líbrame Payot, Rue Grenus 6. 1211, Geneva 1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236; Librairies
Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne. Vevey, Montreux. Neuchätel and
Zurich. TANZANIA. Dar-es- Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd .40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya
Sn, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9. Rajdamnern Ave.,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company. 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD
AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 1 8 Alexandra St.. St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1 . TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S-. Istiklâl Caddesi. No 469. Posta
Kutusu 21 9, Beyoglu, Istanbul UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 7145.
Kampala UNITED KINGDOM. H.M Stationery Office, H M S.O.. P.O. Box
276. London SWS 5DT, and Govt Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; lor scientific maps only : McCarta Ltd., 122
King's Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub. 205 East
42nd St.. New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books and periodicals : P.O. Box
1 222, Ann Arbor, Ml 481 06 USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga. Ul. Dimitro-
va 39, Moskva 1 13095. YEMEN. 14th October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227.
Aden. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2. Lubljana; Nolit. Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 67 Union Ave.. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
z?z
The Earth onfire
(¡lowing streams ofmolten lava pourfrom the
Hawaiian volcano Mauna Loa during an eruption in l'/H4.
(See article page 27}.
Prow Kraitt % E«<*xsf. P«n%
]]>
</page>
</document>
