<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069916eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
N°4-5
1954
(7th year)
Price : I/- (U. K.)
50. francs (France)
YOUTH IN
NEW JAPAN
How much have they changed?
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
* 4**^ #
^ *» w v^
&L^PK
xx\\v^m\\\\\\\XN
* * v
ilfcadNí»
.#£#
KABUKI
The time-honoured stage
art ofJapan. (Seepage 34)
.'T " x
F
#
.>*;
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
NUMBER 4-5 -1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
12 WITHOUT THE CHRYSANTHEMUM
AND THE SWORD
An important Unesco enquiry on
post-war Japanese youth
14 EYES ON THE OUTSIDE WORLD
The good and the bad in
'¡¡in'the foreigner
21 THE IMPERIAL WALLS ARE DOWN
Youth views the Emperor
24 DILEMMA IN THE FAMILY
Respect and obedience or a
clean break with tradition ?
26 A TOKYO TEEN-AGER'S DAY
A photo story
28 A KYOTO STUDENT'S PROFILE
A photo story
OTHER ARTICLES AND FEATURES
3 EDITORIAL
Unesco advocates no one particular form of culture
4 CANCER & WHAT SCIENCE KNOWS ABOUT IT
By François Le Lionnais
9 THE SEA, THE DESERT & THE JUNGLE
Focus point of international research
10 UNESCO TRAVELLERS' CHEQUES
A new aid to travel for
students and scholars
36 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
37 ALMERÍA
A forgotten Spanish province " wakes up "
By Tena Artigas
38 «EL DORADO* IN COLOMBIA
Art worth its weight in gold
40 WORLD WITHOUT END
A Unesco film seen by 250 million people
46 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science and culture
48 BITING THE HAND THAT FEEDS US
Let's protect nature not waste it
By Gerald Wendt
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
' Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France.
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler.
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: José De Benito
Individual articles not copyrighted maybe reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-; $ I.SO or 300 French (rs.
MC. 54.1 81. A.
\}NESCÖ\ UNESCO COURIER. N'" 4-5. 1954
This month's theme
This young Japanese school-girl is growing
up in a changing Japan. Whether the
changes are more than just skin-deep Is
revealed by an important Unesco enquiry
on the ideas and attitudes of Japanese post¬
war youth. (See page 1 2.)
Not long ago we received a letter from a schoolteacher in
Bordeaux, France, who said he hesitated to renew his
subscription to the Courier. (He ultimately did though).
His criticism, curiously enough, was aimed not at our ma¬
gazine at all in fact he said that "no issue of the Courier
is ever without interest and your magazine is extremely useful in
my classes." Instead he voiced objection to what he personally
thought was a preference Unesco, as an organization, gave to one
type of culture as opposed to another.
Another reader in a recent letter attacked Unesco for not giving
direct support to one particular religion and expressed suspicion
that Unesco maintained a philosophy of atheism.
We believe we can give no better answer than to quote parts
of a talk delivered in Rome last November by Unesco's Director-
General himself, Dr. Luther Evans. Here is what Dr. Evans said :
"'Through the medium of international collaboration Unesco has
always endeavoured to improve the conditions whereby the liberty
of the mind can assert itself and bear fruit. There is not, and
there cannot be, any such thing as a "Unesco culture". Unesco does
not preach any particular form of culture; its task is to place in
the hands of all who need them better and more numerous tools
for carrying on their work. The tools in this case are more
extensive information, more frequent contacts with representatives
of other intellectual groups, a deeper knowledge of the art and
thought of other peoples, and sometimes the assistance of experts
in carrying out an enterprise the success of which depends upon
a common effort.
"Unesco fosters contacts between civilizations and cultures. Its
ambition is to be universal, in the sense of remaining open to all
manifestations of the human intellect, but not in the sense of
advocating a single civilization, a privileged culture or, what would
be still worse, the predominance of one over all the rest. If it
were to act in any other way, it would destroy what it has been
created to defend.
"Unesco has been suspected, and at times even accused, of
atheism. The truth is that all religions, all creeds and all philo¬
sophies are represented among our Member States. But it is not
for Unesco, in the fields where it operates, to choose a particular
dogma or system for acceptance or rejection. Here again its
universal character does not imply a desire for uniformity, but a
readiness to welcome all and to co-operate with all.
"When Unesco tries to improve educational conditions by faci¬
litating the exchange of information, by a study of practical
methods, or by experimenting with the use of audio-visual aids,
the results of its technical work are available for religious as much
as for secular purposes. When Unesco plans, in common with
Member States, ways and means of extending free and compul¬
sory education or of raising the school leaving age, it is without
prejudice to the intrinsic content of school curricula, which may
or may not, depending upon the attitude of the national autho¬
rities, include instruction in religious matters. When it suggests
that the syllabus should include instruction on Human Rights,
the United Nations and other international institutions
something that all Member States have shown that they desire,
by the mere fact of their accession to Unesco and their participa¬
tion at the General Conference it Is fully aware that these
subjects alone do not constitute the whole education of man.
"The Organization has a technical and limited part to play;
seen from this angle, the question of atheism does not arise. Not
only would it be out of place in Unesco's particular field of activity,
but it would soon render impossible any co-operation between
Member States^ representing as they do the whole gamut of human
thought and aspirations.
"Within these limits, the services which it has rendered, and still
more those which it will render in future, are considerable. Just
as one proves the power of movement by walking, so international
co-operation in the intellectual sphere gives proof of its usefulness
by the results it achieves."
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
RED BLOOD CELL. This is a normal human red blood corpuscle
photographed with an electronic microscope and magnified
32,000 times. To try to understand the structure of cancer cells
scientists are today carefully studying all types of cell life. It is
a slow and difficult job of penetrating the secrets of a world that
is still full of mystery.
CHICKEN EMBRYOS. Scientist at French Institute of
Cancer Research injects chicken embryo with a special cancer
yirus and will study results. In many parts of the world
today the resources and ingenuity of research workers are¿¡
being applied through varying techniques in an effort to
vanquish this malady one day.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. M" 4-5. 1954
science knows about it today
by François Le Lionnais
A proposal that Unesco should Initiate interna¬
tional action in the struggle against cancer in
co-operation with the World Health Organiza¬
tion was made by Unesco's Executive Board
at a meeting in Paris last April. The Unesco
General Conference, which meets in November, will
be asked to approve a project for international co¬
operation in biological, physical and chemical research
aimed at fighting cancer. The proposal was made by
Professor Laugier who is a member of the Unesco
Executive Board and President of the French Commis¬
sion for Technical and Scientific Research. Professor
Laugier said that international institutions should try
to remedy the dispersion of effort of research workers
all over the world. The Courier has asked M. François
Le Lionnais, President of the French Science Writers
Association to explain briefly what science knows
today about this world scourge.
CANCER is one of the major
concerns of present-day medi¬
cine. Hardly a day passes
without the publication of -articles,
often highly sensational, about the
disease. Many such articles and
even certain books have served to
mislead, a large number of people and
have actually done more harm than
good.
What are the facts about cancer?
Every living being consists of one or
of many living cells; the body of man
is composed of several thousand
millions, grouped in tissues which
form the various specialized organs.
These individual . cells are constantly
dying arid being replaced by new
cells. In the human adult, this repla¬
cement is rigorously exact one cell
forone-cell so that the total number
for an individual who is in normal good
health, hardly varies at all.
It sometimes happens, however,
that certain cells "break the law" and
begin to multiply in excess of the
body's needs. These "extra" cells
constitute a group which is called a
tumour.
A malady as old -
as humanity
AGREAT many such tumours remain
localized and cause little if any
trouble, such as warts which are
called "benign tumours". On the other
hand, as noted by Galen the Greek
physician as early as the second
century A. D., cancer is a "malignant
tumour".' The multiplication of cells
does not remain localized ; the new
cells invade nearby tissues and organs,
choking them, causing haemorrhages,
obstructing open passages, preventing
essential parts of the body from
performing their normal functions, and
finally causing their destruction. When
cells with this diabolic capacity for
multiplication enter into the blood or
lymph, they may be carried to more
remote parts of the body, where they
start new cancer colonies. This pheno¬
menon is called a metastasis. When
metastasis has already begun before
surgery takes place at the original site,
there is often a new outbreak.
The word "cancer" covers a series of
ailments having.different forms, which
may attack the skin, the glands, the
blood, etc. All the organs of the body
are susceptible, but the digestive tube
among men and the reproductive
organs of women -are most vulnerable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
One person out of ten
now dies of cancer
IN THE LABORATORY cancer cells from different animal
tissues are cultivated to permit scientists to study cell growth and
test action of various chemicals on cells. Healthy cell tissue is also
used in research to produce cancer artificially.
Cancers of the respiratory organs and
of the mouth are less frequent.
The disease appears to be as old as
humanity. Hippocrates, the "father"
of médecine, described it during the
fourth century B.C. and gave it a
name which means "crab". Still more
ancient texts from Egypt and India
also mention it. It is reasonable to
suppose that cancer was widespread in
prehistoric times, but as it attacks
flesh far more often than bone there
is little evidence of this in fossils.
It is said that cancer is increasing,
as a result of civilized modes of life,
and statistics have been -published
indicating an increase . of cancer pre¬
valence In modern countries. These
statistics are correct, but they do not
necessarily prove what is claimed.
Heart disease a
greater killer
THEY do prove three things: mo¬
dern diagnostic procedures have
improved, the average life span
has increased, and the fight against
most other maladies has been increas¬
ingly successful. Many people who
die of cancer do so because they have
lived beyond the time when, in previous
centuries, they would have been struck
down by other diseases. We - should
add that, contrary to widespread belief,
diseases of the heart and blood vessels
continue to claim more victims than
cancer, especially in the most developed
countries of the world. '
Cancer is not exclusively a human
affliction. Not only has it been noted
and studied in animals of many dif¬
ferent species, but similar phenomena
have been observed in various plants.
Microscopic examination of cancer
tissue, and research in physics, che¬
mistry and biology, have provided
of enormous value, but
these direct methods have not solved
the fundamental enigma. Research
has also turned to the indirect but
powerful weapon of statistics, in the
hope of discovering significant cor¬
relations between the affliction and
various factors which may be relevant.
Is cancer related, for example, to cli¬
mate, to diet, to various ways of life,
to age, sex or occupation? Many
studies have been undertaken to
answer such questions.
Thus far, only some conclusions are
clear. One study noted that Negroes
are relatively immune to cancer of the
skin; that stomach cancer is especially
common in Japan arid Indonesia;
that cancer of the liver is encountered
most frequently in tropical areas.
One must be very careful however in
interpreting such statistics because
countries having the same climate and
the same ways of
life sometimes pre¬
sent inexplicable
differences in the
incidence of can- .
cer cases.
At the outset of
these studies, it
was believed that
cancer chiefly
affects the most
highly developed
countries with
temperate climates
and is rare in very
cold or very warm
countries. This
belief resulted lar¬
gely from the diffi
culty in obtaining exact statistics in
under-developed countries, and it
appears now that cancer occurs in all
latitudes and afflicts all the peoples of
the earth, with a terrible indifference.
Fifty is the
dangerous age
I
T is generally agreed that about
10 to 15 % of all deaths throughout
the world are due to cancer. This
means that one out of seven to ten
people dies of cancer.
Cancer affects both sexes in about
equal proportions and may affect
individuals of any age, though its
incidence appears greatest at about
the age of 50.
Correlations have been noted bet¬
ween the frequency of cancer and
certain occupations. At the end of
the 18th Century, the English surgeon
Percival Pott described a cancer caused
by the rubbing of soot on, the skin oí
young chimney-sweeps. This is a
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
cause which is disappearing in our
time along with the occupation. A
high incidence has also been noted
among workers in various industries
who handle certain hydrocarbons, such
as tar, pitch, and some of the mineral
oils and dyes.
Cancer, houses a
superstition
THE belief that certain streets or
houses are responsible for cancer
is only a matter, of superstition.
Sometimes this belief is .based upon
unfounded rumours; sometimes there
may be many cases in a particular
place, but not more than can be
accounted for by simple coincidence.
Cancer . unhappily is so widespread
that it is not surprising to find various
victims living at the same time, in
the same house or in the same street.
What are the basic causes of cancer?
How and. why does a healthy cell
transform itself into a cancer cell? At
present, little is known in answer to
these questions. The idea that it is
due to irritation of the tissues is not
accepted by most experts. Other
theories most frequently advanced
today are (1) that cancer is the result
of a cellular upset in the embryo stage
of life which survives through the
years, (2) a virus infection, (3) the
sudden transformation of cells into a
different type which is referred to as
somatic mutation.
Scientists hope that the electronic
microscope, or even more powerful
instruments which will permit explora¬
tion of the molecules of the cell, may
soon reveal more definite information.
Though the causes of cancer are
unknown, the actual growth has come
to be better known through the use
of very short electro-magnetic waves
(ultra-violet, X-rays and gamma rays).
Ultra-violet rays, as such or in sun
light for example'' have given rise to
cancers of the skin- tissue. X-rays
and gamma rays have been responsible
- for the so-called "radiologist's cancer"
affecting doctors, handlers of radio¬
active substances, X-ray technicians,
who are repeatedly exposed to such
rays. (1) In the same category are
cancers which may be produced by'
radio-activity released by atom ex¬
plosions.
A number of chemical substances,
known as carcinogens may stimulate
the development of cancer, tar being
one of the best known. Other subs¬
tances such as the female hormone
called folliculine may play a secondary
role in stimulating its development;
still others may retard it.
In some cases, cancer may be pro¬
duced by a .virus. This has been
experimentally demonstrated with
various animals, but the role of bac¬
teria or viruses in human cancer
continues to be uncertain, though
many eminent scientists are studying
the question. There is no positive
evidence relating . cancer to repeated
minor _ burns, irritations caused by
"badly fitting dentures, etc.
No chance of
contagion
WHATEVER the origin of cancer,
one thing appears to be defi¬
nitely established. It is not
contagious. Except in. one particular
case, a sarcoma of birds, innoculation
with pulverized cancerous _ tissue has
not resulted in cancer. The question
of heredity is more complicated. It
does not appear that cancer itself is
hereditary, but it does seem likely that
a " pre-disposition toward it may be
inherited.
(1) Patients under examination or treatment
by such rays are in no danger from the short
periods of exposure prescribed by physicians.
UNESCO COURIER. N"" 4-5. 1954
It is common for cancer to begin
without any obvious symptoms. In its
first stages, ordinarily, there is no fever
and no pain, a fact which has rendered
diagnosis so difficult. Certain in¬
dications call for examination, but they
should not encourage needless fear,
because examination will often prove
that there is no need for alarm.
A
CELL FROM CHICKEN
CANCER (sarcoma) cultivated
independently and magnified
10,000 times (Left). Note the
highly complex structure of the
cell. Right, another cancer cell
of the same type magnified
26,000 times reveals myste¬
rious black dots which may hold
a clue to the cause of this parti¬
cular type of cancer in chickens.
Delay is likely
to be fatal
MONG these indications are
swellings or small painless tu-
- mours, such as warts or beauty
marks which change quickly; haemorr¬
hages, even when painless; persistent
hoarseness; chronic digestive disorder,
stubborn constipation; anaemia; loss of
weight; unusual whiteness or yellow¬
ness of the skin. One should repeat,
there is nothing in itself alarming
about such symptoms and they do not
justify a cancerphobia which can make
life miserable for those who are affect¬
ed and for their families and friends.
These are simply indications that it is
worthwhile to consult a doctor, who
will make the necessary examinations
and, if necessary, refer the matter to
a specialist or to a cancer clinic. One
of the most usual tests is a biopsy, or
microscopic examination, of a piece of
the suspected tissue. When possible,
there is also an X-ray examination of
the organs affected.
One can never act too quickly in
detecting a cancer. It is most impor¬
tant to note that a cancer discovered
at the beginning is nowadays almost
always curable. Delay, however, is
very likely to be fatal. Cancer is one;
of the rare maladies which does not
heal itself; sooner or later it is fatal if
it has not been treated in time. "
As long as the causes - of cancer
remain unknown, knowledge of its
treatment will remain incomplete.
The present strategy of
defence against the affliction
is based mainly on pre¬
ventive measures of hygiene
and cleanliness, and know¬
ledge of the symptoms to
which we must pay attention.
Until regular examinations
are compulsory, even for
those who believe they are
in good health, it is urgent
to carry on public informa¬
tion campaigns to advise the
public of the necessity for
early diagnosis.
Despite the existing gaps
in our knowledge, there are
nevertheless treatments
which are successful for
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The need to link
world-wide research
certain cancers, especially those which
are discovered early. Year after year,
these treatments become more varied
and successful. First of all there is
the surgical removal of the tumour.
This is sometimes completely success¬
ful although, in some cases, it is not
sufficient to prevent a regrowth. For
this reason, operations are sometimes
completed by irradiation treatment.
Magnetic passes
and incantations
THE Curie treatment by the use of
gamma rays emitted by radium
and various radio-active isotopes
of cobalt, phosphorus or iodine, as well
as X-ray treatments, often has decisive
results. Electro-coagulation and hor¬
mone therapy are sometimes remark¬
ably successful too. Encouraging, if
not definitive, results have recently
been obtained through chemical treat¬
ment. The latter offers very great
hopes for the future but more extensive
research is needed, substantial funds
and many highly qualified researchers.
Whatever the treatment, it can only
be carried out under the direction of
a qualified specialist. It is imperative
to reject all other treatments. This is
true not only of "'magnetic passes",
incantations, etc., but also of homoeo¬
pathic remedies and nature cures.
At present, there is no serum and no
vaccine which is in any way effective
against cancer. In cancer, more
than in any other illness, charlatan¬
ism is fatal because it delays recourse
to a qualified specialist and can trans¬
form a cancer, curable at the begin¬
ning, into an inevitably fatal illness.
In 1791, England set an example for
the World by launching a public cam¬
paign against cancer, setting up a
special service for patients in a London
hospital. Since the end of the 19th
century, the scientific offensive against
the disease has enormously expanded.
Today, all advanced countries have
established treatment centres and
scientific institutes. , Development of
these national organizations led natur¬
ally to concerted international action
and the creation in 1933 of the Inter¬
national Union against Cancer. . The
Union, with headquarters in Paris, has
42 national affiliates and publishes a
quarterly bulletin in six languages.
Its sixth International Cancer Congress
will be held at Sao-Paulo, Brazil, in
July of this year.
This is the framework in which in¬
ternational action against cancer was
discussed at the recent Unesco meeting. .
Such action would not be a duplica¬
tion of the work being done by exist¬
ing national and international bodies,
who are building new hospitals and
cancer clinics, launching extensive
education campaigns for cancer pre¬
vention and detection. The proved
methods of treatment must also be
generally applied and preventive
measures more widely encouraged.
From mathematics
. to biochemistry
BUT all this is still not enough.
Only scientific research is likely
to strike the disease at its roots
and finally vanquish it.
But national and international
research today is still operating in far
from perfect conditions. Funds are
limited, research work is not suffi-
CANCER CELLS ENTERING the blood may be
carried to remote parts of the body and start new
cancer colonies. Here scientists have magnified a
drop of healthy human blood 12,250 times with
electronic microscope. It is hoped that with the
electronic microscope, capable of magnifying matter
ciently co-ordinated, and widely differ¬
ing sciences must be mobilized in this
highly complex battle. These range
from, the most abstract forms of ma¬
thematics to exacting kinds of cell
studies, from physics to chemistry and
from biophysics to biochemistry.
One example of this interplay of the
different branches of science is the
research into carcinogens (cancer sti¬
mulating substances) which has made
much progress in recent years. Cer¬
tain chemicals that occur in tars are
able to produce cancer, because of the
nature of electron distribution within
ALL CELLS MULTIPLY by splitting
into two. These remarkable photographs
show three successive stages of a healthy
living cell becoming two cells. Left, cell
has taken a ball shape and chromosomes,
carriers of heredity, are grouped in middle.
Centre photo shows chromosomes sepa¬
rated in two groups and cell pinching at the
waist. Right, cell separates into two,
each with new. nucleus of chromosomes.
Bottom right another cell begins to split.
' (Photos M. Chèvremont, Institute of Histo¬
logy, University of Liège.)
+r*f,
#*>* - 'V
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N"" 4-5. 1954
up to 300,000 times and other even more potent
instruments, science may obtain more precise infor¬
mation on the structure of cancer cells and the cause
of cancer itself. (This photo and those on four
previous pages are published by permission of the
French Institute of Cancer Research at Villejuif.)
their molecules.- The role of these
electrons was established by making
use of a theory of pure physicswave-
mechanics which itself requires the
use of higher mathematics.
This inter-dependence of the many
forms of science and the need for a
great increase in the number of spe¬
cialists and in the means at their dis¬
posal is a problem transcending na¬
tional frontiers and calls for action on
a similar scale.
The 20th century ought to be the
century of man's victory over cancer.
The sea, the desert and the jungle
Focus of international research
> »
np
Il \
.
THE extension of human life
and civilization over the
earth is limited by large
unproductive and uninhabitable
areas of desert, of jungle and of
the sea. They have long been
mapped and explored; lines of
communication have been laid
across them; explorers have des¬
cribed them well. But they remain
essentially as obstacles to man, not
as assets, though each of them is
rich in unused resources.
To study those .resources and to
make them useful is a large prob¬
lem in research which becomes
more urgent as the population of
the earth increases. It cannot be
solved by any single nation. The
deserts and the jungle do not
respect national boundaries but,
like the sea, touch the vital
interests of many lands: To con¬
trol the jungle, to water and
fertilize the desert and to develop
marine life for human food are
now necessities for they are
activities which would benefit a
large section of mankind. To
make this possible requires an
international research programme.
Such research has been one of
the objectives of Unesco since its
inception, although Unesco is best
known for its educational work. It
is true that the conditions of
human life can be greatly improv¬
ed by the spread of present
knowledge and of practices which
are well established in some
countries. But there are many
fields in which the entire sum of
human knowledge is inadequate
and where more knowledge must
be gained by research for the
benefit of all.
Using the sun's energy
Some of these problems, like the
direct utilization of the sun's
energy and the understanding
of the weather, are world-wide.
Others are primarily of regional
interest. Thus, for instance,
Unesco was responsible for the
organization of the European
Council for Nuclear Research
which will open new opportunities
for the study of this great new
field of science to the students
and scientists of Europe, by
combining the resources of the
European countries to establish
a research laboratory at Geneva
which would inherently be too
costly for any one of them.
Unesco has also sponsored the
organization of an International
Computation Centre to be located
in Rome which will make available
to the scientists of all the world
the most modern electronic equip¬
ment for complicated mathematic¬
al calculations which are vital to
the solution of many problems.
These are typical Unesco
research projects, one of world
importance, the other regional.
The studies of the sea, the desert
and the jungle have progressed
more slowly. One reason is that
they involve many nations scatter¬
ed widely over the earth and not
a single compact region.
Unesco's Advisory Committee on
the Problems of the Arid Zones,
for instance, includes experts from
Peru, Mexico, India, Turkey, Aus¬
tralia, U. S., Syria, England and
France. The Committee covers
the sciences of meteorology
geology, hydrology, plant ecology,
soil science, agricultural engineer¬
ing and zoology.
The ocean's riches
Thus the great problems of the
deserts are jointly attacked
and the results are pooled for
the benefit of all. Slowly but cer¬
tainly the result will be the impro¬
vement of agricultural and even
industrial conditions in the arid
regions and the utilization of sun¬
shine, of mineral resources and of
enhanced arid-zone vegetation. It
may be some time before the desert
"blooms" or can support a large
population but definite improve¬
ments are already a reality.
A similar study is now being
organized for the jungle areas,
technically known as the "humid
tropical zones", where vegetation
of all sorts is ample but where its
control for prosperous and healthy
human life has been difficult. The
conquest of the jungle will not be
effected by explorers but by
scientific research.
Even more important, especially
to the populous nations of the
Orient, is a proposed study of the
resources of the ocean. There Is
far more life and food In the sea
than on the land yet it provides
only a small fraction of man's
food. The cultivation of sea
plants and the collection of fish
and other sea animals for food
could undoubtedly be greatly
increased if the exact conditions
of life in the sea were better
understood, especially in their
relation to adjoining land areas.
At Manila last November,
scientists from the Indo-Pacific "
nations met with officers of
Unesco and of the U. N. Food and
Agricultural Organization to
discuss international action to
promote and serve research in
the marine sciences and the
exploitation of marine resources.
The scope and importance of
Unesco's programme of scientific
research require close contact
with governmental research labo¬
ratories. For this reason a new
Advisory Committee on Scientific
Research has just been created.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO TRAVELLERS9!
CHEQUES
UNESCO COURIER. N"» 4-5. 1954
HOW
TO APPLY
FOR THEM
Travel Coupons are available in the countries which
have joined the Unesco Travel Coupon System. In
each of these countries an Allocating Agency has
been designated to receive requests for them.
Apply for your coupons in the following way :
A Send in a request giving the following informa-
^'tion, to the Allocating Agency in your country:
Name, Address, Nationality, Passport No., Profes¬
sion, Country(ies) to be visited, Planned date of
departure and return, Purpose of travel, Total
amount requested, denominations requested:
... at $ I 0, ... at $2 5, ... at $ I 00.
^ß If this agency approves your request, it will send
you a letter specifying the amount of Travel Cou¬
pons you may draw and where you may buy them.
ÇJTake letter of authorization together with pass¬
port and your money to Issuing Agency selling
Travel Coupons. The Agency may charge commis¬
sion of up to 75 cents per $ I 00.
...AND HOW YOU CASH THEM
You must go in person to the Cashing Agency in the
country(ies) for which your coupons are valid. Counter¬
sign the coupons in the presence of the cashier. Travel
Coupons are not endorsable.
WHAT
THEY
ARE
Officially called Travel Coupons, they
are issued by Unesco to remove
the handicap which restricts educa¬
tional travel between countries.
People in soft-currency areas often find it difficult,
or even impossible, to convert the money of their
own country into the foreign exchange needed to
spend time abroad for study or research.
Unesco has therefore introduced the Travel
Coupon System, which supplements national
allowances of foreign currency and which
enables you to buy coupons in your national
currency and cash them in the currency of the
country to which you are travelling. Unesco
makes its own hardcurrency reserves available
to facilitate this currency exchange.
Unesco Travel Coupons may be cashed in the country of-
destination to defray the cost of personal maintenance
there (lodging, meals, etc.), educational expenses (books,
tuition, etc.), and in certain cases, when tickets cannot be
bought In local currency, to pay for transportation.
Travel Coupons are issued in denominations of $ I 0, $25
and $100.
10
i 	~-
A new travel
y
aid for students and scholars
where
i
, to REQUEST
Fravel Coupons
to OBTAIN
Travel Coupons "
to CASH
Travel Coupons
CAMBODIA
Commission nationale
cambodgienne pour
I'Unesco, Ministère de
l'Education nationale,
de la Jeunesse et des
Sports, Phnom-Penh.
Banque franco-chinoise pour
le commerce et l'industrie,
Phnom-Penh.
Banque franco-chinoise pour
le commerce et l'industrie,
Phnom-Penh.
CANADA
Canadian Pacific Express Com¬
pany, 88 Simcoe Street,
Toronto 1 ;
and C.P.E.C. agencies In
main university towns.
EL SALVADOR
Comisión Salvadoreña de
Cooperación con la
Unesco, Ministerio de
la Cultura, Palacio Na¬
cional, San Salvador.
Banco Central de Reserva, San
Salvador.
Banco Central de Reserva, San
Salvador.
FRANCE
Commission nationale
pour l'éducation, la
science et la culture ;
3. b.s. du Service français
de I'Unesco, 37, quai
d'Orsay, Parls-7B.
Banque nationale pour le com¬
merce et l'industrie, 16, bou¬
levard des Italiens, Parls-9" ;
and B.N.C.I. branches in main
university towns.
Banque nationale pour le com¬
merce et l'industrie, 16, bou¬
levard des Italiens, Parls-9" ;
and B.N.C.I. branches in main
university towns.
ISRAEL
Vtinistry of Finance (Fo¬
reign Exchange Dept.),
Government of Israel,
Jerusalem.
Bank Leumi Le-lsrael B.M.,
Tel Aviv ; and branches In
Jerusalem ; Haifa ; Hadar-
Hacarmel Haifa.
Bank Leumi Le-lsrael B.M.,
Tel Aviv ;
and branches in Jerusalem ;
Haifa ; Hadar-Hacarmel Haifa.
LAOS
Commission nationale
pour I'Unesco, Minis¬
tère de l'Education,
Vientiane.
Commission nationale pour
I'Unesco, Ministère de l'Edu¬
cation, Vientiane.
Banque de l'Indochine, Vien¬
tiane.
THE NETHERLANDS
Amsterdamsche Bank N.V.,
4 Lange Vijverberg, Haag ;
and branches in main univer¬
sity towns.
SWITZERLAND
Crédit Suisse, Genève ;
and branches in main univer¬
sity towns.
URUGUAY
Bank of London and South
America Limited, 402 Cerrito,
Montevideo.
U. S. A.
Council on Student travel, 53 Broadway New York
City, N.Y.
The council will make Unesco Travel Coupons
available to participants of study tours organized
by the council or by organizations affiliated with
the council.
American Express Company,
65 Broadway, New York 6,
N.Y.;
and agencies in main university
towns.
Chase National Bank, Rocke¬
feller Center branch, New
Ycrk City, N.Y. ;
and all its branches in New
York City.
Chemical Bank and Trust Co.,
United Nations Building, New
York City ;
and all its branches in New York
City.
VIET-NAM
Commission nationale du
Viêt-nam pour I'Unes¬
co, 89, rue du Présldent-
Thinh, Saigon.
Commission nationale du Viet¬
nam pour I'Unesco, 89, rue
du Président-Thlnh, Saigon
Banque de l'Indochine, quai
de Belgique, Saigon ;
and branches In Cantho, Datât,
Haiphong, Hanoi, Tourane.
WHO
MAY USE
T H E M
Persons travelling abroad for
educational, scientific or cultural
purposes. For example:
Professors, primary and secon¬
dary school teachers.
Students of universities and
secondary schools.
experts, research
workers in the fields of educ¬
ation, science or culture.
Librarians, senior museum staff,
archivists.
Persons practising the liberal
professions, such as writers,
architects, lecturers, engineers,
artists, etc.
Holders of fellowships or inter-
neships of the United Nations or
its Specialized Agencies.
Social workers.
Workers travelling for educa¬
tional or cultural purposes.
n each country the government-
designated Allocating Agency
will decide whether or not travel
coupons may be made available.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°» 4-5. 1954
ot long ago, the famous American battleship
Missouri the "Mighty Mo" as she was
called was placed "in mothballs" and
retired from the United States naval
service. It was on her quarterdeck, on
September i, 1945, that Japan accepted the
Allied surrender terms and acknowledged the defeat of militarism.
Nearly nine years have passed since the surrender ceremony
took place in Tokyo Bay; and while time has transformed the
once "Mighty Mo" into a "ghost" ship, it has brought revolu¬
tionary transformations to post-war Japan.
Since their defeat, the Japanese have been looking at a new way
of living de-mok-ra-sie. New types of behaviour and new
modes of thought have grown up in competition with the tradi¬
tional forms. The old Imperial régime and everything stemming
from or connected with it have been profoundly altered. To all
appearances, the only thing left is a façade, with the steel framework
and structural depth gone.
The Emperor remains, but only as a symbol of national unity.
Sovereignty has been restored to the people. Laws concerning
the family and inheritance as well as the legal status of women have
entirely changed. Socially and economically a profound revolu¬
tion has been brought about by agrarian reform and the dispersal
of the Zaibatsu (trusts). Militaristic Shintoism the State reli¬
gion has been abolished, and the nation's educational system
has been entirely recast. By an explicit provision of the new
Constitution, the army has been completely abolished. No
fragment survives of the incomparable metal the Samurai sword
was forged from; the chrysanthemum, emblem of the Imperial
House, disappeared entirely.
In the face of such a total upheaval, where did the youth of
postwar Japan stand and what were their feelings and attitudes
to the changes ? Were they really a new generation "without the
chrysanthemum and the sword ? "
12
In 195 1, Unesco began a great enquiry into the subject. Two
Europeans Jean Stoetzel, a French opinion poll expert, and Fritz
Vos, a Dutch Japanologist joined a team of Japanese including
Eizo Koyama, director of the Japanese National Public Opinion
Research Institute (NPORI), Takao Sofue and Feiichi Izumi,
both of the Japanese Association of Cultural Science.
The investigation was undertaken in several parts. The most
comprehensive was carried out by the NPORI through a repre¬
sentative sampling poll of youth all over the country. Other
more specialized surveys were made in selected areas: on the
southernmost island of Kyusku, with its reputation for tradition¬
alism, and the northernmost island of Hokkaido exactly the
opposite. Students in Tokyo, Kyoto (a rich cultural centre)
and Sapporo (seat of the University of Hokkaido) were also
specially questioned. Persons interviewed ranged from the son
of a purged general and the fatherless student of a middleclass
family whose mother was a labourer, to the secretary of a miners'
union and young fishermen living on the northeastern tip of
Hokkaido within sight of the Kuriles, who had to be reached by
sledge across snowfields.
The Unesco enquiry has now been completed and its findings
are reported in a 300-page study by Dr. Stoetzel (1). Though
the enquiry covered all age groups it focused attention on youth,
15 t02 5 , who make up one fifth of the population or 1 5 million per¬
sons ; two-thirds of whom are country dwellers. In this group all
boys and girls attend school up to 1 5 ; about half of both sexes are
employed between 15-20 years; and a small minority continues
studies after 20.
The questions put to the young men and women of Japan
covered almost every aspect of their life, but they were especially
(1) ' Without the Chrysanthemum and the Sword A study of the Attitudes
of Youtb in Post-war Japan' . By Jean Stoetzel. Published by Unesco. Avail¬
able in July, 1954. Price : $ 2.50: I2¡6: 600 fr.
grouped around a few main themes: what Japanese youth think
about foreigners; their attitudes toward higher authority and their
country's institutions; their attitudes toward tradition vs. social
change and the personal values they most treasure.
The answers can help us assess New Japan's chances of evolving
along democratic lines or reverting to some form of totalitarianism.
For if the young people of Japan have become self-reliant and
independent, if their thinking shows confidence and assuredness,
if they have found the strength to cast off the heavy burden tradi¬
tionally placed on them by the state and their family, then the
cause of democracy will be safely guarded in Japan by the citizens
of tomorrow. If not, then quite different political inferences can
be drawn.
The Unesco investigation was not a political study, however.
The primary aim was to try and reduce the enormous distances
still separating Japan, its people and its customs from other coun¬
tries. It was part of the much vaster Unesco programme for
promoting understanding between peoples. International goodwill
and a co-operative spirit are not enough in themselves; they must
go hand in hand with accurate knowledge about the different
peoples of the world.
In the case of Japan, insofar as Westerners' minds are not a
complete blank on the subject, their knowledge mostly boils
down to a collection of arbitrary clichés whether favourable
or not stemming from misleading propaganda, the warped
judgment of political events, or inaccurate books.
In the past, the Japanese people have been described by certain
individuals as "two-faced", "crafty", and "bellicose". Such
stereotyped opinions are largely based on ignorance and the
emotions of those who expressed them suspicion, hatred and
anger.. They are purely subjective and unrealistic and false.
It must be admitted however that it is no simple matter to
"understand" a nation whose whole social structure, way of
thinking and philosophy of life are poles apart from one's own.
As Jean Stoetzel poses the problem, "For a foreign observer,
Japanese behaviour, like that of other peoples... is on three different
planes. First there is the exotic plane the one that strikes the
tourist, and which Herodotus delighted to note in his descriptions
of Egypt." And he cites the Japanese author, Atsuharu Sakai
who in his book "Japan in a Nutshell" lists 58 contrasts between
Japan's customs and those of the West. Here are a few: Japanese
strike matches away from them, wear white for mourning, write
from top to bottom and from right to left, touch their nose when
they say "I" or "me", beckon with palms downwards.
"The second plane", continues Dr. Stoetzel, "isthat of 'human
nature'... this is normally the plane on which relations with
strangers are established and interchanges between peoples of
different cultures are possible.
"Below these however, there is a third plane, deeper in a sense
than the others, where the motivations, values and mechanism
of the individual are to be found. While something very near
to understanding can be achieved on the second plane, the true
and full interpretation of behaviour can be obtained only on the
third." But even Dr. Stoetzel, who states that the aim of the
authors of the Unesco enquiry was to penetrate that third plane,
frankly admits "We cannot say that we have entirely succeeded."
Whatever the plane, however, any understanding of the Japanese
must accept their right to think and* behave like Japanese. Thus,
the Japanese consider all pleasures legitimate provided they are
given minor importance, but they reject as scandalous the pursuit
of happiness as the serious purpose of life. In fact the word
"happiness" has no exact equivalent in the Japanese language.
Many terms such as freedom and slavery, good and evil,
happiness and misery, democracy and totalitarianism which the
West accepts as clearcut opposites are often pointless when
applied to Japan.
On the following pages, we present some of the findings of
the Unesco enquiry on post-war Japanese youth.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°" 4-5. 1954
mm
youth eyes the outside world
mm i
| NY attempt to understand
I Japanese thinking and
U behaviour must take into
Bl I I Bk I account the fact that up
^^^^fl until a relatively short time
l ago, Japan was an island-
universe all of its own that
had deliberately cut itself off from all
contact with the Western world.
The Portuguese made a chance
landing in the south of Kyushu in
1542 ; _ Saint Francis Xavier reached
Kagoshima in 1549 and the Jesuits
followed. In 1600 the Dutch appeared.
Within a few years, however, Chris¬
tianity was banished and foreigners
were expelled. By the middle of the
17th century, not a single foreigner
remained in Japan except for the
Dutch who were confined to a small
commercial concession in Nagasaki,
and a few Chinese. Travel by Japan¬
ese outside the Empire on any
pretext was prohibited as was the
building of any ship with a draught- of
over 500 koku (92 tons).
The modern era was ushered in with
the Meiji Restoration (Meiji means
"order of light") in 1868. It marked
the end of Shogun (feudal family) rule
in the name of the Emperor. The last
of the Shoguns abdicated and the
Emperor reassumed full powers ; feu¬
dalism was abolished and a feudal
lord revolt crushed. Japan flung open
its ports to- the commerce, science,
institutions and customs of the West.
And then the Japanese, who had
embarked on only one foreign war of
aggression in 1500 years of their history
(the ill-fated Korean expedition of
1592-98), plunged headlong into mi¬
litary adventure war with China,
Russia, Korea, Germany, Manchuria,
Indo-China, and finally Pearl Harbour
in 1941 which ended with Japan's total
defeat and unconditional surrender in
1945.
- The world saw the Japanese people,
who had waged a savage, bitter war in
the Pacific receive the news of their
capitulation if not without emotion at
least without any mass uprising. The
Occupation provoked no outbreaks of
violence and there was no "resistance".
The Japanese set themselves court¬
eously and diligently to mend their
ways. The defeat, the far-reaching
changes in the regime, the trial and
execution of Japan's military leaders
caused even less protest than the Meiji
revolution which had at least provoked
one revolt in 1877. As Jean Stoetzel
remarks "such docility is not merely
suspicious after the determination
shown by the people in their struggle
against half the world; it is incom¬
prehensible."
This complete turn-about, however,
is an integral part of the conduct of
life in Japan whether in personal or in
international relations. In her re
markable study of Japanese culture,
the late American social anthropologist
Ruth Benedict has emphasized this
point. Writing in "The Chrysanthem¬
um and the Sword" she says "Japan's
real strength which she can use in
remaking herself into a peaceful
nation 'lies in her ability to say of a
course of action, 'That failed,' and
then to throw her energies into other
channels. The Japanese sees that he
has made an error in embarking on a
course of action which does not achieve
its goal. When it fails, he discards it
as a lost cause, for he is not condition¬
ed to pursue lost causes. 'It is no use',
he says 'biting one's navel'."
What, however, was the effect of all
this on , Japanese youth ? How did
they accept the fact of the 1945 defeat?
Did they withdraw into themselves and
nourish feelings of revenge or were
they prepared to turn optimistically
to the future, ready to . co-operate
sincerely with the other nations of the
world ? If so, how did they picture
the other nations. What were their
attitudes toward war, pacifism and the
recent decision to rearm ? These were
some questions that the Unesco survey
of Japanese youth sought to answer.
One fact stands out : The youth of
Japan have not withdrawn into them¬
selves. On the contrary, their eyes are
open wide to the outside world. The
polls carried out for Unesco by the
J 853
The arrival
of Perry
On the night of July 8, 1853, after Commodore Matthew Calbraith
Perry of the U.S. Navy had anchored his small flotilla off the Japanese
coast at Uraga, a meteor shot across the sky. 'This', noted the Commo¬
dore, ' could be construed as a favourable omen '. And so it was
for Perry's visit marked the opening of Japan to international intercourse
after two centuries of almost complete Isolation. This is how a Japanese i
artist depicted the Commodore a century ago. The second illustration
shows a Samurai guarding his homeland against Perry's "black ships".
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
'It is no use biting
one's own navel'
One
girl
out of
eight
In I 949 there were
about 400,000 uni¬
versity students in
Japan of whom one-
eighth were girls.
Nearly two thirds of
the total student body
is divided between the
universities of Tokyo,
Kyoto and Osaka. To¬
kyo University alone
has an enrolment of
over 180,000 stu¬
dents. Here, a crowd
of students from Kyo¬
to University assem¬
bles in the square
outside the "famous
old Kabuki Theatre.
Japanese National Public Opinion
Research Institute showed that as
many as 58 % of the Japanese "want
to know all about events abroad."
Amongst the teen-age group the per¬
centage was as high as 73 %. And
curiously enough, teen-agers living in
the rural areas show the greatest
interest in foreign countries (76 %).
There one can say that if war often
brings nations into closer contact than
does peace, defeat opens the windows
still wider, acts as a spur to national
self-appraisal, to the desire for reform,
and leads to comparisons with other
ways of life and a search for examples
to follow.
It should not be inferred from this,
however, that the Japanese now look
at foreign affairs or foreign countries
through rose-coloured glasses. The
Unesco enquiry clearly shows that the
desire for knowledge about other
nations is closely linked with a deep
feeling of fear and anxiety which
permeates Japanese youth. In fact
nearly eight out of ten young people
who "want to know" feel that "events
in foreign countries can adversely
affect the Japanese way of life".
Unlike the Japan of the pre-war
militaristic period, the post-war
Japanese freely admit that Japan is
16
not the hierarchical superior of all
other nations and see many countries
far ahead of her.
By far the most popular is the
United States, which over 80 % of
Japanese youth considered ahead of
their own country. Although criticism
of the U.S. is not lacking, the credit
side by far overweighs the debit side,
and there is deep Tespect for America
the victorious power. This is an im¬
portant element in the psychology of
Japanese youth.
After the United States, the countries
considered ahead of Japan are England
(18 %), Prance (7 %), Germany (6 %),
the Soviet Union (5 %), Switzerland
(2 %), and Denmark (1.5 %). These
percentages may seem . small but
actually they represent large numbers
of people; one per cent of the
population 15 years of age or over
representing some 500,000 persons (1).
But more interesting perhaps than
the countries considered superior to
Japan are the factors which the
Japanese feel put these nations ahead
(t) It Is Interesting- to note here that 72 % or
Japanese youtli are eager to go abroad, the 10
countries most frequently mentioned being: :
USA (48 %) ; France (8 %) ; Great Britain (6 %);
Germany (3 % ) ; Soviet Union (3 % ) ; Switzer¬
land (3 %) ; China (2 %) ; Brazil (2 %) ; Hawaii.
(2 %) ; Denmark (1 %).
of their .own country. Far and away
above all other considerations the
Japanese admire foreign material
power, that is, scientific, technological
and industrial advances, rather than
foreign achievements in the intellec¬
tual, cultural or moral spheres.
This casts a revealing light on the
idea that the , apáñese really have of
the West, and indirectly on their
opinion of how Japanese civilization
compares with that of the Christian
industrial West. The Japanese look
at the West as materially powerful and
thereby enviable; but not truly cul¬
tivated and a little lacking in soul.
The table published on page - 19
shows the degree of importance at¬
tached by the Japanese to different fac¬
tors they deem superior in the six
foreign countries most- frequently
named.
Thus while technology is the most
important factor which makes for
American superiority in Japanese eyes,
it is even more marked in the case of
Germany. In only two instances is
any other factor of -superiority the
most frequently mentioned for a
foreign country:- economic evolution
for Denmark and intellectual values
for Prance.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. M°« 4-5. 1954
The highest standard of living is
attributed to America, France and
Germany; the most advanced political
development to Switzerland, Great
Britain and the Soviet Union in that
order; and the highest "spiritual
values" (i.e. manners and customs,
politeness and strength of character)
to Great Britain and Germany.
When asked to say what Japan
could learn from the way of life of
foreign countries, by far the largest
number of young people and adults
alike chose Western comfort in the
home: Western labour-saving devices,
improvements in the kitchen, electricity
at home, and scientific appliances
which facilitate the housewife's job.
Some Japanese stressed that Japan
should adopt the Westerners' punc¬
tuality, respect for women, and health
techniques. Western clothing, food
and housing aroused relatively little
interest on the whole. A third of the
Japanese though could see nothing at
all in foreign ways that they wanted
Japan to adopt.
t Despite the fact, too, that a good
half of the Japanese public had
nothing to say about Western traits to
be avoided, criticism of foreign ways
and customs was by no means lacking.
Here are a few of the things par-
JS60
A mission goes abroad
After the signing of the U.S.¬
Japanese Treaty of Friendship
in 1 854 Japan established official
diplomatic relations with Euro¬
pean nations. But the first
Japanese diplomatic mission was
not sent abroad until I860.
Arriving in the United States it
was received by President
Buchanan in the White House,
where delegates were startled
to find that the President was
dressed like other people and
he did not even wear a sword.
The first foreign trading settle¬
ment in Japan was established
in 1 877 at Tsukiji (Tokyo Pro¬
vince). Foreigners who arrived
that year saw the flying of the
first balloon by the Japanese
Navy Ministry. The flags of
nearly every nation which flew
within the settlement showed
that Western civilization was-
beginning to penetrate Japan.
Special foreign areas with extra¬
territorial rights disappeared in
1 894, Under the new agree¬
ments reached with other coun¬
tries Japan was now recognized
as an equal for the first time.
J 877
Foreigners settle in
ÏSS5
First western house
Rokumeikan, the first Western style building
constructed in Tokyo in 1883, caused a great
sensation in Japan. The Japanese Government
held «lavish parties there for the leaders of the
foreign colonies. Rokumeikan was the result of
a Government policy for the "Westernizing of
Japan", and its purpose was to increase Japan's
international prestige. This engraving depicts a
ball given to honour the birthday of Emperor
Meiji who opened Japan to the Western World.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Ancient traditions
and new aspirations
Along with the influence of age-old tradi¬
tions symbolized by the statues of Kyoto,
famed city of classical culture, young people
in post-war Japan are now exposed to new
ways and ideas. One of the most important
social revolutions since the war has been
the change in the status of women. For
centuries men have dominated Japanese
culture. Today women can votepreviously
an unheard-of privilege. ~ Schoolgirls of
today are growing up under the influence
of a new feminist slogan, "Lets develop
the power to think and act for ourselves."
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. K»' 4-5. 1954
The good and the bad in
'Ijin' the foreigner
ticularly criticized by Japanese youth:
1). Social relations between men and
women are too crude and too free.
"They walk -arm in arm or hand in
hand.'!
2) Women are placed on a high
pedestal. "The position of men is
humiliating."
3) Women's dresses are extravagant
and gaudy. There is slavery
to fashion". Too much lipstick, ex¬
cessive makeup, and addiction to
permanent waves. "Westerners kiss in
the presence of others."
4) Foreigners don't understand the
art of good living. "They are con¬
stantly eating and chewing both at
work and in the street."
5) There is no strong family bond.
"They don't take care of their parents
and have no sense of filial duty."
6) Their outlook is too materialistic.
"Foreigners ' attach too much im¬
portance to money. They depend too
much on science and their mechanical
civilization. They measure spiritual
values in terms of material ones."
The actual percentage of the people
voicing these criticisms is small in
each case (at no time exceeding 8 %
and usually 3 to 5 % of those polled)
but the remarks are significant and
doubtless reflect Japan's close ex¬
perience with the Occupation.
The Unesco enquiry also furnishes
us with revealing information on the
foreign reading habits of Japanese
youth as weH as their interest in
foreign films and radio programmes.
The Japanese are a great reading
nation. Illiteracy contrary to popular
vestigator concluded: "Generally
speaking, Japanese films (historical or
otherwise) and American Westerns are
favoured by the lower classes of the
population and French films by the
upper. One can say that the cinema
is the most popular pastime of the
youth of Japan."
Similar findings are noted by Unesco
for radio listening habits. Japanese
' youth are more interested in pro¬
grammes broadcasting foreign music
than in their traditional music. And
the younger he is the less he wants to
listen to Japanese music.
Thus for the third time in the
history of Japan, the country is wide
open to Western influences. The
nation as a whole clearly is eager to
multiply contacts with the outside
world and this eagerness is greatest
amongst the young.
But we should not forget that the
Nature of superiority
over Japan
United
States of
America
Great
Britain
France Germany U.R.S.S.
Swit¬
zerland
Denmark
Science and Technology . . 71%
14%
18%
7%
N%
5%
6%
55%
. 23 %
16%
22%
11%
14%
3%
38%
55%
19%
>o%
7%
7%
4%
77%
17%
18%
3%
8%
M%
2%
63%
14%
5%
"9%
14%
5%
3%
42%
"2%
14%
29%
15%
6%
9%
26%
10%
12%
14,%
67%
2%
o%
opinion in the West is practically
non-existent despite Japan's complex
system of writing. The public's read¬
ing taste is highly developed. Daily
newspapers are numerous and the most
important have circulations among
the highest in the world (the two
leading papers of Tokyo, Asahi
and Mainichi, have a daily circulation
of over three million each) . Many
weekly and monthly magazines exist,
volumes published in 1950.
and the output of books is considerable
Of the young people questioned by
Unesco in Tokyo, only three percent
never read newspapers and 18 did' not
read the weekly or monthly magazines.
Fifty-two per cent read books. Inter¬
est in' Japanese translations of foreign
publications was high. Foreign books
most often cited are French, especially
the works 'of Romain Rolland, André
Gide and Camus.
The Japanese also seem to prefer
foreign films to their national pro¬
ductions. Out of 100 persons ques¬
tioned in Tokyo, for example, only 7
preferred Japanese films, 12 gave their
preference to foreign films generally
without specifiying nationality, 11
preferred French films, 7 American -
films, and 7 British films.
In interior villages, Japanese films
and American Westerns are most
popular; while in the towns young
workers of both sexes prefer French
and Italian movies. - A Unesco in-
two previous occasions did not produce
fortunate results. The economic and
religious infiltration which began in
the middle of the 16th century ended,
a century later, in the complete self-
Isolation of Japan. The Wester¬
nization of the Meiji period led to the
development in the Japanese of con¬
tempt for the other Asiatic nations
along with hatred and envy of the
peoples of Europe and America. It
was thus responsible for one of the
most brutal attempts at aggression in
modern history.
In the years following the Second
World War the military and industrial
power of the United States gave rise to
a wave of respect and admiration. The
presence of the Occupation troops and
services enabled the Japanese to
acquire direct knowledge and better
understanding of these "strangers"
in Japan as in many other languages
a "foreigner" Xijin) means a "strange"
or "different" man.
According to Unesco's enquiry, the
Japanese harbour no intentions of em¬
barking on any sort of war of revenge
and the youth of the country even less
so. The last war has left deep scars
in the minds of the Japanese, and to
a traveller journeying through the
country, Japan appears one of the most
passionately pacifist nations in the
world today. .
The Japanese have conceived such a
deep fear of war that it finds ex-
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
t~2*l&&xm-£
»V . ¥ <$
J 9 45
'Twentieth century hell'
The first atomic bomb exploded over Hiroshima on August 6, 1945, and caused the deaths of over
260,000 people. This was the final blow which shattered the militaristic regime. Two Japanese painters
Maruki and Akamatsu have depicted some scenes from this "Twentieth Century Hell", spending more
than four years to finish a set of five pictures.
pression on every possible occasion.
When the National , Public Opinion
Research Institute asked "what is the
thing personal or otherwise which
worries you most and makes you most
unhappy at the present moment?", the
most frequent reply was "economic or.
money problems", while the second
was "fear of war". It is here that one
of the most burning problems of post¬
war Japan rearmament is raised.
The new Constitution of Japan con¬
tains an Article solemnly renouncing
war and provides that Japan will not
maintain an Army, Navy or any means
of waging war. .As a result, the only
armed forces in . Japan were the
National Police Reserve Corps and the
Coastguard. In June 1950, however,
the Korean War broke out. Historic
events such" as the Korean War, the
Peace Conference in San Francisco in
1951 and the signing of the peace
treaty restoring independence to Japan
have driven the problem into critical
focus. In January 1952 the National
Police Reserve was reorganized into
the National Safety Force. By degrees,
Japan has started out along the path
of rearmament.
In May. 1946,. immediately after the
adoption of the new Constitution, an
enquiry by the Mainichi Shimbun (one
of the important Tokyo dailies) cover¬
ing some 2,000 intellectuals showed
that a large majority (69 % of the men
and 73 % of the women) thought the
Article in the Constitution renouncing"
war was "necessary ".
Since then, however, a marked
change of adult public opinion has
taken place. In August 1950, 39 % of .
the population was for rearmament,
33 % against. By March 1951, the
figure ' had risen to 47 % for, 24 %
against, and by January 1952, to 57 %
for rearmament and 24 % against.
The Unesco survey, however, shows
a different picture for Japanese youth.
Young people appear to be consistently
more pacifist than their elders, and
this is particularly marked among
university students. Opposition to
re-armament was in fact found to be
strongest in all age brackets among
those people who' had had a university
or equivalent education.
But investigators also reported: "The
forces of pacifism in Japan are perhaps
less substantial and effective than may
have appeared a few years ago... many
undoubtedly sincere pacifist opinions
are seen, on analysis, to be superficial,
sentimental, and easy to upset."
The wave of pacifism which flooded
Japan after the war was only partly
due to a recognition of the evils caused
by military" adventures. It ' also grew
from a sincere belief that war was not
only avoidable, but that it would
undoubtedly be avoided in the future.
There are still plenty of people who
believe this today, but world events
since the war have had a strong in¬
fluence on most Japanese. The ma¬
jority no longer feel that "peace at any
price" is worthwhile and this is a view
which young - people especially are
quick to affirm.
In considering the implication of this
trend in public opinion, it is worth¬
while recalling the words written by
Ruth Benedict m 1946:
"At present the Japanese know
militarism as a light that failed. They
will watch to see whether it has also
failed in the other nations in the
world. If it has failed elsewhere,
Japan can set herself out to prove how
well. she has learned the lesson that
imperialistic dynastic enterprises are
no road to honour."
19§4 A child of Hiroshima
-
When" Hiroshima experienced
its cataclysm this youth was ~
still a small child. Today he
lives in the rebuilt city whose
wooden houses still recall scenes
of disaster and misery. Here
and in other cities the Japanese
have cleared away the ruins,
turned their backs on an
unhappy past. The children of
Hiroshima have not yet grown
to manhood and their memo¬
ries are still scarred by the war,
but* their generation already
offers encouraging signs to sug¬
gest that the Japan of tomorrow
will be a better place than the
Japan of yesterday.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. M" 4-5. 1954
THE IMPERIAL WALLS
ARE DOWN
THE question of young Japan's attitudes towards its national Institutions is
the kernel of the whole Unesco study carried out by Jean Stoetzel, Frits Vos
and Japanese public opinion pollsters.. .
The legal and "administrative structure of Japan has undergone a profound
transformation since the end of the war. The economic organization of town and
country has been extensively recast and the Empire has become a democracy
with a strong bias towards decentralization in certain spheres.
Women have been given equality, with men, not only politically, but in the
family and in daily life, while the principle of primogeniture (inheritance by
eldest son only) apparently strongly entrenched in the country areas, has been
severely modified. The young men are free to marry as they wish, and no longer
need the consent of their families; at the same time attention has been drawn
to the dangers of over-population, and to all intents and purposes official sanction
has been given to birth control. Lastly the "established" religion has been abo¬
lished root and branch and freedom of worship has been- granted to all faiths.
But however important laws may be, institutions exist only through the men
who make 'them work. If these radical innovations are to be incorporated into
Japanese society, it will be primarily through the agency of the young. The
Unesco enquirers therefore attempted to determine the attitudes of young people
-towards economics, politics, the family and religion.
The object of all the reforms mentioned was to reduce the excessive pressure
of authority on the individual, in,his family relationships, in his work and in his "
'I am not a living
god'
In the Imperial Rescript of Janu¬
ary I, 1946, the Emperor Hiro-
hito solemnly declared to the Japan¬
ese people: "I am not a living god".
With these words, the Emperor
formally put an end to the absolute
power which he had held until the
Japanese surrender in 1945. Later,
the new Japanese Constitution pro¬
claimed: "The Emperor shall be the
symbol of the State and of the unity
of the people, deriving his position
from the will of the people in whom
resides sovereign power." Tradi¬
tional respect is still paid to the
dynasty which has reigned over
Japan since 600 B.C. The Emperor
Hirohito Is, in fact, head of the
oldest of the world's reigning
families. Previously, the wall sur¬
rounding the Imperial Palace was
a barrier separating the "Son of
Heaven" from his people. Demo¬
cracy in Japan has not yet abolished
all barriers, but between the people
and the Emperor the wall is down.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Problem N° 1: Overpopulation
civic and public life. What, in the
result, is the attitude of the young
towards authority in all its forms? "Do
they feel free? Do they want to be.
free? Do they feel what freedom is?
In other words, do they intend to play
an active part in the life of the com¬
munity, with a fully developed sense oí
their responsibilities ?
. On the whole, and despite very real
grounds for apprehension, Japanese
youth are not pessimists. The majority -
think that living conditions through¬
out the world will become progressively -
better and the youngest age groups are
frankly optimistic.
However attached they may be to '
tradition, the Japanese waste no time
on futile regret for the
past. In one of the ~ "
groups interviewed,
barely 7 % said they OQ million
would have preferred
to live in a past era, n_ .,_.
37 % preferred the 87 million
, future while 41 %
(54 % of the men)
were content with the
present. The Japanese put their trust
in their capacity for hard work and
in technology which they admire most
in foreign nations and which they most
wish to import.
The chief cause of their difficulties,
as they see it,' is overpopulation.
The population problem, in fact, has
become the most important question
since the war and both the government
and civil institutes are studying ways
to solve it. The population is increas¬
ing at the rate of one million persons
a year latest statistics show a rise
from 83 million in October 1950 to 87
million in October 1953. In 1950 the
Japanese National Public Opinion Re¬
search Institute asked what should be
done to remedy the shortage of food,
housing and employment; over-popula¬
tion was mentioned in 60 % of the
replies, and the same investigation
showed that the younger generation
was considerably better informed on
the problem than their elders. Many
public opinion polls have been made on
this question since the war. Family
planning has been advanced by many
Japanese as a way of solving the prob¬
lem. However, other views are strong¬
ly advanced : planned emigration,
and the introduction of reforms to eli¬
minate social inequalities.
As far as the general economic pic¬
ture is concerned, Japanese youth are
not highly critical and seem to prefer
personal solutions to their financial
and material problems. Do they have
a more independent attitude toward
political institutions or do they conti¬
nue- to follovv' the traditional path of
submission to higher authority? Unes¬
co's enquiry seems to indicate that the
latter is both more prevalent and more
deeply rooted but with some reserves.
Japanese youth are making a real
effort to break away from the political
thinking of the past and the heroes
and rulers of yesterday are being repu¬
diated. The following question was
put by one of Unesco's investigators to
youth in Tokyo : "Do you think that
the ideas of Japan's military and polit¬
ical leaders between 1930 and 1940
were basically correct though these
leaders were unable to achieve their
aims ?" A total of 49 % said that the ,
ideas were wrong, but 26 % thought
they were correct up. to a point while
15 % considered them correct.
The new watchword "freedom" has
been greeted with en¬
thusiasm by young
people but they do not
jjj 1950 think M» *s as new as
all that. "In the Heian
i inro era", said one 19-year-
DJ 195o old sales girl, "we tried
to find it and now
we're trying again." A
majority of the young¬
er generation, though, do not feel that
regimes such as those in
Great Britain, France or the U.S. would
be suitable' for present-day Japan.
This does not mean that they reject
democracy but rather that they are
searching for a "Japanese democracy"
which has still to be created. " Every
nation is different", they say, "'so each
country's system must differ too."
On the whole political activity or
interest on the part of the young is
not very marked though it is slightly
greater than among adults. Young
people living in the towns furthermore
are more politics-conscious than those
living in the villages.
In the face of the civil authorities,
Japanese youth appears to have more
independence though this attitude is
still more the exception than the rule.
Thus while most Japanese (70 %)
think that citizens should be able to
discuss public affairs in general, the
view that this should
be left exclusively to
the government" is
quite common in the All fan
rural areas for all age
groups. In all instan- ,
ces surveyed, though, must DC
the younger the indi¬
viduals questioned the
more they maintain
that expression of opinion should be
as free as possible. When the investiga¬
tion is pressed further, ' however,
their certainty about "freedom of
speech and the right of discussion
begins to crumble and authority re¬
covers all its prestige. Women tend to
hold aloof from civic life and do not
generally take sides in situations where
the civil authority is implicated.
Up until the end of the last war the
Emperor was the supreme head of the
traditional political structure of Japan.
The terms of the Japanese surrender
on 15 August 1945 put an end to the
absolute power of the Emperor and to
the bases for the "blind subjection of
the people to Imperial power.
Have .these changes, in- effect, meant
an end to the traditional Emperor
worship, particularly amongst the
young people? Reporting on Unesco's
investigation in this respect, Mr.
Stoetzel remarks that "not a few
traces of the traditional devotion to
the Emperor are still to be found in the
young."
In one of the polls conducted the
following question was asked : "Al¬
though Tojo has been sent to the
gallows as a war criminal, the Emper¬
or, who declared war on the United
States of America, was not regarded as
a war criminal. Do you think this is
reasonable or unreasonable? " The
vast majority about 78 % thought
it reasonable : the commonest reply
(73 %) was that after all, under the
dictatorship of Tojo, the Emperor had
. no real power; in 5 % of the replies the
point was also made that it was the
Emperor who gave the cease-fire order
over the radio.
The Emperor remains, at the very
least, the symbol of the nation, not
merely on paper but in the hearts and
minds of the people. This, was the
view of 74 % of the young people ques¬
tioned in Tokyo. As regards Emperor-
worship, 17 % of the same group had
no opinion about it, 37 % had. objec¬
tions to it, but the majority, 46 %, still
thought it good or even necessary.
Attachment to Imperial and national
traditions thus remains very strong.
The great annual celebration of the
foundation of the Empire, on February
11, is now omitted from the list of offi¬
cial holidays. But 85% of the young
people questioned in one series of polls
favoured the revival of Empire Day.
The comments are worthy of note :
" Reviving Empire Day is a good idea;
but all displays of
. fanaticism must be
rigorously excluded. No
a j- j p i a »»i attempt must be made
to treat a myth as if
_ - j it were the truth." "I
excluded am in favour of reviv-.
ing Empire Day but
only as a way of
marking the birth of
the new Japan. We should therefore
change its name/'
These remarks give us an idea of the
sincere desire for -reform which exists*
among some of the people. On the
whole, however, the replies confirm
one extremely important fact that
the youth of Japan have preserved
intact their sense of continuity with
their country's most distant past and
retain a sharp awareness of Japanese
history even in its mythological
aspects. For today's Japanese youth,
Japan is still a nation with a past.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°» 4-5. 1954
One Japanese out of two
is under 25 years of age
The population of the world increased by 30 million persons between the middle of 1951 and
mid- 1 952, according to the latest edition of the U.N. Demographic Yearbook. If this increase
continues it will take less than 70 years for the world to double its present population. This
rejuvenation of the world's population is nowhere more obvious than in Japan whose population
has tripled during the past 70 years. One out of every two Japanese is less than 25 years of age. -
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THERE is an old Japanese riddle
which asks : "'Why is a son who
wants to offer advice to his
parents like a Buddhist priest who
wants to have hair on the top of his
head ?" (Buddhist priests shave their
heads). The answer is," "No matter
how much he wants to do it, he can't."
To Western minds this riddle may
seem like an Oriental version of the
Ifefe. '
y
tiS
i
¿k. j¿^l---' ¿";
";|ll ' t ^Bm
"^^
Bfy i^^j^^^^^^! < \ *
.%
. "' ^"ipj-fat*- *t^r1\
"jMri '
! Ï
\ 4 ' ' '
r,
* - * , -
	> * -	
November 3 is Japan's Culture Day.
A national holiday, it is an occasion for
cultural meetings, exhibitions and all kinds
of festivities. Here a juggler balances
a single bamboo on his chin causing 46
paper lanterns (chochin) to bob and sway.
once current remark "Children should
be seen but not heard." In reality,"
there is no connexion between the two
since the son in the Japanese, riddle
means not only a little boy of, say,
eight, but sons of 30 and 40 who are
married with children of their own.
Although the attitudes of young
people toward their family is under¬
going important changes today, the
riddle does help to illustrate two fun¬
damental aspects of Japanese life the
idea of hierarchy and filial piety.
Hierarchy is basic to Japan's whole
notion of social relations. It is to be
found in the many infinitely complex
rules, customs and conventions that
regulate every-day life; every greeting,
every contact indicates the" kind and
degree of' social distance between
people. The Japanese " have built up
a "respect language" which they
accompany with bows and kneeling. It
is not enough to know to .whom one
should bow but also to exactly what
degree, for this . may range from a
slight bow to kneeling with the fore-
*head touching the hands on the floor.
Etiquette and hierarchy
HIERARCHY is observed above all
in family life. Whereas in the
West etiquette is usually quite
relaxed within the intimacy of the
family, this is not the case in Japan
where it is precisely in the family that
respect rules are learned and applied.
The Japanese family is a tightly-
knit social and economic unit. The
sense of family of belonging to a
family, of acting, in the family name,
of defending family honour, of doing
things orí behalf of the family, of being
worthy of the family ancestors is
extremely powerful particularly in the
rural regions. The common cult is a
symbol of the family bond and people
regard reverence of the family shrine
as one of their most important duties.
Membership in many kinds of
organizations is on a family basis.
Marriage is a family affair, and family
continuity is so important that when
there is no male heir every effort is
made to adopt a son to carry on the
family name (usually the husband of
the eldest daughter).
The Japanese family is hardly larger
than most Western families. In
addition to the married couple and
their children, it usually includes either
the husband's or wife's parents, a
brother or two and their children. On
an average there are from 4-6 persons
in the towns and from 7-8 in the
country areas.
First in line for the bath
THE structure of the family is
strictly hierarchical. All author¬
ity is vested ir. the father or the
grandfather (if he is alive). At meals
he is served first and he is the first to-
enter the communal hot bath (men,
women and children bathe together in
almost boiling hot water). All the
rest of the family bow to him; owner¬
ship of the family property is vested in
him; he is the family priest and makes
and breaks the marriages of his child¬
ren even when they are grown up
with children of their own. His au¬
thority ends only with his death or
voluntary retirement.
Immediately after the father in
seniority comes the* eldest son. Accord¬
ing to tradition and former laws he
was the sole heir and inherited all the
family property. Since the war a new
law provides that all children and
relatives have the right to share in the
inheritance on an equal basis.
In practice, though, the law .is not
strictly followed. Most farmers feel
that their land holdings are too small"
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
and that equal partition would ruin
the family economically. They ignore
the law and leave all the land to the
eldest son. Others split it up unequally
according to age, and only a small few
do so equally among the sons (but not
the daughters).
The feeling of dependence on the
family and of respect for hierarchy is
inculcated in children's minds from an
early age. A child learns during baby¬
hood to bow to the head of the family
and takes part in social functions even
before he can walk. His mother who
carries him everywhere on her back
pushes his head down whenever she
herself bows. At all times the child
absorbs the idea that he needs his-
family.
Hierarchical authority comes to be
accepted not as the dictation of auto¬
crats but as a duty in the interest of
the family. As Ruth Benedict puts
it: "The Japanese learn in their family
experience that the greatest weight
that can be given to a decision comes
from the conviction that it maintains
the family honour. It is not a decree
enforced at the whim of a tyrant who
. happens to be the head of the family.
He is more nearly a trustee of a
spiritual and material estate which
demands of them all that they subord¬
inate their personal wills to - its
requirements.
This, then, is the traditional basis
for life and learning. How has it
fared in Japan's changed post-war
conditions? Have official reforms
really changed the way of life? Have
they encouraged young people to show
more initiative and independence
within their own families? Do young
people welcome the new opportunities -
offered them?
KEEP SMILING
When in sorrow, the Japanese do not like
to make others feel sorry and so they often
talk about their misfortunes with a broad
smile. Some Japanese do so even when they
say: "My father died this morning".
The Unesco enquiry focused on the
situation caused by the conflicting
pull between traditional ways and the
new social evolution in Japan. This
conflict is especially strong in the
minds of young people, many of whom
are torn between the age-old tradition
of respect and obedience to their
parents and a desire to display more
independence and initiative.
From the enquiry it soon became
clear that the younger generation in
Japan no longer accepts its elders'
ideas unquestioningly. AU those who
were asked whether they had
disagreements with their parents and
the other older members, of their
families replied that they did. To
Westerners with their much freer and
easier family relationships there is
nothing very surprising about this. But
for young people in Japan to question
their elder's authority and wisdom
involves the whole structure of the
traditional form of Japanese family
life.
Most disagreements arose "between
old-fashioned views and new ideas
about social problems such as divorce,
equality between the sexes and the
principles on which children should be
brought up." As might be expected,
they were at loggerheads with their
fathers more often than with others
in the family.
Some people went even further.
Among a hundred young people ques¬
tioned in Tokyo, 35 accused the previous
generation of not having acted correct¬
ly; and only 21 had no criticism to
make. In the same group, 50 thought
there was a gulf between themselves
and the previous generation; 14 others
said the gulf existed but was not very
wide' and only 27 thought that the
UNESCO COURIER. K« 4-5. 1954
link between themselves and their
predecessors was unbroken.
That youth is viewing its family
relationships from a new angle was
confirmed .by their elders. A National
Public Opinion Research Institute
investigation showed that 66 % of
Japanese consider that "the number of
children who pay no attention to their
parents has increased of late." A Tokyo
Family Court Judge, speaking about
the connexion between juvenile delin¬
quency and family tensions, instanced,
among other causes, the fact that the
family "no longer interests" many young
people. In Sapporo, teachers said that
the conflicts between parents and
children were increasing not because ,
moral training in the schools had. been
done away with, but because the idea
(Continued on page 30)
Firmly anchored
It is only after a baby has been taken to the local shrine at the age of 30 days that his life is thought
to be firmly anchored in his body so that it is safe to carry him around freely in public. He is carried
on his mother's back, a double sash passed round the mother's shoulders and tied in front of the waist.
LJI\lr-Çffl 0'der children carry the baby, too, even at play.
ARCHIVES
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°« 4-5. 1954
Though Michiko Jinuma is aged 20 in Japan,
she is still only 19 by Western reckoning.
In Japan children are already counted as being
one year old on the day of their birth.
Michiko, daughter of a Tokyo judge, lives
with her parents and three sisters in a typical
Japanese wooden house with nine rooms.
Every other day she travels into Tokyo by the
electric trainrarely getting a seat, for young
men don't make room for girls to attend
classes at a fashion school where students
learn dressmaking, designing and dancing.
Out of classes Michiko loves to stroll through
Tokyo's streets, "window shopping" and
admiring the dresses with a growing profes¬
sional eye. Returning home in the evening,
she prepares her work for the next day or
sets about altering one of her dresses. She
has quite an extensive wardrobe: four two-
piece dresses, five one-piece dresses, two
kimonos and six pairs of shoes. VVith the
kimono she always wears the Japanese "gethas"
(wooden shoes). Michiko, in fact, lives the
easy and care-free life of a middle-class girl.
She is on good terms with her parents who
allow her plenty of freedom. "If you think
it is right, then do it; if you think it is wrong,
then don't", her father tells her. She uses
powder and lipstick, nail polish, face lotion
and oil for the hair. In the home she helps
her mother with the houseworkbut without
much enthusiasm. Before meals she always
says a prayer before the shrine of Buddha in the
house, and every two weeks she changes the
flowers and leaves that decorate it. When she
is not in school she likes to read the paper and
listen to the radio (plays and Western classical
music are her favourites). In the evening she
helps her mother to prepare dinner, and then
comes the most delightful time of the day for
the family. They are all together and tell each
other the happenings of the day. Michiko
has plenty of friends, but no boy-friend in
the Western sense. She would like one older
than herself with whom she could talk about
everything. She hopes to marry and have three
or four children, but no more. Overpopula¬
tion in our country is a menace, she says,
"and we women have an obligation there".
CHANGES IN THE WARDROBE. MICHIKO MAKES HER OWN DRESSES. STUDY IN SKIPPING. HEALTH GOES WITH BEAUTY. CONFIDENCES IN THE LUNCH HOUR. A CLASSICAL HEAD IS EAVESDROPPING.
26 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A UNIVERSITY UNION MEETINGTALK, SMOKE
A BOWL OF "SENCHA" (ORDINARY TEA) IN THE STUDENT CANTEEN.
I «...
life*.*
^ RARE RELAXATIONA CHAT AND "SAKE" IN A KYOTO BAR
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. K«' 4-5. 1954
AND SUNLIGHT FILL THE ROOM. GORO WORKS FOR THIS UNION.
'» HI
*r*
J-*~
AN OLD TRADITIONSPORT, BUT NOWADAYS JUST FOR SPORT'S SAKE.
A. BREAK FOR. LUNCHTEA, NOODLE SOUP, FISH STEAKS.
A LIGHT BURNS UNTIL THE EARLY HOURS.
Student's
profile...
(KYOTO)
Goro Suma is a law student at Kyoto University. As his
family lives far away in the north of Honshu, the main Japan¬
ese island, Goro rents a tiny room where he studies and
sleeps. He takes his meals in a restaurant nearby rice,
mussel soup, "natto" (a kind of bean), "tsukudani" (seaweed
with small fish) figure largely on the menuor preferably
at the student canteen where food is cheaper. Apart from his
books, he owns three suits, two uniforms (student clothes),
a pullover, two pairs of shoes and a pair of gumshoes. To pay
for his studies he works as secretary of the university profes¬
sors' and employees' union. For this he is paid 6,000 yen
(almost $20 per month). He spends 3,000 yen on food,
1,000 on books, and every day he rations himself to I 5 cigar¬
ettes of the cheapest brand (30 yen) and he buys a news¬
paper each evening (90 yen per month). As much of his
time is taken up with his work for the University Union,
Goro "burns the candle" until about two each morning to
catch'up with his studies. But he still finds time for games
of baseball and ping-pong and occasionally for skiing. Like
most Japanese youth he is interested in films, especially
"realistic" ones and is fond of Western classical music. He
disagrees with his father on many matters, but when he
is in trouble he seeks his father's advice. He does not belong
to any religious sect. Goro wants to become a teacher and
he hopes to marry soon. He intends to have two children.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Equality between
the sexes, but...
Til
arp a Bamboo Pole
The carp is a Japanese symbol of courage and perseverance. Every May 5th, for the Boys Festival
(Tan-go-no-sek-fcu) bamboo poles are raised outside every house from which fly Ko-noborl, hollow
fish made of gaily painted paper or clothone fish for every young son in the family. The fish (here
floating before the castle of Osaka) serve as symbols for boys In overcoming the difficulties they meet.
30
Well-dressed bride and ¿room:
Autumn (September to November) is the most
popular wedding season of the year in Japan. Most
brides wear very elaborate kimono at the ceremony,
and traditionally are given a taka-shimada coiffure,
with a white hairband to cover the "horns of
jealousy" that all women are superstitiously believed
to possess. The old custom of shaving the eyebrows
(Continued from page 25)
oí freedom had been misinterpreted.
"Democracy is not properly under¬
stood", they said.
But the view held by older people
and teachers that young people" are no
longer interested in family life was not
borne out by other investigations.
Attitudes of the young towards the
hierarchical system in the family are
undoubtedly changing but youth still
appear to attach a good deal of
importance to family values.
Both boys and girls gave first place
to family relationships when asked to
indicate from which activities they
expected to get most satisfaction in
life. They gave it preference over such
alternatives as careers, community
work, religious beliefs, etc. , On another
occasion people were asked to name a
particular thing they hoped to achieve
during their lives.- Many replies
showed concern for family affairs
"to be a good son or daughter;"
"to bring up one's children properly."
A dilemma for youth
no way out
IN Japan young people depend psy¬
chologically on their families and
also look to them for economic
security. And that is why many
attempts by young people to eman¬
cipate- themselves come to nothing.
The psychological predicament of
some is reflected in the following frag¬
ment of a conversation with a youth
of 17, the son of a purged- officer:
Question: Do you think that when you.
are a man you will be happier than
you were as a child?
Answer: Yes, I think so.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. r\- 4-3. 1954
and blacking out the teeth is no longer kept up. According to custom the
room where the marriage takes place is decorated with lucky emblems
storks for fertility, bamboos for plenty and tortoises for wisdom. The '
bridegrooms, however, are usually dressed in Western style. But as soon
as the ceremony is over, most couples start on their honeymoon in their very
best Western dress! Although a Japanese officially reaches his majority
when he is 20 and is granted the right to vote, the real line of demarcation
between adolescence and adulthood is considered to be marriage and even
parenthood since the marriage is often not registered before the birth of
the first child. Fatherhood makes a man a full member of the community
while motherhood entitles the wife to smoke, drink and tell indelicate stories.
In traditional Japan all marriages were arranged by the parents. Todaywlth
new legal freedom, young men can choose their own wives. Curiously,
though, many seem reluctant to become adults and are using their new
freedom to postpone marriage as long as possible. It is quite usual nowadays
for young men to wait until they are 26 or even 30 before getting married.
Do you think your children will
be happier than you have been?
I will try to make them happier.
Will your wife be happier than
your mother has been?
I think so.
What do you want to do in life?
I want to teach in a university.
My father was an officer, but I do not
want to be one. Being a military man
made my father very hard with his wife "
and children. Now that he is a farmer
he is less hard. My brother was an
officer and he too was very hard.
Since he was purged he is less hard
than before.
At what age do you intend to"
marry? Will you follow your parents'
advice?
I shall marry when I am 25 or 26.
. I shall ask my parents' advice and then
decide for myself.
Do you approve of the traditional
marriage by arrangement?
No, I disapprove, but I think that
when one is older, one understands and
approves one's father's advice. I now
realize that my father's orders and
advice to me were sound. My mother
was too soft; she spoilt me.
But you just said- that your
children would be happier than you
have been. In other words you don't
consider that your childhood was
happy. Now you say that you approve
of the way your father brought you up.
Does that mean you will bring your
own children up in the same way?
Before, you said the opposite.
To this the youth did not reply. He
realized the contradiction but saw no
way out of his quandary.
It is easy to imagine how this youth .
was dragooned in his childhood, not
only by his father but also by his elder
brother; how he suffered from it; how
he longs to emancipate himself now
and identifying himself, with his
future children how he wants to give
them a more liberal upbringing.
But the prestige of paternal wisdom
still strongly impresses him. He may
say he disapproves of the traditional
marriage by arrangement, but admits
he will seek his father's advice before
getting married. He may even go
further, for he acknowledges that his
father's advice was sound. And he
. blames his mother for not being
sufficiently strict.
The officer's son was moulded by a
more autocratic upbringing than the
majority of young Japanese so his case
is not by any means representative.
Wider investigations do show, however,
that the country's tradition of respect
Y o f u k u
versus
i ni o n o
Many Japanese, es¬
pecially in the cities,
live a "dual life" wear¬
ing yofuku (Western
clothes) out-of-doors
and kimono (Japanese
dress) at home though
the reverse can also be
seen. Western dress
is preferred in street
because it is easier to
get about in. Here
with confidence and a
sense of total equality.
They no longer walk
the small, mincing
steps of their mothers
and grandmothers in
their kimonos.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A new wind blows across
ancient
and obedience
still , remains
strong.
Although on¬
ly a relatively
small propor¬
tion of people
(between 8 %
and 16 % ac¬
cording to age
groups) said
they thought children should .obey their
parents in all circumstances, a remark¬
ably high proportion (50 %) preferred
not tb offer an opinion. This shows
how many are still influenced by a
tradition of obedience and even when
they do not approve of it are still not
prepared to commit themselves."
A drudge and the
butt of mother-in-law
THE same poll showed that it was
not the younger groups who spoke
up- most frequently for emanci¬
pation within the family. "One gets
the impression", concluded the inves¬
tigators, "that it will be difficult for
the young to win emancipation in the
family by themselves; it is more likely
to be granted them from outside."
Similarly, younger groups showed the
. greatest caution in accepting new ideas
regarding the functioning of the family.
A case in point is the status of the
mother-in-law and her traditional
treatment of her daughter-in-law,
whose position is not an enviable one
for, living away from her own family,
she is often the household drudge and
butt of the older woman.
Of the people questioned in Tokyo,
41 % thought that a change was need¬
ed in this traditional relationship,
against only 2 % who saw nothing
wrong in it. Of the remainder, 30 %
condemned the- situation without sug¬
gesting any change, and 27 % had no
opinion to offer.
This, of course, is just one aspect of
a much wider problem raised by
the status of Japanese women who
traditionally are minors and whose
position is fixed according to the
Confucian maxim: "A woman owes
obedience three times in her life, to
her parents when she is young, to her
husband when she is married, and to
her children when she is old."
Though this rule is not applied
rigidly in all parts of the country, the
inferior lot of women is still in many
cases a reality, both established and
sanctioned by law prior to the war,
and recognized in the customs of today.
Before 1945, women had no vote and
were only allowed to own property
conjointly with their husbands; they
32
could claim no share in the estate of
their deceased husbands or fathers and
could not initiate divorce proceedings.
Under the new régime they have equal'
rights with men. But personal status
is not determined merely by law; it is
only given real effect by popular
acceptance. Nowadays women have
the right to demand a divorce, but
many men laugh heartily at the idea
of a wife taking the initiative in break¬
ing up the marriage.
In everyday life, the 'wife takes her
meals separately, serves her husband
and stays at home, or, when she does
go out with her husband, walks some
paces behind him. It is only when a
Japanese woman is wearing Western
dress that she will walk beside a man
in the street and precede him through
doors; back at home in her kimono,
she will serve dinner to her husband
and his European guests but will not eat
with them herself.
It is not only the prolonged influence
of Confucian' .ethics which determines
the social inferiority of women.
Another important factor is her mar¬
riage role. To the Japanese, love counts
among the minor satisfactions and is
kept quite apart from the serious things
. of life, in which the family is included.
A woman's primary role the bearing
of children to perpetuate the family
line overides other personal consider¬
ations. .
The fact that they were able to earn
their own living helped Western women,
to earn their freedom. Japanese women
who aspire to emancipation, also seek it
by the same path. This is why many
country girls, both before and since the
war, have sought employment in the
cities. But progress in achieving
freedom has been slow. A 1948 survey
showed that out of 100 women in paid
employment more than half had
accepted the jobs without knowing
what the work was or what pay was
attached to it."
Casting their votes
to avoid ridicule
POLITICALLY women have equal
rights and crowd the polling
booths at election time, but their
political life usually stops there. An
enquiry in a country area showed that
women voted to avoid ridicule. In
their votes they preferred to
follow the
lead of pro- .
minent local
women ra¬
ther than ask
the advice of
their men-
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N"» 4-5. 1954
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Giri' the word with a
thousand and one meanings
folk. Men were amused at the idea of
women having political rights ; and,
indeed, women themselves said they
thought it was too early for them to
take part in politics.
In Japan, as in most countries, tra¬
ditions are maintained more strongly
in the countryside than in the cities.
Broader surveys showed that, osten¬
sibly at any rate, the majority of
people had accepted the principle of
equal status of women, and this was
ecpecially so in the case of the young.
'Fine ideas but
they are not for us'
WHEN representative groups were
asked: "Are women right to
profess their own inferiority?"
91 % of the men replied '"No".
Women were slightly less positive, only
86 % giving the same answer. A si¬
milarly large majority of both sexes
thought that girls should be given as
good an education as boys.
Whether the young people of Japan
are already prepared to work actively
and personally for equality between
A Kabuki
'actress'
Japan has two kinds of
dramathe classical and
the modern. Kabuki, the
most important of the clas¬
sical dramas began centu¬
ries ago, so the story goes,
when the shrine darner
O-Kuni danced on a river
bed with improvisations
of her own and caught
the popular fancy. The
company of men and wo¬
men dancers she and her
husband later organized
became the people's thea¬
tre. It underwent many
changes before it attained
its present prestige, one
being that men play all
roles including those of
women (photo right). Ka¬
buki is a combination of
acting, singing and dancing
with costumes and stage
settings of fabulous colours.
Though Kabuki the time-
honoured stage art of
Japan is still enormously
popular with the older
generation the youth of
Japan today prefer modern
drama and the cinema.
V
the sexes is less sure. A discussion
between investigators and a represen¬
tative group of young men and girls in
Nemuro helped to throw some light on
this question. Primarily the questions
concerned co-education, and as. long as
the discussion was restricted to matters
of principle full agreement was shown
on equality of status between men and
women.
But as soon as the practical impli¬
cations of such equality were discussed
'Should it be possible for a woman
to become Mayor of this town?";
"Could any of the girls here become
town councillors?" the young people
first showed astonishment, then inde¬
cision and finally they withdrew from
their first emphatic agreement on
equality of status.
The feeling they expressed was :
"These are very fine principles and we
admire them because we see others
admiring them; but they have not yet
been put into practice here, they are
not for us; elsewhere conditions must
be such as to make them possible;
conditions here are not like that."
Students at Kyoto and Sapporo uni¬
versities were asked this question: "If
you get married and have a family,
who do you expect will be more in¬
fluential in the direction and control
of the affairs of the family?" A clear
majority said they intended to apply
the principle of sex equality in their
own homes. Yet, even among these
cultivated young people, who are
absorbing the whole range of liberal
ideas and are destined to be the leaders
of the new democratic Japan, 12 % of
the male students at Sapporo, and 16 %
of the women students and 21 % of the
men at Kyoto considered that affairs
in their own homes would be run by
the husband.
Most Westerners have the impression
that marriages in Japan are arranged
and decided by parents, and that the
future marriage partners have little or
nothing to say in the matter. In
actual fact, reported the Unesco inves¬
tigators, it is doubtful whether this has
been the universal custom in recent
times. Today, in any case, this type
of marriage is favoured only by a very
small minority.
Though many young people now
regard the love-match as the ideal, it
seems certain that an intermediate
type of arranged marriage, in which
the interests and the preferences of the
two families and of the couple concern¬
ed are all taken into account, is, and
will continue to be the most common.
"It can hardly be said," added the
researchers, "that this particular type
of marriage is a novelty in Japan."
The unimportance of
being in love
LOVE does not seem to occupy a
very prominent place in the life
of young Japanese to judge by the
results of an enquiry made among
students at Kyoto and Sapporo who
were asked to name the three most
significant events in their past exis¬
tence. Love was rarely mentioned in
the answers of these young people who
were at what is generally regarded as
the "romantic age". It was men¬
tioned by 18 % at Sapporo and 10 %
at Kyoto. This second percentage,
being an average of male and female
replies is smaller because only 5 % of
the girls included love in their replies.
The male percentage was 17 % almost
the same as for the Sapporo (all-male)
answers.
In the overturning of traditional
values and beliefs do the youth of
Japan still have a clear pattern of rules
of conduct to guide them in life? How
are they affected by the crisis through
which their country's traditional mor¬
ality is passing ? Since the war the
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N"" 4-5. 1954
^nft
> *^
F\
ifc
Democracy
in the class
The Japanese have always been
interested In education as the
nation's 99 per cent literacy rate
shows, but as one teacher recently
put It: "Our pupils are learning
more than facts now. They're
learning how to be responsible
citizens in a closely-knit world."
Since the end of the war Japan's
I whole education system has been
g completely transformed. New text¬
books have been written, the teach¬
ing of militarism and ultra-nation¬
alism abolished and emphasis plac¬
ed on social studies. Strong accent
Is put on oral activities such as
conversation, using the telephone,
school broadcasting transmissions,
"recitations" in class, class discus¬
sions, round tables and symposiums,
extempore speeches and participa¬
tion in discussions conducted on
parliamentary lines. The study of
Chinese classics has been suppressed.
Important reforms have been made
in the teaching of the Japanese
language (there are four different,
ways of writing it and four widely
differing styles). Compulsory prim¬
ary education has been prolonged
for one year to the age of 1 5.
Many more girls now attend senior
high schools and colleges but the
percentage Is still far from high.
teaching of ethics has been suspended
in the schools. Adults frequently com¬
plain about the immorality, of the
young. In the universities, the Unesco
- investigators were sometimes told:
"There is too much academic, and -not
enough moral teaching. We ought to
be teaching a new code of morals."
To test this situation questions were
put to representative groups of people
concerning giri, the basic traditional
moral conduct of Japan. It is not easy
for Westerners to understand giri and
indeed the Japanese in their dictio¬
naries can hardly define it.
Its great importance in Japanese life
and ethics was stressed by Ruth Bene¬
dict in The Chrysanthemum and^the
Sword. This is how she understood it.
The relations between men in society
are regulated that is, a set of rules
of conduct exists. The Western com¬
ment on a person who does not observe '
the rules is "he does not know how' to
behave." What the Japanese often say
is "he does not know giri". A rough
equivalent of the phrase might be "he
does not know his duty" or "he does
not recognize his obligations". But
giri does not mean just any kind of
obligation. ' The Japanese have a
complex vocabulary of. debt-notions,
each . with special types of meanings
which enmesh Japanese life with an
intricate network of commitments. ~~ .
First : there is the on . (pronounced
own). A person who receives a favour
is said to "receive an on" or to "wear
an on". He thus becomes a "debtor".
There are certain debts which
everyone is born with, which are com¬
pulsory, considered limitless, the obli¬
gation never fully repaid. According
to Japanese tradition, this life-long,
universal debt (called gimu) is due to
the Emperor, to one's father and
mother, to one's ancestors and to one's
country. "Japanese say "one never re¬
pays one ten-thousandth of (this) on."
A tradition which is
now dying out
GIRI is not a limitless, abstract con¬
ception of duty or moral obliga¬
tion or even compulsory as gimu
is. It is a form of debt-contract obli¬
gation one underwrites on receiving an
on. To neglect giri means, in a nut-'
shell, failure to honour one's undertak¬
ings, the destruction of one's credit,
exactly as in bankruptcy.
The Unesco enquiry tends to show
that the notion of giri is not as univer¬
sally understood and applied as Ruth
Benedict believed, that instead it is a
tradition which seems to be growing
weaker since the young are less
acquainted with it and less interested
in the concept. At the same time since
it does survive to -a' greater extent in
cities than in rural areas, it appears to
be an aristocratic rather than a popular
feature of Japanese society.
Consequently, if we leave aside tech¬
nical consideration of the nature of
giri and of the way this concept was
disseminated among the Japanese
public, we find, as regards the young,
in particular, that they show a mini¬
mum knowledge not merely of tradi¬
tional and limited moral values but
even of the general morality.
Those who have reached adult status
betray this shortcoming by their less
refined thinking, while among the
youngest obvious gaps can be discern¬
ed. It is not possible to attempt a
forecast on the strength of the evidence
so far available. Will subjects who
have not yet reached the age of twenty
develop, as they grow older, on the
same lines as their elders? Or will
they advance beyond the point their
elders have reached? To answer these
questions we should have to know, not
only the ethical development of the
individuals concerned, but also, without
doubt, the direction Japan will take
now that the end of the Occupation
has left her to her own devices.
All photos on pages I, 2, 12-35, are copyright by
Magnum. Photos, ' Black Star and the Mainichl
' Newspapers.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Sir,
I am pleased to inform you that the
Ministry of Education is so impressed
by the superior quality of the Courier
and its photographs that it is noto
planning to make a regular series of
¡ilmstrips based on Courier material.
The Ministry will begin by making film-
strips of most of the illustrations con¬
cerning the Republic of Haiti which
appeared in Vol. VII, No 2.
F. Vandenborre
Director-General, *
Educational and Cultural Services,
Ministry of Education,
1 Brussels.
: Sir.
Have you heard any of the musique
1 concrète that there is an article on in
the Courier this month (N° 3) ? / heard
Í Schaeffer's Symphonie pour un Homme
. Seul, and found that twenty minutes was
as much as I could bear.
The last edition was, I thought, a
thousand times better than any other
; issue I have had. The others, I found,
: usually had one or tico really interesting
¡ articles, but this one was very interest-
! ing all through. It is much better in
\ its new shape. I don't mean by this
that I did not think it was good
before, but it is now so much better
that I feel it calls for special praise.
: The photos are surprisingly good for
photos on newsprint.
Julian Farr (aged 17)
I Durham,
; England.
Sir,
... It's a pity that there is no German
language edition for wider distribution
''. - in our country.»
Franz Schmidt
: Head,
: Education Department,
"Konsumverband",
Austria.
Sir,
... The old format was unusual, suitable
to dramatic treatment of issues. New
format is more conventional, less dra¬
matic, presents fewer opportunities for
unique artistic treatment.
U.S.A. George Gerbuer
Sir,
How different your first two issues
i of 1954 are from those which I received
' up until December 1953. It is sad to
' ¡ee how so admirable a review can
decline instead of improving».
Benita Asas Manterola
Bilbao, Spain.
I consider that the - Courier fills an
important need. I am recommending it
for special reading to prospective
teachers in my classes in the Teaching
of Social Science which I give in addi¬
tion to my classes in Geography...
U.S.A. Clara Hinze
Sir,
I consider the Unesco Courier one of
the finest publications ' in the world
today. Material, writing and artwork '
are all superb. I would like to see the
Courier "lean over backwards" to in¬
clude material on Soviet culture, science
and education... I would! hope to see
editions in the near future in Hindi,
Russian, German and Chinese even if
it would require a rise in subscription
rates in the English edition. The Rus¬
sian and Chinese editions would be
small with the aim of gradually leaking
into their respective countries.
U.S.A. ' . Harold Iischner
Sir,
... We subscribe to The Courier which
comes here by surface route. If our
copy of The Courier could be air¬
mailed, perhaps "we could put the
material to greater use by distributing
translations (in Gujarati). We wish to
express the fervent hope that a Hindi
(India's national language) edition of
The Courier will be published at the
earliest, so that a link is established bet¬
ween millions of our countrymen and
their comrades in other lands "working
for a richer life in a peaceful world."
Mahendra Meghani
Editor "Milap",
Bhavnagar, India.
Sir,
... The language map you publish in
issue No. 1 1954 is wellnigh indeci¬
pherable...
Ü.S.A. Raines F. Meyerowitz
Sir,
On the map "The World's Lan¬
guage Families" the Estonian area is
marked as belonging to Slavic language
family, in fact Estonian is a Finno-Ugric
language... Estonian is still the lan¬
guage of the majority of the people in
Estonia.
Valter Tauli
Chairman, Cultural Committee,
Estonian National Council,
'Stockholm, Sweden.
Sir,
...More light should be thrown on the
various activities of Unesco to give
sufficient idea of it even to the layman	
SJi. Sinha
Headmaster,
High School,
Colgong, Bihar, India.
Sir,
In this unstable world the part Unesco
plays and will play for the mutual un¬
derstanding and lasting world peace is
great. To understand more closely each
other, I want to correspond with the
people of the world and exchange .
knowledge or opinions. And I shall be
very happy if you will give me- an'
opportunity to have friends in foreign
countries through your periodical or
other means.
I am a Japanese boy, 23 years old.
My hobbies are sports, reading, walking,
collecting stamps. I understand English,
French and some German and Spanish...
Mototaka Yamakami
92 1-chôme, Yamasaka-cho,
Higashi-Sumiyoshi-ku,
Osaka, Japan.
ALMERÍA, with 80,000 inhabitants,
is the capital of the most
southerly - province of eastern
Andalusia. It has been described as
one of the forgotten provinces of Spain.
Its poor communications and the fact
that it lies off ' the beaten track of
trade and tourism have always kept it
somewhat apart from the main
currents of culture in Spain.
' The city has some historic buildings,
such as the magnificent Alcazaba. The
climate is dry (rain is almost unknown)
and the light brilliant. Save in two
fertile valleys watered from the Sierra
Nevada and producing grapes that are
exported all over the world, not a blade .
of grass or a bush is to be found
growing naturally anywhere in the
province. The surplus population re¬
gularly emigrates to other richer and
more prosperous provinces along the
eastern seaboard.
Such was the setting in which, as
part of a general scheme which started
hundreds of libraries in all the pro¬
vinces of Spain, a library was opened
in Almería in 1947.
The new library was named after
one of the province's poets, Francisco
Villaespesa, the poet of the Tierra
Arabe and the last troubadour of
Al'Andalus. Today it contains more
than 30,000 volumes. Even so, it would
not be particularly noteworthy, were it
not for the undoubted influence it has
had on the artistic and cultural life of
the province.
Books began it all
IT began like all libraries : as a
depository for books, with a read¬
ing-room. The reading room was
soon crowded out, for everyone went
there every day. Books were issued on
loan; subscriptions' to reviews were
taken out; and exhibitions were begun.
Thus the library was popular, function¬
al and dynamic; but, as well as that, it
soon became the most effective adult
education centre in the province.
In addition to books, the best media
for the spread of culture were brought
into play films, pictures, concerts,
radio, plays, puppet shows and strip
recordings. There is an auditorium,
separate from the library proper, with
a seating capacity of 250, and here
numerous concerts have been presented
with the best known/ performers of
Spain. These activities have had a
profound effect on the town.
The library has likewise started a
music section which includes some 200
works for quintets and quartets.
Today the whole undertaking has
overflowed from the purely local orbit
and numerous concerts have been given
in the towns of the province where-
ever possible, in their own libraries.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. M" 4-5. 1954
A forgotten Spanish province 'wakes up'
by Tena Artigas
Director Unesco Relations,
Painting in the province has un¬
dergone a profound change since the
founding of the library. Encouraged
by the lectures and discussions on. art
provided, a group of young painters
began to meet at the library. These
young men,' the majority of whom were
poor, constituted a nucleus of pioneer¬
ing artists and writers who have given
a new impetus to artistic life in the
province and have achieved a renown
which in some cases for example
Percival, Capuleto and Alcaraz has
gone beyond the national frontiers.
There is a stylized totem in Almeria
of great antiquity, which looks rather
like a silhouette of a man with a
skipping-rope but is in fact the figure
An imposing wall encloses the ancient- castle
where not a blade of grass or a bush is to be
Spanish Ministry of Education
. of a man or god holding in his hands
the rainbow which foretells fan-
weather. This symbol the group re¬
vived and called "Indalo", a gipsy
corruption of "Indalecio", the com¬
monest name in Almeria. Saint In¬
dalecio, one of the six "apostles" of
Spain, landed a few kilometres away
at Urci, the modern Pechina; and the
Christianization of the peninsula began
from there.
The "Indalics" believe that they too
have an evangel to proclaim, a new
aesthetic to preach, and it was in the
Francisco Villaespesa library that the
new movement came to life. Later
they were called to Madrid by the
philosopher Eugenio D'Ors who
arranged an exhi¬
bition of their
works in the Na¬
tional Museum of
Modern Art. To¬
day several of
them have achiev¬
ed success and
their works, which
always bear as well
as their signatu¬
res, the dancing
silhouette of the
genie of the south,
can be found in
Madrid, Paris,
Rome or Buenos
Aires. Many others
of the group have
remained in Alme¬
ria and the Fran¬
cisco Villaespesa
library is still their
meeting place.
Of the 31 lectu¬
res given in the
library during the
present academic
year, a . number
have been on topi¬
cal subjects the
latest advances of
science ; the cam¬
paign against in¬
fantile paralysis;
new medicines to
combat tuberculo¬
sis; talks on the
latest works in
Spanish literature
by their authors,
and lecture - con¬
certs which are
always very well
received by the
public. Some of
.these have been
given by first-rate
scholars and well-
of Alcazaba in Almeria
found growing naturally.
known contemporary authors and
composers.
Within three years of its foundation,
the library had 17 branch libraries in
full operation, and 12 travelling libra¬
ries through which it has been possible
to get books to the most distant corners
of the province.
The work of the library has won the
interest of the provincial population at
every level, from the governor (who
initiated the idea and provided the
money for - the building) to those to
whom any form of cultural activity is
normally most alien.
A Society of Friends of the Library
was founded and now has 500 mem¬
bers. This was the first association in
the city with a' purely cultural objec¬
tive. The public have a decisive say
in the library's administration.
Each year new services are set up,
drawing all citizens more closely into
the library's activities and reflecting
their desires.
Cultural 'irrigation'
OTHER departments are a biblio¬
graphical information service from
which data can be secured by
letter, by telephone or by personal visit,
a periodicals library and micro-film
service, the provincial copyright re¬
gister and the legal deposit of printed
matter.
The press and the two broadcasting
stations of the locality are constantly
used to arouse the interest of the
population and draw . attention to
. the library's various services.
Thirty thousand volumes have been
distributed over the 20 branch libraries.
They receive about 200 reviews; and
the number of readers rose from 4,224
in 1947, to 149,235 by 1952.
Those of us who, from outside, have
followed the surprising growth of this
model library, believe that many
factors contributed to it and made it
possible the perfect interlocking of
effort, the help and interest of the
authorities, the enthusiasm of those in
charge, and perhaps the fact of having
hit on the method which best suited the
special outlook of the populace. What
is certain is that its cultural work was
as readily absorbed in the district, and
has had as beneficial an effect, as would
be water coming to irrigate its dry
fields. Some of the fruits of the
library's efforts for instance the work
of the "Indalic" painters can, like the
district's splendid grapes, be exported,
and the library is as much a symbol of
hope as the rainbow skipping-rope
which the prehistoric totem "holds in
its hands.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
*4
.A
A4 ,
&
a*.
>
WA
EL DORADO' IN COLOMBIA
Art worth its weight in gold
For centuries the golden treasure of the
pre-Conquest inhabitants of South America
has captured man's imagination. The various
legends of "El Dorado" led to the exploration
of half a continent and the discovery of the
Amazon River, and lured Sir Walter Raleigh
on the ill-fated expedition that .finally cost
him his head ; legends that were immortal¬
ized in literature by Milton and Voltaire.
In both America and the Old World gold
was the first metal to be known and worked
because it was found in rivers or in veins in
the mountains, and because the most prim¬
itive technique for working gold was much
the same as that of working stone. Man
. was attracted by the colour of gold, and could
make a piece of nugget into a sheet by
beating it with one stone," using a fiat stone as an anvil.
It is not yet definitely known when and where the
invention of working gold took place in America but the
most likely regions are Peru, Equator and Colombia. In
these countries gold objects dating from about 300 AD.
have been identified, and allowing for the time required
to develop working techniques, it is possible to place the
origin of goldwork in this region as several centuries before
the Christian era.
The area's extraordinary wealth of native gold suggests
that it wa,s here that the working of gold first began in
Latin America, and certainly in no region did the art and
techniques of the indigenous goldsmith reach a higher state
of development than it did here.
Gold was melted in stone or clay crucibles and the molten
metal was poured into open or two piece moulds of stone
or fired clay.
Ornamental elements were attached by welding or by
using as a solder some other metal, having a lower melting
point than the parts to be joined. Metal, wood, stone or
shell objects were covered or sheathed with gold foil.
Sometimes sheets of gold foil were moulded in sections on
an object and were joined together with staples of gold
wire or tiny gold rivets.
These were the treasures prized only for their intrinsic
value and sought after by the Conquistadores and those
who followed them. It was, in fact, only a century ago that
.the first scientific studies of .the native pre-Hispanic gold-
work found in Colombia were made.
Towards the end of the 19th century, however, some
Colombians began to form private archeological collections
which included not only ceramics and stone pieces but
also gold objects. Some came from accidental finds and
others were bought from the "guaqueros" who made a
living by hunting for and robbing pre-Hispanic tombs in
which a wealth of gold was hidden.
Since 1939, many of the most important private collections
have been purchased by Colombia's National Bank, the
Banco de la República, and are now assembled in the Gold
Museum established by the Bank in Bogota, the capital.
The Museo del Oro was set up as a cultural centre to house
what Colombians rightly regard as an important part of
the nation's artistic and historic patrimony.
Today the collection of the Museo del Oro numbers 6,726
pieces, four times as many pre-Hispanic gold objects from
Colombia as exist in all the other museums and private
collections in the world put together. Human and animal
figures, armlets, bangles, necklaces, ceremonial implements,
body ornaments representing individual styles peculiar to
certain regions leave the visitor to the Gold Museum
marvelling at the mastery of technique and expression of
beauty achieved by the ancient craftsmen.
Recently, the Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York,
and several other museums in the United"States have been
exhibiting a selection of 80 of these golden treasures, "which
were loaned to them by Colombia's Gold- Museum and from
which the examples published , in these pages are taken.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°" 4-5. 1954
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
PRESENTS
WorldWithoutEnd
"E,
1VERYTHING that has to do with human beings has something to do with me too. " This
is the enduring vision and the enduring fact that the Unesco film "World Without End" vividly
proclaims. "World Without End" is a story about the United Nations and the people of the United
Nations about fishermen and doctors, rice-farmers and teachers, nurses and mothers, children
and grown-ups. The story unfolds in Mexico and Siam but is just as true for other countries where
today people are at work teaching and learning how to grow more food, how to live healthier lives,
how to share the United Nations' ideal of progress and prosperity in a peaceful world.
Two world-famous film makers, Paul Rotha and Basil Wright, working together at opposite ends
of the earth, have created this one hour documentary film of the world's knowledge at work for the
people of the world. The film has already been seen by some 250 million people on TV screens and
in theatres in the United Kingdom, United States, France, Germany, Denmark and numerous other
countries. In the United States, the "Saturday Review" called "World Without End" "...the most
vibrant and emphatic statement yet made on film about our postwar world..." The "New York
Times" critic, Howard Thompson, termed it "a truly masterful blend of sensitivity and realism...
directed with compass-needle precision." "Canadian Newsreel" wrote, "film societies should hound
their cinemas, public libraries, film councils... even write letters to Parliament if need be, in order
to get it shown as widely as possible." Film critic Jack Smith of "Look and Listen", London, said,
"the film should be shown often and everywhere ; in schools it will teach young people to see
that benevolent internationalism is no cold ¡deal but can have a warm heart and a sturdy pur¬
pose... It could tug at the conscience of the world." On the following pages, "The Unesco Courier"
is proud to present the script of "World Without End" written by Rex Warner and selected
photos from the film. A few short passages are omitted for reasons of space.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 4-5. 1954
"lama man myself, arid I think that everything
which has to do with human beings has something
to do with me too. "
We are looking at human beings and we are
seeing something oí two countries where they live.
In the West, Mexico. In the East, Thailand, or Siam.
as many people still call it. Different languages,
different religions, different animals, trees and
flowers.
Yet in both places people get their living from
the earth and from the water; in both places people
feel pain and hunger, and people enjoy health and
the good things of life. They have enemies and
they have friends. They have children and they
want their children to be happy.
MEXICO
This man's name is Faustino. He is a Tarascan
Indian. His country is Mexico. He is a fisherman
who lives on an island in Lake Patzcuaro.
Long ago, before any European came to the Amer¬
icas, this lake was the centre of the great Tarascan
Empire. The Tarascan Indians still live here. They
have lost their empire; but they still get their living
from the lake, and they retain their old love for
music and for singing.
It is a market day in Patzcuaro and the Indians
have come in to the town from the islands where
they live, from the settlements along the lake shore
and from the villages in the mountains that
surround the lake., This is a social occasion,' as
well as the occasion for buying and selling. There
1
are processions to be enjoyed, and all the noise too.
It's like an old-fashioned revolution.
Here also is something which is, in its own way,
like a revolution. The people In the launch are
students who belong to an organization called
Crefal... Crefal means "the Fundamental Education¬
al Centre in Latin America". It is supported by
"Unesco and by the governments of 21 nations in the
New World.
3
Every day this team
of students goes to one
of the "islands in Lake
Patzcuaro this one
is where Faustino Uves.
It is an island where,
since men first came to
it, Ufe has depended
on the water of the
lake and on the fishing
nets that are the
islanders' most
valuable possessions.
By this time the
people of the island know the students from Crefal
well and are glad to see them. There is Moreno,
who is a Mexican; Nellie who comes from Uruguay;
Tristan, the man who sings, is from Panama;
Torrico from Bolivia; Rene from Haiti; Violetta
from Cuba.
'3
4
Each student is studying some particular subject,
Uke agriculture, health or education. They are
Unked by these interests of theirs with one or other
of the United Nations Agencies which are dealing
on a world scale with the problems of knowledge,
health, food, work and the conditions of work. And
when, in the end, these students go back to their
own countries, they will no longer be students, but
teachers among their own people.
Now, what Crefal is doing for them is to prepare
them for this task and to give them the chance of
learning not only from books and lectures but also
from human beings. Their job is to learn about
how people Uve. To do this they must be able and
willing to help them.
'"* **Ç
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
- 5 -
It has become a custom for one
of the students to ring a bell, just
to show that the team has arrived.
Now they all set off to different
parts of the island. They are
here to learn how people live. You
cannot do this unless you under¬
stand the people. You cannot
understand them unless you
receive their confidence. You do
not deserve their confidence unless
you are prepared to love them and
to help them.
By now Moreno is an old friend
of Faustino and his family. He
can often give them advice which
is useful to them. A Mexican
himself, Moreno may, later on, be
able to help even more actively in
solving some of their problems.
But now, while he is training him¬
self for the future, he is learning
rather than teaching. He is
learning some very simple things
from a man who knows what he
is talking about.
For Faustino everything in¬
cluding his plans for the future of
his children depends on the lake,
the level is rapidly sinking?
Twenty years ago there were boats moored against
jetties that are now high and dry. Why is it that
there are not so many fish as there used to be,
and they are getting smaller, too ? It is not so
easy as it was to catch the big fish that can be
sold at a good price in the market. Why are weeds
and thick mud appearing in parts of the lake where
the water used to be clear and deep ?
SIAM
Life, Death, what changes and what does not
change. These are the themes of the religious
teachers, of poets and of philosophers.
In different countries .there are different ways. of
Why is it that approaching these problems, but the problems are
the same for all.
Here the religion is Buddhism. The country is
Siam. The people are by nature a happy people.
, Here, as in the island in Lake Patzcuaro, life
depends on water. The rich rice crops grow in the-
water and in the same fields grow the fish.
People talk of "the unchanging East". But there
are changes' all the same. Here the new and the
old, the changing and the unchanging are side by
side and are inter-related.
This is Bangkok, the Temple of the Dawn. Here, .
too, there is music on the water old tunes and
new tunes.
Those who live in this big city with its rich and
various life have the same difficulties as are known
in all big cities. Here, -too, there are slums as well
as fine buildings. There is tuber¬
culosis in the East as well as in the
West.
There are clinics to go to and
hospitals. - But it is also important
to deal with the disease in the
home itself, to give advice and
instruction which wUl help to
prevent spreading the infection to
other people in the family.
MEXICO
The work the nurses in Siam are
doing is the same kind of work,
perhaps, that NeUie wUl organize
later on in her own country in
Latin America.
- Now, by Lake Patzcuaro, in
Mexico, she is being rather success¬
ful at getting these chUdren
actually to like a haircut. When
she first suggested the idea, they -
used to run for miles; but now
they look forward to it. It isn't
entirely a joke. ' This beautiful
long hair is often crawling with
lice.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°» 4-5. 1954
_ 6
Violetta, who comes from Cuba, is good at embroi-'
dery, and Señora Salud enjoys learning. It is a
useful thing to learn, since embroidery fetches a
good price at the market, and when fishing doesn't
pay as well as it did an extra source of income is
all the more welcome.
There are moments in the life of the island when
everything seems to stand still, when everything is
calm.
SIAM
How can you be calm when your skin is covered
with painful and disgusting growths? These people
in Siam are suffering from a disease called Yaws,
which is found in nearly all tropical countries. It
is a disease which gets into the blood and affects
not only the skin but also the structure of the bones.
7
*S& It is extremely infectious; both the old and the
young can have it, and sometimes as many as 14 %
of the inhabitants of one village have it at the same
time. It poisons your mind as well as your body.
Your energy ebbs away and you lose hope. You lose
the will to live. And, so far as you know, there is
nothing whatever to be done about it; no possible
cure; no relief.
Within the last few years scientists have discov¬
ered that one injection of penicillin will produce a
complete cure in ten days.
But the medical team, has first to convince the
villagers that penicillin really is going to do them
8 9 -
good. It is a difficult thing for them to believe.
The teams who give the injections have had to
discover what is the quickest and least painful
method. This is because their own time is short.
MEXICO
There is a good deal of filth in the water of Lake
Patzcuaro. - People have washed their clothes in it
for generations, but they have not all been lucky or
strong enough to escape from the various illnesses
which come from the water. Here too, as Violetta is
explaining, the right kind of soap, full of DDT will
help. ,
Moreno and the other students, while they have
been learning from the islanders, have also been
spending their leisure hours with them. They have
^^^^^^^ worked together in
making a new
j basket - ball pitch
for the village.
As night begins to
fall the Indians and
the students gather
i % fort the local Fiesta.
i Together they sing
an old Tarascan
song which is called
"The Drum of Hap¬
piness".
SIAM
It is now dawn in
l> Siam, and here the
fishermen are casting their nets. Here there are
plenty of fish, and here the fishermen are untroubl¬
ed by the weeds which Faustino knows. But not
everywhere. Originally one or two roots of the
water hyacinth were introduced into Siam because
of the beauty of the flower. But this beautiful
flower, with its long roots, spread and spread,
choking up the water-ways, and making even the
water barren.
The farmers with handrakes will never catch up-
with-the flower they are attempting to destroy.
Dr. Ling, who comes from China, has been sent
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
- 10 -
by the Food and Agriculture Organization to work
with the Siamese.
By spraying the water hyacinths with hormone
weed-killer room can be made once more for the
fishermen and for the fish. Dr. Ling and his experts
are not only clearing the water; they are putting
bigger and better fish into it. So, in these waters,
there is likely, before long, to be more food than .
there has ever been.
MEXICO
The problem of water supply can be a big one
even if you live near a lake. The water has to reach
II
s^the higher ground where the villages are, and where
it is needed for irrigating the land and for house¬
hold purposes... These women have to carry every
drop of it for a mile up from Lake Patzcuaro.'
At this place the men are building a new well.
The next thing they will have to do is to save or to
borrow enough money to buy a pump and a filter.
When they get these, life will be a good deal easier
for the women, and the water will be pure.
SIAM
In Siam the great wealth of the teak forests in
the northern mountains has for a long time been
- 12
carefully preserved. A tree may take 100 years to
grow, and there is regular replanting of seedUngs.
None of the people who are doing the planting will
live to see the fuU-grown tree.
But there is no doubt about their interest in what
they are doing for future generations. It is a satis¬
faction to know that your work will live on after
you, and these men's work for the future makes it
safe to take the harvest of the present.
Five hundred "miles to the south of the teak
forests there are some villages where the farmers
also are thinking about ' the future. They have'
reclaimed land from the salt-mar-shes and on their
newly-won land they are experimenting in a new
way of living, pooling their manpower and their
equipment, and making their own plans for the use
of what they gain. In all this they are helped by
- 13
their own government and by experts from the
United Nations. In these communities books are
really valuable. Not a very great number of books
can be carried on a van on wheels, but a mobile
library is much better than none at -all, and all the
books that can be brought here will be read. These
libraries are provided by Unesco and by the Siamese
Ministry of Education.
Ignorance is not bliss, and wherever the opportu¬
nity is offered people are glad to escape from igno
rance. - Here, by Lake Patzcuaro, the first steps are
slow ones. But they become effective. People want
knowledge, and once they have begun to acquire it
they extend it amongst themselves.
In Siam new educational methods are being
.employed throughout the country. But when you
have a fine and old culture of your own, however
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. H°" 4-5. 1954
- 14 -
useful new methods can be, you don't want your
own unique things to disappear. It has -happened
too often in the world that an old culture has been
destroyed by contact with something new. It is
as important to carry on a cultural tradition as it
is to make certain that the forests are being
replanted.
Children here, as everywhere, like to act and to
dance. Later, when they grow up, they will be able
to appreciate and some of them will be able to carry
on the great tradition of their land.
We cannot dance or think; we cannot live at all
without food, shelter and health. Health has come
back to this vJUage which we last saw ten days ago.
How 'can you believe in a
miracle unless you have
actually seen it happen ? To
these people, who have seen
it and felt it, it still seems
too good to be true. And the
experts who h e lp e d to
organize the miracle are
rewarded by what they see.
They came a long way to do
this work. The man is from
Trinidad. The woman is
from Canada. Quite simply,
they wanted to do good, and
they have "succeeded. Child¬
ren are smiling who have sel- -
dorn or never smiled before.
MEXICO
When the students of
Crefal and many more like
them have finished their
course they will return to
their own countries in"Latin
America to apply the know¬
ledge of life and the sym¬
pathy with living people
which has come to them
partly by nature and partly
' by study and experience.
NEW YORK
Here, at the headquarters
of the United Nations at New
York, there are more flags
than those of Latin America,
and many more countries are
represented than Mexico and
Siam. It is an organization
which was formed because
people were, ashamed of the
past and because they had
hopes for the future. For
a long time the peoples of .the world have been"
organizing their fears and their hatreds.^ This is
something ' different ; and, though no organization
is perfect, no plans can be guaranteed to be success¬
ful, we do know this :
Love can cast out fear, and, as we have seen, it
is not impossible to love your neighbour. Now, as
the world shrinks, the neighbours are closer toge¬
ther. Moreno the student and the man on the
elephant, the fisherman and the farmer, the chil¬
dren, happy or unhappy, are not so far apart; and,
though we may not all have learnt to accept this
fact, .it is a fact that we all live in the same world,
with them and with others.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
GÍOODWILL FROM
WALES: Every year on May 18
a remarkable international
event takes place when the boys
and girls of Wales greet by radio
the boys and girls of the whole
world. For thirty-two years they
have sent out their message
by wireless, and this year, 1954,
with as much enthusiasm as
ever. Their goodwill message
said, in part, "We rejoice today
in all the efforts of men and
women of every race and peo¬
ple who are doing their best to
set the world free from war. By
our confidence and courage, by
our thoughts and deeds we can
help to spread a new spirit
throughout the world". May
18th is the anniversary of the
first official Peace Conference
at The Hague in Holland in
1899.
* THE U.N. STORY: Efforts
to make the people of the
Pacific more aware oj the
work of the United Nations
have been spurred by a se¬
minar on teaching about its
work and about international
understanding which has
been held at the University
of the Philippines in Manila.
The seminar was arranged
by the World Federation of
the United Nations Associa¬
tions at Unesco's request.
A*IRT AND EDUCATION:
Major problems of art educa¬
tion and the variety of methods
open to teachers are discussed
in a book just published by
Unesco. "Education and Art",
a work of 130 large format pages,
with many colour ana black-
and-white illustrations, is a
symposium of essays on aspects
of art through education, con¬
tributed by more than 40 spe¬
cialists. Contributors include
Henri Matisse, Sir Herbert Read
and Jean Piaget. (Some of these
articles in abridged form were
included in the October 1953
issue of The Courier, whose
theme for that month was "Art
and Education".)
M. DUPONT'S SHAKE¬
SPEARE: To enable French
people who lack a wide
knowledge of English to
appreciate some of the mas¬
terpieces of English litera¬
ture in the original text, a
Paris publisher is now print¬
ing simplified and' interpre¬
tative versions of English
classics. In a column be
side the original text are
given the explanation and
pronunciation of the more
difficult words, and footnotes
explain unusual grammatical
constructions. First to be
published is Lamb's "Tales
from Shakespeare".
C,NBLOCKING CULTURE:
The Canadian and Italian Go¬
vernments have made a special
cultural exchange agreement.
Blocked Canadian dollar credits
in Italy will be used to set up
a Canadian cultural foundation
in Rome and for study research
by Canadians in Italy. In Mont¬
real, an Italian Cultural In¬
stitute will be established at
Italian Government expense to
carry on similar activities in
June. From an initial 110,000
books, the library's stock is ex¬
pected to grow to 600,000. Other
library facilities will include an
auditorium, children's library, a
library on Berlin history, music
and record collections, as well
as a listening room.
AFRICAN ART FESTI¬
VAL: A Festival of the Arts
aimed at showing the links
between past art forms of
Eastern Nigeria and its pre¬
sent-day culture has been
held in this African territory.
Exhibitions by artists, crafts¬
men, sculptors and photogra¬
phers, performances by thea¬
trical, musical and dance
groups, and broadcasts by
writers, poets and musicians
U. S. S. ft., Byelorussia and Ukraine
become members of Unesco
On April 27 the Union of Socialist Soviet Republics formally joined
Unesco. Under the Unesco Constitution any member of the United
Nations can become a member of Unesco simply by signing the Consti¬
tution and depositing an Instrument of acceptance. Because Unesco
was created at a conference in London in 1946, Its Constitution ¡s In
the safe keeping of the British Foreign Office. Mr. Malik, Ambassador
of the Soviet Union in Great Britain, on the Instructions of his Govern¬
ment signed the Constitution at the Foreign Office on April 21.
Three weeks later, on .May 12, Mr. Malik returned to the Foreign
Office to sign Unesco's Constitution on behalf of the Governments of
Byelorussia and the Ukraine. The addition of the three states now
brings Unesco's membership to 72.
Canada. The two governments
will co-operate in spreading
knowledge of each other's ways
of life and. culture, and in ex¬
changing scientific publications
and techniques as well as teach¬
ing materials.
IN THE EDITOR'S
CHAIR: A group of Danish
schoolchildren were recently
given a free hand to produce
their own newspaper by the
editor and staff of a leading
Copenhagen daily. Aided by
journalists, they wrote arti¬
cles and news items, took
photos and assisted in the
typesetting and proof read¬
ing. Their newspaper was
published as a supplement to
the regular morning paper.
.FOR BERLIN:
One of Europe's largest free
public libraries, built and partly
stocked with U.S. aid funds, will
be opened in West Berlin in
were included in the Festival,
the second of its kind in this
region.
1 OOKETERIAS : People
shopping in three of the super¬
markets the United States'
self-service food shops in Nash¬
ville, Tennessee, can also draw
books from self-service libraries
there which have been dubbed
"Booketerias". The supermar¬
kets agreed to allot space for
books because branch libraries
are lacking in outlying districts.
Shoppers fill' in a library regi¬
stration form and help them¬
selves to three books. When
they return the books, they also
put back a book card and mark
the date. If they have exceed¬
ed ten days they work out the
fine and deposit the money in
a fine box.
WORKING THEIR WAY:
To earn money for their stu¬
dies, Dutch university stu
dents in Amsterdam run their
own cinema which is admin¬
istered by a special founda¬
tion that includes professors,
businessmen and student re¬
presentatives. Only the ma¬
nager and chief projectionist
are professionals, all work¬
ers being students for whom
part-time work is indispen¬
sable if they are to continue
their studies.
A,ILL ABOUT BOOKS: An
Italian information service on
international children's litera¬
ture has been set up in Florence
to give Italian and foreign pub¬
lishers news about the best
Italian books for children. Be¬
sides keeping in contact with
specialists in children's litera¬
ture in other countries, the ser¬
vice will also survey the read¬
ing tastes of children, promote
the setting up of children's lib¬
raries, prepare bibliographies
and will establish a manuscript
reading service."
UNIVERSITY THEA¬
TRES: Theatre companies
from universities all over the
world have been discussing
theatre problems and tech¬
niques at an international
conference on student drama
presentations held in Parma,
Italy. The meeting was or¬
ganized by the Piccolo Tea¬
tro Stabile, the student
theatre of the University' of
Parma.
BeÍOOKS FLY CHEAPLY:
Books sent by air between Eu¬
ropean countries now benefit
from a special air-freight rate
fifty per cent lower than normal
cargo rates according to a de¬
cision by the International Air
Transport Association (IATA) .
This action which forms part of
Unesco's programme to reduce
postal, tariff and transport ob¬
stacles to the international cir¬
culation of educational mater¬
ials, was taken by an IATA
conference at Unesco's request.
-k CARDS FIGHT DISEASE:
Enough money to immunize
2,000,000 children against tu¬
berculosis, or to cure 750,000
young victims of the crip¬
pling yaws disease this is
the profit balance realized by
the United Nations Chil¬
dren's Fund (UNICEF) in a
worldwide sale of 2,000,000
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER N"" 4-5. 1954
Christmas cards. The cards
netted $95,000 at Christmas
1953. UNICEF plans to push
Christmas card sales for 1954
to the 3,000,000 level in a re¬
newed effort to help more
needy children throughout
the world. Current UNICEF
feeding and medical pro¬
grammes will reach 20 mil¬
lion children this year.
CONFERENCE IN MINIA¬
TURE : Students from 25 British
colleges and universities "chang¬
ed their nationality" recently
to take part in a model Unesco
Conference at Cardiff, Wales.
They formed 25 teams each act¬
ing the part of a different go¬
vernment delegation to a Unesco
Conference, and' following as
far as possible the policies
usually defended by the coun¬
tries they were supposed to be
representing. During plenary
meetings and committees, they
examined Unesco's programme
and its budget. Conference or¬
ganizers attained two main ob¬
jectives: The students got a
better understanding of Unes¬
co's activities; they were given
a good picture of problems in¬
volved in organizing an inter¬
national conference.
FREEING KNOWLEDGE:
The United Kingdom has
extended to more than 30
overseas territories the Unes-
co-sponsored international
agreement which abolishes
import duties on educational,
scientific and cultural mater¬
ials. Such items as books,
newspapers, works of art,
music scores and articles for
the blind are exempted from
duty- by this agreement
which is now operated by
17 nations.
COMMUNITY HELP: In¬
ternational work camp activities
are now being transformed from
post-war reconstruction work
to community tasks such as
slum clearance projects and
fundamental education work,
according to work camp organ¬
izers who held a meeting under
the auspices of Unesco, near
Paris recently. This trend be¬
gan last year when work camp
volunteers from many countries
helped to build schools, youth
hostels, sports fields and chil¬
dren's recreation centres.
POWER FROM THE
SUN: It has been estimated
that if an area the size of
Egypt was used to convert
solar radiation directly into
usable form it could provide
the world's present needs for
power, writes E. W. Golding
in the Spring, 1954, issue of
Unesco's review "Impact of
science on society". Discus¬
sing the possibilities of using
such natural sources as wind,
solar radiation, peat and
waste vegetable matter ito
expand production resources
of under-developed areas,
Mr. Golding quotes one au¬
thority as saying that only
4 per cent of water power
potential has so far been de¬
veloped. "Impact", a quarter¬
ly, costs $.50; 2/6; or 125 fr.
per copy.
JtEOPLE'S COLLEGE: Liv¬
ing conditions and methods of
farming in the villages around
New Delhi, India, are changing
for the better, thanks to a flow
of ideas, techniques and help
coming from Janata College, a
people's rural - training centre,
which was opened three years
ago. Courses have been given
in improved farming techniques
based on co-operative endeavour,
in leather and linen work, ani¬
mal husbandry, health, hygiene,
the manufacture of soap and
tinwork. -Janata College is one
link in a chain of Unesco Asso¬
ciated Projects, a scheme by
which fundamental and adult
education projects in many parts
of the world are linked through
Unesco for the sharing of in¬
formation, materials and me-
.thods and the exchange of
ideas.
THE WASTELANDS :
Scientific research can do
much to transform the arid
zones between one quarter
and one third of the world's
land surface into inhabi¬
table and productive lands
providing its work is brought
within a framework of inter¬
national co-operation. Unes¬
co's arid zone programme
aims to co-ordinate the ef¬
forts of scientists and re¬
search workers in different
countries, and also to arouse
a wider awareness of the
problem. The Advisory Com¬
mittee on Arid Zone Research
which guides the Unesco
programme met recently to
take stock of past efforts and
plan future studies. It con¬
sidered, among other sub¬
jects, research on plant life
in arid zones, closer associa¬
tion with research institu¬
tions and the production by
Unesco of a film on arid
zone research.
Crafts in the com¬
munity: Traditional arts and
crafts are threatened by modern
economic and industrial deve¬
lopment and as a result not
only traditional skills are lost
bi^t standards of taste and ar
tistic appreciation decline. How
can the traditions be safeguard¬
ed and yet brought into line
with the needs and standards of
modern life. This problem and
the artistic, educational, social
and economic factors affecting
it will be considered at a Unesco
Regional Seminar to be held in
Tokyo, Japan, next Autumn,
attended by artists, craftsmen,
teachers and directors of craft
industries from countries in the
South Pacific and South East
Asia.
ABORIGINAL ART -."Aus¬
tralian Aboriginal Culture",
the first exhibition prepared
by a Unesco member state
for circulation in other
member countries has begun
a two-year's tour of the
United States and Canada.
The exhibition is the Aus¬
tralian Government's answer
to the request of the Unesco
General Conference asking
members to prepare exhib¬
itions, especially work by con¬
temporary artists and of folk
art. The Canadian Govern¬
ment, is also organizing an
exhibition consisting of con¬
temporary paintings by na¬
tional artists. This will be
first circulated in Europe.
w,ORKERS ABROAD: As
members of Unesco's travelling
study group for workers some
1,200 European workers will
this year visit people who do
similar jobs to their own m
other countries. Altogether,
74 groups of 15 to 25 persons
from 15 countries will see the
working conditions and ways of
life of their counterparts else¬
where in Europe. This is the
third such programme organized
by Unesco. Last year 40 visits
were arranged for 850 persons.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom -
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Fnck Verlas, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street. P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon. v
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen. K.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa 2, Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
-99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, 1 9, Avenue
Kleber, Pans- 1 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece :* Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Inter¬
nationale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd. Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
Si Stationery Co., Scmdia House," New
Delhi; Raj kamal Publications Ltd., Hima-
lay House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NY.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djkarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstei's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road. P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzan Co, Inc., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Liberia : Jacob Momolu Kamara, Gurly
and Front Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
/Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kmgsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff,*
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : Unesco Publications Centre
7 De Lacy Street, Dunedin, N. E. 2.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokh ¡omet, Stortingsplass; 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs, 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A B.C.E. Friztes Kungl. Hovbok-
handel Fredgaatan 2, Stockholm I 6.
Thailand : Suksapan Pantt, Arkarn 9
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
' P.O. Box 569, London S.E.!.
U.S.A. : Columbia University Press, 2960
Broadway, New York.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Our folly toward nature
BITING THE
HAND THAT
FEED S D S
by
Gerald Wendt
The protection of nature is some¬
times considered a sentimental
notion, an idealistic desire to
preserve unique or beautiful plants and
animals, especially in reserves or na¬
tional parks. It is much more. It is a
stern and practical realization that
man is completely dependent on the
resources of nature and that these are
by no means inexhaustible. It is an
international effort to assess and safe¬
guard the sources of our food, energy,
material wealth and those of aesthetic
inspiration too.
SOME REFUGEES
SET UP THEIR
NEW APARTMENT
National parks, forest preserves and wild-life refuges are quickly
populated by the many animal species that recognize them as home.
In a new marsh, created primarily for ducks and geese, a mixed
colony of double-crested cormorants and blue herons have set up
nature's equivalent of an apartment house. (Photo C.-J. Henry.)
In past centuries, when men were
few in number and scattered widely
across the continents, the riches of the
earth seemed endless. But today the
earth is crowded with 2,400 million
persons, an average of 47 for every
square mile. And the population is
growing more rapidly than ever before,
with an increase of twenty-five million
persons per year.
This means that every week the
added population is equal to that of
Oslo, Athens, Düsseldorf or Kansas
City, and the annual increase equals
the entire population of Korea, Spain
or Mexico. In, a mere eight years the
added population will equal the pre¬
sent population of all Africa, of North
America or of the U.S.S.R.
If the present growth-rate persists
the population of the world will be
3,500 million by 1980, more than 4,000
million by the end of the century, and
about 7,000 million a hundred years
from now. - By the year 2000 there
would be an average of 30 persons per
square kilometre (78 per square mile).
To provide them with the necessities
of life will certainly be a problem of
world dimensions.
This has been said many times by "
Gerald WENDT is a member of the Unesco
Staff in Paris in charge of the improvement of
science education in schools and its dissemina¬
tion by press, radio and film. Formerly he was
' Professor of Chemistry at the University of
Chicago and Dean at the Pennsylvania State Col¬
lege in the United States and science editor of
the Time publications. In recent years he has
devoted all his time, as a leading writer and
lecturer on science' In his country, to improving
public understanding of science.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N°" 4-5. 1954
UP GOES A DAM
FOR ANIMALS
Great dams on rivers and mountain torrents provide much-
needed hydro-electric power. But valuable too are dams on
small streams among lowland hills, partly as a means of flood
control, but also to create small lakes for fishing and as wildfowl
breeding grounds. They also spread the water resources for
grazing animals and generally enhance the refuges for animals
and birds. Photographs show one such lake under construction
and as it appeared when completed. (Photos U.S. Fish and
Wildlife Service by T. R. Lawhorn and E. Hackenberg.)
scholars and experts. The United
Nations Food and Agricultural Organi¬
zation at Rome devotes all its efforts
to the nutritional aspects of the prob¬
lem. Yet it is only a minor item in
the programme and budget of most
governments and plays almost no part
in the thought of most people. Except
in time of local famine, the problem
seems remote because the twenty-first
century^ seems a long way off. Yet in
many countries the average length of
life is today almost seventy years so
that in those countries most children
will live well beyond the year 2000.
They cannot escape the problem.
It also seems remote because more
and more people are crowded into big
cities and forget their dependence on
nature. They buy their food, clothing
and fuel in the shops and forget that
the shops must get them from the
farms, the forests and the mines.
The metals, minerals and .major
fuels lie deep in the earth, deposited
there during the millions of years of
previous geologic epochs, ample in
quantity for present needs but limited
in amount and irreplaceable. The
most optimistic estimate of the
amounts of fuels underground is about
8,000,000 million tons but these fuels
are now being used at the rate of
2,400 million tons, a year. At this rate
there is enough for. -some 3000 years.
But the consumption in the highly in¬
dustrialized United States is far
higher than the world's average. Its
own coal resources may be exhausted
within the next 75 years.
In a recent book (1) Professor Harri¬
son Brown of the U.S.A. has estimated
that if the rest of the world develops
its industries to a similar degree and if
the estimates of population increase
are correct, the world's resources in
underground fuels will become inade¬
quate within a century. Iron ores are
also being used up and the lesser
metals, such as copper, lead and tin are
disappearing rapidly. Once used, such
materials are gone . forever. For this
reason the conservation of natural re¬
sources is a major project for industrial
engineers and for governments.
Even more important are the pro¬
ducts of the fields, the forest and the
seas that provide food and clothing for
mankind. They grow under the rays
of the sun and are renewed each year.
They have always been lavishly wasted
In most countries. Even the soil has
washed into the rivers and then to the
sea so that vast areas that once fed
large populations are now barren. For¬
ests have been cut and grasslands cut
by the plough, their fertility exhausted
by over-use. In dry regions the
sparse vegetation has been devoured by
animals or cut for fuel so that the
wind carries off the soil as dust and a
sandy desert remains. Since the soil
gives us our food this is indeed biting
the hand that feeds us.
' Thus the problem of protecting na¬
ture includes the conservation of miner¬
als and of the soil. 'But pure air and
(1) The Challenge of Man's Future, by Har¬
rison Brown ; New Yor'c : The. Viliing Pres-,.
1934.
water must be preserved also and the
insects that fertilize the flowers, the
natural balance of animal species and
the forests that conserve the rainfall.
Much can be done on a national scale
by wise legislations and internationally
by the Specialized Agencies of the
United Nations.
But fundamentally the solution of
the problem lies in the education of the
peoples of all nations to make them
aware of the danger to their own chil¬
dren, to obtain support for local laws'
and campaigns, and to co-operate with
the international agencies. The entire
world must learn to understand nature
and to live with her, not on her.
In some cases this means' that
world-wide research studies must be
made. To avoid the spread of the de^
serts and to improve the food produc¬
tion of dry areas, for instance, the
special Unesco "Advisory Committee
on Problems of the Arid Zones" has
already brought together the experts
in all the sciences involved and from
nations where rainfall is inadequate.
The aim is to plan a world-wide
programme of research and education
that looks to increased rainfall, con¬
servation of water resources, irrigation,
the use of wind energy and of dew, the
selection of plants that thrive with
little water, and the control of land-
use. Since nearly one third of the land
area of the earth is deficient in rain,
the committee's task is a vital one. "
But for most of the world what is
needed is chiefly a friendly understand¬
ing of nature, based on direct contact.
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
PROTECTING
NATURE
SOMETHING
MORE THAN
SENTIMENT
THE GREAT Forest and brush fires are sometimes started by lightning,
DESTROYER ^ut most °^ten ^y man's carelessness. They not only destroy
timber and game, but also open the soil to erosion and the
rivers to floods that threaten homes and lives. Equipped with water-tank and hose and able to cross
rough ground, a fire-jeep is an effective weapon for forest rangers.- Controlled burning of dried brush
and weeds (photo, right) at the right season and under proper conditions soon replaces them with
new green shoots which provide ample food for wintering birds. (Photos F. Dufresne and P. Haddon.)
This is the aim of the International
Union for the Protection of Nature,
founded in 1948 under the sponsorship
of Unesco, with headquarters in Bel¬
gium at 42, rue Montoyer, Brussels. Its
members are governments as well as
national and international organiza¬
tions.
The Union calls together experts
THE BISON RETURNS
At least 75 million bison once roamed the prairies of western North
America. They were reduced almost' to extinction by the advance
of wheat, maize and cattle farming. Today, protected by law, they are
multiplying on the natural grasslands of their old home in Montana.
from many countries for frequent
meetings to discuss such topics as
"Nature Protection and Tourism",
"The Protection of Fauna and Flora in
High Altitudes", and "The Protection
of African Fauna and Flora". These
were the topics at meetings in 1953 at
Salzburg in Austria and at Bukavu in
the Belgian Congo.
The 1954 meet¬
ing will be held
at Copenhagen
in August to
discuss the pro¬
tection of Arc¬
tic animals, the
effect of mo¬
dern insectici¬
des on mam¬
mals, birds and
insects, and the
methods and
'. means of publi¬
city for the pro-
" tection of na¬
ture.
The recom¬
mendations of
the Union for
the official pro¬
tection of na¬
ture take effect
in laws and
actions of the
member go¬
vernments, but
the important
work of the
Union is the
education
of the peoples,
and especially
of the children
of all lands so
that the value
of nature may
be understood
and its beauty
appreciated by the people themselves.
The Union has issued many pam¬
phlets on nature protection and re¬
cently has published "A Guide to Con¬
servation" by E. Laurence Palmer of
Cornell University, U.S.A. The Union is
also a stimulus for the organization of
nature clubs in many countries, espe¬
cially in Europe and is now producing,
under contract with Unesco, a film
strip on nature education for the use
of such clubs.
A typical project of the Union is the
sponsoring of international summer
camps for nature study. The first of
these was held at'Houyet in Belgium
in July of 1952 which -was attended
by about fifty young men and women
from ten different countries of Europe.
In 1953, a second summer camp met at
Hasselfors in Sweden; plans are now
being made for . a third camp to be
held at Terschelling in Holland this
year. These camps brought together
youthful nature lovers from Austria,
Belgium, France, Germany, Greece,
Holland, Italy, Sweden, Switzerland,
Turkey, Yugoslavia and the United
Kingdom , to study methods of nature -
study and of organizing nature clubs
For the 1954 camp at Terschelling,
Unesco has granted two travelling fel¬
lowships, one to a young Canadian,
another to a youth from India.
The participants return -to their home
lands to take a lead in the development
of public sentiment for the enjoyment
of nature and for governmental mea¬
sures which will protect the value and
beauty of their natural resources and
thus eventually help to preserve the
sources of national wealth in the form
of food, fuel, clothing, shelter, good
water and fresh air. It is a movement
on which future generations depend for
their very life.
o
z
<
SO
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
*
f
-*
«
^ -»*
J? «
vr*
s
COUNTING THE WATER BIRDS. A government plane observes the
great concentration of wintering ducks on Laguna Madre on the Gulf Coast
of Mexico. Other planes keep count as far south as Guatemala and in the
Arctic, where the birds migrate for summer. Below, land management In
Devonshire a cover of grass on the uplands for sheep, broad fields protected
from wind and erosion by hedges.' (Copyright R. Schmidt and IPA.)
^. jf&Skl 2****
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
