<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069982eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
,if«.SYCW«2£
mm
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
N°7
1954
(7th year)
Price: 7d (U. K.)
30 francs (France)
s. o. s.
FROM
THE PAST
Saving Our Heritage in Stone
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
DOWN
TO SAFETY
When the last world war broke out in 1939 art
museums hurriedly removed their paintings and
other treasures to safety. Photos show special
techniques used at Royal Fine Arts Museum in
Antwerp, Belgium (left) and the Rijksmuseujn in
Amsterdam, Holland. Through special trap doors
in floor, over-sized masterpieces are lowered to
safety of underground shelters. Dutch medal
(above) was awarded in I 946 to those who helped
protect cultural treasures during the war.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
NUMBER 7-1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
To save our heritage in stone
4 PROLONGING THE LIFE OF OUR ART
. TREASURES
8 THE FLAG WITH THE BLUE AND WHITE SHIELD
International symbol for protecting cultural property
I I TREASURES OF SYRIA AND LEBANON
12 MINARETS OF DAMASCUS
13 STORY IN STONE
15 THE LAND OF COUNTLESS RUINS
Palmyra
Krak des Chevaliers
The Pillar Hermit of Qalat Seman
Baalbek
OTHER ARTICLES AND FEATURES
20 UNTOLD TREASURES OF THE SEA
The exciting story of Oceanography
By Gerald Wendt
23 THE EXPEDITION OF H.M.S. CHALLENGER
A 70,000 mile voyage to map the world under the oceans
24 WORLD HISTORY
Toning down its "Western accent"
By Marshall G.S. Hodgson
26 KALINGA
' An historic Indian name revived by a Unesco science prize
29 GREEN LIGHT FOR EDUCATION
From Afghanistan to the banks of the Nile
By Georges Fradier
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science and culture
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, I 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris 1 6, France.
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: José De Benito
Individual articles not copyrighted maybe reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-: $ 1.50 or 300 French frs.
MC 54.1 83. A.
UNESCO COURIER. N» 7. 1954
THIS MONTH'S THEME
This ancient theatre near Lyons, France, was
built in the first century A.D. to seat 6,500
people and is one of the most striking monu¬
ments at the Gallo-Roman city of Fourvière.
Since it was uncovered in 1946 it has under¬
gone important repairs and now "comes to
life" each year as the setting for a festival
of music and drama.
WHY not face the truth? Life would be a good deal easier for
many people if there were no old buildings. Ever since
man stopped living in caves he has been raising edifices
into which he has put the best of himself, his knowledge and his
dreams. He has raised so many that it has been impossible to
destroy them all, even though many allies have worked at the job
fire, earthquakes, war, invading conquerors, time and oblivion.
Every civilization has sacked, crushed, pillaged and burned.
Temples, churches and entire cities have been razed. The kings
of antiquity destroyed the images and sanctuaries of enemy gods;
Rome-sowed the ruins of Carthage with salt; Christianity overturn¬
ed temples to -build its first cathedrals. Modern civilization has
done little better.
But in the eyes of some these losses mean little. What if
there are lands where man has stubbornly striven for greatness
for 5,000 years? What if these lands are literally sown with
relics of past civilizations and are the altars of civilization itself?
Cities drowned under sand, temples on the banks of rivers, castles
clinging to mountainsides, churches, palaces, mosques. Why
preserve them? Why repair and restore them? There are those
to whom it is a waste of time and money.
Back in the Paris of 1945 when food was rationed and wine
was rare, a restaurant owner complained one day to his customers:
"It's a scandal. We don't have butter, but we pay taxes so that
they can throw our money "away on ruins and museums." He had
a good deal in common with the farmer who wanted to pull down
an old Gallo-Roman wall to make room for a chicken run.
The people who sneer at old stones are not always ignorant
men. To some urban planners with visions of wide avenues,
geometrically-aligned buildings and easy-flowing traffic, a stubborn
old quarter with winding medieval alleys is too often a stumbling
block to progress.
But not to all of them. In many a city, architects and engi¬
neers are defending the ramparts of history and their voices are
echoed in municipal councils. A Gothic town hall may not be as
efficient as a modern steel-and-concrete building but tourists
seldom go out of their way to look at office buildings and tourists
mean prosperity for all nations.
Happily, the magic of ancient stones has lost none of its awe
for large numbers of people. Today it has spread to buildings
which would have been scorned by our ancestors. A humble coun¬
try inn is carefully preserved because it stood at an important
crossroads for two centuries. It recalls a date or a series of events
which may have faded from our daily lives. Historical buildings
deepen our feeling for history and the great heritage of the past
which we call culture.
But above all we cherish these ancient buildings because they
are miracles of beauty irrespective of the religion or civilization
which produced them. We recognize that beauty cannot be the
monopoly of any century or any tradition.
Today men are at work everywhere in an effort to preserve our
heritage of beauty or to repair those parts which have been
destroyed or mutilated by the frenzy of war. Entire nations have
joined forces to protect our cultural past. Engineers and architects,
curators and archaeologists are aiding each other across frontiers.
Unesco has helped to organize and support their work. It has sent
men to ancient Cuzco in Peru, to Ochrida in Yugoslavia, to Baalbek
and Palmyra in the Middle East. It has helped create the Inter¬
national Council of Museums, and has prepared a new internation¬
al code of law, now signed by 38 nations, to protect works of art
and historical buildings should any future armed conflict occur.
Mankind's heritage is too great and too rich for us to do
anything less than everything within our power to prevent it from
being lost.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE I3TH CENTURY CATHEDRAL OF RHEIMS is considered the crowning glory of Gothic archi¬
tecture in France, and the Western facade one of the most perfect masterpieces of the Middle Ages. The
great sculptures of the Coronation of the Virgin have been much damaged and repeatedly restored. But now
they are in danger of falling to pieces. A copy of it was msde in 1941 and French authorities
are now considering radical steps, urgently necessary, to preserve what is left of the original work.
This photo shows a detail of the central portal with the figures of the Christ and the Virgin.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 7. 1954
Prolormins the life
of our art treasures
Paintings, stone statues, temples and
castles : these are our great "cul¬
tural heritage" of the past and
probably the most precious possessions
of mankind. If we seek to preserve
them it is not just because they are
old but rather for their great beauty.
Yet not even the most persistent
memory of passing generations and no
amount of book knowledge by itself
can hope to keep them alive. No "ima¬
ginary museum" can equal the actual
touch or sight of the frescoes
of Ajanta in India or the
Winged Samothrace in the
Louvre.
But few of us realize how
entremely frail most of these
treasures really are. A mas¬
sively built stone arch can
sometimes be more fragile
than a small terracotta vase.
All of them need care and all
of them need protection
against damage, theft or
A century and a half ago
Napoleon won regrettable
fame for his confiscation of
Italian art treasures, though
his plundering was outclassed
by the systematic and mas¬
sive appropriations of Nazi
art connoisseurs in our own
time. Today it seems that
official thefts of this kind
have been condemned once
and for all.
Certain famous works of
art epitomize in their his¬
tories the vicissitudes suffer¬
ed by art treasures through
theft and damage. None is
perhaps so representative as
the renowned Mystic Lamb, a
work of the van Eyck bro- -
thers, completed in 1432 and
deposited in the Cathedral of
St. Bavon at Ghent. In the
following century one part
was damaged beyond repair
during cleaning ; in 1794 the
four great central panels
were carried off by the
French and only returned
21 years later. Then most of
the panels were sold to
Frederick William III of Prussia
went to the Berlin Museum.
During World War I, what remained
of the Mystic Lamb was kept in a secret
hiding place throughout the German
occupation of Belgium. The return of
the panels from the Berlin Museum in
1920 provided the opportunity of com¬
pletely restoring the famous work, but
some years later one of the finest
panels, The Honest Judges, was stolen
and has never been recovered.
After the outbreak of World War II
the altarpiece was sent for safe keeping
to the Chateau de Pau in southern
France. In the summer of 1942, the
Nazis forced the Vichy Government to
surrender the painting. It was trans¬
ferred to one of the great salt mine
repositories at Alt-Aussee where Hitler
and Goering stored their booty of art
treasures. Finally in 1945, it was restor¬
ed to the Cathedral of St. Bavon.
But after its wartime adventures the
masterpiece showed the ravages of time
and needed immediate attention. In¬
stead of relying solely on its own skill
and knowledge, Belgium called in
foreign specialists as well. Thus for the
BRONZE PORTAL of Basilica of St. Zenoin Verona (12 th century) is
one of most famous in world. It escaped damage during last war but
over 5,000 churches and historic buildings were either destroyedor
damaged. Since then Italy has undertaken the greatest repairing job
in its history. Much of the damage has been repaired.
and first time in history, a nation owning
an outstanding masterpiece regarded
itself not as the exclusive owner but as
a trustee and summoned to its aid some
of the greatest specialists in the world
for consultation and advice. Today,
restored to "good health" the work is
back in its chapel. (See Unesco Courier,
February 1952.)
-' Since then "art doctors" from differ¬
ent countries have gathered round
other ailing masterpieces. They have
examined paintings on wood at Lisbon,
the works of da Vinci in the Louvre,
and the frescoes of the Church of St.
Sophia at Ochrlda in Yugoslavia, and
have advised on methods of treatment.
In all cases cleaning or restoring old
paintings and protecting them against
old age, dry or damp weather, cold,
smoke and dust, are delicate jobs calling
for extremely delicate techniques.
Since the 19th century when it was
the practice to "protect" pictures by
daubing them with varnish that later
went yellow and mixed with the
original colours, notable progress has
been made in methods of cleaning and
restoring. But even today techniques
vary according to the paint-
^^^ ing, its age and its author,
and methods are still largely
a matter of individual taste.
When it comes to statues,
though, science is on much
firmer ground. We are no
longer as completely helpless
as we used to be when faced
with stone or bronze that is
decaying, corroding or slowly
crumbling away. Diseases in
stones, metals and glass were
once dark mysteries ; today
they no longer are at least
for the chemist.
Unfortunately the chemist
is not always called in. A
Swedish scientist, J. Arvid
Hedvall, recently deplored
the lack of systematic colla¬
boration between the expert
on ancient monuments and
the scientific research worker
who understood the various
agents that attack stones
and metals and could help
prevent their destruction.
Offhand one would think
that preserving a building is
a much less delicate problem
than restoring a painting.
This is not so. Moreover the
work is so costly that it often
requires the financial support
of the entire city or the
whole nation and sometimes
foreign aid as well. The care
of historic buildings needs
help from the man in the
street as much as from the
expert.
- "Time passes the stones
remain", the saying goes,
and some of the great structures of
ancient civilizations do seem to have
defied time. The Great Wall of China,
the Pyramids of Egypt and the great
Inca temples appear like age-defiant
"Shangri-las" fixed in a kind of
majestic eternity. But we know just
the same that they cannot escape the
universal law; that they need help in
resisting time's ravages.
The great square-stone buildings of
Cuzco and Machu-Picchu in the Andes
are in a first-class state of preservation
because Peruvian archaeologists recent¬
ly re-erected them by replacing all the
fallen stones in their proper place.
Where the pieces exist no ancient
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
* PRESERVING OUR ART TREASURES (cont'd)
building is a "Humpty Dumpty."
Patient effort and jig-saw puzzle brain
work will "put the pieces back again."
This was how many famous structures
were resurrected from their ruins.
One of the temples at Baalbek, the
basilica at Pompeii, the temple at
Paestum, the castle at Sidon (where
the masonry was simply fished out of
the nearby sea) and especially the
great temples of Egypt were all no
more than gigantic jig-saw problems
for the engineer.
In most cases though, preserving a
building means having to repair it.
The Chateau of Versailles would soon
be a pitiful ruin were it not for the
carpenters, masons and roof repairers
who are today busily and hastily at
work on it. Engineers predicted the
palace would collapse within 60 years
unless something was done to save it.
France is now raising 5,000 million
francs ($14,000,000) to rescue Versailles.
In Europe buildings that have been
properly repaired may be left alone for
quite long periods, but in the monsoon
lands of Asia preservation demands
frequent attention on a scale unknown
in the West. In India, Indonesia,
Cambodia and elsewhere, annual repairs
are necessary to prevent the infiltration
of water into walls and the invasion of
swiftly spreading weeds and plants
disastrous for ancient buildings.
Threat to Taj Mahal
Thus, the world-famous Taj Mahal
in India has been under constant
care since 1936. The great dome
was completely repaired and the pillars
and broken lintels were dismantled and
replaced. (Fantastic as it may seem,
a proposal was actually set afoot in
1828 to demolish the whole building for
the value of its marble and was serious¬
ly considered for seven years).
Resurrecting a monument from its
original stones and pieces strewn on
the ground is technically known as
anastylosis. There is practically no-
controversy among experts about the
usefulness of this procedure just as
there is general agreement about the
need for regular maintenance work.
But the restoration of damaged or
destroyed sections of an ancient build¬
ing is another matter. Not so long
ago, in fact, just the mention of the
word restoration touched off violent
discussions and arguments between
the experts (1).
In the 19th century, a young French
architect-historian named Viollet-le-
Duc, appeared on the scene. He
revealed to France and to the outside
world the logic and beauty of Gothic
(1) In speaking of preservation, experts dis¬
tinguish carefully between the two words
coiiseruitiuii mid restoration. J he first means
prolonging the life of <i building without mak-
imj any marked changes m il; the second
implies more radical changes such as replacing
destroyed parts or exposing original sections
that had been covered up.
STEFANSDOM: Famous high pitched
roof of Vienna Cathedral, Austria's noblest
Gothic structure ( 1 5th century) burned
for three days in 1945 and was totally
consumed. Photo shows steel framework
built to replace former wooden one. Con¬
crete platform was built to protect the
arches of the aisles. Roof has now been
completely restored.
architecture which was then despised
as a "barbarous" medieval construction.
In due course he became the chief
prophet of the Gothic revival, and
restored the walled city of Carcassonne
and cathedrals at Amiens and Laon.
Unfortunately, Viollet-le-Duc carried
his love of Gothic a little too far. He
felt that the style had reached its most
perfect purity in the 13th century and
imagined therefore that all Gothic
churches and buildings should have a
single unity of style. Under his
influence, many Gothic structures were
rebuilt according to what was consider¬
ed the "pure" Gothic. Where a
church differed it was "brought into
line" by skilful imitation.
Thus the flamboyant balustrades of
Amiens Cathedral were replaced with
parts copied from Chartres, and the
Renaissance features which had been
added to Gothic buildings between the
17th and 18th centuries removed.
Worse was done to the little church of
Saint Laurent which stands next to the
Gare de l'Est in Paris. The facade
with its superimposed columns was
completely demolished to make room
for a Gothic facade. The survival of
two styles in the same edifice seemed
an absurdity to the old restorers and
not worth discussing since it was a
glaring departure from stylistic unity.
The restorers of the Viollet-le-Duc
school actually thought they were doing
a great service to history and art. In
reality they were purists who could not
see that styles, like people, vary and
that buildings, like nations, have
histories that evolve with time.
Today, the old Viollet-le-Duc concept
has been discarded. The tendency now
is toward straight conservation with
all restoration excluded as far as pos¬
sible. As a rule, the experts try to
leave the works of antiquity untouched.
If a new part must be added, they are
careful to construct it with materials
completely different from the original
ones so as to avoid any confusion.
The curious thing is that the old
battle is still going on today more
often between the experts and the
general public which has taken quite a
lively interest in restoration questions.
"Don't restore the crumbling church in
its original form", say the experts.
"Rebuild it exactly as it was before !"
cry the citizens for whom the ancient
edifice was hallowed in tradition. This
was how the great Campanile of San
Marco in Venice was entirely rebuilt
early in the century after its collapse
in 1902, when the whole city' clamoured
for it to be done. The Campanile is
now usually cited as the classical
example of reconstruction by pure
imitation.
War's 'red-hot rake'
Before the last war the preservation
of historic buildings was still a rel¬
atively simple affair. It was nearly
always prompted by the more or less
justifiable desire to restore the original
.appearance of a masterpiece even
though it was neither damaged nor
likely to fall into ruins. Most coun¬
tries cleared away encumbrances block¬
ing parts of a building. Walls
obstructing the view of a loggia or a
porch were torn down ; stones were
scraped clean to uncover ancient
capitals and cornices. There was
nothing urgent about the work and
most of it in fact was hardly necessary.
But when the last war ended, "a red-
hot rake" as Winston Churchill termed
it, had been drawn across all of Europe.
So much had been lost that something
had to be done and done fast to
salvage at least the remnants of what
was left. But what ? Conserve the
ruins ? Restore them partially ?
Restore them totally or construct new
buildings? There was no easy answer.
Great Britain, which has never been
favourable to the idea of restoration
has sought to preserve the ruins of her
abbeys and churches and some of her
bombed monuments. The Ruskinian
tendency to "let approach the sad day
of ruin" was against undue interven¬
tion. Instead of being repaired, cer¬
tain churches were left as ruins and a
garden was made around them. Thus,
surrounded by green lawns and flowers,
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N° 7. 1954
they have an air of romantic charm.
But even the British recognized that
this was no answer for all destroyed
or partially destroyed buildings, and
Exeter Cathedral, for example, which
was severely damaged, was carefully
repaired and restored after the war.
The countries of Europe realized that
they simply could not leave their
churches and other buildings in ruins.
Some compromise had to be reached
with the pre-war rules of restoration.
Restoration for the purpose of simple
consolidation gave way to the recon¬
struction of important parts of a build¬
ing or to something midway between
restoration and the construction of a
new building. Almost everywhere it
was decided to restore badly damaged
historic monuments.
The reconstruction of enormous
surfaces in" cathedrals often seemed
impossible at first sight, but finally it
was accomplished, even down to the
sculptures a job for which craftsmen
had to be trained. Modern engineering
and" architectural techniques have
made much of the rebuilding possible.
Without reinforced concrete and steel
beams, for example, many roofs might
never have been rebuilt nor crumbling
walls strengthened and straightened.
Thus, in the cathedral at Poznan,
Poland, where the walls had been
seriously weakened by fire and threat¬
ened to collapse outwards, a system of
reinforced concrete blocks and props
was used to bolster the structure.
Today the preserving, the repairing,
and the restoring goes on. In the face
of the uncounted ruins of the recent
past, men of all nations have shown
that they refuse to abandon the
artistic wealth we have all inherited,
and of which each generation in turn
is the trustee. Our world is often
accused these days of being too
materialistic. The example of these
men shows that we sometimes do prize
beauty above all else.
Much of the information in this article is
based on material which appeared in Unesco's
publication, Sites and Monuments, a study of
current problems, and also on material publish¬
ed in Unesco's Quarterly review Museum.
GROÓTE KERK or church of St. Eusebius (late Gothic) In Arnhem has been under repair since end
of last war. Famous 318 foot West Tower, almost totally destroyed, is still in ruins. Over 1,000
ancient monuments were destroyed or mutilated by the war in Netherlands.
$ 14,000,000
REPAIR BILL
Three centuries of war, weather and
revolution have dealt severely with
the palace Louis XIV built at Versailles
on the site of a hunting lodge. Leaks
sprouted under Its 30 acres of roofs,
beams were rotting and Its famed Hall
of Mirrors (above) was in danger.
Engineers predicted the palace would
collapse within 60 years, unless some¬
thing were done to save It. Something
is being done. France is raising 5,000
million francs (§14,000,000) to save
Versaillesnot only to preserve it as
a monument to one of the high-water
marks of French civilization but to
recreate the atmosphere of its most
glorious days. Once certain apartments
have been refurnished, once its theatre
has been stripped of gloomy 19th
century alterations, and once its life
is no longer in danger, Versailles is
to be a centre for dramatic and musical
festivals and not merely a museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
THE FLAG WITH
THE BLUE AND
WHITE SHIELD
A flag with a blue and white shield
is now the international symbol for
the protection of great cultural
treasures and historical monuments
the event of any future armed conflict.
On May 14, 1954, the representatives of thirty-seven
governments including the United States of America,
Soviet Russia and France, signed their names to a new
International convention to protect cultural property from
destruction should conflict break out within any country
or between countries (1). The new convention thus sets
up what is tantamount to a cultural "Red Cross" under
the banner of which works of art, monuments and historic
buildings would receive the same sort of protection as is
now universally given to hospitals, ambulances and
medical personnel in time of war.
An international code of protection of this kind has
been considered necessary for a long time and has become
particularly vital since the ruthless fury of the first and
second World Wars left a path of destruction in its wake
unprecedented in the history of mankind.
Certain limited steps for safeguarding the objects our
civilization cherishes have been taken in the past by in¬
dividual countries. In 1935 the Roerich Pact was signed
in Washington but it applied only to countries in the
Americas and contained no measures for international'
control. The Hague Conventions of 1899 and 1907 also
contained provisions for protecting cultural property but
these were so vague and imprecise that its practical effects
were nullified.
In 1937 the International Museums Office drew up a
draft agreement which was submitted to the League of
Nations. Before it could be adopted war broke out.
This preparatory work, however, was not completely
wasted since during the war a number of governments,
influenced by the League's plan, actually adopted some of
.the measures advocated even though they were not bound
by any convention.
Thus the United States set up a special commission in
1943 "for the protection and salvation of artistic and
historic monuments in war areas." A special officers'
corps, known as M.F.A. and A. (Monuments, Fine Arts and
Archives) was set up by the Allies. The German armies
had a "Kunstschutz" as early as the 1914-18 war. Two
orders issued by General Eisenhower, Commander-in-
Chief of the Allied Forces, contained precise instructions
for the safeguarding of cultural property. The first issued
in December 1943 concerned operations in Italy; the
second, in May 1944, operations in Europe following the
invasion of June 6. They laid down the principle that
it was the duty of each army commander, within the
limits of possibility, to respect the cultural heritage of the
countries where troops were engaged.
The last war however was also characterized by sys¬
tematic pillage of cultural objects in the occupied countries.
A new technique was used to dispossess the rightful
owners of their works of art under a semblance of legality.
By demanding huge daily indemnities from the occupied
countries, deliberately forced transactions were made to
appear like free commercial dealings.
(Continuée/ on page 10.)
(1) Andorra, Australia, Belgium, Byelorussian SSR, China, Cuba,
Czechoslovakia, Ecuador, France, German Federal llepublic, Greece,
Hungary, India, Iran, lrag, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Libya, Luxembourg,
Monaco, Netherlands, Nicaragua, Norway, Philippines, Poland, Portugal,
Rumania, San Marino, San Salvador, Spam, Syria, Ukrainian SSR, U.S.A.,
Uruguay, U.S.S.H., Yugoslavia. (.Lebanon has since also signed).
8
MOORE IS
BOXED UP
Large sculpture by Henry
Moore in San Francisco Museum
of Art in US is given special
packing for shipment. Special
bolts not nails are used to join
wooden boards and protective
covering is used where each bolt
may touch sculpture. Photos on
this and following page, as well as
page two, are taken from a special
study just published in French
by Unesco which describes the
latest "Techniques for the
Protection of Cultural Property
in ' Case of Armed Conflict".
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 7. 1954
SAMOTHRACE
PACKED AWAY
Monuments, works of art, precious
books, scientific collections and all
objects which make up the cultural
heritage of a nation run grave risks
in case of war, and various measures
have been devised for protecting them.
Here, the famous Winged Victory of
Samothrace in the Louvre, Paris, is
shown being packed in case built around
it after outbreak of war in 1939 and
shipped to special shelter. (Photos
Marc Vaux and Lau re Albin Guillot.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
(Continued from page 8.)
In January 1943,' eighteen Powers signed a Joint
Declaration in London solemnly condemning these acts of
pillage. The armistice agreements with Nazi Germany and
her satellite states later provided for the restitution of art
and other types of cultural' property plundered. Often they
were more or less seriously damaged. Many were never found.
The whole problem of the preservation of historic treasures
and famous buildings has since then been reassessed and
new solutions sought in the light of the inadequacy of
existing international agreements and the failure during
World Wars I and H to prevent tragic and irreparable losses.
In 1949, the Netherlands proposed that Unesco investigate
the problem fully. The following year Italy suggested that
an international convention be prepared and submitted a
preliminary draft to Unesco's General Conference in Florence
as a basis for future discussions.
For the past four years Unesco has worked on drafting the
new convention with suggestions coming from its member
governments and the International Council of Museums.
After lengthy discussions at a special conference in the
Hague, it was finally signed by 37 countries and will enter
into force as soon as five of these have formally ratified it.
The Blue Shield Convention represents an important step
forward in international law. It takes into account all
previous agreements on the subject, complements them, and
brings them into line with present-day needs. _ The signa¬
tories recognize that the threat to cultural treasures is today
increased by the suddenness with which hostilities break out,
the force of new destructive weapons and the large areas
. over which wars extend.
While it would certainly be over-optimistic to suppose that
the convention will save all treasures in case of another war,
experience has shown that measures can be taken to restrict
the damage if planned well in advance, during peace time.
The signatories therefore pledge themselves to take a
number of unprecedented peace-time steps: 1) special bomb¬
proof shelters, taking into account the power of modern
weapons, will be built to house movable objects such as art
works, manuscripts, scientific collections, archives and
treasured books. 2) Detailed technical plans will be
elaborated and be ready to be put into operation to protect
buildings; various other kinds of protective measures will
also be worked out. 3) All armed forces will set up
monuments and fine arts services in peace time with special
personnel trained in protection. 4) New provisions for the
respect of cultural property will be introduced into military
regulations applying to all troops, and the importance of the
regulations explained. 5) An International Register, des¬
ignating in advance those edifices which will enjoy special
protection in wartime, will be created and kept by Unesco.
If a civil war or any other armed conflict should occur
these buildings will immediately hoist the 'Blue Shield Flag
or be marked with three huge blue and white shields clearly
visible from the ground and air. Governments agree not
to use such buildings for military purposes and to leave them
immune from attack. This immunity may be waived, says
a clause, "only in cases where military necessity imperatively
requires such a waiver". The inclusion of this clause was
the subject of considerable and heated discussion at the
Hague. It was finally adopted with a limiting proviso
however, stating that immunity cannot be withdrawn for
This reinforced concrete shelter in the Netherlands was
built before the. last war to house works of art in case of
hostilities. When World War II came hundreds of paintings,
statues and other treasures were placed in its vaults for
safekeeping and were thus saved from destruction. Entire
framework is made of steel bars one inch in diameter. The
walls are IS feet thick and the roof, at highest point.
30 feet thick. In most structures roof Is most vulnerable.
reasons of military necessity except by an officer
commanding a force of at least a division or more. In no
case may reprisals ever be made against cultural property.
Special protection will be granted to a limited number of
refuges where works of art and other movable" treasures are
placed in safe keeping. Like Red Cross ambulances,
vehicles transporting works of art to safety will bear the
special Blue Shield markings. They will be granted special
protection to transfer great cultural objects within a
territory or to another territory and will be immune from
"seizure, placing in prize or capture".
Persons guarding property are to be allowed to carry on
their work if captured, and in all cases of either partial or
total occupation of a country, cultural property will be
safeguarded and preserved. All acts of vandalism, any form
of pillage or theft or misappropriation are henceforth
prohibited by the new code of international law. The
signatory states pledge themselves to prevent such acts and
if they should be committed to take the necessary steps to
nalt the expropriation of art treasures.
An additional Protocol provides that works of art cannot
be exported from any territory under occupation and lays
down that they can no longer be retained as war reparations.
The signatories to the Blue Shield Convention finally pledge
that any persons, of whatever nationality, who violate the
Convention or order it to be violated, will be prosecuted on
criminal grounds and penal or disciplinary sanctions imposed.
Hill»-
. Protection of the main portals of the Cathedral
in Genoa, Italy, by strongly revetted sandbag wall.
10
Pulpit of cathedral in Pisa, Italy, protected by
sandbagging against bomb splinters and blast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 7. 1954
The city of Tripoli in northern Lebanon is noted for the peculiarly
oriental fascination of its narrow streets teeming with life, its historic
souks (bazaars), khans (caravanserais), hammams (baths), mosques and
madrasahs (Mohammedan colleges). These are set among houses and
shops in an amazing tangle of arcades, vaults, projections, domes and
minarets. The old town owes its distinctive character to the old
madrasahs, converted into mosques, rather than to the mosques them¬
selves. (Photo shows AI Burtasiyat madrasah with square-minaret
near the old bridge crossing the Nahr Abu-Ali). Lebanese authorities
are today faced with problem of modernizing the city and Unesco spe¬
cialists have suggested schemes for doing so by careful re-planning which
will enhance rather than destroy the beauty of the ancient monuments.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Minarets of Damascus
The Mozaffari Mosque (1202-1213)
Al-Muradiya Mosque (15th century)
Sheik Mohiy ad-Din (1518)
Manjak Mosque (1368)
Jami Juban (14th century)
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 7. 1954
'THE CITADEL OF ALEPPO, with its deep moat and Its steeply sloping bank, etches a lacy crown- around the hill formed by the accumulated
ruins of older civilizations. At its foot spread out the serried network of thoroughfares converging from desert and sea. Relic of the struggles between
Arab and Crusader, the citadel is symbolic of the city which, throughout its long history, has weathered events that brought ruin and death everywhere
around it. The Syrian Government has already done considerable work on the restoration of the citadel, the city walls, and other monuments. Aleppo
has over 200 mosques. For a better idea of the steepness of slope around the citadel, turn photo upside down.
Between the Euphrates and the Mediterranean there are
lands which are literally sown with the relics of civi¬
lizations gone by. In towns, villages and deep in the
desert, there are marvels which might well be the envy
of a score of nations.
These countries, among the richest in history and in its
heritage of stone, are today setting an example to the rest
of the world in protecting the past. The names of their
monuments have a grandiose ring : Tyre, Sidon, Byblos,
ever-prosperous Tripoli, and Baalbek in the Lebanon where
the emperors of Rome trekked in pious pilgrimages
1,800 years ago; Damascus, Aleppo, St. Simeon Stylites, Quse-
el-Heir, the Krak des Chevaliers, Palmyra in Syria...
Here preserving ancient monuments requires more than
good intentions. Many of them lie in remote oases separated
by hundreds of parched miles from the nearest city. Others
are buried in sand, still others nest like eagles on isolated
peaks.
During the early centuries of the Christian era, villages
huddled around monasteries sprang up on Syria's northern
plateau, bounded on the west by the valleys of the Orontes
and the Afrin Rivers. Water tanks made life possible on this
great stretch of limestone and villages prospered with their
olive groves and vineyards. These were peaceful centuries;
oil and wine travelled down roads protected by Rome.
But Rome fell. The roads were no longer safe and the vil¬
lages became deserted islands. For 1,200 years, the plateau
remained lifeless and its ruins were left in the hands of time.
Today, peace has returned to the plateaux and with it the
people of an independent Syria. Obviously, this is progress.
But what about the old basilicas in the forgotten villages?
How can you stop new farmers from tearing them down and
using their stones to build barns ? Ideally, the answer would
be to station a curator with a platoon of guards in every
village but *;hat would not be a practical solutionfor Syria
or any other country.
Obviously, the military and the religious works left by the
Crusaders deserve to be saved. They contain some of
the most beautiful vestiges of medieval architecture on the
face of the earth. But the mere maintenance of these enor¬
mous stone blocks to say nothing of reconstructing entire
sections ready to crumble at any moment is far beyond
the budget of any one ministry.
In Syria, as in the Lebanon, the Government's Antiquities
Service has done remarkable work, but its means are limited.
The' Krak des Chevaliers, one of -the most famous of all
Crusaders' Castles, was restored in 1936 after tremendous
effort. Walls were rebuilt, arches were repaired, an entire
staircase was reconstructed, missing sections of windows
were fitted together and the entrance to its great hall was
completely restored.
Then new disasters struck; lightning demolished the tower
and plants began to invade the foundations. Maintaining
the Krak des Chevaliers is a »ever-ending taskand this is
only one castle among the many to Sprisu
Still, this problem is simple eempared to the dilemma in
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
the expanding cities of Syria and the Lebanon. Since the
war, these cities have been confronted with the need to
adapt themselves to new ways of living. Within three decades,
they have watched their populations double or triple with
a corresponding increase in political and commercial activity.
New buildings, offices, factories. and hotels have sprung up
on the sites of ancient cities. New municipal services have
been grafted onto the old ones or else have replaced them.
In new sections the engineer and the technician have been
able to find solutions. But there remain the old hearts of
cities with their crystallized architecture dating back centu¬
ries. Can they be changed without being destroyed or, at
best, disfigured?
Faced with these problems, Syria and Lebanon both decided
to enlist the help of impartial international experts. The
two countries requested advice from Unesco and, in 1953,
Unesco was able to furnish them the services of Professor
Paul Collart of the Universities of Geneva and Lausanne and
Armando Dillon, superintendent of historical monuments at
Palermo, Sicily. In the Lebanon, the two men worked with
Emir Maurice Chebab, Director of the Lebanese Service of
Antiquities; in Syria, they carried out their mission with Dr.
Selim Abdul-Hak, Director-General of Syrian Antiquities.
Illustrated with maps, plans, sketches and photographs, two
reports which were drawn up these missions have just been
published by Unesco (1).
These books, written in elegant
but simple style, are intended
not only for specialists but for
any reader interested in the fas¬
cinating history and beauty of
Syria and Lebanon. Their pages
contain moving passages on
Baalbek and Palmyra, Tripoli
and the Crusaders' Castles, on
"the land of countless ruins", the
"dead cities of the North", and
"the great ruins in the desert."
The authors point out that
even the most illustrious of pala¬
ces or temples needs to have a
good road leading to it if visitors
are to be able to reach it and
provide the money required to
keep it alive.
In the words of the mission :
"It should only be necessary to
improve certain sections of roads
and establish one or two con¬
veniently situated and unpre¬
tentious but well-run hotels or-
rest-houses, where visitors can
eat and sleep in pleasant sur¬
roundings... to organize tours
either by road or air. In this
respect, Greece, where the tourist
trade has advanced by leaps and
bounds in the space of a few
years, and is now making a con¬
siderable contribution to the
country's economic resources,
seems to us to provide a particu¬
larly good example of what can
be done in this way."
From the wonders of the
desert, the missions then turned
to the growing pains of the historic cities of the Middle East.
The old quarters of Damascus, Aleppo and Tripoli hide un¬
believably beautiful works nearly always ignored by tourists
in a hurry. Most of these buildings are inextricably tangled
in a seething mass of shops, warehouses and homes which,
together, form the picturesque souks.
Of course the souks are anathema to a certain school of
city planning which holds that a street must be a mighty
river ignoring the houses on its banks and mercilessly
washing away any. pedestrians who might venture onto it.
In these cities of the Middle East, many a planner has pro¬
posed at least the partial destruction of old quarters as alive
and as useful today as at any period in their history.
The Syrian and Lebanese Governments, disturbed by the
possible effects of these plans on the historical and artistic
value of ancient buildings and on the character of the
bazaars, asked the Unesco mission to weigh the arguments
for the preservation or destruction of the old quarters.
Concerning the Syrian city of Tripoli, for example, the
authors explained the character of the quarters affected,
their peculiar features and their right to survival after
KHANS such as the Al-Khayyâtin khan in Tripoli (above)
are the business centrescaravanserais or storehouses of
the old towns of the Lebanon and Syria. For 600 years tailors
have been working in the shops among the arcades of this one.
making allowances for the requirements of a modern city.
They wrote:
"The bazaars, set among houses, mosques, khans, ham-
mams, and madrasahs, might be compared to the arteries
and veins of a living body; time and use have made them
throb with a life that gives some inner meaning to every
corner, every view. They are inseparably linked with the
motley-dressed" crowd and the shops crammed with wares.
"These are not streets in the modern sense of the word:
nowadays, in the new districts, the street is public property;
at the same time it is necessary to all the houses on either
side. But here, the street is hewn, as it were, from the
substance of the architecture itself. Making One's way
through the. souks is like joining a natural process of ebb
and flow, drifting with a current, walking through the very -
buildings. Every corner has an air of its own.
"Yet one can pass repeatedly along the same stretch of
road, or walk round and round the same khan quite unaware
that one is doing so. Merely to turn back is to have the
impression of seeing something fresh, as though peering at
the ever-changing forms and colours of the patterns in a
kaleidoscope. In the maze of streets which seem to put
out fresh tentacles, intertwining to lead us astray, the mo¬
numental doorway of a mosqüe or madrasah, the lofty pin¬
nacle of a minaret, or a glimpse of some dome or khan,
serves as a reassuring landmark.
"AU big modern towns now
have their 'stores' great com¬
plex buildings which, like the
khans and caravanserais of for¬
mer times, are planned to include
large warehouses, and where
goods of every type can be found.
To a visitor, the old town of Tri¬
poli looks like one enormous
store, with its different depart¬
ments for produce and manufac¬
tured articles, handicrafts and
business negotiations.
"It is delight to stroll through
the souks, sheltered from sun and
rain, wind and dust, admiring
the wide range of goods on sale,
from costly jewellery offered by
the goldsmiths, deep-piled car¬
pets and an endless variety of
multicoloured textiles, to fruit
vegetables and sweetmeats.
"The visitor has the same pleas¬
ure here that he feels in wander¬
ing through the by-streets and
mercerie of Venice or the old
parts of Vienna, Paris or Flo¬
rence. Leaving the wide streets
where the traffic is controlled by
police and signals, to plunge into
the old districts where modern
vehicles cannot penetrate, 'he
feels relaxed and rested."
(1) "Lebanon" Volume VI (price $1.25; 7/6; 350 fr) and "Syria" Volume
VII 'price $1.50; 8/6; 400 fr) inthe collection "Museums and Historical
Monuments".
The report recognizes that these
quarters may have to undergo
change, but it pleads for prudence.
The authors lay down a principle:
the preservation of historical
monuments is not merely a convenience, but is a moral obliga¬
tion as well. These monuments stand as symbols of spirit¬
ual values; as long as they stand, they are part and parcel
of the education of a people. Their destruction means turn¬
ing our backs on what we have inherited from our ancestors.
The conclusions drawn from this study of a few cases in
Syria and the Lebanon are valid in every country at least,
in every country where man has been able to leave age-old
traces of his labour and of his genius. In . every city with
historical monuments worthy of the name, citizens are
coming to realize that saving their monuments is in then-
own interest, v It is the responsibility of the town planner
to conserve these monuments and even to create more'
favourable surroundings for them, taking into account their
proportions, their character and their style.
As Professor Collart puts it, "far from hindering the na¬
tural development of a city, (historical monuments) should
continue to embellish it, being given their rightful place' in
the scene so as to do full justice to their cultural significance
as well as to the needs of modern life. To that end, efforts
should also be made to allow historical monuments to serve
their original purpose, or to find a suitable new one for them,
so that they are not left aside as useless relics of the past
but play a real part in the Ufe of the city."
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 7. 1954
'£^Á*'**m ^"
a sS^a^^P
" > A *
.' A'."' : -3r
It was not until the close of the 17th century that the ruins of Palmyra, forgotten and fallen
into decay, were rediscovered. In background stands Palmyra's ancient Arab castle.
The Land
of Countless Ruins
s,'TRIA is a corridor and a meeting place. From east to west and
north to south, it is traversed by two natural highways, one winding
through the valleys of the Euphrates and Orontes to link the East with
the Mediterranean world, and the other carrying the northern peoples
southwards to Africa. Through the ages the country has been occupied
for short or long periods by Mesopotamians, Egyptians, Hittites, Assy-
nans, Persians, Greeks, Romans, Arabs, Crusaders and Ottomans.
In Syriaat Kadesh and the Yarmuksome of. the great clashes of
history have taken place. Out on the Syrian desert, I 50 miles northeast
of Damascus, stands Palmyra, the Tadmor of the Bible, said to have been
founded by Solomon. Before the Christian era, the city was a trading
post on the camel route between the East and the Mediterranean world.
But its real glory came after the Romans captured it in 130 A.D. and
made it the headquarters of a great colony and outpost against the
revival of a Persian empire. Under Odenathus, ruler of Palmyra, and
later his widow Zenobia, the city became virtually independent. Zeno¬
bia extended her domain until it reached from Egypt to Mesopotamia
and came Into conflict with Rome. Her armies were defeated by the
soldier-emperor Aurelian and Palmyra fell in 273. Zenobia was taken
away in chains but the Palmyrenes revolted. Aurelian returnedT
swiftly and destroyed the city. Thereafter the caravans took!
other routes and the magnificent ruins remained stark and empty j
under the desert skies or else slowly vanished under the sand.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
-fr LAND OF RUINS (Cont'd.)
PALMYRA
THE Syrian desert is not uniformly
barren. There are enormous
stretches of steppeland, where
life is not impossible, or at least not
permanently so. The winter rains,
rare though they are, make the pas¬
tures green and fill the water-holes. The
wandering Bedouins manage to feed
" their flocks all the year round ; and
their camps are found here and there
in the desert solitudes. In some
places indeed, there is sedentary as
well as nomadic life ; near a well or
a spring a group of dwellings may be
built, palm trees grow up and crops
are cultivated.
The necessary conditions for the de¬
velopment of certain sites, when cir¬
cumstances are favourable, may thus
be found. At certain times in history,
irrigation work has been undertaken to
assist crop growing and reservoirs have
been dug to make permanent settle¬
ment possible. Trade has provided a
means of livelihood for a larger popula¬
tion than the products of the earth
would have sufficed to maintain. Mili¬
tary defence requirements have led to
the building of forts and castles, and
the necessary supplies for those who"
manned them have had to be found.
This accounts for the establishment
of the great desert routes, with their
chains of halting-places at the only
spots where the existence of natural or
artificial resources made life possible.
The natural route from the Persian
Gulf to the Mediterranean, via the Eu¬
phrates valley to Aleppo and Antioch,
was shortened by the short cut across
the desert which of necessity passed
through" Palmyra, either continuing
straight to the Horns Gap or turning
south towards Damascus and Palestine.
Settlements grew up, at each end of
the desert route or at oases along it,
or again at strategic points such as
river crossings or mountain gorges.
The ruins of Palmyra are striking
both for their size and their wonderful
state of preservation. From the~ regular
chessboard pattern of the streets, still
discernible inside the outer wall of the
town, rise rows of columns, sanctuary
precincts, porticos and steps of public
buildings. Round the city lie the vast
burial grounds, with their varying types
of burial vaults, tombs in the form of.
houses, hypogea, and sepulchral towers,
all of which, though violated from an¬
cient times onwards, still retain their
decorations and inscriptions as well as
most of the innumerable sculptures
they contained.
Whole structures still remain to their
full height : large sections of the main
colonnade are still upright and the en¬
tablature is still supported on the
pillars with their consoles ; the temple
of Baal, surrounded by its courtyard
wall and porticos is almost intact ; the
sepulchral towers in which the dead
mount guard along the pass leading
to Horns and Damascus stand out
square and sombre against the hill¬
side, flanking the route. Crowning the
mountain with its tours and redans
stands the Arab castle, one of the most
striking features of the landscape.
As far as the parts of the buildings
which lie below the surface are con¬
cerned, excavations have shown how
little they have suffered from the ra¬
vages of time, a fact accounted for
by the excellent condition of the sub¬
soil and the dryness of the climate.
The freshness of the paintings inside
the tombs provides an illustration.
Moreover, as the ancient city is almost
everywhere covered by a layer of earth
9 to 12 feet thick, even those monu¬
ments which are entirely concealed are
preserved to a considerable height.
Another reason is that the town ra¬
pidly fell into decay after its destruc¬
tion in 273 and never regained its for¬
mer importance ; buildings were seldom
converted to other uses and, . except
for a few that later served for military
purposes (such as the one now known
as Diocletian's camp, or the forecourt
of the temple of Baal, which was
transformed into an Arab fortress in
the twelfth century), the buildings
were never intentionally demolished or
their stones carried off.
The Syrian Directorate of Antiquities
has worked out an admirable and ex¬
tensive scheme for uncovering the en¬
tire ruins. The clearing of the agora
before the war, and that of the theatre,
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 7. 1954
quite recently, have shown what spec¬
tacular and instructive results may
one day be gained from the scheme.
The work is proceeding steadily but the
task is immense.
The monumental arch, the temple of
Baal, the great colonnade and innumer¬
able tombs, towers and hypogea re¬
quired extensive restoration and con¬
solidation. The removal of the decora¬
tive sculpture of the Yarhai hypo-
geum and its reconstruction in the
Damascus Museum was a difficult
undertaking, successfully accomplished.
A bold plan was adopted to allow of
the uncovering of Baal's sanctuary.
The modern town, whose houses filled
the temple precincts, was removed and
rebuilt further north, beyond the boun¬
dary of the ancient city. Now, after
20 years, the whole population agrees
that the step was well justified, for the
new village, with its wide airy streets,
affords healthier and more convenient
living conditions ; this may serve as
an example. . *>
But Palmyra is not only a city ; it
is the natural centre of an .immense
region stretching from the Anti-Leba¬
non mountains to the Euphrates, a re¬
gion whose prospects and importance
are now beginning to be realized.
Along the desert routes which meet
and cross within it, and where they
reach the river, are other sites, mark¬
ing wayside centres which existed at
various times in history.
1 Courtyard colonnade of Temple of Baal,
Palmyra, which became an Arab fortress.
2 Two aerial views of -the striking ruins of
Palmyra, once a great trading centre.
r
V,fc-fcr-
I, 7 -*-,(_
ÍV-
r- <^^y-
T
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
* LAND OF RUINS (Cont'd.)
UNESCO COURIER. N" 7. 1954
B a a 1 b
Despite the Inroads of earthquakes, emperors and "collec¬
tors", the Roman temples of Baalbek in the Lebanon are
among the most grandiose of the monuments of antiquity
surviving today. The Byzantine rulers pulled down the
altars to build a church there ; the Arabs converted the
temples into a fortress ; and hardly more than a century
ago, Lamartine carted off a full camel load of their rich
treasures. The site was saved following a German archaeo-
oglcal expedition en 1900. The Lebanese Government
began the tough Job of consolidating, restoring and clearing
the ruins in 1934 and this was resumed at the end of the
last war. Unesco proposals for enhancing and easing
access to the ruins are now also belny considered. Below
are the six pillars of the Temple of Jupiter, the tallest
columns in the world. The substructure contains some
of the largest single blocks of stone ever cut, weighing at
least 1,000 tons. The largest block ' the world though is
In a near-by quarry still not completely cut away. It mea¬
sures 60 feet in length and 17 by 24 feet In cross-section.
Above right, ruins of the Arab mosque. Left, the
Temple of Bacchus, whose lofty portico and Interior deco¬
ration have been preserved almost Irjtáct, making It the
richest Corinthian building of the Roman world to come
down to us in present times.
Krak des
Chevaliers
The most striking monuments in the whole Syrian region
from the coast to the mountainous hinterland are the great
buildings raised by the Crusaders. They bear witness to
the colossal efforts made by the Western peoples over two
centuries to gain a foothold on this coast, as do the opposing
Arab citadels built along the valley of the river Orontes in
order to hold them In check. Most famous of all the Crusaders
castles Is the Krak des Chevaliers perched on its lonely vantage-point among the bare mountains, standing
guard over the great Horns gap. Its double line of fortifications, machicolations, underground passages
and great sloping glacis contrast not only with the architecture of the great hall and Its portico with their
cross-ribbed vaults, pillared doorways, mullloned windows and carved ornamentation but also with the aus-
terer architecture of the chapel. The surrender of the Knights Hospitallers to Beibars, and the fall of the
Krak in 1271, heralded the collapse of the Crusaders. In 1936 the Krak was restored and an entire village
built within the ramparts dislodged. But since then it has suffered considerable damage which meant re¬
building walls, repairing vaults and reconstructing a stairway. Unfortunately few people visit the Krak (less
than 120 a month) since it can be reached only by Jeep.
The Pillar -Hermit
of Qalat Seman
Few regions have so many ruins in so small
an area as does northern Syria. Of these,
Qalat Seman (St. Simeon Stylites) west of
Aleppo, has been termed "the greatest and
grandest Christian ruin in the East" (centre
photo). It grew up round the almost unbel¬
ievable figure of St Simeon, the world's first
pillar-hermit. At the age of 16 Simeon retired to a monastery. Because of his excessive austerities (he
once buried himself up to the chin in the monastery garden for an entire summer to discipline himself), he
was expelled and became a solitary hermit In the desert. In 423 A. D. he took up his abode atop a ten-foot
pillar. From this he graduated to higher and higher pillars finally mounting a 50-foot column where he re-
18
mained for 27 years, without ever descending, until his death. To prevent his falling off, he had an iron
collar round his neck attached to the stone by a chain, and a low railing built round the edge of his tiny
perch. It was so small that he could sit or kneel on It but not lie down. Meagre food rations were brought
to him daily by ladder. Twice daily he preached to the crowds below and prostrated himself over 1,000 times
a day in prayer. Thus he lived on from year to year, through the bitter winter cold of north Syria and the broil¬
ing summer heat, a miracle of endurance. His fame spread at once and. pilgrims flocked to Qalat Seman
the whole Christian world, even from remote Britain, to hear his wise counsel or In the hope of a mira¬
culous cure. After his death in 459, the existing huge church was built, centred around the saint's pillar ins¬
tead of the usual altar. (Photo left, shows ruins of central octagon and base of St Simion's pillar).
In the valley below there grew up a large pilgrim town (Deir Seman) with hostels, public baths, churches,
convents and private houses, the majestic ruins of which still remain. (Photo right, church of Deir Seman).
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
^ Courtes/ "Scientific American '
UP FROM THEOCEAN FLOOR comes a water sampler
(right) used by oceanographers to explore the lower depths.
Above, six other exploring instruments: I) fine net to
filter plankton out of water. 2) a "grab" to bring up samples
showing the composition of the ocean bottom. 3) thermo¬
meter. 4) bottle for sampling water at different levels.
5) reel to measure length of cable paid out. 6) bathyther¬
mograph to record temperature and pressure.
THE UNTOID
TREASURES
OF THE SEA
Geography is a Mature
Science, Oceanography
a Growing Infant
by Gerald Wendt
Courtesy " Scientific Monthly "
The soil and the sea are the two great resources of mankind. Both
have been explored for centuries and have yielded their treasures for
man's use. But man can walk on the land and cultivate it for food and
clothing; he can dig holes in it to bring up fuels, minerals and building
stones from beneath. Though part of the land is too dry, too cold, or too
steep to have much value,. most of it offers an adequate abode for man
and has been inhabited for many thousands of years. Within the past
century geographers have studied and mapped nearly all of it, seeking
the best utilization of its resources.
Not so the sea. Its vast fluid mass offers no home, no foothold.
Courage and much skill were needed by ancient Phoenicians and Poly¬
nesians to embark upon it and by Columbus to cross it. It has majestic
beauty but it is not hospitable and defies permanent conquest. Its rest¬
less surface is familiar but its treasures are in the mysterious depths
wnere no man can live. There life began and there it is still the richest
on earth. As the resources of the land become exhausted by a crowding
population, the unknown and unused resources of the sea become an
insistent challenge to man's intelligence. The science of oceanography
succeeds geography as the guide to future wealth.
Like the weather, the sea is of universal interest. It touches all
countries except a very few, among them Switzerland, Austria, Czecho¬
slovakia, Hungary, Bolivia, Paraguay, Afghanistan and Rhodesia. The
island and peninsular nations such as England, Greece, Norway, Den¬
mark and Japanhave had the longest contact with it, both in coastline
and in history.
In the Philippines, for instance, none of the 20 million people is
more than 75 miles from the seashore and most of them live close to it.
There are 7,100 islands with a total coastline of 10,800 miles. Their land
area is about 115,000 square miles but the Philippine marine waters
cover almost six times that area, or 650,000 square miles. Such nations
know the sea and depend on it for food and trade. But the oceans are
free except for a narrow strip near the shore. They belong to no nation
and their resources and problems are essentially international.
Nearly three quarters of the earth's surface is covered by the sea.
The total ocean area is 139 million square miles compared with 58 million
square miles of land and less than 10 million square miles under
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 7. 1954
cultivation. Thus almost 72 percent of the life-giving sunshine
falls upon and into the sea and at present is chiefly useful
to man by evaporating the surface water to form clouds and
rain upon the land. Most of the sunlight, penetrating into
the water, keeps the ocean warm but is otherwise lost to
man's use. It is mankind's greatest waste.
Unlike the land, the ocean has three accessible dimensions.
It is not only wide but deep, and the depths can be reached.
There are shallow waters close to the continents but the-
deepest areas are farther beneath the surface than the
highest mountains are above it. If the earth's highest
mountain, Mount Everest in the Himalayas, could be dropped
into the Marianas Trench in the Pacific its peak would be
more than a mile under water, for it is only 29,002 feet high
while the floor of the ocean trench lies 35,640 feet down. The
average depth of the ocean, the world over, is about 12,450
feet (2.38 miles).
Covering such an area to such a depth, the total amount of
water in the ocean surpassés the imagination. It occupies
331 million cubic miles. While one cubic mile is a mere drop
in the ocean, a cubic mile is so large that the entire human
race could be packed into less than one tenth of it. Or, if a
cubic mile of water were loaded into railway tank cars, each
containing 10,000 gallons and 40 feet in length, it would fill
113,200,000 such cars. They would make a train 834,000 miles
long. Running steadily at 40 miles an hour, the train would
take two years and five months to pass any one point.
Compared with- man's needs and dimensions, the sea is
practically infinite.
The sea is much more than water. It holds in solution
enormous quantities of materials dissolved from the rocks
and washed from the land by the rain and the rivers. Every
cubic mile of it contains 141 million tons of common salt.
There are other minerals, such as magnesium and bromine
which have already been extracted commercially. It contains
gold and iron in solution and can perhaps provide man with
metals when the mines are exhausted.
Most important of the dissolved minerals, however, are
those that are necessary to plant growth and are used by
man as fertilizers for the soil. Each cubic mile contains
750 tons of nitrogen as nitrate, 225 tons of phosphorus and
1.8 million tons of potassium (potash). They are not impor¬
tant because they can be extracted from the sea but because
they are available in the ocean waters to play their part in
the luxurious growth of sea plants of all kinds.
Even more important is the fact that sea water contains in .
solution twenty or thirty times as much carbon dioxide as
there is in the earth's atmosphere. Plants are built up from
carbon dioxide and water under the energy of the sun, with
the assistance of a few fertilizer minerals. The ocean has
them all. It is the scene of enormous plant growth and thus
of teeming animal life that feeds upon the plants.
Since plants need sunshine and the sunshine is absorbed
in the upper regions of the sea, there is little or no plant
growth in the dark depths. Most of it occurs near the
surface. No accurate measurement is possible of the amount
of growth each year but experts estimate it at about 18 tons
per acre of ocean surface.
:'
FISH AT THE BOTTOM is photographed at the
great depth of 1,000 feet by an underwater television
camera. Underneath the fish is its shadow. Television
cameras first showed their great possibilities for glean¬
ing information below the sea surface in 1951 when
one of them identified the wreck of a British submarine,
280 feet down at the bottom of the English Channel.
Photo courtesy " Scientific American "
This is a greater average than plant production on land
and, because the ocean surface is so much larger than the
land surface, the total production in the ocean far exceeds
that on land. It is never interrupted by droughts, storms or
other natural catastrophes and is also entirely independent
of what man can do to increase or decrease it. This steady,
unseen production of 12,000 tons of new vegetation per
square mile every year over an area of 139 million square
miles is probably nature's most impressive feat.
Most of the plants thus produced are microscopic and are
consumed by microscopic sea animals. The two together are
called plankton and form the food of. the smaller fishes,
which, in turn, feed the larger ones. Some of the plankton
settles to the bottom to feed the crawling life there. Even¬
tually the plant and animal residues on the bottom form an
organic deposit which is the source of future petroleum.
Meanwhile the sea supports an enormous population of
swimming fishes whose number and weight are beyond
estimate. This mass is certainly comparable with the
12,000 tons of vegetable plankton produced annually per
square mile. Yet the amount of ocean fish caught each year
is only 396 pounds per square mile or 0.6 pounds per acre.
(Continued' on next page)
M I 1> 6 E T
L I Vï A
MONSTERS
MILE DOWN
These ferocious little fishes live in a dark and cold world. Scarcity of food
stunts their growth to about four inches or less. Water pressure is a to« per
square inch. If the fishes rise too high above the sea bed the gases in their
swimming bladders expand and they become lighter. Once they lose control
of their movements they are doomed to rise until they burst. These deep-sea
creatures are thus in the curious danger of dying by "failing" upwards.
DRAGON FISH, like its fellow
deep-sea fish would burst if
it was ii.ougnt to the surface.
LINOPHRYNE ARBORI-
FER Is a fish with a
luminous bulb and a beard.
PHOTOCORYNUS SINICEPS though only
two and a half inches long, is a fierce prowler.
THE ANGLER FISH attracts its prey with
the light which grows from its head.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
LIGHT ENDS
EXPOSED PLATE ,
SHOWS NO IMAGE
PRESSURE INCREASES
AT RATE OF LISTONS
TO THE MILE
AVERAGE DEPTH
OF OCEAN""
THE UNTOLD TREASURES OF THE SEA (Continued)
It is evident that the food resources of the sea
are as yet hardly touched by man.
Nevertheless the total annual catch of sea¬
foods the world over amounts to ,25,000 million
tons, not including whales which would add
another ten percent. But this weight includes
the shells of oysters and of crustaceans and
large quantities of fish that are used for bait,
oil, fish meal and fertilizer. The edible por¬
tions of the . fish caught amount to about
10,000 million tons a year. As food for the
earth's 2,400 million inhabitants this provides
a yearly average of nine pounds per person.
But the average consumption of all foods is
about 1,100 pounds per person per year; thus
fish and all seafoods account for less than one
percent of human nutrition. Since fish is a
cheap and healthy food with 18 % protein,
5 % fat and about 500 calories per pound, it is
apparent . that the consumption of fish could
be greatly increased with benefit to all. Thus
from the standpoint of both consumption and
production a precious and
much needed resource laps
on the shores of, most
nations of the earth.
The United "Nations
Food and Agriculture
Organization (F.A.O.)
asserts that the world
aquatic resources are
capable of furnishing man
with a quantity, of food
many times larger than at
present and that one of
the chief obstacles to an
increase in the fish supply
is the lack of a larger
demand. This, in turn, is
partly because of com¬
mercial and economic fac¬
tors but also is largely a
result of ignorance of the
nutritive value of seafoods
and of prejudices and
taste habits.
A great increase in the
fish supply can be attained
by greater mechanization
of - the fishing boats so
that they can cover larger
areas and by better
methods of locating fish.
But a great underlying
need is better knowledge
of the life-habits ' of fish
and the interrelations
between the many forms
of life in the ocean, the
possible destruction of
predators and the culti¬
vation óf preferred species.
The practical improvement
of fishing is, indeed, only
one aspect of research in the larger problems
of oceanography.
Marine biology has long been a fascinating
study, conducted largely by many government
agencies and by private laboratories such as
the Océanographie Museum founded by the
Prince of Monaco and by such foundations as
the Carnegie Institution at La Jolla, California
and the Wood's Hole Océanographie Institu¬
tion established by the Rockefeller Foundation
in the U.S.A. Deep-sea expeditions, such as
that of H.M.S. Challenger in 1872-75 and of
the Swedish Albatross, in 1942-48, have long
explored the depths and the life in them. But
the systematic exploration of the sea and its
complex physics, chemistry, biology and geo¬
logy is now seen as an international problem.
Oceanography includes the study of the
oceans themselves, their contents and their
interrelations with the rocks, sediments and
shores and with the atmosphere. -It is the
study of the water masses, their chemical
composition and movements and the vast
complexity of biological organisms which they
contain. It includes the effect of atmospheric
changes, winds, the effect of the sun's radiation
4 M 1 LES
5 MILES
3500
40O0
	
4500
6 MILES
5000
DEEPEST POINT SO
FAR DISCOVERED OFF
GUAM 35,640 FEET.
PRESSURE ABOUT
15,800 POUNDS,
NEARLY 8 TONS PER
SQUARE INCH.
6.7MILES \
5500
5900
£» ç-ïtea'jr..
A MIGHTY GULF in the floor of the
Atlantic Ocean is the Lydonia Canyon
whose profile is" shown here as it was
traced with a fathometer (echo sounding
device) by the U.S.S. Albatross. Scien¬
tists of the I 947 Swedish Deep-Sea Expe¬
dition crossing the Atlantic in another
Albatross found that the ocean floor
rose and fell in curious steps on a Gargan¬
tuan scale, half a mile to several miles wide.
SIX MILES
OF OCEAN
If you could ' drop
Mount Everest, the
world's highest moun¬
tain, into the Marianas
Trench, the deepest
part of the ocean, it
would not reach within
a mile of the surface.
Note that only a thin
layer at the top is
lighted by rays of sun.
and the circulation of currents "in the ocean.
It includes also the study of the ocean
bottom, its geological features and history
and the study of the deep sediments that
" have accumulated there through the ages.
The study of the ocean floor is already
the subject of specialized international study
under the leadership of the Joint Commission
on Oceanography of the International Council
of Scientific Unions. This Commission has
recommended the establishment of an Inter¬
national Deep-Sea Council for the world-wide
co-ordination of these researches.
In 1952 the Indo-Pacific Fisheries Council
proposed a programme of international co-ope¬
ration in océanographie studies which would
establish a complete register of all laboratories
and vessels engaged in such research, a file of
all available data and publications, a consult¬
ing service for governments in the planning of
océanographie researches and of industrial
applications, and which would co-ordinate all
national programmes with
the co-operation of Unesco
in the fundamental
oceanographical sciences
and of the U.N. Food and
Agriculture Organization
in the application of these
sciences to fisheries.
In the Indo-Pacific area
many laboratories already
exist for océanographie
researches. They include
the Central Marine and
Fisheries Research Station
at Mandapan, South India,
the Océanographie Insti¬
tute of Indochina at
Nhatrang, the océanogra¬
phie department of the
Bureau of Fisheries in the
Ministry of Commerce and
Agriculture at Manila,
the Philippines, the Océa¬
nographie Institute of the
Fisheries Department of
Singapore and The Fede¬
ration, the Laboratory for
the Investigation of the
Sea at Djakarta, Indone¬
sia and the Océanographie
Institute, New Caledonia.
Japan has more than a
dozen organizations devot¬
ed to océanographie re¬
search and has organized
a Special Committee on
Marine Resources in the
Unesco Committee of the
Science Council of Japan.
The Japanese National
Committee for Unesco in
1953 revived the publica¬
tion of the Records of Océanographie Works in
Japan which World War II had interrupted.
In November, 1953, a group of experts met
at Manila in conjunction with the Eighth
Pacific Science Congress and under invitations
issued jointly by Unesco and F.A.O. to discuss
the possibilities of establishing an interna¬
tional océanographie organization in the Indo-
Pacific region.
Thus the earth's last great frontier is under
increasing exploration. There are spectacular
forays such as Professor Piccard's descent in
his bathyscaph and those pleasant scouting
expeditions by many amateurs armed with
oxygen tanks who swim freely in shallow shore
waters to study marine life, or undertake
archaeological treasure hunts for sunken ships.
But the real treasures of the sea lie far off
-shore and far beneath the waves.ä They are
the vast quantities of food for the ever-grow¬
ing human race and, even more important, the
hidden secrets of how life originated a thous¬
and million or more years ago. If earth is the
mother of man, the sea is the mother of life.
The earth's lesson has to a large extent been
learned. Those of the sea have just begun.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. _ N» 7. 1954
N December 21, 1872, the 2,300 ton wooden
corvette H.M.S. Challenger sailed out of
Portsmouth, England, to explore "condi¬
tions of the Deep Sea throughout all the
Great Oceanic Basins". During three
and a half years she sailed and steamed
nearly 70,000 nautical miles around the globe, and
made observations by soundings at 362 stations scatter-
- ed over the 140 million square miles of the ocean
floor. When she returned to England in May 1876,
she had sounded the depths of every ocean except the
Arctic and had laid the foundation for the modern
science of oceanography.
The scientific expedition,^ coming only 40 years
after the famous voyage of Darwin aboard the Beagle
(1831-36) aroused considerable public attention. It
proved beyond question that life existed at, great
depths in the sea, disproved the myth of the lost conti¬
nent of Atlantis, charted the first systematic plot of
ocean currents and temperatures, showed that the
temperature in each zone was fairly constant in all
seasons , and charted what is ' still today our basic
map of the world under the seas.
Before the Challenger only a few isolated soundings
had been taken of the ocean depths , and it was generally
believed that nothing could live in the cold , black waters
of the deep sea.* Even the British biologist Edward
Forbes, one of the first men to take a scientific interest
in the ocean depths held the belief that no life existed
below 1,500 feet. A century ago he wrote: "As we
descend deeper and deeper into this region, the inha¬
bitants become more and more modified, and fewer
and fewer, indicating our approach to an abyss where
life is either extinguished or exhibits but a few sparks
to mark its lingering presence."
But Forbes urged more exploration of "this vast
deep-sea region" to settle the question definitely, and
his own pioneer work in the Aegean Sea led the way
for the Challenger expedition. In 1818 worms were
brought up by an Arctic expedition from 1 ,000 fathoms ;
in 1860, a cable in the Mediterranean bed at 1,200
fathoms was found encrusted with corals and other
animals.
Then came the voyage of the Challenger. "From
bottoms lying under miles of water", writes Rachel
L. Carson in her now famous The Sea Around Us,
"from silent deeps carpeted with red clay ooze, and
from all the Hghtless Intermediate depths, net-haul
after net-haul of strange and fantastic creatures came
up and were spilled out on the decks. Poring over the
weird beings thus brought up for the first time into the
light of day, beings no man had ever seen before, the
Challenger scientists realized that life existed even
on the deepest floor of the abyss."
The Challenger was fitted with everything that could
be carried in the way of appliances for scientific research
at the time. Its equipment included sounding
instruments, water bottles, undersea thermometers,
144 miles of sounding rope and 12.5 miles of sounding
wire; sinkers, nets, dredges, and "spirits of wine"
for preserving specimens. A fully equipped zoolo¬
gical laboratory was set up on board. The Royal
Society drew up a complete scheme of instructions for
the voyage, captained by George Nares and led by
. Charles Wyville Thomson.
For a year the Challenger fitted with auxiliary
steam power in addition to her sails, explored the
Atlantic depths, crossing from the Canary Islands
to the West Indies, skirting the American side as far
north as Nova Scotia, then recrossing the" Atlantic
to the Azores. She then sailed to the Brazilian coast
and crossed the southern Atlantic to the Cape of Good
Hope. From there, the Challenger headed into the
southernmost part of the Indian Ocean and was the
first steamship to cross the Antarctic Circle. After
reaching the ice-pack she was caught in a dense snow¬
storm and crashed into an iceberg (losing the jib boom
and other rigging, later recovered.) The Challenger
then proceeded to Australia, Fiji, the Philippines,
Japan, China and the Sandwich Islands.
On March 23, 1875, off the Marianas Islands, the
expedition made its deepest sounding 26,850 feet.
With a little luck, the Challenger might have disco¬
vered the deepest known place in the ocean, the Maria¬
nas Trench, some 200 miles southwest of Guam. It
was a second H.M.S. Challenger that obtained a
sounding of 35,640 feet in October 1951, 200 feet
deeper than the Mindanao Trench off the Philippines
reported by a German cruiser in 1927.
After sailing due south to the Tropic of Capricorn,
the Challenger expedition took an easterly course to
Valparaiso, Chile, made its way into the south Atlantic
again through the Straits of Magellan and ended
its remarkable voyage in England on May 24, 1876.
The narrative of the expedition has been told in popu¬
lar form in Moseley's: "A Naturalist on the Challen¬
ger." Thecomplete account of the scientific results of the
voyage was published over a period of ten years in 50
volumes , the first of which contains an Interesting
"Narrative of the Cruise".
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
WORLD HISTORY
Toning down its
' Western accent '
By Professor Marshall G. S. Hodgson, University of Chicago
DURING the past decade or so
there has been an increasing
awareness of a need for history
of a world scope. But what goes by
the name of "world history" is still
essentially Western history amplified
by a few unrelated chapters on other
parts of the world, notably India,
Ch*na and Japan. During the last
3,000 years there has been one zone,
the Eastern Hemisphere, in which
various lands of urbanized literate
civilization have been in commercial
and commonly in intellectual contact
with each other. Today at least 90%
of the world's population now traces
its history to some segment of this
zone of nations. A history of inter¬
regional developments among the
civilizations of the Eastern Hemi¬
sphere, developments transcending
cultural regions like Europe, the
Middle East, India or the Confucian
lands, will go far toward meeting our
needs for world history. These are
some of the points made by Professor
Marshall G.S. Hodgson, of the Univer¬
sity of Chicago, in an article which
appeared in Journal of World History
(Vol. In' 3) published by the Inter¬
national Commission for a History of
the Scientific and Cultural Develop¬
ment of Mankind, part of which is
-published below.
When we set out to give history
a world-wide perspective we
find our attempts being
paralysed by habitual distortions in
our ideas of mankind dating from
the days of Western world domi¬
nance. In Western thinking
and this thinking still dominates
too greatly other parts of the world
as well the West was the centre
of the world ; and the world at
large was to be regarded, historically
most especially, in the light of its
effect upon and contributions to the
modern West. Is not the world now
Westernized? we have justified our¬
selves; not noticing that (even if this
were true) there is a great difference
of historical structure and perspective
between even such a world and the
West itself.
All too often men of other regions
also have tacitly accepted the Western
criterion, trying to show the suprem¬
acy of their own region by showing
how much it helped to form or is
worthy to alter, the West. Such an
explicit orientation is now being
sloughed off; but it has left innumer¬
able traces in our thinking which do
not disappear so easily.
A peculiarly important example of
the results of this attitude is the
concept of "the Orient". The word
has meant many things; as used by
historians it has come to mean, if
taken " generally, all those urbanized
and literate countries of the Eastern
Hemisphere, whether south or east of
Europe, which were eventually sub¬
jected in various degrees to the West-
European expansion after 1500. There
is no internal point 'of unity among
these peoples, apart from their rela¬
tion to Europe, which they do not
share as much with Europe itself as
among one another; the term is
therefore a negative one, like "for¬
eign" ; it has meaning only in a com¬
mon contrast to the triumphant West.
Yet repeatedly it is taken to have
a substantive content. One hears not
only general remarks about the
"Oriental" character, bred of the
same ignorance in the West as similar
general remarks about "foreigners". -
One, hears mention of -"Oriental"
philosophy, or art, or even race.
Such mentions, in practice, usually
refer to some particular region, rather
than the formless conglomerate that
would result from an attempt to lump
the greater part of civilized man
together in a single cultural pattern.
But the more inclusive expectations
they foster are nevertheless often
taken seriously often even by
"Orientals" themselves; it is not rare
for a native of Egypt or some equally
Mediterranean country to take the
credit for the best lives of India on
the one hand and China or Japan on
the other over three thousand years,
as proof of "Oriental" superiority over
the materialistic modern West.
T
he root f'allacy is to take
"Orient" and "Occident" for
-"- two equal halves of the world.
A Mercator projection map of the
world, which frankly exaggerates
the Western countries in comparison
to more southerly lands like India,
may encourage this. (One wonders
how much less tenacious the concep¬
tion would be if mapmakers could
be persuaded to drop that mischie¬
vous projection altogether!) But
the new global maps, as well as the
briefest study of linguistic and histor¬
ical variation, will remind us that the
West is historically simply one among
several regions in the Eastern Hemi¬
sphere, each of the same order as
itself in size, populousness, and cul¬
tural wealth.
The elimination of catch-all
categories like "Orient" and the
very similar "Asia" will automatic¬
ally rid us of many absurdities in
daily conversation (at least in the
United States). For instance, that
one *or another gathering is truly
world-wide because it has members
from "all the continents" so many
from North America, so many from
South America, so many from Europe,
a couple from Africa, and even one
or two from "Asia".
Or the fatuous remark of a popular
"world" historian, that Europe pro¬
gressed and "Asia" did not, because
Europe's rivers flowed from the heart
of the continent out to the sea,
whereas "Asia" had no such rivers.
The Narbadda is roughly as long as
the Rhine, and the Ganges as the
Danube, and waters lands as diverse.
B
fm ut even in serious history such
II absurdities take their toll. It
-m^ is very hard to persuade a his¬
torian of "world literature" that it is
misleading to give a chapter to each
of the little literatures of Europe, and
then one chapter to that of "India"
as if he shared the supposition so
often found among the uninformed
that one should learn "'Indian" before
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 7. 1954
going to live there. If it is worth¬
while treating world literature at all,
then Tamil and Bengali and Maratha
should have chapters as distinct from
Sanskrit as are the Italian and Ger¬
man from the Latin; if this should
show up a cultural poverty in Bengali
or Maratha, that would already be a
point gained.
But in any case, for the purposes of
comparison and of perspective, it
would reflect the position of India as
an understandably complex sub-con¬
tinent not as one incomprehensibly
vast "country" in "Asia" roughly
answering to Italy in the more com¬
prehensible Europe. Throughout the
serious work of scholars we find
"international" affairs in Europe
treated as matters of world import,
while relations between parts of
Africa or even between India and
China come under the head of
regional studies; a war among West¬
ern powers is a "world" war, while
one between China and Japan is
"localized"; a new language based on
all European tongues claims to be a
"world" language, while a threatened
alliance of Russia, China, and India
could be referred to as merely an
"Asian bloc".
\
I m more explicit cultivation of
/ interregional history can be
-*- vitally important to our his¬
torical understanding generally. For
a particular historical form of this
Westward distortion of our view of
mankind has tended to vitiate most of
our popular conceptions of general
history. The most significant error
Westerners have made lies not in
ascribing to themselves too much
glory or virtue in any particular com¬
parisons with other peoples. More
dangerous has been the West's prac¬
tice of reading the very structure of
history in a distorted fashion, for
this has been carried over uncon¬
sciously even by non-Westerners.
Judging all the world by its effect
on the West, Western history used to
set about tracing civilization from its
earliest times in Egypt and Babylon
only up to a point 'only so long as
these lands remained the nearest
direct antecedents of the modern
West. We ceased tracing civilization
in those countries almost as soon as -
Greece and Rome came to have a
literate history, concentrating on
each of them, in turn; ignoring each
time any further history in the lands
farther east (except when forced to
pay attention, by their role in a more
westerly story). So soon as north¬
western Europe came to have an in¬
dependent story, all lands east of the"
Adriatic dropped from sight, and the
very words we used suggested that
henceforth the West was the world.
" Something like this might have
been legitimate if done consciously;
but generally no recognition was
made that the focus of our vision had
been, shifted in the process. The
whole story commonly ran as if (as
Westerners have indeed actually
believed) civilization itself had been
moving steadily west. From this false
Impression of the story's continuity
arose a number of illusions, which
continue to have their effects after
the grosser aspects of the above
process have been abandoned.
V
W] IRST, it came to be supposed
I that after the early years the
more eastern nations had in
fact little significant history. This im¬
pression was early extended from
Egypt and Iraq to other lands; rein¬
forced by a number of accidents, in¬
cluding the habits of Indians and
Chinese of glorifying and exaggerat¬
ing the antiquity of their institu¬
tions. A variant of the same notion,
encouraged by the rapid rate of
change in the modern West, and by
illusions of distance, was that of the
static, changeless East.
Second, a different -and more
persistent illusion produced by the
pattern was that of a certain his¬
torical discontinuity recurrent de¬
generation, followed by a new start.
Not that such degeneration has never
in fact happened; but in the west¬
ward historical pattern the contrast
between one age and another was
confused and compounded with that
between places, as our attention
moved west.
This occurred especially when the
focus was shifted from the Mediter¬
ranean Roman Empire, in which
Rome was a western outpost from the
cultural and even economic point of
view, to Latin Christendom of the
Western Middle Ages, in which Rome
was a southeastern outpost on the
very edge of Greek 'and Muslim ter¬
ritory. A relative decline intervened
in the Imperial lands between the
age of the Antonines and that of
Justinian and the Hagia Sophia; the
shift of attention meanwhile from the
seaways of the Mediterranean to the
forests of Germany and Gaul mag¬
nified this decline into the fall of
the Roman Empire and the Dark Age
of civilization !
T
I he grosser misconceptions which
I have accompanied the West-
-m- ward pattern of history are now
less inclined to judge the fate of Greek
culture by its eclipse in Merovingian
Gaul. But the illusions which it
fostered were a strong influence
making possible the Nineteenth-
Century theories of history which
still tend to hold sway. The idea of
inevitable and < triumphant progress
probably owes something to the prac¬
tice of watching only those nations,
as civilization spread, which were
just taking on its' graces; a partly
borrowed progress always seems fast.
Those conceptions of history which
reduce it to stages or cycles owe far
more to these illusions. The famous
fall of the Roman Empire seems to be
the kernel from which such concep¬
tions have grown. Spengler decried a
Westcentred history, yet accepted the
limitations imposed by the Westward
pattern, allowing no history to
India or' China in the last two mil¬
lennia. Toynbee is anxious to recog¬
nize the continuing evolution of
the non-Western nations; yet
he seems to have used the "Fall
of Rome" as his starting point, and
hence involved himself in a system of
distinct societies, definitively rising
and falling, which naturally' bristles
with fundamental anomalies. Thus
the distortion has infected his work,
even though he guarded explicitly
against the illusion of the "static
East", as well as escaping the impos¬
ing list of those whose data suffers a
displacement in space which they
treat as if it were a change merely in
time.
Perhaps a more significant evidence
of the pervasive effect of the West¬
ward distortion in what we have
called world history, is its effect upon
so great a historical analysis as the
Marxist. Like others, the Marxists
have envisaged stages of evolution,
appearing in a predictable order.
Thus the slavery "stage" of Carolin-
gian Gaul.
Ü
l| ut the picture becomes awk-
I I wardly complicated if the
Syrian or Anatolian provinces
are focussed on, rather than
Gaul: for the Abbasid and Byzantine
societies represent alternative sequels
to the Roman. Accordingly, as the
historical vision of Victorian Europe
has widened, Marxism has been faced
with the need to patch up its theory,
and possibly to revise it thoroughly,
allowing for more varied elements in
and outcomes of the dialectical
process; it is my impression Marxists
have not -yet adequately met the
problem.
Some will have the impression that
in advocating an interregional his¬
tory of the Eastern Hemisphere, I am
advocating not world-oriented his-
tory, but just Oriental history- Not
quite: a history of '"Asia** without
Europe could conceivably resemaMe
a history of Western art or letters
without France. (Yet I "will
that just as a history of Earopa with¬
out France would better «Jessitc
the name of European history ttojm
one of France without Erarapa, so &
history of wittnaat tha West
could be more readily called a w
history, than the reversa),-
The point is that firtsix a tsxsrHd.-
historical point of rtep, what is ira-
portant is not European Mstary im
itself, however important that be for
us all; but its role to interregional
history This role has latterly been
momentous; but our very concentra¬
tion on internal Western history has
commonly obscured our view of the
West as one dynamic region among
others in the wider world.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
'3. -J.
An Historic Indian Name
Revived by A Science Prize
The Kalinga Prize for distinguished pop¬
ular writing in science is awarded
annually by Unesco on the basis of a
grant by Mr. B. Patnaik (right), Indian
industrialist from the State of Orissa.
Centuries ago Orissa was the heart of
the great Kalinga empire of King Asoka.
The four lions of Asoka (left) are today
the emblem of the Republic of India.
he name of Kalinga
achieved a place in his-
Tl tory more than twenty
I two and a half centuries
I ago. In 500 B.C. India
I was a continent of small
| warring states, of rigor¬
ous castes and of con-
I flicting religions. Buddha
had died at the age of 80 in the year 544
B.C. That great spiritual leader attack¬
ed the superstitions and ceremonials of
his day, denounced the metaphysical
outlook, miracles, revelations and deal¬
ings with the supernatural. His appeal,
strangely modern, was to logic, reason
and experience; his emphasis was on
ethics and his method was one of
psychological analysis. For more than
two hundred years, the Buddhist faith
was merely one of many, competing
quietly for the attention of the millions
of people living in India.
Then in 323 B.C., Alexander the
Great, conqueror of what the West
called the whole known world, died at
Babylon. Seleucus, the " general who
inherited Alexander's eastern empire,
stretching from Asia Minor through
Persia to Afghanistan, was forced to
give up for ever the effort to conquer
the East. He was defeated by the ruler
26
of northwest India," who was named
Chandragupta Maurya.
Inspired by Alexander's vast
conquests, Chandragupta turned his
attention eastward and within two
years had won the capital of north
India, Pataliputra, which today is call¬
ed Patna. Soon the Maurya empire
covered the whole of India from the
Arabian Sea to the Bay of Bengal. It
was the first large centralized govern¬
ment that India had ever had.
Forty-eight years later, in 273 B.C.,
the young grandson of Chandragupta,
named Asoka, inherited the empire.
Fired with his grandfather's ambition,
he set out to conquer what remained'
of India. His one great objective was
the state of Kalinga which extended
along the long diagonal strip of coast¬
line from near the present Calcutta to
the present Madras and inland for
500 miles. The Kalingans resisted
obstinately. In the clash a hundred
thousand persons were slain, many
times that number died and one
hundred and fifty thousand were carried
off as captives. India was united
except for the small southern tip that
is the present Travancore, Cochin and
Tamil Nad.
Asoka's empire was not only the
greatest of all Indian history; it was
also the turning point of that history.
The slaughter in Kalinga so revulsed
the conquering emperor, moved him to
such sorrow and regret, that he swore
never to tolerate any more killing or
captivity. He never moved against the
southern states though he could have
taken them easily. "True conquest"
he said "consists of the conquest of
men's hearts by the Law of Duty and
Piety. Should anyone do him wrong,
that too must be borne with by His
Sacred Majesty. For His Sacred Majesty
desires that all animate beings should
have security, self-control, peace of
mind and joyousness".
This powerful emperor became a
Buddhist and was himself chiefly res¬
ponsible for the spread of that gentle
religion through India and through the
whole of the Kalinga kingdom which
extended far into the Malay States,
Ceylon and Indonesia. By his influence,
Buddhism spread into Nepal, Tibet,
China and Mongolia. Yet Asoka was
tolerant of all religious sects and
generous to them. He was responsible
also for the growth of vegetarianism,
abstention from alcoholic drinks and
(Continued on page 28)
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 7. 1954
1932
Louis de Broçjlic
Professor Louis de Broglie, Nobel
Prize winner and Permanent Secre¬
tary of the Section of Mathematical
Sciences of the French Academy of
Science; first winner of the Kalinga
prize, 1952, nominated by the
Institut de France. Celebrated for
his research and findings in wave
mechanics, Professor de Broglie has
also written many popular books,
including : Matière et Lumière (Mat¬
ter and Light), Physique et Microphysique (Physics and Microphysics)
and Savants et Découvertes (Scientists and Discoveries).
1953
Julian II u x 1 e v
Dr. Julian Huxley, of London, first
Director-General of Unesco 1 946-
I 948; winner of the Kalinga award
for 1953, nominated by the Royal
Society of Great Britain and by
the Institut de France. Scientific
subjects have been interpreted by
Dr. Huxley through books, articles,
lectures, radio and films. His many
works include : The Individual in
the Animal Kingdom ; The Stream
of Life ; Essays' in Popular Science ; Scientific Research and Social
Needs ßird Watching and Bird Behaviour ; Evolution and Ethics.
1954
W a I cl c m a r
Kacmpiicrt
Mr. Waldemar Kaempffert, science editor of the
New York Times since I 927, has been awarded
the I 954,Kalinga Prize for his distinguished career
in science writing. Mr. Kaempffert, who was
nominated for the prize by the British Association
of Science Writers, has written, during nearly
30 years, a two-column Sunday feature entitled
"Science in Review". He has also written many
editorials and reviews of scientific books for the
Times and a large number of special articles in
American weekly and -monthly magazines. His
books include : The New Art of Flying, The ABC
of Radio, Invention and Society Today and Tomorrow,
Science Today and Tomorrow (2nd Series), Explo¬
rations in Science.
Mr. Kaempffert was born in New York City
and graduated from the College of the City of
New York. He later received a law degree from
the New York University and an honorary degree
of Doctor of Science from Clarkson Institute of
Technology. He began his career as a patent
attorney but- early became managing-editor of the
Scientific American and later editor of Popular
Science Monthly. He left the New York Times
in 1928 to become Director of the Museum of
Science and Industry in Chicago but returned to
the Times in 1931. He was one of the organizers
of the National Association of Science Writers and
has had a profound influence both on the quality
of science reporting in the U.S. and on the exten¬
sive employment of specialized science writers by
American newspapers.
"Current Biography" says of Mr. Kaempffert that
"no one has done more to bridge the gap between -
the. abstract hypotheses of the laboratory and the
mind of the common man". For more than half
a century he has devoted himself to the popular
interpretation of scientific ideas, always in sim¬
plified language, often in dramatized form. He
has always stressed his conviction that the advances
of scientific research inevitably bring broad social
consequences and that only an educated demo¬
cratic public can wisely adjust to them.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
it KALINGA (Continued)
the prohibition of all animal sacrifices.
India assumed almost its modern
aspect at the time of Asoka more than
twenty two centuries ago.
H.G. Wells, in his Outline of History,
says "Amidst the tens of thousands of
names of monarchs .that crowd the
columns of history... the name of Asoka
shines almost alone, a star... More
living men cherish his memory today
than have ever heard the names of
Constantine or Charlemagne".
Kalinga, which was the heart of
Asoka's empire, is the modern state of
Orissa in- independent India. The four
Lions of Asoka are the emblem of the
present Indian government. But
Orissa, through the vicissitudes of
history, is now a relatively small state,
indeed a backward one. Yet it has
perhaps the richest concentration of
valuable minerals in all the world, and
the ferment which came with in¬
dependence is now developing that
state to a prominent position.
The business leaders who are build¬
ing steel mills and industries there and
are changing the ancient city of
Cuttack into a modern capital, have
founded the Kalinga Foundation Trust,
based on the entire profits of some of
the new and major industries. It is
dedicated to scientific, industrial and
cultural research and to the develop¬
ment of the state of Orissa. The
Chairman of this Trust is the Honor¬
able Dr. H. Mahatab, Minister for
Commerce and Industry.
One of the directors is a young
executive, a distinguished aviator
during World War II, and friend of
Premier Nehru, Mr. B. Patnaik. In
1951 he took the unprecedented step
of offering to Unesco an annual grant
from the Kalinga Trust Fund to
establish a prize for effective and
distinguished science writing.
In doing so he wrote: "It is only with
the aid of science that we hope to
complete our task and it is to science
that we turn with anxiety and hope for
a solution of our stupendous problems.
I "am particularly convinced of the
necessity of making the great masses
aware of the methods and achieve¬
ments of scientific research, and to
make them understand, in a form
which they can assimilate, the impact
of science on our daily behaviour.
To build a nation, to achieve common
welfare, mutual respect and under-
SCIENCE MAKES SENSE even to young children when it is explained in
simple, everyday terms. It was to give recognition and encouragement to the
type of writing which brings scientific progress into clear focus for the average
person that the Kalinga Prize was established. Another effective medium for
popularizing science is the travelling exhibition. Here, two young Indians
take their first look into a microscope at a Unesco Exhibition, "Our Senses and
the Knowledge of the World", which has recently been touring their country.
standing is, as the Emperor Asoka
wrote, difficult without great zeal.
While doing everything possible to
develop India's strength and industrial
resources, Mr. Patnaik said "I wish to
attract world attention to this part of
the world, indeed to this part of the
country, and wish very much that the
great men of science would help in
focusing world attention on this place
with the object of revitalizing the great
.mass of people."
This outstanding ambition on the
part of one of the young pioneers of
new India is now being realized
through the visits to -India of the
distinguished interpreters and teachers
of science who have received the
Kalinga prize. This year, Dr. Julian
Huxley, grandson of the great Thomas
Huxley and the first Director-General
of Unesco, spent nearly three months
in India as winner of Unesco's Kalinga
prize and as an informal ambassador
from the scientific world.
In -1955, the third prize winner, a
great public educator through books,
magazines and the pervasive columns
of the New York Times, Waldemar
Kaempffert, dean of American science
writers, will also visit India as prize
winner. In future years the effects of
these visits will be visible and the
accounts that they write of their visits
to India will reveal to the world what
independence, high ethical principles
and the best of modern science have
done for the ancient Kalinga Empire
and the whole realm of Asoka.
Language barriers
THE great fund of knowledge
acquired by science in past
decades, steadily increased by
modern research, becomes a resource
for humanity and a means of im¬
proving the conditions of life only
when it reaches the public, is under¬
stood and put to use. Yet science
becomes ever more specialized and
more remote from common life, with
its own technical languages and
disciplines. Although the knowledge is
essentially international, the enormous
cost of modern laboratories and of
organized research campaigns tends to
confine the results to the wealthier
nations. A concerted international
effort is needed to make the new
knowledge available to all peoples
across the barriers of geography,
language and ignorance.
The dissemination of science is
.therefore one of Unesco's vital tasks,
through its own publications like The
Courier, Unesco Features, the Worid
tReview and Impact of Science on
Society. Every possible assistance is
also extended to the established
science writers > of the - world and
especially to their associations.
To give public recognition to the new
profession of science writing, Unesco in
1952 established the Kalinga prize.
The winner of the prize is invited to
spend a month or more in India,
.speaking on the progress of science in
his country and its consequences to the
world, and studying Indian science at
scientific institutions and universities
for use in his future writing.
Nominations for the. prize are
invited annually by Unesco from the
18 national Associations for the Ad¬
vancement of Science and from the
ten existing national Associations of
Science Writers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
From Afghanistan to
the Banks of the Nile...
UNESCO COURIER. N° 7 1954
A DRAMATIC CHANGE is taking place in the
Middle East today as countries adopt modern techni¬
ques to attack the roots of ignorance and poverty.
Photos show a technical training centre under con¬
struction in Iraq and a village audience attending an
evening class at a " cinema school " in Egypt.
*o*
FTER a 10,000 mile
journey through the
Middle East where
I toured Unesco's
technical assistance
missions, I frankly
hesitate to use the
expression "Middle
East" at all. Most
of us have the
curious notion that
it is a homogeneous
region where all the countries are more or less alike, with
the same Arabs and camels, deserts and palm trees, and an
almost equal degree of illiteracy, poverty, and disease.
Except for the fact that the Muslim religion has been an
important factor in the development of the region as a whole,
there is really little in common between Afghanistan and its
mountain solitudes and Egypt with its teeming Nile Valley;
between Iraq and its vast open plains and the Lebanon with
its narrow constricted terraces; between ancient Iran and
the newly created or re-created nation of Libya.
All of these countries are today receiving technical
assistance from the United Nations and are seeking to adopt
modern technological skills and train new technicians. This
doesn't mean though, as some people think too, that they
. have no technical skill.
Iran, for example, has so many skilled craftsmen and their
workmanship is of such superb quality that it made me think
of the great craftsmen's Guilds of Medieval times. Vocational
training one of the high points of modern technical
assistance is nothing new in this country where so many
young people are learning to engrave on copper and silver,
embroider leather, paint on ivory arid produce magnificent
in-laid work in mother-of-pearl. To the master mason
laying his sun-dried bricks to the rhythm of a song, illiteracy,
I thought, was undoubtedly a handicap in many ways but
GREEN
LIGHT
for
EDUCATION
by Georges Fradier
it certainly had not prevented him from constructing the
perfect vaults and arches I saw.
I marvelled at the "ganat" and the "foggara"the
extraordinary system of underground waterways which
generation after generation of specialist workers has
maintained and extended for the past 5,000 years in Persia
and Syria. The shafts follow underground water courses to
sources in the mountains sometimes as much as 30 miles
distant. For centuries, the workmen digging these shafts
have taken their bearings with a primitive form of compass
which probably ante-dates the marine compass by several
hundreds of years.
Irt all countries, farmers are always looking for better
ways to cultivate their land. But there is probably not very
much the West can teach the Syrian cotton producer, or the
vine grower of the Lebanon, or the Iraqi farmer I saw whose
palm groves were so carefully cultivated they looked like
gardens. As for the peasants of the Nile valley, they already
manage to produce three crops each year from every acre
of land despite their primitive implements.
I know that it has been pointed out time and again that
traditional skills have not prevented these countries from
falling behind others, often to an alarming degree. Nor
have they solved the major economic and social problems
which plague them, and in fact they have helped to intensify
them. Today, however, these traditional skills do form a
solid foundation for the important changes which are taking
place throughout the Middle East.
One thing struck me above everything else. The apathy and
resignation which was said to be widespread among the people
of the Middle East is completely gone today, particularly
amongst the younger generation. Everywhere the battle has
been joined against poverty, against inequality, and, more
precisely, against their deep basic causes. Each nation,
without exception, has its plan for modernisation and re-
equipment. Not all schemes for improvement are of equal
scope of course, nor -are the funds allotted to them of equal
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
* GREEN LIGHT FOR EDUCATION (Cont'd.)
'our future depends
on our schools'
NEW FACTORIES like this modern cotton mill in Damascus, Syria, are
springing up all over the Middle East, under national plans for modernization-.
importance, but everywhere new land is being conquered for
cultivation, new industries are springing up, and new roads
and hospitals, new laboratories and new schools are being
built. Sweeping land reforms are taking place alongside
significant administrative* changes and amazing improvements
in the social structure. Everywhere the "unchanging East" is
changing.
This desire for progress, for new techniques and new ideas,
has seized not only statesmen and other top-level leaders but
every section of the population in the Middle East. Today, from
Afghanistan to the banks of the Nile, the common slogan is
"Our future depends on our schools*', and the green light is
being given to educational improvement.
In the past ten years literally thousands of new schools have
been built in the countries of the Middle East. Primary schools,
destined first for those regions where hardly any existed before;
secondary and technical schools, industrial training centres;
universities; engineering institutes as well as new libraries and
laboratories have been created. Education, these countries have
discovered, can no longer remain the slow percolating process
of the past, starting at the top social stratum and only rarely
getting down to the broad mass at the base. Today the
ordinary people who need education most can no longer afford
to wait. They want education at all levels and they want it now.
. Some countries have given first priority to expanding
secondary education, others to .the development of higher
education. But nowhere are the funds used for one branch of
learning obtained at the expense of another. ' ;
Afghanistan has launched a vigorous campaign against
illiteracy, has revised its teacher training and recruiting methods,
and in the past few years has also opened a number of new
secondary schools. In 1950, the Afghan Institute of Technology
was founded in Kabul, the capital, and it has now graduated
civil and electrical engineers, mining and automobile
technicians. This year courses are open for civil aviation
technicians too.
Iran's problems are different. It can be proud of its secondary
schools, engineering colleges and its fine university, but it is
handicapped by a lack of skilled supervisors and foremen to
man its industries. The traditional methods of the copper
engraver's shop or the goldsmith's workroom cannot be applied
in operating a mine, a seaport, a railroad or an oil refinery. -
NEW LIFE is coming to parched Middle East lands through
large scale irrigation schemes which will eventually provide
millions of acres of new cultivable ground in former deserts.
NEW KNOWLEDGE is being gained here by Iraq's future
science teachers in the spacious laboratories of Baghdad's College
of Arts and Sciences. Three years ago Baghdad had no laboratories.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 7. 1954
NEW TECHNIQUES are being taught here to apprentice metal workers In
Iraq which plans to train enough specialists to staff all its growing factories.
> So today Iran is giving technical education the biggest green
light. All children (aged 11 to 13) in the last two classes of
primary school will henceforth spend 50 per cent of their time
on manual work at work benches in city schools, at school
farms in the villages. Each rural school will have its own fields
for cultivation and experimentation and special watering
systems for market gardens. Each city school will have its
workshop complete with tools and equipment.
Within the next five years some 3,000 of these new classes
will be giving practical instruction to over 90,000 children.
Iran's revolutionary programme, to cost about 300 million rials
(about $65,000,000), is one which many technically advanced
countries might well envy today.
¡ In the Lebanon educators are busily revising the school
textbooks using scientifically exact criteria, and are now
applying psychological tests to teacher trainees and primary
and secondary school children in order to select better qualified
teachers and provide vocational guidance for young people.
Since this work began, Lebanese industrial leaders have>
adopted similar methods in recruiting personnel, and govern-
NEW SKYLINE in the countryside at Horns, Syria, is made by
silhouette of a newly built, electrically powered grain mill.
ment services are contemplating doing likewise. This is current
practice in the most modernized countries but many people are
quite unaware of how up-to-date and modern the Lebanon
really is since it is in the "Middle East", and they have heard
only of its ancient past and its ruins of Byblos, 'Tyre and
Baalbek (see page 29).
This is equally true of Syria, which is known mostly for its
magnificent architecture of antiquity and its picturesque
villages. But Syria is also a country of new factories, new
dams and new schools. Since 1946, some ' 337 primary and
48 secondary schools have been built, new colleges have been
founded (Faculties of Letters, Science, Engineering, Education
in Damascus and -Aleppo) and building' is still going on.
Within the past seven years this tiny nation of three million
inhabitants has ended the teacher shortage in primary,
secondary and vocational schools. The next goal is to train
enough qualified teachers in higher technology and advanced
science.
Baghdad, the capital of Iraq, is a city whose name once
ranked high in the history of science. "It will once again
become a great centre of science" say the people of Iraq. A
few years ago the idea would have seemed simply absurd.
Baghdad had no laboratories, no science faculty, not even a
scientific library. Iraq's chemists, physicists and biologists are
usually graduates of British, American or German universities.
Today, students who want to study science at college are no
longer obliged to go abroad. Baghdad now has an excellent
school of engineering, a medical school, and a newly created
College of Arts and Sciences which will ultimately form part
of the future University of Iraq. The departments of chemistry,
physics and mathematics are only three years old but the
standards and quality of instruction are already on a par with
other 'long-established college faculties in other countries.
"We've started from scratch", one professor told me, "but
now we're in full swing". As I visited the spacious laboratories,
and saw how fully equipped they were, with students in white
blouses busy working over Bunsen burners, test tubes, scales,
microscopes and other apparatus installed on long tile-covered
benches, I could not believe that only three years before none
of this had existed.
Egypt has not had the same predicament of creating a higher
educational system overnight. Its very modern universities in
Cairo and Alexandria attract students from many countries, and
the celebrated El Azhar University, once restricted to theological
teaching, is now a new centre of modern learning.
Today Egypt is expanding technical education to meet the
expected acceleration of industrial development. Training is
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
GREEN LIGHT
FOR EDUCATION
(Continued)
being geared to research in the sciences, and particularly
research in industrial chemistry. But for the man in the
street in Egypt, "scientific research" means the Desert Insti¬
tute at Heliopolis, north of Cairo. When the Institute was
founded in 1951 it was chiefly a museum of natural history
of the desert. Now it is becoming the national centre for
specialized research on soil, climate, desert flora and fauna,
desert chemistry and geology.
"More than any other people", one scientist told me, "we
Egyptians are influenced by the desert. Shut in on two sides,
our great Nile flows in reality like a trickle between two'
immense deserts. The lands watered by the Nile are among
the most fertile in the world, but only a thin green strip of
land can be irrigated despite the water stored up by our huge
Aswan barrage." The Nile Delta supports a population of
17 million fellahin so crowded together that the density is
747 per square kilometer. Every acre of barren ground that
science can turn into arable land means a new chance for
life for a peasant family.
All the countries of the Middle East, thus, are on the move.
Their educational problems in practically every case are now
directly linked with . technical and economic development
plans. Even in Libya, where almost no primary schools at
all existed in the past, every school built has an immediate
repercussion on local crafts and agriculture (the modern
schools now going up stress manual work). Hence, one
cannot speak of technical assistance in the Middle East
without also speaking of the new education in the Middle
East, for the assistance would mean little without the
remarkable progress being made in education.
It is here that the technical experts Unesco has sent to
the Middle East are working in technical school workshops,
in university laboratories, in libraries and nursery schools,
and sometimes in the offices- of a Cabinet Minister where
new education programmes are being drawn up.
The work of most of these men may seem undramatic and
uninspiring but in reality it is filled with moving excitement
and drama. The Unesco experts working in this part of
the world are in fact a fortunate and enviable group. For
they are conscious of helping old nations suddenly grown
young in reaching for a new future. One thing they are
certain of: they are not wasting their time. As one of them
told me, quoting a phrase of Charles Malik, the Lebanese
delegate to the United Nations: "The sun is risen in the
Orient on a world hard at work; only those who are asleep
do not see it."
OUTDOOR ACTIVITIES form an important
part of the primary school programme. The
school is also a training ground for the young Iraqi "
teachers who have been recruited.
A BREAK FROM CLASS for the boys and girls.
At Dujaila, Iraqi children have discovered a new
kind of learning in which games and " dressing
up " also have their place in the programme.
HOUSEWIVES
have come to learn
about improved
health and home
conditions in the
women's classes.
Sewing, cooking
and baby care are
among the sub¬
jects taught them.
A SCHOOL
FARM and a gar¬
den now provide
practical lessons in
benefits of new
farming methods.
A club for young
farmers and co¬
operatives are also
in action here.
A NEW SPIRIT
IN DUJAILA
Ten years ago the flat alluvial plain at Dujaila in the bend
of the Tigris river, south east of Baghdad (Iraq) was a parched
wilderness. Today, irrigation canals fed from the Tigris
have made it a huge chessboard pattern of fields and farms
where 2,000 colonists cultivate wheat and barley and raise
sheep and cattle. Dujaila is the largest land settlement in
the Near East and also the site of the first fundamental
education pilot project in this region. Helped by farmers,
a Unesco team has been developing this centre since I 952 and
today it has become the first village and the " nerve centre "
of this land of farms. Men, women and children come to
its schools and workshops to free themselves from illiteracy,
to learn the skills of metalwork, carpentry, weaving, spinning,
building and simple farm mechanics and to find out how
they can protect themselves from disease. Since prejudices
against education for women have been overcome, a new
girls' school has been opened and now has over 50 pupils.
Young Iraqi are trained at Dujaila as teachers in fundamental
education: Above all, this village education centre has
made the people of Dujaila a community-minded group.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER N» 7. 1954
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
EDITOR'S NOTE
In its first issue of 1954 The Courier
published a series of articles on the
world's language problems. These brought
many letters from readers, particularly on
the question of international languages, of
which a few were published in our No. 3
issue. Since then several hundreds of
Esperantists have written us from places
as far apart as Japan and Sweden, taking
exception to some of the statements made
in these letters. Lack of space makes it
impossible to print even a small propor¬
tion of this correspondence, but we
believe that the points raised are adequa¬
tely covered in the long letter from
Professor Ivo Lapenna of the Universal
Esperanto Association, Rickmansworth,
England, which we publish below almost
in its entirety.
Sir,
In Courier n° 3, 1954, you were good
enough to publish my letter concerning
the international petition in support of
Esperanto and the decision taken by the
Seventh Session of the General' Conference
of Unesco with regard to it. In the same
number you also published several other
letters on the language question.
The Executive Committee of the Uni¬
versal Esperanto" Association has reques¬
ted me to draw your attention to a num-
' ber of important errors :
In these letters... may be found a whole
collection of fallacious and fantastic asser¬
tions. The following are but a few of
them :
(a) Mr. Jacob among other things states
that Volapuk "was once spoken by two
million people". This project was, in
fact, never transformed into a living lan¬
guage. During the first Volapuk congress
in 1884 those attending had to speak
German! On account of its internal struc¬
tural deficiencies, great difficulty and, in
addition, the impossibility of normal evo¬
lution (dictatorship by one person instead
of evolution brought about collectively by
the users), this project like many others
before and since soon ceased to attract
any attention.
(b) There is a great tendency to speak
about "international languages" (in the
plural). Messrs. Jacob, Thersant (French
edition) and Brismark do so. It is true
that there have been and presumably,
will be in future many projects for a
common tongue. After the genius of Dr
Zameñhof had found the solution, any
educated person who cared to interest
himself in the problem could, in the
course of a few days, produce some sort
of reasonable project.
Much longer, much more arduous, is the
transition from a project to a living,
completely functioning language. Esper¬
anto alone has accomplished this transit
ion. It alone with its abundant trans¬
lated and original literature, numerous
magazines, scientific and specialist reviews,
radio broadcasts, congresses and confer¬
ences, and thousands and thousands of
people who use it daily in international
contacts has become an indisputable
social reality.
Not to understand the part played by
quantity (not only regarding the number
of persons, but also regarding the diver¬
sity of publications, and many-sided, prac¬
tical applications of the language, as also,
resulting from this, the internal evolution
of the language itself) in the determina¬
tion of quality, in this case the distinction
between an individualistic project and a
socially living language, is to understand
nothing, absolutely nothing, of the matter.
(c) Mr. Thersant (in the French edition)
misrepresents the facts when he says that
in 1922 "cet idiome... fut rejeté" by. the
Commission on Intellectual Cooperation
of the League of Nations "après les sé¬
vères conclusions du rapporteur, qui
demandait surtout de ne point apprendre
l'Espéranto aux enfants, afin de ne point
déformer leur esprit".
I have re-read the minutes of the meet¬
ing in question (League of Nations, Com¬
mittee on Intellectual Co-operation, Mi¬
nutes of the Second Session, 1923). Cer¬
tainly, at this session a multitude of
fantastic assertions were made about
Esperanto (e.g. regarding the number of
words in the language). This is partly
understandable (but nevertheless unpardon¬
able) when one considers that none of
the members of the Committee knew Espe¬
ranto.
It is as though people with no idea at
all of, say, Chinese, or any other lan¬
guage, were to pass judgment on the
qualities of that language ! In such cir¬
cumstances it seems to me that all inac¬
curate "evidence" does more harm to the
scientific reputation of the persons giving
it than to the subject under consideration!
Setting aside my personal opinion, how¬
ever, I must say that, in spite of careful
perusal, I did not find in the minutes the
words quoted by Mr. Thersant, who, inci¬
dentally, does not know the year of this
famous meeting. The committee decided
that it could not recommend the teaching
of Esperanto in schools, but at the same
time it declared that "it does not dispute
the practical advantages which would
result from the universal adoption of an
artificial language".
Dr. Nitobe (Japan) expressed the opi¬
nion that in twenty years time, when the
number of people speaking Esperanto
would have increased, "they might hold
up any adverse and unfavourable reso¬
lution of this Committee as a sign of its
lack of wisdom". The League of Na¬
tions, probably for this very reason, never
approved the decision of the Committee
on Intellectual Co-operation.
The report accepted unanimously by the
Third Assembly of the League of Nations
on September 21st, 1922, accordingly
remained fully valid. This ended with
the following words :
"Language is* a great force, and the
League of Nations has every reason to
watch with particular interest the progress
of the Esperanto movement which, should
it become more widespread, may one day
lead to great results from the point of
view of the moral unity of the world."
(d) There is also a tendency to speak of
the degree to which this or that project
is " scientific ". This is not the place to
discuss this aspect of the matter. One
thing, however, is certain : an essential
prerequisite of the scientific consideration
of any question is to know and to
recognise the facts. Then, and only
then, can one begin to analyze them. Il
is precisely this nothing more which
the Universal Esperanto Association,
which I have the honour to represent, and
I personally expect of Unesco. With
regard to the assertions that Esperanto
does not enjoy the support of linguists,
may I draw your attention to the fact that
among the signatories to the Petition to
Unesco were more than 1,500 linguists
and over 40,000 teachers, many of whom
were language teachers.
In connection with all that has been
sqid there arises a question of principle,
namely, whether it is prudent for a review
such as the Courier to publish letters
which contain grave, factual errors. De¬
mocracy demands that the opinion of each
individual should be fully respected.
That is beyond question. Nevertheless,
the truth of assertions of fact should be
verified. I very much doubt whether the
Courier would publish a letter which
stated, for example, that Beethoven com¬
posed 99 symphonies! To say that Vola¬
puk was spoken by two million people is
really no less fantastic!
I ask your pardon for the length of this
letter. If the Petition in favour of Espe¬
ranto were not at present before Unesco,
if, therefore, the International Language
question were not in a sense sub judice,
I should have been much briefer. Under
the circumstances it seemed essential to
draw attention to at least the basic errors
and inaccuracies which, if left uncorrec¬
ted, could endanger the objectivity of the
decision to be taken on this matter at
Montevideo.
Yours faithfully,
Prof. Ivo LAPENNA,
Universal Esperanto Association,
Rickmansworth,
England.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom...
PORTABLE GUIDES :
Visitors to the American
Museum of Natural History,
New York, now tour the
exhibits carrying a "guide"
slung from their shoulders.
These are portable short-
range radio receivers, known
as guide-a-phones, which
pick up recorded talks on the
exhibits sent out by trans¬
mitters in each hall.
w<ORLD FACTS : Accord¬
ing to statistics available in
September 1953 the total world
population has now reached
2,460,000,000. Between 45% and
50% of people over ten years of
age are still illiterate. To give
all children between the ages of
5 and 14 a primary education,
authorities would have to provide
schools and teachers for bet¬
ween 500 and 550 million chil¬
dren. These three items of
information are published in
the second edition of "Basic
Facts and Figures" in which
Unesco has collected world¬
wide information on illiteracy,
education, libraries, museums,
books, newspapers, newsprint,
film, radio and television.
ART AND EDUCATION:
Education through art is to
be promoted on a world-wide
basis by a newly formed or¬
ganization The Interna¬
tional Society for Education
Through Art which recent¬
ly held its first General
Assembly in Unesco House,
Paris. The society will serve
as a channel of information
for art teachers and special¬
ists, an agency for exchan->
ges and a centre of co-ordi¬
nated research and action.
Membership is open to indi¬
viduals as well as groups.
wORLD CHILDREN'S
DAY, 1954 : The International
Union for Child Welfare in
Geneva and its affiliates in
forty countries will celebrate
World Children's Day on October
4. They have chosen Article n
of the Declaration of the Rights
of the Child "The child must
be cared for with due respect
for the family as an entity"
as the theme for this year's
celebration.
TV v CLASSROOM
TEACHING: How effective
are teaching courses by tele¬
vision, as compared with
classroom teaching ? Stu¬
dents at the University of
Houston, Texas, U.S.A. re¬
cently helped educators to
compare the two methods.
One student group attended
normal classes. The other
saw the same lecturers and
demonstration by television.
Later examinations revealed
no significant difference in
what the two groups learned.
Further experiments are now
being carried out.
B
work, much of it voluntary, has
given to the Peruvian National
Union for the Blind the second
largest Braille library in the
Western Hemisphere. Since it
was established 13 years ago,
the library has accumulated a
stock of 3,400 books all of
them made by hand. Works
include the greatest books of
world literature.
CULTURAL EXCHANGE:
A new cultural agreement
between Luxemburg and
France provides for recipro¬
cal fellowships, the equating
of certain academic degrees
and studies, exchanges of
CONTINENTAL MODEL :
A Unesco library pilot project
designed as a model for pub¬
lic library development
throughout Latin America is
being set up in the Palacio
de Bellas Artes, in Medellin,
Colombia. The library is to
be run on similar lines to the
Delhi Public Library organi¬
zed by the Government of
India and Unesco. It will co-
. operate with United Nations
fundamental education pro¬
grammes in Colombia.
D OLLS OF MANY
LANDS: Dolls from many coun¬
tries, each dressed in the
THE CHILDREN VOTED
Fifteen hundred primary school children recently sat as judges in
a film competition organized by the Internationaf Children's Centre
in Paris with the co-operation of educators, psychologists and film
producers. The aim was to determine the kinds of films children
prefer, to establish criteria for good-quality children's films and to
promote their production. The children cast their vote for the film
they liked best and also explained the reasons for their choice. The
greatest value of the competition lay in the analysis of the children's
spontaneous reactions to each film, obtained from special recording
devices. These fixed with precision the audience reactions throughout
each phase of the film. The information was completed by observers
noting the actions and comments of the children and from photo¬
graphs taken in the dark by ultra-violet rays.
teachers, students and artists
and other cultural exchanges
of books, radio programmes
and films.
Ni
OOKS FOR THE
BLIND; Many thousands of
hours of patient and exacting
EW RURAL TEACHERS:
A new type of fundamental
education teacher who will work
in the rural areas of Cuba is to
be trained at the fundamental
education pilot centre which the
Cuban Ministry of Education
has decided to establish. Five
Cuban graduate teachers from
Unesco's Regional Fundamental
Education Centre at Patzcuaro,
Mexico, will help to train these
new rural teachers.
national costume, will form an
international exhibition in New
Delhi early next year. The ex¬
hibition is regarded as a simple
and effective way of making the
children of India aware of the
culture and traditions of other
countries. The dolls will visit
many parts of India before
being housed in New Delhi as a
permanent exhibit.
* 'VACATIONS ABROAD' :
Unesco has recently issued
under the new title of "Va¬
cations Abroad" a popular
publication that has appear¬
ed ' in previous years as a
summer-time supplement to
the well - known "Study
Abroad". "Vacations Abroad"
provides information about
more than seven hundred
vacation courses, summer
schools, tours and work
camps organized in fifty-one
countries, all of which might
meet the needs of persons
who want to combine educa¬
tional experience with fo¬
reign travel during their
summer holidays. The book
is published in a trilingual
edition m English, French
and Spanish.
TiWO "SILVER ANNIVER-
SARHES": It is just 25 years
since the International Bureau
of Education changed its status
from a private institution to
that of an intergovernmental
organization. On July 25, 1929,
government representatives sign¬
ed an agreement recognizing
the need "to collect educational
data through investigation and
research, and to facilitate the
exchange of such information
so as to encourage each country
to profit by the experience of
others.". The TBE is also cele¬
brating the 25th anniversary of
the appointment of Professor
Jean Piaget, the Swiss educator
and psychologist as its Director.
BULGARIA AND UNES¬
CO: Bulgaria has applied for
membership of Unesco. As
this country is not a member
of the United Nations, its
request has first to be
approved by the Economic
and Social Council of the
United Nations. Bulgaria
may then join Unesco upon
recommendation by Unesco's
Executive Board and appro¬
val by a two third's majority
vote of the General Confe¬
rence of the Organization.
ILINESCO - ZAANDAM -
LIBYA: Unesco in Paris, the
hewly independent nation of
Libya and Zaandam, a small
town near Amsterdam will be
linked for two weeks in Sep¬
tember through a special pro¬
gramme being held in this
Dutch town. Two Unesco
exhibitions will be shown
"Education and Peace", in the
schools, and "Men Against the
Desert", in the town's shop win-
dews. The Unesco fllm, "World
Without End", will be screened
at an open-air meeting. A
Zaandam citizen, Mr Adrian
Pelt was U.N. Commissioner in
Libya until the country became
Independent in 1952. Unesco
Gift Coupons which can be
used to aid educational and
cultural institutions will be on
sale, and those bought by the
people of Zaandam will be sent
to the Primary Teacher Train¬
ing Centre in , Tripolitania
Libya.
PEN FRTENDS WANTED :
Young people in Istanbul,
Turkey, wish to exchange
letters, postcards, stamps and
publications with boys and
girls overseas who write in
French, German or English.
Those interested should wri¬
te to : Tiirkive Genclik Ha-
berlesme Kulübü, Gümüssuyu
Ogrenci Yurdu, Istanbul. .
v
z
<
ID
Z
o
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
e UNESCO COURIER
"... a window open on the world"
COMING NEXT MONTH... IN A 52-PAGE SPECIAL ISSUE:
A UNESCO REPORT ON
THE FRONTIERS OF CIVILIZATION
The Problem oí the World's Primitive Peoples
TO SUBSCRIBE
In the United Kingdom send your
remittance to U.M. Stationery Offi¬
ce P.O. Box 569, London S.E. 1.
In other countries write to National
Distributors listed below.
If your country is not listed write
directly to Unesco Sales Division
19, avenue Kléber, Paris, France.
THE LEGENDARY FIGURE
OF GENERAL RONDÓN
Pacifier oí Rrazil's Indians
VISIT TO THE
PEOPLE OF NEW GUINEA
THE HILL TRIBES OF INDIA'S
WILD BORDER AREAS.
WHAT IS A "PRIMITIVE"?
And many other interesting articles and regular features
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Fnck Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma ; Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen. K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O.B. 120 Addis-Ababa.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa 2, Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, 1 9, Avenue
Kleber, Paris- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Inter¬
nationale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd. Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima-
lay House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.i
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djkarta.
Iraq : McKenzie'* Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstei's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road. P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzan Co, Inc., 6Ton-Nichomee,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J.I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Liberia : Jacob Momolu Kamara, Gurly
and Front Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135.
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kmgsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : Unesco Publications Centre
7 De Lacy Street, Dunedin, N. E. 2.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S, Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi» Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenscraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A B.C.E. Fnztes Kungl. Hovbok-
handel Fredgaatan 2, Stockholm I 6.
Thailand : Suksapan Pamt, Arkarn 9
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London SEI.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475,
5th Ave., New York 17, N.Y.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO Courier
*"
February a French Navy bathyscaph
off Dakar descended over 12,000 feet
under the sea, the greatest depth yet
reached by man. Though this broke
a world record, the main purpose
was to test the efficiency of an
apparatus designed as a laboratory
for deep-sea research in the modern
science of oceanography. (For arti¬
cle on the Untold Treasures of the
Sea, See page 20.) Official French Ñavy 'pttami
]]>
</page>
</document>
