<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="069962eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
Special
Number
IHE AMERICAN NEGRO
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
MONT.
CAL.
WYO.
NEV.
UTAH
COLO.
ARIZ.
N. M.
WIS.
.MICH.
PA.
ILL. IND.
OHIO N. J.
DEL.
D.C.
TENN.
N. C.
OKLA.
S. C.
\MISS
ALA.\ GA.
TEXAS
THE PATTERN
OF SCHOOL
SEGREGATION
ON MAY 17, 1954
Segregation required in
17 states and District of
Columbia : Alabama, Arkan¬
sas, Delaware, Florida, Geor¬
gia, Kentucky, Louisiana, Mary¬
land, Mississippi, Missouri,
North Carolina, Oklahoma,
South Carolina, Tennessee,
Texas, Virginia, West Virginia.
Local option on segrega¬
tion in 4 states : Arizona,
Kansas, New Mexico, Wyo¬
ming.
No specific legislation in
I I states : California, Maine,
Montana, Nebraska, Nevada,
New Hampshire, North Dako¬
ta, Oregon, South Dakota,
Vermont, Utah.
Segregation prohibited in
16 states : Colorado, Con¬
necticut, Idaho, Illinois, In¬
diana, Iowa, Massachusetts,
Michigan, Minnesota, New
Jersey, New York, Ohio,
Pennsylvania, Rhode Island,
Washington, Wisconsin.
SHIFTS IN THE NEGRO POPULATION OF THE O.S. 1940-1950
I -THE SHIFT OUT
OF THE SOUTH
Distribution of
Negro Population
2 -TH E SHIFT
TO URBAN AREAS
Distribution of
Negro Population
REST OF U.S.
28%
SOUTH
72% II
1940 1950
37.5 %
62.5 %
URBAN AREAS
48.6 %
RURAL AREAS
51.4
62.5 %
37.5
1940 1950
Unesco Courier Maps.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
NUMBER 6-1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
An amazing social phenomenon,
4 I. A LOOK AT U.S. RACE RELATIONS
The scoreboard for the Negro.
By Morroe Berger.
9 II. WHEN SKILL, NOT COLOUR, COUNTS
Job discrimination and its reduction.
14 III. THE COURT STEPS IN
Interpreting the Constitution.
17 THE DECISION WAS UNANIMOUS
"Separate but equal signifies unequal."
By Murray Stedman Jnr.
18 THE HONORABLE, THE SUPREME COURT
Some facts about the highest U.S. judicial body.
20 THE WORDS OF A. MOMENTOUS DECISION
Text of the May 17, 1954 Supreme Court ruling.
22 THE GREAT TEST OF «CIVIL RIGHTS'
A commentary on the legislative attack.
By Thurgood Marshall.
24 SOCIAL SCIENTISTS TESTIFY ON SEGREGATION
The harmful effects of a racial doctrine.
By Otto Klineberg.
26 GOING TO SCHOOL WITH THE NEGRO
A century of struggle for educational opportunity.
30 THE ROAD TOWARDS EQUALITY
A calendar of significant dates.
31 VOTING RIGHTS & NON-SEGREGATED HOUSING
So'me facts and figures.
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science and culture.
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 1 9, Avenue Kleber, Paris 1 6, France.
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: José De Benito
Individual articles not copyrighted maybe reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-! $ 1.50 or 300 French 1rs.
MC. 54. 1 82. A-
Special Issue
THE U.S. NEGRO
This Negro doctor who is the chief surgeon
at the Ohio State Penitentiary, symbolizes the
enormous progress of the Negro in the past
50 years in achieving equality of opportunity
in the United States. (Photo copyright, pub¬
lished by courtesy of "Ebony", Chicago).
FOR the average person the racial question means little more
than conflict, clashes and similar dramatic events. Facts
about the progress made by minority groups and the improvement
of their status usually pass unnoticed unless something occurs
as spectacular as the recent decision of the United States Supreme
Court outlawing segregation in American public schools.
It is too early as yet to judge the full practical import of this
decision but we do know that it was made possible by the efforts
of both whites and Negroes working together in many fields.
There is no country in the world where racial discrimination is
accepted as a dogma by the whole of the population. Everywhere
associations have been formed for the advancement of minority
groups. In certain countries, as in the United States, the Federal
government itself has stepped into the struggle and has sought
to put into effect an equalitarian policy.
The battle against racial discrimination and the prejudices which
cause it have been a special concern of Unesco since its creation in
1946. Unesco has sought to focus attention on the positive achieve¬
ments in race relations rather than on the negative aspect of the
conflicts themselves. Thus it has been making a critical survey
"of the methods and techniques employed for facilitating the
social integration of groups which do not participate fully in the
life of the national community by reason of their ethnical or
cultural characteristics or their recent arrival in the country."
During the past few years Unesco has undertaken special studies
of the racial situation in six countries Brazil, France, Western
Germany, Yugoslavia, Mexico and the United States each of
which has made a contribution to the solution of the .problem, and
each of which Unesco feels is worth knowing and publicizing.
There are many ways of combatting race discrimination. Some
people believe that the most effective means is through progressive
education of the public in order to eliminate the basic roots of
prejudice; others pin their hope on legislation; still others look
to the steady progress of the minority groups themselves.
There is, of course, no one and only road for eliminating discri¬
mination. But historical circumstances and even individual tem¬
perament are often 'factors which determine what particular method
a group prefers. All methods have been tried out in different parts
of the world and each has a lesson to teach us.
Let us take the case of legislation. Is it true, as has often been
said, that "'you can't legislate against prejudice", or on the
contrary, can law help to uproot prejudice itself by placing the
stigma of illegality on discrimination ? The question is important
and an answer can come from an examination of the facts.
Doubts have similarly been raised about the effectiveness of
educational campaigns. The caution and hesitation of scientists
regarding races has often been misinterpreted as an admission of
ignorance. Individuals have not found it difficult therefore to
point to one theory of race as opposed to another in refusing to
discard their prejudices or traditional beliefs.
Facts and the figures speak for themselves and are therefore
much more eloquent. The swift transformation of many civiliza¬
tions which the world is witnessing, obliges us constantly to
revise our opinions about other peoples. How can anyone still
speak of "inferior or superior peoples" when advances representing
hundreds and even thousands of years of progress are being
achieved by so many ethnic groups in the space of a few years?
Yet despite the wealth of information on the subject, the fact
of this rapid progress and its deep significance are but little known.
In earlier issues, The Unesco Courier . has drawn attention to the
ease with which certain so-called "backward" peoples have assi¬
milated the elements of our industrial civilization. It has also
dealt with the racial situation in various parts of the world such
as Brazil, Hawaii and Australia which seem to be on the road to
satisfactory solutions of the problem. This issue is devoted in
its entirety to the American Negro whose progress in less than a
century is one of the most amazing social phenomena of our time.
Alfred METRAUX.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A look a
THE
SCOREBOARD
FOR THE NEGRO
by
Morroe Berger
Princeton University
Dr. Berger, formerly political
analyst, Foreign Affairs Depart¬
ment of the American Jewish
Committee and instructor in
sociology at New York Univer¬
sity is assistant professor of
sociology at Princeton Univer¬
sity. He is the author of an
authoritative " study on local
controls over group discrimi¬
nation entitled "Equality by
Statute" (Columbia University
Press, New York, 1952) and
the author of the Unesco
study published early this year
entitled "Racial Equality and
the Law" from which the articles
on pages 4-15 are taken.
0
(Photo USIS )
SPORTS OF ALL KINDS have helped to reduce racial discrimination in the U.S. Major leagues
In professional baseball began in 1947 to hire Negro players, and by now they are so well accepted
as to occasion little comment. In college basket-ball (above) Negroes are "one of the team".
IT is something of a paradox that the
world has long pointed to the
United States as a classic, example
of both political democracy and social
inequality. Indeed, as political freedom
has diminished in large areas of the
globe and colour discrimination arouses
even more bitter resentment with the
decline of colonialism, the United
States has become the object of much
critical examination:
While observers most concerned 'with
political freedom and economic and
technological advances have been
favourable in their comments on United
States institutions, observers more
concerned with group relations and the
problems of social equality have often
been highly critical. What both groups
have tended to overlook is that in
recent years the United States has
applied the identical machinery that
operates its political democracy to
effect considerable improvement in its
traditional pattern of social, discri¬
mination.
Indeed, it already seems safe to say
that in the "contest" between the
implications of political democracy in
the United States and the implications
of its system of unequal social status
based in part on custom and in part
on law, the former are prevailing over
the latter. The issue is certainly not
fully settled. Yet, unless there is a
sudden and sharp reversal, all present
trends show the "contest" resulting in
a clear-cut, if not uniform, victory for
the principles of democracy over those
of inequality. Such a victory will
serve also to demonstrate that le¬
gislative and legal techniques can
effectively reduce and even eradicate
deeply rooted prejudices and habits.
While discrimination in any form is
Itself undemocratic (although there
are theorists and groups who have held
that the milder forms of it are wholly
compatible with democracy where
everyone has the right to express his
tastes) its most injurious aspect is
economic. Before equality of status
and other minority rights can be
assured, it is above all essential to
remove the barriers to earning a living
and other impediments which block
anyone from attaining the more
desirable professions and vocations.
In developing relations with other
people, all of us are constantly making
choices on the basis of more or less
conscious deliberation. We select this
person over that one as a friend; we
adopt attitudes towards others ranging
from love to hostility; we choose to be
intimate with this acquaintance and
prefer to remain more formal with that
one. In one sense this process might
be called discrimination, since by it we
select one among several courses of
action and exclude others. But so long
as this selection is based upon
consideration of the individual qualities
of other persons, we do not call it
"discrimination" in the sense in which
this word is used in the analysis of
group relations.
Consider now another sort of se¬
lection. Suppose a man to select his
friends, or the neighbourhood in which
he will live, or the school his children
will attend, in such a way as to bring
him and his family into as little
contact as possible with individuals of
a certain religion, nationality, social
class, or skin colour.
Suppose further that he arrives at
these decisions not -by evaluating the
merits or demerits of members of these
groups but simply on the basis of his
dislike or fear of those groups as such;
or, as is frequently the case, on the
basis of his belief that all the members
of a particular group are inferior to
him or unworthy of his association.
Such a person can be called prejudiced.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
This person groups and evaluates
people on the basis of traits which
have no validity, according to the
scientific data we now have, as an
index to individual intelligence, taste,
capacity to learn, or to such qualities
as honesty, trust-worthiness, ambition,
and so on. Nevertheless, the actions of
a person who makes such prejudiced
judgments is not discrimination in the
sense in which the word is used here,
although it usually leads to it.
Discrimination, in this sense, is not
simply an attitude or an opinion,
although it may be (and usually is)
based upon either or both. Discri¬
mination, rather, is a specific act, a
deliberate attempt to exclude some
individuals from something desirable
because they are presumed (correctly
or incorrectly) to belong to a certain
group. The groups that are most often
the objects of discrimination are
identified by means of religion, national
origin, colour, language, and social
class.
Discrimination on such grounds
means the denial of a right or privilege
to a person on the ground of his
presumptive membership in some
group, regardless of his individual
qualities. We may accept the following
brief definition given by the United
Nations Sub-Commission on Prevention
of Discrimination and Protection of
Minorities: "... discrimination includes
any conduct based on a distinction
made on grounds of natural or social
categories, which have no relation
either to individual capacities or merits,
or to the concrete behaviour of the
individual person."
Discrimination, then, is an overt act
usually, although not necessarily,
derived from an attitude of prejudice.
We say "not necessarily" because we
know that many persons who discri¬
minate do so not out of their own
prejudice but out of a tendency to
conform to a discriminatory pattern
they find in their communities or at
their place of work. Since it is an act
rather than a feeling, discrimination is
more easily combatted than prejudice,
is more amenable to control by law,
and is more easily measured by the
student of social relations. Likewise,
its growth or decline is more easily
studied and measured than is the
decrease or increase of prejudice.
Among the most recent efforts to
determine quantitatively the amount of
discrimination in various areas of
American society is a study by Ralph
H. Turner of employment discri¬
mination against non-white (mostly
Negro) Americans. Mr. Turner, by
measuring the differences in occu¬
pational distribution of whites and
non-whites having the same degree of
formal education, has reached some
noteworthy conclusions, among them,
the following:
1..Nearly two-fifths of the difference
in occupational distribution between
whites and non-whites is due to the
fact that whites have more formal
education. But the remaining , three-
fifths cannot he traced to educational
superiority and may therefore be
attributed to discrimination.
2. Unemployment strikes non-whites
more heavily than it does whites. Only
about one-fourth of this difference can
be attributed to the lower educational
level of the non-whites. The re¬
mainder may be said to be due to
discrimination.
3. Discrimination against non-Whites
does not occur primarily in the form of
a complete refusal to hire them but in
the refusal to hire them in those
capacities for which their formal
education qualifies them.
The assumption that education is
the chief determinant of employment,
qualification also points to another'
significant form of discrimination,
(Photo? USIS)
THE GREAT
EMANCIPATOR
The United [States fought a bloody war over the question of Negro slavery. In
1 863 while the war was still in progress, President Abraham Lincoln issued his famous
Emancipation Proclamation which declared all slaves within the states which had seceded
from the Union to be free. As soon as the Northern armies captured a region, the
slaves were immediately freed. The remaining slaves in the U.S. were freed by the
13th Amendment to the Constitution (ratified December 18, 1865). Above, the
statue of Lincoln in the Lincoln Memorial, Washingtona shrine visited by thousands
of persons every year. Left, in the simpler setting of a housing development one
of the many statues raised to Lincoln by the people of the United States.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
* A LOOK AT U.S. RACE RELATIONS (Cont'd)
(Photos UM)
CHANGING PATTERNS. The federal
government has taken an unequivocal stand
against colour discrimination In the civil
and armed services of the U.S. Today a
new pattern is being set in the Army,
Navy and Air Force. Men of both races
train, work and live together (above).
The change-over from segregation to non-
segregation has been achieved without
serious friction. In a modern housing
.development, children of all races play
together in "Jungle Gyms", left.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
the deep-running currents of change
inequality of educational opportunity.
In a society where training is so im¬
portant, practices of this type are
simply an early form of occupational
discrimination. The groups that suffer
most in this respect are the Negroes,
who find that their access to higher
education is severely limited, and the
Jews who are not freely admitted to
some privately supported colleges and
professional, especially medical, schools.
It would be futile to deny that these
conditions in education and employ¬
ment do exist in the United States.
But it would be equally futile, after
considering the changes that have
recently occurred and comparing past
and present conditions, to deny that
noteworthy advan¬
ces have been made in
eliminating these evils.
It is highly significant
that most of the
recent advances have
been closely connected
with the policies and
acts of the federal
and state governments.
During the great de¬
pression of the 1930's,
the United States un¬
derwent a profound, far-
reaching and probably
lasting change in its
conception of the proper
role of government.
New interpretations of
the United States con¬
stitution greatly en¬
larged the power of the
federal government at
the expense of the states,
particularly in the re¬
gulation of economic
affairs.
At the same time, the
state governments found
their own power to
regulate their internal
social and economic re¬
lationships strengthened
and increased. De¬
cisions of the United
States Supreme Court acknowledged
and confirmed that government had
the power to regulate, in some respects,
the hiring and firing of workers and to
prescribe working conditions.- And it
was this change in the broad philo¬
sophy of government that set the stage
in America for the newest and most
effective methods of coping with
discrimination.
It was in 'response to the depression,
too, that the federal government
instituted programmes that eventually
affected group relations in every
community in the country. Many of
these programmes were designed to aid
the indigent and inevitably reached
those groups that had suffered most
from discrimination. Although the
anti-depression measures were not
aimed specifically at these "under¬
privileged" groups, the government
definitely sought to carry them out
without regard to the colour, religion
or origin of the beneficiaries.
Money was distributed directly to the
poor; plans were developed for aiding
farm owners, tenants and workers; the
government built houses or contracted
for them to be built; through a vast
public works programme hundreds of
thousands of men and women were
hired for every kind of work from
menial labour to the most advanced
kind of artistic creation. In all this
variegated activity, minority groups of
every kind received fairer treatment on
a national scale than they had ever
enjoyed before.
The Negroes, in particular, ex¬
perienced a much greater measure of
equal opportunity and treatment than
they had enjoyed in the past. Of
course, equality in the distribution of
charity or government relief funds is
not precisely the answer to the
aspirations of underprivileged groups.
But the full acceptance of their rights
was an indication of the new spirit in
, the land and an augury of more
significant gains. Taken in con-
INCREASED MIGRATION of Negroes from the south to the north of the U.S.
took place between 1930 and 1940, and was again sharply accelerated during World
War II. It was accompanied by an urbanization of the Negro population. Between
1940 and 1950 the proportion of Negroes in 27 cities rose from 17.5 per cent to
30 per cent. Industry also opened its doors to Negro workers, more and more of
whom are now employed in skilled jobs and therefore enjoying an improved economic
status. The one shown here is a worker in a Detroit automobile factory.
junction with vast changes in the
distribution of the Negro population,
federal recognition of their status
helpçd to set in motion forces tending
to make for their greater participation
in the benefits of democracy.
A considerable migration of Negroes
from South to North had begun during
World War I. This trend continued
during the post-war period, increased
during the thirties, and, owing to a
variety of factors, was sharply acceler¬
ated during the war-interrupted decade
of 1940-50. The suddenness and size of
the change may be measured by the
fact that during . this last-mentioned
decade the total population of 16
Southern states nearly doubled, where¬
as their Negro population increased by
only 2.5 per cent.
Another aspect of the changing role
of the Negro in American life was his
growing urbanization. In 1940, 27
cities contained 17.5 per cent of the
total Negro population; 10 years later
the same cities contained more than
30 per cent of the total. The hectic
pace of Negro urbanization can be
measured by the simple fact that
whereas from 1940 to 1950 the white
urban population rose from 58 to 64
per cent of the total, the Negro urban
population expanded at more than
twice the white rate, rising from 48 to
61 per cent.
Along with increased educational and
employment opportunies, an important
consequence of these population trends
is that Negroes are more concentrated
than before in ' Northern cities and
states where they are free to vote and
to utilize their strength at the polls.
These cities and states, moreover,
owing to their large populations, are
influential in national elections. One
indication of the potential power of the
free Negro vote is that in 1948 and
1952 this vote was greater in many
states than the margin of victory of
either of the two major political
parties, Republican and Democratic.
Negro voting has like¬
wise grown rapidly. In
1948 it was estimated
that there was a record
Negro vote of 750,000; in
the 1952 national election
this vote was put at
1,350,000. These gains
were registered not only
in the North but also in
the South, where the
trend toward Negro
disfranchisement has
been decisively reversed
and Negroes are becom¬
ing an important in¬
fluence in elections.
Meanwhile, during
this period of the 1930's
and into the next two
decades as well, the
United States Supreme
Court was both respond¬
ing to this new spirit
and stimulating i t s
growth. In a series of
remarkable decisions,
the Court reversed a
tradition of a half-
century and began to
give special protection
to the rights of minority
groups protection re¬
dounding especially to
the benefit of Negroes, the most under¬
privileged among these groups that
have suffered from systematic ' discri¬
mination.
During the decade following the end
of the Civil War, the federal govern¬
ment had sought, through five major
laws and three constitutional amend¬
ments, to protect the newly-eman¬
cipated Negroes in their exercise of the
rights and privileges of United States
citizens; but in the period that
followed, the Supreme Court by its
verdicts in case after case restricted
the application of these statutes and
amendments.
During the 1930's, however, the
decisions of the Court began to
emphasize the protection of civil
rights. As we shall see later in
more detail, the Court gave the
federal and state governments greater
power in protecting minority groups
against discrimination by private in¬
dividuals and groups, and at the same
time diminished the power of govern¬
ments themselves to discriminate.
These decisions bolstered minority
rights in the administration of justice,
citizenship, employment, and voting,
and helped considerably to weaken
segregation in education, housing, and
public transport, (continued next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A LOOK AT U.S. RACE RELATIONS (Cont'd/
In the thirties, too, a. period began
during which the legislative bran¬
ches of both the federal and state
governments were continuously in¬
fluenced by the trend towards equality
of opportunity. True, up to the end of
1953, the United States Congress had
been unable to overcome the tenacious
opposition to major civil rights
legislation. But even this body, which
reflects all the interests of every
geographical region, including the
South, where discrimination and se¬
gregation are strongest, has felt the
powerful impact of the new spirit.
400 Anti-bias Laws
ALTHOUGH it has actually passed
none but minor laws, Congress
has served as the arena for many
long-drawn, widely publicized battles
for measures against discrimination.
These struggles have done much to
educate and arouse the public and to
unite all the organized groups seeking
corrective legislation. The number of
bills introduced is itself impressive.
In 1937-38 there were only 10 bills
dealing with minority problems; during
the next 10 years 170 such bills
were presented and in 1949-50 alone
72 bills were introduced.
The state legislatures have also
experienced this growth of interest in
the outlawing of discriminatory prac¬
tices, and many of them have enacted
effective laws. From the establishment
of the United States until 1953, the
states have enacted almost 400 anti¬
discrimination and anti-bias laws.
Two-fifths of these laws have been
passed since 1940. These statutes have
outlawed discrimination or segregation
in employment, places of public
accommodation, education, health care,
housing, insurance and loans, the
armed forces, voting, the professions,
or have sought to remove irregularities
in marriage laws, or have dealt with
group defamation, the rights and
status of aliens and the foreign born,
and mob violence.
Popular upsurge
UNDERLYING these government
activities has been an extraord¬
inary upsurge of popular feeling
for democratic equality as revealed in
the activities of a host of private
voluntary organizations, including busi¬
ness and religious groups, athletic
organizations, professional groups, etc.
Only a few years ago discrimination
became for the first time a subject
treated openly, frankly and extensively
in the movies, over the radio, and in
the mass circulation magazines.
Dozens of cities, in response to
demands by their citizens, established
special agencies to improve group
relations. The major leagues in pro¬
fessional baseball began in 1947 to hire
Negro players, and by now they are so
well accepted as to occasion little
comment. Since the 1940's, too,
religious, labour and . professional
groups have admitted to membership
all qualified persons irrespective of
race, colour, religion, or national
origin; these include national Church,
groups and local Churches of all
religions and denominations, trade
unions, and associations of doctors,
dentists, nurses, lawyers, teachers,
scholars, and students in all parts of
the country, including the South.
The upshot of all this government
and private activity is that the Negroes,
who have constituted by far the most
underprivileged large group in the
United States, have made great strides
towards achieving living conditions on
a par with other United States, groups.
These advances can be measured in
certain indices of welfare as reported
recently in a special study by the'
United States Bureau of Labor
Statistics. Two conclusions are drawn
from the facts presented in this official
study: "The first is that in' almost
every significant economic and social
characteristic that we can measure
including length of life, education,
employment, and income our Negro
citizens, as a whole, are less well off
than our white citizens. The second
is that in almost every characteristic
the differences between the two groups
have narrowed in recent years."
In terms of basic health, while the
death rate is still higher among
Negroes than whites, the difference in
these rates has declined markedly. In
1935, the Negro death rate was 17.3 per
1,000 of the population, the white rate
11.1 per 1,000. By 1949, the death rate
had declined to among Negroes 12.6
as the white rate dropped to 8.4, the
Negro decline being proportionately
greater.
In education, likewise, the sta¬
tistics for the same period re¬
vealed that the
gap between
whites and Ne¬
groes had been
considerably re¬
duced. In 1940,
Negroes at the
age of 25 had
completed an
average of 5.7
years of school;
in 1950 this fig¬
ure had risen to 7
years. In 1940,
whites had com¬
pleted 8.7 years of
school, and, in
1950, 9.7 years.
The Negroes' gain
was thus propor¬
tionately higher
than that of the
whites.
Progress in em¬
ployment can be
measured by the
degree to which
Negro workers
have been able to
leave ill-paid jobs
in agriculture for
skilled or un¬
skilled jobs in
industry. In 1940
more than 40 per
cent of all
Negro workers
were in agriculture; by 1952 this
number had declined to 19 per cent.
This decrease in the proportion of
Negroes in agriculture was more than
twice the decline among the Whites.
The total improvement in the economic
condition of the Negro may be gauged
from the fact that in 1939 the average
Negro worker's income was about $400
a year or less than 40 per cent of the
average wage of white workers. In
1950, the Negro worker earned an
average of $1,300 a yearor 52 per cent
of the white worker's average wage.
Still much to do
ALTHOUGH these changes, during
a relatively short period, are
evidence of significant progress,
no one would deny that much remains
to be done to improve group relations in
the United States and to ensure the
rights and privileges of all the in¬
habitants. The advances have taken
place under favourable economic con¬
ditions, they have not been uniform
and, in scattered urban areas both in
the North and South, they have been
accompanied by some illegal violence.
Nevertheless, the progress is per¬
ceptible and so is the will and deter¬
mination of the majority of the
American people to move forward
towards the realization of full equality
of rights and opportunity for all. And
as the United States has become in¬
creasingly subjected to world scrutiny,
the government and American citizens
have realized that the United States
minority problem is one which, for good
or ill, can seriously affect American
status abroad.
SLUM AREAS. Many Negroes are still confined, because
of housing segregation, to "black belts". Here in many
American cities they live in overcrowded, dilapidated struc¬
tures in slum areas. But many efforts are being made to
improve the lot of both city and country dwellers. Of
150,000 housing units recently built by the government,
50,000 were allotted to Negro families.
(Photo Magnum - Carlier-Ëresson )
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Employment
discrimination
and its reduction
SKILLED
NEGROES WANTED
®
EMPLOYMENT discrimination as it exists in the United
States persists as the result of a situation involving
contradictory elements. On the one hand, such discri¬
mination can only become a serious problem in a society
that is highly industrialized, that is, a society in which
workers are employed in large-scale, mechanized enterprises
under what is known as a capitalist or entrepreneurial
system of production. Such a system is considered highly
"rational", since it tends to encourage science and technology
and gears itself to making profits through the most efficient
processes of production and distribution.
On the other hand, discrimination could not exist without
such irrational factors ¡j
as prejudice, bigotry, ]
anxiety, etc., all of i
which introduce into j
the process of pro- i
auction . judgments j
based on race, colour, a
religion, or national j
origin that function, \
demonstrably, to mili- j
täte against maximum I
efficiency.
Discrimination I
depends, therefore, \
upon the coexistence of j
two developments, each 3
typical of radically j
different patterns of ]
life. To begin with, \
there must be a high j
proportion of wage- *
workers in the employ of owners or managers and a high
degree of occupational specialization yielding different
rewards from small to relatively large for those working at
different tasks. But alongside these modern, capitalistic
economic modes persist older patterns of thought and
behaviour, which do not have efficiency as their sole criterion
and allow the operation of prejudice, irrationality and
sentiment to influence the process of production.
As the American sociologist, Everett C. Hughes, has pointed
out, modern industry mixes various kinds of peoples, brings
various groups together in a pot-pourri of nations and classes
within nations. While it brings people together on a large
scale, industry also segregates individuals and groups
according to their function .and status.
This kind of segregation is very apt to develop along ethnic
or racial lines. Thus, in almost every country, whether
economically developed or underdeveloped, certain groups
concentrate in particular crafts or industries. When this
sorting process is unrelated to actual qualifications and when
members of particular groups are excluded against their
wish from desirable employments, a discriminatory pattern
may be said to exist.
Occupational discrimination is not confined solely to the
United States. It plagues other countries too, but does not
usually cause so much domestic agitation or so much
comment from foreign observers. The reasons for the in¬
tensity of feeling generated by the presence of discrimination
in the United States are numerous, rooted in its history of
mass immigration and the development of its democratic,
highly industrialized society.
To begin with, successive waves of new immigrants into a
land where no political compulsions exist have created a
(Pliotift USIS)
nation where minorities of one kind or another formed, in
1950, fully one-third of the population of some 150 million.
In that year the United States contained more than
28 million Roman Catholics, over 15 million Negroes and more
than 5 million Jews. Persons of Asian and Latin American
birth or ancestry numbered more than another million.
And though the rate of immigration has been comparatively
low for a generation, there were still 10 million people in the
United States who were born outside its boundaries. The
difficulties of reconciling opposing interests, beliefs and
habits in so heterogeneous a society are readily apparent.
American minority groups have, moreover, a very different
relation to society from similar groups in European countries.
In Europe, for the most part, discrimination is or at least
Was the product of a legally-imposed pattern involving
restriction of the opportunities of genuine "minorities", that
is, groups in a national state which did not wish to become
part of the community but wanted certain rights guaranteed
to enable them to withdraw from the rest of the community.
A "minority" in the United States today is something
else it does not denote a group constituting an enclave
seeking to isolate itself from national life as a whole. By and
large, United States minorities desire and strive towards full
participation in the life of the community. The result is an
emphasis on factors such as prejudice and discrimination
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
-¿-REDUCING JOB DISCRIMINATION (Cont'd;
WHAT DISTURBS
THE NEGRO MOST
that frustate the powerful urge towards full integration.
Moreover, it is precisely because the United States makes
it possible for all individuals to share in the country's great
wealth that such resentment is created among those who
suffer from unequal treatment. In other countries the
problem is apt to be less acute because there is less wealth,
the approaches to it fewer and the class-structure too rigid
to permit much movement. The greater social mobility, of
the United States, coupled with its philosophy of ambition
and ability to reward successful achievement, means that
any block in the aspirations of a group has the most serious
social and political consequences.
Finally, the ideals and traditions of American democracy,
the highly industrialized economy which militates against
all irrational prejudices that interfere with productivity,
tend to make the existence of inequalities a serious matter,
disturbing the security and way of life of the nation as a
whole.
Discrimination, in America, takes many forms and excludes
individuals from various desirable offices and activities for
a host of different reasons. Thus, it is extremely improbable
at present that anyone but a white Protestant would be
elected President, but this is not yet considered a serious"
grievance to those so barred. Indeed, it is common for
groups to he disturbed very little by certain kinds of barriers,
while those who erect them feel most strongly about their
maintenance.
In his monumental work, An American Dilemma; the
Negro Problem and Modern Democracy, Gunnar Myrdal, the
great Swedish economist, has pointed out that a curious
hierarchy of discrimination against the Negro prevails in
America. Those who discriminate feel most strongly about
items regarding which the Negroes themselves have only
a minimum of concern. Here is the list, going from the
items which arouse the highest intensity of emotion in those
who discriminate to the lowest:
1. Intermarriage, and sexual relations involving white
women.
2. Other personal relations, e.g., eating, dancing, bathing
and general social intercourse.
3. Use of public facilities, e.g., schools, churches, means of
transportation.
4. Political rights, e.g., the right to vote.
5. Discrimination in courts of law and by police and other
officials.
6. Economic activities, e.g., land ownership, . employment,
obtaining credit, public charity.
The ,intensity of the Negro's feelings about these items is
diametrically opposed to those of the white man; he feels,
for the most part, much less disturbed by the items at the
top of the list than he does by those at the bottom. The
chief reason for this is his relatively low economic status.
INDUSTRY AND
FARMING. During
World War II, a million
Negroes went into defen¬
ce industries. In general
they have stayed in indus¬
try ever since. To-day
nearly I l%of all industri¬
al workers are Negroes,
twice as many as in I 940.
During this period the
number of Negro agri¬
cultural labourers has
greatly decreased, but
for those who remain
conditions have become
better. Negro farm
owners today number
more than 18,9,000.
10
IT WAS NOT UNTIL I 942 AND THE LABOUR SHORTAGE OF WORLD WARIlJT
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIERf. N» 6. 1954
HAT RACIAL BARRIERS TO NEGRO EMPLOYMENT IN INDUSTRY REALLY BEGAN TO CRUMBLE.
This accounts for the large proportion of his hopes, energy
and resources that the Negro has put into the struggle for
fair employment practice legislation. A correspondingly
strong reaction from those opposed to this kind of legislation
and the involvement of other minority groups have combined
to make the issue of fair employment a crucial one in the
campaign for equality in the United States.
However, for other groups Catholics, Jews and people of
foreign ancestry, for example employment discrimination
is less of a problem than it is for the Negro, as they are
much closer to full equality. But, occupation discrimination
is more keenly resented by these groups because it represents
almost their sole major grievance, while the Negroes suffer
from other forms of discrimination as well.
The social discrimination from which the other minorities
may suffer, however much it may affect some individuals,
is not of such intensity nor does it cause such resentment -
that the group as a whole feels strongly compelled to take
serious action against it. It is moreover wellnigh impossible
to redress all private wrongs by law.
It is apparent then that discrimination is a complex
phenomenon requiring a complex solution. Forces at work
to end discrimination for one group in
one part of the country are often
neutralized by other forces at work for
a different group or in an another area.
The mere geographic distribution of
the affected groups is testimony to this
fact. Most of the 25 million Catholics
are concentrated in the north-eastern
part of the country; about 60 per cent
of the 15 million Negroes still live in the
Southern states (although this pro¬
portion is declining rapidly) ; about half
the Jews live in New York City. People
of Mexican origin and descent are con¬
centrated in the South-west; Puerto
Ricans are to be found chiefly in New
York and other parts of the East while
the Orientals live mainly in California
and other West Coast areas. The
Catholics, Jews, Chinese, Puerto Ricans
and northern Negroes inhabit mostly
urban areas, thé southern Negroes live
in rural sections, while the Japanese,
Mexicans and Filipinos are about evenly
divided between the rural and urban.
This variegated checkerboard of
colours, religions and ethnic origins is
not merely the result of recent develop¬
ments; the United States has been
heterogeneous from its -earliest colonial'
days. The first white settlers were,
themselves, religious minorities, dis¬
senters frorn the dominant religions in
their European home countries. Fric¬
tion between ethnic groups was
manifested early, among the various
groups of white settlers themselves, as
well as in their relations to the Indians
they were displacing and to the Negro
slaves they were importing from Africa.
Meanwhile, immigration from Europe
continued and increased. Until about
the middle of the nineteenth century,
most of the newcomers were of English,
Scottish, German and Dutch origin.
Since they were not "too dissimilar in
appearance, culture and origin, their
differences were composed without
much difficulty.
But in the 1840's a new element, the
Irish Catholics, arrived, provoking con¬
siderable religious and ethnic discri¬
mination, especially as their numbers
grew. From about 1880 onwards,
during the great period of United
States industrial expansion, a huge in¬
flux of immigration from Southern and
Eastern Europe brought to the New
World millions of people who differed
markedly from the earlier settlers in
religion, appearance and ways of life.
They were mostly Roman Catholic,
Jewish or Greek Orthodox in religion,
and came from Russia, Italy, Poland
and other countries close to those,
geographically and culturally.
From the Orient, too, in the middle of
the nineteenth century came a large group of Chinese who
worked on the growing railroads, in the mines and on the
farms of the West, causing resentment among labourers who
often found themselves displaced because of the willingness
of the Chinese to work for much lower wages.
A considerable number" of Japanese arrived in 1900 and
found employment, for the most part, on West Coast farms.
In 1920, Filipinos arrived in substantial numbers. Mexicans
arrived in small numbers before World War I and have been
entering in larger numbers since. Masses of Puerto Ricans
came to the United States, mainly to New York City, after
having been granted United States citizenship in 1917; in
recent years, still larger numbers of the islanders have
migrated to New York City.
A certain amount of local strife, agitation and discri¬
mination has attended the arrival of nearly all these foreign-
born groups. Most of them found employment in occu¬
pations they had practised in their home countries, or similar
work. By and large they were, at first, confined to the jobs
that appeared less desirable in an expanding economy. But
as time went by the majority of the immigrants and their
children found the road to occupational and educational
advancement relatively open. (continued next page)
1 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
TWO OPPOSING TRADITIONS:
Rugged Individualism; Respect for Law
(CONTINUED FROM PREVIOUS PAGE)
This cannot however be said to be true of the Negroes,
whose history in this country is unique and unlike that of
any other group. Before the Civil War Negro slaves"
performed the labour of the agricultural South. After the
abolition of slavery they continued to work on southern
farms as tenants and then as free workers. In the urban
areas of the South they were employed as domestic servants
and unskilled labourers in mining, the iron and steel
industries and tobacco-processing.
During the slavery period, also, a substantial number of
free Negroes in the South were employed as skilled workers,
mostly in the construction industry. In the period
immediately following the Civil War, when Negroes were
excluded from many kinds of life and work in the South,
they lost their hold on skilled construction jobs. The
introduction of new methods in the industry caused the skill
of the unemployed quickly to become obsolete. Discri¬
mination by employers and the excluslonist policy of trade
unions prevented the Southern Negro from realizing the
promises of emancipation.
In the North, at the same time, there were relatively few
Negroes, and most of them worked as servants, janitors,
porters and labourers. Between 1890 and World War I, a
great wave of labour troubles offered the Negroes the
opportunity to get jobs in some heavy industries as strike¬
breakers. The labour shortage of World War I opened up
employment to them in iron, steel, meat packing, and the
automobile industry.
As can be seen, discrimination in the United States is not a
simple, uniform phenomenon. Nor is it possible to obtain
absolute agreement on the best means for ending it, even
among those most deeply concerned with the problem.
We are primarily interested here in the use of legal means
to end discrimination in employment. This does not mean
that all concerned believe it the best means for the purpose
nor that other methods and agencies have not been tried
with considerable success. Thus, to cite -only one of scores
of organizations, the National Urban League with Negro and
white members and branches in cities everywhere in the
United States, has done remarkable work In securing for
Negroes positions for which they are qualified by education
and training. Since the League relies solely on the goodwill
of employers, its success shows that compulsions of law are
not the only means to effect reduction of discrimination.
Strikes and labour unrest
APART from the work of voluntary organizations and the
effect of legal compulsion, the picture of discrimination
Is constantly being changed and shaken by great social
forceswar, strikes, prosperity, depressions, and population
changes. The very dynamics of American democracy tend to
foster a real equality in order to eliminate internal con¬
tradictions. Strikes and labour unrest often open up avenues
that were formerly closed to minority groups. - ,
A shortage in any given profession, or an overall labour
shortageas during World War IIoften allows new groups
into occupations, industries and jobs from which they Were
formerly excluded. For well over a decade now the United
States has been In a period of "full employment" with
concomitant benefits and advantages to everyone in a
position to put labour power of any kind on the market.
The successful workings of law and legal techniques utilize,
and to some degree require, these other factors. The climate
of opinion created by private initiative, the needs' created by
inexorable social and economic trends, are often simply
expressed by the enactment of a statute or administrative
order. The law in this case tends to accelerate and regulate
a change which would come about in any case but in a
slower, more haphazard fashion. Where a law is arbitrary,
unsuited to the conditions of the period and prevailing
opinion, observance is apt to be difficult to obtain.
Law in the United States is of several Varieties! the statutes
passed by federal, state and local legislatures, and law in
the sense of administrative actions and rulings by the
government; while, as a result of the commonlaw system
and the written Constitution which is interpreted by the
highest court in the land, judicial decisions create law too.
Law in the United States, then, emerges as thé end result
of a great number of pulls and counter-pulls, as the final
resolution of the needs, rights, desires and powers of the
individual, the community and the central government.
II
The American system of "checks and balances" has come
into being as a result of the desire not to delegate too much
to any. one branch of government. The Constitution, itself,
contains a series of compromises, the most important of
which, the distribution of power between the federal and
.state governments, derives from the desire of the original
colonies to retain as much autonomy as possible.
Every citizen of the United .States is a citizen not only of
the country as a whole but of one of the 48 states. The
states have their own judiciary systems; the criminal laws
that are most often actually applied are state laws and, in
daily life, the American citizen is more likely to come in
contact with local than federal authority. .
The drafters of the Constitution, influenced by the liberal
eighteenth-century belief that the great threat to individual
liberty was the central government, specifically enumerated
and described federal powers but left the rest, undefined, to
the states. The resultant federal-state- balance has had
profound effects upon the rights of minorities and the
political freedoms of the individual.
i
Rough justice of frontier days
THE first 10 amendments to the Constitution constitute
the American "Bill of Rights" which secures the rights
of individuals against infringement by the federal
government. On the other hand, no power is expressly given
to the federal government by the Constitution which would
enable it to secure civil liberties and rights against encroach¬
ment by private individuals.
These limitations have seriously hampered efforts by the
federal government to protect groups whose rights have
been jeopardized by state and local governments or by
individuals; and while amendments to the Constitution have
been passed which enable the national government to
protect "minority rights" against violation by states and
municipalities, it is still the state and local authorities which
exercise the police power that most intimately affects people
in their daily lives.
The institutions of the United States, then, reflecting as
they do a delicate balance between the national, state, local
and private interests, make the uniform solution of the
problem of discrimination by legal methods a difficult matter.
Two sharply opposed traditions are at work in the United
States to shape individual attitudes towards law and govern¬
ment. There is the tradition of the moving frontier, derived
from the period when the boundary of the settled area of
American life was constantly moving westward, creating
large border areas in which there was only a rudimentary
state power. In the rough and tumble atmosphere of new
communities in the making, the inhabitants of these areas
became accustomed to doing things for themselves, relying
upon their own power and initiative instead of the distant
authority of a government whose laws and agencies were
shaped to the needs of more civilized areas.
Invasion of 'private' rights
WORKING against the American tradition of '.'rugged
individualism" is the Puritan conception, so powerful
in the original colonies and enduring throughout the
development of the United States, that all aspects of man's
behaviour are amenable to control by law and that men are
better off when their lives are so regulated,
These two tendencies of American life, the frontier
tradition of individuals taking into their own hands things
usually left to law, and the Puritan tradition of legislating
on matters usually left to private conscience, often combine
to produce a uniquely American phenomenon the enactment
of laws that seem Intended as ideals of behaviour rather
than regulations to be observed.
To many Americans, even some of those most earnestly
against discrimination, government regulation of these
matters is regarded as an invasion of the "private" right to
choose one's friends, neighbours and business associates and
to conduct one's business with a minimum of government
interference. On the other hand, the voluntary associ¬
ations, some wholly and some partly devoted to the
elimination of discrimination, have done a vast amount of <
work in the reduction of prejudice through education and in
campaigning for its elimination by legislation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 6. 1954
(Photos Ropho-ßlack Star and USIS)
EQUAL CHANCES -
In I 945 it was New York
that became the first
state to pass a law outlaw¬
ing discrimination in em¬
ployment. Since then
I 2 states and 30 munici¬
palities have followed
suit. Unions have done
much to break down
colour barriers in indus¬
try. Above, a Negro
woman presents her
views at a factory union
meeting. Whether in
industry or the profes¬
sions (like nursing and
scientific research work
the American Negro is
seeking equal opportu¬
nity and equal pay.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE
COURT
STEPS
Vß ] "*
¡JböJ
SEAT OF THE GOVERNMENT. When the French architect
Pierre l'Enfant arrived in 1790 to help establish Washington,
he at once spotted the logical location for the new "Congress
House"'Jenkins Hill, 88 feet above the river. .Here, the Capitol,
which cost S 20,000,000, was built. It is now the home of
the House of Representatives, the Senate and various adminis¬
trative services, which together constitute the Congress.
EARLY in the development of the United
States it became established that the
Supreme Court, the highest tribunal in the
land, had the right and the function of passing
upon the constitutionality of federal, state and
'local legislation. Theoretically, the Court may
not pass upon the wisdom of such legislation
but merely -upon the right, according to the
Constitution and previous judicial decisions, of
any law-making body to enact a specific law.
But the broad language of the Constitution
and the great variety of "precedents" created
by earlier decisions have given the Court
considerable freedom in selecting policies it has
wanted to advance at the expense of alternatives
it has not found attractive. The Court,
throughout its long and controversial history,
has in fact often been able to impose its own
philosophy of government and, by its inter¬
pretations, to engage in what is tantamount to
the act of legislation.
It is necessary to understand how the
Supreme Court has interpreted the Constitution
and its amendments, for its decisions have
defined the power of the federal and local
governments to enact laws and issue regulations
protecting the rights of victims of discri¬
mination. In addition, the Court has recently
been in the forefront of the trend toward
greater protection of civil rights of all kinds,
including the right to obtain employment
without disadvantage because of race, creed,
colour, _ or ethnic origin.
The decisions of the United States Supreme
Court on matters of group relations have varied
greatly, during the last 100 years. From about
1868, when the Fourteenth Amendment to the
Constitution went into effect, until about 1937,
the Court usually supported those laws which
tended to enforce the separation of Negroes and
whites. Concomitantly, it acted in such a way
as to weaken the effects of those tending to
promote the association of Negroes and whites
except in situations where the superiority of
the whites was clearly maintained.
Since 1937, however, the policy of the Court
has changed drastically and it has consistently
upheld the rights of victims of discrimination.
Before 1937 the Court felt it imperative to
restrain the legislatures, from regulating and
limiting the rights of property holders: thus,
during the 1920's it blocked legislation on child
labour, minimum wages for women, farm
problems, and public utility valuation. About
1937, however, the Court elevated the protection
of civil rights to a preferred position; since then
it has tended to refrain from blocking
legislation on economic rights and to restrain
legislatures, individuals and groups from un¬
fairly discriminating against "minority" groups.
(Photo Ropho-SJock Star)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The new outlook of the tribunal ~was
clearly expressed in 1940 by Associate
Justice Hugo L. Black, when he stated
for the entire Court : "No higher duty,
no more solemn responsibility, rests
upon this Court, than that of translat¬
ing into living law and maintaining
this constitutional shield deliberately
planned and inscribed for the benefit
of every human being subject to our
Constitution of whatever race, creed
or persuation."
Three historic clauses
OF all the provisions of the United
States Constitution none has
been more significant for the
rights of Negroes and other minority
groups than the Fourteenth Amend¬
ment. This amendment reads: "No
State shall make or enforce any law
which shall abridge the privileges or
immunities of citizens of the United
States, nor shall any State deprive any
person of life, liberty, or property
without due process of law, nor deny to
any person within its jurisdiction the
equal protection of the laws."
Over and over again, in any study of
minority problems, mention will be
made of the three main clauses of this
amendment, the "privileges and im¬
munities" clause, the "due process"
clause, and the "'equal protection"
clause. Endless scrutiny and inter¬
minable debates have gone into the
attempt to fix the precise meaning and
application of the words of the
legislators. Various interpretations of
these clauses have had through the
years a crucial impact on the welfare
of minorities in the United States.
In 1873, in the very first case under
the Fourteenth Amendment to reach
it, the Supreme Court laid the basis
for a lengthy series of decisions which
weakened the force of its provisions.
In its final opinion, the Court estab¬
lished a distinction between the rights
of an individual as a citizen of the
United States and the rights of an
individual as a- citizen of the state in
which he or she resides. The privileges
and immunities clause, it ruled, pro¬
tects' only federal rights from hostile
state action.
Privileges violated
FROM that time onward, the Court
refused to consider the civil
rights of "minority" groups as
rights which they had by virtue
of their United States citizenship;
such rights, the Court stated or
implied, were enjoyed by virtue of
state citizenship and hence were not
affected by the Fourteenth Amend¬
ment. In 1935, however, the Court for
the first time invalidated a state law
on the ground that it violated the
privileges and immunities clause. But
five years later the Court flatly reversed
its position, and thus made the clause
virtually inoperative again.
The "due process" clause has,
likewise, been the subject of changing
interpretations in a changing world.
Although "due process of law"
originally meant a fair hearing by a
properly constituted authority in
criminal and civil cases, in 1890 the
Court began to invoke it to invalidate
legislation which it held to be un¬
reasonable.
For many years the Court protected
property rights by means of this clause,
but restricted the federal government's
power to use it for the protection of
the rights of accused persons against
various forms of state action. Then, in
1925, it accepted the notion that the
"due process" clause of the Fourteenth
Amendment forbids the state govern¬
ments to do what the First Amend¬
ment (1)' forbids the United States
Government to do.
Thus, in piecemeal fashion, the
Court's interpretation of the Fourteenth
Amendment has extended the scope of
the Bill of Rights until it now serves as
a means of protection not only against
the actions of the federal goverment
but those of the 48 state governments
as well. This extension has meant a
great deal, particularly to Negroes,
who have always found state legislation
and state authority more oppressive
than federal law and authority. In
1945 the Court took an important step
in this direction when it upheld the
constitutionality of a federal law
(originating as far back as 1866) which
has since served to deter state and
local officials from depriving Negroes
accused of a crime of the protection to
which they are entitled.
The third of the clauses in the
(1) "Congress shall make no law respecting
an establishment of religion, or prohibiting the
free exercise thereol ; or abridging the freedom
of speech, or of the press ; or the right of the
people peaceably to assemble, and to petition
the Government for a redress of grievances."
UNESCO COURIER. N° 6. 1954
Fourteenth Amendment, the "equal
protection" clause, has been the chief
constitutional source for the protection
of the rights of minorities. Its scope
was considerably limited only a few
years after it came into being, when, in
1883, the Court held that the Four¬
teenth Amendment restricted only the
state governments, and not private
citizens, from discriminating. This
interpretation still stands.
Birth of a doctrine
IN 1896 the Court upheld a state law
requiring separate but equal ac¬
commodations for Negroes and
whites on railroads moving within the
borders of Louisiana. In deciding this
case, (Plessy v. Ferguson) the Court
stated the famous "separate but equal"
doctrine, which inaugurated a new
epoch in United States group relations,
in the following words :
"A statute which implies merely a
legal distinction between the white and
coloured races a distinction which
is founded in the colour of the two
races, and which must always exist so
long as white men are distinguished
from the other race by colour has
no tendency tö destroy the legal equality
of the two races, or re-establish a state
of involuntary servitude."
True, the Court insisted, in cases it
decided later, upon adherence to this
"separate but equal" rule but with only
moderate practical consequences. Thus,
despite the Fourteenth Amendment,
which forbids the states to "deny to
any person within its jurisdiction the
equal protection of the laws," Negroes
have in fact enjoyed separate but far
from equal facilities in the Southern
(Acme)
THE HIGHEST JUDICIAL BODY The drafters of the Constitution of the United States divided
federal power into three parts to form a system of checks and balances executive, legislative and
judicial. The executive is the White House, that is, the President and the government ministers; the
legislative is the Congress and the highest judicial body is the Supreme Court. Originally the Court sat
in the same building as Congress, but since I 935 it has had its own white marble home on Capitol Hill.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE COURT
STEPS IN
(Continued)
states. But, even under the "separate
but equal" doctrine, Negroes have been
able to win rulings that materially
weakenejd the entire system of colour
segregation in the United States.
A costly business
THESE gains have been made in
two ways. First, the Court has
adopted a progressively stringent
interpretation of what "equal facilities"
means, thus making segregation more
costly and cumbersome than ever.
As a result of a series of cases
involving discrimination In education, *
there are, today, thousands of Negroes
attending unsegregated, state-support¬
ed institutions of higher learning in
the South, whereas there were none a
decade or so ago. Similar, although
less spectacular, gains have been made
in the effort to eliminate discrimina¬
tion and segregation in transportation
facilities, mainly through decisions that
interpret broadly the power of Con¬
gress to regulate interstate commerce.
The second way in which the
Supreme Court has weakened the legal
basis of discrimination and segregation
has been by a broadening interpretation
of what constitutes action by the state
and by state and local officials falling
under the purview of the United States
Constitution and certain federal laws.
In this way Negroes have been able to
advance their rights to be considered
for membership of juries and, if under
trial, to be judged by a jury from which
none has been excluded because of race
or colour. They have also been able
to strengthen their vote in the
Southern primary elections, where the
right to vote counts most.
After many years of seeking to
weaken discrimination and segregation ,
by securing Supreme Court decisions
of these two types, a few years ago the
leaders in this struggle adopted a new
plan they began to challenge the
"separate but equal" doctrine directly.
20th century trends
BY and large, the history of the
Supreme Court decisions has run
parallel to the development of the
American nation, influencing and being
influenced by new trends in an evolving
society. In the great nineteenth cent¬
ury period of commercial and industrial
expansion, its decisions seemed to place
the greatest emphasis on the protection
of individual economic rights against
government interference. In the twen¬
tieth century, when local events often
have nation-wide consequences and in¬
dividual and national welfare are more
closely .bound, its interpretations have
tended to support those seeking to
reduce discrimination and segregation.
Recent Supreme Court decisions have
thus set the stage for major advances
in the protection of civil rights, while
its hearings and opinions have served
to educate the public and clarify the
complex issues involved in the problem.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N" 6. 1954
The decision
was unanimous:
'EQUAL BIT SEPARATE
SIGNIFIES U IM EQ U AL'
by Dr. Murray S. Stedman Jr.
Professor of Political Science, Swarthmore College, Pennsylvania
CPhotos USIS)
LONGER TO
LIVE AND
MORE TO
LIVE FOR
The life expectancy of
this little Negro boy has
gone up from 47 years
in 1 920 to 60 today.
In the same period, the
white's life expectancy
has risen more slowly,
from 56 to 66 years.
With greatly improved
standard of living and
medical care, the gap
between the white man's
and the Negro's life span
is closing. The photo¬
graph, left, was taken
in 1937 and shows an old
Negro couple who were
slaves in the early
part of their childhood.
ON Monday, May 17, 1954, the Supreme
Court of the United States issued a his¬
toric decision which proclaimed that racial segre¬
gation in schools supported by public funds
was a violation of the American Constitution.
In the two decisions the Court handed down it
thus gave a dramatic demonstration of-its»power
to review the constitutionality of laws.
Under the system of government in existence
in the United States of America, power to go¬
vern is derived from the Federal Constitution,
drafted^ in 1787. Both federal and state laws,
as well as state constitutions, must be in accord
with the Federal Constitution.
In case of dispute as to the applicability of
portions of the Constitution, the United States
Supreme Court is the final arbiter. A law, or
a section of a law, found by that Court to be at
variance with the Constitution ceases to be en¬
forceable. In actual fact, the Supreme Court
finds very few laws, in whole or in part, to be
unconstitutional. But, since the decisions of
the Court, unless it subsequently reversen itself,
are final, .those decisions become binding on
all lesser courts, both federal and state.
The May 17 ruling affected public schools in
one-third of the 48 American states and also
public schools in the District of Columbia
(where the city of Washington is located), an
area governed under federal law.
Its guiding principle
As of May 1954 a total of 17 states and the
District of Columbia required that Negro
and white children attend public schools set
apart for each race. Four states provided that
segregation could be adopted by local option.
Of this group of states, one, Wyoming, never
exercized the option. In some 16 states segre¬
gation in public schools was prohibited by law.
In the remaining 11 states no specific legislation
on segregation existed. In the areas of segregated
schools are some 8.1 million white and some 2.5
million Negro pupils.
In the two decisions rendered on May 17, the
Court first announced its guiding principle in
-a consolidated decision involving public schools.
in four states. In the second decision, the Court
then applied this principle to public education
in the District of Columbia.
In the United States there is no ministry of
education and public education in the ¡states
is a function of state government. In the excep¬
tional case of the District of Columbia, which
is not a state, public education is handled
through a school board deriving its powers
from ¡acts of Congress. Hence, it was the first
decision, involving the powers of the states,
which attracted the bulk of attention.
From four states
The 'consolidated decision concerned cases
originating in the states of Kansas, South
Carolina, Virginia and Delaware. In each case,
according to the Court, "minors of the Negro
race, through their legal representatives, seek
the aid of the courts in ohtaining admission
to the public schools of their community on a
non-segregated basis. In each instance, they had
been denied admission to schools attended hy
white children under laws requiring or permitt¬
ing segregation according to race." Because a
common legal principle bound the cases, they
were considered together.
It was alleged by the lawyers for the Negro
pupils that segregation was unconstitutional, on
the ground that it deprived such children of the
equal protection of the laws under the Four¬
teenth Amendment one clause of which pro¬
hibits any state from denying "'to any person
within its jurisdiction the equal protection of
the laws."
In the first case decided by the Supreme
Court construing the 14th Amendment, it was
held that the Amendment prohibited all etate-
imposed discriminations against the Negro race.
However, as seen in the previous article, in
1896, in its decision in the case of Plessy v.
Ferguson, involving not education but transpor¬
tation, the Court evolved the "separate but
equal" doctrine. Under this doctrine, equality
of treatment is accorded when the races are
provided substantially equal facilities, even
though these facilities be separate. Segregation
in railroad transportation, as provided for in
the Louisiana statute whose constitutionality
had been challenged, was thus upheld.
. (CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE)
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 6. 1954
Tkeffuku
"EQUAL BUT SEPARATE
SIGNIFIES UNEQUAL" (Cont'd)
Between the time of the Plessy case and the 1954 deci¬
sion, the Court heard six cases involving the "separate but
equal" doctrine in the field of public education. In most
of the recent cases, all on the graduate school level, ine¬
quality was found in that specific benefits enjoyed by
white students were denied to Negro students of the same
educational qualifications. The questions as to whether
the Plessy doctrine was applicable to public education
was not at issue, merely the question of inequality of
facilities.
In the four cases about which the consolidated decision
was given on May 17, the facilities offered students of both
races were found to have been equalized or in the process
of being equalized. Hence, the problem faced by the Court
was the practice of segregation as such. In the words of
the Chief Justice, Mr. Earl Warren, speaking for the Court :
"We must look instead to the effect of segregation itself on
public education."
That the Court deliberated a great deal is apparent from
the record. The cases first reached the Court on appeal
in 1952. Arguments were made on December 9-10 of that
year, but the Court ordered reargument and heard the
18
THE NINE MEMBERS of the United States Supreme Court who made the unanimous decision of May 17. Left to right, seated :
Associate Justices Felix Frankfurter and Hugo Black; Chief Justice Earl Warren; and Associate Justices Stanley Reed and Wil¬
liam O. Douglas. Standing: Associate Justices Tom Clark, Robert, H. Jackson, Harold H. Burton and Sherman Minton.
cases again on December 7-8, 1953. Reargument was heard
in the spring of 1954 on certain questions propounded to
counsel by the Court.
In reaching its decision, the Court noted the overwhelm¬
ing importance of education as the foundation of good
citizenship, and concluded that education is the principal
instrument in preparing a child for later life. This being
so, if a state provides free education, it must be available
to all on equal terms. The Court then stated: "We come
then to the question presented : Does segregation of children
in the public schools on the basis of race, even though
the physical facilities and other 'tangible' factors may be
equal, deprive the children of the minority group of equal
educational opportunities." Answering its own question,
the Court unanimously declared: "We believe that it
does."
In support of this view,- the Court relied heavily upon
the findings of modern psychological knowledge, citing
various authorities. The Court accorded more weight to
modern scientific findings that it did to the historical cir¬
cumstances surrounding the adoption of the 14th Amend¬
ment, since, in Its view, the latter approach led to incon¬
clusive results.
The Court found it unneccessary to inquire as to whether
segregation was prohibited in state public schools on the
b||sis of the due process clause of the 14th Amendment.
But in its second decision, involving segregation in the
Dfctrict of Columbia, the. Court found that the due pro¬
cess clause of the 5th Amendment (an Amendment which
imposes restrictions upon the Federal Government) was
relevant. Referring to its earlier decision on state public
schools, the Court asserted:
"In view of. our decision that the Constitution prohibits
the states from maintaining racially segregated public
schools, it would be unthinkable that the same Constitu¬
tion would impose a lesser duty on the Federal Go¬
vernment. We hold that racial segregation in the public
schools of the District of Columbia is a denial of the due
process of law guaranteed by the Fifth Amendment to the
Constitution." As in the state case, the decision of the
Court was unanimous.
Clearly recognizing that the implementation of its deci¬
sions would create complexities, the Court requested the
assistance of all parties for further argument at its fall
term. The Attorneys-General of the states requiring or per¬
mitting segregation in the public schools were invited to
appear as amici curiae, as was the Attorney-General of the
United States. The Court particularly invited argument
as to its own equity powers, and also to the procedure to be
fallowed, in the formulating of any decrees.
The United States
Constitution contains
provisions calculated to
ensure the Supreme
Court's independence of
the President and Con¬
gress. The Justices are
appointed for life and
Congress cannot reduce
the pay of a Justice while
he is In office. However,
Congress has the right
to determine the num¬
ber of Justices and the
President the authority
to appoint them. The
Court's decisions are kept secreteven from the Presidentuntil
they have been read at a public hearing. "Opinion Day"when the
Court announces its verdictis always a Monday, the decision
having been reached
the previous Saturday,
when the Justices vote
on the case in reverse
order of seniorityfrom
the youngest back to the
Chief Justice. A special
branch oftheGovernment
Printing Office operates
in the basement of the
Supreme Court building
in order to minimize the
possibility of leaks in the
process of printing the
decisions. Inside the
Court building is a magni¬
ficent courtroom featuring twenty-four marble columns and
bad acoustics. There are suites for each Justice, conference
and robing rooms, a library and separate chambers for the
clerks, lawyers, marshals
r
'i
and the Attorney-Gene¬
ral of the United States.
The Justices have pri¬
vate dining facilities as
well as private eleva¬
tors. The chairs where
the nine black-robed
Justices sit behind their
high bench partly sym¬
bolize the independence
which each may assert,
being of assorted shapes
and sizes and chosen
personally (although all
are upholstered in black).
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
THE
THE following are the principal passages from
. the decision of the U.S. Supreme Court, on
racial segregation in state-supported primary
and secondary schools in the United States :
"...Minors of the Negro race, through their legal
representative, seek the aid of the courts in obtain¬
ing admission to the public schools of their com¬
munity on a nonsegregated basis. In each instance
they had been denied admission to schools attended
by white children under laws requiring or permitting
segregation according to race.
"This segregation was alleged to deprive the
plaintiffs of the equal protection of the laws under
the Fourteenth Amendment.
"In each of the cases other than the Delaware
case, a three-judge federal district court denied relief
to the plaintiffs on the so-called -'separate but equal'
doctrine announced by this court in Plessy v. Fer¬
guson.
"Under that doctrine, equality of treatment is
accorded when the races are provided substantially
equal facilities, even though these facilities be
separate.
"In the Delaware case,
the Supreme Court of De¬
laware adhered to that
doctrine, but ordered that
the plaintiffs be admitted
to the white schools be¬
cause of their superiority
to Negro schools. The
plaintiffs contend that
segregated public schools
are not 'equal' and cannot
be made 'equal', and that
hen^e, thev are deprived
of the equal protection of
the laws."
Examining the circum¬
stances surrounding - the
adoption of the 14th,
Amendment in 1868 and"
public education at the
time, the Court found
them inconclusive for re¬
solving the problem.
"In . the South, the
movement toward free common schools, supported
by general taxation, had not yet taken hold. Edu¬
cation of white children was largely in the hands
of private groups. Education of Negroes was
almost non-existent and practically all of the race
was. illiterate. In fact, any education of Negroes
was forbidden by law in some states. Today, in
contrast, many Negroes have achieved outstanding
success in the arts and sciences as well as in the
business and professional world... Even in the
North... compulsory school attendance was virtually
unknown.
"As a consequence, it is not surprising that there
should be so little in the history of the Fourteenth
Amendment relating to its intended effect on public
education.
"In the first cases in this Court construing the
Fourteenth Amendment, decided shortly after its
adoption, the Court interpreted it as proscribing all
state-imposed discriminations against the Negro
race.
"The doctrine of 'Separate but Equal' did not
make its appearance in this court until 1896 in the
case of Plessy v. Ferguson involving not education
but transportation.
"American courts have since laboured with the
doctrine for over half a century. In this Court,
there have been six cases involving the 'Separate
but Equal' doctrine in the field of public education...
"The validity of the doctrine itself was not chal¬
lenged. In most recent cases, all on the graduate
WORDS
OF A
MOMENTOUS
DECISION
school level, inequality was found in that specific
benefits enjoyed by white students were denied to
Negro students of the same educational qualifica¬
tions.
"In nine of these cases it was necessary to re¬
examine the doctrine to grant relief to the Negro
plaintiff. And in Sweatt v. Painter, the Court ex¬
pressly reserved decision on the question whether
Plessy v. Ferguson should be held in application in
public education.
"In the instant cases, that question is directly
presented. Here, unlike Sweatt v. Painter, there
are findings that the Negro and white schools in¬
volved have been equalized, or are being equalized,
with respect to buildings, curricula, qualifications
and salaries of teachers, and other 'tangible', factors.
"Our decision, therefore, cannot turn on merely a
comparison of these tangible factors... We must look
instead to the effect of segregation itself on public
education...
"We cannot turn the clock back to 1868, when the
Amendment was adopted, or even to 1896, when
Plessy v. Ferguson was written. We must consider
public education in the
light of its full develop-
- ment and its present place
in American life through¬
out the nation. Only in
this way can it be deter¬
mined if segregation in
public schools, deprives
these plaintiffs of the
equal protection of the
laws.
"Today education is
perhaps the most im¬
portant function of state
, and local governments.
Compulsory school at¬
tendance laws and the
great expenditures for
education both dem¬
onstrate our recognition
of the importance of
education to our de¬
mocratic society. It is
required in the perform¬
ance of our most basic public responsibilities, even
service in the armed forces. It is the very founda¬
tion of good citizenship.
"Today it is a principal instrument in awakening
the child to cultural values, in preparing him for
later professional training and in helping him to
adjust normally to his environment. In these days,
it is doubtful that any child may reasonably be
expected to succeed in life if he is denied the
opportunity of an education. Such an opportunitv,
where the state has undertaken to provide it, is a
right which must be made available to all on equal
terms.
"We come then to the question presented; does
segregation of children in public schools solely on
the basis of race, even though the physical facilities
and other 'tangible' factors may be equal, deprive
the children of the minority group of equal edu¬
cational opportunities ? We believe that it does.
"In Sweatt v. Painter, the Court in finding that a
segregated law school for Negroes could not provide
them equal educational opportunities, relied in large
part on those qualities which are incapable of objec¬
tive measurement but which make for greatness in
a law school.
In a second case (MCLauren v. Oklahoma State
Regents) the decision states: "the Court, in requiring
that a. Negro admitted to a white graduate school
be treated like all other students, again
resorted to intangible considerations: (Continued
'his ability to study, to engage in dis- on page 23)
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N° 6. 1954
And the Doors
Shall Open
Today over 128,000 Negroes are attending colleges or universities in the U.S.A. More than half are students in
Negro institutions such as Fisk University at Nashville, Tennessee (inset) where whites were also admitted even before
the Supreme Court decision on segregation. In the North and West the typical practice is to admit Negroes to all
higher institutions. In the South, the battle against segregation in graduate and professional schools is practically won.
Even before segregation in public schools was outlawed, Negro children, like the boy above, were attending elemen¬
tary and secondary school classes in two Southern states (Delaware and Kansas), and in June, St. Louis, Missouri announced
that it will end bias in public high schools next February, and in all elementary schools by September 1955.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
SEEN HERE- LEAVING
the U.S. Supreme Court, is
Thurgood Marshall Special
Counsel of the NAACP (Na¬
tional Association for the
Advancement of Colored
People). The small team
of Negro lawyers which he
headsthe legal department
of the NAACPis concerned
with the protection of the
legal rights of more than
15,000,000 American Ne¬
groes. This makes It prob¬
ably the world's biggest
law firm, with the difference
that it operates not for profit
but for principle. Photo,
below, shows Thurgood
Marshall conferring with
NAACP leaders In New
York. (Photos copyright ;
published by courtesy of
"Ebony" magazine, Chicago.)
(Photos courtes/ ' Ebony ')
THE GREAT TEST
OF 'CIVIL RIGHTS9
by Thurgood Marshall
Special Counsel, National Association for the Advancement of Colored People.
1 Jfl
~ ^** ^P^^^V^
^L - ^^k. J . j^^^^*. Jk ^m fl
*?2 fc^l
T
A he recent decisions - of the
United States Supreme Court
outlawing racial segregation in
public schools have. finally settled the
question as to whether segregation
per se is a form of discrimination
which is inhibited by our funda¬
mental laW. These decisions also
demonstrate that one's right to be
free from distinctions based upon
race can come only from the law.
They finally show that some laws
do not give this freedom. This brings
us to a consideration of the distinc¬
tion between the adjudicative and
legislative processes.
Adjudication is the function of
courts. It decides and enforces indi¬
vidual liabilities as they stand on the
basis of existing facts and under
existing law. On the other hand,
legislation is rule-making. It creates
a right, duty or status directed toward
the correction of a situation rather
than particular persons and is inde¬
pendent of the existence of any pre¬
vious right, duty or status. There¬
fore, adjudication may be called anti¬
dotal laW, a remedy for counteracting
injurious effects, whereas legislation
is prophylactic law, a means of pre¬
venting an anticipated harmful effect.
In the combat against racial discri¬
mination, we cannot afford to ignore
the importance of resort to the legis¬
lative process. Historically, the earli¬
est blows delivered against racial¬
ism in America were legislative
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 6. 1954
THE WORDS OF A MOMENTOUS DECISION (Cont'd from
page 20)
eussions and exchange views with other students and
in general to learn his profession.'
"Such considerations apply with added force to
children in grade and high schools. To separate them
from others of similar age and qualifications solely
because of their race generates a feeling of inferiority
as to their status in the community that may affect their
hearts and minds in a way unlikely ever to be undone.
"The effect of this separation on their educational
opportunities was well stated by a finding in the Kansas
case by a court which nevertheless felt compelled to
rule against the Negro plaintiffs:
"Segregation of white and coloured children in public
schools has a detrimental effect upon the coloured
children. The impact is greater when it has the sanction
of the law; for the policy of separating the races is
usually interpreted as denoting the inferiority of the
Negro group. A sense of inferiority affects the
motivation of a child to learn. Segregation with the
sanction of law, therefore, has a tendency to retard the
educational and mental development of Negro children
and to deprive them of some of the benefits they would
receive in a racially integrated schools system.'
"'We conclude that in the field of public education the
doctrine of 'separate but equal' has no place. Separate
educational facilities are inherently unequal. Therefore,
we hold that the plaintiffs' and others similarly situated
for whom the actions, have been brought are, by reason
of the segregation complained of, deprived of the equal
protection of the laws guaranteed by the Fourteenth
Amendment..."
enactments. For example, in 1777 and
1846 Vermont and Rhode Island,
respectively passed . laws forbidding
slavery in their lands. In 1855, Mas¬
sachusetts prohibited racial segrega¬
tion in its school systems. The
Thirteenth, Fourteenth and Fifteenth
Amendments to the Federal Consti¬
tution are also a species of legisla¬
tion: and, of course they were intend¬
ed to forbid states to indulge in
racial discrimination. Furthermore,
- federal statutes were enacted in 1870
and 1875 to implement
these Amendments.
Although this federal
legislation did not survive
the test of judicial chal¬
lenge, it pointed the
way for states to breathe
life into the Civil War
Amendments. The states
responded with a flurry of
legislation designed to
prohibit racial discrimi¬
nation in many- walks
of life. After the turn
of this century, there
was little activity on the
part of the states and
none by the federal go¬
vernment other than a co¬
dification of the remanants
of the Civil Rights Act of
1870. But a resurgence of
activity in this area has
developed in the states in
the past decade.
A brief review of exist¬
ing laws against discrimi¬
nation reveals that only
17 states and the Dis¬
trict of Columbia have not
changed their laws sanc¬
tioning racial discrimina¬
tion in public schools.
Thus a majority of 31 sta¬
tes have passed acts which
have either expressly bar¬
red this type of discrimination or acts
which have been interpreted to effect
this result. Significantly, five states
have extended the coverage of their
laws to prohibit private schools from
practising racial discrimination.
In the field of public employment,
the federal government and fifteen
slates have enacted legislation bann¬
ing discriminatory hiring practices in
the agencies and operations controlled
by them. Eight states have required
that both governmental and private
employers cease racial discrimination
in their establishments; and penalties
have been provided to enforce these
laws. Four other states have passed
similar laws but without enforcement
provisions. At the municipal level,
some 29 cities have also passed fair
employment practices ordinances. It
is of some interest to point out that
only four of these cities are located in
ONE OF 1,629 NAACP LOCAL U.S. BRANCHES. Legal anion
undertaken by the National Association for the Advancement of Colored
People is financed by contributions from sympathetic individuals and organiza¬
tions as well as from the Association's 1,629 city and county branches spread
across 44 States. This is the entrance of one local NAACP branch in New York.
states with state laws enforcing non¬
discrimination in employment. Three
more cities have forbidden race dis¬
tinctions to be made in public em¬
ployment.
So-called "civil rights" laws have
been passed and are being enforced
in 19 states and the District of Co¬
lumbia. These laws generally for¬
bid racial' discrimination or any de
nial of full and equal enjoyment of
public accommodations (e.g. hotels,
restaurants, etc.), places of public
amusement (theatres, amusement
parks, etc.) and vehicles of public
transportation.
What does all of this mean? First,
each of these laWs prohibiting racial
discrimination represents a definitive
statement of governmental policy as
well as a standard for future conduct.
They have notified the persons sub¬
ject to their jurisdiction that indivi¬
dual prejudice must be
lost in the quantum of the
greater good. Such legis¬
lation also provides for
legal protection which mi¬
nority groups need in a
society where there is go¬
vernment by majority rule.
Furthermore, the educa¬
tional effect of laws
prohibiting discrimination
should not be minimized.
In this respect, the legis¬
lative process can promote
an individual's understand¬
ing of himself, his fellow
man, and the dynamics of
the democratic way of life.
While there is much to
be done even after laws
are passed, the setting
down in print of a law
which implements or ex¬
pands the principle that
our Constitution is- colour
blind is a tremendously
vital step. Of course,
anyone can validly com¬
ment thai legislation does
not extract the roots of
prejudice and intolerance.
These are personal con¬
quests. Neither will le¬
gislation completely pre¬
vent all oufcroppings of
discrimination in the spe¬
cific situations which il seeks to
correct. But it does create new rights,
duties and status which are consistent
with, rather than in derogation of,
the cherished aims of the democratic
creed "all men are free and equal in
the eyes of the law". For these rea¬
sons, therefore, we must develop both
preventive and corrective measures to
stamp out racialism in our land.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
32 social scientists
testify against segregation
SIGNIFICANT social changes are
usually the result of many differ¬
ent factors acting in combination,
and the historic United States Supreme
Court decision on segregation is no
exception to this rule. The heightened
social conscience of the American
people, in the South as well as in the
North ; the greater awareness of the
meaning of a democratic tradition
which in many parts of the world has
been under attack; the precedents set
through desegregation in a number of
universities ; the skill with which the
legal case was' prepared; the tre¬
mendous progress made by Negroes
themselves all these, and other
causes as well, contributed to the end
result.
There is one aspect of the decision,
however, which has not always been
recognized and
by Otto Klineberg
come to regard themselves, as inferior,
are severely handicapped in their per¬
sonal and intellectual development. It
is pointed out, for example, on the basis
of a number of important scientific
studies, that "minority group children
of all social and economic classes often
react with a generally defeatist attitude
and a lowering of personal ambitions.
This, for example, is reflected in a
lowering of pupil morale and a de¬
pression of the educational aspiration
level among minority group children
in segregated schools. In producing
such effects, segregated schools impair
the ability of the child to profit
from the educational opportunities
provided him."
which has far-
reaching im¬
plications, name¬
ly, the role played
by the social
scientist.
Throughout all
the legal develop-
ments which
paved the way for the final outcome,
the National Association for the Ad¬
vancement of Colored People, which
conducted the case against segregation,
called in social scientists as consul¬
tants, to give advice regarding the
present scientific position on the issues
being debated, as well as the manner
in which that position might best be
integrated into the legal argument.
In all the cases heard in the lower
courts, social scientists psychologists,
sociologists, anthropologists and educ¬
ators were called in as witnesses.
As an appendix to the brief presented
to the Supreme Court by the NAACP
counsel, there was filed a social science
statement entitled "The Effects of
Segregation and the Consequences of
Desegregation", signed by 32 dis¬
tinguished American social scientists.
It was described as "a consensus of
social scientists with respect to the
Issue presented in these appeals". Its
contents form the basis of many of the
questions to which the Supreme Court
Justices addressed themselves during
the final hearings.
Its conclusions are devastating to
the doctrine, previously maintained,
that separate but equal educational
facilities for Negro children are in fact
compatible with the American Consti¬
tution.
In essence the Statement insists that
enforced segregation is a symbol of
inferiority, and that children who are
regarded by others, and consequently
Dp Klineberg, Professor of Psychology, Colum¬
bia University, and a member of Unesco's Social
Sciences Department, has devoted much of his
life to a study of the Negro problem. He is
the author of several boohs on the subject in¬
cluding Uace Differences, Negro Intelligence and
Selective Migration, and Characteristics of the
American Negro. He testified at recent U.S.
Court heariiu/s on the effects of seyregation on
the personality of children.
24
Harmful effects
A questionnaire"
sent to a 'large
number of Ame¬
rican social scien-
t i s t s inquiring
into their views
on all children ^mTeffSs'
of enforced se-
gregation under
conditions of equal facilities, indicated
that 90 % of them felt that "enforced
segregation is psychologically detri¬
mental to the members of the segre¬
gated group." More than 80 % were of
the opinion that enforced segregation
was detrimental to the majority group
members as well.
Children of the majority group gain
status not always in terms of per¬
sonal ability and achievement) but
through the unrealistic conviction that
they are superior ,
r e
because of their
physical appear¬
ance or racial
origin.
The Statement
also disposes of
the question as
to whether there
are inherited dif¬
ferences in the abilities of Negroes'
and Whites which would justify edu¬
cational separation of the two racial
groups. After a brief review of
the relevant evidence, the conclusion
is reached that "fears based on the
assumption of innate racial differences
in intelligence are not well founded."
The writer might add that he himself
gave testimony to this effect in one of
the cases heard In the lower courts,
and his conclusions were not challeng¬
ed by the attorneys for the state con¬
cerned.
. Attention is given to the question of
the probable effects of desegregation,
since it has often been predicted that
this would have dire consequences even
leading to violence and bloodshed. In
this connection an imposing array of
evidence is available which indicates
that the process of desegregation can
and usually does occur without such
unfavourable consequences. The ad¬
mission of Negroes to a number of
southern universities, for example, took
violence unfounded
place much more smoothly and un¬
eventfully than many people had anti¬
cipated.
The Statement rightly points out
that the "most direct evidence avail¬
able on this problem comes from ob¬
servations and systematic study of
instances in which desegregation has
occurred. Comprehensive - reviews of
such instances clearly establish the
fact that desegregation has been
carried out successfully in a variety of
situations although outbreaks of vio¬
lence had been commonly predicted.
Extensive desegregation has taken
place without major incidents in the
armed services of both Northern and
Southern installations and involving
officers and enlisted men from all parts
of the country, including the South.
Similar changes have been noted in
housing and industry."
Apparently many people believe that
somebody else will start the rioting,
even though they themselves are pre¬
pared to accept the new situation.
There will of course be difficulties in
the way of further desegregation, but
previous experience indicates that they
can be surmounted.
It is not easy to determine just how
large a part this Statement, as well as
the continuing consultations between
NAACP counsel and American social
scientists, played in the final outcome.
Possibly the Supreme Court would have
reached the same conclusion in any
case. It is significant, however, that
the actual decision as handed down
refers explicitly to recent ^progress in
the field of psychology, and particularly
to, what is now known regarding
the harmful ef¬
fects of feelings
of inferiority on
the personal and
social develop¬
ment of children.
Thus, a far-
reaching change
in human rela¬
tions, which will
affect the whole pattern of democratic
existence in the United States, with
possible repercussions on other parts of
the world as well, has been set in mo¬
tion at least in part through progress
in the social sciences.
Some years ago Gunnar Myrdal in
his An American Dilemma called for an
"educational offensive" to reduce the
gap between public opinion and social
science in the whole area of race rela¬
tions.
Unesco, through the work it has
undertaken on race problems, has been
actively engaged in such an "offensive" ;
so have many individual social scientists
in many parts of the world. The gap
has been greatly reduced, and the
conclusions of the social scientists now
find much wider acceptance.
The Supreme Court decision repre¬
sents the most spectacular and con¬
vincing example of the part which
science can play in contributing to
human progress. \
i ci ions o
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER. N» 6. 1954
NEGRO WOMEN
OUTNUMBER THE MEN
Between 1890 and I9S0, the Negro population ¡n the U. S. rose from
7,500,000 to over 15,000,000. From 1940 to 1950 there was a great shift
away from the South to industrial and urban areas in the North and West,
but some ¿0 % of American Negroes still live In the South today. Since the
Civil War, Negro women have outnumbered male Negroes and this difference
has recently increased still more. It is only since 1950 that statistics showed
more white women than white men. On the average Negro households are
somewhat larger than white households in all regions. In nearly one out of
four Negro families in the U. S. a woman is the head. The Negro " granny "
wields strong authority In many rural families. .
UNESCO
ARCHIVES
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Going to school
Willi the Negro
As long as he was ignorant and illiterate, the American Negro
could not hope to qualify for the better jobs. Today, more
Negroes are going to schools and colleges than ever before.
Above, a Negro studentone of the 130,000 enrolled in U.S.
universities and collegesreceives his diploma. Right, students
on Howard University campus in Washington, D.C., one of the
great Negro universities in America, joke with a class president
candidate. Below, white and Negro youngsters in New York
City enjoy school puppet show. (Photos USIS and Black Star).
|EW people who were
¡not right in the midst
of the scenes can form an exact idea
of the intense desire which the people
of my race showed for an education.
It was a whole race trying to go to
school. Few were too young and none ,
were too old to make the attempt to
learn."
Booker T. Washington, the great
American Negro teacher who was born
a slave, wrote these words half a
century ago in his powerful auto¬
biography, "Up From Slavery", in
describing the fever for education
which gripped the newly-freed Negro
slaves in the United States.
The Negro has travelled a long road
since he was brought to the American
continent in chains, and education is
perhaps the most significant index of
the American Negro's over-all progress.
As long as he was. ignorant and
illiterate, the Negro could ,not hope to
qualify for the better jobs; without the
improved income from better jobs he
was unable to afford better housing;
and with poor housing, disease, crime'
and discouragement often go together.
Education enabled the Negro to speak
up for his rights, to increase his own
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
self-respect, bring prestige to his
community, and develop relationships
of real friendship with his white
neighbours. Most of all, it permitted
him to achieve a true cultural status
and a sense of social responsibility.
Professor Harry J. Walker of Howard
University, Washington, in a study
under preparation for Unesco on
changes in the status of the Negro in
American society, writes: "Although
the provision of education for Negroes
has been inadequate, it has been a
-means of bringing Negroes into wider
contact with the larger world, and thus
has contributed to their desire for
equality in American society."
Literacy in 1865 : 5 %
At the end of the Civil War, Negro
literacy stood barely at five per
cent. In 1900, thirty-five years
later, it had risen to 55.5 per cent; in
1950,. over 90 per cent out of a total
Negro population of 14,894,000 was liter--
ate. Today, illiteracy has been all but
ended among Negroes between the ages
of 14 and 24.
Formal education for Negroes did
. not really begin until the Civil War.
And though facilities existed in a few
Northern cities before the War, there
were laws prohibiting the instruction
of Negroes in Southern states where
slavery existed.
After the War between the States,
thousands of missionary schools were
opened for ex-slaves in the South and
'state legislatures began public educa¬
tion systems for both white and Negro
children. For a short period, in certain
towns in Louisiana and South Carolina,
schools were available for white and
Negro children to attend class together.
But since opposition to Negro educa¬
tion had existed all during the' slave
period and because of the acute racial
tension at this time (about 1876),
whites generally boycotted these
schools. This, added to some instances
of violence, resulted in the establish¬
ment of separate schools.
For the Southern Negro, then,
segregation came with the first schools
he knew, and this was hardly surpris¬
ing for the time, since he lived in a
wholly segregated society. A similar, if
less dramatic social process was going
on in other parts of the nation in the
post-Civil War years. Negroes concen¬
trated in sizeable numbers in the non-
South ran into social and economic
pressures which forced them to live
apart from the white community.
If the South did little to provide an
education for Negroes in these post¬
war years, it did little more for the
whites. The industrial revolution which
was transforming the North and the
newly-opened West, completely by¬
passed the South which remained
agricultural and extremely poverty-
stricken. By 1900, only one Southern
state Kentucky had made school
attendance compulsory and less than
40 per cent of all children of school age
attended school regularly. Over 11- per
cent of the whites were illiterate.
At the beginning of the 20th century,
public education generally in the South
received a strong impetus as the region
began to move toward industrialization.
Negro education also .profited, though
by any measurement it still lagged far
behind white education. In 1933 for
example, over 200 state counties in the
South still had no Negro high schools
at all. The number of Southern Negro
high schools, it is true, had risen from
67 in 1916 to 1,860 in 1928 with a corres¬
pondingly sharp increase in enrollment.
Except in rare instances, the Negro
rural schools which then served two-
thirds of the South's Negro children
had never reached even the minimum
standards, and half were primitive one-
room frame structures.
Demand for equality grows
Many Negro leaders of the 1920s
and 30s condemned the post-Re¬
construction spokesmen of their
race as too conservative. Yet signifi¬
cant progress was made in the period
which was symbolized by the states¬
manship of Booker T. Washington.
Washington argued for the advance¬
ment of Negro education but avoided
any attack on segregation in the
schools. Shortly before his death in
1915, however, he raised his voice
against segregation laws as unjust,
unnecessary and harmful to both races
in the long run. His earlier moderate
philosophy prevailed in the South until
the 1930s.
The thirties saw a great change take
place in the popular conception of the
role of government in the life of the
community. It saw the growing in¬
sistence on the part of Negroes for
equality of treatment and the develop¬
ment of public opinion favourable to
the extension of minority rights.
In the South, liberal white leaders of
standing began to question the old
notion that Negroes were entitled to no
more than a limited education. They
did not challenge the dual school
system itself«; instead they advocated
that the word "equal" in the Plessy
doctrine of "separate but equal" for¬
mulated by the Supreme Court in 1896,
be made a greater reality as regards
Negro education. A school of "gra¬
dualism" arose for the equalization of
Negro schools with those of whites so
that the Negro could ultimately achieve
the full status of citizenship.
This liberal point of view gained
considerable ground and led in effect
to a reduction of a great number of
.inequalities in the schooling available
to Negroes as compared to whites.
Negro teachers' salaries were raised,
funds for school buildings and equip¬
ment were increased, and school terms
were lengthened. Progress varied bet¬
ween states and within each state, but
the general trend was upward.
It was in the new climate of opinion
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Victory in 1935
First Negro
student enters
a university
in the South
by court order
of the thirties that Negroes turned to
the courts in their determination to
achieve equal status.
In the latter part of the 1930's dis¬
crimination in teachers' salaries came
under attack through various court
suits. Favourable court decisions in
some of these cases, together with the
insistence of the National Educational
Association, were effective in bringing
about a number of improvements.
From 1865 until about 1935, a total
of 44 cases involving the constitu¬
tionality of the separate school came
before the higher state and federal
courts. All decisions held the bi-racial
school system constitutional. Negro
leaders then focused their legal atten¬
tion on higher education for Negroes.
After the first World War there had
been a great increase in the enrollment
of Negro students in elementary and
secondary schools in the South. As a
result increasing numbers of students
sought training in institutions of
higher learning, including graduate and
professional schools.
Since it was financially difficult for
each Southern state to maintain
separate institutions of this kind for
Negroes, several states devised pro¬
grammes for out-of-state scholarships
usually to Negro institutions or
Northern colleges and universities.
Eventually all Southern states except
Mississippi provided such scholarships.
In 1935, a young student named
Donald Murray entered the law school
of the University of Maryland at Balti¬
more and. became the first Negro to
cross the colour line of a Southern
campus under court order.
Murray had applied for admission to
the law school and had- been refused in
accordance with Maryland's segregation
laws. He took his case to the state
court and argued that Maryland had
no law school for Negroes within its
boundaries. Instead it offered less
than 100 out-of-state scholarships for
some 280 Negro applicants, in order to
meet the Plessy doctrine. The state
court ordered Murray to be admitted
to the Maryland law school, holding
that the scholarship arrangement.was
discriminatory.
Following the Murray case, the U.S.
Supreme Court three years later, in
1938, invalidated the legal basis for
providing out-of-state scholarships for
specialized training. The Supreme
Court later ruled on a number of other
specific cases and largely invalidated
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
segregation in graduate and profession¬
al schools.
By 1953, all but five state universities
in the South had opened their doors
to Negroes. In two states they have
been admitted to the undergraduate
college which had formerly been res¬
tricted to whites. Also, some 45 priv¬
ately-supported white institutions have
voluntarily departed from the practice
of excluding Negroes. It was estimat¬
ed in 1953 that between 1,000 and 2,000
Negro students were enrolled in Sou¬
thern institutions which a few years
ago maintained a policy of exclusion.
If summer school attendance is
counted, the total figure is probably
three to four times as large.
Facing the inevitable
The University of North Carolina
Press has just published the
result of a long investigation
carried out by 45 scholars under the
auspices of the Ford Fund for the
Advancement of Education. In the
study called The Negro and the
Schools, the author, Harry S. Ashmore
of the Southern state of Arkansas, re¬
views the long legal history of the issue.
These are some of his comments on
racial integration at the university
level:
"In most cases there was a marked
contrast in official attitudes before and
after the fact of Negro admission. All
the Southern universities firmly
excluded Negro students until the
Supreme Court had systematically
undercut the legal basis of their
admission policies.
"It is impossible to determine how
often this represented the attitude of
university administrators, and how
often it only reflected passive accept¬
ance of existing statutes and prevailing
public opinion.
"In any event, it must be noted that
no university administration in the
South, public or private, actively sought
to abandon segregation until it was
faced with what its board of trustees
could agree was the inevitable."
Outside of the South, school segrega¬
tion has been the result more of resi¬
dential patterns than of law. It is
almost inevitable that segregation in
housing should produce segregation in
education. Children usually attend
the school nearest their home and
when they live in an all-Negro neigh¬
bourhood they will in all likelihood
attend an all-Negro school.
' About 94 per cent of the Negro
population outside the South resides in
urban areas. Since the Negro popu¬
lation in the larger cities is usually
segregated into residential areas it _
makes possible the maintenance of
some separate schools. The exceptions
are the children of Negroes living in
rural areas and small towns and those
who live in sections of the great cities
inhabited by both whites and Negroes.
Certain practices such as gerrymander¬
ing school districts and encouraging
"voluntary" transfers to schools in
Negro areas have helped to tighten
segregation in some cities.
Recently, however, a strong trend
away from segregation has been
apparent. In certain border states
school segregation laws have been
repealed or liberalized ; where segreg¬
ation was not sanctioned by law legal
and administrative action has been
taken to apply desegregation.
As shown on the map published on
page two of this issue, only four states
outside the South permit segregation
by option of local school authorities.
Eleven have no laws on segregation
and in 16 the law specifically prohibits
it. Many communities which have had
bi-racial schools for many years have
moved away from segregation volun¬
tarily.
This voluntary trend towards de¬
segregation has had a variety of
reasons. Foremost among these reasons
has been the pre-occupation of the
American people with the question of
civil rights for minority groups since
the last World War. It has been
spurred by the uninterrupted pressure
from Negroes, from church and civic
groups, from educators, school adminis¬
trators, and social scientists. The press
has been a positive force, particularly
outside the South where even the most
conservative newspapers are now sym-
do is shoulder the burden the courts
have placed upon them and work
. soberly to redirect their educational
effort along lines that will be acceptable
to all..."
Two states, Delaware and Kansas,
have already started to abolish segre¬
gation in elementary and secondary
schools. On June 22, the Board of
Education of St. Louis, Missouri,
announced that the integration of
white and Negro students in the city's
public high schools would begin next
February 1, and that racial segregation
in the elementary schools would be
eliminated by September 1955.
' South has reached a point in
its development," the author of The
Negro and the Schools has written,
"where educators and laymen alike
are going to have to take a close, new
look at their educational problems.
Wise leadership at the upper levels
can help, and emotional excursions by
TWO RACES, FOUR FRIENDS "Mixing white and Negro in the same university will only lead
to incidents". People who advanced this idea have been proved wrong by time and experience. Except
in a few isolated cases the best of relations exist between white and Negro students in universities
which have put an end to segregation. (Photos USIS and the Council Against Intolerance in America.)
pathetic to the Negro's demand for .
complete equality.
The United States Supreme Court
has now handed down its decision
placing a ban on segregation in schools
anywhere in the land. The verdict is
a- momentous one but fraught with
difficulties and complexities. It affects
the 8,200,000 white children and the
2,530,000 Negro children attending
school in the District of Columbia and
the states where segregation is
sanctioned by law. But there is more
involved than putting Negro and white
children into the same schools. ' The
absorption of Negro teachers, super¬
visors "and administrators into the
desegregated system, the re-arrange¬
ment of buildings, finances and tax¬
ation all will require a decade to
complete.
As one Southern newspaper, the New
Orleans Times-Picayune, put it, "...In
the states where most U.S. Negroes
live, the public school systems face the
prospect of considerable "turmoil for
some time to come... all the South can
the leaders of either race can do great
harm. But in the end the new
patterns will have to be hammered out
across the table in thousands of
scattered school districts, and they will
have to be shaped to accommodate not
only the needs but the prejudices of
whites and Negroes to whom these
problems are not abstractions but the
essence of their daily lives.
"In the long sweep of history the
public school cases before the Supreme
Court may be written down as the point
at which the South cleared the last
turning in the road to reunion the
point at which finally, and under
protest, the region gave up its peculiar
institutions and accepted the prevailing
standards of the nation at large as the
legal basis for its relationship with its
minority race. This would not in itself
bring about any great shift in Southern
attitudes, nor even any far-reaching
immediate changes in the pattern of
bi-racial education. But it would re¬
define the goal the Southern people,
white and Negro, are committed to
seek in the way of democracy."
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE ROAD TO EQUALITY:
some significant dates
1849 Abolitionist Charles Sumner
argues first school segregation case
in U.S. for Negro girl barred from a
white school in Boston, Massachu¬
setts. He lost case but in 1855 the
state outlawed all school segregation.
1862 U.S. Congress passes bill abo¬
lishing slavery in Washington, D. C.
1863 President Lincoln puts into
effect his Proclamation declaring all
persons held as slaves in rebel states
free.
Congress votes bill to eliminate
segregation in street cars. First
anti-segregation legislation in trans¬
portation.
1865 Thirteenth Amendment ra¬
tified, abolishing slavery in the
United States and its territories.
1868 Guarantees of "equal protection
. of the laws" for all citizens be¬
comes part of Constitution as the
Fourteenth Amendment.
1870 Fifteenth Amendment ratified
declaring that the right to vote
should not be denied to anyone on
grounds of "race, colour or previous
condition of servitude".
Congress passes Enforcement Act,
designed to bring Federal Govern¬
ment' pressure to bear against any
effort to circumvent 14th and 15th
Amendments. (Supreme Court nul¬
lifies act in 1876 as exceding proper
role of Federal Government.)
1875 Congress passes Civil Rights
Law, later nullified by courts, guar¬
anteeing to all persons regardless of
race, the use of "inns, public con¬
veyances on land or water, theatres,
and other places of amusement".
1880 Supreme Court invalidates
West Virginia law excluding Negroes
from juries as denial of equal
protection guaranteed by Fifth
Amendment.
1896 In Plessy v. Ferguson, Supreme
Court establishes principle of "se¬
parate but equal" facilities for
Negroes in railway transportation.
1909 National Association* for the
Advancement of Colored People
established.
1914 U.S. Supreme Court decides
that "grandfather clause" device for
restricting Negro voting in South
is unconstitutional. Opinion was
written by Justice White, a
Southerner.
1917 White women of Southern
Presbyterian Church hold first large
conference in South with Negro
women.
Supreme Court holds that a mu¬
nicipal housing ordinance segregating
whites and Negroes deprives real
estate owners of property without
due process of law.
Segregation Ordinance prohibiting
Negroes from living in white districts
and whites in Negro districts declared
unconstitutional by Supreme Court
as "not a legitimate exercise of police
power of the state and in direct
violation of... 14th Amendment".
1918 Serious race riots in Chicago
and other cities result in more at¬
tention to conditions of life of urban
Negroes.
1922 Young Women's Christian
Association (YWCA), leader in broad
inter-racial policies, announces its
national - conventions will be held
only in places where all delegates
alike may share in all facilities.
1923 Federal Council of Churches
_ appoints committee on Church and
~ Race relations.
1923 Leading newspaper editors in
six Southern states" call for mutual
co-operation between races, for more
education for Negroes, equality
before law.
1926 National award established for
outstanding creative achievements by
American Negroes.
1927 Texas law barring Negroes from
voting in Democratic primary elec¬
tions is unanimously overruled by
Supreme Court. (Five years, later,
attempt to bar Negroes from prim¬
aries by Democratic party resolution
is declared illegal by Supreme Court.)
1930 North Carolina Supreme Court
decides that buses must carry Negro
inter-state passengers.
1931 Association of Southern Women
for Preventing of Lynching organized,
1934 Anti-racial Catholic councils
established in New York, Washington,
Chicago, St. Louis and other cities.
1935 CIO (important national trade
union) adopts constitution barring
discrimination in union affairs on
grounds of race or colour.
Donald Murray becomes first
Negro to enter all-white Southern
university by court order.
Supreme Court decides that a
Negro was denied equal protection of
the law at trial on which no Negroes
were on jury.
Negro woman is appointed Prin¬
cipal of New York primary school
where 22 of 25 teachers are white.
1937 Movement spreads to admit
Negroes in Catholic colleges outside
South.
U.S. Housing Authority announces
it will house Negroes in third of
housing units built.
1938 Supreme Court rules a state
must admit a Negro to its law school
or establish comparable separate
facilities. This decision and others
opened doors of Southern professional
schools to" Negroes.
1939 Maryland District Court rules
that Negro teachers must be paid
same salaries as white teachers for
same work.
1940 Life sentence conviction of
Southern Negro is reversed by
Supreme Court on grounds that
Negroes had been barred from jury
service at his trial.
First Negroes begin serving on
Southern juries.
Supreme Court refuses to review
- Circuit Court of Appeals decision that
Negro and white teachers must
receive equal salaries for equal work,
thus tacitly accepting decision.
Colonel Benjamin O. Davis, a
West Point graduate, becomes first
Negro general in U.S. Army.
1941 President Roosevelt establishes
Federal Fair Employment Practices
Commission (FEPC), with in¬
structions to seek elimination of
discriminatory practices in industry.
Washington, D.C. Bar Association
admits to its library all lawyers in.
good standing.
First Negro conducts a symphony
orchestra on nation-wide radio hook¬
up.
First Negro is elected member of
National Institute of Arts and
Letters.
1942 New York hospital sets pre¬
cedent by becoming completely inter¬
racial as to trustees, staff, nurses and
patients.
1944 Supreme Court rules that
railroad unions cannot act as
bargaining agents unless they grant
equality of membership rights to
Negroes.
1945 New York State passes first
state Fair Employment Practices law
forbidding "discrimination because of
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
1849-1954
race, creed, colour or national origin"
, in employment, and sets up State
Commission against discrimination.
Four Broadway plays deal with
the theme, of race relations.
1946 Booker T. Washington is first
Negro to be honoured in U.S. Hall of
Fame. " Half dollar coin is also
issued in his honour.
A Negro, Alain Locke of Howard
University, is elected President of the
American Association for Adult
Education.
American Nurses Association
adopts unsegregated membership
policy.
"Jim Crow" practices on interstate
buses barred by Supreme Court.
1947 President Truman's Committee
on Civil Rights calls for an end to
all forms of segregation.
Jackie Robinson becomes first
Negro to play on a major league
baseball team, opening way for other
players.
1948 Supreme Court rules that
"racial covenants", (private real es¬
tate agreements involving residential
race restrictions) cannot be enforced
by the courts.
President Truman issues executive
order establishing as a policy for the
armed forces "equality of treatment
and opportunity for all persons...
without regard to race, colour or
national origin'".
1949 Alabama constitutional pro¬
vision giving local registration of¬
ficials wide powers to deny franchise
nullified by a Federal court.
1950 Segregation in railroad dining
', cars is banned by Supreme Court.
"' Supreme Court in a decision
(McLaurin v. Oklahoma) acknow¬
ledging that inequality is inherent in
segregation, directs University of
Oklahoma to stop segregating a
Negro student in classrooms, library
: and other facilities.
1953 Supreme Court rules that
- restaurants in District of Columbia
cannot legally refuse to serve meals
. to Negroes, ending a segregation
practice that had prevailed there
since Civil War days.
1954 Supreme Court, in a ruling
' based on principle that separate
facilities are inherently unequal, out¬
laws segregation in free elementary
and secondary schools as "a denial
of the equal protection of the laws"
guaranteed by the Fourteenth
Amendment.
THE NEGRO VOTE in the South has increased from 250,000 in I 940
to over one million in I 952. This has come about through population
shifts into the towns, improved education, changes in public attitude
regarding the Negro's status and the relaxation of voting restrictions
(Photo USIS)
THE VOTE
A HOUSING FACTS and FIGURES
NEGROES first came to America as explorers not as slaves. Ancient
manuscripts mention Alonzo Pietro, il nigro (the Negro) , as the pilot of the
Nina one of Columbus's ships. The territory now forming New Mexico and
Arizona was first explored by a party led by Estevanico, a Negro. Aviles de
Menendez had Negro artisans with him when he founded St. Augustine, Florida,
in 1565.
IN August 1619 "a dutch man of warre" brought to Jamestown, Virginia,
"twenty Negers" who were sold for needed provisions. This was one year
before the Mayflower landed the first refugees from civil and religious
oppression in England. The first census in 1790 showed 697,000 slaves in the U.S.
of whom 292,000 were in Virginia alone. In 1807, on President Thomas Jefferson's
recommendation, the U.S. Congress prohibited further importation of slaves; but
illegal trading continued. By 1860, before the Civil War began, the Negro
population was 4,440,000. Five years later they had all been set free.
3
THE slaves in the South made three considerable attempts at revolt: in 1800
under 'Gabriel Prosser in Virginia; in 1822 under Denmark Vesey in South
Carolina; in 1831, again in Virginia, under Nat Turner. These and other
attempts failed. During slavery Negroes could gain freedom by some outstanding
service, be freed at their master's death, or if they were children born of free
Negroes or white servants. They could also buy their freedom. Denmark
Vesey had purchased his for $600 after winning $1,500 at a Charleston lottery
in 1800. The first census in 1790 showed 8 per cent of the Negroes, or 59,311, to
be free.
S
SLAVES had no vote during slavery but free Negroes voted in many of the
Colonies. Gradually this right was taken away. After emancipation, Negroes
exercised political rights between 1865-1895. Except for Georgia, Negroes
for a time controlled all Southern state governments. Eight states were
represented by Negroes in Congress and for seven years Mississippi was repre¬
sented in the Senate by Negroes.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
NEGRO OFFICE HOLDERS have grown
in number as voting rights have been
extended. Illinois and New York are
each represented in the House of Repre¬
sentatives of the national Congress by a
Negro. Others serve in the legislatures
of the 1 7 states. The Negro woman
shown here is a member of the City
Council in Cleveland, Ohio, a city with
a million-and-a-quarter population.
(Photo USIS)
The right to vote and
the movement toward
non - segregated housing
WHEN the North withdrew its
armies and the Southern states
resumed control movements
developed to exclude Negroes from
politics. In 1890, Mississippi's revised
constitution disfranchised the Negro.
Seven other Southern states followed
the example, and by 1910 Negroes lost
the right to vote in nearly all the
Southern states.
3
IN the North during the Civil War
period, only New York and five
New England states allowed Negro
suffrage. After the war a U.S. Con¬
stitutional amendment enfranchised
the Negro. Since then there has been
no significant attempt in the North to
deprive the Negro of the right to vote.
3
VARIOUS methods were used in the
Southern states to bar Negroes
from voting. Voters were dis¬
qualified if they were illiterate, or did
not possess $300 worth of taxable
property, or had not paid a poll tax, or
did not have a regular occupation, or
had not served in the army, or were
not persons of "good character", or if
they or their descendants could not
vote prior to 1867 ("Grandfather
clause"), or did not understand
properly a clause of the Constitution
and could not explain it when it was
read to them. The "Grandfather
Clause" was declared null and void by
the U.S. Supreme Court in 1914.
3
AS the racial animosities generated
in the post-Civil War period
subsided, many restrictions were
relaxed so that in communities
scattered throughout the South small
numbers of Negroes were able to vote
and take part in politics, particularly
in 'cities.
Since 1940 the Negro vote has risen
markedly: over one million in 1952
compared to 250,000 in 1940. This
change has occured as a result of the
growing urban population of Negroes in
the South, improved education, the re¬
organization of life during the second
World War, and an important change
in public opinion regarding the status
of the Negro in American society. It
was also made possible by the elimi¬
nation of the "white primary" by the
courts, the abolition of the poll tax in
six states and other relaxations of
voting restrictions.
3
THE poll tax was "repealed by six
states between 1920-1949. Only
five states still require it for
voting and in several, opposition to it
is mounting. Despite the wide pub¬
licity the poll tax received as a device
for restricting Negro voting, its effects
are now considered to have been
exaggerated. The poll tax had to be
paid before registration for voting.
Registration was held several months
prior to elections and a receipt for
taxes paid had to be submitted.
3
WITH increased voting rights came
an increased political awareness
and a great increase in Negro
office holders. Illinois and New York
are each represented in the House of
Representatives of the national Con¬
gress by a Negro. In 1900 only one or
two Negroes were members of state
legislatures. By 1946 there were at
least 38. In 1952 a Negro woman won
a seat in the state senate of Michigan.
The 17 states in which Negroes now
serve in state legislatures include
Kentucky, in the South, and Missouri
and West Virginia, border states.
3
THE most striking development
since 1947 has been the election
or appointment of Negroes to
offices in communities in the South.
They are members of the city councils
of Richmond (Virginia), Nashville
(Tennessee), Atlanta (Georgia), and
three cities in North Carolina: Winston
Salem, Greensboro, and Durham.
Negroes have been appointed to state
or city boards of education in at least
seven states in the South. In recent
years Negroes in Southern towns have
been elected magistrates, constables,
commissioners. In 20 North Carolina
cities last year Negroes were candidates
for municipal offices. Sixteen major
Southern cities . employ nearly 65,000
Negro persons, 468 of whom are
engaged in managerial or professional
tasks. In the North there has been a
similar increase in the number of
appointive positions held by Negroes.
3
THE great migration of Negroes to
the North that began before
World War I and reached its
climax within the last 20 years has
created a difficult housing problem for
the Negro.
In many large Northern cities,
Negroes often live in overcrowded,
dilapidated buildings in segregated
slum areas. In the South, Negroes
often live not only in the same section
of town but on the same streets with
whites. Most Southern cities today
have several large concentrations of
Negroes with a light scattering over
most of the cities.
Negroes waged a long fight to elimi¬
nate "racial covenants", private real
estate agreements, which confined
them to ' restricted areas. They won
the battle in the courts in 1948 and, as
a result, Negroes have been able to
move into new areas in certain cities.
But although Negro income has in¬
creased considerably in the last decade,
Negroes have benefited from only a
small proportion of new housing built
during this period, and continue to
occupy a greater proportion of sub¬
standard housing than whites. About
9 million new dwelling units were built
by private enterprise between 1935-50
of which 100,000 or slightly more than
one per cent went to Negroes.
3
IN recent years, however, a strong
movement has grown for mixed
Negro-white public housing pro¬
jects. New York City, Chicago, Phila¬
delphia, Los Angeles, New Haven,
Pittsburgh, Seattle, and Washington,
D.C. are some of the cities that have
shown that whites and Negroes can get
along without friction. Though not
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
often publicized these housing pro¬
grammes represent one of the most
important gains in the Negro's struggle
for racial equality since the Civil War.
3
PERHAPS the most outstanding
success in non-segregrated public
housing occurred in New York
City. In 1947 all 14 of the city's housing
projects had Negro and white tenants,
and the authorities reported that :
"Negro and white families live side by
side... in harmony and peace despite
the scepticism this policy met in the
early days." Almost all metropolitan
cities in the North with large Negro
populations (except Philadelphia and
Detroit) made advances during the
1940's in the direction of eliminating
segregation in public housing.
The greatest success in integration
has been achieved where Negroes are
assigned appartments in the same
buildings with whites. Here tensions
have gone, differences have been
adjusted and a peaceful atmosphere
created.
Where only token integration exists
or where the races are separated by
buildings or other lines of demarcation
much less is accomplished. Tenants
cling to their old prejudices and it is
found that the races stay apart and
that white children often do not play
with Negro youngsters.
3
A RECENT study . of four public
housing projects in New York and
Newark, New Jersey, throws light
on the effect of racial contacts on
people's attitudes concerning other
races. Two projects had segregated
buildings, the other two had mixed
tenants in the same buildings. A
comparison of the two groups showed
that in the non-segregated buildings
there were many 'more cases of
friendly, neighbourly, contacts between
different races ; a more favourable
attitude toward Negroes in the project
and Negroes in general ; a more
favourable attitude toward living in an
inter-racial project. The survey also
showed that some white tenants who
had been loudest in objecting to living
next to Negro families came to accept
as neighbours these Negro families.
The experience with racially mixed
public housing has encouraged a
series of privately-financed mixed
housing. In 1944, as a result of pressure
from Negro organizations aided by
white groups, an ordinance was passed
in New York City prohibiting discrimi¬
nation in tax-exempt housing projects
developed by private industry. Many
people predicted that white people in
the higher income brackets would
refuse to live side by side with Negroes
and that investments would be
curtailed. These fears have proved
wrong. Millions of dollars have been
invested in such projects. In 1951 for
example, it was announced that New
York City had obtained sponsors for
the housing settlements amounting to
a cost of $10 million. Rental of all the
units in this project are covered by the
city's anti-discrimination law. Private
investors in Chicago have planned
several similar developments in non-
segregated housing in its slum
"clearance programme in the Black
Belt. But so far projects for mixed
housing by private investors only
exist in New York and Chicago.
BETTER HOUSINGIn many cities across the
U.S. housing construction is under way on a
larger scale than ever before. In New York,
the municipal housing board, labour unions
and insurance companies have built landscaped
dwelling developments for Negroes and whites
(above and below). A city ordinance passed
In 1944 prohibits race discrimination. Plans
exist to destroy all slum areas such as this one
in Harlem (right) where a backyard serves as a
playground for the local children.
(Photos USIS and Rapho-Black Star) 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom..
E,EUROVISION IS HERE:
Eight European countries have
recently been exchanging pro¬
grammes over national tele¬
vision networks in an inter¬
national experiment known as
Eurovision. The countries tak¬
ing part in the exchange Bel¬
gium, Denmark, France, Ger¬
many, Italy, Netherlands, Swit¬
zerland and. the United King¬
dom have been relaying the
programmes to eighty stations
covering a 3,800 imiles network,
with a potential viewing public
of some 90 million people. Pro¬
grammes were chosen to show
various aspects of each coun¬
try's national life. During the
relays, broadcasting organiza¬
tions made, at Unesco's sugges¬
tion, surveys of audience reac¬
tions to these programmes. At
the end of Eurovision month,
the first international TV se¬
minar opened in London, orga¬
nized by the British Broadcast¬
ing Corporation and- Unesco.
Television producers and direc¬
tors of educational and cultural
programmes from different
countries all over the world ex¬
changed views and discussed
ways of using television for
educational and cultural pur¬
poses.
YOUNG COMMUNITY
BUILDERS: Leaders of
youth, students and young
workers' groups from 20 La¬
tin American countries are
to meet in Havana in Octo¬
ber for discussions on ways
in which young people can
contribute to the life and de¬
velopment of their commu¬
nities. This seminar is be¬
ing held under the auspices
of Unesco.
Jr OLITICAL FREEDOM
FOR WOMEN: The United Na¬
tions Convention on the Poli¬
tical Rights of Women signed
by 35 nations, has now come
into force following its ratifica¬
tion by six countries. It pro¬
vides that women shall be en¬
titled to vote in all elections, to
hold public office and to exer¬
cise all public functions, on
equal terms with men.
CATHOLICISM AND
MARXISM: At a recent
press conference in Madrid,
Dr. Luther H. Evans, Unes¬
co's Director-General, was
asked to comment on whe¬
ther it was true, as some per¬
sons believed, that the orien¬
tation of Unesco was Marxist
and anti-Catholic. Since his
reply was misunderstood by
some members of the press,
it is necessary to give a pre¬
cise statement here of what
was said. Speaking in Eng¬
lish, Dr. Evans replied that
Unesco had no such bias,
that its fundamental prin-
34
ciple was to preach tolerance
in regard to religion, and not
to take part in the conflict
of political ideologies. Dr.
Evans indicated that he be¬
lieved the erroneous impres¬
sion about Unesco's attitude
concerning religious matters
had originated in part with
an essay which Dr. Julian S.
Huxley had published pri¬
vately while serving as the
Organization's first Director-
General. He did not believe,
however, that anyone could
fairly construe Dr. Huxley's
essay as being Marxist in
tone or orientation.
group to make use of new
travel coupons issued by
Unesco. The conference dis¬
cussed contemporary archi¬
tecture, teaching methods,
openings for graduates and
international exchange s.
Purchasers of travel coupons
pay for them in their home
country with their own cur¬
rency and cash them abroad
for the currency of the coun¬
try they are visiting. Italy,
although not one of the ele¬
ven countries officially tak¬
ing part in the travel coupon
plan, agreed to cash the stu¬
dent's coupons.
and 1,343 violation of human
rights on political grounds.
U.S. SENATE APPROVES RATIFICATION OF
UNIVERSAL COPYRIGHT CONVENTION
The Senate of the United States approved on June 25 by a vote of
65 to 3 the ratification of the Universal Copyright Convention which
was adopted in September 1952 by an inter-governmental conference
convened at Geneva under the auspices of Unesco and the Swiss
Government. This Convention will modify in several respects' the
domestic legislation of the countries involved. And in order to permit
these modifications in American law, identical bills were presented
to the Senate and the House of Representatives.
The President of the United States transmitted the Convention to
the Senate last year.' It will devolve upon the President to proclaim
the formal ratification of the Convention by the United States
Government, and to deposit the instruments with the Director-General
of Unesco. At that time, the United States will for the first time have
with the countries of Europe, Asia and Africa multi-lateral links of
considerable importance in regard to the protection of the rights of
writers and artists.
EilUROFE'S NUCLEAR
RESEARCH: " Professor Felix
Bloch, of Stanford University
(U.S.A.), and 1952 Nobel Phy¬
sics prizewinner, has been pro¬
posed "as Director of the Euro¬
pean Nuclear Research Organi¬
zation (CERN) which will build
an international laboratory in
Geneva and promote other
forms of collaboration in this
field. Research at CERN will
be of a non-military character
and its results will be made
freely available. The Conven¬
tion establishing CERN was
signed last year by 12 Unesco
member states. So far, the
United Kingdom, Switzerland,
Denmark, and the Netherlands
have ratified it. Its entry into
force requires ratification by
seven states whose contributions
total 75% of the Organization's
budget. It is expected that Pro¬
fessor BIbch's appointment will
be confirmed by. the Council of
this new organization.
FIRST COUPON TRA¬
VELLERS: Sixty-five stu¬
dents representing France at
an international conference
in Rome formed the first
w,ORLD HOUSING PROB¬
LEM: One hundred and eighty
million families are today with¬
out adequate housing according
to Mr. David A. Morse, Direc¬
tor-General of the International
Labour Organization. Report¬
ing to the ILO annual confer¬
ence, Mr. Morse said: "The
world has now accepted that
starvation and raggedness are
not tolerable as part of the
worker's lot. We have been less
aware of the damage to work¬
ers' health, happiness, efficiency
and citizenship that is done by
the appalling state of housing
in most parts of the world."
HUMAN RIGHTS DE-
ND3D: A confidential list of
communications alleging vio¬
lations of human rights is
regularly submitted to the
United N at ion's Human
Rights Commission meeting
in closed session. The cur¬
rent list contained summa¬
ries of or references to 9,524
communications received be¬
tween March 13 and Decem¬
ber 31, 1953. The great ma¬
jority, 7,850, alleged viola¬
tion of freedom of religion,
Si»TAMPS SPREAD
KNOWLEDGE: "Why throw
away the most instructive of
toys?" asks- a circular sent to
business firms in the Lebanon,
to request them to save stamps,
from their mail each day. This
is part of a campaign started
by the Lebanese "Friends of
Unesco Association" to collect
stamps to help in teaching geo¬
graphy and history in the
schools. In the United States,
the U.N. Postal Administration
is helping to form United Na¬
tions Stamps Clubs whose aim
is to encourage youngsters to
learn about peoples and places
throughout the world through
stamp collecting. Unesco is
awarding a $500 prize for the
design of a postage stamp illus¬
trating its work. Over 200 de¬
signers have been invited by the
UN Postal Administration to
take part in the competition,
result of which will be announc¬
ed in September.
MEET THE SCHOOL:
French schoolchildren have
recently been taking part in
a series of broadcasts in
which individual French
schools have been "introduc¬
ed" to the public. From
these programmes listeners
have learned a great deal
about the history and tradi¬
tions, geographical situations
and attainments in music,
sports and other fields of
their country's schools.
REE FLOW FILMS :
A Unesco-sponsored interna¬
tional agreement removing tariff
and trade barriers to films,
sound recordings and other au¬
dio-visual materials has come
into force after being ratified
by ten countries. Another
Unesco treaty removing tariffs
on books, works of art and a
wide range of educational ma¬
terials, is already bemg operat¬
ed by 17 countries.
RUMANIA AND UNES¬
CO: Rumania has applied
for membership of Unesco.
As this country is not a
member of the United Na¬
tions, its request has first to
be approved by the Econo¬
mic and Social Council of
the United Nations (.ECO¬
SOC). Rumania may then
join Unesco upon recom¬
mendation by Unesco's Exe¬
cutive Board and approval
by a two-thirds majority of
the General Conference.
The Unesco Executive Board
is next meeting in Venice on
July 14, and the General
Conference will hold its next
session in Montevideo, on
November 12.
u
2
<
Z
5
<
z
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
"... a window open on the world" *
The
UNESCO COURIER
COMING - Next Month
PROTECTING OUR CULTURAL HERITAGE
in peace and war a special report.
THE UNTOLD TREASURES OF THE SEA
pageant oí oceanography
GREEN LIGHT FOR EDUCATION
from Afghanistan to the Nile
ASOKA THE ANCIENT INDIAN KING
and a modern science prize
PRESENTING WORLD HISTORY
toning down the "Western accent"
TO SUBSCRIBE
In the United Kingdom send your
remittance to U.M. Stationery Offi¬
ce P.O. Box 569, London S.E. 1.
In other countries write to National
Distributors listed below.
If your country is not listed write
directly to Unesco Sales Division
19, avenue Kléber, Paris, France.
and other interesting features
Reserve your copy NOW by subscribing TODAY
Yearly subscription: 6/-; 300 French francs
or equivalent in local currency.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below. Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P'O.
Box 244, Colombo I. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen. K.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa 2, Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd ,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue
Kléber, Paris- 1 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Inter¬
nationale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kow loon
India : Orient Longmans Ltd. Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co , Sctndia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima-
lay House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.t
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djkarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstei's Bookstores Ltd., 3 5,
Allenby Road. P.O. Box 5154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldtngs.
Japan : Maruzan Co, Inc., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo. ,
Jordan : J. I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Liberia : Jacob Momolu Kamara, Gurly
and Front Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass, 7,
New Zealand : Unesco Publications Centre
7 De Lacy Street, Dunedm, N. E. 2.
Nigeria : C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway :
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B.C.E. Frutes Kungl. Hovbok-
handel Fredgaatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London SEI.
U.S.A. : Columbia University Press, 2960
Broadway, New York.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Copyright Magnum-Cortier-Bresson
A MAJOR VICTORY against educational segreg¬
ation has been won by the U.S. Negro. The elimi¬
nation of housing and employment discrimination
throughout the United States is the next goal set
iy groups working for the advancement of the
American Negro. Here a group of youngsters
plays in a Negro quarter in city of Pittsburgh.
]]>
</page>
</document>
