<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="070464eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
SPECIAL
NUMBER
K° 12
1954
(7th year)
Price : 7d (U. K.)
30 francs (France)
THE
PROMISE
OF ATOMIC POWER
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO Courier
Number 12 - 1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
The Beneficent Atom
4 A TURNING POINT
5 LET'S USE THE ATOM
FOR THE GOOD OF MANKIND
10 THE POWER-PACKED ATOM
It could end the world's shortage of energy
14 HOW NATIONS WILL WORK TOGETHER
U.N. and UNESCO action for global co-operation
15 TRAINING THE KEY MEN FOR THE ATOMIC AGE
19 THE GENERATION OF ATOMIC POWER
Types of reactors and basic facts about the atom
23 EUROPE'S NEW NUCLEAR RESEARCH CENTRE
Giant machines to explore a tiny world
25 RADIO-ISOTOPES
I MEDICINE'S NEW 'MAGIC EYE'
28 II ISOTOPES AND RADIATION HAZARDS
32 III THE WAY TO BIGGER CROPS
38 IV INDUSTRY'S NEW WORKER
41 THE WORLD ATOMIC POWER PICTURE
A review of the most recent developments
48 TOMORROW WILL BE TOO LATE
Learning to live with the atom today
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France.
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronak Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation
Jean Groffier
U.S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not copyrighted may be reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by che following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represenc the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER : 6/-; $ 1.50 or 300 French fn.
MC. 54.1 87. A.
Unesco Courier. Nr 12 1954
THE PROMISE OF
ATOMIC POWER
Looking into the future at a scale model of an
atomic power plant. Scientists consider that
the world's tremendous need for increased
power can be met by such plants, using atomic
fuel converted from the world's reserve of
uranium. This reserve is many times the
energy equivalent of the world reserve of
coal and oil. (Photo USIS).
_§_ or almost ten years the atom has shown an evil face.
Before the General Assembly of the United Nations in
November, it began to show a happier one.
By one of the tragic accidents of history, the discovery
that enormous energy is released when a uranium atom is
split by a neutron came in 1939, just before the outbreak of
the greatest war in history. It was at once used to create
the horrendous succession of bombs which ended that war
and have now made another war almost unthinkable. But
it is the bomb that brings death and destruction, not the
atom. In better times and in wiser hands the energy of the
atom can do far more good than the harm the bomb has
done. Today there is great hope that a better time is at
harfd and that the atom will become a benefactor of humanity.
The use of atomic energy to do the world's work has long
been the dream of scientists. The measure of man's progress
in civilization has been his increased use of energy. But we
still have far to go. A new source of energy that can be used
at any place on earth would benefit the non-industrialized
nations at once and would enable them to develop now the
coal-free and oil-free economy that all nations must sooner
or later adopt.
This is the promise of atomic energy. One pound of ura-
. nium fuel can provide as much energy as 1,300 tons of coal,
yet the coal weighs nearly three million times as much.
Furthermore, atomic fuels have precious by-products in the
radio-active materials, called isotopes, that are produced in
the atomic furnaces. They will almost certainly benefit
mankind as much as will the use of atomic energy itself.
Knowing all these possibilities, scientists the world over
have been dismayed at the restriction of atomic materials to
military use. They expected to avoid further development of
atomic weapons and to stimulate the peaceful uses of atomic
energy for all the world. Nationalism and international
tensions made this impossible.
But a new start now has been made. A proposal was
made by President Eisenhower to the United Nations General
Assembly on December 8, 1953, for international co-operation
in the peaceful development of atomic energy and atomic
materials. Suddenly the great hopes of long ago were
revived by the unanimous adoption of this proposal by the
Political and Security Committee of the General Assembly
on November 23, 1954, and by the General Assembly itself,
also unanimously, on December 4. This makes certain one
great advance : international co-operation in atomic deve¬
lopment under the United Nations. It makes possible
another, equally great : the full use of the atom for the
good of mankind.
This may be a turning point in history. The prospect
needs careful study.. It is not a problem for scientists and
statesmen alone. In a democratic world an understanding
of the atom and its possibilities is necessary for every
literate and thinking person. It will no doubt be quickly
introduced into the schools. But it must also be introduced
into public discussions.
The Unesco Courier, as Unesco's medium of public
information and education, devoted its December issue a year
ago largely to an exposition of the fundamental sciences of
atomic energy. Now, with the assurance of international
action by the United Nations and by Unesco toward the
practical use of atomic power and atomic materials, this
entire issue is devoted to a realistic examination of the facts,
the possibilities, and the prospective consequences of the
beneficent atom.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A TURNING POINT
By Gerald Wendt
THE unanimous vote of the
General Assembly of the United
Nations on December 4, 1954, for
the setting up of an international
atomic energy agency and for a
United Nations conference on the
peaceful uses of atomic energy was
hailed in countries all around the
world.
The problem of making the full use
of the atom for the good of mankind
is not one for scientists and statesmen
alone. Every thinking and literate
person should have an understanding
of the atom and its possibilities. Men
and women everywhere should un¬
derstand the implications of the U.N.
decision, and they should welcome it
with enthusiasm. The reasons, plain
to see, are these:
1 After the years of fixation on
I. weapons and on the chill fear
of destruction, the dark skies broke
and a beam of sunshine brought hope,
if not a promise, of better times to
come. The evil spell of the -atom was
cast off by honest plans for peace and
benefits to humanity from the great
new resource that science had
created. It brought a relief from war
talk, if not an end to it.
2 It was a unanimous vote for
a unanimous benefit. It meant
that all the member states would pro¬
fit together, large and small, east and
west, industrial and agricultural, rich
and poor. And it meant that the
United Nations is a force in being
which can seize upon a great vision
and can act to give it reality. For
once it was not merely a nation or a
power-group but the whole organized
world that agreed to co-operate in
exploring a new road to human
welfare.
3 It is a road that will eventually
lead to a large increase in use¬
ful energy, in power to do the world's
work. And energy creates material
wealth and replaces hard human
labour by leisure and well-being.
4 Just as surely, the by-products
of the atomic furnaces, the ra¬
dio-isotopes, are instruments for the
exploration of nature as powerful as
were the microscope and the telescope
in their early days. Especially in the
revelation of the deep secrets of the
life processes, they will bring a new
era in science and therefore in human
living.
5 In order to achieve these bene-
fits in the nations that are not
now active in the study and produc¬
tion of atomic energy, a major in¬
crease in educational facilities will be
needed. They must be provided in
advance. The production of atomic
energy on a large scale demands
not only highly specialized nuclear
physicists and chemists but also
thousands of engineers, electrical,
civil and mechanical, and many more
skilled workmen to operate and
maintain the reactors, the electrical
generators, the entire electrical dis¬
tribution system and the myriad
motors and electrical machines that
will use the energy. Furthermore, in
order to use radio-isotopes as a
research tool, there will need to be
scientific laboratories, especially in
the biological and medical sciences,
and training schools for the use of the
new techniques in nearly all the
research sciences and in industrial
research. Indeed, in order to provide
training at these levels, the nations
who expect to participate will need a
broad programme of improved ( se¬
condary education, including 'the
provision of modern laboratories and
teaching methods in the secondary
schools. If the atomic energy pro¬
gramme serves as an incentive to
stimulate such programmes of scien¬
tific education in the countries that
do not now have them, this in itself -
will constitute a benefit, quite apart
from the direct benefits from the use
of atomic energy.
6 Finally, the availability of
. ample energy, especially in
lands where power -has been scarce
and industry therefore weak, will
bring a social revolution comparable
with the industrial revolution of a
century and a half ago. The advan¬
ces in agriculture, nutrition, medicine
and health will alone cause rapid so¬
cial changes, even in the industrial
countries. The world has in the past
let such revolutions develop un¬
foreseen, often with disastrous con¬
sequences as well as benefits. This
time we can see it coming. This time
many a people will leap from the age
of bullock-power to the atomic age.
If the prospect is breathtaking, it is
also an inspiring challenge to the
: educators, social scientists, national
planners and governments.
It is because benefits from the in¬
ternational development of atomic
energy are so incalculable and
because the pace at which these
changes will proceed are dependent
on so many factors that the whole
international atomic project deserves
study not only by the international
conference that will be called by the
United Nations in 1955, but by the
informed public in every country.
Much depends on the demand for
energy in various countries, on the
cost of atomic power, on the location
cf atomic reactors, and on the
ability of each country to utilize the
additional energy and the new
knowledge. That is why the reasons
given above for welcoming the U.N.
decision are considered in the sub¬
sequent articles of this series.
* For a biographical note on
Dr. Wendt, the author of the
articles in this issue, see page 50
Let's use
the atom
for the
good of
mankind
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
HISTORIC PROPOSAL for international co-operation in the peaceful
development of atomic energy and atomic materials was made by
President Eisenhower to the United Nations General Assembly, on
December 8, 1953. (Photos, above and inset, show President Eisen¬
hower addressing the General Assembly. Seated behind him are,
left to right: Mr. Dag Hammarskjold, Secretary-General of the United
Nations; Madame Vijaya Lakshmi Pandit, of India, President of the
General Assembly at that time; and Mr. Andrew W. Cordier, Executive
Assistant to the Secretary-General. Just under a year later, on December
4, I 954, the General Assembly unanimously voted for the establishment
of an international atomic energy agency and for a United Nations
conference on the peaceful uses of atomic energy. (U.N. photos)
During the years since the end of
World War II in 1945, the power
of the atom seemed too great
for human wisdom. Developed under
military necessity and regarded in a
time of tension as the supreme weapon,
it forced its sponsors into rivalry and
secrecy. Persistent efforts to abolish
its military use failed for lack of
mutual trust between the nations
involved. Instead, its power grew
under the fierce competition and mul¬
tiplied a thousandfold until, if it were
now used in war, the entire human race
would suffer and perhaps perish.
Meanwhile, any wide use of that great
power for the peaceful work of the
world has been impossible because
relaxation of secrecy also requires in¬
ternational control based on mutual
trust. So the world stood still while
the evil grew.
Door to the future
Then, on December 8, 1953, the Pre¬
sident of the United States ad¬
dressed the General Assembly of
the United Nations and opened a new
door to the future. He said in part:
"The United States knows that if
the fearful trend of atomic military
build-up can be reversed, this great
est of destructive forces can be deve¬
loped into a great boon, for the henefit
of all mankind. The United States
knows that peaceful power from atomic
energy is no dream of the future.
That capability, already proved, is
here now today. Who can. doubt, if
the entire body of the world's scientists
and engineers had adequate amounts
of fissionable material with which to
test and develop their ideas, that this
capability would rapidly be transformed
into universal, efficient, and economic
usage?
"To hasten the day when fear of the
atom will begin to disappear from the
minds of the peoples and the govern¬
ments of the East and West, there are
certain steps that can be taken now.
"I therefore make the following pro¬
posal:
"The governments principally involv¬
ed, to the extent permitted by elemen¬
tary prudence, to begin now and conti¬
nue to make joint contributions from
their stockpiles of normal uranium
and fissionable materials to an inter¬
national atomic energy agency. We
would expect that such an agency
would be set up under the aegis of the
United Nations...
"Undoubtedly, initial and early
contributions to this plan would be
small in quantity. However, the pro¬
posal has the great virtue that it can
be undertaken without irritations and
mutual suspicions incident to any
attempt to set up a completely accept¬
able system of world-wide inspection
and control."
Protecting the ' bank '
çç r-pi he atomic energy agency", said
I the President, "could be made
responsible for impounding,
storage, and protection 'of the contri¬
buted fissionable and other materials.
The ingenuity of our scientists will
provide special safe conditions under
which such a bank of fissionable ma¬
terial could be made essentially im¬
mune to surprise seizure.
"The more important responsibility
of this atomic energy agency would be
to devise methods whereby this fission¬
able material would be allowed to serve
the peaceful pursuits of mankind.
"Experts would be mobilized to apply
atomic energy to the needs of agricul¬
ture, medicine, and other peaceful
activities. A special purpose would be
to provide abundant electrical energy
(Cont'd on next page)
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Pool i ng atomic
knowledge (Cont'd)
in the power-starved areas of the
world. Thus the contributing powers
would be dedicating some of their
strength to serve the needs rather than
the fears of the world.
"The United States would be more
than willing it would be proud to
take up with others 'principally involv¬
ed the development of plans whereby
such peaceful use of atomic energy
would be expedited.
"Of those 'principally involved' the
Soviet Union must, of course, be one.
"I would be prepared to submit to
the U.S. Congress, and with every
expectation of approval, any such plan
that would:
First. Encourage world-wide in¬
vestigation into the most effective
peace-time uses of fissionable mate¬
rial.
Second. Begin to diminish the
potential destructive power of the
world's stockpiles.
Third. Allow all peoples of all na¬
tions to see that, in this enlightened
age, the great powers of the earth,
both of the East and of the West, are
interested in human aspirations, first
and foremost, rather than in building
up the armaments of war.
Fourth. Open up a new channel
for peaceful discussion and initiate at
least a new approach to the many
difficult problems that must be solved
in both private and public conferences
if the world is to shake off the inertia
imposed by fear and make positive
progress toward peace.
"Against the dark background of the
atomic bomb, the United States does
not wish merely to present strength,
but also the desire and hope for
peace."
A fearful dilemma
This effort to help solve the fearful
atomic dilemma at once inspired
new hope in the hearts of many
nations. In the British House of Com¬
mons, Sir Winston Churchill said that
he considered the speech as one of the
most important events in world history
since the war and referred to it as pos¬
sibly "a turning point in our destiny".
The speech was, however, but a first
step and not a complete solution. In¬
deed, the Soviet delegate, the late
Andrei Y. Vishinsky, soon pointed out
that it did not mention banning of
atomic weapons, would involve only a
small part of the existing atomic ma¬
terials, and, in effect, merely transfer¬
red the. discussion to a new aspect of
the problem. But in most nations this
was nevertheless considered a major
step in advance. Mrs. Vij aya Lakshmi
Pandit of India, then President of the
United Nations General Assembly,
stated that "the proposal was of the
highest importance and deserves the
careful consideration of all the gov¬
ernments of the world. It is something
my country welcomes."
Months of careful consideration by
governments, scientists and leaders of
thought raised no doubts as to the
value of atomic energy in the peaceful
ways of life. The questions related
only to the other and deeper purpose
of the proposal: the extent of interna¬
tional co-operation. Did it mean an
international "pool" of atomic mate¬
rials? If so, which nations would
contribute and which receive? Did it
mean that an international staff in an
agency of the United Nations would be
in charge of operations and research?
If so, from which nations would they
come and how would their expert secret
knowledge be safeguarded? Above all,
did the proposal imply any reduction
of atomic armaments?
This last point was the major ques¬
tion raised by the Soviet Government
on December 21, 1953, in stating that
its attitude was: "to turn this great
discovery of the human mind not
against civilization, but for its thor¬
ough progress; not for mass extermi¬
nation of people, but for their peaceful
needs; for thorough safeguarding and
raising the welfare of the population."
(Cont'd on page 8)
ÛTflMIP PíllAiTR FílR PFflPF is symbo,ized ¡n the coat of arms adopted
nlUlTlIU rUVlLK füll iCntlL by Britain's newly created Atomic Energy
Authority. Savage heraldic animals chained to the earth represent the power of
the atom brought under control. The stars on each animal having a total of 92 points,
symbolize uraniumNo. "92" in the list of chemical elements. Inverted triangle
on the shield is a heraldic symbol called a "pile" the first name for an atomic reactor
or power furnace. The zig-zag lines represent the electricity developed from
atomic energy. On top of the helmet, which is a symbol of co-operation, a
sun signifies the benign power of the atom. The bird inside is a sign taken from the
crest of the late Lord Rutherford, one of the world's most distinguished pioneers
in nuclear research. The motto chosen by the Atomic Energy Authority, which
forms part of this coat of arms, means : " The most from the smallest."
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
? lâ -¿ ATOMIG POWERHOUSES
A few months ago the Soviet authorities announced
that the world's first electric power station to make
use of atomic energy had begun operating in the
U.S.S.R. on June 27, 1954. The plant, with an output
of 5,000 kilowatts, provides electricity for neighbour¬
ing industrial and agricultural installations. Soviet
scientists and engineers, it was also stated, are working
on the construction of other atomic power plants
whose outputs range from 50,000 to 100,000 kilo¬
watts. Drawing on left, taken from " Teknika Molo-
dieji ", (a Russian popular science and technology
magazine for young people) represents " one type
of electric power station using nuclaar energy.
The key accompanying the drawing describes the
different elements as follows : (I) atomic reactor
(2) heat exchanger (3) steam condenser (4) main
steam pipes (5) condenser pumps (6) turbo-generator
(7) cooling towers (8) water cooling tank (9) transfor¬
mer station (10) pumping station (II) workshops
( 1 2) stores ( I 3) administrative buildings. Other coun¬
tries, in particular the United States, and Britain,
have for some time past been working on projects
to use heat provided by atomic reactors to generate
electricity. On September 6, 1954, work was
begun on a commercial atomic power plant in Pennsyl¬
vania that is expected to provide electricity for
100,000 people. Artist's sketch (below) shows how
two nuclear reactors might be used to produce elec¬
trical power from atomic energy. Such an arran¬
gement might be one of the applications leading from
an experimental programme now underway in the
United States. Atomic fission in reactors, (centre,
and lower centre) would produce heat which would
be transferred by liquid sodium through primary and
secondary coolant systems to produce steam in the
steam generators, (right). Steam would be used to
power turbo-generators, (top) to produce electri¬
city. About 200,000 kilowatts of electricity could
be generated. (Photo North American Aviation, Inc.)
COOLING TOWERS
STEAM GENERATORS
SECONDARY COOLANT
SYSTEM
U.S.A.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Pooling atomic
knowledges co ntc/j ^
THE UNITED NATIONS SCENE: Architectural and
decorative beauty of the world's "workshop for peace"
United Nations Headquarters in New York is high¬
lighted by photographs on these pages. (U.N. photos)
The Soviet Government expressed its
readiness to take- part in negotiations
on the United States proposal but
would expect that a proposal of its
own would be considered at the same
time, namely that:" The States taking
part in the agreement, guided by their
wish for reducing international ten¬
sion, undertake solemn and uncondi¬
tional pledges not to use atomic,
hydrogen or other weapons of mass
extermination."
This disarmament proposal would
return the discussion to the military
area where no progress had been found
possible in seven years and which the
United States had tried to avoid. Thus
sentiment grew in the United States to
proceed without Soviet participation.
Mr. David Lilienthal, a private citi¬
zen but also the former chairman of
the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission,
for instance, suggested, late in Decem¬
ber, that there was no time to be lost,
that a United Nations agency could
have the plan in operation by August
1954, preferably with Soviet participa¬
tion but, if necessary, without.
He proposed that an experimental
power plant be located- at Brussels and '
an international atomic research cen¬
tre at Geneva. He listed the possible
participants as Great Britain and the
United States, which have stocks of
high-energy or "fissionable" materials;
Canada, Belgium and Australia, which
have large quantities of natural ura¬
nium; Brazil and India because they
have large deposits of thorium which
can also be converted into atomic fuel;
Norway, Holland and France, which
have a supply of radio-active materials
for research and highly competent
leaders in the atomic sciences.
But private discussions between the
U.S. and the Soviet Governments
continued from January 2 until March
19, 1954, when the U.S. proposals took
a more definite form in a memorandum
from the U.S. Secretary of State to the
U.S.S.R. Ambassador at Washington.
They included:
Formation of an international atomic
energy agency "under the terms of a
treaty among the participating nations"
which would be financed by contribu
tions from the member states; its faci¬
lities would include storage of nuclear
materials, control laboratories, admi¬
nistrative offices and such facilities
"as might in time be necessary" for
education and training, research and
development, fuel fabrication and che¬
mical processing!
Again the weeks passed until in April
and early May, Soviet Foreign Minister
Vyacheslav M. Molotov and U.S. Secre¬
tary of State John Foster Dulles
conferred at Geneva and again failed
to agree on the prohibition of atomic
weapons as a preliminary to the estab¬
lishment of the atomic power agency.
This question was then referred to a
new sub-committee of the United Na¬
tions Disarmament Commission which
met; without result in London in
May. This seemed to mark the end of
President Eisenhower's proposal to the
United Nations as well as the failure
of the Soviet effort for atomic disarm¬
ament.
As a result, American thought turned
again to the development of peace¬
ful atomic power without Soviet co¬
operation and even without the United
Nations. An emissary of the Atomic
Energy Commission visited Brazil, Uru¬
guay, Peru and Chile in August to
discuss the feasibility of small atomic
power plants in those countries.
On September 6, President Eisenhow¬
er participated in the start of con¬
struction on a commercial atomic power
plant in Pennsylvania that is expected
to provide electricity for 100,000 people.
On this occasion he announced that
the United States had agreed with "a
number of other nations to go ahead
now with the formation of an interna¬
tional agency which will foster the
growth and spread of the new atomic
technology for peaceful use... We hope
that no nation will long stand aloof
from the work of this agency."
The President mentioned negotia¬
tions to this end as beginning with Ca¬
nada and Belgium and the press re¬
ported that Britain, Australia, South
Africa and France were also included.
It was widely noted, however, that
there had been no mention of the
United Nations. Three days later,
Admiral Lewis S. Strauss, Chairman of
the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission,
stated that the United States was
preparing to call an international
conference of nuclear scientists in 1955
in which all interested countries,
including the Soviet Union, would be
invited to participate.
But on September 23, Secretary Dulles
again appealed to the United Nations
General Assembly in these words:
"The United States Is determined
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
that President Eisenhower's proDOsal
shall not languish until it dies. We
are determined that it shall be nurtur¬
ed and developed. And we shall press
on in close partnership with those na¬
tions which, inspired by the ideals of
the United Nations, can make this
great new force a tool of humanitarian-
ism and of statesmanship and not
merely a fearsome addition to the ar¬
senal of war.
United States is here proposing
an agenda item which will enable us to
report further on our efforts to explore
and to develop the vast possibilities for
the peaceful uses of atomic energy.
These efforts have been and will be
directed primarily toward the follow¬
ing ends:
(1) The creation of an international
agency, whose initial membership will
include nations from all regions of the
world. And it is hoped that such an
agency will start its work as early as
next year.
(2) The calling of an international
scientific conference to consider this
whole vast subject, to meet in the
spring of 1955, under the auspices of
the United Nations.
(3) The opening early next year, in
the United States, of a reactor training
school where
students- from
abroad may
learn the
working p r i n -
ciples of atomic
energy with
specific regard to
its peacetime
uses.
(4) The invi¬
tation to a
substantial
number of me¬
dical and sur¬
gical experts
from abroad to
participate in the
work of our
cancer hospitals
in which atomic
energy tech¬
niques are among
the most hopeful
approaches to
controlling this
menace to
mankind. "I
would like to
make it perfectly clear that our plann¬
ing excludes no nation from partici¬
pation in this great venture. As our
proposals take shape, all nations inter¬
ested in participating and willing to
take on the responsibilities of mem¬
bership will be welcome to join with
us in the planning and the execution
of this programme."
The response to the American
proposal before the General Assembly
was immediate and favourable. After
almost ten months of delay, -during
which the fear of the atom had grown
throughout the world, the members of
the Assembly showed eagerness to
make a start in the opposite direction.
On the following day, Mr. Vishinsky
expressed the approval of the Soviet
Delegation for incorporating the Ame¬
rican statement in the agenda and
asked for unanimous approval by the
General Assembly in favour of studying
the United States proposal. The report
mentioned by Mr. Dulles was immedia¬
tely referred to the Political and Secur¬
ity Committee of the General Assem¬
bly. In a few days, a number of nations
endorsed the U.S. proposal.
Then, on October 1, a study of the
proposal was begun by a special UN
committee, headed by Dr. Ralph J.
Bunche, who has been named as Un¬
der-Secretary of the U.N. Secretariat.
At the same time, Mr. Henry Cabot
Lodge, Jr., permanent U.S. represent¬
ative at the United Nations, said at a
press conference that the United States
would submit a resolution to the Gene¬
ral Assembly asking the United Nations
to call a conference of scientists and
others to settle the details of the new
agency. He said that the United States
would suggest that the entire pro¬
gramme be placed in the hands of a
new agency similar to the World Health
Organization, for instance, which would
decide on its own relations with the
United Nations.
On November 5, Mr. Lodge addressed
the Political and Security Committee
to propose the organization of such an
agency. A draft of the resolution was
submitted jointly by Australia, Belgium,
Canada, France, South Africa, Britain
and the United States. The resolution
suggested that a technical conference
be held not later than August 1955 at a
place to be selected by the Secretary-
General and an advisory committee.
On November 12, Mr. Vishinsky ad¬
dressed the Com¬
mittee and stat¬
ed that he would
vote for the reso¬
lution provided
the proposed in¬
ternational agen¬
cy were placed
under the U.N.
Security Council
instead of having
the separate
status of a spe¬
cialized agency.
This was on the
ground that the
production of
atomic materials
for peaceful pur¬
poses would in¬
crease the amount
available for
weapons and that
the production
of radio-isotopes
would itself have
military impor¬
tance.
This Soviet pro¬
posal lead to further long discussions.
Unexpected action by the United
States on November 15 had the effect
of bringing the discussion to a conclu¬
sion. On that day, Mr. Lodge told the
Political and Security Committee that
the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission
had allocated 100 kilogrammes (220 lbs)
of fissionable material for use by the
proposed international agency. This
material could be used in a considerable
number of small experimental atomic
reactors, but it could not be put to use
in the form of weapons.
On the next day, Anthony Nutting,
Head of the British Delegation to the
General Assembly, announced that the
British Government would hold avail¬
able 20 kilogrammes (44 pounds) to be
used by the international agency as
fuel in experimental atomic reactors.
The composition of the advisory com¬
mittee for the creation of the interna¬
tional agency was announced as: Uni¬
ted States, Soviet Union, Britain,
France, Canada, Brazil and India, and
Mr. Vishinsky accepted for the U.S.S.R.
the invitation to serve on this com
mittee. This was taken to mean that
the Soviet Union would participate in
the conference planned for 1955.
Finally,- on November 23, the Political
and Security Committee of the United
Nations voted unanimously to endorse
the proposal as made by the seven
nations: United States, Britain, France,
Canada, Australia, Belgium and South
Africa. The resolution thus unani¬
mously carried expresses the hope that
"international co-operation in develop¬
ing and expanding the peaceful uses
of atomic energy will assist in lifting
the burdens of hunger, poverty and di¬
sease" and suggests that "once the
agency is established, it negotiate an
appropriate form of agreement with
the United Nations, similar to those of
the Specialized Agencies".
respect to the international
conference on the peaceful uses of ato¬
mic energy, the decision was made that
"an international technical conference
should be held under the auspices of
the United Nations" in which all Mem¬
ber States of the United Nations or of
the Specialized Agencies would be invi¬
ted to participate "in order to explore
the means of developing the peaceful
uses of atomic energy through interna¬
tional co-operation, to study the deve¬
lopment of atomic power", and to
consider related questions in the tech¬
nical areas and fundamental sciences.
The resolution requested the Secre¬
tary-General to call such a conference
not later than August 1955, and sugges¬
ted preliminary consultations "with
the competent specialized agencies, in
particular fao, who and unesco".
One final formal action was needed,
namely the approval of this committee
action by the entire membership of the
General Assembly. This was done by
unanimous vote on December 4, just
under a year after President Eisen¬
hower made his historic proposal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
THE POWER-PACKED ATOM
It could end the world's shortage of energy
RAW MATERIAL of ato¬
mic energy is plentiful in
France. Here official of the
French Atomic Energy Com¬
missariat is examining a
"sample of pitchblende (ura¬
nium bearing ore). Map
behind him shows locations
of uranium deposits. These
deposits in France as well
as others of thorium and
beryllium in Madagascar have
been important factors in the
development of France's
atomic energy programme.
As a man needs food to stay alive,
so modern urban, civilized living
demands energy for its sus¬
tenance. Energy is hard to define,
since it is not a thing and has no size
or weight. It is the basis of action, the
capacity for doing work. It is the
difference between an object in motion
and one at rest, the difference between
hot, expanding steam and cold water,
between coal that can burn and rocks
that cannot.
In each case the first material con¬
tains energy which it loses in action.
Invisible and intangible, energy is res
ponsible for anything and everything
that happens in the universe.
Men and animals get energy from the
food they eat. In a primitive society
that energy is enough for a day's work,
but in most parts of the world a man
can barely support himself and his
family by the work of his own muscles.
A horse, camel or bullock increases his
production and his wealth. In an
organized society, light and warmth,
transportation and manufacturing
must all be supplied from fuels, the
wind, or energy from the sun. The
more industrial a society is, the more
it needs energy and the "development"
of a country requires first of all a
supply of energy.
A pound of bread or of rice provides
about 1,200 calories to the human body.
Two or three pounds of food a day
2,500 to 3,000 caloriesfurnish the
energy that is needed for an ordinary
day's work. This, plus a little more
for cooking or for warmth, is enough
for a simple life. But an industrialized
country needs far more energy.
In the U.S.A., for instance, the total
for each person is 172,000 calories per
day. This is almost sixty times the
THE BEST SAMPLES of uranium
ore can be selected by exposing them
to ultra-violet rays. Here (photo
above) a sample of uranium ore is
shown as it appears in ordinary light.
Subjected to ultra-violet rays (photo
right) it gives off a strong lumino¬
sity which is proportional to the
quality of the uranium it contains.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 12. 1954
energy that a man generates, so that
in such countries every man, woman
and child has the equivalent of sixty
labourers working for him.
In the discussion oí the United
Nations project for the use of atomic
energy, M. Jules Moch, French delegate
and former Minister of the Interior,
discussed the growing need for energy
in all the countries of the earth. In
the major industrial countries the use
of power doubled during the first third
of this century and at present is about
half a horsepower per
person. In the U.S.A
the power used in fac¬
tories, excluding trans¬
portation and motors,
was only 0.19 horse¬
power per person in
1909 but 0.50 horse¬
power in 1950. This is
approximately 400 times
the power demand in
the underdeveloped ter¬
ritories of Asia, Africa
and America.
For the world as a
whole, the average use
for power per man is
now only one sixth of
that in the U.S.A.
Hence if the industria¬
lization of the rest of
the world is to reach
the level prevalent in
North America, the
total energy available
will have to be multi¬
plied at least six times
over. Expressed in
terms of coal, the pro¬
duction would have to
be increased from 2,500
million tons to 15,000
million tons per year.
The average American
uses 8 tons of coal a
year, the European, 2.2,
whereas the man in a
practically underdeve¬
loped country only
makes use of 0 02 tons.
This is another way of
saying that the most
industrialized countries
use 400 times as much
energy per person as
developed.
If the world's consumption of fuels
were doubled, to say nothing of being
multiplied sixfold, our underground
resources would soon prove inadequate.
The oil and natural gas will last for
only decades and the coal for some
centuries. Yet in the industrial coun¬
tries the coal of high quality that is
easily mined is already becoming
exhausted, so that at best the cost of
coal will increase and its quality will
decrease. For this reason far-seeing
engineers are gravely concerned over
the future of the industries that depend
on underground fuels.
But what is more important is the
striking disparity in the coal resources
available in different countries. An
industrial future is hardly possible for
countries that have little coal or oil.
To transport a hundred million tons of
coal for thousands of miles would incur
a cost of a thousand million dollars for
freight alone. It is a prohibitive cost.
It is for this reason that the newly
created resource of atomic energy is
attractive. If the atom can be
harnessed to provide the energy, the
PROBING NATURE'S SECRETS: One day energy from the atom wrll help to ease
the dram on such natural fuels as oil, coal and natural gas, on which the demands of industry
and modern life are making ever-greater inroads. In the meantime scientists are experi¬
menting with the production of synthetic fuels. Here, two scientists of the Gulf Oil
Company, in Pennsylvania, probe into the still mysterious reaction by which petrol is
made from coal. They use radio-isotopes as "tracers". (Photo, Gulf Oil Co.)
do the least industrialized countries need not fear
the increasing cost and decreasing
supply of coal. The countries that
have no coal can hope to compete at
once even if its cost is higher than the
present cost of energy in the industrial
countries.
A striking example is the situation
of so highly industrial a country as
Switzerland. The economy of that
country is based on water power
generated from the ample Alpine
streams. Yet Switzerland faces a
future in which this power will not be
enough to meet its needs.
Recently, Mr. Alfred Winiger de¬
scribed the situation to representatives
of Swiss electrical industries. He fore¬
sees a continuing increase in the de¬
mand for energy of about 3.8 % per
year. On the basis of this estimate he
concludes that : "By 1975 the demand
for energy in Switzerland will no lon¬
ger be met by our hydraulic resources,
which are today used at 50 % of the to¬
tal available. According to circumstan¬
ces, we should have new sources of
energy at our disposal between 1970
and 1975 if we wish to avoid being too
dependent on foreign sources for our
energy requirements.
"Taking these fac¬
tors into consideration,
it is quite logical that
we should turn to nu¬
clear reactors for our
future source of energy.
We should then conti¬
nue to depend on for¬
eign sources for the
delivery of atomic fuel,
but, on the other hand,
the cost of transport of
the fuel, which at pre¬
sent weighs heavily on
our economy, should
be virtually eliminated.
In effect, a ton of ura¬
nium, used to the
maximum, produces as
much heat as 3 million
tons of coal. To trans¬
port this coal from the
mines of the Ruhr to
Zurich would alone cost
nearly 120 million Swiss
francs, plus the cost of
storage. The saving in
transport costs would
permit us to lighten
considerably our ba¬
lance of payments
abroad."
M. Jules Moch, speak¬
ing to the General As¬
sembly of the United
Nations said:
"These considerations
point out the direction
to be taken by human
effort. If the standard
of living of the under¬
developed majority of
mankind is to be in¬
creased and if the standard of living
of the industrialized minority is to be
maintained and improved man must
and soon exploit new power resources
The achievement of that goal is, in the
last analysis, the very condition of
social progress.
"Does atomic energy offer a solution
to this problem of replacing exhausted
or decreasing power resources? Theo¬
retically, this is no' doubt true... The
total annihilation of a gramme of
material, any material, would release
the power equivalent to that released
by the burning -of 20 million tons of
coal. The present needs of all
mankind, -counted in millions of tons
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ENOUGH FUEL FOR
CENTURIES (cont'd)
PROSPECTOR of the atomic
age uses a' Geiger-Muller
counter an instrument
which measures intensity of
rays given off by radio-active
substances to detect the
presence of uranium-bear¬
ing ores. (Photo USIS.)
of coal, would thus be realized by the
disintegration of 300 pounds of matter.
"However, we do not yet know how
completely to annihilate a particle of
matter and turn it into energy. Per¬
haps not even our descendants will
know how to do so. The phenomenon
of fission obliterates less than one-
thousandth part of the materials
involved. The phenomenon of fusion,
if it could be carried out in a slowed-
down manner, would bring about the
disappearance of less than a hundr¬
edth part of the materials involved.
"We should therefore have to subject
to fission masses of material one
thousand times larger than the
quantities I have just mentioned in
order to produce the same amount of
energy and power. In other words, we
would have to operate in terms of tons
rather than in terms of pounds. In
fact, still speaking theoretically, it
would be necessary to bring about the
fission of 130 long tons of uranium 235,
rather than 300 pounds to produce the
equivalent of the energy produced by
the burning of 2,500 million tons of
coal.
"Let us suppose that fission becomes
industrially feasible in a number of
years. It is not so today and... we have
still a few years to go. Let us also
assume that a procedure can be used
that is still in the experimental stage,
the "breeder" procedure (see page 21).
Let us also suppose that the output of
this operation in a certain number of
years reached 50 per cent efficiency,
under these conditions the reaction
would have to use 300 tons of material
per year in order to produce the total
power now being used. However, since
URANIUM MINE near Limouzat, France, is one of several
being worked by the Research and Mining Operations Branch
of the French Atomic Energy Commissariat (C.E.A.). Uranium
has been known since 1789 when a German chemist, Martin
Klaproth, discovered an oxide of this element and named it
after the planet Uranus. But a French chemist, Eugène Péligot,
¡n 1841, was the first to isolate pure uranium.
EXTRACTION TOWER at a uranium mine in the Puy-de-
Dôme, Central France. Here the ore is brought to the surface
and transported by cable car to nearby processing plant. In
its pure form uranium is a white metallic element, slightly softer
than steel and more than I 8 times as heavy as water. It occurs
widejy in the earth's crust, though most minerals contain only
a small proportion of the element.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. W 12. 1954
we cannot hope for such technical
progress except after a lapse of a
number of years, we must envisage a
doubling of the power' consumption
over the same period, and it would be
necessary to have natural uranium at
our disposal, as well as thorium, at the
rate of 600 tons per year.
"And finally, in order to give the
peoples of the world the American level
of industrialization, the quantity re¬
quired would be almost 4,000 tons per
annum. Since fruitful breeder ma¬
terials are involved, these figures can
be reached without any insurmountable
difficulties, but the technical pro-
to all peoples. In the same manner,
the portable reactors now being built
in America which are known by the
striking and expressive name of "power
package" constitute a happy augury
for the international proletarization, if
I may so call it, of power to be placed
at the disposal of mankind.
"One hurdle remains, and that is the
question of cost. It is certainly rash to
prophesy, since we do not know the cost
oi atomic power production in large
central plants which would utilize
breeder and fissionable materials at
the same time. We do not know to
what point the progressive exhaustion
ORE -WASHING
MACHINE in ura¬
nium processing
plant at Láchaux,
Centrai France. Un¬
like most metals
uranium is not ex¬
tracted by smelting
the ore, but by
putting it through
series of processes,
involving dissolv¬
ing, filtering and
precipitation, dur¬
ing which the wan¬
ted elements are
separated from the
unwanted. Finally
the uranium is
brought down to a
solid salt and from
this it can be redu¬
ced to a metal.
M.JULES MOCH
of France, told the
U. N. General As¬
sembly that in theo¬
ry atomic energy
can solve the pro¬
blem of replacing
exhausted or de¬
creasing power re¬
sources, but that
transition from the
classical power era
to that of atomic
energy would be
gradual and prolong¬
ed. (U. N. photo.)
May 1953. In England, the cost of
electric current over the same period
was .8 cents and the price at which it
was sold to industry was between 1.1
and 1.3 cents per kilowatt hour. I
shall not cite the French figures,
because we are rather poorly endowed
so far as power costs and power
resources are concerned. It might be
hoped that in the near future a cost
of .7 cents or .ßVents per kilowatt hour
could be achieved by means of atomic
energy if such projects were realized in
conformity with the hopes of their
sponsors, and it might be supposed that
atomic energy would rapidly competo
with conventional energy sources, even
in those countries where the latter are
low in cost.
"The ease of transportation... would
give atomic energy this rare virtue of
being saleable everywhere at the same
prices or at just about the same prices.
cedures must still be perfected and,
therefore, the general use of atomic
energy by this process, which as yet
has not been fully explored can be
carried out only gradually.
"Let us, therefore, forego any exag¬
gerated hopes. And here we come to
the core of the problem. The ad¬
vantages of this process, as regards the
underdeveloped areas of the world, are
incalculable. The 600 tons of uranium
which I previously envisaged would
correspond to a doubling of today's
consumption of fuel, equivalent to the
consumption of 5,000 million tons of
coal. With an extraction rate of 1 per
cent of metal, the 600 tons of uranium
would require 60,000 tons of ore, which
is a tonnage 80,000 times less than that
of the coal that would be required to
produce the same energy.
"The transition from the thermal era
to the atomic era would thus take the
form of a reduction, by a ratio of 80,000
to 1, of the weight of the. materials or
ores to be extracted, and a reduction of
100 times larger would make the ratio
8 million to 1 in the weight of the fuel
to be transported from the mine to the
furnace. Atomic power thus appears
to be easily dispersable and transferable
into regions lacking in other resources.
"This sort of dissemination doubtless
would spell immense social progress in
making available large power resources
METALLIC URA¬
NIUM being pro¬
duced in a plant at
Bouchet, r\ear Pa¬
ris. The solid ura¬
nium compound,
now highly purified,
is mixed with chips
of calcium metal in
a mould and fired,
and thus reduced to
a metal. The metal
reduction process,
one phase of which
is shown here, is one
of the most strik¬
ing aspects of ura¬
nium production.
(Photos C. E. A.)
of coal and of oil resources will raise
the price of conventional power
sources. Comparisons of future prices
are still impossible, and we must there¬
fore limit ourselves to the present day,
even though we are fully aware that
the present data will not apply
tomorrow.
"Today, the cost of power produced
in large American power plants using
coal is in the region of .4 cents per
kilowatt hour. The average for other
countries is between .5 and .6 cents per
kilowatt hour, according to the study
carried out by Professor Weinberg in
It would therefore be the main power
resource of countries where con¬
ventional power sources are scarce or
costly, that is to say, essentially in most
of the under-developed areas of the
globe. Perhaps an international orga¬
nization, prompted by some feeling of
international solidarity, might assign
some sort of priority to the latter areas.
"But even if atomic energy were to
become competitive, the fact would
remain that the transition from the
classical power era to the atomic power
era will be a gradual and prolonged
one."
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
HOW NATIONS WILL WORK TOGETHER
"The entire world will
rejoice", said Dr. Eelco
N. Van Kleffens, Presi¬
dent of the U. N. Gene¬
ral Assembly, comment¬
ing on the decision which
opened the way to inter¬
national co-operation
in the use of the atom.
ON December 4, 1954, the atomic age entered into a new and promising phase.
Meeting in New York on that day, the General Assembly of the United Nations
unanimously adopted a seven-nation resolution for the international develop¬
ment of atomic energy for peaceful uses and expressed the hope that an international
atomic energy agency would be set up without delay.
About the same time, the General Conference of Unesco, meeting in Montevideo,
had proposals from India, France and Japan to undertake studies on atomic energy,
isotopes and radiation effects. It delayed action, however, until the United Nations'
decision had been made, then adopted a programme to accord with it. "This is a
matter of momentous importance", said Dr. Luther Evans, Unesco's Director-General,
"Unesco must respond to this great opportunity".
A full account of the United Nations action and the discussion that preceded it
is given in the article on page 5 of this issue. Here are the main features of the
projects adopted by the United Nations and by Unesco :
THE UNITED NATIONS
Two separate projects are authorized,
not formally connected with each other :
The International Atomic Energy Agency
This 'will be organized in joint discussions between the
seven nations who sponsored the U.N. resolution : Australia,
Belgium, Canada, France, Great Britain, South Africa, and
the United States, and others that desire to join. All states
that are members of the United Nations or of one of the
Specialized Agencies will be eligible to membership. It will be
financed by its member states, as are the existing Specializ¬
ed Agencies such as the Food and Agriculture Organization
in Rome, the World Health Organization in Geneva, and
Unesco in Pans. Once established, it will negotiate an
appropriate form of agreement with the United Nations, and
it is thus expected to become one of the Specialized Agencies.
As conceived by the General Assembly the agency will
act as international broker for the allocation of fissile, or
atomic-energy materials, and will study and supervise the
world-wide use of atomic energy for industrial power and
of atomic materials and isotopes for research and scientific
applications. It may also undertake the training of spe¬
cialists in nuclear science. Its work will be related to that
of the atomic energy commissions of member states, the
European Centre for Nuclear Research in Geneva, and the
existing Specialized Agencies of the United Nations.
Conference on Peaceful Uses of Atom
The Secretary-General of the United Nations will call an
international conference to be held not later than August
1955, to "explore means of developing the peaceful uses of
atomic energy through international co-operation and, in par¬
ticular, to study the development of atomic power and to
consider other technical areas such as biology, medicine,
radiation protection, and fundamental science in which
international co-operation might most effectively be
accomplished.
The Secretary-General will have the advice of a committee
composed of representatives of Brazil, Canada, France, India,
the U.S.S.R., the United Kingdom and the U.S.A. in selecting
the place of meeting, in issuing invitations, and in prepar¬
ing a detailed agenda for the conference. The Specialized
Agencies, in particular Fao, Who, and Unesco, will be con¬
sulted in connexion with the planning of the conference and
will be represented at it.
The conference will cover" the wide variety of topics that
are touched by this new phase of science, including those
discussed in the articles in this issue of the Unesco Courier.
It may discuss the functions of the international atomic
energy agency. But the agency does not need to await the
report of the conference and there is some international ,
enthusiasm for the establishment of the agency in the
immediate future, well before August.
14
UNESCO
Unesco's own function ¡n support of the United Nations'
atomic energy programme has three phases :
Research Co-operation
Unesco is the United Nations Specialized Agency especially
responsible for the promotion of international co-operation
in science, and in particular for research and training and
the diffusion of scientific knowledge. It was responsible for
the establishment of the European Centre for Nuclear
Research and will now assist in the preparation of the scien¬
tific aspects of the international conference. Unesco will
also assist other U.N. Specialized Agencies, such as the World
Health Organization, in studying the effects of radio-activity
on life in general. It will continue to study ways of aiding
international scientific co-operation in such questions as
the use of radio-isotopes in research and industry. It may
prepare preliminary reports on scientific subjects that. are
essential to .both the conference and the atomic energy
agency, and will be ready to carry out conference suggestions
relating to international research co-operation.
Scientific Training
The conference and the international atomic energy
agency will certainly provide a stimulus to scientific edu¬
cation and technical training in many parts of the world.
Even in the industrialized nations, there is already a grave
shortage of competent science teachers. The sudden dawn
of an atomic age will create an emergency demand for
vocational training, for science teaching in the secondary
schools and for specialized courses in the universities of
almost all nations. Unesco will expand its services in these
fields, particularly in the underdeveloped countries. It will
hold a workshop conference on vocational training in the
Middle East in 1956. In addition, Unesco will prepare ma¬
nual and visual aids for the introduction of the facts and
concepts of atomic energy, radiation and radio-active
materials into school science teaching.
Public Education
The large public expenditures necessary for the develop¬
ment of atomic power in many nations will demand informed
public support. The fruitful application of the results of
atomic research in agriculture, medicine and industry also
require public understanding. Most of all, the economic
and social consequences of the imminent power-revolution
in countries that have not yet felt the impact of technology
demand foresight in government and a broad incorporation
of science into cultures. The atom can become a friend to
humanity only when it is universally understood and wel¬
comed. Unesco will call two conferences on the public under¬
standing of science, with the participation of national science
associations, science writers, and science teachers. One will
be held in Europe in 1955, the other in Latin America in
1956. The media of public education "will be widely used,
as is exemplified by this issue of the Unesco Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. N' 12. 1954
Training the
technicians
of the new
atomic age
NUCLEAR STUDIES CLASS at Oak Ridge
National Laboratory, U.S.A. (left). Instructor
explains mam features of the Laboratory's
ten-year-old graphite reactor. Since 1948,
Oak Ridge has given instruction courses in
peaceful uses of the atom to well over 1,000
scientists, technicians and engineers both from
the U.S.A. and other countries. The wide appli¬
cation of atomic energy for peaceful purposes
will involve large-scale training of scientists
and engineers, and also broad educational
campaigns to create an understanding of the
atom and its peaceful uses.
Model of the same Oak Ridge reactor (below,
left) has shown people in the United States how
atomic energy is generated, and how radio-iso¬
topes are produced for use in medicine, industry
and agriculture. Sketch (below,) shows some
details of this reactor : (I) Boron steel control
rod (2) Long graphite holders (3) Graphite
moderator in which aluminium rods containing
uranium are inserted. Chain reaction takes
place here (4) Uranium slugs are introduced
here (5) Holes for aluminium tubes (6) Alumi¬
nium tubes containing uranium (7) Graphite
moderator (8) Elevator (9) Graphite reflector
(10) Cooling air circulation space (II) Lead
protective screen (12) Removal of aluminium
tubes containing isotopes (13) Concrete pro¬
tective casing. (Photos USIS).
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The atomic power project of the
United Nations carries a promise
of great and real boons, even of
an effective social revolution in many
lands. But a closer view reveals its
magnitude and complexity. It is not
merely a matter of the distribution of
nuclear' fuels and the building of
atomic furnaces. Those powerful new
forces need to be understood and
managed by many men in many
nations who are fully trained in their
erudite principles and their intricate
and dangerous techniques.
Yet the heritage of war and the
years of secrecy have given only a few
countries adequate knowledge in this
field while most countries
have little or none. It is
obvious that the engineer¬
ing and production opera¬
tions must be preceded by
a period of intensive
training and education in
those countries that are to
participate. Several years
of preparatory education
may well be needed.
Even in the early United
Nations debate this was
made clear by Mr. Paul
Martin, the Canadian de¬
legate, who said:
"The most immediate
need is for information and
training to spread the technology
required for the application of atomic
energy for peaceful purposes on a wide
scale. It would be visionary to
imagine that if by this time next
year the international agency had been
set up it would shortly thereafter be
in a position to start exporting power
reactors, for instance, to various parts
of the world... I say this as plainly as
I can to prevent possible miscon¬
ceptions being followed by a certain
disillusionment.
"The Canadian Government does
hope, however, that the agency,
when established, would assist other
countries participating in the agency's
programme to set up their own
research reactors and to
join with those countries
already possessing them in
pressing forward with the
search for developing ato¬
mic power on an economic
basis and with the whole
range of other actual and
potential applications of
atomic energy for peaceful
purposes.
"And in order to con¬
struct reactors and carry
on useful creative research
in this field, not only is it
necessary to have the
technical information on
the subject much of it
already available but one
must also have scientists,
and technicians trained at least to
some degree in the use and inter¬
pretation of these extremely compli¬
cated research tools.
"For this reason we believe that the
agency not only should foster the in¬
terchange of information on peaceful
uses but should facilitate where
possible the arrangements which will
have to be made for those countries
which wish to set up research reactors
to have their people suitably trained.
The agency should, in fact, encourage
world-wide research and development
and should, in addition, be in a position
to arrange for the nuclear materials
which will be needed for this purpose.
In this connexion I may say that
16
Mr. Paul J. Martin, Cana¬
dian Delegate to the United
Nations General Assembly.
Mr. Henry Cabot Lodge,
Permanent U.S. Represent¬
ative to the United Nations.
engineers
Canada would be a potential source not
only of information but of raw material
and fissile material."
But the United States had an¬
ticipated this need. Mr. Henry Cabot
Lodge, the United States delegate
explained what the United States is
prepared to do in 1955, even in advance
of the establishment of the new
international agency. He said in part:
"No one has to be a scientist to
appreciate the fact that basic to
success in the development and use
of power-producing reactors in any
country is the existence of a body of
trained technical men.
"We are prepared to establish a
reactor training school
early in 1955. The first
course of this school would
deal not only with atomic
power theory, but also with
the application of that
theory. Our present plans
call for inviting between
thirty and fifty scientists
and engineers from over¬
seas to study practical
reactor engineering, in
order to furnish sufficient
basic science and engineer¬
ing knowledge to permit
the members of this group
not only to understand the
theory, but also to become
competent to operate
reactors...
"Second comes the field of safety.
Because we are dealing with a power
which is both a danger and a boon, it
is necessary also that special training
courses in radiation safety and
medicine should be instituted simul¬
taneously with any training in atomic
power development. We propose,
therefore, to establish under the spon¬
sorship of the United States Atomic
Energy Commission the following
courses, vJhich will be open to all other
nations; Industrial Medicinea one-
to-two-year course... concerned with
atomic energy activity; Industrial
Hygienecourses in the techniques of
maintaining healthful conditions in
industries dealing with
hazardous atomic ma¬
terials; Radiological Physics
and the theory and use of
radiation instruments...
"Third in our training
programme comes the vast
field of atomic biology and1
medicine. The A r g o n n e
Cancer Hospital at the
University of Chicago, the
Brookhaven National Labo¬
ratory, and the Cancer
Research Hospital at the
Oak Ridge Institute of
Nuclear Studies will be
open for one to two-year
courses on the use of ato¬
mic energy in medicine
and biology, for approximately five to
ten foreign students per course.
"The field of cancer is so important,
and other countries have made such
strides, that we do not wish to restrict
our collaboration simply to the study of
our techniques. We are therefore
prepared to invite as many as 150
competent and distinguished visitors
in the field of cancer research from
overseas to visit our cancer research
facilities during 1955. These guests
will not only be free to study our
facilities and techniques, but will also
be encouraged to exchange views with
our doctors and scientists.
"Fourth and last in our training
(Cont'd on page 18)
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12 1954
ATOMIC BIOLOGICAL RESEARCH
Recently the United States an¬
nounced that several of its
research centres where atomic
energy is used in biology and
medicine are to be opened to
foreign students. In the vast
field of atomic biology and
medicine, in which training pro¬
grammes are being developed
today, a vital role is played
by radio-isotopes. These are
vital elements both in healing
and research. Photographs on
these pages show examples
.of atomic biological research
whose results will help doctors
in all lands to fight disease. In
the Division of Biological and
Medical Research at the Argonne
National Laboratory, U.S.A., an
X-ray (above, left) shows a bone cancer loca¬
ted on the second lumbar vertebrae of a mo jse.
This is part of an experiment to determine
the levels of various isotopes that, if absorbed
internally in sufficiently large doses, might
ultimately produce cancers or other injury.
The isotope used here is strontium-90 (a
bone seeker). At Brookhaven National Labo¬
ratory, U.S.A., students can follow studies of
nutrition and disease control (above, right) in
which animals are fed or injected with different
radio-active elements. These can be traced
by the rays given off through the most complex
chemical body processes. At the Radium
Institute in Paris (below, left) the quantity of
radio-active carbon (C 14) in the blood of a
living mouse is tested. Tagged (radio-active)
rimifon is injected. The experiment is sup¬
plemented by an examination of the mouse's
excretion. Drawing, below, indicates the
different phases of another experimental use'
of radio-active carbon. (Photos USIS)
RADIOACTIVE CARBON ~ C 14
FOR STUDYINC FATE OF LABELED STEROIDS
0
LABELED STEROID
TISSUE SAMPLES
MEASURED FOR
RADIOACTIVITY.
NORMAL CANCEROUS
INDICATES:
(UPTAKE OF STEROIDS IN VARIOUS ORGANS
2- FATE OF STEROIDS IN EACH ANIMAL
3- REASONS FOR DIFFERENCES DUE TO DISEASI
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A 700,000-page nuclear library
(Continued from page 16)
programme comes the field of radio¬
isotope tracer techniques. In this
field, until now, the Atomic Energy
Commission has been able to conduct
only a limited training programme for
foreign scientists. The Commission is
now prepared to establish special
courses for foreign technicians to begin
early in 1955, these courses to cover a
four-week period and to be divided into
laboratory work, lectures on laboratory
experiments, and seminars on special
topics. The laboratory experiments
would cover the use of instruments, the
purification and separation of radio¬
active from inert materials, and the
application of various isotope tech¬
niques to airfields of research.
Vast flow of facts
ÇQ ry-iHE training courses we propose
I in safety, medicine and biology
. A would bring basic - knowledge
and training to more than 250
technical men from other nations
in the course of the next twelve
to fifteen months the limitation on
numbers, let me add, being imposed
not by our desire to restrict the sharing
of this knowledge, but simply by our
ability to absorb this number of
observers, students and trainees effec¬
tively and efficiently within our present
facilities.
"So much for our early plans for
training. Closely allied to this is the
question of written information about
the atom. We anticipate that from the
outset the international agency will
carry on a series of information and
service activities, obtaining information
from the operations of member states
in connexion with their own atomic
energy programmes and from the
agency's own activities. Here is a brief
outline of the type of information
materials which the United States is
prepared to make available in 1955 to
the international agency, when set up.
"Contrary to popular belief, the
United States has, ever since the begin¬
ning of its atomic development, made
available through published documents
of the Atomic Energy Commission and
articles in scientific journals a vast
body of research material on the
peaceful uses of atomic energy... Up to
now, the publication by the United
States of documents available to all on
the peaceful uses of atomic energy
comes to more than 20,000 papers, to¬
talling more than 700,000 pages of data.
"Always mindful of the day when
it might be beneficial to present this
material in package form, despite the
fact that it has always.been available
in individual items, we have accumulat¬
ed ten complete libraries of our own
material, which we are prepared to
give to the principal technical libraries
of co-operating nations. And we shall
provide more than ten if there is a
demand for more. Besides these
libraries of our own material, we are
prepared to provide complete sets oí
index cards, and our journals of the
ENRICO FERMI :
Great teacher,
out sta nding
experimenter
Professor Enrico Fer¬
mi, who died recently
in Chicago, was one
of the great figures
in the history of
physics with out¬
standing talents both
for theory and for
experiment. He was
the first investigator
to use neutrons to
split atomií nuclei
and he was one of
the team of scien¬
tists wno built the
first atomic pile. He
was also a remarkable
teacher and a fasci¬
nating lecturer on
every level. Fermi,
who trained the mo¬
dern school of Italian
physicists, leaves be¬
hind him a generation
of brilliant students
who are enriching
the scientific life of
Europe and America.
18
past seven years, abstracting 50,000
scientific and technical books and
reports published in all countries.
Stated in physical dimensions, what
we are prepared to furnish to each
one of these foreign libraries is the
equivalent of more than 300 lineal feet
of published reports and over 200,000
index cards.
- "Furthermore, we shall add to all of
these libraries as the material is
published, asking only in return that
the co-operating nations provide their
collections of official non-secret
papers, not available in the general
scientific literature, to be placed in the
appropriate U.S. libraries."
These proposals in technical training
are planned for 1955 without waiting
for the organization of the interna¬
tional atomic energy agency or even
for the United Nations scientific confé¬
rence. They are designed to save
at least a year in the development
programme. They should produce a
small body of experts who will return
to their own countries as authorities
ready to take responsibility for the
large developments to come. If and
when the international agency is
organized it may itself undertake to
continue this training programme.
Science and the schools
But the proposal assumes that com¬
petent men with a general back¬
ground in engineering, science or
medicine can be sent from many lands
for this specialized training. In the
future much larger numbers will be
required. This, in turn, means that
there must be a rather large increase in
the number of men who are trained at
home in the fundamental sciences and
in the principles and practice of en¬
gineering. It means that in many
countries both the scientific depart¬
ments of the universities and the
engineering schools will need to prepare
for a future in which thousands of
scientifically- and technically trained
men will find effective employment.
The improvement of science and
engineering teaching in the univer¬
sities is already a function of Unesco's
Department of Natural Sciences and is
a major item in the related programme
of Technical Assistance. With such
aid universities and engineering schools
will have to be enlarged and new ones
will have to be founded wherever the
atomic age is to become a reality.
Furthermore, in many countries the
universities and engineering schools,
though well equipped and well staf¬
fed, suffer from the lack of adequate
science instruction in the secondary
schools. Thus the demands of the
atomic energy programmes are cer¬
tain to reach into the general
educational programme also and to
stimulate a radical -improvement in
secondary-school science instruction.
Here again, it is the responsibility of
Unesco to foresee the need and to
extend its services in the improvement
and expansion of secondary-school
science teaching. The General Con¬
ference of Unesco, meeting at Montevi¬
deo in December, has authorized such
a development and a new Section of
Science Teaching has been established
in the Department of Natural Sciences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courjer. Nr 12. 1954
NUCLEAR REACTORS
t h
REACTOR FOR
RESEARCH which
is being built by the
North Carolina
State College, in the
U.S.A. Radiating
trenches will carry
water, gas and elec¬
tricity as well as
pipes, wires and
instrument cables
to the reactor. The
reactor structure in
the centre will
house a one-foot
diameter spherical
core. (Photo USIS).
e i r e s i g n an use
Before we can evaluate the realities
of atomic power, as distinct from
visions of the future, we need to
understand the basic science involved,
the installations that generate the
power and the factors that enter into
their operation. This in turn takes us
on an excursion into a realm of science
that was not taught in any school even
ten years ago. It also brings us into
contact with words that hardly existed
then but are now becoming familiar in
every language.
' It is now well known that all matter
is composed of atoms, discreet particles
that are the smallest and ultimate
units of the chemical elements. Until
the discovery of radium they were
thought to be indestructible and un¬
changeable. Radium provided the first
clues to an atomic interior and its
study led eventually to present-day
"atom-splitting" in which the atom is
laid wide open to fragmentation, to
separation of some of its parts and
even to the addition of more units and
the synthesis of wholly new atoms.
The process of splitting is now known
by the more accurate term, "fission",
and those types of atoms which un¬
dergo fission with relative ease, as in
the atomic bomb, are known as "fis¬
sionable" or "fissile". It is pity that,
in the English language at least, there
is as yet no verb to express the action
of fission. "To fiss" is almost unthink¬
able and "to fissure" does not quite
convey the meaning but can hardly be
improved upon.
The complex installation in which
fission takes place with the release of
energy and the production of new
elements from the fissile material was
known originally as a "pile" because
it was in fact a pile of uranium rods
and blocks of graphite. It is more
properly called a "reactor". In com¬
mon speech it . is the atomic furnace
where the energy is generated from the
atomic fuel, though there is no fire and
no combustion in the usual sense.
The new science is one of events
within the atom but more especially
within the nucleus of the atom. It is
unfortunate that the terms "atomic
energy" and "atomic power" have
become popular, for in truth "nuclear
energy" and "nuclear power" are more
correct. The world within the atom,
as revealed by the natural rays from
radium and by cosmic rays, is almost
incredible from the ordinary human
point of view. This is not merely
because it is so complex but also
because the basic particles within the
nucleus have new and odd relations to
both matter and energy that do not
fit into cur common conceptions.
The nucleus of the atom contains all
the "matter", yet is so small that it
occupies only a thousandth of a mil¬
lionth of a millionth of the space
within the atom. It occupies a rela¬
tively smaller space within the whole
atom than the sun occupies in the
whole great solar system. In that case
its density (that is, its weight per
cubic inch) must be a thousand'times
' a million times' a million times that of
ordinary materials. Whatever that
atomic core is made of, it is so dense
that a.1 lump of it as large as a drop of
water would weigh two million tons.
But that is only half of the aston¬
ishing situation. Energy is similarly
concentrated there. Within that ex¬
ceedingly minute volume of the atomic
nucleus there are new forces that hold
the mass together. The earth itself
is held together by gravity but the force
within the nucleus must be so much
stronger than gravity that there is no
word to express it. The force of gra¬
vity would have to be multiplied by a
number that comprises the figure 1
followed by 37 zeros. Gravity holds
the planets in their courses and the
stars in the sky but has no place in
the nucleus.
The binding force within the nucleus
is of a new and unknown form. It is
complicated and depends on the velo¬
city of the nuclear particles and even
on their spinning motion or rotation.
On the other hand the force, whatever
it is, does not depend on electrical
charges, for (neutral) neutrons and
(positive) protons seem to attract each
other to the same degree that they
attract their own kind.
This is the present mystery of the
nucleus and therefore of the atom and
thus of matter and energy in general.
There, in the intimacy of the atomic
NUCLEAR
REACTION begins
with splitting of a
Uranium 235 or
plutonium atom.
When fission oc¬
curs, great energy
is released and se¬
veral neutrons are
elected. These strike
other U-235 or plu¬
tonium atoms like
bullets and fission
them, thus freeing
more energy and mo¬
re neutron bullets.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Th sources of atomic energy
nucleus, lies the secret of the true
nature of matter, of energy, and of
their relation to each other. It is the
purpose of the great cyclotrons and
synchrotrons, such as those now being
built at Geneva for the European
Organization for Nuclear Research, to
study this nuclear world. (See page 23.)
It is the nucleus that explodes during
fission, that emits rays in radio-activ¬
ity, and that combines with other
nuclei to generate the sun's heat. It is
the nucleus that will provide the
energy for what we have- called the
atomic age. It is
by the explor¬
ation and partial
mastery of the
nucleus that
science has in
recent years been
able to duplicate
and greatly im-
prove on the
radio-activity of
radium, for
instance, and has
surpassed the
dream of me¬
dieval alchemists
by changing one
chemical element into another, such as
changing gold into mercury or pro¬
ducing explosive plutonium from harm¬
less uranium.
Just as the atoms of the various
chemical elements combine with
others to form the molecules of che¬
mical compounds, so a number of still
smaller particles combine to form the
different atomic nuclei. Three such
primary particles must be mentioned
briefly: the proton, the neutron and the
electron, the last being the familiar
"particle of electricity" that flows
through wires in countless millions to
form an electric current. It has a
charge or perhaps one should say it is
a charge of negative electricity, which
is to say that all electricity is negative
(and thus misnamed).
Less familiar is the proton. It is
almost 2,000 times heavier than the
electron. It is definitely matter rather
than electricity. Indeed it is for some
reason positively charged, as if it had
itself lost a negative electron. It is an
essential component of all atomic
nuclei, combined and compressed in
them into firm union. But it has a
comfortable existence all its own as
the entire nucleus of the hydrogen
atom, the simplest and lightest atom.
At the surface of the hydrogen atom
is a single electron, vibrant and
dancing in a complex mathematical
orbit. That electron is responsible for
the atom's chemical properties and
enables it to combine with other atoms
to form molecules, such as with oxygen
to form water. But at the centre of
the hydrogen atom is its concentrated
mass, its nucleus, the single proton
whose positive charge balances that of
the relatively distant electron, making
the whole atom electrically neutral.
Every other atomic nucleus is more
complex and heavier than that of
hydrogen and every one contains
neutrons in addition to its protons.
The neutron is practically identical
with the proton, with almost exactly
the same weight, but it has no positive
charge and so is electrically neutral.
When neutrons form a part of an
atomic nucleus they add to its mass
The alchemists'
dream has been
surpassed
and weight but do not affect its
positive charge and therefore do not
change the number of external
electrons that are responsible for the
atom's chemical properties.
These are the essential components
of all nuclei: protons, neutrons and
electrons, plus positrons, mesons and
others that need no mention here.
There are, however, several com¬
binations of protons and neutrons that
form well-known nuclear particles.
For instance, the "alpha particle", long
known as emitted by radium, is com¬
posed of two pro¬
tons and two
neutrons, and
thus has two po¬
sitive charges
When the alpha
particle is emit¬
ted by radium it
quickly picks up
two wandering
electrons and be¬
comes an atom
of helium, for the
alpha particle is
identical with the
helium nucleus
and two external,
circulating electrons make it a neutral
whole atom.
Another such stable group comprises
a single proton and a single neutron,
and thus has a single positive charge.
This group takes part in many nuclear
reactions and is called a deuteron.
When it picks up a single electron in
an external orbit it forms an atom that
is identical with hydrogen in its
chemical properties though it is twice
as heavy because its nucleus is not
merely a proton but has a neutron
added. Deuterium is therefore an
"isotope" of hydrogen that is called
"heavy hydrogen". Two deuterium
atoms combine chemically with one
atom of oxygen to produce "heavy
water".
Hydrogen,' with only one proton, is
the simplest and lightest atom. But
there are 92 different chemical elements
and the atomic nuclei of all the others
are made up of larger numbers of both
protons and neutrons. The heaviest
and most com¬
plex of all the
common atoms is
uranium, whose
nucleus contains -
92 protons and
146 neutrons, a
total of 238.
But this is not
the only type of
uranium that can
exist and there¬
fore not the only
possible composi¬
tion of the nu¬
cleus.
There are other forms with 141
neutrons, or 143, or 147. They all
have 92 protons and thus all of them
have identical chemical properties.
But the weight of the atom is the sum
of the weights of the protons and
neutrons, so that these three varieties
of uranium have atomic weights of
233, 235 and 239, respectively.
Such varieties of atoms of the same
elements, all with the same chemical
properties but with different weights
and a differing number of neutrons, are
Swift neutrons
explode the
adjoining atoms
known as isotopes. Most of them seem
to be under some sort of strain and
undergo a disintegration during which
they emit particles and rays of various
sorts. Thus they are radio-active and
are known as radio-isotopes. Their
rays are useful and will be discussed in
a subsequent article of this series.
(See page 29.)
Isotopes of the naturally radio-active
elements have long been known, pri¬
marily because of their distinctive rays.
But bombardment of almost any of the
92 elements by high-speed protons in
one of the great modern cyclotrons or
bombardment by neutrons in an atomic
reactor will add or subtract neutrons
from their nuclei and convert them
into isotopic varieties, some stable, most
of them radio-active.
Thus isotopes of all the chemical
elements are now known a total of
more than a thousand different atomic
varieties. In fact neutrons and protons
have been added to uranium in various
stages so that six new, previously un¬
known elements have now been created,
the last of them up to now being
No. 98, Californium.
In the case of uranium that variety
known as uranium 235 (from the
weight of its atom) spontaneously
disintegrates when struck by a stray
neutron, coming perhaps from outer
space as a cosmic ray, and ejects some
of its neutrons. When such a neutron
strikes an atom of uranium 238 it is
captured to form uranium 239. This in
turn instantly goes through a more
complicated nuclear reaction and
forms plutonium, with a weight of 240.
When that atom is struck by a neu¬
tron perhaps from another atom of
uranium 235, it is literally split in two.
Smaller atoms of lighter elements
result but the important thing is that
when this happens some of the binding
energy within the plutonium nucleus is
released and the atom not only splits
but the fragments fly apart with
tremendous energy. This reaction is
the basis both of the atomic bomb and
of atomic or nuclear power.
In the bomb the explosion of one
atom releases swift neutrons which at
once explode ad¬
joining atoms,
and the neutrons
from them in
turn explode still
other atoms.
Within a mil¬
lionth of a se¬
cond the entire
mass disintegra¬
tes in the indes-
:ribable explosion
that has horrified
the world. But
when this dis¬
integration i s
controlled so that
it proceeds at a manageable rate, then
the energy of disintegration may be
liberated over the course of hours,
months or years. Precisely the same
energy that feeds the bomb feeds the
atomic furnace, the "nuclear reactor".
The reactor is thus the scene of
controlled nuclear explosions. In it,
the high-speed nuclear fragments, and
neutrons too, are slowed down, their
energy is absorbed in the surrounding
materials and reappears as heat. It
may be that by future research the
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier KT 12. 1954
high-speed nuclear projectiles can be
harnessed to generate electricity di¬
rectly but for the present all atomic
reactors generate heat and their
energy can be used only in that form.
But if reactors are to be used for
industrial power this heat must be
captured and put to work. Modern
reactor design is largely a problem of
how to capture a maximum quantity of
heat and thus to utilize the energy of
the exploding atoms efficiently. The
crucial point in present atomic power
development is precisely that: whether
or not enough
heat can be cap¬
tured to justify
the enormous
cost of the reac¬
tor and of the
fissionable ura¬
nium and whe¬
ther or not the
power produced
will compare in
cost with the po¬
wer made by the
combustion o f
coal or any of
the other fuels.
task is complicated by the fact
that neutrons are emitted during fission
at very high speed, which are dangerous
to personnel, ruinous to equipment and,
in addition, convert many of the atoms
that they strike into radio-active
isotopes which are themselves dan¬
gerous. Consequently, the heat cannot
be removed from the reactor by any
simple device. The cooling liquid that
flows through the reactor becomes
radio-active and cannot be used direct¬
ly to operate an engine.
In one common type of reactor the
coolant is liquid metallic sodium. This
flows from the reactor through pipes
to a heat-exchanger where it is in turn
cooled by water before it returns to
cool the reactor once more. In that
exchange the water turns to steam that
is not dangerous because the radio¬
active sodium does not emit neutrons
and thus does not affect the water or
the steam. The 'latter can then be
passed through a steam turbine where
its high-pressure energy spins the
turbine and thereby generates electri¬
city. Thus by successive steps the
energy which came from the exploding
plutonium or uranium atoms emerges
from the power house as electric
current and is in no way different from
a current generated by other methods.
It is apparent then that the nuclear
reactor is merely the source of energy
and in a large power house would
replace only the coal furnace; all the
remaining parts of the power installa¬
tion would be unchanged.
There are many types of nuclear
reactors. They all have features in
common that differ only in degree.
The fuel is always a fissionable
material, either uranium-233, 235 or
plutonium. .Each of these releases
almost three million times as much
heat when it disintegrates as does the
combustion of an equal weight of coal.
The pure fissionable materials are,
however, extremely difficult and costly
to produce. Uranium-235 is present
in all natural uranium but comprises
only 0.7 % of it. Since it is chemically
identical with the 99.3 % of uranium-
238, it can be separated from it only
by complex and costly physical
methods. Plutonium must be made
from uranium-238 in a reactor and
uranium-233 can be similarly made
Three million
times the heat
of coal
from thorium. The pure fissionable
fuels therefore cost many thousands of
dollars per pound. For the generation
of power they are commonly used in a
less pure form in which ordinary
uranium is merely "enriched" with the
fissionable varieties.
If the purpose of the reactor is to
produce plutonium, high grade ura¬
nium-235 is the fuel. It converts
ordinary uranium-238 into plutonium
which can then be chemically separated
in the pure form and used in the bomb
or as the fuel in another reactor. If
the purpose of
the reactor is to
test the resis¬
tance to neutrons
of metals and
other materials
that are to be
used in the reac¬
tors or in atomic
engines, the fuel
may again be a
pure fissionable
uranium in or¬
der to get a
I maximum con-
centration of
neutrons acting
upon the materials being tested. If po¬
wer alone is the purpose of the reactor
the fuel is "enriched" uranium because
a high intensity of neutrons is not
needed and a slower reaction is more
likely to generate usable heat.
Every reactor also has some form of
"moderator", a material like graphite,
heavy water or beryllium, which serve
primarily to slow down the neutrons
from their original speed of many
thousands of miles per second to a
speed at which they are more likely to
be captured by the uranium atoms and
thus to cause fission.
Every reactor also needs a material
which actively captures neutrons but is
not capable of fission by them. The
commonest material for this purpose is
the metal cadmium. It reduces the
number of flying neutrons and thus
reduces the rate of the fission reaction.
The cadmium is commonly used in the
form of thick rods which can be in¬
serted into the reactor if the reaction
is going too fast and thus slow it down.
They may, in
fact, be inserted
fully, whereupon
they stop the
reaction cornel °-
tely and shut
down the rear" ".
Thus the speed
of both the fis¬
sion reaction and
of the power ge¬
neration is then
controlled and
danger of, a
runaway reaction
or an explosion
is avoided.
Also every reactor must be provided
with means for carrying away the heat.
While this is necessary for all reactors
to keep them from melting, the cooling
liquid is the crucial part of a reactor
that is used for generating power, as
has been said.
Finally, every reactor must also have
an effective shield to absorb neutrons
that escape from the fission reaction
and prevent them from penetrating
into the room where scientists and
attendants are at work. Such shields
are usually heavy walls of lead or con¬
crete, or both. No reactor can safely
operate without a shield and it is for
- - r .
Th e / urnace
wh ich b reeds
its own fuel
this reason that there is no hope that
atomic reactors can ever be used for
the propulsion of automobiles or for the
heating of homes. The shield alone
must weigh many tons. While this is
no obstacle to its use in a large power
station or in a marine vessel, it is one
of the severe limitations on the use of
any atomic engine for airplanes.
Until May of 1953 the prospect of
using atomic fuels and reactors as a
major source of industrial power was a
bright hope but not more than that.
There were two major obstacles. One
was the cost of the pure fissionable fuel,
which has never been stated, since it is
made only by governments for military
purposes and it cannot now be bought
anywhere. It was nevertheless certain
that the cost per pound was very high
indeed. The second obstacle was the
lack of any certainty that there is
enough uranium available in the
minerals of the world to supply an
atomic industrial age. Both obstacles
were eliminated by the announcement
of the success of the experimental
"breeder" reactor, operated by the U.S.
Atomic Energy Commission at Arco,
Idaho, since 1951. At one stroke the
effective supply of uranium was mul¬
tiplied by 140 and the effective cost of
the fuel was reduced almost to zero.
The breeder reactor is a major item in
the prospect of atomic power.
Briefly it is a reactor that generates
power and at the same time produces
as much new fissionable material as it
uses up, and probably more. This at
first thought seems as impossible as
would a coal furnace that consumes
tons of fuel to generate heat but at the
end contains more fresh coal than was
fed into it. Such a furnace would
operate without any fuel cost and, in
fact, could sell new coal to other users.
In the case of coal it is, of course, im¬
possible. But with atomic fuels in a
breeder reactor it is only one of many
apparent miracles.
When an atom of uranium-235
fissures it emits high-speed neutrons,
as has been said. If the fission
reaction is maintained, one of the
neutrons must strike another atom of
uranium-235 so that this, in turn, will
undergo fission. If two neutrons are
emitted the se¬
cond may do the
same, but if ordi¬
nary uranium-
238 (which does
not fissure) is
also present the
second neutron
may strike it,
and thus change
it into plutonium.
Plutonium is fis¬
sionable, exactly
as is uranium-
235, and the ori¬
ginal value of
the fuel has thus
been restored. If the uranium-235 fis¬
sion always emits two neutrons and if
both processes are 100 % efficient, the
furnace would be continuously manu¬
facturing its own fuel out of the cheap
natural uranium-238. The practical
questions then are : How many neu¬
trons does uranium-235 emit on fission
and how efficient is the process ?
The exact number of neutrons emit¬
ted has never been revealed. It has,
however, been annouced that there are
"more than two". The margin this.gives
is such that some neutrons may be lost
by striking the rods or other inert ma¬
terials in the reactor and yet leave one
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE COST OF
FUEL WILL BE
NEGLIGIBLE
to carry on the reaction and one to
make new fuel. If three neutrons are
emitted there is ample margin and it
thus becomes possible that the reactor
may even make more fuel than it uses.
That this is possible is still a real
hope, though it has as yet no official
confirmation. What the U.S. Atomic
Energy Commission did announce in
May 1953 was that fissionable plu¬
tonium is produced in the breeder
reactor "at a rate that is at least equal
to the rate at which the uranium-235
is being consumed".
In the case of thorium, however, it is
known that more fuel can be produced
than is used. The original fuel in this
case is also uranium-235. If a neutron
from it strikes an atom of thorium-232
(which is not fissionable) that atom is
converted into fissionable uranium-233.
The reaction is
efficient enough
' so that more ura¬
nium-233 is pro¬
duced than the
uranium- 235.
When more fuel
is produced than
consumed, the
excess can be
sold to other
users , presum¬
ably the Govern¬
ment itself, and
the returns would
reduce the net
cost of power
which has been
produced in the nuclear reactor.
In both cases common and relatively "
cheap materials, uranium and thorium,
are converted into atomic fuels by the
reactor whose primary purpose is the
economic generation of power. This
means that all the uranium and
thorium in the world could be con¬
verted into effective fuels instead of
only the 0.7 % or l/140th of the
uranium that is present as uranium-
235. This multiplies the world's re¬
sources of uranium fuel 140 times.
What is more, it adds all the great
deposits of thorium to the fuel supply.
The breeder reactor which has
supplied this information and created
this confidence is a relatively small one
with a production of 250 kilowatts of
electricity enough 'for only a small
town. At its centre is the core of
fissionable uranium-235, about the size
of a football. Around this core is a
thick cylinder of ordinary uranium-238
which catches the neutrons to form
plutonium. The heat evolved is equi¬
valent to 4,000 watts for every cubic
inch of the active core.
In comparison, an oil-fired boiler,
such as is used in battleships, gives
only 600 watts per cubic inch of fuel.
The heat from the breeder reactor is
conducted away by a flow of liquid
sodium through inserted pipes. The
sodium stream emerges from the
reactor at a temperature of about
660° F and delivers its heat to water in
a heat-exchanger and thus forms steam
to drive a turbine.
COSMOTRON, at Brookhaven National Laboratory U.S.A., is the second most
powerful of giant machines used by scientists to bombard atomic nuclei with
high energy particles and thus learn more- about their make-up and nature. (Most
powerful machine operating at present is the Berkeley Bevatron, at the University of
California.) The huge "doughnut-shaped" magnet, 75 feet in diameter, guides the particles
in a circular path while a succession of electric boosts gives them phenomenal speeds.
Collisions between high-energy particles and nuclei are seen as thin white tracks (photo,
left), when photographed in an instrument called a cloud chamber.
To calculate the cost of the fuel used
in producing power is easy enough. As
has been explained, this is now not the
cost of the expensive, fissionable
uranium-235 but of ordinary uranium-
238 the price of which is approximately
$35 a pound. Since 20 pounds of
uranium will produce some 52 million
kilowatts hour of electricity enough to
light a fairly large city for a year the
cost of the fuel used would be only
0.0013 cents per kilowatt hour. Since
the usual price of electricity is more
than one cent per kilowatt hour, the
fuel cost itself is quite negligible.
But such a calculation is illusory
because other expenses are involved.
The most important of which is the
occasional removal of the covering
cylinder of natural uranium and its
chemical processing to extract the
plutonium for the future fuel. This is
a difficult operation because the very
strong radio-activity of the materials
makes it necessary to conduct the
chemical operation by remote con¬
trol, without contact with personnel.
Furthermore, the core itself gradually
becomes exhausted as the fission
products accumulate in it. It too must
therefore ultimately be removed so that
the remaining uranium-235 can be
extracted from the variety of other
and smaller radio-active atoms that are
the products of fission. The processing
of the fuels therefore adds an item of
cost which is at least ten times that of
the original uranium. In that case the
fuel cost is 0.013 cents per kilowatt
hour, which is still negligible.
But there are other costs. The
highly radio-active products must be
disposed of. Some of them are valuable
for use as radio- isotopes. Most of them
are of no value but are intensely radio¬
active and are therefore a serious
hazard. In any case the cost of
disposing of radio-active wastes is an
important one.
But the major cost is the building of
the reactor itself which is between
2 million and 20 million dollars, or even
more. The calculation of the practical,
final cost of electricity must therefore
be postponed to a more comprehensive
discussion of other reactor installations
and the plans of electrical power com¬
panies m a subsequent article (page 41).
OMEGATRON, a miniature mach'ne
for research with high energy particles,
developed by the National Bureau of
Standards, Washington. The heart of
the instrument, enclosed in a glass tube,
is little larger than a packet of cigarettes,
but for experimental purposes it is
mcuited between the bulky pole pieces
of an extremely powerful electro-magnet.
The omegatron makes possible for the
first time, the exact evaluation of the
Faraday, a unit of quantity of electri¬
city. Its other uses include measure¬
ment of the mass of nuclear particles
and analysis of gases and vapours. Here
the omegatron is being lowered between
the magnet poles, (Photo USIS).
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
-¿
AN INTERNATIONAL
CENTRE for carrying out
nuclear research is being built
near Geneva. This plan shows
layout of the centre which will
house the world's most power¬
ful instruments to explore mat¬
ter and energy. One machine
will generate particles which
approach the speed of light.
Numbers on plan indicate :
(I) entrance, (2) lecture room,
(3) library, (4) restaurant, (5)
laboratories for theoretical
work, (6) experimental labora¬
tories, (7) central workshop.
(8) workshop for synchro-cyclo¬
tron, ' (9) synchro-cyclotron
control room, ( I 0) synchro-cy¬
clotron (a high energy accelera¬
tor), (II) power station, (12)
fuei tanks, ( I 3) cooling towers,
(14) circular magnet for pro¬
ton-synchrotron (this giant
magnet will be buried in a
concrete filled trench), (IS)
experimental halls, (16) pro¬
ton-synchrotron workshop, (17)
generators, (18) laboratories
for theoretical work, (19) lin¬
ear accelerator (machine for
accelerating nuclear particles).
CERN WHERE GIANT FORCES WILL
PENETRATE A TINY WORLD
At the end of the last century, great scientists, often
working alone and under difficult conditions, discovered
radio-activity, radium and the X-ray, but none of them
considered that the atom had an interior. Today scientists
delve within the atomic nucleus and study a maze of funda¬
mental particles of matter and of energy inside electrons
and positrons, protons and neutrons, mesons and neutrinos.
But today, the frontiers of atomic science are so far from
the everyday world that it takes large, expensive and highly
organized expeditions to reach -them. A large cyclotron for
penetrating the nucleus of the atom costs millions of dollars.
To operate it costs thousands of dollars per day and requirec
the combined work of large teams of physicists, chemists,
mathematicians, engineers, and electricians, and also biolo¬
gists and physicians.
The work, in fact, is so expensive that no university can
establish a modern fully-equipped laboratory without help
from its government. And for that matter, very few gov¬
ernments can- afford to finance a major nuclear research
programme by themselves. The only solution is interna¬
tional collaboration.
Unesco has been concerned with this problem since 1950
when it was asked to help bring together European scientists
and governments to establish a European centre for nuclear
research. A few months ago this project became a reality
when the European Organization for Nuclear Research came
into being following the ratification of an international
convention by nine countries.
CERN, as the Organization is usually called (from the
French title Conseil Européen pour la recherche nucléaire
of the temporary body which preceded it) is the first in¬
ternational organization for scientific research set up by an
intergovernmental Convention. Today this Convention has
been ratified by ten countries: Belgium, Denmark, France,
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
EUROPE'S NUCLEAR EXPLORERS
DIRECTOR-GENERAL of CERN is Professor Felix Bloch, of
Switzerland. Professor Bloch was winner of the I 952 Nobel Physics Prize.
German Federal Republic, Greece, Netherlands, Norway,
Sweden, Switzerland and the United Kingdom. Italy and
Yugoslavia have also signed the Convention but have not yet
ratified it.
CERN is not concerned with atomic energy, but only with
basic research on the structure of the atomic nucleus. The
part played by Unesco in its establishment offers a good
example of the way the Organization can help to develop
international co-operation in the field of scientific research.
M. Henri Longchambon, Secretary of State at the French
Department of Scientific and Technical Research, recently
said that while technicians now know how to produce atomic
energy, the mechanism and behaviour of nuclear forces are
still shrouded in mystery. In investigating these pheno-
PRESIDENT of CERN is Sir
Ben Lockspeiser, Director,
Department of Scientific and In¬
dustrial Research, Great Britain.
mena, research is focussed on
very high-energy particles,
found principally in cosmic
rays reaching the earth from
outer space, but which can be
created artificially by bom¬
barding atomic nuclei with
the help of machines called
particle accelerators.
The creation of these artifi¬
cial cosmic rays in laboratories
is an essential part of nuclear
research. That is why physi¬
cists and engineers, for the
past twenty years, have been
building more and more po¬
werful accelerators. In Europe only a few countries have
enough money and a sufficient range of scientific and tech¬
nical resources to build their own machines.
England, with a thousand-million electron-volt accelerator,
is very advanced in this field, and France has just decided to
build one which is to reach- 2.4 thousand-million electron-
volts, and several medium-power accelerators.
But even for such countries, the advantages of interna¬
tional co-operation in this field are very great. Even the
most modern American institutions, which were still, quite
recently, leading in this field, entrust such research to spe¬
cialists recruited from all over the world, and particularly
from Europe.
CERN has therefore set up teams of the foremost special-
its in its Member States to design the two accelerators : a
600 million electron-volt synchro-cyclotron and a 25 thous¬
and-million electron-volt proton-synchrotron. The construc¬
tion of the first machine one of a classical type raises no
special difficulties and can be completed in 2 or 3 years.
The construction of the second machine, however, is a dar¬
ing venture. It' is to have five times the power of the most
powerful accelerator at present operating in the USA (the
Berkeley Bevatron) and is to be built on an entirely new
principle. The speed of the particles it generates will
approach the velocity of light the absolute ceiling. It will
take six or seven years to build.
There will be nothing secret about CERN's work. Its
creators hope that it will mark the beginning of a new era
of international collaboration in atomic research. Its ela¬
borate and costly equipment will serve all science and
through it a world that is anxious to make good use of the
secrets of the atom.
CONSTRUCTION of CERN'S central laboratory is now going ahead on a site some 2,000 feet square about three miles north¬
west of Geneva, Switzerland, and adjoining the French border on land offered by the Geneva Canton. The cost is estimated at
120 million Swiss francs (28 million dollars) for the first seven years, including construction and operation. Project was first
proposed by the European Cultural Conference in 1949 and adopted by the Unesco General Conference in 1950. In 1953, a
Convention establishing the Organization was signed in Pans. CERN became a reality on September 29, I 954, when the Conven¬
tion had been ratified by nine of the twelve nations which have signed it.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 12. 1954
A NEW POWER TO
SERVE HEALING
AND RESEARCH
One of man's greatest hopes has been that he can
eventually control disease, and today, greater
opportunities exist than ever before for mastering
it. Atomic energy is the amazing tool which now helps
doctors to learn the processes of the human body and to
fight illness. Radio-isotopessubstances containing the
atoms which give off radiations and which are now being
produced in ever-increasing quantitieshave been des¬
cribed by doctors as the most important discovery since
the invention of the microscope. In healing, isotopes
with strong rays penetrate the affected area of the body
and attack disease. In research, isotopes with weak,
harmless rays are swallowed or injected and their rays
trace hidden changes in the body. Photographs on this
page and overleaf illustrate some of the ways in which
the energy in the atom is being used to fight disease.
TRACKING DOWN AND ATTACKING CANCER. Radio-isotopes are used
as "tracers" to locate cancers because these absorb some radio-active, substances
more than ordinary tissues. Photo, left, shows how a cancer has been charted by
use of a scintillation counter which records the radiations given off from an isotope
injected into the patient's arm. Radium, once the principal weapon for attacking
cancers, is now commonly replaced by less expensive radio-cobalt. Another means
of bombarding a cancer with powerful rays is by machines such as the Van de Graff
generator (above). This can produce high energy beams of either X-rays or electrons.
RADIOACTIVE IODINE - 1131
FOR STUDYING THYROID GLAND PHYSIOLOGY
PATIENT DRINKS SMALL
AMOUNT OF I 13!
I 131 EMITS PENETRATIN6
,	 CAMMA RAYS
DETECTS RADIATIONS
FROM ABSORBED I 131
SHOWS:
I -THYROID' GLAND TAKES UP MOST RADIOIODINE RETAINED BY BODY
2- IODINE ABSORPTION PROPORTIONAL TO PRODUCTION OF THYROXINE
3- RELATIVE ABSORPTION SHOWS PHYSIOLOGICAL ACTIVITY OF GLAND
RADIO-ACTIVE IODINE is a tracer iso¬
tope which^tells doctors how the thyroid
gland is working. Patient drinks a small
amount of radio-iodine which is largely
taken up by the thyroid gland. This absorp¬
tion is proportional to the gland's production
of a hormone called Thyroxine. Measure¬
ment of the amount of radio-iodine absorbed
thus shows whether the thyroid is function¬
ing normally. Greatest use made of iso¬
topes is for tracer, techniques. (Photos COI
Crown Copyright Reserved and USIS).
UNESCO
ARCHIVES
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ATOMS IN THE SERVICE OF MEDICINE (Continued)
\ *
RADIOACTIVE PHOSPHORUS - P32
FOR LOCATING EXTENT OF BRAIN TUMORS
(D
P32 ABSORBED
OY TUMOR TISSUE,
® ^^-^ X n
,P 32 INJECTED, (f^m^ \ 'ÍV--M
<D
RADIATION SURVEY
MADE DURING SURGERY,
J SMALL (3.. DIA.)
1 PROIE COUNTER
(D MEASURES P32 IN TUMOR
ADVANTAGES:
I -ABSORPTION GREATER (5-IOO TIMES) IN TUMOR THAN NORMAL BRAIN TISSUE
2- LIMITS OF TUMOR MASS ACCURATELY DETERMINED
3- METHOD CAN BE USED DURING SURGERY
îd-jsaî:
BRAIN TUMOURS can be diagnosed and located with the aid of a number of tracer
isotopes. How one of these, radio-active phosphorus, is used is explained in the
simplified drawing, above. Below, a patient suspected of having a brain tumour si
examined by means of a scintillation counter in a hospital at Houston, Texas, U.S.A.
Radio-active iodine, with which he has been injected, accumulates in tumour tissue.
Recording of the radiation from various areas of the skull helps the doctor to deter¬
mine whether there is a tumour present, and if so, its approximate location and extent.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 1954
PLANTING SEEDS
OF RADIO-GOLD
The use of powerful tissue-destroying rays from
radium is well established in the treatment of
cancers. But radium has a long radio-active
"life" and if implanted in cancer tissue must be
removed after a time. Today several kinds of
radio-isotopes are replacing radium for implan¬
tation. One of these is radio-gold, which has a
half-life of three days. (The "half-life" is the time
taken for the activity of a radio-active substance
to decay to half its original value). As it is also
inert in body tissues, it can be placed in them and
forgotten. Photographs (top of page) show some
phases in localization of a deep-seated brain
tumour and its treatment with radio-gold grains
at the Sainte-Anne Hospital in Paris. Use has
been made of what is called the Stereotaxic
method for locating an exact point (the site of
the tumour, in this case) by taking measurements
from three directions, with a specially developed
apparatus. Above, doctors examine a radiograph
of the patient's skull taken while the head was
held in the frame of the Stereotaxic apparatus.
Centre, the apparatus itself. Right, after injecting
patient with a radio-isotope, surgeon obtains
confirmation of the tumour site. Inserting a
needle-like probe, combined with a Geiger
counter, he is able to pin-point the exact depth
(to within one millimetre) of the tumour because
of the stronger radiations which come from the
tumour tissues due to a greater concentration
there of radio-active isotope, as compared with
those from normal tissue. Afterwards, through
the same tiny hole in the skull, he places grains
of radio-active gold in the centre of the tumour
with the aid of a special instrument. Photo,
left, is a radiograph taken after two grains of
radio-gold had been placed in a brain. Outlines
of two needle-like instruments used to implant
the gold are shown, and, slightly below 'their
points, the two grains of radio-gold are seen as
black specks. (Photos USIS by André Steiner.)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
«*»*
^OíJ¿¡J'-JSjI
I*« ¿i trr*»
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
REMOTE CONTROL devices are used for handling those radio-active
isotopes which emit dangerous radiation. Photos show how this is done
at Oak Ridge National Laboratory, U.S.A. from where isotopes are sent
to many parts of the world for use in industry, medicine and agriculture.
Devices for bottling and transferring radio-active solution shown here
are operated by personnel who are protected by two feet of concrete
shielding. Operation is observed by means of overhead mirrors and a
periscopic device fitted on the handling tongs. (Photos USIS).
As soon as atomic power begins
to be widely used by industry
throughout the world an impor¬
tant flow of by-products will come from
the atomic furnaces that provide this
power. And important and valuable
as is the energy to be obtained from
the atom, it is safe to say that these
by-products of the atomic furnaces
will be at least as valuable.
When an atom of uranium or thori¬
um undergoes fission it splits into
two or more smaller atoms. The velo¬
city of these fragments becomes useful
as heat but the new atoms remain
buried in the reactor core. They are
subjected there to a con¬
tinuing intense bombard¬
ment by neutrons. This
induces further nuclear
changes and in their final
form nearly all these
atoms are so charged with
energy that when they
are later separated from
the remaining uranium
they are intensely radio¬
active.
Similarly, almost any
other material inserted "
into the core of the
reactor, by means of a
special inlet tube, for
instance, is also so bombarded that it
emerges in a strongly radio-active form.
As has been explained in an earlier
article of this series, these new forms
of otherwise stable atoms are known as
isotopes and, when they are radio¬
active, as radio-isotopes. The core of
a reactor is an immensely powerful
device for manufacturing them.
The radio-activity consists of atomic
disintegrations which are small conti¬
nuing atom-by-atom explosions. The
energy or tension in the atom of a
radio-isotope is, in effect, relieved by
the ejection of an electron, or an alpha
particle and is accompanied by an
intense emission of very short ether vi¬
brations, called - gamma rays, which
resemble X-rays except that they are
usually much more penetrating than
any X-rays.
Isotopes of the various elements
differ in the rate at which they decay
and give off their energy. Some com¬
plete the process in a small fraction of
a second, others in minutes, hours,
days, years or even centuries. Obvious¬
ly those in which the process is rapid
give a very intense radiation while they
last. Those that require years or cen¬
turies to decay give relatively only
feeble radiations at any time.
There is thus an enormous variety
of isotopes. The total number known
at present is close to 1,300 of which
about 800 are radioactive and more than
150 are useful and stable enough to be
kept in stock on shelves for sale. Some
are used for the intensity or penetra¬
tion of their rays and others because
their rays are feeble. The type of ray
desired,for specific practical effects also
determines the choice of an isotope.
Furthermore, the isotopes are chemical
elements such as carbon, iron, phos¬
phorous and gold, and they may be
chosen for use because of their normal
chemical reactions.
Before the days of the atomic reactor
most radio-active materials were rela¬
tively weak. One of the strongest was
radium, long used in the treatment of
cancer. In those early days it was sold
in milligrammes, thousandths of a gram¬
me and cost approximately $100 per
milligramme. When the women of Ame¬
rica honoured Madame Curie toward
the end of her life, they presented her
with a whole gramme of radium at a
cost of more than $100,000.
All the purified radium in the world
amounts to less than 2,500 grammes
a little more than five pounds. Modern
reactors however produce radio-active
isotopes in quantities thousands of
times as powerful as radium. A quan
tity of radio-active cobalt that is equi¬
valent to 10 kilogrammes of radium
10,000 grammes or 10 million milli¬
grammes can now be purchased at a
reasonable price.
With such materials radiation effects
can be obtained that were hardly con¬
ceivable ten years ago. For instance,
the University of Michigan in the
U.S.A. has recently announced that
pork briefly exposed to the intense ra¬
diation from an isotope of cobalt can
be freed of the trichina parasites.
About 18 % of all pork is infected with
these dangerous worms. The way
trichinosis is avoided today is by cook¬
ing pork thoroughly.
For another example,
research men at Oregon
State College in the U.S.
have reported that pota¬
to e s similarly exposed
"are in perfect condition
after almost two years in
a bin under commercial
storage conditions." The
U.S. Army is now study¬
ing preservation of food
by means of radiation
from radio-isotopes with¬
out using refrigeration.
It is possible completely
to kill the bacteria, es¬
pecially in meats, but perhaps also in
fruits and vegetables, so that the food
will not spoil and can be exposed on
the shelf for many weeks without
deterioration.
Such uses of intense rays are closely
related to the radiation hazard in the
vicinity of an atomic reactor. These
are always enclosed within heavy wails
of lead and concrete to prevent expo¬
sure of the operators to tht rays. It
must be said that the reactor also
emits high-speed, very penetrating
neutrons but the radio-isotopes do not.
One of the most hazardous operations
in the world is the removal of the core
of an exhausted reactor and the dispo¬
sal of the enormously radio-active
waste products that have accumulated
in it. Special devices are used, such as
allowing the spent uranium rods to
fall directly from the reactor into a
large pool of water and into an under¬
water cart by which they are removed
for safe disposal. But that disposal is
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
itself one of the major problems of the
atomic industry, for the intense radio¬
activity may in this case last for deca¬
des and part for centuries.
The reactor wastes have been buried
in deep pits and they have been hauled
far out to sea sealed in great blocks of
concrete. Neither of these is satisfac¬
tory in the long run so that Dr. Ira M.
Freeman, of Rutgers University in the
. United States, has suggested that one
of the best uses to which a future
space-rocket can be put is to send a
container of radio-active waste far out
into space where it would continue in
an orbit around the earth or perhaps
around the sun for ever, gradually
exhausting its radio-activity. On the
other hand, if the demand for radio¬
isotopes in industry, agriculture and
medicine continues to grow the wastes
of the reactor would provide an ample
supply.
In spite of the radiation hazards,
men working with the atomic reactors
are very seldom harmed. In fact, the
published figures show that accidents
and injuries in the many large atomic
plants in America are decidedly less in
relation to the number of men em¬
ployed than in ordinary industry. This
is because the danger is understood
and is guarded against. Not only are
all dangerous operations conducted
behind thick walls by remote control,
but employees who may be exposed to
radiation wear special clothing and
all of them are constantly inspected by
photographic and electronic instru¬
ments for any traces of radio-active
contamination.
'Precisely the same source of danger
arises when the atomic bomb is ex¬
ploded, except that in that case the
radio-active atoms are very finely
blown throughout many cubic miles of
the thin stratosphere. There are many
millions of cubic miles of air above the
earth and the dispersion by the bomb
itself, by heat and by winds is so great
that the concentration of radio-active
material in the air is almost vanish-
ingly small. But it can be detected
by sensitive instruments. It is thus
A DRY BOX is used where the
handling of substances involves
risk of poisoning. The research
worker here is handling a radio¬
isotope with rubber gloves let
into the walls of the box.
Substances with toxic properties
are placed inside the dry box
through the doors of small
chamber at right. (Photo C.O.I.
Crown Copyright Reserved).
that the explosion of an atomic bomb
can be detected on the other side of
the earth.
There is no doubt, however, that the
slow accumulation of radio-active mate¬
rial from successive bombs and espe¬
cially from hydrogen bombs, which are
thousands of times as powerful as
uranium bombs, would eventually pro¬
duce concentrations of radio-active
materials in the air that would harm¬
fully affect all living things. In Sep¬
tember 1954, Dr. E. D. Adrian, President
of the British Association for the Ad¬
vancement of Science warned that "we
must face the possibility that repeated
atomic explosions will lead to a degree
of general radio-activity which no one
can tolerate or escape."
It is not now possible to estimate
whether this point will be reached
after the explosion of a hundred
atomic bombs or after a few thousand.
Experts agree that the two score of
bombs that have been exploded up to
now have done no harm. The one
exception was one hydrogen bomb ex-
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
Lasting fire from the atomic furnace
ploded over the Pacific which did
shower radio-active dust over a much
larger area than had been expected
and caused burns on 23 unfortunate
Japanese fishermen of whom one has
since died. Their boat, the "Fukuryu
Maru", was between 70 and 90 miles
from the centre of the explosion. Such
danger from the explosion itself, is,
however, enormously greater than from
the isotopes dispersed at great heights
and over a wide area.
Nevertheless the radiation hazard
needs more careful study and on a
motion of the Japanese delegation at
the Montevideo General Conference in
December, Unesco was authorized to
co-operate with the World Health Or¬
ganization (WHO) in studying protec¬
tion against the effects of radio-acti¬
vity on life in general.
The sterilization of meat and vege¬
tables by intense rays from powerful
isotopes, though technically possible, is
still too expensive. The use of isotopes
for sterilization will come first in the
case of more valuable materials such
as penicillin and other antibiotics.
These drugs are injected or used inter¬
nally and so must be completely free
of all bacteria or other infections, yet
they cannot usually be heated or boiled
to sterilize them. The vials containing
the drug can be briefly exposed to an
intense radiation equal to many kilo¬
grammes of radium and can thus be
safely and completely sterilized in the
cold.
Another use was recently demonstra¬
ted by Admiral Lewis Strauss, Chair¬
man of the U. S. Atomic Energy Com¬
mission, who carried with him a small
box weighing about 20 pounds, light
enough to be carried on a battlefield,
but which gives sufficiently intense
gamma radiation to equal that of a
WORKING
YOU ft« INTtHNG
ACTIVE AfttA
1^' W/ÍU«tíl '
OS .>** mi>'
I ¿4fl£(M*S O«
1" tlr ctf.w^n ,
STRINGENT PRECAUTIONS protect atomic
energy laboratory and plant workers against
ingestion of radio-active gas or dust. Eating
and smoking are forbidden in "active" areas.
Outdoor clothes are left in one locker and work
clothes in another. Here, a research worker
puts on overshoes before entering a laboratory.
(Photo N.F.B.).
powerful X-ray machine without using
any machinery or power supply. The
isotopic rays from the portable
container can be used as X-rays are to
detect flaws in metal and in machinery
or to make examinations of persons
injured in accidents, for instance.
Where no intense radiation is de¬
manded the isotopes are already cheap
enough to be in industrial use. Large
quantities are
available, for in¬
stance, to stimu¬
late the lumino¬
sity of fluores¬
cent materials,
hence to repla¬
ce expensive ra¬
dium in luminous
watch and clock
dials and on ad¬
vertising signs.
An isotope of
strontium isbeing
used by the U. S
Navy on many
thousands of self-
luminous markers
which are twice
as bright at night
as a sheet of whi¬
te paper in full
moonlight and
may be had in al¬
most any colour
except deep red.
Here the cristal¬
line material is
stimulated to lu¬
minosity by the
rays given off
by the strontium
which decreases
in strength at so
slow a rate that
the markers re-
m a i n lumi¬
nous for a score of years or more.
Another application is in the ordi¬
nary fluorescent tube. When isotopes
are mixed with the luminous material
they increase the conductivity of the
air in the tube so that it requires less
voltage to start the lamp and it starts
much more quickly. A similar use is
made of a tube of such materials weak¬
ly radio-active, where there is danger
of sparks from static electricity. The
faint rays make the air a sufficient
conductor of electricity so that static
does not accumulate.
A typical industrial use of the rays
from these radio-active materials is in
the automatic control of the produc¬
tion of thin sheets of paper or plastic,
or the metal for making tin cans. As
the sheet leaves the rollers which
squeeze it to the desired thickness, it
passes through' an instrument that
holds a small amount of radio-active
material under the sheet and holds a
detecting instrument such as a Geiger
counter, over the sheet. The rays
penetrate the sheet and are received
and detected on the other side.
But if the sheet for some reason
becomes either thinner or thicker than
is desired, the amount of radiation
received by the detecting instrument
instantly increases or decreases as a
result, because it is partly absorbed in
the sheet. Thus the instrument is a
constant and automatic inspector of
the thickness and it can easily be
SHORT-LIFE ISOTOPES which must be
employed within a few days following their acti¬
vation in an atomic pile are despatched by air.
Here a canister is being placed in the wing-tip of
a South Africa bound aircraft at London Air¬
port. (Photo C.O.I. Crown Copyright Reserved).
adjusted to regulate the rollers and
correct the error so as to produce a
sheet of uniform thickness.
A suggestion of things to come was
given by the Radio Corporation of
America in a recent demonstration of
a small electric battery which uses the
actual power of the electrons that are
continuously emitted from about half a
milligramme of radio-active strontium,
amplifies them in
a modern "trans¬
istor", and thus
achieves enough
power to work a
telegraph relay
or work a tele¬
phone transmit¬
ter. Thus the tiny
battery gives a
current of 5 mi¬
cro-amperes and
one fifth of a
volt. Small as it
is, it is the first
practicable con¬
version of atomic
energy directly
into electricity
without the use
of heat.
A well-known
use of the direct
rays from radio¬
isotopes is in me¬
dicine.
The use of the
powerful tissue-
destroying rays
from radium is
established in the
treatment of can¬
cers. They have
the same effect
as equally power¬
ful X-rays but a
cancer can often
be reached with a small pellet or tube
of radium that cannot well be reached
by X-ray tube. The new radio-isotopes
can be used in exactly the same way,
but with the advantage that the
amounts of radiation that can be
obtained from them are far larger than
in the case of radium and cost less. '
The commonest substitute for radium
is radio-cobalt. A small cylinder of
metallic cobalt gives gamma rays equal
to that of radium costing several
hundred thousand pounds sterling.
Such a piece of cobalt, weighing little
more than an ounce is enclosed in
heavy metal but an intense beam of
radiation is directed through a small
window at the cancerous growth.
In other forms, both radio-phos¬
phorus and radio-gold are very
conveniently used for this type of
treatment. For skin cancers, an
ordinary blotting paper is soaked with
radio-active phosphate solution and
when dry it is cut to the size and shape
of the tumour, then is strapped to the
tumour with adhesive. Radio-cobalt
can be drawn out into a fine wire or
cut into tiny beads which can be
placed within the cancerous growth.
And radio-gold can be formed into tiny
grains which are fired directly into the
cancer from a small "gun". In both
cases they remain in the cancer until
it is destroyed.
In another method of treatment, the
(Continued on page 35).
3I
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
TRACKING INSECT PESTS with radio-isotopes. Scientists at the Rothamstead Experimental Station, Harpenden, England, carrying
out a series of experiments on aphids, a family in insect pests which include the greenfly and blackfly. Here, an aphid is being marked
with radio-active paint before being put to feed on young turnip plants. These tracers reveal insect's migration from plant to plant.
(Photo COI Crown Copyright Reserved).
PRESERVING POTATOES by exposing them to gamma rays was part of a study of radiation
effects on plants made by agricultural scientists at Brookhaven National Laboratory. Irradia¬
tion of unsprouted tubers kept them firm after months underground, where they would
normally have rotted. Another experiment showed that when radiation is spread over a
protracted period, living organisms can tolerate a total exposure which would cause serious
injury if concentrated into a short time. (Photo USIS).
32
GAMMA FIELD with radio-active cobalt at its
centre at Brookhaven National Laboratory, as
seen from the air, is shown in background of
this photo. Scientists study hereditary changes
due to gamma rays. Four ears of corn shown
here were grown at different distances (seen
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
THE WAY
TO BIGGER
HARVESTS
NEW PLANT STRAINS, capable of yielding more food per plant are being developed by
scientists at Brookhaven' National Laboratory, New York. Vegetable crops have been exposed
to radio-activity, and since radiation accelerates variations of strains, years of time may be
saved. As changes occur the plants are selected and crossbred. Corn variations include
changes in colour, sweetness and other characteristics. Photo shows a new hybrid, about
as tall as a man, which has been developed. Photo USIS).
The world's poorly fed people number hun¬
dreds of millions. In some countries famine
hovers at innumerable doorsteps every
year. Yet more and better food for hungry
peoples could be produced if better .types of
crops could be developed, and if agriculturists
could learn more of the secrets of plant life
and growth. In time, atomic energy may help
to dispel the spectre of hunger from homes all
over the world. It can guide plant scientists to
improved ways of raising crops, teach them how
to combat insects and plant diseases more effec¬
tively, and even create new types of plants which
yield a larger harvest or better-quality produce.
Using radio-isotopes as "tracers" scientists have
been able to learn much about plant growth and
how to make the best use of fertilizers. One
authority has said: "The advances made with
isotopes in the knowledge of phosphate fertilizers
during the past four years is equal to and may
exceed the progress in this field during the
preceeding 50 years." Some day, scientists may
be able to create food in laboratories. The day
when hungry peoples will be fed will come more
quickly if atomic knowledge is shared by all.
as rings In aerial photo) from the cobalt,
which is lowered Into ground while men work
in field. Greatest changes occurred in plants
nearest centre where rays were strongest,
showing normal reproduction can be altered
from one generation to another. (Photo USIS).
DESTROYING BACTERIA that cause food to deteriorate. At the Massachusetts Institute of
Technology, filets of codfish are placed on a moving belt for exposure to high intensity rays
which kill the food-spoiling bacteria in one second. Tomatoes, fish and raw meat have been
sterilized in this way and kept in storage without deterioration for ninety days. This method
of food preservation is still in experimental stage, but may eventually play an important part
in cutting down world food spoilage. (Photo USIS).
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
PLANTS TAKE
OWN PHOTOS
Using radio-isotopes, scientists are today
probing deeply into the greatest secret
of nature how green plants use the
sun's energy to build their substance from the
water and carbon-dioxide of the air, releasing
oxygen in the process. Photosynthesis, as it is
known, is the basic biochemical process under¬
lying all life, since it provides the ultimate
source of food for all living things and replenishes
the oxygen in the atmosphere. It is an apparently
simple reaction in which the molecule of water
and that of carbon dioxide are combined, lose
some oxygen and form starches, sugar, cellulose
and more involved chemical materials. So far
man has been unable to duplicate the process,
but the availability of a faintly radio-?ctive
isotope of carbon has given much information
to scientists and may eventually explain the
reaction completely. Exposed to radio-active
carbon dioxide for only one minute, green
leaves of certain plants were found to have
already manufactured over fifty separate com¬
pounds. Photo, below right, shows one of the
detailed studies of the mechanism of this basic
plant reaction. Isotopes are now widely used
in tracing other complicated plant processes
of growth and food production. Photo, right,
shows an image made by a bean plant containing
radio-active materials. Twenty-five millionths
of a gramme was applied to one leaf. During
the next three days the material was absorbed
into other parts of the plant. In photo below,
tomatoes have "taken their own photographs"
after being tagged with radio-active isotope
and placed on photographic plates. Radio¬
active zinc has concentrated in the seeds.
Experiments like these will not enable man to
dispense with plants for food production, but
may well mean that food production by plants
can be greatly improved. (Photos USIS).
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
Geiger counters on the mosquito's trail
(Continued from page 31)
radio-isotope can be given internally
or can even be swallowed to find its
way into the blood stream. It is
absorbed from the blood by cancerous
tissue. This is one of the respects in
which cancer differs from ordinary
tissue: it does absorb the radio¬
isotope. Consequently, one disease, in
which the red blood cells are formed
in such profusion as to clog the blood
vessels, can be treated by radio-phos¬
phorus which sharply reduces the
production of red blood cells in the
body for a period of about a year.
Isotope's travels
In these cases, the powerful rays are
used directly. But there is an entire¬
ly different use of radio-isotopes
involving small quantities of isotopes
with very faint radiation, far too weak
to do any harm, indeed too weak to be
detected by anything but sensitive spe¬
cialized instruments. These are known
as tracer isotopes because they reveal
their presence by their faint radiation,
wherever they go, no matter through
what chemical reactions they are put,
and thus permit their detection at any
point of their travel or adventures.
By such means it is possible to follow
the course of chemical atoms through
the human body, for instance, and not
only to locate them physically but to
detect the chemical changes through
which they have gone. By far the
greatest use of radio-isotopes is in this
new technique of tracing the course of
mechanical action, of chemical reac¬
tions or biological processes.
Another example of the direct
industrial use of the radiations from
isotopes is the control of the flow of
oil through long pipe-lines. Such a line
can seldom be used for long periods to
deliver one single grade or variety of
oil. Instead, different oils are pumped
through, one after another. It is
important for the operators at the
receiving end to know when one grade
or one shipment is at an end and
another is to begin in the continuous
flow of oil from the pipe.
Radio-active piston ring
This is now done by mixing in a
at the boundary between one
small quantity of radio-active oil
batch and another as they are pumped
into the pipe. When that radio-active
oil reaches the receiving station,
perhaps hundreds of miles away, the
radiation counters immediately detect
its arrival so that valves can be adjust¬
ed to shift the flow from one tank into
another.
Another example from trie on
industry illustrates the use of isotopes
in research. The Shell Petroleum
Company in England now measures
friction and engine wear by exposing
a piston ring to bombardment by
neutrons until a small part of the iron
is converted to a radio-active isotope.
The ring is then fitted in an operating
engine. As it wears by friction the
debris goes into the crank case oil and
that oil is then pumped through a
sensitive detector of radiation. The
very small quantity of weakly radio
active iron is sufficient to be measur¬
ed and therefore to give an immediate
indication of the amount of wear on
the engine. This method of testing
avoids the long operation of the engine
and the troublesome analysis of the
oil for iron, and can show the effect
of different lubricants within minutes.
The California Research Corporation
reports that in similar researches a
programme of friction studies that
would have taken 60 years and cost a
million dollars was completed in this
way in four years at a cost of thirty-
five thousand dollars. Others have
employed this method to show that
high speed driving on the open road
causes only about one-third of the
in the fertilizer. Since it constantly
gives off a weak and harmless radiation
that can be detected by proper instru¬
ments, it is a very simple matter to
follow or trace what happens to the
phosphorus in the soil and the plant.
Important agricultural information
has thus been obtained. For instance,
Swedish investigators have found that
phosphate in a fertilizer is taken up
by the plant roots almost immediately
when it is spread on the soil; there is
no delay. American investigators have
discovered that pasture grasses can
take up phosphate that is spread over
their leaves and roots, so that old
pastures can be rejuvenated by phos¬
phate without the need for ploughing.
^^^ M
in
m, jL^^^^^B
m s ' tjú
I ~~"ÎTGL
^^
TESTING MATERIAL in a special
reactor at an atomic research
centre in the U.S.A. On left, cans
of meat are inserted through the
water canal leading to the reactor.
Tests will show how the meat and
containers have been affected by
radiation. On the right, techni¬
cians are using long-handled tongs
to remove an aluminium tube filled
with radio-cobalt. This will be ship¬
ped away for use in cancer therapy.
engine wear that is involved in city
driving. The end result of these
researches, however, is the reduction
of friction and the ' improvement of
lubrication.
Even mosquitoes can be traced by
radio-isotopes. Mosquito larvae that
swim in a very weak solution of radio-
' phosphorus remain radio-active all
through their lives and their presence
can be detected with Geiger counters.
The habits of mosquitoes are now
being studied by this method to learn
how long they live, how far they fly,
and what they feed on. It is expected
that similar treatment of birds may
give reliable information on bird habits
and especially on their migrations.
Another very practical application of
the tracer technique which has saved
a large amount of money for the
farmers is in the study of the action of
fertilizers.
For example, phosphate is a neces¬
sary plant food and is a component
of nearly all fertilizers. It is an easy
matter to produce the isotope of phos¬
phorus that is weakly radio-active and
to mix it with the normal phosphate
Even more interesting is the fact
that maize, sugar beets, tobacco and
cotton take up phosphate from the
fertilizer only during the early stage
of growth. Fertilizer spread on the
soil late in the season is of no value
to these crops. On the other hand,
potatoes take up phosphate from the
fertilizer in large quantities through¬
out their entire growing season.
Finally, it has been found that
phosphoric acid added to irrigation
water is just as effective as fertilizer
spread dry on the soil. All of these
results were obtained by measuring
the amount of radio-active phosphorus
detected in the growing plant. While
its quantity is small, like the black
sheep in a flock, it can reliably be used
for measuring the fate of all the
phosphorus.
vMany other tracer elements utilized
in this manner have given information
of value to the farmer. Radio-active
potassium, painted on a branch of a
dormant plum tree, in weather below
fieezing point was found to enter the
sap and move several feet both up and
- down the branch in spite of the fact
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Body rebuilt every year
that^the sap is supposed to be motion¬
less in winter. On the other hand, in
summer the phosphorus moves all the
way to the roots within twenty-four
hours.
Another agricultural application of
this tracer technique with radio-iso¬
topes is in the study of insects and
fungi. Radio-iodine has been used to
study the spread of the oak wilt fungus,
through the roots and from the roots
of one oak to another. Insecticides
also can be tagged with radio-isotopes.
Thus it has been shown that plant
leaves absorb insecticides principally
on their under surface and do so only
during the day.
Such work has also emphasized the
difference between broad-leafed plants
and narrow-leafed grain and grasses in
their response to weed-killers. A broad-
leafed plant was found to absorb a
weed-killer sprayed upon it and within
two hours the entire plant is permeated
with it. On the other hand, the grasses
absorb very little weed-killer and
what is absorbed stays on the spot
without affecting the plant as a
whole.
One of the first results of the use
of "tracer" isotopes was the discovery
that all the tissues in the body are
in a constant process of replacement.
It is natural to think of the body as
a stable structure which uses food only
to maintain its heat and for replace¬
ment of worn parts. This is not so.
When fats, in which some of the
hydrogen atoms have been replaced
chemically by "heavy hydrogen" are
eaten, the new fat is deposited in the
fatty layers of the body while the older
fats, already in the body, are burned
for heat.
So, too, eating proteins which contain
"heavy nitrogen" results in the use of
the fresh protein for building body
tissues, muscles and blood cells, while
the proteins already present are
oxidized and excreted. Every part of
the- body is thus constantly being
rebuilt by a steady exchange of new
materials from food to replace the
established materials.
Every twelve months every human
PROTECTIVE TROLLEY is a device used at the
Saclay Atomic Energy Research Centre, near Paris,
10 remove "hot" (highly radio-active) materials from
the Centre's Atomic Pile. Running on rails alongside
GIANT HAND has been built in the United States to enable atomic engineers to carry
out operations in dangerously radiated chambers without exposing themselves to rays.
The "O-Man" (contraction of'"overhead manipulator") weighs I 5 tons and can lift 7,000 lb
loads. It combines enormous strength and gentle dexterity, for, among other feats, it
can rivet, weld, solder, hammer and use a knife. Co-ordinated by remote control levers,
its movement is controlled by an operator in a shielded adjoining room. (Life Photo)!
36
or animal body is completely rebuilt.
Even the bones are thus rebuilt and
the only exception is the iron, chiefly
in the red blood cells, which is not
rapidly replaced by new iron atoms in
the food. This process is a funda¬
mental to life, but would probably
never have been discovered without
the use of tracer isotopes.
Nature's secret process
The most promising investigation
of this sort is the study of the
process by which green plants
build their substance from the water
and carbon-dioxide of the air. . This
reaction is the fundamental one for all
life since all the green plants depend
upon it and all other plants and all
animals depend on the green plants.
It is apparently a simple reaction in
which the molecule of water and that
of carbon-dioxide are combined, lose
some oxygen, and form sugars, star¬
ches, cellulose, and more involved che¬
mical materials.
Nevertheless, no one knows how the
plant does it and man is unable to
duplicate the reaction. But the avail¬
ability of a faintly radio-active isotope
of carbon has already given much
information and may within the next
year or two explain the reaction
completely. This will not mean that
man can dispense with plants for food
production, but it may well mean that
the food production by plants can be
greatly improved once this reaction' is
understood.
The process involves the formation
of carbon-dioxide gas from carbon
which contains a small proportion of
the radio-active isotope of carbon.
The product is "heavy carbon-dioxide"
but is used by plants in the presence of
sunlight exactly as they use ordinary
carbon. The result is that the radio¬
active carbon is built into the materials
of the plant and its presence and
location in the plant can be detected
immediately.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 12. 1954
the reactor it can withdraw isotopes and other
materials which have been activated inside, through
the small square doors seen on left. Its heavy cov¬
ering protects operator from rays. (Photo C.E.A.).
LEAD BRICKS are sufficient protection for minor laboratory operations where only low radiation
strengths are involved. Research worker here is guided by reflection in the mirror. Safety
precautions in atomic laboratories are not intended to give I 00% protection against radio-active
radiations, but rather to ensure that any dose received does not exceed a safe level. (Photo USIS).
When the green leaves of certain
plants were thus exposed to radio¬
active carbon-dioxide for only one
minute, at least fifty separate com¬
pounds were found in the leaf, tagged
with radio-carbon. When the time of
exposure to sunlight was reduced to
two seconds, the leaf had already
manufactured two or three compounds
from the carbon-dioxide of the air.
It turns out that the first products
made by the plant are compounds of
phosphoglyceric acid which thus are
shown to be steps in the manufacture
of fruit, or grain, or sugar. After two
minutes of exposure, radio-carbon tests
showed that even proteins and fats
already contained the new carbon just
received from the atmosphere. The de¬
tailed investigations of these reactions
are now in process and the full mechan¬
ism of this basic plant reaction should
be understood very soon.
By studying the process in different
plants it is now known that the early
stages of the reaction are identical in
all plants. Only later does the process
diverge into the production of com¬
pounds that are characteristic of each
plant, such as aromas, colours, and
drugs. In the case of the green algae,
it has thus been possible to divert the
reaction among the algae so that either
a preponderance of sugar or of malic
acid can form early in the process.
$100 million saving
On this basis, the experiments have
now been continued to show that
the same algae which normally
contain about 50 % of protein can be so
altered as to produce about 75 % of fat
instead of protein. In fact, the protein
content can be varied all the way from
7 % to 88 % , while the fat content can
be changed from 1 % to 75 %. At the
same time, the carbon-dioxide can 'be
changed from 6 % to 38 %. This ob¬
viously opens enormous possibilities
for changing and increasing the food
supplies available both to animals and
to human beings.
These examples are only a few of the
many thousands of uses of radio-iso¬
topes in research, industry, agriculture
and medicine. The U.S. Atomic Energy
Commission estimates that the total
savings accomplished by the use of
isotopes in these various fields is
more than $ 100,000,000 a year. Mean¬
while, the sales of isotopes by the Com¬
mission amount to more than $ 500,000
a year. The European atomic reactors,
especially those at Windscale and Har¬
well in England, are producing radio¬
isotopes that are sent all over Europe.
Radio chemists at Amersham have
achieved results which are distinctive
and in some instances in advance of
the American so that air shipments of
isotopes across the Atlantic are now
considerable.
As more reactors are installed and
the use of atomic energy becomes gene¬
ral throughout the world the produc¬
tion of radio-isotopes will also increase
with a resulting reduction in their
price. One can be certain that the ato¬
mic age is only in its infancy and that
in their impact on history the benefi¬
cial peace-time uses of the atom will
far exceed their misuse in war.
CONCRETE SHIELD weighing 3,000 tons is built around this materials-testing reactor
in the U.S.A. Reactor, in the centre of a large room, is connected by a bridge to a nearby
balcony from where it is operated by remote control. Thanks to concrete shield men
around reactor and on upper platform are protected from radiation. (Photo USIS).
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
METAL PRODUCTION plant in Michigan, U.S.A. makes use of a large quantity of radio-active material for an industrial experi¬
ment. Radio-active powdered iron ore was mixed with ordinary powdered ore and fed into a blast furnace. Measurement of
radio-activity from gases (shown here) helped technicians to decide» on suitability of ore in powdered form for smelting iron.
AUTOMOBILE MANUFACTURERS now save time and money by using radio¬
active materials in testing engine wear. Engine piston rings, made radio-active by
exposure to reactor radiations, are placed upon a piston. The piston is run for
several hours in a test engine, during which time some of the radio-active atoms are
transferred to the lubricating oil. Periodic measurement with a counter shows
how the metal wears and how the oil reacts to friction. (Photo USIS).
OIL INDUSTRY now uses isotope tracers to con¬
trol pipe-line flow. Boundaries between different oils
in same pipe are marked by small injection of
radio-active chemical. Geiger counter at the receiving
end shows exact division between two oils, so they
can be switched to different tanks. (Photo USIS).
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
INDUSTRY'S
NEW WORKER
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
The magic of the atom is now serving many and varied indus¬
tries. Radio-active materials are being employed in dozens
of ways for testing and improving industry's products, making
them faster and easier to produce. Safer drugs and medical
supplies, better motor oil, better quality plastics, improved
automobile tyresthese are only a few examples of impro¬
vements which atomic energy can contribute to progress in
industrial development. As when primitive man first disco¬
vered fire and. gradually learned to make its power serve him,
so men of today gradually are learning how the power of the
atom can be made to work for them.
RADIOACTIVE SOURCE
FOR GAGING THICKNESS
RADIATION
METER CONTROLS
ROLLER SETTINGS
QQC
SOURCE
ADVANTAGES:
I -RADIATION SOURCE SELECTED TO SUIT MATERIAL
2- NO CONTACT -NO TEARINC - NO MARKING MATERIAL
3 RAPID AND RELIABLE
USASC-tOMA
NEW METAL ALLOYS capable of great resistance to heat and corrosion are being sought by metallurgists to aid atomic energy
development. Success of such research will bring benefits of atomic power more quickly to industry, and the new alloys will
almost certainly find,wide industrial uses. Photomicrography (above) of a uranium alloy is an enlarged picture of an etched cross-
section of the metal from which a metallurgist can trace the existence of different physical properties (resistance to corrosion,
mechanical behaviour etc) from local variations in the composition of the alloy. Pencil points to a new "phase"a sudden appear¬
ance of new physical properties in an alloy produced by changes in the proportions of its chemical components. Such "phases"
are clues which guide metallurgists in the production of alloys for special purposes. (Photo USIS).
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
A BIRTHPLACE OF
BETTER PRODUCTION
Laboratories and other research centres are
the places to which industry looks for the
answers to production problems involving the
materials it uses. On this page are shown
some ways in which technicians are using atomic
energy to help improve industry's products.
Radiographs, like the one above, of a telephone,
taken in Gt. Britain with radio-gold, make it
possible to "look inside" products. They are
particularly useful for detecting flaws in castings
and defects in industrial products. Eventually
isotopes may be used for large-scale inspection
of packages, sterilization of food and medical
products. Right, a research engineer In a
U.S. laboratory follows the progress of radio¬
active atoms through internal structure of metal.
He co'unts high speed particles with a Geiger
counter as they shoot out from a small sample
of metal which has been injected with radio¬
active carbon. Lower right, radio-active bac¬
teria are used to test efficiency of various soaps
and detergents, for washing clothing. Bacteria
have been placed on small pieces of cloth which
are then washed. Those bacteria which remain
are easily detected by their radio-activity.
Below, smoother-running, longer-lasting auto¬
mobile parts have their beginning in this "radio¬
active materials room" at an American factory.
Here, technicians are placing a radio-active
distributor point into a standard engine distri¬
butor. After a test run, wear on the point
can be measured from radio-active atoms which
have been transferred to the distributor.
(Photos Crown Copyright Reserved and USIS).
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
How Close
Are We ?
NUCLEAR
POWER IN
NDUSTRY
AUSTRALIA is consi¬
dering the development
of a nuclear power indus¬
try. For fuel she has
vast reserves of raw
material in the form of
uranium deposits. So far
her universities have limi¬
ted their research to
studies of the atomic
nuclei using such ma¬
chines as the Cockcroft-
Walton 1,250,000 volt
multiplier in the Austra¬
lian National University,
Canberra (left). Recent¬
ly, however, it was an¬
nounced that a £ I 2 mil¬
lion industrial nuclear
reactor is to be built
in South Australia, (Aus-
. tralian Official Photo).
It is now ten years since the prospect
of using atomic energy to develop
power for light, heat and the work
of the world began to intrigue scientists
and governments alike. In 1945, when
the world adapted once more to a
relatively peaceful life, it was hoped
that industrial atomic power would
become a reality within ten years.
This has not happened partly because
international tensions have continued
the policy of secrecy and partly because
the engineering problems have been
enormous. The great strides that have
been made in the use of nuclear
reactions and in the design of reactors
have been by-products of the large
expenditures for military purposes.
But in the past three or four years
attention has shifted to the study of
industrial power and to the economics
of the use of nuclear fuels. There has
not been time enough to provide
experience for a realistic forecast in
economic terms. There was, in fact, no
great hope until the American breeder
reactor in May 1953, first showed that,
common and cheap uranium and
thorium can be used as fuels. That
fact has greatly advanced practical
industrial power from the atom.
The development has gone farthest
in the United States because of that
country's active development of react¬
ors during the war and because of the
large economic resources it had
available after the war. Even there,
however, there is as yet no operating
atomic power reactor for industrial
purposes.
The U.S. has constructed more than
a score of major reactors, some for
the manufacture of plutonium and
uranium-235, some for the intensive
testing of materials that are to be
exposed to atomic rays, some to test
the principle of breeding and most of
them to test the feasibility of different
types of reactors, operating on different
fuels, with different intensity of
neutron bombardment, with different
methods of cooling and other mo¬
difications.
In one type, for instance, the fission¬
able uranium is dissolved in water and
the heat of fission causes the water to
boil and generate steam directly. In
another type the uranium is dissolved
in metallic bismuth. Such experiments
will continue, but they have already
produced actual designs for two full-
size power reactors.
The first of these has been installed
in a new type of submarine which
depends wholly on atomic energy for
its. motive power, and which was
launched on January 21, 1954. It
extracts from a small piece of atomic
fuel the equivalent of 460,000 gallons
of fuel oil or 3,000 tons of coal. Consi¬
derations of cost have not entered into
its construction because the advantages
of an atomic engine outweigh the cost.
The submarine can cruise for an
Indefinite period of time under water
because its engines need' no air. It
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
The world atomic power picture
does not need to return for refuelling
because the charge of atomic fuel will
propel the ship for any voyage. The
keel for a second atomic submarine
with improved engines has already
been laid.
The submarine demonstrates the
reality of atomic power without cost
figures. . But experience with its engine
for two years has now justified the
construction on the same basic design
(with enriched uranium as fuel and
with water under high pressure as
coolant) of a full-scale atomic power
plant near Pittsburgh at a cost of
30 million dollars which will produce
60,000 kilowatts of electricity enough
for a city of 60,000 to 100,000 population.
Its power will be fed directly into the
network near Pittsburgh.
Optimism in the U.S.A.
The cost of its power will probably
not be as low as that of power
made from coal, but the U.S.
Atomic Energy Commission will pay
five-sixth of the cost of the plant and
provide the uranium fuel so that the
Duquesne Light Co. of Pittsburgh will
buy the steam from the reactor econo¬
mically. This expenditure by the
government is considered justifiable in
order to gain experience in actual
commercial operation on a large scale
which will make possible the cons¬
truction as soon as possible of another
plant that should produce power as
cheaply as it can be made from coal.
Meanwhile, the American technical
world is fascinated by a variety of
atomic projects, with the electrical
industries taking the lead. Mr. Ralph
J. Cordiner, President of the gigantic
General Electric Company has urged
corporations and private business to
enter the field, and recently told the
National Association of Manufacturers:
ATOMIC AGE CLOCK bu.lt by the
National Bureau of Standards, Washing¬
ton, would require at least 3,000,000
years to lose or gain one second. Scien¬
tist on extreme left is holding a model
of the ammonia molecule whose absorp¬
tion of radio energy provides the inva¬
riant frequency on which clock is based.
"It is our optimistic estimate that by
1976, 50 % of the new electric power
facilities being installed will be atomic."
General Electric engineers have
recently calculated that while a coal-
burning electric plant costs about
$130 per kilowatt of electrical pro¬
ductive capacity, an atomic plant costs
from $195 to $215. This additional cost
is balanced by the fact that the atomic
fuel cost, including the processing of
the uranium and the disposal of
chemical wastes, is only about 0.1 cents
per kilowatt hour of . electricity pro¬
duced, while the coal cost for a plant of
similar size is about 0.35 cents. Thus
the saving in fuel makes up for the
additional cost of the atomic plant and
the total cost
of electricity |H|R^^^^_
from the atom B^.
is 0.67 to 0 68
cents a kilo¬
watt hour
compared with
0.69 cents for
that from
coal.
It is in such
an atmosphere
that the New
England Re¬
gional Atomic
Energy Com¬
mittee has
been organi¬
zed, covering
the six small
states in the
northeastern
corner of the
country, which
have neither
coal nor oil yet
are highly in¬
dustrialized.
Its purpose is to take the first oppor¬
tunity for adopting atomic energy for
the region. Similarly in the western
mountain state of Colorado a group of
four co-operatives engaged in rural
electrification have begun a campaign
to obtain the first atomic reactor for
a small electrical station.
The attractive calculations of costs
are based on large plants; small ones
will be more expensive to operate. Yet
many small plants are proposed for
special purposes. For instance, an able
physicist, Dr. Lyle B. Borst, of the
University of Utah, has . published
designs developed in co-operation with
five railroad and nine manufacturing
corporations, for an atom-powered
locomotive with 7,000 horse power and
a length of 160 feet. It would cost
$1,200,000 but its reactor, of the water
boiler type, would use only 11 pounds
of uranium in a year's operation.
In France, Mr. Louis Armand,
Director-General of the French Railway
System, has commented that it would
be wiser to use a reactor to provide
power directly to the electrified railroad
system. This is true where such a
system exists, as in France and Swit¬
zerland, but the great distances and
lack of electrification in other countries
make the nuclear locomotive a real
possibility.
For other isolated stations that
require power the U.S. Army has
already awarded a contract for the
design and construction of a 2,000
kilowatt nuclear-power, plant to cost
ELECTRIC BULB was lighted for the first time by
atomic energy at the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission's
testing station in December 1951. An atomic plant
powers the generator which supplies all the electricity
for the building in which it is housed. (Photo USIS).
about $2,000,000 which is to be so
constructed that none of its constituent
parts is too large or heavy to be
carried by airplane. A plant of that
size would be adequate to serve a
community of 2,000 persons and could
be carried intact to outlying military
posts, such as those in the Arctic, to
provide power, light and heat.
This is what has been called the
"package power reactor", referred to by
M. Jules Moch before the U.N. General
Assembly. (See page 13.). If it is
successful it may well be_a model for
the small reactors in many countries.
It could, for instance, be flown to desert
areas to serve pumps for irrigation
from underground streams, or to
coastal deserts
for the pro¬
duction of
fresh water
from the sea.
The interna¬
tional atomic
energy agency
will probably
stimulate such
uses.
The 220
pounds of ato¬
mic fuel that
the U.S. has
promised to
provide
through the
international
agency, plus
the 44 pounds
offered by the
British G o -
v er nment,
would be suf-
ficient to
provide fuel
for some 15
research reactors in different countries.
The U.S. Atomic Energy Commission
is continuing its expensive researches
into still newer types of reactors and
has authorized the construction of five
in addition to the score already in
operation. They are of two major
types, one of which uses water as the
coolant and the other liquid metal.
Among them are the "homogeneous"
reactor in which the fuel is dissolved
in a liquid that acts both as moderator
and as coolant and the "fast breeder"
reactor which is compact and operates
at high temperature. The investment
of many millions of dollars by the
government in a wide variety of ex¬
perimental reactors is expected within
a few years to result in a practicable,
reliable and economic design for in¬
dustrial reactors. -
The Chairman of the Atomic Energy
Commission, Admiral Louis S. Strauss
has recently said "Our children will
enjoy in their homes electrical energy
too cheap to meter". He has also said
that by a conservative estimate, only
five years from now 10 % of the new
American power plants will use atomic
energy instead of coal, oil or gas and
that by 1980 half of them will do so.
Such optimism is impressive because it
is made in a country where coal, oil
and natural gas are all plentiful and
cheap and where atomic fuels face
severe cost competition. One may
conclude that in countries where these
ordinary fuels are expensive or must
be transported over long distances the
atomic age cannot be far off.
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Unpsco Courier Nr 12. 1954
POCKET REACTOR was built by the
North Carolina State College, U.S.A. to
train engineers in the use of atomic
energy. Reaction, obtained from ura¬
nium-235 contained in the cylinder,
starts when two of the rods in the
can are lifted by remote control.
Canadian atomic research and pro¬
duction have been closely related to
that of the United States for more
than ten years, especially in the pro¬
duction of uranium ores and the manu¬
facture of uranium. Aside from a
pilot model, the only Canadian reactor
is a large one at Chalk River, with an
energy-output of 30,000 kilowatts and
a neutron flow of 60 million million
neutrons per square centimeter. It
has probably been the world's most
powerful reactor using natural ura¬
nium, and produced large quantities of
highly active radio-isotopes for use in
commerce and research. It was in
operation for more than five years,
from 1947 to 1952 when it was taken
apart for repairs after an accident.
A second large reactor, now being
built and due for completion in 1955,
will cost more than $30,000,000. It will
be more "powerful than the first, will
use heavy water as a coolant and is
designed to permit nuclear engineering
-studies for a future power-producing
reactor. Three large Canadian electric
power companies and the Ontario
Hydro-Electric Commission are asso¬
ciated in the project, though it is
controlled by a crown corporation,
Atomic Energy of Canada, Ltd. This
is in the expectation that future ato¬
mic power generators should be in the
hands of the producers and distributors
of electric power.
Confidence in Britain
The development of atomic power is
more urgent in Britain than in
the U.S. or Canada because the
exhaustion of easily workable British
coal mines is already noticeable. As
a result the cost of coal is slowly
increasing and it is officially estimated
that there may be a deficit of twenty
million tons in the British coal supply
by 1965.
Work on atomic energy did not begin
in England until 1946, however, all
British efforts having been combined
with those of the U.S. and Canada in
North America during the war. That
year saw the beginning both of the
research station at Harwell under the
direction of Sir John Cockcroft and
the production division, with head-
. quarters at Risley, under Sir Christo¬
pher Hinton. The first research reac-
"tor was built at Harwell while a plant
for the manufacture of uranium from
Australian and African ores was built
at Springfields. Two reactors, side by
side, for the production of plutonium
from uranium were begun at Sellafield
on the Cumberland coast in 1947.
By May 1953, confidence in the pos¬
sibilities of power production was
sufficient to justify the start of a full-
scale industrial power, reactor at Calder
Hall, adjoining the Sellafield plant.- It
is now in construction and is expected
to be in operation in 1956. It is de¬
signed to produce 50,000 kilowatts of
power and has a distinctive cooling
system which utilizes carbon dioxide
under pressure to carry the heat to the
steam boilers.
It will probably be the world's first
large-scale power reactor to reach the
operating stage. No cost figures are
available but Sir Christopher Hinton
has stated that "a cost analysis does
not suggest that the price of electricity
generated from atomic energy will
make it uncompetitive" with electricity
from coal. And the British scientific
weekly, Nature, has- expressed the opi¬
nion that "by the time such a station
could be brought into operation, techni¬
cal and economic developments would
give nuclear power very considerable
economic advantages."
A breeder reactor has been in re¬
search operation at Harwell for some
time and the construction at Dounreay,
in Caithness, Scotland, of a large
breeder reactor, which should greatly
reduce costs, has been authorized. In
justifying the government plans, Sir
David Eccles, Minister of Works, em¬
phasized the need of training men
who would design, construct and ope¬
rate reactors not only for Britain and
the Commonwealth but for friendly
countries the world over.
PACKAGED POWER PLANT: An exhibit on the Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy, pre¬
pared by the United States Government, has recently been on display at United Nations
Headquarters in New York. Taken from the exhibition is this model of a "package"
atomic power plant. Broken down into sections, it could be taken by air to a remote
site where regular fuels are unobtainable or too expensive to transport. The plant could
provide electricity for a mining community or pump water to arid zones, and a single
plane could carry enough atomic fuel to run it for several years. (U.N. photos.)
Progress in Russia
On July 2, 1954, Soviet News publish¬
ed a "Statement by the Council
of Ministers of the U.S.S.R."
which read :
"Work on the design and construc¬
tion of the first industrial power station
run on atomic energy, with a useful
capacity of 5,000 kilowatts, has been
successfully completed in the Soviet
Union, by the efforts of Soviet scientists
and engineers. On June 27th, 1954, an
atom-driven power station was put
into operation and generated electri¬
city for the use of industry and agri¬
culture in the neighbouring districts.
For the first time an industrial turbine
is working, not on coal or some other
fuel, but on atomic energy the product
of fission of the nucleus of the ura¬
nium atom. By putting the atom-
driven power station into operation, a
real step forward has been taken in
the utilization of atomic energy for
peaceful purposes."
Speaking to the "First Committee"
of the U.N. General Assembly on No¬
vember 12, 1954, the Soviet delegate,
the late Andrei Y. Vishinsky, repeated
this announcement and added:
"There are no obstacles in the Soviet
Union to the further successful and
rapid progress along this path of uti¬
lization of atomic energy for peaceful'
purposes and the implantation of these
methods throughout our economy...
The Soviet Union State, which has
broad facilities for the extensive pro-
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
IMPRESSIVE PROGRESS has been made during the past ten years in applying the forces of nuclear
fission to peaceful and constructive uses, thus opening up to our own future generations an ever-
expanding prospect of material betterment. After having been rendered radio-active, in nuclear
reactors (above, left), isotopes have been put to work on a thousand tasks for medicine, industry
and agriculture. Great strides have been made in the design of reactors and in the use of nuclear
reactions. More than a score of major reactors, such as the one at Brookhaven National Labo-
duction of atomic energy, is profoundly
interested in the utilization of this new
type of energy for peaceful purposes
and for the well-being of our people
because this kind of utilization of ato¬
mic energy, by countries which are
prepared broadly and extensively to
use it for peaceful ends, would open
wide, tremendous prospects of a vast
growth of productive forces, technolo¬
gical and cultural progress, and the
increased well-being of society."
The historic succession of disting¬
uished research physicists in France,
and the fact that France itself has
large uranium deposits and very large
deposits of thorium in Madagascar plus
its diminishing coal reserves, have all
been factors in the French atomic
energy programme. A small research
reactor was established at Chatillon, a
suburb of Paris in 1948. A second,
larger one at Saclay, near Paris, has
been in operation since 1952, using
pure metallic uranium in a moderating
bath of heavy water. It was designed
for an energy output of 1,000 kilowatts
but delivers more, and may be improv¬
ed to reach 2,000.
A pilot plant in the Rhone valley for
a reactor that will produce 50 to 100
grammes of plutonium per day has also
been planned. This is preliminary to
the construction, also in the Rhone
valley, of two large reactors that will
each generate between 50,000 and
100,000 kilowatts and will produce at
least 75 pounds of plutonium a year,
which will, in turn, permit the develop¬
ment of nuclear engines for marine
vessels. The official expectation is
that there may be industrial utilization
of atomic energy in France within four
to eight years, but that its use by cen¬
tral electric power stations is perhaps
still a dozen years away.
The approach of various nations to
the atomic energy problem varies with
their own needs and resources. Nor¬
way's is influenced by the fact that it
is the world's largest producer of heavy
water, which is made by the repeated
electrolysis of ordinary -water with the
use of very large quantities of electric
power from the Norwegian hydro-elec¬
tric installations. While heavy water
is an effective moderator for some
reactors its price is about $560 a pound,
or close to $1 a drop. A reduction in
the price is needed for larger-scale use,
and Switzerland, Israel, Italy, India
and New Zealand have all been consi¬
dering its production.
In 1951, Norway had under construc¬
tion a reactor to use its heavy water,
but it had no uranium. Meanwhile
Holland had several tons of uranium
on hand that had been farsightedly
purchased when uranium fission first
became a possibility. The two Govern¬
ments therefore organized the Nor¬
wegian-Dutch Joint Establishment for
Nuclear Energy Research at Kjeller,
Norway, under the direction of Dr.
Gunnar Randers. It is supported by
the two Governments through their
Research Councils and scientists of the
two countries work side by side. The
Norwegian firm, Norsk Hydro, which
produces the heavy water, supplied
about half the money for the construc¬
tion of the first reactor and has a
contract with the Norwegian Govern¬
ment for further work on the develop¬
ment of atomic energy. Both Dutch
and Norwegian industries are supply¬
ing funds and obtaining rights for fu¬
ture energy exploitation.
A 300 kilowatts reactor has been in
operation for almost three years for
the production of radio-isotopes and
for studying the feasibility of using
heavy water. Within a few years a
reactor using natural uranium with
heavy water as the moderator will be
built to produce steam at about 250
degrees centigrade and to give from
5,000 to 10,000 kilowatts of power.
Dr. Randers, speaking before the Eco¬
nomic Society of Norway recently,
stressed his opinion that without the
use of atomic energy as a source of
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 	 1954
ratory, from which workers are shown removing "spent" uranium (above, right) have been built
in the United States. - But in the past four years, attention has shifted to the study of industrial power.
Here again, so much progress has been made that authorities in the United States have declared
that in twenty years time half the new electric power facilities then being installed will be atomic.
Scientists say this is only a beginning. They believe the use of atomic energy materials will increase
tenfold or more in the next few years. (Photos Edison Electric Institute and USIS.)
power, the world's population will by
the end of this century be faced with a
power deficiency that will lead to
stagnation or to a lowering of the
general standard of living. In England
Josiah Eccles of the British Electricity
Authority made a suggestion pertinent
to Norway that countries with surplus
hydro-electric power should use it to
concentrate and purify fissionable fuels
such as uranium for export to regions
with power shortages.
Sweden has been producing uranium
for some time and is now increasing its
production from the deposits of oil-
shale at Karnstorp which contain
lumps of kolm, a hydrocarbon that
contains as much as 3,000 grammes of
uranium per ton. Sweden has one
small reactor of 100 kilowatts capacity
which uses three to four tons of ura¬
nium. It is .built in Stockholm in a
special underground chamber hewn out
of bedrock. A 10,000 kilowatts reactor
is to be built by A.B. Atomenergi Co. of
which the Government owns 57% and
fifteen private firms own the remain¬
der. Officials do not believe that ato¬
mic energy will be competitive, with
water power in Sweden until all the
nation's hydro-electric sources have
been put to use, which will presumably
be in about twenty years.
Belgium has long been the world's
major producer of uranium from its
great Shinkolobwe mine in the Belgian
Congo. The uranium has been shipped
in large quantities to the United States
since 1944 under a ten years contract.
Negotiations on this question have been
going on between the Belgian and U.S.
Governments. Belgium wants to re¬
ceive technical information on the
peaceful uses of atomic energy and
nuclear material produced in American
plants that could be so used.
Belgium is now building an experi¬
mental reactor at Mol intended pri¬
marily to train personnel and secure
operating experience. It should be in
operation early in 1956, providing 2,000
kilowatts of power. This reactor is
being financed "without intervention of
the Treasury or of private industry, in
accordance with arrangements of an
international nature", said Pierre de
Ryckmans, Commissioner for Atomic
Energy. Presumably this refers to a
new agreement with the U.S. Atomic
Energy Commission.
Belgium has also signed an agree¬
ment with the Swiss Government
whereby small amounts of uranium
from Belgian ores will be supplied to
Switzerland along with the exchange
of information and experience in the
operation of reactors. The Swiss ex¬
pect to begin construction of a power
ZEPHYR, a fast reactor now operating
at the Harwell Research Centre, England,
is helping scientists to find out more
about the "breeding" process, by which
a reactor creates more atomic fuel than
it consumes. If this system can be deve¬
loped, nuclear energy electricity generat¬
ing systems should operate with smaller
fuel suppliesa major factor ¡n the
prospect of developing atomic power.
(Photo : Britich Atomic Energy Authority)
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
...Into Peaceful and Constructive Paths'
reactor at a cost of about $4,500,000
within a year. It will use natural
uranium and heavy water and will be
classified at 10,000 kilowatts. It is one
of the few that will be privately financ¬
ed and controlled, being built by three
Swiss electrical manufacturing corpo- '
rations. In Geneva, Switzerland also
is host to the large new research ins¬
tallation now being built by the Euro-
nean Centre for Nuclear Research.
This, however, while it will have the
world's most powerful synchro-cyclo¬
tron, will have no reactors nor- fission¬
able materials and has no direct
concern with the production and uses
of atomic energy.
Latin American prospects
All work on atomic energy was
banned in West Germany by the
Allies at the end of the war.
Nevertheless, the Max Planck Institute
of Göttingen has processed and dis¬
tributed radio-isotopes that are flown
in from Harwell in England. The
mining of uranium, with Allied per¬
mission, is now also under way in the
deposits in the Black Forest and the
Fichtel Mountains. Very recently four
major German industrial concerns
have formed a group with 12 others to
build an atomic reactor of 10,000 kilo¬
watts. It is expected to cost $5,000,000
and will operate under severe res¬
trictions intended as military safe¬
guards.
There are as yet no reactors in Latin
America, but a representative of the
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission has
reported on the basis of an extended
trip that uranium is as plentiful as lead
in much of Latin America's subsoil so
that some Latin America countries, ,
using their own uranium, can expect
to base their industrial revolution on
atomic power. Brazil, however, has at
Niteroi, across the bay from Rio de
Janeiro, a Centre of Physical Research
attached to the University of Brazil.
Its cyclotron has been operating for
some years. This development is an
outgrowth of a United Nations Technic¬
al Assistance mission to assist in the
installation of cosmic ray observatories
in Bolivia. One of the exrjerts, Dr. Ugo
Camerini, of Italy, remained in Brazil
to become chief of the Centre's de¬
partment of physics.
Recently these nuclear studies de¬
veloped into government approval for
the establishment of an uranium
treatment plant at Pocos de Caldas, a
spa in the state of Minas Gerais. Ac¬
cording to Admiral Alvaro Alberto,
President of the Brazilian National
Council for Scientific Research, work
will begin within three years on the
construction of a pilot reactor to use
nuclear fuel produced at Pocos de
Caldas. This is the first step toward a
later Brazilian programme for the
production of atomic power for indus¬
trial use.
There have also been reports in the
press that Argentina has developed an
atomic energy pilot plant with a nu¬
clear reactor at Huemul Island, but
this has not been officially confirmed.
One of the major problems of the in¬
ternational atomic energy agency will
be the assignment of priorities for
atomic power development. This will
involve large decisions of policy as to
need and successful prospects of de¬
velopment but one of the members of
the U.S. Atomic Energy Commission,
Mr. Thomas E. Murray, is already on
record as favouring a priority to Japan
which as yet has no nuclear power de¬
velopments. Speaking to a Convention
of the United Steel Workers of America,
one of the major labour unions,
Mr. Murray recommended that the
building of a nuclear power plant
in Japan should be high on the
agenda" of the American Govern¬
ment. He was speaking in Octo¬
ber prior to the discussion of the Uni¬
ted Nations Agency. He urged that
America should express its intentions
and must "give by action and not by
words alone clear and tangible proof of
our own determination to channel the
energy of the atom as soon as possi¬
ble into peaceful and constructive
paths".
India is rich in nuclear raw materials
in the enormous deposits of monazite
sand on the shores of Travancore.
These deposits contain at least a
million tons of thorium in a form that
is easily extracted, and widely scattered
minerals of uranium. The Government
is so conscious of the value of these
materials for India's future as an in¬
dustrial country that the export of
thorium and uranium ores, as well as
those of beryllium, has been sharply
restricted. A plant for the extraction
of both uranium and thorium from
monazite is in operation at Alwaye in
Travancore-Cochin State and a second
plant at Trombay, near Bombay, will
be in operation by May 1955.
Similarly, the Indian Government is
advancing the production of heavy
water at Bagkra Nangal where large
amounts of cheap power are available
and where five to six tons of heavy
water can be produced per year as a
by-product for the production of
250,000 tons of fertilizer. The construc¬
tion of an atomic reactor lies in the
future after the preliminary stages of
the production of uranium, thorium
and heavy water. Nevertheless, India
plans to have her first atomic reactor
in operation by 1958 and adequate
funds have been made available by the
Government to the Indian Atomic
Energy Commission.
India looks ahead
On November 26 and 27, a two-day
Conference on the Development of
Atomic Energy for Peaceful Pur¬
poses in India was held at New Delhi,
and attended by Prime Minister Nehru,
Dr. H.J. Bhabha and some hundred
scientists. Closing the Conference, the
Prime Minister stated that India has a
formal agreement with France which
has yielded good results in that young
Indians are being trained in France for
worK on atomic energy development in
India. There is also a limited agree¬
ment with the U.S. and informal
agreements with Norway and Sweden.
"It is beginning to be realized by
people all over", said the Prime Mi¬
nister, "that something rather basic in
experience has been happening
in connexion with all that has gone on
in recent years in regard to the de¬
velopment of atomic energy. It is
something which gives you some
glimpses... into all kinds of secret forces
of nature. But this tremendous power
suddenly opened out for human use-
can be used for good or evil... it there¬
fore becomes necessary for us to try to
understand it, to try to train our people
in it, and try not to lag behind in this
process."
Unesco's National Distributors from whom
the English edition of THE COURIER can be
obtained are listed below Other Unesco
Distributors are listed in the French and
Spanish editions of THE COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Fnck Verlag, 27, Gra¬
ben, Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop.
551-3 Merchant Street, P.O. Box 222,
Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press,
Toronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., P.O.
Box 244, Colombo J. Rs. 5.
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. 473,
Nicosia.
Denmark : Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Nor-
regade, Copenhagen, K.
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Ethiopia : International Press Agency,
P.O B. 120, Add.s-Ababa.
Finland : Akateeminèn Kirjakauppa, 2 Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I,
Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, I 9, Avenue
Kléber, Pans- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb fur Deutsch¬
land, R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Inter¬
nationale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd., Bombay, Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co., Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Hima¬
laya House, Bombay 7. Rs. 4
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Do. NV.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35,
Allenby Road, P O. Box 5 154. Tel-Aviv.
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Har¬
bour Street, Kingston; Knox Educational
Services, Spaldings.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc , 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J I. Bahous and Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Korea : Korein Nacional Commission for
Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
Liberia : Jacob Momolu Kamara, Gurley
and Front Streets, Monrovia.
Malayan Federation and Singapore :
Peter Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135,
Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kmgsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N. V Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout 9 ,The Hague.
New Zealand: Unesco Publications Centre
7 De Lacy Street, Dunedin, N. E. 2.
Nigeria : C M S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornec, Stortingsplass, 7t
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferozsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar. Rs. 3.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1 1 04 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila. 3.00
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Ltd.,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokhdnde', Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. 20 ticals.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 5 69, London S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Service, 475
5th Ave., New York 17, N.Y.
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Nr 12. 1954
'UNDER WAY ON
NUCLEAR POWER'
The use of nuclear power for the propulsion of
ocean-going vessels became a reality recently
when a U.S. atom-powered submarine, the
Nautilus, began its sea trials and its captain
signalled: 'Under way on nuclear power.' Costs
must be reduced, however, before this form of
propulsion can become commercially practical.
Photos on this page show some aspects of the
development of atomic marine engines in the
United States. (I) The prototype of the
reactor which drives the Nautilus being tested
in its land-based hull at a testing station in the
Idaho desert. Reactor was generating power
when this photo was taken. (2) The same
power-plant seen through the door of the
testing station. (3) The Nautilus being fitted
out in a shipyard. (4) The 225-feet high sphere
at West Milton, New York in which tests are
made of a land-based prototype of a second
nuclear submarine, the Sea Wolf.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
We must ¡earn to live
with the atom today.,.
...TOMORROW
WILL BE TOO LATE
The atomic bomb erupted unan¬
nounced in August of 1945 from
behind an impenetrable wall of
military secrecy. The world was totally
unprepared. Since then every nation
has been revising its military and
political plans to adjust to the global
consequences of that explosion. The
peaceful uses of the power of the atom
have been slower in coming and their
consequences will also be less sudden.
Yet in the perspective of history the
effects will be both large and relatively
rapid.
The new products of science and its
major ideas have always in the past
had far-reaching influence on man's
| way of life and on the social structure,
particularly during the rapid progress of
the past century. Ages ago it was the
invention of the smelting of bronze and
iron from their minerals, or it was the
proof that the earth is a sphere, or the
invention of gunpowder, that led to
large political, geographical and social
readjustments.
The era of machines was made pos¬
sible by Sir Isaac Newton's exposition
of the principles of mechanics. Less
than a century ago Charles Darwin
changed human ideas everywhere by
his theory of evolution. It was the
invention of the steam engine and
the railroad, then the electric motor,
then the internal combustion engine
and the automobile that led to the
development of great cities and the
word "civilization" comes from the
Latin word for city. Still more re¬
cently, medical advances have increas¬
ed the average .length of life from
some 30 years to almost 70 in the
scientifically more advanced countries.
Idea of the century
Each of these developments has
changed the very structure of
society, and has altered human
culture, education and even the attitude
toward religion. Such changes are the
combined effect of the new things and
devices, of new practices in industry,
medicine and agriculture, and of new
philosophical ideas. Together they
are the most powerful of all the forces
48
that continually change life and so¬
ciety, and speed social evolution.
In this century the basic new idea
is Einstein's theory of relativity. This
has as yet hardly begun to influence
popular thinking. But its greatest
consequence today is the fact that, as
Einstein predicted, matter and energy
are not two separate, immutable com¬
ponents of the universe but that they
can by proper means be changed one
into the other.
This is probably the most revolu¬
tionary idea that has come from
the mind of man in all the centuries.
It was a mathematical theory, generally
disregarded, until Otto Hahn and F.
Strassmann in Germany in 1939, con¬
ducting esoteric experiments with
single atoms of uranium, showed that
these atoms, when struck by neutrons,
explode with the annihilation of about
1 % of their matter and the corres¬
ponding generation of an almost
incredible energy.
Fearand its antidote
That was the year in which the
second great World War began
so that the experiment was almost
unnoticed by a frantic world. Yet in
the records of history it will probably
appear as far more important than the
war itself. It proved that Einstein was
right. Only three years later at the
University of Chicago a group headed
by the Italian Professor Enrico Fermi
was generating energy on a respectable
scale by this method and three more
years later the atomic bomb, based on
the same principle, made all the world
realize that a new era had begun.
If science is the most powerful force
acting on society, then Einstein's idea
that energy can be created out of
matter is now the primary force for
change in man's way of life and in his
attitude toward the universe. This will
become evident during the next fifty
years,, perhaps by the end of the
century and that means within the
period when our present youth and
children will inherit the earth.
Science enforces social change. Yet
to the human mind change is seldom
welcome. It is opposed because it is
feared and feared because it is not
understood. The fear of the atomic
bomb is universal and hysterical. The
fear of the beneficent atom will develop
later when its consequent social chan¬
ges become evident. Governments may
decree that such changes are desirable
and will result in improved living for
more people. So they will, probably.
But if means are not taken in advance
to safeguard the individual persons
who will be displaced or whose lives
will be changed, evil results will
accompany the good.
It cannot be forgotten that the
industrial revolution that followed the
invention of the steam engine created
appalling social conditions in England
a century and a half ago, chiefly
because no one foresaw the inevitable
developments. This time consequences
must be foreseen. Above all, the
element of fear must be reduced or
eliminated.
Since fear is usually fear of, the
unknown, the preventative of fear is
education. The United Nations project
for the wide use of atomic energy and
materials must , consider well the
experience in the work of Technical
Assistance to underdeveloped countries,
namely that new powers, new methods
and new wealth cannot be imposed by
the donation of machines and facilities,
however precious, unless they are
understood and are welcomed by a
people that understands them and
wants both, them and their con¬
sequences.
Science-conscious world
The atomic power project is there¬
fore not merely a matter of
placing great nuclear reactors in
countries that need more energy and
more wealth. It requires not merely
the education of scientists and en¬
gineers. Even more it needs a prelimi¬
nary programme that may require years
but must prepare the minds ,and the
hearts of the peoples who are to receive
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier. Nr 12. 1954
ATOMIC-POWERED LOCOMOTIVE shown here only exists today in
Lilliputian form as a model designed at the University of Utah, U.S.A., anticipat¬
ing the day when railroads will make practical use of nuclear energy for power.
Cutaway section (left) illustrates basic principles of the engine. Nuclear
reactor (A) containing a solution of uranium 235 would produce steam which
would pass through pipes (B) to steam turbine (C). Turbine would drive
four generators producing electricity to drive the locomotive. A 500,000
pound steel block four feet thick (D) would protect the train crew from radiation
its benefits for the changes that are
to come.
Such education of the public, and
particularly of the adult public, in turn
means much more than explaining
atomic energy. In a sense it will, in
many lands, require what amounts to
a cultural revolution.
It will involve first the adoption of
the scientific attitude of mind which
is in its essence one of welcoming a
problem to be solved whether it be a
problem in mathematicsf mechanics or
science, whether it be a problem in
economics, world trade or in relations
between social classes or between
nations. In an unscientific culture a
problem of whatever sort is often the
occasion for despair, for violence or for
prayer. Then a problem is a thing to
be avoided because thé answer seldom
comes with it.
But the scientific mind thrives on
problems, analyses them, attempts one
solution after another until the answer
is found, usually on the basis of past
experience or general principles. In
science most problems eventually
though sometimes only after extended
and patient effort find a satisfactory
answer. Thus scientists typically wel¬
come a problem as a challenge to their
intelligence, as an inspiration to their
best thought. Such an attitude will
certainly be needed in the face of the
enormous possibilities that are in¬
herent in the atomic project.
Try it and see
Secondly, an economy based on
atomic energy must certainly adopt
what is often called the scientific
method but which is in fact the simple
method of experiment. Its first im¬
pulse is to "try it and see", if possible
on a small scale, in order to test
whether the idea, explanation or
project is correct or feasible. In the
dawn of the atomic age there will be
numberless concepts and plans in
engineering, public works, legal mea¬
sures and social readjustments, whose
consequences cannot be foreseen for
lack of experience. It will be the part
of wisdom to test such ideas experi¬
mentally and to adopt a conclusion or
a plan after such tests and not hastily
under pressure of emotion or prejudice.
Such considerations are cultural.
They imply not the substitution of
science for an unscientific culture but
the integration of scientific -attitudes
with cultural ideas that have come
down through the centuries, largely
untouched by science. In many in¬
dustrial countries scientific ideas have
perhaps been all too dominant so that
ethical principles and spiritual ideas
have faded. A synthesis would there¬
fore be desirable on both sides. If this
is so, a profound revival of values- is
everywhere desirable.
If the atomic age is to be one of
plenty, of good living and of benefits
both broad and deep in all nations, it
must be accompanied by a revision of
education in. all countries, both ad¬
vanced and underdeveloped, which
must start in the primary schools in-
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
a c i n g up to the problems ahead
deed in the home and hence must start
even further back with the re¬
education of parents and teachers.
If, under the incentive of the
development of atomic power science
thus achieves a place in older cultures
and the scientific attitude and scien¬
tific method become a part of popular
thought, then the practical facts of
life will also result in the assimilation
of a host of incidental concepts and of
new words. Matter and energy, space
and time, will be discussed with
precision, in poetry and in prose. The
concept of velocity, as a change of
position in space in relation to the time
elapsed, will be commonplace.
From proteins to genetics
The difference between quantities
and rates will not always need
to be explained by scientific
writerssuch as the difference bet¬
ween a kilowatt and a kilowatt hour
or the difference between calories and
horse-power. Such simple words from
the world of science will be commonly
understood when energy and power
are everywhere supplied to remote
farms by transmission lines from the
atomic reactors. Common also will be
the understanding of what electricity
is, and electrons, solutions, proteins, vi¬
tamins and hormones. The principles
of heredity and genetics will be
understood to the great benefit of race
relations.
Large principles, such as evolution,
celestial mechanics, the nature of the
planets and the origin of the earth,
will all merely be background for
human studies, not academic specia¬
lities limited to the erudite. Such
topics will be part of the curriculum of
the primary schools and it is in
learning the facts and the logic on
which they are based that children and
adults will learn the methods and mode
of thought of science.
Job for the State ?
If this seems visionary it is because
the time is still far off. Yet it must
come if the human race is de¬
mocratically to solve such problems as
the atomic age will certainly bring
problems such as how to grow enough
food to support the workers that the
atomic industries will require; how to
provide water to the arid zones so that
the population can thrive and use the
electric power that can easily be
brought there; how to provide medical
care to large populations that atomic
energy will make possible; how to
distribute the wealth that great atomic
industries will create and that auto¬
matic factories, perhaps, will convert
into tangible goods; how and by what
steps it will be possible to increase the
standard of living.
These are problems that each nation
must solve for itself. There will be
diverse answers. An example is in the
statement of Prime Minister Nehru of
India who said, in opening the Confer¬
ence on the Development of Atomic
Energy for Peaceful Purposes in India,
on November 26: "No State can allow
atomic energy to be developed in a
private way it is much too dangerous
a thing for a private agency to
develop... it is six years ago that we
envisaged the development of atomic
energy and stated that this is the
exclusive responsibility of the State."
On the contrary, the same problems
h^ve led the United States during the
past year to deprive the Government
of its former exclusive monopoly,
precisely because it was considered
much too large a responsibility to be
left to a central authoritative group but
should be broadly developed through
the various venturesome ideas of
private groups.
There are even larger questions that
will arise. As countries profit from
ample energy and thus increase
their productivity and reduce the cost
of their goods, there will be in¬
creased competition in the inter¬
national markets and radical re¬
adjustments in international trade.
These, in turn, will lead to new
tensions between States. And finally,
in all countries increased production
will mean more things and more money
but it will also mean more free time
for the workers.
In the hard-working industrial
countries this payment of profits in
time rather than in money will present
a major problem. It will, however, be
an unequalled opportunity for the
development of a true culture based
on the assurance of an adequate income
in things and in money plus time to
enjoy them. In the non-industrial
countries, where leisure has often been
more prevalent than money, it will
present a problem of maintaining the
values of a leisurely life while letting
the engines and the machines do the
bulk uf the work.
After such a brief review of the
prospect it is no longer startling to
speak of -a revolution in the world's
work and in its way of life. Perhaps
the term should be "rapid evolution",
not quite so fast as a revolution. In
any case, one's vision must go far
beyond mere nuclear physics and the
technology of reactors. It is obvious
that the coming atomic age requires
foresight not merely from physicists
and engineers but also from educators,
social scientists and exponents of
culture. It requires not only foresight
but planning and action, lest the
revolution overwhelm us. This great
development must be guided for the
benefit of mankind.
World plan for progress
Under its charter, Unesco faces a
new challenge long before it has
solved the problems of the pre¬
sent. Every department of Unesco will
be concerned in the development of the
atomic age and the special functions of
the World Health Organization and the
Food and Agriculture Organization will
also be needed. The Specialized Agen¬
cies of the United Nations will there¬
fore welcome a new Agency when it is
created and will be prepared for the
sake of their member states to co¬
operate in the discussion, the planning
and the operation of a programme for
world development that is inherent in
the programme for the peaceful uses
of atomic energy.
GERALD WENDT
The series of articles on atomic energy
in this issue of the Unesco Courier
was written by Dr. Gerald Wendt,
Head of the Division of Teaching and
Dissemination in Unesco's Department
of Natural Sciences. He is the author
of The Atomic Age Opens and of Atomic
Energy and the Hydrogen Bomb. For¬
merly a professor of chemistry at the
University of Chicago and Dean at the
Pennsylvania State College, he has devoted
recent years to the interpretation of
science and its social consequences in
public lectures, on the radio and by
television. He has been Director of
Education at the World's Fair in New
York, Science Editor of the American
weekly, Time, and Editorial Director of
the 'monthly, Science Illustrated. At
Unesco he organized Impact as a
quarterly journal on the effects of
science on society and is editor of
Unesco Science News. His articles on
science in the Unesco Courier and in
Unesco Features have been translated
into many languages and reprinted in
the newspapers and magazines of a
large , number of countries.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
WORKING TOGETHER on nuclear energy research,
Norway and Holland have set up a joint establishment
at Kjeller, Norway, where a 300 kilowatt reactor has
been in operation for three years, serving the double
purpose of research and of radio-isotope production..
Here, technicians with radiation counters are measur¬
ing the neutron intensity (radiation) at the top of the
reactor. Below the counter the reactor's uranium
rods are visible. (Photo USIS).
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
m
i-
Vrïl
V" '
,V
mm
...,/,v
II I M m
im, , , ;
I Ml Ml
	 M
M
III,
MUMM
M I M M
MIMM
M M M
MIHI
MM M
MMM
MIMM
MMIIII
l M : i i i U
I M II Mil
M M M M II
u niiilll
	IIIMi
	 IHH
II i MIMM
un Ml Ml
MIM""
	 MIHI
IIIIIM»'»1.,
I l U M M M 1 M
Vu ' >AMA'AV
SAFETY SUIT of the type worn by atomic energy plant workers
doing certain |obs where there is danger of exposure to high degrees
of radio-active contamination. Mask prevents the inhalation of gas or
radio-active dust. Constant vigilance is exercised and, in fact, workers
In atomic energy plants are in far less danger of injury from radiation
than are other workers from the ordinary hazards of industrial life-
burns and scalds, cuts and bruises. Leakproof suit shown here is
entered by the worker from an adjoining room through a plastic tunnel
which culminates in the suit itself. It is part of an exhibit on the
Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy held recently at U.N. Head¬
quarters, New York, and is being examined here by Mrs. Lakshmi Menon,
a representative of India to the General Assembly. (U.N. Photo).
]]>
</page>
</document>
