<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="072293eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
FEBRUARY 1987 9 French francs
$k
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Festival in Bavaria
Festivals and folk traditions abound in the Alpine region. Above, near
Bad Tölz, a spa town and tourist resort in the Bavarian Alps (Fed. Rep.
of Germany), a grandmother and her granddaughter, wearing hats
typical of the region, take part in a religious festival in honour of St.
Leonard of Noblat. Blessings are bestowed on horses during the festival,
which is held each year on 6 November. Popular in the Limousin region
of central France, the cult of St. Leonard of Noblat is also practised in
Belgium, in Italy, and above all in the south of the Federal Republic of
Germany and in Austria.
51 Federal Republic of Germany
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
From the Ligurian Sea, between Genoa and Nice, to Vienna,
Ljubljana and the Adriatic coast, the Alps stretch in a broad, arc-
shaped band through seven European countries: France, Italy,
Switzerland, the Federal Republic of Germany, Liechtenstein,
Austria and Yugoslavia. Over 1,000 kilometres long and with an area
of almost 250,000 km2, they are Europe's most important mountain
system. Their width varies from some 50 km between the plain of the
Po and the Gulf of Genoa in the west, to over 200 km in the Tirol
between Austria and Italy in the east. Alpine ridges and peaks, rising
in many places to over 4,000 metres, reach their highest point in Mont
Blanc (between France and Italy) at 4,807 metres.
The Alps are one of Europe's most important hydrographie
systems. Three of the continent's greatest rivers and their major
tributaries rise there the Rhine, the Rhône and the Po, as well as
some of the main tributaries of the Danube. Scattered through the
Alpine chain are over 4,000 lakes, including Lakes Geneva (France
and Switzerland), Constance (Fed. Rep. of Germany, Switzerland
and Austria), Neuchâtel (Switzerland), the Chiemsee (Fed. Rep. of
Germany), and Lakes Garda, Como, Lugano and Maggiore (Italy).
For thousands of years this vast mountain system has formed a
distinct historical and cultural region. Man crossed the Alpine passes
in early times, leaving many traces of his presence such as the rock
engravings of Valcamonica in Italy and the finds unearthed at
Hallstatt in Upper Austria and La Tène in Switzerland, sites of major
archaeological importance which gave their names to periods of the
Iron Age in western Europe. Today the Alps are a focal point of the
communications system linking northern and Mediterranean Europe,
crossed by many road and rail passes (the Brenner, the St. Gotthard,
the Great and Little St. Bernard, the Mont Cenis) and tunnels such as
the Simplón, the St. Gotthard, the Fréjus, the Mont Blanc, the San
Bernardino, the Arlberg and the Great St. Bernard.
The Alps also constitute a remarkable example of mountain
ecology. Over the centuries man has left a strong imprint on them by
painstakingly creating a remarkable landscape and economy, the
balance of which is today in many cases threatened by modern
developments.
Germanic, Latin and Slavonic elements have largely contributed to
the composition of the Alpine population. But demographic and
linguistic variety does not preclude the existence of strong common
cultural features, such as the affinities which characterize the folk
music of different Alpine countries.
This issue of the Unesco Courier is an attempt to trace some salient
features of the Alpine world which is the geographical heart of
Europe, as well as a great historical and cultural centre and a leading
tourist attraction.
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
February 1987
40th year
In harmony with nature
The making of the Alpine landscape
by Leo Lienert
When men and mountains meet
Unesco ecology projects in the Alps
by Jörg Schaller
The great transalpine routes
by Bruno Parisi
The Walser
Migrant farmers who settled in high places
by Paul Zinsli
Grenoble, France's high-powered
mountain city
by Pierre Frappât
The Alpine culture of Slovenia
by Matja2 Kmecl
Getting to the top
The conquest of the great peaks
by Peter Meyer
Horn of plenty
by Brigitte Bachmann-Geiser
Song without words
The art of yodeling
by Mario Müller
The ranz des vaches
Distant echoes of an old Swiss melody
by Guy Métraux
The ALPEX experiment
An international study programme
on Alpine meteorology
by Roger Newson
Lakes and glaciers of the Alps
by Heinz Löffler
11
14
16
18
24
29
31
32
34
36
A time to live...
FED. REP. OF GERMANY: Festival
in Bavaria
Cover: climbing in the Aiguilles chain near
Chamonix (France), in a range of granite
peaks (average height around 3,500 m),
which forms part of the highest massif of the
Alps and provides a variety of testing climbs
for mountaineers. Back cover: the
Königssee, near Berchtesgaden in the
Bavarian Alps (Fed. Rep. of Germany). The
impact of tourism and other human activities
on the ecosystem and economy of the
Berchtesgaden National Park (208 km2) is
today being studied as part of Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme. See
article page 9.
Photo Jean Gaumy © Magnum, Paris
Photo Kurt Wagner © Berchtesgaden National Park, Fed.
Rep. of Germany
The Courier
A window open on the world
English
French
Spanish
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 32 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational ,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
German
Arabic
Japanese
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
ISSN 0041-5278
N°2-1987-CPD-87-l-442 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
In harmony with nature
The making of the Alpine landscape
by Leo Lienert
WHEN we talk of the Alps, we
usually think of the mighty arc
of mountains extending
across much of Europe from Marseille on
the Mediterranean to Vienna in the east.
But the word alp (or alpage) also means
"high mountain pasture". How did this
double meaning come about? Probably
because in former times people were only
interested in the useful parts of moun¬
tains passes and the pastureland on
their flanks.
It was only much later that the terrible
beauty of the Alpine peaks came to be
appreciated. Gradually the town and city
people began to wish to climb the Alps
instead of simply crossing them. To reach
the summits they had first to cross the
high pastures, and the "back to nature"
fashion found an embodiment in the life
of the Alpine herdsman. Life in the Alps
became a symbol of nature, of man's true
vocation.
The well-tended, varied landscape,
restful to eye and mind alike, that can be
admired in the Alps is not the creation of
nature alone. It is the result of stubborn
and patient work by mountain farmers
and foresters who slowly and
painstakingly created the cultivated
environment to which we are
accustomed. Today, it is our respon¬
sibility to preserve this environment, and
hand it down intact to future generations.
This can be achieved only by a com¬
prehensive environmental protection
policy.
Most of today's meadows, heathlands
and fields were wrested from the pri¬
meval forest by human effort. Except
The perseverance of many generations of
mountain farmers has shaped an Alpine
landscape whose harmony is the result of
a fragile balance between the action of
nature and the hand of man. This balance,
on which the Alpine economyandenviron¬
ment depend, must be protected against
excessive pressures from the consumer
society. Right, a village in the Dolomite
Alps in northeastern Italy. The Dolomites
are Italy's leading Alpine tourist centre,
with such well-known summer and winter
sports resorts as Cortina d'Ampezzo.
24 SO 7S km
FRANCE
A
OV0*
BAVARIA
/
ZECHOSLOVAKI A
Der***
®
.
7 N
T-7COI »un LIECHTENSTEIN. ,_- _____ v
TZERLAND vj*«/» -nw ALP5 **#«»< .tí** _ Z
*í imm» ,iT*"' CENTRAL ALPS O^
^T; °"A *&* a " .s"""~< «««i. -^
S KM««, '"*A TT;
r. .. .. _T? A»* .n .... J
iMi
. PK"
Maççor* £o",°
Bulto ArtiiK)
L|ubi|*n*
YUGOSLAVIA
^
Zw<>
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
where there are lakes, peatbogs, steep
rocky slopes, scree and eternal snows,
forest is everywhere the natural vegeta¬
tion. All grassland situated beyond the
limits of the forest must therefore be
tended if it is to be preserved. It is a
transitory formation which, without con¬
stant human toil, would soon become
overgrown and would subsequently
revert to native forest. Secondary forest
has grown in areas which have been
farmed and later abandoned.
As soon as human settlement in the
Alps began, the forests began to be
cleared and burned. They receded before
the grassland established near the earliest
villages. A number of sources show that
Alpine agriculture developed rapidly in
the late Middle Ages. Encouraged by
population growth and a period of mild
climate, the mountain pastures were
intensively exploited. Villages were grad¬
ually established up to an altitude of 2,000
metres . Large tracts of forest were felled ,
and unfortunately felling also took place
in areas where trees were indispensable in
order to retain the topsoil. As a result,
many disasters avalanches, uncon¬
trolled torrents, rockfalls, landslides
occurred on the edge of forests and on
steep slopes. During this period the first
mountain roads were made and the first
defences against erosion were con¬
structed.
The farmer's task is not only to provide
food for the population but to tend and
safeguard the agricultural landscape,
which is a reflection of human activity
and hence of culture. One of the main
characteristics of natural areas such as the
Alps is their wealth of plant and animal
life. The advent of modern farming meth¬
ods geared to maximum profit (especially
single-crop farming) has seriously
impoverished the environment as compe¬
tition with industrial output has forced
farmers to increase production and use
more fertilizers and chemicals. This is a
dangerous situation. Exploitation of the
natural heritage of soil, water and air for
exclusively economic ends must stop.
Instead, these resources should be hus¬
banded as well as possible, taking
account of the requirements of plants and
animals, as well as human needs.
The dwindling of botanical and animal
species is due to the shrinking of their
habitat and to changes in farming meth¬
ods. In all biotopes regions uniform in
environmental conditions and in their
populations of animals and plants there
is a strong interdependence between
flora and fauna, and any reduction or
change in type of grassland has drastic
consequences for the animal life associ¬
ated with it. For example, if areas of dry,
sparse, hot grassland are more intensively
cultivated, grasshoppers disappear. Sim¬
ilarly, dragonflies, frogs, and certain
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
In recent years the rich variety of flowers
and animal life in the Alps has been dwin¬
dling because their habitat is shrinking
and because of the increasing use of ferti¬
lizers and pesticides in agriculture. The
ecological balance is thus being distur¬
bed. Above, from left to right, three exam¬
ples of Alpine animal life: two specimens
of the rock ptarmigan (Lagopus mutus),
camouflaged against the snow by their
whiteplumage; two male Alpine wildgoats
(Capra ibex) in combat; an Apollo butterfly
(Parnassius apollo).
One way of coping with the problem of
avalanche risk is to use artificial means to
trigger off avalanches when there is no
one around. Below, a young French¬
woman from the resort of Alpe-d'Huez,
Haute-Savoie,one of few women to do this
dangerous job, is about to hurl a stick of
dynamite. When it explodes on the slope it
will start the avalanche.
birds which are extremely useful for
maintaining the equilibrium of natural
living communities, can no longer find
food or reproduce when pools, ponds or
marshland disappear. Biologists realized
some time ago that destruction of the
ecological balance is far more of a threat
to living species than hunting or gather¬
ing. In the Alps, therefore, emphasis
must be placed on overall protection of
the environment, on the care and mainte¬
nance of the biotope in a state which, if
not entirely natural, is at least close to the
true Alpine nature.
The key to the efficient maintenance of
an agricultural landscape close to nature
is use of the land according to methods
that are geared to the natural conditions
in the area in question, and preservation
of the necessary habitat of indigenous
plants and animals. A thorough knowl¬
edge of local conditions is indispensable.
Study and mapping of the local geology,
soil patterns and plant resources will lead
to an understanding of the ecological and
biological environment: planning of the
Alpine economy must be based on the
findings of such research. Land use
geared to local conditions will involve
separating forest from pasture, and tend¬
ing wooded areas as carefully as grass¬
land. The forest is protected if livestock
are kept out of it, and new stands of
young trees can grow in safety.
It has long been known that only
healthy and regularly renewed forests
afford protection against avalanches.
Less well known is the fact that the main¬
tenance or neglect of mountain slopes
also does much to determine avalanche
risk. Short grass, for instance, offers
snow a good hold. Long, withered grass
lying flattened in a downhill direction
forms a surface that favours sliding and
thereby increases the risk of avalanches.
In other words, every ungrazed slope and
every unmown strip of grass is a potential
danger.
The factors determining avalanche risk
therefore change radically when styles of
mountain farming change or disappear.
Remote slopes, where in the past skiers
could venture without danger, suddenly
become death traps. New avalanche cor¬
ridors soon threaten roads, railways and
villages. In such areas, protection must
be provided by avalanche barriers, dikes
to contain torrents, and by costly
reafforestation. But avalanches hurtling
down unwooded slopes have undesirable
long-term consequences as well as being a
source of immediate danger. When snow
freezes, clinging to stalks of dry grass
which have been left unmown in the
autumn, an avalanche will carry down all
the grass with it and, even more impor¬
tant, all the topsoil in which it is growing.
After such a disaster, only bare rock or
loose stones remain. The descending ava¬
lanche becomes a rushing mass of earth
and mud. In its wake, nothing will grow,
and the gaping wound will not heal; the
CONTINUED PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Thepeople of the Alps have always been aware of the need to
protect their environment and with it their way of life both
against natural hazards andsometimes a more difficult
taskagainst the consequences ofhuman activity. (1) A floo¬
ded meadow at Feldmoos Glswil In the Swiss canton of
Obwalden. (2) Anti-avalanche barriers. (3) Ski-slopes In the
Swiss canton of Graubünden (Grisons), during the summer.
The grass has totally disappeared as a result of erosion
caused by skiing. (4) Barriers channel an Alpine torrent at
Rotmoosgraben in the Obwalden. (5) Two kinds of Alpine
meadow separated by a fence: at left, grass cropped by
livestock; at right, grass mown for hay.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
scar merely spreads as the years go by.
Gradually the whole region becomes
defenceless against ever greater torrents
of snow, mud and stones and all
because the grass on the slopes was no
longer used!
Making and maintaining paths and
flights of steps is the responsibility of the
local communes and the owners of moun¬
tain pastures. When the latter are no
longer used, it is difficult to find road-
menders, especially if the forestry
authorities cannot take over the task of
their upkeep. All hikers should remem¬
ber that, stone by stone and step by step,
the paths leading them through the
mountain scenery that they so much
admire were made by skilful and hard¬
working men who knew how to turn the
land to the best advantage, digging
ditches and building retaining walls
where necessary. At any moment, snow,
snowmelt and landslides can destroy the
results of this painstaking work, unless
they are constantly maintained and
repaired.
In the mountains, maintenance of a
forest that is healthy and close to the nat¬
ural state is the central task of landscape
protection. All forests even those
grown for timber must be properly
cared for and managed. The quality of
the forest soil can be maintained only
when the trees are regularly replaced: the
forest's health depends on this. For
example, in recent decades, there has not
been enough grazing for cloven-hoofed
game animals, with the result that these
animals were often forced to feed on
shoots and saplings. This jeopardized
efforts to renew the forest, and it became
necessary to reintroduce predators which
had died out, such as the lynx, in order to
restore the balance between the forest
and its natural inhabitants. If forests were
left alone, the new growth of young trees
would be inadequate, and there would
not be enough protection against ava¬
lanches, flash floods and rockfalls.
It is the mountain farmer who, from
generation to generation, has created
today's Alpine agricultural landscape,
and he alone can maintain and safeguard
it effectively. At the same time, many
mountain farms depend on tourism for
their survival. This clearly demonstrates
the interdependence of the different eco¬
nomic sectors and the absolute necessity
of joint planning. In the context of such
planning and its implementation pri¬
ority should be given to safeguarding the
landscape by providing economic
security for mountain farmers.
Every living mountain landscape has a
character of its own, expressed in its lan¬
guage, customs, architecture and crafts.
This variety makes a particular region a
home for its people. Every valley that
loses its inhabitants and every village that
dies is an irreplaceable loss. We can no
longer afford such losses and such
damage.
LEO LIENERT is a former forestry engineer at
the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology,
Zürich. After working in the Royal Forestry Admi¬
nistration in Sweden and the Forestry Depart¬
ment of the Principality of Liechtenstein,'he was
appointed director of the Cantonal Department
of Land Improvement and Forests, Obwalden,
Switzerland. Among his published works are
Naturschutz in Obwalden (1970, "Nature
Conservation in Obwalden") and (as co-author)
of Alpwirtschaft und Landschaftspflege im
Gebiet Glaubenbüelen, Obwalden (1972, "The
Alpine Economy and Landscape Protection in
the Glaubenbüelen District of Obwalden").
An engineer performs an acrobatic feat to
repair the wheel of a ski-lift at Flaine, a
French winter sports resort in Haute-
Savoie. Tourism is essential to the Alpine
economy today and enables many Alpine
farms to survive. At the same time, only the
mountain farmer who has created the
Alpine landscape can effectively maintain
andpreserve it. The differentsectors of the
Alpine economy are today interdependent
and planning must take into account and
reconcile the interests of all concerned.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Unesco ecology projects in the Alps
by Jörg Schaller
When men
and mountains meet
THE aim of Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) Project 6 in
the Alpine region is to reveal the
impact of interrelationships between eco¬
nomic activities, land use and ecology
and to identify and describe those pro¬
cesses which jeopardize the long-term,
sustained protection of the mountain
region as a living space, an area of econo¬
mic activity and a recreation zone.
The research fields and major problem
areas were defined by MAB experts in
1973 as human settlements at high alti¬
tudes, land use in the mountains, the
impact of large-scale technical installa¬
tions in mountain areas, and the effect of
tourism and recreational activities on
mountain ecosystems.
Out of a total of 160 MAB 6 projects
throughout the world, 85 concern
research into the ecosystems of high
mountain areas and 10 of these apply to
the European Alps (see map). These
investigations result from the successful
integration of scientific disciplines into
regionally co-ordinated research projects
largely designed to meet practical re¬
quirements.
Thanks to close geographical proxi¬
mity, many publications on the subject
and personal contacts between MAB
researchers in the Alpine region, an
^t^pKP^y^rv
A*M*
#*
JSi» _
m
Jff\ «jp^ -#*p a%>
/**
-ft
*>.
1. Aletsch, Switzerland
2. Berchtesgaden, Fed. Rep. of Germany
3. Briançon, France
4. Aime, Haute Tarentaise, France
5. Pavos, Switzerland
6. Grindelwald, Switzerland
7. Obergurgl, Austria
8. Hohe Tauern, Austria
9. Pays d'Enhaut, Switzerland
10. Salzburger Alpen, Austria
Map shows ten sites in the European Alps
where research into the effects of human
activities on mountain ecosystems has
been carried out as part of Unesco 's inter¬
national Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
programme. Above, cattle grazing below
the Grossglockner, the highest peak
(3,797 m) in the Hohe Tauern range of the
Eastern Alps. Winter sports, mountain¬
eering and beautiful scenery make the
Grossglockner a major tourist attrac¬
tion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
exchange of experiences has been possi¬
ble which has led to a substantial im¬
provement in research methodology and
the transferability of methods.
Case studies on the impact of different
activities on natural resources have been
carried out in all MAB projects in the
Alpine area. They relate essentially to the
land-use impacts of agriculture, forestry,
tourism and housing development, which
are often in conflict with efforts to protect
natural resources. Typical problem areas
studied are mountain pastures, the effect
of erosion on fertilization and cultivation
at high altitudes, the protection and res¬
toration of mountain forests, the disap¬
pearance of wild game populations, dying
forests and the resultant problems such as
landslides, reafforestation, the negative
effect of traffic, damage to vegetation,
the massive impact of summer and winter
tourism (walking and skiing), as well as
the aesthetic impact of changes in
methods of cultivation or the intro¬
duction of infrastructural equipment for
tourism.
In many conservation areas there is the
additional question of protecting endan¬
gered plant and animal species or symbio¬
ses, as well as of monitoring ecosystems in
Alpine regions that have hitherto been
largely undisturbed. For example,
through research at the MAB test sites of
Grindelwald (Switzerland), Berchtesga¬
den (Fed. Rep. of Germany) and Haute
Tarentaise (France), the possible impact
on the ecosystem and regional economy
of holding the Winter Olympics was
examined.
The results of MAB research in the
European Alps point to three fields of
practical application which are exceptio¬
nally important for the future develop¬
ment of the sustained management of the
natural system on which human life in the
Alps is based.
Practical tools for dealing with com¬
plex ecological problems have been deve¬
loped and can be applied to other moun¬
tain regions.
Thanks to the case studies, bases for
decision-making have been created
which will enable politicians to introduce
the long-term demands of the sustained
management of resources into everyday
policy.
Valuable stimuli and ideas for long-
term research into ecosystems and the
permanent observation of Alpine ecosys¬
tems can be drawn from the results of the
MAB Research Project because, thanks
to its integrated approach, limited
research resources can be concentrated
on priority areas and on acute problems.
Grindelwald in the Bernese Oberland, near
Interlaken, is a leading Swiss mountain¬
eering, summer and winter sports resort.
The impact of tourism and recreational
activities on natural resources is one of
the major questions being studiedby MAB
research projects In the Alps.
JÖRG SCHALLER, of the Federal Republic of
Germany, is an agricultural engineer speciali¬
zing in landscape ecology and landscape plan¬
ning. Since 1984 he has been director ofa lands¬
cape planning bureau and manager of the
Environmental Systems Research Institute
(ESRI) in Kranzberg, near Munich. He is director
of research into the ecosystem of the Ber¬
chtesgaden Alpine and National Park, Bavar¬
ia, one of the test sites in Unesco's Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) Project 6: Impact of
Human Activities on Mountain Ecosystems.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
,.¿ -C
u
:-1
N
, *fl
<* -t
n \TJ
_j m
The great transalpine routes
by Bruno Parisi
THE Alps carry more traffic than
any other mountain system in the
world. The total length of roads
and railways is 405,000 kilometres. Over
this network between 1978 and 1982
passed an annual average of 87 million
tonnes of goods, 78 million passengers,
and 6.8 million light and heavy motor
vehicles. Most of the main routes are the
same as those which have been used for
the last 3,000 years, since the time when
the technological revolutions in the use of
bronze and iron took place in the Alpine
region.
Archaeological findings show that
about four centuries after the foundation
of Rome in 752 B.C., there were at least
forty settlements in the Alps, each of
which had a relatively large, stable popu¬
lation predominantly engaged in extrac¬
ting and working copper and iron. Judg¬
ing from investigation of their ancient
burial grounds, there were such settle¬
ments at Hallstatt (near to what is now
Salzburg, in Austria) and La Tène (Lake
Neuchâtel, in Switzerland), two major
sites which have given their names to Iron
Age cultures.
As early as the second century B.C.,
the Roman historian Polybius knew that
there were four passes over the Alps
one through Liguria, two through the
The "Julian columns", top, stand at the
highestpoint of the Julier Pass (2,284 m) in
the Swiss Alps. Of Celtic or Roman origin,
they are shown here in an engraving from
a guide to routes across the Alps written
by the Swiss naturalist Johann Jakob
Scheuchzer (1672-1733). Above, the
modern road across the St. Gotthard Pass
in Switzerland (2, 1 12 m).
kingdom of the Taurini and the Salassi,
and another through Resia. The route
that Augustus made into a highway
doubtless led to the first of these. Near to
this highway, in A.D. 13, he erected a
monument in Turbia, near Nicala (now
Nice) to mark the subjection of forty-five
Alpine tribes. This road continued west¬
ward to the port of Massilia (Marseille),
which the Phoenicians had made a centre
of the tin trade. The second pass was
probably the Col de Montgenèvre; the
third may have been either the Little
Saint Bernard or the Great Saint Ber¬
nard, and the fourth was probably the
Brenner Pass.
The Mont Cenis Pass, by which Hann¬
ibal crossed the Alps in 218 B.C. with
20,000 infantry, 6,000 cavalry and 27 ele¬
phants and, after him, his brother
Hadsrubal was used by the Romans in
their wars against the Gauls and to pro
tect Marseille. It is the only pass of which
we have a detailed description by later
classical writers such as Strabo (first cen¬
tury A.D.) and Ammianus Marcellinus
(fourth century).
There were no surfaced roads over the
Alps before Roman times, only paths by
which the mountains could be crossed on
foot, by donkey or on horseback.
Nothing was done to make these old
tracks into roads for wheeled traffic until
12 B.C., when the emperor Augustus
built the Via Julia Augusta, a coast road
with extensions into several transalpine
countries. A few years later the great
highway from Verona to Pons Drusi
(Bolzano) was begun; it went as far as the
Resia and Brenner Passes, and it was
known as the Via Claudia Augusta
because it was completed by the emperor
Claudius.
The Roman legions and settlers were
thus able to make their way across all the
main Alpine passes by excellent roads,
along which large, stable settlements
appeared.
In the early Middle Ages, after the fall
of the Roman Empire and the collapse of
the old pagan civilization, the ethnic sub¬
divisions that we know today were com¬
ing into being in the enclosed feudal
world of the Alpine region. But along the
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
old Roman roads, which made contacts
between people easier, Christianity was
gaining ground as a result of the work of
evangelists. Evidence of the spread of
Christianity can be seen in the chain of
monasteries in the Alps, from the early
eighth-century abbey of Disentís (in what
is now the Swiss canton of Graubünden),
to the monasteries of Pfäfer, San Can-
dido, Scharnitz (near Partenkirchen),
and Kremsmünster (founded as the base
point for the conversion of the Slavs), and
the monasteries on the Great Saint Ber¬
nard, the Simplón and Mont Cenis.
In the Middle Ages the Via Claudia
Augusta of Antiquity was still the main
route across the central Alps. There was
Early 18th century engraving of the Devil's
Bridge across the Schöllenen gorges in
the upper valley of the Reuss river, which
rises in the Aare-Gotthardmassif (Switzer¬
land). The gorges were impassable until
the Devil's Bridge was constructed in the
13th century, giving access to the St. Got¬
thard Pass and opening up one of the great
transalpine routes.
no real improvement until the demo¬
graphic and socio-economic revival early
in the second millennium A.D.: in 1237,
the Schöllenen Pass from the Devil's
Bridge to the Saint Gotthard the
so-called "people's road" was opened.
The opening at that time of good roads
capable of carrying wheeled traffic was
due mainly to the efforts of the great mer¬
chants who wished to trade in the urban
fairs. Thus the road over the Simplón,
which was not used for a century after
1450, was reopened through the efforts of
Kaspar von Stockalper (1609-1691), a
typical figure of the pre-capitalist mer¬
chant era, who became known as the
"king of the Simplón". Then the Fischer
family of Berne set up a regular postal
service over the Simplón; similar services
were set up along other roads the
Splügen, the Saint Bernard and the Saint
Gotthard. Goods were still conveyed by
long trains of pack animals.
The modern network of roads across
the Alps only began to take shape in the
first half of the nineteenth century, when
many carriage roads were built. As early
as 1801-1805, Napoleon gave orders for
the construction of a new highway across
the Great Saint Bernard; as much as 8.4
metres wide in places, and 63 kilometres
long, it had 611 bridges and seven tun¬
nels. The modern highway over the Mal-
oggia Pass dates from 1839.
The situation began to change more
rapidly with the coming of steam, which
in turn was stimulated by strategic consid¬
erations that led to the construction of the
first railway line in the Alps, the Semmer-
ing line (Austria) in 1854. A few years
later the Brenner line (1867) and the Fré-
jus line between Piedmont and France
(1871) were built. After the invention of
nitroglycerine and of the pneumatic drill
a number of railway tunnels were built (a
total of 250 kilometres): the Saint Got¬
thard (1882), the Arlberg (1884), the
Simplón (1906) and the Caravanche and
Wocheim tunnels on the Salzburg-Trieste
line. Besides these great international
tunnels, national railway lines were built,
mainly to attract tourists. Notable among
them was a line opened in 1898, which ran
through a tunnel under the Kleine
Scheidegg and rose to a height of 3,457
metres above Interlaken in the Jungfrau
massif.
Since then the importance of roads has
grown steadily, with the development of
motor traffic, the introduction of asphalt¬
ing, protection against avalanches and
the ventilation of tunnels. In this decade,
the volume of traffic across the Alps
amounts to 20 per cent of the number of
passengers and 15 per cent of the goods
transported in the EEC countries.
In recent years the Mont Blanc (1965)
and Saint Gotthard tunnels, together
with the Great Saint Bernard, San Ber¬
nardino and Fréjus (1985) tunnels and
the Tarvisio motorway (1966) have been
the principal factors in the extension of
the road network in the Alps.
Modern transport technology has also
played an important role in the installa¬
tion of pipelines, which in 1979 conveyed
43 million tonnes of hydrocarbons from
Liguria, the Padua region, Trieste and
the Swiss canton of Valais, to Ingolstadt
(Bavaria) and Vienna (via Linz), and in
the development of high-tension electri¬
cal lines.
BRUNO PARISI, of Italy, is associate professor
at the Facoltà di Magisterio (teacher training
faculty) ofMilan and Brescia, director of the Insti¬
tute of Geography at the Catholic University of
the Sacred Heart, Milan, and president of the
Central Scientific Committee of the Italian Alpine
Club. Among his published works are "Funicular
Railway Transport in the Service ol Tourism in
the Alps" and "Geographical Bibliography of the
Alps".
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Pass of St. Gotthard (c. 1803-4), oil on canvas by the English painter
Joseph Mallord William Turner (1775-1851). The work reveals the
artist's amazing skill at painting mountain peaks glimpsed through
swirling mist and anticipates the atmospheric effects that he was to
obtain in later paintings.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The
Walser
by Paul Zinsli
Migrant farmers who settled in high places
THE Walser were peaceful moun¬
tain farmers who in the late Mid¬
dle Ages left their homeland in
the Upper Rhône valley, in what is now
the Swiss canton of Valais, and founded
new, widely scattered settlements in high
valleys where they lived in seclusion
among groups of earlier settlers who,
unlike them, spoke a Romance language.
To a certain extent they have managed to
preserve their identity and especially
their language, a distinctive old German
dialect, up to the present day.
For centuries scholars argued about
the origin of these "Alpine Germans".
Some thought that they were the original
inhabitants of the region. Others main¬
tained that they were descended from the
guards posted at the Alpine passes by the
powerful German Hohenstaufen family.
According to other hypotheses, they
were the descendants of the Cimbri, the
Carrying his implements and provisions
on his back, a Walser mountain farmer
sets out for his Alpine hut in the Graubün¬
den highlands.
Teutoni, the Saxons, the Frisians, the
Swedes, the Huns or even of the
Mongolian prince Genghis Khan! They
have also been referred to as Burgun-
dian, Goth or Lombard peoples.
Scientific research long ago showed
that the original home of the Walser peo¬
ple was in the Rhône valley. Early four¬
teenth-century documents refer to them
as Uli de Wallis or "those from the Val¬
ais". Feudal charters and documents of
enfranchisement granted to the inhabi¬
tants of the Rheinwald valley (now in the
Swiss canton of Graubünden), in the late
thirteenth century, specify the origin of
these immigrants. After leaving the
Conches valley (now in the Swiss Valais),
most of them passed through Val For-
mazza in Italy on their way to the Raetian
area of the Central Alps.
This migration, which took place
within a short space of time, was a curious
event. With great boldness, this small
group of farmers from the Upper Valais
scattered in all directions, despite the
obstacles of the rugged terrain, and set¬
tled over an exceptionally wide area.
The Walser have accumulated long experi¬
ence of farming at high altitudes in places
where the rugged Alpine terrain might
have discouraged a less tenacious people.
Lett, a typical Walser barn perched on a
hillside in the Swiss canton of Ticino.
In the south, some of them settled in
Val Formazza. They built new villages on
the upper reaches of nearly all the valleys
on the southern flanks of the Alps
between the Simplón and Theodul
passes. In the far west, in Savoy, there
were once two small Walser settlements,
significantly known as Les Allamands. In
the north they settled in the catchment
area of the upper Aare River and, still
further afield, their settlements extended
into the Bernese lowlands. Their exodus
eastwards took them beyond the present
frontiers of Switzerland, to the slopes of
Liechtenstein until, finally, they spread
into the Vorarlberg region.
Initially it is probable that only small
groups of families and their modest
herds, consisting mainly of goats, left to
set up new homesteads far away. The
vitality of these emigrants must have been
considerable, enabling them to survive
the losses that they suffered. It is
recorded that each family had many
children.
Why was this small group of farmers
seized by a sudden compulsion to mig¬
rate? Several hypotheses have been put
forward: overpopulation of their original
homeland, climatic changes or invasions.
However, recent research has established
that the Walser were forced to move by
feudal landlords. In the Bernese Ober¬
land the people of Lötsch were even sold
as serfs to the monastery of Interlaken.
On the Italian slopes of the Alps, heredi¬
tary rulers with estates on both sides of
the mountains installed their solid Ger-
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
manic farmers to defend the passes and
the pasturelands.
In return the landowners often had to
grant certain freedoms to their subjects.
Those who had emigrated to Val For-
mazza, for example, obtained highly
favourable conditions for settling and
cultivating the land. The Rheinwalder
who emigrated further afield expressly
cited these time-honoured "customs"
when, like the Walser of Davos
(Graubünden), they secured not only full
individual freedom of movement based
on contracts of hereditary fief, but also
the right to have their own independent
judicial bodies.
As they settled on still uninhabited or
sparsely colonized Alpine lands, the Wal¬
ser acquired new territory. With the
tenacity of those bred to mountain life,
they cleared the forests, built new home¬
steads and worked the higher pastures to
obtain winter fodder, living exclusively
by cattle raising and dairy farming.
Naturally the Walser colonies changed
in the course of time. Entire districts once
settled by the Walser again became
Romanized, many communities were
unable to cope with the hardship of living
at rugged heights and disappeared, while
others were submerged by the social
upheavals of modern life and lost their
originality.
The Walser had rarely been allowed
to settle anywhere except at high alti¬
tudes where the land could not be culti¬
vated permanently. It was in such areas
that the bright mountain sun, healthy air
and winter snow came to attract moun¬
taineers and winter sports enthusiasts
from the lowlands. No wonder, then, that
world-famous resorts developed on Wal¬
ser soil.
fc ¿/
One example is Davos, where owner¬
ship of the land was confirmed by charter
in 1289 to a Walser, "Wilhelm dem
amann [William the Bailiff] and his com¬
panions in fair tenure". In today's busy
holiday town only some 200 of the 10,000
inhabitants still speak the pure local Wal¬
ser dialect.
Everywhere, but especially on its most
easterly borders, the old, robust Walser
speech is dying out, and with it the
heritage of a vigorous, dynamic people.
PAUL ZINSLI, of Switzerland, is a professor
emeritus at the University of Berne, where he
formerly taught the language, literature and folk-
studies of German-speaking Switzerland. He is
the author olWalser Volktum ("Walser Folk Heri¬
tage", 5th edition, 1985).
The village well at Alagna, on the Italian
slopes of the Alps, a region settled by the
Walser.
The challenge of living in rugged, isolated
surroundings schooled the Walser in
resourcefulness and self-reliance. Above,
an elderly couple in Graubünden.
A mountain village in the eastern Swiss
canton of Graubünden. Migrant groups
belonging to the Walser, a people whose
original home was in the upper Rhône
valley, settled in the high, secluded val¬
leys of this region from the 13th to the 15th
centuries.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Grenoble
France's high-powered
mountain city
by Pierre Frappât LOCATED in southeastern France
between the massifs of Belle-
donne, Chartreuse and the Ver-
cors, Grenoble is the biggest city in the
Alps, demographically speaking. Although
it made its name as a dynamic Alpine city by
hosting the 1968 Winter Olympics, Greno¬
ble today is primarily an industrial city.
Its most famous son, Stendhal, the author
of Le Rouge et le Noir, wrote at the begin¬
ning of the nineteenth century: "Everything
that is low and flat in the bourgeois spirit
reminds me of Grenoble; everything that
reminds me of Grenoble fills me with hor¬
ror; no, horror is too noble a word: with
nausea." In Stendhal's time Grenoble had
only 20,000 inhabitants; today, counting the
outer suburbs, it is a conurbation with a
population of between 400,000 and
525,000; and everything, or almost every¬
thing, has changed.
The spectacular expansion of Grenoble is
the result of two waves of industrialization.
The first was linked to hydroelectric power,
and was triggered off in 1869 when the
engineer Aristide Berges (1833-1904) har¬
nessed the energy potential of a high water¬
fall at Lancey near Grenoble. Hydroelectric
power was to stimulate the development of
a wide range of industrial activities, inclu¬
ding electro-metallurgy, boilermaking and
the manufacture of electrical equipment,
some of which still go on today. The second
wave of industrialization took place in the
1950s and 1960s, and is associated with the
French scientist Louis Néel (Nobel Prize for
Physics, 1970), who founded the Grenoble
Centre for Nuclear Studies. While a highly
diversified pattern of industry continued to
exist, there was an increasing emphasis on
research which encouraged the rapid
growth of the electronics industry.
In the space of twenty years, the popula¬
tion of Grenoble almost tripled, rising from
147,000 in 1954 to 388,000 in 1975. At this
Afore than halfof the workingpopulation of
Grenoble are employed in industry. Lett,
an employee ofa leading French electrical
company whose activities are centred on
Grenoble and the surrounding region.
period Grenoble led all other French cities
in demographic growth.
Immigration was the essential factor in
this population growth. At first the new
migrants came from the nearby mountains
of the historic French province of Dau-
phiné, which underwent rapid depopula¬
tion in the second half of the nineteenth
century. The Pre-Alps of Chartreuse and
the Vercors, but above all, the Matheysine
plateau and the Oisans massif south of Gre¬
noble, and even the more distant massifs of
the Briançonnais and the Maurienne, sent
what were in many cases the most enterpri¬
sing members of their population to try
their luck in the flourishing city. Whereas
the people of Savoy, another nearby pro¬
vince, left the region (winning a name for
themselves as "little chimney-sweeps" in
Paris) the mountain people of the Dauphiné
found their openings nearer home.
However, the mountains only provided a
quarter of the new population of Grenoble.
Most of the immigrants came from else¬
where in France or abroad, as part of an
influx that illustrated the growing attraction
of Grenoble. The newcomers filled the
ranks of the two social groups that are
characteristic of Grenoble: the industrial
workers who constituted as much as 42 per
cent of the labour force in 1968(31 percent
today), and the higher executives and
supervisory staff who today make up some
32 per cent of the city's working popula¬
tion.
Immigrants of non-French origin were an
important source of industrial labour. Bet¬
ween the wars the non-French element was
already substantial (18 per cent of the popu¬
lation). Today foreigners may constitute no
more than 13 or 14 per cent of the total, but
many of them are well integrated, especially
the Italians, who mostly originate from sou¬
thern Italy. Several thousand Grenoblois
originate from the little town of Corato in
Apulia. The Italians of Grenoble are stron¬
gly attached to their identity; they have
their own Catholic parish, a radio station
broadcasting in Italian, and even a Juventus
supporters' club which crosses the Alps to
attend football matches in Turin. But today
the most numerous foreigners are Alge¬
rians, Tunisians and Moroccans. Attracted
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
to Grenoble at a time when big public works
projects were in full swing, they are tending
to settle in the city, many of them with big
families. They now account for about 5 per
cent of the population.
The very high percentage of executives
and supervisory staff, which is the salient
feature of Grenoble society, is due to the
large number of technicians, engineers,
researchers and teachers employed in high-
technology industrial activities, research
centres and universities. Grenoble was one
of the first French cities to refute the pessi¬
mistic thesis advanced by the economist
Jean-François Gravier in 1947 in his book
Paris et le Désert Français; it became, espe¬
cially in the 1960s, a centre of social, cultu¬
ral and political initiatives.
In the last ten years new trends have
appeared as a result of which Grenoble has
lost its distinctive character in demography
and in many other fields. The balance of
migration is now negative and the popula¬
tion has stabilized. It is true that more
people are leaving the city than before
Grenoble has always been a place where
--*- -,.
.'^SbHHHBB
people come and go but above all far
fewer are moving in. The mountains no lon¬
ger send emigrants, the influx from other
countries has slowed to a trickle.
On the other hand, continuing executive
and other immigration from within France
shows that Grenoble has not lost its power
to attract, in spite of an economic crisis from
whose effects it is to some extent, but not
entirely, spared. Non-French companies,
international laboratories and universities
have also attracted highly qualified people
from outside France who have brought Gre¬
noble a degree of international standing and
added to the diversity of a city whose site at
the foot of magnificent mountains has
always been a crossroads and meeting place
of peoples.
PIERRE FRAPPAT, of France, is an economics
teacher in Grenoble and a contributor to the
Rhône-Alpes regional edition of the French daily
Le Monde. His published works include Greno¬
ble, le mythe blessé
Photo © A. Muñoz de Pablos, Paris
Above, view of Grenoble and its river, the
Isère, against a backcloth ofsnowy moun¬
tains.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Alpine culture
of Slovenia
by Matjaz Kmecl
THE Slovenes are a Slavic people
who settled long ago in the south¬
eastern part of the Alps, in a
region where the jagged limestone peaks
of the Julian and Savinian Alps slope
down towards the Dinarides, and to some
extent in the plain of Pannonia. Nowa¬
days, the vast majority of the Slovenes
live in Slovenia, the most northerly of the
Yugoslav republics, although another
substantial group has its cultural and his¬
torical centre at Klagenfurt (Celovec) in
southern Austria. There is also a group in
an area of north-eastern Italy stretching
from Trieste to the Carnic Alps, and a
small Slovene community in Hungary.
There are some two million Slovenes in
these areas; if the members of the far-
flung Slovene diaspora are counted, they
number between two and a half and three
million.
This region, opening onto the Adriatic
in the south, forms an east-west corridor
through which many peoples have passed
in the course of history. Those who
crossed it in a southeasterly direction
include the Romans, the Crusaders, and
the armies of Napoleon and Hitler; those
who struck westwards include the Rus¬
sian General Suvorov and the armies of
Austria. In the sixteenth and seventeenth
centuries, the region lay on the route of
Turkish incursions into central Europe
from the south.
The ancient "amber road" and many
medieval trade routes passed through
Slovene territory, which was also a con¬
duit through which many ideas of the Ital¬
ian Renaissance spread eastwards. The
Slovenes played an important role in the
foundation of the university of Vienna,
and after the Reformation were instru¬
mental in taking Protestant. ideas and
writings into the Balkans. Around 1560,
Ljubljana, the Slovene capital, already
had its own printing press, and the first
Slovene translation of the Bible appeared
in 1584.
In short, Alpine Slovenia on the Adria¬
tic was a staging-post between the Roman
and Germanic worlds of western Europe
and the Slavic east, between Venice and
Vienna, Italy and St. Petersburg.
Under these influences, an original
Slovene culture took shape over more
than a thousand years. Among its many
creative figures were Herman Sclavus of
Carinthia, a monk, astronomer and theo¬
logian who translated the Qur'an into
Latin in the twelfth century and dreamt of
bringing about a synthesis of Islam,
Christianity and the paganism of Anti-
Above, Yugoslavia's highest peak, Mount
Triglav (2,864 m) dominates a popular
mountaineering and winter sports region
of the Julian Alps in Slovenia. The sacred
mountain of the Slovenes, Mt. Triglav ("the
three heads") is also a pilgrimage centre.
In the words of the Slovene writer Julius
Kugy, "Triglav is not a mountain but a
kingdom. "
quity; the great sixteenth-century poly-
phonist Jakob Handl (also known as
Jakob Carniolus Gallus, 1550-1591);
Anton Jansa (1743-1773), one of the
founders of modern European apicul¬
ture; the mathematician Jurij Vega
(1754-1802), who revised the logarithmic
tables; Marko Anton Plencic (1705-
1786), who discovered the principle of
microbial contamination; Friderik Jernej
Baraga (1797-1868), linguist, missionary
CONTINUED ON PAGE 23
Colour page opposite
Above, Ansicht von Arco (1495, "The Arco
Valley"), watercolour and ink by the Ger¬
man Renaissance artist Albrecht Dürer
(1471-1528), who visited Italy for the first
time in 1494. He remained until the fol¬
lowing spring and painted a number of
watercolours of the Alps of the southern
Tirol, which rankamong his mostbeautiful
works.
Photo © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Louvre, Paris
Below, Paysage à Maloja (Piz Margna)
(1924, "Maloja Landscape [Margna
Peak]"), oil on canvas by the Swiss sculp¬
tor and painter Alberto Giacometti (1901-
1966). TfíeMaloja Pass in the Swiss Alps,
at Borgonovo, where Giacometti was born,
is near the village of Stampa (canton of
Graubünden). The artist, who settled in
Paris in 1922, often returned to his birth¬
place in later life.
Photo Pierre Gianadda Foundation, Martigny© ADAGP,
1987, Paris. Private Collection, Switzerland
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
r-^< r¡¿..
3& ^lÁ- *
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
iS&fac
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
a
d
*^í
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Covered racks for drying hay (right) are a
familiar feature of the landscape in the Slo¬
vene Alps where the rainy climate often
prevents hay from drying in the fields after
being mown. The racks are made from a
piece of fencing topped with a roof. In
another variant, not shown here, the roof
rests on two pieces of fencing which
enclose a sheltered space where the far¬
mers store their tools. ^
Colour pages
I 2 3 4
5 7
8
6
Centre pages: (1) Cross-country skiing
race at Autrans (France). (2) Vineyards in
Liechtenstein, a tiny European principality
(160 km2) in the rugged foothills of the Cen¬
tral Alps, with a population of 27,200
(1984). The mild climate, affected by the
warm southerly Foehn wind, permits culti¬
vation ofgrapes, unusual in such a moun¬
tainous area. (3) Haymaking In the traditio¬
nalstyle in Valle di Gardena, northern Italy.
(4) View of Hallstatt, near Salzburg. This
little Austrian town, whose saltmines have
been worked continually since 2500 B.C.,
gave its name to the firstmainperiod of the
European Iron Age. In 1846 a vast ancient
burial ground was discovered at Hallstatt,
excavations over the nexthalfcenturyyiel¬
ding a mass of finds of major archaeologi¬
cal importance, including bronze and iron
objects remarkably well preserved by the
salt. (5) Grenoble (France) is the major
Alpine city. Its numerous industries
include the manufacture of plastics, rub¬
ber, cement and paper. A centre for
nuclear research and electronics, Greno¬
ble hosted the Winter Olympic Games in
1968. (6) The Nösslach Bridge on the high¬
way across the Brenner Pass, one of the
lowest (1,371 m) and most important pas¬
ses through the main chain of the Alps on
the Austrian-Italian border. (7) The Mont
Blanc massif, crowned by the highestpeak
(4,807m) in western Europe, lies along the
French/Italian border. It owes its name
("White Mountain") to the 100 km2 of gla¬
ciers which cover its slopes. (8) Ranks of
ripening Gruyère cheeses. A hard cow's-
milk cheese, Gruyère takes its name from
the region of La Gruyère in southern Swit¬
zerland. The wheel-shaped cheeses are
aged for at least 3 to 6 months, although
some may be allowed to ripen fora year or
more.
Photos: 1 . J. G. Jules ©ANA, Paris. 2. S. Weiss© Rapho, Paris.
3. H. Gritscher © Rapho, Paris. 4. H. Gritscher© Rapho, Paris.
5. O.Meot ©Explorer, Paris. 6. H.Grltscher©Rapho, Paris.
7. H. le Campion © ANA, Paris. 8. E. Mandelmann © Rapho,
Paris
Lett: Detail from Hunters in the Snow by
the great Flemish painter Pieter Bruegel
the Elder (c. 1525-1569). Bruegel travelled
to Italy in the 1550s, and his appreciation
ofthe sublimity ofAlpine sceneryacquired
on the journey was of fundamental impor¬
tance for his art. In this famous depiction
of a winter scene, the artist mingled ele¬
ments of the Alpine landscape with that of
the Low Countries.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18
and bishop, who was one of the first
authors of grammars and dictionaries of
the amerindian languages of North
America; and many more, scattered
around the world.
It was not until 1918 that the Slovenes
were enabled to have their own univer¬
sity, but for centuries before that Slovene
scholars and students had made a brilliant
contribution to European university life,
and even today there are many Slovene
intellectuals and artists in universities and
scientific institutions all over the world.
The nineteenth-century French writer
Charles Nodier, an admirer of the poly¬
glot Slovene culture, pointed out how as a
result of their cultural history all Slovenes
mastered two or three living languages in
addition to their own.
Slovenia is a densely wooded region:
half its area, or more than one million
hectares, is covered with forest. Its
wealth of animal life includes bears,
wolves, ibex, marmots and chamois, and
its plant life is equally abundant (some
seventy endemic species). There are
many natural caves in the limestone Karst
region.
Characteristic features of the land¬
scape are small Baroque and pre-
Baroque churches built on the uplands,
covered racks with harp-shaped roofs to
shelter the hay from the rain which falls
when the south wind meets the barrier of
the Alps, and castles in varying states of
preservation.
Traditional forms of art and craftsman¬
ship still survive. They include lacework
from the town of Idrija, naive paintings
which have been used to decorate bee¬
hives for two centuries, and regional cos¬
tumes. Male and female choirs such as the
Slovene Octet sing serious pieces of
music a cappella, and instrumentalists
play versions of the Alpine tunes known
in central Europe as the music of Upper
Carniola (Carniola is the ancient name
for Slovenia), which have been moderni¬
zed by groups such as the Avsenik
Quintet.
Among its achievements in the fine arts
Slovenia can point to the school of archi¬
tecture founded by the Slovene architect
Joze Plecnik (1872-1957); the Impressio¬
nists of central Europe, notably the
painter Anton Azbe (1862-1905), who
founded a school of painting in Munich in
1891 at which almost all the leading Slav
Impressionists studied, as well as Wassily
Kandinsky and Nadezda Petrovic (1873-
1915); and the Ljubljana school of
graphic art. The major figures of Slovene
literature include France Preseren (1800-
1849), who had affinities with Byron and
Pushkin, and is considered to be the
greatest Slovene poet; the prose writer
Ivan Cankar (1876-1918), creator of the
psychological short novel and of social
drama, and the short story writer Ciril
Kosmac (1910-1980).
An episode from recent history may
help to explain how such a small people
has managed to survive without losing its
identity and its language. The Slovenes
gave proof of their tenacity during the
Second World War when they mobilized
an army of partisans in their mountain
fastnesses and maintained a backbone of
national institutions. Then in 1945 the
Republic of Slovenia was created within
the Socialist Federal. Republic of
Yugoslavia. As the emblem of their coun¬
try the Slovenes chose their highest
mountain, Mount Triglav (almost 2,900
metres high), "the three heads" which
has nourished a host of their legends and
beliefs since they became an Alpine peo¬
ple almost 1,500 years ago.
One of the last massifs in the eastern
Alps, Mount Triglav is the sacred moun¬
tain of the Slovenes; one of its heads
looks to heaven, another to earth and the
third to the underworld.
MATJAZ KMECL, Yugoslav playwright and
essayist, teaches history and the theory of litera¬
ture at the University of Ljubljana. His published
works include Mala literarna teorija (1978,
"Concise Literary Theory") and Rojstvo slovens-
kega romana (1981, "Birth of the Slovene
Novel").
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Getting to the top
Above, the Vrsic Pass in the People's
Republic ofSlovenia (Yugoslavia) crosses
the Julian Alps not far from Yugoslavia's
frontier with Italy and Austria. The moun¬
tains towering above the pass, some 2,400
metres high, are rocky bastions of jagged
dolomltlc limestone. For centuries such
magnificent Alpine scenery filled travel¬
lers with fear and even revulsion.
ANYONE who studies the history
of the opening up of the Alps
might by forgiven for thinking
that until the eighteenth century these
mountains were a deserted wilderness.
Writers on the subject are fond of quoting
from early travellers who describe the
mountains as "dreadful", "repellent",
even "hideous" stretches of bare rock and
ice, reactions which today seem astonish¬
ing. Such was the accepted view from
Roman times until the eighteenth cen¬
tury. The great Italian poet and humanist
Petrarch, who in 1336 wrote an enthusias¬
tic description of a journey he had made
to Mont Ventoux in Provence, was for
centuries a notable exception to this gen¬
eral rule. Even the Zürich municipal doc¬
tor Johann Jakob Scheuchzer (1672-
1733), otherwise an enlightened scientist
and scholar who is regarded as one of the
founders of modern paleontology,
seriously maintained that the mountains
harboured dragons!
This was how the mountains appeared
to the occasional travellers from out¬
side scholars, merchants, soldiers
who came from the lowland cities and
towns. However, a history of the Alps
written "from the inside" would tell a dif¬
ferent story. Many big Alpine valleys
were already inhabited in pre-Roman
times, and it is clear that this mountain
population had a different, much more
natural, relationship with the mountains
where they lived. By the early Middle
Ages, many valley farmers owned "alps" ,
pastures high up on the sides of the val-
In this terrifying depiction ofan avalanche
from a 16th-century chronicle, a massive
ball of debris and flailing branches
crushes everything in its path.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The conquest of the great peaks
by Peter Meyer
leys where they grazed their cattle during
the summer. From the twelfth to the fif¬
teenth century still higher mountain
regions up to about 1,600 metres
were permanently settled and farmed, in
many cases by the Walser, an ethnic
group which migrated from the Swiss
Valais and established farming commu¬
nities in wide areas of the central Alpine
region (see article page 14). It is also
known that at a very early stage a number
of Alpine passes were regularly used for
trading and also occasionally for mili¬
tary purposes. Finally, the Alps were
mined for salt, iron ore, and silver, an
activity which brought wealth to some
and provided a means of subsistence for
many more.
This mountain world cannot, there¬
fore, have been as terrible as the trav¬
ellers' tales cited above would have us
believe. But even if there are no dragons,
life in the mountains is hard even today,
full of privations and fraught with danger.
It is also true that until very recently the
snow-covered peaks, which are for us the
most important and fascinating feature of
the mountain landscape, were of no inter¬
est to anybody. Until the eighteenth cen¬
tury, they were shown on maps in a very
summary fashion and many were
unnamed. Only villages, passes and
Alpine pastures were indicated. Even
where the description "mountain" or its
Latin equivalent mons appears, it usually
signifies not a mountain but a pass or a
pasture. Perhaps one or two peaks had
been climbed by local people, but such
ascents had not been reported and so the
world took no notice.
The eighteenth century brought a big
change, marked at the outset by a new
approach to nature. People became not
only more sensitive to the attractions of
nature, but also, under the influence of
the writings of authors such as Albrecht
von Haller (1708-1777) and Jean-Jacques
Rousseau (1712-1778), showed a fresh
interest in the real or imaginary charms of
country life. Stimulated by this romantic
longing, the European élite then began to
travel to the Alps, thus laying the founda¬
tions for Alpine tourism, which expanded
rapidly in the nineteenth century.
Once the attractiveness of mountains
and their inhabitants was recognized,
sporting feats soon began to be accom¬
plished, the first of which was doubtless
the ascent of Mont Blanc (4,807 metres)
in 1786 by a doctor, Michel Paccard, and
a hunter and mountain guide from Cham-
onix, Jacques Balmat. Thus the conquest
of the highest Alpine peak took place,
not at the end but right at the beginning of
a long series of mountaineering exploits.
(The ascent was repeated in the following
year by a leading Geneva naturalist,
Horace-Benedict de Saussure [1740-
1799] who inaugurated the era of scien¬
tific research in the Alps with a series of
interesting experiments and measure¬
ments, including the barometric deter¬
mination of the height of the peak.)
After the conquest of Mont Blanc,
mountaineers turned to other of the high¬
est and most challenging Alpine peaks.
This humorous depiction of "An Alp-
climber" kitted out for a mountaineering
expedition appeared as an illustration in
Mark Twain 's travel book A Tramp Abroad
(1880). The Alpine tourist is carrying an
alpenstock, a long iron-tipped stick once
widely used by hikers and mountain¬
eers.
The first to be conquered almost a
quarter of a century after Mont Blanc
were the two highest Austrian peaks: the
3,797-metre-high Grossglockner (1800)
and, four years later, the Ortler (3,905
metres, now in Italy). The latter would
probably have been climbed first were it
not for the fact that people then believed
the Grossglockner to be the higher of the
two. The ascent of the Grossglockner was
a full-scale expedition in which sixty-two
persons took part. The Ortler ascent was
much more like modern Alpine moun¬
taineering in the sense that the chamois
hunter Joseph Pichler who made the
ascent was accompanied by only two fel¬
low climbers.
These achievements were soon fol¬
lowed by other feats, outstanding among
which were the first ascent of the
Jungfrau (4,158 metres) in the Bernese
Drawing of the "Lindwurm ", an evil dragon
which, according to a legend from the tiny
Alpine country of Liechtenstein, once ter¬
rorized the people of Mais, a little town
near the Rhine. After vainly trying to get rid
of the Lindwurm, the townsfolk begged the
Virgin Mary to help them. Their prayers
were answered and the dragon disappea¬
red from the face of the earth. (Even today,
certain crevices in the rocky cliffs over¬
looking Mais are known as "dragon
holes. ") Located between Switzerland and
Austria, Liechtenstein is an independent
principality (160 km2) with a German-
speaking Catholic population. The capital
is Vaduz (5,000 inhabitants).
Photo from Sagen aus Liechtenstein ("Tales from Liechtens¬
tein") by Otto Seger, Jahrbuch des Historischen Vereins für das
Fürstentum Liechtenstein, 1 966
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
->j;
s
x
©
S
j.
.y- /
'.h-
r*1 '
1
.-
-/*;.
... >:
-
Alps in 1811 by two industrialists and nat¬
uralists from Aarau, Johann Rudolf and
Hieronymus Meyer, and the first ascent
of the Zugspitze (2,962 metres), Ger¬
many's highest peak, in 1820, as part of a
cartographical mission by Lieutenant
Karl Naus and two companions. These
expeditions were followed in 1850 by the
ascent of the Piz Bernina (4,049 metres),
the only peak in the Eastern Alps higher
than 4,000 metres and in 1855 by the first
ascent of Switzerland's highest peak, the
4,634-metre Dufourspitze in the Monte
Rosa massif. In 1865 the first ascent of the
Matterhorn (4,478 metres), reputedly the
most beautiful mountain in the Alps, hit
the headlines because a tragic accident
occurred during the descent, in which
four members of the expedition, led by
the Englishman Edward Whymper, per¬
ished. This was the first catastrophe of
the early days of Alpine climbing but
typical of this sport it acted not as a
deterrent but as a spur to further feats by
climbers who, after the highest peaks had
been conquered, began to undertake
ever more difficult climbs.
Mí
rr
©
Above, Storm Breaking over a Village in
the Foothills of the Alps, a drawing by Leo¬
nardo da Vinci (1452-1519). With Pieter
Bruegel the Elder and Albrecht Dürer (see
colour pages), who both crossed the Alps
on their way to Italy, Leonardo was among
the first European painters to depict the
grandeur of high mountain scenery.
Drawing of the Via Mala by Johann Wolf¬
gang von Goethe (1749-1832), dated 1
June 1 788. This Alpine route leading to the
Splügen Pass was extensively used in
medieval times, although it was known as
"the bad road" because of the gorges
through which itpassed. It has come back
into use since the opening of the San Ber¬
nardino road tunnel.
<
The Geneva-born writer and philosopher
Jean-Jacques Rousseau (1712-1778) was
one of the first Europeans to celebrate the
beauty of mountains. Engraving, left, by
the French artist Jean-Michel Moreau the
Younger, illustrates an episode from Emile
(1762), Rousseau's treatise on education.
It shows Rousseau and the Savoyard
vicar, a composite portrait of two priests
whom Rousseau had known, contempla¬
ting the river Po and the Alpine range
beyond.
Vi
The conquest of peaks gave way to that
of certain rock facesin 1872 the 2,000-
metre east face of Monte Rosa, and in
1881 the almost equally high east face of
the Watzmann. The first winter ascent of
Mont Blanc was made in 1876 by an
Englishwoman, Mary Isabella Straton,
accompanied by guides from Cham-
onix.
In the nineteenth century moun¬
taineering began to spread from Europe
to other continents. The volcanic moun¬
tains of Mexico were conquered at a very
early date Popocatepetl (5,452 metres)
in 1827, the Pico de Orizaba (5,700
metres) in 1851, Iztaccihuatl (5,286
metres) in 1889. The highest mountains
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Competitors in a cross-country ski mara¬
thon in the Engadine, Switzerland, trace
their way like ants across the snowy land¬
scape. Cross-country skiing was prac¬
tised before the development of Alpine, or
downhill, skiing.
I »t'*4 ;
*
1*'í,;'i«ffr
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
in Africa, Kilimanjaro (5,895 metres)
and Mount Kenya (5,200 metres), were
climbed for the first time towards the end
of the nineteenth century.
In our time, mountains everywhere
have become places of refuge, not only
for many animal and plant species, but
also for millions of human beings in
search of relaxation from the stress of the
modern world. Winter, previously
endured as a season of cold, darkness and
privation, has suddenly become attrac¬
tive. And in few places does winter, apart
from its dangers, display so many pleas¬
ant features as in the mountains. The
snow is better and more plentiful than in
the lowlands, and there are more sun
shine and fresh air, commodities for
which there was already a great demand
in industrialized, urbanized Europe of
the mid-nineteenth century.
Again it was the British who gave the
lead. When they first started to slide
down the Swiss mountainsides on long,
narrow laths of wood, they drew smiles
from the local people. But soon they were
being eagerly imitated. Naturally they
could not have foreseen the extraordin¬
ary popularity which skiiing would even¬
tually achieve. By the 1930s there was
already a boom in winter sports, but it
was cut short by the Second World War.
As soon as the War was over, winter tour¬
ism began to develop more rapidly than
2
Jtt M
v n» KU Di m
...
*r.
The traditional Alpine house
ever. Other forms of winter sport, such as
curling, tobogganing, ice-skating, and
cross-country skiing, soon developed
alongside downhill skiing, but none of
them has ever equalled the latter in popu¬
larity.
Nowadays the Alps this sweep of
mountains extending for 1,200 kilo¬
metres from Vienna to Nice have
reached saturation point. People must
realize that they cannot get all they want
from this unique region unless they
accept certain disciplines. Development
possibilities are now exhausted. The
space still available belongs to nature, to
the world of Alpine plants and animals.
Only if they are allowed to live and
breathe will the Alps survive as an irre¬
placeable recreation area.
PETER MEYER is a Swiss musicologist and
specialist in German and English literature. He
has been active in publishing since 1964, and is
the publisher of an illustrated work entitled Das
Grosse ADAC-Alpenbuch ("The Big ADAC Book
oh the Alps"), and the bi-monthly magazine
Berge ("Mountains").
Five examples of traditional domestic architecture in the Swiss Alps. (1) An apartment J
house for two families at Evolène in the canton of Valais, built in 1543. (2) House with a
steeply sloping roof at Einsiedeln, canton of Schwyz, dating from 1802. (3) Two-family |
house with adjoining living quarters at Ernen in the Valais. It dates from 1686. (4) Another <S
two-family house with separate entrances at Lenk, canton ofBerne. It was built in 1 777. (5) J
Group of stone-roofed houses including a large house for two families, at Vrin, canton of 3
Graubünden. «
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
©
by Brigitte Bachmann-Geiser
Horn of plenty
A Swiss legend describes how the
alphorn was invented when a
young dairy farmer was invited to
choose a gift from among those offered by
three weird strangers. A red ogre offered
him strength and prosperity for his cattle; a
green huntsman tempted him with guile,
gold and the loveliest of maidens; but the
youth chose to accept a gift from the third
stranger, a pallid individual who offered the
ability to yodel and play the alphorn.
Although the wooden trumpet has
undoubtedly long been used by Alpine
herdsmen, it is not recorded historically
until the sixteenth century. The Zürich nat¬
uralist Conrad Gessner, seeing an alphorn
for the first time in 1555 on Mount Pilatus
near Lucerne, described it as being "made
Barely 2 metres long, the alphorn of the
early 19th century was held in an almost
horizontal position by the instrumentalist,
unlike its much longer modern counter¬
part which is played with its bell resting on
the ground. Engraving (above) by the
Swiss artist Franz Hegi (1 774- 1850), aftera
painting by Gabriel Lory, adorned the
cover of a book entitled Sammlung von
Schweizer-Kühreihen und alten Volkslie¬
dern ("Collection of ranz des vaches and
old Swiss folksongs"), Berne, 1818.
of two slightly curved, hollowed-out pieces
of wood thickly covered with willow."
This simple design has changed little.
Until about twenty years ago, however, the
practice was to choose a fir tree growing.on
a slope and therefore curving up from the
roots, strip off the bark, split the tree in two
lengthwise and hollow it out with chisel and
gouge. Alphorn makers now prefer to stick
together pieces of high-quality wood and
then carve them into the outer shape of the
instrument, but the work of hollowing out
the two halves has scarcely changed it still
takes more than seventy hours. The two
halves are finally stuck together and cov¬
ered with split cane. Formerly, protection
from the weather was provided by whatever
material lay to hand cord, wire, birch or
cherrywood bark, strips of nutwood or
pieces of linen soaked in pitch.
Alphorns made in the nineteenth century
have a recessed blow-hole, but today a
mouthpiece specially cut out of boxwood
enables players to transmit their lip vibra¬
tions to the air captured in the conical tube.
With no finger holes, flaps or valves, this
instrument cannot produce all the notes of
the tone-scale. Consequently, the only
notes that can be produced on the alphorn
are natural sounds, including the well-
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
©
known "alphorn F" (see page 32), a note
that sounds rather false. This limited range
of notes over long intervals explains why all
Swiss alphorn tunes have a family
resemblance, whether they are traditional
or recently composed.
Since the key of an alphorn is no longer
determined by the length and thickness of a
fir tree, and standardized instruments are
Below, a postcard sent by Johannes
Brahms to Clara Schumann on 12 Septem¬
ber 1868. On it the German composer
noted a Swiss alphorn melody with the
message: "From the mountain heights,
from the valley depths, I send you a thou¬
sand friendly thoughts." Brahms later
incorporated this melody into the fourth
movement of his Symphony No. 1 in C
Minor.
now manufactured in a variety of pitches,
the one-time calling and signalling instru¬
ment of the mountain herdsman can now be
played by amateur musicians in duets, trios,
quartets and, of late, in alphorn choirs. This
instrument, formerly used only in folk
music, was introduced into "serious" music
in 1971 with Jean Daetwyler's Concerto for
Alpine Horn and Orchestra. Thanks to a
number of professional hornplayers and to
compositions by Etienne Isoz, André
Besançon and Jost Meier, the alphorn is no
longer a rarity in concert halls, or even in
churches as an accompaniment to the
organ.
The extension in the use of this herds¬
man's instrument to contemporary and
"serious" music has brought the alphorn
Herdsmen in central Switzerland today
often take a smaller version of the alphorn
called a Biichel with them to the summer
pastures. They use this trumpet-like in¬
strument, above, to play their traditional
calls.
Since 1971, when the Swiss composer
Jean Daetwyler wrote a Concerto for
Alpine Horn and Orchestra, the alphorn
has made frequent appearances in the
concert hall. Below, Joseph Molna is the
alphorn soloist in a performance of Daet¬
wyler's work given at Nymphenburg Cas¬
tle, Munich (Fed. Rep. of Germany) by the
East Switzerland Chamber Orchestra,
conducted by U.P. Schneider.
©
O
Él
( .'
t
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
back into fashion in Switzerland, and the
thirty or so craftsmen who still make the
instrument set lengthy delivery dates!
This was not always the case. The
organizers of the first Alpine festival, held
near Interlaken in 1805, expected a big
turnout for their horn players' competition,
but their hopes were in vain. Only two can¬
didates appeared, and they shared the prize
of two black sheep. Travellers' accounts
from the early nineteenth century reported
that the Swiss national instrument was
dying out. Thus the Berne painter Franz
Nikiaus König wrote in 1814 that "the
alphorn is scarcely heard or seen anymore"
and suggested to the authorities of his can¬
ton that they organize the manufacture of
the instrument and instruction in its play¬
ing. The Sankt Gallen composer Ferdinand
Fürchtegott Huber (1791-1863), who was
interested in the music of the mountain peo¬
ple and had recorded the songs and yodels
of the herdsmen in the Bernese Oberland,
was sent to Grindelwald in the summer of
1826. He gathered young singers from the
region into an inn and had them each sing in
turn. The six most promising were enrolled
in a two-month course, which was repeated
the following summer.
The well-known form of alphorn with an
upcurved bell, the trumpet-like, serpentine
Biichel of central Switzerland and the
straight metal tuba of the Graubünden
highlands were still being played by herds¬
men in the 1940s as traditional working
instruments. As recently as 1972, an aged
Valaisan from La Sage (Val d'Hérens)
recounted how people waited every sum¬
mer evening for the sound of the alphorn. A
melodic air meant that up in the Alps all was
well, while single, repeated notes were a
signal for the men in the valley to go to the
aid of the herdsman on the mountain.
On 12 September 1868, Johannes
Brahms noted a horn melody on a postcard
he sent to Clara Schumann. Was it a tune
from the Rigi or the Stockhorn? We do not
know. We do know, however, that the great
composer immortalized this melody from
Swiss folk music in the fourth movement of
his first symphony, which he completed in
1876.
BRIGITTE BACHMANN-GEISER is a specialist
in Swiss folk music instruments, about which she
has written a number of works including Die
Volksmusik-instrumente der Schweiz (1981).
With the suppod of the Swiss Federal authori¬
ties, the canton of Berne and the municipality of
Burgdorf, she is currently setting up a museum
and institute of folk music and instruments at
Burgdorf.
by Mario Müller
Song without words
The art of yodeling
TOURISTS visiting Alpine lands,
especially Austria and Switzer¬
land, tend to regard yodeling as a
uniquely Alpine phenomenon.
However, although this special kind of
singing is strongly developed in the Tirol
and the Swiss Alps, it is also practised
elsewhere. It can be heard in Poland,
Lapland, Romania, the Caucasus, China,
Democratic Kampuchea, Thailand, Java,
Melanesia and Polynesia, and among the
African Pygmies.
Yodeling is a form of singing without
words in which the performer vocalizes
syllables and changes frequently from
low chest notes to high falsetto notes over
a wide range. In the Alps, yodeling is
performed solo or by up to five voices and
exists in different forms such as the
Jauchzer (cry of joy), and the Lockrub
(birdcall), folksongs with a yodel refrain
and quite recently even yodel masses.
There is much evidence to suggest that
yodeling was widely practised in pre¬
historic times. Among the variety of
theories put forward to explain its origin,
some see it as a search for echo effects or
as a way of expressing emotions, others as
a reflection of the landscape in which its
devotees live.
Whatever the true explanation may be,
yodeling seems undeniably to be of very
ancient origin; its archaic character is
strikingly apparent in the so-called Natur-
jodel with its F natural lying between F
and F sharp, which is still sung today in
the Swiss valley of Muotathal (canton of
Schwyz).
|r J.krrir^
At one time, yodeling was a part of
everyday life and tradition, developing as
it was transmitted from one generation to
the next. Today, in a more artificial form,
it has become part of the urban cultural
repertoire. Yodeling now has its authors,
its composers and its public.
MARIO MÜLLER, ol Switzerland, teaches Ita¬
lian and French language and literature at the
cantonal school, Schaffhausen. From 1976 to
1984 he was Secretary-General of the Swiss
National Commission for Unesco. He was a
co-founder in 1979 of the Société pour la
Musique Populaire en Suisse, of which he is
president. He contributed to a collective work,
Volksmusik in der Schweiz ("Folk Music in Swit¬
zerland"), published in 1985.
In many parts of Switzerland festivals are
held each summer to celebrate the cultural
heritage. Right, a group of yodelers from
the Bernese Mittelland wearing traditional
costume.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The ranz des vaches
Distant echoes of an old Swiss melody by Guy Métraux
V"
\*&C- z, - [tfff^ ..
*t ,
+mn»-»i
Sp «j*1
JGRU&S tuidtn g EJ^ñ f M
50UVfN|Pft_, ^
<
©
IN ail pastoral societies in which live¬
stock are central to the economic
and cultural life of the community, a
relationship that is both practical and per¬
sonal develops between the men and the
animals in their charge. This relationship
is expressed in calls, either vocal or
instrumental, wordless tunes, onoma¬
topoeic noises, songs, or even incanta¬
tions used to control the herds.
On a more subjective level,- the herds¬
men can express a variety of feelings in
this way. Poems, songs and calls in which
the human voice or the horn are the
chosen instruments of communication
between man and beast are found in the
Rundi pastoral societies of Central
Africa, among the shepherds of the Bal¬
kan plains and the Lapps of the Far
North, on the Argentine pampas, and
among the cowboys of the American Far
West.
In Switzerland, in the cattle-breeding
communities of the Pre-Alps and the
Alps with the exception, however, of
the outlying Graubünden (Grisons), the
Valais and the Jura the ranz des vaches
is a working song which is part of the
Above, a souvenir postcard from Appen¬
zell, Switzerland, depicting the annual trek
of herdsmen and animals to and from the
high pastures.
universal oral tradition of pastoral music.
Published for the first time in 1545 in a
German book, it has been transmitted in
various forms, scholarly and otherwise,
collected by travellers, musicians and,
later, musicologists. Over the centuries it
has become imbued with symbolism and
cultural significance that extend far
beyond its original purpose in pastoral
society.
Initially, the ranz des vaches was prob¬
ably a melody or tune played on the
alphorn (see page 29), which was used to
call the herds of cattle scattered through
the mountain pastures. The words came
later; the few versions that we have are all
dated later than 1750.
Characteristic of the ranz des vaches
are its varied rhythms and a highly spe¬
cific tonal feature of traditional music,
the F of the alphorn. This is a note mid
way between F natural and F sharp, to
which the modern ear is no longer
accustomed, and which has disappeared
from most of the learned transcriptions
that have come down to us. In fact, the
modern ranz des vaches is no more than a
distant echo of the music that once rang
out in the Alps.
One example of the traditional ranz
des vaches is that of Appenzell in north¬
east Switzerland. Transcribed around
1750, it seems very close to the early
model whose words and music had a
three-part structure.
The call: The herdsman (or the
alphorn) lets the herd know that it is milk¬
ing time, or time to return to the cow¬
shed, or to go up to the high pastures. The
key word is Lobe in German or Liauba in
French. This is a term of uncertain origin,
possibly onomatopoeic, which designates
a cow.
The roll-call of the herd: This is an
individual call to the cattle. Each cow is
singled out by its name, which may be
picturesque, descriptive or affectionate.
The Appenzeller herd of 1750 consisted
of twenty-seven head of cattle, with such
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
names as: "the Old Woman", "the
Limper", "Hairy", "the Flibbertigibbet",
"Fat Belly" and "the Dazzler".
Narrative: The singer sprinkles this
working song with comments on life in
the high pastures and the difficulties of
the herdsman's life. "Since taking a wife,/
I'm out of bread ;/Since taking a wife ,/I'm
out of luck", recalls the anonymous com¬
poser of Appenzell. Obviously, each
singer had his own personal frame of
reference and there was no standard text
as is the case today.
Since 1813, when it was transcribed by
P.C. Bridel, the ranz des vaches of
Gruyère has been the basic model which
most Swiss people know and which fea¬
tures in the repertoire of popular and
"serious" music in many countries.
In the early decades of the nineteenth
century, in Switzerland, in neighbouring
countries and even in England, musicians
and poets began to draw inspiration from
the ranz des vaches in composing Alpine-
style neo-folk music in which the themes
and images of Romanticism recur. The
many composers who used the ranz des
vaches as a source of rural colour include
Beethoven (in the Pastoral Symphony),
Berlioz (in the Symphonie Fantastique),
Robert Schumann (in Manfred) and
Wagner (in Act 3 of Tristan and Isolde).
Many operas also contain allusions to the
ranz des vaches, including Rossini's
William Tell and the Swiss composer
Gustave Doret's Les Armaillis. In 1828,
at the Royal Opera House in Covent
Garden, London, Sir Henry Rowley
Bishop, the author of the well-known
song Home, Sweet Home, produced a
work entitled Home! Sweet Home! or The
Ranz des Vaches, in which the old Alpine
tune is cleverly blended with his work.
Franz Liszt also composed many varia¬
tions on the ranz des vaches based on
versions which he had heard during his
travels in Switzerland.
For the Swiss, the ranz des vaches has
always had a very special meaning. It has
long been a reminder of the past, a
Rousseauist "memory marker" of a
golden age in the heart of the Alps, as
well as a poetic image of nature in which
people lived their lives in freedom.
Today, it is a mythical evocation of a cer¬
tain vision of Switzerland and the pas¬
toral folklore associated with it.
GUY METRAUX is a Swiss historian and a for¬
mer Unesco staffmember who served as Secre¬
tary-General of the International Commission for
the publication of a History of the Scientific and
Cultural Development of Mankind and as editor
of the international journal Cultures. He is the
author of Le ranz des vaches Du chant des
bergers à l'hymne patriotique (1984, "The ranz
des vaches From the Herdsmen's Song to the
Patriotic Hymn").
Above, Lioba, (1885), a painting by the
Swiss artist Auguste Baud-Bovy (1848-
1899). An Alpine herdsman calls his cattle,
widely scattered over the mountain pas¬
tures.
Two scores based on Swiss ranz des
vaches melodies. Right, a popular, tradi¬
tional version by Ferdinand F. Huber, enti¬
tled Der Ustig ("The Spring"). Below, one
ofmany variations on this theme by Franz
Liszt, who, like many other European
musicians and poets in the 19th century,
drew inspiration from Swiss folk music.
V.
:k>jl:t:si74
>frù Ihufcfr
f<ton
Mm t <
ptcirl
JUtoiItofc ff_\ t f_ï , j '
-
i Li
..- r T' "*_'
:
- :---,' 1
»,, I. I, « .fc. J. Nltavarjnl «4- J«
m m ¡r /tm . lm.fr fml f~J~ ' I* <W.+r
I ,!'"!^*"«*;'".'! '/''U'"'
: |
-:* ' I
/; îi - j; »tf^ti .'-
< ;
Photo © Central Library, Zurich
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The ALPEX experiment
An international
study programme
on Alpine meteorology
by Roger Newson
>vj;w.j^r-.»ULH»ii.i'.i.'i.B'M.iJi"'»iw^-.j».i .u.i.i.u« rwumujati.; wm- %
THE unique character of the
weather over and near the
world's mountainous areas is
well known, and the great diversity of
weather events that may occur in this sit¬
uation is nowhere better illustrated than
by the meteorology of the Alpine region.
There is an enormous variety of weather
types in this region, and the rapidity of
change from one type to another can be
breathtaking.
In countries near the Alps some of the
most significant meteorological effects
are associated with the generation of
deep depressions in the Gulf of Genoa
which are known as "Genoa cyclones".
These depressions develop very rapidly
and are often associated with strong
winds, heavy rain, flooding and storm
surges in the Mediterranean basin. The
catastrophic floods in Florence in 1966
were linked with the development of one
of these "Genoa cyclones", as are the
periodic tidal surges which from time to
time affect Venice. The characteristic
local winds in the Alpine region, such as
the Foehn and the Mistral, which occa
sionally blow with destructive force, are
also well known phenomena.
In principle, the fact that extensive
mountain ranges have major effects on
the weather should cause no real sur¬
prise, since a mountain barrier will
obviously deflect the atmospheric cir¬
culation both vertically and horizontally.
The Alps straddle the path of the prevail¬
ing westerly winds and weather systems
coming from the Atlantic, thus causing
significant interruption to the natural air
flow and leading to a variety of sometimes
dramatic local effects. The sudden
development of a Gulf of Genoa cyclone
as an Atlantic weather system comes up
against the Alps is vividly illustrated in
the sequence of satellite pictures above.
The important role that mountains
play in determining weather and climate
over considerable areas of the globe was
recognized from the outset of a major
international meteorological research
investigation, the Global Atmospheric
Research Programme (GARP), whose
overall objective was to study the dynam¬
ics of atmospheric phenomena in order to
extend the range of useful weather fore¬
casts.
The success of this fifteen-year
programme, jointly organized by the
World Meteorological Organization
(WMO) and the International Council of
Scientific Unions (ICSU) in response to
resolutions adopted at the 16th and 17th
sessions of the General Assembly of the
United Nations, has led to dramatic pro¬
gress in meteorology as a whole. In par¬
ticular, GARP included a major field
investigation, the 1982 Alpine Experi¬
ment (ALPEX), the aim of which was
specifically to understand the way in
which air flows over or around moun¬
tains, the development of cyclones such
as those in the Gulf of Genoa, and local
mountain winds.
One of the main characteristics of
mountain weather is the small scale,
meteorologically speaking, of the fea¬
tures involved and their sudden genera¬
tion and disappearance. Accordingly,
ALPEX was designed to gather suffi¬
ciently detailed information in space and
time over the Alpine region. The mete-
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A sequence ofsatellitepictures taken on 4,
5 and 6 March 1982 shows the develop¬
ment of a cyclone over the Gulf of Genoa.
Left, the clouds ofan Atlantic weather sys¬
tem approach the Alps; centre, a cyclone
develops between Genoa and Corsica;
right, the mature depression covers much
of the Mediterranean.
orological services and scientific commu¬
nities of twenty nations took part in the
Programme, and several years of inten¬
sive efforts and detailed planning culmi¬
nated in the implementation of a Special
ALPEX Observing Period from 1 March
to 30 April 1982.
For this, the existing network of
observing stations was supplemented by
thirty-four additional stations which
provided many extra measurements of
pressure and wind at all levels of the
atmosphere. An array of sixty microbaro-
graphs, capable of tracing with great pre¬
cision the slightest fluctuations in pres¬
sure, was set up along the St. Gotthard
and Brenner sections of the Alps. Seven¬
teen aircraft operating from Geneva
undertook numerous sorties on pre
defined tracks, collecting many observa¬
tions on wind speed and direction. In the
Mediterranean itself, information was
gathered from eleven research vessels
and many buoys, field platforms and tide-
gauges. All this was supplemented by
images and atmospheric sounding data
from meteorological satellites. This
extensive range of observations has been
assembled to form a unique quality-con¬
trolled internationally available data set.
Never before have observations of com¬
parable quality and density been pro¬
duced over a mountain region.
Since 1982, the ALPEX data set has
been fully exploited as both a foundation
and an inspiration for research and, as a
result, considerable advances have been
made in knowledge of the effect of moun
tains on the atmospheric circulation. One
of the main achievements has been a
greatly increased understanding of how
mountains should be treated in the
numerical models of the atmosphere now
used routinely for forecasting the move¬
ment of weather systems and the genera¬
tion of new features such as depressions
and anticyclones. It was found that at
least a fraction of the error in forecasts
could be attributed to an insufficient
representation of the blocking effect of
mountains on the air flow. Improvements
have now been introduced into numerical
models in this regard with consequent sig¬
nificant benefits for operational weather
forecasting.
ALPEX data have also permitted a
detailed analysis in three dimensions of
the structure of lee cyclones such as the
Genoa cyclones and identification of
mechanisms contributing to their inten¬
sification. It has also proved possible,
using particularly refined versions of
numerical models, to reproduce the
behaviour of these features more^
faithfully. Again, an improvement in the
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The weather station at Gornergrat, near
Zermatt in the Swiss Alps. Mountains play
an important role in determining weather
and climate over large areas of the earth.
skill of predicting the occurrence and
intensity of lee cyclones, which can have
such severe effects, has important
implications for operational weather
forecasting.
Using the ALPEX data set, it has also
been possible to examine in detail the
behaviour of the atmosphere flow as it
approaches a mountain range, revealing
a sharp division between the low level
flow going predominantly around and the
upper level flow moving over the moun¬
tain. The reproduction of this splitting
pattern in weather prediction models is a
key test of their performance in capturing
the perturbing effect of mountains. The
phenomenon of flow splitting is also a
factor in the deformation of weather sys¬
tems as they cross the Alps and much has
also been learned on this subject as a
result of ALPEX.
Finally, using particularly the data
gathered in the aircraft missions, it has
been possible to carry out studies of the
structure of the strong local wind systems
which occur near mountains, and views
on the nature of the driving mechanisms
for these winds are now converging.
In the light of the results obtained, it
can already be said that ALPEX was a
highly successful project. The co-opera¬
tion of the participating countries and the
authorities involved was outstanding,
especially that of the many aviation
bodies. Indeed, there is considerable fol¬
low-up action in some of the Alpine coun¬
tries Switzerland, Austria, the Federal
Republic of Germany and Italy have
formed an organization called "ALPEX
Regional" which is continuing the
co-operation established in ALPEX and
undertaking further examination of par¬
ticular mountain weather manifestations.
The impact of the scientific results on
atmospheric physics has already been sig¬
nificant and will grow in the next few
years. An important side effect has been
the stimulation of research and the gener¬
ation of many new ideas.
ROGER NEWSON, of the United Kingdom, is
senior scientific officer of the World Climate
Research Programme, which is a joint pro¬
gramme of the World Meteorological Organiza¬
tion and the International Council of Scientific
Unions, based in Geneva, Switzerland.
TODAY glaciers cover 3,200 km2 of
the Alps roughly the same area
as those of Scandinavia and some
twenty times more than those of the Pyre¬
nees, but barely one-tenth of the maxi¬
mum glacier area during the Pleistocene
Epoch. The erosive action of this enor¬
mous mass of ice as it advanced and
retreated gradually shaped most of the
lake basins in the Alps, although tectonic
occurrences also contributed to the for¬
mation of many such basins including
those of the Bodensee and the Traun-
see.
But one thing is certain. The basins of
some Alpine lakes were formed very long
ago, possibly even in the Tertiary Period
(more than 1.5 million years ago), where¬
as the present lake stage may be scarcely
older than 18,000 years.
So one of the most interesting ques¬
tions facing limnology, the scientific
study of lakes, is how our modern lakes
developed. So far our knowledge of their
history is fragmentary. One piece of
information was gleaned when construc¬
tion work on the highway near the Mond-
see in Upper Austria brought to light lake
sediment from the last interglacial period
(between the Riss Glacial Stage and the
Wurm Glacial Stage). This revealed not
only that the water level of the Mondsee
was then 60 metres higher than it is today
but also that it formed part of a much
bigger lake embracing both the Irrsee and
the Attersee. It has also been established
that the water level of Lake Waginger in
Bavaria has fallen 15 to 20 metres since
the Wurm Glacial Stage.
On the other hand, archaeologists are
convinced that the construction methods
used in Alpine lakeside dwellings be¬
tween 4,200 and 5,900 years ago were
possible only if the water level was several
metres lower. But this assertion, which
would imply the absence of outflows and
therefore a higher salt content in the lakes
in question, has not been confirmed by
limnology.
There were also and no doubt still
are a number of lakes with a lifespan of
no more than a few thousand years. They
largely originated during the retreat of
the great glaciers, as in the Salzach and
Enns valleys, which were filled with boul¬
ders and debris within this short period.
Masses of water could also be dammed up
behind terminal moraines and lead to the
flooding of valleys. This phenomenon,
which is found more rarely in the Alps
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Lakes and glaciers of the Alps
by Heinz Loffler
than in some other mountain regions, led
to catastrophe in the Andes not long
ago.
Some small lakes connected with the
advance and retreat of glaciers have an
even shorter lifespan. Since the last maxi¬
mum glacier level around the middle of
the nineteenth century, many lakes have
emerged in this way and in some cases
disappeared, including the small Eisrand-
see near Hochkönig (Salzburg), which
completely emptied through a newly for¬
med ice tunnel in September 1934.
The Alpine lakes have been subject to
human influences since ancient times.
Control and drainage operations and
wetland reclamation led to the drying out
of some basins. Water pollution as a
result of the discharge of chemical waste,
stocking with fish and lakeside housing
Pasterze, Austria, the largest (8 km long
and around 5 km wide) glacier of the
Eastern Alps and one of the most beautiful
ofallAlpine glaciers, is fedby the snows of
the Grossglockner. It has been for many
years in a state of recession.
4*
s3^ v.
'
TO». \
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Mondsee and the Attersee lakes in
Upper Austria, both of which formed part
of a bigger lake during an interglacial
period in prehistoric times when relatively
moderate climatic conditions melted
Alpine snow and ice to create a water level
60 metres higher than it is today.
development were and are human activi¬
ties whose effects have been known for
years and are, albeit sporadically,
controlled. In the meantime, however,
transregional phenomena such as acid
rain and water pollution by effluents (see
the Unesco Courier, January 1985) are
affecting extensive areas in the Alps, and
causing new problems in lake protec¬
tion.
However, while the disappearance or
pollution of lakes in the distant and more
recent past is to be deplored, it must be
admitted that new stretches of water have
been created in recent decades. Dammed
lakes (Alpine reservoirs), artificial lakes
and controlled natural lakes containing
considerable quantities of water (over 1.5^
thousand million m3 in Austria alone)
contribute primarily to energy produc¬
tion.
These developments create problems
for landscape and nature protection.
Lakeside areas, devoid of scenic attrac¬
tion and mostly arid, at low water levels
unfortunately resemble the astatic waters
of arid zones. In many cases the damming
of lakes has destroyed valuable wetlands
or even led to thé disappearance of ende¬
mic species two Coleóptera belonging
to the Staphylinide group in the case of
the upper Stubach valley in Austria.
Today the threats once posed by gla¬
ciers, snow and Alpine waters are well
understood and generally controlled as
part of water supply management pro¬
grammes. If catastrophes still occur in
our time, they are chiefly connected with
human intervention such as deforesta¬
tion, acid rain, tourism, housing develop¬
ment in unsuitable areas, and, last but not
least, the drainage of wetlands and the
diversion of watercourses in such a way as
to destroy the beauty of the landscape.
HEINZ LOFFLER, of Austria, is director of the
Institute ofLimnology at the Austrian Academy of
Sciences and teaches at the University of
Vienna. He has worked with Unesco's Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) Programme and with the
Scientific Committee on Problems of the Envi¬
ronment (SCOPE) of the International Council of
Scientific Unions (ICSU). He is the author of
Neusiedlersee Limnology of a Shallow Lake in
Central Europe.
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 PÍace de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. ,111 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
NedaelKhazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille: Frederick Potter
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Scrvat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
AH correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian:
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
38 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Février 1987
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de I'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
An audio-visual teaching aid on Man
v txcsco
tfeö at»
\ \\\C
and the Biosphere
Unesco's Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
Programme is an international programme of
research and training. Its aim is to provide
the scientific knowledge and trained
personnel needed to manage natural
resources in a rational and sustained
manner. MAB studies not only the impact of
man on the environment, but the
repercussions of environmental changes on
man. Scientific research is combined with a
practical approach to solving some of the
world's conservation problems, by
establishing protected areas known as
"Biosphere Reserves", now totalling 243,
located in 65 countries.
Man: the key to conservation is a slide-tape
show consisting of 55 colour slides, a
20-minute cassette tape, and a booklet
containing the script and instructions for use.
Invaluable as a teaching and study aid, the
slides and the accompanying commentary
introduce many examples of Biosphere
Reserves around the world, endangered
plant and animal species, use of natural
resources, and human activities as part of
ecosystems.
MAB audio-visual series 3
Bilingual English/French
ISBN 92-3-002139-3 220 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors In countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 56a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne, Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co,, Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BAHRAIN. United Schools International, Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726,
Bahrain. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Couner" Dutch
edition only: Internationale Drukkerij en Uitgevenj Keesing, Keesinglaan 2-20,
2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. CCP 000-0012775-68. French edition and general
Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels,
CCP 000-0070823-13. BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Intemacionais Ltda,
Processing Dept., R Peixoto Gomide 209, 01409, Sao Paulo SP. CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road, Ottawa. Ontario K1B 3W8.
STORES: 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa, 21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. SALES OFFICE:
7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305. St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CHINA.
China National Publications Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88,
Beijing. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve
Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1 -27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura. 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Pub-
lishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munk-
sgaard Export-OG, Tidsskriftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn
K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications,
No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box
128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641
Vantas 64. Rautikirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1 , 01 641 Vantas
64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP
12598-43. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig. Post¬
fach 140. 710 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basartstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides
Entreprises, P.O. Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box
1 0073, 541 1 0 Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore,
4 Nikis Street, Athens T 1 26. Kostarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2
Hippocratous Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock
Rd., Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre,
Baskerville House. 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B.
149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co.. H.F.
Hafnarstraeti 9. Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave.. Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road. Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-
500001. Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St., Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco,
1188 Englab Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-
4498, Teheran. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Bally-
mount Rd., Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box
1 283, 71 Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionana
Sansoni. S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo
1 1 3. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Libraine Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El Correo de la
Unesco, Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle, Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British
Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Pol-
chowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1 000 AD
Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 14277-
Kilbirnte, Wellington; 1 30 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1 721 . Christchurch; Alma
St., P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin. NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 2B6.
NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1177Sentrum -Oslo 1; Narvesen
A/S. ütteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No.
729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 6950,
Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI
ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Mam Street. Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building,
Riyadh. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2
Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas
Publications (Pty) Ltd., Subscnption Sen/ice. P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg.
Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaik's
Bookstore (Pty) Ltd., Libri Building, 268 Church Street, Pretoria 0001 . Central
News Agency Ltd., Group Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 613, Cape Town
8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampaiam Gardiner
Mawata, P.O.B. 244. Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box 2943, Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams AB, Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidsknft-
scentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101 . 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zürich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne,
Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.,
40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Tnnidad W 1 . TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu. Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008, Nine Elms
Lane, London SW8 5DR, and H.M. S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Belfast. Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta
Ltd., 122 King's Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan
Associates-UN I PUB, Penodicals Department. 10033-F King Highway.
Lanham MD 20706. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimrtrova 39,
Moskva 113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva
Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA.
National Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
When men andmountains meet
(see page 9)
tspud&m
]]>
</page>
</document>
