<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="073068eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m e Courier
«
»to«
travellers
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
From station to museum
Built between 1898 and 1900, the Gare d'Orsay in central Paris was for
some thirty years a mainline railway station. After the station was closed
to mainline traffic, the vast central hall with its soaring metal arches was
used for a variety of purposes. For some years the station was threatened
with demolition, but in 1978, with its adjoining hotel, it was earmarked
for conversion into a great modern museum in which French State
collections of art of the second half of the nineteenth century could be
permanently displayed. In 1986, the new museum the Musée d'Orsay
opened its doors to the public. Above, view inside the central hall of the
museum. The alignment of exhibition rooms and terraces follows the
layout of the old railway tracks and platforms. The former station clock
can be seen at the far end of the hall.
53 France
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial April 1987
40th year
Travelling is one of the oldest and most important of human
activities. The reasons for the traveller's quest have been many
and varied, ranging from early man's search for new hunting
grounds to modern man's attempts to conquer space. Impelled by
commercial, religious or political motives, travellers have crossed
the face of the earth in search of territory. Through initiatory
journeys they have sought communication with the invisible
world.
This issue of the Unesco Courier does not pretend to be a
catalogue of all forms of travel, past and present. It focuses
instead on the ways in which travel can reveal people and cultures
to each other. To show travellers discovering other peoples and
other worlds the Editors have compiled an anthology of extracts
from travel literature written in many different ages and places.
Through anecdotes and reflections chosen to represent the widest
possible geographical and cultural spectrum, we see travellers
noting the similarities and differences between themselves and
those they "discover", in some cases feeling the impact of pro¬
found cultural antagonisms. We see them recognizing, often in
unexpected forms, the common bond of human experience. We
see a slowly emerging realization of the extent of human diversity.
To comply with this general criterion we decided to exclude
from the anthology "objective" descriptions of climate, land¬
scape, plant and animal life, customs and forms of political
organization , the kind of scientific observations which are made in
the course of anthropological and ethnological studies.
The extracts have been grouped in a number of sections.
Clearly, many more passages could have been chosen from the
rich harvest of world travel writing, but if such great names as
Marco Polo, Louis-Antoine de Bougainville and Alexander King-
lake are missing from our anthology, it is because we have sought
to use the limited space at our disposal to present travellers such
as Olaudah Equiano and Jan Myrdal, who are perhaps less well
known to an international public, and above all to show that the
appetite for travel has taken man to every point of the compass.
Our goal has been to bring together writing which reveals the
images, sometimes distorted, which men create of each other
when they meet.
Front cover: design features an 18th-century Russian wood-cut, one of a
series of folk images entitled The Story of Joseph the Magnificent.
Document © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
Back cover: Japanese print by Keisai Yoshiku (1833-1904) shows an
elegant French lady listening to the travel reminiscences of a cigar-
smoking Dutch sailor whose ship is anchored in the harbour. At top of
print is an approximate phonetic transcription into Japanese of certain
English and Dutch words.
Photo George Ducret © Galerie Janette Ostier, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
4 The traveller and his quest by Jacques Brosse
The potency of myth
8 The earthly Paradise by Christopher Columbus
9 In search of the Amazons by Cristóbal de Acuña
10 The first men on the Moon by Neil A. Armstrong
and Edwin E. Aldrin
The discoverers discovered
11 Mass to the sound of gunfire by Ferdinand Magellan/
Antonio Pigafetta
12 Saved by the Indians by Jacques Cartier
12 Festivities in the Friendly Islands by James Cook
13 A Russian on the coast of Alaska by Grigori Shelikhov
14 The swimming postman by Alexander von Humboldt
Merchants and adventurers
15 Reflections on solitude by Athanasius Nikitin
16 Scholar Gypsy by George Borrow
The art of meeting others
17 How I became Gustavus Vasa by Olaudah Equiano
18 Long nose, white skin and 'honey mouth' by Mungo Park
23 Island fling by Victor Segalen
Pilgrims and missionaries
24 How Buddhism came to Karnasuvarna by Xuan Zang
25 A visit to the regent of Tibet by Régia-Evariste Hue
The spiritual journey
26 The mystic way by Farîd oddïn 'Attär
Men of letters
27 Diplomats under surveillance by Fukuzawa Yukichi
Vive la difference! by Yuan Zuzhi
Dance-floor democracy by Domingo F. Sarmiento
A Chinese general in Paris by Chen Jitong
28
30
31
32 An Indian poet visits an English parson
by Rabindranath Tagore
The armchair traveller
33 Paris-on-Thames by Joris-Karl Huysmans
Footloose and fancy free
34 The obedience due to princesses by Ibn Batutah
35 Into the heart of Africa by René Caillié
36 Psychic sports by Alexandra David-Néel
37 Thoughts from the roof of the world by Jan Myrdal
, A time to live:
FRANCE: From station to museum
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 32 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
Thai
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N°4-1987-CPD-87-l-444A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
by Jacques Brosse
IN ancient times, travellers modelled themselves on the
heroes whose great deeds were recounted in mythology. By
virtue of their semi-divine, semi-human origin, the heroes
had a mission to unite the unknown to the known and to bring
into communication the human world, the divine empyrean and
the Underworld of the dead . They were able to cross the thresh¬
old of the Underworld in both directions, and, indeed, this was
one of the ordeals that faced them, for, destined though they
were to be immortal, they nevertheless had to achieve immor¬
tality by travelling to the ends of the earth where no one before
them had ever set foot.
So it was that Heracles travelled to the Garden of the
Hesperides and then to the Underworld, Jason and his compan¬
ions sought the Golden Fleece, and the Trojan Aeneas, human
son of Aphrodite, wandered from Asia to Africa before foun¬
ding in Italy a small nation that one day would rule the world.
And then there is Ulysses, the prototype of so many travellers.
The story of his travels, the Odyssey, is the gateway to Greek
literature, but it was preceded, many centuries earlier, by the
Epic of Gilgamesh, the Sumerian hero who travelled far and
wide in search of immortality. Similarly, the earliest journeys
by the Chinese were made in search of the Isles of the Blest and
the Kunlun Mountains, the axis and centre of the world. Cer¬
tain divinities, too, set off on journeys, and human beings
awaited their return with impatience. Thus the Mexicans, to
their cost, mistook the army of the Conquistadors for the
retinue of Quetzalcoatl, the Plumed Serpent. The Hawaiians
inevitably interpreted the arrival in the bay of Kealakekua of
great ships laden with undreamed-of wealth as the return of the
god Lorono, whom they identified with the person of Captain
Cook, who perished, a victim of this misapprehension.
Traditionally, a journey is not so much an adventure as a
quest. It is true that the decision to leave one's country springs
from a desire to break away from familiar surroundings and the
sterile stagnation of habit, but an even more powerful factor is
determination to be free from one's old self, to embark on the
path of self-transformation. The stages of the journey corre¬
spond to a process of initiation: they beat time on the march
towards mystery; encounters with monsters are symbolic tests
to which the future initiate must submit. To his friends and
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The traveller
and his quest
kindred, who admired his recklessness as they watched him go,
the returning traveller is no longer the same person. Still trailing
clouds of glory from the unknown, he has become a hero.
In extreme cases, the journey may entail no movement at all,
and be made wholly within the self. Sometimes it takes place in
a kind of waking dream, like Dante's descent into the circles of
Hell. There is a tradition of initiatory journeys which culmi¬
nates in Rabelais's Pantagruel, and Swift's Gulliver's Travels,
and includes the Quest for the Holy Grail. In the Grail story,
knightly exploits are of secondary importance, and the hero can
only achieve his aim the rediscovery of the lost vessel con¬
taining the blood of the Redeemer if his deeds are accom¬
panied by an inner metamorphosis. Lancelot and Perceval only
half understood this and failed, whereas Galahad ultimately
succeeded, but only by attaining so high a degree of selflessness
that he became the reflection of the object of the quest, Jesus
Christ. This is the moral of all journeys. They can succeed only
if the traveller, setting out in search of the Other, achieves
identification with that Other.
Such an esoteric meaning is also to be found in the Chinese
Passage through the
ice. An illustration front
A Voyage of Discovery .
. . for the Purpose of Ex¬
ploring Baffin's Bay in
which the Scottish navi¬
gator John Ross (1777-
1856) described his first
expedition in search ofa
northwest passage be¬
tween the Atlantic and
the Pacific, in 1818.
and Japanese tales which are probably based on the journey of
the Shaman, since Shamanism, later confined to Siberia, was
once known throughout Asia. However, it should at this point
be emphasized that when the Shaman engages in this dangerous
magical undertaking, he is not remotely concerned with per¬
sonal gain, but is acting as an intermediary between the human
community that he represents and the world of the gods, who
have chosen him for this office by giving him the power to enter
their celestial realm, denied to all others. Likewise, Dante
descends into the circles of Hell , and Galahad seeks the Grail in
order to report to others what they have seen and what others
cannot see: they reveal the unknown.
We may take these to be imaginary journeys, but this is only a
modern interpretation. In the ancient tales, myth and reality
are inextricably mingled, making any rationalist interpretation
very difficult, since it is not always possible to distinguish the
geographical from the symbolic, and a single item of informa¬
tion may be both at once. This is true of the Odyssey, and
perhaps even of the highly didactic Voyage ofBrendan, a tale of
adventure which was extremely popular in the Middle Ages;
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
©
Masked man from the Sandwich Islands
(today the Hawaii archipelago) as depicted
in the atlas of the third voyage (1 776-1780)
of the English navigator James Cook.
but it is also true, despite the fact that its authors were mer¬
chants, of the Periplus ofHannon, by the Carthaginian Hanno,
who in all likelihood explored the western coast of Africa as far
as the Gulf of Guinea around 450 B.C., and of the travels of
Marco Polo, which are also a "description of the world", and
hence a cosmology. We should, after all, remember that until
his death Christopher Columbus was convinced that he had
discovered, not the New World, but the islands of Japan and the
coasts of China.
Until the great transoceanic expeditions of the Renaissance,
every journey took place in two dimensions, one vertical, or, as
we would nowadays say, subjective, and the other horizontal,
situated in physical space, and hence objective. It should be
borne in mind that this ambiguity, which modern minds see as a
defect, then gave a journey its real meaning. How could it have
been otherwise in medieval Europe, where the typical travellers
were the pilgrim and his warlike counterpart the crusader?
These men travelled so far afield to seek forgiveness for their
sins and the certainty of salvation. What they found at the end
of their journey was their true home, Jerusalem or the New
Jerusalem. The few travellers' tales that have survived from this
period were written in this spirit; they are guides to pilgrimages
in the Holy Land.
Descriptions written by Chinese monks of their visits to the
holy places of Buddhism reflect similar preoccupations. But
these monks were scholars. On their journeys to India they
sought holy scriptures rather than relics, and writings such as
those chronicling the journeys of Fa Xian in the fifth century,
and of Yi Jing and especially of Xuan Zang in the seventh, are
remarkable historical and geographical documents.
It was for religious reasons, too, that the Arabs travelled
throughout the East. Muslims are virtually forced to become
travellers, since one of their obligations is to make the pil¬
grimage to Mecca at least once in a lifetime. Furthermore, since
the Arab presence had spread to a large part of the old con¬
tinent, the masters who were capable of passing on the oral
teachings essential to Islam were scattered. The faithful Mus¬
lim, eager to perfect his knowledge, was obliged to travel from
one to another, and hence to journey throughout the Islamic
world, but wherever he went he would find others of his faith to
understand and help him. As a result, we have, for example, the
records of the journeys of Ibn Djubayr, in the twelfth century,
and later those of Ibn Battuta, who in a quarter of a century
travelled across half the world.
Another consequence of the spread of Islam was the creation
by the Arabs, who were skilled merchants and excellent naviga¬
tors, of the only real international trade, by land and sea, of
medieval times, and in particular the spice trade. Merchants
who travelled as far as China and Indonesia gathered informa¬
tion which Arab geographers pieced together to form the most
comprehensive picture of the Orient of their day. Highly culti¬
vated men, these Muslim scholars were astronomers as well as
geographers, travellers as well as theorists. With them, travel
writing began to acquire investigative qualities. Their aim was
to be precise, rational one might almost say scientific on the
model of the "inquiry" (the true sense of the word historial) of
Herodotus in Greece, in the fifth century B.C., for the Arabs
were heirs to the Greeks. In the heart of the Middle Ages, the
Muslims were already modern travellers.
Our purpose in dwelling on the origins of travel writing has
been to describe the mentality of the earliest travellers, and
their status which set them apart from other members of
the community for they constitute the prototype of all later
travellers.
During the thirty years or so which elapsed between the
expeditions of Christopher Columbus and the first voyage
round the world in 1520-1522 by Magellan, a period which saw
the successive discoveries by Westerners of America, of the
route to India and of the Pacific Ocean, travel acquired an
entirely new meaning: it became secularized and limited to a
single dimension, the horizontal. The aim was no longer to
make contact with the Other World, but with other human
societies. But there was no feeling of fellowship with the mem¬
bers of these societies; they were pagans and first had to be
converted.
With few exceptions, sixteenth-century travellers tended to
be cast in the new mould of the conquistador. They were no
longer curious, cautious individuals, but leaders of armed expe¬
ditions, violent and avaricious, engaged simultaneously in the
forced conversion of indigenous populations, the conquest of
their land and the furtherance of their own interests. God and
the King, whom they served so well, owed them this reward.
These men were Portuguese and Spaniards, later Dutch, and
then British and French, the builders of colonial empires. Mis¬
sionaries and merchants followed close on their heels. The
image which they exported, and which they imposed on Amer¬
indians and Asians alike, was to be seen for many years by these
peoples as the very face of the Christian West.
And yet, on the fringes of this aggressive policy, the strong
impulse of curiosity reactivated by the Renaissance was still
flourishing: the humanist desire to know the whole universe in
all its natural and human diversity. This attitude is to be found
in the travelling naturalists, from the Frenchman Pierre Belon
and the Italian Prospero Alpini in the sixteenth century to the
Swede Peter Thunberg in the eighteenth century and the Scot
David Douglas at the beginning of the nineteenth. These mis¬
sions, which could not have been more peaceable, undertaken
individually by determined men whose whole lives were
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
devoted to increasing the store of human knowledge, are the
positive counterweight to a brutality that was often cynical.
Such a tendency, which indicates the existence of a new type
of traveller, is not always given much prominence by historians
of travel. It continued without interruption until the early nine¬
teenth century, reaching its apogee during the "Enlighten¬
ment", when, shortly after 1750, great sea-borne expeditions
set out to explore what remained to be discovered in the South¬
ern Hemisphere as far as the Antarctic continent, the existence
of which was hotly disputed. Their mission was to fill in the
empty spaces on the map, and to construct a fuller and more
accurate picture of the world.
Such was the achievement of Captain James Cook on his
three voyages. Like his immediate predecessor, Louis Antoine
de Bougainville, and like his successors who drew inspiration
from the methods he tested, Cook was accompanied by a skilled
team of scientists who were to draw up a systematic inventory,
hitherto lacking, of animal and plant life. Thanks to highly
detailed accounts of his voyages of discovery, we are familiar
with the young and enthusiastic scientists who willingly com¬
plied with the discipline that is indispensable at sea, enduring
harsh conditions and often facing mortal dangers.
It is remarkable that many of the survivors followed the
example of their model and hero Cook and immediately set out
on fresh voyages lasting between three and five years. The son
of a farmworker, and a sailor who rose from the ranks, Cook
was not only an experienced navigator, whose authority, was
tempered by his constant concern for the well-being of his crew.
More surprising, to us, is his generous attitude towards the
Engraving (c. 1857) by the French painter
Edgar Degas (1834-1917) shows Dante
and Virgil (crowned with laurel leaves, left)
at the gates of Hell, an episode from
Dante's Inferno.
peoples he visited. Not only did Cook never use violence except
when he saw no alternative, but he tried to understand totally
unfamiliar customs and beliefs with an unprecedented open-
mindedness and with such minute attention to detail that, auto-
didact though he was, he unwittingly founded the science of
ethnography, which involves hot only observation but also
dialogue.
However, Cook never went to the opposite extreme to the
colonialists he did not embrace the cult of the "noble savage"
as practised by late eighteenth-century "philosophers" such as
Jean-François de Galaup, comte de La Perouse, who for a while
shared their illusion, but who was forced to abandon it, and
would proclaim: "They write their books by the fireside, but I
have been travelling for thirty years," shortly before he and his
subordinates were massacred by these "children of nature".
Unfortunately, this golden age did not last long. The French¬
man Jules Sébastien César Dumont d'Urville, discoverer of the
Antarctic continent, and even his rivals, the American Charles
Wilkes and the Englishman James Clark Ross, were still, as late
as 1843, Cook's disciples. But with their deaths and with the
ending of the great voyages of discovery, a certain attitude of
mind disappeared. Humanitarian idealism gave way to the mer¬
cantile concerns of the rising bourgeoisie. All too often, the
religious missions aided and abetted the great powers and were
the vanguard of armed occupation.
Nevertheless, the fever of discovery and the admiration
aroused by natural rather than supernatural wonders continued
unabated in the scientific explorers, of whom Alexander von
Humboldt, in the early years of the nineteenth century, was an
outstanding example. He belonged to a rich and noble family
and was one of the last humanists to possess a truly universal
culture. As such, the Prussian Humboldt seems to be the
opposite of Cook, the empirical Englishman, and yet, in many
respects, they are alike and complementary. The Personal Nar¬
rative of Travels to the Equinoctial Regions ofthe New Continent
During the Years 1799-1804 was long used as a model by over¬
land explorers, as were the Voyages of Cook by navigators.
Worthy heirs to both these men were the Englishman Charles
Darwin on board the Beagle, Henry Walter Bates and Alfred
Rüssel Wallace, hacking their way through the splendid, fear¬
some Amazon jungle, and, lastly, the solitary travellers who
penetrated to the unknown heart of the African continent, from
the Scot Mungo Park and the Frenchman René Caillié, to the
fearless missionary David Livingstone. But the death of
Livingstone in 1873 marked the passing of a certain type of
modest, disinterested hero, with qualities which even his imme¬
diate successor, the Anglo-American journalist Stanley, did not
embody.
From this time onwards, exploration increasingly came to
serve capitalist interests, and became the prelude to a new form
of subjection. Although the fascination was still alive in the last
of the explorers the discoverers of the polar regions their
adventures came increasingly to resemble sporting achieve¬
ments.
What remains of the spirit which inspired these adventurous
travellers, in an age when any tourist who takes a plane can cast
himself in the role of a hero? How far does contacj really go
between this new type of traveller, the modern tourist, and the
people he meets on his travels? How far, at heart, does he care
about such things? Perhaps the only future left for travel is
space exploration. But it is still too early to tell.
JACQUES BROSSE, French naturalist; has written many works on
exploration and travel, including Great Voyages of. Discovery: Circum¬
navigators and Scientists, 1 764-1 843 (English translation by Facts on File
Publications, New York/Oxford, 1983), and the first biography of the
French explorer Alexandra David-Néel, entitled Alexandra David-Neel,
L'aventure et la spiritualité (Retz, 1978).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The potency of myth
In the minds of European explorers of medieval times and the Renais¬
sance, legend and fact were inextricably mingled. Men like Vespucci,
Magellan and Columbus were influenced by the writings of earlier trav¬
ellers such as Marco Polo (whose Description of the World was one of
Columbus's favourite books) who often wove a thread of fantasy into their
first-hand observations. Their world-view was also conditioned by the
limitations and inaccuracies of contemporary cartography, as well as a
number of tenacious myths which persisted until much later times.
The earthly
Paradise
by Christopher Columbus
In the time of the Genoese navigator
Christopher Columbus (1450 or 1451-
1506), the existence of an earthly
Paradise was unquestioned. The origin of
this myth is found in the Bible, where it is
written (in Genesis, II. 8): "And the Lord
Godplanted a garden eastward in Eden;
and there he put the man whom he had
formed." For Columbus the questfor the
earthly Paradise was an obsession which
lasted throughout his search for a western
sea route to China and India. His dream
was sustained by the luxuriant plant and
animal life, the mildness of the climate
and the abundant waters of the New
World. When, during his third voyage in
1498, he discovered the mouth of the
Orinoco on the coast ofSouth America,
he thought that he hadfinally located the
earthly Paradise, which he imagined to be
at the source of this vast effluence of
fresh water.
HOLY Scripture testifies that Our Lord made the earthly Paradise in which
he placed the Tree of Life. From it there flowed four main rivers: the
Ganges in India, the Tigris and the Euphrates in Asia, which cut through a
mountain range and form Mesopotamia and flow into Persia, and the Nile, which
rises in Ethiopia and flows into the sea at Alexandria.
I do not find and have never found any Greek or Latin writings which definitely
state the worldly situation of the earthly Paradise, nor have I seen any world map
which establishes its position except by deduction. Some place it at the source of
the Nile in Ethiopia. But many people have travelled in these lands and found
nothing in the climate or altitude to confirm this theory, or to prove that the
waters of the Flood which covered, etc. ... reached there. Some heathens tried to
show by argument that it was in the Fortunate Islands (which are the Canaries);
and St. Isidore, Bede, Strabo, the Master of Scholastic History,* St. Ambrose
and Scotus and all learned theologians agree that the earthly Paradise is in the
East, etc.
I have already told what I have learnt about this hemisphere and its shape, and I
believe that, if I pass below the Equator, on reaching these higher regions I shall
find a much cooler climate and a greater difference in the stars and waters. Not
that I believe it possible to sail to the extreme summit or that it is covered by water,
or that it is even possible to go there. For I believe that the earthly Paradise lies
here, which no one can enter except by God's leave. I believe that this land which
your Highnesses have commanded me to discover is very great, and that there are
many other lands in the south of which there have never been reports. I do not
hold that the earthly Paradise has the form of a rugged mountain, as it is shown in
pictures, but that it lies at the summit of what I have described as the stalk of a
pear, and that by gradually approaching it one begins, while still at a great
Detail from The Earth orThe Earthly Paradise,
painting on copper by the Flemish artist Jan
Brueghel, known as "Velvet Brueghel",
(1568-1625).
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
distance, to climb towards it. As I have said, I do not believe that anyone can
ascend to the top. I do believe, however, that, distant though it is, these waters
may flow from there to this place which I have reached, and form this lake. All this
provides great evidence of the earthly Paradise, because the situation agrees with
the beliefs of those holy and wise theologians and all the signs strongly associated
with this idea. For I have never read or heard of such a quantity of fresh water
flowing so close to the salt and flowing into it, and the very temperate climate
provides a further confirmation. If this river does not flow out of the earthly
Paradise, the marvel is still greater. For I do not believe that there is so great and
deep a river anywhere in the world.
The potency
"Letter to the Catholic Kings on the third voyage to the
Indies (1498)." The Four Voyages of Christopher
Columbus, edited and translated by J.M. Cohen, Pen¬
guin Books Ltd., Harmondsworth, U.K., 1969.
* Petrus Comestor, author of Historia scolastica (trans¬
lator's note).
T '	 ' >i -i^'JWfflBtWIIIIPMHW^^
This depiction of an
Amazon as a
symbol ofAmerica
appears in a book
on world costumes,
published in 1784,
by the French
writerand artist
Jacques Grasset
de Saint-Sauveur
(1757-1810).
A hundred and fifty kilometres below the last village of the Tupinambas, as
one travels down the River Amazon, one comes upon a tributary to the
north which flows from the province of the Amazons, and which is known
to the local people as the Cumuriz. This river takes its name from the Indian
communities dwelling at its mouth. Above these are the Apotos . . . Then come the
Iagaris, and beyond them the Guacaris, the fortunate tribe that enjoys the favours
of the Amazons. The Guacaris have built their village on mountains of stupen¬
dous height (the Guyana Range). One mountain in this range is called Tac-
amiaba. Its summit rises well clear of the others, and it is barren, being constantly
buffeted by the winds. Here live the Amazons.
These women live together in isolation and protect themselves without any help
from men. However, at certain specific times of year they are visited by their
neighbours, the Guacaris. When the latter arrive, the Amazons run for their
weapons for fear of an ambush. But as soon as they recognize their friends, they,
all hurry down to meet the boats of the newcomers. Each woman takes a ham¬
mock from a boat and goes to hang it up in her home. Then she lies down and
awaits the men. A few days later, the Amazons' guests go home, returning
without fail the following season. The girls that are born of these unions are raised
by their mothers. They are taught to work and to bear arms. As for. the boys,
nobody knows exactly what becomes of them. I have been told by an Indian who,
in his youth, went with his father to one of these assignations, that the following
year the Amazons hand back to the children's fathers any males to whom they
have given birth. But, as a rule, it is thought that they put these male children to
death. I cannot be certain.
Be this as it may, these women own treasures that could enrich the whole world.
The mouth of the river on whose banks they live is situated 20° south of the
Equator.
In search of the
Amazons
by Cristobal de Acuña
According to ancient Greek mythology,
the Amazons were warlike huntresses
who burned off the right breasts of their
daughters so that they could use the bow
and arrow more freely. In the 16th
century, a Spanish explorer in South
America, Francisco de Orellana, claimed
that he hadfought against a band of
Indians resembling Amazons, and
accordingly the river Marañan, near
which this skirmish took place, was later
renamed the Amazon (although some
believe that the name is derivedfrom an
Indian word). When they heard this story,
several travellers in South America set out
in search of the Amazons. One of these
travellers was a learned Spanish Jesuit,
Father Cristóbal de Acuña (1597-1675),
who in 1639 took part in an early
expedition to explore the Amazon region.
(Even a century later, in the "Age of the
Enlightenment", a scientific explorer in
South America such as Charles Marie de
la Condamine still took the myth of the
Amazons seriously.)
Nuevo descubrimiento del gran río de las Amazonas el
quefuey se hizopor orden de su Majestad el año 1639por
las provincias de Quito en los Reynos del Perú, 1641.
("New discovery of the great river of the Amazons,
made on the order of His Majesty the year 1639 in the
provinces of Quito in the Kingdoms of Peru, 1641")
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
of myth
The first men
on the Moon
&
a
o
Cl
[C by Neil A. Armstrong and
Edwin E. Aldrin
An old dream came true on 21 July 1969,
when the two American astronauts, Neil
A. Armstrong and Edwin E. Aldrin,
became the first men to set foot on the
Moon. At right, some of their remarks on
that historic occasion. A cosmic symbol
from time immemorial and the source of
countless myths, legends and cults, the
Earth's nearest neighbour in space at last
, showed its true face. From Antiquity to
modern times, the Moon has inspired
many feats of imaginative writing. In the
17th century, the French author Cyrano
de Bergerac wrote a novel of imaginary
travel in which a small sailing boatflew to
the Moon powered by evaporating dew,
and in the 19th century, the heroes of
Jules Verne's From the Earth to the
Moon orbited the Moon in a comfortably
furnished ballistic shell. In the 1950s, the
characters drawn by the Belgian
cartoonist Hergé (Georges Rémi, 1907-
1983) made an eventful trip to the Moon
which has already fascinated two
generations of readers, many of whom
find it hard not to think ofHergé's
fictional hero Tintín as the first human
being to walk on the Moon ...
Armstrong: Okay, Houston,* I'm on the porch.
Houston: Roger, Neil.
Aldrin: Halt where you are a minute, Neil.
Armstrong: Okay.
Aldrin: Everything's nice and straight in here.
Armstrong: Okay, can you pull the door open a little more?
Aldrin: Right.
Houston: We're getting a picture on the TV.
Aldrin: You've got a good picture, huh?
Houston: There's a great deal of contrast in it and currently it's upside down on
monitor. But we can make out a fair amount of detail.
Armstrong: Okay, will you verify the position, the opening I ought to have on the
camera.
Houston: The what? We can see you coming down the ladder now.
Armstrong: I'm at the foot of the ladder. The LM* * footpads are only depressed in
the surface about one or two inches, although the surface appears to be very, very
fine-grained as you get close to it. It's almost like a powder. It's very fine. I'm
going to step off the LM now.
That's one small step for a man, one giant leap for mankind.
The surface is fine and powdery. I can pick it up loosely with my toe. It does
adhere in fine layers like powdered charcoal to the sole and the sides of my boots.
I only go in a small fraction of an inch , maybe an eighth of an inch , but I can see the
footprints of my boots and the treads in the fine sandy particles. ...
Actually no trouble to walk around.
It's quite dark here in the shadow and a little hard for me to see if I have good
footing. I'll work my way over into the sunlight here without looking directly into
the sun. Looking up at the LM, I'm standing directly in the shadow now looking
up at ... in the windows and I can see everything quite clearly. The light is
sufficiently brightly backlighted into the front of the LM that everything is clearly
visible.
I'll step out and take some of my first pictures here.
Aldrin: Are you going to get the contingency sample? Okay. That's good.
Armstrong: The contingency sample is down and it's up. Like it's a little difficult to
dig through the crust. It's very interesting. It's a very soft surface but here and
there where I plug with the contingency sample collector I run into very hard
surface but it appears to be very cohesive material of the same sort. I'll try to get a
rock in here.
Houston: Oh, that looks beautiful from here, Neil.
Armstrong: It has a stark beauty all its own . It's like much of the high desert of the
United States. It's different but it's very pretty out here. Be advised that a lot of
the rock samples out here, the hard rock samples have what appears to be vesicles
in the surface.
Aldrin: Ready for me to come out?
Armstrong: Yeah. Just stand by a second, I'll move this over the handrail.
Aldrin: Okay?
Armstrong: All right, that's got it. Are you ready?
Aldrin: All set. ...
How far are my feet from the ...
Armstrong: You're right at the edge of the porch.
Aldrin: Small little foot movement. Porch. Arching of the back ... without any
trouble at all. Now I want to back up and partially close the hatch making sure
not to lock it on my way out.
Armstrong: Good thought ...
Aldrin: That's our home for the next couple of hours; we want to take care of it.
I'm on the top step. It's a very simple matter to hop down from one step to the
next.
Armstrong: Yes, I found that to be very comfortable, and walking is also very
comfortable, Houston. You've got three more steps and then a long one.
Aldrin: I'm going to leave that one foot up there and both hands down to about the
fourth rung up.
Armstrong: A little more. About another inch. There you got it. That's a good
step.
Aldrin: About a three footer. Beautiful view.
Armstrong: Ain't that somethin'?
Edwin E. Aldrin, the second manto
walk on the Moon, descends from
Apollo 1 1 's lunar module, which rests
on the dusty surface of the Sea of
Tranquillity.
* City in Texas, USA, and location of the Lyndon B.
Johnson Space Center, from which NASA (the National
Aeronautics and Space Administration) manages the
manned flights of the United States astronaut
programme.
* * LM = Lunar Module, the vehicle used to carry two
of the three astronauts from the Apollo 1 1 spacecraft to
the surface of the Moon and then back to the space¬
craft.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The discoverers
discovered
On their great voyages of discovery, European explorers encountered
other peoples, other climates. Their idea of the world changed. A world of
confrontation, sometimes outright opposition, between explorers and
those they "discovered" replaced a world-picture rooted in fantasy and
myth. An awareness of the differences between civilizations began to
emerge.
ermsnmm ^¡Û^ÏHOiiHfKJ^^
ON Easter Sunday, the last day of March, the Captain sent the chaplain
ashore early in the morning to celebrate Mass. And the interpreter went
with him to tell the king that we were not landing in order to dine with
him, but simply to hear Mass.
When he heard this, the king sent two dead pigs. And when the time came to say
the Mass, the Captain went ashore with fifty men, unarmed except for their
swords and each one dressed as decently as it was possible to be. Before the
barques reached shore, our ships fired six rounds of artillery as a sign of peace.
The two kings were there as we disembarked and graciously received our
Captain and placed him between them, then we went to the place prepared for the
celebration of Mass, which was not far from the shore. Before the Mass began, the
Captain threw a quantity of musk-rose water over the two kings. And when the
Mass was offered, these two kings went to kiss the cross like us, but they made no
offering. At the moment of the Elevation of the body of Our Lord, they were
kneeling as we were and worshipped our Lord with their hands joined in prayer.
And the ships fired all their guns at the Elevation of the body of Our Lord.
When Mass had been said, each one did his Christian duty, receiving Our Lord.
Then the Captain got his men to demonstrate swordsmanship, which greatly
pleased these kings. Next he had a cross brought, with the nails and the crown, to
which these kings bowed down. And the Captain had it explained to them that
these things which he was showing them were the sign of the Emperor his master
and lord, who had charged and commanded him to place it everywhere he should
go or pass by. And he told them that he wished to erect it in their country for their
benefit, because if some Spanish ships later came to these islands, when they saw
this cross they would know that we had stayed there. And thus they would do
nothing to harm them, neither their people nor their belongings. If they took any
of their people prisoner, they would let them go at once on being shown this
sign.
Furthermore, the Captain told them that it was necessary that this cross should
be erected on the summit of the highest mountain in their land, so that on seeing
the said cross each day they should worship it and that, if they did so, neither
thunder, lightning nor tempest could harm them.
These kings thanked the Captain and said that they would gladly do so. Then he
had them questioned as to whether they were Moors or Gentiles, and what they
believed in. They replied that their only form of worship was to join their hands
while looking at the sky, and that they called their god Aba. On hearing these
words the Captain was filled with joy. ... So the Captain had him [the first king]
asked if he had any enemies who made war against him , and that if there were any
he would go and defeat them with his men and his ships in order to bring them to
obedience. The king, thanking him, replied that there were two islands on which
the people were his enemies. However, this was not a good time to go and attack
them. The Captain therefore said to him that if by God's grace he should return to
this country, he would bring so many men that he would force them into obeying
the king. Then he had the interpreter tell them that he was going to dine and that
he would come back afterwards to have the cross erected on the summit of the
mountain; the two kings said that they were well pleased and, on this, they
embraced the Captain, and parted. ,
Painting on the ceiling of a church at
Cebu (Philippines), where Magellan
Magellan's Voyage Around the World, by Antonio landed ¡n 1521, shows the navigator
Pigafetta. having a cross erected.
Mass to the
sound of gunfire
by Ferdinand Magellan/
Antonio Pigafetta
A Portuguese navigator in the service of
the Spanish crown, Fernäo de
Magalhäes, (Ferdinand Magellan,
c. 1480-1521), sought the western route to
the "Spice Islands", in particular the
Moluccas, for trading purposes. But his
voyage, which supplied practical proof
that the Earth was round, had many
repercussions as a result of the account of
it brought back by Antonio Pigafetta,
chronicler of the expedition. Pigafetta was
one of the few survivors of this first
voyage around the world, which lasted
almost three years and cost Magellan his
life. In March 1521, the navigator
reached the Philippines.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
úiscovereú
Saved by the
Indians
£2 by Jacques Cartier
S
O
O
(S One of the most important exploits by
early European explorers in America was
the discovery of the St. Lawrence River in
1535 by the Breton sailor Jacques Cartier
(1491-1557). The Indian guides and
interpreters who accompanied him during
his explorations of Canada were
invaluable allies. They taught Cartier
about the country's geography and
resources, andfamiliarized him with
Indian customs and language. On his
secondjourney, during a long and severe
Canadian winter based in Stadaconé [the
Indian name for Quebec], an epidemic of
scurvy claimed the lives of many of his
men. One ofCartier's interpreters showed
him the antidote: a herbal tea rich in
vitamin C.
ONE day, our captain, seeing the sickness gaining such a hold and his men
so severely stricken by it, set out from the fort and, walking on the ice, saw
approaching him a company of people from Stadaconé, and among them
Dom Agaya, whom the captain had seen ten or twelve days previously sorely
distempered, with the same sickness from which his men were suffering; for one of
his legs was so swollen at the knee, that it was the thickness of the body of a two-
year-old child, wholly nerveless, while his teeth were loose and decayed and his
gums rotting and foul. The captain, seeing Dom Agaya healthy and nimble, was
overjoyed, hoping to learn from him how he had been cured, in order that he
might bring help and succour to his men. And when they drew near to the fort, the
captain asked him how he had been cured of his sickness. Dom Agaya replied that
he had been cured with the juice of the leaves of a tree and the crushed leaves
thereof, and that this was the sole remedy for the sickness. The captain then
inquired of him whether there might not be such trees nearby, and whether he
would show him some, that he might heal his servant, who had fallen sick of the
disease in Canada while dwelling in the house of Lord Donnacona; for he did not
wish to reveal how many of his companions were sick. Then Dom Agaya sent two
women with our captain to seek out such trees, and they brought back nine or ten
branches; and they showed us that the bark and the leaves must be pounded and
then boiled in water; that water must then be drunk one day in two, and the
residue placed on the sick and swollen legs; and they told us that this tree cured all
disease. In their language they call this tree annedda.*
Soon afterwards the captain had a brew made for the sick men to drink, and
none wished to try it, save one or two, who boldly put it to the test. As soon as they
had drunk of it, they felt relief forthwith, which was indeed a miraculous thing; for
of all the diseases afflicting them, they were cured and recovered their health,
after having drunk twice or thrice of the brew; so much so that one of the
companions who had been sick of the pox for five or six years before this new
sickness was altogether cured by this medicine. When these things were seen and
known, there was such a press for the said medicine that the men would have
murdered one another for it; so that a tree, as tall and broad as any I have ever
seen, was used up in less than a week, and wrought such an effect, that if all the
physicians of Louvain and Montpellier had been present, with all the drugs of
Alexandria, they would not have done in a year what that tree accomplished in a
week; for we had such advantage of it, that all who made use of it were cured, and
recovered their health, praise be to God.
Jacques Cartier meets a group
of Indians on the banks of the
St. Lawrence River, during
his second expedition to Canada,
in 1535.
* It has not been possible to determine exactly which
tree was used, but it is generally thought to have been
the Canadian hemlock spruce.
Voyages au Canada. A vec les relations des voyages en
Amérique de Gonneville, Verrazano el Roberval.
Festivities in the
Friendly Islands
by James Cook
The great English navigator and explorer,
Captain James Cook (1728-1779), wrote a
classic account of his voyages in the
Pacific. Cook made a great contribution
to geography by dispelling the myth that
an Antarctic continent reachedfrom the
South Pole as far as temperate latitudes,
and by bequeathing to posterity a
remarkable collection of extremely
accurate maps. To his investigations of
the lives and customs of the peoples he
encountered he brought such a high
degree of rigour and objectivity that he is
regarded as one of the first
ethnographers. During his third voyage,
in 1777, he visited the Friendly Islands
(Tonga.) where he hadfirst landed three
years before.
FEENOU* had expressed a desire to see the marines go through the military
exercise. As I was desirous to gratify his curiosity, I ordered them all
ashore, from both ships, in the morning. After they had performed various
evolutions, and fired several volleys, with which the numerous body of spectators
seemed well pleased, the chief entertained us, in his turn, with an exhibition,
which, as was acknowledged by us all, was performed with a dexterity and
exactness far surpassing the specimen we had given of our military manoeuvres. It
was a kind of a dance, so entirely different from anything I had ever seen, that I
fear I can give no description that will convey any tolerable idea of it to my
readers. It was performed by men; and one hundred and five persons bore their
parts in it. Each of them had in his hand an instrument neatly made, shaped
somewhat like a paddle, of two feet and a half in length, with a small handle and a
thin blade, so that they were very light. With these instruments they made many
and various flourishes, each of which was accompanied with a different move¬
ment. At first the performers ranged themselves in three lines, and, by various
evolutions, each man changed his station in such a manner that those who had
been in the rear came into the front. Nor did they remain long in the same
position. At one time they extended themselves into one line, they then formed
into a semicircle, and lastly into two square columns. While this last movement
was executing, one of them advanced and performed an antic dance before me,
with which the whole ended.
The musical instruments consisted of two drums, or rather two hollow logs of
wood, from which some varied notes were produced by beating on them with two
sticks. It did not, however, appear to me that the dancers were much assisted by
these sounds, but by a chorus of vocal music, in which all the performers joined at
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
the same time. Their song was not destitute of pleasing melody, and all their
corresponding motions were executed with so much skill, that the numerous body
of dancers seemed to act as if they were one great machine. It was the opinion of
every one of us that such a performance would have met with universal applause
on an European theatre; and it so far exceeded any attempt we had made to
entertain them, that they seemed to picque themselves upon the superiority they
had over us. As to our musical instruments, they held none of them in the least
esteem, except the drum, and even that they did not think equal to their own.
In order to give them a more favourable opinion of English amusements, and to
leave their minds fully impressed with the deepest sense of our superior attain¬
ments, I directed some fireworks to be got ready; and, after it was dark, played
them off in the presence of Feenou, the other chiefs, and a vast concourse of their
people. Our water and sky-rockets, in particular, pleased and astonished them
beyond all conception; and the scale was now turned in our favour.
Feenou, the chief, was considered to be ruler of the
entire archipelago.
Captain Cook's Voyages of Discovery, Everyman's
Library, J.M. Dent & Sons Ltd., London, 1948.
Captain Cook watches men of the
Friendly Islands (today Tonga) perform
a nocturnal dance, during his third
voyage (1776-1780).
The discoverers
MEN, women and girls pierce the sides of their noses; they likewise pierce
their ears and their lower lips; some men also have stitching around their
necks, but not many, and each man has his lower lip split, so that at first
glance he seems to have two mouths. In the hole made in the side of the nose they
insert a long piece of bone, and those who own beads and coral dangle these from
their ears, their lips and their noses, and consider them altogether admirable and
the finest of ornaments. They never shave their chins, not all of them wear shirts,
their feet are bare, and indoors they go about wholly unclothed except for a scrap
of animal skin or flowers and grass which they wear around their waists, knotted in
front. They wear parkas made from the skins of beaver, fox or bear, feathers, or
the skins of Arctic hare, muskrat or lynx. There is a type of parka with a special
name which is made from the intestines of sea-lions, seals and whales. On their
heads they wear headgear fashioned out of pine roots and grass, plaited together
to form curved and concave wooden caps. To hunt marine animals they use
harpoons, which they hurl from platforms, and for warfare they have bows and
spears made of iron, copper, bone and stone. Their axes are of a special type,
consisting of a small piece of iron. Their pipes and knives are of iron and bone, and
their needles are of iron. ... Before our arrival, the women manufactured their
needles themselves. Thread is made of gut, and their crockery is made of wood,
the horns of wild sheep, clay or hollowed stone.
They have large and small boats which are made, not of planks but of skins,
sewn over the framework so as to be watertight, with just one opening, and these
they use to fish or to hunt marine fauna. In the rivers they fish by building small
dams with stones and impaling the fish on pointed implements similar to spears; in
the end of these is a notch into which they insert a stone or iron pin held in place
with bone pegs and attached by a length of gut to a piece of wood. In the gulfs and
bays hollowed out by the sea, they use harpoons to kill the larger fish when they
emerge from the water. They make fire by friction on wood; for lamps they use the
blubber of seals, bears, sea-lions or whales, which they burn in stone receptacles,
dipping lengths of grass into these to serve as wicks.
When visitors arrive, they greet them by daubing their own faces with red dye
and putting on their finest apparel; they beat tambourines and perform a dance,
brandishing their weapons of war; the guests themselves arrive as if for a battle.
As soon as they approach the banks, the hosts jump into the sea and wade chest
deep. They drag large and small boats onto the banks as fast as they can, and then
hurry to lift out their guests, whom they carry one by one on their backs to the
place chosen for the feast; there, they seat them in their allotted places, and all
remain silent until they have eaten and drunk to satiety. The first attention shown,
and the most keenly appreciated, is to give cold water to the guests, after which
Frontispiece ofa Russian edition of
Grigori Shelikhov's account ofhis
travels, published at St. Petersburg
(Leningrad) In 1 793.
A Russian on the
coast of Alaska
by Grigori Shelikhov
In 1740-1741 a party ofRussian explorers
with their Danish guide, Vitus Jonassen
Bering, discovered Alaska and the
Aleutian Islands. A fur trade was
established in anarchic conditions and
continued until it was organized on a
sounder basis by Grigori Shelikhov (1747-
1797), an enterprising Russian merchant.
Shelikhov assembled all the merchants
into a single "Company ofAmerica",
which set up trading posts on almost all
the Aleutian Islands. Between 1783 and
1786, Shelikhov comprehensively
explored the islands, of which he made
the first detailed and accurate maps. His
descriptions of the way of life of the
inhabitants and of their surroundings are
ethnographic documents ofgreat value.
The strait between Kodiak Island and the
Alaska Peninsula still bears his name.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
discovered
S
O
o
"O
CD
¡5
"Peregrinations of the Russian merchant Grigori She¬
likhov from Okhotsk to the coasts of America by the
Eastern Ocean (1791)"
the boys serve out the food fat, a-mixture of fat's, seal, whale and sea-lion. They
also serve berries, and in particularjed whortleberries, cranberries, bilberries and
Arctic brambles, to which they add various roots; the berries are not mixed. They
also provide dried fish known as pokola, and the meat of various animals and
birds, according to the best that each has at his disposal. Salt is unknown to them.
Each dish and each drink must be tasted first by the head of the household,
otherwise the guests will not touch it; the occurrence ofpoisons is, apparently, not
unknown. When the head of the household has tasted each dish, he passes it to the
first of his guests, who helps himself and passes it on to his neighbour, and so on
from first to last. Anything left is sent back to the first, who sets it aside, and, when
they leave, the guests carry away all these leftovers with them.
The swimming
postman
by Alexander von Humboldt
When thirty-year-old Alexander von
Humboldt set offfor South America in
1799, with his friend Aimé Bonpland, he
had already studied a vast range of
subjects, including botany, chemistry,
mineralogy, and galvanism the theories
of the Italian physiologist Luigi Galvani.
Naturalist, explorer, geographer and
geologist, historian andpolitician, this
Prussian baron (1769-1859) and polymath
qualifies, through the objectivity of his
descriptions of the Indians, as a founder
ofAmerican anthropology, ethnology and
archaeology. In 1802 he was in Peru,
where he mapped the volcanoes around
Quito (today the capital ofEcuador),
almost reached the summit ofChimborazo
(6,272 metres), described the remains of
the Inca Empire, and stayedfor a short
time in the Amazon region, where he may
have seen the swimming postman.
Humboldt later reached the coast of the
Pacific, where he discovered the famous
cold oceanic current which was
subsequently named after him.
Alexander von
Humboldt and his
friend and
travelling
companion, the
French naturalist
Aimé Bonpland
(1773-1858),
observe a shower
ofshooting stars on
the coast of South
Américain 1799.
THE inhabitants have a very singular way of using the lower reaches of the
Rio Guancabamba, at the place where there are a great many waterfalls, in
order to enable the area to communicate with the sea-coasts to the south.
To speed on their way the few letters that are sent from Truxillo to the province of
Jaén de Bracamoros, they use a swimming messenger. In two days, this unusual
postman, who is as a rule a young Indian, swims down from Pomahuaca to
Tomependa, following first the Rio Chamaya, the name given to the Rio Guan¬
cabamba in its lower reaches , and then the River Amazon . He carefully wraps the
few letters that he must carry in a large piece of cotton cloth which he rolls like a
turban around his head. When he reaches the waterfalls he swims ashore and
enters the river again lower down, walking through the woods that shade its
banks. In order to swim for so long without becoming exhausted, he often
encircles one of his arms with a strip of very light wood (ceyba, palo de balsa) of
the Bombacaceae family. Sometimes, too, he swims in company with one of his
friends. Neither of them need worry about food and lodging, since they are sure to
receive a hospitable welcome in the huts scattered among the splendid huertas of
Pucará or Cavico, densely fringed with fruit trees.
The Rio Chamaya is not, fortunately, infested with crocodiles. In the Marañón
itself, these animals do not travel further upstream than the Mayasi cataract;
being indolent by nature, they prefer quieter waters. I have observed that from
the ford or paso of Pucará to the point where the Rio Chamaya flows into the
River Amazon, below the village of Choros (that is, over a distance not exceeding
22 leagues), there is a gradient of 542 metres. The governor of the province of
Jaén de Bracamoros has assured me that the letters thus transported seldom get
wet and are seldom lost. I myself, shortly after my return from Mexico to Paris,
received a letter from Tomependa which had followed this route. It is the custom
among many Indian communities living on the banks of the Marañón to travel in
the same way, swimming downstream in a group. I once counted in the river the
heads of thirty or forty men , women and children of the Xibaros tribe , just as they
were arriving in Tomependa. The "swimming postman" returns on foot up the
steep path of the páramo del Paredón. u
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Merchants
and adventurers
No trade without travel, and vice versa. In prehistoric times men and goods
began to move along the trade routes which would in the course of time
develop into great arteries for the diffusion of cultures and ways of life (see
the Unesco Courier, June 1984). Unsuspected dangers sometimes lay in
wait for intrepid merchants who set out for distant lands.
aimirti ijifai.ii^?;,-«!'*.^ mr»ii«>-jj^'j>A^..igM..^j]>M/^..) j>-.r,.
THE city of Bidar is guarded at night by a thousand men under the fortress
commander. They are mounted, wear armour and each of them carries a
torch.
I sold my stallion in Bidar. He had cost me sixty-eight futun. I had fed him for a
year.
In Bidar one can see snakes twelve feet long slithering through the streets.
I arrived in Bidar from Kodangal for the feast of St. Philip, and I sold my
stallion for Christmas. I remained in Bidar until Lent. I made the acquaintance of
many Indians there. I told them my religion not Muslim but Isâ-dîni, Chris¬
tian and that my name was Athanasius but that my Muslim name was Khoja
Yusuf Khorasani. They didn't try to hide from me, either to eat, to do business or
for their mana, or for anything else. Likewise, they did not hide their women from
me.
I asked them about their religion and they said, "We believe in Adam."
According to them the But are Adam and all his descendants. Altogether there
are eighty-four religions in India, and they all believe in the But. ...
In May, I celebrated Easter in the Muslim city of Bidar .... The Muslims for
their part celebrated Baghrâm on a Wednesday in May. I began the Lenten fast on
the first day of April. Oh faithful Christians, he who travels much in many lands
commits many sins and loses his Christian faith. And I, Athanasius, poor servant
of God, have suffered greatly for my religion. Already four Lents have passed and
four Easters, and I, a sinner, know neither Easter nor when Lent is, nor Christmas
nor the other feasts. I know neither Wednesday nor Friday. I have no book. When
they robbed me they took my books. Because of all these misfortunes I went to
India, for I had nothing to take back to Russia, I had no goods left. In the first
year, I celebrated Easter at Nâïn, in the second at Chapakur in Mazanderan, in
the third at Hormuz and in the fourth at Bidar in India, amongst the Muslims. And
I wept much for the faith, the Christian faith.
Malik the Muslim strongly pressed me to adopt the Muslim faith. I said to him,
"Sir, tu namâz qïlar-sàn, man da namâz qïlar-man; tu bes namâz qïlar-siz, man da
3 qïlar-man; man gharîb e sän în-jây [you pray and I pray too. You say five
prayers, I say three. I am a stranger; you are in your own country here]."
And he said, "In truth, you claim that you are not a Muslim, but you do not
know the Christian religion."
Then I began to think a lot and I said to myself, "Woe to me, accursed. I have
strayed far from the path of truth and do not know the way back! Here I am
walking alone! O Lord my God, master of all things, creator of heaven and earth,
do not turn your face away from your servant because I am indeed close to
misfortune. Lord, behold me, have pity on me your creature. Do not let me stray
from the way of truth. Put me O Lord on your right road since I have done nothing
which could please you in this misfortune, O Lord, since I have spent all my days
in evil. Allah perverdigâr Allah kerim Allah rahîm Allah kerim Allah rahîm
Allah câlîm alculamâ [God the protector, generous God, merciful God, God the
wisest of the wise]. I have spent four Easters in Muslim lands and have not
renounced my Christian faith. Only God knows what will happen. Lord my God, I
put my trust in thee. Save me, Lord my God."
Reflections on
solitude
by Athanasius Nikitin
The travels ofAthanasius Nikitin, a
Russian merchantfrom the town of Tver
(today Kalinin), lastedfrom 1466 until
1472, the year in which he died near
Smolensk. After trading in the Turkish
countries on the borders of the Caspian
Sea and travelling through Iran, he lived
for almost three years in India. Nikitin
left a short account of his journeys,
including a notable description of his
experiences in the Bahmani Kingdom of
the Deccan Plateau where he livedfor a
time in the town ofBidar, in which
evocations of the landscape are mingled
with practical information on food, prices
and travel. His book is also a reflection
on solitude: during his sojourn in Muslim
and Hindu India, the Christian merchant
felt that he was losing his identity.
Still from Journey Beyond Three Seas (1958),
a Sov/ef-ind/an film by Vassili Pronin and
Ahrmat Abhat based on Athanasius Nikitin 's
traveljournal. Oleg Strijenov is seen in the role
of the 15th-century Russian merchant and
traveller.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
adventurers
The Burial of the Sardine, painted around
1810 by the Spanish artist Francisco Goya
(1746-1 828). This carnival scene is one of
Goya 's most powerful depictions of Spanish
life.
Scholar
Gypsy
by George Borrow
A tall, strapping Englishman "standing
sixfoot two in his stockings", George
Borrow (1803-1881) was, with his shock
of white hair, a man of distinctive
appearance. An accomplished horseman,
knife-thrower andfriend of the Gypsies
whose language he spoke fluently, he
bore more resemblance to a character in a
novel than to the travelling salesman he
became when the British and Foreign
Bible Society, after sending him on a
mission to Russia, commissioned him to
distribute the Bible in the Iberian
Peninsula. The Bible in Spain (1842), his
account of this evangelical mission, is
sub-titled "The Journeys, Adventures,
and Imprisonments of an Englishman in
an Attempt to Circulate the Scriptures in
the Peninsula". This story ofBorrow's
adventures, by turns amusing, dramatic
and tragic, was an overwhelming success
when it was published and is still as
popular as ever. The incident he describes
here takes place in Madrid.
* Twelve ounces of bread, small pound, as given in the
prison. (Borrow's note.)
The Bible in Spain, Everyman's Library, J.M. Dent &
Sons Ltd., London, 1969.
APROPOS of bull-fighters: Shortly after my arrival, I one day entered a low
tavern in a neighbourhood notorious for robbery and murder, and in
which for the last two hours I had been wandering on a voyage of discov¬
ery. I was fatigued, and required refreshment. I found the place thronged with
people, who had all the appearance of ruffians. I saluted them, upon which they
made way for me to the bar, taking off their sombreros with great ceremony. I
emptied a glass of val de peñas, and was about to pay for it and depart, when a
horrible-looking fellow, dressed in a buff jerkin, leather breeches, and jackboots,
which came halfway up his thighs, and having on his head a white hat, the rims of
which were at least a yard and a half in circumference, pushed through the crowd,
and confronting me, roared
"Otra copita! vamos Inglesito: Otra copita!" ["Another glass! Come on, little
Englishman, another glass!"]
"Thank you, my good sir, you are very kind, you appear to know me, but I have
not the honour of knowing you."
"Not know me!" replied the being. "I am Sevilla, the torero. I know you well;
you are the friend of Baltasarito, the national, who is a friend of mine, and a very
good subject."
Then turning to the company, he said in a sonorous tone, laying a strong
emphasis on the last syllable of every word, according to the custom of the gente
rufianesca [brigands] throughout Spain
"Cavaliers, and strong men, this cavalier is the friend of a friend of mine. Es
mucho hombre. [He's quite a man.] There is none like him in Spain. He speaks the
crabbed Gitano though he is an Inglesito. "
"We do not believe it," replied several grave voices. "It is not possible."
"It is not possible, say you? I tell you it is. Come forward, Balseiro, you who
have been in prison all your life, and are always boasting that you can speak the
crabbed Gitano, though I say you know nothing of itcome forward and speak to
his worship in the crabbed Gitano."
A low, slight, but active figure stepped forward. He was in his shirt sleeves, and
wore a montero cap; his features were handsome, but they were those of a
demon.
He spoke a few words in the broken gipsy slang of the prison, inquiring of me
whether I had ever been in the condemned cell, and whether I knew what a
Gitana* was?
"Vamos Inglesito, " shouted Sevilla, in a voice of thunder; "answer the monro
[fellow] in the crabbed Gitano."
I answered the robber, for such he was, and one, too, whose name will live for
many a year in the ruffian histories of Madrid ; I answered him in a speech of some
length, in the dialect of the Estremenian gipsies.
"I believe it is the crabbed Gitano," muttered Balseiro. "It is either that or
English, for I understand not a word of it."
"Did I not say to you," cried the bull-fighter, "that you knew nothing of the
crabbed Gitano? But this Inglesito does. I understood all he said. Vaya, there is
none like him for the crabbed Gitano. He is a good ginete, [horseman] too; next to
myself, there is none like him, only he rides with stirrup leathers too short.
Inglesito, if you have need of money, I will lend you my purse. All I have is at your
service, and that is not a little; I have just gained four thousand chulés by the
lottery. Courage, Englishman! Another cup. I will pay all. I, Sevilla!"
And he clapped his hand repeatedly on his breast, reiterating, "I, Sevilla! I "
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The art ofmeeting othersî
The extracts in this section have been chosen to illustrate the give-and-
take inherent in human encounters, rather than the destructive aspects of
contacts between different civilizations. The following descriptions of three
extraordinary experiences which happened at key moments in the history
of the relations between peoples, are a celebration, imbued with a certain
nostalgia, of human diversity.
SOME of the people of the ship used to tell me they were going to carry me
back to my own country and this made me very happy. I was quite rejoiced
at the sound of going back, and thought if I should get home what wonders I
should have to tell. But I was reserved for another fate and was soon undeceived
when we came within sight of the English coast. While I was on board this ship, my
captain and master named me Gustavus Vasa. I at that time began to understand
him a little, and refused to be called so, and told him as well as I could that I would
be called Jacob; but he said I should not, and still called me Gustavus; and when I
refused to answer to my new name , which at first I did , it gained me many a cuff ; so
at length I submitted and was obliged to bear the present name, by which I have
been known ever since.
The ship had a very long passage, and on that account we had very short
allowance of provisions. Towards the last we had only one pound and a half of
bread per week, and about the same quantity of meat, and one quart of water a
day. We spoke with only one vessel the whole time we were at sea, and but once
we caught a few fishes. In our extremities the captain and people told me in jest
they would kill and eat me, but I thought them in earnest and was depressed
beyond measure, expecting every moment to be my last. While I was in this
situation, one evening they caught, with a good deal of trouble, a large shark, and
got it on board. This gladdened my poor heart exceedingly, as I thought it would
serve the people to eat instead of their eating me; but very soon, to my astonish¬
ment, they cut off a small part of the tail and tossed the rest over the side. This
renewed my consternation, and I did not know what to think of these white
people, though I very much feared they would kill and eat me.
There was on board the ship a young lad who had never been at sea before,
about four or five years older than myself: his name was Richard Baker. He was a
native of America, had. received an excellent education, and was of a most
amiable temper. Soon after I went on board he showed me a great deal of
partiality and attention and in return I grew extremely fond of him. We at length
became inseparable , and for the space of two years he was of very great use to me
and was my constant companion and instructor. Although this dear youth had
many slaves of his own, yet he and I have gone through many sufferings together
on shipboard, and we have many nights lain in each other's bosoms when we were
in great distress. Thus such a friendship was cemented between us as we cherished
till his death, which to my very great sorrow happened in the year 1759, when he
was up the Archipelago on board his Majesty's ship the Preston, an event which I
have never ceased to regret as I lost at once a kind interpreter, an agreeable
companion, and a faithful friend; who, at the age of fifteen, discovered a mind
superior to prejudice, and who was not ashamed to notice, to associate with, and
to be the friend and instructor of one who was ignorant, a stranger, of a different
complexion, and a slave!
Olaudah Equiano as portrayed on the
frontispiece of the first edition of his
autobiography, The Interesting
Narrative of the Life of Olaudah .
Equiano, or Gustavus Vasa, the
African. Written by Himself (1 789).
How I became
Gustavus Vasa
by Olaudah Equiano
At the age often, Olaudah Equiano, born
in 1745 in a village in what is now
Nigeria, was captured and sold as a slave
to a planter in the West Indies and worked
there and aboard slave ships that plied the
Atlantic. By the age of nineteen, he had
saved enough money to buy his freedom.
As a free man, he served as a merchant
seaman and quartermaster and did a
variety of otherjobs. He visited the
Mediterranean and took part in Phipps'
expedition to the Arctic in 1773. Equiano
was an ardent and active member of the
Anti-Slavery movement and towards the
end of his life was appointed Commissary
ofStores on a ship carryingfreed slaves
to Sierra Leone. His autobiography,
published in 1789, was famous in his
time, and ran into some 12 editions in the
United Kingdom and the United States
between 1789 and 1827.
Equiano's Travels, edited by Paul Edwards. Heincmann
Educational Books, London and Ibadan, 1967. Photo © Heinemann Educational books Ltd., London and Ibadan
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
meeting others
ce
Long nose,
white skin and
'honey mouth'
by Mungo Park
In 1795, a young Scots surgeon named
Mungo Park was commissioned by the
African Association ofLondon to explore
the true course of the Niger. As he
advanced into the interior ofAfrica he
discovered a continent comprising many
busy, sovereign States engaged in trade.
In his account of his travels, a unique
description of the west African slave trade
and an outstanding ethnographic
document, Mungo Pdrk brings back to
life the vanished world of the upper
Gambia river. Uncompromisingly written,
free from exoticism, his book presents a
series of encounters made by a traveller of
outstanding human qualities.
Portraitofthe Scottish explorer Mungo Park (1 771-
1805). In 1798 he pub/isriedTravels in the Interior
Districts of Africa Performed Under the Direction
and Patronage of the African Association in the Years
1 795, 1 796, and 1 797 by Mungo Park, Surgeon.
WHEN we came to the entrance of the court in which the king resides,
both my guide and interpreter, according to custom, took off their
sandals; and the former pronounced the king's name aloud, repeating it
till he was answered from within. We found the monarch sitting upon a mat, and
two attendants with him. I repeated what I had before told him concerning the
object of my journey, and my reasons for passing through his country. He
seemed, however, but half satisfied. The notion of travelling for curiosity was
quite new to him. He thought it impossible, he said, that any man in his senses
would undertake so dangerous a journey, merely to look at the country and its
inhabitants; however, when I offered to show him the contents of my portman¬
teau, and everything belonging to me, he was convinced; and it was evident that
his suspicion had arisen from a belief that every white man must of necessity be a
trader. When I had delivered my presents, he seemed well pleased, and was
particularly delighted with the umbrella, which he repeatedly furled and unfurled,
to the great admiration of himself and his two attendants , who could not for some
time comprehend the use of this wonderful machine. After this I was about to take
my leave, when the king, desiring me to stop awhile, began a long preamble in
favour of the whites, extolling their immense wealth and good dispositions. He
next proceeded to an eulogium on my blue coat, of which the yellow buttons
seemed particularly to catch his fancy; and he concluded by entreating me to
present him with it; assuring me, for my consolation under the loss of it, that he
would wear it on all public occasions, and inform every one who saw it of my great
liberality towards him. The request of an African prince, in his own dominions,
particularly when made to a stranger, comes little short of a command. It is only a
way of obtaining by gentle means what he can, if he pleases, take by force; and, as
it was against my interest to offend him by a refusal, I very quietly took off my
coat, the only good one in my possession, and laid it at his feet.
In return for my compliance, he presented me with great plenty of provisions,
and desired to see me again in the morning. I accordingly attended, and found him
sitting upon his bed. He told me he was sick, and wished to have a little blood
taken from him; but I had no sooner tied up his arm, and displayed the lancet,
than his courage failed, and he begged me to postpone the operation till the
afternoon, as he felt himself, he said, much better than he had been, and thanked
me kindly for my readiness to serve him. He then observed that his women were
very desirous to see me, and requested that I would favour them with a visit. ...
They were ten or twelve in number, most of them young and handsome, and
wearing on their heads ornaments of gold, and beads of amber.
They rallied me with a good deal of gaiety on different subjects, particularly
upon the whiteness of my skin , and the prominency of my nose. They insisted that
both were artificial. The first, they said, was produced when I was an infant, by
dipping me in milk; and they insisted that my nose had been pinched every day till
it had acquired its present unsightly and unnatural conformation. On my part,
without disputing my own deformity, I paid them many compliments on African
beauty. I praised the glossy jet of their skins, and the lovely depression of their
noses; but they said that flattery, or (as they emphatically termed it) "honey
mouth", was not esteemed in Bondou. In return, however, for my company or my
compliments (to which, by the way, they seemed not so insensible as they affected
to be) , they presented me with a jar of honey and some fish , which were sent to my
lodging, and I was desired to come again to the king a little before sunset.
I carried with me some beads and writing paper, it being usual to present some
Continued page 23
Colour pages
Opposite page
The Cathedral of Mexico City, illumination
from the Tarikh-i Yeni Dunya ("History of the
New World") by 'AH Chelebi (Iran, second half
of 17th century). Eastern and Western fea¬
tures are mingled in this original composite
¡mage. At left of tree, possibly a guava, stands
a church with a roof shaped like an Aztec
step-pyramid. Inside sits a venerable
greybearded patriarch who supports himself
by means of an Indian meditation band. Out¬
side two figures dressed in Mughal costume
carry a man kneeling in prayer, an image
which recalls the wooden statues of Catholic
saints borne in religious processions. Above
is a group of figures in partial European cos¬
tume, intended to be conquistadors.
Photo © Chester Beatty, Dublin
Centre pages
Clockwise, starting from bottom left: (1) Two
officers from the expedition led by the French
navigator La Perouse (1741-1788), measure
the giant stone statues of Easter Island
(Chile), on 9 April 1 786. This engraving (c.
1820) is based on a drawing by Duché de
Vancy. (2) Watercolour of Guang Zhou Street,
Canton, southern China, painted in 1863 by
the German artist Eduard Hildebrandt (1818-
1869). (3) Map from a 13th-century Maghreb
manuscript of the Kitâb nuzhat al-mushtäq fi
ikhtiräq al-äfäq ("The Pleasure Excursion of
One Who is Eager to Traverse the Regions of
the World") by the Arab geographer al-ldrisi
(1100-C.1165). This great descriptive work
divides the known world into seven climatic
zones. Map shown here represents the 6th
part of the 4th zone. In accordance with a
convention of early Arab cartography, the
south is at top of map. The River Tigris and its
tributaries are at bottom right. In bottom left
corner, part of the Caspian Sea. (4) Mural
executed in 1986 at Jacmel (Haiti) com¬
memorating the arrival of Columbus in Amer¬
ica. (5) Camel caravan in the Malian desert.
(1)Photo © Rojas Mix, Paris. (2) Photo © Jean-Loup Charmet,
Paris. Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs, Paris. (3) Photo ©
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris. (4) Photo © George Buxin, Paris.
(5) Photo M. Huet © Hoa-Qui, Paris.
Page 22
Above: Saturn and its rings photographed on
3 November 1980 by the American inter¬
planetary probe Voyager 1, from a distance of
13 million kilometres. Two of the planet's
moons can be seen: Tethys (below) and
Dione. Below: Paysage exotique ("Exotic
Landscape", 1908), by the French painter
Henri "Le Douanier" Rousseau (1844-1910),
shows a jungle jungle landscape transformed
by the artist's imagination.
Photo © Collection PPP/NASA Photo © Artephot/Lavaud
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
aï*
«.^
¿Jjiï'ConJW
f 1
o»\o L 1
ft! 1
*&.**.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
'--f. tW&terXJt&i
*!¿'
->>'
^ <>^
*M
M
HOMMRGE)
CCOLOMB
5DC <
1492
V
w
*.%
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Continued from page 18
small offering on taking leave, in return for which the king gave me five drachms
of gold, observing that it was but a trifle, and given out of pure friendship, but
would be of use to me in travelling for the purchase of provision. He seconded this
act of kindness by one still greater, politely telling me, that though it was custom¬
ary to examine the baggage of every traveller passing through his country, yet, in
the present instance, he would dispense with that ceremony; adding, I was at
liberty to depart when I pleased.
The art of
CD
CD
£
Travels into the Interior of Africa. Eland Books,
London, 1983.
CD
3
rwty^wnwBitpiwHi BMHffMWWWBWPPI
THAT an impression of the "exotic" is relative stands in no further need of
proof. It is the effect of a mere spatial shift, distance, or, when distance is
abolished, the surprise of the first few moments. Here I am, now living
quite naturally in "faraway places", moving easily and without curiosity among
the same old customs. ... Now, it is the thought of returning to Old Europe that
seems like a mirage. ...
Consider me, yesterday morning, on the track which follows the circumference
of the island, riding in an American buggy harnessed to a rather frisky horse, with
Le Morne as the hub around which we turn. The endless reef, the calm sea, the
rustling of dry leaves that the land-crabs haul laboriously into their holes . . . there
is Faa-Nui, the great valley, the priestly name of Bora Bora itself.
Towards evening comes the beat of the drum, the conscientious summons to the
Upa-Upa, but it is not taken up. Cheerless couples pass by. A mere four dancers,
including the fine figure of Terii Farani. Night falls. The drum throbs in a frenzy,
played by an old blind man whose only joy in life is drumming.
The man's whole being is rhythm. His shoulders shake and follow the move¬
ments of the dance with great precision. He works up to emotional crescendos. He
is cajoling people to dance. The dejected couples look on indifferently. Half¬
heartedly, they form a ring. And now here is Terii Farani, in a white tapa,
crowned with large white flowers, her slightly hooked nose with its fine curve, her
flashing eyes, her delicately shaped and attractive mouth, and her proud stance
and she decides to take the lead. Her feet mark time with quick, tiny steps. Her
hips sway beneath her steadily motionless torso. Her arms undulate and swing;
her hands, from time to time, vibrate. Before she is drunk for later we shall give
her ample opportunity this woman is truly beautiful. Then, in the arms of a tane,
with her hand on his broad shoulder and the other clasping his equally broad
hand, in the very pose of our European waltz, she mimics our feeble little dances,
our fragile porcelain polkas, and gives them her beautiful gestures and attitudes,
and all the "grandiose grace" of her race.
And I think how very ridiculous a Frenchwoman would look if, spontaneously,
without any practice beforehand, she tried to imitate some native dance step!
This woman has a pure beauty.
The few lights go out and the old drum slackens its pace. The great grass-fringed
lawn darkens to black, and the night swallows thefare-himene, the fare-puera and
the school, three great edifices, the last two of which have proved lethal to the
country. We are doing much to force "civilization" into retreat, and doing it
cheerfully! In disobedience to official orders and moral injunctions, a few gallons
of strong rum have been brought ashore, together with plentiful supplies of wine.
We go indoors, and encourage the dancers and musicians to drink. And these
dignified women get drunk as if they were performing a duty, promptly, draining
at a draught each glass as it is held out to them, until their eyes turn up in their
sockets and their lips grow thick. ... The company includes the very young
Tanahoa, a nice fellow, who asks for "perfumes" and offers his relative in
exchange; and there is Atu, the relative in question, tall and gentle, with such kind
eyes, and Hina (the Moon-child), nearly auburn and wilder, and then Rereao,
slighter and livelier; and finally, Terii Farani, who complicates her dances with
new steps, inspired by alcohol, who nevertheless holds her graceful posture, and
who, above all, is prudent enough to withdraw from the scene before her inevi¬
table collapse.
The honest schoolteacher, who leads a devout and upright life and sings in
church, must be losing sleep, in his fare almost next door!
Journal des îles, Les Editions du Pacifique,
Papeete (Tahiti), 1978.
An illustrated page from thejournal of
Victor Segalen (1878-1 91 9), dated 1
January 1904 at Mangareva, the largest
of the Gambier Islands (French Polynesia).
Island fling
by Victor Segalen
s
In 1903 and 1904, the French writer
Victor Segalen (1878-1919), a surgeon
aboard the Tahiti-based sloop la Durance,
sailed the length and breadth of
Polynesia. He was immediately aware of
the drama then being enacted in the
islands: the slow disappearance of the
traditional Maori civilization. He set out
to collect the surviving evidence of this
civilization about which he wrote a
masterpiece, Les immémoriaux,
published in 1907 under the pseudonym
ofMaxAnély. He also returnedfrom his
voyage with the draft of an "essay on
exoticism". In his denunciation of the
tragedy ofa people being deprived of its
myths and language, Segalen draws
attention to the fatal inner destruction
which the clash of two civilizations can
bring about.
h ' î **. j < fti*.
{** i\ÁÍ'*/t <***-
Ùl c* hi***- fr****,
(' ma
U+ **** 4x*i<,~ X
* > ( MUUV
£**-.. fr . A/w* -
/i*-rt.««^-. **t ***
¿U A4*** gf>1 !
-_^_t. _ ¿tf*í**"^' 4* *****
/l». (.«I* *v
fju. kxjLs t**^u*'
Lj, . ¡fit**Jé U**k <-.. UJ t
¿i. m H*à dm. Mf* ufuà
vi**./ /» e»-*'. '' í*' ífcVí* «
»***¿t*-#
"~V	¿TE
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Pilgrims and missionaries
The pilgrim is a universal figure. Between the 4th and the 11th century,
Chinese Buddhist pilgrims often made their way to India by land or sea,
and several of them wrote exciting accounts of their "journey to the West".
The missionary is a more typically Western figure. From the 16th century
on, many Christian evangelists set out from Europe to preach in the Far
East. Some of them were great travellers.
KWillliM^'iffEHBWWfcMMW» wmwmppvm
How Buddhism
came to
Karnasuvarna
by Xuan Zang
The most famous Chinese pilgrim who
visited India was Xuan Zang (602-664), a
Buddhist monk with encyclopaedic
religious knowledge. Unhappy about the
doctrinal errors and divergences he had
noted in the Chinese versions of the '
sacred Buddhist scriptures, he decided to
go to India in search of the original texts
and to study with Indian masters. After a
stay lasting several years, he returned to
China with over 600 works, relics and
souvenirs. He spent the rest of his life
translating philosophical texts and
teaching. His Ta-T'ang Hsi-yü-chi
("Records of the Western Regions of the
Great Tang Dynasty") describes his
journey.
Illustration from Sun Wukong becomes a
Buddhist (1984), a Chinese book ofchildren's
stories adapted from Xiyouji (The Monkey
King or Pilgrimage to the West), an epic novel
based on Xuan Zang'sjourney to India. The
Monkey King, Sun Wukong, protects Xuan
Zang (on horseback) from a tiger.
KARNASUVARNA was 4,400 or 4,500 li in circumference and its capital
was over 20 li in circumference. It was a prosperous state with a large
population. Its land was low and moist and farming operations there were
conducted regularly in accordance with the seasons. Everywhere in the state,
there were blooming flowers and trees laden with rare fruits. The climate was
temperate and the people were of good character. They were patrons of learning
and believed in both Buddhism and other religions. There were more than ten
Buddhist monasteries and over two thousand Brethren who were all adherents of
the Sammatiya School. There were also fifty Deva-Temples and the followers of
the various religions were very numerous. There were another three Buddhist
monasteries where the Brethren did not eat milk products in accordance with the
teaching of Devadatta.
Near the capital was the Luoduoweizhi Monastery (or Red Mud Monastery in
the language of the T'ang Dynasty). With its spacious rooms and courtyards and
lofty pavilions and platforms, it was a magnificent and famous establishment, the
resort of illustrious Brethren and scholars from throughout the state. They
gathered there to exchange ideas and discuss theories and philosophies.
In earlier years, no one in the state believed in Buddhism. Once, a person of
another religion from South India strutted into the capital with a walking stick in
his hand, with his stomach girded by a copper sheathing and bearing on his head a
light.
Someone asked this person: "Why are you putting such odd things around your
stomach and on your head?"
The man answered: "I have too much learning and my stomach would burst out
(if not protected by the copper sheathing) and I pity those stupid and ignorant
masses, so I bear a light on my head to enlighten them." ,
He was beating a drum and challenging anyone to debate with him. Ten days
went by, and no one dared to ask the man any questions. Even a search through all
the elites in the state proved vain.
The King said: "Why is it that we can't find a wise and illustrious person in the
whole state? It's a galling shame that when a guest here asks a question, no one in
the state can answer it. Try again among those hermits."
Then someone came forward and told the King: "There is a stranger in the
forest who calls himself Sramana. He has been living in solitude for a long time
and devoting himself to study. If he is not a learned and highly moral person , how
could he behave in this way?"
After hearing the story, the King himself went to the forest to invite the stranger
to take part in the debate.
Sramana told the King: "I am from South India and staying here as a guest. I do
not have much learning and probably cannot live up to your expectations. I am
grateful for your invitation and cannot persist in declining it. If I win the debate, I
wish you would found a Buddhist monastery and invite the Brethren to spread the
doctrines of Buddhism."
The King answered: "I promise and we will never forget your great kindness."
Sramana accepted the King's invitation and went to meet the braggart. The
latter made a speech of more than 30,000 words on the doctrines of his religion.
The speech, imbued with profound meaning and a wide range of knowledge,
touched on almost everything under the sun, from theories created by famous
persons to his own experiences.
However, after listening to the speech no more than a moment, Sramana saw all
the meaning in it. He used only a few hundred words in his reply and interpreta¬
tion, making not a single mistake, and then asked some hard questions about his
opponent's doctrines. The braggart realized that he had been defeated in the
argument, and fell silent. He was totally discredited and retreated in disgrace. The
King deeply respected the talent of Sramana and founded the Luoduoweizhi
Monastery to begin spreading the doctrines of Buddhism.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
WE had reached the dessert, in other words, we were rinsing out our
bowls with buttered tea when the two Lamas, so-called merchants,
reappeared. "The regent," they said, "is waiting for you at his palace.
He wants to speak to you."...
There was no longer any doubt about our situation. The Government intended
to take an interest in us. But for what purpose? Was it to do us good or to do us ill?
To free us or to keep us prisoner? To let us live or to have us killed? "Let us go and
see the regent," we said to ourselves, "and for the rest, God's will be done!"
Having put on our finest gowns and our imposing fox-fur bonnets, we said to an
attendant, "Let us go!"
"What about this young man?" he asked, pointing to Samdadchiemba, who
turned his eyes upon him in a most unfriendly way.
"This young man? He is our servant. He will look after the house during our
absence."
"It's not that. He must come too. The regent wants to see all three of you."
By way of toilet, Samdadchiemba shook his great sheepskin gown, tilted a little
black fur hat over his ear in a very cocky fashion and, after padlocking the door of
our dwelling, we all set forth together.
After charging along for five or six minutes we came to the palace of the first
Kalon, regent of Tibet. We crossed a large courtyard where many Lamas and
Chinese were gathered. When they saw us appear they began to whisper. We were
made to stop in front of a gilded double door whose leaves were ajar. The master
of ceremonies went along a small corridor on the left and almost at once the door
opened. At the end of a simply decorated room we saw a figure seated cross-
legged on a thick cushion covered with a tiger-skin. It was the regent.
As soon as we were seated, the regent began to contemplate us at length in
silence and with keen interest. He bent his head, now to the right, now to the left,
and smiled at us with a mixture of mockery and benevolence . Finally we found this
kind of pantomime so funny that we could no longer refrain from laughing.
"Good!" we said to ourselves in French, in a low voice, "this gentleman seems
to be good-natured enough. Our case will succeed."
"Ah," said the regent, in a voice full of affability. "What language are you
speaking? I did not understand what you said."
"We are speaking the language of our country."
"Come, repeat aloud what.you have just whispered."
"We were saying: this gentleman seems to be good-natured enough."
"Do you understand this language?" he asked, turning to those standing behind
him. They all bowed together and said they did not.
"You see, no one here understands the language of your country. Translate
your words into Tibetan."
"We were saying that there was much kindness in the face of the first Kalon."
"Ah, so you think I am kind? But I am very cruel. Is it not true that I am very
cruel?" said he, turning to his followers. They began to smile but did not reply.
"You are right," the regent continued. "I am kind, for kindness is the duty of a
Kalon . I must be kind to my people and also to strangers . " Then he made us a long
speech of which we understood very little.
When he had finished we told him that, not being sufficiently familiar with the
Tibetan language, we had not fully understood what he had said. The regent
beckoned to a Chinese, who stepped forward and translated his speech, which can
be summarized as follows: we had been summoned without the slightest intention
of molesting us. Because of the conflicting rumours which had been circulating
about us since our arrival in Lha-Ssa, the regent had decided to question us
himself in order to find out where we came from. "We are from the West," we told
the regent. "From Calcutta?" "No, our country is called France." "You are
perhaps from Peling?" "No, we are French." "Can you write?" "Better than we
can speak."
The regent turned away and spoke briefly to a Lama, who disappeared and
returned a moment later with paper, ink and a bamboo stylus.
"Here is somepaper," the regent said to us. "Write something."
"In which language? In Tibetan?"
"No, write some characters of your country's language."
One of us took the paper on his knees and wrote the following sentence: What
does it profit a man to gain the whole world if he loses his soul?
"Ah, so these are the characters of your country! I have never seen anything
like them. And what is the meaning ofthat?" We wrote the translation in Tibetan,
Tartar and Chinese and had it handed to him. "I was not deceived," he said. "You
are men of great learning. You can write in all tongues and the thoughts you
express are as profound as those to be found in the books of prayer." Then,
shaking his head slowly, he repeated: "What does itprofit a man to gain the whole
world if he loses his soul?" m
Filgrims and
A visit to the
regent of Tibet
by Régis-Evariste Hue
In 1846, the Lazarist missionary Régis-
Evariste Hue (1814-1860) became the first
Frenchman to enter Tibet. Determined,
adaptable and with a passion for
discovery, Hue successfully overcame the
many obstacles he encountered during his
travels in Mongolia, Tibet and China.
The story of his experiences, in which
Hue shows himself to be a remarkable
explorer and ethnologist, is today a
classic. Commissioned to take Christianity
to "Tartary" (Mongolia), Hue realized
that if he was to convert the people to
Christianity he wouldfirst have to study
Buddhism. He reached the capital of
Tibet, the holy city ofLhasa, after eight
months ofperilous wandering
accompanied by a young converted lama
named Samdadchiemba, a camel, a white
horse, and a dog named Arsalan.
I
1
C/>
Father Régis-Evariste Hue in Chinese dress.
Souvenirs d'un voyage dans la Tartarie et le Thibet,
pendant les années 1844. 1845 et 1846, par M. Hue,
ancien missionaire apostolique, edited by Gaumc Frères
et J. Duprcy, Paris, 1868.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The spiritual journey
Whether a visit from this world to the great beyond or the progress of a soul
in search of the divine, the spiritual journey has been described in many
books of wisdom from both East and West, from the ancient Egyptian Book
of the Dead to Dante's Divine Comedy, and the Kitab al-ishärät wa at-
tanbïhât ("Book of Directives and Remarks") by Avicenna (Ibn Sïnâ) which
describe the mystic's spiritual journey to a direct and uninterrupted vision of
God. In modern literature, the theme of the "inner journey" has reap¬
peared, notably in mystical writings and in poetry.
The mystic
way
by Farïd oddïn 'Attär
Farid oddïn 'Attär (d. c. 1220) is one of
the most celebrated Persian Sufi poets and
mystics. In the West his best-known work
is the Manteq ot-teyr (The Conference of
the Birds), an allegorical poem describing
the quest of30 birds (sï morgh) for the
Simorgh, or Divine Bird. This poem has
been a constant source of inspiration for
mystic poets. But 'Attar's masterpiece is
doubtless the Mosibat-nämeh ("Book of
Affliction"), which describes the quest of
the soul, embodied by the Pilgrim, for
unity. The passage published here is
taken from the beginning of the poem, at
the moment when the path to God is
revealed to the Pilgrim. Each stage of the
innerjourney on which he embarks is
punctuated with anecdotes rich in
spiritual meaning.
DISTRAUGHT and dumbfounded, the pilgrim saw a hundred universes,
oceans upon oceans of seething waters, each in search of God, all of them
engulfed in the vortex of God. A hundred thousand times he sifted all the
earth, and cast aside intelligence, doubt and aporia. A hundred thousand times he
sifted the earth of the world and as many times he laid upon the bench the pearl he
had won. At last, success came to him from God. As he was sifting, a wise man
came to him, a sun illuminating both worlds, gathering in myriads of stars on the
Way, in the world and out of it, in the centre and out of it; settled, and forever
travelling; invisible, and forever present; sun flooding the two worlds with light,
and frightened by his own brilliance; red flame on the Way, vast heart like the
green ocean. Let him perish who makes no khôl with the dust of his steps, be he
pure or impure! Ah, son, the road is long and full of pitfalls, the traveller must
have a guide. How can the blind man find his way without a stick? There is no
Wise One, thou sayest? Ask, seek desperately! If there was not in the world a
single Wise One, the earth would rise up and time would stop.
In short, when the Pilgrim met the Wise One, the guide on the Way, he bowed
low before him. His heart overflowed with joy. With all his heart, he fixed the ring
of servitude to his ear. A hundred thousand rosebuds blossomed in the garden of
his heart. Grace brought him ecstasy, impiety fled, the way opened.
The Wise One said to him:
"Brigands lurk on the Way. Sleep not, do what you have been told. The road is
long. Son, watch out! Let sleep await the tomb, keep watch! To each a task has
been assigned. Many have suffered such distress. On this long road beware of
being hindered by trifles. Wherever you halt you will remain prostrate for ever.
May heartbreaks and burnings in your'breast be calls. May this echo of the Qur'an
sing in your soul like the nightingale's song! Walk upright, do your best, be
vigilant. Carry the burden, eat the thorn, keep your ears wide open!"
The Pilgrim became inflamed like a lover seized with passion. He threw off
melancholy and rapture and plunged naked into the ocean. He laid complaint and
gratitude aside, and set out along the endless Way.
26
"-
A meditating Sufi
portrayed in a 15th-
century Persian miniature
(Shiraz school). Sùfism
consists ofa variety of
ascetic rules and mystical
paths followed by Muslim
orders and brotherhoods.
One of the saints of
Sùfism is ¿alai ad-Din ar-
Rùmi (1207-1274),
founderof the
Mawlawlyah orderof
Sufis better known in the
West as the "whirling
dervishes" because of the
dance their founder
prescribed for them.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Men of letters
In the 19th and early 20th century scholarly writers, diplomats and states¬
men from all over the world visited Europe for the first time. Under their
penetrating scrutiny, European life and institutions sometimes appear in an
unexpected light. Of particular interest as a source of information about
both observers and observed are the reflections of travellers from coun¬
tries such as China and, especially, Japan, which were then largely inac¬
cessible to the West.
WJMMff'MPWÏ, W^ww
'"K.
THERE were about forty of us altogether, all in Japanese dress, and we
must have been a curious sight walking around London and Paris with two
swords hanging at our side. Before we left Japan we were told that we
would have the greatest difficulty in getting supplies abroad. So we were provided
with several hundred boxes of white rice for the journey, and to light the corridors
in inns at night we were given dozens of specially made "metal lanterns"
lanterns with two square legs, surrounded by mesh plus a whole assortment of
portable lanterns, candelabra, standing lanterns and candles. In short, what was
loaded onto the ship was doubtless intended to correspond to what a daimyô and
his retinue would need in the coaching inns of the Tôkaidô.
On our arrival in Paris, and after the customary salutations, the first request
made to the official who received us was that the accommodation of the atten¬
dants should not be too far away from the residence of the heads of mission , which
meant that the latter did not feel very secure and intended to keep their escort
close at hand. Our host immediately agreed and asked how many of us there were.
When he learned that there were some thirty of us he replied that if there were not
more of us than that, ten or twenty groups like ours could be put up in a single
hotel. This reply left us flabbergasted. Whereupon we were conducted to the
hotel where we were to stay. This was the Hôtel du Louvre, at the very gates of the
Palace, an imposing five-storey building containing no less than six hundred
rooms and with a staff of over five hundred. It could easily accommodate a
thousand guests, so that the Japanese mission passed unnoticed there and our sole
concern was not to get lost in the corridors. Warm air circulated in the rooms,
where neither stove nor radiator was to be seen. Rooms and corridors were
lighted by countless gaslamps and one hardly noticed the coming of night. Every
Diplomats
under surveillance
by Fukuzawa Yukichi
The Japanese official mission which visited
Europein 1862. Fukuzawa Yukichi, the
interpreter, is standing second from right.
In 1862, a Japanese official mission
visited several European capitals:
London, The Hague, Berlin, St.
Petersburg and Paris (twice). The young
interpreter who accompanied them was
Fukuzawa Yukichi (1835-1901), who in
his Autobiography described the trip,
which took place at the time of the Meiji
Restoration when the Japanese
government wished to bring the country
out of its isolation. In 1866, Fukuzawa
published Seiyö jijo ("Conditions in the
West"), a major work which made him
the most important writer of the new
Japan. He later wrote many popular
educational works in which he explained
Western culture to the Japanese public,
and was a dedicated educator whose
school, "Keiö Gijuku", was granted
university status in 1903.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Men of letters
4
«
kind of food from the seas and mountains was available in the dining room to
satisfy our appetites, and the worst detractors of the barbarous West forgot their
prejudices while enjoying these exquisite dishes. So we were hampered by all this
baggage that we had been dragging around with us since we had left Japan.
Obviously there was no question of lighting our lanterns in the hotel corridors or
of cooking our rice in the kitchens. We ended up therefore by presenting all our
material, starting with the rice, to one of the minor officials in the reception
committee, a man named Lambert, and we considered ourselves fortunate that he
deigned to accept it.
Our ignorance of local customs caused us not a few difficulties over which we
had many a good laugh. A waiter whom we sent out for tobacco understood
"sugar" for "cigar", and brought us sugar. Our doctor thought he had bought
ginseng, which turned out to be powdered ginger.
At that time Japan was a closed world, and there was something laughable
about the precautions taken to prevent our meeting foreigners, even though we
were in a foreign country. The three emissaries were Takenushi, Matsudaira and
Kyogoku. The last-named was responsible for our surveillance and he had several
specially trained agents for this purpose. Since these kept a constant eye on their
companions, it was very difficult to meet foreigners. We were all Bakufu officials
but there were three of us who thought alike and pursued the same objective
Mitsukui Shûbei, Matsuki Kôan and myself. We had been students together and
already at that time were inseparable, trying to see everything that was to be seen.
Our good agents did not seem to appreciate this overmuch, especially since all
three of us were of inferior rank and , what was worse, read Western books a fact
which prompted them to be on their guard. The orders were, therefore, that
whenever we wanted to go out we had to take one of the agents with us, who
followed us everywhere. Nevertheless, we had no treasonable intentions and
there was no reason to fear that we would betray any State secrets! To be always
followed by an agent of strange appearance was, therefore, simply annoying. This
was bad enough, but when our henchman had something else to do we could not
go out either! This was a great nuisance. On such occasions I would say to my
friends, "Pooh, it's nothing! It's as though we were doing the tour of Europe
bringing our tightly closed Japan along with us!" This made us all laugh.
Vive la
différence!
by Yuan Zuzhi
A member ofan illustriousfamily of
Chinese literati, Yuan Zuzhi (1827-1898)
visitedEurope in 1883 in the entourage ofa
group ofChinesepoliticians, andsome time
laterpublisheda briefguide containing
useful informationfor travellers to Western
Europe. The extractpublishedhere is taken
from a long comparison between Chinese
andEuropean civilization which Yuan
Zuzhi wrote in the mid-1880s. Not without
humour, he seeks to reveal the goodpoints
ofChinese civilization.
*W
rESTERN customs are not without similarities to those of China,
and if at times they diverge a little, it is not surprising in view of the
tens of thousands of // which separate these two regions of the
world. But they can be in complete contrast, a few examples of which follow: in
China, the place of honour is on the left, in the West it is on the right. Men are held
in higher regard than women on Chinese soil; in the West it is the other way
round.
"On Chinese soil, doors and windows are left wide open; in the West, doors and
gateways are there to be closed. In China, people find it more comfortable to
change out of their formal clothes before sitting down to table, while in the West it
is impossible to attend a banquet without dressing for the occasion. It is the same
in the home. In China, the role of women is to serve and care for others; in the
West, it is they who give the orders: the husband obeys.
"In China, a man's place is out of doors, a woman's, inside the house: what is
said indoors never goes beyond the walls of the inner apartments; what is said
outside does not enter the home. This is why a woman who stays at home and
never goes out is highly regarded for her fine virtue. In the West, the women think
of nothing but going out; the streets are full of their skirts and their jewellery.
They mingle with passers-by and travellers. The husband has no right to stop his
wife from going out; if he does so, he risks being prosecuted and thrown into
prison. In China, people of the opposite sex must not touch one another while
handing something over; in the West, when a man and woman shake hands it is
only an expression of respect.
"In China, we consider it obscene to kiss with the lips; in the West, a close
embrace and a kiss on the mouth is a gesture of politeness and of respect. ...
"In China, drinking cold water is advised against in order to avoid stomach¬
ache, while in the West it is a way of dealing with the heat. In China, wine is
warmed before drinking; in the West, it is only drunk chilled. In China the main
dishes are served first and the soup comes afterwards; in the West the soup is the
first course. ... In China, the eating of beef is avoided because that animal is
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
essential for work. In the West, the horse is used for work and the ox is only for
eating.
"In China, women dress to protect their bodies; they would feel the greatest
shame if they exposed any part of themselves. In the West they uncover their
shoulders and their breast, but do not allow their underwear to be seen. ...
"In China people do not talk while they are eating; gossips are made fun of. In
the West, people think you are ill if you do not talk during a meal. ...
"In China, young people do not let their beards or side whiskers grow; it is only
when they reach maturity that they give up shaving. In the West, it is the other way
round.
"The Chinese could never have hair on their faces; Westerners' faces are
covered with hair.
"In China, it would be impolite to appear bare-headed; on the contrary,
people's headwear is chosen to fit the occasion; in the West, it is considered
correct to take off one's hat. ...
"The Chinese bend their fingers to count on them, while Westerners straighten
them out. ...
"The Chinese peel vegetables or fruit with the knife-blade facing away from
them; in the West, it is turned inwards. ...
"In China, when the head of the household has people to dinner, the mistress
retires and does not meet the guests. In the West, she must not only keep them
company, but shake the hand of the guest of honour and take his arm on sitting
down and on leaving the table.
"In China, when people meet, they normally ask one another's name before
talking about the weather. In the West, people plunge into conversation without
troubling about such niceties , and only exchange visiting cards if the talk naturally
leads them to do so.
At the heightof fashion: a French ladyof 1910
and a Chinese lady of 1930.
CD
3
CD
CD
3
"In China, the upper floors of a house are the most respectable, contrary to
practice in the West, where the servants usually live on the fourth or fifth floors.
"In China, women's hair is admired for its sheen,for the subtle way in which it is
groomed, and for its blackness. In the West, people like curly or wavy hair worn
loose, and a deep yellow shade. Chinese ladies pride themselves on letting their
nails grow long and pointed; Western ladies take pains to trim theirs and think
their nails beautiful when they are rounded like the end of a mallet.
"In China, white is the colour of mourning and red that of marriage and joy. In
the West, white stands for joy, while black is the colour of mourning. In China,
the hands and face are washed after a meal; in the West, before.
"In China, black is worn to do dirty jobs, in the West, it is the colour of formal
dress.
"Chinese women would feel humiliated and insulted to be watched and
appraised. In the West, women are flattered to be observed and inspected by all
and sundry and take this as a compliment.
"The Chinese court prides itself on endeavouring to reduce taxes and lighten
duties, while in the West people unhesitatingly accept arbitrary taxation and
exorbitant impositions. In China, rich families fill their stores and attics, while in
the West the wealthy invest their money outside.
"In China, women but not men are repelled by the idea of showing their naked
bodies; in the West, the opposite is the case.
"The listing of these contrasts could go on indefinitely ..."
Nouvelles lettres édifiantes et curieuses d' Extrême-Occi¬
dent par des voyageurs lettrés chinois à la Belle Epoque.
Editions Seghers, Paris, 1986.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Men of letters
The Mabille, a fashionable Parisian dance-
hall of the mid- 1 9th century, as shown in an
engraving of 1867.
Dance-floor
democracy
by Domingo F. Sarmiento
Outspoken writer, tireless educator and
statesman, Domingo Faustino Sarmiento
(1811-1888) became President of the
Argentine Republic in 1868. He is the
author of a masterpiece of Spanish-
American literature, Facundo (1845), an
impassioned denunciation of dictatorship
in which he analysed what he saw as a
conflict in his country between
"civilization and barbarism". In 1846 he
was sent on an official mission to study
educational methods in Europe, returning
with materialfor a voluminous report On
the Education of the People, and a lively
account ofhis travels (Viajes), which was
published in 1849. Sarmiento's reflections
on equality inspired by his visits to
Parisian dance-halls assume fuller
significance in the light of his decision to
live in exile in Chile rather than under the
dictatorship ofJuan Manuel Rosas in
Argentina.
Viajes ("Travels") (1849), Vol.
Buenos Aires, 1955.
1, Hachette S.A.
THESE profound reflections made me think of the public dances of Paris,
which I attend from time to time as a distraction from the torments of
homesickness. I have neither the time , the inclination nor the means to lose
myself in these delightful frivolities, the enjoyment of which I envy in others. Ah,
if I only had forty thousand pesos, what a year I would give myself in Paris! With
what memories I would brighten up my old age! But I am sensible, and content
myself with observing, rather than scrounging from others as some people do.
The Paris dance-halls are public buildings rather like the theatres which they
attempt to outdo in sumptuousness, brilliance and style. The Rannelag
[Ranelagh] is comparable to the Italian operas as regards the quality of its
patrons. There I have come across Balzac, George Sand, Soulié and other leading
literary figures. The Château-Rouge is illuminated, at the end of each month, by
eighty thousand lamps; the Bal Maville [Bal Mabille] attracts the most famous
dancers; the Chaumière, paradise of Latin Quarter students, is a fortress at the
entrance to which even the policeman must leave his sword. Every other day these
public dance-halls open their doors to their thousands of customers. The men pay
an entrance fee on some days three francs, on others two, one franc fifty
centimes on a Monday and five francs at the end of the month, for the Grand
Festival. The ladies, who are always allowed in for nothing, come from all social
strata, behaving with more or less familiarity depending on the day of the week
and on their relationship with the men who pay either one franc fifty centimes or
five francs, according to their means. Very well-bred ladies go there to watch, and
young women of all classes are regular and passionate fans of one dance-hall or
another. The premises are decorated with exquisite taste: vases and statues tower
over masses of foliage and platforms of rare, sweet-smelling flowers, and by the
fiery light of the gaslamps, in asphalted avenues beneath swaying, multi-coloured
Chinese lanterns, quadrilles of two hundred couples execute frenetic polkas and
feverish waltzes. Here reputations are made, as important and European as that
of a Dumas or a Rachel . When La Rigolette stands up with her companion (who is
not Jerman), the whole company points her out, and the crowd of spectators
throng around her. English lords, Russian boyars and princes would pay up to a
hundred francs to be in the front line. The German orchestra begins to have an
effect on this whirlpool of bodies , who quiver with excitement and stamp their feet
to the dominant strains of the cornet. The dancing speeds up and becomes
animated and passionate, revealing the nature, the character of each dancer: the
dreamy, voluptuous languor of some, the extravagant, unreasonable violence of
others. La Rigolette becomes agitated, and, completely carried away, loses all
semblance of human shape or form. Her admirers close in around her, inciting her
with their applause, dizzying her with their cheers, until inspiration seizes the
prophetess in an explosion of passion, a poetic outburst of flashes of genius,
impossible cabrioles, bacchanalian contortions. ...
The dramatic intensity of these public dances has its positive side: they are
social levellers where the classes mix freely with one another. Ordinary women
rub shoulders with high-born young ladies, their manners become more refined
and people acquire a kind of unity and homogeneity. Among this company,
partaking of pleasures where they can drown their misery, the most humble of the
common people can have their little bit of happiness too.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
MY excellent friend, M. Félix Regamey, has recently published in this
same journal a very interesting article entitled: Le Japon vu par un
artiste.
I have known and esteemed M. Félix Regamey for a long time, first as a friend,
later as an artist and a keen Orientalist. ...
Well, I was greatly surprised by his article in the Revue bleue. I realized that M.
Regamey has not seen China. True, he has been there, but I am obliged to say to
him what he said to Pierre Loti: "Port-of-call observations are risky."
As soon as he sat down on his folding-stool in a Canton street to make some
sketches of this interesting and, indeed, unique city, the great artist was imme¬
diately discouraged both by the curiosity of the crowd around him and by the
remarks they made about his actions and gestures. So he quickly returned to his
ship and made for Japan, where he stayed longer and was better received, so that,
on his return to France, he placed Japan above China. This, it must be allowed, is
quite natural. I would not even take the liberty of reproaching him for it, since he
had seen very little of China and a lot of Japan.
But I must say that, had I acted like M. Regamey, if a few unpleasant incidents
had sufficed to deprive me of the wish to continue, I should never have got to
know Europe. I remember that when I first went to Berlin, in 1877, 1 was strolling
one day in the Kaiser-Gallerie something like the Passage de l'Opéra. I was soon
surrounded by such a crowd that the gallery was literally blocked. To escape from
this stifling curiosity I was obliged to go into a shop and beg the owner to send for
the police in order to clear the way for me.
The crowd was very noisy. They were making all kinds of remarks in German ,
which I did not yet know. I was less perceptive than my friend Regamey, who
realized at once that the Chinese being spoken around him in similar encounters
was full of "contemptuous or grotesque abuse".
And this was not an isolated case. When China opened a legation in Berlin, my
compatriots were followed around, surrounded and jostled so much by curious
passers-by, especially by children, that the rector of the university had to have a
special article added to the school regulations saying: "It is forbidden to follow
and annoy the Chinese."
One day in Paris, when I was admiring a painting of the Flemish school in the
Louvre, two ladies who, it seemed to me, had just come up from the provinces,
wagered loudly behind me that I was a woman . I think it was the prettier of the two
who lost the bet. ...
Such incidents would have discouraged M. Regamey, but they amused me. For
I know that, side by side with this idle curiosity, which is typical of ignorant people
of all races and countries, one finds everywhere the politeness and hospitality of
those who know what consideration is due to a foreigner. It is this good side of the
public which should be seen and appreciated.
True artists are as rare in my country as elsewhere. Those who are less good
have the modesty not to show themselves. But in a general way art forms part of
our education. Together with handwriting, we learn as children to draw and paint
watercolours. The teacher thinks his pupils know nothing until they are able to
draw a cloud chased by the winds which is more difficult to capture than a man
falling off a roof. True, the models are not so scarce, there are wind and clouds
everywhere, whereas men falling off roofs, of which M. Regamey speaks, are
not, I think, encountered very often, except at the Ambigu in M. Zola's play
L'Assommoir. ...
I agree that Chinese children just like Japanese ones, whatever M. Regamey
may say are often frightened and cry if they see a foreigner. But what's strange
about that? I appeal to any father. If M. Regamey had children, he would have
seen them run off as children do, at the sight of a new face, and cry if they were
obliged to stay. Such have been the fashions, laws and habits of children in all ages
and in all countries. It is not the "foreigner" who frightens them, but the
"unfamiliar". Thus, in China as elsewhere, babies are devoid of any anti-interna¬
tional instinct. I beg the reader's pardon for having invented this horrible word.
A Chinese
general in Paris
by Chen Jitong
General Chen Jitong, a scholar from a
traditional background and a noted
calligrapher, was for several years
Chinese military attaché in Paris. While
there, he struck up a friendship with a
number of Western writers and artists,
notably with the French painter Félix
Regamey, who had brought back to
France many sketches and portraits of life
in Japan and other countries he had
visited. In 1890 Regamey published an
article in a French magazine about his
visits to Japan and China. The article
brought a vigorous and ironic rebuke
from the General, an extract from which
appears here. Chen Jitong had already
published, in French, a book in praise of
China entitled Les Chinois peints par
eux-mêmes ("The Chinese as they see
themselves"), Paris 1884.
CD
3
CD
5!
La Chine vue par un artisteRéponse à M. Félix
Regamey, Revue bleue, Paris, 29 November 1890.
Watercolour by the French painter Félix
Regamey (1844-1 907), sketched from
life in 1874 and used as an illustration
forPromenades japonaises, a book by
Emile Guimet, founder of the Museum
ofAsian Art in Paris which bears his
name.
(3
®
f
T
ft
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Men of letters
Rabindranath Tagore
An Indian poet
visits an English
parson
by Rabindranath Tagore
The most celebratedfigure in modern
Indian literature, the great Bengali writer
Rabindranath Tagore (Nobel Prize for
Literature 1913), was a prodigious
traveller as well as a prolific writer. In the
second half ofhis life, he visited England
and the United States several times, and
toured Europe and Asia, making contact
with writers and scholars, giving lectures
on Indian civilization, working to bring
together East and West and expounding
his beliefs on the universalism of cultures.
In 1912 Tagore was in England. During
his visit, the Irish poet and playwright
William Butler Yeats read to him and a
group of Western writers Tagore's
translation into English of his most
famous collection, Gítañjali (1910, "Song
Offering"). Tagore spent part of the
summer of 1912 at the home of a
Staffordshire parson.
Rural England, from A Tagore Reader, edited by Amiya
Chakravarty. Macmillan, London and New York, 1961.
Unesco Collection of Representative Works.
IT is August, high summer in England; townsmen are longing to visit the
countryside. People rush to parks and open fields; whenever they can get a
few more hours they go out of town. Joining the flock of flying townsmen, we
also got away.
When we reached the house, our hostess took us to the warm drawing room
where a fire had been lit. The house was not an old parsonage but a new one; the
garden was also new, perhaps they had themselves cultivated it. Clusters of many
coloured flowers fringed the deep lawn. I had never seen such profusion, such
freshness of foliage. It is unbelievable, unless one has seen it, how richly green and
thick the grass can be.
The rooms of the house were neat and tidy, the library full of books on many
subjects; there was not the least trace of negligence. Furniture, decoration and
comfort are of a much higher standard than in our country; every object is kept
spotlessly clean with vigilant care. Slackness would not be tolerated by these
people.
In the late afternoon my host Mr. Outram took us on a walk; the rain had
stopped, but there was no gap in the clouds. On all sides was the deep green of
undulating meadows divided by low hedges. Though hilly, the landscape had
nowhere the roughness of hills; earth's exuberance was held in a beautiful har¬
mony.
While walking, Mr. Outram met an acquaintance and discussed some business.
I learned that a rural committee had been appointed for encouraging farmers to
do some gardening of their own ; some days ago a competition had taken place and
this stranger had received the first prize for flowers. Mr. Outram took me to the
houses of a few farm-holders. Everyone had a flower garden around their cottage
and a kitchen garden, and there was an atmosphere of homely toil leading to
happiness and simplicity. After the day's labour in the fields they returned to their
homes and did gardening in the evening. I had occasion to see many other proofs
of the human fellowship developed through services and welfare work that existed
between Mr. Outram and the village people who were under his care.
Institutional religion may occasionally hamper the progress of people but in
spite of it the spirit of religion works in this country and there is no doubt that the
clergy have kept the inner standards fairly high in the life of the village people. In
our country this was the work of the Brahmins but being based on varna the
system led to inevitable neglect of individual responsibility. I do not believe that
all clergymen have accepted the ideal of Christ in their lives, but they are not
clergymen by birth, and have to be responsible to society. It would be difficult for
them to allow their character or behaviour to be debased, and they have on the
whole held up the pursuit of pure character as an ideal of religion.
The religious orders have arranged for a generalized provision of religion for
the communities. But this is not enough the great problems of humanity that
present themselves to the country from time to time demand spiritual power and
inspiration which institutionalism cannot provide. Such problems should be faced
by clergymen with the inner music of Christ's own words in their hearts, by
establishing Him in their lives. But how rarely this happens.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The armchair traveller
Many would-be travellers decide to stay at home and let their imagination
do the rest. The literature of imaginary travel has a long history and persists
today in some forms of science fiction. Among its practitioners have been
some of the world's greatest writers, on a canvas ranging from satire,
fantasy and humour to utopianism. The following passage is but one
illustration of the powers of the imagination to transcend the boundaries of
time and place.
ITwas now seven o'clock by his watch: he had just time enough to dine before
catching his train, which was due to leave at eight-fifty. He worked out how
long the crossing from Dieppe to Newhaven would take, added up the hours
on his fingers, and finally told himself: "If the times given in the guide are correct,
I shall arrive in London dead on twelve-thirty tomorrow afternoon." ...
While the table was being laid, Des Esseintes inspected his neighbours. ... he
saw a crowd of islanders with china-blue eyes, crimson complexions, and earnest
or arrogant expressions, skimming through foreign newspapers; but here there
were a few women dining in pairs without male escorts, robust Englishwomen
with boyish faces, teeth as big as palette-knives, cheeks as red as apples, long
hands and long feet. They were enthusiastically attacking helpings of rump-steak
pie meat served hot in mushroom sauce and covered with a crust like a fruit tart.
The voracity of these hearty trencherwomen brought back with a rush the
appetite he had lost so long ago. First, he ordered and enjoyed some thick, greasy
oxtail soup; next, he examined the list offish and asked for a smoked haddock,
which also came up to his expectations; and then, goaded on by the sight of other
people guzzling, he ate a huge helping of roast beef and potatoes and downed a
couple of pints of ale, savouring the musty cowshed flavour of this fine pale beer.
In the course of his sedentary life, only two countries had exerted any attraction
upon him Holland and England. He had surrendered to the first of these two
temptations; unable to resist any longer, he had left Paris one fine day and visited
the cities of the Low Countries, one by one. On the whole, this tour had proved a
bitter disappointment to him. He had pictured to himself a Holland such as
Teniers and Jan Steen, Rembrandt and Ostade had painted. ...
Still thinking of this past disappointment, he once more consulted his watch:
there were only ten minutes now before his train left.
"It's high time to ask for my bill and go," he told himself. ...
"Get up, man, and go," he kept telling himself, but these orders were no sooner
given than countermanded. After all, what was the good of moving, when a fellow
could travel so magnificently sitting in a chair? Wasn't he already in London,
whose smells, weather, citizens, food, and even cutlery, were all about him? What
could he expect to find over there, save fresh disappointments such as he had
suffered in Holland?
Now he had only just time enough to run across to the station, but an immense
aversion for the journey, an urgent longing to remain where he was, came over
him with growing force and intensity. Lost in thought, he sat there letting the
minutes slip by, thus cutting off his retreat.
"If I went now," he said to himself, "I should have to dash up to the barriers and
hustle the porters along with my luggage. How tiresome it would be!"
And once again he told himself:
"When you come to think of it, I've seen and felt all that I wanted to see and
feel. I've been steeped in English life ever since I left home, and it would be
madness to risk spoiling such unforgettable experiences by a clumsy change of
locality. As it is, I must have been suffering from some mental aberration to have
thought of repudiating my old convictions, to have rejected the visions of my
obedient imagination, and to have believed like any ninny that it was necessary,
interesting, and useful to travel abroad."
He looked at his watch. ,
"Time to go home," he said. And this time he managed to get to his feet, left the
tavern, and told the cabby to drive him back to the Gare de Sceaux. Thence he
returned to Fontenay with his trunks, his packages, his portmanteaux, his rugs,
his umbrellas, and his sticks, feeling all the physical weariness and moral fatigue of
a man who has come home after a long and perilous journey.
Paris- on-Thames
by Joris-Karl Huysmans
Duke Jean Floressas des Esseintes, the
hero of A rebours (1884) by the French
novelist Joris-Karl Huysmans (1848-
1907), is a prey to boredom, despite his
nobility and wealth. As a form of
escapism, he immerses himself in "the
tumultuous spaces of nightmares and
dreams". In des Esseintes, the
personification of refined decadence,
Huysmans created a character who
epitomized the. spirit o/fin de siècle
European art and literature. At once
grotesque and pathetic, a figure in some
ways reminiscent ofDon Quixote, this
armchair traveller who imagines himself
in Dickensian England while dining at an
English tavern in Paris is one of
literature's most memorable portraits ofa
mind in torment.
Le train engourdi, a collage by Max Ernst
(1891 -1976). The work belongs to a series
entitled La Femme 1 00 têtes (1929) which is
one of the masterpieces ofSurrealist art.
A Rebours, English translation© Robert Baldick, 1959,
under the title Against Nature.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Footloose and fancy free
"But the only true travellers are those who leave/ for leaving's sake....".
These lines by Baudelaire are still as valid as ever. However serious the
ostensible reasons for his journey may be voyage of discovery, pil¬
grimage, exploration, trade, archaeological investigation for the passio¬
nate traveller these are merely pretexts. He travels because he is drawn by
the call of the open road, the lure of what lies around the next corner.
"v wjntwwnwvj
The obedience
due to
princesses
by Ibn Batutah
"No intelligent man," wrote Ibn Djuzayy,
the scribe to whom Ibn Batutah dictated
his memoirs, "can fail to see that this
sheikh is the traveller of the age." But
Ibn Batutah (1304-1368 or 1377) was not
only the greatest Arab traveller of the
Middle Ages, he was one of the greatest
travellers ofall time. When he set out
from his birthplace, Tangiers (Morocco),
for Mecca in 1325, he was embarking on
an adventurousjourney that would take
him halfway round the world as far as
China and would last almost 30 years.
The first stage of his travels took him to
the Middle East. During a second, longer
stage he visited central and eastern Asia.
Finally, after returning to Tangiers, he
set off again, this time for the Sahara and
the Sudan: his is the only description of
these regions to have survivedfrom the
Middle Ages. Ibn Batutah was not a
geographer like the great al-Idrisi (1100-
c.1165), author of the famous Kitâb
Rudjâr ("The Book ofRoger"). His
observations are those of a curious,
intelligent and cultivated Muslim tourist.
His account of his travels (the Rihla ), in
addition to its literary value, gives a
panoramic picture of the 14th-century
world. The extract published here is
thought to show Ibn Batutah in the
Philippines, before his visit to China.
ON the second day after our arrival at the port of Cailoûcary, the princess
invited the nâkhodhah, or skipper of the ship, the carâny^ or secretary,
the merchants, the chiefs, the tendu, or general of the infantry, and the
sipâhsâlâr, or general of the bowmen, to partake of the meal that Ordoudjâ was
accustomed to provide as a hospitable gesture. The skipper asked me to'go with
them; but I refused, for these people are- infidels, and it is not lawful to eat their
food. When the guests came to the princess's abode, she said, "Has any of your
number not come?"
The skipper replied, "Only one man is not here the bakchy, or judge, who
does not eat your food."
Ordoudjâ answered, "Send for him."
Her guards sought me out; with them were the companions of the nâkhodhah,
who said to me, "Obey the princess."
I went and found her seated on her great chair, or ceremonial throne; before
her stood women, holding in their hand's registers which they presented to her.
Around her were old women, or duennas, her counsellors; they were seated
below the throne, in sandalwood armchairs. The men, too, were in front of the
princess. The throne was covered with silk, and had silk curtains above it, and it
was made of sandalwood encrusted with gold leaf. ...
When I had greeted the princess, she said to me in Turkish, Khochmicen
iakhchîmîcen, which means "Are you well? How are you?" She made me sit
down near her. The princess could write Arabic correctly, and she said to one of
her servants, Daouâh oué betecguétoûr that is, "Bring the inkwell and paper."
He did so, and the princess wrote, "In the name of God, the merciful and
compassionate"; then she said to me, "What is that?"
I answered, Tangry nam that is, "It is the name of God."
She replied, Khoch, which means, "That is right." Then she asked me what
country I came from, and I told her that I came from India. "The land that pepper
comes from?" (Malabar), she said, and I replied that that was so. She asked me a
lot of questions about the country and its history, and I answered them all. The
This masterpiece of 1 6th century Arab
cartography is from the Portulan of the
Mediterranean Sea, a bookofsailing charts
by Ali Ibn Ahmad ibn Muhammad a/ Sharqiof
Sfax (Tunisia). Following the usual practice of
medieval Arab cartographers, the south is at
top ofmap. The Mediterranean is at centre.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Footloose and
princess then said, "I really must make war on this country and take it for myself;
for I am attracted by its abundance of riches and of troops."
"Do so," I said. The princess caused me to be given: (1) clothing; (2) as much
rice as two elephants could carry; (3) two female buffaloes; (4) ten ewes; (5) four
pounds of julep or syrup; (6) four marthabân, or large porcelain jars, full of
ginger, pepper, lemons and mangoes; all was salted, as food is when it is to be
eaten at sea. .
The skipper told me that in Ordoudjâ's army there were free women, slave girls
and female captives, who fought like men; that she went to war along with the
troops, both male and female, invaded her enemies' lands, was present at the
battles, and fought the most valiant of her foes. He also told me about a desperate
battle that once took place between the princess and one of her foes; many of
Ordoudjâ's soldiers were killed, and her whole army was about to flee; then the
princess rushed forward, and made her way through the ranks until she reached
the king whom she was fighting; she stabbed him to death, and his troops fled;
Ordoudjâ returned, bearing her enemy's head on a spear; her enemy's kin
redeemed the head by handing over great sums of money to Ordoudjâ; and when
the princess returned to her father he gave her this town Cailoûcary which had
been governed by her brother before her. The skipper also told me that the sons of
kings ask Ordoudjâ's hand in marriage, and that she answers, "I shall marry none
but a man that fights me and defeats me;" but they will not fight her, for they fear
that their reputation would suffer if she were victorious.
I was born at Mauzé in the département of Les Deux Sèvres. My parents were
poor and I had the misfortune to lose them when I was still a child. The only
education I received was that given in the free village school. As soon as I
could read and write I was put to learn a trade, but I soon got tired of this because
of the travellers' tales which I devoured during all my spare moments. My young
brain was especially excited by reading the story of Robinson Crusoe. I longed to
have adventures like his and I already felt an ambition growing within me to
achieve fame by making some important discovery.
I was lent geography books and maps. My interest was excited above all by the
map of Africa where I saw only desert countries or those marked unknown.
Finally this taste became a passion to which I sacrificed everything else. I ceased to
take part in the games and amusements of my comrades and locked myself up on
Sundays to read travellers' tales and all the travel books I could procure. I told my
uncle, who was my guardian, of my wish to travel. He disapproved, painting a
vivid picture of the dangers I would encounter at sea and the homesickness I
would feel far away from my country and family. In short, he made every effort to
dissuade me from my project. But I was not to be put off. I continued to insist on
going and he abandoned his opposition.
I had only sixty francs and with this small sum I proceeded to Rochefort in 1816.
I embarked on the Loire, a store-ship that was about to sail for Senegal. ...
The town of Timbuktu is inhabited by blacks of the Kissur nation who form its
main population. There are also many Moors, who engage in trade. They remind
me of those Europeans who go to the colonies in the hope of making a fortune.
These Moors later return to their own country to live in peace. They have much
influence over the natives. Nevertheless the king or governor is a black man. His
name is Osman. He is greatly respected by his subjects and is very simple in his
habits. Nothing distinguishes him from the others. ...
This prince received us in the middle of his courtyard. He was seated on a
beautiful mat with a rich cushion. We remained seated for a moment at a short
distance from his person. My host told him that I had come to pay my respects. He
told him of my adventures. I could not follow their conversation for they spoke in
the Kissur language. Then the king addressed me in Arabic and asked me some
questions about the Christians and how they had treated me. We withdrew after a
brief visit. I should like to have seen the interior of the house, but was not to have
this satisfaction. This prince seemed to be an affable person. He might have been
fifty-five years old. His hair was white and curly, he was of average height with a
handsome face, very black-skinned, with an aquiline nose, thin lips, a grey beard
and large eyes. His clothes, like those of the Moors, were made of European
material. He wore a red bonnet with a large piece of muslin around it in the form
of a turban, and shoes of morocco leather which resembled our bedroom slippers
and were made locally. He made frequent visits to the mosque.
As I have said, there are many Moors established in Timbuktu. Theirs are the
finest houses in the town. They grow rich very quickly from trading. They are sent
consignments of goods from Adrar and Tafilet, and also from Taouat, Ardamas,
Into the heart
of Africa
by René Caillié
I
Although the French writer René Caillié
(1799-1838) was long viewed as a kind of
colonialist before his time, a very different
figure emerges from the journal, rich in
all kinds of observation, of his journey
(1824-1828) to the renowned Malian city
of Timbuktu. Humble and determined,
Caillié died as a result of the sickness and
privations he endured on his journey,
sacrificing himself to his dream of
reaching the mysterious city on the banks
of the Niger. A remarkable human
document, Caillié's journal is also a
unique portrait of still-sovereign Arab and
African societies and of cross-cultural
exchanges across the Sahara from the
Maghreb to Black Africa before the
arrival of European colonialism.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
fancy free
£ I
CO
O
o
I
Plate from the first edition of René Caillié 's
boo/cVoyage àTemboctou et à Jenné (1830).
The caption reads, "Mr. Caillié meditating on
the Qur'an and taking notes".
Journal d'un voyage à Temboctou et à Jenné, dans l'Afri¬
que Centrale ... pendant les années 1824, 1825, 1826,
1827, 1828. Editions La Découverte, Paris, 1979.
Tripoli, Tunis and Algiers. They receive large quantities of tobacco and mis¬
cellaneous products from Europe, which they forward in boats to the town of
Jenné and elsewhere. Timbuktu can be regarded as the principal entrepot in this
part of Africa. All the salt from the Tudeyni mines is stored there. This salt is
transported by camel caravans. The Moors of Morocco and other countries who
travel to the Sudan stop in Timbuktu for six to eight months to engage in trade and
await a new load for their camels.
The slabs of salt are tied together with rope of inferior quality made from a kind
of grass which grows in the neighbourhood of Tandaye. This grass is already dry
when it is gathered. Before it is used it is soaked, then buried to protect it from the
sun and the east wind which would dry it too quickly. As soon as it is well
impregnated with moisture it is disinterred and twisted into rope by hand. The
Moors use it for various purposes. Sometimes the camels throw off their loads and
when the slabs of salt arrive in the town they are partly broken. This would make
them less saleworthy if the merchants did not take the precaution of having them
repaired by their slaves, who restore the broken pieces and pack them again with
stronger rope made from oxhide. The slaves draw patterns in black on the slabs in
the form of grooves, lozenges, etc. They like this work because it enables them to
collect a small supply of salt for their own use. As a rule men of this class are less
unhappy in Timbuktu than elsewhere. They are well clad, well fed and rarely
beaten. They are obliged to attend religious services, and this they do very
scrupulously. But they are nonetheless regarded as merchandise and are exported
to Tripoli, Morocco and other places on the coast where they are less happy than
in Timbuktu. They are always sorry to leave this town although they have no idea
of the fate in store for them.
When I was leaving, I saw several slaves take leave of each other in a most
touching manner, although they were not acquainted. The similarity of their
unhappy situations leads to feelings of sympathy and mutual interest amongst
them and they exchange recommendations of good conduct. But the Moors
responsible for taking them away often speed up the departure and tear them
away from these gentle effusions which might lead to pity for their fate.
Psychic sports
by Alexandra David-Néel
Anarchist, Buddhist, Orientalist, explorer
and writer, Alexandra David-Néel (1868-
1969) was a woman of indomitable energy
and strength of character. Adventurous
both as a thinker and as a traveller, this
prototype of modern woman made many
journeys in the East, above all in Tibet,
and became the first European woman to
enter Lhasa and spend some time there.
She was the author of several works about
her travels and about Buddhism, notably
Mystiques et magiciens du Tibet (1929),
from which the extract published here is
taken. In it she describes the practice of
toumo,'psychic exertions whereby the
lamas (spiritual leaders in Tibetan
Buddhism) generate heat.
©
Alexandra David-Néel
dressed asa Tibetan
pilgrim and beggar,
carrying her belongings
Top her back. She was
wearing this outfit when
she entered Lhasa in
1924.
Experts in the art of toumo.
A kind of examination sometimes concludes the students' period of training
in toumo. On a moonlit winter's night, those who think they are capable of
passing the test go with their masters to the edge of anunfrozen stream. If
there is no running water in the region, a hole is pierced in the ice. The chosen
night is one of those when a violent wind is blowing. Such nights are not rare in
Tibet.
The candidates for the title of respa* sit down cross-legged on the ground,
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Footloose and
completely naked. Sheets are plunged in the freezing water; they freeze and
emerge stiff. Each of the pupils wraps himself in a sheet which he is required to
unfreeze and dry on his body. As soon as the sheet is dry it is again plunged in the
water and the candidate again wraps himself in it. The operation goes on in this
way until daybreak. He who has dried most sheets is proclaimed the winner.
It is said that some manage to dry as many as forty sheets in the course of a night.
Exaggeration must be taken into account and also the size of the sheets which in
some cases may be very small and purely symbolic. However, there is no doubt
that the respas really do dry on themselves several pieces of fabric the size of a big
shawl. I have seen this with my own eyes.
It is necessary to dry at least three in order to be recognized as a true respa
worthy of wearing the white cotton skirt which marks out the toumo graduates. At
any rate this was the original rule but it is doubtful whether it is very strictly
observed in our time. ...
In addition to the sheet-drying test there are several others. One involves sitting
down in the snow. The amount of snow which melts beneath the respa and the
area which melts around him denotes the degree of heat which he radiates.
It is difficult to get a totally accurate idea of the importance of the results of
toumo. Nevertheless they seem proven. Hermits live entirely naked or covered
with a thin garment all through the winter, in the midst of snow at high altitudes. I
am not the only one to have seen them. Members of the expedition which tried to
climb Mount Everest have seen some of these anchorites from a distance. As for
me, to the slight extent to which I have practised toumo, I have obtained striking
results.
Mystiques et magiciens du Tibet. Editions Pion, Paris,
1929.
Helmet thought to have
belonged to King Srong-
brtsan-sgam-po, founder
of the unified Kingdom of
Tibet in the 7th century.
This and other little-
known Tibetan artefacts
feature in a "Treasures of
Tibet" exhibition which is
being held at the Natural
History Museum, Paris,
from April to October
1987.
t > 'i^.ayiwi.iMajpijiHwiBiMii^
AS soon as I recovered and was able to think about the future, we resumed
our plans to continue our interrupted journey. We applied for permission
to go to Tashkurghan, the Pamirs and western China. We had to wait
sixteen years for it.
The women bring the meat. Behind them, through the opening in the yurt, we
can see the mountains, dazzling white against the dark sky. The meat is mutton
Marco Polo's mutton.* Not only is this a great honour; the meat really tastes like
meat.
The people who welcome us here are the same as those among whom we lived
seventeen years ago, but on the other side of the mountain. They welcome us with
the same hospitality and natural dignity. ... We are seated on a Tadzhik carpet of
great beauty, contemplating the dishes of meat and the great jars of curds set
before us.
I am happy. To be here makes the seventeen years of waiting worthwhile. And
from here the roads lead eastwards. Yet it will never be said of me that I followed
the steps of Marco Polo. What use is it to be the first foreigner to travel in the
Chinese Pamirs since 1949, what use is it to have made my way here by road and
river from the North Cape to the China Sea, what use is it to have toiled for twenty
years to achieve all this, when there will still be a few dozen kilometres of the road
over the passes between Afghanistan and China that I have not covered? To be
only a few dozen kilometres short of my goal is as if I have achieved nothing!
Perhaps I shall get permission if I wait another seventeen years. Pakistan once
promised to give me permission to make the ascent to Tashkurghan by this route,
and if I also get permission to cross the frontier of Afghanistan and go down to the
Vakhan region the journey will be done. And not only Marco Polo's journey, but
also the journeys of Fa Xian and Xuan Zang. That is what I dreamt of one summer
when I was eleven years old, in a loft in the Swedish countryside of that and
much else.
So perhaps I shall get permission, but by that time I shall certainly not be
capable of making the journey. Again we hear music; they are still dancing
outside. Above 4,000 metres the altitude starts to cause me problems. ... The
height of the pass we were going over was 4,700 metres. I went to have a look at
some tombs a little below the road. They were very similar to the tombs in the
valley near Tashkurghan, and they also reminded me of the tombs in the Bashgul
valley in Nuristan, beneath the Hindu Kush, to the south of these passes. So I had
the strength to get as far as this, but I shall certainly not be strong enough to do so
in ten or twenty years' time. Even if I got permission, I should be unable to cross
the Afghanistan passes, over there. They are even higher than these, here.
It is a strange feeling to be here, to listen to the music and to know that now it is
so far, but no further.
I took these notes in the camp east of Tashkurghan. The grey skies gave them a
Thoughts from
the roof of the
world
by Jan Myrdal
The Silk Road, followed by merchants
and travellers since ancient times, links
the West to the heart ofChina. From
childhood on, Jan Myrdal dreamt of
following in the footsteps of the great
medieval traveller Marco Polo. Myrdal is
a widely-travelled Swedish writer (born
1927) who has crossed Europe and Asia
in the footloose style associated with the
poets and writers of the American Beat
movement. In 1957 he set out for China
in a small car. He was near the Pamirs in
central Asia when he fell ill and had to
abandon the journey. From his hospital
bed his only thought was to continue the
journey. The story of his travels was
published in Sweden in 1977.
* There are many wild sheep which are very large
because their horns are easily six hands long, and from
these horns the shepherds make bowls for eating and the
fences where they stay with their animals during the
night." The Book of Marco Polo.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
fancy free
c
?>
CO
o
o
o
In the little town of Tashkurghan (Afghanistan),
a caravaneer cooks rice for the evening meal.
Sidenvägen. En resa ¡ran höga Pamir och Hi genom
Sinkiang och Kansu. An English translation by A. Hen¬
ning has been published by Victor Gollancz Ltd.,
London, under the title Silk Road.
touch of sentimentality. Travelling has a dimension that is sometimes over¬
looked.
The great travellers who came here and later recorded their impressions are all
very objective and down-to-earth. They give perfectly convincing reasons for
their travels. They were trading, or they were seeking religious writings, or they
wanted to make sure that this really is the road to China. They were going to draw
maps. That's fine.
We, too, have our objective reasons. I read somewhere that the reason why I
travel is to describe what I see. That's fine too.
But this does not really explain why I have spent more months abroad than at
home in Sweden, in the last twenty years, and still less does it explain why the
great travellers whose accounts of their travels we admire so much undertook
their journeys.
For travelling has a third- dimension the strange, tormenting longing for
something beyond your reach ; setting out at dawn ; the pleasant feeling of exhaus¬
tion after crossing a mountain; the taste of the sea in your mouth before you can
see the sea; the smell of water and growing things when you are still in the desert;
reaching a town at dead of night, keeping still in the darkness and listening to new
sounds.
Travelling is more than seeing new things; it is leaving them, too. The traveller
not only opens doors , he closes them after him , never to,return . Yet when he shuts
his eyes he can always see the place he left forever. No town is as clearly visible at
night as a town you have left for ever.
And it is here, on the roof of the world, just when I realize that I shall never
finish the journey I began twenty years ago, that I see how powerful was my need
to set out, to go on, to go further, to leave places and to see more. Writing reports
and descriptions of what one has seen is a good thing; it is useful and sensible; but
in its third dimension it also seems to be the rationalization of a strong desire
whose roots reach down to the depths of human life.
Bookshelf
Great Voyages ofDiscovery: Circumnaviga¬
tors and Scientists, 1764-1843, by Jacques
Brosse. Facts on File Publications, New
York/Oxford, 1983.
A Book of Travellers' Tales, assembled by
Eric Newby. Pan Books Ltd., London,
1986.
The Four Voyages of Christopher Col¬
umbus, edited and translated by J.M.
Cohen. Penguin Books Ltd., Harmond-
sworth, U.K., 1969.
Captain Cook's Voyages of Discovery, by
Captain James Cook. Everyman's Library,
J.M. Dent & Sons Ltd., London, 1948.
The Bible in Spain, by George Borrow.
Everyman's Library, J.M. Dent & Sons
Ltd., London, 1969.
Equiano's Travels, by Olaudah Equiano,
edited by Paul Edwards. Heinemann Edu¬
cational Books, London and Ibadan, 1967.
Travels'into the Interior of Africa, by Mun¬
go Park. Eland Books, London, 1983.
Against Nature, by J.-K. Huysmans, trans¬
lated by Robert Baldick. Penguin Books
Ltd., Harmondsworth, U.K., 1959.
Unesco Collection of Representative Works
European Series
Poetry of Soviet Ukraine's New World An
Anthology, translated from Ukrainian. Un-
esco/Paul Norbury Publications Ltd.,
Ashford, U.K., 1986.
Indian Series
The Decade of Panipat (1751-61), translated
from Marathi by Ian Raeside. Unesco/
Popular Prakashan Private Ltd., Bombay,
1984.
A Tagore Reader, edited by Amiya Chakra-
varty. Unesco/Macmillan, London and
New York, 1961.
Correction
We apologize to readers for an error in a
caption on page 6 of the February issue in
which the Alpine resort of Alpe-d'Huez in
the Isère département of France is wrongly
stated to be in the département of Haute-
Savoie.
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courler", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. ,111 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
38
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C1 - Avril 1987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Four Unesco
international quarterlies
resources
ß Prospects
Prospects
A quarterly review of education which
benefits from the direct collaboration of
institutions and academics from more than
150 countries. Intended not only for
specialists, it considers education in all its
socio-economic and cultural contexts.
Annual subscription 100 French francs
Single issue 30 FF
Nature and resources
Provides international news and informa¬
tion about Unesco programmes concerning
environmental activities, natural resources
research and conservation. Issues soon to
be published include such topics as: water
resources and energy; environmental
geology; land development in the tropics.
Annual subscription 60 FF
Single issue 18 FF
CopyriB"
buUeun
Museum
The sole international journal that presents
museological evolution and its multiple
facets around the world, from security to
cultural policies and curating.
Annual subscription 156 FF
Single issue 48 FF
Copyright bulletin
A quarterly to meet the needs not only of
specialists in the field, but authors, librar¬
ians, publishers, editors, record producers,
broadcasters, film makers, scientific re¬
searchers and lawyers.
Annual subscription 60 FF
Single issue 18 FF
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a GippsSl.. Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33. Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne, Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BAHRAIN. United Schools International, Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726.
Bahrain. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch
edition only: N.V. Handelmaatschappi] Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications agent:
Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internaciones Ltda. Processing Dept., R
Petxoto Gomide 209, 01 409. Sao Paulo SP. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co,
Ltd., Central Distribution Centre, 61. Sparks Street. Ottawa ONT K1P 5R1.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box
88, Beijing. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51 -1 13 02, Prague 1 ; Ve
Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag.-Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export-OG, Tidsskriftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970
Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications. No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box 1 28, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
P.O. Box 2. 01641 Vantas 64. Rautikirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O.
Box 1. 01641 Vantas 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. CCP 12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig. Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig, or from
Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides Entreprises, P.O. Box
14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE John
Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers. P.O. Box 10073, 541 10
Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore, 4 Nikis Street,
Athens T 1 26. Kostarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2 Hippocratous
Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 1 3-15, Lock Rd., Kowloon.
Hong Kong Govt. Information Services. Publication Centre, Baskerville
House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT. P.O.B. 149-H-1389.
Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount
Road, Madras 2: 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park
St., Calcutta 70016; Scmdia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr.
Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. 1 188 Englab Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158. P.O. Box
1 1 365-4498. Teheran. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Rd., Walkinstown. Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61000. ITALY. Licosa (Ubreria
Commissionana Sanson, S p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552,
50121 Florence. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome
Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB
2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue.
Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO.
DILITSA, Distribuidora Literaria SA, Apartado Postal 24 448, Mexico DF
06700. N & E Omicron SA, Bookseller & Subscriptions Agency. Col Condesa
Deleg. Cuahtemoc, Apartado Postal 40 075. 06140 Mexico DF. MONACO.
British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan
Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000
AD Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirnie. Wellington; 130 Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721,
Christchurch; Alma St., P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1104,
Dunedin. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of He; The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P.O. 286. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum-
Oslo 1; Narvesen A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602
Oslo 6; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitelssentret, Postboks 307
Blindem, Oslo 3. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box
8950, Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw;
Ars Polona-Ruch. Kraxowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw,
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd.
Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA.
American & Overseas Publications (Pty) Ltd., Subscription Service. P.O. Box
42476. Johannesburg. Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria
0001. Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty) Ltd., Libri Building, 268 Church Street,
Pretoria 0001. Central News Agency Ltd., Group Overseas Periodical Div.
P.O. Box 61 3, Cape Town 8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chirtampalam Gardiner Mawata. P.O B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943, Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Forbundet. Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65
Stockholm; Wennergren-Wilhams AB, Nordenllychtsvagen 70. S-104, 25
Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 -101 .20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairie
Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11. CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also
in Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zürich. SYRIA.
Aleppo University Books Establishment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo.
TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road. Siyaeg Phaya
Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit. Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave..
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco. 18
Alexandra St., St. Clair, Trinidad W 1. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl
Caddesi, No 469, Posta Kutusu 21 9, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office, Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals
Section-Room 008, Nine Elms Lane. London SW8 5DR, and H.M. S.O.
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham. Bristol;
for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd.. 122 King's Cross Rd., London WC1X
9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan Associates-UN IPUB, Periodicals
Department, 10033-F King Highway, Lanham MD 20706. USSR. V/O
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova39, Moskva 1 13095. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Ilica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana;
Noltt, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National Educational Distribution
Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales
(PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
ffi i* iï * * ífyf-?*>* * * M! ** ¿ £S *.**» * q 9
Y^t^r^v^ j X
< /v r
* * > Í t
' ^
> a * «> ¿
» C
£222222222
£4¿ M¿ » ft
g * -f /t>
I
)
25 S *?
isi v^.
41
T
i
I
M
]]>
</page>
</document>
