<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="073178eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
MAY 1987-9 Frtncb franc«
;*<^.-;#
,.
SrèfJ£*\
ii
...-. :
***s
The spice of life
Food and culture
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live . . .
.
^-,^E» v
(
-
2
©
Water and life
Mali is the largest of the French-speaking States of West Africa. Through
this land-locked country, half of which is desert, flow two major rivers,
the upper Sénégal and the Niger, whose middle course brings water and
life to parts of the drought-stricken Sahel. The population (some 7.5
million in 1984) is essentially rural. Farming, using irrigation water from
the two rivers, is the country's main source of wealth, although livestock-
raising and fishing, with outlets in both the domestic and the export
market, also play an important role in the economy. Fishing on the Niger,
in particular, gives rise to a significant export trade in dried and smoked
fish. Above, traditional net fishing on the Niger.
54 Mali
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
"Tell me what you eat and I will tell you what you
are." The maxim penned a century and a half ago by
the French lawyer Anthelme Brillat-Savarin in his
celebrated work on gastronomy, The Physiology of
Taste has not gone unheard by modern anthropolo¬
gists. The foods people select from the range avail¬
able to them in their environment, the ways in which
they prepare those foods for consumption, the sig¬
nificance they attach to the act of eating and the
code of manners which govern it can shed remark¬
able light on many other aspects of the societies in
which they live. Food and drink are so profoundly
important for humanity that they are often linked
with matters that have nothing to do with nutrition.
To take but one example described in this issue, for
some groups of Mexican farmers, maize is not only a
staple of their diet but an object of veneration, the
very heart of their culture, myths and religious
practices. If food satisfies an essential human need,
it is also an essential ingredient of cultural identity.
This issue of the Unesco Courier examines some
of the connections between the eating habits of
peoples in different parts of the world and other
aspects of their behaviour. These connections, as
our contributors point out, are many and varied.
Eating together is a way of initiating and maintain¬
ing human relations. Meals convey social messages.
Through eating together as a family cultural values
are transmitted from generation to generation.
Symbolic meanings are attached to food and drink
by the major world religions, and eating is associ¬
ated with initiation and burial rites and other cere¬
monies. Food is used as a form of currency. The
consumption of rare and expensive foods is a mark
of status.
This issue is thus intended as an introduction to
the "anthropology of eating" rather than an ex¬
amination of the problem of world hunger. If the
question of food aid to the victims of natural catas¬
trophes and other disasters is evoked, it is in terms
of the impact of such aid on the nutrition habits of
those who receive it.
Finally, the importance of food and eating is
reflected in proverbs, folk wisdom and metaphor in
many languages. We hope that the following pages
will whet our readers' appetite for knowledge about
mankind's "consuming passions", provide them
with some food for thought, and leave them hungry
for more.
Cover: Summer, fantastic head composed of flowers, fruit,
vegetables and other crops, by the Italian painter Giuseppe
Arcimboldo (c.1527- 1593) . Photo © Réunion des Musées Natio¬
naux, Paris. Louvre Museum
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
May 1987
40th year
The anthropology of eating
4 Food, culture and society by Igor de Garine
The spice of life
8 A grain revolution
The impact of imported rice on millet-based African
civilizations by Thianar Ndoye and Malick M'Baye
10 Of maize and meat
Culinary traditions and cultural identity in Mexico and
Argentina by Perla Petrich
13 Beneficial beans?
14 Reflections on the potato by Nick M. Joaquin
17 The ones that get away
A coastal community that turns its back on fish by John Durnin
Eating together
18 (Table) manners makyth man
The emergence of homo sapiens as a convivial animal
by Naomichi Ishige
22 The meal is the message
The language of Brazilian cuisine by Roberto DaMatta
24 China's health food tradition
by Li Ruifen
Too much and too little
28 Paradise lost
Bulimia, anorexia and drug addiction by Piero Camporesi
32 Food aid and food habits by Jeremy Shoham and
Bruno Stainier
2 A time to live...
MALI: Water and life
Advertising in the Courier
We wish to inform readers that as of June 1987 the Courier
will be introducing advertising pages into its English,
French and Spanish editions.
Advertising matter will be entirely separate from the
editorial content and will be restricted to fields in which
Unesco takes an active interest, such as educational publi¬
cations, communications technologies, and the work of
international organizations.
Advertising revenue will be used primarily to assist the
non-Headquarters editions of the magazine.
We hope that readers will understand the nature and
purpose of this project, which is a new departure for the
Courier but is already the practice in certain other publica¬
tions of the United Nations system.
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 33 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
Thai
Vietnamese
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N°5-1987-CPD-87-l-445 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The anthropology
Food,
culture
and society
UNLESS they satisfy their needs for food, living creatures
cannot survive. Human beings, however, appear to differ
slightly from other animals in the solutions they have de¬
vised for this problem. Thanks to our physiological omnivorousness
and our nature as social animals with a culture, a sense of symbolism
and the ability to create a favourable micro-environment for our¬
selves, we can live equally well in the polar regions and in the
equatorial rain forests. We may wonder, however, whether our
efforts to adapt to the symbolic standards dictated by our culture are
always in keeping with our optimum biological adaptation, either in
the short term_as. individuals pr in the long term as members of the
human species.
Food is one field in which biology and culture are to some extent
out of step. Human beings are equipped with internal regulatory
food-consumption mechanisms whose purpose is to maintain certain
balanced states in the organism; but these mechanisms are often
faulty.
In industrialized societies evidence of this phenomenon can be
seen in the pathological consequences of an overabundant food
supply. Although their lifestyle is tending to reduce their energy
output, people eagerly consume animal proteins, fatty and sugary
food, stimulants and intoxicants whose nutritional value is, to say
the least, questionable.
Is this a recent development, specific to urban societies which are
located in a man-made environment, alienated from natural
rhythms, and have not had time to adapt to new types of stress? This
is by no means certain. Where food is concerned we must beware of
ecological providentialism and of the belief that in traditional
societies people naturally consume the diet that is physiologically
best for them.
As the American anthropologist Margaret Mead once pointed
out, human societies make a selection from the potential range of
foodstuffs which are provided by their environment and brought
within their reach by the technical resources at their disposal. The
survival of a human group obviously depends on a diet which
satisfies its members' nutritional needs. However, the level of
satisfaction of those needs, the definition of which is a matter of
controversy, varies from one society to another both qualitatively
and quantitatively.
It often happens that some available foodstuffs are either neg¬
lected or used to meet other needs. The example most often given is
that of the Hindu populations of India, whose respect for animal life
leads them , for religious and philosophical reasons , to practise more
or less strict forms of vegetarianism. Pastoral peoples, who might be
thought to eat large quantities of milk and meat, usually consume
these foodstuffs sparingly. Cattle are used primarily to provide
other forms of satisfaction, as a bride-price, for example.
Many African population groups live in climatic zones where
cereal farming is possible, but they choose instead to grow tubers,
especially cassava, which is less nutritious. People eat according to
patterns prescribed by the societies to which they belong. Their
culture determines the range of what is edible and imposes the
dietary taboos which, when necessary, serve to distinguish their
society from others.
The discrepancy between what is recommended by the culture
and what is nutritionally indispensable is most strikingly apparent in
the nourishment given to children after weaning. They are nearly
always given what is thought to be the best possible nourishment,
and are lucky if this provides them with the ration of protein they
need to guarantee their growth and resistance to infection. In most
cases, children are looked upon as small adults, and they receive a
ration appropriate to their size but not to their specific needs for
protein.
Populations afflicted with malnutrition for reasons which may
include dysfunctional cultural choices, also undoubtedly pay a price
in terms of death-rates (especially child mortality), physical de¬
velopment and longevity. The influence of malnutrition is,
however, often difficult to disentangle from that of the major
endemic diseases. In traditional societies there is a marked differ¬
ence between known potential food resources and those which are
actually used. Subsistence is usually based on a small number of
foodstuffs of plant origin which, even in most hunting and fishing
communities, provide nearly all the calories in the diet. The diet of
traditional societies is extremely monotonous; perhaps familiarity is
a source of comfort. Variations are the result of seasonal fluctua¬
tions of resources.
What reasons underlie the choice of what have been called
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
"supercultural" foods? Both practical (and possibly nutritional) and
symbolic considerations, notably the quest for prestige or for identi¬
fication with an envied model, should be taken into account. These
foods are often treated as divine gifts. The acts of cultivation and
their accompanying rituals give form and pattern to the com¬
munity's yearly round.
Eating habits, likes and dislikes are formed by the sense-impress¬
ions conveyed by the flavour, smell and texture of certain foods and
the dishes of which they form part. These preparations provide the
basis for human gastronomy and for the food of the gods, since
offerings and sacrifices are a special means of communicating with
the transcendent. Not only vegetable foods are used in this context.
Meat comes into the diet through celebration: its consumption
nearly always has a festive or ritual aspect. Blood is seen as an
essential ingredient in Vedic sacrifices, in the Christian mass, and in
the cutting of a chicken's throat as an offering to the ancestors in
African ceremonies.
The esteem in which certain foods and dishes are held by different
human groups is no indication of their real nutritional value, which
is, as it were, a bonus. What is usually sought is a food which rapidly
produces a feeling of repletion. One example, the thick porridge
made from unsifted flour by the Massa people of Cameroon,
contains a large quantity of indigestible carbohydrate which is filling
but interferes with the assimilation of the other nutrients in the food
ration.
Man is not a frugal animal. Some specialists believe that human
beings are among the mammals with the greatest propensity to store
fats. In most traditional societies, the quest for a full stomach,
participation in a banquet to which both the living and the dead are
invited and its digestion in common with other people, are among
the main lubricants of social relations and provide a means of
communication.
by Igor de Garine
"What have been called 'supercultural' foods are often treated as
divine gifts. The acts of cultivation and their accompanying rituals
give form and pattern to the community's yearly round." Left, a
Chadian farmer holds a cluster of sorghum.
In the first hours of life a child comes into contact with the flavours
and textures typical of the foods eaten by the group to which it
belongs. Although taste remains something distinctive and indi¬
vidual, it is imprinted from birth with the stamp of a culture. A
child's emotional response to the foods that its culture considers to
be good is part of the process whereby it is integrated into society.
Without a doubt, the relative plasticity of early eating habits is a
factor that must be taken into account when considering the future
of our species. If the survival of a group depends on it, or for other
reasons, it is possible to profoundly modify the eating habits of the
members of that group, provided that a start is made at birth.
Although the connection between food and physical health may
not be clearly perceived, all societies to some extent attribute
magical medicinal properties to food. The general principle is that
the body and the mind should be given the foods that are most
appropriate, both materially and symbolically. The tendency in the
West is to follow the Galenic theory of medicine, whereby ingested
foods are converted into humours on whose balanced relationship
the health of the individual depends. In India and China, the
systems ofcorrespondence are extremely complex , and in the choice
of food account is taken both of the fundamental elements of the
Universe and of contingent matters such as place, season, time and
the distinctive characteristics of each person (see article page 24).
"Tell me what you eat and I will tell you what you are," wrote
Anthelme Brillat-Savarin (1755-1826) in his celebrated work on
gastronomy La physiologie du goût, (English translation, The Phy¬
siology of Taste, 1925). Food consumption expresses the status of
individuals according to a whole range of criteria (age, sex, social
and economic status) within a society in a particular spatial and
temporal context, which is itself in contact with other self-contained
societies. It provides a counterpoint to most other overt social
characteristics and may, as the French anthropologist Claude Lévi-
Strauss has suggested , unconsciously reveal the underlying structure
of societies.
Eating is a form of expression whereby a person in a sense acts out
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
his or her position in a particular society. For this reason, the quest
for prestige and distinction is a constant feature of the dynamic of
food selection. This dynamic operates between individuals, between
groups within a society, and between traditional societies today
faced with the overwhelming influence of urban industrial civiliza¬
tion. Monetary income has doubtless become the main variable that
influences food consumption, but the dynamic of choice has by no
means been brought under control. Any understanding of the
process calls for considerable knowledge of local problems and the
complexities of their historical background.
One example will suffice. In northern Cameroon, the Massa, the
Toubouri and the Fulbe live side by side in approximately the same
ecological setting. They can grow the same crops, but until recently
some Massa were willing to forgo the benefits of dry-season trans¬
planted sorghum, although they knew about it. They based their
rejection of this crop on a religious argument (the curse of Mother
Earth on upstart innovators) probably wishing to defend their
cultural authenticity by distinguishing themselves from the other
two peoples. Today, traditional beliefs and antagonisms have faded
and the Massa are more inclined to see themselves as members of
the Cameroonian nation. They have adopted dry-season trans¬
planted sorghum and are tending to abandon their own varieties of
red'sorghum for strains which produce white flour, and for rice,
which was the food of both the wealthiest peoples in the towns and of
the Fulbe, who were historically dominant in the region.
This example shows that the influence of industrial civilization is
not all-powerful and that local cultures (which are separate) also
provide role models for neighbouring populations. This factor is
seldom turned to account for development purposes.
Even if a standardization of everyday eating habits is taking place,
linked to the trend towards a single world food economy, local food
consumption patterns continue to flourish and traditional foodstuffs
continue to be produced. Developing countries can probably free
themselves to some extent from the need to import foodstuffs if they
are willing to make an effort to promote indigenous products on a
par with the efforts made to promote imported commodities.
One of the many reasons for fostering a degree of attachment to
local foods is that self-sufficiency in food production is still an ideal
situation for rural societies where money is too scarce a commodity
to be wasted on food. The other reasons are symbolic. Individuals
are emotionally attached to their childhood eating habits which are
usually imbued with their traditional culture. The perpetuation of
the traditional style of nourishment in daily life or in the calendar of
festivities is a pledge of authenticity and social cohesion and a
defence against outside aggression. This phenomenon is also found
among emigrants. It has been pointed out that consumers fall into
two categories: those who see a Golden Age in the past and uphold
traditional cuisine, and those who envisage a Golden Age in the
future and put their trust in scientifically approved nutrients. This
dichotomy can also be observed in developing countries.
Preparation of taro gruel, a ceremonial
dish consumed during festivities and
rituals in the Melanesian archipelago of
Vanuatu.
Right, lamas of the Tamang people of
Nepal partake of a ritual meal.
Far left, ancient Greek cantharus or drink¬
ing vessel in the form of a satyr's head
decorated with a sacrificial scene (5th cen¬
tury BC).
Left, fragment of a ceramic urn in the form
of the young god of maize is from the
pre-Columbian city of Monte Albán in Mex¬
ico. (Zapotee civilization, c. 500-750).
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Admittedly, the advent of urban industrial civilization has made a
big difference to the relationship between people and what they eat.
This relationship is now independent of time and space. In some
societies, those who can afford to do so can eat or drink anything,
any time, anywhere and in any quantity. Food choices have become
more individualized. Less repressed than they were by material
constraints and the search for food, personal tastes are being more
strongly expressed.
Anxiety about food has taken a new form. Seasonal hunger and
the search for a full stomach have given way to a permanent and
legitimate quest for pleasure in eating as a means of easing tensions
whose origins specialists in the psychopathology of eating interpret
as expressions of a nostalgic desire to return to the womb.
Food production has become monetarized, and food is now, as it
were, secular. This does not mean that food has lost its symbolic
value or its social significance. Although there is something anarchic
in our habits of nibbling, it is still the person who runs the household,
or, nowadays, the restaurant-owner or canteen manager who
chooses what food is consumed at meals.
This choice is determined by many criteria whose range, thanks to
advances in communication, has steadily widened. Urban industrial
civilization encompasses many subcultures. Every social group has
its own range of foods which helps to express its values and lifestyle.
In accordance with a wide variety of criteria, each group makes a
choice from the countless resources available to it, and this reduces
the likelihood of a uniform worldwide food model, the establish¬
ment ofwhich sometimes seems to be imminent.
IGOR DE GARINE, French ethnologist and specialist in the study of food
and nutrition in relation to culture and ecology, is currently director of
research at the National Centre for Scientific Research (CNRS), Paris,
where he heads a research team on "differential food anthropology". A
former head of the food habits section of FAO's Nutrition Division, he is the
author of around a hundred scientific anieles and studies in French and
English, and of eleven ethnographic documentary films.
1,
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The spice of life
by Thianar Ndoye and Malick M'Baye
A grain revolution
The impact of imported rice
on millet-based African civilizations
IN rural Africa today, drought and
desertification have wrought pro¬
found changes which have upset the
balance of the agrarian food-production
system.
For centuries, millet and sorghum were
the food staples that enabled the farmers
of the Sahel to achieve self-sufficiency in
an exchange economy. These farmers
domesticated and improved Pennisetum
spicatum, or bulrush millet, also known
as "pearl millet". Owing to its short
growth cycle, this crop draws the fullest
benefit from the short rainy season.
In the southern Sahel, millet is culti¬
vated as a supplement to sorghum, or
"great millet", which originated in the
Sudanese regions of tropical Africa. The
area under sorghum cultivation has ex¬
panded considerably in the tropical re¬
gions of other continents, and even in
warmer temperate countries. This cereal
is nowadays the staple food of more than
300 million people, most of whom live in
Africa, India and Central America.
Millet and sorghum have always been a
powerful link between the African far¬
mer and his environment . From a cultu¬
ral point of view, millet plays a central
role in the organization of community life
and in the interpenetrating systems of
kinship and values. Learning to grind
millet with the traditional pestle and mor¬
tar and to process it into an edible food¬
stuff was part of every girl's introduction
to the art of cooking.
The grain is dehusked by moistening
and pounding with a pestle and mortar.
After drying it is milled, by means of a
second and then a third pounding, each of
which is followed by winnowing. Then
comes the fermentation stage, achieved
by humidification, kneading, mixing and
even germination. The end product is
cooked in water and eaten with milk or a
sauce, types of nourishment which are
more liquid than solid.
Steaming became popular with the ad¬
vent of recipes for couscous from the
Maghreb peoples, who invented the tech¬
nique and utensils and transmitted them
to other cultures. The Senegalese cook
has improved the recipe by meticulously
working the flour by hand into a finer,
firmer texture. The resulting semolina is
then steamed, sealed with laalo (dried
baobab leaves, ground into powder) and
given a smoother consistency before
being soaked.
Recorded in every African's memory
are the working songs of women pound¬
ing millet, sung to the rhythm of the
thudding pestle as it crushes the grains
into flour. This millet or sorghum flour,
made into porridge, is an excellent res¬
torative for those who do hard manual
work, for women who have recently
given birth, and for convalescents.
Millet cakes are the first symbolic solid
food given when a child is weaned. And
couscous, thanks to traditional proces¬
sing techniques, will keep for several
months. It is the food on which nomad
peoples survived during their long jour¬
neys. Millet, a sacred cereal, is also
valued for its use in sacrifices connected
with the Islamic or animist traditions of
West African countries. In Africa dried
millet stalks are used as building mate¬
rials and as cattle fodder. Red sorghum is
used to make beer.
Sorghum and millet also have ex¬
change value in the rural African world
and are bartered for other foodstuffs.
The millet granary is a sign of wealth and
abundance, and has a mythical signifi¬
cance. It is a symbol of fertility and a link
between man and the earth. Thus it is
appropriate to speak of a "granary cul¬
ture", of the sacred characteristics of mil¬
let and, by extension, of all cereals.
Sorghum and millet may be traditional
cereals, but they are nevertheless full of
promise for the future, owing to their
capacity to resist drought. Today, in Cen¬
tral America and in the United States,
where high yields of sorghum are
obtained thanks to fertilizers and irriga¬
tion, it is used essentially for cattle feed.
In many countries facing food shortages,
millet and sorghum hold out a hope of
self-sufficiency.
However, rice has ousted millet and
sorghum from their economic and
mythical primacy, thereby increasing the
food crop deficit of many Sahel countries
and placing them in a vulnerable food
supply situation.
The changeover from millet to rice
took place in a particular historical con¬
text. The Portuguese introduced ground¬
nuts to Senegal in the fifteenth century,
and groundnut production was soon in¬
corporated into the cultural system and
Senegalese village women grind millet In
large wooden mortars before sifting the
flour from the bran.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A young Chadian woman prepares a thick
millet porridge, one of the staple foods of
the African savannah.
developed within a colonial market eco¬
nomy at the expense of the traditional
crops which had enabled the farmers to
be self-sufficient. To make good the food
deficit caused by the cultivation of
groundnuts, the colonial authorities
imported cheap broken rice from Indo¬
china.
New eating habits thus began to
appear. Rice was adopted by Senegalese
urban society and soon became fashion¬
able throughout the country as the cereal
to be eaten on festive occasions. It even¬
tually pushed into the background an
essential social and economic feature of
African granary civilizations. Urban soci¬
ety began to impose alternative ways of
life and styles of thought on the rural
population and, in particular, to revolu¬
tionize habits of food consumption
through the overwhelming acceptance of
rice served with fish or meat.
Unlike millet, the preparation of which
is a lengthy and laborious task, rice is
ready for cooking: this is surely the main
reason for its success. "Rice and fish"
cooked in oil is a typically Senegalese
recipe and may even be considered the
national dish of Senegal. Today it has
spread to all the countries of West Africa.
Rice and oil, essential to the preparation
of this dish, are increasingly important to
the economy. A complex network of
transactions has been established: the
farmer sells his groundnuts, purchases
rice with the proceeds, and buys back the
oil from the groundnuts that he has sold.
The terms of trade in these transactions
have deteriorated for the farmer. Rice
imports are increasing (approximately
300,000 tonnes a year), and oil produc¬
tion is no longer keeping pace, owing to
the poor harvests of recent years blighted
by drought.
But, contrary to all expectations, re¬
cent studies show that rural consumers
still favour a number of the traditional
millet recipes, a preference which high¬
lights the importance of food symbolism
to Black Africans and the crucial role
played by traditional forms of nourish¬
ment in cultural identity.
THIANAR NDOYE, of Senegal, was assistant
director of ORANA, a Dakar-based institute for
food and nutrition research in Africa, from 1952
to 1965. A co-founder of his country's food and
applied nutrition service, he played a leading role
in the WHO programme for nutrition education In
Senegal (1972-1982). He has carried out mis¬
sions as a consultant with Unesco, FAO and
WHO, and has published anieles in a number of
journals.
MALICK M'BAYE, of Senegal, is currently work¬
ing with Unesco's Division for the Study and
Planning of Development. The author of a num¬
ber of scientific studies on development, gene¬
tics and sexuality, he has carried out research
with the French National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS) and has taught at the Uni¬
versity of Toulouse.
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Of maize and meat
by Perla Petrich
O
Culinary traditions and cultural identity
in Mexico and Argentina
MlJIMIIilHI.'Nf" \'
©
ALTHOUGH the food that groups
of people choose to eat is un¬
doubtedly dictated by their phy¬
siological needs, their environment and
the technical and economic facilities
available to them, these factors form part
of a wider context the social and histor¬
ical background and the outlook on the
world which are specific to each society.
In other words, exclusively ideological
motives play an important role in the
choice of the staple foodstuffs and food
processing techniques that make it possi¬
ble to create a culinary tradition that is
primarily recognized as a sign of cultural .
identification.
The ideology that each society creates
in relation to food and eating is reflected
in the choice of foodstuffs, the techniques
employed in preparing them, and the
rules laid down for their consumption.
What is the relationship between the
physical need to eat and the ideology
which justifies or determines what is
eaten? In an attempt to answer that ques¬
tion, we shall take two examples from
Latin America: maize (Indian corn) in
Mexico and meat in Argentina.
Even if soybeans or rice were cheaper
to grow or produced higher yields, Mex¬
ican farmers would never dream of grow¬
ing these crops instead of maize, which
accounts for 80 per cent of their diet. For
them maize is a cultural landmark of
fundamental importance as well as a
source of nutrition. According to Maya
mythology, man was created by the gods
from maize dough. Other materials such
as clay and wood had proved useless.
Only people made from maize survived
to venerate the plant from which they had
originated and which provided them with
their daily sustenance.
Every ear of maize, every morsel of
tortilla (maize cake), every sip of atole
the traditional beverage made from
maize flour provide incontrovertible
proof that feeding is not merely a chemi-
.cal and biological process but a form of
direct communication with the deities.
Through that communion, which is re¬
newed every day, people bear witness to
their faith in the gods, whose presence
guarantees that life will go on.
Since the gods chose maize to create
and feed mankind, how could man ever
doubt its perfection, cease to revere it, or
fail to believe in its origins and its divine
reproductive powers? Maize has had di¬
vine status for centuries. Even today,
Mexican Indians are reluctant to sell their
maize because that would be tantamount
to trading in their own flesh. Maize is
grown exclusively for personal con¬
sumption.
Maize is the Mexican farmer's only
criterion of taste, to the exclusion of all
others. No other foodstuff can replace
the tortilla which the women prepare with
maize dough and then brown on the com¬
al, a baked earthenware hotplate. In this
context, quantity is not important; even if
people gorge themselves on meat or fish
they will still feel unsatisfied if they do not
eat tortillas. On the other hand, a few
tortillas accompanied by a pinch of salt or
chili pepper will be sufficient to stave off
hunger.
The tortilla has formed the Mexicans'
taste for food. It is made from maize
which is boiled and then kneaded into a
soft, smooth dough. Compared with such
a food, which calls for little chewing,
meat is unpleasant, regardless of its qual¬
ity. Roast meat is regarded as hard and
dry, and it often happens that when hun¬
ters roast the animals they kill, the
women later boil the roast meat in the
kitchen.
In this indigenous culture there is a
general feeling that maize is the only
nourishing food. All other foods may be
eaten for pleasure but they are not consi¬
dered to have any nutritional value, be¬
cause, it is assumed, they will be quickly
expelled as waste. A man achieves social
recognition when he begins to farm the
land, and a woman when she begins to
cook. Only when they have shown that
they can grow and cook maize can they
start a family. Only then do men become
eligible for positions of responsibility
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
within the community. The influence of
maize thus permeates every aspect of hu¬
man life, since it provides physical suste¬
nance, integrates men and women into
the system of agricultural production,
justifies their existence and reaffirms
their beliefs.
Paradoxically and tragically, this con¬
ception of maize is not confirmed by the
biological facts. Maize cannot cater for
the individual's energy requirements un¬
less it is supplemented by a substantial
protein and calorie intake. With few ex¬
ceptions, the Indian's diet is limited to a
maximum of 45 grams of protein a day
compared with the 70 grams that are con¬
sidered essential, and to 1,300 calories
instead of the 2,600 calories needed by
people engaged in regular physical
labour.
The Pampa, the vast humid plain in
central Argentina, has always provided
the country with its food. It was there that
the Indians hunted game and that Span¬
ish and Creole settlers grew wheat and
then began to rear cattle on a large scale.
From the seventeenth century
onwards, beef formed the staple diet and
roasting was the most common culinary
technique. To the Argentines, roasting
evokes lavishness and plenty, in contrast
to boiling, which is symptomatic of scarci¬
ty and frugality. Boiled meat not only
preserves its juices but increases in
volume. Roast meat, on the other hand,
shrinks as it dries out.
Opposite page, detail from the "Codex Fe-
jervary-Mayer" a 14th-century Meso-
American pictographic manuscript. The
water-goddess can be seen pouring water
on maize with a hand that emerges from
her head. Maize is depicted as a sturdy
young man firmly rooted in the soil.
Lassoing (1820), a watercolour by the
English artist Emeric Essex Vidal (1791-
1861).
The maize harvest as depicted in the
"Codex Florentino", a manuscript contain¬
ing information from indigenous sources
which was used by the Spanish monk and
ethnologist Bernardino de Sahagún (1500-
1590) in his study of Aztec civilization,
Historia general de las cosas de Nueva
España (Genera/ History of the Things of
New Spain).
A comparison of roasting in Argentine
cookery with boiling as practised in Mex¬
ico shows how food preparation patterns
reflect not only different ecosystems but
contrasting forms ofxsocial and cultural
organization. In Mexico, from the six¬
teenth century onwards, the areas on
which farmers were able to grow food
were reduced as a result of colonial set¬
tlement. This land shortage was" com¬
pounded by low crop yields caused by
constant soil erosion. In Argentina, on
the other hand, food production called
for little effort until the mid-nineteenth
century. The gauchos who lived on the
plains considered themselves the
monarchs of all they surveyed. If they felt
hungry, they killed an animal, cut off a
piece of flesh sometimes only the
tongue and left the rest for the dogs or
birds of prey. Today things have
changed; unless they own livestock, peo¬
ple have to buy their meat. Even so, meat
is still reasonably priced and continues to
be the staple of everyday diet.
The hospitable ethos of the Pampa and
its seemingly boundless vistas influenced
ways of cooking. Food was prepared in
the open air meat was spit-roasted in
the courtyard of the home or in the
fields for the entire extended family
and friends who would turn up to eat
without a formal invitation. Another sig¬
nificant feature of this type of cooking is
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
its masculine character. As hunters and
livestock raisers, men not only procured
the food and did the slaughtering and
skinning; they also did the cooking. The
meat was either impaled on a spit, one
end of which was driven into the ground
so as to maintain it at an angle over the
flames, or else placed, with the entrails,
on a grill, to avoid direct contact with the
hot cinders.
It was the usual practice and still is in
rural areas for everybody to take his
knife and cut off the slice he fancied, and
then eat it without any seasoning. The
only drink that went with the roast
meat the asado was mate, an infusion
prepared in a small gourd and drunk
through a metal tube, or bombilla.
Women took no part in the preparation
of the asado and only emerged when the
meat was cooked. Their culinary duties
lay elsewhere in boiling, frying or bak¬
ing the food for the daily meal when the
family circle was confined to the intimacy
of parents and children, and when the
food was both prepared and consumed
inside the home. Women prepared the
puchero, a stew consisting of beef, Span¬
ish-type chorizo sausage, black pudding,
bone marrow, bacon, pumpkin, yams
and potatoes, and the carbonada, a dish
made with charqui, salt meat dried in the
sun.
The Argentine culinary horizon
broadened with the arrival of Italian,
Spanish, Syrian, Lebanese and Jewish
immigrants at the end of the nineteenth
century and the beginning of the twen¬
tieth. However, the choice of food was
not greatly modified ; roast beef remained
the staple diet and all other types of meat
or cereal were secondary. Roasting con¬
tinued to be the favourite cooking
method.
For the Argentines, roast meat sym¬
bolizes the direct assimilation of the ani¬
mals vitality and of nature. People must
eat plenty of meat to conserve their
strength. All other foods are regarded as
secondary, inessential. This approach to
food has led to excessive meat consump¬
tion, to the detriment of dairy products
and other foodstuffs. Argentina's vast
herds of cattle have been used almost
entirely for meat production. Even
today, the consumption of milk and dairy
products is negligible.
Both in Mexico and in Argentina, the
appetite can only be satisfied by the sta¬
ple food, the tortilla in one case, roast
meat in the other. This does not exclude
the consumption of other foodstuffs or
the use of other cooking techniques,
especially in the urban areas where they
were introduced by immigrants in the
early years of the century. Pizza and pas¬
ta, for example, have become part of the
everyday diet, and although roast meat is
still the most highly prized dish, it is no
longer a regular feature. In urban areas,
it has been replaced by steak, which ful¬
fils for those who eat it the conditions
A herd of young cattle on an Argentine ranch
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
described by the French critic and I
essayist Roland Barthes: succulence and
simplicity.
The long-standing preference for beef I
is reflected not only in the high rate of I
beef consumption but also in the rejec¬
tion of other types of meat. The offshore
shelf of Argentina abounds in an extraor¬
dinary variety of fish, but the lean, white
flesh of fish is no substitute for beef, let
alone a complement to it. Fish is only
eaten occasionally and has an exclusively I
symbolic significance ; as a result of Span- I
ish influence, salt cod is eaten on Fridays I
in Lent and during Holy Week.
These occasions apart, fish almost nev- I
er appears on the family table. The I
reasons are clearly neither biological nor I
economic (domestically caught fish is no I
more expensive than beef), nor are they I
imposed by the natural environment.
The same symbolic significance can be I
seen in the "imported" Christmas menu,
which is a carbon copy of that prepared I
by the family forebears in the Iberian I
Peninsula and includes the pinenut cakes , I
almonds and nougat which were designed I
to make good the calorie deficit caused by I
the European winter but are quite unsuit- I
able as well as being indigestible in a I
sultry South American summer, even I
though the family continues to decorate I
its Christmas tree with cotton-wool snow.
In short, roast beef has undoubtedly I
come to be a practical sign of "Argentine- I
ness" and boiled maize of "Mexican- I
ness", in that they are both nourishing I
foodstuffs, the natural environment lends
itself to their production, and the tech- I
niques are readily available for turning
them into food. Fundamentally, I
however, these dishes embody the sym¬
bolic values which the two peoples have
vested in them and which add to the
pleasure of eating them. Referring to I
these intellectual models for interpreting
and giving meaning to reality, the people I
of one region of Latin America look upon |
themselves as "maize people" who have
been created and nourished by the tender
grain which they venerate, while the peo¬
ple of another region see themselves as
consumers of meat whose consistency
evokes the boundless, rich and untamed
land which, like the meat itself, can only
be conquered by biting at it vigorously.
PERLA PETRICH, of Argentina, Is professor-of
Latin American literature at the University of
Paris VIII and a member of the French National
Centre for Scientific Research's Laboratory of
Languages and Civilizations with an Oral Tradi¬
tion (LACITO). She is the author ofseveral works
on food and nutrition, including La semántica del
maíz entre los mochó ("The Semantics of Maize
among the Mochos").
Beneficial beans?
THE bean, certain kinds of which are
among the most nourishing vegetables
eaten by man, has also since very
ancient times produced a luxuriant crop of
beliefs, cultural practices, rituals and taboos.
A bean taboo imposed on those rendering
sacrifice is mentioned in the oldest Indian
ritualistic text, the Yajurveda. In ancient
Greece, the use of beans is mentioned at
banquets and festivals, and a bean-god,
Cyamites, was worshipped. In the Roman
world beans played a role in magic rites, and
the priest of Jupiter was forbidden to touch a
bean or mention its name.
These and many other examples of the
cultural and religious importance of beans
have been recorded by the American anthro¬
pologist A.C. Andrews, who has written that
"the ancients felt towards beans a mingled
respect and dread, a complex of emotions
generally applied to an object believed to be
charged with some supernatural force, con¬
tact with which might be either beneficial or
harmful".
The Greek philosopher Pythagoras (c.580-
500 BC) forbade his followers to eat beans
"on the ground that beans were occupied by
the souls of the dead and thereby took on the
qualities of human flesh". Through this pre¬
sence, according to the Pythagorean theory,
beans became dynamic receptacles of gen¬
erative power.
Two American specialists, Solomon H. Katz
and Joan Schall of the University of Pennsyl¬
vania, have made a study of the consumption
patterns of fava beans in the Mediterranean
region and have suggested that the "rich
growth of cultural beliefs and taboos sur¬
rounding the fava bean may be a product, in
part, of the fact that many individuals who
consume the beans become very sick". This
sickness, known as favism, is "an acute
haemolytic anaemia resulting in fever, jaun¬
dice and possibly death". Those who are sus
ceptible to favism are those who suffer from a
hereditary metabolic defect in a red blood cell
enzyme, known as glucose-6-phosphate de¬
hydrogenase deficiency (G6PD-). A particu¬
larly severe variant of this condition (GdB-)
has been found to occur at frequencies of 10
to 30 per cent in certain populations in the
Mediterranean region.
"Why", ask Katz and Schall, "are fava
beans consumed in areas with high G6PD-
frequencies since so many people would face
a serious health risk? If the consumption of
fava beans is so disadvantageous, they
should be used less and/or be replaced by
other nutritionally equivalent legumes ... In¬
stead, fava cultivation and consumption have
been widespread in the Mediterranean region
since Neolithic times, suggesting that fava
consumption confers some adaptive advan¬
tage through its nutritional qualities, [and/or]
possible psycho-pharmacological effects ..."
In fact, it seems that the distribution of fava
bean cultivation and consumption corres¬
ponds closely with that of the enzyme de¬
ficiency described above and with the inci¬
dence of malaria in the Mediterranean region.
Since fava beans contain a number of sub¬
stances which are similar to those used in
antimalarial drugs, could it not be possible that
their consumption may confer some protec¬
tion against malaria?
For Katz and Schall, "The consumption of
fava beans may indeed confer an antimalarial
effect on G6PD normal individuals, similar to
antimalarial drugs. In some individuals ...,
fava consumption could prevent malaria,
while in others ... it could precipitate serious
disease and death. The continued use of fava
beans as an important staple crop in these
populations with high GdB- frequencies is
more understandable if positive health effects
are enjoyed by many, even though there are
clearly deleterious consequences for some
GdB- individuals."
ùi&ïtpm t j?
"Pythagoras and Music". Woodcut from a
late 1 5th-century illustrated book by a Ger¬
man musicologist, Michael Keinspeck.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Reflections on the potato
ACCORDING to the German wri¬
ter Günter Grass, the introduc¬
tion of the potato was a more
important event in the history of the Ger¬
man people than all the martial victories
of King Frederick the Great. Indeed,
Grass considers the potato a crucial fac¬
tor in the development of Europe. It was
the potato, he believes, that made possi¬
ble the industrialization of Europe and
the rise of the proletariat.
We can see what he means. The potato
is a highly nourishing food that is also
very cheap because it can be grown so
quickly and easily. The coming of this
"fast food" liberated the masses of
Europe from age-old hunger. It de¬
veloped a sturdier working class. It re¬
leased more and more people from farm
work and made them available for factory
labour.
The factories in turn led to the develop¬
ment of a strong labouring class that
democratized Europe, and to a science
and technology that made Western cul¬
ture supreme in the modern world.
It can be argued therefore that the
by Nick M. Joaquin
identity of the modern European as a
highly civilized, cultured and progressive
individual can be traced back, partly at
least, to the coming of the potato.
But now let us bring in a counter¬
argument. Let us imagine, say, a Euro¬
pean who is rabidly anti-potato because
the potato is not indigenous to Europe.
As this chauvinist argues, the potato
should never have been allowed to
change Europe because it, the potato, is
so foreign and exotic. By eating the pota¬
to, the European lost something of his
original nature, with the result that Euro¬
pean culture today is a deviation from a
pristine original. The true European is
the European before the introduction of
the potato.
But how can that uncorrupted original
be restored?
Our imaginary European chauvinist
demands the abolition of the potato.
At once, of course, we see the flaw in
his proposal. Abolishing the potato will
not restore European man to his pre-
potato condition. Why not? Because
from the potato have come such develop
ments as industrialization, democratiza¬
tion, modernization, and so forth. And
these developments have so radically
altered European man that he would still
remain what he has become even if he
stopped eating potatoes altogether.
In other words, potatoes are the cul¬
ture and history that cannot be cancelled
in a desire to recover a former innocence.
You may smile at my potato story,
which seems to make the potato like the
forbidden fruit in the Garden of Eden.
But I think that some such story would
illustrate the problem of nationalism to¬
day in my country, the Philippines and
not only in my country but also in most of
Asia, and Third World countries in
general. When Adam and Eve ate of the
apple, they lost innocence, they lost para¬
dise. And I would say that among the
peoples of the Orient, certainly among us
Filipinos, there is a feeling that, by tasting
of Western science and technology, we
lost innocence, we lost a primordial
paradise.
Our feelings towards Western culture
are therefore ambivalent. We are fascin-
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A family meal on Luzon Island, the Philip¬
pines
ated by it and we are also repelled. We
fear and resist it even as we hanker for it.
And though we crave to progress in the
Western manner, we wonder at the same
time if we should not rather go back
back to the culture we had before we
were "corrupted" by the West.
Not long ago I had dinner with a Filipi¬
no family whom I admire for their
nationalism, although they rather tend to
make a display of it. At this dinner, the
display consisted of a round grey stone
about the size of a baseball. This stone
it was actually a piece of rock salt was
passed around instead of salt because,
said my host, that was how the ancient
Filipinos salted their food. You pressed
the stone on your rice and fish, you
rubbed it against your meat, you soaked
it in your broth, to obtain the desired
saltiness.
I'm afraid they all looked down on me
when I said I'd rather have ordinary table
salt. That piece of rock salt reminded me
of the stones we used in the old days,
when bathing, to scrub our bodies with.
And I was putting no such stone into
anything I was going to eat! Still, I was
charmed by the sentiment behind the dis¬
play, the nationalist nostalgia. What
bothered me were the implications be¬
hind the sentiment.
In effect, my hosts were saying: "See
how truly Filipino we are. Instead of us¬
ing a saltcellar, which is foreign, we use a
salt stone, which is native." The implica¬
tion therefore is that the more we return
to what is native and the more we abolish
what is foreign, the more truly Filipino
we become.
This may be true but what I couldn't
help noticing then was the inconsistency.
Why pick ön the poor saltcellar? On the
table were fork and spoon, which are not
native; and beef and cabbage, which are
also not originally Filipino, and I knew
that the food had been prepared using the
sauté method, which is foreign, and
cooked in a saucepan or kettle, both also
foreign. To retain these, while abolishing
the saltcellar, is tantamount to saying that
the saltcellar is a bigger hindrance to
becoming truly Filipino than cabbages
and kettles.
Of course I know what question was
supposedly being answered at that dinner
table with the abolition of the saltcellar:
the question of identity.
Identity, I would say, is like the river in
philosophy. You remember the saying:
"You can never step into the same river
Needy children eating potatoes. Detail
from "St. Diego of Alcalá and the Poor" by
the Spanish painter Bartolomé Esteban
Murillo (1618-1682).
twice." The river has changed even as you
step into it. Nevertheless, the Sumida
River remains the Sumida River, though
from one moment to the next it is no
longer the same river.
This is the dynamic view of identity.
I'm afraid that we in the Orient or
anyway we Filipinos have a different
idea of identity, different because we re¬
gard identity as static: something given
once and for all, something to which
things happen but is itself never a hap¬
pening, never becoming. We ourselves
are, or were, a fixed original identity to
which certain things alien cultures,
alien histories have been added, layer
upon layer. Therefore, if such cultures
and histories are addition, identity is sub¬
traction. All we have to do is to remove
all those superimposed layers and we
shall end up with the true basic Filipino
identity.
That is the static view of identity.
But culture is not simple addition. Cul¬
ture is not a stew to which you can add
anything and it will still remain a stew.
Instead, culture is like those laboratory
experiments in physics where the mo¬
ment you add a new ingredient the orig¬
inal mixture becomes completely
transformed into something different.
When history added the saltcellar, the
fork and spoon, beef and cabbage to our
culture, the identity of the Filipino was so
completely transformed that there can be
no going back to a pristine original even if
we abolished the saltcellar, the fork and
spoon, and so on. Culture and history are
the flowing waters that make it impossi¬
ble to step into the same river of identity
twice.
NICK M. JOAQUIN is a Philippine novelist, jour¬
nalist and playwright. Among his published
works are The Woman who had Two Navels
(novel), Tropical Gothic (short stories) and a
volume of poetry, El Camino Real and Other
Rimes.
A cereal chronology
BC
10000 Jordan: einkorn and emmer wheat
and two-rowed barley
8000 France: wild grasses
7500 Japan: buckwheat, barley and
various wild cereals
6500 Romania: various grasses
6000 Crete: emmer wheat
Mexico: maize
Central Europe and Western
Hungary: large-seeded grasses
Mauritania: wild millet
Balkans: wild millet, einkorn and
emmer wheat
5000 Japan: millet
Southern Europe: einkorn wheat
Spain: tour varieties of wheat and
two of barley
4500 Northern China: millet then sorghum
4000 Denmark: varieties of small cereal
Egypt: wheat
Siberia: millet
Southern China: rice
3000 India: millet, rice
Babylonia: barley, millet, sesame,
emmer wheat
Africa: millet (from east to west)
Ethiopia: "great millet", barley and
wheat
2000 Central Europe: rye
Mauritania: cultivated millet
500 Persia: wheat
400 Italy/Greece: soft wheat then hard
wheat
300 Northern China: soft spring wheat
(from west to east)
Japan: rice
AD
100 Sudan: barley, sorghum
Europe: rye (from east to west) and
cultivated oats
Sahel-Chad: sorghum
1400 Italy: rice
1520 America: wheat
Europe: maize
1640 France: rice
c. 1800 Australia: wheat
Source: Histoire naturelle et morale de la nourriture by
Maguelonne Toussaint-Samat, Bordas, Paris, 1987.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Cereals and especially wheat have long been a staple of the human
diet. The diet of the Latin peoples, for Instance, was for centuries
based on the consumption of different forms of bread. An impor¬
tant crop since Antiquity, grain also had mythical associations in
many civilizations. (1) "Harvest crown" (1987) woven in traditional
style with winter wheat by the French artist Martyn Lévêque. (2)
Wood and stucco model of a granary from an ancient Egyptian
tomb (c. 2000 BC). (3) Kneading dough. Earthenware statuette
from Cyprus (2000-1600 BC). (4) Greek earthenware statuette
(525-500 BC) depicting bakers shaping oven-ready loaves.
Photo © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris. Louvre Museum
16
Photo © Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris. Louvre Museum
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
I-Bl
The ones
that get
away
FOR many years, the protein intake
of some Papua-New Guiñean
villagers was thought to be so low
as to be incompatible with adequate pro¬
tein equilibrium. Moreover, as an appa¬
rent paradox, these people were usually
well-built and muscular. The amount of
physical work they performed and their
levels of fitness were also high: indeed
their results in fitness tests put them well
above well-fed European populations.
A satisfactory explanation was difficult
to formulate until relatively recently,
when it became clear that protein de¬
ficiency was much less common through¬
out the world than had been supposed
and that the requirement of the human
body for protein is relatively modest. The
low protein intake of these New Gui-
neans was therefore unusual but not phy¬
siologically harmful.
However, if people are allowed access
to even a relatively restricted choice of
foodstuffs, they almost invariably seem
to make a choice which provides an in¬
take of protein which is equivalent to
between 10 to 14 per cent of the total
energy content of their diet, whatever the
particular foods that comprise that diet.
The New Guiñean population whom
we studied was therefore a very unusual
group since, although its members lived
on the coast and had easy access to the sea
and to fishing, they had an extraordi-
Two Melanesian cooking utensils from the
Sepik River valley In north-east New
Guinea: below, anthropomorphic earthen¬
ware bowl; below right, ladle made from a
coconut shell.
by John Durnin
The eating habits of these Papua-New
Guiñean villagers are a biological puzzle.
Although they have plenty of opportuni¬
ties to fish and hunt, they persist in follow¬
ing a very low-protein diet. Their physical
condition is superior to that of some "well-
fed" peoples.
narily low protein intake. They lived in a
large village of about 1 ,200 people, on the
edge of moderately open jungle. The
mainstay of their diet, grown in gardens
cleared from the secondary forest, was
taro (a root vegetable) and bananas, both
of which were grown in several varieties.
They also ate some nuts and fruit, and
consumed occasional small amounts of
animal protein from flying foxes (which
they shot with bows and arrows) and
opossum. Taro, bananas and nuts contri¬
buted about 75 per cent of the total ener¬
gy intake, and animal protein accounted
for less than 20 per cent of the total
protein in the diet.
The extraordinary feature of the vil¬
lagers' diet was that although they lived
near the coast, possessed canoes which
they used frequently for leisure activities
when they went to the beach, and had no
apparent taboos against eating fish, they
caught and ate an astonishingly small
quantity of fish. The amount of sea-food
in their diet was negligible although fish
was relatively plentiful in the sea, was the
object of leisure-time hunting, and in¬
deed was eaten when it was caught.
A coastal community
that turns its back on fish
5 The behaviour pattern of these New
»j Guiñean coastal people is at variance
© with the accepted norm. It would appear
that although their protein intake was
low, it was adequate in biological terms
and they had no "intrinsic", fun¬
damental, biological urge to supplement
it by increasing their protein intake from
animal sources.
This particular study, on a group of
people living in very simple circumstan¬
ces, seems to have revealed a biological
conundrum, in that the presence of
reasonably plentiful animal protein in a
situation where other sources of protein
were of inferior type and limited quan¬
tity, did not seem to have provided any
stimulus to increase the total intake of
protein to a "usual" level.
An adequate amount of protein in the
diet is regarded as important for renew¬
ing body tissues, for the constant manu¬
facture of enzymes and hormones, and
for replacing body losses in general.
From a psycho-social point of view it is
widely assumed that people prefer to eat
a diet containing around 10 to 14 per cent
of total energy in the form of protein. The
basis of many theories of what constitutes
a desirable diet depends upon this idea. If
it is not universally valid as would seem
to be the case from our studies in New
Guinea the implications are quite wide-
ranging.
JOHN DURNIN, British nutritionist, is professor
of physiology at the University of Glasgow. He
has carried out research on energy requirements
in a number of countries and has published over
a hundred scientific articles and texts on topics
such as energy metabolism.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Eating together
The emergence
of homo sapiens
as a convivial animal
- by Naomichi Ishige
EVEN the most delicious food lacks
savour if it is eaten in solitude. To
enjoy our meals we need a com¬
panion to sit at our table and share our
food with us. Of course, this does not
mean that the pleasures of the table
should be shared with just anyone. It is
better to eat alone than with a stranger.
But we all know people with whom we
are on close terms members of our
family, friends or colleagues, a group
which varies from country to country and
from person to person the people we
feel at ease with when we are at table. We
all belong to a social group through which
we relate to other people. One such
group consists of those who eat together,
and might be called the kyöshoku shüdan
or "conviviality group".
Eating together strengthens the group
and gives it a certain cohesion. A meal is
also a means of communication whereby
people assert their identity within the
group.
Those who share a meal also share
sensations. That is why, in many
societies, ritual celebrations are often
accompanied by feasting, which provides
an opportunity to create new bonds be¬
tween people and to strengthen those
bonds that already exist.
In the animal world, eating is a solitary
activity. A meal is neither a means of
communication nor an occasion to get
together. Mammals give milk to their
young, and birds bring their chicks food
as long as they stay in the nest. But that
can hardly be called conviviality. It is a
temporary relationship, for when the
young have reached maturity they will
feed alone. Carnivores which hunt in
packs sometimes gather around a good
catch and eat it together. But here too
there is no conviviality, despite
appearances.
On the other hand, studies have shown
that chimpanzees may beg their food
from other members of the troop, who
sometimes let them have part of a meal
composed mainly of plants but some
times of prey. If a chimpanzee catches a
large animal or gets hold of some fine
fruit, he is quite prepared to share his
precious trophy with any member of the
troop who pesters him for it. It is often
the female who presses the male to feed
her on his return from the hunt. The
behaviour of chimpanzees is in some
ways reminiscent of the division of labour
between man and woman in the early
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
(Table) manners makyth man
days of mankind, when the man went
hunting and the woman gathered the
fruits of the earth.
There is no reason, however, to think
that the sharing of food among chimpan¬
zees means that they have a preference
for certain members of their troop, espe¬
cially since they behave as individuals
when actually eating.
We can therefore conclude that con
viviality is an attribute peculiar to man,
and has been so since the emergence of
the human race.
Man has been defined as an animal
with the power of speech and the ability
to use tools, but it could also be said that
man is a convivial animal in the sense that
he likes to eat in company. And the basic
unit in which every human being likes to
share his rneal is the family.
"The basic unit in which every human
being likes to share his meal is the family."
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
"In many societies, ritual celebrations are
often accompanied by feasting, which pro¬
vides an opportunity to create new bonds
between people and to strengthen those
bonds that already exist." Left, a wedding
ceremony In the Japanese Shinto tradi¬
tion. The couple make their marriage vows
by exchanging a bowl of saki three times.
"The usefulness of home cooking is chal¬
lenged by ready-to-eat orpre-cooked food
products, or the increasingly popular
practice of eating out In fast food or self-
service restaurants." Below, automatic
vending machines dispense an instant
family snack.
According to the French anthropolog¬
ist Claude Lévi-Strauss, marriage is the
exchange of women between groups, and
women were the first currency in the
history of mankind. Food, however, was
another form of currency. We do not
know whether the family started with the
formation of a couple or whether the
sharing of food between man and woman
came before the couple this is the old
problem of which came first, the chicken
or the egg.
As soon as man stood upright he began
to hunt and learned to handle tools. Meat
began to assume an important place in
people's diet. In all hunting communities
today, the males do the hunting. Since
the dawn of mankind this activity must
have been left to the men because of their
greater physical strength.
The basic unit of society, the family,
was probably established when a man
began to share an animal he had caught
with one particular woman and her chil¬
dren. The family came into being when a
stable sexual relationship was begun be¬
tween the man and the woman, who were
linked by the sharing of food, and when
someone had to be chosen to bring up the
children born of their union.
The man left the dwelling-place to go
hunting and led his life in a wider orbit,
where he had what might be described as
a social life. The woman stayed in or near
the home. Her life was directed more
towards the family gathering fruit and
nuts, looking after the children and the
household. So their ways of life became
differentiated, and the work was divided
into male and female tasks. In almost all
societies the woman is expected to pre¬
pare the family's meals. But a man a
professional chef is often entrusted
with the preparation of meals eaten on
social occasions.
It is clear that man does not regard
eating as a solitary but as a profoundly
social activity. A meal is something to be
shared, not to be consumed in solitude.
This means that rules of conduct must be
established. Table manners are the codi¬
fication of these rules.
All societies have their own rules of
behaviour while eating, even those
societies which do not use tables or any
kind of cutlery whether chopsticks,
knives, forks or spoons where, for ex¬
ample, people eat with their fingers. Such
rules reflect the complex nature of each
culture; they are the outward sign of the
power either of the head of the family or
of religion. When a number of people eat
together, the main cause of disagreement
is the question of how the food is to be
shared. Obviously, if there are no rules
the strongest will prevail. This may be the
origin of table manners, the observance
of which had to be enforced by a familial
or religious authority as a means of keep¬
ing order. In any society, the appropria¬
tion of food which has been offered to
someone else, especially if that person is
about to eat it, is considered to be ex¬
tremely impolite. However, these rules
may be set aside when close relatives or
friends (parents and their children, or
couples) exchange food that has been
partly eaten.
Sex and food are the two principal
bonds that hold the family together. Sex¬
ual relations are reserved for husband
and wife, and are regarded as incestuous
if they occur outside the couple. But all
the members of a family are entitled to
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
share the food on the table, and sharing it
is designed to bring them closer together.
That is why in many cultures the family is
symbolized by the hearth and the oven
which are used in the preparation of food .
This symbol, however, is tending to
lose its meaning in highly industrialized
societies. The usefulness of home cook¬
ing is challenged by ready-to-eat or pre¬
cooked food products, or the increasingly
popular practice of eating out in fast food
or self-service restaurants.
Thus, in technologically advanced
societies, giant food and catering indus¬
tries constitute a challenge to the family
home. Meals have become more indi¬
vidualized. In days gone by, when the
home was both the unit of production and
of consumption in a self-sufficient eco¬
nomy, the individual could not decide
unilaterally when and what to eat. Now,
it matters less if some members of the
family are not present at meal-times.
They eat whenever and whatever they
wish. Does this mean that the very mean¬
ing of the family, based as it is upon the
sharing of food, is disappearing, and that
the human race will soon be eating as
individuals again, much as animals do?
The family has made a material and
economic contribution to the success of
industrialized societies, but it is doubtful
whether society can take its place in pro¬
viding the emotional relationships which
family members husband and wife, pa¬
rents and children establish between
themselves.
The members of a modern family
spend over half their time outside the
home, at work or at school, and for them
the family table is the main meeting
place, the opportunity to confirm mem
bership of the group. If people were to
stop eating together the family would
cease to exist.
The origins of the family can thus be
traced back to the sharing of meals. Mod¬
ern civilization has not yet found another
basic living unit, compatible with human
psychology, to take its place. The present
family system should thus be preserved,
even if it appears outdated, through the
institution of the common meal. For
although eating has become more of an
individual activity than it was in the past,
it seems unlikely that the kitchen or the
family table will cease to be part of our
homes in the near future .
NAOMICH1 ISHIGE, Japanese cultural anthro¬
pologist, teaches at Japan's National Museum of
Ethnology. He is the author of many published
works Including "An Investigation into Food and
Life" and "The Ethnology of Gluttony".
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The meal is the message
The language of Brazilian cuisine
by Roberto DaMatta
EVERYONE has to eat to live, but
each society defines in its own way
the significance of the act of
eating, and stipulates what should be con¬
sumed regularly and what must never be
eaten for fear of turning into an animal or
a monster.
Strict rules define the relationship be¬
tween the food consumed and the condi¬
tion of the person who consumes it. All
Brazilians know that they should fast be¬
fore taking communion, in order to main¬
tain the assumed state of purity compati¬
ble with the host which they receive into
their bodies. They behave very dif¬
ferently, however, when they entertain
their relations or friends at home for Sun¬
day lunch. On these occasions they care¬
fully choose the food that will help them
to define the social situation they wish to
create.
If I am invited to eat a feijoada, a
cozido, or apeixada, I expect to take part
in an informal ritual of meal-sharing in
which there will be a connection between
what is eaten, the way in which it is eaten,
and the people with whom it is eaten.
These dishes consist of a variety of ingre¬
dients (either meat or fish combined with
vegetables and flour) from which the
guests help themselves and make their
own mixture of the various items offered
on the table, Brazilian-style, establishing
a parallel between the act of eating and
the ideal of "mixing" socially those who
eat together.
Brazilians have strict rules for match-
Above, a food-vendor in a street of Salva¬
dor, capital of Bahia State (Brazil). Among
her wares are crab, pé de moleque (a kind
of nougat made from brown sugar, far
right) and fried bananas coated with flour.
ing a meal to those who eat it. I should
never think of inviting home the Gov¬
ernor of my State for a feijoada. A more
classic menu would be appropriate on
such an occasion and might include such
dishes as roast chicken with salad, or
meat cooked in a more cosmopolitan
style. However, there is nothing wrong in
having a cup of coffee or a snack with
strangers, but in this case you eat stand¬
ing up in a downtown snack-bar or bal-
cäo. This is a mode of eating in which the
utilitarian concept of "eating to live"
takes precedence over the moral or sym¬
bolic aspects of a meal. During a slap-up
meal with your friends, on the other
hand, Socrates' adage is forgotten and
instead of eating to live you live to eat.
In Brazilian cooking and hospitality a
great effort is made to combine the
"universal" aspects of food (such as its
nutritive and energy value, its capacity to
sustain the organism and its protein con¬
tent) with its symbolic characteristics,
since "man does not live by bread alone"
and the act of eating has great social
significance. All this is connected with
"totem commensality", as the French
anthropologist Claude Lévi-Strauss de¬
scribed a system in which people and
their mood, the surroundings, the food
and even the way of preparing the meal,
must all be in harmony.
This no doubt explains why in Brazil a
sharp distinction is made between the
concept of "food" and the concept of a
"meal". In the language of Brazilian
cuisine, these terms express a fun¬
damental semantic opposition between
the universal and the particular. Brazi¬
lians know that all edible substances are
"foods" but that not every food is neces¬
sarily a "meal". In transforming food into
a meal the preparation is of critical im¬
portance, but a degree of ceremony is
also required. When preparing a careful¬
ly organized and well-thought-out meal,
no Brazilian will be satisfied with simply
buying top-quality produce and then obe¬
diently following a cook-book recipe. He
will take great pains to prepare the ingre¬
dients and season them properly. Since
the quality of the meal, served copiously
and with care, expresses consideration
for the guests, it would be inconceivable
for a Brazilian to serve pre-cooked con¬
venience foods, as is now the practice in
Anglo-Saxon countries.
The meal is also a means of expressing
and asserting a national, regional or local
identity, or even the identity of a family
or an individual, depending on the con¬
text. Essentially, the act of eating crystal¬
lizes emotional states and social identi¬
ties. Outside my country I can use a re¬
gional dish to express my national iden¬
tity, but within Brazil I identify many
regions and even families through the
99
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
way in which they prepare and serve cer¬
tain foods. In a genuine system of "totem
meals" social identities can be expressed.
Every Brazilian knows that the people of
the Northeast are as fond of flour as mice
are of cheese; that tutu con linguiça (a
dish based on sausage and beans) is typic¬
al of Minas Gerais State; and that chur¬
rasco is the favourite dish of the gauchos
of the South.
And so, when speaking of Brazilian
cooking both the modes of eating and the
groups of people who are invited to share
certain kinds of food must be taken into
account. There is no doubt that in some
contexts meals acquire a personality of
their own, which explains the enormous
importance of meals as offerings in Brazi¬
lian traditional cults. Thus there are
foods associated with the sacred (or the
profane), with sickness (or health), with
virility or femininity, with childhood or
with maturity.
Sitting down at table is supposed to put
an end to disputes. Brazilians believe that
some dishes and some situations (the
Carnival, for instance) are, like some
women, irresistible, so that the very pre¬
sence of certain dishes should be enough
to create a degree of conviviality and
bring harmony to those who are assem¬
bled around the table.
But the symbolism of meals also pro¬
vides an opportunity to examine a highly
complex question which is usually over¬
looked in "anthropologies of eating"
the search for a rational explanation for
the culinary peculiarities that are found in
every society. Every society has dishes it
would almost be ready to die for. It is not
fortuitous that North American society
has an individualistic culinary model
according to which everyone tucks into a
Ritual offerings for a macumba ceremony
in Rio de Janeiro (Brazil).
solitary meal from a tray in front of a
newspaper or television set. There must
be some connection between the fast
food and junk food industries, self-ser¬
vice restaurants, and the values of self-
reliance and independence which under¬
pin society in countries such as the United
States.
But what is happening in countries like
Brazil where traditional cuisine exists
alongside modern, more individualized
patterns of food consumption? There is
no doubt that in these countries, the mod¬
ern practice of eating an individual food
product such as a hamburger, either
alone or with strangers, coexists with tra¬
ditional eating habits which reassert
themselves at banquets held in that
atmosphere of friendliness and convivial¬
ity to which people are still strongly
attached.
The Brazilian example reveals that
these two practices are not mutually
exclusive. On the contrary they can re¬
inforce each other; dual eating habits
seem to exist in societies of this kind. One
practice is an expression of "modernity",
while the other can provide a focus for
personal relationships. In Brazil there is,
indeed, an impersonal, individualized,
public cuisine, in contrast to traditional
home cooking which keeps people in
touch with the basic social relationships
that give form and meaning to life.
On the whole, however, the concept of
the meal as an act of sociability is insepa- .
rabie from family, friends and colleagues,
in other words from all close relation¬
ships. In this connection it is worth men¬
tioning that all Brazilian national dishes
such as feijoada, peixada, cozido, vatapá
(a dish based on manioc flour or rice with
fish or meat) and cararú (typical of Bahia
State), specifically combine solids with
liquids, meat with fish, and dried veg¬
etables with green vegetables.
In Brazilian cooking the utmost im¬
portance is attached to combining ingre¬
dients which in other countries are served
separately. Brazilians pay close attention
to the arrangement of the table and care¬
fully blend black beans with assorted
meats, cabbage, oranges, torrezno
(pieces of bacon) and white manioc flour,
all of which are eaten in a rather curious
manner, taking a little here and a little
there and mixing everything up in the
centre of one's plate.
Echoing the layout of the table, where
the main dish is surrounded by accom¬
panying dishes in a perfectly-defined
hierarchy, the centre of each plate is re¬
served for the principal item of food, as
though gradations were emphasized at all
levels. The ideal of Brazilian cooking is to
assemble appropriate dishes and guests
on an important occasion in a harmo¬
nious ceremony which is the main symbol
of sociability in Brazil.
Does this arrangement of the table
(where there is always a leading figure
and supporting actors), table manners
(the main dish is served first, then the
others) and even the method of eating,
have a direct correlation with what I
would call "intermediate meals", an
embodiment of the ties which for centur¬
ies have enabled so hierarchical a society
to absorb and harmonize values from
other cultures? It is similar to the effect
achieved by humbly and subtly blending
in the same dish black beans and white
manioc flour to form an intermediate
mass that is as delightful as a mulatto
skin.
ROBERTO DAMATTA, of Brazil, is professor of
social anthropology at Brazil's National Museum,
Rio de Janeiro. He has also taught and studied at
universities in the United States, the United King¬
dom and France. Among his published works are
A Divided World and Carnavais, Malandros e
Herois ("Carnivals, Bandits and Heroes").
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
China's health
/
MANY people appreciate the
subtle and delicious flavours of
Chinese food and drink, but
few are aware of the important role they
play in preventing illness, curing disease
and preserving health.
Over thousands of years the Chinese
people have learned that many foods
have a medicinal value. During the
period of the Longshan culture 4,000
years ago, our ancestors learned how to
make wine for drinking, for use as a
condiment, as a medicine for invigorating
the blood, nourishing the qi (vital ener¬
gy), warming the stomach, and keeping
out the cold. The lower part of the orig¬
inal Chinese character signifying doctor
and healing ( ^ ) contains the character
for wine ( jgjj = jjjf ), illustrating the point
that "food and medicine originate from
the same source; a food is also a
medicine".
Professional food doctors already ex¬
isted in China during the Zhou Dynasty
(c. 11th century-221 BC), and The Canon
of Medicine, the first work of Chinese
traditional medicine written in the Spring
and Autumn Period (770-476 BC) stated
that food as well as medicine should be
used in the treatment of disease. Bain
Que, an eminent doctor who lived during
the Warring States Period (475-221 BC),
used food treatment before prescribing
medicines. The Peaceful Holy Benevolent
Prescriptions, a work written during the
Sung Dynasty (960-1279) gave recipes for
the treatment of twenty-eight diseases
with instructions for the preparation of
appropriate foods. Porridges made with
different nutrients were prescribed for
different illnesses: black bean porridge
for oedema; almond porridge for coughs;
fish porridge for dysentery.
Over forty years' experience as a clinic¬
al dietician have taught me how success¬
ful food treatment can be. As a mother I
feel special concern for women during
childbirth, and pay great attention to the
restoration of their health after delivery.
I once looked after a fragile young
woman who weighed less than 50 kg be¬
fore she became pregnant. She was wor¬
ried that she would not be able to with¬
stand the strain of childbirth. I drew up
Left, preparation of fish as depicted by a
sculptor of the Han Dynasty (3rd century
BC). Right, making pasta by hand in mod¬
ern China.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
food tradition
by Li Ruifen
special menus for her in accordance with
Chinese traditional practice stewed hen
without soya sauce, eggs in glutinous rice
wine, millet porridge with brown sugar
and sesame, and other re (hot by nature)
foods. Within a few months she had re¬
covered, even though she breast-fed her
baby. In fact, she became much healthier
than before.
According to traditional Chinese
medical theory, the physical constitution
of a woman after childbirth is xu (weak),
han (cold by nature), and her internal
organs do not function normally. Such
patients should take either wen (warm by
nature) or re foods to obtain vital energy
and to restore the balance within the
body. On the other hand, pork, duck,
mung beans and other han foods are not
suitable for women after childbirth.
I have also advised hundreds of
mothers on a suitable diet for their
babies. One pale-looking premature
baby was so weak that it lacked even the
energy to suck. It is generally believed
that only in rare cases can such weak
babies survive. This particular baby was
placed under my care. First of all, I fed it
the thick liquid skimmed from rice por¬
ridge to provide it with the calories it
needed. (Doctors practising Chinese tra¬
ditional medicine assert that rice is sweet
and neutral by nature, and is easily
absorbed in the spleen and kidney. Li
Shizhen, a famous doctor of the Ming
Dynasty (1368-1644) said, "Skinny and
dark babies fed on the thick liquid from
rice porridge become plump and white
after a hundred days".)
Then I gradually added milk powder,
egg yolks, fish paste and bean soup to the
baby's diet to provide amino acids, and
liquids from vegetables and fruit as a
source of vitamins and minerals. The
baby was fed very small amounts at first,
and then gradually increasing quantities,
and from eating a single kind of food
progressed to eating many different
kinds. In less than a hundred days, the
baby was heavier than other babies of the
same age. When it was six months old, I
cut down on its starch intake to control its
weight and added more vegetables and
fruit to the diet. By the time the child was
one year old, it was healthy and lively. In
China, some mothers are always afraid
that their babies may be hungry and so
they overfeed them with protein-rich
foods. The results are unsatisfactory as
overfeeding harms the digestive system.
Old people often come to me for advice
on how to eat to prolong life, and I always
quote them a rule laid down by the re¬
nowned Doctor Sun Simiao of the T'ang
Dynasty (618-907) which recommends
"many small meals". This is good advice
for older people whose physical faculties
are gradually failing. They should take
light meals with little sugar, little salt, and
not much fat. I also advise them to eat
two or three snacks between their three
regular daily meals. At each meal, they
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
should stop eating before their stomachs
are full, and should include at least twen¬
ty and if possible between thirty and forty
different kinds of food in their daily diet
in order to obtain the many kinds of
nutrients they need.
Madame Zhang is an elderly writer
whose way of life I highly approve of.
Every day she eats some millet, dried
shredded corn, beans, peanuts or other
grain. A green leafy vegetable dish forms
part of every meal. One of her favourite
foods is bean curd. She does all she can to
maintain a balance between han and re
foods in her diet and a balance between
motion and rest in her daily activities. She
rises early and goes to bed early, and
often takes an outdoor stroll as well as
walking 7,000 paces around her rooms
each day. She also massages herself daily
and ^does some household chores.
Although she is in her eighties, Madame
Zhang is physically fit and mentally lucid
and is able to keep up with her writing.
I told her that the rate of metabolism is
slower for old people and that she should
add more protein to her diet. Instead of
dining on "four-legged animals" (cow,
pig, lamb, etc.), it was better to eat "two-
legged fowls" (chicken, duck or other
birds), "single-leg edible fungi"
(mushrooms) or "legless fish". Poultry
and fish have a high protein content, are
low in fats and their short fibres are easy
on the digestive system. Fungi are a rich
source of plant protein.
Once I made a special "eight-treasures
duck" for Madame Zhang. This is a high¬
ly nourishing festive dish with a low fat
content. I used protein-rich plants for the
stuffing xianggu mushrooms (which re¬
plenish vital energy, regulate blood cir
culation and reduce phlegm), lotus seeds
(which are credited with sedative prop¬
erties, strengthen the function of the
heart and reduce blood pressure) , sesame
(which nourishes and builds up the body
and moistens the intestines), Chinese
dates (which reinforce the spleen, nor¬
malize the functions of the stomach,
nourish vital energy and replenish body
fluids), chestnuts (which nourish the
spleen, invigorate the functions of the
stomach, reinforce the kidney and invigo¬
rate blood circulation), gingko seeds
(which warm the lungs, nourish vital
energy, check asthma and act as a detox-
icant) , peanuts (which enliven the spleen,
normalize the function of the stomach,
moisten the lungs, stop coughing), bam¬
boo shoots (which clear up internal heat,
reduce phlegm, regulate the stomach,
moisten the intestines) and glutinous
rice. Thus the combination of these foods
with duck (nourishing to the yin1 and an
eliminator of dampness) makes an excel¬
lent dish for the aged.
I usually follow our traditional method
of selecting appropriate foods which will
gradually restore the physical strength of
my patients, especially those who are cri¬
tically ill. The patient must first acquire
enough calories to maintain life, to im¬
prove resistance against disease and
strengthen the immune defence system in
order to increase the opportunities for
recovery.
Some years ago I treated a woman who
had undergone an operation for stomach
cancer. It was found that the cancer had
spread to all the lymph nodes. The doc¬
tors predicted that the patient had only
three months to live. At the time the
patient was undergoing chemotherapy
which seriously impaired her health. She
was constantly vomiting as a reaction to
the chemotherapy and lost between 2 and
3 kg after each course of treatment.
I decided not to make her eat in the
morning when she had her chemotherapy
treatment which caused her to vomit. But
after 4 o'clock in the afternoon when the
climax of the toxic effect of chemother¬
apy had passed, she was put on a special
diet which included her favourite foods.
For a patient in her condition, every
mouthful counted and so she was con¬
stantly fed until night. The next morning,
when chemotherapy continued, she was
given a slice of ginger to suck to prevent
vomiting and to warm the spleen and the
stomach. With such care, though the pa¬
tient underwent eight courses of che¬
motherapy treatment in over a year, she
gained more than 10 kg in weight. She
lived five years longer than predicted.
Chinese traditional medicine insists
that diet should vary according to the
individual. The human body needs a cer¬
tain amount of all kinds of food, but the
amount taken must be based on such
factors as age, physical constitution, diet¬
ary habit and climate. Over-eating or
starvation must be avoided to protect the
spleen and the stomach. By proper use of
food to build up the body, it will be
possible to give priority to the prevention
of disease.
According to Chinese traditional medi¬
cine, the physical constitution of the hu-
Regional traditions of Chinese cooking re¬
flect climate, customs and natural pro¬
duce. In Shanghai, below, and elsewhere
in eastern China, people are fond of hot,
spicy dishes while the people of western
China tend to prefer tart flavours.
"
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photos Dai Jiming © Xinhua News Agency, Beijing
Three specialities of traditional Chinese cuisine: above, shrimps,
strips ofmeatand vegetables are simmered in soup kept boiling in
a pot heated by burning charcoal; top right, "turnips in chicken
soup" accompanied by bamboo shoots and ham; right, "Hudie
Su", butterfly-shaped pastries.
man body is classified as yin, yang,2 xu,
han. Food materials are han, re, bu (re¬
plenishing) or xie (reducing) in nature,
and taste sweet, sour, bitter, salty or hot.
Selection of foods must be made accord¬
ing to the season and the climate and the
corresponding relation between them.
Doctors of Chinese traditional medicine
classify the four seasons as spring-warm,
summer-hot, autumn-dry, winter-cold
and believe that the physical condition of
a person undergoes corresponding
changes in the different seasons. Unless
appropriate changes are made in their
diet, people are likely to fall ill.
Since there is a release of vital energy
and the qi (vital energy) and blood tend
to rise to the surface in spring, people
should eat more vegetables and less fats
at this time of year. Hot, pungent foods
must be avoided. In summer, there is
usually a loss of appetite and a slackening
in the function of the digestive system.
Thus it is desirable to take tart foods and
other innately cold foods to facilitate the
removal of toxic heat within the body.
With the arrival of autumn and cool
weather, people regain their appetite. In
this season a reasonable amount of hot
and pungent foods serves to expel inter¬
nal residual summer heat. When winter
comes, the rate of metabolism rises and
thus more hot and pungent rich foods
may be included in the diet.
The styles of Chinese cooking have
been developed according to the geog¬
raphical location, customs and habits,
and the material resources of the diffe¬
rent parts of our country. The people of
the Sichuan Basin, for example, are fond
of peppery foods. This can be related to
the fact that they live in an area which is
damp all the year round. Hot peppery
foods help to remove dampness within
the body and thus restore its inner balan¬
ce. In our country, the southerners are
fond of sweet foods while the northerners
prefer salty fare; easterners favour hot
foods and westerners like tart flavours.
The reasons for this variation in the local
flavours may be found in differences of
climate, geographical characteristics and
material resources.
Chinese food treatment is based on the
hypothesis that "if there is genuine ener¬
gy within the body, diseases will not be
able to attack". Prevention is of primary
importance. Treatment after a person
falls ill comes next. Food treatment is too
complicated a subject to be expounded in
a short article, and I shall leave the last
word to a distinguished thirteenth-cen¬
tury doctor, Chen Zhi, who wrote that
"regardless of hundreds and thousands of
kinds of edible foods found on land and in
the sea, their five colours,3 five tastes and
their natures oihan re, buxie are inherent
in the yin yang and the five elements4" .
1. Yin the female or negative principle.
2. Yang the male or positive principle.
3. Five colours blue, red, yellow, white, black.
4. Five elements wood, fire, earth, metal and water
with their characteristic properties an ancient philo¬
sophical concept to explain the composition and phe¬
nomenon of the physical universe. Later used in tradi¬
tional medicine to expound the unity of the human body
and the natural world and the physiological and patholo¬
gical relationship between the internal organs.
LI RUIFEN, Chinese dietician, is deputy manag¬
ing director of the Beijing Gastronomy and Nutri¬
tion Research Association and deputy director of
the Beijing Nutrition Association.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Paradise lost
Bulimia, anorexia
UNTIL modern times, melancholy
was always regarded by Western
medicine as the worst enemy of a
"well-ordered", harmonious life, in
which the humours were perfectly bal¬
anced, especially in the blood, which was
held to be the very "food of life". It was
possible to govern the body and maintain
its balance by keeping a rein on desires,
by a wise and prudent administration of
the "treasure of life" on which the quality
and length of human existence depend.
The key to life was thought to lie in the
phenomenology of nutrition, in the
mysterious "faculties" and "virtues" of
food. Natural scientists of the old school
saw clearly that the body was responsible
for its actions to none but itself neither
to moral standards nor to religious laws.
The ancient Delphic precept "Know
thyself" was extended to cover know¬
ledge of the physical as well as the inner
life. Governance of the passions was
united to control over the body's hidden
drives and rhythms and over the world of
desires and needs. Self-knowledge meant
taking good care of oneself.
In this conception of the well-bal¬
anced, consciously ordered life, the only
limitation on the enjoyment of pleasures
was that prudent, carefully controlled ba
lance of the biological and physiological
functions which was the basis of physical
wisdom.
At the centre of this system of vigilant
self-regard was moderation in eating, or
dietetics, which became the absolute
arbiter of the fate of the body and the
harmony of the mind. The delicate ba¬
lance of the four humours, on which the
marvellous edifice of the human body
reposed, could be upset not only by foods
which were unsuited to the individual
"temperament" or by ignorance of the
"nature of foods", but also by incorrect
proportions and by an unreasonable ex¬
cess or insufficiency of certain foods.
If that balance was upset, the hell of the
disorder and corruption of the humours
opened up before the feet (and in the
blood) of the immoderate man who was
hungry or the exhausted man who had no
appetite. The moderate, balanced
nourishment of the body, which gov¬
erned the balance of the mind, was upset
by such extravagant forms of alimentary
deviationism. The destabilization of the
healthy diet caused irreparable harm to
the governance of the soul and psyche. It
is no accident that our forebears thought
that the paradise of delights was identical
with unspoiled, incorruptible Eden
( -
V
Walking Man (c. 1950), oil on paper by the
Swiss painter and sculptor Alberto
Giacometti (1901-1966).
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Too much
and too little
Detail from "The Fight between Carnival
and Lent", by the Flemish painter Pieter
Bruegel the Elder (c. 1525-1569).
and drug addiction
s
©
"Palaeolithic Venus" unearthed at Dolni
Vestonice (Czechoslovakia) Is made of a
mixture of clay and powdered bone (11.4
cm).
where the perfect moderation of the
humours before Adam's fall brought
the scourge of imbalance and immodera¬
tion into the world warded off both
sickness and evil. Paradoxically,
however, dreams of Eden or the dread of
falling into the infernal abyss provoked a
short circuit in the form of food neuroses
and upset the delicate system of the phy¬
siological order.
Even today, the dietary pattern and the
fragile mechanism of self-control can be
disturbed either by alienating fears or by
excessive, inordinate desires. When this
happens, compensatory or renunciatory
attitudes towards food are bound to be
produced.
The appetite for sweet, sugary things
that appeal to the senses, and the plea¬
sure of gormandizing, are greatly stimu¬
lated by the unconscious desire to recre¬
ate artificially the Eden-like happiness of
our dreams, and to recapture in some way
the delights of the honey, manna and
milk enjoyed by our remote ancestors.
The uncontrolled bulimia of high-calorie
diets is caused by the tormenting dream
of re-creation. It is due to a desire to
retrieve, through the consumption of res¬
torative, invigorating nutrients, a place in
paradise lost, to take refuge in the uncon-
by Piero Camporesi
taminated, contented womb of Mother
Earth, to counteract the squandering of
life during the daily round, and to ex¬
orcize the grim uncertainties of the future
by means of food.
For centuries, the vain hope of being
able to prevent entropy and the dissipa¬
tion of heat and energy has kept alive the
myth of the tonic, the fortifying cordial,
the miraculous elixir of youth which will
restore the life-force and bring back lost
happiness.
Anorexia, on the other hand, express¬
es a premature, much-feared descent into
an underworld of darkness and bitter¬
ness, hunger and thirst. It marks the de¬
feat of the libido by the death instincts
and a surrender to the decay of the flesh.
It is a symptom of an irresistible desire to
taste the perverse pleasures of the death
throes by deliberately and gradually anti¬
cipating the moment of decomposition.
In the allegory of the drama, the battle
between fat, jovial, cheerful, sanguine
Carnival and dismal, melancholy, emaci¬
ated Lent, symbolized the conflict be¬
tween the two great principles that gov¬
ern life (Dante's two "great powers") and
preside over the destiny of the world, the
two temptations, and the call of the nega¬
tive and the positive: the rift between
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
*'fc^
M-' -Jl
'% Ir 43
1 ^>jkil
©
"The Ham Lunch" (detall) by the French
painter Nicolas Lancret (1690-1743).
night and day, the stages of life which
alternate between the two opposite poles
of intensification and diminution of the
vital forces.
The dream of longevity, of returning to
the age of the patriarchs, the various
formulae and secrets for delaying the
onset of old age and lengthening the life¬
span, as well as the opposite temptation
to shorten life, to reject it by freeing
oneself from the primordial life instinct,
and to lighten the weight of the flesh once
and for all both these impulses are ex¬
pressed in a pathological appetite or the
lack of it, and quantified accordingly.
Both originate in the logic of lack and
absence, in yearning for lost happiness.
For some, happiness was to be recovered
at all costs; while for others, it was
irretrievable.
Scepticism about life, failure to achieve
fulfilment, a frustrating awareness of the
wretched limitations of the human con¬
dition, confined in both space and time
such are the motives behind the desper¬
ate search for alternative solutions. They
lead people to build dream factories for
themselves, producing artificial paradises
to push back the narrow confines of
biological necessity and put back the
clock of life, of history and of inevitable
social change.
In all ages and all cultures, man has felt
the need to recreate a time which is non-
temporal or timeless, outside history, and
to regain an Eden-like condition in a
different place, to invent a different
abode by going back to the prehistory of
the ego, to divide man's earthly lifetime
into an infinite number of ages and to
reconstruct it according to a new geomet¬
ry. This need has led to a long and drama¬
tic search for "mediators of oblivion",
ranging from food and drink that produce
euphoria, to tonics and cordials that bring
elation and conviviality, philtres and
other magic potions, and insidious hallu¬
cinogenic substances.
Ritual drugs (fungi, herbs, leaves)
have been used in some religious prac¬
tices to help people expand their con¬
sciousness, explore the realms of the un¬
seen world by embarking on imaginary
journeys, and make contact with the
celestial spirits that preside over the cos¬
mic order. (The fumes of the tobacco
used by Amerindian cultures and of the
incense used in the Christian liturgy are
like frail olfactory threads intended to
make communication easier and help
people to understand messages from the
unknowable.) These drugs have long
been a potent means of magical and reli¬
gious communication. Institutionalized
by the liturgy and ordered by the sacred
calendar, the hallucinogens used in
worship were deeply rooted in the collec¬
tive culture of the social group which used
them and kept them under control.
Society today is largely desacralized;
and now that the regulated use of drugs for
a specific purpose has been abandoned
their consumption has become a danger¬
ous experiment undertaken by individuals,
a desperate attempt at personal escape, an
act of negation that marks the disintegra¬
tion of the tribe and a lawless attempt to
escape from the body of society envisaged
as a grey, oppressive prison, without light,
colour or fragrance.
PIERO CAMPORESI, Italian cultural historian
and essayist, is professor of Italian literature at
the University of Bologna and visiting professor
at the Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences
Sociales in Paris. He has published a number of
works on the anthropology of literature and the
history of popular cultures, which have been
translated Into several languages.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Detail from "The Meal in the Monastery", a
fresco by the Italian painter Luca Slg-
norelli (c. 1445-1523). The fresco, which
depicts the life of St. Benedict, is In the
abbey of Monte Oliveto, near Siena.
Food shortages and food aid
EXCEPTIONAL climatic conditions, such as the widespread and persistent droughts that
have caused great hardship in sub-Saharan Africa in the last decade, are usually
accompanied by severe food shortages. The effects of these climatic hazards last longer
than those of any other natural catastrophes and include crop failures, risk of epidemics, and
large-scale migration from rural areas to better-fed towns and cities.
Other factors which have an Impact on food production and consumption include the current
world economic recession and the imbalances stemming from it higher rates of unemployment,
falling national income, increase in external debt which in many developing countries are
leading to deteriorating living conditions and malnutrition. In some regions the situation has been
made much worse by civil disorders or war.
At the end of 1985, the Global Information and Early Warning System of the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) reported that 1 1 countries were experienc¬
ing abnormal food shortages 6 in Africa, 4 in Asia and 1 in Central America. The situation had
improved considerably since 1984, when the total was 34 countries (25 in Africa, 6 in Asia, 2 in
Central America and 1 in South America), mainly because of better weather conditions and
increased food production in sub-Saharan Africa.
At the end of 1 985 FAO estimated that shipments of food aid in cereals had amounted to some
12.5 million tons in 1984-1985, 2.7 million tons more than the previous year. This significant
increase mainly reflected larger shipments to Africa. The estimate of commitments of food aid in
cereals for 1985-1986 was much lower, since increased rainfall had had a positive effect on
Africa's food aid needs.
Source: The State of Food and Agriculture 1985, FAO Report.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Food aid andfood habits
by Jeremy Shoham and Bruno Stainier
A cloud of locusts almost blots out the African sky.
DROUGHT, floods, locust plagues
and other disasters can dramati¬
cally dislocate families from their
normal environment. Households may
then be forced to rely on donations of
food to survive, and as a result changes in
food consumption habits may occur. A
number of questions have been raised
about food aid of this kind. Is it likely to
alter food habits? If it does, will such
changes be to the benefit or detriment of
individuals? How will such changes sub¬
sequently affect local and national econo¬
mies? Might they establish a dependence
on imports if local agriculture proves un¬
able to adapt to altered tastes?
Questions about the potential effects
of emergency food aid programmes are
particularly pertinent at this time, in view
of the possibility of increasingly frequent
food emergencies in many parts of
drought-prone and war-affected Africa.
The beneficiaries of emergency food aid
are likely to become increasingly depen¬
dent on the food ration they receive, and
in some cases may have to endure the
situation for several years. Most major
donors make every effort to supply foods
traditionally used by intended benefi¬
ciaries, but this may not always be possi¬
ble if such foods are not available among
the surplus food commodities stored in
donor countries. Local purchases may
also be problematic in food emergency
situations as food scarcity causes
inflation.
It is convenient to distinguish between
emergency programmes which bring food
aid to indigenous populations, and refu¬
gee feeding programmes (although refu¬
gee aid is also usually described in the
early stages as emergency aid). The dis¬
tinction may be important in its implica¬
tions for food habits, since emergency
programmes are generally of shorter
duration than refugee feeding pro¬
grammes and receive more traditionally
consumed foods, as donors have a greater
chance of finding suitable short-term
stocks.
Also, emergency food aid recipients
will not necessarily receive a full subsist¬
ence ration and may well continue to
consume some local foods, while refu¬
gees are likely to be totally dependent on
the ration for some time. While these
factors may make food habit changes less
likely among emergency programme re¬
cipients than among refugees, the fact
that such populations may be consider¬
ably larger than refugee populations sug¬
gests that if food habit changes did occur,
their effects on local agriculture would be
far more significant and diffusion to other
population groups more probable.
The World Food Programme (WFP)
supplies the bulk of refugee food aid.
Generally, at least three commodities are
provided: cereal (400 grams), either
maize, rice or wheat; oil or another fat
(30 grams); and a protein source such as
pulses or dry skimmed milk. In some
programmes WFP also provides fish,
meat or cheese. The total ration usually
supplies upwards of 1,800 kilocalories* a
head. However, in emergency rations the
WFP may not be the only major donor, so
that such rations are limited both in terms
of the number of commodities and quan¬
tities. The main commodity is a staple
food, cereal, associated if possible and if
necessary with fat. The average ration
provides about 1,400 kilocalories, and 40
grams of protein are recommended.
Many factors influence food habits,
and people never eat simply to satisfy
their physiological needs for various nut¬
rients. They eat to achieve satiety and
they eat foods with certain textures which
they like. Colours also play an important
role, as do cultural, social, economic and
demographic factors. Some of these fac¬
tors may dictate that certain foods are
prohibited, and in some situations a
radical change in food habits, externally
imposed, may amount to a symbolic
breaking with society. Hence, in the 1944
The prefix kilo is commonly omitted from the term
kilocalorie, and the "calories" counted by dieters are in
fact kilocalories.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Bengal famine, many rice-eating Benga¬
lis preferred to starve rather than eat
wheat flour provided by an aid pro¬
gramme.
The provision of food aid could affect
food habits in many ways. It may, for
example, cause a reduction in the price of
locally produced substitutes and a subse¬
quent fall in agricultural production in
response to the low price. Increased
quantities of food aid would then be re¬
quested to fill the resulting agricultural
deficit and the increased availability of
the food aid commodity would gradually
encourage altered food habits. In many
cases the change in food habits would
probably require little encouragement.
For example, the availability of wheat
and rice food aid allows rural as well as
urban consumers access to staples which
are considered by many to be better
foods. However, in spite of many studies,
particularly in India, there is no firm evi¬
dence that long-term food aid is a disin¬
centive to local agriculture.
In contrast there have been no studies
on the effect of bulk emergency food aid
on agricultural production and food
habits. Recent evidence from emergency
programmes in sub-Saharan Africa sug¬
gests that this may be an important omis¬
sion. In Sudan, for example, dramatic
price deflation of the staple grains millet
and sorghum in 1985 and 1986 closely
mirrored patterns of food aid flow. Prices
were actually lower than in 1982, in spite
of an annual inflation rate of 30 per cent.
Wages were also affected and labour
costs on two irrigation schemes tripled
over 1984 levels. Food aid appeared to be
acting as a work disincentive, with the
resulting labour scarcity causing wage in¬
flation. Many large farms around
Gedaref were reportedly left unhar-
vested in 1986 because of the squeezing of
agricultural profit margins. It seems
probable that as a result of this a signifi¬
cant proportion of Sudanese farmers sub¬
sequently cut back production of the nor¬
mal staple and changed their cropping
patterns to reduce future risks. Clearly,
this has implications for food habits.
Food aid may of course have a more
direct impact on food habits. Recipients
may react quickly to factors such as taste,
ease of preparation and the status
attached to certain donated foodstuffs.
Some reports on mother/child health,
food-for-work and school feeding pro¬
grammes have revealed the rapid accept¬
ance of new food items. In Sri Lanka a
previously untried weaning mixture in¬
troduced through mother/child health
clinics caught on so quickly that it stimu¬
lated local production of vegetables con¬
tained in the mixture to the point of self-
sufficiency within two years. There are
also examples of foodstuffs which have
proved unacceptable. For example, the
unfamiliarity, texture and odour of fish
protein concentrate have caused it to be
withdrawn from a number of program-
V
,
> 4 I J i
' * % . .
.- : sa*- *
i
%
mes. Other reports describe situations in
which new foods are tolerated rather than
wholeheartedly accepted or rejected, as
with sorghum-grits in Bangladesh.
Overall, it seems probable that a num¬
ber of factors militate against enduring or
widespread changes in food habits from
food aid provided by this type of project,
most of which are small-scale with limited
national coverage. In India, for example,
only 1.5 per cent of pre-school children
are reached by the mother/child health
programme. Most beneficiaries are only
attached to such projects for short or
A refugee family in an African camp. It is
Increasingly felt that measures to develop
sound nutrition habits should be an indis¬
pensable part of food aid and other relief
programmes.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
intermittent periods. World Food Prog¬
ramme mother/child health programmes
only encourage attendance for one to two
years, while food-for-work projects
attempt to offer employment at a time
when there is seasonal slack in labour
demand. Most projects also provide only
a proportion of food subsistence needs,
so that participants consume traditional
foods concurrently.
It might be expected that refugee feed¬
ing programmes would be more likely to
encourage changes in food habits, since
many of these programmes are long-term
and involve total dependence on food
aid. In Asia and Latin America,
however, refugee food aid items have
been the same as, or very similar to,
normally consumed foods. This contrasts
with Africa where, for example, the main
refugee food aid staple items have been
wheat" and maize, which have therefore
substituted for the more traditional sor¬
ghum, millet and teff used by the Somali
and Ethiopian peoples. While these don¬
ated staples have generally been accepted
in the camps, largely because of their
convenience and ease of preparation, it is
not clear whether long-term use of these
staples and other unfamiliar food items
will lead to an eventual change in food
habits, should these refugees return
home.
Some refugee settlements have been
allowed to cultivate areas of land, and
have therefore managed to grow a prop¬
ortion of their former staple. Other
camps have allowed refugees individual
or community gardens where traditional
spices, vegetables and other items are
grown. But even if refugees learn to grow
and process new staples and other foods
in the settlements, it may prove difficult
for them to do so on their return. Furth¬
ermore, as surveys have shown, agricul¬
turalists, who comprise the bulk of refu¬
gee populations, are notoriously con¬
servative with regard to certain food
habits. This is borne out to some extent
by the number of food aid items which
end up in local markets as refugees ex¬
change them for preferred traditional
foodstuffs.
On the other hand, many refugee
populations tend towards a younger than
normal age distribution (as vulnerable
older segments of the population may
have died in the period of hardship lead¬
ing up to the refugee exodus, or may have
been abandoned), and may therefore
adapt more readily to changed food cir¬
cumstances. Indeed, in many camps, chil¬
dren under five will have known no other
source of nutrition than refugee food aid.
At present it is impossible to say with
certainty whether food aid, and in particu¬
lar emergency and refugee aid, affects
long-term food habits. What is certain,
however, is that some changes in food
habits, such as greater use of appropriate
weaning foods, may be very desirable
while others such as those that may create
dependence on expensive imports, are
fions expand and as emergency pro¬
grammes recur with greater frequency in
those countries increasingly vulnerable to
food crises, the need to link food aid
distribution with educational and produc¬
tive activities must be recognized, in
order that relief operations of a certain
duration may be used as an opportunity
to protect and develop sound nutrition
habits.
JEREMY SHOHAM is a nutritionist anda consul¬
tant on food aid matters with FAO.
BRUNO STAINIER is headofthe Nutrition Prog¬
rammes Service of FAO, based in Rome.
Social Structures and Food Deficiency, a
book based on the proceedings of an interna¬
tional seminar organized by Unesco in 1985,
will be published later this year in English and
Spanish editions. (English edition published
by the Unesco Regional Office, Bangkok.)
£L 17
Food for all
THE world now has the means to attack
childhood malnutrition and disease on
a massive scale. The lives of over 4
million children have already been saved in
the last five years by countries which have
mobilized their resources in order to put
today's low-cost solutions into effect. But in¬
fections and undernourishment still kill
280,000 children every week.
Through its major programme IV, "The For¬
mulation and Application of Education Poli¬
cies", Unesco is contributing to the fight
against this situation by implementing, within
its sphere of competence, a series of activities
in the field of nutrition, notably through co¬
operation with other agencies of the United
Nations system and non-governmental orga¬
nizations concerned with nutrition and health
education.
Many individuals are also engaged in the
struggle against the tragic consequences of
famine and undernourishment. One of them is
the Greek poet and politician Yannis Cout-
socheras who, wishing to remedy a situation
which he considers to be unworthy of human¬
ity and also a major obstacle to world peace,
has for some years been advocating the prop¬
osition that free access to staple foodstuffs
should be recognized and practised as a basic
human right.
Since 1975, when, as a member of the
Parliamentary Assembly of the Council of
Europe, he proposed that "the basic food
products necessary to humanity should not be
subject to market forces and should be de¬
clared freely available to all", he has cham¬
pioned this ideal through speeches in the
Council of Europe, at Unesco and elsewhere,
and also through his writings (including his
trilogy White Hand, Black Hand). An interna¬
tional meeting is scheduled to take place later
this year to discuss ways of implementing his
proposal.
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A. ; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. ,111 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savi tri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
34
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed In France) - Dépôt légal : C1 Mai 1987
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de l'Unesco - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
For people who care about
the rest of the world . . .
A monthly magazine , each
issue usually devoted to a single
theme
Stimulating and informative
coverage from a wide range of
viewpoints
A window open on the world
A meeting-place for different
outlooks and cultures
A valuable source of ideas and
information on current issues
such as development, new
technologies, human rights and
the rights of peoples , and the
cultural heritage
A powerful instrument in the
service of international solidarity
and understanding
The only magazine in the world
published in 33 languages, with 4 (free) language editions in Braille.
Forthcoming issues include:
The world ofmedicine
The baroque
Underwater archaeology
Japan
Join or ask
your friends to
join our international
family of more
than 3 million readers
around the world.
Annual subscription
12 issues: 90 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 56a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian
Division, 326 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung
Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools
International, Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726, Bahrain. BARBADOS.
University o( the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64,
Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: Internationale
Drukkerij en Uitgeverij Keesing, Keesinglaan 2-20, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen.
CCP 000-001 2775-68. French edition and general Unesco publications agent:
Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internacional Ltda, Processing Dept., R
Peixoto Gomide 209, 01 409, Sao Paulo SP. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K1B 3W8. STORES: 61 Sparks
Street, Ottawa, 21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. SALES OFFICE: 7575 Trans Canada
Hwy. Ste. 305, St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1 V6. CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 68, Beijing.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L, Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1 ; Ve Smeckach
30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1 -27 Prague 1 (Permanent display) ; Zahranicni literatura, 1 1
Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag -Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tids-
sknftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box 128, SF-00100
Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641 Vantas 64. Rauti-
kirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1, 01641 Vantas 64. FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier; Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb. Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides Entreprises. P.O.
Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE John
Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box 10073. 541 10
Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore. 4 Nikis Street,
Athens T 126. Kostarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2 Hippocratous
Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-15, Lock Rd., Kowloon.
Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville
House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389,
Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bom¬
bay 400038; 1 7 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road,
Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001.
Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St., Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House. New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T.. Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1 188 Englab
Ave.. Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 131 58. P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498, Teheran.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Rd., Walkin-
stown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd..
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv 61006A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71
Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sanso-
ni, S.p.A.). Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence. JAPAN.
Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El Correo de la
Unesco, Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle, Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British
Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Pol*
chowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD
Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 14277-
Kilbirnie, Wellington; 130 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721, Christchurch; Alma
St., P.O. Box 857. Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1 1 04, Dunedin. NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of lie; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O;286.
NORWAY. Johan Grundl Tanum, P.O.B. 1 177 Sentrum - Oslo 1 ; Narvesen
A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad. N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No.
729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI
ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building,
Riyadh. SINGAPORE, Federal Publications (S) Re Ltd. Times Jurong, 2
Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas
Publications (Pty) Ltd.. Subscription Service, P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg.
Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaiks
Bookstore (Pty) Ltd., Libn Building, 268 Church Street, Pretoria 0001 . Central
News Agency Ltd., Group Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 613. Cape Town
8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner
Mawata. P.O.B. 244. Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box 2943. Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
FOrbundet. Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams AB. Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidskrift-
scentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -1 01 , 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zürich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6. 121 1,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne. Basle, Berne.
Vevey. Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment. University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.,
40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok;
Suksapan Panrt, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istikiâi Caddesi, No 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008, Nine Elms
Lane, London SW8 5DR. and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham. Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta
Ltd., 122 Kings Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan-
UNIPUB, Periodicals Department, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham, MD
20706 4391 . USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankan'eva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd.. P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The false banana tree The ensete (Ensete ventricosum), or "false banana tree" grows abundantly in
Ethiopia's Sidamo region. Paste made from a pulp extracted from the tree and
then fermented is shaped into small cakes which are cooked on metal or
earthenware hotplates and eaten with butter or vegetables. Although this tradi¬
tional food is eaten at almost every meal (each person consumes an average of
500 grams per day), studies carried out by Italy's National Institute of Nutrition
(Rome) have shown that its nutritive value is very low. Ensete consists largely of
carbohydrates and is almost totally lacking in proteins and fats. Photo shows a
villager preparing ensete paste according to the time-honoured method.
]]>
</page>
</document>
