<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074184eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
VOLUME'I-N. 11 PRICE : 10 Cents (U. S.), 6 Pence (U. K.), or 20 Francs (FRANCE). ,., DECEMBER 1949
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
'UNESCO COURIER-Page 2
THE Director-General of Unesco, M. Jaime Torres Bodet, made a special journey to Holland
last month to attend four important meetings and ceremonies there associated with the work
of Unesco.
The primary reason for his visit was the annual conference of the Netherlands National
Commission for co-operation with Unesco, held in the Peace Palace at The Hague on November 7.
M. Torres Bodet, who made the opening speech, paid tribute to Holland when he said :
"The intelligence of your people, as much as history and geography, has made of the Nether-
lands a meeting ground for many great cultures of the Western world. But you have given your
very personal impress to their alloy. Enriched by such contributions, whether they came singly
or at intervals, your primary concern has been to express alike in painting and in literature those
universal values which genius can discern in things in themselves most individualistic."
The Director-General also spoke at the Students'Congress on the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights held at Leyden University.
Other engagements in his busy three-days itinerary were the inauguration of a Unesco Infor-
mation and Documentation Centre at Amsterdam, set up by the Netherlands National Commission,
and the opening of a Unesco Exhibition in the Municipal Museum in the same city.
The smooth-running arrangement of this concentrated programme was largely due to the
initial work of Professor Kruyt, President of the Netherlands National Commission, a member
of his country's delegation to Unesco General Conference. Dr. Bender, Head of the Cultural
Relations Department of the Ministry of Education, and Dr. Van Peursen, Secretary of the National
Commission.
The hallmarks of the journey were those of enterprise and achievement, a typical example
being the Unesco Information and Documentation Centre, at264. Keizersgracht. in Amsterdam,
which the Director-General opened on November 7.
Another example of Unesco's policy of communication with the general public and students
in all Member States, the Centre is governed by a Council, under the chairmanship of Dr. Ph.
J. idenburg. Its creation owes much to the work of two Dutch student members of the Council.
MM. E. Alderse Baer and Jean Morreau.
Two large rooms had been set apart in the Amsterdam International Institute building to house
the display of Unesco's documents and publications. Workers at the centre gave their services
voluntarily, and a number of Amsterdam university students offered their help.
An Information and Documentation Centre of the kind now available to the Dutch public at
Amsterdam represents a bridge across which Unesco makes contact with the general pubic,
particularly young people-the men and women of to-morrow.
Here, students, workers and members of the liberal professions, can find the type of infor-
mation which will bring home to them the problems which will be solved if the world is to emerge
from its present state of international instability. Here, they can see how closely the work of
Unesco is associated with their own aspirations.
It is hoped that the results achieved by this experiment in the Netherlands will serve as a mode
for the setting up of centres by National Commissions in Unesco's other Member States.
When each Member State has its Unesco Centre working as a Unesco publicisiog unit
and clearing house for examining educational, scientific and cultural questions, the solution of
one of the fundamental problems met by the organization since its constitution will be in sight
TORRES BODET visited the Uni-
Me versity of Leyden. on November 6.
and was welcomed by the Rector
and Senate. In the great hall of the
University, he addressed faculty and
students, at the close of the Congress
convened by the Association of Dutch
Students for the study of the United
Nations and Federalism, with partic-
ular reference to the Universal Declara-
tion of Human Rights.
His address was listened to with
lively interest and warmly applauded.
Extracts from its text appear else-
where on this page.
The Dutch students movement has
been working hard, during the past
two years, exploring ways and means
of building a better world. For the
purpose of studying the United Na-
tions and Federalism, the Association
of Dutch Students has fomed five
sectors, each established in one of the
five principal universities of the
Netherlands : Amsterdam, Leyden.
Utrecht, Delft and Rotterdam.
Within these universities, members
of the Association are divided into
various groups for the study of each
individual question. Among the lead-
ing groups are those concerned with
teaching, legal problems, the United
Nations and Federalism, a special
group dealing with Federalism in Eu-
rope, another with Human Rights.
and finally. a group studying the eco-
nomic aspects of present day world
problems.
The Association, now, has a mem-
benhip of five hundred-about one
hundred from each university, of
which approximately 10 per cent are
girls. They co-operate enthusiastical-
ly in all the Association's activities.
The students who founded the move-
ment on 29 November 1947, numbered
twenty. Since then it has been conti-
nuously active, and has held three
congresses. One studied the subject
of Benelux in Amsterdam last year,
another, in Rotterdam, discussed the
Marshall Plan and, at Leyden. there
was a conference on the question of
Germany.
Present scope of the movement is
shown in the holding at the end of
August this year, due largely to the
efforts of the Association of Dutch
Students, of a world federalist con-
gress attended by no fewer than two
hundred and forty foreign delegates.
The Association also maintains contact
with the international movement
S. M. U. N. and with federalist youth
throughout the world.
President of last month's Congress
on the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights was Professor Rypperda, of the
Faculty of Law of Leyden. The Con-
gress was divided into four commis-
sions : philosophy, legal questions, eco-
nomic and social questions and edu-
cation.
The UNESCO COURIER is an international periodical devoted to the work
of UNESCO and to activities and developments throughout the world in edu-
cation. science and cuAure.
Until now some of our readers have been receiving free copies of our
periodical. In order to permit us to supply the many thousands of new readers
in almost every country in Use world we are undertaking a special drive tor
subscrihers.
A full year's subscription (12 issues) costs only $1. 00 US., or 5/-or 200
French Francs.
SUBSCRIBE NOW ! Tell your friends about the UNESCO COURIER and
get them to subscribe too.
Write to our agent in your country listed below, or directly to UNESCO
House, 19, avenue KIeber, Paris, 16', France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana S. A. Alsina 50C Buenos-Aires.
Australia : H. A. Goddart Ltd., 255a. George St., Sydney.
Belgium : Librairie encyclopedique. 7, rue du Luxembourg, Bruxelles IV.
Brazil : Livraria Aqir Editora, Ruo Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 329]. Rio-de-Janeiro.
Canada : Mr Victor P. Seary, Manager, The Ryerson Press, 299 Queen Street West,
Toronto.
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda 924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Mr Emilio Royo Martin. Carrera 9a, 1791, Bogota.''..
Cuba : La Casa Belga, Mr René de Smedt, O'Reilly, Havana.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6, Norregade, Copenhagen.
France : N. M. P. P., 111. Rue Reaumur, Paris (2').
Great Britain : H. M. Stationery Office : London : York House, Kingsway (Retail Counter
Service) : P. O. Box 569, London S. E. I. (Post orders).-Manchester 2 : 39-41 King
Street.-Edinburgh 2 : 13a Castle Street.-CardiH : I St Andrew's Crescent.-
Bristol I : Tower Lane.-Belfast : 8G Chichester Street.
Greece : Eleftheroudakis, Librairie Internationale, Athens.
India ; Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. Scindia House, New Delhi.
Italy : Messagerie Italiane, Via Lomazzo. 52, Milano...--.
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie Universelle. Avenue des Franglais, Beirut.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo Sierra 16, Mexico DF.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhofi, Aid Fondsadministratie, Lange Voorhout 9, The
Hague.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass 7, Oslo.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru. S. A. Girón de la Uni6n, Lima.
Portugal : Uniao Portuguesa de Imprensa, 198 Rue de S. Bento, 30 Esq. Lisbon.
Sweden : C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandet. Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
Switzerland : Librairie Payot. Lausanne.
United States of America : International Documents Service, Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York 27. N. Y.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperación Científica para la America Latina, Unesco. Avenida
Agraciada 1875, Montevideo.
Holland is the first country to be visited by the exhibition whose figures, graphs,
charts and coloured panels illustrate the scope and variety of Unesco's tasks
and survey the fields in which it works. This photo shows M. Jaime Torres Bodet.
Director-General of Unesco, (left) chatting with Her. Arnold J. d'Ailty. Burgomaster
01 Amsterdam. following the inauguration of the Unesco Exhibition in the Muni-
cipal Museum of Amsterdam.
no single people, no single race, that has
not made its contribution. This new code
is not proposed by us to the world, but
proposed by all men, wherever and when
ever they may have lived, to us."
The Right to Life
""W E must therefore regard this docu-ment as summing up the rich
heritage that the history of the
wor'td has bequeathed to us ; and it comes
at the end of a long series of tragedies.
Nature endowed us with no rights ; she
merely presented us with obstacles to be
overcome. Everything had to be fought
for, at the cost of countless sacrifices.
The very recognition of our idea of rights
had to be fought for. And the battle
had constantly to be resumed, for human
victories are very rarely final. Beneath
[he calm statement of those right. what
appeal, what cries assail our ears ! We
are free-that is Indeed the word-we
are free to discuss the right to vote ; but
can we ever forget the desperate effort
of those who actually won that right, only
to lose it and win again, so that at last
we ourselves can use it ?
The right to life is bequeathed to us
by millions of men who have been killed- and their memory is stlll young, for
tt was not long ago that none was assured
of his right to live. of h : s right to claim
respect for body and soul. We all know
by name some who died that we might
feel more certain of those rights.
That is where the real value of Human
Rights lies-not in legal traditions, nor
in high precepts, nor yet In philosophical
principles-but In the toil, suffering and
blood of men".
WAR HAUNTS PAST MEMORIES AND FUTURE
EXPECTATIONS
III the cours of a speech which he
Exhibition, in Amsterdam's Municipal
Bodet said :
"'T HE world we live in is a maze of dif-faculties. its organization cannot
keep pace with its growth, and com-
p : exity waxes more quickly than coher-
ence. Its population Increases every day.
but there Is no comparable Increase in
the areas of cultivable soil, or In the
number of classrooms. Epidemics, famine,
poverty, ignorance and oppression are
chrontc evils, so common, deep-rooted and
long-established that most of them have
come to be regarded as necessary condi-
tions of human existence. They are de-
plored, no doubt, but only as natural
calamities such as droughts or t : dal waves
are deplored. We do not feel responsible
for them. a, nd tt seems useless to try to
lessen their disastrous effects."
made at the opening of the Unesco
Museum, on November 7, M. Torres
"The case is otherwise with war. the
renewed menace of which the peoples have
been unable to ward off. It haunts their
memories of ths past and their expecta-
tions of the future. This time, man
cannot escape the fact that it is he who
manufactures the catastrophe that may
grind him to powder, that it is he who
is responsible for the misfortunes that will
overtake him in a new war, in which his
very life will be at stake. He is therefore
pressing the governments to do something
to stop war from recurring.
"One of the steps taken with this end
in view was. as you know, the creation
of Unesco. It was given by its founders
[he task of constructing the defences of
peace in the minds of men."
it. SI VIS PACEI.,
PARA CONSCIENTIAS
Addressing the annual conference of the Netherlands Sational Commission for
Unesco, held in the Peace Palace at The Hague, on november 7, M. Torres Bodet
declared :
"E XACTLY half a century ago the deci-sion to build this palace was taken
by the first Peace Conference held at
The Hague in 1899. The building was a
Joint endeavour shared in by all the
States represented at the Ccnference.
Yet. less than a year after the building's
formal opening, the First World War broke
out. To-day after yet another war In such
a short span, the Peace Palace has again
become the chief centre of world law.
"The basic principle which such a
centre seeks to prescribe for peace-'St
vis pacem, cole Justitlam'-is a grea :
advance on the traditional principle of
force. But when in this Palace we recall
those 50 years of history, it must lead us
to the thought that the law of Justice
may not be enough unless It postulates a
deeper agreement, the agreement of m1ncis
sincerely won to the cause of peace and
setting peace above all other Interests.
I am even tempted to add to-day :'Si
vis pacem, para conscientias.'That 1s
why Unesco exists."
DUTCH YOUTH WORK FOR
"ONE WORLD"OUTLOOK
"THE REAL VALUE OF
HUMAN RIGHTS"
"H OLLAND of the XVIlth Century wasnot merely the symbol of national
Independence. Much more. it was
the haven of the persecuted, a kind of
paradise of Intellectual and rellgious tole-
rance and freedom. It was In your coun-
try that Descartes and S. spinoza were able
to write their works, in an atmosphere of
security that no other land could offer.
It was your deep attachment to free
thought that was responsible for the
flourishing of the great universities that
attracted so many humanists, frcm Justus
Lipsius to Scaliger and Saumaise."
"The peoples are now closely"Interde-
pendent, but It would be a mistake to
regard their collaboration as a characte-
ristic of our age alone. Were it ; ; 0, I
should have had to seek elsewhere, and
at a far greater remove, for the origins
cf the great Declarations of Rights. That
loo. perhaps betokens one form of modern
progress : a certain knowledge, at once
historical and geographical, of man. In
any case. we all know to-day that the spi-
ritual conquests of humanity are not the
monopoly of any single person.
What is described as civilization is the
product of countless contributions, made
by every people and every culture. Jus-
tice. peace and freedom are often spoken
of as it they were abstract ideas ; and it
is then, perhaps, that no defenders can
be found for them. In fact. however.
these words represent something concrete.
for which men have tolled ; they represent
what man has up to now achieved. This
list of r : ghts which we have formally
drawn up is replete with history. The
freedoms we enjoy, the freedoms that
seem to us the most natural, we owe to
those who have gone before us. There is
On November 6, M. Torres Bodet, Director-General of Unesco, addressed th ?
closing session of a Dutch Students Congress, herd in the University of Leyden,
on the subject of Human Rights. Below, we publish extracts from his speech.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
carved Indian pipes from British Columbia.
(Musee de 1'Homme Collection. Paris.)
POPULAR Arts, a term which
includes not only the collective
N expressions of those civiliza-
tions having a conscious and
personal"Art", but also the
artistic expressions of so-called pri-
mitive cultures, are being abandoned
in many parts of the world today.
The seriousness of this decay and
neglect has been realized in many
countries where efforts are being made
to stimulate both their preservation
and development.
Unesco itself cannot afford to ignore
the danger threatening these folk
arts, in a world which seems to be
heading towards uniformity, and re-
cently, it called a meeting of experts
at Unesco House, to discuss what
contribution it could make to this
work of preservation and develop-
ment.
Unesco also has a special interest
in this question through one of its
main activities, fundamental educa-
tion, whose object is the raising of
living standards in economically
backward countries.
But the peoples who most need aid
are often those among whom the po-
pular arts continu9 to nourish, and
thus, the very success of a funda-
mental education project may en-
danger a whole artistic tradition,
bound up with customs and beliefs
that are doomed to disappear. In a
very large number of civilizations the
traditional arts are rapidily dying out,
for where industrialism has taken
firm root. standardized and cheap
output destroys craftsmanship.
With too many new needs to be sa-
tisfied, people are no longer able to
attach the same value as formerly to
articles whose manufacture calls for
patient workmanship. Big industry,
by removing men from their native
soil, has in its turn helped to destroy
their taste for objects and amuse-
ments characteristic of their place of
origin ; social levelling and the popu-
larization of culture have also greatly
contributed to the decay and neglect
of the popular arts.
Danger of Community
"Inferiority Complex"
if N far-oS countries where arts ofhigh quality survived, the decline
of popular arts inevitably resulted
from those countries coming into
contact with our own civilization.
These arts were the fruit of a specific
culture and met particular needs.
Where they were associated with reli-
gion, for example, they disappeared
along with belief in the ancient deities.
Modern techniques, which foreign
FOLK ARTS IN
THE PATH OF
CIVILIZATION
By Dr Alfred METRAUX
peoples have eagerly adopted, facili-
tate labour output, but have a disas-
trcus effect upon the beauty of form
and perfection of workmanship that
characterized the old-time products.
One of the commonest reasons for
the abandoning of folk arts is bound
up with the psychological factor,
commonly known as"the inferiority
complex". Many communities tend to
look upon the practice of traditional
popular arts as something derogatory
which ranks them with a backward or
barbarous people. On this point the
Expert Committee found much sup-
porting evidence. All over the world,
peoples who are beginning to absorb
the customs and practices of our civili-
zation, are rejecting aethestic expres-
sions, of which they were very proud a
few y) ears ago. One example is Haiti,
where Voodoo songs and dances are
banned by the educated classes and
condemmed as relics of barbarism.
These are disappearing as the working
class adopts the same ideas. Those
who wish to preserve an artistic tra-
dition must therefore try to dispel
this sense of inferiority and convince
those who still cultivate folk arts that
there are many forms of beauty. More-
over, they'must be shown that they
will be esteemed rather than despised
for maintaining their traditions.
Unfortunately, such appeals alone
are not enough to preserve the popu-
lar arts intact. As the living expres-
sions of cultures, they represent a
"living and changing reality". To
try to maintain them in their existing
state, when culture is changing
would be to resist the will of a com-
munity and therefore to condemn arts
to an artifical and sterile archaism.
An example of this very real danger
was the pressure brought to bear on
the Indian tribes in America to adhere
to ancient forms and motifs. This
led to a shoddy art, devoid of all vi-
gour or interest. When the condi-
tions which favoured the flowering of
A bronze head from Benin, capital of what
was once one of the most highly organized
states on the West African coast. The people
of Benin, who first had contact with
Europeans at the end of the l5th century.
possessed a culture rare among native races.
(Charles Ratton Collection, Paris.)
artistic creation disappear, it is fool-
ish to perpetuate its memory.
In this connection, the Committee
of Experts rightly emphasized"that
the attitude towards popular art must
not be that of the archaeologist
concerned with the preservation of the
past, but rather that of a sociologist
who records the changing forms of a
social state and tries to look into the
future".
Nevertheless, it would be a mistake
to abandon all interest in the fate of
the popular arts on the plea of avoi-
ding misguided interference. Facing
new conditions, the producers of
works of art need help. They work
for a different public nowadays and
have to satisfy different tastes. They
therefore need to be informed about
the demands of their new customers
and. to be protected against exploita-
tion. All too often, an art that was
once vigorous degenerates in pander-
ing to the bad taste of buyers. In
such cases the public must be made to
understand and appreciate other
forms than those to which they are
accustomed. There is an unfortunate
prejudice in favour of grading the
arts, and as a result they are auto-
matically esteemed according to the
category in which they are arbitrarily
placed.
Why Preserve
Folk Arts ?
SOME people may ask, what is thepractical value of assuring the
survival of folk arts which are
bound to go down before the
advance of industrialization ? Others
will question the possibility of Unesco
being able to do-anytliing to arrest
this movement.
There are several answers to these
Questions and objections. In the first
This carved stool is another example of the
popular arts which Hourished in Dahomey.
especially during the period of thehierarchical monarchy.
(Musee de 1'Homme Collection Paris.)
These carved heads from the Solomon Islands
reflect the influence of"secret societies,
which exist in all parts of Melanesia. Such
carvings have been developed from the masks
which are widely used in the rites of these
societies.
(Musee de I'Homme Collection, Paris.)
place the preservation of folk arts-
the. products of various cultures-
is needed in order to avoid the fright-
ening uniformity that is growing in
the world. The industrial civilization
of today with its great capacity for
expansion, gains ground every year,
and everywhere imposes identical
habits, needs and tastes. If there is
no reaction against this universal
standardization, the sources of fresh
inspiration will run dry, for cultures
are ren8wed by contact with and bor-
rowings from other cultures.
Economic Recovery of
Navaho Indians
N 0 culture, however complex andbrilliant, can embody all man's
potentialities. Each of them
specializes in one or more fields,
which it endeavours to bring to per-
fection. A single culture embracing
the whole universe would lose the be-
nefit of the diverse efforts which each
culture makes for its own needs.
There are other, though less impor-
tant, reasons for preserving the pour
lar arts. They express a communi-
ty's cultural personality, and are often
Statue of King Gezo of Dahomey, French
West Africa, who during his reign (1818-
1858) raised his kingdom to the height of its
power and prosperity, thus providing a
favourable stimulus for the native arts.
(Musee de 1'Homme Collection, Paris.)
a factor in social cohesion. Their
disappearance is responsible for much
of the weakness and demoralization
to be found in many native tribes.
Very often the practice of folk arts
has an economic aspect of some
importance. Many non-industrialized
peoples Ciilnnot afford the products
which would improve their living
conditions. The popular arts can
very directly contribute towards rais-
ing the standard of life in many com-
munities. The recent history of the
Navaho Indians is a good instance of
this factor. The revival and deve-
lopment of goldsmith's work and
weaving among these people helped to
restore their collapsing economic si-
tuation. Such a result, however, calls
for a careful study of the local or
foreign market possibilities, for all too
often, efforts and enthusiasm have
been raised, only to be eventually frus-
trated and disappointed.
What can Unesco do to preserve the
artistic inheritance of the many com-
munities whose ways of life are now
being transformed ? The International
Institute of Intellectual Co-operation
asked itself the same question and car-
ried out a large-scale enquiry into the
problem. The solution of the imme-
diate problem lies, of course, with
each country, but Unesco can do some-
thing to guide individual efforts. As a
start, it can compile a ( balance
sheet ? of existing popular arts in the
world. The fundamental educational
campaigns initiated by Unesco will
devote much attention to popular
artistic activities and will use them to
bring the message and purposes of
fundamental education to under-
privileged peoples.
Freedom of Artist
Primary Condition
THE Committee of Experts also
recommended that an appeal be
made to certain specialists in
this field to combine in book
form their respective studies of parti-
cular problems.
The Committee said in its report
that"regard for the present must be
accompanied by a wish to preserve the
memory of artistic expressions in pro-
cess of disappearance". Many com-
munities today despise their arts, but
the day will come when they will che-
rish their past and regret the loss of
these works. It is, therefore, the
duty of those who realize the value of
these traditions to save them.
One of the most striking aspects of
the meeting of international experts
was the unanimity with which they
condemmed all"dictatorship"in art.
Proclaiming the need for the freedom
of the artist, of whatever race or leveJ
of culture, the experts protested
against the tendency in some quarters
to give the arts too much protection.
since, in their opinion, a"style that
enjoys too much. outside protection
becomes sterile and disappears".
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-PAGE 4
What can Unesco do to help preserve the authentic
values of local cultures while at the same time
working for their integration into a world civiliza-
tion ? Seeking the answers to this important problem,
a committee of experts from ten countries met in
Unesco House, last month, and examined the results of
an enquiry undertaken by Unesco into the comparative
study of cultures.
From this enquiry, which began in 1948, Unesco received
over 80 replies from distinguished scholars and humanists
in all parts of the world.
In a combined report, issued at the close of its meeting,
the committee of experts laid special emphasis on the
situation of peoples who have recently acquired their
independence, such as the Philippines, India, Pakistan,
Burma and Israel, and of ee those that are rapidly moving
towards autonomy and self-government It.
The committee recommended that Unesco should
make available to these peoples the educational and
scientific techniques and materials they need."Unesco..
it added,"should also assist these peoples to study and
understand their own pasts, to preserve the monuments
õf their ancestral achievements, and to spread the know-
ledge of and respect for, their cultures among the peoples
of the world".
In the following article, M. Jean-Jacques Mayoux,
former Director of the Institute for Intellectual Co-ope-
ration, who has been carrying out Unesco's enquiry on
the inter-relation of cultures, describes the scope of this
work and the use which can be made of its results.
Tt-x no other field of its acti-
t vities is Unesco faced with
so many Inherent difficulties
as in that or culture.
On the one hand, it comes up
against cultural diversity, as
old as the world, reinforced by
the clan mentality and all the
herd instincts which still sur-
vive in us. Taking shape in
different languages and diffe-
rent attitudes of mind, this
diversity prevents communica-
tion, encourages misunderstand-
ings and delays friendly
contact between the peoples.
On the other hand, we see
the tremendous levelling and
standardizing forces of the
Western technical civilization,
which are at present penetrating
and destroying traditional and
more or less static civilizations
throughout the world, some of
which had remained at a very
primitive stage. Peoples who
had progressed little beyond
Homeric times now hear wire-
less broadcasts, see aeroplanes
passing overhead and tlnd the
machine age all about them.
They find, or think, themselves
despised, and begin to develop
a scorn of their own ways.
They become ashamed, and
quickly acquire an inferiority
complex.
Dressing Up
in Western Garb
As soon as possible, theytat, e on the veneer of
what others have taught
them to call civilization, and
indiscriminately discard their
own past, their textile crafts,
their dances and their arts-
the good with the bad. They
consider a future-OM)'West-
ern future-of radical change
to be their right, and we cannot
convince them how great are
the merits of the culture they
are losing. They would simple
think that we were trying to
prevent them from acquiring
what they lack.
Not only does this entail the
loss of a great store of irre-
placeable treasures for the
people concerned and for lm-
manity as a whole, but it also af-
fects international understand-
ing, which is certainly not en-
courage by the new state of
affairs. The loss or surrender
of an ancient culture-even
when the surrender is ( volun-
tarv and the result of a free
but ill-advised choice-entails,
at the very least, the upsetting
of a delicate balance, which
contains the seeds of many
future tensions.
How can an international
organization like Unesco inter-
vene in this field, in which
the pace of these dangerous
changes is steadily increasing ?
Unesco's Constitution requires
it to"preserve diversity", and
on a strict interpretation, that
would mean refraining from alI
interchange. The prestige of
the West is likelv to result in
the dressing up of the whole
world-physically, intellec-
tually and morally-in West-
ern garb, and it is not only our
love of the picturesque which
will suffer should thIs happen.
To refrain from action is not
a solution ; the real need and
the true internatio-
nal duty is to pre-
pare and contrite
exchanges in such a 1
way as to streng-
then insteall of des-
troy the I/Umblel'01',
rathel',.. humiliat-,
ed"cultures, mak-.
ing them richer and-
at the same tine 1
helping them to
enrich their neigh-
hours. woe have to
think, both of the
smallest parts and
of the world as a
whole. It is not iso-
lation, but co-ordi-
nation and relation
to the whole, that
provider the best
hope for-the different elements.
First of all, we may regard
what is most characteristic of
each civilization as a part of
the common heritage of
mankind, to be preserved in the
archives of knowledge even if,
for a time or for ever, it must
cease 10 be a part of daily
life. Countless teams of research
workers will then have to
labour, in every corner of the
world, to seek out what is past,
or note down what is. passing
- all the peoples'symbols of
expression, from carved stones
to the technical vocabularies of
today. The present division of
mankind into nations, with
unequal resources, not always
corresponding to their respon-
sibilities, does nothing to assist
the systematic and exhaustive
collection or the study of the
results.
In this field, at the moment,
Unesco is the harbinger of the
universal conscience of the
world of tomorrow, whose
heritage it is prepaying.
Already, L'nesco has been In
touch with students of Africa
and America and is soon 10
bring them into contact with
other students of the South Sea
Islands and the great Republics
of Asia, in order to decide, with
them, on the means of preserv-
ing the"treasure"of the
various civilizations.
Common Destiny
of all Peoples
THE preservation of thattreasure is a task for a
museum. a Museum which
must be everywhere, and
for which Unesco is already
collecting material of ever
sort-written documents, pho-
tographic archives, recordings-'and which must be circulated
widely among men. In addition
to scientific exhibits and those
tremendous monuments of
human endeavour \\1lose collec-
tion is urgently necessary,
provision must be made for'a
comprehensive and constl'uctivl'
display, In which there must
be no hesitation to emphasize
the common destiny of aU ages,
all peoples and all civilizations.
Unesco Is planning a Scientific
and Cu/. tural History of Mankind
for the express purpose of
tracing and bringing to light the
complex structures of that con-
tinuing process of creation, in
which all countries have taken
part, by which man has, in the
practical Held, transformed his
environment and the conditions
in which he lives and, in the
realm of the mind or the spirit,
his understanding of himse ! f
and of the universe.
Influence on
Western Culture
THERE are obvious instances :our science is of Arab aha
well as Greek origin,
many of our technical methods
are derive from China, our
agriculture owes much to the
American Indians, our religious
or philosophical thought is
imbued with the influences of
the East, and our arts have
drawn fresh inspiration from
contact with Africa. \\'e have
to investigate these instances
and restore their full signifi-
cance and value to these form
of culture. We have to be
acquainted with them in order
to recognize them.
BO/'rowing must no longer be
theft. If the West borrows its
form of expression from Negro
art, it must riot be ignorant of
the Negro civilization on which
those forms depend ; in this
way all the non-western peoples
will regain confidence, first of
all in others and then, and
above all, in themselves.
In this preliminary survey.
we have asked a few civiliza-
tions to tell us about them-
selves : India, Japan and Africa
(represented by its white
friends). \\'e have tried to add
to this picture of the older civi-
lization another of some new
and still developing cultures
which we believe we have found
in Latin America. Needless to
say, none of the writings we
have collected upsets the com-
monly accepted ideas, by show-
ing us an India, for pi !',
enjoying high technical deve-
lopment or a China concentrat-
ing on efficiency.
But I do not think anyone
will remain unaffected by such
works as Zavala's description of
Mexican civilization and the
way the country has reconciled
the'Indian elements with its
Spanish structure ;' Romero's
analysis of the state of philoso-
phy in Latin America and the
difficulty it has in rising above
the level of teaching ; the pic-
ture given by Atroya and Raju
of the essential humanity of the
Indian civUzation ; Shih Hsiang
Chen's absorbing analysis of the
Chinese idea of literature or the
painful complexes revealed by
our Indonesian and Japanese
contributors.
Victims of History
ir SHALL stop at this last ques-tion of complexes. Among
civilizations, there are some
which are constantly denied
appreciation and finally aban-
don their own values. There
are victims of tnstory, and there
are those who are"never
understood". There have been
misunderstandings between
Islam and the West, between
Islam and India, between the
West and the East as a whole,
between those who call them-
selves"civilized"and those
who are described as"primi-
tive".
In asking for these subjective
accounts of cultures, we have
tried to bring to light both
hopes and dangers. It is pro-
bable that a collection of the
best of these essays, presenting
the most diverse of these cul-
tures side by side will be pu-
blished. Experts from ten
countries in four continents
meeting in Unesco House have
not discussed academic pro-
blems, but what form of action
should be faken throughout the
world, either by Unesco, 01'
under it guidance, for the fur-
tllerance of the priceless variety
of cultures and the vital unity
of civilization.
A"BIBLE"FOR PUBLISHERS,
WRITERS AND TRANSLATORS
THE International Bibliography of Trans-
lotions, which Unesco has prepared for
early publication, is, in its quiet way, one
of the most curious and interesting
compilations which the Department of Cultuml
Affairs has produced so far. Thirty countries.
covering nearly every part of the globe, are
represented in this report on the status of
translations covertng the year 1948. and among
the 8, 500 single items included can be found
documents translated into at least twenty tong-
ues from more than 55 languages.
What are these documents, exactly ? They
cover writings on the whole range of human
activity from midwifery (a translation into
Swahlli from Luganda) to the Tibetan Book of
the Dead (from Tibetan, via English, into Ger-
man). There are books on children and for
children, the rarest classics from ancient India,
Greece and the Arabic lands, phllosophical and
religious works of all ages, histories and mathe-
matical treatises, biographies and books of
travel, political manifestos-'books from many
lands and from all times up to the best-sellers
of yesterday.
From Arabian Nights
to Dostoievski
IN the compilation of the Index Translationum1 Unesco has had the assistance of librarians,
"publishers, educational institutions and
individuals in many parts of the world. The
result is a cross-section of those books, great
and small, which have been able, through
translation, to retell a tale, or ! reState a
scientific truth or raise points stlll valid
for discussion and argument, beyond the
boundaries of thetr original linguistic area.
The Arabian Nights, the fairy-tales of Hans
Christian Andersen and the Brothers Grimm,
the novels of Dostoïevski and Dickens, the
sonnets of LouIse ! Labe and of Michelangelo
can stir the minds of readers in regions far
removed from those where they first came into
being.
For a number of reasons it is important that
such a report be made regularly and over a
wide area. In the first place, the United Na-
tions, both in its General Assembly and in
its Economic and Social Council, has expressed
its strong belief in translations as a valuable
force for understanding among different per-
pIes ; whether among peoples of different
nationalities, or for those speaking different
languages within one nation's boundaries.
Unesco, which was given responsibility for
encouraging translations, has already taken
steps to increase both the quality and the
quantity of translations, so that it will even-
tually be possible to see where serious gaps
exist and what efforts can be made to fill such
gaps. With the aid Of the Index Translationum,
publishers will be able to gain an insight into
the kinds of books which are being translated
in various parts of the world, translators can
T
gauge the potential field of their endeavours,
and writers will see where their books are
finding readers beyond their own frontiers.
China, India, Soviet Union
still Isslng
HE Idea of an International Bibliographyt of Translations was nrst carried into
effect is the days of the League of Na-
tions'Institute of Intellectual Co-operation.
when, from 1932 to 1940, a quarterly bulletin
at first listed the translations published In
six countries and by the time its last issue
appeared, in fourteen countries. Unesco has
had the advantage of being able to reach a
greater number of countries, through its Mem-
ber-States and their National Commissions.
and has also been able to cover, more or less
completely, the published translations of seve-
ral countries not members of Unesco.
Thirty countries (of which four reported
that no translations had been published in
1948) represent, nevertheless, only a small
proportion of all those which are actively
engaged IU making translations and distributing
them within their boundaries. Three of the
largest countries In the world, with vastly
complicated problems of translation, and to
the best of our knowledge, with highly deve-
loped programmes for solving those problems.
are not yet represented In the Index : these
three are China, India and the Soviet Unlom.
In its form, the Index Translationum com-
prises, In reality, four Indexes : the main body
of the work Is divided first into the national
brbllographies of the different countries repre-
sented. Each country's bibliography Is divided
according to the ten general categories of the
Universal Decimal Classification system, a
useful aid to one who Is searching for works
In a specific field, since the works In each
category are arranged by alphabetical order of
authors. At the end will be found cross-
Indexes of authors, translators and publishers
In alphabetical order.
It is Unesoo's goal to be able to Include for
each work listed, complete information concern-
ing the published translation and In addition,
to give full details of the original edition. In
a few cases, the original edition has been
fully described, but In all too many cases
there has been no mea, ns of supplylltlg all the
desired information.
It Is expected that before the end of 1949
the first volume at the Index Translationum
will have made Its appearance-the first
volume, that is. of the new series-and work
has already begun on the second volume.
which will record the translations published
In 1949. There are already signs that the
second issue will be more comprehensive than
the first, and It cannot but benefit from a
wider geographical coverage and from the
example of the initial volume.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
WAR BROKE FABRIC BUT NOT
THE SPIRIT OF RENNES UNIVERSITY
SINCE August 1944, when Rennes University
was severely damaged during the liberation
of Britanny, its faculty and students have
been living up to the University's motto
"Heaven Helps Those Who Help Themselves".
The only institution of its kind in the region,
Rennes University serves seven north-west
departments of France, comprising an area as
large as Belgium. It was therefore a severe blow
to French scientific education when the Nazis
blew up a bridge facing its modern science fa-
culty, devastating the physics, chemistry, zoo-
logy and botany sections.
Since then, the students have been working
under almost unbelievable conditions : carrying
out chemistry and physics experiments in cellars
and former air-raid shelters and pursuing medical
studies in the open air, or, when it rained, in the
central heating boiler house for that, at least,
had a roof.
Although reconstruction measures provided the
place for them to work, the students and profes-
sors still needed the means, in the form of
scientific equipment. Now, through a Unesco
grant of $ 7, 000, the Faculty of Science at Rennes
is being equipped to carry on its teaching and
research activities.
Evidence of Mankind's Solidarity
T HIS grant brings tc almost 895. 000 the amountwhich Unesco has spent to help in equipping
scientific laboratories in eleven countries,
since the beginning of 1949.
It was to pay tribute to Rennes and, at the
same time, to all other universities that suffered
during the war, that M. Torres Bodet, Director-
General of Unesco, visited the University, on
November 19th, to attend the formal re-opening
of the academic year.
At the re-opening ceremony, held in the
Rennes City Hall, M. Torres Bodet told the
faculty and students :"The international conflicts
of the 20th century have cruelly affected
the academic world. In many countries intellec-
tual leaders have been persecuted and educational
systems deliberately destroyed. The aggressor
seemed to be trying to enslave the nations by
reducing them to the status of forced labour
camps for illiterates. Knowledge and freedom
go hand in hand and Universities, particularly in
France, proved that afresh by becoming centres
of resistance.
"I am filled with admiration for many countries
which, like your own, have been impoverished by
war and enemy occupation and, set free, have
undertaken courageously and confidently the
rebuilding of their ruins", he added.
Unesco was doing all it could to help in this
By
Gerda FRIEDMANN
(UNESCO NATURAL SCIENCES DEPT.)
reconstruction and had spent 1, 533, 000 dollars an
the work in the three years from 1947 to 1949 ;
that represented 7 % of its total budget.
"What does all this represent ?" asked M. Tor-
res Bodet."These gilts are, in fact more than
material aid and cannot be measured solely in
terms of dollars or of equipment supplied. They
are evidence that the intellectual and moral soli-
darity of mankind has not been finally des-
troyed, and that it is still possible, by restoring
Lt to conscious activity to reassemble the broken
fragments.. Our modest contribution to repairing
war damage is only a single stage in the building
of a new world."
M. Torres Bodet referred to another vital step
in the building of a new world when he
spoke of the United Nations Technical Assistance
Plan"for countries whose progress has been
retarded because of historical or geographical
reasons".
"The unanimous vote on November 16, by the
General Assembly of the United Nations on the
scheme worked out by the Economic and Social
Council, in collaboration with the Specialized
Agencies, is in many respects one of the outstand-
ing events of our century,"he said."It is a long
time since a proposal of such far-reaching impor-
tance has been given the unanimous support of
the United Nations.
"The Plan is based on three essential principles.
Assistance will be granted only at the request of
interested governments, to the extent and under
conditions to be laid down by themselves.
Main Purpose of U. N. Aid Plan
"Its main object will be to help the under-pri-
vileged countries applying for assistance to
'strengthen their national economies through the
development of their industries and agriculture,
with a view to promoting their economic and
political independence in the spirit, of the Char-
ter of the United Nations, and to ensure the
attainment of higher levels of economic and so-'
cial welfare for their entire populations'".
"Unesco,"said M. Torres Bodet,.'is helping to
Fonfirm the unity of reason and the identity of
the laws governing the life of the mind, by taking
part in this scheme of the United Nations, after
preparation, and by the practical implementation
of its own programme".
"It will be realized,", said M. Torres Bodet,
"that reconstruction is not a finite process and that
it naturally makes way for construction, through
which we hope, a better world will emerge bound
together by closer feelings of brotherhood."
"Such is the fabric of intellectual relations and
material services which Unesco is patiently
weaving from country to country... so that every
individual and every community may grasp the
true unity of the world in which they live."
SPREADING SCIENCE THROUGHOUT THE WORLD
China's Enginccr
Studcnts Get Ncw
Equipment
TMec) <do/Me ! <'a)', <) ! Me
AT Ihe end of the war, in theFar East, the United Nations
Relief and Rehabilitation
Administration (UNRRA) initiated
a programme for helping engineer-
ing education in China, small
indeed in com p a r i son with
UNRRA's other undertakings, but
large in relation to funds nor-
mally available for providing
emgineering college equipment in
underdeveloped countries.
The programme involved she
purchase u {$. 2, 000, 000 worth of
machinery amounting to some
720 tons, for engineering teaching
and its dcspatch to China. It was
at Unesco's Mexico City General
Conference in 1947 that the
requcst came from UNRRA for
Unesco to complete the pro-
gramme, at which. time about
85 per cent of the equipment had
already reached China.
Allocations were made to about
35 Chinese Universities and tech-
nical colleges, including somme
very well-known ones, such as
Tangshan College, and other in-
stitutions depending on the Minis-
try o {Communications, which
have trained several generations
of Chinese engineers. The average
value of the equipment allotted to
each college was some $70, 000,
and, in many cases, this amount-
ed to three or four times the
FIELD
SCIENCE
OFFICE
IN ISTANBUL
11 branch office of the
Unesco Middle-EastScience Co-operation Of
fice in Cairo is to be opened
at Istanbul, Turkey, this
month.
The regional scientific ad-
viser is Professor Ratip Ber-
ker, Istanbul Teknik Universi-
tesi. Gumussuyu, Istanbul.
Since Unesco opened its
Middle-East Science Co-opera-
tion Oiiice. many enquiries
have been coming in from
Turkey. In suture, these will
be handled directly by the
new branch office.
value of the total equipement pre-
viollsly in Use.
During 1\H8, the work of dis-
tribution went ahead, the expenses
of Installation being met from
other UNRRA funds remaining in
tile country. By August 1948,
370 tons had been despatched to
the recipient colleges, and by
February 1949 only 130 tonsremained for distribution.
The politically disturbed stale
of the country then began 10
interfere with the programme, and
some 80 tons have been stored
temporily in Taiwan (Formosa).
But these quantities amount to
less than 15 per cent of the
whole. within recent weeks, till'
remainder of the equipment has
been installed.
winged Victory Award
for Science writers
CLEAR and effective sciencewriting will develop a
constantly Increasing public
which will know and understand
not only current advances In
science but will habitually share
In the intellectual integrities and
habits of mind of scientists.
Only out of a population having
such qualities can-a successful
and enduring civilization be
developed."
This was how Dr. Moulton
defined the Important task of
science writers, when in 1946, he
announced the establishment of
the George Westinghouse Science
Writing Awards, described In the
Unesco report."Science Writing
Awards In the USA", by Borge
Michelsen.
Now, It is announced that the
Americans have instituted a new
prize for science writing-two
Awards for journalism In the
field of medical research and
public health established by the
Albert and Mary Lasker Foun-
dation. The purpose of these
Awards is to encourage the writ-
ing and publication In general
newspapers and magazines of
outstanding articles on the
Improvement of public health and
the prolongation of life, espe-
cially through medical research
and public health programmes.
The Awards will be $500 each
and a statuette of the Winged
Victory of Samothrace.
The Lasker Awards for 1949
will be administered. by the Nie-
man Foundation for Journalism,
44 Holyoke House, Cambridge 38.
Massachusetts, and the entries
will be judged by a jury of emi-
nent journalists, doctors and
non-professional persons.
Uneseo Science Essay
Contest in Philippines
A Pllilippines national essaycontest under the sponsor
ship of Unesco, has been
started by Dr. William J. Ellis,
Director of Unesco's Field Co-
operation Office in Manila.
The title of the essay is "How,
Which came first, the chicken or the egg ? This giant hen shown at
agricultural exhibitions in the United States cannot answer this time-
honoured question, but it does explain how it lays eggs.
By means of a recording during its egg-laying demonstrations, it also tells
how much grain, mash. greens and mineral salts it requires.
Throughout the world, young
people are becoming more and
more interested in accurate scien-
tific knowledge, a desire that is
fostered aid met by the Division
for the Popularisation 01 Science 01
the Natural Sciences Department 01
Unesco. But it is not only the teen-
agers who express this great
interest :"It is my experience that
children are more interested in
science than anything else", says
Miss Margaret de Woll Tulloch.
Director 01 the Children's Museum
of Brooklyn, where science club
work for children starts at the age
of six. At this Museum, lectures
are given at the pre-school and
early-school hour every Saturday
morning. The picture shows three
young visitors to the US Naval
Observatory in Washington D. C.,
with one eagerly looking through
the 26''refractor. This is typical of
a scientific curiosity that is beco-
ming increasingly apparent, not
least in the USA, England and
France, but also in the under-deve-
loped areas.
Information about Unesco's Popu-
larisation of Science programme
may be obtained by writing to
Unesco House in Paris.
in your opinion, can science and
its application assist in the deve-
lopment of tile philippines ?"
Entrants, who must be undergra-
duate members of any university
or school within the Philippines,
are advised to take into account
the over-all needs of their coun-
try and then to assess how best
the resources of science and tech-
nology can be used.
There are to be too prizes, the
first o/f00 pesos and the second
o/50 pesos. This money is to be
"sed for the purchase of books.
Growth of
Science Clubs
in India
"I hold the unconquerablebelief than Science and
Peace will triumph over
Ignorance and War, that Nations
will come together-not to des-
troy-but to construct-and
that the future belongs to those
who accomplish most for huma-
nity."
Science Clubs in India have
taken these famous words of
Louis Pasteur as their motto.
Since 1944, when there was only
one Indian Science Club, the
movement has been steadily grow-
ing, helped through the interest
shown by Ministers of Education
in various provinces.
By the end of 1945. 50 Science
Clubs had been formed In Indian
High Schools, and by 1947 they
numbered-310. In 1948. there
were 340. and today it is estimated
that there are about 400.
Are there any other countries
(apart from the USA, where there
are 16. 000 Science Clubs, at the
present time) with as many
Science Clubs ?
"
U. N. DAY
The United Nations Associa-
tion of Great Britain (UNA)
distributed over 250. 000 pam-
phlets, posters, leaflets. Rims,
film-strips and other material
for the celebration of United
Nations Day in Britain, on
October 24.
UNA also held several hund-
red meetings, discussions and
film shows and obtained mes-
sages from the Prime Minister,
and from Mr Churchill and
Lady Violet Bonham Carter
which were widely publicized.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 6
MYSO
FO R AN
this trend has led to a desire and will to assist the
cover themselves, the main action being centred rot
of Adult and Fundamental Education.
Now, all over Asia, enthusiastic and devote !'"vôr
with limited means, improvised techniques, and, : n th
difficulties, to bring education, or"uplift"as it is
Asia. Lo the rural areas.
literacy from Humanity's Viev
THAT is why Unesco's undertaking to hold a S
Adult Education at Mysore from Novembet 2 u
was hailed with deep satisf ction by all Asian
To this first Asian Seminar, plans for which w
Unesco's Third General Conference in Beirut last
experienced adult education experts, a1 med with the
through achievements, and failures, in practical eXI
out in other so-called"backward"areas of the wor
The 30 delegates, representing 15 countries, v
together at Mysore include energetic Barbara MoLac :
who arrived fresh from her work among the Papuan
and veteran adult education leader Spencer Hatch,
time's experience of work in India, Mexico and Cost
Among the Asian educators are amiable U Tin
Dirgharaj Kourala, who travelled several days on he
native Nepal, to reach the train which brought him
The advisers sent by Unesco include Dr Frede
Division of Fundamental Education, who helped
Fundamental Education Pilot Project in the Marbia
and who more recently took part In the Unesco Sem
in the Americas, at Quitandinha, Brazil and Dr
Director of the Institute of Educational Research
of Puerto Rico.
Twelve of the 14 observers at the Seminar are far,
the remaining two being from the World Health
the International Labour Office.
Since the Seminar was inaugurated by India's E
WHILE THE]
THE WHOLE
or ROM the cave-dwellers to modernhas tried to hand on to its succes
life less cruel. a civilization nobler
Mahatma Gandhi so well said'all riqh
served come from duty well done. TJ
accrues to us only when we do the duty
"Too much has been said in the tWE
01 enlightenment and zones 01 èt"kne
backward areas. Humanity is one. Sc
backward area, the whole earth-will be
there is a single culturally dark zone,
cultural darkness. In tact, though owe.
forward like ships in convoy, at the spei
TWELVE miles north of the city of Mysore in Southern India, are the celebrated Brindavan Gardens, whose. Might.
orange-colored flowers, red blossomed trees, canals and artificIal lakes attract visitors from all parts of India
and from abroad.
At night., these enormous gardens are illuminated, and the cascades of water, floodlit in all the colours of the
rainbow, produce a magnificent and unreal effect-like an endless display of fireworks against the black Indian night.
A group of some 50 men and women who arrived early last month at the Hotel Krishnarajasagar, which overlooks the
gardens had not, however, come to Brindavan to admire this beauty..
As delegates to the Seminar on Rural Adult Education for Community Action, organized by the Indian Government on
LIIL'SCO'S lJe ! wlf, tlleir illlerest was centred on a dítlcl'ellt kind of spectacle common to many of the nearby, villages : a picture
of people living wretchedly in overcrowded huts, alongside thoir cattle, goats and fowls, without proper sanitation and under
the ever threatening shadows of famine and disease.
Such villages, as well as the breathtaking beauty of Brindavan Gardens, mirror the real India and bring into stark relief
the age-old problems of ignorance, poverty, famine and disease.
These Indian villages are described in that great work"The Discovery or India", in which Prime Minister Jawaharlal
Nehru, relates how the intellectuals and political leaders of hits generation found their way back to the villages.
He wrote :"It was a disturbing sight, not only because of Its stark misery and the magnitude of its problems, but because
it began to upset some of our values and conclusions"...
The same process has been going on all over Asia, and has led to a sharpened sense of community responsibilities and a
changing of values. Because the villages are fhe real Asia. But, Nehru and others who re-discovered their countries and
countrymen also found a rich cultural and ethical tradition.
There is a deep connection between the re-discovery of the vitlages and the arising of a new Asia which we see to-day ; and
The Rural Education Seminar is being held in the Hotel Krishnara-
jasagar, (above) which overlooks the magnificent gardens of Brindavan.
The effect of this beautiful setting is heightened by the contrasting
poverty and squalor of nearby villages visited by delegates.
INDIA'S GIGANTIC
ILLITERACY PROBE, M
- NDIA'S Minister 01 Education, Maulana Abul Azad, inau-j gurating the Seminar on <&lt; Rural Adult Education for
Community Action a. at Mysore, stated that out of
India's 180 adults only 17 millions can read and write.
This means that in spite 01 what. has been done in the
last decades, India's illiterate adult population numbers
153 millions, or more than 90 %. The percentages and
figures vary from country to country and.. from province to
province in Asia, but there is no doubt the majority of
illiterates in the world-fifty percent 01 its population-
live in Asia.
Maulana Azad told the Seminar :"We are considering
in India the possibility of using the basic school teacher
for our programme of Social Education. We are also ex-
amining a proposal to use some kind of social conscription
by which all educated persons will be required to contri-
bute to this national service for a specified period. If
all students after matriculation are compelled to teach for
even six months this would, of course, go some way toward
finding the solution."
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
RE : A NEW
HOPE
Page 7-UNESCO COURIER
OLD CONTINENT
, the villages to dis-
round the concepts
work is being done,
n the face of endless
it is often called in
ewpoint
a Seminar on Rural
2 until December 14,
sian countries.
were approved by
ast year, have come
i the lessons learned
experiments carried
world.
, who are meeting
LacMan of Australia.
uans in New Guinea,
: ch, who has a life-
: osta Rica.
in from Burma and
I horseback from his
jm to Mysore.
ederick Rex, of the
led to institute the
rbial Valley of Haiti
; eminar on Illiteracy
Dr Rodriguez Bou,
) h at the University
: from Indian States,
th Organization and
s Education Minister
Maulana Azad, on November 2, leaders and delegates have clearly
indicated the practical lines on which they will work.
There is, however, no confusion in the mInds of those working
near Mysore on the difference between literacy and education.
The Right Hon. Pin Malakul, Thailand's Under Secretary for
Education, and Director of the Seminar, stressed this at the opening
of the Seminar when he said :"We as educators must look at it
(literacy) from humanity's point of view. What is needed most is
education, and literacy is just a medium through which this can
be realized. A man is not better off if he is just able to read and
make some scribbling that goes for his name, if he Mill has to
live in abject misery Adult education is concerned with healthy
living, the means of living, social contacts and culture. The concerns
of the Seminar will therefore be wider in scope than mere Meracy".
Adult fundamental education problems are directly linked with
those of health. economics, nourishment and standards of life.
In a broadcast from the Seminar, Professor Humayun Kabir. Joint
Secretary, Indian Ministry of Education, gave this definition of funda-
mental education for adults :
"It must be the education of free man in a free soctety and not
merely a course in literacy. It must liquidate the problem of
illiteracy, help the people to improve their living standards, through
reform in the forms and customs of family life. It must bring to
them new techniques in old crafts and introduce new cmfts and
skills so that their economic standards are raised. It must inculcate
in them a sense of citizenship ana community living."
An Avenue Named Unesco
UNESCO and the Indian Government have called the Mysore
Seminar in order to provide educational leaders from Asia and
elsewhere in the world with the opportunity to giv  content
and practical shape to this definition.
Reports which each national delegation has prepared on the state
and progress of rural adult education in its own country are of
immense value and together form what is probably the first
comprehensive survey of fundamental education, in Asia's rural areas.
At a Hindu temple near Mysore, Dr. Spencer Hatch, a veteran education worker and leader
of the Seminar group working on economic questions, examines some of the intricate stone
carvings. With Dr. Hatch is his daughter, an orientalist from Columbia University.
But these reports only constitute a background for the work of the Seminar
which is organized in four working groups, each having carefully planned objectives
and scope for studies. In each group experiences are pooled so as to find the
most efficient means of tackling the particular problems under discussion.
The early days of the Seminar were taken up with general meetings, visits,
lectures and development of tile general"get-together"spirit which must accompany
an experience in"international living", such as a Unesco Seminar.
Vidyapeeth, a people's college for training in rural leadership, modelled on the
Scandinavian folk high schools, was also visited. Vidyapeeth is probably the only
college in the world with a road called Unesco Avenue. During their visit, delegates
from each country planted young palm trees along the main avenue leading to the
college, as Indian officials, in the presence of villagers from the whole district, named
it in honour of Unesco.
Vidyapeeth gave the Seminar an encouraging example for the opening of its
work. It showed the immensity of the problem, and the devotion, despite meagre
means, with which it is being tackled.
: RE IS ONE BACKWARD AREA
E EARTH WILL BE BACKWARD
rn legislators, every generation
cessor a world less unjust, a
ler and more harmonious. As
ights to be deserved and pre-
Thus, the very right to live
uty of citizenship of the world.
twentieth century about zones
kness, about progressive and
So long as there is a single
be backward and, as long as
te, the whole earth will be in
ve may not realize it, we move
speed of the slowest...
"Two thirds of the human race live in fear of enslavement-ensla-
vement by ignorance. Wherever any man suffers, there all huma-
nity suffers. Convinced of this undeniable truth, you have met
together to light against illiteracy in a land which breathes the
spirit of good. India offers a vast field for international co-ope-
ration. Not in vain did one of her finest poets write in the twilight
of his days these unforgettable lines :"For the good of mankind
and for full spiritual growth, we must devote ourselves to the cause
of the spiritual unity of man."
Jaime Torres Bodet Director-General of Unesco, in a message
to the Mysore Seminar on Rural Adult Education for Community
Action.
Seminar Learns from the Army
plans for the next live years and samples of books and pam-
phlets prepared for newly literate people were also displayed.
The first group which studies various literacy teaching
techniques was also able to see a demonstration and hear
lectures on fundamental Education work in the Indian Army.
About 80 % of all new recruits are now being made
literate through the simple, efficient teaching given in all
units.
In view of the available financial resources-two annas
(about 5 cents) per man, each month, is provided by the
Army Education Budget-the results obtained are remarkable.
All Asia's Problems at"Tiger's Pond"
coil. \f) tMAx of Group 2. which is studying health and home
life problems in rural areas, is Professor S. Y. Cho, of
the China Mass Education Movement. Professor Cha
who has repaesented China at two of Unesco's General
Conference, brings with him experience gained during
2j years work with the Mass Education movement.
Group 8, which is concerned with the economic aspects
of rural adult education, is led by Dr. Spencer Hacth, of
the inter-American Institute of Agricultural Sciences. Dr.
Hatch's group is studying ways of impruving agriculture
in Asian countries, the development of rural and home
industries, the raising of housing and equipment standards,
and the teaching of basic economics.
Jovial Professor A. X. Basu, of Calcutta L'niversitv, who
attended Unesco's first Seminar at Sevres, near Paris in
l : 1947 is directing the studies of the fourth group into social
and cilizenship aspects of rural education.
Should they need a physical reminder of the problems
they are discussing, the members of the Seminar have many
"living laboratories"close at hand. When some of them
visited the little village of Hulikere, which means"Tiger's
Pond", about a mile away from their meeting place, these
problems suddenly became dramatically alive.
In this village of 600 people, life has not changed for
centuries. Hoads and homes are filthy, cattle and human
being are housed together : the farming tools are primitive
and each man works for himself and his family and not for
the community. There is no water in the village, and soil ero-
sion has ruined inost of the land. Sanitation, medical care,
persona hygiene are practically unknown. The school is
. a windowless mud-hut. This village is one of the more
backward ones, hut it is far from being an isolated case.
One of the Indian delegates, Shri Aryanayatam, who has
worked closely with both Tagore and Mahatma Gandhi.
ealled the village leader and council together. and talked
to them.
"Clear the dirt from your roads, homes and lives", he said.
"I am ashamed of you. You have a school that is not fit for
cattle to live in. 1 worked with the Mahatma and was with
him when he decided to settle down in the most backward of
all villages. Gandhi chose that village because he said if he
could accomplish something there he could do anything. But
you too must do something. for yourselves. Build a new school,
keep your village and homes clean. Then you will live a happier
life,"
The sight of this village and others like it has impressed
the members of the Seminar with a sense of urgency and
impatience and a feeling that they'are fighting against time,
fighting for the millions of people now living In extreme
miserly and poverty.
II is this need for practical, tangible'results that caused
the organizers ùf the Seminar to add the words :"For
Community Action"to the original title of "Seminar on
Rural Adult Education".
The problems which the members of the Seminar have seen in the villages
around Brindavan Gardens are not problems for any one specialist : they must
be attacked by a team. This has. been realized in the setting up of the four
working-parties, whose very names indicate the close relationship between
modern literacy teaching and the welfare of peoples.
The first group, under the chairmanship of Dr. Mohamed Salim, of Iraq, began its
studies of literacy and adult education, wilh discussions on the definition and purpose
of literacy. The problem of literacy is a very real one for the participating-countries.
They have all initiated ambitious literacy drives, sometines on the lines of the"each
on teach one" method, sometimes through evening classes, often in the open air, or
anywhere the teachers can find an audience.
The whole Seminar, but, in particular this first group, has been greatly helped
through an exhibition arranged by the Mysore State Adult Education Council. The
excellent material sent to the exhibition by Indian States and provinces, included
detailed statistics on illiteracy in relation to density of population. Graphs showing
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8
V
T U ; I< : H is a to-ordinating council of interlÌaUonal non-govern-
mental organizations actively contributing to the habilitaUon of
education and euUure in war devastatcd areas.
Its menlbership is limited to those international OI"IJanizations
most actively engaged in this field, but, as each member is actually
a ledcration of national branches, the particil, ants 01 TICEH repres-
ent over 700 national organizations in more than M) countries.
"'hill'presen'ing their lull autonomy and independence, the
members of TICER have formally associated themselves with
Unesco and hold their meetings in Unesco House.
The article below describes how TICER has been working
with Unesco during the past two and a half years and demonstrates
how its radius of action is now being extended to problems other
than those directly connected with war devastation.
THE STORY OF VOLUNTEERS IN THE FRONT
LINE OF EDUCATIONAL RECONSTRUCTION
EARLY thIs year, the General Con-
r1 ference of TICER representatives
appointed a fact-finding committee
to establish whether or not the
Council had fulfilled Its purpose.
This three-member committee met
shortly before the opening of Unesco's
Fourth General Conference, in September,
and with the aid of records, correspon-
dence and other documents, it reviewed
TICER's activities during the last two and
a half years.
At the end of its enquiry, the committee
decided that the Council had fully justified
its exIstenae and its finding was endorsed
by the Unesco General Conference, when
It later approved the Reconstruction
Department's proposal for"collaboration
with non-governmental agencies".
What is the purpose of keeping alive a
temporary council for educational recon-
struction when, as a body, it does not have
the means to reconstruct ? TICER itself
has not even sent a gross of pencils to a
wrecked school-building In a war devas-
tated country, since it was set up.
On the oiher hand, the member orga-
nizations of TICER together spend a
hundred times more on educational
reconstruction than Unesco. To quote
only one example, the World Student
Relief has between October 1947 and
September 1948 spent over $100, 000 on
relief work.
What would happen, if TICER did not
exist ? In the first place, Unesco's Recons-
truction Department Is not a relief
organization. It may receive donations
and has an emergency fund of $175, 000.
but spread over a number of countries
this amounts to token rather than sub-
stantial help.
Thus, to carry out its tasks of stimulat-
ing and co-ordinating relief, Unesco would
in the absence of TICER itself, have to call
on other agencies engaged in educational
reconstruction, supply them with infor-
mation on urgent needs and publicize the
reports on assistance given.
It would not consult each organization
individually, but would call on groups to
discus specific situations or categories of
needs. Some groups would be concerned
with work camps, others with library needs
In war damaged countries, some would
be consulted on the role of young people
In educational reconstruction and so on.
Advantages of contacts
through Ticer
t LL this is exactly what has beenhappening since 1947, thanks to
TICER, with the exception that being
a semi-permanent organization, TICER has
certain advantages over the alternative
system of looser and more occasional
contacts. Its existence has resulted In
the gradual growth of a close relationship
between its members and Unesco, through
the widespread, friendly and permanent
contacts It has maintained.
Unesco's educational relief programme
In the Middle East, for example, would
never have been so quickly Implemented
If some relationship between Unesco and
the agencies In the field had not already
existed.
But, both TICER and Unesco are con-
tinually striving to improve the efficiency
of these contacts and the scope of the
work being carried out.
TICER's standing committee met
recently to discuss the best ways of using
the experience and machinery of non-
governmental organizations in implement-
ing Unesco's programme. One of the
most important points raised at the
meeting was whether Unesco should call
In as many organizations as possible or
limit its consultations to organizations
doing a specific job connected with its
programme.
The Committee finally recommended
that the best results would be achieved
if Unesco continued to convene working
parties of TICER member organizations to
deal with specific reconstruction subjects
such as aid to handicapped children,
exchange programmes and fellowships anQ
international work camps.
The discussions which take place at
these working parties help organizations
to plan more efficient working methods
for a wide range of activities.
Recently, at a working party on exchange
programmes and fellowships, Mr P. Bearton
Akeley, of the Friends World Committee,
raised the question of whether short visits
abroad help in producing better under-
standing between peoples. He cited the
case of a group of German students which
he brought to Paris after the war.
Psychological hazards
of tourists
THESE students had wonderful time.) Most of them saw Paris for the first
time and they expressed great enthu-
siasm for French culture and love for
French life. Once back in Germany, how-
ever, the same students developed and
spread resentment,"W) ly are they (in
France) so much better ofi than we ?",
they asked.
Mr Akeley, therefore, felt that their
visit had been damaging to France and on
neither side was there more understanding.
Typical of the
work done by
TICER'S member
organizations is
that 01 the World
Student Relief
which, during the
twelve months
ending September
1948. spent over
 100. 000 on relief
work. This photo
shows packages
being distributed
by its representa-
tives in Greece to
tubercular students
at Sotiria sanato-
rium, near Athens.
There were three factors, he felt, which
might help to create the kind of contacts
useful for comprehension and international
understanding. Young travellers should
be trained psychologically to look for
comparable rather than Identical apectB
in cultures different from their own.
Arrangements should be made for them
to meet people of more than one national-
ity simultaneously, thus lessening the
chance of prejudice being developed.
Young travellers should also be left
dependent on the courtesy of their hosts,
with : he feeling that they need to be
understood rather than with the notion
that they have come there to judge.
Mr Akeley also suggested the preparation
of a pamphlet on the psychological hazards
of the tourist.
Working together. TICER and Unesco
have directed more than $100. 000, 000 in
money and gifts for the rehabilitation of
cultural life in war devastated countries.
In continuing and expanding this work
for other needs, in particular to those of
under-developed countries, Unesco needs
the energetic co-operation of international
voluntary relief organizations and through
them, of the millions of men and women
of goodwill.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
PORTR
OF A PE
At. the request of the Governmentof Afghanistan, a UNESCO Mis-
sion recently completed a su,.., ey
of the educational system of that country,
With a yiew to adYising the Government
on possible lines of deYe/Of'ment. The
Mission was headed by Dr Jean Debiesse,
Inspecteur d'Académie, French Ministry
of Education, who was concerned mainly
with the problems of Secondary Education.
With Dr Debiesse were Dr Harold
Benjamin, Dean of the College of Educa-
tion, Uniyersity of Maryland, U. S. A.,
whose field was Primary Education,
Dr William Abbott, H. M. Staff Inspector,
9'rtinistry of Education, England, who
coyered the problem of technfcot eduea-
tion and Mile Jacqueline Aillet, of the
UNESCO staff, who accompanied the
Mission as Secretary.
In the following article, the members
of the Mission haye set down some
Impressions of their two months stay and
At Bomion. in Central Afghanistan, described by a member 01 Unesco's Mission as"an
earthly paradise", the green, fertile valley is surrounded by pink and rose-red mountains.
In the sandstone clills are carved huge Buddha, and innumerable shrines and monastic
cells. The Buddha in the centre of this photo is 180 feet high and the"Lillie Buddha"on
the right is 60 feet shorter.
Bamian. once the centre of a great Greco-Buddhist civilization was conquered first by Islam
and then by Genqhis than. who depopulated the area.
A school scene at Istalii. a village in the mountainous country north of Kabul. Pupils in
Afghanistan's elementary schools start learning the country's two main language, Pushtu
and Persian, in the primary grades. In this class, where the boys have close cropped heads
and wear their caps during lessons, one of them is reading aloud from a Persian manual.
have described the general educational
situation in Afghanistan, for the improve-
ment of which they will formulate recom-
mendations in their report.
WHILE it is true that Afghanistanis still at a primitive stage in
its development, its reputation
of being a dangerous and
savage country found no confinnation
in the experiences of the Mission,
each of whose members returned
with the impression that it would be
quite safe for him to travel freely and
alone anywhere within its borders.
The Mission had its headquarters in
Kabul, the capital, but completed an
extensive tour of the country so as to
obtain not only first-hand knowledge
of the existing schools,'but also of the
general physical and social conditions
found throughout the country to-day.
This tour took the members to such
towns as Faizabad, Konduz ; Mazar-i-
Cherif, Maimanah, Herat, Ferah,
Kandahar, Ghazni, Gardaiz and
Djelelabad, and enabled them to as-
semble a great deal of on-the-spot
information and considerable back-
ground'knowledge, all of which will
make its report strongly factual and
in no sense an"armchair"one.
During its tour, the Mission was
accompanied by Dr. Achmed. Afghan-
istan's Director of Primary Education ;
Mr. Aslam, Director of School Equip-
ment ; Mr. Rahim, who is responsible
for Unesco affairs in Afghanistan ;
Mr. Aziz Mohammed, Inspector of
Schools ; and Dr. Bashir who looked
after the health of the party.
Fantastic colours,
dedlish shapes
S SERVANTS and mechanics travelledin an accompanying truck, carry-
ing baggage, petrol, oil and spare
parts, the latter being needed all too
often.
Afghanistan has no railways. The
poor surfaces, loose stones and ever-
present dust of its roads are not
conducive to the longevity of automo-
biles. At times the party was maroon-
ed with empty radiators, bogged down
in deep sand or awash in river fords
which were deeper than expected. No
major trouble overtook the Mission,
but the number of minor breakdowns
was exasperating.
The scenery of Afghanistan is often
grand and in places awe-inspiring. The
gigantic ranges of the Hindu Kush are
naked and snow crested. The melting
snows create a number of large rivers,
Kabul and during its 2500 miles tour
of the country, the Mission was able
to establish a comprehensive picture of
existing educational resources.
No women
university students
OUT of Afghanistan's population,which has been v riously estimated
at something between 8 million
and 15 million-the actual figure is
probably around twelve million people
- there are about one and a half mil-
lion children of elementary school age.
To-day, about 86, 000 children, most-
ly boys, are being taught in 289 ele-
mentary schools. There are also 40
secondary schools, but a large pro-
portion of the pupils are actually in
the elementary stages of combined
elementary-secondary schools.
In Afghanistan, there are no mixed
classes, and the total number of girls
the flow of which is greater in summer
than in winter.
Some of the mountain scenery is
fantastic, both in colour and in
contour ; pink, rose red, brown and
black are combined with devilish
shapes that appear to have cooled to
their present forms only yesterday.
The plains of Afghanistan are fer-
tile and produce good crops whenever
water is made available by irrigation.
No rain falls during the long summer
and autumn months, and cloudless
blue skies greeted the Mission day
after day. High midday temperatures
- up to 119 degrees F.-were found
bearable because of the dryness of the
air.
In the north and west the major
industry, apart from agriculture, is the
raising of sheep for the karakul lamb
skins. These are dried on the hot de-
sert sands, and the orderly rows of
skins with their white undersides up-
permost give the impression from a
distance of large military cemeteries.
In the south, is Kandahar, a city
surrounded with most extensive orch-
ards, comparable to Damascus. Its
fruits are famous anS* find a ready
market in Pakistan. A new road has
been built by American engineers
from Kandahar to Chaman in Pa-
kistan, and along it pass trucks with
their valuable loads Of grapes, peaches,
apples and melons.
From the information it obtained in
attending schools is around 3, 000. At
Kabul University, which has faculties
of Medicine, Science and Arts, there is
not a single woman among the 300
students.
English is becoming the most widely
spoken foreign language used in the
country, and, apart from two secon-
dary schools in Kabul which give in-
struction in French and German, all
others teach English, along with Af-
ghanistan's two main languages.
Pushtu and Persian.
In conformity with the government's
aim to make all Afghans bi-lingual.
children start learning Pushtu. and
Persian in the first elementary school
grade.
There are* also Moslem schools
where the Koran and Islamic customs
and history are taught, together with
arithmetic and reading and writing in
Arabic. This is useful for the study
of Persian and Pushtu which are both
written in Arabic characters.
While investigating Afghanistan's
general educational needs, the Mission
also examined those of technical edu-
cation.
Urgent need for
industrial development
THE country has still only smallscale i dustries and all tho e of
importance, including textile fac-
tories, sugar beet plant, power stations
and coal mines, were visited. Any great
extension of industrialization, which
would seem to be urgently necessary,
would involve the provision of much
more electricity-for which water
power is available in abundance-and
a major development of technical edu-
cation-a matter on which the Mission
will advise.
It intends to report on the type
and extent of technical education re-
quired for existing industries and also
what will be required if the country's
resources are to be developed. A
questionnaire has therefore been sent
to the Afghanistan government, asking
for information on development plans
over the next 10 to 20 years, so that
the mission can indicate what will be
needed in the way of technical colleges
and what their curriculums should be.
The total in trill labour force of
Afghanistan is way estimated at less
than 10, 000, so t t present\technical
training needs are not considerable.
There is already a colle for training
craftsmen, and Afghans who have been
trained abroad, together with a number
of foreign specialists are also available
to give technical instruction. Between
these two means of training there is
a void which somehow must be filled.
Lazy elements
"Go under"
THE people of Afghanistan arei devout Muslims, leading simpl
and laborious lives. They have a
proud bearing and are obviously inde-
pendent in spirit. Many of tñem are
fine physical specimens. They dis-
played an exemplary courtesy to the
members of the Mission and were al-
ways ready to give help and advice.
They were naturally most curious
concerning : the, to them, strange look-
ing foreigners ; but, then the foreigners
were equally curious about the Af-
ghans.
Each member of the Mission has
conceived an admiration for these
people, and believes them to be well
worthy of the assistance which more
developed countries can give them.
When people live for centuries under
hard conditions, in a harsh climate
amid rugged mountains, most of the
shiftless or lazy elements are elimi-
nated. You then get a people with
great drive and energy. With the help
of education, they will go farther than
other people who have lived in"softer"
countries and climates.
The Mission's report should be
completed early this month and will
be transmitted by Unesco to the Go-
vernment of Afghanistan, who, it is
hoped, will eventually authorize its
publication in whole or in part.
A it
OPLE , >
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 10
A MAGIC CARPET
FOR CHILDREN
Leading radio producers fromthree or four countries are to
collaborate with Unesco in a
European radio tour next year.
Working as a team, they will visit
several countries to carry out an
international experiment in radio
programme production.
Using Unesco's mobile recording
equipment, the radio caravan,
as it was named by M. Théo
Fleischman, Director-General of
the Belgian Radio, will begin its
tour either next Spring or at the
beginning of Autumn, to obtain
material for a series of radio pro-
grammes on a theme which is of
special interest to Unesco.
The subject chosen for the first
tour in 1950 is"Children in the
Post-War World", the idea being to
present to the world a factual
picture through the radio of how
children are being cared for and
educated to-day in several Euro-
pean countries.
One of the obvious advantages of
such a co-operative effort in pro-
gramme production is that the in-
ternational team will be made up
of producers having a wide know-
ledge and experience of different
types of radio audiences and tech-
niques. Each one will contribute
his own ideas and working methods
to the task of assembling sound
documentary material on a subject
which offers wide scope and which
should have an appeal in almost al !
countries of the world.
Putting children's
villages"on the air"
Camps and villages for the edu-cation and r habilitation of
children of many nationalities
already exist in France, Italy, Swit-
zerland, Czechoslovakia and Aus-
tria, and it is considered that
excellent and moving material
exists there from which program-
mes could be built to explain and
illustrate this important problem.
The suggestion that Unesco's
mobile equipment should be used
on a"combined operation"of this
type was first made by a group of
radio experts who met at Unesco
House, earlier this year, and the
plan was endorsed by Unesco's
Radio Programme Commission,
when it met recently.
This Commission, which holds a
yearly meeting to examine the
work done by Unesco's Radio Sec-
tion and to make suggestions for its
development, recommended that at
least three producers should be
invited to join in the tour.
Already, broadcasting organiza-
tions in Great Britain, France,
Switzerland, Italy and Mexico have
offered to send producers to colla-
borate in obtaining programme
material. The final selection will
be made by Unesco.
The Radio Commission also pro-
posed that the tour should last at
least three weeks to allow several
European countries to be covered,
and asked that similar experiments
should be made in the future on
other continents.
Finding the
best material
For the European tour, Unescointends to send out a"recon-
naissance party"several weeks
before the tour begins, to visit
camps and other centres where
children are living, to discover
where the best and most appro-
priate material is to be found.
This means that when the pro-
ducers, together with a Unesco
guide and an engineer to operate
the recording equipment, set-out
from Paris, they will have a detail-
ed itinerary to follow.
Unesco may also call on radio
organizations in the countries visit-
ed to assist the project by loaning
additional mobile recording equip-
ment and staff when necessary.
Broadcasting organizations in
Switzerland, Italy and Austria
have already offered to provide
such facilities should their coun-
tries be chosen for the visit.
At the end of the tour, each
producer will take back to his own
country the sound documentation
he has collected, and the work of
programme building will begin. A
record of completed programmes
prepared by each producer for
broadcasting by his own organiza-
tion will later be sent to Unesco, so
that copies can be made for distri-
bution to other parts of the world.
In this way, millions of radio
listeners will be given a vivid and
interesting impression of the ways
in which European children are
being helped to adapt themselves
to. the changed living conditions
which the war has brought about.
his year in some 2, 500 schools ofthe English-speaking world, chil-
dren are doing the next best
thing to going abroad themselves-
they are reading and hearing colourful
letters about foreign lands from tra-
vellers who know them well.
Every fortnight, the letters arrive,
full of lively details about the Scandi-
navian countries, the British Isles, the
West Indies, the U. S. A. Each letter
is about 1, 500 words in length and is
amply illustrated with coloured draw-
ings of the people, places and things
described in the typewritten text.
These serial letters, issued under
the general title « My Foreign Corres-
pondent)), are the result of an inge-
nious scheme to help teachers not
only to arouse the interest of children
in other lands and peoples, but also
to create an attitude of friendliness and
understanding toward them. The let-
ters are written and illustrated by
artist-writers who actually travel in the
countries they describe and every
Unesco poster describing thepossibili tie  of public libra-
ries as an agency for popular
education will soon be displayed in
25, 000 libraries and other public
huildings in all parts of the world.
The poster is entitled"The Public
LibrarJj, a Living Force for Popular
Education", and its text, in the
form of a leaflet, wilt be made
available to the public through
adult education groups and libra-
ries.
Both leaflet and poster have been
printed in English, French, Spanish,
Italian and Polish. An Arabic edi-
tion is planned for later in the year.
In general, the publication will be
distributed to libraries and educa-
tional organizations in each country
, through Unesco National Commis-
sions with the co-operation of
library associations.
It is true that. some libraries do
extremely effective popular educa-
tion work and are indispensable to
their communities ; they provide an
adequate servJce of information and
book needs for people near them ;
co-operate closely with local adult
education groups, clubs, labour
unions, schools and universities ;
and organize their own discussions,
film shows and other meetings.
But for every town with a good
library service, there are dozens
with no public libraries at all, and
hundreds of other towns, cities and
rural areas have in ! completely
developed libraries. The creation
and expansion of librari. es in these
places depends greatly on public
interest and support, but frequently
the average person has little or no
idea how helpful to him relatively
complete public library services can
be.
The leaflet and poster, by giving
a clear picture of first-rate public
library servite, will be valuable aids
to librarians in their efforts to stim-
ulate demand and get support in
their communities for the standard
of service endorsed by Unesco.
While public interest is essential
for public library development,
detail is checked
by experts to
ensure accuracy.
THE"BABY"
WEIGHS TWO
TONS
Easy languageand a"perso-
nal touch"keep
the innumerable
particulars from
becoming a dry
recital of facts.
For example, in
the letter from
Sandefjord, Nor-
way, about whal-
ing :'I was sur-
prised to hear
that they go so
far. but there are
so few large whales left in the northern
waters that the whalers have to go
south for them.
"Now, most of the whaling fleets of
the different nations have agreed to
protect the stock of whales by limiting
the size of each season's catch... When
1 asked him how big whales are, he
told me that a baby blue whale (the
largest kind) weighs 2 tons and is 22
feet long when it is born. By the time
it is full grown it is 100 feet long and
weighs about 150 tons ! Blue whales
feed on shrimps called'Krill'., which
are so numerous that they colour the
water pink. The main food of sperm
whales is octopi, which fight fiercely,
and the whales are often scarred all
over from their stings... If you would
like to know more about whaling in
the olden days you should read,'Moby
Dick'".
In this informal manner the letters
range over a Moslem wedding in
Trinidad, the architecture of huts in
Lappland, the system of street-number-
ing in New York City, the mysterious
monoliths of Stonehenge and scores
of other subjects. The"why"and
"how"of customs, attitudes and stand-
ards of people in far places are skil-
fully worked into the material to make
each letter a complete and realistic
exercise in education for international
understanding.
Information concerning the letter
series can be obtained from Meikle-
john & Sons Ltd., 15 Bedford Street,
London, W. C. 2, England.....
effective nctiC$pends to a large
extent on the knowledge and vision
of librarians and1'\ff1e'rs responsible
for the provision of library services.
Unesco is therefore nlî' ; i) publishing
a series of practice) guides for
librarian, educators and govern-
ment officials who need help in
planning for new and expand-
ed public library services. These
Unesco Public Library blanuals in
elude the following titles :
Education for Librarianship
(English, French, Spanish, Polish,
Arabic editions).
Public Library Extension (Eng-
lish, French, Spanish, Italian, Po-
lish, Hungarian, Czech editions).
Adult Education Activities for
Public Libraries (English, French,
Spanish, Italian editions).
The Public Library, a Force for
Popular Education (English,
French, Spanish, German editions).
most of the editions of the ma-
nuals will be ready for distribution
through Unesco Sales Agents this
year ; others will follow early in
1050.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Page I I-UNESCO COURIER
T its nearly two and a half
years since Unesco brought
together teachers, students
and educators from over
30 countries to take part, at,
Sevres, near Paris, in an experi-
mental form-of international
conference to which it gave the
nan1e"Seminar".
This first Seminar or Study
Conference on"Education fo'
International Understanding"
enabled these educators, meeting
in small informal study groups,
to exchange information, discuss
ideas and methods and to suggest
solutions for specific aspects of
the general question before them.
At that time, there were many
who doubted whether bringing
people together from all parts
of the world would help in
finding solutions. Most of the
teachers were strangers to each
other, their home educational pro-
blems differed'widely, and fre-
quently, because of language
difficulties, it was hard for them
to make their point of view
understood.
But the Seminar was a success.
People who came as strangers
went away as friends. They
went home appreciating more
fully other peoples'viewpoints
and problems.
Since then, Unesco has been
developing International Semi-
nars on an increasing scale, and
they have now become one of its
most important educational acti-
vities.
Arthur RAMOS
1903.. 1949
DR. ARTHUR RAMOS, who for thepast three months had been Head
01 Unesco's Department 01 Social
Sciences, died suddenly on 31 Octo-
ber. His passing, after an illness 01
only a few hours, was a severe loss
to Science, to Unesco, and to his
native Brazil.
It was principally as an anthropo-
logist that Professeur Ramos made
his mark in science. His researches
in anthropology and ethnology result-
ed in very important discoveries. It
was largely due to his work that
anthropological study in Brazil is now
on a sound scientific basis. Founder
and first President 01 the Brazilian
Anthropological and Ethnological So-
ciety, he was the author 01 several
works. These included : 0 negro
brazileiro (The Brazilian Negro).
translated into English, 1934 and 1940 ;
o Folklore negro do Brasil (Negro
Folklore in Brazil), 1935 ; As culturas
negres no novo mundo (Negro civi-
lizations of the New World), 1937, a
work which was to be translated
into Spanish and German ; Introdu-
çao a antropologia brazileira (An
introduction to Brazilian anthropo-
logy), two volumes 1943-1947 ; Les
Poblaciones del Brasil, 1945.
Professor Ramos was also a psy-
chiatrist, who had both practised and
taught. In 1934 he established and
directed the mental health branch 01
the Brazilian Ministry 01 Education.
He was a member of the Society of
Forensic Medicine, Criminology and
Psychiatry of Bahia and 01 the Bra-
zilian Society 01 Neurology and Psy-
chiatry. He wrote several works on
psychiatry and psycho-analysis :
Primitivo e Loucura (Primitive man
and madness), 1926 : Estudos de psi-
canalise (Studies in psycho-analysis),
1930 ; Freud, Adler, Jung,. 1934 ; Psi-
chiatria e psicanalise (Psychiatry and
psycho-analysis), 1934 ; Educaçao e
psicanalise (Education and psycho-
analysis), 1934 ; Loucura e crime
(Madness and Crime), 1937.
As a social psychologist he was
the first holder of the Chair of Social
Psychology at the University of Rio
de Janeiro in 1935. The following year
he wrote his lntroduceo a Pzicologia
Social (Introduction to Social Psycho-
logy), the only general work dealing
with that science in a Romance lan-
guage. He was also interested in
child psychology, as shown in his
last book : A crianca problema (The
problem 01 the child), 1948,
Members 01 Unesco's Social Scien-
ces Department mourn the loss of one
who gained the friendship 01 all his
colleagues, and sympathize deeply
with his widow, Madame Luiza de
Aranjo Ramos, who was also his de-
voted assistant.
Participants in Unesco Seminars are active in carrying out <&lt; ioHow up"work
when they return to their own countries. Miss Winifred Chalmers, who attended
the UN-Unesco Seminar on <&lt; Teaching about the United Nations and its Specia-
lized Agencies", in 1948. is now co-ordinating Unesco-UN studies in the schools
of Los Angeles. One of the ways in which the Unesco message is spread in Los
Angeles is through school newspapers. This photo shows pupils of Starr King
School preparing their paper which has had a Unesco news column since 1946.
Even from the initial results
of the Sevres Seminar, Unesco
saw that something worthwhile
was being achieved, and in July
and August 148, it organized
three other seminars under the
general title of 'Education for a
World Society".
At the Ashridge College of
Citizenship, in England, 47 educa-
tors and teachers studied"'The
Education and Training of
Teachers", while at Adelphi
College, in the United States,
representatives from 27 countries
worked together on the problems
of'''teaching About the United
Nations and ifs Specialized Agen-
cies".
Back in Europe, at the ancient
castle of Podebrady, in Czecho-
slovakia, 32 people from 17 coun-
tries were discussing problems of
educating children from three to
thirteen years of age.
What has been achieved as a
result of these Seminars ? Broadly
speaking, Seminars have fully
proved their worth as an effective
method of exchanging educatio-
nal ideas on a world scale.
But, the real value of a Semi-
nar cannot be judged solely on
reports and documents produced
by the people attending it. Its
final test is the influence which
it has on the participants, living
and working in an international
community, and through them,
on education in their own coun-
tries.
Spreading the U. N.-Unesco
Message
IT is therefore only to-day thatthe concrete results of the'work
done at the Seminars are be-
coming known. Reports are no\v
coming in from teachers and
educators who attended them,
describing the practical use they
have made of the experience and
information they obtained, and
showing the impetus that has
been given to the spreading of the
L'. N.-Unesco idea.
Searll} all Seminar members have
given talks or lectures about their
experiences, or about the Low and
Unesco. One Ametican school supper-
intendent has given over 200 talks and
many othel'people have deliveted be-
tween 20 and 50. Practicany everyone
has 1vritten neu ; spaper or maga ; ; ine
article, and a number have given
talks on the radio.
New teaching methods and
materials have been put to good
use. The group work method has
been employed with satisfactory
results almost everywhere, while
from Scandinavia to America,
films and film strips have been
widely used.
The influence of the Seminars
has also been responsible for
some changes in teaching me-
thods, and in the education and
training of teachers in those coun-
tries which sent representatives.
From Swit : : erlancl, the head of a
teacher's training college reports chan-
ges in the institution's training pro-
gramme, while a French participant
announces the organi : : ation of clubs to
study Unesco and also the setting up of
an exhibitton mom in the"Musée Peda-
gogique". One of the most important
steps has been taken in Los Angeles,
where the authorities have introduced
the study of U. N.-Unesco into the public
school cW'/Ículum, and have appointed
co-ordinators to direct these studies.
Seminar"Old Boys"Club
INDIVIDUAL contacts establishedat the Seminars are being
maintained and are helping to
ensure the continuity of the
work begun at Sevres, Podebrady
or Ashridge, through the free
exchange of ideas and informa-
tion. A Swedish member is keep-
ing in touch with others in In-
dia and South Africa, a Scottish
professor with educators in the
U. S. A., Canada, Australia and
Norway, and a Czech educator
correspondent with his opposite
numbers in Eng-lLlnù-and the
L'nited States.
Inspired by their experienes
at a Unesco Seminar, Norwegian,
Austrian, Swiss and New Zea-
land participants are planning
seminars of their own, and the
Australian Office of-Education
has alreadly organized one on
"Teaching-abouF the United
Nations and its objecti-es". One
Norwegian has even organized a
dub of former members of
Unesco Seminars. without ex-
ception, the replies receiyed by
Unesco testify to the--worth of
Seminars and stress the advisa-
bility of continuing and expand-
iug the programme.
Unesco, in the meantime, has
been making use of the reports,
speeches and other material-from
the Seminars to produce a series
of booklets for teachers, published
under the general heading"To-
wards World Understanding".
Written in a simple, straight-
forward style, these booklets are
valuable and e"asy-to-read hand-
books for teachers to add to their'
professional libraries.
One 6ooMet,'T/te Education and
Training of Teachers"tl ; as based on
three group reports from the Ashridge
Seminar and deals, among other
subjects, UJith the problem of sllO/dng
teachers hou ; in their'IL'ork they can
help to better international undel'stanä-
ing.
A group report from the Adelplli
College Seminar forms tTle main part of
"The Unitect. Vations anct lI'orlä Citi-
:, unship : Some Bar-kgrounct Injormation
for Teachel"s", ann, in a tllirct booklet,
"In the Classroom'Iei/h Children C ; ndel'
Thirteen", a group working at the
Poctebrady Serninar, has tried to anSl/Jer
some of the questions faced by their
coll. eagues in all parts of the Icorlct.
Fow'papers also produr-ed at Pode-
bmdy are reproduced in"The Influence
of llome and Community on Cllildren
Undel'Thirteen", including an address
given by the late Dr Ruth Benedict,
Professor of Anthropology at Teachers'
College, Columbia University. This u ; as
one of the last speeches made by Dr.
Benedict before her death, in Septembel'
1948. (The partial text of this speech
tl ; as published in the Coude/", Vol 1,
. Y" 9, October 1948.)
These, then, are some of the
practical results already achieved
through Unesco's Seminars on
education for international un-
derstanding, held in 1047 and
191. 18..
During 1040, Unesco's interna-
tional Seminars have been put
at the service of fundamental
education. The first, on Illiteracy
in the American. was held in Bra-
zil from July 27 to September 3,
and the second, on Rural Adult
Education in Asia, is now taking.
place in Mysore.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 12
AD international conference-the first of its kind since the war-metrecently at Unesco House to resume and expand the work done by the
League of Nations before 1939 for the conservation and restoration of
monuments of art and history. The Conference decided to set up an inter-
national council of 14 experts and approved the creation of an international fund
to help this work.
Experts from 11 countries who were present studied the question which
occupied the Member States at Unesco's General Conferences in Beirut (1948)
and Paris (1949) : WHAT CAN UNESCO DO FOR THE PROTECTION,
CONSERVATION AND RESTORATION OF ANTIQUITIES, MONU-
MENTS AND HISTORIC SITES ? Speaking in this connection, M. Torres
Bodet told the Conference that it was no longer simply a question of safeguarding
culture, but also the feelings of peoples and. their attachment to the glorious relics
of their past". 
In an interview with the Courier>&gt;, which we reproduce here in the form of
'counterpoint"to extracts from recent documents assembled by Unesco on
post-war restoration, Professor Roberto Pane, the Italian expert-consultant
who arranged the recent Conference, stresses the educational aspect of the
international problem of protecting the cultural wealth of mankind.
H The truth is", said Professor Pane,"that the problem is, above all,
one of popular education. There
can be no protection of historic monuments
without the assistance of the people.
"In some areas, especially in the Near
East, the good intentions of governments
meet a general apathy which raises extre-
mely difficult problems.
"If the Conference insisted upon the
Importance of scientific missions, it was
because there is every reason to fear that
within the next ten years many works of
art of immense historic value in the Near
East will have totally disappeared.
"Every cultivated person will under-
stand that this would be not merely a
national and regional disaster, but also an
international one."
bb he conservation of paintings is a most intricate problem". This wasthe comment of a Ne r Ea t specialist in a report submitted to t e Con-
ference. <It is often impossible to conserve frescoes in situ. Through lack of
suitable transport facilities, valuable frescoes, such as those at Arslan-Tash in
the North of Syria, had to be sacrificed, despite the rarity of Assyrian paintings'.
Dr. Julian Huxley, Unesco's first Director-General, in a memorandum ad-
dressed to the Organization's experts, reported that : <'all the antiquities of Trans-
jordan are in packing-cases owing to lack of funds to exhibit them... At Latakia,
I watched the local administrator pulling down various Greco-Roman pillars.
This seemed to me wanton destruction').
The Church of San Lorenzo Fuori Ie Mura is said to be the oldest existing basilica of the
Eternal City, and tradition has it that the Emperor Constantine was responsible for it
construction. 11 was severely damaged by bombing during the war, as is shown by this
photo, but has now been completely restored by the ltalian Goverment.
 l, IR. UISl, IEIE  COUlf\Jl, IR. 111ES M\UISl, SAIFIEGUIAIR. ID
MANK ! NDS AR. T ! ST ! C HEMTAGE
"T h. e urgency of the Near East pro-lems", continued Prof. Pane,
-'-"must not blind us to the fact
that in the West, where conservation is
quite well organized, there are also pro-
blems and not all of these are due to
wartime destruction.
there are"rich"countries which do
not spend enough on the protection of their
monuments.
"In the view of the specialists who met
at the recent Conference, Unesco's work of
education and publicity-the most useful
activity for the Organization to undertake
in the immediate future-should be addres-
sed as much to governments as to the
public.
"In France, one of the countries where
protection is best organized, the budget
allowed for this protection amounts to
barely one-fiftieth of requirements (843
million francs, or 0. 05 per cent of the
total budget).
"The same difficulties exist in several
other countries, aggravated In some cases
by war-time devastation. Very many
countries today find it materially impos-
sible to ensure out of their own resour-
ces, the safeguarding and restoration of
artistic and historical treasures of which
they are the trustees.
"The Conference was particularly struck
by the restoration efforts of Poland,
whose tosses in the last war exceeded the
total damage to its artistic treasures
Inflicted in the course of its 1, 000 years
of existence."
"warsaw, Danzig, Poznan and Wroc1aw>&gt;, said Professor Stanislas Lorentz,Director-General of Museums and Protection of Monuments, <&lt;are h
most striking examples of this unparalleled devastation. At first all our efforts
were spent oñ at least provisionally protecting damaged buildings, which it
was important to prevent falling completely into ruins... In the second stage,
1948-1949, we continued this work of protection, but went on to the recon-
struction proper of the most important monuments. During the third stage
which, will take from 1950 to 1955, it is intended, among other things, to rebuild
the Royal Castle in Warsaw and the old historic parts of Warsaw and Danzig).
"India'"added Professor Pane,"also)) occupied the Conference's atten-
tion, because of the vigour with
which that country has for several years
protected its immense archaeological and
architectural wealth, tndia's monuments
need protection more particularly against
the effects of the climate, the rains and
the spread of rank vegetation. This has
raised special problems of conservation
which were discussed by the Conference."
The Taj Mahal, supreme achievement of Mohammedan art, was built (1629-1650) near Agra,
India, by Shah Jahan, as the burial place for his favourite wide. Mumtaz-i-Mahal. Although
it is considered bv some to be the most beautiful building in the world, it is only twenty
years ago that the Taj Mahal was threatened with destruction. In 1928, a proposal to
demolish it was adopted by the government, but was fortunately not put into execution.
The building, however, suffered through neglect, and in 1942, the Indian Government ordered
large-scale restoration work to be carried out. This photo shows the scaffoldings placed
round the dome 01 the Taj Mahal while restoration work on the masonry was taking place.
Presenting the Conference with the conclusions of his memorandum, MrN. P. Chakravarti, Director-General f Archaeology in India, said : (<Some
of the problems of murals in India are highly complex. For example, at Tanjore
there are two layers of wall paintings superimposed one over the other, and it is
a problem to remove the upper layer intact, and, without damaging it, to expose
for preservation in situ the under layer... Through the good offices of Unesco
my enquiries about similar work in other countries were passed throughout
the scientific world... I would therefore urge the establishment of a properly
equipped research centre, under the auspices of Unesco, from which expert
advice would be available to all the member countries').
To fulfil its role as a centre of"*) information and documentation
in this field, Unesco must above
all co-operate with Institutions concerned,
and especially with tourist services. Its
education of the public will merely become
more thorough and effective.
"The tourist industry is working for us
and we are working for it.
"It is not the climate which takes
traveiierstoRheims, Ghent, Pisa, Salisbury
to the Taj Mahal or the Royal Cometery at
Chang-Ping.
"For many countries, travel Is today
the first and most complex of its export
industries. In 1948 it earned for France
more than 30 milliards of francs In foreign
currency.
"The economic importance of these
resources, combined with the intrinsic
cultural value of historic monuments, has
created in some countries extremely im-
portant popular movements."
"In Sweden, according to a Conference memorandum, awe owe to the popularmovem t Hambygder relsen, mad -up of more than 800 local societies, the
safe-guarding of an impressive number of monuments, documents and works of
art. Building which have been saved by this public zeal now number 2, 6239.
66TTn every field of protection", Pro-fessor Pane conclud d, Unesco
has clearly an immense task before
it, a task out of all proportion to the
means with which it is at present supplied
by its Member States.
"In 1950 the Organisation's budget will
not allow it to send out a single one of
those scientific missions, whose Importance
was stressed by experts at the Conferen-
ce. In 1951 Unesco hopes to be able to
organize one such mission with a budget
of 12, 000 dollars... It will thus perhaps
be possible to save a few of the artistic
treasures.
"But, there must be more of these mis-
sions. The war has brought about their
urgent need, and at the same time made
them too costly for the resources of one
country or one international institution.
"Accordingly, the Conference approved
Unesco's wish to see the establishment of
an international fund, which could be used
at the start for certain particularly im-
portant missions and for the restoration of
monuments having an international cultural
interest.
"The Conference also recommended the
establishment of a Council of 14 Experts,
as a kind of international General Staff to
direct Unesco's campaign for the con-
servation and restoration of historic sites
and monuments.
"It would be the duty of these experts
to consult Unesco upon the choice of
priorities, in such matters as the prepar-
ation of International agreements for pro-
tection against dangers arising from war,
in the organization of international photo-
graphic archives of the world's treasures,
and in the sending out of scientific mis-
stones. They will also have to direct
Unesco's programme of publicity and pop-
ular education.
"In this second post-war period this
Council will take the place of the Inter-
national Committee set up by the League
of Nations. The League Committee had
30 national representatives and was, there-
fore, a far larger and more ofncia) body.
The Council will have a more technicai
aspect, In keeping with the urgency of Its
task."
]]>
</page>
</document>
