<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074639eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
8
THE FESTIVAL OF FOLK DANCIN
AT OPATIJA WAS AN IMPORTANT
EVENT IN THE CULTURAL LIFE OF
YUGOSLAVI
(pages 4-5)
1  1
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 2 NOVEMBER t95)
EDITORIAL OFFICES :
UNESCO HOUSE
19, Ave. Kléber, PARIS-16
n
Editor-in-Chief : S. M. KOFFLER
EDITORS
English sedition : R. S. P. ENTON
French edition : A. LEVENTIS
Spanish edition : J. DE BENITO
A) t reproduction* authorized
imprimerie GEORGES LANG
I I, rueCuria), Paris.
MC. 51. I. 54. A.
A full year's subscription (12 issues)
costs only 51. 50 U. S., * or S/-or 200
French Francs.
Write to our agent in your country
listed below, or directly to UNES ( ; O
House, 19, avenue KIeber, Paris-16',
France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana,
S. A., Alsina 500, Buenos Aires.
Australia : H. A.. Goddard Ltd., 255 a
George Street, Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27 Gra-
ben, Vienna 1.
Barbados : S. P. C. K. Bookshop (Regional
Office Caribbean Area), Broad Street,
Bridgetown.
Belgium : Librairie Encyclopedique. 7,
rue du Luxembourg, Brussels IV.
Bolivia : Libreria Selecciones, Av. 16 de
Ju ! io216, Casilla972, LaPaz.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio
de Janeiro.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop,
551-3 Merchant Street, P. O. Box'222.
Rangoon.
Indo-China : K. Chantarith, C. C. R..
3B, rue Van Vollenhoven, Phnom-Penh.
Canada : English speaking : University
of Toronto Press, Toronto. French
speaking : Benoit Baril, 4234, rue de
la Roche, Montreal 34.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The
Associated Newspapers of Ceylon,
Ltd, Colombo I.
Chile : Libre. ria Lope de Vega, Moneda
924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera
9a, 1791, Bogota.
Cuba : La Casa Belga, O'Reilly 455,
Havana.
Czechoslovakia : Orbis,-Narodni 37,
Prague I.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6 Norre-
gade, Copenhagen.
Ecuador : Casa de la Cultura Ecuato-
riana, av Mariano Aguilera 332,
Casilla 67 : Quito.
Egypt : Librairie James Cattan, Four-
nisseur de la Cour, lie, Rue Emad
el Dine, Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Koskuskatu. Helsinki.
France : Librairie Universitaire, 26, rue
SoufMot. Paris (5')..
Greece : Elelthéroudakis, Librairie In-
ternationale, Athens.
Hungary : Kultura, P. O. B. 149, Buda-
pest 62.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co.,
Scindia House, New Delhi.
Bombay and South India : Vidya-
bhavan Granthagar, Chowpatty
Road, Bombay 7.
Indonesia : G. C. T. van Dorp and C"
NV.. Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
brae ! : Leo Blumstein, Book and Art
Shop, 35, Allenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Japan : Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Tori-Ni-
chome, Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Lebanon : Librairie Universelle, Avenue
des Franglais, Beirut.
Malaya and Singapore : Peter Chong
and Cho, P. O. Box 135, Singapore.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria. Justo
Sierra 16, Mexico D. F.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff.
Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : Whitcombe and Tombs,
Ltd, G. P. O. Box 1526, Welling'on.
Nigeria : C. M. S. Bookshop, P. O. Box
174, Lagos.
Norway : AjS Bokhjornet, Stortingsplass
7, Oslo.
PakiØlan I Thomas and Thomas, Fort
Mansions, Frere Road ; Karachi 3.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru,
S. A., Giron de la Union, Lima.
Philippine. : Philippine Education Co.,
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : PubIicacôes Europa-America,
Ltda, 4 Rua da Barroca, Lisbon.
Spain I Aguilar S. A. de Ediciones, Juan
Bravo 38, Madrid.
Sweden t AB. C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hov-
bokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stock-
holm 16.
Switzerland I French. speaking cantons :
Librairie de 1'University. 22-24, rue de
Romont, Fribourg. German speaking
cantons : Europa Verlag, 5 Römi-
s'rasse. Zurich.
Syria : Librairie Universelle, Damascus.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9,
Raj-Demnern Avenue, Bangkok.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union o ! South Africa I Van Schaix't
Bookstore, Ltd., P. O. Box 724,
Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H. M. Stationery
Office. P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
United State. of Anaerica I Columbia
University Press. 2960 Broadway.
New York.
Urugnay : Centro de Cooperacion Cien-
I1hca para la America Latino. Unesco,
Bulever Artigas 1320, Montevideo.
'Outside o< the United States, $ 1.
Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do
not necessarity represent the
opinions ot Unesco or the
f'dilors of the COURTIER.
Young Yugoslavs greet M. Torres Bodet, Unesco's Director-general, during his visit to an orphans'home at
Zagreb, in the People's Republic of Croatia.
In Belgrade, Ljubljana and Zagreb, M. Torres Bodet sees success of
CULTURAL DEVELOPMENT ON
A REG ! ONAL BAStS
Drawing on the wealth of their individual cultures and traditions, the peoples of Yugoslavia are today makinga determined effort to develop the educational, scientific and cultural resources of their country.
Each of Yugoslavia's six federated republics, for example, organizes its primary, technical and higher
schools, its academy of arts and sciences, and its research laboratories, which, while fostering the culture of
the people they serve, are designed to meet the social and economic needs of modern life.
This cultural decentralization, which is co-ordinated by the Council for Science and Culture of the Federal
People's Republic of Yugoslavia, has been accompanied by a series of measures to make education generally
available for the bulk of the people, and to provide generous financial allowances for the development of cultural
institutions.
When M. Jaime Torres Bodet, Director-General of Unesco, visited the cities of Belgrade, Ljubljana and
Zagreb recently as the guest of the Yugoslav Government, he was able to measure the extent of these efforts
and appreciate the practical results of the constructive collaboration between Yugoslavia and Unesco.
M TonnES BODET'S visit began in Belgrade, seat of theFedel'al Govel'nment, \vhere the Yugoslav National
Commission for Unesco was set up early this yea ;.
Severely damaged during the war, and in particular by
bombing attacks m 1941, the capital of the new Yugoslavia
is in the process of being rebuilt. On the ramparts of. the
ancient citadel, which down the centuries has occupied a
strategic site between the rivers Danube and Sava, an exhibi-
tion commemorating Yugoslavia's resistance and liberation
from 1941 to 1945 has been organized. It tells. simply and
effectively, the story of a courageous four years'struggle
waged by people who showed themselves capable of the
greatest sacrifices for the sake of their freedom.
Belgrade's university, which has always filled an important
r6) e in the political and intellectual ife of the country.
continues to maintain this tradition through the Intensive
studies and research carried out within Its walls. It was
here on September 28 that the Yugoslav National Commis-
sion for Unesco held its first meeting under its President,
Professor Sinisa Stankovic.
welcoming M. Torres Bodet, Professor Stankovlc declared :
"Our country has joined Unesco because It Is inspired by
a sincere wish to help the development of Intellectual co-
operation between peoples and states.
"Yugoslavia's Independence and freedom to develop
according to her own ideas have only been won at the cost
of great sacrifices. The maintenance of this Independence
and freedom is-today more than ever-Yugoslavia's su-
preme task.
"This country has been transformed into an enormous
workshop to build up a new future ; but we are flr ! !} l)' con-
vinced that this task will be accomplished above all by
fighting actively to safeguard and maintain peace.
"Fighting for peace means righting for the truth ; fighting.
by education and science, agamst war psychoses and hate
among peoples ; fighting, in fact, for mutual understanding
and respect as well as for international collaboration which
allows the different peoples of the world, great or small, to
develop freely their own national cultures."
At the same meeting, 1\1. Torres Bodet outlined the basic
principles which guide Unesco and the goals towards which
It works.
"Unesco takes care not to be guided in its actions by a
philosophy of uniformity"he satd."It is not the expres-
sion of anv one faith, or mode of thought, or way of civil-
ization. It is rather an ensemble of means of action for
realizing certain practical aims. These aims-peace and
general prosperity-and these means-the development of
education, science and culture through international collabora-
ton-correspond to some of the deepest aspirations of the
peoples.
INCREASING LIFE'S VALUE
/I F OR \'ho, indeed, would not desire to dwell in security.
improving by means of intellectual and moral co-
operation the conditions in which the v live' ! It is
then. onlv with these aims in view. and hy means
such as these, which are common to all mankind, setting
aside particular ideologies that Cnesco carries on its work.
On the other hand, the universatist character of its missions
is cleal'lv not to be denied.
"If t were to sum up the programme of L'nesco in a few
words. I should say that it aims at increasing the vatue of
human. life through educattun, science and culture.
"Secondly, as man cannot live In isolation, it seeks to
assist every country's progress towards a better way of life
through the augmented capacities of fuUy-educated citizens... And lastly, taking into account the dependence of one
country upon another, which makes collective isolation as
impossible and suffocating as individual solitude, L'nesco
tries to create or develop the intellectual and moral con-
dilions of international collaboration in peace, mutual assist-
ance, the iibertv of the peoples, and equality of rights."
During his tM'0 days'stay in the capita). 1\1. Torres Bodet
was receives, by Marshal Tito ; Mr. Edvard Kardelj, Foreign
Minister : Mr. Rodoljub Kolakovic, President of the Federal
Council for Science and Culture, and other leading figures
in the political and cultural life of the nation, including
M. Vladislav Ribnikar, a member of Unesco's Executive
Board.
M. Torres Bodet then travelled to Ljubljana, capital of the
People's Republic or Slovenia and a citv which is proud both
of its rich cultural heritage and of the advanced stage of
industrialization it has reached. This modern progress has
been aided by the work of the city's institute of technology
- visited by five Director-General-whose laboratories have
contributed to the economic and social progress of the whole
country.
Yugoslavia's reconstruction and {) \'ogressive industriaii-
zation has created a need for a growling army of specialized
workers. This is a problem IWluch the institutes or techno-,
logy, whose numbers have greatly increased since the war,
are helping to solve.
Unesco has already turned its attention to this acute
problem, a partial solution for which may be found by the
setting up under the Technical Assistance Programme or a
modern documentation centre and a scientific iibrary in
Yugoslavia.
During his visit to Ljubljana. Unesco's Director-General
was welcomed by Mr. Boris Ziherl. President of the Council
for Science and Culture in the Slovene People's Republic.
He also visited an exhibition commemorating the 400th anni-
versary of the printing of the first Slovene Book.
INTERNATIONAL CONTACTS
I x the City or Zagreb the Director-General visited the Aca-demy of Arts and Science, set up by the Croat people in
the middle of the 19th century. From Its founda-
tion this institution ptayed. in the field of cultures and
literature, a leading part in the liberation and political uni-
fication of the Yugoslav peoples, and today it continues to
hold a vital place in the intellectual life of Croatia.
l'nder its aegis, a series of institutes and laboratories to
carry out specialized \work of direct importance to the
indusll'ial and economic development of the country has
been set up since 1945.
Visits to the Institute which carries out research into
problems of workers'heaith, as well as 10 the Physics
Institute of the University, showed the Director-Genera) the
important part. which Croatia can p) ay in the service of the
Yugoslav peoples. Similarly, in the Zagreb Academy, the
Croat people. have a modern centre of artistic and cultural
rife. One of the best examples of the vitality of this present
day culture is the work of the great sculptor Mestrovic.
many of his sculptures are to be found n Zagreb's Museum.
Allied to the effort which Yugoslavia is making to build
its new social order is a firm wish to co-operate inter-
nationally. Yugoslav intellectual circles attach the greatest
importance to the contacts and intellectual exchanger which
Lnesco can help to establish in all its fie : ds of activity.
Already they are participating in the work of several
organizations set up under Unesco's auspices such as the
International Theatre Institute and the International Council
of Museums. Yugoslavia is turning. more and more to
Unesco for help and technical advice. In this connection a
mission of experts may be sent to assist in the resioraion
of one of the most ancient and noble monuments of medIeval
Yugoslavia-the church of St. Sophia in Macedonia.
Yugoslavia's scientists, scholars and men of letters are
clearly showing their \viliingness to associate themselves
with all Unesco's efforts which can contribute directiy to
the maintenance of peace and the development of inter-
national understanding.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1951 Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
YUGOSLAVIA'S UNIVERSITIES ARE GUARDING
TRADmONS WH ! LE SERVtNG MODERN NEEDS
Dhl'OUghout centuries of in-
yasion and oppressive outside
tJ) influences, the peoples of
Yugoslavia have retained a deep
attachment for their own tra-
ditions, languages and cultures.
The history of their universities
is a reflection of this struggle
between culture and war, which
might easily be symbolized in the
story of the first Yugoslav
printing works. Shortly after
this was set up at Cettinje in 1493,
the town was attacked by the
Turks-and the people of Cettinje
had to melt down the type to make
ammunition.
If, even in recent times, Yugo-
slavia had an unduly high illiteracy
rate, this was probably because its
inhabitants were more often called
upon to take up arms to defend
their country than to study and
work for its development. But,
even after the worst devastation,
they have always found strength
and courage to rebuild on the
ruins.
Nowadays, the Yugoslav univer-
sities can at last fulfil the aims of
those who founded them and then
often fought hard to keep them
in existence. They link respect
for the rich cultural traditions of
each republic with the task of
instructing men and women in the
modern techniques of which the
nation has need.
Success has meant valiant effort
and heavy sacrifices. After the
second world war, it was not only
the universities of Yugoslavia that
had to be reconstructed, but its
entire schooling system : for
eighty per cent of the schools had
been destroyed. Now, not only
the universities have been rebuilt,
but many new institutes of higher
studies have been set up.
Before the war, there were three
universities in Yugoslavia, with 21
faculties and eight centres for
higher education. Now there are
five universities, with 42 faculties
and 25 attached centres. The
number of students has risen
from 17, 734 in 1938 to 60, 000 in
1950.
Shut by an empire
study of the history of
Yugoslav universities shows
that they have some common
characteristics. The oldest, which
were founded by the religious
orders, had to fight for centuries to
maintain their right to teach in
their own languages. Those most
recently established are constantly
trying to link traditional studies
- philosophy, theology, law-with
technical instruction.
The University of Ljubljana,
founded by the Jesuits in 1595, is
the country's oldest. Originally
confined to faculties of theology
and philosophy, it was not until
the setting up of the Illyrian Pro-
vinces (1809-13) that it began to
extend. It was in this period that
the"central schools"first came
into being. A period of general
instruction was substituted for
philosophy, and this was followed
by four or five years of higher
studies. Later, when the"se-
condary school"was separated
from the"academy", a university
in the real sense of the word was
formed, with five faculties : philo-
sophy, natural sciences, medicine,
law and theology.
But, after the fall of Napoleon,
Slovenia once again was incor-
porated into the Austro-Hunga-
rian Empire, and the higher
studies of the University of Ljub-
ljana were cut down to what they
had been before the French re-
gime. In 1848, despite Slovene
pleas for a university in their
capital, the imperial government
closed Ljubljana's schools of
higher studies, and education was
concentrated in the German-
language areas. The fight for the
setting up of a Slovene university,
however, continued right up to the
end of imperial domination. In
1919, after the collapse of the Cen-
tral Powers, the Slovene univer-
sity got back its prerogatives, with
four faculties (philosoDhy, law,
technical instruction and the-
ology), and a school of medicine.
Reconstructed and re-organized
after the second world war, the
university of Ljubljana now has
four faculties : philosophy, natu-
ral sciences and mathematics, law
and economics. The technical fa-
culty has become an institute of
technical studies with six facul-
ties : architecture, civil engineer-
ing, electrical engineering, ma-
chine construction, chemistry,
mines and metallurgy. The faculty
of medicine is divided into two fa-
culties : medicine and stomatology.
Autonomous institutes, outside the
university, have taken over instruc-
tion formerly given by the faculties
of theology, agriculture and forest-
ry. Its scope therefore is very va-
ried, but its modern techniques
have not meant any lessening of
respect for Slovene traditions and
culture.
State aids 60 her cent
If tel'Ljubljana, Zagreb is the
i oldest of Yugoslavia's uni-
versities. It was in 1632
that the Jesuits started to
widen the scope of their Zagreb
school by adding theology and
philosophy to the curriculum.
On September 23, 1669, the
Emperor Leopold I accorded the
rights and privileges of an inde-
pendent university to the Academy
of Zagreb-privileges already en-
joyed by those of Cologne and
Prague. This meant the rector
had the right to confer the degrees
of doctor, licentiate and bachelor,
and that these degrees would be
recognized elsewhere. But, in
practice, the university could only
partly avail itself of these rights.
In 1773, at the suppression of
the Jesuits, the Academy of Za-
greb was placed under the autho-
rity of a bishop. Three years la-
ter, the Academy of Sciences was
set up by order of the Empress
Maria Theresa. In 1848, however,
this Academy of Sciences was sup-
pressed, and the Faculty of Phi-
losophy dissolved. Only the Facul-
ty of Law continued to function,
as an independent juridical acade-
my, and from 1853 to 1860 lec-
tures were given in German. It was
not until 1874 that a university
was established again in Zagreb,
with three faculties : philosophy,
theology and medicine.
Today, the University of Zagreb
has ten faculties, compared with
seven before the war. The number
of students has risen from 6, 436
in 1939 to 16, 000 in 1950. Sixty
per cent are assisted by State
grants, and the annual influx of
new students is such that the
building of a vast university city
has been undertaken.
Respect for diversity
melgrade University was, at its
. origin, a secondary school in
Kragujevac. Founded in
1838, it was transferred to Bel-
grade in 1841. In 1863 it became
a centre for higher education with
three faculties (philosophy, law
and technical instruction) and in
1905 it was designated as Belgrade
University. Of all the Yugoslav
universities Belgrade suffered most
in the second world war. Out
of 174 institutes, seminaries and
laboratories, 72 were completely
destroyed, while another 58 lost
half their installations and col-
lections.
It was largely thanks to the ef-
forts of the students themselves
that the University of Belgrade
has since, not only been recon-
structed, but also enlarged. Once
again, the need to expand and to
facilitate studies and technical re-
search has led to wide changes in
its structure. In 1948, the tech-
nical faculty was separated from
the University and made into a
higher education centre which
ranks as a university. It is com-
posed of the faculties of architec-
ture, civil engineering, electrical
engineering, machinery construc-
tion, mines and technology, geolo-
gy. Today the faculties of medi-
cine, pharmacology and stomato-
logy are being reorganized, and
will soon be formed into a School
of Medical Studies. Over 25, 000
students now attend the Univer-
sity.
The reform of the old Yugoslav
universities, which was under-
taken at the same time as their
postwar reconstruction, answered
the need for extending and improv-
ing the technical instruction that
they could give. It is this same
need that has led to the foundation
of new universities, and the estab-
lishment in each of the Yugo-
slav republics of an independent
cultural centre. Thus, in the same
way as Ljubljana is the Slovene
University, Zagreb the Croat Uni-
versity, and Belgrade the Serbian
one, so Skoplje is the University
Centre of Macedonia, and Sarajevo
that of Bosnia-each of them
deeply steeped in the traditions and
cultural lives of the people they
serve. Respect for this diversity
has also led the Yugoslav Govern-
ment to set up schools for many
linguistic minorities. Thus, Ru-
manian, Czech and Slovak children
living in Yugoslavia receive in-
struction in their own languages.
Entry will be difficult
The progressive elimination of
illiteracy and the economic
progress made by the country
have caused a number of students
to increase three-fold since the
war, thus raising serious problems.
Entry to the universities, there-
fore, will shortly become. more dif-
ficult, and examinations will aim
more and more at restricting en-
try to those who show themselves
most likely to benefit from the
instruction.
These then are Yugoslavia's uni-
versities. Built and maintained
over the centuries with courage
and perseverance, rebuilt or newly
established despite every diffi-
culty, they show the attachment
of their founders to their own
cultures. Since the last war, the
enthusiam which has led teach-
ers and students to join their
efforts in constructing-sometimes
with their own hands-laborator-
ies and libraries, university cities
and faculty buildings, is further
proof of the courage and faith
with which the Yugoslavs are
making their ancient country into
a modern one.
Medical students listen as Professor Andrija Stampar, President of the Faculty of Medicine at Zagreb and President of the
Yugoslav Academy of Science and Art in Zagreb, gives a lecture in the University of Zagreb.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 4 NOVEMBER 1951
FOLKLORE IS AN EVERYDAY
EVENT) N YUGOSLAV ! A
YUGOSLAVIA is one of the few European countries
where folklore is not something to be revived
on special occasions, but a prominent feature
of everyday life.
The Yugoslav villager consider it quite normal
to sing or dance over his daily joys and sorrows.
He can express his joie de vivre in humorous
dances, work dances, miming dances, his unhappi-
ness in combined song-dances. He can display his
vigour in the so-called"deaf"or"mute"dances,
which have no musical accompaniment.
But all these vary wlaely U'on
one region to another. Yugo-
slavia's cultural heritage has
come under Greek, Turkish, even
Russian influences ; yet, the na-
tional obstacles which her moun-
tains present have, to a large
extent, resulted in each area
retaining its own original and
different folklore.
Musical traditions in the towns
for instance, are quite different
from those in the country. Urban
folklore is mainly homophonic,
while that of the rural areas is
polyphonic. These local va-
riations are also found in dance
steps. In the mountains, where
the shepherds are usually alert,
their dancing is nimble. In the
plains, it is more"heavy"-
nearer to the soil, so to speak.
by Georges Fradier
shuttle. Then there is the sostarska, which imi-
tates the shoe repairer as he sews, drills and drives
in the nails. In Macedonia, the metalworker is
represented in a dance which shows the cleaning
of copperware with the feet before it is tinplated.
The work of the farm has also inspired the
poetry of the dance. Six singing youngsters drag-
ging a plough which bears a couple of festooned
pine trees will pretend to dig three furrows in
INTERNATIONAL MUSIC COUNCIL WILL ISSUE
'GUIDE BOOK'FOR LOVERS OF FOLK MUSIC
Serene, tenacious
THE Yugoslavs, it is said, are
serene and tenacious : cer-
tainly these qualities are
reflected in the oro dances.
These dances will often have a
sung accompaniment, which can
vary from plaintive chants to
(what is more usual) the most
joyful of rhythms. At other
times, musical accompany. meant is
played on instruments made by
the peasants with tools they use
in their daily work-flutes and
drums in Bosnia and Hercego-
vina, gusle violins in Monte-
negro, gajde bagpipes in Croatia.
The art of making these instru-
ments has been handed down
from father to soy. But chanees
are creeping in : instead of using these instruments,
more and more people now go to the shops in the
towns to buy accordeons.
The Yugoslav dances to express the most varied
of emotions or circumstances. Sometimes his
dances are transformed into pantomimes, with
humorous digs at the individual or at people in
general. Drunkenness and laziness are typical sub-
jects for this satire in dance which easily becomes
a play or comedy.
An infinite variety of dances deal with his many
crafts. In Slovenia, for instance, he likes the
thalecka polka, a survival of the weavers'country
fetes. A handkerchief which the dancers pass
underneath their knees represents the weaver's
T XTEREST in folk music is becoming Increasingly widespread. while some people findin it something of the spirit of life in pre-industrial times, others are attracted
by the musical richness of folk melodies from which so many modern composers
have drawn inspiration.
Though they cannot be classed directly with the concert-going public, such people do,
however, represent the strongest group of opponents to mass produced melodies and
pseudo-jazz.
Never satisfied with their own often too arbitrarilv defined national folklore. these
enthusiasts feel the urge to explore the wider avenues of the world's musical folklore.
They like, for example, to compare a Scottish song with one from Iceland, or a French
ballad with a chant from the Russian steppes. Wet, in their desire to come closer to the
things that attract them, they meet with all snorts of difficulties.
Today one rarely comes across collections of folk music, and those that exist generally
cover a few selected areas or are intended only for specialists. Moreover their authen-
ticity is by no means assured. In any case the writing down of folk songs presents
many problems, especially when their essential characteristics lie in the vocal inflexions
of the singer. Yet, despite such difficulties, the International Music Council is publishing.
with Unesco's help, an international collection of this type of music compiled by leading-
specialists, which should be especially useful for the teaching of folk music in schools.
As a teaching aid, however, no book or published text can replace a recording of
authentic folk music. The value of these records, unfortunately, varies considerably,
and it is generally impossible for the public to verify, their genuincnøss.
It. is true that valuable work is being done by such institutes as the Library of Congress
in the United States, Ie Musée d'Ethnographie in Switzerland, and the Musee de I'Homme
in France. Up to the present, however, no international authority has ever offered to
provide lovers of folk music with a complete and accurate catalogue.
This situation is now to he changed by a recent decision of the International music
Council. At its conference at Opatija, in Yugoslavia, the Council decided to compile a
catalogue of all authentic folk musIc recordings made to date both by commercial com-
panies and scientific institutions.
Unesco is supporting this initiative, which complements its own past work in this
fleld. Under the Organization's auspices, for example, the International Music Council
is publishing a World Collection of Recorded Folk Music, the first album of which was
received M'ith enthusiasm by experts at the Opatija conference.
is stripped from a birch tree in a ceremony honour-
ing the spirit of Spring.
The origin of the ritual dances goes back into
the distant past, and in certain cases-such as
the rusalia-they are a reminder of pagan
cults. Some still bear traces of ancient customs
which called for sacrifices.
No people and no era is without its romantic
dances. The Yugoslavs have their wedding dances,
which imitate the ceremony and the preparations
for it, and the young bride going to her new home.
tion and elopement.
War, too, is an inevitable
theme. A favourite dance recalls
the exploits of a princely hero.
Another, probably dating from
the 16th century, tells of Turkish
raids into Croatia, and is a form
of defiance against the con-
queror.
The koala, which originated in
the centre of Serbia-so rich in
folklore-is the most widely
known dance, although its steps
vary greatly in the different pro-
vinces and villages. But the koala,
like another Yugoslav dance, the
lessee, always remains a collective
dance.
In each of these, the leader
plays an important role-and, in
Macedonia, an indispensable one.
It is he who starts and finishes
the dance, and orders the change-
over from one movement to an-
other, like the leader of a quad-
rille. He may separate himself
from the others to perform spe-
cial steps ; for he is not only the
best dancer, but also a person of
note, worthy of this honour and
the reponsibility it brings.
The extraordinary vitality of
the Yugoslav dance-the most
expressive and richest form of
a centuries-old culture-surprised
foreign visitors at the recent
Opatija festival. Every Yugo-
slav republic chose. from the
remotest villages the groups
which were considered most
worthy to represent their art.
More than 700 men, women and
front of a house, and wish the owner of the house
good luck and an abundant harvest. Evil spirits
of winter, darkness and illness flee before the
youthful strength of the"ploughmen,"who repre-
sent the good spirits of spring, light and health.
In Serbia, masked dancers perform magic rites
called koleda, as they dance around platters contain-
ing the products of the soil to frighten off evil.
'Hagic* is dying out
BUT Yugoslavia's magic and ritual dances, which
are reserved for special feasts, appear to be
dying out, although they have lost nothing of
their liveliness and freshness. In Slovenia, for
instance, during the ritual dance of St. George, bark
children took part in the festival, which was
acclaimed by the critics as something of un-
forgettable beauty and passionate interest.
To preserve their artistic traditions in all their
true anthenticity, every village has its own folk-
lore group, while the youth societies and the trade
unions have brought together over 50, 000 dancers
in the towns. There are also professional groups.
In Yugoslavia, folk dancing therefore is not just
something reserved for special occasions. It has
kept its vitality, fostered by the creative imagina-
tion of the people. It is something that is spon-
taneous and improvised. There can be few
countries where folklore has such enthusiastic
support.,
AFTER 500 YEARS,
MOSLEM WOMEN IN
YUGOSLAVIA NOW
SHED THEIR VEILS
Since the end of the war, social legislation in
Yugoslavia has been progressively aimed at
removing inequalities in status between men and
women. This year, the promulgation of a law
abolishing the wearing of the veil by Moslem
women was an important step in efforts to
help these women to take a more active part in
the social and economic life of the country.
Whole districts of Bosnia-Hercegovina and of
Macedonia are completely Moslem in culture
and population. These peoples, however, are
not a Turkish minority left behind after 500
years of Ottoman rule, but the descendants of
Southern Slavs who embraced Islamism during
this period. The effect of this law prohibiting
the wearing of veils-a custom which has set
Yugoslav Moslem women apart for some 500
years-is illustrated above in the photographs
of one woman member of the country's 1, 600, 000
Moslem people. Until this year, Miss Hanka
Zeko, village school teacher at Katcharevo, in
the province of Kosmet, had to wear the
faredjia or veil whenever she went out (1).
After the passing of the Government decree,
Miss Zeko, without her veil for the first time,
gives a geography lesson in the classroom (2),
and leads playtime games in the school
courtyard beside the minaretted mosque (3).
o [f) J ø
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
A young man joins village girls from Macedonia in na struga ducan, one of the most popular dances of this region.
Recital by an old Slavonic piper in national costume. Lightness characterizes this dance performed by the Rumanian minority.
The tchifte tchantche is a popular dance in Bitol
NOVEMBER 1951
LAND OF COLOURFUL DANCES
The Slavonic kolo visa colourful round dance full of movement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A NEW nation will be born on Jan-uary 1, 1952, when the three pro
vinces of a former Italian colony
will be united as the independent State
of Libya-the first country in history
to be created by a world organization.
Since World War II, Cyrenaica and
Tripolitania have temporarily been
administered by the United Kingdom
and the Fezzan by France. The future
status of the three regions was finally
settled in November 1949, when thé
United Nations General Assembly, without
a dissenting vote, recommended that
Cyrenaica, Tripolitania and Fezzan
"shall be constituted an independent,
sovereign State."
PoliticaIIy, Libya is weIl on the road to
shouldering the responsibilities of State-
hood. A provisional government was
established by the Libyan National
Assembly in March, 1951. This Assembly
also recommended that Sayed Mohamed
Idriss El Sennusi, the Amir of Cyrenaica,
should become the constitutional monarch
of the new country, the United Kingdom
of Libya.
But national viability requires more
than a political constitution. Mr. Adrian
Pelt, who has been United Nations
Commissioner in Libya since January
1950, has continually emphasized that
the United Nations has an equally great
responsibility in providing Libya with
the technical assistance it needs to
develop a sound economy and set up
efficient governmental machinery.
The immensity of this task is express-
ed in his reports. The three regions of
Libya total 1, 150, 000 inhabitants living on
1, 750, 000 square kilomètres, but much of
this land is desert. The country's
average per capita income is a mètre
$35 a year.
Mr. Pelt summed up Libya as"an
THE UNITED NATIONS HELPS A NEW STATE
. Ta PREPARE FOR INDEPENDENCE
LI BYA
underdevelcped area with a marginal
agricultural economy, basically handi-
capped by inadequate rainfall and poor
soil :' Irrigation, dry farming, and
animal husbandry in the coastal regions,
however, can support Libya once she
possesses the knowledge and skills needed
to work land in these regions efficiently.
This need raises serious educational
problems. From 1942 to 1946, no schools
were open in Libya. Even today, the
elementary school population of the
entire region is only 39, 000 (and no more
than a few hundred children attend
secondary schools). Mr. Pelt reported that
Libya's minimum requirement is school-
ing for 100, 000.
This deficiency, couplet with antiquat-
ed agricultural methods and heavy war
damage, Jed him to write :"Unless means
are found to improve the agricultural
techniques of the country and to bring
in new capital investment, there is a
grave danger that the Libyan economy
will sink back toward a pastoral economy
of nomadism, with inevitable social and
political consequences which may jeo-
pardise the very existence of the State."
In July 1950, at Mr. Pelt's request, a
United Nations mission surveyed Libya
to ascertain in what ways the United
Nations Expanded Programme of Tech-
nical Assistance for Economic Develop-
ment could help the creation of the new
State. On the recommendations of this
mission, a programme was drawn up
showing the means by which the United
Nations and its Specialized Agencies
could begin furnishing aid.
This called for international experts to
begin work in Libya in such fields as
pilblic finance, education, agriculture,
viticulture, irrigation, wool production,
electric power and social welfare.
A study of public finance in Libya has
already been published, and the United
Nations experts are now advising on
specifie problems. In the field of vital
statistics, a sample census of three
selected tribes has been conducted, thus
giving the region reliable demographic
statistics-a prerequisite for any sound
economic development plan.
In the field of education, Unesco was
given a specialized rôle. Working in
co-operation with the British administra-
tion of Tripolitania, it has set up a
technical training centre to prepare
young Libyans for posts in the new
government.
This centre, in which 230 students
were enrolled during its first year of
operation, does not aim much higher
than supplying the foundations-the
clerks, the typists and the secretaries-
needed for an efficient civil service.
Unesco is alsQ awarding fellowships to
enable Libyans to study abroad and
prepare themselves for higher adminis-
trative posts in their country's new
government.
In addition, Unesco has begun to
establish another centre in Libya design-
ed to train primary school teachers and
to produce the teaching materials they
require. This centre is also intended to
furnish specialized personnel tue attack
the problem of illiteracy, of which Libya
has a high percentage.
In ail, more than sixty experts have
been sent te Libya by the United Nations
and its Agencies and nearly 50 fellowships
and scholarships have been awarded.
This aid has been described by
Mr. Pelt as"one of the most constructive
and most useful examples"of how the
United Nation's technical assistance
programme for underdeveloped regions
can operate.
FEZZAN
Greatest area, fewest people
THE Fezzan is bounded on the west bv southernJL Algeria, southern Tunisia and Tunisia, n the
south by Trench zest Africa and French Equa-
torial Africa, on the East by Cyrenaica and on the north
hy Tripolitania. It is a vast depression, with an area
of some 800, 000 square kilometres, enclosed within pla-
teaux which isolate it from the sea-some 500 to 600 kilo-
metres distant-and from the neighbouring lands.
Within the depression lie three oases-Sebha, Brak and
Murzak-around which is grouped the non-migratory
population. Widely scattered and thinly planted
palm groves are also to be found in the Zelal.
The population of the Fezzan is estimated at 50, 000,
of which one-fifth are nomads or semi-nomads. The
non-migratory population is found within the depres-
sion ; on its fringe and beyond live thé nomadic or semi-
uomadic peoples. In the north these are tribes of fair-
skinned stock with a strong Berber influence. In the
south, in the foothills of the Tibesti and in ail thé area
as far as Fort Lamy, Tebbous of Hamitic origin are to
be found. ln the Tassili, in the west, there are sections
of the Berber Confederation of the Tuareg-Adjer, who
are scattered between Timbuctoo and Nigeria.
Ethnically, the non-migratory population of the
interior is mixed, containing Elements of both fair and
black races. They ! ive among palm trees, cultivating
wheat, dates, barley, millet and sorghum. This popu-
lation can be divided into two groups ; three-quarters
are very poor, deriving their livelihood from the harsh
and unremitting labour with which they irrigate small
lots of land ; the remaining quarter might be described
as the middle class of the country, living in relative ease.
These are the landowners, traders and officiais.
The subsistence economy of thé Fezzan, based upon
an oasis pals-gardien culture, is handicapped hy the
difficulty of obtaining water and by primitive methods
of irrigation and cultivation. The depressed economic
situation is reflected in the under-nourishment of the
population and the al1llUal emigration, which further
aggravates the problem of manpower.
The chief resource of the Fezzan is the date patm.
Estimâtes of their number vary considerably, but most
of them are wild and uncultivated, and it is probable
that not more than 1, 000, 000 date palms are product-
ive. The date crop, of about 15, 000 tons annuaUy,
is in excess of local needs, and the surplus is bartered
for oil and barley with the nomads or exported by cara-
van or lorry. The poor quality of the crop, together
with the transport cost to markets, limits its export
value. Local production of grain is insufficient to
meet the requirements of the population 3nd must be
supplemented by imports. The meagre grazing sup-
ports few animais.
In the three principal valleys of the Fezzan, a water
table of varying depth makes it possible to increase the
area of irrigated land, either by open wells in the areas
where the phreatic folds are near the surface or by
flowing wells from the artesian lever. open weus, in
the present stage of technical development, can only
be exploited by traditional methods, efforts to introduce
Free elections were a novel experience for the people of Libya, some of whom are
shown here in animated discussion during polling at Tobruk (Cyrenaica). About
80 per cent of Cyrenica's townsmen and 66 per cent of tribesmen voted.
A citizen of the new United Kingdom of Liya.
This Tuareg from Fezzan wears the litham or
shawl muffler, which is wound round the mouth
to keep out the blown sand of the desert.
A meeting of the National Assembly of Libya, taking place under the chairmanship of the Mufti of Tripoli, Mohammed Abdul
Asa'd AI Alem. The three territories are represented equally, each by 20 delegates : the Cyrenaicans at left, theTripolitanians
at right and the Fezzanese in the foreground.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
pctroieumpumps havingprovedafaiiure. Artesian
wells, which do not require the labour of men and beast,
not only relieve the pressure on the utilization of man-
power, but also provide for a greater area of irrigable
land in proportion to expenditure.
The condition of the serf-like jebbad or drawer of
water, bound by a system of contracts to the proprietor
and receiving only a share of the harvest, has been pro-
gressively improved during the French administration.
The lot of the jebbad and the entire population can be
improved by the further distribution of newly irrigated
lands, continued supervision of the harvesting and stor-
age of crops and maintenance of the security of the
non-migratory population against raids by nomads.
The only known minerai resource of commercial value
is natron (sodium carbonate), the annual export of
which is less than 100 tons. There is no industry ;
rudimentary handicrafts have only limited local import-
ance.
TRtPOUTAN) A
Main asset-farming
THE existing administrative division between Tripo-± Utania and the Fezzan was agreed t  F ance
and the United Kingdom for the duration of the
occupation of Libya. Tripolitania, by this definition,
extends over some 250, 000 square kilometres between
Tnnisia and Cyrenaica. The greater part of its area is
desert. The widely settled parts of Tripolitania consist,
first of the narrow coastal belt of oases between ; \visu-
rata and Zuara, which contains 60 per cent of the popu-
lation of the territory, and, secondly, of the northern
edge of the Jebel, a broken plateau running north-east
from the Tunisian frontier to Homs, where it intersects
the coastal belt. The Jebel is separated from the coast-
al area by a wedge of steppe, and south and west of
the Jebel this merges into semi-desert and desert country
suitable only for pastoralism and the shifting cultivation
of barley. The total area of productive land varies
with the annuairainfai), but only about 1. 6 per cent of
the total area is devoted to static farming. This area
is, however, generally well-watered and ofIers a fertility
in striking contrast to the greater part of Libya.
The population of Tripolitania is estimated at 800, 000.
The indigenous population, numbering about 730, 000,
is Arab with a considerable admixture of Berbers, of
whom some groups in the. western part of the country
have retained their distinction of community and their
langage, and continue to folio,,'the schismatic lbadite
rite. Arabs and Berbers live amicably together in spite
of past différences. AIl are ; \Ioslems ; the religious
followers of the Senussi Order have been estimated at 30
per cent of ail ; \Ioslems.
The urban population is about 165, 000. Some 105, 000
Moslems live in the towns, mainly engaged in handi-
crafts and small trade. ylost of the rural population
are settled farmers living in the coastal oases and in the
Djebel. Semi-nomads are numerous, both in the Jebel
and in the steppe areas bordering the oases. lnasmuch
as many of the non-migrating population combine
pastoralism and shifting cereal cultivation with statìc
farming during parts of the year, it is impossible rigirlly
tociassify thé population bynumbersaccordingto thé
ways of lifte. The wholly nomadie population is much
less important than in Cyrenaica and is found principally
in the Sirtica and Ghibla areas. Only among the nomads
and a few of the hi) i tribes exists the closely knit tribal
structure which characterizes Cyrenaica. ln the more
prosperous and populous coastal ares thé tribe is grad-
ually giving way to a village and town society.
The minorities comprise about 45, 000 Italian, 13, 000
Jews, 2, 000 Maltese and 400 Greeks. The level of the
Italian community has, as far as possible, been main-
tained numerically by the British Administration at the
point ta which it had fallen at the end of the war. The
Italians, about haIf of whom are town dwellers, have
large commercial and agricultural interests which had
been developed during Italian rule.
The Jewish minority, now almost exclusively urban,
has been rapidly diminishing in the last 18 months
because of emigration, largely to Israel.'fhis sxodus
has reduced the Jewish community from about 29, 000
in 1948 to 13, 000. The rate of Emigration has recently
s) ackened.
The economy of Tripolitania is based principally on
agriculture, animal husbandry and fisheries, with esparto
grass and rough handicrafts as auxiliary resources.
Olives, barley, citrus fruits and grapes, which cover a
considerable area of the coastal beat, are the principal
crops. The Moslem population of the coastal belt lives
chiefly by gardens and palm groves, cultivating market
crops and fruit tress irrigated from wells operated
1I10stly by animal power. Some Arabs have, however,
undertakenfarmingona) argersca) e. Inthenorthern
part of the Jebel olives and other fruits are grown in
important quantities and tobacco, which is a monopoly
of the British Administration as it was of the Italian,
is grown with some success, although it is mostly of
inferior quality. ln the steppe and semi-desert sheep
and goats are pastured and bar) ey cultivated by scratch
pioughing.
The ltalian cOll1munity outside the town is chiefly
engaged in the cultivation of olives, citrus fruits, vines,
almonds, and, on a lesser scale, wheat. Thé Italian
farms, both private concessions and para-statal settle-
ments, represent a remarkab) e feat of pioneering and
land recJamation, which, chiefly owing to the comparat-
ively long period of immaturity of the olive tree, has
only recently begl\n to demonstrate its full productive
value. Indeed, many of the plantations wili not bear
fully for some years ta come. They are, however, the
greatest economic asset of the territory, an asset which
can easily be lost if constant care to prevent erosion and
other deterioration is not maintained. Both the con-
cessions and the ettlements were assisted by the con-
siderable tax exemptions, subsidies and credit facilities
accorded to agriculture by the Italian Government. A
certain unbalance is becoming apparent in their nnan-
cial position as a resu) t of the graduai expiration of these
facilities, and it is likely that some measures wiII be
needed in order to maintain them, since production and
markets are not yet proportionate ta the capital and
maintenance outlays.
After two years of serious droughts in 1947 and 1948,
the territory has enjoyed good harvests, and export-
able surpluses of agricultural products have increased.
CYRENAICA
Problem No. 1 is water
CYRENAICA extends over 700, 000 square kilometres.It lies betwe  the Western Desert of Egypt on
theeastandTripolitaniaonthewest. On the
south, it reaches to the Anglo-Egyptian Sndan and the
mountain wilderness of the Tibesti, in French Equatorial
Africa. Its area is almost enÜrely désert, which is
rainless throughout the year. In the north, however,
a low plateau of limestone hills benefits from rainfall
adequate for the profitable cultivation of cereals and
fruit. A number of fresh-water springs are also to be
found in the hills, which support a considerable vegeta-
tion. This plateau is fringed by a narrow coastal belt,
where the rainfaIl again declines. The plateau grad-
ually falls away to plains in the south and east, which
provide pasture over a considerable area and where
barley is grown, as the rainfaIl permits, year by year.
In the few oases of the southern desert, date palms and
some vegetables are grown.
The population of Cyrenaica is estimated at 300, 000,
the overwhelming majority of which are Arabs. There
is a Jewish minority of some 200, reduced from 4, 500
in 1948, and smalt Maltese and Greek communities.
Except for a few priests and nuns, the Italian pre-war
population left the country before its final occupation
by the AIlied Forces.
The town-dwellers number some 85, 000. The rural
population consists mainly of semi-nomadic tent-
dwetlers, mostly inhabiting the coastal plateau where
they cultivate their barley and herd their animais. On
the plateau tribal boundaries are weIl defined and nomad-
ism consequently severely restricted. In the de sert
fringes to the south of the plateau the vagaries of the
rainfall necessitate a greater latitude of movement, but
it is only a minority which leave their habitat on the
plateau to find grazing and cultivate in the désert. thé
rural population is organized in tribes, among whom the
land is divided. The main tribes (Sa'adi) hold their
land by right of conquest dating from the Arab invasion
inthellthcentury. In addition, there are dependent
groups (Marabitin) who have attached themselves to
the powerful Sa'adi tribes. AU the Bedouin daim pure
Arabian extraction, but there is undoubtedly an admix-
ture of Berber stock, especially in the oases to the south
of the plateau.
The economy of Cyrenaica is handicapped by the
lack of natural resources and the underdevelopment of
its land and water. lt is based on the raising of live-
stock which is carried on, together with the shifting culti-
vation of barley, by the majority of the rural population.
On the northern plateau, however, and in some parts
of the coastal belt, wheat is grown by modern mothods,
and olives, vines, apricots, and other fruits thrive to-
gether with market vegetables. The development of this
area is actively encouraged by the ministre of Agricul-
ture.
11ljornlatÎol1 yiuen ÌIl these payes reyardiny the yeoyraphy,
populalion and economy of Ihe Ihree regions of Libya, is laken
tram Ihe report of Ihe United Nations Commissioner i/1 Libya la
1/.. l'nited l\"alions Secretary-General.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8 NOVEMBER) 95)-
TEACHING OF COLLECTIVE SECURITY
AIDED BY UNESCO PAMPHLETS
PEACE and collective security among annations ultimately depend upon the
thoughts and feelings of individual men
and women ever. ywhere on earth-and educa-
tion remains an indispensable means for
developing such individual attitudes of aware-
ness and co-operation.
The authority for this view is Professor A.
Appadorai, formerly of Madras University in
India, one of the world's most distinguished
experts and educators in the field of inter-
national relations, and author of a pamphlet
entitled Collective Security, one of three on
the subject prepared for Unesco and just
published by the Organization as part of its
vigorously continuing efforts to explain and
make widely known the principles and activ-
ities of the United Nations.
"The relevant attitude to be cultivated,"the
Indian educator explains,"consists of two ele-
ments : nrst. the attitude of'live and let live',
a sense of tolerance and cha-
rity, a recognition that the very
existence of a diversity of cul-
tures contributes to the increase
of human happiness ; and, se-
cond, the attitude of non-vio-
lence, that is, the recognition
that a bellicose attitude is not
something inherent in man, but
that man is by nature a social
unit capable of living in neigh-
bourly friendliness and love."
Parallel with Professor Appa-
dorai's pamphlet, written in
English, Unesco has published
two companion works, one in
French prepared by Dr. Jean
Dupuy, Secretary-General of
the French Association for the
United Nations, and one in
Spanish by Professor Guillermo
Francovich, Rector of the San
Francisco Xavier University of
Sucre, Bolivia. Their titles are
L'Etablissement de lea Security
Collective and La Seguridad Co-
lectiva lnternacional.
of Unesco's General Conference in Paris
in July 1951 declared moreover"that, if
there is to be widespread understanding of-and
popular support for United Nations action,
there must be adequate education regarding
specific acts of aggression and breaches of the
peace, as well as the actions taken by the
United Nations to maintain and restore the
peace". (The full text of this resolution is
published on this page.) The Executive Board
and the Director-General were authorized to
provide"widespread understanding"of United
Nations action to maintain or restore peace
whenever the Security Council or the General
Assembly took such action.
"History", says Professor Appadori in
analyzing the meaning of collective security,
"is in large measure a record of man's efforts
to achieve greater security together with per-
sonal freedom. War, with the aid of science,
has come to mean total annihilation. Clearly,
Foundations of peace
T HEI preparation and pub-
j lication by Unesco stems
directly from the Con-
stitution of the Organiza-
tion, for the view of Professor
Appadorai, shared by Dr. Dupuy
and Professor Francovich, that
collective security depends upon
the attitudes of individual men
and women, links directly with
the statements in Unesco's basic
Charter that :
"Since wars begin in the
minds of men, it is in the minds
of men that the defences of
peace must be constructed... the
education of humanity for jus-
tice and liberty and peace are
indispensable to the dignity of
man and constitute a sacred
duty which all nations must
fulfll in a spirit of mutual
assistance and concern... peace
must therefore be founded, if it
is not to fail, upon the intellect-
ual and moral solidarity of
mankind."
All three pamphlets are de-
signed to provide teaching aids
for use in primary and adult
education, as part of the sup-
port which Unesco gives in the
various fields within its compet-
mint t. n t. np. < : t. ru ! ! ! ! le of the'-'. 1.'-''''' \IV \1. 1."'" VU"'''''''bÞ'''''''.............-
United Nations on behalf of the collective
security on which a just and durable peace
depends. From the very start of its existence,
Unesco has carried out educational activities
in the light of the judgment that the subject
of collective security is of such vital import-
ance to mankind that it demands well-
informed and objective study.
The decision that the Organization should
select collective security as a major theme in
its educational work was made by the Execut-
ive Board in September 1950, in the light of
the action taken by the United Nations with
respect to Korea, and at the request of the
Economic and Social Council of the United
Nations.
The Board instructed Director-General
Jaime Torres Bodet to develop"the execution
of the programme resolutions concerning
teaching about the United Nations and its
Specialized Agencies, putting particular em-
phasis on the necessity for collective security,
based on respect for law, with the aid of con-
crete examples."It also authorized him"to
prepare, in close and constant collaboration
with the United Nations, both written and
audio-visual materials for use in schools, adult
classes and universities".
A Resolution adopted by the Sixth Session
ACTION IN THE SERVICE OF PEACE
Resolutions adopted by the Unesco General Conference
at its seventeenth plenary meeting on July 77, 1951
T THE various Governments repre-JL sented at the Sixth Session ot
the Unesco General Conference.
conscious of the collective moral
responsibility which the dangers of
war place upon them from the
political, economics and social
standpoints, solemnly bind them-
selve to work for peace and peace-
ful ends, in full and friendlv
trust, complete independence, and
full equality of rights.
MAINTENANCE OF PEACE AND
INTERNATIONAL SECURITY.
NOTING the resolution'''Unitin
for Peace"of the Genera ! Assembly
of the United Nations, which pro-
vides that the General Assembly
may make recommendations to
Members for collective measures
for maintenance of pellce and se-
curity, if the Security Council fails
to act ;
NOTING the resolution of the
Economic and Social Council, which
(1) Requests the Secretary-General
: of the United Nations]... to consult
with the Specialized Agencies as to
the specitic arrangements they
might most appropriately make in
order to provide for the furnishing
by them of such information and
for the rendering of such assistance
in the maintenance or restoration
ot international peace and security
as may be requested by the Se-
curity Council or the General As-
sembly, such arrangements to cover
action on an emergency basis and
within the constitutional and bud-
getary limitations of the agencies
to meet urgent requests ; and (2)
invites the Specialized Agencies to
approve arrangements to this end
as soon as possible ;"
CONSIDERING that acts of
aggression and breaches of the
peace constitute direct threats to
those objectives and to the high
purposes for which Unesco was
established ;
MINDFUL of its responsibility for
advancing, through the educational,
scientific and cultural relations of
the peoples of the world, the object-
ives of international peace and of
the common welfare of mankind for
which the United Nations Organiza-
tion was'established ;
BEARING in mind that, if there
is to be widespread understanding
of and popular support for United
Nations action, there must be
adequate education regarding spe-
cific acts of aggression and breaches
of the peace, as well as the actions
taken bv the United Nations to
maintain or restore the peace ;
1. DECLARES that the United Na-
tions Educational, Scientific and
Cultural Organization, on request of
the Security Council or the General
Assembly, will co-operate with the
United Nations in the maintenance
of international peace and security
and upon the request of the Se-
euritv Council of the General As-
semh'tv will furnish information
and emergency assistance for this
purpose within the limits of com-
petence, as de1ined by the Constitu-
tion and in accordance with bud-
getary provisions ;
2. AUTHORIZES the Executive
Board and the Director-General,
whenever the Security Council
finds the existence of a threat to
the peace, breach of the peace, or
act of. aggression, or whenever the
General Assembly takes action in
accordance with the General As-
sembly Resolution to facilitate, in
consultation with the Secretary-
General of the United Nations,
through educational and other
appropriate means at its disposal,
widespread understanding of the
nature and background of the ac-
tion taken by the United Nations to
maintain or restore the peace.
international affairs. In preparing his work for
Unesco, he consulted with the Royal Institute
of International Affairs in London and the
Institute of Pacific Relations in the United
States.
Dr. Dupuy was President of the International
University Federation for the League of Na-
tions and of the Executive Committee of the
World Federation of United Nations Associa-
tions ; a member of the French Delegations to
the San Francisco Conference and five Gen-
eral Assemblies of the United Nations. He is
the author of many works on international
affairs including San Francisco et la Charte
des Nations Unites.
Professor Francovich has filled high political
and diplomatic posts in addition to his work
as an educator. He is the author of El Mundo,
el Hombre y los Valores and of other books
in the fields of history and philosophy.
The three writers agreed, in consultation
there must be a rule of law among individuals
within each State. The attempts to establish
such a rule of law among nations represent a
continuance and extension of man's efforts to
achieve personal freedom."
The authors of all three of the Unesco
booklets point out how, as the culmination of
a slow and difficult historical process, man's
will for peace found its instrument in the
United Nations. Moreover, the United Nations,
through its adoption of the Universal Declara-
tion of Human Rights, became also the
vehicle for the spread and development of the
principles of enlightenment and progress.
Three militant writers
THE three men chosen to prepare the pam-phlets were not only educational experts,
but also militants in the cause of collect-
ive security with long and brilliant records of
achievement.
Professor Appadorai is Secretary-General of
the Indian Council of World Affairs, joint
General Secretary of the Asian Relations
Organization, and the author of The Sub-
stance of Politics, Revision of Democracy, De-
mocracy in India and of many pamphlets on
to seize power".
But the essence of the idea of collective
security which has emerged from the tragic
experiences of recent years, he stresses, is that
"freedoms must defend themselves."Such a
security"can exist only in the collective effort
of all States within an international organiza-
tion. We must really want peace and above
all be ready to accept on its behalf, each
according to his means, a share of the burdens
imposed by its establishment and mainten-
ance."
And Professor Francovich, in the Spanish
language pamphlet, comes to the conclusion
that"Force must be the effective and tangible
contribution of the peoples to the defence of
collective security ; for force will represent the
irresistible power of the human will put at
the service of all peoples'aspirations to a har-
monious and pacific community."
It is as a continuation of Unesco's vigorous
efforts to teach and spread awareness that in
the long run Human Rights can be enjoyed
only in a world at peace and free from the
threat of aggression, that the pamphlets were
conceived, prepared and published. Some
editorial suggestions were made by the Unesco
and United Nations secretariats, but the
authors were free to accept or reject them.
with officials of the United Na-
tions and Unesco, on the main
outlines of the form and content
of the pamphlets they would
prepare. Within the general
framework thus established,
each author was given freedom
to develop the subject as he
judged best, in the light of his
knowledge of the needs of the
educators and students who
were to form his particular
audience.
'Germs of confHct'
PROFESSOR Appadorai divideshis 34-page pamphlet into
four sections : the Meaning
of Collective Security ; the De-
velopment of the Idea ; the
United Nations and Collective
Security ; Strengthening the
Foundations. After tracing the
history of United Nations steps
to help solve problems in Iran,
Indonesia, Greece, Palestine and
Kashmir, he analyzes the les-
sons of the Korean experience.
"Power held in reserve,"he
says,"has always played an im-
portant part in international
politics ; the United Nations can
be an effective instrument of
collective security only if the
statesmen of the powerful na-
tions are prepared to use the
power of their States on its be-
half.
"Without a system of collect-
ive security, there can be no
stable peace ; yet, unless all
nations accept the system in
practice, it must be enforced or
it will fail. But if we can deal
with international problems by
reasonable rather than violent
methods, that will greatly help
to produce a political climate in
which the sense of collective
security can grow".
Dr. Dupuy points out in the
French language pamphlet that
the concept of collective secur-
ity has evolved to include social
security and economic organiza-
tion."An international struggle
should be carried out", he
writes,"against unemployment,
hunger, poverty, illness, ignor-
ance, misunderstanding ; against
all these defects, all these germs
of conflict which dictators and
dema ! !"O ! ! : Ues can exnloit in order
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1951 Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
FOR several years past, a message of international unity has beenfinding its way into the albums of many stamp collectors who have
avidly been seeking postage stamps, envelopes and cancellation
marks related to the activities of the United Nations and its Specialized
Agencies. Since the celebration of United Nations Day on October 24,
this"international'''stamp collection has been enriched'by several new
items, some of which are reproduced on this page. One of these,"People
of the World", is a one-cent maroon-coloured stamp which symbolizes
the principal races of mankind being released from bondage and looking
with hope towards the United N'ations. Another stamp,"World Unity",
is for 20 cents, and shows the United Nations emblem between the hemi-
spheres of the world, with the words"United Nations"in French and
Spanish. The first group of stamps issued on October 24 consisted of
one-cent, one-and-a-half-cent, three-cent, five-cent, 25-cent and one-
dollar denominations. Five denominations-two, ten, 15. 20 and 50
cents-will be released on November 16, and four air mail values-six,
ten, 15 and 25 cents-on November 30. The United Nations stamps will
be used on official communications despatched by mail from United
Nations headquarters in New York, and on private correspondence sent
through the headquarters post office. A special philatelic sales office
will also be opened at the Palais de Chaillot in Paris, where the United
Nations General Assembly meets this month. Postage stamps have
already shown their value as a means of spreading ideas and informa-
tion, and these latest issues will undoubtedly help to make better known
the ideals and work of the United Nations. Although Unesco has not
itself issued any stamps its work has been recorded on those issued by
several countries which include Belgium, France, Italy, the Lebanon and
Mexico. In Belgium, for example, a new series of three special stamps
with surtax has helped the work of Unesco's Rehabilitation Service. In
France, a cancellation mark which reads :"Through Education, Science
and Culture, Unesco is serving the cause of Peace"is stamped on
envelopes by post offices in Paris, Bordeaux, Lyons and Lille.
A NEW MESSAGE
OF WORLD UNITY
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 10 NOVEMBER 195\
ASTRONAUTICS : THE NEW SCIENCE
OF SPACE TRAVEL
A STROXAUTICS is a new science.It is the science of space
travel, of flight beyond the
earth's atmosphere and of voyages
to other worlds. Its rapid develop-
ment during these past few decades
is bringing a note of hard reality
into the world of mythology and
fantasy that for centuries has been
fed by the writing of men who
dreamed of exploring the realms
of space.
It was Galileo who-as in so
many other cases-laid a foundation
for this reality. Through his teles-
cope he saw 400 years ago what
no other man had ever seen before.
"It is a most beautiful and delight-
ful sight to behold the body of
the moon, which is distant from
us nearly sixty semi-diameters of
the earth, as near as if it was at a
distance of only two of the same
measures,"he wrote."And conse-
quently any one may know with
the certainty that is due to the
use of our senses, that the moon
certainly does not possess a smooth
and polished surface, but one rough
and uneven, and just like the face
of the earth itself, is everywhere
full of vast protuberances, deep
chasms, and sinuosities."
Galileo's telescope bore out the
theory of Copernicus that the sun,
and not the earth, was the centre of
our planetary system ; and that
the earth was only one of many
planets of its kind. Indeed, Galileo
was able to discover"four planets
neither known nor observed by any
one of the astronomers before my
time."
Arthur C. Clarke, chairman of
the British Interplanetary Society,
points out in his new book The
Exploration oaf Space, that only one
writer of ancient times wrote a
story about travelling to the moon.
He was Lucien of Samos, who, in
about the second century A. D.,
told how a man was taken to the
moon in a waterspout which seized
his ship when he was sailing beyond
the Pillars of Hercules ! Another
more recent story of a journey to
the moon was written just over
400 years ago, following Galileo's
by Maurice Goldsmith, Unesco Science Editor
discoveries, by another great astro-
nomer, Johannes Kepler. The hero
of his storv arrived on the moon by
supernatural means, but his des-
cription of what he found there was
based upon the latest scientific
knowledge of that time.
Since that day, travel in space
has provided the theme for innumer-
able stories. Now however, the
moon is actually coming within our
reach. In two or three generations
the first man may land there, and
long before then-perhaps with-
in a few vears-an unmanned
rocket mav have reached the moon.
We have already contacted that
planet by radar. A signal has been
sent across 240, 000 miles of space
and it has brought back an"echo"
from the moon. The naked eve
and the revealing telescope will
no longer be our main means of
"exploring"the heavens. woe shall
be able to travel through inter-
planetary space and see the realities
for ourselves.The instrument which will make
this possible is the rocket. (It is
interesting that this seemingly most
modern of inventions originated
about 700 years ago in China).
To leave the earth and to travel
in space we require to do two basic
things : first, to devise a means of
overcoming the earth's gravita-
tional pull so that we can get into
space ; and secondly, once there,
to find a means of travelling around
in an airless vacuum, which is
basically what outer space is.
We are all familiar with the force
of gravity. If it did not exist,
neither would we. It is gravity
which makes life possible for us
by keeping a thin blanket of air
tightly round the earth. With in-
creasing height, however, the force
of gravity slowly diminishes. At
250 miles up-the greatest height
yet reached by a rocket-it loses
only 10 per cent of its value at sea
level. But at 12, 000 miles up, a
one-pound weight would weigh only
one ounce."It follows, therefore",
says Clarke,"that the further away
one goes from the earth, the easier it
is to go onwards. In terms of
gravity, leaving the earth is rather
like climbing a hill which at first
is very steep but later becomes
more and more gentle until finally
it is almost perfectly flat."
It was Sir Isaac Newton, the
English scientist, who first formu-
lated the laws of gravity. It was
also he who gave us the clue that
has enabled us to understand the
mechanics of travel in space, when
he said :"For every action there is
an equal and opposite reaction."
To understand what this means,
take an ordinary sausage-shaped
rubber balloon and blow it up.
Then let go of the balloon, and it
will dart rapidly around until the
air has gone out of it. What has
happened is that molecules of
compressed air in the balloon are
bombarding the closed front end
of the balloon-and it is this which
is pushing the balloon forward.
That is, the action of the molecules
in bombarding the front end of the
balloon is producing the reaction
of balloon movement.
This is basically what causes a
rocket to move. It is essentiallv
a cylinder with the back end open.
It carries along its own oxygen,
and the chemical reaction causes
the molecules to move about swiftlv
and to bombard the confined space
in the cvlinder. The molecules
fly out of the open end. In this
way, the action of the molecules
bombarding the closed front end
produces the reaction that pushes,
or thrusts, the rocket forward.
The great virtue of this is that the
rocket would actually move faster
if there were no air at all, because
the air in front tends to slow it
down.
The rocket is, therefore, the ideal
form of space-ship because it can
generate enormous power for little
weight or size of engine (for example,
the V2 was four times as powerful
as the Queen Elizabeth), and this
will enable it to overcome the
earth's gravitational pull. It will
also work most efficiently in the
vacuum of outer space and at high
flight speeds.
To escape from the earth a rocket
needs a velocity of 25, 000 m. p. h.
This may seem utterly fantastic,
but we should remember that while
in 1940 the top flight for a rocket
was under 1, 000 m. p. h., in 1950 it
was nearer 5, 000 m. p. h. It is
certain that there will be great
developments in the immediate
years ahead.
Rocket research is proceeding in
all advanced industrialized coun-
tries, for a variety of purposes :
to assist the take-off of aircraft ;
to propel aircraft at extreme speeds
and heights (for example, the Ame-
rican Bell rocket plane was the first
to fly faster than sound) ; for high-
altitude research by instrument-
carrying projectiles, and for guided
missiles. So far as fuel is concern-
ed, it is probable that future rocket
spaceships will ultimately make use
of atomic power.
On the basis of all this work,
experts declare that within the next
few decades there will be set up
in space an"earth-sateIIite-vehicle,"
a man-made"planet"in a close orbit
around the earth. This would circle
the earth without remaining at a
constant distance, and would stay
there indefinitely without using any
power.
It could be used, for example, as
a research observatory beyond the
atmosphere, for physicists and astro-
nomers ; as an observatory for
meteorologists who would be able
to"see"the earth's weather system
developing ; as a radio relay station,
which would allow, for instance, of
world-wide reception of television ;
and, unfortunately, as a military
base for reconnaissance.
Since early pioneers began some
40 years ago to study the theory
of space flight (Goddard in the
U. S. A., Oberth in Germany, Esnault-
Pelterie in France, and Tsiolkovsky
in Russia), we have made tremendous
advances. So much so, that man
may soon be setting out on the
"roads"to the planets.
HAS THE UNIVERSE A FUTURE ?
PERHAPS the greatest and mostpersistent riddle in all of
science is that of the nature
of the cosmos. Almost inevitably,
a glance at the night sky with its
seemingly innumerable stars and
wispy nebulae bring to the human
mind such questions as :"What is
this universe in which we find our-
selves ? How did it all begin ?
What is its ultimate destiny ?"
By the very nature of such ques-
tions, definite, positive answers are
beyond the powers of science. Ne-
vertheless, from earliest times men
have pondered the subject of cos-
mology as it is called-the study of
the universe as a whole. Such spe-
culations come not only from theo-
logians and philosophers but from
scientists as well ; for it was inevi-
table that the increasing success of
physics in explaining our imme-
diate surroundings should have en-
couraged attempts to supply a ra-
tional basis for the more distant
reaches of our environment.
In a subject so devoid of land-
marks as cosmology, one is forced
to assume the existence of some-
thing to begin with. In the
eighteenth century the German
philosopher Kant and the French
mathematician Laplace imagined
a primordial cloud of gas which
eventually contracted, shedding
material to form the planets as it
did so. The remaining central body
was assumed to be the sun, our
own star. This process was presum-
ably taking place all through
space to give birth to the cosmic
population of sun-and-planet sys-
tems. Early in the present century
the American astronomer F. R.
Moulton subjected the contraction
hypothesis to mathematical scru-
by Ira M. Freeman
tiny and found it dubious. He, to-
gether with geologist T. C. Cham-
berlin, advanced an alternative
idea : a universe consisting initially
of already formed stars moving
haphazardly through the void.
When, on the average once in a
million million years, two of these
stars happen to pass close to each
other, great filaments of matter are
torn from their sides by gravit-
ational attraction. This material,
drifting along with each parent
star, would ultimately condense to
form planets coursing about it. This
so-called"PIanetesimal Theory"was
refined and improved by English
astronomers such as Jeans and Jef-
freys, and became the accepted doc-
trine in its field.
While these close-to-home pro-
blems concerning mere planetary
systems were thus claiming atten-
tion, the relativity theorists had
been busy with attempts to under-
stand the structure and pattern of
the universe as an entity-ques-
tions having to do with the nature
of space and time and with such
ideas as whether or not the uni-
verse is limited in extent. From
their intricate, mathematical equa-
tions they distilled suggestive ideas
bearing on the inherent curvature
of space ; of a cosmos that is finite
in extent, yet unbounded ; of a uni-
verse whose members may all be
fleeing from each other at tremen-
dous rates.
In the meantime, observation had
been advancing, too-not only as-
tronomical observation, but obser-
vation of laboratory phenomena
which might some day contribute
sturdy props to the structure of a
truly comprehensive theory of the
universe. The spectroscope had re-
vealed the composition, tempera-
tures and speeds of motion of the
stars and nebulae within reach of
our telescopes. Nuclear physics had
disclosed the source of the lavish
outpouring of stellar energy to be
nuclear condensation of the hydro-
gen of which stars are, for the most
part, composed.
It was shortly before the begin-
ning of World War II that two
young Cambridge University ma-
thematicians, Fred Hoyle and Ray-
mond Lyttleton, began a collabora-
tion that was to give science its
boldest and most comprehensive
cosmology up to the present time.
They subjected to mathematical
analysis the often-proposed idea
that the stars are formed as-con-
densations from a thin cloud of gas
stretching through all of space.
The results showed that the fate of
a star is governed by the extent to
which it sweeps up and draws to
itself this wispy matter. As an in-
cipient star gathers together suffi-
cient material it becomes hotter
and hotter and finally (after thou-
sands of millions of years) its tem-
perature is high enough to kindle
the nuclear reaction on which all
stars must rely for producing their
energy. What occurs subsequently
depends on how abundant are the
cosmic clouds of gas through which
the star moves. Our sun, as it
happens, has in the past browsed
through relatively barren pastures,
picking up only a few shreds of
matter and-fortunately for us-
remaining an average, middle-class
star. If a star greedily gathers too
much matter, it heats up at a pro-
digious rate and soon, after mere-
ly a few hundred million years, it
blows up. The Hoyle-Lyttleton
theory gives a plausible account of
the manner in which the planets
might be formed from the debris of
such an explosion.
Having put the explanation of
the origin of stars and their pla-
nets on a reasonable basis, Hoyle
and Lyttleton turned to a consi-
deration of the mechanism of the
universe in its entirety. Here they
joined forces'width two colleagues,
Bondi and Gold, to develop what
is certainly one of the most revo-
lutionary of contemporary scienti-
fic theories. Briefly, they adopt
the now familiar idea that the uni-
verse is expanding, and that this
swelling of space itself finally car-
ries the distant galaxies of stars
out of existence entirely. To com-
pensate for the loss it is assumed-
and this is the boldest of their
postulates-that new matter is con-
tinually being created, atom for
atom, through all of space. The
entire picture is one of serene,
comfortable continuity. But plea-
sant as it is to contemplate, the
Hoyle-Lyttleton-Bondi-Gold version
of our cosmos is assuredly not the
last word on the subject ; for it is
probable that theorizing about the
umverse, like the universe itself, is
something without end.
If YUI/arr illlerrsll'd iI/rrallillg furll/p,
allOl//Cosmolog ; cal 1'hl'ol' ;/'s, lL','ile 10
the Vi,. ; s ; !)//. for the l'u} lIi/al'izatioll ul
Science, Fuesco.. 19, Al' {>nue Kleber,
/' (1/'i8, fol'a free bibliogralllty UI//I/is
S/ffJjl'd.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Page II-UNESCO COURIER
ENTERTAINMENT FILMS FOR CHILDREN
by Lady Allen of Hurtwood
In our september issue, devoted to the cinema as a means of international understanding,we publish d an article entitled "Children's Films-For Adults O ly ?" by a French
writer, writer, Jean Bloch-Michel. As the title suggested, this article maillly dealt with the
effects of adult films on  children. M. Bloch-Michel did not attempt a study of the special
production of films for children. The publication of this article has aroused considerable
interest and comment from our readers in different countries. Lady Allen of Hurtwood,
Chairman of the Advisory Council on Children's Films in Great Britain from 1945 to 1950.
has sent us an article dealing with some of the efforts made in recent years to provide
better entertainment films specially made for children in Britain and other countries of
Europe. We are pleased to publish this artilce below.
In the September issue of the Courier, Mr. RossMcLean (Head of Films and Visual Information
Division, Unesco) wrote that makers of films
"all have a common duty to the world's child-
ren, and an opportunity greater than ever before
10 dischar'ge it, because of the vast challenge it.
presents." The impact of films on children for
good or for-evil Is becoming widely recognized, hut
the challenge has only been accepted in a few
countries. Jean Bloch-Michel writes on children's
films in the same Issue as though no attempt had
been made to produce entertainment films for
children. He Ignores the pioneer work done by the
U. S. S. R., Czechoslovakia. Denmark and the Cnited
Kingdom. He even makes the error of deseribing
the Disney fiims as"fiims meant especially for
children."These films are made for the ordinary
cinema audiencps and their unsuitability for
children is clearly shown in the article. Further-
more, these films are not available for children's
matinées until they have exhausted their commer-
cial run. lie asks "What producer will undertake
to make a picture which he knows will not be
aeeepted by the usual circuits ?"
Early in the near, the J. Arthur Rank Organza-
tion, aware of the harm ilone 10 the sensibility of
child'yen hy seeing old adult films, subsidized a
department charged with the quite new problem
of making children's entertainment films. During
five years, this group, led by Miss Mary Field, was
responsible for producing over 220 films-shorts,
features. a monthly world magazine, fantasy.
adventure, musical. historical and what Sir Michael
Balcon describes as"feature documentary" or John
nrier"on as"making drama frum our da'il'events.
and poetry of our problems."
II was not long hefore the, advisory Council on
Children's Entertainment Films (a group appointed
10 watch and guide this important adventure, and
representing all the principal organizations and
government departments interested in children)
realized that, apart from entertaining children, them
had a unique opportunity of showing how children
lived in other lands. Some of the most popular
British films were stories made in. Australia.
Germany. Norway, Basutoland and Austria. Child-
ren of these countries were the actors and In many
cases spoke their native languages. These and the
English-speaking films have been shown in coun-
tries where the language was unfamillar. and the
children had no difficulty in following the stories
because the spoken word is only incidental to the
action. Here then Is a tremendous opportunity to
show children that "foreigners" are in essence
like themselves, adventurous, clever, warmhearted
and normal human heings with whom they would
rejoice to be friends.
Unesco Is the body to which we all hopefully
turn for assistance to develop this fundamentally
important work. It Is not enough to devote one
article in one issue of the Courier. Why, for in-
stance, should not children's entertainment films
be included with the newsreels, scientific and
cultural films In the Unesco-sponsored interna-
tional conventions soon to be ratitled and so assisl
the free flow of films already made and stimulate
further production ? Is there any reason whv a
viewing library should not be established at Unesco
House, as has already been done for educational
and welfare films" ? Would Unesco convene a
small conference of expert and experienced per-
sons to discus the whole problem and to rccom-
mand the best ways Cor Unesco to Cosier and
guide the making and distribution of children's
entertainment films In relation to the needs and
possibilities in each continent? The implications
are immense and the interest vivid-so much
that there is a danger that other bodies outside the
United Nations may assume international leader-
ship.
EDITOR'S NOTE
Children's films, if certified by the Government of
the producing country to be of an educational,
scientific or cultural character, come under the
duty free provisions of the Unesco Agreement for
Facilitating the International Circulation of Visual
and Auditory Material of an Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Character. In addition, the second
Unesco Free Flow Agreement would allow
educational, scientific or cultural institutions
approved by the Government of the importing
country to import such films duty free. The
subject of children's films wos the theme of a
series of film group meetings held in Venice from
. August 16 to 19 at which Unesco was represented,
and at which Unesco's publication Recreational
Film for Juvenile Audiences serred as a basis of
discussion. Unesco is at prensent collaboratin with
an international committee formed in Venice
during these meetings to prepare the first world
congress on children's films, scheduled to be held
next year in Europe.
INTER-AMERICA
CULTURAL COUNCIL PLANS
EDUCATIONAL CAMPAIGN
FOR A CONTINGENT
by Michel Dard
ALEXANDER VON HUMBOLDT, the famous
19t century German naturalist and traveller,
who once called Mexico,"the treasure house of
the world," was probably thinking of its precious
metals, its opals, jades and turquoises.
Today, not only Mexico, but the whole Latin American
continent is regarded as a treasure house, but of a
different sort, for its modern riches are the infinite
possibilities for development which have earned for it
the name of"the continent of the future."
Recently, however, when the Inter-American Cultural
Council held its first meeting in Mexico, observers were
struck by evidence of still another form of wealth
enjoyed by Latin America-its tremendous store of
spiritual energy.
This showed itself in determination expressed by
Conference delegates to develop and share the rich,
varied and ancient cultural traditions of the continent ;
in the recognition of responsibility for bringing the full
benefits of human progress to those communities which
do not yet enjoy them ; and also in the stressing of inter-
American solidarity in face of the world situation.
The Inter-American Cultural Council is the third of
the specialized bodies set up by the Organization of Ame-
rican States (O. A. S.) which groups all States in the
Western Hemisphere with the exception of Canada, and
which works in close collaboration with Unesco.
Some weeks before the Cultural Council's conference
in Mexico, Dr. Lleras Camargo, Secretary-General of the
O. A. S., declared :"Unless the various cultures draw
closer together and get to know, understand and respect
one another, all the other acts of Inter-American co-
operation will not avail to increase the friendship of the
peoples, or strengthen the solidarity of the continent."
The justification for this"priority of the mind,"as
it has been called, was clearly expressed by M. Jaime
Torres Bodet, Unesco's Director-General, who addressed
the Council's opening session."No man,"he said,
"will defend with all his heart a fictitious liberty or a
social order which does not command his sincere
allegiance, nor a truth which demands of intellect,
and sometimes of his instincts, the denial of his spon-
taneous and incommunicable sense of culture."
"In the name of an Organization dedicated to the
conciliation of the peoples of the world through the
minds of men, I should like to express the hope that
the Council's activities may strengthen not merely the
cultural solidarity of the world, but also the confidence of
the world in the cultural solidarity of the Americas."
The programme drawn up by the Cultural Council
provides justification for this hope. Made up of some
fifty resolutions which include projects covering educa-
tion, literature, art and science, it is broad yet precise ;
ambitious, yet based on a realistic view of the continent's
needs.
One of the main problems before the delegates was
illiteracy. In the Americas, there are some 70, 000, 000
people who cannot read or write, and 19, 000, 000 children
for whom there are no schools. The adverse effects
of this situation on the well-being, cultural progress.
civic life, and agricultural, industrial, and technical
development of the continent are enormous.
Delegates also stressed the fact that as long as
millions of Americans remain ignorant of their cultural
heritage, the continent will be unable to claim to have
reached the goals of liberty, hope and peace.
To meet this challenge, the Cultural Council decided
to launch a large-scale educational campaign. This
will go much further than mere literacy teaching, for,
as M. Torres Bodet pointed out, fundamental education
embracing basic instruction in civics, home economics,
agriculture and hygiene must more and more replace
literacy teaching as such. In this continental effort,
the aid of governments, employers, trade unions, families,
churches, teachers and pupils, army instructors and
cinema and radio organizations will be mobilized.
The Council also urged member states to allocate
sufficient funda to ensure free and compulsory primary
schoo1ing for all, for unless these facilities are made
available, the ranks of the illiterates will continue to
grow and fundamental education projects will never
achieve lasting results.
The Council's programme not only harmonize8 with
that of Unesco, but in many ways represents it on a re-
gional basis. To combine all efforts and to avoid over-
lapping of activities, and consequent wastage of resources,
the Council asked the Organization of American States to
suggest to Unesco the setting up of a commission
charged with co-ordinating the work of both Organiza-
tions on projects of common interest. Through
agreements and administrative arrangements this could
lead to the pooling of resources and experiences.
D. H. Lawrence, who wrote one his finest novels against
a Mexican background, once compared humanity to a
giant tree which, having been felled, was lying with its
roots in the air. "We must replant ourselves in the
world,"he wrote.
In such a task there is a vital need for the close colla-
boration of two organizations which represent two reali-
ties of our time ; the effort to achieve a universality of
the human mind and the need for authentic national
cultures which are, in the words of Unamuno, the great
Spanish thinker,"an immanent covenant, a real but
unrecorded social contract, which is the true inner conati-
tution of every people."
---.
NOVEMBER 1951
Three stills from the film-
"Bush Christmas"...
and how the children
react to them
Infra-red photographs taken by Miss Mary Field and other film makers during showings
can help them to produce films that are really suitable for children. At the moment when
the stills shown on the left appeared on the screen, photographs were taken of the unsus-
pecting audience. Here are shown the children's reactions to (1) a boy who eats a grub
because there is no more food ; (2) a tracker who dashes into the river to chase a thief ;
and (3) children out In the open all night, sheltering from the rain. (Copyright, G. B.
Instructional, Ltd.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
A LOST BELIEF
STILL SURVIVE
IN THIS STONE
This is one of the most
famous knights in Yugo-
slavic-but nobody
can tell who he was.
There are thousands of
tombs and slabs like this
throuhout the country,
especially in Serbia, Macedonia and Bosnia-Hercegovina. They were
built during the 13the and 14the centuries by a sect which has borne
various names : BogomiJs, Gnostics, Cathars, Albigenses. Their
monoliths, often grouped together in enormous cemeteries in remote
forest or mountain areas, may be decorated with scenes from the
hunt or the dance, with foliage or with geometrical figures ; but for
the most part they contain a symbolism which archæologists have
been unable to"translate"with any certainty. Why, for instance,
does the bare-headed knight above have a disproportionately large
hand extending towards a star ? Artists cannot agree whether the
sculptural style represents an artistic revolution or a synthesis of
survivals from the ancient days of slavery. Attempts have been made
to link it with Nordic motifs, ancient Scythian and Sarmatian orna-
mentation, Mycenaean spirals, Roman influences, Venetian decora-
tion, even with long-lost aboriginal lore. Some declare that this
form of art stems from a conception of the world and of life of which
we only know from documents left by the Inquisition which tried to
eliminate it. Its origin certainly lies partly in the conflict between
the Eastern and Roman churches. Yugoslavia was torn by these dis-
sensions, and bui) dings in the architectural styles which each religion
favoured are to be found in different parts of the country. Later there
was a tendency to introduce some of the characteristics of the one into
buildings used by the other. Add tothismanyotherforeigninftuences,
and the result has been a school of architecture with monuments that
have no parallel in either east or west. Yugos ! avia's monuments, as
well as her fine traditions of craftsmanship, music and dancing, are an
irresistible attraction to all students of her rich and ancient culture.
]]>
</page>
</document>
