<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074691eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ourier
OF THE WO
-ÍJ
:'
Awasthi
Boal
Chitakasem
Cirilov
Cournot
Fabregas
Hayman
Kornienko
Lu Tian
Malanda
Morisseau-Leroy
Niemi
Oatman
Wassef
Yamaguchi
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
Photo © Juan Bottin, Pdris
© GREECE 'All the world's a stage'
International theatre festivals, many of which include performances of ballet and opera, provide an ideal opportunity
for the exchange of ideas and for experiment with new theatrical forms. Among the most famous festivals are: the Theatre
ofNations (itinerant); Avignon Festival (France); the Festival of Two Worlds, Spoleto (Italy); the Edinburgh Festival
(United Kingdom); the Theatre Rally, West Berlin; the. International Theatre Festival, Caracas (Venezuela); the Festival
ofCarthage (Tunisia); the Dubrovnik Summer Festival (Yugoslavia). Above, the cast of a classical Greek tragedy rehears¬
ing for the Epidaurus Festival (Greece) in the magnificent 4th-century BC theatre which can hold 14,000 spectators and
is renowned for its incomparable acoustics.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
APRIL 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 26 lang uages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese i Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 4 - 1983 - OPI - 83-1 - 396 A
page
12
15
18
21
22
29
30
32
35
36
38
41
44
2
Latin America - A THEATRE OF URGENCY
by Augusto Boat
7 Europe - WHO'S AFRAID OF THE AVANT-GARDE?
	by Ronald Hayman	
11 SHARED DISILLUSION
by Michel Cournot 	
Africa - THE CHANGING SCENE
by Ange-Séverin Malanda
Japan - NOH AND KABUKI: THE BEAUTY OF FORM
by Masao Yamaguchi
Haiti - THE AWAKENING OF CREOLE CONSCIOUSNESS
by Félix Morisseau-Leroy
Egypt - THE SHADOW AND THE SUBSTANCE
by Magda Wassef	
Soviet Union - THE THEATRE OF THE MARKET-PLACE
by Nelly Kornienko
Yugoslavia
THE BELGRADE INTERNATIONAL THEATRE FESTIVAL
by Jovan Cirilov	
India - THE GIFT OF THE GODS
by Suresh Awasthi
Spain - CURTAIN UP ON CATALONIA
by Xavier Fabregas
THE 'PADDY-FIELD' PUPPETS OF VIETNAM
Finland - WOMEN IN THE LIMELIGHT
by Irmeli Niemi
China - THE SYMBOLIC LANGUAGE OF BEIJING OPERA
by Lu Tian	
United States - ALTERNATIVE THEATRE
by Eric Oatman
Thailand - THE THEATRE OF KINGS
by Manas Chitakasem
A TIME TO LIVE...
GREECE : 'All the world's a stage'
~W~W THETHER popular in origin
m/w/ like the Italian commedia
Y r dell'arte, courtly like the
khon theatre of Thailand, linked to ritual
as in Africa, religious like the miracle
plays of medieval Europe, or avowedly
divine like India's kathakali, theatre has^
always been the "concentrated exprès-"
sion" of a culture, drawing on popular
myths, legends and customs, historic ways
of life and experiences, and assimilating
all forms of art, human expression and
communication.
World theatre covers an immense can-~)
vas. It ranges from the dazzling spectacleJ.
of kabuki, European opera, and North
American musical comedy, to the austere
settings, devoid of scenery or props, of
Japanese noh and the "theatre ofpover¬
ty" practised by the popular groups of
Latin America. It may be performed in a
traditional purpose-built theatre, or out¬
doors in streets and squares, as in parts of
the USSR. It may be governed by
rigorously codified conventions, like Beij¬
ing Opera, or improvised, like the avant-
garde experiments of the Living Theater.
It may recreate great moments from
myth, religion or history, like Greek,
African or Thai theatre, or become aform
of direct action on behalf of marginal
social groups, as in North and South
America. It may vehicle a classic literary
text or, as in certain works by Peter Han-
dke and Robert Wilson, reject "the tyran¬
ny of the word". It may, as in India,
Egypt and China, continue an ancient
dramatic tradition, or it may systematical¬
ly cast tradition aside (as in the countries
of the West where it could be said that re¬
jection of tradition has almost become a
tradition in itself). In every case theatre
has always triggered the creative capacity
of the individual and the community and
provided a mirror of identity.
Theatre is also a meeting place for dif¬
ferent cultures, and a vehicle for their
enrichment. Sophocles' Antigone has
been transposed into Creole language and
Afro-Haitian beliefs, Shakespeare's
Macbeth into the expressive forms of In¬
dia's Yakshagana theatre, Brecht 's
Caucasian Chalk Circle into the traditions
of Georgia, and works of Sophocles and
Aristophanes have been adapted to the
distinctive political situation of Catalonia.
Theatre is a place for reaffirmation and
assertion of cultural identity. While such
Oriental techniques as those o/kabuki are
being adopted in Europe, Shakespeare is
performed in a production influenced by
Chinese circus, and Peter Brook takes an
international troupe of actors to African
villages, Third World countries which
send the best of their traditional theatre to
international festivals are using the latest
avant-garde techniques to recreate, de¬
nounce, and dramatize their own
situations.
These and other aspects of world
theatre are examined in this issue of the
Unesco Courier, in the light of the belief
that this total art is one of the finest ex¬
pressions of Unesco's overriding ideal:
the promotion of mutual comprehension
between peoples through knowledge of
the immense variety of their cultures and
forms of expression, eschewing hierar¬
chies and invidious value judgments.
Cover: below, mask of Dionysos (1st cen¬
tury AD), Louvre Museum, Paris: Photo ©
Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris. Cen¬
tre : African mask (Zaïre), Institut- des
Musées Nationaux du Zaïre, Kinshasa:
Photo © Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris.
Above: Noh mask (Japan): Photo C. Lem-
zaouda © Musée de l'Homme collection,
Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
LATIN AMERICA
A theatre
of urgency
by Augusto Boal
LATIN American theatre should
not be considered from the
standpoint or in terms of the
values of European theatre. It should
be understood within its own context as
part of the Latin American situation.
Latin America is a diverse, many-
faceted continent. This variety may be
seen, for example, in its ethnic com¬
position. In some Latin American
countries which have a large propor¬
tion of indigenous peoples, there were
highly developed cultures when the
first European invaders arrived with
Christopher Columbus, Pedro Alvares
Cabrai and others. The Incas inhabited
Peru, Ecuador and Bolivia. Such
peoples as the Aztecs, the Mayas, the
Toltecas and the Chichimecas lived in
Mexico. In other countries such as
Brazil, already inhabited by Indians in
the Stone Age, the Portuguese invaders
decimated the indigenous population,
and in Brazil and Uruguay today the
Indian presence is virtually
unnoticeable.
On the other hand, the influence of
the black cultures brought by slaves
from Africa is immense in such coun¬
tries as Venezuela, but almost non¬
existent in Argentina. The influence
which European economic exiles have
contributed to Latin America is
similarly diverse: Italian is spoken in
entire districts of Sao Paulo, Buenos
Aires and other cities; 90 per cent of the
population of the Brazilian city of
Marilia are Japanese or their direct
descendants; in some cities of the
Brazilian State of Santa Caterina, Ger¬
man is the language you will hear in the
street.
AUGUSTO BOAL, of Brazil, is the author of
many dramatic works, including The Great Inter¬
national Agreement of Scrooge Mack Duck, and
essays on the "theatre of the oppressed" which
have been translated into a number of languages.
Among the groups he has directed are the Teatro
Arena ofSao Paulo (Brazil), the Grupo Machete
(Argentina), and the Grupo la Barraca (Por¬
tugal). He is currently director of the Centre
d'étude et diffusion des techniques actives d'ex¬
pression (Méthode Boal) in Paris.
Economically the differences are no
less great. There is the well-known ex¬
ample of Rio de Janeiro: in the hills a
few hundred metres away from the lux¬
urious apartment blocks of Copaca-
bana beach is the desperate poverty of
the favelas. Several million people are
concentrated in a handful of big cities,
while millions more live scattered over
millions of square kilometres. Immense
wealth is concentrated in select quarters
of a few cities, while the grip of poverty
reaches far over the mountains of the
altiplano, Amazonia and the waste ex¬
panses of northeastern Brazil.
There is one fundamental reason for
this massive disparity: the inequality in
economic relations between North and
South which reduces the majority of
Latin Americans to inhuman living
conditions.
And so Latin America is both
homogeneous, principally because of
the ills that beset it, and diverse in its
social, economic and geographical
composition. These simultaneously
identical and distinct societies produce
a theatre which is simultaneously the
same and different.
The theatre standardized by North-
South relations in the great capitals of
Latin America is the same as that you
will find in the capitals of Europe and
in New York; the same West End co¬
medies, with the same music,
sometimes with the same choreography
and décor, carbon copies of their
originals.
Fortunately there is another theatre,
the popular theatre, which is as diverse
as the peoples which populate our
America and which must adapt itself to
the conditions in which it is produced.
The story of the Bolivian director
Liber Forti is instructive. He became
used to working in extremely
precarious conditions and with slender
means, and put on shows wherever he
could, including the open air. He stag¬
ed performances in the mountains
where there was no electricity, for the
tin miners of Catavi and Siglo Veinte.
There was no point in holding perfor¬
mances during the daytime when the
miners were at work, and so he decided
to ask the audience to light up the stage
using their miners' lamps. "For the ac¬
tors," said Forti, "this was a
remarkable way of finding out whether
a scene was any good dramatically;
when the miners were bored with the
action the lighting dropped off, and
when something interesting was hap¬
pening the stage was more brightly lit. "
When I talked with Luis Valdez, who
directs California's Teatro Campesino,
and with the director of a remarkably
interesting Mexican group called Los
Vendedores Ambulantes de Puebla
("the travelling salesmen of Puebla"
the members of the company actually
are salesmen from the Mexican town of
Puebla who use theatre to denounce
their working conditions), I realized
that we had all three found similar solu¬
tions to identical problems. I told them
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
A scene from White Dream produced at the Tabarka Festival (Tunisia) by Graziella
Martinez's theatre and dance company from Argentina.
Photo © Hamid Belmenouar, Pans
how, when we were working in Brazil,
we were so poor that we had to make do
with discarded objects as décor and
props. When we presented Lope de
Vega's play El Mejor Alcalde, El Rey,
the nobles' costumes were made from
old carpets we found on the municipal
rubbish dump, and things of that kind.
Valdez told me that he and his group
had done the same thing and that they
had called their production "rascuachi"
(poor, meagre, worthless). We felt a
certain pride at having created beauty
from filth. Our Mexican friend told us
that they had done the same thing at
Puebla, "except that we never gave a
name to this form of presentation. We
used garbage because we had nothing
else."
Popular Latin American theatre is a
theatre of urgency. Plays are usually
chosen or improvised in accordance
with local social needs. Theatre is used
as a form of debate and protest, to
stimulate awareness and to help in
working out tactics. The social and
political nature of a play is never ignor¬
ed, even in the case of major works
from the international repertory. For
example, Molière' s Tartuffe was used
to denounce "parareligious" groups of
the extreme right which were using the
same methods as Tartuffe, that is
transforming God the Supreme Arbiter
into a partner in the social struggle. The
play was the same, the text was
Molière's, but the performance reveal¬
ed connotations, relationships and
meanings which remained hidden in
other more "aesthetic" productions.
This also proves the extent to which
Molière is universal, for he becomes in
this way a Brazilian, an Argentine or a
Uruguayan author.
In addition to the great universal
classics, which provide popular theatre
with many themes and ideas, all kinds
of stories or sources of dramatic in
spiration may be used. I remember the
case of the Paraguayan director An¬
tonio Pecci who decided to present a
life of Christ; it would be hard, one
might think, to imagine a subject more
inoffensive and less subversive from
the censor's point of view. All the
same, Pecci, knowing full well that the
people of Paraguay are bilingual and
that Guarani is the real mother tongue
of 90 per cent of the population, decid¬
ed that Christ, the Apostles and the
people in general would speak in
Guarani, while Pilate, the centurions
and other Romans would speak in
Spanish. In this way the audience
understood that Jesus lived in a coun¬
try occupied by foreign troops and this
of the Gospel came to serve as
a model of behaviour for the public.
Everything is grist to the mill of
popular theatre as long as it is con¬
nected with the social situation here
and now. A theatre group in Peru >
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
specialized in the "revision" of televi¬
sion serials. One such serial, which at¬
tracted a wide following, was called
Esmeralda; it told the story of a
domestic servant who eventually mar¬
ried the son of the master of the house.
The stage production followed the
original plot more or less faithfully,
and after the performance there was a
debate which focused on the overt and
hidden meanings of the play the public
had just seen. The members of the au¬
dience discovered the anti-feminism
which was built into the story: for the
son of the house a wife was not really
a woman he loved and with whom he
wished to live but a domestic servant
whose job was to look after his clothes,
see to the food, and keep house.
In one Andean country, a theatre
' company travelled through the moun¬
tains improvising sketches from true
stories told by the villagers. One of the
most successful was the story of a
rascally mayor, a man who existed in
real life. When the sketch was perform¬
ed in the mayor's home town, the au-
Photo © Roger Pic, Paris
Gimba, by Gianfrancesco Guarnieri, is set in the world of the Brazilian
favelas (shanty-towns). Above, scene from the Teatro Popular do Brasil' s
version of the play, directed by Flavio Rangel.
Photo © Augusto Boal, Pans
All the world's a stage for popular theatre
in Latin America, where actors perform
anywhere they are likely to attract the
public. Above, Sao Paulo's Teatro Arena,
directed by Augusto Boal, used a con¬
verted truck as a stage when taking
Revolución en América del Sur ("Revolu¬
tion in South America") to the desert
regions of northeast Brazil.
dience reacted with fury, went off to
the town hall and had the man arrested.
A few days later, the company an¬
nounced that they. would be perform¬
ing the same sketch in a nearby town
whose mayor was equally dishonest.
The latter decided to exploit the
widespread belief among the peasants
of the region in the existence of demons
known as pistacos, carnivorous spirits
which assume human form and eat
people. He broadcast on the local radio
the news that a group of pistacos
Photo © Roger Pic, Pans
Adapted from a story by the popular Colombian writer Tomás Carrasquilla,
A la Diestra de Dios Padre ("On God's Right Hand") is one of the most
successful productions of the Teatro Experimental from Cali, directed by
Enrique Buenaventura. Above, a scene from the play.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
disguised as actors were in the vicinity.
When the company reached the town
they found the streets deserted; the ter¬
rified population had taken refuge in
their homes. Even the radio station had
been abandoned, although its
microphone was ^still "live". At the
drop of a hat the actors broadcast an
improvised sketch denouncing the
stratagem of the mayor, who suffered
the same fate as his colleague when the
people found out the truth.
Those who take part in this kind of
theatre are not professional actors with
the same training and the same
economic guarantees as their fellow-
artists in Europe and North America.
They are people's artists; they are the
people.
In the last twenty years I have travell¬
ed constantly in almost all the countries
of Latin America. I have been in con¬
tact with many of these forms of
theatre which are used principally as a
means of promoting dialogue, of
treating the theatre as a form of expres¬
sion. Thus I have been in permanent
contact with the many-sided reality of
Latin America as I have striven to work
out my own technique of "theatre of
the oppressed", the main objective of
which is to help any oppressed human
being to achieve a form of dramatic ex¬
pression through which he may attempt
to reach a deeper understanding of the
reality of his situation and transform it.
The fundamental forms of the theatre
of the oppressed are based on the same
principle, that all men are capable of
achieving everything within the limits
of human possibility. Theatre is, or can
be, an occupation, a profession, but it
is above all a vocation. And this voca¬
tion is within the reach of everyone.
Every art is a language. But what is
learned through one language cannot
be learned through another. The most
perfect and total perception of reality
can only be obtained through the sum
of all possible languages. Theatre is
precisely this total art, the sum of all
the arts: poetry, painting, sculpture,
music, dance, etc. And theatre, even at
its most impoverished, takes man as the
centre of the universe. It is urgent and
imperative that all those who are op¬
pressed should recover this dense, rich,
profound totality in order to under¬
stand the mechanisms of the oppres¬
sion they endure, in order to struggle
more effectively for their liberation.
"Theatre of Image" (which ex¬
presses itself through images, not
words), "Forum Theatre" (in which
tactics and strategies are discussed in
dramatic form) and "Invisible
Theatre" (in which fiction is
transformed into reality, that is, the
performance of a drama becomes real
action in the real world) are three
manifestations of "Theatre of the Op¬
pressed" which can only achieve
systematic form if they emerge from a
living, changing reality. That of Latin
America, for example.
Augusto Boal
EUROPE
Who's afraid
of the avant-garde?
Scene from The Conference of the Birds, a production staged by the British
director Peter Brook at the Bouffes du Nord theatre in Paris. The work is based
on an allegorical poem by the Persian poet Attar (12th- 13th century) which
describes the quest of the birds for the mythical Simorgh whom they wish to
make their king. Each actor symbolically portrays a bird.
by Ronald Hayman
RONALD HAYMAN, of the UK, is the author
of a number of books about acting and theatre,
including Artaud and After and British Theatre
since 1955. He is a regular radio broadcaster and
contributor to the London Times Literary Sup¬
plement. His most recent book is a biography of
Kafka, and his biography of Brecht will appear
later this year.
BOOKS are like bananas, said
Jean-Paul Sartre. They have to
be consumed immediately if the
flavour is to be fully appreciated.
Marcel Duchamp considered that the
life of a painting was limited to forty or
fifty years, and Antonin Artaud said:
"The masterpieces of the past are good
for the past; they are not good for us."
Indubitably avant-garde theatre is
indispensable if the theatre is to be kept
alive, but it is self-evident that avant-
garde theatre cannot go on for very
long doing the same thing, and in
Europe, it might be asked, what is there
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
During a rehearsal of the Polish dramatist Tadeusz Kantor's
Où sont les neiges d'antan? in Paris, the author can be seen
behind a member of the cast.
Photo © Nicolas Treatt, Pans
left for it to do? The main landmarks in
its past have been moments when the
audience has been shocked, and the
easiest way to shock is to break a taboo
or defy a convention. In 1896, when
Alfred Jarry's Ubu Roi had its
premiere, the opening word "Merdre"
was enough, in spite of the extra r, to
provoke fifteen minutes of pandemon¬
ium in the auditorium. In 1968, when
male nudity was fully exposed in Oh,
Calcutta!, a convention, which had
survived since the Greeks, was
slaughtered. But how many conven¬
tions still have life in them?
The convention that actors must be
audible? This came under attack in the
second decade of this century at the
Cabaret Voltaire in Zürich when
Dadaists performed on stage with their
backs to the public. That a play must
tell a story? In Peter Handke's Publi¬
kumsbeschimpfung (Offending the
Audience, written 1965, staged 1966)
the public was implicitly being
challenged not to submit to the pro¬
cedure which was being substituted for
the usual one: four speakers were ad¬
dressing the audience directly, teasing-
ly, talking mainly about the immediate
situation in the auditorium, where no
illusion was being created, no narrative
unfolded. How much further can the
8
avant-garde advance? How much fur¬
ther up the beach can any new wave
wash?
Though each wave has to recede, it
becomes increasingly hard to shock an
audience. Not long ago it would have
been quite disturbing to see two iden¬
tical middle-aged male twins, dressed
as cardinals, tangoing together up and
down an acting area to the tune of
"Hernando's Hideaway" from The
Pajama Game. But theatrical images
like this fall into place within the
natural progression of a piece like
Tadeusz Kantor's Où sont les neiges
d'antan, which was first seen in Rome
during 1978 and featured in 1982 at the
Autumn Festival in Paris. Today it is
easier to provoke an audience than to
shock it. In June of last year, at the
Holland Festival in Amsterdam, the
production of Walzer by Pina Bausch's
Wuppertal Dance Company incited
booing and catcalls. The audience was
irked by the exorbitantly slow perfor¬
mance of a song, and there were ap¬
parently unrehearsed incidents, as
when a dancer tauntingly shouted to
"the audience: "None of you are going
to entertain me, are you?" A great deal
can depend on the delicate art of con¬
trolling the way in which things appear
to be going out of control.
Fundamentally, by consenting to be
members of an audience, we are con¬
tracting to remain passive voluntarily
lowering ourselves under the surface of
the pool in which Narcissus will con¬
template his image and there will not
be much we can do to register com¬
plaint if the exhibitionistic performers
become sadistic. The six-hour produc¬
tion oí Hamlet in December 1982 at the
Schaubühne in Berlin looked as though
it had been central to the intentions of
the director, Klaus Michael Grüber,
either to ignore the audience altogether
or challenge it to clamber up on stage in
order to see and hear what was going
on. The dividing wall had been remov¬
ed between two of the theatre's three
auditoria, but instead of trying to fill
the enormous space, Grüber used it to
make the human figure look small. It
was like being forced to watch the play
through the wrong end of a telescope.
Luca Ronconi's production of
Ibsen's Ghosts at the 1982 Festival of
Two Worlds in Spoleto a four-hour
production in the crypt of the Chiesa
San Nicolodisplayed the same deter¬
mination to test the patience of the au¬
dience, which was distanced as far as
possible from the action and had to put
up with the slow, somnambulistic
movement of the actors and with pro¬
vocatively histrionic mannerisms in
both speaking and gesture.
One of the central paradoxes in con-
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
temporary theatre is that the avant-
garde needs the classics; the other is
that avant-garde theatre is on display at
the international festivals and in the
big, subsidized theatres with large
budgets and vast technical resources.
At the end of the sixties, when Rainer
Werner Fassbinder was working in
Munich with his Anti-Theater, the
group performed in cellars, changing
rooms and a room above a skittle alley.
In 1968, Jim Haynes, who had founded
the small Traverse Theatre in Edin¬
burgh five years earlier, opened the
Arts Lab in Drury Lane, London. It
gave hospitality to some of the earliest
fringe groups, including the People
Show, and it brought others into
existence. Pip Simmons formed a com¬
pany to put on a series of fifty-minute
plays, while David Hare and Tony
Bicat, who collaborated on a show
compiled from Kafka's Diaries, went
on to form Portable Theatre, a com¬
pany to take productions into non-
theatrical venues. It was not predic¬
table but it was not unnatural that
Fassbinder should move into cinema
and that David Hare should graduate
to directing his own plays at the Na¬
tional Theatre.
What is odd is that in spite of the
popularity fringe theatre has achieved,
there should be no eighties equivalent
to Anti-Theater or to the Arts Lab.
Contemporary theatrical conditions
Photo © Antonello Penssinotto, Padua, Italy
Commedia dell'arte mask worn by a character in La Moschetta
("The Fly"), a work written in Paduan dialect by the Italian
dramatist and actor Angelo Beolco, also known as Ruzzante
(1502-1542).
are not conducive to experimental
writing, while establishment theatres
quickly appropriate the most successful
experimental directors from fringe
theatres. One consequence is that plays
with a large cast and plays which for
other reasons are unsuitable for perfor¬
mance in a small space are no longer
protected from anti-theatrical aggres¬
sions. At the Berlin Theatertreffen of
1982, fashionable directors tried to
outbid each other in displays of ir¬
reverence towards the classics. Post-
Brechtian alienation effects were in¬
troduced into plays by Büchner, Less¬
ing and Kleist, while the text of
Goethe's Faust was submitted (by
Grüber) to drastic dramaturgical
surgery.
Scene from a production of the Austrian playwright Peter
Handke's They Are Dying Out, at the Théâtre des Amandiers,
Nanterre (France).
Photo © Nicolas Treatt, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
At the same time, avant-garde
theatre is becoming more international.
The festivals are encouraging ,this
cross-fertilization. London, unfor¬
tunately, has lost its World Theatre
Season, which exerted a healthy in¬
fluence on British theatre, but discerni¬
ble ripples of influence were spread
over a wide area after the Rustaveli
Company of Tbilisi, Georgia, was seen
at the Avignon Festival, the Edinburgh
Festival and at the Round House in
London.
Oriental influences, too, are strongly
apparent in contemporary Western
theatre. Peter Brook was one of the
great pioneers of intercontinental eclec¬
ticism in theatrical style. He recruited a
Japanese Noh actor for the polyglot
company he assembled in Paris at the
end of the sixties, and one of the central
ideas for his 1970 production ofA Mid¬
summer Night's Dream was derived
from Chinese circus. In Ariane
Mnouchkine's production of Richard
II last year at the Cartoucherie de
Vincennes in Paris, Japanese Kabuki
visibly influenced the design of the
stage, the declamatory acting style, the
percussive accompaniment and the
stylized movement with half-bent
knees.
The devaluation of the word a
tendency which had long been promi¬
nent in avant-garde theatre prepared
the ground for this new wave of inter¬
nationalism. Artaud believed in "the
absolute dominance of the director
whose creativity eliminates words". It
is only very seldom in such plays as
Peter Handke's My Foot, My Tutor
(1969) that words can be eliminated
altogether, but Mike Leigh is one of
several directors who have been using
their creativity to elicit a text from ac¬
tors by means of improvization, while
Peter Brook has been experimenting
with his international team of actors to
find whether there is "another
language, just as exacting for the
author, as the language of words... a
language of actions, a language of
sounds a language of word-as-part-of
movement, of word-as-lie, word-as-
parody, of word-as-rubbish, of word-
as-contradiction, of word-shock or
word-cry". When he commissioned the
poet Ted Hughes to invent a new
language for a production at the 1971
festival at Persepolis, he was trying to
test how far human beings could be
made to ignore differences of race,
language and cultural tradition, com¬
municating through movements and
sounds, using the lowest common
multiples of human expressiveness, and
raising them to a higher power.
When he took his actors to play in
African villages, he was again trying to
create a form of drama immediately
comprehensible to any human being, to
traverse linguistic and cultural fron¬
tiers. It is in the nature of avant-garde
theatre to pit itself against problems
that are at most partially soluble. As
one wave rolls back, the next is already
advancing, and it may be that different
parts of a solution are floating on each.
Ronald Hayman
Anthropological theatre
In January 1982 the Rome-based Teatro dell'IRAA (Institute of Research about the Actor's Art), founded by Renato Cuocolo and
Raffaela Rossellini, launched with Unesco aid a project entitled "Theatre out of Theatre". The aim, in Cuocolo's words, is to explore
"the possibility of a theatre of communication which could promote knowledge and understanding among different cultures and
peoples". The first experimental step in this direction took the Italian actors to the Rucahue reserve in southern Chile, the home of
many of the country's Mapuche Indians. There they presented their work to an audience remote from their usual European public,
took part in the daily activities of the Indians, and joined in their festivals and rituals in order to study certain cultural forms such
as shamanism, which is still prevalent among the Mapuche. Photo shows Italian actors and Mapuche villagers taking part in a
ceremony to consecrate the spot where the performances were held. The Machi (shaman) is seen initiating a rite of welcome and
fertility which took place near a sacred cinammon tree planted by the cacique (the chief of the community) in honour of the actors
from a distant land.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Right, panel in an exhibition on the theme of "Masks" held
at the Commonwealth Institute in London in 1980.
Shared
disillusion
by Michel Cournot
THEATRE is: one or several human beings, physically
present in the here-and-now, who simulate, who pre¬
tend, to do, to say something in the same place as other
human beings who are also physically present and who as a rule
do not move and are silent.
Those who make believe, who "play", are called "actors";
those who are silent are called spectators.
Considered coldly, from outside, theatre is not different
from that which is not theatre. It is the mother who sings a
lullaby or tells her child a fairy story; it is the unknown man
who contrives to dress, control his gestures, facial expressions
and tone of voice, and chooses his words in order to attract the
unknown woman. '
But the purely utilitarian act, like that of the workman who
performs the gestures of the assembly-line beneath the
foreman's eye simply to earn his living and without being in¬
volved heart and soul in his work that too is a form of theatre.
These gestures are so profoundly alien to the workman, so
much a matter of indifference and even distress, that the "acts"
when he performs them.
And then there are the more common theatres of social life:
judges and lawyers in the courtroom; political leaders watching
the parade from the rostrum; the soldiers or civilians marching
by (actors in the presence of actors); or the waiter in the
restaurant who "playfully" serves with stylized gestures.
Theatre in the strict sense, the "art" of theatre, so called to
distinguish it from the continuing social game, usually takes
place away from the workplace, in special premises in the even¬
ing after business hours, or on Sundays and during holidays.
In these moments and places of "leisure", actors and spec¬
tators perform this parallel activity: beginning again "outside
the real world", the acts, gestures and words of reality.
This counterfeiting, this imaginary imitation of real life, is
not a phony operation, a shared lie. The men and women who,
on stage on this particular evening, do the actor's job, really do
endure the physical and spiritual effort, the sufferings, joys and
anguish of authentically accomplished acts; it may even be said
that they have a stronger physical perception and awareness of
these acts than many clerks, labourers or intellectual workers in
their working life.
As for the theatre audience, all its members have been spec¬
tators before, leaning out of the window and watching the
MICHEL COURNOT, French journalist and writer, is theatre critic with
the Paris daily Le Monde and literary critic of the weekly Le Nouvel Obser¬
vateur. He has written several books (one of which won the Fénéon Prize)
andafilm Les Gauloises Bleues which was presented al the Cannes Festival
in 1968.
world go by, but the act of visual and auditory perception which
they perform in this particular place on this particular evening
they experience with far more attention and keenness.
Time spent at the theatre might be considered as time in a
thoughtful, contemplative life, a life of awareness and en¬
durance, in the tension of truthful expression, imaginative and
creative effort, while time spent away from the theatre, often
fraudulent and tedious, at home, at work or travelling between
the two, might be time in a mechanical, forced, uncommitted,
fictitious life.
The workaday repetition of life in society might be con¬
sidered as a fragile collective fiction which possibly continues to
function because it rests on an age-old nucleus of habit, submis¬
sion and thoughtlessness.
A spectator at the theatre, begun anew, of a great city in the
morning might feel giddy at the sight of these hundreds of
thousands of men and women who do not stay in bed, or at
home in an armchair, but instead go down into the metro once
again, take the dust-sheet off the typewriter, open the shop, sit
down again, wrists chained as a safety precaution, in front of
the automatic machine.
The whole performance begins anew, without conviction,
above all perhaps because the new beginning is in itself a train¬
ing to perform the gestures and words of this life. The perfor¬
mance begins anew independently of each person's real choice,
the true hopes and discernment he once had, the performance
begins anew and will go on until the final day in this woolly
unanimous state of sleepy assent and accustomed acceptance.
And some evenings, for some who steel themselves, in those
places of creation and reflection called "theatres", on the
fringe of this collective sleep, gestures and words are ac¬
complished in the light, in full awareness, with spectators who
are at last awakened. A few hours of responsible life stolen
from the illusion of the day.
This seems to be the meaning of Theatre in the old world.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The outline of Africa serves as a
backdrop for the Togolese actor and
dramatist S. Kokou Allouwassio.
Photo © All Rights Reserved
AFRICA
The changing scene
by Ange-Séverin Malanda
AFRICAN theatre is a pheno¬
menon which long sowed con¬
fusion and perplexity in the
minds of those who observed it. In¬
stead of questioning the premises
which underlay their vision of African
forms of theatre, such observers
jumped to the conclusion that these
forms merely indicated the existence of
a "pre-theatre" in Africa. In other
words, they were voicing a preference
for the norms of European theatre at
a given stage in its history.
Some aspects of the festivals and
other ceremonies of traditional Africa
were undoubtedly theatrical. These
festivals, often held to mark specific
occasions, had religious undertones
ANGE-SEVERIN MALANDA is a Congolese
poet who has studied at the Institut d'Etudes
Théâtrales in Paris.
and their social and economic repercus¬
sions were countless. In fact the dif¬
ficulty of defining African theatre in
precise terms arose from the fact that
the moments of "drama" were part of
such an immense canvas of experience.
Any attempt to make a brief survey
of African theatre today is bound to
face difficulties because of all the acts
and gestures, all the salient events,
which are dramatized in it. However,
let us try to review some of the most
significant experiments in African
theatre, bearing in mind that we are
confronted by a phenomenon which
has, in a sense, neither centre nor
periphery. It exists on a continental
scale, since theatre troupes travel wide¬
ly and learn from and influence each
other. As a result of the generally
prevailing production conditions, ex¬
periments tend to be similar in nature,
and as African theatre people today
map out new perspectives, they find
themselves grappling with more or less
the same problems.
The William Ponty training college
in Senegal at the end of the 1930s is
considered by many to be the seedplot
of today's African theatre. But this is a
restrictive, narrowly chronological
judgment; the same claim could be
made, for instance, of the Collège
Saint-Joseph in the Belgian Congo
during colonial times. Contemporary
African theatre has been nurtured by
several schools through which certain
models of European theatre have made
inroads in Africa.
Essentially, theatre is an event which
is never repeated, since each perfor¬
mance is an original, ephemeral version
which is different from, though akin
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
to, previous performances. Traditional
performances took this strictly into ac¬
count and were a measure of all its
possibilities. The irruption of the writ¬
ten text into African theatre struck a
blow at this conception of drama.
As I have noted, the schools were the
initial medium through which many
classics of the European theatre came
to Africa. The churches were the other
channel through which elements of
European theatre came to be somewhat
rapidly engrafted onto African theatre.
The most striking example of this
phenomenon is undoubtedly the kan-
tata, as practised in such West African
countries as Togo and Ghana. These
dramatizations of passages from the
Bible, associated with references
adapted to the African social and
cultural context were at first performed
in the churches and then went on to win
a fresh audience outside.
African theatre is based on a dual
tradition. It is increasingly tending to
absorb elements originating from
Western forms, while also drawing on
local or regional traditions. It
thus renews itself using traditional
myths, stories, songs, masks and cos¬
tumes, and absorbing various other
influences.
Photos © National Museum of Malt
Koteba is a traditional form of theatre in Mali where, during the dry
season, farmers and villagers turn into actors, singers and musicians.
Koteba plays either recount events from village life or dramatize rela¬
tions between villagers and the authorities. Above, a scene from The
Arrival of the Commandant. The show always begins with a "proces¬
sion", top, in which the actors slowly walk on stage singing to per¬
suade the spirits to leave the stage to human beings. Photos show ac¬
tors of the National Theatre of Mali, directed by Aguibou Dembele.
"Theatre is really on the move in
West Africa," says Alain Ricard. "It
uses local languages, it is not always
written, and often it is not written at
all. Written drama, frequently in Euro¬
pean languages, is in a paradoxical
situation. Drama written in a European
language is often used to train
schoolchildren to use that language. As
a result it loses its theatrical nature and
becomes a stylistic classroom
exercise."
Despite the influence of the classics
of European theatre and the growing
number of locally written plays, the
relationship between the African
theatre and written drama is an am¬
bivalent one. The comparison made by
the Togolese Senouvo Agbota Zinsou
between the concert party and the corn-
media dell'arte is not without validity.
The commedia dell'arte appeared in
Italy after breaking away from the
commedia sostenuta (a form connected
to written drama). The concert party,
like the commedia dell'arte, is based on
improvisation and on the actor's cor¬
poral and verbal dexterity: there is no
text to dictate what he should act. In
the concert party, which is nevertheless
derived from the kantata, there is no set
text to govern the pace of the acting or
the performance. The dramatic effect
is thus not dictated by the written word.
Below, Shakespeare African-style. A
scene from the Théâtre Sénégalais
production of Macbeth at the Theatre of
Nations, Paris.
Photo © Nicolas Treatt, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Languages other than those used in
most of the repertory of written drama
(English, French) are now taking the
stage. Another kind of dramatic
rhetoric is being shaped from new raw
material. Bernt Lindfors' comment
that "forms of oral expression have a
greater impact than the written word in
Kenya" can be applied to Africa as a
whole.
The relationship between the African
theatre and the written text is one of
knot-like ambiguity. It expresses all the
issues involved in the transformation of
a heritage and lies at the heart of the
work done in recent years by such
groups as the Roccado-Zoulou Theatre
directed by Sony Labou Tansi in the
Congo, by Koteba theatre as directed
by Souleymane Koly in the Ivory
Coast, by the Mwondo Theatre of
Zaire, and the many Yoruba theatre
groups of Nigeria. The bold ex-
independently of a written text, instead
of theatre as we know it in the West,
bound to and limited by the text." This
comment also explains, incidentally,
why people dared to insinuate for so
long that African theatre did not
exist failing to acknowledge that the
emergence of the "Gutenberg galaxy"
was related to the importance attached
to the written text in the dominant con¬
ception of European theatre. A glimpse
of Souleymane Koly at work is enough
to see how far away he stands from this
approach. As he has explained, he puts
on plays in which there is "little textual
matter, a lot of corporal expression,
dancing, music and singing." The play
sometimes becomes musical comedy.
African theatre today can be
distinguished from traditional theatre
in a number of ways. What the French
historian Marcel Détienne has called a
Theatre created a show based on the
mythology associated with twins. They
transformed, mimed and sang these
myths, drawing on a variety of ethnic
traditions.
Above all, urbanization has changed
the material conditions in which shows
are produced and reach their audience.
Very few theatres are open on a perma¬
nent basis. Shows are often staged on
improvised stages (in bars, schools, on
trestles, etc.). The fact that theatres ex¬
ist, regardless of their numbers, re¬
quires dramatists to devise a new kind
of practice. Even the itinerant troupes
of Nigeria, which seem to be becoming
professionalized (their tours follow
regular circuits) are facing increasingly
acute production problems. Whereas
the triumph of the director in Europe
dates from the nineteenth century, in
Africa his reign has yet to begin. Out¬
side the "institutional" stage (such as
The Troupe du Roccado-
Zoulou of Brazzaville (Peo¬
ple's Republic of the Congo),
directed by Sony Labou Tan-
si, has won a reputation in re¬
cent years for taking themes
from everyday life and
presenting them in a style in
which the country's cultural
identity is expressed through
speech and gesture. Photo
shows a scene from Ils sont
là ! ("They are there!"), a
stage adaptation of seven
stories published under the
title Tribaliques.
perimental work done at the Kamirithu
cultural centre in Limuru (Kenya) in
1977 with their production in Kikuyu
of Ngaahika Ndeenda is part of the
same phenomenon.
The work produced in the early years
of modern African theatre was charac¬
terized by frantic and sterile imitation
of European theatre. Paradoxically,
new perspectives were then emerging in
the West through the discovery of non-
European drama. Paul Claudel was
studying Japanese theatre, Antonin
Artaud Balinese theatre, and Bertold
Brecht Chinese theatre.
In 1935, Artaud noted in Le Théâtre
et son Double that "the revelation of
Balinese theatre" had been for him an
opportunity "to give a physical and
non-verbal dimension to the theatre, in
which drama is contained within
everything that can happen on stage,
14
veritable "process of laicization" has
boosted the transformation of tradi¬
tional theatre. Theatre in the past was
marked by the imprint of sacred
rituals. The birth of contemporary
drama took place at a time when the
sacred aspects of certain traditional
forms of dramatic expression were
becoming less prominent.
New social and historical deter¬
minants, including those caused by the
intensive urbanization process which
has been taking place in Africa in the
last few decades, have shaped
theatrical activities, which are now cen¬
tred primarily in the cities, their impact
being felt only sporadically in the rural
areas. In the mid-1970s, Catharsis, a
group from Lubumbashi, scoured the
country observing and collating traces
and vestiges of traditional theatre prac¬
tices. In 1976, members of the Mwondo
that of the Daniel Sorano Theatre in
Senegal) suitable solutions to produc¬
tion and stagecraft problems are hard
to find. Here the African theatre is han¬
dicapped by its material poverty.
As far as audience reaction is con¬
cerned, the forms of drama which com¬
mand the most faithful public are those
which are produced in local languages,
by such troupes as those which perform
Kotéba in Mali and Nigeria's Yoruba
theatre. These are the forms which en¬
courage audience participation open-
air theatre being particularly successful
in this respect.
Urbanization has thus not stifled the
emergence of new forms of drama in
Africa. Through these new forms, a
new aesthetics is today being created.
African theatre is a theatre of experi¬
mentation.
Ange-Séverin Malanda
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
JAPAN Noh and Kabuki:
The beauty of form
by Masao Yamaguchi
First performed in 1 71 3, Tsuuchi Jihei's Sukeroku Yukarino Edozakura (Sukeroku, Flower of Edo) is one of Kabuki's most scintillating
plays. With its extravagant procession scenes, sword fights and passages of pure slapstick, it portrays all the sensuality, vitality and
humour of Kabuki plays of the Genroku period (1688-1730). Below, a famous scene in which a comic servant, Sembei (right) con¬
fronts Sukeroku, the hero of the play.
OF the various forms of classical
Japanese theatre, Noh and
Kabuki are the best known
outside Japan. Chronologically speak¬
ing, Noh theatre, which originated in
the second half of the fourteenth cen¬
tury, preceded Kabuki, which dates
from the early seventeenth century.
Noh theatre was the invention of the
actor Kan-ami Kiyotsugu (1333-1384)
who, under the patronage of the all
powerful shogun Yoshimitsu Asikaga,
combined several earlier theatrical
forms to create a new genre known as
MASAO YAMAGUCHI, of Japan, is a staff
member of the Institute for the Study of
Languages and Cultures of Asia and Africa,
Tokyo University of Foreign Studies. He is the
author of several published works, the most re¬
cent of which is "Invitation to Cultural An¬
thropology" (1982).
sarugaku-no-Noh. Kan-ami's new
creation was refined by his son Zeami
who not only raised Noh to the height
of artistic perfection but also left
behind him a corpus of philosophical
writings on the principles of its
performance.
Noh had immense appeal for the
warrior class of medieval Japan, partly
because its aesthetic rigidity seemed to
have something in common with
samurai rigorism. However, unlike the
rigour of the warrior ethic, the
aesthetic rigidity in Noh was achieved
through the creation of formal beauty
by means of body movements that had
the power to reach the subconscious
level of the mind of the audience.
Essentially, Noh is based on the
shamanistic layer of Japanese culture.
Economy in the décor is characteristic
of the staging of Noh. We see only a
picture of a huge pine tree on the
backdrop, a picture which reminds the
connoisseur of the kaju, or plank in the
shape of a tree, that is to be seen centre
stage in the wayang kulit (shadow
theatre) of Java and Bali. In Japanese
folk tradition big old trees were
venerated since they were thought to
be, like the kaju of the wayang kulit,
the mediating point through which the
gods descended to earth. The pine tree
may, in fact, have been thought to be
the axis running through the centre of
the earth and its association with the
notion of eternity supports the ex¬
planation that it is the pivot of the
world. It is therefore the focal point of
transformation where the gods, the ac¬
tors in whom they become incarnate,
and the audience undergo some kind of
change.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
-The Noh repertoire includes several
types of play: okina and sambaso,
celebratory plays in which a god
assumes human form as an old man
and holds a dialogue with a local spirit
wearing a black face-mask; waki Noh,
in which local gods of lesser status are
represented; "warrior-ghost" plays;
"woman" plays; plays about insanity;
and "demon" plays.
Although outwardly different, these
Noh plays are all expressions of a
similar basic structure. They follow a
narrative pattern in which unworldly
figures, whether demons, the sub¬
conscious spirit of women, or the souls
of the dead, are evoked on the stage
through the agency of the "bystander",
act out their story in dance form and
finally disappear after having been ap¬
peased by the prayers of the priest.
There are usually three major roles in
Noh plays: the shite (hero), the waki
(the" "bystander", normally in the
character of an itinerant priest) and the
ai-kyogen (an intermediary represen¬
ting a local personage).
The role of the shite is divided into
two parts: the mae-shite, in the early
part of the play, and the ato-shite,
when the character appears in another
form. Thus the shite appears first as an
ordinary person who withdraws after
meeting the waki; the ai-kyogen then
explains the local legend relating to the
hero, or shite, who reappears after an
interval in his second form wearing a
mask.
In addition, a chorus, seated at the
right hand side of the stage, recites nar¬
rative parts of the script and, at
moments of climax, comes on to the
stage with highly symbolic expressions.
The chorus is said to represent the inner
voice of the audience.
The role of the waki is of interest
because it is in part a reflection of a
historical reality. In late thirteenth cen¬
tury Japan there was a Buddhist sect
known as jishu which specialized in
communication with dead souls by
means of chanting and dance.
Members of the sect are said to have
visited ancient battlefields and prayed
for the warriors who had died there.
The jishu priest would recount the
story of a fallen warrior to the people
who gathered round him, evoking the
spirit of the dead hero through the
power of his performance. These
priests were thus, in a sense,- the suc¬
cessors in medieval Japan of the
shamans of ancient times who acted as
intermediaries between this world and
the world beyond.
One category of Noh plays is known as "women
pieces" or Kazura Noh (literally "wig pieces",
since wigs are often used for women's roles). The
performers' masks and elaborate heavy silk
costumes contrast with the traditional austere
stage setting of Noh plays which consists of a
representation of an aged pine tree. In this scene
from Hagoromo (The Robe of Feathers), by the
great Noh playwright Zeami (1363-1443), a god¬
dess captivates a humble fisherman by the beauty
of her dance.
Photo © Mireille Vautier, Paris
16
Noh theatre is essentially a theatre of
fantasy. The stage can be visualized as
being the equivalent of a cinema
screen, the unworldly figures projected
on it being an extension of the waki's
subconscious mind which acts, as it
were, as the film projector. In watching
the "screen" of this theatre of fantasy,
each member of the audience sees deep
into the recesses of his own mind.
It is through these ancient roots in
the Japanese shamanistic experience
that Noh theatre still has power to
move the audiences of today. Watching
Noh is thus like a psycho-therapeutic
process which cures the audience of the
frustrations caused by its alienation
from the roots of human existence.
Kabuki is a later theatrical form than
Noh, being developed early in the
seventeenth century; but the relation¬
ship between the two forms should not
be seen only in chronological terms. In
the history of Japanese theatre, and in¬
herent in its very nature, we see a
tendency for new theatrical forms to be
created in terms of dialectical
frameworks.
From early times, the appearance of
gods in Japan was marked by the
presence of two in part opposing
figures: the kami (god) and the modoki
(interlocutor, intermediary). This di¬
chotomy is repeated over and over
again in the structure of kami belief
and also in the creation of new
theatrical forms in Japan.
Although this opposition between
kami and modoki originally signified
an opposition between god the visitor
from outside the community and
modokithe local interpreter of the
god's messageit could also explain
various types of dialectical relation¬
ship, for example: kami modoki;
sacred profane; master servant-
clown; conqueror defeated; shite
waki; aristocratic popular; senior
junior.
It was against this dialectical
background that Kabuki came into ex¬
istence. The art of Kabuki is said to
have been originated by a legendary
figure, Okuni, reputedly a priestess at¬
tached to a shrine called Izumo-taisha.
Appearing on stage as a waki who
evoked the spirit of Yamasaburo
Nagoya, a young and handsome war¬
rior said to have fallen in battle, Okuni
succeeded in attracting large audiences.
It should be noted that the essential
structures of Noh as a shamanistic
theatrical form was maintained in
Okuni's Kabuki.
However, Kabuki had a different
orientation and different patrons from
Noh. Whereas Noh had been patroniz¬
ed by the Samurai class and was
oriented towards the past, Kabuki drew
its patrons from the new merchant class
and was oriented towards the contem¬
porary world of affairs rather than the
legendary and historical past. While
evocation of the spirit of the past in
order to reach deep down into the unex¬
plored recesses or the mind was one of
the more important purposes of Noh,
Kabuki was concerned with glorifying
the vital energy of the urban commer¬
cial class. Although Kabuki often
employed historical settings, these were
used to disguise the contemporary
nature of events since the Tokugawa
government forbade Kabuki per-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
/
¿r%s
t\
1
Irf
',' ,
An actor preparing for an aragoto (violent or warrior style) Kabuki play, applies a special form of stylized make-up, called
kumadori, which makes use of bold designs of bright red, blue, grey or black on the background of the whitened face. The
red lines represent the veins of the hero standing out in anger at the evil deeds of the villain.
WSKKKKÊtÊÊBKKmKIBÊBBKÊBKBKÊI^KKKBÊÊÊ^ÊmBBa
formers to draw on material from con¬
temporary political affairs.
The art of Kabuki was developed in
two cities, Osaka and Edo (today
Tokyo), with two different styles
emerging from the two cities: wagoto
and aragoto. The citizens of Osaka, be¬
ing principally engaged in commercial
activities, developed a gentler, more
realistic attitude which was reflected in
wagoto (soft or merchant style)
Kabuki, whereas at Edo, the centre of
military government, the mix of war¬
rior and citizen gave rise to a specific
life style and short-tempered behaviour
which was echoed in the highly stylized,
more violent aragoto (violent or war¬
rior style) Kabuki. Here again we find
a dialectical contrast similar to that bet¬
ween harmonious and violent gods
harmony being the attribute of the
parental deity and violence that of his
offspring.
Scene from a Kabuki
dance-play, Kagami Jishi
(The Dancing Lion).
Kagami Jishi is a Kabuki
version of an older Noh
play. Persuaded to dance
by her companions, a
lady of the court dons a
lion mask which gradual¬
ly takes possession of
her and begins to dance
of its own volition.
Photo © Toshiro Monta, National
Theatre of Japan
The association of violence with the
emergence of a young deity, as
reflected in aragoto, had long been an
element of the Japanese folk imagina¬
tion, while wagoto seems to have in¬
herited the structure of the visiting god
who is met by a local priest or priestess.
In a wagoto performance the scene is
usually set in the geisha quarter to
which rich merchants come to conduct
stylized love affairs following strict
rules of etiquette. The client is assumed
to be the visiting god, while the geisha
is cast in the role of the priestess. Thus
there is a continuation of the structures
based on the shite, or main character,
and the waki, or interlocutor.
Wagoto and aragoto developed in
different urban settings and are
.classified as different and contrasting
styles. Nevertheless, both forms are
sometimes found in the same play, as in
Sugawaradenju-tenaraikagami ("The
House of Sugawara"), and sometimes
the hero of a wagoto is transformed in¬
to the bloody hero of an aragoto, as in
Natumatsuri-naniwakagami (a bloody
incident in the festival of Osaka).
Being a free and popular form of art,
Kabuki was able to integrate many of
the arts of the street performer and
achieve a synthesis of various forms of
music, dance and performing style
which were excluded from the closed,
sophisticated Noh art form. It was par¬
ticularly suited to the assimilation of
material from marginal categories,
such as thieves and geishas, and turning
it into a refined aesthetic performance.
It is this ability to synthesize the central
and the marginal, the sublime and the
mundane, that enables Kabuki to con¬
tinue to attract large audiences in
Japan. Whereas Noh bases itself on the
deep structures of human experience,
Kabuki takes as its starting point the
trifling incidents of daily life. Both
forms, however, end up by achieving a
similar effect of formal beauty. In this
way each encompasses the other.
Masao Yamaguchi
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
HAITI
The awakening
of Creole
consciousness
by Félix Morisseau-Leroy
FELIX MORISSEAU-LEROY is a Haitian poet, novelist and dramatist
who writes both in French and in Creole. After studying in the United
States, he worked in the theatre in Ghana and Senegal. He is the author of
a number ofdramatic works including Natif-natal (poems), Kasamansa and
Jadin Créol (stories), and a trilogy about Creon, the figure from
Sophoclean tragedy.
THE Creole language theatre
scored its greatest success with
Sophocles' Antigone in a ver¬
sion which was not only linguistically
transposed but also adapted to take in¬
to account the traditions of the Haitian
people, their gods and the ways of their
leaders. The première on 23 July 1953,
at the Rex theatre, Port-au-Prince and
the performance in May 1959 at the
Theatre of Nations festival in Paris,
had a worldwide impact.
But in the opinion of the author
nothing confirmed this success more
than an exclamation by one of the five
thousand spectators, mainly peasants,
who were attending a performance of
the tragedy on the lawns of the Agricul¬
tural College at Damiens. Just when
Creon, in desperation, was calling on
Tiresias to invoke Danbala in his
favour, the spectator exclaimed: "Dan¬
bala won't reply!" Evidently the spec¬
tator who voiced this ill-timed com¬
ment had foreseen the dénouement of
the tragedy; he had already clearly un¬
derstood that the gods of African
Guinea, who had taken the place of the
Greek gods in the Haitian adaptation,
had abandoned Antigone's murderer.
Antigone continued its run at Port-
au-Prince, Saint Marc and Cap Haï¬
tien. It was performed in New York,
Boston, Montreal and Miami where the
Haitian community, comprising all age
groups, rediscovered their home coun¬
try or discovered aspects of it .which
were completely new to them.
Below, a production of Antigone by the Théâtre de Haïti. Sophocles' tragedy was not simply translated into Creole but adapted to
traditional Haitian ways and beliefs of African origin. An English version of this "Afro-Haitian Antigone" has been staged by the Arts
Theatre of Ghana. Right, a scene in which Tiresias, the Theban seer, invokes the African divinity Danbala.
Photo, © Roger Pic, Pans
V
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
An English version of the Haitian
Antigone, translated by Mary
Dorkonou, was performed in Ghana.
A young chief who had attended three
consecutive performances rushed back¬
stage at the end of the show to enquire
when he could see it for the fourth time.
The same version, slightly adapted for
a Jamaican audience, was performed at
the National Theatre Festival of
Jamaica.
After the initial success of Antigone
in Creole at the Rex theatre, Franck
Fouché put on his Oedipus Rex there
for the same popular audience. Later,
drawing on Haitian traditions, he
wrote a large number of plays in
Creole, which he staged for middle-
class audiences at the Rex theatre and
at the Théâtre de Verdure Massillon
Coicou. After his death his Bouki au
Paradis was performed at Port-au-
Prince before an enthusiastic audience.
It is difficult for me to talk about
Creole language theatre without using
the first person. The more I write in
Creole, the more I feel part of a Creole-
speaking community. Personal ex¬
perience is no more than the experience
of each of my characters within the
context of each new play.
I do not consider it immodest to talk
about it any more. Bernard Shaw said
that Joan of Arc wrote Saint Joan. I
can claim with even more justification
that, once they are placed in a dramatic
situation, my characters write my plays
in Creole, just as the people whose im¬
passioned scribe I am dictate the poems
and stories I publish.
In 1953, I said to Pradel Pompi-
lius who after thirty years of hesita¬
tion has become a fervent enthusiast of
Creole that if I were to cast Creon in
the role of a rural police chief obliged
to kill his niece and daughter-in-law-to-
be in order to affirm and consolidate
his authority, he would be quite
capable of expressing his dilemma of
conscience in Creole, "unless", I
stated, "one must speak French to have
a dilemma of conscience, or even to
have a conscience at all."
The men of letters of my generation
who, thirty years ago, did not think
that there could be a viable Creole
literature now support it fervently. For
me the case is won and I call on young
writers to stop wasting time on futile
polemics about the last of Toussaint
Louverture's sons and to devote them¬
selves to creative writing. The real pro¬
blem is whether one wants to emulate
Placide, Toussaint's son, who joined
the French army and fought against his
father, or Isaac, his son-inlaw, who
fought at his side.
Of course there were other issues that
bothered me, some of which have now
been resolved and others whose solu¬
tion has been put off till better days.
Where, for example, could actors for
the Creole language theatre be
recruited? The answer in this case was
obvious among Creole-speakers or
among those who, while speaking one
or more foreign languages had main¬
tained a Creole awareness.
Antigone was created in 1953 for the
literate audiences of the Rex theatre.
Anatol, written in .1955 and staged at
my theatre at Mont Hercule with a cast
recruited from the habitués of the oun-
fo, a temple of the Haitian popular
religion in the Plaine des Frères, en¬
abled me to put into practice many of
my new options.
Séfi, a fearless manbo (a high-
ranking member of the voodoo hierar¬
chy in Guinea) realizes that the power
which the gods on the side of good had
granted to Bout, her husband, until
recently a famous oungan (high priest),
is weakening because he uses it to do
evil. She therefore hands over the ason
(a rattle with a bell attached, the sym¬
bol of spiritual power) to her son. The
ceremony of this transmission of
authority is so moving that all the peo¬
ple present enter into a trance. All the
dramatic art of the Griots and the
Anansi story-tellers of Ghana and the
Ivory Coast combined with the tradi¬
tions of the commedia dell'arte to bring
about a miracle at the end of the per¬
formance the president of the Alliance
Française himself led the applause.
At the Institut Français the audience
interrupted the performance, rising to
acclaim Anatol for five minutes at the
moment when he raised his sword in
salute to the laplas, the voodoo master
of ceremonies.
At the open-air theatre, although it
started to rain in the middle of the
second act, the audience, far from dis¬
persing, called the actors back after the
end of the third act and began to sing
with them.
La Tragédie du Roi Christophe by the Martinique poet Aimé
Césaire, in a production by the Compagnie du Toucan at the
Theatre of Nations, in Paris. Henri Christophe, a freed slave,
became President of Haiti in 1 806. Proclaimed king in 1 81 1 , he
committed suicide in 1820 after an insurrection. His kingdom
became part of the Haitian Republic.
Photo © Information Service, Accra
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Monsieur Toussaint, as performed by the Théâtre Noir de Paris. In this Antillean work, "a prophetic vision of the past", Toussaint
Louverture, a captive in the fort de Joux in the French Jura, evokes the slave insurrection on Saint Domingue which he led from 1 796
until 1802 when he was arrested and imprisoned by the French.
In Ghana, Anatol was renamed
Kweku, a title more in keeping with the
traditions of the Fanti chiefs. During
the 1960s the Dramatic Workers
Brigade troupe of Ghana, benefiting
from conditions conducive to the
development of popular theatre, per¬
formed it more than a hundred times
throughout the country.
In Dakar, Anatol was given the
Wolof title of Doodoo, but it was less
of a success since the favourable condi¬
tions mentioned above did not exist.
I have already spoken of Franck
Fouché, whose memory we cherish. It
must be stressed, however, that the new
generation of writers has hoisted high
the flag of the Creole language. In the
United States, the Koukouy Society
organizes Creole language cultural
evenings during which poems are
recited and dramatic songs are sung.
Among the most talented members of
the Koukouy Society Jean Mapou, the
author of Pwezigram, and the poetess
Deita, the author of Majordiol, can be
singled out. -
In 1953 it was unthinkable that
Creole would be used for all literary
genres, although the "literary men" of
the time reluctantly conceded that,
because it was closer to oral expression
than the written word, it was con¬
ceivable for the theatre to be in Creole.
But then a star of the first magnitude
20
appeared in the firmament of the Hai¬
tian novel. Astronomers adjusted and
re-adjusted their telescopes to focus
on... Frankétienne. A binary star? Two
surnames or two first names? At all
events a personage who quickly became
famous. One cannot think of his Dézafi
without a dozen passages worthy of
any anthology springing to mind. It
would take up too much space to quote
them here. I shall merely say that the
novel revolves round a zombi who,
having tasted the savour of love, comes
down again to reality.
But Frankétienne did not stop there.
He turned to the theatre and provided
us, in rapid succession, with two plays,
Twou Foban and Pelen Tel, which
were performed at Port-au-Prince to
packed houses. The second of these
Creole plays has achieved great success
among emigrant Haitian communities,
which are firmly opposed to any "zom-
bification" of the masses.
I do not want to write a conclusion.
I am opening the discussion. For, clear¬
ly, I have not told the whole story. I
will, however, say that the lyrical
theatre in the Creole language, just like
the successful Creole records and songs
of Maurice Sixto, Koralen, Martha
Jean-Claude, Faran Juste, Kiki Wain-
wright and others, has attracted the at¬
tention of the critics. No, I have not
told the whole story so I cannot write a
conclusion. My African experience
has, however, shown me that there are
new horizons for the popular theatre in
national languages. The Anansi, the
theatre of Ghana, the Gwee, the cir¬
cular stage of Senegal and the arena of
Casamance, to mention only a few of
the more striking aspects of traditional
African theatre, have given me an en¬
tirely new concept of theatrical
architecture.
In March 1982, in the "note to the
critics" for my Vilibone, I predicted
that, within twenty years, when speak¬
ing of the revolution in Haitian
literature, they would be referring to
the emergence of literature in the
Creole language. Haitian literature has
already gone beyond this irreversible
stage of cultural liberation. Even
though the government has shelved the
national educational reform aimed at
making Creole official at all levels of
primary education, the few, increasing¬
ly rare opponents of Creole seem
almost as backward as those who main¬
tain that the earth is flat.
Today, more and more authors are
writing in the Creole language and
none of them seems to be about to lay
down his pen. On the contrary, a mili¬
tant Creole language movement which
extends beyond the confines of the ar¬
chipelago is gradually taking shape,
ready to defend itself against the wiles
of cultural imperialism.
Félix Morisseau-Leroy
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
EGYPT
The shadow
and the
substance
by Magda Wassef
MAGDA WASSEF is an Egyptian specialist on film and theatre. She is the
author of several studies on cinema and a doctoral dissertation on "The
image of the peasant woman in Egyptian cinema". For Unesco she has writ¬
ten a study on "The cultural heritage in Arab cinema".
Photo © All rights reserved
Dakket Zar (literally, "Music for a dance of exor¬
cism") by Mohamed El Fil, in a production directed
by Mohsen Helmy in Cairo, in 1 980. The play takes
a critical look at certain ancestral Arab rites.
THE origins of Egyptian theatre have been the subject ot
much debate: has it been influenced more by shadow
theatre and Karaghöz or by Western drama? Today this
debate is closed. For more than half a century theatre has been
fully integrated into Egyptian social and cultural life, and Egyp¬
tian playwrights, directors and actors today, like their counter¬
parts elsewhere, have other preoccupations. They are concern¬
ed with problems of modern theatre and forms of production,
the relationship between the latter and traditional and popular
theatre, the question of freedom of expression in relation to the
State, urban theatre and rural theatre, and so on.
Here I should like to give a brief account of the first of these
problems, that of modern theatre, taking into account the link
which exists between experimentation with forms inspired by
Western theatre and those derived from the Egyptian and
Arabic cultural heritage.
Egyptian theatre, has been characterized by two conflicting
trends since the 1960s, a period during which theatre has ex¬
perienced a remarkable flowering. The first trend is inspired by
Western formal experimentation and trends such as the theatre
of the absurd of Ionesco and Beckett, while the second draws
its inspiration from Egyptian and Arabic stories and popular
drama.
The "Pocket Theatre" created by Saad Ardash in 1962 and
the "Avant-Garde Theatre" founded a few years later both en¬
courage experimental work, but the more traditional National
Theatre and the "El Hakim Theatre" also support bold
productions.
These theatres have staged Tewfik el Hakim's Ya Tale'e El
Shagar (You who climb the tree), a first attempt at Egyptian
"theatre of the absurd", and El Farafir (The Fledglings) by
Yusef Idris, in which the author brings together Western
theatre and traditional forms by taking his two main characters
from the Egyptian shadow theatre. In El Ardehalgui (The Public
, Writer) and El Wafed (The Outsider), Mikhail Romain evokes the
absurdity of life through characters who shun reality and sink
into a kind of paranoia. Alfred Farag was one of the first Egyp¬
tian playwrights to draw inspiration from the Arab cultural
heritage. His well-known trilogy the Barber of Baghdad, AH
guénah el Tabrizi and The Letters of the Judge of Seville have
had a strong influence on the new Egyptian theatre. Farag is an
innovator in the sense that he adapts old tales to modern times;
he handles language and dialogue with great skill.
These playwrights produced their main body of work during
the 1960s, and left their mark on that decade. There are also
a number of talented young directors who have contributed to
Egyptian theatre the knowledge and experience they acquired
in Europe.
The development of Egyptian experimental theatre is largely
due to such directors as Saad Ardash, Karam Metawe, Galal el
Sharkawi and Ahmed Zaki. Their different approaches to their
work have brought great diversity and richness to Egyptian
theatre.
While social theatre was the dominant trend in Egypt in the
1960s and formal experimentation was relatively limited, the
1 970s saw the birth of a more aesthetically advanced theatre.
Certain forms, such as "poetic theatre" and "epic theatre" en¬
joyed a heyday. Salah Abdel Sabour, whose The Tragedy of El
Hallaje had enriched "poetic theatre" as early as 1 963, produc¬
ed Leila and the Madman and After the Death of the King. Draw¬
ing inspiration from the Arab cultural heritage, Chawki Khamis
brought a new dimension to epic theatre. Already perceptible in
The City of Masked Men and Love and War, this epic dimension
reached its apogee in Sindbad directed by Ahmed Zaki, a play
in which the chorus and not the individual hero plays the leading
role.
Fawzi Fahmi's The Virgin of Rachid is also a work of epic
theatre, but here the language used by the author is of para¬
mount importance; it is akin to the language of poetry, although
it does not respect all the rules of poetry, and is close to the
literary language, though lacking its rigidity.
The experiments carried out in modern Egyptian theatre thus
reflect the current preoccupations of their authors. Today a
period of pure experimentation seems to be over and to have
given way to a less esoteric, more popular form of theatre.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
SOVIET UNION
The theatre of
the market-place
by Nelly Kornienko
THE theatre is as many-sided as
life itself. As the centuries go
by, its forms undergo modifica¬
tion, extinction, renaissance and
transformation, and its faces, imagery
and masks may change. But all these
formsthose which have had their
day as well as those which have been
transformed or reborn still continue
to sustain the culture of peoples.
...Colourfully painted with scenes
from fairy-tales, the curtain rises to
show the market square of an old Rus¬
sian town. On to the stage bursts a
noisy crowd of jesters, clowns and
buffoons. A dancing bear shuffles at
the end of its chain. Someone has
climbed up on a pair of stilts. Carriage
wheels turn, horses neigh and whinny.
There is a jingling of bells, a great
strumming of balalaikas and gusli*, the
shrill sound of pipes. This is how
Soviet director Les Tanyuk's produc¬
tion of Alexander Pushkin's Tale of the
Fisherman and the Fishwife begins.
First. staged at the Central Children's
Theatre in Moscow in 1966, it has
been performed since then on
something like 700 occasions before
audiences in Bulgaria, the German
Democratic Republic, the United
States, Canada, the Federal Republic
of Germany, and other countries.
In accordance with the conventions
of the entertainment staged by stroll¬
ing players at the old yarmarki, or fairs,
the actors become wild animals, trees,
the sun, the moon, the wind, with the
popular comic figure Shut Gorokhovy
leading the dance. "Look! Look! The
sea!" cries a little girl in the audience.
And lo and behold, embroidered cloths
which the actors have stretched from
one side of the stage to the other are
suddenly transformed into waves
which sweep over the heads of the
heroes of the tale. Flashing and
splashing, dancing on their crests,
Zolotaya Rybka, the Golden Fish of
Good Fortune, converses with Starik,
the old fisherman. Originally written as
a short story, Pushkin's fable about
NELLY NIKOLAEVNA KORNIENKO is a
Soviet specialist in stage aesthetics and the
sociology ofculture. Among the 40 works she has
published in the USSR and elsewhere is a transla¬
tion into Ukrainian ofOn the Art of the Theatre,
by the famous English director and innovator
Edward Gordon Craig. She has worked in the
Sociology of Culture Sector of the All-Union
Scientific Research Institute of Art, and is cur¬
rently on the staff of the Russian language edi¬
tion of the Unesco Courier.
22
human pretensions and the cost of un¬
bridled ambition, carries a timeless
message. In the traditional fairground
entertainment played to a noisy, ap¬
preciative audience, with the spec¬
tators mocking the behaviour of the
characters portrayed, the director has
found a satisfactory means of adapting
Pushkin's story for the stage.
... On the stage of the Bolshoi Drama
Theatre in Leningrad, an old grey horse
bemoans his unhappy fate. Once he
was famous and handsome, a great
winner of rosettes. Today he is for¬
saken and condemned. Very soon, he
will be led off to the knacker's yard.
Never, perhaps, has this pathetic story
of a horse and not just any horse, for
we are listening to Tolstoy's
Kholstomer been told as movingly as
in this performance by Yevgeny
Lebedev, under the direction of Georgi
Tovstonogov.
Brought to the stage, exposed to the
eyes and ears of an attentive public,
related "from the inside", an individual
existence is revealed in all its
vulnerability and fragility. Perhaps for
the first time, the aesthetics of popular
theatre here venture into the hidden,
inner dimension of the human condi¬
tion. Human, because, in the last
analysis, Kholstomer's "internal mo¬
nologue" concerns each and every one
of us. It is a reflection of "the life of the
human spirit".
But for the existence of the berikaob,
a Georgian carnival masquerade
whose origins reach back to the pagan
fertility rites of an agricultural society
of the second millennium BC, Robert
Sturu's production in Tbilisi of Bertold
Brecht's The Caucasian Chalk Circle
would not have been both authentical¬
ly Georgian and authentically Brech-
tian, so international in spirit that it
was comprehensible without transla¬
tion to audiences from Mexico and
Greece, England and Yugoslavia.
In this production, the deliberate ra¬
tionality and restraint of Brecht's
original treatment is unexpectedly
replaced by a colourful, carnival at¬
mosphere in which the audience itself
participates. Brecht's "reasonable"
heroes break into snatches of Georgian
song, and punctuate their talk with the
spirited gestures of the country's
mountain people. They have, indeed,
become kinsmen of the traditional
characters of Georgian folklore the
* Gusli, a popular Russian stringed instrument.
Warrior, the Fiancé, the Match-maker,
the Bride... The device could hardly
fail after all, Brecht himself set the
action of his Chalk Circle in the
Caucasus and it is only surprising
that nobody had the same idea before
Sturu.
On the other hand, Sturu's choice
was perhaps a natural one. His produc¬
tion was staged in 1976, after a
decade which had seen a revival of in¬
terest in the roots of national cultures,
in the sources of different peoples'
ways of thinking. In the theatre, this in¬
quiry found expression in a renewed in¬
terest in, for example, the puppet
theatre of the Ukraine; the mummers
and wandering musicians of Moldavia;
the strolling players of Tajikstan, im¬
provising their performances with the
aid of masks; and the oyunthe
popular farcical plays of Azerbaijan.
In the Soviet Union, the renaissance
of the people's theatre, the "theatre of
the market place", may be observed
today in a great variety of dramatic
contexts from opera to vaudeville,
from ballet on ice to the experimental
theatre of the universities, from
festivals of sport and the Olympic
Games to overtly political theatre.
The Taganka Theatre in Moscow,
directed by Yury Lyubimov, con¬
sistently builds its productions around
the search for a synthesis between the
popular, festive, carnival tradition
(from which Lyubimov borrows the
spirit of improvisation but not the co¬
lourful atmosphere: his own approach
is particularly austere), and psycholo¬
gical, committed, morally didactic
drama. It is not by accident that the
foyer of the Taganka Theatre is
decorated with four symbolic
portraits of Stanislavsky, Vakhtan-
gov, Meyerhold and Brecht.
Brecht's The Good Woman of
Szechwan, Vladimir Mayakovsky's
Listen!, Mikhail Bulgakov's The Master
and Margarita and other productions
by the Taganka Theatre embody just
such a synthesis, which is also
reflected in the dramatic evocation of
the peasant rebellion of the eighteenth
century, led by Emel'yan Pugachev.
Here, the setting is the square where
the main events of the historical occa¬
sion took place, but the performance
CONTINUED PAGE 27
Colour page right
Pali, the monkey general allied to Rama,
fights with Thotsakan in this scene from
Thai Khon ("mask drama") theatre. Works
in the Khon repertory dramatize the pursuit
of Thotsakan, the ten-headed demon king of
Longka, by Rama whose consort. Sida, he
has abducted. The actors mime a text which
is recited and sung by a narrator and a
chorus. Scholars believe that the steps and
dance movements of Khon derived from
those of Chinese shadow theatre.
Photo © School of Oriental and African Studies, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Centre colour pages
Left hand page
Above, Beijing Opera uses a codified dramatic "language"
in which gestures, movements, vocal intonations, musical
instruments and rhythms all have precise meanings which
are understood by the audience. Here, in "Return to
Jingzhow", a scene from the opera "The Happy Associa¬
tion of the Dragon and the Phoenix", princess Sun Shang-
xiang tearfully takes leave of her mother the Dowager
Queen, played by a man.
Photo Fred Mayer © Magnum, Pans
Below, Macunaima. a play adapted by the Grupo Arte Pau
Brasil (director Antunes Filhol from a novel by Mario de An-
drade. Songs, myths, legends and dance are all used with
telling effect in this Brazilian epic directed in a style which
is less realistic than visionary and fantastic (see photo). The
young hero is a picaresque figure, a compound of sensuality
and demoniacal cruelty. In a phantasmagorical universe his
quest takes him from the virgin forest to the big city and
ultimately to the sky-where he is transformed into the
Great Bear.
Photo © Maison des Cultures du Monde, Paris
Right hand page
Above, Solsolet ("Sun, Little Sun"), staged by Barcelona's
Els Comediants troupe, which specializes in street theatre.
The show features juggling, balancing acts, horse training,
dancing giants, and midgets. Sol solet has toured in a
number of countries and has been performed at the Reyk¬
javik Festival (Iceland).
Photo © Pau Barcelo, Barcelona
Below, agrarian dance of the Bobo people of Upper Volta.
The dancers, who wear leafy masks which entirely cover
their bodies, are incarnations of Dwo, a divinity who
represents fertility and growth and acts as intermediary
between the creator (Wuro) and men, who jeopardize the
original balance between sun, earth and rain. Once a year,
they run through the village, catching in their leaves the
"dust" of evil and thus "washing away" all the misdeeds
committed in the previous year by the community, which is
regenerated by taking part in the vegetation-renewal rites.
Photo Michel Huet © Hoa Qui, Pans
Opposite page
Above, a version of Shakespeare's Richard II performed in
Paris in 1981 by the Theatre du Soleil directed by Ariane
Mnouchkine. The staging, costume, and the general
rhythm of dialogue and movements were directly inspired
by Japanese Kabuki. Ariane Mnouchkine has said that
"theatre as a mirror is not enough... unless the mirror says
'look at the other person, someone you do not know at all,
someone from the antipodes of time, space, or mind; look
at him, for he concerns you'." This emphasis on human
similarities rather than differences may explain why
Shakespeare's play about a medieval English king, produc¬
ed in accordance with the tenets of an Oriental conception
of drama, should have aroused widespread interest among
the French public.
Photo Martine Franck © Magnum, Paris
Below, a scene from a Kathakali dance-drama of southern
India, acted by members of the Keralakalamandalam com¬
pany. Some fifty of the original hundred-odd Kathakali
plays, based on the great Hindu epic poems, (the
Ramayana, the Mahabharata, and the Bhagavata Purana)
still remain popular on the stage. About sixty varieties of
elaborate make-up and costumes exist, divided into nine
main types. The colours and designs enable the audience to
recognize immediately the nature of the character being
portrayed.
Photo © Roger Pic, Pans
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 22
includes extracts from the works of the
great modern Russian poet Sergei
Yesenin, which the actors declaim in
the manner of town criers or old
masters of the art of rhetoric.
The "popular theatre" of a country
is a theatre which bears a specifically
national imprint, which is distinctive
and which exists in its own right. But it
is not merely an art form; it is also a
deeply ethical manifestation, the soil in
which a people's wisdom is rooted, the
repository of the axioms, standards of
behaviour, rituals, ceremonies and
concepts about the world which it has
accumulated over the centuries. For
this reason, the popular theatre is, as a
general rule, a matter of particular in¬
terest to creators and innovators, in
other words to.those whom history has
designated as the founders of a fun¬
damentally new art. In the Soviet
theatre, this was the role of such Rus¬
sian directors as Stanislavsky, Nemiro¬
vich-Danchenko, Vakhtangov and
Meyerhold, the Ukrainian Les Kurbas,
the Georgian Mardjanishvili, the Arme¬
nian Kalantar, and many others.
This year marks the centenary of the
birth of one of these great men of the
theatre, Yevgeny Bogrationovich
Vakhtangov. The event is being
celebrated by the international com¬
munity, in accordance with its inscrip¬
tion on the Unesco calendar of anniver¬
saries. Vakhtangov was one of the
most brilliant, original and famous ar¬
tists of his age. Joining the Moscow
Art Theatre in 1 91 1 , he quickly proved
to be one of the most talented disciples
of Stanislavsky and an ardent advo¬
cate of his system. For Vakhtangov,
the central precept of Stanislavsky's
teaching was that man's inherent crea¬
tivity must be awakened. If it failed to
convey an image, if it lacked inven¬
tiveness, if it did not speak in the
language of poetry, if it merely copied
life, the theatre had no claim to be call¬
ed an art. On the other hand, the
popular imagination was capable of
working wonders, because it was
nourished by, but never simply im¬
itated "real". life.
Vakhtangov believed that the mak¬
ing of an artist depended on the pos¬
session of the three faculties of inspira¬
tion, imagination and inventiveness. "I
love the theatre in all its manifesta¬
tions", he wrote in 1917, "but what
attracts me most of all are those
moments when the human spirit is at
its liveliest."
Even earlier, in 1912, he had spoken
of his dream of establishing a work¬
shop where, in a genuinely creative at¬
mosphere, a close-knit community of
apprentice actors could prepare
themselves for their great calling.
After the October Revolution, which
he called "a phenomenon of cosmic
dimensions", Vakhtangov addressed
himself specifically to the subject of
the popular theatre, which he con¬
sidered to be an ¡deal medium for the
expression of man's innate creativity.
"If the artist is chosen to bear the
Over the past twelve years, the "Subbota" (Saturday) Young Theatre Club, a
Leningrad-based amateur group, has been putting on avant-garde shows inspired by in¬
cidents of everyday life. There is virtually no separation between stage and auditorium
and everyone present is invited to take part in the performance and the discussion that
follows. Above, the group photographed in a Leningrad street.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Princess Turandot, based on an
eighteenth-century Italian play by
Carlo Gozzi, had its première on 28
February 1922, and has become a
classic of Soviet and world theatre, the
subject of thousands of pages of
criticism and analysis. At the
Vakhtangov Theatre in Moscow it has
been performed over 2,000 times, by
four generations of actors and before
as many generations of spectators.
Vakhtangov's unbridled imagination
lifted the spectator into the realm of
"fantastic realism" where everything
was possible. There was an orchestra,
but the musicians' instruments were
combs and paper. The beards of the
male heroes were made of scarves, or
tufts of coarse fibre. In place of tur¬
bans, the female slaves in the play
wore rolled-up pairs of trousers.
Sweet-box covers served as portraits,
paper-knives took the place of steel
daggers and, with suitable dignity, a
tennis-racket was brandished as a
regal sceptre. And God knows how
many other surprises awaited the au¬
dience on this gaudy stage!
What was being celebrated was the
rapturous free flight of the spirit a ge¬
nuine commedia dell'arte, an art form
which had leapt across time and space
to transform this Moscow theatre into
a place of popular festivity and car-
One of the rare photographs
of the Russian theatrical
director Yevgeny Vakhtangov
(1883-1922), the centenary of
whose birth is being celebrated
by Unesco and the international
community. A pupil of Konstan¬
tin Stanislavsky, the founder of
the "method" school of acting,
he is noted for his innovative
productions of Chekhov's The
Wedding and Carlo Gozzi's
Turandot.
spark of Immortality", he said, "then
let him direct his inner eye towards the
people, because what is in the people
is immortal. Today, the people are
creating new ways of living. If they are
doing so through Revolution, it is
because they had no other means of
proclaiming their sense of Injustice to
the world."
Vakhtangov's project for a truly
"popular" theatre, as accessible and
universal as the open-air, market-place
theatre of old, took shape in his mind in
1919; but it was not destined to be
carried to fruition during his lifetime.
Vakhtangov died three years later, and
failed to see the first public perfor¬
mance of his last great production
the embodiment of his central thesis,
that unfettered creativity, the celebra¬
tion of delight, abandonment to festivi¬
ty in all its forms are manifestations of
the highest spiritual leanings of
mankind.
The leading characters in Behold
Brecht's The Caucasian Chalk Circle, in a
scene from the adaptation by Robert
Sturu. Brecht's characters are portrayed
as traditional characters of Georgian
folklore.
On the stage of the
Bolshoi Drama Theatre,
Leningrad, actor Yev¬
geny Lebedev in the
role of the old grey
horse in the play based
on Tolstoy's short
story Kholstomer, a
satire on human beings
as seen from the point
of view of a horse.
Photo ©Bakhrushm State Museum
of Theatrical Art, Moscow
nival, where everyone could join the
crowd of merrymakers, exchanging his
identity for that of one of the "eternal"
jesters, Brighella or Truffaldino, Pan¬
taloon or Tartaglia.
Vakhtangov's Turandot was a
revolutionary event which brought
new ideas and new means of expres¬
sion to the theatre. His aesthetic
method, in which the actor both under¬
went his own authentic emotional ex¬
perience, in Stanislavskian style, and
also expressed his relationship with
the character he played, became one
of the key principles of the Brechtian
approach. His synthesis of the popular,
democratic values rooted in the com¬
media dell'arte, as reflected in Turan¬
dot, with the new principle of the
"dual" life of the stage character lent
itself to unlimited variations. The foun¬
dations had been laid for a tradition
based on a universal approach to the
future of the theatre. Vakhtangov was
a man who thought in terms of the
future. After him the scope of theatre
had to be redefined. The ideas of
popular theatre which he cherished still
live on today.
Nelly N. Kornienko
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
YUGOSLAVIA The Belgrade
International Theatre Festival
by Jovan Cirilov
THE Belgrade International Theatre Festival (BITEF) was found¬
ed at a time when great changes were occurring in the
European theatre. Its establishment was the outcome of a
meeting of actors held in Belgrade at Workshop 212, the theatre
which, during the 1950s, staged the first performances of the
works of Beckett, Ionesco, Adamov, etc., to be given in a socialist
country. Its slogan, "New Trends in the Theatre", proclaimed the
general line the Festival was to follow.
This was a period when a new form of theatre was reaching its
height, when informal groups were coming into being, the stages
of baroque and traditional theatre halls were being abandoned in
favour of the street, garages or disused sheds, a time of political
commitment which called for a theatre in its own image, a protest
theatre, an anti-literary theatre which saw itself as a theatre of ac¬
tion rather than of words.
It was a time when the avant-garde theories which had emerged
during the inter-war period, such as Antonin Artaud's "theatre of
cruelty", and Expressionism were being revived and new trends
were emerging such as the "guerilla theatre", the "theatre of ac¬
tion", "poor theatre", the "theatre of panic", the "theatre of the
absurd".
The first Festival, in September 1 967, brought together troupes
which had embarked on innovative courses, such as the "Living
Theater" of New York, with Julian Beck and Judith Malina, the
"Teatr Laboratorium" of Wroclaw, with Jerzy Grotowski, the
"Divadlo za Branou", with Otomar Krejca.
From the first, however, it was decided that the BITEF should not
be devoted exclusively to an avant-garde repertoire. Krejca, for ex¬
ample, staged Chekhov's Three Sisters, although he gave this
classic a new perspective which took account of the most advanc¬
ed research.
For sixteen years the Festival has been guided by this twofold ap¬
proach. Through many presentations of the masterpieces of the
world repertoire it has sought to provide a new interpretation of the
classics, be it Shakespeare re-interpreted by Peter Brook, Peter
Zadek or Yury Lyubimov, Strindberg by Ingmar Bergman, Molière by
Anatoli Efros or Roger Planchón, to name but a few. At the same
time, in keeping with the main purpose of the Festival, the most
JOVAN CIRILOV, of Yugoslavia, is drama critic with the Belgrade
newspaper Politika and has been artistic director of BITEF since it was
created. The author of a number offilm scenarios and plays which have
been performed in Yugoslavia, he has also published a collection ofpoems
and a novel, "A Time in Salzburg". He has translated into Serbo-Croat
works by Genet, Christopher Fry and Tom Stoppard.
diverse trends of the avant-garde theatre have been represented
through the work of directors from all over the world, including Vic¬
tor Garcia, Robert Wilson, Luca Ronconi, Shuji Terayama, Tadeusz
Kantor, Ariane Mnouchkine, Ljubisa Ristic, and many others.
The BITEF also pays homage to the guiding influence of age-old
traditional theatre forms on twentieth-century drama. In addition to
modern works, the Festival hosts almost every year a performance
which takes the public back, as it were, to the very roots of drama
thus giving them greater insight into aspects of present-day
theatre. There have been performances of Kathakali, Noh and
Kyogen, of the Beijing Opera and African ritual theatre, of Sicilian
puppets and the naive theatre of Naples.
Over the past sixteen years, virtually every performance has
been followed, the day after its première, by discussions between
the artists and the audience. Thus members of the public have been
able to put questions to the greatest directors, authors and actors
and let them know their own point of view.
Ever since the tenth festival, which was also that of the Theatre
of Nations, there has been a parallel festival called "BITEF on film".
Shows which for one reason or another could not be performed live
during the Festival are presented on film or video-cassette. The
public has thus been able to see, among others, Peer Gynt by Peter
Stein, Shakespeare's Memory by Giorgio Strehler, Ariane
Mnouchkine's film Molière, and Mother Courage by Bertold Brecht.
BITEF shows are often performed in other major cities in
Yugoslavia such as Zagreb, Ljubljana, Skopje, and Sarajevo, as well
as in smallercities, and the Belgrade television network broadcasts
the most important shows live or recorded.
At the close of the Festival a Yugoslav jury awards prizes
(sculptures by the Belgrade artist Nebjsa Mitric) and diplomas of
merit for those shows which best express the new trends. Au¬
dience surveys are conducted throughout the Festival and a further
prize is awarded on the basis of the views of the public.
During its sixteen years of activity, the BITEF has also dealt with
a variety of themes such as "the origins of the theatre",
"theatricalism", "directors of the new reality school", "new
stages", "the classics in a new light", and so on, which have led to
deeper research into contemporary problems in aesthetics and have
given rise to discussion in specialized reviews throughout the world.
Finally, the concept bf "Third Theatre" was born in Belgrade in
1976 during the tenth BITEF, when, at a special meeting on the
theatre in the Third World, it was proclaimed by Eugenio Barba who
has since brilliantly affirmed its practical, concrete existence
throughout the world. (See Unesco Courier January 1 978.)
The Performance Group of
New York in a scene from
Dionysos 69, directed by
Richard Scheckner and
performed at the Belgrade
Festival.
Photo © BITEF, Belgrade
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
a?*-.* <*A
1 - m vom £Ë>
fh*~-
N
i.
! ... .
* -^
w*
Ipil\M
lite .
1^
^1
1 j
Ardjuna, a hero of the Mahabharata, one of the great epic poems of Hinduism, as he appears in the Kathakali dance-drama. The
Kathakali theatre, which originated in Kerala, south-west India, in the 17th century, is part of the Indian theatrical tradition in which
poetry, music and dance are interlinked. The characters are easily identified by their stylized costumes, make-up, and gestures.
INDIA
The gift of the gods
by Suresh Awasthi
KATHAKALI, the world-fa¬
mous classical dance theatre of
Kerala in southern India, is the
product of a theatrical tradition in
which drama is the gift of gods, an art
in whose creation all the deities of the
great Hindu Trinity Brahma, Vishnu
and Shiva are involved. Drama was
divine in origin, and when it descended
from heaven to earth and was practised
by men it became an offering to the
SURESH AWASTHI, Indian theatre scholar
and teacher, is a former director of the Tradi¬
tional Academy of Music, Dance and Drama in
New Delhi, and a visiting professor at New York
University. He is currently visiting research pro¬
fessor at the Institutefor the Study of Languages
and Cultures ofAsia and Africa, Tokyo Univer¬
sity of Foreign Studies.
30
gods. The outstanding Sanskrit poet
and dramatist Kalidasa (4th century
AD?) rightly described theatrical per¬
formance as Chakshu-Yajna "visual
sacrifice".
In Hindu religious thought God is
engaged in an eternal play. Play is the
modality in which He displays His
presence in the world, assuming human
form to restore order and righteousness
at critical junctures in human affairs.
His worldly deeds in His incarnation
are called lila sports, illusion. Just as
God becomes incarnate and acts as a
player (lilikara) in this world, men im¬
personate and play gods. Kathakali
theatre reflects this vision of life in
which the divine and the human are
constantly mixed.
Kathakali is also representative of a
tradition in which theatre is an arena of
confrontation between gods and
demons, the forces of good and evil.
Through the kaleidoscope of some fifty
plays in the current Kathakali reper¬
toire, we get glimpses of stirring scenes
of challenge and encounter, and of
fierce fighting, killing and .dying.
Kathakali theatre is a ritual glorifica¬
tion of the eternal theme of conflict
between sat and asat, good and evil.
In its aesthetics and performing
techniques, Kathakali belongs to a
theatrical tradition which emphasizes
the values of stylization, imagination
and poetry. To give the fullest
autonomy to the actor and his art, the
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
dramatic text is recited by two reciters.
Thus liberated from the tyranny of the
word, the Kathakali actor has
cultivated and developed other aspects
of acting, namely bodily movements
accompanied by symbolic hand-
gestures, make-up and costume, and
the expression of psychic states. This is
consonant with the Indian dramatic
tradition whereby acting is conceived
as having four aspects: vachika (ver¬
bal), angika (bodily movements),
aharya (costume and make-up), and
sattvika (psychic states).
Kathakali has evolved a unique
system of training to prepare the actor
to deal with this relationship between
the performer and the text. Elaborate
eye-exercises and the learning of sym¬
bolic hand-gestures known as mudras
are the two special features of the train¬
ing system. Movements of the eyeballs,
eyelids and eyebrows enliven facial ex¬
pressions and accentuate hand-
gestures. With twenty-four basic hand-
gestures used in various permutations,
a whole sign language has been evolved
to interpret the dramatic text.
Gesture does not duplicate the func¬
tion of the word; it enables the actor to
heighten its emotional impact. The
choreographic structure of Kathakali
closely follows the recited text; it is in¬
terdependent with and fully integrated
into the verbal structure.
Kathakali is a unique example of a
fully evolved and integrated form of
drama which has taken elements from
a variety of sources such as earlier
classical forms like Kuttiyattam (the
oldest classical form of drama for the
presentation of Sanskrit plays) and
Krishnattam, ritual performances, and
Kalari, the martial art of the region. It
also borrowed from certain simpler
forms of recitation and story-telling.
Recitation remains the basis even in its
fully evolved form, and performance is
in essence a dramatization of the
recited text. Most of the time there are
only two or three characters present in
the performance area, telling and
listening to a story, reflecting and
recapitulating.
The history of written Kathakali
plays goes back only to the early seven
teenth century. These plays deal with
the two great Hindu epics, the
Ramayana and the Mahabharata, and
the Bhagavata Purana, the sacred book
of the Krishna legend. Indian theatrical
tradition prefers the use of familiar
thematic material, and Indian theatre
derives its mystical power from the
sharing of myth between the per¬
formers and the spectators. Perfor¬
mances dealing with the Rama and
Krishna legends are not merely a thea-
tricalization of the myth, they are also
a restoration of the myth. It was
natural that these performances should
have originated in the temple, the place
of the meeting and marriage of heaven
and earth.
The thematic material of known and
shared myth also determined the
aesthetics, performing techniques and
conventions of Kathakali. It facilitated
the development of the art of the actor,
and of a scheme of stylization covering
every aspect of the performance. The
elaborate system of make-up with sym¬
bolic . colours and intricate designs
specifying character-types, gorgeous
costumes and huge headgear, as well as
the codified body movements and sym¬
bolic hand-gestures, are all part of the
scheme of stylization. The scheme thus
provides for multi-channel communi¬
cation; each channel has its own
autonomy, but the aesthetic scheme
provides for links.
A traditional Kathakali performance
in a temple courtyard is a spectacle to
delight the gods. A three-foot-high
brass lamp at front stage centre dimly
lights the small performance area,
which is at ground level. The audience
sits in darkness, and the whole at¬
mosphere is filled with a sense of
mystery and awe. The lamp serves as
the focal point, the actor treating its
wick as the god of fire through which
the offerings of his hand-gestures are
made to the audience.
A half-curtain held by two stage
hands is the only prop and the only
piece of scenery. Skilful manipulation
of the half-curtain intensifies the spec¬
tators' expectancy as they strain to
catch a glimpse of the actor, giving his
entrance the force of revelation and
making his exit mysterious. Similarly,
in certain temples the vision of the deity
is given to the worshippers only after a
ritual removal of a curtain. In
Kathakali, the half-curtain also solves
the problem of time and space in a non-
realistic, metaphysical way. The cur¬
tain stands for a lapse of time, any
length of time. It connects different
time sequences divine and human
time, mythical and historical time
and different spaces, linking even
divine and human spaces. Thus, in a
sense, time and space are made to
vanish.
Forms such as Kathakali, which deal
with legendary material and use an¬
cient, codified performing techniques,
are the product of cultures which mix
the mythical and the historical, the
religious and the secular, the tradi¬
tional and the modern.
It was because of their inherent
power that Kathakali and other tradi¬
tional forms of Indian drama readily
responded to efforts for their
rehabilitation and rejuvenation in the
1930s when the first wave of cultural
renaissance enlivened the traditional
theatre arts which were languishing
under foreign rule. The second wave,
which began after independence in
1947, has not only fully restored their
artistic power and glory, but encourag¬
ed some extremely exciting experimen¬
tal work by bringing about a lively in¬
teraction with the contemporary
theatre.
The noted playwright K.N. Pan-
nikar, of Kerala, with the semi-trained
Kathakali actors of his group
Sopanam, has staged a most successful
production of the world classic
Shakuntala by Kalidasa, as well as
some other Sanskrit plays revealing the
theatrical power of the classics for the
first time. Creatively using the elements
of Yakshagana, the traditional theatre
of his region, Karnataka, B.V. Karanth
in 1980 put on a fascinating production
of Macbeth which made Shakespeare
relevant for contemporary Indian au¬
diences. Ratan Thiyam, of Manipur,
using elements from the traditional
ritual theatre of his region, has evolved
in his own plays dealing with social pro¬
blems a style which has unusual power.
The work of these and some other
young directors is the result of their
search for roots and part of a larger
phenomenon of cultural decoloniza¬
tion. Traditional theatre, with its stag¬
gering variety and vitality, is playing a
meaningful role in this crucial moment
in the history of modern Indian
theatre.
Left, scene from a performance by a
Kathakali troupe at the Theatre of Na¬
tions festival in Paris. Lighting is provided
by a lamp placed at the front of the stage.
The only prop is a curtain which is used
to symbolize the passage of time and to
dramatize the actor's entrances and
exits.
3 i
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
SPAIN
Curtain up
on Catalonia
by Xavier Fabregas
BECAUSE of its geographical
situation, Catalonia has been
a land of passage for widely
differing peoples. As a result its
culture is an amalgam wrought over
many centuries from the most
diverse ingredients into new and
original forms. This must be kept in
mind in any consideration of the
Catalan theatre and any study of its
present forms.
It is not by chance that the first
man of the theatre in Catalonia
whose name has come down to us is
Emilius Severianus, a second-
century mimographer, or author of
directions for pantomimes, who,
judging by the stone monument
erected in his honour by his fellow
citizens in the Roman theatre at Tar¬
ragona, achieved great popularity.
The name of Emilius Severianus
stands for the predominance of
gestural expression and dramatic ac¬
tion over the written word,
characteristics that have been
preserved in the Catalan theatre of
today. Two of the most represen¬
tative present-day theatrical com¬
panies, Els Joglars and Els- Come-
diants, lay stress on mime, on the
movements of the actor, on the con¬
tinuing validity of inherited forms of
culture in the technified, automated
world of today. This does not mean,
however, that oral communication or
contemporary customs are ignored.
The medieval theatre of Catalonia,
which coincided with the period of
expansion of an independent State,
now constitutes a literary heritage
that can stand comparison with that
of any other European culture of to¬
day. However, some authors of the
Renaissance, Baroque and neo¬
classical periods, whose works are
now being re-published and revived,
followed foreign trends without suc¬
ceeding in giving them a new per-
XAVIER FABREGAS, Catalan writer and
drama critic, is head of the research department
of the Barcelona Theatre Institute. His published
works range from theatre criticism to studies on
folklore, and include a "History of Catalan
Theatre", "Tradition, Myths and Beliefs of the
Catalonians", and "The Ritual Source of Daily
Life".
32
sonal formulation. It is not until the
nineteenth-century Romantic move¬
ment that we come across some
playwrights whose works conquered
a wider public and who still occupy a
place which, in other theatrical
cultures, is reserved to older
classics. Among these. Angel
Guimerà (whose works have been
translated into more than twenty
languages), Frederic Soler, Ignasi
Iglesias, Santiago Rusiñol and
Josep M. de Sagarra are names
which are known today throughout
the Catalan-speaking world (more
than eight million people) and their
plays continue to be acted.
A taste for acting and the theatre
seems to be part of the Catalan way
of life. In every locality, however
small, there ¡s a group with its own
hall which rehearses and produces
plays more or less regularly. Accor¬
ding to a survey conducted some
years ago, there are about 3,000
theatrical groups in Catalonia.
The professional theatre is
developing rapidly in Barcelona and
Valencia, the two most important
cities where Catalan is spoken. The
Theatre Institute is located in
Barcelona and provides courses in
acting, production and scenography
for more than 1,500 students.
Catalan writers for the theatre
represent a wide range of trends.
From 1 939 to 1 945, because of the
cultural repression conducted
against the Catalan people by the
dictatorship, plays in Catalan were
completely prohibited, and from
1 946 to 1 975, owing to the censor¬
ship, plays had to be staged either in
elliptical form or underground. This
favoured a theatre of more or less
veiled political satire, which led to
some brilliant successes such as El
retaule del flautista by Jordi Teixidor.
The most representative figure of
that period is the poet Salvador
Espriu, who wrote for the theatre an
Antigone which is a symbolical
reconstruction of the Civil War, and
The First Story of Esther in which he
superimposes two worlds, that of
the Old Testament and that of his
Catalonia, with an au¬
tonomous nationality and
its own distinctive lan¬
guage and culture within
the Spanish context, of¬
fers a remarkable exam¬
ple of theatre in a national
minority language. Right,
scene from Joan Ollé's
production of Plany en la
Mort d'Enric Ribera ("La¬
ment for the Death of
Enric Ribera") by the
Valencian playwright Ro-
dolf Sirera.
Photo © Pau Barceló, Barcelona
own Myth of Sinera, which are a
transcription of contemporary Cata¬
lan society compared to the Jewish
people and in danger of extinction. In
The First Story of Esther, Salvador
Espriu sought to write the elegy of
his people in an apocalyptic moment
of enforced silence.
The theatrical work of another
Catalan poet, Joan Brossa, although
also politically committed, follows
very different lines. An heir of Sur¬
realism and friend of Joan Miró, with
whom he collaborated on several oc¬
casions, Brossa has written over four
hundred "theatrical proposals"
which can be classifed in several
groups: works in which he tries out
new forms modelled on established
theatrical forms, such as the saínete
(sketch) or naturalistic drama;
theatrical "happenings" which
either avoid the Italian style of décor
or use it as a sort of Pandora's Box;
a long series of stripteases with
dramatic content; works involving
impersonation or conjuring; ballets
and musicals, some of which have
been produced with music by Josep
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
M. Mestres Quadreny and décor by
Antoni Tapies.
Salvador Espriu and Joan Brossa
belong to a generation which,
although very young, took part in the
Civil War of 1 936-1 939 and suffered
the consequences of the defeat and
repression which followed it. They
were followed by a large number of
younger writers born after 1939, of
whom I shall mention only two, who
are now in full maturity Josep
M. Benety Jornet, and Rodolf Sirera.
The works of Benêt y Jornet offer
an account and an assessment of
childhood based on the author's
youthful surroundings and personal
experiences; he very quickly moved
away from the initial strict realism of
Una vella coneguda olor (An Old
Familiar Smell) to create a dream
world which reflects the rebellion
provoked by the adult world (The
Disappearance of Wendy). Benêt y
Jornet has also achieved renown as
the author of imaginative texts for
children. His works have been
translated into Spanish, Portuguese
(in Brazil), English (in the USA), etc.
Rodolf Sirera learned his craft in
the fringe theatre of the Valencia
region. Since 1970, he has been
director and promoter of the El Rogle
theatre group. He began by writing
plays for this group such as La pau
retorna a Atenas (Peace returns to
Athens), a very free adaptation of
Aristophanes. His works, some of
which were written in collaboration
with his brother Josep Lluis, soon
became investigations of contem¬
porary Valencia society. The search
for new theatrical forms represents a
very important aspect of the theatre
of Rodolf Sirera. For instance, The
Murder ofDoctor Moraleda was writ¬
ten as a puzzle which the spectator is
called upon to piece together to
reconstruct the story.
Although Catalan is a Romance
language, closely related to its neigh¬
bours, and occupies a geographical
area which can be regarded as
privileged from the point of view of
the cultural history of the West, its
literature encounters many dif¬
ficulties when it comes to its
dissemination beyond its own
linguistic area. This is not due to a
weak demographic base. Statistical¬
ly speaking, Catalan is well placed
amongst the spoken and written
languages of Europe. The causes
must be sought in the absence of in¬
stitutions with responsibility for the
diffusion of literary works abroad.
Only this can explain why Catalan
painters like Joan Miró, Salvador Dalí
and Antonio Tapies are very well
known everywhere while, on the
contrary, poets, novelists and
playwrights of similar importance are
not.
At all events, the most important
theatrical companies are determined
to break into the international circuit
and have succeeded in doing so on
many occasions with works whose
contents could be understood
despite language barriers. Els Joglars
and Els Comediants are two such
companies whose activities are not
limited by frontiers.
The history of Els Joglars is closely
linked to that of its director, Albert
Boadella. Boadella and Els Joglars
initially presented themselves to the y
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
public as a traditional mime group
with whitened faces and black body-
stockings. However, they began
gradually to use speech, abandoned
the brief sketch in favour of the
single-theme production and
adopted masks, make-up and varied
costumes. According to Boadella,
the theatre should play a provocative
role, reconstructing topical issues in
aesthetic terms. For instance, in M-7
Catalonya he has posed the dilemma
of national cultures at a time when
the world is moving towards unifor¬
mity and mechanization; in Laertius,
the features of a post-nuclear biology
which is gradually developing to
move again towards self-destruction;
in Olympic Man Movement, the
deceitful illusions of Neo-Nazism.
Boadella writes and directs his
own plays, some of which, like La
Torna, in which he presents the case
of an ordinary prisoner who is con¬
demned to death by the military
authorities so that they can justify
the shooting of a political prisoner,
have caused him real problems.
Following the staging of La Torna,
Boadella was imprisoned. Having
feigned illness and been transferred
to hospital, he escaped by walking
along the ledge outside the fifth
floor, in the centre of Barcelona,
while jeering at the police. It was a
fantastic feat, worthy of one of his
own plays.
Els Comediants have sought their
inspiration in popular festivities, and
their plays are sometimes acted on
the streets with giants and large-
headed dwarfs, like the fight of Saint
George and the Dragon, sometimes
in traditional theatres in the form of
dances or verbenas, but the produc¬
tions are always very carefully plann¬
ed. The amount of improvisation
which may be included in each pro¬
duction of Els Comediants is strictly
calculated according to the overall
rhythm of the piece.
Some actors have followed a path
of their own. One of them is the
mime Albert Vidal, who has succeed¬
ed in achieving a synthesis of Euro¬
pean gestural forms with those of
the Far East, especially Japan, and
has created works like El bufó (The
Buffoon) in which the search for new
forms does not exclude contact with
a popular public.
Xavier Fabregas
The Catalan theatrical group
Els Joglars (The Jugglers) in
a scene from M. 7 Catalonya.
Originally a mime group. Els
Joglars are directed by their
founder Albert Boadella.
The title of the play, which is
a reflection on Catalonia and
its culture, is derived from
Catalonia's listing (No. 7) in
Wallace Muller's inventory
of twenty-three Mediterra¬
nean cultures.
Scene from The First Story
of Esther, by the great
Catalan poet Salvador
Espriu, performed by the
Adria Gual School of
Dramatic Art, Barcelona.
When he wrote Esther, near¬
ly forty years ago, Espriu
was writing, in symbolic
language, an elegy for the
Catalan people reduced to
enforced silence.
Photos © Pau Barceló, Barcelona
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Tran Van Khe, Paris
The 'paddy-field'
puppets of Vietnam
THE villagers have gathered on the banks of the
village pond. The air is filled with the sound of
gongs, drums, and folk instruments. On one side
of the pond a brick construction (it might equally well be
of planks or bamboo) has been erected. A bamboo screen
reaches from the roof to the surface of the water. The
rhythm of the drum-beats rises to a frenzy. Pushing aside
the curtain, a wooden puppet the size of a small child ap¬
pears on the water. It is Teu, the compère of the show.
He begins to speak...
Thus begins a water puppet show in a village on the
Red River delta in northern Vietnam. This very ancient
art, in a region of rice-fields where water is everywhere,
is now being rediscovered. Its themes are inspired by
village events, popular myths and legends, and the
familiar figures of life in the delta, such as the angler
shown in the photo above.
How does it all work? "The puppeteers are concealed
behind the bamboo curtain", explains the Vietnamese
specialist Tran Van Khe. "Their hands and feet are in the
water. Only their silhouettes are visible". Some puppets
are simply placed at the end of long bamboo poles.
Others are manipulated by an ingenious mechanism of
stakes and strings beneath the muddy water. The pup¬
pets may be highly complex; in some cases they are ar¬
ticulated and can perform several movements
simultaneously. Thanks to the ingenious manipulation
system surprise effects can be obtained which draw
cries of applause from the audience: banners suddenly
emerge from the water, completely dry, and flap in the
wind; soldiers in red or blue uniforms parade and turn
right or left according to their colour; a girl astride a fish
crosses the pond to offer betel leaves to the audience.
Unesco's International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture is helping the Socialist Republic of Vietnam to
restore this extraordinary and unique art to its former
glory. Other activities connected with the theatre which
are also receiving support from the Fund include: the
creation of the Centro de Investigación y Creación
Teatral del Ateneo in Caracas; the Centre Mandapa in
Paris, which is concerned with the study and promotion
of the Asian dramatic arts; the Aty-Ne'e theatre group in
Paraguay (for the creation of an itinerant theatre
workshop); a film on the "Elche Mystery" in Spain; and
a book on the Chikwakwa popular theatre in Zambia.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
FINLAND
Women in the limelight
UNTIL quite recently, the ap¬
pearance of a woman on the
stage was considered a
strange and even suspect pheno¬
menon. Shakespeare's great female
roles were created to be played by
men. When women were finally able
to play them, the enthusiasm arising
from this innovation led to excesses:
scripts were loaded with purple
passages, casts were swollen with
supplementary female characters
and plays were on occasions padded
with new episodes and even given
dénouements other than those con¬
ceived by their authors.
Primitive theatrical tradition, based
on folklore, was also linked primarily
to the world of men, with allusions to
hunting and war, and was acted out
by men. There was one exception
the famous Finno-Ugrian wailers. For
a long time, they prefigured the
future actors of Finnish drama. The
wailer communicated powerful feel¬
ings of sadness and despair to the
rest of the gathering and, although
her frenetic lamentation was based
on a model handed down from
generation to generation, it was part¬
ly improvised and was therefore a
personal interpretation. In playing
her lyrical role, a professional wailer
could arouse in the gathering a wave
of collective emotion when faced
with the dead and death or during the
ritual of marriage.
It was during the seventeenth cen¬
tury that women started to appear on
stage in Europe. Many actresses
followed the example of the famous
German actress Caroline Neuberg.
At that time, a woman who wanted
to be an actress had to leave her
family, start by playing breech roles,
and then marry a partner or the direc¬
tor of the troupe.
In Scandinavia, the influence of
foreign theatre first made itself felt
through itinerant troupes. These
troupes had to fight against hunger
and poverty for the theatre was not
highly regarded, especially in
religious circles which set the
fashion by considering the theatre as
a source of depravation. In order to
survive in this unfavourable social
climate they had to display a great
1RMELI NIEM1, of Finland, is professor of
comparative literature and drama al the Univer¬
sity of Turku and a research professor of the
Academy of Finland. A Ihealre critic, she has
published several studies on Finnish and Euro¬
pean drama.
36
by Irmeli Niemi
deal of cohesiveness. They were fre¬
quently family concerns in which the
father, the mother and the children
worked together.
The rise of the nationalist move¬
ment in nineteenth-century Finland
sparked a passionate desire to create
a Finnish national theatre. Students
started putting on short plays for a
limited public. Aleksis Kivi
(1834-1872) began writing the first
plays in Finnish of real artistic value.
He was, however, opposed to having
female roles played by male students
and this caused serious problems.
Finally, a famous Swedish-born ac¬
tress, Charlotte Raa, who had not
really mastered the Finnish language
but who was inspired by a desire to
foster Finnish culture, undertook the
first major role in Finnish. The perfor¬
mance, given in 1870, gave the
necessary fillip to the Finnish theatre
which soon acquired the status of a
highly-valued art form actively prac¬
tised by all social groups. Referring
to Charlotte Raa's courageous initia¬
tive, Aleksis Kivi wrote that "lacking
men's fatuous self-satisfaction,
women usually accomplish what
they set out to do".
Before the turn of the century, in
all the Scandinavian countries, great
actresses had a remarkable influence
on the fortunes of the theatre and in¬
spired many young playwrights. Dur¬
ing the "naturalism" period, the
theatre helped to highlight many
social problems. The status allotted
to women by society became,
through the theatre, the subject of
general and occasionally heated
discussion. In this connexion, no
play has stirred as much passion as
Ibsen's A Doll's House. A hundred
years ago the character of Nora was
at the centre of the argument as to
whether it was possible for a woman
to make decisions about her own life,
her duties and her responsibilities.
At the end of the nineteenth cen¬
tury, following in Ibsen's footsteps,
Minna Canth, "the harsh Amazon of
literature" as she was called, wrote
plays depicting uncompromisingly
the wretched condition of working
women tormented by unfaithful,
drunken men. She also exposed the
hypocrisy of the rich and the engrain¬
ed, superficial ways of the bour¬
geoisie, although she subsequently
adopted a more conciliatory line,
recommending family solidarity and
mutual tolerance.
The scathing force of her works
was not appreciated by all. The
management of the theatre which
staged her revolutionary play
Children of a Harsh Destiny cut short
its run fearing that the author's ideas
would spark off agitation and revolt
among the people. In this play Canth
portrays various categories of
women mothers, wives and re¬
jected mistresses while the male
characters were good-for-nothings
modelled on Zola characters or
liberating heroes reminiscent of
Schiller's Brigands.
The agrarian matriarchy of Finnish
society, that peasant cultural tradi¬
tion dominated by strong women,
was portrayed in a remarkable man¬
ner in the plays of Hella Wuolijoki at
the beginning of this century. Her
series of five plays focusses on the
history of the country estate of
Niskavuori and lays bare the violent
moral and economic conflicts
smouldering under the apparent
serenity of country life. The
characters speak of life in Finland in
a universal and easily communicable
manner and Wuolijoki's plays have
been performed in several countries,
including the Soviet Union and the
United Kingdom.
Wuolijoki was also politically ac¬
tive and circumstances brought her
into contact with Bertold Brecht.
When the exiled German author and
his companions arrived in Finland she
welcomed them into her house. This
meeting led to a collaborative project
the outcome of which was Mr. Pun-
tila and his Hired Man Matti, her own
version of which Wuolijoki published
in Finnish.
Finnish women playwrights of to¬
day, like Eeva Liisa Manner in her
work Burnt Sienna Land, are often
concerned with the problems of
young girls. Pirkko Sáisio's works
depict the hidden face of the con¬
temporary welfare society. Accor¬
ding to Saisio, women do not suc¬
ceed in life because they are unable
to set themselves well-defined ob¬
jectives. But, for her, there is no
direct relation of cause and effect
between the unscrupulousness of
men and the weakness of women,
such as is portrayed in naturalistic
plays. Even while defending women,
Saisio also sees man as a victim of
circumstances; the faceless econo¬
mic forces that exert pressure within
society do not distinguish between
the sexes.
Although in Finland plays written
by women are still often produced by
men, they tend to arouse particular
interest in women directors who are
also often involved in producing new
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
interpretations of plays belonging to
the great European theatre tradition.
Shakespeare has always fascinat¬
ed women. During the 1 920s, for ex¬
ample, EIN Tompuri drew inspiration
from Sarah Bernhardt's work for her
production of Hamlet. And a few
years ago, at the Kom theatre in
Finland, the director Laura Jantti
transformed Shakespeare's The
Tempest presenting it as a power
struggle among women pro¬
tagonists. This interpretation was, in
fact, a criticism of extremist
feminism and aimed to demonstrate
that power corrupts regardless of
whether it is held by a woman or a
man. Laura Jantti added a
psychoanalytic and mythocritical
touch Prospero's island symbolized
both the subconscious and the total¬
ity of the world to which man is link¬
ed by his thoughts and by his acts.
The contribution to drama of
women who have gained renown in
recent years in various sectors of the
theatre has been more autonomous
than in the past and has been
courageously progressive. At the
same time, conflict has emerged bet¬
ween objectives and reality; there is
not always enough work for ac¬
tresses and programming policies do
not always allow women to expound
or to impose their point of view. This
has led to the creation of permanent
or temporary women's theatre
groups ranging from the militant
feminist informative theatre to the
one-person monologue theatre.
Laura Jantti's daring
feminist production of
Shakespeare's The Tem¬
pest, staged at the KOM
theatre, Helsinki. In Jant¬
ti's interpretation. The
Tempest is the chronicle
of a power struggle
among women.
Photo © KOM Theatre, Helsinki
Many actresses would like to play
more interesting roles than the Euro¬
pean theatre, often subject to purely
financial goals, is able to offer.
Unless strenuous personal and col¬
lective efforts are made the woman
in the theatre will continue to be an
office employee, a ticket vendor, a
make-up girl or a prompter, or, if she
is in the cast, merely a foil for the
male actor, restricted to the role of a
sex object.
Nevertheless, women's field of ac¬
tion in the theatre today is no longer
so restricted or so tied to certain
types of role as in the past; on the
contrary, it encompasses the whole
range of artistic expression that the
world of the theatre affords.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
CHINA
The symbolic language
of Beijing Opera
BEIJING Opera, the unique
dramatic form which is part of
China's great cultural herit¬
age, is today not only popular in China;
it has won for itself a special place on
the international stage.
In Beijing Opera, the plot, charac¬
ters, events and setting are all described
solely through the acting and singing of
the performers, a unique feature which
makes the form more comprehensive
than operetta, dance drama or spoken
drama. This ingenious .combination
consists of singing, acting, recitation,
using skill in martial arts, musical ac¬
companiment and stage design, in
order to symbolically reflect rather
than imitate real life. The personality,
the inner feelings, the development of
the plot and the general atmosphere of
the performance are all expressed
through established and precise codes.
All drama attempts to reflect real
life. As a result of different creative
resources, different national charac¬
teristics, aesthetic judgments, cultures
and traditions, a variety of dramatic
forms has arisen. In general, contem¬
porary drama has evolved from three
different conceptual approaches, that
of Stanislavsky which advocates the
presentation of reality, that of the great
Chinese actor Mei Lanfang which ad¬
vocates conveying the essence of real¬
ity, and that of Brecht which integrates
a Stanislavskian "realistic presenta¬
tion" with Mei Lanfang's "symbolic
presentation".
The Stanislavsky method takes "im¬
itation" as a guiding principle and can
be traced back to ancient Greece, to
Aristotle and the then-prevalent theory
that "art imitates nature". The seven¬
teenth century produced the dramatic
concept of "constructing a plot set in a
fixed place and within one complete
day" and the nineteenth century saw
the emergence of Ibsen's works of
modern drama, all of which inherited
much from classical dramatic forms.
They treated drama as an imitation of
LU TIAN is a member of the Chinese
Dramatists' Association, a permanent member
of the council of the Chinese Stage Art Society,
and vice-director of its Department of Theory
and Research. He is the author of The Art of
Long .Tao (small-part players in Beijing Opera)
and The Painted Faces of Kunqu (a local opéra
form which originated in southern China).
38
by Lu Tian
life or a faithful representation of real
life with a "fourth wall" * to create an
illusion of reality. According to Mei
Lanfang and to the theory of Beijing
Opera, however, no such "fourth
wall" exists. This is a fundamental dif¬
ference between Beijing Opera and
other types of theatre. Mei Lanfang's
dramatic theory is that of non-
illusionism, quite different from that
which advocates the presentation of
reality.
The basic aesthetic of Beijing Opera
is a theory of "symbolic style", not of
"imitation". The beauty of the perfor¬
mance is not found in a simulation of
the original appearance or the repro¬
duction of real life. It does not seek
superficial similarities but instead uses
its symbolic methods to convey a sort
of essence or intrinsic spirit of real life.
It is a formalization of real life, a code
of highly condensed actions intended
to produce concrete and exact images
in the audience's imagination.
During the performance, players and
audience together carry out the artistic
process, since without the active par¬
ticipation of the audience's imagina¬
tion the art form would not succeed.
For instance, on a stage without props,
special movements by the performers
can signify such actions as opening or
closing a door, riding in a carriage or
on a horse, or rowing a boat. As Mei
Lanfang once said, "The performer is
in possession of all the necessary
props".
In The Crossroad, for example, two
performers use stylized movements to
show two men fighting in the dark.
Under a bright spotlight, the acting of
the performers draws the audience into
this drama taking place on a dark
night. A performer walking in a circle
indicates a long journey from point A
to point B. If the performer raises his
sleeves to cover his face and then sings
a solo, delivers a soliloquy or a bei gong
(aside), it indicates that he is in a dif¬
ferent location from others who,
though on the same stage, are not
supposed to hear him.
In literary terms, the scripts belong
more to the category of "open theatre"
than to the Ibsen-type "closed
theatre". Some are written in the first
person, but in the majority third-
person narrative is used to describe the
characters and develop the plot. In
Wronged Su San, for instance, the
wronged courtesan Su San is escorted
to the provincial capital to stand trial.
While on her way to the capital she
sings: "Su San has left Hongdong
county and is on the way...", thus
describing the setting. Highly flexible,
Beijing Opera is thus not restricted by
time and space, and performances can
suggest "broad expanses of water with
fish swimming about or vast open
plains with birds flying in the sky".
In order to accommodate this "open
theatre" type of script and resolve the
inherent contradiction between inter¬
pretation and consistency of perfor¬
mance, a set of dramatic conventions
has been derived from life, stylized and
standardized artistic expressions which
create both aural and visual images
through music and dance.
Traditionally, roles in Beijing Opera
are classified into sheng (male roles),
dan (female roles), jing (the "painted
face" male roles, most of which have
special personalities or features), and
chou (the clowns). Each of these has its
own set of stage movements and styles
of expression. The long tao role can be
performed by one actor who represents
a number of attendants or soldiers.
Four soldiers and four generals on
either side of the stage symbolize an ar¬
my several thousand strong. Qi ba is a
type of dance which symbolizes a
general full of energy before an expedi¬
tion; zhou bian indicates walking at
night; tang ma riding in the field, etc.
All these conventions are of course
unlike real life, but as Goethe said:
"Once the artist grasps the object, that
object will no longer belong to
nature." Beijing Opera, through this
standardization or codification of life
creates a highly distinctive form of ex¬
pression, an image which is acceptable
to and acknowledged by the audience.
There are two categories of symbolic
convention: one type is métonymie and
adheres strictly to an established pat¬
tern of movement; for instance, the ac¬
tor may dance carrying an oar to repre¬
sent rowing a boat and the audience
will automatically understand even
* The "fourth wall is a concept of the
naturalistic theatre, according to which the pro¬
scenium arch represents the fourth wall of the
room in which the action of the play takes place,
lemoved for the benefit of the audience but
without any of the performers taking cognizance
of the fact.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The horn-like feathers this character from Meeting
of Heroes is holding in his mouth signify anger and
determination. The dragon design on his costume,
in this performance by the Beijing Opera, indicates
that he is an intellectual.
Photo Fred Mayer © Magnum, Paris
Chen Miao Chang, a Taoist nun, has boarded a
fishing boat in pursuit of her lover. Pan Bizheng, a
young scholar, in this performance of Autumn
River by the Sichuan Opera, whose acting style is
patterned on that of the Beijing Opera.
Photo © Chinese edition of the Unesco Courier
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
though there is no boat on stage. The
second type is totally without any stage
props. In a scene in Song Jiang Slays
Yan Poxi, for instance, Song Jiang
goes upstairs to meet his mistress Yan.
On the stage there is no prop to repre¬
sent the stairs and the actor stands in
the centre of the stage swinging his
"rippling sleeves" and holding up the
hem of his robe to simulate the move¬
ment of climbing stairs.
The powerful, rhythmic music of
Beijing Opera also has conventions
which are understood by the audience.
The musical modes consist mainly of er
huang, to express a melancholic mood,
contemplation, recollection or yearn¬
ing, or of xi pi, to express excitement
and liveliness. The percussion in¬
struments play their traditional roles: si
ji tou (four beats on a gong) is generally
used when the actor first comes on
stage, or is about to exit, or is perform¬
ing without words; luan chui (confused
beats of gong and cymbals) expresses
confusion, defeat or the tense at¬
mosphere of battle, but with additional
drum beats it can also express the
sound effects of a conflagration or a
storm. In addition there are symbolic
sound effects such as flowing water (in¬
dicated by beating a small gong), the
watchman's clapper, or wind, rain and
snow, as well as the roaring of tigers,
the neighing of horses and the singing
of birds. They are not intended to be
realistic reproductions of the actual
sounds.
Stage design is also executed through
the use of particular conventions which
combine visual images with conceptual
images. Clouds, water, wind and fire,
for instance, are all natural
phenomena. On the Beijing Opera
stage they are represented either by
boards painted with moving clouds, or
flags painted with flowing water or
rustling wind or burning fire. By carry¬
ing these boards and flags the per¬
formers are able to suggest various
changes in natural phenomena.
Characterization is also ruled by
conventions. It is interesting to study
the "painted face" (a special type of
make-up) in Beijing Opera, because no
precedent in daily life can be traced.
The different colours of the "painted
faces" represent different per¬
sonalities, red for loyalty, white for
treachery, black for courage, yellow
for cruelty, blue for staunchness, and
so on. The audience can easily
recognize the character by his make¬
up.
The costumes are fundamentally a
synthesis of ancient costumes develop¬
ed for the aesthetic requirements of the
performance. The basic feature is an
ample, exaggerated shape which suits
the roles by conveying strong dramatic
effects, different from ballet costumes
which show the beauty of the human
body. A clown has a hanging beard
with its lower tuft dropping downward
over his chest; lao sheng (aged and
bearded male characters) wear a jade
belt loosely over the ceremonial robe;
wu sheng (military male characters)
have long sashes which hang at the
front of the actor's waist.
To sum up, Beijing Opera perfor¬
mances, scripts, music and stagecraft
are all fundamentally unrealistic. The
symbolism of the performance, with its
various conventions and devices, is in¬
terpreted and understood by the au¬
dience. The ordinary actions of real life
are "distilled" and transformed into
drama on the stage of Beijing Opera.
Lu Tian
Scene from The Story of Liwa, a traditional Chinese opera performed here by the Chong Qing Opera Company.
Photo Ariane Bailey, Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Photo © All rights reserved
A collage of photos of actors appearing in various plays put on at the East West Theatre, New York.
SOMEONE wishing to find out
how the United States changed
over the past twenty years would
be wise to visit the nation's alternative
theatres. In 1963, for example, Black
playwrights had few outlets, although
Black Americans made up nearly 1 1
percent of the nation's population. To¬
day, nearly every major city has at least
one showcase for Black writers, who in
two decades have created an impressive
body of dramatic literature.
Other groups to whom the theatre
was virtually closed twenty years ago
have managed to plant their feet firmly
on the stage. Among them are Mexican
Americans, Asian Americans, Puerto
Ricans, feminists, and homosexuals,
and radical political groups that use the
theatre sometimes with extraordinary
inventiveness to call attention to their
views. Even handicapped minorities,
such as the deaf, have learned to make
the theatre's special language work for
them.
ERIC OATMAN is a US journalist, based in
New York, with a special interest in education
and the arts. He is the editor of Scholastic
Search, a magazine on A merican history, and has
published several works of fiction and non-
fiction.
by Eric Oatman
But the historical lessons of a
burgeoning advocacy theatre are not
the only ones that the nation's non¬
profit theatre has to offer. A good por¬
tion of today's alternative theatre
groups look inward, testing the ability
of new aesthetic structures to frame
and illuminate human experience.
Here, too, in the ways we see and feel,
there have been enormous changes, all
of which are being charted by ex¬
perimentalists clustered, for the most
part, in the cities of San Francisco and
New York.
Fittingly, it was a time of social and
intellectual upheaval that gave birth to
the alternative theatre. Those most
alienated from the dominant culture of
the 1960s hippies, political radicals,
anti-war and civil rights activists
vowed to reshape the nation's con¬
sciousness. Some chose theatre as their
weapon and trained themselves to use
it.
Simultaneously, among a handful of
theatre professionals in New York,
another alternative movement took
flight. Frustrated by the commercial
theatre's fear of risk, it began staging
offbeat plays in coffee houses such as
La Mama Experimental Theater Club
and Caffe Cino.
When the impulses to make the U.S.
over and revitalize its theatre merged,
powerful energies were released. One
group, Julian Beck and Judith
Malina's Living Theater, turned con¬
ventional notions of theatre upside
down. Their lengthy, plotless, cast-
developed productions shaped
theatrical styles that today's groups
continue to explore. They performed
political theatre, street theatre, and en¬
vironmental theatre, mingling per¬
formers and spectators while offering a
choice of activities to focus on.
Sometimes, the Living Theater's ex¬
periments even resembled those
chaotic, mixed-media "happenings"
that have resurfaced on the farthest
shores of the current alternative theatre
scene as performance art.
The sheer number of alternative
theatre groups today New York city
alone boasts well over 100 makes
most generalizations about them half-
truths. Still, today's alternative theatre
¿5 quieter than the one that exploded in¬
to the 1960s. For one thing, the
political issues that fuelled the move¬
ment in its earlier days are no longer on
everyone's agenda. For another thing,
the national economy, more fragile
now than it has been in forty years, has
made caution a byword among alter-
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Members of the Negro Ensemble Com¬
pany in a production of Ray Aranha's
Sons and Fathers of Sons, at Theatre
Four, New York.
Photo © Bert Andrews, New York
native theatre people. Their survival
these days largely depends on an
evaporating pool of government and
corporate subsidies.
Locating funds has always been
toughest for minority groups, which is
why the Black theatre movement has
failed to grow deep roots inside Black
communities. Ten years ago, there may
have been more than 200 Black
theatres; today, less than half of them
survive, and to do so most have had to
find ways to lure white audiences.
The most visible Black theatre com¬
pany is New York's Negro Ensemble
Company (N.E.C.), which in seventeen
years has consistently proven its worth
as a training ground for Black theatre
people. In January, the N.E.C. closed
Charles Fuller's A Soldier's Play after
a 14-month run that garnered the
author the nation's top drama award,
the Pulitzer Prize.
The N.E.C. is one of the few Black
theatres that white critics visit regularly
(it is not in a Black community), and
for this reason many white theatregoers
rarely hear of the vital work being done
elsewhere. In New York alone, two
other institutions play commanding
roles. One, the Frank Silvera Writer's
Workshop, is in the Black ghetto of
Harlem, and the other, the New
Federal Theater, is in a racially-mixed
neighbourhood a good distance from
the commercial theatre district. The
Workshop has developed more than
1,000 plays by Black writers over the
past ten years, and Woodie King, Jr.,
who heads the New Federal, has been
nurturing Black plays since the
mid-1960s.
For the Black audiences, the move¬
ment's centre is wherever they are: at
Philadelphia's Freedom Theater,
Chicago's Kuumba Theater Work¬
shop, San Francisco's Lorraine
Hansberry Theater, Baltimore's Arena
Players, Atlanta's Just Us... The list
goes on and on.
Among other minority groups,
Asian Americans and Hispanic
Americans have been the most suc¬
cessful in carving out places for
themselves in the American theatre.
Asian Americans have set up com¬
panies in Los Angeles, San Francisco,
and New York to provide forums for
their playwrights and to present works
that reflect their audiences' unique ex¬
periences in the U.S.
Several theatre groups nourish the
cultural pride of Chícanos, people of
42
American Indian and Spanish extrac¬
tion. The best known of these groups is
El Teatro Campesino, which a young
actor named Luis Valdez founded in
1965 to aid a union that was organizing
farmworkers in California. Valdez
moved from writing actos skits to in¬
spire social actionto the more
spiritual mitos, which were dramatiza¬
tions of Mayan and Aztec myths. To¬
day, his group is experimenting with
corridos, staged ballads that chronicle
the lives of people on both sides of the
Mexican-U.S. border.
In political theatre, few groups have
been more tenacious than the San Fran¬
cisco Mime Troupe, which was formed
in 1959. In 1969 the group became a
collective and began using its robust,
outdoor performance styles to focus at¬
tention on social issues ranging from
sexism to, this past year, the U.S. role
in Central America.
Feminism has become a respectable
topic in the commercial theatre with
three plays sinking their teeth into it
this season in New York. Encouraged,
alternative groups continue to supply
fresh material. In San Francisco,
Lilith A Women's Theater just staged
a play on choices that revolutionary
women are faced with, and New York's
Women's Project unveiled a play about
two "abnormal" women: the
American suffragist, Susan B. An¬
thony, and Joan of Arc. The hardest-
hitting of the women's groups, the
Spiderwoman Theater Workshop,
weaves its members' personal stories
into bawdy explorations of women and
violence.
On first sight, Mill Valley, a sleepy
suburb of San Francisco, is an unlikely
place to begin an investigation of the
radical aesthetics of today's experimen-
Scene from Alan Flnneran's The Man in
the Nile at Night (1980) at the Soon 3
Theatre, New York.
Photo © All rights reserved
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Ellen McElduff of the Mabou Mines group
in a production of Dead End Kids: A
History of Nuclear Power, by JoAnne
Akalaitis. Mabou Mines is one of the
most exciting experimental groups in the
United States today.
Photo © Carol Rosegg. New York
talists. But there, in a former post of¬
fice, Chris Hardman's Antenna Com¬
pany has created a play in which au¬
dience members are the only actors.
Hardman, a visual artist who moved
naturally from carnival funhouse
design to environmental theatre, equips
each spectator with a miniature tape
player and earphones and sends him,
alone, through a maze of seventeen set¬
tings. Following pre-recorded instruc¬
tions to sit, kneel, lie down, pick up
props, and so forth, the spectator
becomes the criminal hero of this walk¬
through theatre piece, which Hardman
calls Artery.
Another San Francisco group that
plugs into new technologies is Alan
Finneran's Soon 3. For more than a
decade, Finneran has been mixing
drama, sculpture, painting, and film to
create "performance landscapes"
places where actors (and machines)
perform tasks according to Finneran's
intuitive design. In 1981, he added
music and an organizing theme:
violence as an "illusionary product" of
California's movie industry.
Women are at the forefront of the
avant-garde in San Francisco. Bean
Finneran, Alan's wife, will travel this
spring with Red Rain, a visual theatre
piece about having and living with
children. In New York, Elizabeth
LeCompte's Wooster Group, housed
in a former truck garage, mounted the
first part of a visual and verbal collage,
LSD, in January and February this
year, then left for three months in the
Netherlands, where they will create a
fantasy musical, North Atlantic. In
LSD, characters are apt to deliver their
lines either in slow motion or so fast
that only the emotions behind them are
communicated.
Squat Theater, a Hungarian com¬
pany that has lived in New York since
1977, has been performing Mr. Deadd
Mrs. Free before the curtained window
of the group's ground-floor storefront.
When the curtains are raised, the
troupe operates on two stages at once:
one inside the building, the other on the
busy sidewalk outside, where passersby
become unwitting actors in this earthy
and surreal concoction.
More and more, groups today seem
to be working toward Richard
Wagner's nineteenth-century ideal of
Gesamtkunstwerk, a performance
which unites all art forms. Yet few
seem able to integrate the forms as well
as Mabou Mines, the seven-member
collaborative for which Lee Breuer and
CONTINUED PAGE 46
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
THAILAND
The theatre of kings
by Manas Chitakasem
LIKE most Thai art forms. Thai
theatre originated in the court
under the patronage of ruling
monarchs who maintained actors,
dancers and musicians for kingly and
aristocratic pleasure. In addition,
dramatic texts were produced in the
royal court and the kings themselves
often took part in their composition.
Traditionally, theatrical perfor¬
mances and ancillary entertainments
Right, illustration from a
Thai manuscript depicting
one of the basic dance
movements of Lakhon nai, a
form of Thai dance drama
which was performed by all-
women casts, inside the
royal palace, exclusively for
the king and his court.
(shadow play), the khon (mask
drama) and the lakhon (dance
drama).
The traditional performance of the
nang is known as nang yai (nang
means "leather", yai means "big").
According to the palatine law of the
Ayuthaya period (1458), nang yai
was an essential entertainment for
special occasions such as the cap¬
ture of a white elephant, the blessing
nang figures are held aloft both
behind and then in front of the screen
by the dancers who dance to the
music and the narration.
Nang yai and khon use the same
story, but in the khon the puppeteer,
instead of holding the puppet, puts
on a mask representing it and dances
out the story in front of the nang yai
screen. Originally khon was perform¬
ed entirely by men who played both
Far right, scene from a
lakhon phan thang which
relates the story of a
Javanese king and queen.
Lakhon phan thang (dance-
drama in a thousand ways)
is a modern form of Thai
theatre which borrows
tunes and dance movements
from foreign sources and
whose principal ingredients
are adventure, romance and
melodrama.
Photos courtesy of M Rutnin, London
in Thailand were associated with
court ceremonies. The generic term
for these entertainments is maho-
rasop, which means "grand spec¬
tacle". The Thai chronicles provide
us with an extensive list of the occa¬
sions on which they were organized:
coronations, royal marriages, the
ceremony of the royal tonsure, on
the capture of a white elephant, at
the site of a royal pilgrimage, at an¬
nual rites.
Thai classical theatre is generally
divided into three types: the nang
MANAS CHITAKASEM, of Thailand, is pro¬
fessor of Thai at the School of Oriental and
African Studies, in London. He is the author of
a number of published works on Thai language
and culture.
of soldiers and their arms and the
founding of a new city. Today nang
vat has lost its popularity but it has
been preserved and revitalized by the
National Theatre of the Fine Arts
Department.
Nang yai is usually performed in
the open air. The size of the screen is
9 x.16 metres, with a transparent
section of 8 x 1 5 metres in the mid¬
dle, leaving one metre for the sur¬
rounding red border. Behind the
screen ¡s a torch or more usually to¬
day an electric light bulb. Behind the
light is a circular white screen to pro¬
ject the light on to the front screen.
The puppeteer, who is also a dancer,
wears embroidered fabric and a
jacket with a high formal collar with
a sash around his waist and a head¬
band. During the performance the
male and female roles. By the mid-
nineteenth century, however, both
men and women appeared on stage
together. All players wear masks
save those portraying female roles.
The khon is renowned for its for¬
malized but vigorous action. Acting
and dancing are inseparable, each
movement having a definite meaning
regulated by the precisely defined
music for specific dance and action,
for example, walking, marching, cry¬
ing. Because khon performers wear,
masks and cannot speak, a narrator
and a chorus group sit with the ac¬
companying musicians and recite or
sing verses from the text to which
the actors mime.
The repertoire is entirely drawn
from the Ramakian (the story of
Rama the Famous) but favours
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
episodes involving combat and battle
scenes depicting a victory for morali¬
ty always triumphs over evil.
Costumes are elaborate and the main
characters are identifiable by the
dominant colours of their costumes
and masks. Rama wears deep green,
his younger brother yellow, and
Hanuman, the monkey-general,
white. In contrast to the costumes,
the khon stage is generally bare.
Like the khon, the lakhon is a
dance drama but performers do not
wear masks, except those playing
the parts of monkeys, ogres and
other non-human non-celestial be¬
ings. The lakhon was divided into
two types, the lakhon nai and the
lakhon nok (nai = inside, nok = out¬
side), a split which may have occur¬
red as early as the seventeenth
century.
Lakhon nai was performed inside
the palace using only female players.
Dancers for lakhon nai were original¬
ly the consorts and female atten-
character plays an important role,
provoking hilarity among the au-
dience. Stories for lakhon nok are
drawn from local legends and tales
together with many jataka stones
(stories of the former lives of the
Buddha).
In the mid-nineteenth century,
King Rama IV gave permission for
female lakhon to be performed out¬
side the grand palace. As a result
lakhon nai and lakhon nok acquired
some common features. The players
could be either men or women, or
both, appearing on stage together,
and performances could take place
either inside or outside the royal
court. Only the original purpose of
the two forms was preserved, the
lakhon nok being performed purely
for entertainment and amusement
whereas the lakhon nai was acted
primarily for its aesthetic beauty.
During the reign of King Rama V
(1868-1910), the steadily growing
impact of Western political and
% X ,j29
;w#-::-:> m^ £2
j ^ i « «Ml^w^îf
Bppi^^^»"^"^^^ .
-, t>
*3A *? V#
dants of the king and, very likely,
they represented the celestial
dancers of the god-king. Lakhon nai
was therefore a royal prerogative
and performed exclusively for the
king. The music has a definite con¬
vention expressed in specific musical
tunes for specific actions or emo¬
tions. Thus a particular musical
theme will signal, for example, the
rally of an army, a march, a forest
scene or a love scene. The dance, the
music and the text are closely linked
through the medium of the chorus.
Outside the palace only lakhon nok
could be performed, and since
women performers were reserved
exclusively for palace dance drama,
the lakhon nok could only employ
men players. The dance, songs and
music tend to be quick and the comic
economic pressures caused the Thai
authorities not only to make a
positive approach to the threat by
pursuing policies of political and
economic adaptation and concilia¬
tion, but also to encourage apprecia¬
tion and understanding of the values
of their own culture in a far more con¬
scious way than had hitherto been
necessary.
The desire for a greater knowledge
of Thailand's own heritage was
strong and the process of reform and
modernization introduced by Rama V
had a great impact on development
and innovation in Thai theatre. There
was, for example, the revival of khon
and lakhon and a more general ex¬
pansion of dramatic literature. Most
significant, however, was the in¬
troduction of a new form of drama
under Western influence. Three new
types of lakhon emerged lakhon
rong, lakhon dukdamban and lakhon
phan thang.
The influence of Western opera
was evident in the lakhon rong (sing¬
ing dance drama) where, for exam¬
ple, the story of Madame Butterfly
was given the setting of Chiangmai,
a northern province of Thailand.
Whereas the essential elements of
the traditional dance drama were
preserved, there were innovations in
the music, dialogues, plots, dance
movements, costumes and set
designs. Actors sang their parts and
spoke the dialogues in prose.
Lakhon dukdamban (named after
the theatre where its first perfor¬
mance took place) is a classic exam¬
ple of a transformation of traditional
Thai elements into a more modern
form whilst preserving everything
essentially Thai, so that the new
form remains Thai. The stories for
lakhon dukdamban are taken from
the dance drama but condensed to
suit performances lasting one or two
hours. Costumes are traditional with
head-dresses and embroidered
garments but the poetic texts are
modernized with new tunes. Actors
sing and dance at the same time
without any chorus or narration. Im¬
portant innovations are the stage
settings, elaborate painted scenes
with realistic designs. New methods
and techniques of stage design, in¬
cluding Western perspective pain¬
ting of scenery, are among the major
contributions of lakhon dukdamban
to modern Thai theatre.
The third type of lakhon created
during this period was lakhon phan
thang (dance-drama in a thousand
ways). This type of lakhon inclines
towards adventurous romance and
melodrama. The plays often take
place ¡n foreign lands or in regions of
Thailand with romantic scenery and
local colour. It introduces many new
types of story from Thai and foreign
tales in orderto give an exotic flavour
to the lakhon.
When the absolute monarchy
came to an end in 1932, classical
theatre lost its royal sponsorship, but
it continued to survive under the
various post-revolutionary govern¬
ments. During the world wars,
theatrical productions were used as
propaganda, producing several
patriotic lakhon of various types. To¬
day, the pace of the dances, the sing¬
ing and the texts has quickened to
suit the rapid rhythm of modern life.
Significantly, the various dramatic
elements peculiar to the different
genres have become intermixed; the
khon, for example, now employs
many movements, musical airs and
songs from the lakhon, and many
songs written for lakhon dukdamban
are now used in khon performances
instead of the traditional script. Khon
stage and scenery have been moder¬
nized and the performances now
concentrate on dramatic action, in¬
terpretation of the text and lighting
effects as well as on the suitability of
dance movements rather than on the
traditional beauty and refinement of
the classical dance.
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Alternative
theatre
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 43
JoAnne Akalaitis have written
memorable works. The group is now
putting together Bill Raymond's Cold
Harbor, a biographical study of
Ulysses S. Grant, an army general who
became U.S. President in 1869. The
work continues the study of short¬
sighted but world-shaking decisions
which Mabou Mines began with Aka-
laitis's Dead End Kids: A History of
Nuclear Power.
Another work scheduled to open this
spring in New York is Richard
Foreman's Egyptology, said to involve
American soldiers, World War II,
dreams, and contacts with exotic
cultures. Dreams is probably the key
word here. In his Ontological/Hysteric
theatre, Foreman eschewed conven¬
tional story lines in favour of elaborate
visual and aural presentations of
thought processes, usually his own.
The most ambitious avant-garde
project in the works ever is Robert
Wilson's extravaganza, 77ie Civil
Wars: A Tree is Best Measured When it
is Down. Wilson is the world's best-
known dramatic formalist, a former
painter and architect whose concern in
theatre, like Foreman's, is with struc¬
ture. His last large work, operatic in
scale, was the five-hour Einstein on the
Beach, which toured Europe in 1976.
The Civil Wars, nine hours on the
theme of the brotherhood of man,
should dwarf Einstein. Wilson will
create its many parts in seven countries
and bring them all together in June,
1984, at the Olympic Games in Los
Angeles, California.
Wilson is best known outside the
U.S., so it seems appropriate that most
of the funding for The Civil Wars will
come from abroad. Inside the U.S.,
where only about one percent of the
population patronizes any live theatre,
experimentalists tend to get overlooked
by all but a small band of critics and
followers. Eric Oatman
The International Theatre Institute
The Unesco-sponsored International Theatre Institute was founded in 1948 with
the aim of promoting international exchange of knowledge and practice in theatre arts
(including music theatre and dance) as a means of consolidating peace and friendship
between peoples, deepening mutual understanding, and increasing creative co¬
operation between all theatre people. Among its activities are World Theatre Day (27
March) and a wide range of seminars and workshops. Themes of seminars held in
1982 included "Stanislavsky's heritage and the Development of the Soviet Multi-
National Theatre" (In Tashkent), "Composer and Librettist" (Prague), and "Indian
Dance Traditions and Modern Theatre" (Calcutta). The Institute also organizes the
Theatre of Nations which was until 1973 based in Paris, but is now itinerant and held
every two years. Forty-five companies from 32 countries took part in last year's
Theatre of Nations, held at Sofia, Bulgaria. The Institute also publishes a lively
quarterly magazine. Theatre International, which is dedicated to the exchange of
theatre work and experience worldwide. The magazine is bilingual (English-French)
with abstracts of articles in Spanish, Russian and Arabic. Articles in recent issues
have included "Lee Strasberg: the Master and the Method", "The Tibetan Theatre of
China", "Dance Theatre in Ethiopia", "Stanislavski's Method of Physical Analysis"
and "The Raun Raun Theatre of Papua New Guinea".
Theatre International is published, with Unesco financial aid, by the International
Theatre Institute, Unesco, 1 Rue Miollis, 75732 Paris Cedex 15, France, and edited
from the British Centre of the International Theatre Institute, 31 Shelton Street, Lon¬
don WC2H 9HT. (Subscriptions per calendar year: £12, US$20 [institutions and
organizations]; £8, US$15 [individuals]).
BOOKSHELF
UNESCO'S LITERATURE
TRANSLATIONS SERIES
JAPAN
Treelike. The Poetry of Kinoshita Yuji,
translated by Robert Epp. Preface by
Ooka Makoto. Oakland University
Katydid Books, Rochester, Michigan,
USA. Published in association with the
Centre for Japanese Studies, University
of Michigan, 1982. 272 pp.
Kabuki. Five Classic Plays, translated
by James R. Brandon. Harvard University
Press, Cambridge, Mass., and London,
UK, first published 1975. 378 pp.
AFRICA
Ignorance is the Enemy of Love, by
Faarax M.J. Cawl. Translated from the
Somali, with Introduction and Notes, by
B.W. Andrzejewski. Zed Press, 57
Caledonian Road, London N1 9DN, 1982.
104 pp.
EUROPE
Curial and Guelfa, translated from
Catalan by Pamela Waley. George Allen
and Unwin Ltd., London, 1982. 287 pp.
They've got us taped
Unesco plans to record, on casset¬
tes, in English, French and Spanish,
the quarterly Unesco Braille Courier,
starting with the selection for March
1983. The cassettes are intended
primarily for those who become
blind after the age of about 50 who
often lack sufficient sensitivity in
their fingers to learn to read Braille or
for those who suffer from a physical
handicap which prevents them from
holding or turning the pages of an or¬
dinary magazine or book. Requests
for cassettes, which are supplied
free of charge, should be sent to:
Frederick Potter, Editor of the
Unesco Braille Courier, Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition. Indian Head.
Inc., 111 West 40th Street. New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Yi Kae-Seok (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.-
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Just published
The second volume in a projected annual series,
the Unesco Yearbook on Peace and Conflict
Studies 1981 seeks to meet the needs of teachers
and researchers concerned with problems of
peace and conflicts. It reports on:
trends and approaches in peace and conflict
studies
background documentation on non-violent
action and civilian-based defence (biblio¬
graphical essay)
the peace-related activities of Unesco, high¬
lighting the World Congress on Disarmament
Education
institutional developments at the internation¬
al, regional and national levels
Co-published with Greenwood Press Inc., Westport, Con¬
necticut, USA, who have exclusive sales rights in the USA
and Canada.
ISBN 92-3-102032-3 238 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collmg-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub- agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, P 0. Box 175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000. - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd , Ittefaq
Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publications agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP000-0070823-1 3 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 21 82 St. Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. -SNTL,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. -6, 893 31 Bratislava
CSSR DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI. National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuja 2.-01 640 Vantaa 64 FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 1 2598-48.
- GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig,
Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish
editions): Mr. H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publica¬
tions: Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps
only Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA.
Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 1 95, Accra; Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd , P.O. Box 7869, Accra: The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom - HONG KONG.
Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion,
12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co , 13-15, Lock
Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government Information Services,
Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street.
HUNGARY. Akadéimiai Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A K V. Konyvtiirosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. - ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 1 3, 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-41/1
Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi
Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots. Oxford Book & Stationery
Co. 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 7001 6, Scmdia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 1 0001 . IN¬
DONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto
Iskandardmata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 1 09, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakar¬
ta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co ,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O Box
314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iran-
chahr Chomali No. 300, B P. 1 533, Teheran. - IRAQ. McKen-
zie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 -
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome,
Mmato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait;
for the Unesco Courier Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LI BERIA. Cole and Yan-
cy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P O Box 34-35,
Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-
Rue, Luxembourg MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd , 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd des Moulins, Monte-Carlo
NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only: Dekker and Nordemann
NV, P.O. Box 197,1 000 AD Amsterddam, for publications only:
KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
- NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N V , P O.
Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at.
Rutland Street, P 0 Box 5344, Auckland; 1 30. Oxford Terrace,
PO. Box 1721 Chnstchurch, Alma Street, P.O Box 857
Hamilton, Princes Street, PO Box 1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA The University
Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286,
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana
NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers),
Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1, Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssentret, POB 307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco
Courier only A S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo
6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-
azam, P.O. Box No 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The
Modern Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila
D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, War¬
saw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Por¬
tugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon, SEYCHELLES. National
Bookshop, P 0. Box 48, Mahé, New Service Ltd., Kingsgate
House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay,
Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops,
Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd.,
No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road,
Singapore 19 - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC.
Modern Book Shop and General, P 0 Box 951 , Mogadiscio.
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications- Van Schaik's Book-store
(Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. .
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only Central News agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 1 00 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P O B. 244
Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P 0. Box 1118,
Khartoum - SWEDEN. All publications A/B C E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications. Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, POB. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P 0 Box 402, Bangkok Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 1 8 Alexandra Street, St Clair,
Trinidad, W I - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevl A S , Istiklâl Caddesi,
No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA.
Uganda Bookshop, PO Box 7145, Kampala. - UNITED
KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London,
SEI, and Govt Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, for scientific maps only
McCarta Ltd. , 1 22 King's Cross Road, London WC 1 X 9 DS -
UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South, New
York, NY 10010 - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200 - YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11,
Zagreb, Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana, Nolit, Terazi-
je 27/1 1, Belgrade - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd ,
67 Union Avenue, Harare.
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
i
. he street's the stage
at camiuiMjme
Nowhere more than iniLatïrr^BHp to¬
day, from Rio de Janeiro to Oruro, TraP
throughout the Caribbean, carnival is the
occasion for a colourful, effervescent ex¬
plosion of joie de vivre. Its origins are
remote. In medieval Europe at carnival
time mimes would parade the streets for
days on end in a dramatic pageant in which
performers and spectators alike enjoyed
the release of saturnalia and mocked at
morality and religious institutions. Italian
carnivals such as the still-celebrated car
nival of Venice moderated this anti-
Christian spirit. Photo shows a scene from
the 1981 carnival in Trinidad.
<^J
g
m
W t
t i
/Í
M
/-
]]>
</page>
</document>
