<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074676eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
OThe Ö
ínesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
THE HAND
OF
FRIENDSHIP
by the Director-General
of Unesco
WE live in an age of grave uncertainties and immense hopes, an age
in which all the nations of the world are, for the first time, joined in
a single network of reciprocal relationships. Their destinies are
henceforth interdependent, and the scientific and technological resources at
their disposal could enable them to solve the bulk of their most urgent
problems.
But in order to do this, they must stand united in their purpose and combine
their efforts as they face a common future. In other words, humanity must
prove capable of making a transition from interdependence to solidarity.
The practice of solidarity requires that each one of us should be always at
the disposal of those who, however far away they may be, remain and must
remain, our neighbours.
Solidarity cannot be enforced; it is lived.
ONE of Unesco's fundamental tasks is to bring solidarity into effective
being, for only solidarity can weave a fabric of friendship capable of
uniting peoples and individuals from different cities, countries and
continents.
And so today I am appealing to each of you to take part in a campaign of
solidarity involving the Unesco Courier.
You who are a reader of the Unesco Courier, think of someone who is
unknown to you and is yet your brother, of someone who because of his living
conditions often feels alien to you, someone to whom the Unesco Courier can
reveal all that brings you together and unites you. Offer him a subscription and
thus contribute to Unesco's efforts in favour of peace and friendship between
men.
By so doing you can help make the Unesco Courier the authentic voice of
universal solidarity. i
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
(For details of how to offer a "friendship" subscription see coupon opposite).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
ry&ehandof^Friendshipj
"The hand of friendship" is the name of a solidarity
campaign which gives Unesco Courier readers the
opportunity to offer a gift subscription to someone
who is unknown to them and who is materially unable
to become a subscriber. The World Federation of
Unesco Clubs and Associations is associated with the
campaign as part of its efforts to promote internatio¬
nal exchanges worldwide. The Federation will be res¬
ponsible for establishing the chain of solidarity bet¬
ween present and future readers, who will then be free
to make contact and become friends.
J
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ry[hehandoiRiendship^
In response to the "Hand of Friendship" appeal I wish to offer one
or more one-year subscriptions to the Unesco Courier to one or
more friends whom I do not yet know.
( -\
Special rate for this solidarity campaign
D 1 one-year subscription : 48 FF*
D 2 one-year subscriptions: 96 FF*
D 3 one-year subscriptions: 144 FF*
D 4 one-year subscriptions: 192 FF*
D 5 one-year subscriptions: 240 FF*
D 10 one-year subscriptions: 480 FF*
D 20 one-year subscriptions: 960 FF*
* French francs
'
In this campaign, the choice of langua¬
ges is limited to the 4 editions publish¬
ed at Unesco Headquarters.
(number of subscriptions)
D English
D French
D Spanish
D Arabic
Fill in using Block Capitals
My NAME
TOWN
COUNTRY
I am not a subscriber to the
Unesco Courier
lama subscriber; my number is:
Please specify whether, on expiry of the
subscription or subscriptions you are offe¬
ring, the subscription renewal request should
be addressed to you.
D Yes D No
Request not accompanied by the appropriate
payment will be considered as void.
I enclose payment in French francs (by
cheque made out to Librairie de l'Unes-
co) or the équivalent in another converti¬
ble currency or by international money
order.
Please return to:
Unesco/Hand of Friendship
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris
France
In the three months following reception
of your gift, the World Federation of
Unesco Clubs and Associations will
send your name and address to your
future friend or friends. You will be infor¬
med of his/her or their names and
addresses.
If you wish your gift to be made anony¬
mously, please tick this box D.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
FEBRUARY 1984 37th YEAR
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 2 - 1984 - OPI - 84-1 407 A
pages
'A MORAL IMPERATIVE'
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
THE CULTURAL ROOTS OF LITERACY
by Marcos Guerra
9 WHERE THERE'S A WILL...
Changing societies and motivation to learn
by Marcel de Clerck
12 WHAT NEXT?
A world panorama of back-up materials for new literates
by Adama Ouane
15 THE POLITICAL ECONOMY OF LITERACY. TRAINING
by Herbert Gintis
17 REPORTS FROM AROUND THE WORLD
22 ILLITERACY IN THE 'FOURTH WORLD' j
Rich countries become aware of a disturbing trend
by Ali Hamadache
26 CHILDREN IN NOMANSLAND
The dilemma of second-generation immigrants
by Sonia Abadir Ramzi
29 WORD WITHIN WORLD
A critical reading of the universe
by Paulo Freiré
32 UNESCO AND THE STRUGGLE AGAINST ILLITERACY
34 THE 1983 LITERACY AWARDS
l-IV THE HAND OF FRIENDSHIP
(Campaign leaflet inserted between pages 2/3 and 34/35)
/T can never be too strongly
affirmed that the struggle
against illiteracy must and
will continue so long as a single
man or woman is thereby exclud¬
ed from the world of knowledge
and deprived of the possibility of
making for himself or herself
those vital decisions that affect
each individual's life.
Illiteracy, however, is more
than just an individual handicap;
it is also perhaps the most impor¬
tant impediment to the social and
technological emancipation of the
peoples of the developing world
and one of the major factors con¬
tributing to the widening of the
gap between the industrialized and
the less developed countries.
Finally, it constitutes an
obstacle to the interpénétration
and' mutual enrichment of dif
ferent cultures. Learning to read
and write not only helps to con¬
solidate one's own cultural roots,
it also opens the door to
knowledge of other cultures.
The effects of illiteracy are also
felt in the richer countries, the
daily-increasing complexity of
whose structures multiplies the
difficulties faced by the non-
literate.
From its beginnings, Unesco
has played a leading role in pro¬
moting and guiding the world
struggle against illiteracy. And
though in certain sectors some
success has been achieved and the
tide ofilliteracy has to some extent
been turned back, under pressure
of world population growth the
absolute number of illiterates con¬
tinues to rise:
The pursuit of literacy cam
paigns is therefore a matter of
overriding urgency. In this issue
of the Unesco Courier we attempt
to give a picture, however in¬
complete, of the present status of
literacy campaigns around the
world and to highlight some of the
prerequisites for greater effec¬
tiveness and success. Of these, it
now emerges, the foremost and
most imperative is that, in the
planning of literacy campaigns,
full account be taken of dif¬
ferences of environment, of the
traditions and specific interests of
each cultural milieu. As one ofour
contributors writes "people are
not made literate, they make
themselves literate".
Cover. Wall painting in the Tepito district of
Mexico City. ,
Photo © Populart, Oullins, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
'A MORAL IMPERATIVE'
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
HE eradication of illiteracy represents a moral
imperative for the international community. The
reasons for this are evident. It is sufficient to
consider the number of illiterates, an estimated 824
million in 1980 or 29 per cent of the adult population, a
number which is constantly on the increase even as the
rate of illiteracy slowly declines.
If present trends continue, there will be 900 million il¬
literates towards the end of the century. Illiteracy is
generally closely associated with poverty. It is most
widespread in the most deprived areas of those countries
which have the least resources, and among the most
destitute sections of the population those that suffer
from serious inadequacies as regards food, health and
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
housing or who are affected by unemployment.
The persistence of widespread illiteracy is a major im¬
pediment to development, and makes it impossible for
millions of men and women to take their destinies into
their own hands. It condemns to failure the fight against
poverty, the elimination of inequalities and the attempts
to establish relations of equity and justice between both
individuals and nations.
Unesco's strategy and actions in favour of literacy
have evolved over the years to reflect the experience ac¬
quired by Unesco and its Member States. Thus the pro¬
gramme approved by the recently concluded 22nd ses¬
sion of the General Conference for the 1984-1985 bien-
nium contains several noteworthy innovations.
The most important of these is the adoption of a global
strategy whereby action for generalization and renewal
of primary education the only means of attacking il¬
literacy at its very root is combined with literacy educa¬
tion for young people and adults. It is a fact that illiteracy
thrives on the inadequacy of primary education. There
are today some 120 million children of primary school
age who do not have the opportunity to attend school
and who, if adequate measures are not taken, will swell
the ranks of adult illiterates in the future. Sixty per cent
of these children cut off from school are girls, the women
and mothers of tomorrow whose role and influence in
every sphere of life are of decisive importance.
But even many of those fortunate enough to attend
school will not necessarily pursue their studies long
enough or receive an education of a sufficient quality and
relevance to their lives to enable them to achieve an en¬
during level of literacy. Hence, the extension and reform
of primary education is an indispensable element in any
realistic strategy to overcome illiteracy.
Unesco's programme also gives immediate attention
to an alarming phenomenon the relapse into illiteracy of
many young people and adults. Studies must be under¬
taken to diagnose this complex problem systematically.
Another aspect of the problem of illiteracy which has
recently attracted the attention of researchers is the no¬
tion of "functional illiteracy". With the rapid develop¬
ment of science and technology, the level of literacy re¬
quired to cope with the demands of social and economic
life is rising. The measure of "functional literacy" is not
fixed, but is steadily advancing. For example, the level of
instruction which qualified one for employment yester¬
day may not suffice tomorrow.
It is only by acquiring literacy skills that each individual
begins to become a full and active member of his culture,
is able to benefit from the accumulated wealth of
knowledge and know-how and takes part in the collec¬
tive process of reflection on the implications of his socie¬
ty's evolution in a word becomes a full-fledged citizen.
While its elimination requires first and foremost a
strong national commitment, illiteracy has become a pro¬
blem of truly planetary dimensions. Its eradication also
calls for efforts on a world-wide scale and in particular for
international co-operation reinforced by a greater con¬
cern than in the past for the fundamental human re¬
quirements of authentic development.
I therefore appeal once again to all those in positions of
authority to increase the total volume of aid devoted to
literacy work, thus enabling the upward trend in the ab¬
solute number of illiterates to be halted, then reversed,
before the end of the century. In this way we shall ensure
that we enter the new millennium in a climate of liberty,
creativity and progress for all.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The cultural roots
of literacy
by Marcos Guerra
COMMON sense dictates that the
features of a people's cultural iden¬
tity should be integrated into the
process of teaching them to become literate.
Why, then, has this principle not always
been understood? Why is it not
systematically and scrupulously applied
today?
At the present time both the Third World
countries and the industrialized countries
are equally preoccupied with the question
of educating and making literate their
adults and young people. A sound ap¬
proach would be to examine what has hap¬
pened in the recent past in order to deter¬
mine how many educational activities have
failed because of lack of respect for the
MARCOS GUERRA, from northeastern
Brazil, is a consultant on education and
development problems with Unesco and other
organizations of the United Nations system,
and with several European non-governmental
organizations. He has taken part in literacy
campaigns in Brazil and directed projects for
the training of supervisory staff in Niger and
the Ivory Coast.
cultural values of the populations with
which they were concerned. In a broader
perspective, how many political measures
and how many development projects have
suffered as a result of contempt for these
values?
All educational activities are, in our opi¬
nion, essentially cultural in the sense given
them by the Brazilian educator Paulo Freiré
(see article page 29). It is not enough simply
to respect cultural identity. We must
endeavour to integrate as fully as possible
into the educational process the values of
the culture, the civilization and the society
to which we have come to live and work.
This integration is essential not for educa¬
tional, economic, psychological or political
reasons, nor in order to save time
although each one of these reasons may be
justified but because these values are part
and parcel of the educational process,
which would be incomplete without them
and could foment resistance among the
learners.
If the requisite political commitment,
and coherent, realistic policies are forth
coming, it may reasonably be hoped that
some countries will be able to eradicate il¬
literacy before the end of this century or else
reduce it to an insignificant level. But it is
no secret that for millions of people in other
countries, inability to read and write will
aggravate the difficulties of their daily lives
and make it harder for them to be fully in¬
tegrated into the societies in which they live,
to achieve access to the services these
societies offer, and to share in the wealth,
privileges and responsibilities that are tradi¬
tionally reserved for an élite. Whether the
masses will have an opportunity to live
easier lives or whether they will be banished
to the fringe of society may hinge on the
choice of educational policies and the in¬
tegration of cultural values into these
policies.
With few exceptions the early literacy
programmes wrongly equated illiteracy
with lack of culture. Traces of this attitude
still survive but fortunately nowadays they
encounter another form of cultural
resistance which rules out the kind of
genocide of which Latin American civiliza-
Photo © Denis Fogelgesang, Metz, France
Pestles and mortars for grinding millet attract potential buyers at the market held during an an¬
nual festival at Touba in Senegal. Although in many cases they may be illiterate, market traders
and their customers in Third World countries often display dazzling capacities for totting up
prices at lightning speed.
> *.
m: '
fm
--
m'
. 1 **?
F JWW
Hfl fluB j m \
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Strong incentives are needed to provide adults with the motivation to
undertake and persist in the considerable effort required to achieve
literacy. Such Incentives may take a variety of forms: cultural,
religious, economic or political. Below, patients register for vaccina¬
tion in northern Brazil. Bottom, young Tibetan monks learn to write in
the Buddhist monastery of Mamali, Himachal Pradesh, India.
Pieces of reed, bark and bit¬
ter herb entwine to form a
"message-knot", above,
which marked the conclu¬
sion of peace between two
peoples of New Caledonia.
The knot proclaims that
"here is thatch and bark for
you to rebuild your houses,
and there Is no longer any
bitterness between us". It Is
an example of the ways in
which oral civilizations use
non-written systems of
symbols for memorizing,
organizing and expressing
thought.
Phoio i Frmco.» Oupuv. P*ri»
Pholo Lemi*oud»
Ë Mulé« dB l'Homme. Pint
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
tions, among others, have been the victims.
Decisions relating to the language in
which literacy is taught, to the ways in
which written calculations are performed,
and to the choice of the methods and con¬
tent of cultural action are directly linked to
this respect for cultures and the integration
of their values. The choice of techniques
and materials and the definition of "sen¬
sitization" and post-literacy programmes
present opportunities to integrate or ex¬
clude important aspects of national
cultures. This means power-sharing: pro¬
grammes and policies should no longer be
defined by specialists alone but should
democratically bring in those who are
defending their culture.
Astonishing though it may seem, literacy
work in a given country almost always gives
rise to a vast network of simultaneous and
continuous action. It calls for-a degree of
assiduity and devotion often more impor¬
tant than the activities of a political party.
Young people and adults who meet to learn
together are often far more motivated than
when. they come into contact with other
public services, including medical dispen¬
saries. But this tightly-knit permanent net¬
work is only used in a downwards direction:
the message is transmitted, the programme
is followed, people learn to read and write.
They are transformed, and so is the leader
of their group. But the channels which
transmit information upwards, enabling
cultural values to emerge and express
themselves and enriching the process of ex¬
change, often function less well when they
cannot be easily quantified. Or else such
channels exist outside the field of action of
literacy work and do not always influence
the educational process itself.
It is also necessary to keep policies and
programmes relevant and up-to-date. In
revolutionary societies in the throes of
change we have come across avant-garde
militants carrying out literacy programmes
and using textbooks that have not been
modified in any way for almost ten years.
In Africa it is still often possible to find
literacy programmes into which notions of
cultural identity have not been integrated.
There are various reasons for this. Some are
straightforward, such as the fact that it is
only relatively recently that the importance
of these questions has come to be ap¬
preciated, or in any case that they were not
given sufficient consideration by specialists
when national policies were being prepared.
Some are more complex, such as those
relating to the major difficulty of working
out a coherent policy for the choice of the
language in which literacy is to be taught;
this difficulty arose from the necessity to
use a so-called language of national unity
(often that of the former colonial power) in¬
stead of one which might accentuate inter¬
nal differences and be harmful to national
unity and sovereignty.
In literacy work and in the education of
adults and young people, the question of
language is of paramount importance, not
only because it is an essential medium of ex¬
pression for a culture and a civilization but
also because it is an essential medium of
communication. The choice of a language
other than the mother tongue in which to
achieve literacy, if it is justified, makes it
necessary to develop other forms of cultural
expression which will not reinforce literacy
and its gains but which may strengthen
cultural identity. This choice imposes a
double task on illiterate people: literacy and
acculturation.-
As far as arithmetic is concerned, an at¬
tentive observer soon realizes that an il¬
literate person who is incapable of noting
down either the processes whereby he per¬
forms a calculation or even the final result
is nevertheless often capable of doing com¬
plicated sums. Even the casual visitor to
Third World countries can see people play¬
ing cards or traditional games in the streets,
or skilfully dealing at market with mer¬
chants who display astonishing gifts for
mental arithmetic. For some time
mathematicians and information scientists
have been taking an interest in popular
games played in the Third World, largely by
people who are illiterate yet can do
arithmetic at lightning speed.
The challenge facing us is to take into ac¬
count all these factors as well as the ex¬
perience and knowledge accumulated over
generations and exclusively transmitted by
the oral tradition and with the aid of certain
non-written materials. Any coherent
literacy and education policy for young
people and adults is bound to mobilize these
values and give them a place in the educa¬
tional process, to stimulate critical thinking
about them, and to foster a dialogue and
confrontation between them and new
values in our interdependent world.
The courage, perseverance and tenacity
of those who learn to read and write is well
known. Integrating the values of their
cultural identity can only stimulate their
work. But it is vitally important that the ob¬
jectives of educational policies and pro¬
grammes should be tailored, through a
democratic consensus, to the needs and
aspirations of illiterate people.
Marcos Guerra
Deep in thought as they ponder their next move, these two Kenyans are playing wari, a game of skill
played with pieces such as nuts or dry beans on a board divided into compartments. Wari is one of many
similar games found in different parts of the world. Generally known as máncala games, they have been
played for thousands of years in Egypt, spread through parts of Asia and Africa, and were taken to the
West Indies by African slaves.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Where there's a will.
Changing societies and motivation to learn
Above, women in Niger form a human chain to haul water from a well. Niger is one of the
world's 31 least developed countries. In 11 of these countries less than 10 per cent of the
female population is literate, and in 4 of them female literacy is less than 0.6 per cent. In all
of them illiterate women outnumber illiterate men.
MARCEL DE CLERCK, of Belgium, has had
a long career with Unesco as an educator and
a rural development specialist. He served as
regional adviser for adult education at
Unesco's Regional Office for Asia in Bangkok,
before assuming responsibility at Unesco
headquarters for the training of literacy
teaching personnel. He is the author of The
Operational Seminar: a Pioneering Method of
Training for Development (Unesco, 1976) and
L'Educateur et le Villageois, de l'éducation de
base à l'alphabétisation fonctionnelle ("The
Educator and the Villager, from basic educa¬
tion to functional literacy") which will be
published later this year.
by Marcel de Clerck
FROM the point of view of those who
direct literacy campaigns, to be il¬
literate in the twentieth century is a
scourge, and its eradication an act of social
justice. But what is the opinion of the il¬
literates themselves? Do they consider lear¬
ning to read and write as something impor¬
tant, necessary, or desirable? How will they
receive the literacy programme? Will they
rush en masse to the classes that are opened
for their benefit, or will they shun the
generous efforts of those who promote the
campaign? What motivations or situations
could possibly encourage illiterates to take
an interest in acquiring literacy?
The essential factor in any literacy opera¬
tion is the milieu in which it takes place.
Generally speaking, the rate of illiteracy of
a given community has a direct effect on the
attitudes and behaviour of its members in
regard to literacy training. Experience
proves that the attitudes towards literacy
training, and especially towards writing, of
individuals who belong to a milieu where il¬
literacy is still widespread can differ enor¬
mously from those encountered in a milieu
where illiteracy survives only as a residual
phenomenon. For ease of analysis, let us
consider four distinct milieux in regard to
illiteracy.
A pre-literate milieu, typified on the
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
With the aid of the International
Development Association
(IDA), an affiliate of the World
Bank, the Government of Mali
undertook between 1973 and
1978 the second phase of an
integrated rural development
programme called "Operation
Arachide". The programme
englobed the supply of equip¬
ment to farmers, agricultural
research, the improvement of
medical and veterinary ser¬
vices, and an expanded func¬
tional literacy programme.
Right, Malian villagers learn to
read and write in a village in the
Kita area.
Photo © Ray Witlin, World Bank/IDA
communications level by orality, and in
which recourse to oral communication
predominates almost exclusively in the
manifold relations of everyday life, is a
milieu in which life is lived as though
writing and the printed word did not exist.
The few literate individuals one encounters
behave as if they had never learned to read.
The illiteracy rate in a milieu of this type
can exceed 75 per cent. There are insuffi¬
cient motivations to awaken sustained in¬
terest in a rudimentary literacy programme
of the traditional type, considered as an end
in itself.
It would be wrong, however, to conclude
that a pre-literate milieu is impervious to
every kind of literacy programme. In Chad,
very high illiteracy rates have been observed
amongst the Sara of the Middle Chari83
per cent amongst men and 99 per cent
amongst women. Nevertheless the pro¬
gramme for teaching written arithmetic has
been extraordinarily successful both
amongst men and women. True, this educa¬
tion, limited to the teaching of counting and
addition, was aimed at enabling peasants to
market the cotton they produced. It enabl¬
ed them to check the weight and value of
their crops, in other words, to create a self-
managed market. There was no question of
a traditional literacy programme, which
had no interest for them, but of training
them to cope with a problem situation of
which they had direct experience.
The second milieu is predominantly il¬
literate but already includes a minority of
literates. Contrary to what happens in a
pre-literate milieu, the latter behave as
literates. A milieu of this type has an il¬
literacy rate which corresponds roughly to
between 50 and 75 per cent of the adult
population. Motivation in regard to literacy
training confined to the teaching of reading
and writing is still very poor.
While literacy training of the traditional
10
type has little lasting success in a milieu of
this kind, a literacy operation conceived as
a component part of structured action aim¬
ed at achieving socio-economic and
political changes in the interests of develop¬
ment has a good chance of succeeding if it
is well conducted, as is proved by the na¬
tional literacy campaign conducted in the
United Republic of Tanzania as part of the
Ujamaa programme, and which succeeded
in reducing the illiteracy rate of the adult
population from 67 per cent in 1967 to 39
per cent in 1976, since when it has continued
to decline. It is now reported to be lower
than 10 per cent.
The third case is that of a milieu which is
becoming literate. A majority of persons
practise reading and writing for private or
collective purposes. In theory the illiteracy
rate in such a milieu is between 25 per cent
and 50 per cent. The bulk of the illiterates
is normally composed of women and the
older generation. Motivation for becoming
literate varies.
In the village of Khanh Hân in Vietnam,
where we conducted an opinion poll about
literacy training in 1958 and where the
literacy rate was already nearly 70 per cent,
the few men who were still illiterate were
ashamed to be so. They dared not take part
in the public activities of their community
for fear of being mocked on account of
their ignorance. In this Vietnamese village,
illiterates behaved as though they were
mentally handicapped, social outcasts.
Finally there is the literate milieu with an
illiteracy rate of less than 25 per cent, where
it is normal to be able to read and write and
where this norm is recognized and accepted
by the vast majority of the people. Here, il¬
literacy is to be encountered only in small
groups of people on the fringe of society, or
amongst isolated individuals. In a milieu of
this type, where most communications are
conveyed by the written or printed word, il¬
literacy is tending to become an
anachronism. At every step the illiterate is
confronted by the imperative need to
master the alphabet. In San Salvador, the
capital of El Salvador, the literacy classes
were overcrowded and illiterates were oblig¬
ed to enter their names on waiting lists.
Some of them had to wait for nearly a year.
In 1970 only about ten of the world's
least developed countries had a
literacy rate of 20 per cent. By 1980,
19 of these countries had exceeded
this rate and in 1 0 of them over 40 per
cent of the population had achieved
literacy. Above, a schoolgirl from
Bangladesh.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The United Republic of Tan¬
zania's National Institute for
Productivity was established in
1965 with the aid of the Inter¬
national Labour Organization
(ILO) and the United Nations
Development Programme
(UNDP) to provide training
courses for management staff.
Left, trainee supervisors study
sisal stacking in a Dar es
Salaam warehouse.
Photo ILO. Geneva
'©
And yet it was a literacy course of the most
traditional type.
The illiteracy rate of a given milieu not
only indicates the numerical size of the
problem, it also provides valuable informa¬
tion for deciding which strategy to adopt
for its elimination. Obviously an 80 per cent
illiteracy rate calls for a different type of ac¬
tion than a rate of 20 or 15 per cent. Every
literacy campaign requires a policy, objec¬
tives, an approach, a time-table and even a
methodology which meet the specific needs
of the situation. Success depends on this
diversified approach to the problem in
terms of the milieu.
Illiteracy is, in fact, an element of
underdevelopment which cannot be dealt
with in isolation, as though it were indepen¬
dent of that complex phenomenon. Il¬
literacy is synonymous with the absence of
change. It is linked to the reproduction of
social models that repeat the past. Literacy
training is in itself a changethe transition
from an oral culture to one based on the
written word. But it is a change which oc¬
curs in a given society only after other
changes caused by forces that may be either
internal or external to the milieu, such as
national reconstruction, the setting-up of a
new society, the transition from a sub¬
sistence to a market economy all forms of
development action which imply a dynamic
of change.
In the eyes of the population literacy
training then becomes a significant,
motivating activity whose essential aim is
adaptation to the changes affecting society.
The success of the United Republic of Tan¬
zania's national literacy campaign is due to
the fact that it forms part of a much larger
campaign whose aim is to transform the
countryside in depth, to create Ujamaa
villages (still called development villages)
and democratically administered
communities.
Literacy, the key to progress, is at the
very centre of the Ujamaa concept. Every
citizen must be able to read, write and
count skills that are essential for awaken¬
ing a political conscience and stimulating
political participation as well as for increas¬
ing productivity. Familiarization with the
basic workings of society and civic and
socio-economic training appear as in¬
tegrated activities in the literacy process.
The creation of a new society, with the
structural changes and changes of mentality
that that implies, was also behind the
undeniable success of Ethiopia's national
literacy campaign. In 1974, that is, before
the revolution, 93 per cent of the popula¬
tion was illiterate. At the end of the third
stage of the campaign in 1980 the illiteracy
rate had fallen to 65 per cent, a spectacular
reduction.
In other countries, especially in Africa,
literacy action has been conceived and
planned as a component part of develop¬
ment programmes. In Mali, literacy as a
factor of adaptation to change is an integral
part of large-scale operations for the
organization and development of
agriculture (ground-nut, Ségou rice and
fishery programmes). Upper Volta- has
opted for a literacy programme that caters
from the start for village communities in¬
volved in specific rural development pro¬
jects. The hope is that, through this
strategy, special interest in literacy will
spread.
The examples cited above confirm that
the change which a society undergoes is a
prerequisite for a successful literacy "cam¬
paign or programme, especially in those
milieux which we have defined as pre-
literate or predominantly illiterate. But this
change, which we call development or
modernization, will only take place to the
extent that the population participates ac¬
tively in it.
The individual or group is both the
beneficiary and the ultimate target of every
development action, but he is also the deter¬
mining factor. However, very few rural
dwellers in Africa, Asia and Latin America
have completed their primary education.
The majority of those who have been lucky
enough to go to their village school have at-',
tended it for only three or four years. Most
Third World farmers are illiterate or semi- ;'
literate. They are hardly capable of reading
and understanding the directions for use of
fertilizers or insecticides. They have scarce¬
ly learned the most elementary arithmetic
such as the rule of three or the calculation
of percentages. How can they keep ac¬
counts or calculate the interest they will
have to pay on an agricultural credit loan?
Their low level of education, starting with
illiteracy, is a veritable "counter-
development" factor which blocks any real
possibility of continuous progress in the
agricultural sector from the start. One
might say that there is complete incom¬
patibility between this inadequate level of
education and development in the rural
sector.
This is where what has been called func¬
tional literacy training comes in, because it
fulfils a function that is related to specific
needs and problems. The aim of the func¬
tional literacy programme is to equip in¬
dividuals intellectually and to bring them to
a level where the knowledge acquired
becomes usable on both the social and
economic levels. In fact the objective of the
functional literacy programme is to adapt
the individual to change and to make him
responsible for change. We seem to be
faced with a kind of circular causality, the
two factorschange and literacybeing
interdependent, one determining the other.
In reality, people are not made literate, they
make themselves literate. Only when il¬
literates, both men and women, realize that
their ignorance of the written word or
number is a stumbling-block in their path to
greater progress will they become their own
most eager pupils. Marcel de Clerck
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
What next?
A world panorama of back-up materials for new literates
by Adama Ouane
ONE of the basic problems involved
in the process of bringing people
to literacy is the production,
acquisition and proper utilization of
pedagogical material. This may be
printed matter or material based on the
modern communications media (radio,
television, audiovisual systems), or it
may be traditional (theatre, folklore,
various games and similar activities).
Some countries have also developed a
variety of structures to provide easier ac¬
cess to pedagogical materials (such as
libraries, exhibitions, fairs), or other
methods of helping the greatest number,
of people to draw the fullest possible
benefit from these materials (listening to
programmes in groups, study circles, ac-'
tivity groups).
Printed material can be divided into
two categories textbooks and other
reading manuals; and rural newspapers
and wall-magazines. The first category is
of particular concern to the developing
countries. The aim is to prevent regres¬
sion into illiteracy, to motivate the newly-
literate and to inculcate the habit of
reading, as well as to produce a sufficient
quantity of. reading matter on subjects
which meet their needs, tastes and
interests.
ADAMA OUANE, Malian specialist in
linguistics, is currently engaged on research at
the Unesco Institute for Education, Hamburg
(Fed. Rep. of Germany). Formerly assistant
director-general of the national directorate for
functional literacy and linguistics at Bamako,
he is the author of several studies and articles
mainly concerned with the use of national
languages in literacy campaigns.
12
Attractive reading materials must be available for the newly literate if
they are to maintain and develop their hard-won skills. In the Ivory
Coast, above, the visit of the mobile library or "bibliobus" with its
stock of publications in vernacular languages is an exciting event in
the life of the community.
The content of this material varies
widely. Some reading manuals are
graduated and structured to meet the
needs of various classes and levels. This
is particularly true of countries where
literacy programmes have been given a
distinctly academic orientation and
where links have been established bet¬
ween literacy programmes and out-of-
school education and the official educa¬
tion system. This is the case in Cuba and
Venezuela. It is also true for the com¬
plementary education programme in the
Socialist Republic of Viet Nam and the
part-time schools of the People's
Republic of China, two programmes
which are in effect parallel education
systems designed basically for rural
populations, workers and executives of
various levels. Their purpose is to provide
a second chance of acquiring an educa¬
tion for those who dropped out of the for¬
mal school system at an early age.
Complementary reading material is
vital to this strategy. In 1980 alone,
China produced 4,600 million copies of
21,000 publications for readers in rural
areas, but only a small proportion of this
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
torrent of reading matter was destined
for the newly-literate.
The United Republic of Tanzania has
produced a series of texts, graduated at
four levels of difficulty, for the newly-
literate, but these differ from and are in¬
dependent of the levels established in the
formal school system. The aim is to pro¬
vide manuals of increasing levels of dif¬
ficulty for some five million people of
whom about one million attend post-
literacy classes. There is a teacher's
guide to go with each type of manual.
Traditional oral literature, systematically
collected and transcribed, occupies an
important place in these reading
manuals.
Following the broad lines of its
education-for-development strategy, In¬
donesia has launched a vast
"Employment-oriented Learning Pro¬
gramme" and has set up a co-ordinated
out-of-school education programme
under the aegis of the Community Educa¬
tion Authority. In 1 977, the Authority in¬
itiated a new, detailed and all-embracing
literacy programme. The teaching
materials consist of a hundred innovative
publications containing basic teaching
and information concerning every aspect
of daily life and aimed at those who left
school early or never had the opportunity
of attending school.
In Brazil, the pedagogical material used
in the mass literacy campaign MOBRAL
(Movimento Brasiliero de Alfabetizaçao)
is known as "literature on a string",
because the manuals used are suspend¬
ed on strings from the walls of the in¬
struction centres. Most of these
manuals, prepared by specialists and put
into easily-read form appropriate for new
literates by professional writers, deal
with such subjects as agriculture, public
health matters and locally-used
technologies.
In Mali, the output of post-literacy
pedagogical materials is very varied.
Manuals are produced jointly by the Na¬
tional Functional Literacy and Applied
Linguistics Authority, other development
organizations and, where appropriate,
certain technical services, including
those concerned with public health,
agriculture, co-operation and water and
forest resources. In these manuals oral
tradition and local tales are given pride of
place.
Countries differ considerably in the
way in which they produce these reading
materials. In one group of countries,
among them notably the French-
speaking countries, they are produced in
a rather informal manner with a small
number of books being produced on a
series of specific subjects. The new
literates themselves take part in their
production, at times carrying out such
technical tasks as making roneo copies.
These manuals are not generally intend¬
ed for use in formal education and they
allow of a certain flexibility and in¬
dependence in the teaching method
adopted. In other countries reading
materials for the newly-literate form an
integral part of carefully developed post-
literacy courses. Although the contents
allow for individual use, they are clearly
intended to be taught, and this is why
these manuals are usually accompanied
by teachers' guides.
Two other methods of production are
widely used in Africa and Asia. They con¬
sist of collecting the abundant heritage
of traditional oral literature and of
writers' workshops which are organized
Below, an Indian health educator uses an illustrated wall-chart with ex¬
planatory texts when telling a village mother about the nutritious qualities
of leafy vegetables and fruits. Collaboration between writers and specialists
in such fields as health, agriculture and women's education is widely en¬
couraged in the production of educational materials for literacy and post-
literacy work.
in a variety of ways, ranging from gather¬
ings of writers to produce texts to more
or less formal on-the-job training ses¬
sions for editors. Most countries try to
seek out, encourage and stimulate in¬
dividual talent or collective creativity by
organizing regular literary competitions
for which prizes are awarded. In India, for
example, more than 800 works have
already been rewarded in this way.
In most multilingual African and Asian
countries, where the language used
within the family and in normal social life
is rarely the same as that used by the ad¬
ministration or in the official education
system, achieving literacy, generally in
the local language, means not only ac¬
quiring a means of communication but
also the adoption of new means of ex¬
pression. These languages often have
only recently been given a written form.
Becoming literate means making the leap
from an oral tradition, with all its specific
attributes, to the written word, with all
its inherent modes of perception and
thought.
It is easy, therefore, to understand the
persistent efforts which certain coun¬
tries make to maintain an economic,
social and cultural climate favourable to
the use of the written word. The aim is to
immerse new literates in an environment
in which they must permanently face the
challenge of the written word. The provi¬
sion of written material, however ag¬
gressive it may be, is not enough to
create this challenge; the newly-literate
must be involved in activities of a com¬
plexity such that they cannot fall back on
memory alone and are obliged to turn to
written communication.
Rural newspapers are both an impor¬
tant source of reading material and a
means of communication accessible to
the newly-literate and their value as a
vehicle for the spread of basic knowledge
and as an answer to the urgent need for
simple reading matter able to reflect the
many aspects of foreign and local news
has been quickly recognized.
In some countries, such as Upper
Volta, Indonesia, Mali and Senegal,
newspapers are produced only at na¬
tional level. Niger, on the other hand, has
developed a truly decentralized rural
press ranging from the national organ
Gangaa to regional publications such as
Jine Koy Yan.
In India, where some 8,000 weekly or
monthly newspapers are produced in
rural areas for the rural populations,
bulletins and monthly publications are
produced sporadically for the newly-
literate and those with limited reading
experience.
Wall-newspapers often meet the need
for a community newspaper. In many
villages a wall is painted black so that
news and information of interest to the
villagers can be chalked up. In Mozam¬
bique and in Thailand the central
blackboard, situated in the main square
of the village, black-painted walls or wall-
newspapers are-used for educative pur¬
poses and to inform new literates about
international, national and local events.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Printing methods are often rather
modest. One method which is catching
on is the use of the linograph for printing
village newspapers. This method is most
widely used in Niger where village
newspapers, which form the basis of the
rural press, are produced by the new
literates themselves. Aided by local
literacy instructors they form the
editorial committee and undertake every
stage in the production process from the
manufacture of the necessary materials
to the writing of articles.
Libraries also play an important role in
literacy campaigns. The distribution of
reading materials seems often to be an
almost insurmountable problem and the
rural library, whether well or poorly
stocked, permanently located or mobile,
is a vital instrument in post-literacy
follow-up. Each of the 2,000 districts of
the United Republic of Tanzania has at
least one rural library. At present there
are 2,781 rural libraries in all out of a
planned total of 8,000 to cover all the
villages in the country.
Although in India there is widespread
interest in village libraries, their impor¬
tance to the post-literacy strategy varies
from State to State. Many libraries fulfil
other cultural and social functions in ad¬
dition to providing reading facilities. They
also aid post-literacy follow-up by acting
as a meeting place for clubs, discussion
groups and radio listening circles.
Many of these libraries are mobile and
can be transferred from place to place by
bicycle, on horseback or in a librarian's
knapsack, by truck or by canoe. But the
stock available to these libraries rarely
exceeds a thousand books. As well as
this shortage of stock there is another
drawback; the books available tend to be
on "useful" subjects aimed at continuing
the learning process or the application of
knowledge to the solution of immediate
practical problems rather than the epics,
novels or other light reading that some in¬
quiries suggest new literates would
prefer to read.
However, the real problem is not one of
libraries or the way they function, the
quality of the materials or the service
given, but the lack of publications in the
languages used in literacy campaigns.
Many countries have therefore examined
the possibilities offered by the use of the
modern mass media to promote educa¬
tion and to consolidate the use of the
written word, bearing in mind that these
media should be used as a complement
to and in conjunction with printed
matter.
In Cuba a vast programme of post-
literacy follow-up, standardization of at¬
tainment levels and other links has been
initiated to enable the newly-literate
emerging from the mass literacy cam¬
paigns to become integrated into the
country's formal education system.
Radio and television have been given the
vital task of ensuring the continuing
education of workers and peasants and
are also being used to raise the
pedagogical and methodological levels of
thousands of non-professional teachers.
In Venezuela the most important
educational television programme, Fe y
Alegría (Faith and Joy), is conducted by
the Catholic Radiophonie Institute. This
programme reaches four of the country's
largest cities and there are plans to ex¬
tend it to reach others. It consists of four
courses at different levels and is aimed at
illiterates and those who have not com¬
pleted their primary education. Radio
programmes have also been integrated
into this system of tele-instruction.
In Brazil the MOBRAL literacy move¬
ment uses television, radio, films and
other modern technologies for its lifelong
education programme and other post-
literacy follow-up strategies. Among
these programmes mention should be
made of the Community Health Educa¬
tion Programme, which is broadcast by
300 radio stations in twenty-five States
and three Territories, and the Ap¬
propriate Technologies Programme,
which demonstrates by exhibitions,
radio and above all television the way in
which various techniques are invented
and applied in order to provide practical,
readily available solutions to the daily
problems facing the most disadvantaged
sections of the population.
Since it is impossible with these new
methods of communication to limit
reception to an individual or a specific
group, such as the newly-literate, some
countries are trying to organize the target
audiences more effectively by grouping
them around receivers that have been
given free of charge/for a nominal sum or
sold in the normal way to radio clubs and
listening and viewing groups. The objec¬
tive is to prolong, to channel and to
enhance the impact of a broadcast by en¬
suring that it is heard by those whom it
most concerns.
In the United Republic of Tanzania
7,000 radio receivers have been
distributed free of charge to listening
groups. In Mali there are 1 ,444 organized
listening groups, each with its own radio
receiver. In Upper Volta radio clubs have
been established for educational pur¬
poses at literacy centres where collective
listening sessions are organized.
In Latin America, and in Brazil, Cuba
and Venezuela in particular, classes by
radio offer an alternative method of entry
into the formal education system thanks
to the establishment of levels of
equivalence and the award of certificates
and diplomas to listeners who have pass¬
ed examinations in their subjects.
The pedagogical effectiveness of radio
and television can only be enhanced by
progress now being made in telematics
and video-recording. The paths that are
being opened up before us offer new op¬
portunities, unequal though these may
still be. It must be stressed that if the ob¬
jective is to create a climate favourable to
an interaction between education and
practical action, a strategy relating solely
to the provision of literacy materials will
not be enough. The objective can only be
attained by the combined application of
several strategies.
Adama Ouane
Children wait for the lesson to begin at an open-air school cinema in southern Morocco. Film, radio and TV are
being imaginatively used in many countries today to support and supplement more traditional methods of com¬
batting illiteracy.
14
J-i.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The political economy
of literacy training
by Herbert Gintis
HERBERT GINTIS, of the United States, is
professor of economics of education and of
political economy at the University of
Massachusetts and a former educational con¬
sultant with the World Bank. He is co-author,
with Samuel Bowles, of Schooling in
Capitalist America (Basic Books, 1976) which
has been translated into Spanish, French,
Italian, German, Japanese and Portuguese.
IT is well known that the question of
literacy training is an economic prob¬
lem: there are specific per unit costs
involved in literacy attainment, and there
are equally specific individual benefits, in
terms of higher labour productivity and
earning capacity, associated with such at¬
tainment. What is less often recognized,
however, is that the benefits of literacy
training are quite as often political as they
are economic. This is true in two quite
distinct yet complementary ways.
First, literacy must be considered a basic
right precisely because it is a virtual pre¬
requisite to political participation in social
life. The illiterate population of a country is
normally concentrated among social groups
and in demographic areas which have been
systematically deprived of political
resources and access to social power.
Historically, literacy has been a prime force
in the development of those forms of
popular consciousness, social solidarity,
and political awareness upon which the ef¬
fective exercise of political influence
depends.
Indeed, it is often an important point for
educational planners to understand that op
position to literacy programmes is quite as
likely to emanate from groups opposed to
the potential empowerment resulting from
their success, as from those opposed to the
implementation costs themselves.
Second, the social rewards that induce in¬
dividuals to acquire literacy and once ac¬
quired, to maintain and improve their levels
of literacy, are quite as often political as
economic. There are many groups and in¬
dividuals whose conditions of life render
the exercise of reading and writing skills of
minimal importance for the day-to-day
tasks of home and work. Yet for such in¬
dividuals and groups, literacy remains a
fundamental tool of participation in local
community, work, and national politics. It
follows that in many situations a pre¬
requisite for a successful literacy training
programme is the widespread existence of
popular representative and participatory
democratic forms, within which the exercise
of literacy becomes a socially meaningful
and rewarding act.
Literacy and popular democracy, then,
are to a greater extent than many planners
are willing to countenance, two faces of a
coin. When individuals are continually call-
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ed upon to contribute to the making of deci¬
sions which affect their lives, and when
such decisions depend on the knowledge of
social conditions and the opinions of con¬
tending parties or interests, the develop¬
ment and exercise of literacy become of
paramount importance. When these oppor¬
tunities are absent, trie development of
cognitive skill may be of purely abstract
interest.
In short, the nature of political life facing
individuals and groups becomes a critical
ingredient in determining whether literacy
programmes will be implemented or, if im¬
plemented, will be of long-term success
particularly in situations where on-the-job
use of literacy is of less than overwhelming
importance. But what of the form of
literacy training programmes themselves?
Here again, it is all too common to treat the
methods of imparting cognitive skills as
though they were purely technical issues of
pedagogical method. Yet issues of politics
and power are always central to the learning
process.
The political aspects of literacy training
are more likely to be recognized in a pro¬
gressive society, which is so organized as to
be unthreatened by the full development in
its citizens of the personal capacities to con¬
trol their collective destinies, and which
does not fear the power and knowledge of
a literate citizenry. Thus the first step in the
development of effective literacy pro¬
grammes, I believe, is the weakening of
those backward and elitist forces which arc
threatened by the prospects of popular
power.
Effective literacy training, I suggest, re¬
quires the rejection of many standard no¬
tions in educational theory notions which
have well served élites, but are not well
geared to the needs of the many. For in¬
stance, education is often treated with the
model of the active teacher and the passive
learner. In this active/passive model, skills
are seen as passing from the initiator who
controls, to the receptor, who is controlled.
As such, educational institutions in general,
and literacy training programmes in par¬
ticular, are systematically exempted from
the general criteria of democratic participa¬
tion. The active/passive model in literacy
training often fails, then, for two inter¬
related reasons connected to the
undemocratic nature of the educational
process.
First, true learning occurs precisely when
individuals acquire a personal capacity by
exercising their personal control over their
environment. The reduction of the
learner especially the adult learner to a
passive instrument of the teacher, removes
from the educational encounter the most ef¬
fective basis of skill acquisition. Second,
the natural reaction of the learner to the
lack of power in the educational setting is to
oppose the will of the powerful. Thus not'
learning becomes a positive act of self-
assertion and the maintenance of personal
dignity. The political economy of learning,
by contrast, is based on the principle that
learning occurs most effectively, and with
the greatest positive acceptance on the part
of the learners, when the educational en¬
vironment empowers the learners, and
engages them in the active exercise of their
individual and collective powers.
How, finally, should literacy pro-
16
grammes be integrated into the social fabric
of people's lives? Education (literacy train¬
ing in particular) is often considered a
separate sphere of social life, and hence
should be provided in social settings distinct
from home, community, and work. This, I
believe, is a distinct error. Education is a
practice, not a place. Education is that
practice whose object is the personal
capacities of individuals, and whose project
is the full development of these capacities.
Like all other social practices, educational
practices take place everywhere.
The usual treatment of education is quite
otherwise. The most common view of
education is that learning takes place in
special institutions which prepare people
for other sets of social institutionssuch as
politics and work. But in fact education is
the practice involving the production of
people.
Where are people "produced"? The
answer, I believe, is that people are
producedand hence are educated in
each and every social environment in which
they participate. In particular, people are
produced in politics, and people are pro¬
duced in work. Politics does not simply pro¬
duce leaders and political decisionsit pro¬
duces educated citizens. The economy does
not simply produce goods and services it
produces people. In short, education is a
practice which is, whether consciously or
unconsciously, whether planned or
unplanned, an aspect of democratic
political development, and egalitarian
economic development.
Ignoring this fundamental point tends to
lead educational planners into two errors.
The first is to associate education with
children, since specialized educational in¬
stitutions are normally geared to the young.
Yet by this association, it is forgotten that
education must occur throughout life, and
that the economic and political benefits of
adult education are quite as significant as
those of childhood education. The second is
to think that the provision of such adult
education programmes as literacy training
must be thought of as co-operating with,
but lying essentially outside of the day-to¬
day institutions which govern politics, com¬
munity affairs, and economic production.
I would like to suggest that often the most
effective means of implementing literacy
training and other forms of adult cognitive
and occupational training is to integrate
such programmes into work-life and
community-life. Literacy programmes
should be a worker's right in agricultural
and industrial production, and provision
should be made during the work day for
literacy training as part of the worker's job
benefits. In addition, employers should be
urged to reorganize the division of labour
so as to draw upon the literacy skills of
workers as these skills manifest themselves
and develop, even in situations where the
immediate pay-off in higher productivity is
not evident. For the long-run benefits to.
society (and usually to productivity within
the industry itself) of such programmes are
significant.
In effect, recognizing that education is a
practice integrated into the fabric of daily
life, rather than being a specialized service
provided to individuals at specific points in
their lives, radically changes our notion of
the relationship of literacy training to post-
literacy programmes and vocational train¬
ing. One of the most vexing problems for
educational policy makers has been that of
the maintenance of literacy in the years that
follow the completion of successful literacy
training. I have already noted that, in the
absence of the proper mix of concrete
economic and political incentives, the
maintenance of literacy cannot be expected.
I wish merely to add that when literacy and
vocational training are integrated into com¬
munity and work, the importance of "post-
literacy" programmes recedes dramatical¬
ly. For the process of literacy becomes a
continuous part of the lives of individuals,
and in addition acquires a momentum by
virtue of the fact that learners themselves
are taking the initiative in the control of
their own education.
Herbert Gintis
'Literacy programmes should be a worker's right in agricultural and industrial produc¬
tion, and provision should be made during the work day for literacy training as part of
the worker's job benefits." Below, a tea plantation in Cameroon.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Reports from
around the world
TT/^^ 's actuaHy being done to combat illiteracy? We
^/mf present below a number of specific examples, together
* * with relevant statistics, concerning the present state and
future prospects of literacy activities in major regions of the world.
The information provided comes either from communications ad¬
dressed directly to the Unesco Courier orfrom documents available
in the Unesco Secretariat. The text is illustrated by literacy cam¬
paign posters from each region (above, poster from .Suriname). In
boxes on double page overleaf three newly literate adults from
Canada, Ethiopia and the United Republic of Tanzania tell how
their lives were changed when they learned to read and write.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Ethiopia: The literacy campaign launched in 1976 is still
being vigorously pursued. With the encouragement of the
National Co-ordinating Committee, the campaign now in¬
volves all the people's organizations of the country, in¬
cluding agricultural workers' associations, citizens'
associations (Kebeles), as well as 984,700 volunteer
literacy workers (teachers, students and other volunteers).
14.1 million of the country's 22 million inhabitants over the
age of 10 have followed literacy courses; 8.35 million (59
per cent) of the 1 2.8 million taking the final test have reach¬
ed the required standard, with the result that the literacy
rate has now been raised to an estimated 90 per cent and
49 per cent for the urban and rural populations respectively
(in 1 974, only 7 per cent of all Ethiopians were able to read
and write). It should also be pointed out that the literacy
campaign has been carried out in the 1 5 major languages of
the country (out of a total of 80) which are spoken by 90 per
cent of the population.
The Central African Republic: Under difficult conditions
and on a more limited scale, a literacy campaign has been
launched for the rural population (more specifically, for
3,650 cotton-workers between the ages of 15 and 35
Now Ifeel great and self-confident..
NDUGU Rukia Okashi is a 53-year old farmer
living in Arusha, Tanzania. She grows maize,
beans and vegetables, has seven children and
became literate about ten years ago. She says :
There is a great difference in my present situation
when compared with the old days. A lot of changes
have taken place. When I was required to sign various
papers and documents I could only use the thumb
print and one never knew what exactly one was sign¬
ing. Consequently, you could sometimes suffer in¬
justices and exploitation. Now that I am literate no
one can ask me to sign just blindly, ¡first have to ask
what the whole business is all about, I read the papers
myself, and it is only after I am satisfied that I agree
to sign. If I don 7 agree with the contents of the
documents, I just don't sign. Whereas before one
could never refuse to sign a document: you were just
asked to put your thumb print. . .
Literacy has helped me in many other ways.
Through literacy I now know the nutrient values of
various foodsthose which build the body, those
which help us to prevent some diseases, and so on. I
know what a balanced diel is.
Formerly, when one walked through the streets one
couldn't read any signs. You may come across a
"danger" signboard but you continue to walk ahead
until someone shouts, "Mama, mama, mama, mama,
stop!" But these days, I can read all the sign-posts
such as "Don 7 pass here, Don't walk on the grass".
In travelling also, I used to ask the driver to let me get
down at a certain place, but sometimes the driver
would take you much further beyond your destina¬
tion. If such an incident occurs now, I shout and
protest.
So now I feel great and self-confident. I have the
ability to refuse or disagree whereas formerly I easily
became a victim of great injustices because I was
illiterate,
(Source: Convergence, International Council for Adult
Education, Toronto, Canada, Vol. X N° 3. 1977). '
enrolled in 61 literacy centres and taught by 122 literacy
workers). An interesting feature of this campaign is that
post-literacy stimulation to continue reading is provided in
the special supplements for the newly literate, contained in
the newspapers, Linga and Nzoni Kode.
Lesotho: Use of the rural press is a feature of post-literacy
work in Lesotho, with a special supplement in the
newspaper, Moithuti. Before the literacy campaign, out of a
population of 1 .2 million, about 55 per cent were literate.
Today, after six years of effort, 6,000 illiterate and 20,000
semi-literate persons have been helped to literacy. This
literacy campaign also reached 600 herdboys and young
girls as well as miners from Lesotho working in South Africa
and the inmates of the country's prisons. In collaboration
Poster from the Republic of Cape Verde
with the Lesotho Distance Teaching Centre, a multi-media
literacy training programme uses the facilities offered by
radio, the rural press and apprenticeship centres for the rural
and migrant populations. Lesotho's literacy campaign has
also had a certain impact, thanks to similarities of language,
in Botswana and Swaziland.
Mali: Concern with Post-literacy follow-upthe stage
which succeeds acquisition of the ability to read and
write is ensured in Mali by publication of the monthly
newspaper Kibaru ("The News"), with a circulation of
20,000.
United Republic of Tanzania: 8 rural newspapers, with a
total circulation of 450,000, both inform and teach the
newly-literate population; the best known of these, Elimu
Haina Mwisno ("Education Never Stops") has a circulation
of 100,000. Tanzania's large-scale literacy campaign has,
in the space of a few years, made it possible to reduce the
adult illiteracy rate from 75 per cent to 21 per cent. In addi-
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
When you can V read or write you are poor. . .
AT the age of thirty, Janice Taylor, of Pem¬
broke, Canada, was totally illiterate. She had
not continued her studies beyond the fifth
year because of adaptation problems and, unable to
read or write, had found herself virtually cut off from
normal social life.
One day she heard talk in her neighbourhood of
ALSO, an organization established to help illiterates.
At first I found it all very difficult, but I was deter¬
mined to continue because I wanted to go to college
and learn a trade. When you can 7 read or write, you
can 't get work, you are poor, you can 7 take pari in
many activities and sometimes you don 7 even under¬
stand what people are saying to you. You are not
aware of what is going on around you.
Since- last May, Janice has been the proud possessor
of a diploma of the Department of Trade and
Technology's Algonquin College and now specializes
in the repair of small mechanical and electrical equip¬
ment such as typewriters, radios and light fittings.
When ! started taking the course I was embarrassed
about my age and I was afraid that people would
laugh at me. ¡soon found that everybody else felt the
same.
(Source: Article by France Pilon in Le Droit, Ottawa, 9
September 1983).
tion to the newspapers mentioned above, a series of inter¬
connected and co-ordinated activities maintain and extend
the rudimentary skills in reading, writing and arithmetic of
the newly literate, and encourage the application of these
skills to problems encountered daily in personal and com¬
munity life. There are some 3,200 rural libraries, with an
average of 400 books each. Between 1976 and 1982, 52
Folk Development Colleges, functioning in a unique manner,
enabled 38,000 students to follow development-oriented
training courses.
Furthermore, special educational radio programmes have
reached an audience of millions, organized in listening
groups, with instruction in health, nutrition and other sub¬
jects. Lastly, correspondence courses designed particularly
for adults and future teachers, provide out-of-school educa¬
tion at the primary and secondary levels.
Angola: The entire population has been mobilized by an
efficiently organized campaign making use of radio, televi¬
sion and the press and run essentially by volunteer teachers,
especially young people. Teaching materials are produced in
six national languages as well as Portuguese.
The Syrian Arab Republic: In a particularly vigorous
literacy campaign launched in 1958, 10,766 courses have
been provided; 263,318 pupils have been enrolled;
130,000 have completed the course. A particularly
noteworthy achievement has been the mobilization as
literacy workers of a large number of citizens aged 18 or
over, who have themselves already received an education.
Kuwait: Before the launching of the literacy campaign in
1 981 , 32 per cent of the male population and 52 per cent
of the female population was illiterate; since then, 17,076
pupils have been taught to read and write. Teaching,
organized in eight-month courses and provided in 66 literacy
centres, is particularly intensive consisting of three hours of
classes each day, on five days per week. There is no shor¬
tage of teaching materials, and use is also made of wall-
newspapers, slides and films.
The Yemen Arab Republic: In 1975, 74 per cent of the
male and 97 per cent of the female population were il¬
literate. A recently launched literacy campaign aims to
teach some 700,000 people to read and write between
1982 and 1986.
Iraq: The national campaign for compulsory literacy laun¬
ched in 1 978, constitutes a significant effort in the struggle
to eliminate illiteracy, and at the same time is particularly
concerned with the provision of the education and training
that will enable the newly literate to play an active part in na¬
tional development.
Brazil: A mass literacy campaign, the Movimento
Brasiliero de Alfabetizacaö (MOBRAL), was launched as
long ago as 1967. The campaign is conducted through
1,141 literacy centres, and uses the facilities offered by
1,157 newspapers, 650 radio programmes and 1,414
public address systems. In association with the Programme
for Functional Literacy (PAF), MOBRAL has recently been
extended to provide cultural programmes, vocational train¬
ing and community health education as well as literacy
teaching. Self-instruction constitutes an interesting ele¬
ment of this latest enterprise; pupils who have already learnt
to read and write are taught to continue the learning process
on their own.
Ecuador: Significant progress has been made in the field
of literacy training. In 1974, there were 965,000 illiterates
in the country. Since then, 536,000 have been taught to
read and write. The number of literacy centres is a measure
of the scale of the undertaking courses are provided in
7,562 schools and also in premises built by the participants,
in clubs, community centres and even in private homes.
Suriname: A campaign entitled "Alfa 84", to be carried
out between August 1 984 and March 1 985, aims to reduce
to a negligible figure the illiteracy rate of 35 per cent ( 1 978)
in the 1 5 to 59 age range, i.e. 60,000 illiterates out of a total
population of 360,000. Today's illiterates include a con-^
// is like being reborn...
BIRKE is a 27-year-old woman from Sidamo
province, Ethiopia, who has just completed a
six-month literacy programme. She tells her
own story:
The very idea of sending a girl to school was
formerly considered immoral in our society. If there
was any opportunity at all for education, it was
always the boys who were given this privilege. A girl
was supposed to stay at home until the day ofher mar¬
riage. And once marriednot to the man of her
choice, but to the one who promised the biggest
amount of mine (dowry)her chances of going to
school became absolutely inexistent, fn fact in this
new phase of her life she had to face many other in¬
justices and hardships. Every day she would have to
go to the river tofetch water, collect woodfor thefire
and prepare the food; she looked after the cattle and
the household, and that was how she would live for
the rest of her life.
But times have changed. A small local reading cen¬
tre was set up in our village and those who had already
learnt to read would read out to the others what was
in the newspapers. When my turn came to attend a
literacy class I studied hard and in six months I was
able to read and write. Today whenever J get
newspapers I enjoy reading them- I have become
aware of things. It is like being reborn or like a blind
man who has regained his sight. I never thought this
would happen in my lifetime.
(Source : Communication Media and Education for
Development The Case of Ethiopia, by Fikre Mariam
Tsehai)
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
siderable number of former primary school pupils who aban¬
doned their studies prematurely. A particular problem is pos¬
ed by the fact that a total of 20 mother tongues are spoken
by the population. Only 40 per. cent of the population, most
of whom are already able to read and write; master the of¬
ficial language, Suriname Dutch. The organizers have
calculated that it will be necessary to mobilize some 22,000
literacy workers, including volunteers from women's
associations and youth organizations, trade unions,
agricultural workers' associations and religious institutions
as well as^professional teachers during "Alfa 84". The
Government estimates that the overall cost of this cam¬
paign will amount to some US$1 5,400,000, half of which,
it is hoped, will be provided through international co¬
operation.
The Dominican Republic: Thanks in part to assistance
from Unesco, the Organization of American States and the
Inter-American Bank, significant progress has been made in
a country with a million illiterates aged 1 5 or over. Since the
literacy campaign was launched in 1 982, 79,833 illiterates
have been taught to read and write in 1 2,523 basic educa¬
tion centres by 31 ,331 volunteer workers using 1 ,777,703
teaching manuals and other types of educational material.
Peru: In 1981, Peru had more than 1,700,000 illiterates,
or 1 7.4 per cent of the population over the age of 1 5. A total
of 499,000 adults have since been taught to read and write,
or are currently receiving literacy training. A special effort
has been made to distribute the necessary basic materials
free of charge: these include 274,000 primers and the same
numbers of writing manuals, 200,000 sets of instruction
cards and copies of an elementary arithmetic textbook not
to mention 2,000 oil lamps! A strategy for post-literacy
training is being implemented with the collaboration of
those responsible for other branches of education, in the
context of cultural projects and local or regional pro¬
grammes of vocational or continuing education.
20
A CATALUNYA SOM
300.000
ANALFABETS
n L_
fJP
,2.ñ %\ .1
fe
L'ANALFABETISME : UNA URGÈN
Posters from Catalonia (above),
the United Arab Emirates (below)
and Bangladesh (left).
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Nicaragua: Launched in 1979, the literacy teaching cam¬
paign has reduced the illiteracy rate from 50 to 1 3 per cent.
Based on people's education collectives and community
education groups, the campaign recruited and trained
120,000 volunteer teachers who, in the space of five
months, taught more than 400,000 Nicaraguans to read
and write. Students in secondary schools are obliged by law
to spend six months participating as teachers in the adult
education programme.
Functional illiteracy has by no means disappeared in all
the industrialized countries of the world.
Canada: 856,060 Canadians (5.5 per cent of the popula¬
tion aged 1 5 or over) have failed to complete their primary
education and may be considered virtually illiterate. There
are considerable variations in the illiteracy rate in the dif¬
ferent provinces: 7.5 per cent in Quebec, 1 1 .9 per cent in
OKUMA YWg
BILDICÍNI ÖGRET
BiLMEDiGiNi ÖGREN
Poster from Turkey
Newfoundland and as much as 23.3 per cent in the Nor¬
thwest Territories. Although more than 70 million dollars
were spent on literacy teaching between 1979 and 1980,
the scale of the problem has only recently become fully ap¬
parent, as was seen in the importance attached to the
celebration of International Literacy Day on 8 September
1983, in Ottawa (see back cover). A special feature of
literacy work in Canada is that it is carried out not only by
the Department of the Ministry of Education responsible for
basic education for adults, but also by volunteer services (in
Quebec) and by a hundred or so officially-sponsored or
private bodies.
Poland: During the early post-war years, the illiteracy rate
was very high, but it was considerably reduced as a result
of the literacy and school enrolment campaign launched by
the Government in 1951. In 1981, 2.7 million Poles overthe
age of 15(10 per cent of this age group) had not completed
the full course of basic education. During the school year
1982-1983, however, only 0.34 per cent of children of
school age were not actually enrolled.
Turkey: Although it was launched comparatively recently
(1981), the national literacy campaign has already produced
substantial results 3,156,799 new literates. These in¬
clude a large number of women, agricultural workers and in¬
habitants of shanty-towns and destitute villages. Before the
campaign was launched 69 per cent of the population over
the age of 6 was literate; today the figure has risen to 74.8
per cent. For women the figure has risen from 53.8 per cent
to 61.2 per cent. Many of these new literates have con¬
tinued their studies to the level of the adult primary educa¬
tion certificate. Turkey hopes to eliminate illiteracy entirely
by 1995.
India: As might be expected in such a large country,
literacy activities have long been extremely decentralized.
Between 1961 and 1972, the movement for the develop¬
ment of the villages of Maharastra (Gram Shikshan Mohin)
completely eradicated adult illiteracy in 36,693 villages,
teaching almost 10 million adults, more than half of them
women, to read and write. The National Federation of Indian
Women has opened 1,500 literacy centres in impoverished
urban and rural areas in nine States. The Social Service
League of Bengal has trained 8,700 instructors who, bet¬
ween 1961 and 1974, in 320 sessions, taught 105,000 In¬
dians to read and write. In 1975, the Adult External Educa¬
tion Directorate of the Federal Ministry of Education and
Social Affairs launched a literacy programme for 300,000 il¬
literates. Lastly, in 1 978, the Federal Government launched
a large-scale Five-Year Adult Education Programme cover¬
ing 22 States and designed to provide literacy teaching for
1 00 million young people and adults between the ages of 1 5
and 35, special attention being paid to women in rural areas,
certain castes and tribes and the most disadvantaged
classes of the urban and rural populations.
The Socialist Republic of Viet Nam: In 1945, when the
literacy- campaign was launched, the illiteracy rate in a
population of 20 million was 95 per cent. Popular en¬
thusiasm was such that during the first year 2.5 million peo¬
ple were taught to read and write, and a further 10 million
in the nine years which followed. By 1 958, virtually the en¬
tire population between the ages of 1 2 and 50 was literate.
In the southern part of the country, the 4 million illiterates
remaining in 1975 had been taught to read and write by
1977. Today, efforts are being made to eliminate illiteracy
in the ethnic minorities, and to develop a comprehensive
system of complementary education.
China: The past 32 years have seen the transition to
literacy of 128 million people aged between 12 and 40, in
a country where, in 1 949, 80 per cent of the population was
illiterate. Today 90 per cent of the country's workers and
miners have attained an educational level equivalent to that
of pupils who have completed their primary school educa¬
tion. It is estimated that only some 5 to 7 per cent of the
people in this group remain illiterate. In the rural areas, 70
per cent of the younger generation of agricultural workers
have acquired basic reading and writing skills. In order to
maintain and perfect these skills, the local authorities pro¬
vide workers and peasants with secondary education out¬
side working hours.
Thailand: In 1981, some 14.5 per cent of the population
aged over 10 was illiterate, including a large proportion of
former primary school pupils who had completed four years
of education, but subsequently relapsed into illiteracy. In
the Fifth National Social and Economic Development Plan,
launched in 1982, the Government set as a target, the
reduction of the illiteracy rate to 10 per cent by 1986, by
which time, it is hoped, primary education will have become
universal. In addition, six specially-conceived extracur¬
ricular literacy programmes are currently being implemented
with the collaboration of volunteer teachers, students from
teacher training institutions and Buddhist monks. Several of
these programmes are designed for the country's larger
minority groups.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Illiteracy
in the
'Fourth World'
Rich countries become aware
of a disturbing trend
by Ali Hamadache
IT would be a mistake to assume that illiteracy is confined to the
Third World. Many countries which have provided universal
education for generations are today finding to their astonish¬
ment that they are having to face a problem which they thought
they had eliminated but which is spreading at an alarming rate, af¬
fecting even those countries which for decades have enjoyed a high
level of material prosperity.
The predicament of illiterates in industrialized countries is
doubtless more difficult than it is in the Third World and
sometimes assumes dramatic proportions. A North American or
Scandinavian adult who cannot write properly will suffer more in¬
tensely from isolation than someone similarly handicapped in a
country where the illiteracy rate is high. In some Third World coun¬
tries, moreover, a rich community life and an oral tradition develop
other ways of exercising the memory and organizing thought
through a different system of symbols, and this is a source of sup¬
port for the illiterate person.
In a society that is economically and technologically advanced,
where written communication predominates and where the printed
word, in particular, is ubiquitous, the person who is not conversant
with the fundamental technical skills of reading, writing and
arithmetic inevitably finds himself in a position of inferiority in a
number of everyday situations: in shops, public transport, at the
bank and the post office, in the exercise of civil rights and duties,
and even in access to employment. An illiterate unemployed person
will even avoid applying for work at an employment agency because
he is ashamed of his inability to complete the necessary forms. An
illiterate worker will find it difficult to play an active part in trade
union activities.
Illiterates are also handicapped when confronted with the com¬
plexities of life in industrially developed countries. Since they can¬
not read street signs, the names of underground stations, or bus and
tram destinations, they have difficulty in finding their bearings and
getting around in a city. They cannot compare labels in a big store;
they cannot calculate the price of the foodstuffs at the grocer's or
the butcher's. Having a child admitted to hospital, completing a
child allowance form and other administrative formalities all
dealings with the authorities, school and the law, in factrepresent
insurmountable obstacles to the illiterate.
The illiterate does not enjoy the respect of the society in which
ALI HAMADACHE, a specialist in literacy work, is a staff member of
Unesco's literacy, adult education and rural development division. A
former senior civil servant in Algeria (1962-1968) he has also served
as a literacy specialist in what is now the Lao People's Democratic
Republic and as an adviser with the Ivory Coast's TV education
programme.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
i *
SEK- :,,
- ' _- *.. - ._
V9k^t}jiiäm
PPi^****-**-^ -^r » *
r*
y
«'
ai,
Although it is most widespread in the Third World, il¬
literacy is also a growing problem in some of the
world's richest countries where it is rampant among
the underprivileged sectors of society which have
been called the "Fourth World" and include residents
of dilapidated inner-city districts, migrant workers
and their families, and some low-income rural
populations.
he lives nor even that of his family. Children, who cannot be helped
with their school work by illiterate parents, will eventually look
down on them and even disobey them. Many illiterates feel a sense
of shame that often makes them wish to hide from others the fact
that they do not know how to read and write; this shame paralyzes
them when they are presented with an opportunity to learn to read
and write. Sometimes the intelligence of illiterate persons ceases to
be used, developed and kept alert; and the introduction of an ever
wider array of modern technology introduces new discrimination
against illiterates.
In the rich as well as the less affluent countries, illiteracy and
poverty are linked in such a way that each condition is sometimes
a cause, sometimes an effect, of the other. Illiteracy is closely
related to a number of factors that influence one another, including
low or non-existent income, poor-quality education or insufficient
time in school, poverty of cultural environment, poor health, and
insalubrious living conditions. It is particularly widespread among
those who are now referred to as the "Fourth World", that is the
most underprivileged categories of society, especially the poor liv¬
ing in marginal city districts, or on the outskirts of cities and in run¬
down areas, migrant workers and their families and certain
minorities or underprivileged groups. This category of the popula¬
tion mainly comprises those who are out of work, occasional
workers, workers confined to jobs that require few or no qualifica¬
tions, people living on social security, some rural populations
whose standard of living is particularly low, and where the child's
contribution to the family budget is sometimes more important
than its regular schooling... in short, all those who are at the bot¬
tom of the social and economic ladder.
Illiterate persons are over-represented among the unemployed
since, although a high level of education is not a guarantee of
employment in the present economic climate, it is nevertheless a
prerequisite for entry into a secure and well-paid profession. They
are also over-represented among prisoners, who suffer the conse¬
quences of illiteracy acutely because writing is for them an impor¬
tant means of communication with the outside world.
Most industrialized countries today admit more or less explicitly
that part of their adult population is illiterate. But even where the
existence of the problem is acknowledged very few studies have
been carried out with the appropriate means to estimate its extent,
and fewer still to analyse its causes.
The problem of illiteracy in industrialized countries is com¬
plicated by the "qualitative" aspect, mainly in reversion to il-^
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Photo H.W. Silvester © Rapho, Paris
Comparing labels and prices in the supermarket is but one of many everyday activities
in the urban industrialized world which require mastery of the written and printed word.
literacy and in functional illiteracy which are difficult to evaluate
statistically by census alone. However, neither the absence of
statistical data on illiteracy nor a refusal to acknowledge its ex¬
istence can make the problem disappear.
Many industrialized countries which instituted compulsory
education long ago and which therefore consider the problem solv¬
ed have removed the question concerning illiteracy from their cen¬
sus forms. But even where a question on illiteracy still features on
a census form, it is not always easy to obtain reliable answers since
most illiterates try to conceal their deficiency for psychological
reasons as well as for practical considerations connected with their
employment prospects. "To be without work is hard, but to be
without work and not to know how to read and write is terrible and
shameful", said Mr. H., of Rastadt, in the Federal Republic of
Germany.
With a view to standardizing educational statistics at an interna¬
tional level, a recommendation of the tenth session of Unesco's
General Conference defined as illiterate any person "unable to
read, write and understand a short, simple statement of facts
relating to his daily life". In 1978 this recommendation was revised
with the following significant specification: "A person should be
considered 'functionally illiterate' who cannot engage in all those
activities in which literacy is required for effective functioning of
his group and community, and also for enabling him to continue
to use reading, writing and calculation for his own and the com¬
munity's development."
Nevertheless, the criteria of functionality differ widely from one
country to another. In one place it is enough to be able to read a
set of instructions or a poster; in another, anyone who cannot com¬
plete a complicated questionnaire or assimilate written instructions
of a fairly technical nature is considered illiterate. Somewhere else,
a person who has not completed five or even nine years of elemen¬
tary education is considered illiterate.
Given the different definitions of illiteracy in the countries under
review and the standards required by each society, figures can vary
substantially.
The estimates made by the Unesco Office of Statistics and up¬
dated in July 1982 using the latest available official surveys are bas¬
ed on the number of people who admit to being illiterate. Accor¬
ding to these estimates, in the industrialized countries (Europe [in¬
cluding the Soviet Union], the USA, Canada, Japan, South Africa,
Australia and New Zealand) in 1980 2.5 per cent of the adult
population aged fifteen and over, some 22.5 million people, can be
considered illiterate. It must be pointed out that these are mainly
older people, since only 3 per cent of them are in the 15-19 age
group, 20 per cent in the 20-44 age group and the vast majority 77
24
3X.MAMAHfl!EbMA-Ebl Tbl
rPAMOTHOM.nOMOMA-Ebl MHE !
In the Soviet Union the drive against illiteracy was
one of the priority tasks of the new régime after
the Revolution of 1917. "Woman! Learn to read
and write!" runs the top caption of this poster
dating from 1 923. Lower caption reads: "Oh, little
mother, if you were literate you could help me!"
per centare 45 and over. It is also clear that the quantitative
aspect of illiteracy varies considerably from one country to
another: a clear divide separates one group of countries, most of
which are in the Mediterranean basin, from the others. Southern
Europe has an overall illiteracy rate of 8.1 per cent, the rates in in¬
dividual countries varying from 4 to 20 per cent.
Another significant fact is that, in most countries, the rates of il¬
literacy among women are particularly high, often double and in
some cases triple the rate of illiteracy among men.
It is also certain that these estimates do not convey the full extent
of the problem, since they omit those who have reverted to il-
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
literacy: those who, through insufficient education or because they
did not go beyond the minimum level determined by the society
concerned, have certainly learned the basics of reading and writing
but have lost them either partly or totally because they have not us¬
ed them in their everyday life.
Functional illiteracy covers a variety of situations that are defin¬
ed by the economic, technological and cultural context of each
society and the level of basic knowledge each society requires. In
the United Kingdom, for example, the definition adopted by the
British Association of Settlements (BAS), which classes as illiteracy
a level below the standard of a nine-year-old child, revealed in 1979
that there were two million illiterates. In the English-speaking part
of Canada, the Canadian Association for Adult Education defined
functional illiteracy as "A level of instruction equal or inferior to
eight years of schooling", while in Quebec the definition is based
on less than five years. A study published by the Canadian National
Commission for Unesco in 1983 registered 5.5 per cent of Cana-
"All I remember of school is that everyone used to jeer
at my father when he came to fetch me", said a boy
interviewed during a recent survey on "Illiteracy and
Poverty in the Industrialized Countries" carried out,
with Unesco support, by the international movement
ATD Quart Monde. His words echo the widespread
sense of isolation and the family tensions which ac¬
company adult illiteracy in the industrialized world.
dians (850,000 people) as having less than five years' schooling and
as many as 28.4 per cent (4,400,000 people) with less than nine
years' schooling, and with a level of education that was considered
inferior to that required for adaptation to the complexity of in¬
dustrialized society. In Poland, after the literacy and education
campaign launched by the government in 1951 to reduce the high
rate of illiteracy, there were still, in 1981, 2.7 million Poles of 15
and over who had not had a complete basic education.
In the USA in 1970, a study published by the Louis Harris Poll
and financed by the National Reading Centre showed that 18.5
million Americans aged sixteen and over were functionally il¬
literate; the criteria used included ability to read a newspaper and
answer questions on its contents, to use a telephone directory, to
complete correctly various forms (applications for employment,
social security, a bank account, etc.), to write a cheque, and under
stand a bus timetable. A comparable study made by the University
of Texas from 1971 until 1976 used similar criteria, with an em¬
phasis on everyday life: tasks such as calculating a car's fuel con¬
sumption, giving the correct change and understanding the deduc¬
tions from a pay slip. The survey concluded that illiteracy among
English-speaking Americans was in the region of 15-20 per cent.
With 23 million people classified as functionally illiterate, it caught
the attention of the media and the American public. According to
the White House press service, the figure is increasing by 2.3 million
annually.
In France no survey has been conducted nationally, but some en¬
quiries have been carried out in recent years among sub-proletarian
groups. In the Essonne département outside Paris, for example, a
survey carried out in 1976 by the Departmental Union of Family
Associations and covering 6,000 families with which the authorities
were in regular contact showed that 47 per cent of the men and 51
per cent of the women were either illiterate or barely able to read
and write. An international social service organization, Aide à
toute détresse Quart Monde, has studied a sample of seventy-eight
sub-proletarian provincial families: 27 per cent of the men and 30
per cent of the women were classified as illiterate.
Another study carried out by Aide à toute détresse Quart Monde
and published by the European Commission revealed the existence
of illiteracy in certain urban areas of Belgium and Luxembourg: 5
per cent of Belgians in Liège and 5 per cent of the population of
Luxembourg, with 20 per cent illiteracy among the immigrants in
both cities. In Belgium the only reliable data are those collected by
the army during recruitment: in 1979 0.4 per cent could neither read
nor write and 15 per cent were unable to complete correctly an ap¬
plication for leave. In this category in France, 0.7-0.9 per cent of
conscripts can be considered as illiterate; 10-20 per cent in Denmark
and Sweden are totally or partially illiterate. Within a given country
the data obviously vary considerably from place to place, the
poorest areas being the worst affected. An extreme example is that
of two regions in Greece with different levels of economic develop¬
ment: Athens has an illiteracy rate of 7.6 per cent, and Thrace one
of 27.4 per cent. Spain affords another example: in the Burgos
region 2.5 per cent of adults are illiterate and in the Granada area,
13.5 per cent (1975 census). In the USA, 40 per cent of functionally
illiterate adults belong to the sector of the population whose income
is less than $5,000, whereas only 8 per cent earn $15,000 or more
(University of Texas survey). In France, statistics published in 1981
show that at the beginning of secondary education, after five years
of schooling, 55 per cent of the children of workers have already
repeated at least one class while only 15 per cent of the children of
people in higher management or in the professions are in the same
situation.
The causes of relapse into illiteracy are various. Unfavourable
environmental conditions produce situations which do not foster,
and even discourage, written communication in sectors of the
population. School is often blamed for failing to cultivate either the
taste for reading which makes reading a habit or the practice of
writing.
Other, admittedly less numerous, studies have also blamed the
tendency to watch a great deal of television, to the detriment of the
reading habit.
Few industrialized countries have a comprehensive literacy
education policy for their indigenous population and/or immigrant
workers; and only a few have set up the coherent organization re¬
quired for co-ordination of the necessary activities and resources.
The solution of this problem calls for political determination
which, in spite of mounting concern about the issue, has generally
been absent until how. Most programmes, whatever their scale,
have been launched by private organizations. In some cases they are
nationwide, but often they are local in scope and do not always en¬
joy official backing. The authorities would give higher priority to
the struggle against illiteracy if they were convinced of its impor¬
tance. This presupposes more effective identification of illiterates
and their environment, as well as a fuller understanding of the
causes of different forms of illiteracytotal illiteracy, recurrent il¬
literacy, functional illiteracy, or even "technological" illiteracy
in certain sectors of the population. Finally, it calls for political
decisions in the form of legislative, administrative and educational
measures and the mobilization of material, financial and human
resources.
Ali Hamadache
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Children in nomansland
The dilemma of second-generation immigrants
>^^ui^S^
Some countries are trying hard to put an end to the cultural nomansland in which many second-
generation immigrants live. Above, in a school at Oullins near Lyons (France) young musicians take
part in a creativity session held during a series of encounters with art and artists organized in the
town's schools in 1983. In school shown here, 97 per cent of the pupils are the children of
immigrants.
26
Photo © Populan, Oullins, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
<
©
"What is needed is to ensure that society regards the child of
an immigrant as a person and not as the fruit of an economic
policy. He is, indeed, a person, with his own capacities and
gifts, who has a right to education and training, just as he has
a right to be different."
"The illiterate are excluded because they cannot read, but at
the same time they cannot read because they are excluded",
says a recent French Government report on "The Illiterate in
France". Above, a literacy lesson in Paris.
by Sonia Abadir Ramzi
CERTAIN European countries count
amongst their, populations today
a very large number of immigrants
from a variety of countries and cultures.
(In the case of the Federal Republic of
Germany and France, they represent 7
per cent and 8 per cent of the population,
respectively). This means that the most
diverse cultures are destined to co-exist
permanently in the host country. This
necessary and unavoidable co-existence
gives rise to conflicts if the groups con¬
cerned continue to ignore, or even to op¬
pose, one another.
According to statistics, 85 per cent of
immigrants belong to the working class,
and their working conditions are ex-
SONIA ABADIR RAMZI, of Egypt, has
taught at the University of Algiers. She is the
author of a book entitled La Femme Arabe au
Maghreb et au Machrek (at press) and has col¬
laborated on a collective work, La Femme et la
Politique, to be published by Unesco.
tremely hard. A large majority of them
are illiterate. To this major handicap must
be added the effect of being removed
from their traditional cultural milieu,
unhealthy living conditions (75 per cent
of the insanitary dwellings in France are
occupied by immigrants), precarious
economic conditions and permanent
legal insecurity. Immigrants are con¬
fronted with an industrial civilization
which is interested in them only as "pro¬
ductive" individuals, denies their right to
be different and ignores their cultural
potentialities. Consequently immigrants
and their children live on the fringe of
social and civic life. Nevertheless,
second generation "immigrants" have
never emigrated from anywhere!
Some host countries give immigrants
the chance to become citizens after a
certain period of residence, others give
them no security of long-term residence
and maintain them in a permanently
uncertain, temporary legal situation. This
situation has repercussions on the
second generation. In five European
countries (Belgium, France, the Federal
Republic of Germany, Sweden and
Switzerland), 3,800,000 persons under
25 have not formally acquired the
citizenship of the host country.
The marginalization, not to say rejec¬
tion, of immigrants is due to racial or
xenophobic prejudice, often transmitted
via the media, which belittles the
cultures of people from formerly coloniz¬
ed countries. Because of a cultural
heritage shared in common with the host
countries, this problem is, relatively
speaking, less manifest in the case of
Italian, Portuguese and Spanish
immigrants.
Immigrants especially those of
Islamic origin are cut off from their
roots without for all that succeeding in
acquiring the cultural identity of the host
country. Consequently they live in a
cultural no man's land. Whereas adult im¬
migrants, whose personalities have
already been formed by a set of values,
moral codes, customs, myths and sym¬
bols, can to a certain degree resist the
"dangers" of their new situation,
second-generation immigrants cannot
escape exposure to the effects of a
double sub-culture. The result is that im¬
migrants constitute an anxious, disturb¬
ed population. The initial insecurity and
inequalities lead to a loss of interest in ac¬
quiring literacy. The consequence of this
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
is a structural form of illiteracy and il¬
literacy due to revulsion, both amongst
adult immigrants and their children,
which places them at a disadvantage as
regards access to employment or job
advancement.
Whatever the circumstances, impar¬
ting literacy to immigrant workers is a
special problem. Not only are the majori¬
ty of these workers and their families in¬
capable of reading or writing their native
language, but making them literate is
rendered more difficult by the fact that,
at the same time, they have to learn a
new language. So, belonging to under-
stance, action has been conducted for
the past six years under the auspices of
the European Community. Its aim is to
improve collaboration between native
and -foreign teachers. Efforts are not
limited to teaching the language and
culture of origin. The regular teachers
meet the foreign ones and gradually
establish the programme of school ac¬
tivities. In very many cases, this has
enabled immigrant children to reach the
normal level of education. But the experi¬
ment is still on a limited scale; it has not
been extended to Belgium as a whole
(which has between 10 and 16 per cent
Photo Salgado Jr. CÇJ Magnum, Paris
Scene from a performance staged during
immigrant workers' theatre festival in Paris.
privileged socio-economic milieux,
deprived of their traditional cultural sup¬
port, having in many cases only an inade¬
quate command of the host country's
language, the children of immigrants
have a disturbing school failure rate. Dur¬
ing the symposium on immigration
problems held in Luxembourg from 4 to 5
May 1982 and organized with the co¬
operation of, amongst others, Unesco,
the representative of the European Com¬
munities stated: "We now know that the
degree of failure or backwardness of 60
per cent of the children of immigrants on
leaving school is still so serious that they
cannot be rescued by the educational
system".
Nevertheless, efforts have been made
in various countries in recent years to
remedy this state of affairs. In the
Belgian province of Limburg, for in-
28
of foreign pupils, depending on the level).
In the Netherlands/special courses in
Dutch have been provided for foreign
pupils since 1974 in addition to instruc¬
tion in the culture of origin. Whenever the
number of immigrants justifies it, schools
are allowed to employ supernumerary
teachers, 80 per cent of whom are
recruited amongst the immigrants
themselves.
In France, the eleven training and infor¬
mation centres for the education of the
children of immigrants have been in¬
tegrated by the Ministry for Education in¬
to the teachers' training colleges in the
main cities. They receive a thousand
teachers per year for further training
courses. Provision is made for time to be
allotted to native language courses for
immigrant children in elementary schools
but, despite the Ministry of Education cir¬
cular of 3 April -1 975 providing for an in¬
crease in the number of such courses,
there were only 2,510 integrated
courses in the 1979-1980 school year,
which were attended by 33,600 pupils
out of the 400,791 foreign pupils in
primary schools. The agreement of 1
December 1981 between France and
Algeria provides for the inclusion of in¬
tegrated Arab language and civilization
courses in elementary schools, within
the official French school time-tables. At
the secondary level, Algerian students
may choose their language of origin as a
first or second foreign language. The
number of Algerian teachers, at present
1 50, will be doubled.
Education policies affecting children of
immigrants in the Federal Republic of
Germany vary from State to State. In
North Rhineland, for instance, they are
given complementary education in their
native tongue. Elsewhere they are taken
into preparatory classes for two, four or
even six years.
In Luxemburg, a bilingual country,
reception classes are aimed at bringing
foreign pupils up to an acceptable level in
French and German.
In Switzerland, the reception classes
introduced in the sixties have been
replaced by support programmes.
In the United Kingdom, a law dating
from 1 966 authorizes local authorities in
whose areas immigrants account for
more than 2 per cent of the population to
seek reimbursement of 75 per cent of the
cost of salaries for teachers and social
workers responsible for the reception of
immigrants. The National Association for
Multi-cultural Education leads the cam¬
paign to adapt the British education
system to the presence of immigrants.
It is, perhaps, in Sweden that the big¬
gest effort has been made in favour of
minorities. Under a law of 1 976, bilingual
education is guaranteed to all im¬
migrants, both young and adult. The
number of teachers providing this educa¬
tion in the 20 native languages of the im¬
migrant children (7 per cent of Sweden's
school-going population) grew from 835
in 1974'to 2,000 in 1977.
In spite of these advances, all the
problems will not be solved until the reali¬
ty of immigration and the riches it brings
are better appreciated by the host socie¬
ty. It would be desirable that campaigns
be launched to prepare the latter to see
itself as a multicultural, multiracial socie¬
ty and to accept this fact with all its at¬
tendant consequences in the school, at
work, in the life of the community, in the
laws, the mass-media and recreation.
These campaigns should also stress that
over the past twenty years the influx of
foreign workers has slowed down the
ageing of the total population in most of
the host countries.
In fact, what is needed is to ensure that
society regards the child of an immigrant
as a person and not as the fruit of an
economic policy. He is, indeed, a person,
with his own capacities and gifts, who
has a right to education and training just
as he has a right to be different.
Sonia Abadir Ramzi
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Word within world
A critical reading of the universe
Photo Claude Jacoby © Parimage, Paris
"Reading the universe must always precede reading the word, and reading the latter implies continui¬
ty in reading the former." Below, pupils in a primary school near Victoria de Santo Antao, Brazil.
by Paulo Freiré
PAULO FREIRÉ, noted Brazilian educator, is
the originator of a method of literacy teaching
which has attracted widespread attention. He
developed this system, which is based on en¬
couraging adults to become "critically con¬
scious" of their situation, in Brazil, Chile and
other Latin American countries. Formerly pro¬
fessor of history and philosophy of education
at the university of Recife (Brazil) and a
visiting professor at Harvard, he has also
worked with the United Nations and Unesco.
Among his published works in English transla¬
tion are: Pedagogy of the Oppressed (Penguin,
London, 1972), Education for Critical Con¬
sciousness (Sheed and Ward, London, 1974)
and Education and the Practice of Freedom
(Writers and Readers Publishing Co-operative,
London).
BEFORE discussing the importance of
the act of reading, I feel I should
say something about the process in
which I engaged as I wrote this text. It is a
process that presupposes a critical
understanding of the act of reading, which
is not simply a matter of decoding the writ¬
ten word or language but is preceded by and
extends to an understanding of the world.
Language and reality are linked
dynamically. The understanding of a text
that is achieved through a critical reading
implies a perception of the relationship bet¬
ween the text and the context. When I at¬
tempt to write about the importance of the
act of reading, I feel impelled to "re-read"
essential moments of my experience, from
the earliest memories of my childhood,
adolescence and early manhood, in which a
critical understanding of the importance of
the act of reading was developing within
me.
While I was writing this text, I was
"distancing" myself from the various
moments in which the act of reading took
place in my existential experience. First of
all "reading" words, which during my
schooldays was not always reading the
"word-world". For me the recollection of
my distant childhood, trying to understand
my act of reading, the special world in
which I lived, is very significant. In this ef¬
fort in which I am engaged I recreate and re¬
live in the text I am writing my experience
at a time before I could read words.
I can see myself in the modest house sur¬
rounded by trees where I was born, in
Recife. This old house, with its rooms, cor¬
ridors, cellar and spacious patio was my
first world. It was here that I crawled on all
fours, uttered my first sounds, learned to
stand, walk and speak. Indeed, this special
world was offered to me as the world of my
perceptive activity and, therefore, the world
of my earliest readings. The "texts",
"words" and "letters" of this context (the
more practice I got in perceiving it the more
my perceptive capacities grew) were em¬
bodied in a number of things, objects and
signs, and in the course of my contacts with
them and of my relations with my older
brothers and sisters and my parents, my
comprehension grew.
The "texts", "words" and "letters" of
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
this context were embodied in the song of
birds the sanhacu, the elha-pro-caminho-
quem-vem, the ben-te-vi, the nightingale; in
the dance of the treetops swayed by strong
gusts of wind that foretold storms, thunder
and lightning; in rainwater playing at
geography, inventing lakes, islands and
rivulets. Other "texts", "words" and "let¬
ters" were the whistling of the wind, the
clouds, their colours and movements, the
colour of the foliage, the shapes of leaves,
the scent of flowers (roses and jasmin), tree-
trunks and the skin of fruit.
Animals were also part of the context
the household cats with their clever ways of
coiling themselves around people's legs and
their miaows of supplication or anger; my
father's old black dog Joli. It also included
the world of language in which the old peo¬
ple expressed their beliefs, tastes, fears and
values. All this was linked to wider contexts
than that of my immediate world, contexts
of whose existence I was totally unaware.
In this attempt to return to my distant
childhood, as I try to understand the act of
reading the private world in which I moved,
I recreate and relive in this text I am writing
the experience I had before I could read
words.
But I must insist that "reading" my
world, which was always of essential impor¬
tance to me, did not transform me
prematurely into a man, a rationalist in
short trousers. My childish curiosity would
not be deformed simply through being exer¬
cised, and here too I was helped by my
parents. Indeed, it was with them that I was
introduced to the reading of words, at a cer¬
tain moment in that rich experience in ap¬
prehending my immediate world, an ap¬
prehension that did not contain any an¬
tipathy for its enchantment and mystery.
Decipherment of words was not super¬
imposed on my "reading" of my private
world; it flowed naturally from it. I learned
to read and write on the floor of the patio,
in the shade of the mango trees, with the
words of my world, not those of the adult
world. The floor was my slate and twigs
were my chalk.
This is why I could already read when I
began to attend the private school run by
Eunice Vasconcelos. Eunice continued my
parents' work and took it further. With her,
reading words, sentences and prayers never
meant a break with "reading" the world.
With her, reading words was reading the
"word-world".
Continuing this attempt to "re-read"
essential moments in the experience of my
childhood, adolescence and youth, during
which a critical understanding of the impor¬
tance of the act of reading was developing
within me through the practice of reading,
let me return to the period when I was
studying for my baccalauréat and I trained
myself in the critical perception of texts
which I read in class with the help (which I
still remember today) of my teacher of
Portuguese.
Some of us teachers sometimes entertain
a false idea about the act of reading which
emerges when we insist on students
"reading" a massive quantity of chapters
of books in a single semester. In the course
of my wanderings around the world young
students often told me of their struggles
30
&&K8Í
"I learned to read and
write on the floor of the
patio of my house, in the
shade of the mango
trees, with the words of
my world, not those of
the adult world of my
parents. The floor was
my slate and twigs were
my chalk." Right, a little
girl in an Indian village.
Photo Jyoti Bhatt,
©ACCU. Tokyo
Baroda India.
with long reading lists of books which they
had to devour rather than read or study,
veritable "reading lessons" in the most
traditional sense to which they were sub¬
jected in the name of scientific training and
of which they had to give an account in a
test. I have sometimes even seen in book
lists indications of which pages should be
read in a given chapter of a given book.
Insistence on the quantity of matter to be
read, without due in-depth study of the
texts so that they are understood and not
just mechanically memorized, reflects a
magic approach to the written word. This
approach should be rejected. The same ap¬
proach, although from a different angle, is
found in the case of a writer who identifies
the potential quality or otherwise of his
work with the number of pages he has writ¬
ten. And yet one of the most important
philosophical documents we have, the
Theses on Feuerbach, consists of barely two
and a half pages...
However, in order to avoid any
misunderstanding I must emphasize that
my critical remarks about the magic con¬
cept of the word in no way imply an ir¬
responsible attitude on my part towards the
need for us educators and students to read
constantly and seriously the classics in all
fields of knowledge, to deepen our
understanding of them and to create that in¬
tellectual discipline without which our work
as teachers and students loses its viability.
From my rich experience as a teacher of
Portuguese, I remember as if it were only
yesterday and not long ago how I used to
pause to analyse the writings of Gilberto
Freyre, Lins do Rego, Graciliano Ramos
and Jorge Amado. I would bring these
works from home and read them to the
class, pointing out those aspects of their
syntax which were closely related to the
good taste of their language. To these
analyses I would add some remarks about
the obvious differences between the Por¬
tuguese of Portugal and that of Brazil.
In this paper on the importance of the act
of reading I am trying to showand I shall
never tire of doing so that my main pur¬
pose has been to explain how that impor¬
tance emerged in my personal experience. It
is as if I were studying the "archaeology"
of my understanding of the complex act of
reading throughout my existential ex¬
perience. This is why I have spoken of cer¬
tain moments in my childhood, adolescence
and early youth, and I shall now conclude
by recalling in broad outline some of the
main features of the proposal I made some
years ago in the field of adult literacy
teaching.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
First of all, I have always regarded adult
literacy teaching as both a form of political
action and as an act of cognition and
therefore as a form of creative activity. Per¬
sonally I should find it impossible to par¬
ticipate in work which consisted in the
mechanical memorizing of ba-be-bi-bo-bu
or la-le-li-lo-lu. For this reason also I can¬
not reduce literacy training to a form of
teaching where the teacher "fills" the sup¬
posedly empty heads of his pupils with
words. On the contrary, the subject of the
literacy learning process as a cognitive and
creative act is in the pupil.
The fact of needing the teacher's help, as
is the case in any pedagogical relationship,
does not mean that such help does away
with the pupil's creative role and his respon¬
sibility in constructing his written language
and reading it. In fact both the teacher and
the pupil, when, for instance, they grasp an
object, feel it, perceive the felt object and
are capable of expressing the felt and
perceived object verbally. Like me, the il¬
literate person is capable of feeling a pen, of
perceiving it, and of saying "pen". But I
am capable not only of feeling and perceiv¬
ing a pen and saying "pen" but also of
writing "pen" and therefore of reading
"pen". Literacy consists in the written
creation or montage of oral expression.
This montage cannot be performed by the
teacher for or on the pupil. This is the mo¬
ment when the pupil performs his creative
role.
I do not intend to say more here about the
complexities of this process, which I have
analysed more fully elsewhere. But I should
like to revert to one point which I have rais¬
ed several times in this text because of its
importance for a critical understanding of
the act of reading and consequently for the
task of literacy training which I have mark¬
ed out for myself. I am referring to the fact
that "reading" the universe must always
precede reading the word, and reading the
latter implies continuity in "reading" the
former. This movement from universe to
word and back again is always present in
literacy teaching. It is a movement in which
the spoken word is born of the world itself
through our "reading" of the world. In a
sense, however-, we can go further and say
that the reading of the word is preceded not
only by the "reading" of the universe but
also by a certain form of "writing" it or
"rewriting" it in other words, of
transforming it by means of our conscious
practice.
In my opinion this dynamic movement is
one of the central features of the literacy
process. That is why I have always insisted
that the words with which literacy training
is organized must be selected from the
universal vocabulary of the persons con¬
cerned, expressing their real language, their
desires, anxieties, demands and dreams.
They should be charged with the meaning
of their experience of life and not of that of
the teacher. Investigation of what I have
called the "vocabular universe" thus gave
us the world-charged words of the people.
They came to us through the reading of the
universe effected by groups of the people.
Afterwards they returned to them, grafted
on to what I called and still call decodifica-
tions, which are representations of reality.
The word brick, for instance, would be
included in a pictorial representation of a
group of building workers constructing a
house. But before the oral word of a group
of the people was restored to them in writ¬
ten form for comprehension and not for
mechanical memorization, we would con¬
front the pupils with a set of coded situa¬
tions whose decodification or "reading"
led to the critical perception of what culture
is, through an understanding of the human
practice or work which transforms the
world. Basically, thanks to this set of
representations of concrete situations it was
possible for the group to "read" a previous
"reading" of the world before reading the
word.
This more critical "reading" of the less
critical previous "reading" of the world
enables groups of the people, who are
sometimes fatalistic about injustices, to
have a different understanding of their
needs. In this sense, a critical reading of
reality, whether made in the course of a
literacy process or not, and primarily
associated with certain clearly political ac¬
tions of mobilization and organization, can
become an instrument of what Antonio
Gramsci would call "counter-hegemonic
action".
Paulo Freiré
Photo Bruno Barbey © Magnum. Paris
"The 'texts', 'words', and 'letters' of this context were embodied in... rainwater playing at
geography, inventing lakes, islands and rivulets... in the colour of foliage, the shapes of leaves,
the scent of flowers...". Below, amidst giant lilies a boy fishes in a Brazilian river.
\p'
r5* \ 'Pir***
J
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Photo J.-P. Laffont ILO © Sygma. París
Photo Leonard Freed © Magnum, Pari:
Four
stumbling
blocks
In 1980 an estimated 824 million persons were illiterate.
Among the factors which combine to maintain or even in¬
crease the level of the world's illiterate population, four
stand out. (1) A slowdown in the extension of primary
school enrolment combined with population growth
(right) has led to a situation in which more and more
young people are out of school. (2) When they leave
school early (above) many of these young people lose the
benefits of schooling and again become more or less il¬
literate. (3) This "relapse into literacy" is also affecting
the industrialized countries where it is most prevalent
among the least privileged sections of society such as
the unemployed (above right). (4) An increase in the
numbers of refugees and migrants (below) is swelling the
ranks of the illiterate even further.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and the struggle
against illiteracy
DESPITE the huge effort that has
been made to advance educa¬
tion and despite the progress
achieved, the full exercise of the right
to education is still far from being at¬
tained worldwide. The most visible
sign of this, in terms of the number of
human beings it affects and the
number or countries it concerns, is
illiteracy.
In 1980, illiterates accounted for
60.3 per cent of the adult population in
Africa, 37.4 per cent in Asia and 20.2
per cent in Latin America. In spite of a
decrease in the world illiteracy rate,
which fell from 32.9 per cent in 1970
to 28.6 per cent in 1 980, the absolute
number of adult illiterates is still grow¬
ing because of the population increase.
There were 760 million illiterates in
1970, 824 million in 1980 and, if pre¬
sent trends continue, there will be 900
million illiterates towards the end of
the century.
At its twenty-first session, in
Belgrade in September-October 1980,
the General Conference of Unesco
recognized that the elimination of il¬
literacy had become a matter of the
greatest urgency, and deserved the
highest priority. At the same time, the
Conference stressed the importance of
acting simultaneously on two fronts to
secure the general introduction of
primary education, on the one hand
and to promote adult education, and
adult literacy in particular, on the
other.
This double strategy for the develop¬
ment and renewal of primary education
and the promotion of the elimination of
illiteracy will be one of Unesco's
priorities during the coming decade.
Unesco's Medium-Term Plan
(1984-1989) includes a Major Pro¬
gramme: "Education for All". This pro
gramme proposes a new approach,
designed to stem illiteracy at its source
by reducing considerably the number
of children not attending school, while
continuing to increase the literacy rate
among young people and adults. In
practical terms, this implies as mat¬
ters of priority the strengthening of
national research, planning and train¬
ing capacities, and the institution of
regional programmes of co-operation
to prepare the ground for the im¬
plementation of integrated school
enrolment and literacy training
strategies, the aim being to arrest or
even reverse, by the end of the period
covered by the Medium-Term Plan, the
current trend towards an increase in
absolute figures for illiteracy. As far as
Unesco is concerned, activities will be
directed towards four objectives:
A better understanding of the prob¬
lem of illiteracy with the aim of identi¬
fying illiterates more closely (in¬
dividuals and groups) and throwing
light on the reasons for illiteracy in
each particular context, its conse¬
quences for the population and possi¬
ble measures to eliminate it;
Assistance in the framing and im¬
plementation of national, regional and
international strategies for the promo¬
tion of general access to primary
education and for the eradication of il¬
literacy, special attention being paid to
rural areas, with stress on action in
favour of disadvantaged groups and of
girls and women in particular;
Strengthening of training and
retraining of various kinds of literacy
workers able both to teach children
and to run adult literacy programmes;
Promotion of the struggle against
relapse into illiteracy and of educa¬
tional activities to help young school-
leavers to develop further the
knowledge and skills acquired in
school or through literacy courses, and
to impart know-how which will enable
these young people to find employ¬
ment, particularly in the agricultural
and craft sectors.
The Organization has already in¬
itiated training programmes for na¬
tional literacy personnel and
specialists; promoted regional con¬
ferences and regional co-ordination in
the different continents; organized
meetings and seminars; facilitated the
dissemination and exchange of ideas,
information and experience; and en¬
sured the publication and distribution
of technical documents and promo¬
tional materials. Steadily increasing
encouragement and support for na¬
tional strategies are accompanied by
efforts to arouse and mobilize the inter¬
national community, on behalf of the
least-favoured countries in particular.
At the same time, while encouraging
the policies and measures which will
enable the developing countries to
render their own efforts to eliminate il¬
literacy more effective, the Organiza¬
tion also stimulates direct co-operation
between countries with common
problems and interests. Multi¬
dimensional, mutual assistance of this
kind in the field of education is beginn¬
ing to bear fruit, through "horizontal"
co-operation such as that embodied in
the Major Project on Education in Latin
America and the Caribbean, and the
Regional Programme for the Eradica¬
tion of Illiteracy in Africa.
It cannot be over-stressed that ,
Unesco's contribution has been in the
past and continues to be motivated by
the concern to activate and materialize
national initiatives, and to encourage
solutions which take account of na¬
tional realities and respond to specific
national problems.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Literacy awards for 1 983
At a ceremony held at Unesco's Paris headquarters on 8 September to mark
International Literacy Day 1983, ten institutions and two individuals received
prizes or honourable mentionsfor distinguished action in the struggle against
illiteracy. The award winners were selected by an internationaljury under the
chairmanship of Mr. Malcolm S. Adiseshiah, of India.
NADEZHDA
KRUPSKAYA PRIZE
The Nadezhda Krupskaya ' Prize,
established by the USSR in 1969, went
to the Lesotho Distance Teaching
Centre. Using a combination of radio, its
own newspaper for new literates,
Moithuti, specially developed teaching
materials and 28 "learning posts", the
Centre has taught people to read and
write at the rate of a thousand a year over
the last six years. The learning posts are
set up in primary schools or village huts
and serve 3,000 pupils in three of the
country's ten districts. The Centre was
created in 1974 and implements a
strategy worked out following a survey
which revealed that only about 55 per
cent of the population of some
1,200,000 was literate.
Honourable mentions:
(I) Mrs. Joyce Robinson, of Jamaica.
After helping to establish a national
public library system, Mrs. Robinson
went on to become head of JAMAL,
Jamaica's major literacy organization.
(II) Mr. Vuong Kiem Toan, of the
Socialist Republic of Viet Nam. Now
aged 81, Mr. Toan worked for 44 years
to promote literacy in his country, finding
local materials to replace paper, ink and
chalk in time of war and later heading the
Vietnamese committee for the elim¬
ination of illiteracy.
NOMA PRIZE
Presented by Mr. Shoishi Noma, of
Japan, the Noma Prize was awarded to
the Literacy Movement of Burma for
its determined efforts, begun in 1 964, to
eradicate illiteracy through a massive
movement based on community par¬
ticipation and relying on local resources
and voluntary services. The strategy
adopted is to launch a campaign within a
township and to continue until all the in¬
habitants are literate, a process which
takes between one and three years.
Since 1964, 231 communities have run
campaigns and over 1.8 million people
have become literate.
Honourable mentions:
(I) The National Language and
Literature Planning and Development
Agency of Malaysia. The Agency
works to promote literacy in the national
language and produces low cost texts.
(II) The Latin American Association
for Education by Radio, Quito
Ecuador. The Association provides
technical support for 41 institutions
using radio to promote literacy in 1 7 Latin
American countries.
INTERNATIONAL
READING ASSOCIATION
LITERACY AWARD
This $5,000 award was conferred on the
Government of Kenya's Department
of Adult , Education whose pro¬
grammes, launched in 1 979, have reach¬
ed more than a million of the country's
five million illiterates. To implement the
programme the Department has enrolled
3,000 full-time teachers, 5,000 part-
time instructors and 6,000 "self-help"
teachers. Experience in more than
13,000 classes with some 350,000
pupils has shown that an adult can
become literate in six to nine months.
Honourable mentions:
(I) The Barreirnho Project of the
Brazilian Literacy Movement MOBRAL.
The jury thus recognized the efforts
made by MOBRAL to integrate literacy
and post-literacy activities into the
cultural life of the communities concern¬
ed. (II) The General Federation of Iraqi
Women. The Federation has made
literacy a priority aim and has contributed
to the planning and execution of Iraq's
national literacy campaign.
THE IRAQ LITERACY
PRIZE
Presented by the Government of Iraq,
this Prize was awarded to Alfalit, of
Peru, a mainly voluntary institution
which works in urban slums and disad¬
vantaged rural areas. It has developed its
own teaching and follow-up materials
which take into account the life-styles of
literacy learners. Working through cen¬
tres each staffed by four volunteers and
backed by the local community, Alfalit
has set up 1 1 7 literacy courses and, bet¬
ween 1979 and 1982, taught 9,557
people to read and write.
Honourable mentions:
(I) The Village Education Resource
Centre of Bangladesh. The Centre pro¬
motes participation in rural development
and runs an innovative programme link¬
ing formal and out-of-school education.
(II) The Kano State Agency for Mass
Education, Nigeria. In 1981 the Agen¬
cy's basic literacy programme brought
literacy to 100,000 people, thus pro¬
viding a solid foundation for the national
literacy campaign launched in 1982.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff. The boundaries on maps published in the maga¬
zine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100.
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb,- Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
çyjhehandofcFriendship/^
by
the Director General of Unesco
We live in an age of grave uncertainties and. immense hopes, an age
in which all the nations of the world are, for the first time, joined in a
single network of reciprocal relationships. Their destinies are hen¬
ceforth ' interdépendant, ' and the scientific and technological
resources at their disposal could enable them to solve the bulk of
their most urgent problems.
But in order to do this, they must stand united in their purpose and
combine their efforts as they face a common future. In other words,
humanity must prove capable of making a transition from interde¬
pendence to solidarity.
The practice of solidarity requires that each one of us should be
always at the disposal of those who, however far away they may be,
remain and must remain, our neighbours.
Solidarity cannot be enforced; it is lived.
One of Unesco's fundamental tasks is to bring solidarity into effec¬
tive being, for only solidarity can weave a fabric of friendship capa¬
ble of uniting peoples and individuals from different cities, coun¬
tries and continents.
And so today I am appealing to each of you to take part in a
campaign of solidarity involving the Unesco Courier.
You who are a reader of the Unesco Courier, think of someone who
is unkown to you and is yet your brother, of someone who because
of his living conditions often feels alien to you, someone to whom
the Unesco Courier can reveal all that brings you together and
unites you.
Offer him a subscription and thus contribute to Unesco's efforts in
favour of peace and friendship between men.
By so doing you can help make the Unesco Courier the authentic
voice of universal solidarity.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
(For details of how to offer a "friendship" subscription see coupon opposite)
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
c^ßiehandofcFriendship'}
In response to the "Hand of Friendship" appeal I wish to offer one
or more one-year subscriptions to the Unesco Courier to one or
more friends whom I do not yet know.
Special rate for
1 one-year
2 one-year
3 one-year
4 one-year
5 one-year
D 10 one-year
D 20 one-year
this solidarity campaign
subscription : 48 FF*
subscriptions: 96 FF*
subscriptions: 144 FF*
subscriptions: 192 FF*
subscriptions: 240 FF*
subscriptions: 480 FF*
subscriptions: 960 FF*
French francs
In this campaign, the choice of langua¬
ges is limited to the 4 editions publish¬
ed at Unesco Headquarters.
(number of subscriptions)
D English
D French
O Spanish
D Arabic
-ill in using Block Capitals
COUNTRY
D I am not a subscriber to the
Unesco Courier
D I am a subscriber; my number is:
Please specify whether, on expiry of the
subscription or subscriptions you are offe¬
ring, the subscription renewal request should
be addressed to you.
D Yes D No
Request not accompanied by the appropriate
payment will be considered as void.
I enclose payment in French francs (by
cheque made out to Librairie de l'Unes-
co) or the équivalent in another converti¬
ble currency or by international money
order.
Please return to:
Unesco/Hand of Friendship
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris
France
In the three months following reception
of your gift, the World Federation of
Unesco Clubs and Associations will
send your name and address to your
future friend or friends. You will be infor¬
med of his/her or their names and
addresses.
If you wish your gift to be made anony¬
mously, please tick this box D.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
abroad
àl'étranger
L^
enlxtranje
? / /
", -f 'r,
s s. y.
T T
X
X
3 T3
t/3 3
i
A Unesco best-seller
77ie /a/etf #4//i> edition of Unesco 's popular reference book detail¬
ing opportunitiesforfurther study and training available in allparts
of the world.
Lists over 200,000 offers of scholarships, assistantships, travel
grants and other forms offinancial assistance offered by interna¬
tional organizations, governments, foundations, universities and
other institutions in more than 115 countries.
Provides easy-to-use information on who can study what sub¬
ject and where, details of each award including how and where to
apply.
The offers are mainly for post-secondary study and training, in
all academic and professional fields, but include some Unesco co-
sponsored post-graduate courses.
1104 pages
Trilingual: Knglish/French/Spanish
55 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications. 5BA Gipps Street. CoMino
wood Victoria 3ÓM; Pubkcations: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2 1 00, NSW. Periodicals: Oommie
Pty. Subscriptions Dept, P.O. Box 33. Brookvale 2100, NSW.
Sub- agent: United Nattons Association of Australia, P.O. Box
1 75. 5ih floor. Ana House, 2B Elizabeth Street, Melbourne
Victoria 3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co..
Graben 31, A -1011, Vienna. - RAH AMAS. Nassau Sta
tuners Ltd , P.O. Box N-313B, Nassau. BANGLADESH.
Bangladesh Books International Ltd., ittef iq Building. 1. R K
Mission Rd , Hetkhola, Dacca 3. - BARBADOS. University
of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Beut 64,
Bridgetown. - BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition
onfy: N V. Handeimaatscheppij líeesing. Keesinglaan 2 18.
2 1 00 Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publication s agent: JeandeLanncy, 202, avenue du Roi. 1060
Brussels, CCP 000 007082 3 13 BOTSWANA. Botswana
Book Centre. P.O. Box SI , Gaborone BURMA. Trade Cor
[H] rat i on No. 9. S50-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon.
CANADA. Renoul Publishing Co. Ltd-, 2132 St. Catherine
Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7. - CHAD. Libraihe
Abssounout, 24 av. Chartes de Gaulle, B.P 388, N Diamena.
CHINA, China National Publications Import and Expon Cor
porabon, P.O. Box SB, Beijing CYPRUS. jrMAM". Ar¬
chbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue. P.O. Box 1722. Nicosia. -
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. SN T L SpaleneSI , Prague 1 (Per¬
manent display), Zehranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukemcka, Prague
1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Vertag. Publishers. Hurbanovo
nam. 6 893 31 Bratislava - CSSR - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service. 35 Norre
Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K. EQYPT (ARAB
RE PUBLIC OF), National Centre lor Unesco Publications. No
1 Telaat Herb Street, Cairo. - ETHIOPIA. National Agency
for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996. Addis Ababa FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. Kaskuskatu 1. SF-OOlOO Helsinki
10. Suomaiamen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01640
Ventea 64. FRANCE, Librairie de r Unesco. 7, place de
Fontenoy. 75700 Paris. CCP. 12598-48. - GABON.
Librairie Hachette, B.P. 3923, Libreville GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig. Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Interna tionalen Buchhandlungen m the G. D.H.
FED. REP. OF GERMANT. For the Unesco Courier fGer
man, English. French and Spanish editions]: Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco Kurier Vertrieb, Basartstrasse 57, 05300
Bonn 3- for other Unesco publications- Karger Vertag, Germer¬
ing München For scientific maps only- Geo Center. Postfach
800830, Stuttgart SO. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd.. P.O. Box 135. Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd..
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Ac¬
cra, The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop ol Legon. P Q Box 1, Legon, - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom - HONG KONG. Federal Publications
IHK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion. 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong Kong Government Information Services. Publication
Centre, Baskorville House, 22 Ice Street. - HUNGARY.
Akademiai Konyvesbort, Vaci u 22, Budapest V; A.K V
KonyvtürosokBoltja.Nepköitartatagutja 16, Budapest VI. -
ICELAND, Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co .. H.F.. Hafnarstraeti 9.
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.. Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road. Madras 2;
5 9-41 n Bashir Bagii Hyderabad 500001 i API. 80/1 Mahat
ma Gandhi Road, Bangalor s -560001; 3 5 B20 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad 500001 Sub Depots: Oxford Book A Stationery
Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016, Scindia House, New
Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Cultura, Ex.
AFO Hutments, Dr Rejendre Prasad Road. New Delhi 1 10O01.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers. 29 Jl
Oto Itkaodardinata HI, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam
Ratulangie 37. Jakarta Pusat. IRAN- Kherejmie Publishing
and Distribution Co., 2B, Vestal Stiiwi Street, Enghelab
Avenue. P.D. Box 314/1 486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco. Seyed Jamal Eddm Assad Abodi Avenue 64th Street,
Bonyed Building P.O. Sox 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ« McKan-
;re s Bookshop. AI Rashid Street. Baghdad IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd, Baitymount Road,
Walklnstown. Dublm 12; Tycooty International PuW. Ltd 6
CrotVofl Terrace. LXin Looghaire Co., Dublin. - ISRAEL-
ABC. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283. 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 6 1 000. ITALY, Ucosa iLibrena Commissionaria San-
soni. S p .A.) Via Lamarmora 45, CaseJI a Postale 552, SOI 21
Florence, - JAMAICA, Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lone. Kingston. University of the West In¬
dies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston. JAPAN, Eastern Book
Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-choma Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113.
KENYA. East Alrican Publishing House. P.O. Box 30571.
Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco.
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwart: for the Unesco
Courier; Fararella Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541,
Kuwart. LESOTHO, Mazenod Book Centra, P.O. Mazenod.
Lesotho. Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cod« and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd.. P O Box 288, Monrovia LIBYA, Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution. P.O. Box
34 35, Tripod LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22,
Grande-Rue, Luxembourg - MALAWI. Malawi Book Ser¬
vice, Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichi«. Blantyre 3. -
MALAYSIA, University of Malaya Cooperativa Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22 11 MALTA. Sapien/as. 26 Republic
Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS, Naianda Company Ltd , 30,
Bourbon Street. Port Louis. - MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulin*. Monte Carlo NEPAL. Safha Prakashan
Polchowk. Kathmandu - NETHERLANDS. For periodicals
only; D&N Faxon B.V , P.O. Box 197. 1O00 AD Amsterdam,
for publications only: KEESING BOEKENB V . Postbus 1 1 18
1000 BC Amsterdam - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van
Oorp Eddine N V . P 0. Box 200. Willemstod. Curaçao. N.A
NEW ZEALAND, Government Printing Office. Govern¬
ment Bookshops at Rutland Street, P. O Box 5344, Auckland,
130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Akne
Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamiltor , Princes Street. P.O. Box 1 104,
Dunedm. Mulgrove Street, Private Bag, Wesengtari.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P 0. 286, The University Bookshop of
Nsukka. The University Bookshop of Logos, The Ahmodu Bello
University Bookshop oí Zana. ¡NORWAY, AH publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum 4 Book sellers I. Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universrtets Bokhandeten, Universitetssentret, P.OB.
307 Blindem. Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Nervesens
Liieraturtanaste. Box 6125. Oslo 6 PAKISTAN, Mir*a
Book Agency, 65 Shahrnh Qund-i-aiim, P.O. Box No 729.
Laboral PHILIPPINES. The Modem Book Co . 926 Rizal
Avenue. P.O. Bom 632. Manila D 404. POLAND. Orpan
Import. Peloc Kuttury I Nauki. Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch,
Krakowskie Priedmiescw No. 7 00 066 WARSAW POR¬
TUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Lrv rana Portugal, rua do Carmo
70. Lisbon SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
46,Mahe, New Service Ltd , Kmgsgate House. P.O.Box 131,
Mahé SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay. Njala University and
Sierra Leone Diocesan Book shops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (Si Pte Ltd. Times
Jurong, 2 Jurong Pott Rood, Singapore 2261. SOMAU
DEMOCRATIC REPUBUC. Modern Book Shop and
GeneraF. P/0. Box 951 . Mogadiscio SOUTH AFRICA. For
the Unesco Courier [single copies! only: Central Ne ws agency.
P.O Bbx 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA, Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box
1116, Khartoum SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C E
Frittes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regen rvgsgalan 1 2, Box 16356.
10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Forbundet, Skolgrend 2, Box ISO SOS 104 65, Stockholm
- SWITZERLAND. AU publications; Europa Vertag 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot. rue Grenus 6. 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP 12 236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne,
Basle, Berne. Vevey. Montreux, Neuchatel and Zurich, -
TANZANIA. Darás Salaam Bookshop, PUB. 9030 Dar es
Salaam THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Lid, 40 42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyeeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402;
Bangkok: Suksapan Penrt, Mansion 9, Rejdamnarn Avenue,
Bangkok, Suksit S*om Company. 1715 Rams IV Road,
Bangkok TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO, National Commis
sion lor Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair. Trinidad, W.l
TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi AS-, IstiklH Ceddesi. N* 469,
Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop. PO. Box 714S, Kampala UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office. H. M. SO-. P.O. Box 276. London.
SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshop« in London. Edinburgh,
Belfast. Manchester. Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps
only. McCaMa Ltd., 122 King's Cross Rood. London WC IK 9
DS UNITED STATES. Umpub. 205 East 42nd Street.
New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders lor books & Periodicals; Box
433. Murray H* Station, New York. NY 101 57. - U.S.S.R.
Meihdunorodrujye Kniga, Moscow. G 2 CK) -
YOU G OS LAVI A MLadosi, lhc> 30/11, Zagreb; Cenkarjeva
Zaloiba, Zoprtariave 2, LuUjana, Nofet, Tera/i|e 27/11.
Belgrade ZAMBIA. National Educational Distribution Co.
of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664 Lusaka - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales IPVTI Ltd.. 67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
International literacy day
These paintings, displayed in a park in Ottawa on 8 September 1 983 on the occasion of the 17th International Literacy Day,
express the feelings of a group of Canadians about their handicapilliteracy. The artists all attend literacy classes provided
by ALSO, an Ottawa-based organization established to help illiterates. The 8th of September was proclaimed International
Literacy Day by the Unesco General Conference, in 1966, as a means of awakening the international community to the
problem of illiteracy, its nature and its social consequences. The Day is celebrated each year throughout the world so as
to make known the measures each country is taking in the struggle to promote world literacy.
]]>
</page>
</document>
