<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074741eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
i
Ünejco ouri
JUNE 1981 - 4.50 French francs
i»
à
f
New ways to learning
INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF DISABLED PERSONS
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Ethiopia
Pre-Aksumite portrait
This bust is part of a limestone statue (82 cm high) unearthed at Haoulti in
northern Ethiopia and probably dating from the 5th or 4th centuries of the
pre-Christian era. The statue represents a seated woman with her hands
on her knees, dressed in a long robe with narrow vertical pleats. She
wears a wide three-stranded necklace, and her hair is depicted by rows of
small lozenges. This portrait in stone dates back to a time when the in¬
fluence of south Arabia, during the supremacy of the kingdom of Saba, is
widely agreed to have been strong in this part of Africa where, some cen¬
turies later, the powerful kingdom of Aksum rose and flourished.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Ihr
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JUNE 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (II issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.CR. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc.. 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (31 Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Braille
Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
SOS PARENTS
The decisive role of the family
in rehabilitating handicapped children
by Leo F. Buscaglia
7 AN AFRICAN APPROACH
by Gustave-Justin Nlo
8 THEIR HANDICAP IS HUNGER
10 CHILDHOOD AWAKENING
A Jamaican experiment
by Marigold Thorburn
12 UNESCO AND SPECIAL EDUCATION
FOR HANDICAPPED CHILDREN
16 Special schools or integrated education ?
I. 'The integration of the handicapped into society
can be best prepared in special schools'
by Vladimir I. Lubovski
20 II. 'Our task is to bring the retarded into the community
from which they have been excluded'
by Marten Soder
18 THE RIGHTS OF MENTALLY RETARDED PERSONS
How far are they observed?
24 COMMUNITIES THAT CARE
by Mahfoud Boucebci
26 SOUNDS FROM SILENCE
by Li Hongtai and Shen Jiayin
28 SELF-RELIANCE AND THE RIGHT TO WORK
by Ed. Sackstein
31 DISABLED CHARACTERS
IN SEARCH OF AN AUTHOR
by Tordis Orjasaeter
34 UNESCO NEWSROOM
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
ETHIOPIA : Pre-Aksumite portrait
1
«
*- 1
Cover
This issue, a follow-up to our January num¬
ber, is largely devoted to the role of modern
education in helping handicapped people to
overcome the problems facing them in their
search for full integration into society. Photo
shows a physically and mentally handi¬
capped child, wearing a protective helmet.
Photo Laurence Srun © Petit Format, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
SOS parents
Photo © Gilles Cohen, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The decisive role of the family
in rehabilitating
handicapped children
by Leo F. Buscaglia PARENTS are the most important and
vital resource in the process of
evaluating, educating, and rehabili¬
tating a child with a handicap. Yet, for some
mysterious reason, the child's parents are
often seen as "the enemy". They are con¬
sidered by many professionals as uninform¬
ed meddlers who are much too emotionally
involved in their child's problems to offer
even the simplest objective insight or
positive action. They are, therefore, treated
as secondary citizens in the diagnostic and
re-educational processes, if not excluded
altogether.
This is true, even though research find¬
ings consistently indicate that well inform¬
ed, optimistic, accepting parents have a
most positive and significant effect upon the
education, well-being, and adjustment of
their handicapped child. In the long run,
their influence is far more productive and
long-lasting than that of physicians, nurses,
therapists, psychologists, or any of the
many other helpers who will encounter the
child in his lifetime.
It is, therefore, of monumental impor¬
tance that parents and professionals strive
to form a mutually beneficial partnership
dedicated to the social, physical,
psychological, and educational growth of
the child.
The following four principles are offered
as a possible guide to action designed to
achieve this end.
To begin with, the parents must be helped
to understand their emotional and intellec¬
tual responses relating to their handi¬
capped child, for these feelings may be
preventing them from understanding
clearly, and co-operating fully, in any
therapeutic process.
Parents must be offered an honest, mean¬
ingful, and accurate medical, social,
psychological, and educational evaluation
of their child's physical and emotional
condition, and intellectual abilities.
The parents must be given a thorough
understanding of educational or rehabilita¬
tions! programmes designed and recom¬
mended for their child.
The parents must be encouraged to
assume an active role in the re-education
of their child and be offered a means for
evaluating the effectiveness of the pro¬
gramme at every stage of its progress.
At best, it is not easy to be a parent. In
fact, it is perhaps the greatest and most
LEO F. BUSCAGLIA, of the United States of
America, is professor of education at the Univer¬
sity of Southern California, Los Angeles. He is the
author of many articles and of seven books in¬
cluding: Love; The Disabled and their Parents: a
Counselling Challenge; The Way of the Bull;
Human Advocacy; and Personhood. A world
traveller, he has taught and lectured in many
countries. His programmes broadcast on United
States National Public Television have been wide¬
ly acclaimed.
complex of human responsibilities. Yet,
most of us are tragically unprepared for this
demanding task. It is even more difficult to
be trie parent of a handicapped child, for
birth is, in a very real sense, a gift. It is an
awesome discovery to learn that one has
produced an imperfect gift.
This realization often brings with it natural
feelings of fear, pain, disappointment, loss,
guilt, confusion, and general feelings of
helplessness and inadequacy. Most parents
have little knowledge of the conditions that
provoke handicaps and few resources
necessary to understand them. This lack of
understanding can produce feelings which
freeze them into inactivity, depression and
self-recrimination, and prevent them from
dealing adequately and productively with
their handicapped child.
It is, therefore, inconceivable to expect
that parents can immediately accept the
birth of their handicapped child and be ready
to help in the educational process. They
must first be encouraged to understand that
their feelings are appropriate, that it is
understandable that they should be feeling a
sense of disbelief and depression; that it is
acceptable that they are in emotional pain,
questioning and fearful; that they would
like to wish it all away; that they should
curse the fates that brought them this
"misfortune".
At this point it may be impossible for
parents to imagine that there is anything
positive about a handicap. It is only with
time, insight and re-education that the
parent can be shown that whatever is
positive is to be found not in the han¬
dicap in the child who is handicapped.
Their child is a child like other children. But
he or she is also a unique creation, a com¬
bination of not only what there is, but also a
limitless possibility of what, with their active
participation, can be. So, the first step in the
rehabilitation process lies in emotionally
aiding parents through their incapacitating
feelings, on to acceptance and active
participation.
Professionals often feel that it is a waste
of their time and energies to give medical,
psychological and educational information
to parents. After all, they state, it takes
years of training to prepare a professional.
Their argument is usually that parents would
not understand the problem anyway, and a
little knowledge is a dangerous thing. To
know "the facts" would only confuse and
frighten them more.
Nothing could be further from the truth!
Knowledge and understanding are great
eradicators of fear providing that the infor¬
mation given is not shrouded in mysterious
medical jargon or half truths or uncomfor¬
table pronouncements. What information is
given must be honest, gentle, straight- 1
forward, and clear. In addition, diagnosis I
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
often is nothing more than a statement of
what is wrong with the child, what the prob¬
lems are, the skills that cannot be perform¬
ed, the abilities the child does not have. It is
no wonder that parents leave such an ex¬
perience in pain, bitterness and pessimism.
A real diagnostic presentation must be
equally concerned with what the child can
do, at what levels he is able to function,
those aspects which show promise and
where the strengths lie for it ¡s with these
positive aspects that the therapeutic pro¬
gramme can be actualized. In her book, The
Siege, Clara Clarborne Clark describes the
results of such a diagnostic interview follow¬
ing months of tests and examinations of her
autistic child. She says she needed informa¬
tion and techniques and the professionals
gave her none. "I needed references," she
continues, "I needed to know all about my
daughter Elly, because whoever else may or
may not work with her, her main therapist is
me."
Too many professionals, because they
often feel a general discomfort and inade¬
quacy when faced with the human problem
A young handicapped girl learning to walk at a centre for the disabled
in Lesotho, southern Africa.
Photo Martine Frank © Magnum, Paris
of talking to parents about their children's
handicaps, hide these inadequacies in test
results, complicated medical case histories,
mysterious labels and high-sounding jargon
which only serve to leave parents feeling
abandoned, confused, and more fearful and
despairing than ever.
Parents must be given the facts, for the
facts will free them and bring them the
necessary sensitivity and wisdom which will
lead them to acquire the realistic skills
necessary for their participation in their
child's education and growth. The facts will
offer them the resources to see and under¬
stand their child in a realistic fashion and
make them a more knowledgeable and com¬
fortable part of the rehabilitation team. Pro¬
fessionals must realize that no matter how
many trained individuals work with the han¬
dicapped person in his or her lifetime, none
will have more consistent contact, or a more
significant and lasting effect than the
parents.
The rehabilitation and education pro¬
grammes for the disabled require the best
possible interaction between and the parti¬
cipation of many individuals. Depending
upon the disability, expertise may be needed
from general physicians, neurologists,
psychologists, occupational and physical
therapists, educators, language and speech
pathologists, and a variety of others. But the
individuals who give significance and pur¬
pose to this process, and are at the core of
it, will always be the handicapped Individual
and the parents.
It is therefore imperative that the parents
thoroughly understand whatever remedial
plans are designed for their child. Yet when
parents bring their handicapped child to
hospital for consultations or therapy ses¬
sions, which could be great educational ex¬
periences for them, they are more often than
not asked to "wait outside". If they ask
questions they are often put off or embar¬
rassingly talked down to. The inference is
that information on their own child is private
and none of their concern, that they are too
ignorant to understand it even if it were ex¬
plained. It is no wonder, therefore, that
parents of the handicapped so often ex¬
press feelings of isolation, inadequacy and
impotence.
To exclude parents from the educational
planning for their child, as is so often the
case, is both ludicrous and counter¬
productive, for no one has a greater need to
understand the child than its parents. It is
they who will experience the dally progress
or lack thereof. It is they who will observe
and aid their child through pain and tears as
the child battles his or her way through the
therapeutic programme. Professionals must
understand that parents may not be perfect,
they may not always know or do "what they
should know or do", but nonetheless, they
will still have to understand and do more
than anyone else. For who else will be
spending more time and energy in perma¬
nent, everyday contact with the child?
Parents are more than willing to take an
active part in their child's remedial pro¬
gramme and will carry out their charge with
the tender loving care and consistency that
most professionals do not have time for. It is
logical that since they will be doing
something anyway, they may as well be do¬
ing the right thing.
It is important not simply that parents be
given time to work through their feelings.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
that they be given accurate information and
made integral partners in the planning of the
programme for their child, they must also be
encouraged to do something tangible and
positive with the strength and Information
they have acquired. Knowing is a beginning,
but the true value of knowledge lies in its
daily application.
The rehabilitation process is a long, ar¬
duous, demanding journey through which
the parents must be supported and advised.
They will be required to learn how to
schedule their time so as to be able to meet
their child's needs, without giving up their
own personal physical, psychological and
intellectual requirements for growth. I have
known parents who have not had time for
themselves in all the years since the birth of
their handicapped child. They cannot even
obtain the help of baby-sitters who often,
due to their fears or lack of information, are
reluctant to take responsibility for handicap¬
ped children.
Parents will have special motivational
problems, for the rehabilitation process is
often slow. So much expended energy on
their part often seems to produce so few
tangible results and so little progress. They
will have to be given the courage to con¬
tinue. In addition, they will have to learn
how to cope with the problem of rejection
by society.
As part of the team they will need to know
precisely what they can do for their child,
what realistic demands can be set, and what
possible limitations there are. They must be
helped over feelings of inadequacy and Im¬
perfection as they involve themselves in the
learning process. They must be made to
understand the fact that they are not ex¬
pected to be perfect but rather, only
human that, perhaps, their love, concern
and humanity are their greatest assets.
If these conditions are adhered to, a
bridge between parents and professionals
can be constructed over which the han¬
dicapped child may be guided to in¬
dependence, growth, security and self-
esteem.
What is needed is a bill of parental rights
regarding parents' partnership with pro¬
fessionals ¡n helping the handicapped child.
It may be stated as follows:
Parents have a right to take the necessary
time to deal with the myriad confused and
painful feelings associated with giving
birth to an exceptional child.
Parents have a right to sound medical,
psychological and educational knowledge
regarding their child's present condition
and future possibilities.
Parents have a right to a clear under¬
standing of their specific role in meeting
their child's unique needs.
Parents have a right to participate in the
programme of remediation and re¬
education of their child.
Parents have a right to periodic ré¬
évaluation and involvement in the con¬
tinual planning for new goals which may
be required as a result of time, maturation
and new findings.
Parents have a right to information re¬
garding available community support
systems to meet their financial. Intellectual
and emotional needs.
Parents have a right to some interaction
with other parents who have handicapped
children so that they may share feelings,
hopes, and general human considerations
as they meet the challenge of raising their
handicapped child.
Parents have a right to develop in their
roles as persons, apart from their role as
parents of a handicapped child.
Given these rights, parents grow to
become real assets in the rehabilitation and
education of their handicapped child.
As one parent of a handicapped child
wrote, "You wake one day to realize that all
the trials, the turmoil, the anxiety, the fear
have given you a modicum of that which
you sought understanding. You find,
somewhat to your surprise, that the lessons
you have learned are priceless. Although
you have sometimes rebelled against it all,
questioned it, resented it, you would not
relinquish these lessons. For you have
begun to acquire that depth you have long
sought. Your experiences have brought you
into closer touch with others. Therein lies
the victory for you. Therein lies your ability
to appreciate your child. If the child can
understand that you have grown to this con¬
viction he or she will feel freer, not a burden
to you or anyone, not a pulllng-down ele¬
ment in your life but an uplifting one. If the
child can understand that, then he will know
he has given you the opportunity to grow
with him. And the growing process will con¬
tinue onward. The possibilities are endless.
Isn't that what It's all about?"
To this, I can only add, "Yes that is truly
what it is all about!" , Leo F Buscag|¡a
An African
approach by Gustave-Justin Nlo
IN traditional African society, care is
lavished on the mentally handicap¬
ped child, who is brought up and
taught by its mother and father. The
youngster will be given a taste of work
in the fields (with the cacao trees,
groundnuts and maize), of household
jobs (drawing water at the spring, split¬
ting logs, fetching wood from the
bush, washing clothes and utensils), or
he may learn the rudiments of a craft.
He will be initiated into traditional rites,
take part in funeral ceremonies,
palavers and confessional assemblies.
If the child is seriously handicapped,
the family will do the best it can to
educate him and give him the utmost
help and support in the home.
In the rural areas the mentally han¬
dicapped child has always been a fully
accepted member of the African ex¬
tended family, that expansive unit
whose hospitality is not confined to
father, mother and children but en¬
compasses aunts, cousins, and uncles.
Since one advantage of the extended
family is that all its members feel an
acute sense of their responsibilities to
each other, the handicapped child can
find food and lodging in every
household in the village. He gives a
helping hand to all and sundry and ¡s
cossetted in return. Everyone in the
village stands by him, for his fate is not
solely the concern of his father and
mother.
The village faces many problems
when it comes to his schooling.
Specialized institutions are few and far
between, and in such schools as exist
GUSTAVE-JUSTIN NLO, of Cameroun,
is secretary-general of the Association of
Parents of Handicapped Children, in
Yaounde.
in the vicinity no one will agree to take
him on because he will be a nuisance
during lessons. Only in rare cases will
the family be able to afford to send him
to a specialized institution in town; and
he will usually have to stay in the
village.
As a rule, the children's handicaps
are detected by specialists during infor¬
mal consultations, at school, and in
child- and mother-care centres.
Some families are ashamed to tell
the truth about their child because a
preliminary examination may diagnose
his handicap as due to some such
cause as chronic alcoholism or a
hereditary defect. However, such in¬
formation must be noted if the
teachers are to receive reliable informa¬
tion about the child.
When a child has been accepted by a
centre, most parents expect to see him
miraculously transformed into some¬
one who can be reintegrated into the
productive world, whereas in most
cases his "normalization" can only be
partial.
In any case, the role of the institu¬
tion is complementary to that of the
family, which must give regular sup¬
port to the teachers. It is in collabora¬
tion with the teachers, for example,
that the family will encourage the
youngster to take upa craft for which
he shows a special aptitude, such as
carpentry, basketwork, pottery, sew¬
ing, farming or gardening. Then, when
the child is properly apprenticed, those
concerned with following his progress
will advise the parents how to help him
make his way in working life, for the
support of the family will continue to
be the mainstay of his integration into
the modern world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Their handicap is hunger
IN any consideration of the plight of the
handicapped, one simple truth should
never be forgotten: a large proportion
of the handicaps with which they are af¬
flicted could be prevented if the millions of
starving and malnourished people in the
world were given an adequate, balanced
diet.
In a world in which man is capable of
reaching the moon, hunger is a scandal
which every year causes untold numbers of
deaths among the poor of the Third World
and leaves millions more marked for life by
severe physical and mental impairment. Of
the 450 million handicapped people in the
world, therefore, a large proportion owe
their disability entirely to malnutrition.
In the Preliminary Assessment of the
World Food Situation, Present and Future,
published by the United Nations in 1974, it
was estimated that "in the Far East alone
more than 100,000 children go blind each
year due to vitamin A deficiency... Iron and
folate [a vitamin of the B complex] deficien¬
cy anaemias are widely prevalent in
developed and developing countries and are
the cause of ill-health and result in a
decreased ability to lead an active life... A
comprehensive world review of endemic
goitre revealed that there were 200 million
people suffering from the disease...which is
usually accompanied by endemic
cretinism... Half the children under five in
developing countries are inadequately
nourished, and for many this will inevitably
lead to premature death". The Sixth Report
on the World Health Situation, published by
WHO as recently as last year, confirms the
gravity of the problem.
Vitamin A deficiency is one of the most
elementary forms of malnutrition and one of
the easiest to combat. The 1974 United Na¬
tions World Food Conference, in its second
report, stated that "considering each child
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
World food map: dietary energy supply (per capita), around 1975
Source: World population data sheets, 1975 and 1978, Population Reference Bureau, Inc., reproduced in the Sixth Report
on the World Health Situation, Volume I, World Health Organization, Geneva, 1980. No official data available for China.
has to be given two capsules lof vitamin Al,
the total annual cost of protecting 100
. million one-to-five-year-old children all over
the world against the risk of xerophthalmia
(caused by vitamin A deficiency) would be
around three million dollars." In other
words, with just three dollars, one hundred
children could be insured against the risk of
blindness, an infinitesimal sum when com¬
pared with the enormous amounts spent on
armaments.
One essential aspect of malnutrition as a
source of handicaps is the effect it has on
the brain of the infant both before birth and
during the early years of life. Protein-calorie
deficiency, the cause of maladies such as
Kwashiorkor and Marasmus which decimate
the infant populations of the poor countries,
combined with lack of a stimulating environ¬
ment, is the chief cause of retarded develop¬
ment and brain damage.
The problem begins with the mother. A
malnourished mother is unable to supply the
unborn child with the nutrients essential to
its proper growth. Mothers whose diet dur¬
ing pregnancy has been deficient in protein
and calories often give birth to children of
below average weight and with smaller than
average brains.
Recent medical findings have confirmed
the relationship between low birth weight
and mental retardation. It has been shown
that less than one per cent of newborn
children of normal weight suffer from men¬
tal deficiency as compared with fifty per
cent of those who weigh less than one and a
half kilos at birth. Malnutrition has similar ef¬
fects during the first five years of life, the
most important periods for human brain
growth.
A large proportion of the victims of
malnutrition, and this includes the majority
of the children of the developing world, will
suffer all their lives from irreversible
disabilities problems of sight and hearing.
motor defects, epilepsy, cerebral palsy, etc.
The result is mental retardation and stagna¬
tion of the faculty of comprehension, with
all the dire consequences for later life that
this entails (failure at school, inability to
learn a trade, failure'to adapt normally to
society).
Seen against this background, it becomes
clear that the great effort that has been
made over the last few years by the United
Nations and its specialized agencies, such as
Unesco, to achieve a new world economic
order is also, in effect, the most important
step forward ever made towards the preven¬
tion of handicaps resulting from malnutri¬
tion. M
A Unesco enquiry
on
malnutrition
and
child welfare
Under its Research and Human Needs programmes Unesco has launched a research pro¬
ject aimed at improving our understanding of the effects of malnutrition on young
children. The project is based on four countries of the Mediterranean but there are plans to
extend it later to other regions in Africa, Asia and Latin America. The objectives of the
research project are to identify and evaluate the nutritional, biological, environmental and
other requirements of infants, young children and pregnant and nursing mothers and to
propose and promote effective measures to be taken within a given social and cultural
context. The research will be undertaken by teams of local scientists in collaboration with
Unesco and various scientific organizations and will cover many fields including nutrition,
biology, chemistry, genetics, neurophysiology, sociology and cultural anthropology.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Childhood awakening
A Jamaican experiment
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
by Marigold Thorburn
THOSE of us who grew up in loving homes with parents who
played with us and gave us toys seldom stop to think how
important these things were to our eventual growth and
, development. Yet they are of enormous importance, for without
them we learn slowly, if at all. If you have no toys as a baby how do
you learn to focus on an object or grasp it?
It was to remedy situations of this kind that early childhood
stimulation programmes were devised. In poor countries lack of
stimulation is more often due to lack of knowledge and poverty than
to deliberate neglect, but the result is the same are slow
and regarded as dull when ¡n fact they are merely uninformed.
There are, of course, other causes of delayed development, for
example, a disability due to illness or brain damage. In these cases
doctor and therapist have to work very closely together and obtain
the enthusiastic co-operation of the parent, grannie, auntie or other
parent substitute. The parent has as much to learn as the child; he or
she needs to understand that handicapped children are not-
necessarily helpless or dependent and that given more attention and
training results can be achieved that make the extra effort involved
well worth while. When a child suffers from both parental indif¬
ference and malnutrition, the health and social welfare workers have
to make a special effort to rouse the interest of and motivate the
parents. In all these situations education is the key.
The Jamaican Early Childhood Stimulation Project ¡s a continuous
remedial action programme designed to meet the individual needs of
the child and to arouse and hold the imagination of the parent,
usually the mother, and get her involved in the learning process.
The Jamaican project is based on a North American model
modified to fit local needs and resources. It consists of four main
stages.
First, the children needing help have to be identified. Mothers,
members of the family and friends are often the first to recognize
that a child's development is slower than usual. The most common
signs are lateness in sitting, walking or talking. Sometimes a doctor
or nurse on a routine visit to a clinic notices the tell-tale signs of late
development. In other instances late-developing children are
detected by means of simple tests carried out in day nurseries and
creches. In all these cases children can be brought to our offices for
confirmatory checks and examinations.
At the second stage, if a child is found to have a significant delay
in development, a further in-depth assessment, including the
establishment of a full case history and a complete medical examina¬
tion, is carried out in our offices. On the basis of our findings a pro¬
gramme of treatment and intervention is drawn up.
During the third stage this programme, which consists mainly of
various forms of teaching and training, is put into practice in the
child's own home. One very important aspect is that the mother
becomes fully involved in the programme and herself carries out the
teaching at home in between the weekly visits of the social auxiliary.
The final stage involves a review and evaluation of the child's pro¬
gress. The mother brings the child back to our offices once every
three months or so for this reassessment and, if necessary, the pro¬
gramme can then be adjusted.
The Jamaican project is supervised by a public health service
nurse, but this task could be carried out by anyone with the ap¬
propriate training and experience, such as a teacher or a social
worker. Identification of children in need of help is the responsibility
of specially trained workers of the Jamaica Youth Corps.
Assessments are made with the help of the Portage Check List, a
systematic, sequenced list of child behavioural skills and aptitudes,
each aptitude on the list corresponding to a specific item of the
education programme. In this way the child, the mother and the
social auxiliary form a mutually dependent team.
In Jamaica, the auxiliaries, known affectionately as "Crashies"
because they had been through an accelerated training or crash
course, were selected from participants in a special employment
programme. In the new project being carried out in St. Catherine the
auxiliaries have been recruited from the local communities and the
parents themselves are also being trained.
MARIGOLD THORBURN, of Jamaica, is regional co-ordinator with the
Caribbean Institute on Mental Retardation and Other Development Pro¬
blems, at the Northern Caribbean University, Kingston.
This innovation has worked well and each auxiliary visits about a
dozen homes a week. The auxiliaries work under the guidance of a
supervisor but it is they who keep in touch with the mothers.
Medical assessment is undertaken by a doctor. Exercises and ac¬
tivities are specially developed for each child and involve the use of
simple toys, often made from waste materials.
In 1978, five years atfter the Early Childhood Stimulation Project
started in Kingston, we decided to take a look at what had happened
to some of the children who had participated in the project from the
very beginning. Half of them were still involved in the project and the
remainder are attending either ordinary elementary schools or
special schools for handicapped children.
The progress made by fifty-six children who had had continuous
care over a period of eighteen months was also assessed. The
children were divided into three groups mildly, moderately and
severely handicapped and progress was measured by the average
number of skills learned by the children during the period. This was
compared with what would be expected of a normal child. Over a
given period of time a normal child would probably learn six skills per
month. We found that the mildly and moderately handicapped
children gained 50 per cent more skills than would have been ex¬
pected in normal children. The children of the severely handicapped
group, however, did not do so well, but they nevertheless acquired
more than twice as many skills as they would have been expected to
learn without any stimulation.
Many medical conditions can cause delays in development, retar¬
dation and other types of handicap. Among. the commoner ones
found in our project were Down's Syndrome, brain damage due to
complications at birth, jaundice after birth, meningitis, epilepsy and
rubella contracted by the mother during pregnancy. In almost one
fifth of the children seen it was impossible to determine the cause of
handicap.
In almost all these conditions early stimulation can produce
remarkable results and it is anticipated that, in the long run, children
who have benefited from early stimulation programmes will meet
with fewer problems in their education and have better prospects of
achieving'independence in their adult life. Furthermore, seeing the
improvement in her child, the^ mother becomes more optimistic
about its future. The combination of loving care and well planned
stimulation can, therefore, produce real progress.
There are still those who think that it is too expensive and, indeed,
scarcely worth the trouble to provide help for children with delayed
development. In Jamaica we have shown that the cost per child can
be remarkably low (280 Jamaican dollars per child per year), that
there is no need for highly specialized staff since ordinary, well-
motivated, intelligent people can be trained for the work involved,
and that, with proper care and attention, children with delayed
development can become happy, useful, productive and indepen¬
dent adults. Marigold Thorburn
The Jamaican Early Childhood Stimulation Project for children
with delayed development relies for its success on close teamwork
between the child, the mother and the social auxiliary (below),
backed up by the doctor in the clinic. The auxiliaries visit the
children's homes once a week, but between visits the mothers
themselves continue the programme of educational stimulation
and training (opposite page).
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
and special education
for handicapped children
Photo Eduardo Gajeiro, Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Alarge proportion of the population
in all countries (10 to 15 per cent)
is affected by handicaps, whether
sensorial, motor or mental, which limit their
capacity to benefit from an ordinary educa¬
tion. The handicapped require an education
adapted to their potential, their capabilities
and their needs "special education" as it
has come to be called which will enable
them to develop their skills in order to
become full members of the society to
which they belong and to achieve personal
development towards independence.
Special education is thus the educational
component of rehabilitation. It is needed for
all those individuals who experience or are at
risk of experiencing significant and continu¬
ing difficulties in learning and in adjusting to
normal educational opportunities made
available to other persons.
It need hardly be said that special educa¬
tion has always been a matter of prime in¬
terest to Unesco, an interest that was
underlined in 1966 when at its 14th session
the General Conference of Unesco authoriz¬
ed the Director-General to "develop a pro¬
gramme in special education for handicap¬
ped children and young people on the basis
of voluntary contributions from Member
States."
Since then significant advances in
teaching techniques and important in
novative developments have taken place in
the field of special education, particularly
during the past decade, and much more can
be achieved in the teaching of handicapped
persons than was previously thought possi¬
ble. Many of these advances in teaching
techniques can be adapted to the needs of
developing countries with limited reserves of
materials and personnel.
In the light of these developments the
General Conference of Unesco, at its 20th
session held in October-November 1978, in¬
structed the Director-General to "formulate,
with the assistance of outside experts, a
comprehensive, long-range programme of
action designed to enhance the rights of all
handicapped persons to an appropriate
education which meets their needs and
aspirations".
As a first step an international meeting on
special education, attended by experts from
fourteen countries, was held at Unesco
headquarters in Paris in October 1979. The
experts drew up a statement of principles
by which Unesco's programme should be
guided.
Reaffirming the right of every child to an
education, the experts declared that the pur¬
poses and goals of education were essential¬
ly similar for all children, even though the
techniques required to help individual
children progress might be different. Some
children would require substantial modifica¬
tion of the educational programme while the
needs of others could be met by only minor
variations. Educational resources for han¬
dicapped students should be comparable to
those available for other students and ap¬
propriate to meet their special and often
long neglected needs.
The experts pointed out that while special
educational programmes would necessarily
entail additional expenditures and each na¬
tion was faced with the fact that it had insuf¬
ficient funds to meet all its purposes, the
costs of failing to provide early identification
and education of handicapped children and
subsequently to train those children and
place them in the work force were much
greater. Studies of rehabilitation and educa¬
tion programmes across the world showed
that the economic advantages from such
programmes in productivity, payment of
taxes by handicapped persons and reduced
need for welfare assistance and disability
stipends, outweighed the costs. Failure to
educate and train handicapped persons in
proportions equal to the provisions of ser¬
vices for the non-handicapped, because of
the problem being perceived as a lower
priority, resulted later in expensive pro¬
grammes to care for the untreated disabled.
Developing nations, as they formulated new
approaches to educating children, should be k
aware of the problem other nations had had |
WORLD CONFERENCE IN MADRID, NOVEMBER 1981
How can physically and mentally
handicapped persons best be given the
opportunity to become involved and
integrated into daily life as independent
and productive members of their
communities? This question, together
with the problem of the prevention of
handicaps, will be the focus of discussion
at a major international conference to be
held in Madrid later this year, from 2 to
7 November. The conference is being
prepared by Unesco in collaboration with
the Spanish Government and with the
help of the competent intergovernmental
and non-governmental organizations
(especially the United Nations, the World
Health Organization, the International
Labour Organisation and the United
Nations Children's Fund). The Madrid
Conference will be multidisciplinary in
nature and will provide a forum for a wide
exchange of experience, views and
information on the present state of
education for handicapped people and an
occasion on which "the main lines of
international action in favour of special
education and in favour of prevention, of
re-education and of assistance for the
physically and mentally handicapped will
be studied and defined".
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
( ¡n following this approach of giving a low
priority to the handicapped.
Special educational services should, the
experts declared, be tailored to meet the
assessed and agreed needs of the individual
student and should lead to clearly stated
curriculum goals and short-term objectives
which should be regularly reviewed and
where necessary revised. They should be
within reasonable travelling distance of the
pupil's home or residence except in special
circumstances where the pupil's needs
could not be met by these means. They
should be comprehensive, serving all per¬
sons with special needs irrespective of age
or degree of handicap. No child of school
age should be excluded from educational
provision on grounds of severity of handicap
or receive educational services significantly
inferior to those enjoyed by any other stu¬
dent. They should offer a range of choices
commensurate with the range of special
needs in any given community.
The experts devoted part of their discus¬
sion to the question of the integration of the
handicapped into the normal educational
system, a matter about which there is still
considerable controversy, which is reflected
in the articles on pages 16 and 20 of this
issue of the Unesco Courier.
Special education programmes would in
the future be found in a variety of settings,
with some disabled children able to par¬
ticipate in a regular school setting, while
others would require very intensive pro¬
grammes. There should be, as a basic
assumption underlying educational and
other efforts on behalf of the handicapped,
a commitment to integrating the disabled
person as fully as possible into the com¬
munity of non-handicapped persons.
History was replete with examples of un¬
necessary segregation of disabled, and con¬
sequent substandard treatment and
discrimination.
Integration of the handicapped into the
normal educational system was an increas¬
ingly common practice. Short - and long-
term studies showed that achievement
among handicapped people who were
educated in a specialized setting was no
greater than that of .those educated in
regular classes. The special class or school
tended from the outset to take a pessimistic
view of the pupils' potential, which under¬
mined their chances since they were inclined
to conform to this pessimistic ¡mage.
It was necessary to stress the positive ad¬
vantages of integration. With integration
there was less need for costly special
building and additional highly specialized
staff; in developing countries, educational
facilities were extended to more children; a
handicapped child adapted more easily to
living in ordinary society the earlier he or she
began to do so; the non-handicapped grew
up with the handicapped and learned to ac¬
cept them and their disabilities from the
beginning.
The experts pointed out, however, that
integration was not the answer to every
problem and it did not mean the mere
physical placement of handicapped children
in ordinary schools. It required very careful
planning and preparation of teachers, and
the development of support services.
Care should always be taken to ensure
that integration was in the best interests of
the child. For this reason the needs of each
individual child had to be considered, and
decisions made as to what type of educa¬
tional provision, given the options available,
would best suit him or her.
Finally, the experts stressed that, ¡n view
of the discrepancies in types and degrees of
handicaps as well as the diversity of condi¬
tions in different countries, there was a need
for a variety of appropriate educational pro¬
vision for handicapped children; some might
need special schools, others separate pro¬
grammes for part of the day or for certain
periods of their lives, while other children
could profit from a regular classroom with
some extra periods of instruction or help.
Countries would have to study what was
best suited to their conditions and develop
their strategies accordingly.
Photo La Nacion-Unesco
ACCESS TO WORKS
PROTECTED BY COPYRIGHT
In line with objectives of the International Year for Disabled Persons, Unesco has taken steps to
facilitate access by disabled persons to works protected by copyright.
A request has gone out to Member States to help meet a pressing need in developing countries
for printed works and audio-visual materials. Assistance is also being sought in arranging for the
holders of copyright to assign the reproduction, translation or adaptation rights for Braille
publications and audio-visual materials designed for handicapped persons on preferential terms
to publishers in developing countries.
A second programme has been undertaken jointly with the World Intellectual Property
Organization (WIPO) in co-operation with the World Council for the Welfare of the Blind (WCWB).
States party to the two major copyright Conventions, the Universal Copyright Convention and
the International Convention for the Protection of Literary and Artistic Works, administered
respectively by Unesco and WIPO, have been asked to consider questions relative to the free
flow of recorded and embossed reading materials for blind and physically handicapped readers.
Comments on a study prepared by the WCWB will be used as the basis for recommendations
aiming to define and harmonize international co-operation and provide the widest possible access
to materials for the visually handicapped. A similar study is being undertaken regarding the
problems facing the hard of hearing in co-operation with the World Federation of the Deaf.
INTERNATIONAL RESPECT FOR
THE RIGHTS OF THE DISABLED
What legal protection is offered to handicapped children by existing international instruments?
The answer to this important question can be found in La protection des Droits des
Personnes Handicapées par Différents Instruments Internationaux ('The Protection of the
Rights of Handicapped Persons by Different International Instruments"), which is being published
(in French! by Unesco later this year. (An abridged version in English is in preparation!. Most
international organizations have long been concerned, each in its own field of competence, with
promoting the rights of handicapped children. But the texts they have produced are scattered as
to their sources and of variable legal value. The Unesco publication presents analytical
assessments of international texts relating to the handicapped child in the fields of civil,
economic, professional, social and family life. Through this work Unesco is seeking to persuade
governments to ratify existing conventions and to respond to the need to generalize these rights
in a single international convention. Left, handicapped persons demonstrate in defence of their
rights in Costa Rica.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
r~
Photo i Bester Kanyama, Salisbury
Photo © Centre for Special
Education, Chimbóte, Peru
UNESCO'S CO-ACTION PROGRAMME AND THE
INTERNATIONAL YEAR OF DISABLED PERSONS
Unesco's Co-Action Programme, which offers individuals, groups and institutions the opportu¬
nity of participating in self-help community projects throughout the world, has decided,
during the International Year of Disabled Persons, to concentrate its efforts on providing
much-needed equipment and training facilities to schools and centres for the handicapped in
the developing countries. Photos show three of the many schools and centres receiving aid.
Above, the Waterfalls Centre, Zimbabwe, for children suffering from cerebral palsy; below
left, the Centre for Special Education at Chimbóte, Peru, a school for blind and deaf children
and for children with speech and learning problems, as well as those suffering from multiple
handicaps; below right, the Sri Sangwal School, Thailand, which accepts physically handicap¬
ped children from kindergarten to tenth grade. All these establishments are in urgent need of
funds and Unesco receives fresh requests for help every week. Anyone -individuals, groups,
institutions-can help, either by sending a donation in support of a particular project (Unesco
will supply a list of all the projects in hand) or by making a contribution, however small, to
Co-Action's General Fund. Administrative costs are borne by Unesco and the entire sum sent
will go to the project. You can also correspond directly with the people running the project
(Unesco will supply the address). Donations, as well as requests for further information,
should be sent to: Unesco, Co-Action Programme, OPI, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Photo Sudchit Bhinyoying, UNICEF
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Special schools
or integrated education?
/. 'The integration
of the handicapped
into society
can be best prepared
in special schools'
by Vladimir I. Lubovski
INTEGRATION is one of the most frequently discussed problems
of special education. The integration of handicapped children
into the normal education system has many supporters both
among workers in the field of special education and (especially)
among the parents of handicapped children, who are attracted by
the thought that their child will not be set apart in a special group
among his normally developing contemporaries.
At the same time, it must be said that an over-simplified concep¬
tion of integration an indiscriminate, superficial approach to the
problem is widespread. In many cases, the practical application of
this approach leads to no more than a mechanical solution of the
problems. The handicapped child is placed in an ordinary class in a
normal school, among normally developing contemporaries, and is
given the opportunity to spend a small amount of extra time with a
specialist in the education of persons with his kind of handicap. For
all the apparent attractiveness of the slogan "integration in educa¬
tion", the superficial approach cannot be considered as a step for¬
ward in special education.
To make this clear, let us look at the concept, and the goals and
problems, of integration.
First, since education in school represents only a small part of a
person's life, and a period during which he is not independent, what
is of greatest importance is his subsequent integration in society
when he is independent. The completeness and success of this in¬
tegration depend on how satisfactory the person's contacts and in¬
teraction turn out to be with those around him, at home and at
work.
For a handicapped person, the chances of establishing sound'rela-
tionshlps with other people and of becoming a successful worker
are, in their turn, governed by the extent to which he has been
prepared for such things by his education. This is a matter where it is
helpful to begin a pre-school education at the earliest possible age,
aimed at remedying the handicap, and where help is given by the
whole system of organization and work in special schools, which
takes account, for each particular kind of handicap, of the
peculiarities of the child's mental and physical development and of
his capabilities. In such a school, the child is one among equals. The
system is designed to develop the personalities of handicapped
children as comprehensively as possible.
When he is integrated into the ordinary education system, in the
sense of being placed in a normal school among normally developing
children, the handicapped child in effect finds himself in a situation
of inequality, in far more difficult circumstances than the other
children. Handicapped children are, as a rule, incapable of
assimilating subject-matter or of completing exercises at the same
rate as other children, and, in the circumstances we have described,
they are deprived of the necessary educational facilities and are
unable to obtain adequate training for employment.
In our opinion, the integration of handicapped children during the
period of their education must, under an advanced system of special
VLADIMIR I. LUBOVSKI, Soviet expert on special education for the han¬
dicapped, is head of the laboratory of children with educational difficulties at
the Institute of Defectology of the USSR A cademy of Pedagogical Sciences.
The author of many articles and several monographs on the problems of
special education, he is editor-in-chief of the Soviet monthly review Defec-
tologia.
16
education, be understood first and foremost as the incorporation of
special education into the ordinary education system. This in turn
implies that the sum of knowledge, habits and skills which the han¬
dicapped children will be asked to acquire must correspond to a par¬
ticular stage in the education of normally developing children. The
mentally handicapped are an exception in this respect, since,
because of their mental characteristics, there is a substantial part of
the curriculum of a normal school which they are incapable of
assimilating, even in specially created optimal circumstances.
The preparation of handicapped young people for integration into
society can be undertaken best in special schools. This is so
because, in a special school, the process of educating and bringing
up the child is carried out in its entirety by specially trained profes¬
sional teachers using special equipment and methods, at the speed
and in the order which are appropriate for each category of han¬
dicap. Where necessary, the curricula of special schools are sup¬
plemented by additional material. The schools have special
workshops with appropriate equipment and skilled instructors to
prepare the children for employment. It is only within the framework
of such schools that it is possible to organize specialized medical
care, including the necessary systematic remedial work.
In the USSR (where education is compulsory for all children, in¬
cluding of course the handicapped, medical care is free, and special
schools and pre-school institutions receive additional funds), ex¬
perience of the development of the special education system, in¬
cluding testing of the feasibility of incorporating individual handicap¬
ped children and individual classes for such children into ordinary
("normal") schools, has confirmed that the most effective means of
preparing handicapped children for their integration in society is to
educate them in a special school.
This does not preclude the possibility of educating in normal
schools individual handicapped children who, thanks to their
abilities, to their level of development, and to the fact that they are
equipped with special aids, are in a position to assimilate the lessons
on an equal footing with their normally developing classmates.
Given those conditions, handicapped young people (with the excep¬
tion of the mentally handicapped) are capable of going on to the
higher levels of the normal education system (specialized secondary
schools and higher educational establishments) once they have
completed their studies at the previous level in a special school
equivalent to the corresponding stage in that system.
While a child is being educated in a special school, the necessary
integration with normally developing children is ensured by means of
extra-curricular activities (games, excursions, club meetings and
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
various forms of amateur activity, etc.); during vocational training,
integration is ensured through practical work in a general production
unit.
Experience shows that, once they have acquired an adequate level
of general education and vocational training in a special school, han¬
dicapped young people are capable of working successfully on their
own. For example, the mentally handicapped prove capable, in ap¬
proximately 50 per cent of cases, of working successfully in jobs for
which they have received vocational training at school.
From an analysis of the problem, it can be said that genuine (as
opposed to mechanical) integration of the handicapped into the
general educational and social structure is possible, subject to cer¬
tain conditions.
The first of those conditions is the elimination by legislation of all
forms of discrimination that may exist against the handicapped in
society (in the field of law, this concerns particularly the regulations
governing access to employment). Due allowance must, of course,
be made for the limitations which the handicap in question imposes.
Thus, in the USSR secondary education for handicapped children is
prolonged from two to four years. The majority of the schools are
boarding schools, and the teaching and educational equipment are
provided by the State.
The second is the acquisition by the handicapped (with the excep¬
tion of the mentally handicapped) of a sound education (with no
omissions) to a level no lower than the State-wide mandatory stan¬
dard for normally developing young people. The Youth Employment
Commission, which sits on all local government bodies in thé USSR,
is bound to set aside, as a matter of priority, jobs for young han¬
dicapped persons.
The third is vocational training which will give the handicapped
the ability to work in industry today. Soviet specialized schools are
equipped with professional workshops which provide handicapped
young people with a training in various professions.
The fourth is the provision for the handicapped of supplementary
social security benefits which will, for example, give them extra
funds to meet certain needs associated with their handicap. The
Soviet State spends from three to five times more on the education
of a handicapped child in a special school than on a child in an or¬
dinary school.
The fifth condition, obviously, is to educate normally developing
children to have a proper attitude to people with handicaps. The
fulfilment of these conditions gives handicapped young people the
chance to pursue their studies at the higher level, and, when their
studies are completed, to find employment in all the spheres of
economic, cultural and scientific activity.
THE GIMBI SCHOOL FOR
THE BLIND, ETHIOPIA
In the early 1970s, a group of Ethiopian
church leaders, with the assistance of an
organization for the blind of the Federal
Republic of Germany, established a school
for the blind at Gimbi, in eastern Ethiopia.
The purpose of the school was to show
that, far from needing charity or pity, the
blind are fully capable of participating in all
spheres of life. High priority is therefore
given at Gimbi to preparing blind pupils for
life in their communities, teaching them
how to handle social and everyday tasks
and providing them with vocational
training. Top photo, arithmetic is taught
with the aid of special frames and
Japanese abaci, a gift from abroad. Centre
photo, two pupils examine the articles on
the class "discovery board". Bottom photo,
with the aid of a teacher, a pupil measures
part of the school building using a rule with
a slide made in the school workshops.
Photos Unesco. From a slide presentation of a Unesco project
on "Innovative information and examples of good practice in education
of the handicapped".
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The rights of menta
How far are t
The Declaration on the Rights ofMentally HandicappedPersons, proclaimedby the United Nations General
Assembly on 20 December 1971, marked an important step forward for the world's mentally handicapped.
One of the documents on which the UN Declaration was based was a "Declaration of Generaland Special
Rights of the Mentally Handicapped" which had been developed and adopted by the International League
of Societies for the Mentally Handicapped (ILSMHI. The League (now the InternationalLeague ofSocieties
forpersons with Mental Handicap) is a Brussels-based non-governmental organization which was founded
In 1960 to promote the Interests of the mentally handicapped. Its membership Is drawn from over 60
countries. A study carried out in co-operation with the League In 1974-1975 reached the conclusion that no
country in the world had then implemented alt the rights set forth in the UN Declaration for any of its
ARTICLE 1
The mentally retarded person has, to the
maximum degree of feasibility, the same
rights as other human beings.
Is the mentally retarded child provided with the same right to life,
including the same medical life-saving remedies at birth and later,
as another child?
Is the basic right to have a caring parent or parent surrogate,
who provides both nurture and advocacy, supported to the same
extent as for a normal child? Can a retarded child be adopted?
Is the retarded child entitled to education for at least the same
number of years as other children?
Is the mentally retarded adult permitted to vote unless he or she
has been specifically found ineligible under a general law specifying
when the franchise may be denied?
Is the retarded person given the same help and protection by the
police as are other citizens?
Is the retarded person advised of his rights and responsibilities as
a citizen in ways which he can understand?
the members of the police force oriented to understand the
retarded person's behaviour?
If charged with a crime, is the retarded person presumed inno¬
cent until proven otherwise? Is this presumption accepted by the
general public and the police?
groups of retarded persons or individuals often refused the
use of public premises such as playgrounds, buses, restaurants,
etc., simply on the grounds that they are "different" or perhaps
disconcerting to other clientele?
Is there any kind of "oversight agent" to assure that basic rights
are enforced?
ARTICLE 2
The mentally retarded person has a right to
proper medical care and physical therapy
and to such education, training, rehabilita¬
tion and guidance as will enable him to
develop his ability and maximum potential.
Is there a maternal and child health service which reaches all ex¬
pectant mothers and their infants with prenatal care, well-baby
care, and early intervention for infants who appear to be "at risk"?
Is the medical care given to infants and children who are known
to be handicapped of as high quality as is given to children believed
to be "normal"?
Is the same quality of dental care, immunization, routine screen¬
ing for hearing and vision impairments, and the like, provided for
retarded as well as for other children? Is this quality the same in
the various clinics, group practices and special residential facilities?
Do foster parents who care for retarded persons have access to
medical care for them of the same quality as they would expect to
secure for their own family members? Do foster children in fact
receive equal care?
retarded persons given doses of tranquilizing drugs in excess
of those given to persons not considered retarded? Is this done for
the convenience of the persons caring for them, to make them
more docile?
a mentally retarded person with an ordinary physical
disorder or disease requiring hospitalization be admitted and
receive the same quality of care, degree of attention to his comfort
and wishes, and the same privileges of having visitors, etc, as other
citizens having the same illness?
Are the rights of the retarded person respected to the extent that
he is encouraged to participate in decisions about his treatment to
the full degree of his understanding? Are explanations of conditions
and proposed treatments made to him in language he is most likely
to understand? If he cannot participate, is his parent or guardian
fully informed and consulted?
If there are free public schools for normal children, are there also
free school programmes especially suited to the needs of the
retarded of the same ages which are sufficient in quantity, quality,
geographical distribution and accessibility? If parents pay tuition for
normal children, do they have to pay more for education of their
retarded children? Are there provisions for even the most severely
and profoundly retarded who live at home?
the educational provisions for children in residential facilities
at least as extensive and suitable as for those living in natural
homes? And vice versa?
Is the education programme oriented toward developing social in¬
dependence (as far as possible) for the retarded person? Are there
programmes leading to appropriate employment in economically
valued jobs which actually exist in the economy of the country?
Does the fact of having been in a special school or class cause
discrimination in employment unrelated to the person's actual abili¬
ty to do the job?
Are there programmes for the proper preparation of teachers,
therapists, counselors and physicians to meet the needs of the pre¬
sent and future services?
ARTICLE 3
The mentally retarded person has a right to
economic security and to a decent standard
of living. He has a right to perform produc¬
tive work or to engage in any other mean¬
ingful occupation to the fullest possible ex¬
tent of his capabilities.
there barriers daws, attitudes) which prevent a mentally
retarded person from obtaining a job which he is capable of perfor¬
ming?
Are there circumstances under which he may be paid less than
another person for an equal amount of work?
persons in residential facilities who work regularly at tasks
which contribute to the running of the facility (janitorial work, kit¬
chen work, etc, beyond what would be their share in their own
homes) paid a fair wage for this work? Are they permitted to keep
at least part of their earnings for their personal use (rather than
paying it all toward the cost of food and shelter at the facility)?
If a retarded adult is unable to earn at least as much as would be
considered a "living wage" for another worker, is there a system
(social insurance, compensation) which permits him to receive a
regular income from public funds as a matter of right?
Is the social insurance or assistance benefit sufficient, consider¬
ing the additional costs of living which handicaps may impose?
Are there family allowances or "invalidity" allowances paid to the
parents (as well as foster parents) who maintain their child at
home, to assist them in meeting the extra costs of caring for such
a child, as compared to a normal child? Are similar allowances
available for disabled adults?
Is there a national health service or a national system of paying
for health care such that the services of hospitals, clinics, physi¬
cians, etc. are either free or available at a cost no greater than a
non-handicapped person would pay?
there adequate insurance (or other alternative) against
unemployment ? Does the mentally retarded worker have the same
rights as other workers?
If there are laws which require or favour the employment of han¬
dicapped peisons, are the mentally retarded also covered by these
provisions?
If the retarded adult needs further training (vocational or other
adult education) is it available to him on a basis at least com¬
parable to other persons?
ARTICLE 4
Whenever possible the mentally retarded
person should live with his own family or
with foster parents and participate in dif¬
ferent forms of community life. The family
with which he lives should receive
assistance. If care in an institution becomes
necessary, it should be provided in surroun¬
dings and other circumstances as close as
possible to those of normal life.
Do physicians, teachers and other professional persons who ad¬
vise the family give the family encouragement to keep their child
with them? Is practical help given to make this more feasible?
Are parents and foster parents respected as the people who have
the first responsibility for the care, nurture and education of their
retarded child as for their normal child?
Do professional people share their knowledge of the child's condi¬
tion and potentials for growth with the parents or foster parents,
and assist them to understand how to foster growth in accordance
with such potentials?
community recreation and leisure time facilities open to
retarded persons? Is any effort made to provide adapted program¬
mes (for example, special swimming fessons)? Are these facilities
physically accessible (free of architectural barriers) to retarded per¬
sons with physical handicaps? Are the churches and religious
organizations open and receptive to retarded persons? Are public
attitudes accepting of people who are different?
If residential care is provided other than in natural homes and
foster family homes, are the facilities homelike? Are they situated
in residential areas? Are the conditions of living such as to en¬
courage the retarded residents to become as personally indepen¬
dent as possible, and to make choices for themselves in respect to
activities, friends, articles of personal use, clothing, etc.? Does the
individual have a choice among alternative arrangements? Does
this include a choice to have a single room or to choose with
whom he will share quarters? If he is unable to make a choice for
himself, does his personal representative have an opportunity to do
so?
Do such facilities accommodate persons of both sexes? Are they
convenient to local transportation? Do the conditions encourage
the retarded residents to participate in community activities and to
behave in as culturally normative a way as is compatible with the
degree of handicap?
residential facilities distributed in the various residential
neighbourhoods so that there is not an excessive concentration in
any one area and so that the residents have opportunity for infor¬
mal interaction with neighbours and normal peer groups?
Are the families of residents actively encouraged to visit frequent¬
ly and informally the retarded member who is living away from
home? Does he have something to say about when and how he
visits them?
steps taken to minimize expressions of prejudice or
discrimination by neighbours toward retarded persons living
or moving into apartments, hostels, etc. in the community?
architectural barriers to persons with physical handicaps
reduced to a minimum?
there appropriate daytime activities outside the home for per¬
sons who are too handicapped to be employed for wages?
ARTICLE 5
The mentally retarded person has a right to a
qualified guardian, when this is required, to
protect his personal well-being and interests.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
lly retarded persons
hey observed ?
mentally retarded citizens, nor any of the rights fully for all of Its retarded citizens. Consequently, the
League set up a task group to prepare materials which would help its member societies to initiate steps
toward the implementation of these rights in their respective countries, the first step being to make a
careful analysis of the extent to which the rights were currently observed in practice. On this double page,
the Unesco Courier presents the text of the United Nations Declaration, accompanied by a series of
searching questions drawn up by the League's task group. We hope that these, questions will draw
Increased attention to the condition ofmentally handicappedpersons and will help readers to work out for
themselves how well each major right is being applied in their country.
Is there a formal procedure for determining whether a person is
impaired in such a way as to require a guardian (limited or plenary)
and does such procedure provide for (1) evidence to be presented
both for and against the finding, (2) legal representation for the
retarded person, (3) adequate professional evaluation of his specific
capacities and deficits relative to his making appropriate decisions
for himself in his own interest and according to his own
preferences?
Is the legal procedure to declare a mentally retarded person in
need of guardianship, or the actual appointment of a guardian, as
the case may be, costiy, or are provisions made for these pro¬
cedures to be carried out without cost to the person or his family?
a person identified as mentally retarded becomes of age, is
he necessarily presumed to be incompetent? Is he so treated by
parents and others without objective verification?
happens to a mentally retarded person when he is orphan¬
ed or has no family or is abandoned by his family? Are active in¬
terventions assured in this situation? Are there alternatives to ad¬
mission to an institution?
Are there available persons qualified to act as guardians of in¬
dividuals when no appropriate relative or friend offers?
there public or private agencies legally authorized to in¬
tervene on behalf of mentally retarded persons where their welfare
is threatened?
Do specific guardianship societies for the mentally retarded exist
independent of agencies providing care and training? Are there pro¬
grammes to assure the appointment of a guardian (limited or
plenary) if needed?
there other forms of public or private advocacy of retarded
persons apart horn or instead of, guardianship? Is there active
recruitment of volunteers to act as guardians or as "citizen ad¬
vocates"?
there any public officer who acts as guardian either in an
emergency or when no other is available?
Are the directors of institutions or other persons who serve the
retarded professionally considered ineligible to act also as guar¬
dians of their clients/patients?
there legal provisions to assure that the person entrusted
with the guardianship of a mentally retarded person does not
neglect the person or mismanage his funds? Are there special
follow-up programmes for mentally retarded people who have been
found in need of guardianship?
Is it possible to separate guardianship of the person and guar¬
dianship of property?
Are there provisions for "limited guardianship", i.e. assignment of
decision-making responsibilities to the guardian only to the extent
necessary in the individual case?
Is a seriously incapacitated person who has some residual capaci¬
ty to make decisions allowed to take advantage of that capacity?
ARTICLE 6 (first part)
The mentally retarded person must be pro¬
tected from every kind of exploitation,
degrading treatment and abuse.
Do the regular protective services for abandoned, neglected or or¬
phaned children extend equally to retarded children?
nurses, physicians and social workers show equal zeal in
reporting cases of child neglect or abuse, or malnutrition, etc. for
retarded children as for others? For those in institutions also?
Are professional protective workers instructed to deal with the
retarded and how to do it?
Are mentally retarded children or adults exhibited or exposed to
visitations by members of the public or by the press or professional
workers under circumstances which would be considered inap¬
propriate in a regular public school or hospital?
Are retarded pupils given the least desirable classrooms in the
school buildings, or usually expected to use buildings abandoned
for use by normal people?
"labeling" applied for purposes other than constructive
diagnosis and prescriptive programming or scientific study?
Are there places where the surroundings of the retarded persons
are made visibly humiliating such as by the use of bars on win¬
dows or by requiring the retarded persons to be seen by strangers
in inferior clothing, or not clothed?
Are reporters or comedians rebuked when or if they use insulting
language in referring to the mentally retarded, or if they make slur¬
ring jokes?
ARTICLE 6 (second part)
...If prosecuted for any offence, he shall
have a right to due process of law with full
recognition being given to his degree of
mental responsibility.
Is the mentally retarded person entitled to all the legal safeguards
due to any other citizen accused of a crime?
Is the person who is recognized as mentally retarded and who is
unable to understand police and judicial procedures afforded proper
assistance in the exercise of his rights?
Do the police receive any training and guidance in the recognition
and pre-trial handling of mentally retarded persons suspected of
crime?
Does the mentally retarded person have a right to the presence
of a lawyer, relative, or friend during the course of any police inter¬
rogation? Does he (or his guardian or parent) have an opportunity
to choose the person who will represent him?
Does he have a right to the guiding hand of counsel (lawyer) at
every stage of a criminal proceeding?
In any prosecutorial proceedings, is a person believed to be men¬
tally retarded entitled to a diagnosis and evaluation of his social
capability by qualified experts?
Does that evaluation include a determination as to whether he is
"fit to stand trial" Ce. mentally competent to understand pro¬
ceedings and assist his counsel in his defence)?
If found not fit to stand trial, is the retarded person entitled to a
reasonably prompt opportunity to have a trial or to have the
charges against him withdrawn?
if the retarded person (charged with crime but found not fit to
stand trial) is diverted to civil authorities on grounds of his alleged
dangerousness, is he entitled to proper legal safeguards to the
same extent as any other alleged "dangerous" person not accused
or convicted of any crime?
At a criminal trial, is the mentally retarded person entitled to the
defence of "diminished mental responsibility" or similar defence to
mitigate or excuse from punishment in such cases in which the
person lacked the mental capacity to form a criminal purpose, or
had some such degree of incapacity?
If convicted of a crime, or if otherwise placed in custody, is the
mentally retarded person entitled to receive treatment in the least
restrictive setting suited to his needs, his degree of responsibility
and the public's safety?
If placed under custody (except for a specified short period of
time), is he entitled to an automatic periodic review and a right of
appeal to independent, higher authorities?
ARTICLE 7
Whenever mentally retarded persons are
unable, because of the severity of their han¬
dicap, to exercise all their rights in a mean¬
ingful way or it should become necessary to
restrict or deny some or all of these rights,
the procedure used for that restriction or
denial of rights must contain proper legal
safeguards against every form of abuse. This
procedure must be based on an evaluation of
the social capability of the mentally retarded
person by qualified experts and must be sub¬
ject to periodic review and the right of
appeal to higher authorities.
Before any procedures to deny or restrict rights are initiated, are
other less restrictive or non-restrictive procedures fully considered,
such as those which provide him with counseling, advice, or social
and emotional support for his own decision-making and action?
Before any restriction is considered, is an evaluation made of his
social capabilities as related specifically to his ability to exercise the
right in question having in mind that many citizens are expected to
make decisions for themselves which do entail risk and which may
not always have the most desirable results? If rights are to be res¬
tricted, is the determination of need for such restriction preceded
by a careful evaluation of the retarded person's specific capabilities
which is carried out by experts in the evaluation of social compe¬
tence in persons who are mentally retarded? Is the expert evalua¬
tion interdisciplinary?
a person is found incapable of exercising certain rights, is
this finding based on essential protection, i.e. is the restriction
necessary to protect the individual himself or others from signifi¬
cant harm?
Is any restriction which is imposed limited only to the specific
activities (i.e. exercise of specific rights) in respect to which the
person has been found incapacitated, leaving to him those rights he
may prudently be allowed to exercise?
If some restriction is so required, is the restriction carried out in a
way which imposes the minimum degree of constraint needed to
accomplish 'its purpose? (i.e. limited guardianship rather than ple¬
nary guardianship; supervision rather than committment, commu¬
nity based rather than institutional care, if possible, etc.)
Does the retarded person, his family, or other interested person
receive prior notice in advance of any serious restrictive procee¬
dings?
Is the person, his family, or his friends entitled to the assistance
of advocates to act on behalf of the mentally retarded person in
any proceedings?
Does the retarded person have access to a qualified representa¬
tive (attorney, advocate) whose interests do not conflict with his
own?
Are the opportunities to ask for reconsideration or independent
review of any restriction, both at the time imposed and later,
appropriate to the degree and duration of the restriction? Is there
also automatic periodic review?
if the rights involved are fundamental ones, are the proceedings
judicial in character?
the mentally retarded person or his representative have
opportunities of submitting information to the tribunal, appearing
before it, and challenging information submitted by others?
Is the retarded person or his representative informed of his right
to appeal and given assistance, legal and otherwise, in exercising
that right?
Does the retarded person (or his natural advocate, e.g. relative,
general guardian) have a right to select the attorney or other per¬
sons who may represent him in such proceedings?
Congress Proceedings. 7th World Congress of
the ILSMH oh Mental Handicap. Edited by
Lebenshilfe für Behinderte, Österreichischer
Dachverhand © 1978 ILSMH
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Special schools
or integrated education?
77. 'Our task
is to bring
the retarded
into the community
from which
they have been
excluded'
by Marten Söder
AT the end of the 1960s, normaliza¬
tion and integration became
widely accepted watchwords for
those concerned with the welfare of mental¬
ly handicapped children. According to this
new approach, the mentally retarded were
to enjoy the same conditions as other
children, living with them and attending
their schools. This outlook was largely a
reaction to the formerly prevalent view
which had resulted in the segregation of
mentally retarded youngsters in special
schools and institutions.
The integrationist viewpoint contrasts
sharply with its predecessor not only on the
measures to be undertaken on behalf of the
handicapped but on other important points,
such as the definition of what constitutes a
handicap. According to the segregationist
thesis, mental retardation is an absolute,
unalterable defect and nothing can be done
about it. Mentally retarded people are defec¬
tive and the appropriate action is to separate
them from the rest of society. Segregation is
in any case part of the natural order of
things.
The integrationist position, on the other
hand, stresses that handicaps are relative, in
the sense that they only exist in relation to a
MARTEN SÖDER, Swedish sociologist working
with the Swedish Centre for Working Life, has
been involved for the last 8 years with questions
concerning the mentally handicapped in Sweden.
He has also participated as an expert in con¬
ferences sponsored by the United Nations and
OECD. His doctoral dissertation, "Organization of
Services, Ideologies of Care and Integration", is
being presented at the University of Uppsala this
month.
given environment. This approach is coup¬
led with a more dynamic, optimistic belief in
the potential of mentally handicapped peo¬
ple than the static pessimism of the segrega¬
tionist view. It holds that integration is the
"natural" condition, and that segregation is
caused by social and political decisions to
separate the handicapped from the non-
handicapped. Such decisions attach a label
to the handicapped which stigmatizes them
and limits their possibilities of living a "nor¬
mal" life.
Since segregation is created by social and
political decisions, so the integrationist
argument continues, then integration can be
brought about when the authorities take
measures which separate the handicapped
as little as possible from the non-
handicapped. In schools one might imagine
a kind of sliding scale of integration whereby
a handicapped child in an ordinary class is
"more integrated" than he or she would be
in a special class, while a special class form¬
ing part of an ordinary school is "more in¬
tegrated" than a special school.
In Sweden, integration of the mentally
handicapped has taken the form of "facility
integration", whereby special schools have
been assigned classrooms in ordinary school
buildings, as opposed to "individual integra¬
tion" whereby individual handicapped pupils
are taught in ordinary classes. During the
1970s, facility integration took place at a
rapid rate, and today over 90 per cent of
Sweden's special school classes are in¬
tegrated on ordinary school premises.
Before examining how successful this ap¬
proach has been, let us first examine the
idea of integration and its implications,
especially as they appear in the Swedish
context.
Many writers who have studied the ques¬
tion have made a sharp distinction between
a superficial, "organized" form of mixing
handicapped and non-handicapped persons
and a more genuine and psychologically
meaningful integration which they often
refer to as "social integration". The latter
assumes that social relations will be
established between the two groups, and
some writers also stress how important it is
in this respect that handicapped persons
should feel a sense of security in their rela¬
tions with others.
This distinction calls into question a fun¬
damental assumption of the integrationist
position, the belief that handicapped per¬
sons are segregated from the rest of the
community primarily by the special educa¬
tional measures taken on their behalf. But
surely this ignores the possibility that
segregationist mechanisms may also exist in
the "normal" environments in" which the
handicapped person may be placed. Here
the integrationist viewpoint runs the risk' of
romanticizing the real world by regarding it
as a welcoming community in which de¬
viants are automatically accepted in a "nor¬
mal" context when decisions are taken to
place them there. In the desire to abolish
segregative measures taken by the
authorities, the segregative measures of the
real world may be overlooked.
This leads to another point on which the
integrationist position is vulnerable to
criticism. This is its assumption that the in-
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Thomas Bergman, from Who Understands Us?, Liber publishers, Stockholm
tegration of mentally retarded children in
school is somehow synonymous with what
sociologists call their "societal integration",
their full integration into society as
adults or at any rate that there is no incon¬
sistency between these two processes. But
school, it might be argued, is not the same
as society. Integration Into the school,
therefore, cannot be the same as integration
into society. In response to this it is often
said that integration into school constitutes
a means to the end of societal integration.
One way of testing whether this is so in
practice is to examine the avowed alms of
schools regarding their mentally retarded
pupils. In the case of Sweden the results of
such an enquiry are illuminating. According
to Swedish law, special schools for han¬
dicapped children aim to "promote the
development of the pupils into harmonious
people and into competent and responsible
adults." In this respect there is no
divergence between the alms of the special
school and those of the ordinary com¬
prehensive school. However, other texts
relating to the curricula in the two types of
school tell a different story.
In the special school, the teacher is to
"endeavour to promote [the pupil's] per¬
sonal development", whereas in the com¬
prehensive school the aim is to "endeavour
to promote his personal maturity into a free,
independent and harmonious person."
Whereas the special school sets out to
"develop all aspects of the pupil, encourage
alertness, provide motivation for study and
work and promote emotional balance", the
pupils at the comprehensive school are to
"prepare themselves for their roles as active
citizens in the society of tomorrow." In the
special school, each pupil is to be brought to
"develop his various qualities and come to
terms with personal problems", whereas his
peers at the comprehensive school are "in
the long term to be a positively creative
power in the development of society."
This comparison between the aims of or¬
dinary comprehensive school education and
those of special school education makes it
clear that in Sweden at any rate the aims of
the special school centre more on the in¬
dividual than those of the ordinary school.
The special school sets out to produce well-
adjusted and "harmonious" mentally retard¬
ed adults who are able to cope with their
personal problems. The ordinary school sets
out to produce active, productive and
critical citizens who are capable of full par¬
ticipation -in society. Given this disparity of
aims, it is hard to see how integrating
special schools into the ordinary education
system can lead necessarily to societal in¬
tegration.
Another problem arising from the integra¬
tionist approach is its emphasis on social
goals at the expense of educational ones.
For although special education may not aim
at the societal integration of the handicap¬
ped, this does not mean that it has no aims
as regards the pupil's adult life. In order to
"promote the development of the pupils into
harmonious people and competent and
responsible adults", special demands are
made in the special school, such as "the
need to gear teaching to the individual level
and special characteristics of each pupil in
various areas of learning and training". The
special measures required consist of
creating smaller groups for tuition and pro¬
viding more resources than are usual in the
ordinary school system.
But these demands for specially arranged
learning situations always produce segrega¬
tion in some form or other. And so if we are
seeking to promote social integration, these
educational demands must be questioned.
Here there is an obvious conflict between
the alms of social integration and the educa¬
tional demands ensuing from the need to
produce "competent and responsible
adults". The integrationist view often
obscures this conflict of alms.
The conflict between educational and
social goals has not yet become acute in
Sweden, because integration has taken the
form of facility integration. This is one of the
conclusions which may be drawn from a
large-scale project to evaluate the integra¬
tion of special schools for the handicapped
into the ordinary school system which was
recently carried out by the department of
sociology at the University of Uppsala. A
number of different concepts, each describ¬
ing a different kind of integration, were for¬
mulated as a starting point for our studies.
We differentiated between four forms of in¬
tegration: physical, functional, social and
societal.
By physical integration we mean the
reduction of the physical distance between
the mentally retarded and the non-retarded.
By functional integration we mean the
reduction of the functional distance bet- 1
ween the two groups when they use dif- 1
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
, ferent equipment and resources. Functional
integration is therefore a question of the
joint utilization of resources.
Social integration entails a reduction in
the social distance between the two groups.
Social distance implies both lack of contact
and the psychological feeling of being cut
off. The mentally retarded are socially in¬
tegrated if they form part of a community
with non-retarded persons, come into
regular and spontaneous contact with them,
and feel themselves to be a natural part of
the group.
Societal integration refers to adults, as in¬
dicated above, and signifies that the mental¬
ly retarded have, as adults, the same access
to resources as others, the same opportuni¬
ty to influence their own situation, have a
productive working role, and form part of a
social community with others.
By using these terms we were able to
describe various aspects of integration in
terms of physical distances and of the extent
to which resources were jointly used by both
handicapped and non-handicapped. This
conceptual framework also enabled us to
bring into focus the problems involved in
relating physical and functional integration
on the one hand, and social and societal in¬
tegration on the other. And this, as shown
by the above critique of the integrationist
view, is a matter of particular urgency.
In Sweden, facility integration has first
and foremost taken the form of physical In¬
tegration. To some extent it has also involv¬
ed the special school and the ordinary
school making use of joint resources. Facili¬
ty integration has thus been associated with
a degree of functional integration.
Any more advanced form of functional in-
tegraiton in the shape of co-operation at the
teaching level has, however, been a relative¬
ly rare occurrence. With respect to social in¬
tegration, in general it can be said that this
has not taken place.
Thus one of the big question marks con¬
cerning the integration of special schools in
Sweden is why so little co-operation and
social contact has developed from the
"base" formed by facility integration. For
such co-operation is usually sporadic, con¬
sisting of joint activities of an exceptional
nature.
Nevertheless, school staff were con¬
sistently favourably disposed towards full-
scale co-operation between the two types of
school. From a study of fifty . integrated
schools, it emerged that approximately 80
per cent of teachers in both the ordinary and
the special school were in favour of co¬
operation in one of the practical subjects.
Even though there may be a difference bet¬
ween expressing a favourable attitude on a
questionnaire and accepting the conse¬
quences in practice, it would seem to be a
simplification to blame the low occurrence
of co-operation on lack of interest on the
part of the teachers.
Perhaps one reason why there has not
been more co-operation is that co-operation
has been regarded only as a subsidiary goal
of integration. Instead, the emphasis has
been laid on promoting physical integration
and the co-ordination of certain resources.
There has been surprisingly little discussion
of how facility integration affects the actual
educational work within the special school.
It is difficult to make any general
assessments about social integration in the
22
facility-integrated school. But it we were to
attempt to characterize the social relations
between special school and ordinary school
pupils, they might best be described as "ac¬
cepting indifference". The mentally retarded
pupils were, as a rule, accepted by their
peers in the ordinary school. There was vir¬
tually never any systematic harassment or
bullying. But more positive relations were
also uncommon. Facility integration has not
resulted in any actual social Integration.
However, the "normal" school environ¬
ment is in itself poorly suited to social In¬
tegration of the mentally retarded. Social
contact between pupils is largely along class
lines, and contact between school classes at
different levels ¡s uncommon. The lack of In¬
tegration of mentally retarded pupils must
be seen in this light.
Another factor which renders social In¬
tegration more difficult is that the special
schools have such large catchment areas.
"Normal" children attend the same school
as their friends at home, at least at the
primary and middle levels. By and large the
same children mix together at school and ¡n
their leisure time at home. Mentally retarded
pupils often have long journeys to school.
The non-retarded friends they have at home
go to other schools, and their friends at
school live near the school. This is a fact
which also makes it more difficult for men¬
tally retarded pupils in the same class to
meet during their leisure time.
The conflict between educational and
social goals really comes to a head,
however, where individual integration is In¬
volved the mentally retarded pupils
go into ordinary classes. This is generally
regarded as the most far-reaching form of
integration. Although the underlying
assumption is that putting a handicapped
child in an ordinary class automatically leads
to him or her becoming "socially
integrated", in a sense integration of this
type also means that the mentally retarded
pupil is confronted with the segregative
mechanisms existing in the class.
At the same time, when individual in¬
tegration is pursued, the conflict between
the possible gains that might be made ¡n
social relations and the educational
demands made by the curriculum becomes
manifest. The "normal" school environment
articulates and puts a premium on those
very intellectual achievements which the
mental disability of the retarded pupil does
not allow him to produce. As in the case of
social segregation, it ¡s the "normal" school
environment which operates in a segregative
manner.
Dictionary definitions of the term integra¬
tion tell us that ¡t means uniting separate
parts in a whole. According to the integra¬
tionist view, the detachment of the mentally
retarded as a "separate part" arises as a
result of social and political decisions and
the special educational measures which are
taken by the authorities. Our task, uniting
the parts into a whole, consists in bringing
the retarded into the community from which
they have been excluded. But this view
disregards the fact that segregation takes
place in our society and in our schools ir¬
respective of such official action: the educa¬
tional and social measures of segregation
are a part of the reality of the "normal"
school. The problems in what we have call¬
ed the integrationist view arise from a
refusal to accept that this is the case.
I Marten Söder
3 Photos Unesco. From a slide presentation of a Unesco project
on "Innovative information and examples of good practice
in education of the handicapped".
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
1 Francesco (standing beside blackboard) is a victim
of Down's Syndrome and suffers from mental
retardation and serious visual and speech
impairment. He is one of the 70,000 Italian
handicapped pupils who attend ordinary schools.
He is 12 years old and attends a first grade class in
a lower secondary school. A pupil seated at the
teacher's desk is explaining to the class the work
he has done on the blackboard. When Francesco
starts to interrupt him a girl goes up to Francesco
and persuades him to go back to his place. She
does this by touching him and showing
acceptance and affection. The teacher, who is
sitting at the back of the class, does not intervene.
2 Francesco also participates in manual activities.
Here he is seen holding a cardboard box steady
while a classmate cuts it out. They are making
cylinders of different sizes for a geometry lesson.
3 Realizing that he is unable to follow the outline of
a drawing correctly, Francesco asks a classmate
to help him. He takes the girl's finger, puts it on
his paper and says: "You are the train and I am
the bicycle that runs after the train. "The girl
traces the outline of the drawing with her finger
while Francesco follows her finger with his pencil.
4 Using a mattress, Francesco has built himself a
"hut" to which he withdraws when he wants to
be alone. He goes to the hut to read while the rest
of the class continues with the lesson.
Living and learning together
«if
V «
. to
%
Photos © Martin Knutsson, Munkhatteskolan, Malmö
Just over three years ago the primary and
secondary schools at Munkhatteskolan, near
Malmb, Sweden, began to integrate handicapped
pupils into their ordinary classes. They now have a
total of twenty handicapped children, with two or
three in each class. Specially adapted vehicles
transport the handicapped pupils to and from
school. Some pupils have up to an hour's journey
in each direction.
Although some modifications have been made to
the school buildings to enable handicapped pupils
to get around more easily. It has not been
necessary to make any major alterations to the
classrooms. The disabled pupils are, however,
provided with desks adapted to their special needs
and, where necessary, with aids such as electric
typewriters and reading lamps equipped with
magnifying glasses.
From the start, the handicapped pupils were very
well received by their classmates and relations
between them have remained extremely good,
both in the classroom and during leisure periods
when they can often be seen playing together.
A gymnastics department has been created at
Munkhatteskolan to enable the handicapped
pupils to follow courses prescribed for them by
specialists. They also take part in the ordinary
physical training classes even if they cannot
participate in all the exercises.
^^J
£*4i W. 0M
If wy À
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Communities
that care
by Mahfoud Boucebci
SPECIAL education is not, whatever
the term may suggest to the con¬
trary, a distinct, separate form of
education designed to produce social "out¬
siders". Nor is it a single, monolithic activi¬
ty, for the notion of "mental handicap"
covers a wide variety of conditions.
Special education must give permanent
consideration to the place of the mentally
handicapped in society today and tomor¬
row. When choosing an educational system
for the handicapped, preference should be
given to the one which is least likely to
relegate them to a social backwater. As it
happens, this type of system is best suited
to the conditions and resources of the
developing countries.
Furthermore, it would be very dangerous
to establish a system of special education
that excludes the family, for unless the fami¬
ly is made fully aware of the problems and
allowed to participate in the care and train¬
ing process, the disabled will rapidly become
a marginal group completely alienated from
and rejected by the community.
On the basis of these principles, various
models of special education may be drawn
up for the different age-groups. For very
young children, the largest and most
neglected group in the Third World, any
break with traditional ways of stimulating
and caring for infants must be avoided. The
fact that specialists are available should not
cut the child off from its mother or family.
Educators working with disabled children
must thus be thoroughly familiar with the
most widely used traditional methods of
child care, as well as the place of the han-'
dicapped in the traditional culture. The first
risk to be parried is that when an infant is
found to be handicapped it will be rejected
by its family.
Motor-sensory stimulation sessions in
which several mothers and children take part
have proved a practical and useful method,
for they develop a relationship based directly
on traditional community relations which is
a source of encouragement and mutual
assistance.
Two lines of approach have been
developed in work with young handicapped
children in the Algiers area.
The first involves groups of children of the
same size or at the same level of intellectual
development. Initially, children with serious
human relations problems or those deprived
of autonomy of movement are excluded
from these groups. But as a general rule
every effort is made to provide care and
training for disabled children in nursery
schools for "normal" children.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Information campaigns have helped to
make the staff of these institutions aware of
the plight of handicapped children, and it
has been possible to place them alongside
normal children. We have been able to do
this with certain children suffering from
Down's syndrome, certain deaf children,
children suffering from motor cerebral defi¬
ciency, epileptic children whose fits have
been brought under control,' and epileptics
with or without slight mental de¬
ficiency or a motor-neurological deficiency.
Placing these children in a "normal" en¬
vironment was not easy in the early days.
There were very few nursery schools and re¬
quests for admission were many. At the
same time, failure to recognize the problems
raised by handicaps, as well as false ideas
and prejudices reinforced the often negative
ideas of some of the teachers. However, in¬
formation sessions organized during the pre¬
school teachers' training courses helped to
make the staff aware of these problems and
to dedramatize the situation.
But the fact remains that the admission of
disabled children to ordinary nursery schools
is only successful with certain categories of
disability, for there is always a risk that
disabled children will be left out of things. If
they are too abnormal or raise too many
problems they will be rejected, with
traumatic consequences both for them and
for their families.
For the other categories of pre-school
children we have adopted a second ap¬
proach in the form of experimental "district
centres". These centres do not have
elaborate facilities, they are near the
children's homes, and they call for participa¬
tion on the part of the parents. The key to
this type of education ¡s continuity as the
child grows older, either in the same institu¬
tion or in another school where the basic
principles of the district centre continue to
be applied.
The parents must be involved in
educating their child, and there must be an
incentive for them to join in the activities of
the various associations and societies for the
handicapped. Where these possibilities do
not exist, parents should be kept informed
of the many ways in which they can, help
their child, for paradoxically such oppor¬
tunities are often neglected. The family can
be told what progress to expect in the short,
medium and long term, and informed about
the possible advantages of certain types of
specialized training, or about whether
medication is required. One vital point that
needs to be stressed to the parents is that
progress may take time, perhaps even a very
long time.
Finally, we believe that some types of
handicap should always be accommodated
within the normal educational system for
example, a class for blind children in an or¬
dinary school.
The role of institutions such as district
centres is decisive for young children and
adolescents who are "not capable of
benefiting from a scholastic education".
These children can only be treated if the
family and community are prepared to ac¬
cept the handicap and recognize that it is
impossible for them to attend school. The
day centres, with relatively small premises
and simple but functional equipment, can
each accommodate between thirty and forty
Jocal children aged four to thirteen. Children
with multiple handicaps are admitted provid¬
ed that they are affected with minor motor
or sensory handicaps connected with men¬
tal deficiency. Bedridden children and those
with serious personality disorders are not ac¬
cepted. Each centre has between eight and
twelve teachers.
The centres do not aim to provide an
academic type of education. Their activities
are directed towards educating the child in
the broadest sense, and all their activities are
in some way educative. They include:
training for dally life, such as washing
and dressing oneself; household chores
such as laundry, cooking or gardening; .
activities designed to promote better
knowledge of the environment including the
discovery of nature: walks in the district,
visits to the local market, to a public garden,
a festival or cultural event, a swimming
pool, pony club, the beach and the moun¬
tains. Through experiences like these the
child is helped to make progress and ac¬
quires greater independence and ease in
social relationships;
educational games, weaving, carpentry,
sewing and odd jobs about the house which
are designed to develop sensory and manual
skills;
self-expression activities such as playing
with water, sand, clay, paints and puppets,
as well as music (singing and playing in¬
struments) and psycho-motor activities;
the rest of the child's life at the centre
breaks, meals, rest periods, etc.
This broad range of activities gradually
leads to improvements in the child's speech,
in the level of his practical and motor-
sensory intelligence, and the integration of
his bodily functions, and helps to develop
his capacity for observation and expression
so that he can participate more actively in
the life of the community.
Pre-school and school activities that re¬
quire abstract thought are only introduced
for children who possess this capacity. The
methods used are always based on concrete
experience and take account of each child's
individual learning rhythms and capabilities
as well as his staying power.
Each pupil's progress is recorded in detail
on special attainment and observation
cards. This enables the teacher to pinpoint
each child's specific problems and needs
and to adjust his tuition accordingly.
The parents have an opportunity to meet
the educational team every morning and
evening and are often in contact with the
psychologists. Regular parents' meetings
are also organized, and as members of the
parents' association the parents are en¬
couraged to play an active role.
The atmosphere in the centres is generally
very relaxed. Children, teachers and other
staff members form one big family within
which the child can develop in a secure en¬
vironment and gradually become capable of
more sustained effort. The centre may offer
advantages over the home environment in
particular nourishing meals provided
freewhich help to promote the child's
overall development.
Whatever the stage at which responsibili¬
ty is assumed for a child, the objective is
that he should be integrated into the com¬
munity. And so, to avoid any break in the
training process, vocational training centres
and workshops should be planned right
from the start.
The social situation in the developing
countries and the vast number of children
and young people in relation to the popula¬
tion as a whole make it imperative to provide
care and training for these age groups.
But the structures outlined here and the
approaches on which they are based should
not be exclusive: other approaches should
also be fostered. Craft work seems to be one
of the most promising types of activity
its possibilities for developing human
relations open to certain categories of the
mentally handicapped.
The handicapped are still excluded from
many cultural and leisure activities, especial¬
ly in sport, where much remains to be done
to make people aware of the needs of the
handicapped. Swimming, for example, is
one of the most beneficial activities for some
handicapped persons, but paradoxically a
handicap often rules out admittance to
swimming pools.
Generally speaking, the independent
African States have retained the main bulk
of earlier legislation concerning the han¬
dicapped, and this is now outmoded. If
jurists and sociologists could collaborate
with educators and medical and health of¬
ficials in the study of these problems, then it
would be possible to review existing legisla¬
tion and make further provisions for preven¬
tion, care and treatment of the mentally han¬
dicapped and the furtherance of their rights
to special education and to their rightful
place in the community.
MAHFOUD BOUCEBCI, ofAlgeria, is professor
of psychiatry at the university of Algiers and
department head at the university psychiatric
clinic. He has published many articles related to
problems of mental deficiency and, more
specifically, to the question of mental health in
developing countries. A synthesis of his work ap¬
peared in Psychiatrie, Société et Développement
("Psychiatry, Society and Development")
Algiers, 1979.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Sounds from silence
China's deaf children find a voice
by Li Hongtai and Shen Jiayin
IN old China the severely deaf, who cannot hear spoken language
and thus fail to develop the power of speech, were subjected
to widespread discrimination and deprived of the chance to be
educated.
Today attitudes have totally changed. Education is provided for
the deaf ¡n schools whose target is to help their students to achieve
all-round development.
Methods also have evolved. In the old days most teaching was
done by means of gestures and facial expressions. This hindered the
development of the students' ability to handle language and express
their ideas.
To improve the education of the deaf, the Ministry of Education of
the Central People's Government decided in 1954 to launch pilot
speech teaching projects in certain schools for the deaf in order to
develop the pupils' oral ability. Two years later, it was decided to
start oral teaching in all schools for the deaf throughout the country.
The basis of this speech teaching is the Chinese Phonetic
Alphabet. This alphabet has a comparatively small number of letters
and is worked out in accordance with the phonemes, or speech
sounds, of putonghua, the common speech of the Chinese
language. It makes it easy for deaf children to learn pronunciation.
The teaching materials used combine the study of transliteration
with recognition of characters and words. The children learn to
recognize characters and words and study the language on the basis
of the learning of pronunciation. This approach overcomes the
obstacles caused by the fact that the same Chinese character can
represent a number of different sounds.
Whenever a new letter is introduced in the textbook, it is il¬
lustrated with diagrams and pictures of lip-rounding. The teacher
demonstrates the position of the tongue and the lip movements
while the pupils use mirrors to watch and imitate. Some letters are
aspirated, some are not. The pupil is made to feel the difference by
placing the back of his or her hand in front of the mouth to feel for
the air flow. Some sounds are made with the vocal cords vibrating,
others are not. The pupil learns to distinguish between them by
touching the teacher's throat or his own. In a word, the pupil's
senses of sight and touch, as well as his sixth sense, are brought ful¬
ly into play to help him or her to grasp the correct way to articulate
each letter.
The thinking of deaf children is necessarily linked to visual images
and acts. It is thus essential that the teachers demonstrate real ob¬
jects and use their histrionic gifts to the utmost. It is equally impor¬
tant that the meaning of the words should not be misunderstood. In
the case of words or phrases that are difficult to define clearly, pupils
are encouraged to apply them to real-life situations.
It is mainly through lip-reading that the pupils learn new things.
However, this does not work with certain sounds such as ge, ke,
and he. It is hard to distinguish between these sounds unless lip-
reading is backed up by other means. So far the major tool used for
this is the hand alphabet formulated in accordance with the Chinese
Phonetic Alphabet. This alphabet is part of the syllabus in schools
for the deaf because it can be used to express all the syllables in the
LI HONGTAI, of China, is dean of Peking's No. 1 school for the deaf. He
helped to produce the first set of Chinese textbooks for the deaf, and is a
correspondent with two periodicals for the deaf, The Deaf in China and
Newsletters for the Education of the Deaf.
SHEN JIAYIN, of China, teaches at Peking's No. 4 school for the deaf, and
was formerly on the staff of the Shanghai school for blind children. She is
also concerned in the editing of textbooks used in schools for the blind, deaf
and dumb, anda correspondent with The Deaf in China and Newsletters for
the Education of the Deaf.
f^b^U¿)
Chinese language. By looking at the diagram, forming the hand
alphabet with his fingers, and uttering the sound with his oral cavity,
the pupil is using three sense-organs at a time. This imprints what he
is learning more firmly on his memory and also helps to reinforce his
grasp of ways of articulation.
Nevertheless, this hand alphabet has certain drawbacks when it is
used to spell out a syllable which ¡s usually made up of three
phonemes. This means making a large number of finger
movements, which might be acceptable when spelling out words,
but not when it comes to sentences. Accordingly, some teachers
began to think of the possibility of using a manual alphabet to spell
out syllables instead of single phonemes. In collaboration with
specialists from the Chinese Written Language Reform Research In¬
stitute, we have designed a system for finger-spelling syllables one
at a time in which both hands are used (see diagram this page).
A pilot programme using these "manual syllables" is being carried
out in a small number of schools, and the preliminary results suggest
that they are easy to use. The changes in lip and finger movements
are closely co-ordinated, and sign language thus becomes more sim¬
ple, expressive and vivid in supplementing speech.
Thus the approach to speech training for deaf pupils which we are
now beginning to systematize is.based on oral teaching. Other forms
of expressing language are used in support, and training in the use
of the written language is reinforced.
H Li Hongtai and Shen Jiayin
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Eloquent hands enable a deaf Chinese youth to bring a smile to the face of his
deaf companion. In China manual systems of communication (opposite page)
are used in support of oral teaching for the deaf, to help them overcome their
additional handicap of speech difficulties.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Blind workers assembling books in Braille in an Indian publishing house.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Self-reliance
and the right to work
by Ed. Sackstein
A major purpose of the 1981 Interna¬
tional Year of Disabled Persons is to
turn the spotlight on the handicapp¬
ed and help remove the prejudice and
discrimination which bar their way to "full
participation and equality" the UN theme
for the Year.
In most situations, these two goals can¬
not be achieved unless the disabled get the
opportunity to become self-supporting and
to participate in active economic life.
It means training and jobs. This, of
course, is easier said than done, for the alar¬
ming fact is that despite all efforts and ap¬
peals for aid, the outlook for handicapped
people is as bleak as ever.
The majority of the world's disabled300
million live in developing countries which
also have a backlog of over 300 million
jobless or underemployed citizens.
To contemplate the possibility of placing
many disabled in the open labour market is
for most, therefore, just a pipe dream.
Consequently, the International Labour
Organisation's main efforts have been
directed towards the setting up of produc¬
tion workshops on small-scale industry
lines, small business co-operatives and self-
employment schemes for Third World
disabled.
Nine in every ten of these people live in
isolated rural communities and, for them,
the ILO's efforts are directed to teaching
practical skills for everyday life rather than a
specific trade for which there may be little
demand, if any.
In the industrialized countries, the current
economic slump has thrown some 17 million
people out of work, but no group is having a
tougher time in the tight job market than
disabled men and women who often are the
first fired and last hired.
ED. SACKSTEIN, of the United States of
America, is deputy chief of the Vocational
Rehabilitation Branch of the International Labour
Organisation, Geneva. A specialist in vocational
rehabilitation training and psychotherapy, he has
special responsibility for developing vocational
rehabilitation programmes for the mentally ill and
for drug-dependent persons as well as for work
on the prevention of alcoholism and drug addic¬
tion at the workplace.
In some places, their rate of unemploy¬
ment is twice that of able-bodied persons.
Because of sex bias, the situation is doubly
difficult for disabled females.
Experience has shown that protective
legislation which alms at promoting employ¬
ment of disabled people can help but that it
is no panacea. In the United Kingdom, for
example, the quota system has proved to be
relatively ineffective in a depressed labour
market situation.
Designated employment and reserved
jobs programmes, even if implemented, pro¬
vide little relief. Moreover, the jobs in ques¬
tion are usually menial, low-paid and of low
status.
ILO specialists say that legislation concer¬
ning employment of the disabled would
have a better chance to be effective if, in¬
stead of being coercive, it were more flexible
and formulated in such a way as to stimulate
private and government initiative.
Some countries pay grants and
allowances to employers who offer training
to disabled persons at the workplace. This is
a positive development which should be en¬
couraged further, together with financial in¬
centives to make ergonomie and other job
adaptations that facilitate and increase the
performance of disabled workers.
In Sweden, the so-called "adjustment
groups", sponsored jointly by management
and labour, are helping in many enterprises
to secure alternative employment for dis¬
abled people. Similar programmes are
underway in Poland and Norway.
In other forms of vocational rehabilitation
training, it is essential that the skills being
taught are geared not only to the present-
day needs of the labour market but also to
future requirements resulting from
technological and structural change.
Furthermore, vocational rehabilitation
specialists must Increasingly and directly
plug in to the world of work if they wish to
meet the challenge of preparing disabled
persons in appropriate and realistic ways. It
might be necessary for rehabilitation profes¬
sionals to shed some of their traditionally
"humanitarian" approach in favour of one
which is tempered by the hard realities of
the market place. The disabled are showing
professionals and the non-disabled every
day that they have enormous energy and
potential to accomplish far more than was at
one time thought possible. They therefore
deserve and have the right to more oppor¬
tunities to realize that potential.
There is also a certain danger in over-
reliance on professionals. Over recent years
vocational rehabilitation specialists have
developed their field of work into a highly
specialized discipline and the extensive
research they have undertaken has yielded
positive and often exciting results. This has,
however, had the unfortunate consequence
that the disabled, their families and the
general public have come to believe that on¬
ly the specialists can find solutions to their
social and employment problems
When helping people with disabilities, or
any group in a community with particular
difficulties for that matter, higher priority
should be given to encouraging each com¬
munity to take on part of the challenge itself
and to come up with simple workable solu¬
tions. This means contacting employers'
groups, trade unions, employment ex¬
changes, vocational schools, the press and
private groups (such as, for example, con¬
cerned parents or citizens who have a direct
interest in the problem). But let us by no
means forget to include the direct participa¬
tion of the disabled themselves in planning
and implementing programmes on their own
behalf.
In this context the new concept of voca¬
tional training developed by the ILO, and
known as "Modules of Employable Skills",
holds great promise of improved employ¬
ment opportunity for the disabled.
The key to this system and its unique
feature is creating completely self-contained
training packages or modular
units around each useful function and
limited to the essential skills, knowledge and
aptitudes required to perform a task. The
relevance of this infinitely variable and flexi¬
ble approach to training and employment of
the disabled is obvious; for it allows the
training and reintegration of those severely
handicapped who can only undertake a
limited range of activities.
An important objective of all ILO voca- k
tlonal rehabilitation projects in developing f
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
, countries is to try and ensure that they
become self-sufficient and that they are
profit-oriented right from the start.
An ILO expert, Edward Johnson, who has
wide experience with rehabilitation pro¬
grammes in the Third World, states that one
purpose of rehabilitating a disabled person is
to make a taxpayer out of him.
"This helps to convince governments,
although that is not the main reason", he
explains. "The object is to turn the disabled
person into a self-reliant citizen, standing
shoulder to shoulder with the able-bodied
members of the community. Nothing gives
disabled men and women the confidence
they need as does the knowledge that they
are doing a job of work, paying their
taxes..."
Rehabilitation of the disabled does pay off
in hard cash terms. For example, US Depart¬
ment of Labor statistics show that for every
$1,000 invested in the rehabilitation of a
disabled person $35,000 will be generated by
that person's work during his lifetime, part
of which goes to Federal and State taxes.
Even more impressive, it is estimated that
the employment of 100,000 disabled persons
in the US adds at least $500 million to the
GNP. And disabled persons who are
economically independent do not burden
community public assistance funds.
If present trends continue, and unless
resolute remedial action is taken, the
number of handicapped people seeking help
might swell to some 800 million by the turn
of the century. Among them will be an in¬
creasing number of people whose disability
is an extreme difficulty in adjusting to
existing social norms. In addition to the
mentally ill this number will include drug ad¬
dicts and alcoholics.
"The question of how to tackle the for¬
midable challenge of helping the world's
disabled is not one of policies or ap¬
proaches", says ILO Director-General, Fran¬
cis Blanchard. "These exist, we have
developed them. What is lacking, however,
is the political will to act and putting it
quite bluntly money.
"ILO experts have calculated that in order
to help stem the tide, the world would have
to find a minimum of 25 additional cents to
spend on each disabled person annually or
in total some $100 million a year.
"This at least would help to establish pilot
vocational rehabilitation programmes in
those countries where no such services ex¬
ist; equally important, it would provide the
means to set up some sub-regional and
regional training centres where much-
needed specialized staff could be trained.
"It is a modest, realistic goal", Mr. Blan¬
chard adds. "And if the term human dignity
has any meaning at all, these 25 cents
should certainly be found."
H Ed. Sackstein
KIDS ON THE BLOCK
Renaldo Rodriguez, 10 years old, is almost totally blind; Mark
Reilly, 11 years old, has cerebral palsy and gets around in a
wheelchair, his "cruiser" as he calls it; Melody James, 9 years old,
suffers from nothing more than short-sightedness and is very
curious about her more severely handicapped friends. All three
(inset), together with Ellen Jane, 17 years old, who has Down's
Syndrome and works as an assistant to a veterinarian, and B renda
Dubrowski, 10 years old, a "normal" child with a weight problem
(pictured performing below), plus Mandy Puccini, 12 years old and
deaf (not shown), are members of an amazing troupe of puppets
whose purpose is to help children to develop positive attitudes
towards people with disabilities. Created by Barbara Aiello, a
former teacher of handicapped children and a writer on special
education, the "kids on the block" are three feet tall and wear real
children's clothes and shoes. Mrs. Aiello believes that "children
will talk more readily to puppets than to adults or even to other
children" and that the integration of handicapped children into
regular classrooms fails less often because of their disabilities than
because of the other children's attitudes. "Kids on the Block" has
two important goals. "First", says Mrs. Aiello, "I want to teach
children about handicaps in a non-threatening fashion. Second, I
want to show non-handicapped children how to develop positive
relationships with their handicapped peers. The puppets show
them how they can be friends."
Photo Marcel Salvaro. Unesco
Photo inset © Kids on the Block, Inc., Washington, D.C,
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Disabled characters
in search of an author
by Tordis Orjasaeter
Photo Laurence Brun © Petit Format, Paris
TORDIS ORJASAETER, of Norway, is
associate professor at the Norwegian Advanced
College for Special Education, and the author of
several books on children's literature. The present
article has been extracted from "The role of
children's books in integrating handicapped
children into everyday life", a background paper
prepared for the Seminar on Books and Disabled
Children organized by Unesco in co-operation
with the Bologna Children's Book Fair in April
1981.
IT is important for handicapped children
to meet themselves in children's
books, to see pictures and read about
children like themselves, their lives, prob¬
lems, feelings, circumstances. And it is im¬
portant for other children to get acquainted
with handicapped children, since an unfor¬
tunate segregation policy in many of our
countries has for decades placed many han¬
dicapped children outside our neighbour¬
hoods. It is thus all the more necessary that
we meet them in books to prepare the soil
for Integration.
Mentally retarded, physically handicapped
or other disabled children almost never see
children like themselves on television or in
films, unless the programme specifically
concerns handicapped children. They
almost never belong to their environments in
the mass media as naturally as other children
do. If one never reads about anyone like
oneself or meets anyone like that in televi¬
sion or on the radio, it is a sort of affirmation
that one is not good enough or does not
belong anywhere or has no value.
During the last decade quite a few books
have appeared about handicapped children,
but many of them are not good enough.
They often activate our mechanisms of re¬
jection and make integration even more dif¬
ficult. Because literature influences us for
better or for worse, especially when we are
children, it is important to evaluate it critical¬
ly. So many books are well-intentioned, and
their authors have surely tried to encourage
understanding, and yet the results are disap¬
pointing.
There is the hidden rejection found in k
many well-intentioned books where healthy f
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
young people who meet handicapped per¬
sons are filled with gratitude for their own
good health. The underlying attitude is that
the normal thing is to be healthy, beautiful
and charming and the handicap somehow
is a kind of punishment for our sins.
In children's books about handicapped
children we frequently find a certain princi¬
ple of compensation so heavily stressed that
it constitutes a hidden sort of rejection: blind
people who automatically, almost by virtue
of their blindness, are so exceptionally kind
and good and have such a good ear for
music; or the brave boy in a wheel-chair.
The blind characters in children's books
are mostly girls it seems so suitable that
girls should be sweet and gentle and play
the piano. The characters in wheel-chairs
are mostly boys, extraordinarily clever boys,
the best companions anyone can think of
and such excellent referees in a football or
baseball game. The handicap is compen¬
sated far beyond reasonable limits.
One might say that such books provide a
certain degree of information about the han¬
dicapped. But on the whole they give a false
picture. A handicap does not automatically
make anyone into an extraordinarily fine per¬
son. The opposite pattern of rejection is
heavily utilized in cheap serial literature, in
which most frequently the villain is physical¬
lyt handicapped. This kind of reading is a
hothouse for discrimination against the han¬
dicapped.
There are so many misleading books
about mentally handicapped children. Some
typical examples: many authors use the
description HI when they write about mental¬
ly retarded children. They are not ill, no
more than other children unless they have
measles or colds or something like that.
They are not ill, they are retarded in their
mental development.
Other authors tell us that an autistic child
can suddenly become normal if his brother is
kind to him, or a girl stops stuttering if she
gets a pet, and another boy starts talking
when he gets a friend, although he has
never been able to talk before. Such things
may happen, but very rarely. Handicapped
children do not become "normal", they just
become grown-ups.
The most common pitfall is to concen¬
trate only on the handicap and make han¬
dicapped children very special. The truth is
of course that a child with a handicap is first
and foremost a child.
We need books containing good
psychological descriptions of the handicap¬
ped person as one of the main characters
and books where handicapped children
belong to their environment as naturally as
do other people. Happily, books exist ¡n
which the author shows both insight and
poetic power. A typical feature of many of
these books is that the author himself states
that his books are written both for children
and for adults. Many of these authors have
experienced a handicap, either personally
Drawings Kasumi Matsushita © Keiko Yoshimura-Kasumi Matsushita, 1980, Publishers Kaisei-Sha, Tokyo
t>tzb t^^fe/u
The Disabled are People Too
is the title of a recently
published book in the form
of a poem by twenty-five-
year-old Keiko Yoshimura,
who was stricken with
cerebral infantile paralysis at
the age of fourteen months.
It ¡s a frank account of what
it feels like to be physically
handicapped and confined
to a wheelchair. The book is
entirely illustrated with
striking black and white
representations of a
wheelchair, the work of
Keiko's long-time friend,
artist Kasumi Matsushita.
THE DISABLED ARE PEOPLE TOO
If I am honest with myself
I admit
I don't like going out
I like people
But I hate crowds
I hate places where there are
likely to be crowds
Amusement parks are not fun
for me
Department stores are hell
In cinemas I am a nuisance
If I am honest with myself
I admit
I don't really like going out
If people stare at me
I hate it
If people pretend I am not there
I hate it
But why should I feel this way?
I am "people" too
I am not a creature from another planet
I am not a freak either
I don't have to hide away
I have an appetite for life,
I enjoy good things to eat and drink
I enjoy feeling
I sleep, dream and wake
I think, laugh and cry
I enjoy feeling
Why do people stare at me?
or look away from me?
Why do they treat me differently?
My heart behaves normally
It beats as it should
It is quite ordinary
The disabled are people too
All people are different
What is so special about my difference
A friend warned me
Be strong, be brave, she said
I thought about being strong and brave
What did being strong mean to me?
If I am not strong now
how should I become strong?
If I need to become strong
there must be a way
How would I change
If I were strong?
Would amusement parks be fun?
Would I enjoy department stores?
Would I like crowds?
A friend warned me
Be strong, be brave, she said
I don't understand becoming strong
Perhaps being strong
is not for me
If I were strong
People might be afraid of me
Better by far that I be brave
People will still stare at me
or look away from me
But if I am brave I shall not mind
Keiko Yoshimura
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
or among their children, friends or
neighbours.
Most children's books about the han¬
dicapped tell us about children with physical
or sensory handicaps, and the authors' in¬
tention is quite obviously to make the
readers identify themselves with these
children. Books about mentally handicap¬
ped children are fewer in number and mostly
written from the point of view of a sister or
brother.
During the last decade we have seen a
number of photographic picture books
about handicapped children. Children who
read them are usually as fascinated by this
documentary material as by fiction. It ac¬
quaints them with handicapped children in
their daily life. Such books are often ex¬
cellent for handicapped children as well;
they can look at pictures of and read about
children who look like themselves and
have to struggle with some of the same
frustrations.
Especially interesting are picture books
made by authors or artists who are
themselves parents or siblings of handicap¬
ped children using their personal experience
and love, trying to tell other children how it
can be for a family to have a handicapped
son or daughter, sister or brother.
In many cases it is a relief to read about
the experiences of others. It can be a help
towards seeing one's own situation in a
wider perspective. There is comfort in
knowing that others have been through the
same experience, even if their conditions
and situations in life are utterly different. For
some people fiction can be an inspiration
towards giving new Insight, awareness and
acceptance.
H Tordis Orjasaeter
Photos Shozo Murase © Graphic Design Associates, Tokyo
Picture books
to be seen with the hands
Why are there so few books for the blind with pictures that can be
"seen" with the hands in the same way Braille texts can be "read"
with the finger-tips? This was the question that inspired Japanese
designer Shozo Murase to produce a five-volume work In which
the illustrations are in relief. The illustrations on this page are from
the volume which aims to give blind children an understanding of
the shape of things in nature and of how they change during the
four seasons of the year. Photos above, the development of a
tulip; left, an octopus.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
0 IP
ÜD G3 LU
rn
Unesco Clubs support
IYDP worldwide
Unesco Clubs totalling some 2,500, in
78 countries are supporting the Inter¬
national Year of Disabled Persons (IYDP)
with a wide range of initiatives linked to the
needs and cultures of the communities to
which they belong.
Their efforts are proving to be particularly
effective in publicizing the objectives of
IYDP. Many Clubs, notably in Belgium,
Spain, the United States, France, India,
Japan, and Mauritius, have devoted all or
part of their newsletters to articles on IYDP
themes, as well as producing and
distributing posters, tracts and other
documents.
A sample of lYDP-linked activities by
Unesco Clubs around the world: in Morocco
the Federation of Unesco Clubs has
launched an information campaign in a
dozen cities, including film shows to raise
funds for national organizations of the
handicapped. The 80 Unesco Clubs on the
island of Mauritius have drawn up a
questionnaire on the situation of the
disabled to help in understanding their
problems and needs. A similar approach has
been adopted in India. The Mangalore Club,
for example, has carried out a survey among
handicapped persons in one of the villages it
has "adopted", as a prelude to action on
their behalf. Also in India, the Nagpur
"friends of Unesco" have held a public
seminar on handicap and donated medical
and other supplies to local centres for the
disabled. In Gabon, an "IBOBU" Club
(Ibobu means "handicapped" in a Gabonese
dialect) has been created. In Japan, the
Federation of Unesco Clubs, which groups
some 450 associations of clubs for adults
and young people, has launched a nation¬
wide fund-raising effort for Unesco's Co-
Action Programme (see page 15) and in Italy
the Unesco Centre in Florence is extending
to disabled children its work on behalf of
literacy teaching for children in hospital. In
the Congo, a competitive game for
schoolchildren is being ingeniously used to
draw attention to IYDP, and Clubs in
Ecuador have published a brochure ending
with the question;
help?"
'What can we do to
Unesco to issue bibliography
on handicapped children
A worldwide survey of reading materials
for and about handicapped children has
been prepared for Unesco by the Interna¬
tional Youth Library (Munich) and will be
published later this year.
A broad selection of titles, each followed
by a brief description in English, is presented
by country, language, author, reading age
and type of handicap. The books listed in¬
clude those for handicapped children and
young adults, children's and young people's
books about the handicapped, and publica¬
tions for young adults that help to illuminate
the special problems of the handicapped.
The bibliography will be available in the lat¬
ter part of 1981 and may be obtained upon
request from Unesco, Division for Book Pro¬
motion and Encouragement of International
Cultural Exchanges, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris (France).
Letters to the editor
EPILEPSY -
A NEGLECTED HANDICAP
Sir,
The term handicap describes a very wide
range of conditions. In common parlance,
however, its meaning is extremely limited
since when people talk of "the handicap¬
ped" they are generally thinking of persons
afflicted with a physical handicap.
And yet those who suffer from other
kinds of handicap are also handicapped per¬
sons, who face the problems of finding a
place in society. Moreover, the non-
physically handicapped often find their prob¬
lems all the more difficult to bear because
others find it hard to accept their existence.
Here is an example of what I mean. An
employer will not create too many obstacles
in taking on a one-armed person or a han¬
dicapped person confined to a wheel-chair,
but he will refuse outright to employ an
epileptic capable of producing work of an
equal quality.
I have been epileptic for 18 years. It is im¬
possible for me to find a job, in other words
to live like other people, simply because I am
labelled "epileptic" a word which causes
apprehension for being too little
understood.
And yet there has never been any ques¬
tion of ignoring the work of Flaubert,
Molière, Dostoevski, Maupassant, Caesar,
and many others simply because they were
epileptics. (Needless to say, I am not
presuming to compare myself with them!)
I am convinced that providing the public
with precise information about epilepsy, a
34
form of nervous illness which originates in
the brain but has nothing to do with insani¬
ty, would lead to much greater social accep¬
tance of epileptics and would further their
integration into society.
Yves Dupin
Bordeaux
France
BRINGING
THE WORLD TO OUR FINGERTIPS
Sir,
I wish to express the heartfelt gratitude
and pleasure I felt on receiving the Unesco
Braille Courier. Your magazine, in addition
to its cultural importance, offers us, the
blind, a unique opportunity to learn about
the international situation. Please put me on
your list of subscribers. Ant0¡ne Tchaby
Littoral Province
Cameroun
A SELF-IMPOSED HANDICAP?
Sir,
Your January issue on the handicapped is
almost entirely devoted to "noble" han¬
dicaps. When can we expect to see a cover
showing a child suffering from Down's Syn¬
drome? Or, where the misfortunes of the in¬
nocent are concerned, are your attitudes
moulded by an unconscious (or shrewd)
racism? Georges Leugé
Rouen
France
The boundaries on this map do not imply official endorsement
or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations.
CORRECTION
Part of the outline of the map of Yugoslavia
which appeared on page 16 of the
November 1980 issue of the Unesco Courier
should be rectified as indicated above.
Because of its reduced scale, the corrected
drawing of course only provides a broad in¬
dication of the boundary line.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Peace on Earth is a selection of writings, some famous,
some less familiar, through which men and women from
different cultures, speaking different languages and holding
different opinions, have described what seemed to them the
possible ways to peace. These texts, from many historical
periods and all the world regions, echo the age-old aspira¬
tions of humanity to peace and understanding between
peoples. Contents include :
PEAGE
ON
EARTH
The age-old dream of peace
Voices raised against war through the centuries
A PF. A CF. A NT HO LOCI Y Peace and the role of force
The role of law and international law
The rise of international institutions
Observance of human rights
Education for peace
UNESCO
227 pages 38 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 -Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
- BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Rol, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display): Zahranicnj literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 None Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI.
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kiria¬
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions):
Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse
57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications:
Ka'rger Verlag Germering/München. For scientific maps only:
Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Pres¬
byterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co.,
13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government Informa¬
tion Services, Publications Centre, GPO Building, Connaught
Place. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Vàci u. 22,
Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Nêpkoztarsasâg utja
16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F.,
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
B-3/7 Asaf AN Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia '
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shlrazi Street,
Enghelab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
A.B.C Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.CÍ Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. - MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Cario. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. Agent for all Unesco
publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The
Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Tenace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New Ser¬
vice Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. - SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, *5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Com¬
pany, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklal Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25. P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
m
JE:
Good vibrations
The question of whether handicapped children should be
educated in special institutions or integrated, more or less com¬
pletely, into the ordinary school system is today giving rise to
widespread debate. Photo shows two pupils, one of whom is
physically handicapped, in a Paris school.
]]>
</page>
</document>
