<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074758eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JUNE I960 3.50 FRENCH FRANCS
LITERACY
Gateway to fulfilment
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
w
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
(2)
Poland
V
Photo © Bulloz, Paris
The Madonna of Kruzlowa
Cracow, then the capital of Poland, became in the 15th century a flourishing centre of
Gothic painting and sculpture which drew to it artists from all over Europe. Produced
around 1400, this carving of the Virgin and Child is part of a full-length painted limewood
figure (118 cm high) which illustrates the variant of the Gothic style typical of Cracow.
Perhaps the most outstanding work of Polish sculpture of its time, the statue once stood
in the parish church at Kruzlowa, in the district of Nowy Sacz. Since 1899 it has been
preserved in Poland's National Museum at Cracow.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JUNE 1980 33rd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly 111 issues a
year including one double issue). For list of distributors see
inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: 11) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition. Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedlcto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris. .
page
4 LITERACY-A RIGHT DENIED TO 800 MILLION
10 NICARAGUA'S NATION-WIDE LITERACY CAMPAIGN
An appeal by the Director-General of Unesco
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
12 LITERACY AND THE LIBERATION OF A PEOPLE
by Julio Cortázar
14 NINE AWARD-WINNING CAMPAIGNS
Photos
19 UNWRITTEN WISDOM
21 'I WAS MADE TO WORK LIKE A PLOUGH'
by Yusufu Selemani
22 SECRETS OF THE WRITTEN CODE
Mother tongues and access to literacy
by John W. Ryan
24 THE THREE 'R's' - AN OPEN BOOK
Photos
27 LETTERS FOR A YOUNG NATION
by Paulo Freiré
31 UNRWA AND UNESCO: A THIRTY-YEAR PARTNERSHIP
A comprehensive education service for Palestine refugees
by Hussein Husnu Ferldun
34 THE READING HABIT
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
POLAND: The Madonna of Kruzlowa
l-XVI POPE JOHN PAUL II AT UNESCO
Special supplement
Cover
"In present-day societies only men and
women with direct access to modern
knowledge and know-how become capable
of fully mastering their destiny. The
conquest of illiteracy thus becomes not
only a fundamental requirement of
democracy, in that it enables everyone
better to exercise his rights and assume his
responsibilities, but also one of the means
of changing the way of life of many
peoples by opening up for them the paths
of progress both in work and in all other
spheres of activity."
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, International
Literacy Day, 10 September 1979.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Literacy a right
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
denied to 800 million
Modern literacy training
methods aim to link the learning
of reading and writing as closely
as possible with the realities of
the pupil's daily life and with his
cultural, economic, technical
and political environment. This
Senegalese alphabet wall-chart
is a good example of the
practical application of this
approach. Ingenious drawings
link common objects with the
shapes of letters that occur in
their names in Mandingo, a
language spoken by some three
and a half million Africans.
THE world illiteracy problem in the last
quarter of the twentieth century
could be summed up in two simple
observations: as a result of colossal efforts
many countries have succeeded in substan¬
tially reducing the percentage of illiterates in
their populations; meanwhile the absolute
number of illiterates is constantly rising
because of soaring population growth.
It has been estimated that if present
trends are not corrected, the number of il¬
literates may rise from 814 million in 1980 (or
approximately three adults in ten) to 884
million in 1990, and that mankind may enter
the twenty-first century with at least 954
million illiterate adults.
The proportion of women in these figures
is getting larger and larger. In 1960, 58 per
cent of illiterates were women; the cor¬
responding figure today is more than 60 per
cent, and in some communities virtually the
whole of the female population is illiterate.
Nearly three-quarters of the world's il¬
literates live in Asia, approximately 20 per
cent in Africa, and 5 per cent in Latin
America. Eleven Countries have a combined
illiterate population of over 400 million.
Twenty-three countries have an illiteracy
rate higher than 70 per cent. Hence the
situation is serious.
Insofar as it affects every man and woman
both as an individual and as a member of a
community, illiteracy hampers his or her per¬
sonal development and constitutes a denial
of the fundamental right to education, now
widely recognized, on which so many others
are contingent. A reversal of the present
world trend towards a constant increase in
the numbers of illiterates would therefore be
a major victory in the fight for human rights.
But illiteracy is in many respects more
than a problem of individuals and even of in¬
dividual nations. Its dimensions are world¬
wide and it has direct and far-reaching
economic and social effects on the develop¬
ment of whole regions of the world.
The map of illiteracy coincides almost ex¬
actly with that of poverty, revealing the
isolation of a large part of mankind, of
human groups which are at once the
poorest, the worst fed and the least well
cared-for. Deprived of the right to education
set forth in the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights, these millions of men and
women are unable to participate effectively
in the progress of the societies to which they
belong, that is to say, in the making of their
own destiny. No country can use the
benefits of science and technology on the
scale necessary for its development if its
population includes a high percentage of il¬
literates. Moreover, in changing societies.
the written word is one of the means
whereby a sense of cultural identity can be
renewed and perpetuated.
For Unesco and its Member States, to
struggle against illiteracy means to struggle
for the respect of human rights and to work
on behalf of development in the widest
sense.
In the light of the figures quoted above,
the task facing the international community
may seem a gigantic one; but it would be a
mistake to lose heart. Between 1950 and
1970, for example, the number of illiterates
admittedly increased by 83 million; but at
the same time the number of literates in¬
creased by 625 million. Likewise, the latest
available estimates show a reduction in the
illiteracy rates among the adult population
(aged 15 and over), which should fall from
28.9 per cent in 1980 to 25.7 per cent in
1990.
Whereas illiteracy among the adult
population aged 15 and over is the outcome
of a long-term situation covering several
decades, that among the population aged
from 15 to 19 gives a clearer idea of recent
developments and provides a yardstick with
which to measure the scale of the
phenomenon for a group of particular
strategic interest, namely those who swell
the ranks of the illiterate because they have
received inadequate schooling or none at all.
As a result of the effort to increase school
enrolments, it has been possible to stabilize
at between 70 and 75 million the absolute
number of illiterates in this age-group, and
the number of literates in the group should
increase by more than 60 million between
1980 and 1990. This will mean a reduction in
the illiteracy rate in this group from 21.8 per
cent in 1980 to 18.4 per cent in 1990.
Globally, the total number of literates
should increase, as a result of a gradual ex¬
pansion of schooling, by 556 million by
1990.
Unesco has been strongly committed to
the struggle against illiteracy ever since the
Organization's first General Conference in
1946, but the concept of literacy and literacy
instruction has developed significantly in the
last three decades.
Pioneering activities to awaken govern¬
ments and public opinion to the seriousness
of the problem culminated, in 1960, in a
World Conference on Adult Education, held
in Montreal, which advocated the organiza¬
tion of a vast campaign aimed at eradicating
illiteracy within a few years. According to
the terms of a Recommendation concerning
the international standardization of educa¬
tion statistics, drawn up by. Unesco two
years before, an illiterate was defined as a
person "unable to read, write and under-
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
stand a short, simple statement of facts
* relating to his daily life."
But there was still a need to investigate
ways and means of tackling the immense
task which the international community had
set itself. And so, in 1964, Unesco's General
Conference decided to initiate an ex¬
perimental literacy programme to pave the
way for an international campaign in this
field. The programme was centred on the
newly-developed concept of "functional
literacy". At a World Congress of Ministers
of Education on the Eradication of Illiteracy,
held in Tehran in September 1965, the con¬
cept was defined in the following terms:"
"Rather than an end in itself, literacy should
be regarded as a way of preparing man for a
social, civic and economic role that goes far
beyond the limits of rudimentary literacy
training consisting merely in the teaching of
reading and writing."
Applying this concept, the Experimental
World Literacy Programme (EWLP) was car¬
ried out between 1967 and 1973 under the
auspices of Unesco and with the co¬
operation of the United Nations Develop¬
ment Programme and other agencies of the
United Nations system. The programme's
objective was not to eliminate or even to
reduce illiteracy on a world scale, but to
"test and demonstrate the economic and
social returns of literacy and, more general¬
ly, to study the mutual relations and in¬
fluences which exist or may be established
or strengthened, between literacy train¬
ing among the working
population and development". Special
importance was attached to the imple¬
mentation of intensive and selective projects
in eleven of the twenty-two countries which
took part (Algeria, Ecuador, Ethiopia,
Guinea, Iran, Madagascar, Mali, Sudan,
Tanzania, Venezuela and Zambia).
A critical evaluation of this programme,
published in the form of a global report (see
"Bookshelf" page 34) provided a rich
harvest of significant information about
organization, financing, methodology and
international co-operation with regard to
literacy action. One of the first constructive
consequences was that programmes
launched in Algeria, India, Mali and Tan¬
zania were extended.
During the 1970s, the notion of functional
literacy was gradually extended. Over and
above the process of learning the skills of
reading, writing and arithmetic, literacy
came to be seen as part of a global educative
process conforming to the principles of
lifelong education, and acquired a new
dimension as an instrument for the liberation
of man and his full development. A declara¬
tion adopted at an International Symposium
for Literacy held at Persepolis in 1975 stated
that "literacy creates the conditions for the
acquisition of a critical consciousness of the
contradictions of society in which man lives
and of its aims. It also stimulates initiative
and his participation in the creation of pro¬
jects capable of acting upon the world, of
transforming it, and of defining the aims of
an authentic human development. Literacy
is not an end in itself; it is a fundamental
human right".
The definition of illiteracy was also chang¬
ing. A revised version of the Recommenda¬
tion concerning the international standar¬
dization of education statistics, proposed by
Unesco in 1978, declared that "a persons
should be considered 'functionally illiterate Y
The social causes
of illiteracy
SOUTH ASIA
Hunger. So long as
millions of human
beings, the great
majority of them in
the Third World, are
living precariously on
the border-line of
starvation, no
educational policy,
however well
conceived, can by
itself eradicate
illiteracy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Lack of funds for education, results in
limited facilities, lack of teaching aids and
the use of teachers who have not always
received suitable training.
Rest
of South Asia
Indonesia
Bangladesh
Pakistan
Iran
Afghanistan
India
Diagram shows the distribution of the esti¬
mated numbers of illiterates aged 15 and over
in 1980. (Figures for the People's Republic of
China, the Democratic People's Republic of
Korea and the Socialist Republic of Viet Nam
are not included). It should be pointed out that,
in India, which has the second largest popula¬
tion in the world (about 600 million), great pro¬
gress is being made in tackling illiteracy and
both the illiteracy rate and the absolute num¬
ber of illiterates are expected
to fall considerably in the near
future.
Nigeria
Ethiopia
Egypt
Rest
of Africa
Brazil
Rest of
Latin
America
24
i millions L
AFRICA LATIN AMERICA REST OF THE WORLD
Education imposed from
outside. Systems of
education copied from
other countries and
which do not take into
account a nation's
specific conditions and
needs can never be
expected to come to
grips with the basic
problems of illiteracy.
Poverty. In the developing countries,
without the earnings of their school-age
children, many poor families cannot even
afford the basic essentials of life. Deprived
by harsh necessity of their schooling, these
children will grow up to swell the ranks of
the great army of the illiterate.
Isolation. When a country's population is scattered, the
establishment of schools and attendance at them
becomes much more difficult. This problem is
compounded by the fact that these isolated groups of
people are amongst the poorest and the least well-fed and
are unable to share in the progress of the societies to
which they belong.
wm
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
who cannot engage in all tnose activities in
which literacy is required for effective func¬
tioning of his group and community and also
for enabling him to continue to use reading,
writing and calculation for his own and the
community's development".
Against this background of experience,
Unesco has in the last few years set out to
renew the principles of its actions.
Adult illiteracy and low school enrolment
are two sides of the same coin, and so it
seemed essential to integrate efforts in each
field into a global approach in which literacy
training for adults is associated with the
general introduction of primary education.
If the causes of illiteracy are to be rooted
out once and for all, it is essential that all
children of school age should have access at
least to basic elementary education. But
despite the considerable progress which has
been achieved in many countries in this
field, it must be admitted that the overall
situation continues to be very disturbing. In
the developing countries where at present
nearly one young person in four enters
working life without having received a
minimum of education, considerable efforts
will be needed to achieve universal primary
education by the year 2000.
In 1985, if the situation is not remedied,
only 18 of the 46 African countries
(representing 23 per cent of the African
population) are likely to have enrolment
rates of 80 per cent or above. In south Asia,
the enrolment ratio in 1985 will probably be
50 per cent for girls and 71 per cent for boys.
Owing to the effects of population growth,
Africa's education systems would have
almost to triple by the end of the century
rc^^^^^^^^^^r^H
	 M, -. .. v~-
DIMANCHE Dibéér Diiboor Alet a 13 20 27 Alahada Alhadô Alahadi
LUNDI Altine Tening Altine 7 14 21 28 Tener) Teneqo Tenerçe
MARDI Talaata Talaata Talaata i g 15 22 29 Talaata Talaató Talaata
MERCREDI Alarba Ardaba Alarba ? i 16 23 30 Araba Arabo Araba
JEUDI Alxemes Arxemes Alkamnsa 3 10 17 M 31 Araamisa Araamiso Alxamisa
VENDREDI Ajuma Jumaling Aljumaa 4 n 18 25 Arijuma Arjumoo Aljuma
SAMEDI Gaawu Fugaaw Aset S 12 19 26 Si'bi'tè Sibitô Sibiti
The struggle against illiteracy is especially
complex in those Third World countries where a
number of languages are spoken. One example is
Senegal, where literacy programmes are to be
carried out in the six languagesWolof, Serer,
Peul, Diula, Mandingo and Soninkewhich figure
on this calendar. The phrase, in Mandingo, at the
top of the page reads: "That's very good".
8
just to achieve the projected enrolment
ratios, whilst those of Latin America and
south Asia would have to double.
This determination to include literacy
work in an overall strategy for the develop¬
ment of education, linking together both
formal and non-formal education, has been
confirmed by recent regional conferences of
Ministers of Education of Unesco's Member
States, especially by the regional conference
for Latin America and the Caribbean which
took place in Mexico City in December 1979.
In the "Mexico Declaration" which it
adopted, the Conference urged Member
States to "provide a minimum of 8 to 10
years' general education and establish as
their goal to incorporate all children of
school age in the system not later than
1999" and to "adopt a clear-cut policy with a
view to eradicating illiteracy before the end
of the century and to extending educational
services for adults". In addition, the Con¬
ference expressed the hope that Unesco
would put forward a major project so that
the entire population of this part of the
world may enjoy the right to education
before the end of this century.
The adult literacy campaigns which con¬
stitute the second aspect of the action pro¬
posed by Unesco may find helpful a number
of principles which the Organization has
identified from its past experience.
First of all, it is noteworthy that the most
spectacular successes in adult literacy cam¬
paigns have often been achieved in a con¬
text of profound social change or in a situa¬
tion of economic expansion and a broaden¬
ing employment market. In these circum¬
stances, literacy is regarded as a means of
enabling individuals to face a new situation
or to be active protagonists in bringing
about the desired changes in society.
Secondly, it has become clear that literacy
work can only be effective if the
beneficiaries themselves participate in it,
each adult becoming the agent of his or her
own literacy training and being aware of the
need for this personal involvement. This
principle of participation is fundamental. It
implies that literacy work is based on the
commitment of the entire population, a
commitment which can help to strengthen
its feeling of. cultural identity. Here the
choice of language or languages to be used,
a political decision which should be based
on technical and cultural criteria, is of key
importance.
A third essential principle is that of the in¬
tegration of literacy programmes: integra¬
tion both into the process of life-long educa¬
tion and into a wider context of economic
and social reforms. One of the most striking
examples of this principle is that of rural
development, which is affected by the world
food crisis, natural disasters and problems
of unemployment and under-employment,
as well as by the structure of society itself.
Self-sustained development is inconceivable
without the mobilization of the rural popula¬
tion. Literacy work can be both a con¬
tributory factor in, and a consequence of,
this mobilization, but its impact depends
ultimately on the scope of the measures
adopted and on changes introduced in other
spheres.
Integration into the process of life-long
education presupposes that literacy work is
followed up. Literacy and numeracy are
useless accomplishments unless these basic
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
skills are put to use in everyday life and
unless the newly literate are provided with
suitable material in the form of texts written
in their own language which take account of
their level of education and of their interests.
It has also become clear that no universal¬
ly valid model can be devised for literacy
programmes, which must, on the contrary,
be tailored to circumstances, to the social,
economic and cultural contexts and living
conditions of those concerned. The diver¬
sification of methods and content is
therefore essential to success.
But success depends, in the last resort,
on the political commitment of individual na¬
tions. Governments have a key role to play
in a field where objectives must be establish¬
ed, strategies chosen, and the nation's
energies, its material, financial and human
resources must be mobilized to make
literacy an instrument for achievement of
the necessary transformation of society.
The cost of the programes required to
combat adult illiteracy and achieve universal
primary education is immense. In addition to
intensive efforts on the part of the nations
concerned, the task demands a strengthen¬
ing of international co-operation. Many
countries involved feel that the present
volume of assistance is too small, difficult to
harness and not flexible enough to cope
with a wide variety of situations.
Unesco is committed to the fulfilment of
its role as a co-ordinator and catalyst of in¬
ternational co-operation through its pro¬
gramme studies and the collec¬
tion of information on illiteracy; helping
Member States to frame national strategies
and plans; supporting activities to train
literacy personnel; and mobilizing interna¬
tional public opinion. Unesco's role in rally¬
ing the international community could be
greatly developed if additional resources
were available. Against this background, the
1978 General Conference called on Member
States to contribute generously to Unesco's
Special Account for voluntary contributions
for literacy work.
The world illiteracy problem cannot be
remedied solely through an educational ap¬
proach dissociated from other aspects of
development; on the contrary, the objec¬
tives of development should be an inspira¬
tion for education and literacy work. In the
final analysis the problem should be seen in
the wider context of efforts being made by
the international community to establish a
new world economic and social order. Ac¬
cordingly, Unesco has pressed for literacy
work to be included as a basic component of
the Third United Nations Development
Decade which begins in 1981.
Great strides have already been made dur¬
ing the previous Decades. But the fact re¬
mains that each year vast numbers of
children deprived of schooling swell the
ever-increasing ranks of the world's adult il¬
literates. It is vitally important that, through
the solidarity and commitment of the inter¬
national community and its sense of respon¬
sibility towards these millions of human be¬
ings, this alarming trend should be halted
and reversed.
This article was prepared in collaboration
with the Education Sector of Unesco.
Education
for social change
I should like to pay tribute. Ladies and
Gentlemen, to your Organization's
outstanding work, and at the same time
to the work of the States and institu¬
tions you represent and their commit¬
ment to the task of promoting the
general provision of education for the
people at large, at all grades and levels,
and of eradicating illiteracy, which
reflects the non-existence of even the
rudiments of instruction, a grievous
deficiency not only from the point of
view of the basic culture of individuals
and their environment, but also in terms
of socio-economic progress. There are
alarming signs of disparities in this field,
linked with an often acutely unequal
and unjust distribution of wealth: we
need only think of situations where a
small plutocratic oligarchy coexists with
starving multitudes living in extreme
poverty. The disparity can be remedied,
not through bloody struggles for
power, but, above all, by systematically
promoting literacy through the
widespread provision of education for
the masses. This is the direction in
which we must work if we wish after¬
wards to bring about the changes need¬
ed in the socio-economic domain. Man,
who "is more" because, also, of what
he "has", and what he "possesses",
must know how to possess, that is to
say, how to deal with and administer
the resources in his possession, for his
own good and for the common good.
For this, education is essential.
Pope John Paul II
Unesco Headquarters,
2 June 1980
Paris
Public expenditure on education and military expenditure
l'as percentage of GNP [Gross National Product] and per inhabitant, in U. S. dollars)
Public expenditure Military Public expenditure Military
on education expenditure on education expenditure
as a % of as a % of per inhabitant per inhabitant
GNP GNP in U.S. dollars in U.S. dollars
4.9 6.8 38 54
5.4 6.6 58 71
5.8 5.3 111 103
5.2 7.5 87 127
5.6 7.1 139 176
6.0 5.5 269 246
3.2 2.6 5 5
4.Q 2.9 8 7
4.4 4.5 20 21
World total
Developed
countries
Developing
countries
1965
1970
1975
1965
1970
1975
1965
1970
1975
These figures do not include data relating to the People's Republic of China, Democratic Kampuchea, Democratic People's Republic of Korea, Lao People's
Democratic Republic, South Africa and Socialist Republic of Viet Nam. 	
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
FEW nations, in the course of their re¬
cent history, have endured so much
physical and psychological suffering,
or been so gravely afflicted materially, as the
people of Nicaragua. Besides the great
poverty of most of its inhabitants, there
have been the disasters caused by the earth¬
quake in 1972 and the destruction suffered
during the liberation struggle. The treasures
of the country have been pillaged; its
resources destroyed, its towns and villages
severely damaged and its infrastructures
dislocated. But it is the toll taken among its
people which is the heaviest: 35,000 dead,
100,000 injured, most of them adolescents,
and 40,000 orphaned, out of a total popula¬
tion of 2,200,000.
At its 108th session, the Executive Board
of Unesco expressed "its total solidarity
with the people and Government of
Nicaragua in their arduous task of national
reconstruction, and its determination to co¬
operate in that task within the fields of com¬
petence of Unesco", and requested me to
take the necessary steps to achieve those
ends.
I visited Nicaragua from 16 to 19
December 1979, and was able to judge for
myself the extent of the work that had to be
done to rebuild the country.
What is required is to mobilize all the
country's manpower, to reorganize and ex¬
pand its educational, cultural and scientific
institutions and to redeploy its means of pro¬
duction, in line with a coherent, overall pro¬
gramme. The country's new authorities
have committed themselves to achieving
these goals, and in order to do so have
drawn up a national reconstruction plan
which deserves both our sympathy and our
support.
A key objective in this plan is the achieve¬
ment of general literacy throughout the
country, because illiteracy is a major
obstacle to conscious participation by all
citizens in the task of national revival and
because such participation is the first pre¬
requisite to enable the people of Nicaragua
to follow their own path of development,
with due regard for their cultural identity
and in keeping with their own aspirations.
At the present time, 35.2 per cent of
children between the ages of 7 and 12 have
no opportunity of undergoing primary
education and 50.2 per cent of the popula¬
tion aged 10 and over some 850,000
people are illiterate, the rural areas being
the worst affected in this respect.
The campaign for the eradication of il¬
literacy has therefore been planned to serve
as the lever for an educational and social ad¬
vancement movement which is to be ex¬
tended to all categories of the population.
Far from being confined to the younger
generation, it is to cater for all illiterates,
without any restriction or discrimination.
10
Nicaragua's
nation-wide
literacy
campaign
An appeal
by the
Director-General
of Unesco
The campaign, which began on 24 March
1980, will enlist the services of 200,000
literacy teachers who will devote themselves
to teaching 850,000 illiterates. For six
months, they will live together and share
the same living conditions. This is a stirring
experiment, the aims of which go beyond
the sphere of education alone, seeking to
bring about a profound change in the rela¬
tions between the various social strata in
the country.
The scope of this campaign and the spirit
informing it both reflect the determination to
reconcile all the country's citizens by bring¬
ing them together in a great effort of na¬
tional solidarity. It should enable them all,
individually, to develop their full potential
while helping to improve the well-being of all
and, in particular, should assist the young,
who had to break off their studies in order to
take part in the national struggle, in finding
their place again, without delay, in working
life.
Nicaragua will not, however, be able to
achieve these objectives unless it receives
moral and material support from the world
community. At a time when the country is
only just beginning to lift itself out of its
ruins, this support should make it easier for
it to rely on its own efforts in the future. The
total financial contribution which it hopes.
today, to receive from international solidari¬
ty amounts to 20 million dollars.
Contributions in kind will also be
welcome, particularly school supplies and
equipment paper, pencils, exercise books,
blackboards, audio-visual aids, radios as
well as motor vehicles, camping equipment,
clothing, blankets, oil-lamps, powdered or
tinned foodstuffs.
Moreover, since illiteracy cannot be over¬
come unless it is, so to speak, cut off at the
very source, a large number of new schools
will have to be opened for children reaching
school age. There will therefore be scope for
international solidarity to be shown firstly,
by providing Nicaragua with the means to
build these schools and, secondly, by
assisting in training and refresher pro¬
grammes for those who are called upon to
teach in them.
Nicaragua has made heavy sacrifices for
its liberationwhich is also, in some
measure, the liberation of each one of
usand it is embarking on an experiment
of the greatest interest from the ethical
and educational points of view which
may be useful to many other peoples.
We are therefore in duty bound to meet its
expectations.
On behalf of the United Nations Educa¬
tional, Scientific and Cultural Organization,
and with the unanimous support of its Ex¬
ecutive Board, I accordingly invite all
governments. National Commissions for
Unesco, public and private institutions in all
Member States, and international founda¬
tions and organizations, both governmental
and non-governmental, to give proof of their
active solidarity with liberated Nicaragua.
I invite the Churches of various denomina¬
tions, trade union organizations and profes¬
sional associations, women's organizations
and youth movements, to make available to
the Nicaraguan authorities financial and
material resources that will enable them to
achieve the objectives they have in view.
I make this appeal to all those who have
responsibilities in the field of education: to
public services and private programmes con¬
cerned with education and literacy work, to
universities, to teachers' associations, and
to research centres, in the hope that they
will offer the Nicaraguan Government all the
technical assistance within their power in
this undertaking.
Lastly, I appeal to all those who enjoy the
benefits of education, to the adults, the
children and the young people who are to¬
day receiving education and realize how
much it is enriching them. I am confident
that they will be able to organize them¬
selves, to collect resources, on however
modest a scale, and to arrange for them to
be sent to those in Nicaragua who are en¬
deavouring to take their future in hand.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
In the main square of Managua the people of the Nicaraguan
capital give a rousing send-off to members of the People's
Literacy Army, the E.P.A. Organized into squads of thirty
students, high school boys and girls and teachers, the E.P.A.
is being deployed throughout Nicaragua in a massive,
popular crusade whose objective is the total eradication of
illiteracy. Opposite page, the emblem of Nicaragua's National
Literacy Crusade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Literacy
and
the liberation
of a people
by Julio Cortázar
Afew months after its liberation, Nicaragua has launched a
nation-wide literacy teaching campaign which will even¬
tually turn the whole country into a vast school in which
one half of the population will teach the other half how to read
and write.
Only once before has Latin America witnessed such a
dramatic and momentous mobilization of forces seeking to
strengthen a people's sense of self-awareness. This was in
Cuba, shortly after the triumph of the revolution in 1959, when
the people embarked on a colossal effort to extirpate
backwardness and ignorance, with results which Nicaragua is
seeking to emulate and if possible surpass. Two small Latin
American countries have thus pointed the way which many
others must one day take in a continent where illiteracy is not
only a brake on development but an oppressive obstacle to that
search for authentic roots and identity whose stirrings have
become perceptible in the Latin American turmoil of recent
decades.
By a curiously ironic twist of fate, the independence
movements of our countries sprang from ideals of education and
popular culture which their leaders and heroes inherited from the
French Revolution and which, bearing the imprint of
romanticism, imbued proclamations, constitutions and acts of
government. The idea that the sovereign people should be
educated and the belief that only a man who could read and
write could possibly be a good citizen were widespread in the
nineteenth century. But civil wars and the rise of authoritarian
regimes, leading to an increasing number of dictatorships and
tyrannies, soon dissipated illusions and notions which could only
have come to fruition if time and more favourable conditions
had been available.
The immensity of our continent, ethnic differences, and
foreign interference which went on parallel to and hand in glove
with despotic régimes these factors combined to isolate and
alienate our peoples and led to a preference for naive and
submissive masses instead of citizens with a capacity for
culture, reflexion and critical appraisal. The case of Nicaragua is
an extreme example: the legacy of forty years of oppression and
exploitation was an illiteracy rate which has been calculated at
over fifty per cent of the population.
The victory of the Nicaraguan people on 19 July 1979 found
immediate expression in a determination to "rebuild" which
went far beyond the literal meaning of that yvord. When the
ruling Junta defined its aims as reconstruction it knew that the
term would be fully understood by those who feel to the depths
of their being the immense disadvantages of ignorance. Not for
nothing does the Government include poets and intellectuals
such as Ernesto Cardenal, Sergio Ramirez and Tomás Borge, for
JULIO CORTÁZAR is an internationally known Argentinian writer whose
novels and short stories have been widely translated. Among his works
which have appeared in English are 62: A Model Kit (1976) and Cronopias
and Famas (1978) both published by M. Boyars, London.
12
whom reconstruction means not only raising the country from
its still smoking ruins but also enabling children and adults to
participate fully, consciously and critically in this undertaking.
Their design is based on an idea of the Nicaraguan as an
active agent in this reconstruction and as an individual capable
of understanding what he is doing, why he is doing it,' and how
he should do it. The notion of a passive and downtrodden
people, as understood during the Somoza régime, has been
replaced by a dynamic notion of participation and consultation;
such a process is inconceivable without a minimum of
intellectual preparation which goes beyond the bounds of
ancestral and traditional knowledge, using such knowledge
when it is deemed to be constructive, discarding it when it is a
cause of backwardness and stagnation.
All this makes it easier to understand the passionate interest
aroused in Nicaragua by the preparation and launching of the
country's literacy campaign. In the absence of the most basic
teaching facilities, the whole country understood that the
campaign had to be organized before the provision of any aid
and solidarity that might be forthcoming from friendly countries.
The appeal launched by Unesco is a wholehearted and
enthusiastic response to this decision made by the Nicaraguan
people, a decision to which it is impossible to feel indifference.
Contrary to what happened during the Cuban literacy campaign
in the 1960s, when Unesco waited for the movement to get
underway, then checked out the results and presented them in
glowing terms, today the Organization has unhesitatingly come
forward and appealed to the world community for aid, thus
showing its full confidence that another Latin American people
will be able to rid itself of ignorance through its own efforts.
According to official reports, it is estimated that the criminal
bombardment of Nicaragua's towns and villages has cost the
country over a hundred million córdobas (about ten million
dollars) in destroyed school buildings, furniture and educational
equipment. This devastation on the one hand, and the terrible
toll of 35,000 dead and some 100,000 wounded on the other,
reveal the full dimensions of the difficulties to be faced in this
new battle being fought for popular education. The problems
are many: shortages of equipment, transport facilities and funds,
the difficulties of communicating with the regions of the interior,
especially the Atlantic coast, and the need to extend the
campaign to regions with a predominant Indian population.
The problems will be tackled in an extremely realistic way:
anyone who can read and write can take part in the campaign
as a teacher. Most of the teaching will be done in fact by young
high school pupils, since they are not yet in employment and
can devote all their time to the task. These members of the
"literacy brigades" will go to the various rural and urban areas
accompanied by more experienced advisors and with all the
necessary logistical back-up. They will live in the fields and
forests, in factories and villages, in mountains and ports, sharing
the lives and occupations of their pupils, most of whom will be
adults. The whole country will become a single school, with
methods and techniques being worked out as the campaign
progresses. The Indians, who belong to communities with their
own deep-rooted culture, must be taught to read and write in
their own languages as well as in Spanish. On the Atlantic coast
English is also spoken; this is another problem which will have
to be solved.
While teaching literacy to adults is indispensable, a visit to
Nicaragua's towns and hinterland brings home the full extent of
the concern of the government and people for the young.
Nicaraguan children have begun a totally different life since the
liberation of their country, which it will be their responsibility to
lead in a few years' time. The fact that they also constitute the
bulk of the army of literacy teachers gives the campaign its
distinctive character. Nicaraguan families are still amazed at the
new atmosphere of life that can be felt in the streets, in the
squares, wherever the people gather. If the change in
atmosphere means liberty and security for them, the most
beautiful and moving symbol of this conquest are the children,
with their vitality, their games and their songs.
On my first visits to Managua I was astonished by the
enthusiasm of my guides, young Sandinista soldiers, whenever
they saw groups of children in the streets. Eventually they
explained to me that under the dictatorship children were never
seen out in the open air because they were suspected or hated
by the guards, through bitterness and cruelty. They knew that
many children and teenagers were carrying out liaison missions,
and that some of them were capable of taking part in military
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
IwJfcJ '~ -.
ALHUCTCAOON
All available government vehicles, from coaches to open trucks, are being pressed into service to transport Literacy Army squads to
every corner of Nicaragua.
action; they were often captured or killed as a means of
terrorizing the population.
"The mere appearance of a uniform of any kind made children
fly away like sparrows", one of my guides told me. "They
weren't even allowed to play football on patches of waste
ground because the guards suspected that this was a
camouflaged form of training."
At the same time, the participation of children and teenagers
in the campaign raises problems which have no ready-made
solution. First of all, it may be risky for many of them to venture
into regions far from the towns, since the supporters of the
dictatorial régime have made no secret of their intention of
taking revenge.
Consequently, the Junta has decided that only children
specifically authorized by their parents will be allowed to go to
the remote regions where, not surprisingly, most of them want
to Work. In Managua I saw things sometimes take a dramatic
turn when parents refused to give permission for their sons to
leave, creating a tension which was often unpleasant between
them and their schoolmates who had been authorized to go.
The reaction to this may appear surprising to someone who
has not lived with the Nicaraguan people since their victory. The
children who will constitute the literacy teaching brigades have
not only shown solidarity towards those of their comrades who
have not been allowed to join the campaign, more than once
they formed delegations to visit the parents, explain their point
of view, beg them to reconsider their decision, and grant
permission as requested by their sons. This response seems
totally spontaneous, and it is already clear that an overwhelming
majority of the high school children will leave to carry out, with
school and university teachers, a task which fills them with
pride. Each one will take with him a small handbook prepared in
Nicaragua and printed in Costa Ricaa modest piece of
equipment with which to confront inexperience, geographic and
climatic hazards, endemic sicknesses, food shortages and the
harsh conditions of life inoften inhospitable regions.
All of this may contribute to a fuller understanding of
Unesco's urgent appeal for international solidarity with
Nicaragua's literacy campaign. Unesco estimates that the
necessary aid will amount to twenty million dollars. Set against
military expenditure and commercial profits, this may seem a
modest sum; but it will be enough to lead a nation of less than
three million people out of the backward conditions in which it
was kept by dictatorship.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Nine
award-winning
campaigns
The 14th International Literacy Day, 10 September 1979, was marked by the
presentation by Unesco Director-General, Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, of two
literacy prizes administered by Unesco, the Nadezdha Krupskaya Prize and
the International Reading Association Prize. The international jury
responsible for selecting the prizewinners from the twenty-seven
candidatures presented made two awards of the 5,000 rouble Nadezdha
Krupskaya Prize, established in 1969 by the USSR Government. They went
to the Supreme Council of the National Compulsory Comprehensive
Literacy Campaign, in Iraq, which has mounted a mass drive to eradicate
illiteracy, and to the Popular Union of Peruvian Women, which has
organized women's participation in development activities through literacy
courses. The $5,000 International Reading Association Prize, being awarded
for the first time, went to the Papua New Guinea Branch of the Summer
Institute of Linguistics, which has been working for several years on the.
transcription of local languages and the training of local literacy teachers.
Photo © Upper Volta National Commission for Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Papua New Guinea
The Papua New Guinea Branch
of the Summer Institute of Linguistics
International Reading Association Prize
The Papua New Guinea branch of the Summer
Institute of Linguistics started work in 1956, in co¬
operation with the Education Department, on
problems of literacy and adult education in rural
areas. Work began with the analysis of the
grammatical and phonetic systems of local
languages, the establishment of rules for the
transcription of local and vernacular languages
and the preparation of teaching materials. By 1973,
126 languages had been transcribed and literacy
programmes were being carried out in 90
languages. A preliminary linguistic and literacy
directory for all Papua New Guinea has been
completed which indicates that there are 717
languages, many of them without alphabets.
Literacy instructors are chosen from local
community members and are given a short
training course followed by in-service training.
Over the past five years more than 18,000 people
have been taught to read in their vernacular
language, 470 instructors have been trained,
village libraries have been established in 4 villages
and people of 17 different language groups have
been selected to attend courses in community
development at Ukarumpa.
Drawing © Gudia Muri, Papua New Guinea
q Photo Kay Lawson © Rapho, Paris
Popular Union of Peruvian Women
Nadezdha Krupskaya Literacy Prize, 1979
Founded in 1970, the Popular Union of Peruvian Women has always paid
particular attention to the problem of illiteracy, since two thirds of Peruvian
illiterates are women. Since 1975, the Union has taken an active part in the
Peruvian Government's Integral Literacy Programme. At present the Union
is preparing a National Literacy Campaign aimed at bringing literacy to
some 10,000 illiterates throughout the country. The problem of illiteracy in
the Quechua language is being tackled by the employment of literacy
teachers of Quechua mother tongue in the provinces of Huancavelica and ,
Junin. The Union's programme has given rise to other activities such as the
creation of day-nurseries in nine provinces and the publication of the
magazine Rehilete.
Photo © Permanent Delegation of Iraq to Unesco
Iraq
Supreme Council of the National Compulsory Comprehensive
Literacy Campaign Nadezdha Krupskaya Literacy Prize, 1979
Launched in December 1978, Iraq's National Campaign for Compulsory
Literacy was set the target of bringing literacy to some two million (one
sixth of the country's total population). Earlier attempts to eradicate
illiteracy, while achieving a certain success, had been hampered by lack of
co-ordination among literacy agencies, lack of follow-up programmes and a
serious drop-out problem in primary education. These problems have now
been resolved. With primary schooling now compulsory the flow of new
illiterates has been cut off at source. Of illiterates over primary school age
1,394,000 women and 660,000 men are registered at literacy centres where
they follow 14-month literacy courses. During the basic stage students
receive instruction in reading, simple arithmetic and general knowledge,
and at the integrated stage the reading material is diversified and support is
given by special lessons transmitted by television. Follow-up is provided in
the recently established People's Schools which offer condensed study
programmes lasting 16 months.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Bolivia
Professor Mario Guzman Molina
Honourable mention
For long an outstanding figure in the educational field.
Professor Molina, now National Director of Bolivia's
adult education and non-formal education
programmes, began his lifelong struggle against
illiteracy when, at the outset of his career, he created
a night school for workers which provided literacy
courses as well as courses in mechanics and electricity
for men and in sewing and home economics for
women. Realizing the educational potential of the
mass media, he established a centre for adult training
by radio (CETCAR) and launched the periodical Acción
for new literates and a specialized educational journal
Educación Popular para el Desarrollo. Meanwhile he
had founded and become the first director of the
Institute of Cultural Research for Popular Education
(INDICEP) where the outlines of a truly popular .
pedagogy were drawn up. After a meeting with the
Brazilian educationist Paulo Freiré, Professor Molina
developed a method for popular education, known as
Dinamización Cultural, which incorporated many of
Freire's ideas adapted to the social and cultural
realities of Bolivia.
Benin
Literacy and Rural Press Directorate
Honourable mention
Established in November 1974, the Directorate was
given the task of promoting popular culture and
literacy as an essential factor of development.
Following a massive, two-year sensitization campaign,
a four-stage literacy method was elaborated, teaching
personnel were trained and the work of producing
spelling books in the national languages was begun.
Between 1974 and 1979, 10,000 spelling books in 18
languages were printed. The new literacy method was
tried out in experimental courses which brought
literacy to some 33,000 people. A post-literacy
programme was developed involving the promotion of
the rural press and the publication of literacy material
in the national languages. The Directorate produces or
co-operates in the production of monthly journals in
the Bariba, Fon, Waama and Dendi languages; in
addition it selects and publishes works of great literary
merit in the national languages.
~ ^ :	
WS«
___
Panama
General Directorate of Literacy and Adult
Education Honourable mention
The General Directorate implements literacy
programmes at the national level aimed to reach the
entire illiterate population within the context of
lifelong education and the social and economic
development of the country. Breaking with traditional
educational patterns, the Directorate makes use of all
available existing human and material resources to
carry out its programmes: rural and agrarian
committees, co-operatives, trade unions, mining and
sugar refinery community groups and educational
development centres. In the literacy programmes
addressed to specific indigenous groups, special
attention has been paid to the preservation of their
cultural values and customs whilst bringing them into
the mainstream of national life. Between 1970 and
1978, 4,432 centres gave instruction to almost 170,000
adults in literacy, completion of primary education,
popular culture and technical and word-related
subjects. A total of 28,806 adults achieved literacy
during this period.
_
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Viet Nam
The Commune of Cat Hanh
Honourable mention
The commune of Cat Hanh, in the province of iMghla
Binh, has a mainly agricultural population of some
10,000. After the war, at the end of 1974, the commune
had about 2,000 illiterates. As literacy was one of the
requirements for voting in the 1976 elections, an
intense campaign was mounted and the first
programme was launched in the village of Khanh Loc
which had suffered particularly during the war. The
work in Khanh Loc was a great success and the
campaign spread rapidly to other villages. The villagers
of the commune themselves built sixty classrooms
which were used by children by day and adults by
night. Within a few months, in 1975, 1,896 men and
women of the Cat Hanh commune became literate. As
literacy became more general greater emphasis was
placed on complementary education. First and second
level classes for professionals and first level classes
for workers have been instituted. The first level
classes serve as a post-literacy follow-up.
Thailand
The Functional Literacy Programme, Adult
Education Division, Department of Non-Formal
Education Honourable mention
The Thai Functional Literacy Programme has adopted
a problem-oriented approach to the task of bringing
literacy to the approximately 14 per cent of the
population over the age of ten considered illiterate.
The programme's specific objectives are to develop
the process of problem solving and critical thinking, to
prepare learners to seek and use the services available
and to provide literacy and numeracy skills which will
serve as learning tools. The curriculum offered
provides for 200 hours of study divided into four
subject areas: occupational, health, economics and
civic responsibility. Most of the teachers are formal
school teachers who volunteer or are specially
recruited for the programme. In order to take regional
differences into account there are six literacy sub-
programmes: courses given at specific centres,
courses given by volunteer travelling teachers, courses
given by Buddhist monks, courses given in ordinary
schools, courses given by radio and special courses for
the mountain peoples. So far more than 100,000 people
have taken advantage of these literacy courses and
the programme is expanding steadily every year.
Indonesia
Agency for the Development of Education in the
Malang District Honourable mention
Established in 1973 to tackle the problem of illiteracy,
the Agency consists of institutions active in education
such as the Institute of Teacher Training and the Boy
Scout Movement. The Agency has four task forces
responsible for primary school drop-outs, the training
of the young unemployed, the development of the
national character, and the eradication of illiteracy. In
1976, the Agency established a literacy programme in
the village of Sidodadi where 1,430 of the population
of 3,597 were illiterate. Following the success of the
Sidodadi experiment (92 per cent of the pupils passed
the literacy test after a four-month course), the
programme has been extended to over 400 other
villages. Each course consists of three, four-month
stages. During stage I pupils are expected to learn to
read and write and do simple arithmetic. In stage II
they learn about Indonesia, geography, nutrition,
civics and hygiene. At stage III they can acquire skills
such as farming, serving, automobile repair, cattle-
raising, welding, radio repair and carpentry.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Unwritten
wisdom
Although they may not be attuned to
the presentation of technical
information, the systems of symbolic
representation elaborated by rural
societies, often highly sophisticated,
bear witness to cultures that have
found ways of expressing themselves
other than through the written word.
Above, The Dismembering of
Huatacame, a mythological "painting"
in coloured woollen yarn by José
Benítez Sánchez, an artist of Mexico's
Huichol people. Left, decorated gourd
from the Yola district of north-eastern
Nigeria. Each motif symbolizes an
element of the real world: a the leaves
of a tree; b river worms; c knife
handles; d the back of a fly; e the
teeth of a fish.
THE portrait which is painted of traditional rural societies, where
illiteracy rates are highest, often tends to be sketchy and
superficial. It is overlooked that the absence of reading and
writing does not prevent people in these communities from perform¬
ing complex mental calculations, transmitting knowledge orally from
generation to generation, and developing a highly retentive memory.
Although he can write nothing down, the illiterate villager makes use
of processes of mental arithmetic, often of a complex nature and
whose mechanisms are little known. It seems likely, although this is
no more than a supposition, that the calculations made by illiterate
villagers are neither more nor less simple than those made by literate
people when they are for some reason deprived of the medium of
writing. Visiting markets in rural or urban areas of non-industrialized
countries, or strolling through the few remaining cattle-markets of
industrialized countries, it soon becomes evident that the transac¬
tions conducted in these places are extremely complicated; fairly
large amounts may be involved, equivalences may have to be
calculated between very varied products of quite different values, »
and all these dealings are carried out without a single written entry, f
This article is based on Contribution to Study of the Rural Environment
within the Framework of Functional Literacy Operations, a document
prepared by the Education Sector of Unesco.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
All social groups, however illiterate they may be, use arithmetic.
There is no known society that does not possess a sequence of
numbers, though not necessarily with the figure 10 as a base. Many
societies use counting systems based on 5 or 20. Some social
groups use two bases for their arithmetic, according to the type of
activity for which numbers are required. What is striking is the
remarkable agility in mental arithmetic which is displayed both for
practical purposes and in play, for many games require the use of a
highly developed combinative sense.
Another error is to assume that what distinguishes the illiterate, is
the lack of strict accuracy in the use of measurements of length,
area, weight and, especially, time. The peasant certainly does not
know about centigrade, millimetres and seconds; his own units of
measurement are those of experience and not objective units. Many
societies have, for example, a developed sense of the cycle of
events, particularly of agricultural cycles of good and bad crops, the
cycle of the seasons and of the moon. Many coherent systems of
measurement exist which use as units of measure various parts of
the body (hands, feet, etc).
The units of measurement used by illiterate villagers may strike us
as being rather lacking in precision. This does not mean that the
villager is not aware of this lack of precision or that he does not com¬
pensate for it in one way or another. The Western world also ex¬
perienced a similar variety of systems of weights and measures
without major drawbacks as long as the volume of goods traded was
comparatively small. Those involved in such transactions were
familiar with the various systems and switched from one to another
with the greatest of ease. Admittedly abuses may result from these
practices, but they always reflect a power struggle. The creditor,
having the upper hand, easily imposes his conditions on his debtors.
He does not cheat them, he robs them. They are quite aware of this
but are in no position to refuse transactions that are to their disad¬
vantage.
This was the case during the pre-harvesting season in Viet Nam
when the villagers from the mountain plateaux turned, in times of
difficulty, to merchants who lent them a can of paddy in exchange
for two cans of hulled rice to be paid back later once the harvest was
over. The villagers knew perfectly well and to what extent they were
being swindled, but there was no alternative for them as they had no
money to buy supplies.
The illiterate can legitimately boast of having developed a faculty
that industrialized societies have tended to neglect, namely memory,
one of the most important faculties. This functional memory could
even be said to be the main element that holds together these com¬
munities, which are sometimes of considerable size. Memory is the
key to the oral tradition, thanks to which a precious legacy of
knowledge of all kinds has been handed down through the cen¬
turies, especially in Africa (see the Unesco Courier,
August/September 1979). Memory in this instance is not merely
oral, however; it is made up not only of what has been said and
heard, but also of gestures of all kinds. This explains why rituals de¬
pend on memory, both collective and individual.
Careful consideration shows that literacy campaigns can benefit
greatly from the various types of memorization to be found in il¬
literate societies. Unfavourable comment has been made, for in¬
stance, about the so-called mechanical learning of the Koran in the
marabout schools of Africa. Undoubtedly, some criticism is
legitimate, but the fact remains that the memory is activated to a
remarkable degree and individual human potential is built up that
can certainly be used for new learning processes, and especially for
writing, reading and arithmetic.
Cloth woven by the Bobo people of the village of Bondouki, Upper Volta.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Ethnological- literature has amply shown that illiterate societies do
not lack systems of symbolic representation. Unfortunately these
systems are often not understood because many illiterate societies
are concerned not with figurative realism but with non-figurative
abstraction. A tourist strolling around a market in any non-European
country may stop to look at some richly patterned local material
which he finds decorative, but nothing more. If, however, he were
to delve more deeply, he would be astonished at the wealth of the
symbols that the patterns or motifs depicted in these products of
local craftsmanship conjure up in the minds of the people.
Representations of this kind are probably ill-suited to convey
technical messages. But it would be a mistake to claim that illiterates
are unable to read (and to draw and write, so to speak) images. All
that can be said is that they find it difficult to understand conven¬
tional graphic representations even if all the objects depicted are
within their visual experience. Either they do not visualize the objects
in their own surroundings in such a way, or they do not understand
the codification of the representation of reality.
It is also time to dispel the prejudice that the illiterate villager can¬
not grasp anything that is technical. If by techniques we mean
operations that make it possible to transform materials efficiently for
man's real and symbolic needs, then it is difficult to deny the villager
credit for mastery of such techniques. Consider the illiterate
carpenters who built those vast, magnificent pagoda roof structures
without a single nail, using only wooden dowels (as did the illiterate
carpenters of Europe until the end of the nineteenth century) and us¬
ing only a few perfectly adapted tools which owed nothing to
technically-minded Europe.
The prejudices most frequently expressed against traditional
cultivation methods are so categorical that no one bothers to acquire
more than a rudimentary knowledge of them, since it is generally
assumed that they are destined to disappear. This attitude deprives
us of the opportunity to appreciate the rich store of experience built
up over years by farming communities in their efforts to survive in
regions where living conditions are often very difficult.
Under the pressures of the world economy profound modifica¬
tions have taken place, bringing such results as the over-utilization
of land and the abandonment of soil conservation practices. The
villager' is perfectly well aware of this and, today, it is no longer so
certain that the old farming methods, for long considered sterile by
the Western world, should be eliminated. Indeed, attention is now
being given, in the Mediterranean area, to early farming methods
that ensured the subsistence of large social groups while limiting the
effects of erosion. A whole series of minor operations, seemingly
trivial but meticulously supervised, sufficed to protect the soil. It is
quite possible that in some countries and this is already the case in
the Sahel it will be necessary to return to "soft technology", a
term adopted, no doubt, so as to avoid having to acknowledge the
debt owed to "traditional" techniques.
Finally, it must be realized that if the countryman sometimes has
difficulty in adapting to new agricultural methods, this is not
because of some kind of deep-rooted mistrust which, with a great
deal of patience, may perhaps be overcome; rather it is because he
feels (even if he does not always say so explicitly) that the adoption
of such methods would disrupt his entire social structure, his whole
system of reference as well as all his customs. He knows that a new
technique is not just a technique as such, but an expression of the
society that produced it.
' I was made to work
like a plough'
by Yusufu Selemani
I had missed the opportunity for schooling during my childhood
because the nearest school was forty-three miles away. When
I grew up I felt very bitter about that. Those were hard times.
But now educational facilities have been brought closer to the
people to the village and work-place. And so I was only too hap¬
py to take advantage of this great opportunity for learning right
here at my factory.
When I was first employed at this factory, I used to face burden¬
some problems because of my illiteracy. Whenever I was asked to
carry a bag of coffee, my supervisor had to accompany me to the
store to make sure that I deposited a bag of coffee of a particular
grade in the appropriate storage places. Now that I have become
literate, I can do this job all by myself without being physically
escorted by my supervisor. How can you as an adult and father of
children tolerate being treated like a child "go there, take this,
bring that"all under close physical supervision? But now I can
even detect mistakes made in the storage exercise and point them
out to the supervisor.
I can now read all the letters I receive from my relatives and
friends and I am able to reply to them. I can without anyone's help
send money home. Previously I had to beg and implore someone
to help me write letters for me to my wife and send her some
money whenever she went home. In that process, all my secrets
were exposed. It is also possible that the person who writes letters
for you to your wife can write a lot of rubbish and you don't know
about it.
Literacy has opened our eyes and it has done us such a lot of
good that I now believe that if anyone refuses to become literate
he should be dismissed from his job. I now realize that when I was
illiterate I was made to work like a plough being dragged by a cow
and that was a humiliating experience.
The benefits of literacy are innumerable. Now that I have
become literate I feel that before I was carrying a small lantern but
now a pressure lamp has been brought to me. I can now see much
better. I can now hold a pen and sign my own name instead of us¬
ing a fingerprint.
As a result of literacy I now understand the whys and
wherefores of things and because I understand I can now maintain
my own self-respect. If I see a signpost which says "Don't Pass", I
stop and thereby preserve my self-respect. If I don't obey the in¬
structions I will lose my self-respect. People realize that yesterday
and the day before this man used to get his letters written but now
he can write them himself.
Literacy has broadened my mind. For example, through literacy
primers I have now learned the best methods of growing maize on
my little plot of land.
Before, the word education used to terrify me. When you heard
that someone had an education you were led to believe that it was
something very difficult and inaccessible. Previously it never oc¬
curred to me that the so-called educated man must have started
from scratch too that is, by acquiring the basic literacy skills first.
Instead, you thought that this man was born with education. It
was a baffling phenomenon. Education had the aura of some kind
of magic. But now I know that anyone can learn and anyone can
get an education. I realize that education is a thing that is taught to
you and education is development.
Ndugu Yusufu Selemani is a worker at the Tanganyika Coffee Cur¬
ing Company Limited, Moshi (Tanzania). He is thirty-eight years
old and has been working at the factory since 1967. He is married
and has five children. He started to learn to read and write in 1975.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The experience of adults may
complicate the learning task. An
implement (here a hunting knife
from Central Africa) is still an
implement regardless of what
direction it is turned or its
handle pointed. A letter form,
by contrast, may have several
different values (b, d, p, for
example) which are entirely
dependent on its positioning.
For the world's millions of
adults who have never even
encountered a written language
the attainment of literacy means
initiation into a new world of
signs and symbols, the
development of powers of
recognition and association
which may be very different
from those used in everyday life.
the written code
Mother tongues
and access to literacy
by John W. Ryan
EFFORTS to promote literacy depend
upon the learner's motivation to learn
and this inclination is strongly condi¬
tioned by his social, political and economic
circumstances, perceptions and aspirations.
The landless peasant of Asia cannot be
made literate until the basic conditions of his
life are transformed. The same is true of the
Arab housewife, the African tribesman, the
dwellers in a Latin American favella or an
American ghetto. Literacy has meaning and
is actively sought only when it leads to fuller
participation in culture and society and to a
more equal sharing of social, economic and
political rights and privileges.
22
In addition to these social, economic and
political pre-conditions of literacy a number
of important linguistic factors condition the
success of literacy programmes.
In teaching children to read, a great deal
of attention is given to readiness. It is usual¬
ly tacitly assumed that adults because of
their maturity are ready to begin literacy in¬
struction immediately. But it has to be
remembered that the term "illiterate" does
not denote a precise state but rather a con¬
tinuum including, at one pole, those who
have never encountered a written language
and at the other, the semi-literate. The lat¬
ter, who in most developing countries will
be primary school drop-outs, may indeed be
ready to proceed immediately to literacy in¬
struction. Their months or years in school
may not have made them literate, but they
will have acquainted them with the
"secrets" of the written code.
.The "naive" illiterate, on the other hand,
will have to develop powers of recognition,
association and discrimination before lit¬
eracy instruction can be usefully begun. In¬
deed, it has been observed that the life ex¬
periences of adults may complicate rather
than facilitate the learning task to pe
mastered. A hoe, for example, is still a hoe
regardless of what direction its blade is turn¬
ed or its handle pointed. A letter form, by
contrast, may have several different values
which are entirely dependent upon its posi¬
tioning: for example, b, d, p or q.
Knowledge of such conventions cannot be
assumed, but must be systematically and
carefully taught. The danger in classes of
mixed ability the usual situation in adult
literacy courses is that the teacher may
assume that because basic principles are
understood by some, they are understood
by all. When this occurs, the unschooled il¬
literate is lost at the outset.
JOHN W. RYAN of the United States of Amer¬
ica, is a literacy training specialist and a member
of Unesco's Literacy, Adult Education and Rural
Development Division. The author of many
studies and articles on literacy problems, he was,
from 1971 to 1979, Director of the International
Institute for Adult Literacy Methods, Teheran,
Iran.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Word recognition is another area where
essential skills have to be developed before
literacy instruction can begin. A principle of
pedagogy is to begin where the learner is. In
the teaching of literacy, the obvious "entry
point" is with the spoken language, assum¬
ing the learner commands it adequately. The
success of such a teaching strategy,
however, depends not only upon the degree
of correspondence between the written and
the spoken media, but also upon the ability
of the learner to recognize such similarities.
A literate individual is conscious of letters
and words as basic language units and con¬
veys his awareness to those around him. For
the naive speaker, orthographic words do
not necessarily possess psychological reali¬
ty; they are not perceived as the intuitive
units from which language is constructed.
Speech is perceived as a stream of meaning
rather than as a delicate mosaic of words. In
pre-literate or illiterate societies, there may
be a sophisticated language consciousness,
but it is not necessarily focused on those
aspects of the spoken language upon which
the learning of the written language will
depend.
An awareness of these features will,
therefore, have to be developed. Unfor¬
tunately, this is often neglected. It is a per¬
sonal observation, confirmed by the pattern
of drop-out statistics, that the first lessons
of a literacy course are the most critical.
Once the fundamental ideas of the written
language are understood and the requisite
auditory and psychomotor skills developed,
literacy instruction can proceed with sur¬
prising speed and success in supportive
environments.
On the basis of what is known of the
reading process particularly the finding
that fluent reading appears to depend upon
an ability to anticipate the meaning of
passages it would be expected that one of
the important factors in achieving literacy in
a language would be the learner's mastery of
its spoken form. Empirical evidence con¬
firms this expectation. Recognizing this rela¬
tionship, international meetings have
recommended that initial literacy should,
wherever possible, be achieved in the
learner's mother tongue.
Yet, even a cursory examination of the
language situation in developing nations
suggests how difficult it will be to apply this
recommendation. To seek to do so is to con¬
front two obstacles: the vast multiplicity of
languages spoken in many developing coun¬
tries and the meagreness of available
resources, both financial and manpower, for
rendering the spoken languages effective
media for literacy instruction.
Thomas P. Gorman in his review, "Lit¬
eracy in the Mother Tongue: a Reappraisal"
draws a striking comparison between the
language situation in the Soviet Union and
Europe and that in Africa.
"There are more languages spoken in
Tanzania than in the USSR and more
languages spoken in the Cameroon than in
CONTINUED PAGE 26
Outdoor reading lesson with
improvised "blackboard" in the
People's Republic of the Congo.
For many reasons it is preferable
to teach people to read and
write in their mother tongue,
but in some developing
countries problems arise when a
language does not exist in
written form and long-term
research has to be undertaken
to establish an alphabet and
determine linguistic rules. As a
result many adults throughout
the world are seeking to attain
literacy in a second language in
which they may not be fluent.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
loyr*é!«'
*m^
kékére
The 3 "R's"-
an open book
ré té
ké ké
é
k I kit
loutetá'té kékelé loùté
kélc Iské
6 PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF THE CONGO
On this double page we present a montage of teaching materials
from six countries which are seeking to wipe out illiteracy:
Bolivia, the People's Republic of the Congo, Costa Rica, Ethiopia,
Mexico and Niger. Whereas in the past educators often had to
make do with imported textbooks in which words, illustrations
and subjects bore little relation to local conditions, many
countries have now created their own teaching materials. The
new generation of primers, manuals and other visual aids are
designed and written with the specific interests of local
populations in mind and are also adapted to the needs of the
various categories of teachers. The materials embody a variety of
approaches. Some literacy programmes, for example, merely
seek to teach the skills of reading and writing. However, since
illiteracy, poverty and sickness are interrelated in the isolated
rural areas where the overwhelming majority of the world's
illiterates live, literacy teaching often forms part of a concerted
effort to cope with these problems, and the teaching materials
convey practical information about diet, housing and other ways
of attaining a better material life. (1) Ornate filigreed crosses are
used as symbols in these subtraction exercises in an Ethiopian
teaching aid. After doing the sums the pupil is asked to write
them out using figures. (2) In lesson one of a Costa Rican primer
the student gets to grips with the basic hand movements used in
cursive writing. (3) A Bolivian manual for Aymara Indians with
exercises based on the Aymara words for comb, bridge, river,
cloth and eagle. (4) The sounds of a squeaking mouse and
hooting owl as used in a Mexican primer for Maya Indians of the
Yucatan peninsula during a campaign to teach literacy
simultaneously in Maya and the national language, Spanish.
(51 A textbook produced by Niger in Hausa. which is one of the
most important languages in West Africa, combines literacy
teaching with advice about health care here the prevention and
treatment of malaria. The mother is taught how to recognize the
symptoms, to wrap her sick child in a blanket and provide
emergency treatment before taking him to the dispensary.
(6) Part of the transcription of the Lari language as used in a
literacy campaign in the People's Republic of the Congo. Many
countries in Africa, where more languages are spoken than on
any other continent, are currently engaged in the transcription of
hitherto unwritten tongues. Unesco's activities in support of this
long-term effort to promote African languages as media of
culture and instruments of lifelong education cover a broad
spectrum, including contributions to the training of specialists,
the preparation of dictionaries, spelling books and grammars,
and a variety of material for use in literacy work.
Photos All Rights Reserved
24
MVf> nft*
nt-rc t-f*-
1 ETHIOPIA
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Ulc.r
5 NIGER
4 MEXICO
Ejercicios de /vu
.Trof «»to, 6vo/01 . . BOMCOI
I O le
' má» rápido
ÎSSBiSTâ*.
mejor
^ft-
^C^r0t'dTd*°0"^or
3 BOLIVIA
2 COSTA RICA
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 23
the Soviet Union and Eastern and Western
Europe combined. Yet there are almost
three times as many languages spoken in
Nigeria as in Cameroon."
The situation in many developing States
outside Africa is similar. There are, for ex¬
ample, over 800 languages spoken in In¬
donesia and over 600 in Papua New Guinea,
a country of fewer than three million in¬
habitants. Moreover, the vast majority of
the languages in developing countries are
unwritten, unstandardized languages
spoken by communities of a few hundred or
a few thousand persons.
Confronted with these facts, it becomes
apparent that a rational policy for literacy
promotion imposes a painful choice: in
which languages should literacy instruction
be offered and literacy be attained? A cor¬
ollary to this is that in many countries a ma¬
jority of participants in adult literacy courses
will be seeking to attain literacy in a
language other than their mother tongue.
The alternative is a long-term one: the
making of orthographies and the standar¬
dization and development of languages into
media capable of conveying information and
ideas that a modernizing society will require.
The planners of literacy programmes are,
thus, in the meantime, faced with a dilem¬
ma. For pedagogical reasons it may be best
to begin with the mother tongue or more
accurately with a language which the learner
commands fluently, be it his mother tongue
or a language learned later in life but this
best choice will often prove a practical im¬
possibility or, if possible, may lead to a dead
end if there are not opportunities and incen¬
tives to read and write regularly in the
mother tongue.
The practical implication of this situation
for the adult literacy class is that many
learners will be seeking to achieve literacy in
languages which they do not command
fluently. Thus, the literacy class is going to
be engaged in two distinct forms of instruc¬
tion: second language learning and literacy
training. It has been pointed out that these
are fundamentally different operations and
should not be confused with one another, as
they too often are. Gorman suggests that in
such situations greater use might be made
of "diglot" materials: i.e., materials using
two languages, one better known to the par¬
ticipants which serves as a bridge to the
language in which literacy is ultimately to be
attained. He notes, however, that such
materials, although often recommended,
have been seldom used because of the prac¬
tical difficulties their preparation presents.
One aspect of the issue of language
choice relates directly to the development of
orthographies. Recognizing that learners in
multilingual societies will frequently be re¬
quired to achieve literacy in more than one
language, it has been frequently recom¬
mended that related or adjacent languages
make use of the same or similar or¬
thographies. In this way, the task of achiev¬
ing literacy in a second language is
facilitated. A related advantage is that the
same typesetting and printing equipment
can be used for several languages.
The outstanding example in this respect is
the experience of the USSR which has com¬
bined a policy of language preservation and
development with measures directed
towards an increasing standardization of na¬
tional orthographies based on the Cyrillic
alphabet. In West Africa, an agreement has
been reached among neighbouring states to
develop a unified orthographic system for
six language groups: Hausa, Kanuri, the
Mande group, Fulani, Songhai-Zerma and
Tamashek. This latter development
represents a considerable departure from
the colonial period where two or more or¬
thographies were sometimes developed and
put into use for the same trans-national
language by different colonial authorities.
The development of orthographies must
be seen as one aspect of national and/or
regional language policies and not as a
technical exercise to be performed in isola¬
tion. The promotion of literacy, in many
countries, rests on the formulation of
coherent language policies and the develop¬
ment of instructional approaches which take
into account the realities of the learning
situation these policies impose.
John W. Ryan
Those who have acquired
the basic skills of literacy
are in danger of losing them
unless they are provided
with a continuous supply of
interesting reading material.
Unesco has for many years
been active in advising and
helping developing countries
to meet this need through
newspapers specially written
for newly literate persons in
rural areas. Left, three of
Africa's rural newspapers:
Kisomo (Education) in
Kikuyu (Kenya); Kibaru (The
News) in Bambara (Mali);
Game Su (It is Time) in Ewe
(Togo).
Photos Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Letters for
a young nation
by Paulo Freiré
The Democratic Republic of Sao Tomé and Principe consists of
two volcanic islands situated in the Gulf of Guinea, some 300
kilometres from the coast of Africa. Formerly a Portuguese
colony, this small country (964 sq. km.; population less than
100,000) achieved independence in 1975 and became a member
of Unesco on 22 January 1980. Its economy is based on
agriculture, the main crops being cocoa, coffee, palm oil and
copra. Below we present excerpts from a literacy teaching
handbook prepared by the Brazilian educator Paulo Freiré as a
contribution to a literacy campaign recently launched in Sao
Tomé and Principe. The handbook is written in the form of
letters addressed to the country's literacy workers and shows
how the method of education based on "conscientization",
which Freiré has developed, can be put into practice. It is
published by the Co-ordinating Commission of the Popular
Culture Circles of the Republic of Sao Tomé and Principe.
OUR task is to enable many of our
comrades, especially but not exclu¬
sively those living in rural areas, to
read and write, which they were forbidden
to do under the colonial régime. This task is
a political one. The very decision to teach
people to read and write is a political act.
And come what may we must be on our
guard against insinuations, sometimes in¬
genuous, sometimes sly, which are made to
convince us that teaching reading and
writing is purely a technical matter, a ques¬
tion of training, and that accordingly it
should not be "mixed up with politics". The
fact is that education, teaching adults to
read and write, can never be neutral. All
education presupposes, by its very nature, a
political intention.
And so, as the people's educators and
"candidates for education", we should con¬
stantly be bringing our political choices into
clearer focus and making sure that there is
no contradiction between our self-
proclaimed objectives and the work we do.
We must be clear-minded about our
ultimate aims and clear-minded about those
for whom our work as educators is intend¬
ed. And the focus becomes sharper as we
devote ourselves, in a militant and critical
spirit, to our practical tasks, and as a result
we can learn more about how we should
act. The proper form of militancy is that
which teaches us that only through unity,
discipline and work with the people shall we
become educators conforming to the
revolutionary choice which we proclaim.
In Sao Tomé and Principe our most
urgent need is for clear-thinking militants
who can become specialists through work¬
ing with the people, not for "experts" who
are remote from the people, do not believe
in the people, and are incapable of com¬
municating with the people.
If teaching people to read and write, like
all education, is a political act, it is also an
act of knowledge. In the relationship bet¬
ween the educator and the person being
educated, the acquisition of a piece of
knowledge is always at stake. And in
broaching this problem we are bound to in¬
sist, yet again, that there must be no in¬
coherence between our political choice and
our practical work as educators. For exam¬
ple, can we as revolutionary educators act
towards those who are being educated in
the same way as colonialist teachers, con¬
forming to a colonialist ideology, behaved
towards "their" pupils? When faced with
this question, we must not simply tell
ourselves that we should be different from
colonialist teachers; we must consciously
adopt a practice which is totally opposed to
theirs.
The colonialist educator usually transmit¬
ted "his" knowledge to us, and it was up to
us to swallow wholesale this knowledge
which, to cap everything, distorted our own
experience by colouring it with the interests
of the colonialists. The colonialist who
taught reading and writing "taught" that b
and a equalled "Ba", and this had to be
repeated and memorized by the learner.
Our revolution now underway demands
us to be in tune with it at every level of our
action. And so we do not talk of "Night
Schools for Adults" but of "Circles of
Culture"; we do not speak of illiterates but
of persons "on the way to literacy"; we do
not speak of . "literacy teachers" but of
"Culture Group Leaders" who work with the
Circles of Culture; we do not talk about
lessons but about debates, about the peo¬
ple's authentic experience referred to by
what are called "generator words" and
depicted in "codification" which is analysed
and discussed with the people.
And so, in a society in which "silence is
not possible", the function of the man or
woman who becomes a culture group
leader, considered in relation to the
members of the group who are on the way
to literacy, is not that of a transmitter of
knowledge but that of someone who,
through discussion, tries to learn jointly with
those who are on the way to literacy.
According to the political principles which
guide our movement, literacy teaching is an k
activity during which the persons on the Y
PAULO FREIRÉ, noted Brazilian educator, is the
originator of a method of literacy teaching which
has attracted widespread attention. He developed
this system, which is based on encouraging
adults to become "critically conscious" of their
situation, in Brazil, Chile and other Latin Ameri¬
can countries. Formerly professor of history and
philosophy of education at the university of
Recife (Brazil) and a visiting professor at Harvard,
he has also worked with the United Nations and
Unesco. He is now a consultant with the World
Council of Churches in Geneva. Among his
published works in English translation are: Peda¬
gogy of the Oppressed (Penguin, London, 1972),
Education for Critical Consciousness (Sheed and
Ward, London, 1974) and Education and the
Practice of Freedom (Writers and Readers Pub¬
lishing Co-operative, London).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
way to literacy and the group leaders jointly
' "read and write their own reality, thinking
critically about their world, becoming more
aware and integrating themselves more fully
in a real situation which is being transform¬
ed". And so it is of paramount importance
that we should not remain at the "b and a
equals ba" stage but should slowly,
together with the comrades who are learn¬
ing with us, come to a "reading", a "new
reading" of our experience. Another con¬
sequence of this approach is that we must
relate literacy teaching to production and
health, and link it whenever we can with
concrete community action programmes.
Since we conceive of literacy teaching as
a cultural activity in favour of the
reconstruction of our country and not simp¬
ly as training pupils how to read and write,
we may find in some parts of the country
that our work with the people has to focus
initially on a "reading", "rereading" and
"writing" of reality and not on language
learning.
This means that in certain situations the
crucial thing is to organize the people in
groups and discuss with them their real ex¬
perience, always in terms of down-to-earth
activities; to analyse local conditions with
them and find solutions to some of their
problems in such fields as health and produc¬
tion; to encourage them to organize
themselves, for example, around a com¬
munity work project, a collective farm. And
the act of "reading", "rereading" and
"writing" their own experience in this way
may induce them to want to read and write .
words as well, acquiring a skill which comes
to possess a real meaning for them.
In other instances, cultural action begins
with literacy teaching per se. In these cases
the literacy teaching should be a kind of
launching pad for a determined effort to
create projects in which the people can
make an impact on the local situation. A
dynamic relationship is thus established bet¬
ween the educational work of the culture
groups and the down-to-earth task of
transforming a real-life situation; each activi¬
ty is vitalized and revitalized by the other.
Now I should like to raise a number of
points which, when explained, will help us
to understand what the Culture Groups
should do. These points can be summed up
in three terms: the "generator word",
"codification", and "decodification".
A generator word is one which, chosen in
accordance with certain criteria, can be
broken down into component syllables
which when combined enable other words
to be formed. If, for example, we take the
word MATÁBALA, the name of a root
vegetable widely cultivated in Sao Tomé,
and break it down into its syllables, we
obtain:
ma, me, mi, mo, mu
ta, te, ti, to, tu
ba, be, bi, bo, bu
la, le, li, lo, lu
We call each group of syllables a
"family"; hence we have the ma, me, mi,
mo, mu family; the ta, te, ti, to, tu family,
etc.
Using these four families, a series of
words can be created, such as: mata (tuft of
grass); mate (maté, infusion); meta (goal,
objective); mimo (pampering), lata (tin); tela
(cloth, fabric); tomo (I take); tomate
(tomato); tema (theme); cola (tail); libelo
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Learning to read is a political act and constitutes a step
towards full participation in the life of the community.
Men and women, whether literate or not, are creators of
culture. Some of the conditions in which people live are
man-made and can therefore be changed. The difference
between nature and culture is based on the distinction
between man and the other animals, and in this
distinction oral and written language plays an important
role. These are some of the principles which form the
basis of the method of adult education originated by
Paulo Freiré, the Brazilian educator and sociologist.
Working in Recife (Brazil) Freiré was instrumental in
creating a number of "Circles of Culture" whose
members, aided by a series of ten pictures and without
any written material, were encouraged to analyse the
realities of their lives (in a process which Freiré called
"conscientization") and to become aware that they could
transform the situation in which they lived. Reproduced
on these pages are four of the pictures, the work of the
Brazilian artist Francisco Brennand. Left: an image
designed to show a basic distinction between nature and
culture. The co-ordinator of the Circle of Culture asked
questions such as: Who made the well? Why did he do
so? Who made the house? the hoes? the book? Who
made the tree? the pig? the birds? In what way is the tree
different from the well? Gradually the discussion moved
to the conclusion that people use natural materials to
change their situation and create culture. Members of the
circle knew the distinction but the discussion taught
them words to clarify it. The second discussion,
prompted by picture above left, concerned the
relationship between people. People can create culture,
whereas animals cannot, and people can communicate
extensively with each other. The natural world is real and
can be known through investigation and dialogue.
Communication should take place as a dialogue between
equals. Picture at left illustrates the transformation of
nature into culture. Not only has the clay been
transformed into a vase but flowers, which in the field are
part of nature, have been changed into culture by the
person who arranged them. In this picture a "graphic
symbol" is introduced for the first time, in the drawing of
flowers which decorates the vase. Nature, transformed
into culture, has been transformed once again, this time
into a written symbol. The last of the ten pictures (above)
enabled the group to look at itself and reflect on its own
activity. It shows a Circle of Culture at work and the
members could easily identify it as representing
themselves. The function of the Circle was examined:
what the experience signified, what dialogue was, what it
meant to develop one's consciousness. By now the
participants had gained great confidence and pride in
their culture, and the desire to learn to read. The next
stage was literacy teaching in the strict sense (see
overleaf).
(pamphlet); batuta (orchestra conductor's
baton); bebo (I drink); batata (sweet
potato); and so on.
But it should be stressed that where these
"families" of syllables are concerned, the
role, of the Group Leader is not to form the
words but to encourage the persons on the
way to literacy to create them for them¬
selves.
Nevertheless, whenever the group leader
notices that the learners seem to be hanging
back because they feel shy, he should en¬
courage them by creating two or three
words himself. This is a common occur¬
rence during work on the first generator
words.
The generator words are always
associated with certain themes which
should be dealt with in the Circles of
Culture. The word matábala, for example,
can be the starting point for discussions on a
series of themes such as production, the
need for crop diversification, or the nutri¬
tional qualities of plants, which in turn leads
to the problem of health. This question, like
that of production, can and should broaden
out into a political analysis concerning, for
example, the conscious participation of the
people in boosting production and in health
care.
The generator words are not chosen at
random but in accordance with certain
criteria such as thematic richness, in other
words the variety of themes to which they
refer and which can be connected with the
local experience of those on the way to
literacy and make it possible to analyse cer¬
tain aspects of the national situation;
phonetic richness and the possibilities of¬
fered by these words to the learners when
overcoming difficulties such as the sounds
LHA, NHA, double s, double r, and so on.
The word codification, put in in its
simplest terms, means the graphic represen¬
tation of reality, as in a poster, a photograph
or a film strip. The generator word is
superimposed on the codification.
Let us take as an example the word
PUEBLO (people) as given in the First
Notebook of Popular Culture, a guide for
literacy teachers and learners. The codifica¬
tion of the word PUEBLO is a photograph of
a popular demonstration on Independence
Day, with the people gathered in the square
which is now theirs.
It should be stressed that codification
must always be considered as a challenge
for the group and the group leader, as an
"object" which must be analysed by the
group with the participation of the leader,
and not as an aid which he "gives to his
class".
Decodification is the act of analysing the
poster or photograph. Decodifying a graphic
representation of certain aspects of the real
world gives us a "reading" of reality. The
group leader plays an important and sen¬
sitive role in this process. He must not be
too self-effacing, nor must he intervene too
much; decodification is a dialogue in which
all the learners are involved. While respec¬
ting the way in which the group com¬
prehends the meaning of its experience, he
should also provoke debate so that both he
and the learners can together progress to
more complex ways of understanding their
world.
It now becomes apparent that a culture |
group is a school but a school with a dif-J
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ference in which there are neither
teachers, nor pupils, nor lessons in the tradi¬
tional sense. The culture group is not a cen¬
tre for the diffusion of knowledge but a
place a school hall, a room in a house, a
shady spot under a tree, or a cabin built by
the community where a group of com¬
rades meet to discuss what they do at work,
the local and national situation and also in
certain cases to read and write.
In this "school with a difference" the
traditional type of teacher who talks and
then makes the pupil illustrate and repeat
what he has said, is replaced by the culture
group leader, who should be a militant who
sees things clearly. Instead of the passive
pupil, the "illiterate" who is on the receiving
end of the teacher's lessons, there is
someone who is on the way to literacy,
someone who is as much a participant in the
group's activities as its leader. Instead of
reading primers, which the pupils have to il¬
lustrate with drawings and repeat from
memory, we have generator themes referred
to by generator words, both themes and
words being depicted in the "codifications".
Now let us look for a few moments at the
work of the culture group leader. First of all,
since his or her task as an educator has a
political dimension and is not that of the
teacher who gives purely technical instruc¬
tion in reading and writing from a supposed¬
ly neutral point of view, it is not confined to
debates within the group but should range
widely over the life of the district, farm or
village in which the group meets. The more
deeply the leader identifies with the people,
the better he or she performs his or her
political-educational task.
It may help the leader if he gets into the
habit of jotting down in a notebook things
that attract his attention in the area where
the group meets. He should also make a
point of noting down salient points from the
group's discussions. These notes will be of
great help in day-to-day work and will be ex¬
tremely valuable when it comes to the
evaluation seminars which we shall have to
hold with everyone.
Another possibility is for the group leader
to present from time to time as discussion
topics some of the observations he has
made during the group's sessions, as well as
impressions drawn from his experience
within the community. However, it is essen
tial to avoid any comments of a personal
nature and he must be sure not to lose the
respect he should feel for the people. When
presenting one of his observations to the
group, the leader should act as someone
who is questioning himself and trying to
learn; he should not hold forth about what
he has noted down. This does not mean,
however, that he should not also express his
way of seeing things.
While the group leader should not allow
the group's activities to revolve around him,
he should not be the only one to have a say,
nor always have the last word and give the
impression that he knows all the answers,
neither should he be reserved and self-
effacing.
Both the group leader and "those on the
way to literacy" must be active participants
in the culture group. In the political perspec¬
tive which is ours, in accordance with the
principles of our movement, it is not the
leader's role either to manipulate the
learners or to leave them to their own
devices. In other words we should try to
steer a middle course between control and
spontaneity.
Paulo Freiré
30
Literacy in 30 hours
Paulo Freiré believes that adults can learn to read rapidly as long as reading is not part of a "cultural
imposition" on them and that teaching is rooted in the daily life of the community. He and his
colleagues discovered that no more than 17 words (which they call "generator words") were necessary
as a basis for teaching adults to read Portuguese and Spanish. According to Freire's method, which has
been practised in Brazil and other Latin American countries, as well as Sao Tomé and Principe, the ideas
represented by these words must be critically discussed before the words themselves are analysed as
"graphic symbols". And so a picture was prepared to illustrate each word. In the case of the word tijolo
("brick" in Portuguese) the picture (called a "codification" in Freire's terminology) depicted a
construction scene. At first the picture was shown without the word tijolo. Only after the group had
taken part in a discussion (the process which Freiré calls "decodification") on building with bricks, their
own houses, and housing as a community problem, was a second picture introduced which showed the
construction scene together with the word tijolo (above). In the third picture the word tijolo appeared alone.
The same procedure was followed for the 16 other words. The adults learned, to read in 30 to 40 hours.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
UNRWA and Unesco:
a thirty-year partnership
A comprehensive education service
for Palestine refugees
by Hussein Husnu Feridun
AUGUST 1980 will mark the 30th
anniversary of a unique internatio¬
nal co-operative effort in educa¬
tion. In August 1950, Unesco entered into a
partnership with UNRWA, the United Na¬
tions Relief and Works Agency for Palestine
Refugees in the Near East, to provide educa¬
tion services for a people who had been the
victims of a situation which reduced them to
the state of refugees.
During the Palestine conflict t of 1948,
some 750,000 Palestine Arabs fled 'from their
homes and lands and sought refuge in parts
of Palestine which had not been proclaimed
as Israel the Gaza Strip and on the West
Bank of the River Jordan or in neighbour¬
ing Arab countries (Jordan, the Syrian Arab
Republic and Lebanon).
This exodus has had far-reaching con¬
sequences over the years. It has compelled
Palestinians to transform their way of life.
Until 1948 some two-thirds of the in¬
habitants of Palestine made their living from
agriculture; today, as refugees, they have
become a more diversified community. For
them the education and professional
achievement of their children represent not
only a vital practical necessity but also a
form of moral support and a source of pride,
the pride of a people who have little else.
The sudden arrival of some hundreds of
thousands of refugees in the neighbouring
Arab countries during 1948-49 created so
many urgent relief problems (food, shelter,
health care) that, at first, only the most im¬
mediate and elementary needs could be
met.
Nevertheless, .although provision for
education was not formally part of the pro¬
gramme of the then United Nations Relief
for Palestine Refugees (UNRPR), efforts
were made in the winter of 1948-49 to pro¬
vide some welfare and educational
assistance to the children among the
refugees. International voluntary and
religious organizations served as the
operating agencies for UNRPR in the field of
education, and with funds from Unesco to
the amount of $38,000 in 1949, the first
classes for refugee children began in the
camps. In some instances, the refugees
themselves made the initial moveteachers
who took charge of children they knew and
could collect together; sheikhs who gave
readings from the Koran, and so on. The
very first classes were held in the open air,
without desks, blackboards, copy books or
pencils. However, by 1 May 1950, 64 such
schools had been established, employing
730 teachers and providing elementary
education for 33,631 children, in the propor¬
tion of about three boys to one girl.
On 8 December 1949, the General
Assembly established the United Nations
Relief and Works Agency for Palestine
Refugees in the Near East (UNRWA), which
thus took over from UNRPR as from 1 May
1950.
Again in 1950, following an appeal
launched by the UN General Assembly,
Unesco undertook activities on behalf of the
Palestine refugees in the Near East. An
agreement was signed betwen the
Commissioner-General of UNRWA and the
Director-General of Unesco. Under the
terms of this agreement, which was
renewable every two years, Unesco assum¬
ed technical responsibility for the educa¬
tional services to be provided by UNRWA
for the children of registered Palestine
refugees. This marked the birth of the
UNRWA/Unesco Education Programme for
the Palestine Arab refugees.
From the first UNRWA/Unesco agree¬
ment in 1950-51, the emphasis of the
Unesco contribution and participation has
been on technical guidance and direction of
the refugee education programme.
Recommendations of the UNRWA/
Unesco Department of Education on educa¬
tion matters have been crucial over the past
thirty years in the formulation of policies and
the development of programmes for
Palestine Arab refugee education. Each new
step in the development of the education
programme can usually be traced back to a
Unesco source.
To give practical effect and proper
technical direction to the programme,
Unesco has made itself reponsible for
seconding appropriate experts to UNRWA,
and paying their salaries, for varying periods
of service. In a certain way, Unesco
assistance to UNRWA has been unique.
Unesco experts are usually provided as ad¬
visers or consultants to governments and in¬
stitutions; but in the UNRWA context, the
Unesco experts are executors and super¬
visors as well as advisers or consultants.
Special reference must be made to
Unesco's efforts towards solving the text¬
book problem for UNRWA's schools in the
occupied territories of the West Bank and
the Gaza Strip, following the 1967
Arab/ Israeli war.
After June 1967, the Israeli occupation
authorities banned the use of most of the
textbooks in UNRWA/Unesco schools in
the occupied territories on the grounds that
they incited hatred. UNRWA referred the
matter to the Director-General of Unesco
and it has occupied the attention of the
Unesco Executive Board at various sessions
from the seventy-seventh, in November
1967, to the present.
On the basis of Executive Board deci¬
sions, the Director-General has been engag¬
ed in taking action towards resolving the
textbook problem. Textbooks for the West
Bank and the Gaza Strip approved by the
Director-General of Unesco are subject to
the further requirement of a special import
permit from the Israeli authorities. As a
result, on 1 April 1980, there were 28 text¬
books which had been approved by Unesco
but refused import permits by the occupa¬
tion authorities into the West Bank and
Gaza Strip.
Another important activity by Unesco was
the organization in August 1969 with the
collaboration of the Egyptian and Israeli
authorities, of the Egyptian secondary
school leaving certificate examinations for
some 7,000 boys and girls (the majority of
whom are refugees) in the Gaza Strip. The
hostilities of June 1967 had halted this Egyp¬
tian State examination in Gaza, and con¬
sequently thousands of young people who
had completed their secondary education
were being denied the opportunity to qualify
for entry to higher level studies. The efforts
of Unesco were successful in solving this
crisis at the time. The holding of the ex¬
aminations under Unesco supervision in
Gaza was resumed from the summer of 1969
until 1979, when the Israeli authorities
ordered the Unesco team conducting these
examinations to leave the Strip.
Today, the education services provided by
the UNRWA/Unesco programme for
registered Palestine refugees are com¬
parable to a national system of education for
a population of nearly 1.8 million spread
over five fields of operation Lebanon, the
Syrian Arab Republic, Jordan and the
Israeli-occupied West Bank and Gaza Strip.
They comprise elementary education,
preparatory (lower secondary) education, k
vocational education and teacher training )
HUSSEIN HUSNU FERIDUN, of Cyprus, is
director of the UNRWA/Unesco Department of
Education, based in Vienna. An expert on science
teaching, he is the author of several articles and
studies on the development of educational
systems.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Thirty years ago, when Unesco began working in
partnership with the United Nations Relief and Works
Agency (UNRWA) to provide education for Palestine
refugees, many classes (above) were held in the open air
or in improvised classrooms set up in tents, with rocks as
benches and the desert sands as "blackboards". Photo
below, taken in 1980, shows buildings of UNRWA-Unesco
educational facilities for the large Palestine refugee
community living in the Jabal-el-Nuzha area of Amman,
the capital of Jordan. Today there are 628 UNRWA-
Unesco schools attended by over 340,000 refugee pupils.
.(both pre-service and in-service). In addi¬
tion, through a system of financial grants-in-
aid and scholarships, the UNRWA/Unesco
Department of Education has been pro¬
viding assistance for refugee students at the
upper secondary level in government or
private schools and at Middle Eastern
universities and other higher educational in¬
stitutions.
Today the enrolment ratio of registered
Palestine refugee children for the age group
corresponding to the elementary cycle is
83.5% (about 232,000), and for the age
group corresponding to the preparatory cy¬
cle this ratio is 70.5% (about 100,000). The
percentage of girls in each of these cycles is
47.7% and 45.4% respectively. From the
age group 15-17, corresponding to the
secondary cycle, 40.4% are attending
UNRWA/Unesco post-preparatory voca¬
tional training centres (about 2,300) and
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Left, student
pharmacists at an
UNRWA-Unesco centre
which provides
technical training for
young Palestine
refugees. Over 22,500
trainees have graduated
since the launching of
the UNRWA-Unesco
vocational and technical
training programme in
1953.
government and private secondary schools
(about 52,500). At post-secondary level
some 2,300 attend UNRWA/Unesco
technical and teacher training centres and
about 354 receive UNRWA fellowships to
attend higher educational institutions and
universities, mostly in the Arab States.
About 24% of the teaching force of 9,372
in the UNRWA/Unesco system are universi¬
ty graduates and of the total 43% are
women.
UNRWA/Unesco elementary and
preparatory schools have to follow the cur¬
riculum and textbooks prescribed by the
relevant Ministry of Education in the host
country where they are located. Although
this policy obliges the UNRWA/Unesco pro¬
gramme to operate four allied but different
systems of education with four curricula and
four sets of textbooks, it has the over¬
whelming advantage of permitting refugee
children in UNRWA/Unesco schools to take
State examinations at the end of each cycle,
and thus to qualify for upper secondary and
university education in the region on terms
of equal educational opportunity with the
local population.
The UNRWA/Unesco education system
provides six years of elementary and three
years of preparatory education (four in
Lebanon). When the education services
started in the 1950s many schools were ac¬
commodated in tents. Gradually these tents
were replaced by buildings specially con¬
structed for the purpose, though many
schools are still in unsuitable rented
premises. Today there are 628 administrative
school units which are accommodated in
423 buildings, through extensive double-
shifting. Of these buildings, 278 have been
constructed by UNRWA in the course of the
past 30 years.
The UNRWA/Unesco system operates
four teacher education centres: one in Jor¬
dan, one in Lebanon, and two in the West
Bank which take 50 per cent of their enrol¬
ment from the Gaza Strip. Total enrolment
capacity in the two-year courses at these
four teacher education centres is 740 men
and 620 women.
The programme is of two years' duration
and prepares teachers for the elementary cy¬
cle, with. some degree of specialization.
About six hundred teachers graduate from
the centres each year.
In the early years of UNRWA's existence
the vast majority of teachers in UNRWA/
Unesco schools had little experience and no
professional training.
In 1963, an estimated 90 per cent of the
UNRWA/Unesco school teachers were still
professionally unqualified, which was a ma¬
jor obstacle in the way of developing a
satisfactory education programme. The
UNRWA/Unesco Department of Education
recognized that an innovative approach to
teacher training was needed, and the UNR¬
WA/Unesco Institute of Education, a
specialized institution for in-service training
which has focussed on introducing modern
teaching methods throughout the UNR¬
WA/Unesco education programme, was
created and began operating in 1964, with
the aim of improving the quality of educa¬
tion in UNRWA/Unesco schools.
In the first stage of its operation, the In¬
stitute devoted most of its efforts to the up¬
grading of professionally unqualified
elementary school teachers. Later, in-
service courses were organized for
preparatory school teachers. With the
decline in the number of unqualified
teachers in UNRWA/Unesco schools, it was
possible to diversify the activities of the
Institute.
The UNRWA/Unesco vocational and
technical training programme provides op¬
portunities for young refugee men and
women, thereby augmenting the supply of
craftsmen for the developing Arab world,
craftsmen with the skills that are essential to
the progress of the area.
It dates from 1953/1954 when the Kalan-
dia (West Bank) and Gaza vocational train¬
ing centres were established for Palestine
refugees with a capacity of fewer than 400
trainees. Today there are seven UNR¬
WA/Unesco training centres, altogether of¬
fering about 40 different trade and technical
courses for post-preparatory and post-
secondary school graduates. The total train¬
ing capacity is 3,436 (including around 500
women). With the exception of a few one-
year courses, the courses cover two years.
Some 1,750 male and female trainees now
graduate from these vocational training
courses annually. More than 22,500 have
graduated since the training programme
began in 1953. Most of them work in the
Middle East.
Employment opportunities for vocational
training graduates in UNRWA's area of
operations and in the neighbouring Arab
States continue to exceed the output from
the UNRWA/Unesco training centres. At
the same time, applications from suitably
qualified Palestine refugees to join the train¬
ing centres greatly surpass the number of
places available. Already, to derive max¬
imum use of the training facilities, many
courses are operated on double-shifts.
Recently, funds to the extent of $2.5
millions have been made available by the
OPEC Special Fund which will be used to
expand the centres' capacities through
enlarging the existing facilities by providing
a wider range of current courses and exten¬
ding the double-shift arrangement.
It is obvious that the UNRWA/Unesco
Department of Education provides the
registered Palestine refugees with essential
educational services. Less obvious, but
perhaps equally important, is that the
educational system has significantly con¬
tributed to the preservation of the cultural
identity of a displaced and dispersed people.
The achievement of both objectives is an in¬
creasingly arduous task in a rapidly chang¬
ing world and in a political climate ag¬
gravated by recurring crises. The system is
correspondingly dynamic and in need of
continuously increasing support in order
that its immediate and long-term objectives
can be met.
Unfortunately, as has happened all too
frequently in the past, the programme is at
present threatened with serious cut-backs
unless UNRWA's cash deficit of over $56
million for 1980 can be bridged. Out of this
huge deficit, savings of about $16 million
will need to be made in the school pro¬
gramme unless additional funds are received
from the international community.
It is paradoxical that this programme, the
largest single and longest lasting United Na¬
tions co-operative enterprise in the field of
education, may have to be drastically curtail¬
ed or wiped out because of lack of funds.
Hussein Husnu Feridun
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
The reading habit
ALTHOUGH statistics on the world's
illiterate populations are relatively
easy to obtain, little is known about
the millions of literate adults, who, in both
the developed and the developing countries,
rarely pick up a book or open a magazine, or
about schoolchildren for whom reading has
come to mean textbooks and little else.
The causes of this phenomenon are all the
more difficult to determine because there is
not one kind but many kinds of reading, and
because reading habits vary considerably ac¬
cording to age group, educational level and
socio-cultural background.
Many influences promote or deter the
development of the reading habit. They are
sometimes -subtle and often interrelated,
and are not always straightforward or evi¬
dent on the surface. Although observers
may be tempted to assign a single deter¬
minate, depending upon their biases or van¬
tage points, no single cause is usually clear.
Some people develop the habit of reading
books. And some do not. Among the latter,
many have learned to read, but do not.
Perhaps they should be called "lapsed
readers".
Special problems exist in developing
countries that have embarked on massive
literacy campaigns. All too often, it has been
found that large proportions of newly
literate adults lapse back into illiteracy for
lack of sufficient reading material geared to
their special needs and interests. Maintain¬
ing and improving reading skills, motivating
adults who have never read before to adopt
the reading habit, and providing the right
books and periodicals in adequate quantities
are among the challenges to be met through
a combination of foresight and careful
planning.
In Brazil, for example, this is being
accomplished through a mass literacy effort
called MOBRAL (Movimento Brasileiro de
Alfabetizaçâo) which has brought literacy to
thirteen million people in less than ten years.
The planners of this well-organized literacy
programme recognized the need for an
ongoing cultural programme to follow its
programmes for Functional Literacy and
Integrated Education. In view of the enor¬
mous size of Brazil and the wide network of
MOBRAL posts, mobile units, "Mobralte-
cas", are proposed to support the various
cultural activities scheduled. It is planned
that the Mobraltecas will have a library, tele¬
vision receiver and video-tape equipment,
sound equipment, film projectors and film-
strips and slide projectors. The Mobralteca
programme is now engaged in preparing
reading material for those people who have
just finished the initial course for illiterates.
An examination of the purposes for which
34
people read suggests that there can be many
reasons for engaging in the reading act.
Some are clearly individual and personal,
while others are societal, with many degrees
of interrelationship between these two ex¬
tremes of influences. The lover's apprecia¬
tion of a certain poem may stem from the
motivation provided by one individual and
by his romantic feelings.
A reader rarely says, "I am reading this
book because..." Reasons are not verbaliz¬
ed. Reading is a tool which is particularly
useful for a given purpose, and it is used
just as a hammer might be used to hit a nail
or a screwdriver to tighten a screw. In other
words, the habit of using reading is based
upon real human needs. Variations in
motivation for reading may occur in various
cultures throughout the world, but this list
of purposes provides a useful foundation:
As a ritual, or from force of habit.
From a sense of duty.
Merely to fill in or kill time.
To know and understand current hap¬
penings.
For immediate personal satisfaction or
value.
To meet practical demands of daily living.
To further avocational interests.
To carry on and promote professional or
vocational interests.
To meet personal-social demands.
To meet socio-civic needs and demands
(good citizenship). .
For self-development or improvement,
including. extension of cultural
background.
To satisfy strictly intellectual demands.
To satisfy spiritual needs.
The "bookaholic", whose story has been
told so amusingly by journalist Tom Zito, is
the least likely to know why he needs to read
books. Tongue in cheek, Zito wrote: "Life
without plenty of books lying around the
house is like a day without orange juice for
the bookaholic. Go a week without an ac¬
quisition and the hands start to shake.
We're not talking of old books here. None of
that snobby first-edition, out-of-print stuff.
Just your basic on-the-shelf material that's
waiting to be taken home. Bookaholism
knows no bounds and blurs all borders..."
Most habitual readers are not nearly so
extreme. Desire and aptitude are not the
only factors involved in developing a habit,
of course. Time is also involved, for habits
grow over a period of days, months and
years. The automatic response of a habit
can come only with long practice.
This article is based on extracts from the book
Roads to Reading, by Ralph C. Staiger of the In¬
ternational Reading Association, published by
Unesco, 1979.
UNESCO
BOOKSHELF
ON LITERACY AND
ADULT EDUCATION
The Evaluation of Literacy Pro¬
grammes, A Practical Guide, by Roger
Couvert. 1979, 168 pp. (24 F)
The Experimental World Literacy
Programme. A Critical Assessment.
Published by Unesco and the United Na¬
tions Development Programme (UNDP).
1976, 195 pp. (24 F)
MOBRAL-The Brazilian Adult
Literacy Experiment. A study prepared
by the Unesco Regional Office for
Education in Latin America and the
Caribbean. (New series: Educational
Studies and Documents, no. 15) 1975,
70 pp. (8 F)
The Operational Seminar: a
Pioneering Method of Training for
Development, by Marcel de Clerck. A
study on the training of personnel for
literacy programmes. ("Educational
Studies and Documents" series, no. 20)
1976, 59 pp. (8 F)
Mother Tongue Education: The
West African Experience, edited by
Ayo Bamgbose. Co-published with Hod-
der and Stoughton, London, 1976,
153 pp. Available through Unesco
(39 F), except in U.K. where co-
publisher has sales rights.
The Education of Adults: A World
Perspective, by John Lowe. Co-
published with the Ontario Institute for
Studies in Education IOISEI, Toronto.
Available through Unesco except in
Canada where OISE is sole distributor.
1975, 229 pp. (30 F)
Communication and Rural
Development, by Juan D. Diaz
Bordenave. A selection of projects in
Colombia, Brazil, India, Senegal, Peru,
Iran, the United Republic of Tanzania,
Canada, Tobago and the Philippines.
1977, 107 pp. (18 F)
The Rural World: Education and
Development, by Louis Malassis. Co-
published with Croom Helm Ltd., Lon¬
don. 1976, 127 pp. (39 F)
'The World Literacy Situation: 1970,
1980 and 1990' is discussed in an article
by E.A. Fisher in the latest issue of Pro¬
spects, Unesco's quarterly review of
education (Vol. X no1, 1980). The
dossier in this issue is "Mass Media,
education and culture". (Subscription
42 F, 1 year; 70 F¿ 2 years; single issue,
12 F)
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Roads
to reading
Kilph C Saigtr
iresoo
After literacy . . . What next?
ROADS TO READING by Ralph C. Staiger, Executive Director of
the International Reading Association, presents a series of imagina¬
tive campaigns and programmes which have been used in many
countries to promote the reading habit and to encourage already
literate persons to achieve a higher literacy.
Contents include:
How we read
Who influences reading?
Changing reading habits
Developing reading habits
Reading research
The reading child
Library outreach
International bibliography on motivation for reading
Published under the auspices of Unesco's Book Development
Programme
141 pages 15 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victorial, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 560-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking -
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenlcka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI. National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed only)- 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
oniy: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/ München. -
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra- Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyves-
bolt, Václ u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtiirosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad. -
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL. A.B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. - LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Naukl, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue,
Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chlttampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 121 1, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dares-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM.
H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and
Govt. Bookshops In London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester, Birmingham, Bristol. UNITED STATES. Unipub,
345 Park Avenue South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA.
Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade;
Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
POPE JOHN PAUL II
AT UNESCO
During an official visit to Unesco on June 2, 1980, His Holiness Pope
John Paul II was received by Mr Napoleon LeBlanc, President of the
General Conference, Mr Chams Eldine El-Wakil, Chairman of the
Executive Board, and Director-General Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow. As
a souvenir of the visit, Mr. M'Bow presented the Pope with a
specially bound copy of Peace on Earth, the Unesco anthology
published in connexion with the John XXIII Peace Prize which was
awarded to Unesco in 1974. The Pope then gave an address which set
the seal on the 30-year-old relationship between the Holy See and
Unesco. The text of his speech as well as those of Messrs LeBlanc, El-
Wakil and M'Bow are reproduced here in their entirety.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL
SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
ADDRESS BY
Mr. NAPOLÉON LEBLANC
President of the General Conference
of the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
Most Holy Father,
It is a great honour and a source of particular joy and emotion for me, as President of the General
Conference, to extend to you a warm and respectful welcome on behalf of the 150 Member States
that at present make up the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
Your presence among us today, which will represent a landmark in the annals of Unesco, testifies
in my eyes to the unfailing interest of the Holy See in the lofty intellectual and ethical mission that
Unesco has pursued since its inception and, in particular, symbolizes your commitment to the work
of intergovernmental co-operation patiently and persistently carried on under the Organization's
auspices.
Except when the General Conference is held away from headquarters, as happened in Nairobi in
1976 and as will be the case this year in Belgrade, it is in this very hall where we are now assembled
that the delegations of all the Member States come together every two years to examine, in plenary
meeting, the Organization's programme and budget.
In this forum of deliberation and dialogue, meeting-place of civilizations and cultures where
plurality does not exclude consensus, Member States determine collectively those practical actions;
that the Director-General and the Secretariat for their part strive faithfully to implement in the
fieldsvital to the world community of nations and peoplesof education, the natural sciences, the
social sciences, philosophy, culture and communication.
One has only to enumerate the fields of competence of Unesco to realize implicitly that the
Organization's action cannot but be wholly centred on man or, to employ the expression that ap¬
pears in your address of 2 October last to the United Nations General Assembly, on "man
understood in his entirety".
It is therefore not surprising that the programmes approved over the years by the General Con¬
ference of Unesco should have reflected the constant desire of Member States to work together to
create, in every part of the world, conditions conducive both to the fulfilment of the individual and
to the harmonious and balanced development of the environment in which man leads his life.
Today, when the very notion of development has evolved and when governments, in response to
these two requirements have increasingly found themselves obliged to integrate their sectoral policies
within a framework of overall development, the cultural dimension has come to assume special
importance.
However, if we may justly rejoice to see an increasingly fruitful and mutually enriching dialogue
developing between the different cultures, none of us can fail to be aware of how much remains to be
done to guarantee the dignity and inalienable rights of the individual. Here is a sacred task for all of
us to fulfil.
For this reason, I should like to say again, before making way for the distinguished Chairman of
the Executive Board of Unesco, how happy I am to greet you, Most Holy Father, as the august
messenger of peace and hope.
PARIS, 2 JUNE 1980
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
nés
ADDRESS BY
Mr. CHAMS ELDINE EL-WAKIL
Chairman of the Executive Board
of the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Most Holy Father,
It is a great honour for me to welcome Your Holiness on behalf of the Executive Board of Unesco.
Your visit to the headquarters of this Organization, which has as the cornerstone of its
philosophy indeed, I would say, of its faith construction of peace in the minds of men, takes on a
special importance in the troubled times in which mankind is living.
It was important for the nations of the world, who meet within these walls to share a message of
brotherhood and understanding which will match the aspirations of men and strive to fulfil their
legitimate hopes, to hear your voice. It was important for the men and women of all races and creeds
who gather here to speak of education, science, culture and communication, believing as they do in
the comprehensiveness of a development centred on man, to hear Your Holiness, whose &st en¬
cyclical, Redemptor hominis, emphasized precisely the fullness and multiform richness of existence.
Most Holy Father, at the end of his encyclical Populorum progressio, your great predecessor
Paul VI said that " if the new name of peace is development, who would not wish to labour for it
with all his powers?". Since your election to the chair of Saint Peter, you have not ceased to carry
this conviction to every corner of the earth.
A messenger of hope, you have faith in the goodness of man and in his capacity to act for the im¬
provement of his condition and for the happiness of humanity as a whole. For, while unique in
respect of his subjectivity and his own particular moment in history, man is at the same time part of
the history of humanity, to which he contributes his cultural identity, his individual experience, his
desires and his suffering.
A similar faith informs the hearts of the representatives of the peoples of the world who meet here.
They also believe in man and strive to create a better future one in which the exercise by every man
of his inalienable rights is a daily occurrence, indeed a way of life.
To educate man so that he may better comprehend his destiny, to educate him so that he is able to
determine his own development, his orientation and his own objectives, as well as the form that he
wishes to give to this development, such is the horizon upon which the eyes of all those assembled
within these walls are fixed.
We must combat ignorance so that freedom may blossom more fully; so that dreams of in¬
dependence may become a reality; we must combat ignorance, finally, so as to open up the paths of
peace, of brotherhood and of truth in a world united by the same hope and the same determination.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Science and technology, the instruments of mankind's progress, distinguish human beings from
the rest of nature. The Creator of all things wished in this way to give man the means to affirm his
own existence and define his place in the universe. But in order that this ideal should be accomplish¬
ed, a vital effort has still to be made to conquer injustice and inequity. Knowledge must be
disseminated, the bread of learning must be shared, so that the possessors of knowledge may teach
and learn as part of a constantly renewed dialectic.
The cultural riches of the world are immense. They are constituted not only by the sum of the
traditions of its peoples but, even more, by the individuality of every man, of his outlook, his vision
and his experience. What could be more striking than the image of a great cultural crucible in which
are blended all the creative ideas of the globe and from which spring, by a process of reciprocal fer¬
tilization, flowers radiant with authenticity but proud of their ability to grow in any field and under
any sky!
To foster understanding and harmony and to enable knowledge to be shared, the world possesses a
network of communication systems without precedent in history. The instrument of freedom when
its benefits are fairly distributed, it becomes, in the absence of justice and enlightenment, a means of
enslavement and subordination.
In all these fields, Unesco acts not merely to further knowledge, but above all, to promote a just
and genuine development in a more equitable world.
Believing that the path of peace lies in this direction, citizens from all the nations of the world
assemble here to seek the happiness of man.
Has not the happiness of man been the goal of all religions and all communities in the world since
the beginning of time? And is not the liberation of man from his suffering an expression of the divine
will?
But the suffering of the world, those gaping wounds in the side of humanity, can only be van¬
quished by a common desire to build a more just and more equitable world; a new world that goes
far beyond mere material concepts, which carry the risk of imprisoning the human spirit, subjecting
it to immediate desires and preventing it from transcending these in the fulfilment of superior
needsthe true path to freedom and peace.
Most Holy Father, your visit to Unesco today is a solemn and revered symbol, an eternal benedic¬
tion bestowed upon the Organization's guiding principles and a glowing testimony rendered to its
ideals. The appeal you launch today from within these walls, on the eve of the twenty-first session of
the General Conference, will be an abiding source of inspiration for the representatives of the
peoples of the earth as they seek a better future and the well-being of mankind in a world of
brotherhood, justice and peace.
UNESCO
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
UNES
ADDRESS BY
Mr. AMADOU-MAHTAR M'BOW
Director-General
of the United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
Most Holy Father,
It is a signal privilege and a great joy for Unesco, for its Executive Board, for its Permanent
Delegates, for its Secretariat and for me personally, to welcome you here today. To this House of all
cultures and all branches of learning, where 150 Member States are represented and whose
Secretariat is staffed by nationals of all races and creeds from 121 countries; to this hall where a
welcome of equal fervour is extended to you by the Ministers of Education of a great many coun¬
tries, some of the most distinguished intellectuals of our time, including an eminent Head of State,
and workers employed on the most humble tasks of the Secretariat; to this epitome of the world,
Most Holy Father, you bring an epitome of human experience with your message of universal hope.
For you have known the most widely differing social conditions; you have come into contact with
the most diverse convictions; you have confronted the simplest and the most complex problems alike
and you have performed both the lowliest and the most exalted duties. Worker and poet, fighter and
peacemaker, priest and writer, a man rooted in your native soil and through it accessible to the entire
world, true to your faith and ever receptive to that of others, an indefatigable explorer of continents
and of souls, you bring to the immense task that is now yours an irreplaceable knowledge of man as
the servant of all mankind.
And perhaps you will allow me to say how deeply moved I was as I watched the television pictures
relayed from so far away and saw Your Holiness kiss the soil of that continent of Africa where I was
born, that continent so long crucified and even now barely resurrected. For me for the man who is
welcoming you here todayyour presence in his native Sahel, your smile as you held aloft those
children of Africa to whom you gave your blessing, were the poignant symbols of the long-awaited
turning of a new leaf, the symbols of dignity regained.
Most Holy Father,
Your visit to Unesco has a twofold justification: it forms part of your pastoral visits and it marks
the co-operation that has been built up over three decades between the Church and our Organiza¬
tion. That co-operation, which began in 1948, was to flourish under the noble aegis of Mgr. Angelo
Roncalli, the future John XXIII, who was at that time Papal Nuncio in Paris and was later to
become the Holy See's first Permanent Observer at Unesco.
Relations between the Holy See and Unesco are based on the profound convergence of our respec¬
tive ideals: both armed with ethical principles work towards a world that will have man as its sole
object, a world in which peace will be founded on justice and will nurture the spirit of brotherhood.
This is why, from the start, collaboration between us has been tended by the Sovereign Pontiffs, just
as it has constantly been encouraged by the Directors-General of the Organization.
My predecessors and I have, accordingly, often been received by the Sovereign Pontiffs and I,
myself, had the very great joy of meeting His Holiness Paul VI on several occasions. I should like to
say how moving and edifying was the friendship with which he honoured me. We had lengthy discus-
j(J sions together, but when the time came for us to part, I always felt that we had put into words only
^=- an infinitesimal part of what we had to say to one another. From John Paul I, alas, I had time to
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
UNES
receive only one message, as brief as it was full of warmth. But since your election to the Chair of
Saint Peter, Most Holy Father, I have already been fortunate enough, with my wife, to have an
opportunity to visit you, and our memories of that visit are vivid and precious. I hope, with all my
heart, that it may be the first of many.
The links between the Holy See and Unesco, which such visits serve to strengthen at the highest
level, are also reinforced by the presence of delegations from the Vatican at the General Conferences
of the Organization and at all the major meetings that it has organized, both internationally and
regionally. They are maintained by your Permanent Observer, Mgr. Renzo Frana, with rare effi¬
ciency and exemplary modesty; they are extended through the tireless devotion of the members of the
International Catholic Co-ordinating Centre for Unesco, and carried further by the manifold and
highly fruitful activities of the 20 Catholic international non-governmental organizations which have
consultative relations with Unesco.
Those links received further impetus when, in November 1974, we were awarded the John XXIII
Peace Prizethe proceeds of which I decided to allocate to the publication of a Peace Anthology, a
collection of writings from many different periods in time and from all parts of the world, bringing
out the shared aspirations of mankind which override specific historical and cultural circumstances.
Most Holy Father,
In answering the invitation that I extended to you and in expressing the desire to visit Unesco dur¬
ing the 109th session of its Executive Board, you have given a solemn consecration to all those links.
But in speaking from the platform of our Organization in order symbolically to address the com¬
munity of nations, and through that community, all the peoples of the world, you also pledge your
personal commitment to the efforts being made to achieve a just and fraternal peace, at a time when,
after a period of confidence and optimism, the world is experiencing the tremors of new and disturb¬
ing anxieties.
In the past two decades, our generation witnessed the first frail hope of the brotherhood of all
mankind. We truly believed, then, that the suffering and destruction caused by two world wars in
succession, the mutual injuries, and the shared sacrifices, had convinced all peoples of the need to
overcome the prejudices and lack of trust which, in the past, caused their disputes to degenerate into
conflicts.
We thought that the age-old temptation of the strong to use violence against the weak for the pur¬
poses of domination or exploitation would gradually subside in the face of our urgent need to listen
to one another, to hear and help one another on a basis of shared principles.
We believed that the more fortunate individuals and peoples were becoming aware of the fact that
the wealth of which they were the privileged beneficiaries represented the culmination of a long chain
of creative efforts which had been continued and supplemented for thousands of years, the result of
the use of knowledge and productive forces which no minority should arrogate to itself exclusively
because all mankind had contributed to it.
We thought, then, that the advance of science and technology, freed from the trammels imposed,
often against the will of the scientists themselves, by selfish interests and greed for power, would at
last be harnessed to the development of all nations, and would make a decisive contribution to the
victory over ignorance, disease and hunger.
We thought that the last bastions of oppression, the last pockets of resistance where the violation
of the rights of individuals and peoples still persisted, would soon yield, one after another, to the
firm determination of the world community to work towards a future of justice and peace.
We thought that yesterday's dispossessed and oppressed, with renewed self-confidence and draw¬
ing inspiration from their rehabilitated cultures to find original solutions to the new challenges con¬
fronting them, could open up the way to an authentic rebirth and would find themselves surround¬
ed by hands outstretched, not for alms, but in loyal co-operation, based on mutual respect and a
spirit of reciprocity.
If such hopes seemed reasonable, it was because great changes had occurred in the world. The
1960s had brought the impressive awakening of the former colonies to political sovereignty. The
voices upraised in unison from so many peoples who had hitherto been condemned to silence, the
revival of so many buried memories, and the freeing of so many thwarted initiatives, shook to their
foundations the structures, habits and calculations which, for several centuries, had endeavoured to
impose unity through uniformity. It was the dawn of a new era, with a profusion of identities and the
exploration of differences.
Between countries, regions and continents, information circuits wove an increasingly dense net¬
work of communication, linking countless local and national communities with the world communi¬
ty. With its efficiency rapidly heightened by recent scientific and technological discoveriesin par¬
ticular those of computer science this network made possible a growing flow of knowledge and
know-how, and greatly increased the opportunities afforded for promoting education for all; it en-
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
NES
couraged creative participation by all men and women in both the development of their country, and
the peaceful onward march of mankind as a whole. Thus, fearfully, fervently, or with amazement,
man's gaze ranged for the first time to the furthest horizon of the human race.
It is true that negative phenomena continued to embitter the mutual relations between many
nations, as also relations within individual nations.
We were witness to the perpetuation, sometimes even the extension in new forms, of structures of
cultural, economic, technological and social domination; the exacerbation of inequalities all the
more shocking in that they were unforeseen; the traumatic widening of the gap between the recurrent
rhythms of traditional society, custodian of all that was inherited from the past, and the pace of the
modern city, with its promise of progress still imperfectly assimilated.
We were witness to the rending of the fabric of family communities, the loss of some of the most
precious values they transmitted and the weakening of interpersonal communication; the individual
was then abandoned to solitude, selfishness and indifference, vulnerable to the insidious temptations
of violence.
We were witness to growing disappointments, born of great hopes which were too slow in
materializing which increased in absolute figures despite the efforts made to eradicate it;
endemic diseases, which were rife even though man had acquired the scientific and technical means
of overcoming them; famines, which broke out without promoting the movements of world-wide
solidarity which might have been expected.
We were witness to racialism, linked to prejudices of another age, still deep-rooted in the un¬
conscious mind of many communities, feeding on differences not easily accepted and on shameful
inequalities, breaking out again in new guises and invoking new pretexts. And we were witness to the
continuation of the arms race, diverting a vital share of human and material energies in most coun¬
tries, including the poorest, complicating international relations and promoting the outbreak of
countless conflicts between small countries, in which the rivalries between large countries found
arenas for direct confrontation.
We were indeed witness to all thatbut we were tempted to think that the call of the future would
be felt to be more important than nostalgic harking back to the past. We thought that the promise of
the horizons opened up to us by the reconciliation of our differences would finally prove stronger
than the urgings of our individual interests.
We had grounds for thinking that, with a foretaste of its unity, mankind would gradually draw on
the moral and intellectual resources and the physical and material energy, which would enable it to
refashion the world on a truly human scale, fertilizing the creative contributions of all past eras and
intermingling the living dreams of all peoples and all cultures.
But the facts of the situation today increasingly fail to meet this expectation. Attempts at a
dialogue come up against growing disagreements. Contacts suddenly appear to encounter
underground opposition; between nations which are neighbours or competitors, there seems to be a
greater willingness to have recourse to violence than recourse to reason; between different visions of
the world, the search for converging views seems to be on the ebb, before a floodtide of intolerance.
And science increasingly has objectives assigned to it which betray the expectations placed in it by the
peoples of the worldobjectives dictated by the will to dominate, and directed towards destruction
and death, rather than towards construction and life. The hopes raised at the dawn of the 1960s are
now mingled with growing misgivings, at the twilight of the 1970s.
This kind of evolution was not unavoidable. And we do not believe in the fatality of misfortune. If
the main causes of conflict have not been overcome, if the threats they conceal have still not been
removed, if so many peoples continue to live below bare minimum subsistence standards, this is not
due to any lack of the necessary material resources or institutional machinery. It is because at the
time when we possess them at last, we still lack a common faith in the unity of our destiny. It is
because we still lack a "reason for living together" which will gradually transcend our selfishness and
establish solidarity on a world-wide scale, reconciling all our differences round shared values.
Yet, it is not illusory to imagine that we can still find this reason. For beyond everything that
makes them different from each other, people all over the world experience similar forms of anguish,
are faced with comparable choices and cherish common hopes which, combined in varying fashions
and expressed in a thousand ways, all come together in the same place, which is the ethical founda¬
tion of our existence.
Beyond their individual languages, customs and beliefs, the peasants of the Amazon, the Ganges,
the Niger, the Nile and the Yangtze, the workers of Potosi, Calcutta, Saint-Denis, Cracow, Detroit
or Lagos, men of letters and scientists, craftsmen and artists everywhere, believers and non-believers,
Muslims and Christians, Buddhists and animists, feelthe great majority of themthe same need
for human dignity, the same concern for truth, and the same thirst for justice and fraternity.
This is what religions have revealed to us, what the prophets have in turn taught us, and what the
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
sages and philosophers at the dawn of all cultures and the theorists of all ideologies have already
presaged. But most men and women do not yet know that their dreams coincidein all climes and
that their upward gaze lights on the same lofty heights.
Our age can bebecause it possesses the intellectual and technical resourcesand must
bebecause our survival depends on itthe age that will for the first time be able to formulate our
common reasons for living in a language which is that of mankind as a wholea language that
belongs to no specific culture, but is one in which all countries can instantly recognize themselves.
Those things that at present we still find so commonplace and almost natural will then begin to ap¬
pear intolerable to us: the afflictions of others on our doorstep; inequalities of opportunity which are
bound up with differences of race, ethnic origin or social status; daily violations of human rights;
and the harnessing of technological progress to the production of ever more monstrous instruments
of death.
The dignity of each individual and of each people will then be seen to be indissociable from the
dignity of all the others. The human person will be everywhere inviolable and the contribution of
each nation and of each culture to the heritage of the world will be seen to be irreplaceable.
In the face of such a vital requirement no culture can henceforth develop fully while withdrawing
behind the frontiers of its identity. Such a temptation would be both anachronistic and destructive.
The challenge facing each culture is that of full self-realization, while making of its difference one of
the modes of expression of an evolving world-wide communion, one of the paths to a universally
shared ethic. No nation can henceforth impose on others its sole standpointand its particular
aspirations will have no chance of fulfilment unless it helps to develop a burgeoning hope open to all.
It is this future design that Unesco is endeavouring to bring about. In every domain of the life of
the mind, our Organization stands at the world crossroads, the point at which the efforts made
everywhere to pave the way to an ultimately universal humanism converge. Constantly alert to the
swift emergence of every fresh achievement in the world, it sets out to be the catalyst of a moral con¬
science on the scale of mankind as a whole, for its activities lay emphasis on the primacy of human
dignity, of the brotherhood of peoples and of the indivisibility of the historical heritage which they
share.
Accordingly, Unesco seeks, on all the issues with which it is concerned, bases for agreements
which will allay latent antagonisms and reveal areas of convergence where the need to engage in
dialogue in order to promote greater justice and solidarity is greater than the temptation to clash.
The Organization is thus taking part in the development of a new type of approach within the inter¬
national community by giving special consideration not only to the outcome of debates or of
negotiations but to the procedures whereby they are carried through and the processes by means of
which all parties come gradually to discover their common fields of action; ways forward, often un¬
foreseen at the outset, which may lead to a consensus and, step by step, indicate the bases on which
to anchor these collective hopes, towards which, simultaneously yet independently, so many past
generations have tended, and the key to which it is for us to find together.
Thus, Most Holy Father, the doubts that are arising at a time when some of the hopes of the 1960s
seem to be fading away may engender the worst and the best. The worst would be for them to lead us
into despondency, resignation orand this comes to the same thinga return to the rivalries of the
past and, hence, to increased tension. The best would be for them to make us aware of the respon¬
sibilities which we have not yet assumed in regard to a future which is henceforth shared. And for
them to instil into us the firm resolve to do so.
On this solemn occasion, and in the ennobling presence of His Holiness John Paul II, may I
appeal to the community of nations, to peoples and to governments and to the youth of the world in
order that all may, from this day forward, join together in opening up the path to an order of digni¬
ty, of freedom, of justice and of solidarity.
These are narrow, difficult paths but how great is the incentive they offer. They alone are com¬
mensurate with our destiny; the only ones open to us if we want the dawning period of the third
millennium, for which our generation will be answerable before history, to be that in which man,
who bears the legacy of all past wars, will usher in peace; that in which man, who has amassed all the
rivalries of the past, will usher in fraternity; in which man, who has suffered the fear of all past ages,
will usher in hope.
NES
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
ADDRESS BY
HIS HOLINESS
POPE JOHN PAUL II
ON THE OCCASION OF HIS VISIT
TO THE HEADQUARTERS
OF THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL,
SCIENTIFIC
AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
(UNESCO)
2 June
1980
NESC
Mr. President of the General Conference,
Mr. Chairman of the Executive Board,
Mr. Director-General,
Ladies and Gentlemen,
I wish first of all to express my most sincere thanks for the invitation extended to me on
a number Tof occasions initially on the first visit with which he has honoured me by Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-General of the United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization. There are many reasons why I am happy to be able to respond
today to that invitation, which I deeply appreciate.
i
For their kind words of welcome, I thank Mr. Napoléon LeBlanc, the President of the
General Conference, Mr. Chams Eldine El-Wakil, the Chairman of the Executive Board
and Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, the Director-General of the Organization. I also wish
	 to greet all those assembled here for the 109th session of the Executive Board of Unesco. It
if) is with great joy that I see gathered together on this occasion so many delegates from na
tions throughout the world, so many outstanding personalities, such a wealth of talent and
so many distinguished representatives of the world of culture and science.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
Your
organization
is the creation
of nations
impelled
by a desire
for peace,
union and
reconciliation
In this address, I shall attempt to make my own modest contribution to the edifice that you, ladies
and gentlemen, are building with unfailing perseverance by your deliberations and resolutions in all
Unesco's fields of competence.
Let me begin by referring to the origins ofyour Organization. The events which marked the foun¬
dation of Unesco fill my heart with joy and gratitude towards Divine Providence: the signing of its
Constitution on 16 November 1945; the coming into force of that Constitution and the establish¬
ment of the Organization on 4 November 1946; the agreement between Unesco and the United
Nations approved by the General Assembly of the United Nations that same year. Your Organiza¬
tion is indeed the creation of nations who, in the wake of the terrible Second World War, were im¬
pelled by what may be called a spontaneous desire for peace, union and reconciliation. Those nations
sought ways and means of co-operation that might consecrate, deepen and perpetuate this new
understanding. Unesco thus came into being, like the United Nations, because the peoples of the
world knew that great enterprises designed to promote peace and the progress of mankind
throughout the earth must necessarily be founded on the union ofnations, on mutual respect and on
international co-operation.
Continuing the work, the thinking and the message of my great predecessor, Pope Paul VI, I had
the honour of speaking to the General Assembly of the United Nations last October, at the invitation
of Mr. Kurt Waldheim, the Secretary-General of the United Nations. Shortly afterwards, on
12 November 1979, I was invited by Mr. Edouard Saouma, the Director-General of the Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United Nations in Rome. I have thus had divers opportunities to ad¬
dress myself to questions intimately linked with the whole range of problems relating to the peaceful
future of man on earth. All those problems are indeed inextricably linked. We are faced, as it were,
by a vast system of communicating vessels: the problems of culture, science and education do not
arise, in the life of nations and in international relations, independently of the other problems of
human existence, such as those of peace or hunger. The problems of culture are fundamentally
affected by the other dimensions of human existence, just as they in turn influence those other
dimensions.
There is however as I stressed in my address to the United Nations when referring to the Univer¬
sal Declaration of Human Rightsa fundamental dimension, which is capable of shaking to their
very foundations the systems within which the whole of humanity lives, and of liberating human ex¬
istence, both individual and collective, from the threats that hang over it. This fundamental dimen¬
sion is man, man in his entirety, man living simultaneously in the sphere of material values and in
that of spiritual values. Respect for the inalienable rights of the human person underlies everything
(cf. Address to the United Nations, Nos. 7 and 13).
Any threat to human rights, whether in the realm of spiritual or of material well-being, does
violence to this fundamental dimension. For that reason, in my address to the Food and Agriculture
Organization, I stressed that no man, no country and no system in the world can remain indifferent
when confronted with the "geography of hunger" and the awesome threats which will result from it
if the entire direction of economic policy and, in particular, the pattern of investments, are not
substantially and radically changed. For this reason, too, I must stress, in referring to the origins of
your Organization, the need to mobilize all those forces that serve to orient the spiritual dimension of
human existence, that bear witness to the primacy of the spiritual in man to what befits the dignity
of his intelligence, his will and his heartso that humanity shall not succumb again to the monstrous
alienation of that collective evil which is always ready to employ material power in the lethal conflict
of man against man and nation against nation.
Unesco then, like the Universal Declaration of Human Rights, originates from these primary
noble promptings of the human conscience, intelligence and will. I call to witness this origin, this
beginning, these premises and these first principles. It is in their name that I have come to Paris to¬
day, to the headquarters of your Organization, bringing with me a plea that, at the close of a period
of more than thirty years in your work, you should rally yet more closely around the ideals and prin¬
ciples that were there in the beginning. It is likewise in their name that I now propose to place before
you some truly fundamental considerations for it is only in the light they cast that the significance of
this institution, Unesco, the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization, can
be fully appreciated.
Genus humanum arte et ratione vivit (cf. Saint Thomas Aquinas, commenting on Aristotle, in
Post. Analyt., No. 1). These words from one of Christianity's greatest minds who, at the same time
fruitfully carried further the thinking of the ancient world, have an impact that goes beyond the con¬
fines and contemporary significance of Western culture, be it Mediterranean or Atlantic. They bear a
meaning which applies to the whole of humanity, in which the various traditions that make up its
spiritual heritage and the different stages of its culture come together. According to St. Thomas
Aquinas, the essential significance of culture lies in the fact that it is a characteristic of human life as
such. // is through culture that man lives a truly human life. Human life is also culture in the sense
that it is through culture that man is distinguished and differentiated from everything else that exists
in the visible world: man cannot do without culture.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Respect for
the inalienable
rights of the
human person
"underlies
everything
Culture is a specific mode of man's "existing" and "being". Man always lives according to a
culture of his own which, in turn, establishes among men a bond which is also, in itself, peculiar to
them, determining the inter-human and social character of human existence. It is in the unity of
culture as the distinctive mode of human existence that the plurality ofcultures within which people
live is rooted. Within this plurality, man develops without, however, losing the essential contact with
the unity of culture as a basic and essential dimension of his existence and his being.
Man who, in the visible world, is the only ontic subject of culture, is also its only object and its
end. It is through culture that man as a human being becomes more human, "exists" more fully and
has more "being". And it is therein that the fundamental distinction between what man is and what
he has, between being and having, is grounded. Culture is always essentially and necessarily related
to what man is, while its relation to what he has, to his "possessions", is not onlysecondary, but en¬
tirely relative. All that man "possesses", is of importance for culture, and a factor creative of
culture, only in so far as man, by virtue of what he "possesses", is also able to "be" more fully man,
to become more fully man at all levels of his existence and in everything which marks out his humani¬
ty. The experience of the different periods of history, not excluding the present, shows that we think
about culture and speak about it first and foremost in connexion with human nature, and only
secondarily and indirectly, in connexion with the world of human production. This does not mean
that we do not judge the phenomenon of culture by what man produces, or that at the same time we
do not draw conclusions about man from it. This kind of approach typical of a posteriori reason¬
ing affords the possibility of working back towards the ontico-causal dependences. It is man,
and man alone, who "acts" or "makes" culture; man, and man alone, expresses himself in culture
and finds his own balance in it.
All of us, present here today, meet on the ground ofculture, the fundamental reality which unites
us and which underlies the establishment of Unesco and the Organization's purposes. We meet, by
the same token, around man, and, in a sense, in him, in man. Man, who expresses and objectifies
himself in and through culture, is unique, complete and indivisible. He is both the subject and the
maker of culture. Consequently, he cannot be considered solely as the result of all the concrete con¬
ditions of his existence, as the result to give but one example of the production relationships
prevailing at any given time. Does this mean that the criterion of production relationships is in no
way a key to understanding of the historic quality of man, to understanding of his culture and the
manifold forms of his development? It is indeed a key, and even a very useful one, but it is not the
basic, decisive key. There is no doubt whatever that human cultures reflect the various systems of
production relationships; but culture originates, not in any particular system but in man, man who
lives within the system, and accepts it or seeks to change it. It is impossible to conceive of a culture
without human subjectivity or human causality; but in the field of culture man is always the prime
factor: he is the primordial and fundamental element of culture.
And man is always such in his wholeness: in the entirety of his spiritual and material subjectivity.
While there is a real distinction between spiritual and material culture in terms of the nature and con¬
tent of the products in which culture is expressed, it must also be noted that, on the one hand, works
of material culture always reveal a "spiritualization" of matter, a subjection of the material element
to the spiritual powers of man, in other words, to his intelligence and his will; and, on the other,
works of spiritual culture specifically show a "materialization" of the spirit, an incarnation of what
is spiritual. This dual characteristic appears to be both primordial and permanent in works of
culture.
Here then, by way of theoretical conclusion, we have a sufficient basis for understanding culture
through man in his wholeness, through the entire reality of his subjectivity. Here tooin the field of
actionwe have a sufficient basis for seeking always in culture the whole man, man in his entirety, in
all the truth of his spiritual and bodily subjectivity; a sufficient basis for not superimposing pre¬
conceived divisions and oppositions on culture, which is a genuinely human system, a glorious syn¬
thesis of mind and body. In point of fact, neither the absolutization of matter in the structure of the
human ¿ubject, nor, conversely, the absolutization of the spirit in that structure, expresses man's
truth or serves his culture.
I should like to dwell here on another essential consideration, of a very different kind. It is best ap¬
proached by observing that the Holy See has a Permanent Observer accredited to Unesco, whose
presence is entirely in keeping with the very nature of the Apostolic See. On an even broader plane,
this representation is consonant with the nature and mission of the Catholic Church and, indirectly,
with that of Christianity as a whole. I should like to take the opportunity offered me here today to
express a deep personal conviction. Although the representation of the Apostolic See in your
Organization is also motivated by the specific sovereignty of the Holy See, the most important
reason for it is the organic and essential bond between religion in general and Christianity in par¬
ticular, on the one hand, and culture, on the other. This relationship takes in the manifold realities
which must be defined as concrete expressions of culture at different stages of history and in all parts
of the world. It would certainly be no exaggeration, for example, to maintain that, in a multiplicity
of ways, all Europefrom the Atlantic to the Uralstestifies to the links between culture and Chris-
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
The primary
and
indispensable
duty
of culture
is education
tianity in the history of each nation as well as in that of the community as a whole.
In saying that, I do not wish in any way to detract from the heritage of other continents or from
the uniqueness and value of that heritage, derived from other sources of religious, humanist and
ethical inspiration. If anything, I am moved to render the mostprofound and heartfelt homage to all
the cultures of the great human family, from the most ancient to those of the present day. And I am
thinking of all cultures as, with respect and admiration, I say to you here, in Paris, at Unesco's head¬
quarters: "Behold the man!". I wish to proclaim my admiration for the rich creativity of the human
mind, for its untiring efforts to fathom and affirm the identity of man, of that man who is always
present in every form of culture.
On the other hand, in speaking of the place of the Church and the Apostolic See in your Organiza¬
tion, I am not thinking only of all the cultural works of the past two millennia by which men who had
accepted Christ and the Gospel expressed themselves, or of the various institutions which were born
of the same inspiration in the fields of education, instruction, charity, social aid, and so many
others. I am thinking above all, ladies and gentlemen, of the fundamental link between the Gospel,
that is, the message of Christ and of the Church, and man in his essential humanity. For that link is
indeed fundamentally creative of culture. For culture to be created, man must be viewed as a distinc¬
tive and autonomous value, as bearing in himself the transcendence of personality, with all that
ultimately implies. Man must be affirmedfor his own sake, and hot for any other motive or reason:
solely for himself! More than this, man must be loved because he is man, love is due to man by virtue
of the special dignity which is his. All these affirmations concerning man lie in the very substance of
the message of Christ and the mission of the Church, despite all that critics may have said on this
score and all that may have been done by the various movements which are opposed to religion in
general and to Christianity in particular.
More than once, over the course of history, we have witnessed and are still witnessing a pro¬
cess, a phenomenon of the greatest significance. Wherever religious institutions have been suppress¬
ed, wherever the ideas and the activities born of religious inspiration and, in particular, of Christian
inspiration, have been outlawed, men rediscover these same elements outside the institutional
framework when, in obedience to the truth and by their inner strivings, they compare what con¬
stitutes their humanity with the content of the Christian message.
You will not blame me, ladies and gentlemen, for this statement. I can assure you that it is not my
intention to cause offence to anyone. I would merely ask you to understand that, in the name of
what I stand for, / could not refrain from bearing this testimony. In fact it also contains a truth
about culture which cannot be passed over in silence if we seek in culture all that is human, wherein
man expresses himself and whereby he seeks to be the subject of his own existence. I wished too, in
saying this, to stress even more my gratitude for the ties which unite Unesco with the Apostolic See,
ties that are reflected in a special way in my presence here today.
From what I have said, a number of major conclusions can be drawn. For the foregoing remarks
point clearly to the fact that the primary and indispensable duty of culture in generaland of every
cultureis education. To educate is to help man become ever more fully man, to enable him to "be"
more, not only to "have" more, so that, through all he "has", through all he "possesses", man may
become more fully capable of "being" man. If this is to come about, man must learn how to "be
more" not only "with others" but also "for others". Education is of fundamental importance in
developing human and social interrelationships. Here, too, I take up a set of axioms, in which there
is a convergence of Christian traditions proceeding from the Gospels with the educational experience
of all the men of goodwill and deep wisdom of whom there have been so many in every century. Our
own times are not lacking either in men who are seen to be great simply because of their humanity,
which they knowhow to share with others, and with young people in particular. At the same time,
the symptoms of the crises of every kind to which the more affluent milieux and societies, as it hap¬
pens, are succumbing and which affect, above all, the younger generations, are striking proof that
the work of educating man is not solely carried out by institutions, by organized, material means, no
matter how excellent they may be. These symptoms also show that what matters most is always man,
man and his moral authority, deriving from the Tightness of his principles and the conformity of his
actions with those principles.
Unesco, in its capacity as the world organization most competent to deal with all problems con¬
cerning culture, cannot neglect another cardinal question: What can be done to ensure man's educa¬
tion above all within the family?
What state of public morality will give the family, and especially parents, the moral authority
necessary for this purpose? What kinds of instruction? What types of legislation uphold that'
authority or, on the other hand, weaken and destroy it? The causes of success or failure in man's
education in the home are always found at the very heart of that basic culture-creating environment,
the family, as well as at a higher level, that which lies within the province of the State and its agen¬
cies, on which they still depend. These problems cannot but give cause for reflection and concern in
the forum where official State representatives gather together.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The
nation exists
'by' culture
and
for' culture.
There is no doubt that the prime and fundamental cultural factor is the spiritually mature in¬
dividual, one who is fully educated, capable of educating himself and others. Neither is there any
doubt that the prime and fundamental dimension of culture is sound morality: ethical culture.
There are, of course, many specific questions in this field, but experience shows that everything is
related and that these questions fall within systems which already clearly interact with each other.
For example, in the whole process of education, and especially in school education, has there not
been a unilateral movement towards instruction in the narrow sense of the term? If we consider the
proportions that this phenomenon has assumed and the systematic growth of instruction exclusively
geared to possession, is not the vision of man himself being increasingly obscured? The outcome is
the literal alienation of education: instead of striving towards what man ought to "be", it operates
only in terms of that to which man can lay claim in terms of "having" and "possessing". The next
stage in this process of alienation is to inure man, by depriving him of his own subjectivity, to
becoming the object ofa host ofmanipulations, whether these be ideological and political manipula¬
tions through public opinion; or manipulations operating through the monopoly or control of the
media by economic forces or political powers; or indeed manipulations whereby people are taught
that life is the specific manipulation of the self.
Dangers such as these in education appear above all to constitute a threat to societies with a more
highly developed technological civilization. These societies are having to contend with the specific
crisis of man, in which man has less and less confidence in his own humanity, in the meaningfulness
of being a man and in the sense of affirmation and the joy that stem therefrom and are a source of
creation. Present-day civilization attempts to impose on man a set of apparent imperatives which its
spokesmen justify by appealing to the principle of development and progress. Respect for life, for
example, is replaced by the "imperative" to snuff out and destroy life; love as the responsible com¬
munion of persons gives way to the "imperative" of maximum sexual enjoyment devoid of all sense
of responsibility; and, instead of primacy being accorded to truth in a person's acts, "primacy" goes
to the latest fashion in behaviour, to self-centredness and to instant success.
All this amounts indirectly to the wholesale and systematic abandonment of the healthy ambition
of being a man. Let us not delude ourselves: the system based on such false imperatives and fun¬
damental denials may well dictate the future of man and of culture.
If, in the name of the future of culture, man's right to "be" more needs to be proclaimed, and if,
for the same reason, the healthy primacy of the family in the whole process of educating man for
genuine humanity needs to be demanded, the right of the nation also needs to be situated in the same
line of thinking. It too must be situated at the root of culture and education.
The nation is indeed the broad community of men who are united by a variety of ties but are above
all joined, in fact, by culture. The nation exists "by" culture and "for" culture, and it is accordingly
the main educative influence ensuring that men can "be more" within the community. It is that com¬
munity which has a history going beyond the history of the individual and the family. It is also in that
community, in terms of which every family acts as an educator, that the family commences its educa¬
tional task with the simplest thing first, by imparting language and thereby enabling man in his early
years to learn to speak, and thus to become a member of the community formed of his family and of
his nation. All I am now saying and shall be dwelling on further reflects a specific experience and a
specific testimonv. I am the son of a nation which has lived throueh the ereatest vicissitudes of
history, which its neighbours have condemned to death more than once, and yet which has survived
and remained itself. It has kept its identity, and despite partition and foreign occupation, it has
maintained its national sovereignty not by depending on the resources of physical force but solely by
relying on its culture. In the case in point, that culture has proved more powerful than all other
forces combined. Hence what I am saying here about the nation's right to the fundamentals of its
culture and its future in no way smacks of "nationalism": that right has been and always will be a
stable factor in human experience and in the humanist outlookfor the development ofman. There is
a fundamental sovereignty of society which is manifested in the culture of the nation. It is that
sovereignty through which, at the same time, man is supremely sovereign. In expressing myself in
these terms, I am also thinking, with deep personal emotion, of the cultures of the many peoples of
old who did not yield when they were confronted with the civilizations of invaders. And those
cultures are still the source of man's "being" in the innermost truth of his humanity. I am also think¬
ing, with a sense of admiration, of the cultures of the new societies, of those societies which are
awakening to life in the community of their own nation, just as my own nation awoke to life ten cen¬
turies ago, and are struggling to maintain their own identity and their own values "against the in¬
fluences and pressures of models proposed from the outside.
To you, ladies and gentlemen, who, for more than thirty years now, have been meeting here in the
name of the primacy of the cultural realities of man, of human communities, peoples and nations, I
should like to say this: use every means at your disposal to watch over the fundamental sovereignty
possessed by every nation by virtue of its own culture. Protect it and cherish it for the sake of the
future of the great human family. Protect it! Do not allow that fundamental sovereignty to fall prey
to political or economic interests. Do not allow it to become the victim of totalitarianism, im-
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
The media
must help
to build a
'more human '
existence
perialism or hegemony, for which man is only an object of domination rather than the subject of his
own human existence. To them, too, the nation whether it be their own nation or that of others is
only an object of domination and a bait for different interests rather than the subject of the
sovereignty deriving from the authentic culture which is its birthright. Are there not, on the map of
Europe and the world, nations which have a marvellous historical sovereignty born of their culture
and yet which are at the same time deprived of their full sovereignty? Is not this an important point
for the future of human culture, especially in our day and age, when it has become so urgent to
banish the remnants of colonialism?
This sovereignty which exists and which has its origins in the specific culture of the nation and
society, in the primacy of the family in the task of education, and in the personal dignity of every in¬
dividual, must remain the fundamental criterion in the approach to the problem of the mass media
(and of the information bound up with them and of what we call "mass culture"), which is so crucial
to mankind today. Since these media are the "social" means of communication, they cannot be the
means ofdomination over others wielded by the agents of political or financial power who set out to
dictate their own programmes and their own models. They must become the meansand a most im¬
portant means of expression for the society which makes use of them and also keeps them in being.
They must bear in mind the real needs of that society. They must take into account the nation's
culture and its history. They must respect the family's responsibility in education. They must have
regard for man's well-being and his dignity. They must not be governed by the criteria of self-
interest, sensationalism or immediate success, but, with due consideration for the requirements of
ethics, must help to build a "more human" existence.
Genus humanum arte et ratione vivit. The basic assertion is that man is himself through truth, and
becomes increasingly himself through an ever more perfect knowledge of truth. I should like here to
pay tribute, ladies and gentlemen, to your Organization's outstanding work, and at the same time to
the work of the States and institutions you represent and their commitment to the task of promoting
the general provision ofeducation for the people at large, at all grades and levels, and of eradicating
illiteracy which reflects the non-existence of even the rudiments of instruction, a grievous deficiency
not only from the point of view of the basic culture of individuals and their environment, but also in
terms of socio-economic progress. There are alarming signs of disparities in this field, linked with an
often acutely unequal and unjust distribution of wealth: we need only think of situations where a
small plutocratic oligarchy coexists with starving multitudes living in extreme poverty. The disparity
can be remedied, not through bloody struggles for power, but above all, by systematicallypromoting
literacy through the widespread provision of education for the masses. This is the direction in which
we must work if we wish afterwards to bring about the changes needed in the socio-economic do¬
main. Man, who "is more" because, also, of what he "has", and what he "possesses", must know
how to possess, that is to say, how to deal with and administer the resources in his possession, for his
own good and for the common good. For this, education is essential.
The question of instruction has always been closely bound up with the Church's mission. Over the
centuries, the Church has founded schools at all levels; it brought into being the medieval universities
in Europe: in Paris and Bologna, Salamanca and Heidelberg, Cracow and Louvain. It still offers the
same contribution today, wherever its action in this field is sought and respected. May I here and
now, on behalf of Catholic families, claim the right of all families to have their children educated in
schools reflecting their own view of the world, and, in particular, the absolute right of believers not
to have their children subjected to atheist-inspired curricula in their schools. This is one of the fun¬
damental rights of man and the family.
The education system is organically linked to the system represented by the various policies follow¬
ed as regards the practice and popularization of science, with which higher education institutions,
universities and also, in the light of the present development of specialization and scientific methods,
specialized institutes, are concerned. These are institutions of which it would be difficult to speak
without feeling deeply affected. They are the workshops, where man's pursuit of knowledge and the
vital bond between humanity and truth as the ultimate aim of knowledge, become a daily reality,
and, in a sense, become the daily bread of so many masters, revered leaders of science, and, around
them, of young research workers dedicated to science and its applications, as well as the multitude of
students enrolled in these centres of science and knowledge.
We are, here, as it were, on the uppermost rungs of the ladder which man has, from the beginning
been climbing towards understanding of the reality of the world around him and of the mysteries of
his own humanity. This historical process has attained a potential in our time unknown in the pajt; it
has opened up hitherto unsuspected horizons to human understanding. It would be difficult to go in¬
to details here for, on the path to knowledge, specialist branches are as manifold as the development
of science is rich.
Your Organization is a meeting-place, encompassing, in the broadest sense of the word, the whole,
essential sphere of human culture. This forum is therefore an ideal place in which to hail all men of
science, and pay tribute particularly to those who are here today and have received the highest
recognition and the most outstanding world honours for their work. Allow me, then, to voice certain
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
The cause
of mankind
will be
served if
science and
conscience
are allied
hopes which will, I have no doubt, find a sympathetic echo in the minds and hearts of the members
of this distinguished assembly.
Just as, in scientific work, we are edifiededified and profoundly gladdenedby that progress in
the disinterested knowledge of truth which scientists serve with the utmost dedication, at times risk¬
ing their health or even their lives, so also must we feel concern at everything which runs counter to
the principles of disinterested objectivity, everything which would turn science into an instrument to
attain goals which are quite alien to it. Yes, we must concern ourselves with everything that proposes
and presupposes such non-scientific aims, when scientists are required to serve their purposes
without having the opportunity of judging and deciding, quite freely, whether such aims are honest
in human and ethical terms, or when they are threatened with the consequences if they refuse to have
any part in them.
Do these non-scientific goals of which I speak and the problem to which I refer need proof or com¬
ment? You know what I have in mind; suffice it to say that among those who were brought before
the international courts at the close of the last world war, there were scientists. Ladies and
gentlemen, please forgive me for uttering these words, but I should be false to my responsibilities if I
did not give voice to them, in order not simply to hark back to the past, but to defend thefuture of
science and human culture; what is more, to defend the future of man and the world! I think that
Socrates, who with his exceptional moral rectitude maintained that science was also a moral virtue,
would be less convinced if he were able to witness the experiments our times.
We are well aware, ladies and gentlemen, that the future of man and of the world is
threatenedvery seriously threateneddespite the unquestionably lofty intentions of scholars and
scientists. It is threatened because the wonderful results of their research and discoveries, particularly
in the natural sciences, have been and are still being exploitedto the detriment of ethical im¬
peratives purposes which have nothing to do with the requirements of science, and indeed for
the purposes ofdestroying and killing. Today, this has reached an unprecedented level and is causing
inconceivable harm. Whereas science ought to be used for the good of human life, we find only too
often that it is subjected to purposes destructive of the true dignity of man and of human life. Such is
the case when scientific research itself is directed to such purposes or when its results are applied to
ends contrary to the good of humanity. There is evidence of this both in the field of genetic
manipulation and biological experiment and in that of chemical, bacteriological or nuclear
armaments.
Two considerations lead me to bring particularly to your attention the nuclear threat hanging over
the world today, which could, if not averted, lead to the destruction of the fruits of culture and the
products of the civilization built up over the centuries by successive generations of men who have
believed in the primacy of the spirit and have spared neither their efforts nor their labours. The first
consideration is this: reasons of geopolitics, economic problems on a world-wide scale, dreadful
misunderstandings, wounded national pride, the materialism of our age and the decline of moral
values have brought our world to a state of instability, a delicate equilibrium which is liable to be
upset at any moment as a result of errors of judgement, information or interpretation.
There is another consideration besides this disquieting prospect. Can we still be sure, nowadays,
that disturbance of that equilibrium would not lead to war, and to a war in which nuclear weapons
would be used without hesitation? Hitherto it has been said that nuclear weapons represented a
deterrent which has prevented the outbreak of a major war; and this is very probably true. But at the
same time we mav wonder if it will always be so. Nuclear weapons, whatever their scale or type, are
becoming more sophisticated year by year, and are being added to the arsenals of an ever-increasing
number of countries. How can we be sure that the use of nuclear weapons, even for purposes of na¬
tional defence or in limited conflicts, will not bring about an unavoidable escalation leading to
destruction on a scale which mankind can never either contemplate or accept? However, there is no
need for me to ask you, scientists and men of culture, not to close your eyes to what a nuclear war
could mean for the whole of mankind (cf. Homily for the World Day of Peace, 1 January 1980).
Ladies and gentlemen, the world cannot go on like this much longer. No one who is aware of the
situation and of what is at stake, and who is guided by an elementary sense of the responsibilities
each individual bears, can avoid the conviction, which is also a moral imperative, that consciences
must be called into play! The efforts ofpeople's consciences must be increased to match the rising
tension between good and evil to which men are being subjected at the close of the twentieth century.
We must become convinced of the priority of the ethical over the technical, of the primacy of people
over things and of the superiority of the spirit over matter (cf. Redemptor Hominis, No. 16). The
cause of mankind will be served if science and conscience are allied. Scientists will truly help
mankind if they preserve "a sense of the transcendence of man over the world and of God over
man" (Address to the Pontifical Academy of Science, 10 November 1979, No. 4).
Thus, availing myself of the opportunity afforded by my being here today at the headquarters of
Unesco, I, child of humanity and Bishop of Rome, address myself directly to you, men of science, to
you assembled here who are the highest authorities in all the domains of modern science. And
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Yes,
world peace
depends on
the primacy
of the Spirit!
through you, I address myself to your colleagues and friends in all countries and on all the
continents.
I appeal to you in the name of this dreadful threat which hangs over mankind, and, at the same
time, in the name of the future and the welfare of humanity throughout the world. I beseech you: let
us do our utmost to institute and respect the primacy of ethics in all the spheres of science. Let us
strive, above all, to preserve the family of man from the terrible prospect of nuclear war!
I took up this subject before the General Assembly of the United Nations in New York on 2
October last year. Today I am speaking of it to you. I appeal to your minds and to your hearts, above
and beyond all passions, ideologies and frontiers. I appeal to all those who, by their political or
economic power, could be, and often are, called upon to determine scientists' conditions of work
and the lines they are to follow. Above all, I appeal to each scientist individually and to the entire
international scientific community.
Together you have enormous power, the power of the intellect and of the conscience! Show
yourselves to be more powerful than the most powerful in our contemporary world! Resolve to show
the most noble form of solidarity with mankind: that which is based on the dignity of man. Build up
peace on the foundation of respect for all man's rights, those bound up with his material and
economic life as well as those connected with the spiritual and inner dimensions of his existence in
this world. May wisdom inspire you! May love be your guide, that love which will overcome the
growing menace of hatred and destruction! Men of science, pledge your full moral authority to save
mankind from nuclear destruction!
Today I have accomplished one of the most ardent desires of my heart. I have been given the
opportunity, here, of entering the Areopagus of the whole world. I have been given the opportunity
of telling you all, members of the United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization,
who are working for good and for the reconciliation of men and peoples through all the fields of
culture, education, science and information, of crying out to you, from the depths of my soul: Yes,
the future of mankind depends on culture! Yes, world peace depends on the primacy of the Spirit!
Yes, peace in mankind's future depends on love!
Your personal contribution, ladies and gentlemen, is important, indeed vital. It consists in adop¬
ting the correct approach to the problems with which you have to wrestle.
My final word is this: Do not abandon the struggle! Continue it without ceasing!
NES
161
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
s*
Willingly to school
Satchels and abacus on their backs, three
Chinese children wend their way to
school. They are among the world's
luckier ones, for one young person in four
enters employment without having
received minimum education. Illiteracy
and poor school enrolment are two sides
of the same coin and the fact is that the
advance of schooling does not keep pace,
on a world scale, with the demands of
high rates of population growth.
Although percentage illiteracy rates are
falling, the absolute number of illiterates
continues^to increase. If present trends
continue the number of illiterates will rise
from 814 million in 1980 to 884 million in
1990 (see article page 4).
]]>
</page>
</document>
