<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074744eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
India
Lotus-ruffed sun worshipper
An endless source of fascination for mankind, the sun has inspired
a wealth of traditions, cults, philosophies and works of art. This
circular motif representing a lotus flower in full bloom is dedicated
to the golden orb, on whose energy all life depends. The figure
framed by the ruff-like lotus is doubtless a sun worshipper. The
bas-relief, now preserved in the Indian Museum at Calcutta, is
from the lintel of a door of the great stupa of Bharhut (India)
which dates from the second century BC.
Photo © Giraudon, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Ihr
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JULY 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IIM 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
. reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprirjted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc.. 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.: (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese-
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition; Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio' de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
. Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
B?
MEETING THE ENERGY CHALLENGE
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
6 THE TRANSITION TO A NEW ENERGY MIX
by Enrique V. Iglesias
9 PROFILES OF CHANGE
All paths to a viable world energy system
lead through a gate marked 'global co-operation'
by Wolfgang Sassin
10 THE CHARACTER OF ENERGY
13 IMPLICATIONS OF A SUSTAINABLE ENERGY SYSTEM
14 THE DEVELOPING WORLD
DEMANDS A PLACE IN THE SUN
by Abdou Moumouni Dioffo
17 WORLD ENERGY FILE
by Zoran Zarió
18 Fossil fuels
21 Nuclear power
23 Geothermal energy
24 Tide, Wind, Wave
27 Hydropower, Ocean thermal energy
29 Solar energy
31 Solar fuels
19 BRIDGING THE GAP IN TRAINING AND INFORMATION
by James F. McDivitt
20 UNIFYING THE FUNDAMENTAL FORMS OF ENERGY
by Abdus Salam
23 NEW AND RENEWABLE SOURCES OF ENERGY:
COSTS AND CONSTRAINTS
by Boris M. Berkovsky
29 SOLAR POWER FOR THE SAHEL:
A UNESCO FEASIBILITY STUDY
32 BRAZIL'S GREEN GASOLINE
by Benedicto Silva
33 BIOGAS: THE INDIAN EXPERIENCE
by Tushar Kanti Moulik
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
INDIA: Lotus-ruffed sun-worshipper
Cover
This issue of the Unesco Courier is devoted
to world energy problems and the need to
engineer a smooth transition to a new "mix"
of energy sources which will reduce depen¬
dence on dwindling fossil fuels. This is not
only a challenge for modern technology, it is
a challenge for international co-operation
and solidarity since the energy crisis, which
affects all nations, is imposing a dispropor¬
tionately heavy burden on developing coun¬
tries struggling to pay for their development
in a world of steeply rising energy prices.
Unesco is closely concerned with world
energy problems and is taking part in a Uni¬
ted Nations Conference on New and Re¬
newable Energy Sources which is being held
in Nairobi (Kenya) between 10 and 21 August
1981.
Cover design Nagai Kazumasa
©Graphic Design Associates, Tokyo
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Meeting the
ENERGY has always been a factor of fundamental importance
in the life of human societies. All activity entails the expen¬
diture of energy and hence, from the draught animal to
nuclear fission, the history of energy merges with the history of
mankind, in whose pattern it is in many respects one of the guiding
threads. The production of energy down the ages has followed the
development of scientific thought, and the forms of energy available
and the manner of their use have often had a direct influence on the
nature of society. In other words energy must be considered, in a
historical perspective, in the light of culture in its broadest sense.
Thus in the nineteenth century the massive use of coal, coupled
with the invention of the steam engine and progress in chemistry and
steel manufacturing, made possible the first industrial revolution
which transformed the essentially agrarian societies of Europe and
then America. Likewise, the discovery of electricity and its host of
uses, whether for lighting, mechanization, or communication, have
made a deep impact on the lives of men and women of every conti¬
nent and have fostered the creation and growth of the world's great
cities. In the twentieth century the exploitation at an increasingly
rapid rate of the other fossil fuels, oil and natural gas, has, along
with the development of hydro-electric power and nuclear energy,
enabled the industrialized societies to pursue the momentous
changes which have given birth to the modern world, with its hopes
and contradictions.
If energy problems are today so acute at the international level as
to justify the holding of a United Nations Conference on New and
Renewable Energy Sources, this is because it no longer seems possi¬
ble to satisfy the world's constantly mounting energy needs by conti¬
nuing to exploit, exactly as before, too limited a range of energy
resources. The international community is thus confronted with the
challenge of making forthwith those structural changeseconomic,
social and technologicalwhich are required by the transition to
new energy sources.
In fact, as this issue of the Unesco Courier makes clear, given the
circumstances. of production and living conditions which currently
prevail in a number of countries, no single energy source can con¬
tinue to meet all energy needs over a very long period; nor are there
new sources capable of taking over fully from those which now exist.
Such is the outcome of a world situation which has been characteriz¬
ed for too long by the intensive exploitation, for economic reasons
related, for instance, to underpayment for energy, of non-renewable
sources such as oil over which there hangs the threat of eventual ex¬
haustion. The study of alternative solutions should aim to increase
energy production but it must also situate this endeavour within a
wider context. It no longer seems possible to envisage the future
without taking into consideration total world energy consumption,
together with the need for changes in the energy economy as a whole,
with all the consequences which will ensue for the environment and
for society.
Such a project concerns all countries, whether industrialized or
developing. It is true that the problems it raises will differ from one
nation to another, but it is in the interest of them all that the transi¬
tion should take place smoothly, as part of a concerted effort. Par-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
energy challenge
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
ticularly important is the tapping of new, less costly energy sources
which can be exploited almost everywhere. For the developing coun¬
tries the problem is of vital importance. The increasingly unequal
situation in which they find themselves today means that their
chances of mobilizing the necessary financial resources are slight.
Consequently they must find new resources, but above all they must
have access, notably through a better flow of information, to the
knowledge and techniques whose mastery is indispensable to their
progress. For this to come about, these countries need to join in
world decision-making as full and rightful partners. The transition
to diversified energy sources is in large measure linked to the setting
up of new rules and new mechanisms designed to alleviate the
tensions of the world economy and to bring into being a more equi¬
table international economic order, in a spirit of solidarity and
concertation.
Unesco is taking part in this process of international reflexion and
action. Apart from the fact that the whole thrust of its activities is to
encourage the emergence of this new order, it is particularly
qualified to contribute to the strengthening of international scientific
co-operation which is indispensable to the advancement of learning
and the free circulation of knowledge. It can also help countries
which are attempting to solve their energy problems to draw up na¬
tional policies which take account of all the factors involved,
whether they are related to science, technology, education, informa¬
tion, or to social and cultural life.
The free flow of scientific and technical information and the ex¬
change of data acquired through experience in different social,
economic and cultural situations can make a decisive contribution to
speeding up the exploitation of new and renewable energy sources,
notably in the developing countries. With this in mind, Unesco is
currently engaged in creating an international information system on
energy sources, the use of which necessitates not only data from
many fieldsthe physical sciences, ecology, the life sciences,
engineering, economics but also access to documentation on pro¬
duction, planning and training at every level, from university
teaching to the education of rural populations. This system will thus
be of interest to a wide range of users, from research workers to
planners, from engineers to educators, not to mention the wider
public whose involvement is essential where energy-saving or the
adoption of new techniques are concerned. The setting up of such an
information network is, of course, indissociable from an intensifica¬
tion of research, teaching, training and popularization, all of which
Unesco's programme seeks to promote.
Unesco is also concerned to put the problems of energy in a con¬
text in which all their complexity can be grasped, and has according¬
ly set out to identify the many non-technical factors (especially those
of a social and cultural nature) which affect the exploitation of the
different energy sources. Social attitudes, differing from country to
country, can have far from negligible effects on the possibilities and
rapidity of change.
The environmental problems resulting from an increased reliance
on coal and nuclear energy should not be neglected, either. Here at¬
tention has tended to focus on certain short-term effects on public
health or working conditions or on direct consequences for the
physical environment, at the expense of the longer-term social,
cultural and ecological consequences for which there are often very
few data available and which, if they are to be tackled comprehen¬
sively, require more concerted international action.
. Through these studies and activities relating to energy problems
Unesco wishes to contribute on the one hand to each country's ef¬
forts to pursue its development along its own specific lines and on
the other to the efforts being made by the international community
in the late twentieth century to achieve a balanced and more
equitable management of the planet's resources, considered as the
heritage of all peoples and of generations present and to come.
But an analysis of energy problems cannot be isolated from a
historical appraisal of the relations between the successive levels of
energy use by mankind and the evolution of the scientific concepts
which make the use of energy possible. Energy produced by human
and animal muscle was, for long ages in the history of mankind, the
most important form of energy, as it still is for many peoples today.
It underlay the earliest development of agriculture and urban
civilization. As a result of the rise of the physical sciences and their
application to the interpretation of natural phenomena, the meaning
of the word energy gradually became wider: to mechanical energy
were added thermodynamic and electrodynamic energy, opening the
way for a first leap in the scale of energy production, from the
; kilowatt to the megawatt, and providing impetus for the first in¬
dustrial revolution. The next theoretical development, the quantum
theory, corresponded to the crossing of a new threshold: the use of
energy from nuclear fission. This discovery, associated with the
development of computers, led in turn to the second industrial
revolution, with energy now being measured not in megawatts but in
gigawatts. Other thresholds will undoubtedly be crossed with the
continuance of fundamental research into the structure of matter
and the development of techniques for effectively eliminating and
recycling radioactive wastes. Nuclear fusion is a promising field
because it releases even greater quantities of energy than those pro¬
duced hitherto, and the fuel required isextremely abundant.
These successive breakthroughs in knowledge, promptly turned to
practical use by human ingenuity, are the fruit of individual
genius the genius of the great scientists of every age whose
achievements are so many milestones in the history of scientific
thought. But just as the quickening tempo of progress in the last few
decades was made possible as a result of the slow accumulation of
universal knowledge and its transmission across time and space, so
scientific and technological innovation, though it may be first and
foremost a matter of individual or collective creation, cannot, given
the complexity of the world today, serve the welfare of all without
close co-operation between all those communities and centres in
which it comes into being and finds application. This intellectual co¬
operation is a cherished field of activity for Unesco^ By encouraging
it, by tightening the bonds between the world's scientists, Unesco, in
the field of energy and elsewhere, is also preparing a future in which
man will possess knowledge to release forces on a par with his im¬
mense needs and will be sufficiently wise to master those forces.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The transition to anew
energy mix
A United Nations Conference
on new and renewable energy sources
by Enrique V. Iglesias
ENERGY is a fundamental issue to all
people. It permeates the fabric of
human society, affecting daily life in
every home as well as world politics, inter¬
national economics and national develop¬
ment strategies. In recent years, energy has
acquired significant importance due to what
has been called, with some ambiguity, the
world energy crisis. Three important
elements characterize this crisis and situate
the problem in its correct perspective.
ENRIQUE V. IGLESIAS, of Uruguay, is
Secretary-General of the United Nations Con¬
ference on New and Renewable Sources of
Energy, which is being held in Nairobi from 10 to
21 August. Since 1972 he has been executive
secretary of the United Nations Economic Com¬
mission for Latin America.
First, at the beginning of the 1970s, it
became apparent that fossil fuels, for so
long the basis of the energy balance of the
modern world, would in the not too distant
future be depleted. For the first time, the
rate of reserve discoveries and the rate of
consumption growth became inverted,
providing mankind with a realistic perspec¬
tive based on scientific assessments that
depletion could take place during the next
generation.
The second element of this crisis comes
from the fact that for the first time in history,
an energy transition will be accompanied by
higher economic cost. Until recently, people
had been living through a period of cheap
energy and depressed oil prices. From now
on, energy will be available only at higher
prices, setting a new challenge of unknown '
prqportions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Lastly, the energy crisis has affected
humanity in a very uneven manner. The
crisis, affecting both industrialized and
developing nations, has had a very special
impact on the developing countries. These
countries will have to go through their pro¬
cess of economic development and moder¬
nization with much higher energy prices
than those paid by the industrialized coun¬
tries. This undoubtedly presents the interna¬
tional community with a problem of equity
and solidarity which should stimulate inter¬
national co-operation.
The United Nations, whose raison d'être
concerns international co-operation in the
search for solutions to common problems of
humanity, is in a unique position to discuss
and initiate activities in the energy field.
For this reason, in December 1978, the
General Assembly invited all governments to
a Conference to be held in Nairobi from 10
to 21 August 1981, whose main objective
was to be the elaboration of measures for
the concerted action needed to promote the
development and utilization of new and
renewable sources of energy, in order to
meet over-all future energy requirements, in
particular within the context of efforts aim¬
ed at accelerating the development of Third
World nations. These measures will be spell¬
ed out in the Programme of Action, one of
the basic documents of the Conference,
which is currently the subject of continuing
negotiation with all participating Govern¬
ments and Agencies.
One fact of enormous political importance
calls for emphasis. For the first time in
human history, the impending world energy
transition necessitates that the international
community work and debate collectively on
possible options. This paves the way for the
-Conference to initiate activities designed to
lead towards a new world energy mix based
on a pluralistic and diversified framework of
available energy sources that can provide a
horizon of peace and security. It would be
useful to recall here five elements of this
energy transition.
The first element is its inevitability. Oil
consumption in the world energy mix will
continue to play a significant role although
of relatively decreasing significance through
the end of the century. The demand for oil
will be important in the industrialized world
where it is expected that the increment in
demand will be of the order of 50% and will
be 4 to 5 times the present demand of the
developing world which requires energy
sources to accelerate its process of develop¬
ment and growth.
All this will occur regardless of conserva¬
tion or investment policies. At some mo¬
ment in the next century, oil will be even less
significant in the world energy consumption
pattern, making imperative a new energy
mix. This is the inevitable challenge facing
the industrialized and developing countries
collectively.
The second characteristic is that the tran¬
sition is viable. It is not possible to say today
that the world lacks energy resources. That
is not the problem. The problem is the
potential scarcity of certain types of fuels,
mainly the liquid fuels. Experts have told us
on several occasions that energy resources
do exist, and point out that the real problem
is one of investment in technological
resources and in production. There will,
they say, no longer be a single alternative
energy source as in the past, but instead a
mixture of such sources.
A third aspect of this energy transition is
that it will be much more complex than
energy transitions in the past a complexity
due mainly to the fact that humanity has
maintained, over many decades, artificially
low and depressed fossil fuels prices and
that the current adjustment has been pro¬
duced by a process which has complex im¬
plications. Over the short term, the prob¬
lems of balance of payments, imbalances in
the energy bill and imported inflation will af¬
fect particularly the developing countries
which have not even been able to make ad¬
justments by expanding their exports but
which are increasing their indebtedness.
More important than this, however, the
transition will mean that higher and higher
proportions of the sums available for invest¬
ment will have to be devoted to energy. This
means that there will be fierce competition
between investment for energy and other
economic and social investment. Some
developing countries might even be obliged
virtually to stop investing in energy, which
would constitute a very serious threat to
their future development.
The fourth characteristic of the energy
transition is that it implies varying degrees of
urgency. It appears that the world is facing
an energy transition which will manifest
itself in a different manner for the modern
Distribution of World Population and Energy Use in 1975
Industrially developed
countries
Developing countries E0.9
2788
H Per capita energy use in kilowatt years per year
I Population in millions
Based on MASA data
sector of the world economy than for the
traditional sector. To the modern sector, the
energy transition presents a strong
technological challenge to make available a
diversity of energy sources. Yet if we follow
historical optimism and humanity's
achievements over recent decades in the
energy field, there will be no room for
pessimism: the world, particularly the
modern sector, will always find ways to ef¬
fect an adequate energy transition. On the
other hand, a very different situation obtains
for the traditional sector basically located in
the developing countries. The rural areas of
many of these countries are still operating
on fuelwood and charcoal and have not yet
made the first energy transition.
Lastly, I believe that the fifth aspect of the
energy transition involves efficiency in the
use of energy as a fundamental element of
this transition. This has been noted very
clearly by the industrialized countries which
in recent years have made very commen¬
dable efforts to conserve energy. However,
there is still a lot to do to improve the effi¬
ciency of primary energy use. When experts
tell us that only 15 per cent of the primary
energy reaches its end use and that 70 to 80
per cent is lost along the way, this obviously
leaves much room for improvement. This is
true not only for the industrialized countries
but also the developing countries.
The Conference therefore has as its
primary objective to examine the options
available for an energy transition involving
these five characteristics.. Another aim of
equal importance is to examine the energy
transition in the context of the requirements
of developing countries. Here is where the
need to consider a development strategy
provides the energy transition with a new
dimension.
In this context new and renewable
sources of energy can play a substantial
role. However, increased access for
developing countries to energy supplies of
a/1 types is fundamental to the process of ac¬
celerating their development and is consis¬
tent with the goal of a more equitable
distribution of economic opportunities
among nations.
One fact is now certain; the prevailing
development patterns can no longer be sus¬
tained in either the developed or the
developing countries on the basis of the ex¬
isting energy systems. Recent studies have
shown that, while there is generally a strong
positive correlation between the level of
development of a country and its energy
use, it is possible to design development
strategies that would require less energy
than in the past. New energy systems have
to be developed for all countries based on
greater diversification and self-sufficiency
and on a significant increase in the efficient
use of energy sources. This may be easier in
the'developing countries for whom options
are more varied, unhampered as they are by
long-established industrial infrastructures.
It is both a sovereign right of as well as a
unique challenge to each country to find an
answer to this question within the
framework of their development strategies
and energy policies. It is a challenge to the
responsibility and solidarity of the interna¬
tional community to find a way to help
developing countries obtain the basic
energy inputs they need to accelerate their k
economic and social development. f
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
How then can we create awareness of the
need to prepare and promote this energy
transition in developing countries in a way
which will be innovative and at the same
time ensure the energy required for develop¬
ment? I believe that the first consideration
needed is to emphasize that countries can¬
not consider an energy strategy in isolation.
Energy is most definitely a central compo¬
nent of any nation's general development
strategy.
The other important consideration is that
when energy strategies in the developing
world become part of an overall develop¬
ment policy, they can be used to promote
economic and social development. Great im¬
agination is required to formulate strategies
for the energy transition that will become
not merely simple passive inputs into the
development process, but an engine of
growth based on the use of natural
resources, of labour, and of local
technologies.
The common global interest to increase
the energy available should be based on a
diversified and sustainable mix which can
ensure for humanity a stream of renewable
resources for the future. This effort com¬
plements a development strategy that will
make an active and dynamic contribution to
the economic and social development pro¬
cess during the energy transition.
The energy transition will have to be con¬
sidered at two levels of urgency. In the short
term, high priority must be given to the
problem of energy for the rural poor
and especially the depletion of fuelwood
resources a particularly important part of
the challenge faced in developing countries.
Over the medium term, it will be necessary
to accelerate strongly and vigorously
technological research in order to reduce the
time it takes for new and renewable energy
sources to penetrate into the energy
mix both of developed and developing
countries.
It will be necessary to stimulate interna¬
tional co-operation, especially through the
transfer of financial resources to developing
countries, to support energy research,
technology transfer and investment and to
do away with bottlenecks in our attempts to
increase and diversify the energy supply,
particularly in developing countries.
Finally, the Nairobi Conference should
serve to promote a strong co-operative ef¬
fort within the United Nations system which
will have major responsibility for implemen¬
ting the Programme of Action. I believe that,
if this Conference can really challenge and
stimulate the co-operative and co-ordinating
capacities of the United Nations system, it
will render that system more effective in
responding to the needs of its Member
States.
Enrique V. Iglesias
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Profiles of change
All paths to a viable world energy system
lead through a gate marked 'global co-operation'
by Wolfgang Sassin
INCREASING interdependence between
nations inevitably gives rise to new prob¬
lems which if they are not tackled and
mastered in good time may become chronic
and form a focus for international tensions.
When things reach that stage nations are
tempted simply to try to adapt as best they
can to the situation on hand, with each
country using available resources to
strengthen its own position. The will to work
together for a long-term solution is lost and
this creates at the very least an additional
obstacle to world as well as national
development. .
The energy problem that became ap¬
parent in the early 1970s seems to be evolv¬
ing along these lines. It arises from the rapid
changeover from national energy supply
systems to a global system based on highly
localized oil reserves.
The swift rise in world energy consump¬
tion that took place at the same time has
been a decisive factor (see diagram this
page).
When the first oil crisis developed, one
small area, the Gulf, was meeting 20 per
cent of the world's energy needs. The major
part of the output of the Member States of
the Organization of Petroleum Exporting
Countries (OPEC) went to the industrialized
countries of Western Europe and to the
United States and Japan.
Today, nearly eight years after the first oil
embargo of 1973 when OPEC took control
of the oil price-fixing mechanism, three facts
are clear: (1) throughout the world, oil con¬
sumption has peaked at about its 1973/74
level; (2) so far no alternative energy source
has been able to take over the role played by
oil up to 1973 as a cheap production factor
promoting economic growth; and (3) the
world economy is going through a phase of
reduced growth and is facing severe struc¬
tural crises and increasing difficulties with
regard to the international division of labour.
In recent years efforts have been inten¬
sified to find national solutions to the energy
problem. Some industrialized countries, fac¬
ed with the prospect of drastically reduced
economic growth and obliged by rising
prices to adopt fuel-saving measures, seem
to have. fairly good hopes of limiting their
dependence on an uncertain supply system.
Other countries, especially in the Third
World, are relying on increased exploration
of their still unprospected territories and on
The deep concern about energy today relates to the fact
that the resources of oil and gas, our most modern and
most important energy forms, are limited. Figure below
summarizes the history of consumption of primary energy
over the past 100 years. Total consumption has grown at
an average rate of 5 % per year, except at times of world¬
wide crises: World War I, the recession of the 1930s,
World War II, and now the oil crisis. It is worth noting
that this high growth rate was supported by coal around
1900. whereas for the last two decades it has been based
on oil and gas, which presently account for 73 % of the
primary energy consumption of the world.
stepping-up technological development in
order to tap resources unavailable up to now
for technical or economic reasons. This is
especially true of biomass, hydropower and
solar energy, through which the rural
populations of the developing countries are
attempting to meet their energy needs using
traditional and at present not very efficient
technologies.
Whether these unco-ordinated efforts can
ever solve the energy problem is an open
question. In any event, for a long time to
come, many countries will still have to rely
on energy imported from abroad.. That is
one of the weak points of national energy
policies, though by no means the most
significant. Energy has been and remains a
decisive factor in industrial development.
Even if it were possible to devise means of
ensuring a fair free 'market distribution,
scarce supplies and high prices are bound to
put a constraint on development and, in a
world based on the international division of
labour, this would be economically damag¬
ing to all countries. There is plenty of
evidence of this. Local and national efforts
in the energy ' sector must therefore be
assessed in a global and long-term context.
History shows that the changeover from
one source of energy to another takes many
decades. The switch from wood to coal, and
then from coal to oil and gas took more than
half a century. The changes to these new
energy forms took place in favourable cir¬
cumstances economic growth and
decreasing production costs of the" new
forms of energy.
In the future it will be more difficult in
many respects to maintain sufficient energy
supplies. In the first place, the world popula-
OIL CRISIS
GAS
WORLD WAR I
WORLD WAR I
1880 1900 1920 1940 1960
PRIMARY GL0GAL ENERGY CONSUMPTION
1980
WOLFGANG SASSIN, of the Federal Republic
of Germany, recently became deputy leader of
the energy systems programme of the Interna¬
tional Institute for Applied Systems Analysis
(IIASA) at Laxenburg (Austria). A physicist by
training, he has been a member of the programme
since 1975.
IIASA is a non-governmental, multidisciplinar/,
international research institution founded in 1972
by the academies of science and equivalent scien¬
tific organizations of 12 nations. Its goal is to
bring together scientists from around the world to
work on problems of common interest, particular¬
ly those resulting from scientific and
technological development. The Institute now
has 17 national member organizations in: Austria,
Bulgaria, Canada, Czechoslovakia, Finland,
France, the . German Democratic Republic, the
Federal Republic of Germany, Hungary, Italy,
Japan, the Netherlands, Poland, Sweden, the
U.K., U.S.A., andU.S.S.R.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
, tion is growing at an unprecedented rate:
some 400 million people have been born and
added to the global population total since
the first oil crisis and their material needs will
soon make themselves felt. Even if there is a
considerable reduction in the average
number of births per family, the world
population will almost double in the next
fifty years.
Projections show that the demographic
growth will be much greater in Third World
countries than elsewhere because of the
large proportion of young people and
children reaching or approaching reproduc¬
tive age. In the next two decades, the in¬
tegration of these new generations into their
country's economy is going to spark off an
explosion in demand for goods and services.
The character
of energy
When people talk about energy, it is not always clear what
kinds of energy they are talking about, and this adds to the
problem. Therefore, in order to understand the physical energy
system, it is important to distinguish between energy at
various stages of conversion and use.
Primary energy is the energy recovered from nature water
flowing over a dam, coal freshly mined, oil, natural gas, natural
uranium. Only rarely can primary energy be used to supply final
energy energy used to supply the consumer with energy ser¬
vices. One of the few forms of primary energy that can be used
as final energy is natural gas, which is why it is a fuel of pre¬
ference whenever it is available.
For the most part, primary energy is converted into secon¬
dary energy. This is defined as an energy form that can be used
over a broad spectrum of applications. Electricity and gasoline
are the major examples. Less convenient (which is why they
are declining in their market shares) forms of secondary energy
include charcoal, sorted and graded coai, and cut and split
fuelwood. In order to apply energy without making undue
demands on the consumer, it must be converted into a form
that may be readily transported, distributed and used in a
variety of devices. The trend has been toward grids, for
obvious reasons specifically toward electricity, gas, and dis¬
trict heating grids For convenience of storage, portability, and
transportability, the trend has also been to liquid fuels, of
which gasoline and diesel oii are the best examples.
Primary energy is converted into secondary energy in several
different ways. For example, central power plants produce
electricity and, sometimes, district heat. Refineries convert
petroleum to more convenient liquid fuels gasoline, jet fuel,
diesel oil, and naphtha. Sometimes the conversion plant is the
end point of a system, as with nuclear fission energy (for which
chemical conversion, isotopic enrichment, and fuel fabrication
all precede the power plant); sometimes, as with a hydroelec¬
tric or a wind generator, it is a simple machine. But regardless,
there are conversion losses in going from primary to secondary
energy and transmission losses in getting that energy to the
consumer. It is wrong to think of these losses as waste. They
represent a trade-off of efficiencies: the use of energy to trans¬
form and transmit energy permits the end user to apply it effi¬
ciently for his purposes.
These final steps are the conversion of secondary energy
into final energy the energy in a motor, a stove, a computer,
or a light bulb and of final energy into useful energy the
energy actually stored in a product or used for a service. It is
important to realize that in providing the service say, a well-lit
room energy is not merely a stored entity, but even more an
input for the efficient use of other resources, of labour, of capi¬
tal, and especially of skill.
Source : Energy in a Finite World, 1981
International Institute for Applied Systems Analysis, Laxenburg, Austria
Establishing the necessary infrastructures is
a highly energy-intensive process, so that,
even given technically improved systems
with higher energy efficiency and reduced
per capita economic growth rates, the
energy supply would have to be increased
substantially in the coming decades.
This prospect shows that it was a mistake
to let the world's energy supply potential
reach near-stagnation, even though as a
consequence certain countries especially
the rich industrialized nations are now
adopting energy conservation measures.
This stagnation has several causes. The
traditional oil-producing countries, pointing
to the finite nature of their reserves, have
been restricting their output; in other coun¬
tries production capacities have fallen; coal
production has not expanded substantially
in spite of the increased oil and gas prices of
1973/74; and, finally, many developing
countries are experiencing a crisis in the
non-commercial energy sector, with large
areas facing a severe firewood shortage.
Against this background the International
Institute for Applied Systems Analysis
(IIASA) in Laxenburg (Austria) has carried
out a comprehensive study of the
possibilities of developing the various
energy sources on a global scale and even¬
tually balancing supply and demand (1). The
idea was to view these problems in a world
perspective instead of approaching them
merely at the national level. In this context
the sum total of imports needed by in¬
dividual countries in order to balance their
energy budgets had to be matched by cor¬
responding export surpluses available in
other countries. Such a method of course
excludes consideration of all but the basic
factors determining the "global" system. It
also involves very broad assumptions about
the behaviour of the various countries within
this "closed global economic system".
The grouping of the world's over
160 countries into seven major regions was
an essential step. The industrialized nations
form three groups classified according to
their economic system and the abundance
of their energy reserves: the market
economy countries of North America; the
planned economies of the Soviet Union and
Eastern Europe; and the Organization for
Economic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) countries minus North
America i.e. Western Europe, Japan,
Australia and New Zealand. The developing
countries are divided into four regions :
Latin America; the oil-rich countries of the
Middle East and North Africa; an area en¬
compassing black Africa and South-East
Asia; and, finally, the planned economy
countries of Eastern Asia.
Taking into account the various stages of
development, the IIASA experts evaluated
the economic and social trends in each of
these regions and on this basis calculated
probable energy requirements. They also
111 Energy in a Finite World (Vol. I: Paths to a Sus¬
tainable Future; Vol. 2: A Global Systems Analysis^
report by the Energy Systems Programme Group of
IIASA, Programme Leader: Wolf Häfele. Ballinger
Publishing Company, Cambridge, Massachusetts, 1981.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Individual consumption
expressed in thousands
of kilocalories per day
Food
Domestic Industry
and and
services (1) agriculture
Transport Total
Primitive man
Hunter
Primitive farmer 12
Developed farmer 12 26
'Industrial" man 32 24 14 77
"Technological" man 10 66 91 63 230
ID The services sector Includes office work, trade, teaching, etc.
calculated each region's potential in fossil
fuel resources and reserves, as well as the
timing and rate for the introduction of new
and renewable energy sources. These pro¬
jections are based on assumptions regarding
the positive outcome of future prospecting,
research and development projects. By ad¬
ding together the figures for all countries
and regions, the global potential in ultimate¬
ly recoverable resources can be obtained,
thus making it possible to quantify the
results of the vigorous efforts required in the
coming decades. In the present state of
technology and at the present level of
energy production costs, only about one
third of the estimated ultimately recoverable
fossil resources is accessible.
Rough calculations already show that
some of the seven regions will not be able to
meet their energy needs entirely from their
own sources, for their traditional non¬
renewable energy reserves oil, natural gas
and economically extractable coal are too
small, and new or renewable sources, such
as oil shales, tar sands and nuclear and solar
energy in all their forms, cannot be
developed fast enough.
All this substantiates the assumption of
the IIASA study, of an open and
production-cost-oriented access to the
world's energy supplies. Apart from certain
limitations with regard to traditional oil
deposits, all seven world regions share the
globe's energy sources and have access to
the new extraction and conversion
technologies.
Despite this optimistic assumption about
universal co-operation in solving the energy
problem, closer studies indicate that insuffi¬
cient power supplies will remain a constraint
.on world economic development for the
next fifty years.
The total energy demand is so great that
questions of preference do not arise: all
sources have to be developed.
On the consumer side, too, energy must
be used more rationally. The unusual and
disturbing discrepancy between the predic¬
tably great efforts required to produce
energy and the limited prospects for
economic growth has led the authors of the
IIASA study to develop a "low-growth"
scenario alongside the initial "high-growth"
one. In the "high-growth" scenario
previously accepted economic targets have
been reduced, especially in the developing
countries, while in the "low-growth" model,
which postulates a reduction in economic
growth, world energy demand is substan- 1
tially decreased. I
PRESENT AND ESTIMATED FUTURE WORLD USE
OF NEW AND RENEWABLE
SOURCES OF ENERGY
Source
Present use
in billion (10=) kWh
m
Utilization
n the year 2000
billion (109> kWh
Solar 2-3 2,000-5,000
Geothermal 55 1,000-5,000
Wind 2 1,000-5,000
Tidal 0.4 30-60
Wave 0 10
Thermal gradient
of the sea
0 1,000
Biomass 550-700 2,000-5,000
Fuelwood 10,000-12,000 15,000-20,000
Charcoal 1,000 2,000-5,000
Peat 20 1,000
Draught animals 30 (in India) 1,000
Oil shale 15 500
Tar sands 130 1,000
Hydropower 1,500 3,000
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
^ No study, however complete, can predict
the future. But carried out with care it can
indicate what kind of political and social
decisions lie before us. The choice will de¬
pend to a large extent on the value system
prevailing at the time, but it will also be in¬
fluenced by the availability of relevant data
on the true situation and on the possible
consequences of having adopted certain
measures and rejected others. In this sense,
NASA's "high" and "low-growth" scenarios
describe future trends that are basically
feasible. Both give an idea of the upper
limits of the global economic development
process. These limits are determined by the
earth's energy resources as provided by
nature and by the efficiency of present
energy production and conservation
technologies. Two key conclusions emerge
from these scenarios:
(1) In both scenarios the construction of a
global energy supply, system calls for
vigorous efforts, but these do not appear
unrealistic given the projected volume of
economic activity in the regions under con¬
sideration. In any case, the relative invest¬
ment burden on the economy is roughly the
same in each scenario. In other words, pro¬
vided the proper preliminary measures are
carried out in good time, it is technically
possible to make available a sufficient
amount of energy to sustain high economic
growth rates. Low growth rates do not help
to overcome energy crises.
(2) If sufficient co-operation for the
development of supply capacities is not
forthcoming, overall costs will exceed the
sum projected in the IIASA scenarios. Ef¬
forts made by individual countries to hus¬
band their own viable energy resources and
develop those that are still unexploited, as
well as to maintain a safety margin for the
future, may be understandable at national
level, but they tend to aggravate the prob¬
lem at world level. They compel other coun¬
tries to make an early changeover to alter¬
native energies that are both scarce and
more expensive.
In practice, political, social and organiza¬
tional difficulties always give rise to
pragmatic energy strategies of this kind.
And this can lead to a vicious circle: the
hasty introduction of insufficiently devel¬
oped alternative energy sources in any part
of the world will strengthen the arguments
of those advocating national and local
solutions.
Then again, energy that proves too costly
is another pitfall to be avoided, for it could
easily foster economic stagnation. The
development of alternative sources requires
more capital and manpower than the tradi¬
tional oil and gas production technologies.
Thus the transition to new and more expen¬
sive forms of energy would be an additional
burden on an already stagnating economy.
Solving the world energy problem is
becoming more and more a race against
time. To win it will take more than scientific
and technical feats. In the first place effi¬
cient use must be made of available
resources, of the possibilities of advanced
technology and of the considerable in
vestments necessary to tap potential energy
sources. This requires close economic and
political co-operation between energy-
producing and energy-consuming countries.
Individual nations must also realize that
ensuring a stable energy supply requires
much more effort than would appear from
short-term local analyses. But even when
these conditions are fulfilled, . the
rewardstability does not in itself pro¬
duce any. immediately consumable benefits.
Rather the rise in costs resulting from the in¬
creased volume of investments needed to
ensure a stable energy supply must be seen
as a share in the global economic develop¬
ment burden.
But here political will, though necessary,
is not enough: suitable technical and institu¬
tional preparations to distribute that burden
are also essential. At the international level
the IIASA studies identify three critical areas
sharing the following characteristics: a
rapidly growing gap between the rising
energy demand and the means of satisfying
it; a very marked dearth of information
about the factors likely to inhibit or en¬
courage the discovery of new technical solu¬
tions; and a lack of vigour in developing
such technical solutions.
These three areas of strategic importance
for the stabilization of the global energy
system are:
(1) The development of appropriate
technological processes and procedures
which in the next twenty to thirty years will
lead to the development of a synthetic liquid
hydrocarbon industry operating on a
worldwide basis. Given the role synthetic
fuels will be called upon to play in the world
energy budget, future production pro¬
grammes will have to outstrip by far the out¬
put of all the nuclear energy programmes of
the last thirty years.
(2) Provision of . energy to the rapidly
growing urban areas of the developing
countries. High energy consumption den¬
sities call for highly efficient conversion and
distribution systems, and the power re¬
quired to operate these cannot usually be
supplied by renewable sources in nearby
areas. Like industrialized countries lacking in
energy reserves, these urban developing
areas are dependent on the existence of an
operational international energy system.
(3) The interaction between the tapping
of the renewable energy potential in the
developing countries' rural, areas and the
ecological and climatic systems. In relation
to yield, the exploitation of renewable
sources such as biomass, hydropower, wind
power and energy from the oceans has in
many cases a greater effect on natural
systems than the tapping of fossil fuel
resources. In order to ensure responsible
land use in many of the world's habitable
areas, studies must be made of the con¬
sequences of extensive farming, changing
hydrological conditions and the use of
"natural" renewable energy sources, as well
as their ecological and climatic effects.
There is an urgent need, therefore, for a
global ecological assessment of the world's
as yet unspoiled natural regions with a
view to controlling future damage to the
environment.
Resolute international efforts to deal with
these problem areas and the list is by no
means complete would help to bring about
a sharper awareness that the energy prob¬
lem represents a common challenge for all
the countries of the world. Such awareness
is essential for the political compromises
that will have to be made if we are to achieve
constructive action instead of being content
with simply managing ever-dwindling
resources.
H Wolfgang Sassin
Two supply scenarios, global primary energy, 1975-2030
(In Terawatt-years per year)
PRIMARY
SOURCE (1)
BASE YEAR
1975
HIGH
SCENARIO
2000 2030
LOW
SCENARIO
2000 2030
OIL 3.62 5.89 6.83 4.75 5.02
GAS 1.51 3.11 5.97 2.53 3.47
COAL 2.26 4.95 11.98 3.93 6.45
LIGHT WATER
REACTOR 0.12 1.70 3.21 1.27 1.89
FAST BREEDER
REACTOR 0.00 0.04 4.88 0.02 3.28
HYDRO ELECTRICITY 0.50 0.83 1.46 0.83 1.46
SOLAR 0.00 0.10 0.49 .0.09 0.30
OTHER 0.21 0.22 0.81 0.17 0.52
TOTAL (2) 8.21 16.84 35.65 U.59 22.39
1. Primary fuels production or primary fuels as inputs to conversion or refining processes.
2. Column totals may not add up exactly owing to rounding off of figures.
Table W. Sassin
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Wetmore - S.P.L. - Cosmos, Paris
IMPLICATIONS OF A SUSTAINABLE ENERGY SYSTEM
Does the world possess the productive and institutional
capabilities, the capital and material resources, and the discipline
to achieve a sustainable energy system? What does it mean to
mobilize building programmes on such a scale around the world
or to build the productive plants to turn out the dozens of billions
of tons of concrete and steel to build these grandiose new
plants? It would take time and material inputs especially
capital. There would also be institutional barriers of all kinds at
all levels to overcome. Above all, it would demand generally
much greater productivity worldwide, and this would mean
increased levels of interregional trading of all kinds -of labour, of
skills, of technologies, of knowledge, of energy, of products, of
food and so forth.
To give an idea of what this means in terms of capital
investment, even the energy demand projections of the IIASA
"low scenario" would require between 1975 and 2030 an increase
in the world's capital stock by a factor of approximately 20 to 30.
This is why it is so important that the eight billion or so people
living in 2030 be rich, not poor, and much richer than today. That
they be rich does not mean that they discover some new treasure
of physical resources that has previously been completely
overlooked; it means that they learn how to use the limited
resources available more efficiently, more ingeniously, more
productively. The process is continuous, and it is cumulative.
The higher our productivity that is, the more wisely we invest
our current resources of energy, labour, capital, and know-
how the closer we will come to transforming the possibility of a
sustainable energy system into a reality. To succeed would be to
cross a distinct threshold to decouple the world's energy supply
from the problem of resource supplies. It is a threshold perhaps
as great as that passed by our distant ancestors when they
launched the era of domestic farming. To cross it is the modern
challenge and it is not beyond our capabilities.
Source : Energy 1981. IIASA, Laxer
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The developing world
demands
a place in the sun by Abdou Moumouni Dioffo
THE developing countries of Africa,
Asia and Latin America are privileged
for the most part as regards renew¬
able energy resources the sun, the wind,
the heat gradient of the tropical seas and the
photosynthetic process in tropical forests.
This is an important asset and, in years to
come, it could lead to the development of a
global energy policy in which the in¬
terdependence of these countries will
guarantee their independence.
But harnessing solar energy in areas
where it is readily accessible calls for a
choice between different technological op¬
tions, and the countries concerned must ex¬
amine very carefully what the direct and in¬
direct repercussions are likely to be on im¬
portant areas of their national life such as
the economy, population distribution, land
use planning, and the choice of a model of
industrial development which, in the long
run, could change the course of their social
and cultural development.
Whether the applications of solar energy
are thermal, mechanical or electrical, the
selection of plant and equipment most likely
to promote economic, social and cultural
progress has first and foremost obvious
economic implications. According to
whether equipment is imported or produced
wholly or partly on the spot the national
economy has to face problems such as cur¬
rency shortages and economic dependence
on the exporting country or inability to meet
investment costs and uncertainty as to
the viability of the equipment under local
conditions.
The demographic implications are
generally less apparent. But where rural
solar equipment for pumping water, grind¬
ing flour and providing light and power for
domestic and community use is centraliz¬
ed, the population will tend to concentrate
round these points. And here lies a danger
for the country in question; exercising what
is supposed to be a purely technological
choice, it could very well end up as a cen¬
tralized society on the lines of the in¬
dustrialized nations, with all the accompany¬
ing social and cultural consequences.
Similarly the adoption of a technology
based on very powerful solar plants from
100 kilowatts to several megawatts is
bound to lead to concentrations of another
kind, where all the main economic and in¬
dustrial activities are grouped round places
equipped with energy-producing installa¬
tions. The type of society that will emerge is
likely to be a replica of the "consumer socie¬
ty", with moral values entirely alien to the
national culture. This represents a real threat
ABDOU MOUMOUNI DIOFFO, of Niger, is a
physicist who has been director of his country's
Office for Solar Energy (ONERSOL) since 1969.
Last year he was appointed rector of the Univer¬
sity of Niamey.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A portable solar still developed
and manufactured by the Office
of Solar Energy (ONERSOL) in
Niamey, Niger. Small solar stills
providing less than 200.000 litres
of water per day have an
important role to play in parts of
west Africa, such as the coastal
region of Mauritania and
northern districts of Mali and
Niger, where the water supply is
brackish. For larger installations,
however, there seems little
prospect at present of solar
desalinization installations
becoming competitive with
those using conventional fuels.
Photo Stambolis © Unesco. From Solar Energy for Educational Buildings, by C. Stambolis with P. Vastarais, Heliotechnic Press, London 1981
to the cultural identity of the peoples of the
developing countries.
Finally, as regards land use planning, a
whole complex of factors has to be taken in¬
to account so as to ensure the balanced
development of all sectors of the economy
(agriculture, stock-breeding, agro-food in¬
dustries and production of building
materials), as well as the wise use of natural
resources to safeguard the environment (in¬
cluding measures to limit or eliminate over-
grazing, deterioration of arable land and
destruction of the plant cover), and a ra¬
tional distribution of industry.
So, more than the type of technical pro¬
cess or even the size of plants, the model of
technological development must be taken
into account when establishing a national
strategy that will give solar energy a place
among accessible energy sources. The
stakes are enormous, since the
technological option selected can either
perpetuate the developing country's
dependence on imported science and
technology or promote the development of
a national capability. The provision of solar
plants on a turnkey basis and the so-called
"transfer of technology", as this type of
transaction is grandly termed, are a delu¬
sion. This must be clearly understood if
decisions are to be based on the country's
real development priorities and not on com¬
mercial considerations divorced from the
people's true interests.
The countries of Africa, Asia and Latin
America enjoy extremely promising natural
conditions for tapping the sun's power, but
because scientific and technological
research has lagged behind they sometimes
lack the know-how needed to develop solar
equipment. The industrialized countries, on
the other hand, are at a disadvantage with
regard to climatic conditions but possess the
industrial bases essential to such develop¬
ment. Genuine co-operation between the
two groups of countries both in scientific
and technological research and in industrial
production is therefore a prerequisite for the
efficient utilization of solar energy to benefit
millions of people in the rural areas of the
Third World.
In the developing world the level and main
trends of solar energy research vary con¬
siderably from one country to another.
Though a great deal of interest has been
generated in this field, the activity of
research institutions often stagnates,
because human and financial resources are
in short supply, and researchers work in
isolation. In such cases it is easy for foreign
firms and organizations offering technical
assistance or bilateral co-operation to effect
what amounts to a "take-over" of national
institutions. The only effective solution lies
in increased scientific and technical co¬
operation between developing countries of
the same region or even different regions.
Then, and then only, can the question of co¬
operation between developing and in¬
dustrialized nations be approached on a
sound basis taking into account the interests
of all concerned.
It was not until the "oil crisis" that large-
scale solar research programmes were
launched by a number of industrialized
countries. At present most of these pro¬
grammes have only very limited targets (the
provision of auxiliary power for domestic
and industrial heating and supplementary
electricity supplies). But their true purpose
in the long term is to develop alternative
energy sources that could be substituted for
the world's rapidly dwindling oil supplies
and, in the short term, to exploit the huge
market of the developing countries to
develop solar equipment in highly lucrative
conditions. To all intents and purposes this
would mean that research and industrial
production would be virtually financed, if
not subsidized, by the developing countries
themselves.
A radical change of approach is therefore
needed to establish genuine co-operation in
this field between the two groups of coun¬
tries. Given the present oil crisis, the. role of
solar energy in the long term and its short-
and medium-term possibilities in many
developing countries, it is in the interests
of both parties to come to grips with the
situation.
Industrial co-operation between devel¬
oped and developing countries in the pro¬
duction of solar installations also raises
many complex problems. The international
division of labour at present reduces the
developing nations to the role of mere pro¬
ducers of mineral and agricultural raw
materials, creating an uneven pattern of ex¬
change which perpetuates the economic
dependence of the Third World on the in¬
dustrialized world. The latter today virtually
monopolizes the various industries basic to
solar energy production, including the
metallurgy of iron and ferrous metals and
that of aluminium, copper and other non-
ferrous metals; glass and transparent
plastics; and heat insulation processes that
use minerals or organic substances. Yet the
raw materials used in all these processes
come mainly from the developing countries.
In most cases they are partially processed
before being exported. This is the case with
aluminium oxide from Guinea and Ghana
which is processed on the spot or in
Cameroon; copper from Zaire and Zambia;
and the petroleum products of Nigeria,
Algeria and the Middle East.
To reinforce the developing countries'
self-sufficiency, industries manufacturing
finished and semi-finished products could
be established in the raw material-producing
countries, provided such measures were
supported by industrial co-operation on a
world scale. This would be in everybody's
interests in the long run. In the present
energy crisis the under-exploited hydroelec¬
tric potential of Africa, Asia and Latin
America seems to offer an ideal source of
power for processing from start to finish the
many minerals found in these areas. r
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
y A basis would thus be provided for the
establishment of light industries producing
components for solar plants electronic
parts, precision engineering, metal and
mechanical equipment, etcand economic
development at national level would be
guaranteed by the interdependence of the
various industries.
This approach would lead to a new inter¬
national division of labour beneficial to the
entire world economy and, by bringing
about a marked lowering of production and
transport costs as well as retail prices, it
would speed the introduction of solar
energy, since under this system plants
would be constructed from start to finish in
the places where they are to be used. In rela¬
tion to the new world energy consumption
pattern the foreseeable consequences are
such that there should be no difficulty in
gaining unanimous acceptance for this set
of measures.
H Abdou Moumouni Dioffo
W*
***»
WrWmm *»** **
1«»
1
Above, photovoltaic panel in the courtyard
of a school in Niger powers the school's
educational television set. Right, the
Maine-Montparnasse skyscraper in the
heart of Paris.
16
T"
H HI!) 111!IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
World energy file
"Thunderbolt", by Roy Lichtenstein.
Photo © Sotheby Parke-Bernet, New York
by Zoran Zaric
THE 4,500 million people on the earth currently use
about 10,000,000,000,000 watts of energy. This is
equivalent to 2.2 kilowatts per head. A single bar
electric fire is usually rated at 1 kilowatt (kW).
To understand the energy problem, it is important to
distinguish between power and energy. Technically, power is
the rate at which work is done or energy used. A 1 kW elec¬
tric fire has a power rating of 1 kW; it uses energy at the rate
of 1 kilowatt-hour (kWh) per hour24 kWh per day, or
24x365 = 8,760 kWh per year. Thus the average rate of
energy use over the whole globe is 19,272 kWh per year per
head, which is the same as 2.2 kW continuous.
When talking of global energy use, figures in watts or even
kilowatts tend to get very large. Scientists use a system of
shorthand to make the numbers seem smaller:
1 kilowatt (kW) = 1,000 orlO3 watts
1 megawatt (MW)= 1,000,000 or 106 watts
1 gigawatt (GW) = 1 ,000,000,000 or 109 watts
1 terawatt (TW) = 1 ,000,000,000,000 or 1012 watts.
Total energy consumption of the whole world is now
10 terawatts (TW).
The same prefixes can be used in front of units other than
watts. Thus 1 gigatonne (GT) is 1,000,000,000 tonnes. While
electrical energy is usually expressed in terms of the watt,
some fossil fuels such as coal and oil are more conveniently
measured in tonnes. The energy contained in one tonne of
hard coal is 8,139 kWh; the energy in one tonne of oil is
11,964 kWh.
However, although the average per capita energy consump¬
tion is 2.2 kW, energy is not used uniformly throughout the
globe. Consumption in North America is about 10 kW per
head. Consumption in the other industrialized countries
varies between 2 and 7 kW. The rest of the world, comprising
three-quarters of mankind, consumes less than 2 kW, on
average about 450 watts. Nearly 400 million people live on
less than 100 watts. Energy consumption, in other words,
follows the global economic order rather closely.
The most reliable forecasts all seem to suggest that by the
year 2000 there will be 6,700 million people, consuming an
average of 3.06 kW per capita. This gives a total energy con¬
sumption of 20.5 TW, slightly more than double that of to¬
day. Fifty years later, by 2050, there will be 10,500 million
people, consuming an average of 5.28 kW. This gives a total
consumption of 55.4 TW, some five and a half times as much
as today.
The "World Energy File" on the following pages is an at-k
tempt to indicate briefly where this energy may come from, f
ZORAN ZARIC, Yugoslav specialist in thermodynamics, is a member of the
Serbian Academy of Science and Arts and president of the Yugoslav
Association for Solar Energy. He has been for many years Secretary-General
of the International Centre for Heat and Mass Transfer, which co-operates
closely with Unesco in the energy field. This article is based on the
manuscript of a book by Zoran Zarió, provisionally entitled Energy for the
Future, fo be published by Unesco in 1982.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ENERGY FILE
Fossil fuels
HE fossil fuels consist of decayed plant matter. Their energy
is contained in chemical bonds, derived originally from the
sun's energy which was fixed by plants millions of years ago
through photosynthesis. Fossil fuels consist mainly of carbon, in
combination with other elements. It is estimated that there are
something like 10'6 (10,000 million million) tonnes of fossil carbon
underneath the earth's rocks. Unfortunately, not all of it can be easi¬
ly or economically recovered. There are four main sources of fossil
fuel.
Coal is found most commonly north of the equator, and in par¬
ticular north of the 30° N latitude line. Some 88 per cent of the
known reserves are found in the Soviet Union, the USA and China.
There are also extensive deposits in central Europe.
So far the world has used up about 130 gigatonnes of coal. The
known recoverable reserves of coal amount to 600 GT (about four
times as much as has been already used). But future estimates are op¬
timistic. There may be as much as 10,000 GT of coal on the earth, of
which it is thought we can expect to recover 2,500 GT.
We are currently using about 2.6 GT of coal a year, worldwide. In
1980 global energy consumption, from all fuels, was the equivalent
of about 10 GT of coal equivalent so coal is now providing about
26 per cent of our global energy needs. Fifty years ago it provided
nearly all our energy, and it may soon have to provide much more of
our energy than it does now. Research is now being done into how to
turn coal into forms of natural gas and oil, and into how to use it
more efficiently.
Oil is undoubtedly the most useful fossil fuel, mainly because it is
so easily transportable. More than half of the proven reserves are
found in the Middle East, and the world has so far consumed about
one-third of what is known to exist and to be recoverable. In some
countries, such as the United States, as much oil has already been
consumed as is known to be left.
Currently we are using about 3 GT of oil a year. Proved reserves
amount to some 88.4 GT but as much as 300 GT may be ultimately
recoverable. At the moment we are discovering new reserves at the
rate of about 5 GT a year, which is faster than we are consuming the
product. However, it is thought that maximum oil production will
occur about 1990, and that thereafter world production (and
therefore consumption) will decrease.
Natural gas is likely to have a longer future than oil. About 40 per
cent of the known reserves are in the member States of the Organiza¬
tion of Petroleum Exporting Countries (OPEC) and 30 per cent in
the Soviet Union. In fact, the USA and the USSR together consume
70 per cent of world natural gas supply.
So far we have consumed about 40 per cent of the known reserves.
In energy terms, the proved reserves are about two-thirds those of
oil. But estimated recoverable resources are probably as large as
those of oil. As we currently use 2.5 times more oil than natural gas
(again, in energy terms), natura! gas is going to last a good deal
longer than oil. World production is expected to peak in the year
2010, by which time we will be using three times as much natural gas
a year as we are now.
Oi! shales and tar sands are the last source of fossil fuels. The
shales are found 70 per cent in North America and 25 per cent in
Latin America; the tar sands are found mostly in Canada, with other
deposits in South America, Siberia and Nigeria. Reserves are quite
extensive roughly comparable to those of natural gasbut the
problem is how to recover the fuel.
Both deposits must be heat-treated to release their fuel, and the
fuel must be upgraded to rid it of impurities. The result is an expen¬
sive fuel. For example, for each barrel of oil extracted from oil shale,
1.7 tonnes of rock must be separated and then disposed of.
It is expected that fossil fuel use will peak in the year 2010 by
which time we will be using twice as much fossil fuel as we do now.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Coal 600x109
Annual energy use
(World) 5x10*
c *?'
Oil
200x109 100x10s
Proven resources total 900 x 109
(or 900 billion) tonnes of coal equivalent
Coal is not a new or renewable source of energy but reserves of coal are huge in
absolute terms and dwarf those of oil, gas and the unconventional
hydrocarbons oil shales and tar sands. In a conventional oil field, the crude oil is
trapped between grains of sand in a stratum capped by other rock which is
impermeable. Drilling a hole through the latter produces a gusher as the weight of
strata above pushes out the fluid below. However the oil may not be fluid but
highly viscous; alternatively it may be trapped among such fine particles that it
cannot flow. The former is calied a tar sand, the latter is an oil shale, but both
terms are imprecise.
A glance at the known reserves, however, is sufficient to stimulate invention. The
amount of heavy oil in the single tar sand deposit along the Orinoco in Venezuela
may exceed that of conventional oil in the entire Middle East. Some oii-importing
developing countries have fields with one to five billion barrels. They include
Colombia, the Ivory Coast, Madagascar and Turkey. The tar sands of Canada
(mostly Alberta) have reserves of 800 billion barrels but are still dwarfed by those of
Venezuela estimated at over 2,000 billion barrels.
Oil shale reserves are even larger. The developed market economy countries
together have 2,247 billion barrels with the lion's share (2,100 billion) in the United
States. Among the developing countries which import oil but also have oil shales
are Argentina, Thailand, and Morocco with 300 million to one billion barrels each
while Brazil has 800 billion barrels. The Soviet Union and Zaire also have substantial
deposits. Current producers include China which gets nine per cent of its oil from
the shales of Manchuria and Kwangsi (45 to 70 million tonnes of shale annual '
production). The Soviet Union processes 35 million tonnes from which 12 million
tonnes of oil is extracted. '
Source: United Nations Development Forum
Oil shales Conventional oil
Heavy crude oils
or tar sands
Source : Energy in a Finite World, IIASA, Laxenburg, Austria
Bridging the gap
in training
and information
by James F. McDivitt
Why has technological progress in exploiting
renewable, non-polluting energy sources not
been followed up by their rapid and
widespread application and use? There is no
one answer to this complex problem, but
there is general recognition that many of the
obstacles are not technical in nature. Among
the major non-technical constraints which
emerge from detailed international studies
carried out by Unesco are lack of specialized
information and public information, and lack
of trained personnel for installation and
repair.
In spite of the explosion of interest in new
energy sources, a Unesco study on educa¬
tion and training in this field reveals that no
systematic approach has yet been developed
to meet the urgent need for skilled man¬
power The survey, which covered some
300 institutions in 86 countries, indicates
that while much more needs to be done to
train research scientists, engineers and
technicians in all aspects of new energy
technology, it is just as necessary to provide
courses for policy-makers who must take
decisions on energy matters.
In many cases lack of information is the
block to more effective training and to
greater public awareness of the possibilities
of alternative energy sources. Even in coun¬
tries where modern information systems are
available it is today virtually impossible to
keep up with new developments in this field
because the volume of publications is so im¬
mense and the information sources are so
scattered. This is another area in which ma¬
jor programmes must be developed and here
too Unesco is playing a leading role.
In 1980 Unesco carried out a study on the
need for and the feasibility of an interna¬
tional information system on new and
renewable energy sources. The study reveal¬
ed universal awareness "of the dangers of
unsound investments based on unreliable in¬
formation. All [users) wish to avoid the over-
enthusiasm expressed in certain circles for
some energy alternatives whose results and
performance might later prove disappoin¬
ting. All users are conscious of the fact that
their choice of an alternative energy could be
influenced by direct or indirect pressures ex¬
ercised by those in charge of the marketing
of relevant materials and processes."
Following this study, Unesco's General Con¬
ference in 1980 approved a programme for
the development of such an information net¬
work, to be based wherever possible on ex¬
isting systems and services. The programme
is now going forward and a number of pilot
projects are at the advanced planning stage.
JAMES F. MCDIVITT, Canadian geologist, is
director of Unesco's Division of Technological
Research and Higher Education.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Unifying
the fundamental
forms of energy
by Abdus Salam
Nobel Prizewinner for Physics, 1979
UNTIL about two decades ago, physicists be¬
lieved that there were four fundamental forms
of energy: the gravitational force; the electric
force (including magnetism); the strong nuclear
force, which is responsible for the powerful attrac¬
tion among protons and neutrons, the particles that
compose nuclear material; and the weak force
which plays a vital role in changing one kind of sub¬
atomic particle into another.
Now it is commonplace that all these forms of
energy can be made to interconvert the gravita¬
tional into the electric, for example (hydroelectricity
is a manifestation of this), or the strong nuclear into
electromagnetic (as when the nuclear energy in the
sun's interior converts into the electromagnetic
energy of the heat of the sun's rays).
Twenty years ago, my colleagues and I suggested
that there were indications that the weak nuclear
form of energy was basically simply identical with
the electromagnetic. This was not just a matter of
interconversion of one form of energy into another.
Our results went deeper. In our view, there should
be no basic distinction between electricity and
nuclear forces. We said that they were simply iden¬
tical. We suggested that under suitable conditions
in the laboratory this identity, normally hidden,
could be made manifest.
The first indication of the theory's correctness
came in 1973, when the European Nuclear Research
Laboratory in Geneva (CERN) found experimental
evidence of neutral currents which are an essential
part of the predictions of the theory. The clinching
evidence was provided in 1978 by the Stanford
Linear Accelerator in the United States which, in an
epic experiment, confirmed its second aspect its
heart as it were the unification of the elec¬
tromagnetic force with the weak nuclear to one part
in four thousand as predicted. An experiment at
Novosibirsk by a group led by Professor Barkov fur¬
ther confirmed this.
The next task is to test if the third form of energy
(the strong nuclear) is also part of this unity.
Together with some colleagues, we have drawn up
a theoretical formulation and suggested ex¬
periments to test the idea. These experiments have
begun in the United States of America, in Europe
and in India. If the results are positive, in about
three years we shall have demonstrated that all
nuclear force not just the weak nuclear is iden¬
tical with the electric force which binds an atom
together.
There will then remain the final goal of uniting the
gravitational force with the newly recognized
electro-nuclear force. The epitome of this will be to
find that the force which makes an apple fall or
which keeps the moon in orbit, the force of gravity,
is an aspect of the same unity of which the electric
force or the nuclear forces are part.
As announced at a meeting 'of the European Physical
Society held on 14 July, in Lisbon, the preliminary results
of an experiment carried out recently at a depth of some
2,000 metres at the Kolar gold mines in India supports
Dr. Abdus Salam's theory and seems to have shown that
three of the four fundamental forces indeed form a single
electro-nuclear force. Editor
Research into the production of energy by nuclear
fusion is carried out in the Soviet thermonuclear
"Tokamak 10" installation, above. To obtain a fusion
reaction the reacting mixture, or plasma, must be
heated to about 100 million degrees centigrade. The
problem is how to insulate the plasma from the walls
of the container. In the tokamak apparatus this is
achieved by holding the plasma in a magnetic field.
The plasma is contained in a doughnut-shaped vesse
right, around which coils are wound to create a
strong magnetic field which stabilizes the plasma,
electric current flowing through the plasma itself
heats the plasma and produces another magnetic
field that holds it away from the container wall.
When young scientists from developing countries return home to pass
on their knowledge after advanced studies abroad, they are likely to
shoulder a heavy teaching load which restricts their opportunities to do
original research. They may feel cut off from the latest developments in
their field. Almost 20 years ago, the International Centre for Theoretical
Physics, at Trieste, was created to offer such men and women a way
out of this intellectual isolation. The Centre, which is financed by Italy,
the International Atomic Energy Agency and Unesco, is a place where
they can update their knowledge, think, work, and above all enjoy the
stimulus of contact with other scientists. It was founded on the
initiative of Professor Abdus Salam who had himself known the
frustrations of isolation in the early 1950s when, after work in high
energy physics at Cambridge and Princeton, he returned home to
Pakistan to teach. He was his country's only theoretical physicist at
that time. "Isolation in my field", he wrote later, "as in most fields of
intellectual work, is death". Today Prof. Salam directs the Centre,
which each year welcomes some 1.500 physicists for visits and
seminars. Above, Prof. Paul Dirac, who won the Nobel Prize for physics
in 1933, delivers a lecture in the Centre's amphitheatre.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ENERGY FILE (CONTINUED)
Nuclear power
NUCLEAR energy is produced when mass is converted into
energy. There are two possible ways of doing this. In nu¬
clear fission, energy is produced when a nucleus is bom¬
barded by neutrons and splits into two. In nuclear fusionso far on¬
ly seen on earth as the thermonuclear explosion of a hydrogen
bombtwo light nuclei are forced together to form a heavier
nucleus which contains less energy. In the process energy is released.
Thermal reactors
The first chain reaction was produced in a squash court in Chicago in
1942. Since then more than 200 nuclear thermal reactors have been
built, with a total output of about 120,000 megawatts. This is about
6 per cent of the world's electricity production. More than one third
of these reactors are in the United States and they produce 12 per
cent of that country's electricity.
By 1985 there are expected to be 414 reactors in operation 196 in
Europe, 170 in North America, 43 in Asia, and 5 in Latin America.
Together they will produce 307,000 megawatts.
By the end of the century nuclear power production may have
risen by a factor of three. This will require about 500,000 tonnes of
nuclear fuel a year, and some 4 million tonnes of uranium will have
been used since nuclear energy began. This is roughly equal to the
total amount of known uranium reserves which are economically ex¬
ploitable. Without either breeder reactors which produce more fissile
material than they consume, or fusion reactors, nuclear energy
would then come to a dead-end.
cool or melt and vaporize their surroundings. This has been done in
the hydrogen bomb, but never in the laboratory. However, research
into nuclear fusion has been greatly increased since about 1975, and
is now running at about $1,000 million a year. It is expected that the
scientific feasibility of nuclear fusion will be established in the 1980s.
Technical feasibility may not be achieved before 1995 and full-scale
demonstration of fusion power plants may have to wait until the
decade 2005-2015.
mIÉ lai I 1 ' ' "
1Z~\ ' S T^«Í
m .J liH 1 ï Ji ï * f* 'B
ta * i * 1 ' v
a.
« i\i ! \mr
C3 i i .' i ÏM' ï
H " » ¿ -Í .i * i ffr>
LU ^^ F* 1 Tll n > i U «H
9 ' J 1 1 ^Ml tI
3 mt i r . m\ i^H :ic
il «-
*~ Bflnu ' I 1 an
S . i -F ! 1 T
o w - i i m
ji - ~^E 1 C , §^ê i
a. 1 j^H \ 1 \. Il . 1 1 I
S^M _ - m 4i 1 't .	 m m L.
m
LU 1 mui ,>, . hL_^
ofi» m mt* Si i
^ P - \w 5'i .i;:
to J^ : P	al ^^^ ¿t1 :
i A»1Cwl Ti 1H 1 1 \ v^n
m
^M1:^*^^^
o I^HM i *^
o
.c
a.
teli^^
Breeder reactors
A breeder reactor, which will double the amount of fissile material in
6 to 10 years, increases fuel usage by about 60 times. Hence, with the
breeder, the uranium available could be made to last very much
longer. Furthermore, it is technically possible to use not uranium but
thorium as the main fuel. There is much more thorium than uranium
available in the world, and this could extend the life of the fission
reactor for a very long time.
Breeder reactors are still being developed. Several are now being
experimentally operated but none is producing commercial electrici¬
ty. The first operational reactors are expected during the 1980s but
large-scale breeder reactors will not be producing electricity before
1990. Technically, breeder reactors are difficult to operate: they re¬
quire a large inventory of fissile material, normally plutonium ob¬
tained from the spent fuel of a thermal reactor running on uranium.
As this is the material used in the manufacture of nuclear weapons,
there is concern about the prospect of having to produce and store
large quantities of plutonium. By 1985 about 100 tonnes a year of
fissile plutonium will be needed. This will rise to some 500 tonnes by
the year 2000.
Breeder reactors have a much greater power density than thermal
reactors, and they have to be cooled by liquid metals such as sodium
and potassium. Liquid sodium is a highly dangerous material; it
catches fire on exposure to air and explodes in contact with water.
Fusion reactors
Fusion reactors are likely to work by fusing together deuterium and
tritium, producing an isotope of helium (an inert gas) and a great
deal of energy. Deuterium can be obtained in unlimited quantities
from sea water; tritium is obtained by irradiating lithiumwhich is
abundantwith neutrons in the fusion reactor itself. Thus there is
no fuel problem with the fusion reactor. Further, the product is
stable and not fissile, so the process is potentially cleaner than any
fission reactor could ever be.
However, to obtain a fusion reaction means heating a very high
concentration of deuterium and tritium to about 100 million degrees
and containing the fuels long enough for fusion to occur before they
There are grounds for concern about the safety of all nuclear
reactors. None is ever perfectly sealed, with the result that each
reactor adds slightly to the level of background radiation in the
atmosphere. There is a natural level of background radiation which
we have now increased by about one third as a result of such
things as nuclear fall-out from weapons tests, medical use of X-
rays and even watching television. A colour television may impart
a dose of radiation of as much as 2 millirems an hour to the
viewer. By comparison, a nuclear reactor increases the dose to the
population living nearby by only 5 millirems a yearwhich is about
2 or 3 per cent of background radiation. So concern about
radiation levels from nuclear reactors is unfounded.
However, there is always the possibility of an accident which
might release large doses of radiation into the surrounding area.
The records, however, are reassuring. In the United Kingdom
nuclear industry between 1962 and 1975 there were four deaths at
work among the staff (none directly caused by nuclear activity). In
the same period, 66 members of the staff were killed in road
accidents.
Similarly, there is now a one in 4,000 chance of being killed in a
road accident every year. The chance of a major nuclear accident
is calculated at one in 5,000 million per year. A major nuclear
accident is more than 1,000 times less likely than a major
earthquake or the failure of a large dam.
However, the problem of disposal of spent radioactive materials
has not yet been satisfactorily solved. Every 1,000 megawatt
reactor produces about 9 cubic metres of highly radioactive
material a year. It must be stored for tens of thousands of years
before it becomes harmless. Deep burial in sealed containers is the
expected solution but the associated hazards are not yet fully
resolved.
The safety problems of breeder reactors are likely to be the most
severe partly because of the greater amount of fuel that is used,
partly because the fuel is potential nuclear weapons material (and
is also the most toxic material known), and partly because the
liquid metal coolants are themselves highly dangerous. None of
these problems appears to be technically insoluble but they are
much more serious than those of the thermal reactor. Above,
Experimental Breeder Reactor II at Argonne National Laboratory's
Idaho site.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
. Photo © A. Ten Dam, Paris
Geothermal energy comes from nature's own nuclear reactor. It
arises from the radioactive decay of an isotope of potassium and
other elements which are spread about in the earth's crust.
For every kilometre down this generalized heating raises the
temperature 30 °C. In some areas geological activity accentuates
this effect and temperatures may rise by 80 °C per kilometre.
Where sandstone and other porous rocks allow groundwater to
circulate, heat is transferred to the water which may come to the
surface naturally at springs or geysers, or may be obtained by
drilling. However, since the weight of the rocks makes the crust
impermeable deeper than four kilometres, geothermal steam is
rarely hotter than 300 °C, limiting efficiency. The water and steam
are often corrosive and are difficult to use in conventional
turbines. New designs may overcome this difficulty.
When geothermal energy provides merely hot water it is used for
space heating and agriculture, or to pre-heat water in conventional
steam-generating power plants. Italy pioneered geothermal
exploitation for its electrified rail system. New Zealand, Iceland,
France and Japan apply geothermal energy to space heating. The
African Rift and Pacific Basin rim are other favoured areas.
There are great hopes for hydro-fracturing hot dry rocks which are
far more widely distributed than porous rock geothermal fields.
Water is pumped down one hole, through the fractured rock and
back up another hole. The main problem is how long before the
hot rocks cool (they take a very long time to heat up again).
Current geothermal electricity costs are competitive with nuclear
and oil-powered stations. Above, a geyser field in California. Right,
diagram shows how geothermal steam is obtained.
Source : United Nations Development Forum, 1981
hot dry rock
cgh. water
22
Drawing © p. Charpiot, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ENERGY FILE (CONTINUED)
New and renewable
sources of energy:
costs and constraints
Geothermal
energy
EACH square metre of the earth's surface
continuously radiates about 0.06 watts
not enough to be felt by a human being
but enough, over the whole earth, to lose the
planet some 2.8 x 1014 kWh every year. At this
rate the earth would cool down to the
temperature of space in only 200 million years.
The fact that the earth is already 4,500 million
years old means that energy is being supplied
from within the earth. That energy comes from
heating from the radioactive decay of certain
isotopes in rocks in the earth's crust. Thus
geothermal energy is really another form of
nuclear energy.
The heat of the earth has been exploited for
hundreds of years even by the Romans who us¬
ed geothermally heated water for bathing. To¬
day there are about 20 geothermal power plants
in operation, ranging from a few megawatts to
500 MW each. Together they produce some
1.5 GW.
Geothermal energy can only be used where it
is available fairly close to the Earth's surface.
This tends to be in regions where there are
volcanoes or frequent earthquake activity. Some
of the countries in which geothermal energy is
now being used include the USA, the USSR,
New Zealand, Japan, El Salvador, Mexico, the
Philippines, Iceland, Italy, France and
Hungary.
The last two countries use only warm water
for space heating. Most of the others use either
dry steam or very high temperature water under
pressure as an energy source for powering tur¬
bines to produce electricity. These are the easiest
forms of geothermal energy to exploit.
However, a great deal of energy is contained
within hot rocks in the crust. If cold water could
be pumped down to them, energy could be
recovered as steam or very hot pressurized
water. This technique is still being researched. If
successful, it would increase geothermal energy
sources enormously.
There is still enormous scope for geothermal
energy production, particularly in the unknown
area of heat recovery from hot rocks, and in the
use of the truly enormous reserves of
underground warm water which could be used
for space heating and the raising of crops in
greenhouses. Geothermal energy also has the ad¬
vantage of rather few environmental disadvan¬
tages. It is, however, technically a finite resource
because the energy contained in the crust
gradually disappears as it is used up. On average
one well will produce about 5 MW and has a
lifetime of 10 or 20 years.
by Boris M. Berkovsky
THE social and economic constraints that hamper wide-scale use of non-
conventional energy sources are not always clearly understood.
Renewable energy sources are highly capital-intensive, mainly because
of the cost of the equipment involved. Analysis of rough estimates of the cost of
electric power generation on the basis of renewable energy sources shows that
only big hydroelectric power stations, under favourable construction and
operating conditions, can compete with the large-capacity power stations using
coal or nuclear fuel. The unique hydroelectric generators installed at Sayano
Shushensk, Ust'-llim, Nourek (see photo page 26) and a number of other sites
were an essential factor in the doubling of electric power production in the 1970s
as compared to the 1960s, and in Syria the El Soura hydroelectric power station,
built with the assistance of the Soviet Union, provides over 70 per cent of the
electric power produced in the country.
In a certain, very limited, number of places geothermal power stations of
medium capacity may be commercially viable suppliers of electric power. Other
renewable sources of energy are less economical than thermal and nuclear
power stations linked together into a common power generation/consumption
system. This is because they are dispersed, they lack continuity and therefore
necessitate the provision of alternative back-up systems, and they involve a cer¬
tain risk factor since they all require the use of technologies and processes that
are not fully proven.
The proposed new large-scale technologies, such as those for the use of solar
energy in outer space or of the temperature gradient of the tropical seas, turn
out, when analysed in depth, to be much more costly than initial estimates sug¬
gested. Calculations show that to produce the power required to light the
homes in an average town of 10,000 inhabitants by one of these methods would
need between 10,000 and 40,000 man-hours annually as compared to 200 to 500
man-hours for a conventional power plant burning hydrocarbons.
High consumption of materials is another constraint hampering the use of
solar and other new and renewable sources of energy. For example, to ensure
the "reaping" of solar energy by special collectors at the rate of 1 Q per year (in
1975 world energy consumption was 0.25 Q) the collectors would have to cover
a surface of 130,000 square kilometres, an area roughly the size of Greece or
Czechoslovakia.
This would involve enormous amounts of material. The manufacture of the
simplest solar energy collector (they are made of blackened sheet metal, usually
aluminium, with tubing inside for the circulation of liquid) requires 10 kilograms
of aluminium per square metre. Thus 10,000 tons of aluminium would be re¬
quired per square kilometre. It would also involve taking out of normal use vast
areas of land.
The alienation of considerable areas of land and sea surface is also a prere¬
quisite for large-scale energy production through direct conversion of solar
energy and the use of the thermal energy of the oceans. Scientists have
calculated, for example, that to produce energy to the value of 1 Q per year us¬
ing the thermal energy of the seas and oceans, the devices needed to capture
and transform this energy would cover practically all the tropical and sub¬
tropical seas, to the detriment of maritime operations and fisheries. In addition,
the one degree centigrade drop in the surface temperature of the tropical seas
that this exploitation might entail could cause a drop in the mean annual
temperature in the tropics and greatly influence the climate on a global scale.
The main constraints impeding development of new and renewable sources
of energy are thus: high initial costs, high consumption of materials, the aliena¬
tion of large land and sea surfaces, lack of sufficient trained personnel, absence
of a specialized information infrastructure, and legal and administrative dif¬
ficulties. The status of non-conventional energy sources is rarely defined in
legislative documents with sufficient clarity and precision and as a result con¬
flicts of interest arise which may take a very long time to resolve.
All the constraints enumerated above are inherent in the development of non-
conventional energy sources and constitute a major obstacle to their large-scale
introduction. The problem calls for an integrated approach at the governmental
level, the elaboration and implementation of long-term plans and programmes
and extensive international co-operation in the promotion of which Unesco will
play an essential role.
BORIS M. BERKOVSKY, a Soviet scientist specializing in the field of thermophysics, is head of
the laboratory for computer methods in thermophysics and energy at the Institute of High
Temperature of the USSR Academy of Sciences in Moscow. From 1973 to 1979 he was a Unesco
staff member responsible for Unesco 's programmes on scientific and technical problems of energy.
He is the author of more than one hundred publications.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ENERGY FILE (CONTINUED)
Tide
ABOUT 3 terawatts of power are locked up in the world's
tides. Only in a few places of the world, however, is it
economic to recover the energy; those are places
where the tidal range is very high as in some parts of the English
Channel, the Irish Sea, and along the North American and
Australian coasts and on some parts of the White Sea and the
Barents Sea. There are in fact some 24 potential tidal power sites in
the world, so this can hardly be described as a global resource.
For technical reasons, tidal power plants only operate at 25 per
cent of their rated capacity so maximum global potential is only
20 GW out of the total possible of 80 GW. Only one large tidal
power station has been built at La Ranee, in France, where capaci¬
ty is 240 MW and about 60 MW is produced, fairly economically.
Studies are in hand for another huge site in France of 12,000 MW
and for a 3,800 MW site on the coast of North America at the Bay of
Fundy.
Wave
Another 3 terawatts of power are stored in ocean waves. The average
wave in the North Sea contains an energy of 40 kW for each metre of
its length for 30 per cent of the time and about 10 kW per metre for
70 per cent of the time. Estimates vary widely as to how much wave
power could be extracted. One estimate puts it at 100 GW global.
Another suggests 120 GW for the UK alone. For the moment,
however, the matter is academic as there are no wave power plants
operating. Several experimental prototypes have been built and are
being tested. The UK and Japan are in the forefront of this type of
research.
Photo © JAMSTEC/lnternational Energy Agency
Invented by Japanese engineer Yoshio Masuda, navigation
marker buoys powered by wave energy have been in use in
Japan since 1965. The motion of the waves is used alternately to
suck and pump air through a low-pressure air turbine which
drives an electric generator. The small electric current thus
produced is sufficient to power the lamps of the marker buoy.
An attempt is being made to use the same principle to generate
power on a larger scale using an experimental sea-going ship-like
buoy, the Kaimei (above) designed by the Japan Marine Science
and Technology Centre. Cockered rafts (below) operate on a
different principle. Named for their inventor Sir Christopher
Cockerell (best known as the inventor of the hovercraft),
Cockerell rafts are articulated platforms which convert into
energy the undulatory motion of waves. The models under test
as shown in our photo are one-hundredth of the size that would
be needed for Atlantic conditions.
Photo ©,United Kingdom Atomic Energy Authority
Wind
The winds blowing over the earth contain some 2,700 terawatts, and
windmills have been used for thousands of years to capture a tiny
fraction of this energy. There is now renewed interest in wind energy
but there are two main problems. The first is that the wind blows ir¬
regularly and so the energy captured must be stored in some way,
which greatly increases its cost. Secondly, the energy in the wind is
very dilute. It actually requires a five times greater land area to cap¬
ture wind energy than it does to capture the equivalent amount of
solar energy with solar collectorsalthough admittedly most of the
land on which windmills were erected could also be used for
agriculture.
Wind energy is useful on a small scale for local needs but to make
a significant contribution machines of between 100 kW and several
MW will have to be developed. Several are now being tested, the
largest being in North Carolina.
Of the 2,700 TW of power in the winds, only a quarter is available
in the first 100 metres above the surface. Taking into account only
the land areas and inevitable inefficiencies, a maximum of 40 TW
would be available if wind machines were built all over all the con¬
tinents. However, even ten per cent of this is 4 TW which is greater
than the hydropower potential.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
iUJÉJM
Above, the tidal power station at La Ranee,
France. Right, a new wind turbine generator on
Block Island, State of Rhode Island, U.S.A. Its
blades measure some 38 metres from tip to tip
and in a 30-kilometre-an-hour wind it can
generate the electricity used in 50 average
American homes. Below, a wind-operated
water pump in the Gezirah district of Sudan.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
\ . ^S^Jfe'íi/W?
>rt
Photo P. Malinovsky © APN, Moscow
Hydroelectric power is generated by
water flowing through turbines. The
quantity of electricity generated varies
according to the mass and speed of the
water passing over the turbines.
Capital costs are high but operating and
maintenance costs are lower, and the
production of hydroelectric power
plants, which may have a lifetime of up
to 100 years, can be regarded as
inflation-proof. In recent years there
has been heavy emphasis on economies
of scale. The world has 2.2 million
megawatts potential power of which
only 18 per cent has been exploited.
Norway, Canada, Sweden, Brazil and
Sri Lanka get over three-quarters of
their total power from hydro.
Environmental and social problems with
some of the larger schemes have dulled
hydro's bright image. Good agricultural
land is often flooded, farmers are
displaced, disease may spread and
climate may be changed. Interest has
recently revived in small-scale hydro for
developing countries. Projects can be
implemented in places without an
electricity grid and electricity demand
structure. They can form a focal point
for industrialization in rural areas. The
manufacturer can involve local
materials and skills and encourage the
population to stay. China has already
built over 90,000 small hydro stations,
and even in rich countries like France
and Sweden, exploitation of thousands
of sites is under way. Combined units
in developing countries can provide
mechanical output for milling during
the day and electric power for lighting
and cooking by night. Technological
advance and standardization is
expected to bring down present costs
by 20 to 30 per cent. Above, the
hydroelectric power plant at Ust'-llim,
in eastern Siberia. Right, a small
hydroelectric power station in Yongan
county, east China. Below, the Kariba
Dam across the Zambezi River on the
border between Zambia and Zimbabwe
which provides 8 million kilowatt-hours
of electricity annually.
Source : United Nations Development Forum, 1981
Photo Paolo Koch (S\ RaDho Pa
:*?>
.¿U**
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ENERGY FILE (CONTINUED)
Hydropower
HERE are a million million million (1018) tonnes of water on
the earth. Only 1 /2000th part of this, however takes part in
the annual water cycle, being evaporated and then precipitat¬
ed again as rain or snow. Even this tiny part is equivalent to
500,000 cubic kilometres (km') of water. In fact every year,
430,000 km' are evaporated from the oceans and 70,000 km' from
the continents. When this water is precipitated 390,000 km' falls on
the sea, and 110,000 km' on land. So every year 40,000 km' of water
runs off from the land and into the sea. As the average height of the
continents is 800 metres, it is easy to work out that the total potential
hydropower of the globe is 10 TW (roughly total global energy con¬
sumption).
However, only a fractionperhaps 15 per centof this can be
economically recovered. This leaves a total potential of 1.5 TW. In
1975 total annual hydropower production was about 11 per cent of
this. Thus there is still some way to goparticularly in countries in
Africa and Asia where the potential is largest but the least used.
Fifty years ago some 40 per cent of world electricity came from
hydropower. Today that figure has dropped to 23 per centbut that
is still much higher than the fraction supplied by nuclear power. In
some countries in Latin America as much as 80 per cent of electricity
demand is satisfied via hydropower.
Today there are more than 70 plants in operation of more than
1,000 MW. Some have a capacity of 10,000 MW. And there are
millions of a few kilowatts. Hydropower is useful in that it runs off a
renewable resource, is extremely efficient as it produces electricity
direct from a form of mechanical energy not heat, and can be pro¬
duced in plants of almost any size.
Ocean
thermal energy
Between 5 and 8 terawatts of power are locked up in ocean currents.
Attempts to recover some of this with ocean current turbines still
look somewhat futuristic. However, the temperature difference bet¬
ween cold water a few hundred metres down and warm water near
the ocean surface does offer an enormous potential energy source,
estimated at 20,000 to 40,000 TW, of which some 4 TW might be
recoverable in practice. The system of using this energy, which
depends on operating a turbine from the small temperature dif¬
ferences which exist, is very inefficient. Nevertheless small power
plants called OTECs (Ocean Thermal Energy Conversion) are now
being tested and a 100 MW prototype is being planned for some time
after 1985. OTEC power plants would either transmit their power to
shore or use it at sea to recover minerals and other resources.
The oceans of the world absorb nearly 70 per cent of the
solar energy that reaches the earth. Ocean Thermal
Energy Conversion (OTEC) is a way of tapping this huge
energy store by exploiting the temperature difference
between the sun-warmed surface water and the cold
waters of the ocean depths to drive turbine generators
which produce electricity. Two types of OTEC
systems the "closed cycle" and the "open cycle"
systems are now being experimented with. Diagram
below illustrates the working of a "closed cycle" OTEC.
Ammonia, which has a low boiling point, is pumped
round a closed circuit. First ¡t is heated by the warm
ocean water (top of diagram) so that it turns into vapour.
The vapour passes through a turbine where it expands,
driving a generator. Emerging cooler and at a lower
pressure it flows to a cold-water heat exchanger where it
cools further to become liquid again and the cycle
recommences. In an "open cycle" OTEC. seawater is used
as the operating fluid, its boiling point being reduced by
passing it through a vacuum chamber maintained at 3.5
per cent of normal atmospheric pressure. Above, artist's
impression of a floating "open cycle" ocean thermal
power station now under study by the French Centre
National pour l'Exploitation des Océans (CNEXO).
Liquid ammonia
(T
^ (~
~
Warm
seawater
29 %
G
cu
LU
Gaseous ammonia
Turbine
Cold
seawater
4°C
P
Pump
Liquid ammonia
Drawing © R.A. Meyer, OTEC, Chicago
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Diagram from United Nations Development Forum, 1981
Discussion of solar energy tends to
concentrate primarily on questions of
technology and cost, but, if solar energy is
to be widely and successfully introduced, a
determined effort will have to be made to
educate the public to understand and
accept this new energy source. Below, at a
school at Tiverton, in England, which has
solar installations for space-heating and
domestic hot water as well as heat
recovery units and rainwater recycling
powered by a wind pump, the services are
exposed internally and colour-coded so
that the workings of the system can be
traced around the school. The children
monitor the system to see how much
energy is being used. Above, diagram
shows the working of a simple,
photovoltaic water pump. Above right, a
Mexican research worker checks solar
photovoltaic panels designed for use in
rural communities. Right, a thermal solar
power station in Senegal.
gpü§g
#
^Hfe«<tot? *Ktattteita /^M* ,
»-il \
Everybody takes the sun for
granted. Constantly and without
fail, it rises in the morning and sets
in the evening. Considering
mankind's residence on earth, the
sun is an object that will last for
ever, radiating the energy that
makes life possible on earth.
The sun is a peculiar hydrodynamic
object, 1,390,000 kilometres in
diameter, which was formed from a
cloud of gas composed mainly of
hydrogen. Its core is extremely hot
with temperatures high enough to
allow the fusion of hydrogen to
helium. This fusion at the solar core
releases energy in the form of high-
frequency electro-magnetic
radiation, which is transferred
slowly out to the surface through a
succession of radiative processes.
The radiation that finally reaches
the earth comes from a narrow
surface region, rather opaque to
visible light, called the
photosphere. The energy output of
Source: Solar Energy for Educational Buildings, by C
London, 1981, a Unesco/UNICEF sponsored study
the sun requires the burning or
conversion of mass into energy at
the rate of 4.2 x 106 tons per second.
Considering that the total mass of
the sun is 22 x 1026 tons, one can
easily calculate that the sun will
continue radiating energy for
another 2,000,000 million years!
Electromagnetic radiation emitted
by the sun's photosphere region
travels through space at the speed
of light (300,000 kilometres per
second) in the form of diverging
rays. The earth, which is at a
distance of 150 million kilometres,
intercepts approximately only two-
billionths of the sun's radiant
output. The amount of solar energy
reaching the earth's surface in any
one year is over fifty times greater
than the present estimates for all
the energy available from the
proven fossil fuel reserves, and
35,000 times greater than present
annual world energy consumption.
Stambolis with Peter Vastardis, Heliotechnic Press,
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
WORLD ENERGY FILE (CONTINUED)
Solar energy Solar power
for the Sahel:
A Unesco feasibility study
y I" 1 HE average amount of solar energy hitting the earth's
I atmosphere is enormousabout 1.353 kilowatts per square
JL metre, or 178,000 terawatts. The amount reaching the
earth's surface is much less; and the fraction of that which could be
recovered less still. The global potential, then, is best counted as the
solar energy falling on land which is neither occupied nor farmed.
The yearly average value for that is some 10,000 TW roughly 1,000
times current global energy consumption.
The maximum value which solar insolation reaches is about 1 kW
per square metreand that only for an hour or two at mid-day dur¬
ing high summer. In most areas of the world the average insolation is
of the order of 200 W per square metre. Africa and Asia appear to
be the best continents for the collection of solar energy.
Although very diffuse, solar energy is highly useful in that it can
be used cheaply for a variety of jobs. Domestic hot water heating is
the best known, and in Israel one family in five has a solar collector
on its roof. Solar energy can also be used for crop drying, air condi¬
tioning, space heating, water pumping, desalination and the genera¬
tion of both very high temperatures and electricity. The highest
temperature so far achieved is about 4,000° on the Kelvin
temperature scale in a solar furnace in the Pyrenees, where mirrors
reflect solar energy over a large area onto a furnace.
The generation of electricity from sunlight appears the most pro¬
mising line of attack. One method is to arrange for mirrors to reflect
solar energy onto a boiler in which steam is raised to drive a turbine.
Many small-scale attempts are now being made to produce solar
farms which will provide electrical power in this way in the kilowatt
range. In addition, there are now a dozen or so attempts to provide
large-scale solar energy power stations in the megawatt range, using
a basically similar technique. A 10 MW solar power station would
need some 2,000 reflectors, each of 25 m2 surface area.
The alternative is to use photovoltaic cells which convert solar
energy directly into electricity, typically with an efficiency of some
10-15 per cent. Small power units in the range 250-1,000 kW have
already been set up, but are expensive due to the high cost of the
cells, which can be as much as $10 per watt installed. With mass pro¬
duction and more research, however, it is hoped to reduce this cost
to below $0.5 per watt, at which point the electrification of isolated
villages with photovoltaic units would become feasible.
Passage of radiation through the atmosphere
Total radiation arriving (solar constant) - 100%
Top' of the
atmosphere
a ' " c d
!
e
5%\ 20 %\ 25% 23% 27%
À
V
Ground \ At"\
a = reflected from the ground 5%
b « reflected from the clouds 20%
c absorbed in the atmosphere 25%
d diffuse, on the ground 23%
e direct, on the ground 27%
Total on the ground 50%
Adramatic reduction in the cost of photovoltaic cells (solar cells
which convert sunlight directly into electricity) by 1985,
comparable to that which occurred in the price of transistors
during the 1960s, is forecast in a Feasibility Study carried out recently
by Unesco for the Regional Solar Centre to be established in
Bamako, Mali.
The decision to set up the Regional Centre was taken in October
1978 at a meeting of the Heads of State of the six countries that make
up the West African Economic Community (CEAO) Ivory Coast,
Mali, Mauritania, Niger, Senegal and Upper Volta. It illustrates the
determination of the countries of the Sahel to solve their energy
problems and move towards greater technological independence.
The purpose of the Unesco Study was to provide guidelines for the
organization, financing and work plan of the Regional Centre which
was conceived of as a large pilot unit for solar training and research
and the production of solar equipment. The Study includes an in-
depth analysis of the energy situation and needs of the six CEAO
countries covering conventional as well as new and renewable
sources of energy. Particular consideration was given to solar and
wind energy.
Of all the renewable energies hydroelectricity is the cheapest, and,
wherever consumption is high and the distances involved justify the
installation of transformers and power lines, this solution is to be
preferred to local energy production.
Where energy consumption is low and distances are too great to
justify the cost of installing power lines, local solar or wind installa¬
tions offer the best solution. The Unesco Study shows that small
diesel-operated power stations of up to 100 kW are more costly to run
than solar or wind installations.
Calculations made for the Unesco Study on the basis of costs as at
May 1979 show that, for pumping water for irrigation in arid areas, for
up to 30 kW of installed capacity, solar pumps are cheaper per cubic
metre of water pumped than diesel-operated pumps. Since then the
cost of oil has almost doubled whilst the cost of photovoltaic cells
has dropped rapidly and the solar pump solution is now probably
cheaper per cubic metre of water pumped for up to as much as 50 kW
of installed capacity. Under average conditions an installation of this
size could handle the irrigation needs of between 50 and 100 hectares
of land.
But energy cost is not the only criterion of choice. Other factors
have to be taken into account such as the reliability and life of the
equipment selected, the qualified personnel needed to produce,
operate and maintain it, the ease with which it is possible to increase
or decrease operating capacity, the possibility of producing all or part
of the equipment in the user country. On all these counts photo¬
voltaic solar installations have a clear advantage over alternative
systems such as diesel, solar thermodynamic or wind installations.
Photovoltaic solar installations require virtually no maintenance,
spare parts or supervision by qualified personnel. They work unat¬
tended and need only a simple monthly check. Their capacity can
easily be enlarged by the addition of further cell panels. Furthermore,
they can already be partially produced in developing countries using
imported solar cells and it is anticipated that in the near future even
these will be produced in the user countries.
A big effort is now being made in a number of industrialized coun¬
tries to perfect new and simpler techniques for the production of
photovoltaic cells. It is forecast that the price of a solar cell module
. will drop from 13 dollars (the price in February 1970) to about 50 cents
by 1985 and to 15 cents in 1988. A drop in price of this scale will make
photovoltaic solar energy an even more attractive proposition for
developing countries.
Although the Unesco Feasibility Study was based on the situation
in the six countries of the West African Economic Community, its
general conclusions are valid for all developing countries in the world
sun belt. It is hoped that the basic technical orientations and
priorities proposed in the Unesco Study will be adopted and that
wide application of its findings will represent a considerable step for¬
ward towards the achievement of a viable new energy strategy.
Source : Koenigsberger er ai, Manual of Tropical Housing and Building,
Pan I, Climatic Design, 1973, Longman 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Photo (c) Randa BishoD
Energy alternatives
and
development strategies
EVER since the world woke up to the harsh
realities of the energy crisis discussion has
tended to concentrate on the technical and
financial constraints that will have to be over¬
come if a solution is to be found. But the in¬
troduction of new energy sources involves much
more than technology and finance and many
non-technical obstacles stand in the way of a
smooth transition to a viable new energy mix.
It was to examine these problems that twenty-
five specialists from around the world attended
an International Workshop on Non-Technical
Obstacles to the Use of New Energies in
Developing Countries, sponsored by Unesco and
nine organizations working in the energy field
and held at the Rockefeller Foundation Study
and Conference Centre, at Bellagio, Lake Como,
Italy, from 25 to 29 May 1981.
One of the major topics discussed by the par¬
ticipants was the problem of the social and
cultural impact of the introduction of new
sources of energy in developing countries and
the lead time needed to prepare the necessary
social and institutional changes and to make
them acceptable to the societies involved.
In their concluding statement the specialists
noted that the impact of change in the energy
mix on all societies and cultures involving the in¬
troduction of new energy sources was not fully
understood. In less developed countries many
social and cultural constraints were intimately
linked to the problems of poverty. The delicate
balance of survival strategies made risk-taking
on new technologies difficult, a factor which
needed greater emphasis in planning and im¬
plementation procedures. Special care would
have to be taken in development programmes
(afforestation, stove design, alternative cooking
fuels such as biogas) to avoid misunderstan¬
dings and possible negative rather than positive
impact.
It was important to distinguish between the
different groups within a society so that
technologies and institutional arrangements
couid be selected and adapted to the needs of
the people who would use them (men, women,
urban, rural, poor, landlords). The institutional
framework for the application of new sources of
energy in developing countries often tended to
favour the urban and commercial sector,
whereas the major needs might well be in the
rural and traditional sector. Institutional support
for new and renewable sources on a small-scale,
decentralized basis might require special atten¬
tion since it did not fit most existing patterns.
Cultural attitudes which favoured energy-
intensive approaches (e.g. large automobiles or
climate-controlled architecture) also impeded
the adoption of new technologies. Alternative
life styles which were less energy consuming
were needed both in developed and developing
countries.
Cultural and social values should not,
however, be viewed only as constraints; they
should also be built upon in the search for alter¬
native development patterns that offered the
possibility of breaking away from exclusive
reliance on the dominant commercial fuels of to¬
day.
Receiving Antenna'
i9.S>9.6kmi
Sokn
wave Antenna
Control
Smui
Waste Heat
Radiator
Rotary Jome Cootovg Equipment
Flights of fancy
The first solar-powered flight across
the English Channel was made on
7 July by the Solar Challenger,
above, a lightweight plastic aircraft
piloted by Stephen Ptacek (whose
name means "little bird" in Czech!).
The 290-kilometre flight took
5 1/2 hours. The craft, designed and
built in California, has over 16,000
solar cells which capture the sun's
rays and convert them into electric
power to operate a motor which
turns the propeller.
Drawing, left, shows the audacious
design concept for a solar satellite
power station, which would orbit at
a height of 36,000 km in space
where solar energy is available
virtually 24 hours a day. The solar
collector would convert solar
into electricity and feed it to
a microwave antenna. The antenna
would direct a microwave beam to
a vast receiving antenna on earth
where the microwave energy would
be converted back to electricity.
Below, newspapers hot from the
solar press were produced during
an experiment in the Tuileries
Gardens, Paris, as far back as 1882.
30
Photo © Musée des Techniques CNAM, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
\	
LEAF [C02+2H20
PHOTONS
I
0,
ICOH
.JL
1+0,1
t
H20
H-
(COH2)n
t
CO,
(COH2)+H20 .
_»C02+2H2
GAÏÏ""
y-
THE HYDROGEN TREE
WORLD ENERGY FILE (CONTINUED)
Solar fuels
SOLAR energy is used by plants via the mechanism of photosyn¬
thesis dioxide in the air and sunlight are in this way
made to produce carbohydrates. All fossil fuels coal, oil,
natural gas and lignitesas well as timber, farm crops and even
animal dung are therefore best regarded as solar fuels. More than 95
per cent of our current energy consumption comes from solar fuels.
About 90 per cent of the energy stored in plants on the earth's sur¬
face is in the form of trees. The total energy stored is about
635 terawatt-years, which is roughly the same as the amount of
energy stored in our coal reserves. Unlike coal, however, this energy
is renewed annually at a high rate. The earth's biomass yield on land
is calculated to be some 28.65 TW three times current global
energy consumption of which half . is produced by forests.
Microscopic plants in the oceans also fix solar energy, producing
about 14.35 TW. These are rather conservative figures, and assume
an efficiency of photosynthesis of 0.2 per cent on land and 0.02 per
cent in the oceans. In fact, photosynthesis tends to be more efficient
than this.
The best known use of solar fuels is burning wood for cooking and
heating. Globally, about 1-2 TW are provided in this way, primarily
in Africa and Asia where in some areas timber provides 80 per cent
of energy requirements. But a consequence of this is that forests are
being used more quickly than they grow.
The burning of dried dung fuel is also common, but removes im¬
portant fertilizer from the land. A more efficient use of dung is to
ferment it anaerobically in a digester to produce methane gas. Small
digesters are now common in India and China, even though they are
rather expensive to build. The dung from one cow should in theory
provide enough methane gas to cook for one person.
A similar technique is to ferment biomass to produce alcohol
which is a good liquid fuel. Brazil leads in this technology and aims
eventually to substitute all petroleum with alcohol fermented from
sugar cane and other specially grown crops. Even under good condi¬
tions, however, 1 km2 of sugar cane is needed to provide sufficient
fuel for 100 cars. Although many other countries are now in¬
vestigating the possibilities of substituting petrol with alcoholeven
industrialized countries there will inevitably be competition for
land with food producing activities.
H Zoran Zaric
A radical new approach to solar energy may come from
biotechnology a broad class of systems that have at their
core photosynthetic and biological energy conversion
processes.
Plants have long "known" how to use the energy of sunlight
to split water, but they do not evolve hydrogen explicitly,
since it is needed only for internal energetic processes within
the plant itself as a means for reducing carbon dioxide.
However, it may be possible to develop new biological
structures that in fact evolve hydrogen. At IIASA, Cesare
Marchetti considered the concept of hydrogen-producing trees.
The concept is essentially one of replacing expensive solar
collectors and solar cells with tree leaves. Swollen plant
tissues, so-called gaits, .located at the tree trunk would be
genetically programmed to use the solar energy captured in
the leaves for generating hydrogen gas as a by-product of
photosynthesis. The hydrogen gas would be collected within
the galls and piped to a central storage system. The essential
features of such a system already exist in nature. Many
insects and bacteria induce the formation of galls in different
types of plants. These various kinds of galls, which number in
the tens of thousands, then provide the shelter or nutrients
needed by the organism that caused them. In at least one
case, that of Rhizobium bacteria in symbiosis with
leguminous plants, substantial hydrogen is produced in the
galls, though currently it simply escapes to the atmosphere. It
has been estimated that in this way U.S. soybean plantations
leak about 30 billion m3 of hydrogen annually. Adapting this
potential so that the plants can be easily integrated with
some sort of collection system will depend on advances in the
techniques of genetic engineering. Left, graphic presentation
of the proposed hydrogen tree with a very schematic
chemistry. The gall actuates a reverse of photosynthesis and
makes hydrogen (or methane) available in an enclosed cavity
that can be tapped by a collector pipe.
More than one-third of the world's population depends on
wood for cooking and heating. Eighty-six per cent of all the
wood consumed annually in the developing countries is used
for fuel, and of this total at least half is used for cooking.
Nearly everywhere, reliance on charcoal as a source of fuel is
increasing. In Tanzania, for example, the charcoal share of
the wood fuel burned, which was 3 per cent in 1970, is
expected to rise to 25 per cent by the year 2000. In principle
this is discouraging, because in preparing the charcoal more
than half the wood's energy is wastefully burned away. But
charcoal makes wood energy easier and cheaper to
transport, and the growing reliance on it is a result of the
increasing distance from harvest site to the user. Also,
charcoal is preferred because of its steady and concentrated
heat, its smokeless burning, and because it can easily be
extinguished when the fire is no longer needed. Charcoal can
also substitute for fossil fuels, which in some places is an
urgent need. Regardless of overall inefficiency, it seems clear
that more meals will be cooked over charcoal in the future.
Above, charcoal manufacturing ovens in Argentina.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
I
Photo Jonathan Blair c Woodfin Camp, New York
The most popular but not necessarily the most economic biomass
conversion process is undoubtedly the production of ethyl alcohol
(ethanol C2H5OH) from sugar-cane and maize. The world's leading
producer is Brazil, above, producing 3.2 billion litres of alcohol
from sugar-cane, sorghum and cassava. The alcohol can be
blended with petrol to a proportion of up to 20 per cent alcohol
and run in a conventional car engine without adjustment.
However, in case of need, cars can run on pure alcohol after
adjustments.
The cost of alcohol in Brazil is higher than most gasoline sold in
Europe in 1980. Nevertheless, the indirect benefits are judged very
beneficial to Brazil. They include the saving of foreign exchange,
the creation of new employment, the encouragement of domestic
technology and industry.
The United States is also deeply involved in the promotion of
ethanol production and has set a target of approximately
3,477 million litres a year of alcohol for fuel use by 1982. Most of
the distilleries use corn as feedstock. Other countries known to be
interested in bioconversion to ethanol include Australia (cassava)
and New Zealand (beet).
Some economists feel deep disquiet at the use of food grains to
produce motor spirit. They feel that It will lead to the rich getting
transport and the poor getting starvation with land currently used
for food production being used for fuel. Several situations can be
envisaged in which production is economic. The developing
countries with a surplus agricultural production but an energy
deficit, such as Brazil, Sudan, and Thailand, are likely to have the
strongest incentives to develop large biomass energy programmes
in order to reduce their dependence on imported energy. Most of
the countries with viable alcohol programmes are likely to belong
to this group. Many of the large developing countries, such as
Bangladesh and Pakistan, however, are net importers of both
agricultural products and energy. In most of these countries
ethanol production is likely to be attractive only if based on
surplus low-cost biomass materials such as molasses and
agricultural crop residues (or sugar-cane during periods of world
sugar surpluses). In countries with surplus energy, such as Mexico,
Nigeria, and Venezuela, there is little incentive to launch major
biomass energy programmes.
Sources : United Nations Development Forum, 1981 , and Finance and Development, 1980
Brazil's green gasoline by Benedicto Silva
TODAY, in a world threatened by the
exhaustion of oil as an energy source,
Brazil is well placed to become the
first country to enter the post-petroleum era
without abandoning its network of
highways or cutting back on the manufac¬
ture and use of motor vehicles. The Brazilian
way of facing, the energy crisis is to
transform vegetable matter into ethyl
alcohol, or ethanol, in such quantities that
as of this year the country has the capacity
to supply at least 20 per cent of its
automotive fuel needs in this way. It is ex¬
pected that ethanol production will continue
to mount until Brazil achieves self-
sufficiency as a non-stop producer of
renewable energy.
It has been shown both theoretically and
experimentally that alcohol can compete on
equal terms with gasoline (petrol) as a fuel,
although it has a lower heating value. An
engine specially designed to run on alcohol
can be regulated in such a way that ethanol
has a slight edge on petrol in terms of
kilometres per litre. Ethanol also has the
outstanding advantage of reducing pollutant
emissions by half.
32 '
The raw materials Brazil needs for large-
scale ethanol production are sugar-cane,
manioc and other plant products. Sugar¬
cane is more productive than manioc in the
sense that it is a better agent for photosyn¬
thesis; in other words it produces more
energy per hectare under cultivation.
However, it is a seasonal crop and its pro¬
duction cycle is less than six months a year.
The advantage of manioc is that it enables
the distilleries to run continuously. In other
words it is useful to rely on both plants to
guarantee an uninterrupted flow of
automotive fuel.
It has been calculated that by using
scarcely two per cent of its cultivable land
Brazil could achieve the enviable position of
being the first country in the world to be
self-sufficient in indefinitely renewable fuel.
Moreover, the efforts needed to carry out
such a programme would probably be big
enough to absorb all the available man¬
power in Brazil. Besides, planting,
cultivating, harvesting, transporting, milling
and fermenting sugar-cane and manioc pro¬
vide jobs which require little more than basic
training. Preparing the necessary work-force
does not require long and costly training
programmes.
As far as transportation costs are involved
(the creation and operation of an ethanol
distribution network) they will be lower than
for petrol since the new fuel can be produc¬
ed in virtually all the States of Brazil.
Finally, it is hoped that the alcohol pro¬
gramme will generate between 250,000 and
a million new jobs in the next few years,
especially in the agricultural sector. The
creation of new employment opportunities
in rural areas will in its turn help to brake the
urban migration which is one of the major
problems facing Brazil's cities.
BENEDICTO SILVA, of Brazil, is director of the
Documentation Institute of the Fundación Getu/io
Vargas and editor in charge of the Portuguese
language edition of the Unesco Courier.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Biogas :
the Indian
experience
Technical feasibility alone
is no guarantee of success
by Tushar K. Moulik
FACING the inflationary consequences
of a rapidly mounting import bill for
oil, the Indian Government some
years ago launched an all-out compaign to
promote the use of biogas produced by
"gobar" gas plants. Various incentives such
as subsidies and low interest credit facilities
were offered to householders willing to in¬
vest in the family-size units, which produce
two to three cubic metres of gas per day.
Nevertheless, the results of the campaign
fell far below the Government's targets,
with not more than five to six thousand
plants being installed annually. What is
more, as many as 50 to 70 per cent of India's
reported 70,000 gobar gas plants today are
thought to be inoperative.
What are the reasons for this lack of per¬
formance? After all, the technology of the
gobar gas plant as promoted in India is said
to be simple enough to allow the units to be
constructed and handled efficiently by
village craftsmen.
However, an evaluation of India's gobar
gas programme clearly reveals that it is sub¬
ject to four major constraints related to:
1) the prevailing social and economic struc¬
ture; 2) cultural practices and values; 3) in¬
formation about and knowledge of the
technicalities of the process of anaerobic
digestion; and 4) the availability of skilled
manpower.
The small, family-size biogas plants pro¬
moted in India require three or four cattle to
provide the necessary input of dung. A plant
of a size requiring less than this number of
cattle for dung-input is economically not
profitable. In addition to this technological
requirement, the cost of each plant, around
5,000 rupees, is prohibitive.
The Indian families which fulfill these
financial and cattle ownership requirements
cannot account for more than 10 to 15
per cent of the rural population. The
technological requirements thus exclude a
significantly large proportion of India's
population, comprising small and marginal
farmers and landless labourers, from using
family-size biogas plants.
Closely related to this basic question are
the two important constraints of space and
water. A three-cubic-metre family-size plant
would require about 27 square metres of
land area for the plant and the compost pit.
It is also advisable to build the plant within a
six-metre radius of the kitchen in order to
provide an efficient supply of gas for cook¬
ing. But in many villages in India dwellings
are clustered so closely together in a net¬
work of narrow lanes and alleys that it is
often rare to find a villager who owns and
can spare the minimum required land area
near his homestead for the biogas plant.
Scarcity of water is an equally serious
resource constraint in many villages. To
enable a biogas plant to operate smoothly,
cow-dung and water are mixed in the ratio
of 4:5 by volume and the resulting slurry is \
fed into the digester. Where water is scarce I
Movable cover
Photo top of page, an Indian woman cooks on
biogas. Right, an Indian biogas digester
installation. Water has to be added to ensure the
smooth operation of the installation and this can
be a serious constraint in areas where water is
scarce. With some seven million biogas digesters
already installed, China leads the world in biogas
development. Above, cross-section of a Chinese-
designed biogas digester.
Drawing Unesco Courier. Source : A. Van Buren, London
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
( and has to be carried from a far-off well or
other source, bringing the necessary
number of buckets for the biogas plant adds
another burden to an already arduous task.
Lastly, and perhaps one of the most im¬
portant economic factors accounting for the
non-adoption of biogas plants, is the way in
which villagers perceive the opportunity
cost of the available alternative fuels used
for cooking and heating, mainly firewood,
dung-cakes and agricultural wastes.
"Why bother about a gobar gas plant
when we can get firewood (thorny bushes)
around the village to be used as fuel?" asked
a farmer in Rajasthan. When reminded that
very soon the available firewood source
would be exhausted, the farmer replied:
"So far it hasn't happened. We've been
using the same firewood source for ages.
Why should it run out now?"
Another factor is that the direct benefits
of a biogas plant in the form of cooking gas
and manure are perceived to be notional
since there is no direct cash-flow of income
from the plant. Since cash income is the
crucial motivating force for a large section of
the rural population, its absence removes
any immediate incentive to adopt a biogas
plant.
Linked to these socio-economic forces,
there is a host of prevailing cultural practices
and norms which seriously inhibit the pro¬
motion of family-size biogas plants in India.
Firstly, there are strong inhibitions about the
use of human excreta as feeding material for
biogas plants, and about cooking food over
gas generated from slurry containing human
excreta.
The second and perhaps one of the most
serious cultural constraints is the role and
status of women in decision-making. The
most conspicuous and immediate
beneficiaries of biogas plants are the village
women. Not only does biogas save them
from the arduous job of cooking for hours in
a smoke-filled kitchen, with the consequent
health hazards, it also provides them with
more leisure because they spend less of their
time cooking and cleaning soot-stained
utensils. The household is also likely to
economize because the utensils last longer.
But these benefits are not usually given high
priority in the rural households, essentially
because the decision-making for investment
is generally done by the men, who do not
consider the benefits for the women as an
urgent necessity. Because of this attitude,
when plants break down, in many cases
they are allowed to remain out of order for a
long period without attention and repair,
and eventually many of them are irreparably
damaged.
But a still more serious constraint faced in
the rural areas stems from the adjustments
and changes required in various traditional
habits and practices in order to use biogas
efficiently. It is often complained, for exam¬
ple, that chapatis cannot be properly
roasted on a gas burner, and that dais
(pulses) take a long time to cook on gas.
Gas has also been found to be inappropriate
for preserving milk, which for this purpose is
generally kept heating over a slow, steady
fire for a whole day. Thus the introduction
of biogas requires a series of interrelated
changes and adjustments in certain deep-
rooted norms and practices.
But in spite of the limiting factors describ¬
ed above, more and more villagers in India
34
are becoming aware of biogas plants.
However, there is a striking lack of
knowledge of the essential facts about
biogas plants not only among interested
potential users but also among those who
have already adopted the system. In many
rural areas there seems to be a persistent
myth about the "magic" of the biogas plant,
a technology which is alleged to produce
fuel and fertilizer from waste, free of charge
and without any effort. This fashionable
myth about biogas plants is clearly the result
of inadequate and distorted information.
Given the exploratory state of biogas
technology and the consequent lack of
dependability in its performance, the
negative attitudes of the users are bound to
be aggravated unless there is a thorough
sharing of knowledge and experience bet¬
ween users and promoters. False promise
and inadequate information can only breed
unrealistic expectations and lead ultimately
to extreme distrust.
The question of manpower is crucial in
the process of promoting the use of biogas.
An assessment of the problems involved in
promoting family-size biogas plants as part
of a decentralized energy system in rural In¬
dia reveals that there is an enormous con¬
straint in this field. In spite of continuing
claims about the simplicity of current biogas
technology, it requires very careful technical
supervision and guidance in order to install,
repair and maintain. The technical expertise
of this kind is simply not locally available in
most Indian villages.
The list of constraints outlined above
looks formidable, but many of them can be
surmounted over a period of time provided
that appropriate organizational efforts are
made in a planned manner. Operationally,
one of the important goals of such efforts
should be to develop local skills and
knowledge through a sustained education
and training programme. For in the last
analysis a decentralized energy system of
family-size biogas plants in rural India can
only operate successfully when it is least
dependent on external resources.
The example of China is perhaps most
relevant here. Through a continuous pro¬
cess of technical training, China has been
developing a small pool of skilled manpower
in each production team to administer and
monitor the biogas promotion programme.
India needs a similar strategy.
What is required is planning at the local
level, using local resources and promoting
the fullest participation of the local people in
the whole process of planning, education
and monitoring. In order to develop sustain¬
ed local participation, a carefully designed
massive training programme is absolutely
imperative. Such a programme should not
only include the technical aspects of biogas
production but also other related aspects of
the question such as analysis of local con¬
straints, local energy planning methods,
data collection and monitoring, and
methods of integrating biogas energy into
other development activities. 9
TUSHAR KANTI MOULIK is a professor at the
Centre for Management in Agriculture of the In¬
dian Institute of Management, Ahmedabad. A
specialist in the social and economic development
of rural communities, he has served as a consul¬
tant with various national and international agen¬
cies. He is currently engaged on several multi-
disciplinary research projects on rural develop¬
ment in India.
OOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS:
Solar Electricity. An Economic
Approach to Solar Energy, by Wolf¬
gang Palz. A survey of all the known
ways in which the sun's radiation can be
converted into power. Already published
in English, Spanish and Portuguese.
French, Dutch, Italian and Bulgarian edi¬
tions will be published shortly. English
edition is co-published with Butter-
worths, London, who have exclusive
sales rights in the U.K.
Impact of Educational Television
on Young Children, edited by Wayne
H. Holtzman and Isabel Reyes-Lagunes.
1981,60 pp. (12 F).
Community Development, edited
by Ronald Dore and Zoë Mars. An analy¬
sis of cases of community development
experience in India, the Republic of
Korea, Mexico and Tanzania. 1981.
446 pp. (170 F) Co-published with
Croom Helm Ltd., London, who have
exclusive sales rights in the U.K.
Women and Development: Indica¬
tors of their Changing Role, edited by
Mayra Buvinic and lisa Schumacher.
(No. 3 in Unesco's "Socio-Economic
Studies" series) 1981, 112 pp. (20 F).
Self-Management in Education
Systems. 1981, 48 pp. (12 F) World
Problems in the Classroom. 1981.
59 pp. (12 F) Nos. 39 and 41 in Unesco's
"Educational Studies and Documents"
series.
World Directory of Peace
Research Institutions. An alphabetical
listing of all international and regional
institutions, and national institutions in
44 countries. 4th edition revised, 1981,
213 pp. (26 F).
Reporting Southern Africa, edited
by Phil Harris. An in-depth analysis of
the role played by the mass media in
reporting events in countries which prac¬
tice apartheid. 1981, 168 pp. (28 F).
Education and Work in the Spa¬
nish Educational Reform, by Ricardo
Diez Hochleitner, Joaquin Artigas and
Marcelino Garcia Cuerpo. A study pre¬
pared for the Unesco Institute for Educa¬
tion in collaboration with the Internatio¬
nal Educational Reporting Service
(IERS) (No. 42 in Unesco's "Experi¬
ments and Innovations in Education"
series) 1981, 64 pp. (10 F).
Education, Training and the Tradi¬
tional Sector, by Jacques Hallak and
Françoise Caillods (No. 31 in Unesco's
"Fundamentals of Educational
Planning" series) Unesco: International
Institute for Educational Planning. 1981,
143 pp. (15 F).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The social
implications of
the scientific and
technological
revolution
\ < HMO WPHfaH
iresco
Just published
This publication reports the proceedings of a Unesco sympo¬
sium on the scientific and technological revolution and the
social sciences. In it, twenty-three essays by leading scholars
from all the world regions take stock of the present state of
knowledge about the interaction between science, technology
and society.
The scientific and technological revolution as a social pro¬
cess
Philosophical problems of technological advancement
Social functions of science and science policy
Science, technology and development
Social sciences and social change
392 pages 80 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor In your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building. 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesingiaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura. 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
' kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions):
Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse
57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications:
Ka'rger Verlag, Germering/München. For scientific maps only:
Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Pres¬
byterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co.,
13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government Informa¬
tion Services, Publications Centre, GPO Building, Connaught
Place. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, VScI u. 22,
Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja
16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND. Snaebjorn JonssonEf Co., H. F.,
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
B-3/7 Asaf All Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co.1, 28. Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL.
A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. Agent for all Unesco
publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The
Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box"1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. - NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadanl
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New Ser¬
vice Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. - SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store IPty.l Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshon, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Com¬
pany, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham. Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovénie, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljublana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
¿«
ti
'.;
This intriguing pattern of wrinkles, whorls and scars is a mosaic of two false-colour
satellite images of China's Tsaidam Basin, where experiments are taking place in the
use of remote sensing by satellite for petroleum exploration. The energy in petroleum
and other fossil fuels was created millions of years ago by the sun. The threat of the
exhaustion of these fuels and the growing global demand for energy have triggered off
a search for a new energy "mix" in which greater reliance will be placed on new and
renewable forms of energy.
Eros Data Center. Sioux Falls, U.S.A.
]]>
</page>
</document>
