<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074715eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
KIEV
1,500 YEARS OF CULTURE
JOYCE BY BURGESS
SPAIN'S HERITAGE OF ARABIC POETRY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
OTHE PHILIPPINES Bajau bride
For many years our "Treasures of World Art" series has appeared on this page of the magazine. With
this issue we launch a new series which will report on the ways of life of peoples in different parts of
the world their occupations, their leisure pursuits, their daily problems, the rhythm of their lives as
individuals and members of a community. We are calling this new feature "A time to live..." The title
is inspired by that of a new book Le Temps des Peuples, by Unesco's Director-General, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, which is being published this month (in French) by the Paris publishers Robert Laf-
font and which retraces the aims and action of Unesco between November 1974 and November 1980.
To open the series we have chosen this photo of a marriage among the Bajau fishing people who live at
the southern tip of the southernmost islands of the Philippines, the Sulu archipelago. The Bajau, who
number some 12,000, are sea-nomads who live exclusively from fishing and make their homes on their
boats. Like their neighbours, the Samáis, they speak a language closely related to Malay. Photo shows
a young bride of Si Tangkay. Her husband sits behind her, holding the umbrella.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
APRIL 1982 35th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 26 LANGUAGES
English Italian
French Hindi
Spanish Tamil
Russian Hebrew
German Persian
Arabic Dutch
Japanese Portuguese
Turkish Macedonian
Urdu Serbo-Croat
Catalan Slovene
Malaysian Chinese
Korean Bulgarian
Swahili
Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 48 French Francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 4 - 1982 - OPI - 82-3 - 385 A
page
4 KIEV: 1,500 YEARS OF CULTURE
by Pavlo Zagrebelnyi
9 SCIENCE CITY OF THE UKRAINE
by Boris Paton
10 AN INTERNATIONAL METROPOLIS
by Dmitry Nalivaiko
12 THE BIRTH OF A LANGUAGE
by Vitaly Russanovsky
14 THE ARTISTIC INHERITANCE
by Grigory Verves
16 MUMMERS AND MUSIC OF KIEV-RUS
by Sergei Vissotsky
18 FRANCE'S UKRAINIAN QUEEN
by Sergei Vissotsky
24 CENTURIES IN STONE
by Yury Aseev
28 A HUNDRED YEARS OF JAMES JOYCE
by Anthony Burgess
33 THE POETS OF MUSLIM SPAIN
by Emilio García Gómez
38 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 A TIME TO LIVE...
THE PHILIPPINES: Bajau bride
<^£e//^tÂû^t fÁe eciï&t
FFTEEN hundred years ago a small
trading settlement was founded on
the banks of the river Dnieper. It
became the nucleus ofKiev, the great city
which is today the capital of the Ukraine,
a Soviet Socialist Republic with a popula¬
tion of50 million. But the Ukraine is not
alone in celebrating this anniversary, for
as well as being the metropolis of the
Ukrainian people Kiev has also been the
cradle of the cultures of two other great
eastern Slav peoples, the Russians and the
Byelorussians. For centuries its influence
spread even further, as it became a cruci¬
ble of civilizations whose links extended
to the Byzantine empire and the
kingdoms of western Europe, to the
peoples of the steppes, to Iran and to the
caliphate of Baghdad.
The anniversary offers a natural oppor¬
tunity to review the great moments of
Kievan history, which began when the ci¬
ty rose at the cross-roads of great
medieval trade-routes. In 988 came a
decisive moment when prince Vladimir
officially introduced Byzantine Chris¬
tianity, an event which would shape the
cultural and political development of the
Slavs for centuries. From the 10th to the
13th centuries Kiev enjoyed a glorious
period. This was the age ofthe greatfairs,
a time when envoys seeking alliances
travelled to the city from all the courts of
Europe. Palaces and churches mush¬
roomed some 400 churches burgeoned
around the most beautiful of them all, the
cathedral of St. Sophia with its magnifi¬
cent mosaics and frescoes. In the 16th
century Kiev was a focus of the confes¬
sional and ideological rivalries which con¬
vulsed Europe. The resistance it organiz¬
ed then gave birth to an astonishing
literary flowering. In the 19th century
there was an intellectual renaissance
whose most celebratedfigure was thepoet
Taras Shevchenko.
But however rich it may be, the past
alone is not enough to define the
character, spirit and dynamism of a city
and its people. Attached though they are
to their history and determined to
safeguard the monuments which enshrine
it, the Kievans are equally concerned with
the expansion and embellishment of their
city (which with over 2,300,000 in¬
habitants is the third largest in the Soviet
Union). They are constructing its future
in schools, universities, libraries, cultural
centres and research institutes which
specialize in the most advanced
disciplines of science and technology.
Another anniversary being celebrated
this year is the centenary of the birth of
the Irish novelist James Joyce. Today
Joyce is established as one of the
great writers of this century, but he re¬
mains an exacting one. "The demand that
I make of my reader, " he once said, "is
that he should devote his whole life to
reading my works. " In Ulysses (1922) he
set out to focus all human experience and
to celebrate the whole of human culture
in the events of a single day in Dublin.
When it appeared, Ulysses was pilloried
in many quarters not only because of the
frankness with which it described aspects
of life about which novels written in
English had until then generally been
silent, but because of its experimental
techniques and its unfamiliar use of
words, myth and symbol. Finnegans
Wake (1939) demands of the reader an
even more exorbitant interest in language.
It would be hard to think ofa more daun¬
ting challenge for a writer than that of in¬
troducing Joyce to the readers of a
magazine published in 26 language edi¬
tions. We felt that if anyone is qualified
to take up this challenge it is the British
writer Anthony Burgess whose lifelong
devotion to Joyce has been expressed in
many books, broadcasts and articles.
Another glorious chapter in world
literature is also discussed in this issue:
the poetry which blossomed in Muslim
Spain (al-Andalus) and which is
associated with the names of the poet-
king AlMu'tamid, IbnHazm of Cordoba
and Ibn Quzman. Their achievement is
described by Emilio García Gómez, an in¬
ternationally known specialist in Arab
civilization.
Cover shows a detail of a mosaic of St.
Gregory of Nyssa, in the cathedral of St.
Sophia, Kiev.
Cover photo V. Morujenko © Mistetsvo publishers, Kiev.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
rmJrzK^HHtiS* .Aft rt^/Mum*ro^ tti^tknmk^iKotíHijA
«0fÄrtA?rroffri'wri«^i2«^^A7Hlirt^Art<ÖnlnT
This miniature, from a 15th-century manuscript, illustrates the legend of the founding of Kiev
as recounted by Nestor in the Russian Primary Chronicle. "And three brothers there were, the
one named Kiy, the other Shchek and the third Khoriv, and their sister Lybed... And a town
they raised, named for the eldest of their brethren, and called it by the name of Kiev."
Photo © Naumka Dumka, Kiev
KIEV
1,500 years
of culture
by Pavlo Zagrebelnyi
Objects such as
coins, bracelets and
buckles uncovered
during excavation of
the hills of ancient
Kiev bear witness to
the early period of the
town's chequered ex¬
istence. Left, silver
buckle from the 6th
or 7th century.
at
I w
O <D
Û- o
THE earliest account of the history of
Kiev that has reached us is in the
Russian Primary Chronicle which
was written by Nestor, an eleventh-century
monk of the Monastery of the Caves in
Kiev. But although Nestor begins his report
of Kiev's history as the capital of the ancient
State of Rus in the year 862, he is also in¬
terested in the remote origins of Rus and in
the first princes of Kiev.
PAVLO ARKHIPOVICH ZAGREBELNYI, emi¬
nent Ukrainian writer, is first secretary of the
Union of Writers of the Ukrainian SSR. A winner
of the Shevchenko literary prize, he is the author
of many historical novels, short stories, plays,
film scripts and songs.
"How", he asks, "did the land of Rus
come to be, and who was it that in Kiev
began the first princedom?" He goes on to
narrate this folk-story: "And three brothers
there were, the one named Kiy, the other
Shchek, and the third Khoriv, and their
sister Lybed. Kiy made his seat on a hill
where there is now the Mount of Borichev,
and Shchek made his dwelling upon the hill
that is now called Shchekovitsa, and Khoriv
on a third hill that bears the name Khorivit-
sa. And a town they raised, named for the
eldest of their brethren, and called it by the
name of Kiev."
But indirect evidence of the existence of
Kiev may be found long before Nestor took
up its history. Zenob Glak, a seventh-
century Armenian historian, recounts the
legend of the building of Kiev. And in the
ninth century, Emperor Constantine Por-
phyrogenitus of Byzantium calls Kiev Sam-
batas, a name first mentioned in a Byzantine
inscription dated 559.
The Arab geographers of the ninth and
tenth centuries, Ibn Khurradadhbih and Al-
Masudi, the tenth-century Arab writer Ibn
Fadlan, Bishop Dietmar of Merseburg and
the eleventh-century Saxon chronicler
Adam of Bremen give descriptions of Kiev
which sometimes seem to exaggerate its size
and wealth. Dietmar of Merseburg, writing
in 1018, describes it as the capital of a
kingdom and as a major city containing 400
churches, eight markets and a countless
throng of citizens.
People have lived where Kiev now stands
ever since the times of the Scythians and the
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
4
: P» ero tkAjfd m* r( rtfh ipa rí-4 1 ma MrfMK- rtrtAfff/KFfíditii
Evidence of the love of music of the in¬
habitants of ancient Russia abounds in
manuscript illustrations, in frescoes and
wall-paintings in church and monastery,
and even in jewellery motifs. Above, Dance
of the Ancient Slavs, a miniature from a
15th-century manuscript.
Cimmerians, their mysterious predecessors.
The town of Gelon described by Herodotus
as the home of the Budinoi tribes who were
the Scythians' allies may have been ancient
Kiev, as is suggested by the occurrence of
the name Zhelan to designate a stream and
an eleventh-century suburb of Kiev.
Herodotus wrote that "the Budinoi are a
large and numerous tribe: they all have light
blue eyes and red hair. In their land is a
wooden town named Gelon. Each side of its
wall is thirty stages long. The wall is high
and entirely made of wood. Of wood, too,
are the houses and the shrines".
It is reported that the Persian Emperor
Darius, during his campaign against the
Scythians, entered their territory and that of
their allies the Budinoi and the Gelonoi, and
burnt down Gelon.
How tempting it is to believe that Gelon
really was ancient Kiev! If this were so, it
would add a thousand years to the age of
our city and we would today be celebrating
its 2,500th rather than its 1,500th anniver¬
sary. But although the Russian historian
The year 988 marked a turning-point in the
history of Russia, when Vladimir the Great,
son of Svyatoslav, prince of Novgorod,
grand prince of Kiev and sovereign of the
State of Kiev-Rus, was baptized in the
waters of the River Dnieper. The mass con¬
version to Christianity of the people of Kiev-
Rus which followed was to have an in¬
calculable impact on Slav culture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
During the reign of Yaroslav the Wise (1019-1054), son of
Vladimir the Great, Kiev grew in power and splendour.
Dominating the city from its central site and with its impressive
size, its architectural balance and the richness of its frescoes
and mosaics, the Cathedral of St. Sophia proclaimed to the
world the might of Kiev-Rus and its lasting attachment to Chris¬
tianity. Left, the central nave and the dome with the Virgin at
prayer. The later additions of the Baroque period in no way
detract from the purity of line of the original building.
Above, a gusli (zither) player
surrounded by pagan motifs
adorns this silver bracelet,
one of the finest existing ex¬
amples of the silversmith's art
from 12th-century Kiev.
Situated at the cross-roads of
the trade routes linking the
Baltic to the Caspian, Kiev
was at that time a prosperous
merchant city with flourishing
guilds whose craftsmen and
artists were the pride of an¬
cient Russia.
In Kiev-Rus the arts of dressmak¬
ing and embroidery were handed
down from mother to daughter.
Everyday clothes, festive
costumes, religious habits, some
of which we can still admire to¬
day, reveal unerring ornamental
skills and their embroideries in
silk, silver and gold display a
combination of good taste and
sobriety that at times recalls the
artistry of the ¡con. Left, this
piece of cloth, dating from the
11th or 12th century, is em¬
broidered with angels and saints.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Tatishchev and the Czech scholar Niederle
both subscribed to this hypothesis, we are
forced to admit, for lack of direct evidence
to support it, that it must remain in the
realm of supposition.
What is certain is that Kiev makes its ap¬
pearance on the historical scene as pre¬
eminently a Slav city, and that the Slav
tribal groups first played a part in history
around the fifth century AD. It is, then,
quite natural to date to this period the foun¬
dation of the great city on the Dnieper that
sprang up along the renowned trade route
"from the Varangians to the Greeks", link¬
ing the world of the Varangian plunderers of
the north with the then centre of the civiliz¬
ed world, Byzantium. (The term Varangians
designates not only the Scandinavian Vik¬
ings, as was traditionally thought, but also
the Slavonic tribes living along the southern
shores of the Baltic. Our earliest chronicle,
describing the crowning of the Varangian
Prince Oleg in Kiev, says: "And there were
with him Varangians and Slavs and others,
calling themselves Russians").
Ill-protected, Kiev presented an easy prey
to the first invader who might chance along.
And indeed this appears to have been the
town's fate, since apart from the story of its
founding by Kiy and the information that he
visited Constantinople and was received
with honour by its Emperor, no record
speaks of the strength or importance of Kiev
in the first two or three centuries of its
existence.
Then the Slavic warrior-princes Askold
and Dir, who were to threaten Byzantium
itself, appeared in Kiev. Like all Slavs, they
were too trusting, and fell victim to the wily
Norman warlord Oleg, who became master
In the mid-17th century, sporadic peasant
and Cossack uprisings in protest against
social hardships gradually spread and
developed into a full-scale war of liberation
and culminated, in 1654, in the reunification
of the Ukraine with Russia. Above, the
statue of the victorious insurgent leader
Bogdan Kmelnytsky, his arm pointing in the
direction of Moscow, in the main square of
Kiev which bears his name. In the
background, the cupolas of St. Sophia.
of Kiev and during his reign forced Byzan¬
tium to sign a trade treaty on terms
favourable to himself. The gates still stand
in Istanbul on which Oleg nailed his shield.
His successor Igor marched on Byzan¬
tium and its provinces, and his wife Olga
was lavishly received by the Emperor.
Svyatoslav, the son of Igor and Olga, whom
history remembers as a great defender of his
territory, routed the Khazars, kept Byzan¬
tium in constant dread and, although he had
little affection for Kiev and even dreamt of
moving the capital to the Danube, was the
first of the lords of Kiev to make the city a
byword.
Svyatoslav's son, Vladimir, was con¬
verted to Christianity and flung the doors of
Kiev-Rus open to all the treasures of world
culture. But it was Vladimir's son, Yaroslav
the Wise, who was the first of Kiev's
educator-princes. Yaroslav built up Kiev
and greatly enlarged it, prompting the
chronicler to enter under the year 1037:
"Yaroslav laid out a great town, and in that
town there is a Golden Gate; he likewise laid
out the Church of St. Sophia for the
Photo © N. Kozlovsky, Kiev
Metropolitan, and then the Church of the
Golden Gate for our Holy Lady of the An¬
nunciation, then the Monasteries of St.
George and of St. Irina." The Monastery of
the Caves was also founded during
Yaroslav's reign.
The first translators and transcribers of
religious books set to work in churches and
monasteries. Chronicles were opened,
schools were started and the first library was
established in the Cathedral of St. Sophia.
Crafts flourished, art schools sprang up,
and the capital of the State of Kiev-Rus
came to rival Constantinople itself, as was
indicated by Hilarión, the first Russian
Metropolitan installed by Yaroslav, who
wrote in his famous Sermon on Law and
Grace, "all manner of men and merchants
flocked thither, and all manner of goods
from all lands were found there".
Even though by the end of the eleventh
century Kiev was no longer the real capital
of the ancient State of Rus (in this far-flung
land there were some fifteen independent
princedoms each with its own capital) it still
remained the symbol of Russian unity, and
the heart of the land of Russia.
It was the focal point of political thought
(it was the birthplace of the first Russian
code of law, Yaroslav the Wise's "Russian
Law"), a centre of crafts and commerce,
economics and culture, ethics and religion.
The church then played a key role in preser¬
ving the unity of the Russian lands and Kiev
was the seat of the head of the Russian
Church, the Metropolitan. From Kiev came
the hierarchs for churches throughout the
land, and the Monastery of the Caves alone
supplied some fifty bishops during the
twelfth century. I
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Modern Kiev is an impor¬
tant administrative, in¬
dustrial, scientific and
cultural centre with a
population of some two
and a half million. Since
the Second World War, the
city has been rebuilt and
has developed at an im¬
pressive rate. Priority has
been given to housing,
with dwellings for ten
thousand people being
built every year over the
past decade.
i> Kiev, not Novgorod, Chernigov, Vladimir
or Galich, was the envy of the independent
princes. Some tried to capture it, others to
weaken its influence, and yet others to
destroy it completely. But Kiev survived,
symbol of the integrity of old Russia, and
the best minds of the age recognized that
this was its role. Hence the appeals to de¬
fend the integrity of the homeland which oc¬
cur in the Russian Primary Chronicle, and
the eulogy of the Kievan Prince Svyatoslav
in the greatest epic poem of ancient Russia,
the Tale of the Host of Igor, in which
Svyatoslav calls on the princes in his "word
of gold" to defend the golden throne of
Kiev.
The name of Kiev resounded throughout
Europe, as Yaroslav's extensive dynastic
relations show. His daughter Anna he mar¬
ried to Henry I of France (see page 18),
Anastasia to King Andrew of Hungary, and
Elizabeth to King Harald Hardraade of
Norway, who was to die at the Battle of
Stamford Bridge. Yaroslav's son Vsevolod
married the daughter of the Emperor Con-
stantine Monomachus of Byzantium, his
son Izyaslav took the daughter of the King
of Poland as his wife, and his son
Svyatoslav married Countess Oda, descen¬
dant of a line of German princes.
Kiev's cultural achievements at that time
may be judged today through the Cathedral
of St. Sophia, which has survived almost in¬
tact, with its famous mosaics and frescoes.
The ruins of the Golden Gate have also been
preserved, but much has been swallowed up
by merciless time.
In the twelfth and thirteenth centuries,
after countless attacks and depredations by
the nomads and also by the independent
Russian princes, who were rightly rebuked
by the talented author of the Tale of the
Host of Igor for their hostility to Russian
unity Kiev slowly lost its importance as a
political, commercial and economic centre.
8
And yet it remained a great city. The immor¬
tal spirit of an entire people was alive in it.
Chronicles were written there, songs and
epic poems were composed and sung. It was
in Kiev that the Tale of the Host ofIgor was
written. Books were transcribed and sent all
over Russia. Goldsmiths made precious or¬
naments, artists and icon-painters adorned
the churches.
In the early thirteenth century, the hordes
of Chingiz-Khan swept in from the far ex¬
panses of Asia, and his grandson, Batu-
Khan, (known to Russians as Baty) advanc
ed westwards to subjugate Europe. For two
whole years, however, he manoeuvred
around Kiev, gathering his troops, sparing
his horses, sending out scouts and spies,
warily testing the ground.
When in late December 1240 Baty moved
against the walls of Kiev with his formidable
army, he was probably deterred not only by
the city ramparts (up to twelve metres high
and twenty thick) the walls of oak with
stone watchtowers, the triple belt of for¬
tifications (the city of Yaroslav, the city of
Vladimir, and at their heart, the palace of
In preparation for the celebra¬
tion of the 1,500th anniversary
of their city, the people of
Kiev have been restoring
monuments, studying ancient
chronicles and manuscripts
and generally reviving the
memory of the past. Right,
mannequins model costumes
of the past against the splen¬
did décor of the Cathedral of
St. Sophia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Yaroslav) or the battle-hardened guard led
by the Governor appointed by the Grand
Duke Daniil Galitsky, Captain Dmitry. He
was deterred by the spirit of this mysterious
city, its enigmatic nature, its renown
throughout the land of Russia. To the
nomads, Kiev was, as it were, the key to
Europe, its wealth and its soul. To capture
Kiev was to take Europe. It meant imposing
a reign of terror, and Chingiz-Khan's com¬
manders were past masters at this.
Baty burnt and destroyed Kiev, blindly
avenged himself upon its defenders,
slaughtered and imprisoned its inhabitants.
The envoy of Pope Innocent IV, the Fran¬
ciscan monk Carpini, who passed through
the city in 1246, noted that it "has been vir¬
tually wiped out: there are hardly 200 homes
left in it, and those people are kept in the
deepest slavery".
But even in defeat Kiev was not im¬
poverished. The Cathedral of St. Sophia
and the Monastery of the Caves and the
Vydubetskii Monastery survived, damaged
but intact. Life continued in the surroun¬
ding areas, and some shades of its former
glory lived on in the city itself. And when,
years later, Kiev was taken by Grand Duke
Gediminas of Lithuania, it was not just a
name on a map but the historic centre for
the entire country.
A city may be destroyed but it will live on
as long as its spirit lasts. And the spirit of a
city is its people.
Where has the undying spirit of Kiev been
preserved? In its inaccessible ramparts, the
desperate courage of its defenders, the
greatness of its cathedrals, the thought of
the chroniclers, the knowledge spread far
and wide by the Mogila Academy (founded
in the sixteenth century), the free-ranging
intellect of our first philosopher,
Skovoroda, the- poetry of Shevchenko and
the talent of the poet of our era, Pavlo
Tychina.
We can trace the continuity and strength
of this spirit through the history of Kiev,
from the period of the princes to the times
of Bogdan Khmelnytsky's peasant wars of
liberation that culminated in the reunifica¬
tion of the Ukraine with Russia in 1654. We
can see its force in the bullet-riddled wall of
the "Arsenal" Factory in Kiev whose
workers rose up in 1918 to defend Soviet
power in the Ukrainian capital. In the
darkness of a November night in 1943 it in¬
spired the soldiers of the Soviet Army when
they stormed the Dnieper near Kiev to free
the ancient capital from the Fascists and
drive them from our land.
I would gladly speak of Kiev as it is today,
with its population of 2,500,000 people and
its 1 1 ,000,000 trees, a city of many factories,
and even more research institutes, including
the world-famous Paton Institute of Elec¬
trical Welding and the Cybernetics Institute.
I would like to evoke the city's streets, its
buildings, its people, ancient Kiev and baro¬
que Kiev, the dazzling gold of the cathedral
and the mighty concrete shapes of the new
developments.
The beauty and greatness of Kiev lie in the
fact that it is rooted in history. Here the cen¬
turies wander through the streets, and the
spirit of Slavdom lives in the ancient dales.
Pavlo Zagrebelnyi
During the early days of the Soviet space programme, Boris Paton, director of the Institute of
Electric Welding, at Kiev, was given the task of studying the problems of metal welding in
space. Laboratory experiments were devised and carried out under simulated space condi¬
tions (weightlessness, almost total vacuum, wide variation in temperature, etc.) to test the
reliability of the equipment to be used. The first welding operation actually performed in
space was effected on 16 October 1969, since when research has continued. Above, a
specialist at the Kiev Institute carrying out an experiment under simulated space conditions.
SCIENCE CITY
OF THE UKRAINE
by Boris Paton
BORIS EUGENIEVICH PATON, of the Ukrai¬
nian SSR, is president of the Ukrainian Academy
of Sciences and a member of the Academy of
Sciences of the USSR. A leading world figure in
thefield ofmetal welding, his many discoveries in
this area have earned him several awards, in¬
cluding the Lenin Prize.
SINCE the coming of socialism Kiev has
become one of the most important
cultural, scientific and industrial
centres of the USSR. In Kiev are located
nearly 70 per cent of the institutes and agen¬
cies of the prestigious Academy of Sciences
of the Ukrainian SSR, which, during the
sixty-odd years of its existence has carried
out an enormous amount of research in the
most diverse fields of technology and of the
natural and social sciences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The Academy of Sciences has given birth
to a number of schools of scientific thought
whose work today is universally recognized.
These include D.A. Grave and his group
who carried out important research in
algebra and numerical theory; and teams
working on the theory of non-linear oscilla¬
tions, led by N.M. Krylov, and on elasticity,
under A.N. Dynnik.
Research conducted by K.D. Sinelnikov,
A.K. Valter, A.I. Leipunsky, G.D.
Latychev and others marked an important
step forward in the development of nuclear
physics. It was thanks to this research that
fission of the lithium nucleus was achieved
for the first time in the Soviet Union and
that the first particle accelerator was built.
In the earth sciences, investigations car¬
ried out by Ukrainian scientists have led to
the discovery of large deposits of oil, iron
ore, coal and other useful minerals.
An extremely important field for the na¬
tional economy is research on the techniques
of metal welding. The methods developed at
the Paton Institute of Electric Welding have
revolutionized industry and have rapidly
replaced the old technology of assembly by
riveting.
Today researchers from the Ukrainian
Academy of Sciences rank among the
world's top specialists in the development of
the theoretical principles of arc-weldjng.
Their work on processes such as electroslag
welding, carbon dioxide shielded welding,
electron-beam welding, plasma welding, ex¬
plosive welding, and underwater welding,
has led to fundamental changes in
metalwork technology.
In 1969 Ukrainian research scored a
major success and a world première when a
cutting and welding experiment was carried
out in space aboard the spaceship Soyuz-6
with the aid of the "Vulkan" equipment
developed by Academy of Sciences
specialists. The experiment marked the birth
of a new space technology that will have a
vital part of play in the conquest of the
cosmos.
Another major achievement of Ukrainian
science has been the development of a
general theory of isotope separation with
important applications in the manufacture
of industrial equipment used in heavy water
production and in the separation of
uranium isotopes. This was a basic starting-
point for the development of nuclear
energy, a power source of increasing impor¬
tance in the present energy crisis.
Finally, mention should be made of the
Academy of Sciences' Institute of
Cybernetics whose research workers have
clarified a number of major theoretical
problems in their field, and of the Institute
of Supra-resistant Materials where impor¬
tant work is being carried out in the field of
industrial technology, in particular on the
equipment required for the production of
artificial diamonds. Boris Paton
Svyatoslav I, grand prince of Kiev (945-972), and his family; from the Svyatoslav
Codex (Kiev, 1073). Svyatoslav was a great hero of early Russian history.
AN INTERNATIONAL
METROPOLIS
by Dmitry Nalivaiko
HISTORIC Kiev is one of those cities
of the world whose cultural signifi¬
cance goes beyond national bound¬
aries, and assumes international dimen¬
sions. This is in part due to its geographical
situation astride the great waterway that led
"from the Varangians to the Greeks", link¬
ing the northern and southern extremities of
the continent, and its proximity to the limits
of the steppe, where Europe came into con¬
tact with Asia and the civilizations of the
east.
DMITRY SERGEIVICH NALIVAIKO, of the
Ukrainian SSR, is a lecturer at the Gorky In¬
stitute of Pedagogical Science, Kiev, and a
specialist in the literature of western Europe and
international cultural relations.
If the culture of ancient Rus, firmly cen¬
tred on Kiev, was undoubtedly European,
both in origin and in nature, it was also
steeped in oriental influences. During the
tenth-twelfth centuries, the State of Kiev-
Rus maintained a network of relations with
many peoples and lands, both European
and eastern, and this contributed in no small
measure 'to the vigorous development of its
culture.
The most important and fruitful contacts
were undoubtedly those between Kiev-Rus
and Byzantium, then a cultural centre of
worldwide significance. Modern scholars
consider that the Byzantine influence in Rus
gradually led to a comparatively
sophisticated level of spiritual exchange.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Within a relatively short space of time,
albeit in great measure through south
Slav that is, Bulgarian and, to a lesser ex¬
tent, Serbianintermediaries, the bookmen
of Kiev became familiar with the immense
treasures of Byzantine literature. The
discovery of the art of Byzantium, and of its
architecture and painting in particular, oc¬
curred with equal rapidity.
As the direct descendant of Hellenism,
the culture of Greek antiquity, Byzantium
bore the heritage on which European
civilization would be founded. Kiev-Rus, by
assimilating the riches of Byzantine
literature and art, thus participated in the
laying of those foundations, as it would par¬
ticipate in the progressive development of
European culture.
But significant though it was, the in¬
fluence of Byzantium did not transform the
culture of ancient Rus into a mere copy of
the original; nor did Kiev become a mere an¬
nex of Constantinople. In the process of
assimilating all that was most progressive in
Byzantine culture, and thus becoming
familiar with cultural experiences and
developments in Europe and to a lesser ex¬
tent the east, Kiev-Rus discovered its own
cultural identity. This is especially apparent
when we consider the originality of its
literature.
The Tale of the Host ofIgor in particular,
is without precedent in Byzantine literature,
and cannot be compared with the epics of
western Europe: contemporary in its theme,
richly lyrical in its treatment, it is rooted in
the imagery and pagan mythology of the
Slavs.
The architecture and other arts of Kiev-
Rus are similarly distinctive. If Kiev's
St. Sophia Cathedral would have been in¬
conceivable without its equivalent in Con¬
stantinople, it speaks of an entirely different
culture. Where Constantinople's cathedral
is in the form of a basilica with a single,
enormous cupola, Kiev's is a cross-shaped
building, the central cupola of which is sur¬
rounded by a number of smaller ones: its
style is typical of ancient Russian architec¬
ture. Other original features of St. Sophia in
Kiev include its open arcades, or galleries,
and an abundance of mosaics, wall-
paintings and frescoes, the subjects of which
are often secular.
The development of world culture,
especially in its earliest stages, is characteriz¬
ed by the emergence in different regions of
"communities of interests" based on the
same cultural and historical characteristics.
Medieval Europe knew two such "com¬
munities": the Latino-Germanic in the
western and the Byzantine-Slavonic in the
eastern parts of the continent. The latter
was reflected in the strong sense of cultural
unity which existed between the countries of
the eastern Slavs (ancient Rus, which later
became Russia, the Ukraine and
Byelorussia) and those of the southern Slavs
(Bulgaria, Serbia, Macedonia). Within this
community of cultures, the dynamics of
history assured pride of place to one or
other of its components at different times.
From the eleventh to the thirteenth century,
for example, the eastern Slav influence was
predominant, and this ensured that Kiev
assumed the leading cultural role in the en¬
tire Orthodox Slav world.
At the same time, and in the eleventh and
twelfth centuries in particular, the capital
city of the State of Rus maintained extreme¬
ly close relations with its eastern neighbours,
as well as the countries of central and
western Europe. Indeed, Kiev-Rus occupied
an important place in the political life of the
entire continent.
One demonstration of this is to be found
in the number of external dynastic marriages
contracted by the great princes of Kiev. Sur¬
viving records show that during the eleventh
century, thirty-eight such alliances were
solemnized, including eight with Germany,
two with France, five with the Scandinavian
countries and England (with which relations
were particularly close at the time), seven
with Poland, six with Hungary, three with
the Polovtsian Khanates and four with
Byzantium.
During the following century,
Byzantium's share increased to eight, but
there was no substantial diminution in the
number of conjugal alliances with ruling
families in central and western Europe. This
state of affairs may be explained by the
power and authority which the princes of
Kiev wielded in European affairs: as a
means of securing their political and
. military support, the rulers of many coun¬
tries were eager to become their kinsmen by
marriage.
The prestige of the ancient Russian State
in European eyes also incited ambassadors,
merchants and soldiers from the west to pay
frequent visits to Kiev, where they were im¬
pressed by the size of the city and the
grandeur of its palaces and religious
buildings. Their reports frequently formed
part of the contents of western chronicles
and cosmographies. Thus, Adam of
Bremen, the celebrated eleventh-century
geographer, commented that Kiev "rivalled
Constantinople" and was "the most
beautiful ornament in the Greek world" (by
which he obviously meant the Byzantine-
Slavonic Orthodox community).
Images of Kiev-Rus and its capital are to
be found in western European epic
literaturein the Scandinavian sagas, Ger¬
man heroic poems and French chansons de
geste and tales of chivalry. It is curious to
note, too, that these works also contained
echoes and images from Russian epic
literature; German and Scandinavian poems
of the eleventh-thirteenth centuries often
mention Prince Vladimir and Ilya
Muromets, who was referred to as "Ilya the
Russian" (Ilias von Riutzen).
The Mongolian and Tatar invasion in the
thirteenth century, the martyrdom of Kiev
at the hands of Batu Khan in 1240 and the
seizure of power by Lithuanian feudal lords
a century later brought about a gradual
decline in the cultural life of the city and in
its international relations. It was not until
the end of the sixteenth century and the
beginning of the seventeenth, when Kiev's
position as the focal point of Ukrainian
culture was firmly established, that a current
of revival began to flow which was to reach
full strength in the second half of the seven¬
teenth and the first half of the eighteenth
centuries, after the reunification of the
Ukraine with Russia.
Kiev's international cultural relations
resumed their former scale and scope;
andmost importantthe city once again
. i
Tfn
lt>At\t\. ^- -
y v r-'..»..,..',-.	 i * r
Phoio © Oleg Safto, Kiev
Above, detail of Antoniy Radivilovsky's illustration for
the title page of a collection of sermons, 77ie Garden
(1671).
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
became a melting-pot where different
cultural traditions were blended. The steadi¬
ly increasing interpénétration of Byzantine-
Slavonic, ancient Russian and modern
European cultures which occurred during
the Renaissance is an outstanding example
of this process.
Viewed against the background of Europe
in its entirety, the Renaissance was not the
only transitional stage in cultural develop¬
ment. In the countries of eastern and south¬
eastern Europe, the passage from the
medieval to the modern period occurred for
the most part during the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries, when Baroque culture
was already spreading art over the whole
continent. Because the Renaissance itself
had not found full expression in eastern and
south-eastern Europe, where its appearance
had been of a sporadic nature, it was in
these regions that Baroque culture assumed
a specific character and functions.
More precisely, it assumed the supremely
important roleelsewhere undertaken by
the Renaissance of secularizing and
humanizing culture, i.e. liberating it from
the tutelage of the Church and impregnating
it with earthly, human qualities. Kiev's
significance during this period was above all
due to its primacy as a disseminator of
Baroque culture not only through the
Ukraine but throughout the Orthodox Slav
community as a whole. Indeed, it was in
Kiev that the functions mentioned above
were performed most intensely.
In this connexion, the foundation in 1632
of the Kievo-Mogilyanskaya College
(designated as an Academy in 1694), the
first institution of higher education in the
Orthodox Slav world, was an event of the
highest importance. Whereas earlier centres
of learning had. been rooted in Byzantine-
Slavonic traditions, the Kiev Academy was a
"Latin school" modelled on Polish and
western European universities, and instruc¬
tion was given in Latin. The most distinctive
feature of its founders' activity was that at a
time when the struggle for religious liberty
in the Ukraine had become particularly
acute, they declined the task of defending
the canons of the Orthodox Church, and
concentrated on promoting among their
pupils the assimilation of contemporary
European, in other words Baroque, culture,
which was a blend of antique, classical,
Renaissance' and medieval "Gothic"
elements.
Philosophy occupied an important place
in the teaching of the Kiev Academy.
Students became familiar with the work of
ancient philosophers from Heraclitus to
Boethius, of medieval scholars and mystics,
as well as Bacon, Descartes, Leibniz, Locke
and other outstanding thinkers. Courses in
poetics and rhetoric, essentially based on the
works of Italian Renaissance humanists,
were another important part of the pro¬
gramme. The poets and rhetoricians of Kiev
were well acquainted with the concepts and
principles of European literary theory in the
sixteenth and seventeenth centuries, and
with works based on that theory; at the
same time, they were responsible for the
reconstruction of Ukrainian, Russian and
other eastern and southern Slav literatures
according to a new European pattern.
Under their influence, new genres and
styles took shape, and developed along
Baroque and Classical lines. Similar pro¬
cesses occurred at the same time in Ukrai¬
nian art which, under the powerful
Renaissance and Baroque influences of
western Europe, turned away from medieval
These stylized horsemen, painted in vivid
colours, are from the Kiev Psalter (1397),
one of the masterpieces of miniaturist art of
ancient Russia.
conventions and began to portray real men
in the setting of the real world. The artists of
Kiev-Pechersk Monastery (the Monastery of
the Caves), for example, created a distinc¬
tive art form of their own, and at the same
time maintained close contacts with Venice,
Augsburg and other European centres of
book-printing and draughtsmanship.
Research has established that from its
very beginnings, the Kiev-Mogilyanskaya
Academy was an institution of international
dimensions. Its records show that students
came there not only from the Ukraine, but
also from Russia and Byelorussia, Serbia
and Bulgaria, Moldavia and Wallachia. Its
founders and those who succeeded them
sought at the same time to establish schools
in all the countries of the Orthodox Slav
world. To this end they dispatched to
TfcTH.C
TO BUKfrifl
TKblMtJ
THE BIRTH OF A LANGUAGE
KIEV came into being in the fifth cen¬
tury at the cross-roads of the trade-
routes linking Asia to Europe and
northern Europe to Byzantium. At this
period the Slav tribes which are thought to
have been living in the territory between the
middle course of the Dnieper and the Bug
began to pour towards the north, west and
south.
At the same time the language they had
long shared began to diversify, giving birth
to the languages of the southern and western
Slavs. In the east, however, in the region of
the middle Dnieper, the southern and
eastern Bug, the upper Dnieper, the Volga,
the Don, and Lake limen, the tribal dialects
VITALY MAKAROVICH RUSSANOVSKY, of
the Ukrainian SSR, is a corresponding member of
the Ukrainian Academy of Sciences and secretary
of its department of literature, languages and
linguistics.
by Vitaly Russanovsky
of the eastern Slavs retained their common
characteristics, fusions and secessions
notwithstanding.
These eastern Slav tribes eventually form¬
ed a social organization of a pre-feudal
kind. Craftsmanship developed, and the
communities joined together to form States.
The ninth and tenth centuries saw the birth
of the first feudal State in the Slavic east:
Kiev-Rus.
Many tribes lived in the immense area of
Kiev-Rus which at the time of the great
princes Vladimir and Yaroslav the Wise
stretched across the vast plains of eastern
Europe. From the heroic legends of these
tribes grew the unique culture of ancient
Russia, with its chronicles, patriotic epics
such as the Tale of the Host of Igor, its
frescoes and mosaics of great beauty. These
peoples all used the same spoken language,
Old Russian, but where the written language
was concerned the situation was more com¬
plicated.
After the introduction of Christianity into
Russia at the end of the tenth century, ec¬
clesiastical books written in Old Slavonic
began to be copied in the Balkans. Old
Slavonic was quite closely related to Old
Russian, and the two languages became in¬
termixed. Old Russian acquired many scien¬
tific and philosophical terms from Old
Slavonic, which in its turn tended towards a
simplification of forms along the lines of
Old Russian. In this way the literary
language of Kiev-Rus came into being.
Local variants from different regions were
later engrafted onto the common trunk.
Major historical events had repercussions
on the linguistic evolution of Kiev-Rus. In
the twelfth century the powerful Russian
State split into a multitude of feudal
princedoms which warred constantly among
themselves for the throne of Kiev and,
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Moscow, Mogilev, Iasi, Belgrade and other
cities what Pyotr Mogila described in a letter
to Tsar Mikhail in 1640 as "seemly ec¬
clesiastics and well-trained teachers".
Graduates of the Academy, who in turn
became teachers, carried abroad with them a
new type of spiritual culture, and helped to
consolidate the new trends in literature and
art. We need only recall in this connexion
the activity of the poet Simeon Polotsky and
his followers in Moscow during the second
half of the seventeenth century, which con¬
tributed in no small measure to the develop¬
ment of a "new" Russian literature, steeped
in Baroque influences; or that of Mikhail
Kozachinsky and other emissaries of the
Kiev Academy in Serbia, during the first
half of the eighteenth century, where they
performed a similar role among the
southern Slavs.
In the early eighteenth century, the poet
and philosopher Theophan Prokopovich,
together with Gavriil Buzhinsky and other
graduates of Kiev, actively supported the
educational and cultural reforms of Peter
the Great and did much to put them into ef¬
fect. All the above examples show that Kiev
and its Academy played an outstandingly
progressive role in cultural development
during the period of transition, not only in
the Ukraine but also in Russia, Byelorussia,
Serbia and other countries of the eastern
and south Slav community.
Kiev was to remain throughout history the
leading centre of Ukrainian culture, and the
chief intermediary for its dissemination to
other parts of the world. Its significance
assumed exceptional dimensions after the
October Revolution, which brought social
and national freedom to the Ukrainian peo¬
ple and opened new perspectives for the
development of their culture and its installa¬
tion among the other cultures of the world.
H Dmitry Nalivaiko
! LABAAyMTrfVW/TK/ADOJ
I «IIA '»*J 'i*
I K àri## f^tlmíj, if i*» Tattajti Wifianlthcf
tri i F : trvtipu t^e>U< lyt
Tnn£ Vvrfut* Tk/olomiiaru ifiiorc
jC^f ¡tLttrt tut JJ^tif^Cmm OrH^Jr,,t
ttcdf Aim! OrrhrJati U^ifch A, tiforii.
Photo © Editions Mistetsvo, Kiev
Minerva, goddess of wisdom, is depicted at the head of the
scholars of Kiev in this late 17th-century engraving by Ivan
Chtirsky. In the background are the buildings of the
celebrated Mogila Academy, one of the centres of cultural
life in the city. The classical-allegorical style is typical of the
Baroque period.
**» 3 8 76*%^
rfdtitímiKíi
G il OR ¿H CM M
runnuru
tf i Ùfi H Hfl c&íK 66HY* ut-
E/fcn«rM.G/wkn«ñ jfiu^« TU«
WM ¿TtWAtfinCTlfjinrA l"qA\
íjuntas
T-PlKOy ô rufWM nu (¡ni £f**r»
ÍP i
y
Title page of the first book of grammar of
the Ukrainian language, compiled at the
Sorbonne, Paris, by a Ukrainian student,
Ivan Oujevich, in 1643. A facsimile edition of
this work, an essential tool for the study of
the Ukrainian language, was published in
Kiev in 1970.
weakened by the fighting, were overcome by
nomad invaders from the eastern steppes in
the middle of the thirteenth century. When
the invading hordes retreated, the territory
on the banks of the Dnieper came under the
control of Lithuania. Then, in the sixteenth
century, the south-western part of the area
became part of the kingdom of Poland. This
is why, in the west, south-west and north¬
east of the old Kievan State, three languages
developed: Byelorussian, Ukrainian and
Russian respectively. The ancestry of all
three can be traced back directly to the
language of Old Russia.
The sixteenth and seventeenth centuries,
which saw the struggle of the Ukrainian peo¬
ple to throw off the cruel yoke which denied
them their identity as a society and as a na¬
tion, were an important period in the history
of the Ukrainian language. They saw the
birth of a polemical literature of exceptional
richness, which emerged in defiance of at¬
tempts to crush the cultural originality of
the Ukrainian people and to impose
Catholicism on them. During the same
period the Ukrainian language was widely
used in business, and for administrative and
legal documents. The first plays in the
Ukrainian language were written at this
time. The reunification of the Ukraine and
Russia in the middle of the seventeenth cen
tury had a strong influence on the develop¬
ment of the language.
The end of the eighteenth century and the
nineteenth century constitute the golden age
of literature in Ukrainian language, first in
poetry and then, after 1850, in prose. The
Ukraine was divided between two empires,
Russia and Austria-Hungary, between
which relations were difficult. Teaching and
the publication of bqpks in Ukrainian were
restricted and even punished. In spite of this
unpropitious political background, the
Ukrainian language provided such great
writers as Shevchenko, Franko, Lesa
Ukrainka and Kotiubinsky with a flexible
instrument with which they could create a
gallery of unforgettable characters.
But it was only after the October Revolu¬
tion that Ukrainian became a means of com¬
munication extending to all fields of social
life: as the language of secondary and higher
education, of science and culture, of radio
and television, theatre and cinema, the press
and the business world. Today countless
masterpieces of world literature have been
translated into Ukrainian, attesting to the
language's development, the richness of its
vocabulary, the diversity of its resources and
its capacity to contribute to the fulfilment of
the spriritual life of the Ukrainian nation.
H Vitaly Russanovsky
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE ARTISTIC
INHERITANCE
by Grigory Verves
THE cultural role of Kiev, both natio¬
nally and among the Slav peoples as
a whole, was considerably enhanced
after the reunification of the Ukraine and
Russia in a single state.
During the nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries, despite the Tsarist repression,
which went so far as to prohibit the use of
the Ukrainian language and dealt a severe
blow to national cultural aspirations, Kiev
lost none of its earlier prestige. It would in¬
deed be difficult to overestimate the value of
the city's contribution to Ukrainian culture,
or the attraction which it exercised on ethnic
Ukrainian communities, wherever they were
to be found.
At the beginning of the nineteenth cen¬
tury, the centre of gravity of Ukrainian
cultural life shifted for a time to Kharkov, ,
whose university was founded in 1805. The
creation of Kiev University in 1834 restored
the city's former pre-eminence in cultural
affairs which was symbolized by the return
in the early 1840s, after graduation from
the Academy of St. Petersburg, of Taras
Shevchenko.
Shevchenko (1814-1861) was a poet, artist
and philosopher of genius whose achieve¬
ment, historically significant both in his own
country and abroad, was to complete the
task begun by his predecessors and to create
a modern, truly Ukrainian literary language.
At the same time, he stimulated public ap¬
preciation of the fine arts, and played a
catalytic role in all other fields of cultural
activity, including the theatre and
dramaturgy, music and social philosophy.
Portraying with a powerful depth of feeling
and reflection the thoughts and aspirations
of his people and the vast range of their
historical experience, Shevchenko may be
considered as the father of a national Ukrai¬
nian culture in the fullest sense of the term,
and his name is associated with all subse¬
quent developments in the quest for an
aesthetic, ethical and social ideal.
GRIGORY VERVES, of the Ukrainian SSR, is a
corresponding member of the Ukrainian
Academy of Sciences and president of the Ukrai¬
nian committee of the International Association
for the study and furtherance of Slav culture.
I will praise to the heavens
The enslaved, the humble, the mute
Keeping vigilant watch in their midst
I will speak out in their name
These lines are by the great Ukrainian poet and painter Taras
Shevchenko (1814-1861) who gave his talents and his life to the
cause of an oppressed people. Freed from serfdom at the age of
24, Shevchenko became a celebrated portrait painter at St.
Petersburg. His first book of poems, The Kobzar, was published
in 1840. Despite his own personal success he never forgot the
humiliations suffered by the people of the Ukraine, and all his
poems are a passionate defence of peasant revolt as the only possi¬
ble means to finish, once and for all, with serfdom and the ab¬
solute power of the Tsar. Poems such as The Dream, Caucasus
and The Testament are steeped in this revolutionary spirit and
ring out with the call for the brotherhood of peoples. After ten
years of enforced exile in central Asia, he returned to St.
Petersburg where he died at the age of forty-seven. His works
have been translated into more than a hundred languages and to¬
day are known throughout the world. Above, Self-Portrait by
Candlelight (1860), aquatint.
14
Engraving (1919) by the Ukrainian artist IMar-
bute, illustrating a famous poem by Shev¬
chenko which relates the story of Katerina,
a young peasant-girl seduced and abandon¬
ed by a nobleman (see also colour p. 22).
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
As in the case of many other peoples
whose natural development was subjected
not only to social but also to national con¬
straints, the cultural roots of the Ukraine
were constantly watered from a perennial
source the creativity of the people
themselves. This explains the great amount
of time and effort spent by successive
generations of intellectuals in the investiga¬
tions of popular history, the editing of an¬
cient manuscripts and the collection and
publication of folklore.
As far as the Ukraine was concerned, the
wealth of this cultural heritage was
acknowledged not only by such eminent
native-born writers as Shevchenko and
Gogol, but also by leading representatives of
Shevchenko knew from personal ex¬
perience the harsh treatment meted out to
political prisoners under the Tsarist regime.
He wrote about it in his poems and depicted
it in paintings like the one below from his
Prodigal Son series. A stick was forced into
the prisoner's mouth to prevent talking.
other culturesthe Russian Pushkin, the
Poles Mickiewicz and Slowacki and the
Croatian Kharambashich. "Even if I did not
have friends living near Kiev", wrote
Honoré de Balzac in a letter, "its literary
and ethnographic attractions would draw
me there".
The traditions of the peopletheir music,
songs, architecture and applied and
decorative artsnaturally contributed in
very great measure to nineteenth century
Ukrainian culture, but they were not the on¬
ly source of inspiration. The "professional"
art of earlier centuries, and reciprocal in¬
fluences with other cultures, were also of
great significance. The church music of
eighteenth-century Kiev, for example, owed
much to the work of Bach and Palestrina,
just as the baroque masterpieces of the
Ukraine were appreciated in the west. In the
seventeenth and eighteenth centuries, Ukrai¬
nian scholars, artists and intellectuals
were not merely graduates, but also members
of many west European learned institu¬
tions.
Photo © Archives of the Cinematographic Museum, Kiev
" A still from Arsenal, a film made in 1929 by the great Ukrainian film director Dovchenko. The
leading role of Timoche was played by actor S. Svachenko.
Nevertheless, the development of certain
cultural forms in the Ukraine may be seen as
a direct and linear progression from simple
origins in folklore towards more complex
structures. In music, popular melodies,
romances and accompaniments to dramatic
performances serve as sources for
sophisticated "choral works, operas and sym¬
phonies; this may be seen, for example, in
the work of the composer Lysenko. The
same development may be observed in the
Ukrainian theatre, which between the 1880S
and the first decade of the twentieth century
was already being transformed from an ac¬
tivity of amateurs, conducted for the most
part by troupes of actor-serfs, into one of
the country's leading art forms.
The prestige of the Ukrainian theatre at
the turn of the century owed much to the ac¬
tress Maria Zankovetskaya (1860-1934),
whose natural delivery, devoid of any
"theatricality" led critics to compare her
favourably with such outstanding per¬
formers as Ermolova, Sarah Bernhardt and
Eleonora Duse. "Awesomely powerful",
was how Chekhov described her. Like
Krushelnitskaya, another actress whose
celebrity extended to western Europe,
Zankovetskaya portrayed the best
characteristics of Ukrainian women.
Kiev also played an important role in the
development of other art forms. The city's
name is associated, for example, with the
work of a number of outstanding authors of
the late nineteenth and early twentieth cen¬
turies. These include the prose-writer Maria
Vilinskaya (pseudonym, Marko Vovchok),
whose homely stories enjoyed wide
popularity among south Slav and western
European readers in the 1860s; Nechuya-
Levitsky, one of the creators of the socially-
centred and historical novel in the Ukraine;
and Larisa Kosach (1871-1913), who, under
the name of Lesa Ukrainka, was the greatest
woman poet of the Slav world. Setting her
creative activity in the context of the
people's struggle for freedom, she was also
the author of fiery political tracts, lyrical
declarations and a number of dramatic
works in which, taking part in the quest for
new dramatic forms that was being con¬
ducted all over Europe, she used themes
from the history and culture of ancient
peoples as the vehicle for portraying burning
issues of the day, and contrasted the pas¬
sionate human impulse towards freedom
with the narrow-minded passivity of
bourgeois life.
Shevchenko's successor as a humanist
and reformer of the Renaissance type was
Ivan Franko (1856-1916), who lived in the
western Ukrainethen part of the Austro-
Hungarian empirebut who maintained
close contact with the literary and scientific
community of Kiev. Franko's contribution
was a dual one: he created popular
awareness of the leading achievements of
world culture; and at the same time applied
his own wide-ranging talents to the produc¬
tion of literary masterpieces and penetrating
studies in a great variety of intellectual
fields. His works, which found an ap¬
preciative readership both in the Ukraine
and abroad, are currently being prepared in
a fifty-volume edition in Kiev.
After the October Revolution, Kiev was
confirmed as the political and cultural
capital of the Soviet Ukraine. The reunifica¬
tion in a single State of all the Ukrainian
lands released new creative energies, and
permitted a strengthening of the links bet¬
ween the Ukrainian and other national
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
iv cultures, including those of the other Soviet
republics.
Cultural relations with Russia became
particularly close. A new generation of
Ukrainian creators emerged, and the
cultural community of Kiev was enriched by
such personalities as the graphic artists Nor-
but and Kaspyan, the painters Krichevsky
and Yablonsky, the composers Lyatoshin-
sky and Bilash, the philologists Beletsky and
Krymsky, the educationist Sukhomlinsky
(one of the most outstanding theorists of the
time), the film director Dovzhenko, the ar¬
chitect Zabolotny and the sculptor
Kalchenko.
It was, however, in literary channels that
the new cultural current flowed most strong¬
ly. Pavlo Tychina (1891-1967) is rightly con¬
sidered to be the founder of Ukrainian
Soviet literature. This poet of the revolution
was above all an innovator, whose verse
reflected the synthesis of modern twentieth-
century poesy with its insistence on
musicality, emotional content, rhythm and
metaphor and the traditional modes of
popular song. Tychina's lyricism, and his
philosophical speculations, find fullest ex¬
pression in such works as Solnechnye
klarnety (The clarinets of the sun), Plug
(The plough), Veter s Ukrainy (Wind from
the Ukraine), Chuvstvo sem'i edinsi (The
sense of a united family), in poems like
Skovoroda (The frying-pan) and
Pokhorony druga (Burying a friend), and in
a number of tracts and pamphlets. The im¬
agery he uses is rich in colours drawn from
nature, and reflects human experience and
activity in all their variety.
Like Tychina, Maksim Rylsky
(1895-1964) initially worked in the tradi¬
tional "neo-classical" style adopted by Rus¬
sian and European poets during the first
quarter of the present century. This may be
seen in the collection Pod edinymy
zvegdami (Under the lonely stars). His later
verse takes on a more social, "civic" colour¬
ing; the moral, humanitarian and profes¬
sional concerns of people in Soviet society
are reflected in such works as Sbor
vinograda (Picking grapes), Goloseevskaya
osen' (Autumn in Goloseyev) and Zimnie
zapisi (Notes in winter), where fidelity to
classical forms is combined with a genuinely
innovative approach. Familiar with foreign
languages and literature, Rylsky produced a
number of brilliant translations and
penetrating analyses of poetry from other
countries, notably France and Poland.
The writer and film director Aleksandr
Dovchenko (1894-1956), who became inter¬
nationally famous, is rightly considered to
be one of the founders of the modern
cinema. Zemlya (Earth), Arsenal,
Ocharovannaya Desna (The enchanted
Desna), Poema o more (Poem of the sea)
and other films by Dovchenko are among
the world's great cinematographic master¬
pieces.
These are just a few episodes and ex¬
amples from the cultural history of ancient
and modern Kieva city set on gently roll¬
ing hills in a décor of luxuriant greenery; a
city graced, through the efforts of its peo¬
ple, with parks, stadiums, sculptures and
distinctive, unique architecture, laid out on
the banks of the blue-grey, endlessly flowing
Dnieper ... G rigory Verves
16
Above, The Mummers, one of the most famous frescoes of the
Cathedral of St. Sophia, Kiev (see article).
MUMMERS
AND MUSIC
OF KIEV-RUS
by Sergei Vissotsky
ON the wall of the staircase leading to the organ loft of
the cathedral of St. Sophia, in Kiev, is the great
"mummers' fresco". It depicts dancers, one with a
scarf in his hand, accompanied by a group of seven musi¬
cians. One is playing the flute, another is beating cymbals.
Two others on the right are playing the trumpet, the lute
and the psaltery. In the centre is an organ to the left of
which the blowers are pressing on the bellows with all their
might in order to fill the instrument with air, while at the
right the organist himself can be seen.
Mummers had a distinct position among the professional
musicians of ancient Russia. They went from town to town
and village to village, performing at markets, fairs and
festivals. These versatile artists included in their ranks
dancers, acrobats, jugglers, bear handlers and exhibitors of
other trained animals.
Old Russia had many musical instruments: wind in¬
struments such as the zurna or suma (which resembled the
oboe), the pipes and the flute; plucked string instruments
-like the gusli (a cousin of the psaltery), the lute, and the
mandora; string instruments played with the bow, such as
the rebeck; percussion instruments such as the tambourine,
the drum, the kettledrums and the cymbals. And to judge
SERGEI ALEXANDROVICH VISSOTSKY, of the Ukrainian SSR, is a
historian and a specialist in the culture of ancient Russia. He is the doyen
of the Archaeological Institute of the Ukrainian Academy of Sciences.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
from the fresco of St. Sophia, the organ should be added to
their number.
The invention of the organ, which was already known to
the ancient Egyptians, is usually attributed to the Greek
engineer Ctesibius of Alexandria, who constructed a "water
organ" known as a hydraulis. The organ was a much-
admired instrument in Rome, where its devotees included
the Emperor Nero who both loved organ music and played
the instrument himself.
After the Roman Empire split into the empire of the east
and the empire of the west, the evolution of the organ and
its uses had a chequered fate. In Catholic western Europe,
organ music was introduced into the liturgy by an edict of
Pope Vitalian (d. 672), but for the Orthodox church the
organ was a pagan instrument. At Byzantium, the organ
found a place as a secular instrument, and it was used pre¬
eminently at great ceremonies of the imperial court. Two
Byzantine organs, with trumpeters and dancers are depicted
on the reliefs of the column of Theodosius the Great (the
column of Arcadius) at Constantinople.
The introduction of Christianity to Russia in 988 con¬
siderably strengthened Russia's economic and cultural links
with Byzantium, the most advanced State of the medieval
world. Some aspects of the ceremonial of the Byzantine
court gradually infused the customs of the Russian court. It
is very likely at this time that the organ appeared in Russia
and that it began to be used as an instrument of secular
music.
In addition to the depiction of the "mummers' fresco",
organ music is mentioned in the Paterikon of the Kiev-Crypt
Monastery, written in the first quarter of the thirteenth cen¬
tury, in which the resonance of organ music, accompanied
by other instruments, is described. "And thus it was", says
the author in conclusion, "for all those who played and
were joyful, as is customary before the prince."
«AWKAAAAVNffMUMni < KBÄ AfWbf t\±AiklMnaT'hi -TAAma
tÍMiVp« Hit AH ÛAÔKM /Klft'yXfcl pArAH-triw A t\(mmô
<7fL Jl
^ muH
This miniature from a 15th-century
manuscript depicts the princess Olga being
received, in 954, by Emperor Constantine
VII at Constantinople, where she was con¬
verted to Christianity. Thus well before its
official introduction by Vladimir the Great,
in 988, Christianity had already penetrated
into Kiev-Rus and the material and spiritual
development of the capital owed much to
its trade and cultural links with Byzantium.
The frescoes that adorn the walls of the two
towers of the west façade of the Cathedral
of St. Sophia (built by Yaroslav the Wise,
grandson of princess Olga) depict scenes of
court life at Constantinople. If the
chroniclers are to be believed, life at the
court of the grand princes of Kiev was very
similar. Left, detail from a fresco depicting
the hippodrome at Constantinople with the
Emperor's guests watching a chariot race.
Photos © S. Vissotsky, Kiev
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Henry I, 37th king of France (1031-1060).
Anna, second daughter of Yaroslav the Wise, prince of Kiev, who married
Henry I of France in 1049. j
FRANCE'S
UKRAINIAN QUEEN
by Sergei Vissotsky
THIS is the story of Anna, one of the daughters of Yaroslav
the Wise, prince of Kiev, as related in the ancient chronicles
of western Europe.
In 1098, Henry I Capet, king of France, sent a delegation to dis¬
tant Kiev to ask Yaroslav the Wise for the hand of his daughter
Anna. The delegation, which was surrounded by great pomp,
was headed, according to some sources, by Roger, bishop of
Chalons, and, according to others, by Gautier, bishop of Meaux,
accompanied by the court minister Gasselin de Chavignac.
Why, one may ask, did the king of France send these
dignitaries so far afield to the distant banks of the Dnieper, laying
them open to all the difficulties and dangers that beset travellers
on the highways and byways of Europe during the Middle Ages?
Could he not have found a bride in another European country
nearer home?
There were in fact good reasons for seeking a bride in distant
Russia, for Henry I's own father, Robert, had been excom¬
municated by the Pope for having married Bertha, his cousin four
CONTINUED PAGE 23
12th- or 13th-century
gold ceremonial head¬
dress of the kind worn
by Ukrainian noble¬
women. The pendants
shown at either side
contained aromatic
essences and are
typical of the Kievan
jeweller's art.
Colour page right
Examples of the skilled craftsmanship of
Ukrainian jewellers in the State of Kiev-Rus,
the two gold and enamelwork pendants
(above left) once formed part of a woman's
headdress (11th-13th centuries). Attached to
small chains or cords such ornaments contain¬
ed a piece of cloth soaked with fragrant oils.
They were often adorned with the forms of
bird-women (harpies), protective images
which seem to have been associated with fer¬
tility and family happiness. The work of an
11th- or 12th-century Georgian craftsman, the
small circular gold and enamel plaque
representing St. Theodore (below left) original¬
ly formed part of a book setting. Above right.
The Angel with Golden Hair, a 12th-century
icon now in the Leningrad Museum. Below
right, miniature of the Virgin of Pechersk is
from a masterpiece of Kievan art, the Psalter
of Gertrude (1078-1087).
Photos V. Zhtchenko © Historical Museum of the Treasures of the Ukraine SSR
Photos V. Morujenko © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
Photo © 0. Saidko, Kiev
Centre pages
4 3
OTT
The cathedral of St. Sophia built between 1017
and 1037 during the reign of Yaroslav the Wise,
is one of Kiev's oldest churches. Although its
architecture is based on the Byzantine
cruciform domed temple, it has features that
belong to the Kievan school of architecture,
notably the more elongated proportions of the
domes, the more marked stepped arrange¬
ment of masses, and the profusion of orna¬
ment. In its long history the cathedral has
undergone significant changes. Photo 1 shows
view of the apses of St. Sophia. Inside the
cathedral is a remarkable array of mosaics and
frescoes. Originally there were 640 square
metres of mosaics, of which some 260 square
metres have so far been uncovered. Shown
here, 3 monumental mosaic figures beneath
the central dome, all produced by the same
11th-century craftsman. The archangel Gabriel
(2) in the annunciation scene is depicted on the
pillar of the triumphal arch; the Virgin Orans (3)
above the high altar; and Christ Pantocrator,
the all-powerful (4) in the vault of the dome.
The association of mosaics and frescoes is a
typical feature of the churches of Kiev-Rus. In¬
tensity and lyricism still shine out from faces
of the St. Sophia frescoes, notably the 11th-
century portrait of St. Adrian (5). The 12th-
century church of St. Cyril is also noted for its
wonderful mural paintings dating from the
12th, 17th and 19th centuries. Over 800 square
metres have survived. The Angel Rolling
Heaven Into a Scroll {6) is a scene from the Last
Judgement which covers the whole surface of
the narthex wall.
Photo © Aurora Art Publishers, Leningrad
Photo © Aurora Art Publishers, Leningrad
Photo V. Moruienko © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
Photo © Aurora Art Publishers, Leningrad
Photo V. Morujenko © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
Photo Vadim Solovsky © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Colour page left
In addition to its splendid 12th-century murals
depicting the life of its patron saint, Kiev's
church of St. Cyril contains several 17th-
century frescoes including the tempera pain¬
ting of Father Superior Innocent Monastirsky
(above left). The portrait of Dmitry Dolgoruky
(above right) was painted in 1769 by Samuil,
who directed the painter's studio in the
monastery of St. Sophia. Typical of Ukrainian
Baroque, the work is today preserved in the
Ukraine Fine Arts Museum, Kiev. At the begin¬
ning of this century Ukrainian art became in¬
fluenced by Art Nouveau. The Family (below
right) by Fuodor Krichevsky is the central
panel of a triptych entitled Life (1923-1927).
Modern in theme and composition it belongs
nevertheless to the Ukrainian tradition in art,
its colours recalling those of Ukrainian em¬
broidery and carpets and the postures of the
figures evoking certain Ukrainian popular
dances. Just as Pushkin celebrated the simple
beauty of rural life and the natural grace of
country folk, the Ukrainian poet and painter
Taras Shevchenko (1814-1861) used his dual
talent to serve the cause of the humble and the
oppressed. In one of his early poems, which he
illustrated by a painting of 1842 (below left) he
told the tragic story of Katerina, a young
Ukrainian peasant girl who was seduced and
then abandoned by a dissipated nobleman.
After giving birth to a child she takes to the
roads and eventually commits suicide. Her son
becomes a beggar and the guide of a blind
kobzar ox wandering minstrel. This plea by the
poet for social justice and tolerance caused a
sensation, as did the painting which is now in
the Shevchenko Museum in Kiev.
Photo Vadim Solovsky © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
Photo V. Morujenko © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
Photo Naoumenko © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
Photo V Morujenko © Mistetsvo Publishers, Kiev
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18
times removed, and the king wished to avoid a similar fate.
Moreover, Russia under Yaroslav had become a very powerful na¬
tion and was held in high esteem throughout Europe. All the rul¬
ing families were therefore anxious to establish an alliance with
the royal house of Kiev. These were the reasons which caused the
envoys of the king of France to set off on their long journey.
One can well imagine the impression produced on the French
delegation by Kiev. With its huge earth ramparts surmounted by
oak palisades, the Golden Gate in stone with the gilded dome of
its church gleaming in the sunlight, and the deep moat that en¬
circled it, the city was a truly impregnable fortress.
Within the gates, the visitors were struck by the grandiose pro¬
portions of the city which contrasted with those of western Euro¬
pean towns at that time. The residential areas were not as densely
populated and consisted of many wooden houses surrounded by
gardens and orchards. All along the route followed by the French
envoys were innumerable churches and chapels, the rich mansions
of the boyars (nobles), towers and palaces. The streets were lined
with great crowds who greeted the Frenchmen with loud cheers.
The pealing of church bells added solemnity to the
occasion.
The procession advanced slowly along the main street until it
reached the square before the great cathedral of St. Sophia with
its golden dome. From the gates of the archbishop's palace a
group came out to meet them headed by the clergy, the
voyevodes (dignitaries) and the boyars. After the official recep¬
tions, religious services and other ceremonials customary on such
occasions in medieval times, the ambassadors were informed that
Yaroslav had consented to the marriage of his daughter Anna to
Henry I of France. And so Anna began preparing for the long
journey which was to change the course of her whole life. To
reach France she probably followed the trade route which linked
Russia with Europe passing through Cracow, Prague and
Regensburg.
The wedding of Henry I and Anna Yaroslavna took place on
14 May 1049 in Rheims cathedral. Anna Yaroslavna had three
sons: Philip, Robert and Hugo. The eldest, Philip, was crowned
king of France at the age of seven, during his father's lifetime.
Anna refused to become regent but remained at her son's side
to educate him and guide him in the affairs of State.
In a letter to Anna written in 1059, Pope Nicholas II praises her
intelligence and virtues and exhorts her to bring up her sons as
chaste and good men and to assist the king in his State duties.
After Henry I's death in 1060, Anna's name appears side by side
with that of Philip on many French State documents. Thus Philip
I's charter conferred on the abbey of Soissons in 1063 bears the
signatures of Anna and her son. On the charter, next to the king's
monogram, are the traces of a seal and two crosses probably
drawn by the young king. Beneath these crosses in Cyrillic letters
is the signature of the queen-mother, "Anna-Rina". She had at¬
tempted to transcribe the Latin "Anna Regina" in Slavonic
writing.
In the little provincial town of Senlis, about thirty miles from
Paris, Anna Yaroslavna founded the monastery of St. Vincent.
French chronicles link the creation of the monastery to a vow
made by the queen before the birth of her first son, Philip. Today,
a chapel in Senlis built in those far-off times still bears the name of
Anna Yaroslavna. A life-size statue of Anna was later placed near
the entrance with the inscription: "Anna of Russia, queen of
France, founder of the church in 1060".
After Henry I's death, Anna and her sons left Paris and took up
residence in Senlis. During this period of her life she was loved by
the powerful feudal lord Raoul II the Great, count of Crépy and
Valois. One day, when hunting in the forest of Senlis, Raoul ab¬
ducted Anna with her consent and married her soon after. But
their happiness was to be marred by great difficulties. For Alpora
of Brabant, the count's wife, appealed to the Pope who declared
the marriage of Raoul and Anna null and void. Despite this, Anna
Yaroslavna continued to live with Raoul at his family estate in
Valois up to his death in 1074. The last-known signature of Anna
on a French document dates from the year 1075.
B Sergei Vissotsky
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Document Yury Aseev © Archaeological mstitude, Ukraine Academy of Sciences, Kiev
CENTURIES
IN STONE
by Yury Aseev
Model at top of page shows how the
wooden buildings of lower Kiev, today
known as the "Podol", must have
looked in the 12th century. Above,
detail of a 10th-century log building. In
the 12th and 13th centuries the lower
city was the artisans' district, largely
inhabited by potters, smiths and
tanners.
THROUGHOUT its fifteen centuries
of history, Kiev has been one of the
most important centres of building
and architecture in the eastern Slav world.
The city's early architectural history is
difficult to decipher from the fragmentary
24
YURY SERGEIEVICH ASEEV, of the Ukrai¬
nian SSR, is a specialist in the history and theory
of architecture and has been awarded the Ar¬
chitecture Prize of the Ukrainian SSR.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Ukrainian Society for Friendship
and Cultural Links Abroad, Kiev
The construction of the stone
"Golden Gate" as part of the
wooden fortifications of the up¬
per city in the 11th century open¬
ed a new phase in the city's
development. Above, the Golden
Gate today, and (right) a reconst¬
itution of its original appearance.
Reconstitution and drawing © S. Vissotsky, Kiev
Cupolas of the cathedral of St.
Sophia dominate the skyline in
the heart of Kiev. Since it was
built in the 11th century the
cathedral has undergone many
alterations, notably during the
Baroque period. Although Byzan¬
tine in style, some of its architec¬
tural features are distinctively
Kievan. It contains an outstand¬
ing collection of mosaics and
frescoes (see colour pages). Left,
St. Sophia as it is today. Above, a
reconstitution showing its
original appearance.
evidence of early medieval chronicles and
the results of architectural investigations.
From the sixth to the ninth centuries, Kiev
was the chief town of the Polyany, an
eastern Slav tribe. It was endowed with
strongholds on the hills of Starokievsk
("Old Kiev") and Zamok ("Fortress")
which protected the settlements between
them. Its growth and intensive construction
really began when it became the capital of
the ancient State of Kiev-Rus, which united
the eastern Slav tribes.
As Kiev-Rus gained in strength, powerful
fortifications were built. Wood was the
time-honoured building material, and the
people of Kiev were carpenters who had
from time immemorial acquired the skills of
working wood, together with a feeling for
the beauty of wooden architecture. The
chief method was frame construction.
The chronicles and folklore tell of the pic¬
turesque appearance of these wooden
buildings (photos 1 and 2) and some of the
draughtsmen of the early eleventh century,
such as Miloneg and Jdan Nikola, are
known by name. However, it only became
possible to really imagine what old Kiev
must have looked like when, amazingly, old
dwellings and streets were discovered ten
metres below ground. in the Podol district
during the construction of the Kiev Metro in
the 1970s.
In 1037, a year after Prince Yaroslav the
Wise had routed Russia's Pecheneg
assailants near Kiev, reuniting the entire
country under the city's rule, a new phase
opened in its development. That year, a new
hilltop site was laid out, the 72-hectare
"Yaroslav's Keep", ringed with great walls
of wood and earth with the stone^built
Golden Gate (photos 3 and 4). Its cen¬
trepiece was the Cathedral of St. Sophia,
built between 1037 and 1044 and set amid a
number of other churches, monasteries and
palaces (photos 5 and 6). This architecture
recalls that of many buildings in Byzantium,
but the galleries running around the
cathedral, the two towers set intd the west
façade and above all the domes, attest to the
originality of Kiev's architects. The original
form of the cathedral remains in all its '
grandeur beneath the accretions, especially
baroque, of later centuries. Some 3,000
square metres of eleventh-century frescoes
and 260 square metres of mosaics of in¬
estimable artistic value have been stripped
of later additions and restored.
In the 1 130s a new and typically medieval
architectural style appeared in Kiev. Instead
of the Byzantine courses of stone and brick
(opus mixtum) that were characteristic of
the tenth and eleventh centuries, architects
turned to brick alone. Churches became
more static in composition. The traditional
structure was retained, but Romanesque
features were incorporated such as half-
columns on façades, narrow windows, and
ornamental arcading. The Church of St.
Cyril is a good example of this medieval
style.
The reunification of the Ukraine with
Russia in 1654 was followed by a new phase
of construction in stone. Building began
again in upper Kiev, and groups of
monumental structures rose in the Pechersk
and Podol districts. Using their own tradi¬
tional compositional devices, and stimulated
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
by their contacts with Russian experts,
Ukrainian architects developed a vivid na¬
tional style known as Ukrainian or Cossack
Baroque. The church of St. Cyril, built by
Ivan Grigorovich Barsky (photo 7) and the
Uspiensky cathedral are notable examples of
the architecture of this period, while an in¬
teresting example of a late seventeenth- and
early eighteenth-century residence is Peter
the Great's house in the Podol (photo 10).
The eighteenth century is the period of the
Baroque style in Kievan architecture. One
striking example that still stands is the bell-
tower of the Monastery of the Caves
(1731-1744), designed by I.G. Shedel
(photo 9). The four-tiered belfry soars to a
height of 96.5 metres, and when it was built
was the highest in Russia. The tower, the
tiers of which are adorned with groups of
Tuscan, Ionic and Corinthian columns, is
the epitome of classical severity. The
monastery buildings, like other structures of
eighteenth-century Kiev, were largely the
work of the monastery architect Stepan
Kovnir, who used traditional Ukrainian
features in his designs and in the moulding
of his façades (photo 8). Another great ar¬
chitect of eighteenth-century Kiev was Bar-
tolommeo Rastrelli, a noted example of his
work being the church of St. Andrew.
The Classical period, which begins in the
late eighteenth century, is chiefly associated
with the work of Andrey Melensky. For
thirty years from 1799, Melensky directed
building operations in Kiev. Among those of
his works which are notable for their poetic
inspiration are the rotundas on the Tomb of
Askold (photo 11) and in the Florovsk
Monastery (1820), and his column com¬
memorating the return of the Magdeburg
Law to Kiev (1808). Besides Melensky, a
major role in Kievan architecture was played
by Vikenty Beretti, who built the University
of Kiev (1837-1843), a severe structure with
an eight-columned Ionic portico, dark-red
façade and black iron fittings (photo 12).
The early twentieth century saw major
stylistic changes in Kiev architecture.
Elements of eclecticism and Art Nouveau
appeared, the most original example of this
new trend being the house shown in
photo 14 in which the architect Vladislav
Gorodetsky gave free rein to his fondness
for animal motifs.
After the October Revolution rationalism
came to the fore in architecture. The Ukrai¬
nian Council of Ministers building
(photo 13), designed by Ivan Fomin and
Pavel Abrosimov, is particularly represen¬
tative of Kievan architecture in the 1930s.
Kiev suffered greatly during the Second
World War. The city centre was destroyed
by the Hitlerite invaders, along with some 40
per cent of the city's housing. In 1945 the
great avenue known as the Kreshchatik lay
in ruins, the university was burnt out, and
many major buildings had been destroyed.
The chief architectural problem in the post¬
war years was to redevelop the Kreshchatik .
and to restore the central districts nearby.
Since then Kiev has acquired many new
buildings, especially in the new districts.
Whether by building or by restoration work,
the architects who are developing modern
Kiev are vigilantly protecting the urban
fabric that the centuries have formed.
Yury Aseev
26
I
^B^~ «
ir ^ ^ m
%
ta
The church of St. Cyril (left) was
built around 1146 in upper Kiev.
Since extensively restored, it is
today a fine example of Ukrainian
baroque.
Photo © Ukrainian Society for Friendship
and Cultural Links Abroad, Kiev
The Lavra (as great monasteries
were usually called) of Pechersk
is a remarkable architectural
ensemble which took shape over
9 centuries. Above, engraving by
Averi Kozachovski (1728) shows
the monastery's Cathedral of the
Assumption (1073-1078) which
was destroyed during the Second
World War. The bell-tower (right)
built between 1731 and 1744, sur¬
vived and is in a good state of
preservation. The octagonal
structure is 95.5 metres high.
Photo © Aurora Publishers, Leningrad
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
An example of Ukrainian Baroque, this house was built for Peter the
Great at the end of the 17th century and rebuilt in the mid-18th.
Askold's grave, erected in 1809-1810 to a design by A.I. Melensky is
an example of the 19th-century classical style (although the upper
colonnade was added in 1936). Askold was a prince of Kiev who died
in combat in 882.
The university of Kiev (1837-1842) by V.l. Beretti. Late Classical style. The Ukraine SSR Council of Ministers building (1935-1938) was
designed by I.A. Fomin and P.V. Abrosimov.
Crowned with strange creatures, this Art Nouveau house (1901-1902)
was designed by the architect V.V. Gorodetsky.
Photos © Taras Chablovski, Kiev
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
A HUNDRED YEARS
OF JAMES JOYCE
by Anthony Burgess
ANTHONY BURGESS is a prolific British writer of novels and non-fiction who is
currently at work on his 45th book. His long-standing interest in James Joyce, who
has strongly influenced his work, led him to write a study which was published in
the United States under the title Re Joyce (Norton, 1965) and in the UK as Here
Comes Everybody (Faber 1965). He is also the editor ofA Shorter Finnegans Wake
(Faber, 1965; Viking, 1967). A composer as well as a writer, his Broadway musical
version of Ulysses, The Blooms of Dublin, was presented on the centenary of
Joyce's birthday, 2 February 1982.
Above, Joyce photograph¬
ed in 1938, three years
before his death.
Right, portrait of the artist
as a young man. Joyce
was 22 years old when this
photo was taken by his
Dublin friend C.P. Curran
in 1904, a crucial year in the
great author's life. It was
16 June 1904 that he chose
as what is known as
"Bloomsday" (the day on
which the events of his
novel Ulysses take place),
and in October of that year
he took the decisive step
of leaving Ireland to settle
in Trieste. - Asked later
what he was thinking
when Curran photograph¬
ed him, Joyce replied: "I
was wondering would he
lend me five shillings."
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
QRAFT0trST.DUBi-l*l.~r03.Vl.t.. t?
Text © Copyright: Reproduction prohibited Photo Lawrence Collection © National Library, Dublin
LET me begin by assuming, or perhaps
merely pretending, that you do not
know anything about James Joyce.
If you already know something, you are
welcome to yawn over the following basic
information. James Joyce was an Irishman
born in Dublin on 2 February 1882. Other
great writers have been born in the Irish
capital, including Oscar Wilde, Bernard
Shaw and Samuel Beckett, to say nothing of
the great poet William Butler Yeats. But it is
usual for a great Dublin writer to be Protes¬
tant, while James Joyce was a Catholic.
Dublin, though the capital of a Catholic
country, had been a British colonial capital
for so long that the religion of the Church of
England was the religion of the educated,
the rulers, the upper class, the Dublin
establishment. Joyce was not of the upper
class, which is another way of saying that he
was a Catholic.
He was educated by Jesuits, who have
always provided the most thorough and
rigorous education of all the Catholic
teaching bodies, and it was intended that he
should become a Catholic priest. But in his
late adolescence he decided to rebel against
everything that he had been taught was
holythe Catholic Church, the holy land of
Ireland, the Irish language, the struggle for
Irish independence from the imperial
British, and even the close bonds of the
family. When his mother was dying he
refused to kneel down and pray for her.
"I do not think any writer has yet
presented Dublin to the world," Joyce
wrote in 1905. Although he never returned
to Ireland after a visit in 1912, the people
and places of his native city remained the
raw material of his art. His portrayals of
Dublin life reveal meticulous attention to
detail. Above, period photo of Grafton
Street which, in Ulysses, "Gay with hous¬
ed awnings lured [Bloom's] senses.
Muslin prints, silk, dames and Dowagers,
jingle of harnesses hoofthuds lowringing
in the baking causeway."
Losing his faith in country, family, and
religion, he sought a new faith a faith in
art. He became one of the first writers in the
English language to regard the making of
literature as a religious activity. The poet or
the novelist was a kind of priest. His task
was to take ordinary everyday experience
and convert it into the shining material of
art. This is very like the priest's taking bread
and turning it into the body and blood of
Jesus Christ the central act of the celebra¬
tion of the Catholic mass.
He left Ireland in 1904, together with an
illiterate girl who had been working as a ser¬
vant in a Dublin hotel, and went to teach
English in Trieste, the Adriatic port which
used to be part of the Austro-Hungarian
Empire but which is now part of Italy. There
Italian became the language of his home and
the first language of his children. These
childrenGiorgio and Luciawere il
legitimate, since Joyce refused to be mar¬
ried. Marriage was a Catholic sacrament,
and he had rejected Catholicism. When the
war of 1914-18 broke out, he removed his
family to Zürich in neutral Switzerland. At
the end of that war he took them to Paris,
where he lived for the rest of his working
life.
In 1940, with all his books written and a
new war raging, he sought refuge in Zürich
again, and in the following year he died. By
this time he was regarded as the most daring
experimental writer in the world. Forty-one
years after his death he is considered to be
one of the great classical writers like
Dante, Shakespeare and Goethe. Why?
Joyce wrote very few books. He produced
two little volumes of undistinguished verse,
a mediocre stage play, and three novels. The
first novel is called A Portrait of the Artist
as a Young Man and is about the author's
own upbringing in Catholic Dublin. It is
remarkable for the brilliance of its writing
and for the frankness with which Joyce
displays the growth of a young mind and
body, with all the sexual and moral prob¬
lems which a sensitive young Irish Catholic
might be expected to suffer. Joyce found it
extremely difficult to have this novel ac¬
cepted by a publisher. No publisher could
understand this new way of writing, and the
candour of its revelations was too much for
that non-permissive age the period of the
First World War. In 1922 Joyce produced
his great masterpiece Ulysses, and it is this
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
When Henri Matisse agreed to illustrate Ulysses in 1934 for a special
American edition, Joyce went to great lengths to make sure that he
got the Irish details right. However, Matisse went his own way.
When asked why his drawings bore so little relation to the book he
frankly admitted that he had not read it. He had based them on
Homer's Odyssey. Above, Matisse's lithograph of the Nausicaa
episode.
I* h*-+i*lt**¿¡-
Joyce drawn by the Rumanian
sculptor Constantin Brancusi.
Photo © Lockwood Memorial Library, State University
of New York at Buffalo, USA
Joyce himself drew this caricature of the hero of Ulysses, Leopold
Bloom, in the 1920s. The Greek text is the opening of Homer's
Odyssey "Tell me. Muse, of the man of many devices..."
book which has ensured his acceptance
as the greatest novelist of the twentieth
century.
We must note one curious fact. When
Joyce left Ireland in 1904 he determined
never to return, and he never did, except for
two very brief visits to Dublin. He lived all
his life as an exile from his native city and
yet he wrote about nothing but the people of
that city. Ulysses is a very long book, and
yet it restricts itself to the activities of a
single day in Dublin16 June 1904. It has a
hero, whose name is Leopold Bloom. He is
half-Jewish and he works as an advertising
canvasser for a newspaper which still exists
called The Freeman's Journal. An advertis¬
ing canvasser is a man who persuades shops
and other business enterprises to place
advertisements in newspapers. Bloom is
married to an Irishwoman brought up in
Gibraltar. Her name is Molly and she is a
well-known Dublin singer, and she is also
unfaithful to her husband. At four o'clock
in the afternoon she commits adultery with
Blazes Boylan, the man who is going to take
charge of her forthcoming tour of Ireland in
a series of song recitals. She and Bloom live
together, but something has gone wrong in
their marriage. They had a little son called
Rudy or Rudolph (after Bloom's father),
and he died a few days after his birth. They
both feel guilty about this, though it is
nobody's fault, and they are shy of sex.
Bloom has a strong desire to be the father of
a son. What happens on 16 June 1904 is that
he finds a son.
This son is James Joyce himself at the age
of twenty-two, under the guise of a young
poet named Stephen Dedalus. Stephen
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Joyce worked for over 16
years on his last book Fin¬
negans Wake, "a night view
of man's life", which was
published in May 1939. As its
composition went ahead, he
published parts of the new
novel in magazines under
the title "Work in Progress."
Below, page proof, heavily
corrected by Joyce, of part
of* "Work in Progress"
prepared for publication in
the avant-garde literary
review transition. Right,
Aux Fenêtres du Fleuve ("At
the windows of the river",
1972) is a work by the French
artist Jean Lancri inspired
by the letters of "Riverrun",
the first word of Finnegans
Wake.
Photo © Jean Lancri, Meaux
spends the evening getting drunk in the
brothel district of Dublin. Bloom is worried
about him and tries to extricate him from a
fight with two British soldiers. He has, in
other words, a paternal attitude towards
him. He takes him home, gives him a cup of
cocoa, and suggests that he take up lodgings
with the Blooms. We don't know whether
Stephen does or not. The book ends before
anything is decided. All we know is that
contact has been made between an ordinary
Dublin man who, because he is half-Jewish,
feels himself to be a stranger in a Catholic
city, and a young Irish intellectual. Molly
Bloom, of course, dreams of taking Stephen
as a lover. A new pattern of relationships is
being formed in three lives, and that is what
the book is about.
It is not much of a story, you will say.
Nothing much happens. It is not a spy
thriller or a tale of love. But what it certainly
is is a representation of human life as it is
really lived. Joyce has invented a technique
known as the interior monologue, which lets
us into the minds of his characters and
allows us to hear their innermost thoughts
and desires. As some of these desires are sex¬
ual, and are expressed very frankly, Ulysses
got into trouble with the -state censors of
various countries, and there are still coun¬
tries where you can't get hold of the book.
There is no reticence at all in the kind of
language the characters use in their thinking
and feeling, and this frankness still shocks
readers more accustomed to romances and
thrillers than to true literature. After all, it is
the duty of literature to tell the truth about
life, and Joyce took this duty with extreme
seriousness.
of bad Friday. Never l> t hog of Un Ufil trample undi ¡loot yotK.
Uly of kiUarney Si vei play lady'« gain** fur the Lord'« »take. Vv«>r>
lose your heart away till you win rúyíjimnuiid l»a< k. Make a -troni;
int of nevt-r kicking up your rompu* in Mi.' J^m Bfy C.oll t>y
Offro/xjs Rungs at,¿ommrrc¡a! trav. lleiV s:n< I i
^__Ü»« <lj»luml>Ig)K nijjhi« pDt«HatHmrnt9 tl*> lik<. of Whit' limln
Oiry noter stop loiïiug. Antf. bv OmM**-**- +t -ymr"tT«'<
U Hin and I hrnjUnuW» "nVrñfííig in I he boT-tjfrirel tli"
" t-TwIcr tlmu «Thtlt not low. I.usl. tliou ^hal< no! i :,
Mevel parle your "brief slays in the men*!, co
ITTTnoi hiilhiiirihr villi your dirty j.» rX buwr
k \»ix Jirst |H'rv.rN^uiijuJùja^i>w* t'y/ .alt pía-
IM »ihrer key throuJtívour (¡ale of «¡il. n «ge. Never / ,
thin i» in HiMl.t/r .pKMv hrwiie ^Uf^MMM
,ome life, Tlii t
jdrlt Itliidarlmrt
'
(TUA ifM.^1
. s,
\r\A-dh>jè,
tKA*-á- yL^,xJi
rvuue \h
any liemondte
ixoÜeci the peril", dial la
© ,
ufa one they j^jct hobbybonica I |
feshroloured panto» iiisladynVtryinj; In
member fbf bitef*« bill'
*¿S&*£
boH theWrtmTTfl ,
,*i^
>**?, 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
But Ulysses is much more than a truthful
account of the innermost thoughts and
desires of a group of Dubliners. The title
refers to the hero of an epic poem by the an¬
cient Greek poet Homer, the Odyssey,
which tells of the adventures of Odysseus, as
the Greeks call him, or Ulysses, as the rest of
us call him, in his attempts to return to his
native island of Ithaca after the Trojan
wars. Ulysses meets giants and nymphs,
magic, storms, enchantments, but he comes
through intact and unharmed through the
exercise of strong will and cunning. In
Joyce's book Leopold Bloom is a modern
Ulysses, all of whose encounters during his
Dublin day are humorously exact counter¬
parts of the adventures of his heroic
prototype.
Joyce is trying to show us that the or¬
dinary man can be heroic, that modern life
is as strange and dangerous as the life
depicted in the ancient epicsbut he shows
us this very comically. Ulysses is a book that
makes us laugh. If Bloom, the new Ulysses,
has comic adventures, the language in which
the book is written has comic adventures
too. Words behave strangely. Other books
are imitated or parodied. One very long
chapter is presented in the form of a fan¬
tastic play, another is a monologue without
punctuation, yet another tries to imitate a
piece of music. This sounds difficult, but it
is really funny, lively and heartening. Joyce
took big risks, as a great author should, but
he produced a big success the most
original novel of the century.
In 1939, just before the outbreak of the
Second World War, Joyce produced his last
book, on which he had spent seventeen
years of hard labourmade all the harder
by increasing difficulty of sight: his eyes
were diseased, and the disease was probably
the result of privation in his early days. The
book is called Finnegans Wake an un¬
translatable title. The word wake means to
be aroused from sleep, but it also means the
Irish custom of holding a drinking party
ES32ES
itf?.Tyjtii
Asked whether Finnegans Wake were a blending of literature and music,
Joyce replied, "No, it's pure music." "But are there not levels of mean¬
ing to be explored?" "No, no" said Joyce, "it's meant to make you
laugh."
over the corpse of a recently deceased
member of the family. Finnegan is the name
of a mythical Irish giant, but it is also the
name of the hero of a New York Irish
song Tim Finnegan, who falls from his
ladder drunk, who appears to be dead, who
has a wake held over his body, but who
springs back to life when a gallon of whisky
is splashed on to him. What Joyce is doing
here is giving us a story of death and resur¬
rection, but all in the form of a dream.
In Ulysses Joyce had exhausted the
literary possibilities of presenting the human
day. In Finnegans Wake he turns to the
human night. His hero, whose name is Ear-
wicker, is an innkeeper in Dublin who goes
to sleep after a busy Saturday night serving
beer and whisky to his customers. In his
dream he re-enacts the whole of human
history, which is always about human sin.
But human sin presupposes human energy,-
and the great sinners, from Adam and Eve
to Adolf Hitler, have all been concerned
with building new human societies. Man
falls, but man's fall is cyclical, and in a circle
to fall is also to rise again. Human history is
circular, in that the same things. recur over
and over again, and Earwicker's dream, in
which he takes the roles of all the great
figures of history and myth, has no beginn¬
ing and no end. What makes Finnegans
Wake an exceptionally difficult book is the
language in which it is written.
Joyce believed that the language of dream
should be a universal language, because
dreaming man transcends nationality and
the national language he has been taught to
speak. So Joyce fabricated an appropriate
idiom for his universal dream by taking all
the languages of Europe and mixing them
together. His language is appropriate to a
kind of mad Unesco, because you find Ger¬
man, French, Italian and Spanish jostling
with the Slav and Scandinavian tongues but
all united under the banner of English syn¬
tax. It is not surprising that the book has
never been wholly translated, for how do
you translate a universal language? tIt
already contains its own translations. What
sounds impossibly difficult is, in fact, very
funny and often very moving. But you have
to spend a good deal of your life studying
the book. I have been reading it for the last
forty-three years, and I am still puzzled by a
great deal of it. If I live long enough, I shall
perhaps understand it all. We may grumble
at the book, but we cannot deny that it was
written by a brilliant and ingenious writer in
love with language and equally in love with
humanity.
It is Joyce's originality and courage we
celebrate in this centenary year of his birth.
He himself celebrated ordinary people, the
suffering and humorous citizens of a
modern city, and on them he poured the
riches of history and language. He is the
greatest comic writer of the age, and the on¬
ly novelist who has ever brought the art of
words close to the art of music. Though dim
of sight he had a superb ear and, incidental¬
ly, a superb tenor voice. No one who loves
books can ignore him. As for those who,
like myself, write books, we regard him as
our master, the mad Irishman who taught us
to take our art seriously, the sane Irishman
who showed us what human beings are real¬
ly like. H Anthony Burgess
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Aerial view of the Great Mosque at Cordoba in southern Spain. Founded around 784 AD, it is one of the
oldest mosques in Islam. The harmony and grandeur of the mosque was disturbed in the 16th century
when the Christian kings of Spain built a Renaissance-style cathedral within its walls.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Pans
THE POETS
OF MUSLIM SPAIN
THE extent to which Muslim civili¬
zation can in substance be regarded
as completely original has long been
a matter of controversy among oriental
scholars. One thing however is certain,
throughout its existence its outward forms
and manifestations have always borne the
indelible, unmistakable stamp of Islam. A
carpet has nothing to do with Islam, and yet
a "Muslim carpet" can be recognized a
thousand miles away. A garden may have
EMILIO GARCIA GÓMEZ, former Spanish
ambassador to a number of Arab countries, is a
member of the Royal Spanish Academy and Pro¬
fessor Emeritus of the University of Madrid.
Director of the celebrated review Al-Andalus for
fifty years, he has written on almost every aspect
ofArab civilization. His major works are devoted
to the history, literature and poetry of Muslim
Spain.
by Emilio García Gómez
nothing in common with Islam, but a
"Muslim garden", like that of the
Generalife in Granada, is in its very essence
Islamic. Nevertheless, poetry, which Islam
inherited not so much from other civiliza¬
tions as from "Arabism", from the times of
"anti-Islamic" darkness (jahiliyya)", must
be considered a special case.
There is a sura in the Qur'an, the "sura of
the poets", which is not exactly complimen¬
tary to them and taxes them with being "im¬
postors". It is true that this can be con¬
strued in rhetorical terms as defining the
"unreality" and "conventions" inherent in
any lyric poetry. In any event, the Prophet
finally admitted the claims of poetry and
even had his own official praise-singers.
Poetry, the "archive of the Arabs" (diwan
al Arab), was adopted by Islam. It is
likewise true that, much later, purely
religious poetry of ascetic or mystical con¬
tent developed, some of it very striking. But
most interesting of all, to my mind, is the
"Muslim stamp" that has indubitably been
left on the most outstanding secular poetry,
even in its most frivolous and indeed at
times spiritually daring aspects. A "Muslim
poem" is Muslim to the core and could not
be anything else.
The most inviting field of research for the
study of the "Islamization" of poetry is that
of the non-Arab countries penetrated by
Islam, setting aside the case of Persia, where
an altogether different phenomenon occur¬
red in that the local language continued to
be used. We can confine ourselves to Mus¬
lim Spain (al-Andalus) where, although bil-
ingualism was current up to the end of the
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
For several centuries after its con¬
quest by the Arabs in 711, Cordoba
was the capital of al-Andalus,
Muslim Spain, and a major centre of
art and culture. It grew to be a city of
250,000 inhabitants, with a university
and a great mosque, and flourishing
political and commercial life. It was
the birthplace of major writers and
philosophers such as Ibn Tufail,
Averroes and Maimonides, and of
the two greatest poets of al-Andalus,
Ibn Hazm, the author of "The
Necklace and the Dove", and Ibn
Quzman. Left, arches and columns
in the great mosque. Below, another
view of the mosque: interlaced
arches in the mihrab antechamber.
century, the local language did not
gain the upper hand and poetry, not¬
withstanding certain regional idiosyncracies,
is undoubtedly Islamic. There was, of
course, specifically religious poetry, from
Al-Ilbiri to Ibn 'Arabi or the mystical zéjeles
of Shushtari, but the main secular current is
so "Muslim" that, together with architec¬
ture, Arab-Andalusian poetry can be
regarded as being one of the main specific
creations of al-Andalus.
Here again, an original and important
feature can be seen in the existence of this
poetry side-by-side with indigenous poetry
in Spanish Romance language. These two
types of poetry Arabic and Romance-
were originally unaware of one another's ex¬
istence, although they eventually came to
blend into new styles. But no sooner had
they done so than they went through a pro¬
cess firstly of "adaptation" and then of "re-
absorption". No matter how cursory the
analysis of these Andalusian developments,
they bear fascinating witness to the deep-
rooted "Islamization" of Arab poetry in all
the countries in which it was introduced.
In every civilization or language,
literature has always begun with poetry
rather than with prose, and this accounts for
the importance of the place occupied by
poetry. In Arabic literature, however, it per¬
forms an even more essential function
because, like the poetry of Homer in
Greece, it was already perfect when it first
came into being and, in a civilization
without any epic tradition, plastic arts or
drama, it had to act as a substitute for all
those forms (inasmuch as they can be liken¬
ed to Western models) and to serve a whole
range of purposes, from political propagan¬
da to love letters.
In Muslim Spain, Arabic poetry in its
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
r / - - Jit /. :
The poetry of "courtly love" composed by the medieval
troubadours of France, Italy and Spain was probably inspired in
part by the music and love poetry of al-Andalus. The great Arab-
Andalusian poets such as Ibn Hazm and Al-Mu'tamid, King of
Seville, presented in their work a "platonic" conception of love,
while the structure of the poems of the troubadours bears a curious
resemblance to that of the Hispano-Arabie zéjel, notably in its four-
lined verses. Above and below left, two scenes from The Story of
Bayad and Riyad, a tale of courtly love originating in eastern Islam,
are depicted in a 13th-century manuscript which may have been
produced in al-Andalus. Below, troubadours are shown playing the
lute, an instrument of Arab origin (al-lud) in a 13th-century
manuscript of the Cantigas de Santa Maria by the Spanish king
Alfonso X the Wise, a noted patron of the troubadours.
Photo © Library of the Monastery of the Escurial, Spam
'¿Ju> ¿lit u j] 3^..¿¿í£2, ixj¿Uj ¡4Ly¿¿sA
Photos © Babey © Ziolo, Paris
most consummate form probably came to
the country with the first military con¬
tingents and was cultivated, for better or for
worse, by all educated men. To cite only a
few names, Gazal, Ramadi, Ibn Hani, Ibn
Abd Rabbih, Ibn Shukhais, Mushafi and
Ibn Darraj all mark different phases in its
development. When the diwan of Mutanab-
bi reached Spain at the beginning of the
tenth century, it became an established form
and subsequently assumed a tone that has
come to be known as "neo-classical".
It may be asked whether this poetry can
be compared with that of Islam in the Near
East. Indeed it can, but not in all respects. It
still continues to be "provincial" in outlook
although distinguished in tone and, more¬
over, it is still too dependent on Baghdad. It
was only towards the end of the Caliphate of
Cordoba, in the latter years of the tenth cen¬
tury, that two leading writers, Ibn Shuhaid
and Ibn Hazm, seemed intent on giving it a
Hispanic flavour and on raising it to a level
comparable with that of the Near East in
both form and intellectual content. But the
civil war (fitna) was to put paid to those
hopes.
The eleventh century, during the reign of
the taifas (princelings who carved up Arab
Spain after the fall of the Caliphate of Cor-
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
doba in 1040), was to be its "Golden Age",
although the standards reached were per¬
haps lower than those maintained by Ibn
Shuhaid and Ibn Hazm, they were, to my
mind, still very high, considering the new
perspectives they opened up and the very
large number of skilful practitioners, of
whom we need mention only two: Ibn Zai-
doun and Al-Mu'tamid, king of Seville.
This new and splendid resurgence went in¬
to decline again with the arrival of the two
African dynasties. In the first half of the
twelfth century under the Almorávides (the
Muslim sect and dynasty that ruled over
Morocco and part of Algeria and Spain
from 1055 to 1 147), Andalusian Arab poetry
lapsed into decadence, except in the region
of Valencia, although, curiously enough,
given the period and what was happening in
other Muslim countries, it was "aware" of
its predicament and grieved over it. This was
the time when the great anthologies were
compiled.
From the mid-twelfth to the mid-
thirteenth centuries under the Almohades
(the dynasty that overthrew the
Almorávides) poetry took on a fresh lease of
life and assumed a solemn and majestic
tone, with the exception of a few admirable
intimate cameos. Finally, towards the end of
the fifteenth century, the collapse was com¬
plete. The technical pattern for lyric poetry
continued to be perfect, but its soul had
fled. At best, it was decorative. Thus it was
that perhaps its last representative genius,
Ibn Zamrak, ended up by decorating the
walls of the Alhambra, in the most lux¬
urious poetry edition history has ever
known. It was to die a noble death gracing
the walls of the palace.
All that has been preserved of Andalusian
Arab poetry are a number of personal
diwans, far fewer than those in the Near
East. We know them through anthologies
and sometimes relatively short fragments.
This fragmentation is due to the rules of
Arabic rhetoric, which seldom allow verses
to run on, so that they each contain a com¬
plete encapsulated thought or at least a
whole grammatical sentence. It is poetry
reduced to a fine multi-coloured dust that
sparkles like diamonds. Since the effect of
the fragmentation was naturally to single
out the best and to discard the dross, we are
left with a set of prodigious verbal Alham-
bras, in which the most striking features are
feeling and passion or, in some instances,
novelty and sensibility, but seldom intellec¬
tual precision.
Virtually all poetic forms were employed.
The most beautiful metaphors gradually
became commonplace, to the point that they
could be said to be stereotyped. They obey
the law of "diminishing gradation": men
compared to animals, animals to flowers,
flowers to precious stones, and so on. A
tulip, for instance, becomes a ruby. As time
went on, the rhetoric became stilted and
fossilized and created a rather ponderous ef¬
fect. However, since this poetry died out
earlier in Spain than in other Muslim coun¬
tries, it did not know the sterile decay of old
age.
In this first example Ibn Hazm speaks in a
modern pre-Freudian vein of the ghostly
spirit of his loved one:
36
/ must needs know what it is and how
it came.
Was it the face of the Sun? Or was
it the Moon?
Was it a pure and rational idea?
Or was it the. image conjured up by
thought?
Was it a ghostly spirit forged of illusions
that seemed to take on. flesh before
my eyes?
Ibn Zaidoun, in his celebrated poem
about absence (nuniyya), evokes his loved
one, the princess Wallada:
None could tell that we lay together
attended only by our love,
accomplices of the complaisant morning
star
with eyelids sealed from prying eyes:
concealed in the bosom of darkness,
like- two secrets
risking
betrayal from the lips of the dawn.
Al-Mu'Tamid, king of Seville, wrote the
following epitaph for himself:
With their endless weeping, the clouds
moisten the soft earth, Oh tomb of exile
enveloping the remains of King Ibn
Abbad.
By his side you station in attendance
three illustrious virtues:
wisdom and grace and mercy.
And fertile plenty, come to root out
famine, and water for times of drought.
But perhaps the culminating point of the
descriptive ease and epicurean elegance
represented by the Valencian school is to be
found in Ibn al-Zaqqaq:
She came in the dead of night, her shade
jet-black like her hair.
Goblets ofpure wine she tendered me,
with their aromatic perfume.
Yet another beverage was pressed upon
me by her eyes and lips.
Three times Ifell inebriate: from the
goblet,
from her mouth and from her
dark eyes.
This being said, it should be added that
Andalusian Arab poetry also displayed a
very surprising feature in that, alongside its
"classical" form, there existed popular
verses that are generally acknowledged as
being a typically Andalusian invention.
In the thirteenth century, the Tunisian en¬
cyclopaedist Tifashi, drawing on very old
traditions, wrote that "In olden times, the
songs of the people of al-Andalus were
either in the Christian style or else in that of
Arab camel-drovers".
Thus, two poetic styles existed side by side
and yet with their backs turned to each
other! However, at the end of the ninth cen¬
tury and the beginning of the tenth, they
were "merged" in a form devised by Mu-
qaddam Ibn Mu'afà Qabri, which was
known as the muwashshaha. Unlike the
qasida, this form consists of stanzas and has
a variety of rhymes. It is not possible to go
into details here, but the main feature is that
the poem was originally "based" on a
Christian couplet in the Romance language
of al-Andalus. Here is an example of one of
those couplets:
Komo sifiliyolo alieno
non más adormes a mew seno
Like another's child,
You no longer sleep at my breast
This short couplet, which was known as
the kharja, meaning ending or "envoi", was
set at the end of the poem. Fifty or more or
these couplets have been preserved in the
Romance language and, in spite of the con¬
troversy surrounding them or indeed
because of itthey are in the process of
revolutionizing studies into the origins of
this poetry.
As was to be expected, as a result of the
hostility voiced by the classicists, the earliest
muwashshaha have disappeared, but some
of them have come down to us from the
eleventh century, while others date from as
late as the end of the twelfth century. In the
course of the same two centuries, and again
on account of the hostility of the classicists,
the kharja eventually came to be written in
Arabic dialect or colloquial Andalusian.
The rest of the poem was in the classical
language, so that we have the two forms ex¬
isting side by side and merging.
The end of the eleventh century and the
early years of the twelfth saw the emergence
in al-Andalus of another important and
novel feature: the invention of the zejel or
zajal, which may have been conceived by the
philosopher and musician Ibn Bajja or
Avempace. The zejel is derived from the
muwashshaha, from which it differs in be¬
ing composed entirely in spoken Andalusian
Arabic, in being sometimes very long, and in
often dispensing with the kharja.
This form was relatively short-lived, for
only a few early and confused examples ex¬
ist, together with a number of not very strik¬
ing sequels in the work of only one great
poet, Ibn Quzman, who lived in the first
half of the twelfth century and from whom,
by chance, we have an almost complete
diwan.
To my mind, Ibn Quzman is the greatest
poet of Andalusian Arab literature,
classicists not excepted. It is a title which I
feel he deserves on the grounds of his in¬
novative sense, breaking as he did with
almost all the conventional subject-matter
of classical poetry, and of his originality, as
reflected in his deliberate use of the popular
language in a great work of art. Breaking
out of the classical mould, he displays in¬
comparable freshness and spontaneity, giv¬
ing free rein to his imagination in handling
themes that are remarkably close to those of
the novel or the theatre. Indebted to no one
and quite unlike anybody else, Ibn Quzman
is an authentic genius.
Emilio García Gómez
If the culture of al-Andalus reached its
zenith at Cordoba, it had a magnificent late
flowering at Granada, especially in the royal
palace of the Alhambra. This roundel of
stucco-work consisting of Arabic script is
one of several in the Sala de las Dos Her¬
manas (Hall of the Two Sisters) at the
Alhambra. The roundels are in fact poems
by Ibn Zamrak, the Granada vizier-poet who
was one of the last representatives of Arab-
Andalusian poetry. The verses here sing of
the beauty of the Alhambra: "The Twins
stretch out a friendly hand to her. And the
celestial moon whispers confidentially."
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
i
\ '
^ nri&O
r*
:v
fr\
«
f3*
\
C'
V.
í,
t'
N ,
v>
* «
»> -w
<
¿^.¿j
%-_»<
aí>
"» » # -_-.»,»
Photo Scaia f imán
7737
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
ffl UD m H
s
ï
Young people proclaim the
rights of the elderly
Over 350 persons, young and less young,
took part in a "Young people's human rights
da/' held at Unesco's Paris headquarters on
10 March. Unesco regularly organizes such
human rights days, which are connected to
a contemporary world problem. This year's
theme, "the rights of the elderly", is also
that of the United Nations World Assembly
on Aging which is being held in Vienna from
26 July to 6 August 1982. The young partici¬
pants strongly expressed their opinion that
there should be no barriers between the
generations and rejected the generalized
forms of discrimination of which both young
and old are victims. Many of the young par¬
ticipants drew a parallel between a country's
level of development and the extent to
which the integrity of the family was main¬
tained. "In the poor countries the old remain
in the bosom of the family", they pointed
out, "but when a country develops it increa¬
singly tends to abandon its old people". The
young people wrote a number of articles
taking into account the situation of elderly
persons and suggested that these articles be
added to the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights. A photo exhibition prepared
by Unesco in collaboration with some 30
national commissions and several internatio¬
nal non-governmental organizations presen¬
ted a vivid picture of old people in various
world regions.
Lebanon's literary treasures
on show at Unesco HQ
A 350-exhibit display, "Lebanon and the
Book", was held recently at Unesco's Paris
Headquarters. The exhibits ranged from
Phoenician inscriptions and ancient manu¬
scripts to books printed in Syriac and Arabic
from the 17th century on, and the first Leba¬
nese newspapers founded in the 19th cen¬
tury. Inaugurating the exhibition on behalf
of the Director-General, Mr. Chikh Bekri,
Assistant Director-General of Unesco,
stressed the outstanding contribution of
Lebanon to Mediterranean civilization and to
Oriental studies and pointed to the impor¬
tance of the exhibition in a year which marks
the 10th anniversary of International Book
Year and will see the World Congress of the
Book ¡n London next June.
Colour film highlights
'channels for Co-Action'
A 71/2-minute 16 mm colour film, Channels
for Co-Action, has been produced to help
publicize Unesco's Co-Action Programme,
which offers individuals and groups the
The Editors wish to apologise to rea¬
ders for delays in the publication of
recent issues of the Unesco Courier,
which were due to circumstances
beyond our control. These difficul¬
ties are now being eliminated and the
normal publication rhythm will be
resumed shortly.
opportunity to participate in self-help com¬
munity projects throughout the world. The
film, available on loan, evokes some of the
main targets of Co-Action: education and
literacy work, assistance to the disabled,
and the promotion of women's status. In
1981 an estimated $ 1 million worth of
UNUM cheques (Unesco Unit of Money)
were attributed to over 80 Co-Action pro¬
jects in developing countries. Requests for
further information should be addressed to:
Co-Action Programme, Unesco, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
The drug dilemma
Many readers have written to ask for further
details about the new study published by the
World Health Organization on which several
articles in our January 1982 issue were
based. The title of the study is Drug Prob¬
lems in the Sociocultural Context: A Basis
for Policies and Programme Planning. It is
no. 73 in WHO's Public Health Papers series
and can be obtained from the World Health
Organization, 1211 Geneva 27, Switzerland.
Reading exhibition
to coincide with
World Book Congress
"Books Live", a display of over 20 schemes
for encouraging adult literacy and the pro¬
motion of reading is to be held in London at
the Central Library of the Royal Borough of
Kensington and Chelsea from 3 to 8 June.
Drawing on material from developing and
industrialized countries throughout the
world, the exhibition will consist of posters,
giveaways, charts and sales displays and is
designed to appeal to everyone interested in
books and reading. "Books Live" has been
timed to coincide with the Unesco World
Congress of the Book which will be held at
Kensington Town Hall from 7 to 11 June.
BOOKSHELF
Recent Unesco books
Domination or Sharing? En¬
dogenous development and the transfer
of knowledge (No. 5 in Unesco's "In¬
sights" series). Deals with the problems
of the transfer of knowledge, the sharing
of technology and the changing power
relationships which result from it, and
with the capacity of societies to realize
and benefit from their own creativity.
288 pp. (45 F).
International Yearbook of Educa¬
tion (Volume XXXIII). Prepared for the
International Bureau of Education by
Robert Cowen, University of London In¬
stitute of Education. 253 pp. (35 F).
ApartheidA Teacher's Guide, by
Godfrey N. Brown. A handbook for
teachers presenting essential facts about
apartheid and its effects, and interna¬
tional and national efforts to eliminate it.
104 pp. (25 F).
Anti-Development: South Africa
and its Bantustans, by Donald
Moerdijk. Outlines the process whereby
the South African government set out to
maintain its policies by the fiction of "in¬
dependence" for its Bantustans. 194 pp.
(40 F).
Avalanche Atlas. Illustrated interna¬
tional avalanche classification. In five
languages: English, French, Spanish,
Russian, German. 265 pp. (160 F).
Assault on the Largest Unknown.
The International Indian Ocean Expedi¬
tion 1959-65, by Daniel Behrman. The
account of an international expedition
which had a significant impact on the
development of marine sciences in the
region and whose discoveries con¬
tributed to a revolution in geological
theory. 96 pp. (60 F).
Apartheid and Social Research,
edited and introduced by John Rex. A
series of articles written by social scien¬
tists within the Republic of South Africa.
199 pp. (52 F).
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly 111 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post*
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100, U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; 131 Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish . Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: .
Arabic Edition: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lee Kwang-Young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es- Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekín)
Bulgarian Edition: Dimitar G radev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion : Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be-addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Just published
by Unesco...
This album of photographs in praise of water is
published to mark the start of the international
water supply decade, a concerted worldwide effort in
which Unesco is engaged and which aims to bring
safe water supplies and adequate sanitation within
the reach of everyone by 1990. Striking black and
white photos by Unesco staff photographer
Dominique Roger evoke the precious qualities of
water and illustrate the part it plays in our lives.
72 pages 45 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij' Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd , 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing - CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display): Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kiriakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kiriakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, C.C P. 12598-48. - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editionsl: Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag,
Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps only: Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University ßookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast, The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong-Kong Government Information Services, Publications
Centre, GPO Building, Connaught Place. - HUNGARY.
Akadémiai Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtiirosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co , H F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcut¬
ta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, B-3/7 Asaf All
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016, Scindia House, New Delhi; Publication Unit, Ministry of
Education and Culture, Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad
Road, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers
and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
A. B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc , Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Sireet, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koener" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS AN¬
TILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V., P.O Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland, 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O Box 857 Hamilton, Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka, The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, Umversitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & An¬
drade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box
131, Mahé. - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University
and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libn Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B C E. Fritzes Kungl, Hov-
bokhandel, Regermgsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND-. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. -'TAN¬
ZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
- THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung
Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Raj'damnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I , and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovénie, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Liubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
:ÄS >5!ÔS
r WjL^á
WÊ.
<<4d
\
Sw>-
M».- \* w
Efgcff
<^Éfoimr*~~'' -^mmJÊ
^W*éâ
«s^ArÀ1«4
VOICES
OF MUSLIM
SPAIN
The unique culture of al-Andalus, Muslim
Spain, speaks out across the centuries from
sumptuous manuscripts and monuments
which are veritable books in stone and stuc¬
co. Photo 1: mirador of the Alhambra
palace, Granada. Photo 2: Page from an An¬
dalusian Qur'an (1304 AD) probably produc¬
ed for Sultan Muhammad III. Photo 3: Dome
above the mihrab of the Great Mosque at
Cordoba. Photo 4: Detail of columns of the
Alhambra. Photo 5: page from a 12th-
century Andalusian Qur'an.
1, 3, 5 Photos Michaud © Rapho, Paris
2 Photo © Bilbiotheque Nationale, Paris
' 4 Photo © Henri Stieriin, Geneva
jl _^^t»L.TJ
]]>
</page>
</document>
