<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074712eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY 1982 - 5 French francs
^
r,
The drug dilemma
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^%
El Salvador
Mayan mushroom stone
This stone figure (33.5 cm high) with its umbrella-like top dates from sometime bet¬
ween 300 BC and 200 AD. It is one of over 200 specimens unearthed in parts of cen¬
tral America where the ancient Maya culture flourished. Scholars tend to believe
that the figures may represent mushroom effigies and, although their significance
in ritual practice is unknown, attest to the sacred use of hallucinogenic mushrooms
by the Mayas. Hallucinogenic mushrooms and plants played an important role in
the religious rites of a number of ancient civilizations, their amazing effects on men¬
tal and physical functions being used to bring the partaker Into communication with
the spirit world. These substances, whose uncanny properties are only now being
subjected to rigorous scientific study, are still held in awe and veneration today by
some peoples bound to ancient traditions and ways of life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JANUARY 1982 35th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 48 French francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier Is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
Arabic
German
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Sayed Osman (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition:
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Bañador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lee Kwang-Young (Seoul)
Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Frederick Potter (Paris)Braille
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
5 EDUCATION AND THE DRUG DILEMMA
A Unesco survey
8 POSTERS AGAINST DRUGS
11 A NEW APPROACH TO DRUG DEPENDENCE
by Griffith Edwards
13 PATTERNS OF DRUG USE
Reports from nine countries
19 THE ROLE OF THE WORLD HEALTH ORGANIZATION
20 LIFELINES
'Treatment is a cultural process and a social act'
25 AN ABC OF DRUGS
Natural and synthetic substances under international control
30 A PILL FOR EVERY ILL
by Ruth Cooperstock
32 NO SMOKING. PLEASE
by Martin Raw
33 A PROBLEM IN CONSTANT EVOLUTION
by Griffith Edwards and Awni Arif
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
EL SALVADOR: Mayan mushroom stone
Cover
It is increasingly being recognized that there
is no single prescription for the management
of drug abuse and that each society must ap¬
proach the question in a way suited to its
own individuality. But it is also clear that in
this field countries have much to learn from
each other's experience. We hope that this
issue of the Unesco Courier, which examines
the issue of drug use and abuse in different
parts of the world and the varied approaches
to drug-related education and treatment
which have evolved within a number of
societies and cultures, will make a useful
contribution to the sharing of some of this
experience.
Photo montage © Peter Angelo Simon, New York
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Drug dependence: 'A state, psychic and sometimes also physical,
resulting from the interaction between a living organism and a drug,
characterized by behavioural and other responses that always include a
compulsion to take the drug on a continuous or periodic basis in order to
experience its psychic effects, and sometimes to avoid the discomfort of
its absence. Tolerance may or may not be present. A person may be
dependent on more than one drug. '
World Health Organization
For just over a decade, Unesco
has been an active participant in the
concerted United Nations action in
the field of drug problems. During
that period Unesco's main concerns
have been the development of
education, both in and out of
school, aimed at both young people
and adults, concerning problems
associated with the use of drugs, in¬
cluding alcohol and tobacco, and
the encouragement of research and
the dissemination of its findings.
The United Nations body in
charge of the co-ordination of the
various aspects of drug problems is
the Commission on Narcotic Drugs.
Within the United Nations system,
the United Nations Division of Nar¬
cotic Drugs and the International
Narcotic Control Board are prin¬
cipally concerned with the interna¬
tional regulation and control of the
production of drugs and trafficking
in them. The United Nations Fund
for Drug Abuse Control (UNFDAC),
established in 1972, helps to fund
the drug-related activities of the
United Nations agencies. The World
Health Organization (WHO) concen¬
trates on epidemiological, biologi¬
cal and medical research and the
treatment of drug users; the Food
and Agriculture Organization (FAO)
organizes programmes for the era¬
dication of drug-providing plant
cultivation and the installation of
alternative cash crops; the Interna¬
tional Labour Organisation (ILO)
assists in the development of voca¬
tional and rehabilitational training
at the place of work for former drug
users.
In the article below we present
findings of a Unesco survey of re¬
cent trends and developments in
drug use and in preventive educa¬
tion in twenty industrialized coun¬
tries. Other articles in this issue,
which is entirely devoted to the
drug question, include a United Na¬
tions dossier on the types of drugs
under international control, which
appears on page 25, and a series of
texts based on an important new
WHO study on "Drug Problems in
the Socio-Cultural Context". These
articles which appear on pages 13,
20, 30, 32 and 33 have been adapted
for the Unesco Courier by Professor
Griffith Edwards who is the co-
editor, with Awni Arif, of the WHO
study. They are presented in an in¬
troductory article on page 11
specially written for the Unesco
Courier by Prof. Edwards.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Education
and the drug dilemma
A Unesco survey
NOT long ago, education was virtually
overlooked as an aid in preventing
drug abuse. Confidence was vested
in other means such as legal controls and
the repression of traffic. Then, in the post¬
war years, changes in the pattern of drug
abuse itself brought a belated recognition of
the need to enlist education in efforts to
grapple with the problem.
Much has happened since the first at¬
tempts to devise serious educational
responses to the drug challenge. A more
penetrating understanding of drug use in in¬
dustrially developed countries and a certain
wisdom gained through educational trial and
error have made it possible to strengthen the
bases and techniques of preventive educa¬
tion. No doubt its evolution will continue,
for while some progress has been made
many questions still remain unanswered.
As regards the central aim of preventive
education, it seems apparent that there has
been a shift of emphasis in a substantial
number of countries. This change has has
significant effects on approaches, pro¬
grammes and methods. In the past the goal
had often been to prevent or minimize all
non-medical use of drugs. At its heart was
the exhortation: don't use drugs. This is
often still the stated aim. Experience now
seems to demonstrate, however, that it is
unrealistic, especially in societies that accept
the virtually unrestricted consumption of
alcohol and tobacco.
The view that there is much to be gained
from working towards more attainable goals
now seems to prevail among specialists. The
report from Canada states, for example: "In
the long term one must examine and decide
upon reasonable objectives. It would appear
that the elimination of drug use may be im¬
possible; however, improvement in the in¬
dividual's capacity to manage his use of
drugs and to make reasonable choices based .
on factual knowledge about the effects of
drug use may be possible".
The same point is made by the author of
the report from the United Kingdom: "... on
the basis of the evidence available from
evaluations throughout the world, no
known methods of drug education can be
said to reduce drug use... demand-
reduction is not an adequate basis for drug
education. Drug education should, instead,
be concerned to minimize the negative out¬
comes of drug use, to abolish unnecessary
stigmatization and self-fulfilling prophecies:
drug education should focus on promoting
relatively safe patterns of drug use...".
Hardly any statement about preventive
education is likely to win universal assent
and the foregoing quotations are no excep¬
tion. Nevertheless, on several fundamental
matters there appears to be a large measure
of agreement.
One of these is the role of information. At
an earlier stage facts about drugs and their
effects formed the core if not the entirety of
many teaching programmes. This approach
was grounded on the assumption that such
knowledge would be sufficient to prevent
young people from experimenting with or
misusing drugs. Accordingly, attention was
focused on substances, and the conse¬
quences of using them were often presented
in a manner designed to shock, to arouse,
fear and thereby to dissuade.
The confidence once placed in this ap¬
proach has faded. "Information only for the
sake of information can potentially lead to
more harm than good"", warns the report
from Yugoslavia. A similar judgement is ex¬
pressed in the report from Spain, which
points out that the information provided
may arouse curiosity or even justify drug use
in the eyes of the young by presenting it as
anti-social and as a form of contestation
against the older generation and its values.
In Norway, a study of teachers' attitudes
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Education and the drug dilemma
showed that, in their judgement, informa¬
tion alone was a weak basis for individual
choices pertaining to drug use. The report
from Australia states : "Information is con¬
sidered to play an essential part in achieving
the objectives of drug education, but is not
sufficient of itself to change attitudes and
behaviour". Similar views are expressed in
most of the other reports.
AND yet the case concerning informa¬
tion is by no means closed. "We do
not fear that giving information to
innocents will evoke curiosity and thereby
increase experimentation in youthful
groups", says the report from , Denmark.
And a research project in Canada has yield¬
ed findings concerning the effects of the in¬
formation approach which may give pause
to its critics.
However, the tactic of using information
about drugs to arouse fear is now generally
rejected, usually on the grounds that it may
make drugs attractive to the more self-
destructive elements of high-risk groups.
The information approach has to a large
extent given way to another. Taken as a
whole the reports reveal a marked trend
towards an approach which, while reserving
a place for information, treats knowledge as
only one of many components of preventive
education. The substance-focused, infor¬
mation-giving approach is more and more
subsumed in what is referred to in some of
the reports as "affective education". Such
education is directed towards the totality of
the individual personality instead of merely
the cognitive, intellectual part. The aim, like
that stated in 1963 for temperance education
in Finland, is the development of "a
physically and psychologically healthy per¬
sonality". As such it is relevant not only to
high-risk students but to all students.
The affective approach is concerned with
individuals in their specific social and
cultural setting and with the interaction of
personality and values in situations of
decision-making about drug use. "It has
been shown in our studies that it is of the ut¬
most importance that the teachers use the
situation-centred approach", says the report
from Denmark.
Although the affective approach has now
taken hold in many programmes, old-style
preventive education continues alongside it
or in combination with it. For example, the
report from the United Kingdom notes that
although national curriculum projects usual¬
ly have rationales or philosophies that favour
the affective approach, the project materials
also tend to rely on a substance-focused,
information-giving approach. The report
adds that this mixture tends, in the
classroom, to be translated into substance-
focused discussion because both teachers
and pupils are most drawn to the subject of
drugs and their effects. The newer curricula
are not being rigorously executed. "The
muddle on the policy level", the author
observes, "is being reproduced on the
classroom level."
The affective approach requires the adop¬
tion of educational methods and techniques
which will stimulate the students' interest
and inyolve them as active partners in learn¬
ing experiences. The trend towards the use
of such methods is one which education in
this field shares with education in general.
Often referred to as "active" methods, they
have proved to be especially useful in such
areas as moral and civic education, where
the formation of attitudes and patterns of
behaviour is an objective.
The need to use methods of this kind
seems now to be widely accepted. A few ex¬
amples will serve to illustrate the generaliza¬
tion. Instructions on temperance and health
education (which include preventive educa¬
tion) in Finland state: "Mere theoretical in¬
struction is not adequate... Teaching is
associated with children's everyday ex¬
periences... Pupil-centred methods of work
are applied" (report from Finland).
An example of such pupil-centred
methods comes from Sweden, where study
often takes place in small groups and is
organized largely by the pupils themselves.
A lesson plan outlined in the report begins
with discussion motivated by a film or some
other element, continues with study by all
pupils of a common syllabus combined with
individual and group project work and
concludes with students' reports and a
discussion.
The report for Flemish-speaking Belgium,
noting the role of dialogue, emphasizes the
importance of having pupils explain how
they perceive and experience the problem. A
statement from Australia on the philosophy
of its national drug education programme
refers, in a list of teaching procedures, to
debates, panel discussions, educational
games, group discussions and committee
work among other active methods.
VALUES-CLARIFICATION, role-play¬
ing, problem-solving and decision¬
making exercises are mentioned in
a number of reports or the materials
transmitted with them. These have become
staple techniques of affective education in
this field. Values-clarification, a process of
choosing among alternatives after consider¬
ing the consequences of each, assists in the
formation of attitudes concerning drugs
which will aid the individual to make deci¬
sions that are helpful to himself or herself
and others. Thus, the technique often cen
tres on situations involving a choice as to
whether or not to accept particular oppor¬
tunities for experimentation or use.
Role-playing helps students to understand
problem situations or value conflicts
through simulated experience and to em¬
pathize with people in positions that may be
very different from their own. Decision¬
making, generally focused on individual
problems and conflicts, and problem-
solving, usually dealing with group prob¬
lems, involve four essential steps: defining
the problem or conflict; listing the possible
choice or alternative ways of resolving the
problem or conflict; investigating the conse¬
quences of each of the alternative resolu¬
tions, and choosing the alternative that is
most satisfying to the individual or group.
Much of what has already been said about
objectives, approaches and methods applies
both to school education and out-of-school
education. Thus, the aim in out-of-school
education is now less commonly to stop
non-medical use of drugs than to develop
attitudes and patterns of behaviour that will
minimize damage from drug usewhat one
report calls the "casualty-reduction ap¬
proach" and active methods such as those
previously described are increasingly
employed.
As regards educational materials, the
resources of the countries surveyed here
range from comparative indigence to abun¬
dance. In virtually all of them, however,
there appears to have been a growth in the
supply of materials of good quality in recent
years.
For use in school education, in addition to
the information included in textbooks for
courses which serve as vehicles for drug
education, auxiliary teaching aids are being
produced in an increasing number of coun¬
tries: illustrated booklets, workbooks and
discussion guides for students; posters,
films, videotapes and charts for classroom
use; and guides, manuals and kits or
packets for the teacher containing all the
essentials for one or more lessons.
The flow of materials intended primarily
(though not necessarily exclusively) for use
outside the school is also increasing. Among
them are information booklets, articles and
advertisements in the press, periodicals,
posters, stickers and radio and television
programmes and "spots". While some of
these are aimed at specific target groups,
most are intended for the general public.
The wisdom of disseminating certain kinds
of drug information indiscriminately to the
population as a whole has been questioned
by some specialists on the grounds that it
may do more harm than good. What is
needed, according to the critics of this
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
method, is information and materials
adapted to the characteristics and re¬
quirements of particular groups and
distributed selectively.
Such targeted materials are now being
produced in many countries for a variety of
groups: children, young people, parents,
workers, the elderly, various professional
groups and others. Particularly noteworthy
is the preponderant attention given in many
countries to materials on alcohol and tobac¬
co, a reflection of the fact that these
substances are at the root of their most
serious and widespread drug-use problems.
The method adopted in Finland illustrates
not only the target-group principle but also
an interesting non-prohibitive approach. In
Finland, the State liquor monopoly, Alko,
has a large programme of information aimed
at consumers of alcohol. It distributes dif¬
ferent kinds of material through appropriate
channels (retail liquor shops, restaurants,
sports organizations, driving schools, etc.)
to specific groups. The goals are to restrain
harmful consumption and to alter attitudes
that favour over-indulgence. The position
taken in the materials rests on four proposi¬
tions: the best way to avoid problems is
abstinence; long-term heavy drinking is
always harmful; even small amounts in the
wrong situations can be dangerous; alcohol
can also have positive effects.
GENERAL guidelines for use in pre¬
paring materials have been issued
in some countries. Here again one
example, chosen because of the unusual cir¬
cumstances from which the guidelines
emerged, will serve as an illustration. In the
United States in the late 1960s a probably
unique problem of a materials glut arose. At
that time, "a major industry emerged that
revolved around one primary activity: pro¬
ducing and disseminating informational
materials that dealt with the dangers of drug
use. A conservative estimate in 1972 gauged
the extent of the drug information business
at $100 million a year. Ultimately the flood of
information and misinformation itself be¬
came a cause for alarm".
A major review of existing materials in
1971 found most of them by far to be inac¬
curate or unsuitable for other reasons. In
response to this finding the federal govern¬
ment declared a moratorium on the produc¬
tion of federally funded drug information
materials. Later the moratorium was lifted
when new guidelines had been issued.
These guidelines ensured audience iden¬
tification and pre-testing of material. They
excluded messages in which fear was the
main deterrent or the way to use drugs was
shown, and recommended general themes
to be promoted.
Provisions for preventive education in
school programmes vary considerably
among the countries covered by the Unesco
survey. At one end of the spectrum it is a
compulsory part of the offical curriculum; at
the other end, there is no specific provision
for it and initiative is left largely to individual
teachers. In some instances it is an extra
curricular activity. The range of differences
is represented by the following examples.
Finland: Instructions on temperance
education in primary and secondary cur¬
ricula have been issued by the National
Board of Schools since the early years of
this century. Since 1967 teaching has been
incorporated at the primary level (fifth to
eighth grade) into a new subject called civics
and citizenship. In the secondary school it is
a part of hygiene and biology, with some
teaching in other courses as well. The pro¬
gramme consists of two to six lessons a
year.
Sweden: Teaching about alcohol, nar¬
cotics and tobacco was made compulsory at
all levels by the curriculum adopted in 1967.
It is given in various courses according to in¬
structions drawn up by the National Board
of Education.
Denmark: It is obligatory for all schools
to offer preventive education from the sixth
to the tenth grade. It is integrated into such
courses as biology, social sciences and
physical education.
Norway: Preventive education is an
obligatory study area in curricula for
students from ten to sixteen years of age.
No specific number of hours is fixed for it.
Greece: Preventive education is in¬
tegrated into different courses in the first,
second and third years of secondary school.
Italy: Preventive education is provided in
the framework of health education, which is
considered to be part of the educational pro¬
cess as a whole and a responsibility of all
teachers. It is explicity assigned to teachers
of natural science and chemistry at the
secondary level.
Federal Republic of Germany: Preven¬
tive education is included in curricula in all
Länder, or States. Usually the subject is
taken up repeatedly from about the seventh
grade (pupils of 13 years) onward. New cur¬
ricula for all grades, now being prepared by
the Federal Centre for Health Education, will
be completed during the next few years.
Yugoslavia: Programmes of preventive
education include teaching in various com¬
pulsory and optional courses, lectures of a
social character arranged by organizations
such as the Red Cross and discussions in
school clubs. As regards teaching, an exam¬
ple is provided by Serbia, where com¬
ponents of preventive education are in¬
corporated into the subject "nature and
society" in grades I to IV and in biology in
grade VIII.
Australia: Preventive education pro¬
grammes are authorized in schools in most
States, but decisions concerning them are
usually left to principals of individual
schools.
Czechoslovakia: Teaching about al¬
cohol and related problems is found
sporadically in school programmes, and
material on the dangers of smoking is in¬
cluded at every level. Teaching about other
drugs is provided through extra-curricular
projects.
France: Preventive education is not in¬
cluded in curricula. Information is provided
to pupils at their request, notably in the
"Life and Health" clubs which are found in
many schools and which are concerned not
only with this matter but also with other
problems that preoccupy young people
(e.g., the environment, sexuality).
There is no advocacy in the reports of a
separate and identifiable course on drug-
related problems. Instead, as the foregoing
examples show, preventive education is
nested in other courses, most often health
education/hygiene with biology and social
studies/civics next in the order of frequen¬
cy. Other courses mentioned as vehicles in¬
clude natural science, chemistry, religion,
moral laïque, psychology, physical educa¬
tion, home economics, anthropology,
history, environmental studies, sex educa¬
tion and languages.
IN addition to information on drug use
and provision for preventive educa¬
tion, many of the reports comment
upon the evolution of attitudes regarding
drug use in general or the use of particular
drugs. The changes described do not fall in¬
to patterns, either within or among coun¬
tries, that permit generalizations of much
significance.
Three observations do, however, seem
justified:
In some countries the public alarm of a
decade ago over the "drug problem" seems
to have subsided. The diminished concern
probably results in part from a growing
tendency to dedramatize the issue. In the
United States, for example, the Director of
the National Institute on Drug Abuse drew
attention in 1979 to "the widespread public
opinion which is, if not supportive, at least
neutral about the harm of drug abuse".
Another official document from that country
refers to an "apparent increased tolerance of
drug use".
Acceptance of the use of certain illicit
drugs appears to have increased. This is
notably the case in some countries as
regards cannabis (e.g., Canada, Denmark,
the United States).
Resistance to the use of permitted drugs
has increased in some countries. Thus,
several reports note that adverse public at¬
titudes are putting tobacco smokers on the
defensive (in New Zealand, for example) and
others indicate development of stronger op¬
position to the use of alcohol (as in Norway,
where 15 to 20 per cent of the population
advocate total abstinence).
To what may these apparent fluctuations
in attitudes be attributed? No doubt many
factors which vary from country to country
exert an influence. Among them certainly
must be counted the content and tenor of
information reaching the public through
education and the mass media.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
IJSS
BtííA VCflfACC^-
%SSBê**
.««i..
assft*
\\#
Posters - All rights reserved
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
an*tog> ;-V*ff0S
..t***
C«o
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
- >
^"VMNift e
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
A new approach
to drug dependence
by Griffith Edwards
OVER the last decade or two "drug
education" has been much in
vogue as a way of meeting society's
worry about illicit drug taking by young peo¬
ple. But in the broadest sense, who
educates the educators? Put simply and
challengingly "Do you know what you are
talking about?"
The teacher standing there with chalk and
blackboard or the latest film strip at the
ready, is of course only a metaphor: what
we are really asking is whether laws and
government policies on addiction, treatment
programmes and prevention programmes,
our reactions to drug use and our own use
of drugs (alcohol and tobacco are drugs) are
based on informed understanding or on
frightened misconceptions.
Misconceptions, for instance, frequently
include ideas such as that alcohol is not a
drug, that drug taking is a problem that in¬
volves only young people, that one type of
explanation can explain all drug taking, that
a solution favoured in the West has the
answers for the East, that we can "cure"
societies', drug problems by ever more ac¬
tive customs and police action, that drug
use inevitably means lurid degradation, that
what is wrong is simply the drug, simply the
individual, or simply society out of balance.
Let us, as it were, put the chalk down for
a minute, and ask ourselves first of all what
meanings and explanations we are really giv¬
ing to this key word "addiction".
The word addiction by immediate reflex
will in most people's minds conjure up im¬
ages of something which is alien, unintelligi¬
ble, and perhaps carrying with it a whiff of
association with evil and enchantment. It is
a word which invites fear, perhaps con¬
tempt, and certainly a suspension of cool
analysis.
Today the nuances of meaning vary great¬
ly between languages, and any international
meeting on drug problems soon discovers
that it is involved in a tangle of linguistics.
There are languages where this word ad¬
diction has no precise translation, and other
languages where there is no concept
available which even remotely resembles
this key term.
We find ourselves again discovering that
words are not only our servants but also our
GRIFFITH EDWARDS, of the United Kingdom,
has been professor ofAddiction Behaviour at the
Institute of Psychiatry, University of London,
since 1979, and Honorary Director of the
Institute's Addiction Research Unit since 1970.
He is a member of the World Health
Organization's Expert Advisory Committee on
Drug Dependence. Among his many publications
are Drugs and Drug Dependence, of which he
was joint editor (1976) and Alcoholism (1977).
masters: vocabulary shapes the way we
think about things and (much more dang¬
erously), the way we think about people.
Some years ago, in 1969, the World
Health Organization promulgated the idea of
drug dependence as an alternative concept
to addiction. The new phrasing was certain¬
ly meant to be more than a mere synonym
for the older term. What was implied was
the need to recognize the fact that different
types of drug can produce very varying
types and degrees of reliance on their use,
whereas the word addiction all too easily
suggests an extreme and stereotyped pic¬
ture, resembling perhaps that produced by
heroin. Because of its brevity and its
penetration of our ordinary language the
word addiction is nevertheless still likely to
remain in circulation for a long time the
word addict comes more naturally than the
phrase drug dependent person.
But whether we designate compulsive
drug taking as bad habit, addiction, or
dependence, what is the essential nature of
the thing we are talking about? There are a
number of possible levels of explanation.
The laboratory scientist will be interested in
the neurochemistry and the influence of the
drug on the transmission of nervous im¬
pulses, and the mechanisms which underlie
tolerance and the withdrawal state. The
psychologist will focus on addiction as
learnt behaviour, the drug experience as re¬
inforcing and conditioning of drug taking
behaviour, or on the learning processes
which came about from the relief of
withdrawal symptoms by a further dose of
the drug. And meanwhile the sociologist will
seek to understand the social determinants
of drug taking, the peer group pressures,
and the nature of the environment which
proposes drug taking. Being an addict is, he
will argue, the assumption of a social role.
The anthropologist will point out the sym¬
bolic meaning of the drug and will see the
rituals and functions of drug taking as
rooted in the individual's culture.
Which explanation is to have pre¬
eminence? There is an invitation here to a
certain kind of chauvinism, with the pure
scientist believing that only his sort of
science can really put a finger on the ab¬
solute nature of addiction, and that truth
can be reduced to the ultimates of the
neuronal synapse: the social scientist may
equally be tempted to claim that the neuro¬
sciences are crass and only work at a level
which is absurdly remote from the social
reality of "being an addict" the electron
microscope no matter how high-powered
does not reveal the texture of the opium
smoker's hillside village, or the street cor¬
ners of the heroin addict's life. To put such
different perspectives into positions
of confrontation and rivalry is, however,
unproductive.
The challenge which is issued by the at¬
tempt to understand drug taking and drug
addiction goes wider though than the im¬
mediate question: it is the challenge to over¬
come a much more general habit in our
thinking which favours one-dimensional ex¬
planations. It is in fact quite impossible to
approach a whole understanding of why, for'
instance, the Andean peasant chews his
coca leaves unless we are at one and the
same time willing to make an effort to
understand the pharmacological properties
of cocaine, the psychological nature of the
drug experience, the working conditions of
that labourer, and the way that society
regards coca chewing.
What a challenge! But this is not a posi¬
tion to be arrived at simply for the sake of
abstract intellectual satisfaction, a sort of
show-off intellectual conjuring trick. On the
contrary, this is the needed basis for all man¬
ner of practical dealings. If we retreat to
one-dimensional vision we will inevitably
find ourselves trapped in ill-adapted policies
and responses.
Having insisted on this need for an
understanding which is balanced and in¬
tegrated, it can probably now be seen that
the worst errors of recent years have come
from a tendency to neglect the social and
cultural dimensions. A policy which at¬
tempts, for instance, to prevent urban
heroin addiction by heavy police penalties
for use or by lecturing school children on the
evils and dangers of this substance, while ig¬
noring the nature of life and the frustrations
of opportunity in a shattered ghetto where
being an addict gives comradeship, a sense
of shared purpose and enterprise and a
definition of self not otherwise easily
available, is to embark on a response which
is likely not only to be ineffective and costly
but also to be cruel.
Addiction certainly matters, but we
should also be much more attuned to think¬
ing in terms of the actual pattern of prob¬
lems which the individual or society is en¬
countering where drugs are con¬
cerned occurring singly or in
clusters, and affecting health in its physical,
psychological or social domains.
We started with the image of a speaker
about to give his talk and very politely we
asked him to pause a minute and define
what he was talking about. In this complex
area the business of understanding is never
completed, but will be much aided by
shared experience from many villages and
streets. The articles which follow have that
aim.
Griffith Edwards
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Patterns of drug use
To map in totality the astonishingly varied patchwork
of drug use throughout the world would be a daunting
task. But the following first-hand accounts by experts
of nine different countries or regions provide us with a
vivid insight into the nature and extent of the diver¬
sities. In each instance the author shows how drug use
is only to be understood against the social and cultural
background. Often today part of that background is
people's sense of the rapidity of environmental change
and the breakdown of the old rules, attitudes and ways
of living changes which are immediately reflected in
altered patterns of drug use.
Reports
from
nine
countries
^EEEi^És¡meiaí^mmmíS0^^^mmmim^sí'0^Mmmmmmisimaiimsmmsm.
THAILAND. Dr. V. Poshyachinda
describes traditional use of opium by
the Hmong, one of the northern hill
tribes. There are well-formed attitudes
and expectations which informally con¬
trol the use of this drug.
A predominant reason for the use of
opium is for treatment of physical ailments.
Opium is also used for its tranquillizing and
euphoric effect. Reactive depression from
the death of a loved one or from loss of
livestock or crops may lead some to opium
use. Thirdly, this drug is a means of recre¬
ation. At social gatherings in the village, tea,
alcohol and tobacco are used as well as
opium. The Hmong have a rather rigid
custom of not allowing children to use
alcohol, tobacco, or opium, until they are
over ten years old. Opium use among the
young is limited to the treatment of
illnesses. Nevertheless, a small number of
young men were found to be dependent, as
a result of curiosity and companionship with
drug users.
The Hmong are well aware of the bad ef¬
fects of opium dependence. In a survey of
villagers' attitudes towards opium use,
about two-thirds stated that opium smoking
was bad. Economic loss appeared to be the
main reason. Some emphasized the
beneficial therapeutic effect and considered
opium smoking to be good if properly used.
Opium is smoked openly in front of other
members of the family, including children.
Some young females who have become
dependent are ashamed of their behaviour
and smoke in privacy or in the woods.
MALAYSIA. Drug use in transition-
fishermen traditionally used opium to
alleviate the stress of a hard life but to¬
day's young people smoke heroin at the
discos, perhaps to meet a new sort of
stress. Dr. V. Navaratnam writes:
Whereas, traditionally, opium was smok¬
ed in opium dens or opium houses as well as
during family gatherings, this is no longer
true of the younger population. Drugs are
used in homes, coffee houses, disco¬
theques, recreation grounds and back-lane
drink and food stalls. Dependent persons
use heroin, and it is smoked in cigarette
form. By tradition, opium was used for
recreation or to alleviate the stress of hard
work, e.g. by fishermen, who spent up to
fifteen hours at a time at sea and worked up
to eighteen hours a day. Nowadays, by con¬
trast, as one study has shown, younger
users begin to take drugs for various other
reasons such as curiosity (about 27 per
cent), peer influence (about 31 per cent),
and a surprisingly large proportion to
forget their problems (18 per cent).
Three possible explanations can be ad¬
vanced for the initiation of drug use by
Malaysian youth: that drug abuse provides a
means of achieving subcultural acceptance;
that it is a manifestation of delinquent-
defiant behaviour; or that it may be a form
of "self-treatment" for frustration caused by
such factors as blocked opportunities and
economic distress.
The third explanation is probably impor¬
tant in developing nations, especially those w
undergoing rapid industrialization. Late f
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
adolescence and early adulthood are even
in normal circumstances turbulent stages. In
Malaysia, these age-groups are likely to have
higher aspirations and better education than
their elders. At the same time competition
for education and work has increased con¬
siderably. Thus, these young people despite
their better education become frustrated
and look for ways of escape.
c 1
INDIA. Dr. D. Mohan writes of ebb and
flow in patterns of drug use in rural
Punjab and assesses the place of legal
controls.
The traditionally used drugs, alcohol,
opium and cannabis, seem to be still those
in common use. However, there appears to
be a change in the pattern of preferred
drugs. Cannabis use has declined; opium
use is more than the official estimates show
but still seems to have declined, while
alcohol use has certainly risen.
Psychotropics are not widely used despite
the increased health facilities. These ob¬
servations are of interest, in view of the fact
that legal sanctions against cannabis and
opium have been in operation for a fairly
long time. Though legal sanctions have con-
Below left, two members of an
International Labour Organisation
(ILO) vocational rehabilitation team
examine an intricate piece of
embroidery produced by a Thai
villager. They are taking part in a
vigorous campaign, launched by
the Government of Thailand with
the help of the United Nations,
against illegal poppy cultivation and
use of narcotic drugs in the
mountain villages of northern
Thailand. The programme, set up
by the World Health Organization
(WHO) and ILO, aims at treating
and retraining drug addicts and at
diversifying farmers' sources of
income by encouraging them to
grow other crops (top) and by the
production of handicrafts.
In traditional societies where
historically certain drugs have been
used, rapid social and economic
change may encourage the
adoption of new habits and life¬
styles accompanied by new
patterns of drug use. Studies in the
rural Punjab showed that one new
habit formed in this context was
the use of alcohol which tended to
impose unfamiliar strains and
tensions on the social fabric. Right,
traditional and modern in
Chandigarh, capital of Punjab
State, India.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
trolled the availability of drugs, the decline in
cannabis consumption when cannabis re¬
mained freely available is inexplicable except
on social grounds. Lastly, heroin and other
synthetic opiates have not appeared.
What are the implications of these obser¬
vations, seen in the historical context of In¬
dia's experience? The first is that there is an
interplay between drugs of dependence and
that, over a period of continuing availability,
attitudes lead to a rise and decline in the use
of particular drugs. These attitudes may be
influenced by availability.
Secondly, in circumstances such as per¬
tain to India, legal action in respect of drug-
availability control should be introduced and
implemented slowly. The laws should not be
enforced for a considerable period of time
but should remain rather as statements of
intention; this is especially so when the
dependence-producing substances are plant
materials rather than synthetic drugs. Yet a
statement of legal intention is necessary,
because it tends to discourage people from
becoming involved with drugs.
Drug use is closely interwoven with the
socio-economic matrix of rural agrarian
society. A stringent legal prohibition serves
only to disrupt this tradition, and makes the
appearance of substitute drugs easier.
When laws are applied wisely, however.
they can be a means of promoting healthy
social change, by guiding the direction of
change.
. -t^.ù- ».v. f-.ar-~.;-.vm: . ..
THE ANDEAN REGION OF SOUTH
AMERICA. Coca chewing is the
custom". Dr. J.C. Negrete gives an ac¬
count of the indigenous use of cocaine
in the Peruvian uplands.
It is around 9:30 a.m. in a high valley of
the Peruvian Andes. A group of peasants
are taking their mid-morning break and have
gathered by the side of a field. They are sort¬
ing dry coca leaves from small pouches they
carry attached to their belts and gently
removing the harder stems before placing
the leaves one by one into one side of their
mouth, between cheek and gums. The
break lasts about thirty minutes. The men
return to. work and the renewed mouthful of
coca will last them from two to three hours.
This is the second time during the day
that the ritual has taken place; the first was
at dawn when the men set out for the fields.
It will be repeated three more times before
they retire to sleep in the evening. With a
few variations, this scene can be observed in
thousands of farming communities
throughout the central Andes, in sugar cane
plantations in northern Argentina, and in the
mines of the Bolivian Altiplano.
The chewing of coca leaves by men at
work is the most widespread pattern of coca
use. Coca use is so extensive and long-
established that most chewers adopt it
simply through normal socialization, with no
need for a conscious individual decision, in
much the same way as people learn to drink
coffee elsewhere. It is no wonder that in¬
quiries into the reasons for chewing may
evoke responses such as es costumbre (it is
the custom).
Further probing, however, reveals that
coca is regarded as capable of giving An¬
dean men "courage", "strength", "en¬
durance", and the "will to work". Inca tradi¬
tions regard industry as a virtue and despise
idleness and laziness. Indeed, a common
Quechua language greeting (ama Hulla, ama
sua, ama qella) includes an injunction
against laziness. Many observers believe
that chewing coca may help the poorer An¬
dean people to adjust to the very limited
food intake permitted by their meagre
resources.
Coca also has therapeutic functions.
Because of its local anaesthetic properties, it
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
rñ
Innocent victims
"Never before have there been so many
children flirting with drugs and their
associated hazards... Drug abuse is
depriving today's children of the right
to enter the coming century with
dignity, good health, and the chance to
make a substantial contribution to the
future of their countries and the
world." These warning words from a
United Nations dossier on children and
drugs draw attention to an issue which
is causing concern in every world
region, from the isolated hill areas
where narcotics crops are grown to the
urban centres of the industrialized
world. Drawings on this page illustrate
three aspects of a many-sided problem.
(1) For some children addiction begins
in the womb. The first they know of the
world is the severe pain of heroin
withdrawal because of their mother's
habit. (2) In highly medicated societies,
open, abundantly-stocked medicine
cabinets may pose another problem.
Combined with the example of frequent
parental use, they arouse the curiosity
of children and lead each year to many
cases of drug abuse and fatal accidental
poisoning. (3) Even more children are
the victims of neglect related to
parental drug abuse. In many cases,
notes the UN document, "children
subjected to a deficient environment
inside and/or outside the home...
search for escape, stimulation, relief or
expanded meaning through the use of
drugs."
Drawings © AIE, United Nations	
w
1
X.
UUMW4- Jffi
r
ja *
ri
a
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
has been used traditionally with much suc¬
cess to treat toothache. As a hot-water in¬
fusion, it is effective against gastrointestinal
disorders.
In addition to these practical functions,
Andean people have traditionally attached
magical properties to coca. Many workers
believe it protects them from dangers such
as accidents and injuries at work, and
insect- and snake-bites in the fields. Another
common practice is that people stick coca
leaves to their forehead or cheeks in the
belief that this will banish headache, worry,
insomnia, toothache and other disorders.
MEXICO. Dr. R. de la Fuente gives this
picture of glue-sniffing and solvent
abuse among the young outcasts of
Mexico City.
The children at the time of the study were
under thirteen years old, the adolescents
between thirteen and sixteen, and the
young adults between seventeen and
twenty-three. They haunted an area of Mex¬
ico City where drug-users can find places to
sleep, hide, eat and take drugs; it has a
market, small shops, vacant lots, cheap
hotels, restaurants, tenement buildings and
small squares.
The regular inhabitants are people who
generally work in the area and belong mostly
to the middle or lower socio-economic
stratum. They have almost no contacts with
the inhalers but if their paths cross the in¬
halers are ostracized since they are regarded
as depraved. The young people, however,
maintain close relations among themselves.
All of them have left homes where they were
used as providers for their parents, who sent
them out to earn money by doing jobs like
collecting garbage, selling chewing-gum or
washing windows. If they came home
without money they were ill-treated, so that,
feeling no attachment to their families, they
chose to live away.
Within a group, the adolescents use the
children to obtain food and money, and seek
the protection of the young adults, whose
business it is to obtain and distribute the in¬
halant. In their search for affection the
children maintain a very close relation with
the other young people.
For a child to be taken into a group he
undergoes a series of tests such as having
his money or some of his garments taken
away, or being beaten; he has to win fights
and show a talent for thieving; if he passes
the tests he is accepted. Upon joining he
must observe certain rules of conduct or
else be expelled. The main rules are not to
reveal the identity of the members of the
group when anyone asks, not to ask about
the members' backgrounds, and to respect
the freedom of others to take drugs or not as
they choose.
The child inhaler then seems to develop
certain characteristics. He has a practical
type of intelligence, acquired through his
day-to-day experiences. He is understanding
and does not criticize his comrades when
they cry or grieve over some recollection or
deprivation. He is a rebel, rejecting every
kind of authority.
UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Chicago
schools: Dr. P. Hughes describes the
distribution system for many drugs,
which was surprisingly overt.
Drug-using students were seen to exhibit
distinctive patterns of behaviour. They were
invariably found in the smoking areas during
their free time, and there was generally a
drug-user meeting-place outside the school
but near the school grounds. They fre¬
quented certain toilets where they could
stand and keep a look-out for teachers who
might be supervising the area. In the
lunchroom they occupied certain sections of
the cafeteria where they could be contacted
each day. These behaviour patterns of the
drug-users were known to a significant
number of students and teachers but no ef¬
forts were made to disrupt them.
One must ask, then, why do not more
parents, teachers and others intervene to
prevent or interfere with drug-using group
activities? Some well-meaning individuals
do, but all too often they have to contend
with unpleasantness and even threats of
violence. Friends and authorities who try to
intervene usually find that talking to, or try¬
ing to help, a drug-user in the school or
smoking-room, on the street corner or in the
park, brings no rapid or dramatic results.
Also, people familiar with the street culture
may be reluctant to communicate their
observations to the police or other com¬
munity authorities for fear of provoking the
drug users to retaliate. Nevertheless, it is
likely that if enough professional workers in
the field of drug abuse began to interact
with drug-users in their community rather
than inside the walls of their institutions new
intervention strategies might evolve.
JAMAICA. Dr. M. Beaubrun describes
the very different meanings and conse¬
quences of cannabis use in traditional
working-class and Westernized middle-
class subcultures.
Ganja, which is the local name for can¬
nabis, has been used in Jamaica for more
than one hundred years. It is readily grown,
and its use, though illegal, is widespread
among the lower socio-economic classes,
especially the rural agricultural workers. An
anthropological field study in 1970-1972
estimated that at least 60 per cent of adult
males were smokers in a typical rural com¬
munity. The heaviest users are a religio-
political group known as Rastafarians, who
ascribe divine powers to "the herb".
The Jamaican worker uses ganja as a
tonic and as a nostrum for all illnesses. He
uses it also to give him energy for arduous
work and to relax after work. He gives it to
his children to make them brighter at school
and to sharpen their understanding. He at¬
tributes mystical powers to it, such as
warding off evil spirits. It has been sug¬
gested that this complex of beliefs, attitudes
and customs has been diffused to the Afro-
Jamaican peasants, who are now the
heaviest users of ganja.
There is a wide gap between these at¬
titudes and those of middle-class
Jamaicans. Ganja smoking is frowned upon
by most middle-class adults. Middle-class
adolescent use, though a growing
phenomenon, is still largely a defiant act of
rebellion coupled with an imitation of the
North American culture. The middle-class
adolescent uses it for curiosity, for enhanc¬
ing sexual pleasure, for listening to music,
for psychedelic effects and as a new ex¬
perience. He has no clear rules to follow and
no respectable models to imitate.
By contrast, the growing child in working-
class Jamaica is gradually socialized into the
use of ganja and has many role models. It
may be fed to him as ganja tea even in his in¬
fant bottle. He may begin smoking at the
age of seven or eight but is usually initiated
in his early teens by one of his peers or in a
group-smoking experience with many of the
features of a rite de passage.
His response to the initial smoking ex¬
perience seems to validate his role as a
smoker or non-smoker in the ganja sub¬
culture. An initial unpleasant experience
may result in his avoiding ganja thereafter
and his behaviour will have cultural support.
Anthropological studies indicate that the
culture has developed built-in controls to
minimize the ill-effects of the drug. Most im¬
portant of all is learning to "titrate" so as to
achieve just the result needed and no more.
These built-in protective mechanisms may
account for the relatively harmless picture
that emerges of chronic marijuana use
among working-class Jamaicans.
In contrast with this picture of cannabis
use among the working class are the reports
of a higher proportion of problems among
middle-class youths, even though the
number of users is much lower. School
drop-outs, transient psychotic episodes,
panic reactions and adolescent behaviour
problems have all been reported.
KENYA. Dr. W. Acuda relates changes
in drinking to the background of rapid
socio-economic development.
There is no doubt that alcohol abuse is in¬
creasing alarmingly in Kenya. A study of
alcoholism in a crowded slum area of
Nairobi fou nd that at least 46 per cent of the
males and 24 per cent of the females could
be classified as alcoholics. A similar study in
a rural area of Kenya also found a very high
prevalence of alcoholism, affecting 37 per
cent of males and 34 per cent of females.
What has caused this sudden increase in
alcohol consumption? There 'are certainly
many factors involved. That most often
mentioned is the rapid change that is taking
place in developing countries. Kenya, like
other developing countries, has undergone
many changes in recent decades. In some
places these changes are so rapid that the
people hardly have time to adjust to them.
Inevitably, this has led to stress and conflict.
Given other factors, such as easy availability
of alcohol, it is not surprising that there has i
been a sudden increase in alcohol abuse and f
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
In many countries there are established
ways of using a particular drug, which
are embedded in social custom. One
such drug is Khat (Catha edulis Forsk.),
a tree that grows in East Africa,
Democratic Yemen and Yemen, whose
leaves and shoots have a stimulant
effect. Khat is chewed in a 'colourful
and scented setting' (below), often in a
special room set aside for the purpose.
r
a change in drinking patterns all over the
country. Phrases like "rapid socio-economic
change" are used too often and too glibly
these days when talking about the develop¬
ing world, without any close understanding
of what this phrase really means in human
terms.
Cultural traditions are disintegrating very
fast in most African societies. There has
been a virtual rebellion against traditional
cultural values and influences. Family ties
have broken down. The extended family,
which sheltered so many people, has
become too expensive. Extra-tribal mar¬
riages are now common, especially among
the educated and these marriages are often
faced with many problems.
Finally, with the spread of Christianity and
the increase in knowledge, especially about
medical treatment, the influence of supersti¬
tion and fear of witchcraft are disappearing.
People no longer believe they will be
punished if they break tradition or behave
immorally.
Lack of recreation or of any fulfilling use
of leisure time is another cause of problems
for new migrants to cities and towns. Food
also can be a source of conflict.
Educated or professional people may have
to adjust to a different type of problem: that
of working to rigid schedules in competitive
situations. In the country, life was relatively
simple and unstructured, and the amount of
work done depended on the individual's
capacity and on natural conditions like rain,
the sun and darkness.
Such changes in drinking behaviour as are
taking place in Kenya, and, at a rapid pace,
in many other parts of the developing world,
cannot be understood without a close and
sympathetic understanding of the
background of cultural and social change
against which they are taking place.
E
F«WTI»BffiWjl'SWC^«iW^Wptlr-yW" ^J^fUJ^^W^ij»
YEMEN. The "colourful and scented set¬
ting" of the Khat party, described by Dr.
R.A. Baasher.
Khat is a tree that grows at high altitude.
The leaves and young shoots provide a
stimulant effect which has led to its wide
use in several countries, including
Democratic Yemen, Djibouti, Ethiopia,
Somalia, Yemen and, to a lesser extent, in
limited areas of Kenya and the United
Republic of Tanzania.
Varied and complex factors underlie the
use of khat. It is commonly used for social
recreation and occasionally as a medicine.
Because of its stimulating effects it has been
used by tribal people when travelling, and in
modern times by students preparing for ex¬
aminations, and drivers of motor vehicles on
long-distance journeys. Though nowadays
khat is chewed, historically it was referred to
as Arabian or Ethiopian tea, a name that
denoted its use as an infusion.
As khat is chewed in a group setting,
many houses in Yemen have a special room
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
for the purpose. It is well furnished with the
best carpets, and is given a special name,
such as "peace room", or "mercy room". In
the centre of the room, ornamented mada'a
(hubble bubbles) are specially placed, ready
for smoking. In this colourful and scented
setting members of the party arrive,
everyone bringing his share of khat. On
entering the carpeted room, each one takes
off his shoes and sits on the mattress, lean¬
ing on the pillows. In a friendly, relaxed and
joyful atmosphere the chewer plucks the
leaves from the twig and meticulously
chews them. Meanwhile, cold water, cola
drinks or sweet menthol drinks are sipped
and tea is served. The segregation of the
sexes in khat parties is faithfully observed.
female parties being less frequent and not so
formal. Shortly after the beginning of the
session, a sense of well-being dominates the
atmosphere. The mind becomes very active,
and the stream of talk flows easily and pas¬
sionately. After about three hours the group
reaches a stage when a sense of "wisdom"
and self-content generally prevails. This,
however, does not continue long, and in
about another hour the mood changes and
personal problems and difficulties emerge.
Some men then become restless and ir¬
ritable and they may erratically and im¬
pulsively leave the party. Those who stay
behind tend to become more intimate. The
discussions may continue or be adjourned,
tobe resumed at the next party.
Dr. V. Poshyachinda is attached to the Institute
of Health Research, Chulalongkorn University,
Bangkok, Thailand.
Dr. V. Navaratnam is Director of the National
Drug Dependence Research Project, Universiti
Sains, Minden, Pu/au Pinang, Penang, Malaysia.
Dr. D. Mohan is Associate Professor in the
Department of Psychiatry, All-India Institute of
Medical Sciences, New Delhi India.
Dr. J. Negrete is Associate Director of the
Department of Psychiatry, Montreal General
Hospital, Montreal, Canada.
Dr. R. de la Fuente is General Director of the Na¬
tional Mental Health Program, at the Centro Mex¬
icano de Estudios en Salud Mental, Mexico City,
Mexico.
Dr. P. H. Hughes is Senior Medical Officer in the
Division of Men tel Health, World Health
Organization, Geneva, Switzerland.
Dr. M.H. Beaubrun is Professor of Psychiatry at
the University of the West Indies, Port of Spain,
Trinidad and Tobago.
Dr. S.W. Acuda is Lecturer in the Department of
Psychiatry, Faculty of Medicine, University of
Nairobi, Nairobi, Kenya.
Dr. T.A. Baasher is Regional Adviser in Mental
Health, WHO Regional Office for the Eastern
Mediterranean, Alexandria, Egypt.
The role
of the World Health Organization
The World Health Organization (WHO)
carries wide responsibilities for the sup¬
port of Member States who request aid
or advice in dealing with their drug-
related health problems (including prob¬
lems related to alcohol and tobacco
use). One of the most important func¬
tions of WHO, which falls within its co¬
ordinating role, is the international
transfer of information on health mat¬
ters, the Organization being used as a
neutral ground for abstracting, assessing
and disseminating information. It is a
responsibility of WHO to make such in¬
formation available to those who need it.
Among its priorities the Organization
must co-operate with countries in rela¬
tion to drug dependence in order to:
a) increase the effectiveness of health
and social service delivery systems by
developing effective low-cost ap¬
proaches to treatment and rehabilitation
of drug-dependent patients;
b) develop strategies for treatment
and prevention through primary health
care and in the framework of country
health programmes, in countries with in¬
adequate or no health or social care
systems;
c) co-ordinate international research in
drug dependence;
d) strengthen the planning of effective
prevention and control programmes
through the international collection and
exchange of data on the epidemiology of
drug dependence;
e) ensure that suitable training pro¬
grammes , are provided to meet man¬
power needs;
f) work in partnership with other
United Nations agencies and organiza¬
tions that have direct responsibilities for
drug problems;
g) fulfil the responsibilities identified
in the international conventions concer¬
ning drugs;
h) establish an effective co-ordinating
mechanism whereby the knowledge and
experience of non-governmental orga¬
nizations and centres of excellence may
be transmitted and adapted to countries
with few technical and human
resources.
WHO responsibilities derive from the
World Health Assembly, the Executive
Board and the Regional Committees,
and from the International Narcotics
Treaties. Resolutions adopted by the
Health Assembly provide policy and
priority directives to implement ac¬
tivities for the control of alcohol and
drug problems.
During the past five years, WHO has
set up a collaborative relationship with a
number of centres of excellence. In the
mental health programme, which in¬
cludes drug dependence activities, col¬
laborating centres serve as a link bet¬
ween WHO and national authorities for
programme -purposes; they are respon¬
sible for formal and informal exchange
of information at national, regional and
global levels, and they function as focal
points for specific research activities,
and as training centres.
So far, five centres have been
designated WHO Collaborating Centres
for Research and Training in Drug
Dependence: the Addiction Research
Foundation, Toronto, Canada; the Mex¬
ican Centre of Studies on Pharmaco-
dependency, Mexico City; the National
Institute on Drug Abuse, Rockville,
Maryland, USA; the Drug Dependence
Research Project, University of Sains,
Penang, Malaysia; and the Health
Research Institute, Chulalongkorn
University, Bangkok, Thailand.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Lifelines
'Treatment
is a cultural process
and a social act'
Treatment of the individual with a drug problem must
be congruent with the ways of feeling, thinking and
acting normally proposed by the society and culture
from which that individual derives. Treatment and
rehabilitation must aim to restore the drug user to
functioning as a social being within that natural en¬
vironment. Treatment itself is a cultural process and a
social act, and will only succeed if it is sensitively in
tune with all that surrounds it.
THAILAND. A vow to the Buddha: Dr.
V. Poshyachinda gives an account of
the treatment of narcotic addicts at the
Tarn Kraborg temple.
Since Thailand became a united free
country over 700 years ago, Buddhism has
been the national religion. The temple and
the priest stand as dominating influences in
society, serving many public welfare func¬
tions such as education and health care. It
has been a natural evolution for the Bud¬
dhist temple to assume the role of treatment
centre in response to the growth of drug
dependence.
The Tarn Kraborg temple is about 130 km
north of Bangkok. It provides simple treat¬
ment facilities. A few wooden benches and
tables placed on an open verandah serve as
the intake registration unit. The living
quarters for the clients are a single spacious
hall not unlike a military barracks. A low
wooden couch, a reed mattress and a
blanket are provided for each client. When
full, the temple holds 300-400 resident
clients and about 100 priests. About forty of
the priests are former clients who were or¬
dained after treatment.
Treatment is carried out by a priest. The
temple never has to resort to hired staff.
While the treatment is free, the charge for
subsistence is about US 1 dollar per day. In
the last few years, the temple has developed
additional supportive services for vocational
training, including cultivation of crops,
masonry and tailoring of ready-to-wear
clothes.
The goal is complete drug abstinence for
life. To enter the programme, the client
must make a clear statement of determina¬
tion to seek treatment. Then the client
makes his vow to the Buddha. The vow is in
essence a pledge of abstinence for life from
opium, morphine, heroin, ganja and other
drugs that cause dependence.
The daily treatment schedule for the first
five days comprises two principal sessions
which the clients attend in groups. A dose
of herbal medicine is given in the morning,
which induces immediate vomiting for about
10-15 minutes. In the afternoon session the
clients take a herbal steam bath for 10-15
minutes. This cycle of sessions is explained
to the client as the means whereby drugs
can be purged from the body. In the morn¬
ing session, clients who have already par¬
ticipated in the first five days join actively in
the treatment. Some assist by nursing
others through the vomiting session, while
others cheer their fellows with spirited
native tunes and jokes. The atmosphere is
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
-
J T
In Thailand, a new arrival at a treatment centre for drug dependence begins an
attempt to break his drug habit with a morning dose of herbal medicine (see
story below)
not unlike that of a lively competitive game
at a temple festival.
For the remaining five days, there is no
prescribed schedule. The client is left to
recover from his physical exhaustion. The
priest usually encourages those who feel
physically strong enough and are so inclined
to help in the daily chores or assist in the
treatment session for newcomers.
On the tenth and last days of admission,
the clients are assembled again in the shrine
and reminded of their pledge; they are then
free to leave the temple.
HONG KONG. Houses called "Humani¬
ty", "Righteousness", "Fortitude" and
"Wisdom": Dr. J. Chi'en describes the
therapeutic community facility in a
comprehensive community-based reha¬
bilitation scheme for narcotic addicts
which is much In tune with traditional
Chinese values. This rehabilitation net¬
work was set up by the Society for the
Aid and Rehabilitation of Drug Addicts
(SARDA).
In 1946 the long-standing monopoly
system and the legalized sale of opium were
abolished in Hong Kong. In the late 1940s
and early 1950s large numbers of refugees
came from China to escape from the civil
war; many of them were opium smokers
who switched to heroin abuse after arrival.
Therapeutic communities are organized,
for those who are motivated, for fuller
rehabilitation after detoxification. A full
course of rehabilitation runs from twenty to
twenty-five weeks. A detoxified patient is in¬
vited to join any one of eighteen houses,
each of which is a group-living, working and
recreational unit, with its own dormitory, tea
house, workshop and vegetable garden or
animal farm.
The new resident earns his acceptance by
the house-group through helpfulness in the
dormitory and diligence in work, while the
senior residents give him encouragement
and advice. Confrontation techniques and
attack therapy, as practised in North
American therapeutic communities, are
seldom applied because traditional Chinese
culture advocates harmony and co¬
operation.
Each house bears the title of a cultural *
value such as "Humanity", "Righteous- f
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ness", "Fortitude" and "Wisdom".
Leaders, who are mostly people who have
gone through the programme and suc¬
cessfully completed the after-care period,
are trained to serve as group leaders and
trade instructors under the supervision of
senior professional staff. Inter-group com¬
petition in cleanliness, work production,
arts, and sports is encouraged and fair play
as well as honesty are promoted. There is a
weekly "graduation" ceremony and enter¬
tainment programme to bid farewell to those
completing the full course of rehabilitation.
After leaving the centre the newly
discharged are welcomed by their respective
after-care workers at the head office of the
Alumni Association (AA) of SARDA, which
is a self-help and mutual support organiza¬
tion composed of and managed by ex-
addicts. There are five such chapters for
men and one for women, each with 200 to
300 members. Those who can maintain
drug-free and crime-free living for six
months are accepted by the respective
chapter as associate members, and those
who lead a productive life for two years in
the community qualify for full membership.
Badges bearing the insignia of AA in dif¬
ferent colours to signify different numbers
of years of continued abstinence from nar¬
cotics, are worn proudly by its members.
JAPAN. Dr. H. Suwaki describes the
organization and working ofDanshukai,
the Alcohol Abstinence Society. Wives
and children can become members.
There are some noticeable differences in
the treatment of alcoholism between Japan
and the West. Alcoholics Anonymous (AA),
which is popular in the West, is found in on¬
ly limited areas of Japan such as Yokohama
and Kobe where Westerners live together.
Instead of AA, Danshukai (Alcohol Absti¬
nence Society) is widespread throughout
Japan. A very active Danshukai was orga¬
nized in Kochi Prefecture in 1958. The
founder had himself been admitted to a
mental hospital five times for alcoholism.
By 1977 one was established in every
prefecture in Japan, with 586 chapters and
35,000 registered alcoholic members.
Twenty-five thousand members were atten¬
ding the meetings in 1977, and 16,000 had
abstained from alcohol over one year.
The activities of the Danshukai are family
and experience oriented and rooted in the
local community. Regular ineetings of the
headquarters, chapters and hospital groups
are held from one to four times a month.
Usually one of the experienced members
takes the chair. Psychiatrists, social workers
and psychologists co-operate with the Dan¬
shukai and often attend meetings. A small
meeting, called a block meeting, is held at
the homes of members who live neareach
other and want to come together. In addi¬
tion to the meetings, the members par¬
ticipate in various recreational activities to
develop closer relations among the members
and their families. They also join the other
Danshukai and Alcohol Abstinence schools
in neighbouring prefectures, and read the
Danshukai bulletin.
The Danshukai has affirmed the following
three principles as its basic policy, in the
light of the experience accumulated so far:
a) There is no alternative but for
alcoholics to abstain from drinking, since
they cannot drink moderately.
b) An alcoholic cannot cure the disease
by himself. The way to a successful cure is
Below, members of the Alumni Association
of Hong Kong's Society for the Aid and
Rehabilitation of Addicts (SARDA) gather
to take part in their "Walk for a Million".
This annual event raises funds for the
Community Chest for Hong Kong which
provides many voluntary welfare agencies
with financial support. Above, "drug-free
badges" are awarded at the Association's
annual assembly.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
open only when those who have suffered
alcoholism encourage each other at a Dan¬
shukai meeting.
c) Co-operation of the family, particularly
of wives, is indispensable for alcoholics to
continue abstaining.
The wives and children of Danshukai
members usually belong to the same Dan¬
shukai as their husbands or fathers,
although some Danshukai have developed
wives' groups as an extended activity.
Almost all the members are male
alcoholics. There are not more than twenty
female alcoholics in the Danshukai through¬
out Japan. Danshukai is not anonymous.
Many Danshukai publish the addresses of
the members, and outside persons can join
the meeting and talk freely in the group.
The treatment of alcoholism will not serve
its purpose well if it deals merely with
physical and psychological needs. It must
contain elements of an individual's beliefs,'
which largely have their roots in his cultural
traditions.
Male alcoholics and their wives attend a weekly meeting
of a branch of Danshukai, Japan's Alcohol Abstinence
Society.
ALCOHOLICS ANONYMOUS. Dr. D.
Robinson analyses the cultural origins
and international diffusion ofAA, a self-
help group which has shown an extraor¬
dinary ability to reach the needs of the
alcoholic. What have the professionals
to learn?
Of all self-help groups Alcoholics
Anonymous (AA) has perhaps the most well
developed written history. AA originated in
the chance meeting at Akron, Ohio, in the
summer of 1935 between Robert Holbrook
Smith, a local doctor, and William Wilson, a
New York stockbroker. A year earlier,
Wilson had been introduced to the Oxford
Group Movement by a friend who said he
was staying sober by attending their small
discussion-group meetings and following
their precepts: confession, honesty, talking
out of emotional problems, unselfishness,
making reparations and praying to God as
personally conceived.
Impressed by his friend's efforts, Wilson
attended some meetings and after a spiritual
awakening found that he also could remain
sober. However, he failed to convert other
alcoholics because of what his doctor called
"too much preaching". So he decided to try
to convince them that they had some kind of
physical allergy and mental obsession and
only to introduce the spiritual aspects later.
This worked first with "Dr. Bob".
Alcoholics Anonymous did not invent the
idea of addiction, or loss of control, any
more than they invented total abstinence as
the only goal of treatment. Nevertheless
they played a major part in the development
of the new disease conception of alcoholism
in the post-Prohibition period.
Alcoholics Anonymous would not have
developed as rapidly as it has done if it had
not been based on ideas that were compati¬
ble with dominant ideas in the American
culture. The USA in the nineteenth century
was above all a middle-class nation in which
an open capitalist society required in¬
dividuals to regulate their business, family
and personal activities in order to survive
and succeed.
At that time, in both Europe and North
America, madness was increasingly being
defined as a disease, the chief symptom of
which was loss of control. The asylum was
changing from being a place of chains and
physical control to becoming a place to
restore, through moral treatment, the power
of self-discipline to those who had lost it. It
became natural, therefore, to redefine
almost all evil or deviance, including alcohol
problems, as disease of will. And, because
self-reliance had become such an essential
feature of belief and culture, in the USA
anything that undermined self-reliance or
self-control became a matter of great impor¬
tance. Liquor was regarded as important
since it would weaken inhibitions in the
short run and deprive people of the ability to
live restrained, moderate and controlled
lives. In AA terms, it could make their lives
'unmanageable".
Just as AA's ideas about the nature of the
problem had to be compatible with domi¬
nant ideas, thought and culture in the USA,
so did the principles underpinning its pro¬
gramme of action. At a personal level the
programme aims at transforming the depen¬
dent, isolated, drinking alcoholic into an in¬
dependent, integrated, sober alcoholic. At a
group level AA aims at being a self-reliant,
self-sufficient organization, beholden to no
one and dependent on no one. It remains
uninvolved in outside philosophical, politi¬
cal, social or spiritual issues although it co¬
operates with other bodies in order to help
to bring as many alcoholics to sobriety as it
can and help them to "conform to the
norms of a dominant middle-class society"-
It is not surprising therefore that AA
should be so well regarded in North
America. However, the fellowship has now
grown from its meagre beginnings, in Akron
in 1935, into a worldwide organization of
groups. By 1974, the General Service Board
of AA was claiming that world membership
had reached 800,000 and by 1977 well over
1 ,000,000. There are groups now in over 100
different countries from Norway to
Nicaragua and from Trinidad'to Thailand.
On a worldwide scale Alcoholics Anony¬
mous has groups in Catholic and Protestant
countries, in developed and developing
countries, in beer-producing and wine-
producing countries, in countries with
private medical care and those with State
health care systems. But although AA is
widespread, its development has, naturally,
been uneven. It is also thin in Eastern
Europe although there are the well-known
clubs in Yugoslavia and elsewhere which
operate on somewhat similar lines to A.A. In
the Middle East and India very many of the
members are employees of foreign firms,
while in Asia many of the groups were
started by the US forces. But in all areas of
the world the number of groups is growing.
Two major themes run through most of
the accounts of why self-help health groups
are flourishing today. The first is the disillu¬
sionment with existing helping services: the
feeling that expectations have not been
fulfilled or that services are unable to pro¬
vide the kind of care that is needed. The
second is the recognition that in many
societies the traditional support systems
such as the church, the neighbourhood and
the extended family are in decline. As a
result there is a search for community by
people who feel helpless and without con¬
trol over their own lives. For many, the
world has moved too fast, is too big and is
too indifferent to quality, to individual dif¬
ferences and to the basic human needs of
understanding, friendship and support.
Alcoholics Anonymous has never been^
made the subject of an international study, f
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
It is not possible, therefore, to say how the
fellowship has adapted to varying socio-
cultural circumstances. But given the well-
known variation between groups within the
same city it is reasonable to assume that AA
in Thailand is somewhat different from AA
in Nicaragua. This is one of the strengths of
the fellowship: its ability to adapt to the
needs of its members, provided always that
it keeps faith with the surprisingly few core
principles and practices which are the
essence of AA.
There is no doubt that Alcoholics Anony¬
mous, with its basis of mutual concern and
continuing support together with its record
of, and public commitment to, co-operation
with others working in the field, could have
a part to play in an overall response to
alcohol-related problems in any country.
UNITED KINGDOM. Dr. R. Wille ex¬
amines the "natural processes" which
interacted with the drug maintenance
treatment given by a clinic to bring
about the eventual recovery of one
young heroin addict.
Treatment is only one variable in a very
complex field of forces. We need to con¬
sider how people do things for themselves,
how they use friends and families, how their
lives interact with chance and life events,
and then see treatment in this context in¬
sofar as it adds to those natural processes.
Bob 0. started using heroin at the age of
sixteen. He had four criminal convictions
between the ages of eleven and seventeen.
His first clinic attendance was at the age of
eighteen in June 1968. His first prescription
was for 120 mg heroin. By 1969 his prescrip¬
tion had become reduced to 30 mg heroin
and 30 mg methadone. During this period
(1969) his life was becoming more and more
chaotic. He started to inject sleeping pills,
lost his job, and was found unconscious on
the road by the police with an accidental
overdose of barbiturates. He comments on
the first reduction in 1969: "It was a period
when I wasn't ready to come down. And if
the doctors force you down then, ifs just a
waste of time".
At the beginning of 1970 his prescription
was increased to 70 mg heroin and 40 mg
methadone, a dose on which he was kept
until 1972. At this time a gradual stabiliza¬
tion of his drug use and social situation
began. He was worried by his physical
deterioration, his abscesses and overdoses,
the death of his best friend from a bar¬
biturate overdose, the decline of his old drug
scene, and his mother's illness and her com¬
plaints about his way of life. He ceased tak¬
ing sleeping pills and started working
regularly. He stopped his contact with the
drug scene and became, as he expressed it,
a "loner". He undertook a slow reduction of
drugs over the next two years and regarded
this as the best possible way for him to
become abstinent.
Why was this second reduction suc¬
cessful? Bob O. reported that he made the
decision because he met his new girl-friend
who did not want to marry him as long as he
was addicted. After ten years of heroin use
he became abstinent at the age of twenty-
six, married his girl-friend and, a short time
afterwards, completed a course as a
carpenter and started a successful career.
He has his own house and car, and has been
abstinent now for four years.
For Bob O., the development of a new
social role manifested by a stable job and a
significant relationship interacted with
chance and life events. Therapeutic efforts
were successful when they complemented
these social changes.
Dr. V. Poshyachinda is attached to the Institute
of Health Research, Chulalongkorn University,
Bangkok, Thailand.
Mr. J. Chi'en is Superintendent of Social Ser¬
vices, The Society for the Aid and Rehabilitation
of Drug Addicts, Hong Kong.
Dr. H. Suwaki is a member of the Department of
Neuropsychiatry, Kochi Medical School, Japan.
Dr. D. Robinson is a member of the Addiction
Research Unit of the Institute of Psychiatry,
London.
Dr. R. Wille is a member of the Addiction
Research Unit of the Institute of Psychiatry,
London.
24
Alcohol consumption in 25 countries per capita (15
in litres of 100 per cent ethanol.
years and older)
Country*
Consumption
1976
Average annual
percentage change
1970-1976
France 21.3 - 2
Portugal 19.4 + 4
Spain 19.3 + 2
Luxembourg 16.8 + 0.6
Italy 16.8 - 3
Fed. Rep. of Germany 15.8 - 0.2
Austria 14.6 + 2
New Zealand 13.7 + 4
Hungary 13.4 + 0.6
Australia 13.3 + 1
Switzerland 13.2 - 2
Belgium 13.2 0
Ireland 12.6 + 12
Yugoslavia 12.0 + 3
Czechoslovakia 11.9 - 3
Denmark 11.8 + 4
Canada 11.7 + 4
Netherlands 11.1 + 7
United Kingdom 11.0 + 5
Poland 10.8 + 7
USA 10.7 + 2
German Dem. Rep. 10.5 0
Finland 8.1 + 5
Sweden 7.4 - 1
Norway 5.6 + 5
byorder of consumption.
Sources: International Labour Organisation
Gedistilleerde Dranken (1977).
(1977); United Nations (1977). Produktschap voor
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
An ABC of drugs
Natural and synthetic substances
under international control
The opium poppy [Papaver
somniferum L.)
This article has been extracted from a booklet The
United Nations and Drug Abuse Control produc¬
ed by the UN Division of Narcotic Drugs, Geneva
(United Nations, New York, 1977).
Natural and
synthetic opiates
Opium. Opium is the coagulated juice from
the unripe capsule of the poppy plant scien¬
tifically known as Papaver somniferum. It
can be grown in most areas of the world,
and in a number of countries it is cultivated
for its seeds or beautiful flowers rather than
for its opium content. The seeds, which
constitute a valuable oil-containing food, are
pressed for oil or used in cakes and pastry.
The poppy is an annual plant and most pro¬
bably originated in the Mediterranean region
and in the Middle East.
The earliest recorded knowledge of opium
is to be found in the Sumerian tablets.
Sumerians lived in Lower Mesopotamia
(modern Iraq) around 5000 BC. Later,
knowledge of the poppy's medicinal proper¬
ties was introduced to Persia and Egypt by
the Babylonians. The Greeks and Arabs also
used opium for medicinal purposes. The first
recorded instance of poppy cultivation in In¬
dia dates from the eleventh century, and
production and consumption of opium in
that country became extensive in the six¬
teenth century during Mongol rule.
Opium was probably introduced to China
by the Arabs in the ninth or tenth century.
The drug was also known in Europe in the
Middle Ages, and the famous physician
Paracelsus administered it to his patients.
Opium was medically a very important
drug, but the prominent place it held in
therapy has been taken over by certain of its
alkaloid (morphine and codeine), and syn¬
thetic opiates (pethidine and methadone).
Formerly a useful therapeutic agent, opium
has now become an important raw material
for the manufacture of morphine and co¬
deine.
As a pleasure-giving drug, opium was
originally eaten or taken as an infusion. The
smoking of opium is a comparatively recent
development, going back only a few hun¬
dred years.
The abuse of opium and its dérivâtes
(morphine and heroin) was the primary con¬
cern of the first international attempts to en¬
force control of narcotic drugs.
Morphine. Morphine is the main active
principle of opium. The average morphine
content of opium is about 10 per cent. Mor¬
phine is extracted either from opium or,
directly, from the poppy straw (the dried
capsules and the upper part of the stems of
the opium poppy after mowing). The use of
the poppy straw process eliminates the pro¬
duction of opium and greatly reduces all
risks of abuse and illicit traffic. This process
has expanded greatly and, in recent years,
about one third of the world's medical re¬
quirements for morphine has been manufac¬
tured from poppy straw.
Morphine was widely used for the relief of
short-term acute pain resulting from
surgery, fractures and burns and in the final
stages of terminal illnesses. Through the in¬
troduction of synthetic narcotics and other
analgesic drugs, the extent of use and the
therapeutic importance of morphine have
been considerably diminished (but it is still
considered to be the prototype of the nar¬
cotic drug).
Codeine and other morphine
derivatives. Codeine, an effective cough
suppressant, is one of the most commonly
and widely employed medicaments. Co¬
deine (methylmorphine) occurs in opium in
low concentration, but for the market is
manufactured principally by the conversion
of morphine. This explains the apparent
contradiction between the decrease in the
therapeutic use of morphine and the in¬
crease in its production:, more than 90 per
cent of the morphine produced by the phar¬
maceutical industry is converted into co¬
deine. It has properties which resemble
those of morphine but its analgesic effects
are milder.
Cases of codeine addiction are relatively
rare, as dependence develops only after
continued consumption of large quantities
over a considerable period of time.
Heroin. Heroin (diacetylmorphine) is deriv¬
ed from morphine by acetylation. On the
recommendation of the World Health
Organization and the Commission on Nar¬
cotic Drugs, it has been banned in most
countries, and its use in medicine has been
replaced by other, less dangerous v
analgesics. f
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Heroin is perhaps the most addictive of all
known drugs. The intense euphoria produc¬
ed by the drug has made heroin the most
popular morphine derivative among addicts.
The quality of the drug available on the
black market relates to several illicit ac¬
tivities, and during the long process from
the clandestine laboratory to the smuggler
and from the smuggler to the street addict,
the original heroin is diluted so many times
that the white (or pink or brown) stuff in a
"bag" may not contain more than 3 to 5 per
cent heroin, in some countries. Adulteration
of heroin is the easiest way for traffickers to
increase their profit.
Synthetic opiates. The term "synthetic
opiates" or "synthetic narcotics" is general¬
ly applied to a number of addictive
substances which have come onto the
market since the discovery of pethidine by
German chemists some thirty years ago.
When first marketed, pethidine was claimed
to be devoid of addictive potential; ex¬
perience, however, has proved otherwise.
Addiction is slower to develop and is less
vicious than addiction to morphine, but this
potential does exist.
The mushrooming development of
various new synthetic drugs and their ap¬
pearance on the market, accompanied
sometimes by unproven claims that they do
not produce drug dependence, have led the
Commission on Narcotic Drugs to repeat
warnings to Governments to apply im¬
mediately provisional control measures to
these substances, pending the definite
evaluation of their effects by the World
Health Organization. The Commission has
taken the view that in such cases commer¬
cial interests must yield to overriding con¬
siderations of public health. In this connex¬
ion, it has also been stressed that, without
encroaching upon the freedom of the press,
a way should be sought to prohibit
misleading publicity and advertising of pro¬
perties of newly developed drugs.
26
A plant of the genus
cannabis
Cannabis
The products of the plant Cannabis sativa L.
have been used by millions of people as an
intoxicant over the last four or five thousand
years. It is used in various forms. People
smoke it, often combined with tobacco, or
mix its resin with drinks or in sweetmeats.
Such use is still tolerated in some countries.
There are few areas in the world where
cannabis cannot be grown successfully.
Depending on the soil, the climatic condi¬
tions and the degree of cultivation, this
weed-like plant may reach a height of from
one to twenty feet. The cannabis plant or
the crude drug derived from it and folk
preparations of cannabis are known under
hundreds of different names. The intox¬
icating constituents of the cannabis resin
(known as hashish) are found mainly in the
flowering tops, particularly of the female
plant. Cannabis resin was the most potent
form of cannabis, until recent years, when a
new cannabis product appeared on the illicit
market: liquid cannabis is a concentrate con¬
taining sometimes up to 60 per cent of THC
(tetrahydrocannabinol) and is more dang¬
erous than other forms of cannabis.
There are indications that the intoxicating
effects of cannabis depend largely on the
amount of THC present in the "cannabis"
used.
According to the Single Convention,
1961, the term "cannabis" means, "the
flowering or fruiting tops of the cannabis
plant (excluding the seeds and leaves when
not accompanied by the tops) from which
the resin has not been extracted, by
whatever name they may be designated"
but in common parlance the use of the term
"cannabis" can differ from this definition,
and the expressions "cannabis", "mari¬
juana" or "hashish" embrace a range of dif¬
ferent cannabis preparations.
Cannabis has become, from the medical
point of view, an obsolete remedy. It has
therefore been recommended that its use be
discontinued in medical practice, but it is
still used for the treatment of certain
ailments by local medical practitioners in
some countries in Asia.
In certain countries, the consumption of
cannabis has been a traditional custom for
centuries, particularly in regions where the
consumption of alcohol is prohibited.
From Unesco...
Further information
on drugs
Drugs Demystified, by Helen Nowlis. This
pamphlet published by the Unesco Press is
available in English, Arabic, French German,
Italian, Portuguese, Spanish, Swedish and
Thai.
The Aetiology of Psychoactive Substance
Use. A report and critically annotated
bibliography on research into the aetiology of
alcohol, nicotine, opiate and other psychoactive
substance use, by C. Fazey. Carried out with
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A coca bush {Erythroxylon coca)
Coca leaf and cocaine
The coca bush is an evergreen shrub
Erythroxylon coca which grows in western
South America. The leaves have been chew¬
ed for centuries in some parts of South
America by highland peoples. The leaves are
also the raw material for the manufacture of
cocaine.
Since the habit of coca-leaf chewing is
conditioned by a number of unfavourable
social and economic factors, the solution of
the problem involves two fundamental and
parallel aspects; the need for improving the
living conditions of the population among
which coca-leaf chewing is a general habit
and the need for initiating simultaneously a
governmental policy to limit the cultivation
of the coca leaf, control its distribution and
eradicate the practice of chewing. The U.N.
Economic and Social Council has recom¬
mended that the countries affected by the
coca-leaf chewing habit be assisted in their
efforts to eradicate this practice.
Cocaine, a potent stimulant* drug, is the
principal alkaloid of the coca leaf and can be
extracted from coca leaves. It was first used
as a local anaesthetic a century ago, but its
therapeutic importance has diminished with
the introduction of other anaesthetic drugs.
In the case of abuse, the stimulant effect of
cocaine results in excitability, talkativeness
and a diminished feeling of fatigue. Cocaine
may produce euphoria and the sensation of
increased muscular strength. Stimulation is
followed by a period of depression. High
doses of cocaine lead to suspiciousness,
fear, hallucinations (characteristics of a
paranoid psychosis) and aggressive and
antisocial behaviour may occur. Effects of
cocaine aré similar to the effects produced
by amphetamines.
* Pharmacologically speaking cocaine is a stimulant
of the central nervous system, legally it is controlled
by the Single Convention on Narcotic Drugs.
Adopted in 1961, the United Nations Single Conven¬
tion on Narcotics came into force in 1964. It replac¬
ed nine existing treaties on international narcotics
control, extended control to the cultivation of
plants from which "natural" narcotic drugs (opium,
cannabis, coca leaves) are obtained, and simplified
the international control machinery. It was amend¬
ed in 1972 with the aim of further strengthening the
international drug control system.
the financialsupport of the United Nations Fund
for Drug Abuse Control (UNFDAC), 1977. 48
French francs.
SOS Drogue, a 16 mm colour film produced in
1979 by the Ivory Coast out-of-school television
education service (in French).
The Jigsaw Puzzle of Drugs. The Unesco
Courier, May 1973.
Requests should be addressed to: Mme N.
Friederich, Education concerning problems con¬
nected with use of drugs, Unesco, Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, France.
LSD
Hallucinogens
The great civilizations offer numerous ex¬
amples of the use of substances producing
hallucinations. The ritual consumption of
hallucinogenic mushrooms in America, the
use of other intoxicating mushrooms by
sorcerers in Asia and the use of certain
plants for witchcraft in Europe are only a
few examples of the diversity of the "tradi¬
tional" hallucinogens, but recently the term
"hallucinogenic" has been more associated
with Lysergic acid diethylamide (LSD)
(STP), (DMT) and other new substances.
Hallucinogens constitute a heterogeneous
class of substances, belonging to a wide
variety of chemical and pharmacological
groups. The propagation of their abuse and
its resultant 'effects have led to the interna¬
tional control of a number of hallucinogens.
The guiding principle of the Convention on
Psychotropic Substances, 1971, in the
selection of hallucinogenic substances to be
controlled is expressed in Article 2 of that
Convention. A substance should be subject
to control "if the World Health Organization
finds: that the substance has the capacity to
produce... central nervous system stimula¬
tion or depression, resulting in hallucina¬
tions or disturbances in motor function or
thinking or behaviour or perception or
mood... and that there is sufficient evidence
that the substance is being or is likely to be
abused so as to constitute a public health
and social problem."
LSD. Lsd (LSD-25, lysergide) is an abbrevia¬
tion of the German expression for lysergic
acid diethylamide Lysergsäure Diäthylamid).
LSD is a synthetic or, more precisely, a
semi-synthetic compound, since it is not
found as such in any natural material, but is
produced from lysergic acid, a natural
substance found in ergot of rye.
For a "psychedelic trip", 100-250 micro-
grammes (1 microgramme .= 0,000001 Gm)
of LSD are used in the form of a diluted
solution or mixed with other substances in
capsule form. Drops of the solution are
usually taken on a lump of sugar or on blot¬
ting paper.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Hallucinogenic mushrooms.. Peyote cactus.
, The ingestion of LSD produces changes
in mood, alteration in sense of time, distor¬
tion in visual and auditory perception,
depersonalization, derealization, auditory
and optical hallucinations.
The most common reactions during a trip
are as follows:
Panic reaction: this appears when the
"traveller" becomes aware that he cannot
control the effects of LSD; he cannot beat
them and tries in vain to end them.
Paranoid reaction: under the effect of
LSD, he has the impression that someone
wants to imprison him or "control his
mind".
Mescaline. Mescaline is the active principle
of the peyote cactus. The scientific name of
this cactus is Lophophora Wil/iamsii; its
popular name, peyote, appears to be of
Aztec origin. This small, fleshy, spineless
cactus grows wild on the Mexican plateau
and in the south-western part of the United
States in dry places, on cliffs or on rocky
slopes.
Peyote was used and revered as a
panacea, an amulet and a hallucinogen in
the mountainous regions of northern Mex¬
ico centuries before the European arrived, in
the 15th century. Peyote has long been
taken by the Huichol Indians, as a medicine,
to induce visions leading to prophetic ut¬
terances and, collectively to obtain the
desired state of trance for ritual activities.
(See Unesco Courier, February 1979.).
Mescaline is a less potent hallucinogen
than LSD, but its effects are very similar,
with personality disturbances and symp¬
toms similar to those of schizophrenia.
Psilocybine, psilocine. Psylocybine and
psilocine are the active principles of the
hallucinogenic mushroom Psilocybe mex¬
icana. This fungus is the most important of
the sacred mushrooms worshipped by the
Indians of Mexico, who have long used
"teonanacatl" (flesh of the gods) in Aztec
religious rites.
Due to the care used by the Indians in
withholding information, it was only a few
years ago that some of the sacred
mushrooms, including Psilocybe, could be
identified. The pharmacological study of
these compounds has confirmed the strong
hallucinogenic properties of the drug.
DMT, DET. DMT and DET are abbrevia¬
tions for dimethyltryptamine and
diethyltryptamine, respectively. Both pro¬
duce strong hallucinogenic effects. DMT is
also the active principle of a number of
South American snuffs, which are snuffed
into the nasal cavity.
Such central substances are used by the
Indians in religious ceremonies to produce
mystical states of mind which are said to
enable them to communicate with their
gods.
Psilocine and psilocybine are chemically
closely related to DMT.
STP. The letters "STP" (dimethoxy-
methamphetamine) designate a synthetic
compound produced in "underground"
laboratories. STP is chemically related to
mescaline and the amphetamines; its action
is of longer duration than that of LSD.
THC. THC designates tetrahydrocan¬
nabinol, one the active principles of can¬
nabis. THC is a very potent hallucinogenic
drug, with pharmacological effects showing
several similarities to those of LSD; these
are changes in mood, alteration in sense of
time, distortion in visual and auditory
perception, depersonalization, derealization,
auditory and optical modifications.
However, there are indications that the two
drugs probably act through different
biochemical mechanisms, and their effects
on brain function are somewhat different.
Amphetamine-type stimulants
and sedative-hypnotics.
Stimulants
The most important stimulants are the am¬
phetamines. The term "amphetamines" in¬
cludes synthetic amines which are similar in
many respects to the human body's hor¬
mone adrenalin. Amphetamines, like co¬
caine, suppress appetite, increase activity
and alertness and arouse the central nervous
system. These drugs were synthesized at
the beginning of the 20th century and used
therapeutically in the 1930s. Because of their
stimulating effects amphetamines were
widely used by soldiers, particularly pilots
during the Second World War. Am¬
phetamine, dexamphetamine, metham-
phetamine are the most common
substances of this group. Other substances
such as phenmetrazineand methylphenidate
have very similar pharmacological effets.
Stimulants are widely used and abused by
truck drivers on long trips, by students when
preparing for exams, and by athletes (dop¬
ing) in efforts to increase performance.
Widespread abuse of amphetamines has
occurred during the last thirty years in urban
areas of many countries. In some countries
the abuse reached epidemic proportions
which compelled the authorities to put these
substances under strict control.
The therapeutic value of such medicines is
rather limited, being confined, in practice, in
some countries to two types of cases in
which they are used: (i) as stimulants in
selected conditions and (ii) for the treatment
of obesity. Since these substances have a
strong suppressive effect on appetite this
action disappears after a few weeks as well
as their stimulating effect, unless the dose is
increased. In the opinion of some experts,
the prescription of amphetamines is justified
only for the treatment of narcolepsy (a very
rare illness).
In contrast with the limited medicinal use
of amphetamines, there is a large-scale illicit
traffic and abuse of these drugs in certain
countries.
Amphetamines, as medicine, are general¬
ly taken in the form of tablets and
capsules.The most harmful form of am¬
phetamine abuse is produced by the ad-
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
ministration of excessive doses of metham-
phetamine ("speed") intravenously. This
new phenomenon of injecting stimulants
may last several days and is characterized at
the end of the "run" by a state of hostility,
aggression and paranoia produced by the
continued administration intravenously of
massive doses of "speed". Heavy abusers of
stimulants are not able to work regularly
because of their drug dependence.
Amphetamines and other stimulants are
very often abused in combination or in alter¬
nation with other drugs such as barbiturates
or opiates. It is worth noting that STP
(dimethoxymethamphetamine) and MDA
(methylenedioxyamphetamine), two potent
hallucinogens, are chemically closely related
to the amphetamines.
Sedatives-hypnotics
Barbiturates. The most employed
sedatives-hypnotics belong to the group of
barbiturates. They have been used in
medicine for over half a century, and in a
number of countries they account for about
10 per cent of the medical prescriptions.
Barbiturates may be considered "safe" if
they are used under appropriate medical
supervision as hypnotics (sleeping pills) or
sedatives in small doses or in larger doses as
anaesthetics. Their therapeutic usefulness is
in marked contrast with that of the am¬
phetamines which is very limited. Regular
use of barbiturates produces profound
physical dependence.
In a number of countries, the use of bar¬
biturates is not subject to control. This has
serious consequences, such as the danger
of dependence; in addition, the uncontrolled
use of barbiturates may lead to combined
abuse that is, to the use of barbiturates in
conjunction with other substances. The
three most widespread and dangerous
associations are barbiturates when used in
combination with heroin, with alcohol or
with stimulants.
Minor tranquillizers. There are a large
number of medicaments known as minor
tranquillizers which are mainly prescribed for
patients suffering from an anxiety or ten¬
sion. Many of these substances are widely
used and abused. In many countries, the
production of, trade in and distribution of
these substances are not subject to effective
control (where there is any form of control)
and cases of addiction to minor tranquillizers
have been observed. Overdose fatalities due
to minor tranquillizers have been observed
but with less frequency than with the bar¬
biturates. Minor tranquillizers (such as
methaqualone, etc..) are often taken in
combination with other drugs to obtain
either longer lasting effects or enhance the
effects of other drugs.
Swallowed, sniffed, injected...
Many drugs are taken just by their be¬
ing swallowed. There is then a fairly long
interval between taking the drug and its
maximum impact on the brain, and learn¬
ing theory suggests that the time-interval
conditions will not be optimal for rapid
establishment of addiction, although
drugs taken in this manner can certainly
set up an addiction. Alcohol is a prime
example of a drug which is ingested; can¬
nabis may be swallowed in cakes or as an
infusion; opium may be eaten; and all
manner of synthetic substances are
taken in pill form. A rather more rapid
way of obtaining an effect from some
substances is to keep the drug in the
mouth pocketed against a cheek, and
hence the efficacity of tobacco or khat
chewing or coca taken in this manner.
For some drugs an even more effective
way of ensuring rapid absorption may be
to sniff or smoke the substance smok¬
ed tobacco, smoked opium, heroin taken
by "chasing the dragon", glue and
solvents which are inhaled, cocaine sniff¬
ing, smoked coca paste, and the can¬
nabis cigarette. The highly addictive
nature of cigarette smoking stems from
the fact that this rolled-up tube is a
brilliantly designed piece of technology
for getting nicotine very rapidly to the
brain each draw on the end of that
cigarette shoots another dose of nicotine
into the blood stream to reach the brain
within seconds.
But where technology really takes over
is with the availability of the needle and
the syringe, and drugs in injectable form.
Heroin derived from opium and injected
in this manner is going to be much more
rapidly addictive than the plant product
as traditionally smoked. However, the
major danger of this innovation is that
accidental over-dose becomes all too
easy, as do the possibilities of accidental¬
ly introducing contaminants or bacteria
into the blood stream. The traditional
opium smoker or opium eater did not
necessarily harm his health or shorten his
life. On the other hand the heroin injector
not only runs the risk of death by acute
over-dose, but of contracting infective
conditions as diverse as bacterial sep¬
ticaemia, tetanus, and malaria: average
life expectancy is shortened not directly
because of the heroin itself, but because
of the unsterile injection.
Griffith Edwards
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
A pill for every ill
by Ruth Cooperstock
RUTH COOPERSTOCK is on the staff of the
Addiction Research Foundation, Toronto, Ontario,
Canada.
Increasingly the world expects a
pill for every ill. What is to be
done about patient expectations
and medical prescribing? Dr.
Cooperstock focusses on
benzodiazepines (the minor
tranquillizer group which includes
such well-known products as
valium and librium).
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
THE pharmaceutical industry is expand¬
ing worldwide at an annual rate of
over 10 per cent. The benzodia¬
zepines, introduced in the early 1960s with
chlordiazepoxide (Librium) and then
diazepam (Valium), were initially marketed
as anti-anxiety agents. Psychiatric disorders
and the emotional discomforts of everyday
life were to be eliminated. Gradually, as
more benzodiazepines came on to the
market (and there are now scores of this
class of drug) the indications for their use
expanded to include not only daytime seda¬
tion, but also night-time sedation, muscle
relaxation and anti-convulsant therapy. Ad¬
ditionally, a number of combination drugs
appeared which included a benzodiazepine.
These were recommended for a wide range
of psychosomatic disorders. Acceptance of
the benzodiazepines was remarkably quick.
Within less than fifteen years diazepam was
the largest-selling drug in the world.
It is increasingly clear that use of ben¬
zodiazepines is not randomly distributed in
populations. Women receive twice as many
prescriptions as men. The elderly and the
chronically ill are the major recipients in ad¬
dition to people in institutions. It is in these
groups that long-term use is most likely.
Because of their ready availability, these
drugs, combined with alcohol, are the most
commonly found in overdoses in Canada
and the USA. Additional studies of motor
impairment (especially likely to affect driving
skills) and of impairment of intellectual func¬
tioning, judgement and social skills are now
appearing. Thus, while there are clear short-
term benefits from these drugs, an array of
minor and major problems have been
created by their use. Other problems of a
more subtle nature relate to some of the
social and behavioural consequences of use,
and are only now being explored.
Because of the numbers of people using
benzodiazepines over long periods, and
because of the issue of limited efficacy and
potential damage, it becomes essential to at
tempt to understand the reasons for these
prescriptions. A simple explanation fre¬
quently heard is that patients demand them.
Research, however, has shown that physi¬
cians are more likely to assume that patients
want medication than are the patients
themselves to want any. Perhaps most im¬
portant in an understanding of current
prescribing patterns is the acceptance by the
medical profession of a biomedical view of
man. This philosophical view sees the locus
of all problems that appear in the physician's
office as being within the individual, hence
requiring biological solutions.
We might ask what has been done to
reorient the concern of both prescribers and
consumers to the long-term use of these
drugs. Psychotropics represent a special
case in that the media and consumer groups
seem to have generated as much concern
about consumption patterns and conse¬
quences of using them as have governments
and the medical profession.
A recent issue of the British Journal of the
Royal College of General Practitioners dealt
almost exclusively with prescribing in
general practice. The editorial pointed out
that the interests of the Government, which
pays for drugs, and of the pharmaceutical
manufacturers are in conflict and "thus
combine to bombard the 25,000 prescribers
with ever-increasing pressures to conform
to one policy or another". It went on to say
"Certainly the use of tranquillizers has been
questioned increasingly and it is possible
that a prescription for tranquillizers can be
regarded as something of a therapeutic
failure". Governments have been sensitized
to the need for intervention, not only
because of escalating costs but also by
tragedies such as that which followed the in¬
troduction of thalidomide.
Consumer organizations in a number of
countries publish magazines that carry ex¬
tensive information on health services, in¬
cluding drug information. By and large,
however, the consumer's voice has not been
heard in this respect. Only in recent years
have research studies been directed away
from the traditional "compliance" studies of
drug consumption (which ask why the pa¬
tient does not take his drugs as ordered by
the physician) to studies which start from
the consumers' perspective. These studies
ask users of health services what they
perceive the social and emotional conse¬
quences of using tranquillizers to be, and
enquire also about physical effects.
Consciousness-raising and self-help groups
have been proposed as alternatives to tran¬
quillizers. In large cities there are self-help
groups to aid individuals who want to break
their tranquillizer habit.
There are thus two divergent trends in
medical care in developed countries. The
first is acceptance of the biomedical model
and its implications, leading to chemical
solutions to social and personal problems,
and the second, the increased questioning
of traditional modes of medical care. The lat¬
ter can be seen in the rejection by many pa¬
tients of the conventional form of the
physician-patient relationship, and by the in¬
creased use of non-conventional medicine in
the form of acupuncture, herbal medicines,
and other methods of healing. The ben¬
zodiazepines, represent a symbolic focal
point for these two trends, thus raising im¬
portant issues for all countries.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
No smoking, please
by Martin Raw
IN the United Kingdom, by the time
it began to be suspected that smoking
was dangerous, it was an established
habit in 65 per cent of adult males and 40 per
cent of adult females. Since 1973, there has
been a slow but steady decline in the
prevalence of smoking and in tobacco con¬
sumption; as a whole between then and
now smoking has become a minority habit
for the first time since 1945. A brief list of
anti-smoking activities can be divided into
seven main categories.
Health education: formal and informal.
These efforts have been associated with the
publication of research findings and of major
reports on smoking and health, the holding
MARTIN RAW is a psychologist at St. George's Hospital, London,
and is a specialist in research on smoking.
of world conferences, the formation in the
United Kingdom of the Health Education
Council (HEC) and of Action on Smoking
and Health (ASH), and formal education
campaigns launched by the HEC.
Legislation. The most important legisla¬
tion in the United Kingdom in this respect
was probably the banning of cigarette
advertising on television in 1965.
Non-legislative pressure on the tobacco
and advertising industries. In spite of
pressure on the British Government to in¬
troduce legislation on issues such as tobac¬
co advertising, it has consistently resisted
such pressure. However, it has attempted to
put pressure on the tobacco industry
through voluntary agreements.
Social control. The restriction of smoking
in public places has become increasingly ac¬
ceptable to the general public and is becom¬
ing commoner in an increasing number of
settings including London Transport
vehicles (1971), cinemas (1971) and
aeroplanes (1972).
Price control. It has been clearly
demonstrated that in Britain cigarette con¬
sumption responds to price, going down
when the cost of smoking goes up. This
represents one of the most powerful
available means of controlling consumption,
but the Government has not yet accepted
that it should use this means to reduce con¬
sumption.
Smoking withdrawal clinics. They do not
represent a large part of the anti-smoking ef¬
fort, though this is partly because they have
never been taken seriously by the health
authorities.
Direct anti-smoking advice from health
care professionals to their patients. The
evidence suggests that this advice could be
effective with various groups of patients,
the most important being patients of general
practitioners.
Once it was established that smoking was
dangerous, we were faced with a most dif¬
ficult problem. The health educators assum¬
ed that once they had persuaded the public
that smoking was dangerous, people would
give it up voluntarily. This assumption prov¬
ed naive, mainly because it did not take into
account and deal with, the many other fac¬
tors that affect smoking. Amongst these
were the addictive nature of the behaviour
itself and the considerable resources that
were being devoted to its promotion. It is
absurd that in the United Kingdom the
Health Education Council should be in a
position to spend only £1,000,000 (2 million
U.S. dollars) a year on anti-smoking ac¬
tivities whilst the tobacco industry spends
nearly £100,000,000 (200 million U.S.
dollars) to promote smoking. Yet the
Government has been loath to take any ac¬
tion that might reduce consumption,
because, it is presumed, of the considerable
revenue it derives from tobacco consump¬
tion. It seems all the more remarkable then
that some combination of fhe seven factors
described above has steadily reduced the
demand for tobacco over the last five years.
Although none of the approaches to the
control of smoking described here could by
itself achieve much (except for price
control), collectively and cumulatively they
are having an effect. However, they will not
solve the smoking problem until much
stronger action is taken by the Government
in those areas where it can act.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
A problem in constant evolution
by Griffith Edwards and Awni Arif
IT is impossible to think about, or help¬
fully respond to, any aspect of drug-
taking without at every stage seeing
drug-taking (and our responses to drug-
taking), in a socio-cultural context. Man or
woman abstracted from society and culture
is a fantasy. This is not to deny the impor¬
tance of understanding individual dif¬
ferences in constitution, but the individual,
however constituted, can live, move, and
have his being only in a culturally and social¬
ly determined environment.
This is not the place for an extended essay
on futurology but it would be futile to sup¬
pose that those who are specially concerned
with drug problems could divorce them from
the world in which we are going to live, and
the future of that world background. Shifts
and growth in world resources, new poverty
or new wealth, are likely to have a fun¬
damental impact on drug problems and to
determine how much money will be invested
in drug programmes.
Beyond those external and material
aspects of the future, drug use (and
response to drug problems) will be pro¬
foundly affected by such factors as values;
the place accorded the individual in society,
in every sense; the value put on freedom and
rights to pleasure-seeking; the importance
and essential meaning given to health. A
concern with these types of question is
sometimes dismissed as Utopian, but it
might be argued that one of the changes we
are seeing is a rediscovery that these ques¬
tions are exactly those which we have a right
to ask. If we ignore them, we do so at our
peril, and among those perils may be an ac¬
celeration in misuse of drugs, or misuse of
treatment and preventive actions.
In a world experiencing upheaval and
breakdown in old structures and values,
much of the long-standing equilibrium bet¬
ween societies and their use of drugs will
break down too. In the immediate future the
world is likely to experience an intensifica¬
tion of drug-related harm.
There is already a tendency towards world
homogeneity in drug use. Cannabis, which
until recent decades was largely indigenous
AWNI ARIF, of Iraq, is Senior Medical Officer
with the Drug Dependence Programme of the
World Health Organization's Division of Mental
Health. He was formerly Director-General of the
Preventive Medicine Service of the Iraqi Ministry
of Health.
to the East, has now become well establish¬
ed in Western societies. Alcohol, which has
been so much the traditional drug of the
Western world, is now increasingly giving
rise to problems in countries of the East. The
misuse of psychotropics is rapidly becoming
la universal problem. But, parallel with this
growing homogeneity, a previous unitary
pattern of drug use is fragmenting in many
cultures into a variety of patterns: plural
societies give rise to plural drug problems.
If we take the definition of what counts as
a problem as being essentially socially and
culturally determined we may also expect to
see profound shifts in the processes of
definition. What counts as a problem now
may not attract the same definition in ten
years; or new definitions of the problem may
emerge over that period.
It is possible, for instance, that in recent
years we have tended unduly to emphasize
drug use itself or the state of dependence as
the essential problem, rather than defining
the problem more fundamentally in terms of
consequent damage. On the one hand,
some societies are moving towards a more
tolerant view of forms of drug use that are
not very harmful but at present disallowed;
on the other, cigarette smoking is increas¬
ingly being regarded as a problem in terms
of the damage it causes. At present, alcohol
use is not seen in most countries as a
problem in terms of its mere use; it is
alcoholism that attracts concern. A move¬
ment is u nder way, however, to define a cer¬
tain level of alcohol use as a problem for
societies, given the probable association
between national drinking levels and the
amount of alcohol-related damage.
Even where there are no large changes in
the definition of problems, there may be
alterations in the ordering of problem
priorities. For example, a trend may be
emerging towards according a higher priori¬
ty to socially accepted drugs such as alcohol
and tobacco or licitly prescribed drugs such
as the benzodiazepines, in relation to the
traditionally illicit drugs. The dichotomy bet¬
ween policies directed towards licit drugs,
on the one hand, and illicit substances, on
the other, may be breaking down.
It is evident that in many parts of the
world socio-medical help at the most basic
level is still lacking for people in trouble with
their drug-taking. In many countries, still,
people often languish in prison instead of
receiving constructive help. Alcoholics die
of delirium tremens for lack of the most sim¬
ple technical knowledge. Much-needed
facilities for drug detoxification are lacking.
Even the rudiments of rehabilitation are
often missing. It must be hoped therefore
that one trend for the immediate future will
be an energetic effort to ensure that these
needs are met and organizational problems
tackled.
But, at the same time, care must be taken
that the extension of facilities does not
mean the cruder extension of the medical
model, which conditions the individual to
learned helplessness and the community,to
surrendering its responsibilities. The helping
professions must not expect or be expected
to take responsibilities for all problems. A
response planned in terms of medical care
alone would be not only beyond the
economic resources of any country, but also
likely to be largely ineffective. What is need¬
ed rather is the further development of a
model that would see treatment as a part¬
nership between the individual, the com¬
munity and the helping professions, with the
helping professions in an assistant role.
Also, it seems likely that over the next
decade there will be increasing interest in
what were previously deemed to be the non-
specifics of treatment: set and expectation,
the role and self-definition given, the op¬
timism that is engendered, the goals that are
collaboratively defined, the sense of
autonomy that can be restored, and the
therapeutic relationship. The hope for the
future must be more in terms of understand¬
ing and developing those processes and less
an expectation of . wonderful new
technologies. There must, of course, be a
willingness to explore further the alliance
.between natural processes that foster and
reinforce recovery and active treatment.
With regard to prevention, the same basic
theme of the need for congruence between
society's response and the socio-cultural
context needs to be emphasized as the issue
that requires continuous awareness and
scrutiny; it must be hoped that this will
receive more attention than it has in the
past. In some areas, what may be seen is a
new balance of investment in overall pro¬
grammes, with prevention being given
higher priority. With regard to alcohol prob¬
lems, for instance, it seems likely that in
some countries there has been too much
emphasis on treatment, and that prevention k
has been neglected. f
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
y Another question, and a disturbing one, is
whether some of our present preventive ef¬
forts may be doomed to failure, whether ac¬
tion on substance problems may be diver¬
sionary activity to excuse our neglect of
more profound societal problems that breed
the misuse of substances. To take the exam¬
ple of the case study on drinking patterns in
Kenya, no one could seriously suppose that
Kenya's drinking problems are going to be
dealt with by an anti-alcoholism campaign
alone. This is not to preach despair or lend
support to neglect, but we have to be
careful lest society is evading responsibility
by focusing unduly and too superficially on
drug problems. We come back to daring to
be Utopian.
Having argued that the cruder application
of the medical model can sometimes carry
with it learned helplessness so far as the in¬
dividual's ability to help himself is concern¬
ed, one might then examine the parallel
argument as regards prevention. Could we
expect that communities themselves peo¬
ple in particular work-places or schools,
groups defined by some special shared
awareness such as women's groups would
take initiative for their own prevention
policies, rather than leave it to the State to
do so?
The sense of future that is being
developed here in terms of a need to be
aware of the relation between wider socio-
cultural changes and drug use and drug
problems, and in terms of changes in defini¬
tions of the drug problem and in treatment
and prevention, carries the implication of a
new research agenda. Without spelling the
matter out laboriously it can be said that all
the issues raised above are potential issues
for research. In practical terms, what one
might hope for is some movement away
from the dominance of a particular form of
epidemiological research on drugs, which,
although it has its place, has at times
become rather mechanistic and perseve-
rative, with the drug user treated as an ob¬
ject of study divorced from the study of the
culture and social institutions.
Whether international effort is mediated
through international organizations or by
any other process, what is clearly needed is
an increased willingness to take account
genuinely of experiences of countries other
than one's own. It must be hoped that in the
future there will be much more open ex¬
change of ideas than has sometimes been
seen, with no one dominant cultural view.
This is a vital consideration equally for treat¬
ment, preventive action (whether dealing
with demand or supply) and research.
To listen to other countries' experiences
one must, first, be given a chance to hear of
those experiences. An enormous amount is
being thought about, argued about, and ac¬
complished in many different countries, and
further ways of exchanging these ex¬
periences are badly needed. Much of
WHO's current drug programme is directed
to that end. It is to that endeavour that this
issue of the Unesco Courier also seeks in
some measure to contribute.
M Griffith Edwards and Awni Arif
NOSOTROS,
LOS ADOLESCENTES
mensaje audiovisual
Producción de los
alumnos Pares Guías
del Colegio Nacional
y Comercial de
Vicente López
Experiencia Piloto
Proyecto DINEMS - UNESCO - FNUFUID
1980
For teenagers, such feelings as loneliness, inability to communicate with others,
and lack of direction or purpose may increase the risk that they will become
dependent on drugs. The educational system can help students tackle these pro¬
blems by organizing in-school activities to break down barriers of communication
and to provide various kinds of help and guidance. Unesco and the United Nations
Fund for Drug Abuse Control are currently collaborating with the Argentine
education authorities in a pilot project along these lines. Photos show pupils at
the Vicente López national and commercial college, one of the schools where the
project is being carried out, taking part in group activities designed to foster a
community spirit. Top left, an "audiovisual message" was used by one group of
children to encourage their friends to express their feelings about adolescent life.
»»«
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
Handbook
for the
leachingof
Social Studies
:ditedbyHov
Just published
As part of its programme to promote education for interna¬
tional understanding, peace and respect for human rights,
Unesco produces handbooks and guides designed to pro¬
vide teachers and educational planners with useful informa¬
tion and suggestions based on international expertise and
experience. This new collection of essays by authors from
many parts of the world aims to give practical and
theoretical help in the teaching of social studies. Part One
deals with the planning of a social studies programme, and
Part Two with its implementation. Among the wide range of
topics discussed are:
a survey of social studies around the world
teaching strategies
values, attitudes and skills
multi-media instructional materials
evaluation and teacher education
Edited by Howard D. Mehlinger, Professor of Education and
History and Director of the Social Studies Development Center,
Indiana University.
A companion volume to the Unesco Handbook for
Science Teachers
Co-published with Croom Helm Ltd., UK
409 pages 90 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals- Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd ,'lttefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing - CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI. National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editions). Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag,
Germering/Munchen. For scientific maps only: Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
Hong-Kong Government Information Services, Publications
Centre, GPO Building, Connaught Place. - HUNGARY.
Akadémiai Kónyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V.
Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkbztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcut¬
ta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, B-3/7 Asaf Ali
Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots. Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016, Sandia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastn Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie
Publishing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street,
Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat.
Comm. for Unesco, Ave Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B P. 1533,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland
Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. - ISRAEL.
A.B.C Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel
Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon
3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African
Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean
National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait -
LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho,
Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd ,
P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication Et Distribution, P O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEM¬
BOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. - MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the
"Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: KEESING BOEKEN B.V.,
Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS AN¬
TILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286, The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens ,
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P O Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila 0-404. - POLAND Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & An¬
drade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box
131, Mahé. - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Niala University
and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New In¬
dustrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libn Building,
Church Street, P.O Box 924, Pretoria For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News agency, P 0. Box 1033,
Johannesburg SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir
Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B C E. Fritzes Kungl, Hov-
bokhandel, Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TAN¬
ZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
- THAILAND. .Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung
Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P 0.
Box 569, London, S E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Lauros-Giraudon. Musée des Beaux-Arts, Besançon
Through a glass darkly
The perception of drug problems and their treatment varies widely
throughout the world according to the values and cultures of different
societies. See article page 20 for the work of Alcoholics Anonymous,
which was founded in the USA, and of Japan's Alcohol Abstinence
Society, as well as other original approaches to the treatment of in¬
dividuals with a drug problem. Here, a still life by the 17th-century
Dutch painter Willem Claesz Heda.
]]>
</page>
</document>
