<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074720eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
Peoples
and
Cultures
The
Courier
in Space
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live..
O CHILE Music for Mother Earth
These musicians from the Chilean altiplano belong to the Aymara group of South American Indians whose culture is today menaced by
the changes that have affected their region in recent years. Wearing headdresses adorned with ostrich and pink flamingo feathers and
playing an instrument called a sicura which is only used for sacred purposes, they take part in a dawn offering of coca leaves and alcohol
to the Earth Mother Pachamama, thanking her for her bounty and calling on her goodwill for the future. Today this ritual is only prac¬
tised occasionally and it may soon die out altogether. The Aymara believe that the spirit of music lives in water, and during the night
before they perform their ritual the musicians leave their instruments at the waterside, so that the murmurings of the water can teach
them the music with which to pay tribute to the Earth Mother.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
JULY 1982 35th YEAR
Published in 26 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 48 French Francs
2 years: 84 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 36 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 7 - 1982 - OPI - 82-1 - 389 A
page
CULTURE AND DEVELOPMENT
4 The human dimension
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
THE EVOLUTION OF A CONCEPT
9 Cultural pluralism in a changing world
by Otto Klineberg
12 Unesco and the idea of cultural policy
AT THE CROSS-ROADS OF CULTURES
17 The writer between two worlds
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
19 National identity and foreign domination
by Ngugi Wa Thiong'o
22 The machinery of cultural power
by Augusto Roa Bastos
30 The woman revolution
by Han Suyin
CULTURAL DIVERSITY AND THE MASS MEDIA
35 In praise of mother tongues
by Chingiz A'ftmatov
40 The global village revisited
by Russell Neuman
45 Unesco Newsroom
2 A TIME TO LIVE...
CHILE : Music for Mother Earth
<P
lEOPLES and Cultures",
our cover title, was
chosen to highlight the
idea of cultural universality and
diversity which is the keynote of this
number of the Unesco Courier. The
issue has been prepared in view ofan
event which constitutes a landmark
in efforts by the international com¬
munity to redefine cultural relations
between individuals and between
nations: the World Conference on
Cultural Policies ("Mondiacult")
which Unesco is holding in Mexico
City from 26 fuly to 6 August.
The second cover title, "The
Courier in Space", refers to an ex¬
ceptional event of a different, kind.
French and Soviet cosmonauts, flying
in a "Soyuz-T6" spacecraft, have
taken with them into space a specimen
cover of this issue together with 100
examples of the serigraph which il¬
lustrates it and which was specially
createdfor Unesco by Victor Vasare-
ly. The proceeds from the sale of
these works will enable Unesco to
finance science scholarshipsforyoung
students from the Third World.
An issue of this kind can pretend
neither to deal exhaustively with all
the complexities of cultural life, nor
to set forth definitive solutions to
world cultural problems. What we
have done instead is to invite a
number of writers and specialists to
illustrate some of the topics that will
be on the agenda of the Mexico City
Conference.
Themes examined by our con¬
tributors include: the evolution of the
concept of culture (Otto Klineberg);
languages and cultural identity
(Chingiz Aitmatov); the writer bet¬
ween two cultures (Tahar Ben
Jelloun); the situation of women
(Han Suyin); culture and power
(Ngugi Wa Thiong'o and Augusto
Roa Bastos); and culture and new
communications technology (Russell
Neuman).
However incomplete, such an
overview may serve to illustrate an
important point: even when the opi¬
nions expressed diverge from
Unesco 's appointed mission, a strik¬
ing impression emerges of what
Unesco is doing in many important
areas of cultural life, while the open¬
ing article by Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow shows the contribution
Unesco has made and is making to
changing perspectives and activities
where culture is concerned.
Nevertheless, readers will in¬
evitably find many gaps in our
coverage, one of them being the
evolution of scientific thinking and
its relations with cultural life. We in¬
tend to remedy some of these omis¬
sions in our August-September dou¬
ble number which will be devoted to
an examination of major problems
facing the world community today.
Cover: serigraph by Victor Vasarely © Unesco
Italicised captions in this issue are quotations from
speeches by the Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, or from Unesco
documents.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
CULTURE
AND
DEVELOPMENT
The human dimension
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
THE fate of modern societies is enacted on a stage
which now encompasses the planet. Societies which
until a few decades ago were able to live in almost
total ignorance of each other are today in increasingly close
and regular contact. There is a growing interplay of recip¬
rocal influences; interdependence is a reality in many fields
of human activity.
Yet while this interdependence is undoubtedly a source of
mutual enrichment, receptivity, new initiatives and creativi
ty, it is also a cause of frustration to the extent that it is ac¬
companied by worsening conditions for certain peoples, and
feelings of growing uncertainty and increased vulnerability.
Sensitivity to changes, wherever they occur in the world, is
becoming acute.
It is perhaps in the field of culture that the contradictory
demands of new world relationships are most readily discer¬
nible. Communication between human beings is becoming
global in its scope, and the quantity of knowledge and infor-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
mation available is constantly increasing. With the develop¬
ment of computer technology, the possibilities of collecting
this knowledge and information, of storing them and
transferring them from one point on the planet to another
are also continually expanding.
These exchanges and contacts are accompanied by a
growing tendency towards a standardization of tastes and
behaviour, and a homogenization of certain patterns of life,
thought and action, of production and consumption pro¬
pagated by the uniform dissemination of the same television
series, the same musical rhythms,, the same clothes and the
same escapist dreams.
This growing conformity, which seems to follow an inter¬
nal logic of its own, is gradually invading more and more
areas of human activity. In its turn it generates distortions,
since it tends to promote whatever conforms to it and to
destroy everything that resists it. Whole sectors of creativity
are thus repressed, and societies mutilated in their in¬
dividuality and their distinctive structure. Carried to the ex¬
treme, this logic could lead to the ossification of mankind
since diversity, if accepted on a footing of complete equality,
is an essential and fertile source of vitality for both in¬
dividual societies and the whole world.
However, as a kind of reaction to this trend, a renewed,
explosive affirmation of individuality is emerging. Com¬
munities everywhere ethnic and national, rural and urban,
cultural and religious are asserting their originality and
endeavouring to take in hand and defend with vigour those
features by reference to which their identity is defined.
The will to affirm and defend cultural identity appears
now as one of the major driving forces of history. Far from
representing a withdrawal into an immutable, self-enclosed
past, it fosters a lively, original and constantly renewed syn¬
thesis. A sense of cultural identity thus appears more and
more to be the sine qua non of progress for individuals,
groups and nations; it is the force that animates and under¬
pins the collective will, mobilizes inner resources and turns
necessary change into creative adaptation.
It is today recognized that the notion of cultural identity
lies at the very heart of development problems, but it is only
recently that this fact has won full acceptance by the interna¬
tional community. It is only in the last ten years that our
understanding of development, its paths and aims, has
broadened and deepened. Originally equated with simple,
linear economic growth vital, certainly, insofar as an in¬
crease in the production of material goods makes a decisive
contribution to the improvement of people's living condi¬
tions, when such goods are equitably distributed develop¬
ment has increasingly been seen to be an infinitely more
complex, comprehensive and multidimensional process,
which is effective only if it is based on the will of each society
to fulfil itself, and only if it truly expresses each society's
underlying identity.
Genuine development can only be generated from within,
willed and conducted by all the vital forces of the nation. It
should therefore encompass all aspects of life and involve all
the energies of a community within which each individual,
each occupational category and each social group has its part
to play in the general effort and has its share in the resulting
benefits.
As so often happens, this growing awareness of the true
nature of development was largely brought about by the set¬
backs experienced in developing and industrialized countries
alike.
The developing countries, tempted to catch up with the in¬
dustrialized countries by following the same paths, have
sometimes endeavoured to adopt approaches to development
which, seeking to achieve rapid economic progress by often
inappropriate means, did not always produce the expected
results, or even brought new constraints which not only
reproduced but aggravated those which had handicapped
the industrialized countries.
At the same time, the industrialized societies, considered
to be the most developed, have also come to realize the very
serious problems caused by economic growth seen as an end
in itself. Damage to the natural environment is exacerbated
by new constraints which threaten man's very existence as a
social being attached to a community with which he can fully
identify.
The whole international community is thus today, in dif¬
ferent ways, increasingly coming to accept the idea of in-
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
tegrated development in which economic, social and cultural
factors are indissolubly linked and contribute together to
progress. Culture, which is connected with all expressions of
life and which, for every human being and every people, is
the expression of their highest values and their very sense of
life, emerges as the factor which is to guide and humanize
economic growth and technical progress.
To take account of the cultural dimension or objec¬
tive of development is to recognize that the goal of develop¬
ment should be to render man unto himself, in other words
to grant him a place in the world which magnifies his ex¬
istence instead of narrowing it, a time befitting his needs and
desires, a city in which he can be integrated rather than re¬
jected, a community joined together in solidarity, and an oc¬
cupation which brings him dignity and freedom. This is to
attach due importance to creativity, which implies that each
people assume its own identity by enriching and continually
reinventing it through acts, words and artefacts.
Tradition must also be reckoned with, although it should
not necessarily be seen as an obstacle to modernization. It is
only when the sign loses its meaning that tradition may
become negative, immobile introspection. It is far more ac¬
curate to see tradition as the cumulative record of the ex¬
periences of a community throughout its history.
As a result of cultural innovation, tradition may take on a
new lease of life, become part of life as it is lived, and even
contribute to development and progress. The conquest of
modernity can be achieved by bringing up to date the forms,
relationships and symbols which constitute, at the deepest
level, the specific face of a culture. Innovation, the dynamic
aspect of cultural identity and action, will be the agent of
this awakening.
Thus the notion of cultural identity is today indissociable
from that of development. Three major spheres of human
activity education, science and communication which are
also Unesco's fields of competence, are closely linked to
culture and combine to extend its action in the service of
development.
Culture and education foster the growth of social roots.
From the viewpoint of development they appear as essential¬
ly complementary. Economic and social development is
largely conditioned by the conception of the world which
prevails in a given society, but this conception of the world is
itself influenced by the message transmitted by educational
systems and the sensibilities which they help to stimulate.
Modern schooling has taken the place of traditional educa¬
tion. This trend is irreversible, but the new forms of educa¬
tion are not always appropriate to the situation and real
CULTURAL IDENTITY AND CREATIVITY
The assertion of cultural identity was considered to be an act of liberation, a weapon in the fight for effective
independence and the best means of achieving the self-fulfilment of individuals and the harmonious develop¬
ment ofsocieties. It was, moreover, the first prerequisite for the advent ofa new world order, based on the in¬
alienable right of nations to dispose of themselves and on the recognition of the absolute equality and dignity
of all cultures.
The Flower Vendor, 1935, by the Mexican artist Diego Rivera (1886-1957). Oil on panel, 121.3 cm x 121.3 cm.
San Francisco Museum of Art, California, USA. Photo © Dominique Darr, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
CULTURAL IDENTITY AND CREATIVITY. Cultural
identity is not a problem for the general public but for the
educated, whose upbringing has often included virtually inevitable
elements of cultural alienation. The élite must return to their
culture to understand it more effectively and experience it as a liv¬
ing reality in order to find their roots in it. Seem from this angle,
cultural identity should be asserted primarily in the schools and
universities. An élite, often educated in other schools and
sometimes unsure of its identity, must be helped into awareness of
its own heritage and its eyes opened to thefact that popular culture
is not merely folklore. -
African students at Bowie State College, Maryland, USA.
American'universities, which are attracting more and more African
students, maintain close ties with Africa. Photo Richard Saunders
© ICA, Washington, D.C.
needs of individuals and groups. A widening rift in intellec¬
tual and cultural life may be observed with the extension of
schooling, an uneasy coexistence between an elitist culture
and a popular or traditional culture which has virtually
nothing in common with the former.
In a number of countries, oral tradition is the authentic
memory of the people and, swelled by new contributions
from each generation, explains the world in all its diversity.
In most cases too, its symbolism opens a door onto a
fabulous world of the imagination. The data recorded in the
oral tradition must be rediscovered and collected, for to
destroy or banish them to oblivion would be irreversible.
But there are many other ways in which education must
be linked to the most significant values of a culture. To take
one notable example, an effort must be made to avoid the
shock of uprooting a child which occurs when he is taught
from the moment he enters school in a language which is not
his own. The use of languages spoken by the community to
which the child belongs thus appears as both an educational
and a cultural imperative. Associated with this major choice
should be various reforms which, through the promotion of
popular arts and traditions, and social values, would aim to
implant education in the realities and history of the nation.
In this way it is certainly possible to gain from peoples
that conscious and active participation without which there
can be no profound sense of cultural identity nor any truly
endogenous development.
Another fundamental question is that of the relations bet¬
ween science and technology, on the one hand, and culture
on the other. Whether we like it or not, the implantation of a
technology is a cultural phenomenon. Even in cases where
the introduction of certain technologies brings the most ob¬
vious benefits, the transfer is not culturally neutral and may
cause a distortion of standards and the emergence of new
values bearing no relation to deep-rooted social and human
realities.
It seems to me desirable, whenever possible, to try to
develop on the spot a technology adapted to the specific
needs of each situation, instead of turning to imported for¬
mulae when the latter cannot be satisfactorily mastered. The
best and most vigorous development will always be en¬
dogenous development, that is to say, development con¬
sciously and fully assumed by everyone. For if the demands
of development require that no society can do without
science, if science is to be most fruitful it must grow roots in
each society. Science will not contribute to improving the
lives of men in countries where it is perceived as a foreign im¬
port until the day when it becomes an integral part of their
culture.
And so the need to participate in decision-making concer¬
ning scientific and technological development appears to be
emerging in various societies. This trend suggests a certain
shift in aspirations, from exclusively economic goals to a
«++<-*-*+**«««++«++«+4 **** +***« * **«* **
¿XJ
KARIN MAGANAA AL'AADAR
DUUNTYAA.
ANDUNYA YAASAY GA CI CIMI.
YflASEEWOL HOKKOTfi YOYRE
SIWTfiflGO NDER DUUNIYfiARU.
KARAW, AJAARAM GAADO YE.
R NON WISSHfiRRN fi-DU
T3W30IY3N.
PROVERBES, REALITES DE LA VIE.
Saatumbaa
Handu yegganta
Suumaye
1978
Sepetamber
Shin erom
Septembre
LAHDl ALHADI ALLAL 3 10 17 24 LAADU ALKHAD DIMANCHE
LIITININ ATINNI ALTINEE 4 n 18 25 13Z3RIN 3LÎTNIN LUNDI
TAIAATAA ATALAATA TAIAATA 5 12 19 26 TALAAWU ALTANATA MARDI
LAARABAA ALARBA ALLARBA 6 13 20 27 LAARAWA 3NARBA MERCREDI
ALHAMIS ALAAMISI ALHAMIISA 7 M 21 28 LAAMISU 3LKH3MIS JEUDI
JUUMA'AA ALZUMA MAWDE 1 8 15 22 29 J3MMA 3LG3MAT VENDREDI
SUBDU ASIBTI ASSAAWEE 2 9 16 23 30 S3BDU 3SS3B3T SAMEDI
%
%
****
- //rr/ftfrt/t
«****««*««*«.
CULTURAL IDENTITY AND CREATIVITY. The question of
each group or nation 's cultural identity, which is at the meeting-
point of culture and communication, shows the importance of
language both as a vehicle of communication and as part of the
cultural heritage. Linguistic richness imposes not only a respectfor
the many languages existing but also a complex and costly adapta¬
tion of the communication networks to the different linguistic
areas, as well as the use of many languages by the communication
media in order to avoid standardization. Language policy therefore
constitutes one of the thorniest and most important issues in the
formulation of communication policies.
Calendar used in Niger and printed in six languages: Zerma,
Hausa, Peul, Tamashek, Kanuri and French. Photo © All rights
reserved.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
range of ultimate objectives related to social and cultural
development. It also appears to be the sign of growing
awareness of the decisive role played by technology in the
development of societies, and of the determination of peoples
to assume greater responsibility for their own future, with a
fuller knowledge of what is at stake. Thus the search for
greater compatibility between the directions in which
technological change is steered and the expectations of socie¬
ty may well be one of the key issues of the coming decade.
Communications technology has made such strides in the
last few years that it has revolutionized life and development
in both industrialized and developing societies. Increasingly
people are encountering other cultures in their everyday
lives, discovering other values, observing attitudes un¬
familiar to them, and thereby coming to know the many
faces of mankind. And soon, through direct satellite televi¬
sion broadcasting, it will be possible to transmit knowledge
globally, and the irruption of other cultures into every home
will be a permanent fact.
Whether the role of the new instruments is beneficial or
harmful will depend on the way in which they are used by
mankind. It seems indispensable to integrate the com¬
munications media into cultural policies, for it would be vain
CULTURAL IDENTITY AND CREATIVITY. Culture, which
was not something separate from consciousness of the
community's identity, was probably regardedfirst andforemost as
a factor making for a stronger sense of national individuality; but
the quest for cultural identity was in all cases combined with sym¬
pathetic receptivity to the other cultures of the region and of the
world, and, ultimately, to all that is universally human, which
ruled out cultural isolationism and entailed the disavowal of
chauvinistic assertions of distinctive nationhood.
Pre-Columbian sculpted heads on a poster published in Mexico in
1970 on the occasion of the World Cup. Photo Bob Schalkwijk ©
Alejandro Von Wuthenau, Mexico.
CULTURAL IDENTITY AND CREATIVITY. One might well
ask whether the perfectly legitimate desire to eliminate the elitist
aspects of culture has not, as a side-effect, led to a certain under¬
valuation of the specific function of creation in the totality of
social functions. To put the question in the most basic terms: what
would disappear if creation were to disappear from society?
A young Balinese sculptor at work. Photo Burt Glinn © Magnum,
Paris.
to pretend that the media only raise problems of a technical
order. They are bound to have repercussions on political at¬
titudes, on social behaviour, on ways of thinking, and thus
on culture in the broadest sense.
If development is the concern of all institutions of the
United Nations system, cultural questions devolve exclusive¬
ly on Unesco, which has for some years been making an
original contribution to the problem of cultural development
by launching and promoting the idea of "cultural policy."
An intergovernmental conference on cultural policy was
held by Unesco in Venice in 1970, and subsequently a
number of regional conferences met in order to deepen and
continue, in their specific contexts, the process of reflexion
begun by the international community and to accelerate the
evolution from an elitist concept of culture to that of cultural
action committed to development which would promote the
fulfilment of individuals and communities.
"Development must find its inspiration in culture", says
the unanimously adopted Declaration of the Bogotá Con¬
ference (1978). Unesco is continuing this long-term effort by
holding a world conference on cultural policies in Mexico
City from 26 July to 6 August in order to make an assess¬
ment of this "first cultural development decade" and to set
forth guidelines for the future.
H Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
THE EVOLUTION
OF A CONCEPT
Cultural pluralism
in a changing world
by Otto Klineberg
FOR most people culture suggests high
artistic or intellectual achievement,
the development of art and science,
the humanities, philosophy, the expression
of the genius of a people.
For the social scientist it includes all this
and much more; it may be defined as em¬
bracing everything that a person acquires as
a member of society; all the habits and
capabilities which are learned through tradi¬
tion or experience, as well as the material
objects which are produced by the group. It
may be expressed in works of art or scholar¬
ship, but also in what we eat and the way we
dress, in the nature of our relationship to
members of our family or to others in the
society, in our system of values, in the
education we receive, in our ideas of good
and bad, in the kind of houses we build, in
the expectations and hopes we have for the
future, in our attitude toward strangers.
This list is far from complete, but it
should suffice to indicate the range and
complexity of the content of cultures. It is
not surprising that a number of writers have
described culture as a concept of major im¬
portance in the social sciences because of the
demonstration of the extent to which our
behaviour and our ideas are shaped by the
group to which we belong. In that connex¬
ion it has served as a needed corrective to
the widespread notion that differences in the
way of life of different groups are determin¬
ed mainly if not exclusively by biology or
race. It is this wider concept of culture
which is used in what follows.
It is perhaps not too surprising that in the
history of human contacts most groups have
been much more impressed by their dif¬
ferences from others than by the similarities.
All too frequently this has been associated
with the belief that if they are different from
us they must be inferior. In the language of
many of the pre-Iiterate societies described
by anthropologists the expression "the
people" referred only to one's own group;
other groups were often considered strange,
exotic, inferior, somewhat less than human.
This attitude, although widespread, is not
necessarily universal, but it has certainly
played an important part in the relations
between peoples, not only in the obvious
cases of colonization and other forms of ex¬
ploitation, but even in situations which are
motivated by liberal high-minded pro¬
grammes such as technical assistance or co¬
operation, in which the receiving areas are
expected to adopt the standards and models
of the donors.
In this respect, however, it is possible to
identify certain counter-currents, character¬
ized by a greater willingness to recognize the
rights of others to their own cultural identi¬
ty, and by a greater concern on the part of
those "others" to maintain that identity. In
the USA, for example, the sociologist
Milton M. Gordon has distinguished three
stages in the approach to the complex
American ethnic structure. The first, Anglo-
conformity, demanded "the complete
renunciation of the immigrant's ancestral
heritage in favour of the behaviour and
values of the Anglo-Saxon core group;" the
second, the melting-pot idea, envisaged "a
biological merger of the Anglo-Saxon
peoples with other immigrant groups and a
blending of their respective cultures into a
new indigenous American type;" the third,
characterizing the present situation, is
cultural pluralism, which seeks "the preser¬
vation of the communal life and significant
portions of the culture of the later im¬
migrant groups within the context of
American citizenship and political and
economic integration into American
society." Problems remain as to the extent
to which such a goal is fully possible or
desirable, but certainly the acceptance of a
variety of cultural forms within the nation-
state is much greater now than it was in the
past. The same is true for other countries .
such as Yugoslavia, the Philippines,
Belgium and France, not always to the same
extent, but in the same direction.
On the other side of the picture, various
ethnic groups in a number of different coun¬
tries are now actively seeking the preserva¬
tion of their own cultural identity. One of
the most striking recent instances of an
ethnic group seeking to establish and main¬
tain its cultural identity is that of the Blacks
in the United States. Slavery and its after¬
math of an inferior socio-economic position
within the larger community were clearly
not conducive to the development of a
positive sense of identity.
What happened during the 1960s was
something approaching a psychological
revolution. There was a refusal to accept the
notion of "cultural deprivation", since the
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
INTERCULTURAL RELATIONS
One of the functions of intercultural activities is to inhibit racism and to promote a better understanding between
cultures. The very fact that young children feel no aversion to what is different and that such aversion is acquired
proves the urgent need to undertake fundamental research which would enable teachers to suggest activities that
respect the evolution and modalities of the relational life of the child.
Make-up artist at work at a children's cultural festival in France. Photo Robert Delpit © Fotogram, Paris.
position of the Blacks was that they had
their own culture. With that went the
development of a whole complex philo¬
sophy (or ideology) of identity. This includ¬
ed the concept of Black Power, the slogans
"Black is beautiful"and "I'm proud to be
Black;" African roots and a Black or
African culture; Black nationalism. Black
psychologists and psychiatrists spoke of a
new Black ethic based upon racial
awareness, high self-esteem, identity and
pride; a sense of adequacy and security.
One aspect of culture which Blacks have
emphasized is that their . self-identity is
always a people-identity; "I am because we
are, and because we are, therefore I am."
This is seen to be in contrast with the
Western emphasis on the self as individually
unique and different. In a recent book by an
American social scientist, Edmund Glenn,
an African ambassador in Washington is
quoted as saying: "The source of the
10
greatest misunderstanding between Ameri¬
cans and Africans is the positive value at¬
tached by the Americans to individualism,
and the negative value attached to it by
Africans."
In France today we are witnessing a strik¬
ing development of concern with ethnic
identity and the preservation of minority
cultures. In Brittany, Corsica, "Occitanie",
etc., this tendency has increased in strength
as it has also among the Catalans and
Basques in Spain, American Indians and
European minorities in the United States
and Canada, the Maori in New Zealand, the
aboriginal population in Australia and
other ethnic groups in many parts of the
world.
All of these developments appear to be in
a direction which we should welcome. The
Unesco Declaration on Race in 1967 in¬
cludes a statement to the effect that "ethnic
groups which suffer discrimination are
sometimes accepted or tolerated by the
dominant group if they totally give up their
cultural identity... Ethnic groups should be
encouraged to preserve their cultural values,
thus contributing to the enrichment of the
total human culture."
Culture, as has already been indicated,
refers to behaviour which is specifically-
human and also to the distinctive ways of
life found in different human populations.
From the point of view of education for in¬
ternational understanding, it has frequently
been suggested that it is important to supply
information as to how others behave;
although such information does not
necessarily lead to friendly attitudes, it does
seem safer to base our relations with other
people on knowledge rather than on ig¬
norance. On the other hand, the
psychologist Gordon Allport suggested a
number of years ago that educators had
gone too far in stressing the differences
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
among peoples, and presenting others as
strange and even exotic in their behaviour.
He called instead for an "encyclopedia of
human similarities," with greater stress on
the common-human. A more reasonable
position would be to include both the
resemblances and the differences. Our
understanding of culture requires a concern
with both similarities and differences, and
also with the ease and likelihood with which
the differences occur.
A serious difficulty* arises when we at¬
tempt to identify the characteristics of a par¬
ticular culture. Every group is a complex,
with variations in behaviour according to
social class or status, occupation, education
or role; the kind of culture exhibited or ab¬
sorbed by the individual will be somewhat
different for men and women, for young
and old, for each individual; in a nation-
state it may vary considerably from one
region to another. These variations are often
characterized as sub-cultures, but it is not
easy to determine how many sub-cultures
should be distinguished. In addition,
cultures change. How much continuity is
there between Czarist and Communist
Russia, Elizabethan and Victorian England,
or the France of Louis XIV and today?
In connexion with cultural change, there
is an important development in recent years
which is usually defined as the "counter¬
culture," because of the position taken by
its adherents in relation to, and often in op¬
position to the prevailing values of the larger
community. It is mainly confined to the
young in industrial societies; it denies the
relevance of many of the ideals of the
parents; it is not concerned with making
preparations for the future, but insists on
living intensely the experience of the present
(the now generation). Success is seen not in
material terms but as personal development,
self-fulfilment, self-realization.
One aspect of this movement is particular¬
ly striking in connexion with cultural varia¬
tions. For many of the devotees of the
counter-culture, salvation is to be found in
the religions of the Orient. Many parents
and teachers of the young in revolt against
their society find it hard to understand the
attraction of Zen Buddhism or Hinduism,
but the emphasis on contemplation and in¬
ner peace must seem very palatable to those
trying to escape from a society which
stresses hard work and material success. Not
only do the Eastern religions provide an
alternative style; they also reduce or remove
any feelings of guilt that may be felt as the
result of defection from the goals which the
young had been brought up to respect, but
which no longer satisfied them.
CONTINUED PAGE 14
INTERCULTURAL RELATIONS. Co-operative relations between nations can as a con¬
sequence of the central role assigned to knowledge be approachedfrom two related stand¬
points, distinct yet interconnected. Direct action must be taken, firstly, to foster understand¬
ing among nations, by promoting "the free flow of ideas" and, generally speaking, ex¬
changes in the sphere of intellectual arid cultural activities. But co-operation is also needed in
order to bring about broader participation in intellectual and cultural activities in all
societies, whence the notions of ' 'popular education ' ' and ' 'the spread ofculture ' '; whence,
also, the ideal of "equality of educational opportunity" and the need to "maintain, increase
and diffuse knowledge". At the meeting-point of these two approaches, Unesco must work
to "give people of all countries access to the printed and published materials produced by
any of them ' ', and also assure ' 'the conservation and protection of the world 's inheritance ' '
in the field of culture.
A montage of newspaper cuttings concerning the rights of the child in The Federal Republic
of Germany. Photo courtesy of the Fed. Rep. of Germany National Commission for
Unesco.
THE BOOK
Although the developing countries
represent about 70 per cent of the world
population, they produce scarcely a
fifth of the books published in the
world, the rest of the production being
concentrated in about 30 industrialized
countries. The chief obstacles to the
development of localproduction are the
cost of intellectualproduction (authors'
fees, acquisition of copyrights, financ¬
ing of translation), and the cost of
manufacture, in which the two main
items are machinery and paper but
which also includes professional train¬
ing. Until they are able to caterfor their
own needs, the developing countries are
obliged to meet their home
demand which is increasing with the
spread of education and the advance of
literacy by recourse to outside sources
of supply. This involves them in expen¬
ditures which are all the heavier in that
high transport costs have to be added to
the price of the books themselves and
that payment has to be made in foreign
currency. Moreover, the imported
books are by no means always suited to
the aspirations of their peoples, whereas
their national authors, who are often
forced to publish their works abroad
because they are not included in the
local publishing economic circuit,
would be in a position to meet most of
their needs. Outside supplies can thus
only be temporary palliatives and not
real remedies for the book shortage.
This multi-purpose library van, of the
New Delhi Public Library, carries some
3,000 books in Urdu, Hindi and
English. Photo E. Schwab, Unesco.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO AM) THE IDEA OF CULTURAL POLICY
The years that have elapsed since the World Conference on Cultural Policies
organized by Unesco at Venice in 1970 have been a very interesting period of
increasing awareness in the cultural field.
At the theoretical level, some key concepts have emerged from the discus¬
sions and meetings held at the instigation of Unesco. Fundamental questions
have been asked about the role of culture in the modern world. Various
regional conferences have pursued in greater depth the forceful ideas first
enunciated at Venice, and have dealt both with problems specific to the regions
and with those that form part of the world cultural problem.
Culture defined solely according to aesthetic
criteria does not translate the reality of other
cultural forms. There is a unanimous feeling in
favour of a socio-anthropological definition of
culture. Culture should describe the sum total of the
existential, concrete characteristics of entire
peoples. It includes ways of life and production,
value systems, opinions and beliefs. Hence the im¬
possibility of applying a single, interchangeable
cultural policy. The dynamic aspect of this defini¬
tion is its recognition of cultural specificities.
Since culture is linked to the various aspects of
social life, any cultural policy should be defined in
terms of its interactions with policies for education,
science and technology, environment and com¬
munication. Hence the key idea of the cultural
aspect of development.
ASIACULT : Intergovernmental Conference on Cultural Policies in Asia
(Yogyakarta, 27 October-6 November 1973)
The main original feature of the Yogyakarta conference was that it put for¬
ward the idea of the cultural development of individuals and societies as a fac¬
tor for national identification and a means to socialprogress. It advocated the
search for original development models to hold the balance between material
and spiritual and between social and individual values and between the preser¬
vation of national cultures and the necessary assimilation of science and
technology. It encouraged the definition ofnational communications policies,
having in mind the potentialities and dangers of the mass media for cultural
development.
Tradition is not to be confused with a rejection of
scientific and technological progress. Access to
modernity should not take place beneath the form
of alienation and economic imperialism. Science
and technology should be controlled by the user
countries and developed in forms adapted to the
social and cultural characteristics corresponding to
the real needs of populations.
AFRICA CULT : Intergovernmental Conference on Cultural Policies in Africa
(Accra, 27 October-6 November 1975)
At the Accra conference, the idea ofcultural identity was highlighted as the
historical basis for any process ofendogenous development by societies and as
the quickest way to recognition of the diversity of cultures. Cultural policies
were defined in their organic links with educational, environmental and com¬
munications policies and policiesfor the revalidation of the national heritage.
While considering that African cultures must remain open to outside contribu¬
tions and receptive to the main creative trends of the modern world, the con¬
ference nevertheless advocated that the terms of international co-operation be
altered so as to foster intercultural dialogue on a basis offair reciprocity.
CULTURAL CONFERENCES
VENICE (24August-2 September 1970): Intergovernmental Conference on In¬
stitutional, Administrative and Financial Aspects of Cultural Policies.
At Venice, States became aware of their new responsibilities in the cultural
field and of the growing importance of cultural values in the life of nations.
Human rights came to include the right to culture. Governments found
themselves under an obligation to create conditions favourable to the exercise
ofthat right. The Venice conference widened the notion of culture to include
the way of life of the people, and began to regard cultural development as an
essential feature of the overall development of any society.
Education is the key concept in all problems
related to culture. Formal and informal education
must be rethought in the perspective of lifelong
education. It is above all necessary to study the en¬
vironment and the people for whom education is
being considered so as to avoid the adoption just as
they are of foreign models. Education should be
critical, creative and liberating, and thus narrow the
gap between popular and élite culture. More
democratization means more social justice.
It seems indispensable to develop a policy of
cultural action which would promote the
democratization of culture. Access to culture does
not imply the acceptance of a finished cultural pro¬
duct; the aim should be for the community to par¬
ticipate actively in cultural events.
EUROCULT : Intergovernmental Conference on Cultural Policies in Europe
(Helsinki, 19-28 June 1972)
The Helsinki conference considered the cultural ends of development and
dealt with the interaction between culture on the one hand and education, com¬
munication and environment on the other. It brought out some highly signifi¬
cant ¡inks between culture and social justice, between culture and youth and
between cultural activity and attempts at democratization. It paid special at¬
tention to artistic creativity and the status of the artist; to the increasing par¬
ticipation of the people in cultural life; to innovations stemming from the in¬
telligent use of the mass media; and to the safeguarding of the environment
and the improvement of the habitat.
The acceptance of cultural diversity within a com¬
munity and the reconciliation of cultural pluralism
with national unity constitute one of the major
challenges for cultural policies in the future.
AMERICACULT : Intergovernmental Conference on Cultural Policies in
Latin America and the Caribbean (Bogotá, 10-20 January 1978)
The Bogotá conference went more deeply into the problems of cultural
identity on the basis of the unusual experience of the region, where cultural
crossbreeding has produced syncretic cultures with a universal mission.
Cultural identity was also seen as correlated with respect for culturalpluralism
and the preservation of the heritage. The conference also stated that no
culturalpolicy worthy of the name waspossible without special attention to ar¬
tistic creativity, to the fostering of creative imagination in books andfilms, to
the training of cultural development staffs and to research in the field of
cultural policies.
Knowledge about human action on the environ¬
ment should be a part of children's education, and
one of the tasks of the authorities should be to train
specialists in cultural development and to make
them aware of the consequences of the choices they
formulate in fields which they may think are totally
distinct from culture.
Third Conference of Arab Ministers of Culture : Baghdad (2-5 November
1981) organized by ALECSO (Arab League Educational, Cultural and Scien¬
tific Organization)
Similarpreoccupations were considered at the Conference ofArab Ministers
of Culture convened in 1981 by ALECSO. The participants admittedly dealt
with questions specific to Arabic culture and to the culturalpolicies ofMember
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
States, but also tackled more general questions such as the specificity and
universality ofculture in the world, the right to culture and the cultural dimen¬
sion of development.
These cultural meetings, bridging the frontiers between Europe, Africa, the
Arab world, Asia and Oceania, Latin America and the Caribbean, naturally
gave regional, interregional and international cultural co-operation between
States its rightfulplace as one of theprimeprerequisitesfor the maintenance of
a fruitful climate of camaraderie, security and peace in the world.
All the Unesco conferences stress the need to con¬
sider the freedom of choice of creators and of
peoples as absolutes which cannot be transgressed,
seeing in them the means of placing man at the cen¬
tre of development.
Communication may be the vehicle of packaged
culture or it may transmit - endogenous cultural
values.
WORLD CULTURAL PROBLEMS: THE CONSTANTS
Thusfrom one conference to the next andfrom one cultural area to another
certain constants emerge in varying degrees of intensity which illustrate the
main topics of world cultural problems as they affect men 's hopes and dreams
at the time, viz. cultural identity, the cultural dimension of development,
cultural rights and the role of imagination and creativity.
The dynamic safeguard of cultural authenticity
implies the revaluation and promotion of minority
languages and their insertion in States' educational
and social systems, as well as the study and promo¬
tion of the oral tradition and folk arts.
OBJECTIVES AND SCOPE OF CULTURAL ACTION
Nowadays there is no country in the world without an urge for cultural ac¬
tivity, whatever the level and type of action taken by the government. Many
governments are pursuing culturalpolicies or programmes ofcultural activity.
The great majority of Member States of Unesco have a ministry or body in
charge ofcultural affairs, and also more or less substantial and diversified net¬
works of cultural institutions and socio-cultural centres. In some countries,
particularly those with a federal constitution, the deliberately limited central
structures are complemented by regional and local structures, semi-
administrative bodies including professionals and experts which act to foster
artistic creativity. There is a great deal ofparallel action, though it is not usual¬
ly integrated in an overall plan.
As regards the objectives, scope and protagonists of cultural action, three
main types of policy may be distinguished. The first, the most widespread,
stresses the development of the arts at professional level or the preservation of
the heritage, the role of the State and the big institutions going unchallenged.
The second, the most "advanced" ofpresent-day cultural policies, sets out to
link culture with education, communication and the environment. Govern¬
ment action is more directed towards the decentralization ofaction, decisions
and resources, and to getting minorities and the underprivileged to play a big¬
ger part in cultural life, particularly through cultural leadership. At the same
time, other administrations begin to take over cultural activities in their own
sectors, e.g. youth, education, equipment, health, information and tourism.
The third type of cultural policy, which so far exists only in the form of
forward-looking studies or very limited experiments, aims radically to remodel
all aspects of development and give them cultural ends, by taking human fac¬
tors into account. What is regarded as the essential feature is that peoples play
a part in creating their own culture, rather than merely having access to the
culture of the élite or to the products of mass culture.
OBSTACLES IN THE WAY OF CULTURAL ACTION
Obviously the great majority of existing situations fall short of the
theoretical level reached by key centres in the international community. The in¬
ternal reasons for this situation are no doubt economic (i.e. small budgets),
technical (i.e. lackoffacilities or specialized staffand insufficient research and
information) or psycho-sociological (i.e. conservatism, bureaucratic influence
or failure to appreciate present requirements for creation and participation).
But the real reason for the limitations encountered in most cases seems to be
more structural: the lack of a really integrated approach to cultural develop¬
ment and socio-economic development is the fundamental defect ofpresent-
day cultural policies, all too often devised and implemented without organic
links with policies which could inject a cultural dimension into all major
development projects. In fact nearly all culturalpolicies are in varying degrees
limited to the specifically culturalfield, and support the big institutions (main¬
ly in the capital cities), the preservation of the historical and artistic heritage,
professional creativity and distribution. All too few of them are defined in
termsofthe whole social spectrum, or incorporate in their thinking the real-life
experience, the aspirations and the dreams of the teeming masses.
International cultural co-operation should be
thought of in terms of equality and reciprocity, the
recognition of cultural diversity implying respect
for national independence and sovereignty.
MONDIACULT : World conference on cultural policies Mexico, 26 July-6
August 1982
Now that Mondiacult is to be convened in Mexico, new life for cultural
policies would take the form of energetic theoretical and practical action
calculated to mobilize the creative efforts of individuals and groups at ail levels
of society. Such a vital force could radically revitalize exchanges and specific
relations between the members of a given society and between thepeoples and
nations that make up the international community. In this new atmosphere,
economics andpolitics, the output ofgoods and services and the symbolic out¬
put of ideologies and the arts would all become ways ofachieving a cultural life
closely linked to daily life and the happiness andfulfilment of individuals and
social groups.
The portents of this transformation in the role ofculture in society call upon
people wherever they may be to make a qualitative change in their cultural
adventure, like the one they made when harnessing theforces ofnature. In this
way they will bring together the still all too scattered currents of world solidari¬
ty in a great world cultural project that will save from the nuclear apocalypse
the very roots of a new understanding worthy of each and every man.
Mondiacult may be this focal point, where those attending the intergovern¬
mental conference convened by Unesco will reach a new view of the world and
thus arrive at a decisive change in cultural relations between individuals and
between nations.
The heritage is not only the sum total of historic
monuments but the dynamic and living totality of
human creation.
From now on, culture can only be seen as apart ofa system ofrelationships:
a process ofgive and take is imperative for each national culture.
The idea is gaining ground that no headway can be made without a consen¬
sus. Unesco has become the promoter of this consensus, of which it intends to
be a focal point.
A Unesco recommendation, of overrriding im¬
portance, proposes to States a sociology of crea¬
tion, through a critical vision of social reality, ar¬
tistic creation being considered as the creation of
new values. The recommendation attempts to
reconcile creative freedom with the economic and
social security of the artist.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 11
The whole movement included within the
concept of the counter-culture has lost many
of its adherents, and is frequently con¬
sidered to have abandoned a good part of its
programme. This may be the case, but re¬
cent research on the attitudes of young men
and women with regard to work and their
future, indicates that at least some of its
components continue to have an impact.
We turn now to a number of specific
issues in connexion with culture contact in
the contemporary world which create
problems for institutions like Unesco and
the United Nations and for all those who
agree with them that the variety of human
cultures should as far as possible be preserv¬
ed. These issues take the form of apparent
contradictions or paradoxes which require
careful consideration.
The first of these relates to the general
programme of technical assistance or co¬
operation designed to improve the standard
of living in developing countries, but which
in practice involves the introduction of in¬
dustrial and technological models from the
"modern", usually the Western world.
This, too, reflects the United Nations pro¬
gramme; the question arises as to whether it
is compatible with the survival of traditional
cultures. The American anthropologist Ed¬
ward Hall reminds us that the various facets
of a culture are interrelated; "touch a
culture in one place and everything else is af¬
fected." The Australian psychologist
Stephen Bochner insists that "there are
many examples of societies which have lost
their cultural integrity as the price for
modernization."
Such "modernization" is, however,
precisely what the leaders of the developing
countries are requesting. The Norwegian
sociologist Johan Galtung points out that
Third World representatives are urging the
creation of "a New International Economic
Order (NIEO) to have faster industrializa¬
tion, increasing exports, better raw material
prices, more financial and technological
transfers." The question then arises: can
this be done without destroying, or at least
disrupting, the existing indigenous, tradi¬
tional culture?
It has frequently been pointed out that
there is a tendency in the industrially
developed world to see itself as a universally
valid model to be imitated by others. In this
connexion Galtung analyzes the important
question of human needs, their universal
and variable character, and the necessity of
avoiding cultural ethnocentrism, paying
more direct attention to what the recipient
societies want, and less to what the donors
think they ought to want. What they want
may, however, be difficult to determine
since the political leaders and the évolués in
many developing countries have themselves
adopted a position close to that of the
Western world.
The fact remains that technological
change is not always accompanied by the
disappearance of traditional culture. There
can be no doubt as to the industrial and
technical achievement of the Japanese, but
at the same time they have retained many
distinctively Eastern and national traits. It
has been suggested, for example, that their
life continues to be affected by the notion of
mutual dependence, whereas the West, cen¬
tred on the individual, tends to develop
more self-reliance. In Japan a business
enterprise, no matter how large, is seen in
the image of a household, with the accom¬
panying interdependence and loyalty
characteristic of the family.
There is a second paradox to be con¬
sidered. The United Nations/Unesco posi¬
tion is in favour of contact among the
peoples of the world, and extensive pro¬
grammes of "exchange of persons" have
been developed by both national and inter¬
national agencies. Bochner, however, in
discussing the forces antithetical to cultural
preservation, includes international educa¬
tional exchange "which acts as the main
vehicle for the uncritical diffusion of
Western culture and therefore the erosion of
non-Western life styles."
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
INTERCULTURAL RELATIONS. The
real question we ought to ask ourselves is
whether, among the patterns of universal
character put forward there is one more
likely to respect diversity in the overall
development scheme. For there are many
advantages in diversity and these advan¬
tages are not only cultural but also
economic. Are there, then, patterns and
ideologies which, while necessarily being
presented as they are that is of universal
character are more likely than others to
maintain diversity rather than consider it as
an obstacle to development, and how can
they be applied?
Left, the three Marys at the tomb; detail
from the Maestà, the altarpiece for the
main altar of the Cathedral of Siena, by the
Italian artist Duccio di Buoninsegna
(c.1260-1319). Photo © Editions d'Art
Albert Skira, Geneva. Right, Malanggan
mask from New Ireland, in the Bismarck
Archipelago, north of New Guinea (see
Unesco Courier, October 1979). Photo W.
Schneider-Schutz © Ethnological
Museum, Berlin (West).
With special reference to Africa, the
Kenyan political scientist Ali Mazrui speaks
of the university as "the pinnacle of the
structure of dependency," and particularly
cultural dependency. He considers that this
phenomenon is to be found not only in the
case of those who go abroad to study but
also of those who attended universities
within Africa, since these were so often built
upon a Western or European model, with
little relation to local needs. One has the im¬
pression that this situation has recently
changed in the direction of greater attention
to problems within Africa, but the fact re¬
mains that the tools and the language of
observation and research have been im¬
ported from outside, so that it is difficult to
contradict Mazrui's argument that the
university frequently leads to cultural
dependency. One is reminded of the oft-
quoted statement by Frantz Fanon, "To be
integrated one must become what one is not,
a White."
Bochner attempts to resolve the issue
which he has raised concerning the negative
effect of international university exchanges
by suggesting a change in their orientation.
He writes that "Programmes will have to
shift their goals explicitly and self¬
consciously from the present purpose of
producing cultural exporters to the aim of
training cultural mediators," that is to say,
people who have been trained to interpret
both cultures to both societies, in the coun¬
try of sojourn arid in the country of origin.
This issue is raised in the volume edited by
Ingrid Eide, Students as Links between
Cultures, which reports the results of
research undertaken at the request of
Unesco and which finds that such a
mediating influence occurs with con¬
siderable frequency among students who
have attended a foreign university. Our own
research also indicates that a substantial
proportion of foreign students in a number
of countries reported that they felt more
positive about their own country after their
experience abroad, with only a very small
minority indicating that they felt more
negative. This suggests that negative at¬
titudes toward one's own culture are not the
usual reaction, but the idea that more atten¬
tion be paid to education for mediation bet¬
ween cultures seems eminently reasonable.
The third and final paradox to be men¬
tioned is that those who advocate cultural
pluralism do so for different reasons, and
expect from it very different consequences.
They may favour it because they respect
other cultures. On the other hand, it is il¬
luminating to read what Gluckman, a South
African-born anthropologist, has to say
about his native country in this connexion.
"As a South African anthropologist, I have
always been impressed by the fact that in
some ways the most sympathetic and even
laudatory analyses of indigenous African
cultures in South Africa come from studies
of scholars who believed in the policy of
ethnic segregation. They describe the culture
of each African people in an idealistic
form and therein was contained the im¬
plication that those cultures were good for
the peoples concerned, an essential part of
their being, something to which they were
entitled and which they should be helped to
maintain."
Presumably these cultures were fine if
they could be kept at a distance from the
White population. It is striking to note that
agreement as to the value of maintaining
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
traditional cultures may be expressive of
such different motivations.
It should be clear from what has preceded
that the position adopted here is that if
ethnic groups wish to keep their culture
alive, they should be permitted, even en¬
couraged, to do so. There is, however, one
argument which has occasionally been ex¬
pressed in favour of increasing the
homogeneity of cultures, namely, that
cultural differences may lead to conflict. In
some cases the conflict may be minor, caus¬
ing annoyance rather than real hostility, but
even then acceptance of other groups may
be made more difficult. This is because
cultural differences tend to create an us and
them psychology.
The major difficulty lies in the general at¬
titude to which reference has already been
made, that if they differ from us, they must
be inferior. This is the major impediment to
the acceptance of cultural diversity. As Hall
puts it, we must "stop ranking either people
or talents and accept the fact that there are
many roads to truth and no culture has a
corner on the path or is better equipped than
others to search for it."
There is no easy way to predict future
developments in this complex area. The
situation may be summarized in terms of
two conflicting tendencies. On the one
hand, there is the desire on the part of the
Third World, particularly its leaders, to pro¬
fit from the technological competence of in¬
dustrially advanced countries; the diffusion
of Western culture is a consequence. On the
other hand, there is a growing concern with
keeping cultures alive, marked by the trends
toward cultural pluralism, concern about
group identity, négritude, respect for dif¬
ferences, increased resistance to a cultural
imperialism which runs the risk of destroy¬
ing the variations in ways of life which
enrich the human condition.
Changes in the direction of "moderniza¬
tion" will undoubtedly continue, and they
are needed in the fight against poverty,
illness, infant mortality, illiteracy, the in¬
ferior position of women, and the political
powerlessness of the mass of the population.
The question remains as to how these
changes may be introduced while preserving
the major aspects of the way of life of the
people concerned.
This would involve a better understanding
of the meaning and value of cultural varia¬
tions; knowledge of the needs and aspira¬
tions of other ethnic groups; the ability to
empathize with others, that is, to imagine
ourselves in their position; greater respect
for diversity; more willingness to have
priorities set by the recipients of aid rather
than by the donors; willingness to admit that
the way of life which we prefer is not
necessarily valid universally.
All of this would require an educational
campaign far more extensive than any so far
attempted. One of its aspects which should
have significant implications is the
demonstration of the interdependence of
cultures, with the tremendous amount of
borrowing and diffusion throughout
history.
The American anthropologist Ralph Lin¬
ton once wrote a convincing article entitled
"One Hundred Percent American". He
describes a day in the life of an American
citizen, the covers of whose bed are of silk
(from China), whose breakfast knife is of
steel, (first made in South India), who
drinks coffee (an Abyssinian plant), and so
on. "As he absorbs (in his newspapers) the
accounts of foreign troubles, he will, if he is
a good conservative citizen, thank a Hebrew
deity in an Indo-European language that he
is one hundred percent American." French
history might be written not only to show
what France has contributed to civilization,
but also to indicate what the rest of the
world has contributed to France. If this
variety of interdependence were more widely
recognized, we might all be able to over¬
come the limitations set on our judgment
and our attitudes by our particular culture,
and to learn that other ways of life may have
equal merit and validity.
In any case, it is a safe prediction that
although there will be some convergence in
the behaviour and values of different
societies, cultural variations will persist
throughout the world in the foreseeable
future. One can only hope that there will
also be increased recognition of the value of
cultural diversity, and of its contribution to
the development of a positive social identity.
At the same time there must also be freedom
of choice for the individual to retain as
much of his ethnic group's culture as he
wishes and to take from other cultures what
he finds most palatable. Societies have the
right to develop their own preferred
character, but so does the individual. The
search for positive identity is both individual
and social.
Otto Klineberg
CULTURAL DEVELOPMENT:
SOME REGIONAL EXPERRÎNCES
(Unesco, 1981, 477 pp.)
CONTAINING contributions from five experts from dif¬
ferent regions of the globe, this important Unesco publica¬
tion presents the essential features ofa number of regional
experiences in cultural development and highlights the many cultu¬
ral facets of the peoples of Africa, Latin America and the Carib¬
bean, Asia, the Arab States and Europe.
In Africa, in a civilization in which religion, art and morals are
the drivingforces ofsociety, the intrusion of the modern world has
often disrupted personal relationships. What new cultural objec¬
tives will come to the forefront and how will these match up to
the administrative, psychological, aesthetic and social realities
of an Africa determined to maintain its traditions and its own
personality?
If the notion of cultural identity is of primary importance in
African countries, in Latin America and the Caribbean, with their
long history of interplay between indigenouspopulations, Africans
and Europeans, there is a heightened awareness of its significance.
For Latin Americans identity means, above all, integration and
mingling. The establishment of regional agreements and educa¬
tional services bears witness to a desire for dialogue between cul¬
tures, a dialogue for which Latin Americans and the Caribbean
peoples are well prepared by the special circumstances of their
ethnic intermixture.
Although Japan and China are not included in the review of
Asia, it nevertheless covers an immense geographical area which
constitutes an astonishing reservoir of values, symbols and tradi¬
tions derivedfrom history, legend and myth. In the past, despite a
multiplicity ofethnic groups, languages, castes, micro-cultures and
religions, established patterns of thought provided the basis for a
certain cultural coherence, but the establishment ofmodern States
and the imposition of economic priorities have met with institu¬
tional as well as social and psychological resistance. In all Asian
16
countries a balance is being sought between the maintenance of
cultural authenticity and receptivity to outside influences. Asia
must rediscover its ancient pilgrimages and caravan trails but also
benefit from the facilities offered by modern communications.
Arab-Muslim culture developed on the foundation ofa spiritual
unity, but today the religious phenomenon is increasingly being
seen as a global sociological phenomenon with differentiated zones
to which the age-old influence of certain geographical, linguistic
and ethnic factors has imparted distinct, characteristic features.
After the advent of the industrial society which has consecrated the
primacy of utilitarianism and contributed to the rejection of
humanism, the author wonders whether the time has come for a
new humanism which will give back to man his physical and
spiritual dimensions. Here the spiritualistic and universalizing role
of Islamic culture will have a role to play.
In Europe, despite the surprising persistence of cultural tradi¬
tions among the people, in the countryside and in ways of life,
there has been an overwhelming development ofuniformizing mass
culture. The consequences of this, says the author, are that the
general public turns away from a cultural reality which it cannot
comprehend and which is divorced from the reality of its own
preoccupations. At the same time a high-level culture has
developed to some extent but finds itself more and more confined
within a sophisticated experimentation accessible only to initiates.
Social, economic and educational inequalities and the new means
of communication are factors whose impact will have a strong in¬
fluence in determining cultural policies.
All these regional experiences tend to the conclusion that cul¬
tural development has become a primordial demand ofboth States
and peoples and that the enhancement and recognition of cultural
diversity can only result in a better, more evenly balanced world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
AT THE
CROSS-ROADS
OF CULTURES
The writer
between two worlds
by Tahar Ben Jelloun
THE Third World intellectual must
live with a terrible fact: over 80 per
cent of people in the Third World
can neither read nor write. No magic wand
can be waved to alter their plight; it will be a
long, hard struggle which will call on men
and women with a real determination for
change. As for the poet, he is concerned by
the plight of the humiliated, whether he ex¬
periences humiliation at first hand or as an
observer. And to be excluded from reading
and writing is possibly the deepest wound
that material poverty and political cynicism
can inflict on a man.
Is it not a paradox to write in a continent
of illiterates? "No," says the Mexican
writer Carlos Fuentes, "it is not as paradox¬
ical as it may seem. Perhaps the writer
knows that he is working to keep alive a
relationship with a past which has rarely
found its political equivalent."
A literature in which many poor and
dominated peoples find a recognizable pic¬
ture of themselves has come from a single
fissure etched in the warm and human earth
of Latin America. The waifs and strays of
Bogotá are part of the same wound as the
urchins of Cairo and the shayatin ("little
devils") of Casablanca. A peasant
dispossessed of his land has the same dreams
whether he lives in north Africa or northeast
Brazil; the same imagination broken by in¬
justice, forbidden to express itself, thwarted
by a tragic fate.
Once he has resisted blandishments and
pressures, the writer born of this reality can¬
not accept that a dispossessed peasant
should be left to live what political and
military authorities call a reasonable life.
Whether he likes it or not, the writer will be
pursued unremittingly by this anonymous
crowd of urchins who have been deprived of
a childhood and who pour scorn on in¬
nocence, of men and women debarred from
a life of dignity and freedom.
Whether silent or muzzled, this crowd ap¬
peals to the writer, not in order to flatter
him but to make him listen. Who if not he
will report on this clamour of fury? This is a
fundamental reason why a writer should
write, even if he will not be read by the
crowd which cries out to him.
It is possible not to write, not to respond
to this pressing demand, not to hear the
silenced voice, to look elsewhere, to be
wrapped up in one's own trivial problems. It
is quite possible for the writer to turn down
this "mission". He may think that the fate
of the people from whence he came is no
concern of his. He may even aspire to
become a member of the dominant class.
But it does sometimes happen that the writer
feels concerned, and questions his writing to
LITERACY AND EDUCATION
Illiteracy is no longer the unhappy prerogative of the developing countries, as certain industrialized coun¬
tries are beginning to realize that they are sufferingfrom a relapse into illiteracy; but as we all know the map
of illiteracy coincides almost exactly with that ofpoverty and that in the 25 least-developed countries the
proportion of illiterates still exceeds 80per cent. Despite the prodigious efforts made by so many countries
of the Third World in the field of education, it is estimated that in 1980 there were still 322 million children
in the world between the ages of 6 and 17 not attending school, and a world total (excluding China and the
Democratic People's Republic of Korea) of 814 million illiterates.
Photo International Labour Office, J.P. Laffont © Sygma, Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
the point that he writes no more about this
reality. Fuentes comments on this: "To
abstain from writing would be to accept
defeat, and one need only walk through the
streets of Bogotá, Mexico City or Lima to
know that Latin America has drunk almost
to the dregs the cup of defeat."
"A continent of illiterates" has a greater
need of writers than a continent sated with
knowledge. Writing here is a refusal to ac¬
cept defeat. For Fuentes it also means bank¬
ing on liberty: "It means saying to yourself
in the intimacy of the act of writing that it is
imperative to keep alive the culture of the
past, without which we have neither a real
present nor an intelligible future; all this in
the knowledge that we shall not achieve con¬
crete results, we shall not change the world
by writing ten books or a thousand, and we
shall receive no reward."
And so we have this gamble on liberty and
on the future, for this continent will not
always be afflicted by the inevitability of il¬
literacy. Those who come later, perhaps the
children of this period, will be entitled to
call us to account. The writer will have to
declare his books or his silence.
Writing cannot be a soft option, for there
is so much want and deprivation in our
societies. The writer must be an all-purpose
figure. The real world cries out for his atten¬
tion. So many appeals call for a response.
He is needed in so many fields. He must
show ingenuity and patience, for he was
born among people who are sick of words.
He must listen and he must act to satisfy the
immediate need. This writer will be regarded
as a journalist, lawyer, go-between, trade
union spokesman, spokesman of a cause,
public writer, prophet of hard times, a man
involved in all his country's struggles, a
symbol, a myth, a social worker, and his
country's ambassador in the firmament of
letters... The list is never-ending.
LITERACY AND EDUCATION. It is to be hoped that by
adopting new structures, new admission procedures and new
methods such as teaching by correspondence, by radio or by
television, universities will open their doors wider to a new
range of students, many of whom will not have been able to
follow a normal academic career. It is to be hoped that they will
organize meetings or seminars to inform and instruct the dif¬
ferent social groups and wide sections of the population and
that they will also play an active role in literacy campaigns,
working side by side with the population, which will, more
often than not, be a rural population, in the national develop¬
ment effort.
The United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and
Unesco are helping the Government of Ethiopia to establish a
functional literacy project for adults. Here a young boy is
teaching his father to read with the aid of a textbook prepared
and distributed under the project. Photo Garraud, Unesco.
Everything remains to be done in these
countries castigated by history, where
ideologies come up against a complex reality
which is more overwhelming and unex¬
pected than any fiction, in which imported
models crumble or remain unused, their
claims to universality intact. The writer is
expected to be permanently on call, open to
everything which shakes up and galvanizes
this poor soil pregnant with millions of
dreams, tales and images. He is not only re¬
quired to be a political militant making an
impact on society; he must also be a poet, a
creator, fertilized by this soil and by this
people.
The commitment of the artist implies
solving his country's problems at the same
time as creating a work of art. This still has
a meaning in countries which are con¬
fronted with life-and-death problems, not
intellectual fads. In this respect the Peruvian
writer Mario Vargal Llora has noted
something which is valid not only for Latin
America but for the Third World as a
whole. "Elsewhere, to be a writer means
primarily and often exclusively, assuming a
personal responsibility for a body of work
which, if artistically valid, will enrich the
culture of the country in which it is created.
In Peru and in other Latin American coun¬
tries, to be a writer means primarily, and
often exclusively, assuming a social respon¬
sibility." There is virtually no escape from
assuming the function. If you turn your
back on this imperative, if you retreat into
isolation, if you refuse to become involved
LITERACY AND EDUCATION. In the
developing countries that have recently
gained their independence, under the
lingering influence of systems inherited
from the colonial period, education still
often fails to some extent to match the real
situations and needs. In many of those
countries, the question of the language of
instruction is still unsettled, even in primary
school, and the use ofcurricula to maintain
and reinforce cultural identity is an acute
problem.
Young pupils in a Mexican school. Photo
© Marino Benzi.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
in the life of the people, if you withdraw in¬
to selfish solitude, it is often taken as an
avowal by the writer that he is not commit¬
ted, so that he is accused because of his
silence and his remoteness of complicity
with the forces of oppression. Not to de¬
nounce injustice, to be silent, is unthinkable
for a writer mandated to speak out and write
by a continent of illiterates. Literature is ex¬
pected to be useful, operational and ver¬
satile in its functions, roles "and powers.
Literature takes its cue from science, just as
it makes inroads on ideology. It becomes an
activity in the service of truth.
If this conception of literary activity
relates to reality by making the writer a
repository of information with his eyes fixed
on the outside world, then it causes a major
misunderstanding. For the main thing is
forgotten, namely how to write, how to
create.
Should we then go far in the other direc¬
tion and regard literature as a pure stylistic
exercise or a lifeless tour de force? The
vogue for the French nouveau roman open¬
ed up several possibilities for the renewal of
academic writing, but it also stripped
literature of flesh and blood. When I read I
love to feel behind the words a stretch of
land, a breathing body, life going on
somewhere. In some novels, however, the
belated products of this fashion, the sterility
of the text corresponds to a social situation
in which land and body have perhaps ceased
to breathe.
There is a widespread misunderstanding
about where the writer's commitment lies.
To militate in a political party or organiza¬
tion is one thing; to write while taking part
in politics as well is another. The one does
not exclude the other. But it is rare that the
two combine in such a way as not to be
mutually harmful and do not create con¬
fusion and misunderstandings. One does
not have to be an artist to feel concerned by
what breaks and stifles the voice of a people.
This is a matter for concern of every citizen
who refuses submission and resignation. If
he also happens to be a writer, then so much
the better, for in principle he has the means,
however limited, to put up a better
resistance to barbarism and to participate
through his work as a writer in affirming his
people's culture, which is itself threatened
over a period of time with asphyxia, abduc¬
tion and death.
As for the writer who deliberately chooses
to live in exile, he leaves far behind him the
prevailing stagnation, the temptation to bit¬
terness and inactivity. He sets out alone,
neither adventurer nor hero but someone
who decides to set his eyes on other
horizons, at his own risk. Whatever he does
is bound to be wrong! If exile leads to
nothing, he is wrong. If exile brings him suc¬
cess, he is wrong. The child who leaves his
family connexions by the wayside is not
forgiven. He will not be pardoned for many
things, and whatever happens an effort will
be made to make him feel guilty, to make
him feel that he is a bit of a traitor, especial¬
ly if he succeeds in being a productive
creative artist. He will be blamed for having
it too easy. He will be the target of am¬
bivalent and often unchanging feelings,
nourished by a host of vague and obscure
ideas.
But voluntary exile, the need to go
elsewhere to encounter other realities and
other worlds, is preferable to marking time,
which is often the prelude to a slow death,
sterility, desiccation and self-absorption.
Others would say, "It's better to mark time
with your own people than to take refuge
abroad." And so the question should be
defined in political terms, not in affective
and moral terms.
Why have so many writers and artists
from our countries felt the need at one time
or another to leave their own country in
order to live and work, temporarily or per¬
manently, in another society? Why have
they been able to create elsewhere? Is it not
because in other countries they have found
conditions and structures propitious for
writing, painting, meeting other people, ex¬
changing ideas, in a word, for communica¬
tion? Have they not found elsewhere what is
most lacking in their own country: rivalry, a
critical spirit, freedom, the sense of dif¬
ference that stimulates creativity? Of
course, it may be countered, but why not
create these conditions, these basic struc¬
tures, in one's own country? True, it is a
priori easier to leave than to stay. For stay¬
ing is not an easy option; one must fight,
often alone, against oppression, against the
ugliness and weight of bureaucracy. The ar¬
tist must fight to avoid the snare held out by
those who want to entice him on to their side
and use him to their own ends. He must
struggle with himself, and resist all kinds of
temptations, discouragement, fatigue and
indifference. Mediocrity becomes dangerous
when it takes root, becomes accepted, and
spreads. It is contagious. The energy and the
instinct to react are lost.
So the writer should remain vigilant and
continue to believe in his creative powers.
He should barricade himself against the out¬
side world, confining himself to an almost
schizophrenic universe which may ultimate¬
ly be his only solution. He should take
refuge in an inner exile, withdraw from im¬
mediate reality, fight to survive and create
his own working environment. But all this
often means that he loses the power to use
words. Inner exile also means losing oneself
in social gossip, in drink, in oblivion, in a
slow decline into narcissism.
To be far away does not necessarily mean
to be absent. To go away is another way of
establishing links with one's land and peo¬
ple. This kind of exile may be fruitful, or at
any rate not systematically negative. It is not
the writer who lives in exile who should be
pilloried, but the political structure which
respects neither his difference nor his
freedom. Wherever it is produced, the work
of a writer or an artist returns in one way or
another to the land of its origin.
But when exile becomes a way of thinking
and of becoming ensnared in the toils of an
unhappy conscience, when it severs a man
from his deepest roots, when it becomes an
end in itself and submerges the individual in
a set of problems which ought not really to
concern him, then exile becomes alienation.
It returns to the mother country another
person, often a stranger who has lost the
capacity of wonder: a wreck apparently in
good health.
I Tahar Ben Jelloun
National identity
and foreign domination
by Ngugi Wa Thiong 'o
THE crisis of culture in the developing
world has too often been seen in
terms of tradition and modernity,
the rural and the urban, and the conflict of
cultures consequently engendered by that
dichotomy. In this schema, the urban (in¬
dustry, technology, electronics) is identified
with modernity, the rural (subsistence
agriculture, economic backwardness) with
tradition.
But ironically, the same modernity is sup¬
posed to evoke images of fast changes, in¬
stability, and human isolation, while tradi¬
tion evokes contrary images of peace,
stability, and communal existence. Rampant
urbanization and industrialization are seen
as destroying a harmony of values embodied
in tradition whose repository is the rural
community. Thus the false glitter of the
electronic culture is seen as luring an unwary
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
«youth away from the stability of a com¬
munal life in a rural village into the chaos
and loneliness of life in the big city.
It is all there in written literature. The
peasant who follows the mirage of prosperi¬
ty and happiness in the big city only to find
the opposite is a familiar character in many
a novel from the developing world. What
often is not stated is that such a character is
actually escaping from the hell of rural
poverty and misery into the Hades of urban
poverty and misery, in both cases brought
about by ruthless exploitation. But even
where this is stated, the schema of rural ur¬
ban dichotomy as the basis of analysis of the
problems of culture in developing countries
remains, and the crisis of culture is still seen
in terms of a conflict between tradition and
modernity.
Two misleading assumptions underlie the
schema. Modern industry, science and
technology are seen as being opposed to
tradition and peasant cultures. The destruc¬
tion of tradition or aspects of tradition and
peasant culture is seen as necessarily evil.
The beauty of rural culture must rest on a
foundation of poverty and abject want. But
surely modern science and technology,
depending on their organization, ownership
and control, now make possible a total
economic transformation of the countryside
and thus the erection of a whole people's
culture on a structure of prosperity instead
of backwardness.
Moreover, far from destroying tradition,
modern technology (e.g. Video, Cinema,
Television, Radio) makes possible a
reclamation of the positive aspects of tradi¬
tion and peasant cultures. Africa for in¬
stance has a rich tradition of oral literature.
Take the tale, for instance. The oral nar¬
rative was often accompanied by mime and
song. With video, film, or television, it is
now possible to reclaim this tradition
through an integration of the visual (e.g.
animated cartoons) and the verbal (i.e. the
voice telling the tale and the accompanying
music).
The same is true in theatre. African pea¬
sant theatre relied heavily on song, dance
and mime, and these can now be permanent¬
ly captured on the screen. Thus not only is it
possible to democratize access to this
heritagemore people can be told the tale
at the same timebut even more crucial, it
is possible to integrate the national cultures
within the geographic State.
The other assumption is that the rural and
the urban are two self-contained islands and
a character who walks from one to the other
is actually journeying across two unlinked
entities. But the two are a creation of each
other. The urban is a creation of the rural as
much as the rural is a creation of the urban.1
The peasantry had to be alienated from the
soil and be driven into towns, that is, they
had to be proletarianized before the modern
city could be born. But where under feudal
and semi-feudal systems, the town was
under the sway of the countryside, the
modern city which emerged with capitalism,
the city of gold, became the master of the
rural of which it had been born and bred.
"The bourgeoisie", Marx wrote of
nineteenth-century Europe, "has sub¬
jected the country to the rule of the
towns. It has created enormous cities, has
greatly increased the urban population as
compared with the rural, and has thus
rescued a considerable part of the popula¬
tion from the idiocy of rural life. Just as it
has made the country dependent upon
20
'VINONMAB
rflNBJNSUO
IMPÍO«
teTwvnree
ifonetinn '
»PBS»
v« ^
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
f u ,
... u« . ^ ^'
¿ *5
/f
¡m
i
-. ?? r/ /r? /i
(Ci¿)'
au B
(* ^&*
G&ip-'i&t > f"
<£ A » -1*5-« >i'.' -..î
'. fíí in.- u-ii , '/3s
. , . 1
.
i>ii* > ¡ai ".1 v
^JL uj* > tfi ^ >liH ir£ »
. » v -O, KJ v
> .
^i^ LÜ '- >'¿
-
.11 M
1
\M¿3j¡I
|
t i ¿fctóu 59
LITERACY AND EDUCATION. ffnï/«£ A<w 6«;« M>/íAoHf í/ow&í r/re otoíí radical and
creative of man 's inventions. Not because it could be said, by itself, to be synonymous
with culturefor there exist rich oral cultures, and all written cultures are partially compos¬
ed of orally transmitted traditions, but because writing adds to culture a fundamental
dimension. This is the possibility of infinite self-enrichment and the capacity for abstrac¬
tion through which a culture can both adapt constantly to change, while preserving the
most characteristic features of its heritage, and establish, beyond the limits of time and
space, a constant flow ofcommunication with others. Whereas oral tradition is a means of
passing on a cultural heritage, only the written word can make that heritage bear fruit.
But with the introduction of machinery, the implements of work become a stronger deter¬
mining factor than manpower in the productive process because they incorporate more
and more scientific and technological elements, and this creates insuperable obstacles for ''
the illiterate population. Complex machinery remains a closed world to them. Thus
literacy must count as one of the few basic, irreducible needs of modern man simply
because it governs his access to progress.
Top left, the Corbie Psalter, a 9th-century illuminated manuscript, now in the Municipal
Library, Amiens. (Photo Belzeaux-Zodiaque © Rapho, Paris). Left, pupil at a Koranic
school at Timbo, Guinea. (Photo © Dominique Darbois, Paris). Above, Solid gold Per¬
sian plaque, 50 cm x 50 cm, dating from the 5th century BC, commemorates, in three
languages, the founding of Babylon. (Photo © Luc Joubert, Paris). Below, Students at a
school in Tokyo prepare banners for the New Year celebrations. (Photo Tamagawa
Gakuen, Unesco).
<3 7SN 1
2 1*1
&
it
"
*
i
*
M ;2
\% - "»ih*
t X ' !* I
'fkJ *
:-^-
^->
towns, so it has made barbarian and semi-
barbarian countries dependent on the
civilized ones, nations of peasants on na¬
tions of bourgeois, the East on the
West".
With the evolution of capitalism into the
higher stage of imperialism, the rural and
urban sectors of the nations of peasants
became even more subjected to the rule of
the nations of bourgeoisie, and with what
results: the subject nations the majority of
the population were now reduced to the
idiocy of the new urban and rural life.
This subjection of the nations of peasants
to the nations of bourgeoisie is the heart of
the matter when discussing problems of the
developing countrieseconomic, political
or cultural.
But by posing the problems of culture in
the developing world in terms of a conflict
between modernity and tradition, between
the rural and the urban, thus concentrating
on secondary contradictions, we are
avoiding the real issues behind the crisis.
What are the real forces behind modernity
and tradition, the urban and the rural? We
have, in other words, to see the whole
problem (modernity, tradition, rural, ur¬
ban) in a historical perspective.
This would reveal to us that the major
contradiction in the Third World is between
national identity and imperialist domina¬
tion. The developing world with its
economic, political and cultural backward¬
ness, its massive poverty, illiteracy and
disease, is a creation of imperialism in its
colonial and neo-colonial stages. The
developing world can in fact be defined as
all those countries in Asia, Africa and Latin
America which have been underdeveloped
by imperialism, those countries whose
economy, politics and culture have been and
continue to be dominated by Western im¬
perialist nations. This in essence means the
economic, political and cultural subjection
of the whole population of the dominated
countries to the ruling bourgeois classes of
the dominating nations.
i "The bourgeoisie", wrote Marx and
! Engels, "by the rapid development of all
instruments and production, by the im¬
mensely facilitated means of communica-
j tion, draws all, even the most barbarian,
nations into civilization. The cheap prices
of its commodities are the heavy artillery
with which it batters down all Chinese
walls, with which it forces the barbarian's
intensely obstinate hatred of foreigners to
capitulate. It compels all nations, on pain
of extinction, to adopt the bourgeois
mode of production; it compels them to
introduce what it calls civilization into
their midst, to become bourgeois
themselves. In a word, it creates a world
after its own image".
A world after its own image: this it tried
to achieve not only through economic
exploitation and political subjugation
but more importantly, through cultural
domination.
But the process created its opposite: the
economic, political and cultural struggle for
national independence and total liberation.
In the colonies and neo-colonies, there in
fact emerged two cultures in mortal conflict:
foreign imperialist cultures and national
patriotic cultures. Thus there emerged, out
of the different nationalities often in¬
habiting one geographic State, a people's
literature, music, dance, theatre, art, in^
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
fierce struggle against foreign literature,
theatre, music, art imposed on colonies,
semi-colonies and neo-colonies.
This to me is still the real and fundamen¬
tal conflict of cultures: a national patriotic
culture in struggle against foreign imperialist
cultures. Other contradictions, between the
urban and the rural, between the different
nationalities, are secondary and can only be
properly appreciated within the context of
the larger, basic contradiction.
In this war of cultures, the people try to
find their roots in the patriotic traditions of
their culture mostly kept alive by the peasan¬
try in their songs, poems, theatre and
dances. The foreign imperialist culture tries
to find a stronghold in the cities mas¬
querading under notions of modernity and
progress.
This is not an accident. The native
bourgeoisie through which imperialism
works in the colonies and neo-colonies
dwells in the city. Very often it controls the
State instruments of copersuasion and pro¬
paganda. In their State-controlled theatres,
cinemas, T.V. stations, radio, they only
allow foreign programmes, while in the
education system they advocate the use of
foreign languages, and the study of foreign
literature only. The impoverished, exploited
peasantry dwells in the countryside. That is
why the struggle between national and
foreign cultures appears on the surface as a
conflict between the rural and the urban, or
between tradition and modernity.
But what is really modern is the new na¬
tional cultures emerging out of the struggle
for total liberation, a culture rooted in the
patriotic and heroic traditions of the people.
This is better seen in the resistance poetry
and songs and theatre among workers in the
urban areas of the developing world. It is a
fighting culture, a resistance culture, and
though fusing different elements, it is in
basic harmony with the resistance culture of
the countryside. The urban and the rural
struggles find this harmony in their opposi¬
tion to both foreign imperialist exploitation
and domination and internal exploitation
and oppression. The urban worker and the
rural peasant are the basis and creators of
truly national cultures in the developing
world.
What then is the crisis of culture in Africa
and in the developing world as a whole?
The real crisis of culture in Africa is still
the imperialist domination of our economy,
politics and culture no country can con¬
sider itself free as long as its economy and
culture are dominated by foreigners.
A pre-requisite of Africa's cultural
development is therefore a continued strug¬
gle for its economic and political liberation
from all vestiges of imperialism. This also
means a continued struggle against the com¬
prador ruling class through whom im¬
perialism continues to dominate the lives of
millions of peasants and workers of the
developing world.
A new world economic and political order
would mean a new world cultural order and
this would see the flowering of a great
modern culture in Africa and the rest of the
developing world, a culture that has roots in
the dynamic progressive aspects of a na¬
tional tradition while remaining open to the
progressive and humanist cultural element
all over the world.
H Ngugi Wa Thiong'o
22
The machinery
of cultural power
by Augusto Roa Bastos
WHEN it comes to the philosophy
and practice of cultural power,
the niceties of literary creation
count for little. No question of getting tied
up in superfluous classifications. The
publicity apparatus of cultural power can
raise up mediocrity and creative nullity to
the level of apparent virtues of the first
order.
Within this cosmic vision of profit, a
book is a book. And with each "successful"
book all of literature is originated, born
daily. In certain cases, it is not the intrinsic
merits of a text which matter, but the epic of
its launching, its promotion and dissemina¬
tion in the most complete gamut of possible
combinations. Sometimes nearly always in
fact the promoters and vendors of such
best-sellers show more imagination than
their authors. Indeed, the best-seller in¬
dustry itself could serve as a hypertrophied
example of the manipulation of the pub¬
lishing industry by cultural power an ex¬
ample which, to a greater or lesser extent
dominates the world literary market.
As is the case with the activities of the
multinationals in other fields, cultural
power (a semantic barbarism which points
to its depredatory origins) sets up its
autonomous rules within imperial metrop¬
olises, ignoring or crossing frontiers and
political barriers as if they were so much
smoke or, alternately, making use of them.
Both in this connexion and in the similarity
of their goalsconquest of markets, profit
and economic and political domination
the now classic model of arms-selling gives
an approximate idea of the way in which
multinationals operate as a cultural power.
In the case of the book industry itself,
from the head offices in metropolitan cen¬
tres to the network of subsidiaries located in
the strategic centres of peripheral cultures, it
is cultural power which dictates the rules of
the game.
As a result, the oldest, most solid and
most prestigious publishing concerns
(publishers, publishing and distribution
outlets, the old and noble profession of the
bookseller as guide and mentor of readers,
library systems, the production of educa¬
tional text-books, specialized institutions,
foundations, etc.) are annexed, blocked, or
subjected to its investment dictates. It par¬
ticipates in, controls or takes over all of the
media (cinema, radio, television, written
press) which can contribute to the expansion
of its business, as well as subsidiary con-
CONTINUED PAGE 27
Colour pages
Culture is a synthesis of all the creative activities
of a people, its modes of producing and using
material objects, the social relationships which
prevail within it, the ways in which it is organized.
8J |	6
7
its conquests and defeats, its Joys and sorrows,
its sufferings, its beliefs, and its artistic and
literary creations, whether these are written
down or, as in the oral civilizations, transmitted
by word of mouth from generation to generation.
Colour pages illustrate various aspects of
the notion of culture.
Page 23
HUMAN SETTLEMENTS (1): New York
LANGUAGE (2): Japanese TV announcer
MYTHS (3): Sleeping male maam, painting on
bark by the aborigine artist Namatbara, Croker
Island, Australia (H. 75 cm, W. 56.5 cm).
Museum of African and Oceanic Art, Paris
RELIGIOUS STATUS (4): Buddhas in the Dam-
bulla grotto (Sri Lanka). 3rd century BC
ORAL TRADITION (5): Griot or "public enter¬
tainer" (United Republic of Cameroon)
TRADITIONAL TECHNIQUES (6): Statue
designed to show trainee doctors the "points" of
acupuncture (China)
SEXUALITY (7): Couple (thermography)
FAMILY LIFE (8): A Peruvian family
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
I
/ j^ i 7%rM
H ^^m
'1
1
\ \
1^
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 22
cerns such as the paper and printing in¬
dustries. It also has at its disposal the
arsenal of modern technology (computers,
data banks, etc.), the main branches of
which form part of its complex industrial
network.
In the so-called peripheral countries,
cultural power has almost totally eliminated
the independent publishing houses which
strove to maintain a balanced exchange bet¬
ween national and foreign literatures.
In such conditions the operative strategy
of cultural power, its philosophy of action,
determines taste on the basis of statistics. In¬
deed, the distinctive mark of a culture can
be made to change to serve its interests. The
best-seller industry already referred to il¬
lustrates the extent of the devastating in¬
fluence which has changed the modes and
values of a conception . and tradition of
book-culture in a number of countries
which rank among the most important in
the world. Nevertheless, it should not be
thought that its privileged monopoly status
has made cultural power something which is
pyramidal in form and importance. Its real
potential is rooted in the idea of competition
between equals, in its capacity to associate
itself with other forces, to elaborate itself in¬
definitely, to infiltrate everywhere.
The objective of these consortia is not
dispersion but ever greater concentration.
This also holds true for their assets in depen¬
dent countries. The increasing bankruptcies
of independent publishing houses, the ap¬
pearance and disappearance of others which
emerge and act as fronts or dissuasive
elements are a sure sign that multinationals
are running the show.
An independent publisherone of the
few who still fights the battle for a just and
harmonious relationship between authors,
publishers and the public in the territory of
book activity occupied by multinationals
was able to confirm the following, well-
founded facts: "The way the current system
works (in terms of its penetration by
multinationals) simply favours the entry in¬
to the market of the large publishing houses
which are themselves subsidiaries of
transnational complexes. These multina¬
tional enterprises find a very large potential
market, a public avid for reading material,
and using their vast experience they produce
an unlimited administrative and financial in¬
frastructure and an international distribu¬
tion network".
In the case of Latin-American cultures
which are to a lesser or greater degree depen¬
dent, what is at stake is more than a certain
statistic concerning taste. It is the very in¬
tegrity of these cultures which is threatened
and, within them, the development of
literatures which are the expression of their
unity and identity in spite of the inequalities,
the lack of synchronization and the absence
of communication which characterizes our
cultural destiny.
The synthesis of these imbalances is ef¬
fected, or has been effected, by the dialec¬
tical process involving culture and society,
tradition and the avant-garde, the local and
the universal. However, if such a synthesis is
to be truly fertile, it must be effected along
the lines of force of a common process, that
is to say, along the lines of force of our unity
and identity, of our Spanish-American
character.
To talk in terms of a process implies
recognition of the existence of a set of cor¬
relations and shared variations in constant
mutation: the interpretation of the vital
rhythms of communities united by a com¬
mon language and subjected to the same or
analogous historical imperatives. So it is
that the well-worn concept of identity ceases
to be an idealistic and "ideologized"
abstraction and comes to express correctly
not the invariables of an unchanging and
inward-looking reality, but the coherence of
this conjuncture of relationships in non-stop
transformation.
Identity is thus unity in continuity of a
characterological complex which defines its
essence in action, the features of its physical
and spiritual personality in its plans, suc¬
cesses and failures, and in its manner of fac¬
ing factors extraneous to its nature, while at
the same time assimilating those which seem
constructive and enriching, whatever their
source. In other words, it refuses a passive
and blind acceptance of dominant cultures.
In this connexion, cultural colonialism is
not only an imposition, it is also a dazzling
fascination, a compulsive need to imitate the
prestigious seigneurial and imperial stan¬
dards and forms. To be dominated cultural¬
ly is to be seduced. At times raped. The old
dispute as to whether the effects of the
dominant influences of central cultures on
surrounding ones are formative or deform¬
ing has been settled by the cultural facts
themselves.
These facts are deforming in the sense
that local cultures see servitude to the forms,
models, procedures and customs of the cen¬
tral cultures as an imposition or a joy. They
are enriching on condition that the local
cultures react critically and convert them in¬
to catalyzers of their own spirit and
character. It is not a question either of the
extreme oppositeof absurdly restoring the
indigenous cultures and of sinking into the
Colour pages 24-25
ARTISTIC TRADITION
(1 ) The English pop singer Mick Jagger during a
concert
(5) The Sainte Chapelle, Paris (13th century)
(6) Scene painted for an illustrated edition of the
Arab manuscript the Maqamat by Al-Hariri,
one of the most striking works of the
Baghdad school (634AH/1237AD).
Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
(8) Lyric (Man on Horseback), 1911, oil on can¬
vas (H. 94.5 cm, W. 130 cm) by Wassily
Kandinsky (1866-1944). Boymans van Beun-
ingen Museum, Rotterdam
(9) Mukishi wa pwo mask of the Chokwe people
(H. 23 cm). Wood, plant fibres and tukuta (a
red wood powder). (Zaire)
(10) Woman decorating a house at Oualata
(Mauritania)
(11) Buddhist monks provide the music at the
Paro Tsechu festival (Bhutan)
(13) Architectural project for an ideal city by the
Tuscan painter Piero della Franceses
(1406-1492). Part of an altarpiece, Urbino
(Italy)
(14) Ashanti craftsmen at the village of Anhniaa
(Ghana)
9
10
_u
12
13
	3|
|	4
1
V J I	5
zj \	^
I	6
	8J
7
THE HISTORICAL DIMENSION
(2) Painting on parchment (H. 9cm, W. 11cm).
Ethiopia, 17th century
(3) Gorée (Senegal). Once a centre of the slave
trade
(4) Sculpture on the Buddhist temple of
Borobudur (Indonesia). 8th-9th century
(7) Detail of two of the four bronze horses, pro¬
bably of Greek origin, which adorn the
façade of St. Mark's basilica, Venice (Italy)
(12) Stele from the Maya site of Copan (Hon¬
duras). 7th-8th century
(15) "Nezem" (nose-ring) Punic terra-cotta mask
used in religious ceremonies (6th-7th century
BC)
Colour page 26
EATING HABITS
(1) Preparing a meal in Bolivia
(6) Mealtime in Bangkok (Thailand)
(7) Large Still Life (1910-1912), oil on waxed
canvas (H. 99 cm, W 135 cm) by the Rus¬
sian painter Niko Piromanaschvili
GAMES AND PLAY (2): Young skateboard
virtuoso (France)
POLITICAL ORGANIZATION (3): Village palaver
(Niger)
WORK
(4) Filming of Orlando Furioso by the Italian
director Luca Ronconi
(8) Fishermen on poles (Sri Lanka)
SOCIAL ORGANIZATION (5): New-born babies
(Asia)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
chaos of a local ethnocentricity which would
be ill-advised and artificial. Neither does it
mean blindly and stubbornly rejecting the
norms from outside, which made it possible
for us to construct our Creole cathedrals, to
develop our material civilization and the
most creative aspects of our mixed culture.
But they also help us to recognize our
cultural identity in the process of racial in¬
termingling and to orient our liberation
struggles in all fields.
In the field of fictional literaturepoetry,
novels, theatre these models and foreign
norms, the work of the great poets, novelists
and dramatists of the central cultures, once
the stage of experimental imitation was
passed, that is to say, once the genuine spirit
of our literatures had been recovered, have
contributed in a decisive way to the develop¬
ment of these literatures in closely-defined
periods and epochs.
In this problematic arising out of the ac¬
tive and vital identity of our cultures the
functions and responsibilities of the élites
are obvious. But it is equally clear that iden¬
tity understood in this way is not the ex¬
clusive apanage of these élites.
Such an identity is forged and constructed
in the fire of social energy by the élites, but
also by the untutored masses who lack ex¬
pression. No genuine culture can reduce
itself to the quintessentially, chemically pure
distillation of elitist values nor can it do
without the life-giving breath of popular
culture, the powerful and obscure palpita¬
tion of the submerged masses whose lack of
culture is a specific form of the culture of
marginalization, of backwardness and op¬
pression. This also holds true for indigenous
cultures, which are more coherent (in spite
of their unstructured form and the threat of
extinction hanging over them) in the impure
context of our mestizo culture.
It is precisely this dichotomy between the
"cultivated" and the "uncultivated" and
the variables of its interaction within a given
society and within societies at large which
enriches the real subsoil of Latin-American
identity: the illuminated part and the
shadowy part of its transitional culture link¬
ed to the vicissitudes of its history under the
sign of economic and cultural dependence.
The "massification" of books produced
by the cultural industry does not imply, or
announce, the establishment of a mass
culture. Quite the contrary. The objectives
of the entrepreneurial economy, in the
original sense of an economy of en¬
trepreneurs, are not to create a mass culture,
but to extract massive dividends from
investments.
Such objectives have even less to do with
the abolition of the elitist taste (or at least
the elitist predilections) of bourgeois
culture. In fact, what counts in this context,
which happens to be its principal theatre of
operations, are the more efficient diffusing
nuclei of prestige and sacralization:
academies, institutes, influential per¬
sonalities, writers who are at the same time
critics, etc.
Conscious of the role which the local and
international intelligentsias perform, the
cultural power uses them unscrupulously.
In the case of local élites, the availability
and co-operation of their members tend
naturally to be put at the service of the
dispensers of prestige and material
remuneration as if it were a mark of distinc¬
tion. In general, they are the most willing
and effective guides, intermediaries and
assessors who prepare the ground for the
multinationals to penetrate national ter¬
ritories with a licence to plunder.
As for the élites of the central countries or
those which continue to perform the role of
dispensers of culture and advanced
technology thanks to the competition which
permits and promotes the division into rival
blocs of the so-called First World, the com¬
plicity of the intellectuals and writers with
the factors of power (political power,
economic power, cultural power) is a
notorious and inveterate fact; one could
almost say it has become institutionalized.
As in other fields of power, cultural
power can only unfold its maximal possibil¬
ities of predominance by engrafting its
structures onto the apparatus of an intellec¬
tual bureaucracy which is attached
ideologically to the philosophy and interests
of that power- and which always, or nearly
always, acts in collaboration with the
political power, whatever its political orien¬
tation: from the reactionary right to the sup¬
posed openings to the left in the unchanging
framework of bourgeois democracy.
This apparatus of clercs (which has
replaced the old corporations of elders
which existed in feudal societies) dominates
all the institutions of official cultures:
academies, universities, libraries, cultural
organisms of every kind, foundations,
literary contests, specialized criticism, radio
and television programmes, etc.
In such conditions, it is not the reader
who looks for, and selects his books. The
latter are imposed on him in accordance
with an indiscriminate programming which,
in its consequences, is actually discrimina¬
tory; the reader is chosen by the omniscient
index of the microprocessor in the prospec¬
tive field of the calculation of probabilities.
The abstract image of this average reader
is projected by the computers in virtue of
certain forms tested in the market and in any
event imposed upon it. The author-text-
reader relationship undergoes, as a result, a
profound change under the impact of the
mass-produced, itemized book and its
publicity which presents it not as an offer,
but as an order. No revealing testimony
about this distorsion is available to the
average reader. He accepts it unawares, just
as he accepts each day the "revealed
truths", the propagandizing gospels of the
mass media on underwear, on varieties of
canned goods or balanced foods for cats
and dogs. Even so-called cultivated readers
end up by giving in to this compulsion which
works on the primary instincts of the
consumer.
In contrast with this real situation, "How
many books are not really published but just
churned out!" exclaimed one independent
French publisher who has experienced from
the inside the fight against the giants of
publishing. The latter are a very special
species whom Swift would have castigated
had he been alive today and witnessed our
era in which millions and millions of Lillipu¬
tians are enslaved by the strong-arm-men of
money. Having appropriated the Gutenberg
Galaxy, they have arranged a match or at
least a cross-breeding operation with the
audiovisual galaxy, thereby nullifying
McLuhan's prophecy about the death of the
book.
M Augusto Roa Bastos
LITERACY AND EDUCATION.
From the standpoint of lifelong educa¬
tion itself, considered not as further
vocational training but rather as an
overall process of education, starting
with the earliest stage and continuing
throughout life, the development of in¬
formal and non-formal types of educa¬
tion, and better co-ordination between
them and the formal systems, also seem
to meet the wish to bring about greater
interpénétration between education and
society as a whole. This would makefor
that diversification of the content,
methods, structures and levels of educa¬
tion and training required by the
modem world. New questions arise as
to the choices to be made regarding im¬
ported technology: how to gain access
to the possibilities of immediate pro¬
gress offered by technology without
falling into a new kind of dependence;
28
how and to what extent a society can
rapidly acquire modern science and
technology without losing its central
values and internal cohesion. Even
more than the transfer of technology,
the decisive factor in long-term progress
seems to be the transfer of knowledge.
Full control even of the choice of
technologies appears unattainable
unless an adequate domestic research
capacity and store of knowledge are
there to be drawn on. There is here cer¬
tainly a common challenge that will
have to be faced by most
societieswhether industrialized or
developing in the years ahead: to nar¬
row the margin of incomprehension,
not to say the cleavage, between the
world of technology and the mass of the
people, and to ensure the dynamic in-,
tegration of the achievements of
modern technology into the reality of
the underlying cultures. A major task
confronting specialists in the social and
human sciences is to find points of in¬
teraction and reconciliation between
technology and culture; an equally im¬
portant task for educational systems is
to narrow the gap between "the two
cultures" by blending elements drawn
from the "humanities" into the training
of scientists, engineers and
technologists and raising the level of
scientific and technological knowledge
in so-called general education.
Above, students receive technical in¬
struction in the carpentry workshop at
Conakry Technical High School,
Guinea. (Photo Marc Riboud ©
Magnum, Paris). Below, Tanzanian
children at work in a school garden
make their contribution to the cam¬
paign to improve nutrition. (Photo
Bernard P. Wolff, Unicef).
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The woman revolution
by Han Suyin
CULTURE is defined as an assembly
of spiritual and material values, at¬
tainments and beliefs, knowledge
and skills, which produce a corpus with
a distinctive identity. This body of thought,
behaviour and social customs is transmitted
by the group or groups practising it to suc¬
ceeding generations as its "culture".
Inter-cultural communication is not new.
Throughout the millennia man has travelled
in groups or singly, and his culture has been
influenced or has influenced other social
groups with which contact was made.
Trade and immigration, exploration,
religion, colonial conquest have all been
promoters of cultural change and interac¬
tion. This is intensified today, when
technology makes even the most remote,
hermetic ethnic groups accessible, vulner¬
able, and their cultures subject to change.
One factor in this increasing inter- '
communication is the ongoing woman
revolution. In all cultures and social groups,
womankind is undergoing a process of
change; and this changed status is occurring
through both a conscious movement on the
part of women, and the increasing mastery
of technology.
Woman, as well as man, is a cultural and
economic reality. Yet all studies of historical
development, in the main, ignore or obscure
the role of woman within her own cultural
pattern. She is treated as marginal, not
pivotal, to the historical development of her
group.
Yet, in the maintenance or rejection of
cultural values, in the affective and physical
shaping of the children-successors to the
culture, in the transmission and communica¬
tion of skills and knowledge of all kinds, in
the acceptance of new economic and social
developments, the role of woman is fun¬
damental to any society and to the cultural
survival of any group.
Woman as creator of wealth has been
totally ignored. Yet the development of
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
MINORITIES AND MIGRANTS
Class and racial and culturalfeatures distort the very conceptions of literacy, knowledge and
intelligence, and, since these cannot be truly objectively measured, the children of migrant
and minority groups become the victims of institutionalized procedures that preserve the
status quo. The failure of the migrant in the classroom is therefore a continual self-fulfilling
prophecy, generated by widespread and often imperceptible discriminatory practices.
Classroom scene in the USA. Photo © Jeanne Hamilton, New York.
civilization, from spinning and weaving by
hand to the industrial manufactures of to¬
day, require woman's labour. Woman the
consumer is also a factor in the economics
of any country. Throughout the ages, the
role of woman as wealth accumulator has
been slighted. Her role as traditional teacher
of arts and language and skills, in dance and
music and singing and many other fields, is
taken for granted and not properly valued.
As a keeper of tradition, as an educator
and communicator, and in the creation of
new needs, new aspirations, in literature and
poetry and painting, in science and in
politics, woman has played a role in the
enrichment and continuity of cultures.
Yet the vocabulary of so many of these
cultures is a masculine one; expressing man
deciding, ruling, designing existence; leaving
woman a "marginal majority" to silence
and to submission.
The oppression of womankind is, in the
history of humanity, the very first of all op¬
pressions exercised by the male sex towards
the fellow-being. "Before all other exploita¬
tions came the exploitation of the female"
says Engels. This universal exploitation
shows a striking uniformity in its patterns of
feminine oppression and enslavement,
despite the variety of the devices employed.
Not least, indeed of first importance, is the
use of physical strength, since physical
strength was accounted, for so long, a male
"superiority". Even today, among civilized
societies, the use and abuse of physical force
goes on. From mutilation such as foot-
MIGRANTS. In both the towns and countryside of the developed world
migrants form a wretched population of outcasts from society, virtual
outlaws, who are socially and culturally excluded. This sub-proletariat
lives precariously in the worst possible social conditions, in unhealthy, in¬
sanitary dwellings, with no cultural advantages, receiving little or no in¬
struction orprofessional training and, as a result, working in unfulfilling,
ill-paid jobs.
Immigrant workers in the shanty-town at Saint-Denis, on the outskirts of
Paris. Photo Bruno Barbey © Magnum, Paris.
binding to other forms of cloistering; from
sexual slavery to the ill-treatment of
widows, from rape (and the scandalous
lightness with which it is still regarded even
in the west) to wife-beating... physical force
is still one of the methods used to cow
woman into submission as an inferior.
But it is in the domain of the mental and
the metaphysical that this oppression has
been most subtly and tenaciously developed
into "cultural values". The utilization of
pseudo-virtues, man-made; of so-called
"sacred" or "God-given" laws; of man-made
laws, legalizing the violation of woman as a
person... all this still goes on, and still in¬
habits the many cultures of the world today.
Religion has played its role in this
shameful oppression. Christianity has, for
centuries, been the total negation of the
teachings of Jesus Christ, who elevated
woman to her rightful place as an equal per¬
son. Confucianism denied woman her
human identity; she was an object, the pro¬
perty of the male.
Yet Taoism, and Buddhism, as well as
Jesus, were world changers recognizing the
essential equality of woman. Taoism is
founded on the duality of the universe; the
Ying and the Yang, male and female, equal,
inseparable, complementary. To diminish
the one is to deny the other.
For centuries, in the West, learned men
and renowned scholars have found abundant
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
THE STATUS OF WOMEN
Any attempt to change the status of women elicits the expression of
deeply rooted opposition and attempts to create equal educational
and better employment opportunities are no exception. The
arguments justifying inaction are numerous but usually based on a
certain conception of women 's traditional role and a fear that, if
this is changed, there will be a breakdown of moral and cultural
values.
(1) In societies where many if not most women are employed, they
do not enjoy the same opportunities for advancement and are not
prepared through their education and training for higher status
jobs; it is acceptable for a woman to be a teacher but not an ad¬
ministrator, a laboratory assistant but not an engineer, a secretary
but not an executive, a field labourer but not a tractor driver or a
farm manager.
Photo Marc Riboud © Magnum, Paris
(2) In some societies it is feared that promoting literacy among
women will lead to dire consequences. In others, primary and
secondary general education for girls is accepted as natural, but
education for employment or for the exercise of a profession is
regarded as useless and perhaps undesirable.
Photo International Labour Office, J.P. Laffont © Sygma
(3) While conventional statistics show that women's working roles
are, at best, secondary or complementary to thefamily income, the
reality in developing countries is that women increasingly are the de
facto heads ofhouseholds with full responsibilityfor their own and
their children 's survival.
Photo © Olivier Martel, Paris
*T>
32 * 1"
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
justification both for racial discrimina¬
tion the exploitation of the other human
being and for the oppression of
woman the inferior being.
The establishment of cultural patterns
based upon woman's inferiority is
widespread, and it has been continuous for
three millennia.
This intra-cultural injustice is the fun¬
damental flaw, vitiating all dialogue, all
communication, not only between the two
halves of humankind, but also between all
human beings.
Today, an opportunity is given to redress
this injustice, through the ongoing woman
revolution which is taking place.
As we confront a world where inter¬
cultural dialogue must be based on essential
equality, the share that womankind must
have in the decision-making processes of
shaping a jusi future is crucial.
In other words, intra-cultural equality
must be achieved, to make inter-cultural
equality, a dialogue between equal human
beings, valid, responsible, and fruitful.
Otherwise the same pattern of superior/
inferior, dominant/repressed, will continue,
both materially and spiritually, to poison
relations between humans.
In the struggles for national liberation of
our twentieth century, as many women as
men fought side by side; but when in¬
dependence was achieved women, even
those leaders who were an inspiration to men
to do battle for justice and freedom, were
denied the fruits of victory and relegated to
"traditional" roles in the "culture" to which
they belonged.
Yet there are exceptions. One of them is
the Chinese Revolution. From its onset, in
the early twentieth century, women, un¬
binding their feet, played a most important
role in the revolution; and when Liberation
came, they were not returned to feudal op¬
pression. Indeed, China is one of the coun¬
tries in the Third World where the
authorities in power back woman as an equal
person to the fullest possible extent.
"Without the emancipation of woman,
man cannot be liberated" said Mao Tsetung,
thus echoing the French social theorist
Charles Fourier who in 1793 had said that all
social progress is conditioned by the progress
of woman towards her own emancipation.
Gisèle Halimi, the renowned woman
lawyer, writes that: "Woman has a global
vocation for revolutionary change."
The word "global" is significant. Just as
there is a striking uniformity in the methods
devised by man to oppress and to exploit
woman, in so many cultures, so is there a
similarity, a basic and identical foundation
for woman's revolt against this oppression.
All women's movements in the world,
therefore, can help and mutually support
each other. For the struggle is the same. For
economic equality. For ordinary human
rights, against female sexual slavery, against
rape and physical abuse, against the thou¬
sand and one legal and illegal ways in which
women are diminished, stunted and
betrayed. "Our struggle is your struggle".
And this platform of communication, across
all cultures, is one which is becoming in¬
creasingly apparent to all women.
Whether among the toilers of India, or in
Latin America; in the liberation movement
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
of affluent America, or elsewhere, though
different in degree, the aims are the same: to
become full persons, in their own right.
As Roger Garaudy says in his book For
The Advent Of Woman: "All these
movements [for feminine liberation] are
one... with a global character... far more so
than the national liberation struggles have
been...." The woman revolution is by its
very nature international, global, inter¬
cultural and intra-cultural.
Technological progress has helped the ris¬
ing consciousness of woman's liberation. A
major factor has been contraception. Birth
control, pioneered in the early twentieth
century by a woman (Margaret Sanger) is to¬
day known, accepted, by women the whole
world over. It is changing, altering the con¬
cepts of woman towards herself. No longer
a mere breeding machine, it enables her to
assume her own personality and potential. It
has, for the first time, given her the right to
own her own body; to decide when she
wants a child, or not.
This change in mentality is enormously
significant. In other ways new technologies
have made obsolete the "superiority" of
physical strength. Skill and intelligence is
displayed by women working computers and
other machines, or engaging in work of high
intellectual calibre. And all this merely
points to one thing: to the end of the tragic
waste of woman's potential, inventiveness,
and intelligence. The world has indeed im¬
poverished itself for some millennia by
discriminating against the brain power of
half of humanity, but now the opportunity
has come to utilize it.
Woman's intelligence and her right to
participate in decision-making affecting the
world's future do not mean a competition
with man, but a partnership. Her approach
to problems will certainly be different, and
her contribution lies precisely in that
difference. 	
Whereas masculine sociologists and
philosophers tend to start their mental ex¬
ploration from intellectualized assumptions,
women are more likely to proceed from liv¬
ed experience than abstract ideation, from
observation, and concrete aspects of living,
rather than from "rational reasoning" or
"logic".
This used to be derided as "feminine in¬
stinct" or "intuition", a "biological", non-
intellectual expression of the woman's
mind. But perhaps this is what the world
needs, and certainly woman's perception of
inter-cultural problems will be all the more
enriching because her wisdom and per-
cipience will not make her reject what is dif¬
ferent as "incomprehensible". There is far
too much obsession with logic, with reason,
which is merely the reduction of an argu¬
ment to the limits of its own assumptions. In
the presence of dissimilar cultural patterns,
"logic" and "rationality" often err.
Whereas common sense, an "intuitive"
perception and appreciation of differences,
and an acceptance of them, will be enriching
and productive.
In our changing world, where all cultures
are changing so rapidly, intra- and inter¬
cultural progress can only become coherent,
harmonious, when woman enters as a full
human being into the dialogue of our dif¬
ferent cultures, as an equal participant in all
the affairs of our planet Earth.
H Han Suyin
COPA DEL MUNDO DE FÚTBOL *?' ESPANA 82
SPORT
As a means of expression that is independent of language, and in¬
stantly understandable to all, by the evidence it provides of the
fundamental equality of men and peoples, by the opportunities it
affords for encounters between individuals and teams from widely
diverse countries, sport can and should pave the way for men to
live together in a reconciled world.
Fiesta, a poster by the Catalan artist Joan Miró for the World Cup
now taking place in Spain. Poster © Société de Production des
Affiches Maeght, Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
CULTURAL DIVERSITY
AND
THE MASS MEDIA
In praise
of mother tongues
by Chingiz Aïtmatov
Astriking feature of Daghestan is the
great number of languages to be
found there. With typical humour,
mour, the Soviet poet Rasul Gamzatov,
himself a native of this mountainous coun¬
try in the north-east Caucasus, explains
why. When the Creator was distributing
languages, a snowstorm was blowing in
Daghestan; in a hurry to be on his way, he
emptied a whole sackful over its people!
It is certainly true that until comparatively
recently, the inhabitants of Daghestan, who
all shared much the same way of life in
neighbouring valleys, were separated by
linguistic differences so great that they
might have been living on different con¬
tinents. Every aul, or village, had its own
local tongue; none in any way resembled
the others.
But no alphabet in the world offered
characters that could be used to transcribe
all the languages of Daghestan. And when,
at the beginning of the Soviet period, at¬
tempts were made to adapt the Russian
CULTURAL DIVERSITY
Various cultures can be identified within a graded social structure from the tribal level
through rural life to urban groups and the urban élite. Superimposed on this there can even
exist a multiplicity of cultures within a political structure, from area to area within national
boundaries and from country to country within a region.
Story-time in the Philippines. Photo A.P. Garcia, Unesco.
alphabet for this purpose, ¡t proved neces¬
sary to add new characters and combina¬
tions of characters to transform speech into
writing.
Today, the people of Daghestan, num¬
bering some two million, speak altogether
more than thirty different languages;
newspapers and literary periodicals appear
in five of them; seven may be heard on the
stage of the national theatres; and books
are published in nine. The country's poets
write not only in the Avar language which,
although the Avarians themselves number
no more than 400,000, is the most
widespread tongue, but also in the language
of the Tats, of whom there are only 15,000,
and even in a language spoken by only 2,000
people.
Unless one is directly involved, the prob¬
lems of the so-called "minority peoples",
who may be found in many different corners
of the world, may well appear to be of little
consequence. But the preoccupations of
the tiniest community can in fact be as
serious, as important and even as alarming
to its members as the collective concerns of
multi-million populations.
This is especially true when it comes to
cultural survival, and more particularly the
survival of language, since a people without
a tongue of its own is a people whose self-
esteem is undermined. Language is not only
the keystone of a nation's culture; it is also
the means by which that culture can
develop.
The language of any people is a unique
phenomenon, a product of its own brand of
creativity; the loss of a people's language is
the loss of its life-blood. To preserve those
which have survived is a duty, for they form
part of the heritage of all mankind.
The world lives in an environment of
language, and the linguistic ecosphere is as
complex and fragile as the natural one.
Pragmatism may be a useful attitude to
adopt when dealing with machines, but this
is not the case where nature and culture are
concerned.
It is true, nonetheless, that "major"
languages tend to displace or absorb those
which are only spoken by a few. However
ardently it may be expressed, any argument
in favour of integration which implies a loss
of national values or of cultural identity
must be received with caution, because it
distorts the issue. To unite profitably,
peoples and cultures must be in some way^
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
different from each other, in some way
dissimilar. The absence of originality makes
mutual enrichment impossible; indeed it
removes the need to unite.
I am deeply convinced that there exists a
real possibility of conserving existing minori¬
ty languages and creating the conditions for
their active participation in new patterns of
spiritual and material existence, as well as
an atmosphere in which they themselves
can develop either through their own inner
evolution or through the direct and indirect
influence and example of cultures conveyed
by other languages. The experience of my
own country, Kirghizia, confirms this con¬
viction, as does that of the hundred and
more nations, peoples and ethnic groups
which exactly sixty years ago freely
decided to join in a single State, the Union
of Soviet Socialist Republics.
At that already distant time, the countries
which lay on the fringe of the former Rus¬
sian Empire were faced with a choice. Were
they to opt for a single, highly-developed
language, i.e. Russian, or to decide on co¬
existence, i.e. the use of Russian as a major
language, but with the parallel development
of their own national tongues?
The easiest and most obvious solution
would have been for them to adopt Russian
and, setting concern with their national
cultures aside, to begin building the future
on the solid literary and scientific founda¬
tions which that language offered.
Such a simple choice must have been
tempting. But did it not imply the atrophy of
their own cultures? Would it not inhibit the
development of those cultures in accor¬
dance with the spirit of the times? And last
but not least, would not such a choice run
counter to the process of creating infinite
complexity and variety which is a welcome
characteristic of human history? In
mankind's storehouse of culture, who
would be bold enough to say, "this must be
kept at all costs, but this can be cast aside"?
The matter was one which required
thought, and the careful weighing of pros
and cons. And if the choice of a language
obviously depends on there being alter¬
natives to choose from, a question of civic
duty is also involved: the duty of the in¬
dividual towards his people the source not
only of his existence but also of his most
precious possession, his language.
A mother tongue is, in its turn, a source
of ceaseless wonder. The language which
we hear and learn in childhood is the only
one which is capable of carrying into our
hearts and minds the poetry of our people's
existence and experience, of igniting in us
the first flame of national pride and of con¬
veying to us the sheer, aesthetic pleasure of
words honed and polished by our ancestors.
At the same time, it should be pointed
out and my own experience confirms
this that a child is capable of acquiring
equal mastery of two languages, and
possibly even more, provided that they are
presented in an identical manner from the
very beginning. In my own case Russian is
no less a mother tongue than Kirghiz; I grew
up with both, and both will remain with me
for the rest of my days.
In the early days of the USSR, it became
clear that the cultural development of the
family of nations which comprised the
Soviet Union could not take place without
reference to cultures which were already
more advanced. After all, more than a third
of those nations had no printed literature of
their own. And this is why the second of the
options mentioned above was preferred.
The challenge was greater, but so was the
prize.
One of the results is that when we speak
today of "Soviet literature", we are in reality
speaking of more than eighty different na¬
tional literatures. The adoption of the princi¬
ple that wherever more than one language is
used for ethnic reasons or for administrative
purposes, those languages shall be accord¬
ed equal treatment, has fully justified itself.
Let me say a word here about the role of
the Russian language which has made it
possible, for the first time in history, to
establish creative links between peoples
who, not so long ago, were unaware of
each other's existence; between peoples
who were on significantly different rungs on
the ladder of civilization; whose cultural and
social histories, like their customs and tradi¬
tions, had little in common; whose
languages were mutually incomprehensible.
If Russian has become the language of
communication between the many peoples
of the USSR, the language of the new
civilization and of cultural co-operation, this
is firstly because it is the language of the
most numerous nation in the Union, and
secondly, because it has adapted and
enriched itself through contact with all the
other languages. Thus, it has become the
second language of non-Russian peoples in
all the national republics and administrative
regions of the USSR; eighty- two per cent of
the entire population speak it fluently.
It is now possible to say that for the first
time in the history of mankind, a single
State has created a multilingual culture,
drawing on all that is best in the cultures of
its majority and minority nations alike and at
the same time conserving their specific na¬
tional characteristics, manner of thinking
and ways of life.
It is a culture which is simultaneously
universal, internationalist and kaleido-
scopically national. Its internationalism does
not imply, as has been mistakenly claimed,
the replacement of national cultures by a
uniform stereotype, but rather the com¬
prehensive development of all the different
national cultures and languages within the
context of a single social ideal.
We may contrast this process with the
levelling and the erosion of national values
which are still to be found, alas, in other
parts of the world and which give rise to
natural concern for the future of world
culture. There is, I believe, an important
humanist and moral lesson to be drawn
CULTURAL DIVERSITY. It is essential that all linguistic, ethnic and
cultural groups be accorded their rightful place in society. Often a
minority group within a country has a great deal to offer by way of
values to the majority groups within the same nation.
Ultima Cena, by the Italian artist Mario Ceroli. Photo © Galleria Na-
zionale d'Arte Moderna, Rome.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
from the fact that the integration of the
cultures of the socialist peoples leads
neither to a loss of identity nor to the disap¬
pearance of differences, but rather to their
mutual enrichment and further growth. In¬
deed, it permits the disclosure of the poten¬
tial of the peoples concerned, of the untap¬
ped resources which each nation possesses
as a result of the spiritual and historical
experience acquired throughout its long
existence.
Needless to say, the process has not been
a simple one. Our experience has been ac¬
quired at the price of enormous and
sometimes agonizing efforts; the quest for
new patterns of creative thought, and for a
dialectical theory of existence, has involved
a tireless journey along hitherto unmapped
paths; we have had to overcome many
obstacles remaining from the past, and to
endure considerable growing pains.
The development of a huge multinational
State like the USSR has inevitably been ac¬
companied by the successive emergence of
new processes and problems where the
relations between nations are concerned.
Suffice it to say in this connexion that re¬
cent years have seen a significant increase,
in many of the Soviet Republics, in the
number of non-indigenous citizens, who
have specific claims to make where ques¬
tions of language, culture and life-style are
concerned.
At the same time, the frontiers of national
life-styles are . constantly expanding.
Moreover, the conditions of everyday life
are changing so rapidly that it sometimes
happens that what were long considered to
be specifically national concerns disappear
from their original, limited context only to
re-emerge as cultural obstructions to
general progress.
When we speak of the national par¬
ticularities which distinguish us from each
other, we do not always take account of the
many features which draw us together: our
common destiny, our common background
and our common age. The world we live in,
the way we live now and, above all, the way
we think: surely this is what should be set
against our differences?
Where the Soviet peoples are concerned,
the greatest changes have occurred in their
attitudes, psychology and behaviour. To
whatever national entity we belong, there
are now many circumstances in our lives in
which our attitudes, assessments,
judgements and standards are the same;
and this can only be beneficial to our na¬
tional cultures. Provided, of course, that
this new raison d'être can find expression in
our own languages, it is to be welcomed as
a means of extending and enriching our
own cultures and of broadening their
horizons.
And this is indeed what is happening. As
we explore more and more thoroughly the
features of what we call "national
character", as we learn to look at modern
life through modern eyes, the notion of
nationality itself takes on a contemporary
colouring.
But what would happen if we did the op¬
posite, if we withdrew like hermits into our^
SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY
Science and technologyform an integral
part of contemporary culture, even
though the uncontrolled development
of certain techniques (mass media, new
audio-visual techniques, telematics,
nuclear systems) must be seen as involv¬
ing undeniable risks. The dialectical
relation between culture and technique
is a particularly delicate problem since
science and technology carry with them
cultural features that belong to their
societies of origin. This does not in any
way mean that they should be rejected
systematically, as they are absolutely
necessary for economic and social
development. However, their dissem¬
ination and use must be controlled by
the countries using them and developed
in forms that are adapted by the scien¬
tists and technicians of these countries
to the traditions and problems of their
own cultures and to the actual needs of
the people.
A "happening" staged at the nuclear
waste treatment plant at La Hague,
France, to denounce the dangers incur¬
red by technicians working in the
nuclear industry. Photo Michel
Lambert © Gamma, Paris.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
own shells? The effect would surely be to
reduce our culture to a mere shadow of
itself, to a pseudo-culture which, at best,
would give only a one-sided picture of our
national character.
To shut oneself off from intercourse with
other cultures, especially if the latter are at a
more advanced stage of development, is to
deprive oneself of the means of one's own
development. Reduced to an end in itself,
"originality" can only lead to isolation, to
national narrow-mindedness; it can only
obstruct the passage of national values
beyond national boundaries.
It goes without saying that cultural ex¬
change leads to cultural change. Interaction
between national cultures involves mutual
enrichment and emancipation from in¬
fluences which have outlived their time. For
some strange reason, the term "national
culture" is almost always pronounced with,
so to speak, a backward glance over our
shoulder in the direction of the past,
whereas creative thought has at all times
been a reflection of the current spiritual
state of the society in question. The
originality of a nation is not merely to be
found in the sum total of the characteristics
inherited during its history, in what has sur¬
vived and withstood the passage of time; it
is also to be found here and now, in the
product of its contemporary activities and
concerns.
If I have dwelt at such length on this mat¬
ter, it is because the question of national
cultures has become in recent years the
subject of worldwide controversy. The in¬
dividual characteristics of a nation are what
makes its culture a unique phenomenon.
Close contact with one's native land, with
one's people and with the most vital prob¬
lems of their daily life constitutes the very
life-blood of a nation's culture; at the same
time, it helps to extend the horizons of that
culture beyond national boundaries,
because, in so many ways, all peoples'
perceptions of the world are the same. This
is why, where culture is concerned, "na¬
tional" and "international" should never be
set in opposition to one another.
Of course, it is not surprising that in cer¬
tain intellectual circles, in Asia or in Africa,
for example, there exists a sentiment of pre¬
judice against Eurocentrism, against the
European way of thought and the European
civilization which they associate with col¬
onial domination and the belittlement of
their own national values. Nevertheless,
progressive African and Asian intellectuals
have long been engaged in the effort to use
the European experience for the enrichment
of their own national cultures, seeing that
experience as part of the universal heritage
of mankind.
I agree with the observation by the
Bengali critic Sarvar Murshid that every
culture must now decide whether to see
itself as an integral part of world culture as a
whole, or as a "great" culture, if only within
its own four walls. As I have already remark¬
ed, excessive self-importance leads to isola¬
tion and, eventually, to dogmatism. It is
quite understandable, however, why this
question is a particularly painful one for Asia
and Africa to resolve: the real threat
of ethnocide has only recently begun
to diminish.
Today, the many people of those two
enormous continents have to decide on the
SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY. Successful development does not
depend solely on material means and techniques. It is also important
that the individuals and groups who are the agents of development
should be convinced that they will themselves be the beneficiaries of it.
Economic growth, which is admittedly the key to all development,
then ceases to be an end in itself. It becomes a means whereby the
needs of all may be satisfied, including an opportunity for the full
development of the individual. Thus culturalpolicies and development
policies merge in their reciprocal effects.
Left, Renaissance perspective exercise in how to draw a chalice, and,
right, rotation of the DNA spiral, the molecular basis of inheritance,
from a computer-graphic display. Photo © All rights reserved.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
means to be employed in resolving the issue
of not only their political and social, but also
their cultural development. The attainment
of political independence poses with con¬
siderable urgency the question of creating
appropriate new forms of economic and
cultural existence, without which in¬
dependence itself will prove to have been a
sterile gain.
"East is East, and West is West..." said
Kipling. But this was poetic licence; history
and culture alike disprove his claim that
"never the twain shall meet". Recent
decades have seen social upheavals on a
scale matched only in biology and geology,
and within an incredibly shorter time span.
The developing countries are still at a stage
when cultural progress will depend above all
on success in their efforts to achieve social
development and to resolve their social
problems.
Thoughts, things and images, as well as
individual destinies and collective histories,
already formed a motley crowd on the
highways of existence when the peoples of
the world lived hidden away in isolation
from each other. Today, whether the strug¬
gle to preserve it intact is conducted in
political or cultural terms, the world is in¬
divisible. International cultural and scientific
collaboration may be seen as part of
the effort to remove tensions between
peoples an effort in which our own share
is second to none.
A new historical period has dawned, and
the first step along the new road has been
accomplished. The peoples of the world
have shown that they are capable of setting
aside the differences between States,
societies and nations in the attempt to find a
common approach to the problems of all
mankind, and, most important of all, the
issue of peace and war.
We are united in our awareness of collec¬
tive responsibility for the fate of human
culture and of civilization in its^entirety, and
for the moral climate of our planet. Does
this not entitle us to proclaim boldly that
now is the moment to choose the directions
in which mankind is to develop? Our respon¬
sibility in this matter is all the more enor¬
mous, in that we cannot leave the decisions
for tomorrow. For tomorrow itself to arrive
will depend in no small measure on what we
can achieve today.
H Chingiz Aïtmatov
INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION
Thefact that the greaterpart of the world's information and communication resources are in
the hands of the industrialized countries places them in a position such that they in fact exer¬
cise a kind of domination over the countries of the Third World and the implications of
this situation are all the more serious in that they are not realized by those in a position to ex¬
ercise domination. Thefact that the mass communication medianewspapers with a vast, in
some cases a world-wide circulation, press agencies which for most countries are almost the
only sources of international news, and complex telecommunication networks are in the
hands of a few developed countries affects both the direction of the flow of information,
which is produced in the developed countries and disseminated towards the Third World,
and also the content of this information which inevitably reflects the point of view, the men¬
tality, the values and even the interests of the developed countries. It might thus be said that
the direction of the flow of information determines its content.
Drawing © André Bonhomme, Pans
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The global village
revisited
by Russell Neuman
IN the mid-1960s Canadian media analyst
Marshall McLuhan began to ponder
the notion of the global village the
people of the world's nations united by in¬
stantaneous inter-communication by tele¬
vision. As TV became available in every
chateau, hut, and tent, he speculated, the
world's nations would inevitably become
more aware of and sympathetic to each
other's cultures and beliefs. How could
bellicose heads of State sustain war fever
and xenophobia among their citizens in the
face of empathie ¡mages of adults and
children the human condition transmitted
by television drama flowing across na¬
tional boundaries? Perhaps also there is
something revealing and spontaneous
about this visual electronic medium which,
in contrast to print, does not lend itself as
well to the self-conscious prose or abstract
propaganda of the ideological journalist or
pamphleteer. It is a vision of new tech¬
nology and cultural harmony.
Today this imagery, although still an at¬
tractive and coherent scenario, strikes a
false chord. Those who struggle with the
harsh realities of economic development,
weary negotiators who face renewed
debates over the New World Information
Order are likely to represent a rather scep
tical audience for a latter-day McLuhan who
would point to new communications tech¬
nology as a panacea for world tensions.
Some have reacted to the technological
determinism of the global village notion by
concluding simply that McLuhan had it the
wrong way around. It is not television's
technology which determines its ideological
and cultural content, but the culture and
ideology which determines the character
and impact of the technology. One might
contrast, for example, the Soviet Union's
lengthy television documentaries cele¬
brating Lenin's life and philosophy and new
industrial development in the Urals with the
theatrical capitalism of such American game
shows as "Let's Make a Deal" and "The
Price Is Right".
Such a view leads quite naturally into the
logic of the New World Information Order.
The news and entertainment produced and
distributed by the dominant Western media,
so the logic goes, will inevitably reflect the
commercial interests and national biases of
their sources with continued insensitivity to
the unique needs and perspectives of Third
World audiences.
Given the disquieting legacy of the col¬
onial era, many in the Third World
understandably cast a sceptical eye on the
prospect of a new electronic colonialism.
But a simplistic model which equates all
new media with neo-colonialism will be no
more helpful in the design of workable inter¬
national communications policy than the
naive optimism of McLuhan's global village.
The North-South and East-West polariza¬
tion of opinion concerning such issues as
the New World Information Order may be a
familiar pattern in international circles but it
sparks special interest among communica¬
tions researchers. My thesis is this: The pro¬
ponents of an unrestricted free flow of
media entertainment and information across
national boundaries tend to reflect
McLuhan's style of technological deter¬
minism content, he was
prone to argue, is inherently neutral. The
spread of new technologies is inevitable.
Each new technology from radio through
television to direct broadcast satellites will
spontaneously determine its own cultural
character. In contrast, those who em¬
phasize cultural sovereignty issues tend to
focus exclusively on entertainment and
news as propaganda and reflect an extreme
scepticism about new communication
technologies an equally simplistic political
determinism.
INFORMATION AND COMMUNICATION. Every country has
its share of communication outcasts or "have-nots" who only
seldom have any say in determining the content of information and
have virtually no opportunity of making their views or problems
known through the media. And so the gap widens between those
who are over-informed and those who are underinformed, while at
the same time the imbalance. between those who issue and those
who receive information grows more pronounced. Admittedly, at
the international level, the imbalance in theproduction andflow of
information and programmes affects primarily North-South rela¬
tions, but it is also to be found within each of the world 's major
regions and even within each country. The need to deliver the
developing countries from the state of dependence they are still in
as regards communication is now widely recognized: 80per cent of
the news distributed throughout the world comes from the in¬
dustrialized countries, and only 10 to 30 per cent concerns the
developing countries. To this imbalance must be added the unequal
distribution of books or radio and television programmes. The
perpetuation ofsuch disparities entails serious economic, political,
40
social and cultural consequences for the most deprived countries
and at the same time constitutes a major obstacle in the way of the
peoples getting to know each other and to the progress of interna¬
tional understanding. Countries with high capacitiesforproducing
and circulating information often tend to neglect other cultures or
are familiar only with their picturesque or anecdotal aspects; and
messages from the industrialized countries often feed back to the
developing countries a simplified, sometimes distorted or indeed
inaccurate image of themselves. Stereotyped and ethnocentric pat¬
terns are thus perpetuated and sometimes even reinforced, while a
sense of insecurity may give rise to restrictive or defensive measures
to guard against what is felt to be a threat to the more vulnerable
communities. The very same fears are becoming apparent in a
number of industrialized countries, aware that they too are using
predominantlyforeign programmes. A reduction of the disparities,
by developing the media of each country and especially of the
developing countries, would undoubtedly make for a freer and
more substantial flow of messages and contribute to the progress
of these countries and to wider international understanding.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
Phoïo Andfoa Bruno, Turin
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
COMMUNICATION
AND CULTURE
It would not be enough to provide
equipment and materials and to
mobilize human and financial
resourcesunquestionably important
as that isfor all communication prob¬
lems to be solved, both within each
country and in relations between coun¬
tries. For the questions that arise also
concern the nature of social relations
and the quality of communication; they
consequently have social and cultural
implications at all levels, national,
regional and international.
The truth of the matter, as usual, lies
somewhere in between. The role of com¬
munications researchers, in studying how
audiences use and learn from the media, will
be to demonstrate that the appropriate
model is one of a continuing interaction of
technological and political forces rather
than a one-way determinism in either direc¬
tion. Such a perspective opens new com¬
mon ground.
The New World Information Order debate
as it stands now is troublesome. Each side
identifies a primary goal apparently incom¬
patible with the other. Western nations pro¬
claim the need to avoid censorship and to
protect the free flow and exchange of ideas
across national borders. Developing nations
and those which tend to import more
cultural products than they export proclaim
the need to protect cultural and political
sovereignty from the intrusion of Western
commercial news and entertainment media.
It might be argued, perhaps somewhat
cynically, that each side shares the same
premise and the same goal. The shared
premise is that in open market competition
between Western and regional or locally
produced materials the Western content will
tend to dominate. The goal each side shares
is to dominate the local media. The Western
media would do so, it is said, by means of
open-market competition and the local and
regional media by insulating the local media
through the use of cultural trade barriers,
tariffs, quotas, or perhaps censorships or
some sort.
Fostering cultural diversity is the common
goal. It finds resonance with the first article
of Unesco's Constitution the goal of col¬
laboration "in the work of advancing the
mutual knowledge and understanding of
peoples through all means of mass com¬
munication, and to that end, [Unesco shall]
recommend such international agreements
as may be necessary to promote the free
flow of ideas by word and image". Cultural
diversity is, however, not necessarily the
natural condition. It may indeed require nur¬
turing. It is here that some recent
technological developments offer special
promise.
The overwhelming and dominant
technological trend, of course, is the move¬
ment toward electronic communication.
Paper and film as storage devices and con-
Photomontage Tsunchisa Kimura © Pacific Press Service, Tokyo, ANA, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Photo International Labour Office, J. P. Laffont © Sygma
COMMUNICATION
AND CULTURE
A crucial problem, how well known, is
that of the major role played by
transnational corporations in regard to
mass media and, more generally,
cultural industries, especially in thefield
of information, as well as that of the ex¬
port of technologies whose supposed
neutrality is disproved in every study
that has been made. In the face of these
problems there is a very evident need to
work out national and international
strategies.
duits for information are giving way to
magnetic tape and laser disc storage and
transmission via wire and the expanded
usable electromagnetic spectrum. The fami¬
ly elder as storyteller is replaced by the an¬
nouncer. The messenger boy and paper boy
seek other careers as information is elec¬
tronically delivered directly into the home in¬
formation terminal.
The printed page in the form of books,
magazines, and newspapers remains
economically viable but is diminished
somewhat by the prominence of broadcast
news and entertainment. The role of com¬
puters and high-speed data lines in
transporting text and data begins to blur the
distinction between print and video. In¬
creasingly a news story might pass from a
reporter's word processing terminal through
an editor's terminal to the news reader's
home screen without ever having taken
form as ink on paper.
Electronic communication is the central
historical trend, but a full sense of its im¬
plications requires special attention to three
characteristics of the technology which
have unique relevance for cultural diversity.
The first factor is lowered costs. Dramatical¬
ly increased economies of scale and efficien¬
cy in manufacture result from the develop¬
ment of transistors and microelectronic
chips. Printed circuit boards of inexpensive
silicon which can be stamped out almost
like pamphlets from a high-speed printing
press replace laboriously hand-assembled
component parts.
Optical cable offers to cut costs of
transmission by wire on an equally dramatic
scale. In 1920 a transatlantic phone call cost
eighteen dollars (US) for three minutes; by
1980 the cost had fallen to under two
dollars. The cost of overseas video trans¬
mission via satellite has dropped equiv-
alently. As the speed and storage capacity
of microcomputers grow and the price of
manufacture falls, some observers predict
that within the next decade it may prove to
be cheaper not only to send a letter but an
entire book via high speed data lines bet¬
ween two microcomputers.
Ultimately the cost of electronic transfer
and display is likely to fall below the cost of
postage alone, not even considering the
rising costs of printing and binding. Minia¬
turization and improved engineering have
reduced the cost of video cameras and
recorders. Professional quality colour video
recording and editing equipment is increas¬
ingly within the financial reach of local
schools and community groups while a
decade or so ago equivalent^ equipped
television studios were economically viable
only in major metropolitan areas.
The second factor of emerging electronic
technology is increased bandwidth. Band¬
width is a term adopted from electrical
engineering which has come to refer more
generally to numbers of channels and the
amount of information each can carry.
There are several related technical
developments here. The increased speed of
data communications mean that a great deal
more can be communicated in equivalent
time (and presumably stored for future
reference) leaving a channel free for others
to use. Refinements in "multiplexing"
technology mean that with the appropriate
equipment, two users of a cable or assigned
frequency can use that channel simul¬
taneously without loss of fidelity or ac¬
curacy. Finally, improved engineering
allows the use of higher and higher spec¬
trum frequencies especially for satellite
communication. In effect, the portion of the
electromagnetic spectrum available for
communication is increasing.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Improvements of coaxial and optical cable
and associated electronics make possible a
dramatic expansion of the number of
distinct video and audio signals that can be
brought into the home. For example, in the
1950s and 1960s most coaxial cable systems
carried a maximum of eight to twelve tele¬
vision signals. Now, with approximately fif¬
ty channels on a single cable, we are ap¬
proaching the practical limits of that
transmission technology.
The third element of electronic com¬
munications is the growth of interactivity.
Perhaps the most notable examples in this
case are the increasing significance of
microelectronics in videodisc, teletext and
videotex monitors which allow individual
audience members to edit, scan, replay and
generally control the speed and character of
video and text presentation. Interactive
videodiscs allow viewers to explore still pic¬
tures, graphics and motion video with the
same control they would exercise in con¬
sulting a dictionary or encyclopedia.
The attentive reader has no doubt already
anticipated the conclusion. Falling produc¬
tion and transmission, and display costs, in¬
creased available bandwidth and the
strengthened ability of the audience
member to review and select preferred con¬
tent leads to the concept of narrowcasting.
Narrowcasting, as contrasted with broad¬
casting, focusses attention on communica¬
tion to smaller, special-interest audiences.
The economies of scale, especially in com¬
mercially supported mass communications,
have traditionally been characterized by the
search for the largest possible au¬
diences pursuit of the common in¬
terest and mass appeal. But as new con¬
duits of information and entertainment
grow, demand is likely to expand as well,
and the changing economics is likely to per¬
mit specialized productions of text and
video which more fully reflect the cultural
diversity of their audiences.
Some sceptical observers of new com¬
munications technologies may simply see it
as the renewed dominance of American
popular culture . being reproduced on
Japanese electronics. Such a perspective is
likely to lead to renewed efforts to build bar¬
riers to transnational communications. But
such a posture neglects a special charac¬
teristic of technological development which
could work to the benefit of the Third World
and an increasingly two-way flow of cultural
communications. It might be identified as a
sequential theory of communications
development.
The underlying idea is simply that as
newer (and initially rather expensive)
technologies such as videodisc, teletext,
direct broadcast satellite and cable TV ex¬
pand first in the industrialized nations, de¬
mand for culturally diverse and specialized
programming is likely to outstrip the supply.
This may represent an opportunity for the
more entrepreneurial of nations further
down the development curve to concen¬
trate their efforts on producing and
marketing specialized materials.
It could prove to be the reverse of the
more traditional pattern in which as televi¬
sion and other media are introduced into
developing countries the sudden demand
for content leads to the mass importation of
American and European programming.
There are numerous cultural subcom-
44
munities in the US from Africa, Asia,
Europe, Latin America, and Scandinavia
which would welcome the opportunity to
renew closer ties with specialized news and
traditional culture from their homelands.
It may be true, generally, that in the world
of the twentieth century there is enough
mobility of peoples across cultural and na¬
tional boundaries to justify a quantum leap
in the transmission of specialized content to
the newly settled. As these cultural
materials spill over and are conveniently
available to their new and curious
neighbours, one might expect a lessening of
cultural differences and misunderstanding.
Perhaps this is the global village notion
reborn via cable television.
M Russell Neuman
What's new
in media technology
BANDWIDTH. A term adopted from
electrical engineering which identifies
the amount of information a channel
can carry, or more generally speaking,
the total number of communications
channels available.
CABLE TELEVISION. The transmis¬
sion of television signals via coaxial
cable. Originally known as CATV
(Community Antenna TV), cable was
first used to conduct TV signals from a
large antenna usually on a nearby
mountain to rural communities who
would otherwise not be able to receive
broadcast signals in their homes.
Gradually, with the expansion of
specialized programming transmitted to
cable operators via satellite, cable has
expanded into suburbs and cities where
it is increasingly a competitor with
broadcast television. Current cable
technology can bring 50 to 100 channels
into the home.
DIRECT BROADCAST SATELLITE
(DBS). The transmission of high power
radio or television signals direct to home
receiving sets from geostationary
satellites. These satellites are located
22,300 miles above the equator and
have fixed "footprints" (broadcast
reception areas) which usually spill well
beyond the borders of a single country.
As a result of the use of space com¬
munication and the international
character of the reception areas, DBS
technology has especially profound in¬
ternational ramifications. The large
broadcast coverage area makes DBS of
special interest to countries with large,
dispersed populations, or especially rug¬
ged terrain which makes terrestrial
broadcast impractical.
NARROWCASTING. A concept con¬
trasted to broadcasting which grows out
of the new media. With many more
channels into the home, this notion sug¬
gests, mass media will increasingly offer
special-interest programming to
smaller, more culturally distinct au¬
diences.
MULTIPLEXING. The term refers to
engineering techniques for com¬
municating multiple messages on a
single channel.
OPTICAL CABLE. A technology still
in development. Cables of thin, flexible
glass or plastic fibres will probably
emerge as a less expensive substitute for
coaxial cable for carrying broadband
communications such as television. The
technology transmits light down optical
fibres rather than electrons down cop¬
per wires to communicate data, audio,
or video information.
TELETEXT. A system for broad¬
casting text information such as news
headlines or weather forecasts to
specially equipped television sets by
means of a small unused portion of the
broadcast signal. Special decoders at¬
tached to the sets at the option of the
viewer store and reproduce frames of
digitally encoded text information and
simple graphics.
VIDEODISC AND VIDEOCASSET¬
TES. Discs and tapes are capable of
reproducing two to six hours of televi¬
sion programming on a special playback
unit in a manner similar to an audio
recording. The discs and disc player are
generally somewhat less expensive to
manufacture than the equivalent
vidéocassette equipment. The disc tech¬
nology lends itself especially to interac¬
tive use giving the viewer unusual con¬
trol on selecting a particular video
frame or the pace and manner of
playback. The primary advantage of
vidéocassette is that, as with audio tape,
the user can continually record new
materials on the cassette.
VIDEOTEX. A two-way text com¬
munications system using coaxial cable
or telephone lines to connect terminals
in homes and businesses with a central
computer and information bank. The
first experiment was the English Prestel
system which found limited success
among business users and few residen¬
tial customers. Nonetheless, new ver¬
sions of the technology are now being
very actively explored in nations around
the world as a way of allowing in¬
dividuals to gather up-to-date informa¬
tion, conduct financial transactions and
order products from home terminals.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
\¡\ TT 0 RI
il
Olympic Order Gold Medal
for Unesco's
Director-General
The gold medal of the Olympic Order was
presented to Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow,
Director-General of Unesco, at a ceremony
in Paris on 6 May. Making the award, the
president of the International Olympic
Committee (IOC), Mr. Juan Antonio
Samaranch, spoke of Mr. M'Bow's untiring
efforts to promote sport and culture and to
spread Olympic ideals throughout the
world. Thanking Mr. Samaranch for the
honour conferred upon him Mr. M'Bow
declared that Unesco would give its support
to a proposal made by the president of the
IOC for the creation of sports museums
around the world.
Venezuelan science-writer
awarded Kalinga Prize
Aristides Bastidas, a Venezuelan science
journalist who had his first article published
when he was only eleven years old and then
went on to become an editor and to write a
regular science column in his newspaper El
Nacional, has been awarded the Kalinga
Prize for the Popularization of Science. In
his acceptance speech Mr. Bastidas
declared that scientific journalism could
contribute to overcoming technological
dependence, which in its turn brought
cultural and political dependence. Created
in 1951, the £1,000 Kalinga Prize is awarded
annually by a jury appointed by Unesco for
work contributing to the popularization of
science. It bears the name of the ancient In¬
dian empire which flourished under the
reign of Ashoka, the enlightened emperor
who renounced war to devote himself to
study and religion.
1st Delphi International
Film Festival
A film festival with no pre-selection or cen¬
sorship and at which all films entered were
shown regardless of length, language and
content, was held in June at Delphi, Fokida,
Greece. The primary objective of the Delphi
festival, which is to be an annual event, is to
act as a centre of attraction for the gather-
Samad Nourinejad
We regret to announce the death of
our colleague Samad Nourinejad,
Editor of the Persian edition of the
Unesco Courier. After a distinguish¬
ed career as a schoolteacher, he was
appointed head of the Department
of International Relations of the Ira¬
nian Ministry of Science and Higher
Education. He was subsequently
named Assistant Secretary-General
of the Iranian National Commission
for Unesco.
ing of information and the exchange of
ideas about film-making and to provide a
forum for free artistic expression.
Two new Member States
Unesco Member States now number 157
with the accession to membership, on 13
April, of the Kingdom of Bhutan and, on 10
May, of Belize.
Centenary of
Nicolae Titulescu
This year marks the centenary of the birth of
Nicolae Titulescu (1882-1941), Romanian
statesman, author and jurist. A professor of
civil law, he attended the peace negotia¬
tions in Paris after the First World War and
as Minister of Foreign Affairs he champion¬
ed Romania's accession to the Little Entente
(1933) and the Balkan Entente (1934). Twice
President of the League of Nations, he was
a leading advocate of European collective
security based on disarmament. As a jurist
Titulescu made a remarkable contribution to
the elaboration and defence of the prin¬
ciples of international law, particularly as
applied to the non-violent settlement of
disputes and respect for independence and
national sovereignty. Behind all his actions
could be discerned an ardent desire to in¬
troduce a new, pacific attitude in interna¬
tional affairs, to determine the causes of
war and to indicate ways by which it could
be avoided. Forty years after his death his
aims and ¡deals remain fresh and untarnish¬
ed and astonishingly relevant to the world of
today.
International Books in Print
The complete current book output of
Unesco and other international organiza¬
tions, as well as thousands of titles from
Third-World publishers, government agen¬
cies and research institutes are listed in In¬
ternational Books in Print 1981-1982, a com¬
prehensive catalogue of English-language
works published outside the United States
and the United Kingdom. The 2-volume
repertory, published by K.G. Saur Verlag
KG, of Munich, lists some 90,000 titles from
publishers in 94 countries.
Window on China
The atmosphere of daily life in China today
can be tasted in Paris this summer at an ex¬
hibition being held at the Centre Georges
Pompidou (until 21 September). Organized
by the Centre de Création Industrielle with
the aim of "letting the Chinese present their
country themselves", the exhibition
presents such aspects of the everyday en¬
vironment as housing, consumer goods,
and communications. Chinese culture-will
be the theme of a forthcoming issue of the
Unesco Courier.
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Cultural Development: Some
Regional Experiences. A collection of
five studies on cultural development in
Africa, Latin America and the Caribbean,
Asia, the Arab States and Europe. 1981.
477 pp. (60 F) See page 16.
Living in Two Cultures. The Socio-
Cultural Situation of Migrant Workers
and their Families. Co-published with the
Gower Publishing Co. Ltd., Aldershot,
UK, who have exclusive sales rights in
the UK (140 F).'
Cultural Policy in the Sudan, by
Mohamed Abdel Hai. 1982. 43
pp. (15 F);
Cultural Policy in the Mongolian
People's Republic. 1982. 49 pp. (15 F)
(Unesco's "Studies and Documents on
Cultural Policies" series).
Communication in the Communi¬
ty. An international study on the role of
the mass media in seven communities.
1982.85 pp. (14 F)
More than Enough? An optimistic
assessment of world energy, edited by
Robin Clarke. (The first study in a new
Unesco series, "Sextant"). 1982. 183
pp. (48 F).
The Social Context of Educational
Planning, by C.A. Anderson. Unesco:
International Institute for Educational
Planning. 2nd reprint, 1982. 35
pp. (15 F).
The Right to Education: What Kind
of Management? by Daniel Haag. A
study prepared for the International
Bureau of Education. 1982. 175
pp. (30 F).
Different Theories and Practices of
Development. Report of an expert
meeting on the role of new theoretical
concepts in the development process,
organized by Unesco with the collabora¬
tion of the United Nations University and
the National Commission for Unesco of
the Mongolian People's Republic. 1982.
258 pp. (80 F).
Technologies for Rural Develop¬
ment. A study of the potentials of self-
help housing, home health care, cottage
industries and other ways whereby rural
people can make their environment an
acceptable alternative to life in an urban
slum. 1981. 174 pp. (35 F).
45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
THIS MONTH'S
CONTRIBUTORS
OTTO KLINEBERG, the distinguished Canadian
psychologist and anthropologist, has taught at
universities in many parts of the world including
Columbia, New York (professor emeritus of
Social Psychology), Sao Paulo (Brazil) and the
Ecole des Hautes Etudes en Sciences Sociales, in
Paris. His association with Unesco goes back to
the early days of the Organization and includes a
period as Head of the Division of Applied Social
Sciences (1953-1955). Since 1970 he has been
Honorary President of the World Federation for
Mental Health. Among his long list of published
works are Race and Psychology (Unesco, 1951),
The Human Dimension in International Relations
(1964) and At a Foreign University (co-author
with Frank Hull) 1979.
RUSSELL NEUMAN, of the United States, is a
sociologist who teaches at the Massachusetts
Institute of Technology. His research focuses on
the social and political impact of new communi¬
cations technologies.
TAHAR BEN JELLOUN, Moroccan writer and
journalist, who has divided his time between
France and Morocco since 1971. Among his
published works are La Plus Haute des Solitudes
(essay) 1977, Les Amandiers sont Morts de Leurs
Blessures (poems) 1976, and a novel, La Prière
des Absents (19811.
CHINGIZ TOREKULOVICH AITMATOV, of
the USSR, writes both in the Kirghiz language
and in Russian. His work, which has been widely
translated and published (over 20 million copies
printed in the past 12 years) has brought him the
highest prizes in the USSR, the Lenin Prize and
(twice) the USSR State Prize, as well as the Tok-
togul State Prize of the Kirghiz SSR. He is an
active member of the Academy of Sciences of
the Kirghiz SSR and president of the cinemato¬
graphic union of the Kirghiz SSR.
NGUGI WA THIONG'O is a well-known Kenyan
novelist, essayist and playwright who has written
widely on questions of African culture and tradi¬
tions. Notable among his published works are
Homecoming (essays) 1972, Petals of Blood
(novel) 1977, and a play I'll Marry When I Choose
(1981) of which he is the co-author with Ngugi
Wa Miire.
HAN SUYIN, Chinese-born British writer, is the
author of many books including A Many-
Splendoured Thing (1952), My House has Two
Doors (1980) and Morning Deluge Mao Tse-
tung and the Chinese Revolution (1972).
AUGUSTO ROA BASTOS, of Paraguay, won
an international reputation with his book Hijo de
Hombre, published in English as Son of Man by
Victor Gollancz, London, 1965. His latest novel
Yo el Supremo is required reading for students of
Latin American literature in a number of Euro¬
pean universities. He is currently teaching Latin
American literature at the university of Toulouse
(France). This article consists of extracts from a
paper presented at the Second Congress of Wri¬
ters in Spanish, which was held at Caracas
(Venezuela) in October 1981.
Photo credits
for colour pages
Page 23
1,4. Photos Vorontzoff /Unesco
2. Photo © Hitachi, Tokyo
3. Photo Michel Claude/Unesco
5. Photo Naud © AAA, Paris
6. Photo WHO, Geneva
7. Photo 1980, R. P. Clark et R. Goff
© S. P. L. /Cosmos, Paris
8. Photo Picou © AAA, Paris
Pages 24-25
1. Photo © 1982, Annie Leibovitz, Contact
2. Photo © Luc Joubert, Paris
3. 4, 7. Photos Dominique Roger/Unesco
5. Photo © Lauros-Giraudon, Paris
6. Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
8. Photo © ADAGP, 1982
9. Photo © Musée des Arts Décoratifs, Paris
10. Photo Robert/Unesco
11. Photo Unicef, Geneva
12. Photo Unesco
13. Photo © Giraudon, Paris
14. Photo L. Burrows © Life Magazine,
New York
15. Photo J. Budny/Unesco . "
Page 26 ^
1. Photo Pierre Pittet/Unesco
2. Photo Christophe Chevrier/Unesco
3. Photo Naud © AAA, Paris
4. Photo © Franco Pinna, Rapho, Paris
5. Photo Unicef, Geneva
u
6. Photo Abbas © Magnum, Paris flj
111
7. Photo © Museum of Art,
Tbilisi, Georgian SSR
8. Photo Fred Mayer © Magnum, Paris
u- C
UJUI
5 i»
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11
issues a year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted
from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and
three voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed ar¬
ticles reprinted must bear author's name. Non-copyright
photos will be supplied on request. Unsolicited
manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by
an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo cap¬
tions and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva
(Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Bahador Shah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Lim Moun-Young (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es- Salaam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
15
8«?
¡§
z
o
u<
u
CO LU
£§
1<
¡s
^£
8?
p
5U
oo
m
Dû o.
46
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Natur and Resources
A quarterly review from Unesco
Featuring articles on global environmental
problems by leading specialists, as well as
international news, and information
about Unesco activities related to:
the environment
natural resources research
conservation
Published in English
French and Spanish
Price, single issue:
10 French francs
Subscription rates:
32 FF (one year),
56 FF (two years)
Above prices are only valid in France. In all other
countries please consult your national distributor (see below).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066, Publications. Educational Supplies Pty Ltd
P 0. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals Dominie Pty
Subscriptions Dept., P 0. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW Sub-
agent. United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Divi¬
sion, Campbell House, 100 Flinders St , Melbourne (Victoria!,
3000. - AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerald and Co , Graben 31,
A-101 1 , Vienna BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books Internatio¬
nal Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca
3 - BELGIUM "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N.V
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent- Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No 9,550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd , 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que H3H
1M7 CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88. Beijing - CYPRUS. "MAM", Arch¬
bishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P O Box 1722, Nicosia CZE¬
CHOSLOVAKIA. - S N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Perma¬
nent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and
Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen
K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaa-
rankuja 2, 01640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco,
7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP 12598-48 - GER¬
MAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140,
710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier
(German, English, French and Spanish editions)- Mr. H. Baum,
Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300
Bonn 3 For other Unesco publications; Karger Verlag,
Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps only Geo Center,
Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Presbyterian Books¬
hop Depot Ltd., P O Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers
Ltd .P.O. Box 7869, Accra, The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast, The University
Bookshop of Legon, P 0. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen Swindon Book Co , 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon
Hong Kong Government Information Services, Publication Cen¬
tre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street - HUNGARY. Akadémiai
Konyvesbolt, Váci u 22, Budapest V, A K V. Konyvturosok
Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H F , Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, B-3/7 Asaf All Road, New Delhi 1 ;
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001, 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016, Scindia House,
New Delhi, Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture,
Ex. AFO Hutments, Dr Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi
110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers,
29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata l|l, Jakarta, Gramedia Bookshop, Jl
Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie
47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribu¬
tion Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P 0 Box
314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat Comm for Unesco, Ave. Iran-
chahr Chomali No 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ McKen¬
zies Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad - IRELAND The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12 ISRAEL. A.B C. Bookstore Ltd ,
P.O Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc , Shuhwa
Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-ku,
Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P O Box
30571, Nairobi KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P 0 Box Central 64, Seoul KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa
LIBERIA Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd , P O Box 286,
Monrovia LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tnpoll. - LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop,
Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic
Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30
bd des Moulins, Monte-Carlo - NETHERLANDS. For
periodicals only Dekker and Nordemann NV, P 0 Box 197,
1000 AD Amsterddam; for publications only: KEESING BOEKEN
B V., Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. - NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Of¬
fice, Government Bookshops at- Rutland Street, P 0 Box 5344,
Auckland, 130, Oxford Terrace, P O Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton, Princes Street, P.O. Box
1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife, The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P 0. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana. NORWAY. All publications-
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, P.O.B.
307 Blindem, Oslo 3 For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens
Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6 - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3.
- PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac
Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przed-
miescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias Et An¬
drade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O Box 48, Mahé; New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P 0. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty I Ltd., Libn Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gar¬
diner Mawata P.O B 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum - SWEDEN. All publica¬
tions A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan
12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier.
Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65,
Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa
Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O B. 9030 Dares-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P 0 Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok, Suksit Slam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair,
Trinidad, W I - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Cad-
desi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGAN¬
DA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNITED
KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London,
S E I., and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bnstol; for scientific maps
only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road, London WC1X
9 DS. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kmga,
Moscow, G-200 - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova
C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubhana - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales
(PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
-.-; .' .;; ., £
Good morning Mr. Vermeer
Art today seems more and more to be becoming the favoured meeting ground for imagery, values and sensibilities
stemming from many distinct cultural regions. In this work, entitled (in Dutch) Goeden Dag Mynheer Vermeer II
(Good morning Mr. Vermeer II), the Peruvian artist Herman Braun could be said to have gone one stage further in
bringing together, across the years, in compelling and surprising proximity, the famous 17th-century Dutch
painter's The Lacemaker and an itinerant Peruvian shoemaker of today.
Photo © B. Pestaña
]]>
</page>
</document>
