<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074735eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Caes«,Courier
UARY 1381 - 4.50 French francs
Cultural traditions
and mass tourism
ALSO IN THIS ISSUE
Water Decade
1981-1990
Learn a language
while you sleep
Brazil's Museum
of the Unconscious
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Photo (cj G. Ingolfsson 1MYND, Reykjavik National Museum of Iceland
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
@
.Iceland
Carved crucifixion
This head, a detail from a Crucifixion, ¡s a very early example of Icelandic Christian wood-
carving. It is thought to date from around 1150, a century and a half after the "land of ice and
fire" was converted to Christianity. Although there are few trees in Iceland today, the Icelan¬
ders have inherited a long and rich tradition of woodcarving. If the most skilled craftsmen
worked in the churches, many more made a living by producing beautifully sculpted house¬
hold objects in native birch, imported fir and oak, or driftwood. Icelanders at every level of
society spent the long winter evenings decorating furniture and utensils, and for centuries
woodcarving was probably the country's most popular craft.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
FEBRUARY 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Drdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.: (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekín)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Portuguese Edition:
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Braille
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 MASS TOURISM AND CULTURAL TRADITIONS
by Abdelwahab Bouhdiba
9 TOURISM-PASSPORT TO DEVELOPMENT?
by Emanuel de Kadt
11 THE WATER DECADE
'A world-wide effort to provide clean water
and adequate sanitation for all by 1990'
13 WHAT THE DECADE WILL COST
14 WATER AND WORLD HEALTH
16 MALAWI : A COMMUNITY APPROACH
UNESCO AND THE INTERNATIONAL DECADE
18 EMPEROR QIN'S BRONZE CHARIOTS
Photo report
20 BRAZIL'S MUSEUM OF THE UNCONSCIOUS
A bold experiment in psychotherapy and art
by Fernanda de Camargo e Almeida
24 HIGH-SPEED LANGUAGE LEARNING
How to study while you 'sleep'
by Mira Vaisburd
28 THE RESURGENCE OF SAIL
by Arthur Gillette
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
ICELAND: Carved crucifixion
Cover
When the international tourist boom began
in the 1960s, few people foresaw its far-
reaching social and cultural consequences,
especially for the, peoples in host countries.
In article overleaf, Abdelwahab Bouhdiba
highlights some of the often cruel paradoxes
Of this phenomenon of the modern world.
Photo shows a Tunisian girl from Djerba.
Photo Yolka © Atlas Photo. Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Right, air view of the old town of Kairouan (Tunisia). Its pattern of baked-clay roofs
criss-crossed by long, narrow alleyways could symbolize the ancient cities and
districts in many countries which have become major tourist attractions. Dazzled
by the beauties of the landscape and the splendours of historic sites and
monuments, tourists on a short visit may sometimes fail to make real contact with
the life of the people in the host country. How to provide short-stay holidaymakers
with the chance to return home with a real appreciation and understanding of
different ways of life? this is one of the challenges facing modern tourism.
Mass tourism
and
cultural traditions
by Abdelwahab Bouhdiba
r
ALTHOUGH mass tourism might seem
to be an instrument for promoting
peace and understanding among
nations and friendship among peoples, its
growth has been viewed in some circles with
great concern.
Many people feel that exposure to hordes
of visitors is bound to alter popular attitudes
and beliefs, that tourism changes men¬
talities and spreads new concepts relating to
work, money and human relationships, and
destroys the ties that bind the people to their
religion and ethics. In short, tourism is seen
as a factor of acculturation in the worst
sense of the word, and even of moral decay.
This accusation warrants calm and objec¬
tive analysis. We hope that this brief study
of the situation as it exists in Tunisia will
help to put the general question in a better
perspective.
For Tunisia, tourism is something that has
developed recently, suddenly and by no
means accidentally. Until independence the
Tunisian hotel industry was insignificant.
Nowdays over a million and a half tourists
visit the country each year. They spend over
fifteen million nights here and statistics
show a strong upward trend. The annual in¬
crease may be as high as 20 to 25 per cent.
The year-round figures are one tourist to
every three inhabitants, and three "visitor-
bednights" to each inhabitant.
Naturally, certain regions tend to be more
heavily "invaded" than others. On the island
of Djerba every single person depends on
tourism, either directly or indirectly, for his
or her livelihood. In Hammamet more than
half the local families are engaged in it.
Naturally, as there is no "tradition" of
tourism, as" such, in these regions, the
phenomenon tends to look like a more or
less well planned invasion. Hotels are
mushrooming. The entire coast of the Gulf
of Hammamet has been taken by storm
while the "hinterland", barely 100 or 200
metres from the coast, remains deserted.
Land speculation has spawned a new breed
of landowners. The local people have not
always benefitted from this manna from
heaven.
Tourism was introduced into Tunisia
deliberately. Tunisians realized that vacation
facilities, sun and sea, are as much con¬
sumer products as anything else and can be
marketed. With the incentives given to the
construction industry and through use of
the plentiful supply of semi-skilled labour,
the hotel industry very soon proved itself
able to alleviate the serious problem of
chronic under-employment.
As it turns out, job creation in the tourism
sector costs as little as one twentieth of the 1
cost in the traditional industrial sector. At ^-
the present time the hotel industry employs |
more than 30,000 people. What is more, ©
tourism has proved one of the key sectors in ~
which profit margins have been sufficiently I
large to attract both national and foreign o
capital. The hotel industry has also opened' §>
the door to a whole chain of new employ- J
ment opportunities. Last but not least, |
tourism has helped a great deal witru s
Tunisia's balance of payments problems, r |
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
PALMY DAYS? In host countries tourism was once thought of simply as a money-spinning
passport to economic development. Today it is increasingly seen to have complex and
sometimes unexpected cultural side-effects when it brings peoples together in an artificial
situation in which real communication may be difficult.
y In short, disproving the pessimism of
earlier studies and despite the risks and fluc¬
tuations and the very real uncertainty of the
sector, tourism has proved, at all levels and
for everyone concerned, at least for the time
being, a source of economic prosperity.
At the same time it is easy to see that only
the economic factors have been taken into
account. This of course is understandable,
considering the urgency of combatting
economic backwardness, and the fact that
during the 1960s development was still a
very real problem. There were very few of us
who could distinguish between develop¬
ment and growth and who understood the
importance of the human and cultural
aspects. The human problems thus, as it
were, forced themselves upon us in a spon¬
taneous and quite haphazard fashion. Little
by little we have been obliged to face up to
the impact that tourism has had on our at
titudes, our values, our beliefs and our
outlook on life.
Let us disregard value judgements about
the behaviour of the tourist himself. Much
more significant is the relationship between
the tourist and the host population. To
begin with, the simple fact of the physical
presence of groups of foreigners is bound to
create new circumstances that affect per¬
sonal relationships. The tourist does not
come on any kind of business, but solely for
recreation. He expects a whole range of ser¬
vices from us for which he is ready to pay at
a price that is naturally assessed somewhat
differently by the two parties but from which
both stand to gain, although in varying
degrees. This relationship with tourists is
something completely new.
According to the traditional concept of
relations between people, the bonds of
hospitality are sacred. "Drinking water and
eating salt" together creates a mystic bond,
and hospitality is a communion from which
grow lasting ties. Tourists, however, are
guests of a different kind. Our tourist visitors
are no longer rare passers-by sent by pro¬
vidence. They are sent to us in mass by
travel agencies. Quantity dilutes quality. A
close relationship between host and guest is
no longer possible. Both know from ex¬
perience that it will not last beyond the week
or ten days' stay.
The occasional friendship that turns out
to be exceptionally long-lasting cannot be
said to be the rule, but applies only to a tiny
minority. What was once the absolute rule
of traditional hospitality turns out to be no
more than a quirk of behaviour outside the
norm. All the more since the tourist circuit is
so organized, stereotyped, standardized and
mechanized that it hardly lends itself to any
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
outpourings of the heart or to any meetings
of minds.
The same kind of comments could be
made, of course, about the general develop¬
ment of economic relations. Traditional
economic production was centred on the
family where much of the work consisted of
services for which there was no payment.
The extension of the wage system to so
many levels of the domestic economy has
transformed into commodities services that
were traditionally provided on a reciprocal
basis. Instead of a society based on services
mutually rendered we have a society in¬
creasingly dominated by money, in the form
of the price tag.
There always was, however, one sector
where money was very little involved... the
recreation sector. Leisure activities were free
in every sense of the word. It was un¬
thinkable, for example, to have to pay to see
people dance (and even more so to pay to
dance oneself), to ride on a camel, or to
bathe in the ocean. Now all these activities
have to be paid for and have become highly
lucrative.
Tourism did not create this profiteering
mentality from scratch. It simply speeded up
its development and accentuated it. But we
must make sure that entire sectors of the
population do not lose their natural sense
of hospitality, and their traditional good
manners.
But there is something even more impor¬
tant. With the advent of tourism the fun¬
damental patterns of the consumer society
are in process of infiltrating our own society.
The tourists are Westerners on vacation
who come here for a week of leisure and to
get away from the year's accumulation of
fatigue and worry. The tourist is a worker
who has escaped. After slaving away all year
he is allowing himself a change of scene and
pace, régime and life-style. One might say
that tourism introduces the behaviour of a
wasteful society into the midst of a society
of want. The rift between rich and poor
societies here is no longer merely a
theoretical scandal based on academic
analysis. It is everyday reality.
The tourist's most insignificant posses¬
sion represents a fortune or a dream for
many of the Tunisians called upon to serve
him and to come into contact with him,
whatever may be involved a beach ball, a
beach towel, a lipstick or a pair of
sunglasses. There is something diabolical
about this cpnstant temptation and this in¬
vitation to taste the extravagant and still for¬
bidden fruits of the consumer society. There
is a tremendous temptation to imitate and
emulate the tourist.
In an enquiry into the problem of juvenile
delinquency we were obliged to recognize
that tourism with its perpetual temptations
is an important factor in the misconduct of
our young offenders. We discovered that
juvenile delinquency in no way stemmed
from the need to satisfy primary and im¬
mediate needs, but rather from secondary
needs created by the development of a dif¬
ferent mentality, new styles of behaviour, a
new outlook on life.
Tourism has undoubtedly played a role in
the changing pattern of morality. The tourist
comes to have a good time. He wants
cabarets, dance halls and night clubs. And
to enliven things and create an "ambience",
the local public is always welcome. There is
no lack of critics to protest against these
dens of "vice and debauchery". It would be
wrong, however, to blame tourism alone for
a trend which in our view is far more
generalized.
The impact of tourism on traditional
values and attitudes is real enough but
should not be blamed for everything. It is
simply a factor in accelerating a develop¬
ment that is already under way. Tourism
acts as a catalyst, working in the same direc¬
tion as the historical trends in the society as
a whole. The main question is whether
tourism, by speeding up developments
which we see as inescapable, might not
throw the machine out of gear when it is
already being subjected to contradictory
forces. The creation of new needs is an in¬
tegral part of the development process. The
ideal would be for new needs to appear only
when society is ready with the means to
satisfy them.
As an industry, tourism's role is to create
these means. But as a social phenomenon
its tendency is to reduce the impact of the
means thus developed by causing these
needs to appear prematurely. The problem is
whether tourism, which is a production
system geared to satisfy the consumption
desires of outsiders, can develop in a climate
of economic and moral austerity.
From another angle, tourism could be
seen as a missed opportunity. It provides an
opportunity for peaceful and friendly
dialogue with those who in the past were
not always favourable to us. Thus the
education of the public and particularly of
those sectors that come into direct contact
with our visitors must aim at instilling the
highest standards not only of welcome,
courtesy and helpfulness but also firmness,
dignity and strong national pride.
We should therefore like to see tourism
become more of an encounter and less of a
tour. An encounter is an exchange leading
to discovery. The tourist who comes to visit
my country does exactly what I do myself:
he expresses himself in terms of his own
culture. And this is how it should be; for it is
the jolt of encountering others that tells him,
by contrast, what he is.
Unfortunately, it does not always happen
like this. The tourist does not always live up
to our expectations, for a simple reason that
has to do with his essential motivations.
Basically the tourist comes to see the coun¬
try rather than the people. He is someone
who passes by without really seeing
anything. And in any case, what does he
want except to have his own prejudices con¬
firmed and enjoy the comforts he is used to,
including the false ideas he entertained
about the country he is visiting?
Cultural mediation is virtually nonexistent.
Local or international intermediairies, travel
agencies, airline companies, hotel chains,
are merely financial intermediaries, with no
pretensions to cultural interpretation. One of
the sumptuous brochures that various com¬
panies use to "sell" our country speaks of:
"Tunisia, the sunny terrace of Africa", "An
enchanting country with vast stretches of
sandy beaches", "A fairy-tale oasis with a
prestigious past", "A revelation of the orien¬
tal lifestyle". Every effort is made to draw
the attention of the potential customer to
the landscape and never to the people. And
when Tunisian culture is mentioned it is
always with reference to the past. Only the
brochures and folders produced by the Tuni¬
sian Tourist Office in several languages, il¬
lustrated with coloured photographs, try to
give our visitors a clear and authentic idea of
our country.
The main thing is to emphasize the
cultural side of tourism. Without running
counter to the deep-seated motivations of
the tourist who wants to relax and get away
from things, we can try to give him what he
wants while offering him the opportunity to
make real contact with the local people. In
this respect, experiments such as the
Festival of Tabarqa deserve to be better
known, looked at more closely, improved on
or perhaps used as pilot experiments.
Lectures before and during his stay, first-
class artistic events, round-table discus¬
sions, guided tours with better-calibre
guides, exhibitions, documentaries all this
is no doubt very expensive, but it would
make the tourist's visit a genuine encounter k
with the country, its culture and its people. F
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Generally speaking, a major mass infor¬
mation and education drive is necessary.
Tourism could and should be seen as a
powerful factor for understanding between
nations and for international friendship. Cer¬
tain measures would of course have to be
taken, first of all among the people of the
host country. They should be urged to
regard the tourist as just another person, a
guest but not necessarily a model to copy.
With the great diversity of mankind there is
no need for subservience or imitation.
But any kind of action, whether national
or international, must be put into effect step
by step. Tourism is an all-embracing term
which covers many different things.
However, we need to define the. different
types of tourist if our strategy is to have a
practical impact. Moreover, tourist types
vary from.one cultural group to another. For
example, they could be classified according
to whether or not they know the language of
the country, their financial means, their
demands, and their socio-cultural level.
The camera does not lie or does it? Below, market-day scene in a Latin American town.
Certainly each different type has its own
identifiable motivations. Once these have
been determined, we can do a better job of
trying to satisfy them. Certain other areas
also need rethinking or even reorganizing
from scratch: archaeological tourism,
sports-oriented tourism, company, profes¬
sional or trade union tourism associations.
In short, tourism needs to be diversified
and multiplied, and given new life and spirit.
Obviously this does not mean that the
economic dimension should be overlooked
or underplayed. We are even prepared to ad¬
mit that it should have priority. Nonetheless,
although all progress involves some social
cost, this does not mean that we should
passively let things take their course.
Tourism could be turned to better advan¬
tage, often at little cost, by using a lot of in¬
telligence and imagination.
It is wrong to see it either as the way out
of our countries' economic difficulties or as
a curse that will plunge our societies into
disorder. It will not bring us ready-made
modernity, although it speeds up the moder¬
nization process and may change its course.
It need not destroy our values nor upset our
beliefs. It simply hastens a trend that started
several decades ago and has been forced by
the overall policies practiced by our country.
If we succeed in reaping the maximum
benefit from the set of circumstances that
tourism brings in its wake, tourism may be
used as the starting-point for an attempt to
open a dialogue between nations.
ABDELWAHAB BOUHDIBA, of Tunisia, is pro¬
fessor of Maghrebian sociology at the University
of Tunis and director of Tunisia's Centre of
Economic and Social Research. He is a member
of the United Nations sub-commission on preven¬
tion of discrimination and protection of
minorities, and the author of many published
works including Sexuality in Islam and Raisons
d'Être.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Tourism
passport to development?
by Emanuel de Kadt
IN the 1960s, tourism erupted on a grand scale. This was
seen as offering a new opportunity for Third World coun¬
tries to secure foreign exchange and stimulate economic
growth. Their sunny climates, sandy beaches, and exotic
cultures attracted a stream of vacationers, and resorts
multiplied to meet the demand.
With the oil crisis and the recession of 1974-75, there was
a pause in the growth of tourism. The end of the boom gave
new urgency to existing concerns about whether tourism
produced sufficient gains for developing countries to justify
the investments required.
In addition to doubts about whether tourism yielded
economic returns commensurate with its economic costs,
there was a general questioning of some of the basic assump¬
tions about the relation between development and economic
growth. In the case of tourism, these doubts were reinforced
by the belief that it brings larger adverse social and cultural
effects than does development of other sectors.
Tourism is in one important respect different from other
potential export activities: the ultimate consumer of the
goods and services comes to the exporting country rather
than having most goods and services delivered to him at
home. An analysis of the economy of tourism therefore re¬
quires more careful attention to transport and marketing ar¬
rangements than in the case of most other exports.
And the very presence of foreigners in the exporting coun¬
try is widely believed to generate significant social effects by
demonstrating alien and, what is perhaps worse, unat¬
tainable life-styles and values. Furthermore, there is strictly
speaking no such thing as a "tourism industry", analogous
to industries as normally understood (construction, steel,
agriculture).
Instead, tourists purchase goods and services from a
variety of industries, with usually rather less than two-thirds
of their expenditures being in the hotels and restaurants nor-
. mally identified with the tourism sector.
Despite these differences, the problems special to tourism
in developing countries still need to be set in the wider con¬
text of development, and the main questions addressed for
tourism must fit in with the more general considerations of
policymakers.
Dominant development concerns have changed over the
past three decades. With much oversimplification, it may
perhaps be said that an earlier simple faith in the merits of
economic growth as such has given way to questions about
the balance of that growth and the distribution of material
benefits. Also, the very definition of development is being
challenged, not only in its economic interpretation but in its
social, political, and human dimensions as well.
Since 1970 a series of Unesco-sponsored Intergovernmen¬
tal Conferences on Cultural Policies has stressed the impor¬
tance of cultural development as an essential component of
the general development of countries. Even so, the cultural
and non-material aspects of development are still often
neglected by those responsible for making the crucial policy
decisions both nationally and internationally.
Growth alone may not suffice to overcome poverty within
a reasonable time, and the distribution of the material
benefits of development among the poorest countries and
the poorest population groups within individual countries
requires special attention. From arguments about the
general effects of different development strategies on
distribution of income, attention has come to rest on the
staggering number of people, more than 900 million of
them, living in absolute poverty.
More than ever before, the development community is
searching for means that will enable the poor to provide for
their basic needs through more productive work, more wide¬
ly available social services, and increased participation in
political decision-making. It needs to be considered whether
the deliberate and large-scale development of tourism, con¬
ceived as a major net earner of foreign exchange, leads to
results consistent with this newly identified goal of develop¬
ment.
"One-world" arguments question whether the pursuit by
all countries of rapidly rising mass consumption will be
feasible for much longer, given the consequent environmen¬
tal deterioration and looming exhaustion of non-renewable
natural resources. According to this view, further rises in the
consumption of the rich will increasingly conflict with at¬
tempts to improve the living standards of the poor. The con¬
sumption patterns of international tourism are a particularly
conspicuous example of the consumerism that is now being
challenged in the industrialized world, out of reach of the
poor countries' masses but within the reach of their elites.
The study of tourism and its effects has not, on the whole,
taken a great deal of account of these broad issues. The
dangers of this oversight are twofold. First, such tourism as
does take place may not be planned so as to generate a max¬
imum effect on development. Second, a pro- or anti-tourism
stance might be taken up without real evidence to support it.
In the past, sociocultural issues and effects on arts and
crafts have been at best considered as afterthoughts by
tourism planners. They have not usually been equipped to
deal with such questions even if there was a lone non-
economist on the staff.
Virtually never assessed nor predicted beforehand are
possible changes in the social structure of tourism develop¬
ment areas, likely modifications in class relations, and the
more general potential consequences for the local area of at¬
tracting the interest of groups with economic or political
power in the national or transnational sphere. These social
changes, together with important material effects on
employment and income, are of course, precisely the results
that determine whether the process of tourism development
is judged good or bad by the people affected.
I believe that it is worth attempting to analyze the impacts
of tourism in the light of the development issues mentioned
above, and that such an analysis will benefit from reference
to the lessons on social and cultural impacts learned from
other projects or other societies.
EMANUEL DE KADT, Dutch sociologist, is a professorial fellow
of the Institute of Development Studies at the University of Sussex
(U.K.). This article is an abridged version of his introduction to
Tourism Passport to Development?, published by the Oxford
University Press, 1979. This volume, which he edited, is based on
the proceedings of a joint Unesco-World Bank seminar on the
social and cultural impacts of tourism, held in Washington, D.C, in
December 1976.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Water Decade (1981-1990)
1981 marks the start of the International Drinking Water Supply and Sanitation Decade, a worldwide
co-operative effort to provide "clean water and adequate sanitation for all by the year 1990". The
Decade has been declared by the United Nations GeneralAssembly in response to a human tragedy
of enormous proportions: more than half the men, women and children living today have no ready
access to clean drinking water, and fewer still have facilities for sanitary waste disposal. Over the
next ten years many groups will join forces to remedy this situation, which gravely affects human
health and productivity and severely impedes development progress. Participants will include
governments of both developing and industrialized countries, non-governmental industry, schools
and colleges, the media and several United Nations agencies, including Unesco.
WATER is essential for life. It makes up nine-tenths of the
human body's volume and two-thirds of its weight. This
vital element covers about three-quarters of the earth's
surface. But some 97.4 per cent is saltwater in oceans, and 1.8 per
cent is frozen in polar regions.
Fresh water, needed by human beings to sustain life, health and
productive activities, constitutes only 0.8 per cent of the world's
supply... and nobody knows just what portion of this amount is
contaminated.
For half the world's people... and three-fifths of those living in
developing countries... reasonable access to a safe and adequate
drinking water supply is still more a wish than a reality.
Water is first and foremost a physiological necessity; without one
or two litres of water daily, a person cannot survive. Some twenty to
fifty litres a day of safe water, conveniently available for drinking,
'food preparation, and hygiene, are generally considered essential to
sustenance of the minimum acceptable standard of living.
About twenty litres is the quantity of water usually used when the
source, such as a well or a standpipe, is within a reasonable
distance up to about 200 metres from the home. Installation of
patio connections increases consumption, often to about fifty litres.
With house connections and the simplest indoor plumbing, in¬
cluding a pour-flush toilet, 100 litres a day per person is normally the
minimum level of consumption.
In developed countries and in the wealthier parts of cities in
developing countries, average daily consumption is generally a
multiple of this amount, ranging between 200 and 400 litres a day
per person. In addition to basic human requirements (or larger
residential consumption), water for industry and commerce, which
typically accounts for 30-60 per cent of total consumption in an area,
is also essential to sustenance of productive life and employment.
In many instances the present difficulties of procuring water are
so great that a significant effect of improvement is a saving of time
and energy. In a study of the effects of rural water supply projects
on women in Kenya conducted by the Co-operative for American
Relief Everywhere (CARE), for example, it was reported that nearly a
fifth of rural households spent more than six hours each day collec¬
ting water. A third of the total work time of female heads of
households was devoted to collecting water, while only 17 per cent
was spent in preparing food and 21 per cent in economic activities,
such as farming, herding, and marketing.
The problem is not confined to rural areas; in one of the poorer
parts of Douala, Cameroon, that was covered in a recent project
The underground drinking-water reservoir
at Montsouris, Paris, France.
Photo Doisneau © Rapho, Science et Avenir, Pans
supported by the World Bank, for example, there were only two
standpipes for 50,000 persons, and some residents walked as far as
five kilometres to fetch water.
Another basic need is the sanitary disposal of human waste that
is, its disposal in such a way as to remove it from human contact.
People generally seek to dispose of their excreta as cheaply and easi¬
ly as possible, and in many rural areas where population density is
low it is usually possible to do this without any large investment in
waste-disposal facilities. In most urban areas, however, where the
concentration of population is greater, a higher level of service is re¬
quired for waste-disposal facilities in order to protect the health of
the community and prevent degradation of the environment.
There is a wide range of facilities that can be used, from simple
latrines to the type of waterborne sewerage known in most advanc¬
ed countries. The need for sewers, as opposed to less expensive on-
site disposal techniques, depends considerably on the permeability
of the local soil, but, broadly speaking, it can be said that sewers in
typical urban residential areas will not function when water con¬
sumption is less than 100 litres a day per person but will be essential
when consumption reaches 200 litres a day per person. Techniques
and systems of waste disposal, like water supply, must be planned
with the needs of industry and commerce taken into account.
The best estimate, on the basis of 1975 country data collected by
the World Health Organization (WHO) and of other information
available to the World Bank, is that fewer than 500 million of the
2,000 million people in the developing countries not including the
People's Republic of China had access to adequate supplies of
safe water and adequate waste-disposal facilities.
The 1,500 million without these basic services consisted of some
1,100 million to 1,200 million in rural areas, or more than 80 per cent
of the total rural population, and 300 million to 400 million, or bet¬
ween half and two thirds of the population, in the urban areas. The
large majority of the former were dependent for water on shallow
wells and natural surface water, of unreliable quality and often at
substantial distances, and for waste disposal on the fields. The ma¬
jority of the latter were in areas that had water-supply systems, but
which were working only a few hours a day or delivering water of
unsafe quality.
The WHO data indicate that the number of people with access to-
public water-supply systems increased dramatically between 1970
and 1975, from some 400 million to around 750 million, but popula¬
tion growth was also substantial during the same period, and the
number of persons not served changed little. The information
reported, moreover, refers only to access and does not indicate the
condition or reliability of the water-supply system.
Levels of urban service in India, for example, are reported to have
increased from 60 per cent in 1970 to 80 per cent in 1975; the number
of people served by house connections or public standpipes increas¬
ed from 66 million to 107 million, and the backlog of population not
served was cut from 44 million to 27 million. At the same time,
however, there was a rapid decline in the quality of service. In many
of the largest cities, customers who had had eight to ten hours of i
service in 1970 had only two to three hours by 1975. Whenever inter- f
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
v-
WHAT THE
n
Photo Dominique Roger, Unesco
Estimates on what it will cost
to provide everyone with clean
water and adequate sanitation
by the year 1990 have varied
widely.
At the United Nations Water
Conference in Mar Del Plata,
Argentina (1977), the price tag
put on the Decade was
$140,000 million. More recently,
however, the World Bank has
produced figures generally
considered more realistic.
Costs are dramatically
affected by choices of
technology and scope and level
of service.
The costliest option, based
on house connections for water
supply at $120-150 per
head and water-borne sewage
(e.g., flush toilets) at $250 per
head is priced in excess of
$600,000 million, or $60,000
million annually (in 1978 U.S.
dollars). It assumes that:
There will be 100 per cent
coverage by 1990;
Rural households will be
served with standpipes or
handpumps and individual
latrines;
Urban households will
receive water taps of their own
and will be connected to a
sewerage system.
A second option is based on
more use of less sophisticated,
lower cost technologies such as
handpumps and pit latrines,
which are perfectly capable of
providing an acceptable level of
service in both urban and rural
areas. It also takes into account
a wider mix of service levels,
and an 80 per cent level of
coverage by the Decade's end.
This figure, the one now cited
most frequently, is $300,000
million, or $30,000 million
annually.
Every day tens of millions of people in the developing countries consume vast amounts of
time and energy carrying heavy loads of water over long distances. In many places, the
trip may take as many as six hours and use up more than half the day's energy.
Women and children bear the greatest burden. Instead of a journey to school, the day can
begin for a child with a long, difficult walk to fetch water. The daily trek uses many hours
women might otherwise spend on more productive educational or income-earning pursuits
which could improve the quality of life for all in the community.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
DECADE WILL COST
On what basis are these total costs determined?
NEEDS :
1990 population of developing countries needing
water supply and sanitation (in millions).
Water Sanitation
Urban 640 650
Rural 1,570 1,670
Total 2,210 2,320
COSTS :
Per Capita costs of alternative types of water supply
and sanitation (1978 US$).
Urban Rural
Water Supply
with house connection $120 $150
with standpipe 40 40
with handpumps 25
Sanitation
with sewerage 250 250
with septic tank 100
with latrine 30 20
SERVICE LEVELS:
Case 1* : (100 % coverage using 1980 WHO Target
Urban Service Standard Distribution)
Urban Water Supply 70 % house connection
30 % standpipe
Sanitation 40 % sewerage
40 % septic tanks
20 % latrine and
communal latrines
Rural Water Supply
Sanitation
20 % house connection
40 % standpipe
40 % handpumps
80 % sewerage
20 % latrines
Case 2* (80 % coverage with service standard as
suggested)
Urban Water Supply
Sanitation
Rural Water Supply
Sanitation
40 % house connection
40 % standpipe
25 % sewerage
15 % septic tanks
40 % latrine and
communal latrines
10 % house connection
30 % standpipe
40 % handpumps
10 % sewerage
70 % latrines
* Both sets of figures are only rough approximations. They are
bound to rise further when costs of operation and maintenance are
added to installation costs.
Source : World Bank, Basic Needs
Disposal, Dec. 10. 1979, pp. 6-7.
Water Supply and Waste
, ruptions in service occur, the safety of the water is also in doubt.
These are among the reasons why the global estimate given of the
number of those who receive adequate service falls below the
number officially reported to have access.
At least two thirds of those without adequate water service are to
be found in South and Southeast Asia. The middle-income develop¬
ing countries, particularly in Latin America and the Mediterranean
region, where there is a high proportion of house connections, have
achieved higher standards of service than other regions.
The figures reported for waste-disposal facilities are somewhat
less reliable than those for water and may give an unduly optimistic
picture. They nevertheless indicate only a very small increase bet¬
ween 1970 and 1975 in the percentage of the population served by
adequate waste-disposal facilities, from 25 per cent to 27 per cent,
and, with growth of population, a substantial increase in the ab¬
solute number of those not served.
These figures are based on very modest definitions of access to
waste-disposal facilities. The usual practice is to regard the ex¬
istence of a latrine at a home as evidence that satisfactory facilities
exist. In congested areas, however, most latrines do not meet
minimal public health requirements. Often they are not designed to
be accessible to children. Poorly designed and constructed pit
privies, furthermore, frequently contaminate nearby shallow wells.
The principal consequence of highly deficient water supply and
waste-disposal is a heavy burden of disease, with consequent suffer¬
ing and hardship, stunted human growth and development, and
diminished productivity.
The most reliable indicator of the overall state of health in a coun¬
try is life expectancy. At the end of the 1940s life expectancy in the
developing countries was estimated to be about thirty-eight years.
By now it is believed to have increased by about 40 per cent, to
some fifty-three years, while in the more highly developed countries
life expectancy is now about seventy to seventy-five years.
For subpopulations characterized by extreme poverty, malnutri¬
tion, inadequate water supply, insanitary disposal of wastes, and
lack of health services, however, there has probably been no im¬
provement in health. The low life expectancy at birth is largely a
reflection of extraordinarily high mortality rates of infants and young
children. If deaths among children under the age of five years could
be reduced to rates similar to those in the industrially developed
countries, life expectancies in the developing countries would be on¬
ly three to five years less than those in Western Europe and North
America.
Water and excreta are prominent factors in the transmission of
most of the more serious diseases of the developing world.
Gastrointestinal infections are the leading causes of both death and
disability in most developing countries. In many areas diseases
related to deficiencies in water supply and waste disposal are con¬
tributory causes of most infant deaths and account for a large pro¬
portion of adult sickness.
Studies made in recent years show clearly, however, that these
problems can seldom be overcome by a single measure or remedy. A
combined approach is usually required that includes ample water
supplies, hygienic disposal of excreta, and education in water-use
practices and household hygiene to change traditional beliefs and
habits; improved garbage collection is sometimes also essential, par¬
ticularly in densely populated, low-income areas. In order to be fully
effective, improvements in water supply and waste disposal must
extend throughout the community, so that risks of infection in
public areas and neighbouring houses are also reduced.
The need to increase the quantity of water available is often more
important than the need to improve its quality, but occasionally this
point is misunderstood and exaggerated. In principle, of course,
water that is adequate for personal and household cleansing does
not need to meet the safety standards of water for drinking and
cooking. The mistaken inference is sometimes drawn from this fact
that the water-supply problem can be adequately overcome by
teaching people to boil the small quantities of water required for>
drinking.
The difficulties of this solution are threefold. First, it is much more
easily said than done; it is hard to keep water segregated in con¬
tainers, and thirsty children in particular tend to drink whatever
water is convenient. Second, it is a very expensive solution; it can be
calculated that the kerosene alone required to boil each day the
quantity of water that a person requires for drinking, cooking, and
minimal personal hygiene would cost at least $20 a year. Third, it i
neglects the extent of the problem. I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
UNICEF estimates that about 15 million
children below the age of 5 die in the
developing countries every year. The absence of
safe water and sanitation plays a major part in
this tragedy. If everyone had access to safe
drinking water and sanitation, infant mortality
could be cut by as much as 50 per cent
world-wide.
According to the World Health Organization
(WHO), approximately 80 per cent of all
sickness and disease can be attributed to
inadequate water or sanitation. For example :
Diarrhoea directly kills six million children in
developing countries every year, and contributes
to the death of up to 18 million people.
Trachoma affects some 500 million people
at any given time, often causing blindness.
Parasitic worms infect nearly one half of the
entire population of the developing countries,
often with very serious consequences. For
example, 200 million people in 70 countries
suffer the debilitating effects of schistosomiasis.
Malaria yearly kills one million children
below the age of two in Africa, south of the
Sahara, alone.
Diseases related to water and sanitation (or
lack of them) may be grouped into five general
categories:
Water-borne diseases spread by drinking
or washing hands, food or utensils in
contaminated water, which acts as a passive
vehicle for the infecting agent.
Water-washed diseases spread by poor
personal hygiene and insufficient water for
washing. Lack of proper facilities for human
waste disposal is another contributing factor.
Water-based diseases transmitted by a
vector which spends a part of its life cycle in
More than four billion people live on our water-rich planet. But over a billion must
drink dirty water. Nearly two billion have no toilet. The World Water and Sanitation
Decade aims to ensure that by 1990 everyone has enough clean water and adequate
sanitation. The cost: US$30 billion a year for ten years five times more than present
global spending.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
water. Contact with water thus infected
conveys the disease-causing parasite through
the skin or mouth.
Diseases with water-related vectors
contracted through infection-carrying insects
which breed in water and bite near it, especially
when it is stagnant.
Fecal disposal diseases caused by
organisms that breed in excreta when sanitation
is defective.
These diseases exact a high toll in human life
and suffering.
The boxes on pages 13-17 are based on documentation produced by the
Inter-agency Steering Committee for the International Drinking Water Supp¬
ly and Sanitation Decade, of which Unesco is a member, and on Unesco
sources. The main article has been largely adapted from Water Supply and
Waste Disposal (September 1980) one of a series of booklets prepared by the
World Bank on the subject of basic needs.
k In practice, provision of good-standard water in rural areas usually
requires only that springs and wells be properly located, con¬
structed, operated, and maintained, while in urban areas the
marginal cost of treating water to make it safe for drinking, cooking,
and personal hygiene is typically very small far less than the $20 a
person that would be required for boiling.
There is considerable evidence that the economic burden of
disease and ill health that is in large part the result of deficiencies in
water supply and waste-disposal is very great in developing coun¬
tries, particularly for the poor. Various studies and estimates indicate
that in these countries disease typically takes up about a tenth of the
average person's potentially productive time and, in addition, affects
risk-taking and initiative adversely, disrupts the education and nur¬
ture of children, stunts physical development, and causes vast suf¬
fering and hardship. The gastrointestinal diseases reduce absorption
of nutrients, in acute cases by as much as 30 per cent. The malnutri¬
tion occasioned by gastrointestinal disease compromises the
defences of the body against infections and is therefore largely
responsible for the diarrhoea-measles-pneumonia complex that kills
a fifth or more of the children born in many developing countries.
Meeting the goal of the International Drinking Water Supply and
Sanitation Decade will be a gigantic task. If everyone in the world is
to have clean water and adequate sanitation by 1990, new water
supply and sanitation facilities will have to be provided for half a
million people every day during the ten-year period.
The United Nations system has evolved strategies for the Decade.
These emphasize promotion and support of national Decade pro¬
grammes through technical co-operation; building up national
capacities and generating dynamic self-sustaining pro¬
grammes, promoting technical co-operation among developing
countries; and encouraging the flow of external funds into national
Decade activities. Several organizations in the United Nations
system (the UN, ILO, FAO, Unesco, the World Bank, UNICEF and
UNDP) have formed a "Steering Committee for Co-operative Ac¬
tion" to co-ordinate their work with Governments in planning and
implementing water supply and sanitation activities.
All countries whether well advanced in the development of
water supply and sanitation or badly in need of better facilities will
be involved.
As a means of working towards Decade goals. Governments are
developing "National Action Plans". A number of countries have set
up National Action Committees to co-ordinate and support Decade
activities.
Besides improving their own national water and sanitation ser¬
vices the industrialized countries are expected to provide more
resources for projects related to the Decade within their bilateral pro¬
grammes of assistance to developing countries... to harmonize in¬
ternational assistance from various governmental and other
organizations... and to increase their contributions to multilateral
Decade-related programmes.
The primary commitment is coming from the developing countries
themselves.
It is their Governments which can accord water and sanitation
adequate priority... integrate schemes with national social and
economic plans for other sectors... allocate required financial,
technical and human resources. They can organize the necessary
machinery and infrastructure at national, regional and local levels,
provide bodies to co-ordinate activities, and devise well-prepared
projects able to attract external aid.
And it is their people, so desperately in need of improved facilities,
who can assume major responsibility for ensuring that they are pro¬
vided and maintained.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
MALAWI:
A
community
approach
COMMUNITY participation is
the cornerstone of natio¬
nal drinking water supply
policy in Malawi, an East African
country with a population of just
over 5 million.
Local involvement at all stages
is largely responsible for the
remarkable progress made
toward the Government's high-
priority goal of providing
everyone with a safe, potable
water supply no further than
400 metres away by the year
1990. The target is well within
reach: clean water is already
available to at least 70 per cent of
the country's urban dwellers and
35 per cent of the rural in¬
habitants (who make up 90 per
cent of the total population).
Typical of Malawi's success
with this approach is the Mulanje
West project in the southern part
of the country where 75,000 peo¬
ple living in an area of 257 square
kilometres are served by 460
village taps.
The problem was that the
traditional shallow wells in this
area and even the river several
miles away were running dry.
The water cycle had been under¬
mined by cutting of trees to clear
land for cultivation thus reducing
the land's ability to retain water.
Villagers appealed to the
Government's Ministry of Com¬
munity and Social Welfare for
Photo Seitz. UNICEF
Unesco
and the
International Decade
Water resources assessment and management. Many
Unesco activities within the framework of the International
Hydrological Programme (IHP) relate to the goals of the
Decade. Several IHP themes relating to water resources
assessment, water quality protection and allocation of water
resources can provide inputs to the Decade. In 1981 Unesco
is to develop three major regional projects (in Latin America,
the Arab States and Africa) on the rational management of
water resources in rural areas, the purpose of which is to
determine the most appropriate ways of developing and
conserving water resources to meet the economic and social
needs of rural communities.
Water-related education and training. Within the water-
related educational programmes and training courses
sponsored by Unesco more emphasis will be placed on
drinking water supply and sanitation. One example is the
regional course being organized at Arusha, Tanzania, for the
training of personnel in the techniques and methods of
prospecting for water in the hard-rock areas of Africa. The
IHP National Committees established in some 110 countries
will be encouraged to promote and participate in the
Decade.
Education in hygiene and water use. Education
concerning hygiene and patterns of water use is an essential
element in the overall strategy of the Decade. Carefully
designed programmes that teach people about the links
between clean water, hygiene and health will have to be
developed, a task for which many countries will need expert
guidance. Unesco's contribution will be concerned with the
planning and implementation of a comprehensive
programme aimed at massive health education at the
community level focussed on the issue of clean water and
sanitation.
Public motivation and participation. In addition to the
development of grassroots health education projects,
Unesco will have a responsibility for national and provincial
public promotional programmes in support of the Decade.
Unesco will also be able to contribute through its activities
in the fields of environmental education, engineering
education (civil and sanitary engineers) and community
motivation and participation and integrated rural
development.
Information systems and services. Unesco's General
Information Programme is aimed at facilitating access to
scientific and technological information and its effective use,
and contributing to the development of information
infrastructures and the theoretical and practical training of
information personnel and users. This Programme will be
able to provide technical guidance for the development of
the Programme on Exchange and Transfer of Information
(POETRI) which is to constitute the information support of
the Decade.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
assistance. This was done
through their District Develop¬
ment Committee, consisting of
members of parliament, tradi¬
tional authorities and local
leaders of the ruling Malawi Con¬
gress Party. The Ministry then
drew up a design for the system.
Steel pipes would take water
from a pool in the fast-flowing
Likhobula River to a sediment
tank where sand and flood debris
would be screened. The water
would then be conducted by
gravity through an asbestos ce¬
ment main pipeline, to sixteen
storage tanks situated in the hills
just above the villages. Plastic
pipes would convey it to in¬
dividual village taps, providing
enough for each person to use
some 23 litres a day.
In October 1972, the villagers
began to plan for their system.
They staked out an area in their
fields for the main pipeline so
that no crops would be sown
there. They began digging and
pipe-laying the following
February and March, after the
rains had made the ground soft.
Village leaders established a
committee to organize construc¬
tion. All villages which would use
the scheme were to share the
labour. As 30 kilometres of
trench were needed for the
asbestos cement pipe (supplied
by UNICEF) the committee divid¬
ed the length into five sections,
assigning several villages to work
on each. About two hundred
people men, women and even
children worked on each of the
sections every day until a trench
1 .20 m deep and 80 cm wide was
completed. Enthusiasm was so
great that, often, people who
had finished their allotted work
for the day stayed on to do even
more.
Project assistants, chosen
from the community, were given
three weeks' training to enable
them to cope with pipe-laying
and other more difficult tasks.
Next came installation of
branch lines which villagers com¬
pleted by laying piping (also sup¬
plied by UNICEF) in 210 kilo¬
metres of trenches they had dug,
80 cm deep and the width of a
hoe. The operation was com¬
pleted when they chose sites for
their village taps and built con¬
crete aprons and drains for them.
In areas where new gravity
water supply systems are install¬
ed, villagers are visibly delighted
and celebrate the opening of
each tap with singing and danc¬
ing. Health has improved
measurably in such areas, as was
evident in 1973-74 when the
country was hit with a cholera
epidemic. While 20 persons in an
average village of 350 were af¬
fected, villages with tap water
had no more than one case, and
in each instance that person had
visited another town.
With self-help labour, gravity
systems are constructed at amaz¬
ingly low costs, which rarely ex¬
ceed $10.00 per capita, even
when the training component is
added. They are designed to last
100 years and operating costs are
nil.
Malawi's villagers also supply
labour for protected shallow
wells in those areas where this
technology is the best solution to
water supply. Village committees
supply bricks and sand and use
their ox-carts to transport
materials. The Government pro¬
vides cement, a concrete slab
and parts for pump assemby.
These wells cost less than $1.00
per person served.
It has been found, however,
that they are easily contaminated
if not protected. To deal with this
problem, the Government has
developed a simple pump, made
from local materials, which is
bolted to a concrete lid, encloses
the entire well, and can be
operated even by children. Its
cost is $25-$30 as compared to
$700-$1,000 for deep well
pumps.
In Malawi's urban areas,
Government policy mandates
that people pay for their water.
Fees are imposed because it is
recognized that people in towns
tend to have full-time jobs, which
makes it difficult to organize dig¬
ging crews. In any case, it would
be neither desirable nor possible
to limit benefits to those who
participate in construction.
Charging for water in towns also
serves to prevent waste, and is a
means of discouraging urban
migration and the accompanying
problems of slums, high un¬
employment and over-exten¬
sion of facilities experienced
by many developing countries.
The Government's commit¬
ment, external support and the
vital contributions of the local
people make it almost certain
that Malawi will meet the
Decade's goal of clean water for
all by 1990.
In the Sudan, members of a rural community at work installing a safe new water supply pipeline. If the
Decade is to achieve its objective of clean water and adequate sanitation for all by 1990, maximum
participation by those who will benefit from the new systems is essential.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Emperor Qin' s
bronze chariots
The Unesco Courier
presents on this double
page recently taken
photos of the latest
remarkable finds
unearthed near the
tomb of Emperor Qin
Shi Huang in China 's
Shensi province. The
Emperor is remembered
as the builder of the
Great Wall and
as the first ruler
(from 221 to 210 BC) of
a unified China.
In 1974, villagers digging a well near
the mound which covers the
Emperor's tomb (above) discovered
a huge vault which turned out to
contain thousands of life-size
terra-cotta soldiers. The
individuality of each figure was so
striking as to suggest that the
soldiers were true-to-life portraits
of members of the imperial
bodyguard. In our December 1979
issue we published a progress
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
?¿<¿t*l
"V
r/-
m
&h
report on the excavations and on
the preservation of this "clay
army".
Since then, two big bronze figures,
two bronze chariots and eight
bronze horses have been unearthed
to the west of Qin Shi Huang's
tomb. The well-preserved relics are
the biggest of their kind ever
discovered in China.
Our photos, by Chinese
photographer Yang Limen, show:
(1) Archaeologists working on the
bronze treasures. Each of the two
chariots is drawn by four horses.
The horses are of the same casting
but the chariots are different in
form and each driver has a different
posture. (2) One of the chariots
with its driver and horses. The
bronze figure is 90 cm high; each
horse is 70 cm high and about one
metre long; the chariot is over one
metre wide. (3) A lifelike driver
grips the reins. His dress indicates
that he belongs to the same élite
group as one of the terra-cotta
figures found in the underground
vault in 1974. The high-ranking
drivers and their well-appointed
carriages provide unique evidence
of the life of Qin dynasty officials.
Photos Yang Limen © New China Pictures, Peking
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Brazil's
Museum
of
the Unconscious
A bold experiment
in psychotherapy and art
by Fernanda de Camargo e Almeida
Raphael was an academic painter before he became an inmate of
Brazil's National Psychiatric Centre in Rio de Janeiro. For twelve
years he was inactive as an artist. Then one day someone gave
him paper, pencils and tubes of paint, and he began to paint
again. "Since he has forgotten the rules of academic painting",
writes the Brazilian critic Sergio Milliet, "he gives free rein to his
imagination. He expresses his true self. His paintings may be
compared with what is most beautiful and sensitive in the works
of the moderns, the Matisses, the Picassos, the Dufys...."
BRAZIL'S Museum of Images of the
Unconscious occupies the ground
floor of one of the pavilions of the
National Psychiatric Centre, in the northern
part of Rio de Janeiro. Created to house the
artistic works of patients who frequent the
Centre's occupational therapy workshops,
the Museum contains some 90,000 drawings,
paintings and models in plaster, ceramics and
other materials, selected over the past
twenty-four years by Dr. Nise da Silveira, the
psychiatrist responsible for the occupational
therapy activities that have long been a
feature of the work of the Centre.
The Museum of the Unconscious differs
from other museums not only in the nature of
the works of art it houses, but also in its en¬
tire organizational set-up. Its collections are
constantly being enriched by the daily arrival
of new works of art from the workshops of
the Psychiatric Centre which are in operation,
every morning from Monday to Friday
throughout the year.
The drawing and painting workshop is a
vast, well-lit room situated at one end of the
museum. In addition to working tables it is
equipped with a piano and an organ; quite
often someone plays or sings, thus
associating ¡mage with sound. Modelling is
usually carried out in another room or in the
garden.
In this excellent atmosphere the patients
work with the aid of occupational therapists,
coming frequently into contact with artists
and personnel from the Carl Jung Study
Group (the Museum's scientific research sec¬
tion), yet never losing their creative freedom.
After leaving the workshops, the works are
listed and catalogued and become the pro¬
perty of the Museum. The cataloguing is car¬
ried out in accordance with the ARAS (Ar¬
chive for Research on Archetypical Sym¬
bolism) system adopted by the Jung Centre
of Zurich, thus forming a complete dossier on
each patient. This enables psychiatrists and
research workers to follow each case and
provides a source of material for studies on
the unconscious. The works are stored until
the opportunity arises to exhibit them, but
they are always available for reference and
examination.
Up until 1973, the Museum suffered from a
number of museological and museographical
deficiencies. Two museologists from the con¬
sultation unit of the Association of Members
of the International Council of Museums
(AM-ICOM) were invited by Dr. Nise da
Silveira to make a thorough study of the im¬
provements which could be carried out
without jeopardizing the Museum's basic
structure.
They came to the conclusion that it would
be necessary to enlarge the temporary exhibi¬
tion rooms, create a permanent exhibition
room which would adjoin the gallery, and
reappraise the display materials such as sup¬
ports, pedestals and lighting.
All this had to be done without losing sight
of the fact that the patient who frequents the
workshop also frequents the Museum, both
of which are indispensable meeting points at
which he or she can make contact with the
outside world. That is why certain display
methods cannot be adopted and why
modifications which might confuse the pa¬
tients cannot suddenly be introduced.
It was decided to proceed slowly, using
methods that would not shock the patients
by their novelty. The rooms were therefore
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1
>
m M
Photo Humberto Franceschi <Q Museum of Images of the Unconscious. Rio de Janeiro
Photo Luis Alberto Peregrino © Museum of Images of the Unconscious, Rio de Janeiro
Above, The Planetarium of God, an oil painting by Carlos.
Produced in 1948, it seems to depict a vision the artist had
had nine years before. Brazilian critic Mario Pedrosa has
described how, one September morning In 1939, Carlos
"saw the sun's reflection in the little mirror in his room....
And there appeared before him a cosmic vision which he
described as 'the planetary of God'. He shouted for his
family to come, for he wanted everyone to see the
wonderful sight before his eyes. On the same day, he was
committed to an institution." Left, Mándala, by Fernando
Diniz, who has painted some of the most exuberant still-
lifes in the history of Brazilian art. The work won an
award when it was exhibited in Paris in 1957. The Swiss
psychologist and psychoanalyst Carl Gustav Jung
believed that the mentally afflicted intuitively produce
depictions of mándalas (magic circles used in some
cosmogonies to represent the universe), these archetypes
of the unchanging basis of human thought occurring in
different historical periods, races and civilizations.
modified during the daytime in full view of
the visitors from the workshops. The
hospital staff helped to cover the walls with
hemp cloth, as in the other rooms, and the
patients themselves helped to arrange the
plants and the lighting. In addition to the
wooden boxes already in use as supports,
bricks covered in hemp cloth and upturned
glass bowls were used as supports for small
ceramic objects. Considerable attention was
paid to this question of supports because
the use of an unfamiliar material might be
considered by the artist as an interference in
his work and create in him a feeling of
rejection.
The Museum's technical personnel posed
another problem how could people unac¬
customed to contact with sick people be in
troduced into this museum with its own very
special characteristics without serious
misunderstandings arising? It was not the
problem of adaptation that worried us or led
us to envisage the need to take extra precau¬
tions. After all, perfectly satisfactory rela¬
tions existed between the patients and the
members of the study group from the Carl k
Jung Research Centre as well as between f
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Intrigued, like many visitors to the museum, by the
symbolism of the archetypes (photo previous page), this
young Brazilian girl is studying a large album of coloured
drawings. Ranged nearby are sculptures on mythological
themes. Below, an upturned glass bowl serves as a support
for a ceramic earth divinity ringed by snakes.
>the patients and visitors to the Museum.
The fear was that if museologists and other
professional museum personnel were to in¬
troduce orthodox museological standards
they might destroy the special character and
authenticity of the Museum of the Un¬
conscious. For it is clear that, however high
their technical level, certain professional
standards and practices cannot be applied in
this Museum.
Encouraged by the close contacts we had
always had with the Museum staff and the
interest they had always shown in helping to
find solutions to problems, we decided to at¬
tempt an experiment. Instead of training
museologists to meet the needs of the
Museum and its setting, we decided to try to
train the personnel actually working in the
Museum and workshops, that is, the
employees of the National Psychiatric
Centre.
- The first step was to give them elementary
instruction on the cultural heritage, on
museology and museography. They were
taken to visit other museums and asked to
give their impressions, to make comparisons
and to undertake projects and research
tasks. Intensive training groups were
established and given increasingly specific
objectives to attain.
Today we continue to collaborate with
museologist Lourdes do Rego Novaes and
with a training unit of AM-ICOM and a con¬
sultation unit; whilst the latter is engaged in
presenting new exhibitions and improving
the Museum, the training unit is working out
a training programme adapted to present
needs which gives a sound general founda'-'
tion to the trainees.
The demand for these courses has been
so heavy that we have had to admit to them
people from other sections of the hospital
who work in related areas. Candidates for
the courses include doctors, psychiatrists,
psychologists, educators, occupational
therapists, administrative staff, nurses and
technical personnel. The rate of attendance
has been between 97 and 98 per cent and
the students have completed all the work
assigned to them.
Each student has been brought to a level
at which he can envisage the themes dealt
with from the viewpoint of his own speciali¬
ty. At first it was thought that once instruc¬
tion on general principles had been com¬
pleted the group would have to be divided
into specialized sections. But this proved
not to be the case since all the students
wanted to gain more knowledge in all fields.
Only later, therefore, will it be possible to
organize smaller groups which will receive
more specialized training.
Since 1974, when the Museum entered
this new phase, some thirty temporary ex¬
hibitions have been organized. These exhibi¬
tions are usually held in the temporary ex¬
hibition room in which the Carl Jung Study
Group meets once a week. The group
studies a theme which is also that of the ex¬
hibition, such as "Affectivity-Contact",
"Metamorphoses of the Feminine
Principle", etc. The presentation of these
exhibitions is very simple; the labels on the
exhibits bear only iconographical details, the
date and the artist's name. No mention is
made of the patient's psychiatric or
psychological condition. Thus, these exhibi¬
tions can be visited by everyone. The theme
of the "Mother Goddess" constantly recurs
in the works of patients and the Museum
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
has made a special selection of the most in¬
teresting representations of the mother god¬
dess figure. The exhibitions include an ever
increasing number of models and sculptures
including works by the students following
the museological courses.
Another question, that of the social,
cultural and educational activities of the
museum, is currently being studied. Clearly
the Museum's first objective, apart from the
preservation of the works of art, must be to
fulfil a social function within its own com¬
munity, that is, among those who are in
direct contact with and participate in its ac¬
tivities. The National Psychiatric Centre,
which is the Museum's immediate setting, is
therefore the object of the particular atten¬
tion of the Museum. Next comes the old in¬
dustrial quarter in the northern part of Rio de
Janeiro which faces the special problems of
a working class area. The people still have
fears about living close to one of the coun¬
try's principal psychiatric centres. As
elsewhere in the world, the proximity of a
big hospital for mentally sick people arouses
fears of patients escaping and attacking
people.
The Museum is tackling this problem not
only by attempting to explain its purpose,
gathering information locally and integrating
itself into the community, but also by work¬
ing with local people, opening up to them
new horizons and making them understand
what the Psychiatric Centre really is, what
mental illness and its treatment is all about.
Through the city the Museum hopes to
reach out to the entire country.
Already visitors come to the Museum
from other parts of the city, from the coun¬
tryside and from abroad, and all show a live¬
ly interest. The Museum is open every day.
Small groups are asked to notify the
caretaker in advance but large groups have
to obtain special permission to make a visit;
the well-being of the patients cannot be
forgotten. The patients themselves walk
freely in the galleries, often accompanied by
cats or dogs. Dr. Nise da Silveira calls them
"my guests", and in her studies and work¬
ing techniques the animals play a "co-
therapeutic" role, indispensable to the
equilibrium of the patients. The excellent
results achieved are confirmed by daily life in
the Museum and the works held in its ar¬
chives. The presence of animals in a
museum of painting and sculpture may
seem incongruous, but it is one of the
features which enable us to grasp the
special techniques used at the Museum of
the Unconscious.
FERNANDA DE CAMARGO E ALMEIDA,
Brazilian museologist and archaeologist, has
responsibility for museology and staff training in
museology at the Museum of Images of the Un¬
conscious in Rio de Janeiro. A longer version of
this article has also appeared in Unesco's interna¬
tional quarterly Museum (Vol. XXVIII, No. I).
Below, the Museum's central gallery. Beyond it is the
painting workshop. The patients' cats and dogs wander
freely through the exhibition rooms, and their presence
seems so beneficial that the therapists look upon them
almost as "colleagues".
MUSEU DE IMAGENS DO INCONSCIENT!
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
***»
Si
x" "*"
-'
fuir.
*- ¿Jjj	
High-speed
language learning
How to study while you 'sleep'
by Mira Vaisburd
TO master a foreign language well
enough for use as a means of com¬
munication is extremely difficult.
Nature and society provide children with the
conditions necessary for learning their
mother tongue, but it is impossible to
reproduce these conditions in adult life.
People are not, as a rule, faced with the
need to use a foreign language until they
have completed their education and have
embarked on their careers. While they are
still studying, it is a problem that appears
remote and not very real. Study of a foreign
language is thus most often undertaken out
of necessity.
Foreign languages are usually included in
secondary and higher education as part of
the general curriculum and the general
timetable, with no allowance whatsoever
being made for the special features of
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Lithography Roland Topor © Topor-Olivetti
language learning. The result is that the
length of the language courses and the in¬
frequent contact between teachers and
students create conditions that are com¬
pletely contrary to the general principles
governing the acquisition of language skills.
In secondary schools, it is thus only possi¬
ble to learn the rudiments of a foreign
language, making further study necessary.
Studying a foreign language involves in
particular: (a) memorizing a very large
number of speech units, a large proportion
of which are difficult to classify; (b) master¬
ing these units thoroughly enough to be able
to use them automatically; and (c) learning
how to use these units in accordance with
the rules of the language, and using them in
a suitable way from the point of view of the
needs of communication.
Accelerated language-teaching involves a
considerable concentration of lesson time,
with at least four hours of lessons every day.
The purpose of this is to prevent students
from forgetting the chief danger when
learning a foreign language.
There are two main ways of accelerating
the teaching of foreign languages. The first
is to ensure that the content, methods,
organization and equipment used
correspond exactly with the objectives being
pursued. The second way is to exploit the
students' character to the full by introducing
personalized teaching. These two
approaches are closely related, but each has
its own peculiarities and sphere of
application, the first being within the
framework of traditional education, the
second being the use of new methods with
which we are concerned here.
Experiments have been made with
teaching during natural sleep, "hyp-
nopaedia", or in conditions of rhythmic
sleep induced by the use of a special ap¬
paratus, "rhythmopaedia", and with the im¬
parting of information to persons in a state
of relaxation, "relaxopaedia".
The method used most widely during the
past few years has been "suggestopaedia",
which exploits the functional reserves of the
brain by the use of suggestion, i.e. by the
use of composite suggestive action on the
student's personality.
Research on these methods is based on
observation of the fact that memorization is
quicker and easier when active control is
relaxed and when the role of the un¬
conscious processes in higher nervous ac-k
tivity is enhanced. }
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
< This research has shown that teaching by
hypnopaedic methods is two to two-and-a-
half times more effective than ordinary
methods. The process of memorization
comprises ordinary classroom lessons with a
teacher (forty-five minutes); listening to a
reading of the study programme and
repeating it out loud in bed, before going to
sleep (fifteen minutes); hearing the pro¬
gramme, played more and more softly, for
fifty-five minutes after falling asleep; hearing
it again, starting softly and growing increas¬
ingly louder, for twenty to thirty minutes
before waking up. The whole hypnopaedic
teaching programme was composed of
thirty-nine teaching units. As a result of this
course, 2,500 words, combinations of words
and basic models were assimilated.
A variant of hypnopaedia is
rhythmopaedia. A state of sleep is induced
in the student with the aid of an electro-
hypnosis apparatus which produces a
monotonous, rhythmic effect on the ner¬
vous system. The student is then fed with
information. It is possible, by varying the
frequency of the light and sound impulses,
to maintain in the student the depth and in¬
tensity of hypnotic inhibition most suitable
for the imparting of new
information.
Teaching during sleep has numerous ad¬
vocates, but even more numerous op¬
ponents. Doubts are expressed about the ef¬
fects that teaching in these conditions may
have'. But since hypnopaedia is used in con¬
junction with other teaching methods, and
the students always have a very strong
motivation for learning, it is impossible to
isolate the effect of the influence on the
student while asleep. Application of hyp¬
nopaedic methods presupposes special con¬
ditions, specially equipped premises, and a
special régime for those being taught.
But the most important objections come
from doctors, who maintain that tampering
with the sleep mechanism may disturb it and
provoke nervous disorders. On this account,
hypnopaedia has not been widely practised,
although research in this field has given
results that are certainly interesting from the
point of view of the possible intensification
of teaching.
Of greater popularity in the USSR is the
notion of teaching in a state of relaxa¬
tion and physical relaxation induc¬
ed by suggestion. Observations and ex¬
periments have established that memoriza¬
tion is easier in this state than in ordinary
conditions.
Through muscular relaxation and
autogenous training, students attain a state
of physical and mental calm in which they
are conscious of the weight and warmth of
the right arm. In this state, sensory percep¬
tion of factors extraneous to the information
presented is reduced, the brain is freed of
external inhibiting processes, attention
becomes more selective, and concentrates
wholly on the information presented.
Relaxopaedia is not regarded as a
separate method of teaching but rather as a
useful part of the normal teaching process
which speeds the assimilation of language
material and leaves more time free for
creative language-learning activities.
The average number of words students
are able to assimilate in the course of one
lesson is fifty to sixty. Data available show
that the best ratio of relaxopaedic to or¬
dinary teaching sessions is one to five.
A special method for feeding information
into the memory unconsciously has been
devised by Professor B. I. Khachapuridze, in
Tbilisi. By means of a special disc with a slot
in it, placed in front of the lens of a projec¬
tor, and rotating at a speed of seventy to
ninety revolutions per minute, the list of
words to be learned is shown on the screen.
The students are familiar with the words
and their translation, since they have already
been projected on to the screen in the or¬
dinary way, and read out by an announcer.
The students repeat these twice, with their
translation, after the announcer, and the
teacher explains any special points to be
noted about individual words. The list con¬
tains about thirty words.
The rapid rotation of the disc makes it im¬
possible to read these words when they ap¬
pear a second time on the screen, but the ef¬
fect of such a repetition is nevertheless very
considerable since memorization by
students using this method is, on average,
42 per cent better than with the ordinary
method only.
The term "accelerated teaching
methods"most frequently refers to the in¬
tensification of teaching through the use of
different kinds and forms of sug-
gestopaedia. Whatever differences there are
in the approaches adopted, they are all bas¬
ed on the idea of influencing students by
New techniques for speeding up language learning are used in this language lab at the
Maurice Thorez State Foreign Language Institute in Moscow. A dozen European languages
are taught at the Institute.
Photo L Pakhomova © APN, Paris
/
'M
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
This young student from
Uzun-Agach in Soviet
Kazakhstan is using a tape-
recorder to help improve her
English accent.
suggestion, evolved by a Bulgarian scientist,
Georgi Lozanov, director of the Scientific
Research Institute of Suggestology.
Suggestology is based on the principles of
joy and relaxation, and of the unity of the
"conscious and the unconscious". A special
atmosphere is created in the lessons a
climate of trust and joy which produces a
desire to learn and confidence in one's abili¬
ty. This is achieved by constant praise and
encouragement from the teacher, by the
choice of psychologically compatible work¬
ing pairs, and by informal classroom
arrangement.
The effect of suggestopaedic teaching
methods is that the learning situation ap¬
proximates to a very great extent to a non-
academic situation, and psychological bar¬
riers hindering natural behaviour are
eliminated. The formerly unused memory
capacity of a student is brought into play
and his mind and feelings are laid wide open
to the influence of the teaching with a clari¬
ty, trust and interest characteristic of
childhood. The adult stops feeling embar¬
rassed and willingly assumes the role pro¬
posed, naturally and unselfconsciously per¬
forming a large number of linguistic and
other exercises, and using new speech units
as freely as though he had been familiar with
them all his life.
However, the methodological assump¬
tions of suggestopaedia do not by any
means all find support. There is also
criticism of the results obtained with this
form of teaching. It is said that it leads to
ungrammatical use of language, that
students do not learn how to form new
sentences independently, and that they can¬
not read anything that they have not en¬
countered in oral practice.
To acquire these abilities, the very con¬
siderable emphasis on language mastery,
i.e. knowing the rules for using various
models in the language, is not enough-
Soviet educationalists note that language
skills are being formed with insufficient
linguistic experience and with no out-of-
class work at all, which means the pupil
does no independent work on the language.
The changes and additions being made by
Soviet educationalists to the sug¬
gestopaedic teaching system are designed
to eliminate these defects. Teachers and
theoreticians are trying to find a way of
combining, in accelerated courses, the living
language, games and music with the
rudiments of linguistics, without which
mastery of any language is inconceivable.
An accelerated language course may be
complete in itself or it may constitute a par¬
ticular stage in the process of learning a
foreign language. As complete cycles there
are, for instance, ten-month courses (full-
time) and two-year courses (part-time), for
qualified specialists.
These courses intensify the learning pro¬
cess by means of improved instruction by
using the best modern methods for the
teaching of foreign languages. Teaching
methods are selected with an eye to the
special characteristics of adult students,
who want to know the reason for everything
and are averse to purely mechanical work.
A short course on comparative Russian-
English grammar has thus been recently in¬
troduced for beginners in some institutions
(e.g. in the department for technical
students at the Maurice Thorez Moscow
State Foreign Language Institute). It is also
compulsory to include in the syllabus, either
at the beginning or at the end, a short stage
using suggestopaedic methods. This,
however, is replaced in some instances by
the use of relaxopaedic or rhythmopaedic
methods.
If suggestopaedic methods are used as an
independent course of study, it is either as
an introduction to independent language
work, enabling students to have confidence
in their own ability and to believe that
positive results are attainable, or as a form
of advanced training.
In the case of scientific workers, use is
made of what is known as total
immersion nine-day courses of eight to ten
hours of classes per day. These are designed
to brush up people's knowledge of a
language before setting off to a conference,
for instance; to demonstrate their ability to
use, in discussion, vocabulary accumulated
in the process of reading; or to give them an
oral foundation for the further study of a
foreign language.
The part played by accelerated teaching
methods should not, however, be thought
of as confined only to the contribution they
can make to the relatively small number of
people attending courses. The development
of these methods contributes to the
improvement of foreign-language teaching
as a whole.
This should take place within the context
of further improvements in the planning
system and in even fuller use of the potential
in higher education institutions in which, in
the Soviet Union, almost half of our
scientific specialists (doctors and candidates
for doctorates) are today concentrated.
MIRA VAISBURD, of the USSR, is Senior
Scientific Worker of the Institute of Scientific
Research on the Content and Methods of Educa¬
tion of the USSR Academy of Pedagogical
Sciences. The author gave a more extensive
treatment of the subject of this article in a study
published in Unesco's quarterly review of educa¬
tion Prospects (Vol. X, No. 3).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
.jtnu'n
WHMH
The resurgence of sail
This photo of the Finnish vessel
Moshulu, taken shortly before World
War II, shows sail in all its billowing
splendour.
by Arthur Gillette
IN August 1980, a Japanese shipbuilding
company, one of the world's biggest,
launched a 66-metre-long craft equipped
with a diesel engine and... two rigid rec¬
tangular sails. This odd-looking vessel, the
Shin Aitoku Maru, followed a smaller ex¬
perimental prototype of a sail-assisted
motorized ship, the 77-ton Daioh, which had
been launched by the same firm three years
before.
Why should nautical engineers in one of
the world's most technologically advanced
countries have suddenly become interested
in sail? The answer lies in soaring fuel costs
which, for motorized commercial craft, rose
fourfold between 1967 and 1978. As a result,
hard-headed businessmen who not so long
ago would have scoffed at the idea of wind-
propelled cargo ships and tankers are now
taking a hard look at the possible contribu¬
tion that some form of the sailing ship could
make to solving the energy problem.
Contrary to a widespread popular impres¬
sion today, much of the world's maritime
commerce was still being carried on wholly
or partly by sail even after World War II.
Lighters sailed cargoes up and down the
Ligurian coast of Italy until 1949, and the
28
maone familiarly known are la barca
bestia was still working the Gulf of Lions,
and particularly the Barcelona-Balearics
route, in 1952. The lumber trade along the
east coast of the United States and Canada
was, until World War II, handled in good
part by sailing ships.
The Soviet schoolships Sedov and
Kruzenshtern once brought phosphate back
from Chile. Many other bulk cargoes were
borne along the world's trade wind routes
by sail until relatively recently, and
sometimes quite rapidly. In the annual
"grain races" from Australia to the U.K.,
which ended shortly before the outbreak of
World War II, the first tall ships to arrive
reaped the benefits of a seller's market.
The period following that conflict witness¬
ed the decline and, ultimately, the demise of
sail power on virtually all major sea trade
routes, and most minor ones as well.
Unleashed by the war, a sudden and inten¬
sive burst of technology research and
development (that produced radar, among
other things) could not but benefit
mechanized shipping in the post-war era.
Motorized shipping also responded better
than sail, in a period of increasingly com
plex, voluminous and rapid commerce, to
demands for quick and dependable
transport. Then, too, the mood and move¬
ment for social reform that swept most in¬
dustrialized countries immediately after the
defeat of Fascism made the long hours and
rigorous working conditions on sailing craft
unacceptable in comparison to the relatively
easier lot of crews on motor vessels.
Finally, the shift from labour-intensive to
capital-intensive maritime transport was
made inevitable, in the late 1940s and 1950s,
by the existence of an abundant and ap¬
parently inexhaustible supply of propellant
over whose production and distribution the
industrialized countries had nearly total con¬
trol: fuel oil. The shift to motor power was
inevitable then. But was it definitive?
Even as fuel-propelled vessels came to
dominate maritime trade routes almost ex¬
clusively in the 1950s and 1960s, in several
parts of the world and particularly in
developing countries sail power persisted.
It successfully resisted, and in some cases
even overcame, incursions from fuel propul¬
sion. Although little-known outside their
countries and zones of use, commercial
craft continue today that rely on sail alone.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
©
or on sail in tandem with motor, or as an
auxiliary to fuel power.
Feloukas sail the Nile as they have for cen¬
turies, with placid grace; and on the other
side of the world, in the West Indies, gom¬
mier canoes that look like hybrids of Carib
Indian dugouts and Newfoundland dories
still scuttle in and out of the bays of St.
Lucia under sail, being the main means of
locomotion of that island's fishermen. It is
worth noting and the point has validity
well beyond the West Indies that while St.
Lucia's sailing gommiers are occasionally
dangerous and require often backbreaking
laboujT, they have at least not disturbed the
coastal bio-system.
Moving further to sea, indeed out of sight
of land, sailing commercial vessels are still
found in several parts of the Third World.
Although not often now used entirely alone,
sail remains a source of at least auxiliary
power for copra and trading schooners in
the South Pacific, for example. The Tiare
Taporo, one of the oldest and best known of
the trading schooners of the region, boasted
thirty years of sailing service to French
Polynesia, the Cook Islands and New
Hebrides when a cyclone wrecked her in
1968, and the ketch Hawk worked the Belep
Islands, north of New Caledonia, until
recently.
A similar species of inter-island schooner
still accounts for the lion's share of seaborne
freight and passenger transport up and
down the Caribbean's necklace-like archi¬
pelago. These boats are still, stubbornly,
one of the Lesser Antilles' cheapest and
most popular ways of moving goods and
people.
Much the same may be said of Indian
Ocean dhows. Figurative descendants of
the craft with which, according to the Old
Testament, the Queen of Sheba and King
Solomon explored these coasts, the East
African version of the dhow owes less to
myth than to long and solid Arabian sea¬
going experience.
Heritage aside, dhows are still the main
vehicles for ocean-going commerce along
the coasts of Somalia, Kenya and Tanzania,
and farther afield, too, since larger dhows of
many nationalities follow the Indian Ocean
monsoon winds in a generally circular route
from Africa to India and Pakistan and back.
Their cargoes include an almost bewildering
variety of goods, from salt, dates and
mangrove boroti poles to coffee, tea, cop¬
per pots and trays, studded coffers, and tiles
brought from India to Africa.
"Our boats, working under sail, will not
die", Captain Omar Ahmed told me on the
dhow beach near Nyali Bridge at Mombasa.
One reason is, simply, that they are good
business. It takes one and one-half days to
travel from Mombasa northward to the
dhow base at Lamu by bus over bad roads,
and the trip costs 120 Kenyan shillings.
When the monsoon is blowing (admittedly
not year-round) the same trip is made under
sail by Lamu's own jahazi dhows in two days
for 65 shillings.
Other reasons, cultural more than mer¬
cantile, contribute to the dhows' persistence
as a way of life perhaps as much as a mode
of commerce. The boats themselves are lov¬
ingly and ritually decorated, boasting col¬
ourful paintwork and, often, intricate carv¬
ing at the bows and around the poop.
Sailmaking is an honour, sailors and
passersby considering it a favour to be
allowed to assist the master sailmaker. Sing¬
ing traditional chanties and dancing, accom
panied by drums and pipes, are favourite
pastimes of crewmen onboard and ashore,
while the drums also encourage them as
rhythmic music did European seamen not so
long agowhen hauling up anchor or sail.
Probably the most striking example of
modern-day sail- powered maritime commer¬
cial sea-going vessels are the Makassar
schooners found in Indonesia. Numbering
something on the order of 10,000 and ap¬
parently now growing after a period of
relative eclipse, these 15- to 30-metre sailing
vessels carry, each, up to 500 cubic metres
of cargo ranging from the mundane to the
exotic: cattle, soybeans, tamarind, bicycles,
fill dirt, a few passengers, and, mainly,
timber. In 1972, they accounted for approx¬
imately three-quarters of all domestic timber
cargoes arriving in Java.
Like a well-disciplined ballet corps, they
scurry toward Jakarta and other ports of
Western Indonesia when April signals the
onset of five months' east monsoon, only to
flutter back as far as Irian Jaya with the west
monsoon, which whistles out of the Malac¬
ca Straits from December to March. During
the "intermissions", the two annual periods
of slack wind, they shelter "offstage" (in
home port, if they can) to refit. For non¬
urgent cargo, these vessels have undeniable
advantages in a non-industrial country like
Indonesia. For one thing, they rely solely on
locally available resources for construction
and operation.
Summing up the main features of today's
commercial vessels that go partly or wholly
under sail, it is clear that they are not exempt
from drawbacks. First, they are slow. Gone
are the days when, between the World
Wars, the four-masted German barks Priwall
and Padua could hit peak speeds of over 14
CONTINUED PAGE 32
The 66-metre-long Shin Aitoku Maru, claimed to be the world's first
tanker-cargo ship equipped with auxiliary sails to save fuel, being tested
in the Japan Sea during August 1980.
-n.
= ii w
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ofgid s31' Flexible triangular
sail \
-\-
A windship revolution?
It would have been unimaginable a few years ago, but today
several industrialized countries faced with soaring marine fuel
costs are seriously thinking of reintroducing the commercial
sailing ship, at least in some form. Engineers have studied and
learned from a wide range of sail rigs and configurations, from
those of the high-speed tea clippers of the last century to those
of Asiatic junks (see back cover) and East African dhows. Highly
competitive yacht races in recent years have also spurred the
application of scientific research to the study of wind propulsion,
and as a result the use of sail has become an exact science. The
Clifton Flasher (opposite page below), which held the world
speed record for her sail area class for six years. Is equipped with
rigid sails, whose success in catamaran racing has suggested
that they may rival soft sails in commercial ship propulsion.
But a possible new generation of commercial sailing ships will
look very different from the windjammers of the past and the
thoroughbred racers of the present. Experiments in Japan have
shown that a big cargo ship driven solely by wind would be
uneconomical, and the new craft coming off the drawing board
tend to be engine-sail hybrids with the sails as an auxiliary form
30
of propulsion. The goal is fuel economy rather than speed at any
price, with other "musts" including easy cargo handling and
maintenance, and labour-saving facilities.
Japan is one of the countries in the forefront of windship
research. Photo above shows the Daioh, an experimental "mini-
tanker" which during sea trials In 1979 proved capable of
reducing fuel consumption by a useful 10 per cent. The Daioh is
equipped with three types of sail (shown in drawings above
photo): one rigid, one flexible, one part rigid and part flexible.
Each is devised to be responsive to different wind conditions.
Another idea of the Daioh's designers: a shipboard computer to
regulate engine output in relation to wind speed. Lessons learned
from the Daioh influenced the design of a bigger wind-assisted
tanker, the Shin Aitoku Maru (see photo previous page).
Photo opposite page above shows the Buckau, an experimental
ship of the 1920s fitted with the rotor system invented by the
German engineer Anton Flettner. The rotor is not a pure wind
propulsion system, as the propulsive force is generated by the
powered rotation of vertical cylinders in the airstream. The
system was operated at sea, including an Atlantic crossing.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Wind patterns throughout the world, like the requirements of
each maritime trade and cargo, are so different that windship
designs may also vary widely according to the route to be sailed,
the ports to be visited, and the commodities to be carried.
Pyramid-rig catamaran (model above) has been designed for a
short-haul route where economy depends primarily on rapid
stowing and unstowing of the sails. The area of sails is varied by
rotating them around their stays. Model, above right shows one
of three French fishing boats now under construction at Lorlent
in Brittany. The main engine will only be used to enter or leave
port, or in totally windless conditions.
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 29
knots, and maintain them for a 24-hour
period (albeit in ballast), while the best day's
run for their sister ship Pamir, when loaded,
was 321 miles, at an average of 13.4 knots.
The Makassar schooners, Indian Ocean
dhows and West Indian schooners probably
seldom average more than four or five
knots a stiff human walking pace, but
three or four times slower than a motor-
powered freighter or tanker.
Then, too, and although there do not
seem to be comprehensive and reliable
statistics on the question, sailing craft may
well be more dangerous than motorized
vessels. Generally small and of rudimentary
construction, they are vulnerable to tides,
storms and that old sailor's nightmare, the
sudden onshore squall.
Their very vulnerability also makes sailing
vessels less dependable. They cannot be
counted on to arrive or depart according to
strict schedules and sometimes have to skip
temporarily unapproachable ports. At times,
such as the slack seasons between mon¬
soons and trade-winds, their sails are of no
use at all.
Finally, the labour-intensive handling of
sail craft is ultimately unacceptable, in
human terms, for sailors and stevedores
alike.
Each of sail power's disadvantages does,
however, appear to have a reverse, positive
32
side. Are the boats slow? Well, not all
cargoes are urgent and shippers continue to
rely contentedly on sail for certain bulky
loads that need only reach their destination
in a matter of weeks or even months, rather
than days. While sailing craft may also be
more vulnerable to danger than motor
vessels, they are concomitantly, because of
their size and component materials, pro¬
bably more susceptible to jury-rigged do-it-
yourself repairs.
The positive side of sailing vessels'
unreliability is their flexibility. Paragons of
tramp shipping, many do not hesitate to
alter their itineraries at will, calling at
unscheduled ports if a cargo or passengers,
that might otherwise not have travelled, are
found to be waiting there.
Similarly, the labour-intensive nature of
sail transport offers shippers the assurance
that certain fragile cargoes will receive in¬
dividual attention with, as a result, minimal
breakage. Tiles, glassware and even elec¬
tronic parts that, had they been loaded by
modern crane-and-sling might well have
been smashed, have been safely carried by
ocean-going dhows.
It may be said, too, that such craft pro¬
vide more employment per cubic metre of
freight or per head of passenger transported
than their motorized counterparts, although
this argument should never be used to
legitimize all-too-often unacceptable work¬
ing conditions and wages.
On the whole, it must be admitted that
the advantages of traditional forms of sea
transport powered wholly or partly by sail do
not decisively outweigh their drawbacks.
Nevertheless, the stubborn survival of tradi¬
tional sail as a viable commercial proposition
is, in itself, an invitation to rethink modern
shipping an invitation made the more
pressing by the rising costs of motorized
vessels.
These include direct economic costs (fuel,
construction, labour) but also what might be
termed bio-social costs. As anyone who has
crossed the Atlantic in a small sailboat can
testify, the trade-wind route from the
Canary Islands to Barbados is littered with
oil spill, fuel drums, plastics of all sorts and
other kinds of pollution that stretch in an
almost unbroken path of industrial civiliza¬
tion's cast-off trash almost three thousand
miles long. In fact, and without romanticiz¬
ing its potential, sail power may offer some
pointers for the development of an alter¬
native maritime technology that has lower
costs than modern shipping in economic,
social and, perhaps, cultural terms.
A growing number of firms and govern¬
ments are today devoting serious study and
experimentation to the windship alternative.
A Californian concern has prepared a design
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
for a 4,500 deadweight ton commercial
schooner while groups in Britain are working
on a variety of approaches that range from a
fairly classical square rig and a. semi-rigid
adaptation of catamaran sails (originally us¬
ed by Sri Lankan fishermen, but now
widespread among yachtsmen) to a "rotor
sail" system and even such exotic notions as
using huge kites to drag freighters.
In France, a group of specialists have
come up with a project for building three
19.30 metre multi-purpose ocean-going sail¬
ing fishing boats whose auxiliary engines
would, it is claimed, use between 20 and 25
per cent of the fuel consumed by similar
craftf today that rely solely on motors. The
boats should be launched in the next few
months.
A central concern of experimenters is to
ensure that labour on board possible future
sailing craft would not be as backbreaking
as it was on traditional sailing vessels. At¬
tention is, for instance, being given to the
idea of computerizing sail mansuvres.
A British firm has developed a design for a
137-metre sailing freighter able to carry full
sail in a beam wind of up to 35 knots, thus
obviating the need for difficult and potential¬
ly dangerous deckside work by crewmen.
The design also features heavy-duty win¬
ches to reduce physical labour. In more
general, cultural, terms, some specialists
feel that far from enslaving crewmen, a
return to sail could be much more
stimulating than life at sea is today, when
work on, say, a huge tanker has the same
uninteresting rote character as does labour
on an automobile assembly line.
But possibly the most advanced nation
now in the windship field is Japan. It is
calculated that the Shin Aitoku Maru uses
only half as much fuel as a conventional
ship. However, only 10 per cent of the sav¬
ing is due to the sails; the rest is due to other
features of the design and equipment.
"Spectacular though the reintroduction of
sails may have been", the engineers point
out, "the engine is, and will remain, the
principal means of propulsion". Never¬
theless, partisans and opponents of wind-
ship alike cannot but appreciate the nice
irony of the fact that the wind-assisted Shin
Aitoku Maru is... an oil tanker!
Two graceful eastern
Javanese fishing
boats small cousins
of the "Makassar
schooners" which ply
through the
Indonesian
archipelago carrying
an immense variety of
cargoes.
ARTHUR GILLETTE, of the United States, is a
staff member of Unesco's sector of Social
Sciences and their Applications. He has worked
as a deck-hand on sail-powered fishing boats in
the Bahamas, and in 1969 crossed the Atlantic on
a 7.6-metre cutter.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
National Languages and Teacher
Training in Africa, by Joseph Poth. A
methodological guide for the use of teacher
training institutes. 51 pp., 1980 (8F).
Education in the Arab States in the
light of the Abu Dhabi Conference, by
Abdelhadi Tazi. Based largely on working
documents and the final report of the Confer-
rence held in Abu Dhabi in November 1977,
the purpose of which was to analyze the
educational situation in the Arab States,
review trends which had appeared since
1970, formulate strategies for the develop¬
ment of education, and devise a framework
for regional and international co-operation.
81 pp., 1980 (12 F).
The Child's First Learning Environ¬
ment. Selected readings in home
economics. Prepared with the co-operation
of the Center for the Family of the American
Home Economics Association. 67 pp., 1980
(12F).
Advances in the Continuing Educa¬
tion of Engineers, by Niels Krebs Ovesen.
(No. 6 in Unesco's "Studies in Engineering
Education" series). 199 pp., 1980 (36 F).
Thinking and Doing. Youth and a new
international economic order, by Barbara
Brühl Day. A synthesis of a series of activities
undertaken by young people in 1977-78, with
the assistance of Unesco. 96 pp., 1980
(20 F).
Communication Planning for
Development: an Operational Frame¬
work, by Alan Hancock. (No. 2 in Unesco's
"Monographs on Communication Planning"
series). 198 pp. 1980 (40 F).
1980-2000: The School Tomorrow is the
theme of the latest issue of Unesco's interna¬
tional quarterly review of education Pro¬
spects (Vol. X, No. 4 1980). Single issue,
16 F; Annual subscription, 56 F.
OTHER BOOKS RECEIVED
The War. Peace Film Guide, by John
Dowling. Describes many of the best films
concerned with war, the arms race and
related themes, provides the necessary infor¬
mation for obtaining them. For people who
are concerned with ending war and wish to
use films to stimulate discussions. World
Without War Publications, 67 E. Madison,
Suite 1417, Chicago, Illinois 60603. 1980 (3rd
revised and expanded edition) 188 pp. ($5).
Brain of the Firm, by Stafford Beer. A
new and expanded edition of a work in which
the author, a pioneer of managerial
cybernetics, develops an account of the firm
based on insights derived from study of the
human nervous system. John Wiley and
Sons Ltd., Chichester, U.K., 1981. 417 pp.
(£11.50/$34.50).
Letters to the editor
CORRECTION
On page 30 of the August 1980 issue of
the Unesco Courier ("Nature and Culture:
The Human Heritage"), the geographical
silhouette which served to indicate the loca¬
tion of Aachen Cathedral in the Federal
Republic of Germany gave, owing to its
reduced scale, the inaccurate impression of
an encroachment onto the territory of the
German Democratic Republic.
34
A CRITICAL EYE ON PICASSO
Sir,
Your Picasso issue (December 1980) is
open to very serious criticism. In it you pre¬
sent the views of museum curators,
historians, writers and other personalities. I
protest against this cultural Diktat! Painting
is a social phenomenon. It is offered to the
public, not imposed on it.
Let me describe some of my impressions,
those of an ordinary person, as I read the
issue.
What strikes the reader is the extreme
ugliness of some of the portraits, such as
the Weeping Woman on page 48. Someone
should have been given the opportunity to
denounce such hideousness. And someone
should have been allowed to criticize the
lamentable mediocrity of the fresco at
Unesco Headquarters in Paris (page 43).
Picasso was a prodigious iconoclast who
brilliantly denuded surfaces and volumes,
strewing his canvases with twitching
geometrical forms and mutilated faces. To
my mind this is not good enough. It makes
one think of a researcher who throughout
his life amasses designs and calculations
which never actually lead to a discovery.
Guernica is typically Picassian bric-à-brac!
Full of violence and demolition but totally
devoid of feeling and fraternity!
On page 32 you show a sequence of il¬
lustrations entitled "The Metamorphosis of
a Bull"?, which shows the different "states"
of a Picasso engraving. The wretched beast
is hacked, slashed and chopped until it ends
up as a ridiculous wire skeleton. These il¬
lustrations are a comic strip which reveals a
failure on the part of Picasso, the in¬
defatigable and cruel bullfighter who is
capable of mutilating and killing but not of
creating.
Painting incapable of producing master¬
pieces is painting which has lost its univer¬
salist vocation. Fortunately, Picasso also
produced humorous works, such as those
depicting Don Quixote and the bullfights
which decorate some of his ceramic plates.
In my opinion this is the best Picasso, by far.
J.M. Geoffroy
Malzeville, France
Sir,
I am very far from sharing the desire, ex¬
pressed by Unesco's Member States, to
honour a painter such as Picasso (December
1 980 issue) . To my mind, his work is the very
negation of painting! Never shall I purchase
a canvas by this man who loved to depict
the human face asymmetrically or even
grotesquely. You consider him to be a
painter of genius. In this case where do you
rank Rembrandt?
You publish a photo of a masterpiece of
sculpture created by Picasso: an old leather
saddle and a pair of handlebars which are
supposed to evoke the head of a bull!
I am convinced that, despite the official
tribute set forth in 25 languages, common
sense will one day prevail.
Robert Neuville
Château d'Etoges, France
Save the whale
This letter bearing over a hundred
signatures has been sent to us by children of
the Maurice-Alice II school in Cannes
(France).
It reads: "To you, ladies and gentlemen,
who undertake the arduous task of protec¬
ting whales, the Maurice-Alice school of the
city of Cannes offers its support in this
struggle against the massacre perpetrated
by irresponsible countries."
JU¿*'\. din e^~i.int»,t ÍU.-Í«. i_t,_w. iltw¿. ta. .m*i .it. t-.ttmu Ojjfwj. **
4, , .-. ti-j-vt^.
<r;
Pai-r -s
£^~\*y.
; r. ' lF
y
AjU.*... -K..I
OMb .-'/>*' "" -1^=^ i
4
./,
>fcjU*v».U*.v
ir'fi fe
.y
¡A J- -
^ r ¿S*
'-ryujjk.T>^ íXjr¿v~
tWÁ
jO?y,
v7
KEEP IT UP!
Sir,
It is encouraging to see that a thirteen-
year-old ("Letters to the Editor", September
1980) reads the Unesco Courier, and I hope
he will continue.
Please, however, keep the Courier at its
present intellectual level ! Today we have
too many things "written down", and need
publications to challenge all of us, young
and less young, to stretch our minds and
grow. Over the years in which I have been
reading the Courier, I have found it clearly
written and well worth any struggle to
understand articles beyond my former com¬
prehension.
May I add a word of special commenda¬
tion for the September 1980 issue on disar¬
mament education.
Ruth A. Leppman
South Burlington
Vermont (USA)
£ a:
£í
lu r^
O
?°
< lO
cc r-
Li- ,
Z <p
I s
A FAREWELL TO ARMS
Sir,
As a twelve-year-old high school student,
I should like to congratulate you on your
September 1980 number on disarmament
education. I should never have thought it
possible that a country could live without an
army. And yet Costa Rica does so. Costa
Rica's example should be followed by all
those who defend the cause of peace and
human rights.
Helga Camalon
Chalabre, France
u. ID
. o
"1
s|
U
W uj
ë ce
§§
8°
go
x 1
%o
ce û_
os
oo
tru
<o
oo
oc I
m o-
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Towards a new
international
economic order
\l .!i.iMinn'd Bedjaoui
"...an exciting and convincing account of why international
law must be drastically reshaped to serve the altered
character of international life. This wonderful book is by far
the best available statement of a Third World position, at
once eloquent and scholarly". This is how Professor Richard
Falk of Princeton University has described Dr. Bedjaoui's
important study Towards a New International Economic Order.
The first in a new Unesco series, "New Challenges to
International Law", the book outlines "the international order
of poverty and the poverty of the international order" that
our world has brought into being, and considers what
"international development law and the development of
international law" could be.
Among the major questions analyzed by Dr. Bedjaoui :
What is meant by the "new international economic order"?
How did the concept come into being?
What is the significance of the current crisis?
What ways and means exist for establishing the new order?
Is the adaptation of the United Nations a necessary and
sufficient condition for the establishment of this new
order?
The author. Dr. Mohammed Bedjaoui, is currently Algerian
Ambassador to the United Nations and a member of the UN's
Committee on International Law.
287pages 38 French francs
Available from national distributors of Unesco publications throughout the
world; co-published in the United States with Holmes and Meier, New York.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications- Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd P 0
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals. Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept , P O Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only NV Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen, French edition and general Unesco publications
agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corporation No 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co Ltd , 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7 CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0 Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA - S N.T L , Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicm literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only Alfa Verlag Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR - DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirja¬
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10 - FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, C.C P.
12598-48 - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions).
Mr. H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse
57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publications
Karger Verlag, Germermg/Munchen For scientific maps only
Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. - GHANA. Pres¬
byterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P 0. Box 195, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P O Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P O Box 1, Legon
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyves-
bolt, Václ u. 22, Budapest V, A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Nép-
koztarsaság utja 16, Budapest VI ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book Et Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016, Scmdia House, New Delhi; Publi¬
cations Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 511
C-Wing, Shastn Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata III,
Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta;
Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian
Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No 300, B P.
1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid
Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of
Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. ABC. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv 61000 JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores
Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. - JAPAN. Eas¬
tern Book Service Inc., Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Tora¬
nomon 3-Chome, Mmato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East Afri¬
can Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942,
Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P 0. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Book¬
shops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P O. Box 34-35, Tri¬
poli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11 MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHER¬
LANDS. For the "Unesco Koener" Dutch edition only. Syste¬
men Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for
all Unesco publications* N V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout,
9, The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-
Eddme N V, P O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government Books¬
hops at: Rutland Street, P.O Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford
Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. - NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P 0 286, The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University
Bookshop of Lagos,The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1 Fpr Unesco
Courier only A S Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6
- PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P 0 Box No. 729, Lahore 3" - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P 0. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P O Box 131, Mahé. -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19 - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P O Box 951,
Mogadiscio SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty ) Ltd , Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only Central News agency, P O Box 1033, Johannesburg
-SRI LANKA Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P 0 B 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN Al Bashir
Bookshop, PO Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B C E Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications'
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, P.O B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P O Box 402, Bangkok- Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnem Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A S , Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P 0. Box 145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P O
Box 569, London, S E.I., and Govt Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bnstol.-UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N Y 10010 - U.S.S R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade, Drzavna Zalozba
Slovénie, Tltova C 25, P O B 50-1, Ljubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i
Full sail ahead!
The graceful ribbed sails of a wooden junk plying through Hong
Kong harbour contrast sharply with the austere lines of a
modern, oil-powered vessel. Junks have been used for many cen¬
turies by the Chinese and other Far Eastern peoples to carry
passengers and freight. Today, faced with soaring fuel costs, in¬
dustrialized countries are looking hard at the possibility of re¬
introducing some form of sail-power to help solve the energy
problem. New craft are being designed to integrate ancient
maritime traditions with the latest labour-saving aids and com¬
puterized navigational equipment.
Photo Emmanuel Guillou © Atlas Photo, Paris
]]>
</page>
</document>
