<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074795eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco (JoUFÍCF A window
open on the world
w
$
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
1
	
* ÛÊy
,x 2L
A
9
4
1
% 1
1
111*-
ri
f w f' jKJKfyPJ
H /
'. táEZ^^ñ
i yr>^ß % H >-. »v\l\
|rywñf T w 1 A\ \a \
I Ir MmW r > \ ** * - \
1 1* Jia A 4 î \
[J i^¡ p| \
1 1 *'-**!mT^ < m \
J
m\ ifr mIII til
i
m
mm y m
^J A
Ë
Er-. A v
& ^B" «SIM flHv
¿ ^H ¿-J| HL L
B Hé i
Ft
^vf »*
M V« $* V 11
^if^ ¿tf^"
/
/* ' vi w
r A
MAIW wBPi' '
t m* ' ; , T^. »^fc^'
j
w M
m V mWm
JA
p
. v
* r
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Sweden
Our Lady of Löderup
The art of stone carving reached a high level in twelfth-century Scania (southern Sweden), whose country
churches are noted for their Romanesque fonts, richly decorated with plant motifs and scenes from the Bible
and the lives of Saints. Shown here is the head of the Virgin Mary, a detail from a font in the church at
Löderup, southeast of Lund. It was carved by an anonymous artist who has been called the "Magister
Majestatis" (Master of Majesty). The almond eyes and elongated face are distinctive features of his work.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco 0)11110"
OCTOBER 1978 31st YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 19 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's Issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when ¡t is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UN ESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is Indexed monthly In the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambu!)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher ,
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey I
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin j
All correspondence should be addressed j
, to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris. !
page
HUMAN RIGHTS
A new school of law and learning
by Karel Vasak
7 TWENTY QUESTIONS
Human rights and the international community
by Leah Levin
11 UNESCO AND RESPECT FOR HUMAN RIGHTS
12 EDUCATION FOR DISARMAMENT
'Freedom from fear ¡s a fundamental human right'
by Swadesh Rana
14 FRANCISCO GOYA
An art that defied the powers of darkness
by Santiago Amón
20 A VOICE FROM THE THIRD WORLD
by Radhika Coomaraswamy
23 THE RIGHT TO BE INFORMED
by Adam Lopatka
25 A CHALLENGE FOR THE UNIVERSITIES
by Thomas Buergenthal
29 THE DOCTORS' DILEMMA
by Louis Corte
30 CHERNYSHEVSKY
A pioneer of social reform
by Eduard Dnieprov
31 UNESCO : PUBLISHER TO THE WORLD
In 32 years, 7,000 titles In 70 languages
by Edward Wegman
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
SWEDEN: Our Lady of Löderup
-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Photo © Bruno Jarret, Musée Rodin, Pans
Cover
To mark the 30th anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, this Issue of
the Unesco Courier is devoted to the
problems of the teaching of human rights
those inherent rights due to man simply in
virtue of his humanity. Our cover shows a
detail of two figures from Auguste Rodin's
famous sculpture The Burghers of Calais,
which records a dramatic incident of the
Hundred Years War. In 1347, the French port
of Calais surrendered to Edward III, king of
England, after a year-long siege. Six leading
citizens offered their lives to the king in the
hope of saving their fellow-citizens. Their
lives were spared on the intercession of
Edward's queen, Philippa de Hainaut.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Human Rights
A new school of law and learning
by Karel Vasak
'To teach respect for human
rights, both our own rights and
the rights of others, and to have
the courage to uphold them
even in the most difficult
circumstances is the major
imperative of our times,"
declared Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, Director-General of
Unesco, speaking at the opening
of the International Congress on
human rights education. The
Congress, organized by Unesco
at the invitation of the Austrian
Government, was held in Vienna
last September.
Addressing the two hundred
participants from some sixty
countries, Mr. M'Bow affirmed
that it was Unesco's duty to
commemorate the thirtieth
anniversary of the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights "by
giving new impetus to the action
it has carried on since its
creation to promote the
recognition of these rights in the
fields of its competence."
Amodern expression of a time-
honoured reality, the rights of men
in virtue of their humanity today
referred to as "human rights" have only
comparatively recently become of more
than passing interest to lawyers.
Tainted by the shadow of political con¬
siderations, they lay for a long time in a twi¬
light zone, screened from the light of pure
law, whose attraction for the jurist versed
in the analysis of age-old codes and rules
was far more immediate. This tradition of
neglect was too strong to be broken by the
isolated individuals whose interest in the
philosophy of law led them to examine
human rights as part of their investigation
of the aims and objectives of power.
Today, however, the old reticence is
being abandoned: those called upon to
pass judgement in the affairs of men are
increasingly inclined to base their rulings
on the declarations of rights to be found in
the preambles to constitutions. And if, in
our age, the banner of revolution is rarely
raised in the name of human rights (some
would say that this is a pity), the number of
proceedings instituted with the aim of
ensuring that these rights are respected is
legion. This change of perspective alone is
enough to indicate that human rights have
indeed become a legal reality.
For human rights to be real in the eyes of
the law, however, three sets of conditions
must exist.
In the first place, the society concerned
must be organized in the form of a legally
established State.
Secondly, the internal structure of the
State must provide for the exercise of
those rights within a predetermined legal
framework flexible enough to take account
KAREL VASAK, French jurist, is Director of
Unesco's Division of Human Rights and Peace.
He has collaborated with the principal authors of
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
including the late René Cassin, with whom he
was a co-founder of Revue des Droits de
l'Homme: Human Rights Journal. He has taught
at The Hague Academy of International Law,
the University of California, Berkeley, and at
several other universities (Singapore, Bangkok,
Besançon, Nairobi, etc.). He is the author of La
Convention Européenne des Droits de l'Homme
(The European Convention of Human Rights),
published In 1964, and general editor of the
Unesco manual Les Dimensions Internationales
des Droits de l'Homme, to be published shortly
in English under the title The International
Dimensions of Human Rights.
of the nature of the rights themselves and
of different circumstances.
Finally, the actual exercise of human
rights must be protected by precise legal
safeguards, particular provision being
made for recourse to ensure their respect.
Man can only be free in a State that is
free; conversely, the freedom of a State
depends on the self-determination of its
people. This collective self-determination is
to societies what freedom is to
individuals the very basis of their exis¬
tence. And if "self-determination" in this
sense cannot be counted as an individual
right, it is undoubtedly the sine qua non of
human rights as a whole: individuals can¬
not be free in societies that are unfree.
Self-determination is thus a prerequisite
to respect for human rights. But is It
enough to ensure that they are respected?
No one would be bold enough to make this
claim, obvious as It is that independence
secured through self-determination,
although invariably synonymous with col¬
lective liberation, may not necessarily entail
the liberation of individuals.
Unless a special place Is reserved for
them in the social order in which they are to
function, human rights are likely to remain
just so many fine-sounding words. In fact,
although they are by definition concerned
with individual human beings, they are at
the same time social in intent. We tend too
often to neglect this aspect of the matter;
and are led in consequence to consider the
two phenomena of human rights and
authority as somehow in opposition to
each other.
Given this opposition, in a sense natural
and automatic, it follows that a balance
between human rights on the one hand
and political power on the other can only
be achieved through the imposition of very
real limitations on each of the parties con¬
cerned. But such a notion of latent or
potential conflict between them ¡s a dan¬
gerous one, especially in the context of
attempts to secure legal status for human
rights. In case of conflict, the latter will
have the backing of law alone, whereas
political power, with or without the sanc¬
tion of the law, will always have force at its
disposal. If conflict does occur, therefore,
human rights will always be the losers.
If we look more closely at the matter,
however, ¡t becomes clear that the social
context of human rights affords fewer
grounds for their limitation than for theirs
promotion (the lawyer would say their F
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Cry, a lithograph by the French artist Ivan Levesque.
I
J
(
!
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
> "regulation"). When the legislator ordains
that vehicles shall keep to the left or right,
he Is facilitating rather than obstructing the
circulation of traffic. When, through the
nationalization of monopolies or steeply
increased taxation, the lawmakers chal¬
lenge the rights of property ownership,
their aim is not so much to encroach on
those rights as to make them as widely
accessible as possible.
The same is true in the case of numerous
human rights, which remain dead letters as
long as the political power which emanates
from society fails to insert them in the
social order. For example, the right to work
may mean no more than the right to starve
if the State makes no provision for its
active exercise; while the right to education
will mean no more for the bulk of the popu¬
lation than the right to remain ignorant if
the State fails to provide them with the
opportunity to learn.
In the last analysis, therefore, the fact
that human rights are intended for applica¬
tion in society makes them, if not directly
dependent on political authority, at least
potential allies rather than enemies of the
latter. It is not for political authority to limit
human rights, any more than it is for
human rights to rebel against authority.
NDISPENSABLE
though this modus vivendi may be, it is
easy to see how difficult it will be to main¬
tain through a system of regulations drawn
up by the authorities with the aim of en¬
suring the harmonious social exercise of
human rights. For where such rights are
involved, it is but a short step from neces¬
sary regulation through limitation to total
suppression.
Even if they are proclaimed by a free
State and regulated by law, human rights
will be of little significance if they are
not backed by effective guarantees
that is to say, those entitled to
them can obtain redress in case of vio¬
lation. Such guarantees may be of two
kinds, which we may call "institutiona¬
lized" and "non-institutionalized".
Within the framework of the State, insti¬
tutionalized guarantees are provided in the
form of recourse which permits individuals
to obtain either the annulment of the mea¬
sures which violate their human rights or,
when this is impossible, financial compen¬
sation for the injury sustained. At the inter¬
national level, provision for such recourse
exists on both a worldwide and a regional
scale.
Among the non-institutionalized guaran¬
tees of human rights, the right to refuse to
obey an unjust law seems to be firmly in¬
scribed, if not in the statute books of every
country, at least in the conscience of all
men. But where institutionalized safe¬
guards prove inadequate, resistance
The first of its kind...
In May 1978 an institute for training lawyers and magistrates in human
rights was set up by the Paris Bar under the auspices of Unesco. The
institute, the first of its kind, has aroused so much interest that other
Bars are considering the possibility of setting up similar institutes.
against oppression is the supreme guaran¬
tee of human rights. Written into the
Declaration of Independence of the United
States of America of 4 July 1776, pro¬
claimed in the French Declaration of the
Rights of Man of 24 June 1793, resistance
against oppression finds a natural place in
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
whose Preamble contains the words:
"Whereas it is essential, if man is not to be
compelled to have recourse, as a last
resort, to rebellion against tyranny and
oppression, that human rights should be
protected by the rule of law".
Distressing though the admission may
be, individual liberties are suffering in¬
creasingly from the encroachments of
modern States. The only means, and an
inadequate one at that, of breaking the
stranglehold imposed by their omnipotence
on human rights is to carry the issue
beyond national frontiers. Whether in
bodies of regional or of worldwide mem¬
bership, the question of human rights
should be raised as a matter of international
importance, and as, perhaps, the only truly
international problem.
Understood within this legal perspective,
human rights, as Unesco's Medium-Term
Plan (1977-1982) declares: "...are neither a
new morality nor a lay religion and are
much more than a language common to all
mankind. They are requirements which the
investigator must study and integrate into
his knowledge using the rules and methods
of his science, whether this is philosophy,
the humanities or the natural sciences,
sociology or law, history or geography. In a
word, the task is gradually to build up or
promote a genuine scientific formulation of
human rights".
Unesco's involvement with human
rights, and with teaching about those
rights, is self-evident: the promotion of
human rights is inscribed in its Constitu¬
tion, and constitutes the raison d'être of
the Organization itself. Its specific role as
far as education about human rights is con¬
cerned has, moreover, been recognized by
the United Nations Human Rights Commis¬
sion, which, in March 1971, instructed it to
examine:
"The desirability of envisaging the sys¬
tematic study and the development of an
independent scientific discipline of human
rights, taking into account the principal
legal systems of the world with a view to
facilitating the understanding, comprehen¬
sion, study and teaching of human rights at
the university level, and subsequently at
other educational levels."
It goes without saying that the study of
human rights constitutes both a meeting-
point and a source of mutual enrichment
for all the human sciences, bringing them
together in "the science of sciences", as a
modern equivalent of medieval philosophy.
Even if there are those who would hesitate
to accord the subject such pre-eminence,
none would dispute the fact that human
rights require an interdisciplinary approach,
which is indeed the only approach through
which not only their wealth and variety but
also their simultaneously local and univer¬
sal character may be appreciated.
Nevertheless, the manual recently
published by Unesco on the occasion of
the International Congress on the Teaching
of Human Rights, which was held in
Vienna from 12-16 September 1978, and
entitled Dimensions Internationales des
Droits de l'Homme, is essentially a law text
book, intended primarily for use in teaching
about human rights in faculties of law and
of political and social sciences in uni¬
versities.
Practical considerations and educational
expediency governed this choice. In the
first place, human rights are formulated in
legal language: the collection and synthesis
of different texts related to the subject is
thus first and foremost a matter for jurists.
Secondly, the earliest response to the idea
that human rights might be subjected to
scientific study came from faculties of law
throughout the world; their teachers and
students are now looking for educational
material which will permit them to go
beyond the generalizations that have now
been everywhere incorporated in courses
on constitutional or international public
law.
The choice of a "legal" approach, rather
than one based on a social science, such as
sociology, entails a certain risk in that it
may obscure the fact that human rights are
a component of social structures and that
their violation may spring from built-in
defects in those structures. This risk can
only be averted through increased inter¬
disciplinary research into the subject and
here Unesco will play its part during the
years to come.
Karel Vasak
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Human rights and the international community
Twenty
questions
by Leah Levin
What is meant by human rights?
The concept of human rights is the acceptance of an inherent
and inalienable right due to man simply because of being mafn. It is
a moral right which derives from being a human being, and which
in turn ensures the dignity of every human being.
LEAH LEVIN is secretary of the Human Rights Committee of the United
Nations Association of Great Britain and Northern Ireland. Her article Is
adapted from a longer study. Human Rights: Questions and Answers, pre¬
pared at Unesco's request to serve'as a model for teaching materials in
human rights education.
How is this idea reflected in practice?
Human life and human dignity have been disregarded and vio¬
lated throughout history and continue to be so violated. Never¬
theless, the idea of natural law common to all mankind equally
dates back many centuries. Natural law was long accepted as the
source and standard of political right.
During the eighteenth century the early ideas of natural law
developed into an acceptance of natural rights, and these rights for
the first time became a basic part of national constitutions, thus
reflecting an almost contractual relationship between the States
and the individual and emphasizing the power of the State as deri-r
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ving from the assent of the free individual. The American Declara-
} tion of Independence and the French Declaration of the Rights of
Man were based. on this premise.
During the nineteenth and twentieth centuries this principle was
followed by a number of European, Latin American, and Asian
States. During the 1960s, with the attainment of independence by
a large number of African States, they too included recognition of
human rights in their new constitutions, sometimes by incorpora¬
ting into them the Universal Declaration of Human Rights.
Despite the recognition of human rights in constitutions, these
rights can be and are still violated by States, and can be removed
by legislation or arbitrary means.
even though they may be prepared to discuss the affairs of other
States. These same governments have supported United Nation's
resolutions which sanctioned investigation into the affairs of other
Member States. Thus different governments have taken different
positions at different times.
It is also widely argued that "intervention" does not include dis¬
cussion and examination since it means essentially "physical"
intervention. There is consequently a growing acceptance in legal
terms that when States have undertaken similar obligations it is
legitimate for each State to undertake that other States respect
them.
Is there any other way of ensuring
the protection of human rights?
The State is the guarantor and protector of human rights, both
traditionally and historically.
But since the First World War there has been a growing belief
that governments alone cannot be left to safeguard these rights,
and that they are a subject for international guarantees. Although
its mandate did not mention human rights, the League of Nations
. nevertheless tried to undertake the protection of human rights
through international means. Its concerns, however, were limited
to the extent of establishing certain conditions for the protection
'of minorities in a few countries.
The major pressure for internationalization, however, built up
after the Second World War, during which totalitarian regimes
grossly violated human rights in their own and occupied territories,
and were responsible for the elimination of entire groups because
of their race, .religion or nationality. This approach to the protec¬
tion of human rights is reflected and reinforced in the Charter of
the United Nations.
Article 1 of the Charter states that the U.N. aims to achieve
international co-operation by "promoting and encouraging respect
for human rights and for fundamental freedoms for all without dis¬
tinction as to race, sex, language or religion". Article 55 expresses
a similar undertaking; and in Article 56 all members of the U.N.
"pledge themselves to take joint and separate action in co¬
operation with the Organization for the achievement of the purpo¬
ses set forth in Article 55".
The provisions of these Articles also form the basis of Unesco's
activity in the sphere of human rights through its relationship as a
specialized agency of the U.N. in accordance with Article 63 of the
Charter.
The provisions of the Charter have the force of positive interna¬
tional law because the Charter is a treaty and therefore a legally
binding document. Its provisions should not be contradicted by
national laws or practices. It also establishes basic duties which all
members must fulfil in good faith. Thus nations, as an integral part
of the Charter, have the obligation to promote respect for, and
encourage observance of human rights and are committed to co¬
operate with other nations in fulfilling these aims.
Why do States resist international scrutiny of
their compliance with their duties to promote
and protect human rights under the Charter?
One of the Articles of the Charter (Article 2[7]) states that the
U.N. should not intervene "in matters which are essentially within
the domestic jurisdiction of any State..."
This provides the basis for the claims of States when they do not
want their affairs discussed, and do not wish to be shown up as
having contravened their undertakings in respect of human rights.
Does it follow that the U.N. Charter can have
an effect on actual situations?
The Charter recognizes that peace and stability among nations is
related to the recognition of respect for human rights and seeks to
establish conditions under which this can be achieved. It also
establishes a close link between human rights and other world¬
wide concerns such as the promotion of economic and social
co-operation.
Since the signing of the Charter, great changes have occurred,
especially regarding decolonization, and many new nations have
emerged.
However, as the provisions of the Charter are of a general
nature, it was necessary to establish more specific definitions of
human rights and freedoms in order that these could be practically
applied.
How was this done?
In 1945, a U.N. Commission on Human Rights was established
and entrusted with the task of drawing up an International Bill of
Human Rights, whereby these rights and freedoms would be
defined.
The first part of the Bill of Rights was achieved when on 10
December 1948 the General Assembly unanimously adopted the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights "as a common standard of
achievement for all peoples and all nations" (1).
Do States which were not at the time members
of the United Nations accept the Declaration?
The impact of the Declaration and the use made of it bear out
the universal acceptance of the Declaration and it has become a
norm of reference in human rights for all countries.
In a formal sense, parts of the Declaration have been cited in
national constitutions and other international instruments.
Governments have no hesitation in invoking the Declaration
when accusing other countries of violating their obligations under
the Declaration; parts of the Declaration were also included in
many new United Nations instruments agreed to by Member
States.
The Declaration, together with the Charter, served both as an
inspiration and a means for millions of people under colonial rule to
achieve self-determination. The universality of the claim to human
rights provided the justification and the means for liberation of
these oppressed peoples. In 1961 President Julius Nyerere of Tan-
(1) The full text of the Universal Declaration was reproduced in the November 1977
issue of the Unesco Courier.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Is the Declaration legally binding upon States?
The Declaration is not, as such, a legally binding document, but
by their actions and use of the Declaration, nations have endowed
the Declaration with a legitimacy which allows it to be invoked
both legally and politically at the international and domestic levels.
The consensus of the international community was expressed in
these terms at the Tehran Conference on Human Rights in 1968:
the Declaration "states a common understanding of the people of
the world concerning the inalienable rights of all members of the
human family and constitutes an obligation for all members of the
international community".
There is no legal sanction to compel States to meet this obliga¬
tion. As with other areas of international law and practice the main
sanction available to the international community is the withdrawal
from States of the confidence of other States upon their unwil¬
lingness to co-operate to discharge their obligations.
What steps were taken toward implementation?
The Universal Declaration of Human Rights was the first tier in a
three-tier objective.
The second and third parts of the International Bill of Rights
were adopted by the General Assembly on 16 December 1966.
They consisted of two Covenants the International Covenant on
Civil and Political Rights; and the International Covenant on
Social, Economic and Cultural Rightsand the Optional Protocol
to the Covenant on Civil and Political Rights. In adopting these
Covenants agreement was reached by the international commu¬
nity, not only on the contents of each right, but also in respect of
the right of States to derogate from or restrict these rights.
The Eternal Victim, a linocut by the French artist Paul Siehe.
ganyika in addressing the United Nations General Assembly said
"We shall try to use the Declaration of Human Rights as a basis for
both our external and internal policies".
All Member States take part in nominating and electing mem¬
bers to the Commission on Human Rights and participate in the
implementation machinery.
What are the rights proclaimed in the
Declaration?
These rights can be broadly divided into two kinds. The first
consists of civil and political rights which include the right to life,
liberty, security of person; freedom from torture or slavery; politi¬
cal participation; property, marriage and the fundamental free¬
doms of opinion, expression, thought, conscience, and religion;
freedom of association and assembly.
The second kind are social, economic and cultural rights which
relate to work, a reasonable standard of living, education and free¬
dom of cultural life. In addition, the first article of the Declaration
expresses the universality of rights in terms of the equality of
human dignity; and the second article expresses the entitlement of
all persons to the rights set out without discrimination of any kind.
The priorities underlying the rights proclaimed in the Declaration
are contained in the preamble to the Declaration, which starts by
recognizing the "inherent dignity, and the equal and inalienable
rights of all members of the human family".
How dó the Covenants differ from the
Declaration?
Firstly, the Covenants, once ratified by thirty-five governments,
are legally binding treaties.
Secondly, upon agreeing to become party to the Covenants,
States undertake to submit reports on their compliance with the
provisions of the Covenants.'
Thirdly, although the General Assembly adopted the Covenants
in 1966, they only entered into force in 1976 when the required
thirty-five States had ratified them.
Fourthly, the Covenants are only binding on those States which
are parties to them. In September 1978 fifty States had become
parties to the Covenants.
How do the Covenants relate to the Charter?
The Declaration interprets the basic rules on international law on
the subject of human rights embodied in the Charter of the United
Nations. Although the Covenants apply only directly to the States
which have ratified them, they have a relevance to all States in res¬
pect of the obligations of Member States of the United Nations
under the Charter and as interpreted by the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights which were both adopted as international stan¬
dards to be achieved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
L What means are provided for implementation?
A special Human Rights Committee has been established under
the Covenant on Civil and Political Rights, consisting of eighteen
independent experts nominated by, but not representing, their
governments. This Committee receives and examines reports from
States as to how they are implementing their undertakings in res¬
pect of the Covenants. The Committee is able to question the
government concerned, and forwards comments to the govern¬
ment subsequently. The Committee is also empowered to receive
inter-State complaints when one State considers that another
State is not giving effect to its obligations under the Covenants.
This provision is not yet operative as the number of States required
to agree to it in the first instance is ten, and to date there have only
been six acceptances.
What can the Human Rights Committee do if it
considers that governments are not complying
with their undertakings?
Since the immediate protection of human rights depends upon
compliance at the national level, the effectiveness of the Commit¬
tee is limited as there is no enforcement machinery. However,
there is a persuasive value derived from the examination of reports
in public. Governments are sensitive to criticism of their human
rights performance. The principal object of the Committee is to
develop a constructive dialogue with reporting States and thereby
promote the compliance of States with the provisions of the
Covenant.
Are there other human rights instruments
besides the Bill of Rights?
There are a number of declarations and conventions adopted by
the General Assembly which elaborate and detail the specific
obligations and safeguards relating to particular human rights laid
down in the Declaration and the International Covenants. Among
these are conventions relating to discrimination and to the right to
life.
Genocide
In December 1948 the U.N. General Assembly adopted the Con¬
vention on the Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of Geno¬
cide. It came into force in 1961 and has now been ratified by
eighty-two States. Genocide is defined in the Convention as the
committing of certain acts with the intent to destroy, in whole, or
in part, a national, ethnic, racial or religious group. Genocide is
designated a crime under international law, whether committed in
time of war or of peace.
Discrimination
The International Convention on the Elimination of all forms of
Racial Discrimination entered into force in 1969 and has been rati¬
fied by ninety-seven States. It represents the most comprehensive
United Nations statement regarding discrimination on the grounds
of race, colour or ethnic origin.
States parties to the Convention undertake to pursue a policy of
eliminating racial discrimination in all its forms and to ensure the
protection of special racial groups guaranteeing their members full
and equal enjoyment of human rights and fundamental freedoms.
A special Committee on the Elimination of Racial Discrimination
was established under the Convention to supervise governmental
compliance.
Does the Committee deal with individual
complaints?
Under the provisions of the Optional Protocol to the Covenant
on Civil and Political Rights, the Committee can act on complaints
by individuals of violations of their rights by a State. Only citizens
of countries which have ratified this undertaking can make com¬
plaints to the Committee, and only after all domestic remedies
have been tried. Representation may also be made by another per¬
son on behalf of a victim who is not able personally to appeal to the
Committee. These complaints are considered privately, and the
Committee then makes its comments to the individual and to the
State concerned.
What provision is there for the implementation
of the Covenant on Social, Economic and
Cultural rights?
Under this Covenant States party to it submit reports to the Eco¬
nomic and Social Council (ECOSOC) of the United Nations on pro¬
gress made in achieving the rights recognized. A working group of
fifteen of its members, representing States which are parties to the
Covenant, has been appointed by ECOSOC to consider these
reports. All other States can attend as observers. In addition, the
sections of the reports relating to the sphere of competence of the
International Labour Organisation (ILO) or of Unesco are examined
by these bodies. Since most of the economic and social rights are
outside the reach of most of the world's peoples, largely through
no fault of their own, it remains the responsibility of the internatio¬
nal community to work towards the realization of these rights for
all peoples.
What are the functions of this Committee?
The Committee has four functions. The first, and hitherto its
main occupation, is the examination of reports from States on the
measures they have taken to implement the Convention. The
second procedure, which has not yet been invoked by any State,
allows the Committee to deal with inter-state complaints. The third
allows the Committee to examine complaints from individuals
against States, provided that the State concerned has recognized
the right of private petition. This procedure is not yet operative as
it requires at least ten States to have recognized this right and only
five have done so, to date. The fourth function is to provide assis¬
tance to the U.N. organs which review petitions from inhabitants
of trust and non-self-governing territories.
The way in which the Committee has conducted its task of
handling and examining reports has yielded a measure of success
insofar as getting States to file reports is concerned, and in en¬
suring that governments are represented at the examination of
their reports. The latter procedure allows for eliciting additional
information to that contained in the report. The Committee
refrains from any formal condemnation and pursues the means of
informal dialogue to encourage governments to comply with their
obligations. It is entitled to make "suggestions and recommenda¬
tions", but is dependent upon the General Assembly to endorse
and give authority to these.
Can anyone who feels that human rights are
being violated appeal to the United Nations?
Since its inception the United Nations has received annually
thousands of complaints from individuals and organizations al¬
leging violations of human rights. Between 1951 and 1971 there
were 120,000 such communications.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
What is done about them?
The Human Rights Commission, which is a subsidiary body to
the Economic and Social Council, is the body primarily responsible
for dealing with these complaints, but it has no power, under any
of its procedures, to take action in respect of individual com¬
plaints. The method of dealing with complaints has been laid down
by the Economic and Social Council.
Confidential lists of complaints are handed to members of the
Commission, and States are informed of complaints against them;
but replies received from States are not passed on to the person or
organization submitting the complaint. In the early 1960s, the deep
concern of many new nations with the colonial and racial
attitudes in southern Africa prompted a move towards extending
the United Nations measures so that gross violations of Human
Rights could be dealt with. In 1967, the Economic and Social
Council adopted a Resolution, instructing the Commission on
Human Rights to "make a thorough study of situations which
reveal a consistent pattern of violations of human rights, as exem¬
plified by the policy of Apartheid"; and to report and make recom¬
mendations to the Economic and Social Council.
Fact-finding studies were then initiated, mainly concerned with
southern Africa, followed later by fact-finding groups of govern¬
ment experts concerned with other territories. Despite the fact that
none of these groups has ever been allowed to enter the territories
concerned they have been able to gather a great deal of evidence
on which subsequent resolutions of the General Assembly and the
Commission on Human Rights have been based. The activities of
these groups are carried out in public; but it has nevertheless been
a restricted operation, as it has not been extended to situations
beyond those mentioned.
In 1970, an Economic and Social Council Resolution set up a
rather complex confidential procedure whereby complaints which
reveal "a consistent pattern of gross and reliably attested violation
of human rights and fundamental freedoms" should be examined.
For the first time, evidence could be submitted not only by victims
of violations, but also by any person, group or non-governmental
organization with a direct and reliable knowledge of the violations.
The complaints are examined in the first instance by a Working
Group of the Sub-Commission on the Prevention of Discrimination
and the Protection of Minorities (a subsidiary of the Commission
on Human Rights), which makes recommendations to its Sub-
Committee, which in turn makes recommendations to a Working
Group of the Commission on Human Rights, which in turn makes
recommendations to the Commission on Human Rights. The Com¬
mission on Human Rights has to decide whether to recommend to
the Economic and Social Council that the situation re¬
quires a thorough study, and report on whether an ad hoc com¬
mittee should be established to investigate the situation in co¬
operation with the State concerned.
The entire procedure is confidential until such time as the Com¬
mission on Human Rights makes a recommendation to the Econo¬
mic and Social Council; hence there has been no official informa¬
tion hitherto regarding the operation of the procedure. For the first
time, in March 1978, the Commission listed the countries which
had been considered at its session that year under this procedure.
To date, however, no situation has been publicly reported to have
been recommended for further study.
Leah Levin
Unesco and respect
for human rights
By a decision of its Executive Board on 3 March 1978, Unesco
has adopted new procedures for dealing with specific complaints
concerning alleged violations of human rights in its fields of
competence. (1)
According to these procedures, any person or groups of persons
may write to the Director-General of Unesco drawing his attention
to an individual case of violation of human rights or to a ques¬
tion of massive, systematic or flagrant violations which result
either from a policy contrary to human rights applied de jure or
de facto by a State or from an accumulation of individual cases
forming a consistent pattern. Acting in conformity with moral prin¬
ciples and within the limits of its specific competence, Unesco
must work in this field in a spirit of conciliation and mutual com¬
prehension, it being understood that the Organization cannot fulfil
the role of an international judicial body.
To be admissible, such complaints must fulfil ten different condi¬
tions and notably be compatible with the principles of the Organi¬
zation, the Charter of the United Nations and the Universal Decla¬
ration of Human Rights.
The procedures laid down by decision of the Executive Board
provide that, on receipt of a communication, the Director-General
shall ascertain that its author has no objection to his communica¬
tion being transmitted to the government concerned and being
brought to the notice of the Executive Board's Committee on Con- .
ventions and Recommendations.
Once the author's consent has been obtained, the government
will be informed of the communication and will be invited to reply.
The Committee will examine the communication in private session
and will first try to bring about a friendly solution. Whatever the
results of its efforts, the Committee will submit to Unesco's Exe¬
cutive Board confidential reports on the communications it has
examined. The Executive Board will discuss these reports in pri¬
vate session, but may decide to do so in public meetings when
questions of massive, systematic or flagrant violations of human
rights are involved-for example, those perpetrated as a result of
policies of aggression, interference in the internal affairs of States,
occupation of foreign territory and implementation of a policy of
colonialism, genocide, apartheid, racialism, or national and social
oppression.
Such questions may also be considered by Unesco's General
Conference in public meetings.
(1) The rights falling within Unesco's spheres of competence are
essentially the following:
the right to education
the right to share in scientific advancement
the right to participate freely in cultural life
the right to information, including freedom of opinion and
expression
Unesco has Issued a
wall-poster
presenting the text
of the Universal
Declaration of
Human Rights (1948).
It features this
design by the Polish
artist Stanislaw
Zagorski.
Photo Unesco
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Education
for disarmament
'Freedom from fear is
a fundamental human right'
by Swadesh Rana
URGENCY, cynicism and helpless¬
ness characterize the current
debate on disarmament. Almost
everyone recognizes the urgency, very few
can help being cynical, and hardly anyone
knows how to transform the desirable into
the attainable.
Beginning with the Declaration of St.
Petersburg in 1868 (which prohibited the
use of explosive bullets), international con¬
cern about disarmament has undergone
two fundamental changes. On the one
hand there has been a shift in emphasis
away from general and complete disarma¬
ment towards arms control, and on the
other an increasing diversification of the
international machinery to negotiate disar¬
mament proposals. Both these develop¬
ments were inspired by the need to trans¬
form the desirable into the attainable; nei¬
ther has really promoted the objectives
visualized.
Enthusiasm for arms control was based
on the logic that limitation would lead to
reduction and ultimate elimination of arms.
As a corollary, those most heavily armed
were considered to be responsible for start¬
ing the process of control.
Since the League of Nations convened a
world' conference to discuss universal
disarmament, in February 1932, the inter¬
national community has adopted no less
that twenty-two major multilateral and as
many bilateral agreements to control the
arms race, in addition to thirty resolutions
of the United Nations, including the latest
SWADESH RANA of India has been engaged
in research at the Institute for Defence Studies
and Analyses, New Delhi, since 1971. A former
Visiting Fellow at the Institute for the Study of
War and Peace, Columbia University, New
York, and at the International Peace Research
Institute, Oslo, she has written widely on
international relations, disarmament and peace.
by the first-ever U.N. Special Session on
Disarmament, held earlier this year. Not
one of these measures has as yet deterred
the acquisition or encouraged the elimina¬
tion of a single weapon which a country
considered crucial for its legitimate national
security interests.
In all disarmament discussions, whether
between nation-states, as in the Eighteen-
Nation Disarmament Committee (now
some forty members strong and re-named
the Committee on Disarmament) or bet¬
ween individuals, at meetings such as the
Pugwash Conferences (1) and in institu¬
tions such as the Oslo International Peace
Research Institute, national security con¬
cerns have emerged as the single most
stubborn obstacle to disarmament. In¬
variably the frontiers of national security
concerns coincide with the geographical
borders of a nation-state. National leaders
view the inviolability of their frontiers with
the same uncompromising attitude as indi¬
viduals perceive their right to survival.
For most of the developing countries,
which by now constitute more than two-
thirds of the international community, the
sanctity of territorial borders as they emer¬
ged with statehood also involves the capa¬
bility to regulate within their frontiers such
events as insurgency and secessionist
threats. For some industrialized countries,
national frontiers extend beyond their geo¬
graphical limits and tie in with their assess¬
ment of regional and global interests in¬
cluding the protection of political values.
Each nation builds up its arsenal to suit
its resources. Very few developing coun¬
tries would envisage using a "Cruise" mis-
ID The Pugwash Conferences are meetings of scien¬
tists from different countries of the world to discuss
problems of disarmament and world security. Pugwash
Is the name of a village in Nova Scotia, Canada, where
the first of these conferences was held.
sible to curb an insurgency. Most industria¬
lized countries find it hard to stop experi¬
menting "just in case" a situation arises
which may require military activity beyond
their frontiers. The countries most anxious
to arm are those with clear-cut adversary
relationships based upon actual military
engagements.
Do nations arm because they feel threat¬
ened? Or do they feel threatened because
they are armed? Rarely, if ever, has the
issue been faced squarely by any interna¬
tional body concerned with disarmament.
At all forums where disarmament is discus¬
sed, the desirability of disarmament is
emphasized because military expenditure is
wasteful and risky, but few find it wise to
explore the possible alternatives to military
strength as a means of protecting national
security interests. A sad result of the proli¬
ferating disarmament exercises is thus an
almost universal attempt at skilful falsifica¬
tion of the motives behind the continuing
arms race.
In the publicity of an international forum,
few participants are willing openly to obs¬
truct consensus. But in the privacy of
national decision-making,, the military
analysts are guided by the political leader¬
ship, the politicians seek clarification from
the scientific community, and the scientists
provide technological grounds for political
reticence on disarmament.
A world armed to annihilate itself many
times over continues, in the meantime, to
spend more than 400 thousand million dol¬
lars a year on arms. The fact that a diver¬
sion of world military expenditure into
development projects would double the
combined Gross National Products of more
than half the developing world (southern
Asia, the Far East, Africa) does not deter
more than half of the world's physicists
and engineers from being engaged in mili¬
tary research and development.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
1 tank
(U.S. $500,000)
Equipment for 520 classrooms
(30 pupils per primary school class)
1 jet fighter
(U.S. $20 million)
40,000 village pharmacies
1 destroyer
(U.S. $100 million)
Electrification for 13 cities
19 rural zones with a population of
9 million inhabitants
Physics and engineering constitute two
of the most exacting branches of the study
of science, which is in itself a demanding
educational discipline. Education, in its
broadest sense, reflects man's endeavour
to understand, control and, if possible,
mould the human environment to his
advantage.
But if the highest goal of education is to
improve the environment then why are
those most qualified to do so adding to its
hazards? The very instinct of survival which
equates military strength with security also
recognizes the insecurity of a world armed
to the hilt and continuing to arm itself. But
how is it that those concerned with human
welfare have never designated the freedom
from insecurity as a fundamental human
right?
Disarmament is desirable not only
because military effort is wasteful and risky
but also because it negates the very pur¬
pose of education. Disarmament is essen¬
tial because freedom from fear is a funda¬
mental human right.
These twin themes should become an
integral part of education because educa¬
tion provides the strongest single determi¬
nant of social awareness. Disarmament
education should involve re-educating
those who make knowledge a hazard to the
human environment and educating those
who have yet to learn.
Future action should take three main
directions. There should be a search for an
alternative to the present predominant
trend whereby military strength is equated
with security. Influence should be brought
to bear on decision makers who are in
clined to look no further than national fron¬
tiers when planning education. It should be
brought home to the largest possible num¬
ber of human beings that they are collect¬
ively as well as individually responsible for
the environment they choose to live in.
The search for alternatives would involve
encouraging research among specialists on
methods of conflict resolution, particularly
in areas with well identified adversary rela¬
tionships. Political parties could be used as
an effective mode of communication in an
attempt to reach the minds of the decision
makers. There cannot be a better way to
mould social awareness than to attach a
kind of Hippocratic oath to all educational
degrees and diplomas. Education is a way
of improving the environment, and it is up
to the educated to decide whether they
want to live in peace or die with fear.
Swadesh Rana
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The great Spanish painter Francisco
Goya y Lucientes died 150 years ago,
on 16 April 1828, in Bordeaux (France)
where he had gone Into voluntary
exile to escape the political and
intellectual oppression which then
prevailed in Spain. The product of an
inexhaustible imagination, much of
his work is a scathing denunciation
of the despotic forces which crush
mankind and debase human values.
Self-portrait shown here is one of
several Goya painted around 1815.
GOYA
An art that defied the powers of darkness
by Santiago Amón
THE mantle of "Champion of Human
Rights" rests easily upon the shoul¬
ders of Francisco de Goya. Indeed,
in most critical assessments of his
paintings, drawings and engravings, praise
for the way in which he succeeded, as
never before, in illuminating aesthetic
values, goes hand in hand with admiring
recognition of his outspoken denunciation
of injustice, oppression and the caprices of
power, and of his moving heart-cry against
the disasters of war.
Goya's arj breaks completely with the
decadent neoclassicism of his immediate
predecessors. But more than this, it has
historical significance as an act of defiance,
a stand against the unjust social and
political conditions of his country and his
age, and as such provides an example and
a lesson for other lands and other times.
The one hundred and fiftieth anniversary
of his death prompts one to begin a
reflection on his life and work in the very
place where his remains now rest, having
SANTIAGO AMON, Spanish art critic, poet
and historian, writes regularly on art in the Spa¬
nish daily El Pais and the Madrid periodical Cua¬
dernos para el Dialogo. Among his published
works are a biography of Giotto and a study of
Picasso (Madrid, 1973). He has written widely
on contemporary Spanish art.
been brought to Spain years after his death
in more or less voluntary exile in Bordeaux.
They now lie in the San Antonio de la
Florida Hermitage in Madrid, at the foot of
the transept, beneath the very dome which
he himself decorated. Rather than
theological allegory or the ecstatic fervour
of the visionary, its magnificent frescoes
portray a conflict of everyday life resolved
in the name of Justice, a protest against a
violation of human rights and a straight¬
forward testimony in defence of truth.
A Witness to Truth. This is the title
which Goya's life and work have truly
earned him and he will for ever be
remembered as a faithful, uncompro¬
mising, incorruptible chronicler of the living
history of his day. He was one of those
daring, noble spirits who proclaimed the
truth, come what might even his own
death in exile. His outspoken artistic
message seems to echo that of his spiritual
forefather, the seventeenth-century poet
and satirist Francisco de Quevedo, who
met imprisonment and persecution crying:
"I shall not rest silent, though your finger
touch lip and brow, enjoining silence or
inviting fear".
The splendid murals which, thanks to his
genius, now crown his tomb in San
Antonio de la Florida, provide, as it were, a
summary of iniquities occurring daily in the
streets, whose flagrant injustice calls for
public condemnation. On the cupola which
he painted for our universal delight, there is
no trace of divine fable or dogmatic pro¬
nouncement from on high. What we see is
a medley of figures from popular life
local Madrid men and women, ragged
children, the Madrid "cockneys" in their
gay dress, working-class beauties, ordinary
labourers and the rogues and wits of the
Spanish underworld, simple people flock¬
ing to see a good deed performed in
defence of Truth by the miracle-working
Saint.
Saint Anthony's miracle is performed in
the street, in an ordinary courtyard with its
typically Madrileño railed balconies. The
sumptuous marble stairways and porticoes
which form the setting for the working of
miracles in traditional art are relegated to
limbo. Saint Anthony has just raised a man
from the dead, not to bring us tidings of life
beyond the grave, but to prove the inno¬
cence of his own father, falsely accused of
murder by the true culprit who is seen run¬
ning off through the astonished crowd. All
present are thanking the Saint for his good
deed and marvelling at the appearance of
the unexpected witness.
The composition of Goya's paintings in
the Saint Anthony cupola are clearly in line
with a renaissance tradition which origina-'
ted with Andrea Mantegna's Camera degli
Sposi, was continued with Correggio and
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Right, The Colossus or The
Panic (around 1809), an
astonishing evocation of the
terror and desolation
unleashed by war. A horror-
struck multitude takes flight
beneath a raging giant. Only a
little donkey in the foreground
seems unmoved by the
prevailing panic.
Photo © Prado Museum, Madrid
Below, detail from the great
fresco which Goya painted in
1798 in the church of San
Antonio de la Florida in
Madrid. The graceful trio of
Madrid belles forms a striking
contrast with the sombre
figure above them, possibly an
Old Testament prophet. Goya
is buried beneath the dome of
San Antonio.
Photo © Snark International, Pans
flourished most brilliantly in Tiepolo's
ceilings. The radical transformation Goya
brings about in these matchless ¡mages
above his tomb is in their content and signi¬
ficance. The old imperial or sacred allegori¬
cal themes here make way for essentially
popular scenes, and the splendours of the
gold and marble and the multi-hued cloud
effects of yesteryear give way to a line of
washing hung out to dry in the patio, to the
colourful hubbub of everyday life, and to
the defence of rights yesterday trampled
underfoot but today restored in the sight of
all.
As for colour, we find that Goya uses a
rather muted palette verging on the aus¬
tere. Flouting the conventions of fresco
painting, Goya dares to replace the classic
splendour of church or palace ceiling paint¬
ing with the bleak harshness of the natural
colours of the earth. The sepias of Sienna
and Seville are the essence of this miracle
of fresco work; which even now stretches
out before the sightless gaze of the artist
within his tomb. The typical countryside of
Spain, melting into faded yellow, a fleeting
patch of bright vermilion, the hard cold
clarity of cobalt blues or a dash of solid,
stiff purple; a countryside, in short, which
epitomizes in his work a basic opposition
charged with human significance the
clash of black and white.
What is the essence of Goya's vision?
Let us leave general historical and aesthetic
considerations aside and concentrate on a
single, immediate aspect of his sensibility.
Goya offers us a vision of blackness, not
only in his so-called black period, but in all
of his work. His art, or at least a great part
of it, is dominated by or oriented around
carefully studied and starkly dramatic black
shading. Goya offers or evokes an after¬
glow of clear white (a veil, a piece of gauze
or a lining) in front of or above a stark slash
of black. This dramatic contrast is based on
an internal dissociation in his painting,
symbolized by a stain of black growing and
invading Goya's plastic vision until it breaks
it down into shreds.
An intruding black against dominant
white is the essence of Goya's innovation k
in art; solid, massive blacks and whites f
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The dark
vision
of a deaf
master
Photo © Prado Museum, Madrid
Even though he was the
official court painter and a
portraitist much sought-
after by the nobility, Goya
always remained a satirist
and a moralist who
relentlessly exposed the
folly and injustice of his
times. In 1792 he was
stricken by a terrible illness
which left him permanently
deaf but also released his
tumultuous imagination.
Enveloped in a curtain of
silence, he produced a
series of 82 etchings known
as the Caprichos. On these
pages we present six
Caprichos on the theme of
imprisonment. (1) and (4)
two drawings in which
Goya attacks one of his
favourite targets, the
Inquisition : To Discover
the Movement of the Earth
(Galileo Imprisoned) and
Zapata, Your Glory Will Be
Eternal. Zapata was a
doctor from Valladolid who
was suspected of Judaism
and arrested because of his
scientific writings. Goya
himself fell foul of the
Inquisition, being
compelled to withdraw the
Caprichos from sale. (2) A
Prisoner In Chains
(drawing). (3) Because She
Was Sensitive, one of many
etchings of prison life.
16
Photo © Lauros-Giraudon, Pans. Bonnat Museum, Bayonne, France
which eschew the profusion of colour and
the fiction of line. "Always line, never
mass", complained Goya at his height; and
turning away from this tradition in order to
look afresh at things themselves, he won¬
dered "Where does one find lines in
nature?" Later he adds:' "I see only bright
or dark masses, flat areas advancing or
receding... My eye never sees lines or
details, so my brush should not see what I
do not see myself... In nature there is only
sunlight and shadow". And to dispel all
doubt, he crowns this statement with the
unforgettable phrase: "Give me a stick of
charcoal and I will make a picture".
A vibrant counterpoint of light and
shade; a duel between black and
white this was the vision which led Goya
to experiment with etching, an art in which
he was to become a master. Nor did the
political dramas and evils of his day escape
his attention in this new art form. Goya
uses the bite of acid on copper to cut a las¬
ting image of the struggle between the
powers of night (terror) and the kingdom of
light (liberty), a struggle then a dramatic
reality in his country. "What his burin and
acid portray in those copper rectangles",
writes the French critic Claude Roy, "is the
struggle then tearing Spain apart, the
struggle between reason and the dreams of
reason, between life and death, between
the unspeakable seething of darkness and
the rationality of light; between night and
day".
Perhaps one should include this critic's
remark that the technique of etching
achieved a degree of autonomy with the
French artist Jacques Callot (1592-1635),
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
but that despite everything it was still con¬
sidered to be a mere technique for making
a copper record of a drawing. It was the
experiments of the Dutch engraver Lucas
Van Leyden, who discovered how to
express distances by an exquisite thinning
of lines and shades, which inspired Rem-
On 2 May 1808 the
people of Madrid
rose against
Napoleon's troops
which were
occupying the city.
Goya immortalized
the first days of the
rising, which
sparked off a war of
national
independence, in
two famous
paintings: 77is
Second of May 1808:
The Charge of the
Mamelukes and The
Third of May 1808:
The Execution of the
Defenders of Madrid,
right. (A detail is
shown on back
cover) Goya
captured all the
horror of these
bloody massacres,
which he saw with
his own eyes and
would later expose
in grim detail in his
Disasters of War.
tyranny and lies, contempt for the human
being and the wretchedness of the down¬
trodden. There is a certain quality which
marks off trivial satire from major satire,
such as we find in Rabelais, Swift or
Goya".
In Goya's reveries, and particularly in his
In this etching Goya ridicules the heavy
burden of taxation imposed on the people
for the benefit of fools and knaves.
Photo © Prado Museum, Madrid
brandt in the same city of Leyden. Lucas
Van Leyden's work released drawing from
its previous rigidity and eventually made
engraving a marvellous medium for recor¬
ding everyday life, a delicate interplay of
light and shade, of "bright masses", as
Goya put it, "and dark masses, flat areas
advancing and receding".
With the genius of Rembrandt, etching
ceased to be simply a method of producing
several copies of a drawing or a means of
using the engraving press to replace hand-
painting with the main purpose of illustra¬
ting literary works. The year 1639 is usually
taken to mark a turning point in the history
of etching. It was in this year that Rem-
brandt,with his famous Pesadora de Oro,
transformed the ancient craft of engraving
into a new art form based essentially on the
interplay of shades of dark and light. More
than a century and a half was to pass
before Goya transformed this interplay into
a dramatic conflict between obscurantism
and freedom, with all the social and politi¬
cal implications that these words bear.
And what, in the San Antonio de la Flo¬
rida frescoes, is a straightforward denun¬
ciation of the trampling underfoot of rights,
becomes, in his etchings, a profound and
detailed social message. "What the Spa¬
niards of 1799 unerringly recognized",
Claude Roy remarks, "was that Goya's
Caprichos are a social document rather
than a metaphysical vision". In this series
of eighty-two etchings, as in Gulliver's Tra¬
vels or Candide, what is brought in ques¬
tion "is not Man Eternal or God, but living
man and the society he creates and which
is an expression of him, throne and altar,
Caprichos with their savage conflict of light
and shadow, many have rightly seen a new
Dantesque descent into Inferno. But his
was not a descent into an otherworldly,
theological or mythological Avernus, but to
the underworld of the life of his day, where
the figures damned to the shades are men
of flesh and blood. Goya goes down into
the inferno of a prison where the convicts
lie in rat-infested dungeons; or he visits a
madhouse where inmates wander the filthy
rooms in grotesque paper hats. Thus does
he offer us a spectacle of the abysmal col¬
lapse of the values of the spirit.
A new religion? This is the view of,
among others, Lionello Venturi, who does
not hesitate to ascribe a clear religious con¬
tent to Goya's work. But he concludes with
the paradoxical observation that "Goya's
contribution is the abolition of. the trans¬
cendental dimension". Venturi draws our
attention to the hapless wretch, in the
famous The Third of May 1808: The Execu¬
tion of the Defenders of Madrid, who is
about to fall with all the savage immediacy
of a charge of lead in his chest. As though
nailed to an invisible cross, his arms are
outstretched, heroic and anonymous, a
moment before the volley is fired. There is
no aura of martyrdom. There is no personal
identity to this emaciated figure; even the
rigid figures obeying a blind mechanism of
destruction of human values are not execu¬
tioners but more like featureless bureau¬
crats or puppets. For Venturi, "the ragged,
unforgettable wretch, with arms tragically
outstretched, is a new Christ on
Golgotha". This, then, seems to be Goya's
way of expressing his beliefs, by a powerful
statement of the driving force behind the
"new religion" of humanity and freedom, a
religion born of the French revolution the
slow and painful emergence of the concept
of human rights.
A blind mechanism is in the process of
annihilating not just a man, but mankind
itself; and the dramatic contrast between
human courage and the inhumanity of the
mechanism is what confers upon the scene
its truly epic proportions. "What Goya
represents is the revolt of popular passions.
He consecrates them, suffers them, weeps
for them. His powerful visual expression
transcends the tragedy of the Napoleonic
suppression of Spanish patriotism, and
acquires a universal human value".
Santiago Amón
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The
disasters
of war
In his series of 82 etchings inspired by the
War of Independence, Goya gave free rein
to his genius for depicting fantasy and
nightmare. The Disasters of War are not
simply the chronicle of a war of liberation
but one of the most powerful indictments
of brutality and sadism ever made. The
artist does not take sides; he simply
records the fact that war is collective
madness. There is no attempt to idealize
or justify; there are no heroics. Men are
tortured, exploited and massacred by their
fellows. Goya's genius brings to these
savage events a dimension of universal
humanism. Like the Caprichos, the
Disasters (executed between 1810 and
1820) bear captions or titles written in the
artist's own hand. These inscriptions are
often ironic or sarcastic and In some cases
their meaning remains obscure. On these
pages we show six of the most heart¬
rending scenes from this great series.
Photos © Mas, Torello Collection, Barcelona
Against the General Good
Grim Forebodings of What Lies in Store
Luckless Motherl
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
They Don't Know the Way^
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
A voice
from the
Third World
by Radhika Coomaraswamy
RADHIKA COOMARASWAMY is a Sri Lanka
lawyer who has specialized in human rights
research and education. She gave a fuller treat¬
ment to the subject of this article in a report pre¬
pared for the Sri Lanka Foundation, Colombo, a
governmental organization for the promotion
and protection of human rights in Asia and the
Pacific.
In impoverished societies the need to
wrest a living from Nature would seem to
come before all else. But, notes Kéba
M'Baye in Unesco's handbook on human
rights teaching for universities, it would
be false "to conclude that there is little
concern about rights and liberties in
societies which have not reached a certain
degree of satisfaction of their material
needs." Traditional Africa had a system of
rights and liberties in which we can see
"an undeniable affinity which links it to
the present system of human rights."
Right, burgeoning traditional house and a
modern building in Addis Ababa highlight
architectural affinities between ancient
and modern in Ethiopia.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
AN impoverished, pastoral, isolated
community needs a set of human
rights different from that which
applies to a highly sophisticated, industria¬
lized society with an integrated legal
system, a long-established judiciary and an
effective police and which belongs to the
principal international organizations.
This is the view of many Third World
thinkers who believe that the whole con¬
cept of human rights acquires a different
meaning in the context of traditional cul¬
tures and impoverished societies. This
belief stems from the assumption that,
even if human rights as listed in interna¬
tional declarations and conventions are
inherent in the very existence of man, the
specific interpretation of these rights
derives not from natural law but from the
social . organization of human beings.
Human rights are seen as dependent upon
the nature of the society that formulated
and enforces them.
Thus many Asian policy-makers consider
human rights to be a Western-oriented sub
ject of low priority for the developing coun¬
tries; as a result the vast majority of stu¬
dents in the Asian region, with the excep¬
tion of those attending Law School courses
in Constitutional Law, Civil Rights or Inter¬
national Law, receive no formal instruction
in human rights.
Of course, no policy-maker in the Asian
region would deny the values implicit in the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights or
the various international convenants;
however, the comprehensive nature of
these international instruments allows lee¬
way for varying interpretations and for find¬
ing justification for inaction on the grounds
of the specific social, political and econo¬
mic realities of a particular country.
The countries of the Asian region are
deeply proud of their traditions and culture
and all would agree that the concept of
human rights formed part of their tradition
and emerged in their struggle against colo¬
nialism.
Even though there is a tradition of human
rights in Asian culture, there is also a wide-
/ 4
spread feeling that the interpretations given
to certain abstract notions, such as the
dignity and worth of the individual, equa¬
lity, justice, freedom from want, etc., are
importations from the West. To present the
concept of human rights as an absolute
value whilst avoiding allegations of ethno-
centricity would be an extremely difficult
process in the Asian region. It may be
necessary, before a region-wide pro¬
gramme for the promotion of human rights
is established, to formulate an "Asian"
interpretation of human rights which does
not compromise the ideals of human rights
law.
The other assumption made by Asian
policy-makers with which advocates of
human rights must contend is that the stark
reality of poverty in some countries of the
Asian region militates against the exercise
of human rights.
Many Asian planners believe that talk of
human rights implies that a level of deve¬
lopment has been achieved which raises
man above the status of a biological entity
and bestows upon him the dignity of being
human. This, they maintain, involves the
most fundamental of all rights the right to
remain human and the right to some say in
the planning of their own survivaland that
therefore achievement of this level of deve¬
lopment must precede the adoption as
government policy of the wide-ranging
rights envisaged in international declara¬
tions and conventions.
To meet these objections, human rights
in the Asian region must be integrated with
the problem of development. They must be
involved in the process of planned social
change and must ensure that the public
power is exercised in favour of the deprived
and dispossessed. At present, human rights
and development remain distinct concepts,
especially in the context of educational
planning.
This approach to educational planning
resulted in low priority being assigned to
subjects of no technical value, and human
rights were, naturally, among the topics
that were completely ignored. More
recently, however, educational planners
have stressed the need for multidisciplinary
knowledge and an integrated approach to
the problems of development. Economic
development is no longer seen as the only
important aspect of planning and priority is
also being given to education aimed at
social and political development.
Research in the area of human rights is
necessary on topics of primary concern in
the Asian regionfor example, on min¬
ority and race discrimination and discrimi¬
nation against women, as well as on econo¬
mic rights. This research should also
include an assessment of the perceptions of
human rights among citizens of the various
countries of the region. This would make
for a better understanding of the attitude
towards human rights in the region and pro¬
vide a better framework for future action.
Radhika Coomaraswamy
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
nPH» 1 1 « te
W. . ! . te ; J
J
;7yvOfWVYYaYrW^y^ *w^WV^Wf^Vh,yvyywrTfyWvwwwWWW*1^
":
1
I
iwvVWVVV/yvvvVVVm> yVVVVWVVVY^VV^VVVVVVW1/ v^YyVYVVYTVYtW' VWí V VVYVW YVVVWWlW"WiWfflV]
nrWWIWym'vVw^
i '
'
«ívvvvvvVyYWWVVYYW
i
"l'vifrl'ri*.
|wv/yvvfTyVïWtY^'v^^
i < ' . '
^<nww\vyvvtyvww\f^^ ' ivifUt¡ihWi'imi'vlW¡
... CÜ
KAZDY IZIEN OSWIE¡UMIA
PuCrilASIAt J370 OSÔB. ITÔRrCH IIC7SI MfYOMAtOMO PUAY2ll.NAKt.A0 W ILOiCI <64l CCCITCK C I OiYIADA ILÜÍO UNI TRWANIA OiOZU
. YíCH'OI.Al 4 MILIONV orriR
The caption to this poster by the Polish artist Jerzy Skapski reads: "Every day at Auschwitz brought death to
2,370 people, and this is the number of figures represented above. The concentration camp at Auschwitz was in
existence for 1,688 days and this is the exact number of copies of this poster printed. Altogether some four
million people died at the camp." In a letter to the Unesco Courier, Jerzy Skapski wrote: "When I had finished
painting this poster I was afraid to put my name on itwhat meaning have names in comparison with people's lives?"
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The right
to be
informed
by Adam Lopatka
NEW human rights emerge as part of
a historical process rooted in deve¬
loping political, economic and cul¬
tural relations.
There are usually three distinct stages in
this process. Firstly, the idea of a new
human right is formulated and gives rise to
the conviction that it should be recognized.
Then, if this conviction becomes suffi¬
ciently strong and widespread, the right is
proclaimed by individual States, in docu¬
ments which apply to them alone, and is
later set forth in an international declara¬
tion. Both the documents and the declara¬
tion define the new right and affirm that ¡t
should be respected, but they do not make
It binding in national or international law.
Finally the new right is incorporated in
the constitutions of individual States as a
civil right, and an International convention
makes it binding under international law, at
least for those States which ratify the con¬
vention.
One example of this process is the right
to work and to social security. Born out of
men's aspirations towards equality, it won
recognition through the pressure of socia¬
list revolutions and was proclaimed in 1917.
Then, after long deliberation at the interna¬
tional level, it was incorporated in the Inter¬
national Covenant on Economic, Social
and Cultural Rights of 1966.
A similar train of events probably led to
the acceptance of the right to freedom of
religion, which can be traced back as far as
the Treaties of Westphalia of 1648, which
brought to a close the Thirty Years' War
and founded a new European order. The
treaties Included articles on religion which
confirmed the halt to the , Counter-
ADAM LOPATKA, Polish jurist, is director of
the Institute of State and Law of the Polish A ca-
demy of Sciences, Warsaw. He was Director of
the Institute ofPolitical Sciences at Poznan Uni¬
versity from 1967 to 1974.
Reformation in Germany and saved Ger¬
man Protestantism from destruction by re¬
affirming the 1555 Peace of Augsburg
(except for those articles which compelled
citizens to adopt the religion of their
prince).
. . The existence of the right of everyone to
be informed about human rights was rec¬
ognized for the first time in a major inter¬
national document when it was in¬
cluded in the Final Act of the Conference
on Security and Co-operation in Europe.
This Act, signed in Helsinki on 1 July 1975,
lists ten principles governing the relations
among the States taking part in the Confe¬
rence. As its seventh principle, the Act lays
down the respect for human rights and
fundamental freedoms, including freedom
of thought, of conscience, of religion or
conviction. The Final Act declares that the
signatory States will in all cases respect
these rights and freedoms in their mutual
relations and will strive jointly, separately
and in co-operation with the United
Nations, to promote universal and effective
respect for these rights and liberties.
The Final Act then declares that the
States participating in the Conference
"confirm the right of the individual to know
and act upon his rights and duties in this
field".
The signatory States have thus pro¬
claimed the existence of this human right at
the international and regional level and
have assumed responsibility for making the
efforts necessary to ensure that it is gen¬
erally respected. They did not, however,
transform this right into a norm of interna¬
tional law, since the Final Act of the Con¬
ference on Security and Co-operation in
Europe does not constitute a multilateral
treaty from the point of view of inter¬
national law: it constitutes a 'multilateral
declaration including moral and political
obligations.
.To further reinforce the legal status of w
the right to be informed about human r
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
> rights as a distinct human right, it would be
necessary to proclaim it without delay by a
declaration of the necessary standing, such
as a resolution of the United Nations Gen¬
eral Assembly or of Unesco's General Con¬
ference. It would thus be universally pro¬
claimed as a new and distinct human right.
Such a proclamation by the United
Nations or Unesco on a universal level
might encourage Member States of these
organizations to add this right to the
human rights in their own constitutions
and to act in accordance with it. Later, the
right could be incorporated in an internatio¬
nal convention and thus become a norm of
international law, in other words, attain the
highest legal status.
However, the right to be informed about
human rights canand should be seen
from another standpoint. For does it not
constitute the application of a more general
right, the right of everyone to hold opinions
without interference?
This right is set forth in the International
Covenant on Civil and Political Rights
which was approved by the General
Assembly of the United Nations on 16
December 1966 and came into force on 23
March 1976. As of 20 September 1978 it
had been ratified by 50 States. This right
constitutes a binding norm of international
law for all the contracting States.
The other States are bound to respect
this right and ensure its general and effec¬
tive recognition, in accordance with the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
approved by the General Assembly on 10
December 1948. Article 19 of the Declara¬
tion lays down that everyone has the right
to freedom of opinion and expression. This
right, which Includes the freedom to hold
opinions without interference and to seek,
receive and impart information and ideas
through any media and regardless of fron¬
tiers, also implies the human right of
everyone to know his rights.
Article 19 of the Covenant on Civil and
Political Rights also spells out that the right,
to freedom of opinion and expression in¬
cludes the freedom of any person to seek,
receive and impart information and ideas of
all kinds, either orally, in writing or in print,
in the form of art, or through any other
media of his choice.
The same Article states that the exercise
of this right carries with it special duties
and responsibilities and may therefore be
subject to certain restrictions provided by
law with the aim of ensuring the respect of
the rights or reputations of other persons,
the protection of national security, public
order or of public health or morals. It would
appear that these restrictions need not, and
should not, apply to the particular aspect
of freedom of opinion constituted by the
right to be informed about human rights. In
fact, taking cognizance of these human
rights cannot endanger other people's
rights or reputation, not to mention natio¬
nal security, public order, health or morals.
The status of this right will be reinforced
as and when an increasing number of
States ratify the Covenant on Civil and Poli¬
tical Rights and as other States display
more respect for the right. In many coun¬
tries this right already has the force of law,
and is sometimes even enshrined in the
constitution. The constitutions of many
States guarantee their citizens the right to
freedom of expression and opinion which,
without doubt, includes the right of the
citizens to know about their human rights.
The constitutions of some countries, for
example that of the Federal Socialist Repu¬
blic of Yugoslavia, proclaim the right of the
citizen to be informed of events in the
country and in the world which are of con¬
cern to his life and work as well as ques¬
tions concerning community life. The
Yugoslav constitution imposes the obliga¬
tion on the press, radio, television and
other public means of information and
communication, to inform public opinion in
a truthful and objective manner and to
publish opinions and information from
organizations and citizens of concern to
public opinion.
There can be no doubt that this obliga¬
tion to inform the public also concerns the
human rights which Yugoslav citizens
enjoy.
HE individual undoubt¬
edly has the right to know all the human
rights contained in the constitution of his
country. He certainly has the right to know
all the human rights which concern him
because they figure in a convention his
country has ratified. He also has the right
to know the human rights proclaimed by
the General Assembly of the United
Nations and the highest organs of the U.N.
specialized agencies. This applies notably
to rights proclaimed as universal "human
rights" whether or not they are defined in
his State's legislation or Included In inter¬
national conventions binding on it. This
has particular importance when a govern¬
ment denies its citizens certain rights and
fundamental freedoms.
In my view, the right to be informed
about human rights is less imperative when
it concerns rights which are only beginning
to make their appearance in the social
conscience, such as the right to develop¬
ment and certain rights proclaimed in regio¬
nal agreements and which concern only the
region in question, such as the right to
diplomatic asylum in the American conti¬
nent.
In speaking thus of human rights, I refer
to civil and political rights as much as to
economic, social and cultural rights. Those
rights which have been called the "rights of
solidarity" could be applied in this domain
if the international community decides to
proclaim them as human rights. The right
to be informed on human rights certainly
includes not only individual rights but also
so-called collective rights such as the right
of each people to self-determination and to
dispose freely of its wealth or natural
resources without infringing any obliga¬
tions arising from international economic
co-operation. These rights are established
by the two United Nations Covenants on
human rights.
However, a fundamental question arises:
does the right of the individual to be in-
i formed about human rights only concern
his rights or does it also include his
duties or at least the most basic ones?
Examples of such duties include the duty of
obedience to the law, of service to the
community and the nation and the duty of
children to help their parents and vice-
versa.
The answer is that the right to be in¬
formed about human rights does include
basic civic duties. Although these are not
explicitly mentioned in the international
instruments and are thus not specifically
included in the right to be informed, the
constitutions of many States, including all
the socialist countries, re-affirm the funda¬
mental duties of the citizens as well as their
rights. These constitutions are based on
the principle that there is close inter¬
dependence between citizens' rights and
their duties, while the Final Act of the Con¬
ference on Security and Co-operation in
Europe clearly declares that the members
of the Conference confirm the human right,
to be informed of rights and duties.
The right to be informed of rights and
duties can be exercised in different ways. It
is, first of all, the duty of the State not to
prevent citizens from enjoying this right. In
reality, the application of this civic right
imposes concrete obligations on a State,
which must in its official gazette or journal
publish the texts of certain laws and inter¬
national treaties on human rights to which
it is a contracting party. It is also obliged to
agree to the publication of other texts con¬
taining information on human rights that it
has ratified or accepted.
The State should also accept that there
should be radio and television program¬
mes, books and scientific articles dealing
with human rights and citizens' rights. Fur¬
thermore, it should authorize the activities
of political parties and various social orga¬
nizations whose activities include inform-
ting the public about all or some of these
human rights. It is equally Important that
the State should allow the circulation on its
territory of information on human rights
published by universal international institu¬
tions such as the United Nations, Unesco,
or the International Labour Organisation
and by others, such as regional organiza¬
tions to which the State concerned
belongs.
Finally, it should be pointed out that
there are no special guarantees to ensure
the respect of the right to be informed
about human rights. This right enjoys the
same guarantees as all the other human
rights. The most that can be said is that it is
easier to observe than some others, thanks
to the advanced development of the mass
media in the modern world.
Adam Lopatka
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A challenge
for the
universities
Sketch for a poster for
the 7th Film Festival
on Human Rights,
held in Strasbourg
(France) in 1978.
by Thomas Buergenthal
MANKIND'S profound yearning
for human rights and human dig¬
nity is a reality of contemporary
international life of major significance. And
this hope for a more humane life and world
is not limited to a few nations or peoples; it
is universal in character.
The ever-increasing legal and political
influence of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights is evidence of this pheno¬
menon. Further proof is provided by the
growing number of human rights treaties
based on the Declaration and the inability
of governments to oppose the establish¬
ment of international institutions designed
to promote and protect human rights. Edu¬
cators who fail to recognize and act on the
pedagogic implications of these develop¬
ments neglect one of the principal moral
and political forces shaping the aspirations
and policies of our era.
If education is to provide the intellectual
basis for understanding and resolving
important contemporary societal problems,
education at all levels will have to deal with
and teach about human rights. Article 26 of
the Universal Declaration of Human Rights
gives expression to this proposition when it
declares that "education shall be directed
to the full development of the human per¬
sonality and to the strengthening of res¬
pect for human rights and fundamental k
freedoms". f
THOMAS BUERGENTHAL is professor of
international law at the Scool ofLaw of the Uni¬
versity of Texas and chairman of the Human
Rights Committee of the U. S. National Commis¬
sion for Unesco. An editor of the American
Journal of International Law and of the Revue
des Droits de l'Homme:' Human Rights Journal
he has written widely on international law and
human rights subjects. He is the co-author of
International Protection of Human Rights
(1973), the basic U.S. university textbook on
this subject and International Human Rights and
International Education (1976), a source-book
for school teachers and administrators.
Drawing Luis Pascal, Portugal © International Institute of Human Rights, Strasbourg, France
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
, This injunction is forcefully reiterated in
the educational guidelines proclaimed in
Unesco's principal pronouncement on the
subject the 1974 Recommendation con¬
cerning Education for International Under¬
standing, Co-operation and Peace and
Education relating to Human Rights and
Fundamental Freedoms. The Recommend¬
ation makes learning and teaching about
human rights one of the basic components
of education for international under¬
standing.
In the universities, human rights subjects
can be taught within the framework of
many disciplines. This is certainly true of
medicine, history, philosophy, education,
sociology, political science, law, as well as
the physical and biological sciences. It is
also true of literature, the arts and econo¬
mics. The effect of technological advances
on the enjoyment of human rights, for
example, is a subject which scientists, en¬
gineers and architects need to address.
Faculties of medicine should explore the
human rights issues posed by the delivery
and cost of health care, genetic and drug
experiments, organ transplants, and the
employment of psychiatry and other bran¬
ches of medicine to further non-medical
objectives. (See article page 29).
Our knowledge of the forces and
causes that lead to torture, genocide, racial
and religious discrimination, poverty and
starvation has thus far proved inadequate
to prevent or eradicate these evils. Solu¬
tions to these problems need to be sought
by historians, sociologists, psychologists,
economists, political scientists and
lawyers. Philosophers and theologians and
the works of poets and artists can provide
valuable insights into the universal support
for certain basic human rights concepts;
this is a topic that social science research
has thus far largely neglected. Research
directed towards solving serious human
rights problems can be stimulated by
university-level teaching about human
rights.
F particular impor¬
tance, moreover, is the teaching of human
rights in education faculties and teacher-
training institutions. Unless future teachers
have an understanding of basic human
rights principles, problems and proposed
solutions, the primary and secondary
schools will not be able to do what the Uni¬
versal Declaration demands of them: to
contribute, through education, "to the
strengthening of respect for human rights
and fundamental freedoms". The many
large-scale violations of human rights that
continue to occur in all parts of the world
serve as a sad and constant reminder that
education to strengthen human rights and
fundamental freedoms is itself in need of
significant strengthening.
In the three decades that have elapsed
since the United Nations adopted the Uni¬
versal Declaration of Human Rights, the
international community has created a
normative and institutional framework
designed to implement the principles of
the Declaration. Today the international
human rights code comprises, in addition
to the U.N. Charter and the Declaration,
the two United Nations covenants on
human rights, which deal with civil and
political rights as well as with economic,
social and cultural rights; the Convention
on the Elimination of All Forms of Racial
Discrimination; and the Convention on the
Prevention and Punishment of the Crime of
Genocide.
HESE documents are
supplemented by the Unesco Convention
Against Discrimination in Education, the
International Labour Organisation (ILO)
treaties relating to discrimination in
employment and related rights, the interna¬
tional agreements to safeguard the rights
of women, the conventions dealing with
refugees and stateless persons, as well as
the treaties outlawing all forms of slavery
and the slave trade. The more recent Con¬
vention on the Suppression and Punish¬
ment of the Crime ofApartheid should also
be included in this list. The same is true of
the various humanitarian law treaties, parti¬
cularly the four Geneva Conventions of
1949 relating to the protection of human
rights in times of war and armed conflict.
This international human rights code,
which requires governments to respect the
basic rights of all human beings under their
control, is in existence today only because
of the pressure of public opinion generated
by mankind's shared commitment to the
protection of human rights in all parts of
the world. But denials of human rights do
not end just because there are laws prohibi¬
ting them. Many governments continue to
commit serious violations of basic human
rights.
While international institutions cannot
stop all of these deprivations, they can pre¬
vent some. The covenant on civil and politi¬
cal rights and the racial convention each
establish special international supervisory
bodies to watch over compliance by
governments. Similar institutions have
been created by the ILO and Unesco. The
U.N. Commission of Human Rights has
now also developed procedures for the
investigation of large-scale denials of
human rights.
The most extensive experience with the
enforcement of human rights rules has
been accumulated thus far by some regio¬
nal institutions for the protection of human
rights, particularly those established within
the framework of the Council of Europe
and the Organization of American States.
The development of these norms and
institutions as well as the ways in which
they can prevent violations of human rights
are issues that need to be taught and stu¬
died in the universities of all nations. As a
subject of university study, "international
protection of human rights" has a great
intellectual appeal because it is a topic of
universal concern that cuts across major
ideological, political and cultural bound-'
aries. Its study can provide valuable insights
into the functioning of the international
system and the prospects for solving most
basic international as well as human pro¬
blems. That is why human rights education
is an ideal vehicle to infuse university insti¬
tutions with "an international dimension
and a global perspective" as urged by the
1974 Unesco Recommendation.
The specific subject matter of internatio¬
nal human rights courses will differ, to a
greater or lesser extent, from discipline to
discipline. An international law course dea¬
ling with this subject should emphasize the
transformation international law has under¬
gone and is undergoing in order to respond
to the human rights concerns of the inter¬
national community.
In such a course the students should
learn that prior to the Second World War
international law left States free, with some
minor exceptions, to treat their nationals as
they saw fit. One consequence of this doc¬
trine was that measures taken by a govern¬
ment against its own citizens, however bar¬
baric or oppressive, were deemed to fall
within that nation's domestic jurisdiction.
This meant that other governments lacked
a valid legal basis to complain formally
against such measures. Under pre-World
War II international law, the offending
governments thus enjoyed international
immunity to violate the rights of their own
people and were, on the whole, under no
obligation to account for this action to any
other country or international organization.
After exploring the disastrous conse¬
quences of the above-mentioned doctrine,
law students should study the effect of the
entry into force of the U.N. Charter, which
imposed human rights obligations on all
Member States. In this connexion, they
should also learn how the adoption of the
Universal Declaration, followed by other
international instruments, strengthened
these obligations.
Taken together, these documents have
internationalized the subject of human
rights by establishing international human
rights standards governing the manner in
which States may treat human beings,
whether their own nationals or not.
Governments engaging in large-scale viola¬
tions of the human rights proclaimed in
these instruments can today no longer
validly claim that these measures fall within
their domestic jurisdiction; other govern¬
ments and the international community as
a whole have a legitimate interest to insist
that these violations cease. Moreover,
various human rights treaties now in effect
outlaw specific violations of basic human
rights.
Law students should also learn about the
need for and development by the U.N., the
ILO and Unesco of institutions and proce- k
dures for dealing with violations of human f
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A profusion of giant murals,
sponsored by community
organizations and groups and
painted by local amateurs as
well as professional artists, is
brightening the walls of New
York and turning the city's
streets into a vast open-air art
gallery. This huge, multi-ethnic
mural enlivens the once drab
intersection of Pitt Street and
Grand Street.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
, rights. This will give them an opportunity
to assess the contribution made by the
U.N., the ILO and Unesco; it should also
enable them to explore the reasons why
these bodies have thus far not proved to be
very effective in putting an end to many
serious violations.
Students need also to be made aware
that there now exist a variety of non¬
governmental organizations engaged in the
promotion of human rights on the inter¬
national plane. Amnesty International
(London) is probably best known. But
there are others which do equally important
work. Among these are the International
Commission of Jurists (Geneva) and the
International League for Human Rights
(New York) as well as lesser known groups
sponsored by professional, religious and
labour organizations. A number of govern¬
ments have recently also established inter¬
national human rights departments in their
foreign ministries.
It is highly instructive, in this connexion,
to study the modus operandi of the inter¬
governmental and non-governmental Insti¬
tutions, and to examine the legal, political,
economic, social, and cultural obstacles
that they encounter. Such an inquiry
should lead, in turn, to a discussion of
other steps that might be taken to streng¬
then the institutional capacity of the inter¬
national community to deal with violations
of human rights.
But central to any meaningful teaching
of this subject is the "internationalization"
of human rights, which has brought with it
the "humanization" of international law.
Critical to the teaching of international
human rights is an understanding of the
legal and political significance of the fact
that- violations of fundamental human
rights, wherever they may occur, have
become a subject of legitimate concern to
the entire international community. Such
an approach allows an instructor to deal
with international human rights not only as
a legal abstraction, but as a subject having
legal, political, economic, social and cultu¬
ral implications for individual human beings
as well as for the entire human family.
Teaching about human rights and how
to assure that they are not violated can be
exciting and highly instructive for the stu¬
dent and the professor. It can also contri¬
bute to the wider observance of human
rights and, hopefully, to the eradication of
genocide, torture, discrimination and the
other deprivations that have caused untold
suffering to generation after generation.
University-level human rights education is
therefore a must in and for every country
that professes to believe in human dignity
and a better tomorrow for all mankind.
Thomas Buergenthal
Drawing by Jacques Gamelin (1738-1803) from Nouveau recueil d'ostèologie et myo/og/e dessiné d'après nature.
Photo © Snark International, Paris
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The
doctors' dilemma
by Louis Cotte
EVERYONE in the modern world is
bound to feel in some way concern¬
ed with the issues raised by the
application of human rights to health and
medical care. There are two reasons for
this. On the one hand, rapid changes in
medical technology have brought the prob¬
lems of human rights in medicine sharply
into focus. On the other, people today are
better informed than they were and are
consequently more aware of what is at
stake.
People are inundated with information
about the possibilities and limitations of
medicine, whereas only a few decades ago
doctors worked in virtual secrecy and
patients had to make do with a trickle of
publications, aimed at the mass market and
often ill conceived.
The general rise in living standards has
imposed greater demands on medicine, but
one of its beneficial side-effects may have
been to encourage the public to take a hard
look at these demands. Questioning of this
kind was a rarity in the more passive and
resigned societies of yesterday.
This change in attitudes is all to the
good, reflecting as it does a more mature
approach to health problems. There is a
greater awareness of the considerable diffi¬
culties involved in applying modern medical
techniques to all their potential "con¬
sumers". There is a keener appreciation of
the responsibilities of the community and
the individual in a field of human activity of
fundamental importance to everyone. This
is a factor for progress on a par with the
scientific and technical breakthroughs
which have changed the face of medicine.
LOUIS COTTE is professor of the law relating to
medicine at the Faculty of Medicine of the Uni¬
versity of Besançon (France). He is also hono¬
rary dean of the university's Faculty ofMedicine
and Pharmacy and head of the neurological ser¬
vice at the regional hospital centre based in
Besançon.
One way of approaching human rights in
medicine is through the study of medical
law and ethics. These subjects are taught
in faculties of medicine, and thus the study
of human rights is not totally absent from
the training of doctors. This is one of the
conclusions to emerge from a world survey
on the teaching of human rights and pro¬
fessional ethics in faculties and schools of
medicine.
The survey was carried out in 1977-1978
under the auspices of the International Ins¬
titute of Human Rights and at Unesco's
request. A questionnaire was sent to 955
faculties or schools of medicine in 107
countries. By 31 May 1978, 145 of them
had sent in replies.
Analysis of the replies shows that the
overwhelming majority (126) of these insti¬
tutions provide instruction in medical
ethics, and that almost half of them (69)
provide human rights teaching. On the face
of it these figures are impressive. However,
it should be noted that replies have so far
only been received from a small number of
the institutions to which the questionnaire
was sent. Furthermore, human rights are
not taught as a separate subject but as part
of the instruction in a whole range of disci¬
plines. Only 61 institutions (42 per cent)
indicate the existence of courses specially
devoted to human rights and medical
ethics. This is a low figure.
The replies to another question also give
some cause for anxiety. The schools and
faculties were asked whether their staff
teaching human rights and medical ethics
were sufficient in number. Forty-nine
(more than one-third of those which sent in
replies) answered "no", while 25 did not
answer the question at all. Asked whether
teaching staff were sufficiently trained, 32
answered in the negative and 31 did not
reply at all.
All the same an effort is undoubtedly
being made. The subjects most widely
taught relate to the right to life (above all
abortion), the right to death (euthanasia)
and the doctor-patient relationship. As far
as the latter subject is concerned, there is
particular emphasis on informing the
patient as a necessary step towards gaining
his consent for treatment, on respect for
private life, on respect for medical secrecy
and on the responsibility of the doctor.
Almost three-quarters of the respon¬
dents (72 per cent) consider that human
rights teaching should be further devel¬
oped. The American continent is most in
favour of this (85 per cent) ; Europe the
least (52 per cent).
Which subjects should be given more
attention? Top of the list come the rights of
the dying, followed by those of the "ordi¬
nary" sick person, the right to be properly
informed (diagnosis, treatment, risks,
etc.), the right to participate in decision¬
making, the rights of the individual as an
experimental subject (for therapeutic or
other purposes) and the rights of the indivi¬
dual to free and equal access to medical
treatment.
By and large it seems that relatively slight
attention is being paid to the role and res¬
ponsibility of the doctor and medical staff
in exceptional situations such as those
giving rise to the practice of torture or
situations occurring in wartime.
So much for the institutions. But what of
the public? It would be interesting to know
how the sick themselves conceive of their
rights and how they judge the behaviour of
doctors. For it is valid to ask whether
human rights teaching as it exists today
(and perhaps even as the medical schools
would like it to be) is properly adapted to
"demand" to what the public today
expects of its doctors.
In France, for example, the situation
appears to be far from satisfactory. The
"Ordre des Médecins", a body which pro¬
motes medical ethics and has drawn up the
code of professional conduct, is inclined to
criticize the faculties of medicine for not
teaching this subject. At the same time,
professors of forensic medicine are reluc¬
tant to base their teaching on an official
code which is manifestly out-of-date and t
ill-adapted to the needs of modern society. Y
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
In spite of its references to illustrious
figures of the past such as Hippocrates,
France's official code of medical ethics
today appears to reflect the opinion of the
medical profession (or at least of most doc¬
tors) on matters which are of much greater
concern to the "users" of medicine than to
the doctors themselves. It is as if the law
had been written by the magistrates whose
job is to enforce it, rather than by represen¬
tatives of the citizens who must respect it!
The study of human rights should be
based on a reversal of this situation and
should emerge from a process of reflection
involving society as a whole. It should
result from a confrontation and a blending
of opinions of everyone concerned, medi¬
cal staff and patients alike. The starting
point for research should be an assessment
of the demands of a rapidly changing
society.
In other words, the teaching of human
rights in faculties of medicine should not be
a matter for doctors alone, nor, come to
that, for professional jurists and moralists.
As part of their education, trainee doctors
should be given the opportunity to meet
people who do not belong to the medical
profession. Only in this way will they find
out what it is like to be on the receiving end
of medical treatment and be encouraged to
be self-critical about the effects of their
actions on patients. These effects are not
all confined to the technical aspects of
treatment.
To be really valid, the study of human
rights in faculties of medicine should not
consist of the formal academic teaching of
. arid texts nor the examination of codes of
professional ethics. Even if such codes are
updated (assuming that such an entreprise
is worthwhile) they only constitute one
aspect of a many-sided subject.
It is vitally important that the doctors of
the future should learn to think, through¬
out their careers, about those human ques¬
tions whose importance and complexity is
bound to increase. These human aspects
of medicine will be increasingly decisive in
improving the quality of life, a task in which
health and medical care are the foundation
stones.
Louis Cotte
Chernyshevsky
A pioneer of social reform
by Eduard Dnieprov
IN the history of every nation, there are
names which symbolize whole chapters
of social development, and which stand
out like beacons along the mainstream of
social and scientific progress. In mid-
nineteenth century Russia, one such name
is that of Nikolai Gavrilovich Cherny¬
shevsky, the 150th anniversary of whose
birth is celebrated this year.
At the age of twenty-seven, Cherny¬
shevsky was already a leading figure
among those seeking to liberate Russia
from the burden of oppression, and exercis¬
ed a strong influence on Russian culture
and social thought. Seven years later, he
was arrested, "removed from circulation"
as the police report put it, and deported to
Siberia, where he remained in exile for
more than twenty years.
Chernyshevsky was born on 24 June 1828
in the provincial city of Saratov, on the
Volga, where his father was a priest. The
local ecclesiastical seminary, which he
entered at the age of fourteen, could not
satisfy his quest for knowledge, and he
quickly outstripped not only his contempo¬
raries, but many of his teachers as well. The
seminary was his first contact with social,
and more particularly with educational re¬
alities, the shortcomings of which were to
become the earliest targets of his criticism.
After obtaining a degree in history and
philosophy at the University of Saint
Petersburg, he returned to Saratov to teach
Russian language and literature at the local
high school. It was here that he came to
understand that the distortions of the edu¬
cational system merely reflected the distor¬
ting conditions of life in Russia generally,
and that radical changes in the latter were a
prerequisite to any educational reform.
In the hope of finding broader scope for
the expression of his opinions, and a wider
battleground for the realization of his
ideals, he returned to Saint Petersburg. For
the next ten years, in scientific, journalistic
and revolutionary circles alike, and in the
simultaneous roles of philosopher, econo¬
mist, historian, writer, literary critic and art
theorist, Chernyshevsky threw all his
efforts into the struggle to transform
society.
EDUARD DNIEPROV, Sower historian, is a
member of the Research Institute of General
Pedagogy at the U. S. S. R. Academy of Pedago¬
gical Sciences. He is the author ofmany publica¬
tions on the history of pedagogy.
"Political authority, material well-being
and education", he wrote, "are inseparable
from each other. No one who lives in
poverty can develop his mental capacities;
no one whose intellectual capacities are
stunted can participate in the exercise of
power: no one who is deprived of political
power can free himself from oppression,
that is, from poverty and ignorance."
For Chernyshevsky, the root causes of
cultural backwardness in different peoples
and social groups were not to be found in
the peculiarities of their natural environ¬
ment or their heredity, but rather in the
unfavourable and oppressive, man-made
social, economic and political circum¬
stances of their lives. His analysis of the
factors which determine the formation and
development of the human personality
made a considerable impact on educational
theory not only in Russia, but throughout
the world.
Chernyshevsky did not deny that heredity
had a part in the creation of the personality,
but he believed that social factors played
the predominant role. Nor did he believe, as
did his predecessors, that these factors
were merely the product of environmental
conditions, or that these conditions were
somehow immutable. Man, he considered,
was not a passive creature of his sur¬
roundings, but an active agent, capable of
reconstructing his own environment. The
goal of education, which he conceived as a
major force for social transformation,
should be to produce human beings who
were indeed active in that way.
He was convinced that the humanities
and the natural sciences should form an
' integral part of general education and that
specialized and general education should
not be seen as alternatives. The content of
education was modified by scientific pro¬
gress, so that what had yesterday been a
matter for specialists alone might well
today become a subject of general educa¬
tion. Chemyshevsky's major contribution
to the development of pedagogical theory
lay in his insistence that a scientific
approach should be adopted to the selec¬
tion of the content of education.
Chernyshevsky considered teaching to be
one of the most noble and far-reaching of
human activities, the product of which, he
said, was "not something apart from man,
but man himself"; it was nothing less than
the construction of the future.
Eduard Dnieprov
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO
Publisher to the world
In 32 years, 7,000 titles in 70 languages
by Edward Wegman
FOUR or five times a week, every week
of the year, a book is published by
Unesco or under its auspices some¬
where in the world. That makes a cascade
of more than seven thousand titles, pub¬
lished in some seventy languages, since the
founding of Unesco in 1946.
The subject matter is diverse, ranging
alphabetically from Art to Zoology or, in
accordance with the Universal Decimal
EDWARD WEGMAN is a formerjournalist and
radio commentator who entered book pub¬
lishing in 1960 In the United States. As a mem- .
ber of Unesco's staff he has been .connected
with the Organization's Book Development
Programme, International Book Year, The Inter¬
national Copyright information Centre and, at
present, the Unesco Press.
Classification system, from Official Publica¬
tions to Geography, Biography and His¬
tory. A bibliography issued by the Organi¬
zation in 1971 to mark twenty-five years of
publishing already employed some two
hundred different subject headings. It list¬
ed more than two thousand authors, start¬
ing with a specialist on Arab affairs named
Abdelbacky and ending with a jurist called
Zweigert; in between it cited many- of the
leading literary and political personalities of
our epoch, all of whom contributed their
writings to illustrate Unesco's goals.
More than a third of the books deal with
education; the next largest group of titles is
concerned with science, while the social
sciences, culture and communication each
represent about ten per cent of the output.
Not all these books and periodicals are
published by Unesco itself. Nearly half of
them are issued by agreement with private
publishers, non-governmental organiza¬
tions and even governments through their
National Commission for Unesco. Nor is
this by any means the totality of books and
periodicals relating to Unesco and its activi¬
ties; innumerable publications about
Unesco have been issued by other bodies,
both public and private. At the moment the
direct output by Unesco as a publisher is
approximately one hundred and fifty titles a
year as well as a dozen or so periodicals.
In the world of books, Unesco is a
publisher with a difference. Not many
publishers consistently distribute all their
publications in several languages in almost
one hundred and fifty countries throughout j
the world. In fact, you are reading these I
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco through
its publications
Organized within the framework of a series of "Unesco Book
Weeks" being held in major cities throughout the world, an
exhibition on the theme "Unesco Through its Publications" was
inaugurated at the Organization's Paris headquarters on 26
September 1978.
More than simply a display of books and periodicals, the exhibition
aimed to present a living picture of all Unesco's activities in the
publishing field, ranging from books produced by Unesco's
precursor, the International Institute of Intellectual Co-operation, in
which such famous personalities as Einstein, Thomas Mann, Paul
Valéry and Salvador de Madariaga collaborated, to Unesco's very
latest publications.
Photo shows Unesco's Director-General Mr Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
and, on his right, Mr Leonard Martin, President of the Executive
Board of Unesco, visiting the exhibition.
Photo Michel Claude, Unesco
t words in one of Unesco's most popular
' publications and in one of the nineteen lan¬
guages in which it is published. Few pub¬
lishers can claim so diverse a readership.
But if the Unesco Courier is a best-seller
as a periodical, with more than two and a
half million readers around the world, the
Organization has had a number of re¬
sounding successes with books as well.
Learning to Be, a pioneering study of
new directions in education, has been
translated and published in thirty-five
languages, and the Unesco Source Book
for Science Teaching has sold more than
one million copies in various languages and
editions and is still going strong.
Conceived as a do-it-yourself book for
high school science classes in war-torn
areas, the original Source Book explained
how to use a burnt-out light bulb as a test-
tube, and how to improvise laboratory
experiments. Its latest version has kept
pace with the growth of and changes in
science teaching. It describes experiments
in traditional physics and chemistry as well
as in biology and earth and space sciences.
Unesco's principal purpose as a pub¬
lisher is to make available material which it
alone can compile because of its unique
international resources and status. In addi¬
tion, Unesco is in a position to invest time,
effort and money in worthwhile projects
regardless of considerations of profitability.
One such enterprise is the Index Transla¬
tionum, a compilation of all the translations
published annually in all languages
throughout the world. Of inestimable inte¬
rest to librarians and publishers, the Index
has a limited circulation in proportion to the
costly international effort required to pro¬
duce it. Nevertheless, it has been going on
since 1948, carrying on the war-interrupted
enterprise initiated in 1932 by Unesco's pre¬
decessor of League of Nations days, the
Institute for International Intellectual Co¬
operation.
Another, perhaps even more impressive
international effort is now under way with
the General History of Africa. Experts from
all over Africa have joined with historians
from many other parts of the world to
undertake the mammoth task of putting
together for the first time a complete and
dispasàionate account of events in Africa
from the dawn of mankind to the present
day. Thanks to supplementary financial
support from Member States, the History
will appear not only in the vehicular lan¬
guages of the continent, English and
French, but also in at least one African lan¬
guage as well as in Arabic.
The idea of creating an international edi¬
torial committee for a single major project
had already been tested successfully with
the creation, a number of years ago, of a
Commission for a Scientific and Cultural
History ofMankind. The fruit of this project
was a six-volume study that has already
appeared in English, French, Greek, Serbo-
Croat, Slovene and Spanish.
Although many Unesco books and perio¬
dicals are aimed primarily at clearly defined
groups of specialists in the fields of educa¬
tion, science, culture and communication,
Unesco publications are becoming more
and more concerned with the broader areas
of interest of our time and are being direc¬
ted more particularly towards the educated
general public. This has involved the crea¬
tion of a number of new, interdisciplinary
series two of which, Insights and Ap¬
proaches, are just getting under way (see
inside back cover). Another series, World
Tribune, is at the planning stage.
Unesco also undertakes important activi¬
ties in the field of copyright aimed at pro¬
tecting the rights of the developing coun¬
tries and facilitating the transfer of copy¬
right. Unesco has sponsored a Copyright
Information Centre to promote the transfer
of rights to developing countries.
This interest in the exchange of know¬
ledge goes back to the very beginnings of
Unesco. One of the first international ins¬
truments approved by the Organization
was the Beirut Agreement, adopted by the
General Conference of 1948. With its sister
agreement, adopted in Florence in 1950,
the Beirut Agreement is intended to
remove obstacles to the free flow of books
and other material of an educational, scien¬
tific or cultural nature.
From this to copyright was but a step;
and from copyright to programmes for the
promotion of publishing in the developing
world was but one more. The effort to sti¬
mulate book production began with a
meeting of experts in Asia, in 1966, and
this was followed by similar meetings in
Africa, in 1968, in Latin America, in 1969,
and in the Arab States, in 1972. These
meetings assessed the difficulties each
region faced with respect to book
production and distribution and came up
with concrete suggestions on how to
solve some of the more urgent problems.
The climax to these efforts to mobilize
the book world was International Book
Year 1972, proposed by the U.S.S.R. and
voted unanimously by the Unesco Member
States. More than one hundred and thirty
countries drew up and executed national
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
programmes to promote the creation, pro¬
duction, distribution and reading of books.
Many of these programmes have con¬
tinued through the years since 1972.
One earlier result of the book develop¬
ment programme was the establishment by
the Japanese of a Book Development Cen¬
tre in Tokyo which, since 1967, has been
training personnel and devising new type¬
faces for Asian languages; Unesco has pro¬
vided assistance for the courses. Several
years ago, the Centre also established an
ad hoc mobile team of experts which has
visited various countries of the Asian
region offering intensive training in diffe¬
rent aspects of book production and distri¬
bution. This supplements the courses orga¬
nized by Unesco itself through its Regional
Cultural Centre in Karachi.
The Tokyo Centre, now known as the
Asian Culture Centre for Unesco, also
developed what has become known as the
Asian Co-publication Programme. The
basic idea was that the Centre would pre¬
pare a master edition of a children's book
which could then be translated by partici¬
pating countries into their national lan¬
guages using the same illustrations. Since
colour illustrations are the most expensive
part of a children's book this was an effec¬
tive way of cutting costs. The first editions
were all printed in Japan, with each partici¬
pating country sending its typeset trans¬
lation to the Centre.
The idea was refined in ensuing years
and the Centre now produces a master edi¬
tion in English which is supplied, free of
charge and accompanied by films of the
illustrations, to Asian countries wishing to
publish the work. The subject matter is
chosen by an international committee of
book experts from various countries of the
region. A Unesco representative also fre¬
quently participates. Four volumes entitled
Folk Tales from Asia have already been
published in at least fourteen Asian lan¬
guages, while two others on Asian
festivals have been issued.
This programme has been so successful
that a number of European publishers have
brought out translations of the publica¬
tions. And similar programmes are under
consideration to provide children's books
for Africa and Latin America. Through the
combined efforts of publishers in a region,
it will thus be possible for each country to
possess more and better children's litera¬
ture, which will at the same time promote
regional understanding.
Another long-term effort to promote
understanding of different cultures was
-started by Unesco in 1948 with its Litera¬
ture Translation Programme. Its purpose
was and is to promote wider knowledge of
works of literature in little-known lan¬
guages. Nearly 450 titles have been pub¬
lished; most of them have been transla¬
tions into English and French,, but some
translations from European languages into
less widely used tongues have also been
made. The books, from sixty different lan¬
guages, cover both classics and contempo¬
rary writing and Unesco is proud to have
included in its translation series
three authors who went on to win Nobel
Prizes for Literature: the Greek poet
Seferis, the Japanese novelist Kawabata
and the Spanish poet Aleixandre.
While the original impetus for the pro¬
gramme was the promotion of knowledge
of the literary heritage of different peoples,
it has also had the effect of improving the
quality of translation. Of what use would it
be to put into English or French a Persian
classic, say, if the work lost in the process
the literary excellence which had led in the
first instance to the decision to translate?
Unesco therefore seeks out the best trans¬
lators it can find and, as a further guaran¬
tee, submits their completed work to other
linguists to ensure that standards are being
maintained. All of this fits in, of course,
with Unesco's activities to improve the
status of translators generally, in¬
cluding the promotion of an international
declaration on that subject.
To be truly effective, Unesco needs to
convey its message in the language of each
country. That is why, in addition to spon¬
soring translations of world literature,
Unesco makes a special effort to promote
the translation of its own publications.
Some assistance may be necessary in
arranging for translation and publication. It
is here that the Member States' National
Commissions for Unesco often play a major
role. The Commissions take over the task
of finding translators and of seeking out
national publishers.
Unesco is exploring many other ways of
imparting knowledge: microfiches, art
slides, magnetic tapes, films, records, etc.
Together with books and periodicals, these
make it possible for more and more men,
women and children in every corner of the
earth to learn what international experts
have to say on problems that touch each
one of them.
Edward Wegman
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Recent
Unesco books
Suicide or Survival? The Challenge of
the Year 2000 (See opposite page).
Global Marine Pollution: An Overview,
by Michael Waldichuk. (No. 18 in Unesco's
Intergovernmental Océanographie Commis¬
sion technical series) 1978, 96 pp. (12 F).
The Spanish Educational Reform and
Lifelong Education, by Ricardo Diez Hoch-
leitner, Joaquin Tena Artigas and Marcelino
García Cuerpo. 1978, 112 pp. (14 F); Insti¬
tutional Leadership for Educational
Reform: the Atlantic Institute of Educa¬
tion, by Gary J. Anderson and Joseph A.
Lauwerys. An innovatory project in
university-level teacher training in Canada's
Atlantic region. 1978, 49 pp. (Nos. 31 and 38
in the International Bureau of Education's
"Experiments and Innovations in Education"
series).
Environmental Effects of Arid Land
Irrigation in Developing countries. Edited
by G.F. White. Based on the conclusions of
an international workshop held in Alexandria
in 1976. 1978, 67 pp. (22 F); Management
of Natural Resources in Africa: Traditio¬
nal Strategies and Modern Decision¬
making. Based on the conclusions of a
workshop on the management of natural
resources in western Africa, held in Dakar in
1975. Prepared in co-operation with the U.N.
Environment Programme. 1978, 81 pp.
(26 F) Nos. 8 and 9 in Unesco's "MAB Tech¬
nical Notes" series. (MAB = Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere programme).
Soil Map of the World. Sheet V-1:
Europe (flat) 50 F; Sheet V-2 Europe (flat)
50 F. Sheets V-1 and 2 folded in binder:
100 F. (The folded sheets with binder are
only sold with corresponding volume, now in
preparation. This will be supplied and in¬
voiced on publication). Compiled by the
Food and Agriculture Organization of the
United Nations (FAO) and published by
Unesco.
Applications of Numerical Heat Trans¬
fer, by E.F. Nogotov, B.M. Berkovsky and
W.J. Minkowycz. Co-published .with the
Hemisphere Publishing Corp., Washington,
and the McGraw Hill Book Co., who have
exclusive sales rights in the U.S.A. 1978,
142 pp. (90 F).
Indicators of Environmental Quality
and Quality of Life (No. 38 in Unesco's
"Reports and Papers in the Social Sciences"
series) 1978, 96 pp. (12 F).
Letters
to
the editor
FREEDOM AND HUMAN RIGHTS
Professor Karel Vasak, Director of
Unesco's Division of Human Rights and
Peace, has sent us the following comments
in answer to the letters from J. S. Gutman
and E.R. Kermode, published in our issue of
July 1978.
In defence of liberty, the international
community has banned slavery and similar
institutions and practices. This is the thrust
of innumerable clauses in international ins¬
truments, among which should be mentio¬
ned the Convention on Slavery of 1926 and
the International Convention on Civil and
Political Rights of 1966. It would be difficult
to maintain that this constitutes an infringe¬
ment of the liberty of anyone who, in the
name of individual freedom, claims the right
to become a slave. In fact, anyone who
wanted to exercise such a "right" would
always do so in the belief that he had the
means and the power necessary to resume
his liberty if he so wished. This might be so
on some occasions, but in most cases he
would be powerless to regain his freedom.
This calls to mind the famous remark of a
19th century French thinker that out-and-out
libertarians would do well to ponder : "Bet¬
ween the weak and the strong, it is liberty
that oppresses and the law that liberates."
Must we always be mistrustful of the law,
seeing in it only a means of limiting the free¬
dom of the individual the freedom to be a
slave, to refuse education, to dispense with
the services of a lawyer when accused of a
serious crime?
A few years ago, I attempted to define
human rights with the aid of a computer. I
fed into it some 60,000 expressions taken
from texts of all kinds and origins; I wanted
to find out which terms occurred most fre¬
quently in order to be able to establish a defi¬
nition of human rights. To my great surprise,
by far the most frequently occurring word
was the word "LAW", that is, of course, law
aimed at establishing a legal framework
which would make the exercise of freedom
possible for all and prevent violations of
liberty law both national and international.
It is, surely, precisely in international law
that we should be able to find answers to the
questions raised by your readers and which,
it must be admitted, it cannot always pro¬
vide, thus leaving it open to the individual
State to remain or to become the arbiter.
From this point it is but a step to the conclu¬
sion that international organizations, such as
the United Nations and Unesco, are not only
useful but a necessity; this step is one we .
must surely all be agreed to take together.
Karel Vasak
Paris
WRONG WAY ROUND
Sir,
The photo on the back cover of your
December 1977 number on Arab culture was
printed in reverse, along with the Arabic text
featuring on it. However, this in no way
detracts from the intrinsic quality of the
issue.
M. Nussmann
Cologne
Federal Republic of Germany
VERNE THE VISIONARY
Sir,
I find it quite incredible that the scientific
world should refuse to admit that
nineteenth-century visionaries had even the
glimmerings of foresight, on the grounds
that the twentieth century made a reality of
what was merely adumbrated in the nine¬
teenth.
I am amazed that Mr Broch ("Letters to
the Editor", May 1978) should flatly deny
that Jules Verne was a visionary.
The number of unfeasible inventions pro¬
duced in the nineteenth century was
legion certainly enough to prove that Jules
Verne's choice of those which had a future
was inspired by uncanny foresight.
Take the case of another French writer
who set out to imagine the future, Albert
Robida. He also took selected inventions
from his own time and projected them into
the future. But everything in Robida turned
out wrong: we don't fly by flapping wings;
the single-seat dirigible balloon does not
exist. Only moving footpaths are now in use,
and even they are somewhat dwarfed by the
immensity of the one created for the 1900
Universal Exhibition in Paris.
I maintain that Jules Verne was a visionary
in the face of all those scientists who forget
that he hardly ever went wrong when pre¬
dicting the future of carefully selected inven¬
tions.
Does Mr Broch know that in his last book
(L'Etonnante Aventure de la Mission Barsac,
published in English as Into the Niger Bend
and City in the Sahara) Verne foresaw the
use of big transport planes and the impor¬
tance of telegraphy. Of course these inven¬
tions already existed, but only as toys. In this
connexion it is worth remembering that
Marshal Foch once observed that flying was
a sport that could have no possible military '
application.
Alain Bombard
Le Brusc
France
THE UNESCO COURIER
IN MALAYALAM?
Sir,
I work in the Press Trust of India, which is
the leading news agency in our country, as
sub-editor/reporter. I am also a freelance
writer in English and in Malayalam which is
my native tongue.
I am a regular reader of the Unesco Cou¬
rier, but I am sorry to find that it is not pub¬
lished in Malayalam. In this context I would
like to put Malayalam into proper perspec¬
tive. Malayalam is spoken by about twenty-
three million people in Kerala, the southern¬
most State of India. What is more, of the
States of India Kerala has the highest rate of
literacy over sixty per cent. Hence Kerala,
more than any other State, deserves an edi¬
tion of the Unesco Courier in Malayalam.
K.S.R. Menon
New Delhi, India
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Suicide or
survival ?
Amadou-Mahlor M'Bow
Lion Bolnler-Palun
Trygve Bra If« I i
Schuyler Chopin
Luti Echeverría
André Fontaine
Buck mimte r Fuller
Paolo Gram
Jeny Grolowiky
Oiwoldo Guayaiamin
Tewf>k Al-Hakim
Han Sufin
Paul-Marc Henry
Mrchiko Inukai
Michel Joberf
Alfred Kattler
Vlad¡m¡r Kemenov
Prem Kirpal
Tchcwdar Kuranov
Takeo Kuwabara
Sean MacBride
Mircea Malilla
M. L. Mehrolra
Hephzibah Menuhi
Philip Noel-Baker
Jean d'Oi
Nancy Reeve t
Tran Van Khe
Peter Uil.nov
Bernard Zehrfufi
The challenge
of the year 2000
A new Unesco series
INSIGHTS, a major new Unesco series focussing on important
themes and critical choices facing mankind today. By creating
INSIGHTS, Unesco hopes to inform a wide public, as well as specia¬
lists, about the contributions of many different disciplines to the
study of world problems.
The first title in the series, Suicide or Survival? The Challenge of
the Year 2000, has just been published. In it, thirty eminent artists,
politicians and thinkers from all over the world engage in lively and
informal debate on a wide range of vitally important topics, in¬
cluding: nuclear disarmament dwindling natural resources
pollution the cities of the future problems of employment, hou¬
sing, education, health and food energy needs for the year 2000.
210 pages
FORTHCOMING TITLES
Biology and Ethics
Violence and its Causes
38 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33-, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keestnglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Cf chenne Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CYPRUS. "1 1AM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 ( Permanent display); Zahramcni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prapje 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahnr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/Munchen. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1, Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztársasag utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson&Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book Et Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing and Distribution Co., 28, Vassal Shirazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. -
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koener"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martmus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrece,
P.O. Box 1721 Christ-church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Sarah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Klngsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop end General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chlttampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgstan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Fórbundet, Skolgrand 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rámistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236. -
TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen
Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok:
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
- UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Station,
New York, N.Y. 10016. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljublana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
OCTOBER 1978 from
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
news
unesco
Teaching about
human rights
"Everyone has the right to life, liberty
and security of person... No one shall
be held in slavery or servitude... no one
shall be subjected to torture or to cruel,
inhuman or degrading treatment or
punishment... No one shall be subjected
to arbitrary arrest, detention or exile...
All are equal before the law and are
entitled without any discrimination to
equal protection of the law... Everyone
has the right to freedom of movement
and residence within the borders of each
state... Everyone has the right to leave
any country, including his own, and to
return to his country... Everyone has
the right to a nationality... Everyone
has the right to freedom of thought,
conscience and religion... to freedom of
opinion and expression..: to education...
to a standard of living adequate for the
health and well-being of himself and of
his family".
These lines are taken from the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, adopted
unanimously just 30 years ago by the
United Nations General Assembly,
which denounced all distinctions of any
kind, whether founded on race, colour,
sex, language, religion, opinion,
national or social origin, property or
birth.
But anyone today reading the
newspapers or following the news on
radio or television is struck by the
disparity existing between these
principles and what actually happens in
practice.
The Declaration was proclaimed as "a
common standard of achievement for all
peoples and all nations, to the end that
every individual and every organ of
society... shall strive by teaching and
education, to promote respect for these
rights and freedoms..."
As part of its celebrations of the
thirtieth anniversary of the Declaration,
Unesco recently organized an
international congress on the teaching of
human rights in Vienna, Austria, from
12 to 16 September. More than 300
participants from sixty Member States
and observers from about fifty non¬
governmental organizations agreed that
human rights teaching should be
developed at all levels of education,
both in and out of school, to provide a
form of lifelong education for men and
women in all countries. They
emphasized the need to recognize that
all human rights, economic, social,
cultural, civil and political as well as
individual and collective rights, were of
equal importance and indivisible. They
also defined the aims of such teaching:
to encourage attitudes of tolerance,
respect and solidarity that are inherent
in human rights; to develop in each
individual an awareness of the ways in
which these rights can be made part of
social and political reality, both at
national and international levels.
Besides the creation of a voluntary fund
for developing knowledge about human
rights through education and
information, the participants proposed a
six-year plan in which the curriculum,
methods, structures and teaching
materials for human rights education
were set down in detail. The plan
suggests, among other things, the
organization of courses and seminars for
lawyers, judges, trade unionists,
doctors, psychiatrists, psychologists,
sociologists as well as members of police
forces, and directors of penitentiaries
and military establishments. It stresses
the importance of the media for
stimulating public awareness regarding
respect for human rights and
recommends the setting up of an
international information and research
centre on human rights.
Twelve sites to be preserved
Hewn out of the rock: the church of Saint
George at Lalibela, Ethiopia. as part of
the world heritage
Twelve cultural and natural sites in
seven countries have been chosen as the
first locations to be placed on a world
heritage list, for preservation for the
benefit of all mankind.
They are: the National Historic Park of
L'Anse aux Meadows and the Nahanni
National Park in Canada; the
Galapagos Islands and the historic city
of Quito, Ecuador; the Lalibela rock-
hewn churches and the Simien National
Park, in Ethiopia; Aachen cathedral,
Federal Republic of Germany; the
historic urban and architectural area of
Cracow and Wieliczka salt mines, in
Poland; the island of Gorée, Senegal;
and two National Parks in the United
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
StatesMesa Verde in Colorado and
Yellowstone in Wyoming.
The decision was taken at the second
session of the World Heritage
Committee held in Washington D.C.
from 5 to 8 September. The Committee
is composed of fifteen of the forty
Unesco Member States which have
ratified the World Heritage Convention
of 1972. * « \'
HIM -.-A*"
By including the sites on the world .
heritage list, the Committee ensured that
special steps will be taken to preserve
them from deterioration or neglect so
that they may be enjoyed by mankind
for centuries to come. \mká
A thirteenth site submitted for
consideration, the Ichkeul National
1
Park in Tunisia, was set aside for lack
of technical data in support of its
nomination as required under the
convention. The park, a waterfowl
reserve of exquisite scenic beauty, will
be considered by the Committee when it
meets again next year. estimai
A frigate bird and its young, samples of the
rare species of wildlife peculiar to the
Galapagos Islands.
Photo Unesco-ÍUCN-Eibl Eibesfeldt
Unesco to host international
youth conference on
liberation of Southern Africa
More than 500 students and other young
people from all parts of the world will
take part in a world conference on the
liberation of Southern Africa to be held
next February at Unesco Headquarters,
Paris.
Organized by the major youth and
student international non-governmental
organizations, the conference will take
place from 19 to 22 February under the
auspices of the United Nations Special
Committee against Apartheid in co¬
operation with Unesco. It will also be
attended by observers from other United
Nations agencies and organizations
concerned.
Major themes for discussion at the
conference include: the system of
apartheid and its effects on the political,
economic, social and cultural lives of
the people of South Africa, Zimbabwe
and Namibia; actions against
collaboration with the racist regimes of
those countries, and the role of youth
and students in the worldwide
movement of solidarity with the
oppressed peoples of Southern Africa.
Announcement of the conference was
made jointly in Paris by Unesco
Director-General Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow and Ambassador Leslie Harriman
of Nigeria, Chairman of the United
Nations Special Committee against
Apartheid. They said that the
conference is another in the series of
joint activities which Unesco and the
Special Committee are undertaking in
connexion with International Anti-
Apartheid Year.
A world soil map
for management
of resources
How can the Earth's limited resources
be exploited to feed its ever-growing
population, the majority of whom are
today under-nourished? This is one of
the vital problems to be tackled in
present-day world development.
An immediate need is for more
knowledge about world soil resources,
and action to ensure maximum
productivity by preventing processes of
soil deterioration. For that purpose it is
necessary to analyze, compare and
collate the data available.
This will now be possible thanks to the
publication of a world soil map which is
the result of seventeen years of
collaboration between Unesco and the
Food and Agriculture Organization of
the United Nations (FAO).
The work was undertaken firstly in an
attempt to overcome the lack of
correlation that characterized the field
of soil cartography in the early Sixties,
various countries having established
their own nomenclatures, survey
methods and systems of classification.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
At the same time many of the newly
independent countries of the developing
world felt the need for soil maps as a
basis for decisions on the agricultural
activities which formed an essential
element in their economies. These
countries were at a loss to know what
language to adopt or what choices to
make, and the advice given by foreign
experts who visited them was influenced
by the various schools to which these
experts belonged.
To prepare the world map based on a
common terminology and nomenclature
acceptable to and understandable by all,
no less than 10,000 existing soil maps,
highly diverse in format, scale,
projection, language and terminology
were collected. Some covered whole
continents, others small regions; some
were limited to the area of a particular
development project. At the same time
it was necessary to adopt a common
legend and cartographic presentation.
Lastly, correlation surveys had to be
carried out in the different regions and
continents.
The soil map of the world makes
possible a preliminary appraisal of the
world's soil resources. It will also
greatly facilitate the work of many
specialists in agriculture, hydrology and
mineral prospection.
The map is composed of eighteen colour
map sheets in format 76 X 110 cm.,
scale 1 : 5,000,000, and a legend sheet,
accompanied by a series of ten
explanatory volumes. Each of these
volumes covers a major region and
contains a description of soil resources
and of their distribution, with particular
emphasis on the use currently being
made of the land and its suitability for
the application of modern agricultural
methods. Information is also given on
climatic, physiographic, geological and
lithographical zones, types of vegetation
and population distribution as well as
statistical data.
Science Ministers
meet in Belgrade
A Conference of Ministers responsible
for Scientific and Technological Policy
in the European and North American
region was held in Belgrade from 1 1 to
16 September. Over 200 delegates from
33 countries examined the rapid changes
which had taken place in this field since
their previous meeting in 1970, the new
issues which had emerged, the present
state of international co-operation and
prospects for the future.
-While in Belgrade for the Conference,
the Director-General visited the
newspaper Politika. To the right of Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow is Dr. Ivo
Margan, Vice-President of the Federal
Executive Council of Yugoslavia, who
chaired the Conference; to his left is
Mr. Vukoje Bulatovic, Director of
Politika.
Increased mobility
the key to meeting
world's engineering
manpower needs
The engineer of the future must be
ready to switch fields, to change from
the industrial sector to the academic
sector or vice versa, or even to move
from one country to another.
Only in this way, a Unesco panel of
experts concluded recently, can the
world's engineering manpower needs be
met. However, they warned, this
increased mobility must be planned with
the full agreement of all concerned,
particularly where the movement takes
place across national boundaries.
Otherwise it may constitute a "brain
drain" and become a negative rather
than a positive factor in the solution of
manpower problems.
As a first step toward improving the
international mobility of engineers and
other higher technical personnel, data
and definitions regarding manpower
requirements must be made more
comparable from one country to
another, the experts said, and they
recommended a series of measures on
the part of Unesco towards this end.
Lack of adequate data, it was generally
agreed, is one of the chief obstacles to
accurate forecasting of future needs as
far as engineers are concerned. Another
is the rapid rate of technological
change.
"How do you train people for
occupations that don't even exist yet?"
one participant asked.
The meeting was called to examine the
role which research in manpower needs
can play in the development of
engineering education and to advise
Unesco on the promotion of
international co-operation in this field.
It was attended by manpower planners,
engineering educators and economists,
as well as representatives of the
International Labour Organisation, the
United Nations Industrial Development
Organization and the World Health
Organization.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The necessity for flexibility in
engineering education was stressed by
Mr. Michel Bâtisse, Unesco Deputy
Assistant Director General for science,
in his opening remarks to the meeting.
"Engineers must be given the kind of
education and training which will enable
them to play their roles in a world
which is constantly evolving", he said.
"This is why we have today a
worldwide movement of expansion and
reform of higher technical training".
During the past 15 years, he added,
Unesco in co-operation with the United
Nations Development Programme had
aided in the establishment and
development of more than 60
engineering schools and other higher
technical institutes in nearly 50
countries. Satisfactory planning of their
future programmes of instruction,
however, depended on a much more
accurate analysis, both quantitative and
qualitative, of the dynamic needs of the
societies they served.
Since this was a question which
interested many other agencies of the
United Nations system as well, he
added,' steps were being taken to
establish an inter-agency committee on
the training of technical personnel. In
addition to Unesco, UNDP, ILO,
UNIDO and WHO, it was proposed to
include representatives of the Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO), the
International Telecommunications
Union (ITU) and the International
Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA).
Informatics and man
Developing countries still at grips with
the problems of industrialization are
simultaneously facing a challenge of the
post-industrial era: the massive growth
of information and the devel¬
opment of new ways of handling it.
The many implications of this
information explosion were examined at
an Intergovernmental Conference on
Strategies and Policies for Informatics
which was held from 28 August to 6
September at Torremolinos (Spain).
Convened jointly by Unesco and the
Intergovernmental Bureau for
Informatics, the Conference was opened
by King Juan Carlos of Spain, who was
accompanied by Queen Sophia.
Informatics has become an
indispensable tool for solving the
problems involved in carrying out
development plans. This means that
nations must develop their capacities in
this field if they are not to lose control
of management processes. Furthermore,
informatics is much less costly and
complicated than is often imagined:
with the advances likely over the next
few years, it is probable that individuals
will have access to an increasingly broad
range of data banks and will be able to
call upon informatics in many different
aspects of daily life.
At the Torremolinos Conference,
delegates from some 80 states reviewed
the present situation and future
prospects in this field, and discussed the
prerequisites for the efficient use of
informatics : the training of both
specialists and users, the evaluation and
acquisition of technology, industrial
capabilities, research and development,
and information on informatics. They
also studied its various applications,
particularly ways in which countries can
improve their facilities in this sphere,
the impact of informatics on social and
cultural development, and the flow of
data between countries this last
question raising such problems as
protection of individual privacy. Lastly,
the importance was stressed of bilateral,
regional and international co-operation.
In this connexion, Unesco's Director-
General, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow,
said at the closing session: ''The
international community must try to
find new ways of co-operating in the
field of informatics, taken in its
broadest sense; we shall have to
reconsider both the dimensions of such
co-operation, with a view to expanding
it, and the content of co-operation with
a view to giving it a better adapted and
more equable form". Unesco, he
concluded, would reallocate its resources
and review its methods of action to that
effect.
World literacy
a call for
greater efforts
Latest forecasts indicate that between
1970 and 1990 the world illiteracy rate
will have fallen from 32.4 per cent to
25.7 per cent; but if current tendencies
continue, the absolute number of
illiterates will have increased in the same
period from 742 million to 814 million.
These figures were cited by the Director-
General of Unesco, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, at the ceremony held at
Unesco Headquarters marking
International Literacy Day
(8 September) during which he presented
the Mohammed Reza Pahlavi Prize
founded by the Shah of Iran and the
Nadezhda K. Krupskaya Prize, donated
by the U.S.S.R. Government.
The first of these prizes was awarded to
the Mwanza Functional Literacy Project
in Tanzania, a four-year programme
which brought literacy to two million
adults. The Krupskaya Prize this year
went to the Pilot Literacy and
Complementary Education Unit of the
commune of Cambinh (Vietnam), which
had associated 60 per cent of the
village's 3,500 inhabitants in adult
education activities.
Among those who received honourable
mentions for the Pahlavi Prize were an
American woman pioneer, ninety-nine-
year-old Dr. Welthy Hensinger Fisher,
who was a teacher in China in 1906 and
who, fifty years later, on Gandhi's
advice, founded Literacy House in
Lucknow, India. Other mentions went
to the General Directorate of Literacy
and Adult Education in Honduras, and
the Literacy and Adult Education
Section of the United Arab Emirates
Education Ministry. Honourable
mentions for the Krupskaya Prize went
to the Mutual Aid and Development
Centre of Burundi, the Andhra Mahila
Sabha of Hyderabad, India, and the -
Syrian Federation of Women.
Mr. M'Bow stressed the insignificance
of the sums devoted to literacy teaching
in the world, pointing out that the
resources needed existed but were
invested in undertakings which were not
only unproductive but constituted a
threat to the future of mankind: some
40 to 60 billion dollars were spent
annually to develop techniques of
destruction and deathmore than twice
the amount spent on education in the
developing countries.
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Arms tragically outstretched, a man Is about to fall beneath the bullets of the firing squad, an anonymous
victim of the inhuman machine of war. In this central figure of his great painting The Third of Muy 1808. Goya
has, concentrated all his horror and loathing of war and oppression and all his passion tor liberty. The whole
work cries out in prolest against the denial of human rights, beginning with the most fundamental right of
all the right to life (see article page 15).
]]>
</page>
</document>
