<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074700eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
AUGUST 1983 - 6 French francs
EDUCATION
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live ...
Photo L. Solmssen, United Nations
© TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO Unlocking the door to speech
The problems facing persons suffering from physical or mental handicaps
are exacerbated in the developing countries where such handicaps are often
the result of bad diet and poor standards of hygiene. Children who are deaf
from birth are a particularly distressing case. Fortunately, big advances in
techniques have made it possible to teach them how to formulate words by
means of special imitative methods, as in this photo taken at a school for
deaf children in Trinidad and Tobago. Next year Unesco is organizing a
meeting of experts on the education of the deaf to evaluate the latest ad¬
vances in this field (see the Unesco Courier for January and June 1981).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
AUGUST 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 8 - 1983 - OPI - 83-1 - 401 A
page
LEARNING FOR A LIFETIME
A challenge modern societies cannot afford to ignore
by Ettore Gelpi
EDUCATION FOR INTERNATIONAL UNDERSTANDING
Unesco's Associated Schools Project
THE CHILDREN'S WAY
by Marcel Canetti
THE ALAJUELA CHARTER
A world human rights congress in Costa Rica
13
14
15
18
WHAT'S NEW IN SCIENCE TEACHING?
by Mircea Malitza
SOWING THE SEEDS OF DEMOCRACY
India's youth parliament competition
by Amar Nath Rai
20 CAN CREATIVITY BE TAUGHT?
Aesthetic education in Bulgaria
by Krestu Goranov
22
26
28
29
30
TOWARDS EQUALITY FOR WOMEN IN EDUCATION
by Maria Eliou
ISLAM'S QUR'ANIC SCHOOLS
by Abdul Aziz El Koussy
'GHANA'S UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY
by Frank Obed Kwami
A MODEL SCHOOL FOR BLIND CHILDREN
SOME FUTURE PROSPECTS
by Boris Kluchnikov
34
2
UNESCO NEWSROOM
A TIME TO LIVE...
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO: Unlocking the door to speech
/N the May issue of the Unesco
Courier we examined the outlook
for and major trends in educa¬
tion; in this present issue we focus at¬
tention on possible strategies of ac¬
tion in this complex field.
Education is a fundamental human
right and a key element in overall
world development; yet despite the ef¬
forts and resources deployed, too
many obstacles still hinder educa¬
tional advance. To overcome these
obstacles, Unesco is relentlessly pur¬
suing the task of analysing the prob¬
lems of education and implementing
solutions on a world scale. The ex¬
amples given throughout these pages
of educational projects to which
Unesco is bringing its active
assistance and support provide some
idea of the solid progress being
achieved in a wide range of Member
States. 	
The international network of
"Associated Schools", in which
children are encouraged to take their
first steps along the path to peace and
international understanding by learn¬
ing to respect the identity of other
peoples, in all their diversity, is but
one reflection of Unesco's goal of
linking education with life, and at
every stage of life. And this
strategy creation of the strongest
possible links between school and
society so as to favour group and in¬
dividual fulfilment is an underlying
theme of all our articles.
Though it was touched upon in
May, readers may be surprised that
no mention is made here of the strug¬
gle against illiteracy. This is because it
is our intention, in the nearfuture, to
draw up a comprehensive, detailed
balance sheet of what has been ac¬
complished in this vital area.
Our purpose in opening this issue
with an examination of "lifelong
education" is to stress the need for a
thorough democratization of educa
tion. The improvement of existing
forms of teaching the transmission
of knowledge, professional training,
arousal of general awareness and
the elimination of any form of
discrimination against any particular
group, necessary though these may
be, are not enough. All educational
possibilities, whether traditional or
modern, formal or non-formal, ex¬
isting or yet to be, must be increased
and intensified.
Only by adopting this strategy of
action, one which Unesco has follow¬
ed since its inception, will it be possi¬
ble to end the compartmentallzation
and eliminate the injustices of the
world's education systems.
Front cover: A student of architecture at
work in an UNRWA (United Nations Relief
and Works Agency for Palestine Refugees in
the Near East) school in Jordan. Photo
Gérard © ANA, Paris.
Back cover: a calligraphy competition , in
Tokyo. Photo Charlier © ANA, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Preparation for working life is an essential function of education systems and a major element in lifelong education.
Just as important as its practical value is the contribution it can make to social and cultural development. This
opening up of education to the practical realities of the contemporary world is far from being a feature of all educa¬
tion systems. Under its major programme on Education, Training and Society, Unesco is giving active support to
efforts being made to strengthen the links between education and the world of work. Above, pupils at work in
the welding workshop of a technical training school north of Beirut, Lebanon.
Learning for a lifetime
A challenge modern societies
cannot afford to ignore
by Ettore Gelpi
LIFELONG education has been
a constant of the history of
mankind, but there is a ten¬
dency to think of the history of educa¬
tion in terms of formal pedagogy and
the written word. Yet the history of
education, which in reality is the
history of lifelong education, is a totali¬
ty of actions, policies, theories, Uto¬
pian visions and rival educational pro¬
jects and is the record of profound con¬
tradictions between these different
elements.
Today, lifelong education is faced
with a number of obstacles. Reform of
educational structures is often blocked
by social and juridical resistance.
Opening up the school to the communi¬
ty and introducing productive work in¬
to the curriculum, giving legal status to
the transition period between school
and work, making the work experience
itself an educational experience, all this
seems to present difficulties for the
educational and productive systems.
ETTORE GELPI is in charge of Unesco's ac¬
tivities in the field of lifelong education. He is
vice-president of the committee on the
sociology of education of the World Sociology
Association and the author of Stona
dell'Educazione (Milan, 19671, A Future for
Lifelong Education /Manchester University
Press, 1979) and Institutions et Luttes
Éducatives (Pans, 1982).
Examples of the constraints imposed
by the productive system include the in¬
ternational division of labour (very un¬
just for certain countries), the
fragmentation of the labour market,
inequalities in the training provided by
businesses of differing size and type,
and the rigid social divisions of the
place of work.
Other constraints affect the educa
tional system and act as a brake on the
extension of lifelong education a
standstill in the resources allocated to
education, inadequacy of the initial
and further training of teaching staff
with regard to creative and productive
activities, and difficulty in recruiting
non-teaching educators (scientists,
technicians and qualified tradesmen
and agricultural workers).
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Legal obstacles to the reform of
educational systems are also far from
being minor ones. Laws and regula¬
tions continue to confine education
within a given space and, to some ex¬
tent, to a given age bracket and to
militate against making education
available anywhere and at any age. The
process of making the necessary provi¬
sions (scholarships, evaluation criteria,
sabbatical leave, alternation between
periods of study and of work) to render
the right to education throughout life
effective for all is slow. Furthermore,
as the educational span grows longer
and claims to the right to adult educa¬
tion grow stronger, psychological,
social and cultural resistance is
encountered.
This resistance to the democratiza¬
tion of educational systems manifests
.itself in the creation of parallel educa-
' and the planning of lifelong education
of placing it in an overall social and
cultural context rather than treating it
in isolation.
In some countries, social policies are
linked with educational policies
relating to certain periods of life or cer¬
tain categories of workers (the
establishment of crèches, education for
the unemployed, for migrant workers
and the elderly). The public response to
these measures is mixed; on the one
hand these educational services are
considered useful, but, on the other,
there is a feeling that the real problems
(the status of women, lack of jobs, the
marginalization of immigrant workers,
the loneliness of the elderly) remain
unresolved.
Positive factors working in favour of
new educational policies and activities
Physical education and sport are being practiced by an ever-gowing number of men and
women. Much remains to be done, however, especially in the organization of school
systems, to achieve a harmonious balance between bodily and mental activity. While
80 to 85 per cent of children in developed countries now receive physical education at
school, it is estimated that in the developing countries 80 per cent of children do.not.
The correction of this imbalance is one of the aims of Unesco's programme for Promo¬
tion of Physical Education and Sport.
tional structures alongside the public
educational institutions and the in¬
troduction of "innovations" in assess¬
ment criteria which in effect represent
no more than the re-introduction of
selection in a barely disguised form.
Hence the importance in policy-making
are, however, to be found both within
and outside the educational system.
New social relationships and an in¬
creasing extension of the time devoted
to education give rise, at all stages of
life, to new educational and cultural
demands which are associated with a
Painting, literature, dance, music, the theatre, the cinema are all forms of expression
which must take their place in the education of children and adults. Encouragement of
creativity, both among individuals and groups, is essential to their involvement in
cultural life. Within the framework of its programme on Creation and Creativity, Unesco
is developing methods of sensitizing and educating the public in relation to the arts.
Left, in a school in Niger.
desire to participate in the running of
society, with the enjoyment of the
aesthetic heritage, in short, with a
refusal to be left on the sidelines of
social and cultural life. The continuing
ferment and change in the fields of in¬
formation and communication are also
playing a part in stimulating and in¬
creasing this demand.
Creation, research, production (and
not simply the transmission of
knowledge) can provide an answer to
the alienation of the nature of the ac¬
tivities, in particular the educational
activities, of non-working time. It is
often difficult, however, to establish
proper communication between the
world of creation and research and that
of institutionalized education, even
though this is becoming more and more
necessary.
It is probable, therefore, that the
educational centres of the future will
evolve in two different but not oppos¬
ing directions. On the one hand there
will be the need to improve techniques
for the transmission of knowledge
(programmed learning, audio-visual
systems, documentation, etc.), and on
the other hand research, creation and
production will become, or rather will
become again, the key elements of
education.
This notion of a convergence bet¬
ween cultural creativity and education
has great attraction for children,
adolescents and adults; the theatre,
dance, music, the cinema seem likely to
achieve pride of place in lifelong educa¬
tion, though this will not be easy. The
degree of liberty accorded to creative
members of society, especially those
associated with educational activities,
the boldness or the conformity they
display, will be reflected in the evolu¬
tion of education.
Scientific research is a special form
of creative activity; it is also a domain
in which, owing to lack of proper com¬
munication with researchers, institu¬
tional education often seems to lose its
way. A lot is said about research at
schools and universities, but this is only
a pale copy of scientific and
technological research, both as regards
method and content. Unfortunately,
research centres are often even more in¬
accessible to the young than are centres
of production.
It is no easy task to construct and
breathe life into centres of education in
which various forms of creation, pro¬
duction and research can take their
place; yet the popularity of circus
schools in several countries as a means
of providing general as well as profes¬
sional training is but one example of
the attraction of a form of education in
which different forms of appren¬
ticeship are combined.
Between the acquisition of know¬
ledge and the full flowering of aptitude
for creation, research and production
there is a long road to travel. And for
this goal to be attained, many places of
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
AFRICA
Unesco-assisted projects
E present below and on pages 18, 22 and 30 a small selection of
educational development projects which Unesco is undertaking
in different parts of the world. In addition to Unesco's par¬
ticipation, these projects are largely financed by the national govern¬
ments concerned and by the United Nations Development Programme
(UNDP) with, in some cases, contributions from other sources.
MALAWI: Preparing a Literacy Programme
The Unesco-assisted project for Malawi, which became operational in
1981, aims to help Malawi prepare for a large-scale literacy programme
which the country intends to launch in the near future. Project
achievements to date include the production of a primer and teaching
charts, the training of some 250 literacy instructors and 75 supervisors,
and the establishment of a National Literacy Board and a National
Literacy Centre.
MOZAMBIQUE: The National Institute for the
Development of Education
A UNDP-Unesco project is assisting the country's National Institute for
the Development ofEducation in 4 main fields: educational research and
evaluation; curriculum development and teacher training; the develop¬
ment ofdocumentation centres; coordination ofeducational activities in
the context of the new national education system. Several programmes
have already been successfully carried out, notably in applied linguistics
research and the development of educational documentation.
RWANDA: The National Pedagogical Institute and the
University of Rwanda
The project, aided by France and Belgium, was launched in 1966 to pro¬
vide training and advanced trainingfor secondary school teachers. Since
then training has been expanded as far as Master 's degree level and since
1981 there has been a programme of on-the-spot preparation for doc¬
torates. Over 450 teachers have been trained so far.
ZAIRE: Post-University Training
Since 1975 Unesco and the Department of Higher and University Educa¬
tion of Zaire have been collaborating on doctoral and post-doctoral
training at Zaire's 3 universities Kinshasa, Kisangani, Lubumbashi.
The objective is to enable Zaire personnel to take over from foreign
teachers in mathematics, chemistry, biology, physics and geography.
learning and many different periods of
learning time are essential, coupled
with a new relationship between
general and professional training.
The fragmentation of the
space/time/age elements of education
will result in the withering away of old
educational structures and the birth of
new ones. Whether there is to be an ar¬
ticulation, a dialectic between the dif¬
ferent educational structures (formal
and out-of-school, initial and continu¬
ing, professional and general, institu¬
tional or self-instruction) or a further
compartmentalization will depend on
the depth and quality of participation
of the people in the running of society.
Self-instruction, the oldest form of
education known to man, is also evolv¬
ing rapidly. Advances in communica¬
tion systems applied to the educational
field, the often uncontrollable prob¬
lems of urbanization, the increasing
cost of .transportation, the weak
linkage between training structures and
professional activity, migration bet¬
ween town and country and from one
country to another, the increase in non-
working time (leisure, unemployment,
underemployment, retirement) are all
encouraging the development of new
forms of self-instruction.
Self-instruction and education for all
and by all mean that every individual,
institution or association (trade union,
political, cultural, social) not only has
access to education but can also play an
educative role.
Education and self-instruction, in¬
dividual and collective, in educational
institutions, in social and community
life, at the place of work, all these dif¬
ferent elements of educational
space/time provide, perhaps, a clearer
idea of the concept of lifelong
education.
In the world of tomorrow will
lifelong education provide an adequate
response to the growing demand for
education from individuals and peoples
caught up in the reality of the con¬
tradictions of everyday life? Teaching
people how to live with these contradic¬
tions is perhaps the principal task of
education today. Education of an
"ideal" man, education which is but
adaptation, or education limited to
strictly professional ends will no longer
satisfy the individual, the community
or the countries of the world called
upon, often at very short notice, to face
up to radical changes affecting
economic, social and cultural life.
Who will be responsible for initiating
policies and activities to further
lifelong education? Individuals, the
creative members of society, social and
cultural organizations, professional
educators, all will have a part to play,
whether in educational institutions, at
the place of work, in the social life of
the community, or in the field of
leisure. Everyone, whether professional
educator or not, will have to contribute
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
to the preparation of policies, legisla¬
tion, planning renewal, the administra¬
tion and the evaluation of education.
Furthermore, it will be for those prin¬
cipally involved in the educational pro¬
cess, whether children, adolescents or
adults, to define the objectives, the
philosophy and the values of educa¬
tion. Those involved in the educational
process, from the school to lifelong
education, arc becoming more and
more numerous and. present a challenge
which existing educational and produc¬
tive systems have often been reluctant
to take up.
Lifelong education means making
full use of a society's human resources.
It is an education which meets in¬
dividual and collective aspirations and
needs and whose end is action. It is in
the search for this full use of human
resources that education stands reveal¬
ed as the sensitive nerve point of rela¬
tions between the social classes, bet¬
ween "central" and "peripheral"
countries and between individuals
fighting for individual and collective
human rights and the forces of
repression.
Ettore Gelpi
Games play an important educative role in
childhood, helping to develop personality and to
build up manual dexterity, a sense of logic and
creative ability. They are both a means of expres¬
sion and an apprenticeship for life. Above, a study
in concentration in a school in the German
Democratic Republic.
Photo © Thomas Billhardt. Berlin, German Democratic Republic
Refugees form one of largest of the world's educationally disadvantaged
groups. There are 10 million refugees in the world of whom 5 million are
in Africa. Under its programme for Promotion of the Right to Education of
Particular Groups, Unesco aims to make the general public aware of the
special problems of refugees and to develop the educational possibilities
open to them. Above, a young refugee in Malaysia.
Photo J. Isaac. Unicef
It's never too late to learn! The extension of non-working time (leisure,
retirement, unemployment) offers increasing opportunities for self-
instruction. Left, knowledge in stacks in a street of the old city of Tunis.
Photo Dominique Roger, Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TO FEED
The mother feeds the baby
FARMER
The farmer ploughs the land with the oxen
allaiter (v.)
la maman allaite le bébé
Jl/mhWuHuO MB^^Jum,-.
cultivateur ie (n. m.)
le cultivateur travaille la terre avec
les b¬ufs
production la (n. f.) PUitS. le (n. m.)
la coopérative agricole achète à
bon prix la production de coton
d'Amadou
les femmes tirent l'eau du puits
WELL
The women draw water from the well
PRODUCTION
The farm co-operative buys Amadou's cotton
production for a good price
Words in pictures
Guy-José Bretones, a French specialist in education for rural development, has produced an illustrated
dictionary of basic French (Dictionnaire du Français Fondamental en Images pour les Ruraux, 1 982)
as a means of helping Third World rural populations to acquire knowledge which they can use to solve
problems in agriculture and in family and social life. The dictionary is intended as a reference book of
integrated education for families and rural communities, for cadres in rural development (teachers,
nurses, social workers, etc.) and for use In literacy and post-literacy work. It contains illustrations of
1 ,500 words clearly and simply presented in 1 ,300 individual figures and 1 8 full-page groups of draw¬
ings. To arouse the learner's interest and motivation, each illustration depicts an everyday activity of
rural life. An explanatory caption contains the word illustrated in the drawing. Beneath each caption
is a blank space in which the pupil can write the French sentence in his own language. Above, four
illustrations from the edition of the dictionary for French-speaking Africa. The handwritten sentences
are in Malagasy.
Drawings Vincent Glon and Jacques Zalhès Editions de l'Harmattan, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A Unesco Fellowship holder from Guinea visits an Associated School in the Federal Republic of Germany.
Education for international
understanding
Unesco's Associated Schools Project
ASSOCIATED Schools do not constitute a separate
category of educational establishments, set
apart from the mainstream of education in their
respective countries. From its beginnings in 1953,
Unesco's Associated Schools Project has been designed
for integration into existing structures, just as its basic
theme education for international understanding is in¬
tended for incorporation in existing curricula and not as
an additional syllabus or subject for insertion into a con¬
venient gap in the timetable.
Associated Schools are, quite simply, educational
establishments in Unesco's Member States at the
primary, secondary, vocational and teacher-training
levels of education which agree that teaching for tomor¬
row's world must involve teaching the basic principles of
international understanding and co-operation for peace,
the neglect or refusal of which may well deprive the
world of its tomorrow, and which assume the respon¬
sibilities of providing such teaching, both on their own
and in collaboration with other partners in the Project.
Over the years, the Associated Schools Project has
greatly expanded. In 1953, there were 33 participating
schools in 1 5 Member States; today there are some
1,600 participating institutions in 81 Member States
throughout the world at primary, secondary and teacher-
training levels.
The National Commissions for Unesco are generally
responsible for the selection of participating schools and
institutions, and for the transmission of applications to
the Unesco Secretariat.
To the greatest extent possible, Associated Schools
are left to devise and implement their own activities, but
they are expected to concentrate on four basic topics:
world problems and the role of the United Nations system
in solving them; human rights; other countries and
cultures; and man and the environment.
Over the years, the point of focus has shifted from the
institutions themselves, i.e. their history, structure,
functions, machinery, etc., to the world problems they
are called upon to solve. Thus, although the contents of
the teaching remain basically the same, the point of
departure is different. A world problem such as hunger,
,the arms race, development, etc., is studied by the
students. Once they have become sensitive to the prob¬
lem and understand some of its implications they search
for possible solutions.' *
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The boundaries on this map do not imply official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations
Countries Participating in the Associated Schools Project
As of I June 1983 there were Associated Schools in
the following Member States of Unesco:
Argentina
Australia
Austria
Bahrain
Bangladesh
Belgium
Benin
Bolivia
Brazil
Bulgaria
Burma
Burundi
Byelorussian Soviet Socialist Republic
Canada
Central African Republic
Chad
Chile
Colombia
Costa Rica
Cyprus
Czechoslovakia
Denmark
Dominica
Dominican Republic
Ecuador
Egypt
Ethiopia
Finland
France
German Democratic Republic
Germany, Federal Republic of
Ghana
Greece
Guatemala
Guyana
Haiti
Honduras
Hungary
India
Indonesia
10
Photo Satyan, Unicef
Source: Associated Schools
Ireland
Israel
Italy
Jamaica
Japan
Jordan
Kenya
Korea, Republic of
Malaysia
Malta
Mauritania
Mauritius
Mexico
Mongolia
Morocco
Nepal
Nigeria
Norway
Pakistan
Philippines
Poland
Romania
Saint Lucia
Senegal
Sierra Leone
Spain
Sri Lanka
Sudan
Switzerland
Thailand
Togo
Tunisia
Uganda
Ukrainian Soviet Socialist Republic
Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
United Kingdom
United Republic of Cameroon
United States of America
Uruguay
Yugoslavia
Zambia
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
^ The value as a means of stimulating interest and im¬
parting knowledge of organizing days or weeks
devoted to specific organizations and their activities (e.g.
Human Rights Day, United Nations Day, World Health
Day, International Literacy Day, etc.) remains un¬
contested and can be accompanied by a problem ap¬
proach, in which students are led from an awareness of
and involvement in social, cultural and economic issues
which are of direct concern to themselves and their com¬
munities, to an understanding of the broader interna¬
tional implications of these issues.
The study of human rights has always occupied a key
position in the experiments of the Associated Schools
Project, since it is clear that á grasp of the principles in¬
volved is a prerequisite to international understanding.
Teaching is based on two complementary approaches.
The first which may be termed "historical" deals with
the evolution of the concept of human rights throughout
the ages in different societies, and their contemporary
significance; the second approach is "comparative",
and is concerned with social relationships at all levels
from the local to the global where human rights are an
important issue (the rights of women, individual and na¬
tional self-determination, racial or other forms of
discrimination, the status of minorities, problems of im¬
migrant workers, employment and unemployment, the
citizen and the law, etc.)
Respect for human rights should be perceived as a
reality rather than an ¡deal, and should be reflected in the
organization and conduct of school life, in classroom
methods and procedures, and in relations between
students and teachers as well as between the teachers
themselves.
Outside the classroom and in the direct contact with
the realities of their community an essential element of
the activity of Associated Schools students have ample
opportunities of learning from personal experience and of
bridging the gap between awareness of problems and ac¬
tion designed to alleviate or solve them.
Comprehension of other countries and cultures, which
is simply a paraphrase of "international understanding",
essentially implies recognition of their right to be dif¬
ferent. But recognition of this right is not always con¬
comitant with the will to co-operate.
Experiments conducted during the early years of the
Associated Schools Project showed that it was not
enough to create a passive tolerance of differences by
showing how other countries and cultures were different
from those of the students concerned; active interest
depended on objective explanations of why such dif¬
ferences existed, and thus of their social, economic and
cultural particularities. Moreover, the study of world prob¬
lems involves the study of the countries where those
problems are most keenly felt, and of the specific cir¬
cumstances of environment and history which make
each country different from its neighbours.
In recent years, the Associated Schools Project has
begun a series of experiments in which teachers and in
some cases even students in a given country select
another country as a subject of study, investigate its
social and development problems in their own
classrooms and then travel to that country to see for
themselves how the problems are being solved.
Awareness of the universal implications of immediate,
local issues can lead to a thorough analysis of the social,
economic, ecological and other problems which all con¬
verge on the environment crisis, and place on-the-spot in¬
itiatives in the broader context of the struggle to preserve
or restore the fragile balance of the earth's resources a
balance which affects not only the relations between the
different elements of the biosphere but also the relations
between the industrialized countries and the countries of
the Third World.
Investigation, for example, of a local case of pollution
can lead to an investigation of its social and economic
Y FAMIL
,-tjMM OfwttiMÙK {VoçMMMr &»
n7- -
The first in a new series published by the Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco, Tokyo, My Village, My Fami¬
ly, My Asia, a 64-page book lavishly illustrated in colour, describes for the young reader a typical day
in the life of a village family in each of 1 5 Asian countries. Above, in the Kashan region of Iran, Rahim
sets out for school while his father heads for a day's work in the fields.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
causes (patterns of production and consumption) and to
the study of preventive or remedial measures (local, na¬
tional or international legislation, community
awareness).
Exchange of correspondence and materials between
Associated Schools (reports, surveys, maps,
photographs, slides, tape-recordings, etc.) might permit
comparison between methods of adaptation to different
social, economic or natural conditions, and lead to reflec¬
tion on the nature of the ideal human settlement.
But how are the special activities designed and im¬
plemented? As already pointed out, "Education for Inter¬
national Co-operation and Peace" should not be con¬
sidered as a separate subject for insertion in the
timetable. Experience has shown that this education can
be effectively provided within the framework of existing
courses and without overloading or disrupting the cur¬
riculum. What is frequently required, however, is some
measure of reassessment of the programme as a whole,
and its realignment in accordance with the principles of
It might be pointed out that the fundamental assump¬
tion of this experiment is that awareness of international
problems cannot be realized by cognitive elements alone
but supposes a socio-affective dimension, based on a
better understanding of oneself and one's immediate en¬
vironment as a prerequisite to a better understanding and
appreciation of other people and other countries.
The number of special activities that may be con¬
ducted in the context of the Associated Schools Project
and within the framework of its four main topics is vir¬
tually limitless, and depends almost entirely on the en¬
thusiasm and ingenuity of the participants. The following
examples may give some idea of the range of possible
activities.
Classroom activities
Projects intended to develop a better knowledge and
appreciation of other countries benefit from cor¬
respondence and exchanges with schools abroad.
Left, the cover of a Unesco
booklet. Children Helping Children,
which contains the 20 best poems
from a world poetry contest for
children under the age of 14, held
in 1980 and sponsored by Unesco
and the Radio Corporation of
America. Almost a million children
from 57 countries took part in the
competition and the 20 best
poems were selected by an inter¬
national jury of poets, writers and
musicians. The first prize went to a
13-year-old Filipino girl, Odina
E. Batnag, for her poem "I am but
a small voice". All the poems are
reproduced in their original
language and are accompanied by
translations in English and French.
Photo Unesco '
international education as referred to in the Unesco
Recommendation on education for international
understanding, co-operation and peace and education
relating to human rights and fundamental freedoms.
What is essential is that the topics for study should be
selected by agreement between teachers and pupils, and
that the specjal activities should be designed co¬
operatively, with the participation of all concerned, in¬
cluding parents and members of the local community
when extramural projects are envisaged.
Courses in history, geography and social studies cer¬
tainly lend themselves more readily to this type of educa¬
tion, and have most frequently provided the framework
for special activities. But foreign languages, civics, cur¬
rent events, natural sciences, art and music have also
made their contribution in many programmes.
Education for international understanding is closely
related to the formation of attitudes. Hence the eff icacity
of experience-centred teaching, particularly with
younger classes.
12
Teachers and pupils engaged in special projects have
found that visits from persons belonging by birth or
association to a country chosen for study, experts
engaged in work or technical assistance and staff
members of United Nations agencies can make an in¬
valuable contribution to their programme.
Essay and drawing contests have been successful in
encouraging students to reflect more deeply on specific
world problems or concerns.
Simulation games and exercises in perception and
communication can be helpful in establishing stronger in¬
tellectual and psychological foundations for international
understanding.
Audio-visual projections of films, slides, video-tapes,
etc., produced by Unesco, the United Nations, Member
States or schools and followed by discussions are useful
in making young people more aware of the work and role
of the United Nations systc.i.
The preparation of exhibitions and displays is useful in
marking the culmination of special projects.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Extracurricular activities
The organization of model assemblies of United Na¬
tions bodies has been an effective way to give students
better insight on how international conferences and
debates are conducted.
Unesco clubs, and art, music and drama circles have
provided excellent opportunities for cultural activities
and community-oriented activities.
Participation in fund-raising campaigns such as the
Unesco Co-operative Action Programme/Associated
Schools Guatemala Project (to provide educational
equipment and materials for schools) can further interna¬
tional co-operation and learning about other countries
and people.
Exchange programmes of teachers and/or students
between schools in different cities or countries can serve
as a positive framework within which to promote educa¬
tion for international understanding.
Successful visits have been made to the headquarters
and regional and national offices and project sites of in¬
ternational organizations by school teachers and
students.
Since international understanding begins at home,
students might wish to conduct surveys and interviews
in their community in order to learn more about their im¬
mediate environment as well as to carry out development
projects for improving their surroundings.
In view of the increasing number of schools in Unesco
Member States taking part in the Project and the
numerous reports of activities submitted by schools to
the Secretariat, the actual record of the Associated
Schools Project during its first twenty-five years is
positive, revealing as it does a community of views re¬
garding such education, and clearly indicating the
multitude of teachers and students who are convinced
that it is necessary, if not vital, and who are willing to
devote themselves to its attainment.
THE
children!;
WAY
Drawing © Plantu, Paris |UWTv^
by Marcel Canetti
IN the certainty that they are powerless to change it, the
young people of today refuse to participate in a world
unsuited to their aspirations. Their horizons blocked, the
future heavy with menace, they are oriented towards
discouragement, to dropping out or to violence rather than
towards a zest for life. Adults react by withholding their con¬
fidence, a dynamic is created and the generation gap widens.
Such a structure is unacceptable in the present world situa¬
tion which cries out for collaboration between the generations.
It is to bring about this rapprochement, to encourage everyone
to contribute to the righting of the situation, that an associa¬
tion. The Children's Way, has been created.
Among the measures the association proposes are:
Adoption of a ten-point text demanding due respect for the
younger generation so that young people will not find
themselves unwittingly or un willingly dragged into a situation
from which there is no way out.
An end to the many conferences on disarmament which have
failed to prevent the world arsenal from increasing millions
of times in the last twenty-five years, and their replacement
by a change in tone in newspapers and television pro¬
grammes. To put out a fire water hoses must be directed to
the base and not to the top of the flames. At the base, at the
grass-roots, is to be found that state of mind which is, to a
large extent, the product of what each one of us reads and
hears.
Encouragement of entente and a halt to rivality in all those
domains where international competition is rampant so as to
avoid the discouragement ofpeoples who, each day, have to
face up to increasingly difficult situations.
Encouragement, beginning with those ofschool age, ofa new
understanding of the concept ofself-preservation. Our grow¬
ing interdependence means that it is no longer possiblefor an
individual or a country to build walls high enough to form
a shield against others. Good relations between men are no
longer a luxury, they have become a vital necessity.
A shift in priorities in schools towards greater motivation. A
passion or a high degree of interest in an activity seems to be
more important than a high level of knowledge. Such a
switch in priorities could have the effect ofmaking individual
interests coincide more closely with those of society.
MARCEL CANETTI, French engineer and former mathematics
, teacher, is the founder of The Children's Way association, the
headquarters of which are at Meudoh (France).
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A world human rights
congress in Costa Rica
A World Human Rights Con¬
gress was held last December in
the old Costa Rican city of Ala-
juela. The Government wished to
use this occasion to celebrate the
33rd anniversary of the constitu¬
tional reform by virtue of which
Costa Rica proscribed "the army
as a permanent institution" and
abolished the death penalty. At
the end of the Congress, the first
of its kind to be organized by a
State, the "Alajuela charter",
published here in its entirety, was
unanimously approved.
The Alajuela
charter
THE first World Human Rights Congress, meeting in the 200-year-old city of
Alajuela de Costa Rica from 6 to 12 December 1982, has proved the impor¬
tance which an entire people attaches to. the rights and duties of the person.
It has also showed that it could rationally deliberate, examine and discuss problems
pertaining to human rights in an atmosphere of total liberty.
Accordingly it considers, recommends and resolves:
1. That given the democratic institutional
system of Costa Rica, characterized by
freedom, justice and the lack of an army, it
would be fitting for Costa Rica to become a
world centre for study and research into
human rights, for the defence of human
rights and the diffusion of information about
them; for this centre a speedy, reliable inter¬
continental information network should be
established, covering everything connected
with human rights experiences and problems
in different parts of the world.
2. That the international community should
recognize and guarantee to Costa Rica a
status of perpetual neutrality, in recognition
of thefact that il is the only country that has
unilaterally opted for peace by deciding, 33
years ago, to abolish its army as a permanent
institution.
3. That it supports the proposal made by
Sean MacBride (Nobel Peace Prize) and Ben
Whitaker that the United Nations should
establish as soon as possible its own world
radio and television information system on
human rights.
4. That the Ibero-American services of the
above project, at least, should begin in Costa
Rica.
5. That Costa Rica should intensify its cam¬
paign in the United Nationsfor the setting up
of a High Commission for Human Rights.
6. That the world's educational systems
should be based on the study and inter¬
disciplinary practice of human rights.
10. That the industry of war, especially
nuclear, bacteriological and chemical,
represents a constant threat to every form of
life and is an immoral attack on human dig¬
nity. To denounce and combat it wherever it
exists is a fundamental right and duty for
free men.
11. That rebellion against any military,
tyrannical, despotic and dictatorial régime is
a fundamental human right and duty. It
should be recognized as such, guaranteed and
broadly extended by the international
community.
12. That the death penally, whether legal or
not, is a practice which attacks the supreme
human right, the right to life. It should
therefore be abolished.
13. That the judicial practice ofphysical and
mental torture constitutes aflagrant violation
ofhuman rights. It is the duty ofallfree men
to denounce and combat this sadistic and
abominable practice and to make the greatest
efforts to win approval for the International
Covenant on Torture and the Optional Pro¬
tocol of the United Nations.
14. That political régimes based on social,
religious, political, linguistic and economic
concepts and practices that discriminate
against national minorities, or discriminate
on grounds ofsex or other factors, constitute
a historical aberration and an intolerable af¬
front to the universal conscience of human
dignity. Men and peoples who love liberty,
democracy andjustice have the right and the
supreme duty to denounce and combat these
practices.
7. That an international human rights in¬
vestigating commission be created.
8. That an international penal court on
human rights be set up.
9. That a political régime characterized by
public freedoms, social security with
economic guarantees, ideological pluralism
and the periodical alternation of political
power through genuine free elections con¬
stitutes the securest guarantee of thefull exer¬
cise of human rights in the world.
14
15. That it is of paramount importance to
awaken the conscience of men, peoples and
nations regarding human rights, and that
consequently it is of the highest importance
that a second world human rights congress be
held, taking account of the experience of the
first, at a place and a date which will be decid¬
ed after consultation and deliberation involv¬
ing all the participants in the present
Congress.
Alajuela the twelfth day of December 1982
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
What's new
in science teaching?
First organized by University College,
Cardiff (UK) in 1981, an experimental
competition for schools in which
drama is used as a vehicle for pre¬
senting, understanding and enjoying
science was so successful that it has
become an annual event. Each entry
is a presentation, devised and per¬
formed by children from junior, middle
or secondary schools, of an episode
from the history of science,
technology or engineering, a con¬
troversial issue related to the social
consequences of science and
technology, or the exposition of a
scientific concept. Right, pupils from
Bodringallt Junior School, Ystrad
Rhondda, South Wales, depict water
in a scene from their prize-winning
1982 dance-drama Metamorphosis
which illustrates the compatibility
between Darwinism and Christianity.
by Mircea Malitza
NEW developments in the exact and natural sciences
have little direct influence on the curriculum.
After all, the requirements of social life guide
education in general; the aims of education are to provide
the student with whatever he needs for active, intelligent
participation in life.
Mathematics thus becomes increasingly "mathematics
for all"; its aims concern the individual as well as society,
and increasingly affect our culture and civilization.
The reform of the curriculum is a specific process in¬
volving the developmental characteristics and educa¬
tional traditions of each country. It seems to be
reasonable to use a negative model indicating which sub¬
jects should not be taught since they are totally outdated
and useless. Such a list could only be drawn up by a large
panel of specialists.
Until now the objectives of mathematics teaching have
mainly been concerned with the logical and formal
aspects, helping the child to acquire the capacity for
rigorous thinking, free from logical contradictions. This
is insufficient; in mathematics as in other fields, educa¬
tion should not shrink from an effort to grasp meanings.
Progressive learning, in which the pupil is exposed to a
variety of situations in which the use of mathematics
becomes meaningful, should accompany the axiomatic
treatment.
Intellectual curiosity should be cultivated. Only in¬
quisitive, critical minds can go beyond the superficial
MIRCEA MALITZA, of Romania, is professor at the faculty of
mathematics of the University of Bucharest and a former minister of
education of his country. He has lectured on international affairs at
academic centres in Asia, Europe and the United States. He is the
author of books on education and mathematics, and co-author of the
report to the Club of Rome entitled No Limits to Learning.
Photo courtesy of University College, Cardiff, UK
aspects of mathematics. In this way creativity is also
developed; it cannot be encouraged by the deductive
presentation of a finite, consistent system.of theories. To
arouse students' interest it is necessary to point out the
origin of concepts so that they can discover by means of
exploratory investigations the notions that are to be learn¬
ed. This presupposes, along with a logical exposition, a
psychological one in which more attention must be paid
to historical developments.
A generally acknowledged objective of mathematics
teaching is the development of probabilistic as well as
deterministic thought. This process should be initiated in
the first elementary grades, especially since mathematics
is increasingly bound up with science in which a pro¬
babilistic approach is common, and notions related to
this approach are not beyond the understanding of
students.
A final objective concerns the development of the
capacity to perceive, and not only to solve, problems.
Along with the usual activities of solving problems and
proving theorems, students should also have experience
of solving their own problems and proving their own
theorems. This issue is related to creativity and
understanding, and is far too often overlooked.
Certain themes should not be neglected in mathematics
teaching. Some of them have already been included in
many syllabuses and include such subjects as probability,
'statistics, discrete mathematics and matrix theory. Others
will be included very soon, namely: courses in the con¬
struction of mathematical models; courses in scientific
organization; and subjects from computer science (infor¬
matics) such as algorithms, formal languages, elementary
numerical analysis, programming; elementary education
in systems science; and applications as an integral part of
mathematics teaching.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Psychologists point to the fact that intellectual maturi¬
ty depends largely on having the opportunity to par¬
ticipate in activities. Hence there is a need to devise ac¬
tivities which lead the child to personal discovery. Ac¬
tivities must be rooted in reality, permitting pupils to in¬
vestigate and examine the environment. They should be
encouraged to collect data for themselves and devise their
own problems. Mathematical applications can be en¬
visaged in real-life activities such as census-taking and
meteorological records.
The impact of new technological inventions should also
be considered from the point of view of participation.
Pushed to its extremes, the technicization of teaching
evokes images such as that of the student isolated in a
cubicle listening to a taped lesson or sitting in front of a
computer terminal pushing buttons marked "yes" or
"no", staring mesmerized before a visual-display
screen all of which are instances of non-participatory
learning. However, if used judiciously, technological aids
enable students to concentrate on problems and their
solutions instead of cumbersome computations. Com¬
puter simulations, for example, permit students to in¬
vestigate more variants of a problem situation.
In science teaching, it seems that the general orienta¬
tion is towards the creation of "accomplished", open-
minded individuals who are aware of the enormous
destructive potential of science. The future scientist
should be actively involved in society and be aware of his
responsibilities.
Almost all contemporary sciences use models as a
means of investigating both the physical and social
phenomena of the real world that surrounds them.
Models may be simulated on computers, and this opens
new perspectives in secondary education. Good pupils are
often disappointed when, after learning classical
mechanics and acquiring a personal outlook on the func¬
tioning of nature, they are told that they were wrong and
that the theory of relativity alone corresponds to reality.
This is a result of inadequate teaching methods that place
too much emphasis on the basic hypothesis of the
Newtonian model, and do not critically discuss the
possibility that it may not necessarily correspond to reali¬
ty. If we teach pupils to conceive physical theories as a
changing mass of facts, theorems and ideas, then we shall
come very close to the ideal of modern thinking.
Integrated education has been intensively debated.
Thus there are discussions on "global" curriculum in¬
tegration, the integration of theory and practice, the in¬
tegration of the natural sciences and the social sciences,
vertical and horizontal integration. A profusion of in¬
teresting works have recently appeared on this theme.
The distinctive characteristic of contemporary science
is undoubtedly the quantity of data. If science continues
to develop at the present rate, specialization will remain
one of the major characteristics of the scientist in the
coming decades. The difficulties of such a situation are
well-known: limitation to a narrow field of knowledge
can hinder the understanding of general phenomena. One
method of coping with this problem is to promote
research groups as opposed to the individual approach to
science.
The integration of mathematics with physics and
chemistry seems at first sight superfluous, since it is a
natural process. However, there is still plenty of room for
improvement, especially when the material is designed for
younger pupils.
Mathematical problems, which are often abstract,
could generally be presented by demonstrating their
16
relevance to physics, particularly as regards probability
theory, the notion of complex numbers, the concept of
limits, the introduction and utilization of differential
calculus, etc. These examples are designed to show that it
would be well worth while to focus mathematics teaching
on the application of mathematics to physical
phenomena.
Although the integration of physics with chemistry is
almost inevitable, the two are still often taught as if they
were separate subjects. The demand for flexible forms of
education calls for the use of a whole range of methods
borrowed from the classic type of education. Non-formal
education must be carefully planned to complement and
supplement formal education. The most often quoted
forms of free scientific activity that concern mathematics,
physics, chemistry and related subjects are "the following:
These two works by the French artist Edgar
Degas 11834-1917) have been used by Pro¬
fessor Istvan Hargittai of the Budapest
Academy of Sciences to illustrate the scientific
phenomenon of isomerism, the existence of
two or more substances that have identical
chemical compositions but different ar¬
rangements of their atoms. Textbooks explain¬
ing isomerism often give the examples of
molecules of a certain type which appear in two
different isomeric forms ("staggered" and
"eclipsed") depending on the disposition of
their atoms (inset in the Degas drawings).
Hargittai noted that in "End of an Arabesque"
(far right) the position of the dancer's arms and
legs recall the staggered form, while the
"Dancer Seated Lacing her Buskin" (right) is a
representation of the eclipsed form.
Special publications and reviews for pupils contain¬
ing series of problems or open situations to be work¬
ed out outside school;
Science clubs or societies the activities of which in¬
clude carrying out projects, designing and building
models of specific items of apparatus, conducting
surveys, collecting data and materials, ecological
investigations;
Competitions on various subjects and at various
levels. They should be a means of furthering learning
in a spirit of friendship;
Popular scientific centres or museums endowed with
scientific libraries and facilities for showing scientific
films;
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
In schools: organization of scientific exhibitions,
productions by pupils on scientific subjects to be
broadcast on closed-circuit radio;
Science fairs, youth science camps, excursions and
field trips, quizzes;
Distance teaching by correspondence, broadcast
courses on national radio and television, and
multimedia teaching systems supported by a wide
variety of audio-visual aids such as slides, tapes,
cassettes, records, open-circuit radio and television
broadcasting.
The teacher is and will continue to be the keystone of
the educative process. In spite of many attempts in several
countries to replace the teacher with monitoring devices
poses that more attention will be paid to the history
of science.
Teaching will include elements of "science ethics"
and "technology assessment" calling into play a
system of values and a normative approach, in con¬
trast to the positivism that has prevailed so far.
It will explore border areas where fields with dif¬
ferent axioms and methodologies meet. This will
amplify the trends towards the integration of the
sciences, which has important consequences for
teaching and teacher-training.
system of interdisciplinary work-teams and
modular education will develop further.
and self-testing systems for pupils, there is no chance that
the teacher/human being will be replaced by the
teacher/machine.
It seems that in the future the computer will be mainly
used for communication rather than for computer-
assisted teaching.
Teacher training is an important problem. The in-,
tegrated teaching of science presupposes quite important
changes in the higher education of future teachers.
In conclusion we should like to emphasize the
following:
Teaching of science will be done in a more "contex¬
tual" way, drawing attention to the problems solved
by science, in contrast to the axiomatic trends of
thought which have prevailed since the beginning of
the century, reaching a climax in the 1950s. This sup-
Computer modelling will have a strong influence on
science teaching; it will be practised in all scientific
disciplines and will result in a spread of numeric
calculus and simulated experiences.
Computers and telematics will shift the emphasis
from data, information and memory to process
modelling, algorithms and operations.
Scientific organization will thrive, based on decision,
systems and games theories and on organization
techniques.
As the immediate future will be dominated by intense
research into new energy sources and less energy-
consuming technologies, the curriculum will reflect
this preoccupation.
Mircea Malitza
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ASIA
Unesco-assisted projects
BHUTAN: Teacher Training Institute and the National
Institute of Education
The kingdom of Bhutan is a mountainous country of 1.3 million people
bordered by China and India. Over 80 % of the population are illiterate.
In 1981 only half the 1,212 teaching posts were filled by nationals.
With the support of the Project, the country's Teacher Training Institute
at Samchi (set up in 1968) had trained 210 teachers by the end of 1982
and another 40-50 were finishing training annually. A language
laboratory, science laboratories and a printing press have been establish¬
ed. As part ofa second project which will run until 1986, the Samchi In¬
stitute is being upgraded into a National Institute of Education which
will provide training for secondary school as well as primary school
teachers. In addition, 3 regional teacher centres will be created.
PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA: Strengthening of
Education System for National Minorities (1982-1984).
The Government of China is aiming to strengthen and improve the
education of the country 's 55 national minorities, totalling about 60
million people. The objectives of the project are to provide cadres of ex¬
perienced lecturers (principally in science), to establish models ofscience
education for minorities in the 4 key Institutes of National Minorities in
Wuhan, Beijing, Lanzhou and Chengdu, and to improve the content of
coursesfor minority teachers and students. Thefocalpoint of the project
is the South-Central China Institute for National Minorities at Wuhan,
Hubei Province, where the physics and chemistry faculties are being
strengthened and where it is hoped that total enrolment will reach 3,000
in 1985 and 5,000 in 1990. Fourteen lecturers will receivefurther training,
and courses in physics, chemistry, mathematics, humanities and social
sciences will be improved. The remaining 6 Institutes for National
Minorities (Yunan, Guanaxi, Guangdong, Qinhai, Guizhou and Tibet
Institutes) will send staff members to the 4 Institutes mentioned above
to learn from the lecturers who have benefited from the project.
INDONESIA: Improvement of Science and Mathematics
Teaching in the Secondary General Schools
A secondary school teacher training programme has in its first 4 years
trained 152 science and mathematics instructors through Unesco
fellowships. These instructors, along with national and Unesco short-
term consultants, trained a further 430 assistant instructors as well as
4,375 science and mathematics teachers. During 1 983- 1 984 some 800 key
science teachers and 200 maths teachers will be trained, and they in turn
will train 11,340 science and 3,000 maths teachers.
REPUBLIC OF MALDIVES: Strengthening of the
Educational System
By the end of 1982, 16 Atolls had been provided with an educational
centreforformalmodern primary education and non-formal community
education. The project has also providedfor the training of teachers for
English and, Dhivehi medium schools, the production of schoolbooks,
and the broadcasting of programmes on the English language, en¬
vironmental studies, community development and adult education.
NEPAL: Education for Rural Development, Seti Zone
The goals of this pilot project in one of Nepal's most remote areas are
to train a new type of teacher with development skills, to prepare a new
action-oriented functional educational curriculum, to assist local com¬
munities in building a new type of school, and to promote literacy.
After 15 months' operation the project had developed a new action-
oriented, functional adult education programme now being implemented
in 20 centres, trained more than 100 teachers, begun construction of 10
improved primary schools, built latrines and planted more than 1,000
trees in school compounds, prepared reading materials for primary
school children, and produced and distributed wall newspapers.
D
EMOCRACY is destined to
last long in India," ex¬
claimed a Delhi-based
foreign educationalist-turned-journa¬
list after watching the performance of
prize-winning Youth Parliament com¬
petition students from a higher secon¬
dary school take part in a contest
recently organized in New Delhi.
If democracy is to be a complete suc¬
cess as a participatory system,
democratic principles and norms must
permeate into every walk of a nation's
life. To ensure this, all sections of
society, especially young people, must
be adequately acquainted with the
functioning of the Parliament and other
legislative bodies.
With this as their prime objective,
the Central Department of Parliamen¬
tary Affairs and the education direc¬
torate of the Delhi Administration co-
sponsored in 1966-67 a unique
scheme whereby annual Youth Parlia¬
ment Competitions would be held
among the students of sixteen higher
secondary schools for boys and girls in
the Union Territory of Delhi. The
scheme had its origin in one of the
recommendations adopted by the All-
India Whips' Conference held in Bom¬
bay in 1962. The Conference desired
that the Government "should en¬
courage the holding of youth (mock)
Parliaments in educational institutions
and through Panchayats (village coun¬
cils) in the rural areas." This recom¬
mendation was reiterated by all the
successive All India Whips' Con¬
ferences. The seventh All India Whips'
Conference held at Madras in 1969
recommended that in view of the suc¬
cess of the Youth Parliament Scheme
in Delhi schools, the wide appreciation
it had received from leading Parliamen-
AMAR NATH RAI is an Indian journalist cur¬
rently working with the Government of India
Press Information Bureau. He has published
two books and over 200 of his articles on a
wide range of subjects have appeared in In¬
dian newspapers and periodicals.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Sowing the seeds
of democracy
India's youth parliament competition
by Amar Nath Rai
tarians, the press and educationalists,
all the States and Union Territories
should take steps to implement the
scheme with a view to building future
Parliamentarians.
The scheme aims at strengthening
the roots of democracy by inculcating
the spirit of discipline, decorum and
tolerance for the views of opponents
so necessary in a democratic society,
forming character, and acquainting the
younger generation with the practices
and procedures of the Parliament of
general concern such as social justice
and reforms, economic development,
communal harmony, the cultural heri¬
tage, national integration, student
discipline, international understanding,
human rights and peace.
Officers of the Department of
Parliamentary Affairs visit each par¬
ticipating school and witness the
Youth Parliament Competition, offer¬
ing on-the-spot guidance and sugges¬
tions. They also maintain contact with
the zonal education officers, other
gress. Within sixteen years of its in¬
auguration over 700 schools have par¬
ticipated and about 3,500 students
have received prizes and certificates
for excellence. A notable feature of the
prize-winning pattern is that the
number of girl students winning
awards has been proportionately
higher than that of boys.
The scheme has become very
popular not only in the Union Territory
of Delhi but further afield. The States
of Haryana, Punjab, Uttar Pradesh,
Union Territories (Chandigarh and
Arunachal Pradesh) have started orga¬
nizing the competition while other
States have agreed to implement the
scheme soon. There is also a proposal
under active consideration by the Cen¬
tral Government to introduce the Youth
Parliament Competition scheme Into
the training programmes of the Central
Board for Workers' Education.
The Department of Parliamentary
Affairs provides the States with the.
necessary training and encouragement
when introducing the scheme, con¬
ducts orientation courses for the com¬
petition organizers, and offers financial
assistance. To popularize the scheme
the country so that they grow into
well-informed citizens and, above all,
well disciplined parliamentarians of
tomorrow.
The working of Youth Parliaments
broadly follows the pattern of working
of the Lok Sabha (House of Com¬
mons). The students selected to par¬
ticipate in the Youth Parliament com¬
petition and the teachers in charge of
this activity acquaint themselves with
the functioning of the Parliament by
witnessing its proceedings during a
Session and learning about the ar¬
rangements made for the members.
The layout of a school Youth Parlia¬
ment is arranged to resemble as close¬
ly as possible that of the chamber of
the Lok Sabha. Though no particular
subjects have been prescribed, it is
desirable that matters raised in the
Youth Parliament relate to areas of
education officials and members of
Parliament, who constitute a panel of
judges who select the prize-winners.
The Department of Parliamentary Af¬
fairs awards four prizes to the best four
students, and the school also awards
prizes to meritorious students. When
assessing performance, the committee
of judges keeps the following points
in mind: discipline anddecorum (10
marks), observance of Parliamentary
procedures (20 marks), selection of
subjects for questions, for supplemen¬
täres and quality of answers thereto
(20 marks), selection of subjects for
debate (10 marks), delivery or quality
of speeches delivered, standard of
debates (30 marks) and general
assessment .of the performance as a
whole (10 marks).
The Youth Parliament Competition
scheme has made remarkable pro-
The Minister of Works and Hous¬
ing (left) answers a tricky ques¬
tion from the opposition front
bench (right). The "parliamen¬
tarians" in our photos, pupils of a
higher secondary school in India,
are taking part in the Youth
Parliament Competition, an im¬
aginative scheme aimed at
familiarizing the younger genera¬
tion with parliamentary practices
and procedures and inculcating
the spirit of democratic debate.
Over 700 schools have taken
part in the competition since its
inauguration 16 years ago and
some 3,500 students have
received prizes and certificates
of excellence, with a propor¬
tionately higher number of girls
than boys winning awards.
among students and the general
public, the Department of Parliamen¬
tary Affairs, the Government of India
and the Film Division of the Union In¬
formation and Broadcasting Ministry
have jointly produced a colour
documentary on the Youth Parliament
which should soon be released for ex¬
hibition throughout the country and
even abroad.
Though the results of the scheme
have not yet been rigorously
evaluated, its impact among young
people can be measured by its growing
popularity. Legislators, journalists and
educators who have seen the contests
take place have been highly impressed
and believe that a nation-building ac¬
tivity of this kind can transform the
social and political Parliamentary in¬
stitutions of the country.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Can creativity be taught?
Aesthetic education in Bulgaria
by Krestu Goranov
IN Bulgaria today great importance
is attached to creativity in all
fields, and consequently aesthetic
education is considered to make an
essential contribution to shaping the
individual both as a personality and
as a member of the community. By
rounding off intellectual, moral,
physical and working education, it pro¬
vides fulfilment for the creative instinct
by harmonizing the intellect with the
sensibility.
This long-established Bulgarian
tradition became stronger when the
country was liberated from the Ot¬
toman yoke in 1878.
First of all it found expression in the
cultural triangle of "school, church
and cultural centre", the latter being
popular institutions which sponsored
libraries and a wide variety of cultural
activities and which still play a major
role in national life.
Later, the artistic ideas and tastes of
democrat-revolutionaries . such as
Khristo Botev, Vasil Levski, Lyuben
Karavelov and of the Socialist Workers
Movement further strengthened the
secular and democratic evolution of the
school and the role it accords to
aesthetic education.
The aim of aesthetic education is to
form taste, that is the capacity to in¬
vent, understand, appreciate, con¬
serve, experience and create beauty in
daily life and in the arts. It also tends to
stimulate the creative gifts and to en¬
courage a desire to change life in accor¬
dance with an aesthetic ideal which is
indissociable from a social ideal. In
conformity with the dialectical rela¬
tionship between these ideals, a na¬
tional programme of aesthetic educa¬
tion was established in Bulgaria in
1975. The school plays a major role in
the programme, which also calls for ac¬
tive participation by artists and their
unions, public organizations and
representatives of the different age
KRESTU GORANOV, of Bulgaria, is pro¬
fessor of aesthetics, the sociology of the arts
and the theory of culture at the University of
Sofia, at the Bulgarian Academy of Sciences
and at Bulgaria 's Higher Institute of Fine Arts.
He is the author of many published works,
notably Art as a Process, Arts and Social Life,
Artistic Culture in a Changing World, and Prin¬
ciples of Aesthetics.
20
Photo Dimitr Boginov © BTA, Sofia
Members of the children's theatre studio attached to the Varna Drama
Theatre (Bulgaria) in a scene from The Moon's Bedroom, a play by
Valeri Petrov with music by Tchaikovski.
groups. On the initiative of the late
Ludmila Zhivkova, a noted figure in
Bulgarian political and cultural life,
youth cultural movements were found¬
ed, notably the "Banner of Peace"
movement which enjoys international
prestige (see Unesco Courier, May
1981) and movements which popularize
the life and work of great figures in the
arts and sciences, such as Leonardo da
Vinci and Einstein.
The school is the centre of the na¬
tional aesthetic education programme,
which should begin at pre-school age.
Much attention is focussed on
children's games, and efforts are being
made to enrich them with musical and
artistic elements. Considerable success
has been achieved, notably in musical
education. Literature, the fine arts and
music are taught in secondary schools
from age eleven until the end of the
course, along with the theory and
history of art.
But other subjects can also make a
contribution to aesthetic education.
After all there is no reason why an
aesthetic meaning should not be given
to work, to social activity and to
human relations in general. Efforts are
also made to complete pupils' aesthetic
education by encouraging them to take
part in rewarding out-of-school ac¬
tivities such as art circles and amateur
dramatics, choirs, orchestras and danc¬
ing. They are urged to visit exhibitions
and museums, and to attend theatres
and concerts.
These out-of-school activities take
place in cultural centres, and centres of
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
aesthetic education belonging to
pioneer and youth organizations. New
conditions the building of socialism,
urbanization and the development of
new communications media permit a
wider application of an advanced
teaching practice whereby young
people teach themselves. According to
the same method, teaching is tailored
to different interests and gifts, and the
children may attend special optional
classes in literature, drama or cinema,
painting or dance studios, or else learn
to play a musical instrument.
In harmony with the national
aesthetic education programme,
Bulgarian schools thus try to serve a
great democratic principle by giving
everyone the opportunity to fully
develop his aesthetic sensibility and to
use his gifts. The school discovers the
most gifted representatives of the rising
generation and provides their earliest
artistic training. Not all the young peo¬
ple who learn the rudiments of painting
will, become painters, but those who
really possess gifts in this field should
be able to express them. The others will
be able to direct the impulse awakened
in them to other activities, in their work
and in their human relationships; and
as a result people's lives will be more
satisfying and more equitable.
The Bulgarian painter Dechko
Uzunov at work amidst a group
of budding artists.
Photo Stefan Tuxov © BTA, Sofia
A group of Bulgarian children
perform a traditional dance.
Photo Zhivko Angelov © BTA, Sofia
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
LATIN AMERICA
and the CARIBBEAN
Unesco-assisted projects
BRAZIL: Technology Applied to Special Education
The project is conceived within the framework of Brazil's policy to im¬
prove the education ofhandicapped persons. It focuses on two main ac¬
tivities: (I) the establishment ofservicesfor the early detection and treat¬
ment of hearing-impaired children through the provision of diagnostic
technical equipment and the training ofspecialists; (2) the installation of
Braille printing equipment at the Benjamin Constant Institute for the
Blind in Rio de Janeiro to provide textbooks and other reading materi
for the blind.
THE EASTERN CARIBBEAN: Development of
Vocational Education
The project, which concerns Antigua and Barbuda, the British Virgin
Islands, Dominica, Grenada, Montserrat, St. Kitts-Nevis, St. Lucia, St.
Vincent and the Grenadines, becomes operational this year. It aims to im¬
prove educational training systems, especially at secondary level, and to
provide training in industrial arts such as woodwork, metalwork and elec¬
tricity so as to prepare students in the 12-15 age group for apprenticeship
programmes or entrance into technical colleges.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC: Planning and Renewal of the
Education System
The overall objective is to contribute to the renewal of the nationa,
educational system. Among the main activities are drawing up a
reorganization project for the Secretariat of State for Education, Fine
Arts and Religious Practices, especially its 160 regional branches, and the
production of a handbook on organization and methods.
ECUADOR: Training of educational Personnel
Since 1979, Unesco has been helping a team of Ecuadorian specialists
commissioned by the Ministry ofEducation to organize a national train¬
ing and in-service training system for educational personnel. Among the
objectives are the creation of a vast correspondence course network for
practicing teachers, the strengthening of the National Teacher Training
Institute, and experimentation with new training and in-service training
methods, notably in basic in- and out-of-school education in rural areas
and in the integration of technical education into general studies. The
programme is scheduled to end in December 1984.
NICARAGUA: Basic Education in Rural Areas
The central idea of the project, conceived within the framework of the
national educational reform, is to associate teachers and the community
at large in tfte management and development of education. Accordingly"
a network of in-school and out-of-school educational services has been
created to remedy the isolation of rural schools. Experimentation with
new methods has been encouraged notably through the creation of 21
"Educational nuclei" and through a continuing effort to provide their
cadres with in-service training.
PERU: A National Multi-sectoral Literacy Plan
Since 1982 the project has been contributing to the training ofspecialists
in audiovisual literacy teaching techniques. It is also helping to produce
video and radio material for use in literacy work, including bilingual
literacy teaching (Quechua-Spanish, Aymara-Spanish), and in basic in¬
tegrated education (reading, writing, mathematics, and community
development).
I
22
THE supply and demand of
education for women
would seem to be in¬
separable from the position oc¬
cupied by women in each different
society. Consequently, the educa¬
tion of women calls to mindia dou¬
ble mirror which simultaneously
reflects both general educational
trends and the status of women.
A straightforward analysis of the
figures relating to the education of
girls and women reveals that a
smaller proportion of them are
enrolled in school than boys, that
their schooling is often disturbed,
that there are disparities in their
distribution among the different
types of education, and that their
education is turned to little account
in working life. The underlying
causes of these trends are to be
sought outside the classroom.
As long as education to a given
level is not fully extended in prac¬
tice to all the members of the age
group concerned, the proportion of
girls enrolled is smaller than that of
boys. In the developing countries
in 1980, girls constituted 43 per
cent of the pupils enrolled in
primary education as against 49
per cent in the industrially
developed world. The overall in¬
crease in numbers of girl pupils
(which is spectacular in the
developing countries) does not
mean that there is equality of op¬
portunity between the two sexes.
It simply reflects a position in
which girls were poorly
represented in education at the
outset, and sheds light on the
development of education in
general.
In many cases girls' school
careers are characterized by
absenteeism, grade repetition and
early leaving. And the difference in
the illiteracy rates between the
two sexes is a good indicator of a
form of discrimination which does
not disappear when the level of
development of schooling rises. In
this connexion a Unesco study
presents data which show
significantly that these disparities
are, more strongly marked in the
south European countries than in
most developing countries.
MARIA ELIOU, of Greece, is professor of
comparative education at the University of
Jannina (Greece). She is also a member of the
Administrative Council of Unesco's Interna¬
tional Fund for the Promotion of Culture and of
the Executive Committee of the European
Association of Development Research and
Training Institutes. President of the Greek
League for Women's Rights, she is the author
of a number of books and articles on educa-
' tional questions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Towards equality
for women in education
by Maria Eliou
The distribution of female pupils
among the various types of secon¬
dary education reveals disparities
which are concealed by the global,
figures. Whereas girls are more or
less well represented in general
education, they are generally
under-represented in technical and
professional education, except for
training leading to the service
industries.
It is quite clear that this trend is
influenced by the "sexist" ¡mage
of different kinds of training and
the professions to which they lead.
The labels of "men's" or
"women's" jobs can be seen in the
background of choices which may
seem free in the sense that they are
not dictated by formal rules
whereas in practice freedom of
choice is virtually non-existent.
In higher education women are
still in a small minority in fields of
training which offer the best pro-^
"As long as collective mentalities support the traditional division of roles, the evolution of women's education will
continue to mask the persistence of their traditional status".
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
fessional prospects. It may be in¬
structive to compare the data in
Unesco's Statistical Yearbook
(1982 edition) for the enrolment
rates of male and female students
in two fields of study: literature,
religion and theology on the one
hand, and engineering sciences on
the other. In the fifty-seven coun¬
tries for which the data exist,
whatever their level of economic
and educational development,
whatever the rate of participation
of young women in higher educa¬
tion, whatever the school system
or the socio-economic system, the
same trends recur: with few ex¬
ceptions women tend far more
often to study literature than men,
but above all far fewer of them
without any exception are enrolled
in institutions which train
engineers.
Thus the individual and collec¬
tive investment represented by the
education of women is turned to
little account, or else it is subtly
diverted in the sense that it serves
only to give "added value" to what
is expected of women as mothers
and housekeepers.
In other words the education of
women bristles with ambiguities.
There is a blatant contradiction
between avowed egalitarian aims
and actual practices, the latter of
which stem from the differentiated
roles, implicitly arranged in a
hierarchy, of men and women. As
long as collective mentalities sup¬
port this traditional division of
roles, the evolution of women's
education will continue to mask
the persistence of their traditional
status.
However, in the last few years
there has been a growing
awareness of these mechanisms,
giving rise to a different conception
of education for women and of
educational policy in this field.
The United Nations Decade for
Women, especially such events as
the World Conferences of Women
in Mexico City (1975) and
Copenhagen (1980), has given a
strong impetus to this movement,
and today the different interna¬
tional organizations are tackling
the complex question of women's
status in an open-minded, forward-
looking spirit.
The major programme on the
status of women in Unesco's
Medium-Term Plan (1984-1989) is
particularly relevant here. The goal
it seeks is no longer equality of ac¬
cess (to education or employment)
but "equal opportunities and
responsibilities in access to
resources as well as in decision¬
making"; it is stressed that this
issue is "basically a political prob¬
lem and that it is related to the
balance of power". For women the
implications of this position would
include "taking advantage of the
education that they have received
in order to gain equivalent
economic, social or political
power" to that of men, and not, for
example, being inclined "more
often towards literary studies...
which provide fewer job oppor¬
tunities than training in science and
technology."
"Whereas girls are more
or less well represented
in general education,
they are generally under-
represented in technical
and professional educa¬
tion ... This trend is in¬
fluenced by the 'sexist'
image of different kinds
of training and the pro¬
fessions to which they
lead." Right, woman
welder at work at
Foshan, a town north of
Guang-Zhou (Canton),
Guang-Dong (Kwantung)
Province, China.
Photo Hersant © Fotogram, Paris
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
In 1980 the question of the
educational and vocational
guidance of women one in which
many countries have shown a
strong interest in recent years-
was examined in a number of
Unesco studies and then con¬
sidered in international meetings
such as the international congress
on the situation of women in
technical and vocational education
(Bonn), the international seminar
on opening up to women of voca¬
tional training and jobs traditionally
occupied by men (Frankfurt) and
the international seminar on
women's education, training and
employment in developed coun¬
tries (Tokyo).
This development has come
about through the support at world
level of a women's movement
which has emerged from the
overall thrust of feminist forms of
expression and from trends which
are as yet still vague and
unformulated.
The women's movement cuts
across not only countries and
régimes, social classes and parties,
but other social movements as
well. Essentially subversive, since
it tends towards the overthrow of
the existing male-dominated order,
it is fundamentally creative in the
sense that it proposes to join with
other movements in a creative
quest for the development of
tomorrow's societies.
In many countries the movement
has led to a spectacular upsurge in
women's studies (see the Unesco
Courier, July 1980, pages 28-34).
The status of women is no longer a
phenomenon hidden from view or
explored only by courageous
pioneers, it is a subject which is
now being studied in countries as
diverse as the United States,
Argentina, Canada, India and
Tunisia. International meetings on
research and teaching with regard
to women (especially the meeting
of experts held by Unesco in Paris
in May 1980; the meeting of Arab
women researchers, also organiz¬
ed by Unesco and held in Tunis in
April 1982; the international sym¬
posium organized by the Simone
de Beauvoir Institute of Concordia
University, Montreal, July-August
1982) have taken stock of these
activities and drawn conclusions
with a view to more effective ac¬
tion in the future.
Interest is also growing in the
field of non-formal education,
which is particularly suitable for in¬
novation. Many activities directed
"The individual and collective investment represented by the educa¬
tion of women is turned to little account, or else it is subtly diverted
in the sense that it serves only to give 'added value' to what is ex¬
pected of women as mothers and housekeepers".
towards the education and promo¬
tion of women are being encourag¬
ed by international organizations
like Unesco, the Council of Europe,
the International Council for Adult
Education, and by small, dynamic
teams of enthusiasts.
Unesco has three experimental
projects in this area: in Upper Volta
(education of women in a rural en¬
vironment); in Nepal (training
teachers for rural primary schools);
and in Chile (on the access of women
to technical secondary education
with a view to their preparation for
technical careers).
Not that the schools have been
neglected. The realization that col¬
lective mentalities have an impact on
the education of women has also led
to appropriate action concerning the
organization and content of school
programmes.
The Greek educational system is
now totally co-educational. In the
Netherlands a large number of
specific measures have been taken
on the principle that "education
should not encourage the determina¬
tion of respective roles but should on
the contrary create the conditions for
maximum fulfilment irrespective of
sex". Action against the inculcation
in and by the school system of
stereotypes concerning the roles of
men and women has also been taken
in Norway, the Federal Republic of
Germany, Denmark and Ireland.
The crowds of girls who throng at
the school gates, their older sisters
who intend to pursue their education
as far as possible and to reap the
fullest benefits from it, the many
adult women without qualifications
who are calling for a training which is
their due all expect to be treated by
society and the educational system'
as members of society whose
horizons will never again be delimited
by the walls of the family home.
I Maria Eliou
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Islam's
Qur'anic schools
by Abdul Aziz El Koussy
THE main objective of the
Qur'anic school is to teach its
students to know by heart the
Qur'an, the sacred book of the Muslims
whose religion is Islam and who
wholeheartedly believe that the Qur'an is
the true word of God.
The population of the Muslim world is
currently estimated to be over 600
million people distributed largely in
Africa and Asia and also in smaller
groups in other parts of the world. For
Muslims the Qu'ran is the Divine Revela¬
tion which the Prophet Muhammad was
bidden to declare and to teach to all
human beings all over the world at all
times, in order to guide them to the right
path in this and the other world.
Muhammad appeared among the
Arab people with his message in the year
610 AD. Arab society was then made up
of a number of tribes, each of which had
its own deity which was usually
represented by an idol. The result was
the prevalence of idol worship, and a
multiplicity of Gods. Islam came to
establish uncompromising monotheism
and to do away with the chaos, to purify
human society, and to bring to it
balance, order, security and peace. The
Prophet was the first teacher, and the
Qur'an was the only book for the new
believers. There was an urgent and basic
need for education and instruction.
In the very early days of Islam the first
teaching place was the house in Mecca of
Al-Arqam, one of the Prophet's com¬
panions, and many of the early believers
received instruction privately in a house.
People would transform parts of their
homes for this purpose. When the Pro¬
phet migrated with his companions to
Medina he built the mosque which still
bears his name, and it was used both as
a place of worship and for instructing his
companions and-followers. The message
had to be accurate to the letter, and in
order to be transmitted to others it had
to be learned by heart. The believers sat
in a circle (Halaka) around the teacher,
and learned by listening, by repeating
ABDUL AZIZ HAMID EL KOUSSY, of
Egypt, is emeritus professor of psychology at
Ain Shams University, Cairo. A member of
Egypt's National Specialized Council for
Education, Science and Technology, he was
the founder-director of Unesco's Regional
Centre for Educational Planning in the Arab
States (1961-1971). His publications include
The Visual Perception of Space and Fun¬
damentals of Psychology.
26
and by trying to understand. For women
believers, the wives of the Prophet and
their companions played a very impor¬
tant role. Teaching and learning ac¬
quired so high a reputation during the
lifetime of the Prophet that the teaching
of reading and writing was accepted
from a non-Muslim as ransom for his
liberation from captivity.
there was at least one in every village in
the Muslim world.
In Egypt the University of Al Azhar,
with its various colleges and branches,
stands at the apex of a vast structure of
institutions including institutes of
Qur'anic elocution, large numbers of
primary and secondary schools, and
6,000 specialized Qur'anic schools. The
A blind sheikh teaching children the Qur'an in an Egyptian village.
As time passed and the numbers of
believers in Africa, Asia and other parts
of the world multiplied, Islamic schools
of various types were created. They had
different names, but all had the same ob¬
jective. In Egypt the Kuttab, which is
neither held in nor attached to a mosque,
teaches reading, writing, arithmetic,
religion and, most important of all, the
memorization of the Qur'an. The
Khalwa in the Sudan is a small room at¬
tached to a mosque and is mainly used
for mystic meditation and as a place
where students are helped to memorize
the Qur'an. Other Islamic schools in¬
clude the Zawia in Libya, the Dox in
Somalia, the Yemeni Milama, and the
Msid school in Morocco, as well as the
various levels of Madrasahs and
Maktabs. Qur'anic schools reached their
highest point in the Middle Ages, when
University receives male and female
students from all over the Muslim world
and offers a wide range of courses in
religious, linguistic, medical, engineering
and other subjects. Other universities
were founded in Damascus, Tunis, Fez
and other great cities over a thousand
years ago, but AI Azhar has won the
most recognition and is still developing.
Backed by the force of faith, the
schools multiplied, flourished,
developed and received financial and
moral support from the people. To give
a donation or help build a school was
considered an act of piety. The fact that
the people have supported this Qur'anic
educational movement spontaneously
and uninterruptedly for almost fourteen
centuries all over the vast Muslim world
is a firm indication of the genuine deep-
rootedness of the faith behind it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Qur'anic school usually has a
single room; the number of students
varies from ten or twenty to some hun¬
dreds. A typical scene during the school
day may be described as follows. The
teacher is squatting on a high platform,
orchestrating and vigilantly watching the
whole scene. Some students are copying
verses from the Holy Book on to a slate
while others revise their assignment
before being tested by the teacher, or
Sheikh. Some are being tested and
prompted by monitors, boys older than '
themselves, before taking the final test.
A group of five or six children in a cor¬
ner are reading chapters in a chorus with
a leading boy. They correct themselves
as they go along, and the chorus goes on
until they have all learned the passage.
The chorus method is very effective since
every child is keen not to be out of
tune hence the concentration of atten¬
tion, self evaluation and self-correction.
When a student can recite any part of the
Qur'an from memory, he too is given the
title of "Sheikh", a big celebration is
held by his family, and the teacher is
given a valuable present.
Pedagogically a number of practices
are questionable, but some others are
sound. It is worth noting that before the
close of the eighteenth century two
British educators, Andrew Bell and
Joseph Lancaster, independently of each
other, adopted the monitor method
from Indian Qur'anic schools. During
the expansion of schools in England at
that time very large numbers of students
were taught using this method by a very
small number of teachers. The monitor
system is also known in France, pro¬
bably as a result of the country's long
contact with North Africa. This practice
of encouraging the younger pupils to
learn from the older and more mature is
to be recommended. In Qur'anic schools
each student can proceed at his own
speed. Some learn the Qur'an in two or
three years, while others need six or
seven years, and it is understood that
some need not learn the whole text.
Until recently, the school day began at
sunrise and ended when the sun was half¬
way between mid-day and sunset. The
school day ended when the shadow of a
person standing in the sun was equal to
his height.
The students mixed their own ink by
collecting soot, mixing it with water and
oil, and soaking with it a piece of cloth
inside the inkpot. Pens were usually
made of Persian reed and were sharpen¬
ed by the students themselves. In some
schools students practised handwork
using local materials, some helped pro¬
duce the arts and crafts of the
community.
In Egypt a minister heads the whole
system of Azharite education, develop¬
ing its primary, secondary and higher
levels. Between Azharite and modern,
formal education there is a gap which is
wide at the lower levels, narrow at the
university level. Sometimes minor ten¬
sions arise. In the Sudan a Khalwa stu-
Right, the 14th-century
madrasah (school) of Bu
Inaniya, at Fez, Morocco.
During the first centuries
of the Hijra the madrasah
was the university of the
Islamic world. The cur¬
riculum was based on the
Qur'an and the Hadith
(sayings of the Prophet),
but grammar, literature,
mathematics and some¬
times medicine were also
taught. Below, detail
from a 15th-century
miniature now in the
Topkapi Museum, Istan¬
bul. It is an illustration for
Layla and Majnun, a
famous romantic poem by
the 1 2th-century Persian
poet Nizami, and shows
Majnun, the hero of the
poem, at school.
Photos Roland Michaud
Paris
Rapho,
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
dent can sit for an examination at the
fourth grade level and if he passes can at¬
tend a complementary school before
entering normal formal schooling. In
Tunisia Qur'anic schools were incor¬
porated into modern formal schooling
immediately after independence in 1956.
It is known that the ulemas or teachers in
the religious schools resisted French
colonization.
In Indonesia the Ministry of Religion
was responsible for some 19,000 schools
with about three million pupils in 1979,
at a time when the country's total
number of primary level pupils stood at
twenty-two million. Indonesia and Niger
are countries where there is no
discrimination whatever between the
Qur'anic school student and the formal
education student. But uniting the
various trends and policies regarding
Qur'anic schools there is an overriding
attitude of respect, and even reverence.
However, difficult problems have
arisen, particularly in Africa and South¬
east Asia. For one thing modern educa¬
tion with a European pattern has inun¬
dated the Muslim world and has had a
strong polarizing effect on resources.
Modern formal education gets practical¬
ly the whole of the State educational
budget while the Qur'anic school still
depends on private donations and im¬
poverished trusts. Qur'anic schools in
some countries occupy small, over¬
crowded rooms with poor and primitive
equipment. People support the
Qur'anic, the Government supports the
formal school.
In some countries two or more
streams of education exist, separated by
an unbridgable gap. This creates in
equality of opportunities and influences
currents of thought and prospects.
Difficulties also arise concerning the
meaning and understanding of the texts
beacause of the difference between
modern Arabic and the seventh-century-
AD Arabic in which the Qur'an was
written.
But the most important problem of all
is the tension in some Muslim countries
today between three types of language:
the official language, which is either
French or English; the vernacular, which
is the mother tongue of everyday living;
and the Arabic language of Islam and
the Qur'an. To be torn between three
very important options, one dear to the
student's creed, one for daily life, and
one for official use, creates a problem
which is difficult to overcome.
Abdul Aziz El Koussy
Ghana's university of
science and technology
by Frank Obed Kwami
WHENthe University ofScience and Technology (UST)
at Kumasi, Ghana, was established in 1961, the Act of
Incorporation specified that the objectives the
University should follow in its academic pursuits should be of
relevance to the needs and aspirations of Ghanaians. This ap¬
parently axiomatic statement reflects a very real difficulty which
faced many establishments ofhigher education in countries emerg¬
ing from the colonial past and which the history of the UST
illustrates.
The UST is the successor to the Kumasi College of Technology
which was founded in 1952 and which was recognized by London
University, in the United Kingdom, as a college providing training
in engineering leading to the London University B.Sc. degree.
Even after Ghana achieved independence (in 1957) and after the
newly established UST was in a position to award its own degrees,
examinations were conducted by external examinersfrom the U.K.
to ensure standards equivalent to those of British universities on
which formal recognition of the UST engineering degree by British
professional institutions depended.
It was soon clear that as long as this arrangement continued the
necessary flexibility in the adaptation of curricula and syllabuses
to reflect national development needs could not exist. Further¬
more, while the majority of the teaching staffand heads ofdepart¬
ments were expatriates, there persisted a residual feeling that a
shifting of educational objectives to reflect these needs was
synonymous with falling standards.
In 1969, the University Council set up a Committee to evaluate
the University's past record and to identify areas in which the
University could make significant future contributions to the
economic, industrial and social development and advancement of
the country. One of the recommendations made by the Committee
was the establishment ofa technology Consultancy Centre, a novel
FRANK OBED KWAMI, of Ghana, is head of the mechanical
engineering department, dean of the faculty of engineering, and
acting vice-chancellor of the University of Science and Technology,
Kumasi, Ghana. He has undertaken a number of missions for the
Government of Ghana, for Unesco and other U.N. agencies.
form of University institution for technology transfer, whose mis¬
sion is to collaborate with all departments of the University, to
keep the outside community informed of their resources and ex¬
pertise and to help them to develop technologies of use to the na¬
tion as a whole. In addition, the Centre receives requestsfor advice
on problems from the outside community which it channels back
to the department of the University concerned.
During 1972 and 1973, the Faculty of Engineering initiated a
thorough review of its curricula and methods so as to make them
more relevant to the country's development needs. Students follow
a four-year degree programme. During their second semester
students receive practical training in the Faculty's workshops and
laboratories where they are introduced to mechanical and electrical
workshop practice, production activities, civil engineering con¬
struction work andfield work in surveying. During vacations they
attend training courses at carefully selected industrial enterprises
under close supervision of the teaching staff. Field trips to in¬
dustrial organizations and engineering sites are organized regularly
for each class.
A striking innovation is the setting up ofproduction units within
the departments of the Faculty. These are virtually mini-enterprises
in which products developed in the departments are produced on
a semi-commercial basis. The units provide students with training
in such fields as work study, production control and management
and familiarize them with all the processes of engineering
manufacturing from production to the marketing stage.
The final year of the degree course is devoted to work on major
projects which are carefully screened by a panel of teachers ac¬
cording to criteria which take into account their local relevance and
engineering content.
In making this review and adaptation of its curricula and
methods the prime objective of the Faculty of Engineering was to
match its education and training programmes to the needs of na¬
tional development without loss of academic standards. In 1983,
with established Departments in civil, mechanical, electrical and
electronic, geodetic and chemical engineering, with a student body
ofover 800, and a seventy-strong teaching and research staff 90per
cent of whom are Ghanaian, the Faculty believes that it has suc¬
cessfully achieved this goal.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
A model school
for blind children
The school for the blind at Bargur, a small town in
southern India.
Parents are encouraged to visit the school as often as
possible. Arna, who suffers from other handicapé in addi¬
tion to his blindness, requires special attention, and his
mother, who lives nearby, comes to school almost every
afternoon to play with him.
,
t \\cm
Au
^^^^m ^B t4^^
iL *h
lin
At the Bargur school, boys as well as girls are taught to
mend clothes and sew on buttons and, if they wish, can
go on to learn fine needlework.
Photos Unesco, from one of a series of slide and script presentations giving examples
of good practice in the education of handicapped children, produced by Unesco's
Special Education Unit, Paris
TEN years ago, in the little town of Bargur in south
India, a school for blind children opened its doors.
Life is hard in this part of India, the majority of people
are very poor, and for most of them life ¡s a struggle for sur¬
vival. There is no industry, farm land is scarce, and the crops
are very often destroyed by droughts or floods. These condi¬
tions result in poverty, disease and malnutrition.
There ¡s a very high incidence of blindness in this part of
India, especially among children. The parents of such
children are helpless, and blindness constitutes an addi¬
tional burden on the family. Assistance and advice are not
available on the contrary, blindness meets with supersti¬
tion, prejudice and fear.
Perhaps the same situation would still exist today had it
not been for a lady whose vision and determination brought
some drastic changes. Near her home she often saw parents
taking their blind children to the local temple in order to seek
miracle cures. One day, while visiting the temple, she sud¬
denly became convinced that she should initiate some kind
of assistance for these unfortunate people.
She happened to meet a representative of an international
organization, Christophe! Blindenmission, based in the
Federal Republic of Germany, and asked him for support.
After a long series of talks and negotiations, in which she
encouraged and stimulated other people in the community,
plans were finalized for the establishment of a blind school,
in close collaboration with the international agency.
However, those responsible were determined not to create
a conservative type of school. Academic knowledge alone
would not be sufficient to equip blind children to cope with
adversity; they would have to learn many other skills to be
able to stand on their own feet.
Consequently, the leaders of the project decided to make
Bargur a "school for life", and the normal curriculum for
blind children was enlarged and enriched by a great variety
of useful and practical projects.
From the day of admission onwards, every student is
helped to become independent. Naturally the three Rs are
not neglected, so that the child learns to read and write in
Braille and do basic arithmetic. At the same time, a wide
variety of daily living skills are taught, including very simple
tasks such as dressing, cooking, laundering, ironing, sewing
and knitting, but also mobility and orientation and a
multitude of pre-vocational skills.
Great efforts are made not to separate the children from
their homes. Realizing that their parents are often more in
need of help than the children themselves, regular home
visits are paid by the school's social worker, and parents are
frequently invited to visit the school. During the school
holidays, all children must return to their homes, and the
school also encourages weekend visits to families and
friends who live in the vicinity of the school. The counselling
service is extended even to blind people beyond school age
and it is planned to organize special handicraft courses for
them in the near future.
When the school opened in 1973 there were already
forty-two pupils, and by 1 979, with the addition of another
hostel and two more classrooms, their numbers had risen to
almost a hundred.
One of the biggest problems was the recruitment and
training of good staff. The Management Committee decided
against sending any of the teachers abroad and instead in¬
itiated an in-service teacher-training programme at the
school. For this purpose an experienced German teacher of
the blind was invited and under her guidance almost twenty
teachers were helped to become familiar with appropriate
modern teaching methods.
Residential schools often have disadvantages for
N children, and the Bargur Committee has seen to it that these
will be avoided in their school. Several visitors have com¬
mented on the atmosphere of joy and happiness which
prevails there, which shows that even in these simple con¬
ditions, children can grow up to be happy young adults.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ARAB COUNTRIES
Unesco-assisted projects
I
ALGERIA: Development of the Education and Training
System
A number ofhigh-level consultants provide services whenever a need oc¬
curs. Several sub-projects are related to a study ofhuman resource needs
for education and employment up to the year 2000, educational manage¬
ment andfacilities, educational content, teacher training and vocational
training.
BAHRAIN: The Centre for Rehabilitation and Integration
of the Disabled
The Centre for Rehabilitation and Integration of the Disabled was
established in the town of Isa in 1979 with Unesco aid. It can provide
education and rehabilitation servicesfor 120 handicapped young people.
Great emphasis is placed on programmes for the mentally retarded,
education of the deaf and vocational training. The integration of
rehabilitated young people into schools, industry and the community is
the ultimate aim of the Centre's activities.
LEBANON: Relaunching and Development of Technical
Education and Vocational Training
The project is concerned with the relaunching of technical and vocational
training which is essential to ensure the quantitative and qualitative
development of the necessary manpower to enable the Lebanon 's social
and economic reconstruction to take place. A 6-year Plan foresaw an in¬
crease in enrolments in technical schoolsfrom 5, 000 to 25, 000 and an in¬
crease in the teaching force from 1,000 to 5,000. Although the project,
which began in 1980, has not been able to achieve all its objectives
because of the difficult conditions in the Lebanon since then, there has
been no interruption in project activities and remarkably good progress
has been made.
OMAN: Towards a Balanced Educational System
The project forms part of the Second Five- Year Plan (1981-1985) which
stresses the need to strengthen training activities to provide a greater
number ofOmani teachers and reduce dependence on expatriate labour.
Main results include: reorganization of the Ministry of Education;
development of educational planning; linking technical/vocational
education to manpower needs; introducing health and nutrition
education.
QATAR: The Faculty of Education
The project was originally designed to establish two teacher training col¬
leges (one for men, one for women) but these have subsequently been
upgraded to become the Faculty ofEducation ofthe University ofQatar.
Initially the main objectives were to assist in the training of teachers and
administrators at all levels, and in the strengthening of links between
educationalfacilities and the country 's social and economic needs. Other
aims have since been added, including the procurement of equipment,
library development, and the development of training programmes for
women.
Agreat deal of thought is being
given these days to the question
of the form education should
take in tomorrow's world. The great in¬
terest this question arouses is doubtless
due to the fact that, by its very nature,
education is more closely involved with
the future than most other fields of
human activity. Will the school as we
know it today be capable of preparing
our children for life in the 21st century
in face of the accelerated pace of
change and innovation predicted in
every field? Should not reform of the
educational system designed to meet
this new challenge be a priority objec¬
tive throughout the world? What pros¬
pects of evolution are open to educa¬
tional systems?
Opinions on this matter range from
extreme pessimism to excessive and un¬
justified optimism. There are those
who maintain that existing structures
are more resistant than is generally sup¬
posed and that things will have changed
little by the year 2000; others build their
hopes on forecasts of technocratic
solutions, some of which belong to the
realms of pure fantasy; some consider
that the educational systems of the dif¬
ferent countries will become more and
more similar in pattern whereas yet
others believe that they will become
more firmly rooted in national cultural
identities and that, as a result, their ob¬
jectives, principles, methods and
educational content will become more
and more differentiated.
The wide disparity between these
views as to the future of education
becomes more understandable if ac¬
count is taken of the often radical
divergences of opinion there have been
in the assessment of the past history of
education, including the period of most
recent years. For the history of educa¬
tion casts its shadow on the future. It
shows that, in most countries of the
world, the last two or three decades
have been a period of unprecedented
expansion. In the developing countries,
in which the overwhelming majority of
the world's population lives, national
BORIS F. KLUCHNIKOV, of the USSR, is in
charge of the research programmes of the
Higher School Institute of the USSR Ministry
of Higher and Secondary Technical Education.
He is a former director of Unesco's Division of
Educational Policy and Planning and before
that served as a Unesco consultant. He is the
author of a number of works on educational
planning and economics.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Some future prospects
by Boris Kluchnikov
Potential future grand masters of chess study the end game in a school at Kislovodsk in the Caucasus
foothills, near Pyatogorsk, USSR. Chess is becoming part of the regular curriculum for children from the age
of 6 in many Soviet schools.
education systems have been establish¬
ed for the first time in their history, and
the elimination of illiteracy and the
provision of primary education for all
have become officially recognized as
priority national objectives.
According to Unesco statistics, dur¬
ing the period 1960 to 1980 the number
of pupils and students in the developing
countries increased 2.4 times at the
primary level, 4.6 times at the secon¬
dary level and 6.3 times in higher
education. At the same time fun¬
damental qualitative changes occurred
which brought about what might be
described as the "decolonization" of
education. Pupils began to be taught in
their own languages and to study the
history, literature, geography and
general nature of their own countries.
In the socialist countries, over a _
relatively, short period of time, secon-
dary education became . generally
available and in the industrialized
countries of the West and in Japan
there has also been a rapid expansion in
education, especially in higher educa¬
tion of both long and short duration;
there- has also, however, been a con-,
siderablë increase in unemployment
among young people with specialist
qualifications.
The notion of the democratization of
education and of equal access and op¬
portunity for all, in the development
and application of which' Unesco has
played a considerable rôle, has spread,
to most countries of the world. Unesco
figures show that, in the hundred coun¬
tries, for which statistics are available,
annual expenditure on education in¬
creased, in real terms, from $115 thou¬
sand million in 1960 to $365 thousand
million in 1976, an average increase of
from 3.7 per cent to 5.7 -per cent of
Gross National Product.
At the same time, however, expen¬
diture on armaments reached the even
greater figure of $600 thousand million
and, in many countries, escalation of
the arms race has led to a reduction in
social expenditure, in particular on
education, . culture and scientific
research for peaceful purposes.
In many countries there is an
ominously growing tendency to push
education into the background; there is
now an evident lowering of political
will to maintain the rapid educational
expansion of the 1960s and 1970s. And
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
the belief is gaining ground that in the
Third World education may be a bot¬
tomless pit. This is the consequence of
the serious problems that have arisen in
the educational systems of many coun¬
tries which are seen to be divorced from
life and the real needs of the communi¬
ty, thus contributing to higher
unemployment particularly among
young people, to be incapable of
eliminating illiteracy, and to be ignor¬
ing the needs of women and girls, and
so on. The rapid emergence of notable
differences in the quality of education
can be clearly discerned and, in many
countries, two distinct forms of educa¬
tion are becoming institutionalized
one for the general public and one for
a socially-privileged élite, a high stan¬
dard of education for the town, a lower
quality for the country, with a similar
divide appearing between the deve¬
loped and the developing countries.
Besides, criticism of the objectives of
education and the rigidity of its struc¬
tures is largely justified, as are charges
that programmes are out of date and
that there are delays in using the fruits
of science and technology to improve
the efficiency of the educational pro¬
cess. All these obstacles to the positive
development of education have given
rise to a far-reaching international
debate on the crisis through which
education is passing.
Nevertheless, a close examination of
the difficulties and successes of educa¬
tion today casts serious doubts on the
reality of a world crisis in education. In
the light of analysis it is possible to af
firm that this crisis is not universal in
nature and that its manifestations are
limited to countries which arevgoing
through a period of overall crisis in
their development.
But in the others too, the successes of
recent decades provide no grounds for
unthinking optimism about the future,
even excluding the possibility of war or
a global catastrophe.
Statistical projections based on
Unesco studies give us some idea of the
future evolution of education and some
alarming trends are being revealed. The
rate of growth in the number of pupils
will probably decline during the 1980s
at all levels and for all kinds of educa¬
tion, and as a result the goal of univer¬
sal primary education for all by the
year 2000 will not be attained. As in the
past, illiteracy will continue to be con¬
centrated in the developing countries in
the countryside and among women. To
the detriment of the people, a growing
number of countries, including some
developing countries, are becoming in¬
volved in the arms race. Over the past
few years, within a whole group of
countries, a relative, and at times ab¬
solute, reduction has been seen in
educational expenditure, in particular
on primary schooling, the eradication
of illiteracy and the training of adults.
We believe that, contrary to what is
sometimes thought, there is no real
choice to be made between the demo¬
cratization of education, primary
education for all, the eradication of il¬
literacy and the concentration of
resources on improving the quality of
education and the training of cadres for
the economy.
Public expenditure on education is
diminishing in certain industrialized
countries. To the detriment of the
general school and of the quality of
education, there is a concentration on
forms of education of interest to the
large corporations and in particular to
the military complexes.
The revival of another alarming
tendency has become evident in recent
years. Neo-conservatives" among
educationists are attempting to make
use of the fact of the inequality of in¬
tellectual capacity to attack the notion
of the democratization of education.
For those who believe in "genetic
determinism" there "is no point in talk¬
ing of equality of opportunity and even
less of equality of achievement. It is
hardly necessary to point out how con¬
venient the notion of genetic deter¬
minism is for those who want to reduce
social expenditure in general and to
limit the financial responsibility of the
State for education.
There is considerable justification
for current criticism of the objectives
of education, of the rigidity of its struc¬
tures, its anachronistic programmes
and the delay in making use of scien¬
tific and technological advances to im¬
prove the efficacy of the process of ac¬
quiring knowledge. Use on a large scale
of new teaching methods, in particular
programmed teaching and informatics,
offers wide prospects for the per¬
sonalization of education. Of course,
everything depends on the way these
An open-air school in the
Cauca district, Colombia.
Photo © Cris Queiroz, Pans
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
"Morning came. Fire was still smouldering in Hiroshima. I entered the city. Many people were dead in the
fire prevention water tank, their bodies scorched black. I saw a dead woman, her standing body scorched
black, holding a child in her arms and still in a running position. Utterly incredible, but this was reality". This
drawing is by Yasuko Yamagata who was 17 years old when the first atomic bomb fell on Hiroshima on
the morning of 6 August 1945. It is taken from Hiroshima-Nagasaki, Pictures of the Atomic Bombings, a
book published in 1 981 by a committee of Japanese citizens, founded in 1 977, whose goal is the abolition
of all nuclear weapons so that the tragedies of Hiroshima and Nagasaki shall never be repeated. The book
records, in photographs and drawings and in the testimony of eye-witnesses, the full horror of the bombings
and their aftermath. Some of the drawings by the Hibakusha (survivors of the bombings) like Yasuko
Yamagata were made up to 30 years after the event, but they retain all the immediacy of a moment in time
etched indelibly on the memory.
Drawing Yasuko Yamagata © 1981, Committee for the Publication of the Book Hiroshima-Nagasaki
new techniques are used. Clearly no
machine will ever replace the teacher
whose task it is to shape the younger
generation's vision of the world.
The potentialities of these new edu¬
cational means relate less to reducing
the cost of education than to improving
its quality. They free the teacher from
the repetitive, routine aspects of his
work, allowing him to devote greater
attention to the personality of the pu¬
pil, bringing out his human qualities
and developing his power of logical
thought, teaching him the methodolo¬
gy of the acquisition of knowledge and
giving him an understanding of his rôle
in life, of his occupation and of his
obligations to society.
The world of work offers great possi¬
bilities for the rounding off and per¬
sonalization of the student's education.
In preparing the 11th Five Year Plan
(1981-1985), Soviet educationists put
forward a number of possible scenarios
for the development of the educational
system up to 1990. Particular attention
is paid to pre-school education and, in
one school model, whilst a structure of
teaching by disciplines is preserved, the
time allocated to practical work in the
laboratory and work-oriented instruc¬
tion is considerably increased.
New objectives were also proposed
for higher education, which is playing
an increasingly important rôle in Soviet
society. In the USSR today, some 12
million specialists, or one worker in 10,
have benefited from higher education.
Generalized higher education, with
universities at Moscow, Tashkent, Sa¬
markand and Baku for 1 50 thousand to
200 thousand students, can now be rea¬
listically envisaged. The problem is to
ensure that this mass education does
not lead to standardization and the
drowning of individual personality and
that personalized instruction is
introduced.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
It is commonly accepted today that it
is no longer possible to have a once-
and-for-all period of study and that it is
vital to know how to renew a person's
educational acquisitions throughout
his entire life. The system of training
specialists must become sufficiently
flexible to cope with rapid re-training
to meet new requirements. The Plan
proposes this objective for the years to
come: "The method of planning the
training of specialists in higher educa¬
tional establishments must allow of a
rapid response to the imperatives of the
national economy". The complexity of
this objective can be gauged by the fact
that in the USSR some 500 special
fields of study appear each year (and
about the same number of old ones
disappear).
This approach, it would appear, can
only be given greater prominence in the
future, and this is why, from now on,
particular attention is to be given to
promising scientific developments such
as quantic electronics, microproces¬
sors, medicine, biology, genetics, the
energies of the future and the safe¬
guarding of the environment. At the
same time, a system of retraining for
specialists is being established which
between now and the year 2000 may be
instructing greater numbers than thé
system of initial training. The educa¬
tion of adults 'with their specific needs
will be closely associated with this
system.
This brief overview would not be
complete without a mention of the ex¬
perimental research on new models of
schools and higher educational estab¬
lishments now being carried out in the
national republics of the USSR and
which take into account local condi¬
tions and cultural differences. Com¬
parison of the experiences of the dif¬
ferent Soviet republics is of great im¬
portance to forecasting in the educatio¬
nal field, and this great undertaking
would be given new impetus if it could
be coupled with a vast effort of interna¬
tional CO-Operation. Boris Kluchnikov
0 p
ID
IB rn
Brazil remembers
a modern master
Brazil has launched a major project to
study and make more widely known the
life and work of the great modern painter
Candido Portinari (1903-1962), whose
estimated output of some 4,000 works
constitutes a vast visual synthesis of the
land and people of Brazil. The project
aims to locate and document all the ar¬
tist's work, create a Portinari data bank
and produce a wide range of publications
and audio-visual material. The ultimate
goal is the establishment of a Portinari
Foundation as a centre for cultural
research and investigation and a means
of promoting the work of contemporary
Brazilian artists.
Recent Unesco books
on education
The Education of Adults, A
world perspective. Co-published
with OISE Press who have ex¬
clusive sales rights in Canada. 2nd
revised edition, 1982. 280 pp.
(45 F)
The Economics of New
Educational Media, Vol. 3. Cost
and effectiveness overview and
synthesis, by Jean-Claude Eicher,
David Hawkridge, Emile McAny,
François Mariet, François Orivel.
(No. 1 in Unesco's "Educational
Methods and Techniques" series)
1982, 150 pp. (35 F)
Higher Education and the
New International Order, edited
by Bikas C. Sanyal. Contributions
by Malcolm Adiseshiah, Theodore
Schultz, Jan Tinbergen, Bogdan
Suchodolski, Rafael Salas, Edmun¬
do Fuenzalida, Samir Amin, Pablo
Latapi, Jean-Louis Reiffers,
Mohamed Moursi Ahmed,
Mohamed Hamdy El-Nashar. Co-
published with Frances Pinter
Publishers Ltd., who have ex¬
clusive sales rights in the UK for
hardbound copies only. 1 982, 242
pp. (100 F)
The Right to Education:
What Kind of Management? by
Daniel Haag. 1 982, 1 75 pp. (30 F)
School Buildings and Natural
Disasters, by D.J. Vickery. 1982
(25 F)
Terminology of Adult Educa¬
tion, by Colin Titmus. Trilingual:
English/French/Spanish. First
published 1979, reprinted 1981.
154 pp. (28 F)
Terminology of Technical
and Vocational Education, first
published 1978, reprinted 1982.
88 pp. (12 F)
Literacy and Illiteracy, by An¬
dré Lestage. 1982, 31 pp. (10 F)
A Systems Approach to
Teaching and Learning Pro¬
cedures. A guide for educators.
2nd edition revised and expanded.
1981, 203 pp. (40 F)
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
3~4
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb,
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Pans.
So
<=>
. o
¡<
ê ce
uj'V
go
1 1
°- w
$o
CE Q.
<DS
QO
<o
Oh
oo
CE I
CD Q.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
World Guide to Higher Education provides a com¬
parative, world-wide, country-by-country survey of
the most characteristic elements of both the systems
and the main stages of higher education. For each
country it presents:
a general description of its higher education system
a glossary of degrees and qualifications awarded in
the system
a table showing the period of study required for
degrees and qualifications in major subject areas.
The information presented in the Guide has been com¬
piled by the International Association of Universities,
and many governments have provided information and
suggestions concerning the texts on their respective
countries.
Second edition Hardbound, 195 French francs
Co-published with Bowker Publishing Co., Epping, and Unipub,
New York, who have exclusive sales rights in the United Kingdom
and the United States respectively.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Collmg-
wood Victoria 3066, Publications' Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub- agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, P.O. Box 175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000. - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31, A-101 1, Vienna.
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd., Ittefaq
Building, 1, P..K. Mission Rd-, Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco
publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1 060
Brussels, CCP000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd , 21 82 St. Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que. H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Bei|ing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display), Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukemcka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa
Verlag Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava
CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI. National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10; Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01 640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
I'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP. 1 2598-48.
- GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig,
Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish
editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57,0 5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publica¬
tions: Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps
only. Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80. GHANA.
Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1 , Legón.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG.
Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion,
12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock
Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government Information Services,
Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkóztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 1 3; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; 5-9-4 1 Al
Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi"
Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery
Co. 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 7001 6, Scindia House, New Delhi,
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001 . IN¬
DONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardmata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakar¬
ta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1 486, Teheran, Iranian Nat. Comm for Unesco, Ave. Iran-
chahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1 533, Teheran - IRAQ. McKen¬
zies Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12 ISRAEL. A.B.C Bookstore Ltd.,
P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 -
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd , P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome,
Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait,
for the Unesco Courier : Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O.
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yan-
cy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35,
Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-
Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapien-
zas. 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street. Port-Louis. MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only: Dekker and Nordemann
NV, P.O Box 197,1 000 AD Amsterddam; for publications only.
KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
- NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V , P.O.
Box 200. Willemstad. Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, ^ Government Bookshops af
Rutland Street, P.O Box 5344, Auckland, 1 30, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P 0. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. - NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana.
NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers),
Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1; Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssentret, P.O.B. 307 Blindem, Oslo 3. For Unesco
Courier only A S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo
6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-
azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The
Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P O. Box 632, Manila
D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, War¬
saw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Por¬
tugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National
Bookshop, P.O. Box 48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate
House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay,
Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops,
Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd.,
No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road,
Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC.
Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951 , Mogadiscio
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van Schaik's Book-store
(Pty.) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central News agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 1 033, Johannesburg. - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 1 00 Sir Chtttampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B 244
Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B C E. Fntzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgránd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sn, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok. Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Raidamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 1 8 Alexandra Street, St Clair,
Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi,
No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. - UGANDA.
Uganda Bookshop, P.O Box 7145, Kampala. - UNITED
KINGDOM. H M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London,
S E.I , and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, for scientific maps only:
McCarta Ltd , 122 King's Cross Road, London WC1X 9 DS -
UNITED STATES. Unipub. 345 Park Avenue South, New
York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11,
Zagreb, Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazt-
je 27/1 1 , Belgrade. - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.,
67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
