<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074737eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
Man
and the
Biosphere
ouner
APRIL 1981 - 4.50 French francs
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
®
Chile
The bird-man
This wooden tangata manu ("bird-man")
statuette is an example of the religious art of
Easter Island. It is connected with the ancient
cult of the bird-god Matemake, in which the
islander who secured the first egg of the sea-
swallow manutara became "bird-man" for a
year and also exercised forms of sacred authori¬
ty and political power. The body of the statuette
is that of a man with skeletal ribs, but instead of
arms there are folded wings and the head has a
long beak. The statuette (33.7 cm high) is today
preserved in the Museum of Anthropology and
Ethnology at Leningrad.
Photo © Museum of Anthropology and Ethnology, Leningrad
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Ihr
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
APRIL 1981 34th YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch. Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 44 French Francs
2 years: 75 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 32 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue)
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ahn Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S A.; (2) N.C.R Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
(Paris)
Portuguese Edition:
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Frederick Potter (Paris)Braille
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Pans.
page
MAN AND THE BIOSPHERE
The first ten years of Unesco's environmental programme
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
ECOLOGY-THE GENESIS OF A SCIENCE
OF MAN AND NATURE
by Francesco di Castri
13 THE TROPICAL FOREST-
A RICH BUT FRAGILE RESOURCE
by Frank Golley and Malcolm Hadley
15 THE TAMING OF A SWAMP
The 'Chinampa' project, Mexico
16 NATURE'S CHEMICAL FACTORY
17 THE CHANGING FOREST
The Tai project. Ivory Coast
18 MARGINAL LANDS
Inhospitable 'fringe' regions ingeniously turned
to human advantage
by Mohamed Ayyad and Gisbert Glaser
21 HOLDING THE DESERT AT BAY
MAB-related research in southern Tunisia
22 MOUNTAIN SCENARIOS
The Pays d'Enhaut project, Switzerland
23 CITIES IN CRISIS
by Valerio Giacomini
24 THE ECOLOGY OF MEGALOPOLIS
by Stephen Boyden and John Celecia
27 CHANGE WITHOUT TEARS
The Lae project, Papua New Guinea
28 CONSERVATION FOR DEVELOPMENT
by Walter Lusigi and Jane Robertson
30 BIOSPHERE RESERVES IN THE USSR
by Vladimir Sokolov and Piotr Gounin
32 POACHERS TURNED GAMEKEEPERS
The Mapimi biosphere reserve experiment
33 GETTING THE MESSAGE ACROSS
by Jeanne Damlamian
34 PERSPECTIVES AND PROSPECTS
by Ralph Slatyer
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
CHILE: The bird-man
Cover
Unesco's Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Pro¬
gramme is ten years old this year. In this
issue of the Unesco Courier we present con¬
crete examples of what MAB has achieved in
four major priority areas of ecological
research during the past decade, a period
which has seen the concept of ecology itself
evolve to become an interdisciplinary,
problem-oriented science, centred on man,
which provides a new and realistic basis for
reconciling the seemingly contradictory
demands of conservation and development.
Graphic Gal © Unesco Courier, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Man and the
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
The first ten years of Unesco's
THIS year marks the tenth anniver¬
sary of the intergovernmental
research Programme on Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) which was
launched by Unesco in November 1971,
and whose purpose is to establish the
scientific basis necessary for land use
planning and for the management of
the resources of the biosphere in
harmony with nature.
By virtue of its scale over a hundred
countries engaged in a common effort
on some thousand applied research and
training projects involving more than
ten thousand scientists and tech¬
nicians Programme, now fully
operational, constitutes a vast natural
laboratory in which several guiding prin¬
ciples developed within Unesco are be¬
ing tested under field conditions.
Thus, confronted with the specific
problems of the environment, MAB has
confirmed a fundamental precept: for
science and technology to serve human
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Biosphere
environmental programme
progress more fully, they must be in¬
tegrated into each country's culture,
and the tasks which are undertaken in
their name should be in keeping with
that country's specific characteristics.
It has also become clear that the in¬
terdisciplinary approach which is fun¬
damental to Unesco's action is the one
best qualified to produce solutions to
the highly complex problems of the en¬
vironment. This is why the MAB Pro¬
gramme brings together specialists in
the natural and the exact sciences, as
well as specialists in the social and
human sciences, and planners.
Another factor in the Programme's
success is the participation of local
populations, both in identifying
priorities and in applying the results of
research. Here it has been necessary to
diversify the methods of presenting
scientific information, so as to make it
more accessible to those who will use
it,, as part of an education which
enables man to assume fuller respon¬
sibility for his natural and cultural
heritage.
The experience of the last ten years
has also yielded extremely valuable
results for international co-operation,
which has fostered the collaboration of
scientists, exchanges of information
and experimental data. By stimulating
and co-ordinating these operations,
Unesco has performed the role it has
marked out for itself as a catalyst of
ideas and action.
Another original feature of the Pro¬
gramme is that it has produced
substantial results from relatively
slender resources. Its action, relayed
from the small MAB secretariat to the
hundreds of persons working on MAB
National Committees and the
thousands of specialists engaged on
research and training activities, has had
a multiplier effect. Likewise, Unesco's
regular Programme budget, necessarily
limited in comparison to needs, has
served to generate funds from other
sources to the benefit of Member
States, or to facilitate agreements bet¬
ween countries, thus considerably in¬
creasing the possibilities of action.
Finally, the Man and the Biosphere
Programme is an excellent example of
the decentralization which Unesco is
striving to promote in all its fields of ac¬
tivity. In this case, decentralization is
almost total, since the Programme ac¬
tivities are carried out directly by the
countries themselves. They are gradual¬
ly acquiring an autonomy in this field
which should enable them to continue
the work they have begun, and to main¬
tain the co-operative relations which
have been established at the regional
and inter-regional levels. If, ten years
after its creation, the Man and the
Biosphere Programme has achieved un¬
doubted success and is continually ex¬
panding, it is essentially because the
participant countries have succeeded in
integrating it into their development
process.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Ecology
the genesis of a science
of man and nature
by Francesco di Castri
DURING the last ten years ecology has
become a fashionable word. It is
used frequently on radio and in daily
conversation and everybody thinks they
know what it means. But do they really?
Even among specialists there are con¬
siderable differences of opinion as to what
ecology is supposed to be and what it is sup¬
posed to do and, hence, how it should be
defined.
What exactly is ecology? A moral
philosophy and a form of action for the pro¬
tection of plants and animals? A political
party? A protest movement against nuclear
energy and pollution? A neo-Romantic year¬
ning for a return to Nature? A scientific
discipline derived from biology? Or
something of all these things? Is it a
philosophy, a message, a myth or a science?
There is no doubt in my mind that ecology
is first and foremost a science, but to say
positively when it began is a more difficult
matter. If it is seen as a science with a
clearly-defined corpus of knowledge and an
established methodology, then ecology is of
recent origin and has had an eventful
history. If, on the other hand, it is con¬
sidered merely as a scientific approach, it is
very ancient.
The works of Roman authors such as the
philosopher Lucretius, the poet Virgil or the
agronomist Columella already contain
elements of ecological principles. But these
are also to be found in all the other ancient
civilizations, and probably more frequently
in the East than in the West. Stretching a
FRANCESCO DI CASTRI is director of
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences. A
biologist, he was formerly Professor of Animal
Ecology at the University of Chile, at Santiago,
and director of the Institute of Ecology of
Valdivia, Chile, which he founded in 1969. He was
an active participant in the International Biological
Programme and was the first vice-president of the
Scientific Committee on Problems of the Environ¬
ment (SCOPE) of the International Council of
Scientific Unions (ICSU). He assisted in the
preparation of the United Nations Conference on
the Environment, held at Stockholm in 1972, and
has been Secretary of the International Co¬
ordinating Council of Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere Programme since it began in 1971.
point one could even say that, in order to
survive the harsh climate and hunt reindeer
and mammoth, cave-men had to show a
more highly developed ecological sense than
many modern ecologists.
The word ecology itself (from the Greek
word oikos, meaning home, habitat) was
coined in 1869 by the German scientist Ernst
Haeckel who used it to define the science
which studies the relationship between an
organism and its environment. Haeckel, a
far-sighted biologist and supporter of Dar¬
win's theories, peppered his writings with
new and often harmonious-sounding words
most of which are forgotten today.
"Ecology" was his most successful creation
judging by its popularity and the scientific
achievements it has encouraged.
Coining new words, incidentally, has
been the besetting sin of generations of
ecologists. The quaint, unwieldy and
sometimes incomprehensible neologisms
which they have invented are often an un¬
conscious way of concealing a lack of preci¬
sion in concepts and methods. These un¬
necessarily complicated terms certainly have
not helped the different schools of ecology
to benefit from one another's influence;
neither have they encouraged planners to
use the results of ecological research or
helped to familiarize the public with
ecological thought and action.
The genesis and especially the evolution
of ecology were very different from those of
the other sciences. Most sciences biology
is an example could be represented as a
tree trunk from which sprout a number of
branches (cytology, histology, physiology)
themselves subdivided into smaller and in¬
creasingly specialized ramifications
(molecular biology, neurophysiology, etc).
Ecology, on the other hand, would be
shown as a mass of roots, all converging to
form a common trunk: first botany, zoology,
climatology, the soil sciences and physical
geography; then biochemistry and
microbiology (for studying the processes of
biological production) and advanced
mathematics (for model construction) and,
finally, sociology, human geography,
psychology and even economics.
It would be difficult to claim that this com¬
mon trunk, ecology, is as consistent and
homogeneous as that of the other sciences.
The various disciplines that form it have not
yet harmonized their approaches and in¬
teractions. Perhaps they never will com¬
pletely. Yet it is this broad convergence of
disciplines which gives ecology its strength,
equipping it to face increasingly complex en¬
vironmental problems and to deal with the
multiple facets of social and natural systems
in which any change, even if it is limited to a
single element in the system, is bound to set
off a series of chain reactions affecting all
the others.
This is the crux of the dialectical debate
between the two types of sciences. The
analytical or reductionist sciences on the
one hand which set out to dissect and
dissociate the elements of a structure in
order to define them and study them in
depth, and, on the other, the synthetic or
holistic sciences (from the Greek word
holos, meaning whole), of which ecology is
the best example, that attempt to 'grasp a
system in its entirety by studying the inter¬
actions between all its elements.
This distinction should not be taken as a
value judgment. These two scientific ap¬
proaches, both equally important, are by
nature complementary and this might well
be better reflected in practice.
The fact remains that during recent
decades the reductionist sciences
(molecular biology, biochemistry and
biophysics) have taken overwhelming
precedence over ecology and the natural
and human sciences, not only in the financ¬
ing of research, but also as regards
academic and social prestige and in science
planning. In order to reverse this trend
ecology must prove much more convincing¬
ly than in the past its raison d'être in terms
of present-day science and society. .
I have not attempted to give a precise
definition of ecology and its achievements
because its research methods and even its
goals are developing so fast that any static
formula describing a single moment in its
evolution would appear forced and artificial.
Instead, I will try to tell the fascinating
story of a branch of science which has
always been trying to find its way, especially
during the last twenty-five years, but which
has now begun to find its true vocation
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
bringing together in one single study the co-
evolution of man and nature.
At the beginning of the present century,
ecology was still a descriptive study of
nature, a sort of natural history which drew
inspiration from the works of the great 19th
century explorers -and naturalists. Among
these was the Frenchman Jean-Henri Fabre
whose Souvenirs Entomologiques, written
between 1870 and 1889, still impress the
reader with their accuracy of observation
and their lyrical descriptions of natural
phenomena. Before long, however, more
detailed studies were to be made of the en¬
vironment in which given species live, and
of their symbiotic and antagonistic relation¬
ships with other species. This auto-ecology,
or ecology centred on a single species, had
and still has important applications, in par¬
ticular in the biological control of plant
pests, research on disease carriers and the
prevention of parasite-borne infections.
But each species, even when studied in
conjunction with those that influence it
directly, is only a tiny instance among the
thousands of plant, animal and microbial
species which inhabita given area a forest,
a pond or a beach. This realization led to the
development in the mid-1920s of
synecology, that is to say the ecology of
communities of species. (In this connexion
special mention should be made of the
names of August Thienemann, J. Braun-
Blanquet and Charles Elton.)
Basic concepts began to be applied, such
as the "food chain" and the "pyramid of
numbers", in which the number of in¬
dividuals decreases progressively from
plants at the base to herbivorous and
predatory animals at the summit. Vito
Volterra, G.F. Gause and Umberto D'An-
cona put forward mathematical laws gover¬
ning the population dynamics of interacting
groups of species. These studies proved
especially useful in aquatic ecology where
they helped to solve problems related to sea
fishing and to promote understanding of
phenomena such as insect invasions.
The publication in 1949 of Principles of
Animal Ecology, a collective work by five
American authors W.C. Allee, Alfred
Emerson, Orlando Park, Thomas Park and
Karl Schmidt drew attention to two impor¬
tant trends, one positive, the other negative.
It demonstrated that ecology in its wide-
ranging disciplines had adopted a strictly
scientific approach. But it also showed that
the new science was dissipating its efforts in
too many different directions, and above all
that it lacked a basic study unit similar to the
atom in physics, the cell in cytology, the
tissue in histology or the organ in
physiology.
This study unit was to be the ecosystem.
It can be described as an entity precisely
defined in space and time which includes
not only all the organisms inhabiting it, but
also physical conditions of climate and soil,
as well as all interactions between the dif¬
ferent organisms and between these
organisms and physical conditions.
An example of an ecosystem would be a
tropical forest, at a given place and time,
with thousands of plant, animal and
microbial species living in its soil and air
space with millions of specific interactions
taking place between them, the various in¬
fluences exercised on the life of these in¬
numerable beings by climate and soil, and
the changes the latter undergo as a result of
the organisms' activities and of the very ex¬
istence of the forest.
The term ecosystem was first proposed in
1935 by Arthur George Tansley. And in 1942
Raymond Lindeman pioneered the concep¬
tual and methodological bases for studying
these highly complex systems: the energy
flows and the nutritional cycles which pass
through all the living and non-living com¬
ponents of the ecosystem.
The story of Lindeman who died at the
age of 27 before his twenty-page paper ap¬
peared posthumously in the journal
Ecology illustrates the constraints to
which the progress and development of a
science can be subjected. In this particular
case, the constraints were imposed by the
scientific establishment itself. His article,
which has influenced ecological theory over
the last thirty years and is regarded today as
a classic, was first turned down by the jour¬
nal's scientific advisers. Lindeman was too
far ahead of his time.
It should be noted that other authors,
especially the Russians and Germans, have w
also suggested terms which to some extent f
THE EVOLUTION OF AN IDEA, This graphic
illustrates the five major stages leading to the
modern concept of ecology. The word
"ecology" was coined in 1869 by the German
biologist Ernst Haeckel, and by the beginning
of this century it had come to mean the study
of a single species and its biological
relationships with its environment (1). The
mid-1920s saw the meaning extended to cover
the study of communities of species and such
notions as "the food chain" and "the pyramid
of numbers" (2). By 1950 scientists had
developed the notion of the "ecosystem" as a
unit of study involving all the interactions
between the physical environment and the
species living in it (3). The next step was
recognition, in the 1970s, that the most critical
areas for study were the interfaces or zones
where different ecosystems meet and that
these ecosystems together make up a whole
which we call the biosphere (4). The final
development, which has become one of the
cornerstones of Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) Programme, has been
recognition of man's dominant role within the
biosphere (5), his responsibility for its evolution
and, consequently, the need to take into
account such intangibles as man's perception
of his environment and the quality of life.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
cover the concept of the ecosystem. But
these words were not very successful, partly
because they were often unwieldy and partly
because works on ecology and specialized
journals were written predominantly in
English. Eugene P. Odum's book. Fun¬
damentals of Ecology, in particular, publish¬
ed in 1953 and translated into several
languages, greatly contributed to the suc¬
cess of the term ecosystem.
The ecosystem concept, moreover, is in
line with Ludwig von Bertalanffy's General
Theory of Systems; the whole represents
more than the sum of its constituent parts,
since its main feature is the interaction tak¬
ing place between its various elements.
During the 1950s and the first half of the
1960s the application of this concept led to
studies on the efficiency of energy capture
and entry into the ecosystem through the
photosynthesis process, on the efficiency of
the transformation of matter as it passes
from one link in the chain to another, and on
the recycling and recovery of nutrients in the
"soil compartment". These studies helped
to elucidate the phenomena responsible for
the biological productivity of the ecosystem.
Analogies between the functioning of an
ecosystem and the metabolism of an
organism have enabled researchers to grasp
the relationships between different levels in
the organization of life.
However, the study of an ecosystem in its
totality called for a more sophisticated
research tool, which was to be supplied as a
result of progress in computer technology
and information processing that made it
possible to construct models of complex
systems. It also required more ample
resources than those hitherto available and
the large-scale organization of groups of
researchers from different disciplines.
These three conditions existed in several
industrialized countries and led to the im¬
plementation of the International Biological
Programme (1964-1974). This was the
period of Frank Blair's Big Biology and
ecological research carried out on a far
larger scale than ever before.
The achievements of the International
Biological Programme (IBP) were
undeniable. The methodologies developed
for the Programme have been adopted
almost universally. And specialists are
beginning to understand the functioning of
certain ecosystems, particularly the simpler
systems of the tundras, certain lakes and
deserts, coniferous and deciduous forests,
and steppes and temperate zone grasslands.
But research has come up against great dif¬
ficulties in studying systems as complex as
those of tropical rain forests, or as varied as,
for example, Mediterranean scrub. In any
event, the series of reports on the results of
the IBP that have appeared in several
languages will provide a basis for understan¬
ding the biology of ecosystems in the next
twenty or thirty years.
But the International Biological Pro¬
gramme, like all innovative undertakings,
had its weaknesses. In the first place, the
complexity of the research together with the
cost of operations prevented most of the
developing countries from taking part,
especially since no provision had been made
for a parallel training programme for
specialists. In addition, so much emphasis
was given to data collection that it has not
yet been possible to process a quite con¬
siderable mass of information, and it pro¬
bably never will be.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
A stylized version of the
ancient Egyptian sign for life
(the "ankh", held by the
Pharaoh Tuthmosis III in the
stone effigy, opposite page)
is incorporated into the
symbol of Unesco's
Programme on Man and the
Biosphere. The sacred bond
which in former times united
man to the earth, considered
as a divinity, appears
symbolically in certain
landscapes shaped by man
and in branches of traditional
knowledge such as the
Chinese feng-shui, which
held that human activity
should accord with the
interests of nature. Left, the
ancient Sassanian circular
city of Gur, near modern
Firuzabad or Fars, in Iran.
Dating from the 3rd century
AD, its plan is a reflection of
the spherical universe of
ancient cosmology. Below
left, a Mexican fishing village
built on a lagoon on the
Pacific coast. The compass,
below, enabled a Chinese
practitioner of feng-shui to
determine the appropriate
sites for tombs, temples or
dwellings, and the best way
to use land. Circles on the
face correspond to the points
of the compass, astrological
influences and features of
the landscape.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
So complex are the situation
and interactions with which
ecology is concerned that the
ideal ecologist, if he existed,
would be a kind of
superman, his brain stuffed
with expertise acquired in
the study of a whole range of
scientific and social
disciplines. Such a man, of
course, does not exist, and
this is why interdisciplinarity,
or team work between
groups of scientists each
representing a different
discipline, has become a
prerequisite of modern
ecological research. Left,
self-portrait by the Romanian
artist Paul Neagu.
Photo Tom Scott © Scottish Natrona! Gallery of Modern Art, Edinburgh
. Perhaps even more serious is the fact that
certain scientists allowed themselves to be
carried away by the sophistication of the
huge computers available to them: some of
the ecosystem models seem to have been
conceived as ends in themselves rather than
as research tools, and the prediction poten¬
tial of other models is too low. Several fun¬
damental questions have yet to be resolved:
to what extent can the results obtained in a
given site be extended to ecosystems of the
same type in other parts of the world? To
what extent can man's intervention in the
ecosystem work to his advantage and even
increase its productivity? And, when such
intervention occurs, what factors ensure the
ecosystem's stability?
Moreover, as the IBP drew to its close, it
became clear that study of the interactions
between ecosystems was just as important
as study of those taking place within a given
ecosystem. In fact, the most ecologically
critical areas are those where two zones
meet. The interfaces between different
ecosystems, such as, for example, the
coastal fringe where land meets sea along
the coast and, in tropical regions, the border
areas between forest and savannah. Similar¬
ly, economic land exploitation systems are
not based on a single ecosystem but on ex¬
changes of energy, materials and people
between different and complementary
ecosystems. Ecology has become increas¬
ingly complex, focusing on the study of in¬
terfaces (or zones of ecological and cultural
interpénétration) and of the various grada¬
tions of effects to which ecosystems are
subjected by man.
But the main problem for the International
Biological Programme was that it had taken
place between two major periods. Launched
at a time of peak economic growth, it ended
in 1974 in a very different period, marked by
three major trends. Following the en¬
vironmental crisis of the early 1970s there
was a new awareness of the limited
character of natural resources and of the
10
dangers threatening the entire planet; the
energy crisis with its economic and social
consequences was looming in many coun¬
tries; and in the developing world there was
a growing realization that the gap between it
and the industrialized world was widening.
In this atmosphere of crisis, politicians and
planners turned to the ecologists with
urgent questions, but the scientists were
unable to provide answers, for, until then,
the time factor had not been sufficiently
taken into consideration in ecological
research.
The developing countries had been made
more aware of these problems by the United
Nations Conference on the Human Environ¬
ment, held in Stockholm in June 1972, and
were entitled to expect realistic advice from
ecologists on the potential use they could
make of ecosystems, especially in tropical
regions and arid zones. But since the
economic and social aspects of these ques¬
tions had not been considered, ecologists
were in no position to provide this advice.
Moreover, in the industrialized countries,
protest movements had jumped on to the
ecology bandwagon and were pressuring
governments to reverse the industrial
policies of the consumer society, which they
considered alienating and dangerous, and to
replace them with a new "quality of life".
It is interesting to analyse how profes¬
sional ecologists reacted when ecology was
suddenly catapulted into the public arena as
a political platform and a means of pressure.
Some were alarmed by the confusion in the
use of terms resulting from ecology's new¬
found popularity and by the fact that
ecological concepts had suddenly become
commonplace. Certain countries, notably
France and Spain, even adopted a new ter¬
minology to distinguish between ecology
specialists (écologue, ecólogo) and political
pressure groups or protest movements
(écologistes, ecologistas). Some specialists
in fact joined these movements, taking up
the cause of social change with varying
degrees of realism or naivety, demagogy or
sincere political commitment.
There was nothing really disturbing in the
ferment of ideas and the mix of personalities
that resulted from all this activity. And, in
fact, the ecology movements sometimes
succeeded, directly or indirectly, in per¬
suading governments to take greater ac¬
count of the ecological dimension of
development. Indeed, to some extent, it has
highlighted the ecologist-scientist's sense of
social responsibility. And one can only
welcome the trend to regard ecology as "a
science for every man and for every day".
We come now to the most recent
developments in the history of ecology. It
is now recognized that , environmental
problems affect all countries of the world in
varying ways and degrees. It is also general¬
ly acknowledged that there are certain prob¬
lems of a global nature, such as the long
distance transport of pollutants, the pollu¬
tion of oceans, or changes in the at¬
mosphere's ozone layer and concentrations
of carbonic gas, which transcend political
frontiers. "Only one earth" was the slogan
of the Stockholm conference. And, as
everyone knows, the phenomenon of life is
only possible in the biosphere, a thin layer
(very thin on land, much deeper on the
oceans) that envelops this planet. The term
biosphere, which was coined in 1926 by the
Russian scientist V.l. Vernadsky, a pioneer
whose work is still amazingly modern in cer¬
tain of its aspects, indicates ecology's
ultimate goal. In the biosphere, man plays a
dominant role and consequently his respon¬
sibility for its evolution should be the most
urgent of our priorities.
It was in this historical and conceptual
framework that Unesco's "Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) Programme" was launch¬
ed in November 1971, following a recom¬
mendation made at the Biosphere Con¬
ference held at Unesco in 1968. MAB
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
benefited at the outset from the
methodology worked out during the I nterna-
tional Biological Programme and learned
from both its successes and its weaknesses.
The programme soon directed its ac¬
tivities towards action in the field, adopting
very simple principles and procedures. The
first task was to solve concrete and specific
land use planning problems which, in the
view of both local planners and scientists,
deserved to be given top priority. To solve
these very complex problems, inter¬
disciplinary research teams had to be
created. Research activities were linked to
training, to field demonstrations and en¬
vironmental education. And, because of the
inevitable budgetary constraints that exist in
all countries, full use was made of interna¬
tional machinery to co-ordinate national ef¬
forts and thus multiply the human and finan¬
cial resources available. Finally, MAB ap¬
plied the experimental method of "learning
by doing", drawing experience from the
successes and failures of field work, and
adopted a flexible approach in response to
the changing needs and emerging priorities
of the various countries.
It is thanks to this adaptability and this ex¬
perience acquired in the field that MAB has
been able to develop its activities so rapidly
during its ten years of existence. The pro¬
gramme's point of departure was the study
of man from the "outside", i.e. the impact
of human activity on the various ecosystems
(tropical and temperate forests, savannahs,
prairies, tundras, lakes and rivers, moun¬
tains and islands). Subsequently, in a grow¬
ing number of research projects, man came
to be considered as an integral part of the
ecosystem and of the biosphere, becoming
in fact the central element of study.
This changeover from "man the outsider"
to "man the insider" is not merely a play on
words. It marks a real revolution in concepts
and particularly in methods, for ecology has
begun to take into consideration the intangi¬
ble and non-quantifiable elements of human
activity and thought the different percep¬
tions which populations and individuals
have of development and of the quality of
life, their aspirations and their feelings of
belonging and of accomplishment.
The methodological difficulties raised by
this new approach are far from being solved.
Clearly, many ecologists find it hard to work
with data that cannot be quantified and
therefore cannot be treated on the same
basis as other data. Nevertheless, "par¬
ticipation" has become the key concept in
the new generation of MAB activities par¬
ticipation of the local population at the
outset when research priorities are planned,
participation of the various disciplines of the
natural and human sciences, and participa¬
tion of decision-makers and planners.
This issue of the Unesco Courier presents
specific examples of MAB projects in four
major priority areas. They illustrate how the
very fragile ecosystems of the humid tropics
can be used without being destroyed; how
the ecological constraints of certain
marginal regions (aridity, cold and altitude)
can be turned to account in developing
these zones; how parts of the biosphere's
representative ecosystems can be preserv¬
ed, not by excluding man from these areas,
but by using him, in fact, as the main con¬
servation agent; and, finally, how life can be
organized in the urban areas, where the
greater part of mankind will be concentrated
in the year 2000, by applying a global
ecological approach which respects man's
dignity and position in the system.
We have now covered the various phases
through which ecology has passed, from its
beginnings to the present day: descriptive
natural history; study of the environment of
a single species; study of ecosystems; study
of the interactions between ecosystems;
study of the biosphere; and study of man in
the biosphere. The last phase, "man in the
biosphere", is the most "natural" since it
completes the evolutionary cycle, reproduc¬
ing in terms of science what has been man's
situation from the very beginning, i.e. an in¬
tegral part of the biosphere, evolving along
with all its other components.
What does the future hold in store for
ecology? There is every reason for con¬
fidence provided ecology can rid itself of
certain weaknesses: it must abandon its
jargon without giving way to generalities
and over-simplification or departing from
scientific rigour; it must prefer action to
preaching and learn through action; above
all, it must cease to be a negative science
(no to pollution, no to deforestation, no to
industrial development, no to intensive
agriculture) and become a science which
provides realistic and specific alternative
solutions to the problems of development.
Its strength lies in its capacity to grapple
with the real problems of our time, to main¬
tain the flexibility and adaptability that will
enable it to face unforseeable situations in
the future, to build on participation as an
operational basis for helping people to live
more harmoniously with one another and
with nature. At a time when science in
general can claim to be increasingly univer¬
sal, ecology can affirm its originality by tak¬
ing as its lodestar the specificity of individual
ecosystems and the cultural identity of dif¬
ferent peoples.
Is ecology a natural science or a human
science? The answer is that it is both, but
not a natural science that excludes man, nor
a human science isolated from nature. It is a
science, but one that can only fulfil its role if
those who are engaged in it are deeply
aware of their responsibility in the evolution
of the human condition.
H Francesco di Castri
"...ecology can
affirm its originality
by taking as its
lodestar the
specificity of
individual
ecosystems and the
cultural identity of
different peoples".
Left, a Bolivian
village in the Andes.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
*.v
A<*
*4r t
4V *
'*
*"*^F j
as^
>**
«»
JÉlfira»^.' '
V* *
*-">
&s
* * «
_* Hfl «y-
S *?£
">
*¿
üäc ">
;4^
:*o
,.««
i .."* 3tf#
v-
:a.^
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The tropical forest,
a rich but
fragile resource
by Frank Golley
and Malcolm Hadley
ALMOST half of the earth's population
lives in the tropical forest environ¬
ment which covers an estimated
2,000 million hectares, mostly in the
developing world. The management of
these forests is a matter of overriding impor¬
tance for the countries in which they are
situated, for not only do they provide timber
for lumber and paper, but their unique diver¬
sity of plant life, if wisely harvested, is a
renewable source of food, medicines and
fuel. Forests also help to regulate the quality
and flow of water, an essential factor in
development. They are the home of farmers,
hunters and gatherers, and yield many pro¬
ducts which are both used by these people
and sought by city-dwellers.
But forests are also of concern to the
world community as a whole. They affect
the climate by helping to maintain the
earth's temperature and to control the
amount of carbon dioxide in the at¬
mosphere. The rare trees and plants of
which they consist are a gene pool whose
value has only begun to be tapped in the
search for drugs to cure some of mankind's
worst diseases, including cancer. And so
everyone in the world has an interest in mak¬
ing possible the sustained rational use of
these forests and woodlands in the humid
and sub-humid parts of the tropics.
In the past, the richness of plant and
animal species contained in humid tropical
ecosystems often led scientists and develop¬
ment planners to incorrect conclusions
about the possibilities for development pro¬
grammes in these zones. Impressed by the
mass of vegetation and variety of organisms
of the tropical rain forest, far surpassing
anything known in forests of the temperate
zones, they concluded that the tropics must
be very productive.
In some parts of the tropics this is true, in
others not. In effect, there are two main
sorts of tropical forests; though they may
look alike to the outsider or non-specialist,
they have very different possibilities for
agricultural development. One sort can
usually be successfully converted to inten¬
sive agricultural crops and tree plantations
like rubber and oil palm; these tend to be-
forests growing on nutrient-rich, generally
younger soils developed from alluvial
sediments or volcanic ash.
However, forests growing on nutrient-
poor, generally older soils, do not have the
same potential. Most of the nutrients in
these forests are tied-up in the tree biomass,
and not in the soil. When the forest is
cleared, for large-scale agriculture, most of
the nutrients in the system are lost, and
yields quickly decline. Hence, the key to the
possibilities for development lies in the in¬
herent characteristics of the tropical forests
themselves.
The complexity and structural variability
of the tropical rain forest are legendary; the
German plant geographer Friedrich Hum¬
boldt described it over a century ago as
"forest piled on forest". Within its depths is
to be found a variety of plants, animals and
micro-organisms, all ecologically dependent
on one another. No other kind of communi¬
ty has so many kinds of plants and animals.
A single volcano in the Philippines, for ex¬
ample, has a greater variety of woody plant
species growing on its slopes than are found
in the entire United States. A two hectare
sample of lowland rain forest may contain
more than 200 tree species; perhaps ten to
twenty tree species would be found in a
comparable area in a temperate forest
region.
But although well adapted to persist in the
relatively predictable environment in which
they have evolved, tropical rain forests are
less resistant to the disturbances wrought
by man than are relatively simple and
apparently more robust temperate
ecosystems. This fragility led the Mexican
biologist Arturo Gomez-Pompa to label the
tropical rainforest a "non-renewable
resource". Another comment, often heard
in scientific and development circles, is that
the tropical forest is an overexploited but
under-used resource.
Recognition of these special features of
tropical forests and the need to guide
development has led research workers to
seek a better scientific basis on which
management can be based. An example
within Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) Programme is a project at San Carlos
de Rio Negro in the Amazon region of
Venezuela.
It has long been known that the upland
soils of the Amazon Basin have a low
nutrient content, and, therefore, are not
suited to continuous intensive agriculture.
What has been less clear is how relatively
large forests with a biomass of about
400 tons per hectare can maintain
themselves more or less indefinitely in the
Amazon Basin, despite the low fertility of
the soil. The Venezuelan Government is in¬
terested in the capacity of these soils to sus¬
tain productive forests.
The MAB scientists from Venezuela, the
United States and the Federal Republic of
Germany, working at San Carlos, have
shown that the key to the question of forest
productivity is a sophisticated series of
nutrient conserving mechanisms of the
natural forest.
The forest acts as a sort of massive
sponge, absorbing nutrients as they enter
the system in the rainfall or from the at¬
mosphere. The well-developed mat of roots,
fungi, micro-organisms and humus which
occurs on the top of the soil surface appears
to be of special significance in the retention
and recycling of nutrients within the system.
In some places, particularly on mineral soils,
this mat can be up to 30 cm thick, and can
be peeled back from the soil like a carpet.
When leaves or pieces of wood fall and
begin to break down, and when rain falls,
most of the nutrients that are released or
present are not leached away to the under¬
lying soil, but are taken up by root mat and
recycled to the living trees.
The efficiency of this root mat in conserv¬
ing nutrients has been demonstrated at San
Carlos through experiments using radio¬
isotopes. Known amounts of radioactively-
marked calcium and phosphorus were add¬
ed to the root mats, and the water which
drained through the mats was collected and
analysed for radioactivity. Hardly any
radioactivity was recorded, even after
6 months following the application of
radioactive materials. Over 99 per cent of
the tagged nutrients were absorbed by the
root mat, indicating that practically all the
dissolved nutrients from decomposing
organic material or from rainfall move direct¬
ly into roots without passing into the mineral
soil. The root mat of an undisturbed forest
therefore prevents the loss of nutrients from
the system.
The critical point about nutrient conserv¬
ing mechanisms like these is that they are
part of the living organic structure of the un¬
disturbed forest, which is destroyed when
the forests are cleared, for agriculture. This
explains why the productivity of these
systems quickly falls away when the forest is
removed.
But the problems of development and
conservation of the ecosystems of the
humid tropics calls for scientific research not
just on plants, animals, micro-organisms
and soil. Man is also a part of the forest
system, an overwhelming part in many
regions, both as an agent of change and as f
an entity affected by change.
FRANK GOLLEY, of the USA, is professor at the
Institute of Ecology, University of Georgia,
Athens, Georgia. He is at present on secondment
to the United States National Science Foundation
as director of the Division of Environmental
Biology.
MALCOLM HADLEY is a staff member of
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences. A
zoologist, he is responsible for the co-ordination
of activities in the humid tropics within Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
***
4É=^:
*Jêê*
Traditionally, many peoples of the humid
tropics practice "swidden" or "shift and
burn" cultivation. A small area of forest is
cut and burned and the land thus cleared is
cultivated for one or two crop cycles. The
area is then left fallow for ten or more
years to allow the vegetation to build up its
stock of nutrients ready for another short
burst of cultivation. Provided the fallow
period is long enough, shifting cultivation
is a perfectly sound system of land use in
poor soil areas which cannot support more
intensive use. Above, an area of forest in
East Kalimantan, Indonesia, being cleared
by burning. Left, two young Indonesians
carry cassava, a crop often grown on
swidden clearings.
JUNGLE CYCLE
A tropical forest ecosystem is the habitat of a multitude of animals including
thousands of insect species. Many of them form communities that are mainly
restricted to a particular layer of the forest, some to the jungle floor, for
example, and others to the tree-tops. Some of these creatures are reservoirs or
vectors of diseases that can be passed on to man. Thus, in the tropical forests
of central and South America, monkeys and marmosets inhabiting principally
the tree-top layer of the forest form a reservoir of yellow fever. The virus is
spread between them by blood-sucking mosquitoes such as the Haemagogus
species. Tree-felling exposes man to the bites of these virus-carrying
mosquitoes and infected forest workers then carry the virus to villages and
towns where it is further disseminated by other mosquitoes such as the Aedes
aegypti species.
Drawing from J. 1. Cooper and T.W. Tmsley, Transactions of the International MAB IUFRO Workshop on Tropical
Rainforest Ecosystems Research, 1977, Hamburg-Reinbek
This process of change is taking place in
regions which have a long and rich history of
human activity, as witness the ancient forest
cultures of the Mayas, the people of Angkor
Wat and the Benin of Nigeria.
In several parts of South-East Asia, South
and Central America and West and Central
Africa, forests were long ago successfully
transformed into rice paddies and other
types of productive agricultural land. The
transformation has been particularly suc¬
cessful in areas with nutrient-rich soils
which for centuries have supported dense
human populations, in such areas as Java
and the Mekong Delta.
However, the intensity of human activity
currently taking place and the consequent
ecological impacts are unique in history. -
Forests are being cleared or altered at an un¬
precedented rate. Although scientists are
not certain how fast tropical forest lands are
being cleared or severely altered, estimates
range from one to two per cent of the ex¬
isting area per year. Unless the present trend
is halted, all the primary lowland tropical rain
forest in the world may disappear well
before the end of the century (except in in¬
accessible sites and a few small biological
reserves).
The major causes of tropical forest dep¬
letion are rapid population growth in tropical
countries and the need for agricultural land
to produce food for these multitudes;
resource development to achieve economic
growth; the accelerated search for new
wood supplies by developed temperate
region countries; and the overcutting of
forests as a source of fuelwood for heating
and cooking.
Commercial logging and transmigration
are having a major impact on the tropical
rain forests of Asia. A MAB research team
co-ordinated by the Indonesian Institute of
Sciences (LIPI), has been looking at the in¬
teractions between these human activities
and tropical forest ecosystems in the In¬
donesian province of East Kalimantan. East
Kalimantan is a large, economically booming
province on the island of Borneo. It covers a
territory of 21 million hectares, an area
about twice the size of Iceland, with a
population of only 1 million people. About
17 million hectares, over three-quarters of
the province, are forested. The area
represents an immense reserve of timber,
much of it valuable hardwoods, as well as a
place for resettling people from the densely
populated islands of Indonesia such as Java
and Bali.
Quite naturally, the central government
has considered East Kalimantan to be a
prime economic asset, which should and
must contribute to the national development
goals. Today, there are more than
100 licensed logging companies busily at
work extracting timber from the 13 million
hectares earmarked for selective logging.
Selective in this case means the cutting of
up to 20 trees per hectare, according to
botanist Dr. Kuswata Kartawinata, leader of
the MAB research effort in East Kalimantan
and Head of the Bogor Herbarium of In¬
donesia's National Biological Institute.
Unfortunately, during the removal of
selected logs, 41 per cent of the remaining
trees have been shown to be damaged. Fur¬
thermore, current selective logging practice
results in the creaming off of the best trees
of the commercial species, leaving only
undesirable, smaller trees in the residual |
stands to provide seeds for the next crop I
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The taming of a swamp
The 'Chinampa' project Mexico
The Problem: to find inexpensive ways of
increasing food output using systems of pro¬
duction that take advantage of the special
characteristics of the tropical forest environ¬
ment, that can be sustained indefinitely
without the need for large scale additional
resources (such as fertilizers) from outside.
The Project: links scientific understanding
of an age-old, traditional agricultural system
with the need for increased food production in
humid tropical zones of Mexico. The chinam¬
pa is a low-capital, self-sufficient agricultural
system which was used by pre-Columbian
peoples throughout tropical America and is
still practised in Mexico Valley.
The system consists of creating small plots
of land on which crops can be grown from
plant materials and mud dredged up from the
bottom of swamps and lakes, the plots being
separated from each other by water channels
in which fish can be raised. The word chinam¬
pa means "net of branches" and it was pro¬
bably on mats of branches and leaves that the
early cultivators first built their chinampa
fields.
A diversity of crops can be grown on these
small "artificial" plots and production is
unusually high and predictable. By its very
nature, the chinampa is a labour-intensive
method of agriculture since the farmer must
constantly maintain the height of the plots and
keep the water channels open. But this can be
a positive advantage in many tropical coun¬
tries where the supply of labour outstrips the
demand.
A group of Mexican MAB scientists
recognized the special nature and the success
of the chinampa method and decided to ex¬
periment with it in order to create a new
method of meeting food needs. The research
team was made up of some fourteen scientists
including specialists in agronomy, biology,
anthropology, sociology, economics and
pisciculture, based at the Institute for the
Study of Biological Resources (INIREB) at
Jalapa.
They selected four rain forest areas in Mex¬
ico. One of these areas, in Tabasco State,
consisted of a combination of semi-evergreen
rain forest and swamps where the human
population could benefit from increased food
production. Another, very different, site was
chosen in tropical rain forest at Chiapas where
shifting cultivation is widely used. Here
chinampas were built near a river which pro¬
vided the irrigation water. The organic mulch
for the chinampa plots was obtained from the
litter (the fallen, decomposed débris of leaves
and branches) of the adjacent rain forest.
The Results: within a few months after
chinampa construction, a variety of crops
were growing, including beans, corn, spinach
and other vegetables. A crop of over 54 tons
per hectare of celery was achieved within a
period of 150 days.
In 1976, the scientists handed over the ex¬
perimental site to local farmers who not only
continued to cultivate it along chinampa lines
but have since enlarged it using their own
resources.
Here then, a team of natural and social
scientists working with the local populations,
have studied and interpreted a traditional,
local technology and then successfully
translated it into modern terms and transfer¬
red it to a new location. This is a case of
transfer of technology within the same
ecological region and not, like many examples
where transfer has failed, from temperate to
tropical regions. The MAB project has thus
demonstrated that in the Mexican chinampa
there exists an ancient and ecologically sound
system of agriculture that could be applied
elsewhere in tropical lands, particularly in
areas where water is plentiful.
Drawing Etudes et Planification des Communications. Unesco Courier Photo MAB Unesco
Drawing, above, shows how the chinampa system works. Small
raised plots of land are constructed (1) and separated by a
network of water channels (2), which are used for transportation
as well as providing a ready source of fish (3) and of water for
irrigation (4). Trees and stakes (5) hold the sides of the
chinampas firmly in place. The soil of the plot is constantly
replenished with organic débris (plant and animal), aquatic plants
and mud (6). The chinamperos scoop up fresh mud from the
bottom of the channels and load it into their boats (7). They
spread the mud on the chinampa plot before planting a new
crop, thus helping to maintain its fertility. A wide variety of
crops is grown including maize (8). beans (9), and green
vegetables (10). The seed nursery (11) is an essential element of
chinampa farming; seeds are sown in small mud cubes, called
chapines, which are transplanted once the seedlings are
established. The adjacent tropical forest (12) is a source of many
other products used by the chinamperos. Above right, a typical
chinampa plot in Mexico.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Nature's chemical factory
There are over one hundred different
chemical elements in the world, arranged in
an infinite number of combinations. If you
were to write a formula for a tree, you would
find you had so many carbons per gramme, so
many calciums, so many zincs, so many
leads, and so on.
Now that chemical formula has developed
through a long process, starting with the
chemical environment in which the tree first
evolved. If the tree originated in a very
calcium-rich environment, it would have lots
of calcium in its original formula.
But in the course of its long evolution the
tree has moved about over the surface of the
earth. In its travels it has encountered whole
new environments and lots of other species,
so its chemistry is constantly evolving. The
chemical formula of a tree is, as it were, the
signature of the species to which it belongs. If
you go into a forest and study the chemistry of
each species you will find that they differ from
one another in fascinating ways.
Scientists working on the MAB project in
San Carlos, Venezuela, have been testing the
effect of location on the chemistry of trees.
They have compared trees which are of dif¬
ferent species but whose roots have the same
soil area with individuals of the same species
whose roots share different soil areas. And
they found that for the essential elements in¬
dividual trees of the same species have the
same chemistrythe signatures are the
same.
Tropical forests have long been known as a
rich source of natural products. Some trees,
like sandalwood, have an aromatic nature and
their oils have been collected for thousands of
years. Some have a beautiful patina when
they are cut, like teak and mahogany. Some
produce materials that have medical value,
like quinine. Other products of tropical forest
trees, like rubber, palm-oil and cocoa have
long played an important role in the world
economy.
But a tree that produces rubber might have
very many other interesting chemical
characteristics that have never been explored.
Literally thousands of chemicals are produced
in trees, in some cases in large quantities. In¬
deed, trees are like factories in that they pro¬
vide major products, sub-products and waste
products. If we adopt this industrial analogy
we begin to get a glimpse of the tremendous
benefits that could result from better
understanding of forest chemistry.
The tropical forest represents a virtually un¬
tapped reservoir of new chemical compounds.
Many show potential as medicines; a tropical
periwinkle plant, for example, is providing a
chemical used to fight leukaemia. One
Brazilian tree holds promise as a source of oil
that can be used directly to power
automobiles.
But the search for new chemical products
has only just begun. Less that a tenth of the
estimated 150,000 species of tropical flower¬
ing trees has been screened for even a single
class of chemical compounds. It can
reasonably be expected that the remaining
plants will ultimately provide numerous new
compounds that will prove useful in medicine
and as sources of industrial products such as
gums, latex, resins, dyes, waxes, oils and
sweeteners, as well as new sources of
energy.
The opportunity is there for imaginative
research. But it is a fleeting opportunity, for,
with our overriding concern to achieve im¬
mediate, short-term benefits and our concen¬
tration on the creation of simplified agri¬
cultural systems, we are condemning many
as yet unexamined species to extinction.
i and this may result in an inferior forest for
future use.
Transmigration of people from densely
populated parts of Indonesia is another ma¬
jor agent of change in East Kalimantan. Ac¬
customed to intensive farming on rich
volcanic soils in Java or Bali which can pro¬
duce two or three crops of rice each year,
the newcomers often found themselves
allocated plots of land too infertile and too
small to provide an adequate livelihood.
Many of these people supplement their liv¬
ing by harvesting the resources of the
forests, particularly the valuable Borneo
ironwood tree. Thus, the transplanted peo¬
ple not only have an impact on the areas of
former forest cleared for agriculture but also
the intact forest reserved for other uses.
Taking part in the MAB project in East
Kalimantan are a group of American human
ecologists. With their Indonesian col¬
leagues, they are looking at questions rele¬
vant to policy-making of the interactions
between people and forests in the province.
Their initial results show that the people of
East Kalimantan are highly responsive to
changing economic opportunity. This is
demonstrated by some of the activities and
processes looked at by the MAB team. For
example, the spontaneous migration of
thousands of Bugis farmers from the island
of Sulawesi in order to convert East
Kalimantan forest land into plantations of
pepper, a crop the people had not grown in
their homeland; the movement of Dayaks
from the interior plateau of Borneo to
lowland areas where they have eagerly taken
to using chain-saws and perahu (canoes)
with outboard motors in their activities as
16
shifting cultivators; the greatly increased
allocation of time and effort to the collection
of incense wood by Dayaks when the price
traders were paying for that commodity
rose.
These examples illustrate the capacity of
local peoples and governments to respond
to a rapidly changing modern world.
However, their ability to change systems of
forestry, agriculture and governmental ser¬
vices to conserve their natural resource
base, their special natural heritage, and pro¬
vide for their needs over an indefinite future
depends upon knowledge applied in
culturally sound ways.
In this modern age of rapid communica¬
tions, the topic of forest transformation has
aroused interest in many parts of the
world not just in the tropical countries
themselves. Different perspectives and
perceptions have emerged, and it must be
recognized that a number of tropical coun¬
tries have felt uncomfortable about the at¬
tention that has been given to tropical
forests by individuals and groups in non¬
tropical countries.
For example, there has been much con¬
troversy over the last ten years or so about
the possible consequences of large scale
vegetation clearance in the Amazonian
Basin. Some scientists and government of¬
ficials, mainly from non-tropical countries,
have argued that the destruction of these
forests could bring, among other conse¬
quences, changes in the composition of the
atmosphere, changes in patterns of rains
within and outside the Basin and disap¬
pearance of animal and plant species whose
potential usefulness for man are unknown.
On the other hand, tropical countries,
such as Brazil, have defended the right to
exploit and utilize for their own benefit the
potential of these regions in the same way
as developed countries.
In middle latitude European countries,
such wholesale transformation of tem¬
perate forests occurred many centuries ago,
and no-one recognized serious deterioration
of the environment. Tropical countries ques¬
tion why a different set of criteria and con¬
siderations should be applied now to them in
the era of change of their national
ecosystems.
Whatever one's views on this question, it
seems clear that interest in, and concern for,
resource development in the humid tropics
will continue to increase in the present
decade. From the scientific and technical
viewpoint, it can be said that transformation
and development of the tropical forests can
be economically successful and ecologically
sound if done in the right place and in the
right way. But great damage will be done,
and is being done, when transformation
takes place in the wrong places or in the
wrong ways. The object of research is to
guide development into sound pathways.
MAB research is aimed at providing new
information about man and natural forests,
derived from field research guided by local
people and their decision-makers, in a form
that can be understood and quickly put to
work. In this endeavour, scientists from all
countries can co-operate. The success of
MAB projects in several tropical forest areas
makes one optimistic that the approach is
viable and that change can be positive.
I Frank Golley and Malcolm Hadley
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The changing forest
The Tai project Ivory Coast
The Problem: to provide a better scientific
basis for managing tropical forests, linking
measures for conservation with the needs of
economic development.
Trie Project: is focussed on the south-west
Ivory Coast, an area of tropical forest which
until recently was largely uninhabited. The
late 1960s and 1970s heralded an enormous
growth in the population of the region. In
1965, the Ivory Coast Government decided to
bring the forest area into the national
economy. Wide-ranging development projects
were started, including the construction of
San Pedro port and town, a hydro-electric
scheme and paper-pulp mill, together with a
railway and various agro-industrial com¬
plexes, such as oil and coco-palm plantations.
The south-west Ivory Coast is therefore an
area of rapid change. It represents a sort of
microcosm of changes, opportunities and pro¬
blems that are occurring in many parts of the
humid and sub-humid tropics. It is also an
area where scientific research can precede or
accompany and thus help to shape the form of
economic development. This opportunity,
seldom encountered, led to the setting up of
the MAB Tai Forest project in 1973, by the
Ivory Coast Ministry of Scientific Research.
The project takes its name from the Tai
Forest, the largest (300,000 hectares) intact
area of tropical rain forest in West Africa.
The MAB project is built around eight
research programmes, co-ordinated by the
University Institute of Tropical Ecology in
Abidjan and involving scientists from a
number of disciplines and countries. Par¬
ticipating institutions include the National In
stitutes of Ethnosociology and of Meteorology
in the Ivory Coast, the Office of Overseas
Scientific and Technical Research of France,
the Mycology Laboratory of the University of
Rome. A substantial facility for field research
and training has been set up at Tai.
The Results: in contrast to most temperate
regions, basic data on the local environment
is lacking in many parts of the tropics. The
first task therefore was to carry out surveys of
soils, vegetation, insects, large vertebrates,
human populations, etc. A team of an¬
thropologists and geographers undertook a
study of the impact of a pioneer front of im¬
migrant farmers on the local people. The im¬
migrants came from the north in the 1960s
and 1970s, to take advantage of new
economic opportunities presented by the
opening-up of forest areas in the south-west
Ivory Coast. At first, the indigenous people
adopted a favourable attitude towards the im¬
migrants, and gave them free access to their
lands.
The newcomers arrived in ever increasing
numbers and, showing considerable initiative
with their cash crops (coffee, cocoa), and in¬
tensive land use practices, began to dominate
the local economy, previously based on shift-
and-burn cultivation.
Research by the MAB team documented the
factors which enabled the pioneer front to
establish itself and highlighted the conflicts
between a new land use strategy and a tradi¬
tional one. At the end of the study, recom¬
mendations were made to the government
concerning the possible consequences of,
and reactions to, the expansion or establish¬
ment of new fronts of pioneer farmers.
Below, a water and soil erosion monitoring station in the Tai forest. Installations such as
this enable scientists to measure-the water draining away and the soil carried with it from
sections of forest that have been cleared and cultivated by man as compared with the
natural water run-off and soil erosion from intact forest areas.
Botanists at Tai have been looking at the
role of a different kind of pioneera group of
sun-loving shrubs and small trees with a
short life span, which appear in the forest
following more or less extensive disturbance.
The primary forest trees are relatively slow
growing. Their seeds are not plentiful and
they require shade and moisture for germina¬
tion. Thus, these trees are not able to re¬
establish themselves on land that has been
abandoned following clearance and cultiva¬
tion. The so-called pioneer species of shrubs
and small trees, however, have a
characteristic, rapidly growing root system.
Full root potential is quickly achieved through
rapid occupation of the upper soil layers.
One reason for the success of the pioneer
plants seems to be their habit of feeding off
each other. After about 3 years, root grafts
appear between individual plants. Using
radio-active substances the Tai botanists have
shown that some individual trees "feed off"
and drain the root system of their neighbours,
and eventually take over the living part of the
root system after the death of the neighbours.
The importance of these pioneer species is
that they create the moist, shady conditions
which enable the primary forest trees to
regenerate themselves. They are therefore an
essential element in the reconstitution of the
original forest after a period of clearance and
cultivation.
The first results obtained by the soil scien¬
tists working on the Tai project show that
forest clearance followed by burning results in
a considerable reduction in the overall activity
of the soil. However, the soil rapidly regains
its former levels of organic matter content,
and other principal characteristics.
The significance of these results is that it
should be possible to shorten present fallow
periods, once the difficulties involved in clear¬
ing dense vegetation, and in countering cer¬
tain animal pests and parasites have been
surmounted.
The Tai soil scientists also studied changes
in the rate of erosion under different land
uses. Rather surprisingly, low rates of erosion
were recorded under traditional shift-and-
burn agriculture; these rates were com¬
parable to those recorded within the intact
forest. However, it was thought likely that
when larger areas were cleared for cultiva¬
tion, erosion rates would rise considerably.
A somewhat startling aspect of the MAB
project is what might be described as a
"gaseous" study. One hardly expects to find
a forest generating gases usually thought of
as pollutants gases like sulphur dioxide and
other sulphur derivatives. But levels of air¬
borne sulphur have been recorded in Ivory
Coast forests that are higher than in
agricultural areas of France and are com¬
parable with those experienced in large in¬
dustrial towns. The clue to their origin lies in
the decomposition of organic material in the
forest ecosystems under conditions of low
oxygen content.
Yet it should be borne in mind that such
"noxious" gases contribute to the overall
composition of the earth' s atmosphere and for
mankind it is vital to know the extent to which
changes in tropical forests are affecting the
delicate balance of that atmosphere. The Tai
Forest project shows how an in-depth study of
a tropical forest such as that undertaken by
the MAB scientists can reveal data of impor¬
tance to the sum total of world studies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Marginal lands
Inhospitable 'fringe' regions
ingeniously turned to human advantage
by Mohamed Ayyad
and Gisbert Glaser
ALTHOUGH we refer to the whole
planet as our habitat, the land sur¬
face on which we live constitutes
only about a quarter of the total surface of
the globe, and of this less than a quarter is
well populated and intensively used. A large
part of the remainder is made up of desert,
ice cap and mountain peaks.
Between these two extremes lie the
marginal lands, areas subject to certain
natural constraints which limit the possibility
of intensive cultivation with high crop yields
and which, if they attain a certain threshold,
make cultivation impossible.
These constraints fall into three main
categories: irregular rainfall and lack of
water (the arid and semi-arid zones); ex¬
tremes of cold (high elevations in mountain
areas and the sub-polar tundra regions in
both the northern and southern
hemispheres); and steepness of slope
(mountain areas everywhere).
Surprisingly enough, despite the great dif¬
ficulties involved, close on eight hundred
million people (though this is a very approx¬
imate estimate) inhabit these marginal lands,
showing great ingenuity in adapting to the
constraints they impose and even, in some
cases, turning them to their advantage.
Before the development of modern
transportation, for example, the true
deserts, such as the Sahara and the high
summits of the mountain chains, con¬
stituted barriers between areas of intensive
human activity which could be likened to the
barrier of the seas. The people living at the
boundaries of the deserts and below the
passes crossing the high mountains were
quick to take advantage of this situation. To
supplement the meagre living they obtained
from the land they assumed the function of
the seafarer, transporting goods and people
across the desert and mountain passes.
Nowadays the camel caravans have
almost disappeared from the Sahara and
other deserts and the high mountain farmers
no longer keep horses and mules for
transport purposes.
But the resourcefulness of the inhabitants
of these regions remains. The major con¬
straints of the Alps snow, ice, cold and
steep slopes have been used to form the
basis of a highly profitable industry, winter
tourism, and the high number of sunny,
rainless days that make agricultural activity
so difficult in North Africa now attract tens
of thousands of sun-loving tourists every
year.
18
Ingenuity on the part of the farmers of the
Nochixtlan Valley in southern Mexico in
overcoming a rather different kind of con¬
straint has been revealed in a recent Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) publication. The
side slopes of the Valley are ravaged by ac¬
tive gully erosion, a process which strips off
the surface soil leaving the slopes barren
and bare of vegetation. What a terrible con¬
straint for agriculture I
Yet the farmers of the Valley took advan¬
tage of this erosion and made a resource out
of it. Over the past thousand years, by direc¬
ting the flow of eroded material from the
side slopes, these Mixtee cultivators have
doubled the cultivatable area of the main
valley floors and have filled in the narrow
tributary valley floors with flights of terraces
several kilometres long. Before large-scale
erosion began the agricultural productivity
of the valley area was certainly much lower
than it is today.
The high culture of the Incas in the Andes
is an outstanding example, on a much larger
scale, of adaptation to natural constraints.
One might have expected the Incas to con¬
centrate in the coastal and lowland areas,
but their preferred environment was the
healthier high mountain, the altiplanos, at
altitudes ranging from 2,800 to
4,000 metres, and the large valley systems
of the central and northern Andes.
Here they created an area of relatively
dense population and evolved one of the
most remarkable pre-Columbian cultures in
the New World. They coped in masterly
fashion with the constraints of cold on the
altiplanos and the steepness of the slopes of
the valleys. On the slopes they developed a
very efficient terracing system; on the
altiplanos they combined llama and alpaca
herding with limited agriculture specifically
adapted to the cold and the reduced oxygen
available. The fact that the potato, which
was to become a staple food over much of
northern Europe in later centuries,
originated from the "marginal lands" of the
Incas provides some measure of the success
of their system.
Although essentially based on the
altiplanos, the Incas nevertheless made use
of the opportunities offered by variations in
altitude, including in their landholdings
some areas with a hot and humid tropical
climate in the low-lying foothills of the
eastern escarpments of the Andes as well as
areas of temperate climate at altitudes of
1,500 to 2,500 metres. Thus their economy
provided for tropical fruit and bananas, cot
ton and maize from the more temperate
altitude levels as well as grain, potatoes and
animal products from the colder high
altitude levels.
A comparatively simple example of a quite
different strategy adopted in other marginal
lands is the transhumance system in France
whereby the sheep and goats graze in the
Alps during the summer and in the Mediter¬
ranean maquis or the Camargues during the
winter. In this way the problem is solved of
how to cope with two constraints, namely
to feed the herds when the Alps are covered
with snow and when Mediterranean France
experiences its summer drought.
On a very much larger scale, trans¬
humance in the arid and semi-arid zones of
Africa takes advantage not of opposing con¬
straints (such as extremes of cold and
drought in the example from France above).
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
but of variations in the rigour of the same
constraint aridity.
In the past, the traditional nomads roam¬
ed with their herds and their families over
hundreds of kilometres in order to make
available to their cattle the fresh grasses and
shrubs that sprang up after the rare days of
rainfall even in the most arid and remote
areas. Today the tendency is more and more
for the herdsmen's families to adopt the
sedentary way of life, settling in villages,
while the herdsmen themselves move their
flocks between three complementary graz¬
ing zones south of the Sahara.
These zones consist of the so-called
Sudanese zone, which has about six or
seven dry months, the Sahelian or semi-arid
zone, with eight or- nine dry months, and
finally the fringes of the Sahara, with ten to
eleven dry months. A system is developing
whereby the Sudanese zone, which has a
strong agricultural element, is beginning
also to specialize in the rearing of young
livestock and the final fattening up of cattle
before they are taken to slaughterhouses for
sale in the major markets in the coastal
zones. The Sahelian zone, where the
nomads are beginning to settle, is devoted
to the reproduction phase, and the fringes
of the desert are only grazed for a few
months after the rare rainy spells in this
area to relieve grazing pressure on the
Sahelian zone.
Mankind has, then, often been very suc¬
cessful in overcoming the varied disadvan¬
tages and constraints that affect marginal
lands, particularly in making use of them for
grazing. Few people realize, for example,
that the arid and semi-arid zones as a whole
support over half the world's stock of cattle.
MOHAMED AYYAD, of Egypt, is professor of
biology at the University of Alexandria. He heads
the MAB project on Regional Environmental
Management of Desert Ecosystems in Northern
Egypt (REMDENE).
GISBERT GLASER is a staff member of
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences. A
geographer, he is responsible for the co¬
ordination of the mountain and island ecosystem
project areas of Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) Programme.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
In northern Kenya, one important cause of desert encroachment is the felling of trees and
shrubs by nomadic herdsmen to make bomas, or night enclosures, to keep their livestock
from straying and to protect them from wild animals such as jackals, hyenas, leopards
and lions that hunt at night. The herdsmen move several times a year and for every move
trees are cut and new bomas are built. Scientists in MAB's Integrated Project on Arid
Lands (IPAL) have found that, for the bomas of the Gabra people, about twelve Acacia
trees are used per household per move, or 70 to 100 trees per household per year. Below,
a typical settlement of the Rendille people with its thin outer thorn fence surrounding the
circle of family dwellings with the livestock enclosures in the centre. Separate enclosures
are used for camels and for sheep and goats. Sponsored by the Kenyan National
Committee for MAB and executed by Unesco, IPAL is designed to provide a better
scientific basis for land management in arid lands. The project was financed mainly by the
United Nations Environment Programme from 1976 to 1980, when funding was taken over
by the Federal Republic of Germany. Deforestation is contributing to the spread of deserts
throughout the arid and semi-arid regions of Africa where wood is virtually the sole fuel
available for cooking and heating. Above, these women of Mali often have to walk many
kilometres every day to gather firewood.
more than a third of its sheep and two-thirds
of its goats.
As the examples given above indicate,
one of the keys to these successes lies in the
application of the notion of complementari¬
ty: that is, the combined use of two or more
zones in such a way that their respective
constraints offset or complement each
other. This may involve zones of different
altitudes (as in the case of the altiplanos and
the foothills of the.Andes), or zones of vary¬
ing aridity (as in Africa south of the Sahara),
or zones of different socio-economic nature
(were it not for densely populated, highly in¬
dustrialized lowlands that surround them,
the European Alps would never have ex- .
perienced the astonishing development of
winter sports and summer tourism that has
occurred in recent years).
So far, however, the most important con¬
straint of all and one which affects all
marginal lands has not been men¬
tioned fragility.
Landscapes, vegetation and soil cover
degrade much more quickly in marginal
lands than in more favoured regions, if un¬
suitable land use practices are adopted.
Once the land has become degraded it is
much more difficult than in other regions to
restore fertility and productivity.
Today, under the pressure of increased
human and animal populations and changes
in land use systems, almost all the world's
marginal lands are in danger and it is becom¬
ing increasingly difficult to ensure the
maintenance of their long-term biological
productivity.
The "Dust Bowl" of the 1930s in the
United States was the result of improper ex¬
tension of dry crop cultivation into the dry
belt of the Middle West. Nobody spoke of
desertification at that time. Yet it was exact¬
ly that and a first example in modern times
of large-scale, catastrophic soil degradation.
A large industrialized country such as the
United States can survive if a small percen¬
tage of its surface becomes unproductive,
barren land. What, however, if the same
situation occurs in a Sahelian country?
What if large portions of a poor country
become affected by desertification due to
over-grazing and extension of rainfed
cultivation into areas which are not suited to
it? Then the ecological problem becomes a
pressing human one as millions of people ¡
see the whole basis of their livelihood placed \
in jeopardy.
For the countries south of the Sahara, it is
estimated that an area of some 685 million
hectares is affected by severe desertification
(out of a total land surface for Africa of
3,011 million hectares), and eighty million
people are already directly affected by a fall
in the productivity of the lands from which
they live.
For all these reasons a large part of the
research being carried out under Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme
is concentrated on halting improper land use
while at the same time increasing food pro¬
duction in marginal lands of such distinct
regions as the Sahel and eastern Africa, the
altiplanos of the Andes, the Hindu Kush-
Himalaya mountains or the traditional
rangelands of North Africa (see box
opposite). Nor does MAB neglect the prob¬
lems for the environment and for society
which may derive from uncontrolled use of .
marginal lands in developed countries. In f
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Holding the desert at bay
MAB- related research in southern Tunisia
The Problem: to improve the productivity of
rangelands and of livestock raising and to
control the extension of rainfed agriculture by
the preparation and introduction of integrated
land management plans in former Tunisian
grazing lands where a combination of human
and livestock population increases, a shrink¬
ing land base, agricultural expansion and
mechanization has led to a serious problem of
land degradation and even desertification.
In central and southern Tunisia annual rain¬
fall varies from 350 mm in the north to less
than 100 mm in the south. Traditionally these
areas were exploited by nomadic herdsmen.
Overgrazing was always a problem, par¬
ticularly in the south, but it was alleviated by
flock reductions in times of longer than usual
drought. Since the beginning of this century,
however, the population has increased con¬
siderably and has become more sedentary.
Large areas of former grazing lands are now
being cultivated with cereal and tree crops
(olives, almonds). At the same time, as the
human population grew so too did the number
of sheep and goats, thereby exerting further
pressure on the land. Finally, the introduction
of disc ploughing during the last twenty-five
years has accelerated the erosion of shallow
soils.
The Projects: as early as 1969, the Tuni¬
sian authorities, realizing the importance for
the country of solving its critical environmen¬
tal and developmental problems, launched a
programme of integrated ecological research.
During the early 1970s, two MAB-related ac¬
tivities were undertaken in this field. In the
first project, Tunisian authorities and
specialists collaborated mainly with French
specialists and institutions with services and
major funding being provided by the United
Nations Development Programme (UNDP), the
Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) and
Unesco. The second project originated under
the International Biological Programme and
brought mainly United States specialists from
the U.S. Desert Biome Project to work
alongside their Tunisian colleagues.
To maintain the continuity of this work, the
Tunisian Government in 1977 established a
National Institute of Arid Regions to which it
entrusted the task of promoting and co¬
ordinating MAB-type research and of training
research workers and technicians. At present
the Institute, with support from the United Na¬
tions Environment Programme (UNEP) and
Unesco's MAB Programme, is carrying out
studies on such problems as reseeding and
camel-raising.
The Results: data acquired in the
UNDP/FAO/Unesco project were used to
develop land management plans which in¬
tegrate rangeland herding, rainfall agriculture
and irrigation agriculture based on oases.
Rangeland maps were prepared showing the
major range units and other features such as
annual and seasonal primary productivity and
optimal period of use, on which rational land
use planning can in part be based. Methods
for increasing animal production were im¬
proved through various forage and animal
husbandry experiments. For the Zougrata
area, simulation models were worked out to
predict trends in productivity. Another exam¬
ple of the results concerns the importance of
the composition of flocks. Studies of mixed
flocks of half sheep and half goats showed
that goats consumed more of the tallest
vegetation group (shrubs) than in an only-
goat flock. Sheep consume larger amounts of
the annual and biennial species when in a
mixed flock than in all-sheep flocks. From a
practical standpoint, this suggests that the
goat is not the nuisance animal that it is
generally considered to be. Man himself, by
associating goats with sheep, has made the
grazing by goats more destructive. Similar
results have been found in other parts of the
world.
Drawing Etudes et Planification des Communications. Unesco Courier
Drawing, above, illustrates an integrated land development plan,
now being adopted in parts of southern Tunisia, which enables
traditionally separate land use systems to complement each
other. A densely populated oasis, with a permanent supply of
water (1) sufficient for irrigation agriculture and to meet the
needs of people and animals, forms the hub around which stock-
raising activities in the surrounding rangelands revolve. Water is
piped out to a watering trough (2) for the animals of the
rangelands where water is a precious resource. Crops (3) such as
cereals, vegetables, and alfalfa for fodder are grown under
irrigation, providing food for the population of the oasis and the
herdsmen of the rangelands. Supplementary forage (4) from
intensive agriculture can be a life-saver for the rangeland herds
during the annual dry season and in times of extended drought.
Supplementary forage may also be provided by growing well-
adapted plants, such as non-spiny cactus (5), which require no
irrigation. The herdsmen once nomadic but now tending to
settle in or on the outskirts of the oasis earn most of their
income from the cattle they graze (6) over an area extending very
many kilometres around the oasis. Combined oasis/rangeland
developments are being integrated into the national economy
and their products (7) sold on regional and national markets.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
some parts of the European Alps excessive
1 tourist development has already started to
destroy the very landscapes on which the
tourist industry is based. To deal with these
problems comprehensive, interdisciplinary
research aimed at understanding and im¬
proving the complex man/environment in¬
teraction is required (see box this page).
To add to all their other difficulties, the
marginal lands face a further problem which
they share, but in a much more intense
form, with the rest of the world the prob¬
lem of energy.
For about a third of mankind the energy
crisis means a daily scramble to find the
wood they need to cook their daily meal.
Nine-tenths of the inhabitants of the world's
poorest countries still depend on firewood
as their principal fuel, and at least half of all
the timber felled in the world is used as fuel
for cooking or as a source of heat.
All too often, however, the growth in
human population is outstripping the
growth of new trees, and villagers in the arid
and semi-arid regions of central Africa and
Asia, in many parts of the Andes, and the
Hindu Kush-Himalayas have to search far¬
ther and farther afield to satisfy their needs.
This constant search for firewood can,
furthermore, have serious environmental
consequences. Shrubs and trees play an im¬
portant role in maintaining balanced func¬
tioning of arid and semi-arid ecosystems.
They provide protection for the soil against
the direct impact of rain, they provide shade
for the lower vegetation, animals and peo¬
ple, they reduce evaporation and they en¬
sure better water regulation within the soil.
In addition, the leaves and branches that fall
from them enrich the humus content of the
upper soil and they provide a habitat for
birds which themselves play an important
role in the functioning of the ecosystem.
Over-use of trees and shrubs for firewood
and other human needs such as housing and
fencing sets in motion a process which
leads from soil erosion and degradation to
desertification.
Energy problems in the high mountain
areas are often equally acute, though,
paradoxically, through the development of
hydro-electric schemes, they have, in many
parts of the Andes and the Hindu Kush-
Himalaya ranges for example, become a ma¬
jor source of energy for urban, industrial and
rural development in the densely populated
valley systems, coastal areas and plains
below. In the actual mountain areas
themselves rural electrification has often not
been developed.
In these areas the energy problem is in¬
trinsically the same as that in the rural areas
of the arid and semi-arid zones, and wood is
likely to remain the principal fuel for at least
another two decades. The deforestation of
mountain slopes that this entails also in¬
volves serious environmental conse¬
quences erosion, the silting up of
hydro-electric dams and, eventually, in¬
creasingly severe flooding of the plains
below.
Solutions to the energy problems of
marginal lands are fairly simple to envisage
but extremely difficult to implement. Trees,
after all, are a renewable resource and a
logical response to the fuel shortage is to
plant more fast-growing trees for use as
firewood. Yet not enough tree-planting
schemes have been implemented and when
they have been introduced their effect has
often been wiped out by population growth.
22
Mountain scenarios
The Pays d'Enhaut projectSwitzerland
The Problem: to anticipate and minimize
the possible environmental effects of various
forms of economic development in an alpine
region of Switzerland.
The Project: despite considerable tourist
development over recent years, the Pays
d'Enhaut, a mountain district of the Vaud
Canton of Switzerland, unlike many other
alpine regions, has succeeded in maintaining
a viable upland agriculture and an unspoilt
natural environment. But important changes
are imminent. The lack of suitable employ¬
ment for young people may lead to depopula¬
tion of the area and a subsequent degradation
of the environment, on this occasion due to
lack of human intervention. Alternatively,
large-scale construction of hotels and chalets
for tourists, with the infrastructure of roads,
etc., that this would necessitate, might solve
the employment problem but could result in
serious deterioration of the environment.
The regional development programme
adopted in 1978 aims to find an acceptable
middle way which would maintain the local
population at its present level by the develop¬
ment of tourist facilities. To achieve this ob¬
jective, however, would involve the creation of
some thirty kilometres of ski pistes, the set¬
ting aside of one hundred hectares as a skiing
area, and the provision of about 4,000 addi¬
tional beds for tourists.
The MAB study now under way is an at¬
tempt to forecast the possible effects of
various levels and types of development and
the precautions needed to maintain the
equilibrium of the environment.
The people of the Pays d'Enhaut are active¬
ly involved in the research. A Project MAB,
Pays d'Enhaut Association has been formed
which includes representatives of every social
level of the community.
Fourteen research units have been
established to examine specific aspects of the
problem and to improve understanding of the
Pays d'Enhaut considered as a system.
The Results: research by the MAB team
only began in 1980 so it is too early to an¬
nounce concrete results. Four possible
scenarios for the future are, however, already
emerging and their implications for the en¬
vironment will be presented to the decision¬
makers and the local population. Very roughly
these scenarios may be described as follows :
1 . A traditionalist approach. This tends
towards the maintenance of the status
quo. with somewhat more emphasis being
placed on the development of farming ac¬
tivities, but with mechanization kept to the
strict minimum. Tourism would remain a
modest supplementary, mainly summer¬
time, activity, the tourist being lodged en
pension or in small hotels.
2 . A modernistic approach. This is resolutely
aimed at maximizing income for the local
population by developing to the maximum
all the resources of the region. Tourism
would become the major economic sector
and some agricultural land would be
abandoned.
3 . An "ecological" approach. The thinking
here is dominated by a desire to pass on to
future generations a biologically intact
region in which pollution, erosion, etc.,
are kept to a minimum. The tourist would
be tolerated only in so far as he was
prepared to respect nature. Building and
private transport would be severely
restricted. Agricultural methods would be
aimed at low energy consumption and the
use of "soft" technology.
4 . A "peripheral" approach. This sees the
district serving the larger urban centres
around it in various ways. Above all, the
Pays d'Enhaut would be a sort of country
retreat for the people of these cen¬
tres would involve the building of
a large number of individual secondary
residences and good access roads and the
provision of facilities for leisure activities.
Attempts are also being made to en¬
courage the use of alternative sources of
energy: bio-gas, solar and wind energy, for
example. But a great deal more research
leading to a considerable reduction in cost
and technological simplification is needed
on these alternatives before they can make a
substantial contribution.
The drama of the deterioration of the
world's marginal lands is that if it is allowed
to continue it may well result in the creation
of a vast army of marginal people, living in
totally inacceptable conditions. Deterio¬
rating ecological systems have a logic of
their own; the damage builds up little by
little until the day comes when the system
collapses. A combined international effort
is necessary if the marginal lands of the
world are to avoid this fate.
H Mohamed Ayyad and Gisbert Glaser
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Cities
in
crisis
by Valerio Giacomini
WHAT constitutes the "ideal city"? For
medieval European man, the goal
was an earthly reflection of a
heavenly model the City of God. For the
Utopian thinkers of the Renaissance it was a
suitable setting for the realization of their
own grand designs. During the past century
or more, architects and city planners have
applied a great deal of intelligence and, on
occasion, genius to the solution of this age-
old question.
The same period, however, has also seen
the expansion of cities on such a scale that
they now seem to defy all attempts at im¬
provement or control. These great centres
of human settlement, activity and culture
once radiated in all directions sometimes
to the very ends of the earth the light of
science, art, philosophy and technical pro¬
gress. Today, they accumulate, and cast
about them with the same profligacy, the
shadows of disorder, degradation and
waste.
The problems of great cities have thus
become one of the major issues, if not the
issue of our age. The enormity of the dif¬
ficulties faced by decision-makers in their at¬
tempts to contain and control the processes
which threaten the quality of the human
habitat is such that renewed efforts are
urgently required.
As long as human communities formed an
integral part of the natural order, their
physical and biological stability was in great
measure assured by the self-regulatory pro¬
cess of nature itself; their specific unity was
enveloped in the greater whole. But the pro¬
gressive alienation of the natural order,
which has reached its apogee in today's
metropolises, has weakened this relation¬
ship to the point of rupture.
What is called for is not a "return to
nature", but the development of an entirely
new pattern of interrelationships. Once,
man was merely a pupil in nature's school;
now his power over the environment, for
better or for worse, is supreme. There is no
ecosystem which has not to some extent
been subjected to interference by man in his
pursuit of personal gratification or im¬
mediate gain.
The urban ecosystem, the environment
which has been most affected by the in¬
terventions of modern man, offers a unique
opportunity for the pooling of efforts in the
task of humanizing science and mobilizing
its resources in the service of society. The
way in which these ecosystems function is
being studied within a major project of the
Man and the Biosphere Programme.
Scientists investigating urban phenomena
should acknowledge with humility that they
are only scratching the surface of a subject
of extreme complexity. Considered in isola¬
tion, the research findings of, for example, a
botanist concerning the flora of the city, of a
zoologist concerning its bird life or of a
hydrologist concerning its groundwater are
of fragmentary and limited significance; but
if they are linked together in logical fashion
and, more particularly, if these findings are
pooled in an investigation of more general
structures and functions, they acquire an
unexpected and sometimes fundamental
significance for the understanding of the
system in its entirety.
The so-called "systems approach" has
been widely utilized, but attention has until
now all too frequently concentrated on the
sub-systems and sub-sub-systems in which
life processes are organized, while the
macrostructures which constitute the only
setting in which human problems can be
properly appreciated remain neglected.
Within the MAB Programme it is ad¬
vocated that, if the systems approach is to
be truly effective, it should engage respon¬
sibilities on a far larger scale than in the past.
The major problems of the human habitat,
which have become extremely critical in ur¬
ban centres, no longer fall within the ex¬
clusive purview of specific disciplines or
technologies; nor are they a matter for
science and technology alone. Their dimen¬
sions are such that they resist limited,
specialized efforts to solve them. All the
resources of human culture must be brought
together in a vast collective undertaking,
and focussed on these problems in their
entirety.
If there is hope for the future, it can only
lie in a new spirit of solidarity between all the
scientific disciplines, between spokesmen
for culture in all its different forms, between
all the inhabitants of the city itself, and bet¬
ween decision-makers at every level.
Like the world of nature itself, the city
should be put to use in the service of in¬
dividual and collective human needs.
VALERIO GIACOMINI. This article is based on
a longer study written by Professor Giacomini, of
Italy, shortly before his untimely death on
5 January 1981. An eminent botanist, he was pro¬
fessor at the Instituto Botánico, Citta Univer¬
sitaria, Rome, and chairman of the Italian MAB
National Committee. He was the originator and
leader of the MAB Rome Project, a major
ecological study of the Italian capital launched in
1977.
The imposing façade of St. Peter's
Basilica, Rome, forms the
backcloth to this scene of traffic
congestion, one of the symptoms
of the problems facing major cities
today. Rome is the subject of a
large-scale ecological study
launched in 1977 by the Italian MAB
National Committee. The study,
which began as a study of energy
flows in the city, now encompasses
seventeen themes, ranging from
environmental perception to
modelling of the entire urban
system. Many groups, including
university research workers,
government institutions such as the
national electricity corporation, and
the local population are directly
involved. The Municipality of Rome
has decided to create a Centre for
the Study of Urban Problems, to
provide a more permanent
framework for the project and to
ensure the wide participation of all
the cultural and technical segments
of the local population. The
Municipality also envisages that the
Centre will eventually have a wider
international role to play in this
field of research.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The ecology
of megalopolis
by Stephen Boyden
and John Celecia
MEXICO City: thirty million inhabitants.
Tokyo and Sao Paulo: over twenty-
six million. These dramatic figures
are taken from the latest United Nations
statistical projections for the year 2000. Ac¬
cording to the same projections, over half the
people on earth are likely to be living in urban
areas by the end of this century (as against
today's 40 per cent), and eighteen cities in
developing countries will each have a popula¬
tion of over ten million. The problems of inner
city decay in the industrialized world pale to
insignificance beside those of the mushroom¬
ing cities in developing countries.
During much of this century urbanization
has been a worldwide phenomenon. Today,
however, under the pressure of the world
population explosion, it is taking place on
such an unprecedented scale that cities are
spreading an ever-widening circle of devasta¬
tion around them as they seek the resources
they need, and courting the risk of virtually
drowning in their own wastes.
The exodus from the countryside to the
towns is particularly dramatic in the develop¬
ing world, where it is taking place much more
rapidly and against a background of much
higher population growth than the urbaniza¬
tion process in the industrialized countries,
which was usually gradual enough to allow
the emergence of institutions capable of cop¬
ing with the problems of transformation.
Why should rural populations be attracted
to cities? It might be thought that rural pover¬
ty, especially when set against the backcloth
of grandiose natural surroundings, is less
brutal than poverty in the slums and shanty-
towns spawned by Third World cities. The
24
fact is that the former is just as deadly,
though less conspicuous, than the latter.
People gravitate to the cities because they ex¬
pect to find there better job opportunities and
social possibilities, availability of food, water,
health and educational facilities. And they are
right to the extent that average income in the
city is usually far higher than it is in the rural
economy. Cities are centres of consumption
on such a large scale that the resourceful may
find a form of sustenance which is a better
alternative than near-starvation in the coun¬
tryside. For the rural masses of the develop¬
ing world, then, migration to towns.and cities
is spurred by the need for survival.
The cruel irony is that this imbalance bet¬
ween town and country, reinforced by the
concentration of public investment in urban
areas, is now contributing to urban growth
on such a scale that it becomes impossible to
maintain the quality of life of city-dwellers.
Another irony: the problem of cities bursting
at the seams is further compounded by
demographic growth within their boundaries
when child mortality rates fall as a result of
the provision of better health care facilities. It
is little wonder that the question is being ask¬
ed in some quarters whether cities are ap¬
proaching, or have already reached, the limits
of expansion.
Although the problems of providing food,
lodging, water and health facilities and jobs
for tomorrow's urban multitudes will be im¬
mense, the signs are that the world is not
yet ready to meet the impact of the urban
explosion. Even when governments do
establish mechanisms and institutions for
dealing with urbanization they often seem
unable to perceive the problem as a whole.
In the last ten years, an ecological approach
to the study of urban settlements has been
evolved within the Man and the Biosphere
Programme. The main objective of these
MAB activities, which have so far led to the
implementation of over 60 field projects, is
to help improve the basis for the rational
planning of human settlements by pro¬
moting research on the complex interrela¬
tionships between man, his urban environ¬
ment, and the interactions between urban
settlements and their hinterland.
Good town and city planners have always
used ecological devices, but in. the past
often tended to deal with problems in isola¬
tion and put forward recommendations
which, though ecologically sound in
themselves, ceased to be so when con¬
sidered within the context of the wider ur¬
ban system. To take one simple example : a
green belt is created to provide a city with
"lungs". This is a desirable thing in itself,
but unless other measures are taken at the
same time, it may simply attract new
settlements and more traffic, so that new
STEPHEN BOYDEN, of Australia, is head of the
Urban Biology Group at the John Curtin School
of Medicine, Australian National University,
Canberra, and leader of the MAB integrative
study on the ecology of Hong Kong.
JOHN CELECIA is a staff member of Unesco's
Division of Ecological Sciences with responsibility
for co-ordinating activities within Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme in Latin
America. A biologist, he takes a special interest in
human ecology.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
roads have to be built. The hypothetical
green belt thus defeats its own object. In
contrast to this piecemeal approach an
integrated, interdisciplinary "ecosystem ap¬
proach" to urban studies is advocated
within MAB, with special attention being
given to the "flows" of food, energy,
materials, people, information and other
elements through cities.
One of the distinctive characteristics of
cities is that they depend on food surpluses
produced elsewhere. In fact urbanization
first began with the development of
agricultural surpluses made possible by
technical advances such as irrigation and the
use of draught animals. Urban growth was
limited until relatively recently by the capaci¬
ty of the immediate hinterland to provide the
city's basic food needs. But whereas in the
past cities drew on nearby land for their food
supplies, in the modern world they import
from distant countries. Their hinterland is
now worldwide. This reliance on food sup¬
plies from distant sources illustrates the
fragility and the vulnerability of the urban
ecosystem.
For those who live in cities, such
dependence has several implications. The
increasing cost of food production, the cost
of transportation, distribution and process¬
ing, and the consequent high energy
demands make food more expensive for the
city-dweller than for his rural counterpart.
The urban poor are hardest hit. They are
potentially vulnerable to serious malnutrition
because not only are they unable to pay
spiralling market prices for food, but
because in urban conditions they are often
deprived of the opportunity to grow their
own.
One answer to this problem, particularly
in developing countries, might be to give
agriculture prominence in national develop¬
ment plans, so that a flourishing agricultural
base could be built up to support decen¬
tralized, labour-intensive industries that
would process farm products and produce
goods useful to small farmers. This in turn
would bolster agricultural production and
help reduce rural migration. Meanwhile, for
millions of the urban poor, the potential
capacity of the urban system to produce
food may be a factor on which their survival
may hinge. The agricultural skills of the
migrant population can be effectively
harnessed with improved land use and the
establishment of intensive cultivation plots,
roof gardens and other productive units.
Composting, urban forestry, irrigation
systems using alternative energy systems for
pumping, aviculture and fish-farming are
some of the practices meriting greater atten¬
tion. Another step forward would be the
development of accessible techniques for
food storage and preservation in order to
counteract the dramatic losses of food in
areas where it is most wanting. In fact in ur¬
ban slums in many parts of the world people
are already displaying great resourcefulness
in producing food and recycling materials,
and this should be taken into account by
planners.
Although cities began with the develop¬
ment of agricultural surpluses, it was the
harnessing of the energy from fossil fuels as
the basis of modern industry that gave real
impetus to urban growth. This brought
more rapid, complicated and profound
changes to cities than any that had occurred
in their millennia of history.
The study of energy flows, with which the
Man and the Biosphere Programme is par-
This model of an urban system is taken from Urban Systems in Crisis, a publication based
on an important study carried out by the Munich-based Study Group for Biology and
Environment as part of the contribution of the Federal Republic of Germany to MAB
project 11 on human settlements. It illustrates the complexity of the interactions that
occur between the various components of an urban system and between an urban
settlement and its hinterland. Although based on a study of a specific area, the Frankfurt-
am-Main region, the model is applicable also to other environments. It was developed as
a tool for decision-makers and as an aid in understanding and planning human living spaces.
ticularly concerned, is an important yard¬
stick which can help us to understand the
urban ecosystem because 'energy is required
for all activities. The study of the energy pat¬
tern of a society touches on all aspects of its
development and draws attention to
ecologically significant changes that are tak¬
ing place. The pattern of the use of energy
from sources other than human or animal
muscle has particularly profound implica¬
tions, for it reflects the pattern of machine
use. This in turn is related to the quality of
the air people breathe, the levels of noise
they experience, the size of the enterprise
for which they work, and even to the time
they spend travelling to work or with their
families. Such factors may also affect the
structure of their families, the extent to
which they practise skills or exercise respon¬
sibility, or the amount of variety or
monotony in their lives. Many of these
aspects of people's lives are difficult or im¬
possible to measure, because they are in¬
tangible, but a truly comprehensive ap¬
proach to the study or planning of urban
systems, as being encouraged by MAB,
must pay full attention to them.
A MAB study on Hong Kong highlighted
the massive consumption of energy which is
another salient characteristic of the urban
system. The city's energy consumption
doubled in the ten years from 1961 to 1971,
whereas population did not greatly increase.
This phenomenon is part of a global trend
which accompanies industrialization. Before
the industrial era, muscle power was the
main source of energy, and consequently
the rate of energy use paralleled the rate of
increase in population. This is no longer the I
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The metabolism of a city
With some five million inhabitants squeezed
into an area of 1,046 square kilometres. Hong
Kong (right) is one of the most densely
populated areas in the world. It has recently
been the subject of a MAB study undertaken
by the Human Ecology Unit of the Australian
National University. The Unit examined the
interplay of urban forces within a city
committed to economic growth, increasing
industrialization, increasing consumption of
energy (much of it imported) and increasing
use of resources. The research team found in
Hong Kong all those elements of growth which
usually give rise to "big-city stress" (neuroses,
states of tension and psychosomatic maladies
in general) caused by endless rivers of traffic,
air pollution, vertical buildings dwarfing the
human scale and massive overpopulation. Yet,
to their surprise, in the course of a general
investigation of the patterns of health and
disease in Hong Kong, members of the MAB
team found a level of mental illness no higher
than that of Australia's spacious capital,
Canberra. They concluded that the people of
Hong Kong were shielded from big-city stress
by their cultural background, one of those less
tangible aspects of city life that research
workers, policy-makers and planners tend to
overlook or ignore because they are not
quantifiable. The upbringing of the
predominantly Chinese people of Hong Kong
remains rooted in traditional Chinese culture,
in a way of life that has long accepted as
normal high levels of population density. In
addition, there is a sense of involvement in the
Chinese extended family tradition. Working
together in Hong Kong's many small family
workshops and factories, family members and
friends retain a strong sense of purpose and
unity and these positive factors make a definite
contribution to well-being and good health.
The MAB approach to research on urban
settlements is to look at them as ecosystems,
examining the complex interactions that take
place within them rather than studying specific
problems in isolation. This technique is
illustrated by the diagrammatic representation
(below) of the flow of important materials into
and through Hong Kong, which might be
described as a chart of the metabolism of the
city. All the figures given are expressed in
metric tonnes per day.
CO S02 NO» C, H» lead particulates
I55 308 IIO 29 0.34 42
FRESH WATER 1,068,000
CARGO IN 18.000 *" ~>^^&'
PEOPLE IN 8,827
^ i**J%3fl
EXPORT:
GLASS-65
PLASTICS 324
WOOD140
IRON 6 STEEL 140
PAPER97
CEMENT 11
HUMAN FO0D602
LIQUID FUELS612
SOLID FUELS 140
CARGO OUT 8.154
PEOPLE OUT 8,632
Msm
SEWAGE SOLIDS6.301
SEWAGE LIQUIDS 819,000
' || : rf
HUMAN FOOD 5,985
ANIMAL F000335
LIQUID FUELS 11,030
SOLID FUELS 193
MATERIALS:
GLASS 270
PLASTICS 680
CEMENT 3.572
WOOD 1.889
IRON & STEEL 1,878
PAPER 1,015
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
.case today when the amount of energy be¬
ing used is doubling about twice as fast as
the population. Extra-somatic energy use in
Hong Kong, although it doubled, was only
about one-tenth of what it is in the United
States and one-fifth of what it is in
Australia.
As demand rises, cities face energy prob¬
lems which are not unlike those of food sup¬
ply: the fuel must either come from the sur¬
rounding countryside or from imports.
In many developing countries the vast ma¬
jority of the urban poor rely on traditional
fuels such as wood and charcoal. To obtain
their supplies they must either bring
devastation to nearby woods and forests, or
else buy fuels such as kerosene or bottled
gas, which they can ill afford. Another alter¬
native, buying their wood and charcoal from
merchants, means that the ecological
damage is done even further away from the
city through the exploitation of distant
forests.
The urban poor use less energy than the
rural poor. There are two reasons for this.
The first is that the need to buy fuel en¬
courages them to use as little as possible;
the second is that a kerosene stove is more
efficient than a countryman's open fire.
However, this energy efficiency is depen¬
dent on increasingly costly imported fuel,
and so there is an urgent need for alternative
energy systems.
The world thus faces a phenomenon of
mushrooming urban growth whose implica¬
tions are colossal. Sectoral approaches have
only brought a limited understanding of the
human system on the one hand and the
natural system on the other. We must ac¬
cept the challenge of interdisciplinarity, of
harmonizing the goals of economic develop
ment with environmental concerns and
human well-being. Within the Man and the
Biosphere Programme a number of coun¬
tries have developed such integrative ap¬
proaches to improve understanding of urban
ecosystems and produce information for
planning and decision-making.
Unfortunately such efforts are still very
dispersed, dependent on limited human and
financial resources, and constrained by
institutions which maintain a sectoral
approach.
In many cases the institutions and scien¬
tists participating in this work have had a
multiplier effect on the , modest resources
available. It is to be hoped that an increased
awareness of the problems of urbanization
at international, national and institutional
level will lead to greater support for these
pioneering efforts.
M Stephen Boyden and John Celecia
The Problem: how to guide urban and
regional planning in ways that help, firstly, to
mitigate the adverse social effects that may
accompany the process of urbanization,
secondly, to conserve energy demand for
which increases dramatically with urbaniza¬
tion and, thirdly, to provide future energy re¬
quirements from renewable resources.
The Project: examines the ecological prob¬
lems associated with the development of Lae,
the major industrial city of Papua New Guinea,
which has grown rapidly in the past decade.
From 1966 to 1971 the urban population in¬
creased by sixteen per cent each year and in
the following six years grew by five per cent
annually. By October 1977 the population had
reached 45,000.
The MAB study, undertaken by a research
team drawn from the Human Ecology Unit of
the Australian National University, started in
1976 and ended its field work in 1979. Par¬
ticular attention was paid to a comparison of
living conditions for a group of highlanders
from the Chimbu province, both in their rural
villages and the urban setting to which many
of them have migrated. Sub-projects examin¬
ed the repercussions of cash-cropping of cof¬
fee and the spread of the market economy;
changes in social behaviour during the pro¬
cess of urbanization; rural and urban food
habits and beliefs; and energy flow for Lae
and Chimbu. The aim was to lay the basis of
an ecologically sound energy future and
create an urban system in Lae compatible
with both the social and biological re¬
quirements of human well-being.
The Results: the comparative food study
shows that attitudes to food are changing
rapidly. Even the most remote hinterland has
felt the effect of the city's market economy
Change without tears
The Lae project Papua New Guinea
through the influence of the village stores
which now import foodstuffs and consumer
goods from Lae. In the village group under
study malnutrition among children was high.
Even though there are enough greens and
other foods available to provide an adequate
diet, cultural preferences for the sweet potato
(which is high in unrefined carbohydrate and
low in proteins) are strong. In the village the
incidence of gastro-intestinal and respiratory
infections was also high, as was childhood
morbidity and mortality. Degenerative
diseases appeared virtually absent.
In the urban environment, however, the
pattern is changing more rapidly. The urban
diet is rich in animal protein, children grow
faster, and malnutrition is half that of the
village. Even so, the diet is more refined,
sweeter, and higher in fat, and tends to in¬
crease susceptibility to degenerative diseases
of the heart, diabetes, and dental caries.
The position of women in society has been
affected. The movement of men from village to
city to work as labourers forced the women
left behind to fill traditional male roles as well
as their own. However the resultant stress
was cushioned by the close-knit social group¬
ings of village life. Less fortunate were those
women who accompanied their husbands.
Dependent on the husbands' earnings for food
they could no longer use their skills in food
gardening and animal husbandry and fre¬
quently suffered alienation. Indeed many of
the social problems identified by the study
team have stemmed from the change to a cash
economy which has cut across traditional
village patterns of wealth and power.
Studies on energy flow and waste disposal
have led to practical measures for conserving
energy. One example is the use of sawdust,
market residues and other resources of
"waste energy'' for producing compost. In
1978 the Lae City Council established the first
120 of a planned 1,500 intensively composted
allotment gardens. Subsequently a design of
a city-wide composting programme to pro¬
duce 11,000 tons per annum was prepared
and construction is now proceeding. A
60,000 gallon bioconversion system was
commissioned in November 1979 as a pilot
project for the recovery of sewage as sludge
for composting, as liquid fertilizer for broad-
acre agriculture, and as methane-rich gas for
industry and transportation.
Allotment gardens kept fertile by compost
from domestic and industrial refuse and
sewage sludge will relieve the burden of in¬
discriminate gardening on the adjacent hills,
which has resulted in devastating erosion. A
project has been designed to re-plant the
hillsides, for conservation and rehabilitation,
tor firewood, and for subsistence agro-
forestry using nitrogen-fixing trees and
vegetables in areas zoned for each purpose.
Another practical follow-up is that the MAB
project triggered the formulation of the
Government's national energy-policy, and a
strategy of implementation, which was
adopted by the National Cabinet in February
1979. National Alcohol Fuel and Wood Fuel
Programmes, plus wind energy, direct solar
heating, cooling and electricity, and large-
scale biogas projects are planned.
The Lae project is therefore an example of a
MAB field project which has produced ap¬
plicable scientific results which have subse¬
quently been applied. One key to the success
of the project was the focus of the research
project on problems of priority concern to local
and central government. In effect local and
regional policy-makers and administrators
were involved at all stages of the research,
from project formulation to transfer of results.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Conservation
for development
by Walter Lusigi and Jane Robertson
T
1 HE biosphere is like a self-regenerat¬
ing cake, and conservation is the
conduct of our affairs so that we
can have our cake and eat it too. As long as
certain bits of the cake are not consumed and
consumption of the rest of it is kept within cer¬
tain limits, the cake will renew itself and pro¬
vide for continuing consumption. For people
to gain a decent livelihood from the earth
without undermining its capacity to go on sup¬
porting them, they must conserve the
biosphere."
This image of the biosphere, evoked by
Robert Allen in his book How to Save the
World, neatly summarizes current attitudes
towards conservation and underlines how
much the concept has evolved over the years.
Four centuries before the Christian era Plato
was complaining that the mountains of Greece
were being stripped of their trees. He was sad¬
dened to see the beauty of his homeland mar¬
red. Others who followed him were less con¬
cerned with beauty than with practical mat¬
ters, with natural resources considered as
commodities useful for specific purposes. The
Romans who argued for the conservation of
certain forested areas wanted to ensure a con¬
stant supply of wood for the construction of
warships; in the Middle Ages yew trees were
planted and protected solely to provide long¬
bows for archers, and the monarchs and great
landowners of Europe set aside forests for
their personal hunting pleasures and as a
source of game for their banqueting tables.
Many of these royal forests the Bialowieza
Forest in Poland and the New Forest in
England are but two examples stand to this
day, vestiges of the ubiquitous mixed forest
that once covered this part of the world.
This was conservation of a sort. But the
humbler people of those times, albeit un¬
consciously, were practising a perhaps more
important form of conservation throughout
their lives. For it must not be forgotten that the
traditional land use practices of farmer and
peasant existed in harmonious balance with
the natural environment. The elaborate ter¬
races on hillsides, whether in Indonesia, in Italy
or in the Andes, the primitive but efficient ir¬
rigation systems in arid and semi-arid areas,
the open animal ranges of the African savan¬
nah and the intricate jigsaw puzzles of field
and hedge in north-western France were all
created and maintained by man, and his cons¬
tant action provided a large variety of habitats
for a whole range of wild and domestic
animals, insects, plants, reptiles and birdlife
which evolved within the framework of
these man-made agro-ecosystems. In Asia,
respect for wild animals and plant life was
perhaps even more developed and, indeed,
was raised to the level of dogma in certain
religions.
In the western world, the industrial
revolution radically altered this situation of
balance and harmony with nature. The new
industrial towns encroached on agricultural
land and subsistence farming dwindled as
farmers developed new methods to make
the land more productive in order to feed the
growing urban populations.
Gradually, during the eighteenth and
nineteenth centuries, a reaction set in
against the waste and degradation of the
land these changes involved. In the United
States of America the wholesale destruction
of natural resources and the massacre of
birds and animals such as the passenger
pigeon and the Great Plains buffalo
precipitated the formation of a conservation
movement. In 1864, the Yosemite Valley,
with its beautiful landscapes and awe-
inspiring groves of giant sequoias, was
designated a protected area, administered
Below, view of the Glacier National Park; Montana, one of the 36 protected areas in the USA designated as biosphere reserves.
With reserves ranging from the Aleutian Island National Wildlife Refuge to the Everglades National Park, the U.S. biosphere
reserve network now covers every biogeographical province within the country's territory.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
by the State of California, and in 1872 the
Yellowstone region of Wyoming was pro¬
claimed a national park, but under Federal
supervision. These two parks, reserved for
man's recreation and aesthetic pleasure,
were the forerunners not only of a national
system of parks but also of similar initiatives
throughout the world and by the 1920s
national parks were to be found in every
continent.
The birth of the national parks movement
marked a major step forward in the evolu¬
tion of the concept of conservation, the im¬
portance of which has become increasingly
evident during this century as industrial
growth and the population explosion place
greater and greater pressure on the world's
natural resources.
However, for a number of reasons, the
national park concept has not always travell¬
ed well. In many cases the mistake has been
made of believing that conservation
methods can be transplanted directly
without being adjusted to suit the new en¬
vironment and with no attempt being made
to assess local cultural values, local fears
and local needs.
This applies, for example, in Africa. Living
in balance with the environment has always
been an integral component of African
culture. From childhood the African is
taught to co-exist with the natural world
around him and that he is part and parcel of
the system. African religions refer specifical¬
ly to the preservation of natural things and
it is taboo to kill more than is needed for
survival.
The communal land ownership system
was also designed to enhance this living in
balance with nature. In pastoral societies
wildlife was regarded as "second cattle" and
was especially used during droughts when
cattle were scarce. Throughout the years
Africans evolved a form of co-existence with
the wildlife around them which permitted
both to survive.
The era of colonization and settlement
and the two world wars that followed did
much to destroy the sense of harmony with
nature that had been part of the African
heritage for so many years. The Kenyan ex¬
perience provides a classic example.
During both world wars there was large-
scale slaughter of wildlife, with the meat be¬
ing used to feed prisoners of war. After the
war, a concentrated effort was made to
develop agriculture in Kenya. Wild animals
were regarded as pests, destroying crops
and competing with domestic livestock for
pasture; it was thought to be in the best in¬
terests of the country to kill off as many wild
animals as possible and this policy was
ruthlessly implemented.
It was against this background that the
Society for the Preservation of the Fauna of
the Empire was formed to protect the
WALTER LUSIGI, of Kenya, is deputy director
of Kenya's National Environment Secretariat. A
former habitat ecologist with the Kenya Wildlife
Management Project of the United Nations, he is
co-ordinator of the MAB Integrated Project on
Arid Lands (IPAL).
JANE ROBERTSON is a consultant with
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences. An
ecologist concerned primarily with nature conser¬
vation, she collaborates with the Secretariat of
the World Heritage Convention and with the
MAB biosphere reserve project.
This poster is
used by Senegal's
National Parks
Service to
publicize the
cause of wildlife
protection.
dwindling wildlife population. The Society
immediately demanded some control over
the indiscriminate slaughter of wildlife, and
the establishment of national parks and
reserves. First a system of reserves covering
virtually the whole of the country was
established, and game could be hunted only
on permit. Later, in 1946, the first national
park was established, to be quickly followed
by others. These were game preserves
where no settlement or hunting were
allowed.
But the needs of Africans in Kenya receiv¬
ed little consideration in this period. First,
the European settlers had ousted many
Africans from their traditional homelands.
Then the introduction of laws which allowed
hunting by permit only made their normal
subsistence hunting illegal. Finally the crea¬
tion of national parks reduced still further
the land available to them. Thus, for the
African, the national parks have been one of
the mechanisms that forced him from his
home, and the penalties imposed for in¬
fringement of the game laws have solidified
his negative attitude toward wildlife and its
conservation.
Meanwhile, ironically enough, the parks
are becoming less and less suitable as
habitats for wildlife, primarily because of
measures originally taken to preserve them
for that purpose. The parks of Kenya were
founded on the premise that nature would
be allowed to take its course and no human
intervention would be allowed. But most of
the parks were established on derived
grasslands, which had been partly maintain¬
ed as grassland by fire. In the absence of
fire, the land is reverting to woody vegeta¬
tion which is unsuitable for game adapted to
open plains.
The Kenya experience has been con¬
sidered at some length, firstly, because it is
an experience which, apart from specific
details, it shares with many other countries
in Africa and elsewhere, and, secondly,
because it highlights the need for a further
evolution in our thinking about
conservation.
If conservation is to win acceptance from
local populations it must take into account
cultural mores, and the long-standing ties
between the population and the natural en¬
vironment. Planning must be based on an
evaluation of cultural, political and socio¬
economic as well as ecological factors, and
conservation must take local human needs
into consideration, in both the short and the
long term. It must offer a solution to the ap¬
parent contradiction between conservation
and development needs.
CONTINUED PAGE 34
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Biosphere reserves
by Vladimir Sokolov
and Piotr Gounin
A
bird that dislikes flying, prefers to run and
climb trees and hides its food in its
burrow like a mammal (the saxaul jay), a
bird that can sing like a lark, chatter like a magpie,
whistle like a man and bray like a donkey (the
wheatear), a type of sparrow that never drinks, '
the world's biggest lizard (the "sand crocodile" or
monitor lizard which can attain a length of one
and a half metres) these are some of the
stranger denizens of the huge (34,600 hectares)
Repetek Biosphere Reserve in the desertic
Karakum region of the USSR.
The Soviet Union has a proud record of nature
conservation with one hundred and twenty-five
State reserves covering a total area of over eight
million hectares. Seven of these State reserves,
including Repetek, have been designated as
biosphere reserves forming part of Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) network of biosphere
reserves. The six other reserves are: The Berezina
Reserve, in the Byelorussian SSR a low-lying
area of alluvial sands and glacial moraines almost
entirely covered with broadleaf and spruce forests
typical of the Russian plain; The Caucasus
Reserve, located in the western part of the
Left, a stretch of the Repetek biosphere
reserve, situated in the Kara-Kum desert,
and two of the bird species found there:
above left, the Egyptian Vulture (Neophron
percnopterus) and, above right, the
Isabelline Wheatear (Oenanthe isabellina).
Biosphere reserves are protected areas
where nature conservation is combined
with basic scientific research, climatic and
pollution observation and measurement,
and environmental education. Drawing,
right, illustrates the various functions of a
biosphere reserve, here set in a northern
temperate ecosystem. The Core zone (1)
contains a representative example of the
major natural ecosystem of the region, in
this case mixed and coniferous upland
forest. The core zone is strictly protected
and serves as a background area or control
for studying man's impact on the natural
environment. The Buffer zone (2) surrounds
the core zone and serves as a protective
screen. It contains areas in which the
ecosystem has been modified by such
human activities as agriculture, timber
extraction and cattle raising. Facilities and
activities in the buffer zone as illustrated
here include (A) traditional land use;
(B) carefully controlled recreation of a non¬
destructive, non-polluting type; (C) facilities
for basic research, laboratories for
measurement, scientific analysis, etc.;
(D) experimental plots used to study
specific plants under controlled conditions;
(E) environmental monitoring, including
continuous observations of rainfall,
temperature and air pollution levels;
(F) teaching the general public about
environmental problems and nature
conservation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
in the USSR
Caucasus mountains a typical mountain land¬
scape covering all altitudinal zones and including
broad-leafed forests, fir forests, glaciers and
alpine meadows; The Pnoksko-Terrasny Reserve,
in the basin of the Oka river a good example of
the ecosystem of the East European plain; The
Sary-Chelek Reserve, in the Chathal mountain
range in south-west Tian-Chan it has an ex¬
tremely diverse and complex vegetation ranging
from nut-fruit forest, spruce forest and mountain
grasslands and its fauna includes the white-
clawed bear and snow leopard; The Sikhote-Alin
Reserve, along the coast of the Sea of Japan its
vegetation is dominated by coniferous and broad-
leafed forests, but includes several relict and
endemic species; The Central Chernozem
Reserve, in the central Russian uplands on the
borders of the Kursk and Belgorod regions a
characteristic oak-steppe forest of the European
part of the USSR, containing rare examples of
undisturbed meadow-steppe.
All seven biosphere reserves had previously
been functioning as State natural reserves for
quite a considerable period (the reserve at
Repetek, for example, was founded in 1928) and
have long records of observations on the basic
components of nature. This facilitated the first
stage of ecological monitoring taking inven¬
tories of plants, animals, micro-organisms,
ecosystems and processes. Another advantage
was the existence of research units within or close
to these reserves.
Thus the Prioksko-Terrasny biosphere reserve
includes the Biosphere Station of the
Agrochemistry and Pedology Institute of the
USSR Academy of Sciences, and the Sand
Desert Station of the Desert Research Institute of
the Turkmenian Academy of Sciences is situated
in the Repetek reserve.
The seven biosphere reserves naturally do not
cover all the variety of nature in the USSR and the
USSR National Committee for MAB is conduc¬
ting preparatory work for the establishment of a.
second series of biosphere reserves, first of all in
Siberia, Kazakhstan and Central Asia where the
rate of development requires rapid, profound and
detailed investigation.
The Prioksko-Terrasny biosphere reserve, in the Oka river basin about 120 kilometres
south-west of Moscow.
Every biosphere reserve is charged not only
with the general task of monitoring and studying
the effects of pollution on the natural environ¬
ment but also with more specific tasks such as
observing the influence of various types of
economic activities on the local ecosystems on a
regional scale. In addition the biosphere reserves
may be used as study grounds for the training of
personnel for other countries.
Training courses of this type are conducted at
the Repetek reserve, where participants from
developing countries are instructed and trained in
various aspects of nature conservation as applied
to deserts. It is worth mentioning that not long
ago deserts were considered to be "errors of
nature" and not worth conserving, whereas in
fact they are extremely rich in biological
resources.
The Repetek reserve'in the USSR is so far the
only biosphere reserve in the temperate deserts of
Central Asia and its functioning as well as the
establishment of other reserves in this climatic
zone is of the utmost importance for the rational
use of natural communities in the desert.
Thus the objectives of the MAB biosphere net¬
work are highly complex and require a further
strengthening of co-operation at every level: na¬
tional, bilateral, regional and global. Man has
reached a stage in his development when his ac¬
tivity has to be commensurate with the capacities
of nature. Researchers throughout the world have
a priority task to learn to use the resources of
the biosphere without upsetting its balance.
VLADIMIR SOKOLOV, of the Soviet Union, is
chairman of the USSR MAB National Committee
and vice-chairman of the International Co¬
ordinating Council for the MAB Programme. He is
director of the Institute of Evolutionary Mor¬
phology and Animal Ecology of the USSR
Academy of Sciences, and chairman of the
theriological section of the International Union of
Biological Sciences.
PIOTR GOUNIN, Soviet geographer and
specialist on arid lands, is a senior member of the
Institute of Evolutionary Morphology and Animal
Ecology of the USSR Academy of Sciences. He is
scientific secretary of the USSR MAB project 8
on biosphere reserves.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Poachers turned gamekeepers
The Mapimi biosphere reserve experiment
The giant desert tortoise (Gopherus
flavomarginatus) has been saved from
almost certain extinction by the
establishment of the Mapimi biosphere
reserve in the State of Durango, Mexico.
The entrance to its burrow is shaped in the
distinctive outline of its shell.
The Problem: to reconcile the seemingly
conflicting demands of development and con¬
servation within a semi-desert basin known
as the Bolsón of Mapimi, situated in the State
of Durango in north-central Mexico, an area
with a surprisingly rich variety of plant life
and animals including such rare species as
the lynx, the cougar, the black-tailed deer,
the wild turkey and the great desert tortoise.
The Project: in 1974, the Mexican
authorities decided to buy up a tract of land in
Mapimi to be set aside as a biosphere reserve
devoted to nature conservation and scientific
research. The site of the reserve lies within a
semi-desert basin of several hundred thou¬
sand hectares which is the exclusive habitat
of the endangered desert tortoise, Gopherus
flavomarginatus.
Field work at Mapimi started in early 1975
with a study of flora and vegetation which
revealed the tremendous ecological diversity
of the area. As a follow-up to these initial
studies, others were begun on the native
animal communities and on the ecological ef¬
fects of cattle grazing. At the same time,
researchers from the Mexican Institute of
Ecology carried out an information-
demonstration-persuasion campaign with the
people of Mapimi, showing them, for exam¬
ple, how small-scale, inexpensive irrigation
practices could give higher fodder yields and
explaining why hunting should be controlled
and certain species protected.
The peasants and stockmen quickly realiz¬
ed that they could only benefit from the
establishment of the biosphere reserve and
agreed to work with the scientists in a large
area surrounding the conservation zone own¬
ed by ranchers and ejidos (peasant collective
enterprises).
The Results: in 1981, Mapimi is a highly
successful example of how to integrate con¬
servation, research and development.
Because of the vulnerability of the main food
cropsmaize and beansto prolonged
drought and parasite pests, research has
been focussed on diversifying food crops and
improving stock raising methods, including
the introduction of a new variety of non-spiny
pear cactus as forage. Production of fruit and
vegetables is now high enough to provide an
exportable surplus and range management
research has resulted in the drawing up of
guidelines, not only in Mexico, but in arid
areas elsewhere.
A great deal has been learned about the
specialized desert-living plants and animals.
Endangered species are now protected by the
people themselves the surest means of pro¬
tection that exists. Although protected by Jaw
before the creation of the reserve, the giant
desert tortoise, for example, was tracked
down for food. Ecologists told the people of
Mapimi that there would be no tortoises left if
hunting continued and convinced them that an
alternative source of protein could be obtained
through rational cattle ranching. The former
poachers have now turned gamekeepers and
themselves protect the desert tortoise.
So successful has the Mapimi project prov¬
ed to be that Rosendo Aguilera, a stock farmer
in Mapimi and an enthusiastic supporter of
the project, is now visiting a biosphere
reserve at Oonana, in southern Spain near
Seville, an area sharing similar problems, to
explain the methods that have brought new
hope and prosperity to Mapimi.
The Desert Research Laboratory in the Mapimi biosphere reserve, Mexico.
-IT-»
V~.«.»»*Ü\
Getting
the message
across
MUCH scientific research pro¬
duces information which can
be useful to a variety of non-
scientific audiences. The key is to
communicate that information in a form
which is adapted to the interests and
needs of each audience. Technical
information on environmental
problems, for example, needs to be
"translated" in order to he understand¬
able to resource planners and
managers, teachers, students, children
and others, all of whom can benefit
from having such information made
available to them.
Four graphic presentations on the
functioning of a tropical forest are
presented below. In each case, the
same information is depicted differently
for scientists, decision-makers,
students and children. Other
effective means for communicating
scientific information are audio-visual
programmes, posters, and exhibits.
Jeanne Damlamian
Unesco MAB Secretariat
: esss-
I
I
Departmental Memo
To: Head, Department of Forestry
From: Chief, Technical Assessment Unit
Subject: Guidelines for land development
in the South East Province
1 . The Department has been requested by
* the Ministry of Natural Resources to
_ evaluate the potential for land develop-
I ment of the South East Province.
The South East Province is covered by
tropical forests with low density popula¬
tion of farmers. The presence of a large
biomass of "natural" tropical forest does
not guarantee rich economic potential.
Soil fertility is a key factor in determining
the suitability of tropical forests for dif¬
ferent types of land use. Nutrient rich
and nutrient poor areas cannot be used in
the same way without risk of long-term
ecological damage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
PRECIPITATION
53.8
COMPARTMENTS kg ha
FLUXES, kgha'yr-'
CANOPY
THROUGH
FALL
STEM
FLOW
I
3.4
I
-9.5
HUMUS
ROOT LAYER
FRUIT
FALL
I
0.13
_i_
LEAF
FALL
18.8
TREE.
FALL
I
6.9
ORGANIC MATTER
MINERAL SOIL
51.41
1.2'
52.6 -34.1-
17.1
10.9
/I
ORGANIC MATTER
MINERAL SOIL
136.5 \
71, v
577.6
40.7
A
WOOD^v
AND
BARK
K
208.2 \- 2.9
14.2
RUN
OFF
3.3
J_
3.3
CLAY AND CONCRETIONS
57.7
9.5
ROOTS
107.9
685.5
I
Compartment model showing composite budget of calcium,
potassium and magnesium in the tropical moist evergreen
forest at San Car/os de Rio Negro, Venezuela.
3 . Land capability surveys and social impact
assessments of South East Province have
been conducted by the National Seien
tifie Research Centre.
-<5>
mo*, and lichens living
ITthe surfaces of leaves
and bark play an ^^
important role in nrtrogen
fixation of the forest.
Multi-layered
acts as a filter of
rainfall and the atmi
'before the leaves
Root tips growing upwards, wh«*
KnTamched to fallen Wer
»«---d,=:strips
act as an «^"^Tutrients can
decomposing litter to roots.
<vofte
Intensive forp^t ñ .,
^s^nh,oggZ¡nteíT°n h «*
forest type. " 9 ,ntenS'ty adjusted to
* Improvement of existing
affro-forestry on nut^n,' SVStems of
fast and South ^^SOi,s in »he
farmers to introduce I9 With ,oca'
"ees and crops used sÚT °f fru*
SÄSKÄ b,ocks of ***
'"sect pests to Z.T °ntro' Potential
Information
for children
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 29
The biosphere reserve concept developed
within Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) Programme contains the elements of
this alternative approach. This concept at¬
tempts to combine the preservation of
ecological and genetic diversity with fun¬
damental and applied research, education
and training.
Significantly, great emphasis is placed on
the co-operation and participation of the
local population and to some extent the
term "reserve" is misleading as it is not in¬
tended that biosphere reserves be forbidden
areas surrounded by protective, separating
barbed-wire fences. Scientific research
within these reserves is not confined to the
ecology of the fauna and flora but also con¬
cerns the rational use of natural resources
in connexion with the economy of the
surrounding region.
One major difference between biosphere
reserves and national parks is that whereas
the latter are often chosen for their natural
beauty, biosphere reserves are selected as
representative examples of the world's ma¬
jor ecosystems in order to preserve samples
of the world's ecological diversity.
As man has altered and transformed the
face of the world from time immemorial, by
definition biosphere reserves must include
man-modified ecosystems where certain
forms of human intervention constitute im¬
portant ecological factors which must be
continued on a sustainable basis if the
ecosystem is to be perpetuated.
In biosphere reserves a combination of
conservation and manipulative research is
carried out. Generally speaking, a biosphere
reserve consists of a strictly protected cen¬
tral "core" zone in which the natural
development of the ecosystem, untouched
by man, is monitored. The core zone
therefore acts as a baseline or control
against which the impact of man on similar
ecosystems elsewhere can be compared.
The core zone is surrounded by a larger
"buffer" zone in which research is carried
out on the impact of various types of land
use such as traditional agriculture, ex¬
perimental agriculture, recreational ac¬
tivities, etc.
Today, within the framework of the MAB
Programme a network of 193 biosphere
reserves, covering most of the world's major
biomes, has been established in 50 coun¬
tries. The results of research carried out
within these reserves is exchanged through
MAB's computerized Information System.
In some cases even closer co-operation is
achieved through the "twinning" of reserves
covering the same type of ecosystem but in
different parts of the world. jn
This is the case, for example of the
Berezinsky reserve in the USSR and the Isle
Royale National Park (which is also a
biosphere reserve) in the United States of
America.
A biosphere reserve is much more than
just another conservation unit. Indeed, the
biosphere reserve concept marks the latest
stage in the evolution of the concept of con¬
servation. Going beyond the important first
stage of preservation, it involves research in¬
to the wider question of man's use and
modification of entire ecosystems. It
resolves the apparent contradiction between
conservation and development and con¬
stitutes a new approach towards the
maintenance of mankind's biological life-
support system.
B Walter Lusigi and Jane Robertson
Perspectives and prospects
by Ralph Slatyer
IT is ten years since the Man and Biosphere
(MAB) Programme was launched by
Unesco, with the aim of providing
improved scientific knowledge and trained
personnel needed to manage natural
resources.
The Programme has passed through a
lengthy period of planning and testing out
new approaches to co-operative research,
into its present stage of active operational
projects in real field situations. In each of the
major themes of MAB there are now a
number of comprehensive well-funded pro¬
jects producing vital management-related in¬
formation, and many more are emerging.
The ingredients which have been essential
to the success of the Programme can now
be seen more clearly than when it was first
commenced.
A first ingredient is participation in a MAB
project of the range of individuals and
organizations that are affected by, or can
help solve, the problems which the project
contains. Thus a comprehensive MAB field
project involves scientists from various areas
of the natural and social sciences, often
from various institutions and sometimes
from several countries or international
organizations. It also involves decision¬
makers and representatives of local popula¬
tions which are affected by land-
management policies and decisions. The
development of such interdisciplinary
groups has meant that basic information
which is collected or made available,
whether in the natural or social sciences, is
co-ordinated and brought to bear on the
practical problems of land management.
A second ingredient is that MAB is a
"from-the-bottom-up" programme, in
which individual countries decide their own
priorities for research, and undertake that
34
research within broad agreed frameworks
for international co-operation. This helps ex¬
plain the wide support that MAB has
generated in countries spanning the whole
range of ecological and geopolitical con¬
ditions found in the world. MAB is their
programme. At the same time, this
characteristic of MAB puts a special respon¬
sibility on countries. Until a particular coun¬
try the government, or an institution
in the country, or even an individual starts
a project, so far as MAB is concerned,
nothing happens. There is no MAB project.
So, there has to be a firm national commit¬
ment before a project gets off the ground.
This helps ensure that the project is dealing
with a problem having some ranking in na¬
tional priorities.
A third ingredient has been the degree to
which individual projects have attracted ad¬
ditional financial support once they have
become established. The initial input of
funds associated with the national commit¬
ment to each project has, in many cases,
been catalysed by modest financial support
from Unesco's regular budget to generate
substantial additional support from both
bilateral and multilateral sources. This
substantial multiplier effect of MAB funds
has been of critical importance to many
projects.
A final ingredient has been the perfor¬
mance of the Paris-based international MAB
Secretariat, a team of less than ten
specialists assisted by a small number of
scientists seconded periodically from
Member States. Although each member of
the team has specific responsibilities for a
part of the programme, the degree of in¬
terpersonal interaction is such that the col¬
lective contribution is much greater than the
sum of the individual efforts. In my view it
would be difficult to overstress the role of
the Secretariat in the present success of
MAB.
In late 1981, MAB will be 10 years old. To
mark the Programme's tenth anniversary, a
conference will be held in "September in
Paris to review the progress that has been
made, to evaluate shortcomings as well as
achievements, and to point the way for the
further evolution of the Programme.
It is, of course, too early to say what will
be the result of this important exercise.
However, it seems likely that MAB will con¬
tinue to be based on an interdisciplinary,
problem-oriented approach; that the Pro¬
gramme will resist the temptation of em¬
bracing everything and will remain concen¬
trated on a few themes of priority impor¬
tance; and that increased attention will be
given to demonstrating the practical implica¬
tions of the results of research, and to
presenting these results in a form useful for
decision-making and environmental educa¬
tion. I also expect that the international
scientific community will play an increasing
role in the Programme as important general,
principles concerned with land utilization;
emerge.
At the same time the Programme is likely
to maintain its characteristics of a nationally-
based international programme of research
and training, rooted in the reality of priority
problems as perceived at local and national
ievels. As such, I hope it will continue to
play a distinctive part in the overall world¬
wide effort to tackle environmental and
natural resources problems.
RALPH SLATYER, Australia's ambassador and
permanent delegate to Unesco, is president of the
International Co-ordinating Council of Unesco's
Man and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme. An
expert on resource ecology, he retains his ap¬
pointment as professor of environmental biology
at the Australian National University, Canberra.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
nature am
resources
MA J *» In r.i. i 1 H, I I , .J F
W-. «j *. ' f nii^Hi r
Unesco's science quarterly for people
who care about the environment
In every issue:
Articles by leading scientists engaged in exciting
research on man and the biosphere, ecology, hydrology,
and the earth sciences.
Information about new developments and international
programmes affecting the environment.
News about forthcoming international symposia, con¬
ferences and training seminars.
A unique and comprehensive book review section cover¬
ing publications on resource management and en¬
vironmental problems.
Published quarterly in English, French and Spanish.
Annual subscription: 30 French francs.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications Educational Supplies Pty Ltd. P.O
Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW Periodicals. Dominie Pty Subs¬
criptions Dept , P 0 Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW Sub-agent.
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St , Melbourne {Victoria), 3000
- AUSTRIA "Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31, A-
1011, Vienna BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R K Mission Rd , Haikhola, Dacca 3
-BELGIUM "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only NV Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13 - BURMA Trade Corporation No 9,550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon - CANADA Renouf Publishing
Co Ltd , 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P 0 Box 88, Peking -
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos3rd Avenue, P O. Box
1722, Nicosia -- CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S N T L, Spalena
51, Prague 1 {Permanent display), Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kemcka, Prague 1 For Slovakia only. Alfa Verlag Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR DENMARK.
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade,
DK 1370, Copenhagen K - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo - ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P O
Box 2996, Addis Ababa - FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirja¬
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10 - FRANCE
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, CCP
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G D R - FED REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish editions)
Mr. H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse
57, D53O0 Bonn 3 For other Unesco publications
Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen. For scientific maps only
Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80 - GHANA. Pres¬
byterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P O Box 195, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd , PO Box 7869, Accra, The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast, The University Bookshop of Legon, P 0. Box 1, Legon.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co , 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY Akadémiai Konyves-
bolt, Váci u 22, Budapest V; A K V Konyvturosok Boltja, Nép-
koztarsaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co , H F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ah Road, New Delhi 1 , 80/ 1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001, 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 Sub-Depots- Oxford Book & Stationery Co
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi, Publi¬
cations Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 511
C-Wing, Shastn Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardmata III,
Jakarta, Gramedia Bookshop, Jl Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta,
Indira P T , Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co , 28, Vessal Shirazi
Street, Enghélab Avenue, P O. Box 314/1486, Teheran, Iranian
Nat Comm for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No 300, B P.
1533, Teheran. - IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid
Street, Baghdad - IRELAND. The Educational Company of
Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Road, Walkmstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. ABC Bookstore Ltd , P O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby
Road, Tel Aviv 61000 - JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores
Ltd., P 0. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston - JAPAN. Eas¬
tern Book Service Inc , Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Tora¬
nomon 3-Chome, Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East Afri¬
can Publishing House, PO Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942,
Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod,
Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA Cole and Yancy Book¬
shops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia - LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tri¬
poli. LUXEMBOURG. Líbrame Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-11. MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo - NETHER¬
LANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Syste¬
men Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007 Agent for
all Unesco publications- N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout,
9, The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES Van Dorp-
EddineN.V., P.O Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao NA -NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government Books¬
hops at: Rutland Street, P O Box 5344, Auckland, 130, Oxford
Terrace, P O. Box 1721 Chnstchurch; Alma Street, P O Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P O Box 1 104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington - NIGERIA The
University Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P O 286, The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University
Bookshop of Lagos,The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana NORWAY. All publications. Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1 For Unesco
Courier only AS Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6
-- PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES The Modern
Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P 0 Box 632, Manila D-404 -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw, Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7 00-068
WARSAW - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd , Kingsgate House, P O Box 131, Mahé -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19 - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P 0 Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier {single copies)
only Central News agency, P O Box 1033, Johannesburg
-SRI LANKA Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P O B 244 Colombo 2 - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, PO Box 1118, Khartoum - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fntzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16 For the
Unesco Courier Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm - SWITZERLAND All publications
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236 - TANZANIA. Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, POB 9030 Dar-es-Salaam
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P 0 Box 402, Bangkok* Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok, Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
AS, Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul - UGANDA Uganda Bookshop, P O Box 145,
Kampala - UNITED KINGDOM-H M. Stationery Office, P O
Box 569, London, SEI, and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol -UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N Y. 10010 -USSR. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade, Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P O B 50-1, L|ubliana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd , 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
In partnership with nature Shaped by centuries-old irrigation techniques, these rice-terraces:
on the island of Bali (Indonesia) are an example of harmonious
balance between traditional land use practices and the natural
environment (see article page 28).
]]>
</page>
</document>
