<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074766eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
DECEMBER 1980 - 3.50 French francs
Picasso
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Self-Portrait with a Palette
In autumn 1906, when he painted this Self-Portrait with a
Palette, Picasso was 25 years old. The "Rose Period" was
behind him and he was preparing for the major break¬
through that would lead to Les Demoiselles d'Avignon (see
second colour page) and Cubism, and would trigger off the
20th century's first radical new movement in the visual arts.
The self-portrait already contains a foretaste of the world of
the Demoiselles, the great canvas he would begin a few
months later. (Note the similarity between the head of the
self-portrait and the heads of the two women in the centre
of the later painting). Schematization and deformation can
already be discerned in the small, mask-like head, the
powerful torso, and the simplicity of colour and line. The
portrait also has something of the Romanesque (Picasso
had just returned to Paris from the Catalonian Pyrenees,
where vigorous examples of Romanesque art abound). The
face, with its expression of serenity and concentration,
seems to reflect the self-confidence and determination of
an artist poised on the brink of a boundless future, all his
faculties alert for discovery and combat.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
DECEMBER 1980 33rd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian
French Hindi
Spanish Tamil
Russian Hebrew
German Persian
Arabic Dutch
Japanese Portuguese
Turkish Macedonian
Urdu Serbo-Croat
Catalan Slovene
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille Is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris!
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Braille Edition: Frederick Potter
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat,
Slovene Editions: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese Edition: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 THE DAWN OF GREATNESS
'Had he produced nothing after 1907, Picasso would still have
been one of the great masters of 20th century art'
by Vitali A. Suslov
11 THE MAN AND HIS WORK: A CHRONOLOGICAL GUIDE
by Rosa Maria Subirana
13 A WATERSHED OF MODERN ART
Painted in 1907, Les Demoiselles d'Avignon
revolutionized our vision of the world
by Santiago Amón
15 GUERNICA
A universal image of the inhumanity of war
by Josep Patau i Fahre
18 A FROZEN NIGHTMARE
by Taro Okamoto
20 PICASSO'S DISTORTIONS
'I am intent on resemblance, a resemblance more real than the real'
by John Go/ding
23 WHAT IS CUBISM?
by Giu/io Carlo Argan
29 PICASSO'S DEBT TO AFRICAN ART
by Beseat Kiflé Selassie
32 THE METAMORPHOSIS OF A BULL
34 BEAUTY AND THE BEAST
by Roland Penrose
38 PICASSO THE SCULPTOR
by Julian Gallego
41 THE MYTHICAL WORLD OF PICASSO
by Alexandre Ciricl Pellicer
47 THE ARTIST AND HIS MODELS
A mercurial, unceasing analysis of the human face
by Dominique Bozo
Cover
Seated Woman (Marie-Thérèse Walter)
1937. Oil on canvas, 100x81 cm. During the
1930s and 1940s, Picasso painted many
portraits of women, most of them of three
of the women who shared his life over this
period Marie-Thérèse Walter, Dora Maar
and Françoise Gilot. In many of these
portraits he used the characteristic device
of placing two eyes on the same side of the
face seen in profile. Unnatural as our cover
portrait may seem at first glance, it
nevertheless bears a profound resemblance
to its model, Marie-Thérèse Walter, here
transformed by the genius of Picasso into
the personification of delicacy and
tenderness.
Photo Réunion des Musées Nationaux © SPADEM 1980, Paris.
Musée Picasso, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Few men have achieved such renown or have made such
an impact on the twentieth century and its art as Pablo
Picasso, who was born almost a hundred years ago, on
25 October 1881, at Málaga in southern Spain.
His life was long and prolific. When he died in 1973 at
the age of 91 he had produced some 20,000 paintings,
engravings, sculptures, drawings, constructions and col¬
lages. But he was remarkable not only for the pro¬
digious volume and variety of his output; perhaps no
other artist of modern times has responded so intensely
and so imaginatively to events, to the changing condi¬
tions and challenges of this century.
Although after his early years in Málaga, Madrid and
Barcelona Picasso moved to France where he spent
three-quarters of his life, he always remained in his
habits, his temperament and his outlook fundamentally
Spanish (perhaps the greatest genius his country has
produced since Goya). And yet his art achieved a
universal significance, as an expression of the triumphs
and tragedies, the vitality and the restless searchings of
twentieth century man. It was nourished by many
tributariesfrom the past, including the work ofhis great
Spanish predecessors and the painters of the late nine¬
teenth century. At the same time, Picasso absorbed
many lessons from art outside the classical, European
traditionarchaic Iberian art, the art of Black Africa.
His vast work reveals not only its creator's sensitivity to
wider issues and to purely artistic problems, it also tells
much about Picasso the man. It is a compellingpersonal
record of his everyday life, his moods, his rages, and his
dilemmas. From beginning to end this man of unflagg¬
ing creative vitality embodied many paradoxes and con¬
tradictions, both in his life and in his art, yet he was
never false to himself or to his inspiration. One
distinguishing quality of this revolutionary, iconoclastic
artist was, for instance, the way in which he constantly
The dawn of greatness
'Had he produced nothing after 1907, Picasso would still
have been one of the great masters of 20th century art'
by Vitali A. Suslov
AMIDST the kaleidoscopic searchings
of the young Picasso, the canvases
of his Blue and Rose Periods stand
out as remarkable examples of purity of ar¬
tistic thought. They are infused with
humanistic ¡deals, not yet eroded by the
poison of scepticism, and imbued with a
belief in man. They are marked, too, by the
nobility of pure artistic achievement.
The Hermitage Museum in Leningrad and
the Pushkin State Museum of Fine Arts in
Moscow contain a number of magnificent
early works which are broadly representative
of Picasso's artistic strivings during those
early years.
Only works produced during the first fif¬
teen years or so of Picasso's creative activity
are represented in Soviet collections. They
reveal nonetheless all the complexity and
paradoxically of Picasso's art with' its sud¬
den and mercurial shifts of imagery, man¬
ners and style. This limited space of time
embraced his Blue, Rose and "Negro"
Periods, it witnessed his explorations in
Cubism, his passion for collages, his ex¬
periments in abstraction.
The beginning of the Blue Period is
customarily associated with Picasso's sec¬
ond trip to Paris, in 1901. On his return to
Barcelona around Christmas of that year, he
brought back with him some finished and
unfinished works which were quite different
in style from anything he had done before.
Art is born of melancholy, he now told his
friends. His paintings were filled with the
blue world of taciturn solitude, the world of
the outcasts of society the sick, the poor,
the crippled, the old.
Picasso already had a predilection for the
paradoxical, the unexpected and the discor¬
dant. The years 1900-1901 are usually re
ferred to as the "Lautrec" and "Steinten"
period to describe the influence of these two
Parisian artists on Picasso's work. And yet it
was during this second trip to Paris, where
he spent a full eight months, that Picasso
made a complete break with Parisian con¬
temporary art. In substance, form and
mood, his Blue Period was strongly inspired
by the Spanish tradition.
The new trend can be clearly seen in two
paintings of the period, The Absinth Drinker
(1901) in the Hermitage, and The Embrace
(1900) in the Pushkin State Museum of Fine
Arts. Both stand on the threshold of the
Blue Period, anticipating many of its themes
and concluding a whole period of ex¬
perimentation in which Picasso was moving
towards the attainment of his own artistic
truth.
By the time he was fifteen, Picasso was
already an accomplished "academic" artist.
Driven by an irrepressible desire for innova¬
tion, he now set out in search of his own
path amidst the tangled web of trends and
schools that characterized European art at
the turn of the century. In pursuit of this
goal, he revealed one remarkable facet of his
talent the ability to assimilate and master a
variety of artistic trends and styles.
The Embrace (opposite page) and The
Absinth Drinker (page 6) date from this period
when Picasso encountered the work of the
Paris School at first hand. The former is
highly reminiscent of Steinten the subject-
matter, the down-to-earth nature of the
characters, the rather thick application of
colour. An exhibition of Steinlen's work
then showing in Paris provided Picasso with
a wealth of material.
It was in Paris that Picasso saw for the
first time some of Van Gogh's paintings in
the gallery of the picture dealer Ambroise
Vollard. They were, he admitted later, a
revelation to him. The Embrace is marked
with a morbid tension, an aura of tragedy,
and was unquestionably inspired by
Picasso's own encounter with the tragic art
of Van Gogh. Despite an element of am¬
biguity in the scene, Picasso was trying to
give shape to an idea that he would develop
later: by drawing together in friendship peo¬
ple can shield themselves from adversity and
the hostility of the outside world.
In The Absinth Drinker Picasso was in¬
spired by Toulouse-Lautrec's scenes of Paris
café life, with their melancholic irony and
sharply defined compositional structure.
The influence of Gauguin is apparent in
Picasso's colour scheme, whose laconism
and inventiveness are suggestive of the
French painter's palette. But Picasso injects
his own dramatic tone into the picture's
fabric. The private world of solitude unfolds
before our eyes. We see a woman sitting in
a café; she is frozen in a state of torpor, cut
off from everything and everyone around
her, lost in her own world of thoughts and
memories. And yet there is a flicker of hope
in the image of this forlorn soul. The artist
believes in the strength of the human spirit.
The Embrace and The Absinth Drinker still
reveal the influence of other masters, but
the young Picasso was already begin¬
ning to speak with his own voice. The things
that troubled and tormented him now
demanded other artistic solutions. He had
slaked his early passions.
Paradoxically, as we have seen, it was in
Paris that Picasso came to this realization
and in Paris that his Blue Period, the purely
Spanish period of his art, began. The fact
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
returned to tradition, confronting time and again the
work of the great painters of the past. Another seeming
paradox: while he relished life and loved the human
body with an ogrish vitality, his depictions of the body
are characterized by brutal distortions of an expressive
power unmatched in Western art. Expression is
.. everything! his work seems to proclaim. For Picasso life
and art were one.
This issue of the Unesco Courier is devoted to this inex¬
haustible, contradictory, astonishing creative genius. It
fulfils a mandate from Unesco 's General Conference
which, meeting at Belgrade in October-November 1980,
noted the "great universal contribution made to culture
and the arts" by Picasso, and called on Unesco and its
Member States to commemorate the centenary of his
birth through various activities including the publica¬
tion of a special issue of the Unesco Courier.
that he now turned his talent to the depic¬
tion of poverty, suffering and black despair
is often attributed to the conditions of his
life during his second trip to the French
capital in 1901 and to the tragic death by
suicide of his friend Casagemas, a poet and
painter. But although it is true that Picasso
was living in extreme poverty at that time,
the springs that fed the Blue Period ran
deeper and wider.
They are to be found in the social climate
of the period, in the atmosphere of life in
Barcelona and in the outlook of Picasso
himself in those days. Barcelona was a
centre of revolutionary and anarchist ideas,
reflecting the harsh contrasts and the pover¬
ty that were features of Spanish life at that
time. All this had an impact on Barcelona life
with its impassioned discussions in clubs,
cafés and meetings. One of these cafés, the
Els Quatre Gats, had become a popular
meeting place for artists and writers since it
had opened in 1897. It was in this semi-
Bohemian atmosphere, where the spirit of
freedom and independence prevailed and
where compassion for "the insulted and the
injured" had been elevated to the status of a
moral principle, that the young Picasso
developed his fundamental attitudes
towards life.
As for Paris, it not only gave Picasso a
multitude of new artistic impressions, it also
laid bare in all its ugliness the amorality of
modern society, characterized by the
egoism of the "haves" and the bleak ex¬
istence of the "have-nots". With the cool
detachment of the truly great artist, the
twenty-year-old Picasso focussed his atten¬
tion on the city's poor. He visited hospitals,
asylums, and doss-houses, and found there v
the heroes of his paintings beggars, f
Young Girl on a Ball. 1905. Oil on canvas, 147x95 cm.
The Embrace, 1900. Oil on cardboard, 51.2x55.3 cm.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
cripples, vagabonds, the derelicts and the
outcasts of society. It was more than sen¬
timental compassion that he sought to ex¬
press in his paintings. The blue world of
silence that envelops his subjects is not
merely a symbol of suffering and misery; it is
also the world of proud solitude and moral
purity.
Two Sisters (colour page 7), which is now
a part of the Hermitage collection, was one
of the first works of the Blue Period. In it, as
in other works of that time, he looked back
to certain traditions of medieval art. He was
attracted by the Gothic, especially Gothic
sculpture and the spiritual expressiveness of
its forms. During this period Picasso also
drew close to the tradition of Spanish art.
He visited Toledo where he "discovered" El
Greco; shortly before, he had come upon
Luis de Morales in the Prado in Madrid. In
their works he found a psychological ex¬
pressiveness, a symbolic use of colour,
sharply delineated forms, and an ennobling
spirituality of figures, all of which were in
harmony with his current mood and artistic
experiments. It was probably in the natural
order of things that Picasso first felt impelled
to steep himself in French art and reinterpret
it before returning to his native sources and
trying to resurrect the ancient Spanish
tradition.
Two Sisters is, in all respects, highly
representative of the Blue Period. Picasso
constructed his picture in the manner of a
bas-relief, striving for a balance in the fusion
of the figures of two women set against a
blue abstract background. In the two timidly
inclined, almost embracing figures can be
seen the melancholy of suffering, silent ac¬
quiescence, unspoken affection and all-
forgiving ness. If a musical analogy is per¬
missible here, it is a Requiem that comes to
mind. The cares of everyday life, the
troubles and misfortunes of the earthly
world pale before the grandeur of the eter¬
nal, of the universal. It is not surprising that
Two Sisters has been likened to the New
Testament parable of Mary and Elizabeth.
In the polyphonic construction of Two
Sisters, the theme of the friendship of two
beings as a safeguard against the misfor¬
tunes of life and the hostility of the world is
heard once again. It would occupy an in¬
creasingly prominent place in Picasso's later
work.
Another typical Blue Period picture in
Soviet collections is The Old Jew (illustration
page 10). It belongs to the series of works
whose subjects are beggars, blind men and
cripples. Here the artist seems to be pointing
an accusing finger at the world of the pro¬
sperous and the complacent, the money¬
bags and the philistines. Picasso wanted to
see his heroes as bearers of truths hidden
from the grasp of ordinary men and accessi¬
ble only to man's inner vision and inner life.
It was no accident that most of the subjects
of the Blue Period seem to be sightless and
faceless. They live in their own internal
world, their slender nervous "Gothic"
fingers do not recognize the external form
of objects, they grasp their secret inner
meaning.
In the spring of 1904 Picasso settled for
good in the French capital, in Montmartre.
With his move to Paris, his Blue Period
came to an end. Delicate tones of pink now
began to pervade the monochromatic blue
of his canvases, soon becoming their domi¬
nant hue. Thus began the "Rose Period".
Below, The Absinth Drinker or The Aperitif, Paris,
1901. Oil on canvas, 73x54 cm.
But much more than a simple change of col¬
our was involved in Picasso's new depar¬
ture. This period is also sometimes called his
Circus Period, a description that more aptly
conveys its content. For Picasso's canvases
now entered an entirely new world, the
world of wandering actors and circus
performers.
There is no single explanation for this tur¬
ning point in Picasso's work. Many factors
were involved, including the versatility of his
effervescent talent, the conditions of his life
and the influence of his surroundings.
Barcelona had ceased to be a source of ar¬
tistic stimulation and the theme of the lower
depths of society was spent. A new ethic in¬
spired him he viewed the future with hope
and was imbued with faith in man. The loyal
Fernande Olivier went to live with him in his
studio. Among his new friends were such
outstanding figures as the poets André
Salmon and Guillaume Apollinaire. It is
worth noting in passing that by this time
Picasso had read widely in modern French
and Spanish literature and had even taken
an interest in Russian literature (Turgenev,
Gorky).
His Parisian friends introduced him into
the literary circles of the city and drew him
into the Bohemian life of the artists and
poets of Montmartre with its romanticism,
its materially uncertain but congenial at¬
mosphere where everyone was always ready
to lend a helping hand to everyone else. It
was undoubtedly Salmon and Apollinaire
who fired Picasso's interest in the circus: at
CONTINUED PAGE 9
Colour page
Top left: Two Sisters, 1902. Oil on canvas,
152 x 100 cm. One of the best-known works
Picasso painted in Barcelona during his
"Blue Period", it is now in the Hermitage
Museum, Leningrad. Top right: The
Acrobat's Family with a Monkey, Paris,
spring 1905. Gouache, watercolour, pastel
and Indian ink on cardboard, 104x75 cm.
(Göteborgs Konstmuseum, Göteborg,
Sweden). Harlequins, acrobats and circus
mountebanks were among Picasso's
favourite subjects during the "Rose Period"
(see article page 4). Bottom: Factory at
Horta, 1909. Oil on canvas, 53x60 cm.
Picasso spent the summer of 1909, right at
the beginning of the Cubist movement, at
the little Spanish village of Horta de San
Juan in the Ebro valley. Cubist techniques
are already strongly apparent in the
landscapes he painted at Horta: the
reduction of space into geometric volumes,
the breakdown of objects into basic shapes
such as cubes, and the rejection of
traditional perspective.
In the words of Guillaume Apollinaire, an
avant-garde poet and a close friend of
Picasso, who was the first to attempt to
define the Cubist aesthetic: "The striking
geometric aspect of the first Cubist
paintings is due to the fact that in them the
essential reality is expressed with great
purity and that all visual superfluities are
eliminated. Expressing this 'conceived
reality' the artist is able to achieve a cubed,
three-dimensional effect."
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
£
V /V
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE
the beginning of 1905, the three friends
became regular attenders at the Médrano
Circus.
Not that the circus and circus perfor¬
mances became the subjects of Picasso's
works. What interested him was the per¬
former, the circus artist as a creative per¬
sonality, the classic members of a travelling
troupe the acrobats, the clowns, the harle¬
quins. They are usually depicted outside the
ring, in everyday life, in their families; on
rare occasions, they are shown rehearsing.
They are always dressed in their circus
costumes, which sets them off from other
members of the human family.
For Picasso, a travelling troupe of actors
was a fraternity of free spirits, bound by ties
of deep affection, leaving no place for self-
seeking or duplicity. Together they shared
their good luck and misfortunes. And
Picasso felt himself to be a part of this
world. In The Harlequin with a Glass, we see
him dressed as a harlequin, seated pensively
at the bar among the habitués of a café. A
harlequin or jester he may be, but it is he
who senses the drama of life and feels the
brunt of the days to come.
Picasso keenly, even morbidly, felt life's
contradictions and the conflicts of his times.
He realized how fragile and illusory was the
world of his clowns and mountebanks, lost
as it was in the confusion of the vast real
world. The artisfs anxiety was reflected in
the sadness and weariness delicately im¬
printed on the face of his heroes. His major
Rose Period compositions. Travelling Actors
and Actors at Halt, graphically convey a
mood of great uncertainty and anxious
anticipation.
For Picasso, happiness and harmony
were attainable only in the bosom of the
family. In a series of works which may be
classified under the general title of "The
Harlequin's Family", he developed his own
version of the Holy Family, where the
warmth of love and the tenderness inspired
by love for children provided a haven from
the harsh realities of life.
Another leitmotif of Picasso's early works
was faith in the goodness of human nature.
This became the dominant theme of the
Rose Period, in an affirmation of belief in
friendship between two creatures in which
one who is strong and experienced protects
and succours another who is weak and
defenceless. It may be the friendship bet¬
ween an old, worldly-wise clown and a
callow youth; between a robust athlete and
a delicate young girl acrobat; between a
man and an animal, as in Boy Leading a
Horse {illustration page 10).
The Young Boy with a Dog (in the Her¬
mitage) belongs to this period. It is painted
in soft, warm, pink tones with the simplicity
and sobriety of form that characterized his
work between 1905 and 1906.
Another important work of the Rose
Period in Soviet collections (in the Pushkin
Museum of Fine Arts) is the Young Girl on a
Ball (illustration page 5). It provides a
brilliant example of Picasso's verve. The
composition and rhythmical structure of the
picture is built on the creative juxtaposition
of contrast and balance, which ensures the
dramatic unity of the whole: a powerful
athlete and a frail young girl, a massive block
and a slippery ball; the solid, thickset figure
of a man sitting on the block and the slender
Colour page
Les Demoiselles d'Avignon (literally "the Young Ladies of
Avignon"), Paris, spring-summer 1907. Oil on canvas, 244x233
cm. With Guernica, this is Picasso's most famous work. The title
was not the artist's own; it was invented later by his friend the
French writer André Salmon, in a joking allusion to the denizens
of a notorious street in Barcelona, the Carrer de Avinyó (Avignon
Street). The painting was not exhibited until 1937, and was only
reproduced for the first time in 1925. But while hidden from the
public gaze, it exercised a compulsive fascination on those who
had an opportunity to see it and acquired a legendary reputation.
In painting it, Picasso made the decisive step which would lead
to Cubism, the first great revolution in 20th-century art. From
then on, in complete mastery of his talents, he drew at will from
the past whatever could be used to serve his own creative
purposes. Among the influences and sources of inspiration which
meet in Les Demoiselles, specialists have drawn attention to that
of archaic Spanish (Iberian) sculpture, with its ruthless
deformation of the face. (While working on Les Demoiselles
Picasso had two Iberian sculptures in his studio). Also discernible
are certain features typical of the Fauve ("Wild Beast")
movement, which Picasso may have borrowed from leaders of
Fauvism, his friends Matisse and Derain. Some writers have also
stressed the influence particularly in the two heads at right of
painting of the African masks Picasso saw in 1907 at the
Trocadero ethnographic museum (see article page 29). Les
Demoiselles d'Avignon initiated a new kind of pictorial
representation. In it the forms have been disrupted and then
reassembled according to an angular, oblique structure which
confounds all the tenets of naturalism. The faces do not claim to
be naturalistic likenesses; they have become signs or symbols of
faces. With Les Demoiselles Picasso demolished centuries-old
traditions and conventions, and created an image that epitomized
modernity. In spite of the apparently trivial subject which initially
inspired it. Les Demoiselles d'Avignon was a prophetic work, far
ahead of its time.
wisp of a girl swaying like a straw in the
wind. Take away a single element from the
picture and the whole edifice crumbles:
without the athlete, the girl loses her
balance; without her precarious instability
the athlete collapses under his own massive
weight.
The Young Girl on a Ball is full of associa¬
tions and metaphors. The figures of the girl
and the athlete, in their contrasts and con¬
vergences, conjure up associations of the
unity and contrariety of the various prin¬
ciples existing in nature, life and man. The
picture also evokes other associations that
go back to the symbolism of the Middle
Ages. The athlete is reminiscent of the
allegory of Valour; the young girl on a ball,
of that of Fortune.
The picture foreshadows a new trend in
Picasso's artistic thought his interest in
classical simplicity of line, symmetry and in¬
ternal harmony. Painted at the close of 1905,
Young Girl on a Ball lies at the source of his
first Classical Period when he became ab¬
sorbed in the art of antiquity, especially
Greek painted vases.
Nothing was more natural for him than to
turn to clear-cut, harmoniously pure and
vigorous pictorial forms, motivated as he
was by a belief in the goodness and ra¬
tionality of man. This explains the flawless
perfection of the physiques of the young
boys and girls portrayed in his works of
1906. Nude, strapping youths spring forth
from the canvas, giving expression to the ar¬
tist's vision of an ¡deal world in which people
are free and proud.
No sooner had Picasso struck out on this
new path than he abruptly abandoned it. It
was as if his strength had failed him, his
faith waned and disillusionment set in. On
his return to Paris in the autumn of 1906
after spending the summer in the Spanish
village of Gósol, he began painting Les
Demoiselles d'Avignon; he completed it the
following year.
It marked the emergence of a new and dif¬
ferent Picasso. He seemed to have begun
his descent into the primeval chaos of the
dawn of creation, where good was in¬
distinguishable from evil, and ugliness from
beauty. It is doubtful that Picasso himself
knew where he was heading at the time; he
was carried away by an irrepressible and all-
consuming passion to discover the truth,
the passion of the experimenter in search of
a mode of pictorial expression in keeping
with his times.
Regardless of the attempts that have been
made to differentiate the "real" Picasso
from the "unreal" Picasso of the Blue and
Rose Periods, it was during those early years
that the fundamental ethical principles of his
art, his moral criteria, his humanistic ideals
and the major themes of his works took
shape. When all is said and done, had
Picasso produced nothing after the year
1907, he would have still been one of the
great masters of the art of the twentieth
century.
VITAD ALEXANDROVICH SUSLOV, Soviet
art historian, is deputy director of the Hermitage
Museum, Leningrad, and Vice-President of the
International ; Council of Museums (/COM). A
specialist in the history of the art of Russia and
Western Europe in the late 19th and early 20th
century, and in questions of museology, he is the
author of many published works. '
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Picasso, Perception and Blindness
The allegory of the blind man, as Sir Roland Penrose has pointed
out, "pursued Picasso throughout life as though reproaching him
for his unique gift of vision". It is especially prominent in the work
of his early years as a painter in Barcelona, where he found many
models for his studies of the blind and produced such moving
paintings as Celestina (below left), and The Old Jew (above right)
in which the boy's keen dark eyes contrast so strongly with the
dead eyes of the old man (see also drawing with blind Minotaur,
page 36). For Picasso, seeing an object was not enough; other
faculties of the mind, the "inner eye" of the imagination, had to be
brought into play if perception was to lead to true understanding.
Boy Leading a Horse (below right) has been viewed as an
expression of this Picassian metaphor of the artist endowed with
"inner sight", a magician and guide with magnetic powers. Above,
Picasso photographed in 1904 in the Bateau-Lavoir, the Montmartre
building inhabited by painters and poets where he had a studio.
The Old Jew, Barcelona, 1903. Oil on canvas, 125x92 cm. Celestina
or The One-Eyed Woman, Barcelona, 1903. Oil on canvas,
81 x 60 cm. Boy Leading a Horse, Paris, 1906. Oil on canvas
220.3x130.6 cm.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The man and his work
a chronological guide
by Rosa Maria Subirana
Early years
25 October 1881: Pablo Ruiz Picasso born at Málaga in southern Spain, the
son of José Ruiz Blasco and Maria Picasso López. Don José, a painter,
teaches drawing at the School of Fine Arts and Crafts. Eager to emulate his
father, Picasso when very young produces drawings remarkable for their
sureness of line and extraordinary powers of observation.
1 891 : The family moves to La Coruna on the Atlantic coast, settling there for
four years. Pablo's career as a painter begins in earnest. His gifts are so
astonishing, his accomplishment is so great that, according to a story told by
Picasso in adult life, his father was so overwhelmed by the superiority of his
son's talent that he gave him his own palette and brushes and declared that
he would never paint again.
1895: Don José obtains a teaching post at Barcelona. That spring the family
visits Málaga, stopping at Madrid where Pablo sees for the first time pain¬
tings by the great masters in the Prado Museum. Although under age, Pablo
enrolls at the Barcelona School of Fine Arts (popularly called La Lonja).
Makes friends with Catalan fellow artists including Manuel Pallares and
Josep Cardona. Notable works from this period are The First Communion
(1896) and Science and Charity (1897). Each is rigorously "academic" but
shows the artist's wonderful precocity.
1897: The family sends Picasso to study at the Royal Academy of San Fer¬
nando in Madrid, but he spends his time wandering through the city streets
and visiting the Prado.
June 1898: Visits Horta, in the Ebro valley, a place which will be of great
significance in his work. On his return, settles in Barcelona. He soon feels at
home in the city where he frequents the modernist café Els Quatre Gats, a
focus for the most advanced artistic and intellectual trends of the time.
February 1900: Holds his first exhibition, at Els Quatre Gats, showing draw¬
ings and sketches of his friends.
October: Picasso and his friend Casagemas leave for Paris. Picasso en¬
counters the latest developments in art through the works of Toulouse-
Lautrec, Degas, Cézanne, Van Gogh, Bonnard... The results of the first visit
to Paris include The Blue Dancer and Le Moulin de la Galette.
The Blue Period
December 1900: Picasso leaves Paris for Barcelona and then Málaga.
January 1901: Back in Madrid, he founds the review Arte Joven with a
Catalan friend. Returns to Barcelona at the year's end. The style of his work
changes. This is the beginning of the "Blue Period", during which blue is the
dominant colour in his paintings of the poor and underprivileged.
Autumn 1902: After a brief visit to Paris, Picasso again returns to Barcelona.
Blue begins to dominate in the works inspired by the death of his friend
Casagemas, culminating in La Vie, which he painted in 1903 together with
The Abandoned, Celestina and The Old Guitarist. (For this period see article
page 4).
Montmartre and the Rose Period
April 1904: Picasso leaves Barcelona for good and settles in Paris. Moves in¬
to the famous Bateau-Lavoir ("Laundry Barge") building in Montmartre.
That autumn meets Fernande Olivier with whom he will share his life until
191 1 . Pink colours begin to dominate his work during what has been labelled
the "Rose Period". The subjects also change: Picasso turns from painting
the poor and destitute and finds inspiration in circus performers (harlequins,
acrobats, tumblers). Outstanding works from this period are: The Family of
Saltimbanques, The Death of Harlequin and Family of Acrobats with
Monkey (all painted in 1905). (See article page 4).
Les Demoiselles d'Avignon and Cubism
1906-1907: Picasso's painting undergoes a fundamental change. The Portrait
of Gertrude Stein displays an Intensification of formal elements. The Self-
Portrait with a Palette of 1906 is treated along the same lines (see page 2).
1907: After many preparatory sketches and studies, produces Les Demoi¬
selles d'Avignon, a transitional painting of major importance, in which
Picasso concentrates on the essential formal elements, the structure, of the
object. This is the starting point of Cubism. (See article page 13).
Picasso meets Georges Braque with whom he collaborates in founding and
developing Cubism. Inspired by the work of Cézanne, Picasso paints still-'
lifes in which the forms are simplified and geometric.
From 1909, Picasso explores the possibilities of Cubism in increasing depth.
This stage has been called analytical Cubism to distinguish it from synthetic
Cubism which came later (See article page 20).
Spring 1909: Picasso returns to Horta where he paints his first Cubist land¬
scapes (see colour page 7). Applies the Cubist approach to portraits in which
the image is broken up into a disjointed series of planes. Examples include
Head of a Woman (1909) and the 1910 portraits of his friends and dealers
Kahnweiler, Vollard (colour page 26), and Uhde.
During the period of synthetic Cubism Picasso abandons the fragmentation
of volumes and introduces plain colours and elemental forms.
Winter 1912: Makes his first collage using pieces of paper and newspaper
cuttings. Notable works from this period are Portrait of a Young Girl and
Playing Cards, Glasses and Rum Bottle (Vive la France).
1914: The outbreak of the First World War finds Picasso in Avignon with Eva
Gouel, Fernande Olivier1s successor as his companion. He returns to Paris in
late October.
Theatre and the Classical Period
1916: The young French writer Jean Cocteau persuades Picasso to collabo¬
rate with him and Erik Satie in a production for Serge Diaghilev/'s Ballets
Russes. Picasso designs the drop curtain, decor and costumes for the
ballet. Parade.
1918: Marries Olga Koklova, a ballerina with the Ballets Russes. A son,
Paulo, is born to the couple in 1921. During this period Picasso produces a
series of "sculptural paintings" strongly marked with classicism. Most repre¬
sentative work in this new style is Three Women at the Spring, 1921 (See
colour page 26).
Surrealism and sculpture
1924: Picasso is connected with the Surrealist movement but keeps his
distance from it. He and the young Surrealists agree on the fundamental
principle that art expresses what nature cannot express. But there are major
differences between them: Picasso, according to the Surrealists, is too
attached to the external world, to the object, and too remote from the world
of dreams.
1925: Picasso initiates a new type of abstraction, incorporating the discov¬
eries of the Cubist period. Examples include: The Dance (see colour
page 27), The Milliner's Workshop (1926) and the Seated Woman (1927).
Renewed interest in volume and mass brings a new preoccupation with
sculpture (See article page 38).
Guernica
1935: Picasso's marriage with Olga breaks up. His current companion,
Marie-Thérèse Walter, gives birth to their daughter, Mai'a. This is a difficult
and anxious period of Picasso's life.
1936: The Spanish Civil War breaks out.
1937: Produces the aquatints and etchings Dream and Lie of Franco and,
above all, the great mural Guernica (see article page 14).
The Second World War
1939: Picasso moves to Royan, near Bordeaux, where he paints a series of
colourful landscapes. During the Occupation, returns to Paris and shuts him¬
self away to work in his studio. From this period dates a series of images of
seated women, especially his new friend Dora Maar (see colour page 28).
Becomes Interested in lithography. Meets Françoise Gilot, who will bear him
two children, Claude and Paloma.
5 October 1944: After the liberation of Paris, the newspaper L'Humanité
announces that Picasso has joined the Communist Party. This political com¬
mitment will later inspire three major works, in 1951 and 1952: Massacre in
Korea, War and Peace (see article page 41).
1949: In response to a request for a work on the occasion of a World Peace
Congress in Paris, chooses a lithograph of a dove which he has done in
January. This is the "Dove of Peace" which will become world famous.
The Meninas and the Mediterranean
1950: Picasso presents a cast of the sculpture Man with Sheep to the French
village of Vallauris on the Mediterranean, where he had begun to produce
ceramics three years before. Paints paraphrases of earlier pictures: Women
on the Banks of the Seine, after Courbet (1949) and Portrait of a Painter,
after El Greco (1950).
1 957: Paints a series of variations on Velazquez's The Maids of Honour (Las
Meninas) (see article page 41). Interrupts compulsive work on the Meninas
to amuse himself by painting the pigeons he can see from his window. His
canvases are infused with the light and colours of the Mediterranean.
Last works
1961: Picasso marries Jacqueline Roque and in June they move to what will
be his last home, the villa of Notre-Dame-de-Vie at Mougins in the hills above
Cannes.
February 1963: Picasso works obsessively on the theme of "the painter and
his model" and by the end of the year has completed fifty canvases. In these
works Picasso calls in question the role of the painter, introduces us into his
private world, and shows us his struggle to capture the essence of his work.
March-October 1968: Produces a series of 347 engravings culminating in a
group of erotic scenes. Three years later makes another series of 156 en¬
gravings on this and other themes.
1972: The last self-portrait.
8 April 1973: Death of Pablo Picasso at Mougins; he is buried in grounds of
his château of Vauvenargues near Aix-en-Provence.
ROSA MARIA SUBIRANA is director of the Museo Picasso, Barcelona. A
Unesco consultant and a former professor at the University of Barcelona,
she is also a member of the executive council of the International Committee
of Modern Art Museums of the International Council of Museums (ICOM).
The Picasso Museum in Barcelona, whose collection throws an important
light on the artist's early work, was established thanks to donations by
Picasso himself (including the Meninas series), his secretary Jaime Sabartes,
and a number of private individuals, in addition to works acquired by the city
of Barcelona. '
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A watershed
of modern art
Painted in 1907, Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon revolutionized our vision
of the world
by Santiago Amón
THE break with the traditional order
which Pablo Picasso deliberately
provoked in 1907, as he created with
firm, confident brushstrokes ¿es
Demoiselles d'Avignon, ushered in a new
order whose consequences have shaped the
modern environment. With Picasso began
the development of a new sensibility, a new
capacity for appreciation. A fresh way of
seeing the world and a new appraisal of
man's history came into being.
There is something which is often
overlooked by those who still contest today
the merits and validity of Picasso's art.
Wherever they may happen to be in
lecture-room or living-room, in cafeteria,
supermarket or airportwhen they repeat
the derisory charge that Picasso came into
the world with the mission of ridiculing his
fellow men, their surroundings have been
designed and constructed in accordance
with principles which can in one way or
another be traced back to Picasso. Did not
the great modern architect Le Corbusier
acknowledge that he owed all his architec¬
ture to one of Picasso's still-lifes?
The French writer Jean Cassou once
declared that the name Picasso is a symbolic
target for all the astonishment and indigna¬
tion that the general public feels about
modern art. The truth is, however, that the
public is neither astonished nor indignant.
The ranks of the indignant are led by those
who regard modern art, and its symbol
Picasso, as the deathknell of a past which,
they hoped, would go on for ever, and as
evidence that there can be no return to a
moment in time when, they hoped, the on¬
ward flow of history could have been halted.
This apparently childish attitude merits
closer inspection. Why should the op¬
ponents of modern art be so indignant? Why
should they curse the name of its founding
father? The answer is that modern art (and
its symbol Picasso) has so brilliantly and in¬
exorably achieved recognition. . Mean
while, the feelings of its opponents have
been aroused by the use of ways of think¬
ing, of forms and structures which made it
impossible, not only for them to return to
the glorious past but even to look back on
that past with nostalgia. And all the force of
their loathing was showered on Picasso's
head because they knew only too well that
the battering ram which had opened up this
irreparable breach in the wall of history was
the genius from Málaga.
There can be no doubt about the fact that
modern art is in tune with other aspects of
reality in the contemporary world. This har¬
mony came into being, the new art put its
finger on the pulse of contemporary history
for the first time, when Picasso painted Les
Demoiselles d'Avignon. From then on the
new relationship was fostered and
developed through the bold actions of a
handful of pioneers.
These artists of the recent past Picasso
and those associated with him possessed
E
©
| Photo © Edward Quinn, Nice. From Picasso de Draeger, 1974 2 Photo Giraudon © SPADEM 1980, Paris
Philadelphia Museum of Art. A.E. Gallatin Collection
3 Photo Giraudon © SPADEM 1980, Paris
Museum of Modern Art, New York.
Lillie P. Bliss Bequest
"The aim was to demolish the old image of man ... and Picasso
chose to begin with his own features". In the central figures of
¿es Demoiselles d'Avignon he mirrored his own gaze. Above,
details from (1) photo of Picasso taken in 1955 when he was aged
74; (2) the Self-Portrait of the Painter with a Palette of 1906 (see
p. 2); and (3) the central figure of ¿es Demoiselles d'Avignon of
1907 (see colour page 8). Left, Picasso photographed in 1949
"drawing" a Centaur in the air using a flashlight.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
.an uncanny prescience (Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon was painted ten years before the
Russian Revolution) which enabled them to
discern the birth and expression of a new
way of living and a new reality. Gertrude
Stein insisted that it was Picasso and
Picasso alone who grasped that twentieth-
century reality bore no relation to
nineteenth-century reality, and that he came
to this realization through painting.
Picasso led the way towards the vision of
an era of rebirth, towards a fresh conception
of man and society. Nor did he lose any time
in propagating this vision through his work
as an artist.
"Death to good taste !" was Picasso's
watchword as, in a state of great excite¬
ment, he worked on Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon, perhaps the boldest and most
challenging act in the history of art. As the
painting took shape, he discovered that it
was becoming the revelation of a side of life
that had been proscribed and concealed for
centuries, of everything that was not on the
side of refinement, ornateness, ostentatious
luxury, and decorum.
This wholesale rejection of good taste
would soon be taken over by the Futurists,
the Dadaists, the Expressionists and others.
But it was made first of all by Picasso. And it
was expressed, not in some defiant
manifesto or programme, but in the
painstaking composition of Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon, a painting whose very existence
is more provocative than all the fulminatory
literature produced by the avant-garde
movements of this century.
"Picasso came into the world to give it a
jolt", wrote the Spanish poet Rafael Alberti,
"to turn it inside out and provide it with a
fresh pair of eyes". The story of his life is in
itself the history of our coming to terms with
a new world into which we have been
"transplanted", the history of our way of
seeing.
It is said that when Gertrude Stein saw an
early study for the portrait which Picasso
painted of her in 1906 she was full of admira¬
tion. Then Picasso requested ninety more
sittings. Next, after correcting and painting
out almost everything on the canvas, he left
Paris for several months, completing the
portrait on his return without any further sit¬
tings. When Gertrude Stein saw the finished
portrait she was unable to conceal either her
surprise or her well-founded misgivings
about its fidelity to her appearance.
Whereupon, according to some sources,
Picasso simply pointed to the picture and
said: "Don't worry, you will look like it one
day." This famous remark has attracted
many interpretations, but perhaps it should
be understood in its simplest terms and be
seen to possess those qualities of directness
and sensitivity, devoid of all theorizing,
which characterized all Picasso's opinions
and were the lodestar of his work.
Les Demoiselles d'Avignon is a synthesis
of all the restless searchings which can be
seen in the studies Picasso made of the
human figure throughout 1906. It expresses
a rejection of the past and illuminates an age
that has been born anew, in the form of a
group of figures, surprised out of their wits,
looking out at a new horizon. "One day you
will look like your portrait", Picasso had said
in 1906. With the Demoiselles, the following
year, that great day arrived and all previously
existing values were overturned. From that
day on, every face would have an essential
14
affinity with those of the figures in the pain¬
ting. And with that of their creator. For
Picasso had not shrunk from using his own
face in the Demoiselles, taking it to pieces
and putting it together again in the violent
upheaval that strikes the five pathetic figures
shown in the painting.
It is surprising to see, in the insulting im¬
age of the five women depicted in Les
Demoiselles d'Avignon how closely
Picasso's Self-Portrait of the Painter with a
Palette of 1906 (see page 2) mirrors the two
central figures whose gaze communicates
itself to their companions. The attitude is
the same, the eyes are identical, and the
faces and colour tones are similar. It is im¬
possible not to make the comparison.
Anyone who cares to set the features of the
Painter with a Palette, or those in a number
of other self-portraits dating from 1906 or
1907, alongside those of the two young
women occupying the centre of the scene,
is bound to reach the same conclusions.
If the aim in Picasso's mind was to
demolish the old ¡mage (imago et similitudo)
of man, it was on his own features that he
inflicted the worst possible insult an insult
which would later become an act of repara¬
tion and would usher in a new era in human
history. Picasso had no hesitation in choos¬
ing the response provided by his own
features. Where, as he embarked on his
great experiment, could he have found a
more familiar and closer face than the im¬
passive face in the mirror?
Picasso, then, is history both through
his systematic rejection of the past and
through the massive breach which Les
Demoiselles d'Avignon opened up and is still
widening in the wall of the future. Picasso
cast a pitiless eye on his own past and on his
own features; he gave equally short shrift to
the onrushing torrent of history. He was an
implacable sniper who smashed to
smithereens the windows of the past and
created from the shattered glass a new land¬
scape and a new face. Beneath the dazzling
zig-zag lines of Les Demoiselles d'Avignon
he left an image whose basic features we
should all, without exception, come to
resemble, just as he had prophesied that
Gertrude Stein would one day come to
resemble her portrait.
SANTIAGO AMON, Spanish art historian, critic
and poet, is the author of Picasso (Madrid, 1973).
He has also published a biography of Giotto anda
number of studies on modern Spanish artists.
by Josep Palau i Fabre
EARLY in January 1937, Pablo Picasso
was commissioned by the Government
of the Spanish Republic to paint a large
canvas or mural for the Spanish Pavilion at
the Paris International Exposition, which
was due to open in the late spring.
On 8 January, he produced a multiple
engraving, consisting of a single plate divid¬
ed into nine rectangular sections and con¬
taining a story or fable which he entitled the
Dream and Lie of Franco, which was clearly
meant to be a caricature. Only three features
were not treated in the comic manner the
effigy of the Republic, the bull and the wing¬
ed horse.
The same day, the artist began a second
plate, also divided into nine rectangles, only
one of which he may have filled in, while
completing two more on the following day.
The remaining six were completed after he
had painted Guernica or while he was put¬
ting the finishing touches to it. On this plate,
as on its predecessor, the central figure was
the bull, which was drawn on 9 January.
January, February and March and much
of April went by and still Picasso did not
start the work that had been commissioned.
It was as if inspiration would not come to
him or as if he could not find a suitable
theme. And then, on 26 April 1937, Nazi
bombers flying for General Franco
destroyed the Basque town of Guernica in
what has been regarded as the first
totalitarian bombing raid in history.
The London 7»r?es of 29 April and the
Paris Ce Soir of 30 April reported the event
with despatches from their correspondents
and, on 1 May, Picasso produced his first
dated sketches or drafts on the subject.
Why should he have been inspired by
Guernica rather than any other event in the
Spanish Civil War? After all, the war had
been going on for more than nine months
and the fighting on the Aragon front and in
defence of Madrid had been on a scale suffi¬
cient to arouse passions and attract
widespread interest. On 13 February
Franco's troops entered Málaga, Picasso's
birthplace. But none of these events ap¬
pears to have ignited the artist's inspiration.
What difference was there between these
actions and the raid on Guernica?
To my mind there was one obvious dif¬
ference. The fighting on the Aragon front,
the defence of Madrid, and the fall of
Málaga were all episodes in a fratricidal
struggle which Picasso may well have found
repugnant. But these were combats in
which fighting men were matched against
fighting men, however unequal the contest
may have been in military terms. Guernica
was different. The bombing of Guernica was
a flagrant display of all-powerful military
strength against a defenceless civilian
population. Picasso's reaction to this was a
moral reaction.
What stage had Picasso reached in his life
and art as he began work on this great
painting?
In the four years before Guernica, he had
evolved his own highly personal Mediterra-
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A universal image of the inhumanity of war
Guernica
At twenty minutes to five in the afternoon of 26 April, 1937, at the height of the Spanish
Civil War, bombers of the Nazi Condor Legion flying for General Franco destroyed the town
of Guernica, the historic capital of the Basque people in northern Spain. The first terroristic
bombing of a civilian population, the raid claimed thousands of innocent victims and
Immediately provoked an international outcry whose echoes have still not faded away. To
express his furious protest at this crime, Picasso turned to his art. Below, the smoke-
blackened ruins of Guernica.
nean mythology, centred on the figure of
the Minotaur which, needless to say, is
Picasso himself. He used this mythological
creature to tell us, in cryptic language, many
of the secrets of his personal and inner life.
Some of these secrets are to be found in the
engravings of the Suite Vollard. The great
Minotauromachy etching of 1935 (illustra¬
tion page 36) appears to constitute a syn¬
thesis of these developments in his work. In
that year the various matters that lay behind
the creation of this coded language finally
came to a head: he broke with his wife Olga
Koklova, and Maïa, the daughter of Marie-
Thérèse Walter, with whom he had been
maintaining clandestine relations since 1927,
was born.
Much nearer in time to the execution of
Guernica is a picture entitled Girls Playing by
the Sea (dated 12 February 1937). In it can
be seen the culmination of a process that
had begun some years before and consisted
of representing the human form in a manner
similar to bone-like structures. This
discovery, here in its full maturity, can be
regarded as the product of the coupling of
Cubism with Surrealism.
One of the problems with which Picasso
would grapple when he embarked on the
Guernica mural was the elimination of the
symbols which had previously formed the
basis of his artistic language. This was
necessary if he was to achieve a simpler,
more direct approach to nature and to feel
untrammelled in face of the tragedy which
he now proposed to represent.
Another question should be asked at this
point. Why did Picasso turn towards the
past at this crucial moment, instead of
creating a new style or method for his art?
Why did he not cast his inspiration in an en¬
tirely new mould, as he had already done so
many times before, either because of a
woman or because of an event that had af¬
fected him? To my mind, the answer con¬
firms the hypothesis that ethical motivations
outweighed aesthetic considerations. The
sense of indignation which overcame
Picasso at this time was too intense to allow
him to think in terms of style or to indulge in
meditations on aesthetics. The case of Guer¬
nica presents the problem of artistic com¬
mitment and committed art with a depth
and authenticity which it would be vain to
seek elsewhere. Picasso's attitude and the
painting itself provide an unequivocal
answer to this problem.
However, Picasso was still wrapped up in
the symbols through which he had express¬
ed his personality, for the sketches which he
began on 1 May still bear the marks of that
allusive language of which he would only
divest himself gradually and not without dif¬
ficulty. This struggle is visible in the contrast
between the bull and the horse, by which he
had initially wished to represent the Spanish
people and Fascism respectively.
In fact the horse is the only really prob¬
lematical figure; it is depicted either in a
comic or deliberately childish language, or
with an antipathetic and repulsive expres¬
sion, or else in its simplest form. Then came i
a moment when a tragic depiction of a J
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
f <î>
o.
A
/min ii
['
¡«ffiTVÎ
ra> §
Guernica, 1937. Oil on canvas, 349.3x776.6 cm. In the 1940s Picasso's vast mural was loaned,
with the artist's consent, to the New York Museum of Modern Art. But Picasso said on
several occasions that its natural home would be a Spain which had regained its democratic
freedoms. Now that these have been restored, Guernica's long exile can be brought to an
end. Early in 1981, one of the most famous paintings of our time will be moved, in
accordance with its creator's wish, to the Prado Museum in Madrid, where Picasso first
came to know the work of the great Spanish masters in the closing years of the 19th
century. There it will be exhibited with Picasso's dozens of preparatory studies and
sketches, as well as the "postscripts" which he drew later.
> horse, harking back to his youth, forced
itself upon him and supplanted his previous
projects which were not in tune with the
tragic subject. Picasso now banished sym¬
bols and produced figures that were naked
and unadorned. After all, the bull and the
horse, two animals familiar to all the people
of Spain, would be important figures in the
painting.
Even so, the preliminary sketches do not
present us with the ultimate features of the
canvas. Even sketch No. 15, dated 9 May,
which is the closest to the final structure of
16
the painting, gives no idea of the amalgam
of styles that would appear in the finished
work.
Accordingly, the mural when completed
differed from the preliminary sketches not
only because of its size (it measures 349.3
by 776.6 cm.), its proportions (the first
sketches were almost square), or the
medium of expression, but because once
Picasso stood before the canvas he assumed
his responsibilities, and became aware of
the gravity of the commission he had ac¬
cepted almost as a self-imposed challenge.
In its first stage, as we know from a
photograph taken by Dora Maar, the picture
was a vast drawing, much larger than the
previous sketches. Although it was done
with a brush it was, nevertheless, a drawing.
At this point Picasso performed a feat of
magic, summoning up his entire past as a
painter and applying it to the needs of the
moment. It might be thought that by reac¬
ting in this way he was not only failing to
create a new style but was actually
retrogressing.
In my opinion his attitude was significant
on two counts. Picasso's past was a
glorious one which had been crowned by
many victories (the Blue Period, the Rose
Period, Cubism, the papiers collés, Curvism,
and so on). He wished to give the best of
himself to the cause he was defending, and
the best he had to offer in compensation for
the holocaust of Guernica was his past as a
painter.
At this time of trial, Picasso mobilized
himself and became a soldier; as a con¬
sequence his art became totally committed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
F
j^><
cy
^>
ß
^
and his past, which had merely seemed to
be of aesthetic significance, became com¬
mitted to the present and assumed a moral
value. But this act of commitment was freely
made.
It is clear that had his previous stages of
development not existed and had they not
been the fruit of complete freedom, then
Guernica could never have come to fruition.
Not only are the problems of freedom and of
artistic commitment not contradictory; they
illuminate and support each other.
And so Picasso, through a feat almost
worthy of a magician or a demi-god, suc¬
ceeded in combining in Guernica both
realistic features, elements from his Blue
Period (which appear in the early sketches
drawn on blue paper but which, like the
Rose Period, would eventually be reduced
to a single evocative patch) and his most re¬
cent experiments in Surrealism and naive
art. Cubism and flat perspectiveless painting
are the two features which most clearly give
the work its overall unity.
Picasso abandoned the contrast between
the bull and the horse, and all the figures in
the finished work share a common
fate that of victims. However, the other
factor in the drama which had initially been
earmarked for the horse did not disappear
from the picture; it actually came to pervade
the spectacle which unfolds on the canvas
before our eyes.
For if we analyse Guernica in plastic
terms, we see that the picture is closed at
the bottom, confined at the sides, and open
at the top. Almost all the elements in the
composition contribute to the creation in
one form or another, of a large number of
gaps or openings towards the top: the bull's
horns and tail, the arms of the falling
woman, the horse's neighing, the woman
with the oil lamp.
The effect of all these elements is to give
the picture a second centre of gravity
situated outside the canvas itself, in the
place which we know to be the origin of
what is happening, the place where the air¬
craft responsible for the havoc we are
witnessing are concealed from sight. In this
sense the mural can be said to rise higher
and higher and, while it is actually rec¬
tangular in shape, its physical proportions
are psychologically counterbalanced and
even transcended by the composition's up¬
ward thrust.
An equally important mystery also calls
for explanation. How did Picasso manage to
create harmony and even a sense of unity
out of such disparate elements as realism.
Cubism, Surrealism, Curvism and papiers
collés? How is it that such a varied mixture
of styles did not result in a chaotic
monstrosity? To my mind the answer is that
Picasso's passion, the inner flame of his in¬
spiration, succeeded in fusing disparate or
even antagonistic features in much the same
way as fire at very high temperatures melts
together the most diverse materials.
It is impossible to conclude this brief
analysis of the gestation and plastic qualities
of Guernica without referring to its striking w
relevance to modern life which, in my opi- t
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
nion, makes it an even more impressive
work of art.
Sketch No. 15 of 9 May, which I believe to
be the most highly developed, as well as
Dora MaaKs photos of the first two stages
of the painting, clearly show that Picasso
originally intended to include in it an uprais¬
ed arm with a clenched fist. That fist was
significant. It meant that there would be no
divine forgiveness for what was happening
in the painting; it was an appeal for God to
take vengeance. When he painted out the
fist, Picasso did away with the idea of
vengeance and I think he did so consciously
and deliberately. In this way the work
became a cry of despair voiced by those
who were suffering the consequences of a
barbarous and unjust act of destruction; it
became Picasso's quejio, or lamentation.
Some features of the painting, the many
despairing cries which echo through it, are
the expression in plastic terms of the heart¬
rending, long-drawn-out notes of typical
Andalusian music. As I see it, Guernica is
Picasso's cante jondo, the "deep song" of
Andalusian tradition. All that was most
deeply held in the artist's cultural
background reaching back not only to his
childhood but beyond, to the times of his
ancestors rose to the surface and merged
with his past as a painter.
JOSEP PALAU I FABRE, Spanish poet,
essayist, dramatist and historian of art, was a per¬
sonal friend of Picasso, about whom he has
published several works including Vidas de
Picasso ("Picasso's Lives"), El "Gernika" de
Picasso ("Picasso's Guernica'7 anda monumen¬
tal study on the artisfs early life and work,
Picasso Vivo 1881-1907. The article published
here is a hitherto unpublished version of a paper
presented to a congress on Picasso held in the
summer of 1980 at the International University of
Santander (Spain).
I have always thought that Picasso's
work, taken as a whole, is the most
representative expression of twentieth-
century man because it englobes so many
different styles and periods, each linked to a
different form of humanity. In the modern
world people everywhere know that there
are others whose beliefs, ways of life, rites,
customs, speech, colour, and other
characteristics are different from their own.
There are only two ways of settling the
problems arising from such diversity. If each
person believes that he alone is right and
everyone else is wrong, then the outcome
must be incessant strife. The alternative is
the way of tolerance and mutual under¬
standing, based on an acceptance of the
fact that other people's ways of life are as
valid as our own, and that had we been born
in some other place or in different cir¬
cumstances then our beliefs and scales of
values might have been the same as those of
people whom we look upon as enemies or
antagonists. I believe that Picasso's work is
a response to this diversity and that as far as
possible it embodies human differences and
contradictions.
Since Guernica is clearly a summing up of
Picasso's past as an artist, the diversity of
styles and periods which it displays is a
lesson that the most diverse and an¬
tagonistic ways can coexist and shape each
other. Guernica is therefore not only a war
picture: it is a picture that preaches human
coexistence. And bearing in mind the
creative process which produced it, its
message seems to be that such coexistence
can only be achieved by deploying the same
strength and passion with which Picasso
achieved a coherent work of art. The name
of that passion is love, for it was love for
those who had suffered, for those who had
been so brutally destroyed, that drove him
to paint his most immortal work. H
A frozen nightmare by Taro Okamoto
IT is my conviction that the essence of art
is to release uncompensated vitality in
all directions, to challenge and struggle
against the routine and the commonplace.
One should never be content with the status
quo. The life of man is, from the beginning,
violently torn asunder. We must confront this
tragic destiny and with creative intensity make
a noble one.
I remember how awestruck I was, when, at
the World Exposition of 1962, I came suddenly
face to face with Picasso's Guernica. By its very
nature it brought vividly flooding back to my
mind all my own innermost convictions.
The canvas is filled with people screaming,
writhing, crying, exploding. A horse is convuls¬
ed in the last agonies of death. I was over¬
whelmed by the shuddering tension of this
almost monochrome vision.
The world knows Guernica as the indignant
Picasso's message to the world, his scathing
denunciation of the massacre of civilians in a
small Spanish town, indiscriminately attacked
by Nazi bombers. Guernica will live in
the history of world art as a model of angry
denunciation.
Yet the shock I felt at that time was more
than simply astonishment and horror, or even
human outrage. I was struck rather by the ar¬
tistic expression itself, which explodes across
the surface of the work in an unmistakable pas¬
sion of rage.
Amid this graphic explosion, the painting as a
whole evokes an uncanny tranquillity. A naked
light bulb hangs from the ceiling and within the
confines of what seems to be an ordinary
domestic interior tragedy appears as a frozen
nightmare. To the left of the picture a bull is
seen in profile. His cold look of indifference
seems to underline the power of brutal
callousness; there is menace in his immobility.
Yet at the same time there is a romantic ele¬
ment, an expression and a movement which
seems to be bursting out beyond the bounds of
the picture, destroying all repose. To the right,
a woman, thrusting up both hands and crying
out, forms an inverted triangle. A horse neighs,
its head thrown back. The arms and legs of the
fallen stretch out toward the outside as if trying
to reach beyond the picture.
With its forceful dynamism and heartless,
austere stillness it is a calculated composition,
uplifted and elaborated to the point of insanity.
Its silence evokes terrible screams, and the
void. Opposites brought together in the com¬
position produce a fearsome sense of tension.
Challenge is essential in art. Art is omni¬
directional, unconditional attack. Compositions
that compromise so that they will find favour
with the public and an easy acceptance cannot
be called art. I recoil when faced with the kind
of work which is labelled "a good picture", a
"Picture" with a capital "P", with paintings
that are merely displays of talent, of facile
virtuosity.
But every time I see Picasso's works I am im¬
pressed, because here is a man who, while
possessing talent and incomparable skill, is able
to transcend these very attributes. "I am saved
because normally I draw so poorly", he
declared, and the calm assurance with which
he challenges both himself and others is the
true measure of his greatness.
TARO OKAMOTO, Japanese painter and
writer, became a leader of the modern art move¬
ment in Japan in the late 1940s. His works have
been exhibited in Paris, New York and at the
Venice Biennale. Among his major works are
eleven monumental ceramic frescoes at the
prefecture in Tokyo and the "Sun Tower" at the
Osaka International Exposition (1970).
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Work on Guernica was still at an early stage when it was photographed, above, by Dora Maar in
Picasso's Paris studio in the Rue des Grands Augustins. The artist would make important changes
before the work was finished (see previous double page). Woman with a Dead Child, below, is a
study Picasso made on 9 May 1937 while working on Guernica. In the completed mural she is
seen, her eyes apparently transformed into tears, beneath the head of the bull at left. She has
been described by the French philosopher Roger Garaudy as "the universal emblem of suffering
humanity". In spite of its title, Picasso's great mural is neither the "anecdotal" representation of a
historical event, nor an allegory, but the outcry of art against inhuman violence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
2 3
Two Nudes, 1906. Oil on canvas, 151.3x93 cm. Bather, 1908-1909. Oil on canvas, 130 x 97 cm.
Picasso's distortions
by John Golding
WHEN asked about his relationship
to Surrealism, Picasso replied: "I
attempt to observe nature, always.
I am intent on resemblance, a resemblance
more real than the real, attaining the sur¬
real. It was in this way that I thought of
Surrealism...".
In his attempt to achieve the sort of
hyper-reality he sought for in his art Picasso
resorted to an infinity of devices. Occa¬
sionally, for example, he rendered his sub¬
jects with a detailed precision that by com¬
parison ;can make the products of the
camera look somehow unfocussed and ap¬
proximate. At other times he exaggerated
tonal contrasts of light and dark to achieve
compellingly dramatic effects. But mostly he
was to achieve the "more real than the real"
through his use of expressive distortion by
altering the natural appearances of objects,
and above all of the human body, in order to
jolt the spectator out of conventional modes
of perception and into a new and heighten¬
ed awareness of the visual world. In none of
20
his subject matter is this more marked than
in his treatment of that most traditional of all
themes, the female nude.
Picasso's use of distortion makes an ap¬
pearance instantly in his earliest works, in
the sketches (often characterized by
cartoon-like exaggerations) which he was
executing for his own amusement, whilst
simultaneously demonstrating his talents as
an infant prodigy in the more academic
studies produced at the succession of art
schools he attended. But it was in 1906, and
significantly enough after a period when
Picasso had been studying the art of
classical antiquity and openly acknowledg¬
ing its influence in his work, that the distor¬
tions in his figure pieces become so extreme
as to become in a sense the very subject-
matter of his art.
The culminating work of this particular
period of formal experiment and unrest was
the Two Nudes (illustration this page) ex¬
ecuted in Paris late in the year. Here
Picasso's art seems to be obeying two con¬
flicting impulses. On the one hand the
figures are exaggeratedly bulky and heavy,
with heads and trunks so massively weighty
that the legs have been shortened and
thickened to support them convincingly. At
the same time a very conscious attempt has
been made to stress and acknowledge the
two dimensionality of the picture plane, a
feature which had become the hallmark of
much of the most advanced painting of the
late nineteenth century: here the two nudes
seem to have been pushed forward from
behind and to spread their bulk across the
canvas support. Although the picture ap¬
pears to depict two nudes, closer examina¬
tion would suggest that we are looking at
the same figure seen twice from diametrical¬
ly opposed views, so that the spectator is
receiving information concerning the model
which is not limited to viewing it from a
single, static position.
The extraordinarily daring Bather (illustra¬
tion this page) of the winter 1908-09 shows
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Woman with a Mandolin, 1910. Oil on canvas, 187.3x61 cm Woman in an Armchair, 1927. Oil on canvas, 130.5 x 97.2 cm.
7 am intent on resemblance,
a resemblance more real than the real'
Picasso combining different views of the
figure, gained by circling it completely, into
a single image. For some five hundred years
Western painting had been governed by
Renaissance traditions which were in turn
based on scientific or single viewpoint
perspective. These conventions are here for
the first time overtly rejected by Picasso. In
the face, profile and full face views have
been combined. The far side of the figure,
its back and buttock, has been pulled
around towards the spectator and joined to
the left contour. The figure's far, right leg is
dislocated in the opposite direction and
finds its place in the same plane as what (in
a traditional rendering) should be the nearer
limb. And yet so convincing are these distor¬
tions that the effect seems surprisingly
natural.
This picture brought Picasso to the
threshold of Cubism, the first of the major
pictorial revolutions of this century, and one
which relied for its effects on the use of a
variable viewpoint and on a more conceptual
approach to its subject matter. Commenting
on African tribal art, which he had begun to
collect, the artist said he admired it because
of its "reasonable" quality, and of his own
work of this period he said, "I paint objects
as I think them, not as I see them".
Picasso's first, fully developed Cubist
manner is exemplified by a work like Girl
with a Mandolin (colour page 25, top left) of
early 1910, one of the most famous of all
Cubist ¡mages. The same distortions and
dislocations of the body that were being
used to produce the Bather of the previous
year are still in use, but here the effect is
much more subtle and harmonious. The in¬
ternal structure of the figure is rendered in
what are basically angular and geometric
shapes, arranged in complex but lucid rela¬
tionships reminiscent of a faceted sculpture
made out of a two dimensional material
such as stiff paper or tin.
The Bather had stood starkly against a
more or less bare background; here the
space around the figure has been subjected
to the same careful analysis as the figure
itself and seems to surround her in a con¬
tinuum of interlocking planes.
The Girl with a Mandolin owes its par¬
ticular appearance to the fact that it was left
unfinished; and this allows us to see that the
next step in Picasso's Cubism, a move
towards a much greater abstraction of ap¬
pearances, was still being elaborated from
drawings and studies, which although they
are distorted by post-Renaissance Western
standards, still have an immediately iden¬
tifiable subject.
And yet the treatment of the same subject
in Woman with a Mandolin (illustration this
page), painted just a few months later in the
summer of 1910, shows the artist taking
such drastic liberties with naturalistic ap¬
pearances that the concept of distortion, im¬
plying as it does the alteration or dislocation
of an accepted visual norm, seems almost ir¬
relevant; here naturalistic appearances have
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Woman Dressing Her Hair, 1940. Oil on canvas, 130x97 cm. Woman-Flower, 1946. Oil on canvas, 146 x 89 cm.
been completely reinvented and in the pro¬
cess a new pictorial language has been
created.
It has been seen that in the work of 1909
and early 1910 the structure of the human
body had been rendered in a conceptual
fashion that initially involved a certain
geometric simplification of forms; but the
subsequent analysis of its component parts
had become increasingly complex, and in¬
creasingly difficult to achieve within the
confines of a closed contour, particularly as
a mobile, multi-viewpoint perspective had
become an essential element in Picasso's
vision.
Already in the earlier Girl with a Mandolin
Picasso felt compelled at certain points to
open up the image into the surrounding
space in order to relieve the figure's inner
tensions.
In the Woman with a Mandolin this pro¬
cess has been given a new and dominant
emphasis by the total suppression of a
closed or bounding contour. Now Picasso
sketches in the composition in terms of a
linear armature suggested by the outlines of
the figure and its inner configurations. This
complex but loose linear skeleton has then
been used as the framework around which a
complex of transparent, shifting and interac¬
ting planes has been built up; this complex
suggests both the presence of a human
figure and at the same time the continuum
of space which envelops and surrounds it.
Contemporary critics and commentators
were quick to draw parallels with certain
contemporary philosophical and scientific
ideas, notably those of Bergson (who had
come to see reality as being in a state of con¬
stant change or flux), and of theories about
relativity and the fourth dimension. And
while it was certainly not Picasso's intention
to illustrate such concepts programmatic-
ally, like all truly great artists his work un¬
consciously reflected and at times an¬
ticipated the intellectual climate and
discoveries of his time.
Two years later, towards the end of 1912,
another radical innovation in Picasso's
vision and approach took place, albeit within
a style which can still be accurately
characterized as Cubist, involved as it was
with creation of images that were represen¬
tational but overtly anti-naturalistic, and
which made use of the concepts of form and
space elaborated over the previous year.
A comparison of the images discussed
above illustrates the way in which Picasso
began with a subject which was relatively
naturalistic but which became ever more
hermetic and abstract as it was subjected to
an increasingly complex analysis or
breakdown in the light of the new Cubist
attitudes to volumes and the space which
surrounds them.
Now, in the period of what has become
known as "Synthetic Cubism", the process
was reversed. Having familiarized himself
with a vocabulary of highly abstracted forms
and under the impetus of the principle of
assembling disparate elements to form a
vivid sculptural ensemble, Picasso began
building up his images in terms of shapes
and forms which because of the way in
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
which they are qualified or combined in a
pictorial context, acquire a representational
significance. Thus two circles placed at
either side of an upright linear form can
become eyes, a line of a curved gash below
is made to "read" as a mouth and so on.
The possibilities of expressive distortion in
such a method of work are obvious and
Picasso exploits them to the full in a canvas
like Woman in an Armchair of 1913 (colour
page 25, top right). Here the breasts are
rendered twice, and the upper breasts with
their peg-like nipples, strongly reminiscent
of certain conventions employed in African
art, appear to nail into place the over-size
pendulous projections below, while the
relatively naturalistic flesh-tones underline
the figure's physicality.
There is, too, a sense of displacement and
visual satire in the way in which the features
of the head, traditionally the seat of in¬
telligence and spirituality, are reduced to a
few insignificant dots and dashes, while the
breasts, stomach and even the hairs beneath
the woman's raised arm are given exag¬
gerated emphasis. The distortions in
Picasso's earlier Cubism had been at the ser¬
vice of producing a new pictorial
vocabulary. Here they are used expressively
and sardonically to produce an image which
is simultaneously witty, playful, and more
than a little threatening.
The view of woman as both sex object
and predator, hinted at here, reached its
fullest expression in the second half of the
1920s and the early 1930s. These were years
when Picasso's art shared certain concerns
common to the Surrealists and in which his
use of distortion was to be most trenchant
and extreme.
In the Woman in an Armchair of 1927 (il¬
lustration page 21) the figure's sleeping
state appears to have released her repressed
sexuality. The figure is rendered in a free,
flowing line and her body and limbs are
polyp-like and tumescent; arms and legs are
rendered by more or less interchangeable
forms, all of which are charged with phallic
overtones and from now on it is seldom in
Picasso's work that the naked female form
does not carry in her anatomy a reference to
an aggressive male partner.
A counterpart to the flaccid, languid
Woman in an Armchair is to be found in the
celebrated canvas of 1930 called simply
Seated Bather (colour page 25, bottom left).
Here the woman's face and limbs appear to
have been chiseled out of stone, and the
head, breasts and limbs are held together in
an elaborate feat of balance. In keeping with
his sculptural experiments of the time, much
use is made of negative spaces or volumes:
the stomach, for example, is here present by
its absence. The air of menace about the
figure is intensified by the fact that it is plac¬
ed against a calm blue background of sea
and sky. Her pincer-like arms and jaws and
her expressionless eyes give her the air of an
enormous praying mantis, carved in granite.
In 1932 there was a marked change which
corresponded to the appearance of a new
vision of femininity: full, passive and golden.
In works like Girl before a Mirror (colour
page 25, bottom right) of this year the
model's heavy, pliant limbs are rendered by
the same undulating forms that had
characterized much of Picasso's work since
1925, but their rhythms have become softer,
more welcoming or organic; colour, too, has
become richer and more lyrical. Here the girl
confronts her own mirrored sexuality calm¬
ly, and the tender lilacs of her face and body
have become in the reflected image deeper,
more mature; the breasts seem to have
ripened into fruit. Everywhere, even in the k
What is cubism?
ANALYTICAL Cubism [a new
method of painting evolved by
Picasso and Georges Braque
around 1909] involved presenting
simultaneously several aspects of a
single object as seen from different view¬
points. The same analytical criteria could
be applied to each and every reality and,
indeed, to thought. When Picasso later
combined in a single portrait a full face
view and a profile, he was in fact doing
just what he did in the period 1910-1912,
when he produced spatial break downs
of glasses, fruit dishes or guitars; but,
with faces, these different viewpoints
also reveal the varied, ambiguous facets
of that Protean amalgam, the human
being.
All these facets combine in one, un¬
ique form, or even in a kind of graphic
symbol; but each provides a key to inter¬
pretation, each imposes a different
"reading" of the image.
In one and the same figure are
presented simultaneously not simply
several different viewpoints, but several
different "truths", each one no less
"true" than the others. Thus it is this
ambiguity, this internal contradiction,
that distorts and breaks down the figure
and then re-assembles it in accordance
with its own true, intrinsic structure.
by Giulio Carlo Argan
Herein for Picasso lay the fundamental
error of the constructivists they sought
the structure in reason, whereas the true
structure of human beings is founded in
the irrational.
We come now to the question of the
third dimension. Anything developed in
depth impinges on our vision through an
optical illusion and, as a result, the way
is open to emotive reaction bringing into
play imagination, memory, feeling. It
was this very way that Cubism, with its
new and rigorous objectivity, wished to
close. Both Picasso and Braque resolve
the problem of the third dimension by
the use of oblique lines (indicating
depth) and curves (indicating volume),
thus transposing onto a plane surface
objects which have depth or relief. This
is where the mental factor comes in, the
ideas that the mind conceives about
objects (and this is the typically Carte¬
sian aspect of Cubism, which places it
squarely within the framework of the
fundamental rationalism of French cul¬
ture). This applies to familiar objects
such as fruit, plates, glasses, bottles and
musical instruments. Now a plate placed
on a table is seen as being elliptical in
shape, whereas we know, in fact, that it
is round; since at the mental level there
is no difference in value between what
we see and what we know, the "round¬
ness" of the plate also appears in the
painting. In other words, we grant the
same authenticity to what is in the third
dimension as we do to the measurable
values of the vertical and horizontal co¬
ordinates. As well as our notion of the
object (which we had before looking at
the picture), the time factor comes into
play; we first see the plate as elliptical in
shape and then as round, as though we
had changed its position in space or
were walking around it and seeing it
from different angles. From this it is to
be deduced that, although empirically a
single object cannot be in two different
places at the same time, in the wholly
mental reality of space (that is, as an
ordered, structured reality ¡h the mind)
the same object can exist in different
forms and, naturally, in different places.
GIULIO CARLO ARGAN, Italian art
historian, is a professor at the university of
Rome and was mayor of the city from 1976
to 1979. He is director of the review Storia
dell'Arte and the author of many essays on
art history, urban planning and methods of
criticism. The text published here is taken
from his study L'Arte Moderna 1770-1970
(Sansoni publishers, Florence, 1970).
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
patterned wall-paper, there are symbols of
growth and fertility.
A series of nudes executed during the
years of the Second World War make use of
some of the basic tenets of his first Cubist
style, evolved some thirty years earlier, to
produce images that in their sense of
claustrophobia and bestiality, recall also
some of the most unsettling and haunting
apparitions of the late 1920s and early 1930s.
However, whereas in these the female form
had been seen as threatening and at times
obscene, now she appears as both predator
and victima symbol for humanity in
anguish.
In Woman Dressing Her Hair of 1940 (il¬
lustration page 22), for example, the abnor¬
mally distented limbs, elephantine in their
solidity, create the impression of a body for
whom freedom of movement has become
virtually impossible, a sensation further em¬
phasized by the Cubistic distortions which
enable the painter to incorporate a view of
the buttocks of the figure into what is
basically a frontal view, while the figure is
simultaneously compressed into a tight,
airless space.
In complete contrast Woman-Flower of
1946 (illustration page 22) seems to
celebrate the presence of a new companion
in his life and, obliquely, nature's generative
powers: a young woman's body has been
reduced to a single delicate, stalk-like form,
supporting full breasts and a head as open
and innocent as that of a simple convolvulus
opening to the first rays of the sun. The
work is joyous and unsentimental, but it is
lent a dimension of pathos by the fact that
one senses that in it Picasso was beginning
to become aware of the discrepancy in age
between himself and the sort of model who
could stimulate his art to self-renewal.
Picasso's final manner of the fifties and
sixties was to be characterized by an ex¬
treme physicality, a feeling of furious energy
and urgency which would be remarkable in a
man of any age but which is little short of in¬
credible in the light of his advanced years.
He continued to be obsessed by the single
female form, but it was the pageant of both
art and life which had become the real sub¬
ject of his art a vast, panoramic vision em¬
bracing the past and the present, in which
historical figures, artists and philosophers,
jostle and mingle with characters and
models which had thronged Picasso's can¬
vases for over seventy years. |
JOHN GOLDING, English painter, has been
Reader in the History of Art at the Courtauld In¬
stitute, University of London, since 1977 and was
Stade Professor of Fine Art at Cambridge Univer¬
sity in 1976-1977. His published works include
Cubism 1907-1914, New York and London, 1959
(revised edition 1968).
Acknowledgments
Page 25: Photo © SPADEM 1980, Paris. Museum of Modem Art,
New York. Nelson A. Rockefeller Bequest; Photo Giraudon ©
SPADEM 1380. Paris. Mr. and Mrs. Victor W. Ganz Collection.
New York; Photos © SPADEM 1980, Paris. Museum of Modem
Art, New York. Mrs. Simon Guggenheim Fund. Page 26: Photo
Giraudon © SPADEM 1980. Paris. Pushkin State Museum of Fine
Arts. Moscow; Photo Ziolo © SPADEM 1980. Paris. Museum of
Modem Art New York. Gift of Mr. and Mis. Allan D. Emit; Photo
Giraudon © SPADEM 1980. Paris. Museum of Modem Art, New
York. Mrs. Simon Guggenheim Fund. Page 27: Photo ©
SPADEM 1980, Paris. Tate Gallery. London: Photos Réunion des
Musées Nationaux © SPADEM 1980. Paris. Musée Picasso, Paris.
Still Life with Chair Caning, 1912. Collage of oil, oilcloth and paper on canvas,
surrounded with rope, 27x35 cm. The first collage of modern painting. This
essentially Cubist technique was invented jointly by Picasso and Braque. It
involves the introduction of real objects paper, oilcloth, rags, wire and other
objects in everyday useinto the plane surface of a picture, thus breaking with
the unity of material and the element of optical illusion of traditional painting.
Following its introduction by Picasso and Braque, collage was to become a
permanent feature of modern art.
Co/our pages
opposite page
Top left. Girl with a Mandolin (portrait of
Fanny Tellier) 1910. Oil on canvas,
100.3x73.6 cm. Top right. Woman in an
Armchair, 1913. Oil on canvas, 148 x 99 cm.
Bottom left. Seated Bather, 1930. Oil on
canvas, 163.2x129.5 cm. Bottom right. Girl
before a Mirror, 1932. Oil on canvas,
162.3 x 130.2 cm. (For these paintings see
article page 20).
Centre pages
page 26
Top left. Portrait ofAmbroise Vollard, 1910.
Oil on canvas. 92x65 cm. Dating from the
early days of Cubism, this portrait
demonstrates the technique of the
systematic fragmentation of the sitter, of
objects (such as the bottle at the top left of
painting) and of the surrounding space. In
this portrait, despite its multi-faceted
fragmentation, in contrast to the
impenetrable, almost hermetic nature of
several other paintings of this period, the
resemblance with the original remains.
Picasso seems to have reversed the normal
order of things, starting with a Cubist
breakdown of space into planes into which,
in the course of a prolonged series of
sittings, he merged the sitter. Top right.
Three Women at the Spring. 1921. Oil on
canvas, 203.9x174 cm. Bottom photo.
Three Musicians, 1921. Oil on canvas,
200.7x222.9 cm. The first of these two
paintings marked the beginning of
Picasso's "classical" period; the second has
been described by Pierre Daix as "the goal
of the Cubist road". Strangely enough,
both of these works were created at the
same time, in the autumn of 1921. at
Fontainebleau, near Paris. An eyewitness
recounts that the two canvases could be
seen facing each other in the studio with
the paint from Picasso's brushes fresh
upon themample evidence of his ability
to work simultaneously in two diverse, if
not contradictory, styles. The Three
Musicians portrays three masked
characters, a pierrot playing a clarinet, a
harlequin with a violin or a guitar, and a
monk, seated at a table beneath which lies
a dog. The subject is gay, but Picasso gives
his festive trio a solemn, even sinister
majesty.
page 27
Top left. 77ie Dance, 1925. Oil on canvas,
215x142 cm. This famous canvas marked a
new chapter in the work of the ever-
inventive Picasso and inspired the French
surrealist André Breton's remark that
"Beauty has to convulse, or it is nothing".
Here can be detected the "convulsive"
surrealist inspiration which was to develop
in the second half of the 1920s and during
the 1930s. Moving far away from his recent
monumental classicism, the forms express
a frenetic movement as syncopated as the
rhythms of jazz. The faces are grotesque,
even bestial (in particular that of the dancer
to the left of the canvas), and the bodies
seem disjointed; it is as though the figures
had become dislocated in a frenzy of fury
and primitive sexuality. Bottom photo. The
Kiss. 1969. Oil on canvas, 97x130. cm.
Picasso took the kiss as the subject of
several paintings, including the famous
canvas of 1925 which was completed at
about the same time as The Dance and is
imbued with the same convulsive frenzy. In
77>e Kiss of 1969 (illustrated here), although
the impact remains powerful, there is a
sense of serenity, of the nostalgia of an
artist nearly ninety years old recalling the
days of his youth. Top right. Mother and
Child, 1971. Oil on canvas. 162x130 cm.
Picasso returns again to a theme he had
tackled many times since adolescence; it is
echoed in the tragic mother and child of
Guernica.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
! £ -
^
'
<A
r
A 4 ;l -j| P
^^^ m< , V
f *
\xS\N\wir T^aYI
1
iSv 'v^Trl \\ \
Lri i
ilBr^^tii*^ v.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Picasso's debt
to African art
by Beseat Kiflé Selassie
MM I
don't say everything, but I paint
everything," Picasso once remark¬
ed in the course of a conversation
with an old friend. And it is true that when
Picasso speaks his words tell us less than do
his paintings. In this respect he is already a
true initiate in the African sense of the word.
For the initiate in African cultural traditions
is a disciple who is sufficiently worthy and
persevering for the spirit of the ancestors to
disclose and pass on to himthrough pro¬
verbs, myths, poertis and riddles the
meaning of the symbols representing
knowledge of man and the universe.
In order to keep away laymen, non-
initiates and "blind" disciples whom the
spirits will never be able to "open" to the
"light" of knowledge or whose "ear" they
will never succeed in "piercing", the initiate,
like Picasso, must not say everything nor
"reveal" everything. The idea is to exclude
opportunists, envious or indiscreet people
who are unfit to acquire the secrets of
nature and to be admitted to the mysteries
of the essence of man and the universe.
In May 1907, during a chance visit to the
Paris Ethnographical Museum (now the
Musée de l'Homme) in the old Palais du
Trocadéro, Picasso experienced a "revela¬
tion" at his first sight of the masks of Africa,
Oceania, the Caribbean and America. Tak¬
ing this discovery as a departure point, some
working hypotheses can be advanced which
may throw new light on the different stages,
high points and itineraries in his works and
on the hidden, underground influences
which marked his prolific and varied output,
both before and after his African phases.
Colour page, left
Top left. Dora Maar Seated, 1937. Oil on
canvas. 92x65 cm. Top right. Head of a
Woman with Two Profiles (portrait of Dora
Maar), 1939. Oil on canvas, 92x73 cm. (See
article page 47). Bottom photo.
Composition with Minotaur (curtain for
Romain Rolland's play "Le 14 Juillet"). 1936.
Indian ink with gouache, 44x54.5 cm. (See
article page 34).
Several authors have already discussed in
detail the impact and lasting consequences
which the visit to the Trocadéro had on
Picasso's development, especially on the
final version of the painting Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon, regarded by art historians and
critics alike as "one of the touchstones of
20th century art". There is no need to dwell
on this further, but controversies and
disputes between different schools of
thought continue to this day as to the real
sources which inspired Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon.
Picasso himself helped to maintain con¬
fusion among critics, by denying at times
that Les Demoiselles d'Avignon, which he
claimed was painted before his visit to the
Trocadéro, had been influenced by the
African masks and sculpture. Yet all the
evidence points to the contrary. Picasso, the
initiate, did not say everything, he painted
everything. In the process, he sometimes
took a sly pleasure in creating myths, among
them the myth of Picasso, the greatest
creator of all times.
In this proclivity for "joking" he also
shows himself to be an initiate, for in African
cultural traditions the initiate knows how
much more revealing "jokes", humour and
laughter are of true knowledge than is or¬
dinary discourse. But in fact what Picasso
says, or does not say, or denies about the
sources that inspired Les Demoiselles, is not
really important. For the figure on the left
and the two figures on the right patently
recall African masks, perhaps even those of
Oceania. Besides, are we not free, indeed
bound to look at the picture differently from
the way in which Picasso claims to present
it? After all, he warned us that he paints
everything but does not say all.
Thirty years later, during a conversation
with André Malraux and the Spanish
philosopher José Bergamin, Picasso recall¬
ed his visit to the Trocadéro, "at the time he
was finishing Guernica," in 1937. In this very
important "admission" he explains what so-
called "Negro" art meant to him far better
than anyone else could do. Malraux begins
by explaining the context in which Picasso
made this statement and emphasizing its im¬
portance. Then he lets Picasso speak in his
own words: "We had talked about Spain
and about painting; he became more reveal-
ingly confidential than I have ever heard
him:
'Everybody always talks about the in¬
fluences that the Negroes had on me. When
I went to the old Trocadéro... I was all
alone. I wanted to get away. But I didn't
leave. I stayed. I understood that it was very
important: something was happening to me,
right?
'The masks weren't just any other pieces
of sculpture. Not at all. They were magic
things. The Negro pieces were in¬
tercesseurs, mediators; ever since then I've
known the word in French. They were
against everythingagainst unknown,
threatening spirits. I always looked at
fetishes. I understood; I too am against
everything. I too believe that everything is
unknown, that everything is an enemy!
Everything! Not just the detailswomen,
children, babies, tobacco, playing but the
whole of it!'"
All the elements in the cosmogony of
African arts and all the themes which stand
out as landmarks in Picasso's life's work are
contained in this statement. First the impor¬
tance of detail, for it is beneath simple
things and gestures and the banality and
triviality of each individual being's daily life
that the essence of Man and Nature is hid¬
den or revealed. In African cultural traditions
supreme knowledge is seen in humble guise.
Next women, who symbolize fertility and
the source of life, nourishing men with the
forces of the universe and of love, but who,
at certain times, can also be incarnations of
malice and evil.
Children, too, play an important role in
traditional African religions, symbolizing the
light of truth; not only the family but every
member of the community must contribute
to their education so as to create that com¬
plex "classical masterpiece" which each
child must become for the whole of society.
And lastly animals, which in African
beliefs symbolize good or evil according to
their species. They appear very early on in
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Picasso's work, as is shown by the bull in
Picador, his first known canvas, painted in
Málaga when he was eight, as well as in his
drawings of Pigeons, dogs and in Blue and
White, all produced in Málaga about the
same time, and especially in The Acrobat's
Family with a Monkey painted in Paris in
1905, sixteen years later. Such "details", in
African philosophy, make up the "sum
total" of daily existence.
For Africans art is deeply rooted in every¬
day life. This is borne out by the importance
attached to familiar objects such as cups,
gourds, stools, pottery, combs, knives,
spears and animal skins with their variety of
decorative styles. All are of practical use and
the trained initiate sees them not only as
works of art integrated into daily life; he is
also able to discern coded messages and
spiritual symbols in the distinctive patterns
decorating each individual object. This is
even more true of ritual objects, masks and
sculpture which in Europe are generally
regarded as purely decorative, whereas in
Africa they are an integral part of belief and,
as such, are not restricted to the small and
privileged circle of initiates but belong to the
whole community.
To sum up, African arts function on the
level of Being, Existence, the Universe and
man's Ideas concerning them; not on the
level of appearances as the eye perceives
them. They seek to embody Thought and
Ideas rather than their superficial, outward
representations and manifestations. This
probably is what led Picasso to say that the
"Negro" arts are "rational". "Rational" in
the sense that he found in them, instinctive¬
ly perhaps at first, but later deliberately,
thanks to his great capacity for assimilation,
a fruitful and coherent source of inspiration
which eventually led to Cubism.
The French poet René Char wrote that
Picasso's faculty of assimilation proves that
he was "naturally revolutionary in his rela¬
tionships and inspiration". By this he meant
that Picasso "created" even when he bor¬
rowed ideas, for however enthusiastic, he
never let himself be carried away. And it is a
fact that, compared with Gauguin, for ex¬
ample, who seemed to be for ever casting
about for exoticism in his revolt against the
society of his time, Picasso adopted the
stance of a revolutionary, drawing strength
wherever he found inspiration and turning
this inspiration into a new basis for discus¬
sion and a new weapon which was none
other than Picasso himself faced with the
challenge of his universe. This shows how
important the arts of Africa were to Picasso
as a springboard but only a spring¬
board the creation of more and more
original work.
The force of the African conception of art
which Picasso had assimilated so perfectly,
lies in the fact that it exists in relationship to
an everyday attitude to life which makes use
of symbols as protection against the evil eye
and the assault of "unknown", external
forces, whether of evil or of good. We are
dealing therefore first and foremost with
fetishes. This is the African approach to art
and Picasso grasped this the very first time
he came into contact with it at the
Trocadéro:
"I understood what the Negroes used
their sculpture for. Why sculpt like that and
not some other way? After all, they weren't
Cubists! Since Cubism didn't exist. It was
clear that some guys had invented the
30-
models, and others had imitated them,
right? Isn't that what we call tradition? But
all the fetishes were used for the same thing.
They were weapons. To help people avoid
coming under the influence of spirits again,
to help them become independent. They're
tools. If we give spirits a form, we become
independent. Spirits, the unconscious
(people still weren't talking about that very
much), emotion they're all the same thing.
I understood why. I was a painter. All alone
in that awful museum, with its masks, its
dolls made by the redskins, its dusty
models. Les Demoiselles d'Avignon must
have come to me that very day, but not at all
because of the forms; because it was my
first exorcism-painting yes absolutely!"
In practical terms exorcism meant that
Picasso succeeded in combining two-
dimensional perspective as used in Western
painting and a third dimension as
represented in the forms of African
sculpture. It was this combination which led
to Cubism.
Les Demoiselles d'Avignon marked the
beginning of Picasso's so-called "Negro"
period (1907-1909), which comes between
his "Blue" (1900-1904) and "Rose"
(1904-1906) periods and the birth and
development of Cubism (1909-1914).
The final version of Les Demoiselles
d'Avignon was painted at the earliest at the
end of July 1907. The first sketches of the
picture, of which there are several, were
done in April 1907. Between then and the
This specimen of the art of
Guinea's Baga people once
belonged to Picasso.
time he stopped working on the painting
Picasso experienced his "revelation" of
African masks and sculpture. Critics often
compare the compositional elements and
general theme of the first rough sketches
with Cezanne's Cinq Baigneuses, or,
because of the tones, with certain paintings
by Matisse and Gauguin. But in my opinion
we might here postulate another new
African phase in Picasso's work, one which
was marked by what I would call Arab-
Muslim influences.
In support of this theory one has only to
consider Picasso's own earlier pictures as
the first source of inspiration for Les
Demoiselles d'Avignon, in particular The
Harem, La Toilette and La Coiffure. All these
pictures were painted during the summer of
1906 in the little Catalan village of Gosol, 10
kilometres from the French border. It is
tempting to explore this theory since the
months that Picasso spent at Gosol con¬
stituted one of his last long visits to his
native country after he moved to Paris and
settled at the Bateau Lavoir. What could be
more natural than for him to draw inspira¬
tion for Les Demoiselles from his own
cultural heritage and environment in order to
maintain his identity as a Spaniard, a native
of a country at the crossroads and meeting
point of European Christian civilization and
the spiritual trends of Islam and North
Africa?
After all. Málaga, where Picasso was born
and where he spent the first ten years of his
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
life, is an Andalusian town in southern Spain
and therefore quite near the coast of Africa.
Málaga was formerly an important centre of
al-Andalus, that is, of Muslim Spain which,
for eight centuries, covered a large part of
the Iberian peninsula and which left a par¬
ticularly strong imprint on present-day An¬
dalusia. As a native of Málaga, therefore,
the young Picasso would have felt the pull
of Arab-Muslim influences across centuries
of Spanish history. His attachment to his
birthplace is attested to by the fact that he
returned from La Coruna and Barcelona to
spend his holidays there in 1895, 1896 and
1897.
This early African phase in Picasso's work
is important chronologically, but up to now
it has never properly been explored. Yet
already in 1905 Guillaume Apollinaire had
drawn attention to this source of inspiration
in the following words: "That Spaniard...
his roots are deep... they go down to the
rich composition and startling decoration of
17th century Spain... his quest for beauty
led him in many directions; he ended up
spiritually a Latin and rhythmically an Arab."
This emerges from the rhythmic tones of
the blue draperies which can be seen in the
background behind the two African women
on the right hand side of Les Demoiselles.
The draperies and rhythmic movement of
the two women in the centre of the picture,
although obviously inspired by Iberian
sculptures, also recall the women in The
Harem and Picasso's first wood carvings, in
particular Head of a Woman and Nude with
Raised Arms, which were both carved in
boxwood between 1904 and 1906, long
before his visit to the Trocadéro.
Taking into account the two African
phases before Picasso painted Les
Demoiselles, as well as the inspiration pro¬
vided by the Iberian sculptures and Spanish
environment and Spanish painting, African
art exerted an obvious influence on all his
subsequent development. On the one hand,
the themes he treated during this
period women, children and animals
(which he reinvents in symbolic form, such
as the Minotaur) are all found in his later
work. His constant preoccupation with
Thought and Ideas, rather than their outer
forms and appearance, and his more than
realistic that is surrealistic represent¬
ations of still life, all testify to the lasting in¬
fluence of African art. Mention should also
be made of his decorated ceramics which
show how art can be integrated into simple,
everyday objects, as it is in Africa.
All this can be summed up in a simple pro¬
position: by retaining and strengthening his
cultural identity as a Spaniard, instead of
allowing it to become diluted, Picasso
"rationally" assimilated African art. And so,
when we look for him in Africa, we find him
in Spain. The work of Picasso, who
"painted everything", teaches us that the
specific and the universal, human difference
and human solidarity, are but two aspects of
a simple reality which finds its synthesis only
in art. I
BESEAT KIFLE SELASSIE, Ethiopian specialist
in interdisciplinary research, lectures at the
University of Paris on problems of culture and
communication. He is the author of several
critical studies on art and artists of the Third
World, including Skunder: l'Homme et le Peintre
and An Introduction to Abstract Painting in
Ethiopia (1970).
Nude with Drapery, 1907. Oil on canvas, 152 x 101 cm.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Ist State, December 5th, 1945 2nd state, December 12th, 1945
9th state, January 5th, 1946 10th state, January 10th, 1946
Text, by Hélène Parme/in,
and photos from
Picasso Lithographs,
by Fernand Mourlot.
Editions André Sauret,
1970, Monaco.
IT happened at Mourlot's works in
1945, in the old workshops in Rue
de Chabrol, Paris. The story is told
by Jean Célestin, a craftsman who was
working with Picasso at the time and
who says of him. "He has left his mark
on me. Working with Picasso has add¬
ed something special to my life." And
he adds: "He has a feeling; he has, how
shall I put it, incredible talents... he is
gifted; he is a painter".
The story of the bull should be heard
in the huge workshops, where the vats
of ink shine, the machines turn, posters
are hung all about, the workmen bustle
at their work and the painters pass by.
"One day", said Célestin, "he started
work on the famous bull. It was a
superb, well-rounded bull. I thought
myself that that was that. But not at all.
A second state and a third state, still
well-rounded, followed. And so it went
on. But the bull was no longer the
same. It began to get smaller and to
lose weight... That same day Henri
Deschamps told me that Picasso 'was
taking away rather than adding to his
composition...' He was carving away
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
7th state, December 28th, 1945 8th state, January 2nd, 1946
V
v .
V\ ' * ' x
->J
/]P~£_
The
metamorphosis
of a bull
11th state, January 17th, 1946
slices of his bull at the same time. And
after each change we pulled a proof. He
could see that we were puzzled. He
made a joke, he went on working, and
then he produced another bull. And
each time less and less of the bull re¬
mained. He used to look at me and
laugh. 'Look Henri', he would say, 'we
ought to give this bit to the butcher.
The housewife could say I want that
piece, or this one...' In the end, the
bull's head was like that of an ant." And
to conclude the story of the bull
Célestin said: "At the last proof there
remained only a few lines. I had watch¬
ed him at work, reducing, always
reducing.
"I still remembered the first bull and I
said to myself: What I don't understand
is that he has ended up where really he
should have started! But he, Picasso,
was seeking his own bull. And to
achieve his one line bull he had gone in
successive stages through all the other
bulls. And when you look at that line
you cannot imagine how much work it
had involved..."
"There are paintings in which there
seems to be nothing, yet which contain
everything", said Corot. And the pro¬
gression to the bull is typical of this.
Each state has its meaning and each of
these meanings leads towards another
form of truth. What remains carries all
the range of thought we imply when we
say the word "bull".
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Beauty and the beast
by Roland Penrose
DURING his long and intensively active
life Picasso produced works which
were acclaimed even by those most
hostile to his disquieting inventions as
masterpieces of undeniable beauty, and yet
there are those who accuse him of being a
destructive and evil influence, a trickster or
mocking demon rather than an artist intent
on quickening our appreciation of the
richness and diversity of human experience.
At an early age he became conscious that
we find ourselves surrounded by both
demons and angels radiating ugliness and
beauty. This is evident in his first drawings
seen at the Museo Picasso in Barcelona of
misery in the streets, battles and matadors
gored by bulls which hang next to tender,
truthful paintings of flowers, landscapes and
the female form.
In early days Picasso's admiration for cir¬
cus folk and his sympathy for the outcasts
of society, the clown, the mountebank, and
his understanding of the misery of blind beg
gars and those in prisons and hospitals were
at the basis of his perception of monsters
rather than the fire-breathing dragons of
romantic tales. It seemed necessary to admit
the co-existence of good and evil and to
achieve the partnership of beauty and hor¬
ror. Inevitably there must be beauty to be
found somehow in ugliness, and beauty, if it
were to be alive, could not be that pure
frozen abstraction made by Pygmalion. A
vital force must emerge from it which will
electrify the duality in our own hybrid emo¬
tional nature.
Picasso found ample acknowledgment of
this situation in myths that symbolize our in¬
ner torments and aspirations; myths in
which the whole of creation gave him the
means of examining that elusive element
called reality.
Frequently in his work he depicts animals
and attributes to them human emotions in
which violence and cruelty play their part. In
the painting Cat and Bird of 1939, a cat with
vicious claws tears its prey to pieces, but the
face of the cat seen against a serene blue
sky is both feline and human. Elsewhere, as
in Bullfight of 1934 (illustration this page),
he shows us with compassion the drama of
a horse gored by the bull in the arena.
Throughout his life Picasso combined a
consciousness of his talent with a
remarkable degree of modesty and self-
criticism. In early days he imagined a
likeness between himself and that legendary
mercurial wanderer and talented outcast.
Harlequin, but in later years he found a more
robust likeness to his own ebullient
character in the mythical monster and
demigod, the Minotaur. Half man and half
bull it brought reminiscences of his childish
fascination for the corrida where man and
bull confront each other in a ritual struggle
between life and death.
In a series of engravings begun in 1933,
known as the Sculptor's Studio, myth is
passionately transcribed as a visual com-
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
mentary on his own life. An enigmatic
similarity in the depths of desire was the
plane on which this became manifest.
After we have been introduced in several
etchings to the bearded sculptor accom¬
panied by his exquisite model at work in his
studio but unhappy at the lack of satisfac¬
tion that his marble creations give him, there
is a change of atmosphere.
Suddenly his studio is brutally invaded by
the shameless, lustful appearance of the
Minotaur which brings with it a release from
the painstaking labour and scrupulous
respect for the sculptor's models. The orgy
that follows, involving the divine yet in¬
tolerable monster in intimacy with the artist
as well as his placid and beautiful girls,
works up through progressive images to un¬
controlled violence and rape culminating in
the Minotaur being put to death in the
arena, . watched with anxiety by the
spectators.
Bullfight, 1934. Oil on canvas,
97x130 cm. The vigour of its
dramatic impact and the
sheer size of the canvas
make this work perhaps the
most striking of all the
paintings Picasso devoted to
the theme of the corrida. The
violence of the shock as the
bull savagely knocks to the
ground and disembowels the
horse is emphasized by the
double outlines of the two
animals. In Picasso's
symbolism the bull stands for
evil and brute force, whereas
the horse usually represents
good and innocence. Here
the dying animal, its head
thrown back in the final
agony, seems prophetic of
the tragic, poignant posture
of the horse in Guernica (see
page 16), painted three years
later.
Later Picasso added a postscript in which
the amorous demigod meets a different
penalty blindness. Landing from the sea
we now find him being led along the quay by
a child carrying a dove, docile and lamenting
to the stars. The sense of touch becomes his
only «means of contact as he stumbles
through the night (illustration page 36). The
affliction of blindness recalls paintings from
the Blue Period, made some thirty years
before, of the blind beggars in the streets of
Barcelona. He reminds us here that the im¬
agination can function without the aid of
physical sight and that the inner eye is
essential to the poet.
The image of the Minotaur continued to
haunt Picasso in drawings, gouaches and
notably in a large engraving of 1935, which
seems prophetic of the Spanish Civil War
due to begin a few months later and also of
his great mural Guernica.
Minotauromachy (illustration page 36)
presents a dramatic scene into which the
monster intrudes with fierce aggression. He
is attacking a girl dressed sumptuously in a
toreador costume who lies dying on a ter¬
rified horse while the bearded sculptor tries
to make his escape up a ladder. But again
the brute is halted in its onslaught by the
presence of a little girl holding a bunch of
flowers who fearlessly confronts him with a
lighted candle. This steadfast gesture
reasserts a precarious balance between the
ugliness of uncontrolled violence and the
forces of light.
The following year Picasso made another
drawing which again testifies to his desire
that in spite of the coexistence of good and
evil he still hopes that the good and beautiful
will somehow dominate. Drawn with the
highly evocative line of his pencil he
presents us with The End of a Monster (il¬
lustration page 36). The Minotaur struck to
death by an arrow is shown his own bestial
face in a mirror held up to him by a woman
of classical beauty emerging from the sea.
In 1936 Picasso produced a gouache
which was enlarged for the drop-curtain for
"Le Quatorze Juillet" a play by Romain
Rolland.
The theme is a duel between two impos¬
ing antagonists (colour page 28). On the
right a powerful winged demon with the
head of a bird carries in its arms the limp
figure of a defeated Minotaur gasping for
breath. It is challenged as it goes by a young
hero mounted on the shoulders of a bearded
man who has disguised himself in the skin of
a horse and prepares to hurl a stone at the
demon. But it is the figure of the wounded
Minotaur that is of particular significance
because Picasso has dressed him in the dia¬
mond cloth of Harlequin.
He combines both the images that
Picasso had adopted for himself, here ex¬
hausted and carried off by a powerful
monster, a circumstance which may reveal
the "holy doubt" with which he viewed
himself and his achievements.
But Picasso had no need to return to the
past nor to invent legends to find his
monsters. They could be found in contem¬
porary tyrants whom he hated and
caricatured, such as General Franco, or
more personally they could appear as the ex¬
pression of the miseries and provocations
that arose in the course of his married life.
For some years he went through great
emotional stress after his separation from
his first wife Olga in 1934. Submission to
violent attacks from her due to her jealousy
for his new love, Dora Maar, aroused an
anger which echoed throughout his whole
production. Distortions of the human form
became grotesque and terrible.
The monsters he could invent with such
power continued to haunt him. This appears
in many different forms throughout the
years that followed. In a drawing of 1934 (il¬
lustration page 37), in which he had in mind
David's painting of the assassination of
Marat, he seems to be laughing at his own
obsession, for humour even in its blackest
form is often associated with the
monstrous.
A furious female figure has invaded the
room like a whirlwind. Her face with small
cruel eyes is dominated by a large open
mouth with fangs bared and a tongue
swollen and thirsting for blood. With
outstretched arm she plunges an enormous
knife into the jugular vein of her victim
seated like Marat in the bath-tub, but to our
surprise it is not Marat who is the victim. It is
a girl with the profile of Marie-Thérèse
Walter, the sensuous blond model who is
found so frequently in paintings of the early
thirties.
A similar kind of metamorphosis could
have its origin in a mixture of sources, some
benign. The obsessive beauty of Dora Maar
inspired Picasso for a host of inventions.
Frequently her radiant face with shining
eyes was transformed into a bird or the head
of a nymph with budding horns and at times
the long aristocratic head of his Afghan
hound was merged into paintings which,
although they could not be called
portraits, were still in essence Dora.
There is for instance a war-time drawing
of a female figure sitting in the chair usually
occupied by Dora Maar at Royan during the
invasion where Picasso with macabre
humour has substituted the enlarged skull of
a rabbit for her head.
This raises urgently the question as to
why he should wish to mock and demolish
beauty he had known and admired so in¬
tensely even when personal animosity was
absent? Can it be that the deeper the shame
and the anguish brought about by
outrageous catastrophes in the world
around him, the greater must be the
sacrifice demanded of him, if it were to con¬
vey a message of sufficient power? In what
other way could he prove better the violence
of his emotion? By this sacrifice beauty
herself gave birth to, or rather became the
monster.
Among the many studies made for Guer¬
nica .in 1937 there is a large monochrome
canvas known as Woman with a Dead Child
(illustration page 37). It is a poetic statement
containing an acute degree of tenderness
and compassion expressed with terrifying
violence, similar in this respect to the small
painting The Crucifixion painted seven years
before but more direct in its appeal.
The movement of the figure of a woman
across the picture culminates in her head
above the dead child she carries. The head
perched at the extremity of a long straining
neck displays a powerful expression of
agony due to the unprecedented distortions
it contains and the associations they evoke.
The eyes brought together on the same pro¬
file rock like small boats in a storm, the*
nostrils suggest birds caught in a gale, while I
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
from the mouth comes a scream, shrill and
as penetrating as the enormous tongue
shaped like a flame. The tongue itself is sur¬
rounded by teeth sharp and dangerous, with
an outer cordon of lips drawn taut like the
arc of a bow.
The grief expressed by this fusion of im¬
ages is the contrary to a passive acceptance
of misery, it calls with authority for justice
with clear and resounding eloquence. Yet
this head may by some be considered
monstrous and hideously ugly but such
qualifications would be meaningless. They
would fail utterly to apply to the vivid ex¬
perience which is stated clearly in this heart¬
breaking image. It is above all because of the
distortions that emotions of anguish, com¬
passion and indignation are aroused, and it
is by the relevance of the metaphors that, as
in poetry, we are able to attain glimpses of
universal truth.
There are moments when Picasso's
irrepressible sense of humour encouraged
him to invent monsters which could
astonish by their grotesque invention and
bring laughs from children. Their prototypes
were to be found on the seashore or among
n 1933 and 1934 Picasso produced a
series of drawings and engravings
on the theme of the Blind Minotaur
Guided by a Young Girl (top photo,
a drawing in the series made in
1934, 33.5x51.2 cm). The principal
elements the blind minotaur and
the girl, with the fishermen and the
sea in the background are
repeated in each work of the series.
In the final etching, referred to in
the article on these pages, the
figure of a youth has been added
and the young girl is seen holding a
dove instead of flowers and leading
the blind minotaur towards the left
of the picture. The girl, whose face
is that of Picasso's companion
Marie-Thérèse Walter, represents
innocence and intelligence in
contrast to the now tamed
lasciviousness and brute force of
the minotaur. In Minotauromachy
(centre photo, etching made in
1935, 49.8x69.3 cm), innocence,
again in the form of a young girl
holding flowers and a lighted
candle, fearlessly confronts the
powers of violence and evil.
Bottom photo. End of a Monster
(pencil drawing of 1937).
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
railway station crowds, in the same surroun¬
dings where other faces inspired drawings
of nymphs of disconcerting charm.
The ¡mages he created are rich in associa¬
tions. They contain so often that which is
called beauty on the one hand and the
monstrous, that disconcerting appearance
of terror, on the other. In his fundamental
desire to exclude nothing that can be ex¬
pressed he refused to set up boundaries and
in conversation with his secretary-
companion Sabartes he once said "Beauty,
what a strange thing!... For me it is a word
devoid of meaning for I don't know from
where its significance comes nor to what it
leads. Do you know exactly where to find its
opposite?".
This refusal to accept a simple dichotomy
between beauty and its opposite gives a clue
to Picasso's attitude and the freedom with
which he could enhance his effects emo¬
tionally by a welding of two extremes. We
can gain from him deep experience of reality
through his sacred monsters. These are not
lacking throughout the world, for man made
gods and, even more successfully,
demigods in his own ¡mage. |
ROLAND PENROSE, English writer and painter,
first met Picasso in 1936 when involved in
preparations for the first International Surrealist
Exhibition in London, thus beginning a friendship
which only ended with Picasso's death. He has
written widely on 20th-century European artists
and their work and is the author of some 10
studies on Picasso including Picasso: His Life and
Work, (revised edition. Pelican Biographies, Lon¬
don 1971) which has been translated into six
languages. Sir RolandPenrose is also President of
the Institute of Contemporary Arts, London,
which he was instrumental in founding in 1947.
The Death of Marat, 1934.
Drawing on cardboard,
40x50 cm. This work was
inspired by a famous painting by
the French artist Jacques-Louis
David (1748-1825).
Woman with a Dead Child, 1937.
Oil on canvas, 195x130 cm. One
of a series of compositions
which can be considered as
"postscripts" to the great mural
Guernica.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
As a sculptor Picasso was an
innovator who succeeded in
transforming the most
unlikely materials into
masterpieces in which
humour and Inventiveness
combine. Perhaps his most
famous transformation was
his juxtaposition of the
saddle and handlebars from a
derelict bicycle to form Head
of a Bull (1943), opposite
page.
In Man Carrying a Sheep
(1944),bronze, 225x78x78
cm., (Museum of Modern
Art, Philadelphia) Picasso
returned to traditional
methods. This vast sculpture
on an ancient, archetypal
theme, has been described as
"a work of resistance to
oppression", and seems to
signify faith in man's ability
to restore peace to the
world.
Picasso
the
by Julian Gallego
ONE of the outstanding sculptors of
this century, the Spaniard Julio
Gonzalez, once declared: "In my
view, the mysterious side of Picasso's
work its nerve centre, as it were is his
sculpture".
There is, however, a general tendency to
consider Picasso almost exclusively in terms
of his painting and to regard his sculpture as
a secondary activity, little more than a hob¬
by. Yet taken in its entirety, his sculpture
alone could well represent the full-time ac¬
tivity of a hard-working and inspired artist.
If, by some misfortune, all his other
works paintings, drawings, prints and
ceramics were to disappear, his sculpture
alone would suffice to situate Picasso at the
very summit of the history of the art of this
century.
It was only to be expected that certain
Cubist painters, such as Laurens and
Braque, should have produced some fine
pieces of sculpture. Yet none of them even
approached Picasso in quality or quantity of
output. He once said to Julio Gonzalez :
"All you need to do to produce sculpture is
to carve up pictures. The colours are simply
guides to different perspectives and sloping
pla nes. . . 0 nee you have eu t u p a pictu re you
have only to follow the lines indicated by
each colour and you are left with a piece of
sculpture".
In retrospect this advice seems to apply to
not a few of Picasso's works in both media.
Indeed, there are grounds for thinking that
despite the fact that he was one of the
greatest painters of the modern era, Picasso
had little regard for purely pictorial qualities.
It was in this that he diverged most from his
friend Matisse, whose conceptions he seem¬
ed at times on the point of sharing.
Picasso's canvases sometimes seem more
like a guide to painting than works compos¬
ed with loving care. The effects he sought
could perhaps be achieved more directly
through sculpture. Especially since, in his
sculptural work, Picasso was so far removed
from academic orthodoxy, replacing the
marble of Carrara which was totally alien to
him with all kinds of odds and ends sheet
metal, wires, planks, stones, ragswhich
he daubed with paint as the fancy took him.
Cubism, with its "collages", and
Dadaism, with its randomly assembled ob¬
jects absurdly elevated to the status of art,
opened up a boundless field of experience in
which Picasso, as in many other fields, was
one of the most indefatigable seekers.
Although, when commenting on the
pseudo-scientific pedantry of the
technological painters, he said : "I do not
seek, I find", he nevertheless spent his
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
sculptor
whole life seeking out and, with extra¬
ordinary genius, transforming junk into
masterpieces.
Jean Cocteau called him "the king of the
rag-pickers", and this was especially true of
that happy period that started in 1943 with
the Bucranio, or Head of a Bull (illustration
this page), made out of a bicycle saddle and
handlebars, which, when assembled, pro¬
duced an overwhelming plastic effect.
But Picasso's attraction to sculpture goes
much further back, to the beginning of the
century. His Seated Woman dates from
1901, and this was followed immediately by
the Blind Man and the Picador, during what
is known, in his painting, as the Blue Period.
Somewhat later, during the Rose Period,
came his bronze bust of The Jester. It is a
fine, very pictural bust on which the light
seems to glide like the strokes of a soft
paintbrush, rather in the manner of a Rodin.
The head of his mistress Fernande Olivier
(illustration this page), produced in the same
year, '1905, displays an exquisite sense of
luminous values and, typical of his skill at
reconciling opposites, enormous strength
and determination.
Fernande was the muse of early Cubism
and her fragmented features appear in both
paintings and sculptures. The head, compo¬
sed of small plane surfaces, which Picasso
made of her in 1909 is the exact three-
dimensional equivalent of the heads which
he drew or painted. It is perhaps even more
striking than the portraits because it offers
us the reality of volume in space rather than
its illusion on a plane surface.
This calls to mind the distinction that the
Prussian critic and philosopher Johann von
Herder drew between sculpture, the art of
the real, and painting, the art of deception.
What the sculptor shows us exists, we can
touch it in our own space rather than see it
only in the illusory space of the canvas.
Picasso was always a "realist" in the sense
in which the Russian sculptors Gabo and
Pevsner used the term "realism" in their
celebrated Manifesto of 1920, that is, as
being something that is not a transposition
or a copy of something else but that has an
existence of its own and that did not exist
before the artist created it. It should be
noted that, ten years before the Manifesto
appeared, Picasso had already sensed one
of the principles it proclaimed that of
emphasizing hollow effects in sculpture as a
means of expressing space.
During the period of "Synthetic Cubism"
Picasso astonished the world with the abun¬
dance of his inventions, although some of
these were little known because they were
made of fragile, short-lived materials. The
exhibition at the Grand Palais in Paris, in
1979, of the so-called Picasso Bequest
(works made over to the French State by his
heirs in payment of death duty) provided an
opportunity to admire a large number of
works made of materials such as cardboard,
metal plate, wood, paper. Some of these
works were tiny and were apparently
preserved in packing-cases by the artist
once the miracle of creation had taken
place. The musical themes of the Cubist
still-life oil paintings re-emerge with added
force and intensity by being expressed in
paltry materials. The most famous of these
works, the Glass of Absinth (1914), seems
to combine all the preoccupations of
Futurism, Cubism and Dadaism. One of the
last examples of that unprecedented series
was the post-Cubist Guitar (1924), which is
made of sheet metal.
During the Surrealist period, when
Picasso collaborated with the group led by
André Breton by designing the cover for the
celebrated magazine "Minotaure", he pro¬
duced several three-dimensional works
which were even more revealing than his
paintings, using unconventional materials
such as the wire in the Woman in a Garden
(1929), or the grains of sand combined with
rope, canvas and so on, in compositions
protected under glass, like the Construction
with Glove, or the Construction with But¬
terfly, both dating from 1930, in which a real
glove and a real butterfly were used.
The first Crucifixion, painted at
Boisgeloup in 1930, marked the beginning of
an expressionist phase which was to con¬
tinue for several years, culminating in 1937
in the celebrated Guernica. During the same
decade, Picasso produced the tranquil,
classical illustrations for Ovid's Metamor¬
phoses, for the publisher Albert Skira. In his
sculptural work, the small wooden figurines,
in the style of ancient votive offerings, and
especially the magnificent women's heads,
free-standing or in relief, with the curve of
the nose projecting beak-like from the centre
of the forehead, had much more in common
with his engravings than with his paintings.
Then, at a time of deep crisis, he began to
produce his exquisite bronze statuettes;
using leaves, shells and corrugated paper to
make impressions in the clay from which
they were cast, he succeeded, with these
humble materials, in resurrecting an idyllic
Greece of hamadryads and water nymphs.
The Bucranio, or Head of a Bull, (1943)
marked the beginning of a very happy and
prolific period of pictorial and sculptural out¬
put during which Picasso's optimism seems
to have known no bounds.
Head of a Woman (Fernande), 1909. Bronze,
40.5x24x26 cm. This head of Fernande
Olivier, Picasso's companion at the time it
was made, is considered to be one of the
finest examples of Cubist sculpture.
Photos Réunion des Musées Nationaux, Paris © SPADEM 1980, Paris.
Musée Picasso, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
But most astonishing of all was the way in
'which, like a conjuror, he assembled and
transformed all kinds of discarded objects.
Surveying a scrap heap or rubbish dump
with his practised eye, Picasso picked out,
for example, a toy car which would be
transformed into a monkey's head. Inspired
by his passionate desire to live his life afresh,
any object was grist to his mill, giving rise to
curious sculptures such as Girl with the
Skipping-rope, Woman with Baby Carriage
(illustration this page), Pregnant Woman
and Woman with an Apple; this was his bid
to make his art accessible to everybody. In
1943-44 he produced Man with Sheep (il¬
lustration page 38), his version of the
Moscophoros, which has since adorned the
main square of Vallauris in the south of
France.
He produced a whole bestiary of domestic
animals presided over by owls, both serious
and comic, and among which the She-goat,
made of palm-leaves and wicker, raises her
peaceful horns. This more naturalistic, less
intellectualized art was symptomatic of a
world-wide tendency in the post-war years
which was shortly to be swamped by the im¬
penetrable new wave of triumphant abstract
art.
Picasso was never to be an abstract
painter. But his figures of women of the
1950s, with their large flat surfaces, the
monumental head of Sylvette, in black and
white sheet metal, now admirably set in a
garden of New York University, and, even
more, the "weathervane" women and dolls,
The Bathers of 1956, and the gigantic plate-
steel figures of the following decade all sug¬
gest that Picasso was weary of facile art, the
art of playfulness and popular rejoicing, and
was retreating into attitudes harking back to
the Cubism of almost half a century earlier.
This general survey of Pablo Picasso's
career as a sculptor leads to the conclusion
that it was as astonishing and as pregnant
with discoveries as his career as a painter. In
his latter years he produced hardly any
sculpture, which is a mach more demanding
art physically than the drawing and engrav¬
ing on which he concentrated most of his
efforts.
It is easy to distinguish a number of con¬
stants in this varied panorama. "Art that
bores people is good for the wastepaper
basket", wrote Jean Dubuffet. Picasso was
never a bore because he himself was never
bored. His sculpture always has an
uninhibited, improvised air, far removed
from the academic solemnity in which that
art form is so often shrouded. Picasso
astonishes us with his miraculous resuscita¬
tions of discarded objects, his metamor¬
phosis of the obsolete and his re-invention
of the everyday. Despite the much-noted
borrowings from Negro sculpture, it is the
dominant classical trait, the Mediterranean
spirit that constantly surfaces in his
sculptural figures, female figures for the
most part, which Picasso shapes, twists
and breaks down, the better to hold them in
his grasp.
JULIAN GALLEGO, Spanish art historian, is a
professor at the university of Madrid. Among his
many published works are Visión y Símbolos en la
Pintura Española del Siglo de Oro ("Vision and
Symbols in Spanish Painting of the Golden Cen¬
tury"), Pintura Contemporánea ("Contemporary
Painting"), and studies on Velazquez, Goya and
Zurbarân. This article is an edited and abridged
version of a hitherto umpublished paper
presented to the Congress on Picasso held at
Santander (Spain) last summer.
Above, Picasso with Françoise Gilot
and their son Claude on the beach
on the Côte d'Azur in 1950, an
occasion that may have inspired,
right. Woman with Baby Carriage
(1950, bronze, 203x145x61 cm).
Elements that went into its
construction include the remains of
a strainer (one of the wheels), old
pottery handles (the child's legs and
arms), an earthenware vase (the
child's hat and head) and a
chimney-pipe from a stove (the
woman's skirt).
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
The mythical world
of Picasso
THE bull plays a prominent role in Medi¬
terranean mythology. Divine bulls are
depicted in the frescoes of Minoan Crete
and in ancient Majorcan bronzes, and the
bull's special place is still perpetuated in the
corrida of Andalusia. This mythology was
often used by Picasso, who saw in the
bullfight the symbolism of a basic duality.
The bull is brute force. The horse disem¬
bowelled by its horns is innocence.
At the height of the Spanish Civil War,
horrified by the destruction of the Basque
town of Guernica by the Nazi airforce on
Franco's orders, Picasso took this theme as
the central idea for his great mural Guernica
(illustration page 16). The conception of this
painting was based on the themes which he
by A. Cirici Pellicer
had already handled in his bullfighting
etchings.
The dynamism of the work, like its theme,
is in line with the classical tradition as
represented by the subject of 77?e Rape of
the Sabine Women, a conventional exercise
which enabled painters and sculptors to
tackle the problems of violence, the physical
victory of brute force, and the ethics and
aesthetics of innocence.
The idea of associating brutality with large
animals was as traditional as that of taking
female figures as the incarnation of the vic¬
tims, endowed with the positive forces of
virtue and beauty. The bull and the horse
epitomize the great drama of violence, while
woman plays a humanizing role: the woman
who cries out and the woman who bears her
dead child in her arms; the woman calling
for action and the woman in agony.
Bullfighting and The Rape of the Sabine
Women, the two main vibrant themes of
Guernica, were returned to many times by
Picasso, in his paintings and to an even
greater extent in his prolific output of
graphic work. There is a magnificent prece¬
dent for the mythology of Guernica in the
Minotauromachy, the etching which he
made in 1935 and in which a huge and som¬
bre Minotaur, half-man, half-bull, has just
disembowelled a horse which, as the victim,
is identified with femininity and whose
entrails form the beautiful body of a
woman.
Interior of the "Temple of Peace" at Vallauris In the South of France, showing War (left) and Peace (right), the two vast murals (each
470 cm. by 1,020 cm.) painted in 1952.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
Joie do Vivre, also called Pastorale, 1946. Oil on fibro-cement, 120x250 cm.
, Joie de Vivre
In 1946, the Spanish Civil War and the Se¬
cond World War at an end, Picasso painted
another major mural. Joie de Vivre (illustra¬
tion this page), at Antibes in the south of
France. The work, a kind of counterpoise to
Guernica, was painted after Picasso had
proposed to the municipality of Antibes that
he should fill all the space in the old Grimaldi
Palace there, turning it into a museum of his
work. This was his way of paying tribute to a
town that had been founded by the Greeks,
and to all that it stood for as a symbol of the
Mediterranean.
The painting is a complete contrast with
Guernica. Whereas in Guernica all is
violence, in Joie de Vivre all is peace. The
blacks and greys have given way to the
purest and softest tones of blue. The exag¬
gerated, relentless movement is superseded
by a sense of calm expressed by the
counterpoint of vertical lines with the
horizontal line of the sea. If Guernica can be
compared to the Rape of the Sabine
Women, then Joie de Vivre can be com¬
pared to Botticelli's Birth of Venus. A splen¬
did female nude is the centrepiece in both
paintings. In both cases the sea forms the
background. The same two groups fill each
side of the two pictures.
These paintings represent the two ex¬
tremes of a single vision of reality. In Guer¬
nica we have the condemnation of Evil,
which is identified with brute force, while in
Joie de Vivre we have a hymn to Good,
which is identified with the sensual pleasure
of beautiful bodies, music, dancing and the
pleasant climate of the Mediterranean. It is a
hymn to freedom.
The identification of the Mediterranean
with freedom is a recurrent theme in
Picasso's work. The Spanish writer Eugenio
d'Ors went so far as to assert that the artisfs
true homeland was the Mediterranean. I
once heard him say that the peoples of An¬
dalusia, Catalonia and Provence were all
made of the same stuff because they were
"Mediterranean", and, he added, "Madrid
and Paris will never understand us". In this
bipolarity, Madrid and Paris clearly epitomiz-
42
ed power, regimentation, the law and the
force of coercion, while Andalusia,
Catalonia and Provence represented life on
the fringe of society, as well as defiance and
even, if necessary, deceit, when there was
any question of breaking free of constraints
and living life to the full.
War and Peace
Unfortunately, the war that ended in 1945
was not the last, and the sky of Joie de Vivre
did not remain cloudless for long. In 1951
and 1952 Picasso produced several paintings
which expressed his reaction to the Korean
War.
His Massacre in Korea of 1951 is another
monumental historical frieze. This time, the
figures are divided into two camps, but not
into two balanced camps as in Velazquez'
Surrender of Breda, nor into two unbalanc¬
ed camps as in Goya's The Third of May
1808, but simply into two, totally separate,
camps treated in a way which perhaps no
one had used since Giotto. The Manichean
dichotomy is highly typical of Picasso. On
one side the shapes are organic, on the
other they are mechanical. Soft contours
confront hard, stabbing forms; smooth,
rounded shapes confront rigid lines; realistic
figures confront monsters.
This dichotomy is fully expressed in the
two panels Picasso painted in 1952 to
decorate a chapel at Vallauris. One depicts
war, the other peace. They are over ten
metres long, bigger even than Guernica.
War is a monstrosity where all is confusion.
The fact that the wheels of the large cart are
square is symptomatic. The horses are not
the limp, broken-down hacks of the
Tauromachies. Their hooves are inordinately
heavy. The warriors are wildly gesticulating
silhouettes. The atmosphere is one of
desolation.
Picasso frequently identifies the male with
mindless violence, and here it is noteworthy
that male figures predominate in the per¬
sonification of Evil. By contrast, the vision
of peace focuses on femininity and
childhood, the two concepts idealized by
the artist, who is unfailingly loyal to the
value he sets on innocence and his
predisposition in favour of the victim.
There is also a horse, but whereas the
horse is the victim of the Tauromachy, here
it has been reprieved and is a winged
Pegasus escaping from ill-fate. A fiery sun,
shaped like a child's kite and decorated with
ears of corn, presides over the scene, in
which the moon is also seen as a kite. There
are vines with clusters of grapes and an
orange tree loaded with oranges, but above
all there are women and children women
who are dancing and children who are run¬
ning or playing the flute. One child is amus¬
ing himself by harnessing Pegasus to a
plough, while the women are tending the
children or are cooking or writing.
The lines and splashes of colour in War
are graceless, hard, angular and weak,
whereas those in Peace display a delicate
sophistication, reaching the very limits of
the impossible foreshortening effects that
are so dear to Picasso and are the spearhead
of his pleasure in playing the game of
creation.
The Meninas
In my view, the cycle of Picasso's main
mythological themes comes to a close with
the series of glosses which he painted in the
late 1950s on Velazquez' celebrated work
Las Meninas ("the little ladies-in-waiting")
(photo 1 overleaf). These are possibly the
most revealing of all his mythological com¬
positions, and by comparing them with
Velazquez' painting, noting the colours
Picasso uses, and the way he increases or
reduces the size of Velazquez' figures, we
can form a precise idea of his system of
values and learn which values he regards as
positive and which as negative (see
overleaf).
From the colours Picasso employs we can
immediately grasp his fundamental position.
"Heavenly" colours such as the yellow of
the sun and the bright blue of the sky he
uses exclusively for the innocent figures: for
the young princess who is the main subject
of Velazquez' painting and who, in spite of
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
her rank, is still too small to be caught up in
her family's system of aggression; for the
monstrous dwarf María Barbóla (second
from right in Velazquez' painting), who is in¬
nocent because she does not possess all her
mental faculties; and for the smaller dwarf
Pertusato (far right in Velazquez' painting),
who is a harmless and childlike buffoon. The
other figures are either gloomy apparitions
in black or grey, or are painted in colours
( red for fire and green for poison) traditional¬
ly associated with demons in Iberian
folklore.
In one version he uses only greyish tones
because, as in Guernica, he wishes to con¬
centrate on showing us, without the in¬
terference of colour, the sheer force of
draughtsmanship and the values of light and
shadow.
There are even more striking lessons to be
learnt when we turn away from the colours
Picasso uses, so different from the golden
tones that suffuse Velazquez' original pain¬
ting, to examine the linear composition of
his Meninas. The most significant feature
here is the greatly increased size of the
figure of the painter, who in Picasso's pain¬
tings appears as a giant whose head almost
touches the ceiling, making all the other
figures look small. In one of Picasso's ver¬
sions (photo 2 on next page) the painter is
shown with an enormous cross of St. James
on his chest, a cruel satire on the vanity of
Velazquez, who painted the cross on himself
to symbolize the fact that he was a member
of the nobility although in point of fact he
was not. The enormous hooks in the ceiling,
like those used in butchers' shops for hang¬
ing sides of beef, constitute another striking
feature of the same work. Similar hooks ap¬
pear in Velazquez' picture, but they are
scarcely noticeable in the shadow and were
presumably used for hanging lamps. Their
increased size in Picasso's painting makes
the room look like a torture chamber.
Picasso creates a tragic atmosphere in
which the scene depicted by Velazquez in
Madrid's Alcazar Palace is transformed so as
to convey the sinister nature of ab¬
solutism two figures in the
background, for example, are made to
resemble upended coffins. The shapes of
the main figures are highly significant and
Picasso returns to them in each of the varia¬
tions. A round-shaped face is associated
with goodness and innocence. It is the
shape of the sun and the ball used in games.
It has no sharp edges; it is agreeable; it is
feminine.
The princess and the two dwarfs all have
round faces. In contrast, Picasso depicts the
two obsequiously flattering ladies-in-waiting
who flank the princess, with sharp, angular
features and pointed heads. These ladies-in-
waiting, Isabel de Velasco (offering water to
the princess) and Maria Agustino Sarmiento
(kneeling) are made to appear anti¬
pathetic and distinctly aggressive.
The contrast between the round faces of
the good people, painted in yellows or sky-
blue, and the sharp faces, the reds and
greens, of the evil-doers, is a feature com¬
mon to all the variations.
One painting in the Meninas series is par¬
ticularly revealing (see photo 3 overleaf). It
shows María Barbóla flanked by two figures.
Its composition closely resembles the central
part of the Velazquez painting (in which the
young princess is seen standing between
the two maids-of-honour), and yet the foot
of the figure at right, above the dog, is that
of Pertusato. The central figure can thus be
identified as María Barbóla, whom Picasso
has substituted for the princess. The face of
the figure at the left, Isabel de Velasco, is
turned in a different direction from that in
the Velazquez painting: she is shown adop¬
ting the same servile attitude to the idiot
child as she does to the princess in the
original painting. Picasso thus expresses his
egalitarian idea that value is measured in
terms of goodness or innocence. This is why
he equates the princess with an idiot child.
In so doing he also underlines the stupidity
of the courtier who is ready to turn in any
direction if advantage can be gained from
making a bow or a curtsey.
The Meninas series is also interesting
because it includes a number of pictures il¬
lustrating views from "La Californie",
Picasso's Art Nouveau villa at Cannes,
whose balconies offer superb vistas of the
Mediterranean. Flocks of doves, the symbol
of peace which Picasso used so often, flit
across the blue sea and sky. This sea and
this sky, so open and luminous, represent
liberty; they are the diametrical opposite of
the blacks, greys, and other sinister tones
used to depict the world of absolutism. This
helps us to grasp the full mythological
meaning of the Meninas series. Absolutism
is seen to stand for stupidity, confinement,
cruelty and servility and, at the very ex¬
treme, diabolical aggressiveness. Freedom,
on the other hand, is synonymous with
responsiveness, happiness and spontaneous
vitality, and is the handmaiden of peace. |
ALEXANDRE CIRICI PELLICER, Spanish art
historian and art critic, is professor of the
sociology ofart at the University of Barcelona. He
is the author of some 80 published works in¬
cluding Picasso Antes de Picasso (Barcelona,
1946) and studies on the Catalonians Gaud!, Miró
and Tapies. He is also a member of the Spanish
Senate and of Spain's delegation to the European
Assembly in Strasbourg. This article is a hitherto
unpublished version of his contribution to the
Santander congress on Picasso.
A gigantic, 80-
square-metre mural
(right) was Picasso's
contribution to the
decoration of
Unesco's Paris
headquarters
buildings,
inaugurated in 1958.
The theme, the fall
of Icarus with a
beach and bathers,
has been seen as
symbolizing the
struggle of the
mind's living forces
against evil.
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Variations on a theme of Velazquez
In mid-August 1957, Picasso embarked on a concentrated period of
work during which he painted over 40 variations on Las Meninas
("the little ladies-in-waiting"), a masterpiece by Velazquez which
he had admired since his early teens. Like his great Spanish
predecessor he was fascinated by the interplay between art and
reality, and Las Meninas, a look "behind-the-scenes" during the
creation of a painting, poses a problem which had always intrigued
him, the relationship between the artist, the model and the
spectator.
In the painting by Velazquez (1), the artist is seen at work on a
portrait of the Spanish king and queen. He is looking out from
beside his easel towards his sitters, whose image appears in a
small mirror in the background. In foreground are the little
princess Margarita Maria and her servants who have intruded into
the studio. The princess is shown between two ladies-in-waiting,
Maria Agustina Sarmiento, kneeling, and Isabel de Velasco. Next
to Isabel are two dwarfs, Maria Barbóla and (far right) Pertusato.'
In his variations, now in the Museo Picasso at Barcelona, the artist
ingeniously transformed Velazquez' handling of the lighting, the
placing of the figures, their gestures and the texture of their dress
(see article beginning page 41). Illustrations show: (2) the large
painting with which the series began (17 August 1957); (4 and 5)
each depicting the little princess, are two of the small studies
Picasso produced during the following month when he was
concentrating mainly on single figures or groups (3). Painting
shown in colour (right hand page, above) is another analysis of the
entire Velazquez work. The world of the Meninas is prefigured in
Studio at Cannes (30 March 1956) reproduced in colour opposite.
The painting, one of a series which Picasso referred to as "interior
landscapes", shows his studio in his villa "La Californie" near
Cannes. This sombre view of a studio "unpopulated by anything
but his art and furniture". Including a blank canvas, is one of
several from the 1950s when as the Picasso scholar Robert
Rosenblum has pointed out, "his work often begins to convey the
hermetic character of a life circumscribed by the immediate facts
of domesticity on the French Riviera and the distant memories of
his own art and that of the old masters". To a visitor who saw a
later version of this interior and remarked how Spanish were its
harmonies of tans, blacks, browns and whites, Picasso replied:
"Velázquezl"
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
s
/
ri<
A - '
SE
5V
s>
79
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Colour page
These two canvases. Still Life with the
Skull of a Bull (130x97 cm.) and Aubade
(195x265 cm.) were both painted in 1942
during the four-year period, "characterized
by unity of location and atmosphere",
when Picasso was practically immobilized
in Nazi-occupied Paris. In spite of the
scarcity of materials his output of paintings
remained prodigious. Many of them evoke
what the British art critic John Berger has
described as "the experience of defeat,
occupation and a terrible vision of evil
which was in no sense metaphysical but
there in the streets in its jackboots and
with its swastika". The Still Life also
echoes a cry of personal mourning; it is
dated 5 April, a week after Picasso had
learned of the death of his old friend the
sculptor Julio Gonzalez. Qi Aubade, also
steeped in the forbidding gloom of
wartime. Berger writes: "The subject ...
may seem unremarkable: a woman on a
bed and another woman sitting on a chair,
holding a mandolin which she is not
playing. Yet in the relationship between
these two women and the furniture and the
room that closes in around them, without a
window or a door, there is all the
claustrophobia of the curfew and a city
without freedom".
Picasso during the making of the film "The Picasso Mystery".
The artist
and his models
A mercurial, unceasing analysis
of the human face
by Dominique Bozo
WE shall never finish discussing
Picasso and his universe, for his
work does not fit in with any re¬
assuring and convincing definition. The
great stream which surged through our cen¬
tury, swollen by all it had gathered and
assimilated from the art of the past and the
new art then developing, remains something
of a mystery to the "general public", art-
lovers and historians alike: all the answers to
their questioning seem inadequate and
incomplete.
This is true of all modern art. But with
Picasso the challenge is greater. Under¬
standing of his work is increasing, as
countless studies make it more widely
known. And laymen are becoming more
familiar with an art which they find
fascinating, but experience as a kind of
violent, barbarian aggression punctuated by
periods of calm and, thus, all the more dif¬
ficult to assimilate.
The real question one must ask therefore
is why the Picasso myth should bear the
brunt of the public's reticence about modern
art in general? Why should Picasso be con¬
sidered the scapegoat of modern art when
the work of Braque, Matisse, Mondrian and
the abstract painters, to mention only these,
gives equal cause for. questioning and
criticism?
The answer is to. be found not only in
Picasso's exceptionally long life: his work,
rooted in the late nineteenth century, spans
nearly a hundred years, almost to the end of
the twentieth century. Neither can it be
found in the continuous calling in question
of his painting, his apparent contradictions
and his successive and complete changes
in genre, or his fluctuations between
classicism and revolution. Again, it cannot
be attributed to the fact that Picasso is the
only artist of this century who introduced |
history as well as his autobiography into his I
.47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Weeping Woman, 1937, Oil on canvas, 60x49 cm.
work and borrowed to such an extent from
the legacy of universal art.
There is something deeper which goes
beyond facile acceptance of the myth
Picasso himself helped to create. "Rejec¬
tion" seems to stem from a simplistic view
of the iconoclastic relationship the painter
was said to have maintained with the
models I mean the human face he ques¬
tioned ceaselessly throughout his career,
particularly during his most prolific period in
the 1930s and 1940s.
For most critics, Picasso remains the
great destroyer of the face. Abstract
painters were content with ignoring it com¬
pletely; Picasso attacked it directly not
merely the image of the classical ideal defin¬
ed by Renaissance artists. Those who reject
his painting do so less because he deformed
nature, objects and man himself, than
because he dared to disfigure and mutilate
the ¡mage of woman. I am sure that most
people looking at one of the portraits he
painted in the 1930s refer unconsciously to
the standards implicit in the classical virgins
of Raphael or Bellini. Picasso's detractors as
well as those who worship his early works
such as the acrobats of the "Blue" and
"Rose" periods, or who admire his realistic
portraits of his wife Olga and his son Paulo,
find it even harder to understand how so
great a talent could have given birth to such
"evil".
'His Cubist paintings are considered less
disturbing, for the face counts for little in
these compositions which most people find
difficult to interpret and many regard as a
closed book. Indeed it ¡s«not easy to identify
or recognize forms in the flat, "analytical"
jigsaw puzzles of symbols. But though the
subject-matter often vanishes in a quasi-
abstract structure painted in monochrome
tones, there is never "disfigurement" in the
proper sense of the word.
After 1917 and up to 1926, Picasso
reverted to realism in the classical tradition.
Most of the work he produced during this
period is "reassuring", even when he takes
pleasure in contrasting huge classical
figures as in Three Women at the
Springwith the Cubist figures of Three
Musicians (illustrations page 26). These
geometrical men, articulated like pieces of
machinery, are portrayed in a theatre setting
which gives them a metaphysical, almost
immaterial quality; they belong to the realm
of dreams and the mind; nothing in them is
aggressive.
But with the first pictures of bathers, also
painted during the 1920s, one again ex¬
periences a feeling of uncertainty and
unease. The giant Venuses born of the
tradition of Ingres' drawing who are seen
running on the beach, athletically muscular
and energetic, full of pure air and propelled
and deformed by physical effort, are
somehow too free and rather terrifying.
Perhaps it is the realism of the setting that
makes them monstrous the fact that they
are depicted in an everyday, down-to-earth
world. Their counterparts are to be seen in
the Vollard suite of etchings devoted to the
"Sculptor and his model".
In the mid-1 930s Picasso again establish¬
ed a . dialogue in his work between
tenderness and terror, using a technique of
explosive colour and arabesque design. It
was these pictures which earned him a
reputation as a "disfigurer", violently ag¬
gressive rather than savage in the manner of
his earlier Demoiselles d'Avignon (illustra¬
tion page 8). Distortion here is in the Cubist
tradition i.e. it results partly from an in¬
tellectual "destructuring" of the model in
order to achieve formal, psychological and
synthetic expression of what, for the
painter, is visible or invisible, known or
discernible. What disturbs in these pictures
is the violent realism which remains after
this process has taken place: one can almost
perceive an identifiable portrait,
reconstituted, magnified and given fresh
unity.
Michel Leiris expressed this clearly as ear¬
ly as 1930: "For [Picasso]", he wrote, "the
object is not to recreate reality just for the
sake of the exercise; an infinitely more im¬
portant aim is to express all the possibilities
and ramifications of reality in order to get a
little closer to it, and truly touch it."
In order to express "all possibilities", the
artist needed absolute freedom. This is how
Picasso himself described his work to the
publisher Tériade: "Time and again, just as I
was about to add some blue, I found I had
none. So I put in some red instead. So much
for the vanity of things of the mind." And
when he says, "I don't seek, I find", he
describes better than any learned treatise or
analysis the extraordinary freedom with
which he conducted his experiments. For
every work involved change or manipulation
of some kind.
When one looks through collections of art
reproductions, it is surprising to find the
portraits of Marie-Thérèse (cover) and Dora
Maar (page 28) along with such familiar
works as Byzantine ikons, Cranach's
Venuses and paintings by Frans Hals or
Velazquez. The two portraits stand out as
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
powerful, self-contained expressions of the
art of our century. All the elements of
Western culture are represented there, from
Ingres' arabesques to the free colour of Van
Gogh.
Tenderness, elegance and stateliness
surge from the portrait of Dora Maar. The
eyes dominate the picture from side-view
and full-face, for both are seen at the same
time, and this adds a mobile, hieratic quality
to the expression. The colour of the
eyes one red, the other green testifies to
the artisfs complete freedom of invention. It
contrasts with the three-quarter stance of
models in classical paintings, yet at the same
time the elegance of attitude recalls the
great portraits of universal painting.
Classicism combines with the most avant-
garde modernism. And this freedom of ex¬
pression and inventiveness gives Picasso's
art a timeless, permanent quality.
The same freedom of line and play colour
can be observed in the portrait (see cover)
of Marie-Thérèse. In this second formulation
of absolute beauty, the artist remains
faithful to the model though one would
never suspect it without comparing picture
and photograph. At the same time, Picasso
gives full reign to his inventiveness, painting
yellow lips and nails, one pink eye, one blue,
and green hair. One is reminded of Van
Gogh and at the same time of Ingres' por¬
traits of La Comtesse d'Haussonville and
Madame Moitessier. Where Ingres used a
looking-glass to reveal the hidden profile of
his model, Picasso resorts to a synthesis of
lines, depicting a head with a full-face ex¬
pression in a three-quarter position. The
fingers are distorted as in Ingres' paintings,
and there is a similar play of hands, the
fingers with their coloured nails branching
out to form a bouquet.
It would take a lot of time and space to
compare these portraits with the great
masterpieces produced by Western classic
art since the Renaissance. Yet such a study
would show that Picasso had assimilated all
the permanent plastic features of classical
art and incorporated them into his painting
in successive waves. This led to the develop¬
ment of new formal concepts are in
fact new ways of expressing
reality capable of expressing psychological
truth in which humour, sadness and a zest
for life mingle.
Why then did Picasso paint his "weeping
women" of 1937, those hysterical, terribly
mutilated, deformed and grief-stricken
figures, who claw at their own faces or
feverishly grasp their handkerchiefs? Prob¬
ably because there were women who cried
in Picasso's own surroundings, as there are
everywhere. Such figures are born in the
drama of war, and Picasso felt he must ex¬
press the horrors of the Spanish Civil War
and, in a premonitory vision, the horrors of
the greater war to come.
These crying' figures do not only sym¬
bolize the tragedy of Spain. However iden¬
tifiable they may be, they are not meant to
portray a particular or individual woman, but
reflect the grief and suffering of the whole
human race. Portraits painted during this
period show an evolution in Picasso's work
from the expression of individual sorrow and
pain to that of universal suffering and death.
One has only to compare the crying figure of
Dora painted in 1937 and the emaciated,
disfigured face of the 1939 portrait, in which
the image is duplicated as by an optical ef-
Portrait of Dora Maar. 1942. Oil on panel, 92x73 cm.
feet, one part of it appearing to be detached
from the portrait while it examines the other,
grief-stricken face.
"I never painted war", Picasso said, "but
war is certainly present in my work". This
makes it easier to understand why the sym¬
bolism of suffering is most poignantly ex¬
pressed in the face of the most cherished
being. Reality for the artist meant the every¬
day universe, and a threat from any quarter
was directed first and foremost against the
loved one who shared his daily life. Above
all, his model, with whom he maintained a
permanent dialogue and whom he
ceaselessly questioned.
Of course, there are other examples of
such psychological motivation in Picasso's
work. It is understandable that a classical ar¬
tist conscious of his responsibility both as an
individual and to contemporary society
should strive to express in his painting the
horror he sees reflected in the human face,
or in inanimate objects a skull, a hunk of
bread, a candle and jug those still-lifes of
war which proclaim the drama being
enacted and the ordeals to come.
But Picasso's painting is that of a
humanist who counterbalances every reac¬
tion with its opposite. By this, I mean that
he had faith in man, and during the darkest
hours of the Second World War, his prewar
pessimism gave way to a more positive ap¬
proach. The year 1942 marked a return to his
great naturalistic figures, with Man Carrying
a Sheep (see illustration on page 38). In this
sculpture, as in the portraits of Dora painted
during the same period, twentieth century
humanism is expressed with immense force
and feeling. One portrait in particular a j
stern, stately figure whosei sombre, t
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
meditative face stands out against a
background partly blue and partly black-
strikingly evokes the transition from
darkness to light.
Such works are landmarks in helping to
understand Picasso's approach. They
enable one to view his creation as a series of
alternating styles and forms of expression,
sudden projections into the future, avant-
garde experiments, and reflections and
reversions.
Like Titian, he remained active as a
painter and creator to the end of his life,
forever examining and analysing his own
face. This can be seen in the self-portraits he
drew in pencil, where the features pro¬
gressively change, gradually taking on the
expression of death. Seated Man Wearing a
Hat (see back cover), most probably a self-
portrait, contains in brief the major themes -
of Picasso's painting. The old man seated in
an armchair, like a broken manikin disap¬
pearing beneath the paint, conjures up the
Harlequin of 1909 as well as the memory of
the crippled Renoir as Picasso himself
depicted him in 1919. It also contains an allu¬
sion to Matisse, whom Picasso evokes with
the Romanian blouse motif, and Van Gogh
with a straw hat. It epitomizes the tragedy of
the painter and painting expressed not in the
staid, academic strokes of an old man's
brush, but with all the vigour and freedom of
a young artist who has assimilated the ex¬
perience of his contemporaries and is con¬
fident that the work he is abandoning is as
alive and strong today as it was at the start
of his career. M
DOMINIQUE BOZO, of France, formerly cura¬
tor of the Musée National d'Art Moderne, Paris, is
at present curator of the Musée Picasso which is
to be opened in 1983. The new museum will .
house a vast collection of the great Spanish
artist's work (paintings, sculptures, papiers col¬
lés, sketchbooks and ceramics) as well as works
by other artists (Cézanne, Matisse, Renoir,'
Douanier-Rousseau) from his private collection,
handed over by his heirs to the Musées de France.
The new museum will be housed in an historic
17th century building, the Hôtel Salé.
Portrait of Renoir, 1919. Charcoal and pencil drawing, 61.2x49.1 cm. Towards the end of
his life Picasso painted Seated Man Wearing a Hat (see back cover), which, if not a self-
portrait in the strict sense, is the image of Picasso himself. It clearly harks back to this
drawing, made from a photograph fifty-two years earlier, of the great French painter
Auguste Renoir in the year of his death when his fingers were so paralyzed that he
worked with his brushes tied to his hand. After half a century the wheel had turned full
circle ; in Seated Man Wearing a Hat Picasso was bidding farewell to his art and to life.
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1980
January
AUSTRALIAN BARK PAINTING (K. Kupka). The games peoples play. What is play? Pal¬
ladio (R. Cevesel. To the North Pole on skis (D.I. Shparo). Valcamonica (E. Anati). Art
treasures: Ivory Portrait (Syria).
February-March
VICTORY IN NUBIA: EGYPT (S.A. Mohamed), SUDAN (N.E. Mohammed Sherif). 'A sin¬
gle, universal heritage...' (A.M. M'Bow). Temples rescued from the Nile (map). Nubia
unearthed (T. Säve-Söderbergh). Nubia's corridor of time (W.Y. Adams). Excavated sites
(map). Highlights of the expeditions. Philae (I.E.S. Edwards). Isis and Osiris (F. Daumas).
Abu Simbel (C. Desroches-Noblecourt). Sermons in stones (T. El Hakim). Nubia's flooded
fortresses (J. Vercoutterl. The blessed land (R.A. Fernea). Art treasures: Fiery steed from
Faras (Sudan).
April
HIGHLANDS AND ISLANDS: ECOSYSTEMS IN DANGER (F. di Castri and G. Glaser).
Unesco's Man and the Biosphere programme. The Bauhaus: Design for living in the
modern world. Kandinsky. Klee. Architects of an educational revolution (C. Schnaidt). Art
in everyday life. The geometry of the functional. Maestro computer (P. Boulez). Sex ste¬
reotypes in the classroom (F.E. Saunders). Art treasures: St. Sergius (USSR).
May
EARTH'S LIVING RESOURCES: A WORLD STRATEGY. Of mammoths and men
(M. Bâtisse). Against the grain. The preservation of genetic diversity. The return of the
native. The mighty minnow. The human touch (F. di Castri). Guidelines for environmental
education. Our evolutionary responsibility (0. Frankel). Living on borrowed time. A million
species threatened with extinction. The global commons. A world conservation strategy.
Art treasures: Owl-shaped wine jar (China).
June
LITERACY: GATEWAY TO FULFILMENT. A right denied to 800 million. Nicaragua's lite¬
racy campaign (appeal by the Director-General of Unesco). Literacy and the liberation of a
people (J. Cortázar). Nine award-winning campaigns (photos). Unwritten wisdom. 'I was
made to work like a plough' (Y. Selemani). Secrets of the written code (J. W. Ryan). The
three 'R's, an open book. Letters for a young nation (P. Freiré). UNWRA and Unesco: a
thirty-year partnership (H.H. Feridun). The reading habit. Art treasures: Madonna of Kruz¬
lowa (Poland).
July
THE INVISIBLE WOMAN (R. Stavenhagen). Yardsticks of social status IE.S. Solomon).
The plight of the woman bread-winner (M. Buvinic, N.H. Youssef and lisa Schumacher).
Women and apartheid (F. Ginwala and S. Mashiane). Women speak. Male chauvinism in
the mass media (M. Gallagher). Women in Soviet society today (A. Birman). Women and
the social sciences: Breaking the male stranglehold (M. Westkott). Africa (Z. Tadesse).
Asia (L. Dube). Latin America (L. Arizpe). Art treasures: Crowned head (Cyprus).
August
NATURE AND CULTURE: THE HUMAN HERITAGE. The international convention
(G. Bolla). A new partnership in the making (M. Bâtisse). The World Heritage List: the first
entries. Wonders of the world (G. Fradier).
September
DISARMAMENT EDUCATION. Education, disarmament and human rights (J. Torney and
L. Gambrell). World opinion, the weapon to end all weapons (L. Waldheim-Natural).
Disarmament education and social justice (J. Diaz). The structure of hunger (M. Huq).
Costa Rica, the country that abolished its army (J. Rodríguez Bolaños). Ten principles for
disarmament education. International law and the right to possess arms (B. Ruling). From
man of war to man of peace (H. Brabyn). Peace begins in the classroom (E. Sokolova and
I. Ivanyan). The Soviet Peace Fund (B. Polevoi). Teaching disarmament at universities
(world survey). Education for international understanding (P. Morren). Art treasures:
Twin-headed deity (France).
October
AVICENNA, A UNIVERSAL GENIUS (M.S. Asimov). My Odyssey (Avicenna). The Canon
of Medicine (H.S. Said). Notes and nostrums from Dr Avicenna's casebook (A. Aroua).
Al-Shifa, the world in a book 1 1. B. Madkur). A philosopher under fire (R. Davari). How Ibn
Sina became Avicenna (S. Gómez Nogales). A forerunner of modern science
(A.S. Sadykov). The secret of the stars (A.S. Unver). Art treasures: Ceramic from Samar¬
kand (USSR).
November
YUGOSLAVIA: A KALEIDOSCOPE OF CULTURES. I. The tides of history, II. The lan¬
guage of styles, III. Birthright of a modern State (M. Prelog). The fdrgotten army of child
workers. Stone Age myth-sculptors of Siberia (V.E. Laritchev). The psychology of mar¬
bles (J. Piaget). Art treasures: St. Benedict, patron saint of Europe (Italy).
December
PICASSO. The Blue and Rose Periods (V. Suslov). Les Demoiselles d'Avignon
(S. Amon). The use of distortions (J. Golding). Guernica (J. Palau y Fabre, T. Okamoto).
Beauty and the beast (R. Penrose). Picasso the sculptor (J. Gallego). Portraits of women
(D. Bozo). The post-Cubist Picasso (A. Cirici Pellicer). An African appreciation
(K.S. Beseat).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. - BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. - CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking -
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue PO Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display): Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. - Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK!
Munksgaard Export and Subscription Service, 35 Norre Sogade
DK 1370, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF)!
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O.
Box 2996,. Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja¬
kauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP.
12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leip¬
zig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhand¬
lungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the
Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): Deutscher Unesco - Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D-5300 Bonn 3. For scientific maps only: GEO
CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications:
S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9,
Postach 2, 8034 Germering/München. - GHANA. Presby¬
terian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra: Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HKI Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowlopn. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kônyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. - INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamah'i Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1 ; 80/ 1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, 8angalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. - IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P.O. Box
. 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
Mckenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. - JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. - LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. - LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. -
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. - MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout 9
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddiné
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing. Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland- 130
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street,' P.o'
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin-
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; /The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. - NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
- PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahtah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé. -
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chrttampalam
Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Saiaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt. Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmin¬
gham, Bristol. -UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue
South, New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Trg Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba
Slovenje, Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana. - ZIMBABWE.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
ï
s
Vf
\
Portraits of the artist
Picasso produced scores of self-portraits
in the course of his long existence, rang¬
ing from youthful sketches to canvases
painted in very old age. Each phase in his
life and work yielded its own distinctive
image of the artist. Portraits shown here
are from three different periods in his
development. Top left, a Self-Portrait
painted in 1901. It depicts Picasso aged
twenty at the beginning of his "Blue
Period", and is marked by the influence of
the painters he admired as a young man,
notably Toulouse-Lautrec and Van Gogh.
Self-Portrait, above, dates from the spring
of 1907, around the time when Picasso
was working on his painting Les Demoi¬
selles d'Avignon, a landmark of
twentieth-century art. The resemblance
between this depiction of the artist and
the figures in Les Demoiselles is striking.
Left, Seated Man Wearing a Hat, an oil
painting completed in November 1971
when Picasso was over ninety, is from the
last stage in his prolific career.
]]>
</page>
</document>
