<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074768eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window
open on the world
t
i
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
(Q
Pakistan
Mother and child
from Mohenjodaro
Mohenjadaro, in the Indus
Valley, was a centre of one of
the world's great early
civilizations, which blossomed
between 2500 and 1500 BC.
Since then the water table in
this region has risen and
Mohenjodaro's ruins today rest
on a quagmire ; salts left behind
when the sun evaporates the
water are eating away like a
cancer at the ancient bricks.
Unesco is actively collaborating
in efforts to preserve
Mohenjodaro, whose artists and
craftsmen were past masters at
using clay, not only for building
but for fashioning household
objects and a host of curious
figurines. Shown here,
terracotta figure of a mother
bearing her child in the crook of
her arm. Throughout 1979
International Year of the Child,
the Unesco Courier will devote
its "Treasures of World Art"
feature to works of art depicting
children.
Photo © A. Martin, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUIíer
JANUARY 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.: (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
Assistant Editor-in-chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editor :
Editors:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Gillian Whitcomb
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Peter Mwombela (Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 THE SILENCED MAJORITY
Two thousand million children
in search of their rights
by Elise Bou/ding
CRADLED IN HUNGER
Half the world's children under six
are victims of malnutrition
by Fernando Monckeberg Barros
13 THE STING IN THE FAIRY TALE
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
17 THE ROAD TO SELF-EXPRESSION
Awakening the latent language skills
of handicapped children
by Anne McKenna
18 DECLARATION OF THE RIGHTS OF THE CHILD
23 MAKING TOYS IS CHILD'S PLAY
Photo story
27 WHAT'S IN A NAME?
by Hélène Gratiot Alphandéry
32 CHILDREN IN THE NEVER, NEVER LAND OF EXILE
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
PAKISTAN: Mother and child from Mohenjodaro
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Cover
To mark the opening of 1979, proclaimed
International Year of the Child by the United
Nations, this issue of the Unesco Courier
examines some of the problems which must
be tackled in order to promote the welfare of
disadvantaged children in many parts of the
world. In 1959 the United Nations adopted a
Magna Carta for children, the Declaration of
the Rights of the Child (for full text see pages
18-19), but today, 20 years later, these rights
are in many cases still In abeyance if not
blatantly violated. The Unesco Courier
intends to devote other issues and articles
later in the year to less sombre aspects of the
world of childhood.
Photo P. Frey © Sipa Presse, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
If all the children in the world
under the age of fourteen were to
stand one on another's shoulders
they would form a column
stretching about three and a half
times the mean distance from the
earth to the moon.
Drawing © Sophie and David Brabyn, aged 7
THE International Year of the Child is
not only an occasion to consider the
needs of children in a world all too
full of violence, hunger and social depriv¬
ation, it is also an occasion to note the
many things that children and young peo¬
ple contribute to the lives of adults their
imagination, their sensitivity, their capacity
for work and play and invention. It is time
to celebrate their presence on the great
wheel of life along which we all move, and
their partnership in creating the world we
live in.
In the eyes of the law, particularly in the
Western world, persons remain "children"
until they reach the legal age of majority.
Only then do they have full rights of con¬
tract and social choice. There is a great
contrast between what children really do in
the world, and what the law permits. Most
adults, even those that are parents, are
largely unaware of this contradiction. In
what follows the young are presented as
thinkers and doers, as shapers of society.
Ageism is a new word in the new human
rights vocabulary. Unesco documents
about youth sometimes use the term "anti-
youth racialism," to refer to the hostility
toward youth which is expressed both in
public policy and private utterance.
The silenced
Two thousand million children
in search of their rights
by Elise Boulding
elderly to do what they want them to do
without using force. The alternative rela¬
tionship of mutual respect and mutual sup¬
port for continued growth throughout life
is all too rarely seen.
Most Western adults would not dare to
talk to their peers the way they talk to chil¬
dren. Nor would they accept the ¡nterrup-
ELISE BOULDING, U.S. sociologist, is secretary of
the Programme Advisory Council of the United Nations
University's Human and Social Development Pro¬
gramme. She has carried out many transnational stu¬
dies on conflict and peace, development, family life and
women in society and is the author of The Underside of
History: A View of Women through Time, a study of
women's social, economic and political roles over four
millennia. Her study Children's Rights and the Wheel of
Life, written especially for the International Year of the
Child, will be published later this year by Transaction
Press, New Brunswick, New Jersey, U.S.A.
tions, corrections, demands for attentive-
ness and instant displays of affection that
children accept as a matter of course.
The theme of all human rights cove¬
nants, and the motif of all liberation move¬
ments, is participation in the shaping of
one's own life and that of the society
around one, and reasonable access to the
resources that will make that participation
possible. In the case of children, either it is
true that they are ignorant and incapable of
significant social participation, and must be
segregated from the adult world until the
age of majority, or they are developing their
ability to participate from early childhood
and should be involved in decision-making
in the family and public spheres to an
extent determined by their interest and abi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
"Ageism" is a better term because it covers
both ends of the age spectrum. Hostility
toward the elderly receives more guarded
expression, but it too is present. Ageism is
the denial of certain rights and responsibili¬
ties to persons simply because of their age.
Emphasizing the "responsibility" compo¬
nent of the word rights helps us to see how
inappropriate it is to conceive of rights as
offering only protection. Even the most
democratic society has strong authoritarian
elements, particularly when it is wearing its
protective face. The individual to be pro¬
tected has no option but to receive that
protection when and how the protecting
institutions of a society decree. As the
Unesco 1972 Report on Rights and Res¬
ponsibilities of Youth says, "Seen in this
light, the responsibilities of young people,
instead of meaning an opportunity for the
young to take the initiative in actions which
concern them and which ultimately con¬
cern society as a whole, seem more like
duties imposed on them by adult
society the duty of submission to the
authority of the family, the community or
the State; the duty to receive education
devised in the main by adults or not
receive it if they belong to underprivileged
social groups; the duty to work, often at an
early age and under harsh conditions, or,
conversely, to be the first to be affected by
unemployment; the duty, lastly, to respect
a world order established independently of
them and which is becoming more and
more alien to them."
In striking at the roots of ageism we
strike at the drive to dominate, to mould
others. Authority, power, statuswords
we could not do without in describing
modern social organization turn sour
under examination when we consider
parent-child relations, or adult-elderly rela¬
tions. Authority is the power of people in
their middle years to get children and the
Photo © Ed van der Elsken, Edam, The Netherlands
Children make up over fifty per cent
of the population of the world, yet
they have little say even in the
ordering of their own lives. During
the International Year of the Child,
the attention of the world will be
focused on this "silenced majority" ir
an attempt to ensure worldwide
compliance with the articles of the
United Nations Declaration of the
Rights of the Child (see page 18).
lity. If the latter is true, some substantial
changes in the current United Nations
Declaration of the Rights of the Child, and
in associated concepts of the rights and
responsibilities of children in families and
communities will be required, both in cus¬
tom and in law.
More than that, some substantial
changes in our conception of society and
the civic order will also be required. Since
children represent well over fifty per cent of
the world's population at present, and are
completely excluded from the reporting,
evaluating and policy-making processes of
every society, an opening up of these pro¬
cesses to all young persons able to express
interest and concern, of whatever age,
would in the long run represent a revolu
tion of unimaginable proportions in every
country in the world, to say nothing of the
United Nations itself.
The Year of the Child can be the occa¬
sion for a basic rethinking of personhood
and human rights because it points to the
only minority human condition that is uni¬
versally experienced, childhood, and the
only human process that is universally
experienced, aging. Here is an opportunity
for every individual to link, in imagination,
his or her own personal life span with those
of the young and old among us today, to
re-experience and rethink the familiar old
dominance patterns, and see afresh what
they mean in terms of stunted physical,
social and spiritual growth for everyone.
The same exercises of power that limit
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
y personhood also support institutions and
processes of social and economic injustice.
Children, adults and elderly alike fall sick,
go hungry, die prematurely as a result of
war, disease and hunger, because
dominance/submission, centre/periphery,
haves/ have-nots struggles are played out
within and between nations as well as in
families and local communities. The young
and the old belong to the world's periphery
and they are always the first to go hungry,
especially if they are poor; and most of the
world's poor are either very young or very
old.
The arena of public policy is both the
first and the last place to look for signifi¬
cant social change toward a more just
social order. If "United Nations Years"
mean anything, they mean an opportunity
to re-examine ends and means with regard
to policy issues. The International Year of
the Child offers policy-makers a fresh place
to start with issues of human welfare: at
the point where child, adult and local com¬
munity relationships intersect. A change in
social attitudes toward children would
affect every nook and cranny of society,
and every person in it.
Adult-child relationships offer a critical
intervention point for breaking the vicious
circle of dominance behaviour that per¬
vades public and international life. These
patterns are laid down in the home every
day through the inappropriate exercise of
power, invisibly interwoven with the acts
of human caring that sustain the institution
of the family as a continuously viable set¬
ting for human growth. We may be unne¬
cessarily sabotaging our present and our
children's future by being blind to the
inconsistencies and irrationalities of the
relations between adults and children in
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
family and community in this century.
Mass media programmes about the right to
a happy and secure childhood, and to a
happy and secure retirement, are no substi¬
tute for the actual experience of frank and
honest confrontation between generations
when perceptions, needs and interests dif¬
fer, in a context of mutual acceptance of
responsibility for each other. Neither can
special feeding, health and education pro¬
grammes undertaken for children be a
substitute for joint community projects car¬
ried out by adults and children together, in
which the capacity of the young to contri¬
bute to the welfare of all receives full reco¬
gnition.
We pride ourselves in the West on
having applied the findings of a century of
child development research to the handling
of infants, children and youth. We have
structured their environments, designed
their toys and learning materials, analyzed
their readiness to receive teaching of
varying degrees of complexity. We are the
potters, they are the clay. The friends of
children in every age have always intuitively
known that there was more to it than that.
New findings are emerging from child
development laboratories that point to an
autonomous self-organized learning pro¬
cess that begins with birth and can be
easily interfered with by adults who treat
the newborn as a blind and cuddly bit of
protoplasm. Observant workers with pre¬
school children are noting the self-
organizing nature of their learning, the
complexity of judgements about body
movements in time and space that they can
develop when not over-organized in their
activity, the sensitive mutual aid that goes
on among them when they are left free to
solve their own problems. We are also
Article 9 of the Declaration of the
Rights of the Child declares: "...The
child shall not be admitted to
employment before an appropriate
minimum age; he shall in no case
be caused or permitted to engage
in any occupation or employment
which would prejudice his health or
education, or interfere with his
physical, mental or moral
development." Official figures for
children under fifteen in the labour
force are relatively low, but they
represent only the tip of the
Iceberg; many children work
unrecorded, whether for their own
parents or as paid labourers,
particularly in the world's rural
areas where they often work in the
fields or help with the housework.
In urban areas the children of the
poor comb the streets in search of
food and odd jobs. t «%**>v^.t.-.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-General of Unesco
It is an oft-repeated truth that children are the hope of our world. Let us make sure during
the International Year of the Child, and in every year that follows, that the world's
children know how much we adults care about and work for their happiness. And let this
year's activities help us also better to understand children and to remember, when we
deal with them, what it was like when we were children. In this way we can avoid
inflicting the pain suffered by so many children in so many countries of the world. I
would like to think that when the International Year of the Child comes to an end, we will
be able to believe that our world has become more brotherly, more united, thanks to the
understanding we will have gained of children and the greater tolerance we will have
taught them.
k rediscovering how children create the
world anew through play. The role of this
most spontaneous of human activities in
the continuous re-creation of society by its
youngest members, is perhaps the major
discovery of the twentieth century.
If we go back to the pre-industrial era in
Europe, and to less industrialized Third
World countries today, we can see people
aged from ten to twelve and over functio¬
ning as adults with full responsibility for
themselves and contributing to the econo¬
mic welfare of family and workplace. The
film. Invention of the Adolescent, pro¬
duced by the Canadian Broadcasting Corp¬
oration in 1970, documents the transition
from pre-industrial to post-industrial
society for children of the first world, and
shows how recent and contrived is our
¡mage of the adolescent as immature and
irresponsible.
At present, adults professionally concer¬
ned with children are somewhat confused
about what position they should take in
regard to child labour. Much of the spirit of
protection that we see in the 1970s stems
from the necessary drive to protect children
from the abuses of an earlier era of the
industrial revolution. Today's generation of
middle-class children in the urban areas of
both the more and less industrialized coun¬
tries are told to run and play, or to study
more. The children of the poor comb the
streets for odd jobs or adventure. Most of
these children feel trapped, whether in the
streets, in the playroom or in the school¬
room, and would love to have their own
job. Their despair is variously exhibited in
high frequencies of suicide, or drug and
alchohol use, and in rising school drop-out
rates.
Why this despair? Play is an empty word
in the absence of free spaces where a child
can shape her environment to suit her
needs and desires. A recent Unesco study
of urban children in different world regions
by Kevin Lynch, Growing Up in Cities,
brings this out with startling clarity.
The situation is different in the country¬
side. In the world's rural areas most chil¬
dren are expected to be at work by ten or
twelve years of age. In fact, they are fre¬
quently at work from the age of five. Boys
work in the fields, girls help with younger
children, and help in household and field
work also. They have always done so, from
earliest times. With urbanization, working
conditions become harderwhether in tra¬
ditional settlements or modern cities. In the
era of the 1970s, when a high social value is
set on keeping children in school, there is
little incentive to report child labour, and
most children work unrecorded, whether
for their own parents or as wage labourers.
If there has been confusion about poli¬
cies regarding children and youth in the
labour force, there has never been any con¬
fusion about policies regarding military ser¬
vice of young persons. Minors have always
been put into armies, and there have been
many teenage military heroes in history. A
substantial part of the burden of national
defence in the modern world therefore
rests on the shoulders of youth under
twenty-one.
We are so accustomed to legal and social
rhetoric about protecting minors that we
forget that a lot of the work of rearing and
protecting the young is done by persons
who are themselves still minors. In 1976,
delegates from thirty-nine countries atten¬
ded a Conference held in the U.S.A. on
Right, a young girl lavishes her
affection on something that was
once a doll. Almost thirteen
million of the sixty million
women who had babies in 1975
became mothers before they
became adults. Not only is the
adolescent mother physically at
risk, she also faces enormous
social and legal handicaps.
Unmarried teenage mothers and
their children. In particular, are
among the most disadvantaged
categories of minors despite the
fact that the first article of the
Declaration of the Rights of the
Child calls for equal rights for all
children regardless of the
circumstances of their birth.
adolescent fertility. According to the Con¬
ference report, entitled Eleven Million Teen¬
agers, close to 13 million of the 60 million
women who became mothers in 1975
became parents before they became
adults. Early child-bearing is increasing
everywhere, is emerging as a serious pro¬
blem in many countries, and has reached
alarming levels in others where it is associa¬
ted with serious health, socio-economic
and demographic implications for young
women, young men, their offspring, and,
indeed, for the whole society.
One significant aspect of teenage preg¬
nancy is that it is not simply a phenomenon
of less industrialized countries, but of the
most industrialized countries, with the Uni¬
ted States a leading producer of teen¬
age child-bearers. Childbearing before the
age of twenty involves high risk to the
mother, and considerably lowered chances
of survival for the infant. Yet in many coun¬
tries large numbers of teenage girls take
these risks, at least in part because their
status as minors prevents them from gain¬
ing access to the preventive measures they
CONTINUED PAGE 34
^¡r ,-f"
F ^M^M^MwMmL
ML
f
¡Nelson©Magnum,P Is
1^ 1
jv
A^i
c
.c
o
->
o
o
.Ci^H
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Twenty lucky ones with
enough to eat in the
world today some 100
million children under the
age of five suffer from
malnutrition.
by Fernando
Monckeberg Barros
Cradled in hunger
Half the world's children under six
are victims of malnutrition
THE care and protection of children
has always been a major preoccupa¬
tion of human society, and this
concern has found expression in the atten¬
tion lavished on children during the early
part of their lives. Since human beings are
born helpless and without defence, the
species is of necessity endowed with a
strong maternal instinct.
As man has progressed and as society
has become more complex, the need to
extend this care and protection to older
children has become apparent. With the
increase of knowledge it has become evi¬
dent that the social environment is a key
factor in the all round development of the
FERNANDO MONCKEBERG BARROS, Chilean pae¬
diatrician and former professor at the universities of
Chile and Harvard, is the author of a large number of
articles and books on problems of food and nutrition,
many of which, such as his Checkmate to Underdeve¬
lopment, have been published in English. He has served
on severe! Unicef and World Health Organization com¬
mittees and is a member of many Chilean, Latin Ameri¬
can and North American scientific societies.
child and in his or her future prospects as
an adult. It is not surprising, therefore,
that, as early as 1924, the "Rights of the
Child" were proclaimed in Geneva or that
later, in 1959, these rights were unani¬
mously adopted by the United Nations.
Principle no. 4 of the Declaration of the
Rights of the Child refers specifically to the
care and protection of the child and the
mother: "The child shall enjoy the benefits
of social security. He shall be entitled to
grow and develop in health; to this end
special care and protection shall be pro¬
vided both to him and to his mother, in¬
cluding adequate pre-natal and post-natal
care. The child shall have the right to ade¬
quate nutrition, housing, recreation and
medical services."
However, as we reach the twentieth
anniversary of the United Nations Declara¬
tion, it must be admitted that the rights of
the child are by no means fully exercised
and that for far too high a proportion of
children they remain no more than a decla¬
ration of principle.
The enormous amount of knowledge
acquired and applied over recent decades
has resulted in substantial social advances
from which children as well as adults have
benefited. During the seventeenth century,
for example, the child mortality rate in
Europe is estimated to have been in the
region of 500 per thousand; already by the
end of the nineteenth century this had been
reduced to 200 per thousand. Recent esti¬
mates fix the current world infant mortality
rate at 98 per thousand, although it is true
that this average figure conceals variations
in rates ranging from 10 per thousand in
some countries to 200 per thousand in
others.
Nevertheless, as a result of the tremen¬
dous population explosion that has occur¬
red during the twentieth century, there
have never before been so many children
suffering from poverty and malnutrition. It
is estimated that 500 million people in the
world today, most of them children, are
suffering from malnutrition and that a fur¬
ther 2,000 million are suffering from under- .
nourishment. I
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
y Research carried out in recent years indi¬
cates that a child can be at risk from malnu¬
trition even before birth and that the
growth of the child within the womb
depends upon the mother's state of nour¬
ishment. The outward indication of this
condition is a sub-normal birth-weight
(below two and a half kilos). Whilst in
industrialized countries only two or three
per cent of children are born under-weight,
in the developing countries the proportion
is between twenty and thirty per cent.
These figures do not refer to premature
infants but to those suffering from pre¬
natal malnutrition as a result of inadequate
nourishment of the mother.
Children born under-weight run a very
grave risk of illness and death. Among
those that survive, abnormalities of growth
and development have been noted. In
many cases the head is smaller than
average and psychomotor difficulties are
apparent.
Today, many children are born into an
unfavourable environment. Lack of ade¬
quate food delays both their physical and
their mental development and reduces their
resistance to disease.
The most recent studies show that lack
of food is not the only problem; other fac¬
tors, such as lack of affection and of men¬
tal and social stimulation, also have a nega¬
tive effect on the child's intellectual and
physical development. Families living in
poverty are affected by all these factors.
Thus poverty in itself, with all that it
implies, is a direct cause of psychomotor
retardation in the child.
The sombre, crushing, twilight world of
poverty provides no stimulation for the
child's curiosity or imagination. It is a world
from which everything bright and colourful
is banished and in which games and other
stimuli so necessary to the development of
the child's natural capacities are exceed¬
ingly rare. Furthermore, the parents' lan¬
guage ability is often limited and their chil¬
dren lack verbal stimulation. The ties bet¬
ween child and adult are weak and, in
general, there is little common family acti¬
vity. Love and understanding are reduced
to a minimum and the child feels perma¬
nently unprotected and insecure.
As well as retarding psychomotor deve¬
lopment, all this affects the child's persona¬
lity and results in a lack of self-esteem. In
conditions of poverty the family structure
usually becomes heavily distorted; the
father's image is debased or is non¬
existent. Thus, in the end, it is the crushing
weight of poverty which causes retardation
of the child's psychomotor development
and which leads finally to what might be
summed up as "society-induced/
biological" damage.
It is this damage which later will make it
difficult for the child to become a fully inte¬
grated, useful member of society. In Latin
America, for example, of every hundred
children who manage to embark on primary
education only ten complete it. There are
many possible causes for this high drop¬
out rate, but the most important is the
intellectual limitation which prevents so
many children from matching up to the
requirements of a normal education.
There are several degrees of underdeve¬
lopment. In some countries the situation is
desperate; in others a certain level of deve¬
lopment has been achieved. The poorest
countries have been defined as those in
which the annual income per head of the
population is less than three hundred dol¬
lars. These countries account for fifty-six
per cent of the population of the develo¬
ping world and include: Afghanistan, Ban¬
gladesh, Burma, Cameroon, Ethiopia,
Ghana, Guatemala, India, Madagascar,
Mali, Mozambique, Nepal, Pakistan, Sri
It can today be asserted that approxima¬
tely half the children of the world under the
age of six present some degree of malnutri¬
tion and that, as a result, their health and
the development of their overall genetic
potential is endangered. This is clear evi¬
dence that the proclaimed rights of children
remain, in reality, a dead letter.
For the child, the family unit forms a
micro-climate, an ecosystem which, when
all its different elements are in harmony,
provides the setting for balanced, integra¬
ted development. On the other hand, when
the ecosystem is not in equilibrium,
because basic needs cannot be met, the
effect is disastrous for the child and will
probably lead to irreparable damage. The
child's possibilities for development are
limited and the child becomes an easy prey
to illness or to early death.
Estimated numbers of children aged 0-4 years suffering from severe or moderate protein-calorie malnutrition
(PCM) in three regions of the world
Region
Latin America
^
Africa
1
Asia (excluding China
and J
Total
Severe PCM
700 000.
2 700 000
6000000
I
9400 000
I
Moderate PCM
9 000000
16000000
64000000
89000000
Total
9 700 000
18 700 000
70 000000
98400 000
Source : WHO Chronicle, No. 1 Vol 28, Jan 1974
Lanka, Sudan, Tanzania, Uganda and
Upper Volta.
In these countries, the percentage of
children suffering from the ravages of
poverty is very high. Thus, for example,
between twenty-six and fifty-four per cent
of children under six years of age suffer
from malnutrition and almost all of them
are affected by undernutrition to a greater
or lesser degree. Almost all of them are
retarded in their physical development as
can be seen from the fact that they are
below average height for their age.
In the other developing countries, the
percentage of severe to moderate malnutri¬
tion varies from fifteen to twenty-five per
cent.
In the developing world, a very high per¬
centage of families is unable to satisfy basic
needs: housing, education, cultural needs,
health and nutrition.
All these basic needs are important, but
paramount among them is the need to eat.
Why do so many families fail to meet this
need? There may be many reasons, but the
root of the problem is neither ignorance nor
lack of access to adequate foodstuffs, but
that such families simply do not possess
sufficient means to obtain a healthy and
balanced diet.
Ignorance or cultural barriers may com¬
plicate matters further, but a simple mathe¬
matical calculation is enough to show that
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
in most cases malnutrition is a result of low
family income. In this situation it is always
the child who suffers most, for he depends
on other people to provide him with food
and is growing so quickly that he needs a
high level of nutrition.
Studies of the diet of different social
groups in poor countries show that there is
a close link between the income of the
family and the amount of calories it con¬
sumes. Quality of diet, consumption of cal¬
ories and animal protein are directly propor¬
tionate to the level of income.
In the social structure of underdevelop¬
ment, incomes are almost always unjustly
distributed; the lion's share tends to be
concentrated among a small segment of
the population. Even so, this is not the
main reason why lower income groups are
unable to get an adequate diet. In almost all
developing countries (except for the oil-
producing countries) the revenues simply
do not exist. Even if the national revenues
of these countries were equitably shared
out, it would only be an equitable distribu¬
tion of poverty.
In the United States in 1970 the average
annual outlay on food was just over six
hundred dollars per head, a figure much
higher than the total average per capita
income in almost all the developing coun¬
tries at that time. Even today over half the
population of the developing world have an
income under three hundred dollars a year.
The average United States citizen
spends 16.8 per cent of his income on
food. In Latin America and India, however,
incomes are low and a much higher propor¬
tion must be devoted to food: 64 per cent
in Latin America and over 84 per cent in
India. Even so, 46 per cent of Latin Ameri¬
cans and 78 per cent of Indians consume
less than the number of calories recom¬
mended, by FAO (the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations) and
WHO (the World Health Organization).
There is no way for the children of the
poor countries to enjoy their rights to the
full unless there is a substantial increase in
the gross national product of these coun¬
tries and unless steps are taken to distri¬
bute national income more equitably within
them. As long as poverty and misery per¬
sist, the rights of the child will be nothing
but a piece of rhetoric.
As far as the future is concerned, the
biggest question-mark is that which hangs
over the size of tomorrow's world popula¬
tion. According to United Nations fore¬
casts, demographic growth between now
and the year 2000 will run at an annual two
per cent, which means that world popula¬
tion will rise from 4,000 million to 6,257 mil¬
lion. Of this increase, only 250 million will
be in the industrially developed world;
2,000 million will be in the developing
countries.
According to FAO figures, world foodw
production is theoretically sufficient to pro- f
Carlos Andrés Peréz, President of the Republic of Venezuela
In the Third World, to which our country belongs, more than fifty per cent of children
under six years of age suffer from some degree of malnutrition, thus indicating the sad
tragedy of the future. I believe that child care is an obligation for the whole world, and
that the industrialized nations should think of our children when they pay the prices of
our raw materials and when they sell us at extremely high and increasing costs the
finished products and capital goods which permit our progress.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
vide adequate nourishment for everyone on
earth. In practice, however, the popula¬
tions of the rich countries currently enjoy a
diet which is usually much more than capa¬
ble of meeting their basic needs, while the
diet available to the people of developing
countries is totally inadequate.
The world's cultivated land today
amounts to 1,400 million hectares, and this
area could be extended to 2,300 million
hectares. Most of this virgin land is in
Africa and Latin America.
The yield of land now being cultivated
could also be considerably increased, but
attempts to boost productivity should be
largely concentrated in the developing
countries since yields in the rich countries
are already high.
It has been estimated that some 700,000
million dollars must be invested in order to
double food production between now and
the end of the century. Most of this must
go to the developing countries, which will
require an average of 32,000 million dollars
a year. They will be unable to find this out
of their own pockets, and the money will
have to come from the industrialized world.
The figure may seem high, but it is only
one-tenth of the world's current annual
expenditure on arms.
In the poor countries, insufficient food
output is only one aspect of a serious social
and economic problem whose complexity
varies from country to country. A variety of
conditions and problems are found in the
developing world. Some developing coun¬
tries are overpopulated, whereas in others
there is room for population growth. Some
dispose of abundant and unexploited
resources, others have practically none. In
some poverty and malnutrition are despera¬
tely serious problems, while others are in a
stage of "intermediate" development.
Some have a subsistence economy, others
have already embarked on industrialization.
In some the population is overwhelmingly
rural, in others the number of town- and
city-dwellers is mounting rapidly. Each
country has different prospects for the
future.
But whatever their situation, they all
need large-scale capital investment and
new technologies. The industrially develo¬
ped countries could provide this aid, but so
far they have been extremely reluctant to
loosen their purse-strings. Those who pos¬
sess an advanced technology do not find it
easy to give it away; on the contrary, they
use their know-how as an effective new
instrument for boosting profits.
And so if all the world's children do not
yet enjoy the "Rights of the Child", it is not
for lack of human ingenuity but because
mankind is not yet fully determined to fight
for the cause. The profound humanitarian
impulse which the task requires has not yet
been born. The necessary generosity and
willingness to make sacrifices for others
still do not exist. Is it too much to ask that
some give up a modicum of their comfort
so that the quality of life of others may be
improved?
In 1963 the General Assembly of the Uni¬
ted Nations recommended that the indus¬
trialized countries devote at least one per
cent of their gross national product to
helping the developing countries. Fifteen
years have gone by and this paltry sacrifice
is still far from a reality. None of the rich
countries is yet committed to devoting this
small proportion of their GNP to develop¬
ment aid.
Of course, this spirit of humanitarian
solidarity should not be confined to the
international scene; it should also infuse
developing countries where the few live off
the fat of the land at the expense of the
many who endure wretched living condi¬
tions.
History provides abundant examples of
mankind's immense capacity for solving
problems which once seemed insurmoun¬
table. Will mankind take up this challenge
and respond to this crisis of our times?
Today when the very existence of our spe¬
cies is threatened, the time has come to
transform hopes into realities.
Femando Monckeberg Barros
His Majesty King Bhumibol Adulyadej of Thailand
Older people, who have experience of life, have a duty to help and support those who
follow by transferring to them their knowledge, goodness and valuable experiences in a
sincere, compassionate and affectionate spirit. In this way the young will achieve
knowledge and understanding and most important of all will learn to reason correctly,
attaining an enlightenment which enables them to distinguish between what is
progressive and what is degrading.
"The little girl was scared to light the firecracker. Her brother was trying to give a helping
hand", ran the photographer's description of the scene below. Firework-time is only one of
many occasions when children must act with the utmost care. Every year many thousands
of young people die or are maimed in fires or explosions, on the roads, from drowning and
from accidents in the home. Photo is a prize-winning entry in a 1978 photo contest on the
theme of "Children of Asia" organized by the Asian Cultural Centre for Unesco in
collaboration with the Japanese National Commission for Unesco and several private
organizations in Japan.
Photo © Ee Hon Teck, Singapore
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The
sting
in the
fairy
tale
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
Photo © R. Canessa, Toulon
IF, as has been said, more children have
been lulled to sleep by the gentle balm
of fairies' smiles than have been kept
quiveringly awake by the grimly staring
eyes of ogres, then perhaps it is time to
examine more closely the instructions for
use, the side effects and the contra¬
indications of this balm, this drug which,
since it was first imported two centuries
ago, has been the bed-time tranquillizer of
Latin America.
Fairy tales probably reached Latin Ame¬
rica towards the end of the eighteenth
century at the same time as such "contra¬
band" cultural shipments as the works of
the Encyclopédistes, the ideas of the
JORGE ENRIQUE ADOUM, Ecuadorian poet and
writer, has published several volumes of poetry, inclu¬
ding an anthology. Informe Personal Sobre La Situa¬
ción (Personal Report on the Situation, Madrid, 19731.
His play about the Spanish conquest of the Inca empire,
published in English as The Sun Trampled Beneath the
Horses' Hooves (The Massachusetts Review, Winter-
Spring 19741 has also been translated into French, Swe¬
dish and Polish and performed in several countries of
Europe and Latin America. He has taken- part in
Unesco's programme of studies on Latin America cul¬
tures, and is now a member of the editorial staff of the
Unesco Courier.
French Revolution and the Declaration of
the Rights of Man and of the Citizen. They
arrived so opportunely as a means of
shoring up the colonial regime whose
downfall this other literature was intended
to help bring about that it might well be
asked whether they were not deliberately
despatched with this aim by the Spanish
Crown.
Unlike Asia, the Latin America of that
time had no established literary tradition
(and tales for children should be conside¬
red as part of general literature) and, unlike
Africa, was not endowed with a particularly
strong oral tradition. The legends, myths
and traditions of the native Indians which
still survive in the countryside, though with
great difficulty since the Indian took ven¬
geance on his conquerors with the weapon
of silence are not, properly speaking,
tales for children. Passing, it must be sup¬
posed, from the wealthy Creole's library to
his children's nursery, thence via the wet-
nurse or the cook to other households,
fairy tales finally filtered down through the
country schoolteacher to reach the minds
and imagination of village children.
Charles Perrault's Tales of Past Time, by
Mother Goose not only marked the begin¬
ning of fairy-tale literature, but was the
example of it most widely distributed in
Latin America. Written in 1697, at the
height of French territorial expansion under
Louis XIV, when the author, a high functio¬
nary and former protégé of Colbert, was
sixty-nine years old, the Tales were signed
by his ten-year-old son Perrault d'Arman-
cour, dedicated to a princess and intended
for use at the court of Versailles.
Already the serpent can be discerned
coiled within the egg! Literature written by
an adult and imbued with the ideology of a
courtier, was presented as being the work
of a child, that is, for children and intended
for the edification and amusement of prin¬
cesses; its purpose is evident, the exalta¬
tion of the divine right of kings and the
inculcation of devotion to the institutions
this right represented and on which it
reposed.
Adults propagated and imposed these
tales on their children at their most vulnera¬
ble age, preferring them to others and erec¬
ting their own experience into an educatio-
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
nal standard and making education a bas¬
tion of the sovereignty of the grown-up.
Believing that these tales were edifying
they became veritable colonizers of the
infant mind.
It would be not only stupid but cruel to
demand of these stories an implacable real¬
ism, thus denying men and, even worse,
children the right to dream. The child's per¬
ception of reality is more limited than that
of an adult, yet this does not mean that a
vast area of the child's mind is no more
than a desert; on the contrary, it is an area
peopled with images infinitely richer than
those that could be implanted there by the
impoverished imagination of an adult.
Because he lacks any basis for compari¬
son and judgement, the child tends to con¬
fuse the literary content of tales with
reality. Thus by imposing on the child an
imaginary reality which not only replaces
"real" reality but also his own fantasies,
the adult obliges him to identify himself
with characters and a context completely
outside his experience and which will be of
little use to him when the time comes for
him to face up to the problems of daily life.
"At one time or another", says Bruno
Bettelheim, "every child dreams of being a
prince or a princess." Yet what child of the
tropical plains or plateaux of Latin America
would ever have dreamed of such a thing if
these images had not been imposed upon
him, images made much more concrete by
Gustave Doré's at times gruesome engra¬
vings and Walt Disney's cloying cartoons
and made superficially more real by the
stage versions of these tales in which
schoolchildren are obliged to take part?
Given the authors and the immediate
audience for whom they were writing, the
kings and queens, princes and princesses
who figure in these tales were inevitably
generous and charitable, beloved of their
subjects and respected by their peers. They
had neither armies nor police forces (at
most a few kind-hearted gamekeepers) and
they never declared war. Only rarely were
their subjects sent to prison or to the exe¬
cutioner's block, and then only through the
spiteful machinations of a wicked step¬
mother. The queens and princesses,
moreover, were all remarkable for their
beauty. The young Latin American was not
slow in recognizing that, in comparison
14
with the realities of his life, all this was
nothing more than a huge adult lie.
In European fairy tales, which draw on
Scandinavian, German and Slav traditions,
the characters are naturally white-skinned,
blue-eyed and fair-haired (with the sole
exception of Snow White whose hair was
"as black as ebony"). Yet in Latin Ameri¬
can society, where economic discrimina¬
tion almost always goes hand in hand with
discrimination of a racial nature, the tacit
identification of this type of beauty with
goodness may have undesirable repercus¬
sions. Young indigenous and mixed-race
Latin Americans who, quite naturally,
reject this discrimination may tend to deve¬
lop a sense of inferiority, especially since at
school and in daily life they are already set
apart by the more or less white children
whose servants they often are.
In the Grimm brothers' version of Cinde¬
rella this identification is quite deliberate:
"this woman (the stepmother) had brought
with her two daughters who though beau¬
tiful and fair of complexion, were neverthe¬
less evil and black-hearted." In establishing
the exceptional nature of this case, the
"nevertheless" betrays the ideological con¬
tent of the sentence. If we were to turn the
phrase round and say that "the daughters,
though ugly and black-skinned were never¬
theless good and pure in heart", the racist
implication, however involuntary it may be,
would become brutally apparent. It is easy
to see why, for Latin American children.
"...what child of the tropical plains or plateaux of Latin America would
ever have dreamed of being a prince or princess if these images had not
been imposed on him...?" Photomontage shows European illustrations
in a Latin-American edition of the seventeenth-century French author
Charles Perrault's Fairy Tales.
¿SSari^y*
f *^fT H '* tF'/Sê
^Mtih
W i i Al ^%
¿^^Êm
^*
wä
*** Sk
t
vi
*^1
!^ ^*v
BSE
i ,
*1 _ « 1» - .
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
the most comforting, or at any rate the
least cruel, of these stories is Hans Ander¬
sen's Ugly Duckling.
Obedience to authority and for the
child authority means other people is
acceptance of one's fate; and one's fate is
the will of others. Male characters such as
Tom Thumb or Puss-in- Boots, although
submissive, are able to elude injustice or to
turn to their own benefit the absurd capri¬
ces of those in positions of power. But in
fairy taleswhich represent society in
miniature girls must obey and wait for
their obedience to be rewarded; thus their
feelings of impotence are reinforced. Cin¬
derella, submitting to the taunts of her
step-sisters, and Snow White, obliged to
live in hiding, are fine examples of patient
resignation, a virtue encouraged by the
establishment in a rebellious continent.
In fairy tales there are rewards and, more
in keeping with real life, punishments.
Bluebeard punishes his three wives' diso¬
bedience by taking their lives, although in
some versions the youngest manages to
save her skin. Little Red Riding Hood was
swallowed up by the wolf despite the fact
that, in Perrault's version, she had been
guilty of no disobedience (nor, indeed, had
her grandmother). It was not until some
hundred years later that, mercifully, Ger¬
man peasant women and wet-nurses
invented the timely arrival of the huntsmen
and her recovery from the wolf's belly, an
invention which was incorporated in the
version recounted by the brothers Grimm.
It was then that she learnt that she should
not disobey her mother and stray from the
path when walking through the forest.
A vital element in this literature, this
ideology, is the solution of problems not by
human endeavour but by providential
means which constitute, moreover, the
reward for submission. A king's son trans¬
forms Cinderella's life, other princes do the
same for Snow White and Sleeping
Beauty, and a dragon and a soldier arrive in
the nick of time to save Bluebeard's third
wife. Two centuries later the situation is
brought up to date. At closing-time, a
humble washer-up in a bar sings at her
work and a film director seated in a corner
"discovers" her and makes her a film star.
Unfortunately there are very few Marilyn
Monroes; millions of young Latin American
match-sellers, goose-girls and Cinderellas
are destined only to become adult Cinderel¬
las. They have no fairy god-mother with a
. magic wand to free them from their toil and
change their rags into silken robes and their
sandals into glass slippers. They have no
prince to come to their rescue, not even a
more prosaic modern equivalent the son
of a President, of an industrial magnate or
of a banker. For most women the dream of
Cinderella becomes the harsh reality of
Snow White; if she wants a roof over her
head she can stay and be provided for so
long as she' is prepared to "make the beds,
cook, wash, sew, spin and keep everything
clean and tidy" for the dwarfs.
More than a century after the brothers
Grimm publicly acknowledged their debt to
the German peasant woman who had
recounted to them several times, with no
variations, the stories that were to become
Grimms' Fairy Tales, psychoanalysts have
observed how adamantly young children
demand to be told the same story over and
over again with nothing left out, altered or
toned down. It would seem that this repeti¬
tion gives children a feeling of security, of
certainty that there will always be a happy
ending; if each detail remains the same
Photo
H.W. Silvester
© Rapho,
Paris
Illustrations
© Editorial
Porrúa, S.A.,
Mexico City
throughout the narrative, there is no
reason to suppose that the ending will
change.
Think, for example of some unhappy
child from a large family (and in Latin Ame¬
rica a large family is almost invariably a
poor one) as he listens to the story of Tom
Thumb. Tom Thumb's parents "were so
poor that their seven sons [aged between
ten and seven] were a great burden to them
since none of them could earn a living...
They decided to get rid of them by aban¬
doning them in the depths of the forest".
Perhaps the fact that he and his brothers
and sisters have been earning at least a part
of their keep since the age of seven will
reassure the little Latin American boy, but,
paradoxically, his certainty that the ogre
will never eat them all up, that they are not
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
y going to get lost and will find their way
home is due to the fact that, in the story,
the birds always eat up the breadcrumbs
that Tom Thumb dropped behind him so as
to be able to find his way home again.
This tendency of the child and the
adult to identify with the characters in a
story and the absence of any incentive to
imagine different outcomes to similar situa¬
tions is what, according to the experts,
gives these tales their therapeutic value.
Because they provide solutions that are as
clear-cut and unambiguous as the child's
unconscious is said to be, the child can
use them to help him to solve various
psychological problems of insecurity and
fear; to master the oedipal impulse or to
reconcile the notion of pleasure with the
understanding of reality. This may indeed
be true, but this is not what we are con¬
cerned with here.
Nor is there any intention of belittling the
literary value of fairy tales or of denying
their virtually worldwide genealogical
Mark Twain and Selma Lagerlöf. But the
argument that fairy tales "cannot be harm¬
ful since they are a part of all the traditions
of the world" is fallacious. They do not
belong to all traditions, not all traditions are
necessarily good for children, and not
everything is good simply because it is tra¬
ditional. Are we not today trying to correct
a whole host of misconceptions about
many aspects of human beings and the
world precisely so as not to pass them on
to our own children only for them to make
the same mistake with their children?
When children who have learnt to read
have access to books, their dreams are fil¬
led with the adventures of Sinbad and
Aladdin, and later of Sandokan, Gulliver
and Robinson Crusoe. Those who cannot
read stick to comics and films about Buf¬
falo Bill, the Indian-fighter, or Tarzan, the
tracker-down of negros. Today, television
has bought heroes such as Superman and
Batman (no words strong enough can be
found to describe the system of values they
"...The young Latin
American was not slow in
recognizing that, in
comparison with the
realities of his life, all this
was nothing more than a
huge adult lie."
roots. Tom Thumb antecedents can be
found in Homer and Rabelais and in Etrus¬
can and Scandinavian legends; Puss in
Boots was foreshadowed in Saint Basil the
Great's Hexameron, in Gianfresco Strapa-
rola's Pleasant Nights, Tales for the Diver¬
sion of Ladies and Gentlemen and in the
Thousand and One Nights; Sleeping
Beauty was referred to by Herodotus; ver¬
sions of Bluebeard exist in French, Ger¬
man, Swedish, Gaelic, Greek, Finnish and
Catalan. Latin American students come
across them in the course of their general
education just as they get to know the
great names of a literature which is not
addressed to adolescents alone, such as
Hans Christian Andersen, Lewis Carroll,
represent) to even the remotest villages.
Here and there, a few grandmothers and
mothers still intone "Once upon a time...";
the younger, more educated mothers seem
to have given up this habit altogether, feel¬
ing that the symbolism of these tales no
longer corresponds to reality, or doubting
their pedagogical and therapeutic value.
The tale is ended.
Aware of the difficulty of creating a tradi¬
tion, writers in Latin America set out first to
decolonize children's literature. The Brazil¬
ian writer Monteiro Lobato probably holds
pride of place among these innovators.
Many others have devoted themselves to
the compilation of indigenous stories, tales
Leonid Brezhnev, Chairman of the Presidium of the
Supreme Soviet of the Union of Soviet Socialist Republics
Children are our future. They will carry on the cause of their mothers and fathers. I am
sure that they will build a better and happier life on earth. Meanwhile, our duty is to try
to ensure that children everywhere are spared war so that they may enjoy their childhood
in tranquillity and happiness. Our purpose is to teach children to be generous, to live in
friendship and as good neighbours with all people, regardless of nationality or colour, and
to work for the benefit of all people.
based on the Indian cosmogony or of Afri¬
can origin. But they seem to have had little
success with children, perhaps because
they are given scant attention in the school
or in the home, perhaps because the chil¬
dren are conditioned to expect a certain
style and content, or perhaps simply
because they have not yet acquired the sta¬
tus of a tradition.
Some Latin American writers have
published, with the best of intentions, new
stories and fables; unfortunately, many of
them seem to consider the child reader to
be mentally retarded if not a complete idiot.
Adopting a quasi-colonialist attitude, con¬
temptuous rather than paternalistic, they
offer the child cheap falsehoods wrapped
up in insipid, pretty-pretty baby-talk. This
is childish literature, not literature for chil¬
dren. Once they have seen on television
men landing on the moon, or the incredible
life of the under-water world, or a cowboy
destroying an entire army singlehanded, it
is easy to imagine what children must think
of those who persist in telling the story of
how Mr. Toad married Miss Frog.
Among those who avoid these pitfalls is
the Argentine poet and puppeteer Javier
Villafañe who roams the hamlets and villa¬
ges of Latin America asking children to
recount to him their own stories and expe¬
riences. These he brings to life again by
presenting them on the stage of his travel¬
ling puppet theatre. The children have the
feeling that they have created something
and, in fact, this is true.
Not long ago I was a member of a jury
judging a competition in Ecuador for sto¬
ries for children written by children aged
from nine to twelve. Almost eighty per cent
of the entries were immediately eliminated
as being no more than pale repetitions of
fairy tales or cowboy films. Was not this a
symptom of cultural colonization? But,
worse still, in those cases where the chil¬
dren had produced original stories, adults
had ruined them with their "corrections".
Was not this another way of silencing the
children?
In every country, children's painting is
encouraged as being one of the most spon¬
taneous and unaffected expressions of the
universe of the child. But children are very
seldom encouraged to express themselves
in words and their right to speak out is
hardly ever recognized. (Thirty years ago,
the Uruguayan writer Jesualdo published a
volume of children's poems which included
lines that any poet would have been proud
to have written).
Imagination is always more ferociously
repressed when it is expressed in the form
of language. We are not disturbed when
the child expresses his vision of the world
in bright colours and touchingly hesitant
lines; what bothers us is his opinion of our
conception of his reality. It makes us smile
when we see a vertical line topped by a cir¬
cle and with two horizontal and two ob¬
lique lines coming from it. After all, that is
what a man is like whatever his stamp or
breed; it is a drawing, a game. But our fear
of words reveals our fear of the truth. We
are afraid to hear the cry "the Emperor has
no clothes", since, as far as children are
concerned, the Emperor is each one of us.
Jorge Enrique Adoum
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Deaf children live In a
world of silence but they
can "listen" to their
parents with their eyes.
Recent discoveries about
early childhood, stressing
the importance of the
gestures and facial
expressions which
accompany speech, are
being increasingly used
by parents and teachers
to help handicapped
children to acquire
communications skills.
The deaf child is trained
to follow the adult's line
of vision before lip-
reading his or her
comments.
The road
to self-expression
Awakening the latent language skills
of handicapped children
by Anne McKenna
ANNE McKENNA of Ireland is editor of The
International Journal of Early Childhood and lec¬
turer in the psychology department of University
College, Dublin.
L
ET us eavesdrop for a few moments
while a normal child talks to his
mother after he has just come out of
school. He rushes through the door and
runs to tell her what he has done since he
last saw her, in school and on the way
home with his playmates. His conversation
carries the outside world into the home,
and as his mother listens sympathetically
the various strands of his lifeschool,
home and friends come together for him
and interweave to make a new pattern and
a new world that he himself has fashioned.
y
Such fortunate children who have been
brought up in happy homes and who pos¬
sess all their senses unimpaired have
taught us so much about the meaning of
the world for a child. In giving us these
insights, they have given us the opportu¬
nity to acquire a new perspective on the
rights of handicapped children on their
long voyage to adulthood.
We now know that children learn many
of the highly complex processes of com¬
munication in a very short time early in life,
long before they reach school age. During
a recent study of a pre-school programme
in a socially disadvantaged area of the United
CONTINUED PAGE 20
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
C
D
COC
O
_C
D
OC
D
Û
O(DO
it
^
N
n
4
¿
4
r
-
r-*
'I:1
¿1C
D
1
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
O
)
mC
O
.QE>OoC
McoC
fl
coT
3
"cw£
-°
o
»
>
-
ro
.
aEa
)
_
q2
<
m
S
TO
§3
Q
O
>
.
5
<5
>
-
r
^
o
o
a
}
o
3oOo
O
.
ü
O
O
J
-
a
<
o
a
s
c
en
3
§
Q
)
o
o
+
-<
M
-
C
O
4
_
i
S
o(U
c
Q
0
)
I
I
S
9
|0
|1
4
B
1
1
9
}
9
l|_
|_
1
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Kingdom, parents were asked whether
the programme had helped their relation¬
ship with their children. About half of them
said that this relationship had improved
and most often they attributed this to the
child's increased verbal facility.
The children had learned new words
which had made it easier for their parents
to communicate with them; the pre-school
experience had apparently provided topics
for conversation. It may seem surprising
that parents and children living under the
same roof should need to be provided with
conversational themes, but the fact is that
there are many situations in which lan¬
guage is superfluous.
Eating and sleeping can be supervised by
the parent with a great deal of efficiency
and even affection, but with very few
words. To wrap up a child carefully against
the cold you do not need to talk about his
red jumper or blue jumper or to differen¬
tiate a woollen from a synthetic coat ; and
you can tuck him into bed at night without
talking about the sun, the moon and the
stars.
The language used on occasions like
these may often be a one-sided set of terse
instructions from parent to child, with an
almost total lack of dialogue. To engage in
dialogue with the child about the names of
things, to perceive, compare and classify
their qualities, to create imaginary and
hypothetical situations, to relate events in
time and space, to discuss the happenings
of a familiar story, and to talk about how
one feelsall of these activities and many
others which form the basis of a good pre¬
school programme, might also become
topics of conversation to try out with
mother as well as with teacher. In giving
the child conversational pieces to take
home, just as we would let him take home
his drawings, we are also giving the parent,
perhaps for the first time, an opportunity to
try out alternative topics of conversation.
But with the child who is handicapped in
language development by deafness, deve-
20
Above, four cards illustrating and explaining gestures from the sign-
language of the deaf. They form part of a set used in the Swedish TV
"Hands Up" programmes described in photo caption on opposite page.
Clockwise from top left, cards show gestures for: "thanktyou"; "please"
"meeting"; and "happy". More than 300,000 sets were sold at shops
throughout Sweden.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
lopmental delays or low:level linguistic sti¬
mulation in the home, we must go back to
the beginnings of language. Early depriva¬
tion through any form of handicap, either
social or physical, can have far-reaching
effects and can result in irreversible
damage. On the positive side, early enrich¬
ment programmes can be highly effective if
they are appropriate to the child's age and
level of development.
What are the essential elements of a lan¬
guage programme for children who have
not yet acquired language? To answer this
question we need to know what the normal
child has to learn before he can begin to
speak. Before language is possible, we
must "learn to mean" as one linguist has
put it to make sense of the world and of
the people in itand what other people are
trying to do for us and ro us. This is the
journey that we embark on from the first
breath of life, and children have travelled
far along this road before speech begins,
indeed before speech can begin.
One of the first things we know to be
essential is the setting up between infant
and adult of a common ground, with the
adult looking at the same thing as the
infant and then commenting on it. This
immersion in the same subject, which the
American psychologist Jerome Bruner has
called "joint attention", is a precious com¬
modity for the language enrichment pro¬
gramme. It is in such conditions that we
see the precursor of language and it is to be
noted that the adult joins in the child's
attention rather than expecting the child to
join in his.
A mother does not say: "Pay attention,
this ¡s a hat", but when the child involunta¬
rily attends and looks with interest at his
daddy's head, so does mother, accom¬
panying this with words like "Oh! look at
daddy's lovely hat". Meaning for the child
is the total content of the event, the words,
the pointing finger, the smile on mother's
face and the question in her eyes. The
younger the child, the more handicapped
the child, the more important is this con¬
text where everything that is happening
around him is a clue to be snatched up if he
is to make sense of the world.
And if the speaker's face expresses
impatience at having to repeat the message j
for, say, a deaf child, this is what the situa- 1
"HANDS UPI" a highly imaginative series of Swedish TV programmes,
has encouraged thousands of children with unimpaired hearing to learn
the sign-language of the deaf. The programmes were intended not only
to break the "sound barrier" of communication with deaf youngsters but
to initiate other children into a fun language they could use for swapping
secrets, communicating in noisy surroundings or from a distance. An
episode of an adventure serial starring two deaf children and two
children with normal hearing was screened each week. Every instalment
contained a key sentence in sign language that the "Hearing" children
and viewers had to interpret. Viewers had an opportunity to familiarize
themselves with the gestures used in the broadcasts by a training
programme preceding each instalment and by a set of explanatory cards
(see opposite page). Top photo page 20: the children, with producer
Gunnel Linde, learn signs connected with one of the secret sentences.
Top photo this page: the boy with normal hearing is telling the deaf boy
what has happened to a key they are looking for. It has been dropped
into a pool and the deaf diver (middle photo) has been told by sign
language where to find it. Left, he breaks surface, key in hand.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
No words neededl This
expressive gesture
clearly means Ugh!
Disgusting!
, tion "means" to the child. You may be
mouthing "Take off your coat", but the
frustration or irritation in your eyes is the
chief message the child is receiving. So too
much of the tone of your voice when
speaking to a blind child, like the press¬
ure of your touch, can underline or cancel
out a spoken message.
No sooner has the child acquired the abi¬
lity to speak a three- or four-word sentence
to get attention, to procure his wants, to
comment on a surprising change, in short
to steer him through all the practical inter¬
changes necessary for living, no sooner has
he acquired this basic minimum than he
shows a joy in experimenting with ¡t. Lan¬
guage becomes something to be played
with, an object to be investigated. And in
the normal course of events the child is the
initiator, pushing the adult into dialogue.
A recent study has revealed just how
active and initiating children can be. When
the spontaneous speech of four-year-old
children in their own homes was recorded,
in circumstances in which neither the
mother nor the child knew when they were
being recorded, it was found that the child
initiated speech to the mother twice as
often as she initiated speech to him.
This finding has caused all of us to think
again about whether we teach language to
a child or whether we set up a situation
which allows the child to teach himself,
and if we do, to ask what sort of situation
this should be.
Once the to and fro of real dialogue has
been established, it provides the frame for
the child to try out new speech interaction
patterns. Here is a sample from an actual
dialogue in which a three-year-old child is
showing active forward planning, which is
revealed when the adult does not say the
"lines" he has mentally written for her.
- (Child) Shall I read this?
(Mother) Yes please.
(Child) O.K. (pretending to read) There
are no monkeys.
(Mother) Aren't there?
(Child) No. Say why aren't there.
(Mother) Why aren't there?
(Child) Because there is only Jane and
Peter.
The question "Aren't there" asks only
for a "Yes" or "No" answer whereas a
question containing the word why asks for
a detailed reply, which in this instance the
child had already prepared and intended to
deliver. This is just one of many examples
from our tape recordings of a child, not
merely initiating speech but also structu¬
ring the form of the dialogue, a dialogue in
which the child is the leader and the adult
thejollower.
What are the implications of this for chil¬
dren who are going through the critical
early years in situations which are less than
¡deal? What kind of language enrichment
programme should we have for the deaf,
the socially and culturally disadvantaged,
the mentally handicapped child? We have
to recognize the great value and producti¬
vity oí those desultory and, to the adult
mind, apparently aimless exchanges which
go on between an apprentice speaker, a
child, and a skilled practitioner, an adult.
Furthermore, we should recognize that
such exchanges will not take place until the
child is sufficiently emotionally secure to
disengage from the practical world of real
life, to play and experiment with language
in his own way and at his own pace.
Are there situations in which the burden
of providing for the family is so overwhel¬
ming that the providers become sources of
anxiety for the child, to be avoided rather
than sought out for little chats? In those
cultures where the child becomes an eco¬
nomic unit of his family before he has mas¬
tered the language learning process, he will
no doubt precociously acquire the scaffol¬
ding of language, but will there be time and
interest his own and that of his
parents to draw out the richness of lan¬
guage that he possesses? The child needs a
listenera listener with plenty of time: one
who appreciates that language itself ¡s a
great adventure for the human spirit and
not just a tool to make children more con¬
forming, more hard-working or even less
talkative.
In this, the International Year of the
Child, we should be facing the fact that
each child is unique and be asking oursel¬
ves how we can compensate for the handi¬
caps from which many children suffer. For
example, many children living in high-rise
flats or overcrowded slums spend a great
deal of their day playing in groups with
other children on their balconies or in their
yards. When their home background offers
a low level of language stimulation, their
needs are surely for more frequent contact
with a responsive adult, an experience
which a child from a more privileged social
background might have in abundance
whilst missing out on the experience of
playing with children of his own age.
For the deaf child we have to examine
our current programmes to ensure that
they are bombarding the child from the ear¬
liest moment with symbolsspoken or
manualwhich he can experiment with
and manipulate. However we must not
make the error of assuming that language
is something "out there" to be poured into
a child so that it finishes up inside him.
Rather the task is to give the child sufficient
appropriate stimulation to trigger off his
own latent language-forming skills.
And for the mentally handicapped child
might not the task for our educators be to
appreciate that a child's utterance, no mat¬
ter how poorly expressed, is his own crea¬
tion, his own unique assembly, to be foste¬
red and cherished rather than to be correct¬
ed in accordance with adult standards?
And for the blind child who is not lacking in
linguistic competence, how can we ensure
that the words he uses are not mere empty
concepts, pseudo-words which lack the
sighted child's richness of meaning?
Such are the questions we should pose
in this International Year of the Child if we
are to ensure that all our children have the
best opportunities to develop fully.
Anno McKenna
Jimmy Carter, President of the United States of America
I would hope, as the world focuses its attention upon children, that all of us could
become much more knowledgeable about their needs, much more willing to assume
responsibilities for meeting those needs and that we might in a positive way assess the
unique opportunity to broaden the horizon of growth and enjoyment and the productivity
of ouf children's lives, both now and in the future.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Do it yourself toys have many times the appeal of the ready-made plaything and all the joy of creation and innovation
can be read in the face of the youthful artisan, right. In contrast, the adult-conceived bouncer, left, seems to evoke
only an expression of bored, passive acceptance.
Photo Kofod © Unicef
Mali
Making
toys
is
child's
Tanzania Photos © Antonio Gálvez, Paris
SUPERANNUATED cardboard
boxes, tangled pieces of string,
dusters that have seen better
days, redundant twists of wire, bottle-
tops and old tin cansso many of the
things grown-ups relegate to the rub¬
bish dump can be a treasure trove for
imaginative children m search of fun.
Usefulness is in the eye of the be¬
holder, and a dustbin may contain an
unlikely hoard of odds and ends from
which, once the magic wand of inge¬
nuity has been waved over them, a toy
or a game can be conjured.
This was clearly shown by an exhibi¬
tion of children's toys and games from
all over the world, organized by
Unesco and all its Member States and
held at Unesco's Paris headquarters in
November 1978, as a prelude to the
International Year of the Child. Fifty-
six countries, representing the cultures
of five continents, sent in 3,000 games
and toys, most of which had been
invented and made by children them¬
selves, the rest being produced by
local craftsmen. Nine hundred toys
were chosen for the exhibition, which
focused on three themes: toys and
play in the child's psychological deve¬
lopment; play and the child's relations
with the community (through folklore,
music and the other arts); and play in
education.
On these pages, some of the high¬
lights of the exhibition: forty toys dev¬
ised and made by children from forty k
countries. f
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
India Tunisia Chile
Brazil Indonesia
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Morocco Malaysia
Photo Michel Claude/Unesco
Unesco's Director-General, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, with two young visitors at the exhibition
"Toys and Games of the World", organized at
Unesco as a curtain-raiser to International Year of
the Child 1979.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A moment of delight and concentration at a school in a Paris neighbourhood heavily
populated by migrant workers. When children from many different countries are brought
together, the classroom can become a seed-plot of international understanding.
What's in
a name?
by Hélène Gratiot-Alphandéry
HÉLÈNE GRATIOT-ALPHANDÉRY, French specialist in child psychology, is honorary
director at the Ecole Pratique des Hautes Etudes in Paris and teaches at the René Descartes
University. Her six-volume Traité de Psychologie de l'Enfant ("Treatise on Child
Psychology"), written in collaboration with R. Zazzo, was published by Presses Universitaires
de France, Paris, between 1970 and 1976.
ONE of the first things a child is
required to do in the famous Binet-
Sirnon intelligence test is to give
his name.
Children seem to know their names by
the time they reach the age of three. In
other words, three-year-olds are capable of
placing themselves in a given set of sur¬
roundings and of providing this indication
of where they belong in society.
But it would be arbitrary to consider a
child's ability to identify himself by name as
merely a sign that he has reached a certain
level of intellectual development. A name is
more than a label ; it is a token of a
person's individuality. It is by our names
that we are known ; we make a name for
ourselves in the world.
The French philosopher Ignace Meyer-
son made an analysis of the social function
of the name in which he highlighted the
importance of names in ancient societies.
"A child does not exist until it has been
named," he wrote. "The name both repre¬
sents and confers individuality. It is the
measure of the place which the group allots k
to the individual and of the protection it F
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The ¡mage the migrant
worker has of the host
country, based on
fantasies about its
wealth, comfort and way
of life, contrasts painfully
with the discomfort of
the shanty-town in which
he often finds himself
living. He feels isolated
and excluded. But his
children have additional
problems to face. If they
do not go to school, they
remain entirely dependent
upon their family and
their social development
is retarded. If they go to
school, they are plunged
into a strange
environment and a
bewilderingly wide range
of activities and
relationships with other
children and adults for
which they are totally
unprepared.
Photo H.W. Silvester © Rapho, Paris
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
k affords him. .. It is a big moment, for exam¬
ple, when his signature begins to carry
weight. A name represents and confers a
very special kind of identity: to give a child
the name of a forebear is to give the fore¬
bear a kind of continuity and even, in a
sense, to transform the child into the fore¬
bear." Meyerson goes on to make the point
that people sometimes change their names
when they change their social status, or
when they are in danger and want to cover
their tracks.
Meyerson also recalls that in Ancient
Greece and Rome, anyone such as a son,
a daughter or a slave placed by birth in
the power of another person, had no name
of his own. He was given that of the house
to which hé belonged.
But this link between the person and his
name is more than just a footnote to his¬
tory; psychological studies reveal that a
child's name has a bearing on the for¬
mation of his personality.
There is a time in early childhood when a
child amuses himself by becoming first one
personality and then another. Then comes
a moment when he speaks of himself as a
single person; the words / and me are con¬
stantly on his lips. This personality crisis,
which occurs around the age of three, is an
affirmation of selfhood and individuality,
which is expressed as opposition to others.
The child's given name is a crucial factor
in this assumption of individuality. It sin¬
gles him out from others and also indicates
his sexchildren tend to take a poor view
of given names which can be used for boys
and girls alike. The given name is more per¬
sonal than the surname. The child learns it
first and uses it in his earliest contacts with
others. It is used by his brothers and sisters
and his playmates. The surname indicates
attachment to a group and offers less per¬
sonal information to the outside world.
Both names assume great importance
when the child steps out of the family circle
and enters the world of school. When a
child utters his name he introduces himself,
exposes himself to the scrutiny of others.
At this point it becomes apparent that there
is a difference between "local" names and
"foreign" names, especially the given
names which are used by the teacher and
the other children. The foreign child is dis¬
tinguished by his given name just as much
as, if not more than, by the colour of his
skin, his hair and his eyes. Now perhaps
more than at any other time he realizes that
he is in some way different from the other
children.
This difference may be oppressive. It
may lead the child to behave aggressively,
to adopt a negative attitude to life, or to cut
himself off from other people. It may also
lead him to make some kind of appeal to
others those others who are both so near
to him and yet so unlike himself. His name
has taken on a far wider significance: it
denotes a country, a homeland.
I OME years ago, Jean Piaget
and Anne-Marie Weill traced the way in
which the idea of the homeland originates
and develops in the child's mind. Around
the age of six the child is still unable to
detach himself from his immediate circle,
but between ten and thirteen he acquires a
broader conception of the national group,
together with an understanding of the ele¬
ment of give-and-take in human relations.
"From the affective point of view", Piaget
has written, "the child initially shows no
preference for his own country over others
(what counts is the immediate unit such as
the family or the home town). Then, once it
is accepted that he belongs to a given
country, he imagines that anyone born
elsewhere would want to belong to the
same country too, if only he had the
choice. It is only when the child is on the
threshold of adolescence that he starts to
feel real patriotic sentiments, which he jus¬
tifies by reference to his birth and his
family. He believes that everyone prefers
his own country for the same reasons".
But logically satisfying though this analy¬
sis is, it does not do full justice to the
intense emotions which the idea of the
homeland evokes in those who live in exile.
When questioned about his nationality, a
child living in a host country conjures up an
image, which may be either fantastic or
nostalgic, of a faraway land where he may
never have set foot. For him the right to a
homeland means the right to say that he
comes from "somewhere else". The chil¬
dren and often the adults who question
him are at home; he is not.
He may realize that he has been up-
Valéry Giscard d'Estaing, President of France
It Is my hope that this year the smiles of children will light up the world and give us faith
and conviction in our struggle for peace and progress.
Childhood is the innocence of the world, the marvellous fountainhead from which nations
draw energy, courage and joy. It is from children's wonder and curiosity that springs the
desire for change, without which our world would grow old and rigid.
rooted, either because he has heard his
parents say so or because he still remem¬
bers a country where he lived, played and
spoke in his own language. But whether
this memory is based on real experience or
whether it is a figment of his imagination, it
is overshadowed by a much more impor¬
tant problem. Every day of his life the
foreign child must cope with the fact that
he belongs to two countries at once.
Beneath the scrutiny of other people he
becomes aware of his identity. In relation
to other people he feels either a friend or an
outsider, depending on the circumstances.
Other factors as well as name, language
and physical type combine to immure the
foreign child in his foreignness. He soon
sees that his life is different in many res¬
pects from those of the children he meets
each day: his living conditions are different,
so are the social and economic status of his
parents and his family's customs and edu¬
cational models. He sees how groups form
according to nationalities and even regions
of origin; and both he and his family expe¬
rience the warmth and security of these
groups, through which he discovers a
homeland of whose landscapes, traditions
and recent history he is ignorant.
The foreign child's image of the home¬
land is thus an ambivalent one. It inspires a
lasting fidelity; he may hope to return there
one day; perhaps some members of his
family still live there. At the same time his
picture of this country may be coloured by
the fact that he has been compelled to
leave it because of poverty or oppression.
In the course of his psychological and
social evolution the child is constantly
making choices, and in this situation he
faces problems which make choosing
extremely painful or even impossible. He is
not equipped to choose between the
country in which he lives and whose cul¬
ture he is acquiring and the country to
which he "belongs". Or else he dares not
choose. Other people, however, do the
choosing for him.
The American sociologist Otto Klineberg
has shown how national stereotypes form
in the child's mind. Many factors are invol¬
ved in this process, including the image the
child has of himself, the image he forms of
others, and the image others form of him.
All these judgements are influenced by fac¬
tors which reflect the insecurity of the
foreign child and his unfailing need to be
recognized and accepted for what he is.
At school foreign children experience dif¬
ficulties of adaptation which all too often
produce a false, distorted picture of their
abilities and their potential. In some
schools they even outnumber and tend to
drive away the other children. As a result
the authorities may apply the principle of
"tolerance thresholds", a measure which
may in itself accentuate the cleavages bet¬
ween nationalities and which certainly does i
not foster "universal brotherhood". I
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
k If the foreign child feels that he is diffe¬
rent from children of the host country, he
also feels different from other foreign chil¬
dren whose nationality is different from his
own. He discovers that being a foreigner
does not necessarily bring you closer to
other foreigners. What he shares with
other foreign children is essentially a wish
to be accepted and to give a good account
of his country of origin, and above all, as
he grows older, a half-formulated desire
not to be an intruder or a parasite.
The child does not work all this out
alone. He gradually absorbs what he hears
at home and learns from the experiences of
his family. But these feelings eventually
become a part of him and influence what
he expects from the world.
The problem is not so much the child's
distinctive cultural situation as the way in
which this situation is appreciated and
valued. The child seeks recognition of his
right to a homeland but he also wants his
homeland to be considered as equal to any
other and worthy of an equally strong
attachment.
But is it not time we realized that such
terms as "the children of migrant workers"
or "the children of refugees" actually
sound like a denial of the right to a home-
One out of every two of the estimated ten
million refugees in the world is a child.
Among the 30,000 refugees from
Zimbabwe (Rhodesia) who have reached
shelter in Zambia, either directly or via
Botswana, seventy per cent are children
or adolescents of whom some 12,000 are
of school age. This has placed a huge
burden on the Government of Zambia
which, with the help of the Office of the
United Nations High Commissioner for
Refugees, has established camps and an
educational centre for young
Zimbabweans not far from Lusaka. Above,
Zimbabwe refugee children in Zambia.
Top left, improvised living quarters for
boys at the H.Z. Moyo Camp. Left, a class
for some of the 5,000 girls housed at the
Victory Camp.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
^/4¿í
/ ét^r
\
>r
land because they associate the children
with the terminology of distress and flight?
Is it not high time to do away with such
oppressive labels? Should we not insist
that the social services and the bureau¬
cracy cease to mark out these children
from the rest? After all, no distinctions are
imposed on people who move about within
a single country. From north, south, east
and west they come, bringing with them
their own traditions and ways of speech.
But they are not given a special social or
professional status.
- i >
Photos Peter Marlow © Sygma, Paris
Should we not recognize at once that
foreign children have a right to a homeland
of their own? They may be Algerians,
Argentinians, Chileans, Spaniards, Italians,
Ivorians, Laotians, Moroccans, Portu¬
guese, Senegalese, Tunisians or Yugo¬
slavs. Let them be recognized as such from
the moment they set foot in the host
country. Their dignity and their hope will
grow out of their legitimate pride in their
name and their homeland.
Hélène Gratiot-Alphandéry
Kenneth Kaunda, President of the Republic of Zambia
To the grown-ups, I would say this. Talk with children, and not just to them. Listen to
what they have to say. Respect their right to be heard. Give them a proper place in our
world village. Help them to play their role in our great family. Above all, let them teach
you what you have perhaps forgotten understanding, tolerance, friendship, peace and
brotherhood, and above all love.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Children
in the never,
never land
of exile
WHENEVER men and women are
forced to go into exile, violence
is inflicted not only on them but
on their families and especially on their chil¬
dren, who are caught up in a situation that
is beyond their grasp» The plight of these
"indirect" victims of political repression
has all too often been overlooked.
When children see their parents put
under arrest or when they visit their parents
in prison, they are the witnesses and some¬
times even the victims of ill-treatment by
the police. When their parents go into
hiding, they are subjected to sudden
upheavals and are torn away from their
schools and their friends. They may have to
endure separation from one or both
parents for a considerable time. If they
manage to go into exile, they have to leave
behind them their customs, their language
and those they love, and then face the
demands abruptly placed on them by their
adopted country.
Three other factors aggravate the effects
of these bitter experiences. In the first
place the children are either fed with con¬
fused or insufficient information about the
events which led to their predicament. This
may be a deliberate attempt to stop such
data from getting out or it may stem from
the difficulty of formulating the kind of
explanations that children can grasp.
Secondly, exile represents a break in conti¬
nuity and prevents the family from making
any definite plans for the future. Thirdly,' it
imposes a constant strain on the parents,
leading to quarrels and separations which
add to the children's feelings of insecurity,
deprivation and helplessness.
In general, it seems that while the chil¬
dren do not experience any major problems
as far as their intellectual development or
their learning processes are concerned,
their imagination suffers: they tend to imi¬
tate rather than create.
By giving substance to fantasies bound
up with the repression of desires, expe¬
rience of political repression and exile may
inhibit, sometimes to a marked degree, the
children's ability to give expression to their
fantasies and to engage in creative think¬
ing. The likely outcome of this is that their
imaginative work will deteriorate in quality
and that the range of their imagination will
diminish.
This deterioration is also reflected in their
powers of oral expression. Their vocabu¬
lary becomes impoverished and deficient in
all those figurative turns of phrase, compa¬
rions and adjectives that enrich linguistic
expression. This happens whatever lan¬
guage the children speak in the host
country.
No disturbances were observed in the
children's perception of situations nor in
their capacity to express these perceptions.
However, many children tended to make
lists of concrete items of information but
could only establish partial relationships
between them and were reluctant to sug¬
gest possible explanations for such rela¬
tionships.
In various tests performed to assess gra¬
phic representation, oral expression and
play, the children displayed a marked
tendency to simplify and were extremely
wary of using their imagination.
Two possible explanations for this emer¬
ged from interviews with the parents, who
confirmed that their children also showed
signs of an impoverished imagination in
their everyday lives. The first was that the
children were cut off from communication
and the kind of information which might
enable them to draw a clear-cut distinction
between fantasy and reality; the second
was that speech, even the utterance of
their own name, might have been dange¬
rous for them at some particular time when
they were in hiding. The parents stressed
the role that imagination played in their
own political activities and underlined the
difficulty of reconciling their own creative
activity with the realities of their situation
as exiles; as for the children, their urgent
need to adapt to life in exile was stifling
their creativity.
The children made an enormous effort to
adapt to school and to their new environ-
This text presents the conclusions of a major
study by a group of psychologists on fifty chil¬
dren ofpolitical exiles living in Europe. The study
was carried out under the auspices of a Paris-
based welfare organization, the Comité Inter¬
mouvements auprès des Evacués.
Marshal Tito, President of the Socialist Federal Republic
of Yugoslavia
There is nothing so noble as working for the welfare and happiness of children, not only
in one's own country but in every corner of our planet. Caring for children and ensuring
their protection and welfare, is an integral part of the struggle for progress, for better
understanding and friendship among peoples, for the happiness and prosperity of all.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The child of a political exile unconsciously sees his father as a man
rejected by his country and reduced in status by the stigma of punishment.
These drawings by the five-year-old child of a Latin American family living
in exile in France show the mother as the most substantial figure of the
family with the father a diminished background figure.
ment and did not come up against any
major obstacles. However, their desire to
imitate was so strong that they adapted in a
submissive, accepting fashion, playing very
little part in what went on around them and
rarely taking the initiative. The parents felt
that this stemmed from a conflict between
the children's need to adjust to their envi¬
ronment and their desire to remain faith¬
ful to their country, political creed and
language.
When the children played, told stories or
drew pictures, they tended to simplify and
to steer clear of difficulties. They stuck to
straightforward description, conventional
forms and expressions, and gave an
impression of isolation. Such characteris¬
tics were closely linked to the profound gap
which had opened up between "here" and
"there", between "now" and "then", bet¬
ween pleasure and duty, play and reality.
The parents were familiar with these
aspects of their children's behaviour and
put forward several explanations for them:
the absence of dialogue between adults
and children; the stereotyped language of
political ideology; reliance on grand¬
parents; the tug-of-war between the need
to adjust to a new set of circumstances
and loyalty to their background; and a
whole series of factors stemming from the
contradiction between the social origin of
militant activity and its orientation.
The parents needed help because they
were living in hiding, and this led them to
rely either on their families or on relief orga¬
nizations. Persecution and dependence of
this kind encouraged a regressive pattern
of behaviour which compromised the chil¬
dren's image of their parents.
Repressive measures against a specific
group creates a climate of violence which
affects the whole community. People were
thus inclined to treat the persecuted as
social outcastsand this rejection in itself
stigmatized them as guilty. Children derive
their values from other people, and these
youngsters were at a loss to understand
how those who had been rejected by
everyone else could possibly be "good".
In exile, however, activism may be more
highly thought of, either through demons¬
trations of solidarity with the exiled militant
or because the host country confers on him
or her an aura of prestige. The child's
impressions of his "double life" become
even more sharply divided between the
claims of the past and the present, home¬
land and adopted country, reality and
myth, and give rise to a welter of imagery
and ambivalent ideas.
In most cases, the parents' ideological
outlook did not coincide with the interests
of the class to which they belonged, still
less with those of the grandparents, who
often looked after the children when the
parents were in hiding. The children may
accordingly be expected to inherit the same
contradictions and ambivalences as their
parents experienced in relation to their own
fathers and mothers.
The father figure, reduced to the status
of a child by the stigma of punishment,
may no longer prove capable of represen¬
ting authority, and the child may look
elsewhere for another person or an institu¬
tion to fill the gap. Institutions, however,
are unable to bestow the affection with
which the family tempers the severity of its
authority and leaves room for the individual
to exercise his freedom.
Children of exiles receive a barrage of
information and value-judgements which
are often incoherent and contradictory.
When they try to work out for themselves
clear, comprehensive and objective rules of
conduct and honesty, they have a hard
time reconciling the treatment meted out to
their parents with the general climate of
opinion and their own appreciation of
events.
Tests on the children showed that their
image of the fathers tended to diminish,
both physically and in terms of his autho¬
rity and of his fitness to perform his role.
Given the facts of life in exile, this diminu¬
tion of the father's authority rarely seems
to be motivated by aggression. On the con¬
trary it appears to be a way of preserving
the father as a real person and of keeping
him close at hand, alive and well. The
parents confirmed the existence of this atti¬
tude, which avoids direct conflict but
causes the members of the family to be¬
come isolated from each other.
The children's drawings showed signs of
isolation and inability to communicate;
they brought out the failings of every mem¬
ber of the family, especially the father who
was shown as a shadow of his real self.
The figure representing the mother was
more substantial and often taller than that
of the father.
Success was the most important thing in
life for these children, although the yard¬
stick of achievement power, money or
dominancewas not clearly defined. At
the same time there was a tendency to
downgrade the idea of conflict and to avoid
all opportunities for acts of heroism. Sub¬
mission was extolled and rationalized as the
most intelligent way of solving conflicts,
which were regarded as evil by nature.
The children had a certain regard for
argument as a form of combat, but the out¬
come or conclusion was always glossed
over, so that the issue of whether or not
reason was actually effective was left
unsettled. The ideas behind the reasoning
were based on such liberal premises as the
defence of human rights, strikes for higher
wages, the defence of the environment,
and were always postulated in relation to
the host country.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Two thousand million children
Continued from page 8
could employ if they knew about them. In
no society does minority status make
sexual activity inaccessible, whatever the
official norms might be.
The onset of fertility ranges from the age
of ten to the mid-teens. One of the trage¬
dies for girl children is that while the majo¬
rity of them live in countries where family
planning services are available and abortion
is legal under certain conditions, the ten-
to-fifteen year olds who are at risk of preg¬
nancy almost never have access to these
services.
The responsibilities of the teenage mar¬
ried woman who is also a mother may be
light compared to the responsibilities of the
teenage unmarried mother. A majority of
these young women keep their babies, and
have their lives programmed for them in
terms of the double task of working to sup¬
port the mother-child household, and of
being sole parent to the child. Economic
support from the father, even if paternal
filiation is legally established, is rare.
Unwed adolescent and teenage mothers
and their illegitimate offspring are among
Bibliothèque
Nationale
honours
Leopold Sédar
Senghor
An exhibition illustrating the life and
works of the Senegalese poet and
statesman Leopold Sedar Senghor is
currently being held (23 November
1978 to 18 February 1979) at the
Bibliothèque Nationale in Paris. The
exhibition traces Senghor's life from
his schooldays in Senegal and Paris,
where he was a classmate of the late
President Georges Pompidou,
through the pre-war years of
intellectual and creative ferment
when France "discovered" African
culture, up to the independence of
Senegal and Senghor's emergence
as a national leader and a world-
respected statesman. From his
earliest childhood Senghor has felt a
spontaneous affinity for the French
language, but his inspiration is
drawn from the poets of his native
Africa. This cultural mixture, so dear
to his heart, has given a unique
flavour to his writing, through which
runs the constant thread of the
search for and definition of the
concept of "Négritude". At the close
of the exhibition Mr. Senghor is to
donate a number of manuscripts and
illustrated editions of his works to
the Bibliothèque Nationale.
the most disadvantaged categories of
minors. While the United Nations Declara¬
tion of the Rights of the Child guarantees
whatever rights there are to all children
regardless of birth, in fact only twenty-two
countries recognize one status for all chil¬
dren whatever their circumstances of birth.
In all the rest, both the unwed mothers and
their illegitimate children carry lifelong
handicaps.
In the industrialized countries, the
increase in the number of school years has
brought about a prolongation of childhood
and of the child's dependence. Conse¬
quently adults have gradually come to for¬
get the roles that children and youth have
always played in social change. And yet the
young are everywhere at work, helping to
create alternative structures in community-
based movements the free schools, the
people's clinics, the refuges for children
who fear to live with their parents. The time
has come when we must cease to under¬
estimate their competence and skills.
Elisa Boulding
Bookshelf
UNESCO'S LITERATURE
TRANSLATIONS SERIES
India
D One Hundred Rural Songs of
India, translated into English verse by
K.P. Bahadur. Motilal Banarsidass
publishers, Delhi. 1978. 198 pp. (Rs. 80).
Egypt
(Contemporary Arab Authors Series)
D The Cheapest Nights and Other
Stories, by Yusef Idris. Translated by
Wadida Wassef. Peter Owen Ltd., Lon¬
don, 1978. 196 pp. (£5.25).
Iran
(The Persian Heritage Series)
D Iskandarnamah, A Persian Medi¬
eval Alexander-Romance, translated by
Minoo S. Southgate. Columbia Univer¬
sity Press, New York, 1978. 237 pp.
OTHER UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
D Educational Reforms and Innova¬
tions in Africa. Studies prepared for the
Conference of Ministers of Education of
African Member States of Unesco. Case
studies from Senegal, Mali, Tanzania,
Benin, Togo, Ethiopia, Somalia and
Kenya. 1978, 77 pp. (12 F).
D Some Suggestions on Teaching
about Human Rights. A teaching
manual showing how educators at diffe¬
rent school levels have introduced the
theme of human rights Into classwork.
2nd impression 1978, 155 pp. (10 F).
D The Book in Multilingual Coun¬
tries, by Abul Hasan. (No. 82 in
Unesco's "Reports and Papers on Mass
Communication" series). 1978, 40 pp.
(8F).
D Cultural Policy in Sierra Leone, by
Arthur Abraham. 1978, 75 pp. (16 F).
D Experiments in Popular Education
in Portugal 1974-1976, by Alberto Melo
and Ana Benevente. (No. 29 in Unesco's
"Educational Studies and Documents"
series). 1978, 45 pp. (8 F).
D Towards a Cultural Policy for
Honduras, by Alba Alonso de Quesada.
1978, 73 pp. (14 F).
D Basic Services for Children: a
Continuing Search for Learning
Priorities-ll, Studies of innovative edu¬
cational services for underprivileged chil¬
dren in developing countries. (No. 37 in
the International Bureau of Education's
"Experiments and Innovations in Educa¬
tion" series). 1978, 229 pp. (28 F).
D Unesco's international quarterly
Impact of Science on Society for
October-December 1978 (Vol. 28, No. 4)
contains the second instalment of a two-
part series on Integrated Technology
Transfer. (Each issue: 12 F; subscrip¬
tions 40 F for one year or 66 F for two
years).
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published by Unesco
The latest (22nd) edition of Unesco's
international guide to study abroad,
covering the academic years
1979-1980 and 1980-1981
Lists over 200,000 offers of scholarships, assistantships,
travel grants and other forms of financial assistance available
throughout the world for study at post-secondary level in a
wide range of academic and professional fields.
Provides easy-to-use information on who can study,
what subject and where, details of each award including
how and where to apply.
The international course section has been considerably
augmented and now contains entries for study in over one
hundred countries under the auspices of some thousand
national and hundred international organizations.
716 pages Composite: English/French/Spanish
38 French francs
o»
xk A ^o
wresco
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept, P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victorial, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-652
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 {Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. -
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI.
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No, 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. -
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/München. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications
IHK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja, Népkoztârsasag utj'a 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,'
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratuiangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing 'and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. .- KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street.
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martjnus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christ-church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias Er Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O.' Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnem
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
January 1979 from
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
news
unesco
Role of Unesco Strengthened by
General Conference Decisions, Declares Director-General
"The spirit of co-operation and the
desire for consensus emerge
strengthened from the twentieth session
of the General Conference" declared
Unesco's Director-General, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, in his final
address to the Conference.
A central element in the session, he
said, had been the Declaration on
Fundamental Principles Concerning the
Contribution of the Mass Media to
Strengthening Peace and International
Understanding, Promotion of Human
Rights, and to Countering Racialism,
Apartheid, and Incitement to War.
"The ovation with which this
Declaration was adopted," he said,
"will without doubt remain one of the
most intense and moving moments that
I have experienced as Unesco's Director-
General. This happy issue is all the
more remarkable because the probability
of failure was so high. It is an
illustration of the triumph of a patient
desire for conciliation which never let
up."
The Director-General also stressed
the significance of the adoption by
acclamation of the Declaration on Race
and Racial Prejudice. "For the first
time in the United Nations system," he
said, "and even in the history of
mankind's long efforts to banish the
spectre of racism, the international
community will dispose of a text which,
without being legally binding, represents
a moral engagement covering all aspects
of the problem."
The General Conference, which was
presided by Mr. Napoleon LeBlanc of
Canada, ended its work on November
28th after approving the Organization's
programme for 1979 and 1980. To carry
out the programme, the Conference
voted a budget of $303 million, an
increase of six per cent compared with
the budget for 1977 and 1978.
In the field of education the
Conference stressed the importance of
forward-looking reflection so that
Unesco can assist governments in the
renewal or development of their
educational policies and long term
plans. In this connection, the 37th
International Conference on Education
to take place in Geneva this July will
have as its theme the improvement of
the organization and management of
education systems. Two regional
conferences on policies and cooperation
in education are foreseen: one for Latin
Mr. Napoleon LeBlanc of Canada (right),
president of the 20th session of the Unesco
General Conference, receives a copy of the
100th record issued in the Unesco Collection
of Traditional Music, from Director-General
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow. The presentation
took place during a musical evening
sponsored by the International Music
Council. At left is Mr. Leon Davico, Unesco
director of public information.
America and the Caribbean in
December 1979, and the other for the
European region in 1980.
Regional networks for educational
innovation set up in Asia, Africa, the
Arab States and Latin America will be
reinforced, and the International
Institute for Educational Planning and
Unesco's Regional Offices for
Education will employ new resources in
the training of educational personnel
able to help the progress of endogenous
development meeting the needs of
different societies and respecting their
cultural values. New educational
industries will be encouraged to provide
children and young people with
adequate school equipment, especially
textbooks in their mother tongue which
reflect more exactly the needs and
aspirations of the communities to which
they belong.
At the same time, the programme
stresses the need for a closer link
between schools and other educational
forces in the context of lifelong
education. It includes a series of
projects on behalf of girls and women,
of children who do not go to school at
all or who leave school early, as well as
for some urban populations who are
particularly disadvantaged such as
refugees and migrant workers. Other
fields where new initiatives are called for
under the programme include the
struggle against illiteracy, the
contribution of Unesco toward
integrated rural development, and the
promotion of physical education and
sport.
The Conference called for a marked
increase in Unesco's activities in science,
both to promote general progress of
science and technology and to cooperate
with States using these as tools for
development. Unesco is playing an
important role in the organization of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
United Nations Conference on Science
and Technology for Development, to be
held this August in Vienna, and as a
contribution to this it will convene in
Paris at the end of May the Second
International Conference on Scientific
and Technological Information in the
Service of Development (UNISIST II).
Among Unesco's fields of action in
the area of science will be the
encouragement of research aimed at
meeting the needs of each society, the
training of specialists and technicians
and the extension of science teaching
adapted to national requirements.
Unesco's Regional Offices for Science
and Technology enable the Organization
to take account of the diversity of
various situations and to aid States to
plan their own science policies and
adapt them to regional or international
endeavours.
The large-scale intergovernmental
research programmes in which Unesco
participates with the support of the
international scientific community will
be marked by new advances in such
fields as the earth sciences, ecology,
hydrology and oceanography. A special
effort will be made in the fields of
informatics and energy
sources particularly solar energy.
Unesco's social science programme
has been conceived along three main
axes: assuring the progress of these
disciplines in the world; promoting the
methodological possibilities of applying
them, and working to make them
contribute effectively in the quest for
solutions to the problems of human
rights, the strengthening of peace, the
study of development and of the
environment, the status of women and
young people and questions of
population.
During the next two years Unesco
plans to give a new impetus to the
teaching of human rights at all levels of
education. In addition, studies will be
undertaken on the scope of existing
human rights and the development of a
possible new category of rights related
to the requirements of a new
international order. Scientific research
on problems of peace and conflict will
also be stepped up and an international
congress on education in favour of
disarmament will be organized next
year.
With regard to culture, the
promotion of cultural identity in
Unesco's activities over the next two
years will be accompanied by research
on the points of convergence of
civilizations. An important innovation is
a programme of intercultural studies
where there has been a particularly rich
mingling of cultures such as the
Caribbean and Indian Ocean areas.
Preparation of the General History
of Africa will be continued and a study
will be made of the possible use of some
African languages as instruments for the
transmission of knowledge in modern
education.
In the context of international
campaigns for the preservation of the
cultural heritage, the Conference
decided to add several new groups of
monuments to those benefiting from
this type of co-operation. They include
the architectural complex of San
Francisco de Lima, in Peru; the Sans¬
souci Palace and La Ferrière citadel in
Haiti; the historical monuments and
sites of Malta; the heritage of the Jesuit
missions to the Guarani Indians in
South America; the Island of Gorée in
Senegal; the monuments of Hué in
Vietnam; the main monuments and sites
of the cultural triangle in Sri Lanka;
and the sites of Chinguitti, Tichitt and
Oualata in Mauritania. Following the
appeal launched by the Director-General
last year, an intergovernmental
committee will be set up to promote the
return of cultural property to its country
of origin.
New investigations will be made into
the place of the arts and the status of
the artist in contemporary societies.
Unesco will also continue its work to
aid the planning of cultural
development. A regional conference on
cultural policies in the Arab States is
foreseen toward the end of this year.
The relationship between culture and
communication and more precisely the
immense possibilities which the mass
media offer for the democratization of
cultural life also figure among the
themes for study in the programme. But
without doubt the major change in the
field of communication is the stress laid
upon aid to Third World countries. It is
not a question simply of using the help
of industrialized countries to give the
poorer countries the infrastructures,
trained staff and equipment which they
lack. They must also be placed in a
position where their voices can be better
heard through an increase in the sources
of information. The General Conference
thus declared its support for a new
balance in the international circulation
of ideas. In this connection, the
International Commission for the Study
of Communication Problems (the
MacBride Commission), which was
established in 1977, is scheduled to
complete its work and publish its report
this year. A preliminary report was
discussed by the General Conference. In
addition, two regional conferences on
communication policies are slated, one
for Asia and Oceania in February 1979,
and the other for Africa ii 1980.
At the invitation of the government
of Yugoslavia, the next session of the
General Conference will be held in
Belgrade in 1980.
El-Wakil is New Chairman
of Unesco Executive Board
Dr. Chams Eldine El-Wakil of Egypt
was elected chairman of the Executive
Board of Unesco when the Board
opened its 106th session 29 November in
Paris. Formerly dean of the law faculty
of Alexandria University, Dr. El-Wakil
has also served as president of Beirut
Arab University and minister of higher
education in Egypt. As chairman of the
Executive Board he succeeds Mr.
Leonard C.J. Martin (United Kingdom)
whose term of office expired in
November.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Race and Mass Media:
Two Important Unesco Declarations
Among the outstanding
accomplishments of the Unesco General
Conference which ended on 28
. November 1978 was the adoption by
acclamation of two important
declarations concerning controversial
fields. The first was the Declaration on
Race and Racial Prejudice, the second
the Declaration of Fundamental
Principles Concerning the Contribution
of the Mass Media to Strengthening
Peace and International Understanding,
the Promotion of Human Rights, and to
Countering Racialism, Apartheid and
Incitement to War.
The race declaration proclaims that
"All human beings belong to a single
species and are descended from a
common stock. They are born equal in
dignity and rights and all form an
integral part of humanity."
"Racial prejudice," it adds, "...is
totally without justification," and "Any
theory which involves the claim that
racial or ethnic groups are inherently
superior or inferior... or which bases
value judgements on racial
differentiation, has no scientific
foundation and is contrary to the moral
and ethical principles of humanity."
The second declaration stresses the
contribution which the mass media can
make to "strengthening of peace and
international understanding, the
promotion of human rights and the
Photo Unesco/Dominique Roger
An historic moment for Unesco : delegates to
the General Conference give a standing
ovation to the Director-General following
adoption by acclamation of the Declaration
on the Mass Media.
countering of racialism, apartheid and
incitement to war." It also insists on the
need for a "free flow and a wider and
better balanced dissemination of
information" and recognizes that "the
exercise of freedom of opinion,
expression and information... is a vital
factor in the strengthening of peace and
international understanding."
In its preamble, the declaration
acknowledges "the aspirations of the
developing countries for the
establishment of a new, more just and
more effective world information and
communication order." It also calls for
the mass media of the developing
countries to be provided with
"conditions and resources enabling
them to gain strength and expand," and
an article lays stress on the protection of
journalists in the exercise of their
profession.
Lack of space precludes longer
citations from these important
documents, but readers of "News from
Unesco" may obtain the full text of
either of these declarations by writing
to: OPI/DPI,
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris, France.
1977 Kalinga Award
goes to
Canadian Scientist
Canadian scientist and broadcaster
Fernand Seguin received the 1977
Kalinga Prize and the Unesco silver
medal for his life's work in the
popularization of science through his
numerous radio and television
programmes. Presenting the awards at a
special ceremony in Paris, Unesco
Director-General Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow said that Mr. Seguin was the
first Kalinga prize-winner to have
demonstrated that television is the most
effective instrument of our time to
popularize science.
During the same ceremony, Mr.
M'Bow presented the 1978 Unesco
Science Prize to a team of researchers at
the United Kingdom's Rothamsted
Experimental Agricultural Station for
their work in developing a new
pesticide.
Mr. Seguin, the Director-General
said, was a true scientist, a lecturer and
researcher in biology and pharmacology,
who had begun broadcasting for Radio
Canada in 1954 and had since made
hundreds of television programmes on
scientific subjects. At a time of rapid
advance in knowledge, he added, the
popularization of science was essential
for the general public to understand and
play its role in the shaping of science
policies. Reaching vast audiences
through television called for uncommon
and varied gifts which Mr. Seguin
possessed to a rare degree.
In reply, Mr. Seguin said the award
honoured Radio Canada too, since
audio-visual information was only .
possible through collective effort. On
the world level, he said, scientific
communication was more than the
simple transmission of knowledge. It
was also the transmission of the desire
to learn a desire which everyone tried
to satisfy by means of his own culture.
This desire, he added, must also be
inspired by the ideals of human
brotherhood.
Dr. Leslie Fowdon, director of the
Rothamsted Station, accepted the
Unesco Science Prize and silver medal
on behalf of the team which had
developed new pyrethroid insecticides
which are effective against a wide range
of insects. The chemicals, however, are
harmless to mammals and, being more
resistant to breakdown in sunlight, have
great potential for use in tropical
countries.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
On Stage at Unesco A diversity of cultures was presented at
Unesco headquarters during the General
Conference through a series of events
and exhibitions.
The Conference opened with a
performance by the Svetoslav Obretenov
Bulgarian National Choir of Schiller's
Ode to Joy from Beethoven's 9th
Symphony; it closed with a rendering of
works by Mendelssohn sung by a
children's choir forming part of the
chorale of Radio France.
For five weeks, enthusiastic
audiences of delegates from Unesco's
146 Member States attended evening
performances given by some 350
instrumentalists, singers, dancers and
actors from 16 countries.
The events varied widely in tone and
content, ranging from the solemn
ceremony marking the 30th anniversary
of the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights to performances on traditional or
historical themes. In this latter category
came the African evening presented by
Dakar's Daniel Soràno Theatre
Company; a show based on Japanese
mythology and performed by the Yoshi
Oida Company; a ballet on the theme of
the liberation of Algeria danced by the
Lehib troupe; The King of the
Monkeys, a Chinese cartoon film
inspired by an ancient novel; and songs
and dances by Navajo Indians of the
U.S.A. Performances which brought
ML**-.*^rv
Young visitors at the exhibition of "Toys
and Games of the World", organized with
the collaboration of the Bernard van Leer '
Foundation (The Netherlands).
together several artists or groups
included an evening of songs and
dancing by 26 pearl fishers from
Bahrein, which also featured the famous
violinist Yehudi Menuhin, the Ghosh
family trio from India and the Brazilian
guitarist Turibio Santos. Performances
of classical music included a recital by
another celebrated violinist, Henryk
. Szeryng, and concerts given by the
Zagreb soloists and Czechoslovakia's
Camerata Nova Ensemble. More
modern in spirit were a recital by
Susana Rinaldi, who brought to life
"the soul of the tango", evenings
featuring the Quebecan humorist Marc
Favreau and the Argentine composer-
performer Atahualpa Yupanqui, an
American show tracing half a century of
jazz history and two films dealing with
youth problems in the U.S.A.
Several delegations also organized
exhibitions, whose themes included : the
castles and palaces of the German
Democratic Republic; the cultural
heritage of Nepal; "Prague 1378-1978";
culture, science and education in the
U.S.S.R.; and the publications of
ALECSO, the Arab Educational,
Cultural and Scientific Organization. On
the eve of the International Year of the
Child, an exhibition of 900 games and
toys from 56 countries, many of them
made by children themselves, displayed
the creativity, inventiveness and artistic
talents of the young, as did exhibitions
of paintings and drawings by African
and Arab children and mosaics
produced by children from Bulgaria.
a
<
a
o
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
°>
o
¿
oc
en
O
J
=
C
D
*
4-»
o
<
b
c
e
(S
-O
"
3
2
"S
(0
J
Z
C
ñ
<
ö
O
O
»
ja
«
to
o
J
=
6
^
s
s
«
-s
»
o
>
c
«o
">
<
,
c
ï
*
S
"O
C
D
0
)
0
)
"Ö
r
-
c
d
]]>
</page>
</document>
