<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074701eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
SEPTEMBER 1983 6 French francs
bTC"*;
w
;r ;.
<
;
Rivers
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live.
© China Emperor Sui's Grand Canal
Opened to navigation by Emperor Sui Yang Di in 610 AD, the spectacular Grand Canal, now fully modernized, con¬
stitutes one of China's principal north-south waterways. 1 ,700 kilometres in length, it links the Beijing region to Hang-
Zhou, its southern terminus, in Zhe-Jiang Province, crossing on its way two great rivers, the Huang-He (Yellow River)
and the Chang Jiang (Yangtze). Above, the Grand Canal at Wu-Xi, Jiang-Su Province.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
SEPTEMBER 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille Is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief:
Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No 9 - 1983 -OPI 83-1 - 402 A
pages
4 The moving highways of history
by Eugenio Turri
8 THE AMAZON
A universe of water
by Thiago de Mello
12 THE CONGO
Waters of life
by Henri Lopes
15 Barges ahoy!
by Benoît Déla fon
16 THE DANUBE
Memoirs of Europe's mainstream
by Friedrich Heer
23 THE GANGA
The goddess who came down to earth
by Lokenath Bhattacharya
26 THE MISSISSIPPI
The stream of American consciousness
by John Seelye
29 THE NILE
Uncommon heritage
by Lotfallah Soliman
32 THE VOLGA
'Matushka'
by Leonid Likhodeev
35 THE YANGTZE
The great river flows east
by Bai Hua
38 Authors
A TIME TO LIVE...
CHINA: Emperor Sui's Grand Canal
TT THETHER they bring life like
u/w/ the Nile, or provide succour ,
r V in the hour of death like the
Ganges; whether like the Mississippi or
the Yangtze they day-in day-out tax the
resources of human ingenuity; whether
like the Volga and the Danube they
have served as ramparts against inva¬
sion; or whether they have kept many
of their secrets like the mighty, im¬
petuous Amazon and Congo, the
world's great rivers are an essentialpart
of the history of mankind.
In this issue of the Unesco Courier we
have invited writers from different
countries to evoke some of these water¬
ways which, in their many-sided roles
as providers of sustenance, subjects of
myth, arteries of communication, have
enabled those living on their banks to
broaden their horizons, build civiliza¬
tions, strengthen their identity. Sacred
bonds have been forged with some, like
the Ganges; others, like the Danube,
have influenced the course of secular
history. Asfor the Amazon, its basin is
a natural laboratory which has seen the
evolution of countless animal andplant
species which man has never fully
catalogued and which he owes it to
himself to preserve.
Our cover shows a stream in Marti¬
nique, for small streams and mighty
rivers share a commonfate. What is the
message of this rivulet to the Congo,
the Amazon, or the Yellow River?
What does the rocky trickle say to these
great repositories of life?
"Rivers of the world, beware. Fear,
as I do, the wantonness of mankind.
Yesterday my waters nourished the
black fish with flat heads, the fat grey
shrimps that are here called native
species that are disappearing or have
already vanished. Recklessly used fer¬
tilizer, rampant deforestation have
sullied my course. " '
But the damage man has caused, man
can repair. Today is no time to weepfor
the past nor to reject the resources
which science and technology offer to
the peoples of the world. Our task is to
adapt these resources to the real needs
ofmankind and to foresee catastrophes
to which unwise use of these resources
may lead. The fate of rivers is in¬
separable from that of threatened
forests, regions of desert encroachment
and flooded farmland.
Cover: Photo J. Ducange ©
Agence TOP, Paris.
Back cover: Yemanyá (1982), oil
on canvas (1.50 x 1.50 m) by the
Uruguayan painter José Gamarra.
Photo © All Rights Reserved.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The moving
highways
of history
by Eugenio Turri
IN the cosmogonies of the Ancient
World rivers were sacred elements
which represented the constant flux
of things in the sense understood by
Heraclitus. In ancient China they were
likened to the dragon, symbol of the
cyclical renewal of life. Generally speak¬
ing they were regarded as a source of fer¬
tility and life, linking the beginning to the
end, the principle to the whole, in an eter¬
nal and purifying cycle that is also the
cycle of the human soul.
In spatial and temporal terms, rivers
often exert a dual, contradictory in¬
fluence over man and his activities: they
both fertilize and destroy, attract and
repel, unite and divide. The forces they
engender are at once beneficial and
harmful. But ultimately, as events have
shown at different times and places, man
is always free to encourage one or the
other of these conflicting tendencies by
exploiting (or not) the great possibilities
which rivers hold for influencing the
course of history and organizing
geographical areas.
Ever since earliest times, man has been
drawn to rivers because they provided
water and enabled him to find his bear¬
ings. At the dawn of history, it was along
rivers that the very first farming com¬
munities began to subjugate the land and
harness nature. And it was the great
rivers of the Ancient World that saw the
blossoming of civilizations which chang¬
ed the course of historycivilizations
sometimes known as "river civiliza¬
tions" because rivers were the decisive
factor in their development, just as
revolutionary techniques for using other
natural elements were decisive in the
evolution of other civilizations such as
those of Neolithic times, the Bronze Age
and the Iron Age.
The great river civilizations, which
were economically dependent on ir¬
rigated crops and consisted of densely
populated, highly urbanized societies,
were located on alluvial plains along or
between major rivers. Thus the cradles of
the Chinese, Indian, Sumerian/Babylo-
The Orinoco
Its discharge is so vast that the rapids,
whirlpools and eddies which agitate its
eternal descent have blended in the unity
of a pulse which beats from the dry
season to the rains, with the same pauses
and paroxysms, since before man came
to be.
Alejo Carpentier
nian, and Egyptian civilizations were
respectively, the Yellow and Blue Rivers,
the Ganges, the Tigris and the Euphrates,
and the Nile. How did these rivers con¬
tribute to the growth of such
homogeneous and enduring forms of
human organization?
The French historian Lucien Febvre,
who formulated a "historical" and
"possibilist" theory of geography, at the
beginning of this century applied the no¬
tion of the "point d'appui" (literally,
"point of support") to define the natural
locations in which man settles. These
points d'appui included the alluvial plains
traversed by the great rivers, the moun¬
tains where they have their source, and
the coasts where they flow into the
sea in other words, the natural settings
which, whether easily habitable or not,
attracted man and encouraged him to
embark, with varying success, on his
historical destiny.
Strictly speaking, the great rivers
were the "points d'appui" of other
"points d'appui" the plains them¬
selves enabled man to perform
outstanding achievements and to em¬
bark on the conquest of nature. For if the
course of history depended solely on
rivers and not on mankind, it would be
impossible to explain civilizations such as
that of Europe, which became dominant
in completely different contexts. It is im¬
portant to understand exactly what
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Pans
]t WW
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
historical and civilizing roles were per¬
formed by the great rivers, as well as the
limitations of the river civilizations.
The various stages of the development
of European civilization took place on the
banks of "small" rivers such as the
Tiber, the Rhine, the Seine, the Thames,
and the Danube; but in order to deter¬
mine the geographical factors which
enabled European civilization to develop
steadily, it is necessary to look to other
areas of communication than river basins
and notably to the seas, or "liquid
plains" as they have been called by
another modern French historian, Fer¬
nand Braudel. First and foremost of these
seas is the Mediterranean, where the
Europeans founded their earliest
cultures, built up a pattern of trade, and
began a process of expansion that even¬
tually took them from Mediterranean
shores to the Atlantic and the other
oceans.
It is easy to see where the river civiliza¬
tions differed from, say, European
The Indus
For this one boon I thank the heavens
¡still,
The view of Indus' stream from Mir
¡Kalán.
Khushâl Khân Khattak
civilization. The latter is essentially
maritime, coastal, thalassocratic, and
outward-looking. The river civilizations,
on the other hand, were land-based,
agricultural and in all respects dependent
on and conditioned by their "liquid road"
and its limitations. They never extended
their communications network beyond
the route traced by the river or beyond
the se3 into which it flowed. This ex¬
plains why they became fossilized and
were eventually superseded and over¬
whelmed by civilizations which were
more dynamic, more open to the outside
world, and not as in their case tied down
geographically to a river.
What is true of European civilization is
even more valid, although in a different
sense, for Arab-Islamic civilization
which, enriched by the historical ex¬
perience and legacy of the river civiliza¬
tions, developed along universalist lines.
It exploited the "solid" overland routes
which took its merchants and preachers
beyond the desert to the confines of the
then penetrable world the humid
equatorial forests.
The British historian Arnold Toynbee
explained history and the great waves of
civilization through a phenomenon which
he called "challenge". In his view man is
instinctively urged to construct
something new where natural conditions
are at their most hostile and put the
greatest hindrances in his way. It is by
responding to this challenge, which
forces him to marshal all his intellectual
resources, technical inventiveness and
organizational abilities that, according to
Toynbee, he becomes increasingly
resilient. He saw confirmation for his
theory notably in Chinese civilization,
which came into being not along the Blue
River, which because of the lie of the land
flows with relative regularity, but along
the dangerous Yellow River, which is
beneficial but impetuous (it is
represented by the dragon in Chinese
mythology) and far more difficult to tame
than the Blue River.
After much debate between Marxist
and non-Marxist historians, it has been
generally agreed that river civilizations
like that of Egypt should be classified as
socio-historical organizations linked to
the "Asiatic production method", so
called because its original and most
typical forms are found in the river
valleys of Asia (in China, India and In¬
dochina). The Asiatic production method
springs from the need to carry out major
hydraulic constructions such as dykes
and canals in order to regulate the flow of
the river and use its waters for irrigation.
Work on that scale had to be carried out
by the community as a whole and re¬
quired a considerable degree of organiza¬
tion. It had to be placed under the control
of a higher authority and governed by ap¬
propriate rules, such as those written
down in the great Code of Hammurabi in
Mesopotamia. According to this inter¬
pretation, river societies were
bureaucratic and despotic by.nature, and
obeyed the decisions of a sovereign who
The Dnepr
On a fine, calm day, the Dnepr is a
wonderful sight as its mighty watersflow
serenely and effortlessly between forests
and hills.
Nikolai Gogol
acted as a mediator between man and
nature (between man and the gods), and
who, in his capacity of enforcer of the
law of the waters was sometimes in the
early period of Chinese history given the
title of "Great Engineer".
But is it true that ancient Egypt ex¬
emplifies the Asiatic mode of produc¬
tion? Compared with the enormous ef¬
forts needed to harness the great rivers
of Asia, especially the Yellow River, the
task presented by the Nile was less for¬
midable. After all, greater sacrifices were
demanded of the Egyptians during the
construction of the tombs, pyramids and
other monuments raised to mark an eter¬
nity comparable to that of the river. But
such massive projects required the same
hierarchical organization of society.
A very different role was played by the
major rivers of Europe, a continent that
has always been politically and
hydrologically fragmented. It would
perhaps be to take a naively deterministic
view of history to argue that the divisions
Wagenia fishermen on the rapids of the Congo, near Boyoma Falls, Zaire.
^^^P^^S^kÊi
* -
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
which continue to be a feature of Euro¬
pean history were originally caused by
the absence of any truly great river, and
in any case Europe has always been
outward-looking and attracted by wider
horizons. But it is a historical fact that
rivers have never been a unifying factor
in Europe. The Rhine, which was an
artery in the spread of the Roman Empire
and of Christianity, and then in the rise of
capitalism and industrialization, has
always tended to divide rather than
unite, even if it now seems to be becom¬
ing the axis of a new European unity. The
same is true of the Danube, which flows
through a mosaic of nations which have
never been united and for which the
river has never been a factor of mutual
understanding.
The Volga is quite different; it is a great
river par excellence, and also a kind of
mother figure (mat) in the Russian mind.
It has always played a fundamental role
in Russian history.
changed more radically over the ages
than those of almost any other river.
But to some extent such changes are
the lot of all great rivers. After com¬
parable beginnings, they each develop in
a way that is strictly governed by the
history of the country they water.
Although this is perhaps less true of the
Nile, it certainly holds good for other
great rivers which entered the nexus of
modern communications in recent
times those that were exploited during
the colonial era, such as the Mississippi,
the Congo and the Amazon.
Until then, these rivers had been a life-
giving force for local civilizations and a
constant presence in the background,
but only in an enclosed, self-contained
context. As symbols of supernatural
forces that could not be controlled by
man, they became part of the mythology
of the societies that lived on their banks.
As such they were respected. Not only
did they act as communication routes,
remotest parts of the continent by boat.
The colonial powers fully exploited that
opportunity to tap the wealth of Africa
(Stanley drew attention to the river as an
ideal channel by which Europeans could
introduce "trade and Christianity" to
Africa). The situation has scarcely
changed today, and the river still has vast
potential as a source of development for
equatorial Africa as a whole.
The Amazon has had a similar fate. An
exceptional artery of navigation, it too
was used as a means of draining the
resources of the continent by the groups
of adventurers called bandeirantes and
by the brief incursion of the seringueiros,
which is commemorated in the midst of
the forest by the Europeanized Utopian
dream of Manaus, built on the plunder of
Amazonian wealth. The time has not yet
come for the Amazon, either, to play a
new role in the history of South America,
although the relationship between men
and river in the region is fundamentally
The Russian world stretched
eastwards across the Volga, enfolding
the world of the steppes, welding
together Europe and Asia, enriching Rus¬
sian culture with new elements and giv¬
ing it an extra dimension, an Asiatic or
Euro-Asiatic consciousness.
Like all great territorial landmarks, the
Volga is a psychological and emotional
point of reference for the Russian people.
And it is no accident that during World
War II their last but impregnable bastion
was on the Volga, at the decisive battle
of Stalingrad (now Volgograd). That
episode brought the river even closer to
the hearts of the people, whose love for
the wide open spaces is not only
reflected emotionally by the Volga but
also historically and culturally determin¬
ed by it, with the result that they have
always had a continental rather than a
maritime calling. The Volga is also a river
whose appearance and function have
they provided a source of food and
reassurance. Then, with the advent of
colonial expansion, they were used by
Europeans as routes by which to
penetrate unknown continents the only
practicable routes for groups of men ar¬
riving by sea. Thus the Mississippi, even
though it flows from north fo south and
the logical way to explore north America
was from east to west, was immediately
recognized as the most suitable route in¬
land because it provided direct access to
the heart of the continent and its riches.
It therefore quickly became a vital axis
for the conquest of the country.
The great equatorial rivers such as the
Congo and the Amazon were not used in
the same way. A natural barrier, the
Stanley Falls (now Boyoma Falls),
prevented ships coming from the sea
from sailing up the Congo. But above
these falls, the slow-moving, broad up¬
per Congo made it possible to reach the
different from that which existed in the
ancient river civilizations.
Once regarded as a source of fertility,
rivers have become resources to be ex¬
ploited, waterways. Once the leavening
agent of civilizations, they now play a
more modest role. They no longer
motivate the industrialized world, which
sees them in purely economic terms as
communication routes. And such are the
scale and nature of communications in
the modern world that even the biggest
rivers, even those which are most impor¬
tant for trade, have ceased to be vital
"points d'appui". Today the natural
order that once prevailed seems to be the
victim of an inexorable process of
disintegration. Even as myths, the great
rivers have had their day, though they
can still excite the passions of those who
live on their banks. To this extent they
have retained a human dimension.
Eugenio Turn
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
y
In ancient China rivers
were associated with
dragons, the symbol of the
cyclical renewal of life. Far
left, three dragons form
the motif of this stone¬
ware bowl dating from the
Sung dynasty (10th to
13th century).
Photo ' The Metropolitan Museum of
Art, New York. Rogers Fund.
Left, these models of
boats on the Nile in ancient
Egypt were found at Dayr
al-Bahri, near Thebes, in
the tomb of Meketer, a
minister of one of the last
kings of the Xlth dynasty
of the Middle Kingdom era
(2040-1710 BC).
Photo Hassia. Paris
The sacred Hindu city of
Varanasi is situated on the
left bank of the Ganga
(Ganges) in Uttar Pradesh
State, northern India. For
centuries pilgrims have
come to Varanasi in their
thousands to cleanse
themselves in the purify¬
ing waters of the sacred
river.
Photo Claude Sauvageot, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
AMAZON
6,280 km.
Rises in (he High Andes and emp¬
ties into the Atlantic Ocean
discharge: 180,000 cubic
metres per second
of basin: 6,915,000 sq. km.
is estimated that the Amazon
carries one-fifth of all water that
runs off the earth's surface
turns the ocean water from salt
to brackish for over 160 km.
from the shore
Right: Manaus stands on the Rio Negro some 13 km above its
confluence with the Amazon. It is one of the most important
and modern river ports in South America, but on the outskirts
of the city it is still possible to see houses built in traditional
style on piles and rafts to protect them from flooding.
A universe
of water
by Thiago de Mello
HIGH among the everlasting snows of the uppermost cor¬
dillera, a thin trickle of water suddenly bubbles forth and
starts to trace a hesitant line on the age-old surface of the
rock. This is where the Amazon is born and, with every instant that
passes, is born again and yet again. As it edges its way slowly
downwards like a twisting sliver of light, it spreads out and, cutting
deep into the greenery, devises a passage for itself and gathers
strength. Underground streams emerge and join the torrent flowing
down from the Andes. The wind buffets the brilliant white
underbelly of the clouds and rain tumbles from the sky. As the
streams come together, their combined flow moves ever onward
and splits into a myriad waterways irrigating the vast plain crossed
by the Equator.
This plain occupies one-twentieth of the land surface of the Earth
we live on. It forms a lush equatorial universe covering nine coun¬
tries of Latin America, almost half the territory of Brazil. Its
thousands of rivers and streams represent the world's largest
freshwater reserve and form an enchanted labyrinth which is con¬
stantly being reshaped as it spreads through the millions of square
kilometres of the green land mass.
Situated entirely within the humid tropics, this universe of water
is the great Amazon basin, with its dense and intoxicating forest
where, ever since the beginning of the Tertiary era, life forms spun
from the fabric of the plant world have continued to pulsate over
vast areas that have remained untouched and free from the en¬
croachment of man. With so many of its endless expanses untrod¬
den and its true nature unplumbed, Amazonia has yet to be
discovered.
Come with me General.
The weather is set fair
and the wind is up.
Gently we glide
as we row in the blackness
of the translucent stream,
taking care not to let
the prow of our craft
cast ripples
on the mirror of the light.
Come discover with me
the green sources of life.
This is the river which Vicente Pinzón saw for the first time in
1500, without realizing that he had left the Atlantic and had ven¬
tured into the mouth of a freshwater ocean, at what came to be
known as Santa Maria de la Mar Dulce. This was the Amazon
whose waters were to be furrowed by the keels of the first sailing-
ships, the Parana Guaço of the Indians living on its banks. The
river went by a variety of names:
the Freshwater Sea,
the River Orellana,
Marañan,
the Guinea of the
Arawaks,
Parançu dos Tupis,
Rio de las Amazonas,
the Great River of the
[Amazonas...
8
Or else, simply the Amazon, the river which stretches for more
than six thousand kilometres from the first trickle flowing down
from Lake Lauri, Lauricocha, among the summits of the Andes
and from Vilcanota, before coming to take shape in the turbulent
silt-laden waters of the Urubamba and then going on to join the "
Ucayali and swell the Solimoes as it winds through the Peruvian
forest. It is under that same name that it enters Brazil and settles
into its main stream bed, accompanied by the tree trunks torn from
its banks. This is the name it keeps until, in a strange and
mysterious region, it meets the jet black waters of the Rio Negro,
with which its own silt-charged flow is never destined to blend. Yet
it is here that it becomes the Amazon proper, the impulsive river
that goes on to carve out the deep straits of Breves before emptying
into the Atlantic and pushing back the waters of the ocean for enor¬
mous distances.
It is true that the ocean takes its revenge. It gathers its salt-laden
strength and comes back in force. Its powerful and deafening
rollers, several metres high, overwhelm the river, sweeping aside
everything in their path and sinking river craft, whatever their size.
The river never relaxes the law it imposes on man. This is the em¬
pire of water. Water that races off in angry eddies, water that tosses
obstacles aside, water that laps, water that uproots, water that calls
and beckons, water that tumbles over cataracts, water that plunges
into whirlpools, water that slowly recedes, water that suddenly
peaks in flood, river water that hardly seems to move at all, and
becomes dangerous when it harnesses the rising wind and lashes
out, water that lies motionless in the silence of the igapo (1).
Water occupying deeps of a hundred fathoms or more, where
huge blind piraibas (2) slowly navigate the silent abyss. Narrow ig-
arapés (3), like that of Pucu whose delightful meanders I know so
well, never dry up completely and leave their beds exposed, even
when the river is at its lowest. Shallow water, transparent or turgid,
where the rays scatter very early in the morning. Water at the mouth
of lakes or gushing out from springs. Still water: in the Lago
Marcelo, beyond the upper reaches of the Parana-mirin-de-Eva,
whenever the uirapururu sings, the entire forest falls silent, the
other birds stop singing, and the water itself is quiet, listening with
only a restless quiver from time to time.
Water straddled from bank to bank by tall grasses or covered by
undergrowth, with a thick bed of tangled vegetation as the only
path. Water bringing diseases; water infected with amoebic y
Right, the Amazon near the port of Tabatinga. Photo was taken
in the middle of April, the month when streams flowing Into the
left bank of the river reach their highest point as a result of
heavy rainfall in the northern part of the basin. The same
phenomenon occurs on the right bank in June.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
"U^ ;
w t%miï i
., r
:* *,
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
>#i
^ parasites or blackwater fever. But also well-water: in the humid
heat of the forest, thin trickles of cool, thirst-quenching water never
run dry. Muddy water in rivers like the Solimoes, the Madeira, the
Jurua and the Purus; blue water like that of the Tocatins; green
water in the Tapajoz and Xingu. The black waters of the Rio An-
dira reflect all the colours of the rainbow.
/ have just journeyed up and down the Solimoes from where it
joins the Rio Negro, not far from Manaus, to the wedge-shaped
area in Amazonia where Brazil, Peru and Colombia meet. The twin
townships of Tabatinga in Brazil and Leticia in Colombia stand
side-by-side and look out across the river on the small and long-
suffering settlement ofRamon Castilla in Peru on the other bank,
which has already been devastated eleven times by the havoc
wrought by the river as it washed away all the fertile land. I spent
day after day travelling in a small craft with its engine amidships.
It was at the time of the year when the river was risingthe en-
chente, when the swollen river had burst its banks andflooded the
low-lying areas, uprooting trees and carrying away thepaltry dwell¬
ings. I spent hour after hour on the river without meeting a living
soul. Then, suddenly, a skein of white cranes flew past, outlined
against the transparent background of the evening, and immediate¬
ly thereafter, in a bend in the river along the bankside, Iperceived
a small canoe hollo wed out of the trunk ofthe itauba tree. Standing
in the prow was a caboclo (4) making signs with his oar, as if he
were calling for help. He was afinefigure ofa man, with a radiant
expression, but he was bowed down with grief, for one ofhisyoung
children had just died, carried off by fever, with no one to help.
The waters of the Amazon go through an endless cycle, starting
with the time known as the "first waters", when the river starts
showing signs of wanting to rise, followed by the full flood, the en-
chente, and then the falling flood, or vazante. It is this ebbing and
flowing of the river which governs and transforms the lives of peo¬
ple living in the Amazon basin from one season to the next.
Everywhere in Amazonia, not only deep in the forest or along the
water's edge but in settlements and urban centres, man feels the
beneficial or adverse impact of the rising and falling of the river,
in his home, in his food, in his daily labour.
The fluctuating pattern of the river is a constant in the decisions
people make in organizing their lives since it is also bound up with
economic cycles. If there is a sharp fall in river level, the harvest will
be plentiful, since the inundated low-lying areas will have been
made very fertile by the mineral salts and organic matter brought
down by the river. This is the season for fishing, and a good time
to plant. By contrast, heavy floods mean disaster and suffering: the
fish hide in stagnant pools that can only be reached through forest
trails, crops are destroyed, livestock have to be driven to higher
ground or herded quickly into the maromba, a kind of narrow
enclosure standing on stilts, where they are liable to attack by
sucuruji snakes; the lower parts of the houses remain under water,
and the snakes come and threaten the domestic animals.
Man is at the mercy of the river, but he does not lose heart. He
waits for the waters to recede and hopes to make the most of the
land enriched by flooding. The river dictates his behaviour and he
10
is always at the river's beck and call. If he fails to comply, he is
condemned.
/ come from that generous land
where the men born of its lushness
remain captive and forgotten.
And yet they are the brothers
of those resourceful and changeless elements:
water, wind and hope.
Come with me
and learn about the river and Us laws.
Come with me
and learn the science of the whirlpool.
Come and listen to the birds of the night
in the magical silence of the igapo,
draped in emerald stars.
Whereas in Genesis it was the countenance of God, today it is
hope that shines on the waters of my river. In spite of all the exac¬
tions: the destruction, the plundering of its wealth, the unbridled
deforestation, its fauna in jeopardy and, above all, the dire poverty
of its riverside populations, hope still exists in Amazonia. There is
no end to man's courage. But our main fear is that the forest is
starting to tire of being ill-treated to the extent it has been.
Rainfall is a regular feature of the virgin forest, not only during
the winter months when the rain falls in solid sheets for days
without ever letting up. Even in summer, which is supposed to be
the dry season, the rain never stops. All of a sudden, the large pot¬
bellied clouds lumber into motion, turn black and break up. The
cloudburst sweeps down and the Amazonian storm and wind blow
in gusts. Such downpours can occur in the early morning or in the
middle of the day or at night, when the darkness of the river cross¬
ing is streaked by lightning flashes illuminating the turbulent sur¬
face of the waves from one bank to the other.
Above left, a young Yagua
Indian from the left bank of
the Amazon. The Yagua and
other Indian peoples such as
the Jivaros and the Zaparos
belong to a group of in¬
digenous communities
which have remained more
or less independent
throughout their history.
Photo Jim Holland Rapho, Paris
The Rio Negro, one of the
major tributaries of the
Amazon, near the port of
Manaus. In some places the
dense tropical vegetation
makes navigation virtually
impossible.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
It was from a storm of this kind on the Peruvian Solimoes that
the Indian Moron and his five-year old son, the caboclo Rios and
I myself once had a narrow escape. I had been spending the day in
a Yagua Indian village talking of one thing or another with a young
tuchaua, or witchdoctor, who knew a good deal about the datura
and other magical plants. Before nightfall, we set off in a canoe fit¬
ted with an outboard motor for Choriaco, a small riverside settle¬
ment, which we expected to reach in about two hours. It was during
the flood season.
We sailed up-river keeping close to the forest-lined bank and
were about halfway when the storm broke. From the stern, where
he was operating the motor, my Indian friend said quietly: "This
is going to be terrible". Close by him, in the bottom of the boat,
was his small son, all hunched up against the cold. I can still see
myself on the seat, turning round and noticing, before it became
completely dark, the brightness of his enormous eyes, intense with
fear. Up front, on a narrow seat, shirtless, was the caboclo Luis
Rios, a native of Choriaco.
We went headlong into the storm without saying a word, bound
together in our silence. As the speed of the current increased, the
canoe started shaking and reared up on the crest of the wave before
falling back with a crash. The rain was lashing against us from all
sides. The time soon came when we could see absolutely nothing
and were surrounded by darkness. The front of the boat was con¬
tinually banging against tree trunks and then suddenly there was a
thudding sound and the canoe looked as if it was about to capsize.
Moron tipped the motor towards him, so that the propeller was out
of the water', safe from the risk of damage. Our only help came
from the lightning flashes, which split the sky in two. In the fleeting
moment of illumination, we could see an enormous trunk, a whole
piece of a tree with its branches still green with leaves, bearing down
on us. Swiftly and silently, with a flick of the rudder, Moron moved
the canoe away from the obstacle.
It was so dark that I could not see my hand a few centimetres
away from my face, yet time and again I was certain that the Indian
Moron managed to see something of the river and its banks in the
midst of the pitch blackness. He was able to see or at least his ears
or all his other very keen senses told him that something was coming
towards the boat. For instance, he would suddenly bear to the left
and then straighten up the craft again by throttling back the motor,
while out of his half-open mouth there came a raucous cry, brief
but powerful which, as if by a miracle, could be heard above the
shrieking and howling of the storm. It was as if he were the kinsman
of the river.
The storm abated shortly before we reached Choriaco. I now feel
the time has come for me to recount two things that happened that
night. First, we had barely entered the approaches to the Parana of
Choriaco when we saw several canoes coming in our direction.
Their occupants were the men and women of the area. I shall never
forget them. They had been expecting usin the early hours of the
night but they had realized that, since we were late, we must have
been caught in the storm, and they had decided to set out and come
to our help. When they saw us, a great prolonged cry of joy went
up among them. Second, after the storm was over, the sky lit up
with starsall the starswhich, enormous, began to shine as they
floated free and unimpeded in the vast space of the Amazonian
night.
Thiago de Mello
(1) Igapo: the ¡ndian word for parts of the forest where the undergrowth
is submerged.
(2) Piraiba: large Amazonian freshwater fish.
(3) Igarapé: literally, the "path of the canoe". By extension, a small
tributary or a channel between two islands or two rivers.
(4) Caboclo: a Brazilian of mixed fndian and white parentage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
CONGO
4,370 km.
Rises in the Shaba region of Zaire
as the Lualaba River, but its
remotest source lies between
Lake Tanganyika and Lake
Malawi, in Zambia, as the
Chambesi river; empties into the
Atlantic Ocean
discharge: 41,000 cubic
metres per second
of basin: 3,820,000 sq, km.
up to Kisangani
known as the Zaire, a
corruption of the African word
nzadi or nzart = river
Waters
of life
by Henri Lopes
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
The Wagenia people, who live on the banks of the Congo near Boyoma Falls, are expert
and daring fishermen. In the rapids they build ingenious wooden scaffolding structures
from which are suspended man cone-shaped fish traps.
t~ r
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
I have travelled so much that on occa¬
sion I have forgotten the map traced
out by glow-worms, the village
dance, and even the way of tightening the
throat muscles to articulate, the men, the
hand, the fire, the drop, the salt and that
which burns, on the path from the thighs
to the pectorals. But when, in some place
or other on this earth, deprived of flam¬
boyant trees and the odour of mangoes,
my heart guided my footsteps aimlessly
along beaches, questioning the
fascinating mystery of the abyss, it was
always to you that my thoughts returned.
For do nof envy the ocean.
Do you know the River, just up-stream
of M'Foa and Kinshasa? When the boat
leaves the port and obliquely fends the
fantasia of foam, its smoke still holds in
long suspension the dream of the
dreamer who follows it from the quays.
It will have disappeared from view before
it reaches Nsélé.
If you have never made the pilgrimage
to Loango, do not hold out the begging
Comparatively little of the vast hydroelectric potential of the Congo basinestimated
to be in the region of 130,000,000 kilowatts- has so far been harnessed. Above, the
hydroelectric dam at Inga, about 40 kilometres upstream from Matadi, was completed
in 1972 with an installed capacity of 300,000 kilowatts. The Inga dam represents only
the first phase of a grandiose scheme which, if completed, would make this site the
largest hydroelectric complex in the world, with a potential capacity of 30,000,000
kilowatts.
bowl, go up to the plateau at the level of
Malébo Pool.
You who hunt or fish by night, what¬
ever your patience, whatever the art of
him who weaves your fish traps and nets,
there's no point in trying, no trick will
surprise the manatees the elders told us of
when they taught us about life and about
the country.
The river has been emptied. The
caymans (or crocodiles, I have never real¬
ly known which) have fled too. If you still
insist on dreaming and on crossing a
stretch or two of the spirit kingdom, then
open Ngando*, by the elder Lomani-
Tchibamba, the first who wanted to set
down the song of the mothers to their
sons, the first to say:
"Beware! Don't go to the river. Go
straight to school... We have enough
water in our well; I will fill you the big
pool and you can amuse yourself as you
like... Beware, my child, not to the
river."
He will also tell you about Ngando
eating the child.
He will tell you about Ngando the
magnanimous returning his prey.
Ah! Do not say, with a sophisticated
scholar's smile, that this is the world of
tales, as beautiful as the unreason of
styles, but a world which the present age
has swept away. The outboard motor-
boat fends the liquid and my heart
breaks. Look at these men of water and
nets on M'Bamou Island. And listen to
them too. Above all listen to them when
the tom-tom throbs to sing the bride and
groom, to calm the river's pain, or simply
to drive away the mosquitoes. Only
yesterday a young man from the city
came and, sneering, bathed there. All the
arts of the swimming pool at his
fingertips.
He went straight to the bottom.
Yes, right before our eyes. Thus light¬
ning puts a stop to all who are oblivious
of the oath to the spirits.
Why do you not learn the wisdom of
silence and humility? By listening to the
leaves of night, they could tell of the
adventure that bends Congo.
As for those boats of yours...
Nodules of noise and grease...
The fish have lost their flesh. Nothing
but bones, bones, bones!
Pass by, tenacious islets. No one will
know the secret of the water hyacinths.
Neither the source nor the sky. But where
are the canoers with the athletes' voices
and the ships with wheels, glow-worms of
strange dreams which answered our
boyish greetings with the lash of the in¬
sults of that time? Oh, you we wished to
adore! Even my song of awakening goes
astray, caught up in your gluey toils.
There must be a return to the water, to
wet the feet there, for the washing of the
hands, the face and the mouth. For garg¬
ling too, sometimes, so that you can cry
until you can cry no more.
These waters gave life.
And like Nzambé, the Father, they
took it away, in a sovereign game.
Always by surprise. Such is the rule,
without explanation. Traveller deprived
of muscled breasts, beware the eyes of
our waters. Beware the beauty who
glistens as she looks at a sky the colour of
a rascally lover. In an overweening desire
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Photo Almasy, Paris
Pile dwellings in the Congo delta.
The Congo waterway system comprises a navigable network totalling
some 1 3,500 kilometres. It carries over two million tons of freight an¬
nually despite the many obstructions which hamper passage, not
least of which is the proliferation of aquatic vegetation, such as these
water hyacinths.
to caress her, a team of canoers smashes
like an egg against the rock. They roll,
rush and sink in the elements. The
faithful women in mourning, on the
banks of Kin and M'Foa, still hold their
breath, seeking to decode in the howling
of the tornado the songs of those who
rush towards Djoué. Thus, like the
hours, until the malanga** of joy.
You would need to go far, far across
the seas, impossible now to say how far,
beneath a like fiery sky, go to the
Amazon, to find such speed, such surg¬
ing. Power of light or of carcass,
whatever you wish, what matter the
geographer's figures. It can be sensed.
They came from the summit of the sea.
They asked for your papers and we
declared Nzadi, Nzadi the River,
naturally.
Zaire repeated their clumsy throats
and they wrote it down on their sea-
route.
But we do not give in, in spite of the
seasons and the centuries. The brothers,
over there, only remember two cradles:
the other is Guinea. "Si no tienes de Con¬
go, tienes de Carabali"*** chorus the
Mambi neighbours.
Congo, then, baptismal fonts
notwithstanding.
Diogo Cao died believing that you led
to the kingdom of Préster John. We
knew better, for once! This meander led
only to the court of the Makoko, that one
to the court of Mani Kongo.
Who has only one name, when all's
said and done? There is the name given at
birth. The name given at circumcision.
That which is won in combat. That of the
enemy. That of the time of the white
beard.
And so it is with you: Oyez for
Lukuga, oyez for Ruzizi, oyez for
Luapulu, oyez for Luvua, oyez for
Lualaba, oyez for the mystery of the
heavenly host. And that's only part of the
magic. Lake Kivu and Lake Moéro too.
Where does the lazy water end, the
alphabet of your course? A weakling, at
first you do not yet dare run. Who will
recognize the tea-coloured youth who
rushes headlong, horns foremost,
towards Lukoléla, after his marriage
with the river of the Sangos? Then,
dignified and powerful, His Majesty pur¬
sues his course to the Djoué. And here is
the inferno where the water can be heard
seething, whirling in the dance of the
demented, hurled in burning spray above
the rocks, stirred up by an unmanageable
fire down there beneath the crust.
Paralysed and delighted, the indifferent
traveller suddenly wants to question the
heavens.
Then, Mai-Ndombé, San Antonio, the
mouth and the horizon. Weary, your soul
at peace, you will stretch yourself out for
ever like a combatant, his task ac¬
complished, in the salt of dissolution.
Congo.
Henri Lopes
* Literally Crocodile.
* * A kind offuneral wake.
*** "Ifyou're not Congo, you're Carabali"
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Drawing © Gate-Pans for Pier N° 1
Project for a floating village of barges on the New York waterfront.
Barges ahoy!
WITH the growth of awareness over the past decade of
the need to husband finite energy resources, there
has been a renewal of interest in rivers and water¬
ways as an economical and reliable, if not the most rapid,
means of transportation. Locks and waterways have been
adapted and improved so as to be able to handle very large
barges and storage facilities at riverside ports have been enlarg¬
ed. One side effect of this has been that a number of the older
smaller barges, though still riverworthy, are lying unused
because they are no longer economic to run.
However, the construction and technical characteristics of
these traditional barges make them easy to convert to a wide
range of other purposes. "Pier No. 1", a Paris-based associa¬
tion formed to develop programmes for the conversion and re-
utilization of these barges, is now bringing its research to
fruition.
The Rhine
It was the voice of the noblest of rivers,
The voice of the free-born Rhine;
To other fields hope guided him, when, high up there,
He bade his kin the Tessin and the Rhone farewell;
Drunk with the taste of travel, eager to depart,
His regal soul to Asia drew him on.
Friedrich Hölderlin
Prompted by Pier No. 1, the New York municipal authorities
are studying a project for the creation of a "village" of tradi¬
tional barges (see drawing), an ensemble of dwellings, craft
workshops, cafés, shops, and so on. This operation, which is
destined to last for seven years, is aimed at bringing new life
to New York's waterfront. The speed with which the village
could be assembled and its low capital and maintenance costs
offer a rapid answer to the municipal authorities' needs.
Flat-bottomed, forty metres long, five metres wide and four
metres high, the traditional barge, dating from the beginning of
the century, has all the characteristics necessary for adaptation
to multiple uses. The living-quarters, narrow, functional cabins,
are situated aft, separated from the hold by the propulsion unit
which usually runs on diesel, although gas, petrol or coal-fired
engines may be used. Unaffected by the corrosion that plagues
marine engines, these units also provide power for other equip¬
ment aboard such as lighting and ventilation.
The hold offers a large space easily convertible to any use.
Transformed into an audio-visual viewing room, for example, it
could comfortably seat eight people. Similarly, if converted for
tourist travel, it could house ten cabins approximately the size
of a railway sleeping-compartment.
Studies being undertaken for the Government of Colombia
show that the hold of a barge converted to hospital purposes
could house some thirty beds, whilst the bridge could be used
as a reception and outpatient treatment area. Several of these
more or less permanently-moored, floating hospital wards
could be serviced by a small number of more mobile barges
equipped as operating theatres or analytical laboratories on
which major surgical operations or medical investigations could
be carried out.
This flexible type of organization has much to recommend it,
particularly in developing countries where patients often have
to make long and arduous journeys to reach the nearest land-
based hospital. Mobile riverborne medical units would make it
easier to maintain closer contact with larger and often widely
dispersed populations and would avoid the much heavier cost
of land-based medical centres.
Suitably adapted barges could also help to change the tradi¬
tional relationship between tourists and tourist centres.
Holidaymakers would no longer be obliged to crowd into
seaside or country resorts causing seasonal strain on local
facilities, encouraging unsightly, unplanned urban develop¬
ment and despoiling beauty spots with their litter.
Large numbers of barges of traditional type are now available
on the market. Their rational adaptation and re-use could effec¬
tively meet a variety of housing, medical, cultural, communica¬
tion and leisure needs, at minimum cost while respecting the
human and natural environment. _ . , M
m Benoit Delafon
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
DANUBE
2,860 km.
in the Black Forest moun¬
tains and empties into the Black
Sea
discharge: 7,000 cubic
metres per second
of basin: 817,000 sq. km.
Danube flows through 8
countries: Austria, Bulgaria,
Czechoslovakia, Fed. Rep. of
Germany, Hungary, Romania,
USSR and Yugoslavia, and is
known variously as the Donau,
the Duna, the Dunaj, the Dunav,
the Dunay and the Dunarea
AS old as the world, gushing forth
from the prehistory of the conti¬
nent, the Danube is Europe's
longest river after the Volga. It was on
this waterway which marked the frontier
of Latin Europe that the Roman
Emperor Marcus Aurelius composed his
Meditations, a work which would be a
source of consolation to later generations
of Europeans. But long before then the
Danube had been woven into the history
of peoples who had crossed it and sailed
Memoirs
of Europe's
mainstream
by Friedrich Heer
its length. The flumen Danubius of the
Romans (who called its lower reaches the
Ister), it had previously been the river of
the Celts, as indicated by its name which
recalls that of a Celtic god.
The Donau of the Germans and the
Austrians, the Dunaj of the Slovaks, the
Duna of the Hungarians, the Dunav of
the Serbo-Croats, the Dunarea of the
Romanians, this sombre mother would
offer peoples a journey a journey to life
and trade, a journey to war and death.
With its abundantJjish it gave sustenance
to the fishermen who settled on its banks.
Some years ago traces of an ancient
culture were found on the shores of the
Danube in Bulgaria. Strange sculptures
depicted gods emerging from the river.
Gods of eternal life or gods of death?
Let us briefly follow the course of the
Danube from its birth in the mountains
until it is engulfed by the sea for, like life
itself, it is born, grows, and hastens to its
dissolution.
»>*;
=*
V
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
It is in the Black Forest, at Donaue-
schingen, an attractive town still unspoilt
by industrialization, that the river is first
called by its name. Here the Brigach, the
Breg and another stream unite. Not yet
laden with history and ships, it flows
smoothly and slowly, a small river that
will grow into a great one.
At Ulm the Danube becomes
navigable. For centuries, from the Mid¬
dle Ages onwards, flat-bottomed,
shallow-draught boats known as "Ulm
boxes" plied between Ulm and Vienna.
The Ulm Münster, one of the loveliest
German gothic towers, which still
delights the traveller's eye, is an opus
Francigenum, for it was the French who
created Gothic and introduced it to
Europe. At Ulm, too, there are echoes of
Descartes. It was here that the French
philosopher, who served as an officer in
the Imperial army, dreamed the great
dream of Reason, clear, alert and intran¬
sigent, which would earn him a place in
the history of universal thought.
Now the Danube threads its way
through rocks towards Sigmaringen. The
fortress of Sigmaringen is still inhabited
by descendants of the Hohenzollern-
Sigmaringen whose ancestors set out
from Nuremberg, riding as far as
Brandenburg, and Prussia where they
Above right, the
Danube at Budapest.
View of the left bank of
the river showing the
dome of the Parliament
building and the town
of Pest. In the
background, behind the
second bridge, can be
seen Margaret Island.
Photo © Almasy, Pans
The plant and animal
life of the Danube delta,
a large area of which
was designated as a
nature reserve in 1962,
is unique in Europe. The
many varieties of birds
to be found there in¬
clude Europe's larg¬
est concentration of
white pelicans (Pele-
canus onocrotalus).
Photo Cordier © Pitch, Paris
became masters of a State which now no
longer exists.
The first great city through which the
Danube flows is Regensburg a city of
great beauty (especially its centre). In the
Middle Ages it was already a town of im¬
portance whose missionaries and mer¬
chants found their way to eastern
Europe. It is a city of old churches,
venerable patrician houses, old inns that
serve fine food and wines. Here in its up¬
per course the Danube is swollen by
tributaries bringing melted snows from
the Alps the Hier, then the Isar, the
Bavarian river that flows through
Munich.
Then comes Passau, today on the
border between the Federal Republic of
Germany and Austria. Here, in the
"town of fat priests", in the sumptuous
chapter-house of the cathedral, the son
of the customs officer Alois Hitler receiv¬
ed his first youthful impressions. His
name is marked indelibly on the
memories of those who survived the great
massacre he unleashed on Europe.
No, the Danube is not harmless, just as
the great current of European history is
not harmless. For centuries a deadly
whirlpool caused by the wrecks of
countless ships which sank after running
on to a treacherous reef brought terror to
the stretch of the river between Linz and
Passau. A stream of death, a journey to
death, a journey to the dark east.
The medieval German epic The Song
of the Niebelung, which was written near
the Danube, evokes journeys in the dawn
of Latin western Europe, and sings of the
fatal journey to Etzel-Attila, king of the
Huns, the husband of Siegfried's widow
Kriemhild. She leads her people to death,
the monstrous revenge of a monstrous
woman. Because the churchman who ac¬
companies them on their journey down
the Danube foretells the fate which
awaits them, Hagen, Siegfried's
murderer, casts him in the river. Thus he
suffers the fate of a Cassandra, here
dressed in ecclesiastical robes, on the eve
of the Middle Ages during which pagan
survivals fused with a touch of Chris¬
tianity, a Christianity of the sword,
Christianity as it was understood by the
men and women of those times. Like the
Spanish poem El Cid and the French
Chanson de Roland, the Song of the
Niebelung was also destined to awaken a
national consciousness.
The Mekong
In the clear blue waters
The mirror image of the coconut palms
From the sea the steady susurration
Of waves that rock
Like the hammock of my infant days
Giang Nam
After Linz, the Danube flows through
the Wachau, its most romantic stretch. In
this land of ancient culture, it passes by
ruined castles and sunny slopes covered
by vineyards. It flows by Willendorf, site
of the discovery of the "Willendorf
Venus", a prehistoric statuette of a
mother-goddess venerated for thousands
of years throughout Europe and even
further east. Strindberg once stayed in
this district, and long before him, at the
time of the Crusades, Richard the
Lionheart was held prisoner in a castle
near Krems, a town once bigger than
Vienna, which still jealously guards its
old centre. On his, way back from the
Crusade, Richard was seized at
Schwechat, outside Vienna, and placed
in the custody of the Austrian Duke of
Babenberg. The bard Blondel sang the
praises of his master Richard Cceur-de-
Lion, the king of England who spoke
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
barely a word of English. That a valiant
knight, a subject of dispute between
Crusaders (when have there not been
disputes, quarrels and wars between our
fathers and our ancestors?) should be
taken prisoner on his return from the
Crusade, then constituted a European af¬
fair of state, a "scandal".
The Duke of Babenberg handed over
the King of England to the Emperor
against payment of a heavy ransom. It
would have been better for Richard had
he remained in the Wachau, drinking
good wine and enjoying the Danube sun.
English lords offered considerable sums
to the Emperor to obtain their king's
release.
The Zambezi
The quivering waters of the Zambezi
[river
Will bear on a silvery blanket your name
Leading it to the echoing of the sea.
Mazisi Kunene
Now, for the first time, the Danube
traverses open country. This is Moravia,
often a battle ground until Napoleonic
times. It was here, close to the Danube
and to Vienna, that the House of Austria
was born on a battlefield. It was also in
a castle near the Danube and Vienna that
Charles, the last Habsburg Emperor,
ended his days as Regent.
Vienna, the Vindobona of the
Romans, lay on the limes or fortified
frontier of the Roman Empire which
linked the Rhine and the Danube. The
limes separated Roman Europe from the
Europe of the Others, the "barbarians",
the peoples who finally struck deep into
the declining Empire, crossing the
Danube and driving their way to Byzan¬
tium, Constantinople, the golden city of
the Eastern Roman Empire. And to
Rome. Migrations of peoples have con¬
tinued into our own times, into the age of
the two world wars, which were initially
and essentially fratricidal European civil
wars.
Vienna does not lie on the blue Danube
of Johann Strauss. Here, the river is dark
and most often grey. It is much more at¬
tractive at Budapest, where it links the
two towns of Buda and Pest. Now it
becomes a t frontier between
Czechoslovakia, Austria, and Hungary,
between Yugoslavia and Romania, bet¬
ween Romania and the Soviet Union. It
becomes the great river of Eastern
Europe, enriched by many tributaries
the Tisza, the Sava, the Morava, the Jiu,
the Olt, the Dambovitsa, the Siret, the
Pruth and enters the Black Sea through
its delta, an island-studded aquatic
jungle.
As I look at the Danube from Vienna,
I see Soviet cargo ships sailing upstream
one after the other, many of which were
built at Linz or Klosterneuburg, near the
city. All of a sudden, there appears a
hovercraft coming from Budapest. It
provides the most rapid means of
transport between the two cities. Then
comes a cargo ship from Yugoslavia
from Belgrade, the "white city" that was
the scene of battles down the centuries,
against the Turks, the Hungarians, the
Germans, the Austrians, even during two
world wars.
Much blood has flowed down the
Danube, but today the river flows
peacefully through Western and Eastern
Europe, a link, a living bridge, between
the two fragments of our continent. As I
write these lines, tourists wave to me in
friendship from the deck of their ship
bound for the Black Sea.
Friedrich Heer
View of the Sulina channel, the only one of the three channels into which the Danube
splits at its delta that is navigable. Owing to the large quantity of silt deposited by the
River, the delta is extending seawards at a rate of some 30 metres annually.
18
Colour pages
Page 19
"The Mississippi is like that great ser¬
pent destroying the house of
Laocoón."
Throughout its lower reaches the
Mississippi meanders like a writhing
snake through a broad fertile valley,
leaving behind meander scars, cutoffs
and oxbow lakes and changing its
length by as much as 80 kilometres a
year.
Photo Fred Mayer © Magnum, Pans
Page 20 (top photo)
"The Nile is born in lands whose
memory rests only on tradition, and it
expires in a land whose memory is
monumental. "
From Aswan the Nile flows for some
800 kilometres through a valley cut
into a limestone plateau whose scarps
rise at times to a height of about 500
metres above river level.
Photo Ferier © ANA, Pans
Page 20 (bottom photo)
"Today the Danube flows peacefully
through Western and Eastern Europe,
a link, a living bridge, between the
two fragments of our continent. "
Exploitation of reeds in the Danube
delta. Reed stems have been
harvested for centuries for thatching
and construction purposes, for mak¬
ing arrows and pens and for pipes for
musical instruments.
Photo Cordier © Pitch, Pans
Page 21
"The Yangtze the right breast of our
motherhas nurtured with her milk
the fertile land that makes up more
than half the Chinese continent. "
Ploughing a paddy field in the valley of
the Yangtze near Chong Qing.
Photo © Schulthess, Switzerland
Page 22
"Mother, you who are born of
Vishnu's footstep, representing his
force and honoured by Him, protect
us, and wash the sins we commit
from birth to death."
Two Hindu sadhus (holy men)
meditate near the Gangotri waterfall a
few kilometres from Gomukh (the
"Cow's Mouth") where the Ganga
emerges from the Gangotri glacier.
Photo Raghubir Singh © ANA, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
4
.¿flP
*&£
' c-
>£.^V*»
%
hj**?
M,
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
1
^Mfe^ ^
l
0
-^^^^^^bB^^^^b
* *»*
t
-
*
4
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
GANGA
(Ganges)
2,506 km.
near Gangotri in the
Himalayas and empties into the
Bay of Bengal
discharge: 38,000 cubic
metres per second
of basin i
(Ganges/Brahmaputra): i
1,730,000 sq. km.
distributaries: the Hooghly
and the Meghna
delta of the Ganga covers an
area of some 57,000 sq. km.
The goddess
who came
down to earth
by Lokenath Bhattacharya
IT is to be acknowledged in all humility that writing about
Ganga, the Ganges as others call her, is an impossibility,
since much of the river exists more in the imagination of
the people who, verily, are her own
children, a repetition of the fallen
Vasus of the Mahabharata, than in
reality. A river is a she, in Sanskrit as
well as in French, and maybe in quite
a few other languages also. But
nowhere is a river she with such force
and presence as in the case of Ganga.
Ganga is the name of a
civilization in fact, many civiliza¬
tions. Epochs of history and
chronicles of cults and cultures lie
dormant in the layers of the soil wash¬
ed by the waters. Dreams and despair,
facts and fiction, creation and
devastation, all have been elements in
a process which has culminated in the
portrayal of her image. In the pan¬
theon of Hindu divinities, especially
as an object of popular worship, she
occupies a unique position. As the
scriptures describe it, her home is
among the stars, where the Path of
Vishnu lies, between Ursa Major and
the Pole Star. "Mother, you who are
born of Vishnu's footstep, repre¬
senting His force and honoured by
Him, protect us, and wash the sins we
commit from birth to death".
Like her elder spiritual sister
Sarasvati, the legendary river now lost
in the desert of time, Ganga too
becomes a "mother of the Vedas",
and is identified with the Word. She is
the pearl of poetry, "engaging herself in grammar, giving
pleasure to the ears".
And what hold she has on her devotees!
Three incidents come to my mind. I can't exactly recall if they
all happened during the same journey. But all were at Gangotri,
the real as well as legendary place not far from the first visible
source of the river of the ringing, singing name, the river that
is the mother, the goddess, the beloved, the flowing, scin¬
tillating life, the life-giving water, the waters of creation.
The first concerns a one-legged youth, ascetic-looking,
standing knee-deep in the icy water of the Bhagirathi, very near
the bend in front of the Gangotri temple. The month was Oc¬
tober, and the time about six o'clock in the morning. A frozen,
frost-bitten picture, not only because of thé shattering, ex¬
cruciating cold, but also because of a certain stillness and a
timelessness that surrounded the air. Yet the river was anything
but motionless, or soundless; its speed had its usual, perpetual
ferocity.
According to Hindu scriptures the Ganga (Gan¬
ges) the most holy river on earth, was created
when the goddess Ganga came down to earth
from heaven. In this 19th-century painting she
rides a saurian, holding a lotus and a pot of
Ganga water.
The man, though, was as immobile as a photograph. He was,
apparently, uttering his sun-prayer, maybe for fifteen or twenty
minutes which, to one or two scattered onlookers like us, seem¬
ed an eternity.
The greater surprise, however, still
awaited us, late in the evening, on the
same day. We saw him return to one
of the resting houses for the pilgrims
where he must have been staying and
were told that he was just back from
Gomukh, "the cow's mouth", known
to be the true source of Ganga, a
formidable-looking ice cave at an
altitude of over 4,000 metres and
twenty-three kilometres beyond the
town of Gangotri. That meant for him
forty-six kilometres going and com¬
ing, on a difficult, makeshift, moun¬
tain path which, at places as narrow
as sixty centimetres, must entirely
be trodden on foot. One-legged; forc¬
ed to use crutches, how could he
make it?
"Everything is possible when the
inspiration is Ganga-mayi (Mother
Ganga), a sannyasin [Hindu ascetic]
who has his cottage on the right bank
of the river flowing downwards at
Gangotri told us, referring to such ap¬
parently incredible events. The san¬
nyasin, who is the object of the second
incident I have in mind, was, as subse¬
quently we gathered from others,
originally a South Indian and had
once served as an engineer in a
government public works depart¬
ment. He had renounced the world, as he himself described, "to
pursue the course of Mother Ganga and realize her true form".
Moving for a considerable time from the plains towards the
source of the river he finally settled down near its icy origins
high in the Himalayas and now divides his twelve months of the
year between Gangotri and Gomukh.
My third incident also concerns a near cripple, a woman of
apparently modest means, about 80 years old, bent from the
waist like a right angle, because of her age, whom I found walk¬
ing, crawling almost, with her stick on the perilous path
somewhere midway between Gangotri and Gomukh, when I too
was alone on my way to Gomukh, my companions having
preceded me by perhaps a few hundred metres. The woman was
walking firmly though slowly, occasionally stopping for breath
and she was moving in the same direction as I was. Uttering the
habitual greeting "Ganga-mayi ki jai" (glory to Mother Ganga)
I tried to overtake her gently and carefully as the path was
uneven and narrow with a steep gorge oh the right pointing to
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
the Ganga which was flowing perhaps one hundred and fifty
metres below.
The river had a frozen look here and there with occasional
tracts of icy roof running to three hundred and fifty metres at
a stretch and covering the flow of the river which, beneath the
roof and before coming out in the open again, moved incessant¬
ly, singingly. The perpetual snowline was still a distance away
and we were in the region of scattered birch forests said to be
the favourite roaming ground for herds of musk-deer.
When I was about to overtake her, the woman suddenly turn¬
ed and asked me in her Hindi, "Son, is this the road to
Bhaironghat?". I told her that Bhaironghat lay in the opposite
direction and would mean for her four to five hours walk, that
the direction she was going would shortly take her to Chirbasa,
the last human habitation of two or three huts along the way,
before the path merged in the perpetual snow. With a touch of
despair in her eyes and voice which still rings in my ears, she
cried out, "Oh my God, what I have done? How am I going to
return now?" But she regained her composure immediately
after and, touching her forehead with folded hands, uttered,
"Ganga-mayi kijai. She has brought me here, she will take me
there".Then without a word more she turned and started to
walk in the opposite direction.
Few rivers anywhere in the world have been elevated to the
exalted position Ganga occupies in the vast hymn literature of
the Hindus. There is no rite or religious ceremony connected
with any important event of a Hindu's life be it birth, mar¬
riage or death which can be performed without use of her
water. She cleanses, purifies; sanctifies. When a Hindu, while
bathing, invokes the seven celestial streams from the solar orb
("Make your abode in this water, oh Ganga, oh Yamuna, oh
Godavari, oh Saravasti, oh Narmada, Sindhu, Kaveri"), he
gives preference to Ganga among all the other ones. Then he im¬
mediately proceeds to address her singly in a series of hymns
one of which says. "In heaven, firmament and earth, as teaches
us Vayu, the god of the wind, are thirty-five million holy places,
but all, mother, are comprised in you".
The legend which gives her the name of Tripathaga, "triple
flowing", meaning thereby that she runs in heaven, earth and
hell, and describes her descent to earth from heaven, has nar¬
rative details which explain well the awe the river inspires in the
visitors to her source region in the Himalayas. The prayers of
A flotilla of fishing boats at
Nimtita in West Bengal.
Photo Raghubir Singh © ANA, Pans
24
Near Sonepur, the con¬
fluence of the Ganga and
the Gandak, elephants are
bathed during a fair com¬
memorating a fight between
Gajendra (lord of elephants)
and a huge crocodile.
Elephants are associated
with rainfall and abundant
crops. In Hinduism the
elephant-headed god
Ganesh is a remover of
obstacles and a symbol of
prosperity.
Photo Raghubir Singh <c, ANA, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Hardwar, where the Ganga
leaves the mountains and
enters the plains, is one of
the chief places of
pilgrimage for Hindus in In¬
dia. Multitudes attend great
bathing ceremonies,
especially the Kumbh Mela
which is celebrated at Hard-
war every 12 years. Left,
throng of pilgrims gather to
bathe at the Har-ki-Pairi ghat
where the footprint of
Vishnu, who could cross the
7 regions of the Hindu
universe in 7 steps, is im¬
printed on a stone.
Photo Raghubir Singh © ANA, Pans
the saint Bhagiratha, it is said in the legend, brought Ganga
down from heaven to purify the remains of the sixty thousand
sons of King Sagara who had been reduced to ashes by the in¬
furiated glance of the sage Kapila. Ganga, angry at being
brought down, could only be controlled by Siva who saved the
earth from the shock of her fall by catching her on his brow and
then checking her course with his matted locks.
The vision of the fury of the river interlocked in the tortuous
lanes and by-lanes of Himalayan rocks near Gangotri, with the
colour of the water as red as blood at places, reminds one of the
hymn starting with bhayanam bhayam bhishanam
bhishananam and saying, "You are the dread of the dreadful,
the terror of the terrible, the refuge of all creatures, the purifier
of all purifiers. Superior even to the supreme protector of all
protectors, you alone rule the high-placed ones".
Depending on her moods and the circumstances, she can be
a soothing, gushing, singing or terrorizing beauty.
The descent of Ganga is an elaborate myth which all through
the ages has inspired Indian artists and sculptors with a peren¬
nially challenging theme. The most dramatic representation of
it is, of course, on the well-known granite rock at the deserted
seaport town of Mamallapuram near Madras.
Not only the Mother, in which form she is so generally wor¬
shipped, Ganga, at times, can also become a most desired
woman of ravishing beauty. How can we forget the lovely
maiden of blazing splendour she was to King Santanu in the
Mahabharata when he saw her for the first time, prompting him
to address her with these words: "Whoever you may be, of
human origin or a goddess, or a daughter of a demon, or
belonging to the race of the Gandharvas or Apsaras, or the
Yakshas or Nagas, oh you of slender waist and celestial beauty,
I want you to be my wife".
In actual fact, originating in the Himalayas and emptying in¬
to the Bay of Bengal, the river covers a distance of 2,506
kilometres, which, we are told, makes it the fifteenth largest
among Asian rivers and the world's thirty-ninth largest river.
The tract of territory it passes through is one of the most fertile
and densely populated in the world. It has also been the cradle
of Hindusthan and Hindu civilization.
At places, especially in the West Bengal region, the course of
the river is sluggish and is often described as dead or dying. And
despite the traditional purity attached to the quality of its water,
in most areas of the Gangetic plain it is an increasingly and
dangerously polluted river. Even the great Akbar, the Moghul
emperor, as recorded by the sixteenth-century chronicler Abul
Fazl.used to call the river "the source of life", because of its
"water of immortality" which, both at home and on his travels,
he was accustomed to drink. Alas, those days of the purity of
its water are long past. But how many times must humanity ask
itself the question: what is more real in life, the reality, or im¬
agination? In the case of Ganga at least, the answer to that
question is: imagination.
In conclusion, here is one last picture of a last act of life. My
grandfather, a pious brahmin and scholar, was dying at the age
of 76. I was then about eight or nine years old. The scene was
our native town some thirty kilometres north of Calcutta.
Ganga flows by the town where, during the daily high tide, she
is one and a half kilometres wide. Following the custom, my
grandfather who had been ailing for quite some time was
brought near the bank of the river three days before, in fearful
expectation that he might expire at any moment.
He was lodged in a large, bare room made specially for the
purpose and attached to one of the bathing ghats (temple). The
whole family, along with him, had shifted to the room not only
to nurse him and be with him in his last moments but, equally
importantly, to take him, when the situation so warranted, hur¬
riedly to the river just before he expired.
But the last moment did not come. There was even talk of
taking him back to our ancestral home. As he was still very
conscious, the prospect of having to die without the touch of
the flowing Ganga made him suffer all the more. Agony was
writ large on his face.
And then all of a sudden it happened. Holding precarious¬
ly the still living body of grandfather, my father and two
uncles rushed down the steps of the bathing ghat and reached
the river. Soon the lower part of the body lay immersed in
the water while its upper part, kept above the water, was held
by my father who was also putting drops of Ganga water into
grandfather's mouth with the faint utterance "Om Ganga,
Om Ganga, Om Ganga".
The time might have been a few minutes past sunset. The
skyline on the other shore, with the silhouette of a tall tem¬
ple, looked a battleground pink with the blood of slain
heroes.
"Om Ganga, Om Ganga, Om Ganga".
Then the agony changed into ecstasy and the light went out
for ever. The face of the dead man, though battered due to
long illness, spoke of a sudden peace and a serenity which
were not of this world. Yes, I can still vividly see it.
Lokenath Bhattacharya
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
MISSISSIPPI
3,779 km. (With
Missouri 5,985 km.)
at Lake Itasca in north-
central Minnesota and empties
into the Gulf of Mexico
discharge: 18,000 cubic
metres per second
of basin (Mississippi/
Missouri): 3,220,000 sq. km.
name Mississippi derives from
the Algonkian Indian words mist
= big and sipi = water
Typical cypress swamp land¬
scape in the lower Mississippi.
With its thick trunk and expos¬
ed roots, the bald cypress (Tax-
odium distichum) is the domi¬
nant tree species in the region.
Photo Fred Mayer *<-> Magnum, Pans
The stream
of American
consciousness
by John Seelye
I am one of a clear minority in Ame¬
rica, for I have travelled on the
Mississippi River by paddlewheel
steamboat, the only way to encounter
that greatest of American streams, if only
because it connects you to a remarkable
epoch in our history. The steamboat was
the Delta Queen, originally a Sacra¬
mento-River auto ferry (the dining deck
slopes upward to the centre, giving your
soup a rakish tilt) built in Scotland, but
the experience was still authentic.
The river was at flood, stage and the
boat made slow time upstream, yet all
time on the river is slow time. Schedules
have to be revised every day, always
backward. Leisure is enforced as the
scenery creeps by, what scenery there is,
which isn't much, not on the lower river.
Because of the levees, which elevate the
stream above the flood plain, there is
literally no shore line by which to gain
perspective, no visible habitation of men.
Relief is provided by sandbars with a
stubborn clump of willows or alders
clinging to them or by an occasional
towboat pushing a string of barges
(towboats on the Mississippi do not tow),
with perhaps a deckhand or two in
evidence, a precious sa mpling of humani¬
ty. The rest is river, a rumpled copper
26
sheet of muddy water, apparently mo¬
tionless at a distance, but hissing around
the hull as it sweeps to the sea, pulling
itself into hundreds of small whirlpools,
a vast field of force drawn down from the
huge interior.
On the map, the Mississippi assumes a
serpentine shape not immediately ob¬
vious to a passenger on the lower river.
Early in the nineteenth century, one mad
projector suggested that the meanders be
bisected the entire length of the river by
means of two canals, with the intention
of improving navigation and reducing
floods. The project was never under¬
taken, but Americans have continued to
impose the rule of the line on the river's
natural inclination towards a serpen¬
tine which is to say spiral course.
Levees and wingdams act toward the
same desired end, but such is the force of
the river that all engineering feats are
never more than compromises with
short-range effectiveness.
Right now, it is only by means of ar¬
tificial devices including a controversial
dam that the river is kept flowing past
New Orleans. Its natural tendency to
change course will eventually win out and
the great city will be left high and boggy.
The Mississippi is like that great serpent
destroying the house of Laocoön: the
river takes its meaning from the futile ef¬
forts of men to overcome it.
Draining the centre of a large conti¬
nent, drawing down water from both the
Allegheny and the Rocky Mountains, the
Mississippi puts forth a seductively sym¬
metrical even neo-classical shape, linear
in implication and inspiring to the im¬
perial sensibility. Ironically (and much
associated with the great river is
ironical), the man who is credited with
discovering the Mississippi, De Soto,
regarded it as a barrier to his westward
search for the fabled Indian cities of
gold.
It was La Salle, a century later, for
whom the Mississippi first assumed a
promising shape: Joined to the St.
Lawrence by a network of lakes and
lesser rivers, it would extend the French
empire in North America all the way to
the Gulf. It is difficult to read the story of
La Salle as told by Francis Parkman
without thinking of the story of Kurtz as
told by Conrad, for both stories are
about the madness that quest for empire
engenders.
Reading the story of La Salle, we are
brought back to a time when the
Mississippi was a truly savage stream, an
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
American Congo: T. S Eliot's great,
brown God. "Nous sommes tous
sauvages," that was the slogan La Salle
found scrawled across the hull of the
boat that was to have taken him down the
Mississippi from Fort Crèvecsur on the
Illinois River. It had been left by de¬
serting coureurs de bois, and contains a
truth that may have escaped La Salle,
who persisted in his attempt to wrest the
serpentine Mississippi into an imperial
shape. The explorer finally did descend
the great river, but on a return trip he was
set upon by his own men and killed.
has many famous streams
the Hudson, the Ohio, the Potomac, the
Susquehanna, among themmost of
which bear Indian names, but it is the
Mississippi that is most Indian in
character. As the earliest explorers
noted, the Mississippi changes its nature
at St. Louis, where it is joined by the
Missouri: "The calm is gone, the
grouped isles disappear, the shores are
jagged and rent, the hue of the water is
clayed, the before moderate current is
rapid and vexed." So wrote Herman
Melville of the difference, drawing upon
not only personal recollection but many
observers before him: "Like a Pawnee
from ambush" comes down the Missouri
from the west, and "under the benign
name Mississippi it is in short the
.Missouri that now rolls to the Gulf... the
Missouri that by open assault or artful
sap sweeps away fruit and field, grave¬
yard and barn." Even now the Mississip¬
pi below St. Louis is still a savage stream,
an American Congo barely contained by
man-made chains. And at the start there
were no chains, the river a force without
constraint.
The symmetrical location of the
Mississippi did not escape that neo¬
classical geopolitician, Thomas Jeffer¬
son, who saw the river as a vast waterway
by means of which the interior of North
America could be settled and exploited.
The negotiations with Napoleon that
resulted in the Louisiana Purchase were
first undertaken merely to obtain naviga¬
tion rights on the Mississippi. Having
bought the river and much of the ter¬
ritory west of it, Jefferson and his con¬
temporaries were presented with yet
another problem, for descending the
Mississippi was not easy and going up it
was nearly impossible.
Flatboats and rafts were the chief
means of down-river conveyance: clumsy
and hard to manoeuvre, they did not all
make it down to New Orleans but were
torn apart by snags or wrecked on hidden
sandbars. Some were attacked by Indians
or river pirates, white renegades who im¬
bibed lawlessness from the wild river.
The up-river voyage was made by
keelboats, graceless yet somehow heroic
craft that were propelled by a unique
kind of boatman of which Mike Fink is
the legendary type: scarcely distin¬
guishable from river pirates because mad
with the licence of the untamed frontier,
these semi-barbarians poled and pulled
their slow way upstream foot by foot,
cordelling with winch and rope when
poles would not work or sometimes haul¬
ing themselves along by grabbing at the
foliage on the bank.
Heroic, yes, but inefficient, and it
would be a later generation that
celebrated Mike Fink and his wild
brethren. Americans of the period of
Washington and Jefferson did not much
prize heroism in its wilder forms, nor
were they charmed by picturesque ineffi¬
ciency. A contemporary carving by
William Rush decorating the Fairmount
Waterworks outside Philadelphia show¬
ed two opposing allegorical figures:
"The Schuylkill Chained" (an old man
lying on rocks wrapped in iron links)
and, "The Schuylkill Freed" (a young
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
William Faulkner (1897-1962), the U.S.
writer who won the Nobel Prize for
Literature in 1949, spent almost all his
life in the State of Mississippi. He
transposed the deep south he knew into
the imaginary "Yoknapatawpha", the
setting of a fictional saga which opened
in 1929 with Sartoris and ended with his
last novel. The Reivers (1962).
Yoknapatawpha, a compound of two In¬
dian expressions, means "the country
where the water flows slowly through
flat lands". Right, Faulkner outside his
home at Oxford, Mississippi.
woman resembling Liberty seated by a
waterwheel). Rush meant to demonstrate
that a river you cannot use is in effect an
imprisoned stream: dam it, pipe it, put it
to work, and you free it.
Robert Fulton, who had earlier seen
canals as the answer to America's
transportation problems (and sub¬
marines and torpedoes as instruments of
world peace) found the solution to the
navigational challenge of the Mississippi
in the steamboat. An eccentric inventor
named John Fitch had actually put
together a working steamboat in the
1780s, but the time was not right and
Fitch.died ruined and half-crazy, killing
himself on the banks of the Ohio.
Robert Fulton was nothing if not a
man synchronized with his age, and
though his submarine and torpedo found
no buyers, his steamboat sailed straight
into the future that is now our history.
Everyone knows about the Clermont (ac¬
tually called The North River, as was the
Hudson in Fulton's day) and its epochal
voyage in 1 807 up the Hudson to Albany.
But not everyone knows that Fulton, like
John Fitch before him, realized that his
invention would be of greatest service on
the Mississippi. Within four years the
New Orleans had made its epical way
downstream against a spectacular
backdrop of earthquake and flood all the
way from Pittsburgh to the Gulf.
28
Shortly after the imperial plan of
western waterways was linked to the
Hudson River by the Erie Canal, De Toc-
queville visited the United States to check
on the progress . of democracy. He
discovered that progress if not
democracy had been considerably ac¬
celerated by steamboats, but he also
learned that these distinctly American
craft were hastily and often shoddily con¬
structed, because, as a riverman explain¬
ed to him, they seldom lasted more than
five years and were always being improv¬
ed upon in terms of design and speed.
Along with Franklin's lightning rod, the
steamboat was an American invention,
perhaps the American invention (before
the light bulb and motion picture for
surely Edison is the American inventor)
in that it was a product of human in¬
genuity spurred by commercial necessity,
one which prized speed over safety.
One of the most beautiful of all
mechanical inventions, the paddlewheel
steamboat is now regarded with a great
deal of nostalgia, but until it was displac¬
ed by the locomotive, the riverboat was
for the mid-nineteenth century American
the apogee of technological progress, and
was celebrated as such in famous
lithographs by Currier & Ives. The Hud¬
son's riverboats were also known for
their beauty, but the steamboats depicted
by lithographers were most always boats
on the Mississippi, usually seen racing by
moonlight, their furnaces glowing and
smokestacks showering the scene with
sparks.
The Great River had at last met its
match, yet the imagery of savagery per¬
sists, put forth by the demon god Steam,
as tricky a servant as ever conjured up by
man (before nuclear power), nor did the
River quietly surrender. As De Toc-
queville's informant noted, the life span
of a Mississippi steamboat was not long,
and what snags and sandbars did not ac¬
complish, exploding boilers effected with
much more dramatic force.
Most of the Currier & Ives prints were
published after the Civil War, even as the
Mississippi riverboat was being replaced
by the steam locomotive as a symbol of
modern transportation. As celebrations
they were already tinged with nostalgia,
as was Mark Twain's Life on the
Mississippi (1883), a book that like its
author is split down the middle, one half
a sentimental memorial to life as it was
on the river before the Civil War ("Old
Times"), the other a paean to the
triumphs of modern technology that had
made piloting no longer a necessarily
heroic act. If the Mississippi is the Trojan
Serpent then Mark Twain is Old Man
Laocoön in our national iconography,
thoroughly wrapped up (as he might have
observed) in his subject, Snake and Man
virtually indistinguishable River and
River God.
Until Mark Twain's appearance upon
the literary scene rivers were not impor¬
tant to American fiction despite their
primacy in American life, but were most¬
ly seen flashing through foliage or
floating a Cooper Indian in a Cooper
canoe. Mark Twain is our premier river
writer as the Mississippi is our para¬
mount stream, and of the many books he
wrote we remember him best for those
through which the Mississippi moves. We
remember him best of all for one book,
through which the great river moves with
all the rights and privileges of a major
(though it is literally a supporting)
character: take away The Adventures of
Huckleberry Finn and you remove not
the cornerstone but the keystone to Mark
Twain's The rest simply will not
stand alone. Next to Old Man Laocoön
writhe his two sons, men in appearance
but boys in stature: call them Tom
Sawyer and Huck Finn, for if Mark
Twain is a boy man surely his greatest
creations, his Gemini, are children in size
only impossible kids.
Mark Twain, his boys, the serpentine
River, combine to put forth a mystical
CONTINUED PAGE 38
Trumpeter, singer, band leader and composer, Louis Armstrong
( 1 900-197 1 ) is one of the greatest names in the history of jazz.
He was born at New Orleans, the capital of Louisiana, on the
left bank of the Mississippi, the longest river in the United
States, initially playing on the riverboats before travelling on to
Chicago and New York.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
NILE
6,670 km.
in Burundi as the Kagera
River and empties into the
Mediterranean Sea
discharge: 3,fJ00 cubic
metres per second
of basin: 2,870,000 sq. km.
White Nile (800 km.) is the
largest tributary of the Nile
Nasser, the reservoir form¬
ed upstream from the Aswan
High Dam (completed in 1971) is
the largest man-made lake in the
world
The Blue Nile scores a deep
gorge through the high
plateau of Ethiopia where it
has its source. Air view,
right, shows bridge on the
road from Addis Abeba to
Asmara.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Pans
Uncommon
heritage
by Lotfallah Soliman
IT is not by chance that, in order to
ensure their supremacy, the Great
Powers are engaged simultaneous¬
ly in an arms race and a memory race.
Victory will no longer go only to the
power who possesses the most
sophisticated weapons, but also to the
one which will provide itself with the
most extensive memory. Memory as an
instrument of power is a fairly recent
discovery, but it has long been known
that memory generates the will to power.
The Nile is born in lands whose
memory rests only on tradition, and it ex-
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
pires in a land whose memory is
monumental. No more was needed for
Egypt to claim mastery of the Nile, in¬
deed to become the Nile. But it was not
entirely her fault. All the great kings of
Egypt, from Ramses to Mohammed Ali,
tried to pass the barrier of the upper
cataract, but the force of the current
always drove them back from Africa to
the sea.
It was only in the second half of the
nineteenth century that the region of the
great lakes was finally discovered, and it
was not until the 1930s that all the
sources of the Nile were identified.
Meanwhile, there was nothing for it but
to live with the Egyptian memory and the
myths it created, and admit that the only
The Euphrates
In dream I saw the Euphrates
Winding its somnolent way, .
Splash of water-rat, wide-curving
[mud-flats
Spangled with arborescent spider's webs
Eugenio Móntale
Nile without a descriptive name is that
which flows from the sixth cataract,
north of Khartoum and Omdurman, but
counting against the current. Further
upstream, the Nile is given an adjective:
the White Nile, the Blue Nile, the Nile of
the Mountains, the Nile of the Gazelles,
the Nile of the Giraffes. The Nile is the
only great river in the world the descrip¬
tion of whose course starts with the
mouth and whose cataracts are
numbered from downstream upstream,
as if to show that, although the flower
and the ear of corn may well be at the tip
of the stem, they are nonetheless the final
ends of all existence.
The Nile is also the only great river to
flow from South to North. Having
entered Asia in pursuit of the Hyksos,
Thutmose I, founder of the New Empire,
halted at Carchemish (now Jerablus). He
had just reached the utmost limits of the
logical world. Was he not confronted
with a river the Euphrates on which
he would have to row against the current
in order to go northwards? He was con¬
tent to cross it, to erect a stele in memory
of his crossing and to turn back, not
forgetting to baptize the river "the sea
whose water flows in reverse".
From earliest antiquity until as recent¬
ly as the late Middle Ages, it was impossi-
Pigeons watch from their
monumental dovecote
"pyramid" in the Nile Valley as
the caravan passes'.*' Perhaps
the first type of bird tamed by
man, the domestic pigeon has
been an important source of
food in Egypt since ancient
times.
ble for any Egyptian, whether he be king,
priest, warrior, geographer, scribe,
craftsman or simple peasant, to imagine
that it was his world that was different.
The Cosmos, like the Nile, could only be
Egyptian.
For centuries, at every summer solstice
the Pharaoh himself, surrounded by the
high dignitaries of his kingdom, would
proceed in state to the river to cast therein
a rolled papyrus. The papyrus contained,
not an offering, but an order to the river
to rise. Did this symbolize the inability of
the priests and wise men of that time to
explain the phenomenon of a river in
spate, a spate regularly repeated and eter¬
nally renewable? No doubt, but it also
symbolized the man-god's will to reign
sovereign over the god Nile.
This symbolism summarizes to perfec¬
tion the sometimes ambiguous relation¬
ship which existed for centuries until
modern times between the men of the
"Nile without an adjective" and the river
that emerges from nothing. "Egypt is a
gift of the Nile". That may have been
true for Herodotus and those coming
after him who would think it clever to
quote him, but not for the Egyptians
whom he stripped of their sovereignty. If
the aphorism were true, if they were no
more than the recipients of a gift, albeit
the tears of Isis, the sister and spouse of
Osiris and the mother of Horus, by what
right could Egypt and the Egyptians
assert their will to power and immortali¬
ty? Since the gods are mortal, only man
bears eternity within him and it is for him
and him alone to command and for the
gods to bow to his will. Between the order
to rise issued by a Pharaoh to the god
Nile, and the Great Dam which tames
this god, there is a continuity which con¬
fers legitimacy on both Menés and Nasser
and makes twenty centuries of foreign
domination a passing incident. "Eternity
is Egyptian", said André Malraux.
This "Egyptianization" of the Nile
was not devoid of excess bordering on
racism before its time. All the great kings
of Egypt dreamed of conquering the
lands of the Upper Nile and even
Abyssinia. But the stele of Semna, which
dates from four thousand years ago,
from the Xllth dynasty, forbade "for
ever" the "negroes" to pass through Heh
when going down to Thebes. And when a
king from the Upper Nile, whose civiliza¬
tion and principal god Amon were, after
all, borrowed from Egypt, tried to set
The Saint Lawrence
Oh childhood that five-leafed hand
Stretched athwart my country
I will run up again on the wave of your
¡wrist
The dim towns watching over cradles
and already your face whole as a sea.
Gatien Lapointe
himself up at Thebes, the riposte was to
be terrible.
Nevertheless, the silt carried by the
Nile is "negro", and' all Egyptian or
rather Nilotic mythology was to bear
the mark of this négritude. The first idol
of the Egyptians has a woman's head on
the body of a hippopotamus. The judge
of the dead is both lion and crocodile. No
other religion has animalized heaven to
the same degree, and the entire bestiary
of the Egyptian pantheon is of equatorial ,
origin. In the absence of written records,
one can only state that the recently
discovered Upper Nile and the Lower
Nile whose history is older, certainly liv¬
ed under the same religion. It is in the
30
Photo Silvester © Rapho, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Cairo Museum that one can see the
African gods Hathor and Apis in statue
form.
Presumptuous or not, Egypt, already
the memory of the Nile, has become the
Nile, and none outside her is the Nile,
and wherever she is involved the Nile
must be present. Some years ago, when
there was no longer any mystery about its
source or the mechanism of its floods, a
Tunisian friend was asked by the taxi-
driver who picked him up at Cairo air¬
port whether they had the Nile in Tunisia.
In the popular mind, identifications had
become superimposed to such a degree
as to be merged into each other. My
friend spoke Arabic. Tunisia was
therefore an Arab country; and since the
Nile, already an Egyptian river, had
become an Arab river, there could no
longer be an Arab country without the
Nile! But the illusion was not new.
Already in the eleventh century the Arab
geographer Al-Idrisi had drawn a map
showing a branch of the Nile that flowed
into the Atlantic after crossing the whole
of North Africa.
Starting from this consciousness, both
mythical and overweening, Egypt saw
herself as the principal, if not the only
regulator of the Nile. She was to reject
every proposal to raise the levels of the
African lakes preferring the creation of a
huge artificial lake between the first and
second cataracts, that is to say, mainly on
her own territory.
The Egypt of the myths died with the
construction of the Great Dam. For the
first time in their history, the Egyptians
are alone, without gods and with no pro¬
spect of miracles. At last! So much the
worse! It is for men to forge their own
destiny.
Lotfallah Soliman
Almost all the population of Egypt is concentrated in villages, towns
and cities on a narrow ribbon of land bordering the Nile. Above, air
view of central Cairo looking downstream shows the islands of Ar
Rawdah (foreground) and az-Zamalik. With a population of over 6
million Cairo is Africa's largest city.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
VOLGA
3,350 km.
in the Valdai Hills north¬
west of Moscow and empties into
the Caspian Sea
discharge: 8,000 cubic
metres per second
of basin: 1,360,000 sq. km.
Volga and its more than 70
tributaries carry two-thirds of all
Soviet inland freight
ancient times the Volga was
known as the Ra
'MATUSHKA
by Leonid Likhodeev
Right, bridge over the Volga
at Ulyanovsk (formerly Sim¬
birsk). A large industrial cen¬
tre at the confluence of the
Volga and the Sviyaga, the
city was re-named in honour
of its most famous native
son, Vladimir llyich Ulyanov
(Lenin).
Photo Zeyons © Rapho, Paris
EVERY river starts at a source, but not every source gives
birth to a great river. There are few mysteries in this
, world more fascinating than the mystery of birth, of
that enchanting moment when nothingness gives place to life.
So it is with the birth of a river from a bubbling spring. If the
Russians call springs "keys", it is because they open on to
highways.
This frozen little spring emerges from the earth in the Valdai
forests. It babbles amongst the dead leaves that serve as its
swaddling clothes, and branches bend protectively over its
cradle. Slowly but surely the little stream forces its way out of
the brushwood. Here a great highway, 3,690 kilometres long,
emerges from the depths of the centuries; here begins a mighty
river the Volga.
Winding its way through field and meadow, it borrows the
colours of their wild spring flowers and draws sustenance from
the living force of its tributaries. Grown to full maturity, it car¬
ries other rivers along with it, ever fuller, ever broader, impa¬
tient to reach the sea. It is the most celebrated river in Russia.
In the dark night of pagan times, man attributed souls to
32
rivers, creating them in his own image and likeness. Rivers were
wise men, rivers were muses, rivers were warriors, knights,
tillers of the soil. But the Volga has always been Matushka, a
mother gentle yet severe, fearsome in anger yet tender in com¬
passion. She has always been a mother because she teaches what
is good. She rewards the brave and consoles the weak, and her
heart is always with those who set forth to seek their fortune.
We Russians become acquainted with the Volga so early in
life that when we reach adulthood we are surprised to find we
have known her so long. From our earliest years her songs have
rocked us to sleep. Her songs are sad because those who in¬
vented them were sons of toil who hauled behind them the
endless chain of daily labour. But there are other songs in which
freedom unfolds its wings. No other river in the world has
become so closely identified with valour and the spirit of un¬
trammelled freedom.
Rivers have memories, and the Volga's memory is vast and
deep. She remembers the thud of the axe as the first isbas (log
huts) were built, and the soft slap of mortar trowelled on to
brick. She remembers the exploits of Yaroslav the Wise and the
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
odd behaviour of his ineffectual successors. She remembers the
ferocious hordes of Batu Khan, the grandson of Chingiz Khan,
and the avenging sword of Dmitry Donskoy. She remembers the
noble appeals of a citizen of Novgorod, Kuzma Minin of the
withered arm, and the daring raids of the Cossack rebel Stenka
Razin. She remembers the Volga boatmen, their route marked
by the rough-hewn crosses on their countless graves along her
banks. She remembers too the battle that decided the destiny of
our peoples.
The Tiber
Those graceful groves that shade the plain,
Where Tiber rolls majestic to the main,
And flattens, as he runs, the fair campagne.
Ovid
The battle took place here, on the banks of the Volga whose
waters now break against the granite quays of a new city, risen
from the ashes of Stalingrad. The Volga was both an obstacle
and a way forward, frontier and defence. Her waters ablaze
with oil, she seethed and foamed in anger, and wept real tears
for her children. Today's children cannot imagine what it was
like, and heaven forbid that they should ever see such combats.
The powerful river pursues her ancient course through new
"seas", the large reservoirs that form the majestic "Volga
Stairway". For a long time there existed on the Volga a short
cut via the "Samara Bend". This involved travelling
downstream as far as Perevelok, where boats were transported
overland on rollers to the River Ussa, by following whose
course the boats could rejoin the Volga. This itinerary was call¬
ed "the Zhiguli Roundabout". It was already in use by brigands
who lay in wait in the Zhiguli foothills for the rich merchants'
caravans. Nowadays the Ussa flows directly into the Sea of
Kuybyshev and tourists and yachtsmen sail its waters. This once
romantic stretch of the Volga has become the river's most in¬
dustrialized area. Three sister towns have grown up on the
banks of the Sea of KuybyshevTogliatti, Komsomolosk and
Zhigulevsk three towns built by young men who remember, as
if it were yesterday, the day work began on their construction.
In former times, the Volga towns were so distributed that
those with masculine names lay on the right bank and those with
feminine names on the left. On the right lay Yaroslav, Nijni
Novgorod (now Gorky), Saratov, Simbirsk (now Ulyanovsk).
On the left were Kostroma, Kazan, Samara (now Kuybyshev)
and Astrakhan. Few Russian towns suffered so much under
Engineers at work in the generator room of the V.l. Lenin
hydroelectric power station are dwarfed by the plant's massive
generators which have a capacity of over two million kilowatts.
Situated at the "Samara Bend", the V.l. Lenin power station
produces about a quarter of the more than forty thousand
million kilowatt hours of energy supplied each year to the
Soviet national grid by hydroelectric installations on the Volga.
enemy attack and few were so seriously damaged. Nevertheless,
although history has dealt harshly with them, these towns have
preserved many unique examples of ancient Russian
architecture.
In these works of architectural art men reproduced the
features of their natural surroundings pyramid roofs that
echoed the pointed silhouette of the fir tree, tracery that recall¬
ed the shadows cast by the birch and decorated with birds and
flowers the setting of their daily lives. It is not by chance that
the popular art of the craftsman was born in the most beautiful
regions of the Volga, and that the objects which emerged from
the hands of these craftsmen bear witness to the extraordinary
charm of this area.
The waters of the Volga now majestically past mountain and
forest, field and meadow, between banks that recall men dear
to our hearts. It was here on the Volga, in former Simbirsk, that
Vladimir Ilyich Lenin was born. From the Volga came many
The right bank of the Volga, just below Kuybyshev.
Photos Eugene Kassin and Marc Redkm © Progress Publishers, Moscow
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Russian writers, musicians and savants whose names are known
the world over, as well as people of every kind, rich men poor
of spirit, and poor men with generous hearts. The petty
bourgeoisie is full of ignominy and tramples on human dignity.
But sometimes great men emerge from its murky depths to de¬
nounce them without pity.
Such a one was the great Soviet writer Maksim Gorky. He
came from a modest home in Post Office Street at Nijni
Novgorod, and he has made it immortal. He travelled the Volga
as a workman wanders down the high street, but he travelled as
a philosopher who searches for the meaning of life. The Volga
was his cross, his joy, his university, the school which places the
pen at the service of the conscience.
Time broods over the Volga, and#tirelessly the Volga pursues
her seaward course. The Akh'tuba, the Volga's main
distributary, makes a sharp bend towards the east and
The Seine
O shepherd Eiffel Tower, your flock of bridges bleats this
[morning
Guillaume Apollinaire
thousands of tributaries, canals and deviations fan out into the
steppes. Peaceful landing stages punctuate the river banks.
Camel caravans cross the sands beside the Caspian and an
odour of wormwood comes from the pastures in the endless
steppes. Everything here depends on the Volga, the hopes of
those who till the soil and raise the cattle. Her waters nourish
the splendid grain, ripened by the sun, that flows in golden
showers into the holds of her barges, alongside the brilliant
white salt from the Basunchak mines: it is with the bread and
salt of welcome that the Volga receives her guests.
Between the Volga and the Akhtuba lie green flood lands, as
unexpected here as an oasis in the desert. This land is fertile and
rich in harvests. If you look at this region and the Volga delta
on the map, you will see that the contours are those of the legen¬
dary horn of plenty turned, as it were, towards the Caspian. To
reach the sea you must descend the river beyond Astrakhan,
passing the island where the flags of the fish factories flap in the
wind, the fishing-grounds and the dense jungle which occupies
the lower part of the nature reserve formed by the delta.
The Astrakhan reserve is a scientific centre of world-wide im¬
portance for ornithological studies. Everything there looks
rather strange, like the illustrations in school books depicting a
universe long since disappeared. Saiga antelopes bound across
the salty expanses, hundreds of varieties of water-birds flap
their wings amongst the reeds, white and black swans sail by,
proudly stretching their necks, brightly-coloured pheasants
hide in the thickets, white herons pick their way on telescopic
legs, and pelicans who have survived from the depths of
geological antiquity make their nests on enormous rafts that
they themselves have assembled from reed and sedge stalks and
willow branches. Seen from afar, their nests look like strange
flowers with motionless white and rose-coloured petals.
In June, when dawn breaks above the tall reeds, the cool
nelumbo lotus unfolds its petals on the motionless surface of a
tranquil cove. The morning breeze gently rocks the pink and
purple flowers above dull green leaves. The Volga delta is the
most northerly point where this legendary flower can be found.
Here, nature's peace is never broken by the noise of engines; on¬
ly the occasional dip of an oar betrays the presence of a man
hidden away with his microscope and test-tube. The law of the
reserve is'never to disturb nature.
Seen from the air, the Volga delta looks like a blue-veined
hand deformed by toil. To be sure that it really does flow into
the Caspian, you only have to look at the map.
Still, it is better to follow the river, to emerge on. the vast ex¬
panse of the Caspian, once known as the Sea of Khvalynsk, and
see that the entire route is a hive of activity, as far as the eye can
see and beyond. Here at its mouth, just when she joins the sea,
it is as if the Volga is musing on the Titanic tasks accomplished.
On her way to the sea she has turned hundreds of turbines,
transported hundeds of thousands of craft of every sort, carried
thousands of tons of goods. She has watered fields and bathed
meadows, and has united the far-off waters of the Baltic with
those of the Mediterranean and the Atlantic.
Leonid Likhodeev
& v
"Jwâfll mlyf^^^^j^^^^
¡S'fJI
5^^
c?
MM
p^^- StAT**
..¡>* -
'
-- ^ . "ri \^99B^I
^
The birthplace of Europe's greatest river. The building in the
background marks the spot at which the Volga first springs
from the earth in the Valdai Hills northwest of Moscow, near
the village of Volgo-Verkhovye.
Photos Eugene Kassin and Marc Redkln Progress Publishers, Moscow
Navigable over the greater part of its length, the Volga and its
tributaries form a vital commercial network carrying some two-
thirds of all Soviet inland freight, with timber accounting for 25
per cent of the total. Above, a member of the crew of the Volga
riverboat "Spartak ".
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
YANGTZE
5,520 km.
in the Tanggula Mountains
in the Tibetan Highlands and
empties into the East China Sea
Mean discharge: 34,000 cubic
metres per second
Area of basin: 1,800,000 sq. km.
river's generally accepted
name in China is Chang Jiang
The great river
flows east
by Bai Hua
With a population of 10 million, Shanghai is China's commercial metropolis and one of the world's biggest seaports. Above, view
over the Su Chou river near the point where it meets the Huang-pu-Chiang, a tributary of the Yangtze.
/ live at the head
Of the Yangtze River,
You at its mouth
Far, far away.
I long to see you, but this cannot be
Though I miss you every day.
And every day we drink
Both from the same river.
THIS poem, written in the elev¬
enth century by a Chinese
poet called Li Zhiyi, brings
back to me many a childhood dream
full of tender feelings. I read it first
before I was six years old, and since
then the Yangtze, the Chang Jiang
(Long River) as the Chinese call it, has
flowed like a poem through my heart.
In my child's imagination the
Yangtze was like an embroidered silk
ribbon meandering between dark green
mountains. At the head of the river, so
the poem goes, lives a beautiful girl and
at its mouth a handsome young man.
Day and night each yearns for but can¬
not see the other, though they always
fetch water from the same river.
The Yangtze flows on towards the
east, carrying with it the girl's pas¬
sionate longings. In the ripples of the
river her lover can see the girl's slim
shadow, and in the splash of its waters
hear her gentle whispers. How did they
get to know each other? And why are
they now separated? Was there no
small boat that could bring them
together? These questions kept nagging
away at me, the puzzle of my childhood
and adolescent dreams.
In the summer of 1938, when I was
eight, my family moved to Wuhan, a ci¬
ty at the confluence of the Han Jiang
and the Yangtze which was formed
from the merger of three once separate
towns. Not until then did I see the great
river for the first time. She was longer
and wider then I had expected, with
many steamboats, junks and tiny I
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
fishing boats which, I feared, might be
swallowed up in her terrifying waves.
I became more worried about the
lovers of the poem, for the people
aboard the steamboat were so
ferocious that I felt sure that they
would refuse them a place aboard.
Alas, perhaps they would never meet
again!
What made things worse that sum¬
mer was the situation in Wuhan, where
agitation was spreading like wildfire.
At that time the iron heel of the invader
was trampling the Central Plains and
fierce aerial combats were going on
night and day over Wuhan. The patriot
composer Xian Xinghai was rousing
the people to fever pitch with his songs
of national salvation.
Thousands took to the streets and
built huge floating stages on the
Yangtze by mooring boats together.
There everyone was a singer and all had
tears in their eyes. Gradually the
seething crowds and the turbulent river
. merged into one torrent in my young
heart.
Almost half a century has passed
since then, but today I can still hear the
singing of the crowds feverish singing
that sounds like the raging waves and
raging waves that sound like feverish
singing. The memory always brings me
new strength; but it also raises another
question: in the long river of human
history, what role should one play? The
Yangtze River is no longer the em¬
broidered silk ribbon of my tender
childish dreams, but the symbol of a
great nation that has experienced
numerous sufferings and catastrophes.
Since the early 1950s, I have travelled
several times on horseback along the
Jinsha River, a stretch of the upper
reaches of the Yangtze. I have seen with
my own eyes the great length of the
river as well as the twists and bends and
powerful resistance she faces on her
course. Above all, I have witnessed the
river's great strength and bravery.
The Yangtze rises among the glaciers
of the Geladandong, the main peak of
the Tanggula Mountains in west China.
Here it is known as the Toutou River,
which can be thought of as the
Yangtze's infant name. Over the next
stretch it is called the Tongtian River,
and further on it becomes the Jinsha
River which rushes down the Qinghai-
Tibet plateau into Yunnan Province.
The Guadalquivir
O Guadalquivir!
At Cazorla your cradle,
At Sanlúcar your bier.
You were a bubbling of spring water
Under a green pine 's shade;
How fine your song, how full of
[laughter.
Brackish as you near the sea
Do your muddy waters,
Like me, dream of their beginnings?
Antonio Machado
Along the east side of the snow-clad
Baima Mountain (White Horse Moun¬
tain) the Jinsha rolls through a rocky,
barren canyon, the Ghost Canyon as
the local Tibetans call it. Of course, the
real creator of the canyon is not a ghost
but the mighty roaring torrent.
From Shigu (Stone Drum), a small
town in Yunnan, the Jinsha enters the
deep gorges of the Hengduan Moun
tains, and there the river is abruptly
forced to veer north-east, forming an
oddly-shaped loop known as the "First
Bend of the Yangtze River". After this
sharp turn the river has once again to
churn its way through a narrow,
sixteen-kilometre-long valley between
perpendicular cliffs and snowy moun¬
tains. This valley is called "Tiger's
Leap Canyon" and is less than thirty
metres wide at its narrowest point.
Legend has it that a fierce tiger can leap
across the canyon here.
The river flow here is fast and
furious and keeps up a constant rumble
like thunder. Every time I lead a horse
fearfully climbing the cliffs of Tiger's
Leap Canyon to the sound of its
deafening torrents I become lost in a
long reverie. I think this must be reac¬
tion to an obstacle, submission to a set¬
back that cannot be avoided. For the
strong, however, a setback is simply an
opportunity for self-assessment and for
building up strength for the next
advance.
Having backtracked northwards for
nearly a hundred kilometres, the Jinsha
abruptly forces its way south again for
more than two hundred kilometres
before it resumes its course towards the
east.
An ancient story of the local Naxi
people says that the Jinsha is the most
beautiful of the three sister rivers, the
Jinsha, the Nujiang and the Lancang,
that flow in the region of the Hengduan
Mountains. There a rude, unreasonable
and overbearing prince, the snow¬
capped Yulong (Jade Dragon) moun¬
tain, intends to stop the Jinsha from
passing through. But when Yulong is
asleep, the beautiful girl sneaks round
him and runs away laughing softly.
Not far from the city of Su-Zhou (Soochow), which Europeans
named "the Venice of China" because of its interlacing canals
and streets, a woman and her two daughters haul their boat
along the Grand Canal.
The Yangtze River near Wu-han, capital
of Hupeh province. The famous bridge,
built between 1955 and 1957, is 1,670
metres long.
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
It is no wonder that kind-hearted
people always try to imagine bright and
happy endings to alleviate the hard¬
ships of some of life's gloomy
experiences.
In the early 1950s, I once saw some
slaves in chains labouring on the moun¬
tain slopes at the place where the Jinsha
river turns south. At that time, people
of the Yi minority in the Xaioliang
Mountains were still living in a typical
slave society.
Even now, on the east bank of the
Jinsha and around Lake Lugu, about
ten thousand Mosuo people still
tenaciously maintain ancient, idyllic
forms of matrilinear society and ahshu
(friend) marriage, now rarely seen in
other parts of the world. What really
links a woman and a man is neither
worldly goods nor their own children,
but pure love. Both the elderly and the
children in a matrilinear society are
looked after by other members of their
family. Despite the fact that there are
usually quite a number of people in one
family, they all manage to live in
harmony.
The Magdalena
On the hard Magdalena,
long project of sea,
isles offeather and sand
crow in the sunlight (...)
Green-black and green-green,
the elastic, tense forest,
snakes and wanders in a dream,
moves and reflects
(...)
Ports with dark open arms
children with swollen bellies
and watchful eyes.
Hunger. Oil, cattle...
Nicolás Guillen
As we follow the course of the long,
long river we can see the heavy foot¬
prints in time of the Chinese people's
painful, slow advance.
When the river enters Sichuan Pro¬
vince, it becomes navigable. But even
today boatmen can still be seen hauling
boats up the river, as described in a
poem by Li Bai (Li Po), a great poet of
the Tang Dynasty:
"Struggling exhausted against
[contrary winds".
Those stone slabs lining the river,
once coarse and rugged, were polished
smooth by our forefathers' bare feet.
Although we are now able to make jet
planes, rockets, ships and tractors, we
still cannot afford to replace those
sweating boatmen or to abandon the
wooden hoes or the yoked-oxen plough
used by our ancestors before the Chris¬
tian era to cultivate vast farmlands.
The Yangtze the right breast of our
mother has nurtured with her milk
the fertile land that makes up more
than half the Chinese continent. From
time immemorial, many sages have
drunk of that sweet milk. Some two
thousand years ago, the poet Qu Yuan
walked the shores of a lake adjoining
the Yangtze while composing his
glorious poems; Li Bai and Du Fu,
great poets of the Tang Dynasty
(618-907 AD), each in turn wandered
along the river bank like lone gulls, giv¬
ing vent to their sorrows in chanting
and weeping. Li Bai finally fell into the
river when trying to catch the shadow
of the moon in its deep waters. Oh what
a beautiful, sad tomb he found for
himself!
The river sings her way through the
Three Gorges, and then an extensive
plain unfolds ahead. Here, suddenly,
the Yangtze calms down and her waters
flow quietly. The river grows wider,
stronger and more confident. She is
musing on the long course she has
taken, a course full of twists and
frustrations. She recalls how she has
built up her strength, absorbing waters
from hundreds of streams and rivers.
Now she flows steadily, mightily to the
sea, to the outside world, carrying with
her melted snow from the glaciers,
flowers from the grasslands on the
banks of the Tongtian River, golden
sand from the Jinsha River, beads of
sweat from the faces of the heaving
boatmen, the moonlight on Lake
Tongding, the lights of the fishing
boats on Lake Panyang and the
fragrance of rice from the Jianghan
Plain.
The bright blue East China Sea
warmly embraces the outflowing river,
swirling down and down. In the end,
the Yangtze becomes merged in the sea,
losing her individuality. No, she has
just changed. No, she has found
herself. No, no, she has fulfilled
herself. Now she is no longer the
Yangtze, but part of the sea which links
all the great rivers that have nurtured
the nations of the world: the Mississip¬
pi, the Amazon, the' Congo, the Nile,
the Danube, the Volga, the Ganges.
This is why I look upon my worries
and moments of depression as hap¬
piness. I am truly proud to "drink from
the same river", all my life, as millions
of my fellow countrymen.
The great river flows towards the
east, towards the sea. Every morning,
the wave there pushes the red, red sun
out of the surface of the bright blue sea.
Bai Hua
Photos (n Schulthess, Switzerland
The town of Fu Ling (population 40,000) stands on the confluence of the Yangtze and
the Wu Chiang. These great rivers are major trade routes for such regional products as
cereals, tung oil, lacquer and citrus fruits.
r
Â^ Or i
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 28
union, a quaternity, the parts of which
are inseparable, caught up in what is less
a struggle than a synergesis. If the
Mississippi is natural power, a great
moving field of force, then Mark Twain's
Huckleberry Finn borrows a certain
energy from the river that runs through
it, for the river seems to have inspired in
the author an imaginative leap difficult
to match in our literature. It released
something in Mark Twain, something
called Huck Finn, an American version
of Wordsworth's Child of Nature, dirty,
smart-mouthed, ignorant, amoral, yet
clearly a blessed Innocent, whose sense of
freedom is invariably linked to the on-
moving River even though it is moving
in the wrong direction.
The explorer Henry Schoolcraft
discovered the ultimate source of the
Mississippi, a lake which the Indians call¬
ed "Elk" but which Schoolcraft named
"Itasca" (Verjitas Cajput), which he
later claimed was an Indian word for a
woman's breast, the very same
Schoolcraft whose Algic Researches gave
Henry Longfellow the Indian legends
which he warped into the weft of
Hiawatha. But in terms of our literature,
the true source of Mark Twain's
Mississippi in Huckleberry Finn is Henry
David Thoreau's Waiden Pond, much as
Huck's raft is Henry's cabin
reconstituted.
Thoreau spent the last decade of his
life pursuing the secret of the American
wilderness, personified for him as the In¬
dian, and though Mark Twain was con¬
temptuous of noble savagery as put forth
in Cooper's novels, his Huck Finn has a
lot more red man in him than does
Longfellow's Sunday-schoolcrafty Hia¬
watha. He is the spirit of American rivers
incarnate, happiest when free-flowing,
wary of civilization and its constraints,
and dedicated to helping his chain-laden
friend Jim escape society in its most
restraining form. These two are perhaps
our most famous pair, like the lovers on
Keats's urn, forever fleeing, forever pur¬
sued, yet somehow, paradoxically, sym¬
bolic of the personal freedom we all seek,
floating forever downstream over the
uneasy bones of De Soto, carried by the
river past the sunken wreckage of a thou¬
sand steamboats as it reflects the light of
a million untriangulated stars.
John Seelye
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Authors
BAI HUA, of China, is a poet,
playwright, film scenarist and novelist.
His published books include An Ancient
Navigational Rout and The Death of a
Fisherman.
THIAGO DE MELLO, of Brazil,
comes from Manaus, the capital of
A mozonas Slate, which is situated at the
confluence of the Amazon and the Rio
Negro. Considered to be one of Brazil's
greatest poets, his works include Silen¬
cio e Palavra (Silence and Words), Ven¬
to Geral (General Wind) and A Cançao
do Amor Armado (Song of Armed
Love).
LOKENATH BHATTACHARYA, of
India, is Director of the National Book
Trust at New Delhi. He comes from
Bhatpara, a small town in west Bengal
on the banks of the Ganges. He is the
author of several works including The
Prose Poems of Lokenath Bhattacharya
(1972) and The Drum of the Guru
(1979).
JOHN SEELYE, of the USA, is Alumni
Distinguished Professor at the Universi¬
ty of North Carolina. He is at present
working on a three-volume study of the
river in American literature, the first
volume of which, Prophetic Waters,
was published in 1977. His other works
include The Kid (1972) and The True
Adventures of Huckleberry Finn (1970).
BENOIT DELAFON is a French lawyer
who, in 1981, in collaboration with a
marine architect specializing in the
design of river boats, established the
Pier N° 1 Association for the adapta¬
tion and re-use of traditional barges.
LOTFALLAH SOLIMAN, of Egypt,
publisher, journalist and leader-writer
with a monthly magazine, comes from
Al-Mansurah, a town on the east bank
of the Damietla branch of the Nile delta.
FRIEDRICH HEER, ofAustria, is pro¬
fessor of the history of cultures at Vien¬
na University. He is the author of a
number of works including Europäische
Geistesgeschichte (History of European
Culture) and Grundlagen der
Europäischen Demokratie der Neuzeit
(Basic Principles of Modern European
Democracy).
EUGENIO TURRI, of Italy, a
geographer known for his studies on the
landscape and on human geography,
has spent many years in Africa and
Asia. His works include Anthropologia
del Paesaggio (Anthropology of the
Landscape), Continenti e Paesi (Con¬
tinents and Countries) and Semiología
del Paesaggio Italiano (Semiology ofthe
Italian Landscape).
LEONID LIKHODEEV, of the Soviet
Union, is a well-known writer and the
author of a number of works including
the popular novels Me and My Car and
Four Chapters from the Life of Maria
Nikolaievna.
HENRI LOPES is Assistant Director-
General for Programme Support at
Unesco. From 1969 to 1980 he held a
number of cabinet posts, including that
ofprime minister, in the Government of
his country, the People 's Republic of the
Congo. He is the author of several
novels and a collection of short stories.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekm)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Just published
This monograph, which launches a new Unesco series entitled
"Women in a World Perspective", presents the findings of a case-
study carried out as part of Unesco's programme of "Studies on
the Status of Women in Relation to Development and Demographic
Behaviour". It throws new light on the relatively high incidence
of female-headed households in the Caribbean, where they con¬
stitute one-third of all households, offers valuable insights into the
composition of such households, the reasons why they exist, their
problems, and the multiple survival strategies employed by women
in this position.
25 French francs69 pages
Forthcoming titles in the series include:
Women and Work in Uruguay
Dynamics of the Female Labour Force: Patterns
demographic and socio-economic change in Argentina
of
Women as heads of
households in the Caribbean:
family structure and
feminine status
Joycelin Massiah
Unesco
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066, Publications Educational Supplies Pty
Ltd PO. Box 33 , Brookvale. 2100, NSW Periodicals
Dominie Pty Subscriptions Dept , P O Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW Sub- agent United Nations Association of
Australia, P O Box 175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000 - AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31. A-1011, Vienna
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd , Ittefaq
Building, 1, RK Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3 -
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N V
Handelmaatschappij Keesing Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen French edition and general Unesco
publications agent JeandeLannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060
Brussels, CCPOOO-0070823-13 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon -CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co Ltd, 21 82 St Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que H3H1M7 - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P 0 Box 88, Beijing -
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0
Box 1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - SNTL,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display!, Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 For Slovakia only Alfa
Verlag - Publishers, Hurbanovo nam 6,893 31 Bratislava -
CSSR - DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K. -
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P 0 Box 2996, Addis Ababa -
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10, Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuia 2, 01 640 Vantaa 64. - FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, C C P 1 2598-48
- GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig,
Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G D R - FED. REP. OF GERMANY.
For the Unesco Courier {German, English, French and Spanish
editions! Mr H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3 For other Unesco publica¬
tions Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen For scientific maps
only Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80 - GHANA.
Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P O Box 1 95, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd , P 0. Box 7869, Accra, The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast, The University Bookshop of Legón, P 0 Box 1 , Legón
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom - HONG KONG.
Federal Publications (HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion,
12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen Swindon Book Co , 13-15, Lock
Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government Information Services,
Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street -
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V,
A K V Konyvturosok Boltja, Nepkoztársasag utja 1 6, Budapest
VI. - ICELAND. Snaebprn Jonsson & Co , H F , Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038, 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13, 36a, AnnaSalai, Mount Road, Madras 2, 5-9-41/1
Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (API, 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi
Road, Bangalore- 560001, 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 Sub-Depots' Oxford Book & Stationery
Co 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 7001 6, Scindia House, New Delhi,
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 1 0001 - IN¬
DONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta, Gramedia Bookshop, Jl Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta, Indira P T , Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakar¬
ta Pusat - IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co ,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghelab Avenue, P O Box
314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat Comm for Unesco, Ave Iran-
chahrChomaliNo 300, B P 1533, Teheran - IRAQ. McKen-
zie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad - IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 1 2 - ISRAEL. ABC Bookstore Ltd ,
PO Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 -
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd , P O Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. - JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc ,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome,
Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing
House. P O Box 30571, Nairobi - KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P O Box Central 64, Seoul
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait;
for the Unesco Courier Farafalla Press Agency, P O Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, PO
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa - LIBERIA. Cole and Yan-
cy Bookshops Ltd , P O Box 286, Monrovia - LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P O Box 34-35,
Tripoli - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-
Rue, Luxembourg - MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd , 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis - MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd des Moulins, Monte-Carlo -
NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only Dekker and Nordemann
NV, P O Box 197,1 000 AD Amsterddam, for publications only
KEESING BOEKEN B V , Postbus 1118, 1 000 BC Amsterdam
- NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine NI V . P O
Box 200, Willemstad, Curacao N A - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at
Rutland Street, P O Box 5344, Auckland, 1 30, Oxford Terrace,
PO Box 1721 Chnstchurch. Alma Street, PO Box 857
Hamilton, Princes Street, PO Box 1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington - NIGERIA The University
Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P O 286,
The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University Bookshop
of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana -
NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers),
Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1, Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssentret, POB 307 Blindern, Oslo 3 For Unesco
Courier only AS Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 61 25, Oslo
6 - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-
azam, PO Box No 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The
Modern Book Co . 926 Rizal Avenue, P 0 Box 632, Manila
D-404 - POLAND Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, War¬
saw, Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7 00-068
WARSAW - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda Livrana Por¬
tugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon - SEYCHELLES. National
Bookshop, P O Box 48, Mahé, New Service Ltd , Kingsgate
House, PO Box 131, Mahé - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay,
Niala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops,
Freetown - SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd ,
No 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road,
Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC.
Modern Book Shop and General, P O Box 951, Mogadiscio -
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications. Van Schaik's Book-store
(Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street, P O Box 924, Pretoria
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only Central News agen¬
cy, P O Box 1033, Johannesburg - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 1 00 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata POB 244
Colombo 2 - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P O Box 1 1 1 8,
Khartoum - SWEDEN. All publications A/BC E FritzesKungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regermgsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16 For the Unesco Courier Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm -
SWITZERLAND. All publications Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse. Zurich Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP 12-236 - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, POB 9030 Dares-Salaam - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co. Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
PhayaSn, PO Box 402, Bangkok Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Ra|damnern Avenue, Bangkok, Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St Clair,
Trinidad, W I - TURKEY. Hasel Kitapevi A S , Istiklàl Caddesi.
No 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul - UGANDA.
Uganda Bookshop, PO Box 7145, Kampala - UNITED
KINGDOM. H M Stationery Office, P 0 Box 569, London,
SEI, and Govt Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, for scientific maps only
McCarta Ltd , 1 22 King's Cross Road, London WC1 X 9 DS -
UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South, New
York, NY 10010 - U.S S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga.
Moscow, G-200 - YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11,
Zagreb, Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana, Nolit, Terazi-
|e 27/1 1, Belgrade - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd ,
67 Union Avenue, Harare
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
of the water's syllables,
patriarch father, you are
the secret eternity
of the fecundations,
rivers swoop down on you like birds,
fire-coloured pistils cover you,
the great dead trunks people you with perfume,
the moon cannot guard you nor fathom you.
You ore charged with green semen
like a bridal tree, you are silvered
with the wild primrose,
you are reddened with timber,
blue between the moon of the stones,
clothed in ferruginous mist,
slow as a planet's path.
Pablo Neruda
]]>
</page>
</document>
