<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074757eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
MAY 1980 3.50 FRENCH FRANCS
*C2Earth'
resource
j
A world strategy for action now
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
^
China
Owl-shaped wine jar
The last three centuries of the Shang dynasty (from the 14th to the 11th century BC) were
an age of great creativity in Chinese history. The earliest examples of Chinese writing,
oracular messages incised on tortoise-shell and bone, date from this period which saw the
rise of a flourishing bronze age civilization in the middle and lower basin of the Yellow
River. Among the many Shang bronze vessels and implements which have survived are
alcohol containers wrought with, a wide variety of animal motifs. This owl-shaped wine
vessel, approximately 30 cm high, dates from very late in the Shang period. It is now in the
Minneapolis Institute of Arts, U.S.A.
Photo © The Minneapolis Institute of Arts, bequest of Alfred F. Pillsbury
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
MAY 1980 33rd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER ¡s published monthly (11 issues a
year including one double issue). For list of distributors see
inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.CR. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York. U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition:. Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
-Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
OF MAMMOTHS AND MEN
Conservation for human survival
by Michel Bâtisse
10 AGAINST THE GRAIN
At present rates one third of the world's cropland
will have disappeared within twenty years
15 SAFETY IN NUMBERS
Ethics and self-interest demand the preservation
of genetic diversity
16 THE RETURN OF THE NATIVE
Photo story
19 THE MIGHTY MINNOW
20 THE HUMAN TOUCH
Man has been shaping his environment
ever since prehistoric times
by Francesco di Castri
23 GUIDELINES FOR ENVIRONMENTAL EDUCATION
25 OUR EVOLUTIONARY RESPONSIBILITY
by Otto Franke!
28 LIVING ON BORROWED TIME
Humanity is rapidly overdrawing
its account with nature
30 A MILLION SPECIES THREATENED WITH EXTINCTION
33 THE GLOBAL COMMONS
36 A WORLD CONSERVATION STRATEGY
38 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
CHINA: Owl-shaped wine jar
v These articles are taken from the WORLD CONSERVATION STRATEGY prepared
. by the International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN).
Cover
Based on a poster by Hans Ulrich Oster-
walder, our cover photo symbolizes the
recognition that man is an integral part of
nature and that his survival depends on the
conservation and rational management of
the earth's living resources.
Poster Hans Urich Osterwalder,
Weltspartag 1979 © Deutscher Sparkassenverlag GmbH, Stuttgart
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The World Conservation Strategy, a compelling new study published in
March this year, provides an assessment of the present state of the global
environment and proposals for world-wide action for rational develop¬
ment and conservation of the resources of our planet. The Conservation
Strategy was prepared by the International Union for the Conservation of
Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN) with the advice, co-operation and
financial assistance of the United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP) and the World Wildlife Fund, and in collaboration with the Food
and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations (FAO) and Unesco. In
this issue of the Unesco Courier, devoted entirely to environmental
problems, we publish large extracts from this important document (on
pages 6, 10, 15, 28, 33 and 36).
Of mammoths and men
Conservation for human survival
by Michel Bâtisse
Agréât deal of talk is heard these days
about protecting threatened animal
species, preserving forests, improv¬
ing the environment, and even restoring the
"quality of life". And yet these notions
sometimes seem hazy and the motives
behind them are as a rule neither very clear
nor very rational. The case for the conserva¬
tion of nature must be more satisfactorily
explained before it can be more effectively
defended.
Some 10,000 years ago, an abundant and
noble form of animal life, the mammoth,
disappeared forever from the face of the
earth, perhaps as a result of the long hail of
blows inflicted on it by our distant
ancestors, doubtless too because its disap¬
pearance had in any case been pre-ordained
in the pitiless book of the evolution of
species.
No one today is concerned about the fate
of the mammoth, whose extinction has
been no hindrance to the development and
flowering of human civilizations. The sur¬
vival or disappearance of a single species
notwithstanding, the great adventure of life
goes on. On the other hand, the world as we
and our children envision it today would
undeniably be the poorer if the elephant, for
example, became extinct. The philosopher
Immanuel Kant maintained that man has
duties to himself only. Does he, then, owe
none to the elephant? Or to the whale?
MICHEL BATISSE, Deputy Assistant Director-
General for Sciences at Unesco, is a French
physicist specializing in problems of the environ¬
ment and natural resources. He was instrumental
in launching the International Hydrological
Decade and Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
programme.
The truth is that in every age certain
civilizations have shown respect for living
species and certain religions have even
raised such respect to the level of dogma. In
every age, too, the rural world has patiently
harvested the bounty of nature's resources
without jeopardizing their productive
physical and biological mechanisms, thereby
securing the very foundations of human
societies and cultures.
These processes are still going on today.
But at the same time new phenomena have
appeared and their impact has been increas¬
ingly felt since industrial civilization and the
agricultural revolution extended their sway
to every corner of the world, since unbridled
population growth began, and since our
needs of all kinds, whether real or imagined,
have come to impose on nature and natural
resources a pressure which is constantly
mounting, often excessive, and will soon
become intolerable.
The idea of "conservation" is simply a
healthy reaction to the new situation created
by the technological and demographic ex¬
plosions. Healthy but belated. There have,
admittedly, been numerous cases of action
in various parts of the world to protect
unique sites and to regulate the use of cer¬
tain resources.
Four centuries before the Christian era
Plato was already decrying the fact that the
mountains of Greece were being stripped of
their trees. As early as the thirteenth century
in Europe, efforts were starting to be made
to bring some order to the practice of
forestry, after the extensive deforestation of
the early Middle Ages. In France, the
celebrated decree on watercourses and
forests drawn up in 1669 by Louis XIV's
minister Colbert was primarily concerned
with obtaining wood supplies for ship¬
building but also provided for the conserva¬
tion of forests. More recently, in 1872, the
world's first national park was created in the
United States on the magnificent site of
Yellowstone.
However, until the Second World War all
the combined efforts to protect nature could
not be said to amount to a solid and struc¬
tured movement. Even in 1946 when Unesco
was founded, governments attached much
more importance to the protection of
monuments and works of art than to the
conservation of the natural heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Fortunately this situation was soon
destined to change. Chance, which
sometimes orders matters wisely, decreed
that the first Director-General of Unesco
should be Sir Julian Huxley, an eminent
- biologist with a passionate interest in evolu¬
tion. In 1948, on the instigation of Huxley
and a group of far-seeing scientists, Unesco
in co-operation with the French government
organized a conference at Fontainebleau
which led to the creation of the International
Union for the Protection of Nature. This
dynamic non-governmental organiza¬
tion in 1957 the International
Union for the Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources has now launched a
World Conservation Strategy whose broad
outlines are presented in this issue of the
Unesco Courier.
In the last thirty-odd years we have come
a long way, in terms both of ideas and of
practical accomplishments. It has to be ad¬
mitted that the earliest essays in the conser¬
vation of nature were tinged with roman¬
ticism and were not always based on a pro¬
found analysis of the hierarchy of needs.
The emphasis was laid on the protection of
attractive animal species, above all the great
mammals, and on that of the most spec¬
tacular sites. I
In partnership with nature, man
has created some of the world's
most pleasing landscapes, living
sculptures like these hillside rice
terraces in Java, Indonesia. Over
the centuries man has altered
his environment, modifying it in
ways favourable to himself, but
at the same time respecting the
physical and biological
mechanisms of nature. Only
since the industrial revolution
and the technological and
demographic explosions to
which it cjave rise has human
pressure on the world's natural
resources become excessive and
even, at times, intolerable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
A world strategy for the conservation of Earth's living resources is
needed now because:
1. Living resources essential for human survival and sustainable
development are increasingly being destroyed or depleted. At the
same time human demand for these resources is growing fast. The
problem is illustrated above. If current rates of land degradation
continue, close to one third of the world's arable land (symbolized
by the stalk ofgrain) will be destroyed in the next 20 years. Similar¬
ly, by the end of this century (atpresent rates of clearance), the re¬
maining area of unlogged productive tropical forest will be halved.
During this period the world population is expected to increase by
almost half- from just over 4,000 million to just under 6,000
million. The predicament caused by growing numbers of people
demanding scarcer resources is exacerbated by the dispropor¬
tionately high consumption rates of developed countries.
2. The action required to cure the most serious current conserva¬
tion problems and to prevent still worse ones takes time: time for
planning, education, training, better organization and research;
and when such action is undertaken, it takes time for the biosphere
to respond reforestation, the restoration of degraded land, the
recovery of depleted fisheries, and so on, are not instantaneous
processes.
3. National and international capacities to conserve are ill-
organized and fragmented split up amongst sectors such as
agriculture, forestry, fisheries and wildlife with consequent
duplication of effort, gaps in coverage, competition for money and
influence, and conflict; and they have little influence on the
development process, with the result that development, the prin¬
cipal means of tackling human problems, too often adds to them
by destroying or degrading the living resource base of human
welfare.
Many cases of land devastation are due to the extraction
rather than the use of certain mineral ores and fuels.
Open-cast or strip-mining can turn vast areas of
productive land into barren, eroded wasteland unless
rehabilitation measures are planned before mining begins.
These usually involve the removal and storage of topsoil
for replacement when mining is completed and the
reshaping of spoil heaps to blend with the surrounding
countryside. Opposite page, above; at Ordjonikidze in the
Ukraine, the desolation caused by strip-mining for
manganese ore. Right, at the same site, after
rehabilitation, scientists check the crop yield.
This baby mammoth (left) was seven months old when it
died of drowning some 40,000 years ago. Dima, as he has
been named, was discovered in 1977 by a Soviet gold
prospector in the Magadan region of eastern Siberia. The
animal's remarkable state of preservation is due to the
fact that he was buried under a landslide of ice, crushed
stone and frozen mud shortly after he died. Although the
mammoth was hunted by prehistoric man, it is unlikely
that this was the direct cause of the extinction of the
species which more probably resulted from climatic
changes towards the end of the Pleistocene Epoch some
10,000 years ago.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photos Vladimir Bogatyrev © APN, Moscow
i. The methods used were not always very
appropriate. Some twenty years ago, for ex¬
ample, an immense photograph of a scor¬
pion was used in a campaign to inform the
Egyptian public about the conservation of
nature; meanwhile, in Cairo alone, stings by
these fearsome arthropods were claiming
several lives each day.
The prevailing approach, a correct one
but followed too exclusively, was to draw up
lists of endangered animal species and to
demand that these species be protected. At
the same time interest was growing in the
creation and management of national parks
and biological reserves. The tourist boom
brought unprecedented crowds of visitors to
those parks which had already been
established, notably in North America and in
Africa, and the creation of new parks was
not entirely divorced from the hope that
they would be a source of revenue. Along
with these efforts, however, certain dif¬
ficulties arose.
How, outside the great parks, would it be
possible to preserve animal and plant
species which might one day be useful,
without protecting the environment' in
which and from which they lived? How
could it be explained "to the peoples who
were traditionally users of areas transformed
into national parks that the transformation
was in their interests, whereas these peoples
needed more land for their herds and their
crops? How could the massive influx of
tourists be prevented from vitiating the very
objectives of nature conservation? How
could protected areas be established on a
long-term basis and achieve full acceptance
except in regions of slight economic in¬
terest, such as high mountains?
Meanwhile, profound changes were tak¬
ing place in the world. Many once-
dominated countries were acceding to
sovereignty, seeking the roots of their
cultural identity, and grappling with the in¬
tractable problems of underdevelopment.
The nexus of problems relating to
economic development, social justice,
human dignity, the use of natural resources
and the preservation of the environment
became the major theme of international
debate and was increasingly felt to be the
essential precondition to peace and har¬
mony between all the peoples of the
planet a planet which the astronauts on
the moon revealed to us as suddenly
shrunken and limited in size, isolated and
fragile in a hostile universe.
In this dynamic situation, in whose fabric
all world problems were interwoven, conser¬
vation was bound to assume a new dimen¬
sion. No longer would it be a more or less
tolerated hobby for some scientists, a hand¬
ful of romantics or a privileged few. It was
taking its place in the very core of world
problems.
A particularly important milestone in this
process came in 1968 with the intergovern¬
mental conference on the rational use of the
resources of the biosphere. The somewhat
abstruse scientific term biosphere, which
designates the very thin layer on the earth's
surface in which life in all its multifarious
forms can exist, was to become part of the
layman's vocabulary.
But above all, the holding of this con¬
ference was the first response from the
world of international politics to the growing
concern felt by scientists biologists, i
pedologists; ecologists, and so onabout I
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
the increasingly rapid use and simultaneous
degradation of the earth's resources.
The conservation of individual species or
landscapes was no longer enough; what had
to be done was to ensure that the exploita¬
tion of nature was put on a rational scientific
basis which would guarantee the permanent
survival of the delicate mechanisms which
condition life. Conservation, which
preserves the genetic capital and the poten¬
tiality for use of all living species, was an in¬
tegral part of this rational approach reflec¬
ting the wisdom and intelligence which
should govern any responsible management
of fragile and limited resources. In other
words, economic and social development
and the protection of the environment must
be systematically integrated.
A new scientific term, ^ecosystem, came
into popular parlance, indicating that living
organisms, including man himself, cannot
be considered in isolation from one another
but belong to ecological systems in which
any modification of one component has an
impact on the rest of the system. The
essence of human genius is to use these
ecosystems for the benefit of mankind
without endangering the very bases which
enable them to function.
Out of the biosphere conference came a
far-reaching programme of interdisciplinary
research aimed at working out the best
methods of managing ecosystems. Some
hundred countries are today participating in
this programme on Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) established by Unesco, within which
a new tool for conservation, the biosphere
reserve, has been defined.
Each of these areas of land, which are
scattered throughout the world, is situated
in an ecosystem representing one of the
world's great biogeographic regions. Each
contains a central protected area in which
the evolution of animal and plant species
can take place in as "natural" a state as
possible.
Around this central core is a more exten¬
sive "buffer" zone in which research is con¬
ducted into the structure and functioning of
the ecosystem when it is subjected to
various forms of manipulation and use by
man. At the same time, the biosphere
reserve constitutes a specimen area in which
environmental change can be continuously
monitored. It can also be used for training
specialists and for educating the public.
The fact that the reserves are linked to
studies and experiments on land use also
means, that their advantages can be shown
to people living in the vicinity who are thus
associated with the protection of the
reserves. Today 177 biosphere reserves have
been officially established in forty-six coun¬
tries, but much remains to be done before
the international network which they are
now beginning to form fully reflects the
various representative ecosystems which
must be studied and protected.
The Biosphere Conference was a kind of
dress rehearsal for the future, as the interna¬
tional community and political circles
became more deeply aware of the capital im¬
portance in the modern world of the preser¬
vation of the environment and the conserva¬
tion of nature and natural resources.
Four years later at Stockholm the United
Nations Conference on the Human Environ¬
ment set the seal on this fundamental
change in the order of priorities of peoples
8
and governments. The Stockholm Con¬
ference led to the creation of the United Na¬
tions Environment Programme whose task
was to stimulate international and national
action in this immense field, in co-operation
with all the other organizations of the United
Nations system.
Meanwhile a bold initiative was to mark
the equal importance for man of
simultaneously conserving the two vital
elements in his environment: culture, with
which he nourishes his mind; and nature,
with which he nourishes his body. In 1972
Unesco's General Conference adopted a
Convention on the Protection of the World
Cultural and Natural Heritage which has so
far been ratified by over fifty countries.
The Convention has, firstly, a symbolic
value. Nature and culture have long been
the subject of separate if not rival study
and devotion. Today they both appear to be
simultaneously threatened, along with man
himself, who can exist only when the two
are combined. By bringing together and
reconciling the cultural and natural dimen¬
sions of the human heritage, the Convention
seeks to harmonize human activities and
aspirations.
From the legal viewpoint, moreover, it is
something radically new. It proclaims that
certain monuments, sites and living systems
are so important for the whole of humanity
that it is incumbent on the international
community to make sure that they are pro¬
tected. It provides for machinery and
finance allowing action to be taken when
any item of cultural or natural property on
the world heritage list is threatened. The aim
of the Convention is not, strictly speaking,
the conservation of nature in general, but it
is yet another tool and one enjoying con¬
siderable prestige in the service of an
overall strategy.
In vast regions of the world the problems
of poverty, sickness and malnutrition
monopolize the attention of governments
and public opinion. Elsewhere there is rising
unemployment and inflation. Everywhere
the arms race goes on apace. Against this
canvas of daily events conservation usually
has to wait. However, an exclusive pre¬
occupation with what is urgent may spell
neglect for what is important. In trying to
cope with the problems of today we treat
the future with contempt. It is imperative to
integrate without further delay the dimen¬
sion of the future into the preoccupations
and actions of today.
On our ill-treated planet, whenever a
patch of fertile land is covered with con¬
crete, whenever tropical soil is transformed
into latérite, whenever a species disappears,
whenever the capital of resources is vainly
squandered, it is for the whole of mankind
that the "bell tolls".
In the course of its slow emergence,
mankind has never had an easy or a
guaranteed future threatened in the past
by plague and famine, threatened today by
nuclear holocaust and by shortages, real or
of its own making. But for the first time in
his long history man now has the capacity
and the obligation to act upon the factors
which condition his very survival. Will he
take heed early enough? Will he act in time?
The answer depends on every one of us. For
it is not the conservation of the mammoth
that is at stake. It is simply that of the
human species.
Michel Bâtisse
Defying
the sands of time
The rocky islet of Mont Saint-
Michel, just off the coast of
Normandy, France, is a site which
combines great natural beauty with
profound historical and cultural
interest. Rising sheer from the calm
waters of the Bay of Mont Saint-
Michel, it has been a place of
worship and pilgrimage since the
8th century. The base of the islet,
some 900 metres in circumference,
is encircled by medieval walls and
its summit is crowned by the
ancient Benedictine abbey, founded
in 966 by Richard duke of
Normandy. Over the years, the Bay
has gradually become silted up until
today the islet is completely
surrounded with water for only 124
days a year and by the end of the
century it will be permanently
attached to the mainland unless
action is taken. In France, 1980 has
been declared the Year of the
National Heritage and the French
Government has decided to launch
a programme of works designed to
halt further siltation and to
maintain this historic site in its
natural island setting. Mont Saint-
Michel is one of the 57 sites listed
under the Convention concerning
the Protection of the World's
Cultural and Natural heritage,
adopted by the Unesco General
Conference in 1972. The Convention
declares that, "it is incumbent on
the international community as a
whole to participate in the
protection of the cultural and
natural heritage of outstanding
universal value." Mont Saint-Michel
typifies the need for a common
approach to the conservation of
both the natural and the cultural
heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
f
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Aerial photo, right, shows
reforestation in the
Extremadura region of
western Spain tracing the
contours of a hilly area. As
well as providing firewood
and timber, forests prevent
soil erosion and flooding and
can also influence climate.
Between 5 and 10 million
hectares of forest are being
felled each year for
agriculture alone, and world
demand for tropical
hardwood is expected to
triple during the next 20
years, requiring the felling of
556 million hectares of forest.
Perhaps more than any other
issue the fate of the world's
forests highlights the vital
need to integrate
conservation into rural
development.
Against the grain
At present rates one third of the world's cropland will have
disappeared within twenty years
SINCE the day in April 1961 when
Soviet cosmonaut Yuri Gagarin
circled the earth in spacecraft
Vostok I, the term "life-support system" has
become common currency. By a life-support
system is meant a combination of supplies
and devices which enables man to live and
work in an environment, such as a
spacecraft or a submarine, in which he
could otherwise not survive. Man needs an
atmosphere he can breathe and supplies of
water and food as well as a means of waste
disposal. On "spaceship earth" the most im¬
portant life-support systems which provide
these elements are agricultural systems,
forests, and coastal and freshwater sys¬
tems. Today, these life-support systems are
under serious threat.
Only about 11 % of the world's land area,
(excluding Antarctica) offers no serious
limitation to agriculture; the rest suffers
from drought, mineral stress (nutritional
deficiencies or toxicities), shallow depth, ex¬
cess water, or permafrost.
The world's cropland currently occupies
14 million km2, and although it may be possi¬
ble to double this area, much of the best
land is already being farmed. Unfortunately
large areas of prime quality land are being
permanently taken out of agricultural use by
being built on.
10
In developed countries at least 3,000 km2
of prime agricultural land are submerged
every year under urban sprawl: between
1960 and 1970 Japan lost 7.3% of its
agricultural land to buildings and roads and
European countries lost from 1.5% (Nor¬
way) to 4.3% (Netherlands).
Soil is a crucial life-support system, since
the bulk of all food production depends on
it. Soil erosion is a natural and continuous
process, but in undisturbed ecosystems
with a protective cover of plants the soil is
usually regenerated at the same rate it is
removed. If soil and vegetation are not in
balance, as often they are not when in¬
fluenced by poorly managed human
activities, erosion is accelerated with
disastrous consequences.
Even under natural conditions of vegeta¬
tion cover, nature takes from 100 to 400
years or more to generate 10 millimetres of
top soil; and 3,000 to 12,000 years would be
needed to generate soil to a depth of the
length of this page. So once the soil has
gone, for all practical purposes it has gone
for good.
Soil loss has accelerated sharply
throughout the food-hungry tropics, which
are generally more susceptible to erosion
than the temperate zone, due to the
topography of the land and the nature of the
soils and rainfall.
More than half of India, for example, suf¬
fers from some form of soil degradation: out
of her total of 3.3 million km2, 1.4 million
km2 are subject to increased soil loss, while
an additional 270,000 km2 are being degrad¬
ed by floods, salinity and alkalinity. An
estimated 6,000 million tonnes of soil are
lost every year from 800,000 km2 alone; with
them go more tham 6 million tonnes of
nutrients more than the amount that is ap¬
plied in the form of fertilizers. It is estimated
that close to one third of the world's arable
land will be destroyed in the next 20 years if
current rates of land degradation continue.
The productivity of agricultural eco¬
systems depends not only on maintaining
soil quality but also on retaining the habitats
of beneficial insects and other animals, such
as crop pollinators and the predators and
parasites of pests.
Effective pest control is no longer a matter
of heavy applications of pesticides, partly
because of the rising cost of petroleum-
derived products but largely because ex¬
cessive pesticide use promotes resistance
(the number of pesticide-resistant insects
and mites has doubled in 12 years), destroys i
natural enemies, turns formerly innocuous I
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
> species into pests, harms other non-target
species, and contaminates food and feed.
Instead pesticides should be used to supple¬
ment a battery of methods integrated in ap¬
propriate combinations: these methods in¬
clude introduction of pest-resistant crop
varieties, special planting combinations and
patterns, mechanical methods, the use of
repellents and hormones, and encourage¬
ment of natural enemies.
Besides supplying timber and other pro¬
ducts, forests have a vital effect on pro¬
cesses of great significance for people. They
influence local and regional climates,
generally by making them milder, and they
help to ensure a continuous flow of clean
water. Some forests, notably tropical cloud
forests, even increase the availability of
water by intercepting moisture from clouds.
Watershed forests are particularly impor¬
tant because they protect soil cover on site
and protect areas downstream from ex¬
cessive floods and other harmful fluctua¬
tions in streamflow. By thus reducing the silt
load of rivers, watershed forests also help
prevent the clogging of reservoirs, irrigation
systems, canals and docks, and the
smothering by sediment of coral reefs. Yet
watershed forests are being widely
devastated by clearance for agriculture, by
logging and cutting for fuel, by overgrazing,
and by badly managed road building.
The results can be extremely expensive. It
costs Argentina $ 10 million a year to dredge
silt from the estuary of the River Plate and
keep Buenos Aires open to shipping: yet
80% of the 100 million tonnes of sediment
that every year threaten to block the harbour
comes from only 4% of the drainage
basin the heavily overgrazed catchment
area of the Bermejo River 1,800 km
Estuaries, mangrove swamps (above) and other coastal wetlands
provide rich and abundant nutrients on which an estimated two-
thirds of the world's fisheries directly depend. Today the fate of
these fisheries hangs in the balance in many parts of the world
as coastal wetland habitats are being degraded or destroyed by
pollution and various forms of industrial development, while in
some tropical regions mangroves are being used for firewood,
fodder and building materials. Some 70 per cent of the world's
great cities, including Hong Kong (below) are situated on
estuaries. Below right, windmills dot the landscape at Kinderdijk
in The Netherlands, part of a delicately-balanced wetland
ecosystem. Interdisciplinary study of the world's deltas, estuaries
and coastal zones forms part of Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) programme.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Regional Distribution of Soils
with or without Limitations for Agriculture
12 3 4 5 6
1. Europa
2. Central America
3. North America
4. South A«ia
5. Africa
6. South America
7. Australasia
8. Southeast Asia
9. North and Central Asia
10. World
No serious limitation
| Drought
I Mineral stress
] Shallow depth
I Water excess
H Permafrost
Source FAO, 1978. The State of Food and Agriculture 1977, FAO, Rome
upstream. In India the annual cost of
damage by floods ranges from $140 million
to $750 million.
Sedimentation as a result of careless use
of watershed forests can cut drastically the
economic life of reservoirs, hydroelectric
facilities and irrigation systems. The capaci¬
ty of India's Nizamsagar reservoir has been
more than halved (from almost 900 million
m3 to fewer than 340 million m3) and there is
now not enough water to irrigate the 1,100
km2 of sugarcane and rice for which it was
intended and hence not enough sugarcane
to supply local sugar factories. Deforesta¬
tion in northern Luzon in the Philippines has
silted up the reservoir of the Ambuklao Dam
so fast that its useful life has been reduced
from 60 to 32 years.
Such problems are not confined to
developing countries: for example, it has
been estimated that more than 1,000 million
m3 of sediment are deposited every year in
the major reservoirs of the USA. Although
they have not been calculated (indeed, pro¬
bably cannot be), the global costs of sedi¬
ment removal, river dredging, reconstruc¬
tion of irrigation systems and loss of invest¬
ment in expensive structures like dams must
be huge. Only 10% of the world's popula¬
tion live in mountainous areas where the
watershed forests are, but another 40% live
in the adjacent plains; so the lives and
livelihoods of half the world directly depend
on the way in which watershed ecosystems
are managed.
In areas under shifting cultivation forests
also act to restore soil fertility. More than
200 million people occupying- about 30
million km2 of tropical forests live by practis¬
ing shifting cultivation cropping an area i
for a few years, then clearing another area, Y
Photos Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
y leaving the first one fallow to revert to scrub
and forest. The fallow period lasts from 8-12
years in tropical rain forests to 20-30 years in
drier areas, and during this time the forest
cover enables the soil to regenerate.
This is a stable, productive practice if the
population itself is stable; but if populations
are growing, which nowadays they usually
are, the pressure on land increases, fallow
periods shorten, the soil has no chance to
regenerate, and wider and wider tracts of
otherwise productive forest land are des¬
troyed.
Almost two-thirds of the land under shif¬
ting cultivation is upland forest, much of it
on steep slopes, and the resulting erosion is
severe. In the Ivory Coast, shifting cultiva¬
tion reduced the forest cover by 30% bet¬
ween 1956 and 1966 and now only 50,000
km2 remain out of the 150,000 km2 that are
believed to have existed at the beginning of
this century. Similarly, shifting cultivators
clear about 3,500 km2 a year in the Philip¬
pines Mindanao alone they cleared
10,000 km2 between 1960 and 1971.
Coastal wetlands and shallows espe¬
cially estuaries and mangrove swamps-
provide food and shelter for waterfowl and
for fishes, crustaceans and molluscs utilized
by an estimated two-thirds of the world's
fisheries. Some are among the world's most
lucrative fisheries, notably those for shrimp.
Seagrass meadows also act as nurseries and
nutrient suppliers for economically impor¬
tant fish species.
Coral ecosystems are of more local, but
nonetheless vital, significance providing
habitats for the fish on which many coastal
communities in developing countries de¬
pend. In addition, coastal wetlands and cor¬
al reefs are extremely important for coastal
protection: without the activities of corals
and other reef-building organisms, for ex¬
ample, more than 400 islands would not ex¬
ist. Similarly, many freshwater wetlands and
floodplains support important inland fish¬
eries, while floodplain agriculture has long
relied on the regular supply of nutrients by
floodwaters.
Wetlands, floodplains, seagrass beds and
coral reefs are being destroyed the world
over, with severe effects on the economies
that depend on them most closely. For ex¬
ample, the cost of damage to US marine
fisheries caused by degradation of coastal
wetlands has been estimated to be almost
$86 million a year. In Sri Lanka repeated
removal of corals for the production of lime
is so extensive that a local fishery has col¬
lapsed; mangroves, small lagoons and
coconut groves have disappeared; and local
wells have been contaminated with salt.
In many parts of the world the construc¬
tion of dams has blocked the passage of
migrating fish and drowned or otherwise
destroyed the habitats of others; and
although the new reservoir may support a
new fiáhery this does not always compen¬
sate for the loss of the floodplain. The
habitats of many other aquatic animals also
are threatened. For example, many sea tur¬
tle nesting beaches have been wrecked for
roads, housing and other developments;
while the breeding areas of gray whales and
belugas (or white whales) are also at risk.
These are typical effects of the impacts on
coastal and freshwater ecosystems every¬
where: impacts such as industrial and
agricultural pollution; the construction of
dams; siltation from eroded uplands; filling
to provide sites for industry, housing,
recreation, airports and farmland; dredging
to create, deepen or improve harbours; .
quarrying; and cutting of mangroves for
fuel.
As the commercially valuable fisheries for
fish, crustaceans and molluscs become
more fully exploited, so the effects of
habitat destruction and pollution par¬
ticularly on those species depending on
coastal wetlands and shallows or on inland
wetlands and floodplains for nutrients or for
spawning grounds and nurseries will
become more evident.
Coral reefs, limestone
formations in the sea
formed by the skeletons
of millions of tiny
animals, provide the
habitats for fish on which
millions of coastal
communities depend for
their livelihood. Today
coral ecosystems are
widely threatened by
various kinds of pollution,
destructive fishing
methods including the
use of dynamite, and
removal for building or
lime production. Below, a
coral atoll off Western
Australia.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
STRATEGY-
Safety in numbers
Ethics and self-interest demand the preservation
of genetic diversity
THE preservation of gene¬
tic diversity is both a
matter of insurance and
investment necessary to sus¬
tain and improve agricultural,
forestry and fisheries produc¬
tion, to keep open future op¬
tions, as a buffer against harm¬
ful environmental change, and
as the raw material for much
scientific and industrial innova¬
tion a matter of moral
principle.
The issue of moral principle
relates particularly to species
extinction, and may be stated
as follows. Human beings have
become a major evolutionary
force. While lacking the
knowledge to control the
biosphere, we have the power
to change it radically. We are
morally obliged to our
descendants and to other
creatures to act prudently.
Since our capacity to alter
the course of evolution does
not make us any the less sub¬
ject to it, wisdom also dictates
that we be prudent. We cannot
predict what species may
become useful to us. Indeed we
may learn that many species
that seem dispensable are
capable of providing important
Each autumn millions of sparrows, sandpipers and plovers set out
from the north-east coast of North America on their long and
dangerous annual migration to the Caribbean and South America.
The white dashes in this photo of a radar screen installed on the
island of Antigua represent migrating birds flying at between 3,000
and 6,000 metres. Most of them are heading south-east,
but a few independent spirits can be seen making
their way towards the south-west.
products, such as pharmaceuticals, or are vital parts of life-support
systems on which we depend. For reasons of ethics and self-
interest, therefore, we should not knowingly cause the extinction of
a species.
The genetic material contained in the domesticated varieties of
crop plants, trees, livestock, aquatic animals and
microorganisms as well as in their wild relatives is essential for
the breeding programme in which continued improvements in
yields, nutritional quality, flavour, durability, pest and disease
resistance, responsiveness to different soils and climates, and other
qualities are achieved.
These qualities are rarely if ever permanent. For example, the
average lifetime of wheat and other cereal varieties in Europe and
North America is only 5-15 years. This is because pests and diseases
evolve new strains and overcome resistance; climates alter; soils
vary; consumer demands change.
Farmers and other crop-producers, therefore, cannot do without
the reservoir of still-evolving possibilities available in the range of
varieties of crops, domesticated animals, and their wild relatives.
The continued existence of wild and primitive varieties of the
world's crop plants is humanity's chief insurance against their
destruction by equivalents for those crops of chestnut blight and
Dutch elm disease.
This is not a remote eventuality. It happened once with the Euro¬
pean grape vine. In the 1860s Phylloxera, an insect which lives on
the roots of the vine, arrived in Europe from North America. Its ef¬
fect was catastrophic. Almost every vineyard on the continent was
destroyed. Then it was
discovered that the native
American vine is tolerant of
Phylloxera. Europe's wine pro¬
duction was saved only by the
grafting of European vines onto
American rootstocks a prac¬
tice that continues today.
The prospects of similar
disasters' striking other crops'
increase as farmers rely on
fewer varieties. Because of in¬
tensive selection for high per¬
formance and uniformity the
genetic base of much modern
food production has grown
dangerously narrow.
Only four varieties of wheat
produce 75% of the crop
grown on the Canadian
prairies; and more than half the
prairie wheatlands are devoted
to a single variety. Similarly,
72% of US potato production
depends on only four varieties,
and just two varieties supply
US pea production. Almost
every coffee tree in Brazil
descends from a single plant,
and the entire US soybean in¬
dustry is derived from a mere
six plants from one place in
Asia.
These and other crops in a
similar position are extremely
vulnerable to outbreaks of pests and diseases and to sudden un¬
favourable changes in growing conditions. Unfortunately, while the
genetic base of the world's crops and other living resources is nar¬
rowing rapidly, the means by which this dangerous situation could
be corrected (the diversity of crop varieties and relatives) are being
destroyed. Many wild and domesticated varieties of crop
plants such as wheat, rice, millet, beans, yams, tomatoes,
potatoes, bananas, limes and oranges are already extinct and
many more are in danger of following them.
Valuable but primitive or locally distributed varieties are to an ex¬
tent victims of their own utility, since the qualities of higher produc¬
tivity and greater disease resistance that give the advanced varieties
such an advantage over them are in large measure derived from
them.
The rapid replacement of traditional varieties by new ones is a
necessary and positive development given the need for more food;
but it could prove counterproductive if the traditional varieties and
their wild relatives are not saved as well.
Primitive populations of crops and their wild relatives are an im¬
portant source, and often the only source, of pest and disease
resistance worth many millions of dollars, of adaptations to difficult
environments and of other agronomically valuable characteristics
such as the dwarf habit in rice and wheat, which has revolutionized
their cultivation and led to greatly increased yields in many parts of
the world.
Useful breeds of livestock are also at risk. Of the 145 indigenous
cattle breeds in Europe and the Mediterranean region 115 are
CONTINUED PAGE 18 -i r
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The return
As part of an international
experiment many species
that now exist only in zoos,
THE BEARDED VULTURE (Gypaetus
barbatusl, an imposing black and
white bird of prey with a wing-span
of three metres, disappeared
progressively from the Alps during
the first ten years of this century.
The youny of five couples raised in
European zoos plus a pair donated
by the USSR are to be released in
the Alps this year.
H *» P.
WV :± t~ i ~ *S^
S I
THE POLAR BEAR (Ursus maritimus) is found only in the northern
hemisphere and usually along the southern fringes of Arctic sea
ice. Although the species is still considered vulnerable,
conservation has improved since the 1960s. In 1973, Canada,
Denmark, Norway, USSR and USA concluded an agreement
which effectively prohibits killing or capturing bears except by
local people using traditional methods, or for scientific or
conservation purposes. The Soviet Government has designated
Wrangel Island, one of the main centres of bear population, as a
protected area.
THE COMMON PUFFIN (Fratercula árctica/ is a
diving bird with a large, brightly coloured,
triangular beak. The successive disasters involving
the oil tankers Torrey Canyon and Amoco Cadiz
reduced the population of the colony at the French
bird sanctuary of the Sept Iles, a group of islands
off the coast of Brittany, from 2,500 couples to 260
couples. In an attempt to avoid the total
disappearance of the puffin from Sept lies, the
French League for the Protection of Birds is to
place puffin chicks taken from the huge colony on
the Faroe Islands in specially constructed burrows
at Sept lies. It is hoped that when, in four years
time, they return from migration to mate and rear
their young, they will return to Sept lies rather
than to the Faroes.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
of the native
reserves or rare natural colonies
are being re-introduced
to their original habitats
THE BARBARY APE (Macaca
sylvana) is a native of the
cedar and oak forests of
Morocco and Algeria; a
colony also exists in
Gibraltar. The apes have
become vulnerable through
exploitation of their forest
habitat, but populations in
the Moroccan central Atlas
mountains appear to be
moderately stable.
Conservationists in France
have established small
colonies in Alsace and at
Rocamadour and are
planning to re-introduce
viable groups of apes to
other regions of Morocco.
THE LYNX (Felis lynx), formerly
widespread throughout Europe, has
declined sharply in numbers over
the last hundred years due to the
diminution of its forest habitat and
to the activities of fur hunters.
During the 1970s, however, groups
of lynx were re-introduced in
Switzerland, Yugoslavia, the
Federal Republic of Germany, Italy,
Austria and France. Most of these
re-introduced animals originate
from the zoological reserve of
Ostrova in Czechoslovakia.
^. »J
THE ARABIAN ORYX (Oryx
leucoryx), formerly found over most
of the Arabian Peninsula, had, by
1972, been hunted virtually to
extermination. Fortunately, in 1962,
three oryx captured in what was
then the Aden Protectorate,
together with others donated by
Saudi Arabia. Kuwait and the
Zoological Society of London, were
sent to Phoenix Zoo, Arizona,
where they formed the nucleus of
the World Herd of Arabian Oryx. In
March this year, five oryx raised in
captivity at San Diego Zoo,
California, from a group of thirteen
oryx on loan from the World Herd,
were re-introduced to Oman where
they have been placed in the care
of nomadic Harasis herdsmen.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 15
threatened with extinction. Yet, as with crops, many traditional
strains are of great valye for breeding purposes.
The very rare Wensleydale sheep has been used to produce a heat
tolerant breed able to produce good quality wool in subtropical lands;
and the Cornish hen, once of interest only to poultry fanciers, proved
so useful for crossing with other strains to produce a quick-growing
meat bird that it is effectively the basis of the broiler industry.
Although only a minute proportion of the world's plants and
animals have been investigated for their value as medicines and other
pharmaceutical products, modern medicine depends heavily on
them.
According to one analysis, more than 40% of the prescriptions
each year in the USA contain a drug of natural origin either from
higher plants (25%) or microbes (13%) or from animals (3%)as
sole active ingredient or as one of the main ones. In the USA alone
the value of medicines just from higher plants is reported to be about
$3,000 million a year and rising.
The most important applications of higher plants and animals for
medicine are as constituents used directly as therapeutic agents for
example, digitoxin, morphine, and atropine, which are still unsur¬
passed in their respective fields; as starting materials for drug syn¬
thesis for example, adrenal cortex and other steroid hormones,
which are normally synthesized from plant steroidal sapogenins; as
models for drug synthesis for example, cocaine, which led to the
development of modern local anaesthetics.
This application should not be underestimated. As one authority
comments: "without naturally occurring active principles, it seems
probable that neither the principle nor the activity would otherwise
have been discovered. Put yourself in the
place of a chemist who would like to
develop a remedy for cardiac insufficiency;
methods currently available would not lead
him to synthesize a digitoxin-like molecule
without knowledge of the natural
prototype".
Paradoxically, a country's dependence on
its own diminishing store of genetic diver¬
sity well as on that of other coun¬
tries likely to grow as the country
develops. Several developing countries, for
example, are currently setting up their own
pharmaceutical industries in order to supply
their peoples with essential drugs at an ac¬
ceptable cost.
As a service to this effort a UN workshop
recently compiled a basic list of medicinal
plants found in Africa, Asia and Latin
America whose active principles are used in
modern medicine. More than 40 of the 90
species listed are available only from the
wild; and another 20, though cultivated, are
also taken from the wild. Preservation of these species and their
habitats is thus one of the preconditions for maintaining indigenous
pharmaceutical industries.
The history of human use of plant and animal species
demonstrates that vanishing and apparently insignificant species can
suddenly become useful, even . important. The "pescado blanco"
Chirostoma estor, a fish which in the wild occurs in a single Mexican
lake, was until recently in danger of extinction as a result of over¬
fishing, habitat degradation, and prédation and competition by in¬
troduced species. Now, as a result of good management and artificial
propagation, the fish is being stocked in several reservoirs and dams
and a 15 hectare farm is under construction.
Many species for example the armadillo and the polar
bearunexpectedly have been found useful for scientific research,
whether as experimental material or as the providers of clues to
technical innovations. Armadillos are the only animals other than
human beings known to contract leprosy. They are now proving to
be invaluable aids in the search for a cure for this disease. The recent
discovery that polar bear hairs are exceptionally efficient heat ab¬
sorbers has provided researchers with a clue that may help them
design and produce materials for the manufacture of better cold-
weather clothing and solar energy collectors.
Preservation of genetic diversity is thus necessary both to secure
supplies of food, fibre, and certain drugs, and to advance scientific
and industrial innovation. It is also necessary to ensure that the loss
of species does not impair the effective functioning of ecological pro¬
cesses. It is unlikely that the particular communities of plants,
animals and microorganisms that make up the ecosystems associated
18
Trading in endangered animal and plant spe¬
cies has been severely curtailed since the
coming into force in 1975 of the Convention
on International Trade in Endangered Species
of Wild Fauna and Flora. Strict regulations
now apply to a long list of species ranging
from musk deer to molluscs, including the
Parnassius apollo, (below), a rare European
butterfly, and the Chrysocyon brachyurus
(bottom), a South American, maned wolf.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The mighty minnow
By the summer of 1973, the $116 million Tellico Dam was nearly complete.
First envisioned in the 1930s by the Tennessee Valley Authority (TVA) which
was created to improve life in one of the most impoverished areas of the
United States, it had been many years in the making. Over 15,000 hectares of
land had been bought for the project, and some 6,700 of them would be flood¬
ed in the 50-kilometre-long reservoir that would form behind the Dam, built
across the Little Tennessee River.
Then the snail darter swam onto the scene.
On 12 August 1973, a University of Tennessee zoology professor named
David A. Etnier was exploring the reach of water behind the unfinished Dam
when he noticed a small fish resting on a bed of sand. Intrigued by its ap¬
pearance, he plucked it from the river. "I immediately realized", he said later,
"that I had something nobody had ever seen in Tennessee waters".
The eight-centimetre-long, light-brown fish was one of the numerous
freshwater fish known as darters which are commonly found in streams of the
eastern and central United States. However, Etnier was convinced that this
particular specimen belonged to a hitherto unknown darter species, and after
lengthy research his conviction was scientifically confirmed. In January 1976
the new species was formally introduced to the world in a scientific journal as
Percina tanasi Etnier. Under its more familiar name, the snail darter (derived
from its main source of food) it became headline news.
Two factors made the discovery of the snail darter something more than a
ripple in the placid waters of ichthyology. Firstly, in the year of its discovery
the Endangered Species Act became part of U.S. law. Section 7 of the Act
specified that all Federal Departments and Agencies should take "such action
necessary to ensure that actions authorized, funded or carried out by them do
not jeopardize the continued existence of... endangered species or result in the
destruction or modification of such species which is determined to be critical".
Secondly it was established that the fish's only known habitat was in the Little
Tennessee River behind the Tellico Dam. When the stagnant lake would be
created by the completion of the Dam, the lives of the snail darters would be
jeopardized.
The snail darter was declared an endangered species under the Act and the
courts ordered the TVA to stop work on the Dam. The TVA appealed and a
protracted legal battle began. The snail darter became a household word, and
the issue crystallized the clash of priorities that could arise between a benefi¬
cent public works project pn which millions had already been spent and the
unknown genetic potential of species threatened with extinction. One Con¬
gressman echoed the thoughts of many people when he said: "It seems silly to
have a little three-inch fish stop construction of a dam the tax-payers have paid
over $100 million for".
The fight went all the way to the U.S. Supreme Court which in June 1978
ruled that a lower court had been correct in halting completion of the Dam
because it was a threat to the snail darter's habitat.
The story did not end there. Opinion both inside and outside Congress con¬
tinued to be sharply divided about the priorities involved. Eventually, in 1979,
new legislation was passed enabling work to continue on the Dam, which is
now complete. Meanwhile, snail darters had been removed to two other rivers;
some have reproduced but scientists emphasize that it will take years before it
is known whether the fish can survive in their new environment. The only thing
which seems certain is that, whatever the future may hold for the snail darter,
.its place in history is secure as the tiny fish that held up the big dam.
The Tellico Dam in Tennessee, U.S.A., before completion.
with so many essential processes particularly .pollination and
naturally occurring pest control can readily be substituted by other
communities. The genetic composition of such ecosystems may be
crucial for their performance.
Just as many varieties of domesticated plants and animals are
disappearing, so too are many species of wild plants and animals. An
estimated 25,000 plant species and more than a thousand vertebrate
species and subspecies are-threatened with extinction.
These figures do not take account of the inevitable losses of small
animal species particularly invertebrates like molluscs, insects and
corals whose habitats are being destroyed. Indeed estimates that
do attempt to take, this factor into account suggest that from half a
million to a million species will have been made extinct by the endtof
this century. If these species disappeared, the loss to humanity could
be irreparable.
The most serious threat is habitat destruction, which includes:
replacement of the entire habitat by settlements, harbours and other
human constructions, by cropland, grazing land and plantations, and
by mines and quarries; the^ffects of dams (blocking of spawning
migrations, drowning of habitat, alteration of chemical or thermal
conditions); drainage, channelization and flood control; chemical
nutrient and solid waste pollution (domestic, agricultural, industrial,
mining); overextraction of water (for domestic, agricultural and in¬
dustrial purposes); removal of materials (such as vegetation, gravel
and stones) for timber, fuel, construction and so on; dredging and
dumping; overgrazing; and erosion and siltation.
The two other most serious threats to species are overexploitation
and the effects of introduced exotic' species. Exotic species,
which may be introduced deliberately or inadvertently, can have
adverse effects on native species in one or more of the following
ways: competition for space or food; prédation; habitat destruction
or degradation; and transmission of diseases and parasites.
The native species of fresh waters and of islands are particularly
vulnerable to the harmful effects of introduced species. For example,
introduced trout and bass are threatening many species of fishes in
the USA; and introduced goats and rabbits are destroying the
habitats of plants, birds and reptiles in the islands of the Pacific and
' Indian Ocean.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The human
touch
Man has been shaping
his environment
ever since
prehistoric times
by Francesco di Castri
WHEN man is accused of crimes
against Nature, the charges are
invariably the same: pitiless des¬
truction of animal species, disturbance of
the sacrosanct balance of nature, spoliation
of harmonious landscapes, and unscrupu¬
lous exploitation of the genetic wealth of
ecosystems and species.
Sentencing of the prisoner, himself con¬
vinced of his own guilt, has been swift: ex¬
clusion from protected areas in which nature
can be preserved and can develop free from
the pernicious influence of man and to
which man will only be admitted under strict
surveillance.
And yet man has been a factor in the
evolutionary process and an agent of con¬
servation ever since he first appeared in the
biosphere. Things could not have been
otherwise, since it is impossible to stop the
course of evolution in which he is an integral
part; furthermore it is impossible to conceive
of a purely static form of conservation, with
animals as stuffed effigies in museums or
shut away in parks and thus deprived of an
evolutionary potential which has always, in¬
evitably, included the risk of extinction.
Caught up in the whirlwind of demo¬
graphic growth, carried along by the frantic
pace of modern life with scarcely the chance
to fully master his role, man is putting on a
deteriorating performance on the stage of
conservation and the evolution of the
species. But the solution is not for him to
make his apologies and opt out but to make
an even greater impact, fully conscious of
his responsibilities and acting with
dynamism and creativity.
Contrary to what might be thought, the
biological balance did not exist and
20
ecosystems were not absolutely stable, even
before man appeared on earth. In any case,
the concepts of balance and stability are the
least definable and most controversial ones
in ecology: they correspond to a dynamic
and elusive situation, the product of
multitudes of interactions, imbalances and
changing adjustments between species.
In addition to these constant changes, the
biosphere has in its history undergone
gigantic upheavals such as the formation
and subsidence of mountains, continental
drift, volcanic eruptions, and glaciation, in
the course of which millions of species dif¬
ferentiated themselves from one another,
evolved, and then disappeared. It could be
said that just as a city has more dead than
living citizens, so the biosphere has more ex¬
tinct than living species.
In the south of France, for example, there
have been successively tropical and
temperate forests, tundra, pineland and
scrub. The species of trees, herbs and
grasses, vertebrates and insects which live
there today are either relict species, ancient
varieties forced to retreat into these regions
by glaciation or advancing deserts, or
newcomers (especially some of the grasses)
which differentiated themselves in relatively
recent times with the gradual setting in of
the Mediterranean climate during the
Pleistocene Age and then after the last
glaciation.
Furthermore, human action on
ecosystems goes back much further than is
often thought. Even through such simple
activities as hunting and gathering, man
changed the relationship between species,
favouring, intentionally or otherwise, some
at the expense of others. The process
became much more marked with the ap¬
pearance of agriculture: by domesticating
certain animal and plant species such as the
dog, the ox and cereals, man performed the
first conscious act of conservation.
In certain cases, notably in Mediterranean
regions where the climate corresponds to a
recent episode in geological history, the
symbiosis between man and certain species
has been so close that it has influenced their
evolution and their adaptive mechanisms.
Thus several species of grass which grow
spontaneously in the Mediterranean region
have inscribed in their genetic heritage the
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Landscape with the Fall of Icarus,
left, executed by the great Flemish
painter Pieter Breughel the Elder
around 1558, isa meditation on
balance, and the relations between
man and nature. According to the
Greek myth, Icarus, wearing wings
made of feathers and wax flew too
near the sun; the wax melted and
he fell into the sea. In Breughel's
painting, curving terraces, trees,
pastures, water and gleaming city
on the horizon form a harmonious
setting shaped by man, while
Icarus, symbol of excess and
overweening pride, has come to
grief. (All that can be seen of the
drowning Icarus is a leg protruding
from the waves near the ship.)
Meanwhile, ploughman, shepherd,
fisherman and sailor go calmly
about their business, oblivious of
the drama which has just taken
place in the sky above them.
adaptations engendered by their interaction
with domesticated herbivores in so marked a
fashion that in the other areas with the same
climate (California, Chile, South Africa and
southern Australia) they have systematically
replaced local plants which were less used
to cohabitation with man and his animals.
When did man begin to influence the ac¬
tual evolution of ecosystems? Pollen
analysis shows that in the Mediterranean
basin the measurable influence of man as a
modifier of the composition of dominant
species goes back some 7,500 years, while
3,500 years ago deforestation was taking
place on a large scale. Massive deforestation
in China began 4,000 years ago, and in the
humid tropics (especially Asia) dates back to
the beginning of agriculture.
The African savannah, the steppes of
eastern Europe and the pampas of South
America are so immense because of the
discovery of fire, which was used by man to
clear his hunting grounds and thus favoured
the great herbivores. Even the island-edens
of the tropics had been profoundly changed
and degraded before the arrival of the Euro¬
peans.
Can man be condemned for such actions?
Have they really prejudiced the evolution of
the biosphere in the very long term?
Besides, what criteria should be used when
judging the "interests" of the biosphere in
relation to the more immediate requirements
of man? The only possible criterion could be
the maintenance of the diversity of
ecosystems, or even its increase, of the
genetic diversity of animal and plant species
and strains, in order to preserve an evolu¬
tionary potential which would enable
mankind to cope with unforeseeable situa¬
tions, to give himself the maximum number
of options for the future.
Even with such unfavourable evidence it
is possible to argue the case for man. By
making clearings in compact and
homogeneous plant formations, by
cultivating mountain slopes, by bringing
water to certain desert areas, and by con¬
tinually experimenting with new types of far¬
ming and animal husbandry, he has increas¬
ed the variety of the world's landscapes and
multiplied the possibilities of evolution for a
vast number of species.
Some of the world's most varied and har¬
monious landscapes have been shaped by
man: the mosaic of flowering meadows,
woodland and alps found in the mountains
of Europe; the terraces and rice-paddies
which stretch as far as the eye can see in
Java and Nepal; the fields and woodlands of
Normandy and Ireland; the pattern of multi¬
coloured slopes and vine and olive terraces
on the coasts and islands of the Mediterra¬
nean; the high plateaux of the Andes with
their precipitous terraces; the luxuriant
coconut groves of the Pacific islands these
ecosystems in all their diversity have been
encouraged by man.
What would happen if man decided to
stop making an imprint on them? Im-
FRANCESCO DI CASTRI, Italian biologist, is
director of Unesco's Division of Ecological Scien¬
ces. Before joining Unesco in 1971, he was vice-
president of the Scientific Committee on Prob¬
lems of the Environment (SCOPE) of the Interna¬
tional Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU) and
director of the Institute of Ecology of Valdibia
(Chile). He is the author of many published works
and editor of two studies on Mediterranean
ecosystems, Mediterranean Type Ecosystems
and Mediterranean Type Shrublands.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A static approach to
conservation, symbolized by
this flock of stuffed birds in
a museum, may prejudice
the development of species
and thus defeat the very
ends of conservation. If
plants or animals are
confined in living
"museums" where
conditions are not
favourable for their
evolution there is a risk that
their genetic potential will
be impoverished.
Conservation in its fullest
sense means not only
protecting a certain number
of species but managing the
genetic diversity of living
resources throughout the
world.
This Tibetan chequerboard,
used in divination, evokes
the diversity and the unity
of the earth's living
resources. On it a cycle of
twelve years is depicted in
the form of animals
associated with the
elements. The balanced and
long-term management of
the biosphere depends on
maintaining the diversity of
ecosystems and preserving
an evolutionary potential
among living species which
will leave humanity the
maximum number of
options to satisfy its needs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
penetrable undergrowth would proliferate.
Most of the animals and cultivated plants
would not stand up to competition with the
new invaders. The terraces would collapse
for want of upkeep, after erosion on a
massive scale (this is already happening in
certain regions). We would thus lose the
"humanized" landscapes we cherish
because they represent Nature's many
responses to the diverse cultural and
aesthetic conceptions of successive civiliza¬
tions.
Seen from this viewpoint, cultural diversi¬
ty and ecological diversity are simply two
sides of the same coin: what is intrinsically
good for the long-term stability of the
biosphere is also good for the stability of
humanity through the strengthening of
cultural, national and regional identities.
Furthermore, man feels attached to
humanized landscapes, sometimes without
even knowing that they have been humaniz¬
ed. The thousands of tourists who each year
make for the African savannah in search of
"wild life" are actually visiting ecosystems
which the earliest ancestors of modern man
fashioned by certain elementary acts of
transformation: they are in fact in an en¬
vironment shaped by the massive use of fire
in very ancient times.
The true "wilderness", nature in its wild
state, only exists in extreme regions (the
Arctic and to a lesser extent the equatorial
regions) or in marginal areas which have
been preserved largely because of their low
productivity; in other words, in areas which
are not strongly representative of the
biosphere as a whole.
It appears that a moderate degree of ac¬
tion by man has more favourable effects on
ecological and genetic diversity than strict
protectionism.
Plant diversity is greater in central Chile
than in California (although the two regions
are fully comparable climatically) because
the wider variety of human intervention in
Chile has fashioned a mosaic-like landscape.
Besides, the strictly protected Californian
chaparrals (vegetation composed of broad-
leaved evergreen shrubs, bushes and small
trees) form an immense mass of potentially
combustible material and constitute a fire
risk of devastating proportions, much more
serious than in Chile.
At the same time, failure to conserve a
given species is, more often than is generally
realized, due to lack of human intervention
to prevent it from multiplying the prolifera¬
tion of a species may lead to a degradation
of the environment on which it depends for
its food. The concept of active management
is thus implicit in the idea of good conserva¬
tion.
Evidence of man's role in multiplying
genetic diversity is provided by the pro¬
digious diversification of domesticated
animal stock (sheep and cattle in the past,
dogs and fur-producing animals today). Not
so long ago, every region and virtually every
village in Europe and the Mediterranean
basin had its own strain of cows, goats,
horses or sheep, each perfectly adapted to
local needs.
It must be admitted that man has
sometimes behaved poorly as. a conserva¬
tionist. Erosion, salination of soils,
deforestation and the massacre of certain
species are not new phenomena, far from it.
But there are extenuating circumstances to
his guilt: if he has acted badly, is it not
because he was forced to fight to ensure his
own subsistence? It is easy, for individuals,
institutions and countries alike, to show
themselves in the best light and condemn
others who are bound by economic and
social constraints, or to recommend for
others courses of action which will in no
way impinge on their own way of life or
economic progress.
Above all, it has to be admitted that, if the
nature of the problems has not changed, the
context in which they have to be faced is
changing at a dizzying pace. Man's action
has cut time short by causing in the space of
one or two generations certain geological
repercussions: unprecedented rates of
deforestation and soir degradation, and the
introduction into the biosphere of vast quan¬
tities of substances which it is difficult to
recycle and whose long-term effects are im¬
possible to foresee.
The quickening tempo is due to human
demographic growth but also to needs
which have been artificially created by part
of the population. The inevitable outcome is
a progressive simplification which will affect
the biosphere, ecosystems and also
domesticated species and strains a rather
extreme means of increasing both ecological
and economic productivity.
The most serious conservation problem is
thus not that of protecting a certain number
of species (not only animals) from the
danger of extinction, but of reconciling the
imperative of productivity with the need to
maintain in the biosphere a network of cen¬
tres of genetic diversity sufficiently vast and
representative to allow the normal develop¬
ment of a wide range of evolutionary pro¬
cesses. Far from being incompatible, these
two requirements are complementary when
long-term productivity is considered. This
approach to conservation of species
necessarily means that we should conserve
their habitats; the alternative is a reclusive
and static form of conservation, that of the
zoological or biological sanctuary, which
would inevitably lead to evolutionary
degeneration.
However, the possibilities at our disposal
when creating a conservation strategy, as
well as our understanding of the problem,
have considerably increased. We must carry
out wide-ranging fieldwork and laboratory
research for, surprising though it may be,
we still lack most of the basic data required
for the management of biological reserves
on a world scale, such as the minimal size of
reserves in the world's different ecological
regions, the amount of disturbance they can
tolerate, or the ¡deal size of the various
animal and plant populations necessary for a
normal evolution.
With the aid of the all-powerful audio¬
visual media, we must also promote the kind
of environmental education which, where
the conservation of species is concerned,
will transcend emotive, manichaean at¬
titudes, reflect the complexity of problems
in a changing perspective, and take into ac¬
count the development needs of much of
humanity. Above all we must involve in con¬
servation activities those who are most im¬
mediately concerned by themthe local
populations, farmers and stock-breeders.
Anyone needing to be convinced that col- k
lective participation in the conservation of f
Guidelines
for environmental
education
Man's behaviour in the biosphere is condi¬
tioned by his understanding and perception
of the environment and of his own position
in it. The nature of the individual's percep¬
tion of his environment is therefore a key
factor in the establishment and achievement
of environmental goals. The problem facing
those concerned with environmental educa¬
tion is how best to help people at all levels to
make sound social choices and decisions.
"The environment" cannot be treated as a
subject in the same sense as, for example,
mathematics, biology or languages. The
need is to provide education in problem-
solving so that, faced with an environmental
problem, the pupil will quickly come to
understand that sound environmental deci¬
sions depend upon a host of interacting
factors.
Organized by Unesco in co-operation with
the United Nations Environment Pro¬
gramme, the World's first Intergovernmen¬
tal Conference on Environmental Education,
held in Tbilisi, Georgia (USSR), in October
1977, laid down the following guidelines for
environmental education.
Guiding principles environmental edu¬
cation should:
consider the environment in its totality
natural and built, technological and social
(economic, political, cultural-historical,
moral, aesthetic);
be a continuous lifelong process, beginn¬
ing at the pre-school level and continuing
through all formal and nonformal stages;
be interdisciplinary in its approach,
drawing on the specific content of each
discipline in making possible a holistic and
balanced perspective;
examine major environmental issues from
local, national, regional and international
points of view so that students receive in¬
sights into environmental conditions in other
geographical areas;
focus on current and potential en¬
vironmental situations while taking into ac¬
count the historical perspective;
promote the value and necessity of local,
national and international cooperation in the
prevention and solution of environmental
problems;
explicitly consider environmental aspects
in plans for development and growth;
enable learners to have a role in planning
their learning experiences and provide an
opportunity for making decisions and accep¬
ting their consequences;
relate environmental sensitivity,
knowledge, problem-solving skills and
values clarification to every age, but with
special emphasis on environmental sensitivi¬
ty to the learner's own community in early
years;
help learners discover the symptoms and
real causes of environmental problems;
emphasize the complexity of environmen¬
tal problems and thus the need to develop
critical thinking and problem-solving ski/Is;
utilize diverse learning environments anda
broad array of educational approaches to
teaching//earning about and from the en¬
vironment with due stress on practical ac¬
tivities and first-hand experience.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
species is something more than a Utopian
} idea has only to visit Mapimi and La Michilia
in Mexico's Durango State. There the local
farmers, once great hunters of the giant
desert tortoise and the white-tailed deer,
have now become ardent conservationists.
The change was brought about by convic¬
tion, not coercion. It is the product of a new
understanding which has been established
between the farmers, university research
workers and the local authorities, and above
all it is due to the fact that they have been
shown, through experiments carried out on
the spot, other development possibilities
(agro-industries) which are more profitable
than hunting or the spoliation of natural
resources.
Mapimi and La Michilia are two units in
the international network of biosphere
reserves created as part of Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) programme. A
wide range of objectives are aimed at in the
biosphere reserves: the conservation of sites
representative of the world's biogeographic
regions, research (into ecological processes
of conservation and development alter¬
natives), education, demonstration and in¬
formation; all these activities are welded
together by the unifying force generated by
the participation of local populations,
researchers from the country in which the
biosphere is situated and elsewhere, and
planners.
The problem of the conservation of
species and ecosystems is extremely urgent.
Immediate action is called for, especially in
terms of legislation appropriate for each
country. Nevertheless, the solution does not
lie in restrictive legislation, still less in the
erection of barbed wire fences around
parks.
A new population explosion, new cases of
famine, the outbreak of political distur-
. bances would mean that the biggest of
these parks, these major tourist centres,
would be swept away by the populations
which are excluded from these protected
areas and in many cases do not understand
why they are there. Presenting them with
simple and realistic development alter¬
natives, strengthening their feeling of "in¬
volvement" through more active participa¬
tion in decision-making these are conser¬
vation measures which are effective where
prohibitions and moral judgements are not.
Instead of seeing ourselves as her con¬
querors or protectors, we must learn to
respect Nature as an ally in the evolutionary
process we are, together, destined to
experience.
B Francesco di Castri
Above, a yoke of oxen draw a plough in Ecuador. Below, replanting young rice
shoots in an Indian paddy field. Man has been shaping his environment for longer
than is often realized, notably since the appearance of agriculture, and became a
conservationist when he domesticated animals and plants such as the ox and rice.
By developing different types of cultivation and strains of livestock, farmers,
multiplied the evolutionary possibilities of many species.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Our evolutionary responsibility
by Sir Otto Frankel
This map indicates regions of the world
described by the Soviet plant geneticist N.I.
Vavilov as "centres of genetic diversity",
that is to say areas where domesticated
plants originated and diversified and where
their primitive progenitors and wild
relatives are still to ba found. Many crop
varieties of traditional agriculture are today
in danger of extinction as they are replaced
by modern strains developed for high yield
and uniformity. The wild species are
threatened by increasing destruction of
their habitats. Thus an important source of
potential evolutionary material, which may
be vital to man's survival in a changing
world, will disappear unless positive action
is taken to organize its protection.
Map im&Tmitonai Board lor Pieni Genetic Resource«, FAO, Rome
THE impact of genetics on society dates
back to the origins of agriculture.
Around 8000 BC our ingenious
ancestors discovered that the variations
which transformed wild plants into crops
could be passed through the seed to the
next generation. Cultivation led to settled
civilization and thus to the origins of our
society. The first agricultural revolution was
the greatest contribution of genetics to
society during the first 10,000 years.
From the areas where plants and animals
were domesticated, they fanned out, diver¬
sifying in the different environments and
cultures to which they migrated, and in
which they continued to evolve and diversify
under the impact of changing technological
economic and cultural conditions. When the
application of science to agriculture, and
especially the advent of scientific plant
breeding, ushered in the second agricultural
revolution, modern varieties, bred for high
production and uniformity, absorbed only a
small proportion . of the ancient stores of
variation.
Today the same, or closely related,
varieties are grown in many parts of the
world. Even in the less developed countries
uniform modern cultivars are rapidly replac¬
ing the traditional or "primitive" varieties
which were still in general use even 25 years
ago. The "green revolution" has greatly in¬
tensified this process in some Asian coun¬
tries. No doubt thj dramatic improvement
of food production has saved mankind from
extensive starvation, at least for the time be¬
ing; but it also has deprived the world of
valuable genetic resources, and much of
what remains is now acutely threatened.
Yet the world needs these genetic
resources more than ever before. The extent
and rapidity of technological and social
change make demands for genetic adapta¬
tion which are as diverse as they are un¬
predictable. They are intensified by the
population explosion and the agricultural
revolution in vast areas previously scarcely
touched by modern developments. The
genetic resources now available are,
foreseeably, the only ones we shall have
available at least for the next few decades.
But even if there is a chance that new
methods of genetic engineering will become
widely applicable in the near future, at this
stage the preservation of what we know and
have seems a responsible measure of evolu¬
tionary insurance.
Genetic conservation has a time scale of
concern, which extends from a day or a year
when there is no need (or plan) for conser¬
vation, to infinity (see table page 27). But
the time scale of concern must not be con¬
fused with the time of action, which clearly
is now.
Let us briefly consider the time scale of
concern for domesticated plants and
wildlife. Neither our pre-agricultural i
ancestor, nor the peasant farmer who sue- 1
SIR OTTO FRANKEL, FRS, is a distinguished
plant geneticist who has been since 1966 Senior
Research Fellow, Division of Plant Industry, Com¬
monwealth Scientific and Industrial Research
Organization at Canberra, Australia. A former
consultant with the United Nations Food and
Agriculture Organization (FAO), he was instru¬
mental in developing FAO's programme of con¬
servation of plant genetic resources. He has
published many articles in scientific journals and
is joint editor of Genetic Resources in Plants:
Their Exploration and Conservation (1970) and of
Crop Genetic Resources for Today and Tomorrow
(1975). He is a Fellow of the World Academy of
Art and Science. This article is based on a paper
presented by the author at the Xlllth International
Congress of Genetics.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
> ceeded him had cause for concern beyond
the next meal or the next crop, the former
because he used a pool of great species
diversity, the latter a pool of self-renewing
intra-specific diversity. This came to an end
with the advent of scientific selection. To¬
day's concern is with preserving and
broadening the genetic base. The time
perspective for gene pool conservation
might be the next 50 or 100 yearswhich is
merely an acknowledgment of the un¬
paralleled technological transience of our
age; we cannot foresee even what kinds of
crops will be used at that time.
For wildlife conservation the position is
altogether different. Concern for its preser¬
vation is new, a consequence of our
destructive age. Nature conservation is
fighting for reserves and for legal recogni¬
tion. The sights often are set for the short
term, although perpetuity is its ultimate ob¬
jective. Genetic wildlife conservation makes
sense only in terms of an evolutionary time
scale. Its sights must reach into the distant
future.
In this context genetics has social respon¬
sibilities in two directions: first, to col¬
laborate in planning the biological system of
conservation so as to establish the highest
possible evolutionary potential; second, to
help in establishing an evolutionary ethic, as
Plant geneticists draw on
the genetic resources of
primitive plant species for
the development of high
performance modern crop
strains. Unfortunately, the
success of these new
strains is leading to the
extinction of the very
species from which they
were derived. Graph
shows the decline in the
percentage of primitive
strains in the Greek
wheat crop over the past
forty years. Left, a
selection of ears of wheat
from a primitive crop in
Afghanistan.
Graph from Survey of crop genetic
resources in their centres of
diversity: First report, FAO/IBP
Photo © Pierre Quéméré, Institut Supérieur Agricole, Beauvais, France
part of our social ethics, which will make it
acceptable and indeed inevitable for man to
regard the continuing existence of other
species as an integral part of his own ex¬
istence. This demands continuing evolution.
In the advanced varieties of modern
agriculture the genetic base is greatly nar¬
rowed by comparison with the primitive
varieties from which they are descended.
The great genetic diversity to be found in
the traditional stocks of peasant agriculture
was first emphasized by N.I. Vavilov half a
century ago; and it is thanks to him and his
colleagues that we came to recognize "cen¬
tres of genetic diversity", situated in Asia,
Latin America and Africa, where
domesticated plants originated (or migrated)
and diversified, and where to this day many
of the presumed progenitors and other wild
or weed relatives of crop species can be
found. Wild and . primitive gene pools,
together with induced mutations, constitute
the genetic resources available for the adap¬
tations of present-day cultivars, or for in¬
itiating new and potentially valuable
pathways of crop evolution.
26
The most important genetic resources of
economic plants are the indigenous popula¬
tions of traditional agriculture. They are also
in the most immediate danger of extinction
through replacement by modern cultivars.
The wild relatives are not nearly as exposed,
but there are exceptions. Forest species can
be virtually wiped out through large-scale
land clearing for agriculture or for replanting
with exotics. The progenitors of various
mediterranean vegetable crops are threaten¬
ed by intensification of land use and wild
fruit tree species are in jeopardy in Malaysia.
Foresters urgently call for gene pool conser¬
vation of threatened communities and other
wild plants of economic significance could
be similarly protected within a framework of
ecosystem conservation.
It is usually argued that the conservation
of wild biota is justified because they are
useful to man, and that long term conserva¬
tion is feasible only in a state of continuing
evolution. But there is also the question of
whether continuing evolution itself has an
intrinsic value. Before attempting an answer
the basis of such a value judgment must be
clarified.
The breeding of cattle for specific
qualities, weight or milk yield for
example, leads inevitably to the
gradual disappearance of certain
strains whose characteristics are less
valued at a given time than those of
other breeds. Of the 145 indigenous
cattle breeds of Europe and the
Mediterranean region, no less than 115
are today threatened with extinction.
In France steps are being taken to
protect the black and white Brittany
dairy cow (above left), which in recent
years has gradually been ousted by
new strains obtained by repeated
crossing with American Holsteins.
Concervation measures are also being
taken to protect the donkey of Poitou
(above), traditional progenitor in
France of sturdy mules, now under
threat of extinction as a result of the
development of modern means of
transportation.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
THE TIME SCALE OF CONCERN
Period Operator Objective Time scale
Wild-life to 8,000 BC hunter-gatherer next meal 1 day
Domesticated to 1850 AD
plants
from 1850
from 1900
"primitive" or
"traditional"
peasant farmer
plant breeder
crop evolutionist
the next crop
the next variety
to broaden the
genetic base
1 year
10 years
100 years
Wildlife today genetical
conservationist
politician
dynamic wildlife
conservation
current public
interest
10,000 years +
next election
For most people the word "microbe" spells disease; but, in fact, microbes are essential to
human life since they help the body to digest food and to synthesize important vitamins.
Many microbian strains, like the Aspergillus niger (magnified photo below), are used in
industrial processes and constitute an important genetic resource. In 1962, Unesco
established the International Cell Research Organization (ICRO) which is carrying out
microbiology research and housing collections of cultures of micro-organisms in a regional
network of microbiological resources centres in Africa, Latin America, the Caribbean region
and the Arab States.
This basis can only be an anthropocentric
one; any other basis, such as "the right to
life," or "the sacredness of nature," is
mysticism and hence outside scientific
reasoning. But there is another and wholly
materialistic reason. Even now, terrestrial
ecosystems which have not been substan¬
tially modified by human impact are few and
far between. In another century there may
be none. It follows that if some natural com¬
munities are to be preserved for any reason
whatsoever, this can be done only at the will
of man.
The question should be re-phrased more
precisely: has the continuing evolution of
wild species a value for man other than an
utilitarian one? To make an answer possible,
the issue must be defined more closely.
What is at stake is not the extinction of in¬
dividual species, though the current rate of
loss in many parts of the world is high and
accelerating. This may not be without prece¬
dent in evolutionary history. But what is
without precedent is the predictable
destruction of habitats for what remains of
the earth's natural and semi-natural com¬
munities and of most of the species they in¬
clude. Without deliberate protection few of
these communities will have a chance of sur¬
vival; nor does the shrinkage of undisturbed
habitats offer a promise of evolutionary
replacement.
This is a situation outside past experience,
a confrontation between man and other
biota which in the short space of two or
three generations could imperil a large pro¬
portion of the wild species that now remain.
Man would direct the evolution of biota that
are of use to him, and the only ones retain¬
ing their evolutionary independence would
be those he is unable to suppress. This is
heavily overdrawn; but the tendency is there
to see.
Even if we reject the prospect of becom¬
ing the arbiters of evolution, can we assume
that future generations will share our con¬
cern?
If one thing about the future is certain it is
that cultural, technological, economic, and
possibly biological man a century or two
from now will differ more greatly from us
than we differ from the early agricultural set¬
tlers. Future man is more unknown and un¬
predictable than at any time in history.
Hence at this point of decision-making it
may be our evolutionary responsibility to
keep evolutionary options open so far as we
can without undue deprivations for those
least able to bear them. This is a modest
precept, but as much as is at all likely to be
socially acceptable at this time. It may grow
into an evolutionary ethic if and when men
come to regard other species as an essential
part of their own existence.
Otto Frankel
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
STRATEGY.
Living on
borrowed
time
Humanity is rapidly
overdrawing its
account with nature
In the world's tropical rain forests shifting cultivation using the "slash and burn" technique
has been successfully employed for thousands of years. A small section of forest is felled,
the trees and undergrowth are burned (photo above) and crops are planted in the ash. When
the areas involved are small and the period of fallow is long enough to allow the forest to
return to the site, the system works well; but, with populations growing, the fallow periods
shorten and the soil has no chance to recuperate. Tropical rain forests are an invaluable
resource and a reservoir of genetic diversity, but, today, eleven million hectares a year, or
twenty hectares a minute, are being felled or burned for agriculture. At this rate all of this
type of forest will have disappeared within 85 years.
THE current world energy crisis has
brought home forcibly to us all that
certain of the earth's resources, such
as oil and coal, are non-renewable and
sooner or later will be completely exhausted.
Luckily for humanity, however, resources
such as corn, rice and other cereals, cattle,
fish and timber renew themselves and can
be regularly cropped to provide the food,
clothing and shelter essential to human sur¬
vival.
What is not perhaps so clearly realized is
that these resources are renewable only to
the extent that their use is rationally planned
and managed. There are limits to the extent
to which we can draw on these resources
which, if exceeded, will destroy their capaci¬
ty for renewal. Making use of resources in a
manner which can be sustained indefinitely
is rather like living on interest while main¬
taining capital. Unfortunately, most current
utilization of aquatic animals, of the wild
plants and animals of the land, of forests
and of grazing lands is not sustainable.
On average, fish and other aquatic
animals account for 6% of the total protein
and 17 % of the animal protein in the human
diet. If this seems small, it should be
remembered that on a world basis most
(65%) protein comes from plants chiefly
cereals, beans and peas, nuts and oilseeds.
Meat accounts for 16% and milk products
for 9.5% of the average total protein intake.
These averages conceal substantial dif¬
ferences between and within countries.
Thirty-two countries get 34% or more of
their animal protein from seafood, and
another 11 countries consume double the
world average for seafood consumption.
Aquatic animals are also important for
trade. There are no world figures for
domestic trade, but it is clear from export
values alone that trade in seafood is both
substantial and growing fast. In 1978 ex-
28
ports of fish and fishery products reached
$10.8 thousand million, an increase of 15%
over the previous year.
Because much utilization of fisheries is
not sustainable, their contribution to na¬
tional diets and incomes is likely to diminish.
The result of past and present overfishing is
that the annual world marine catch is 15-20
million tonnes (or about 20%-24%) lower
than it might otherwise have been, and at
least 25 of the world's most valuable
fisheries are seriously depleted.
The consequences of such overexploita-
tion can be illustrated from the northwest
Atlantic, where due to overfishing in the late
1960s cod catches are still only a third of
their estimated potential. The drops in cod,
herring and haddock catches (all caused by
overfishing) could not be compensated by
increased catches of capelin and mackerel;
and the total catch of the fishery as a whole
has declined from 4.3 million tonnes in 1970
to 3.5 million tonnes in 1976.
It can no longer be assumed that depleted
stocks will recover to their full potential,
because: the spawning fishes and juveniles
may continue to be caught by industrial
fisheries (which take fish for conversion to
animal feed); ecosystem dynamics can
change and another species may take over
because the depleted species can no longer
compete effectively with it; and habitats
essential for spawning or as nurseries may
be degraded or destroyed.
Overfishing is the main threat to marine
living resources and a significant threat to
freshwater ones. It occurs locally in all
regions, but it is generally most pronounced
in regions dominated by developed
countries.
Five of the eight regions with most stocks
that are depleted are developed (northwest
Atlantic, northeast Atlantic, Mediterranean,
northwest Pacific, northeast Pacific). Of the
remaining three, two (eastern central Atlan
tic and southeast Atlantic) are dominated by
developed country fishing fleets: France,
Japan, Poland, Spain, USSR, South
Africawith Cuba and the Republic of
Korea operating the only major developing
country fleets. The only developing region
dominated by developing country fleets is
the southeast Pacific, where most of the
fishing is done by Peru and Chile.
As well as depleting many fish and a few
mollusc stocks, overfishing has almost ex¬
tinguished entire species of whales, sea
cows and sea turtles. Many aquatic animal
groups are also under pressure because of
accidental overexploitation or "incidental
take".
The incidental capture and killing of non-
target animals in the course of hunting or
fishing for other species is one of the more
destructive yet neglected problems of
aquatic living resource management. It is
not only highly wasteful, destroying an
estimated 7 million tonnes of fish every year,
it also threatens the survival of several sea
turtle species, notably the Kemp's ridley tur¬
tle which has been reduced almost to extinc¬
tion. A million seabirds are killed accidentally
in nets every year; and more cetaceans,
notably dolphins and porpoises, are taken
incidentally than deliberately.
Wildlife is an important subsistence
resource in developing countries and an im¬
portant recreational resource in both
developed and developing countries. Many
wild plants and animals of the land are an
important renewable resource and source of
food, particularly for rural communities in
developing countries. In parts of Ghana,
Zaïre and other countries in west and central
Africa, for example, up to three-quarters of
the animal protein comes from wild animals.
The nutritional importance of wild animals
and plants for large numbers of people is in¬
variably underestimated (and often ignor-
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
ed), largely because many of the more fre¬
quently eaten plants and animals (for exam¬
ple, vetches and porcupines) seldom feature
in the diets of nutritionists and are harvested
in areas far from the scrutiny of statisticians.
This is unfortunate for were the true nutri¬
tional value and the use made of wild plants
and animals appreciated by governments
they might be more ready to encourage
these resources to be managed sustainably
and to take steps to retain their habitats.
Wild animals and plants also provide a
significant, and sometimes the Only, source
of income for rural communities. In Canada,
for example, the wild fur trade helps support
40,000 trappers, who in the 1975-1976
season caught $25 million worth of pelts,
mostly from beaver, muskrat, lynx, seal,
mink and fox. By comparison in the same
season, farms produced $17 million worth
of furs, 99% being mink. World trade in
wildlife and wildlife products has become
big business: in 1975 the USA alone im¬
ported more than $1,000 million of wildlife
products.
International trade has become a threat to
many species as well-organized commercial
enterprises attempt to supply a vastly ex¬
panded market (mainly industrialized coun¬
tries) with increasingly scarce "commo¬
dities" taken from the wild (mainly in
developing countries):
hides and skins for the luxury fur and
leather industry; exotic meat and fish for
luxury food; a wide range of other animal
and plant products for pharmaceuticals,
perfumes, cosmetics, aphrodisiacs,
decoration, souvenirs or investment;
specimens for natural history museums;
live plants for horticulture; live animals
for the pet trade, zoos and menageries,
aquaria and other collections; and for the
testing of new chemical products and for
biomedical research.
Most of the trade is openly advertised, but
a significant part of it takes place illegally,
often through channels and by methods not
unlike those of the drug traffic. The impact
of this trade on many species and eco¬
systems is now serious.
For example, overexploitation threatens
almost 40% of all vertebrate species in
danger of extinction, and is the most serious
of the threats faced by reptiles. Because of
the difficulty of securing supplies, world
trade in crocodilian hides has dropped from
an estimated 10 million hides to 2 million.
Finally, wildlife is a major resource base
for recreation and tourism. Tourism, largely
based on wildlife, is among Kenya's top
three foreign exchange earners. In Canada
11% of the population hold hunting
licences; in the USA 8% hold hunting
licences and 13% hold fishing licences; and
in Sweden from 12% to 18% hold fishing
licences.
Many more people enjoy simply looking at
wildlife: in the USA there are about 7 million
birdwatchers, 4.5 million wildlife photo¬
graphers, and almost 27 million nature
hikers. For a great many people, too, wildlife
is of great symbolic, ritual and cultural im¬
portance, enriching their lives emotionally
and spiritually.
Forests and woodlands provide a rich
variety of goods, useful to affluent industrial
and poor rural communities alike; timber,
sawnwood and panels for construction,
walls, doors, shuttering and furniture;
pulpwood for pulp, paper, cartons and
rayon; poles, posts, mining timbers and
railway track sleepers; fuelwood; fodder,
fruits, game meat, honey, pharmaceuticals,
fibres, resins, gums, dyes, skins, waxes and
oils; beauty, amenity and recreation.
Forests have unquestioned importance
for industry and commerce. The value of the
annual world production of forest products
exceeds $115,500 million, and international
trade is worth about $40,000 million a year.
Thirty countries (eight of them developing
countries) each earn more than $100 million
a year from exports of forest productsand
five of these each earn more than $1,000
million a year.
In developing countries the heaviest de¬
mand on forests and woodlands is for fuel
and as a site for shifting cultivation. More
than 1,500 million people in developing
countries depend on wood for cooking and
keeping warm. Their annual consumption of
wood is estimated to be more than 1,000
million m3, well over 80% of developing
countries' total wood use (excluding ex¬
ports). In Africa the contribution of trees to
total energy use is as high as 58%; in
Southeast Asia and Latin America it is 42%
and 20% respectively.
The effect of such intense demand is to
denude the land of wood over wide areas.
Around one fishing centre in the Sahel
region of Africa, where the drying of 40,000
tonnes of fish consumes 130,000 tonnes of
wood every year, deforestation extends as
far away as 100 km.
Fuelwood is now so scarce in the Gambia
that gathering it takes 360 woman days a
year per family. Even when firewood is
available for sale, it is often beyond the
budgets of poor householders. In the
highlands of the Republic of Korea cooking
and heating can cost up to 15% of the
household budget; and in the poorer parts
of the Andean Sierra and the Sahel it can be
as high as 25%. Consequently many
families are forced to do without.
Permanent pastures (land used for 5 years
or more for herbaceous forage crops,
whether cultivated or wild) are the most ex¬
tensive land-use type in the worldoccupy¬
ing 30 million km2, or 23% of the earth's
land surface.
Permanent pastures and other grazing
land are generally in areas of low and ir¬
regular rainfall and are usually unsuitable for
crops without intensive capital investment.
Their productivity is generally low, ranging
from 1 hectare supporting 3-5 animal units
on fertile, well-managed pastures in central
Europe to 50-60 hectares to support 1 animal
unit in Saudi Arabia.
Nonetheless, grazing lands and forage
support most of the world's 3,000 million
head of domesticated grazing animals, and
hence most of the world's production of
meat and milk.
Unfortunately, mismanagement of graz¬
ing lands is widespread. Overstocking has
severely degraded grazing lands in Africa's
Sahelian and Sudanian zones. In parts of
North Africa, the Mediterranean and the
Near East, it is a major contributor to deser¬
tification. In many areas farmers are moving
onto land that is marginal for agriculture,
thereby displacing pastoralists onto land
that is marginal for livestock rearing.
Overstocking together with uncontrolled
grazing is also a serious problem in moun¬
tain areas, such as the Himalaya and the
Andes. There, too many improperly tended
animals remove both trees and grass
coverwhich is often very poor, both as
forage and for soil protection and erosion
accelerates.
Photo © Jean-Loup Charmet, Bibliothèque des Arts Décoratifs, Paris
Noah's Ark, an engraving based on a drawing in a 12th-century manuscript.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Echium pininana. This spectacular arborescent species,
known in only three localities in the north-east of La
Palma, one of the Canary Islands, grows on stony hill¬
sides and in openings In the laurel forest, on basalt rocks.
It is threatened by habitat deterioration and uproot¬
ing by horticultural collectors.
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
Medusagyne oppositofolia. First discovered in 1903, this
plant was not seen again until 1970 when ¡t was re¬
discovered in a different locality. Confined to the island
of Mahé in the Seychelles.
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
Primula palinuri Petagna. A rare species found on the
Tyrrhenian coasts of Italy between Cape Palinuro and
Cape Scalea. May come under threat from increasing
tourism.
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
Streblorrhiza speciosa. Now extinct, this plant once
flowered on Philip Island in the Pacific Ocean. Goats,
pigs and rabbits introduced to the island destroyed the
species. ,
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
A million species
threatened
with extinction
30
HAWAIIAN DUCK or KOLOA, Anas platyrhynchos
wyvilliana. Rare species now found on only two islands in
the Hawaiian group. Hunting, destruction of nests by in¬
troduced predators such as rats, cats and mongoose as
well as the drainage of ponds and reclamation of marshes
have contributed to its decline.
Drawing J. Kuhn © W.W.F., Switzerland
ATTWATER'S PRAIRIE CHICKEN, Tympanuchus
cupido attwateri. A very rare and endangered species
found in a few isolated areas in south-eastern Texas.
Destruction of habitat, in particular the ploughing up of
prairieland is the chief cause of the decline of the species
which is highly specialized and unable to adapt to the
changes taking place.
Drawing Paul Barruel © W.W.F., Switzerland
JAPANESE CRESTED IBIS, Nipponia nippon. Com¬
mon throughout Japan up to 80 years ago, is now very
rare and barely maintaining its numbers. Almost exter¬
minated by man between 1870 and 1890. Deforestation
since 1940 has led to the extermination of all but a few
birds.
Drawing Paul Barruel © W.W.F., Switzerland
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Orothamnus zeyheri. This species of marsh rose is to be
found in South Africa. Although populations have
increased somewhat over the past ten years, the marsh
rose is still under threat from fungal parasites, poor polli¬
nation, rats, invasion of habitat by other species and the
construction of a large dam.
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
Elliottia racemosa. Confined to a few isolated sites in eas¬
tern and southern Georgia, this woodland species is
threatened by habitat destruction through timber exploi¬
tation and woodland clearance for agriculture.
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
I.U.C.N.'s Red Data Book, the authoritative source of information
on the world's threatened vertebrate animals, lists more than a
thousand species and sub-species known to be threatened with
extinction: 400 birds, 305 mammals, 193 types of fish and 138
amphibians and reptiles. As for plants, I.U.C.N.'s Threatened
Plants Committee estimates that at least 25,000 species are now
endangered. Assessments that take into account the lower plants,
such as mosses, liverworts, fungi, lichens and seaweeds, and
invertebrate animals suggest that between half a million and a
million species will become extinct by the end of the century. On
these pages we present a selection of plant and animal species
now under threat.
MONKEY-EATING EAGLE IPithecophaga ¡efíeryil.
Confined to the islands of Mindanao and Luzon, in the
Philippines, this species is very rare (probably less than
100 birds) and decreasing. Decline due mainly to local de¬
mand for stuffed speciments for home decoration and
excessive trapping for sale to zoos. Does not breed in
captivity.
Drawing Paul Barruel © WWF, Switzerland
From top: PINE BARRENS TREE FROG, Hyla ander-
soni; has become rare owing to habitat destruction.
ILLINOIS CHORUS FROG, Pseudacris strecken Uli-
noensis; little known species, but seen in abundance dur¬
ing the breeding season. VEGAS VALLEY LEOPARD
FROG, Rana pip/ens fisheri; the last known specimens
were collected in 1942.
Drawings Urs Woy © W.W.F., Switzerland
iris lortetii Barbey. Only 4 small populations known in
Israel and south-east Lebanon. Threatened by commer¬
cial exploitation, picking and habitat destruction by
afforestation.
Drawing Mary Grierson © W.W.F., Switzerland
HAWKSBILL TURTLE, Eretmochelys imbricata. Thinly
scattered throughout the Atlantic, Pacific and Indian
Oceans, the Gulf of Mexico and the Caribbean, but has
disappeared from the Mediterranean. Threatened with
extinction through over-exploitation for its tortoiseshell.
Drawing Urs Woy © W.W.F., Switzerland
CHINA ALLIGATOR, Alligator sinensis. May already be
extinct. Formerly widespread in eastern China and the
lower Yangtze Valley, it is exterminated as vermin and for
its leather and meat.
Drawing Urs Woy © W.W.F., Switzerland
From top: KERN CANYON SLENDER SALA¬
MANDER, Batrachoseps simatus; LIMESTONE
SALAMANDER, Hydromantes brunus; SANTA CRUZ
LONG-TOED SALAMANDER. Ambystoma macro-
dactylum croceum. Known only in California, these three
species are threatened mainly through destruction of
their habitats. n -|
Drawings © W.W.F., Switzerland O I
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
MANIPUR BROW-ANTLERED DEER or SANGAI, Cervus eldi
eldi. Currently one of the rarest mammals in the world, it is confined
to a wetland area south of Logtak Lake, Manipur, India. By 1975,
ruthless hunting had reduced the population to a mere 14 head.
Drawing Helmut Dlller © W.W. F., Switzerland
SIBERIAN TIGER, Panthera tigris altaica.
Confined to isolated populations in south¬
east Siberia, north-east China and north¬
east Korea, its decline has been due to
over-hunting for its fur and also its bones,
flesh and blood to which medicinal proper¬
ties are attributed.
Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
BLUE WHALE, Balaenoptera musculus.
The decline of the species dates from the
invention of the harpoon gun and the
steam whaling ship in the 1860s. By 1963,
stocks in the Antarctic had declined to a
mere 4,000. Over the last 30 years other
stocks in the world's oceans have been
seriously depleted.
Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
INDIAN WILD ASS or GHOR-KHAR. Equus hemionus
khur. Confined to the Little Rann and possibly the Great
Rann of Kutch regions, the species has been reduced to a
few hundred. Disease, deterioration of habitat, a series of
droughts and human intrusion are among the causes of
this decline. Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
MOUNTAIN TAPIR, Tapirus pinchaque. Occurring principally in
the high Colombian Cordilleras and parts of the eastern equatorial
Andes, the species is threatened mainly by habitat modification due
to stock grazing.
Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
GIANT OTTER,' Pteronura brasiliensis. The most en¬
dangered species of Amazonian mammal, its population
size has been seriously reduced by over hunting.
Relatively easy to hunt, its fur commands a high price.
Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
32
HAITIAN SOLENODON, Solenodon paradoxus. Con¬
fined to parts of the Dominican Republic, it is threatened
by land development, deforestation and pressures
created by a rapidly rising human population as well as
prédation by dogs.
Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
AYE-AYE, Daubentonia madagascariensis. The sole sur¬
viving representative of the Daubentoniidae family, the
Aye-aye occurs in a special reserve in Madagascar. It re¬
quires a forest habitat of tall trees and its decline is largely
due to the effects of deforestation.
Drawing Helmut Diller © W.W.F., Switzerland
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
"WORLD STRATEGY-
The global
commons
Two fishing boats at sea. An engraving by the Japanese artist Hokusai (1760-1849)
Acommons is a tract of land or water
owned or used jointly by the mem¬
bers of a community. The global
commons includes those parts of the earth's
surface beyond national jurisdictions
notably the open ocean and the living
resources found there or held in common
notably the atmosphere. The only land
mass that may be regarded as part of the
global commons is Antarctica, although
several countries have claimed parts of it.
Much of the open ocean remains frontier
country in which people can exploit living
resources as they please as long as they
have the technology to do so. While the
open ocean is not as biologically rich as con¬
tinental shelf areas, it includes unique
ecosystems and provides some (and in some
cases all) of the critical habitats of several
culturally and economically important
groups of animals, notably whales and
tunas.
Species that are confined to the open
ocean should be regarded as the common
resource of all humanity; species that move
between the open ocean and waters under
national jurisdiction are shared resources.
Special provision for the conservation of
both groups of species is therefore needed,
but no satisfactory mechanism exists.
Living resource exploitation in the open
ocean is regulated only in the case of two
groups of species: tunas and whales. There
is no protection of the habitats of open
ocean species and hitherto none has been
needed. However, with the advent of deep
sea mining and the increasingly intensive
use of ocean space generally, protection is
now required. The designation by the Inter¬
national Whaling Commission (IWO- of an
Indian Ocean Sanctuary in which all com¬
mercial whaling is prohibited, while an en¬
couraging step forward, needs to be match¬
ed by international measures to protect the
habitats of the whales, dolphins and por¬
poises in that area.
Means of ensuring the conservation of
open ocean species and ecosystems
particularly ecosystems supporting the
feeding grounds of whales, salmon, and so
on, the spawning grounds of tuna, unique
areas and areas of unusual species diversity
should be devised, promoted and adopted.
An appropriate international organization
should prepare a discussion document,
possibly as a prelude to an expert consulta¬
tion, on priority species and ecosystems and
on ways and means of conserving them.
These might include the introduction of
more effective measures to regulate ex¬
ploitation and the establishment of sanc¬
tuaries where the habitats of cetaceans and
other marine creatures are protected and ex¬
ploitation is prohibited.
The International Whaling Commission
has imposed a moratorium on the taking,
killing, or treating of whales, except minke
whales, by factory ships or whale catchers
attached to factory ships. The moratorium
should be extended to all commercial whal¬
ing until:
the consequences for the ecosystems
concerned of removing large portions of
the whales' populations, and such
populations' capacity for recovery, can
be predicted;
permitted levels of exploitation are safe, ,.
and an effective mechanism exists for r
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Antarctica, the ice-covered
continent which lies concentrically
about the South Pole, is the only
land mass that can be considered
as forming part of the global
commons. Under the Antarctic
Treaty, signed in 1959 by twelve
nations and having effect for 30
years, the area was declared a
demilitarized zone and preserved
for scientific research. A
convention regulating the taking of
living resources from the Southern
Ocean, the sea that surrounds
Antarctica, is now being
negotiated. Below, the British
Antarctic Survey station on
Adelaide Island some 100 km south
of the Antarctic Circle.
iV detecting and correcting mistakes in the
' management of any stock;
member nations of the IWC are no
longer purchasing whale products from,
or transferring whaling technology and
equipment to, or otherwise supporting,
non-member nations, or pirate whaling
ships.
The dumping of wastes at sea is regulated
by the Convention on the Prevention of
Marine Pollution by Dumping of Wastes and
Other Matter and by regional conventions
for which it provides the framework. Those
States not yet party to this convention are
urged to join it.
It is also important to control the effects
of deep sea mining (including oil exploita¬
tion); for this to be done it is necessary to
learn what those effects are. Accordingly,
an internationally agreed area should be
established, in which deep sea mining is pro¬
hibited, as a baseline area to aid the long
term evaluation of the effects of deep sea
mining.
In addition, all nations engaged in, or con¬
sidering, deep sea mining activities or any
other activities with currently unpredictable
effects on open ocean ecosystems should:
precede commercial mining operations
or similar activities by commissioning a
comprehensive ecological survey to
determine the impact of such activities;
designate appropriate areas of the deep
sea bed as baseline reference and
resource zones in which no mining or
other significant disturbance will be
allowed, ensuring that the size and
shape of each area is such that its stabili¬
ty will be maintained;
establish guidelines for scientific
research to ensure minimum disruption
of the natural state of such areas, and
provide for full exchange of information
on the results of research.
The behaviour of the atmosphere, like
that of the ocean, is indifferent to political
boundaries. Impacts on the atmosphere in
one country can affect the living resources
of other countries, both directly and by
altering climate.
Such impacts are increasing. Acid rain
caused by excessive emissions of sulphur
dioxide, mainly in Europe and North
America, has reduced the productivity of
many lakes, rivers and forests in countries
other than the sources of the pollution.
The accumulation in the atmosphere of
other gases such as carbon tetrachloride
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
and methylchloroform (used in industrial
solvents), nitrous oxides from the decom¬
position of nitrogen compounds, the
chlorofluoromethanes (used in refrigerators,
air conditioners and aerosol sprays) and car¬
bon dioxide is potentially a still more
serious problem because of its possible ef¬
fects on climate. For example, it has been
estimated that if chlorofluoromethanes con¬
tinue to be released at current rates, the
ozone layer could be reduced by up to 15%
by the middle of the next century, which in
turn could impair human health and the pro¬
ductivity of the biosphere.
Major alterations of the land sur¬
face as forest clearance, massive
water impoundments and irrigation sys¬
tems, and the expansion of urban
areas also have the potential to alter local
or regional climates, for example by chang¬
ing heat and moisture exchange between
the surface and the atmosphere.
The most acute climatic problem,
however, is carbon dioxide accumulation, as
a result of the burning of fossil fuels,
deforestation and changes in land use. At
present rates of increase, the atmospheric
concentration of carbon dioxide may pro¬
duce a significant warming of the lower at¬
mosphere before the middle of the next cen¬
tury, particularly in the polar regions. This
warming would probably change
temperature patterns throughout most of
the world, benefitting some regions and
damaging others, possibly severely.
Since it would be necessary to redirect
many aspects of the world economy, in¬
cluding energy production and agriculture,
to halt or reduce further atmospheric carbon
dioxide accumulation, accelerated research
at the national and international levels is re¬
quired to determine more precisely the likely
climatic and other effects and their socio¬
economic consequences. There is also a
general need for better climatic data, for
clarification of the relative roles of human
and natural influences on climate, and for
improved understanding of the impact of
climate change on human activities.
Research into all these issues is the main
thrust of the World Climate Programme
sponsored by the World Meteorological
Organization, and this programme deserves
the strongest support of all nations. In addi¬
tion, the immediate problem of acid rain re¬
quires not merely continued research but a
reduction by European and North American
countries of sulphur dioxide emissions. It is
most important that states join and imple¬
ment the Convention on Long-range Trans-
boundary Air Pollution.
Antarctica and the Southern Ocean are
defined as all land and sea south of the An¬
tarctic Convergence (the well-defined but
fluctuating line where the cold surface
waters of the Southern Ocean sink beneath
the warmer waters of the cold-temperate
Atlantic, Indian and Pacific Oceans).
Much of this area that is the entire area
south of 60°S latitude except for the "high
seas" is under the nominal control of the
13 parties to the Antarctic Treaty. Under this
treaty, Antarctica may be used only for
peaceful purposes principally scientific
research. Conservation of the living
resources of the land is provided for by the
"Agreed Measures for the Conservation of
Antarctic Fauna and Flora" which are ex¬
cellent but have not yet been ratified.
Currently the potential of krill (Euphausia
superba), a tiny shrimp-like creature, swar¬
ming in huge quantities in the Southern
Ocean, is attracting a great deal of interest:
it is said that the catch could rise from about
50,000 tonnes in 1 977/ 1 978 to 60 million ton¬
nes or more thereby doubling the world's
current annual fish catch.
However, krill are the major food of five
species of great whales, including the en
dangered blue whale and humpback whale,
and are also important for three species of
seals, many seabird species and several
species of fish. Unless krill harvesting is ex¬
tremely carefully and conservatively
regulated, its effects on other Southern
Ocean species could be devastating. A con¬
vention to regulate the taking of the living
resources of the Southern Ocean is being
negotiated, and is expected to be followed
by a regime for mining and oil exploitation.
Any regime for the exploitation of the liv¬
ing marine resources of the Southern Ocean
CONTINUED PAGE 38
Over 300 metres high, the stacks of a generating station at Cumberland City, Tennessee,
illustrate a trend to build taller chimneys so as to reduce the concentration of sulphur and
nitrogen oxides near the ground. However, by putting the oxides higher into the
atmosphere, the stacks cause them to be carried further. By joining and implementing the
Convention on Long-range Transboundary Air Pollution, States can take a major step in
combatting a form of pollution which by its nature disregards national boundaries. Adopted
in November 1979, the Convention obliges parties to make every effort to reduce air
pollution, especially the discharge of pollutants carried by winds across frontiers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A world
conservation
strategy
THE World Conservation Strategy is
intended to stimulate a more focuss-
ed approach to the management of
living resources and to provide policy
guidance on how this can be carried out by
three main groups:
policy makers and their ad¬
visers;
conservationists and others directly con¬
cerned with living resources;
development practitioners, including de¬
velopment agencies, industry and com¬
merce, and trade unions.
1. The aim of the World Conservation
Strategy is to achieve the three main objec¬
tives of living resource conservation:
a. to maintain essential ecological pro¬
cesses and life-support systems (such as
soil regeneration and protection, the recycl¬
ing of nutrients, and the cleansing of
waters), on which human survival and deve¬
lopment depend;
b. to . preserve genetic diversity (the
range of genetic material found in the
world's organisms), on which depend the
functioning of many of the above processes
and life-support systems, the breeding pro¬
grammes necessary for the protection and
improvement of cultivated plants, dom¬
esticated animals and microorganisms, as
well as much scientific and medical ad¬
vance, technical innovation, and the securi¬
ty of the many industries that use living
resources;
c. to ensure the sustainable utilization
of species and ecosystems (notably fish
and other wildlife, forests and grazing
lands), which support millions of rural com¬
munities as well as major industries.
2. These objectives must be achieved as a
matter of urgency because:
a. the planet's capacity to support peo¬
ple is being irreversibly reduced in both
developing and developed countries:
thousands of millions of tonnes of soil
are lost every year as a result of
deforestation and poor land manage¬
ment;
at least 3,000 km2 of prime farmland
disappear every year under buildings and
roads in developed countries alone;
b. hundreds of millions of rural people
in developing countries, including 500
million malnourished and 800 million
destitute, are compelled to destroy the
resources necessary to free them from
starvation and poverty:
in widening swaths around their villages
the rural poor strip the land of trees and
shrubs for fuel so that now many com¬
munities do not have enough wood to
cook food or keep warm;
the rural poor are also obliged to burn
every year 400 million tonnes of dung
and crop residues badly needed to
regenerate soils;
c. the energy, financial and other costs
of providing goods and services are
growing:
throughout the world, but especially in
developing countries, siltation cuts the
lifetimes of reservoirs supplying water
and hydroelectricity, often by as much as
half;
floods devastate settlements and crops
(in India the annual cost of floods ranges
from $140 million to $750 million);
d. the resource base of major industries
is shrinking:
tropical forests are contracting so rapidly
that by the end of this century the re¬
maining area of unlogged productive
forest will' have been halved;
the coastal support systems of many
fisheries are being destroyed or polluted
(in the USA the annual cost of the
resulting losses is estimated at $86
million).
3. 777e main obstacles to achieving conser¬
vation are:
a. the belief that living resource conser¬
vation is a limited sector, rather than a
process that cuts across and must be con¬
sidered by all sectors;
b. the consequent failure to integrate
conservation with development;
c. a development process that is often
inflexible and needlessly destructive,
due to inadequacies in environmental plann
ing, a lack of rational use allocation and un¬
due emphasis on narrow short term interests
rather than broader longer term ones;
d. the lack of a capacity to conserve,
due to inadequate legislation and lack of en¬
forcement; poor organization (notably go¬
vernment agencies with insufficient man¬
dates and a lack of coordination); lack of
trained personnel; and a lack of basic infor¬
mation on priorities, on the productive and
regenerative capacities of living resources,
and on the trade-offs between one manage¬
ment option and another.
e. the lack of support for conservation,
due to a lack of awareness (other than at the
most superficial level) of the benefits of con¬
servation and of the responsibility to con¬
serve among those who use or have an im¬
pact on living resources, including in many
cases governments;
f. the failure to deliver conservation-
based development where it is most
needed, notably the rural areas of develop¬
ing countries.
4. The World Conservation Strategy
therefore:
a. defines living resource conservation
and explains its objectives, its contribu¬
tion to human survival and development and
the main impediments to its achievement;
b. determines the priority requirements
for achieving each of the objectives;
c. proposes national and subnational
strategies to meet the priority re¬
quirements, describing a framework and
principles for those strategies;
d. recommends anticipatory en¬
vironmental policies, a cross-sectoral
conservation policy and a broader
system of national accounting in order to
integrate conservation with development at
the policy making level;
e. proposes an integrated method of
evaluating land and water resources,
supplemented by environmental
assessments, as a means of improving en¬
vironmental planning; and outlines a pro¬
cedure for the rational allocation of land
and water uses;
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Future park wardens and game
scouts from thirteen African
countries are being trained in
wildlife conservation at the College
of African Wildlife Management, on
the slopes of Mount Kilimanjaro, in
Tanzania. Left, a student from
Kenya holds an impala he has just
tagged so that it can be traced and
its migration habits studied.
f. recommends reviews of legislation
concerning living resources; suggests
general principles for organization
within government; and in particular pro¬
poses ways of improving the organiza¬
tional capacities for soil conservation
and for the conservation of marine liv¬
ing resources;
g. suggests ways of increasing the
number of trained personnel; and pro¬
poses more management-oriented
research and research-oriented mana¬
gement, so that the most urgently needed
basic information is generated more quickly;
h. recommends greater participation in
planning and decision making concerning
living resource use; and proposes en¬
vironmental education programmes and
campaigns to build support for conserva¬
tion;
i. suggests ways of helping rural com¬
munities to conserve their living
resources, as the essential basis of the
development they need.
5. In addition, the Strategy recommends in¬
ternational action to promote, support and
(where necessary) coordinate national ac¬
tion, emphasizing in particular the need for:
a. stronger more comprehensive inter¬
national conservation law, and increas¬
ed development assistance for living
resource conservation;
b. international programmes to promote
the action necessary to conserve tropical
forests and drylands, to protect areas
essential for the preservation of genetic
resources, and to conserve the global
"commons" the open ocean, the at¬
mosphere, and Antarctica;
c. regional strategies to advance the con¬
servation of shared living resources par¬
ticularly with respect to international river
basins and seas.
6. The World Conservation Strategy ends
by summarizing the main requirements
for sustainable development, indicating
conservation priorities for the Third
Development Decade.
Architects of the strategy
IUCN (International Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural
Resources) is a network of governments, non-governmental organizations
(NGOs), scientists and other conservation experts, joined together to promote
the protection and sustainable use of living resources.
Founded in 1948, IUCN has more than 450 member governments and NGOs in
over 100 countries. Its six Commissions consist of more than 700 experts on
threatened species, protected areas, ecology, environmental planning, environ¬
mental policy, law and administration, and environmental education.
IUCN:
monitors the status of ecosystems and species throughout the world;
plans conservation action, both at the strategic level through the World Con¬
servation Strategy and at the programme level through its programme of con¬
servation for sustainable development;
promotes such action by governments, intergovernmental bodies and non¬
governmental organizations;
provides assistance and advice necessary for the achievement of such action.
UNEP (the United Nations Environment Programme) was established
in 1972. Its mandate is to keep the world environmental situation under review in
order to ensure that emerging environmental problems of international signifi¬
cance receive appropriate consideration by governments, and to safeguard the
environment for the benefit of present and future generations. It is the first glo¬
bal UN body with headquarters in a developing country (Kenya).
UNEP plays a catalytic and co-ordinating role with the organizations of the
United Nations family and administers a fund, based on voluntary government
contributions. The Fund of UNEP assists in promoting activities related to envi¬
ronmental assessment and management. Within UNEP's programme, the follo¬
wing priority areas have been identified: environmental health, terrestrial
ecosystems, environment and development, oceans, energy and natural disas¬
ters.
The ultimate aim of UNEP's activities is to promote development that is envi¬
ronmentally sound and sustainable.
WWF (World Wildlife Fund) is an international conservation founda¬
tion, based in Switzerland and with national organizations on five continents.
WWF's scope is the conservation of the natural environment and the ecologi¬
cal processes essential to life on earth.
WWF aims to create awareness of threats to the environment and to generate
and attract on a worldwide basis the strongest possible moral and financial sup¬
port for safeguarding the living world and to convert such support into action
based on scientific priorities.
WWF ensures that its programme has a sound scientific basis by close colla¬
boration with IUCN, with whom it shares a joint world headquarters.
Since its founding in 1961, WWF has channelled funds to more than 2,000
projects in over 130 countries, served as a catalyst for conservation action,
brought its influence to bear on critical conservation situations, and provided a
link between conservation needs, the scientific resources necessary to meet
them, and the governments and other authorities whose action is needed.
WWF, with its distinguished international and national trustees, also provides
a bridge for the conservation movement to the business community.
77?e World Conservation Strategy is available in kit form from the Interna¬
tional Union for Conservation of Nature and Natural Resources, 1196 Gland,
Switzerland. A parallel paperback version has also been produced for the
general reader (see "Bookshelf", next page).
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Global Commons
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 35
should so regulate the krill fishery as to pre¬
vent:
irreversible changes in the populations of
krill;
irreversible changes in the populations of
the baleen whales and those seal, fish
and bird species which feed on krill, as
well as in the Southern Ocean ecosystem
as a whole;
overcapitalization of krill fishing fleets,
which could make it more difficult to
agree on a reduction of the krill take
should this prove necessary, and could
have severe impacts on fisheries outside
the Southern Ocean, due to the need to
redeploy the krill fleets during the An¬
tarctic winter.
An independent observer system should
be provided for in such regulations.
The Antarctic Treaty powers and nations
fishing or intending to fish the Southern
Ocean should exercise extreme restraint on
catch levels until understanding of this un¬
iquely productive ecosystem improves. All
harvesting should be on an experimental
basis as part of a scientific research pro¬
gramme to improve knowledge of krill and
of the Southern Ocean as a whole.
Baseline areas where no krill or other liv¬
ing or non-living resources may be taken
should be set aside and given complete pro^
tection, so that impacts outside can be
monitored and evaluated correctly. The
dimension and location of these areas
should be established according to the best
available knowledge of the ecosystems con¬
cerned. Current research efforts should be
strongly supported; and the collection,
analysis and dissemination of biological in¬
formation should be mandatory.
An International Decade of Southern
Ocean Research, focussing particularly on
ecological processes, should be initiated as
a matter of urgency. Investigation of the
possible environmental impacts of tourism,
scientific research, mining and oil exploita¬
tion, and so on, should be continued. Since
oil degrades extremely slowly in conditions
such as those of Antarctica and since
operating hazards are very high, the
feasibility of oil exploration and exploitation
in particular should be approached with the
utmost caution.
38
Letters to the Editor
The Unesco Courier welcomes readers' let¬
ters, which should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief, Unesco Courier, Place de
Fontenoy, 75700, Paris. Only signed letters
will be considered for publication.
FRANCE'S BREAD MUSEUM
Sir,
Perhaps your readers would be interested to
know that since 1974 there has been a bread
museum in the town of Verdun-sur-le-Doubs in
eastern France. In spite of its limited size, it has
exhibits which bring to life the history of seventy
centuries of corn-growing and forty centuries of
bread-making.
Thérèse Chabredier
Champigny
France
NUBIAN VICTORY
Sir,
I subscribe to the Unesco Courier and some of the
contents, especially the articles relating to Egyp¬
tian and Nubian archaeology are very useful to
me. I am currently studying Egyptology and have
exams in May. Is it still possible to get hold of
back numbers of the Courier relating to my in¬
terests, in particular the issues of October 1961,
December 1964 and February 1960?
Colleen H. Bolton
London
We regret that the October 1961, December 1964
and February 1960 numbers are out of print.
However the November 1974 issue which con¬
tains an article by Henry Stierlin on "the rebirth of
Philae" is still available, as is the August-
September 1979 double issue, which contained
articles on Nubian history adapted from the
Unesco-sponsored General History of Africa.
EDITOR.
CHILDREN OF APARTHEID
Sir,
Mazisi Kunene's article "Children of Apartheid"
(October 1979) admirably commemorates the In¬
ternational Year of the Child. The abominable
conditions M. Kunene depicts have been regularly
condemned through numerous resolutions
adopted by the United Nations General
Assembly. The policy of South African apartheid
has severed not only the indigenous African
population but the European settlers themselves
from the moral confines of the human family.
The policy of racial apartheid is, therefore, the
utter antithesis of the respect for human rights
enunciated in the UN's Universal Declaration of
Human Rights. Like all traducers of human digni¬
ty, the South African colonizers have concealed
the immensity of their crimes through otiose and
equivocal political verbiage.
M. Kunene's article is not only an act of inter¬
national solidarity; it is also a means of focusing
the light of international public opinion upon this
heinous abrogation of human rights. The in¬
digenous population of South Africa must be told
that they, just like their North American brothers
and sisters, are not alone; that their unjust ex¬
ploitation and oppression have not gone unnotic¬
ed, and that the UN's quest for social justice and
world peace will ultimately prevail.
David Slive
New York
The photo on page 11 of our April issue showed
islands of the Republic of the Seychelles. Islands
in foreground: Ste. Anne, Cerf, Cachée, Ronde,
Moyenne and Longue. In background, Praslln
and la Digue.
Bookshelf
Recent Unesco books
D Handbook for Information Sys¬
tems and Services, by Pauline Ather-
ton. A concise and up-to-date presenta¬
tion of current knowledge on all aspects
of the subject. Reprinted 1980, first
published 1977. 259 pp. (58 F)
D Glossary of Conference Terms,
English, French, Arabic, 2nd revised edi¬
tion, 1980. 287 pp. (60 F)
D Tropical Grazing Land Eco¬
systems. A report, summarizing the
results of research undertaken over the
past two decades, prepared by
Unesco/UNEP (United Nations Environ-"
ment Programme)/FAO (Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations). 1979. 655 pp. (135 F).
D Review of Research on Modern
Problems in Geochemistry, edited by
F.R. Siegel. 1979. 290 pp. (95 F)
D Soil Map of the World 1: 5,000,000
Volume IX Southeast Asia. Prepared
by the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion. The ninth of a set of ten which com¬
prise the Soil Map of the World. 1979.
27 x 21 cm. xiv 149 pp. maps, tables.
1979 (55 F)
D Aspects of Iraqi Cultural Policy, by
Abdel-Gawad Daoud El-Basri. .1980.
38 pp. (10 F); Cultural Policy in
Ecuador, by Dario Moreira. 1979. 94 pp.
(18 F) (Both in Unesco's "Studies and
Documents on Cultural Policies" series)
Other books
D How to Save the World. Strategy
for World Conservation, by Robert
Allen, Based on the World Conservation
Strategy prepared by the International
Union for Conservation of Nature and
Natural Resources (IUCN). 1980. Kogan
Page Ltd., London. 158 pp. ($2.95)
D Banking on the Biosphere? En¬
vironmental Procedures and Practices of
Nine Multilateral Development Agencies,
by Robert E. Stein and Brian Johnson.
Lexington Books (D. C. Heath and Com¬
pany, Lexington, Mass.) 1979. Report of
a study conducted by the International
Institute for Environment and Develop¬
ment ($9.50).
D World Studies: Education for In¬
ternational Understanding in Britain,
by Derek Heater. Harrap, London, 1980.
199 pp. (£5.95)
D The IUCN Plant Red Data Book,
compiled by Gren Lucas and Hugh Synge
for the Threatened Plants Committee of
the Survival Service of IUCN, with the
help and advice of experts throughout
the world. Covers 250 selected plants
threatened on a world scale. Published
by IUCN with the financial assistance of
World Worldlife Fund (WWF) and the
United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP)
D Rahn's Coloured Slide Collection.
An iconographical classification of
masterpaintings from 1430 to 1810.
Herbert Lang, Bern, Switzerland and
Peter Lang, Frankfurt am Main, Fed.
Rep. of Germany.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
From Unesco...
the latest findings
in natural resources research
Forests and woodlands form the natural type of
vegetation cover in most of the humid and sub-humid
regions of the world. They fulfil an important role in
meeting man's needs for timber, food and other
economic and socio-cultural requirements.
Prepared jointly by Unesco, the United Nations En¬
vironment Programme (UNEP) and the United Nations
Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO), this "state-
of-knowledge" report:
provides a clear summary of our knowledge of the
structure, functioning and evolution of tropical
forest ecosystems and of the human populations
that live within and around them;
describes some of the main patterns of use of these
ecosystems by man;
identifies gaps in our knowledge and makes recom¬
mendations for future research and the directions to
be taken in land-use development and management
strategies.
683 pages paperback 144
hard cover 180
French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK - 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de rUnesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1 ; 80/ 1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA* Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome,"Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. - LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück. 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Prwate Bag, Wellington.. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The imprint of man
So long as man remained a gatherer of food and an occasional hunter he had no greater
impact on his environment than any other mammal species. But from the moment,
thousands of years ago, that he mastered fire and invented tools and agriculture, he began
to modify his environment. This view of farmland in Cornwall, England, with its lush
pastures, trim hedgerows and orderly furrows is an example of the harmonious landscapes
man is capable of creating. Even the apparently "natural" environments of the African
savannah and the high pasturelands of the Alps are "artificial" in that they bear the imprint
of man and would be quite unrecognizable if he ceased to inhabit them.
Jim»*«
v
]]>
</page>
</document>
