<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074704eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco
OCTOBER 1983 6 French franc*
ourier
1
Luther Kafka Euler Marx Stendhal Gibran Wai
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live...
^ Tunisia The warp of time
Founded in 670 AD, the town of Al-Qayrawan (Kairouan), in north-central Tunisia, is famed for its walled medina
and its Great Mosque which dates from the period of the 9th-century Aghlabid dynasty. One of the holy places
of Islam, Al-Qayrawan has become a craft centre noted for its carpets.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on the world
OCTOBER 1983 36th YEAR
Published in 27 languages
English Tamil Korean
French Hebrew Swahili
Spanish Persian Croato-Serb
Russian Dutch Macedonian
German Portuguese Serbo-Croat
Arabic Turkish Slovene
Japanese Urdu Chinese
Italian Catalan Bulgarian
Hindi Malaysian Greek
A selection in Braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 58 French Francs; 2 years (valid only in
France): 100 French Francs
Binder for a year's issues: 46 FF
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
ISSN 0041 - 5278
No. 10- 1983 -OPI 83-1 - 403 A
page
34
Martin Luther (1483-1546)
THE SCHOOL OF LIFE
by Jacques-Noël Pérès
Leonhard Euler (1707-1783)
A CHILD OF THE SUN
by Emile A. Fellmann
11 Stendhal (1783-1842)
TO THE HAPPY FEW
by F.W.J. Hemmings
15 Richard Wagner (1813-1883)
A DILETTANTE GENIUS
by Mamoru Watanabe
Karl Marx (1818-1883)
18 MANY MANSIONS
by Georges Labica
22 A DRIVING FORCE OF HUMAN EVOLUTION
by Nikolai Ivanovich Lapin
25 Gibran Khalil Gibran (1883-1931)
A VOYAGE AND A VISION
by Ghali Shukri
27 Franz Kafka (1883-1924)
THE DEVIL'S PAY
by Maurice Nadeau
30 THE UNITED NATIONS UNIVERSITY
Gérard Viratelle and Rana Gauhar
talk to Rector Soedjatmoko
UNESCO NEWSROOM
A TIME TO LIVE...
TUNISIA : The warp of time
CANit be that there is a cyclical
element in the appearance
and disappearance of great
men? Over the centuries the year '83
has been marked by the birth or the
death ofan unusually large number of
outstanding figures whose lives and
works have enriched the cultural
heritage of mankind.
In this issue of the Unesco Courier
we evoke the memory of the
prestigious representatives of the
"class of '83" who figure on our
front cover: Luther, Kafka, Euler,
Marx, Stendhal, Gibran and Wagner.
All of them have In their different
ways helped to form the cultural iden¬
tity of the peoples from whom they
sprang; but they are also figures of
universal importance and for this
reason we have, in most cases,
selected authors to write about them
from countries or geocultural areas
other than their own. Thus Luther
and Kafka are portrayed by two
Frenchmen, Jacques-Noël Pérès and
Maurice Nadeau, Stendhal by an
Englishman, F. W.J. Hemmings, and
Wagner by a Japanese, Mamoru
Watanabe.
We have made two exceptions to
this line ofapproach: no one is better
qualified to assess the scientific
achievements of Euler than his
fellow-countryman Emile A.
Fellmann, Secretary of the Euler
Committee of the Swiss Society for
the Natural Sciences, and only a
writer of Arab culture, like Ghali
Shukri, could accurately place the
Lebanese poet Gibran Khalil Gibran
within the context of his time.
The works of Karl Marx, "a body
of thought become a world" as they
have been aptly described, seemed to
demand a two-pronged approach: an
examination of the complex and
eventful history of the works
themselves, presented by Georges
Labica, and an assessment, by
Nikolai Ivanovich Lapin, of the ideas
that have become a powerful socio¬
economic force that has helped to
shape the political landscape of the
world today.
Finally, we take a look at the aims,
objectives and achievements of the
Tokyo-based United Nations Univer¬
sity (UNU) after itsfirst decade ofex¬
istence. One of the youngest of the
United Nations institutions, the UNU
is sponsored by the United Nations
Organization and Unesco, with
whose aims andpreoccupations it has
much in common since its task is to
organize scholarly collaboration to
identify and alleviate "pressing
global problems of human survival,
development and welfare".
Cover: Water-colour by Jean-Pierre
Cagnat © Unesco Courier, 1983.
Clockwise from extreme left: Luther,
Kafka, Euler, Marx, Stendhal, Gibran,
Wagner.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
MARTIN LUTHER (1483-1546)
The School of Life
by Jacques-Noël Pérès
ALTHOUGH Protestant churches
far and wide are this year cele¬
brating the 500th anniversary of
the birth of Martin Luther, the great
reformer, they are not so much com¬
memorating their founder (for they clearly
look upon the Gospel of Jesus Christ as be¬
ing their founding doctrine), or any par¬
ticular saint, as paying authentic tribute to
the genius of the man as he really was, with
his acute intuitive sense yet with his short¬
comings, a man intent on dedicating his
whole life to the Gospel. And when we
speak of his whole life, we are thinking not
only of matters pertaining to the religious
sphere, to faith and the aspirations of the
spirit, but also of the everyday aspects of
existence.
Although the Lutheran reform was
primarily aimed at ensuring observance of
the faith by deliberately ridding it of
everything that was regarded as extraneous,
it also addressed itself to making Christians
responsible-minded citizens in the world of
creation in which God placed them, in other
words citizens also imbued with a sense of
responsibility towards the community and
society in which they are called upon to live.
The age in which Luther lived was indeed
remarkable. Perhaps we do not attach as
much importance as we ought to the fact
that it was also the age of Erasmus and
Rabelais, of Albrecht Dürer and
Michelangelo, of Copernicus and
Paracelsus, of Machiavelli, Ignatius
Loyola, Magellan and a host of other
figures who gave added lustre to science,
literature and the arts and embodied all the
intellectual qualities, so much so that the
age rightly came to be known as the
"Renaissance".
It was also the age of Faust, or, again, of
the Fugger banking dynasty, a time when it
was thought that money could buy
everything. As trade and finance expanded,
the men of the sixteenth century and the
centuries that followed were drawn towards
a new path. Henceforward, they were to see
the world in a different light and, naturally
enough, a new quest for learning likewise
made its impact felt. We attempt, in the few
lines below, to highlight some of the aspects
of Luther's thinking on education which we
regard as very relevant to the culture of his
time and perhaps even of our own time, for
that matter!
Martin Luther was born in Eisleben, in
JACQUES-NOËL PERES, French theolo¬
gian, is a pastor of the Evangelical Lutheran
Church of France. President of the Lutheran
Cultural Centre in Paris and of the "Eglise et
Monde Juif" (Church and Jewish World)
movement, he teaches at the department of
ecumenical studies of the Catholic Institute,
Paris.
Saxony, on 10 November 1483, the son of
Hans Luther and Margretha Ziegler, his
wife. As he himself wrote: "I am a pea¬
sant's son and my father, grandfather and
forefathers were all real peasants". It is true
that he was of peasant stock but his parents
went to seek their fortune in the copper and
silver mines of the Mansfeld region and his
father became a member of the Common
Council of the town, where he had settled
with his family in 1484.
The young Luther had a strict upbring¬
ing, as he recalled in his Table Talk: "My
parents were very harsh with me and, as a
result, I grew up to be a shy child. On one
occasion, for some petty reason, my mother
whipped me so hard that the blood flowed.
My parents had only my welfare at heart,
but they were not good judges of character
and their chastisement knew no bounds".
He was to remember this lesson later in life,
when he came to think about teaching and
about education in general.
However that may be, the young Martin
attended the Latin school at Mansfeld and
was then sent to the school of the Brothers
of the Common Life at Magdeburg, and
later to the parish school of Eisenach. He
then went on to become a student at the
University of Erfurt, from which he
Leader of the 16th-century Reformation movement that led to the
birth of Protestantism, the German monk Martin Luther (1483-1546)
is depicted with members of his family in this engraving after Holbein.
Clockwise from top left: Luther, his wife, mother, and father. In cen¬
tre, his daughter Magdalena.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
graduated as bachelor of arts before taking
his master's degree. He was set for a legal
career but, against his father's wishes, he
chose instead to enter the monastery of the
Augustinian Eremites at Erfurt. He was or¬
dained in the priesthood in 1507 and
thereafter devoted himself to the study of
theology. He was awarded a doctorate in
theology in 1512 and, from 1513 onwards,
taught Holy Scripture at the University of
Wittenberg.
Henceforward, all his energies were to be
directed towards the Holy Writ, which he
expounded with passion and which
prompted him to embark on the task of
reforming the Church, for which he is
known. It was in the name of the principles
which Luther discerned in the Bible that, on
31 October 1517, he publicly posted his
ninety-five theses against indulgences. It is
No tree bears fruit for itself; it
gives its fruit for others.
Luther
this act which is conventionally regarded as
being the starting-point of the reformist
movement, although it had, in fact, already
been taking shape for a long time.
In 1520 came the publication of the
"great reformist writings", the term
designating the Address to the Christian
Nobility of the German Nation and the
treatises on the Babylonian Captivity of the
Church and the Freedom of a Christian
Man. The Papal Bull "Exsurge Domine",
by which the Pope excommunicated
Luther, also dates from that year.
From then onwards, events were to move
quickly. In 1521, Luther was placed under
the ban of the Empire by the Diet of
Worms; in 1521-1522, the Elector of Sax¬
ony had him confined to the Wartburg for¬
tress, where he translated the New Testa¬
ment into German and thereby began to
mould what was to become the modern
German language (he completed the
translation of the entire Bible in 1534); in
1524-1525, the sorry Peasants' Revolt
broke out; in 1525, Luther became embroil-
All creation is the most beautiful
of books.
Luther
ed in controversy with the humanist
Erasmus of Rotterdam over the question of
free will and "unfree" will and, in the same
year, he married Katharina von Bora;
while, in 152°, he published the Short and
Long Catechisms, the remarkable guides to
Christian doctrine in which Luther revealed
his gifts as a teacher.
In 1530, the Protestant theologians
presented their confession of faith to the
Imperial Diet at Augsburg. This accord¬
ingly came to be known as the Augsburg
Confession and can be said to have formed .
the charter of Lutheranism. Up to 1546, the
year of his death, Luther went on writing
and preaching in his bid to exhort and con-
On 31 October 1517 Luther nailed on the door of the castle church
at Wittenberg his famous "95 Theses" attacking various ec¬
clesiastical abuses. His act is usually considered to have precipitated
the Reformation, the religious movement which would soon spread
over northern Europe, have a far-reaching influence on Western
Christianity and civilization, and also act as a seedbed of social,
economic and political thought. Engraving shows Luther preaching in
the church at Wittenberg.
sole the faithful and impart his teaching to
them. To date, the standard Weimar edi¬
tion of Luther's written works, known as
the Weimarer Ausgabe, consists of a
hundred-odd volumes and is still not
complete!
Education in the Middle Ages was com¬
pletely permeated by the "fear of God" and
it would not be altogether wrong to argue
that its chief purpose was to teach people
how to die well, in other words how to ap¬
pear before a God who was primarily look¬
ed upon as an implacable judge. Luther's
great discovery that God is not so much a
sovereign Lord as a loving Father offering
salvation through grace in an act of faith,
prompted him to visualize a new system of
education.
It is significant that, from as early as
1520, in the Address to the Christian
Nobility of the German Nation, one of the
three great reformist writings already men¬
tioned, Luther had already devoted several
pages to the problem of education and had
even sketched out a complete programme
for university reform. He was forthright in
voicing his opposition to scholasticism, in
rejecting knowledge culled at second hand
as a basis of instruction, and in advocating
a return to primary sources.
He urged the study of languages not for
their own sake but as a means, as he saw it,
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
of being able to gain a better understanding
of the Bible. As he himself put it: "I would
willingly agree that we could keep Logic,
Rhetoric and Aristotle's Poetics and that, if
they were put in a new and abridged form,
they could be read with profit and could be
used to give young people practice in the art
of discourse and preaching, but the com¬
mentaries and glosses should be deleted, in
the same way as Cicero's Rhetoric can be
read without commentaries or glosses.
Aristotle's Logic should be read as it
stands, stripped of all its long commen¬
taries. Nowadays, orators or preachers can
learn nothing useful from them, and they
are no longer matter for disputation or
quibbling. Along with these subjects, we
would still have the Latin, Greek and
Hebrew languages, the mathematical
sciences and history, concerning all of
which I defer to people who are more com¬
petent to judge. The results would certainly
be excellent if a serious endeavour were
made to embark on reform. The fact of the
developed an argument which still seems
strangely modern to us even today: "Sirs",
he wrote, "If such large sums have to be
spent every year on firearms, roads,
bridges, dykes and innumerable things of
the same nature, so that towns can enjoy
temporal peace and security, why should
not the same sums be spent on poor young
people in need by maintaining one or two
qualified men as schoolteachers?"
Indeed, the teaching profession was
highly esteemed by Luther, to the extent
that, in his Discourse on the Duty of Sen¬
ding Children to School (1530), he claimed
that, had he not been a preacher, the calling
he would have most liked to follow was that
of schoolmaster. And he went on to explain
how interesting and agreeable it was to
"train and raise young saplings" even if,
alas, some of them were to snap in the pro¬
cess. Thus Luther showed that he was
acutely conscious of the nobility of the task
facing educators and, while he singled out
a specific aspect of Luther's thinking about
education. Although, in some instances, he
claims that it is essential to set up schools
because the parents' own lack of education
prevents them from catering for the educa¬
tional needs of their children, it will be
noted that each of the fundamental points
in his Short Catechism, which dates from
1529, is prefaced by the phrase "as the head
of the family should present it and teach it
simply to his children and servants". This
calls for two comments: in the first place,
instruction (although, in the case in point,
it is true that he is speaking of religious in¬
struction) should not be confined to the
children of the family, but should also be
imparted to servants and to everybody liv¬
ing under the same roofin other words, in
modern parlance, there should be no
"streaming". Secondly, Luther calls for the
participation of the head of the family.
Parents should not stand aloof from the
education of their children and, what is
more, should play an active part in it.
A close friend of
Luther, the German
artist Lucas Cranach
(1472-1553) vigo¬
rously defended the
Protestant cause in
paintings, engravings
and woodcuts. Pre¬
figuring the modern
comic strip, this
engraving contrasts
Luther leading a
wagon to heaven
(above) and his
enemies riding to per¬
dition (below). It was
used to prepare the
ground for a notable
debate in Leipzig in
1519 at which Luther
was pitted against
Johann Eck, a Roman
Catholic theologian.
matter is that the issue is a most important
one!"
However, Luther was not only interested
in university education, and he made a
number of suggestions concerning elemen¬
tary schooling; among other things, he pro¬
posed that every town and village should
open a school not only for boys but for girls
as well. In his own words: "Would to
Heaven that each town had a girls' school,
where they could hear the Gospel in Latin
or in German for an hour every day!" It is
quite plain from this short passage that
Luther's main aim was to enable everybody
to read and understand the Bible.
Several years later, in 1524, in his Letter
to the Mayors and Aldermen of All the
Cities in Behalf of Christian Schoolsthe
title is a whole programme in itselfLuther
that aspect of the profession that was most
exhilarating, he did not gloss over the possi¬
ble failures they might encounter.
On this issue, Luther was neither naive
nor idealistic and he clearly realized that
what might be called theoretical education
was not an end in itself and that it was not
an adequate preparation for everyday life.
This is why he urged that, in addition to be¬
ing given a formal education, young people
should be taught a trade: "Boys should be
sent to such schools for an hour or two a
day but, even so, they should be made to
work in the home for the rest of the time
and to learn the trade or occupation for
which they are intended, so that the two go
hand-in-hand for as long as they are young
and are able to apply themselves".
Here again, emphasis has to be placed on
In the Short Catechism, Luther visualizes
the method of instruction as taking the
form of a dialogue, a sequence of questions
and answers which, little by little, enable
the pupil to grasp what the teacher wishes to
convey, whether this be the father, as
Luther advocated in his day, or the pastor
nowadays, for what is quite remarkable is
that the Short Catechism has dated so little
that it is still being used in a large number
of Lutheran parishes all over the world.
Knowledge is communicated, but there is
absolutely no question of cramming willy-
nilly abstruse notions into young people's
brains. It is much more in the nature of a
tradition, a living thing, an experience
which each generation hands down to that
succeeding it.
After Luther, the Reformers such as
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Melanchthon who was known as the
"schoolmaster" of GermanyCalvin and
others followed the same path. The ap¬
proach they took may have differed, but
their goals were the same. What we are try¬
ing to say is that they all conceived of a ge¬
nuine "cultural design" embracing all the
facets of life, whether it be the life of faith
or life in society. Their main concern was
not to produce scholars but rather men and
women capable of living their lives in accor¬
dance with moral tenets bearing witness to
the immense upheaval in which they had
been caught up through grace. In other
words, the "fear of God" of medieval
education, which we have already mention¬
ed and which taught people to prepare for
death, was replaced by Luther and his
disciples by the passionate love of the God
of salvation which carries people along the
path of life.
In this sense, Luther's ideas on education
could still be said to represent a challenge.
In the wake of Luther the Reformer, the
present-day world, like that of the sixteenth
century, is constantly on the move and we
see the far-reaching changes taking place as
every day goes by. Should we not continue
to hold to the view, therefore, that a good
education, in fact, is an education that is
resolutely optimistic in outlook and evolves
through constant dialogue, with the aim of
teaching us to live with a sense of dignity
and an eye to the future?
It is true that Luther laid stress on what
might be called the Christian dimension of
education, in which the Gospel was ex¬
pected to occupy an overwhelming place.
This is how he set out to instil the idea that
discipline, culture and even morality are all
subordinated to the awareness which Chris¬
tians are expected to have of being invested,
through grace, with a new life that ultimate¬
ly enables them to assert their freedom from
what would otherwise be a form of con¬
straint. Yet Luther seems to be telling us
that this is the only means by which educa¬
tion can escape from the narrow confines
dictated by so-called philosophies or pass¬
ing fashions that go all too often by the
name of culture, so that it can ultimately
become the School of Life and we have
used capitals deliberately.
Jacques-Noël Pérès
The Wartburg castle, above, stands on a steep hill overlooking the town of Eisenach
in the German Democratic Republic. While confined in this romantic setting, Luther
began to translate the New Testament from Greek into German. The result, published
in 1 522, combined with his translation of the Old Testament which followed later,
was a literary masterpiece which did much to shape the development of the modern
German language. Left, the room in the Wartburg where Luther translated the New
Testament is today preserved as a memorial to his historic achievement.
Photos Hellmut Opitz © Panorama, German Democratic Republic
Detail of a group portrait of Luther (left) and his friends including
Frederick, the Elector of Saxony. The portrait was painted around
1530 by Lucas Cranach.
Photo © Edimedia, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
LEONHARD EULER (1707-1783)
A chñd of the sun
by Emile A. Fellmann
THE exact sciences have been so
misused in their technological
and ecological applications that
they have fallen into considerable
disrepute in recent years. But that
should not prevent us from paying
tribute, on the second centenary of his
death, to one who, in the general
history of civilization and scientific
humanism, ranks as one of science's
most eminent representatives.
Leonhard Euler was not only by far
the most productive mathematician in
history, but also one of the greatest
savants of all time. A cosmopolitan in
the truest sense, he spent his early
years in Basel (Switzerland), worked
for a total of more than thirty years in
St. Petersburg (now Leningrad), and
spent a quarter of a century in Berlin,
then the capital of Prussia. In terms of
popularity and fame, he ranks with
Galileo, Newton and Albert Einstein.
Euler's contemporaries and biogra¬
phers all agree that, as the astrologers
say, he was "a child of the sun", of a
gay and open nature, sociable and full
of humour. Sometimes he would lose
his temper, but never for long and he
would always end by laughing at his
own outbursts. There was, however,
one subject about which he would tol¬
erate no levity, and that was religion
and the Christian faith. His strictness in
matters of religious belief explains
many facts of his life such as, for in¬
stance, his relentless assaults on the
Leibniz theory of monads (taken over
by Wolff), or his violent attacks on
some of the encyclopedists and other
free-thinkers (in his theological work
Sauvegarder la Révélation Divine,
1747). Nevertheless, Euler's practical
tolerance was much greater and more
sincere than that of his royal master,
who used the word because it was
fashionable, but readily forgot it if its
practical application embarrassed him
in the least.
Euler was also extremely modest in
regard to scientific copyright. Unlike
most scientists of all time, he never
claimed any prior rights over his own
discoveries. Indeed in his generosity he
sometimes went so far as to make a
gift of new discoveries and ideas. He
never concealed anything in his works,
EMILE A. FELLMANN, of Switzerland, is a
specialist in the work of Leonhard Euler. He is
secretary of the Euler Commission of the
Society of Natural Sciences of the Swiss
Academy of Sciences and a member of the In¬
ternational Academy of the History of
Sciences, Paris.
8
Leonhard Euler (1707-1783)
was the most prolific mathema¬
tician in history and ranks with
such figures as Galileo, Newton
and Einstein as one of the great
scientists of all time. Above,
portrait of Euler executed in
1753 by Emanuel Handmann.
always put his cards on the table, and
gave the reader a fair chance of
discovering something new. What is
more, in many instances he would lead
him to the threshold of a new discovery
and, like a true teacher, let him have
the pleasure of achieving it. This is
why the study of Euler's works is a
unique experience, both entertaining
and fascinating.
However skilled a man may be in
making abstractions and in ob¬
taining general ideas, he could
make no progress without the aid
of languages, which is twofold,
first in the form of speech and se¬
cond in the form of writing.
Euler
The Euler phenomenon is essentially
due to three factors. In the first place,
he had a prodigious memory. Appa¬
rently whatever he heard, saw or read
was for ever engraved in his memory.
For instance, it is said that when he
was quite old he would still delight his
family and friends by faithfully reciting
in Latin any of the verses of Virgil's
Aeneid. Years after they were held, he
still knew by heart the reports of
academic meetings. And this is not to
speak of his memory for everything
concerning mathematics. Secondly,
this prodigious memory was combined
with rare powers of concentration.
Su' ounding noise and bustle scarcely
d¡Ff irbed the workings of his mind. To
qu-e his friend and colleague
Thiébault, "with a child on his knee
and a cat on his shoulder that is how
he wrote his immortal works". The
third key to the Euler mystery was
simply calm, untiring effort.
Euler is a unique phenomenon
because of his output alone. The list
prepared by Gustave Eneström and
published in 1910-1913 of works
printed up to that time comprises 866
items, and the great Swiss edition of
Euler's works, on which many experts
of various nationalities have been
working since the beginning of the pre¬
sent century, so far contains 70 quarto
volumes, to be followed by 14 vol¬
umes of "letters and manuscript".
In the volume of his output, Euler is
in no way inferior to such prolific cre¬
ators as Voltaire, Goethe, Leibniz or
Telemann. The following table, divided
into ten-year periods, gives an idea of
the number of works written by Euler
and ready for printing (not counting
some dozens of still undated items):
Period Works Period Works
1725-1734
1735-1744
1745-1754
35 1755-1764 7 70
50 1765-1774 745
750 1775-1785 270
Classified by subject, this represents
the following percentages:
Algebra, the theory of
numbers, analysis 	40 per cent
Mechanics, physics ... 28 per cent
Geometry and trigo¬
nometry 	 18 per cent
Astronomy 1 1 per cent
Shipbuilding science, ar¬
chitecture, artillery science 2 per cent
Philosophy, musical theory,
theology, etc	 1 per cent
This list does not include some
3,000 letters known to date, nor still
unpublished manuscripts.
The first formal conception of dif¬
ferential and integral calculus by Leib¬
niz and Newton made it possible to ex¬
plain and predict the course of natural
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
SjBiSSBW
; S
,-*... g~a~&-, $ X7.
Q / , t ^ 'ALlkavr* 7,wj
fííe ÙcÂrvlufimo ci L < Ucmmc , r *
ubhasirw Bernoulli
^y c«&
íuM mtmn**fffA
<*»«*.
¿r* * **esvare VC¿a<- ,	 _¿_
-J»¿J -+
/*
-+ î* -#-
*
-+ ft *( ï + -*
-+-
-«Y1 -* ¿5
-f -+
+»
t. s'n
*£) . = - «'. J TT !
./.
Above, the first page of a letter Euler wrote on 20 June 1 740 to his
former teacher in Basel, Johann Bernoulli who duly noted in top right
hand corner "Received 27 July 1740". Lines 5 to 8, which deal with
money matters, were tactfully crossed out by Bernoulli or his son.
Above, schematic depiction of the cosmos as
Euler saw it, from his work Theoria Motuum
Planetarum et Cometarum (1744). Applying
his great mathematical talents to the
movements of the heavenly bodies, Euler con¬
ceived of the solar system as one system
among many others which all obey the same
laws of gravity.
phenomena. For a number of re¬
searchers, foremost among whom
were the brothers James and John Ber¬
noulli of Basel, this opened up a vast,
new domain for conquest by the
human mind in the Age of Enlighten¬
ment. The first to embark on this
voyage of scientific discovery was
Leonhard Euler.
In the domain of pure mathematics,
he established at once a number of
new subjects for research, and deve¬
loped them methodically the theory
of numbers, the theory of functions,
the theory of infinite series, higher
algebra, and the calculus of variations.
The textbooks he wrote on these sub¬
jects are still as up-to-date as ever.
Thanks to his lively style and ex¬
emplary didactic powers, they can still
be read with profit and pleasure. Many
of the mathematical symbols used to¬
day were invented by Euler. Those
used in trigonometry have been kept
unaltered.
In the introduction to his Mechanics
in 1736, Euler outlined a vast pro¬
gramme for this branch of science. The
chief feature of this work, then veryiv
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
modern, was the consistent applica¬
tion of differential and integral calculus
to contemporary problems in mecha¬
nics. Application of the calculus of
variations to the theory of girder stress
led Euler to the formula of stress,
which we now know thanks to him and
without which modern engineering
would be inconceivable. In a special
application of a general theory, he also
discovered the optimum form of profile
for the rim of cogwheels (development
pitches). This was not applied in prac¬
tice until the 1 9th century, since when
it has become indispensable in the con¬
struction of machinery.
Euler's first major study in the field
of fluid mechanics was a comprehen¬
sive treatise on ships. Here he deals
with the general theory of the
equilibrium of floating bodies and an
innovation at that time studies the
problems of stability as well as the ef¬
fect of minor oscillations near the state
of equilibrium. Applying the general
theory to the particular case of a ship,
Euler founded a new science and had a
lasting influence on the development
Euler's work in astronomy covers a
wide spectrum. It includes determining
the trajectories of comets and planets
from only a small number of observa¬
tions, the solar parallax, and the theory
of refraction of atmospheric rays. His
most important treatises deal directly
or indirectly with celestial mechanics,
a branch of research founded by
Newton which engaged the greatest
attention of the leading mathemati¬
cians of that time. His theory concern¬
ing the moon, on which the astrono¬
mer Tobie Mayer of Göttingen based
his famous "Lunar Tables" in 1755,
enabled the longitude of a ship at sea
to be determined with a previously
unequalled precision. For a century,
these "Lunar Tables" of Euler and
Mayer were used in navigation at sea.
theology and ethics, and end with the
famous attempt to refute Berkeley's
absolute idealism and the ideas of
Hume. Euler's place in the history of
philosophy is still disputed, but his
more or less direct influence on Kant
cannot be denied.
Many treasures still remain to be
discovered in the works of Euler, but it
will be a long time before this pro¬
digious body of work is fully in print
and available to all. An adequate
biography of this, the most eminent of
Switzerland's expatriate sons, has still
to be written. Indeed such an enter¬
prise would be almost equivalent to
writing the entire history of mathema¬
tical science in the eighteenth century.
Emile A. Fellman
of maritime navigation and naval
engineering. In the history of technics,
Euler's experiments with Segner's
hydraulic engine and his resultant
theory of water turbines are we
known. About forty years ago, Jakob
Ackeret built a turbine exactly in accor¬
dance with Euler's directions and for¬
mulae, and found that it was more than
71 per cent efficient a remarkable
result considering that today, with the
most modern means and comparable
dimensions, turbines of this type are
scarcely more than 80 per cent
efficient.
Throughout his life, Euler was also
interested in optics. In this field too, he
is the author of the first textbooks in
the modern sense, and formulated a
general theory of the refracting lens
telescope. He played a considerable
rôle in the discovery of achromatic lens
systems (which do not distort colours).
Seven volumes of his Opera Omnia are
devoted to optics.
10
Euler's philosophical testament is
contained in his Lettres à une Princesse
d'Allemagne (Letters to a German
Princess) which, at her father's re¬
quest, he wrote between 1760 and
1 762 to the Margrave Sophie Charlotte
of Brandenburg. They were published
in three volumes from 1768 onwards
and became a bestseller. They were
even translated into many foreign
languages and for long constituted the
most widely circulated synopsis of
popular scientific and philosophical
culture. They embrace musical theory,
philosophy, physics, cosmology,
Title pages of some of Euler's
many works. Clockwise from far
left: Algebra, published in 1 770 by
the Academy of Sciences of St.
Petersburg and translated into
many languages; the Mechanica
(1736) in which Euler laid down
new criteria for the mathematical
treatment of physical phenomena;
the Dioptrica (1769), the first
modern textbook on optics; it con¬
tains a complete theory of the
telescope; the Methodus Invenien-
di Lineas Curvas, in which Euler
developed a new science, the
calculation of variations, which
still plays a major role in mathe¬
matics, physics and engineering.
Photos © Library of the University
of Basel, Switzerland
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
STENDHAL (1783-1842)
To the happy few
/
w_
i
>
'*rf
Portrait of Stendhal 11783-1842) by Henri Lehmann (1841).
by E W. J. Hemmings
F.W.J. HEMMINGS, of trie United Kingdom,
is Professor of French Literature in the Univer¬
sity of Leicester, England. His Stenâhal: a
study of his novels (Oxford, 1964) is one of
several books of his on nineteenth-century
French authors which include Zola, Dumas,
and Baudelaire.
MOST people who have read any
Stendhal at all will have read
Le Rouge et le Noir. This
novel was published as long ago as 1830,
but there are still arguments about what
Stendhal may have intended by his col¬
ourful title. Most probably, Red is meant
to stand for blood and cannon-fire, the
"red badge of courage", to borrow
Stephen Crane's phrase, in other words
the military life, and Black for the
clerical cloth, the Church.
The hero, Julien Sorel, is a young man
with ambitions who has to decide, at the
outset of his life, what career will be most
profitable for him to follow. He belongs
to a post-war generation; it is only from
old men, like the retired army surgeon
who is one of the few real friends of his
boyhood, that he learns of the
Napoleonic epic, when the French flag
was carried in triumph all over Europe;
but at the time the story opens the coun¬
try is at peace, Napoleon is in exile, and
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
France is' ruled by a reactionary govern¬
ment that favours the Church. So Julien
decides to conceal his admiration for
Napoleon, to enter the Church and to use
it as a ladder to make his way to the top.
In fact, Julien is never even ordained.
He begins as a private tutor to the sons of
a businessman in the town in south-east
France where he was born. Then he
enters the seminary at Besançon; but he
leaves this to become the confidential
secretary of a powerful nobleman in
Paris, though he continues to wear the
black suit which is "the uniform of my
century", as he says.
But before the end comes his
employer, the Marquis de la Mole, has
agreed to accept him as his son-in-law
and secures him a commission in the
©
Stendhal carried on a long and tender correspondence with his sister
Pauline. In this fragment of a letter to Pauline he sketched himself
galloping to a burning house near Brunswick.
Words are always a force which
one seeks outside oneself.
Stendhal
army. So there is a symbolic return of the
"red" before, in a rash and one might
think uncharacteristic act, Julien casts
away all he has achieved, is arrested for
attempted murder, tried and executed.
Julien Sorel conforms in many ways to
the stereotype of the romantic hero: he is
intelligent, brave, and handsome; but he
is different in his duplicity and hypocrisy,
necessary in order to keep secret his am¬
bitious dreams and pass himself off as a
humble servant of the Church. Only
women seem to sense in him the potential
greatness that he hides beneath a cloak of
mystery. Stendhal departed from the
normal practice among novelists of his
time by introducing two heroines, each of
whom in turn falls in love with the hero,
though they are as unlike one another as
they possibly could be; Madame de
Renal, the wife of his first employer, is
a gentle, maternal figure, whereas
Mathilde de la Mole, the Marquis's
daughter, is a haughty, unconventional
girl who admires Julien because he is so
different from the buzzing swarm of
empty-headed young aristocrats who are
suitors to her hand.
Le Rouge et le Noir was the first
masterpiece of the French novel to ap¬
pear in the nineteenth century, that cen¬
tury which saw the appearance of so
many masterpieces by such novelists as
Balzac, Flaubert, and Zola. Yet at first it
shocked most of its readers. They did not
know what to make of Julien, so admi¬
rable in many ways, yet so ruthless and
unscrupulous in others. He was the first
incarnation ever of a new phenomenon
the individual at war with society, bent
on dominating it by his own strength of
character. He desires neither money nor,
really, social position, but the simple
satisfaction of attaining each of his suc¬
cessive goals, quite regardless of the
moral implications of his methods.
His creator, the man called Henri
Beyle who adopted, no one knows why,
this Germanic pseudonym Stendhal for
his books, was quite unlike Julien in
these respects and indeed it is often
thought that Julien and the heroes of his
later novels were the creations of wish-
fulfilment, since they all possess the ad¬
vantages he knew himself to lack: good
looks, personal magnetism, will-power,
riches or rank, as the case might be.
Stendhal was already a man in his late
forties when he published Le Rouge et le
Noir, having been born in 1783 exactly
two hundred years ago though not into
a working-class family, as Julien was,
but as the only son of a fairly well-to-do
landowner in Grenoble. He had an
unhappy childhood, losing his mother,
whom he adored, at an early age, but in
1799, at the age of sixteen, he came to
Paris to enrol as a student in the Ecole
Polytechnique, for the subject he had
been best at in school was, oddly,
mathematics. Now 1799 was the year of
the coup d'état by which Napoleon
established himself as ruler of France.
Shortly afterwards, Beyle joined the
army and crossed the Alps to northern
Italy, recently conquered by Napoleon
after a brilliant campaign. Italy had an
immediate and electrifying effect on
Beyle: he fell in love with the country and
everything about it its art, its architec¬
ture, its music, and the countryside itself,
not to mention the women. This passion
for Italy lasted the rest of his life.
For the next fifteen years, as was the
case with so many young men in France
at the time, Beyle's career was bound up
with Napoleon's fortunes. He served for
a while in Brunswick, in the military ad¬
ministration of occupied Germany; he
undertook missions to Berlin and
Moscow, and he participated in the ill-
fated retreat of the Grande Armée in
1812. Whenever he could, he returned to
his beloved Italy and when, in 1814,
Napoleon was compelled to abdicate, he
decided to settle in Milan for the rest of
©
*
12
"I got on badly with my fellow pupils, I realize today that I was then an extremely ridiculous mixture
of arrogance and of need for love", Stendhal noted in his autobiographical novel Vie de Henry Brulard
(The Life of Henry Brulard). Above, a sketch by Louis-Joseph Jay (1 755-1836) of a group of students
at the Ecole Centrale of the Isère département. Stendhal is 7th from the right.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
his life. He did not even return to France
during Napoleon's brief attempt, in
1815, to regain his throne, and so he was
never actually present at the battle of
Waterloo which is so vividly described in
his other great novel, La Chartreuse de
Parme.
Lombardy at this time was a client
state of Austria, and Beyle, who had
close friends among the Italian patriots
who were plotting for national in¬
dependence and unification, was even¬
tually declared persona non grata and
had to return to Paris. It was only then,
This book appeared at the end of the
year, after the revolution of July 1830
brought about a change of government.
Beyle, or Stendhal as we can now call
him, had friends in the new administra¬
tion, who found him a job as French con¬
sul in the little Italian seaport of
Civitavecchia, then in the Papal States.
He kept this situation, which at least gave
him enough to live on, for the rest of his
life, though he was dreadfully bored with
the dull, lonely existence he led in this
out-of-the-way port, and sorely missed
the lively café society of Milan and his
While travelling In Italy with George Sand in 1833, Alfred de Musset
met Stendhal who was then French consul at Civitavecchia. Above,
one of several sketches of Stendhal by Musset.
in the 1820s, that he turned to writing, to
supplement his tiny income as a half-pay
officer. He lent his weight to the efforts
of the young Romantics in France to
found a new, revolutionary style of
writing for the stage; he published a
defence of the Italian operatic composer
Rossini, two quite successful travel
books about Italy, a totally unsuccessful
maiden novel, Armance, and finally Le
Rouge et le Noir.
numerous friends in Paris. Only in 1836
was he able to return to France, having
been granted a short leave which he
managed to spin out for three years.
To while away the dreary hours of
idleness in Civitavecchia, he had started
on another novel, Lucien Leuwen, about
the adventures of a wealthy banker's son
in the army and the civil service. It was
never completed, as Stendhal apparently
lost interest and began writing La Vie de
Henry Brulard, an autobiography which
takes the story of his life down to his first
visit to Italy. Almost everything we know
about Stendhal's childhood and adoles¬
cence derives from this book. We learn
among other things that his favourite
reading as a boy was Don Quixote, and
that he imbibed from his great-aunt
Elisabeth the principles of what he called
espagnolisme, or Spanish honour, which
was the direct opposite of bourgeois
calculations of profit and loss. It implied
a sense of what was truly noble and a cor¬
responding horror of low-mindedness,
and kept a man from ever committing a
base or shabby act. Stendhal maintained
that espagnolisme had been a lodestar in
his life ever since.
At the end of his leave-period in France
Watch out; ifyou continue to be
sincere we are going to agree.
	Stendhal
Stendhal wrote, or rather dictated, his
second masterpiece, La Chartreuse de
Parme. Many readers prefer this book to
Le Rouge et le Noir, for it is less urgent
and less bitter, full of gaiety and yet
steeped in regretful melancholy. All the
characters are Italian which, considering
that the book is written, of course, in
French makes it almost unique, a kind of
Franco-Italian novel; just as Joseph Con¬
rad regarded England as his adopted
country, so for Stendhal Italy, the Italy
of the Po valley and the mountain lakes,
was the land he had given his heart to.
The scene switches between Milan, Par¬
ma, and Bologna, though towards the
beginning of the book there is a long se¬
quence set in France which culminates in
the description of the battle of Waterloo
already mentioned.
Fabrice, the young hero of Stendhal's
story, is a fanatic admirer of Napoleon,
and when he hears that the great man has
left the little island of Elba to which he
had been banished and is engaged on one
last gamble to recover his lost empire, he
decides, though only sixteen, to make his
way to Paris and offer his services to
Napoleon.
Fabrice is full of generous illusions,
and the first thing that happens to him is
that he is locked up on suspicion of being
. a spy. But he succeeds in making his way
to the front, and what he then witnesses
puzzles him as being totally unlike what
he had imagined a battle would be. The
confusion and the general unreality of
the scene is what Stendhal who had
been present at other battlefields, though
not at this one conveys above all else in
these marvellous pages; and the question
Fabrice is always asking: "Is this a real
battle?", has ironic implications when
one remembers that it was Waterloo,
more than any other clash of arms in the
last century, that decided the subsequent
course of history. Tolstoy in particular
admired this brilliant presentation of the
chaos of modern warfare and
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
it when describing the battle
of Borodino in War and Peace.
Apart from Fabrice, there are three
other main characters in the book, who
form a sort of loose association living
their lives according to different prin¬
ciples from the rest of humanity. They
see the power-struggle, in which everyone
else is engaged, as a game of chess or
whist, not to be taken too seriously; one
has to learn the rules of the game, but a
sensible person would never dream of
passing moral judgement on the rules.
This observation is made by Count
Mosca, the middle-aged prime minister
at Parma and an adept at court intrigue;
but political power and influence mean
nothing in themselves to Mosca, for
whom the only serious thing in life is his
love-affair with Gina Sanseverina. She is
undoubtedly Stendhal's outstanding
feminine creation: a woman of sudden
impulses, infinite charm, and complete
amorality. She is secretly in love with
LE IIOUGE
ET LE NOIR
CHRONIQl t I» HI V' SIKCI.K,
I'AUM. DESTENIWAL.
TOME I'lll NIHIL
PA BIS.
A. II. VAVAS.sr.UK. l.l BK AI RE, PALAIS ROYAL.
1831.
Stendhal's prophecy
that his works would
not be properly ap¬
preciated until a cen¬
tury after his death has
proved justified. Left,
frontispiece of an early
edition of Le Rouge et
Le Noir.
Photo © Edimedia, Pans
Fabrice, but, as her nephew, he regards
her with affection but without ardour. In
the second part of the book the cheerful
recklessness of Gina leads her to offend
the Prince; to revenge himself, he has
Fabrice imprisoned in the Farnese tower,
the State prison of Parma. This period of
captivity and danger turns out paradox¬
ically to be the happiest in Fabrice's life,
for it is then that he falls in love for the
first time; and the girl is none other than
the daughter of the prison governor,
Clélia Conti, who is persuaded by Gina
to smuggle in the rope ladder by which he
climbs down from his cell at the top of
the tower.
There is, however, no happy end to the
story. Fabrice escapes with Gina to
Switzerland, but she is driven to fury and
despair when she realizes that he loves
not her but Clélia. There is little hap¬
piness either for the two lovers, for Clélia
has to accept a man she does not love for
husband, and dies a few years later.
Fabrice, broken-hearted, follows her into
the grave, and only Mosca, the oldest of
them all, survives to preside nonchalantly
over the fortunes of Parma, preferring to
remain in power rather than that some
scoundrel should take his place. All in
all, it is a melancholy evocation of the
fine, careless rapture of youth, doomed
to be submerged in the rising tide of
maturity, with all its deceptions, dissen¬
sions, and disappointments.
Stendhal lived only three years after
the appearance of La Chartreuse de
Parme, long enough at least to read with
intense pleasure the magnificent review
that Balzac gave it. Few of his contem¬
poraries, however, shared Balzac's en¬
thusiasm, a circumstance which hardly
surprised Stendhal, who used to say he
would not be properly appreciated until a
century after his death. But he knew
and he was right in this that he would
always have a small number of devotees,
the minority he must have been thinking
of when he dedicated La Chartreuse de
Parme "to the happy few". Today,
throughout the world, the "happy few"
have become a great army for whom
nothing that Stendhal wrote is indif¬
ferent, for in everything we can hear the
echoes of that impertinent, ironical, and
yet enthusiastic voice which reaches us
unimpaired across the gulf of time.
F.W.J. Hemmings
With you this evening, I sing in Stendhal
the dazzling adversary of all dogmas
the enemy of thrones and altars
raised far from the burning feasts of the flesh.
I sing the secret Stendhal-land of each life
the musician of all our travels in Italy
in the age of the nuclear danger
and the endless dramas of the Third World
and of the whole world which beats with
the star of our childhood.
René Depestre
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
RICHARD WAGNER (1813-1883)
A dilettante
genius
by Mamoru Watanabe
RICHARD Wagner belongs to that
select group of world personalities
Napoleon and Goethe are also
of their number to whom biographers
seem irresistibly drawn.
Some, drawn to his glorious music,
feel the urge to study his life; others,
maybe puzzled by the controversy sur¬
rounding his life and character, decide to
seek the truth through the story of his
life. Others, again, feel such antipathy
for the man that they embark on his por¬
trait much like a painter who, because he
does not wish simply to depict beauty, is
attracted to ugliness and uses it in an at¬
tempt to arrive at the truth. Such was my
motive when I set out to write Wagner's
biography.
I believe that no other musician lived
his life on such a vast and varied scale.
Perhaps no artist has ever been so
human, superhuman and sometimes in¬
human as Wagner. His life, like his
musical iuvre, was titanic.
Yet as I advanced in my research, I
realised that the most extraordinary thing
about Wagner was not the variety of his
life, nor the breadth of its range. Those
qualities masked something else a single,
soaring truth: to create great art, the ar¬
tist must be totally uncompromising.
Wagner was certainly that. Why did he
not try to change his life-style instead of
running up debts? Why did he betray the
man who was his generous benefactor by
having an affair with his wife? Why did
he take unfair advantage of the uncondi¬
tional affection shown towards him by
MAMORU WATANABE, Japanese musico¬
logist, was director of the Japanese Cultural
Institute in Cologne, Federal Republic of Ger¬
many from 1976 until 1982. He has published
widely on music and has translated many
works on music and other subj'ects from Ger¬
man into Japanese and vice versa.
This portrait of Richard Wagner (1813-1883) by the French Impressionist painter
Auguste Renoir was painted in Palermo on 15 January 1882. It is now in the Louvre.
the young king Ludwig II of Bavaria?
There is only one answer: the act of ar¬
tistic creation was the be-all and end-all
of Wagner's life; it guided his every deci¬
sion. All else, including bourgeois
morality, was relegated to second place.
There can be no doubt that he believed
in the worth of his music. That self-
assurance led him to publish private edi
tions of his works and get into debt as
a result after music publishers had
turned them down, and to throw his con¬
siderable energies into getting his operas
put on at various opera houses.
But when, on occasion, he acted in
such a way as to offend bourgeois stan¬
dards of morality, he was motivated not
by self-assurance, but by his irrepressible
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Caricature of Wagner by J. Blass
Photo © Edimedia, Pans
The philosopher Friedrich Nietzsche
was right when he detected a certain dilet¬
tantism in Wagner. Thomas Mann was
of the same opinion. Recently, some
Japanese writers have argued that it is a
great mistake to regard Wagner as a di¬
lettante. In my view, however, it is by
recognizing his dilettantism that we can
properly appreciate his art. I do not pro¬
pose to discuss at length those charac¬
teristics of Wagner that marked him out
as a non-specialist par excellence the
grounding in dilettantism he received
when still an adolescent, the awkward
poetic conception of his inordinately
long libretti, his lack of discrimination
the German Romantic composers and to
have taken it to extremes. But in later
composers such as Brahms or Richard
Strauss, all traces of this approach have
disappeared.
It needs to be stressed that Wagner
became a successful artist precisely
because he succeeded, in many respects,
in overcoming his dilettantism. As
regards the technique of musical com¬
position, in particular, he achieved an
almost unparalleled virtuosity. The brio
and originality he showed in his modula¬
tions, instrumental technique, and use of
harmony are still extremely influential.
In the art of dramatic composition, too,
iv creative urge. Fanned by the confidence
he had in his music, that urge became in¬
creasingly violent. He thought it quite
normal for millionaires to give him
financial support so he could continue
creating. If he sank deeper and deeper in¬
to debt, it was not because he was sure
that his operas would be successful, when
staged, and thus enable him to repay
what he owed, but because with' ut
financial assistance he could not h re
created at all.
He believed that society alone, t
himself, bore responsibility for t' e
debts.
It was an attitude that was no doubt
justifiable in part, for if the present-day
system of royalties had been in force at
the time, he would probably have been
spared his financial problems, at least
during the second half of his life. Cre¬
ation also lay at the origin of his love for
another man's wife, and that love be¬
came indissociable for him from his cre¬
ative work. Wagner suffered from the
The goal ofmy work is the eternal
human delivered from every con¬
ventional element.
Richard Wagner
fact that his marriage with Minna had
failed, but he could not bring himself to
conform tö the ordered bourgeois ex¬
istence she wanted him to lead. The act of
creation forbade him to do so.
Moreover, Wagner's view of creation
was such that he did not regard an opera
as completed when he had finished writ¬
ing it: it had to be staged as well. But
staging often posed almost insuperable
difficulties, and caused Wagner to act in
a way which, according to bourgeois
standards, could only be described as
grossly selfish. Wagner was willing to
stop at nothing in order to get his operas
performed.
16
Photo Strohmeyer Photographs '-Q
San Francisco Opera Association,
San Francisco, California
This photo and the top photo on page
1 7 are taken from Richard Wagner:
Opéras de la Création à Nos Jours, by
Oswald Georg Bauer, Office du Livre,
Fribourg/Editions Vilo, Paris.
when it came to the visual arts, the
amateurish way he took up the ideas of
Schopenhauer, and his fondness for cir¬
cumlocution in both the expression and
the theoretical articulation of his essays.
It is more instructive to explore the
positive side of the relationship between
Wagner's art and dilettantism. We
should remember, to start with, that his
dilettantism formed part of, and helped
to accentuate, a trend among nineteenth-
century musicians. Many of them had an
unorthodox or insufficient musical
education, were also interested in other
arts than music (especially literature and
the theatre), and picked up the technique
of musical composition relatively late in
life. Weber, Schumann and Lortzing, for
example, differed in this respect from
earlier classical composers. Wagner's
own artistic approach could be said to
have followed the musical approach of
he displayed expert technical skill, and
Götterdämmerung, the opera he wrote
towards the end of his life, is one of the
great works in the world history of stage
performance. There remains the question
of Wagner's use of language, but as a
non-German speaker I do not feel quali¬
fied to pass judgment on that point.
However, as Thomas Mann pointed out,
there are many passages which undenia¬
bly reveal great talent. It would also be a
mistake, particularly in the case of
Wagner, to remove the poetry from its
musical context and evaluate it separate¬
ly. Wagner's achievements as a techni¬
cian are poles apart from dilettantism.
Dilettantism had another implication
for Wagner, for it enabled him to carry
through such a vast and original enter¬
prise. The proverb which says "the blind
man fears not the snake" is relevant to
the audacity of Wagner's genius. Similar-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
ly, if he succeeded in breaking away from
the rules laid down by professional musi¬
cians and playwrights, it was entirely due
to his dilettantism. How else could he
have conceived his extraordinary theory
of the Gesamtkunstwerk, or total work
of art? How else could he have dared to
draw on German legends that even
Goethe had ignored? How else could he
have aspired to build a theatre where his
works, and his works alone, would be
performed?
Yet, in giving life to his audacious
visions, Wagner was driven by a creative
genius allied to extraordinary powers of
execution.
The fact that Wagner was such an ex¬
treme dilettante brings a note of bur¬
lesque to his biography. His life was a
human comedy, not a drama. Was des¬
tiny astonished by the force of his
creativity, for fortune smiled on him
many times? He had a narrow escape not
only when he fled the revolt of Dresden
but on many other occasions. Whenever
he found himself at bay, assailed by his
creditors, a generous benefactor would
inevitably appear on the scene. His ex¬
traordinary idea for building a theatre
where nothing but his own works would
be staged eventually came to fruition.
And if his operas continue to exert such
a wide appeal today, and to attract so
many directors, is it not because they are
in a way tragi-comedies?
Wagner wrote an impressive number
Where to find the human energy
to resist theparalysingpressure of
a civilization which denies man
utterly, to resist the presump-
tuousness of a culture which uses
the human mind only as the
motive force of the machine?
Richard Wagner
u : ''
*
. 't
V-
\ V
, i
1
'- '. .,
i
1
W'§^^Ë
i W '
4 {
;
|jï " Of, ti :."
©
Choral scene from Act 3 of Wagner's The Flying Dutchman as performed at the
Metropolitan Opera, New York, in March 1979. The structure of the ship is the only
scenery. In foreground the helmsman lies asleep before the ship's wheel. In a spectral
atmosphere created by the hanging skeletons, the choir interprets his nightmare.
of ideological essays and treatises on art
which once again display a combination
of dilettantism and its diametrical op¬
posite, specialization. Acute insights rub
shoulders with faulty judgments. But the
ultimate purpose of these essays was to
act as a spur to their author's creativity.
Among the many problems posed by
Wagner's philosophy, his anti-semitism
is justifiably condemned. Setting aside
the context of their time, Wagner's feel¬
ings appear as an emotional reaction
based on a crude generalization. Wagner
himself wondered whether he did not
have Jewish blood in his veins. The suf¬
fering that wracked his subconscious
mind was a reflection of the dark forces
of anti-semitism in nineteenth-century
Europe.
The number of Wagner operas per¬
formed in Japan is very low compared
with those by Mozart, Verdi or Puccini.
The most recent production of Wagner's famous tetralogy The Ring of the Nibelung,
by Sir Peter Hall, director, and Sir Georg Solti, conductor, was performed in July at the
annual Richard Wagner opera festival at Bayreuth. Above, a scene from The Twilight
of the Gods, the fourth part of the cycle, with Hildegard Behrens as Brunnhilde, Aage
Haugland as Hagen, and Manfred Jung as Siegfried.
This is not because Wagner is not liked in
Japan but because the staging of his
works confronts the Japanese with major
difficulties. When, however, a German
opera company on tour presents a
Wagner opera, all the tickets are snapped
up immediately. More copies of the com¬
plete recording of The Ring have been
sold in Japan than in any other country.
Why does Wagner's music appeal so
strongly to the Japanese, when it is
almost diametrically opposite in charac¬
ter to traditional Japanese art? An ex¬
planation is not easy to find, but since
Bruckner's music has won a following in
Japan in the last few years perhaps the
Japanese today are attracted by art which
is totally different from their own.
Much has been made of the extremely
Germanic nature of Wagner's music. I
cannot fully appreciate this point of
view. Myself I would tend rather to stress
the extremely human nature of his music,
its power to transcend frontiers and
speak to mankind as a whole.
Like the French, who have always lov¬
ed Wagner and towards whom Wagner
felt such hostility the Japanese cannot
resist the enchantment of his music.
Mamoru Watanabe
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
KARL MARX (1818-1883)
Above left, the last photo of Karl Marx (1818-1883). It was taken in Algeria
which he visited in 1882. His health was broken by the recent death of his
wife Jenny von Westphalen, above right, whom he had married in 1843.
Time is the field of human development.
Karl Marx
Many mansions
by Georges Labica
THE centenary of the death of Karl Marx, in London on
March 14, 1883, is being commemorated by an un¬
precedented number of ceremonies in almost every
country in the world. And at a time when, amid unabated sound
and fury people everywhere are making assessments of what
Henri Lefebvre called "a body of thought become a world", it
is perhaps opportune to point out that the works of this man.
GEORGES LABICA, French university teacher, is professor of
philosophy at the University of Paris X Nanterre. He has published some
20 studies on Marx and Marxism, notably Le Marxisme d'Aujourd'hui
(P.U.F., Paris, 1973) and Sur le Statut Marxiste de la Philosophie (Com-
plexe/P.U.F., Brussels/Paris, 1976). He organized an international sym¬
posium on "The work of Marx, a century later" which was held, under
the auspices of the French National Centre of Scientific Research, in
Paris in March 1983.
who wished to claim no country as his own, have not yet
revealed all their mysteries nor spoken their last word.
It is true that his was a singular destiny, a true adventure
story whose climactic moments punctuated the history of his
time, itself full of contradictions.
First of all, Marx published comparatively little during his
lifetime. After submitting his doctoral thesis in philosophy on
The Difference Between the Natural Philosophies of
Democritus and Epicurus, in 1 840, at the age of twenty-two,
he devoted himself to journalism, but his activities were cut
short by the Prussian censors. In 1 844, his two studies On the
Jewish Question and Toward a Critique of Hegel's Philosophy
of Right appeared in the first and only edition of the German-
French Yearbooks. In 1847, The Poverty of Philosophy, a
riposte to the French socialist thinker Pierre-Joseph Proudhon's
The Philosophy of Poverty, was published, and between 1848
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Karl Marx and Friedrich Engels Museum, Moscow
and 1863, interspersed in a mass of articles, appeared Wage,
Labour and Capital (1849), The Class Struggles in France
( 1 850), The Eighteenth Brumaire of Louis Bonaparte ( 1 852), A
Contribution to the Critique of Political Economy (1859) and
Herr Vogt (1860). For the International Working Men's
Association (The First International) Marx prepared the Address
and the Provisional Rules of the International Working Men's
Association (1 864) and the Programme for the First Congress
(1866), as well as The French Civil War (1871) in which he
made an analysis of the Paris Commune. The first volume of
Das Kapital appeared in 1 867 and was followed by the prepara¬
tion of various prefaces to the second edition of The Com¬
munist Manifesto (1872) and to the second German edition of
Das Kapital (1873), of the French translation of Das Kapital
(1 875), of the theoretical introduction to the programme of the
French Workers' Party (1 880) and, finally, of the preface to the
second Russian edition of The Communist Manifesto (1882).
This lithograph dating
from 1836 shows
students from Trier, Karl
Marx's birthplace, at the
University of Bonn. Marx,
fourth from the right, had
been elected president of
the Trier students'associa-
tion. Drawing of Marx by
H. Bach, left, was inspired
by the lithograph.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
In collaboration, primarily with Friedrich Engels, whose,
writings are indissociably linked with his, Marx published The
Holy Family ( 1 844), the Circular Against War (1855), The Com¬
munist Manifesto (1 848) and a chapter of Anti-Dühring (1 877).
To these should be added a vast Correspondence (13 volumes
in the German edition, 1 5 in the French edition now being
published), little of which was made public at the time.
In fact, many of Marx's writings were not known until after,
in some cases long after, his death. The full story of the
upheavals, both theoretical and practical, these unknown
writings were to cause has yet to be written. To cite just a few
examples, the second and third volumes of Das Kapital were
published in 1885 and 1894 respectively, thanks to a mam¬
moth effort of editing by Engels; the Theories of Surplus Value,
three volumes written between 1861 and 1863 and which
together make up the fourth volume of Das Kapital, were
published between 1905 and 1910 after editing by Karl Kaut-
sky who succeeded Engels as Marx's literary executor; the Fun¬
damentals of Political Economy, the vast manuscript dating
from 1857-1858, was not published until 1939-1941.
Moreover, hitherto unpublished texts continue to appear; the
mathematical manuscripts of Das Kapital still await scientific
capitalist production system and social, political and ideological
relationships as being some kind of natural fatality.
The third is Leninism, whose definition gave rise, quite in¬
dependently of the will of its eponym, to heated debates which
foreshadowed the revolution that came in the era of imperialism
in the "weak link" of Tsarist Russia. Stalinism was another, the
most widespread and the most enduring.
This is to say nothing of the other Marxisms, official, semi of¬
ficial or underground that, with little reference to the opinions
of those concerned, have adopted the names of Rosa Luxem¬
burg, Leon Trotsky, Nikolai Bukharin or Antonio Gramsci, and
to evoke only the leading voices of a choir whose ever increas¬
ing numbers, before our very eyes, are even now ceaselessly
producing and thus reproducing the fecundity of the works of
Marx.
Furthermore, Marxism, whether that of its originator or that
of his interpreters and it is exceedingly difficult to make the
distinction is also, indeed perhaps mainly, the record of its
grafts, or of its "fusion" as Lenin used to call it, with the
workers' movement within the context of each nation. Thus
there is, as it were, a problem of translation, in every sense of
the word. What is received? When? How? And from whom?
©
.... -
.^T *-y-~ yk ¿J*.;_ii«S^=- ^5=r:-^ ....v>'?v-sy^i; ~
-r*-wC"^ TP iiJTi* tfr Jg£v*- M* .-w ¿àS^Sîar
ft* *ÎSÊ5 "
The outlines of Marx's
new vision of the world
and the theories and
programmes which he
would spend the rest of
his life elaborating
begin to appear in the
Economic and Philo¬
sophic Manuscripts of
1844 which he wrote in
Paris. Left, a page from
the Manuscripts.
editing and publication and the complete works, the new Marx-
Engels Gesamtausgabe, will not be published in full until about
the year 2000.
What conclusion can be drawn from this? This stirring body
of writings, still vital, like so many revolutionary rockets to
use the words Marx himself .employed in Das Kapital has
disturbed and will continue to disturb our century, despite the
derisory litanies of those who continually declare that "Marx is
dead".
But more than this, the singular destiny of this body of
writings was made even more remarkable by being inextricably
linked with the history of the international workers' movement;
it is to this history that it owes its constitution as a "corpus",
a language claiming universality, in a word, as Marxism(s).
New, criss-crossing roads to Compostella, whose story is slow¬
ly being pieced together again, found here their beginnings. "In
my Father's house are many mansions..."
Let us identify some of them, using the names that they have
given themselves, sometimes unwillingly, for fear of being
relegated to minor status. The first is the word "Marxism"
itself, which Marx and Engels, who found himself reluctantly
obliged to employ it, both mistrusted, sensing in it the odour of
dogma and of magister dixit. The second is the so-called (and
well-called) "Marxism of the Second International" which
owes so much to Karl Kautsky, an economism which saw the
20
And in what political, economic, cultural and ideological cir¬
cumstances? Under what weight of tradition, thought and
practice? In the heat of revolution or in the cold, calm setting
of established institutions? Some simple examples Guesde
and Thorez "Frenchified" Marxism, Labriola and Togliatti
"Italianized" it and Mao Ze-Dong gave it a "Chinese accent",
just as Lenin and Stalin "Russianized" it. What does this mean
if not that the universal everywhere encounters indefeasible
specificities to which it must adjust?
But how? In dogmas, formulae, models, or in the handling of
concrete situations? And by means of what adaptations? Is it
not important in this regard to know how Das Kapital was com¬
prehended in Egypt or in Greece, or how The Communist
Manifesto penetrated Turkey or Colombia? How was
"socialism" translated into Arabic or the dialectic adapted in
China? Although we are aware of how Marx came to be known
in Russia, from populism to the founding of social-democracy,
can we claim to be equally knowledgeable about events in
Belgium or Australia? Was the date of the invention of the term
Marxism-Leninism entirely fortuitous? And what about the in¬
ception of the principle of juche [autonomy or identity] in
Pyongyang is it not just as interesting as the coming of
Austro-Marxism or Eurocommunism? Why did the French and
Spanish communist parties give up the concept of the dictator¬
ship of the proletariat?
Do they not all claim to be Marxist?
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The task of finding the answers to these questions, minor and
academic though they may appear, is nevertheless necessary
to a proper assessment of our era. This work is already in hand
and a great deal is at stake, dealing as it does with a century of
class struggle in which Marx, in reading Hegel, saw the beginn¬
ings of a new life for humanity, and, more precisely, the ad¬
vance from pre-history to history, to the consciously-decided
ordering of social relationships.
But this is by no means all, since the chronological disarray
in which Marx's works became known raises other questions.
The first concerns the way in which they are read and the
reconstitution of a chain whose links have been scattered. In
other words, if we want to be able to understand the evolution
of Marx's thought, it is essential to place in the order in which
they were written works such as On the Jewish Question,
Toward a Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right, The Holy
Family, the Theses on Feuerbach, the Circular Against War,
The Poverty of Philosophy and The Communist Manifesto. It is
also important to put back in their proper place in this progres¬
sion, as Marx himself suggested in one of the rare texts in
which he speaks of his own evolution, not only the important
letters he wrote to his father (1837), to Arnold Ruge
(1842-1843), to Feuerbach (1843) and to Pavel Annenkov
The philosophers have only interpreted the world;
the point is to change it.
Karl Marx
(1846), and articles such as those on Communism and the
Rheinische Zeitung (1 842), on the winegrowers of the Moselle
(1843), against Heinzen and Lamartine (1847), and the so-
called Notebooks of Bonn (1842), of Paris (1844), of Brussels
and Manchester (1845), but also the writings of Friedrich
Engels which Marx himself declared to be indissociable from his
own: first of all their Correspondence, the letters of Engels to
the Gräber brothers (1839), Frederick William IV (1842), the
Progress of Reform on the Continent (1843), the Letters from
London (1843), Outline of a Critique of Political Economy
(1844) and The Condition of the Working Class in England
(1845), the two latter being works to which Marx constantly
stressed his indebtedness. As for A Contribution to the Critique
of Political Economy, how can it be excluded from any study of
the research carried out by Marx starting from the period
1857-1858 and continuing up to the unfinished chapter on
Classes with which the third volume of Das Kapital concludes?
In recent years we have seen what animated discussions, not
only academic but also political, could arise from comparisons
between the Fundamentals of the Critique of Political Economy
and Das Kapital, and the polemics concerning Theories of
Surplus Value and the Unpublished Chapter.
And here we must ask another blunt question: have Marx's
writings really been read?
A further question also arises, to which reference has been
made above, concerning the widely differing ways in which the
works of Marx have been received. In the historical fate of his
works, that is to say, in the successive or even rival ways in
which they have been appropriated, there is a precise reflection
of their chronological avatars. Is it not possible to climb into any
carriage of this moving train and observe, jostling, confronting,
even excommunicating each other, so many different forms of
Marxism that they end by mixing up the labels with which we
try to distinguish them "University", "militant", "national"
of "X" and "Y"? Each one is a revision, but of what dogma,
of what law, of what doctrine?
From all this there is something new to learn. May not Marx
be unknown? And is it not precisely the function of the various
Marxisms, if only in self-defence, to maintain indefinitely this
ignorance of Marx by a continual process of covering up? Does
not the response to the cry of "betrayal", heard from every
quarter, demand a "return to Marx", just as there have been
demands for a "return to Kant", or, with Nietzsche, a call to go
"back to the Greeks"? But the quest for a return to a lost purity,
apart from the fact that it is always illusory or naive, can be
seen in this case to be an anachronism in direct contradiction
with its purpose, that is to say, with Marxism as a theory of
history, since the theory in question strictly forbids the leaving
aside of this history, of its history.
The last century provided a resounding proof of this: Marx¬
ism, the thinking or type of thinking originating with Marx, has
entered the public domain. This means, above all, that it has no
proprietor or authorized interpreter. Its terrain is our era in
which all languages are spoken. Marxism has become public
property was not that its vocation? And, in the end, is not this
the mark of its success? Is not the life of a work indissociable
from its effects, even those it did not seek?
Some decades ago Ernst Bloch suggested that in Marxism
could be distinguished, as it were, two mixed streams of water,
one "cold" and the other "hot". The "cold" stream cor¬
responds to the diagnosis of capitalist production relationships,
a task it is more than ever necessary to pursue. To the "hot"
stream belongs "the powerful recourse to man humiliated,
enslaved, neglected, vilified, and thus the recourse to the pro¬
letariat, seen as the setting of the upheaval that will lead to
emancipation". On the one hand well-founded knowledge and
its essential concepts, and on the other the "New", the
"Hope", the "Utopia" so dear to Bloch. The guerillas of central
America have certainly not read Das Kapital. Nonetheless they
bear witness to that fire that is always in movement and which
catches hold where least expected, to these uncodified Marx¬
isms that are erecting the Tower of Babel of our times, rejecting
our semantics, in Africa, in Asia, in Latin America, everywhere,
even among the well fed, everywhere that men and women
continue to suffer whether in their bellies, their heads or their
hearts. Did not the young Marx believe that philosophies, like
mushrooms, were the fruit of their time? Did he not affirm that
ideas, taken up by the masses, could become a material force?
A hundred years later, this final lesson remains with us.
Georges Labica
^¿j22^L^dlLmJ^
/7"\ ¿i^tc c/fh^j?t ^A^sJu
t
t E
^-vw«rl-«-Vv_
Telegram announcing the news of Marx's death was sent by Engels to F.A. Sorge,
a German worker who had emigrated .o the USA.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
A driving force
of human evolution
by Nikolai Ivanovich Lapin
'T
HE chief guide which must direct us in the choice
of a profession is the welfare of mankind and our
own perfection.
"... If we have chosen the position in life in which we can
most of all work for mankind, no burdens can bow us down,
because they are sacrifices for the benefit of all; then we
shall experience no petty, limited, selfish joy, but our hap¬
piness will belong to millions..."
These were the words of Karl Marx, then a seventeen-
year-old schoolboy whose graduation essay on a subject of
his own choice already displayed an independence of
thought and purposefulness of feeling. He would be true to
this lofty humanistic ideal as long as he lived.
Karl Heinrich Marx was born on May 5, 1818 in the old
Prussian town of Trier, now in the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many. His father Heinrich Marx, a lawyer and a man of the
Enlightenment, guided his son towards a career in law and,
in October 1835, the young Karl Marx entered the Univer¬
sity of Bonn. His interest in philosophy was growing, and,
in October 1836, with his father's understanding ac¬
quiescence, he transferred to the University of Berlin where
he could study both philosophy and law.
Another mentor from whose advice the student Marx was
to benefit was his father's friend Baron von Westphalen, to
whose daughter Jenny he was engaged and was to marry
seven years later, in 1843. The Baron, a lover of the Greek
classics and of Shakespeare and a follower of the French
social reformer Saint-Simon, took a liking to the gifted
young student who in turn expressed his gratitude and af¬
fection by dedicating to him his doctoral thesis on The Dif¬
ference Between the Natural Philosophies of Democritus
and Epicurus.
This early study by Marx, written from an idealistic,
Young Hegelian standpoint, examined the duality of the in¬
terrelationship between philosophy and reality: philosophy
actively influences the real world and transforms it accor¬
ding to its principles; but philosophy itself is subject to a
reciprocal influence and itself becomes worldly.
In April 1841, Marx received his diploma of Doctor of
Philosophy and planned to give a series of lectures on logic
at the University of Bonn. At this time, however, the Prus¬
sian Government, considering the Young Hegelians to be a
subversive element, began to drive them from the univer¬
sities and Marx turned towards active political engagement.
He began contributing to the newly-founded newspaper the
Rheinische Zeitung which he succeeded in turning into an
all-German rostrum of freedom and humanism.
When, in October 1842 Marx became the editor of the
newspaper, he was faced with writing articles on a number
of complex practical questions that were quite new to him.
His analysis of .the debates in the Rheinlandtag on the law
NIKOLAI IVANOVICH LAPIN, is head of the philosophical and
sociological studies department at the Ail-Union Research Institute for
Systems Studies of the USSR Academy of Sciences, and Vice-
President of the Soviet Sociological Association. He is the author of
over 100 works on history, philosophy and sociology. Of his numerous
works on Karl Marx, the most widely known is "Young Marx"
(Moscow, 1968) which has been published in Russian, Bulgarian,
Hungarian, Chinese, German, Moldavian, Slovak, Finnish and French
editions.
22
prohibiting the taking of timber by the peasants from the
forests and his sociological study of the status of the
Moselle wine-growers convinced him that it was not the
State that imposed its will on private interests, as
postulated by Hegel and other idealists, but private interests
that bent the State to their will.
In March 1843, the Rheinische Zeitung was banned, all
hope of a press free from censorship vanished, and Marx
started looking for new, more effective ways of continuing
the struggle. But first he decided, in his own words, to
"retire to the classroom" in order to examine and con¬
solidate the theoretical foundations of his activities. He was
turning more and more away from Hegelian idealism and in
his study Toward a Critique of Hegel's Philosophy of Right,
published in 1844, these doubts grew into a conscious
orientation towards materialistic principles.
In summer 1843, while living at Kreuznach, Marx under¬
took an analysis of world history ranging over the vast
period from 600 BC to the French Revolution. He came to
the conclusion that all historical processes were determined
by changes in the nature of private property; it was this that
exercised real influence on the State and not vice versa. For
the State to express the true interests of the people private
property would have to be abolished.
Atthe same time Marx was developing his views concern¬
ing the "essence of man". "The essence of a particular per¬
sonality, a particular man, is neither his beard, nor his blood,
nor his physical quality, but his social character."
In October 1843 Marx emigrated to Paris with his new
bride, Jenny von Westphalen, and threw himself into the
study of political economy, having come to the conclusion
that the world was ruled not by ideas but by economic laws.
From April to August 1844, working virtually non-stop, at
times going for three or four nights in a row without sleep,
he wrote his famous Economic and Philosophic Manuscripts
which contained all the roots and elements of his world-
embracing theory, a synthesis of his philosophic, economic
and political view of the world.
Comparative analysis of the three sources of income-
wages, interest on capital and land rents led Marx to the
conclusion that the many contradictions in the society of his
day, and first and foremost the antagonism between labour
and capital, were generated by the "alienation of labour".
Marx stressed the economic basis of this alienation: "The
more wealth the worker produces the less he has to con¬
sume, and the more values he creates, the more his produc¬
tion increases, the more he devalues himself. The devalua¬
tion of the world of men is in proportion to the increasing
value of the world of things... The object which labour
produces labour's market product confronts the worker
as something alien, as a power independent of the
producer."
Marx also attributed a wider meaning to "alienation",
seeing it not only in work but also in political, spiritual and
other spheres of social life. A new and genuinely humanistic
society would abolish all forms of alienation and thus
resolve the contradictions between man and man, man and
nature, individuals and groups. The self-alienation of man
would be overcome and a harmonious, whole new man
would emerge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
These new ideas brought upon their author new repres¬
sion. Marx was exiled from France, in 1845, and moved to
Brussels where he was joined shortly afterwards by
Friedrich Engels. Here they wrote The German Ideology in
which they criticized abstract idealistic concepts of man.
While writing it Marx made one of his great discoveries; he
showed that each stage of social evolution was characteriz¬
ed primarily by a certain mode of production of material
goods. His views on the dialectics of productive forces and
the interactions of production as the source of the auto-
development of history, as well as on socio-economic
systems and their changes at important, successive stages,
became the basis of the materialistic view of history.
The basic principles formulated by Marx and Engels in the
Communist Manifesto were put to the test in the crucible of
the European revolutions of 1848-1849. But this did not
mean that the development of these principles was com¬
plete. The main problem that Marx was trying to solve in
London, where he had moved in 1 849 and where he was to
remain to the end of his days, was how to explain the pro¬
cess of the creation of surplus value, that is, how a certain
additional product appropriated by the capitalist emerges on
the basis of the theory of value, i.e. the theory of equivalent
exchange between the workers and the capitalists.
In the process of solving this problem Marx discovered
that labour is a special kind of commodity which costs the
employer much less than the value of goods it creates.
Employing a worker, the capitalist purchases his labour
power and, being the owner of the means of production, he
provides for such use of this labour power that the value
created by it is higher than its own value, in other words, it
ensures that a surplus value is obtained without violating
the theory of value.
Marx's discoveries in economics came as a result of hard
work carried out in the most difficult conditions. Yet not all
his manuscripts were published during his lifetime. Ten
years were to elapse between the production of the great
manuscript of 1857-1858 and the publication in 1867 of
the first volume of Das Kapital. In the meantime, from
1861-1865, Marx produced two huge revised variants-
clear evidence of his conscientious scientific approach. The
second and third volumes of Das Kapital were prepared and
published (in 1 885 and 1 894 respectively) by his friend and
comrade Friedrich Engels; the fourth volume was published
in 1905 after Engels' death.
Das Kapital was the great original, seminal work of Marx's
life, taking account of the whole preceding history of
economic thought and subjecting a mountain of facts to
theoretical analysis. It contains a detailed examination of
the particular mechanisms of the links between the socio¬
economic structure of society and production under the
capitalist system whose tendency towards revolutionary
transformation into a new and more progressive system it
reveals.
Some concepts seem to be less in evidence or to have
been modified, but this does not mean that Marx had aban¬
doned them. In Das Kapital and other studies, for instance,
he consistently employs "alienation" as a philosophic no¬
tion. Generally speaking, Das Kapital has not only an
economic but also a wide-ranging philosophic,
methodological and humanistic content. The discovery of
the materialistic interpretation of the history of mankind and
the creation of the theory of surplus value brought about a
revolution in social thinking and made of socialism a science
rather than a Utopian dream.
Right up to the end of his life Marx worked intensively,
finding new horizons of creative thought. His Chronological
Notes on world history and on the history of specific coun¬
tries (India, Italy, United Kingdom, Russia, etc.), compiled in
the period 1880-1882, totalled over two thousand printed
pages. The idea behind their compilation is still a mystery,
but the most plausible hypothesis seems to be that of the
Soviet scientist B.F. Porshnev who believed that at the time
Marx was interested in the problem of the interconnexions
between the parallel histories of different countries.
While working on Das Kapital Marx had concentrated on
the study of one particular socio-economic system; next he
turned his attention to the problems of the interaction of dif¬
ferent systems existing simultaneously and to the problem
of the common aspects and contradictions of economic,
socio-political and spiritual processes which take place
within the context of humanity as a whole. His aim was to
achieve a global picture of a world in which many societies
co-exist and influence one another in all the main aspects of
their activities. The significance of this design has been con¬
firmed by modern researchers studying global problems.
Marx did not live to implement this great design. Ex¬
hausted by illness and depressed by the loss of his wife and
his daughter, he died quietly ¡n his armchair on March 14,
1883.
For hundreds of years mankind had been seeking ways of
achieving a just restructuring of a society which would be
free from exploitation, violence and material and spiritual
poverty. Many daring ideas had been put forward during the
course of history but few of them had succeeded in captur¬
ing the imagination of millions and becoming a driving force
affecting the evolution of human civilization. The theory of
Karl Marx ranks among the latter, incorporating as it does a
whole range of philosophic, economic and political con¬
cepts that gave people something they had never had
before a proper understanding of themselves and, conse¬
quently, of the way to emancipation.
Marx provided answers to fundamental problems that had
been raised by progressive human thought. He had
assimilated the best of German classical philosophy, English
political economy and French Utopian socialism, but he
drastically revised each of these fields of thought, syn¬
thesizing them into a qualitatively new entity a scientific
world outlook which has emerged as a specific socio-
cultural phenomenon of modern human history.
Nikolai Ivanovich Lapin
After the collapse of the
1848 revolution, Marx
spent the rest of his life as a
political exile in London. His
grave in Highgate Ceme¬
tery, left, is a centre of at¬
traction for visitors from all
over the world.
Photo Vince Blye © Parimage, Pans
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Lebanese writer, mystic poet and thinker Gibran Khalil Gibran (1883-1931) also painted in an allegorical style close to that
of William Blake. Influenced by Nietzsche, he attempted to use the will to power for the improvement of man in accordance
with the precepts of Christ and of Oriental sages. In his many works written in Arabic and English he proclaimed himself a
citizen of the world. His spiritualistic work The Prophet (1923) was a best-seller in the United States and has been translated
into 34 languages. Above, a self-portrait by Gibran.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
GIBRAN KHALIL GIBRAN (1883-1931)
A voyage
and a vision
by Ghali Shukri
GIBRAN Khalil Gibran (1883-
1931) left Lebanon for the
United States in 1895 when he
was twelve years old, but three years
later he returned to Beirut to study
Arabic. Thus 1903, the year in which he
went back to Boston, may be regarded
as the date when he began nearly a
lifetime's residence in North America,
where he divided his time between his
studio in New York and his sister's
house in Boston. Gibran thus spent the
first three decades of the twentieth cen¬
tury in one of the world's major centres
of "modern culture", far away from
his native land, itself a major world
centre of "traditional culture".
Gibran's emigration to the west was
not due to personal or family reasons.
It was part of a larger, more general
movement in which Syrians and
Lebanese migrated to Egypt and to the
Americas, fleeing from the appalling
conditions resulting from the decline of
the Ottoman Empire around the end of
the last century. The origins of this
wave of migration lay in the suppres¬
sion of freedom of expression and
belief and in the series of famines,
epidemics -vars and earthquakes that
ravaged th Levant at the turn of the
century.
In earlier days successive waves of
migration had been motivated by trade
and the other maritime activities for
which the people of Phoenicia had been
famous since ancient times. The novel
feature of the migration at the turn of
the century was that the migrants
associated trading interests with
cultural aims. These Lebanese and
Syrian émigrés laid the foundations of
culture, journalism and the arts in
Egypt, establishing publishing houses,
theatres, cinemas and newspapers. The
same phenomenon occurred, to vary-
GHALI SHUKRI is an Egyptian literary critic
and sociologist. A former professor at the
University of Tunis, he is the author of 30
books of literary criticism and cultural and
political sociology.
West Ton l li Siiool
H<l/t' <c. t <->w,'/!_*-'TV
¿*>¿¿ _i/L	 V > r
'~^~^ -*^ ' T?*f «-" ><*" ¿-¿-^ '
¿&v*¿ ¿~' ¿r' ^ - *'-^^>> -^ <^>J j^>_
« , I'j j& '^*-r '*-»/?
¿ft" >,[ >.^'c^V'-r. if^».'^'*
«-/ <-><*"j^jiSs '< \~ -^ ;>, . '< < ,.
Gibran divided his life
between Lebanon, the
United States, and
France, and carried on a
vast correspondence
with intellectuals of his
own and other coun¬
tries. Left, a letter
which he wrote in
Arabic to the writer
May Ziade. In it he
describes a disturbing
dream in which May
Ziade had appeared
with a bleeding wound.
ing degrees, in North and South
America. Gibran himself tried his hand
at business, alternately making and los¬
ing money, while Mikhayil N'aimi, as
he confesses in his book on Gibran,
worked as a commercial representative.
Thus it was the quest for freedom of
intellectual expression and economic
opportunity that drove the intelligent¬
sia of the Arab East to migrate in suc¬
cessive waves either to Egypt or to
South and North America. All these
men and women combined the trade of
journalist, writer or artist with that of
dealer in stocks and bonds. Trade, art
and politics almost always went
together in their lives and only in rare
cases did one take precedence over the
others. Gibran Khalil Gibran was one
of those rare cases.
Gibran's life and works present a
number of distinctive geatures. First of
all, he was fully a child of his times.
The first three decades of the twentieth
century set the tone for the new age
which Gibran did not live to see. It was
a time of wholesale destruction that
was also marked by an upsurge of ac¬
tivity in culture, art and science and by
an attempt to experiment with vi¬
sionary ideas that had risen from the
ruins. These were the decades of the
First World War, the first socialist
revolution, the birth of Nietzscheanism
and the spread of Freudianism. All
these unprecedented occurrences had a
strong influence on sculpture, poetry,
painting, the novel and the theatre,
shattering old forms and dictating new
subject-matter.
Gibran was immersed in his epoch,
an actor not a spectator. His migration
from Mount Lebanon to Boston may
be seen as the journey of a prophet.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
C 03
E «
CD
c
.a a>
c^Dfu. </7. iuo aJi^-f ***>/£ /&~<r»*-A*rÇJ. f
^r- /LT U^^^/^^Jh i i il I ± /Cnt&t. '
f^r^-y A***-* UJsrt. Ar-' Á4-K
Gibran expressed himself with equal facility in Arabic and English. Above, a frag¬
ment from his "Notebooks".
When the Ottomans began their
slaughtering in the Levant, all the in¬
telligentsia of Syria (which then includ¬
ed the whole of the Fertile Crescent
region) fled. For Gibran and a few
others, the goal was a spiritual one. For
them migration was a stage which
would necessarily be followed by a
return to the homeland. They did not
go in search of refuge, exile, trade or
money, but in search of a vision,
following a circular path that necessari¬
ly ended where it began.
The second feature that epitomizes
the life and works of Gibran is that
while he lived at a geographical
distance from his native land, he main¬
tained close links with it and with its
history. Although distant from
Lebanon, he was always strongly in¬
fluenced by émigré Arab culture and
the Arabic press, and remained in cons¬
tant communication with his
homeland. Geographical distance gave
him a broader and deeper insight into
The earth is my homeland and
humanity is my family.
Gibran
his country and enabled him more
swiftly and more perceptively to iden¬
tify its misfortunes and see where the
remedies might lie. Thus the essential
feature of his migration was that it took
him both away from and back to his
homeland; it was a temporary measure
to enable him to trace the lineaments of
his prophetic message, not to arm
himself with a residence permit. Hence
26
Gibran's "modernity" was the reverse
side of his deep-rooted cultural identi¬
ty; his migration was at once an inward
and an outward journey.
Gibran's greatest creative achieve¬
ment was, then, his own life within
whose short span he was only forty-
eight years old when he died the
public and private dimensions were in¬
distinguishable. His views on women,
marriage and the clergy were not simp¬
ly theoretical standpoints expressed in
his writings and drawings but
represented his practical views on life,
love and religion. More than half a cen¬
tury after the death of Gibran we are
beginning to understand the major im¬
portance of his book The Prophet
(1923); we should not, however, fail to
recognize the equal importance of his
work Jesus, the Son of Man. In fact,
the key to Gibran's works lies in his at¬
titude towards authority, whether
represented by established tradition,
prevailing convention, religious institu¬
tion, social structure, economic system
or foreign occupying power.
The "movement" that grew out of
Gibran's life and art (drawing, painting
and writing) was clearly founded by a
man possessed of prophetic vision.
And his founding of the "Pen
League", his defence of his country
against the Ottomans, his long dedica¬
tion to art in his New York studio and
to literature in a secluded house in
Boston were for him indissociable ac¬
tivities. His metrical verse and his free
verse, his narrative prose and
dialogues, plays and novels, all served
that one vision. The forms these
writings took grew naturally out of
I am a traveller and a navigator,
and each day I discover a new
country in my soul. My friend,
you and I will live as strangers to
this life, strangers to one another
and to ourselves, until the day
when you will speak and I will
listen to you believing that your
voice is mine, until the day when
I shall stand before you, thinking
that I am before a mirror.
Gibran
their subject-matter, for Gibran did
not set out deliberately to modernize
poetry and language. His constant con¬
cern, once he had discovered his life's
mission, was to express his "vision".
Was Gibran a Romantic when he
wrote A Tear and a Smile? Did he
become a symbolist with The Madman,
The Forerunner and The Wanderer?
Was he a philosopher in The Prophet,
The Garden of the Prophet and The
Earth Gods and a novelist in Spirits
Rebellious and Broken Wings?
Gibran's life and death, his writings
and works of visual art defy such
classification to which, moreover, he
was opposed throughout his life. He
fought against all forms of pigeon¬
holing, against all that would strait-
jacket thoughts and feelings.
Throughout his spiritual journey,
Gibran Khalil Gibran remained true to
his vision and through his art and
writings in the first three decades of this
century he proclaimed his prophetic
message.
Ghali Shukri
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
FRANZ KAFKA (1883-1924)
The devil's pay
by Maurice Nadeau
FRANZ Kafka was born in Prague
a hundred years ago, on 3 July
1883. Portraits and photos of him
until just before he died, ravaged by con¬
sumption, on 3 June 1924 show an eter¬
nal adolescent just as Lautréamont and
Rimbaud remained adolescent. There are
authors who do not age, and works
which, from the moment they are writ¬
ten, rush forward in time so that a cen¬
tury or more later we still breathlessly try
to catch up with them. The Penal Settle¬
ment, The Trial and The Castle are
stories we have known we read about
them in the newspaper only this
morningand, alas, they still presage the
future. In the last fifty years since
Kafka's work, most of which was
published posthumously, has come to
light, how many times has its author been
hailed as a saint and prophet? Today
does he not possess one of the common
characteristics of the prophet, namely
that he is (officially) not without honour
save in his own country?
He was nothing if not a man of
Prague, the city where he was born and is
buried. He was more a man of Prague
than he was Jewish (although he was
born a Jew) or German (although his
MAURICE NADEAU, French man of letters,
has been publisher and editor-in-chief of the
literary magazine La Quinzaine Littéraire since
1966, and publisher of Lettres Nouvelles
since 1953. Notable among his published
works are Histoire du Surréalisme (1945), Le
Roman Français depuis la Guerre (new edition
1969), and Gustave Flaubert, Ecrivain (1969).
writings are an adornment of German
literature). Fundamentally neither
Jewish, nor Czech, nor German, or else
all three at once, he belonged to no
category which would enclose him within
a people, a nation (or the conglomerate
of nations which comprised the Austro-
Hungarian empire) or a confession. A
member of the German Jewish minority
which engaged in trade and sent its
children to the Gymnasium, he found
himself at that intersection of space and
time where his family happened to live,
where he worked in an insurance office,
and where his grave is today. Look at his
contemporaries: the superabundantly
Czech Jaroslav Hasek, the undeniably
Austrian Franz Werfel, the militant Jew
Max Brod. It is as if they all insisted on
affiliation to a community. Kafka was
his own man. If he immersed himself in
Hebrew towards the end of his life,
perhaps it was because he felt that he was
so little a Jew. His German is sometimes
the German of the ghetto and sometimes
a German that can be traced directly back
to Goethe. There is nothing in common
with the expressionists of Vienna or
Berlin. What other literary influences
helped to shape him? Flaubert and
Dickens, a Frenchman and an
Englishman.
Shortly after meeting Max Brod, the
faithful friend (whose loyalty went so far
as the act of betrayal which brought
Kafka posthumous fame) Kafka tried to
collaborate with him in writing a novel.
Little came of it. However, the Descrip¬
tion of a Struggle (1905) and Prepara¬
tions for a Country Wedding (1907), in
between which a doctorate in'
jurisprudence had led to a position as the
conscientious and efficient employee of a
workers' insurance company, are already
pure Kafkawhat Sartre would call for¬
ty years later "a universe both fantastic
and rigorously true." In fact, and this
would only be realized later, Kafka was
writing in a new way.
But only on condition that he had the
time and the material conditions in which
he could write. Perhaps, as many com¬
mentators insisted after his death, the
drama of Kafka's life was metaphysical.
First and foremost, however, it was
physical: the drama of someone who car¬
ries within himself a world which he can¬
not bring to birth, trapped as he is bet¬
ween two swing doors in his room in the
family home, and, during the day, in his
office at the "Workers' Accident In¬
surance". He can only indulge his vice,
his reason for living, when all is asleep.
Short descriptions, suddenly interrupted,
a gesture captured in an instant, unusual
and fleeting situationsthese are the in¬
gredients of Kafka's Diaries, interspers¬
ed with outbursts of rage at the short
span of time at his disposal, complaints
about the task he feels entrusted to per¬
form and cannot, and those constant, ap¬
palling headaches. The monotony is
deadly. With a headstrong passion he
takes an interest in a troupe of Yiddish
actors and in its director Jizschak Löwy.
After holidaying with Kafka on the
Italian lakes, Max Brod makes him col¬
lect the texts of his first book Medita¬
tions, which would appear in December
1912.
Franz Kafka (1883-1924) was born and buried in Prague. Below, panorama of towers over the Moldau River,
Prague. In foreground, the Klementinum, a former Jesuit college and university, with its church, library and (far
left) astronomical tower.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
iv 1912 was the crucial year. In January
he drafted the first chapters of The Man
who Disappeared, which would later
become America. While staying with
Max Brod in August, he met Felice
Bauer, his future fiancée. During the
night of 22-23 September he wrote The
Judgment at a single sitting. In
November and December he wrote
Metamorphosis.
In The Man who Disappeared he ad¬
mitted that he had unconsciously
plagiarized Dickens. The "fiancée" was
the woman he wished to marry and could
not bring himself to marry. One of the
dramas of his life, this engagement would
last until the final break came in 1917.
But before that it would be broken off,
then be renewed again, and he would
carry on a 500-letter correspondence, an
astonishing psychological document
If the book we are reading does
not awaken us with a punch on
the skull, what's the good of
reading it?
	Kafka
which shows him oscillating between
commitment and withdrawal, between
the desire to create a family in order to
enter fully into life, and the rejection of
the life of a petty bourgeois. And all the
time, looming in the background, is the
even greater fear that "the other" will in¬
terfere in what is most important to the
writer, his most precious occupation.
After writing The Judgment in a single
night, Kafka expressed his jubilation in
these words: "The fearful strain and joy,
how the story developed before me, as if
I were advancing over water... How
everything can be said, how for
everything, for the strangest fancies,
there waits a great fire in which they
perish and rise up again... Only in this
way can writing be done, only with such
coherence, with such a complete opening
out of the body and the soul. "Here can
be heard the voice of the young Flaubert,
who used almost identical words in his
letters. Flaubert, whose Sentimental
Education Kafka always had with him
and passages of which he knew by heart.
Writing can be a godlike activity or a
devilish one. Kafka talks of plunging into
"the underworld", of conjuring forth
"phantoms" and "demons", of
shadowy indulgence in guilty activities,
of living in the anguish of having
penetrated once and for all the
"nothingness" of life. "The point of
view of art and the point of view of life
are different even in the artist", he wrote
in Preparations for a Wedding. Like
Flaubert he knew that art is not life but
"a place where, in the dark void, without
foreknowledge, the rays of light can be
powerfully intercepted." These rays
make it possible to reveal the "truth"
around which art flies "with the set pur¬
pose of not burning itself." Were it to
burn itself there it would be extinguished
in the common reality, whereas what
must be done is to open reality to its own
potentiality, to "deliver" reality of what
it carries obscurely within itself. The
writer lives vicariously and in a state of
anticipation. The empty page is his
battlefield.
Judging from comments which have
been made on the occasion of the
centenary of his birth, this image of
Kafka as a writer and nothing else is tend¬
ing to become the new stereotype of the
author of The Trial. Perhaps it is more
accurate than the previous ones: Max
Franz Kafka in 1916 or 1917, The
photo, probably from a passport, is
now in the archives of the Beth
Hatefutsoth Museum, Tel Aviv.
Brod's "Saint Kafka" dedicated to
asceticism and transcendence; the
mystical Kafka who was for a time coupl¬
ed with an equally indecisive suitor,
Kierkegaard, the author of the Diary ofa
Seducer and the fiancée of Régine Olsen;
André Breton's Kafka, a practitioner of
"black humour"; Camus's Kafka, the
all-time champion of "the absurd"; and
many more, including the Kafka of
whom in 1945 a newspaper asked, not
altogether frivolously, whether he should
not be "burned" since he was distracting
young people from fundamental, life-
enhancing tasks. This effigy of Kafka as
"Kafka in Prague", a draw¬
ing by the Austrian artist
Hans Fronius, who il¬
lustrated most of the great
Czech writer's works.
Photo © Edimedia. Paris.
Private Collection
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
writer, the Kafka who noted in his diary
the famous sentence "All that is not
literature bores me and I hate it", is the
most acceptable effigy of all. But what
kind of a writer was he? In what sense
was he different from other writers?
The French critics Maurice Blanchot
and Jean Starobinski have said that the
difference lies in the fact that Kafka is
himself the material of his novels. Even
his characters are so much his other
selves that they are identified by the in¬
itial of his name or, like Samsa in
Metamorphosis, by a name related to it
in some way. Furthermore, their torment
is his, even more than the feeling of guilt
which nags at them, the search for the
transgression for which they are being
punished. If the punishment is to be
"slaughtered like a dog" or changed into
a beetle (or a monkey, or a mouse), the
transgression must be unatonable,
perhaps sacrilegious, a serious attack on
the order of things. This is what he wrote
to Max Brod about literary creation:
"Last night I saw clearly, with the
distinctness of a childhood object lesson,
that it is pay for serving the devil. This
descent towards dark forces, this
unleashing of spirits naturally bound,
these dubious embraces, and everything
that can happen down below and which is
unknown above, when one writes these
stories in the sun..." This "devil's pay",
a "sweet and marvelous reward", does
not redeem the transgression, which gives
rise to fear and remorse. "Terrible fear
of death". Not, says Kafka, because it
would end my life but because it would
prevent me from acceding to life "since I
have not yet lived." A terrible confes¬
sion. "Why," he asks again, "is the final
word always: 'I could live and I do not
live'?"
This incapacity to be born in the world,
this fate of someone who does not live, a
zombie, lead to despair but do not con¬
ceal the cardinal sin from him who has
reached the limits of extreme lucidity: "I
have not redeemed myself through
literature... What I have played at is real¬
ly going to happen." Joseph K., executed
on a patch of waste ground, is a victim of
this tragic "game", which will have no
end for the land surveyor in The Castle.
Kafka, writes Starobinski, is
simultaneously "the object of his cre¬
ation" and "the object of his destruc¬
tion". His work bears within itself its
own extinction. It consumes itself as it
burns, in unfulfilment, and perhaps this
is why Kafka did not wish it to survive
him. It is like the machine in The Penal
"Panorama of my existence" is the title Kafka gave to this card he drew in 1918 and
sent to his younger sister Ottla, the only person apart from his friend and biographer
Max Brod from whom he had no secrets.
©
ta.y»v
,$sJM*,
Ktr*. If**«*
¿tX fa/ -VovJ-^t; i
"Vt Ml**;!* «^ tf**v líF-^T' <h Jvvt~* !ri~~\
A /MA^
>(¿t*, Ha»«uv
t w"í ft
34I
Manuscript page from
Kafka's Diary for 1910.
The text reads: "I write
this very decidedly out
of despair over my
body and over a future
with this body.
"When despair shows
itself so definitely, is so
tied to its object, so
pent up, as in a soldier
who covers a retreat
and thus lets himself be
torn to pieces, then it is
not true despair. True
despair overreaches its
goal immediately and
always, (at this comma
it became clear that on¬
ly the first sentence
was correct)."
Men are bound together by ropes,
and it 's a bad thing even when the
ropes loosen around someone
and he falls into the void a little
below the others, but when the
ropes snap and he falls totally, it
is horrible. That is why we should
hold each to the other.
Kafka
Settlement which collapses when it in¬
scribes the fatal sentence on the skin of
the man who usually handles it and who
has offered himself to torture.
How can this body of work whose
material is its author and which is
nourished by his fantasms and his tor¬
ment render such a precise, glowing im¬
age, so clear-cut in its horror, of the
world in which we live? Of Auschwitz,
the totalitarian bureaucracies, everything
which systematically destroys the human
in man? This aspect of Kafka's work
the diagnosis it makes of our universe
has received too much attention for there
to be any need to return to it here. Kafka
says that the force of literature derives
from its nature as an "observation-act",
that is, "observation of a superior kind. . .
which obeys the laws of its own move¬
ment." Movement which mingles, which
should succeed in mingling, with the very
movement of the writing as long as they
both transgress their bound? as long as
(in the words of the Diaries) an assault
on the frontiers" is carried out. Then
comes the moment when, thanks to an
unassailable dialectic, and through a
rigorous form of language, a world
begins to unfold. It is either
transcendental, nor "realistii nor
"different", but it is neve iheless
"something else" just as the X-ray photo
of a body is not the same thing as the
body which has been pierced by the X-
rays; with its dark areas (its unsaid) and
its lines of force finally visible. Kafka
sees just as clearly into himself as nto the
reality around him, even into tht reality
gestating in everyday life. It is this lucidi-
CONTINUED ON PAGE 34
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The
United Nations
University
The United Nations University (UNU) was
established by the General Assembly of the
United Nations in 1972 and began operations
from its headquarters in Tokyo in 1975. Since
September 1980 the UNU's Rector has been
Soedjatmoko, an Indonesian scholar in the field
of international development and politics. Inter¬
viewed for the Unesco Courier by Gérard
Viratelle (of the Paris daily Le MondeJ and Rana
Gauhar (of Third World Quarterly, London) he
discusses the UNU's aims, activities and
prospects.
Gérard Viratelle: There are already several research in¬
stitutions in the United Nations system. Why was the UN
University created?
Soedjatmoko: The major characteristic of the United Na¬
tions University is that it is not an ¡ntergovernmental
body. Non-governmental organizations have greater
freedom to study problems and to come up with findings
without taking into account governmental sensitivities.
Many UN institutions, before they publish reports, have
to check those reports with Governments. We don't
have this obligation. Take, for instance, international
economic problems. The International Monetary Fund
and the World Bank combined have the largest research
capability in the world on international economic issues.
Still, there are several problems that they have not in
vestigated. Why? Because they are too sensitive for
Governments. We feel therefore that the UN University
has an obligation, for instance, to look at global economic
policy problems, especially at the kind of problems that
other intergovernmental agencies have difficulties handl¬
ing. There is an important role for such a non¬
governmental body.
Rana Gauhar: What are your hopes for the World Institute
for Development Economics Research which the Univer¬
sity is planning to set up?
Soedjatmoko: First, I think that the current recession has
made it very clear that it is no longer possible to think of
development only within the isolation of a single nation-
State. The development theory must be revised to take
into account international factors. At the same time, the
impact of national developmental policies on the interna¬
tional system has not been adequately studied. The
whole bank problem is an example of that.
There is also a dearth of study of which development
policies have succeeded and which have not, and why.
The search for more effective development theories
would be helped very much by independent assessments
of which policies have worked and why and which
policies have not worked and why.
Then there is the question of the workings of the inter¬
national economic system. The capacity of the world to
move more effectively in international development is
constrained by the malfunctioning of the international
system. These problems arising from the crisis of the in¬
ternational economic system should be looked at. It
would be very important for an independent institution to
do research on issues of particular relevance to the Third
World, without becoming partisan in the sense of taking
sides. We are a UN institution and we have to serve the
needs of all mankind, but we also have a commitment to
redress the disparities in the world. There ¡s a need for
that kind of research, and I intend that this new institu¬
tion should do it.
Viratelle: Is there not a kind of rivalry between UNU and
some other UN institutions? How is the co-ordination
done?
Human and Social Development and Co-existence of Peoples, Cultures and Social Systems is
one of the five broad themes or "problem areas" which form the framework for UN University
research programmes and projects. Migration within and across national boundaries by migrant
workers and refugees from war, famine and other disasters poses a major problem and over
the coming decades will change the ethnic and cultural composition of many countries and in¬
crease social tensions. Below, on the march in the high plateau near Tug Wajale, in north¬
western Somalia.
5ií i'A
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Soedjatmoko: I don't think it ¡s a problem. We are too
small to be a threat to anyone, and fortunately so. We try
to co-ordinate. We join all kinds of co-ordinating
meetings, but that is not the important thing. More im¬
portant than co-ordination is collaboration and we try to
collaborate with larger United Nations agencies in
specific areas. With Unesco we have a number of col¬
laborative projects in the areas of communications and
the social sciences. In the area of development theory we
have collaborative projects with other UN agencies. I am
not worried about competition. I think a little competition
is good, it keeps everyone on his toes, and as long as it
leads to better quality it is fine.
Gauhar: Let's talk about the University's Charter and the
autonomy which is written into it. As each of your pro¬
jects develops further for instance the one on human
nutritional requirements and malnutrition you are going
to come closer and closer to political questions. At what
stage do you think you will need this academic freedom
when your projects get past collecting data and actually
point fingers at very unpleasant truths?
Soedjatmoko: I believe it is the legitimate task of the
social sciences and the policy sciences to study and
make recommendations as to what kind of food policies
in a given situation might be the best to ensure that the
poorest of the poor get as much nutritional value as
possible. If there are Governments which take exception
to this, then we have a problem. But I don't expect the
problem to arise. Many Governments run into food policy
difficulties, not because they want to but because they
have generally been looking at the supply side of food
and not at the consumption side. So my own experience
is that Governments are first rather surprised, then rather
pleased, that somebody is suggesting ways of making
sure that the poor get more value out of their purchasing
power. Of course, at some point one has to deal with the
fact that purchasing power is not enough and then one
will have to suggest policies. I believe it is the task of the
United Nations University to make recommendations
that are comprehensive and that pay special attention to
Photo © Bernhard Wagner, Stuttgart
Senegalese food scientist and UN University Fellow
Cheikh N'Dlaye examines a small storage silo which has
been made rat-proof using techniques developed at the
Central Food Technology Research Institute, Mysore, In¬
dia, an associated institution of the UN University.
the weakest and poorest in our societies. I think that this
is an obligation. I don't really expect any problems in
terms of academic freedom.
Viratelle: How is the Rector of the University chosen?
Since you have a governing Council what freedom of ac¬
tion do you have?
Soedjatmoko: First, the Secretary-General of the UN and
the Director-General of Unesco agree on the appointment
of the Rector from a list of nominations from various
sources. Once the Rector is appointed, he is a member of
the governing Council. The Rector is the chief Academic
and Administrative Officer, so the selection of research
topics, the direction of the research and the selection of
people is very much his responsibility always, of
course, in consultation with the Council. The Council ap¬
proves the budget and by doing so has its say on the pro¬
posals submitted by the Rector.
In institutional terms, the academic freedom and
autonomy of the University which we have talked about
is based on the Endowment Fund, the income from which
it is the University's responsibility alone to manage.
Viratelle: How are the developing countries participating
in your work and what can they expect from it?
Soedjatmoko: It was the vote of the developing countries
that pushed the resolution for the establishment of the
UN University through the General Assembly in 1 972. If
you disregard the contribution of Japan, more than 50
per cent of the remaining contributions come from the
Third World.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Under the UN University's Pro¬
gramme on the Use and
Management of Natural
Resources, the Alps, the Rocky
Mountains and the Himalayas
are linked in an ambitious pro¬
ject on mountain hazards map¬
ping, a new technique which
aims to define the extent, type
and degree of danger posed by
landslides, avalanches and
similar natural hazards. In
mountainous regions of the
world landslides are a major
threat, increasing soil erosion,
disrupting roads and destroying
houses and painstakingly con¬
structed terracing like these ir¬
rigated rice terraces (left) in
Nepal on the edge of the
Kathmandu Valley.
Viratelle: What do they get for it?
Soedjatmoko: Our research is primarily meant to con¬
tribute to knowledge that is of use to developing coun¬
tries in their development process. We are also providing
training designed to strengthen Third World institutions.
We are currently exploring the establishment of an Inter¬
national Institute for Natural Resources in Africa. This
would help strengthen local institutions that deal with
the various dimensions of the resource problem but don't
have the desirable concentration of expertise.
Viratelle: You don't have any student body, but you
undertake training through fellowships?
Soedjatmoko: Yes, our Fellows are post-graduates in
developing countries. Many of these young scholars are
isolated. It is our task to help identify them and give them
an opportunity to develop, particularly through inter¬
disciplinary training, and go back to their countries with
their skills reinforced. Our Fellowship programme is being
strengthened and developed and I think it makes a
valuable contribution to building Third World institutions
through relevant advanced training for Third World
scholars and researchers.
Then we are also concerned with improving the
dissemination of scientific information. This is one of the
reasons why we have established a new division, the
Global Learning Division, because it is very obvious that
even the available scientific knowledge does not reach
the people who need that knowledge. There are many
reasons why this knowledge does not reach them and we
want to have a more systematic look at that problem. To
take one example: as world population increases, more
and more people will have to move from the lowlands to
the uplands. Upland agriculture is usually done on
marginal land, land that is less fertile, with thin top soil,
and so on. Now if you increase the number of people liv¬
ing on that top soil, it will go beyond the ecological carry¬
ing capacity. You can increase the carrying capacity only
througfi the application of scientific knowledge and
32
The Marga Institute in Colom¬
bo, Sri Lanka, is the co¬
ordinating institution for the UN
University's project for the
study and sharing of traditional
technologies. Above, the tradi¬
tional method of cutting logs in
a Sri Lankan village.
through different social arrangements. There is no way
of bringing that about unless that scientific knowledge
reaches the peasants. This is one of the major world
problems, in my opinion.
Gauhar: Do you feel it is important for peasants
everywhere to know or to share in the experience of
peasants in other regions that will be helpful to them? Is
this something which you plan to do in the future, or is
the UNU already doing it?
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Soedjatmoko: We are at present engaged in activities
along these lines. For instance, we have started on a
village video network activity. The idea is to see whether
it is possible for villagers to talk to other villagers without
interlocutors. In the field of rural energy systems we have
asked villagers in China to put themselves on video tapes
to explain why they have decided to have biogas and
bioconversion systems which created an integrated rural
energy system that has brought them considerable pro¬
sperity. Then they made a second video tape that show¬
ed the technology they developed. This is now being
adapted and shown in other places, in other villages, in
other countries, as well as in China itself. My main in¬
terest in developing this video programme is to transfer,
not technology, but hope; to show villagers, who have
been bludgeoned into passivity for many centuries either
by feudal lords or by the colonial régimes or later on by
military régimes, that it is possible for villagers to do
something for themselves. That, I think, is the most im¬
portant message that we could help bring, by simply
showing that there are villages that have made a success
of things.
There are many local success stories in the Third
World, which are not known. The thing is to eliminate
both the urban interlocutor of your own nationality and
the foreign interlocutor, and let villagers talk about
themselves and their achievements to other villagers.
Gauhar: I hate to inject a note of pessimism, but whether
you are thinking of transferring technology or hope to
peasants don't you have to by-pass the very people you
mentioned earlier, the military or landlords, or the urban
interlocutor?
Soedjatmoko: Yes. A medium like video has multipur¬
pose functions because we have found that there are
Governments which are interested in showing their tapes
as teaching material for their own civil servants.
Gauhar: It creates a greater consciousness?
Soedjatmoko: Yes. A lot of what we perceive as suppres¬
sion arises from ignorance rather than malice. I think that
one of the major problems that has led to violence and op¬
pression has not been any philosophical commitment to
it, but an incapacity to manage social transformations.
Gauhar: Wherever there is change, there is potential for
conflict. Are you saying that it is not necessary that
change will come about violently and that violence is in
fact a kind of mismanagement?
Soedjatmoko: I did not say that. I did not say that it is
possible to eliminate violence completely. The University
is studying the problem of the violence that accompanies
social change. When we started to design the "Peace
and Global Transformation" programme, we were faced
with the fact that there are more than 200 peace
research institutions in the world. What could our role
be? We found that very few studies had been made on
peace as it relates to inevitable social change. If you ac¬
cept that the world is changing, then the study of peace
and conflict resolution should aim at the reduction, as far
as possible, of violence and human suffering. For in¬
stance, massive migration is now increasingly a feature
of global change; the ethnic and cultural composition of
all countries is in the process of changing and this leads
to tension. The tensions may explode along fault lines not
only of class but also of ethnicity, of race and of religion.
These problems have not been sufficiently studied, and
we should understand the phenomenon more deeply.
Such understanding is necessary to enhance the adjust¬
ment capacity of society, because the movement of peo¬
ple from poor areas to rich areas and to empty spaces is
going to increase; no government can do much about it.
And it is a potential source of major conflict.
Gauhar: Although you don't have a student body as
such, every major educational institution tries to in¬
culcate certain values in people who come into contact
with it. Do you think that there are certain values which
are specifically those of the UNU and which UNU Fellows
or other people who come into contact with you should
benefit from? Perhaps a greater global awareness...?
Soedjatmoko: Yes. There are certain values which the
UNU is committed to. Probably the most important is the
sense of human solidarity. The UNU is an academic in¬
stitution which is not linked to any national interest but
is based on an acceptance of human solidarity. I think
that is a very important value perhaps the most impor¬
tant value of all.
1
^1 I The UNU is a new kind of university
1\B I designed to: 1) increase understanding
w ^fc^ of causes and solutions of what its
Charter terms "pressing global problems of human sur¬
vival, development and welfare;" 2) increase the prac¬
tical impact of research and post-graduate training by
organizing collaboration among scientists and scholars
across national boundaries; and 3) strengthen research,
training and dissemination of knowledge activities, par¬
ticularly in developing countries.
In its initial phase, the University developed three
programmesin World Hunger, the Use and Manage¬
ment of Natural Resources, and Human and Social
Development. Their scope has been broadened with the
adoption of a Medium-Term Perspective for the years
1982-1987 to ensure that this early work remains rele¬
vant to the current world situation. The new University
Programme that is emerging, under the leadership of its
second Rector, Soedjatmoko, is thus an organic growth
of the initial work.
This unified University Programme is planned and car¬
ried out by three divisions, each with a distinctive func¬
tion. Problems are explored at the local and country level
by the Development Studies Division. Their broader im¬
plications are looked at under the Regional and Global
Studies Division. The results of the work are com¬
municated to various users in the new Information
Society through the Global Learning Division.
The University's priority concerns are defined by five
themes which range across the modern world's most
urgent anxieties: 1. Peace, Security, Conflict Resolution
and Global Transformation; 2. The Global Economy;
3. Hunger, Poverty, Resources and the Environment;
4. Human and Social Development and the Co¬
existence of Peoples, Cultures and Social Systems; and
5. Science and Technology and Their Social and Ethical
Implications.
In the 1984-1985 biennium, the University's work
will fall under eight programme areas: 1. Peace and
Global Transformation; 2. The Global Economy;
3. Energy Systems and Policy; 4. Resource Policy and
Management; 5. Food-Energy Nexus; 6. Food, Nutri¬
tion, Biotechnology and Poverty; 7. Human and Social
Development; and 8. Science, Technology and the In¬
formation Society.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
(CONTINUED FROM PAGE 29)
ty which in turn terrifies us. The world he
has taught us to read through his eyes is
indeed Kafkaesque.
The image which remains with us a
hundred years after his birth is as com¬
posite as the multitude of interpretations
his work has inspired. We have long been
familiar with the sanatorium patient,
ravaged by guilt and illness, dying of con¬
sumption without ever having succeeded
in really living, with illness serving as a
symbol for the profound evil which he
tried to exorcise through writing. It is
amazing to learn from witnesses that he
was a vigorous, athletic young man who
drew gusts of laughter from his writer
friends when he read them the first
chapter of The Trial. Without denying
the existence of a fundamental despair in
Kafka, one of these friends adds, "he
had weapons with which to defend
himself: they were humour, irony, and
hope." He did not hesitate to assert that
"hope finally triumphed; he possessed a
literally messianic force." Setting aside
the religious connotation, Kafka gave his
friends an impression of force, and it is
not pity he calls for, but the admiration
we feel for those who have had the
courage to take the measure of their evil,
of our evil, and who struggle with all
their might to overcome it.
"Strange and mysterious is the con¬
solation given by literature," he wrote.
Could this be because "literature alone
draws from itself no succour, does not in¬
habit itself, is both a game and despair"?
This desperate game, says another
witness, was "his only chance of hap¬
piness". The attempt of a man to destroy
himself through writing becomes in our
eyes one of the most solid constructions
in all literature, even in its in¬
completeness. The paradox continues to
the inevitable end. While in a matter of
months the illness made terrible inroads
in a body which it would even deprive of
speech, Kafka was at peace when he died
in the arms of his young friend Dora Dy-
mant. Long before he had asked Max
Brod to burn his manuscripts. But
perhaps on 3 June 1924 he thought in¬
stead that Franz Kafka was achieving his
transmutation. It was then that he came
into the world, for ever more numerous
generations of readers.
Maurice Nadeau
G3 rp Gl I
World Assembly for Peace,
against Nuclear War
Some 3,000 participants from 1 40 coun¬
tries attended a World Assembly for
Peace and Life, Against Nuclear War
which was held in Prague (Czechoslova¬
kia) from 21 to 26 June 1983. In res¬
ponse to growing threats to world peace
and the grave dangers engendered by the
arms race, speakers drew attention to
the various aspects of the danger of war;
to the role of education for peace; to the
interdependence of problems of develop¬
ment, international co-operation and the
right to self-determination; and to the
efforts of the United Nations and Unesco
in favour of peace. The significance of
the Assembly was stressed in addresses
by Mr. Gustav Husak, President of the
Czechoslovak Socialist Republic and by
Mr. Romesh Chandra, Chairman of the
World Peace Council. A message was
addressed to the Assembly by Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-
General of Unesco, and an account was
given of the Intergovernmental Confer¬
ence on international education held at
Unesco earlier this year. The final appeal
of the Assembly and reports produced by
working groups are to be transmitted to
the United Nations.
International Appeal
Launched for Havana Site
On 19 July the Director-General of
Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow,
launched an international appeal for the
safeguard of the "Plaza Vieja" (Old
Square) and fortifications of the Old City
of Havana, Cuba. Stressing the impor¬
tance of this architectural complex, in¬
scribed on Unesco's World Heritage List
in 1982, Mr. M'Bow said that the Plaza
Vieja is one of the most representative
examples of architecture originating in
the encounter of various cultures "under
the Caribbean sun". The square,
recognized by the Cuban Government as
a national monument in 1976, is a main
feature of old Havana in which baroque,
neoclassical and Art Nouveau styles are
all mixed in a typically Cuban composi¬
tion. The full text of the Director-
General's appeal will be published in a
forthcoming issue of the Unesco Courier
to be devoted to the arts in Latin
America.
Simón Bolívar Prize
Awarded for First Time
At a solemn ceremony held in Caracas
(Venezuela) on 24 July 1983 to com¬
memorate the bicentenary of the birth of
Simón Bolívar the Liberator, the Director-
General of Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, awarded the International Simón
Bolívar Prize to its first recipients. King
Juan Carlos of Spain, and Nelson
Mandela, the African National Congress
leader imprisoned in South Africa. The
Prize was created in 1 978 to reward ac¬
tivity of outstanding merit which, in ac¬
cordance with the ideals of Simón
Bolívar, has contributed to the freedom,
independence and dignity of peoples, to
the strengthening of solidarity among na¬
tions, and to the establishment of a new
and more equitable international order. In
his address, Mr. M'Bow said that the
Prize had been awarded to King Juan
Carlos in recognition of his role in leading
"the process which has culminated, not
without incident, in the establishment in
Spain of a democratic State based on the
fundamental values of liberty, equality
and justice". Turning to Mr. Oliver Tam¬
bo, President of the African National
Congress, who represented Mr. Mandela
at the ceremony, the Director-General
said on presenting him with the Simón
Bolívar Prize diploma and medal: "I
should like to assure [Nelson Mandela]
that even from the depths of his cell he
has been more than ever among us, and
that through us the immense majority of
mankind is with him, hears his call and
strives to bring him succour, in increas¬
ingly far-reaching and diverse ways, until
the people of Nelson Mandela recon¬
quers its full rights." Nelson Mandela
concluded his statement from the dock
at his trial nearly 20 years ago with these
words: "I have cherished the ideal of a
democratic and free society in which all
persons live together in harmony and
with equal opportunities. It is an ideal
which I hope to live for and to achieve.
But if needs be, it is an ¡deal for which I
am prepared to die".
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on re¬
quest. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the
editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier
staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head,
Inc., 111 West 40th Street, New York, U.S.A.; (3)
Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road. Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Mohammed Reza Berenji (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Kim U-Yearn (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slo¬
vene: Punisa Pavlovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Pavel Pissarev (Sofia)
Greek: Alchis Angelou
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
All correspondence should be addressed to the
Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published...
"Simón Bolívar occupies a prominent place among the
great figures of universal history whom the United Na¬
tions system recognizes as its precursors. . . He was not
just the hero of one country or a group of countries... or
even of the American continent alone; by virtue of the
universal scope of his thought, he endeavoured to voice
the hopes of all the peoples of the world..."
In these words Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-
General of Unesco, sums up the historical importance
and continuing influence of Simón Bolivar in a brief
foreword to an anthology of Bolivar's speeches and
writings published by Unesco as a contribution to the
world-wide celebrations to mark the bicentenary of the
birth of the "Liberator".
The anthology is published in English, Trench and
Spanish editions and was compiled by the Venezuelan
historian José Luis Salcedo Bastardo, who also wrote the
Introduction and provided the Chronology and the
Bibliographical and Biographical Notes. The prologue is
by the Venezuelan writer Arturo Uslar Pietri.
326 pages 75 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscription
rates in local currency, will be supplied on
request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colhng-
wood Victoria 3066,. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd PO Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals
Dominie Pty Subscriptions Dept , P 0 Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub- agent. United Nations Association of
Australia, P.O. Box 175, 5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth
Street, Melbourne Victoria 3000 AUSTRIA.
Buchhandlung Gerold and Co , Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna
BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International Ltd , Ittefaq
Building, 1, R K. Mission Rd , Hatkhola, Dacca 3
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only N V
Handelmaatschappij Keesing Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne- Antwerpen French edition and general Unesco
publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060
Brussels, CCP000-0070823-1 3 - BURMA. Trade Corpora¬
tion No. 9, 550-552 Merchant Street, Rangoon CANADA.
Renouf Publishing Co Ltd, 21 82 St Catherine Street West,
Montreal, Que H3H 1 M7. - CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Bei|ing
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue, P 0
Box 1722, Nicosia - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - SNTL,
Spalena 5 1 , Prague 1 (Permanent display), Zahranicni
literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 For Slovakia only Alfa
Verlag Publishers, Hurbanovo nam 6,893 31 Bratislava
CSSR DENMARK. Munksgaard Export and Subscription
Service, 35 Norre Sogade, DK 1370, Copenhagen K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. - ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10, Suomalamen Kirjakauppa Oy,
Koivuvaarankuja 2, 01 640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans, C C P 12598-48
- GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig,
Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen
Buchhandlungen in the G D R - FED. REP. OF GERMANY^
For the Unesco Courier (German, English, French and Spanish
editions) Mr H Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb,
Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For other Unesco publica¬
tions Karger Verlag, Germenng/Munchen For scientific maps
only Geo Center, Postfach 800830, Stuttgart 80 -GHANA.
Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd , P.O. Box 195, Accra, Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd , P.O Box 7869, Accra, The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra, The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast, The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1 , Legón.
- GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG.
Federal Publications (HK) Ltd , 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion,
1 2 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co , 1 3-1 5, Lock
Road, Kowloo/v Hong Kong Government Information Services,
Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22 Ice Street
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V,
A K V Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI - ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd , Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13, 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2, 5-9-41/1
Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP), 80/1 Mahatma Gandhf
Road, Bangalore-560001, 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad- 500001 Sub-Depots Oxford Book & Stationery
Co 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 7001 6, Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001. IN¬
DONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto
Iskandardmata III, Jakarta, Gramedia Bookshop, J) Gadjah
Mada 1 09, Jakarta, Indira P T , Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37, Jakar¬
ta Pusat IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue, P 0 Box
314/1486, Teheran, Iranian Nat Comm. for Unesco, Ave Iran-
chahr Chomah No 300, B P 1533, Teheran -IRAQ. McKen-
zie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad - IRELAND. The
Educational Company of Ireland Ltd , Ballymount Road,
Walkmstown, Dublin 12 - ISRAEL. ABC Bookstore Ltd ,
PO Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000 -
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P 0 Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc ,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome,
Minato-ku, Tokyo 105, KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P 0. Box 30571, Nairobi KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P 0 Box Central 64, Seoul
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait;
for the Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P O. Box SAFA
4541, Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa LIBERIA. Cole and Yan-
cy Bookshops Ltd , P 0 Box 286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency
for Development of Publication & Distribution, P 0 Box 34-35,
Tripoli - LUXEMBOURG. Líbrame Paul Brück, 22, Grande-
Rue, Luxembourg MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co¬
operative Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur 22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapien-
zas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta - MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd , 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis MONACO.
British Library, 30 bd des Moulins, Monte-Carlo.
NETHERLANDS. For periodicals only. Dekker and Nordemann
NV, P 0. Box 1 97, 1 000 AD Amsterddam; for publications only:
KEESING BOEKEN B.V , Postbus 1 1 1 8, 1 000 BC Amsterdam.
- NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N.V., P O.
Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P O. Box 5344, Auckland, 1 30, Oxford Terrace,
PO. Box 1721 Chnstchurch, Alma Street, PO Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O Box 1104, Dunedin, Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. - NIGERIA The University
Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P 0 286,
The University Bookshop of Nsukka, The University Bookshop
of Lagos, The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana
NORWAY. All publications Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers),
Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1, Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssentret, POB 307 Blmdern, Oslo 3 For Unesco
Courier only A.S Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo
6 - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-
azam, P 0 Box No 729, Lahore 3 - PHILIPPINES. The
Modern Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P 0 Box 632, Manila
D-404 POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury t Nauki, War¬
saw, Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No 7 00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda Livrana Por¬
tugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National
Bookshop, P O. Box 48, Mahé, New Service Ltd., Kingsgate
House, PO. Box 131, Mahé - SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay,
Njala University and Sierra Leone Diocesan Bookshops,
Freetown - SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd ,
No 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road,
Singapore 19 - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC.
Modern Book Shop and General, P 0 Box 951, Mogadiscio
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications Van Schaik's Book-store
(Pty ) Ltd , Libn Building, Church Street, P O Box 924, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only. Central News agen¬
cy, P.O Box 1033, Johannesburg - SRI LANKA. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata POB 244
Colombo 2 - SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P 0 Box 1 1 18,
Khartoum - SWEDEN. All publications A/BC E Fntzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16 For the Unesco Courier Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse Zurich Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236 - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam
Bookshop, P.O B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam - THAILAND.
Nibondh and Co Ltd , 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg
Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Pamt, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok, Suksit Siam Company, 1715
Rama IV Road, Bangkok. - TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. Na¬
tional Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St Clair,
Trinidad, W I - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi,
No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul - UGANDA.
Uganda Bookshop, P.O Box 7145, Kampala UNITED
KINGDOM. H M Stationery Office, P O Box 569, London,
SEI, and Govt. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol, for scientific maps only
McCarta Ltd , 1 22 King's Cross Road, London WÇ1 X 9 DS -
UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South, New
York, NY. 10010 U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kmga,
Moscow, G-200 - YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Ihca 30/11,
Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana, Nolit, Terazi-
je 27/1 1, Belgrade. - ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd ,
67 Union Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Steps to learning
Near Kathmandu, Neto!, rice is grown intensively
on terraced hillsides iJJhed with countless irrigation
canals. These steeply sloping áreas are prone to
landslides, flooding and other hazards. To minimize
the prgbtejnjjgffgnby the local populations and irp-
proj^^^HKse management, mapping and risk
assessment work has been carried out in the region
-fiy an international team of scientists. The project
is one of many undertaken in recent years by the-
United Nations UniversityJsee article).
Photo Bruno Barbey Í Magnum, Paris
]]>
</page>
</document>
