<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074778eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
A window
open on the world
The cultural roots of a new nation
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
O
Turkey
Bronze Age
Mother-Goddess
This bronze figurine
(20.4 cm high) of a mother-
goddess nursing her child is
an example of the original
art developed by
metalworkers of Asia
Minor in the latter half of
the 3rd millennium BC. It
was found in a royal
necropolis at Horoztepe in
northern Anatolia. The
Bronze Age tombs at .
Horoztepe contained a rich
store of female figurines
and other metal objects
such as openwork bronze
standards adorned with
geometrical patterns and
figures of animals, birds
and flowers. Figurine
shown here is now in the
Archaeological Museum at
Ankara.
Photo © Gallimard,
La Photothèque,
Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COMlCr
OCTOBER 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (21 N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street. New York, U.S.A.: (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander B roído (Tel Aviv)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Portuguese Edition:
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey)
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
4 CHILDREN OF APARTHEID
by Mazisi Kunene
12 Papua New Guinea
THE CULTURAL ROOTS OF A NEW NATION
by John Kolia
17 MALANGGAN ART OF NEW IRELAND
by Patrice Godin
20 PROFILE OF PAPUA NEW GUINEA TODAY
22 BERTINA GOES TO ROME
A girl reporter gives a child's-eye-view
of an international conference
by Bertina Wijngaarden
23 BITTER HARVEST
Half the world's population concerned
in the drama of agrarian reform
28 Music of the Gulf
THE SONG OF THE PEARL-FISHERS
by Habib Hassan Tourna
32 THE MINARET OF JAM
A Unesco project to restore
an historic Afghan monument
by Andrea Bruno
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
TURKEY: Bronze-Age Mother-goddess
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special Supplement
Cover
Carved in wood and with an elaborate hair
crest supported on a rattan frame, this
tatanua mask is a stylized portrait of a dead
person. It comes from the north-eastern
coast of New Ireland, one of some 600 islands
that, together with the eastern portion of the
island of New Guinea, constitute the recently
(1975) independent State of Papua New
Guinea. The rich and diverse cultural
traditions of this new nation are matched by
the wealth of its natural resources. In 1976
Papua New Guinea became the 138th
Member State of Unesco.
Photo © Jennifer Steele, Australian Museum, Sydney
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Children
of
apartheid
by Mazisi Kunene
IT has been the fate of several gen¬
erations of the past three or four hun¬
dred years to experience conquest and
occupation of their homelands on a
massive scale. This same process has led to
the emergence in recent years of a much
more closely knit world, of world links and
international institutions such as Unesco
itself, and of a spirit of world citizenry that
seeks to establish a wider world polity.
More and more, nations are realizing that
the various regions of the world we call
countries are no more than villages on the
overall cosmic scale. No longer can any na¬
tion afford to detach itself from the fate of
MAZISI KUNENE is a scholar noted for his
work on the epics of his people, the Zulu, and a
poet who has himself written an epic on the Zulu
Emperor Shaka the Great. His English verse
translation of this work, originally written in
Zulu, has just been published as Emperor Shaka
the Great by Heinemann Educational Books,
Ltd., London, and is the latest title in the African
Authors Series of Unesco's Literature Transla¬
tions Collection. A former head of the depart¬
ment ofAfrican studies of the University College
at Roma (in what is now Lesotho) and director
of education for the South African United Front,
he is currently Associate Professor in African
Literature and Languages at the University of
California, Los Angeles.
others on the same planet, much less af¬
ford an education that distorts the reality of
others.
This has particular implications for the
generation that is' emerging today. Educa¬
tion can no longer concern itself with the
local virtues of insiders and the vices of
outsiders. It can no longer afford the
ethnocentric conceptions which characr
terized the age of expansionism and
occupation.
Education in this context means more
than formal classroom education and ex¬
tends to cover the social education a child
acquires through its association with the
adult population which bears the primary
responsibility for teaching children ethics
and skills. The education of children,
broadly speaking, must prepare them for a
changed world as visualized by a sensitive
and imaginative adult population.
It is within this context that the life and
development of children in South Africa
should be examined. First we should focus
on the black child since it is the black child
who is disadvantaged and victimized by the
system.
The black child in South Africa is born »
stateless, without an automatic citizenship Y
This photo is a reminder, in
International Year of the Child,
that the apartheid regime in
South Africa counts thousands
upon thousands of child-victims
whose plight is as .tragic as that
of their elders. The oppression
and exploitation which are
institutionalized in apartheid
pervade their existence,
affecting their education, health,
nutrition and housing, even in
some cases claiming their
parents' lives. The photo shows
the orphan of the black South
African leader Steve Biko at his
father's funeral. A founder of
the black consciousness
movement which is dedicated to
helping black Africans to
recover their dignity, Steve Biko
died aged thirty in Pretoria Jail
on 12 September 1977, after
being detained without trial,
kept naked for much of the time
in his cell, and being brutally
interrogated. An enquiry was
held into the circumstances of
his death, which aroused
international indignation, but no
criminal proceedings were
instigated. On 8 December 1977,
the General Assembly of the
United Nations adopted a
resolution expressing inter alia
"deep shock" at his "cowardly
and dastardly murder in
detention" and condemned
the "arbitrary arrest,
detention and torture which led
to his murder".
Photo © International Defence
and Aid Fund, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Like their parents, black children in South
Africa face a life as the unprivileged
outcasts of a rich society. Their housing is
liable to be poor and insufficient, while
standards of white housing and other
amenities are high. Apartheid policy is to
house only migrant black workers In the
urban areas and not to provide for family
housing. Shanty-towns mushroom on the
outskirts of towns and cities (below) where
blacks live in wretched conditions in
"locations" to which they must return each
evening under curfew regulations. Left, a
group of children asleep on the steps of
Cape Town City Hall.
Photos © Steve Bloom and International Defence and Aid Fund,
London
that assumes responsibility for its health,
mental development and all-round cultural
and educational welfare. The black child is
born into a deliberately contrived poverty,
which is entirely unnecessary in a country
that is among the world's richest in
resources.
Not too far from the black child's
precinct live the white children and their
parents. These white children have so
much abundance that they play games
with the most coveted morsels of food;
food that could, in fact, feed two or three
children who are dying of kwashiorkor.
Should the parents of a white child choose
they may keep a dog or a cat. These would
be fed on the best food available with the
result that many animals live far better than
humans. This in itself is an education. For
in time the child comes to value animals
more highly than members of its own
(human) race.
Examining the physical world into which
black children are born, we notice that they
are born of parents who are so impoverish¬
ed that they are physically weak and
unhealthy. Consequently, the children
themselves are physically weak and
unhealthy. They may well be potentially
among the 200 per 1,000 infants who are
going to die. If they are from the rural areas
their chances of survival are even lower.
They may be among the 400 per 1,000 in¬
fants destined to die young. The only
reason for this state of affairs is that they
are victims of a deliberate policy of racial
discrimination. Should they survive the
hazardous period of infancy, they remain
candidates for many illnesses and diseases
that beset those who are members of their
race.
Let us take the example of two typical
girl babies, one black, the other white.
Although the black child's parents pay
the highest taxes in the land (750 Rands
minimum taxable income for whites; 360
Rands minimum taxable income for
blacks), her area suffers gross neglect by
the cleaning and health services. Should
she fall ill, she has to undertake a long
journey to a crowded hospital where her
parents may have to wait with her in the
blazing sun the whole day. Why? Her peo¬
ple are supplied with only one doctor per
44,000 people, unlike the white child
whose people boast one doctor per 400
people.
The white child, then, not only eats well
and lives in a healthy and thoroughly super-
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
spoke of my plight to the tall Boer man
who owned the farm. I wanted employ¬
ment, any employment for whatever he
could give me. He was a strange and
unusual person. He actually invited me in,
staring straight into my eyes. I was not
afraid of him. I did not beg. I simply
repeated what I had said before.
"Without a word he went to the
telephone and talked to his brother in
Johannesburg. He asked if he had a job for
me in his firm, and when his brother
answered that he had, still without saying a
word, he wrote down the address and gave
vised environment, she is also given im¬
mediate medical safeguards. Should she
fall ill, all medical facilities are available to
her and within easy reach. She grows up
being looked after and catered for by all the
health agencies of the State. Her nanny
may well be the mother of the black child
who sings:
"So my child died
While I cared for the conqueror's
children,
While they grew fat
On the rich marrow of our forefathers'
wealth."
From this picture it is clear that neither
child is being trained for the world as it is
evolving. The white child develops a wrong
perspective, assuming that she belongs to
a world of an eternally privileged race. The
black child either develops a "victim syn¬
drome" or stocks up bitter hatred of the
brutal world around her. As she grows up
she may well witness the police brutally
dragging her parents out of bed in the early
hours of the morning, leaving her, if she is
lucky, in the care of an older sister. If not,
the neighbours, who know only too well
the violence of the life around them, may
look after her. The reason for the arrest of
her parents may be simply that they have
no permit to live in an urban area.
If such an infant has grown up in the
country, she may grow up knowing only
one parent, since her father may well be
contracted to work in the mines for three
years at a time. Thus she may grow up
without the mutual love and care of both
her parents, a factor that may in itself be
deeply disturbing to her. The "one parent"
feature is common because the laws are
such that the male parent is either working
on contract labour, or in jail (for one or
other of the numerous petty offences set
up by discriminatory legislation), or else his
work-place is so far away that he can only
come home occasionally.
Thus black children suffer not only from
a cruel physical environment but also from
the lack of normal upbringing enjoyed or¬
dinarily by all children. For them life is
hazardous physically, psychologically and
emotionally. For, indeed, even the adult life
that constitutes their environment breeds a
sense of social decay. In such a situation
the family either breaks up or must embark
on some illegal activity to survive. In this at¬
mosphere infants grow into adults very
quickly. For while- remaining physically
young, they have to learn to survive in an
adult, brutal world. They have to learn to lie
to protect their parents from the ubiquitous
police. They have to learn very early that
the adult world is a violent one capable of
extreme physical and mental abuse.
One African father tells a story whose
unusual happy ending only serves to em¬
phasize the horror of his harrowing ex¬
perience.
"I was desperate. I did not know what to
do. I had just lost my child through starva¬
tion. Does anyone know what it is for a
parent to watch a child starve to death? I
have often wondered as I passed by the
homes of the rich whites how they could
give food to animals while our children
starve to death.
"When my second child died I simply
walked until I came to a large farmhouse. I
The battered blackboard in this secondary school at Soweto, the black township
outside Johannesburg, could symbolize some of the grave handicaps which the
South African school system imposes on young blacks. Education is free and
compulsory for whites, but blacks have to purchase their school equipment and
contribute to school funds. Most black pupils never get beyond primary
education, and according to figures provided by the South African Institute of
Race Relations in 1977, 51.8 per cent of black South Africans over fifteen had
actually received no schooling whatever (the figure for whites was 0.9 per cent).
Figures cited in a paper presented by the International Labour Office to a seminar
on "Children under Apartheid" held at Unesco's Paris headquarters in June 1979
reveal that in 1975 only 0.09 per cent of all black pupils obtained the qualifications
necessary to enter university. In 1976-1977, 824 million Rands were spent on
education for whites (17.7 per cent of the population) while 117 million Rands
were spent on education for blacks (65.7 per cent of the population).
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
me twenty Rand. I was dumbfounded. My
ancestors had heard my prayer. From that
day I never ceased to dream of my child.
"When I arrived in Johannesburg, I was
met by a Mr. Buysen who picked me out
from among hundreds of faces. It was pro¬
bably because I was so lost and confused. I
can now tell the story because Mr. Ross
has given me and my family a new life. I
work as a manager on one of his farms and
live there with my family in a comfortable
house. Is this South Africa? How can peo¬
ple like this live here?"
I myself have witnessed many tragedies
involving children. Our neighbours lost
many children through kwashiorkor. The
symptoms were always the sameweep¬
ing eyes, swelling stomachs and slowed
down movements, followed almost in¬
evitably by death. Even as children we
knew that a particular child would soon die
because of these common symptoms.
Such a child would suddenly grow "old",
isolating himself or herself from the rest.
We too began to keep away, peering over
the fence to see what was happening to
our friend. Days after we would be told
that so and so had died.
I'll never forget how we carried our
young cousin in a wheelbarrow because no
ambulance was available for blacks. He
later died. He was only a little boy. He
seemed resigned to death and in his
"matured" state he was better able to cope
with his illness than we could. He was tell¬
ing us what to do like someone who had
suddenly attained great authority over life.
We all became part of a world he had
created. Even the adults stood back as we,
the children, sang and laughed under his
guidance.
- The truth of the matter is that children f
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
The peaceful rural scene, below, is only
superficially idyllic for it reflects what is for
thousands of African women a tragic situation.
Far from their husbands, employed in the white
urban communities, they must remain in special
locations set aside for blacks or in the bantustans.
To provide for their children they must eke a living
from the land. If they follow their husbands into
the white urban areas, they may be committing an
offence, and fear is added to their burden of
poverty. Left, a mother and her children flee in
terror from police and dogs raiding an "illegal"
squatter settlement near Cape Town.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
quickly grow up emotionally under these
' strange and violent conditions. Such
"growth" cannot allow for a healthy men¬
tal and emotional development. Some
children do indeed survive and live to be
normal adults; but some, more sensitive
than others, are permanently maimed by
the shock experiences of their childhood,
accounting for the high population of in¬
humane South African black asylums.
At this point let us observe black children
as they reach school-going age. Being
black they will have no government finan¬
ced or subsidized playschools and
therefore will have had very little exposure
to early pre-school education. The parents
are too busy eking out an existence to
teach their children anything. This is the
complete reverse of the normal African
tradition in~ which grandmothers and
mothers assume early responsibility for
teaching the children through tales and
children's poems.
Under the current discriminatory system
children have become part of the white
man's production machine. This may be
either directly or indirectly; in the latter in¬
stance, which is the more frequent, the
children take over the domestic chores so
that their parents can earn or supplement
their meagre, earnings.
When the children go to school for the
first time, they already consider
themselves, and are considered by their
parents, as an important means of improv¬
ing the family income. This is not so
strange as it might seem since their educa¬
tional life span is often shortjust long
enough to enable them to understand the
white bosses' instructions.
Formal education, therefore, is itself
designed to generate feelings of inferiority,
through an inferior quality education. Its
main purpose is to prepare the black child
for a pre-ordained inferior status in society.
This preparation takes elaborate forms.
Books, teaching and school facilities are all
designed to mould the black children to ac¬
cept their inferior position.
Under the apartheid system, the world is
limited not only for the black child but for
the white child as well. For white children
must also be taught to accept this system
as normal. They must be given a religion
and an ideology that claims supernatural
sanction for this brutalized and disem¬
bowelled world. Their vision of life, of the
world, of history, is circumscribed and
tailored to the propaganda requirements of
power and its maintenance. Hence, both
black and white children are unfit to live in
a wider, changing world. Indeed, the black
child, after rejecting the premise of apar¬
theid, is better adjusted to grow with a
growing world. Nevertheless, this is small
consolation in view of the many thousands
of black children that die needlessly of
disease and are mentally retarded by a
system that is brutal and tyrannical.
In the Year of the Child it is a terrible
paradox that South Africa, a country that
mercilessly maims children, finds moral and
financial support from nations that are
most vocal and sentimental about the
child. Could this be a case of a Judas
Iscariot wailing over his own betrayal?
Mazisi Kunene
3l_ .1 V
.c
5
\
c
c
£.
a.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
PAPUA NEW GUINEA
The cultural roots
of a new nation
by John Kolia
MMS
kEVEN hundred separate lan¬
guages"; "small-scale socie¬
ties"; "diversity of cultures";
how often one has heard or read these
stock phrases applied to that part of
Melanesia encompassed within the borders
of Papua New Guinea.
But such statements and the language
classifications they reflect are based on
data worked out in Europe many years ago.
One of the interesting results of modern
research, in fact, has been the increasing
importance attached to similarities rather
than differences of vocabulary, religion,
ways of maintaining law and order, ar¬
chitecture, artistic expression and customs
in Papua New Guinea, where in the past
there was extensive communication bet¬
ween the valleys, and between the moun¬
tains and the coast.
This is not to deny the existence of a
fascinating range of differences within
those broad similarities, so that the glory of
Papua New Guinea's culture could be sum¬
med up by the words diversity within unity.
The people practised animism, the
world's oldest religion. It was an organized
religion, if only at the local level. In fact it
was organized in a similar way throughout
the country, being based on the needs of
the group and the interpretation of the re¬
quirements of the spirits which, it was
believed, animated the behaviour and
structure of flora, fauna and rock with pur¬
pose, mystery and even caprice.
This religion is still being practised today,
but in adapted forms, for like all products
of the human mind it has had to adapt itself
to ever-changing circumstances. Perhaps
only in the Mortlock Islands of the North
Solomons province have the people
resisted the incursions of the Victorian
brand of Christianity. "We are Christians
now and have given up all our bad old
ways," many villagers will proudly but sad-
Painting of an ancestor or
clan spirit, right, is from a
cult-house at Ulupu In the
northern Maprik district
of Papua New Guinea.
Such portraits, painted
with earth pigments and
soot on sheaths of palm-
leaves sewn together,
were used to decorate the
cult-houses during
initiation ceremonies.
Whole galleries of similar
faces, arranged in rows
and combined with other
motifs, embellished the
gables of the cult-houses.
Remarkable mask on
opposite page is made of
ingeniously arranged
multicoloured feathers.
Photo H. Weber © Ethnological
Museum, Basle. Switzerland
JOHN ALEXANDER KOLIA, of Papua New
Guinea, is acting director of the Institute of
Papua New Guinea Studies and a specialist in
the country's oral history. The photos accompa¬
nying this article were provided by the author.
ly tell you, but fortunately the falsity of this
claim and the fancifulness of such attempts
to denigrate old customs are easily expos¬
ed. People have always philosophized and
attempted to relate the natural to the
supernatural, and the people of Papua New
Guinea today can still adapt to their own
pragmatic purposes theories which have
been introduced into their islands, just as
they have throughout their long history.
As in all well-integrated societies,
philosophy, religious or otherwise,
permeated such hard-to-compartmentalize
aspects of life as social control, artistic ex
pression, the economy, or, to use the con¬
venient Western gloss, customs. What an
intertwining .of customs must have been
evident to an ethnographer such as F.E.
Williams, when he first studied the culture
of the Orokolo people of the Gulf Province!
To superficial observers, of course, certain
ceremonies and seemingly bizarre
costumes appeared malevolent or quaint or
even comical; and these village dramas did
sometimes give rise to laughter.
Nevertheless, each part of the whole
related to other parts, as in the languages
used in ceremonies and in everyday life. I
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo Mas« Museum. Slav*, the Netherlands
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Thus words of similar origin are used to
describe a fish, an insect which it in some
way resembles, a species of vegetable, and
the behaviour of a certain kind of village
character. Such linguistic intra-reflection
may be found in a descriptive word, a
belief, a song or a decoration
Oral evidence provides further support
for the thesis of the homogeneity of
Melanesian customs. The history of -the
New Guinea ¡siands has yet to be written,
and since no one today, presumably,
would pretend that a short century of col¬
onial rule was anything but a recent foot¬
note at the end of fifty thousand years, it is
not surprising that researchers from such
institutions as the University of Papua New
Guinea, the Institute of Papua New Guinea
Studies and the National Museum are
working on the collection of oral evidence.
Much remains to be done, of course, but
the material collected so far has already
brought to light a complex pattern of
movements, battles and trade-routes. Just
as linguistic data eventually lead to the
drawing up of tentative maps and migra¬
tion patterns, the. collection of oral
evidence is now beginning to indicate the
broad lines of past developments. It has
been discovered, for instance, that the
Melanesians were capable not only of
fighting for their rights but of negotiating
peace treaties and coexisting in spite of
language barriers. A well-known example
of such coexistence is that of the Austrone-
sian Motu and the non-Austronesian Koita
at what was later to become Port Moresby.
This also serves to illustrate how history
might be distorted. We know about the
people near Port Moresby because mis¬
sionaries learnt Motu and wrote down as
much as they could understand of old
stories. But the same process of coex¬
istence was going on everywhere, for ex¬
ample between the Kiwai of Tureture on
the Western Province coast, and the non-
Kiwai of Kunini who lived inland of them.
In this case both languages were non-
Austronesian but from different language
families.
Although the Austronesian migrations
must have set up waves among the non-
Austronesian peoples (just as the later non-
Austronesians had done among the earlier
arrivals and the aboriginal peoples over
very long periods), any attempt to describe
Melanesian history as a vast battle between
the Austronesians and the non-
Austronesians would be an extreme over¬
simplification. There was hostility and co¬
existence between villages, between
dialect groups, between language families,
between highland and plain, and between-
¡slander and mainlander.
And there was also a borrowing of ideas,
designs, music and, of course, language,
so that new derivations emerged and what
A Kiwai woman in mourning. Photo was
taken in 1910 at Tirio village. Fly River,
Western Province of New Guinea.
Photo G. Landtman
© National Museum of Finland, Helsinki
The haus tambaran, or cult-house, photographed in the early 1900s at
Malinge village. East Sepik, Papua New Guinea. It was in the haus
tambaran that the menfolk performed the ceremonies of initiation into
the traditional spirit cult.
Photo Rosicke © 1977 The National Cultural Council,
Papua New Guinea
Young men wearing conical
kovave masks get ready for a
race on the beach at Orokolo,
Gulf Province. The masks,
representing the spirits of the
clan, were given to young men
after initiation. For the whole
of the next month they spent
each day at the beach,
receiving gifts of pigs which
they killed with their bows and
arrows. At the end of this
period, the masks were taken
away and burned.
Photo F.E. Williams © Office of Information,
Konedobu, Papua New Guinea
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Tolai dancers of eastern New Britain,
photographed in 1890 wearing traditional dress
and masks.
Photo © Linden Museum, Stuttgart, Fed. Rep. of Germany
the earliest foreign observers saw were the
end results themselves only tem¬
porary a whole series of events and
exchanges.
Today we can see the remnants of this
process. Undoubtedly Western imports,
material and otherwise, have made deep in¬
roads into traditional culture. In some
places the culture, or the visible expres¬
sions of it, have been greatly depleted,
while in others destruction and disruption
have been much less. In some cases, such
as Gogodala in the Western Province, there
has been a revival of culture.
Should we therefore all strive to
"preserve culture"? Obviously this would
be impossible and the "bottling" of past
ideals has often been derided. The glories
of the past can, however, be preserved
when found in the form of artefacts, as in
Papua New Guinea's National Museum.
Music can be preserved on tape, and dance
patterns and decorations on film. All these
things are being done under the auspices
of the National Cultural Council.
However, there is more to culture than
preservation. People can be encouraged to
be proud of their past as well as their
future. At the National Arts School the em¬
phasis is very much on the continuing
development of culture today. Modern in¬
fluences are bound to make themselves
felt, as they always have in the past. But
today the influences come from all over the
world. This is not a bad thing. What can be
done, however, is to help develop the k
natural expression of indigenous artists, Y
te* i m
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
and we should not be surprised if they
¡choose to reproduce patterns similar to
those of the past or to develop their own
patterns. Performances by the National
Theatre Company and at the Highlands
Raun Raun Theatre alternatively use or
blend the traditional and the original.
Similarly, such films as Tighten the Drums,
about self-decoration among the Engas,
and The Red Bowman, about the Ida sago
fertility ceremony of the inland West Sepik
province, present a record of customary
behaviour today. Tomorrow things may be
different. It is to be hoped that they will be
just as interesting and beautiful, and not
just a mish-mash of plastic, consumer
goods.
The skills people developed to fulfil their
functions in traditional society must have
been impressive. Those who see the
hastily-erected fibro buildings of Moresby
suburbia may well be tempted to indulge in
nostalgia and regret the craftsmanship and
architectural grace of some buildings such
as the ceremonial house known as the haus
tambaran. In many places individuals were
specialists. Many men might assist in mak¬
ing a canoe or in dragging a tree from the
forest, but an expert hand was needed to
transform the utilitarian object into
something which had a graphic reference
to the rest of life, or perhaps the after-life.
During the colonial era, some of these ar¬
tists were employed as "unskilled" labour
in the modern sector of the economy.
Those still practising can be encouraged to
fulfil their true roles today, although if they
choose to produce inferior art for the
Bristling masks
and sacred flutes
Top left, bukumo mask under construction at Kurwok village, northern New Guinea. It
was built on a wooden frame which fitted on the wearer's head and was held steady by
handles extending downwards parallel to his arms. Canes tipped with hornbill and eagle
feathers were stuck into the frame to form the huge bristling semi-circle. Initiation mask,
top right, was photographed at Angriman village. East Sepik district, in the early years of
the century. It probably represents the monster which, during initiation, was believed to
gobble up the candidates before spitting them out again as fully-fledged men. Above, two
flute-players, possibly at Kanganamam village, also in East Sepik district. During the
initiation ceremonies the sounds of the flute represent the spirits' voices. Traditionally
regarded as sacred, flutes like these were kept in the haus tambaran, concealed from the
eyes of non-initiates such as women and children.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
tourist trade, their choice can scarcely be
interfered with. Even out of this some new
and interesting form may emerge.
The psychological basis of the extensive
use of the mask has often intrigued the
speculative. The photo on page 16 (top
right) shows a most dramatic use of a mask
which is something more than a mask.
Does it conjure up fearful images or even
protests against "male chauvinism", a
popular accusation against traditional life?
Those who have lived in villages for any
length of time may have a different impres¬
sion. Women work hard, usually everybody
works hard; often village labour requires
co-operation of the sexes.
In some areas, women play highly impor¬
tant, even dominant roles, and descent
through the male line is by no means the
rule. In village life (but not always in the
towns) there are devices to protect the
rights and dignity of women. Women are
even capable of fighting alongside the
men; but the fact remains that the aged
and the women and children often depend¬
ed for the defence of their lives on the ac¬
tive males.
But these are just a few of the thousand
facets of Melanesian man's successful
handling of his environment, his use of
resources and his explanation of the world
around him and remote from him. This ex¬
planation was suitable for the "small-scale
society" in which he then lived, long before
the arrival of foreigners on his shores, but it
was not of course, primitive. "Primitive"
means something quite different, and
"small-scale" is also misleading. The ex¬
pressions of his philosophic outlook which
we outsiders are delightedly discovering
show that this outlook was a "large-scale"
one, for it penetrated to the heart of the
objects around him, into the earth itself
and to the distant horizons of the visible
universe.
John Kolia
Mask with wing-like flaps, above, is typical of the works of art inspired by the malanggan
ancestor and initiation ceremonies of New Ireland (see article). This example, which
actually comes from the Tanga Islands off the northern coast of New Ireland, is made of
painted tapa or bark-cloth (a papery material obtained from the inner bark of certain trees
such as the muiberry) stretched across a rattan frame. With financial aid from Unesco,
the Institute of Papua New Guinea Studies has assembled an important collection of
photographic documentation on malanggan art in the Australian Museum in Sydney.
Malanggan art
of New Ireland
by Patrice Godin
NEW Ireland, which forms part of the
Bismarck Archipelago north of
New Guinea, is the home of an
outstanding traditional art of richly carved
wooden objects known as malanggan.
These carvings were of fundamental impor¬
tance to the community, for they symboliz¬
ed the continuity of life.
PATRICE GODIN, a French ethnologist on the
staff of the Museum of African and Oceanian
Arts in Paris, specializes in the study of the arts
of the Bismarck Archipelago (northeast of New
Guinea).
The malanggan sculptures were the focal
point of the festivals which were held in
memory either of distant ancestors or of
those who had died more recently (between
one and five years before). These festivals
were also known as malanggan (in Raluana,
one of the languages spoken by the Tolai
people today, the word malanggan means
"to dance in honour of the dead"). These
ceremonies were also concerned with the
initiation of youths into manhood.
The malanggan sculptures, carved and
painted in fantastic openwork designs,
originated in the north of New Ireland,
although the ceremonies themselves are
associated with the southern part of the
island, and also with the Gazelle Peninsula
and other parts of northern New Britain,
the biggest island in the Bismarck k
Archipelago. f
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
, ,. The ornamental designs and motifs with
which the wooden figures were decorated
were the property of the elders of the clan,
who directed the wood-carvers and saw
that the appropriate symbols and forms
were used in their proper context.
Sometimes one clan would grant to another
the right to carve its ceremonial figures; if it
did so it was obliged to acquire a new set of
sculptures made by another clan.
Malanggan art thus established both a
"vertical" line of communication through a
genealogical transmission of motifs and
designs, and a "horizontal" line through the
buying and selling of the right to reproduce
these motifs and designs.
It might take years to prepare these im¬
posing wooden sculptures, which
presented a wealth of mythological themes
and totem animals, as well as depictions of
actual historical events. The individual
figures, each of which symbolized a dead
kinsman, were gathered inside a special
bamboo stockade, usually near to the clan's
cremation or burial ground. The craftsmen
also made masks adorned with cloth,
feathers, leaves and fibres; these too played
a part in the festivities.
The malanggan ceremonies thus formed
a link between the living and the dead, and
celebrated the initiation of young men. But
the full sequence of rites, which could last
for months, also had for the community as
a whole a wider significance, which reveal¬
ed itself in three main ways.
Firstly, the commemoration and in¬
vestiture ceremonies were an opportunity
for the dead person's material wealth to be
distributed among the community of the
living. The heirs and descendants took it
upon themselves to share among kinsfolk
and allies the dead man's pearls (which
served as money), pigs, household goods,
and so on.
Then too, the malanggan was a time to
strengthen alliances (marriage alliances as
well as political and military alliances) and
to step up exchanges between different
groups and clans.
Some of the guests might have to travel
great distances, for marital alliances and
commercial exchanges extended not only
throughout the Bismarck Archipelago but
beyond, to New Guinea, to Bougainville
and the Solomon Islands.
Thirdly, the malanggan provided for the
transmission, from one generation to the
next, of property rights as well as rituals
and prerogatives which were to be held in
trust. He who directed the ceremonies ac¬
quired the land, fishing rights, coconut
groves and magic powers (over wind, rain,
and plants) which had belonged to the dead
forebear. The heir thus achieved a higher
social status which enabled him to in¬
fluence decisions of local interest.
And so malanggan sculptures were
something more than "works of art". They
were part of a ritual which was one of the
most distinctive and spectacular features of
an entire system whose purpose was to
control the life of the community, through
marriages and deaths, festivities and ex¬
changes.
Once the ceremonies were over, the carv¬
ings were either burned or abandoned to
the rigours of the tropical climate. Their
fate thus matched either the slow putrefac¬
tion of the corpse or its cremation on the
territory of the clan. The cycle of existence
was now complete; what the dead could
not hand on had been recuperated by the
malanggan. Imagery had been used to
establish, in the face of the death of in¬
dividuals, the permanence of life.
Patrice Godin
The two side-panels flanking many malanggan-sty\e masks are
not ears but stylized representations of the planks which were
used to maintain a corpse's head upright before cremation.
Right, a bapong mask from the east coast of New Ireland.
Photo Jennifer Steele. Australian Museum. Sydney
:TTS #PyT
The fantastic combinations of forms, materials, techniques and
colours which typify the traditional sculpture of New Ireland all
went into the making of this mask from the island's northeast
coast. The bird, a motif which dominates the face and the high
openwork panels on each side, is a symbol often found in New
Ireland's malanggan art.
Photo Jennifer Steele, Australian Museum, Sydney
Wood, rattan and fibres are the materials of the nit mask, right.
As often, mollusc shells have been used as eyes ; they peer out
in a fixed, glittering stare from the elaborately intertwined
carvings of the face. Notice the vertical slot into which one of
the two missing side-panels once fitted.
18
Photo Ethnological Museu
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
il^H' 1
Bjg
&
fiäk
ir
'**
S
Mask from the northwest coast of New Ireland is made of wood,
fibres, bark-cloth and shells. In it are combined images of the
fish (each side of the face) and the snake (around the eye), while
bird motifs adorn the nose, fastened to the face by twine.
Photo Ethnology Museum, Berlir
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Profile of Papua
New Guinea today
THE mainland of Papua New Guinea
lies about 160 kilometres north of
the eastern half of Australia. It
comprises the eastern portion of the island
of New Guinea; the remainder of the island
is the Indonesian province of West Irian.
Although 85 per cent of Papua New
Guinea's land area is on the mainland, the
country also encompasses about 600
islands. In all, the country extends some
2,000 kilometres from east to west and
about 1,300 kilometres from north to
south. Its total land area is 463,000 square
kilometres slightly less than that of
Thailand but substantially more than that
of New Zealand or the Philippines.
The topography of Papua New Guinea is
rugged. Much of the land area of both the
mainland and the islands is characterized
by steep mountains, some peaking at more
than 5,000 metres.
Because of these formidable geographic
barriers, Papua New Guinea is culturally
and economically fragmented. The aircraft
was introduced much earlier and has
penetrated much farther than the
automobile or truck. Papua New Guinea is
said to have more airstrips per capita than
any other country in the world. The early
growth of air transport was associated with
gold mining activities, and it is used for
much of Papua New Guinea's internal ship¬
ping and most of its domestic passenger
traffic.
Roads are in the early stages of develop¬
ment, and the difficult climate and terrain
of Papua New Guinea make their construc¬
tion and maintenance expensive.
There is some inter-island coastal shipp¬
ing and this is a mode of transport with
considerable potential. Ocean shipping is
more important in overseas cargo traffic
than in coastal shipping, but most external
passenger traffic is carried by airlines.
In contrast with its transport facilities,
Papua New Guinea's communications
system is quite modern. The telecom¬
munications network has been significantly
improved in recent years; the posts and
telegraphs organization, a government-
owned enterprise, has built a trunk
telephone system that compares
favourably with those in many developed
countries. The principal means of mass
communication in Papua New Guinea is
radio broadcasting, which is also a govern¬
ment activity.
Papua New Guinea is rich in natural
resources. The many regions with good
soils and a variety of climatic conditions at
different elevations allow a wide spectrum
of agricultural possibilities. Subsistence
agriculture occupies 90 per cent of the
cultivated land and engages from 60 to 70
per cent of the population. Forest cover is
extensive and of considerable commercial
potential, but access to many forest areas
is difficult and expensive. A combination of
heavy rainfall and extensive mountain
ranges provides one of the world's richest
hydroelectric potentials.
Mineral resources are also good. Gold
was once the country's primary export, but
with the opening of the large opencast
mine on Bougainville in 1972, copper has
assumed first place among exports, now
accounting for roughly half of the
country's total exports and 20 to 30 per
cent of its gross domestic product. Gas
Youngsters in a Papua New
Guinea primary school
eagerly join in a question-
and-answer session during a
lesson aimed at developing
their language skills. English
is the main language of
instruction in Papua New
Guinea's school system, but
efforts are also being made
to transcribe, preserve and
promote the use of
vernacular languages.
Achievements in this field
were recognized at a
ceremony held on 10
September 1979 at Unesco's
Paris HQ, when the first
annual International Reading
Association Literacy Award
was presented to the Papua
New Guinea Branch of the
Summer Institute of
Linguistics, for its
educational work in local
languages.
drilling has resulted in encouraging, but not
yet commercially exploitable finds.
The 2.8 million people of Papua New
Guinea comprise a variety of distinct ethnic
groups, predominantly Melanesian. The
isolating effect of mountains, forests, large
rivers, and the sea has preserved unique
cultural and linguistic differences among
the various ethnic groups. Some 700 local
languages have been identified. The size of
these language groups ranges from 200 to
300 persons to the largest groups of about
100,000. There are, however, three
languages that are quite widely
spoken Pidgin, English, and Motu.
The social systems of the various groups
are also different. Patrilineal, matrilineal,
and ambilineal descent systems occur. The
social obligations among kinship groups
are complex. Members of the group have
an obligation to assist and support others
who might be in need and this has created
a kind of local social security system that
makes members reluctant to leave the pro¬
tection of the group environment. Indeed,
this clan group support has survived the
process of urbanization and serves as a
basis of settlement in towns. It establishes
claims and obligations among members
originating from the same clan group, and
mitigates the problems of urban im¬
migrants. Land ownership is also a com¬
munity right, with use granted to in¬
dividuals or families by agreement among
the owning group. About 97 per cent of the
land in Papua New Guinea is held by local
populations under these traditional tenure
systems.
The present population of Papua New
Guinea is nearly the same as that of New
Zealand but only about one-fifteenth that
Photo © J. Häuser, Basel, Switzerland
of the Philippines or Thailand. Thus, the
country has substantial physical size and a
population that is still relatively small.
About 40 per cent of the total population is
concentrated in the highlands in the central
mainland, a region that remained sheltered
from modern influences longer than many
others in the country. Only in the Eastern
Highlands is any population pressure yet
felt. Papua New Guinea's indigenous
population is increasing at an annual rate of
2.8 per cent, and it is expected to reach
about 3.5 million by the mid-1980s.
Because of this rapid growth, the age
structure of the population is quite young;
in 1971, 46 per cent of the population was
less than 15 years old.
Until quite recently, urban settlements
were restricted to the coastal areas and few
towns have more than 10,000 inhabitants.
The largest is the capital. Port Moresby,
with 76,000 residents, followed by the port .
town of Lae, with 38,000. This pattern is
now being changed rapidly by high rates of
rural-urban migration.
Papua New Guinea's school system was
pioneered by missionaries as early as 1872,
but the role of education did not begin to
expand rapidly until about 1960. In that
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
One of the world's newest nations, Papua New Guinea today
houses its national collections in one of the world's most modern
museums. Above, aerial view of some of the new buildings of
the National Museum and Art Gallery, opened in 1977 at Port
Moresby. Sloping roof covers the exhibition area; circular
buildings at right, typical of the round houses found in the New
Guinea highlands, form part of an outdoor entertainment area.
Although the Museum has over 20,000 items in its
anthropological collections, some parts of the country are poorly
represented; when the Museum was established many areas had
already been stripped of their traditional cultural objects by
collecting expeditions, and even in recent years there have
unfortunately been cases of looting and smuggling of works of
art from Papua New Guinea. The new museum facilities
effectively counter any argument against the return of artefacts
to Papua New Guinea on the grounds of failure to protect locally
the country's heritage or of lack of adequate conditions or staff.
Agreements on the return of works from several Australian
museums and from the National Museum of New Zealand have
already been implemented (see Unesco Courier, July 1978).
year 95,000 students were enrolled in
school, 92,000 of them in primary schools;
80 per cent of all primary students were in
mission schools.
By 1975, 69 per cent of the boys and 44
per cent of the girls in the 7-to-l2-year age
group were enrolled in primary school.
Secondary education is also developing. In
1975 there were about 30,000 secondary
students in 88 high schools, and another
10,500 students were in technical, voca¬
tional, or teacher training. Still, about 85
per cent of all enrolments were in primary
schools.
Papua New Guinea now has two univer¬
sities. The University of Papua New Guinea
in Port Moresby has some 1,000 full-time
and 500 part-time students, and the Univer¬
sity of Technology at Lae has around 1,000
students. These are exclusively boarding
institutions.
Health care in Papua New Guinea has
been well developed during the past
quarter century. A rural health care system
through village aid posts has been set up,
and today there are some 1,600 such
posts more than one for every eight
villages. Hospital cases are referred to one
of twenty-one district or base hospitals.
Training facilities are available locally for
aid post personnel and, since 1970, for
medical officers in the Faculty of Medicine
of the University of Papua New Guinea.
The process of modernization has made
giant strides in Papua New Guinea during
the past two or three generations, par¬
ticularly since World War II. Against Papua
New Guinea's complex historical and
geographical background and in the con¬
text of only recently (1975) acquired in¬
dependence, it is remarkable how rapidly
this process is taking effect.
i
This article presents information
contained in a World Bank report:
Papua New Guinea, Its Econo¬
mic Situation and Prospects
for Development. pub¬
lished by the World Bank in 1978.
A student audience in a
lecture hall of the
University of Papua New
Guinea. One of the
country's two
universities, it has some
1,000 full-time and 500
part-time students and is
situated at the national
capital. Port Moresby.
Photo © Parimage, Paris
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Bertina goes to Rome
A lot of people thought it rather risky; what would an eleven-year-old girl do and how
would she react when confronted with a World Conference on Agrarian Reform and Rural
Development?
Bertina Wijngaarden showed them that they need not have worried, writes Netherlands
author Matthijs de Vreede. When she arrived in Rome this summer to cover the
conference as a correspondent for the Netherlands children's monthly development-
magazine Samsam, she acted as professionally as the professionals.
Bertina had been sent to the conference because the staff of Samsam (a word borrowed
from Malaysian which means "all together") wanted to produce a special issue about
rural development and to have one of the magazine's readers as a special correspondent
in Rome. Bertina, who lives on a 33-hectare mechanized farm in the Weringermeer, one of
the new polders of the Netherlands, was chosen from all of Samsam's readers.
So Bertina and her mother were invited to Rome and she was accredited to the
conference as an official correspondent, the youngest ever to cover a UN meeting.
Bertina's performance appeared to be very rewarding indeed. Not only did she write a
good story, she also proved that a child of her age can be well aware of development
issues if he or she is regularly supplied with adequate information, written especially for
his or her age-group.
Bertina Wijngaarden, the youngest ever
reporter to be accredited to a United
Nations world conference, interviews Mr.
Hohamame Brah, Minister for Rural
Development of Niger, in the main
conference hall of the U.N. Food and
Agriculture Organization, Rome.
T
Jl É^^^HIS conference is meant for you and all the other chil¬
dren in the world. We cannot change the world of
today. But here, at this conference, we are trying to
make a better world for the future."
This is what I was told by Mr. Hernán Santa Cruz, the Secretary-
General of the World Conference on Agrarian Reform and Rural
Development that was held this summer in Rome from 12 to 20
July. I had been asked to go to the conference as a correspondent
for Samsam, a Dutch magazine about poor countries. My mother
went with me.
When we entered the room of Mr. Santa Cruz, with two photo¬
graphers, he kissed me on both cheeks and he told me that he was
63 years older than I was. "Once more", the photographers said.
One of them was lying on the floor to make a better picture.
Then I started to interview Mr. Santa Cruz. I asked him what the
conference would mean for the peoples in the poor countries and
he said : "The most important thing is that all those millions of far¬
mers who do not have enough land will get more of it, as well as
machines and all the rest they need to become good farmers".
'but don't they have to learn how to use these"Yes", I said,
machines?"
Mr. Santa Cruz told me that was also necessary and that the far¬
mers themselves should be involved in the making of the decisions.
For example, the people from the rich countries should not say:
"We will give you that and that". The farmers themselves should be
allowed to tell us what they think they need. We should help them
to be able to help themselves, in order that we will not have to help
them any more in the future. Mr. Santa Cruz also told me he hoped
that all the children who read my article would understand what
the conference was about and how very important it is for us to
help the peoples of the poor countries to solve their own problems
now. Because if we don't, things will be far worse when we are
grown up.
Then, we went into the big conference room. There, I inter¬
viewed the Minister of Rural Development from Niger, which is one
of the countries of the Sahel. He told me that there was still not
enough rain. I asked him why they did not irrigate the land. He
explained that there was enough water beneath the surface, but
they did not have the machines and the money to get it out and to
irrigate the land with it. When I wanted to know if there was
enough land for all the farmers in his country, he told me this was
not a problem and that there were enough agricultural schools. So
it is only a matter of money and equipment in this case.
Later that day I spoke to someone from the Dutch Ministry of
Foreign Affairs and I asked him what the Minister of Niger should
do. He told me that if Niger wanted machines and money, it should
make a plan and give it to the ambassador of the Netherlands or
another rich country. The ambassador would send the plan to his
government and if that government thought it was a good plan,
Niger would receive the money and the machines. So that's how it
works.
In the meantime, we had also been in the pressroom. There, I had
to work out the interviews. I had borrowed a little cassette recorder
which was no thicker than two pocketbooks. It was very handy
indeed. During the interviews I did not have to write down anything
and afterwards I could make notes from the tape.
In the pressroom, there were many journalists who wanted to
interview me. But in the end I only spoke to some reporters from
children's magazines in developing countries. I talked with people
from Ghana and Kenya and Tanzania and Iraq. That was very nice
indeed. In fact, I think it was very important to speak to people
from other children's magazines and to explain to those children
about the conference. All the other journalists were not so impor¬
tant. They only wanted to talk to me because I was the youngest
reporter that had ever been at a conference of the United Nations
and because of the International Year of the Child.
The conference itself was also very interesting. You could listen
with a little language-machine to what everybody said. It had seven
different languages. But everybody only talked about the use of dif¬
ferent words and sentences in a text that had been prepared before
the conference by Mr. Santa Cruz. If you wanted to hear about the
problems themselves, you had to talk to people outside the con¬
ference room.
While I was in the pressroom, I received an invitation to go to a
demonstration of agricultural helicopters the next evening. I went
there with my mother because we have a farm at home too, and it
was a good opportunity to see the countryside outside Rome.
There was a free dinner as well. During that trip I spoke to a lot of
people from developing countries. There was a gentleman from
Ghana who had a daughter of ten years old. That is about my age.
Her name was Ramata. He asked me if I wanted to be her penfriend
and he gave me her name and address. That night, we got back to
the hotel at two o'clock in the morning.
At the conference, I also spoke to representatives of women's
organizations, who explained that they had all kinds of program¬
mes to help mothers and children in developing countries. And
there was a lady from the Food and Agriculture Organization, the
FAO, who explained what she had been doing in Rwanda. That ¡s a
country I had never heard of because we have not yet had Africa in
school. But in Rwanda, people eat mainly beans. And, of course,
there are not enough vitamins in beans. Thus, the lady had gone
there for the FAO and had explained to the people about other
vegetables. The water is also bad in Rwanda. In fact, people should
boil it before they drink it, but there is not enough firewood to boil
the water. And so people get sick and have all kinds of worms. We
also had a look at Rome. We saw St. Peter's and the Colosseum
and the Forum and we did some shopping.
The last day, we went back to the conference because they wan¬
ted to have me in a film they were making. I had to work in the
pressroom again and also I had to sit in the big conference room,
listening to the language-machine. Afterwards we had to run back
to the hotel because we had a plane to catch. But the plane was
delayed and we arrived back in Holland very late. My father was at
the airport and he had been waiting for more than an hour and a
half. We went to eat something and then I wanted to go home
because I was very tired. Bertina Wijngaarden
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The urgent need to boost food production in the face of rising
demographic pressure is throwing into relief, perhaps more than
any other issue, the interdependence of the world community
and the necessity for international partnership. But today, as
countries tackle the problem through the adoption of appropriate
modern technology, figures show the persistent inequalities of
this partnership, in a world of haves and have-nots. Between 1961
and 1975, in the developing countries, consumption of fertilizer
tripled and the number of tractors per unit of land doubled, yet
the industrialized countries still consume five times as much
fertilizer per hectare of cultivated land and have ten times as
many tractors per thousand hectares of arable land. Furthermore,
the developing countries are still dependent on imports for more
than fifty per cent of the fertilizer they use.
Bitter harvest
Half the world's population
concerned in the drama
of agrarian reform
This article is based on extracts from a report of the United Nations Food and Agricul¬
ture Organization entitled Review and Analysis of Agrarian Reform and Rural
Development in the Developing Countries since the mid 1960s. This report was
drawn up as a preparatory reference document for the World Conference on Agrarian
Reform and Rural Development, held in Rome from 12 to 20 July 1979.
NEARLY half of all people on Earth live in the villages and
countryside of the developing world. Most are classed in
international statistics as "poor" and no less than
800 million as "destitute". Despite development efforts, the
number of these poor and destitute increases each year. Today
there is new cause for concern. The momentum of development is
slowing. Rates of growth in production and per capita incomes
have fallen, especially in the poorest countries, and several coun¬
tries are also facing acute environmental problems. If the goal of
development is growth with equity nationally and interna¬
tionally it can be seen clearly that the struggle is not being
won, and that the main burden of present trends falls on the rural
poor.
Developing countries have been engaged in an historic effort to
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
, build their national economies and escape the conditions of under¬
development and dependency which in many cases they inherited.
Largely owing to the apparent success of external models, they
have given the highest priorities to industrialization and other
urban-orientated concerns. It is now commonly understood that
within these development priorities the rural sector of national
economies has often been neglected.
The rural areas of the developing world continue to be marked
by a dualism between those who have been able to benefit from
new technological opportunities and the much larger number who
have not. On the one hand, this has led to a small and dynamic
modern sectorwith land, better education and greater access to
public serviceswhich has advanced very rapidly. On the other,
the great majority of rural people, lacking these advantages,
vegetate in traditional patterns of poverty. This appears to be true
in all regions. Landlessness is increasing very rapidly, leading to
uncontrolled migration to cities and the emergence of a rural
proletariat.
Issues of trade are of paramount importance. During the seven¬
ties the terms of trade of most developing countries which are not
exporters of petroleum have appreciably worsened. Continuing
tariff and non-tariff barriers against processed commodities of
developing countries, and consequently lack of access to markets,
have impeded the growth of agro-industries. Meanwhile the
burden of servicing debts has mounted, and official foreign
assistance remains far below target levels set by the donor coun¬
tries themselves.
Foreign private investment, while it has generally supported
host-country export goals, has been almost exclusively directed to
monoculture techniques, often highly mechanized, which tie rural
development to foreign capital, technology and markets without
regard for domestic food supply or levels of employment. In most
cases, dependence on this type of agriculture, whether foreign
owned or linked to foreign marketing networks, has added to the
problems of landlessness and reduced the possibility of
distributing resources more equitably.
The rural population of the less developed regions, which was
estimated at 2,060 million in 1975, is expected to rise to 2,890
million by the end of the century despite urban migration. A rise in
the agricultural labour force of more than 100 million is foreseen
with a subsequent decline in the land/man ratio in all regions. In
many areas it would fall to a level of less than one hectare per
member of the agricultural labour force. This would mean not only
a huge growth in the number of uneconomic, subsistence level
smallholdings, but also a dramatic increase in the number of peo¬
ple who are landless or who cannot be absorbed in agriculture.
Aside from the human problem of how these future millions will
live and work, projections of food needs also point to a dangerous
rise in dependency which is directly contrary to the goals of
developing countries. Current production and demand trends in¬
dicate that the cereal deficit of the developing world, which stood
at 16 million tons in 1970, will rise to over 90 million tons by 1985.
Degradation and depletion of natural resources in rural areas is
another significant factor. The ecological equilibrium appears to be
less stable in the tropics than in the temperate zone. The drive for
increased production has often caused the dislocation of well-
adapted, traditional agricultural systems and their sometimes
overhasty replacement by systems and technologies that are com¬
patible with neither ecological nor socio-economic conditions.
In the tropics, the removal of forest cover, especially on slopes,
has frequently led to serious soil erosion, downstream flooding
and siltation of rivers. In drier regions, similar results have followed
from an increase of livestock numbers and consequent overgrazing
which has stripped the soil of its vegetative cover. Deserts have
spread rapidly and with human consequences which became
sharply apparent with the tragic drought in the Sahelian zone of
Africa in the early seventies. Peasants who are deprived of access
to fertile soil, which is monopolized by large landowners or by
In many developing countries rural underdevelopment and
poverty have led to uncontrolled migration to the cities. The
extent of this poverty is devastating. In 1972, the International
Labour Organization estimated that 1,250 million people, more
than a quarter of the population of the world, were very poor.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
that 700 million of these were destitute, and that 42 per cent of
the population in the developing countries of Asia, 39 per cent in
Africa and 27 per cent in Latin America were living in absolute
poverty; of these, the overwhelming majority lived in rural areas.
Photo B. Wolff, United Nations
foreign companies, have no other resource but the cultivation of
marginal zones, contributing to erosion, deforestation and soil
exhaustion.
Much precious water is wasted through inefficient irrigation
systems, and it is estimated that almost half the existing irrigation
facilities in developing countries require improvement. Saliniza-
tion, alkalinization and waterlogging, all associated with poor
drainage, have reduced the productivity of millions of hectares of
irrigated land and large areas have had to be abandoned.
Disturbingly, in the most seriously affected countries, which are
mainly in Asia and Africa, the annual rate of growth of agricultural
production fell from 2.5 per cent in 1961-1970 to 1.9 per cent in
1970-1977. Meanwhile their population increased at a faster rate so
that per capita agricultural production has been lower in the seven¬
ties than in the sixties.
Among the main agricultural commodities, the most rapid in¬
creases in production have been for products that are mostly for
export, rather than for food crops grown principally by small
farmers. Examples of the former include soybeans (especially in
Argentina and Brazil), palm oil in Malaysia and tea in Kenya. The
production of staple foods, like rice, maize, millet and sorghum,
starchy roots and especially pulses, has risen only slowly. Notable
exceptions, however, are wheat production in India (which in¬
creased by 3.8 per cent a year from 1970 to 1977) and rice produc¬
tion in Pakistan (3.9 per cent a year).
Major programmes of development in the Far East since the mid-
sixties have concentrated upon new technology to increase crop
yields, known as the "Green Revolution" or the "Seed Fertilizer
Revolution", and involving the use of new high-yielding varieties.
But for many reasons the Green Revolution has brought only
limited benefit to the mass of small farmers, tenants and landless
labourers. For example, it is not at present applicable to many of
the crops like starchy roots and pulses which are important
sources of food for the poorer groups. The small farmers are usual¬
ly unable to increase their irrigation facilities to take full advantage
of the potential of new technology.
The Green Revolution can, in fact, increase the gap between the
rich and the poor. Even in parts of Africa, where land tenure
customs had afforded some protection against such
developments, changes in this customary tenure system in favour
of individual interests in land led to fundamental changes in the
traditional economic homogeneity and enabled privileged in¬
dividuals to accumulate wealth and influence.
Gross inequality of the distribution of rights to land remains a
fundamental problem in most developing countries. These trends
are most marked in the poorest countries of the world: Between
1960 and 1970, in Bangladesh, the proportion of farmers holding
less than one hectare increased from 52 to 66 per cent; and in India
from 40 to 51 per cent. In Latin America, the growth in the number
of small holdings and the consequent increase in poverty resulted
in migration from rural areas to urban slums. In Iraq, farmers with
less than 5 hectares formed 51 per cent of the total. In the African
countries of Ghana, Liberia and Malawi, farmers with less than one
hectare accounted for 38 per cent, 52 per cent and 39 per cent
respectively.
In most Latin American countries, where the bulk of land is held
within large estates, attempts to help the rural poor through tenan¬
cy legislation has had little impact. Imposing size limits on large
estates has proved to be more effective and several countries have
adopted this policy, some with considerable direct participation by
peasant organizations.
Despite the achievements of agrarian reform in some countries,
as late as 1973, 85 million people, constituting 70 per cent of the
farm population in Latin America, lived at the subsistence level.
The big landowners, 2 per cent of the farming population, earned
an average per capita income of US $ 2,560. In 1973 they controll¬
ed a total of 47 per cent of the agricultural land, while the mass of
the poor held only 2.5 per cent. I
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
y Most countries of the Near East have very special
characteristics, in particular aridity, customary laws conducive to
fragmentation, and nomadism, all of which influence the course of
distributive reform:
The reform movement for more equitable distribution of land
started with land reform programmes enacted in Egypt in 1952,
Iraq and Syria in 1958, and Iran in 1962, to expropriate the very
large estates, break the economic and political power of the large
landowners and improve the control of the poorer classes over
land.
In several countries redistribution of land rights was followed by
the adoption of group production arrangements, such as farm cor¬
porations in Iran, crop consolidation and co-operatives in Egypt,
agricultural co-operatives on land owned or controlled by the
Government in Sudan, and production co-operatives and State
farms in the People's Democratic Republic of Yemen.
In the majority of countries in the region attempts were made to
improve the conditions in the rural areas through large-scale irriga¬
tion schemes, with varying results. Egypt, using the waters of the
High Dam, reclaimed 380,000 hectares by the end of 1976, of
which about 100,000 hectares were distributed to landless families
in planned settlement schemes at an average cost of US $ 7,000
per family.
Afghanistan, the People's Democratic Republic of Yemen, Jor¬
dan, Libya and Egypt (among other countries) have developed set¬
tlement schemes for nomads. The People's Democratic Republic
of Yemen has recently implemented an integrated development
project raising the living standards of Bedouins, of which the main
objectives are to drill boreholes, to improve pasture, animal
breeding and veterinary services, and to initiate and develop social,
economic and administrative organization.
Algeria's experience merits special attention. Initially, foreign-
owned estates were consolidated and organized into self-
contained units (unités d'autogestion) averaging nearly 1,000 hec¬
tares. The programme involved basic modifications in the cropping
pattern in an attempt to limit the effects of foreign markets (e.g.
wine) on production.
Absentee land ownership was virtually abolished, ceilings were
placed on the size of landholdings, surplus land was distributed in
leaseholds, and beneficiaries were required to become members of
multi-purpose co-operatives.
Recently, a number of countries have promoted programmes to
restructure their rural areas, particularly Madagascar and Ethiopia.
The latter, with a high degree of concentration of landownership
and widespread share tenancy, had no significant reform until
1975, when new measures set low ceilings on landholdings. Pea¬
sant associations, which excluded landowners occupying more
than two hectares, played an important part in the redistribution of
expropriated land. Former serf tenures were abolished and many
landless people gained rights to land and water.
In many African countries, although there has been a shift in
programmes toward food crops since 1965, commodity develop¬
ment programmes continue to concentrate on export crops (e.g.
cotton in Mali, groundnuts in Senegal and Gambia, tobacco and
cotton in Tanzania and tea in Kenya). Some of these programmes
have ha'd notable successes and have benefited large numbers of
smallholders and helped to increase productivity.
A brief review of the development programmes in African coun¬
tries suggests that concentration of limited resources and trained
personnel on export crops does not always lead to an equitable
distribution of available resources which will also ensure adequate
food supplies for the poor.
However, studies of several African countries show that small
farmers have indeed proved to be an effective means of diffusing
innovations and economic development in countries where there is
a favourable environment and the right incentives.
In Asia there have been some striking successes. Where there
were strong peasant organizations and determined governments
(as in Kerala, India), many small tenants received ownership rights.
Some legislation of the early seventies (e.g. Philippines) eliminated
share tenancy, converting the sharecroppers into leaseholders,
and subsequently declaring all leaseholders to be outright owners.
The Philippines carried out experiments with new production ar¬
rangements designed to bring agrarian reform beneficiaries
together gradually for co-operative cultivation in which five to ten
neighbouring farms were merged into one production unit, and
provided with assistance in planning and finance by State
agencies.
The experience of the Republic of Korea may be useful to other
countries in Asia. This country has one of the world's lowest
land/man ratios and the average size of holdings after land reform
was only 0.9 hectare. Before reform the land was concentrated in a
few hands and mostly rented out in small units. The land reform of
1953 gave ownership to the former tenants and established a ceil¬
ing of 3 hectares per holding. Thus the rural community today is
composed of small peasant owners. Rice yield increased from 3.3
tons per hectare in 1952-1956 to 4.6 tons per hectare in 1970. There
was no increase in absolute poverty and gains from growth were
adequately spread.
In the People's Republic of China, all the available land is collec¬
tively owned by the commune; so rent has disappeared as a source
of income, inequality and power. The complex problem of landless
labour and uneconomic holdings faced by other countries after
redistribution of rights in land do not arise.
As land and other means of production are collectively owned,
the basic unit of cultivation is the work or production team of 25 to
30 families, whose area of operation varies from one commune to
another, but in most cases does not exceed 25 to 30 hec¬
tares enough to provide for economies of scale in the
Chinese context, and yet not so large as to alienate the peasant
from participatory processes.
The commune devotes 14 to 24 per cent of the gross revenue of
its agricultural production to capital investments within
agriculture, forestry, fisheries and agro-processing, and a social
fund supports welfare and culture activities. Labour is
remunerated on the basis of individual work points. The fact that
every member of a commune has a stake in returns from on-farm
and off-farm works is an incentive for construction works for such
purposes and has facilitated mobilization of collective labour for ir¬
rigation and land improvement. Farm land improvement construc¬
tion projects completed by the communes and brigades over the
years have greatly helped the struggle against drought, waterlogg¬
ing and other natural disasters.
Before the Cuban revolution more than half of all land was held
by large local and foreign landowners, and a significant proportion
was under, foreign sugarcane plantations. There were wide varia¬
tions jn value of the expropriated properties, but the greatest prob¬
lem was whether or not to redistribute them to the landless
workers. The Government, after a brief experiment with co¬
operatives, chose to run the large estates as State farms and by
1965 some 70 per cent of the agricultural land was on State farms
with the workers receiving fixed wages. Within the private sector
the small farmers have organized themselves into a national
association and have also formed service co-operatives. They still
own the land individually, but irrigation works, agricultural
machinery, storage arid drying sheds are owned collectively, sup¬
ported by credit obtained as a group.
Everywhere, the redistribution of private holdings has been the
most difficult reform to implement, calling for hard political deci¬
sions and popular support. In many cases, redistribution of private
lands has required constitutional amendments, legislation inspired
by social justice to close legal loopholes, and effective administra¬
tion and novel financial and technical measures to implement the
reform laws. In most developing countries, constitutional barriers
not in line with the current aspirations of the people remain and
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Left, aerial view shows
geometric patterns produced
by date-palm cultivation
along the shores of the
Euphrates in southern Iraq.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
will have to be removed before any large-scale reforms can be car¬
ried out.
Even where there were no constitutional obstacles, a serious
problem in implementing land reforms since the mid-1960s has
been ambiguity in the intent and language of the legislation.
In Latin America, for example, the main grounds for expropria¬
tion of large estates were inefficient production and failure to fulfil
the so-called "social function" of property. The latter concept was
never clearly defined in the legislation, nor were criteria for assess¬
ment established. In practice, large estates were regarded as fulfill¬
ing their social function if they were reasonably productive and
free of labour unrest. Thus laws passed during the sixties to set
ceilings on holdings often provided incentives for introducing new
technology which increased production and also reduced the resi¬
dent labour force on large estates in order to qualify for legal ex¬
emption from expropriation. Landowners continued to exercise
considerable political influence, and laws based on the notion of
social function offered ample leeway for legal manoeuvring. As a
result, very little land was affected and that which was ex
propriated was of marginal quality and required heavy public
investment.
In a number of cases attempts to redistribute land and water
rights have been impeded by lack of funds to pay for expropriated
land and to cover the costs of administration. Whereas some
governments have overcome the financial difficulties by con¬
fiscating land and other assets, others have devised systems of
compensation by State bonds or the repayment of costs by the
recipients of expropriated land.
The agrarian systems of the world reflect an immense variety of
considerations land availability and quality, water resources and
constraints of climate, population size and distribution, oppor¬
tunities for non-farm employment, stages of development in other
sectors, political and social value systems, customs and tradition,
and many more. Certainly no single model for agrarian structure is
applicable.
Despite these diversities, however, there are also a number of
points in common. Despite the variety of given agricultural condi¬
tions such as climate and soil, it would appear that most problems
are subject to amelioration or solution by social decisions and
actions.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Music of the Gulf
The song of
the pearl-fishers
by Habib Hassan Tourna
At a time when traditional music in many parts of the world is fading into
oblivion, in the coastal regions of the Gulf, the shallow sea between the Arabian
peninsula and Iran, time-honoured forms of musical expression have not only
survived but are showing renewed vitality. Here, sailors and desert nomads,
farmers and craftsmen, villagers and townsfolk, as well as peoples who have
come to the Gulf from many different lands, all have their own distinctive
musical forms which spring spontaneously from their lives, occupations and
cultural backgrounds. In this colourful kaleidoscope a notable place is held by
the Ifgeri music of the pearl-fishers, described in the article below. Here and in
photos on the next two pages, we present a medley of instrumentalists from the
Gulf who are keeping a diversity of cultural traditions alive in the modern world,
a diversity exemplified in the contrast between the precise, delicate movements
of the Ifgeri drummer, below, and the ecstatic fervour of the oboe player, right.
HABIB HASSAN TOUMA is a musicologist
specializing in Arabian music, on which he has
written several full-length studies and articles.
Born in Nazareth in 1934, he has since 1969 been
lecturing at the Free University of Berlin on Ara¬
bian and Middle Eastern Music. A staff member
of the International Institute for Comparative
Music Studies, he is in charge of the Institute's
Festival of Traditional Music, held each year in
Berlin.
FOR more than 4,000 years, the pearl-
fishers of Bahrain have been
harvesting the riches that lie beneath
the waters of the Gulf. Sumerian tablets
speak of trade with the "Isle of Dilmun" in
the "Lower Sea", as the ancients called the
Gulf, and the "fishes eyes from Dilmun",
referred to in an Assyrian inscription, were
in all probability pearls from Bahrain.
Like seafaring men the world over, the
pearl-fishers sang at their work and over
the centuries they have developed an
authentic musical tradition. Ifgeri, as this
music is called, has a wide and varied
repertoire and is very popular along the
coast, particularly in Bahrain and Qatar.
Ifgeri is mainly vocal and is performed ex¬
clusively by men.
Special songs have been devised to ac¬
company particular tasks aboard ship: the
khrab is sung as the anchor is weighed, the
mejdaf as the sailors bend to their oars, and
the basseh or the gaylaml as the sails are
hoisted. The job being done has a direct in¬
fluence on the musical structure of each
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Carlos Saldi, Paris
song. The khrab, for instance, is sung in
high key by a soloist, while the rest of the
crew chorus a background chant two oc¬
taves lower; this chant is punctuated at
regular intervals by audible exhalations
denoting the pauses for breath between
successive heaves as the anchor is raised.
The words of the Ifgeri songs describe
the hard life and lot of the pearl-fishers, the
dangers of the sea and sea-floor, and the
joys of reunion with one's family; they
often contain prayers to Allah, Mohammed
and AN.
Musically speaking, an Ifgeri song con¬
sists of a series of sections to oe sung by a
soloist and a male chorus. Each section is
characterized by the rhythmic structure
which accompanies the vocal part, and is
named accordingly. The rhythmic structure
underlying the first three sections must be
developed during the performance in
perceptible stages; that of the following
sections is clearly predetermined and con¬
sists of quite short forms.
Ifgeri is sung not only during the long
pearl-diving voyages but also ashore. Bet¬
ween trips the pearl-fishers and other
seafarers meet regularly, usually on
Thursdays, at a kind of community house,
known, as a aar, to drink tea, smoke, talk,
eat, sing and dance. In the 19th century
there were hundreds of dars on the Gulf
coast. Today far fewer remain. Each dar is
distinguished from the others by the
predominance of a particular kind of "sea-
music", the musical quality of the perfor¬
mances and the range of the soloist's
repertory.
For Ifgeri only percussion instruments
are used: double-skin torn toms (tabal and
mirwas), single-skin "flat drums" (tar,
plural tiran), little metal cymbals (tus) and
water-jars (gahlah). The tabal, related to
the Indian pakhwaj, hangs sideways across
the musician's chest and shoulder and is¡
played with the hand or a stick of natural
palm wood. The mirwas is a smaller torn
torn; four to six of them are used in a:
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
> Ifgeri performance. The tiran have a
diameter of about 70 centimetres and their
skins are generally decorated with names,
pictures of flowers and a crescent; before a
performance, they are set out in a circle
and warmed up to heighten the tension of
their skins. The gahlah is a water jar some
60 centimetres high; the opening is struck
with the flat of the hand; the resulting dull
tone can be supplemented by a further
sound, produced by scratching the side of
the jar.
The pearl-fishers learn Ifgeri from their
fathers, who in turn learnt it from the
previous generation. However, the pearl-
fishers of Bahrain recount a legend which
gives a different account of the origin of
this art-form.
Once upon a time there were three
friends; two of them came from Muharraq
Island, the third from Manamah (Bahrain).
They used to walk a few miles out of town
to a place called Abu-Subh, where they
could sing together without disturbing the
neighbours and without being disturbed
themselves. One afternoon, on the way to
Abu-Subh, as they passed a mosque (it still
stands today), they heard strange singing
which seemed to come from within. Their
curiosity was aroused; they wanted to see
who was singing; but as they approached
the entrance to the mosque they were met
by a hail of stones. On entering the court¬
yard they saw a group of seated figures
whose bodies seemed human above the
waist but looked like donkeys below. One
of these creatures asked the young men:
"Are you human beings or jinns?" (the
demons of Arab mythology). The men
replied that they were ordinary decent
human beings and wished the group no
harm; they merely wanted to spend the
evening listening to the others' songs. One
of the seated figures asked the three
friends not to say what was "in their
hearts" i.e. not to speak the first three
verses of the Koran aloud otherwise the
group would disappear: which meant that
they were jinns, because a jinn has to
disappear immediately the name of Allah is
pronounced.
So the three young men sat down with
the others and were allowed to learn the
group's Ifgeri songs by heart: but only
when they had promised never to repeat
what they saw and heard that evening; if
they did they would perish. From that time
on the friends met secretly in a cemetery to
sing these songs. After many years two of
them died. Soon the third also the one
from Muharraq felt that his last hour was
approaching. He called his family and
friends together and told them what had
happened on that distant evening with the
jinns. Then he sang the Ifgeri songs to
them; they learned them immediately and
they have been sung ever since.
With increasing competition from the
cultured pearl industry, pearl-fishing in the
Gulf went into decline and today only a
handful of men follow this ancient occupa¬
tion. Nevertheless the Ifgeri music of the
pearl-fishers and sailors of the Gulf survives
to form part of the proud Arab musical
tradition.
Habib Hassan Tourna
Music of the Gulf
With the financial backing of the International Fund for the Promotion of
Culture, the Co-ordinating Committee for International Voluntary Service
recently completed a programme of recordings of traditional music of the Gulf.
The recordings, totalling twenty-five hours ofplaying time, were made under the
supervision of the musician Boulos Mattar and the performances were
photographed by Carlos Saldi.
An audiovisual presentation of a selection of these recordings will be made at a
Unesco-sponsored intergovernmental conference on cultural policies in Arab
States to be held next year in Tunis.
Marital harmony is the theme song of this musical group, right. Adid ensembles, as these
all-women groups are called, play at weddings and other important family celebrations,
beating out a series of complex rythms on the tar, a shallow drum with a single skin,
usually decorated with names, flowers and a crescent.
Goats' hooves and swaying hips combine to form the mangur, below, one of the most
original of the percussion instruments of the Gulf. Goats' hooves sewn on to a kind of
short skirt strike each other as the performer sways to music of a six-stringed lyre, the
tanboura, to produce an unusual and agreeable pattering sound.
Pied Piper of the Gulf charms all hearers with magical melodies coaxed from the surnai, a
double-reed oboe, below right. Surnai players have developed a technique of inhaling
through the nose while continuing to blow out through the mouth; this enables them to
play for long periods without rests or pauses to take breath.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The
Minaret
of Jam
A Unesco project
to restore
an historic
Afghan monument
by Andrea Bruno
IN the barren highlands of central Afghanistan, 1,900
metres above sea level, a magnificent twelfth-century
minaret stands at the junction of two narrow, steep-
sided valleys. Although it towers some seventy metres above
the two mountain streams which meet at its base, it is dwarf¬
ed by the surrounding mountains, some of them 2,300 metres
high, which also emphasize the minaret's isolation and in¬
accessibility.
It is only some thirty-five years since historians learned of
the existence of this remarkable edifice, and not until 1957
was it finally located, near the modern settlement of Jam, by
a team of specialists who believed that it might stand on the
site of Firuzkuh, the legendary capital of the Ghuridi Sultans
who ruled Afghanistan from 1100 to 1215. The only survivor
of a compound of fortified buildings located in a strategic
position for the control of the valley of the Hari-rud, the
ANDREA BRUNO, Italian architect, is Unesco consultant with the
programme to preserve the minaret ofJam. He lectures on the resto¬
ration of monuments at the Faculty ofArchitecture of the University
of Turin, and has worked on a number of restoration projects in Italy
and Iraq, and in Afghanistan where he was a consultant with
Unesco's programme to preserve and restore the town of Herat.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
^W Ja ' ^Ç
Lonely
splendour
of a leaning
tower
Decorative brickwork spells out
Koranic inscriptions on the minaret
of Jam (left) built some eight
centuries ago in a rocky fastness
walled in by the mountains of
central Afghanistan. Spectacular
aerial view (below) shows full
grandeur of the minaret's remote
setting. Like a tiny "needle in a
rockstack" the edifice is just visible
near bottom left corner of photo. It
stands where river crossing photo
horizontally intersects with another
mountain stream flowing down a
steep-sided valley (which shows up
as dark shadow at bottom of
photo). Today the minaret is
leaning sideways owing to water
erosion. In collaboration with the
Afghan Government Unesco is
carrying out a rescue operation,
described here by its architect,
Andrea Bruno. Right, scale
drawings of vertical and horizontal
sections show features of the
restoration project.
Photos © Andrea Bruno, Turin
bigger of the two rivers which meet
beneath it, the minaret is a striking
testimony to the brief rule of the Ghurid
dynasty.
It is built of bricks and mortar, and is
decorated with a bas-relief in which bricks
are arranged to form highly elaborate
geometrical motifs and inscriptions, in
Kufic writing, of verses from the Koran.
The main inscription, however, is a band of
light-blue lettering which evokes the
Ghurid Sultan who built the minaret during
his forty-year reign. Literally translated, the
legend reads: "The magnificent Sultan, the
august king of kings, Ghiyat al duny Wal-
di, who extolled Islam and the Muslims,
Abdul-Fath Muhammad, ibn Sam, the
associate of the Emir of the Believers, may
god preserve his reign".
The minaret has a circular base, ten
metres in diameter. As it rises, it gradually
tapers to form a cone shape which is "trun¬
cated" forty metres above ground, where
there is an outside balcony (see drawing).
From this balcony rises the minaret's se¬
cond, slimmer section, whose base has a
diameter of eight metres. It too tapers to
form a truncated cone. Inside the lower,
forty-metre-high section, two spiral stair¬
cases wind around a pillar of masonry
which extends for three metres into the se¬
cond stage.
The minaret's stability has been affected
by water erosion and the tower is now
leaning perceptibly towards the Hari-rud
river. The masonry of the foundations has
considerably deteriorated; debris from
landslides surrounds the base and blocks
the original entrance.
In 1961 a preliminary survey was carried
out and suggestions were made for restor¬
ing the minaret, or at least for protecting it
temporarily against water erosion. Two
years later, with the help of the villagers of
Jam, a temporary embankment of stones
and timber was built around the founda¬
tions on the side abutting on the Hari-rud.
This embankment is still the monument's
only form of protection.
A plan of operations was drawn up in
June 1964. It called for the analysis of
samples of bricks and mortar, tests on the
foundations, reinforcement of the founda¬
tions with piles, and the restoration of the
masonry and the facing. Archaeological
surveys were also to be carried out around
the minaret.
It proved impossible to bring this short-
term programme to fruition. Progress was
hindered by a host of practical problems in¬
cluding those of transporting material to a
site which could only be reached on foot or
on horseback. Only in the last few years
has the construction of a road suitable for.
motor traffic made it possible to take really
practical steps to restore the minaret.
In 1974, at the request of the Afghan
Government, Unesco took a fresh look at
the project. The Organization decided to
finance an emergency plan and operations
began on 20 August 1978. An embankment
of large metal cages filled with stones was
built to keep out the water. As a result of k
this preliminary work it was possible to f
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
carry out surveys of the foundations and to
begin removing the rubble covering the
base of the minaret.
Saving the minaret is not going to be an
/ easy job. Apart from the problems involved
in getting equipment to such a remote spot
and organizing a building site there, climate
and geography will limit work to only a few
months per year. Furthermore, the area has
a degree of seismicity which had to be
carefully taken into account when con¬
sidering how to safeguard the minaret.
In order to stabilize the structure in its
present position, the project provides for
the construction of a reinforced concrete
ring around the minaret's foundations. This
ring will be linked elastically to a reinforced
concrete tank which will be ballasted by
water from the river and will be so con¬
stituted as to counterbalance any further
increase in the slope of the minaret (see
drawing).
The overall structural stability of the pro¬
posed project has been tested by com¬
puter, full account being taken of the
minaret's present state and of the seismic
activity to which the area is liable. These
tests supported the viability of the idea of a
tank elastically connected to the base of
the minaret.
The execution of the project will depend
on a series of complex operations which
will have to be carried out in particularly dif¬
ficult conditions. In 1978 it took a whole
season merely to transport to the site
material needed for the first emergency
operation devised by Unesco.
The next step will be to carry out surveys
to establish the size and nature of the foun¬
dations; the minaret's original entrance will
be uncovered from the debris. The rates of
flow and the water levels in relation to the
minaret's foundations will be controlled.
Excavations will be carried out within a
radius of some forty metres of the minaret
in order to obtain an accurate stratigraphie
picture and to bring to light archaeological
remains, if any. New archaeological
discoveries could partially modify the
restoration programme. Next, the base will
be strengthened and its broken masonry
repaired, before the reinforced concrete
ring is constructed. The size of the ring will
depend on data gained from tests on the
stability of the foundations. The final stage
of restoration will be the construction of
the concrete tank: during this phase it will
also be possible to restore the external
decoration of the minaret; this requires the
erection of metal scaffolding, which is not
possible at present.
The concrete reinforcement structure,
which will be built at the original ground
level (some 3.5 metres below the present
level) will be left visible if the rubble now
covering it can be transported away from
the site; if not it will be covered with earth
so that the area around the minaret will
look much as it does today.
The Minaret of Jam is a monument of
outstanding historic and architectural in¬
terest; through the importance attached to
its preservation by the Afghan Government
and by Unesco, it will continue to dominate
the river valleys it was built to protect eight
centuries ago.
Andrea Bruno
Bookshelf
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Introduction to African
Culture: General Aspects, by
Alpha I. Sow, Ola Balogun, Honorât
Aguessy, Pathé Diagne. 1979, 184
pp. (18 Francs).
Socio-Political Aspects of the
Palaver in Some African Coun¬
tries. 1979, 93 pp. (12 F)
Vols. I and II in a new Unesco series
entitled "Introduction to African
Culture"
Peace Research. Trend Report
and World Directory. The third com¬
pletely revised edition of a work
Unesco began publishing in 1966
takes into account new institutions
not listed in previous editions and
also the expanding frontiers of
peace research and its increasing
emphasis on questions of social and
economic development. 1979,
250 pp. (26 F).
National Communication
Policy Councils, Principles and
Experiences, by Marco Antonio
Rodrigues Dias, John A.R. Lee,
Kaarle Nordenstreng and Osmo 0.
Wiio (No. 83 in Unesco's "Reports
and Papers on Mass Communica¬
tion" series) 1979, 44 pp. (8 F).
Letters to the editor
The Unesco Courier welcomes readers' letters,
which should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief,
Unesco Courier, Place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris. Only signed letters will be considered for
publication.
TIME OUT OF MIND
Sir,
I admire the works of Professor Isaac Asimov
(and certainly those of Professor Einstein). I
must respectfully disagree, however, with a par¬
ticular theory of Time as related by Professor
Asimov on pages 9 and 10 of the May 1979 issue
of the Unesco Courier.
Asimov presents a clock showing the time 3
o'clock at point A and a travelling observer (X)
who travels to point B, 300,000 kilometres away
in one second of time at the speed of light. X,
upon arrival at point B, looks back at the clock
standing at point A, showing the time 3 o'clock,
and, because the light from the clock arrives at
point B "at the same time" X sees that time for
him has not progressed. Asimov states that "by
keeping up with the speed of light you as a
passenger... are cut off from the passage of
time".
The fallacy of this view is that time at point B
is not determined by a clock running at point A,
but must be determined by a clock located at
point B. Were this not so, X's one second return
from B to A, at the speed of light, because of the
Doppler effect, would take in two clock seconds
instead of the actual one second (i.e. X would
have begun his one second trip with the clock
reading 3 o'clock and ended this one second trip
with the same clock reading 2 seconds past
3 o'clock).
It would appear, therefore, that it is the veloci¬
ty of the observer of Time, and not Time itself,
which is relative i.e. that Time is Absolute and
that it is the Observation of Time which is in fact
relative.
Professor Einstein was famous for his use of
the "thought experiment". The above thesis is
also such an experiment and I would encourage
others to duplicate it and see if they are not also
in agreement.
Terence L. Hall
Pontiac, Michigan, U.S.A.
It should first be pointed out that the diagrams and
captions that appeared on page 10 of our May 1979
issue are the responsibility of the Unesco Courier
editorial staff and not of Professor Asimov. Einstein
maintained that the only absolute, the only value that
was invariably the same for everyone, was the speed of
light, that there was no basic fi. e. absolute) time scale
applicable throughout the universe, and that every
observer carries his own time scale with him. Observers
in different time reference frames can measure the same
event, but their results will not tally. If there were an ab¬
solute, universally applicable time scale, we could say
that one observer was right in his observation and the
others wrong. But for Einstein no one is wrong because
measurements of time depend upon the reference
frame in which they are mideIn this case the street¬
car or a point on the ground. It is therefore impossible,
as Mr. Hall attemps to do, to make a distinction bet¬
ween time and the observation of time Editor.
SWORDS INTO PLOUGHSHARES
Sir,
Congratulations on your special issue devoted
to the problems of the arms race (April 1979). I
was particularly interested by the article "Three
Myths that Die Hard" which exposed the falsity
of the beliefs that military expenditure boosts
economic growth, that the arms industry offers
a panacea for unemployment, and that military
research is the major spur to technological pro-'
gress. '
These myths still persist. Although a quarter
of mankind is undernourished, tons of explosive
exist per inhabitant of the globe. If man is really
a rational being, he must do all he can to turn
TNT into food, schools and hospitals, and
transform nuclear weapons into useful energy
for mankind.
I hope that we, the Bulgarian readers of the
Unesco Courier, will soon be able to read your
magazine in our own language.
Nikolai Gueorguiev
Sofia
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published...
Constructive
education for
special groups
Handicapped and
deviant children
An important new study
on education
for handicapped and
deviant children
With this look at those youngsters he calls "the casualties of our
system. Professor W. D. Wall completes his study of contempo¬
rary problems in education.
He defines the main groups of handicap, reviews the prevalence
of certain kinds of physical and mental disability, and describes
some of the ways in which society and education may bring about
tangible improvements in identifying and rehabilitating the children
in question.
A book of particular interest to teachers, psychologists and
parents of handicapped children.
Prof. Wall is Emeritus Professor of Educational Psychology at
the University of London. His two previous works published by
Unesco were Constructive Education for Children and Con¬
structive Education for Adolescents.
144 pages 35 French francs
This new title in the Unesco: IBE (International Bureau of Educa¬
tion) series on comparative education is co-published with
George G. Harrap and Co. Ltd., London, who have exclusive sales
rights in the United Kingdom.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors In countries not lis¬
ted, along with subscription rates in local cur¬
rency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 650-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L, Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. DtNMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OFI. National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangle 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. - MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos.The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty. I Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVTI Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istambul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Drawing its inspiration from a wide range of cultural sources, the music of the coastal regions of
the Gulf, the shallow sea that lies between the Arabian peninsula and Iran, presents a fascinating
kaleidoscope of sound (see article page 28). Music at weddings is usually provided by groups of
women musicians known as adid ensembles. Below, an adid musician playing the tar, a shallow,
single-skin drum, at a Bahraini weddino
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
October 1979
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
from
news
unesco
The Director-General presents the
International Reading Association Literacy
Award for 1979 to Dr. Bruce Hooley,
director of the Papua New Guinea Branch
of the Summer Institute of Linguistics.
Looking on is Mr. Chams Eldine El-Wakil,
chairman of the Unesco Executive Board.
Photo Unesco/Dominique Roger
M'Bow Urges
Passive
Mobilization'
of Resources
for Science
Development
Addressing the United Nations
Conference on Science and
Technology for Development, held in
Vienna from 20 to 31 August 1979,
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow called
for a "massive mobilization of
resources" to give new impetus to
assistance to Third World countries in
these fields.
But mere transfer of technology is not
enough, the Unesco Director-General
warned the Vienna conference. "No
nation can make real progress or
secure its future without an
independent capacity for scientific and
technological creation which opens the
way to endogenous development
rooted in its own culture... It is by
integrating modern science and
technology as a living element in their
own cultures that the developing
countries can best enable themselves to
take a decisive step forward in their
development without jeopardizing the
social and human values to which so
many of them are attached.
"To condemn developing countries to
be the mere passive receivers of
knowledge acquired elsewhere," the
Director-General added, "is to
perpetuate the situation of dependence
to which they are subjected 'and
consolidate the division of the world
into different groups of countries,
some of which would have the
exclusive privilege of high-level
knowledge, whereas the others would
be excluded from the great adventure
which is daily strengthening mankind's
control over nature."
The conference, ih which 141 countries
took part, adopted by consensus a
plan of action calling for a new "high
level" organism, in which all countries
would be represented, to outline
policies for international organizations
with regard to science and technology
for development and to report to the
U.N. General Assembly through the
Economic and Social Council. In
addition, pending the creation of a
permanent financing mechanism, an
interim fund of $250 million will be
launched in the next two years for
international aid in this field.
Prof. J.W.M. La Rivière, chairman of
the International Cell Research
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Organization and a consultant to the
Director-General for UNCSTD, said
the conference provided "a unique
opportunity to hear what the
developing countries really want and
thus acted as a yardstick for checking
and adjusting existing programme
strategies."
For ICRO delegates UNCSTD was a
particularly rewarding experience, Mr.
La Rivière said, because it
demonstrated that "the development
of the life sciences fundamental as
well as applied is now being
recognized as one of the top priorities
in applying the natural sciences to
development. Thus UNCSTD provides
encouragement to the many
institutions, organizations and
individual scientists now collaborating
in fundamental and applied cell
research."
Another consultant to the Director-
General, Dr. Mary Brazier of the
International Brain Research
Organization, drew attention to the
need for further research linked to
prevention of diseases as a
contribution to development.
During a visit to the Unesco pavilion at the
"Man and His World" exhibition this
summer in Montreal, Peter Ustinov
autographed copies of the book "What
kind of world are we leaving to our
children?" based on the Round Table
discussion held at Unesco in June, 1978.
Here he is being shown around the
exhibition by Mr. Claude Lussier, secretary
general of the Canadian National
Commission for Unesco.
Unicef Photo
Exhibition Marks
International Year
of the Child
The hopes and joys as well as the
terror and the misery of children
around the world were reflected in the
photo exhibition "The Children of
Bernstein,
Boulanger, Richter
Cited in Unesco
Music Awards
American conductor Leonard
Bernstein, French music teacher Nadia
Boulanger and Soviet pianist
Sviatoslav Richter are among the
winners of the 1979
Unesco/International Music Council
awards.
The awards, announced by the
Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, and the
Prime Minister of Australia, the Rt.
Hon. Malcolm Fraser, were presented
on International Music Day, 1
October, in Melbourne, Australia,
before a worldwide audience of
delegates attending the 18th general
assembly of the International Music
Council.
Other award winners included Jan
Cikker, Czechoslovak composer of
symphonic and piano works; Sir
Bernhard Heinze, Australian musician,
conductor and teacher; Mohammed
Kobanje, leading Iraqi exponent of the
"Mamaq" style of singing, and Zofia
Lissa, Polish musicologist specializing
in the history, analysis and editing of
late 19th and early 20th century
European music.
The International Music Council,
created by Unesco in 1949, is a
federation of 18 international non¬
governmental organizations
representing all aspects of music. Its
interests include the composition and
performance of music, training of
musicians, public education in music,
and music research and promotion.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
This World", displayed at Unesco
headquarters from 20 September to 5
October.
Organized by Unicef and the magazine
Stern to mark the International Year
of the Child, the exhibition contains
more than 500 photographs in colour
and in black and white by 238
outstanding photographers from 94
countries. More than 300 museums
and cultural institutions took part in
preparing the exhibition which is being
presented in the principal cities of
Europe, Asia and Latin America.
One of the 515 photographs in the Unicef
exhibition "The Children of This World"
displayed at Unesco, 20 September to 5
October.
Italy Called
World Leader
in Local Radio
and Television
Italy has more local radio and
television stations in proportion to its
population and land surface than any
other country.
According to official figures, in 1978
Italy had no fewer than 2,275 radio
stations and 503 local television
stations, making one radio station for
every 24,747 inhabitants and one
television station for every 111,930
inhabitants.
This information is revealed in a
document prepared by Giuseppe
Richeri of the University of Bologna
for the International Commission for
the Study of Communication
Problems. The Unesco-sponsored
commission, which has been working
for two years under the chairmanship
of Mr. Sean MacBride, former foreign
minister of Ireland and holder of the
Nobel and Lenin Peace Prizes, is
scheduled to complete its report at a
final meeting in November in Paris.
About ten per cent of the Italian local
stations have frequencies assigned to
them but do not broadcast regularly,
Richeri reports. Of those which do
broadcast regularly, three quarters are
commercial stations operated
essentially for profit, while most of the
rest are affiliated to political parties or
organizations. Only a very few are
genuine community stations, providing
local populations an opportunity to
communicate, and presenting a real
"alternative" to the State broadcasting
organization, Radiotelevisione Italia
(RAI).
Nevertheless, the document adds, the
local stations have provided serious
competition for the RAI, both in
terms of audiences and in advertising
revenues.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Literacy Prizes go
to Iraq, Peru,
Papua New Guinea
A mass literacy campaign in Iraq, an
association of Peruvian women and an
institute working in local languages in
Papua New Guinea these are the
winners of literacy prizes announced
by Unesco for 1979.
Two awards of the 5,000-rouble
Nadezhda K. Krupskaya Prize,
established by the USSR Government,
were made by the international jury
selecting this year's prizewinners. They
went to the Supreme Council for the
National Campaign for Compulsory
Literacy in Iraq, which has mobilized
the forces of the country in a mass
drive to eradicate illiteracy, and to the
Popular Union of Peruvian Women,
which has organized women's
participation in development activities
through literacy courses.
The jury, which did not award a
Krupskaya prize in 1977, decided to
use the funds available for two prizes
this year in view of the variety and
worth of the 27 candidatures, which
they say bear witness to the growing
interest of Unesco Member States and
non-governmental organizations in the
struggle against illiteracy.
For the first time, the $5,000
International Reading Association
Prize is being awarded. It goes to the
Papua New Guinea Branch of the
Summer Institute of Linguistics, which
has been working for several years on
the transcription of local languages.
Local personnel have been trained to
use these languages for teaching
children and adults.
Mexican
and Ghanaian
Named to Senior
Unesco Posts
The Director-General of Unesco, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, has
announced the appointment of
Rodolfo Stavenhagen of Mexico as
Assistant Director-General for Social
Sciences and their Applications. At the
same time Mr. M'Bow said that Yaw
B. Turkson of Ghana had been named
Deputy Assistant Director-General for
General Administration.
Mr. Stavenhagen, who took over as
head of the Unesco social science
sector on 15 August, has been Director
General for Popular Culture in the
Mexican Secretariat (Ministry) of
National Education since 1977. He has
been "chairman of the Latin-American
Faculty of Social Sciences since 1975.
Mr. Stavenhagen was director of
studies at the International Social
Studies Institute of the International
Labour Organization in Geneva from
1969 to 1971 and has participated in
Unesco General Conferences as a
member of the Mexican delegation.
Mr. Turkson, who joined Unesco on
1 August, is a senior diplomat who
was Ghanaian ambassador to France
and his country's Permanent Delegate
to Unesco until July. Prior to that he
had served as director of the West
European and Americas desk and the
international organization and
conferences desk at the Ghanaian
Foreign Ministry. He has also been
ambassador to Brazil and Ethiopia.
Early in his career Mr. Turkson was
first a member of his country's
mission to the United Nations, then a
U.N. official.
The most widely translated work in Neruda, as well as great Russian
the world continues to be the Bible; authors Tolstoy, Gorki and Tchekov.
according to Unesco statistics, thirty These figures, which refer to the year
countries produced translations from it 1975, come from the latest edition of
in a single year. Index translationum, an annual
Close behind come the works of catalogue prepared by Unesco of
Shakespeare, translated in 29 countries books translated around the world.
and then those of Karl Marx and Thus, though not completely
Dostoyevsky, translated in 26 exhaustive, the figures do give a fair
countries. idea of the trends in cultural
Thirteen authors in all were translated exchanges.
The Bible the
in 20 countries or more, including The figures show that out of 47,239
writers of children's classics such as translated books published in 1975,
World's Most
Robert Louis Stevenson, Jules Verne, 28,235 appeared in industrialized
Mark Twain and Hans Christian countries and 13,397 in socialist
Translated Work
Andersen, Jack London and modern
writers such as Solzhenitsyn and Pablo
countries while only 5,417 were
produced in the developing countries.
IV
]]>
</page>
</document>
