<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074761eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The
Unesco Courier
AUGUST 1980 - 3.50 french francs
Nature and culture
the human heritage
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
m
Where the mountains of Montenegro
sweep down to the sea
Along the Gulf of Kotor, a deep, winding inlet on the Adriatic coast of Montenegro
(Yugoslavia), a chain of historic towns and villages lies at the foot of steep limestone
mountains. The development of these settlements was shaped by exceptionally
favourable and unusual natural conditions which gave rise to abundant plant and
marine life, including species rarely found elsewhere. A cross-roads of cultures, this
region has played a decisive role in the evolution of architecture, painting and
craftsmanship in the Balkans. The inclusion of Kotor, with its harmony between the
works of nature and those of man, on the World Heritage List as a region "of
outstanding universal value" is a fitting symbol of the interdependence of the natural
and cultural heritage.
Photo J.-C Berrier © Atlas, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The
UnescoCourier
A window open on tHe world
AUGUST 1980 '33rd year
PUBLISHED IN 25 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish Macedonian
French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene
Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb
A selection in Braille s published
quarterly n English, French and Spanish
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 29 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (11 Issues a
year including one double issue). For list of distributors see
Inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of Issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
' bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
" request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
, accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co.. Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese .Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Krishna Gopal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian Edition: Samad Nourinejad (Teheran)
Dutch Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp) .
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Philippe Gentil
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
Page
NATURE AND CULTURE: THE HUMAN HERITAGE
5 The international convention
by Gérard Bolla
A new partnership in the making
by Michel Bâtisse
33 WONDERS OF THE WORLD
by Georges Fradier
The World Heritage List: the first 57 entries
page
Aachen (Federal Republic of Germany)	31
Abu Mena (Arab Republic of Egypt) 21
Anse aux Meadows (Canada) 13
Antigua Guatemala (Guatemala) ï	7
Auschwitz (Poland) 34
Bialowieza (Poland) 33
Boyana (Bulgaria) 25
Bryggen (Norway) 30
Cairo (Arab Republic of Egypt)	20
Carthage (Tunisia) 22
Chartres (France) 27
Cracow (Poland) 33
Damascus (the Syrian Arab Republic) . 9
Dinosaur Park (Canada) 13
Dubrovnik (Yugoslavia)	, 29
El-Djem (Tunisia) 23
Everglades (United States) 16
Fasil Ghebbi (Ethiopia) 18
Galapagos Islands (Ecuador) 7
Forts and Castles of Ghana 17
Gorée (Senegal) 34
Grand Canyon (United States) 16
Independence Hall (United States)	14
Isfahan (Iran) 11
Ivanovo (Bulgaria) 24
Kathmandu (Nepal) 8
Kazanlak (Bulgaria) 25
Kluane and Wrangell (Canada/United States) 12
Kotor (Yugoslavia) 2
Lalibela (Ethiopia) 19
Madara (Bulgaria) 24
Memphis (Arab Republic of Egypt)	21
Mesa Verde (United States) 15
Mont-Saint-Michel (France) 26
Nahanni (Canada) ;	 12
Ngorongoro (Tanzania) 17
Nubia (Arab Republic of Egypt) 20
Ohrid (Yugoslavia) 28
Persepolis (Iran) 10
Plitvice (Yugoslavia) 	 '. 29
Quito (Ecuador) 7
Sagarmatha (Nepal) 8
Simien (Ethiopia) 18
Sopocani (Yugoslavia) 28
Split (Yugoslavia) 29
Tchogha Zanbil (Iran) 11
Thebes (Arab Republic of Egypt) 20
Tikal (Guatemala) 6
Tunis (Tunisia) 23
Urnes (Norway)	30
Valcamonica (Italy) 31
Versailles (France) 26
Vézelay (France) 27
Vézère (France) 26
Virunga (Zaire) 17
Wieliczka (Poland) 32
Yellowstone (United States) 15
Cover
The roots of human existence are at stake in
the conservation of the natural world and the
preservation of the cultural masterpieces we
have inherited from our forebears. It is now
accepted that these roots, the "universal
heritage" to which all mankind is heir, are
implanted in the earth and extend to all cul¬
tures, past and present. Cover shows
Almayer's Folly, a work by the Belgian artist
René Magritte symbolizing the roots of the
human heritage.
Engraving René Magritte from ¿e Lien de Paille 1969
© Éditions Georges Visât, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The World Heritage
emblem symbolizes the
interdependence of
cultural and natural
properties.
nature and culture
the
human heritage
This special issue of the Unesco Courier presents the first fifty-seven entries on the World
Heritage List of cultural and natural "properties" recognized by the international
community as of outstanding universal value. The list has been drawn up by an
international committee on the basis of proposals submitted by the States (fifty-three so
far) which are party to a major international agreement, the Convention concerning the
Protection of the World Cultural and Natural Heritage, which was adopted by the General
Conference of Unesco in 1972. The Convention, which came into force in
December 1975, has been welcomed all over the world as a new departure in international
co-operation. It sets up a system whereby the international community can participate
actively in protecting those parts of the cultural and natural heritage which have great
universal value. Traditionally, the preservation of the cultural heritage and the
conservation of nature have been regarded as two quite different problems, with
responsibility for the protection of important cultural or natural sites being considered to
lie exclusively with the country in which they are located. Where the Convention breaks
new ground is in linking together the protection of the cultural heritage and the natural
heritage and in providing a permanent framework legal, administrative and financial for
international co-operation in this protection. It also introduces the specific notion of a
"world heritage" whose importance transcends all political or geographical boundaries. In
addition to the World Heritage List, the committee is also establishing a "List of World
Heritage in Danger", featuring property for the protection of which major operations are
necessary. The World Heritage Committee is provided with "muscle" to take firm action
by Article 15 of the Convention which sets up a "World Heritage Fund" financed in part
by contributions from the States party to the Convention and in part from, other,
voluntary sources. Technical assistance through the Fund has already been provided to a
number of States adhering to the Convention.
GERARD BOLLA, Swiss jurist and economist,
has been since 1975 Unesco's Deputy Assistant
Director-General for Culture and Communication
and was formerly director of the Organization's
Cultural Heritage Division.
MICHEL BATISSE, French physicist, is Deputy
Assistant Director-General for Sciences at
Unesco. A specialist in problems of the conserva¬
tion of nature, he has for many years been in
charge of Unesco's programmes concerning the
environment and natural resources.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The international convention by Gérard Bolla
THE Convention concerning the Protection of the World Cultural
and Natural Heritage came into being against a background
of changing attitudes reflected by three symbolic events of the
early 1970s.
The first was the completion in Upper Egypt and the Sudan of the first stage
of the international campaign to save the monuments of Nubia, the most im-
portant archaeological rescue operation the world has ever seen. The fact that
international solidarity made it possible to preserve the temples of Nubia for
posterity gave substance to an idea implicit in Unesco's Constitution the idea
that the nations bear a collective responsibility towards monuments whose im¬
portance is such that they belong to the history of all mankind.
The second event was the United Nations Conference on the Human En¬
vironment, held at Stockholm in 1972, at which the international community
stressed the urgent need for measures to conserve the natural environment, as
well as the works of man's creative genius. Here too was an affirmation of the
idea of the collective responsibility of the nations towards an environment in
danger.
Thirdly, the peoples of the developing and industrialized countries alike voic¬
ed the strong conviction that their cultural identity should be strengthened and
. respected. The most tangible and often the highest forms of this cultural iden¬
tity consist of the heritage of monuments and buildings produced by the
creative spirit of the ancestors and the natural environment in which the nation
achieved its fullest self-expression. It was felt that, while it is for each country
to preserve its cultural identity, it is incumbent on them all in the name of col¬
lective international responsibility to join in the task of conservation.
And so an, international agreement which was originally intended only to lay
the foundations for mutual assistance in safeguarding the cultural heritage of
monuments and buildings was transformed, in response to the wishes of those
concerned with the protection of the human environment as a whole, into an
instrument whose goal is the protection of monuments and natural sites, such
as national parks.
Wishing to contribute to the strengthening of cultural identities, the ar¬
chitects of the Convention also provided that a list of monuments and sites
should be drawn up, incorporating all cultural and natural property recognized
by the international community as possessing universal value and hence as
coming under its collective responsibility.
The system of international protection of cultural and natural property is
thus firmly established; countries nominate such property for inclusion on the
list but it is only accepted after a decision has been taken by a twenty-one-
member international committee. If the need arises, the international com¬
munity may contribute to the safeguard of the property by providing technical
and financial assistance.
The inclusion of an archaeological site or a national park on the World
Heritage List is usually a source of satisfaction and pride to those, the descen¬
dants of its creators or the custodians of its integrity, who have inherited the
responsibility of preserving it. But inclusion on the List has serious implications
for national and local authorities, which thereby pledge to resist with the ut¬
most vigour any pressures that may be brought to bear by private interests,
often with few scruples about respecting the cultural heritage of the past or
the integrity of natural sites. Entries may in fact be removed, and a monument
or national park may be divested of the honour of appearing on a list which en¬
joys high prestige and already includes some of the world's most precious
treasures.
It is hard to imagine any public body failing to do its utmost to prevent
the loss, possibly irremediable, of property which it has undertaken to
preserve and for which it has requested the support of the entire international
community.
The 1972 Convention on the Protection of the World Heritage has been
described as "the peacetime Red Cross" for monuments and natural sites
(another convention, the Convention for the Protection of Cultural Property
in the Event of Armed Conflict, signed at The Hague in 1954, serves as a
"war-time Red Cross" for monuments) . Whatever we may think of the interna¬
tional system for the protection of cultural and natural property, whatever
motives may have led States to adhere to it, this -system now exists. As the
years go by it will be strengthened as more States add their names to the fifty-,
three which, under Unesco's auspices, have already joined to form a great
family determined to protect, in full solidarity, its most precious
possessions.
A new partnership in the making by M¡Chei Bat^e
SOME people may be surprised to see the pyramids of Egypt
and the national park of the Galapagos Islands incorporated
within a single framework and inscribed on a single list. What
can ancient monuments have in common with a group of rocky islands throng¬
ed with iguanas and tortoises? -except, perhaps, the equal ingenuity w¡th
whiéh travel agencies arrange organized tours to each of these sites. But are
the travel agents' efforts not proof that our contemporaries, when they have
the opportunity, are attracted both by cultural masterpieces and by the
wonders of nature?
What then is meant by this "common heritage of mankind"?
In addition to books, music, craft and artistry, the collections of paintings
and sculptures in the world's museums, the cultural heritage comprises much
"immovable" property such as monuments and groups of historic buildings. It
is this "immovable" property with which the World Heritage Convention is
concerned.
As for the natural heritage, it consists first of all of the plant and animal
species whose conservation is of vital importance for human survival (see the
"Unesco Courier", May 1980). These species are today protected £S such by
various (still extremely inadequate) conventions which deal notably with inter¬
national trade in or hunting of them. But the natural heritage also includes uni¬
que sites, landscapes of exceptional beauty or of great value from the point of
view of science or conservation, which can neither be replaced nor reproduc¬
ed. It is this "immovable" natural heritage which is covered by the World
Heritage Convention, although certain threatened plant and animal species are
automatically protected when their habitat is chosen for inclusion on the
World Heritage List.
But although the protection of cultural property and the protection of
natural property may be parallel activities, they raise very different problems.
In most countries the two functions are entrusted to separate administrative
structures, and architects who, for example, are concerned with the preserva¬
tion of historic buildings have little to do with the biologists who administer na¬
tional parks. So the question of why nature and culture should now be brought
together within a single international convention might well be countered by
the point that they have been separated, and even treated as rivals, for far too
long.
At the beginning of his long emergence, man was able to make only a very
slight impact on his physical and biological environment. He was, in a sense,
"within" nature. But as soon as he mastered fire he became the agent of im¬
portant modifications, deliberate or accidental, in the natural world. By the
end of the Palaeolithic age, when he still lived from hunting and gathering, he
was already making an imprint on the natural environment in which he was
pursuing his ascent. It is precisely this imprint, the result of his capacity for in¬
vention, that makes man what he is. What had yet to be called culture was
already at odds with nature.
In Neolithic times, with the appearance of agriculture and the domestication
of animals, the imprint would become deeper and the range of transformations
would grow. Some 6,000 years ago, when man enters history, the discord bet¬
ween culture and nature was already etched on the face of the earth in those
places where forests had been burned and where certain types of plants had
been favoured to the exclusion of others.
But this was merely the modest beginning of a long process. The domina¬
tion of the human species over every aspect of its environment would grow
with its mastery of increasingly powerful tools, with its hunger for new ob¬
jects, with the development of new needs, and with the multiplication of its
members.
The material progress of techniques and societies took place essentially at
the expense of nature and natural resources. And many philosophies and
beliefs glorify this successful struggle of man "against" nature.
A tragic misunderstanding arose and persisted down the centuries:
mankind's mastery of his own "animal nature" became confused with his wan¬
ton domination of the world around him. The warning of Francis Bacon, who
announced at the dawn of the scientific revolution that "Nature, to be com¬
manded, must be obeyed", was ignored. The pre-eminence of mind over mat¬
ter, which is the honour and the essence of man, was wrongly identified with a
superiority that culture, especially in its technological forms, was considered
to have over nature, thus confusing the moral order with the material order.
And so we reach the industrial revolution when the tempo quickens and
matters come to a head. Industrial man has begotten prodigious technical
achievements; he has gone some way to solving the problems of hunger and
sickness. But at the same time his numbers grow to excess, he consumes
relentlessly, he perfects lethal weaponry. His progress towards self-mastery is
thus open to doubt.
Meanwhile, he has taken his conquest of nature so far that it is threatened
with extinction. For nature the reckoning is too heavy: massive deforestation;
the erosion and degradation of soils; the disappearance of animal and plant
species; water, air, land and marine pollution of many kinds; proliferating
slums and shantytowns; expanding concrete and asphalt; dwindling open
spaces...
And yet the message is not hard to grasp. Will modern men realize in time
that if they snap the umbilical cord which attaches them to the natural world
then they are bound inexorably to destroy themselves? Will they turn to the
healthiest sources of their different cultures and learn at long last how to live
"with" nature?
It would be possible to cite many examples of the oenefits man has skilfully
reaped from the resources of the biosphere without endangering the
mechanisms which give birth to these resources: the harmonious landscapes
shaped by human toil, for instance, or the natural sites used for cultural pur¬
poses.
It is highly significant that the Convention already covers some of these
privileged places where nature and culture meet: Ohrid and its lake in
Yugoslavia, Tikal and its forest in Guatemala, Mont Saint-Michel and its bay in
France. Let us hope that one day soon these sites will be joined by others of a
similar kind, such as the tree-girdled temples of Angkor or the ruins of Machu
Picchu in their grandiose Andean setting.
And so the association of nature and culture in the World Heritage Conven¬
tion has first and foremost the value of a symbol a symbol of the new alliance
which must now be cemented between these two poles of human develop¬
ment, which only exists when they are combined.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Tikal National Park, Guatemala
More than 3,000 architectural structures, including temples and stelae, ball-
game courts, dams, canals and majestic highways, reveal the past splendour of
Tikal, one of the most important religious centres of the Maya civilization.
They also trace the history of the Mayas from the time when they lived by
hunting and food-gathering (c. 600 BC) until the heyday of a complex society of
farmers, priests, astronomers, architects and sculptors. The artistic styles and
hieroglyphic writing created by the Mayas spread throughout Central America;^
and then, around 900 AD, the Maya civilization disappeared. An area of 576 km2
surrounding the Ceremonial Centre of Tikal has been set aside as a national
park for the protection of plant and animal life. Photo shows a temple
(c. 700 AD) which rises almost 50 metres above Tikal's great square.
jW*-
fr~ I
-1
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The City of Quito, Ecuador D
In the fifteenth century, seeking to consolidate the northern part of their great
kingdom, the Tahuantinsuyo ("the four parts of the world") the Incas established
their second capital at Quito on the slopes of a volcano, 2.800 metres above sea
level. A century later, the same rugged site was covered by the churches,
convents, spacious squares and university buildings of a Spanish colonial city, San
Francisco de Quito. A seat of government and a major political and cultural centre,
the city soon became distinguished for the quality of its artists. Architecture,
sculpture and painting alike were such that the "School of Quito", in which
indigenous traditions and European techniques were intermingled, is considered to
be one of Latin America's outstanding contributions to world art. The capital of
modern Ecuador, Quito is determined to preserve its historic centre, whose original
layout of streets and squares closely follows that of the old colonial city. Photo
shows richly decorated door in the church of El Sagrario.
Antigua Guatemala
In 1543, after previous attempts to establish a
settlement there had been thwarted by the
resistance of the Indians and by an avalanche
from the slopes of the volcano Agua, the
Spaniards founded the city of Santiago de los
Caballeros de Guatemala. After earthquakes had
reduced it to rubble in 1586, it was rebuilt, and
along streets running north-south and east-west in
straight lines rose churches, monasteries and
palaces in which Gothic blended with a variety of
styles inspired by the Italian Renaissance. After
further earthquakes in 1717, the transfer of the city
was envisaged but then a stubborn decision was
taken to rebuild. Baroque and Ultra-baroque now
came to the fore and ornately decorated columns
and pilasters and animal and plant motifs in
moulded stucco appeared. In 1751 the earth shook
once more, partially destroying the city; in 1773
earthquake struck again. This time, Antigua
Guatemala (the name by which the city had
always been better known) was abandoned. Today
the Guatemalan authorities, undeterred by the
earthquakes of 1976, are endeavouring to preserve
the remains of this beautiful, ill-fated city. Photo
shows the façade of the church of San Francisco.
Galapagos Islands, Ecuador O
Offspring of the volcanoes of the Pacific, a thousand kilometres from
the continental mainland, the nineteen Galapagos Islands have a flora
and fauna whose uniqueness has become more widely known in recent
years. Giant tortoises, marine iguanas (in photo) and the birds which
taught Charles Darwin the secrets of adaptation to the environment,
peacefully welcome the large mammals the sea lions and seals which
come ashore to breed. The first sailors who set foot on the islands, less
than 500 years ago, were amazed that all the creatures there were
harmless. Today, the Government of Ecuador, which took possession of
the archipelago in 1831 and colonized it, is trying to put an end to
hunting. But the protection of the islands' original ecosystem depends
on the expulsion of all the creatures introduced by man, including dogs,
monkeys, goats and pigs, as well as harmful insects.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The Valley of
Kathmandu, Nepal
According to legend, the
Kathmandu Valley was originally
a lake at the foot of the
Himalayas where the primordial
form of the Buddha emerged
from a golden lotus. Its cultural
history began when the
Bodhisattva Manjushri cleft
open the lake's barrier with a
blow of his sword and its waters
flowed away. Although the early
history of the Kathmandu
Valley, from the time of the
Kirati and Lichchavi dynasties
2,000 years ago until the Mallas
of the fourteenth century, is
shrouded in mystery, in every
age Nepalese culture has
succeeded in taking advantage
of Nepal's location between
Tibet and China in the north,
and India in the south between
Buddhism and Hinduism. Out of
the flourishing coexistence of
these two religions came a
unique blend of influences in
architecture and the arts and a
cultural blossoming whose
apogee lasted three centuries
from 1500 to 1800. The legacy of
that period, now protected,
comprises seven groups of
buildings scattered over the
valley: the royal squares of three
large towns Kathmandu, Patan
and Bhadgaon (Bhaktapur)
and the sacred complexes of
Swayambhu, Bodhnath,
Pashaputi and Changu Narayan.
These seven sites include a total
of 132 buildings which the
Government of Nepal wishes to
safeguard in accordance with
the Master Plan for
Conservation which it has
recently approved. Shown here,
temples on Durbar Square,.
Patan.
Sagarmatha National Park, Nepal D
The Nepalese prefer to call earth's highest mountain
"Sagarmatha" ("Whose-head-touches-the-sky") rather
than "Everest" after the British civil servant George
Everest who saw it in the distance around 1840.
Sagarmatha National Park includes the 8,848-metre-high
peak, as well as six other mountains over 7,000 metres
high. It also contains glaciers which feed the rivers that
flow down through deep gorges to the Ganges river
system. There were several reasons for establishing a
park on the daunting slopes of the Himalayas. First, it had
become necessary to protect the forest (the silver fir, the
tree juniper, and the silver birch are in greater danger
than the many varieties of rhododendron such as
Rhododendron arboreum, Nepal's national flower) and its
fauna (the musk deer, the snow leopard, the Himalayan
black bear, the wolf and the lesser panda animals which
it is now forbidden to hunt). But equally vital was the
protection of the culture of the Sherpas who began to
come here from Tibet in the sixteenth century and now live
within the perimeter of the Park. The Sherpas, who
belong to the Myingmapa sect of Tibetan Buddhism, built
temples and monasteries, the most remarkable of which
is perched on a rocky spur some 4,000 metres up. Many
other religious monuments are maintained and even still
built by them: tomb-sanctuaries known as chortens in
and around the villages and along paths; rocks and mani
walls of stone slabs engraved with inscriptions; white
prayer flags and retreats high up the hill slopes, and
water-driven prayer-mills in streams. For the Sherpas,
who believe that compassion towards all living creatures
is the root of perfection, Sagarmatha Park is sacred for
spiritual as well as for ecological reasons.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The ancient city of
Damascus, Syria
Perhaps the most famous building in
Damascus is the Omayyad mosque, built
between 705 and 715 AD on the orders of
caliph Walid I. But Damascus, thought to
be the world's oldest capital, contains
many other riches. The outer walls of the
mosque are those of the Temple of Jupiter
constructed in the third century AD under
the emperors Septimius Severus and
Caracalla on the site of another temple
dating back to the eleventh century BC.
The quarters clustered around the early
Aramaean town show countless traces of
the city's long history. The Islamic heritage
is of course the richest, and the buildings
(110 of which have been classified as
historic monuments) are often in a good
state of preservation if they are still being
used like most of the mosques,
schools, mausoleums and other religious
edifices. On the other hand, the condition
of non-religious constructions such as
hammams, souks and palaces is
deteriorating, as is the urban fabric itself.
The Syrian authorities hope to halt the
ravages of "modernization" by subsidizing
historical monuments, preserving the
traditional activities of shopkeepers and
craftsmen, and adapting the flow of traffic
to the structure of the city.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Persepolis, Iran
When Darius the Great built a new
capital on the arid plains of Fars, he
wished to proclaim the power of his
empire and his calling as a uniter of
peoples: his rule then extended from
the steppes of central Asia to the banks
of the Nile, and from the Indus to the
Danube. Work on the capital began in
518 BC and was continued over more
than sixty years by his successors
Xerxes and Artaxerxes. The result was
Persepolis, an architectural complex of
a sumptuousness the world has rarely
seen. The bas-reliefs (see photo) lining
the monumental stairway leading to the
enormous audience hall known as the
apadana attest to the grandeur of the
Persian empire. Thirteen huge columns
give an idea of the apadana's
breathtaking size, even though the
colossal capitals consisting of
gryphon's heads and roaring lions
which once supported the twenty-
metre-high roof now lie in the dust.
Darius, who was influenced by the
teachings of Zoroaster, was the author
of noble inscriptions which still survive.
"I wish to think of justice for as long as
I can", reads one of them. Once a
dynastic capital into which flowed
offerings and tribute from the "twenty-
three peoples of the empire", a royal
necropolis dedicated to the notion of
universalism, Persepolis had few
inhabitants left by 330 BC when
Alexander burnt it to the ground.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
*
tj*
!
« «
Meidan-e Shah (Royal Square), Isfahan, Iran D
îim
w\
Isfahan, in the centre of Iran, was already a large city
when the Safavid Shah Abbas the First transferred his
capital there in the late sixteenth century, but he turned
it into a place of such beauty that it became known as
Nesfe Jahan ("Half the World"). His most remarkable
innovation was the Royal Square, a piece of town
planning whose like had never before been seen in the
Muslim cities of Iran, where the only airy, open spaces
amidst the serried ranks of buildings were in the
courtyards of the caravanserais and the biggest
mosques. A rectangle surrounded by a double row of
barrel-vaults (¡wan), the Square is 500 metres long and
165 metres wide. It was used for processions, military
parades, and games of polo. Four superb buildings
decorated with murals and brilliant enamelled tiles
stand symmetrically around the Square: the Royal
Mosque; the Sheikh Lotfollah Mosque (the sovereign's
private oratory); the Ali Qapu ("the lofty gate") Palace,
which led from the Square to other palaces surrounded
by gardens; and the gateway to the Qeyssariyeh, where
each evening the crowds were entertained by a concert.
Photo shows aerial view of the Royal Mosque.
Tchogha Zanbil, Iran
The site of Tchogha Zanbil is located in
southwestern Iran, north of the city of Ahwaz
and not far from ancient Susa, on the edge of
a plateau overlooking the Ab-e Diz river and
surrounded by tamarind forests. The complex
consists of three concentric mud-brick walls.
The first encloses a large cistern, three palaces,
five underground tombs and a shrine dedicated
to the fire-god Nusku. Seven temples stand
within the second wall, and three more within
the third. In the centre of the whole complex is
a twenty-five-metre-high ziggurat, or storeyed
tower (it was originally twice as high). It
consists of a mud-brick core covered with a
facing of fired bricks, many of which bear
cuneiform inscriptions in the Elamitic
language. The complex was created by King
Untash Napirisha, who ruled from 1265 to
1245 BC. The city, known as Dur Untashi (the
city of Untash) was still unfinished when its
founder died and for the next six hundred
years, until the Assyrian invasion led by
Assurbanipal around 640 BC, its only
Inhabitants were priests.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Nahanni National
Park, Canada O
The regular meanders of the Flat
River; the 290-kilometre-long
canyon carved out of the
Cordillera by its sibling, the
South Nahanni; cave-like frost
pockets; piping sinkholes;
hundred-metre-high waterfalls;
granitic peaks; hot springs;
underground rivers and deep
caves such as the Grotte Valérie
with its multi-hued stalactites
and stalagmites; the Grande
Galerie de Glace, incrusted with
intricate crystals of ice; and the
Galerie des Moutons Morts
which contains the skulls and
skeletons of sheep which
perished several thousand years
ago... these are some of the
natural wonders of Nahanni
National Park, in the Canadian
Northwest. Species which live in
the park are typical of Boreal
forest and Alpine tundra
ecosystems. Nahanni's 4,770 km2
are the home of some
500 species of vascular plants,
more than 260 species of
bryophytes, 170 species of birds
(including the rare and
endangered Peregrine Falcon
and the Golden Eagle) and over
40 mammal species including
Dall's Sheep, Caribou, Grey Wolf
and Grizzly Bear. Photo shows
the Gate and Pulpit Rock in
Nahanni's Third Canyon.
Kluane National Park, Canada
and Wrangell-St. Elias National Monument, USA D
The world's largest nature reserve lies on both
sides of the L-shaped frontier that separates
Alaska from the Yukon Territory of Canada. In
jointly nominating the area for inclusion on the
World Heritage List, the Governments of the
USA and Canada declared that "the Kluane
National Park and Wrangell-St. Elias National
Monument are... a joint resource which remains
intact as an unbroken natural system... (and)
which we believe possesses World Heritage
significance". It would be hard to disagree. The
region is a huge chain of glaciers, many of
which are still advancing, in a mountain system
which has twelve peaks over 4,500 metres.
Under the pressures caused by plate tectonics,
the mountains move and grow. Earthquakes are
common; volcanoes abound; hot springs burst
out of the earth. Over thirty major rivers,
carrying immense loads of silt and rocks
scraped by the glaciers from the mountain
walls, ceaselessly make and unmake terraces,
plains and deltas. Photo shows the Nabesna
Glacier in northern part of Wrangell-St. Elias
National Monument.
Photo M. Woodbridge Williams © National Park Service, U.S. Department of the Interior
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Dinosaur Provincial Park,
Canada
In the south-west corner of the Canadian
province of Alberta, the eroded badlands
are a geologist's dream of fantastically
shaped rock-piles, mesas, buttes, knife-
edge divides and other dramatic features.
The meandering Red Deer River carves out
terraces of lush vegetation, providing
habitats for birdlife of remarkable variety
and abundance. In winter the mild micro¬
climate attracts such animals as the
pronghorn antelope, the mule and the
whitetail deer. Seventy million years ago,
under a different climate, the great reptiles
flourished there. Between 1910 and 1917
there was a veritable "Dinosaur Rush" to
the Red Deer River Valley, as
palaeontologists uncovered fossil remains
of some sixty different species, establishing
the area as the most extensive dinosaur
fossil deposit known. More than 300 major
specimens, representing all the known
families of these vanished monsters, were
extracted from a twenty-four-kilometre
stretch of the Red Deer River. Many are
now preserved in the great natural history
museums of North America and Europe.
(See also back cover).
Pholo © George Lupien, Parks Canada Photo © Bengt Schonback, Parks Canada
L'Anse aux Meadows National Historic Park, Canada
Ever since the publication of the medieval
Icelandic manuscripts that contain the
Vinland sagas, many people tried, in the face
of widespread scepticism, to prove that the
lands discovered by the Norsemen on their
adventurous voyages westward and to
which they gave such enigmatic names,
were on the coast of North America. Then,
twenty years ago, Norse remains were
discovered at l'Anse aux Meadows (or l'Anse
du Midi) on the shore of Epaves Bay in
northern Newfoundland (above). On a
narrow terrace lying between two bogs and
crossed by a small brook, archaeologists
found vestiges of three large dwellings, a
smithy, and four workshops. The buildings
were thick-walled structures of turf with
steeply sloping turf roofs supported by
wooden frames. Floors were of tamped earth
or sand; the hearths were of stone.
Excavations have yielded slag and a quantity
of iron artefacts, together with objects in
bronze, bone and stone, all of Scandinavian
origin. Inset, stone oil lamp of Norse type.
Radiocarbon dating indicates that the
remains are from the eleventh century AD.
Four hundred years before Columbus, l'Anse
aux Meadows was the site of the first
meeting between Europeans whose voyage
had brought them via Greenland from
Iceland, and inhabitants of the New
World the Beothuck Eskimos. Horizontal to
photo, ring-headed bronze pin of Viking Age
Type. Vertical, wooden floorboard from a
small Norse boat.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Independence Hall, USA
In 1732, Andrew Hamilton, a prominent
attorney, undertook with the help of master
builder Edmund Woolley the construction in
Philadelphia of a large redbrick building in
the English Classical style. He wished to
provide a dignified setting for the
deliberations of the Pennsylvania Assembly.
The product of this enterprise is one of the
world's best preserved and most lovingly
maintained historic buildings. It was the
scene of the Second Continental Congress in
1775, whose debates laid the foundations of
an independent United States. It was here
that George Washington was chosen as
Commander-in-Chief, and within its walls
the Declaration of Independence was
adopted and signed. Here too, in 1787,
delegates signed the Constitution which
would serve as a model on every continent,
and which is the earliest document of its
kind. Every year some four million visitors
pass through the rooms of Independence
Hall, and beneath the steeple built in 1753 to
house the famous Liberty Bell which bears
the inscription, "Proclaim liberty throughout
all the land, unto all the inhabitants thereof".
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Mesa Verde National Park,
USAD
In southwestern Colorado, a "green table"
covered with pinyon pine and juniper and
dissected by deep canyons slopes gently
from north to south at an altitude of
between 2,600 and 1,800 metres. In the
sixth century AD an Indian people known
as the Anasazi established camps there and
built semi-subterranean houses, cultivated
maize, beans and squash, and raised
turkeys and hunting-dogs. Their society
underwent rapid change. Between 700 and
1100 AD, they built villages on the high, flat
lands. Their houses were made of wood,
stone and mud, and arranged in compact
"L" or "U" shapes facing a central
courtyard. Circular underground chambers
called kivas, which were used for religious
activities, were placed near the rows of
houses or within the courtyards. As the
population increased, techniques of
architecture, pottery-making and cotton
weaving became more sophisticated, and
farming methods improved. The Anasazi
built terraces and dug reservoirs and
irrigation ditches. And then, suddenly, in
the thirteenth century, the situation
changed dramatically. Settlements on flat
land were abandoned in favour of villages
built in cliff caves, some of which could
only be reached by ladder. Was the soil
exhausted? Was there a period of drought?
Was the population attacked by the
ancestors of the Ute Indians, or did the
society break up as result of internal
quarrels? Whatever the reason, the Anasazi
moved away to the south (where their
descendants the Pueblos live to this day),
leaving in the Mesa Verde, in almost 4,000
archaeological sites, the testimony of their
early history. Shown here, aerial view of
the Sun Temple.
Yellowstone National Park,
USA
In the early nineteenth century, the fur
trappers and gold prospectors who
ventured into the mysterious wilderness of
north-west Wyoming brought back near-
incredible stories: they had seen fountains
of boiling water, thundering waterfalls and
a great lake full of enormous trout. As a
result, three expeditions were organized
between 1869 and 1871, and discovered the
truth to be even stranger than those early
travellers' tales. The landscape of
Yellowstone, which almost defies
description, is an unfinished history of
volcanic evolution. Twenty-seven forests,
buried by eruptions of ash some 50 million
years ago, have been preserved in fossil
form. Hundreds of hot springs and geysers
spurt between the toes of the mountains.
Lava formation accounts for most of
Yellowstone's waterfalls, the best known
of which are to be found between the
precipitous and many-hued walls of the
river's canyon. If the wonders of the site
explain the almost religious awe which it
inspired in the early American discoverers,
the consequences were no less remarkable.
In 1872, the United States Congress set
aside the whole area amounting to some
9,000 km2 as a "Public park or pleasuring-
ground". For the first time in history, a
Government decided to leave in its natural
state, and to protect in perpetuity, a vast
territory, with its rivers, its lakes, its
forests and its animal life.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Grand Canyon National Park,
USA
When the majestic Colorado River passes
through Arizona, the curtain rises on one of
geology's most dramatic spectacles. Here
horizontal layers of the earth's crust were
lifted to a height of 2,500 metres above sea
level, then gouged out by watercourses
which transported thousands of tons a day
towards the sea. Today the Grand Canyon
is a great gash, 1,500 metres deep, 440
kilometres long, and between 200 metres
and thirty kilometres wide. Within its walls
we have a view of geologic time that
covers two thousand million years. Each of
the great eras into which geologists have
divided the history of the earth, from
Precambrian to Cenozoic, is represented.
Almost all the earth's climatic life zones
exist and the various environments support
life in abundance: from desert life forms
low down near the river, to the conifer
forest communities on the rims and the
Alpine zone on the topmost peaks nearby.
Photo © John Green. Amherst. USA
Everglades National Park, USA
A paradise of orchids, the Everglades once described as a "River of
Grass" are also the home of a strange fraternity of tropical and temperate
trees: ash and palm, mulberry and gumbo limbo, oak and mangrove. Part of
a shallow basin, the Park covers an area of 567,000 hectares on the southern
tip of Florida. It provides a sanctuary for sixty reptile species (the American
Alligator has survived there; the American Crocodile struggles to do so) and
the last refuge of the Florida Panther, the Manatee and the Florida Black
Bear. There are huge colonies of storks, ibis and herons. Water, in the form
of rainfall or overflow from Lake Okeechobee, is perhaps the most
important factor in the composition of plant life in the Everglades, blurring
the lines of the landscape and creating subtle biological harmonies. The
Park lies at the interface between temperate and sub-tropical America;
between fresh and brackish water; between the vast urban sprawl of Miami
and the wilderness. (Left) Roseate spoonbill.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Virunga National Park, Zaire
Located almost entirely in the Kivu region of Zaire,
Virunga National Park is a place of extraordinary
diversity, stretching from marshy deltas through vast
savannah, lava plains and volcanic mountains up to the
eternal snows of Mount Ruwenzori more than 5,000
metres above sea level (below). Beside its rivers and lakes
are found some of the biggest concentrations of wild
mammals in the world, including 20,000 hippopotami.
Gorillas still live in its mountains. The White Nile has its
source there in the fabled "Mountains of the Moon", so
that Egypt is in a sense a "gift of Virunga". Siberian birds
winter in Virunga. A source of pride to the people of
Zaire, this national park which has been threatened more
than once by foreign poachers, is constantly patrolled by
guards from the Institut Zairois pour la Conservation de la
Nature ; more than thirty of them have given their
lives in its defence.
Ngorongoro Conservation Area, Tanzania
Between two immense national parks, Tanzania has established a
conservation area so large that it could easily fit in two or three
nations from other continents. Centred on the Ngorongoro
Crater, the area covers some 81,000 square kilometres and
contains many other craters which are among the largest in the
world. From the edge of Empakaai Crater, which is now the site
of a deep lake, the active volcanoes of Mount Oldonyo Leng'ai
can be seen. The protection of natural resourceswater, soil,
plants and animals is the priority task of the authorities who
have succeeded in reaching arrangements with the Masai
herdsmen who live there but who have to wage an unrelenting
struggle against poachers in order to save threatened animal
species such as the panther, the rhinoceros and the
hippopotamus. But the best-known site in the area is the Olduvai
Gorge, famed for the discovery of the skull of man's most
remote ancestor. -w-
i^^HH
Forts and Castles in the Volta, Greater Accra,
Central and Western Regions of Ghana D
The coast of the Republic of Ghana boasts a remarkable series of forts
and castles of all sizes, some in ruins, others well preserved. They are not
the vestiges of conquest or exploration. They were built to protect
trade mainly the trade in gold. The Portuguese, who sought to hold the
monopoly of trade with the country which would later be called the Gold
Coast, built the first castles towards the end of the fifteenth century;
Elmina Castle (left) dates from 1482. A hundred years later their rivals
began to construct their own forts on every promontory and at every
river mouth that seemed likely to provide protection for their ships and
aid their dealings with the local population. The Dutch, the British, the
Danes, the Germans and the Swedes all built forts some forty in all. The
castles changed hands several times, usually with the aid of African
chiefs who rented, lent or sold the land they were built on and profited
from the transit of merchandise first of all gold, then timber, ivory,
cotton goods, palm oil and slaves. After the abolition of the slave trade,
the British bought forts from the Danes in 1850, and from the Dutch in
1872. Today the Government of Ghana occupies the vast premises of
Christiansborg Castle in Accra. Elmina Castle houses a police training
college, while the fortress of Cape Coast has been turned into a history
museum and research centre. Seven other forts are used to
accommodate tourists.
Photo Frank Johnson Ç Ghana Museums and Monuments Board, Accra
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Simien National Park,
Ethiopia
The mountains in the northwest
of the Ethiopian plateau are
famed for their splendour.
Erosion on a massive scale has
gouged out deep gorges and
chiselled peaks and precipitous
cliffs, some with a sheer drop of
1,500 metres. The region, known
as Simien, harbours animals that
are now very rare in Africa, such
as the Ethiopian ibex (Walia
ibex) (inset), the lion-maned
Gelada baboon, and species of
the Simien fox which have no
other habitat. It was chiefly to
protect these species that the
Simien National Park was
created in 1969. Unfortunately, it
is in danger. Local farmers are
using it as grazing land for their
livestock, excessive cultivation
is eroding the shallow soils, and
in the dry season fires started by
these farmers sweep up the cliff
faces, devastating tree, bush
and grass cover. These factors
combined constitute a serious
threat to the survival of the
Walia and the Simien fox. The
authorities are proposing to
resettle the farmers on more
fertile and less fragile soil
outside the park.
Fasil Ghebbi
Gondar Region, Ethiopia
Gondar became the permanent capital
of Ethiopia in the seventeenth and
eighteenth centuries (before then the
Court had followed the king from place
to place as he moved around his realm)
and today efforts are being made to
preserve the castles and monuments of
this "Gondar period" of Ethiopian
history. The first of these is the Castle
of Emperor Fassilides (1632-1667), a
massive square building of black stone,
with four round corner towers topped
by small cupolas, and a fifth
quadrangular crenellated tower
overlooking the ensemble. Within, the
apartments and reception rooms have
survived, though now stripped of the
sumptuous fittings described by
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
contemporary visitors. The other,
smaller castles display a number of
architectural innovations, such as
architraves, cornices and stone frames.
Other monuments of the Gondar period
include the Chancellery of Tzadich
Yohannes, a lions' den, a wedding
house, the small palace of Queen
Mentuab, arcades, the houses of
dignitaries and guards, and churches
where the King attended mass every
day. Some aspects of the complex call
to mind the fortified rural dwellings of
Arabia. But the effect is Ethiopian, even
if the building methods used were
influenced by the Portuguese. Left, the
castle of Fassilides.
Rock-hewn churches,
Lalibela, Ethiopia D
For hundreds of years, the inhabitants of
several Ethiopian provinces built churches
in caves or shrines hollowed out of cliff
faces, leaving visible only a decorated
façade reminiscent of the tombs in Petra,
Jordan. But later on (probably in the early
thirteenth century) Ethiopian craftsmen
produced a remarkable accomplishment of
engineering and architecture by hewing
entire churches out of the living rock. The
buildings blocks of stone fifty to 100
square metres in area first set apart from
the pink tufa soil, then hollowed out and
decorated both inside and outside look
exactly as if they were built with separate
stones, but each of them is a single hewn
and sculpted rock. The best-known are the
eleven churches of the holy city of Lalibela,
which was once used as a capital by the
king who gave it its name. Each church has
its own distinctive layout, proportions,
style, bas-reliefs and wall paintings (above).
The group of buildings, virtually invisible
against the vast landscape dominated by
Mount Abouna Joseph, is laid out
according to a secret religious pattern
based on the topography of Palestine or of
a new Jerusalem, with each church being
thought to represent a stage in the life of
Christ.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Open Air Museum
of Nubia and Aswan,
Egypt D
The monuments of Nubia are now
familiar to the whole world, thanks
to the success of the international
campaign launched by Unesco in
1960. The names of Abu Simbel and
Philae evoke not only the technical
triumphs of their rescue from the
rising Nile, but also the beauty of
the great temples of Ramses II,
hewn out of the cliffs in the
thirteenth century BC, and of the
island of sanctuaries, where the
Nubians worshipped the goddess
Isis until 552 AD. But other shrines
and monuments were rescued
during the campaign, such as
Amada, with its temples from the
fifteenth and thirteenth centuries
BC; or Kalabsha built during the
reign of the Roman Emperor
Augustus. A number of buildings
and sites which were not
threatened by the waters of the
High Dam are also included in what
is a unique "open-air museum":
monuments to Egyptian officials of
the third and second millennia
which illustrate the importance of
Aswan as a frontier city and the
point of departure for military and
commercial expeditions to the
south. The monastery of
St. Simeon (tenth-eleventh
centuries AD), and Islamic
cemeteries of the twelfth and
eleventh centuries, are more recent
milestones in Nubia's religious
history. Left, detail of a colossus
from the temple of Gerf Hussein.
Islamic Cairo, Egypt B
When, less than twenty years after
the Hegira, the Arabs entered Egypt
as champions of a new faith, Islam,
they settled at some distance from
existing cities. Their first capital
was the camp called al-Fustat (the
Tent), which they set up north of
Memphis, under the walls of an
ancient Roman fort. Then two
centuries later, Ahmad Ibn Tulun
built a residential quarter around
the beautiful Mosque which still
bears his name. Another hundred
years went by, and then, in 969 AD,
a little further downstream on the
eastern bank of the Nile, the city of
al-Qáhira (Cairo the Victorious) was
founded. From then onwards, as a
commercial, cultural and
theological centre, Cairo developed
into the greatest Islamic city of the
Middle Ages. Today, the city
contains some 600 registered
historical monuments of great
value, including mosques, colleges,
churches and monasteries, military
buildings, palaces and bazaars. The
architectural wealth of historic
Cairo is enhanced by the fact that
much of the early urban fabric
remains intact; all the successive
"cities" of Cairo, from its
foundation up to the nineteenth
century, have been preserved.
Above, the Ibn Tulun mosque (See
also back cover).
Ancient Thebes with its Necropolis, Egypt
In the second millennium BC, the city of
Thebes, now hidden beneath the modern
town of Luxor, became the capital not only
of a reunited Egypt, freed from the invader's
rule, but also of a great Empire which
stretched as far as the Euphrates. Thebes
devoted its wealth to the construction of
temples. The two immense temple precincts
of Karnak and Luxor, two-and-a-half
kilometres apart, were linked by an avenue
lined with statues of rams, partly excavated
in recent years. Two thousand years ago,
travellers from Asia, Greece and Italy came,
like the tourists of today, to admire the Great
Temple of Amon, the city's chief god, which
the priest-architects . were constantly
extending. The bas-reliefs and pillared courts
of Luxor reflect the aesthetic refinement of
the fourteenth and thirteenth centuries BC,
from Amenophis III to Ramses II. Across the
Nile from Luxor and Karnak, the richly
decorated galleries of royal and private
tombs hewn out of the rock depict with a
wealth of illustration the beliefs, historical
events and daily life of the period. Perhaps
an even more moving sight is the village
which for centuries housed generations of
masons and artists, and whose surviving
dwellings reveal how these anonymous
workers lived as they created monuments
for kings and gods. Photo shows interior of
the burial chamber of Sennufer.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Photo John G. Ross © Rapho, Paris
The Pyramid Fields from Giza to Dahshur, Egypt O
Founded after the unification of the king¬
doms of Upper and Lower Egypt, 5,000 years
ago, Memphis was the capital of united
Egypt until 2150 BC. It subsequently remain¬
ed an important military, administrative and
above all religious centre, where Alexander
the Great and his successors were crown¬
ed as pharaohs. Hardly anything is left of the
great city except for a few colossal statues,
the remains of a temple and the em¬
balming house of the sacred Apis bulls. The
grandest and best-preserved monuments are
the vast pyramid fields to the north and
south of the site. These cemeteries include
the pyramids of kings Cheops, Chephren and
Mycerinus at Giza (see photo); sun-temples
at Abu Ghurah and Abu Sir; pyramid com¬
plexes belonging to ten other kings and
richly decorated tombs of the aristocracy at
Saqqarah; monuments to Snofru and jewel-
packed tombs at Dahshur... No monuments
in the world are more famous; and for
twentieth-century archaeologists the treas¬
ures of Memphis are still far from exhausted.
Abu Mena, Egypt 0
In 296 AD, a group of Christians brought
home a dead soldier from the distant
shores of the Black Sea, and laid his body
to rest in the Mariut desert, west of
Alexandria and not far from a bubbling
spring. Abu Mena, or St. Menas, was an
Egyptian serving in the Roman army, who
had been martyred after proclaiming his
Christian faith. Soon, miracles occurred at
his burial place; the spring water proved
to have healing powers. A church was
built there, and then a monastery, more
churches, pilgrims' rest-houses, ovens,
and public baths. For 400 years, the
humble settlement was a centre of
pilgrimage of such renown that in the
early fifth century the Emperor Arcadius
built there a great basilica, with three
naves and fifty-six marble columns. The
surviving ruins, which include press-
houses, workshops (where phials were
made for the holy water), monks' cells, a
baptistry and the numerous churches are
precious symbols of the marriage between
Egyptian and European architecture.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Archaeological
site of Carthage,
Tunisia
Its green hills, ochre
cliffs and golden beaches
all basking in the
sunlight of the
magnificent bay, the
archaeological site of
Carthage (left), now a
protected area, is slowly
yielding its hidden
treasure. Surrounded by
gardens, the great
houses built for
eighteenth-century
Tunisian nobles seem
still under the protective
influence of the
sanctuaries created in
the Middle Ages by the
warrior-mystics of Islam.
By the water's edge,
scattered here and there
among the modern villas,
or in the middle of the
corn-fields, is all that
remains of a great city,
once the capital of the
Roman province known
as Africa. Further away
in time and deeper
underfoot lie the ashes
of the capital of the
Carthaginian Empire.
Like a breeze from the
sea, the spirit of the
fabled princess Dido,
who came here 2,600
years ago from Tyre in
Lebanon to found her
"new town". Kart
Hadasht, moves quietly
among the ruins. Above,
lamp in the form of a
frog and the head of a
god dates back to the
early third century BC.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Medina of Tunis,
Tunisia D
Not far from Carthage, and at least
as ancient, Tunis was an obscure
little town on the hills within the
lagoon when Hassan ibn an-Nu'man
furnished it with an arsenal, a
harbour and a mosque in the eighth
century. The mosque, known as the
mosque of the olive-tree (az-
Zaytunah), later housed a
celebrated university, while the
arsenal and the harbour pointed the
way to Tunis's fortunes in trade and
warfare. The city became the
capital of Afriqiyah (Tunisia) in the
twelfth century, and later, before
and after the Turkish-Spanish wars
of the sixteenth century, won a
reputation as one of the wealthiest
cities in the Islamic world; today,
remarkably well preserved, it
remains one of the most
welcoming. The Medina and its two
suburbs are havens of tranquillity
and unostentatious beauty (left) in
the heart of the modern metropolis.
Most of the religious buildings and
patrician houses there still bustle
with life, like the shopping streets
that have been the headquarters of
the guilds since the thirteenth
century. The Tunisian authorities
are committed to preserving the
city's historical monuments, which
run into hundreds. Above all, they
wish to safeguard the Medina,
which is itself a monument in its
entirety.
Amphitheatre of El-
Djem, Tunisia
Some ancient cities are particularly
tantalizing because they are
virtually unmentioned in written
sources. One of these mysterious
places is Thysdrus, in the Tunisian
Sahel, on the site of the modern
village of el-Djem. The wonderful
mosaic floors which are all that
remains of its villas tell of the
prosperity of Thysdrus in the third
century AD but say little of the
origin of its wealth, nor why its
citizens built an amphitheatre
which could hold an audience of
35,000. It is now one of the best
preserved amphitheatres in the
world, although after serving for
games during the Roman era it was
put to a variety of uses: as a
stronghold by the Byzantines, and
as a refuge for local tribes when
they rebelled against the
government, twice being attacked
with cannon by the Bey's troops.
Some of the vaults, stairways and
pillars of the façade were recently
restored. But despite the breaches
made by cannonballs most of the
walls of the podium, the arena, the
underground galleries, the tiers of
Corinthian-style arcades and the
substructure of the seats have
survived the centuries unscathed.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Madara Rider, Bulgaria
The exploits of the earliest Bulgarian nomad tribes, which came from the
eastern steppes to settle in the Balkan territories of the Byzantine empire, are
gloriously commemorated in Madara, a village in eastern Bulgaria. In the sheer
rock of the Madara plateau, twenty metres up from the base of the cliff, an
unknown sculptor carved a monument to the victory of his sovereign or clan. It
represents a horseman, almost life size, with a dog running behind him. The
horse is trampling on a lion. The bas-relief has parallels in Iran and the ancient
provinces of the Persian or Parthian empires, but is unique in Europe. It dates
from the eighth century, and bears Greek inscriptions that refer to events that
took place at the time of the Bulgarian Khans Tervel, Kormisos and Omurtag
(705-831). The bas-relief has survived intact from those far-off times, but is being
affected by the mould, lichens and bacteria that live on the rock. It has been
decided to provide the Rider with a removable protective covering.
The rock-hewn churches of Ivanovo,
Bulgaria D
During the Thracian and Roman periods, people lived in the
caves alongside the Rusenski Lorn river near the village of
Ivanovo in north-eastern Bulgaria. At the end of the twelfth
century, on the initiative of Joachim I, the first Bulgarian
patriarch, monks hewed out cells, chapels and churches in
the rock and connected them with a network of galleries and
wooden arcades. Work continued until 1396, and gradually
almost all the churches and chapels were decorated with
wall paintings. Tsarkvata Church, whose decoration dates
from the fourteenth century, is particularly remarkable. The
anonymous painter of its frescoes departed from the canons
of Byzantine iconography, and in his treatment of the nude,
of landscape, and of the architectural background in his
compositions he showed close ties with expressive
Hellenistic art. The conservation of these works on their
fragile and fissured rock support presents problems requiring
complex study and research. Left, frescoes in Ivanovo
church.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
V Tí
r-^r ï'
tí
jw:
* <fc fc *'
r ¿ *M
» «
«
I
r ^ # *' <¿
Photo © Vasil Eftimov, Sofia, Bulgarian National Institute for Cultural Monuments.
The Thracian Tomb
of Kazanlak, Bulgaria
The Thracians, who in ancient times occupied what is
today Bulgaria (as well as part of Turkey) were renowned
among their neighbours and kinsmen, the Greeks, for the
skill of their goldsmiths, the excellence of their
musicians, and the strength of their religious
inspiration the cult of Dionysus and the myth of
Orpheus came from Thrace. Numerous richly adorned
tombs now gradually being excavated also illustrate their
originality as painters. One of the best preserved is a
fourth-century-BC tomb discovered by chance in 1944
near Kazanlak in the department of Stara Zagora. Built of
brick, it comprises a burial chamber 3.25 metres in
diameter of bee-hive shape with a corbelled dome, and a
corridor (dromos) roofed with a pseudo-vault. The tomb's
most remarkable feature is the fresco decoration in the
corridor and the burial chamber. Two bands of frescoes
are painted in the passage, averaging about two metres in
length and thirty centimetres in width. The frescoes in the
burial chamber embellish the plinth, the entablature, and
the upper part of the dome (photo). The paintings were
brilliantly executed using two methods, distemper and
fresco proper. The most interesting fresco in the tomb,
the "funeral banquet", alone deserves to be regarded as
an important landmark in the history of painting.
The Boyana Church, Bulgaria O
In the former village of Boyana, today part of the suburbs
of Sofia, stands one of Bulgaria's most impressive
historical monuments, a complex of three churches
which, although they differ in style and period, form a
harmonious architectural unit. Each of them has a Greek
cross ground-plan with dome, and richly decorated
façades. The Eastern church dates from the tenth and
eleventh centuries, and symbolizes the emergence of a
nation which, through its close contacts with the
merchant cities of the Adriatic, would produce
outstanding achievements in commerce, intellectual life
and the arts. The Western church, built in the nineteenth
century, marks Bulgaria's awakening after a long period
of foreign occupation. In the centre is the so-called
"Kaloyan" church, dating from about 1250 AD. It might be
expected to reflect the feudal anarchy and decadence
which set in after the disastrous Tatar invasion, ten years
earlier, but its frescoes, completed by an unknown artist
in 1259, are both lively and serene. They display a realism
which suggests local folk-art rather than the refinement
of Byzantium. The life-like attitudes and highly
individualized expressions of the figures, whether in
portraits of the church's benefactors, in the scene of the
Last Supper or in the treatment of venerated icons, are
bathed in a vibrant spirituality.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Palace and Park of Versailles, France
The Palace of Versailles was to all intents
and purposes the capital of France from the
end of the seventeenth century until the
Revolution. It lies at the heart of a vast pat¬
tern of lawns, walks and fountains, forming
an ensemble which slowly took shape over
more than a century and a half. Every inch of
it was dedicated to the glory of the King. To
appreciate the setting fully, the visitor
should approach the Palace from the town of
Versailles along one of the avenues which
run beside the immense stables and con¬
verge on the Court of Honour. With no less
than 216 rooms (not all yet restored) the
Palace is a world whose brilliance dazzles
millions of tourists each year just as it did the
courtiers of an earlier age. Outside are the
gardens, the celebrated fountains and the
two smaller palaces, the Trianons. Louis XIV
employed the finest artists of his time: the
architect Le Vau, the decorator Lebrun, and
the garden designer Le Nôtre. The list of
those who have conferred beauty on
Versailles Is still growing, and now includes
the wonderfully gifted craftsmen who
recently completed the restoration of the
Royal Bedchamber and the Hall of Mirrors.
Below, west façade of the Palace.
Photo Jean Feuillie © Archives Photographiques S. P.A. D.E. M., Paris
Mont-Saint-
Michel and its
Bay, France D
Its site, its architecture
and the continuity of its
history have earned for
the Mont-Saint-Michel
the description of
"Wonder of the West". In
ancient times this rocky
islet off the Normandy
coast was a Celtic place
of worship. Then, in the
eighth century, an
oratory dedicated to
St. Michael the
Archangel was
established there, later
succeeded by an abbey.
The full glory of Mont-
Saint-Michel came with
the Gothic age when the
influx of pilgrims was
such that the monks
constructed bigger and
higher buildings resting
on powerful buttresses.
This was the origin of
the five great rooms
crowned by a cloister
which were built on the
northern side between
1211 and 1228 and are
known as La Merveille.
Later the fortunes of
Mont-Saint-Michel went
into steep decline: the
church was partially
demolished and the
abbey was transformed
into a prison. In the last
100 years restoration has
brought back splendour
to this monument which
is not only a major
tourist attraction but is
once again a place of
prayer: on the occasion
of its millennium in 1966,
Benedictine monks were
resettled in the abbey.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
Decorated Grottoes of the
Vezere Valley, France 0
Beneath wooded cliffs, the Vézère river
winds its way through the historic
French provinces of the Limousin and
the Périgord. Over 100,000 years ago
prehistoric men settled in this river
valley in rock shelters where
subterranean streams had hollowed out
caves. Here, until the New Stone Age,
they lived from hunting, fishing and
gathering. In the last 100 years, chance
discoveries and scientifically organized
excavations have brought to light a rich
harvest of remains from this
civilization. Some 150 deposits studied
so far have already yielded over 500,000
flint tools, and fossilized
remains (the skeletons of Cro-Magnon
man) which have enabled specialists to
establish with greater precision the
chronology of the Old Stone Age. A
landmark in our scientific knowledge of
the past, the Vézère grottoes also owe
their universal value to the
masterpieces engraved (as at Les
Combarelles) or painted (as at Lascaux
and Fond-de-Gaume) on their walls,
which shed a new light on the origins
of art. Above, horse painted on the
cave wall at Lascaux.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
V
r
ilfffc
Chartres Cathedral, France
Built on a site already dedicated to the worship of the
Virgin Mary, the Cathedral of Chartres is one of the glories
of Gothic art. An earlier cathedral was almost totally
destroyed by fire in 1194. All that remains of it are parts of
the crypt and most of the west front with its Royal Portal,
whose statue-columns prefigure the Gothic style. The rest
dates from the thirteenth century. The cathedral was
rebuilt so quickly that it has a unity of style which is rare
in medieval buildings of its size; the nave was completed
in 1220, the choir in the following year, the transept and its
two porches in 1245. The edifice is remarkable for the
great boldness of its architectural conception: it
constitutes one of the first examples of the use of outside
flying buttresses to bear the thrust of the vaults, thus
making possible the construction of great windows and a
profusion of stained glass. The 173 windows which have
survived, all put in place before 1250, cover more than
2,000 square metres, and constitute the biggest collection
of early thirteenth-century stained glass. Today they are
severely affected by glass disease. The "International
Stained Glass Centre" recently established at Chartres
should help to provide the patient skills needed to save
these unique treasures.
A
1 ]*!&%
Vézelay church and hill, France O
At Vézelay, on a hill overlooking a peaceful valley, stands
one of the great achievements of Romanesque art.
Around the middle of the ninth century a monastery was
founded there which became a great centre of pilgrimage
and grew in size and importance soon after the year 1000
when it acquired the relics of a venerated saint. Vézelay
was also the starting point of one of the pilgrimage
routes to Santiago de Compostela in Spain and it was
there, in 1146, that St. Bernard of Clairvaux preached the
Second Crusade in the presence of King Louis VII and an
immense crowd. The 120-metre long monastic church
comprises a Romanesque nave and narthex (1120-1190).
The interior is remarkable for its unity of style. The
majestic sculpture of the portals, the variety and
inspiration of the twenty-four capitals make Vézelay a
masterpiece of Burgundian Romanesque sculpture.
Nevertheless, it came close to disappearing: in 1840 the
church was crumbling into ruin when its restoration was
put in the hands of a twenty-six-year-old French architect
named Viollet-le-Duc, the first commission in his long
career as a restorer of medieval architecture. Right, the
Christ on the tympanum.
Sr ./vvr
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Ohrid Region, Yugoslavia
Lake Ohrid in Macedonia (249 km2, average
depth 145 metres) is one of the oldest lakes
in the world. Its warm dark-blue waters,
transparent to a depth of at least twenty
metres, are drawn mostly from springs and
contain living fossils, creatures which have
scarcely changed since the tertiary era.
Some of its sponges are unique, and along
with many species of snail and certain
species of fish they constitute an animal
life which is considered to be one of the
last remnants of the ancient aquatic region
of the Eurasian continent before the Ice
Age. The lake attracts archaeologists as
well as naturalists, since traces of human
settlement in the area stretch back without
a break to Neolithic times. However, the
main feature of Ohrid's historic and
aesthetic past was created by the monks
who, from the end of the ninth century
onwards, built admirably-sited churches,
monasteries and schools. Today Ohrid and
Struga, towns on the shores of the lake,
are as proud of their region's scientific
resources as of its architecture, frescoes
and icons, and have won a new reputation
for their annual festivals of poetry, music
and folklore.
Stari Ras and Sopocani, Yugoslavia
From the ninth century onwards, the princes of Serbia defended a
clifftop stronghold, Stari Ras, against the assaults of Byzantium and
their Eastern neighbours. In the tenth century, they built a church
there, the oldest in the region, and dedicated it to St. Peter. In the
twelfth century, their fortress. Gradina, became the first capital of an
independent Serbian state, and at its foot the town of Trgoviste and
two monasteries keep alive the memory of those who fought for
independence. In 1170, Stefan Nemanja founded the monastery of
Djurdjevi Stupovi, to commemorate a victory against Byzantium. Its
main church, St. George's, was decorated with frescoes; King
Dragutin's chapel was added later. In the middle of the thirteenth
century, a period of political calm and prosperity, King Stefan Uros I
founded a second monastery, Sopocani, whose paintings rank
among the masterpieces of Byzantine art in the Balkans.
J>$
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Historie Split and
Diocletian's Palace,
Yugoslavia
The Roman Emperor Diocletian carefully
prepared his retirement. In 305 AD, having
set up a tetrarchy or system of joint rule by
four emperors, he renounced the imperial
crown and left to spend the last years of
his life in the gigantic palace he had built
near Aspalathos, the Dalmatian village
where he was born. Three hundred years
later, the inhabitants of the nearby town of
Salona, fleeing invaders, sought refuge in
the palace, settled there, and built houses,
workshops, shops and churches within its
precincts. There were many alterations to
the architecture over the centuries, but
throughout their history the citizens of
Aspalathos (later known as Spalato, then
Split) succeeded in exploiting the structure
of the palace while demolishing as little as
possible. They built a harmoniously laid-out
city within the great Roman walls, leaving
in place the peristyle of the palace, the
mausoleum of Diocletian and the temple of
Jupiter.
The old city of Dubrovnik,
Yugoslavia O
Historians of urban planning feel a special
affection for Dubrovnik. Its fortified walls
enclose a perfectly preserved complex
containing buildings, both private and
public, sacred and profane, from each
period of the city's history since it was
founded in the seventh century AD.
Another remarkable feature: the city still
has in its possession the town-planning
documents, decrees and regulations which
governed every phase of its expansion.
They show how the designs of the planners
were followed with a scrupulous fidelity
which is rare in the annals of urban
development. Their plans brought to
squares and streets, residences and even
the most humble buildings a grandiose
style worthy of a city which was the centre
of a distinctive political and territorial
organization known as the Republic of
Ragusa and which was proud of its
freedom and of its trading
accomplishments.
Plitvice Lakes National Park,
Yugoslavia 0
Playing hide-and-seek among limestone
and dolomite rock formations, the Korana
River in Croatia suddenly pauses to form a
chain of some twenty lakes and emerald-
green pools. The lakes rise in tiers
separated by a staircase of dams crossed
by waterfalls that are often over twenty,
and in one case eighty metres high. This
landscape of stone and water was built by
living organisms. Mosses, algae and
bacteria have all been incrusted and
fossilized by deposits of calcium
carbonate: the cave-pitted natural dams
between the lakes grow a centimetre
higher each year. The Plitvice Lakes are
magnificent architecture in movement, in a
site held in awe by man from time
immemorial. The wooded hills overlooking
the water are a refuge for bears and
wolves, and for rare birds like the
Capercaillie and the Great Horned Owl.
Beech, fir and juniper grow in one of
Europe's few remaining virgin forests.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Bryggen, Norway
In the past, the towns of northern Europe were built
of wood. One of them has survived on the west coast
of Norway. Its name is Bryggen ("The Embankment"),
and it was founded in the eleventh century, if not
earlier, on the natural harbour of Bergen. Until about
1300, it was mainly owned by members of the old
Norwegian trading nobility. Later, at the time of the
Hanseatic League, it was gradually taken over by a
colony of German merchants, who were themselves
ousted in 1754 by "The Norwegian Office", which
traded in dried fish. Bryggen had badly deteriorated by
the beginning of this century, but life is slowly
returning to it through the work of a public foundation
which is buying up and restoring buildings, and is
carrying out archaeological excavations on the site of
the most recent fire to ravage the town, in 1955.
Enough of the houses, all wooden gabled buildings
with a single or double courtyard and stone kjellere
("cellars"), have survived to evoke the austere
elegance of Bryggen as it must have looked when last
rebuilt, after another fire had destroyed it in 1702.
Urnes Stave Church, Norway %
The twelfth-century church at Urnes, in Sogn
og Fjordane county, is generally considered to
be the finest of Norway's thirty surviving
wooden stave churches (stavkirke). The
timber in the northern wall of the nave,
including the portal carved with interlaced
fighting animals, was re-used from a building
some 100 years older. Similar carving covers
the western gable triangle of the nave, and
one of the gables of the choir, which must
also be relics of the older building. The
medieval furnishings of the church include a
wooden Calvary group and two candlesticks
of Limoges enamelled bronze. The altarpiece
and pulpit, the gallery, choir screen, pews and
wall paintings all date from before 1700. The
church is as solid as ever as a result of
scrupulous maintenance and protective
measures against fire, insect parasites and
burglary.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Rock Drawings in Valcamonica, Italy D
Systematic investigation during the last two decades has brought
to light some 130,000 rock engravings in Valcamonica, a narrow
Alpine valley in Lombardy. The most recent date from the
beginning of the Christian era; the oldest go back as far as
7000 BC. From the earliest bands of hunters, who depicted the
quarry they wished to kill, to the bellicose farmers of later times,
who adorned their battle scenes with inscriptions in Etruscan
lettering, the creators of the rock carvings set out for
decipherment the history of a people during 8,000 years of
economic, social, cultural and religious evolution. In the Neolithic
age, the first Camunian farmers depicted worship of the sun and
of the dead, propitiatory dances, and initiation ceremonies. Later
their place was taken by stock breeders, and then traders, who
had a more complex economic life and whose carvings feature
idols and spirits with prominent eyes. Then came the cult of
weapons, the powers of the subconscious, priests and
polytheism. The stone engravers of Valcamonica may have been
illiterate, but their work is more informative than the written
evidence left by many an ancient civilization.
Aachen Cathedral,
the Federal Republic
of Germany O
The schoolchildren of the half-dozen
European countries which claim
Charlemagne as a figure in their
national history learn that his favourite
abode was the Frankish city of Aachen
(which now lies at the intersection of
the borders of the Federal Republic of
Germany, Belgium and the
Netherlands). In 790 he began to build
next to his castle the Palace Chapel
which is today the core of Aachen
Cathedral. Its construction, by the man
who had unified Western Europe, lent
weight to his claim to equality, as the
heir of Rome, with the Emperors at
Constantinople. The chapel, with its
monumental cupola, elegantly
combined late Classical and Byzantine
architectural elements with new
conceptions, and remains the finest
symbol of the technical and cultural
renaissance engineered by
Charlemagne after four hundred years
of anarchy and decline. That
renaissance is also reflected in the
bronzes, ivories and gold treasures in
the Cathedral's treasure vault.
Charlemagne's tomb, a classical
sarcophagus with bas-reliefs depicting
the myth of Proserpina, is more than a
museum-piece or a historical curiosity.
It symbolizes the veneration that has
been attached to his name for eleven
centuries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Wieliczka Salt Mine,
Poland
The Wieliczka salt mine has been
worked since the thirteenth century
and is still in operation. Its miners have
now reached a depth of 327 metres,
and the mine galleries on nine different
levels are three hundred kilometres
long altogether. At Wieliczka a
collection of tools, equipment and
machines demonstrates the
development of salt mining techniques
over 500 years, as well as
improvements in safety measures,
ventilation and lighting systems, and
methods of transporting the salt.
Archaeological finds exhibited at the
mine reveal that surface deposits were
worked as far back as the Neolithic
Period. The mine also contains works
of art subterranean chapels hewn
from the rock-salt and decorated with
salt statues. As far back as the
fifteenth century the "Krakow Salina",
a highly-organized royal enterprise that
was one of Poland's major sources of
revenue, was a "tourist attraction".
Travellers admired its unusual
landscapes and the architectural
grandeur of the excavations in these
mines which are now a museum of
technical ingenuity and a monument to
human effort.
i»*.4.-'«ly. . .. C
iStf* *
>.%
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Wonders
of
the world
by Georges Fradier
Photo >5 CAF. Warsaw
Cracow's historical
and architectural urban centre, Poland D
Trees have replaced the ramparts, except to the north where walls, towers and
barbicans still stand. Otherwise, Cracow is still as its planners designed it in
1257. On the huge market square in the centre (above) stand buildings that
symbolize three powers of the city: the tower of the Gothic Town Hall, the
Church of Our Lady of the Assumption, and the Cloth Hall. This exemplary
model of town-planning is being matched today by a conservation plan which
covers the whole of the ancient capital, as well as the town of Kazimierz, on
the other side of the River Vistula, which was absorbed into the municipality
long ago. Between these neighbourhoods, where dozens of monasteries cluster
round Cracow University (founded 1364, the second oldest in central Europe
after Prague), rises Wawel Hill and its two imposing monuments, the Royal
Castle and the Cathedral. They contain valuable works of Polish art that have
escaped the pillaging of the centuries. In the castle, originally of Gothic design
but transformed into a Renaissance palace at the beginning of the sixteenth
century, is a famous series of tapestries which were executed in Brussels
around 1560 on the instructions of King Sigismund II Augustus. Among the
many priceless objects in the cathedral, whose Gothic vaults house the
sepulchres of kings and queens, is the so-called lance of Saint Maurice, which
the Holy Roman emperor Otto III gave to Boleslav the Valiant in 1000 AD.
The Bialowieza National Park, Poland
In 1919, the European bison vanished from the great Polish forest. Today herds
of these powerful animals have been reconstituted and roam freely in the
Bialowieza National Park. Like the hardy tarpán wild horses, which have also
been saved from extinction, the bison were part of the original fauna of the
Bialowieza forest which lies on the watershed between the catchment areas of
the Baltic and Black Seas, and Is one of the oldest expanses of natural lowland
woods in Europe. Some 700 species of vascular plants are found in the Park,
and twenty-three species of broad-leaved and coniferous trees. As for animal
life, in addition to bison and horses, fifty-four species of mammals and 200
species of birds find sanctuary there.
AT first sight it is bewildering, this list of
fifty-seven wonders of the world (not that
it is closed: in a few years time it will have
swollen towho knows? a hundred, a thou¬
sand and one). When contemplating these mas¬
terpieces proposed by twenty-odd States one is,
momentarily, perplexed. "Here are the most
authentic, the most individual things we
possess", one can almost hear the representa¬
tives of each State presenting their case. So
are we looking at a cavalcade of each nation's
history, a panoply of symbols of its "cultural
identity"?
A people's awareness of its birthright does not
come about by accident. However puerile it may
be, patriotic drum-beating about a nation's archi¬
tecture, exploits, inventions or philosophy, none¬
theless presupposes some kind of education and
publicity. How can you talk to people about a his¬
toric monument if they have no idea about history
and are blind to architecture? So let us welcome
the teaching of national history, the advance of
education, the work of the media.
In a sense, then, the World Heritage Conven¬
tion is a reflection of the state of national cultures
in the late twentieth century.
But it is much more than that; unlike many a
diplomatic treaty, it is ahead of its time. For the
property it presents to us is considered to be of
universal value. Now what civilization has ever
acknowledged that areas of national territory, or
objects of every possible origin and form can pos¬
sess a "universal" value? (True, the ancient
Greeks drew up a list of Seven Wonders of the
World. But what a small world it was! Five of the
seven had been built by the Greeks themselves,
six were products of their own times. The Egyp¬
tian pyramids were the only exception; they were
already 1,500 years old and are, incidentally, the
only wonder to have survived). How justified is
the proposition that monuments and sites ad¬
mired in one country should command admiration
in all the rest in other words that the whole of
humanity now has a common heritage?
In the case of natural property the idea is not
too hard to accept. The world's biological re¬
serves are of concern to everyone on earth. The
great ecosystems know no frontiers, and there is i
something faintly ludicrous about "national" |
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
i ownership of geological phenomena. Everyone
feels that "the beauties of nature" should be
shared or respected by all human beings precisely
because they were not made by human hand. As
for man's own works, it requires little imagination
to realize that we are all heirs to the treasures of
human knowledge and thought. The trouble is
that we are dealing here not with abstractions but
with tangible, immovable things: buildings firmly
established on a plot of land, inseparable from a
landscape, built by the sons of that particular
piece of soil acting in accordance with their own
specific aims and standards.
The list urges us to appreciate the universal
value of the temples of Abu Simbel and those of
Tikal. Mont Saint-Michel and its bay are included
as being capable of stirring the emotions of peo¬
ple all over the world. And why not? One hundred
and fifty years ago, this monastery on a desolate
wave-swept rock was used as a prison, it was a
. miniature Gothic Alcatraz. Presumably, the
French authorities of the day attached no value to
it except as a penitentiary. But today the Mont
Saint-Michel is presented to us as a "wonder" in
the fullest sense. And everyone is bound to agree,
provided that he or she sees the place, can expe¬
rience a sense of wonder at it, is interested in
medieval Christianity, twelfth-century European
architecture, and the glint of wet sand.
At any rate, this is what the World Heritage
Convention implies. History has begun to take on
a human face. Exchanges take place in a spirit of
equality which shatters national self-centredness
and disturbs us as we smugly contemplate "our"
monuments, the inimitable repositories of "our"
values. Here, "in the same bag", we have Aachen
and Isfahan, the age of Charlemagne and that of
Abbas I, Quito and Dubrovnik, Cairo and Kath¬
mandu, because it is seemingly accepted that the
Swedes (among others) will see Isfahan like the
Iranians, and that the Iranians (among others) will
see Kathmandu like the Nepalese.
Far from being backward-looking, the Heritage
Convention seems to be prophetic. But there is
one point where States party to it make a particu¬
larly striking innovation. They pledge to preserve
the cultural and natural property on their inven¬
tory. Each State "recognizes that the duty of
ensuring the identification, protection, conserva¬
tion, presentation and transmission to future
generations of the heritage.. .belongs primarily to
that State". Such an obligation is quite without
precedent!
For we are talking about a heritage, a legacy:
old towns and ancient monuments. People think
that we have inherited this legacy from our ances¬
tors to whom it was bequeathed by their own
forebears and who religiously preserved it with us
in mind. But this is simply not true, except for a
few items on the list. National parks are fairly
recent creations and have obviously been protec¬
ted ever since they were established. Previously,
their contents needed less protection because
they were further from the reach of interference
by our forefathers. In addition, certain buildings
have been deliberately bequeathed to us: royal
palaces, which now belong to the "nation" or the
"people", churches, mosques and temples which
are still in use. But all the other property on the list
is there by chance or through the tireless efforts
of archaeologists who reconstruct ruins and are
still today rescuing monuments from the jungle,
from the earth, from oblivion.
Governments now make it their business to res¬
tore cultural monuments, and sometimes the
general public rallies to the defence of buildings
which have survived from their past. The reasons
for this about-turn in public opinion are well
known. The adoption of the Heritage Convention
coincided with mounting concern about the dete¬
rioration of the environment, the exhaustion of
natural resources, and the stultifying monotony
of much international architecture. In more than
one town and city the authorities actually began
fo stop demolishing. A few voices crying in the
wilderness had already insisted on the value of
buildings and quarters that had miraculously sur¬
vived the centuries. Suddenly their cries were
being echoed by millions of people. These buil¬
dings were seen to be remarkable by any stan
dards, not just objects of nostalgic regard. Each
one is unique and therefore irreplaceable.
These treasures are not only beyond price, they
are terrifyingly fragile. They need the kind of pro¬
tection they have never been given; they could,
not survive a few more years of neglect. Natural
parks are equally vulnerable: a few concessions to
the motorway planners, hotel chains or promoters
of big game hunting would make short work of
them. Protection is becoming a permanent duty.
The States party to the Convention perform this
duty all the more effectively because public opi¬
nion is not only behind them but often ahead. We
have decided to remove from present or future
dangers the little we have salvaged from the past.
In the way of "immovable" property we have
nothing better to transmit to them.
So far none of the cultural property on the Heri¬
tage List (with one exception which I will mention
shortly) is less than two hundred years old. Let us
hope that the twentieth century will be fittingly
represented one day. But how? By which piece of
architecture of universal value? And which monu¬
ment capable of being preserved, in an age when
buildings are designed to last until their cost has
been recovered? Which steel tower, Olympic
monument or nuclear power station will be regar¬
ded as unique and irreplaceable?
And now for the exception, the one twentieth-
century monument already on the list. Its name,
Auschwitz-Birkenau, is that of two localities in
Poland. It is the most hideous compound imagi¬
nable, a fitting site for a place which saw human
absurdity reveal its fullest scope for crime in its
most rational and clinical form. Between 1940 and
1944 Hitler's henchmen packed the camp with
starving deportees from twenty-four countries to
provide slave labour. In those years they slaugh¬
tered four million men, women and children. The
remains of some of themspectacles, teeth, hair
and fabric made from hair have been pre¬
served, with various instruments of torture, in the
Auschwitz "museum". The Polish Government,
which has turned Auschwitz into a Monument to
the Martyrs, has created a zone of silence
stretching one kilometre round the camp.
To this camp of horror should we not add ano¬
ther group of buildings which, behind the ele¬
gance of their eighteenth-century façades, con¬
ceal a sinister reality? This is the Island of Gorée,
off the coast of Senegal near Dakar, where for
centuries millions of black slaves men, women
and children were confined before being trans¬
ported to the Antilles. The prosperity of Gorée
lasted for a long time, as long as the traffic in
"ebony wood". Today the deserted "slaveries"
have been eroded by time and salt. The Senega¬
lese Government wishes to transform this symbol
of the suffering of an entire people into a place of
dialogue, a shrine of reconciliation. Once res¬
tored, Gorée will house a centre of studies on the
black diaspora, a conference centre, and a history
museum.
The members of the World Heritage Committee
deserve our gratitude for having selected these
two monuments. In so doing they have given us a
clearer understanding of the extent to which the
notion of the natural and cultural heritage not
only includes but goes beyond aesthetic and
scientific criteria. The world heritage mirrors the
world. Its natural glories possess a value we che¬
rish because they are untouched by human hand,
except by the hand which seeks to preserve them.
The value of the cultural heritage lies in the quality
of the work through which artists and builders
have expressed the civilizations to which they
belonged. But there is also a moral value: it is for
us to ensure that, tomorrow, the worst no longer
rubs shoulders with the best.
Georges Fradier
GEORGES FRADIER, French novelist and
essayist, was for many years a member of
Unesco's staff, latterly as Director of the Division
of Human Settlements and Socio-Cultural Envi¬
ronment. His published works include Encoun¬
ters and Celebrations (1963) and About the Qua¬
lity of Life (1976) published by Unesco.
z+*
-JL-*
fc*J
" ',>
,
The Island of Gorée. the former slave-trade
centre, off the coast of Senegal. Above, the
Auschwitz-Birkenau concentration camp.
34
BRODARD GRAPHIQUE. COULOMMIERS - Dépôt légal C 1 -Août 1980- IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE ¡Printed in France). Commission paritaire N" 27.253.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Two Unesco publications
on the heritage of Nepal
Unesco and the Nepalese
Government are collabo¬
rating in an international
campaign to preserve the
cultural and natural heri¬
tage of the Katmandu Val¬
ley. In Monuments of the
Katmandu Valley, British
architect John Sanday,
who supervised the
reconstruction of Nepal's
ancient royal palace of
Hanuman Dhoka as a
Unesco/United Nations
Development Programme
expert, describes the val¬
ley's major monuments,
relating them to their his¬
torical and religious back¬
ground and to patterns of
living still found today.
129 pages 18 French francs
Sherpa Architecture stu¬
dies the architectural tra¬
dition of a people who live
in a highly challenging
environment and are
known the world over
because of their role as
guides and porters for
mountaineering expedi¬
tions. Prepared by Italian
architects Valerio Sestini
and Enzo Somigli and
illustrated - with their
drawings and photo¬
graphs, the study is based
on a survey made in 1975
during the expedition to
Nepal organized by the
Alpine Club of Italy.
74 pages 18 francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in
countries not listed, along with subscrip¬
tion rates in local currency, will be supplied
on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne IVictorial, 3000.
- AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. - BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
- BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 560-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena
51 , Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. -
ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis
Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1,
SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7,
place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. - GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
- FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German
ed. only): DEUTSCHER UNESCO - Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57,
D-5300 Bonn 3. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stutt¬
gart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger GmbH,
Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034
Germering/München. - GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana
Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of
Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications IHK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyves-
bolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,.
Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. "
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publications Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare,
511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv 61000
- JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc.,
Shuhwa Toranomon 3bldg, 23-6, Toranomon 3-Chome, Minato-
ku, Tokyo 105, - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O.
Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO.
Mazenod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern
Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box
286, Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication 8- Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue,
Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323,
JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26
Republic Street, Valletta. - MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company
Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British
Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS.
For the "Unesco Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen
Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all
Unesco publications: N.V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9,
The Hague. - NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine
N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office, Government
Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130,
Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.
Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin;
Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The
University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan,
P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University
Bookshop of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No.,729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co.,' 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service- Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033. Johannesburg.
SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam
Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. Al Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All
publications A/B C.E. Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel,
Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the
Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgränd 2, Box 150
50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All publications:
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue
Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar¬
es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi
A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No. 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Govt, 8ookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. -UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Repubtike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT)
Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Nature weathered the curious rock formations in Dinosaur Provincial
Park, Canada (above). The hand of man shaped the historic centre of
Islamic Cairo (belcw). Under an international Convention which breaks
new ground in linking together the protection of the world cultural and
natural heritage, each of these sites has been included on a list of
irreplaceable cultural and natural properties "of outstanding universal
value" (see also pages 13 and 20).
!
:le
]]>
</page>
</document>
