<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074785eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COlinef A window
open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
r>\-
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
128
Ireland
Photo © National Museum of Ireland, Dublin
Celtic crucifix
This gilt-bronze crucifix depicts Christ on the cross surrounded by
the four Evangelists. It was fashioned by an Irish artist during
the 7th century A.D., a time of remarkable cultural flowering in
Ireland. The figures are richly decorated with patterns
incorporating whorls, interlacings and spirals, typical motifs of
Celtic art that date back to the pre-Christian era.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco CoUrfep
FEBRUARY 1978 31ST YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 17 LANGUAGES
Japanese DutchEnglish
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian i
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
"Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
bales and distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In
August and September when it Is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see Inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
Will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
Managing
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Editors
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
' Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
Edition
: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
: Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
: Frederic Rahola (Barcelona)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition :
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
page
4 A GLOBAL CHALLENGE
by Yahia A. Mageed
5 THE IMPENDING WATER FAMINE
If nothing is done, water resources in the world's populated
areas will be nearly exhausted by the year 2015
by Valentin I. Korzun and Aleksei A. Soko/ov
8 THE UNITED NATIONS WATER CONFERENCE
10 MODERN CITIES: AN UNQUENCHABLE THIRST?
15 THE STRANGE WAYS OF H20
by Michel Bâtisse
17 WILL DESERTS DRINK ICEBERGS?
by Paul-Emile Victor
18 BENEATH THE ARCTIC ICE
Photos
23 REDRAWING THE WORLD'S WATERSCAPES
by Jerry Pournelle
25 HYDROLOGY: A SCIENCE 5,000 YEARS IN THE MAKING
by Raymond L. Nace
29 SUMATRA'S SWAMPLAND PIONEERS
by Gérard Francillon
34 IN BRIEF
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
IRELAND: Celtic crucifix
Cover
As its population mounts, the world is making
increasing demands on its limited supplies of
fresh water. Yet all too often water is
squandered, polluted and poisoned, imposing
strains on supply systems which they cannot
withstand for long. If a world water crisis is
to be averted, far-reaching programmes must
be undertaken to provide adequate supplies
of clean water for everyone, while also
preserving the delicate ecological balance in
rivers and lakes. Cover shows three Chinese
fishermen, net hanging at the ready, on the
Yangtse river near Nanking.
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A global
challenge
by Yahia Abdel Mageed
ALL the great challenges facing humanity, all the aspirations
of mankind for a better life with a greater measure of
dignity, justice and security require a greater use of water.
It is impossible to think of raising living standards without
providing adequate supplies of good-quality water for the basic
needs of human existence and survival.
The bold resolves of the United Nations Conferences on the
Environment, on Food, and on Human Settlements held in recent
years will come to nothing unless steps are also taken to assure
growing supplies of clean water to meet these challenging
demands.
The most obvious need is for drinking water for people and
livestock. Those who are accustomed to drawing their water by
turning a tap do not always realize what a precious commodity
water is to others. More than three-quarters of the rural popu¬
lation in developing countries have no access to adequate supplies
of reasonably g"ood-quality water to meet their essential needs.
Lack of water and poor-quality water are the sources of some
of the worst health hazards to which mankind continues to be
exposed. To permit such widespread conditions to continue
would be a slur on our civilization.
To the need for drinking water must be added the need of
water for food. Only a relatively small part of the world's pro¬
ductive acreage consists of irrigated land and the potential of even
this small area is not fully exploited.
It is significant that the U.N. Water Conference (see page 8)
and the U.N. Conference on Desertification (see Unesco Courier,
July 1977) were held in the same year, for the two subjects are
complementary.
In the context of today's world energy crisis, hydropower
assumes special significance in many developing countries and
there is much untapped potential awaiting development.
Another priority claimant is industry, which needs water both
for cooling and for cleaning. The thirst of industries for water
can be gauged by the fact that in highly developed countries the
water needs of industry often outstrip both agricultural and
household use.
Such vast needs can only be met by a major effort of govern¬
ments and the international community to mobilize the resources
required to tackle the job of water development.
The dimensions of the effort needed are truly staggering. The
cost of supplying adequate water of reasonable quality to all who
need it will run into billions of dollars.
We cannot rely solely on new water resources to meet our
greatly increased water needs. Over-use or "mining" of under¬
ground sources must be avoided. Fortunately there is immense
potential in water savings through more efficient delivery and use,
and through the reclaiming of streams, lakes and rivers which
once produced clean water but have since become polluted.
One consideration that makes me hopeful that we will prove
equal to the task is that water represents the point at which all
our international programmes meet: the need for food production,
for a better life for the poorest population groups and for a head-
on effort to restore a healthy balance to our environment.
Yahia A. Mageed
YAHIA ABDEL MAGEED, Sudanese hydrologist, was Secretary-Gene¬
ral of the United Nations Water Conference held in Mar del Plata
(Argentina) in March 1977. The Sudan's Minister of Irrigation and Hydro¬
electric Power, he is also a member of several international commissions
dealing with water problems.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
More than a billion persons (half of them children) In rural areas of the
developing world have no ready access to clean water. In these vast
regions, women and children are obliged to spend hours of each day
walking far from their homes to the nearest source of water, weighed
down with back-breaking containers.
Photo Constantin Manos © Magnum, Pans
The impending
water famine
If nothing is done,
water resources in the world's
populated areas will be
nearly exhausted by the year 2015
by Valentin I. Korzun andAleksei A. Sokolov
THE total volume of water on Earth
has been estimated at the enormous
figure of 1.386 billion cubic kilo¬
metres. If spread evenly over the entire sur¬
face of the globe it would form a layer no
less than 3,700 metres deep!
Since 96.5 per cent (1.338 billion km3) of
all this water is ocean, it would perhaps be
more logical to call our planet "Ocean",
rather than "Earth"!
The process known as the "hydrological
cycle" endlessly evaporates water from the
surface of the oceans into the atmosphere,
precipitates it on to the land as rain and
snow, and then returns it to the oceans
again. This constant circulation restores
the qualities of water and makes it fit for
further use. What is more and this is
what distinguishes water from other natu¬
ral resources such as oil, gas and coal it
can be used time and time again, and yet
its total volume never diminishes.
There is no objective evidence of any
"leak" from the atmosphere into outer
space which could, sooner or later, reduce
the Earth's stock of water, and transform
our planet into an arid and lifeless desert.
But this reassuring news does not mean
that there is no "water problem". For cen¬
turies, men have squandered water and
strained its capacities for self-renewal and
self- purification. And though we do not go
along with the gloomy predictions of some
futurologists, we are convinced that the
water problem is one of the most critical i
social and economic issues of our time. I
VALENTIN IGNATIEVICH KORZUN is chairman of the U.S.S.R. National
Committee for Unesco's International Hydrological Programme and deputy head
of the U. S. S. R. 's bureau of hydrological and meteorological services. He is the
author of more than 30 studies on hydrology.
ALEKSEI ALEKSANDROVICH SOKOLOV is a member of the U.S.S.R.
National Committee for Unesco's international Hydrological Programme. The
head of the U. S. S. R. 's bureau of hydrological and meteorological services, he is :
the author of some 100 studies on world water problems.
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
, The crux of the problem is that in order
to live and work, people require water of a
certain quality, and above all fresh water.
Since the bulk of the Earth's water is con¬
centrated in the ocean, it must be desalted
before it can be used, and desalting, unfor¬
tunately, is still a very costly process.
In some cases of extreme necessity
desalting is economically viable, and will be
used more extensively in the future, but its
role in the world water balance should not
be overestimated.
During the International Hydrological
Decade, Soviet scientists prepared a detail¬
ed inventory which revealed that world
fresh-water reserves, including rivers,
lakes, groundwater, snow fields and ice¬
caps, totalled 35 million km3, or some 2.5
per cent of all the Earth's water.
But the readily available supply is even
smaller, because 70 per cent of these assets
(more than 24 million km3) are, quite liter¬
ally, frozen in the ice and snow of the
Arctic, the Antarctic and Greenland, and
are virtually inaccessible.
More than 10.5 million km3 of fresh water
lie underground. These reserves constitute
one of the main sources of supply for many
countries. -£ut exploitation of such "natu¬
ral reservoirs" is severely limited, firstly
because they are unevenly distributed
throughout the world, and secondly
because they can only be tapped when the
inflow of water filtering down from the sur¬
face (in the form of natural precipitation or
waste water from human use) matches or
exceeds the outflow.
In most countries, the principal source of
water for human consumption and use is
and will continue to be the surface water
contained in rivers and lakes. But these
stocks are far from limitless. The latest
figures show that rivers and lakes contain
no more than 95,000 km3, a mere 0.26 per
cent of the world's fresh water (0.007 per
cent of its total water reserves).
Most of the water found on the land
comes from moisture absorbed into the
atmosphere from the seas and oceans.
Deposited on the land in the form of preci¬
pitation, it replenishes lakes and rivers. The
ocean thus acts as a gigantic natural desalt¬
ing plant, guaranteeing the quantity and
quality of fresh water resources.
The most recent data indicate that total
annual precipitation on land amounts to
1 19,000 km3. But only some 45,000 km3 of
this are returned to the ocean by rivers, and
some 2,000 km3 via the glaciers of the Arc¬
tic and Antarctic. (The rest evaporates into
the atmosphere or infiltrates deep into the
earth.)
It is thus the river flow generated by this
annual precipitation that constitutes our
renewed water supplies. It might be com¬
pared to a return on invested capital, which
can be used without "tapping", the original
investment.
Thus, the real problem is not that the
Earth is short of water, but that its reple¬
nishment in /ires/7 water is limited. Some
countries and regions of the world are
today facing a shortage of fresh water that
is growing more acute because of popula¬
tion growth and the development of
industry and agriculture. The situation is
aggravated by the reckless and often rapa¬
cious attitude of those who take water for
granted as a free gift of Nature. This leads
to the impoverishment of supplies and to a
rapid deterioration in quality, which in turn
causes irreparable damage to animal and
plant life, upsetting the ecological balance
of the biosphere.
How much water does man need? No
branch of industry in the modern world can
develop without water. Ten cubic metres
öf water are needed to produce one tonne
of fuel oil and 5,600 m3 to manufacture a
tonne of synthetic fibre! A thermal power
station with a capacity of one million kilo¬
watts "drinks" between 1.2 and 1.6 billion
cubic metres of water every year.
But the main factor in increasing demand
is the population explosion. Since 1900,
the world's population has more than dou¬
bled, rising from 1,670 million to over 4
billion:
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Friend
and foe
These scenes from
different parts of the
world show the diversity
of man's complex and
often dangerous
relationship with water.
Left, raising water by
leverage and muscle-
power from a well near
Lake Chad in Africa.
Right, in northern Alaska
an Eskimo has pierced a
hole in the ice in order
to fish in the frozen
waters of River Meade.
Below, In Kampuchea
(formerly Cambodia) a
farmer and his water
buffalo cross a flooded
river. In southeast Asia
each year thousands of
lives are lost in floods,
which also destroy
over 5 million hectares
of crops.
Demographers predict that by the year
2015 it will reach 7 or 8 billion.
However, the calculation of future water
needs must take into account not only
population growth, but also improved
living standards, which directly depend on
increased water consumption.
While the world population has more
than doubled since 1900, the total annual
consumption of water has increased seven¬
fold, from 400 km3 to 2,800 km3. Moreover,
during the same period per capita con¬
sumption approximately trebled, largely
because of the demands of an increasingly
urban population.
In 1900, average annual water consump¬
tion totalled 240 m3 per person. By the year
2015, according to our calculations, this
figure will have risen to 1,130 m3 per year.
There has been a virtually unbridled
increase in the amount of water used by
industry, from 30 km3 per year at the begin¬
ning of the century to 630 km3 per year in
1975 more than a twentyfold increase.
During the same period, the consumption
of water for agriculture rose sixfold, from
350 km3 to 2,100 km3 annually.
By the year 2015, according to our calcu¬
lations, industry will be using 2,750 km3 of
water per year; agriculture 4,700 km3 and
domestic consumption will have risen to
650 km3. By the same date, the world as a
whole will be consuming 8,500 km3 per
year.
This projected consumption figure repre¬
sents 19 per cent of the annual runoff
figure mentioned above (45,000 km3) which
constitutes the replenishment of our water
supplies.
At first sight, one might be tempted to
draw an optimistic conclusion: by 2015
demand will be less than one-fifth of fresh¬
water resources. In reality, however,
demand should not be compared with the
total runoff, but with that portion of the
flow which can actually be exploited.
Since river flow varies considerably from
year to year (and even during the course of
a single year), unless some form of control
is applied, we can only use that part of the
flow which remains constant, that is,
approximately 25 per cent. If more big
reservoirs are built, this figure could be
increased, at the outside, to 50 per cent.
Furthermore, annual river flow is ex¬
tremely unevenly distributed. The Earth is
roughly divided into two parts: one where
there is excess moisture but not enough
heat, and another where there is more than
enough heat but where moisture is in short
supply. The latter part includes 33 per cent
of the territory of Europe, 60 per cent of
Asia, almost the whole of Australia, most
of Africa, the western part of North Ame¬
rica and 30 per cent of South America.
If we consider the per capita supply of |
fresh water, we find that Europe (with I
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
, almost 20 per cent of the world's popula¬
tion and only 7 per cent of its fresh-water
resources) is in the worst position. Asia,
with 60 per cent of the world's population,
has barely 31 per cent of reserves.
In all the populated regions of our planet,
the annually renewable fresh-water resour¬
ces which could really be exploited amount
to some 12,500 km3. This is not much
more than the projected figure for con¬
sumption in the year 2015.
But the water problem is further compli¬
cated by the progressive deterioration in
the quality of fresh-water resources. The
amount of used water discharged through¬
out the world into sewers and reservoirs is
already enormousapproximately 700 km3
per year. By 2015, the annual discharge of
effluent, including runoff water from irriga¬
tion, will exceed 2,000 km3.
Even when purified by modern tech¬
niques, used water must be diluted in at
least ten times its original volume of pure
water to be fit for further use, though the
effluent from some- chemical -industries
may require as much as 100 or even 200
times the original volume. By the year
2015, some 20,000 km3 of pure water will
be required for this purpose, that is,
approximately twice the amount of the
available fresh-water resources of the
populated regions of our planet.
This leads inescapably to the conclusion
that by the year 2015, water resources will
be close to exhaustion in the populated
regions of the globe. In certain regions and
river basins, they will be exhausted by the
end of this century.
The only way to alleviate the water prob¬
lem and stave off the impending "water
famine", is to devise a comprehensive and
overall approach to the exploitation of
resources. With scientific planning, mea¬
sures can be developed and implemented
at the national, regional and global levels
alike to prevent the pollution and exhaus¬
tion of water supplies.
One way of replenishing resources in the
world's populated regions would be to use
water from less densely populated areas in
that part of the globe where there is an
abundance of moisture. Here lie some 50
per cent of the world's fresh water resour¬
ces, which up to now have been left out of
our calculations concerning the situation in
the year 2015.
The exploitation of these resources by
redistributing river flow to areas which lack
water will pose enormous engineering
problems. But, despite the complexity of
the task and the huge expenditure
involved, an approach of this type offers
one of the most realistic solutions to the
water problem in a number of countries.
The North American Water and Power
Alliance has proposed a gigantic project to
divert up to 196 km3 of water from the
Yukon, Fraser, Peace and Athabaska
rivers, and part of the Columbia River to
the dry plains of Canada and the United
States. (See article page 23.) In South
America, there are plans to divert the flow
of two of the world's greatest rivers, the
Amazon and the Plate.
In Africa, specialists are examining the
problem of transferring a considerable part
of the water of the Congo towards Lake
Chad, in order to irrigate neighbouring
parts of the Sahara. In the Soviet Union,
the question of diverting part of the Ob and
the northern rivers of European Russia
towards the south, to the arid regions east
of the Volga, to Central Asia and to
Kazakhstan, is under consideration. Stu¬
dies of a similar nature are being made in
Australia, Pakistan and other countries.
Some scientists have voiced fears that
interference with Nature on such an unpre¬
cedented scale may lead to unforeseen and
unpleasant consequences and even to
changes in the rotation of the Earth and in
the climate of our planet. Soviet studies
have shown that such fears are groundless.
The amount of water involved in these pro¬
jected transfers is only a very small propor¬
tion of the total amount of water circulating
in the hydrological cycle (approximately
12,900 km3).
Aware that this problem was becoming
acute in many countries, Unesco's General
Conference at its 13th session in 1964,
adopted a global programme of internation¬
al scientific co-operation the Internation¬
al Hydrological Decade. This piogramme
included more than 60 projects, involving
scientists from 108 countries, as well as a
number of governmental and non¬
governmental organizations.
The experience gained by participants in
the International Hydrological Decade has
been discussed at many scientific confe¬
rences, symposia and seminars, and pub¬
lished in international handbooks and other
documents. But although the achieve¬
ments of the International Hydrological
Decade were far from negligible, many
problems still remained to be solved, and
some of them have as yet barely been
touched upon.
Consequently, in 1975, immediately after
the conclusion of the International Hydro-
logical Decade, a new, far-reaching and
long-term programme of international col¬
laboration was launched under the aegis of
The
United Nations
Water
Conference
THE United Nations Water Conference, held at Mar del Plata (Argentina) from 14
to 25 March 1977, was attended by 1,500 participants from 116 countries. Its aim
was to find ways and means of satisfying the world's need for water. The dele¬
gates faced a daunting task: some $100 billion must be invested by 1990*to provide the
world's urban and rural areas with adequate water supplies, while a further $100 billion
of investment will be needed by T990 for irrigation.
The Conference endorsed a Plan of Action comprising a series of important recom¬
mendations and resolutions. These cover the major problem areas, including: the
assessment of water resources, notably drinking water; the rational use of water in
agriculture; the control of waste and pollution; fisheries; hydroelectric power; inland
navigation; natural hazards (flood and drought management); public information, edu¬
cation, training and research; international co-operation (including financing for water
development); and technical co-operation among developing countries.
Specialized bodies of the U.N. system Unesco, the Food and Agriculture Organi¬
zation (FAO), the World Health Organization (WHO), the U.N. Children's Fund (UNI¬
CEF), the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) and the U.N. Development Pro¬
gramme contributing to a concerted effort to devise programmes for the develop¬
ment and management of world water resources.
The Conference recommended that 1980-1990 should be proclaimed "International
Drinking Water Supply and Sanitation Decade" by the U.N. and devoted to the deve¬
lopment and implementation of national water supply plans tailored to the social, eco¬
nomic and sanitary needs of each country.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The world's
arid lands
Unesco has recently published a new map of the world distribution of arid regions, taking
into account the latest advances in knowledge of climates, soils and vegetation. Above,
simplified version of the map. It shows how vast areas of the continents are affected
by water shortages. Even "subhumid" regions experience water supply problems.
The great thirst
This graduated glass shows
average world per capita water
consumption (in millions of litres
per year) since 1900, as well as a
forecast up to the year 2015.
Industrial and agricultural needs
are Included. The population
explosion is accelerating growth
in demand for water. World
population, 1.6 billion at the turn
of the century. Is now more than
4 billion and Is expected to reach
nearly 7 billion by the year 2000.
Unesco and with the active participation of
many countries and international organiza¬
tions.
This programme, known as the Interna¬
tional Hydrological Programme (IHP), pro¬
vides for the exchange of experience con¬
cerning the collection, processing and
analysis of hydrological data; the develop¬
ment of physical and mathematical models
of natural and artificially induced hydrologi¬
cal phenomena; the improvement of
methods of calculation and data-feeding
for automated water management
systems; the use of the latest techniques
and equipment for the study of water
resources (satellites, remote-sensing,
etc.); and collaboration in the training of
scientific and technical personnel.
Scientists from all over the world are
today co-operating in Unesco's Internatio¬
nal Hydrological. Programme, with the
active participation of the World Meteoro¬
logical Organization (WMO), the Interna¬
tional Association of Hydrological Sciences
(IAHS), the Food and Agriculture Organiza¬
tion (FAO) and other international, govern¬
mental and non-governmental organiza¬
tions. This increasingly close international
collaboration is essential if the Earth's
water problem is to be solved.
Valentin I. Korzun
Aleksei A. Sokolov
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Modern cities:
an unquenchable
thirst?
Photo Gilles Peress © Magnum, Paris
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Deep wells
and dead fish
Hard pressed to keep pace
with soaring domestic and
industrial demand for water,
modern cities must make
massive investments to bring
supplies from long distances
and drill wells deep
underground (above). Drawing
shows the geological structure
of the Paris basin with pipe
descending to a water-bearing
bed some 600 metres down.
Measures have been taken to
prevent excessive "mining" of
these reserves. Water
pollution is another major
problem facing modern cities.
Left, dead fish float in the
Seine amid reflections
of Paris buildings.
ALTHOUGH half the world's popula¬
tion will be living in cities by the
end of this century, many questions
still remain unanswered about the impact
of urban growth and industrialization on
the world's water resources.
This was one of the findings of a work¬
ing group set up by Unesco and the Food
and Agriculture Organization of the United
Nations (FAO) in 1971.
Four years later, in 1975, the Inter¬
governmental Council of Unesco's Interna¬
tional Hydrological Programme approved
five projects designed to provide. a better
understanding of the problems of urban
hydrology. They involved research into
water catchment areas, groundwater
pollution, and the interaction of economic,
social and ecological factors on urban
hydrology.
This research, carried out under Unesco's
auspices and within the framework of co¬
operation with other United Nations spe¬
cialized agencies, will make it possible in
1979 and 1980 to draw up an international
programme for the management of urban
water resources.
Any modern city has to face three main
water problems: the supply of water for
drinking and other purposes (chiefly
industrial); the removal of sewage; and
the renewal of supplies.
Cities need to be supplied first and fore¬
most with drinking water for domestic
consumption. Estimated daily needs vary
greatly, from 50 to over 400 litres per
inhabitant. It has been calculated that a
Swede uses on average 210 litres of water
per day for personal hygiene and house¬
hold appliances. These domestic require¬
ments of course account for only part of
total needs. Even so, the amount of water
used by a big town may seem small com¬
pared with the flow of even a small river.
But in addition to safe water needed for
domestic consumption, cities also have to
satisfy many other demands, particularly
those of industry. The supply of water to
industry (quite apart from piping off of
untreated water from rivers) represents a
high proportion of total consumption.
Cities are greedy for water. The total
urban needs of the United States in 1965
were estimated at 1,000 cubic metres per
second. The figure will probably rise to
1,500 cubic metres per second by 1980,
and to over 3,000 cubic metres per second
by the year 2020. Such amounts are the
equivalent of the flow of major rivers.
Some towns and cities bring their water
from long distances. A 300-km.-long
pipeline provides Stuttgart and its suburbs
with drinking water. In Sweden, the
needs of the Malmö-Lund-Helsingborg
conurbation could only be met by some
300 km. of pipelines. The California State
Water Project, set up to supply the state's |
cities and agriculture, includes an aqueduct I
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Photo Sumí Janah, Unesco
1,100 km. long, with a flow of 167 cubic
metres per second.
Another frequently used method of
urban water supply is to tap groundwater.
This can sometimes cause changes in the
natural water balance. For quite apart
from cases where the water has to be
treated because of its high mineral content,
the amount of water drawn off can exceed
the natural supply. The level of the water
table drops, and this in turn can cause
land subsidence, as has already happened
in certain parts of the United States,
Japan and Sweden.
Forty-seven per cent of the water used
by Swedish cities is supplied by ground¬
water. Its removal, combined with the
weight of buildings, has caused subsidence
particularly in Stockholm, where some
structures have suffered serious damage.
In other cities the ground has sunk by
between 50 centimetres and one metre.
Sewage and rainwater also have to be
removed from cities. The total length of
sanitary sewers and storm-sewers in the
United States is over 300,000 kilometres.
The figure for Sweden, a country whose
population is 25 times less than that of the
United States was 35,000 km. in 1971. The
combined lengths of the Nile, the Amazon
and the Mississippi-Missouri, the world's
three longest rivers, amount to less than
20,000 kilometres. The geography of the
world's water has completely changed.
Cities thus modify the way water circu¬
lates. Nearly 7,000 km. of artificial chan¬
nels run under New York City's 329 square
kilometres. The city of Milwaukee, on
Lake Michigan, has a mere 60 km. of
natural watercourses and 13 km. of water¬
front, but 900 km. of sewers, 1,300 km.
of storm sewers, and 1,000 km. of sanitary
sewers.
Natural water networks are also affected
by urbanization. Watercourses are cover¬
ed over, integrated into artificial systems,
and often turned into sewers. A rural area
of 68 square kilometres near Washington
contained 103 km. of watercourses in 1913.
By 1966, it had turned into suburbia and
was left with only 43 km. of "natural"
open streams.
Urbanization also changes the pattern
of rainwater runoff. In cities the volume
of water seeping into the ground dimin¬
ishes, whereas there is an increase in the
amount which drains away in streams and
rivers.
The reason is that in towns and cities
rain does not fall on natural terrain, but on
large expanses of concrete and asphalt, a
type of impermeable surface that is also
becoming increasingly common in the
suburbs.
As a result, the sponge that once soaked
up part of the water is no longer there. It
has been observed in many countries that
all the rainwater in urban areas now finds
its way directly into the drainage system,
and then flows by the shortest possible
route into the nearest river. The flow in
such rivers thus rises steeply, which was
not the case before urbanization. In one
German valley, which has undergone
urban development during the last 30
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Industrial development generally goes hand in hand with urban growth and also makes
heavy demands on water resources. The pollution of streams and lakes with industrial
waste is no longer a problem confined to the developed world. Opposite page, Tata iron
and steel works (India) seen from across its cooling basin forms a stark contrast with
pastoral lakeside idyll (above) as a Bengali fishes in untroubled waters.
Photo © Guy Van de Berg, Brussels
years, certain types of rainfall cause the
river to rise not only faster but twice as
high as in 1919.
Research in the United States has
shown that flooding is tending to become
more frequent and more serious in urban
areas, which are often located near rivers.
The degree of flooding increases in pro¬
portion with the extent of urbanization.
Not long ago, there was dangerous flood¬
ing near Marseilles, in France, ¡n an area
where there has been extensive building
over the last 15 years. Concrete was
identified ' as the main culprit of this
disaster.
It is becoming vital, then, to control the
flow of rivers by building dikes and reser¬
voirs in order to take the "punch" out of
floods. The natural regulatory mechanisms
which have been removed must be replac- -
ed by artificial control.
As well as altering the runoff pattern, _
cities have also affected the quality of"
water in a variety of ways:
A city like Philadelphia, in the United
States, produces 2,900 tonnes of pol¬
lutants every day. Each year its two
million inhabitants, spread over 330 square
kilometres, dump more than 1,500,000
tonnes of refuse, as well as industrial
waste. To this should be added the waste
produced by the asphalting of streets (30
to 40 km. per year), the wear and tear
caused by four million' pairs of shoes and
of more than two million car tyres, the
erosion of the city's 650,000 buildings and
the pollution of the pavements by some
250,000 domestic pets.
Similar figures could probably be pro¬
duced for all major cities. Naturally most
such deposits are removed via the drain¬
age and sewerage system, especially when
it rains. Flooding in such areas can cause
particularly serious damage, .as the first
surge'of water., is, always .extremely, pol¬
luted. The average amount of sediment
carried by a river is much greater as it
leaves ah urban area at least 5 to 10
times more than' in rural areas. According
to a survey carried out in the U.S.S.R. 20
to 30 tonnes of matter is dissolved and
deposited annually by rainfall on each
square kilometre of urban areas, as
opposed to a mere 5 to 10 tonnes in rural
areas.
In the U.K., sewage was examined to
see how much waste from building sites it
contained: one of Birmingham's main '
sewers was found to have a deposit of
building debris up to 50 cms. deep. In
Stockholm, 850,000 cubic metres of snow
are removed annually from the streets and
dumped in Lake Malaren. According to
estimates, they contain 30,000 kilos of
lead, 6,000 kilos of oil, and 130,000 kilos
of salt.
Pollution on this scale has introduced a
' new stage in the water cycle: purification.
All major cities 'now have one or ' more
plants/where "used" water is: generally
. put in sedimentation basins before being
y treated biologically (the actual purification l
( being ' carried out by bacteria). After a F
t13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
To combat pollution In streams
and rivers, purification plants
have been built near major
cities. The water is put
through a complex process of
sedimentation, filtration, and
chemical and bacteriological
treatment. The Kuryanovo
plant, left, near Moscow,
treats 2,500,000 cubic metres of
water per day, making the
Moskva river clean enough for
the people of the Soviet capital
to swim In it in summer.
second sedimentation, it is returned to the
river.
As water needs. are increasing all the
time, it is often necessary to turn river
water into . drinking water. But water
: often needs to be purified on its way into
cities as well as on the way out, for there
are usually other towns or industrial plants
further upstream. Thus, a plant in the
eastern suburbs of Paris takes 600,000
cubic metres of water a day from the
river Marne (a tributary of the Seine) and
purifies it for drinking purposes. . It is a
highly sophisticated process: the river
water attains a state of absolute microbio¬
logical purity only after a quick filtration,
treatment with chlorine dioxide, then with
ferric chloride, then a slow, filtration, an
adjustment of acidity with common soda
and lastly an ozone treatment. It is not a
simple process to get pure water. .
So-called "natural" watercourses are
today becoming less and less natural.
This is not necessarily bad, since changes
in streams and rivers can be the result of a
deliberate policy to conserve or improve
their condition. The waters' of the River
Ruhr, which flows through one of the
most built-up and industrialized areas in
the world, have remained' very pure,
thanks to efforts by the German authorities
to maintain the river for local consumption
and recreation purposes.
: To prevent the Ruhr. from being pol¬
luted, sewage, and waste is , channelled
into another another . tributary : of the
Rhine, the Emscher, which flows a little
further north... and passes through a
purification plant.
In the Ruhr area each river performs its
own special task. A similar solution 'is
being envisaged for northern France. In
the Netherlands, there are plans to specia¬
lize the branches of the Rhine delta. Arti¬
ficial, man-made solutions are becoming
more and more widespread. > rSoon,
perhaps, the maps of : river systems ' in
school geography books will have. to be
redrawn.
Most of the ¡nfoimation in this article is drawn from
."Hydrological Effects of' Urbanization",- a " study
published by Unesco in 1974.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
by Michel Bâtisse
The
strange ways
of H2O
WATER is the universal symbol of
purity and simplicity. Yet noth¬
ing is in fact more rare than
pure water and nothing is less simple than
this strange substance with its surprising
physical, chemical and biological properties.
The Greek philosopher Thaïes of Miletus
looked upon water as the principle of all
things. Later, Empedocles of Ag'rigen-
tumfollowed by Plato and Aristotle-
classed water as one of the four elements,
along with earth, air and fire, of which all
matter was composed.
. From then on, until the end of the 18th
century, no one questioned the notion
that water was a single element. In 1775,
a French chemist, Pierre-Joseph Macquer,
collected a few drops of water following
the combustion of some hydrogen. Yet
so tenacious were the ideas of Plato and
Aristotle that, three years later, he wrote
MICHEL BATISSE, French engineer and phy¬
sicist, is Unesco's Assistant Director-General
for Natural Resources and Environmental
Sciences.
Above, model of a water
molecule. The large black sphere
is an atom of oxygen. It is
surrounded by electrons (shown
as white balls) and linked to two
hydrogen atoms, as though it had
two ears. This combination
gives water its well-known
chemical formula H20.
Hydrogen is the most abundant
element in the galaxy. Left,
photographed from space, the
Earth and the hydrogen "blanket"
around it take on the appearance
of a multi-toned crescent.
(Contrasts were heightened in the
photo lab.)
that water appeared to be an "unalterable
and indestructible substance" which could
not be broken down.
Suddenly, however, these old ideas
were overturned in a flurry of chemical
experiments. In England, Henry Cavendish,
in the course of his studies on gases, was
the first to show, in 1781, that water was
formed by the combination of hydrogen,
which he called "inflammable air", with
atmospheric oxygen, which he called "vital
air".
As is often the case at the great turning
points of scientific advance, the researchers
of the day stumbled forward like sleep¬
walkers, to use Arthur Koestler's ¡mage,
and were hard put to it to distinguish what
their experiments indicated, all the more
so in that they were tackling several pro¬
blems at the same time. And as is w
again often the case, discovery was in the f
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
, air and many researchers, both in England
and in France, had inklings of the truth.
Great scientists such as Gaspard Monge,
Joseph Priestley and James Watt all
contributed to the discovery of the com¬
position of water. But credit for under¬
standing and interpreting the nature of
water must go to the famous chemist
Antoine-Laurent de Lavoisier, assisted by
Pierre Laplace, the future astronomer. On
24 June 1783 Lavoisier succeeded in
actually synthesizing water from oxygen
and hydrogen, proving clearly that water
was composed of these two elements;
soon after he succeeded in carrying out
the reverse operation of decomposing
water. He it was, indeed, who gave
them their present names of oxygen and
hydrogen, the latter signifying "producer
of water".
Today everyone knows that the water
molecule results from the combination of
one atom of oxygen with two atoms of "
hydrogen. And this apparently very simple
molecule is the very basis of all life on
Earth.
Yet water does not behave at all like
other liquids; to take one simple example:
in its solid form as ice, it floats.
Normally, liquids contract as they cool;
when they solidify, they contract even
more and for this reason are more dense
in the solid than in the liquid state.
"Normally", therefore, ice should not
float. Water does in fact contract as it
cools down to 4°C, but then it starts to
expand again before solidifying as ice.
In addition to this, the compressibility
of water, which is very slight, diminishes
further at increasing temperatures between
0 and 50°C, quite the reverse of what
happens with other liquids. In the same
way its viscosity decreases as pressure is
brought to bear on it, instead of increasing.
A
ND if we compare water to simi¬
lar combinations, such as hydrogen and
sulphur or hydrogen and selenium, we find
that water should be gas at normal tempe¬
rature, that it should boil at 90° below zero
and become ice at 100°C. Obviously life
on this planet would be impossible if this
were so. We ourselves are two-thirds
composed of water and it is difficult to
imagine a world functioning at around
-90°C.
This is not all. Water has another
"abnormal" property of the greatest
importance it likes to remain in the liquid
state and is very resistant to temperature
change. In fact, it requires the expenditure
of a great deal of energy to transform
water into vapour or into ice. This is what
is meant when we say that its "latent
heat" of freezing or vaporization is very
high. Thus it is the "heat pump effect"
produced by the melting of an ice cube
that cools our drink rather than its actual
temperature.
Similarly it requires a relatively very high
amount of energy to increase or decrease
water temperature: we say that water has
a very high "calorific capacity", and it is
this remarkable propertywhich, of course,
applies to the enormous ocean masses of
our planetwhich saves us from the very
considerable variations in temperature
between day and night and between
summer and winter to which we would
otherwise be subjected. Water is our
great thermic regulator. Everyone knows,
for example, that countries directly border¬
ed by the oceans have much less contrast¬
ed climates than continental countries.
Water has many other curious properties,
such as the ease with which it dissolves
many substances (as a consequence of
which it is rarely pure), its strong tendency
to creep up and wet walls and to rise in
capillary tubes, its propensity for getting
trapped during the formation of rocks in
the form of hydrates which at times take
on highly iridescent colours, as in opal.
What, then, lies behind these unusual
properties? It would appear that they are
due to the special structure of the water
molecule and the way in which it binds
itself to other molecules.
Modern physics no longer admits of the
representation of atoms in drawings.
However, a simple geometric model would
show that an oxygen atom has six
electrons on its outer orbit whereas, for
this orbit to be stable, it should have eight.
Similarly each hydrogen atom has one
electron on its orbit, whereas, to be stable,
it should have two. Thus, (as shown on
page 15) two atoms of hydrogen and
one atom of oxygen place their outer
electrons "in common" to form the stable
water molecule. But this link is not just
formed anyhow; the two hydrogen atoms
place themselves next to each other, giv¬
ing the water molecule a special configura¬
tion, as though it had two "ears".
Two very important facts result from
this. Firstly, the water molecule is
extremely stable, the link between the
oxygen and the hydrogen being due to a
very harmonious sharing of electrons-
known as a covalent bond as a result of
which the molecule is very difficult to
break down. This explains why, for so
long, water was thought to be a simple
substance.
It also explains why it is difficult to
envisage the economic use of the enor-
mous.quantities of hydrogen contained in
the sea as fuel for use, for example, in
motor cars. It is true that hydrogen is
used as a propellant for space rockets,
where its combustion with oxygen consists
in fact in synthetizing water, but the
process of producing the necessary
hydrogen is extremely costly.
Secondly, the water molecule is elec¬
trically dissymetric, the oxygen part being
negatively charged and the hydrogen part
positively charged. Thus it acts like a
small magnet, which explains much of the
anomalous behaviour described above.
The electrical interactions between the
hydrogen of one molecule and the compa¬
ratively "free" electron pairs of another
molecule constitute a link known as a
"hydrogen bond". Through the interplay
of these bonds each molecule of water
tends to link up with four other molecules
and this produces, in ordinary ice, a crystal
structure which is rigid yet not very
dense and in which the water molecules
are arranged geometrically, rather as they
are in snow crystals and for the same
reasons. This not very compact structure
gives ice its lightness. The disorderly
structure of liquid water is, in fact, more
dense and more compact than ice, since
the hydrogen bonds are less systematic
and break up as temperature rises.
I
NVERSELY, the structure of or¬
dinary ice cannot withstand very strong
pressure. This led to the discovery of eight
other kinds of ice produced at pressures
reaching 20,000 kg/cm2 which are, in fact,
of a higher density than water. But these
laboratory-produced forms of ice do not
exist in nature, and it is as well for us they
do not. What would happen if the ice of
the North Pole were to sink and to pile up
gradually at the bottom of the sea? Noth¬
ing very good for us!
Hydrogen bonds seem to be at the root
of other curious properties of water. It is
these bonds that ensure the cohesion
between the molecules of living cells
which are largely composed of water, and
they are responsible for the fact that water
only boils at a relatively high temperature.
The truth is there is still a long way to go
before we know everything about the
complex substance of liquid water and
physicists continue to propose theories
and construct models to explain all its
properties.
Perhaps the greatest paradox of all is
that this liquid, which was thought to be
so simple but which is so non-conformist
in its behaviour, is the one that was select¬
ed as the standard of reference for the
measurement of temperature (by definition
water freezes at zero degree centigrade
and boils at 100°C), of heat (a calorie is
the amount of heat required to raise the
temperature of one gramme of water from
15 to 16°C) and of mass (one gramme
being the mass of one cubic centimetre of
water at a temperature of 4°c). Most
wonderful of all is the fact that the
abnormal properties of this unique,
mysterious liquid have determined the
nature and structure of the physical and
biological world of which we are part.
Michel Bâtisse
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
by Paul-Emile Victor
Will
deserts
drink
icebergs?
IF the earth were the size of a large
orange, all its water, whether suspend¬
ed in the air, subterranean, or visible
in the form of oceans, seas, lakes and
rivers, would amount to no more than a
tiny droplet carefully deposited on its rind
with a pipette.
Almost the whole of the droplet (97 to
PAUL-EMILE VICTOR is a distinguished
explorer who has organized and led numerous
French expeditions to the Arctic and Antarctic
in the last 40 years. He was head of the inter¬
national glaciological expedition to Greenland
from 1967 to 1970, and since 1974 has been
president of the "Groupe Paul-Emile Victor" for
the protection of man and the environment.
His achievements as an explorer and scientist
have brought him international recognition,
including the award of the gold medal of the
Royal Geographical Society, London.
98 per cent) would be made up of salt
water from the world's oceans and seas.
The remaining 2 to 3 per cent would
consist of the fresh water that is vital for
human lifeso little that in comparison
with our orange it would look much
smaller than a pinhead.
Of these fresh-water resources, some 75
per cent is solid, in other words frozen.
Most of the rest is groundwater and soil
moisture, and less than 1 per cent is
actually available for human use in streams,
lakes, swamps and in the ground. It is
this minute quantity that we squander so
recklessly, pollute so unashamedly and
use up at an ever faster rate.
Every attempt, then, has to be made to
find further supplies of fresh water. There
are two viable methods of doing this, and
two only: the desalination of sea water,
and the tapping of the only existing
reserves of fresh water the ice of the
polar regions, formed by the accumulation
and compression of snowfall over many
thousands of years.
The desalination of sea water is expen¬
sive, whereas the production of fresh
water by the transportation of icebergs is
both economically competitive and feasible.
Icebergs are composed of fresh water
so pure that it often approaches the
characteristics of distilled water.
It has been estimated that the Antarctic
icecap loses more than 10,000 billion
cubic metres of ice every year in the form
of icebergs, which eventually melt and
disappear.
This figure is probably an underestima¬
tion: the most gigantic iceberg so far
recorded (and measured) was 350 kilo-
CONTINUED PAGE 21
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Beneath
the Arctic ice
The remarkable underwater photos on this dolible page were taken during
recent Soviet "North Pole" expeditions, when explorers made some 1,500
dives in the Arctic Ocean. Much remains unknown, even today, about the
formation of pack ice, the behaviour of drifting sea-ice and its
characteristics above and below the water-line. Scientists from many
countries are today engaged on research in this field in order to improve
the safety of shipping and to promote the exploitation of natural resources
in polar waters. Photos were taken by V. Grichenko of the Leningrad
Institute of Arctic and Antarctic Scientific Research, head of an Arctic
underwater exploration group. Above, a diver measures the intensity of
sunlight shining through a "ceiling" of drifting pack ice. Right, another
submarine explorer examines the cloudlike forms of submerged ice,
8 metres deep. Below, underwater mountaineering by diver at work
beneath an island of floating ice.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Floating
Antarctic island
Right, one of the largest Icebergs ever
recorded, photographed in January 1977
(after being tracked since 1967) from a
satellite 900 km. above the Earth. The ice
in such a gigantic berg (74 km. long, 40
km. wide and from 230 to 345 metres
thick) could provide enough fresh water to
meet California's needs for centuries.
,-t-|F
J . . . «-
IH i 5*
m-'K*
** - ^
. .. Mac
r - 1 w. ~ »*«
W ^^
1 :'*» * * '' '
1 m\. .1
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Arctic peaks
Above, a U.S. cutter is dwarfed as it
passes between two peaks of a huge
Arctic berg. The peaks are joined
below the water, forming a single
block of ice. Arctic icebergs are
generally less regular in shape than
those of the southern hemisphere.
Salty ice floes
Unlike icebergs, which break off the
end of continental glaciers and are
composed of fresh water, ice floes
are sheets of frozen sea water a few
metres thick. Left, the Soviet
icebreaker Arktika which on 17
August 1977 became the first surface
ship to reach the North Pole.
( metres long, 90 kilometres wide, and
roughly 250 metres thick, in other words
the area of Belgium; it alone contained
8,000 billion cubic metres of ice.
But each year, the source of the icebergs
(the ice cap) recovers the same amount,
and possibly more, through accumulated
snowfall.
How much water would be provided by
an iceberg towed to one of the ports in
the "thirst belt"? Let's take the example
of Saudi Arabia, and an iceberg of a size
frequently encountered: 100 million tonnes,
1,200 to 1,500 metres long, 300 to 400
metres wide. Even though the iceberg
would lose about 20 per cent of its volume
during transport, the amount of water
which could be used would still be
enormous: 80 billion litres.
If the Red Sea port of Jidda, in Saudi
Arabia, were surrounded by a green belt
20 kilometres wide, the area could expect
a rainfall of some two metres per year, as
opposed to the present figure of only a
few centimetres. Within a few years,
Jidda would become the centre of a lush
oasis. But why go to the South Pole to
get icebergs? Why not the North Pole?
There are two reasons for this. First,
most Arctic icebergs are irregularly shaped
and dangerously unstable. Secondly,
Arctic bergs come from mountain glaciers
(from Greenland, for example) which
precludes their ever being large enough.
The "tabular" icebergs from Antarctica,
on the other hand, are often big and
regular in shape.
The snow that accumulates on the
Antarctic plateau turns gradually into ice,
then very slowly flows (or slides) ice is a
fluid towards the edge of the continent.
Sometimes it forms a fairly regular ice
shelf 250 to 300 metres thick, as in the
case of the triangular Ross Ice Shelf,
which is about the size of France. It is
"moored" by two of its sides to the coast
of Antarctica, while its front part, the
shelf, consists of a 50-metre-high cliff,
chunks of which break away to form
tabular bergs of variable sizes.
Another reason against using Arctic
icebergs is that the ocean currents which
move southwards from the Arctic are not
usually favourable, whereas currents
moving northwards from Antarctica tend
to be so. True, powerful tugs will be
needed to shift such gigantic masses of
ice, but without any currents to help them
their progress would be much slower and
more difficult.
The operation would be economically
viable: on delivery to Jidda, Antarctic
water would cost roughly 60 cents per
cubic metre, whereas the cost price of
desalinating sea water from the same area
is 80 cents per cubic metre.
But is such a project really feasible?
An international conference held in
October 1977 at the University of Iowa
(U.S.A.) concluded that the problems
posed were well within the reach of exist¬
ing technology, and that icebergs as a
source of water would cost between 30
and 50 per cent less than the production
of fresh water by desalination.
The idea of towing icebergs is not a
new one. The present renewal of interest
in the technique (as shown by international
meetings held in Paris and Iowa last year)
began in September 1975 when Prince
Muhammad al-Faisal of Saudi Arabia ask¬
ed my opinion on the feasibility of towing
an iceberg to his country. (1)
Our conversation triggered off a wholes
series of research studies, calculations, r
(1) Prince Muhammad al-Faisal is President of Iceberg
Transport International Ltd., one of the sponsors of the
Iowa Conference.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
, and development projects under the super¬
vision of consultant engineer Georges
Mougin.
An international scientific commission
was appointed at the Iowa Conference to
organize the necessary theoretical and
practical research into the subject. It is
made up of ten internationally known
scientists, most of whom are glaciologists.
We need to know more about the
structure of icebergs (snow, névé, and
ice), their internal stresses, and their
crevasses, cracks and other weak points.
A "suitable" iceberg should be large
enough (100 million tonnes) to provide the
required amount of water by the time it
arrives at its destination. It should be
tabular, as regularly shaped as possible,
and, to make towing easier, much longer
than it is wide. The berg should also be
as homogeneous as possible in other
words, it should have the smoothest
possible surface, with no cracks or
crevasses.
Icebergs of this type, always supposing
that no internal or invisible cracks and
stresses are subsequently detected, are
produced in the Pacific sector, in the
Atlantic sector, and in the Indian sector.
Observations of iceberg drift around the
Antarctic continent carried out by the
French Polar Expeditions (in the course of
the 1971-1973 Berg-Eole Operation) show-
Icebergs could be transported by
tugs, but alternative methods
are also being studied, such as
using the difference in
temperature between sea water
and ice to drive a turbine (left).
Less than 2 per cent of the berg
would be lost as "fuel" during
a journey from the Antarctic to
the Pacific coast of the
United States.
Another concept of iceberg self-
propulsion. It involves the use
of electrically-powered
propellers or paddle-wheels
driven by engines mounted on
the berg or on escort ships.
To prevent excessive melting
caused by the sun and warm
tropical seas, it has been
proposed to cover bergs with a
protective wrap during transit.
Drawings by Saisi, Unesco
ed that bergs from ice shelves in these
sectors converge off the Amery Ice Shelf.
They then drift northwards and
disappear. They can be detected with
greater accuracy through analysis of
satellite photographs.
But the most important problem will be
to protect the icebergs against all types of
erosion, such as melting, evaporation,
mechanical erosion by waves, and friction
caused by movement through the sea.
It would, for instance, take eight to nine
months to cover 6,000 nautical miles at
optimum towing speed (about one knot or
roughly two kilometres per hour).
Various solutions to these problems
have been suggested. One of them involves
the protection of the sides by strips
(similar to those of a Venetian blind) made
of a reflective material.
The submerged portion of the sides
would be protected by a similar curtain (or
skirt) made of insulating material, while
the insulation itself would be provided by
a pool of cold fresh water between the
skirt and the sides of the iceberg. The
underneath of the berg would also be
protected by a kind of wrap held against
the bottom by inflatable floats.
Protection against mechanical erosion
could be provided by a belt made of various
materials.
The manufacture and assembling of
such units in Antarctic waters will involve
various problems that are not yet solved.
The actual towing operation should, in
theory, cause no problems at all, as the
largest modern tugs have a tractive force
of 125 tonnes. The tractive force needed
to shift an iceberg of 100 million tonnes is
in the region of 600 to 700 tonnes, so five
or six large tugs could do the job.
Once the iceberg arrived at its destina¬
tion it might have to remain several tens
of kilometres offshore, depending on the
shallowness of the continental shelf.
Melting water would then have to be
pumped by pipeline to the coast. But a
water storage and supply network would
first have to be constructed on land, for in
most of the countries that urgently need
fresh water no such network exists.
Paradoxically enough, the heat of the
sun will not be enough to produce water
in sufficient quantities. The melting
process will have to be speeded up, either
by spraying melt-water over the pool
which will form on top of the berg (to
absorb heat from the atmosphere), or by
a heat transfer with the sea, or again by
the use of external sources of heat.
Throughout this operation, the outer
protective covering of the iceberg would
of course remain in position.
The production of fresh water by the
transportation of icebergs is undoubtedly
one of the most original and exciting
ventures of our time.
It is also one of the most useful: the
most urgent problem soon to face man¬
kind will be how to obtain fresh water. For
a man can survive for 40 to 50 days without
food, but he can die after only four days
without water.
Paul-Emile Victor
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Redrawing
the world's waterscapes
The next generation may see projects
so vast as to compete with Nature'
Canada, the U.S. and Mexico are associated in the North
American Water and Power Alliance (NAWAPA) which would
bring vast quantities of water across the continent from Alaska
to parts of Canada, the U.S. and northern Mexico.
Under a massive water redistribution system now being studied in the
U.S.S.R., north-flowing streams would be diverted to supply arid
regions in the south. Another plan under discussion for the distant
future would create a veritable inland sea in Siberia.
by Jerry Pournelle
JERRY POURNELLE, American science writer
and Journalist, Is the author of more than a
dozen books on scientific subjects.
WATER has always been civiliza¬
tion's most essential resource,
and that has not changed.
Modern industrial nations consume some
2,000 litres per person per day. Agriculture
needs incredible quantities of water4,500
tonnes to produce one tonne of rice, and
nearly 10,000 tonnes of water for each
tonne of cotton fibre harvested.
Drought and flood have been twin
scourges of civilization throughout. history,
and in ancient as well as modern times the
ability to manage water resources was one
of the most important functions of govern¬
ment. Today, in much of the world, floods
and drought are still. vital threats. Often,
too, both occur in the same country in the
same year.
In California, for example, there is
drought. Farmers and city dwellers alike
face severe rationing, with resulting eco¬
nomic losses running into billions of dollars.
And yet a few hundred kilometres to the
north the state of Oregon endures disas¬
trous floods.
Nature has provided man with vast
quantities of water, far more than would
be needed to industrialize the entire world,
but the water is not in places where it is
needed. Most of the water in the Soviet
Union flows northward into the frigid
tundra above the Arctic Circle and thence
to the Arctic Sea. Vast quantities of water
that might be useful in Canada, Mexico i
and the United States are in Alaska, where
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
they are useless. China is often trapped
by alternate years of drought and flood.
For millennia man had no choice but to
settle near a water source, although even
primitive civilizations made some attempt
to manage water resources. Today we
should not have to submit to flood and
drought. We can bring the water where
it is needed.
Already the California Water Project in
the western United States carries water
thousands of kilometres to supply such
cities as Los Angeles, and turns formerly
arid regions into some of the most
productive land in the world. The Soviet
Volga-Don canal system has brought
water into the Caspian Basin, thus
temporarily arresting the drying up of the
world's largest fresh-water sea.
Despite the large investments and
tremendous achievements in hydraulic
projects, there is a great deal more to be
done. The Caspian basin still receives too
little water, and more cannot be diverted
from the Don without severe damage to
the Azov sea. California still suffers from
periodic drought and much potentially
productive cropland in North America
cannot be planted.
A
J ^ LL this can change. The
MWêB. next generation may see
m m water projects so vast as
to dwarf those already built, indeed, so
vast as to compete with those of Nature.
Projects now seriously under study in both
the United States and the Soviet Union
would not only make deserts bloom and
bring industry to uninhabited areas, but
would actually change the climate of vast
regions of the Earth.
Although such projects as the North
American Water and Power Alliance.
(NAWAPA) which would bring nearly 200
billion cubic metres of water from Alaska
into Canada, the lower 48 United States
and Mexico, and the Soviet plans for
diverting north-flowing streams into the
more inhabitable southern regions involve
engineering on a scale much greater than
anything previously attempted, no one
seriously doubts their technical feasibility.
In both the United States and the Soviet
Union projects exist which, though small
compared to what is now proposed, are
large enough to demonstrate that truly
staggering quantities of water can be
transported over long distances. The
studies now under way in both nations are
devoting special attention to economic
feasibility and ecological effects. Can such
.vast projects be carried out with available
resources at costs that are not prohibitive?
And should they be done at all?
Most economic studies indicate1 that
although the initial investments for such
large hydraulic projects are enormous,
running into hundreds of billions of dollars,
the benefits are so great that they can be
considered as good investments.
There remain the environmental effects.
Until a few years ago, the environmental
effects of shifting enormous quantities of
water could not even be guessed at. There
were simply not enough data, and no good
theories. This situation is changing. The
U.S. Viking probe on Mars has transmitted
meteorological data about that planet's
weather and climate. Martian meteorology
is much simpler than that of Earth but the
principles are much the same. Mars is
becoming a laboratory for the study of
simplified weather systems. This makes
possible new theories on how weather
operates.
Meanwhile, satellite data make it possible
to obtain a unified picture of Earth's
weather and climate. Scientists can
observe the effects of slight warming of
the seas, shifts in the jet streams, and all
the other myriad factors that generate
weather.
Finally, a wide variety of studies, from
examination of tree rings to cores taken
from the ocean floor, have provided new
data on the climate of the past. From
this scientists are able to assemble a
picture of how the weather machine
operated under vastly different conditions,
such as in Ice Ages.
But even without these studies it is
clear that our present climate and weather
are not "natural" in the sense that they
have always been as they are. During
historical times there have been major
changes in climate. Greenland was once
inhabited, and Iceland thrived as recently
as 1200 A.D. There was plentiful rainfall
in areas that are now desert, and once-
dry regions bloom today.
Yet these changes, which can be found
in history books, are trivial compared with
the alterations Nature can make in the
Earth's weather patterns. At one time
much of North America and Europe was
covered with vast sheets of glacial ice.
The seas were hundreds of feet lower than
at present. Nothing man will or indeed
can do compares to the wild shifts in
climate this planet has already endured
not once, but dozens of times.
Then, too, hydraulic projects are not like
Nature's, for they can be controlled,
monitored, even reversed. When, through
changes in the Earth's orbit and tilt, Nature
begins to change the climate, it all happens
at random, uncontrolled and uncontrolla¬
ble. But pumping stations and dams are
very much under control; they can be
used not only to halt undesirable man-
made trends, but even to reverse Nature if
need be.
There will always be those who find the
whole prospect frightening, and their
arguments have merit. At bottom the
desirability of enormous hydraulic projects
becomes not so much a matter of opinion
as a matter of emotional bias. Certainly
projects such as NAWAPA and the Soviet
Pechora project or - the even more
ambitious Soviet plan to construct what
amounts to a new inland sea in the Yenisey
Basin can potentially wreak havoc on
weather and climate patterns. By the
same token, though, the ability to transfer
large amounts of water implies the ability
to control the effects of such a transfer.
Is control better than none at all?
Control implies the possibility of error; but
lack of control relies on luck. Those who
are frightened by the new hydrology
projects have, knowingly or subconsciously,
assumed that nature will continue to act
kindly, and that we will not need the
control over Nature implicit in the big
water projects.
The historical evidence runs counter to
that assumption. We in the 20th century
live in what may be the most favourable
climatic conditions that have ever prevailed.
Nearly all studies of long-term climate
changes indicate that we are due for a
change and that it will be for the worse.
The- warming trend that has prevailed
since the end of the "Little Ice Age",
which drove the Viking settlers out of
Greenland and greatly reduced the
habitability of Iceland, may well be coming
to an end.
During the American Revolutionary War,
cannon were carried across the ice in New
York harbour. There has not been such
a hard freeze in this century. Even the
"Great Freeze" of 1976 was mild compar:
ed to normal conditions in 1776. Now,
however, the trend seems to be moving
downward. The average number of days
in which crops may be grown in the
northern ' hemisphere has measurably
decreased since the turn of the century.
Hydrology may be able to reverse this
trend. For example, the Soviet Yenisey
Basin plan would provide climate stability
in much of Siberia. Parts of that inhospita¬
ble region would become enormously
productive farmlands.
THbHb would oe another
trend, though, and one
not clearly understood.
Warmer climates close to the Arctic might
affect the northern ice cap. The precise
effect is simply not predictable at this time.
There could be either an increase or a
decrease in the amount of snowfall in the
Arctic, and thus the icecap might either
grow or shrink.
Given this ambiguity, a natural reaction
is to say "Best leave things alone. Why
take chances? If the icecap grows it could
turn much present arable land into desert;
if it shrinks, the resulting rise in sea level
would drown coastal cities. The concept
is far too dangerous, and surely no one
seriously intends to do that!"'
And yet, without such projects, there is
no control at all.
24
CONTINUED PAGE 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Where do our water supplies come from?
How are they replenished? It was only
after centuries of observation and
speculation that science discovered how
water circulates in Nature. Left, drinking
fountain in a Paris street.
HYDROLOGY
A science 5,000 years
in the making
by Raymond L. Nace
IT was only some 300 years ago that
man began to understand how Nature's
system of circulating water through
the oceans, the atmosphere and land
really works. And it took a further century
before the concept of this water cycle, in
which the world ocean is both the source
of all water and its final destination, was
fully and clearly stated.
However, archaeological evidence indi¬
cates that man has had a working know¬
ledge of some aspects of hydrology for
thousands of years.
RAYMOND L. NACE is senior research hydro-
logist with the Water Resources Division of the
United States Geological Survey. He is a
former chairman of the U. S. National Committee
for the International Hydrological Decade.
The earliest civilizations arose in arid and
semi-arid regions, seemingly almost simul¬
taneously in several parts of the world.
Men who lived in dry areas had to under¬
stand and manage water in order to go
beyond mere nomadic survival and achieve
stability and security.
As early as 5000 B.C. irrigation was
practised in a few areas in southwest
Asia. Cities surrounded by irrigated fields
evolved around 4000 B.C., and this involv¬
ed extensive irrigation in the plains of
Mesopotamia. Basin-type irrigation with
flood waters in the Nile Valley began at
about the same time.
The Egyptians were an intensely practi¬
cal people and they began recording
annual flood heights before 3000 B.C.,
furnishing us with the oldest known hydro-
logical measurements. They had no
apparent scientific interest 'in floods, but
flood height was indicative of the amount
of land that would be flooded and could
be used as a basis for crop taxation.
Systematic irrigation with groundwater
began much later than that with surface-
water. A groundwater control device
known as a khanat was in use as early as
the 7th century B.C. In simple terms a
khanat is a tunnel whose head taps a
water table.
Water reaches the surface at the mouth,
from where it can be diverted for village
water supply or irrigation. It was the most
efficient method of groundwater use until
the invention of the modern drilled well
and power-driven pumps. Khanats were t
constructed in Armenia, Persia, Afghanistan, f
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Nature's water cycle
The Earth's water circulates continuously from the oceans to the air, to
the land and back to the oceans again. Through evaporation (and
transpiration from plants) water rises as vapour and falls back to Earth
as rain, snow, etc. Most of it drops directly Into the ocean, the rest on
land. According to some estimates, an average 106,000 km3 of this
precipitation falls on the world's land masses each year (and almost 4
times more on the oceans): 68 per cent of it evaporates; 31 per cent
reaches the oceans via streams and rivers, and 1 per cent via
underground flow.
North Africa and China, and many are still
in use.
In Asia proper, in areas of rainfall agri¬
culture, the idea of measuring rainfall as a
basis for crop taxation arose early.
Measurements for such purposes began in
India as early as the latter part of the 4th
century B.C. This has generally been
called the birth-time of rain-gauging.
However, meteorological observations
were recorded in China as early as about
1200 B.C., rain gauges were used -as early
as 1000 B.C., and systematic rain-gauging
was well established by about 200 B.C. A
dynamic concept of the water cycle arose
as early as 900 B.C. China at that time,
however, had no influence on Western
thought.
Science in the West received a great
impetus from the Greeks during the
Hellenic period. Aristotle formulated a
number of ideas about hydrology, but they
were almost completely erroneous. He
thought that most of the water in rivers
originated in great, cold undergound
caverns where it was transformed from air.
His belief that rain could account for only
a small part of stream flow held sway for
2,000 years and was the intellectual road¬
block that prevented recognition of the
dynamic water cycle almost until modern
times.
Despite their consummate skill as
hydraulic engineers, the Romans had little
or no notion of a cycle or the relation
between precipitation and water supply.
One Roman, however, Marcus Vitruvius
Pollio, did have a non-Aristotelian concept.
He wrote that water which evaporates
from the sea and other water bodies forms
clouds; rain from clouds penetrates the
ground and emerges as springs.
The rapid intellectual decline that began
in the 4th century A.D. was followed by
the Dark Ages, during which all science
was at a virtual standstill in Europe for a
1,000 years.
The awakening of Western science from
its long submission to ecclesiastical and
Aristotelian authoritarianism was spurred
strongly in Italy by that universal genius
Leonardo da Vinci (1452-1519). His concern
was largely with hydraulics rather than
hydrology, but in some passages Leonardo
expressed ideas consonant with what are
now known to be the correct principles of
the water cycle.
He recognized the importance of per¬
meable geological formations as aquifers
in the Alps, how groundwater replenish¬
ment occurs, and how lowland springs are
fed with water. Other men developed
these ideas more fully but much later.
In France too a few men were beginning
to think independently. Notable among
these innovators was Bernard Palissy,
who published a small book in 1580 in
which he said for the first time that springs
are fed by rain-water and that alone.
Palissy gave a correct explanation of
artesian wells, of the relations between
groundwater and rivers, and of the general
water cycle. Concerning artesian wells,
he preceded by 200 years Erasmus Darwin,
who has been credited with the first
"proper explanation" in 1785.
The early 17th century marked the
turning point in the history of hydrology
and its related sciences.
The invention of the barometer, the
scaled thermometer and the hygrometer
early in the century made possible some
notable advances in meteorology and
hence in hydrology. The first international
meteorological network was organized
around 1654 by Ferdinand II, Grand Duke
of Tuscany. The groundwork was develop¬
ing that would make possible the birth of
truly scientific hydrology, based on the
cyclic concept.
It was Pierre Perrault (1611-1680), a
French lawyer turned natural philosopher,
who broke fully with the most hallowed
traditions about water. He made the first
serious attempts to measure the factors in
hydrology, and showed that precipitation
in a selected upper part of the Seine river
basin was at least six times more than the
discharge of the upstream tributary of the
Seine. Thus he exploded the ancient
dogma that precipitation is inadequate to
account for the flow of springs and rivers.
He also observed that rivers disappear
into sinkholes in certain limestone areas
and noticed the rise of the water table in
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Drawing © Natural History, NYC
the vicinity of Paris when the level of the
river rose. He correctly inferred from this
that river water was sinking into the
sediments of the Paris flood plain.
Perrault did not discuss the relative
importance of marine and land evaporation
for the replenishment of atmospheric
vapour. It is implicit in his ideas, however,
that some atmospheric moisture is derived
from the sea. Inasmuch as one-sixth of
precipitation runs off to the sea, a return
mechanism is implied, otherwise continental
air masses would soon become perma¬
nently depleted of vapour.
It remained for the English astronomer
Edmund Halley (1656-1742) to close the
atmospheric arc of the water cycle. Halley,
in 1687, was apparently the first person to
estimate evaporation from the sea and
directly to credit this as a source of vapour
for precipitation on land areas.
Halley made some crude experiments
on evaporation at controlled temperature
in his laboratory in England, using a flat
pan of water on a beam scale, a thermo¬
meter and a pan of coals to maintain the
temperature of the water.
Based on evaporation during two hours
from a pan eight inches in diameter, Halley
made a tremendous extrapolation to total
annual evaporation from the Mediterranean
Sea. Astonishingly, in the light of present
knowledge, the result was in the right
order of magnitude.
In another extrapolation based on the
flow of the River Thames, adjusted to
derive an estimate of the flow of rivers
into the Mediterranean, he showed that
daily evaporation from the Mediterranean
is equivalent to about three times the
amount of water discharged into it by
rivers. Halley recognized the processes of
evaporation and transpiration from land
areas, so that not all precipitation runs off
in streams.
Perrault started with water already in
the atmosphere and described its disposi¬
tion after precipitation. Halley identified
the ocean as the main source of atmo¬
spheric vapour and attempted to show a
balance in the complete cycle of water
movement. Their main combined contri¬
bution was the concept of a cycle support- .
ed by crude but convincing measurements.
The proof came nearly a hundred years
later.
The great pioneer French chemist
Antoine-Laurent de Lavoisier (1743-1794)
proved that water is a chemical compound,
which he synthesized by burning hydrogen.
He deduced that water is 85 parts by
weight of oxygen and 15 of hydrogen.
(The actual ratio is 88.9 and 11.1) The
atomic theory in effect had arrived, but it
lay largely fallow until it was taken up by
the Englishman John Dalton.
In a publication in 1793, based on
experiment, Dalton asserted that water
retains its chemical identity when vaporiz¬
ed. He made another pronouncement,
now elementary but profoundly important
at that time: evaporation from land areas
must be less than precipitation, or else no
rivers could flow.
Dalton thus laid the groundwork for
estimates of water balances and he was,
in fact, the first person on record to attempt
to strike a water balance for a sizable
area, namely England and Wales.
In 1845 Sir Robert Kane calculated the
water power available from Irish rivers on
the basis of estimations of runoff obtained
by subtracting evaporation from precipita¬
tion. This implied recognition of the basic
water-balance equation: runoff = precipita¬
tion
Although some surprising empirical
knowledge of groundwater dates back at
least several hundred years B.C., true
understanding of groundwater hydrology
had to await the development of geology
as a definite discipline. This did not occur
until the early 19th century, notably with
the work of William Smith (1769-1839),
the "father of English geology", which set
stratigraphie and structural geology on its
modern path. The geological framework
of an area is the plumbing system of
groundwater, and the water cannot be
understood without a good understanding
of this plumbing system.
Smith used his knowledge of geology
and groundwater to solve the problem of
a water supply for the town of Scarborough,
including construction of a tunnel into an k
artesian aquifer with a regulation system f
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
, so that storage could be increased during
the recharge period and drawn down dur¬
ing the summer.
Smith's hydrological works were
ingenious innovations in his time. His
mapping and stratigraphie work laid the
foundations for the flowering of ground¬
water hydrology during the 19th century.
During the mid-century period, extensive
research on groundwater was carried out,
notably in France.
The Abbé Paramelle (1790-1875), a
French parish priest, was appalled by the
scarcity of water supplies in small villages,
towns and farms in the Jurassic limestone
region of the Causses, near to the Massif
Central.
Knowing that precipitation was adequate
to supply streams and springs, he spent
nine years studying the terrain and lime¬
stone hydrology with resounding success.
He resigned his priesthood in 1831 and
devoted his entire time to locating sites for
wells. In his book on fountains he claimed
to have found 10,000 subterranean sources
of water. Out of hundreds of localities he
chose as sites for wells, his ratio of success
to failure was 12 to 1 . His Art de Découvrir
les Sources, published in 1856, was a
landmark in groundwater hydrology.
Paramelle had no experts to consult and
was almost entirely self-taught.
In the latter part of the 19th century,
however, prominence in the whole field of
hydrology began to shift to the United
States. North American hydrologists
capitalized avidly on the brilliant laboratory
studies that had been carried out in Europe,
and North America became a major world
scene of hydrological studies with special
emphasis on field data and studies. This
permitted the testing, elaboration and
modification of theories and the extensive
development of instruments and methods
for studies at all scales, both small and
large.
In Europe, too, many 19th-century
investigators concentrated on measure¬
ments and compilations of data. One
outstanding accomplishment was that of
the eminent Hungarian hydraulic engineer
Pal Vasarhelyi (1795-1846), who made the
first hydrological survey of the middle
Danube.
This work, accomplished between 1822
and 1840, has been overlooked by most
historians, but it became the basis for all
subsequent control and surveys of the
Danube. Vasarhelyi also prepared plans
in 1846 for control of the River Tisza,
providing for flood control and drainage of
3 million hectares of marshland that had
been an effective barrier to human activity
and movement since prehistoric times.
Ideas about world-wide hydrology have
been advanced for some 2,500 years.
However, the importance of the global
cycle did not receive much serious recogni¬
tion until relatively recent times.
Much credit for this recognition is due
to Russian scientists, beginning in the
second half of the 19th century. During
the period from 1875 to 1911, A. I.Voyeikov
stressed the importance of vapour derived
from the Atlantic Ocean in the precipita¬
tion régime of Russia. He suggested that
evaporation from forested areas furnished
an important component of continental air
vapour. Soviet scientists were also early
to recognize the inseparability of the heat
and water balances of the earth.
The study of the world's water balance
was one feature of the International Hydro-
logical Decade (1965-1974) programme,
which gave great impetus to all the main
branches of hydrology and set up avenues
for the exchange of information throughout
the world.
Today, the International Hydrological
Programme, launched by Unesco in 1975
to help promote a rational policy for the
development and management of water
resources, is providing a continuing
stimulus to the study of world hydrology.
RaymontfL. Nace
Rivers of
blindness
In vast areas of the developing
world, water is the source not
of life but of debilitating and
often fatal diseases, such as
malaria and bilharziasis which
alone claim an estimated 200
million victims each. Right,
Sudanese fishermen at work
in a turbulent river. In
Africa some 20 million persons
are afflicted with "river
blindness" caused by a
parasite which breeds in
fast-flowing water.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
by Gérard Francillon
At Kampung Laut in Sumatra, villagers have dug drainage canals
in the surrounding swamp forest to turn it into productive farmland.
Sumatra's
swampland
pioneers
The "Unesco Courier" presents
here a study of the problems
faced by migrant farmers in
swamp forests of the Upang
Delta in Indonesia. Indonesia
has launched a major research
project in the Upang Delta to
answer a wide range of questions
concerning the environmental and
social aspects of swamp forest
management. The project forms
part of Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere Programme (MAB)
which seeks to develop a basis,
within the natural and social
sciences, for the rational use of
planetary resources and to
improve man's partnership with
the environment.
SERIOUS demographic problems are
facing the government of the Indo¬
nesian Republic in Java and Bali,
two islands which comprise 65 per cent of
Indonesia's population, but represent only
10 per cent of the country's total area.
Though birth control and increased agri¬
cultural yields have produced encouraging
results, these alone will not be enough to
solve the problems of one of the most
densely populated areas in the world.
According to the 1973 census, there were
600 inhabitants per square kilometre in
GERARD FRANCILLON, French social anthro¬
pologist, has carried out a number of research
projects in Indonesia in recent years, notably in
the Padang highlands of Sumatra (for the
University of Nanterre, France). For Unesco
he has studied the effects of mass tourism on
traditional societies and cultures in Bali, and in
1974 took part in the regional meeting of MAB
(Man and the Biosphere) committees held at
Kuala Lumpur (Malaysia).
Java, and the figure is expected to rise to
over 1,000 by the year 2000. It is above all
the cities that will have to absorb the sur¬
plus population.
Transmigration is emerging as the swift-
test and most rational method of easing the
mounting pressure on the central islands.
Outlying areas are not so overcrowded.
Kalimantan (the Indonesian part of Borneo,
the biggest island of the archipelago and
one of the biggest in the world) has only
5.5 million inhabitants, while Sumatra,
Indonesia's second largest island, has
some 20 million people, which works out at
only slightly over 40 inhabitants per square
kilometre.
But while travel is extremely difficult in
most of Kalimantan because, of the many
impassable rapids on its major rivers,
Sumatra still has immense tracts of relati¬
vely accessible forest that is both uninhabi- v
ted and virtually unexploited. f
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
, The two main rivers of southeast Suma¬
tra, the Musi and the Batang (river) Hari,
are wide and deep throughout their lower
courses. The provincial capitals, Palem¬
bang and Djambi, located about 40 to 60
km. inland, are major ports that are readily
accessible to sea-going traffic. Both of
these cities held an important place in the
early history of Sumatra, and Palembang
was capital of the Srivijaya empire which
flourished from the 7th to the 13th century.
On each side of these great waterways and
their vast deltas, only a few metres above
sea level, lies most of Indonesia's 13 million
hectares of swamp forest which offered the
most promising conditions for the govern¬
ment's settlement scheme.
If the migrants were to settle for any
length of time, it was not enough simply to
clear the forest and supply them with seed.
Aware that any development project is
bound to have important ecological reper¬
cussions, the Indonesian government set
up a group of environmental specialists to
meet the planning and management needs
created by the accelerating pace of land
and water resource development. One mil¬
lion hectares of swamp forest is scheduled
to be developed under Indonesia's 1974-
1978 Development Plan.
The Indonesian MAB national
committee, with Unesco's support, was
given the task of preparing and co¬
ordinating research into the natural and
human environment, and of training young
researchers and engineers, both in the
field, at Bogor Agricultural University, and
at Bandung Institute of Technology.
The "field" consists chiefly of the
150,000 hectares of swamp forest in the
delta of the Musi river, whose main bran¬
ches (from west to east) are the Banyuasin,
the Telang, the Musi itself and the Upang.
A workshop for the Upang Delta pilot
project was established in 1974 to serve as
a base for teams of geologists, hydro-
logists, climatologists and botanists.
These were soon followed by experts con¬
cerned with practical aspects of the
scheme (soil scientists, foresters and ocea-
nographers) and then by specialists in com-'
batting various pests and parasites, in rice-
growing, pisciculture and land manage¬
ment. The aim was to broaden the scope
of the project, which was initially intended
above all to turn the Delta into a rice paddy.
The study of the various groups in the
Delta was approached from an ecological
standpoint and entrusted to a team of
researchers from Bogor Agricultural
University. The project was carried out in
liaison with the MAB committee and
Unesco's social sciences sector.
From an ecological point of view, the
project was intended as a large-scale expe¬
riment in swamp forest management, a
kind of gigantic laboratory that could prove
useful to many Southeast Asian countries.
One of the chief aims was to examine as
closely as possible the relations between
different groups of migrants and the extent
to which each group adapted to a new
environment.
It was known that some pioneer
migrants belonging to the Bugi people had
already settled in the Upang Delta without
any government aid, but their exact num¬
bers, system of settlements, farming
methods and real motives for migrating
remained a mystery. The only certainty was
that all along the southeast coast of Suma¬
tra they had preceded the first govern¬
ment-assisted transmigrants, and had suc¬
cessfully cleared and drained the forest,
and farmed without either advice, capital
or machinery.
Brief preliminary investigations sugges¬
ted that these Bugis had emigrated
because of population pressure in their
native peninsula on another Indonesian
island, Sulawesi. It was originally thought
that by clearing the forest and planting rice
paddies they had degraded the environ¬
ment and were forced, as soon as rice
yields began to drop, to plant coconut
groves.
It was supposed that they were biting
further and further into the forest to make
clearings for fresh rice paddies. It was also
generally assumed that once the Bugis had
made their fortune in the Delta they re¬
turned home or at least wanted to do so.
There was also some suspicion, despite
the lack of any firm evidence, that they
were not setting the best example to other
transmigrants.
After thorough investigation, however,
the team of researchers from the Bogor
Agricultural University reached quite diffe¬
rent conclusions. Their findings showed
that the Bugis were not forced to leave
their native island because of overcrowding
or uncertain crop yields, and that it was an
exaggeration to ascribe lower yields in the
Delta solely to intensive rice growing that
had exhausted the soil following the sud¬
den removal of its forest covering.
The team also discovered that the last
pioneers to arrive were frequently more
keen to go home than their predecessors.
Finally, the researchers had to admit that
the reason for the orderly and disciplined
atmosphere in the Bugi settlements was
due not to an innate acceptance of traditio¬
nal hierarchies (which had in fact fallen into
abeyance), but to the almost father-to-son
relationships existing between the more
recent settlers and their predecessors,
especially the most important man among
them, the so-called "canal head". They
also observed that the highest yields ob¬
tained were due to the intensity and regula¬
rity of the farmers' efforts the oldest drai¬
nage systems were the cleanest, and the
first land to be cleared produced the big¬
gest harvests.
But there is another side to the Bugis.
They have left their mark on the history of
the Malay-Indonesian archipelago not only
as settlers but as navigators. In fact a
migrant in the Buginese language is
pasompé, which literally means "he who
sets sail."
It is difficult to say exactly when the i
Bugis' long pioneering tradition first began, I
permanent dwellings
temporary dwellings 1
rice fields
coconut palm groves
30
Patterns of
penetration
Network of drainage canals (left)
in a typical swamp-forest
settlement established by Bugi
people who have migrated to
Sumatra from other Indonesian
islands. A long, straight canal
is linked to a river with smaller
drainage canals branching out on
either side. The canal network
grows as the first settlers are
joined by relatives, each of whom
clears just enough land to provide
enough rice for his family. Note
the three zones of vegetation: the
original swamp forest, coconut
groves, and rice-fields.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
F ..*
#- ~~
The heirs to a long maritime tradition,
many Bugis are accomplished seamen as
well as farmers. In the last few years
they have more than tripled the size
of their fleet of sailing boats, which
they use for inter-island trade. Above,
Bugi sailors dance a bowsprit ballet on
the Batang Han river (Sumatra); below,
a ship's cook sifts rice. Right, all hands
on deck to work the windlass.
[ l l P m. -
'
te
**_ ti
m^mm^. *
y*«*. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Jef Bros, Paris
Although many Bugis are recent migrants to Sumatra, their expertise as farmers is so
admired that some long-established Sumatran villages such as Sungsang (above) have
called on them to transform adjacent swamp forest into rice-fields. Below, a flotilla of
Bugi boats in port at Palembang (Sumatra).
, but according to most historians the likely
date is 1669, when the fortress of Makasar,
in Sulawesi, fell to the Dutch.
This event prompted the Bugis to seek
refuge in estuaries near and far, and to
found a series of sultanates such as Kutei,
Selangor, Johor and Riau, most of which
are still prosperous today. But even before
then the Bugis had already proved them¬
selves to be a sophisticated and powerful
people. In 1638, for instance, the Makasar
Prime Minister was conducting negotia¬
tions in Latin, and in 1640 a prince wishing
to go to war could build 40 junks in less
than 40 days and embark in a galley with
400 oarsmen. In 1655, a sultan command¬
ed a fleet of 1,183 junks.
The wars in Europe and their repercus¬
sions on the Malay Straits tended to slow
down the expansion of the Bugis in the
early 19th century, but their influence really
began to dwindle only at the beginning of
this century.
Then the naval power of the Bugis went
into a long decline until 1970 when they
began to build a new fleet in order to sail
from the ports of Java to Bima in the east,
and Palembang and Djambi in the west. By
the following year, the Bugis had some 800
sailing boats, a.nd by 1976 3,000 or more.
During the same period the length of these
boats went up from 15 to 25 and even 30
metres, and vessels up to 40 metres long
and 12 metres wide were on the stocks in
the Palembang boatyards.
Most of these vessels are magnificent
ketches designed along the lines of 19th-
century brigantines. Some are sloops
which cost less to build and are easy to
handle. This considerable fleet carries tim¬
ber to Jakarta, usually returning empty to
Sumatra. Profits are enough to provide an
average annual wage of almost $550 for
each member of the crew. The income of
the Bugis, whether sailors or farmers, is
much higher than the national average and
is certainly well above the poverty line.
The Bugis in fact bear no resemblance at
all to either of the traditional roles in which
they have been typecast as sea-faring
adventurers, or itinerant farmers, wander¬
ing from one patch of fecklessly burnt
forest to another. On the contrary, as sai¬
lors who have navigated the archipelago
for centuries, they have methodically and
often audaciously seized every opportunity
history has offered to acquire power or
wealth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Similarly, as farmers who have maintain¬
ed a centuries-old pioneering tradition, the
Bugis have always known how to spot the
right kind of opening in the dense forest
bordering the estuaries and coastline that
are so familiar to them.
They explored all the tributaries of the
major rivers down to the smallest inlet in
the coastal swamps. Then they sailed
upstream, and when they reached a likely
settlement site, they would go ashore, test
the soil, assess the depth of the peat layer
and decide which trees should be felled and
which left standing. ,
Then once they were far enough from
the bank or coast to enjoy natural protec¬
tion from intruders, they dug long straight
canals by the side of rivers or coastline
exposed to the northern monsoon.
Branching out on either side of them small¬
er drainage canals would be excavated for
the brothers or cousins who followed in the
footsteps of the first pioneer, the "canal
head"
In time, a regular hydrographie network
came to replace the more erratic pattern of
the original, naturally formed watercourse.
After 10 or 15 years, the ageing canal head
would decide to stop growing rice, with its
laborious cycle of constant thinning and
planting out, and replace it with the coco¬
nut palm, which produces fruit every three
months.
The old man and his original canal would
then be surrounded by the permanent
homes of his fellow pioneers, and together
they would gradually do less and less farm
work, leaving to their younger relatives the
task of clearing the forest as far as their
increasing numbers required. Little by little
the forest yielded to the rice paddies. These
in turn were replaced by coconut groves,
which slowly reconstituted a new forest
covering. This development has now rea¬
ched its final stage on the southwest coasts
of Riau and Johor, on either side of the
Malay Straits.
Many Bugis switch from being sailors to
farmers and back again, and both sailors
and farmers are found in every family, at
least among the Bugis of Boné in southern
Sulawesi. This is one of the main reasons
for the success of the Bugis who have set¬
tled on the southern coast of Sumatra. The
fact that each family and indeed each indi
vidual practises the same two occupations
enables any Bugi to communicate easily
and rapidly with his kinsmen and to partici¬
pate, wherever he may happen to be, in
community life.
The study of the Upang Delta peoples is
a highly original venture and marks' an
important stage in the still youthful science
of human ecology.
Gérard Francillon
Redrawing the world's waterscapes (continued Nom page m
Many climatologists believe we are
already at the beginning of a new Ice Age,
and some seriously believe that the reason
why glaciers have not already begun
their march is that man-made heat has
been added to the atmosphere, not merely
directly by burning fossil fuels, but indirectly,
by adding more carbon dioxide to the
atmosphere (which causes the atmosphere
to retain more of the sun's heat).
Others believe that the smoke particles
man has added to the atmosphere have
reduced the amount of sunlight falling on
the Earth, and have contributed to cooling
the planet. There are even a few who
believe that these two factors have cancel¬
led each other outthe carbon dioxide
causing more heat to be retained, the
smoke particles reflecting more.
But in the midst of this debate comes
more disturbing news. There is now
considerable evidence that the sun does
not always emit the same amount of
heat and light. Studies of sunspots as
reported in historical records indicate long
periods of "quiet" with no sunspots at all,
which would affect the sun's output.
Thus we find that nature has a great
number of ways to alter our climate. It is
only recently that man's efforts have
become sufficiently great to have any real
effect.
And that is where the debate lies now:
should we build the means for transferring
vast quantities of water vast, but still
quite small compared to the amounts of
water locked in glacial ice that flowed
across the continents not too many
thousands of years ago or should we be
content to let nature dictate our climate?
Suppose we go ahead. The earliest
projects would probably be the NAWAPA
plan in North America, and the Soviet plan
to divert much of the Pechora into the
Volga basin.
The Soviet Pechora project would
provide water to irrigate 10 million hectares
of land, to generate 3 billion kilowatt-hours
of electricity, and to save the Caspian
Sea from drying, with consequent increas¬
ed salinity. It would also provide water
for the Azov Sea, restoring that basin to
its natural salinity.
The U.S. NAWAPA Project is even
more ambitious. Affecting three nations,
it would open up deserts for cultivation
and provide sufficient water to flush out
the Great Lakes, restoring the water purity
they once enjoyed before industrialization.
The climatic effects of both projects are
relatively easy to understand. In the
Soviet case, the increased surface areas
of the two major bodies of water, the
Caspian and the Azov Sea, would cause
increased evaporation, and subsequent
rainfall in the regions to their east. Those
regions are drained by the rivers affected
by the water project, so that an equilibrium
would soon be established. To the extent
that there would be climate changes, they
would tend to restore conditions prior to
man's industrialization of the region.
The NAWAPA project similarly tends to
restore lakes and land areas to the condi
tions prior to industry and farming of the
regions. Both the U.S. and Soviet projects
would also provide water for irrigating
lands that, because of extensive farming,
become dustbowls in dry years.
Beyond those benefits there is another
new knowledge. While to some it may be
criminal to experiment with weather and
climate, it cannot be said too often that
nature herself "experiments" and her
experiments are not at all controllable. We
have today enough technology to assess
the changes that we could bring about.
We can monitor the climatic effects of
NAWAPA and the Pechora Project, and
from them learn just what does happen to
weather when we move large quantities
of water.
And that would make possible even
larger projects. The Soviet studies of the
Yenisey Basin have not gone beyond the
early-planning stage, and wisely so. The
creation of an inland sea so close to the
Arctic would have drastic effects on
climate for not only Soviet Asia, but the
rest of the world. Without a better under¬
standing of those effects it would be
folly to invest in such a vast project...
But someday we may need it.
Neither the sun nor the earth remain
unchanged. Through the millennia climate
has varied; and we are due again for a
change, with all indications that it will be
a change for the worse.
Unless we do something about it. And
we can.
Jerry Pournelle
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
tralMaíNDoTj DU OD
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Ethnicity and the Media. An analysis
of media reporting in the U.K., Canada
and Ireland, introduced by James D.
Halloran. 1977, 376 pp. (68 F)
Towards Lifelong Education: anew
role for higher education institutions
by Gareth Williams. 1977. 188 pp. (42 F)
Human Rights Aspects of Popula¬
tion Programmes, with special refe¬
rence to human rights law. 1977.
154 pp. (20 F)
Cultural Policy in Colombia, by
Jorge Eliécer Ruiz with the assistance
of Valentina Marulanda. 1977, 93 pp.
(18 F)
A Manual on Mass Media in Popu¬
lation and Development, by Frances
J. Berrigan. 1977. 105 pp. (18 F)
The Man-Made Landscape, prepared
in co-operation with the International
Federation of Landscape Architects. An
appeal for the preservation of the natural
and man-made environment by famous
landscape architects from different
countries. 1977, 178 pp. (42 F)
Museums for the 1980s. A survey
of world trends, by Kenneth Hudson.
Co-published with The Macmillan Press
Ltd., London, who have exclusive sales
rights in the U.S.A. and the U.K. 1977,
198 pp. (120 F hardbound)
Time and the Philosophies. A col¬
lection of philosophical essays reflecting
the diversity of interpretations of time,
by scholars from a wide variety of
cultures. 1977, 256 pp. (45 F)
OTHER BOOKS
Weapons of Mass Destruction and
the Environment, by Stockholm
International Peace Research Institute
(SIPRI). Taylor and Francis Ltd.,
London 1977, 95 pp. (£5.00)
Strategic Disarmament, Verifica¬
tion and National Security, by Stock¬
holm International Peace Research
Institute. Taylor and Francis Ltd., 1977,
174 pp. (£6.50)
Primates of South Asia: Ecology,
Sociobiology and Behavior, by M.L.
Roonwal and SM. Mohnot. Harvard
University Press, Cambridge, Mass. and
London (U.K.), 1977, 421 pp. (£15.75)
Steady-State Economics: The Eco¬
nomics of Biophysical Equilibrium and
Moral Growth, by Herman E. Daly. W.
H. Freeman and Co. Ltd., San Francisco.
1978, 185 pp. (Hardbound: $12; soft-
bound: $5.50)
Fossil Evidence: The Human Evolu¬
tionary Journey, by Frank E. Poirier.
The C.V. Mosby Cd., Saint Louis,
U.S.A. 1977,342 pp.
India WatchingThe Media Game,
by Amita Malik. Vikas Publishing House
Pvt Ltd., New Delhi. 1977, 174 pp.
(Rs40)
The computer
and the brain
It is unlikely that computers will ever be able to
reproduce human intelligence, according to
Soviet researcher Nikolay M. Amosov, writing
in the latest issue of Unesco's quarterly Impact
of Science on Society, devoted to the brain,
memory and learning. Other subjects discussed
in the issue include sleep, the understanding of
language, and the role of placebos in thera¬
peutics.
(Impact of Science on Society, Vol. 28, No. 1:
9.50 Frs.)
Death certificate
for smallpox in Asia
A commission of medical experts from 9
countries has certified that smallpox has been
eradicated from Asia. The commission signed
the final eradication certificate after studying
the evidence of a 2-year search for cases. Dr.
Halfdan Mahler, the Director-General of the
World Health Organization (WHO) declared
that the results in Asia opened the way to
global abolition of smallpox vaccination by
1980. Such a step would represent a saving of
some $2 billion annuallyto the world community.
Sabah acts
to save turtles
The famous Turtle Islands off the northeast
coast of Sabah (East Malaysia) have become a
national park. All trawling vessels are now
excluded from the reserve, which is of immense
value to conservationists.
Australia's
sun-powered TV
Solar energy will power 13 repeater stations in
Australia's telephone, television and cable
communications system. Each station will
amplify and retransmit telephone, TV and cable
signals to the next station, some 45 km. away.
Australia already has over 40 solar power
systems to supply telephone services in isolated
areas.
Curbing
food losses
The U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization
(FAO) has established a new fund of $10 million
to reduce food losses in the developing
countries. It will finance projects for reducing
post-harvest losses of foods such as grains,
roots and tubers, using storage techniques
easily adaptable to rural areas. The target is to
cut such losses by at least 50 per cent by 1985.
Tree farms
for development
The U.S. Agency for International Development
(AID) has launched studies in the Philippines,
Indonesia and Nepal to help develop "tree
farming", the cultivation of ligneous plants as a
crop which would be harvested regularly 3 or 4
years after planting. As well as providing
fodder and domestic fuel, tree farming is also a
source of jobs, energy for rural industries, and
supplies of wood to paper and other industries.
Ten centuries
of Spanish
On 30 January 1978 a ceremony was held at
Unesco HQ to mark the 1,000th anniversary
of the earliest known text in the Spanish
language (also known as Castilian), today
spoken by some 300 million people. Sr. Rafael
Lapesa, Secretary of the Royal Spanish Acade¬
my, traced the history of the language from the
gloss on a Latin manuscript penned by an
anonymous monk in 977 A.D. to the work of
today's great Spanish and Hispano-American
writers. An exhibition of Spanish books was
opened at the end of the ceremony. (In its
August-September 1977 issue devoted to Latin
America, the "Unesco Courier" published an
article on the history of Spanish by the
Argentinian philologist Marcos A. Morinigo.)
Mediterranean states
against marine pollution
Scientists in 78 labs in 18 Mediterranean states
are working together to monitor pollution in
their sea, estimated to contain about half the
world's floating tar and oil on 1 % of the global
ocean surface. Unesco's Intergovernmental
Océanographie Commission (IOC) is partici¬
pating in this unprecedented example of
Mediterranean co-operation.
History museum
for Saudi Arabia
The importance of Arabia as a bridge between
east and west in Antiquity is revealed in Saudi
Arabia's new Museum of Archaeology and
Ethnography in Riyadh. The exhibits, including
important specimens dating back to 4000 B.C.
unearthed by the Saudi Arabian department of
antiquities in the country's eastern province,
range from Stone Age times to the recent past.
Flashes...
Senegal has promised $7 million to the U.N.
University's endowment fund over a 5-year
period.
UNICEF has granted special aid of $7.2 mil¬
lion to drought victims in Haiti.
777e 7th World Congress on Mental Handicap
will be held in Vienna (Austria) from 1 to 6
October 1978.
' Thailand is preparing a country-wide nature
conservation plan.
World food production rose by only 1.5% in
1977, while world population rose by 2%,
according to the FAO.
By 1980, world production of single cell
protein (SCP) is expected to be over 1 million
tons, roughly equivalent to nearly 1 million
hectares of soybeans.
<£
iu
o
2
-<
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
The latest titles in Unesco's series on
practical aspects
of communication technology
A handy guide to the uses of the
audio-cassette recorder and its
possibilities in formal and non-
formal education.
the development of audio-
cassette technology
operation and production
cassette projects for
development
53 pages, illus.
10 French francs.
Audio
cassettes:
ihr user medium
I
« iU-r..
UT300
rk>lioi):VTRworksnop:
small formal
\ ideó
UTESCO
Already published in the same series
Super 8: the modest medium
92 pp. illus. 10 F
Describes in simple terms the
operation and uses of small
format videotaping, covering
operating details
editing and maintenance
key applications of video to
development tasks
114 pp. illus. 10 F
Film Animation: a simplified approach
92 pp. illus. 10 F
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P 0. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, Campbell House, 100
Flinders St., Melbourne (Victonal, 3000. - AUSTRIA. Dr.
Franz Ham, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung, Industne-
hof Stadiau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220 Wien. - BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N V. Handel-
maatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H
1M7. CYPRUS. "MAM", Archishop Makanos 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahrancni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahnr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kiriakauppa, Keskukatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G D R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. onlyl. 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22, C.C.P. Hamburg 276650. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications* S. Karger GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/Munchen.
Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd , P.O Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legón, P.O. Box 1,
Legón. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen Swindon Book Co ,
13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kony-
vesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtùrosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf All Road, New Delhi 1, 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publi¬
cations Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 511
C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardmata III,
Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta;
Indira P. T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave ,
opposite to University of Teheran, P.O. Box 14/1480, Teheran;
Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No.
300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ. McKenzies Bookshop, Al-
Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Com¬
pany of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formely Blumstem's Book-stores,
35 Allenby Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9,
Shlomzion Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P O. Box
1728, Tokyo 100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House,
P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commis¬
sion for Unesco, P O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co , Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Maze¬
nod Book Centre, P O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Mon¬
rovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication Er Dis¬
tribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie
Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA.
Federal Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
- MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd , 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koener"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N V. Marti-
nus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHER-
LANDS ANTILLES. G CT. Van Dorp Et Co. (Ned Ant.), N.V.,
Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O.
Box 5344, Auckland; 130. Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christ-
church; Alma street. P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street,
P.O. Box 1104, Dunedm, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Welling¬
ton. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The Univer¬
sity Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Book-shop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zana. NORWAY. All publications'
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturje-
neste. Box 6125, Oslo 6 PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65
Sharah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIP¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila D-404. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury i
Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.
7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL Dias & Andrade Ltda,
Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schalk's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central' News Agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
(PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P 0.
Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rámistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030
Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd , 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaegi Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402,
Bangkok:Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
- TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Sta¬
tion, New York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in Spanish:
Santillana Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington Avenue,
New York, N.Y. 10022. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazij'e, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenije, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Water, water
everywhere...
Though the Earth has a superabundance of water, only an infinitesimal fraction of
it (about one ten-thousandth) is fresh water readily available for human use, in
streams, lakes and swamps. Under the pressures of mounting world demand,
supplies of good-quality water may soon become critically short even in areas
where it was once considered an inexhaustible resource.
]]>
</page>
</document>
