<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074771eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco CoUFÍCF A window
open on the world
Einstein
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
H '
"rag
ibH
T, I
>>.:\ > $s&
ptwn&j-*?"* '
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
India
Photo René Roland © Ziolo, Paris
The smiling boy
This head of a smiling boy is an example of early Indian art dating from some time during the Maurya
(322-185 BC) or Sunga (185-72 BC) periods. The boy is portrayed wearing a two-cornered head-dress
gracefully swathed in cloth. Fashioned in terra cotta which still bears traces of colour, the head (12 cm
high) is now in the Museum of Patna, capital of Bihar state in northern India.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COMier
MAY 1979 32nd YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 20 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch Swahili
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when ¡t is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier Is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street.
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief: Jean Gaudin
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Swahili Edition: Peter Mwombela (Dar-es-Salaam)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
Page
4 ALBERT EINSTEIN 1879-1955
The story of a genius
by Jürgen Ehlers
9 RELATIVITY IN A NUTSHELL
by Isaac Asimov
10 EINSTEIN'S TOPSY-TURVY UNIVERSE
17 THE TEST OF TIME
by Paul Dirac
18 LIGHT CAUGHT BENDING
Photo story
24 THE MOLE AND THE BUTTERFLY
Reflections on Einstein, science and subjectivity
by Pierre Thuillier
26 A CONSTELLATION OF COSMOLOGISTS
29 THE FRONTIERS OF SCIENCE
by Arkadii Migdal
31 THE SCIENTIST'S DILEMMA
by Albert Einstein
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
INDIA : The smiling boy
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Photo © Anne Desallly, Paris
Cover
Art pays tribute to science in the dazzling
curves of "space-time" which sweep across
Victor Vasarely's painting Einstein (1976). The
work symbolizes the genius of the great
physicist, born a hundred years ago, who
opened up a new age in science. The reach
and brilliance of his work, especially his
theories of relativity, were such that the full
implications of his thought are still being
explored. Einstein's deeply-felt humanism and
lovable personality also profoundly marked
his epoch.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Albert Einstein
1879-1955
The story of a genius
by Jürgen Ehlers
JÜRGEN EHLERS, noted German theoretical
physicist, is a Scientific Member of the Max
Planck Institute of Physics and Astrophysics at
Munich (Federal Republic of Germany). This
article is an edited and abridged version of a lec¬
ture given at Munich University in September
1978, at a Unesco symposium on the Impact of
Modern Scientific Ideas on Society.
ACCORDING to the eighteenth-
century German romantic poet and
science-enthusiast Novalis, "theo¬
ries are nets: only he who casts will catch".
Using this metaphor one can say that no
fisherman in this century was more suc¬
cessful than Albert Einstein.
In his annus mirabilis, 1905, comparable
in the history of science perhaps only to the
memorable year 1666 when Isaac Newton
conceived most of the ideas which were to
govern science for more than two hundred
years, Albert Einstein published in one and
the same volume of the German scientific
journal Annalen der Physik three papers
each of which, besides containing impor¬
tant specific results, laid the ground for ex¬
tensive new areas of fundamental research.
Who was this man Albert Einstein who,
as a twenty-six-year-old technical expert,
third class, at the Swiss patent office in
Berne, invented in his spare time new
methods in statistical mechanics,
discovered light quanta, gave a proof of the
existence of atoms, solved the problem of
constructing a correct electrodynamics of
moving bodies, a problem attacked without
definitive success by leading scientists of
the time like Hendrik Anton Lorentz and
Henri Poincaré, by setting up a new theory
of space and time?
Albert Einstein was born on 14 March
1879, in Ulm, Germany, in the same year in
which Max von Laue and Otto Hahn were
born and James Clerk Maxwell, the
founder of the modern theory of electro¬
magnetic fields, died.
The Einsteins were Jews, but did not
follow the rituals and laws of the Jewish
religion any more. In 1880 the family moved
to Munich, where Albert's father Hermann
ran a small electrochemical factory with his
brother. In the same year Albert's sister
Maja, his only sibling, was born. The
young Albert has been described as a
taciturn, pensive, day-dreaming little boy,,
slow at learning to speak, not liking
physical activities or playing much with
other children.
When he was four or five years old,
Albert Einstein experienced, according to
his recollection, what appeared to him as a
miracle. A magnetic compass, shown to
him by his father, appeared to be drawn
steadfastly and by a mysterious, invisible
power, always into the same direction, ir¬
respective of how one moved the housing
of the compass.
Does this deep impression, vividly
remembered after many years, indicate a
longing for something dependable,
something which the young as well as the
mature Einstein did not find in the human
world surrounding him, but which he did
find in the unchanging, impersonal struc¬
ture of nature?
Albert attended a Catholic elementary
school, and at the age of ten entered the
Luitpold Gymnasium. He disliked the strict
discipline, the authoritarian spirit, the lack
of freedom at the gymnasium, where he
had to learn Latin and Greek grammar
which interfered with his studies of
mathematics and science, the interest in
which had been excited in him by his uncle
who was an engineer.
Unhappy and depressed, an ill-adapted
outsider, considered by his teachers as
having a disruptive influence on his class¬
mates, Albert Einstein soon followed his
parents, without a school diploma, to
Milan where they had moved in 1894
because of business difficulties. After one
year of studies at a school at Aarau in
Switzerland where he felt much happier,
Albert Einstein was admitted as a student
of mathematics and physics to the famous
Polytechnic Institute in Zurich.
Among his fellow students were Mileva
Marie, a Serbian girl who in 1902 became
his first wife and who was to be the mother
of his two children, and Marcel
Grossmann, who eighteen years later k
became his mathematical collaborator.*
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
k Among his teachers was the outstanding
mathematician Hermann Minkowski, who
in 1907 invented the concept of space-time
and thus contributed in an essential way to
the development of the theory of relativity.
i After graduation in 1900 Einstein failed to
obtain a position at the Polytechnic or as a
teacher, but in 1902, with the help of his
friend Marcel Grossmann, he got a post at
the Patent Office in Berne. Here he
prepared himself for the examination for his
doctor's degree which he took in 1905, and
found enough time to pursue his research
in theoretical physics.
Einstein kept the position in Berne until
the end of 1909 when he accepted his first'
full-time academic appointment as
associate professor at the University of
Zurich. His accomplishments had by then
been widely recognized. He had extended
his research on the agitation of microscopic
particles known as Brownian motion, on
light quanta and relativity. He had created
the first quantum theory of specific heats
of solids; and, in 1907, he had formed the
opinion that a satisfactory theory of
gravitation would have to incorporate in a
basic and natural way the equality of iner-
tial and gravitational mass, and the fact,
already noted by Galileo, that all test bodies
fall with the same acceleration.
Gravity and inertia are essentially the
Photo © Parimage, Pans
One of the few surviving pictures of
Einstein as a young man. It was taken
when he was a pupil at the Polytechnic
Institute in Zurich in 1900, five years
before the publication of the great paper
in which he set forth the special theory of
relativity.
Photo © Ullstein, Fed. Rep. of Germany
Albert Einstein at the age of four. He was far from being a precocious
child and did not begin talking until he was three years old. Later, his
mother wrote anxiously to a friend : "I really don't know what we shall
make of Albert later on; he learns next to nothing".
same thing, Einstein decided, and therefore
a satisfactory theory of gravity required a
generalization of the space-time framework
of his theory of relativity, for if gravity is
taken into account the concept of a finitely
extended, strict inertial frame of reference
is no longer adequate.
In 1910 Einstein accepted a full pro¬
fessorship at the German University of
Prague. For the reasons just indicated Ein¬
stein was searching for a generalization of
what he now called the "special theory of
relativity", in order to include gravitation.
Gravitation theory was his main concern
between 1907 and 1916. Whereas the ma¬
jority of physicists had by then accepted
special relativity as a solid part of the
building of physics, Einstein was occupied
with finding out its limits of validity and
struggled for a more inclusive and more
precise mathematical representation of
physical processes. In Prague, in 1911, he
arrived at the prediction that light waves
are bent by gravitational fields, but not un¬
til 1914 was an expedition ready to make
appropriate observations during a solar
eclipse. The First World War ruled out this
attempt, and the first measurement had to
wait until 1919.
After eighteen months in Prague, at the
end of 1912, Einstein returned to Zurich,
this time to become a full professor at the
Polytechnic Institute where he had studied
a dozen years before.
In Zurich, in collaboration with his friend
Marcel Grossmann who had become a pro¬
fessor of mathematics, Einstein published a
preliminary version of a new theory of
gravity.
At the end of 1913, on the initiative of
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
the German physicists Max Planck and
Walter Nernst, Einstein was offered a well-
paid position as a member of the Royal
Prussian Academy of Sciences in Berlin
and director of the yet-to-be-founded
Kaiser-Wilhelm Institut für Physik.
His duty was to be the organization of
research. He was not obliged to teach, but
could do so if he wanted. Einstein had
always considered formal teaching a
burden, and he was attracted to the lively
scientific atmosphere of Berlin. So he ac¬
cepted the offer. Soon after his arrival in
Berlin he separated from his wife Mileva.
Einstein was now thirty-four years old and
a star of the first magnitude in the sky of
science.
In Berlin, in spite of many contacts with
colleagues, in particular with Max Planck,
Max von Laue, Walter Nernst and later Er¬
win Schrödinger, and many others, Ein¬
stein felt somewhat isolated and a
foreigner. He did not lecture, but par¬
ticipated actively in the discussions follow¬
ing colloquia. Being a pacifist and opposed
to nationalism, he felt even more isolated
during the First World War.
, He now concentrated fully on the theory
of gravitation and after a strenuous effort
Einstein succeeded at the end of 1915 in
formulating a coherent theory which is still
considered as the most admirable part of
classical physics. This theory has come
through all experimental tests performed
up to now with flying colours.
In 1917, in a paper which is regarded as
his most important contribution to quan¬
tum theory, Einstein proposed a statistical
description of the interaction of atoms and
photons and gave a new derivation of
Planck's law of radiation, which had laid
the foundations of quantum theory. In the
same year Einstein founded modern
cosmology, the science of the large-scale
structure of the universe, by constructing
the first mathematically consistent model
of the universe containing gravitating,
homogeneously distributed matter.
During the years 1921, 1922 and 1923
Einstein travelled in the United States,
Europe and Asia. Convinced by Chaim
Weizmann, he engaged himself for the
Zionist movement. In 1921 he was awarded
the Nobel prize, not for his relativity theory,
but "for the photoelectric law and his
works on theoretical physics".
When Hitler came to power in 1933,
Einstein was travelling in the United States.
He never again entered Germany. After a
short stay in Belgium, during which he
resigned from the Prussian Academy and
the Bavarian Academy of Sciences in pro¬
test against the passive attitude taken by
these academies when academic freedom
was suppressed in Germany and many
scientists and intellectuals were removed
from their positions for "ideological
reasons", Einstein accepted a position at
the newly founded Institute for Advanced
Study in Princeton (U.S.A.). He continued
research, concentrating mainly on the crea¬
tion of what he called a unified field theory
which would, so he hoped, give a deeper
account of both gravity and elec-
tromagnetism, and in addition would
describe particles as stable regions of high
concentration of the field. In these efforts.
Einstein did not succeed, but in a modified
form his programme of using geometry to
create such a unified theory has received a
strong new impetus and has had con¬
siderable success in recent years.
' Besides these efforts Einstein occa¬
sionally returned to his gravity theory of
1915 and enriched it by new results. In
1932, he collaborated with the Dutch
astronomer Willem de Sitter to construct a
model of an expanding universe which is
still a possible candidate to represent the
large-scale structure of the material world.
Joint work with Nathan Rosen in 1937
resulted in solutions of his field equations
which describe gravitational waves, and a
celebrated paper published in 1938, written
with Banesh Hoffmann and Leopold Infeld,
was devoted to the derivation of equations
of motion of particles from the gravitational
field equations. The subject of this paper is
still under discussion. Research on it is be¬
ing carried out by, among others, my col¬
laborators and myself at the Max Planck In¬
stitut für Physik und Astrophysik, at
Munich (Federal Republic of Germany).
Even after his retirement in 1945 Einstein
continued to work right up to his death on
18 April 1955, at the age of seventy-six.
One important characteristic of Ein¬
stein's approach to basic problems of
physics was that he questioned the ade¬
quacy of even those concepts and relations
which were generally regarded as evident;
in this sense he was a philosopher.
According to Einstein, concepts are free
inventions, and the axioms or basic laws of
a theory are guesses; they cannot be
deduced. or inductively inferred from ex-|
periences or observations. '
Photo © Ullstein, Fed. Rep. of Germany
With his second wife Elsa, homeward bound after a trip to California. In the 1920s
and early 1930s, Einstein travelled widely, visiting the United States, China, Japan
and most of Western Europe to explain and discuss his theories.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
On the other hand, a theory should per¬
mit the derivation of propositions which
can be tested experimentally, and therein
lies its value. Thus, science requires three
human activities: free invention or guess¬
ing, logical-mathematical deduction, and
observation or experiment.
As Einstein as well as Paul Dirac (see arti¬
cle page 17) remarked, the process of
guessing is guided hot only by factual ex¬
perience and experience with previous
theories, but also by a sense of structural
simplicity and mathematical beauty. There
is not much point in classifying Einstein as
a positivist, a rationalist, an empiricist or
any other "...ist", but if some such label
were required, I would propose to call him
a logico-empirical artist.
It appears that Einstein has strongly in¬
fluenced natural philosophy not so much
through his philosophical statements as
such, but because of the manner in which
he practised science, constructed new
theories and thus contributed to
knowledge, often in a surprising way.
Einstein regarded himself as a physicist
and not as a philosopher. He was proud of
the general theory of relativity which he
considered as his greatest intellectual
achievement.
"Einstein's Theory of Relativity has ad¬
vanced our ideas of the structure of the
cosmos a step further", wrote the German
mathematician Hermann Weyl. "It is as if a
wall which separated us from Truth has
collapsed. Wider expanses and greater
depths are now exposed to the searching
eye of knowledge, regions of which we had
not even a presentiment. It has brought us
much nearer to grasping the plan that
underlies all physical happening."
Jürgen Ehlers
At the blackboard during a lecture to the American Association for the
Advancement of Science. In 1933 Einstein accepted a post at the Institute for
Advanced Study at Princeton, where he worked until he died in 1955, a
page of uncompleted equations at his bedside.
Photo © Keystone. Paris
* «
i II
-
i ' \ ! 4
1 lIM I =£# i
-
4ft
15L * *w ,
HEBT K*- fTvl - V
L
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
WHAT IS RELATIVITY ? The following way of illustrating the
concept of relativity was thought up by the celebrated French
mathematician Henri Poincaré. Just suppose, said Poincaró, that
one night while you were fast asleep everything in the universe
somehow became a thousand times bigger. Everything : the
stars, the sun, the earth, your home, your bed, you yourself, the
length of light waves, atoms and electrons. When you woke up,
would you know that anything had changed ? No, said Poincaré;
no experiment could possibly prove that anything had changed.
It would be meaningless to say that the universe had become
bigger, because if you say that a thing is "bigger" you imply that
it is bigger than "something else" and in the case of the universe
there is no "something else". In other words size is a relative
concept.
Drawings Philippe Gentil Studio, Paris © Unesco Courier
Relativity
in a nutshell
by Isaac Asimov
ISAAC ASIMOV of the USA is internationally
known as a popularizer of science anda science
fiction writer. His huge output of published
works reflects the variety of his interests which
include : literary criticism, psychology, mathe¬
matics, mystery, poetry and humour. Earlier this
year he published his 200th book, assigning the
same number to two works: Opus 200 (Hough¬
ton Mifflin), an Asimov anthology, and In
Memory Yet Green (Doubleday), the first
volume of his autobiography.
ACCORDING to the laws of motion
first worked out in detail by Isaac
Newton in the 1680s, different mo¬
tions add together according to the rules of
simple arithmetic. Suppose a train is mov¬
ing away from you at twenty kilometres an
hour and a person on the train throws a ball
at twenty kilometres an hour in the direc¬
tion of the train's motion. To the person,
moving with the train, the ball is moving
twenty kilometres an hour away from him.
To you, however, the motion of the train
and the ball add together, and the ball is
moving away from you at the rate of forty
kilometres an hour.
Thus, you see, you cannot speak of the
ball's speed all by itself. What counts is its
speed relative to a particular observer. Any
theory of motion that attempts to explain
the way velocities and related phenomena
seem to vary from observer to observer
would be a "theory of relativity".
Albert Einstein's particular theory of
relativity arose from the fact that what
works for thrown balls on trains doesn't
seem to work for light. A moving source of
light might cast a beam of light in the direc-
tion of its travel, or against the direction of
its travel. In the former case, the light
should (according to Newton's laws) travel
at its own speed plus the speed of the light-
source. In the latter case, it should travel at
its own speed minus the speed of the light-
source. That's the way the thrown ball on
the moving train would behave.
Light doesn't behave so. It always seems
to travel at its own speed regardless of the
motion of the source. Einstein attempted
to arrange the laws of the universe to ac¬
count for that.
Einstein showed that, in order to ac¬
count for the constancy of light's velocity,
one had to accept a great many unex-k
pected phenomena. He showed that ob- f
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Einstein's topsy-turvy universe
The curious tale of a ride on a beam of light, clocks that
run slower when they are in motion than when they are
stationary, the long-playing record whose centre is older
than Its outer rim, light rays that bend, objects that
change in size and weight, a man only half as old as his
twin, black holes in space from which not even light can
escape all these Alice-in-Wonderland notions which
seem to fly in the face of common sense form part of
Einstein's topsy-turvy world of relativity. Did Einstein
really throw common sense out of the window ? Not at
all. The curious effects his theory postulates only become
evident when we enter the world of very high velocities.
Although they are of great importance in physics, in
ordinary life they are so infinitesimal that they can be
ignored. Many of the implications of the theory of
relativity are so complex that they can only be fully
expressed in mathematical terms. The drawings and
captions on this and following pages are an attempt to
give an approximate visual introduction to Einstein's
mysterious universe.
300000 km
nz7,
A street-car named relativity
As a teenager in Zurich, Einstein asked himself a seemingly innocent question the
answer to which contained the core of the principle of relativity. "What would the
world look like", he pondered, "if I rode on a beam of light ?"
Let us make this imaginary journey with Einstein. Picture yourself boarding a street¬
car at the foot of a clock-tower in Berne, as Einstein used to do every day on his way
to work at the Swiss Patent Office. Imagine that, instead of travelling along its usual
track, the street-car carried you away at the speed of light (300,000 kilometres per
second) on the very beam of light with which you saw the time indicated on the clock.
Suppose the clock showed three o'clock when the street-car whisked you off to a
destination 300,000 kilometres away. The journey ought to take you exactly one
second. But the clock as you see it (assuming that you could see it from a distance of
300,000 kilometres) would still say three o'clock; this is because it takes the beam of
light from the clock showing the time you set off as long as it has taken you to reach
your destination. By keeping up with the speed of light you as a passenger in the
street-car are cut off from the passage of time. But to a man left standing on the
pavement in Berne the same clock would indicate one second past three. In other
words, time runs differently for you in the street-car and for the man on the pavement
in Berne; contrary to what Newton thought, therefore, there is no such thing as
universal time. Furthermore, although in the street-car you discover the same laws,
the same relations between time, distance, speed, mass and force as everyone
everywhere discovers, the actual values that you get for time, distance, and so one,
are not the same as for anyone else. The only value that is invariably the same for
everyone is the value for the speed of light.
For Newton, time and space formed an absolute framework and the world looked the
same to every observer, wherever he might be and however he might travel. For
Einstein, what two observers see is relative to each of them, to their position and their
speed. We cannot know what the world is like, we can only compare what it looks
like to each of us. Relativity is the understanding of the world not as events but as
relations.
Drawings Studio Philippe Gentil © Unesco Courier
kjects would have to grow shorter in the
"direction of their motionshorter and
shorter as their motion was faster and
faster, until they would have zero length at
the speed of light; that moving objects
would have more and more mass the faster
they moved till their mass was infinite at
the speed of light; that the rate at which
time progressed on moving bodies decreas¬
ed the faster they moved till it stopped
altogether at the speed of light. For each of
these reasons the speed of light in a
vacuum was the maximum speed that
could be measured.
Furthermore, he showed that a little bit
of mass was equal to a great deal of
energy, according to his famous equation,
E = me2, where c stands for the speed of
light.
All this, he worked out in 1905 for bodies
moving at the same speed in an unchang¬
ing direction. This special kind of motion
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Time out of joint
A curious prediction of the theory of relativity was that a
stationary clock would run faster than a moving clock. In 1905,
Einstein wrote "that a clock fixed at the earth's equator will run
slower by a very small amount than an identical clock fixed at
one of the earth's poles". This was proved experimentally by the
English scientist H.J. Hay who visualized the globe squashed into
a flat disc with the North Pole at the centre and the equator at
the rim. Placing a radio-active clock at the centre and another at
the rim he set his model turning. Einstein's prediction was
proved correct, the clock at the rim kept time more slowly than
the clock at the centre. This holds true for any spinning disc on
every turntable, and each time a long-playing record revolves on
a record-player its centre is ageing faster than its rim.
was dealt with in Einstein's "special theory
of relativity."
The effects predicted by Einstein are
noticeable only at great speeds. The simple
arithmetic of Newton's laws therefore
works at ordinary speeds, simply because
Einstein's effects are too small to notice.
Because we are always surrounded by the
working of those laws, they come to seem
like "common sense" to us while Einstein's
effects seem strange.
Nevertheless, at the time Einstein
published his theory, scientists were work¬
ing with subatomic particles hurled out¬
ward by exploding atoms. These sub¬
atomic particles moved at great speeds and
the Einstein effects could be noted in them
exactly. Atom-smashing machines and
nuclear bombs couldn't exist unless the
special theory of relativity was correct.
In 1916, Einstein worked out a more
complicated version of the theory of
relativity, one that included not only mo¬
tion at constant speed in the same direc¬
tion any kind of motion at all, motion
that changed speed or direction or both.
Since it dealt with any motion in general,
this version of his theory is "the general
theory of relativity."
The most common reason why objects
move at varying speeds and in changing
direction is because a gravitational force is
acting on them. A ball when dropped
moves faster and faster because earth's
gravity is pulling it. A thrown ball follows a
curved path because earth's gravity is pull¬
ing it. The earth follows a curved path in
space because the sun's gravity is pulling
it.
For this reason, Einstein's general theory
had to deal with gravitation.
Einstein worked out a set of equations
which showed that if there were no matter
anywhere and no gravitation, a moving
body would follow a straight line. If there
were matter, the surrounding space would
be distorted so that the moving body
would follow a curved line. Einstein's
general theory showed what those curves
ought to be and they weren't quite what
Newton's theory of gravitation predicted.
The differences between Einstein's equa¬
tions and Newton's equations are very
slight indeed, and only the most careful
and delicate measurements can show us
which set of equations is actually followed
by moving bodies.
One way of telling whether Einstein or
Newton is right is by studying the
behaviour of light when it passes through a
strong gravitational field. According to
Einstein, the light would pass through the
distorted space and follow a very slightly
curved path. This would not be so accor- w
ding to the Newtonian rules. f
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Drawing studio Philippe Gentil <& Unesco Courier
A matter of gravity
To Newton, gravitation represented the mutual attraction of
masses of matter, the power of bodies to influence each other in
proportion to their size and the distance between them. This
force acted everywhere in the cosmos, whether causing an apple
to fall to the ground or the moon to circle the earth. Setting
aside this concept of an active force, which formed the
underlying mechanism of the Newtonian universe, Einstein
thought in terms of the "gravitational field". Thus the
gravitational field of the earth governed the fall of Newton's
apple and the solar gravitational field governs the motion of the
planets around the sun. Matter, Einstein maintained, creates this
gravitational field by distorting what he called the "space-time
continuum" around it. This has been likened to an outstretched
rubber sheet which is deformed by heavy objects (the sun, the
stars) placed upon it. Diagram shows how light rays move along
the curves thus formed and are thus "bent" round large heavenly
bodies.. Einstein predicted that starlight passing near the sun
would follow the curved pathways in space caused by the sun's
presence, thus seemingly "bending" round it. His prediction was
confirmed in a famous experiment by the English astronomer Sir
Arthur Eddington in 1919 (see page 19)
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
\\a\\\\WLmmL\WLmL\a\\UÊLWLwmLmm
y In 1919, a total eclipse was observed and
the positions of the stars near the sun were
accurately measured. If the light travelled a
curved path, each star should seem to be a
little farther from the sun than it ought to
be. The amount of displacement would de¬
pend on how near the sun the light passed.
Einstein's theory predicted exactly how
large the displacement ought to be. The
measurements at that 1919 eclipse, and at
every total eclipse since then, seem to
place the stars where Einstein predicted
they would be.
These were hard measurements to
make, though, and difficult to get exact. In
our space age, we have been able to do
better.
In 1969, for instance, two probes were
sent toward Mars. When the probes were
on the other side of the sun, the radio
waves that they beamed back to earth had
to pass near the sun and therefore followed
a distorted path. Because of the distortion,
the path was longer than a straight line
would have been, and it took a bit more
time for the waves to reach us. It took them
a ten-thousandth of a second longer, ac¬
tually, something which could be measured
and which was just what general relativity
predicted.
Another prediction of Einstein's general
theory is that in space distorted by gravity
time slows up.
A large object giving off light, emits that
light in waves that are longer than they
would be otherwise, because the slowing
of time in the object's gravitational field
keeps one wave going longer before the
next one comes out. Even the sun, though,
has a gravitational field that is not strong
enough to show a measurable effect.
Just about the time Einstein advanced
his theory of general relativity, however, a
new kind of star was discovered. This was
the "white dwarf." A white dwarf might
have all the mass of the sun squeezed
down into a volume no larger than that of
the earth. Its gravitational field at its sur¬
face would be two hundred thousand times
as intense as the sun's gravitational field
was.
Particular light-waves emitted by a white
dwarf would have to be longer by a par¬
ticular amount than those same light¬
waves emitted by the sun. In 1925,
measurements were taken of the light com¬
ing from a white dwarf and were found to
be longer by just the right amount
predicted by Einstein.
It was, of course, very difficult to take
the measurement of the light from a white
dwarf. Such stars are very dim and trying
to analyse their feeble beams of light is a
tricky matter.
It has been found, however, that under
certain conditions, a collection of atoms in
a crystal would emit gamma rays. Gamma
rays are made up of waves like those of
light, but much shorter. The crystal emitted
' gamma rays that all had the same
wavelength exactly, and the wavelength
could be measured with great accuracy.
If Einstein's general theory were correct,
however, the gamma ray wavelength could
be slightly changed if the gravitational pull
upon the crystal were either increased or
decreased.
Here on earth, gravitation increases as
one gets closer to earth's centre. If you live
in an apartment house, earth's gravity gets
stronger with each floor you descend but
so slightly that you can't possibly tell the
difference.
But it shows up in the gamma rays. As
the crystal was taken down from the attic
to the basement, the wave grew very
slightly (but detectably) longer, and by ex-
CONT1NUED PAGE 16
161/2 grams at the North Pole
grams at 40°
ilMorth Latitude
0 grams at the centre
of the earth
151/2 grams
at the Equator
An object does not weigh the same at all
points on the earth's surface. This is
because the earth is not perfectly round
and It is rotating. An object would weigh
nothing at the centre of the earth because
the earth's matter pulls on it equally from
all directions.
Drawing studio Philippe Gentil © Unesco Courier
adapted from The World Book Encyclopedia © 1979 World
Book-Childcraft International, Inc.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
TN.'
I
V
Photo © I. P.S., Paris
Really massive stars burn more fiercely than the sun, have much shorter lives and end their
existence In a colossal explosion. The Crab Nebula, above, consists of the remains of a star
explosion which was recorded by Chinese astronomers in AD 1054. In 1969, astronomers
discovered a neutron star at the heart of the nebula. This small but extremely dense body
consists of the compressed residual mass of the original star. Such bodies are also known as
pulsars because they emit light and radio signals in regular pulses.
Goalkeeper's nightmare
Imagine the astonishment of a goalkeeper
facing an ace centre-forward capable of
kicking a football in such a way that it
would accelerate from rest up to the
speed of light. The football, which at rest
weighs some 450 grams, would become
heavier and heavier, becoming heavier
than an elephant, a group of buildings and
even the sun until finally, at the speed of
light, its weight would become infinite.
All this can be deduced from Einstein's
famous equation E = mc2 (energy equals
mass multiplied by the velocity of light
squared). The equation tells us that if we
divide the energy of motion (kinetic
energy) of the football by the square of
the velocity of light, we will discover the
football's mass; since its energy is
increasing with acceleration, then its mass
must also be increasing. Mass has been
defined as the amount of matter of which
an object consists, but scientists prefer to
define mass as a measure of inertia, the
resistance of all matter to being
accelerated. In everyday life we usually
measure weight rather than mass; indeed
the two are very closely related, although
weight is a more complicated notion than
mass because it depends upon the
strength of the earth's gravitational field.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Drawings studio Philippe Gentil © Unesco Courier
Giant stars and black holes
When we look up into the sky at night, we can see stars because
they emit light. But one of the most baffling consequences of
Einstein's general theory of relativity is the possibility of the
existence of "black holes", the "corpses" of what were once
massive stars, which we cannot see because their gravitational
field is so intense that not even light can escape from them. How
are black holes formed ? And if we cannot see them how do we
know that they exist ? The diagrams above illustrate, from left to
right, the stages in the formation of a black hole. During the
stable life of a massive star equilibrium exists between
gravitational pressure (represented by the inward-pointing
arrows) and radiation and the heat from the star's core (outward-
pointing arrows). But as the star burns up its core of nuclear fuel
the equilibrium is broken and the star begins to collapse towards
its centre (middle diagram). Finally, the star crushes itself into a
tiny volume of enormous gravity and density. Black holes, by
definition, can never be visible even to the most powerful
telescope, but their presence can be detected by their effect on
neighbouring visible stars. With their immense gravitational pull,
black holes act like vast vacuum cleaners in space sucking in
everything they meet. Below, gases from a visible massive star
(left) are pulled towards the invisible black hole. As these gases
spiral into the black hole they are heated and compressed and
emit X-Rays that astronomers can detect.
" 7~ ' ..
IT ^S!^ Z^aaW\^LaW\ ^^^^^fc*«.- ^^^^^
^'r'J' "^w
IÉ3
HH^HH^^H^HUHI^HHilHHH HBi MHHH
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 13
y actly the amount predicted by Einstein's
theory.
Still another consequence of Einstein's
treatment of gravitation in his general
theory of relativity is that gravitation, like
light, can be given off in waves. In this
way, gravitation, like light, can carry
energy away from the object giving it off.
Such gravitational waves are given off
when an object moves round and round in
response to gravitation, or back and forth,
or pulses in and out. The earth, when it
moves around the sun, gives off gravita¬
tional waves, according to Einstein. It is
losing energy so that it is slowly dropping
in closer to the sun.
Gravitational waves are so weak,
however, and carry so little energy that the
waves given off by earth are far too feeble
to be detected. The energy they carry off is
so tiny that earth won't drop closer to the
sun by more than a few metres in billions of
years.
It may be, though, that somewhere in
the universe there are more intense gravita¬
tional fields than there are here in the solar
system. Extremely rapid motions may in¬
volve the giving off of gravitational waves
that are just barely energetic enough to
detect.
Many scientists have been trying to
detect such gravitational waves using very
delicate instruments. Some have reported
success, but the results were very
borderline and such reports have not yet
been accepted.
In 1967, however, a new kind of star was
discovered, a "pulsar". Such a star is even
smaller and more compressed than a white
dwarf is. A pulsar may have a mass equal
to our sun and yet have it all squeezed into
a little ball no more than twelve kilometres
across. The gravitational field at the sur¬
face of such a pulsar would be
10,000,000,000 times that of the sun.
In 1974, two pulsars were found that
circled each other. With circlings in so in¬
credibly powerful a gravitational field, ef¬
fects that are barely noticeable in our solar
system become easy to measure.
For instance, there is a small component
of Mercury's motion about the sun that
isn't accounted for by Newton's theory of
gravitation. A particular point in Mercury's
orbit makes a complete circle about the sun
in a little over 3,000,000 years although by
Newton's theory it shouldn't move at all.
Einstein's theory, however, accounts for
the motion exactly.
That same point in the orbits of that pair
of circling pulsars should make a complete
circle in a mere eighty-four years according
to Einstein's theory, and the point is mov¬
ing at the proper speed to do so.
What's more, the pulsars should be giv¬
ing off gravitational waves as they revolve,
much stronger ones than earth does. The
energy carried off by the gravitational
waves ought to be enough to cause the
pulsars to be spiralling in toward each other
at a noticeable rate. This, in turn, should
cause certain radio wave pulses they give
off to reach us at shorter and shorter
intervals.
In 1978, delicate measurements of those
radio pulses were made and they were
found to be coming at shorter and shorter
intervals by just the predicted amounts.
What it comes to is this: In the three-
quarters of a century since Einstein advanc¬
ed his theory of relativity, scientists have
tested it in every way they could think of,
over and over again, and Einstein's theory
has passed every single test they have
devised without exception.
Isaac Asimov
Einstein's work gave new impetus
to cosmology, the study of the
universe as a unified whole. The
Russian mathematician Alexander
Friedmann had shown that
Einstein's theories suggested that
the universe was unstable and
probably expanding. Einstein
himself was at first unable to
accept the logic of his own
equations and in order to arrive at a
closed model of the universe he
introduced a factor into his
gravitational equations which he
called the "cosmological constant"
(see article page 29). In 1924, the
American astronomer Edwin
Hubble proved experimentally that
Friedmann's view was correct, that
the distant galaxies were receding
at increasing speeds and that the
universe was in fact expanding.
Einstein finally bowed to the
evidence and described his earlier
stance as "the biggest blunder of
my life". Right, representations,
top, of an open universe which will
expand for ever, and, bottom, of a
closed universe that will .eventually
contract.
Drawings studio Philippe Gentil © Unesco Courier
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Paul Dirac seen with
Einstein at the fifth
Solvay Conference, held
in Brussels in October
1927.
Photo © Palais de la Découverte,
Paris
The test of time
by Paul Dirac
PAUL DIRAC, eminent British physicist, won
the 1933 Nobel Prize in physics with Erwin
Schrödinger, an Austrian scientist, for his bril¬
liant studies and research in atomic physics. He
is a Professor Emeritus of Cambridge University
and Professor ofphysics at Florida State Univer¬
sity, USA. This article is an abridged version of a
lecture given by Prof. Dirac ata Unesco sympo¬
sium on the Impact of Modern Scientific Ideas
on Society, held in September 1978 at the Uni¬
versities of Munich and Ulm (Federal Republic of
Germany).
THE big discoveries in science are
made in two ways. Sometimes the
time is ripe for a certain discovery
and there are many people hot on the trail.
It becomes a race between them and
whoever wins the race gets the credit.
If you look through the list of Nobel Prize
winners you will see that very often the
prizes are awarded to two or three people
who have worked on the same subject and
the credit is divided between those who
win the race. This kind of discovery is such
that if one particular man had never existed
the discovery would soon have been made
by somebody else.
Now there is another kind of scientific
discovery where one man works all alone,
follows new lines of thought entirely by
himself with no rivals and no competitors.
He goes into new domains of thought
which no one has previously entered. The
work of Einstein is mostly of this kind.
If Einstein had not existed these
discoveries would not have been made by
anybody else for many years or for many
decades. Einstein alone entirely changed
the course of scientific history.
Einstein's theory of relativity remained
unknown, except to a few specialists, until
the end of 1918, when the First World War
came to an end. It then came in with a ter¬
rific impact. It presented the world with a
new style of thinking, a new philosophy.
It came at a time when everyone was
sick of the war, those who had won as well
as those who had lost. People wanted
something new. Relativity provided just
what was wanted and was seized upon by
the general public and became the central
topic of conversation. It allowed people to
forget for a time the horrors of the war they
had come through.
Innumerable articles about relativity were
written in newspapers and magazines.
Never before or since has a specific idea
aroused so much and such widespread in¬
terest. Most of what was said and written
referred to general philosophical ideas and
CONTINUED PAGE 21
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
m? mWaW aaaaWl
Light caught bending
Perhaps the most famous and dramatic test of the General Theory
of Relativity was carried out just sixty years ago under the
direction of the British astronomer Arthur Eddington (1882-1944). In
1915, in the General Theory, Einstein predicted that gravity would
bend the path of a ray of light when it passed near a massive star
such as the sun. Eddington decided to test the theory during the
total solar eclipse of 29 May 1919, for during a total eclipse It
would be possible to take photographs of stars near the sun. These
photos could then be compared with photos of the same stars
taken when the sun was in a quite different part of the sky. Any
difference between the positions of the stars in the two sets of
photos would show that the starlight had "bent" and calculations
could be made to show how much bending had occurred. The 1919
eclipse would be particularly propitious because it would take
place in a region of the sky rich in bright stars that would be
visible against the solar corona. Eddington organized two
expeditions, one to Principe Island in the Gulf of Guinea, the other
to Sobral in Brazil. Both expeditions were able to obtain sets of
photos showing the positions of stars. Eddington, In charge of the
African expedition, remembered his first measurements of the
photos as the greatest moment of his life : they showed that the
starlight had Indeed been deflected. The Principe results showed a
deflection slightly less than Einstein had predicted; those from
Brazil rather more. On 27 September 1919, by which time the data
had been more fully analysed, Einstein wrote to his mother :
"Good news today... the British expeditions have definitely
confirmed the deflection of light by the sun". Photos show
1) Einstein with Eddington at Cambridge in 1930. 2) The British
astronomer Andrew Crommelin, who led the Sobral expedition,
with some of the instruments used. 3) The solar corona during the
1919 eclipse. 4) A scene at Sobral during the expedition.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
perihelion
finish still waterstart
Mercury violates a cosmic schedule. Scientists
were bothered for a hundred years because
Mercury in reaching its perihelion, or point
closest to the sun, did not revolve exactly once
around the sun from one perihelion to the next.
It seemed to exceed the celestial speed laws by
travelling a little bit more. In the course of a
century, this discrepancy amounted to forty-
three seconds of arc, represented in the
diagram by A...B. Einstein's explanation of this
"aberration" was one of the outstanding
results of his general theory of relativity.
start with the tide finish
Relativity of speed. The speed of any moving object is relative to an observer,
as these three drawings illustrate. The submarine is moving forward under the
maximum speed of its engines in each case, but the distance covered in one
hour varies because of the motion of the water. Thus, while the ship's velocity
in relation to the water remains the same in each case, its speed appears to be
variable to an observer on land, who, not knowing about the tides, would
assume that the submarine's engines were being run moderately fast, then very
slowly, and finally with great speed.
Speed of light is constant. Two mythical cannon at opposite ends of the earth
fire a projectile at the moon. Because of a difference in speed due to the motion
of the earth, the two projectiles arrive at their destination days apart. But the
beams of light which appeared from each cannon at the same instant arrive at
the moon simultaneously, exactly one and one third seconds after the firing of
the cannon. The speed of light is not affected by any motion at its source or of
the medium through which it passes, and for that reason is an important
standard of measurement under the theory of relativity.
RELATIVITY
IN
PICTURES
Relativity of direction. What appears to us as a straight line may in reality be a
curve. A person dropping a stone from the top of the tower sees it fall in a
straight line to earth. But he forgets that the earth is moving. Because of this
motion, an observer in space would see the stone fall not in a straight line but
along the curved path A...B.
Drawings and captions on these pages were done under
Einstein's guidance. They are taken from Albert Einstein
Maker of Universes by H. Gordon Garbedian © 1939
Cassell and Co. Ltd., London.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 17
did not have the precision required for
serious scientific discussion. Very little
precise information was available. But still
people were happy just to expound their
views.
I was an engineering student at Bristol
University in England at the time, and of
course the students took up this subject
and discussed it extensively among
themselves. But neither the students nor
the professors had precise information
about it or knew anything about the
underlying mathematics. We could only
talk about the philosophical implications
and accept the universal belief that it was a
good theory.
In England, one man, Arthur Eddington,
really understood relativity and became the
leader and the authority on the subject. He
was very much concerned with the
astronomical consequences of the theory
and the possibility of checking it by
astronomical observations.
Three possible tests of the theory were
proposed.
The first of these concerned the motion
of the planet Mercury. The perihelion of
Mercury (the point in the planet's trajectory
nearest to the sun) was observed to be ad¬
vancing about forty-three seconds of arc
more than it should be according to the
Newtonian theory, a fact that had been
bothering astronomers for a long time.
Einstein's new theory predicted just this ef¬
fect and Eddington's tests confirmed this
prediction.
This was really a wonderful success for
Einstein's theory, but it is said that Einstein
himself was not very excited when he
heard of Eddington's confirmation because
he felt that his theory had to be right in any
case.
The second test concerned the deflec¬
tion of light passing close by the sun. Ein¬
stein's theory of gravitation requires that
light passing close by the sun shall be
deflected. The Newtonian theory also re¬
quires a deflection, but only half the
amount of the Einstein theory. So, by
observing stars on the far side of the sun,
whose light has passed close to the sun to
reach us, we can test Einstein's theory.
Now we can only observe the stars close
to the sun at a time of total eclipse, when
the sun's light is blotted out by the moon.
There was a suitable total eclipse in 1919
and Eddington prepared two expeditions to
observe this eclipse, leading one of them in
person.
Both expeditions obtained results which
confirmed Einstein's theory. However, the
accuracy of this confirmation was not very
great because of the difficulties in making
these observations. So people were not
altogether satisfied with it. At many total
eclipses of the sun that have occurred since
then, people have again checked for this
effect and they have always got results
agreeing with Einstein's theory with a
greater or lesser accuracy.
More recently it has become possible to
check this effect with radio waves instead
of light waves. Radio stars have been
discovered and when a radio star is behind
the sun we can observe whether the radio
waves passing close by the sun are
deflected. This can be done without
waiting for a total eclipse because the sun
is only a very weak emitter of radio waves.
Using radio waves instead of light waves
there is an added complication because
radio waves are deflected by the sun's cor¬
ona. But this deflection is different for
waves of different lengths, so by making
the observations for two different
wavelengths, we can separate the effect
arising from the corona from the Einstein
effect. The result is that Einstein's theory is
confirmed with an accuracy much greater
than can be attained with light waves.
The third test concerned the prediction
of the general relativity theory that light
waves which have been emitted from a
source in a gravitational field will be
deflected towards longer wavelengths, i.e.
towards the red end of the spectrum, an ef¬
fect known as the red shift. The obvious
place to look for this effect is with a light
that has come from the surface of the sun.
But it is difficult to observe the Einstein ef¬
fect there because of another phenomenon
(the Doppler effect) arising from the mo¬
tion of the matter in the sun's atmosphere
which is quite large and which is not very
well understood. Nevertheless, we can
make estimates of the effects of this mo¬
tion and obtain a rough agreement of the
requirements of Einstein's theory.
The discovery of the white dwarf star
provides a better way of testing for this ef¬
fect. With the white dwarf stars we have
matter in a very highly condensed state.
The gravitational potential at the surface of
a white dwarf is very much greater than it is
at the surface of the sun and the Einstein
effect is correspondingly greater. If we
have enough information about the white
dwarf to be able to infer what its mass is
and its size, we can get a very good check
of Einstein's theory. This effect can now
also be checked by laboratory observations
with greater accuracy than we can get with
astronomical observations.
Recently a fourth test has been added to
the three classical ones. This is concerned
with the time taken by light to pass close by
the sun. The Einstein theory requires a
delay. This can be observed if we project
radar waves to a planet on the far side of
the sun, and then observe the time taken
for the reflected waves to get back to
earth. With the use of radar waves the
retardation is affected by the sun's corona
and again we have to use two different
wavelengths to disentangle the corona ef¬
fect from the Einstein effect.
The observations have been carried out
by Irwin Shapiro and again there is good
confirmation of the Einstein theory.
This enumeration of the successes of
Einstein's theory is impressive. In every
case Einstein's theory is confirmed, with
greater or less accuracy depending on the
precision with which the observations can
be made and the uncertainties that they
involve.
Let us now face the question, that a
discrepancy has appeared, well confirmed
and substantiated, between the theory and
the observations. How should one react to
it ? How would Einstein himself have
reacted to it ? Should one then consider
the theory to be basically wrong ?
I would say that the answer to the last
question is emphatically No. Anyone who
appreciates the fundamental harmony con¬
necting the way nature runs and general
mathematical principles must feel that a
theory with the beauty and elegance of
Einstein's theory has to be substantially
correct. If a discrepancy should appear in
some application of the theory, it must be
caused by some secondary feature relating
to this application which has not been ade¬
quately taken into account, and not by a
failure of the general principles of the k
theory. f
Relativity of time. Two widely separated
lighthouses flash a warning beacon at the
same Instant. A man on the ground, exactly
half-way between the two towers, sees the
two flashes simultaneously. But to an observer
in the airship, moving towards the beacon at
the left, the two flashes would not be
simultaneous. Relative to him, the flash from
the tower nearest to him would appear a
fraction of a second ahead of the other, as it
has less distance to cover.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
*
* *
1 . -1
1 - .
m ^ ft *
*
1
_^^T&fl_ _ i- -^.
ftr>-
* * ^^* ' ' w
' \ -
* *
m : !
*
*
*
*
*
*
Above, the first ever picture of an X-ray star was transmitted from the three-ton orbiting
space observatory HEAO-2. The star is called Cygnus X-1. It is part of a dual system in the
Cygnus constellation about 6,000 light years away. This dual system is believed to contain
a black hole (see page 15). Below, four quasars photographed through the Hale telescope
at Mount Palomar in California. Quasars (quasi-stellar radio sources), celestial bodies that
emit radio waves, were first discovered in 1962. Some quasars also emit X-rays. The quasar
known as 3C-273 (lower left) is the most powerful X-ray source so far discovered.
Photos © I.P.S., Paris
When Einstein was working on building
up his theory of gravitation he was not try¬
ing to account for some results of observa¬
tions. Far from it. His entire procedure was
to search for a beautiful theory, a theory of
a type that nature would choose.
He was guided only by the requirement
that his theory should have the beauty and
the elegance which one would expect to be
provided by any fundamental description of
nature. He was working entirely from these
ideas of what nature ought to be like and
not from the requirement to account for
certain experimental results.
Of course it needs real genius to be able
to imagine what nature should be like; just
from abstract thinking about it. Einstein
was able to do it.
Somehow he got the idea of connecting
gravitation with the curvature of space. He
was able to develop a mathematical
scheme incorporating this idea. He was
guided only by consideration of the beauty
of the equations.
The result of such a procedure is a theory
of great simplicity and elegance in its basic
ideas. One has an overpowering belief that
its foundations must be correct quite in¬
dependent of its agreement with observa¬
tion.
I had the privilege of meeting Einstein on
various occasions. The first time was at the
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Solvay Conference in Brussels in 1927 at
which the leading scientists of the world
discussed recent developments.
By that time Einstein's theory was firmly
established and generally accepted and it
was not a subject of discussion at that con¬
ference. The major topic was the new
quantum theory of Heisenberg,
Schrödinger and others. Of course, we all
wanted to have Einstein's impressions of
the new ideas.
Einstein was a little hostile to these ideas
because he had obtained such a marvellous
success with his own ideas of introducing
geometry into physics and he thought that
further development would also be on the
lines of introducing more exotic kinds of
geometry. He had spent many years of his
life working on those lines without any very
substantial success. Probably these ideas
of Einstein are basically correct but they
have not yet led to a satisfactory
solution.
I also met Einstein at a later Solvay Con¬
ference; then he came to Cambridge,
where I was working, and later went to
Princeton and became a permanent
member of the Institute for Advanced
Study. I was also a temporary member of
the Institute from time to time.
I attended lectures which Einstein gave
and sometimes he invited me to his. house
which was a great privilege. I got to know
KNUDIIH HIRIIN JlANl
*t»lvlt WIIH
»«»»I« CU»I
him personally on those occasions. I was
able to see how scientific ideas dominated
pretty well all his thoughts; even when you
were given a cup of tea and you stirred it,
the motion of the tea-leaves was
something which Einstein figured out how
to explain.
During the course of Einstein's discus¬
sions with physicists, he made one remark
which has become very famous and is now
carved into the stonework over the
fireplace in the common-room of the
Mathematics Institute at Princeton Univer¬
sity. To appreciate this remark you really
have to be a research physicist and under¬
stand that God has set certain problems
which the research physicist is trying to
solve. Furthermore, you must try to ap¬
preciate the mentality of God in setting
these problems. Einstein summed up his
view of this situation with these words :
"Raffiniert ist Gott, aber bösartig ¡st Er
nicht", "God is clever, but not dishonest".
Paul Dirac
IINtTIIK L1KIIV
The first Solvay Conference (so named
after the Belgian industrialist Ernest
Solvay who sponsored it) was held in
Brussels In 1911 to discuss the
consequences of Max Planck's law of
black body radiation, formulated in 1901,
which laid the foundation of the quantum
theory. This group of scientists, perhaps
the most prestigious ever gathered
together, was responsible for advances in
knowledge that form the basis of
modern physics.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The mole
and the butterfly
Reflections on Einstein,
science and subjectivity
by Pierre Thuillier
Text Copyright © Pierre Thuillier, 1979
Reproduction prohibited
J[§ F we consider science as a completed body of knowledge,
I it is the most impersonal of human works; but if we see
I it as a continuing project, it is just as subjective and
psychologically conditioned as any other human undertaking."
This declaration of Einstein's may surprise the defenders of a cer¬
tain form of logical positivism. But it constitutes a sort of invitation
to scrutinize the "subjective" genesis of relativistic ideas.
Let there be no misunderstanding. "Special relativity" and
"general relativity" are scientific theories; only by considering the
state of physical science at the beginning of the 19th century can
we understand the nature of these theories and evaluate their im¬
portance. If our only interest lies in the "progress" of knowledge
per se, we may even feel justified in ignoring (or condemning as
too anecdotic) all psychological or sociological contributions to the
history of science. The fact remains that Einstein himself was
always at pains to analyse his ideas and the influences he had
undergone.
Let us seriously consider the objection implied above that
science is essentially "objective", or at least is only of value insofar
as it is "objective". If this is so why deliberately place so much im¬
portance on the "subjectivity" of the scientist, even if his name is
Einstein? In other words, it would be ill-advised and even
dangerous to confuse art and science. Artists do not seek to
describe reality "as it is": they interpret it and reconstruct it ac¬
cording to the dictates of their sensitivity and imagination. But
scientists, we are given to understand, go about it quite different¬
ly; they prefer to silence their "subjectivity" and listen only to the
"voice of facts"; relying on a strict methodology they succeed in
establishing perfectly precise "laws of nature".
According to this view of science, what counts is that the con¬
cepts be precisely defined and workable and the results confirmed
experimentally. Scientific "geniuses" are, undoubtedly,
remarkable in their own way: but their work would seem to have
nothing "subjective" about it.
This approach has all the appearances of everyday common
sense. However, it may well conceal the difficulties inherent in the
notion of objectivity. No one would dream of denying that scien-
PIERRE THUILLIER, professor of the history of science at the University
of Lille III and the University of Paris VII, is a member of the editorial staff
of the French scientific periodical La Recherche. His interests in
epistemology (the theory and science of knowledge) and the broader
questions of the relations between science and society are reflected in his
Jeux et Enjeux de la Science (Games and Stakes of Science) published by
Robert Laffont, Paris, 1972.
tifie Statements must be able to stand up to experiment. But even
when the "verdict of the experiment" is favourable, can it really be
said that the theory's "objectivity" has been established?
In fact, only the value (or validity) of the theory has been con¬
firmed. Strictly speaking, a positive result does not prove that the
statements tested are absolutely "true". For another theory may
turn out to be as good or even better. In other words, one is never
sure of having complete and definitive knowledge of the "objects"
studied. Experiments can show that, in certain conditions and
within certain limits, a given theory explains phenomena. But they
do not prove that this knowledge is absolute and completely true.
Examples abound. Thus, for a long time it was thought that
Newton's mechanics offered a strictly accurate ("objective")
description of nature. But it is this very idea that the theory of
relativity calls into question. We must admit that science aims at
giving an objective description (or explanation) of phenomena. But
it would be going too far to assert that scientific theories, such as
they exist in reality, are wholly objective constructions, that is to
say, devoid of any "subjective" element. It is for this very reason
that theories are constantly evolving.
The approach adopted to the problem of subjectivity in science
is closely linked to the solutions given to certain purely
epistemological questions (questions concerning the nature and
value of scientific knowledge). Einstein himself was well aware of
this, as is attested by his analyses concerning the connexion bet¬
ween "facts" and "theories".
Newton, he said, believed that "the laws and basic concepts of
his system could be derived from experiment". But this is not so.
Contrary to what some empiricists think, "any attempt logically to
deduce concepts and fundamental postulates from elementary ex¬
periments is doomed to failure". In fact, the foundations of
theoretical physics must be "freely invented". Which means that
to develop their science physicists do not passively record sense
data, but build a theoretical framework with the aid of principles
and concepts that they have not only selected, but, as Einstein
repeated time and again, freely selected.
This view could be described as constructivisme. Not only does it
allow that the theoreticians' "subjectivity" is involved, it also ad¬
mits that this involvement is practically unavoidable and entirely
legitimate. True, some theories are better than others. But, as
Einstein observes, "there is no logical bridge between phenomena
and the principles intended to explain them". But if these prin¬
ciples do not stem from the phenomena, then what is their source?
Einstein's view can be summarized, as follows: although the
scientist seeks to give a "rational" ¡mage of the world, he has no
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Einstein at his desk at
Princeton University in
1948. When someone once
asked him where his
laboratory was he took a
fountain pen out of his
breast pocket and said :
"Here".
Photo © Parimage, Paris
access to unique and absolute Reason which will present him, in a
purely logical way, with the concepts and principles he needs. It is
by using their own resources and their own experiences that men
try to invent intellectual tools that are more or less suited to
"reality". So the genesis of scientific theories lies not only in logic
and epistemology, but in psychology, sociology and cultural
anthropology.
The so-called advanced societies propagate an image of science
which, more than anything, emphasizes its stringent, logical,
"objective" aspects. But Einstein, both by his declarations and his
scientific activity itself, gives us a wonderful opportunity to get a
better look at the reverse side of this ¡mage with its concomitant
emotions, flights of fancy, philosophical convictions, even
"mystical" passion.
We know that Einstein and Michèle Besso enjoyed a long
friendship. One day Besso's sister asked Einstein: "Why hasn't
Michèle made any major discovery in mathematics?" Einstein
laughingly replied: "But that's a very good sign. Michèle is a
humanist, a universal spirit, with too much interest in too many
things to become a monomaniac. Only a monomaniac gets what
one calls 'results'." Urged by Besso to explain, he went on: "I still
believe you would have developed significant ideas in the field of
science if you had been obsessive enough. A butterfly is not a
mole, but no butterfly should mind that".
And so it would be nice to know: to what extent was Einstein a
"mole", a "monomaniac"? What was the obsession that could
more or less directly engender special relativity and general
relativity? In answer Einstein suggests: the real scientist is totally
imbued with "cosmic religious feeling".
According to him, this is the third degree of religious life, the
first two being religion-fear and religion-morals, in that order. "I
maintain (...) that cosmic religiosity is the strongest, most noble
incentive to scientific research.. Only someone who can measure
the enormous efforts. and, even more,- the dedication without
which scientific creations opening up new ways cannot be
realized, is in a position to appreciate the strength of feeling which
alone can engender a work of this kind, detached from everyday
living. (...) It is cosmic religious feeling that gives man this
strength".
So on this point Einstein thinks very differently from the
positivists: "In our materialistic age, serious scientific researchers
are the only men who are deeply religious". Remarks like this are
two a penny in Einstein. Sometimes we even get the impression
that hé is rather overstating his idea: "I cannot imagine a genuine
scientist who does not have deep faith. The situation can be
summed up in a metaphor: science without religiop is lame,
religion without science is blind".
A few observations on this Einsteinian religion would not come
amiss. First of all, it has no connexion with religions which accept
the existence of a personal God who dispenses punishments and
rewards. Einstein feels that this sort of doctrine is impure and that
religions should reject it out of hand. True, the idea of a personal
God breeds hopes and fears and gives priests enormous power
over the minds of men. But in the long run it can only cause
"incalculable harm to the progress of mankind". Therefore
Einstein prefers to call himself a pantheist. To be religious is to
endeavour in all modesty to understand the order of the world.
In this way Einstein makes an almost systematic connexion
between the idea of "religion" and the idea that the world is
intelligible and rational. More precisely, the scientist must believe
that the world is so. If he is brave enough to dedicate himself to the
study of nature, it is precisely because he is convinced that nature
is constructed according to harmonious laws.
For Einstein this means, among other things, that everything is
determined by strict causality. The real scientist thinks "that causal
law determines all events", from which it is easy to understand
why he cannot accept the idea of a personal God, that is a being
who dictates the course of events. In his own way, Einstein is very
lucid. Instead of using causality as absolute evidence, he makes it k
the object of religious belief, of personal commitment. This*
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
From Empedocles to Newton: a constellation of
The work of the Greek philosopher Empedocles (490-430 BC) is a
milestone in the history of Western thought because, not relying on
the intervention of divine or supernatural forces, he imagined a
universe consisting of four basic substances fire, air, earth and
water combined in various proportions.
Like the ancient Babylonian astronomers whose observations
had come down to them, the Greeks of Antiquity believed that the
earth was the centre of the universe. This idea was central to the
work of the great astronomer Hipparchus, who around 150 BC
discovered the processional movement of the equinoxes. This
means that each year the so-called "equinoctial point" at which the
sun crosses the equator shifts slightly westward. The ideas of
Hipparchus were taken up and developed by Ptolemy (c.90-168 AD)
one of the greatest astronomers and geographers of Antiquity,
whose system of cosmology was to dominate Western thought for
over a thousand years.
His work is preserved in a compendium known as the Almagest,
a composite Greek-Arab term meaning "the greatest". In it
Ptolemy constructed an elaborate model of the heavens composed
of large circles, called deferents, and small circles, called epicycles.
Each planet rode on the circumference of an epicycle, the centre of
which revolved on the deferent. From the Hellenistic Age until the
Middle Ages, this system of epicycles and deferents remained,
with some modifications, "the last word in astronomy". The earth
was immovable, fixed by God in the centre of the universe beneath
the concave dome of the stars.
Then in the 15th century, the Polish doctor, jurist and astronomer
Nicolaus Copernicus (1473-1543) set out to perfect the Ptolemaic
system. However, as his studies progressed, he became
increasingly dissatisfied with Ptolemaic astronomy, and his
calculations were to lead him to a radically different picture of the
universe. Ptolemaic astronomy left certain phenomena
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
( evidently does not prevent him in practice from using the principle
of causality as a decisive criterion in evaluating scientific theories.
So it was that he consistently refused to recognize the
legitimacy of quantum mechanics. For "God does not play dice".
With this oft-repeated formula Einstein declared his faith in a rigid
determinism of natural phenomena. He could not accept "the
statistical craze" as evinced in the speculations of the Bohrs,
Borns, Heisenbergs and Paulis.
The major stumbling-block of quantum theory, in his view, is
that it does not provide a complete description of reality ; "pro¬
babilities" cannot be the last word in knowledge. The Eins¬
tein/Born correspondence is eloquent on this point: Born never
succeeded in shaking Einstein's "cosmic religion" Einstein found
it shocking that a particle might be considered not to behave in a
totally predictable way.
But the belief in universal causality is rather commonplace: it
could never on its own have "inspired" the theory of relativity. On
the other hand, it is quite remarkable that Einstein often defined his
"religious" position by contrasting "the inanity of man's longings
and objectives" with nature's "sublimity" and "wonderful order".
Individual existence is a "kind of prison". So the quest for
knowledge has a thoroughly fundamental significance: man, as an
individual, does not amount to much, but he has the capacity to
contemplate and understand the universal order. Through
knowledge "the individual endeavours to experience the universe
as an entity with a meaning". A religious man is a man who has, as
far as he can, freed himself of the trammels of selfish desires, and
turned towards thoughts, feelings and aspirations of supraperso¬
nal value.
In his Autobiographical Notes, Einstein returns to this theme:
we must "free ourselves from the shackles of the purely personal"
and endeavour to discover an "extra-personal world" which will
constitute a new paradise. Thus is established the existence of a
"real world", independent of ourselves, the contemplation of
which has (or will have) a liberating effect.
Einstein's epistemological realism, we see, is deeply and directly
rooted in his "subjectivity". And here we are in a position to ad¬
vance a crucial hypothesis: if Einstein worked out special relativity
and general relativity, it was precisely in order to enjoy a world that
is more real and more satisfactory than the poor world in which we
live from day to day.
What is in fact the essence of the "theory of relativity"? It is suf¬
ficient to read Einstein to realize that, despite its name, this theory
expresses the wish to find "laws of nature" the form of which re¬
mains constant regardless of the system of reference adopted.
Special relativity only applies to the Galilean systems, that is to.
say, systems in which there is validity for "the fundamental law
known as the law of inertia: a body sufficiently removed from other
bodies persists in its state of rest or uniform rectilinear motion".
The general theory of relativity can be expressed as follows: "All
systems of reference, regardless of their state of motion, are equal¬
ly valid in the formulation of the general laws of nature."
To put it more simply, let us say that the theory of relativity
represents the wish to find an image of the world independent of
the position of different observers. For some time now various
authors have been struck by the fact that a "postulate" of this sort
quite faithfully reflects Einstein's personal ideas mentioned earlier
on. Everything seems to point to the fact that relativistic physics is
the realization, in a particular field, of a more general programme:
to build a "suprapersonal" world, a world situated beyond our sen¬
sations and perceptions but possessing a superior reality.
The detractors Of the new theory were not mistaken; they clearly
perceived that relativistic speculations were by no means founded
on pure and simple "objectivity". So we have Christian Cor-
nelissen, in a little book published in Paris in 1923, deploring Eins¬
tein's hallucinations. He regretted that Einstein had taken certain
ideas "to the absurd" and "let himself stray into the realm of
metaphysics". In a way he was right! To dare to formulate such
theories, Einstein had to be (there is a tendency to forget this
nowadays) extraordinarily confident about various presuppositions
which were by no means evident. It is not surprising that less dar¬
ing minds than his at the turn of the century were hard put to share
this "faith".
Einstein displayed his originality in the article published in 1905 in
which he laid the foundations of the theory of relativity. But this
originality lay not so much in the novelty of the ideas he used as in
the way in which he deployed them.
The French mathematician Henri Poincaré had seen quite clearly
the new uses to which the "theory of relativity" could be put,
while the Dutch physicist Lorentz developed the "transformation"
which bears his name and the formalism of which was adopted
by Einstein. So much so that Sir Edmund Whittaker, an
Englishman and author of the authoritative History of the Theories
of Aether and Electricity, could attribute the theory of relativity to
Poincaré and Lorentz, which rather shocked Max Born. In fact, far
from being the fathers of this theory, neither Poincaré nor Lorentz
ever really accepted it. Whittaker's mistake is both a psychological
and an epistemological one: he underestimated Einstein's intellec¬
tual courage, what could be called his philosophico-scientific
radicalism.
For Poincaré probably understood the theory of relativity as well
as Einstein did. But he thought of it as being only "a convention
suggested by experience". Physicists, he said, could well do
without it. In other words, Poincaré hesitated to demolish the
classical theory. This sort of timidity is quite foreign to Einstein. He
makes no bones about it. He decides that the "theory of relativity"
is a sine qua non if one is to rebuild the theoretical edifice from
scratch. At least temporarily; it must not be called into question.
Therein lies all the difference between the two: Poincaré
adopted a conservative strategy while Einstein decided to pioneer
an entirely new path. Hence the importance of being a
"monomaniac". For intelligence was not enough to invent the
theory of relativity; one also had to be "mad" to select the new
bases despite their paradoxical nature.
In his 1905 article Einstein showed his audacity by admitting two
basic principles from the outset: the principle of relativity (which
has just been discussed) and the principle of the constancy of the
speed of light. It was all the more daring since, according to Eins¬
tein himself, these two principles were apparently incompatible.
This raised certain questions: how did Einstein get the idea of
asserting the constancy of the speed of light?
Many physicists and philosophers felt that Einstein had been led*
cosmologists
unexplained. Why, for example, did certain planets seem to stop
and move backwards and forwards in a loop ? Copernicus
audaciously wondered whether such movements of the planets
might not be explained in terms of the movement of the earth. "All
the visible movements of the sun and the planets", he wrote, "are
not thus in themselves but only as seen from the earth".
Copernicus' great treatise on the movements of the earth and the
other planets was not published until 1543, the year of its author's
death. It attracted immediate criticism and was soon put on the
Church's Index of prohibited books. It was many years before the
"Copernican revolution" became fully accepted.
The English physicist and mathematician Isaac Newton (1642-
1727) was one of the greatest figures in the scientific revolution of
the 17th century. In mathematics he was the discoverer of the
infinitesimal calculus, and in mechanics his three laws of motion.
the basic principles of modern physics, led to the formulation of the
law of universal gravitation. He erected a model of the universe
which, in the words of the scientific historian J. Bronowski,
"ticked on without a hitch for about two hundred years"; until, just
after 1900, "time and light began to go awry" and Einstein asked
himself "What would the world look like if I rode on a beam of
light ?"
Photo 1. Empedocles examining the Universe, by the 15th-
century Italian painter Luca Signorelli
Photo © Alinari, Florence
Photo 2. Sun, moon and planets turning around the earth in the
Ptolemaic system. Engraving by Cellarius (1661)
Taken from Harmonía macrocosmica by Andreas Cellarius, Amsterdam, 1961.
Photo 3. The Copernican system. A new astronomical vision of
the universe
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris.
Photo 4. Contemporary cartoon satirising Newton's theory of
gravitation
. Photo John Freeman Group © British Museum, London.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
.to this idea by the Michelson experiment (1881) and the Michelson-
Morley experiment (1887). At this time it was widely accepted that
light moved about in an absolutely motionless medium, the ether;
and that it should be possible to show the earth's motion through
this ether. It is unnecessary to go into Michelson's experiment in
detail here. Suffice it to say that he was working on light beams
and that what he hoped to show was the influence exerted on
them by the "ether wind".
But this hope failed to materialize as the mysterious ether proved
impossible to detect. The empiricist interpretation has it that it was
this experimental fact that inspired Einstein; by making a broad
generalization from it he was able to establish that light always
travelled at the same speed (and was therefore outside the sphere
of certain well-known laws of classical physics).
This interpretation is certainly debatable. First of all, it is clear
that various interpretations could be put on Michelson's experi¬
ment. Thus the Dutch physicist Lorentz followed up a suggestion
of the Irish physicist Fitzgerald and put forward an original ex¬
planation: "the ether wind" caused matter to contract, which
prevented any verification of the expected light effects. This
proves that the solution put forward by Einstein (the theory of the
constancy of the speed of light) had not been strictly based on
"facts".
Better still, we now know that Michelson's experiment was not a
determinant in Einstein's approach: "I can't say for certain when I
first heard of Michelson's experiment. I was not aware that it had
any direct influence on me". He made this point time and time
again: "Michelson's experiment played no part, or at least no
decisive part, in my personal struggle". On the other hand, we can
assume that some "subjective" influences intervened.
Einstein explains in his Autobiographical Notes that for ten years
he pondered a paradox which he had spotted at the age of sixteen.
It was a kind of "thought experiment" in which he asked himself
this question: what would happen if I pursued a beam of light
while I myself was travelling at a speed equal to the speed of light?
He suggested the following reply: "I would observe this beam as
an oscillatory electromagnetic field at rest".
But for more reasons than one he considered this to be impossi¬
ble; and for him this was a problem, an exciting paradox. "We
see", adds Einstein, "that the germ of the special theory of relativi¬
ty is already present in this paradox". This confirms that Einstein
had been mentally prepared for some time to manipulate some
basic problems in order to get certain concepts to work.
Naturally, he was conversant with the results of various ex¬
periments. Hethought that, generally speaking, physics should be
developed in contact with experiment and validated by it as far as
possible. But the theory of relativity was not conceived in order to
resolve the difficulties arising out of a particular experiment. It was
the outcome of a much more general and much more theoretical
development.
It was another problem that gave birth to special relativity: the
lack of symmetry of action between electrical conductors and
magnets. In fact if we use the Scottish physicist James Clerk Max¬
well's theory of electricity and magnetism we have to resort to two
different interpretations to explain what happens: 1) when a con¬
ductor is moved in relation to a magnet at rest and 2) when the
same magnet is moved in relation to a conductor at rest. For Eins¬
tein this was nothing less than scandalous. In an unpublished
manuscript he wrote that he found this asymmetry "intolerable".
We must remember, however, that Maxwell's theory takes into ac¬
count the results of experimentation.
But Einstein is guided by aesthetic conviction: since in reality the
only thing that counts is the relative motion of the magnet and the
conductor, the theory must also be symmetrical.The first sentence
of the 1905 article is quite explicit: "We all know that Maxwell's
electrodynamics, as understood today, when applied to a body in
motion, leads to asymmetries which do not appear to be inherent
in the phenomena".
This brings us once more to Einstein's "subjectivity", to his need
to find (and at any rate postulate) a harmonious order in the
universe. He repeatedly resorted to aesthetic considerations to
work out his theoretical conceptions. For that is what "cosmic
religion" is all about: it demands as elegant an explanation as
possible (that is, with as few basic statements as possible) of the
largest possible number of phenomena. So Einstein's
"rationalism" is very deeply rooted; it is nurtured and guided by
personal ideas, personal ¡mages and personal emotions.
To a question put to him by Jacques Hadamard during an in¬
vestigation on invention in mathematics, Einstein replied: "Words
and languages, whether spoken or written, seem to play no part in
my thought process. The psychic entities which serve as elements
to thought are reasonably clear signs or images which can be
reproduced and combined 'at will'. There naturally exists a certain
relationship between these elements and the logical concepts in¬
volved". In his Autobiographical Notes Einstein returned to the
subject: "In my opinion, there is no doubt that our thought func¬
tions mostly without using signs (words) and that, what is more, it
functions unconsciously for the most part."
The implications of such observations are wider than are at first
apparent. In fact, it could well be that the use of "thought in im¬
ages" was effective in helping Einstein to think out the concepts of
time and space in an original way. This statement certainly has the
merit of going straight to the point: "I sometimes wonder how it is
that I was the only person to develop the theory of relativity? I
think the reason is that a normal adult doesn't bother about
problems posed by space and time. He assumes that he has known
all he knows about it from infancy. But I, on the contrary,
developed so slowly that I only oegan to ask myself questions
about time and space after I was grown up. As a result, I was able
to go more deeply into the heart of the problem than a child who
had developed normally would have done." In other words, it is a
stroke of luck that, as his biographers confirm, Albert Einstein as a
child experienced difficulty in speaking.
Deep down, what did the baby Einstein's refusal to speak in¬
dicate if not resistance to certain cognitive schema imposed by
Zurich as it was
in the early years
of this century
when Einstein was
a professor there.
Photo © Zurich
City Archives
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
society? A "successful" education is an education which makes
people accept as natural a number of concepts about, and inter¬
pretations of, "reality". So it is also by definition an education
which makes those who receive it conform; and which deprives
them of the possibility of challenging the generally implicit presup¬
positions which are the basis of the knowledge it transmits.
Another idea dear to Einstein was that certain difficulties
presented by a cognitive system can only be resolved if the more or
less arbitrary and fortuitous bases for the system are first grasped.
A mind that has been too well socialized and too well moulded
cannot have the necessary detachment. So the critical approach
which gave birth to the theory of relativity was only possible
thanks to true intellectual autonomy. From this point of view, it is
important to emphasize that Einstein had adopted an attitude of
detachment with regard to generally accepted ideas. In his own
words, he had arrived at "positively fanatical free thought", which
manifested itself in the form of "suspicion of all forms of authority
and scepticism about convictions in vogue in any social context".
Various historians have also observed that, in his youth, Einstein
lived in an, atmosphere that did not encourage intellectual conven¬
tionalism. He received his higher education at the Zurich
Polytechnic, and he was working in the Berne Patent Office when
he wrote his 1905 article on relativity. At this time, Switzerland
"was opening its doors to a cosmopolitan crowd of students,
émigré revolutionaries and young people who had fled national or
social oppression rampant in their countries". Zurich around 1900
was "a huge permanent club".
Let us mention some important names: Rosa Luxembourg,
George Plekhanov, Mussolini, Karl Radek, Lenin. Discussions
were as numerous as they were heated; and not only about
politics, but about epistemology and psychoanalysis. Einstein was
fond of describing himself as a "heretic", and these details about
his life help us understand the theoretical daring which enabled
him to put forward such novel ideas.
Before we close, let us look at the problem posed by the now
commonplace expression: theory of relativity. Few labels have in¬
spired so many misconceptions as if this relativity had anything
to do with relativism or subjectivism. In fact, it would be better to
talk, as Minkowski suggested, of the "postulate of the absolute
world". This would be less misleading.
True, according to Einstein's theory, our measurements of
space are relative, as are our measurements of time. Which means
that they depend on the observer's point of view; and that there is
no such thing as a privileged observer. But the famous "space-
time" is in itself something absolute; it expresses in theoretical
form the existence of a "reality" which is not directly accessible,
but in relation to which all individual ("local") observations take on
specific significance.
The expression "theory of relativity" does not in fact appear in
the title of Einstein's works prior to 1911. He preferred to speak
about "theory of invariants" (Invariententheorie) and, in 1928, he
said that the theory of relativity would be more accurately called
"theory of covariance" (that is, the principle that demands that all
basic equations keep the same form in all systems of reference).
Why then did he finally agree to a label that was misleading, to
say the least? Doubtless, even here psychological factors played
their part. To speak of "relativity" is to recall that the Newtonian
absolutes were dead; there is no absolute space, there is no ab¬
solute simultaneity. This label underlined the mutation worked out.
by Einstein, a mutation which many scientists and laymen con¬
sidered "revolutionary". As the historian L.S. Feuer put it, the
word relativity is in keeping with the spirit of the time and, more
precisely, with the spirit that was at large in Zurich and in Berne.
Pierre Thuillier
The frontiers
of science
by Arkadii B. Migdal
THE transformation of an idea into an
accepted scientific truth, of a hypo¬
thesis into a rigorously formulated
physical law, is a long and often tortuous
process. But is it possible to retrace the
various steps in this process? And what ex¬
actly is the difference between the scien¬
tific assessment of a phenomenon and the
comprehension of it that common sense
dictates?
ARKADII B. MIGDAL, noted Soviet theoreti¬
cal physicist, is a member of the USSR Aca¬
demy of Sciences and adviser to the Academy's
Landau Institute of Theoretical Physics. A spe¬
cialist in the field of the theory of elementary
particles and atomic nuclei, he is the author of
over 150 scientific papers and five longer stu¬
dies. His Qualitative Methods in Quantum
Theory was published in the USA in 1977 by
Benjamin-Cummings Publishing Co., Menlo
Park, California.
The first step in any scientific undertak¬
ing is to draw up the boundaries which
mark off the area of indisputably establish¬
ed scientific truths from the area of "im¬
possibilities" which conflict with the data
yielded by repeated scientific experiment.
Between the two lies a no-man's-land em¬
bracing phenomena which have not been
studied but which, a priori, seem to lie
within the bounds of the possible.
In our time the frontiers of the possible
have been pushed back so far that they
merge into those of wonderland. Men cir¬
cle the earth in spacelabs for months at a
time. Televiewers can watch a sporting
event while it is taking place thousands of
kilometres away. Equally miraculous, com¬
puters can play chess, translate, write
verse and above all carry out in a matter of
minutes calculations which would other¬
wise take years.
It is tempting to ask whether science
knows its limits, and to wonder whether a
scientific revolution may not lie ahead,
which will turn our ideas upside down. The
history of science and epistemology rule
out the possibility of such an upheaval.
Even the astonishing concepts of the
theory of relativity did not constitute a total
revolution; they were a consequence of
scientific evolution, solidly based on earlier
scientific discoveries. Furthermore, they
only affected a relatively limited number of
problems and did not change the existing
laws of mechanics and the electrodynamics
of bodies moving at normal speeds.
What happened was that our knowledge
was extended in the then unstudied field of
speeds near to that of light. Before the
theory of relativity was developed, it was
logical to suppose that the laws of j
mechanics and electrodynamics were valid I
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
at speeds higher than those for which they
had been established experimentally.
Doubts only emerged when this
hypothesis was contradicted by scientific
experiments. This is the usual path of
scientific progress.
Science, it has been said, is the product
of truth multiplied by doubt. At the begin¬
ning of the nineteenth century, descrip¬
tions of meteors, "celestial stones", were
dismissed by many scientists as the fruits
of fantasy. Stones, after all, could not drop
from the sky. Such a refusal to accept the
inexplicable is highly dangerous and often
leads to error.
Many examples could be cited of the
way in which preconceived opinions have
slowed the development of science. The il¬
lustrious inventor of the theory of relativity
himself made a mistake of this kind, draw¬
ing a false conclusion from a preconceived
idea when he attempted to establish an en¬
tirely new cosmology.
After demonstrating that the laws of
Euclidian geometry were not valid in the
vicinity of a large mass, Einstein wished to
take a new and staggeringly audacious step
forward. He applied his theory of the
gravitational field to the universe, replac¬
ing, as is the practice in the study of a gas,
the real distribution of masses in space
with the notion of the average density of
matter.
It transpired that the equations of
gravitation for a universe such as ours did
not admit a static solution. To achieve a
solution corresponding to his description of
a finite universe whose radius of curvature
was independent of time, Einstein artificial¬
ly introduced into the gravitational equa¬
tions an additional factor which upset their
harmony.
Around the same time, an outstanding
Petrograd mathematician named Alex¬
ander Friedmann was studying various
possibilities of solving Einstein's equations
without introducing this new factor. He
came to the conclusion that the universe is
expanding and that beside the "closed"
model, there can exist for certain values of
average mass density, an "open" model in
which the dimensions of the universe in¬
crease indefinitely. At first Einstein was
critical of Friedmann's work, but later came
round entirely to his position and rejected
the introduction of an additional factor in
the gravitation equations.
"After reading Friedmann's letter, which
Mr. Krutkov [a famous Soviet theoretical
physicist] communicated to me", wrote
Einstein, "I am now convinced that my
criticisms were based on an error of
calculation. I consider that Friedmann's
results are correct and throw a new light on
the question." Friedmann learned of the
existence of this text shortly before his
premature death in 1925. His solution was
later confirmed experimentally when the
U.S. astronomer Edwin Hubble
demonstrated that the galaxies appear to
be moving away from each other.
Several cases of scientific error have
been analysed and methodological conclu¬
sions drawn from them, the most
unassailable being that scientists should
avoid taking up categorical positions in in¬
sufficiently studied fields. When scientific
errors occur today, they are soon rectified.
Science does not, however, confine
itself to defining the bounds of the possi¬
ble, it also rigorously sorts out hypotheses,
even the most likely ones, from
demonstrated propositions. In this way it
draws attention to propositions which re¬
quire further research. It is possible to
believe, for example, that the earth has
been visited by emissaries from another
world, but scientists have no grounds for
affirming that this is so.
This weeding out process, disagreeable
though it may often be for the scientist,
has the effect of highlighting certain
phenomena which though apparently
strange are in fact real. Such a
phenomenon is the "twin paradox". Ac¬
cording to the theory of relativity, if one of
a pair of twins were to go on a journey in a
spaceship travelling at a speed approaching
that of light, when he returned he would be
younger than his brother who had remain¬
ed on earth. This astonishing affirmation
has been demonstrated not only
theoretically but experimentally. Time
measured during a space flight by a high-
precision atomic clock is less than that
shown by an identical clock which remains
on earth.
Here is another example of a peculiar
phenomenon which is nevertheless authen¬
tic. It has always been thought that marine
animal and plant life only exist near the
ocean surface where the sunlight can
penetrate and make photosynthesis possi¬
ble. However, volcanic areas of seabed, in¬
accessible to sunlight, have recently been
discovered several kilometres beneath the
surface where temperatures are high and in
which specific forms of animal and plant
life subsist, possibly as a result of pro¬
cesses of chemical synthesis.
It cannot be said of such phenomena
that "I'd like to believe in them but there
are no grounds for doing so". The expres¬
sion "no grounds" signifies that the ques¬
tion has been studied and that initial con¬
jectures have turned out to be unjustified.
To put the scientific approach into a nut¬
shell: "one would like to believe" in a given
proposition, but if "there are no grounds"
for doing so then it must be rejected.
Human nature is such that mankind
spontaneously aspires, not only to the
beautiful but also to the mysterious and the
unusual. In Pushkin's words, "an illusion
which exalts us is dearer than the shadows
of shabby truths". I would add to
Pushkin's words the following remark by
Einstein: "The most beautiful thing that we
can experience is the mysterious". For
Einstein the sense of mystery lies at the
root of the fundamental tendencies of art
and science. Alas, the same aspiration
towards the mysterious is at the origin of
much unscientific thought.
The task of science is to select the most
likely explanations and to stick to them un¬
til experimental results demand that others
be found. This does not mean that there
should be an embargo on research into
unlikely phenomena. As the U.S. physicist
Richard Feynman pointed out: "One of the
surest ways to stop scientific progress is to
limit experimentation to fields in which the
laws have already been discovered".
The following hypothesis, which is both
simple and convincing, was adopted by
science long ago. The processes which
operate in nature are governed, in the last
analysis, by the same laws which govern
interactions in experimental physics. Until
The twin
Drawings studic Philippe Gentil © Unesco Courier
^r-S^^
m ; JB
Y 1
m il II T H
W\\}\ V3 J
FH
mW'gf
r s
(^ ,»-
te $tW
mmym
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
now this hypothesis has never been dis¬
proved; in fact it has shown itself to be so
fertile that it has explained such a mys¬
terious phenomenon as heredity.
The different branches of the exact
sciences have many procedures in com¬
mon. Methods exist, for example, which
can prove an idea to be false even before
research into it is begun. But the most im¬
portant factor, without which success will
elude even the most brilliantly gifted scien¬
tist, is the capacity for enthusiasm and
astonishment at even the smallest achieve¬
ment, and for approaching science with the
veneration Einstein described when he
wrote: "Full of astonishment, I simply
make conjectures about mysteries and
humbly try to paint a mental picture, which
is far from being complete, of the perfect
structure of the being".
Arkadii B. Migdal
paradox
The assertion of the relativity theory that
time and distance are not absolute values,
but are dependent upon the relative
motion of observers, and that the only
absolute constant is the speed of light
leads to some apparently very bizarre
conclusions about events occurring at
ultra-high speeds. For example, to a man
standing on a launching pad and watching
a spacecraft moving away at a speed
approaching that of light, a clock in the
spacecraft (if he could see it) would
appear to be moving very slowly. To the
space-traveller looking back it would be
time on earth that appeared to be slowed
down. This apparent contradiction gave
rise to a famous brain teaser known as
the "twin paradox". If the man on the
ground and the space-traveller were
twins, what difference, if any, would
there be in their ages on the return of the
spacecraft to earth ? Ultra-high-speed
travel, it seems, helps to keep you young.
Einstein showed that, because of other
relativistic effects, including, for instance,
the effect of acceleration on the space-
travelling twin involved in turning the
spacecraft and bringing it back to earth,
the astronaut would age more slowly than
his stay-at-home twin. The English
astrophysicist Herbert Dingle, however,
maintained that this conclusion was
absurd. If, as the theory of relativity
states, there Is no absolute movement,
only movement in relation to other
objects, it could be argued that the
spacecraft had remained motionless and
that the earth had moved away from it at
great speed and then returned. In this
case the earthbound twin would be the
younger. But, obviously, both brothers
cannot be younger than each other. There
is, however, a fundamental difference
between the relative movement of the
astronaut twin and that of the stay-at-
home. If the earth were said to move
away from the spacecraft, the entire
universe would have to move with it. In
other words, the earth would remain
motionless in relation to the universe and
the relativistic effects associated with
acceleration would still only apply to the
twin in the spacecraft. So after all high
speed travel does keep you young.
Albert Einstein and Robert Oppenheimer. In 1943 Oppenheimer was appointed director of
the Los Alamos Atomic Research Laboratory where the first nuclear bomb was
developed, and in 1947 became director of the Institute for Advanced Study at Princeton.
"Einstein is often blamed or praised or credited with these miserable bombs,"
Oppenheimer wrote. "It is not in my opinion true... His part was that of creating an
intellectual revolution, and discovering more than any scientist of our time how profound
were the errors made by men before them... Einstein himself is really not answerable for
all that came later."
The
scientist's
dilemma
by Albert Einstein
WE are living in a period of such
great external and internal in¬
security and with such a lack of
firm objectives that the mere confession of
our convictions may be of significance
even if these convictions, as all value
judgements, cannot be proven through
logical deductions.
There arises at once the question: should
we consider the search for truthor, more
modestly expressed, our efforts to under¬
stand the knpwable universe through
constructive logical thought as an
autonomous objective of our work? Or
should our search for truth be subordinated
to some other objective, for example to a
"practical" one? This question cannot be
decided on a logical basis. The decision.
however, will have considerable influence
upon our thinking and our moral judge¬
ment, provided that it is born out of deep
and unshakeable conviction. Let me then
make a confession: for myself, the struggle
to gain more insight and understanding is
one of those independent objectives
without which a thinking individual would
find it impossible to ha"ve a conscious,
positive attitude towards life.
It is the very essence of our striving for
understanding that on the one hand, it at¬
tempts to encompass the great and com¬
plex variety of man's experience, and that
on the other, it looks for simplicity and
economy in the basic assumptions. The
belief that these two objectives can exist k
side by side is, in view of the primitive state f
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
of our scientific knowledge, a matter of
faith. Without such faith I could not have a
strong and unshakeable conviction about
the independent value of knowledge.
This, in a sense, religious attitude of a
man engaged in scientific work has some
influence upon his whole personality. For
apart from the knowledge which is offered
by accumulated experience and from the
rules of logical thinking, there exists in prin¬
ciple for the man in science no authority
whose decisions and statements could
have in themselves a claim to "Truth". This
leads to the paradoxical situation that a
person who devotes all his strength to ob¬
jective matters will develop, from a social
point of view, into an extreme individualist
who, at least in principle, has faith in
nothing but his own judgement. It is quite
possible to assert that intellectual in¬
dividualism and the thirst for scientific
knowledge emerged simultaneously in
history and remained inseparable ever
since.
Someone may suggest that the man of
science as sketched in these sentences is
no more than an abstraction which actually
does not exist in this world, not unlike the
homo oeconomicus of classical economics.
However, it seems to me that science as
we know it today could not have emerged
and could not have remained alive if many
individuals, during many centuries, had not
come very close to the ideal.
Of course, not everybody who has learn¬
ed to use tools and methods which, direct¬
ly or indirectly, appear to be "scientific" is
to me a man of science. I refer only to,
those individuals in whom the scientific
mentality is truly alive.
What then, is the position of today's
man of science as a member of society? He
obviously is rather proud of the fact that
the work of scientists has helped to change
radically the economic life of men by
almost completely eliminating muscular
work. He is distressed by the fact that the
results of his scientific work have created a
threat to mankind since they have fallen in¬
to the hands of morally blind exponents of
political power. He is conscious of the fact
that technological methods, made possible
by his work, have led to a concentration of
economic and also of political power in the
hands of small minorities which have come
to dominate completely the lives of the
masses of people, who appear more and
more amorphous. But even worse: the
concentration of economic and political
power in the hands of a few has not only
made the man of science dependent
economically, it also threatens his in¬
dependence from within; the shrewd
methods of intellectual and psychic in¬
fluences which it brings to bear will prevent
the development of independent per¬
sonalities.
Thus the man of science, as we can
observe with our own eyes, suffers a truly
tragic fate. Striving in great sincerity for
clarity and inner independence, he himself,
through his sheer superhuman efforts, has
fashioned the tools which are being used to
make him a slave and to destroy him also
from within. He cannot escape being
muzzled by. those who have political power
in their hands. As a soldier he is forced to
sacrifice his own life and to destroy the
Relativity
and
the atom
According to the relativity theory,
the mass of an object increases
with its velocity (see drawing
page 14). In the everyday world
velocities are much too low for us
to notice the effects of relativity,
but in the world of the atom
smasher, or nuclear accelerator,
relativistic effects become very
noticeable indeed. Atom smashers
are huge machines in which
atomic particles are accelerated to
fantastic speeds. At the Linear
Accelerator Center at Stanford,
California (aerial view, right)
electrons are accelerated so close
to the speed of light that their
mass is increased 40,000 times. At
the end of the 3,050-metre-long
installation is a storage ring where
the particles are smashed into one
another, creating new matter.
Scientists can observe colliding
particles in detail using a "bubble
chamber" containing a special
superheated liquid under pressure.
The particles, which are too small
to be seen are shot through the
liquid and create strings of tiny
bubbles which, when
photographed, enable scientists to
measure the mass and other
properties of the invisible
particles. Top photo, far right,
shows traces made by particles in
the "Gargamelle" bubble chamber
of CERN (European Council for
Nuclear Research) in Geneva.
Lower photo, view of
"Gargamelle's" observation
portholes. Accurate
measurements can be made of
the conversion of the energy of
motion Into matter and mass
which confirm Einstein's famous
equation expressing the
equivalence of mass and energy,
E = mcJ.
lives of others even when he is convinced
of the absurdity of such sacrifices. He is
fully aware of the fact that universal
destruction is unavoidable since historical
development has led to the concentration
of all economic, political and military power
in the hands of national States. He also
realizes that mankind can only be saved if a
super-national system, based on law,
would be created to eliminate for all time
the methods of brute force. However, the
man of science has slipped so much that he
accepts the slavery inflicted upon him by
national States as his inevitable fate. He
even degrades himself to such an extent
that he helps obediently in the perfection of
the means for the general destruction of
mankind.
Is there really no escape for the man of
science? Must he really tolerate and suffer
all these indignities?
Is the time gone for ever when, aroused
by his inner freedom and the independence
of his thinking and his work, he had a
chance of enlightening and enriching the
lives of his fellow-human beings? In placing
his work too much on an intellectual basis,
has he not forgotten about his responsibili¬
ty and dignity? My answer is: while it is true
that an inherently free and scrupulous per¬
son may be destroyed, such an individual
can never be enslaved or used as a blind
tool.
If the man of science of our day could
find the time and the courage to think
honestly and critically over his situation and
the tasks before him and if he would act ac¬
cordingly, the possibilities for a sensible
and satisfactory solution of the present
dangerous international situation would be
considerably improved.
Albert Einstein
This article is a slightly abridged version of
a message read before the forty-third
meeting of the Italian Society for the Ad¬
vancement of the Sciences in 1950.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Medal
for
Einstein Centenary
To commemorate the hundredth anniversary of Albert
Einstein's birth on 14 March 1879, Unesco has issued a
medal minted in gold, silver and bronze. The work of the
French engraver Max Léognany, the medal (above)
shows on one side the scientist in his later years, with
the inscription 1879 ALBERT EINSTEIN 1955 - UNESCO
1979. On the other side a silhouette of Einstein's head
forms the background for three of the mathematical
equations that sum up Einstein's essential contributions
to physics. The best-known equation, E = mc2,
established a fixed, quantitative relationship between
energy (E) and matter (m) as determined by the square of
the speed of light. The second equation symbolizes the
results of Einstein's research on the law of the photo¬
electric effect, for which he was awarded the Nobel
Prize for physics in 1921. The third stems from his work
on the theory of relativity. Einstein is the first man of
modern times to be honoured in Unesco's "Anniversaries
of Great Men" series, in which medals have already been
dedicated to Aristotle, Michelangelo and Rubens. The
medals, struck by the Paris Mint, are also available with
a chain-ring for wear as jewellery. They can be obtained
from : the Philatelic and Numismatic Programme of
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Photo Michel Claude, Unesco
Further reading
on Einstein
Einstein: A Centenary Volume, edited by A. P. French. Pub¬
lished by Heinemann, London, for the International Commission
on Physics Education, 1979. (Initiated by Unesco, the centenary
volume project was carried out with Unesco co-operation and
financial support).
Einstein's Universe, by Nigel Calder. Published by the British
Broadcasting Corporation, 1979.
Albert Einstein and Relativity, by D.J. Raine, Priory Press
Ltd., London, 1975.
Einstein and the Generations of Science, by Lewis S. Feuer,
Basic Books, Inc., New York, 1974.
Relativity for the Layman, by James A. Coleman, Penguin
Books, Harmondsworth, Middlesex, U.K. Revised edition 1969.
Relativity and Common Sense, by Hermann Bondi. Hejne-
mann, London, 1965. Reprinted 1978.
The Einstein Century : Four Generations of Revolutionary
Thought is the theme of Unesco's scientific quarterly Impact of
Science on Society, Vol. 29, No. 1 (Jan.-March 1979).
The Ascent of Man, by J. Bronowskl. British Broadcasting Cor¬
poration, 1973.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Stars, strings,
shadows and spheres
Einstein playing the violin. Drawing by the Russian
artist Leonid Pasternak (1862-1945)
Photo Studio Edmark © Mrs. Lydia Pasternak Slater. Oxford, U.K.
When Einstein was in Hollywood in 1931, Charlie Chaplin invited him
and his wife to attend the première of the film City Lights. During the
drive to the town they were recognized by the crowd and
enthusiastically cheered. Chaplin calmly remarked to his guest : "The
people are applauding you because none of them understands you and
applauding me because everybody understands me."
Genius in silhouette. Cut-outs of Einstein and his family made
by the great man himself in 1919.
Taken from Einstein, A Centenary Volume, edited by A. P. French,
Heinemann Educational Books Ltd., London
Scientists today are using high-precision engineering to test
Einstein's theories to increasingly accurate limits. Here, a
perfectly round (to within a millionth of an inch) sphere of
quartz the size of a tennis ball is being checked at Stanford
University in California in preparation for an ingenious test of
General Relativity. Sometime in the 1980s four such spheres
will be set spinning as gyroscopes in a spacecraft orbiting the
earth. The experiment is designed to detect the very slight
dragging of space by the rotation of the earth.
34
BRODARD GRAPHIQUE. COULOMMIERS. - Dépôt légal C 1 - Mai 1979 - IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France!.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published by Unesco
Soil Map of the World
Prepared by the Food and Agriculture
Organization of the United Nations
(FAO) and Unesco in co-operation with
the International Society of Soil Science
Covers all continents identifies 106
soil units according to composition,
texture and slope of the landscape,
employing 18 base colours ten
volumes of explanatory texts (250-300
pages each) accompany the 18 sheets
(115x82 cm each)
Various purchasing formulae are
offered. Prospective buyers should
apply to their national distributor for
Unesco publications (see below) for
price in local currency.
Unesco also publishes:
maps Metamorphic maps Quaternary maps Mineral and metallogenic
maps Hydrogeological maps Climatic maps Vegetation maps Océanographie
maps
For further information about Unesco maps and atlases, please write to: Unesco
Publishing Services, Unesco, Place Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors In countries not lis¬
ted, along with subscription rates In local cur¬
rency, win be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victorial, 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschapplj' Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CHINA. China National Publications Import Corpora¬
tion, West Europe Department, P.O. Box 88, Peking.
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L, Spalena
51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranlcni literatura, 11 Sou-
kenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DENMARK.
Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK 1165, Copenha¬
gen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Tahrir Square,
Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box
2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10. - FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. -
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach
140, 710 Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the
G.D.R. - FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific
maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830.
Other publications: S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung,
Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen,. Swindon Book Co., 13-
15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HÜNGARY. Akadémiai"
Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok
Boltja, Népkoztársasag utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna
Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1 ;
80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House,
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001.
- INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza Avenue, P.O. Box
314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave.
Iranchahr Chomall No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. - IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286,
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling
Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street,
Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco
Koerler" Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat
71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskle Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courler: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. -
SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030 Dares-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co.
Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box
402, Bangkok: Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern
Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission
for Unesco, 18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I.
TURKEY." Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesl, Beyoglu,
Istambul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops In
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South,
New York, N.Y. 10010. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
May 1979
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
fromnews
unesco
Scientists Note
Gradual Progress
in Earthquake
Predictions
Frioul, Italy : damage from the
earthquake of 6 May 1976.
Although gradual progress has been
made in improving earthquake
prediction, scientists still do not have a
general theory to explain why an
earthquake occurs in a particular place
at a particular time.
Nor, said the chairman of a Unesco
symposium on the subject, can they
predict with much accuracy the
magnitude of earth tremors.
Nevertheless, he added, many lives have
been saved through successful
predictions in past years, especially in
China, and "the experience and the
success of China in this field is one of
the main causes for optimism that
effective earthquake prediction will be
possible elsewhere."
Dr. Frank F. Evison, of the Institute
of Geophysics, Victoria University of
Wellington, New Zealand, was speaking
at a press conference during a week-long
International Symposium on Earthquake
Prediction, held at Unesco
Headquarters, Paris.
The progress which has been made
in recent years, he suggested, has
consisted in compiling additional
observations and additional data
concerning about 15 types of earthquake
"precursors" natural phenomena and
anomalies which had already been
known to precede major earthquakes.
"The situation at present," he said,
"is that we're waiting to test out
hypotheses about earthquake
predictions. But this requires not only
more observations and more data but
more earthquakes taking place, unless
and until a major theoretical
breakthrough occurs."
Dr. Tsuneji Rikitake, of the
department of applied physics of the
Tokyo Institute of Technology, pointed
out, however, that China had
successfully predicted four out of five
major earthquakes (those with a
magnitude of more than 7 on the
Richter scale) in the years 1975 and
1976. These "imminent" predictions
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
(ranging from a few days to about 20
minutes) had enabled many lives to be
saved in the case of one earthquake, at
least. The others had occurred in
sparsely settled regions of China.
Japan itself has a budget for
earthquake prediction this year of some
$ 36 million, according to Dr. Makane
Simizu, of the office for earthquake
prediction of the Science and
Technology Agency, Tokyo.
Furthermore it is spending about
$ 3.5 billion a year for mitigation of
earthquake hazards, including seismic
engineering programmes. Japan has also
developed sophisticated machinery for
translating earthquake predictions into
governmental decisions. Thanks to these
procedures, an earthquake warning can
be issued, if necessary, about two hours
after the initial detection by scientists of
a geodetic anomaly.
If progress has been gradual in
earthquake prediction methods,
however, research on the social and
economic effects of earthquake
predictions and warnings is only in its
initial stages, said Dr. Ralph H. Turner
of the Department of sociology of the
University of California at Los Angeles.
"Developing earthquake predictions
is only half the job," he said. "You
have to know how to make the best use
of them, and this is where social science
research comes in. The effectiveness of
earthquake prediction as a tool for
reducing hazards depends upon
developing community response plans
that can be implemented when
predictions are issued. The development
of such plans depends in turn on
understanding how individuals and
groups will respond to the news of an
earthquake warning."
Systematic research in this area
began only about three or four years
ago, Dr. Turner said. Before that,
social scientists depended on what they
knew about behaviour in other types of
catastrophes. Even now, knowledge is
quite incomplete and based mainly on
studies in Japan and the United States.
What is known, however, "is
enough to put to rest the more bizarre
fears of mass panic and wildly irrational
response to earthquake prediction. Most
people tend to continue life as normal,
whenever they can."
Communication Commission Studies
Technology and Media Impact on Development
Communication media in India play
an important role in promoting
development objectives, but are biased
toward politics (rather than economics),
middle class interests, a male public and
the urban population.
This emerged from a discussion by
Indian specialists at a Unesco-sponsored
round-table discussion on
communication and development in
New Delhi in March. The round-table
was held in conjunction with the fifth
session of the International Commission
for the Study of Communication
Problems and members of the
Commission also took part.
During a second round-table, on the
theme of communication and
technology, experts from Canada, India,
Japan, USA, USSR and Yugoslavia
presented papers on the implications of
the technological revolution for
communication.
The 16-member Commission, headed
by the former foreign minister of
Ireland, Mr. Sean MacBride, is
preparing a final report for submission
to Unesco by the end of this year. At its
New Delhi meeting it gave particular
attention to two papers prepared by
members of the Commission : one by
Mr Johannes Pieter Pronk of the
Netherlands on the implications of the
new international economic order on the
diffusion of information ; and a paper
by Mr. Elie Abel (USA) on
"Communication for an interdependent,
pluralistic world," which was discussed
at length.-
Mr. Abel's paper set out areas in
which the Commission might take
concrete decisions and other issues of
political sensitivity which, it argued,
were not likely to yield a consensus.
During the discussions it emerged
that Commission members did not feel
that communication technology was
"value free" or neutral; questions like
access, control, cost and manpower had
to be taken into account. Members also
expressed the view that the choice of
technology could not be made by
technicians alone without directions
from governments. There was general
agreement on the need to reduce
telecommunication tariffs, to make access
to communication satellite services easier
and to bring about speedy transfer of
technology from the rich to the poor
nations.
Another topic discussed during the
fifth session was the protection of
journalists. This important subject was
previously debated with some
international jurists and journalists'
organizations, leaving it to professional
associations and interested circles to
inform the Commission of the results of
further consultations. Some members
felt that no special protection was
needed, others that the nature of the
profession called for permanent
guarantees.
The Commission decided to meet
again from 4 to 8 June, when it will
consider particularly the question of
culture and communication, as well as
continuing the debate on the outline of
the final report.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Director-General addressing the
United Nations Committee on the
Elimination of Racial Discrimination. At the
right is Mr. George O. Lamptey (Ghana),
chairman of the committee.
Photo Unesco - Michel Claude
Peace Depends on
Ending Racism,
M'Bow Tells U.N.
Committee
World peace requires not only better
understanding among nations and real
disarmament but also a victory over
poverty and racial and social
segregation, the Unesco Director-
General told a U.N. committee meeting
at Unesco Headquarters.
Speaking at the opening of the 19th
session of the United Nations
Committee on the Elimination of Racial
Discrimination, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow declared that "nothing is more
urgent than to mobilize the vital forces
of all humanity to battle the scourges
which menace mankind and to struggle
against racism and racial prejudice,
everywhere and in every way, so as to
erase them from the memory of every
child, every woman and every man."
Tracing the history of Unesco's
action in this field, the Director-General
noted that it had been given new
impetus by the Declaration on Race and
Racial Prejudice adopted by
acclamation at the last General
Conference of Unesco. The Declaration,
he said, "constitutes a coherent
synthesis of all the challenges raised by
racism biological, sociological and
judicial, as well as cultural, political,
economic and ethical. It constitutes a
reference instrument all the more
important since its moral force was
enhanced by its unanimous adoption by
the representatives of all Member
States."
The main task of the Committee on
the Elimination of Racial Discrimination
is to examine reports from the 27 States
which are parties to the International
Convention on the Elimination of all
Forms of Racial Discrimination. In
addition, during its April meeting, it
discussed methods of implementing the
Unesco Declaration on Race and Racial
Prejudice.
Symposium Urges
Fund to Aid
Third World
Communication
Unesco has been urged to study the
possibility of creating an international
fund for the development of
communication, the purpose of which
would be to aid developing countries to
improve their communication
infrastructures.
The recommendation was one of
several addressed to Unesco at the close
of a week-long symposium on "The
Right to Communicate", sponsored by
the international non-governmental
organizations with consultative status at
Unesco. (A similar recommendation had
been adopted by the Intergovernmental
Conference on Communication Policies
in Asia and Oceania last February in
Kuala Lumpur.)
Representatives of some 70
organizations took part in the Paris
meeting which consisted of a series of
round-table discussions on such themes
as languages and communication ;
diversified communication for
diversified publics ; feedback and
participation ; the right to communicate
as a human right; and the new
international communication order.
Another recommendation urged
Unesco to consider launching an
international scholarly journal in the
communication field.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
' 'Children' ' theme
of Unesco Pavilion
in Montreal
In honour of the International Year
of the Child, the Unesco pavilion at the
"M,an and His World" exposition in
Montreal this summer will be centered
on the theme : "What kind of world are
we leaving our children ?",
The pavilion, in which Unicef and
the International Civil Aviation
The "children's corner" in the Unesco
Pavilion at "Man and His World", 1978.
This year the space will be enlarged and will
cover more varied activities.
Organization are also co-operating, will
be open from 21 June to 3 September.
The central theme will be illustrated by
a dramatized presentation of the world
in the form of a geodesic globe designed
by American architect and futurologist
Buckminster Fuller. The same room will
also contain an exhibition of children's
toys from various parts of the world
and an audio-visual show describing
Unesco's work with children.
Photo displays will illustrate other
aspects of Unesco's programme while
the cinema will show Unesco and Unicef
films. In addition, there will be a special
cinema for children in which children's
films will be screened. Also on exhibit
will be the winning designs from a
children's drawing contest organized in
more than 80 countries by Unesco, in
collaboration with Unicef and the U.N.
High Commissioner for Refugees.
Homage to Korczak
at Unesco
To celebrate the hundredth
anniversary of the birth of Janusz
Korczak, the permanent delegation of
Poland to Unesco and the French
association "The Friends of Janusz
Korczak" organized an international
week of homage to the famous educator
and paediatrician from 2 to 12 April.
The week included an exhibition on
"Korczak and the children" as well as
an international symposium on the work
of Korczak in the world of today and
the training of educators. In addition,
there was a projection of the film "Le
Roi Mathias Ier", based on the novel by
Korczak.
. Born in Warsaw, Korczak (his real
name was Henryk Goldszmit) died in
1942 in the Treblinka extermination
camp after a life entirely devoted to
children. Trained as a doctor, he
became interested in the education of
children through paediatrics. He was the
author of a remarkable series of books
about and for children.
Unesco Coupons :
a new record
During 1978, more than $ 17,500,000
worth of Unesco Coupons were sold,
setting a new record for this
programme. Established in 1950, the
Unesco Coupon Scheme enables
countries to use non-convertible
currencies in order to import
educational, scientific and cultural
equipment and supplies from abroad.
Turkish Professor
Awarded Unesco
Prize for Human
Rights Teaching
Mr. Mumtaz Soysal, a professor at
the University of Ankara and vice-
president of the executive board of
Amnesty International, has become the
first winner of the Unesco Prize for
Human Rights Teaching.
In announcing the award, Unesco
Director-General Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow said Professor Soysal's activities
extend far beyond his university and
have made his life and work an example
for the entire international community.
Mr. Soysal was nominated for the
award by an international jury, headed
by Prof. Shigeru Oda of Japan, a judge
at the International Court of Justice.
The jury also nominated for honourable
mention Prof. Thomas Buergenthal
(USA) and Maitre Louis Edmond Pettiti
(France).
The Unesco Prize for Human Rights
Teaching was created last year by the
Executive Board of the Organization to
mark the 30th anniversary of the
adoption of the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights.
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
The light of genius
"In my opinion Einstein would be one of the greatest theoretical
physicists of all time even if he had not written a single line on
relativity", wrote the distinguished German physicist Max Born.
In fact, Einstein was awarded the 1921 Nobel prize for physics,
not for his relativity theories, but for a paper published in 1905 on
the photo-electric effect in which he declared that light consisted
of particles. And in 1916 he formulated the principles which were
to lead, forty years later, to the development of the laser, a
device capable of producing a light beam intense enough to
vaporize the hardest and most heat-resistant materials. Among
the many applications of the laser today are delicate eye surgery,
the drilling of diamonds, making ultra-accurate measurements
and producing holographic effects. Photo shows the scintillating
light effects produced when a laser beam passes through a
diffraction grating. Part of the beam is dispersed into its
constituent colours; the remainder continues vertically down the
side of the picture.
	Photo © Fritz Goro. courtesy of Scientific American
]]>
</page>
</document>
