<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074816eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COllIier A window
open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
í 4sf-'
\ -y I
i %
\\\
V V
P,A:
hf*
//
i i
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Prehistoric bison
An outstanding example of Paleolithic art, this bison's head was incised in the clay
floor of a cave at Niaux, southwestern France, in the 11th millenium of the pre-
Christian era. The artist used tiny natural cavities formed in the clay by dripping
water to indicate the animal's eye as well as ritual wounds in its body.
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco ÇoUFlfT*
NOVEMBER 1977 30TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 16 LANGUAGE
English Japanese Dutch
French Italian Portuguese
Spanish Hindi Turkish
Russian Tamil Urdu
German Hebrew
Arabic Persian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 28 French Francs
2 years: 52 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when ¡t is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna-
' tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street. New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co.. New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
: Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Managing Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu Edition
page
4 "APARTHEID, THE VILEST FORM
OF MODERN SLAVERY"
By Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
re
R<->
as
5 THE U.N.'s WORLD CAMPAIGN AGAINST APARTHEID
By Enuga S. Reddy
8 SOUTH AFRICA: FACTS AND FICTION
Behind a barrage of propaganda, the grim truth about apartheid
By Leslie Rubin
12 "SOME ARE MORE EQUAL THAN OTHERS"
14 SOUTH AFRICA'S CAPTIVE WORK-FORCE
16 NAMIBIA MOVES TOWARDS INDEPENDENCE
By Sean MacBride
20 NAMIBIANS TRAIN FOR TOMORROW
By Hage G. Geingob
22 FROM RHODESIA TO ZIMBABWE
For Rhodesia's blacks, the name Zimbabwe symbolizes past glories
and future freedom
By Marion O'Callaghan
26 STIGMA ON SOUTH AFRICAN SPORT
By Stéphane A. Ogouki
27 UNESCO AND APARTHEID
29 A 30-YEAR STRUGGLE
The sustained efforts to give force of law
to the Universal Declaration of Human Rights
By Karel Vasak
30 THE UNIVERSAL DECLARATION OF HUMAN RIGHTS
33 UNESCO NEWSROOM
33 BOOKS IN 151 LANGUAGES
By Boris I. Stukalin
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
FRANCE: Prehistoric bison
Cover
In three countries of southern Africa
today South Africa, Namibia (formerly
known as South West Africa) and Rhodesia
(Zimbabwe) the non-whites who constitute
the overwhelming majority of the population
are deprived of the most fundamental human
rights. This issue focuses on the crisis in
southern Africa and the efforts being made by
the African peoples and the international
community to put an end to racist oppression.
Photo Reno Burri © Magnum, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Apartheid represents today the vilest form of modern
slavery. Unesco's patient but tenacious and vigorous
action ties in with the struggle of the South African blacks
themselves, who have shown that with the courage of
revolt they have discarded fear and regained hope. If the
international community is to remain true to itself, it must
mobilize and act firmly in order not to disappoint that
hope.
Unesco's position is based primarily on a detailed
analysis of the effects of apartheid on education, on
culture and on information. What is involved is not just
isolated occurrences. Apartheid is a whole, a system, and
this system is not the result of chance, it cannot be
improved with a little tinkering here and there. It is, like
Nazism, the coherent ideology of a racist state which,
though it first hits the numerically largest black
community, also affects the coloureds, the Asians and the
whites themselves. Nobody escapes this master-slave
dialectic.
This ideology finds expression in every institution of the
Republic. It permeates the educational system at all
levels, it is taught in the schools, it is imposed on creative
artists and it controls information within South Africa
and seeks to control it in other countries as well.
Unesco has repeatedly proclaimed that it is totally and
radically opposed to this system. The "respect for...
human rights... without distinction of race, sex, language
or religion" stipulated in Article I of Unesco's Constitution
would lose all meaning if such an ideology were to be
tolerated.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Director-General of Unesco
From an address given at the
opening of the World Conference
for Action against Apartheid,
held In Lagos, Nigeria,
22-26 August 1977
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Human Rights Day is celebrated each year on 10 December, for it was
on 10 December 1948 that the General Assembly of the United Nations
adopted the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. (See page 30 for
full text of the Universal Declaration.) To coincide with the 30th
anniversary of the Declaration, the United Nations is preparing to
proclaim 1978 "International Anti-Apartheid Year". On the eve of this
International Year, the Unesco Courier has devoted this special issue
to an exposé of the intolerable conditions in which the African peoples
of southern Africa are obliged to live under a system of racial
discrimination enforced by law and daily practice.
The U.N.'s
world campaign
against apartheid
by
Enuga
S. Reddy
Of all the crises in the world today, the grow¬
ing conflict between the minority régimes
and the liberation movements in southern
Africa is of most direct and urgent concern
to the United Nations. At stake are the
purposes and principles of the U.N. and the
imperative need to eliminate colonialism and
racial discrimination, which are major
sources of international tension and conflict.
The African people in Rhodesia, South
Africa and Namibia patiently tried for
decades, by peaceful and non-violent means, to obtain their
legitimate rights. But the authorities consistently rejected peace¬
ful change to full equality, and met the African demands with
increasingly ruthless measures of repression. The African political
movements were-obliged to abandon non-violence and organize
underground activity, sabotage and armed struggle.
Rhodesia is now the scene of an armed conflict between the
illegal régime and the liberation forces in which, according to
official accounts, over 5,000 people have been killed.
Encounters between the South African forces and the freedom
fighters of the Namibian liberation movement, the South West
Africa People's Organization (SWAPO), have become a frequent
occurrence.
In South Africa, many hundreds of Africans have been killed
and thousands wounded since the killings of African school¬
children demonstrating against racial discrimination in Soweto in
June 1976. The violence has been entirely by the police, but the
beginnings of armed resistance by the black people have i
appeared. |
ENUGA S. REDDY of India is Director of the United Nations Centre against
Apartheid, and also heads the U.N. Educational and Training Programme
for Southern Africa and the U.N. Trust Fund for South Africa. He was
Executive Secretary of the World Conference for Action against Apartheid
held at Lagos (Nigeria) in August 1977.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
These conflicts have spilled beyond national boundaries.
South "African and Rhodesian forces repeatedly committed acts
of aggression against Angola, Mozambique and Zambia in pur¬
suit of freedom fighters and to intimidate the neighbouring
African states which support them.
In 1946 the United Nations was seized with the problem of
racial discrimination in South Africa and with South Africa's
moves to annex Namibia. Since then, U.N. action on southern
Africa has evolved from mere appeals to attempts to apply
sanctions and other forms of pressure, and finally to wide-
ranging programmes of international action at governmental
and non-governmèntal levels.
Until 1960, the United Nations annually appealed to the
South African government to end racial discrimination in the
hope that it could be persuaded by world opinion. These appeals
failed, but the United Nations debates were not without value.
They resulted in the gradual acceptance by all Member States
of the competence of the U.N. to consider the situation in
South Africa, in greater world awareness of the aspirations of the
black people of that country and in the moral isolation of the
South African government.
The discussions on Namibia reinforced by advisory opinions
of the International Court of Justice affirming the international
status of the territory and the accountability of the South African
government for its administration helped prevent an annexation
of that territory. The Namibian people were enabled, despite
strenuous South African objections, to approach the inter¬
national community through petitions to United Nations organs
and hearings before them.
By 1960, the rapid advance of decolonization in Africa and
the entry of newly-independent African states into the United
Nations drew greater world attention to southern Africa.
The South African government, determined to resist the
"winds of change" sweeping the continent, stepped up repres¬
sion against the growing movement for freedom in South
Africa and Namibia. On 10 December 1959, Human Rights Day,
the South African police opened fire on a crowd of Africans in
Windhoek, peacefully demonstrating against a forcible move
to a segregated location, killing 11 and wounding 44.
On 21 March 1960, in Sharpeville, South Africa, police shot
indiscriminately at a peaceful demonstration against racist
"pass laws", killing 68 and wounding over 200.
These tragic events heightened world concern over the situa¬
tion, especially in Western countries which had earlier resisted
strong condemnations.
On 1 April 1960, the Security Council consi¬
dered the situation in South Africa for the
first time, and called on the South African
government to abandon apartheid and racial
discrimination. In December of that year,
the General Assembly adopted the historic
Declaration on the Granting of Indepen¬
dence to Colonial Countries and Peoples,
solemnly proclaiming the need to bring
colonialism in all its forms to a speedy and
unconditional end.
As the South African government continued to defy United
Nations resolutions, the African states, supported by Asian,
Socialist and other states, pressed for economic and other
sanctions against South Africa.
They felt that South Africa would pay little attention to
United Nations resolutions so long as it was able to count on
continued political, economic and other relations with the
Western countries and its other major trading partners. The latter
resisted sanctions, arguing that they were neither feasible nor
appropriate, and that they could not achieve the desired results.
United Nations deliberations began to reflect a consensus on the
objectives but sharp differences on the means of promoting them.
On 6 November 1962, the General Assembly adopted a resolu¬
tion requesting Member States to break off diplomatic and eco¬
nomic relations with South Africa, and to refrain from supplying
arms and ammunition to that country. This resolution was
opposed by the main trading partners of South Africa, and many
other states abstained. The Security Council decided in
1963-1964 to recommend an arms embargo against South Africa
but could not agree on mandatory sanctions.
In 1966, the United Nations General Assembly decided by an
overwhelming vote to terminate South Africa's mandate over
Namibia and declared that the territory was henceforth under the
direct responsibility of the United Nations. (See article page 16.)
Following South Africa's refusal to withdraw from the territory,
the General Assembly and the Security Council recommended a
number of measures to secure its compliance but again there
was no agreement on mandatory decisions.
Meanwhile, the United Nations became increasingly concerned
with the situation in Southern Rhodesia as the minority régime
in that territory attempted to obtain independence without
granting equal rights to the African population.
After that régime made a unilateral and
illegal declaration of independence in 1965,
and on the proposal of the administering
power, the United Kingdom, the Security
Council imposed mandatory sanctions
against Southern Rhodesia. The effective¬
ness of these sanctions was, however, limit¬
ed by the fact that South Africa (and
Portugal until the independence of Mozam¬
bique in 1975) enabled the Rhodesians to
circumvent the sanctions.
Most nations of the world have broken, or refrained from esta¬
blishing, diplomatic relations with South Africa, but 21 countries,
including the main trading partners of South Africa, maintain
diplomatic representatives in Pretoria. All countries have recog¬
nized the illegality of South African administration over Namibia
and almost all have terminated official relations with it. No coun¬
try, except South Africa, maintains diplomatic relations with the
illegal régime in Rhodesia.
But in the economic field, the results have been particularly
disappointing. Though many countries complied with U.N. reso¬
lutions, some at considerable sacrifice. South Africa was able to
increase its economic relations with its main trading partners.
Even more alarming was the military build-up by South Africa,
despite the arms embargo. While most governments prohibited
the supply of arms and military equipment to South Africa, a few
. arms exporting countries delayed action or followed restrictive
interpretations of the United Nations recommendations. South
Africa increased its military budget from $ 168 million in 1962-63
to $ 1,900 million in 1977-78. It acquired an enormous amount of
sophisticated military equipment, and developed local manufac¬
ture of arms and ammunition.
While continuing to press the powers concerned to disen¬
gage from the minority régimes, the United Nations organs began
to push for greater action in directions where there was broader
agreement. Particular emphasis was placed on assistance to the
oppressed people of southern Africa and their liberation move¬
ments, on dissemination of information on the situation in
southern Africa and on encouragement of action by inter¬
governmental and non-governmental organizations to reinforce
United Nations efforts.
Two important world conferences were held in 1977 with
impressive participation of governments, liberation movements
and intergovernmental and non-governmental organizations: the
International Conference in Support of the Peoples of Zimbabwe
and Namibia, held in Maputo, Mozambique, from 16 to 21 May;
and the World Conference for Action against Apartheid, held
in Lagos, Nigeria, from 22 to 26 August.
The United Nations has recognized the legitimacy of the
struggles of the national liberation movements for freedom, and
has granted them observer status in its deliberations on southern
African problems. It has encouraged the specialized agencies
and other intergovernmental organizationsas well as churches,
trade unions, anti-apartheid and solidarity movements and other
non-governmental organizations to take all appropriate action.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
SWAZILAND
LESOTHO
each within its mandate, to isolate the minority régimes and
assist the struggles for freedom.
In 1967, it established the office of the Commissioner, for
Namibia to help execute the decisions of the Council for Namibia,
administer assistance to the Namibian people and mobilize public
support to press for South Africa's withdrawal.
It also established a Centre against Apartheid, to help the
Special Committee against Apartheid develop an international
campaign, to expand information activity and to administer
humanitarian and educational assistance to the victims of
apartheid.
As a result of persistent efforts by the United
Nations and other organizations, as well as
by African and other Member States, the
minority régimes are increasingly isolated.
The specialized agencies of the U.N. and
other intergovernmental organizations have
all excluded Southern Rhodesia, and have
refused to recognize the South African
administration in Namibia. Many of them
have accepted the United Nations Council
for Namibia as the legal authority for Nami¬
bia, and have invited the national liberation movements from the
three countries to their conferences and meetings. South Africa
withdrew from Unesco in 1955 and has since been expelled from
or obliged to leave many other intergovernmental organizations.
None provides any assistance to South Africa or Rhodesia.
An important aspect of the effort to isolate the minority
régimes is the encouragement of public action, especially in coun¬
tries which continue to maintain relations with South Africa.
Non-governmental groups have organized boycotts of South
African and Namibian goods.
. They have exerted their influence to dissuade transnational
corporations from collaborating with South Africa and from
practising racial discrimination in their operations in southern
Africa. The campaign to boycott racially-selected sports teams
from South Africa has involved hundreds of thousands of
sportsmen and sports enthusiasts in "many countries, and has
brought home to the white communities in southern Africa the
extent of worldwide abhorrence of racial discrimination.
Several Western countries and other main trading partners
of South Africa have taken further steps, however cautious and ,
moderate, towards the implementation of U.N. resolutions.
France, for example, announced in 1977 that it was halting
supplies of military equipment to South Africa, and the Federal
Republic of Germany has decided to close its consulate in;
Namibia. Scandinavian and other states have taken steps to stop
new investments in South Africa.
The United Nations and related agencies undertook humanita¬
rian and educational assistance to the victims of colonialism and .
apartheid in the early 1960s when repression greatly increased
and sizeable numbers of refugees began to come out of southern
Africa. In subsequent years, they established and encouraged
programmes of direct assistance to the liberation movements,
including help in preparing cadres for the' future development of
these countries. ,
The U.N. Trust Fund for South Africa established in 1965 to
assist political prisoners and their families in South Africa,
Namibia and Southern Rhodesia has received over $5 million in
voluntary contributions.
The United Nations Educational and Training Programme for
Southern Africa, also financed by voluntary contributions, has
received over $10 million to train inhabitants of the three territo¬
ries. It now administers over 1,300 scholarships. .
The Fund for Namibia, established in 1972, has received over
$9 million. Part of this goes to the Namibia Institute, establish¬
ed in Lusaka in 1976, to train cadres for the future administration k
of Namibia. r
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A turning point in African resistance to apartheid came on
16 June 1976, in the black township of Soweto, outside
Johannesburg, when 10,000 black pupils made a protest march
(right) against the compulsory use of the Afrikaans language
in school. The police opened fire, killing a 13-year-old boy, and
sparked off months of riots and strikes around the country.
In the first week alone, 176 were killed and over 1,200 wounded.
The United Nations Development Programme has allocated
substantial funds for assistance to national liberation movements,
to be administered by Unesco, the International Labour Organi¬
zation (ILO), the World Health Organization (WHO), and the
Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO). The U.N. High
Commissioner for Refugees has been assisting tens of thousands
of refugees from the three territories. Unicef provides assistance
to mothers and children through the national liberation
movements.
Few liberation struggles in history have
received greater political support and con¬
crete assistance from the international
community.
The minority régimes in southern Africa are
increasingly isolated and face mounting
pressure. This has resulted in some move¬
ment towards settlements in Zimbabwe and
Namibia, with U.N. participation in the
process of transition to independence.
But the South African government remains
adamant in rejecting majority rule and so long as it and its
supporters resist change, there can be no secure peace in the
region. The threat of a widening conflict, perhaps even a race
war, with enormous casualties and inevitable repercussions
beyond the region, will remain.
The United Nations is attempting, as a matter of utmost
urgency, to maximize international efforts to avert this danger.
Full observance of International Anti-Apartheid Year in 1978
can make an effective contribution to this effort.
Enuga S. Reddy
The vignettes in the above text are by the Polish artist Zygmunt Gasowski
© International Institute of Human Rights, Strasbourg, France
South Africa
facts
and fiction
by Leslie Rubin
LESLIE RUBIN, professor of Comparative Government at Howard University, Wash¬
ington D. C, was a Senator, representing Africans, in the South African Parliament
from 1954 until he left South Africa in 1960. A formerNational Vice-President of the
Liberal Party of South Africa (1953-1960), he presented a petition to the U.N. Special
Committee on Apartheid in 1963. Among his many published works are Apartheid in
Practice, published by the U.N. in 1970 and translated into eight languages, and (with
Brian Weinstein) Introduction to African Politics: A Continental Approach, published
by Praeger, New York, 1974.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
M^HBH^HMi
Behind a barrage of propaganda,
the grim truth about apartheid
SINCE 1948, . when Afrikaner
nationalism came to power in
South Africa, the outside world
has become increasingly aware of what is
being done in the name of apartheid by
4.5 million whites to more than 22 million
non-whites: 19 million Africans, 2.5 million
coloureds, and some 800,000 Asians <1).
South Africa has responded to growing
international criticism by mounting a
massive propaganda campaign designed
U) The term "white" is used for people of European
stock. The term "African". replaces the word "Bantu"
which is at present used by the South African govern¬
ment to designate people of African stock, except in
direct quotations where, if the word "Bantu" was
originally used, it is retained. The term "Asian" is used
for people of Chinese or Indian descent, and "colour¬
ed" for those of mixed European and African or Asian
background. In this issue the use of these terms
"white", "African", "Asian" and "coloured" has been
unavoidable because of the nature of apartheid
itself. However, Unesco rejects the concepts of race
and ethnic group relations that such terms imply.
to present a favourable image of its racial
policies.
Government spokesmen, including the
Prime Minister, make frequent use of the
media. A generously-financed propa¬
ganda machine pours out information
through embassies, the Information Ser¬
vice, and unofficial bodies like the South
African Foundation, and the Committee
for Fairness in Sport.
Leading European and American news¬
papers carry full-page advertisements
asserting the contentment of all South
Africa's peoples. Illustrated publications
describe the successes of apartheid.
Well-trained, persuasive officials of the
information Service attend the opening of
every session of the United Nations.
In 1948 the information budget was
$ 140,000; by 1969 it had grown to
$ 5 million. For 1976-1977 it was more
than $ 15 million.
All this costly propaganda is intended
to demonstrate that apartheid is a just and
viable system. The methods" used are
usually sophisticated, subtle, and shrewd:
but deliberate misrepresentation is
common. Taken as a whole the propa¬
ganda offers a grossly deceptive picture
of South Africa today.
What follows is an attempt to expose
this deception by looking at some of the
claims made by South African propa¬
ganda in the light of available facts.
The indigenous
of South Africa
inhabitants
CLAIM: South Africa persists in claiming
that the white man and the African came
to South Africa at about the same time.
Addressing the Los Angeles World Affairs
Council on 6 June 1975, the South African
Minister of Information said, "The Bantu were
not indigenous. They came after the Dutch I
and the British". f
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Three months after the first Soweto riots, black African
demonstrators (right) badly jolted the white community when they
dared to turn out in force in the white districts of Johannesburg.
They were promptly arrested by the police. In another, more ominous
police crackdown in October 1977, the government arrested or banned
persons, organizations and newspapers considered till then to be
moderate. Under existing Internal Security legislation, political
opponents can be detained for up to 12 months at a time.
In the last year, some 20 blacks have died in detention. The General
Assembly of the United Nations has proclaimed 11 October the
Day of Solidarity with South African political prisoners.
, FACTS: Anthropological and archaeo¬
logical research has established that
settled African communities existed in
South Africa several centuries before the
first white man arrived in 1652.
An archaeological group reported in 1966
that there were settlements in what is
today Johannesburg "as early as
1060 A.D." The distinguished anthropo¬
logist, Monica Wilson, writing in 1959,
cited 15th-century Portuguese records
proving that shipwrecked sailors had
encountered settled black communities in
South Africa, and added: "None of these
facts is new, all have been published at
one time or another, but their implica¬
tions appear to have been overlooked by
the myth-makers of this generation".
In 1966, Professor Vernon McKay of
the School of Advanced International
Studies, Johns Hopkins University
(U.S.A.) told a Congressional committee:
"A second popular theme to divert atten¬
tion from the real issues is the argument
which implies that South Africa's policy is
just because 'the white man got there first'
or, in the amended version used by South
African officials today, blacks and whites
arrived 'about the same time' or 'more or
less simultaneously' . . . Although the
above argument is largely irrelevant, it may
be worthwhile to point out that South
Africa's own scholars have proved that it
is also untrue".
Separate development
CLAIM: The South African population consists
of whites, several distinct African nations, the
coloureds, and the Asians. The policy of sepa¬
rate development is Just, ensures a sound poli¬
tical, social and economic future for each
group, and is in the interest of the country as a
whole.
In May 1977, in an article published in the
Los Angeles Times, the South African Secretary
for Information wrote that "a plurality of
democracies" was coming into being... "The
homelands of black people who settled in what
is today South Africa, either have been given
back to them or are in the process of being
handed back"... The Asian and coloured com¬
munities, through their elected representative
councils already administer most of their own
affairs".
FACTS: No African, coloured or Asian has
the right, either directly oc through repre¬
sentatives," to take part in thé government
of South Africa.
The Bantu areas, arbitrarily reserved by
the whites for exclusive African occupa¬
tion, amount to 13 per cent of the total
land area of South Africa; the remaining
87 per cent is reserved for exclusive white
occupation.
Leo Marquard, a noted authority on
South Africa, has described the Bantu
areas as "poverty-stricken areas, incapable
of standing up to the periodic droughts
and floods of South Africa, and unable to
support the existing population... They are
in fact vast rural slums whose chief export
is their manpower, which goes to the
mines and factories and farms to earn
enough money to pay taxes and support
the families".
These, comprising 10 fragmented terri¬
tories allocated to 10 African "nations" are
the so-called homelands of the African
people.
One of them, the Transkei (population
1.9 million), was granted "independence"
by South Africa in 1976, but every country
in the world (except South Africa) has
refused to recognize the Transkei as an.
independent state.
Another, Boputhatswana, is due to
become "independent" in 1977. The
remaining eight have rejected "indepen¬
dence". In 1976 their leaders said, "...We
do not want to abdicate our birthright as
South Africans, as well as forfeiting our
share of the economy and wealth which
we have jointly built".
The functions of the Coloured Persons
Representative Council and the South
African Indian Council are consultative and
advisory. The coloureds and the Asians
do not share power with the whites.
Government plans do not envisage such
power-sharing in the future.
Personal freedom, education,
work, health and housing
CLAIM: In October 1975 the Information
Counsellor of the South African Embassy in the
United States wrote in the New York Times
Magazine: "...Blacks in South Africa enjoy
more personal freedom than probably else¬
where in Africa and, in fact, have a more effec¬
tive political voice than in much of Africa;
South African blacks have the best educational
facilities on the continent of Africa; there are
a/most 4 million black schoolchildren in South
Africa; blacks in South Africa enjoy better
health services,' better housing, and a higher
standard of living across the board than any¬
where else in Africa ".
FACTS: A network of laws and regulations
(the notorious pass laws) severely restrict
African movement, " while maintaining a
controlled supply of African labour for the
needs of commerce and industry. All Afric-
, ans whose labour is not required are
removed to putative "homelands".
Every African must carry a reference
book; failure to produce it on demand by
a policeman or other official is a criminal
offence. Prosecutions under the pass laws
for the period 1974-1975 totalled 386,000,
equivalent to 989 trials for every day of the
year.
Right to work: There are laws that
prevent an African from doing skilled work;
empower the government to reserve
specified occupations exclusively for
whites, and deny to Africans the generally
accepted rights to strike and organize in
trade unions. An African worker's oppor-
tunity to acquire skills and efficiency is
limited by the grossly inferior educational,
facilities available to Africans... The
earnings of African workers are conside¬
rably lower than those of white workers.
Employment of Africans as shop mana¬
gers is prohibited. In March 1977 a white
divisional manager of a national retailer
and his African shop manager both
received a suspended sentence of a
$ 230 fine or imprisonment for 3 months.
The permanent ban on black managers
was confirmed by the Minister of Bantu
Administration and Development in July
1977.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
J
"41 Í r- 7
The "homelands" are not alleviating
African unemployment. In 1971 and 1972
barely 10,000 jobs were created annually
through industrial development in the
"borderlands" and "homelands". Mean¬
while 60,000 persons were sent to the
Bantustans each year. In 1968-1969 alone,
26,736 Africans lost their jobs in the white
urban areas.
In 1973 the per capita earnings of
whites in Johannesburg were $ 131 per
month. Africans in the adjoining town¬
ship of Soweto earned $ 19 per month.
Health: The health system for South
African whites is one of the best in the
world, whereas African medical services
are characterized by inadequate hospital
facilities and a serious shortage of
doctors.
According to a report published in June
1977 by the U.N. Centre Against Apar¬
theid, there is one doctor for every 400
white South Africans as against one for
every 44,000 Africans. Of the 693 medical
practitioners who graduated in 1975, 601
were white and 6 were African. Facilities
for training African doctors have been
reduced.
South Africa does not provide statistics
of African infant mortality but those avail¬
able for the city of Johannesburg indicate
that the African rate is the highest of all
ethnic groups.
In 1977 the World Health Organization
reported that "Mental health services for
the non-white groups, especially for the
African population, are inadequate in
quantity and very poor in quality... There
is not a single black psychiatrist in
South Africa".
Housing: Speaking in Parliament on
28 April 1976, opposition leader Helen
Suzman said Soweto, with a population
of at least 1 .3 million, had an average of
14 people living in a house. She warned
that Soweto and other townships were
becoming "gigantic overcrowded slums".
Education: Almost 30 years of rigidly
separated and white-controlled schools
and universities have resulted in grossly
inferior education for blacks, both quanti¬
tatively and qualitatively. The cause of the
1976 Soweto riots and demonstrations
since then, that resulted in extensive loss
'of life and damage to property, was the
strong resentment of this system.
In 1976 per capita expenditure on white
education was $ 696; African, $ 45. The
teacher-pupil ratios for that year were:
white, 1 : 22; African 1 : 60. The over¬
whelming majority of African children stop
schooling at the primary level; only
5.5 per cent are in secondary schools.:
Schooling for white children is free and
compulsory; for Africans it is not compul¬
sory, and African parents have to find the
money for fees, uniforms and books.
Integrated education is prohibited in
private schools. In 1977, two Roman
Catholic schools were officially threatened
with closure unless a few African and
coloured children "admitted in the past
few days" were removed. .
In 1975, 15,467 degrees and diplomas Y
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SOUTH AFRICA:
"SOME ARE
MORE EQUAL
THAN OTHERS
WHITES
4.5 million Population
BLACKS
19 million
87 per cent
75 per cent
Land allocation
Share of national
income
13 per cent
less than 20 per cent'1'
14
Ratio of average
earnings
750 rands
Minimum taxable
income 360 rands
1 for 400
27 per 1,000
Doctors/population
ratio
Infant mortality rate
$696
Annual expenditure on
education per pupil
1 for 22 Pupil/teacher ratio
1 for 44,000
200 per 1 ,000 in urban areas
400 per 1,000 in rural areas
$45
1 for 60
(1) The remaining 5 per cent is divided between the coloureds and the Asians.
awarded at South African universities went
to white students, 1 ,757 to Africans.
Police have assaulted, arrested, and
prosecuted hundreds of students at South
African universities. Student leaders, stu¬
dents, and school pupils have been
detained under Security legislation.
Freedom of the press: The law penalizes
criticism of apartheid. There is also increas¬
ing government interference with news¬
paper investigation and reporting, by
Facts and figures in this table are drawn from U.N. sources
and from the article on these pages
means of harassment, threats, arrests,
and detention of newspapermen, partic¬
ularly African reporters describing condi¬
tions, and police behaviour in African
townships.
In 1976 nine journalists were detained
under the Internal Security Act, many of
them while they were covering the
Soweto riots. In December 1976 Percy
Qoboza, editor of The World, South
Africa's leading African newspaper, was
detained by the police following an edi¬
torial which described Prime Minister
Vorster as "sleeping through one of the
country's' most dangerous times". He
was released the same day following
widespread protests. In October 1977 he
was again arrested and The World was
closed as part of a general crackdown on
the black civil rights movement, in which
some 70 leaders were arrested.
In 1977 Winnie Mandela, wife of the
imprisoned African leader Nelson
Mandela, was banished from Soweto.
The Security Police officer in charge of a
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
force of 20 policemen carrying out the
removal from her home, told reporters
present that if they took photographs
they would be detained for 14 days.
The family
CLAIM: The pass laws, which deny Africans
the right of permanent residence in a South
African urban area, are justified by the govern¬
ment on the grounds that they do have such a
right in their "homelands".
FACTS: More than half the total African
population about 8 million live in the
towns of white South Africa, and their
number has increased steadily since 1970.
The pass laws continue daily to disrupt
and undermine the family life of these
millions. One of these laws, the Urban
Areas Act, makes it a criminal offence for
an African woman to live with her husband
for more than 72 hours if she has not
received a permit from a white official to
do so.
White students from the University of Cape Town (above) manifest their
solidarity with black African pupils during the 1976 Soweto riots.
A number of South African whites writers, politicians and schoolteachers have
been actively engaged in combatting apartheid ever since the 1950s. Some are
now in exile or, like the distinguished poet Breyten Breytenbach, in prison.
In his essay "Vulture Culture", Breytenbach summed up the insidious effects
of apartheid on South Africa's whites as follows:
"Apartheid isolates the white man...
His windows are painted white
to keep the night in."
Sport
CLAIM: A full-page advertisement in an
American newspaper in 1977, with photographs
of black and white competitors, claims: "... our
teams are selected on merit and merit only...
South Africa has been barred from the Olympics
and many other international sport organizations
on the pretext that it practises discrimination
in sport..."
FACTS: On 23 September 1976 Dr. P.H.J.
Koornhof, Minister of Sport and Recre¬
ation, announcing the government sport
policy, declared that "white, coloured,
Indian, and black sportsmen and women
should all belong to their own clubs. Each
should control, arrange, and manage its
own sporting fixtures." The government
approved of consultation between "the
different race groups wherever possible,
practical, and desirable", and of competi¬
tion between teams "from different racial
groups... by mutual agreement in consulta¬
tion with the Minister".
In October 1976 Dr. Koornhof said that
a rugby match played between a white
and a black team was contrary to sports
policy, which did not provide for mixed
teams. In July 1977 the Minister rejected
a formula providing for multiracial play
which had been adopted by all four na¬
tional rugby bodieswhite, African, Asian
and coloured. (See also page 26).
The rule of law
CLAIM: South Africa proclaims its adherence
to the rule of law, pointing to the fact that
apartheid is applied in terms of laws which are
passed by Parliament and interpreted by an
independent judiciary.
FACTS: The blacks have no say what¬
soever in the making or the application of
the law. As Nelson Mandela put it, "The
white man makes all the laws, he drags us
before his courts and accuses us, and he
sits in judgement over us."
To curb black opposition to apartheid,
South Africa has created a draconian
police state apparatus. Since 1950, 60
laws relating to "internal security" have
been enacted. These laws grant to Cabinet
Ministers, policemen, and other officials,
widespread powers of arrest, detention
(often incommunicado), house arrest,
search of person and property, interroga¬
tion, banning, and banishment, without
right of recourse to a court of law.
During the past 17 years thousands of |
men and women have been deprived of I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
y freedom under these laws. The Christian
Institute of South Africa estimates the
government does not provide information
that several hundred are in detention at
the present time. From April 1976 to
August 1977, 19 persons died while in
detention. The police claimed they were
all suicides. Urged repeatedly to appoint a
judicial commission to enquire into police
behaviour. Prime Minister Vorster has
refused to do so.
The future of apartheid
CLAIM: Roelof Botha, South African Repre¬
sentative at the United Nations, said on
18 October 1974: "...My Government does not
condone discrimination purely on grounds of
race or colour. Discrimination based solely on
the colour of a man's skin cannot be defended.
And we shall do everything in our power to
move away from discrimination based on race
or colour. "
FACTS: Since 1974 blacks have been
permitted access, formerly denied to them,
to some of the country's public amenities.
But the changes that have taken place are
minimal and peripheral. They leave the :
essential structure of apartheid unaltered.
On 10 March 1977, Prime Minister
Vorster told the South African Parliament
that his party "did not and never would
support power-sharing" with the blacks.
In June 1977, United Nations Secretary-
General Kurt Waldheim said that the past
17 years had "seen racism progressively
institutionalized in every aspect of South
African society."
Leslie Rubin
South Africa's
captive
work-force
IN South Africa, access to education,
vocational training and jobs are deter¬
mined by the racial group to which a
person belongs: apartheid affects every
aspect of economic life.
Millions of Africans live permanently in
"white areas", where they are deprived of
the most fundamental rights and are reduc¬
ed to the status of foreigners within their
own country.
And yet the rapidly expanding South
African economy is becoming increasingly
dependent on African labour, and the num¬
ber of Africans in the white areas is mount¬
ing steadily. Such a growing interdepen¬
dence between blacks and whites in econo¬
mic activities could lead to a form of racial
integration. To stop this from happening,
the South African government has built as
many barriers as possible between the
races.
The working conditions of the Africans
l have been denounced many times. Each
year the International Labour Organization
(ILO) carries out a survey of developments
in the labour situation in South Africa. An
ILO study published in May 1977 draws
attention to the many ways in which black
African workers are deprived of their free¬
dom and of any hope of improving their
conditions. A Nationalist Party Member of
Parliament stated the official position in
unequivocal terms: "...The Bantu labourer
is supplying a commodity to us... it is
labour we are importing and not labourers
as individuals."
No African may remain in a white area
for more than 72 hours without permission,
unless he qualifies to be there because he
has lived or worked there over a long
period. He may be granted a permit to stay
in the area to look for work, but the permit
will stipulate the class of work he may
accept and the length of time he may work
in the area.
All male Africans over the age of 15 who
are either unemployed or not lawfully
employed must register with a labour
bureau, and, as a general rule, employers
can only hire Africans registered at these
bureaux. Every African aged 16 or over
must be in possession of a reference book
containing a record of his work contracts
and when they ended.
In practice, the Africans have no free¬
dom to choose their employment, since
they can only accept work to which they
have been directed by a labour bureau and
cannot freely change jobs. An African who
refuses on three consecutive occasions to
accept a job offered him by a labour bureau
may be defined as "idle". Such "idle per-,
This article is based on information drawn from
"The ILO and Apartheid", a study published
by the International Labour Organization,
Geneva, May 1977.
Throughout southern Africa black
workers are poor in the midst of plenty.
Whites monopolize skilled trades and
professions, while blacks who form
the mainstay of the economy are
subject to restrictive legislation.
African trade unions are not
recognized by South African
law and black strikers are dismissed
and often fined and imprisoned.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
sons" may be sent back to their home area,
placed in -a work colony or a rehabilitation
centre, or, subject to their agreement, be
ordered to take up employment with an
employer for an officially approved period.
An African worker can only be accompa¬
nied by his wife if she is entitled to reside in
the same area as her husband. Otherwise,
she cannot visit her husband for more than
72 hours at a time, and if she fails to report
her arrival or overstays the authorized
period, may be summarily deported from
the area.
Another prominent feature of the South
African labour system is the "colour bar"
whereby skilled occupations are reserved
for whites. This is backed up by a battery
of laws. Under the Industrial Conciliation
Act, the Minister of Labour can prohibit the
replacement of white employees by per¬
sons of another race, or reserve certain
jobs or classes of work wholly or partly to
persons of a specified race. Up to the end
of 1975, 26 of these "job reservations" had
been proclaimed. Special measures have
been taken to "protect" work in the mines,
the building trades, public transport and
nursing.
Legislation has become even stricter
since 1970. The Minister of Bantu Admi¬
nistration has announced his intention of
prohibiting the employment of Africans in a
number of occupations (including those of
shop assistant, receptionist, typist, clerk
and cashier) except in African townships
and areas.
There is also a traditional colour bar pre¬
venting non-whites from carrying out work
above a certain level of skill or
responsibility.
The question of the colour bar in educa¬
tion is closely interwoven with that in
employment. In this respect, non-whites in
South Africa are handicapped from birth,
since their racial category determines the
educational system they will find them¬
selves in. The same is true of vocational
training.
Africans do have some opportunities to
acquire technical and professional training,
but these are almost exclusively in the
Bantu territories. In practice, states the
ILO report, it is "almost impossible for
significant numbers of Africans to qualify
for admission to apprenticeship and
advanced training".
African salaries and working conditions
are determined by a board of government-
appointed white officials.
There is a wide gap between the earn¬
ings of Africans and those of whites. In
mining, the average monthly wage is 79
rands for Africans and 590 rands for
whites. (The rand is worth about U.S.
$1.15). It is a fact that in mining African
workers get free board and lodging, but in
the manufacturing industries, where they
do not, the disparity is still enormous:
R 117 on average for Africans, R 550 for
whites. According to unofficial surveys,
the average monthly income of African
households is still much lower than the
minimum subsistence level. In almost all
sectors of the economy, the wage-gap be¬
tween whites and blacks is still growing.
The Industrial Conciliation Act grants
legal existence to registered trade unions,
but expressly excludes Africans from its
definition of what constitutes an
"employee". And so the Africans cannot
belong to registered trade unions. Of
course, they are not prohibited from form¬
ing their own unions, but such legally
unrecognized bodies enjoy no legal protec¬
tion for their activities, and can play no
effective part in industrial relations.
It comes as no surprise, then, that the
right to strike is strictly curtailed for Afri¬
cans in a way which does not apply to
other workers. The Bantu Labour (Settle¬
ment of Disputes) Act provides penalties of
up to three years' imprisonment for Afri¬
cans who go on strike. Furthermore, since
African trade unions do not enjoy legal
recognition, they are not exempted from
repressive legislation. Strikers run the risk
of harsh penalties, including the death
penalty.
Strikes still take place: there were 169
between January 1975 and June 1976. In
many cases they were followed by waves
of arrests and other police action. And yet
, African unions continue to exist and to
grow.
í . i
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Namibia
moves towards
independence
by Sean MacBride
VERY few now can have any doubts
as to the future of Namibia. It will
acquire full independence in the
near future; it is now only a question of
when and how. But before dealing with
this aspect let us look at Namibia.
In order to place Namibia geographically
and historically for those who are not Afri-
canists, let me briefly summarize; Namibia
is one of the larger African countries, with
an area of some 820,000 square
km.about the size of Texas and Florida
combined or, in an international context,
the size of Germany and France.
It lies along the South Atlantic Coast of.
the African continent. The Orange River is
the boundary between Namibia and South
Africa, which lies to the south. Namibia
has a frontier of some 1,300 km. with
Angola. It also has a short frontier with
Zambia about 130 km.along the nor¬
thern side of the Caprivi Strip. (See map
page 7.)
At the eastern end of the Caprivi Strip it
barely makes contact with Rhodesia. On
the southern side of the Caprivi Strip it has
a border of 500 km. with Botswana. On its
eastern side Namibia has a frontier of over
1,000 km. with Botswana. The fighting
between South Africa and SWAPO
South West Africa People's Organization)
has been taking place mainly in the Caprivi
Strip and along the frontier between Nami¬
bia and Angola.
SEAN MacBRIDE, the distinguished Irish politician
and jurist, was United Nations Commissioner for
Namibia from 1973 to 1976. He was awarded the
Nobel Peace Prize in 1974 and the International
Lenin Peace Prize in 1977. One of the founders of
Amnesty International (Nobel Peace Prize 1977), he
was chairman of its international executive from 1961
to 1975. He has ¡ust been appointed by Unesco to
head an international commission set up to examine
world communication problems (see news item
page 33).
Namibia consists primarily of desert and
a semi-desert central plateau, where cattle
and karakul sheep are widely grazed.
Beneath the soil lies a wealth of minerals:
copper, lead, uranium, and many others.
The population is officially claimed to be
around 800,000, although I believe it to be
well over a million. Some 90,000 are
white, primarily of South African and Ger-,
man origin.
Namibia, formerly called South West
Africa, became an Imperial German colony
in 1884. This occurred at the great "Colo¬
nial carve up" which took place at the Ber¬
lin Conference of 1884, when the European
colonial powers divided Africa among
them.
The German Empire then conquered the
area most ruthlessly and colonized it. It
became German South West Africa. It was
ruled with an iron hand; entire population
groups including women and children were
exterminated. The surviving African popu¬
lation became virtual slaves. German cul¬
ture and the German language were
implanted.
During World War I British and South
African forces successfully invaded and
took over the entire territory. The territory
became a League of Nations mandate at
the end of World War I. When World War
II ended, South Africa alone among the
former mandatory powers refused either to
free its mandated territory or to place it
under the United Nations trusteeship
system.
South Africa also refused to recognize
the right1 of the U.N. to supervise its
administration of the territory. Unable to
resolve this issue by negotiation or by deci¬
sion of the International Court, the General
Assembly finally revoked South Africa's
mandate in 1966 and established the Coun¬
cil for Namibia to administer the territory
until independence.
Let us now look in more detail at the his¬
torical development of international legal
responsibility for Namibia before analyzing
the current situation.
Apart from gradual outlawing of slavery
and the slave trade, international protec¬
tion for people under colonial rule scarcely
existed in the 19th century. They were
regarded as "outside the law". Indeed, the
main responsibility for them seems to have
been to ensure their orderly and effective
subjection to colonial rule.
Thus South West Africa, as Namibia was
then called, was brought under the "pro¬
tection". of the Imperial German Reich in
accordance with the rules issuing from the
Berlin Conference of 1884-1885, which was
called to legitimize the division of Africa
and to prevent the! European powers
from going to war with each other over
the spoils. '
The first expression of general interna¬
tional legal responsibility for colonial peo¬
ples came with the creation of the mandate
system at the end of World War I and
even that had to be forced on the victorious
allies by President Wilson. Under Article 22
of the Covenant of the League of Nations,
the former German protectorate of South
West Africa was placed under South Afri¬
can administration as "a sacred trust of
civilization"
The mandate agreement granted the
mandatory "full power of administration
and legislation over the territory... as an
integral part of the Union..." and directed it
to "promote to the utmost the material and
moral well-being and the social progress of
the inhabitants of the territory... "
In the years between the two World
Wars, the League Council, aided by the
Permanent Mandates Commission, exerci¬
sed limited supervision over South African
administration of its mandate. It forced
South Africa to modify a number of lightly
veiled attemps to claim outright sove¬
reignty over the territory; but it could only
censure the Union for sending its air force
to bomb Bondelswarts women and child¬
ren when the men of that small Nama com¬
munity rose up with ancient hand weapons
against the government.
After World War II, the Union sought
United Nations approval for the annexation
of Namibia. The Organization exercised its
responsibility by refusing to agree to the
annexation and by urging South Africa to
place the Territory under trusteeship.
South Africa in turn refused. Claiming
that the mandate had terminated with the |
demise of the League, the Union govern- I
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
South Africa's illegal occupation
of a neighbouring territory
must inevitably come to an end
In defiance of the United
Nations, South Africa
continues to administer
Namibia (the name given by
the U.N. to the former
territory of South West
Africa) and has introduced
apartheid laws there.
Thousands of Africans have
been forcibly removed to
"homelands" in those parts
of the country most devoid
of wealth and resources.
Thus many Namibians seek
contract jobs outside these
"reserves". These migrant
workers are often wretchedly
housed in compounds and
spend up to two years apart
from their families. Left, a
migrant worker returns to his
home village.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
ment quit reporting to the General
} Assembly on its administration of the Terri¬
tory and began to impose its apartheid
system there.
In response to requests of the General
Assembly for guidance on issues raised by
South Africa, the International Court of
Justice advised the Assembly, inter alia,
that the mandate still existed, that the
Assembly should supervise its administra¬
tion, and that South Africa could not alter
the international status of the Territory
without United Nations approval.
The Assembly was, however, unable to
translate the Court's advice into effective
action. So, in 1960, Ethiopia and Liberia
brought a contentious proceeding i.e.,
one in which the judgement binds the
parties against South Africa, charging
the Union in substance with maladministra¬
tion of the Territory.
However, in somewhat dubious circum¬
stances, six years later the Court held that
the complainants had no standing to bring
the proceedings and thus avoided ruling on
the merits of the case.
Unable to persuade South Africa, by
either negotiations or judicial proceedings,
to live up to its mandate obligations, the
General Assembly thereupon took an histo¬
ric action: it revoked the mandate and
made itself responsible for administering
the Territory until independence.
Subsequently, it established the Council
for Namibia, composed at present of 25
Member States, to act on its behalf. The
name of South West Africa was changed
to Namibia by General Assembly resolution
2372 (XXII) (of 1968), and the name of the
Council for South West Africa, as it was
originally called, was correspondingly
changed to Council for Namibia.
South Africa, however, refused to recog¬
nize the Assembly's right to take these
steps. Consequently, the International
Court of Justice was asked to rule on
States' obligations in the situation.
The new Opinion dealt with the issues in
considerable depth and included the fol¬
lowing findings (given hereunder in a con¬
densed and re-arranged form for clarity): .
1. The termination of the mandate by the
U.N. General Assembly was legal and
did not require South African consent.
2. It follows that the continued presence
of South Africa in Namibia is illegal and
South Africa is therefore under an
immediate obligation to withdraw.
3. States that are members of the U.N.
have an obligation to recognize the ille¬
gality of South Africa's occupation and
are to refrain from any acts or dealings
with the South African régime implying
recognition of a legal South African pre¬
sence in Namibia.
4. In terms of Article 25 of the Charter
of the United Nations, Member States
are obliged to comply with Security
Council decisions even if they had voted
against such decisions.
5. South Africa remains accountable for
any violations of the rights Of the people
of Namibia. (Author's italics)
The Opinion of the International Court of w
Justice was accepted by the General*
Photo Jan Kopec © Parimage, Paris
White villas
and black
shanty-towns
Namibia is a prosperous country, but its wealth is
almost entirely in the hands of a white community
numbering some 90,000, about a tenth of the total
population. Above, a tree-shaded residential quarter of
the capital, Windhoek (estimated population 76,000),
dominated by the spire of a Dutch Reformed church. It
makes a stark contrast with the shanty-towns (below)
where many black Namibians live. The name of
Windhoek's main street, the Kaiser Strasse (below
right), is a reminder that this vast corner of southern
Africa was once a German colony (1884-1919). Right,
black policemen and two traditionally-clad Herero
women in a Namibian town.
'-V-. ****7.- *
4t 2
%n
*>
Photo Peter Fraenkel © Parimage, Paris
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Photos Jan Kopec © Parimage, Paris
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
^Assembly and- the Security Council.
Basically the obligations imposed on
States by the International Court required
States to treat South Africa as having no
rights whatsoever in Namibia. South Africa
is declared to be a naked usurper; an oc¬
cupier on a par with the Nazi forces occupy¬
ing Norway, Belgium, or other parts of
Europe and it should be treated as such.
The mere fact that the wrongful occupa¬
tion has stretched on for over a decade is
no ground for automatically upgrading it to
that of being a de facto government. The
lapse of time can certainly not legitimize in
any way, or to any extent. South African
illegal occupation.
States are bound to make it clear at all
times that South Africa has no legal auth¬
ority to levy or collect taxes in Namibia.
Consequently, governments whose natio¬
nals invest in Namibia should not grant
them tax credits for "taxes" paid on such
investments to the South African Govern¬
ment or its local surrogate.
Similarly, States should recognize that
the Republic of South Africa has no valid
authority to issue permits, concessions,
licences, mining and prospecting rights,
and so on. For this reason the Council for
Namibia has issued a decree, approved by
the General Assembly, making it unlawful
to exploit any Namibian natural resource
without a licence from the Council, or the
Commissioner acting for it. Under General
Assembly resolution 2248 (S-V) the United
Nations Council for Namibia was given full
authority "to promulgate laws, decrees
and administrative regulations as are
necessary..."
Resources exported without a United
Nations licence are subject to seizure and
forfeiture to the benefit of the Namibian
people, wherever in the world they may be
found.
The legal basis for the decree adopted by
the United Nations Council for Namibia and
approved by the General Assembly is quite
simple:
1. The United Nations has given full
powers to the United Nations Council
for Namibia to protect the natural
resources of Namibia on behalf of the
people of Namibia.
2. The mining and export licences issued
by the South Africans in respect of
Namibian resources were granted by an
illegal authority and are null and void.
3. The natural wealth of Namibia belongs
to the people of Namibia and not to the
illegal administration set up by the
Government of South Africa nor to
South Africa nor to any firm authorized
by South Africa to despoil Namibia of its
natural assets by an illegal authority.
4. In these circumstances it is open to the
United Nations Council for Namibia to
have these seized and held in trust for
the people of Namibia. These assets can
be pursued as stolen property illegally
taken from the people of Namibia.
There are ample precedents and auth¬
orities to support this view.
The decisions of the International Court
of Justice and the Security Council are
clear and unambiguous. South Africa
must relinquish all claims over Namibia and
surrender the Territory to the United
Nations. It will then be for the United
Nations to ensure the holding of free elec¬
tions on the basis of universal adult suf¬
frage for the whole Territory as one entity;
such elections to be held under the super¬
vision and control of the United Nations.
The elections will be to á constituent
assembly which will choose an interim
government and adopt a constitution for
Namibia.
The Security Council has also insisted on
a number of preliminary steps such as an
immediate amnesty for all political priso¬
ners and freedom of movement and free¬
dom of association for all SWAPO mem¬
bers in the Territory. While South Africa
does not accept SWAPO as representing
the majority of the population of Namibia,
it does reluctantly agree that SWAPO is the
biggest single political entity in the country.
The danger is that unless the South Afri¬
can Government agrees rapidly with the
terms laid down by the United Nations, the
existing armed conflict will escalate, thus
rendering a peaceful transfer of power
much more difficult.
The United Nations, in cooperation with
Unesco, has established in Lusaka the U.N.
Institute for Namibia. This is an institute for
applied research and training to prepare the
nucleus of a civil administration for an inde¬
pendent Namibia. The students over 100
of them are all Namibians.
The very highly qualified staff are all Afri¬
cans and many of them are Namibians.
Even now, the institute is in a position to
provide Namibians who could assume
administrative responsibilities. Ultimately
it is the intention that the institute will form
the nucleus of the future University of
Namibia.
The initiative of the United Nations in the
setting up of the Institute for Namibia was
constructive and far sighted. It will do
much to remedy the effects of South Afri¬
can misrule of the Territory.
Sean MacBride
Namibians
train
for
tomorrow
by Hage G. Geingob
THE Universal Declaration of Human
Rights clearly states that everyone
has the right to education and that
education shall be free. This right is denied
to almost the entire Namibian population.
In 1949, when the Nationalist Party came
to power in South Africa, the government
officially took over the administration of
African education in Namibia, which till
then had been in the hands of missionary
societies. Even though there is now a more
co-ordinated curriculum, the quality and
content of education have not improved. In
both South Africa and Namibia it could be
defined as an instrument to perpetuate
white domination.
The policies of the Nationalist Party are
the same in South Africa as in Namibia.
HAGE GOTTFRIED GEINGOB of Namibia has been
Director of the U.N. Institute for Namibia at Lusaka
(Zambia) since 1975. From 1964 to 1971, he was Chief
Representative of the South WestAfrica People's Orga¬
nization (SWAPO) to the United Nations and sub¬
sequently became a staff member of the Office of
the U.N. Commissioner for Namibia.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
In Namibia race determines which school system white, coloured or African a child must enter. The
African system is further segregated, along ethnic lines: above (from left to right) a Herero, a Baster and a
Damara girl. In black schools the level of teaching is very low, and only a few dozen pupils graduate each
year from secondary school. To prepare for Namibian independence and to train administrators for the future
state, the U.N. in cooperation with Unesco has set up the U.N. Institute for Namibia in Lusaka (Zambia).
Apartheid permeates the entire educational
system in Namibia: there are three separate
school systems, one for whites, one for
coloureds and one for Africans. The Afri¬
can system is even further segregated
according to ethnic groupings: hence there
are Herero schools, Ovambo schools,
Nama/Damara schools, and so forth.
Education for whites is compulsory up to
age 16, whereas education for African chil¬
dren is not compulsory at any age. It is
extremely rare that an African child com:
pletes even primary schooling: 97.8 per
cent leave school before then.
In secondary education, the teachers
have a shockingly low level of education.
Over 60 per cent have only completed pri¬
mary school.
Students who complete their secondary
schooling and who wish to attend univer¬
sity must go to South Africa, for there are
no institutions of higher learning in
Namibia, for either Europeans or Africans.
It is very easy for whites to obtain passports
and financial assistance, whereas for Afri¬
cans it is very difficult.
Consequently, many Namibians have
been forced to go elsewhere in order to
avail themselves of U.N. scholarships and
other aid offered by various associations
and foundations. It was only after many
Namibians had left the country and had
obtained their degrees abroad that South
Africa allowed a few to enter universities in
South Africa. This decision was sparked by
a SWAPO (South West Africa People's
Organization) statement that, as a libera¬
tion movement, it had trained more people
in 14 years than South Africa had done in
over 60 years.
University education for Africans in
Namibia continues to be a dream. Two or
three African students who do very well
and whose political persuasion is deemed
acceptable to the régime may be selected
and given a scholarship to one of the three
Bantu Universities in South Africa. But they
are advised to study theology or teacher
training and not courses that contribute to
nation-building, such as engineering, medi¬
cine or the sciences.
In the final analysis, Bantu education is
designed to provide Africans with only that
measure of self-management which will
alleviate feelings of acute deprivation, thus
minimizing the possibility of African revolt
while perpetuating white economic and
political interests.
A new Namibia must therefore have a
new educational system. Both the U.N. Ins¬
titute for Namibia and SWAPO's Education
Centre at Nyango in Zambia are working
towards this end.
The Institute is to carry out research on
the educational system of Namibia to sug¬
gest solutions for the future Namibian
government. It is also training middle-level
administrative cadres in the field of
education.
Meanwhile, the SWAPO Educational Cen¬
tre has established its own primary and
secondary school systems and conducts
adult literacy courses. Its aim is to over¬
come an ingrained colonial mentality and to
restore to the Namibian his self-respect as a
citizen able to contribute to the new
Namibia which is about to be created... a
Namibia where all will be educated regard¬
less of colour, ethnic origin or sex.
Hage G. Geingob
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
For
Rhodesia's
blacks,
the name
Zimbabwe
symbolizes
past glories
and future
freedom
by
Marion
O'Callaghan
MARION O'CALLAGHAN of Trinidad
and Tobago is a social anthropologist and
the author of Southern Rhodesia: the
Effects of a Conquest Society on Educa¬
tion, Culture and Information (Unesco,
1977; see inside back cover) as well as
various articles on racism and culture. A
staff member of Unesco's Division of the
International Development of Social
Sciences, she is also a novelist under her
maiden name of Marion Patrick Jones.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE two names Southern Rhodesia and Zimbabwe symboli¬
cally represent the history of a single country. The Zimbab¬
we complex of ruins, south of Salisbury, goes back to the
11th century and was the political and religious centre of an Afri¬
can society which spread far beyond the boundaries of today's
state.
This civilization produced not only impressive buildings but also
pottery, a settled agriculture, domesticated livestock, mining and
smelting, and the manufacture of fabrics. There was already some
occupational specialization and a highly developed internal and
external trade.
We will not go into the details of shifts of power and of sov¬
ereignty within Zimbabwe, preferring to concentrate on the crea¬
tion of Southern Rhodesia. In 1870 Lobengula became king of
Zimbabwe and faced the growing push of British influence north¬
wards from South Africa.
The Moffatt treaty signed between the government of the Unit¬
ed Kingdom and Lobengula established a British sphere of interest
Zimbabwe. Through the Rudd concession, the British South
Africa Company was granted mineral rights. There is, however,
some indication that Lobengula did not understand and was not
told the implications of these two treaties.
In 1890, that part of Zimbabwe known as Mashonaland was
occupied by the "Pioneer Column", an expeditionary force fund¬
ed by the British South Africa Company.
Within a few years white settlers proceeded to evict the Shona
people from their lands, to exercise an authority never before exer¬
cised by Lobengula, and to force the Shona people to work for
them. The European settlers also dislocated the Matabele's eco¬
nomy, seized their cattle, countermanded the orders of Lobengula,
and punished the Shona and the Matabele if they resisted settler
. rule.
In the face of this the Shona and the Matabele united in the
"rebellion" of 1897. This was harshly put down, and in its wake
was established today's Rhodesia, named after Cecil Rhodes, the
founder of the British South Africa Company, which was deleg¬
ated by the British Government to administer Rhodesia. In prac¬
tice this meant settler rule, and from the beginning ensured that
the colonization of Rhodesia would follow a different pattern from
that of most of Africa.
Indeed as early as the end of 1898, the major institutions of
administration and legislative policies had been elaborated. These
were to last in their broad outlines until today. A franchise was ela¬
borated that was, like today's, theoretically non-racist. But few
Africans could meet the property, monetary and literacy qualifica¬
tions for voting.
White political power was consolidated by the unequal tenure
and allocation of land, by white control over the labour power of
blacks, and by the system of education which ensured that there
was a white monopoly of technology as well as of the trade
unions. The old society was shattered.
Chiefs and headmen were retained but they were apppointed
and could be removed by the central white government: they were
salaried civil servants. Their power was now subordinate to that of
the white District Commissioners and their main occupation was to
collect taxes for the white government.
Just as important was the introduction of a money economy,
which while it did notand was not meant toend the semi-
subsistence farming of all Africans, forced many to seek work on
European farms or mines in order to buy the things they needed
and which were no longer produced, or which were new needs
created by the nature of the new economy.
African society was further disrupted by the introduction of a
new religion Christianity that was closely linked with the politi¬
cal power of the settlers, -by. new laws elaborated by a settler
government, by new methods of settling disputes (the European
courts) and above all by the massive alienation of land and cattle
which, together with a hut tax, forced Africans to become
labourers.
Land became more important for the settlers as the hopes enter¬
tained by Rhodes of vast mineral wealth receded. The result was a
continuing appropriation of African land from the 19th century on.
Indeed, between 1936 and 1959, according to a Rhodesian Select
Parliamentary Committee on Resettlement (1960), over 113,000
Africans were compulsorily removed from "white" farming areas.
B
Y 1969, 250,000 whites had the legal right enshrined in the
Constitution to 44.95 million acres, while 5 million Africans
had the right to 44.94 million acres.
Africans, moreover, have been hampered by the nature of mar¬
keting, which is tilted in favour of white farms; by the little com¬
mercial credit available to modernize their holdings compared with
that granted to whites; by the fact that they have to pay higher
interest rates than Europeans on what credit is available; by the
lack of resources to employ paid labour; by the small size of their
farms; and by the fact that their land is often poorer than that alio- .
cated to white farm's.
It is not surprising, therefore, that with the constant degradation
of the African rural areas, an increasing number of Africans were
forced to seek work in the white areas, not only to maintain them¬
selves but to subsidize the reserves.
Work on the plantations is poorly paid, and contact with outside
society is discouraged. In 1975, adult workers on European planta¬
tions were often getting as little as between $8 (Rhodesian) and
$15 (R) for 30 days' work, semi-skilled and skilled workers earning
between $30 (R) and $40 (R). In 1964, the African agricultural
wage was 4.6 per cent of the European wage; by 1974 it had drop¬
ped to 4.3 per cent.
Child labour is often part of the farm school system, children
being given half-day schooling and $1.50 (R) to $3.00 (R) for
30 days.
The mines present a similar picture. In 1964 in mining the ave¬
rage African wage was only 8.6 per cent of the average European
wage. By 1974, average African wages were only 6.9 per cent of '
the average European wage.
The difference between European wages and African wages has
become greater in nearly every sector of the economy, but it is in
mining and farming that inequality is greatest.
Most Rhodesian Africans therefore prefer to go to the urban f
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
¡L
m^t&5ry'
Drawing ©
Ian Mackenzie Kerr
Zimbabwe:
eloquent ruins
of an ancient
capital
Massive granite remains of Zimbabwe
dating back to the 11th century rise on a
hilltop to the south of Salisbury. They
include a 10-metre-high tower and
ramparts (detail, right) that measure some
300 metres around. Zimbabwe, which
means "dwelling of a chief" in the Shona
language, was a sanctuary and the burial
place of kings, as well as the capital of a
flourishing African civilization until it was
sacked in the early 19th century. Drawing
above depicts one of the famous carved
soapstone birds discovered at Zimbabwe
that were symbolic representations of the
dead kings.
. areas to seek jobsthe men in industry, the women in domestic
* service.
African movement is regulated by the 1957 African's Identifica¬
tion and Registration Act. This law, which provides not only for
the registration of Africans, but obliges them to carry a special
identification card, is the Rhodesian equivalent of the South Afric¬
an pass laws. Certain Africans are exempt from this: chiefs, head¬
men, property owners, master farmers and licensed traders.
The number of Africans who can inhabit a particular township is
fixed, and Africans who live there must prove that they are either in
employment or have a bona fide reason for being there. The effect
is to limit African urbanization to the number of Africans needed
by European employers and to channel African labour into farm
jobs.
The African townships themselves are, partly for security rea¬
sons, isolated by land and trees from the European areas. In the
major European towns the townships have not been incorporated
into the European municipalities. They remain outside of them
although often controlled by themand therefore do not elect
municipal councils and are not administered in the same way as
white municipalities.
Housing in the African areas is often deplorable, and recreation
centres, local amenities and social welfare are unequal to those
available in white areas. African social welfare is maintained
through the beer profits of halls often run by the municipalities.
There is therefore a vested interest in promoting the sale of beer
and its consumption.
Housing varies from tin huts to men's barracks and family dwel¬
lings. The tendency however is to establish single dwellings, so
even when men can legally bring their wives from the rural areas,
there may be no accommodation for them. The result is a new type
of concubinage, prostitution, and a number of relatives who live
there illegally children hoping to get to school or adults looking
for a job.
It is not surprising, therefore, that the African rate of urbaniza¬
tion is much lower than that of Europeans. However, in spite of.
the government policy of regulating the flow of Africans to the
towns, the African urban population has risen from 676,000 in 1969
to about 970,000 today.
Africans, with the exception of a small middle-class of teachers,
lawyers and priests, are employed in the lowest paid jobs in the
economy: semi-skilled and unskilled labour, with as many as 14.08
per cent in domestic service.
It could be argued that this picture would change with the
spread of education. Let us therefore look at the educational
policy and practice of the Rhodesian authorities.
Separation in education started with European settlement.
After conquest, the dynamics of European control led directly to
the establishment of separate systems, first for the education of
settlers, and then for that of Africans.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
African education was intended to maintain African inferiority
both on the labour market and in terms of access to political
power.
'' Both the economic role expected from Africans and the method
of maintaining white political control through a limited franchise
dictated the level and the content of African education. Efforts
were concentrated on providing Africans with primary education,
and then only on the first four years of schooling, thus ensuring
that most Africans who had gone to school at all were
semi-literate.
Secondary education, on the other hand, expanded very slowly,
and there wasand isan increasing emphasis, not on the acade¬
mic subjects that lead to a university career, but on technical sub¬
jects, such as carpentry for boys or domestic science for girls.
As long as the status quo was not threatened, African education
could remain the affair of the missionaries. This provided a
method of, not only conversion, but of decreasing government
expenditure on African education. After the Rhodesian Front
made a so-called Unilateral Declaration of Independence in 1965,
and in the light of statements from most churches in favour of
social justice, the Rhodesian authorities took certain measures to
increase government control over education and to implement the
government's overall policy of "community development".
Rhodesia has not officially announced an apartheid policy. Its
aim has rather been stated in the more neutral terms of "commu¬
nity development". The aims of "community development"
however, differ only slightly from the Bantustan policy of the
South African Government.
In both cases apartheid and community development chiefs
are resurrected, tribes are recreated, and a so-called "traditional"
political structure imposed. It has nothing to do, however, with
the old traditions of black Rhodesians or black South Africans. It
is a modern device whereby it is hoped that nationalism will be
diverted into tribal loyalties.
The policy of the present illegal régime is to transfer African edu¬
cation from the missions to "responsible" community boards and
councils, themselves politically controlled by the central govern¬
ment. These community boards are to be responsible for collect¬
ing extra taxes and contributions for African education, thus
decreasing its cost to the white government as well as finding
"voluntary" African labqur for school building.
The financing of education follows the same lines as the division
of land. Approximately the same amount of money is spent by the
Rhodesian government on the education of white children as on
Africans. Yet there are 275,000 whites and. 6 million Africans.
We have gone into education in some detail. But the same
situation exists with regard to health services. Hospitals are segre¬
gated both because of deliberate policy and because housing areas
are segregated. Nor are they "separate but equal". Africans are
more likely to suffer from diseases linked to malnutrition and
poverty. They also have less access to medical care. The same
situation is repeated in access to amenities and social services:
water, electricity, roads, pensions.
The situation in Rhodesia, however, is not quite the same as that
in the Republic of South Africa. First, the present ratio between
the black and white population is much greater than in South
Africa, and in recent years the possibility of increasing the white
population by immigration has vanished: more whites now emi¬
grate than enter the country. Moreover, nearly 60 per cent of Rho¬
desian whites were born outside Rhodesia. The excuse of 300
years' settlement used by the Afrikaners in South Africa is hardly
relevant to the situation of white Rhodesia.
The so-called Unilateral Declaration of Independence in 1965
was in fact made to stem any advance towards majority rule.
The flowering
of modern
Shona sculpture
In recent years, a number of sculptors of the Shona
people, descendants of the builders of ancient
Zimbabwe, have come to the forefront. They are
producing powerful creations that have nothing in
common with copies of traditional Shona objects
made for the tourist trade. Exhibitions of their work
have been held at major museums in New York, Paris
and London. A recurrent theme of Sona sculpture is
a head with two or more faces, with a cyclopic eye in
mid-forehead. Above, "Spirit of Wisdom" by
the Shona sculptor John Takawira.
Times, however, have changed since 1965. First of all the Portu¬
guese empire collapsed and was replaced by independent states
such as Mozambique^which is hostile to racism, and which,
moreover, won its independence through armed revolt. Guerrilla
incursions into Rhodesia had started before the independence of
Mozambique: they increased afterwards.
But besides armed revolt, Rhodesia was faced with the non-
recognition of its so-called independence and with sanctions
which partly dislocated its. economy. It continues- to exist only
because of the massive assistance still provided by the Republic of
South Africa.
The arms budget soared; Africans were forcibly removed to be
concentrated into so-called "safe" guarded villages; the age for
compulsory military service was extended; and a series of "raids",
sometimes amounting to an invasion, was made on Mozambique
and other front-line African states. Even internally, the chiefs on
whom the Rhodesian authorities depended were less willing to be
informers, faced with the opposition of their people.
Faced with almost total isolation and an African population
determined to be free, supremacy has become impossible to main¬
tain without a massive military effort. Even so, it is unlikely to last.
Indeed, Africans look confidently to the future. For is not white
rule at best only a century in the long history of their country and
will not Zimbabwe continue long after Rhodesia is nothing but a
name?
Marion O'Callaghan
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Stigma
on South African
sport
by Stéphane A. Ogouki
OVER the last decade, the Supreme
Council for Sport in Africa, which
has 43 Member States, has been
one of the harshest critics of racial discri¬
mination in sport.
Though the white minority régimes in
South Africa and Rhodesia are champions
of racial discrimination today, it should not
be forgotten that racism is nothing new in
Africa. Racist attitudes date back to the
time when the whites first settled in black
Africa: as the indigenous inhabitants were
not really human beings, it was better not
to mix with them.
Apartheid in South African sport is sim¬
ply the application of the official policy of
"separate development" to the playing
field. Athletes are divided according to
race into whites, Asians, coloureds and
blacks, the latter being further subdivided
according to ethnic groupings.
Articles 1 and 24 of the Charter of the
International Olympic Committee (IOC)
expressly forbid any form of discrimina¬
tion, and their spirit is echoed in the sta¬
tutes of the various international sports
federations. It was because they did not
comply with these articles that South Afri¬
ca and Rhodesia were excluded from the
Olympic movement, the. former in 1970,
the latter in 1975.
"Separate development" in South Afric¬
an sport means that non-white athletes are
barred from joining white sports clubs,
that white teams may not compete against
non-white teams ("mixed" teams do not
exist), and that games and sports are admi-.
nistered by organizations corresponding
to racial groups. Lastly, only white sports
organizations represented South Africa at
the international level.
It goes without saying that the best
sports facilities are found in areas reserved
for whites. Non-whites have no access to
them, except on special occasions such as
visits by foreign dignitaries or committees
investigating racial integration. Even then,
non-whites are confined to areas fenced
off with barbed wire, and in no circum¬
stances can they use the facilities for their
own competitions.
Some putative attempts at integration
have been made, the most spectacular
being the so-called "multi-racial" games.
Anyone can attend these events, but each
racial group of spectators is confined to a
specific area which is separated from the
others by barbed wire. The whites com
pete among themselves to select their
champions, then the non-whites do the
same. Black athletes are obliged to wear
jerseys bearing the name of their ethnic
group in capital letters.
The only real efforts made by the lead¬
ers of South African sport have been the
direct result of internal opposition to apar¬
theid. This opposition was sparked off by
South Africa's exclusion from almost all
the governing bodies of international sport,
a situation which many South African
athletes cannot accept.
HHHHHMBHBBHMHIH
Because of its persistence in practising racial segregation in sport. South
Africa has been expelled from the Olympic movement (1970) and many
other international sports federations, including the International
Federation of Football Associations (FIFA) in 1976. Above, a
Johannesburg mine-worker joins in an improvised soccer game.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Unesco's role
in alerting world opinion
IN 1955, the Union of South Africa with¬
drew from Unesco. The reason given
was "interference in South African
racial problems" by means of Unesco publi¬
cations and studies being distributed in
South Africa.
These studies proved that the theory of
racial inequality- had no scientific founda¬
tion, that intermarriage between individuals
of differing "racial" groups was not
harmful, and that racial separation was not
"natural" to the human species but was
often imposed by discriminatory practices.
In view of this South Africa decided to leave
Unesco.
By 1955, the system of apartheid was
already firmly established in South Africa.
The Population Registration Act of 1950 had
divided the population into three main
groups: the Africans (called Bantu); the
coloureds (persons of mixed European and
African or Asian origins); and the whites.
Since 1952, the movement and residence of
Africans had been more tightly controlled.
The first major application of apartheid to
education dated from 1953.
Unesco has always sought to keep world
opinion informed about these questions. In
1965, the United Nations Special Committee
on the Policies of Apartheid of the Republic
of South Africa requested Unesco to pre¬
pare a study on "the effects of apartheid in
the fields of education, science and
culture". Unesco's Executive Board accept¬
ed this task and added another field of
research: information.
The report appeared in 1967. A second
revised, and enlarged edition was published
in 1972, and the report was further updated
in 1975. It concluded that " 'separate deve¬
lopment'... is a policy of deliberate inequa
lity built into the educational system,
expressed in scientific and cultural activi¬
ties, and underlined in the regulations-
governing access to information."
In 1973-1974, again at the request of the
United Nations, Unesco sponsored a twin
study: Racism and Apartheid in Southern
Africa. Part I, South Africa and Namibia,
appeared in 1974 and Part II, Rhodesia, by
Reginald Austin, came out in the following
year. In 1974, Unesco also published Portu¬
guese Colonialism: the End of an Era.
In 1976 came a study on the African town¬
ship of Mucheke, which is located at the
edge of the white town of Fort Victoria in
Southern Rhodesia. The study analyzes the
living conditions of Africans and whites in
each of these communities, and their inter¬
relations.
In 1977, Unesco published Southern Rho¬
desia: The effects ofa Conquest Society on
Education, Culture and Information, by
Marion O'Callaghan with an introduction by
Reginald Austin. (See inside back cover.)
This study shows the degree to which the
education provided for Africans is inferior
to white education, as well as giving a list of
banned books and describing how the radio
and press are controlled. A further contribu¬
tion to this series of works, Namibia: the
Effects of Apartheid on the Economy and
on Education, is to appear at the end of
1977.
Unesco is thus actively pursuing its task
of informing the public. This was stressed
by the Director-General of Unesco,
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, in his opening
address to the World Conference for Action
against Apartheid, held in Lagos (Nigeria) in
August 1977. Mr. M'Bow drew attention to
certain facts concerning South Africa: that
most newspapers published for the blacks
are in the hands of white financial groups;
that most African writers are in exile; and
that in 1974-1975 expenditure on education
totalled 131 million rands for Africans (71
per cent of the population) as against
435 million rands for whites (17 per cent of
the population).
Further research is in progress, including
a study on the way in which the internatio¬
nal press has presented the situation in
South Africa over a ten-year period. A spe¬
cial effort will also be made to analyze ob¬
stacles to the circulation of anti-apartheid
information.
Another study will examine the effect of
apartheid and racism on the situation of
women in South Africa, Namibia and
Zimbabwe.
Unesco has not, however, confined itself
solely to informing the public. In 1971, it
organized a meeting at Dar-es-Salaam (Tan¬
zania) on "the influence of colonialism on
the artist, his milieu and his public in deve¬
loping countries". In 1976, Unesco con¬
vened a conference at Maputo (Mozambi¬
que) on "Social Structure, Revolutionary
Change and Culture in Southern Africa".
This meeting brought together for the first
time an international group of social scien¬
tists and members of the liberation move¬
ments of Zimbabwe, Namibia and South
Africa. Unesco also contributed to the
Dakar International Conference (January
1976) devoted to the violation of human
rights in Namibia.
Finally, Unesco has given direct assis¬
tance for education to several liberation
movements recognized by the Organization
of African Unity. Aid totalled $ 2 million in
1975-1976.' This cooperation will be
strengthened in the near future.
The Supreme Council for Sport in Africa
is convinced that the Pretoria régime will be
forced to liberalize its policy, so that all
South African athletes will enjoy the same
opportunity to compete and be judged ac¬
cording to their prowess as athletes and
not according to the colour of their skin.
In Rhodesia, racial discrimination is not
institutionalized as it is in South Africa,
but this does notmean that sport is inte¬
grated. A series of legal provisions inherit¬
ed from the British colonial period was up.-
dated, enabling the Salisbury régime to
practise apartheid in sport just like South
Africa.
The laws governing land allocation have
divided the country into two zones, one for
whites, the other for non-whites. Sports
facilities are by and large in the white areas,
and are managed by private clubs whose
rules discourage non-whites from apply¬
ing for membership.
Should these obstacles prove insuffi¬
cient, they are reinforced by laws obliging
people to practise sports only in areas allot¬
ted to their racial group. As there are very
few sports facilities in the black areas, the
Africans are to all intents and purposes
banned from sport.
The Supreme Council for Sport in Africa
is fighting this curious conception of sport
because all its Member States are pro¬
foundly hostile to apartheid and have broken
diplomatic relations with Pretoria and Salis¬
bury. They were spurred to take action
because the International Olympic Commit¬
tee did not attack the problem until 1963,
although by then apartheid had already
been practised for some years. The mem¬
bers of the IOC knew what was happening
in South Africa, but they did not admit the
facts until they had heard evidence from
. a number of committees of inquiry.
Putting South African sport in quaran
tine is the only way to get the Pretoria
régime to admit that in sport, as in other
fields, people should be judged solely on
merit. In August 1977, came news that the
four South African sports federations were
to merge into a single, fully integrated non-
racial association. If this is true, and if the
South African government does not veto
the merger, this first step will constitute
a great victory.
S.A. Ogouki
STEPHANE A. OGOUKI, Senegalese journalist, is
head of the press and information services of the
Supreme Council for Sport in Africa, which seeks to
develop sport throughout Africa and fights all forms of
discrimination in sport.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Africans from neighbouring countries such as Lesotho, Botswana and Malawi come to
work in South African and Rhodesian mines in the absence of employment at home. This
inflow ties white southern Africa's neighbours to the industrial nexus of apartheid and
keeps them in a state of economic dependence. Above, black mine-workers are
numbered and referred to by their number.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE United Nations system is in a
sense based on a paradox. A group
of Organizations, comprised exclu¬
sively of States, has as one of its
tasks the defence of human rights
vis-a-vis the governments of these
very same States.
Does this not imply that the
ultimate goal of those who wield political
power should always be the protection of
every individual and group, without any
form of discrimination?
P At the end of World War II the. United
Nations set itself a three-fold task in the
field of human rights:
the proclamation of a Universal Declara¬
tion of Human Rights that was to be taken
"as a common standard of achievement for
all peoples and all nations";
the elaboration of one or several interna¬
tional covenants on human rights having
the force of law in all the ratifying states;
the setting up of bodies to supervise the
observance of the covenants.
with the optional protocol, on 23 March
1976(1).
The rights proclaimed in the Universal
Declaration fall into two categories: on the
one hand, civil and political rights and, on
the other hand, economic, social and cultu¬
ral rights. Because of the changing patterns
of society in recent years, it has become
imperative to formulate what the Director
General of Unesco has termed "the third
generation of human rights".
The first generation concerns "negative"
rights, in the sense that their respect
requires that the state do nothing to inter¬
fere with individual liberties, and corres¬
pond roughly to the civil and political rights.
The second generation, on the other
hand, requires positive action by the state
to be implemented, as is the case with
most social, economic and cultural rights.
The international community is now em¬
barking upon a third generation of human
rights which may be called "rights of
solidarity".
A 30-year
struggle
The sustained efforts to give force of law
to the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights
by Karel Vasak
The first part of this task was completed
on 10 December 1948 with the proclama¬
tion by the General Assembly of the United
Nations of the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights.
The second and third parts were only
accomplished 18 years later, with the adop¬
tion on 16 December 1966 of two cove¬
nants on human rights. One dealt with
economic, social and cultural rights; the
other, completed by an optional protocol
providing machinery for complaints by in¬
dividuals, dealt with civil and political
rights. The first covenant came into effect
on 3 January 1976. The second, along
KAREL VASAK, French jurist, is Director of Unesco's
Division of Human Rights and Peace. He has collabo¬
rated with the principal authors of the Universal Decla¬
ration of Human Rights, including the late René Cassin
with whom he was a co-founder of Revue des Droits de
l'Homme: Human Rights Journal, an international quar¬
terly on the theory and evolution of human rights in
international law. He has taught at The Hague Aca¬
demy of International Law, the school of law of the uni¬
versity of California at Berkeley and at other universities
(Singapore, Bangkok, Besançon, Nairobi, etc.). His La
Convention Européenne des Droits de l'Homme ("The
European Convention on Human Rights"), published in
1964, was awarded a prize by the Paris Academy of
Moral and Political Sciences.
Such rights include the right to develop¬
ment, the right to a healthy and ecologi¬
cally balanced environment, the right to
peace, and the right to ownership of the
common heritage of mankind. Since these .
rights reflect a certain conception of
community life, they can only be imple¬
mented by the combined efforts of every¬
one: individuals, states and other bodies,
as well as public and private institutions.
The Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, like the French Declaration of the
Rights of Man and of the Citizen in 1789,
has had an immense impact throughout the
world. It has been called a modern addition
to the New Testament, and the Magna
Carta of humanity, and has become a cons¬
tant source of inspiration for governments,
for judges and for national and interna¬
tional legislators.
The constitutions of many states express
the ¡deals enshrined in the Declaration, and
(1) As of October 1977, the number of Member States
that have ratified or acceded to these covenants is 69 .
for the Covenant on Economic, Social and Cultural
Rights, and 68 for the Covenant on Civil and Political
Rights.
in some cases even incorporate its provi¬
sions verbatim. Laws without number
have been drawn up or modified to tie in
with specific clauses or to reflect the spirit
of the Declaration,
Time and again judges have used it to
buttress their most convincing arguments.
Countless men and women have fought
and suffered in its name.
On the international level, the Declara¬
tion has become so widely accepted as the
basis for universal and regional norms in
the defence of human rights that one may
ask what its legal force is. For since it is not
a treaty and therefore not a compulsory
legal instrument the Declaration may ini¬
tially seem to have no more binding force
than any other strong recommendation of
the General Assembly.
However, in recent years, there has been
a tendency, insofar as the Declaration is
concerned, to look further than the distinc¬
tion between mandatory and non-manda¬
tory texts. Some specialists today consider
that the Universal Declaration is binding on
Member States; others feel it has become
part of customary law; still others see it as a
kind of "common law" for all mankind.
In all probability, none of these views is
entirely correct. But by recognizing the
Universal Declaration as a living document
and leaving the jurists to argue among
themselves, one can proclaim one's faith in
the future of mankind.
The adoption of the Universal Declara¬
tion in 1948 opened the way for the drafting
of a "network" of texts of unequal juridical
value. Today the corpus of international
law governing human rights is comprised
of some 15 declarations, the most import¬
ant being the Declaration on the Granting
of Independence to Colonial Countries and
Peoples, adopted by the U.N. on 14
December 1960.
In addition, some 50 treaties can be con¬
sidered as offshoots of the principles laid
down in the Universal Declaration. Some,
were drawn up within the framework or
under the auspices of the U.N. or its Spe¬
cialized Agencies, notably the International
Labour Organization and Unesco. Others,
like the European Convention on Human
Rights of 4 November 1950 and the Ameri¬
can Convention on Human Rights of 22
November 1969, are limited geographically
to such regional organizations as the Coun¬
cil of Europe or the Organization of Ameri¬
can States.
The task now facing human rights orga¬
nizations, which have grown in number
over the years, is not so much to draft
new texts as to see that existing texts are
applied and respected.
The work of the U.N. Commission of
Human Rights, which is made up of repre¬
sentatives of Member States, has. been
fairly successful as regards the definition of
international norms concerning human
rights. With the entry into force of the
International Covenants on Human Rights,
the U.N. added a new human rights body
to its structure which may help it achieve
one of its original goals. The Human
Rights Committee, established in accor¬
dance with the Covenant on Civil and Poli¬
tical Rights, will play a more or less impor-
CONTINUED PAGE 32
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The Universal Declara
Proclaimed by the United
Preamble
Whereas recognition of the inherent dignity and of the equal and inalien¬
able rights of all members of the human family is the foundation of free¬
dom, justice and peace in the world.
Whereas disregard and contempt for human rights have resulted in barb¬
arous acts which have outraged the conscience of mankind, and the
advent of a world in which human beings shall enjoy freedom of speech
and belief and freedom from fear and want has been proclaimed as the
highest aspiration of the common people,
Whereas it is essential, if man is not to be compelled to have recourse, as a
last resort, to rebellion against tyranny and oppression, that human rights
should be protected by the rule of law, ' ,
Whereas it is essential to promote the development of friendly relations
between nations.
Whereas the peoples of the United Nations have in the Charter reaffirmed
their faith in fundamental human rights, in the dignity and worth of the
human person and in the equal rights of men and women and have deter¬
mined to promote social progress and better standards of life in larger
freedom.
Whereas Member States have pledged themselves to achieve, in co¬
operation with the United Nations, the promotion of universal respect for
and observance of human rights and fundamental freedoms.
Whereas a common understanding of these rights and freedoms is of the
greatest importance for the full realization of this pledge.
Now, Therefore,
The General Assembly proclaims
This Universal Declaration of Human Rights' as a common standard of
achievement for all peoples and all nations, to the end that every individual
and every organ of society, keeping this Declaration constantly in mind,
shall strive by teaching and education to promote respect for these rights
and freedoms and by progressive measures, national and international, to
secure their universal and effective recognition and observance, both
among the peoples of Member States themselves and among the peoples
of territories under their jurisdiction.
Article 1 - All human beings are born free and equal in dignity and
rights. They are endowed with reason and conscience and
should act towards one another in a spirit of brotherhood.
Article 2 - Everyone is entitled to all the rights and freedoms set forth
in this Declaration, without distinction of any kind, such as
race, colour, sex, language, religion, political or other opinion, national or
social origin, property, birth or other status.
Furthermore, no distinction shall be made on the basis of the political,
jurisdictional or international status of the country or territory to which a
person belongs, whether it be independent, trust, non-self-governing or
under any other limitation of sovereignty.
Article 3 - Everyone has the right to life, liberty and security of person.
Article 4 - No one shall beheld in slavery or servitude; slavery and the
slave trade shall be prohibited in all their forms.
Article 5 - No one shall be subjected to torture or to cruel, inhuman or
degrading treatment or punishment.
Article 6 - Everyone has the right to recognition everywhere as a per¬
son before the law.
Article 7 - All are equal before the law and are entitled without any
discrimination to equal protection of the law. All are entitl¬
ed to equal protection against any discrimination in violation
of this Declaration and against any incitement to such discrimination.
Article 8 - Everyone has the right to an effective remedy by the compe¬
tent national tribunals for acts violating the fundamental
rights granted him by the constitution or by law.
Article 9 No one shall be subjected to arbitrary arrest, detention or
exile.
Article 10 -' Everyone is entitled in full equality to a fair and public hear¬
ing by an independent and impartial tribunal, in the deter¬
mination of his rights and obligations and of any criminal charge against
him.
Article 11 - (1) Everyone charged with a penal offence has the right to
, be presumed innocent until proved guilty according to law
in a public trial at which he has had all the guarantees necessary for his
defence.
(2) No one shall be held guilty of any penal offence on account of any act
or omission which did not constitute a penal offence, under national or
international law, at the time when it was committed. Nor shall a heavier
penalty be imposed than the one that was applicable at the time the penal
offence was committed.
Article 12 - No one shall be subjected to arbitrary interference with his
privacy, family, home or correspondence, nor to attacks
upon his honour and reputation. Everyone has the right to the protection
of the law against such interference or attacks.
Article 13 - (1) Everyone has the right to freedom of movement and resi¬
dence within the borders of each state.
(2) Everyone has the right to leave any country, including his own, and to
return to his country.
Article 14 - (1) Everyone has the right to seek and to enjoy in other
countries asylum from persecution.
(2) This right may not be invoked in the case of prosecutions genuinely
arising from non-political crimes or from acts contrary to the purposes and
principles of the United Nations.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
tion of Human Rights
Nations on 10 December 1948
Article 15 - (1) Everyone has the right to a nationality,
(2) No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his nationality nor
denied the right to change his nationality.
Article 16 - (1) Men and women of full age, without any limitation due
to race, nationality or religion, have the right to marry and to
found a family. They are entitled to equal rights as to marriage, during
marriage and at its dissolution.
(2) Marriage shall be entered into only with the free and full consent of the
intending spouses.
(3) The family is the natural and fundamental group unit of society and is
entitled to protection by society and the State.
Article 17 - (1) Everyone has the right to own property alone as well as
\ in association with others.
(2) No one shall be arbitrarily deprived of his property.
Article 18 - Everyone has the right to freedom of thought, conscience
and religion; this right includes freedom to change his
religion or belief, and freedom, either alone or in community with others
and in public or private, to manifest his religion or belief in teaching, prac¬
tice, worship and observance.
Article 19 - Everyone has the right to freedom" of opinion and
expression; this right includes freedom to hold opinions
without interference and to seek, receive and impart information and ideas
through any media and regardless of frontiers.
Article 20 - (1) Everyone has the right to freedom of peaceful assembly
and association.
(2) No one may be compelled to belong to an association.
Article 21 - (1) Everyone has the right to take part in the government of
his country, directly or through freely chosen represen¬
tatives.
(2) Everyone has the right of equal access to public service in his country.
(3) The will of the people shall be the basis of the authority of government;
this will shall be expressed in periodic and genuine elections which shall be
by universal and equal suffrage and shall be held by secret vote or by equi¬
valent free voting procedures.
Article 22 - Everyone, as a member1 of society, has the right to social
security and is entitled to realization, through national effort
and international co-operation and in accordance with the organization and
resources of each State, of the economic, social and cultural rights indis¬
pensable for his dignity and the free development of his personality.
Article 23 - ( 1 ) Everyone has the right to work, to free.choice of employ¬
ment, to just and favourable conditions of work and to pro¬
tection against unemployment.
(2) Everyone, without any discrimination, has the right to equal pay for
equal work.
(3) Everyone who works has the right to just and favourable remuneration
ensuring for himself and his family an existence worthy of human dignity,
and supplemented, if necessary, by other means of social protection.
(4) Everyone has the right to form and to join trade unions for the protec¬
tion of his interests.
Article 24 - Everyone has the right to rest and leisure, including reason¬
able limitation of working hours and periodic holidays with
pay.
Article 25 - (1) Everyone has the right to a standard of living adequate
for the health and well-being of himself and of his family,
including food, clothing, housing and medical care and necessary social
services, and the right to security in the event of unemployment, sickness,
disability, widowhood, old age or other lack of livelihood in circumstances
beyond his control.
(2) Motherhood and childhood are entitled to special care and assistance.
All children, whether born in or out of wedlock, shall enjoy the same social
protection.
Article 26 - (1) Everyone has the right to education. Education shall be
free, at least in the elementary and fundamental stages.
Elementary education shall be compulsory. Technical and professional
education shall be made generally available and higher education shall be
equally accessible to all on the basis of merit.
(2) Education shall be directed to the full development of the human perso¬
nality and to the strengthening of respect for human rights and fundamen¬
tal freedoms. It shall promote understanding, tolerance and friendship
among all nations, racial or religious groups, and shall further the activities
of the United Nations for the maintenance of peace.
(3) Parents have a prior right to choose the kind of education that shall be
given to their children.
Article 27 - (1 (Everyone has the right freely to participate in the cultural
life of the community, to enjoy the arts and to share in
scientific advancement and its benefits.
(2) Everyone has the right to the protection of the moral and material inte¬
rests resulting from any scientific, literary or artistic production of which he
is the author.
Article 28 - Everyone is entitled to a social and international order in
which the rights and freedoms set forth in this Declaration
can be fully realized.
Article 29 - (1) Everyone has duties to the community in which alone
the free and full development of his personality is possible.
(2) In the exercise of his rights and freedoms, everyone shall be subject
only to such limitations as are determined by law solely for the purpose of
securing due recognition and respect for the rights and freedoms of others
and of meeting the just requirements of morality, public order and the
general welfare in a democratic society.
(3) These rights and freedoms may in no case be exercised contrary to the
purposes and principles of the United Nations.
Article 30 - Nothing in this Declaration may be interpreted as implying
for any State, group or person any right to engage in any
activity or to perform any act aimed at the destruction of any of the rights
and freedoms set forth herein.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
A 30-year struggle
tant role depending on the number of
states ratifying the Optional Protocol which
provides for individual petitions (2).
The activities of the Specialized Agen¬
cies of the United Nations such as the ILO
and Unesco are, broadly speaking, concen¬
trated on the promotion and protection of a
limited range of human rights.
The International Labour Organization,
concerned entirely with the protection of
social rights, has drafted some of the most
important human rights conventions. They
deal with such matters as forced labour,
and the right to organize and to participate
in collective bargaining. Above all, the ILO
has developed a number of procedures to
ensure that its Member States respect
human rights. The most important of these
concerns the international safeguarding of
trade union rights through the Committee
on Freedom of Association of the ILO
Governing Body, which has received over
1,000 complaints from trade unions.
Unesco seeks to promote education,
science, culture and information as rights
and fundamental freedoms. Thus it has
given priority to the fight against discrimi¬
nation in education and has drawn up a
convention to this effect. The right of
everyone to education is reaffirmed in ar¬
ticle 13 of the International Covenant on
Economic, Social and Cultural Rights.
Unesco has further elaborated this right .
in a series of conventions and recommen¬
dations, including the Recommendation
concerning Education for International
Understanding, Cooperation and Peace
and Education relating to Human Rights
and Fundamental Freedoms (1974).
In the major international documents on
human rights, cultural rights have a rather
curious status:
They are associated either with civil and
political rights (and thus, as we have seen,
are considered as "negative") or with
economic and social rights (and are consi¬
dered as "positive"). They sometimes
appear in both categories of human rights
(2) As of October 1977, the following 28 countries have
ratified or acceded to the Optional Protocol: Austria,
Barbados, Canada, China, Colombia, Costa Rica,
Cyprus, Denmark, Ecuador, El Salvador, Finland, Gui¬
nea, Honduras, Italy, Jamaica, Madagascar, Mauritius,
Netherlands, Norway, Panama, Peru, Philippines,
Senegal, Surinam, Sweden, Uruguay, Venezuela,
Zaire.
in documents produced by the same Orga¬
nization.
They are always defined juridically as
individual rights, whereas culture is essen¬
tially collective in nature, since it should be
available to the whole community.
In view of the uncertain status of cultural
rights, they should be recognized as having
a specific nature, since they are at once
individual and collective. Unesco has been
and still is working along these lines.
ARTICLE 27 of the Uni¬
versal Declaration refers
to the right of everyone
freely to participate in
the cultural life of the
community. It is only
recently, however, that action has been
taken to define how this right should be
exercised and to give the individual the
opportunity to express his cultural identity.
Intergovernmental conferences conven¬
ed by Unesco in Venice (1970), Helsinki
(1972) and Yogyakarta (1973) led to the
adoption by the General Conference at its
19th session in Nairobi on 26 November
1976 of the Recommendation on Participa¬
tion by the People at Large in Cultural Life
and their Contribution to It.
The protection of copyright and the
preservation of the cultural heritage are
indispensable if people are to participate
fully in cultural life. The moral and material
interests of all forms of intellectual output
are protected by a number of international
agreements, including the Universal Copy¬
right Convention of 1952, which was revis¬
ed in Paris in 1971.
As far as the protection of cultural pro¬
perty is concerned, Unesco has paid spe¬
cial attention to the preservation of certain
monuments, sites, manuscripts, collec¬
tions of books and archives from destruc¬
tion or damage in the event of armed
conflict, as well as from theft, pillage or
vandalism.
Freedom of expression as defined in
Article 19 of the Universal Declaration and
in the International Covenant on Civil and
Political Rights includes freedom to seek,
receive and impart by any means informa¬
tion and ideas of all kinds regardless of
frontiers. ,
The free flow of information has always
played an important role in Unesco's work.
But to meet the challenge of the vastly
increased volume of international com¬
munication and exchange of information
in a world in which facilities for the trans¬
mission and reception of information and
ideas are unevenly distributed, the Organi¬
zation has progressively broadened its
approach.
It has adopted a number of international
agreements in this field, beginning with the
Agreement Facilitating the International
Circulation of Visual and Auditory Materials
of an Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Character of 10 December 1948.
More recently, on 15 November 1972,
the General Conference proclaimed the
Declaration of Guiding Principles on the
. Use of Satellite Broadcasting for the Free
Flow of Information, the Spread of Educa¬
tion and Greater Cultural Exchange.
This brief survey of Unesco's activities
in the field of human rights, placed in the
legal perspective of the Universal Declara¬
tion, would be incomplete without a refer¬
ence to the sensitive issue of the action
which is or should be taken when private
individuals or non-governmental organiza¬
tions write to the Organization, claiming to
be the victims of violations of human rights
that fall within Unesco's competence.
The United Nations, which receives tens
of thousands of such complaints each year,
is faced with the same problem. The issue
has provoked many and often heated
debates.
At Unesco, it was decided in 1967 that a
committee of the Executive Board should
examine such complaints which fall within
Unesco's competence.
At its Nairobi session, the General
Conference requested that this procedure
should be made "more effective", and it is
currently being re-examined by the Execu¬
tive Board. In seeking a more effective way
of safeguarding the rights of individuals
and groups, Unesco intends to remain
faithful to its mission to serve mankind.
Karel Vasak
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
G3 P
ib
-
ß es
Unesco sets up
world communications
advisory group
Unesco has set up a 16-member international
group of advisers to examine world communica¬
tion problems. The group, comprising a wide
range of specialists, was set up following a reso¬
lution of Unesco's General Conference in 1976
and is to be headed by Mr. Sean MacBride of Ire¬
land (see biographical note page 16). It is
expected to make a preliminary report to
Unesco's 1978 General Conference and a full
report which will be available in 1979.
Cooperation guide
for developing countries
A guide informing developing countries of
services they can obtain from one another has
been published by the U.N. Development
Programme (UNDP). Entitled Directory of
Services for Technical Cooperation, the guide
lists over 900 organizations ' in 67 countries
which offer other developing countries technical
cooperation in 16 economic and social sectors.
Please send orders, accompanied by payment
($10.00 or equivalent in other currencies) to
TCDC Special Unit, UNDP, One United Nations
Plaza, New York, 10017, U.S.A.
Stamps
against racism
On 19 September 1977, the U.N. Postal
Administration at Geneva issued a set of four
commemorative stamps on the theme "Combat
Racism". The stamp issue is part of the U.N.'s
campaign to involve world opinion in the
struggle against racism and racial discrimination.
2,000 cell scientists trained
The International Cell Research Organization
(ICRO), which celebrates its 15th anniversary
this year, has organized courses for over 2,000
scientists from all over the world since its
creation under Unesco auspices in 1962. At a
ceremony held at the Pasteur Institute in Paris
to mark the anniversary, speakers emphasized
the shift in ICRO's priorities from Europe to the
developing world in the past 15 years.
International
Fair Play
Awards
The International Fair Play Committee has made
its annual Pierre de Coubertin awards to the
Hungarian fencer Jeno Kamuti. Presenting the
awards ata ceremony at Unesco HQ in Paris on
26 September 1977, the Director-General of
Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, declared
that the principle of fair play which links sporting
and ethical values should form the basis for the
International Charter of Physical Education and
Sport now being prepared by an intergovern¬
mental committee composed of 30 Unesco
Member States. The Charter will be submitted
to Unesco's General Conference in 1978. The k
International Fair Play Committee also awarded r '
Books
in 151 languages
A major exhibition of translated works-
one of many events marking the
60th anniversary of the October Revolution
by Boris I. Stukalin
Photo © Tass, Moscow
Each year in June, the village of
Mikhailovskoye in'the Pskov region
of the U.S.S.R. holds a book fair to
commemorate the great Russian
writer Pushkin, who spent part of his
life there.
AN important exhibition of translated
books was held in Moscow last
July. Over 13,000 exhibits were on
show, but they represented only a fraction
of the total Soviet output: since the founda¬
tion of the U.S.S.R., more than 2 billion
copies of over 73,000 translated works have
appeared. This impressive total is made up
of books written by authors from 136 coun¬
tries and published in 151 languages.
BORIS I. STUKALIN is chairman of the State Commit¬
tee of the U. S. S. R. Council of Ministers on Publishing,
Printing and Book Distribution.
As the U.S.S.R. developed, culturally as
well as economically, there was a corres¬
ponding growth in the publication of books,
including translations. In 1961, some 67 mil¬
lion copies of books and booklets by
foreign authors appeared in the U.S.S.R.
Five years later the figure had mounted to
97 million. During the same period 11,497
titles were translated, of which 457 million
copies were printed. Over 4,000 of these
titles (357 million copies) were fiction.
These translations were made not only
into Russian but into dozens of other lan¬
guages spoken by the different nationalities
and ethnic groups of the U.S.S.R.
For many foreign writers printings, are
bigger in the U.S.S.R. than in their own
countries. Over 200 of them have had
works published in the Soviet Union in edi¬
tions ranging from 1 million to 40 million
copies.
In 1976, for example, there were 65 print¬
ings of works by modern American
authors translated into nine languages of
the U.S.S.R. in either book or serial form,
and 25 printings of contemporary French
authors translated into 10 languages. Works
by modem writers constituted 50 per cent of .
the translations from English literature, and L
85 per cent of the Italian literature total. Y
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO NEWSROOM
, diplomas of honour to the U.S.S.R. ice hockey
team, the Luxembourg racing driver André Bas¬
tin, and Chris Ripard, a 12-year-old yachtsman
from Malta who successfully opposed the dis¬
qualification of an opponent during an interna¬
tional race, thus losing his chance to take part in
an international regatta. The committee also
made a posthumous award to Juan Manuel San-
tistéban, the Spanish cyclist who was killed in an
accident during the Tour of Italy.
Unesco award for
International Catholic Centre
The Paris-based International Catholic Centre for
Unesco tells Catholics in 100 countries about
Unesco's work through "The Month at Unes¬
co", a newsletter published in English, French,
Spanish and German. To mark the 30th anniver¬
sary of the Centre's creation, Mr. Amadou-
Mahtar M'Bow, the Director-General of Unesco,
presented Unesco's silver medal to Mr. Jean Lar-
naud, Secretary-General of the Centre since its
foundation.
Medal for a militant
Dorothy Nyembe, a leader in the struggle for
human rights in South Africa and in the wom¬
en's and rural labour movements, was sentenced
in March 1969 to 15 years' imprisonment under
the country's apartheid laws. The Food and
Agriculture Organization of the United Nations
(FAO) has issued a medal portraying Dorothy
Nyembe as Ceres, the Roman goddess of agri¬
culture. Ears of wheat are incorporated into the
portrait design, depicting Dorothy. Nyembe
against prison bars. The reverse side of the
medal shows a woman's hands breaking chains
and supporting a pot in the shape of southern
Africa, from which maize is growing. For further
information, please apply to the FAO Money and
Medals Office, FAO, 00100 Rome, Italy.
Education and the
environment
An intergovernmental conference on environ¬
mental education was held from 14 to 26 Octo¬
ber 1977 at Tbilisi (U.S.S.R.). More than 150
governments, nearly 80 international and regio¬
nal organizations and over 100 non-governmen¬
tal organizations were invited to attend the con¬
ference. Organized by Unesco with the co¬
operation of the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP), the conference was con¬
vened to work out recommendations for action
to promote and develop education at national,
regional and international levels that will help
solve and prevent environmental problems.
Unicef greeting cards
Unicef, the United Nations Children's Fund,
today "helps 116 developing countries to help
themselves", providing needy children with bet¬
ter nutrition, improved health care, clean, safe
water, and educational opportunities. For
nearly 30 years, sales of its greeting cards have
enabled the public to contribute to Unicef's pro¬
grammes. This year Unicef offers a wide selec
tion of cards ranging from five designs in mini-
format to full-size cards designed by artists from
some ten countries and a stationery portfolio
containing' ten different cards and five post¬
cards. All these cards are now available at
Unicef sales points throughout the world. A
1978 Unicef desk calendar is also available in two
versions, one trilingual (English, French, Span¬
ish), the other bilingual (French and German).
The calendar's theme is "the tree of life". Card
shown here is one of five designs from a 15th-
century Italian treatise on medicinal herbs.
BOOKS IN 151 LANGUAGES
Since the end of World War II about 1 bil¬
lion copies of books from Western coun¬
tries have been published in the U.S.S.R.
This figure includes: American authors,
7,377 works (221 million copies); French
authors, 4,664 works (298 million copies);
British authors, 4,590 works (230 million
copies); Italian authors, 901 works (16 mil¬
lion copies); Danish authors, 482 works (61
million copies).
The publication of translated works by
Asian, African and Latin American writers
is being stepped up. So far 764 books by
Indian writers have appeared (over 30 mil¬
lion copies), 288 translations from Turkish
(over 12 million copies) and 295 from Japa¬
nese (some 12 million copies).
In the last few years there has also been a
growing trend to publish anthologies of
poetry and prose from developing
countries. Four recent examples are: Above
All, a collection of stories by African writers
from Zambia, Kenya, Mozambique, Nigeria
and Uganda (translated into Armenian); a
volume of short stories by 30 modern Latin
American writers from Argentina, Brazil,
Venezuela, Mexico, Uruguay, Peru and
Costa. Rica (translated into Georgian); The
Poetry of Struggle, an anthology of writing
from Angola, Mozambique, Sao Tomé and
Principe, and the Cape Verde Islands; and
This is Our Land! a collection of patriotic
poems from Latin America (both published
in Russian).
A new series entitled "Writers and Think¬
ers of the Orient" has just been launched. It
aims to inform a non-specialized public
about Asian writers and thinkers from anti¬
quity, through medieval times to the pre¬
sent day.
The first Moscow International Book Fair,
held in September this year, marked a new
contribution to the implementation of the
agreements concluded at the Helsinki Con¬
ference on Security and Cooperation in
Europe, held in 1975. More than 1,500
publishers from 67 countries took part.
In the early days of the Soviet Union's
existence, Lenin paid special attention to
the development of book publishing, often
pointing out that only an educated person
can take an informed part in his country's
political life and in the management of the
state. .
In 1913, there were 62 books and booklets
for every 100 persons in Russia. By 1925 the
figure had risen to 153, and in 1974 it rea-'
ched 672. It now stands at over 700. In the
U.S.S.R. today there are some 200 large
publishing houses, two-thirds of which are
based in the national republics, and in
regions and districts. The Soviet Union also
has 360,000 libraries which provide free ser¬
vice to 180 million readers from their fund of
4,000 million books.
But this does not mean that Soviet pub¬
lishing does not come up against difficulties.
For one thing, it cannot keep up with the
constant and rapidly growing demand for
books. Thanks to a far-reaching cultural
policy, almost all Soviet citizens today are
regular readers.
Another problem is the paper shortage.
This cannot be solved merely by felling
more trees each year, even though the
Soviet Union has immense forests. One
method being used to decrease wood con¬
sumption is the collection of waste paper
from the general public. Persons who hand
in a certain quantity of paper are given a
token which enables them to acquire books
that are otherwise difficult to find.
Some 380,000 tons of waste paper have
already been collected for recycling. In this
way 20,000 hectares of forest have been
saved and millions of new books have been
published. This voluntary programme is to
be stepped up, and, combined with mea¬
sures being taken to improve the paper
industry, is enabling us to satisfy the
demand for reading materials more fully.
No matter how quickly the audio-visual
media develop, we are convinced that
books will never lose their place as the
heralds of the ideals of peace, progress and
cooperation between peoples.
Boris I. Stukalin
34.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published
SOUTHERN RHODESIA:
the effects of a conquest society
on education,
culture and information
A carefully documented analysis, based largely on the
regime's own data, of the impact of Southern Rhodesia's
minority government on the schools, religion, cultural life
and freedoms of the country's 6 million blacks.
Also examines teacher training censorship libraries
propaganda.
Other important Unesco studies on race relations in Africa
Racism and Apartheid in Southern Africa: Rhodesia
1975 124 pp. 10 Francs
Racism and Apartheid in Southern Africa: South Africa and Namibia
1974 156 pp. 15 Francs
Portuguese Colonialism in Africa: the End of an Era
by Eduardo de Sousa Ferreira
1974 170 pp. 20 Francs
Apartheid: its Effects on Education, Science, Culture and Information
3rd impr. 1973 256 pp. 24 Francs
293 pp. 60 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, alona with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd., P.O. Box 33,' Brookvale, 2100, NSW; Periodicals;
Dominie Pty., Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33,' Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent; United Nations Association of
Australia. Victorian Division 5th floor, 134-136 Flinders St.,
Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. -' AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Ha'in,
Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung, Industriehof Stadlan,
Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasses 5, 1220 Wien. BELGIUM: "Unesco
Courier" Dutch edition only; N.V. Handelmaatschappij Keesing.
Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition
and general Unesco publications agent; Jean de Lannoy, 112,
rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 000-0070823-13. - BURMA.
Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552 Merchant Street. Rangoon.
CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H 1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. '
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka,
Prague 1. For Slovakia only; Alfa Verlag Publishers,
. Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DEN¬
MARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency
for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, SF 00100 Helsinki.
FRANCE, Librairie de l'Unesco. 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
. Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Interna¬
tionalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only); 53
Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22, C.C.P. Hamburg 276650. For
scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach
800830. Other publications; S. Karger GmbH, Karger Buchhand¬
lung, Angerhofstr. 9, Postfach 2, D-8034 Germering/München.-
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - GREECE.
International bookshops. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
Division, Far East Publications Ltd., 5 A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, Wong Chuk Hang Road, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémial
Könyvesbort, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok
Boltja, Népkoztârsasâg utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New
Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots; Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House.
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop. Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave., opposite to University of Teheran,
P.O. Box 14/1486, Teheran. Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco,
Ave Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533. Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad. IRELAND.
The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachtat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street Je¬
rusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo 100-92. - KENYA. East
African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, P.O. Box
2942, Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O.
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA.
Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O.
Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal Publi¬
cations Sdn. Bhd., Balai Berita, 31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lumpur. -
"MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. - MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30, bd des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications; N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp Et Co. (Ned Ant.). N.V.,
Willemstad, Curaçao. N. A. - NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street,
P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; '130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721,
Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton;' Princes
Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag,
Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife. The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University
Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The
Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY.
All publications; Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl Johans-
gate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only; A.S. Narvesens
Literaturtjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Ouaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore
3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. ORPAN-IMPORT, .
Palac Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.- PORTUGAL. Dias &
Andrade Ltda, Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMAU DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop
and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Buil¬
ding, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier (single copies) only; Central News Agency P.O. Box
1033, Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook
Sales IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.B. 244 Columbo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier; Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, "Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse,
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus è, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030
Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaég Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London. Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill
Station, New York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in
Spanish: Santillana Publishing Company, Inc.. 575 Lexington
Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenije,
Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Majority protest
vs. minority rule
Despite demands for equal rights by Rhodesia's
6 million blacks, the present régime is stubbornly
defending the entrenched interests of 275,000 whites.
See article page 22.
rr -,
k«^.
A>-»
yJ\ i;/*<
«T
V ~- ;'
X:
Vt^N*
ul)
7 '^álf
Photo Darquennes Sygma, Pa
2^ Jr<
& 4*-
w
]]>
</page>
</document>
