<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074806eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COMier A window
open on the world
.»
9^^^^ < 1
Urn
.
' s*jj
mmmmWJ
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
©
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Bolivia
High art from the Andes
Centuries before the Spanish conquest, a major civilization arose in the high Andes whose most important
centre was at Tiahuanaco near Lake Titicaca in present-day Bolivia. Much is still unexplained about the origin
and development of this civilization but its influence is known to have stretched over a wide area of South
America from AD 250 to 750. Hundreds of megalithic carved stones have survived at Tiahuanaco as well as
many examples of polychrome pottery. Shown here, a ceramic head fashioned by a Tiahuanaco potter.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUlier
NOVEMBER 1978 31st YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 19 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.: (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head. Inc.. 111 West 40th Street,
New York. U.S.A.: (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Edition:.
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
Edition:
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish Edition: Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Urdu Edition: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan' Edition: Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Malaysian Edition: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean : Edition: Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Assistant Editors: "
English Edition: Roy Malkin ;
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey »
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin |'
All correspondence should be addressed z S
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris. . Í2 !
page
4 TODAY'S LOST GENERATION
For young people in the West, a prospect of frequent joblessness
by Peter Melvyn
9 THE RIGHT TO WORK
10 THE MANPOWER SITUATION
IN EUROPEAN SOCIALIST COUNTRIES
11 THE EMPLOYMENT CRISIS IN THE THIRD WORLD
13 HIGHER QUALIFICATIONS-A TICKET TO NOWHERE?
15 THE MULTINATIONALS AND THE THIRD WORLD
16 THE BRAIN DRAIN:
A HIDDEN SUBSIDY FROM POOR TO RICH
18 WOMEN AT WORK: A EUROPEAN PROFILE
by Evelyne Sullerot
23 WORKERS CAN BE CHOOSERS
by Gösta Rehn
24 SOCIETY'S POOR RELATIONS
Teachers count among the lowest paid workers
28 Copyright
THE CREATOR'S BREAD AND BUTTER
by Henri de Saint-Blanquat
32 UNESCO, YOUTH AND THE RIGHT TO WORK
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 IN BRIEF
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
BOLIVIA: High art from the Andes
Cover
' Photo Hartman © Magnum, Paris
Fifty million unemployed, 300 million
underemployed, one thousand two hundred
and fifty million new jobs required by the
year 2000, including one thousand and sixty
million in the developing world these cold,
impersonal figures supplied by the Statistical
Department of the International Labour
Organisation reflect a burning human
problem on a worldwide scale. Horrifying as
they are, the figures for unemployment do
not reveal the whole picture since they
include only those people looking for work
who are registered with national employment
services. The magnitude of the
underemployment problem is also almost
certainly understated and in the developing
world In particular many kinds of work yield
incomes insufficient to enable the working
poor to meet their basic needs. Among the
hardest hit are the young, first-time job-
seekers and women. Cover photo shows an
employee at work in an American factory
manufacturing globes of the world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Today's lost
generation
The unemployed young
in the Western industrialized
countries face the prospect
of frequent joblessness,
a long search for work,
and marginal employment'
by Peter Melvyn IF all the unemployed people in the
twenty-four industrialized countries
that make up the Organization for
Economic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) were to line up outside an employ¬
ment office in London, they would form a
queue long enough to reach all the way to
New York.
The queue would be a youthful one; of
the seventeen million people in it, seven
million, or forty per cent, would be under
the age of twenty-five. For although the
current world economic recession affects
all age groups* young people have been
particularly hard hit and over the past few
years the gap between the unemployment
PETER MELVYN is project manager in the Edu¬
cation and Labour Market Policies Branch of the
Employment and Development Department of
the International Labour Organisation (ILO),
Geneva. This article is based on a longer study
which appeared in the July-August 1977 issue of
the ILO periodical International Labour Review.
rates of adult and young workers has
widened disturbingly with young workers
accounting for thirty-six per cent of the
total increase in unemployment between
1973 and 1975. In 1976, over one third of all
the unemployed in the European
Communities were under twenty-five. In
Australia at the end of 1976, forty per cent
of the total registered unemployed were
under twenty-one, while in Canada in 1974
males aged from fourteen to twenty-four
accounted for close to half of the.
unemployed, double their proportion in the
work force. In the United States young
men between the ages of sixteen and
nineteen account for twenty per cent of all
the unemployed compared with an overall
unemployment rate of just under nine per
cent.
These figures do not, however, reveal
the whole picture. They include only those
young people in the unemployment count
who are actively looking for work and are
registered with the national employment
services. Many, particularly first-time job-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
I
seekers under eighteen who are not
entitled to unemployment benefits and may
have applied for jobs or training places in
vain, see little purpose in registering. The
real unemployment figures may, therefore,
be considerably higher.
There is also evidence that growing
numbers of young people are now
remaining out of work for longer periods,
although these periods are still shorter than
those of adult workers.
Teenagers, first-time job-seekers and
those with the lowest educational
qualifications are the hardest hit. From the
statistics of the few countries that publish
data correlating unemployment with age,
sex and educational and training levels, it
appears that most youngsters who lose
their jobs have had no training or are semi¬
skilled. However, data for 1976 from the
Federal Republic of Germany show that a
third of all unemployed people under the
age of twenty had served an apprenticeship
or had been trained at a vocational school.
Clearly, training and skills are not in
themselves an infallible protection.
Unemployment among girls and young
women is also disproportionately high.
Demographic changes in a number of
countries are likely to make matters worse
before they get better. Between now and
the end of the 1980's the number of young
people reaching working age in the
countries of the European Economic
Community (EEC) will continue to rise
substantially. Not until 1985 will their
numbers go down and stabilize.
Why are young people so severely
affected? Clearly, the general decline in the
number of jobs due to the recession is
highly significant. But this holds good for
adult as well as young workers and the fear
is that certain long-standing structural
problems exist which may not disappear
with economic recovery. Well before the
recession the unemployment share of
young people was disproportionately high
in such countries . as Canada, France,
Ireland, Italy, the United Kingdom and the
United States. Even today in countries
such as Sweden and Norway where
unemployment is very low, the proportion
of young people out of work is two or three
times that of adults. All this points to a
structural trend towards growing
unemployment for the fifteen to twenty-
five age group.
One of the most often quoted reasons
for youth unemployment is the preference
of employers for adult workers. Particularly
in time of large-scale layoffs, employers
prefer to hire or keep experienced adult
workers. The , costs of employing young
people are greater in the short term than
the benefits to the firm. An employer tends
to fill job vacancies with older workers who
have job experience and skills, as well as
habits of reliability and punctuality, and in
this way keep his training costs down to
the minimum.
Research into the nature of employers'
recruitment policies under current
employment conditions is lacking in most
European countries. However, according t
to one such survey carried out in the United f
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
50 million jobless
in the world today
> Kingdom, "about half the employers
interviewed believe that the calibre of
young people has deteriorated over the
past five years in terms of their motivation
and basic education. Particular dis¬
appointment was voiced at the quality of
recruits to skilled manual jobs. So far this
attitude on the part of employers has not
markedly affected recruitment policies;
most employers continue to employ the
same proportion of young people."
There is also evidence that relative wage
costs may be a barrier to the employment
of young people. Each successive rise in
the minimum wage rate reduces employer
demand for inexperienced workers. In a
number of countries minimum wage
legislation now lays down lower minima for
the sixteen to twenty-one age group. In
Denmark, for example, where adult wages
are payable only from the age of eighteen,
unemployment is lower among the younger
age groups.
Paradoxically, young workers are often
disadvantaged by legislation originally
designed for their protection. In practically
all industrialized countries there are barriers
to the employment during school hours of
young people under sixteen. Yet the
emergence of work experience pro¬
grammes or of other schemes combin¬
ing study and work at secondary school
level raises the question of whether
legislation and practice should not take
these recent developments into account.
Thus it has been argued recently in the
United States that "enacted many years
ago to counteract a then widespread
exploitive practice, these laws operate
today to deny some forms of work
experience that would generally be
recognized as valuable... Surveys made by
the Department of Labor indicate that work
experience results in (or at least is
accompanied by) substantial reductions in
dropouts, truancy and tardiness, as well as
in significant improvements in school
grades. The findings appear sufficient to
recommend amendment of the federal or
state laws."
The same sources also point out that
employers are worried about the scope of
federal or state legislation concerning the
employment of persons under the age of
eighteen in "hazardous occupations" and
consequently are reluctant to hire anyone
under eighteen for fear of violating the law
in this respect.
In the discussion on the problems of
youth unemployment reference is often
made to the allegedly negative attitudes of
young people towards work, and par¬
ticularly towards jobs in industry. Yet it
remains to be demonstrated that their
attitudes are markedly different from those
of adult workers. The large body of
literature dealing with job satisfaction and
quality of work reflects society's growing
concern with the work situation. Is it
therefore surprising if the attitudes of older
people towards work influence the young?
Recent studies in France show con¬
siderable variations in attitudes among
young workers according to age, sex,
social origin, education, training and type
of job. Moreover it is not easy to
distinguish between the questioning of
work as a major social value and of the
circumstances under which it is done.
Difficulties during the transition from
school to work unemployment, unsatis-
itative supervision or a work organization
that imposes intolerable constraints and
deprives them of initiative and respon¬
sibility. They tend to refuse a type of
human relations at work that many adults
have come to accept.
It is often said that young people do not
want to go into industry but prefer jobs in
the service sector. It is true that many try to
avoid work on the assembly line and other
repetitive and monotonous jobs. But so do
many adults. Despite all the talk about the
high skill demands of modern technology
and the need for education and training to
prepare people for these demands, there
are still many jobs which require very little
skill, training, intelligence or judgement.
The deficiencies of the educational
system, especially at the secondary level,
are increasingly apportioned part at least of
the blame for the difficulties young people
are experiencing on the labour market. It is
frequently argued that schools do not fulfil
the function of bridging the gap between
the world of childhood and the world of
work. In many countries there is hardly any
communication between the educational
system and the labour market. With the
exception of those who go on to higher
education, young people move suddenly
from the protected, ivory-tower
environment of school into a harsh,
competitive, production-oriented work
situation where the performance and
behaviour expected of them are very
different from anything they have
previously known. During this transition
many of them undergo a good deal of
physical and psychological strain.
Yet concern about the problems young
people experience in making the transition
from school to work is nothing new. A
300 million persons
in the world
are underemployed
factory working conditions, low material
rewards, frustrated career and income
expectations, etc. certain to dampen
the outlook on work and are bound to give
rise to discontent, indifference or
despondency in young people. First
impressions may be lasting and thus cause
considerable social and personal harm.
Yet there are noticeable differences in
attitudes which are not necessarily
negative. For instance, whatever their
educational level, young people- become
increasingly reluctant to accept author-
report submitted to the United Kingdom
Government in 1959 drew attention to "the
abrupt transition from school to work" and
stated that "now that the school leaving
age is 15, a good many people have doubts
whether school conditions should not be
brought for everybody a little' nearer to
working conditions... There is a duty to
these older pupils, who are already half
independent in their activities and
behaviour, to assist them to fit into life as
it is generally lived by adults. Abundant
experiment will be necessary ; and,
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photo <© Marlborough Fine Arts, London
because this is a no man's land between
school and work, it is pretty certain that
some of the experiments which ought to be
tried will be difficult to carry out because
they will not easily be kept within the
bounds set by school regulations, trade
union rules, labour legislation and
insurance requirements..." However, it
was not until many years later that the
experiments recommended in the report
were started under the impulsion of
alarmingly high youth unemployment.
This criticism of the educational system
for being too academic mounted rapidly
during the mid-1970's and was accompa¬
nied by concern over an increasing lack of
basic literacy, numeracy and communi¬
cations skills.
What is being done to cut youth unem¬
ployment in the industrialized countries?
Most governments are adopting a multiple
approach involving innovations in edu¬
cation and training, employment subsidy
schemes and job creation programmes.
Spanish Horizon 1960,
a painting by the Spanish artist
Juan Genovés
Many governments are encouraging
sixteen-year-olds to stay on at school
rather than do nothing. This advice has
been heeded in Sweden where seventy-
two per cent stay on at school, and in the
Netherlands where many youngsters go in
for vocational subjects. Under a new
British scheme known as "link courses"
so far rather limited in application pu¬
pils in their last year of compulsory
schooling gain practical experience by
working in industry, commerce and the
public services. Before lending its support
to the scheme, however, the Trades Union
Congress insisted that work experience for
schoolchildren must among other things be
"an integral element in a properly planned
course of general education (and) comply
strictly with all the statutory restrictions
applying to the employment of children and
young persons".
In the Federal Republic of Germany a
year of basic vocational training is being
tried out in two Länder. Its purpose is to
prepare the pupil for entry into the world of
work, either entirely at school or in co¬
operation with an enterprise, by supple¬
menting general education with broad vo¬
cational subjects as a basis for subsequent
training. In Sweden much attention is
being paid to improving contacts between
school and working life, and in Canada,
Japan and the United States programmes
of alternate work and study have been in
existence for many years.
Since most governments consider train¬
ing to be one of the best ways of combat¬
ing youth unemployment, a number of
them have established programmes de¬
signed in particular to help young people
with poor educational records and little or
no work experience. These have generally
taken the form of subsidies to firms
providing training or of direct grants to
trainees.
In France a number of schemes have
been initiated including one which encou¬
rages employers to offer young people a
minimum of work experience through "em¬
ployment-training contracts" of from six to
twelve months' duration. The contracts
may be concluded by private or public in¬
dustrial, artisanal and commercial enter¬
prises. Employers' training costs are re¬
imbursed by the State through subsidies
of between thirty and one hundred per
cent of the minimum wage.
In the United Kingdom, in addition to a
number of short-term training programmes
and temporary work schemes, a work
experience programme has been launched
to provide school-leavers with six to twelve
months experience in factories, shops or
offices under close supervision. Simi¬
lar combined training and employment
schemes are in operation in the Nether¬
lands and in Australia.
Closely linked with these training
schemes are the employment subsidy
schemes adopted in a number of countries.
The Italian Government, for example, has
established a four-year regional employ¬
ment fund for Sardinia and is also offering
subsidies of 32,000 lire a month for each
worker aged between fifteen and twenty-
two hired at national minimum wage rates
for a combination of work and training.
France, the United Kingdom and Sweden
all have various forms of employment
subsidy schemes.
Another line of attack now widely adopt¬
ed is the institution of special job creation
programmes for groups experiencing spe¬
cial difficulty in finding jobs. The United
States and Canada were the leaders in this
field and the programmes usually serve
social rather than commercial ends.
The Canadian programme has been
based from the outset on involvement of
local groups and communities in the
creation of new jobs. The underlying aim is
to combat seasonal unemployment, a par¬
ticularly serious problem in a country that
experiences such hard winters. What is
unusual about the programme is that ideas
for projects can be submitted by anyone-
individuals, groups, municipalities or
corporations. The projects must be
designed for community betterment, not
for profit, and the jobs must be filled by
unemployed people. There is no age limit,
but about forty per cent of all participants |
have been under twenty-five years of age. |
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
In the 23 richest
countries in the world,
4 out of
every 10 unemployed
persons are under 25
Apart from being economically wasteful,
unemployment is felt as rejection and
discrimination and is therefore socially
damaging, especially to young people.
Most of the measures taken so far have
been of a short-term nature whereas the
problem itself is a long-term one which
calls for new and imaginative approaches
affecting the educational and training
system as well as the labour market. This
will require a determined joint effort on the
part of governments, educational and
employment authorities, employers, trade
unions, voluntary bodies and the public at
large.
Peter Melvyn
A job creation scheme modelled on the
Canadian programme but aimed exclu¬
sively at young people has been initiated in
the United Kingdom. As with the Canadian
scheme the goal is to provide short-term
jobs of social value, including community
tasks which would not otherwise be under¬
taken. Several other countries have taken
similar initiatives. In Denmark public works
programmes for young people have been
launched by the municipal authorities with
government funding. Since 1975 the Ne¬
therlands Government has been providing
temporary subsidies to public bodies and
non profit-making institutions for work
projects that are socially useful and do not
compete with normal economic activities.
The Netherlands is also experimenting with
an original scheme whereby two young
people share one job, one wage and one
full unemployment benefit.
If the various training and employment
creation measures mentioned above seem
in many cases to lack continuity and co¬
ordination, it should not be forgotten that
they were nearly always adopted under the
considerable pressure of a rapidly deterio¬
rating employment situation. That govern¬
ments are learning from experience is
shown by their continuing quest for new
and more comprehensive approaches, par¬
ticularly as regards long-term action to
meet educational and training needs and to
achieve better articulation between the
educational system and the labour market.
Most of these new moves are still in the
planning stage and are the subject of public
discussion and controversy.
Although it is hard to predict what the
future will bring, the unemployed young in
the Western industrialized countries face
the prospect of frequent joblessness, long
job search and marginal employment.
While youth unemployment is part of
general unemployment, the proportion of
young people out of work remains sub¬
stantially higher than that of other workers.
The reasons for this are partly cyclical but
also to a significant extent partly structural.
The high level of employment of the post¬
war years tended to conceal occupational
and technological change. Increasingly
jobs are lost through capital investment in
equipment; fewer new jobs are created and
these often demand skills that many young
people cannot offer. The recession has laid
bare the gap between the school and the
world of work.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
;/".-.
<
/
THE RIGHT TO WORK
Universal Declaration of Human Rights
Article 23
1 Everyone has the right to work, to free choice of employment, to just and
favourable conditions of work and to protection against unemployment.
2 Everyone, without any discrimination, has the right to equal pay for equal work.
3 Everyone who works has the right to just and favourable remuneration ensuring
for himself and his family an existence worthy of human dignity, and supplemented,
if necessary, by other means of social protection.
4 Everyone has the right to form and to join trade unions for the protection of his
interests.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
In spite of major efforts to train personnel, the socialist
countries of Europe today face a manpower shortage. In the
U.S.S.R. alone, only some 40 per cent of the new jobs in
industry were filled in 1975. Left, a Soviet worker dwarfed
by a hydroelectric installation in Siberia.
The manpower situation
in European
socialist countries
THE U.S.S.R. and other European socialist countries have, in
recent years, achieved rapid rates of economic growth. Yet
this does not imply that employment problems, such as
those associated with long-term manpower planning and produc¬
tivity, have been absent.
Although specific policies differ from one socialist country to
another, employment problems are now viewed in all of them as
part of the more general problem of improving productivity and
efficiency.
In the early years of Soviet planning, however, the authorities
had to grapple with a serious problem of urban unemployment and
extremely low productivity in rural areas. The strategy adopted was
to link employment policy to a programme of rapid industrialization
so that the attainment of full employment became a by-product of
the priority accorded to industry.
Careful attention was paid to the choice of technology, particu¬
larly In the early stages when unemployment was a significant
problem. In general, capital-intensive techniques were used in the
new branches of industry, whereas labour-intensive, capital-saving
methods of production were adopted in those industries In which
there was the possibility of choice.
According to official statistics. In all socialist countries, except in
Yugoslavia, open unemployment was virtually eliminated by the
1950s. In subsequent years a combination of a shift of labour out of
agriculture, increasing entry of women Into the paid labour force
and the coming of age of children born during the post-war baby
boom ensured that labour bottlenecks did not arise until recently.
Today, however, with the able-bodied population increasing by less
than one per cent a year, labour scarcity is likely to become an
increasing problem.
Growth in output and productivity has been accompanied by a
high degree of apparent price stability.
Price policies have been complemented by wage and Income
policies. The wage structure in the European socialist countries is
notable for its low differentials. In Bulgaria, for example, the mini¬
mum wage is about two:thirds of the average wage.
In addition, a considerable part of the national income in socialist
countries is distributed in kind to the population in the form of col¬
lective or public consumption. Health and educational services, for
example, are free, as is the use of many cultural, recreational and
sporting facilities.
The trends in growth, productivity, prices and income distribu¬
tion described above have developed during a period of rapid struc¬
tural change. The proportion of the labour force engaged in
industry and construction has risen rapidly and there has been a
steady fall in the proportion of the labour force engaged in agricul¬
ture and forestry while increasing numbers are being absorbed into
the service sector.
Labour shortages are beginning to make themselves felt and
there is little prospect of relief through population growth. More¬
over, the rapid growth of education and training is certain to result
in a fall In the proportion of the able-bodied population engaged in
productive occupations. Nor is there any possibility of increasing
substantially the participation rate of women since they already
constitute a large proportion of the paid labour force. Thus the
need for improvement in labour utilization is becoming more and
more evident.
For the past fifteen years considerable effort has been devoted to
increasing output and productivity in the agricultural sector in the
U.S.S.R. Investment in farming has increased faster than in
industry and its share of the total has almost doubled, from 14 per
cent in 1960 to 27 per cent in 1974. Agricultural incentives have also
been improved.
Parallel to the need for faster progress In agriculture, there is an
increasingly recognized need to shift more resources to the produc¬
tion of manufactured consumer goods.
Thus the socialist economies have reached a stage of develop¬
ment at which there must be simultaneously a shift in the balance
of production and hence in the balance of investment between the
various sectors, and in the rate of technical change with a view to
reducing manpower needs.
It Is in this context that the economic reforms now under way
acquire their significance. Their aim is to increase productivity by
decentralizing decison making and placing greater responsibility
for economic performance at the branch and enterprise level.
Another urgent requirement will be to satisfy the more qualita¬
tive basic needs of the citizens of socialist countries. As In other
industrially advanced societies, the satisfaction of basic material
needs through rising living standards and higher levels of education
leads to demands for an improved quality of life, greater participa¬
tion in decisions affecting management of enterprises and an
improved working environment, including safety, health and job
satisfaction.
This text is based on a longer study which appeared in
Employment and Basic Needs, A One-World Problem, a
report of the Director-General of the International
Labour Office, Geneva, prepared for the Tripartite
World Conference on Employment, Income Distribution
and Social Progress and the International Division of
Labour.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The employment crisis
in the Third World
1,060 million
new jobs needed
before the end
of the century
CHILD OF OUR TIMES. It has been estimated that migrant workers from the
Third World occupy some 12 million jobs in the industrialized countries with a
market economy and the oil-producing countries of the Middle East. About half
of them work in western Europe, where the main countries of immigration are
France and the Federal Republic of Germany. In Berlin (Fed. Rep. of Germany)
alone, migrant workers and their families number 3 million. Adjusting to life in a
new country poses difficult problems for the children. (Above, the son of a
migrant worker living in France) Unesco is actively promoting research to aid
migrant workers and their families to adapt to social conditions in the host
country, while at the same time preserving their cultural identity, and to help
them acquire knowledge and skills which will be useful if they decide to return
to their country of origin. Particular stress is laid on the need to provide
additional training for educators working in areas with a high proportion of
migrant workers.
F
employment and a reduction in
poverty and inequality are not auto¬
matic consequences of rapid natio¬
nal economic growth. This is the harsh les¬
son to be learnt from the experience of the
developing countries over the past three
decades.
During the 1960s, national income per
head of population grew exceptionally fast
by historical standards in most developing
countries. Indeed, throughout this period,
the rates of economic growth in the devel- ^
oping countries often exceeded those f
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
98.0
31.3 35.4 32.7
11.6
76.Í
7FFI
à
46.4
§ß
37.5
M
rf^
Algeria Botswana Ghana Ivory Coast Kenya Sudan Zambia India Korea Rep. of Kuwait Malaysia, W
Design © Fitnat, Paris. Based on a graph published in "The basic arithmetic of youth employment", ILO, Geneva
There is no single answer
to the employment problem
in developing countries,
where there are not only
high rates of
unemployment and
underemployment (working
short hours and wanting
more work) but too many
of those in jobs earn
incomes inadequate for
meeting even their basic
needs. In Asia alone an
estimated 180 million new
jobs must be created by the
end of this decade. Left,
these Indian students in the
examination room will soon
face another test the
search for a job
commensurate with their
qualifications and abilities.
achieved by the industrialized countries
when they were going through their
development phase.
Unfortunately, economic growth in the
developing countries has tended recently
to be concentrated in relatively limited,
capital-intensive sectors of the economy
rather than in the traditional rural sector or
the less organized urban sector which bet¬
ween them account for by far the greater
part of total employment. As a result, the
benefits of growth, and in particular
increased employment opportunities.
have mainly gone to a very small part of the
total population.
Several factors have contributed to this
uneven development. Production structure
and wealth distribution patterns in the
developing countries are often a legacy of
colonial or other alien regimes, and the
continued application of foreign patterns
has often led to the perpetuation of inap¬
propriate systems in such fields as educa¬
tion and health. Government policies have
frequently been ill-adapted to the circum¬
stances of an independent nation in which
the reduction of poverty ought to be the
major objective of economic policy.
Even since independence inappropriate
institutions and policies have continued to
lead to a poor allocation of investment
resources, the selection of economically
inefficient methods of production in rela¬
tion to resources available, the under-
utilization of labour, capital and land, and
an increasing concentration of income and
wealth. Very high and sustained rates of
population growth have aggravated these
problems. These interlocking factors have
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
98.0
75.5
$
41.1
V? 13.2 Y/ 15.5
27.9
95.8 98-°
Philippines Singapore Sri Lanka Syria Thailand Brazil Chile Costa Rica Guatemala Mexico Panama Peru Venezuela
Total modern sector vacancies as
a percentage or the age cohort.
Completing primary school and
higher as a percentage of the age
cohort. 1 The balance.
Higher qualificationsa ticket to nowhere?
The phenomenon of "educated unemployment" is not
confined to the industrialized countries. Only 10 to 15
years ago in many developing countries almost everyone
who completed 6 or 7 years of educationat a time when
only 10 to 15 per cent of the age group did socould be
fairly sure of a non-manual, modern-sector job.
Modern-sector jobs may be defined roughly as jobs which
(as distinct from traditional, self-employed, rural and
artisan occupations) provide security and a predictable,
regular, higher than average income, comfortable, modern
working conditions and social status.
Hardly anywhere can one now get such a job with less
than 9 or 10 years of education and a secondary
certificate. In parts of south Asia college graduates
compete unsuccessfully for routine clerical jobs with no
great prospects.
If there are too many certificated young job-seekers
chasing too few modern-sector jobs, and if the imbalance
is likely to grow rather than diminish, what are the
prospects for the future?
The diagram above is based on figures presented in The
Basic Arithmetic of Youth Employment, a publication of
the ILO World Employment Programme. Assuming a
rather conservative rate of growth of 2 per cent in
modern-sector employment opportunities, it portrays
graphically the likely employment situation in 1980 for
those whose education encourages them to aspire to jobs
in the modern sector. It underlines the seriousness of the
situation and the urgency of the task facing educational
planners in the developing countries.
For each of the countries shown on the diagram the first
column shows the total projected vacancies in the modern
sector in 1980 as a percentage of young people coming on
to the labour market; the second column shows the
percentage of these young people who will have
completed primary and higher education; the third column
shows the balance. Thus in the case of Algeria, for
example, out of 100 young people coming on to the labour
market in 1980, 46 will have completed at least primary
and/or higher education and will become available for jobs
in the modern sector of the labour market. However, of
these 46 only 7.5 will find a job in the modern sector, so
that 38.5 have no hope of finding a job in this sector.
combined to keep vast numbers of people
in abject poverty, deprived of any share of
the benefits of the increase in total output.
By the end of the 1960s it was clear that
in most developing countries following
conventional patterns, growth was not
leading to a reduction of poverty. On the
contrary, the numbers of the very poor
were rising, the degree of inequality was
only rarely diminishing and the employ¬
ment problem remained largely un¬
resolved.
Open unemployment in developing
countries can be measured fairly accura¬
tely. It frequently reflects, to a greater
extent than in the industrialized countries,
more the problem of young dependents
seeking employment than that of experien¬
ced workers losing their jobs. Despite very
high rates of open unemployment for some
areas and some age-groups, and much
higher rates in urban than in rural areas,
it is not generally a large fraction of the
total labour force. The unemployed in
many developing countries are dispro¬
portionately concentrated among young
people, first-time job-seekers, women and
the relatively better educated.
Other dimensions of the employment
problem in the developing countries are of
much greater importance. Seasonal unem¬
ployment is often extreme and under¬
employment (working short hours and
wanting more work) is widespread. But
the most widespread and critical phenom¬
enon is simply that work of various kinds
(especially self-employment) yields an
income inadequate for the working poor to
meet their basic needs.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
In the developing world the number of new jobs which can be
created in the modern sector of the economy is extremely
limited. In many developing countries the maximum number of
new modern-sector jobs which can be expected even at the most
optimistic rates of growth would not provide for more than 20 or
30 per cent of the young people coming on to the labour market.
Photo Roland Michaud © Rapho, Pans
In countries without unemployment
compensation, those in the most desperate
need (particularly heads of households
with dependents) can spend little time
looking for the kind of work they prefer.
They must find something even if it yields
only a pittance. Thus heads of households
are more likely to be found among the ina¬
dequately employed or underemployed, for
example in precarious low-productivity
self-employment, than among the unem¬
ployed.
I HE crux of the employ¬
ment problem in the developing world thus
lies in the high proportion of the labour
force earning inadequate incomes. The
proportion of the labour force classified as
underemployed is approximately the same
as the proportion of the population classi¬
fied as "destitute". Thus, problems of
employment and poverty are inseparable
and the magnitude of the total poverty
problem is regularly understated.
The labour force of the developing coun¬
tries with market economies is now estim¬
ated to be around 700 million. About 5 per
cent of this labour force is openly unem¬
ployed and a further 36 per cent is under¬
employed, the proportion being lower in
urban and higher in rural areas. Of the total
of unemployed and underemployed, about
80 per cent are to be found in rural areas.
The growth of the labour force in the
developing countries with market econo¬
mies has accelerated in recent years and it
is likely that the acceleration will continue
for some time after the overall rate of popu¬
lation growth has finally begun to slow
down. United Nations estimates (which
assume quite substantial reductions in fer¬
tility rates) suggest that between 1975 and
the year 2000 the labour force of all the
developing countries (including China) will
rise by some 75 per cent.
In the developed countries the agricultu¬
ral labour force has long been decreasing
not only as a proportion of the total labour
force but also in absolute terms, whereas in
the developing countries it continues to
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
increase in absolute terms. This state of
affairs is likely to continue in the developing
countries as a whole until the beginning of
the second decade of the next century,
even if non-agricultural employment were
to expand much more rapidly. Thus agri¬
culture, in addition to absorbing a substan¬
tial backlog of underemployment, will have
to continue to provide employment for new
entrants to the labour force for a long time
to come if rural-urban migration is to be
slowed to a rate commensurate with the
creation of non-agricultural jobs.
That the incomes of so many of the
working poor are inadequate does not
mean that, like the unemployed, their
labour is totally unused. Some of them are
no doubt very fully occupied. However,
they are available for more productive and
better paid work when it becomes availa¬
ble. How can full use be made of these
labour resources so that the working poor
can meet their basic needs?
There are still many areas where factual
knowledge is far from complete. More
information is needed on the relation of
unemployment and underemployment to
poverty. What are the employment charac¬
teristics of the poor? Are they available for
rural works programmes? Would they
migrate to seek work or do they find secu¬
rity in their home villages? How many of
the poor are sick or old? Without such
knowledge it is impossible to tell what kind
of government programmes are needed to
reduce poverty.
From nearly every point of view, inade¬
quate employment in the traditional rural
and informal urban sectors is usually more
critical than open unemployment in the
developing countries. Creating the condi¬
tions where the former disappears will
make it very much easier to deal with the
latter. Measures aimed solely at reducing
open unemployment, on the other hand,
will worsen the basic problems of under¬
employment and poverty. Either additional
waves of seekers of jobs in the modern sec¬
tors will appear, or even more resources
will be used for the interests of the few and
thereby perpetuate the poverty of the
many.
This article and the box, right, are
based on studies which appeared in
the ILO report Employment and
Basic Needs, A One-World Problem.
The
multinationals
and the Third World
MULTINATIONAL enterprises cov¬
er a wide spectrum of econo¬
mic activities. Their ownership
is varied: the bulk of them are private,
but they can also be state-owned. A
high and increasing proportion of inter¬
national transactions in goods, services,
capital and expertise takes place under
the auspices or through the mediation
of such firms.
For a number of years now, criticisms,
some severe, have been levelled against
the activities of multinational enter¬
prises, particularly in developing coun¬
tries. From the research carried out so
far by the ILO and others the conclusion
has emerged that it is very difficult to
generalize about their effects on such
phenomena as employment, technology
and labour skills.
It has been estimated that the multi-
tionals directly employ a total of 13 to 14
million people. Out of this total, the
share of developing countries has been
estimated at approximately 2 million
persons, or roughly 0.3 per cent of the
active population, all of whom are in the
"modern" or "formal" sectors. But this
figure takes no account of indirect
employment effects or the jobs created
through activities of multinational
enterprises other than direct invest¬
ments. Moreover, employment effects
vary enormously from sector to sector.
For example, in 1960 in Chile, Argen¬
tina, Brazil and Mexico, the jobs directly
created by multinationals in extractive
industries represented only a small per¬
centage of total employment. Both
foreign and domestic firms in these
industries use highly capital-intensive
processes, and generally very little
transformation of the raw material
takes place on the spot. In the case of
agriculture, however, direct employ¬
ment creation by the .multinational
enterprises is much larger, since pro¬
duction techniques In agriculture are
traditionally labour-intensive. In 1968, in
Zaire, the large foreign agricultural com¬
panies had 230,000 - employees plus
200,000 "independent contractors", that
Is, 10 per cent of the active population.
In the case of manufacturing, direct
employment in the multinational enter¬
prises has increased sharply in recent
years although the number of jobs cre¬
ated Is still quite small when compared
with the rest of the economy. For exam¬
ple, in countries such as Brazil and
Mexico the multinational enterprises
employ less than 10 per cent of the wor¬
kers in manufacturing whereas their
share of investment amounts to 30 per
cent. This Is partly because they are
investing increasingly by taking over
existing firms rather than by creating
new ones. There is indeed a risk that
multinationals may in some cases re¬
organize firms in such a way as to lead
to a fall in the number of jobs.
Among the criteria for evaluating the
role of particular multinational enter¬
prises (particularly when engaged In
direct investments) in the creation of
employment or the meeting of basic
needs are: the adaptability of their pro¬
duction technologies to local environ¬
ments, the appropriateness of the pro¬
ducts which they promote for local
mass consumption, their performance
in the training of workers and mana¬
gers, their behaviour with respect to
social policy and wage rates, and the
extent to which they have developed
local subcontracting.
Many studies have shown that the
technologies adopted by the multinatio¬
nals in the host country are the same as
those used In the home country. The
reasons for this situation include the
need for standardization of production
techniques, the small size of domestic
markets, the scarcity of supervisory
skills and distortions in prices. This is
not to minimize the importance of the
adaptations to existing capital-intensive
technologies and the Introduction of
labour-intensive ones which some firms
have undertaken or the marketing
efforts in the field of major agricultural
crops which others have conducted. On
the other hand, very few of the applied
research and development activities of
the multinational enterprises have been
undertaken in the developing countries.
In the sphere of social and wage poli¬
cies, ILO studies suggest that multi¬
national enterprises typically abide by
local laws and customs and, if anything,
tend to pay higher wage rates than local
firms in similar lines.
By importing advanced management
and productive techniques, the multina¬
tionals can also contribute to training in
developing countries. While almost all
production staff are given training, the
position is not necessarily the same for
management. Localization of skilled
labour and management posts has
taken place at a steady pace but it is not
yet clear to what extent the training
efforts which made it possible have yiel¬
ded benefits to the host countries out¬
side the firms.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The brain drain
a hidden
subsidy
from poor
to rich
TßßTfHE developing countries have,
over the past fifteen years,
witnessed a significant loss of
their human capital through the process of
'reverse transfer of technology' or 'brain
drain'. For the receiving countries, on the
other hand, such an inflow has helped to
increase the highly qualified manpower at
their disposal with. corresponding savings
in education costs.
"For example, a report prepared for the
United States House of Representatives
Committee on Foreign Affairs estimates
the total educational cost savings to the
United States of immigrant scientists, engi¬
neers and doctors from the developing
countries at around $1.8 billion for the two
fiscal years 1971 and 1972, an average of
little less than $1 billion per year."
These observations, which highlight a
situation which is having dramatic con¬
sequences for the developing world, are
taken from a new study prepared by the
United Nations Conference on Trade and
Development (UNCTAD) (1).
(1) The Reverse Transfer of Technology: An In-Depth
Analysis of Major Issues and Suggestions for a Frame¬
work of Approach.
The United Nations has been concerned
with this disturbing problem for some
years. In 1975 the General Assembly adop¬
ted a resolution which underscored "the
urgent need to formulate national and
international policies to avoid the 'brain
drain' and to obviate its adverse effects",
and last December, at its 32nd session,
called for an in-depth study of the subject.
It was requested that particular attention
be devoted to a proposal concerning the
establishment of an international labour
compensatory facility to idemnify labour-
exporting countries for their loss of highly-
trained personnel.
The UNCTAD study was prepared in res¬
ponse to the General Assembly resolution.
Based on work by UNCTAD including case
studies on India, Pakistan, the Philippines
and Sri Lanka, it also draws on the work of
other international organizations such as
Unesco.
It throws into relief the main features of
the brain drain, investigates its causes and
suggests ways in which developing and
industrialized countries alike could develop
an equitable system of exchange between
those who lose and those who gain from
the brain drain.
According to the study, an estimated
305,000 highly skilled persons migrated
from developing countries to the United
States, Canada and the United Kingdom
alone between 1961 and 1976. Nearly
61,000 were physicians and surgeons, over
100,000 were engineers and scientists, and
123,000 were technical staff. In addition,
some 115,000 more skilled migrants are
reckoned to have moved to other countries
of western Europe.
The study also shows that in 1971-1972
half the new doctors in the United States
and 40 per cent of those in the U.K. came
from the developing countries. The burden
of these losses was all the heavier for the
developing countries since the migrant
doctors, engineers and scientists tend to
leave these countries during the most pro¬
ductive period of their lives.
The case studies on India, Pakistan, the
Philippines and Sri Lanka underline the
sombre implications of skilled migration for
the developing countries. In the 1970s bet¬
ween 50 and 70 per cent of Pakistan's
newly-trained doctors were believed to be
emigrating each year, while in the mid-
1960s it was reckoned that some 25 per
cent of India's newly-trained engineers and
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Draeger, Pans. Private Collection
some 30 per cent of its new doctors were
leaving the country. In the Philippines in
the mid-1970s, one newly-trained doctor in
every five was leaving the country to find
work elsewhere.
Between 1971 and 1975 some 35 per cent
of Sri Lanka's accountants left to work
abroad, along with 20 per cent of its doc¬
tors and 18 per cent of its engineers.
Although Asia has been the major catch¬
ment area for skilled migration, the lower
figures for other developing regions still
reflect a grim reality. For a developing
country, the loss of only a handful of skilled
personnel may be critical, either because
they represent a big proportion of the
country's limited resources of skilled man¬
power or because they are concentrated in
areas of key importance to the economy.
A survey of the causes of migration sug¬
gests that a number of factors are involved,
including international income differences,
employment opportunities, living and wor¬
king conditions and the social environ¬
ment. Analysis of these causes does not,
however, "suggest any strong implication
of responsibility on the side of either the
developing or the developed countries;
rather the brain drain seems to be sympto¬
matic of the overall situation of unequal
development of the international
economy".
The UNCTAD study draws attention to
the "need for concerted action at the natio¬
nal, regional and international levels in
order to assist the developing countries to
find solutions to the brain drain problem."
Within this broad framework several alter¬
native proposals have been advanced in
recent years.
It is clear that the main brunt of the battle
to stem the flow of skilled emigrants must
be borne by the developing countries them¬
selves. Three kinds of policies are currently
envisaged:
incentive policies to encourage professio¬
nals to stay in their home country or to
return from abroad;
"restrictive policies" to discourage pro¬
fessionals from leaving their country or to
oblige them to return after a specific period
abroad;
policies aiming to minimize the need or
desire of professionals to go abroad.
Action by the developed countries could
help make these policies more effective.
Décalcomanie, a work
by the Belgian
surrealist painter
René Magritte (1898-1967).
Traditionally, the most common measure in
these countries has been to limit immigra¬
tion of skilled workers from the developing
world through the application of selective
immigration quotas. However, since such
restrictions on immigration pose questions
concerning discrimination and the right of
individuals to free movement, the recom¬
mendation of bilateral or multilateral agree¬
ments may prove especially useful.
CONTINUED PAGE 32
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Women at work:
a European profile
by Evelyne Sullerot
EVELYNE SULLEROT, French sociologist, spe¬
cializes in the study of women's position in
society. She has prepared many studies for
international organizations on aspects of the
situation of women in working life and the ques¬
tion of equal pay for equal work. Among her
published works, which have been widely trans¬
lated, is Women, Society and Change (McGraw
Hill, New York, 1971). This article has been
adapted from a report prepared for the
United Nations on "Changes in the Roles of Men
and Women in Europe"
IN Western society, a person tends to
be "identified" above all by virtue of
his or her professional activities. The
question "Who are you?" has been re¬
placed by the question "What do you do?"
It is therefore inevitable that women
should feel a growing need for a social
identity which is not defined exclusively by
reference to the economic role of men.
Better trained and educated than in the
past, less tied to the home thanks to a
iighter burden of housework and less fre¬
quent child-bearing, they naturally wish to
use their gifts, knowledge and skills to
ensure their independence and play a fuller
and more influential part in human affairs.
The first impression to emerge from sta¬
tistics concerning women in employment is
that the working world has been conceived
and organized by men and for men.
Definitions of "working women" vary
from country to country: in one farmers'
wives, shopkeepers and unpaid workers in
family businesses are all included in this
category; in another they are not consider¬
ed a part of the labour force on the grounds
that it is impossible to assess the nature or
the regularity of their remuneration. In
Europe these different definitions account
for disparities in calculating "woman-
power" amounting to several millions of
persons. The differences can be particu-
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Equal work... unequal pay
In some parts of the world women are still earning less than men doing the came jobs. A 50-country survey
carried out by the International Labour Organisation in 1976 covering six kinds of job (spinners and machinists
in the textile industry, bookbinders, laboratory assistants, grocery shop assistants and accounting machine
operators in banks) revealed, for example, that in twelve countries women machinists were paid between 0.7
per cent (Italy) and 40 per cent (Madagascar) per hour less than men. However, in Hong Kong (below) and
Hungary women machinists' average hourly earnings were actually from 6 to 8 per cent higher than those of
men. Women laboratory assistants (bottom photo) earned 7 per cent less per month than men In Peru and
around 20 per cent less in Norway and Venezuela, while women grocery shop assistants earned much less than
men in Canada (Montreal), Finland, Ireland (Dublin), Malaysia (Sarawak) and Mall. In certain countries,
including Cyprus, Morocco and Venezuela, the difference was over 30 per cent. The survey also showed that in
some countries the monthly earnings of women accounting machine operators were up to 20 per cent less than
those of men and that In Hong Kong the top monthly earnings for a woman in this job were 30 per cent less
than those of a man.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The textile industry is still, at times, more of a money-spinner
for men workers than for women. ILO figures show that, in
1976, the difference In hourly wage rates ranged from 5 per
cent (Algeria, Hong Kong, New Zealand) to 30 per cent
(Honduras, Mauritius, Venezuela). However, in the majority of
countries for which figures are available the rates for the two
sexes are the same and in Hungary, in 1976, women spinners
actually earned an average of 5 per cent more than men.
k larly startling in countries where agriculture
is important. Thus the statistics show that
in Turkey the proportion of women in the
total labour force is one of the highest in
Europe, while the figure for Greece is one
of the lowest. But is it really possible that in
one country the majority of women are
employed and in the other they are not?
There is a wide margin of error in assess¬
ing the work of women in each country,
but it grows even wider when there is an
attempt to make international compari¬
sons. Different countries use different age
limits for calculating the numbers of their
"active population." The percentage of
women working part-time is sometimes
ignored by the statisticians. This figure
varies considerably from country to
country: in Belgium part-time workers
constitute 8.2 per cent of the total female
working population as against 38.3 in the
United Kingdom.
A society only assesses accurately what
it deems to be important, and the vague¬
ness of the statistics concerning women's
employment is a sign that women's econo¬
mic role has long been considered to be
marginal.
In the mid-1970s the proportion of
women in the total labour force varied
widely in different parts of the world. It was
highest in the U.S.S.R. (49.3 per cent),
followed by eastern Asia (38.9 per cent).
North America (35 per cent) and Europe
(34.4 per cent). Between 1970 and 1975 the
proportion of women in the total labour
force dropped in Africa and eastern Asia,
for various reasons. In the U.SiS.R. the
figure went down from 51.6 per cent to
49.3 per cent because the demographic
equilibrium between the sexes, which had
been upset by the high rate of male mor¬
tality during the war, is gradually reestab¬
lishing itself. In Europe it rose slightly from
33.6 per cent to 34.4 per cent, and accord-,
ing to ILO projections it will register a fur¬
ther slight increase between now and the
end of the century.
. However, this overall figure conceals big
disparities between different European
countries : disparities in the level of
women's employment and disparities in
development. Austria and the people's
democracies of central and eastern Europe,
where women constitute over 40 per cent
of the total labour force (46 per cent in Cze¬
choslovakia) form one group of countries.
In all of them the proportion is on the
increase.
In three northern countries (Sweden,
Finland and Denmark), the proportion of
women in the work force has risen sharply
in recent years (by 6 per cent in Sweden in
four years) and now stands at around 41
per cent. But although this figure is high, it
includes a large percentage of part-time
workers (between 30 and 45 per cent). Nor¬
way is a case apart; the proportion of Nor¬
wegian women workers has been low for
many years and still only stood at 28 per
cent in 1970. Since then the figure has risen
spectacularly to 35.5 per cent.
In some countries of western Europe,
such as the United Kingdom, France, and
the Federal Republic of Germany, where
women constitute some 38 or 39 per cent
of the working population, women have
traditionally formed part of the labour force
and have played a major role in economic
activity for almost a century.
In southern Europe the situation is diffe¬
rent, although the figures are on the
increase. In Yugoslavia the proportion of
women in the labour force rose from 24 per
cent in the 1950s to 33.9 per cent in 1975.
The lowest figures in Europe were those for
Spain and Portugal (around 22 per cent),
although the number of women working
on the land in these countries has been
underestimated. In Spain the number of
women in jobs has risen in the last five
years. The case of Italy is particularly inte¬
resting; in the 1930s women constituted
some 38 per cent of the Italian labour force.
Post-war industrialization and agrarian
reform brought the percentage down to 26
per cent by 1974, but this is a gross
underestimate, particularly because of
the incidence of undeclared labour.
Within a single country, women's parti¬
cipation in economic life may vary widely
from region to region. The extent of their
economic role bears little relation to their
willingness to work: whatever the econo¬
mic activities of a given region, men get
priority in the queue for jobs. If there is no
industry, for example, it is the men who
work in the service sector. As a general
rule, the rate of female employment is
determined by a "filter" of male employ¬
ment.
The rate of female unemployment also
varies widely from region to region. In
western Europe as a whole the rate of
unemployment is proportionately higher
for women than for men. But there is also a
hidden form of unemployment, which
reveals itself, for example, when new jobs
are created in a region where hitherto there
have been few women workers. Discourag¬
ed in advance by the hopelessness of find¬
ing a job, many women do not even bother
to register as job-seekers.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Ever since the industrial revolution there
has been a distinction between "men's
jobs" and "women's jobs", Some occupa¬
tions have become "professional ghettos"
for women, with low status and salary.
This distinction fs often artificial, in the
sense that it is not based on biological dif¬
ferences between the sexes, and is becom¬
ing increasingly flagrant as technological
progress takes the backbreak out of work.
A comparison between the "feminized"
jobs in different countries also highlights
the artificiality of this distinction. In the
U.S.S.R., many women work in theprin-
ting industry, whereas in France and Bel¬
gium it is an all-male preserve. The fur and
tobacco industries are other examples of
the same phenomenon.
What unwritten laws lay down this distri¬
bution of functions between men and
women? By and large it can be said that
when a job is downgraded it becomes a
"woman's job" and vice versa.
Furthermore, women in minor jobs are
proportionately more numerous than men.
They climb the ladder of promotion more
rarely and more slowly. They have a "pre¬
ference" for jobs in the service sector,
which they often prefer to jobs in industry
even when the latter are better paid. They
outnumber men in industries such as the
garment and textile industries which are an
extension of their traditional functions.
Their output is higher than men's in preci¬
sion jobs. But although they work quickly,
their dexterity generally receives little
reward.
Contrary to an often-made assertion, it is
not women who do the most unpleasant
jobs. The toughest work (mining, deep-sea
fishing, foundrywork, etc.) as well as the
humblest and least attractive jobs (refuse
collection, sewer cleaning, etc.) are
everywhere done by men. Men are in a
much wider spectrum of occupations than
women, ranging from the most prestigious
to the least enviable.
Even at school boys have a much wider
variety of ideas and ambitions than girls
where jobs are concerned. Girls' choices
focus on two main activities: teaching and
nursing. This trend is universal and appears
in countries as different as the U.S.S.R.,
Italy and Sweden. Nor does co-educational
schooling seem to encourage wider
choices. Obviously, social conditioning
is all-important here, and even if we are
performing an act of faith rather than true
reasoning, we must do away with the
prohibitions and stereotypes. School
textbooks must be monitored to see that
they do not present stereotyped images of
men's and women's jobs.
Maternity has an important bearing on
the whole question of women's employ¬
ment and poses many role problems both
for the mother, the father and society at
large. Should mothers be encouraged to
stop working? Should child care facilities
be provided for them during working
hours? Should they be given the opportu¬
nity to go back to work later on?
Women everywhere are starting work
later than in the past because of the raising
of the school leaving age. The number of
women workers between the ages of 20
and 55 is on the increase throughout
Europe, but the statistical pattern varies
widely from one country to another. In the
eastern countries all women generally work
until retirement age, which is earlier than
that of men and is brought forward even
further if the woman has had several chil¬
dren. In the Soviet Union the pattern is
sharply outlined: 85 per cent of women
aged 20 are in employment; almost 90 per
cent of those between 30 and 50; after the
age of 55 the figure drops sharply to 26 per
cent, and then falls to 7 per cent after the
age of 60. Even if the Soviet definitions of
"activity" are very broad, this pattern
shows that a strong priority is given to the
economic role of women through their pro¬
fessional activities over their role as wives,
housekeepers and mothers.
The same pattern is found in the east
European countries, with certain variants.
However, sudden downturns in population
growth have caused some of these coun¬
tries (Hungary, Czechoslovakia, the Demo¬
cratic Republic of Germany and Poland) to
allow women to take about two years off
work after the birth of a child, in addition to
a long period of maternity leave. This inter¬
ruption in working life is unpaid in the case
of the first child, but starting with the
second the mother has the right to an
allowance. In Hungary in 1974, 229,000
women, or 10 per cent of the total number
of women in employment, had temporarily
stopped work after a birth. These figures
show that Hungary has come to give prio- i
rity to the role of the mother. I
"Man's work lasts till set of sun;
Woman's work is never done". In
this satirical 17th-century
engraving. Woman is depicted
festooned with household
utensils and condemned to a
life of drudgery. P?"*'M¿,
I Photo © Snark International, Pans (Private Collection)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
In countries such as Spain, Luxem¬
bourg, Ireland and the Netherlands the
situation is quite different. There women
take jobs as soon as they leave school until
the age of 20 or 21. By the age of 25 only
between 20 and 30 per cent of women are
still at work, and the figure drops even fur¬
ther later on. The drop is so abrupt that it
can almost be taken to indicate the age of
marriage and the birth of the first child. The
roles of wife and mother have taken prece¬
dence over professional activities. There
is no large-scale return to work after
maternity.
The same phenomenon occurs in Bel¬
gium, Italy and Greece where the activity
peak is reached at age 21-22, but in these
countries the drop is much less abrupt and
less closely linked to marriage. In Belgium,
married women even represent a particu¬
larly high proportion of the total number of
working women: 60 per cent.
Fifteen years ago, the rates of working
women in the FederaJ Republic of Ger¬
many, France, the United Kingdom, Swe¬
den and Denmark peaked around the age
of 21 (70 per cent). The figures dropped at
the age of maternity and then began to rise
again after the age of 35, reaching a second
peak around age 50. This indicates that for
many women life was divided into three
phases: work, maternity, work. Since then
things have changed (except in the United
Kingdom). More women are working at the
age of maternity, and more and more
young mothers are continuing to work. In
the United Kingdom there is still a drop at
the age of maternity but more and more
women are returning to work later on: in
the U.K. the average age of women in
employment is relatively high.
I NE observation which is
rarely made is that women everywhere on
average live longer than men but finish
their professional lives sooner, whether or
not they have had children. Except for
women who work on the land, few carry
on beyond retirement age and many retire
even before. In the case of men the situa¬
tion is totally different. Does this mean that
women are less energetic? Do they feel that
they are less "defined" by their profession,
Are they less affected than men by the
trauma of retirement? Is their grandmother-
role more important than is often thought
and does it influence their decisions?
Research on these questions still remains
to be done.
It is known that farmers' wives are the
most "active" category of working
women, but the professional activities of
women vary according to the social and
professional status of their husbands. The
proportion of married women who do not
go out to work reflects a U-curve in relation
to the salary of their husbands. They are
proportionately numerous in families where
the husband earns little, less so when he
has a moderate salary. The figure rises
again in the case of women whose hus¬
bands have a high income. Far from ten¬
ding to promote equality in family incomes,
the wife's work sometimes accentuates the
disparities in income between families in
the lower and middle strata of society,
since it is more common for the woman to
make a significant contribution to the
family budget in households where the
husband already earns a decent salary.
The social and professional category of
the husband is often more important in
determining whether or not the wife works
than that of the wife. Furthermore, rela¬
tions between man and wife are often on a
more equal basis in the middle strata of
society while certain aspects of patriarchy
have persisted among the very poor and
the very rich.
Few data exist on the relationship bet¬
ween the number of children, their age and
the working lives of the mother. However,
such figures as we have all tell the same
story.
The birth of a third child often has a
strong influence on whether or not the
mother goes out to work. Between 80 and
90 per cent of mothers of children under fif¬
teen do not go out to work, even in coun¬
tries like France and Belgium which lead
Europe in their provision of day-care facili¬
ties for children between two and six years
old.
The value attached to a job is generally
indicated by its remuneration. In Europe it
was traditionally accepted that women
should be paid less than men, either as a
sanction of their natural "inferiority" or of
their presence in the world of paid work,
considered to be abnormal and detrimen¬
tal. Today the principle of unequal pay is no
longer accepted, but it has not totally
disappeared. However, although a good
deal of ink has flowed on this question, it is
still not widely understood by the public.
The only way to appreciate the question
of equality or inequality of pay for the same
job or an equivalent job is to make a com¬
parison between workers of both sexes
doing the same job, with the same qualifi¬
cations and the same amount of expe¬
rience, etc. Only then is it possible to
appreciate the disparity in virtue of sex.
The application of the principle of "equal
pay for equal work" is not easy, in spite of
all the legislative instruments surrounding
it: the ILO International Convention Con¬
cerning Equal Remuneration for Men and
Women Workers for Work of Equal Value
(1951); article 119 of the treaty setting up
the European Economic Community; the
fundamental laws incorporated in the
Constitutions of many countries; provi¬
sions in different countries for punishing
infringements of the principle and for
taking a case to court.
A list of such laws and decrees would be
a long one. However, many of these mea¬
sures have only been promulgated in the
last ten years, and the principle of "equal
pay for equal work" is most respected
where it has already been applied for a cer¬
tain time. It takes time to remove discrimi¬
natory provisions from collective agree¬
ments, to establish an efficient monitoring
system and to bring home to workers' and
employers' organizations a full awareness
of the issues involved.
Above all, it takes time to thwart
attempts to twist the law and undermine
the principle of equal pay for equal work by
changing professional definitions and clas¬
sifications. It takes even more time to per¬
suade women that they have rights of
redress when they are victims of prejudice,
even in a period when the employment
situation is giving rise to concern.
N the last few decades
there has been a movement towards grea¬
ter similarity between men's and women's
role. There has been widespread concern
about women's status and roles, and the
results of this concern have been and
should continue to be beneficial to women.
Yet whatever women's roles may be, and
even if in the less hidebound societies they
are recognized as being of considerable
importance, they still take second place to
those of men. Is this because women are
somehow incapable of exploiting their roles
in terms of power, at least off the beaten
track of private life where they are accusto¬
med to do so? They are often led to empha¬
size the negative, constricting and subordi¬
nate aspects of their roles rather than seek¬
ing to transform them into organized
power.
The most serious studies of women's
attitudes often show that women who go
out to work do not justify themselves by
defending their work but by criticizing
home life, while housewives point to the
alienation of women who go out to work
instead of speaking out for the powers of
the wife and mother in the home. This is a
classic attitude in groups which have been
treated as inferior: they tend to denigrate
themselves by matching themselves
against the performances and values of the
dominant group.
Women could certainly do better in wor¬
king out and establishing their roles both
those which they once monopolized but
are now beginning to share and those
which are now open to them and which
they are learning to perform. If they did so
they would achieve something more than
uncertain and unsystematic forms of pro¬
tection; they would achieve power in public
life.
A minority of women are thinking along
these lines, but only a small minority. Time
is going by, and the climate of opinion may
become less favourable. In any case, defi¬
ning female roles in terms of power may be
yet another instance of slavish obedience
to the male stereotype, which aspires to
conquest and the assertion of power.
There always remains the possibility, of
course, that men may adopt less aggres¬
sive and competitive patterns of behaviour.
If they do, modern society will really have
broken new ground.
Evelyne Sullerot
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Workers can be choosers
In defence of free choice in working life
by Gósta Rehn
GOSTA REHN, head of the Swedish Institute
for Social Research, University of Stockholm,
was formerly Director for Manpower and Social
Affairs with the Organization for Economic Co¬
operation and Development (OECD) in Paris. A
slightly longer version of this article has also
appeared in ILO Information, Geneva (Vol. 14,
No. 1, 1978).
THERE are many dimensions of work¬
ing time: hours per day or week,
days per month and year, years of
work versus years of study and retirement.
Traditionally these aspects have all been
regulated separately and rigidly with little
allowance for the idea that different indivi¬
duals or groups might want to use their
time along different lines.
Individual requests for deviations from
the norms are subjected to scrutiny and
tutelage. Thus you must prove that you are
either a very gifted and stable person or
else definitely retarded and unstable in
order to get particular support from society
for studies and training. You must prove
that you are unable to work to get an early
pension. You must be strong and healthy
not only in order to be able to work but also
to overcome all legal, administrative and
socio-psychological hurdles, if you want to
continue working after normal retirement
age; even then you may be penalized by a
tax rate on your additional earned income
similar to that levied on the income of a mil¬
lionaire. And if you do not use holiday
rights before a certain date every year you
simply lose them.
The fact that social insurance funds or l
other arrangements now exist to provide f
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
income maintenance during all the periods
of non-work could, however, be the basis
for a greater freedom of choice. The
various sorts of income maintenance,
including the tax-based study financing
system, could be combined into one com¬
mon scheme of exchangeable drawing
rights. Assets accumulated on each indivi¬
dual's social security account, thus integra¬
ted, could be made available to him at any
time for purposes of his own choice.
I basic credit for studies
after compulsory school would be needed,
as a starting fund for everybody, but peo¬
ple should not lose their rights in this res¬
pect if they prefer working instead of going
to higher schools for some years of their
youth; this should instead create extra draw¬
ing rights for them once they want to use
the money. This feature would imply a rec¬
tification of some present inequities: that
persons who use big societal resources for
long studies get high pensions on the basis
of a low number of working years, while
the opposite holds for those who work and
pay pension fees all their lives from sixteen
to sixty-five.
With such generalized drawing rights it
would also be up to the individual when
and whether he opts for late retirement
with a high pension or the opposite; whe¬
ther he takes a "temporary retirement"
with full rights to return to work; whether
he accumulates holiday rights in order to
use them for studies, leisure, or an increa¬
sed pension; whether he interrupts his
work career for further education, or his
studies for work. The choice would be his,
and the authorities would have no reason
to scrutinize the "legitimacy" of his use of
his own fund.
Under such a system of drawing rights,
records of "debit" and "credit" should be
available to the individual at any time, just
as with a bank accountwith the impor¬
tant difference that the state is in a position
to guarantee its value against inflationary
erosions, thanks to the fact that the gen¬
eralized contributions would grow auto¬
matically with inflation as they already
do in most social insurance schemes. We
assume of course that the individual is not
permitted to exhaust his assets; he must
still have money left for a reasonable pen¬
sion without extra contributions from tax¬
payers to keep him from starving in his old
age.
It would also be possible to offer certain
advantages to persons who use their draw¬
ing rights in ways that are useful to society,
for instance those who time their periods of
further study or extended leave to coincide
with periods of low demand for their type
of labour, thus making savings on unem¬
ployment insurance. Training for higher
skills and qualifications could be encoura¬
ged and rewarded especially if it implied
switching from an unemployment area
toward shortage occupations.
This idea is not Utopian. Various forms of
flexible retirement do already exist. The
new fifth holiday week in Sweden is avail¬
able for accumulation so that the worker
can take nine weeks off every five years if
he so wishes. In Australia such "long ser¬
vice leave" is a tradition.
With growing levels of real income,
people will want continuing reduction in
working time. Different persons, however,
want this in different ways. To meet all
requests for shorter weekly hours, more
holidays, more schooling, and earlier retire¬
ment by across-the-board regulations is
not possible. People would not like the
ensuing limitation on income and the high
taxes and fees needed for financing the
necessary income maintenance. This over¬
all limitation should not hinder us in letting
the individual choose his own form of
working time reduction, to be financed out
of his own account for drawing rights in
the overall social insurance system.
In some respects such freedom may
create difficulties for the production pro¬
cess. But it can also be a help. Well organi¬
zed flextime systems have helped to reduce
irregular absenteeism and high labour turn¬
over. And a systematic co-ordination with
labour market policy, offering incentives to
people to use voluntarily their drawing
rights in a way that helps to maintain balan¬
ced full employment would also be advan¬
tageous to workers and employers alike
and make shorter working time economi¬
cally more feasible.
Human freedom and technical and eco¬
nomic efficiency may sometimes appear at
first sight to be incompatible. It is up to the
social and economic policy makers to work
out ways of eliminating any incompatibili¬
ties and of making these aspirations
mutually supporting.
Gösta Rehn
Society's
poor
relations
Teachers
count among
the lowest
paid workers
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photo Satyan, Unicef
IN both developed and developing
countries primary school teachers
starting their careers are often paid
less than semi-skilled workers in their first
job in manufacturing industry.
As in few other professions, the impact
of teachers, who in some countries repre¬
sent over 2 per cent of the active popula¬
tion, is felt on the economic and social
health of the country concerned for as
much as forty years. And yet, it may be
thirty years, or just prior to retirement,
before a primary school teacher catches up
with the worker on the pay scale long
after his first pupils have entered the
employment market themselves.
This is one of the findings of an ILO
study (1) which contains information on
some 70 countries and was undertaken to
ascertain the methods of determining tea¬
chers' earnings and the relation of these
earnings to those of other occupations.
Incremental progression, compensation
for non-scholastic duties, difficulty of
recruitment in isolated areas and large
cities are but a few of the factors which
must influence the final determination of
teachers' earnings. These considerations
vary from country to country and even
within countries, from one locality to an-
(1) Teachers' Pay. ILO, Geneva. 1978.
other, making it impossible to lay down
hard-and-fast rules on a global scale.
However, for purposes of international
comparison, average earnings in manufac¬
turing industry were found to present the
most practicable universal norm with which
to relate the earnings of primary school tea¬
chers at the start of their careers.
Using this as a yardstick, among the 27
countries (with a total population of 1,900
million) for which detailed data for 1976
were available, Canada (New Brunswick)
paid the lowest salaries44 per cent less
than average earnings in manufacturing
industry to primary teachers at the bot¬
tom of their salary scale, while the highest
went to their counterparts in Nigeria, who
received the unusually high pay level of 144
per cent more than the relevant workers'
remuneration. Next to. Nigeria, teachers in
Switzerland (Aargau) did best with 27 per
cent more, followed by teachers in the
Federal Republic of Germany with 14.3 per
cent more.
Other countries where teachers in the
same situation received less than the ave¬
rage manufacturing industry worker during
1976 were Japan where it was 35 per cent
less; England and Wales, 32.5 per cent less
while in Norway they received 5 per cent
less.
Figures for 1975 show that, by this same
yardstick, the best place for beginner pri¬
mary teachers that year was Argentina
where their salary was 60 per cent more
than that of the worker. Starting salaries in
Denmark during the same period showed a
respectable 30.1 per ceni more, but in Italy
the percentage was 41.8 less; in Austria,
33.6 less; Kenya, 28.7 and Australia (New
South Wales), 19.6 less than the workers.
In countries where relevant data were
available only up to 1974, beginner primary
school teachers were best off in Mali with
12.7 per cent more than workers in manu¬
facturing industry, while in Belgium they
received 6 per cent more and in France, 4.8
per cent more. In both the Philippines and
Sri Lanka teachers and workers were paid
approximately the same. Teachers' salaries
for 1974 were less than those in manufac¬
turing industry in New Zealand where the
difference was 3.7 per cent; in the
Syrian Arab Republic, 11 per cent less; the
German Democratic Republic, 18.9 per
cent less and Zambia, 34.2 per cent less.
Statistics from both the United States
and the U.S.S.R. covered the ten-year
period from 1965-75 but were compiled on
an average salary basis. In the United
States salaries- of primary and secondary
teachers averaged out slightly ahead
(about 5 per cent) of average earnings in ma- 1
nufacturing industry, over the entire period. I
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
h During the same decade in the U.S.S.R.,
average earnings of educational personnel
in general trailed those of manufacturing
industry and in 1975 were 26.5 per cent
less. However, these figures do not take
into account subsidized rentals, social ser¬
vices, etc. Moreover, in 1977, the govern¬
ment increased salaries of educational per¬
sonnel by 18 per cent.
One of the most pressing problems
which has become acute in the last decade
is the defence of the purchasing power of
teachers' salaries against rampant inflation.
Methods of determining periodicity and
amounts of cost-of-living increases range
from ad hoc, almost casual arrangements,
to regular reviews which may be carried out
by an autonomous government agency
such as the National Personnel Authority in
Japan. The time interval between reviews
may be as much as two years or more as it
is in some of the ad hoc surveys, or as little
as three months as is the case in France.
However, in the countries for which it has
been possible to construct true scores, it is
clear that the purchasing power of teachers
has shown a general upward trend,
although government intervention has
sometimes been necessary to bring this
about.
Although the study draws no con
clusions, several trends are apparent. Over a
number of years, differentials have narrowed
between the salaries of primary and
secondary school teachers and between
salary levels at the bottom and top of indivi¬
dual scales. This may be socially justifiable
but it tends to dampen enthusiasm for
obtaining higher qualifications which in
turn could lead to a deterioration generally
in the calibre of education, the study
warns. There are also indications that in
some educational systems graduate tea¬
chers in secondary schools as well as pri¬
mary school teachers receive less than the
average earnings in manufacturing industry
when commencing their careers.
With the advent of audio-visual tech¬
niques, programmed learning and new
approaches to traditional subjects, the tea¬
ching profession is becoming more com¬
plex and more demanding, and teachers'
organizations are requesting, more and
more, that recognition be made of these
new responsibilities when it -counts the
most on pay-day. ]
The salaries that teachers receive reflect
the importance that society attaches to the
profession. The study points out that the
question is often asked "can the country
afford to pay?" The question may equally
well be asked, "can the country afford not
to pay?"... After the family, the teacher is
the most important influence on the next
generation.
This article has also appeared in the
International Labour Organisation's
bulletin ILO Information, Geneva
(Vol. 13, No. 5, 1977).
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
"A teacher affects eternity; he
can never tell where his
influence stops", wrote the
American historian Henry
Adams (1838-1918) in The
Education of Henry Adams, one
of the world's great
autobiographies. And yet in
spite of the far-reaching
influence teachers exercise and
the growing number of skills
they must have at their
fingertips, in many parts of the
world their economic status
leaves much to be desired. An
ILO study on teachers' pay
reveals that in some countries
today young teachers earn less
than semi-skilled workers in
their first job, with few
prospects of catching up with
these workers on the pay scale
until just before retirement.
Photos on these pages show
teacher and pupils in the little
village of St. Maurice d'lsbie in
southern France. Twice a week
the youngsters leave books and
blackboard behind them and
take a ramble in the countryside
to learn about natural history at
first hand.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Copyright The creator's
bread
and butter
by Henri de Saint-Blanquat
ARE authors an endangered species?
Will they be extinct, a hundred
years from now? These questions
are not entirely facetious. Judging from the
present state of affairs as far as the protec¬
tion of their livelihood is concerned, their
future is, to say the least, uncertain.
This statement may come as a surprise.
Never have so many books been printed;
never have there been so many authors,
whether of literary or other works. Yet the
explosion in modern means of communica¬
tion carries with it a threat to the author
and to the notion of "intellectual
property". Authors may well soon find
themselves the victims of technological
advance.
Not that authors were treated more
favourably in the past. In the early 18th
century, an author who sold a manuscript
to a bookseller surrendered all his rights as
far as his work was concerned; the book¬
seller could dispose of it as he wished. And
if the notion of literary property is of more
ancient origin (the Romans recogniz¬
ed it, just as they recognized the funda¬
mental principle of moral interest, which
allowed the author some say in the for¬
tunes of his work, even after he had sold it
to another person), this early "copyright"
was a matter of unwritten agreements and
traditional arrangements: it carried no
legal consequences.
It was not until the end of the 18th cen¬
tury that the first copyright laws made their
appearance, according official recognition
to the rights of authors to obtain equitable
payment for their work, and to retain some
measure of ownership of their literary pro¬
perty, even when it had been published.
This was a hard-won victory; in a great
many cases, authors were obliged to go to
court to obtain recognition of their rights.
In France, it was not until the Revolution
was well under way that their rights began
to be recognized in law. As far as writers
for the theatre were concerned, the drama¬
tist Beaumarchais put the matter in a nut-
HENRI DE SAINT-BLANQUAT, French scien¬
tific journalist, is the author of many articles on
anthropology, ethnology, sociology and
archaeology. His study on medieval and early
modern Europe, La Vie en Europe (Life in
Europe) was published by Hachette, Paris, in
1970.
shell when he remarked: "They are saying
in the theatre lobbies that it is ignoble for
writers, whose pretension it is to aspire to
fame, to plead for vulgar monetary reward.
Yet in truth, whatever the attractions of
fame, to enjoy it but for one year, nature
obliges us to dine three hundred and sixty-
five times."
But it was not enough for a country to
give legal recognition to literary and artistic
rights, for this only afforded the author
protection within the frontiers of his own
country. What the 18th century began, the
19th century had to continue, not only by
ensuring that authors' rights were recogniz¬
ed abroad, but also by ensuring that their
works enjoyed truly international protec¬
tion, so that a book by an Italian author, for
example, remained as much his property in
Iceland or Japan as in his native land.
This was easier said than done. Bilateral
treaties were a beginning, later to be fol¬
lowed by international unions and conven¬
tions. 1886 saw the adoption of the Berne
Convention for the Protection of Artistic
and Literary Works a European agree¬
ment and the first multilateral copyright
convention in history. Three years later, the
first in a series of pan-American conven¬
tions was adopted.
But that was not the end of the story.
Protection can always be improved. The
Berne Convention was revised and correc¬
ted in 1908, 1928 and 1967, while a series
of pan-American conventions were con¬
cluded between 1889 and 1946.
The fact that there were two different
sets of conventions posed a number of pro¬
blems that were partially resolved by the
adoption in 1952, under the aegis of
Unesco, of the Universal Copyright Con¬
vention. But this Convention, which in its
turn would be revised in 1971, did not
replace the earlier instruments. States
remained free to adhere to the Universal
Copyright Convention in its original or re¬
vised form, or to any of the non-universal
unions or conventions. This explains why
the Berne Convention could be revised for
the third time in 1967, fifteen years after the
Universal Convention was adopted.
At present, some States adhere only to
the Berne Convention; others (72 in all)
adhere to the Universal Convention; still
others adhere either to both or to none.
while the Soviet Union is a signatory of the
Universal Copyright Convention, in the ver¬
sion of 1952. All of which goes to show
that the protection of literary, artistic and
scientific works is a complex affair, and one
which may become even more complicated
as time goes on.
At this point, it might be asked, what
exactly is to be protected, and how? The
answer depends on the situation; and the
number of different situations is virtually
unlimited. Anglo-Saxon law, for example,
merely protects works that have been for¬
mally deposited, registered and legally
identified, whereas "continental" Euro¬
pean, law tends to protect the act of cre¬
ation itself. The existence of these two dis¬
tinct schools of legal thought explains why,
for so long, two series of international
agreements have existed side by side.
Furthermore, the Socialist countries
have their own ideas on the subject. In the
Western countries, notwithstanding cer¬
tain national differences, copyright law is
based on the notion of property and the
laws of a free market. In the Socialist coun¬
tries on the other hand, where the State
assumes the role of publisher, works of
authorship are sometimes considered as
property that can be exchanged (in which
case the author enjoys certain rights of
ownership); but they are above all con¬
sidered as cultural values .and as instru¬
ments to be placed at the service of
society, so that the author receives no
royalties when they are used for educa¬
tional purposes.
To complicate matters still further, there
is the case, only recently acknowledged, of
the developing countries, which must rely
on massive imports of intellectual works,
, and at the same time develop their own
output. Efforts to help them solve this pro¬
blem have led to the granting of certain
facilities as far as copyright is concerned,
which in effect limit the rights of authors of
works circulating in those countries.
The key word here is the word "limit". It
might be presumed that during the past
two centuries works of the mind have
come to enjoy greater and greater protec¬
tion, and that their authors' livelihood has
increased accordingly. Such is indeed the
case, and bodies like Unesco and the
World Intellectual Property Organization
(WiPO) are doing what they can to consoli-
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
It has been calculated that if Sophocles' play Oedipus Rex were presented on television today, the audience it could reach in a
single showing would be far bigger than the total number of spectators to have seen It In a theatre since it was written 25
centuries ago. Above, Oedipus in a 1967 film version of the play, directed by the Italian film-maker Pier Paolo Pasolini. A recent
Unesco-ILO survey on the condition of writers and artists in the modern world drew attention to "the small extent to which the
artist exercises control over the management of his own affairs, and the problem of obtaining remuneration commensurate with
the commercial use made of his work."
date this trend. Nevertheless, there are
limits to the progress that can be made,
and a number of disquieting signs indicate
that the situation is not evolving as fa¬
vourably as it might, at least as far as
authors are concerned.
One thing is certain: there will always be
limits of some kind. When is an author not
an author, and where do creation, imita¬
tion, plagiarism, execution and interpreta¬
tion begin and end? Precisely what should
copyright protect? There are no easy
replies to these questions, as may be seen
from a number of lawsuits heard in recent
years.
In 1975, for example, a French court was
called upon to rule whether or not the for¬
mula of a particular perfume was protected
by the laws of copyright. In the same
country, the unauthorized reproduction of
photographs has given rise to lengthy
debates and contradictory judgements.
French law, it is true, protects "photo¬
graphic works of an artistic or document¬
ary nature". But what is "artistic", and
what is "documentary"? That is where the
difficulty lies.
The attribution of royalties poses an¬
other problem. On orders from their supe¬
riors, two American soldiers designed and
erected a statue destined to serve as the
emblem of their garrison. When they retur¬
ned to civilian life, they claimed royalties on
their work of art. The courts decided other¬
wise, ruling that the Army had financed the
project, and discharged the executants
from any further obligations. "If copyright
is due," ruled the judges, "it is due exclusi¬
vely to the Government of the United
States of America."
Whether or not plagiarism has been
committed can also be the subject of end¬
less debate. It should be pointed out here
that copyright, as a general rule, protects
creations but not ideas, in other words, the
substance but not the inspiration. Follow¬
ing a competition for the design of a monu¬
ment to the liberator of Paris, General
Leclerc, to be erected on the outskirts of
the French capital, an unsuccessful compe
titor took the winner to court, claiming that
his project had been plagiarized. The
defendant claimed that he had merely
"borrowed" his rival's idea of a grandiose
and symbolic "Victory-V". The initial judge¬
ment in favour of the plaintiff was revers¬
ed on appeal: since the defendant had
merely adopted the plaintiff's idea, plagia¬
rism had not occurred.
These examples are more than anecdo¬
tic. They reveal not only that the exercise
of rights at any given time (our own time,
in the cases mentioned) is subject to limita¬
tion, but also that the limits are mobile and
subject to constant dispute.
The rights of individuals, of authors, are
one thing, but the right of access to literary
and other works of society as a whole and
the public at large must also be protected.
In addition, there are various "pressure
groups", whose primary concern is with
protection of their vested interests. To
keep all these different elements in equili¬
brium requires a veritable juggler's skill, i
The see-saw is never horizontal.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Copyright and
computer art
Electronic music, graphics and other
works created with the aid of a computer
today pose a highly sensitive copyright
problem. One major difficulty is where to
draw the line between human intervention
in the creative process and the point
where the computer might be considered
to "take over". Unesco is carrying out
studies on this and other related questions
as part of the international community's
effort to define the copyright status of
computer art. Right, computer graphic by
artists from the Fed. Rep. of Germany.
( Translators are another category of peo¬
ple with problems of a similar kind. It was
not until 1976, during the General Con¬
ference of Unesco at Nairobi, that an
international Recommendation was adopt¬
ed on the legal protection of translators
and translations. In its opening lines, the
text recalls that the principles of protection
are one thing, and their actual application
another. In principle, translators are pro¬
tected by the Universal Copyright Conven¬
tion, by certain provisions of the Berne
Convention and by a number of national
laws. In reality, the text prudently observes
"The practical application of the principles
and provisions is not always adequate."
This remark is followed by a series of sug¬
gestions for further action a modest step
forward after so many years of effort.
It would, in any case, be an error to
believe that steady and irresistible progress
is being made towards increased recog¬
nition of authors' rights. The example of
the developing countries mentioned above
shows, on the contrary, that it has been
necessary in their case to impose certain
limits on authors' rights with regard to
works translated in or imported into those
countries. The copyright conventions thus
provide for various facilities, reductions or
dispensations designed to enable the deve¬
loping countries to obtain more books and
to make more translations, as a matter of
extreme urgency.
These measures reflect a certain moral
concern or at least an enlightened self-
interest on the part of the major book-
producing countries. But the extension of
copyright protection is threatened by other
limitations, which are yet to be clearly de¬
fined and which are due to the manner in
which the techniques of communication
are evolving. If the recognition of copyright
poses few problems where radio and tele¬
vision programmes are concerned, the task
is far more difficult in the case of repro¬
ductions: tapes and cassettes for creative
works in sound, cables and video-cassettes
for visual images, and photocopies for
texts.
Here, too, one or two case-histories will
show the kind of difficulties that can arise.
At the beginning of 1974, a Paris court
handled a lawsuit involving a number of
publishing houses, including publishers of
scientific works in particular, and the
French National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS), on the subject of photo¬
copies.
Instead of purchasing several copies of a
given book, this research centre, like many
other laboratories and libraries, preferred to
buy single copies, and to make use of a
photocopying machine to reproduce the
pages which their scholars and students
required. Quite obviously, the more the
photocopier was used, the fewer copies of
the book were sold by the publishers and
the smaller the royalties received by the
author. In this case (similar ones have
occurred in the United States), judgement
was given against the CNRS, but in merely
symbolic terms; if it had gone further, the
court would have infringed the right of
public access to published works.
This ruling indicates that the trend is
towards compromise: laboratories and
libraries, whose requirements are uncon¬
tested, are assimilated to private indivi¬
duals, and their photocopying activities are
not considered as an offence. On the other
hand, the case showed that a limitation had
indeed been imposed on authors' rights.
Another recent case concerned radio
sets installed in hotel rooms. France's
Society of Authors, Composers and Music
Publishers (SACEM) took a Paris hotel to
court, claiming that rights were due on
behalf of its members in respect of pro¬
grammes broadcast on those sets.
SACEM's position Was clear: the hotel was
a public place, and thus subject to copy¬
right. The hotel management, supported
by the French Federation of Hoteliers,
claimed that its rooms were private, and
thus exempt from copyright law.
The court found in favour of the hotel,
basing its ruling on the fact that the man¬
agement did not select the programmes
broadcast. If, on the other hand, the man¬
ager had relayed programmes to clients'
rooms from a receiver situated somewhere
in the establishment, he would have been
found guilty, since the programmes would
then have been considered as public per¬
formances. This, incidentally, was the
judgement given in an Australian case,
where the organizer of a dance for mem¬
bers of a private club was found to have
given a public performance.
Many copyright problems have yet to
find solutions. "Pirate" recording is one of
them. Countless young people today lend
each other records, and re-record them on
to cassettes. There is nothing to prevent
them from doing this: as members of the
public, they are merely exercising their
right of access, with the help of the latest
techniques. Some countries have, how¬
ever, found solutions to the problem. In the
Federal Republic of Germany, for example,
the purchase price of a tape-recorder in¬
cludes a sum destined for the benefit of
performing artists.
The "rediffusion" of programmes of all
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
kinds is another issue that awaits solution.
Here, the situation is complicated by the
fact that a distinction is made according to
whether or not the body responsible for
retransmission is the originator of the pro¬
gramme concerned. No solutions have as
yet been found in this connexion, whether
with regard to radio, to cable or television
or to video-cassettes, although the matter
is being considered by a number of inter¬
governmental committees, under the aegis
of Unesco.
Cable television was the subject of a
meeting in July of this year, and video-
cassettes were considered in September.
While it is to be hoped that positive so¬
lutions will eventually be found, one thing
is already clear. The latest techniques of
communication permit ever-increasing
access to an ever-increasing number of
works of all kinds, and it is morally un¬
thinkable to obstruct this process.
The increasing use of satellites carries
the problem of copyright into space, and
into a new and extremely important dimen¬
sion. Three well-placed geostationary
satellites can in fact cover the whole sur¬
face of the Earth. This means that un¬
authorized countries or organizations,
which have not signed any of the interna¬
tional agreements, will be able to pick up
programmes transmitted to other destina¬
tions, and to become "wavelength pirates"
on a grand scale. Can this be avoided?
In 1974, Unesco and the World Intellec¬
tual Property Organization (WIPO) adopted
a Convention specifically devoted to this
question. Under the provisions of its Article
2, each Contracting State "undertakes to
take adequate measures to prevent the dis¬
tribution on or from its territory of any
programme-carrying signal by any distribu¬
tor for whom the signal... is not intended."
At present, four States have signed this
convention. It is true that the problem is an
enormous one, and goes beyond the mere
risk of piracy: certain transmission net¬
works are capable of monopolizing the
attention of the whole world.
Last in this series of problems of copy¬
right are those posed by computers. What
can be done, for example, with regard to
their programmes? How can they be given
legal protection? Are they covered by copy¬
right or by patent law? Should they be the
subject of special legislation? WIPO is
studying the question. But here again,
reproduction is a stumbling-block.
Computers, in fact, represent automatic
The protection of folklore
In its customary setting, folklore undergoes a natural growth which ensures its
authenticity, but when transplanted from its native soil and used for
commercial purposes it is laid open to the same risks as other works of the
creative imagination: plagiarism, amputation, misappropriation and unlawful
reproduction or use. Unesco, in collaboration with specialized bodies such as
the Berne Union, is engaged in the search for ways of protecting the world's
heritage of folklore by regulations enabling it to retain its authenticity. Below,
musicians of Kahemba (Zaire) playing the balafon, a kind of xylophone.
documentation carried to the heights of
perfection. And whether they store cata¬
logues, inventories, data, quotations, ab¬
stracts, analyses or automatic translations,
they are of direct concern to authors,
whose attempts to secure their rights are
likely to meet stubborn opposition on the
part of the computers' owners and pro¬
grammers, who will no doubt use all the
means at their disposal to avoid paying
royalties.
Today's technological revolution, as
Marie-Claude Dock, head of Unesco's
Copyright Division has pointed out, is full
of promise and at the same time fraught
with dangers. It recalls an earlier leap for¬
ward: the invention of the printing-press.
After Gutenberg, authors were for a long
time powerless in the face of printers and
publishers. They had to wait three full cen¬
turies before they were officially entitled to
draw real benefit from the extraordinary
opportunities that printing offered.
Their problems today are of a similar
kind. The explosion in communication,
which has virtually acquired the dimensions
of a chain-reaction, is not to be deplored;
science and culture will undoubtedly be its
beneficiaries. But there is as much risk as
promise in the situation. New economic
forces have made their appearance or are
waiting in the wings, and this cannot but
affect works of the mind. And since identi¬
cal phenomena lead to identical solutions,
unless care is taken the rights of authors
may well be swallowed up and lost in the
dark waters of economic interest.
And meanwhile, today as in the age of
Beaumarchais, authors must, if they are to
survive, sit down to dinner three hundred
and sixty-five times every year.
Henri do Saint-Blanquat
Record piracy
and plunder
The booty of "record pirates",
whose illegally reproduced
recordings rob record producers,
authors, composers and performers
of their financial rewards, is
reckoned to have reached $500
million in 1977. Cassettes are the
main target. A meeting of record
producers recently estimated that
70 per cent of the cassettes sold in
the U.K., 50 per cent of those sold
in Italy and 5 per cent of those sold
in France (mostly Arab music) had
been reproduced illegally.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco,
youth
and the right
to work
JJ young person has the same
MB inalienable right as all other
human beings to perform fairly
paid, creative work" this was a major con¬
clusion of the European Regional Meeting
of Youth organized by Unesco In Venice
(Italy) from 7 to 11 November 1977. The
gathering's theme was "the effects of the
economic situation on the access of young
people to education, culture and work".
The problem of unemployment was
uppermost in the minds of many speakers,
at a time when there were six million unem¬
ployed in the European Community, one-
third of them young people.
On the other hand, delegates from the
socialist countries, where the right to
employment is effectively guaranteed by
the constitution, pointed out that the prob¬
lem did not arise in the same way in their
countries, although it was recognized that
the question had many different forms,
perhaps more difficult to pinpoint but no
less important. One of these was employ¬
ment in jobs unsuited to the holders' abili¬
ties, education or aspirations.
Although most speakers were concerned
with factors bound up with the prevailing
economic situation, they all expressed the
view that a more human approach should
'be adopted regarding unemployment. Pre¬
sent concepts of work were questioned,
and participants stressed that young work¬
ers and employees are particularly sensitive
to the boredom, frustration and lack of ful¬
filment that characterize many employ¬
ment situations today. Work, they felt,
should be viewed as an integral part of cul¬
tural life, and education should be con¬
ceived with this in mind.
Participants formulated a number of
recommendations seeking: to facilitate the
exchange of information and experience
between young workers in Europe and
those in the developing countries; to pro¬
duce studies on the transition from school
to work, on work as young people see it,
and on the role of the mass media in rela¬
tion to employment problems; to promote
the adoption and implementation by the
United Nations of a code of conduct for
multinational enterprises; to organize inter¬
national meetings on problems faced by
young workers such as new forms of voca¬
tional training and the access of young
workers to culture.
As a follow-up to the Venice meeting,
Unesco's Youth Programme has accorded
increased attention to the problems of
young people at work or seeking work. In
early 1979 an international study will be
published on the specific difficulties of
schooled or university-trained jobless
youth.
An agreement is being concluded bet¬
ween Unesco and ILO to review special
employment-related youth training pro¬
grammes in Africa.
Finally, the renewal of vocational training
programmes, which should prepare youth
educationally and culturally as well as for
job mobility but which are at present over
rigid, has become a central concern of the
world community and thus of Unesco.
THE BRAIN DRAIN continued from page 17
In addition, developed countries could
assist the developing countries to absorb
their skilled manpower better by setting up
and supporting funds that encourage
Research and Development activities in
developing countries. Another possibility is
to use personnel or consultants from deve¬
loping countries to carry out programmes
or projects in these countries which would
be funded by the industrialized nations.
The problem of compensation is particu¬
larly complex because of the difficulty of
clearly establishing the cause and effects of
migration, and of assessing its scope in
statistical terms.
One major obstacle is the lack of com¬
prehensive and standardized statistics.
Definitions and categories used for clas¬
sifying immigrants to developed countries
have not yet become standardized, and
even when they are available, the data take
no account of emigration back to the deve¬
loping countries which, according to one
UNCTAD study, may represent 25 per cent
in some cases.
IINALLY, inconsistencies
may arise from the general practice of
recording immigrant data on the basis of
last permanent residence as distinct from
nationality. This is important since, to take
one example, as many as 80 per cent and
50 per cent of Pakistani scientists and engi¬
neers entering the U.S. as immigrants in
1966 and 1973 respectively appeared to
have resided outside their country of birth.
In such cases, therefore, the use of the
"last permanent residence" concept would
tend to underestimate the figures of immi¬
grants from developing countries into
industrialized countries. The United King¬
dom has, for instance, often been regarded
as a stopping-off point for migrants from
developing countries whose ultimate desti¬
nation is the United States or Canada, and
these migrants may constitute a significant
proportion of both the inflow and the out¬
flow from the U.K.
A number of proposals have been made
regarding compensation:
Contributions by host developed coun¬
tries, related in some way to the imputed
value of skilled migration from developing
countries. These might take the form of
direct assessment or tax-sharing arrange¬
ments under an agreed formula, supple¬
mented by the possibility of permitting
migrants from developing countries to
make voluntary tax-deductible contribu¬
tions to charitable organizations in develo¬
ping countries and of earmarking, again on
a voluntary basis, up to 10 per cent of their
income tax payments in developed coun¬
tries for development purposes;
A moderate supplementary tax levied on
the income earned in developed countries
by skilled migrants from developing coun¬
tries (at a rate, say, of 5 per cent for a
period of no more than ten years);
The creation of specially chartered orga¬
nizations created in conformity with a
model to be prepared and continually re¬
vised in accordance with internationally
agreed procedures. These organizations
could receive and spend funds raised
through the foregoing measures;
The possible extension of the Internatio¬
nal Monetary Fund compensatory finan¬
cing facility to take account of "adjustment
problems" associated with fluctuations in
migrants' earnings.
In recent years there has been a decline
in the numbers of skilled immigrants from
developing countries to the industrialized
world, but although it is difficult to forecast
the likely size of the brain drain in the next
decade, it can be plausibly argued that this
decline has been related to a number of
factors which are mainly cyclical and tem¬
porary in nature. Future trends in such
migration would, consequently, depend in
part at least on the rate of recovery in the
developed countries.
They may also partly be determined by
the extent to which the economies of the
developed countries have become structu¬
rally dependent on certain types of impor¬
ted skills. As the Report prepared for the
House of Representatives Committee on
Foreign Affairs observed: "Future projec¬
tions of American requirements... suggest
that shortage rather than surplus of techni¬
cal manpower may characterize this cen¬
tury from the late 1970s or early 1980s on.
To satisfy these needs, the advanced coun¬
tries may complement their own indige¬
nous stock with emigrants from developing
countries."
According to one estimate a 4 per cent
annual growth rate in 1978-1980 and a 3.5
per cent rate in 1980-1990 in the Federal
Republic of Germany might necessitate an
additional inflow of foreign labour (both
skilled and unskilled) of the order of two
million by 1990 in that country. In the Uni¬
ted Kingdom, the maintenance and deve¬
lopment of the National Health Service
depends on an inflow of foreign doctors
ranging between 2,500 and 3,000 a year.
"The current system under which skilled
manpower migrates from country to
country is largely a legacy of the past",
concludes the UNCTAD study, "and fails
to distribute equitably to the developing
countries the value of their contribution, in
the form of skilled manpower, to the deve¬
loped economies. The various proposals
outlined above, which aim at correcting
some of the asymmetries in the internatio¬
nal market for labour, are neither novel nor
would they involve any change in existing
international practices; rather they may be
regarded as a step towards broadening the
application of existing international rules to
take into account the concerns of the deve¬
loping countries as suppliers of skilled man¬
power."
The material on which this article is
based represents UNCTAD's
contribution to the in-depth study
of the brain drain problem called
for by the General Assembly of the
United Nations In December 1977.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to
the editor
WASTE NOT, WANT NOT
Sir,
I enjoyed the February issue of the Courier
but I was somewhat disappointed that in an
issue devoted to ways of averting a world
water famine, there was hardly a mention of
the potential that exists for reusing some'
of the water which at present carries our
wastes.
Korzun and Sokolov (page 5) predicted a
bleak outlook for the world's populated
areas which by the year 201 5 are expected to
have come close to exhausting their water
resources. Victor (page 17) is of the opinion
that there are only two viable methods of
providing further supplies of
freshwater desalination of seawater and
exploitation of icebergs. Desalination is an
expensive process and often requires large
amounts of energy, and the feasibility of
using freshwater from icebergs has still to be
established. On the other hand, wastewater
reclamation and reuse is a known techno¬
logy being practised in a number of coun¬
tries.
The New Zealand Commission for the
Environment is compiling a worldwide biblio¬
graphy and directory on the utilization of
waste nutrients from domestic and industrial
wastewaters. Over 350 individuals and agen¬
cies have already responded to our request
for references and our efforts amassed over
4000 titles on the subject. I would like to sug¬
gest that in view of the considerable amount
of information available and the comparable
degree of interest, you could consider an
issue of the Courier dedicated to this very
necessary change in our basic philosophy:
we should not be expending money and
energy searching for ways of disposing of
our wastes, we should be channelling our
efforts to seeking ways of how to use these
"wastes";
we should not search for new sources of
water, but rather, we should be looking for
ways of using what we already have more
efficiently.
Phililp Tortell
for Commissioner for the Environment
Wellington, New Zealand
S.O.S. TAJ MAHAL
Sir,
Art-lovers and ecologists throughout the
world are worried that one of the wonders of
the world, the Taj Mahal, most appropriately
described as "poetry in marble", is going to
be slowly but surely destroyed by the acid
fumes from the six-million-tonne oil refinery
destined to be sited upwind of it.
This region of Mathura-Agra, located
along the valley of the Jamuna river, expe
riences atmospheric inversion for most of
the time during winter. Under the existing
conditions of industrial growth and environ¬
mental pollution control in India, it is very
difficult to ensure proper water and air qua¬
lity standards. As many acidic fumes, gases
and dusts from this refinery travel to Agra,
get converted to acids and attack the mar¬
ble, there is bound to be discolouration and
disfigurement of the Taj Mahal within a short
time after the refinery starts working.
Since world-famous monuments like the
Taj Mahal are considered part of the cultural
heritage of mankind, it is the sacred duty of
everyone to preserve them with all their
grandeur for posterity.
The stone cancer of Cologne cathedral, of
the marble Madonna of Milan cathedral and
the gargoyles of Notre-Dame in Paris must
be an eye-opener to those who do not know
about the long-distance travel of air pollu¬
tants and their impact on acid-rains and the
corrosiveness of the industrial environment.
T. Shivaji Rao
Professor of Environmental Engineering
Andhra University
Waltair, India
A WISH FULFILLED
Sir,
Your November 1977 issue ("Southern
Africa at grips with racism") made instruc¬
tive reading, especially Karel Vasak's article
on the long struggle to give legal force to the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
accompanied as it was by the full text of the
Declaration.
I feel that readers of the Unesco Courier
would welcome the opportunity to read simi¬
lar studies on other conventions, declara¬
tions and documents of general interest set
forth by the United Nations and its specia¬
lized agencies, along with the texts of the
documents in question.
Andrés Rogríguez Gómez
Pinar del Río, Cuba
Our October 1978 issue on teaching human
rights goes some way towards fulfilling your
wish. In addition to articles on various
aspects of human rights, it contained a study
entitled "Twenty Questions" which dealt
with the terms of the Charter of the United
Nations, the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, the International Covenant on
Social, Economic and Cultural Rights, and .
the International Covenant on Civil and Poli¬
tical Rights and the Optional Protocol to the
latter. In the same issue we also presented
certain Unesco recommendations in the field
of human rights along with Unesco's proce¬
dures for dealing with specific complaints
concerning alleged violations of human
rights in its spheres of competence Editor.
UN-AIRWORTHY ISSUE
Sir,
A subscriber to the Unesco Courier since
1969, I am invariably interested by your arti¬
cles on historical and educational subjects
and on the conservation of the environment,
as well as your attacks on racism and discri¬
mination.
Ever since I became a subscriber, I have
looked forward to reading an issue on avia¬
tion and so I was thrilled to receive the April
1978 number on "Aviation at Age 75"
When I came to read the issue, however, I
was terribly disappointed. I had hoped that
you would have paid tribute to the contribu¬
tion of aviation to human progress by telling
readers about the history of aviation, its trail-
blazers and their discoveries. Instead of
doing this you concentrated on aviation
today and its prospects for tomorrow,
paying scant attention to its history.
Armando Carnet Nunez
Manzanillo, Cuba
WHO MADE THE FIRST
PLANE FLIGHT?
Sir,
The author of "Flight without Frontiers",
an article published in the April 1978 issue of
the Unesco Courier, notes that on 17
December 1903, Wilbur Wright, at the con¬
trols of "a frail structure of metal, wood and
fabric struggled into the air" and that man
thus "succeeded for the first time in flying a
heavier-than-air, engine-powered machine".
I am prompted to write to you not so
much because of this statement, debatable
though it is, as the assertion that follows it:
"This date is generally considered Year I in
the history of aviation". This is far from
being the truth. Brazil, for example, officially
chose to celebrate 1956 as "Santos Dumont
Year" to mark the fiftieth anniversary of the
Brazilian inventor Alberto Santos Dumont's
historic flight at the Bagatelle park near Paris
on 23 October 1906. On that day Santos-
Dumont, flying his "14-bis" aircraft, solved
the threefold problem of engine-powered "
flight: taking ' off, achieving sustain¬
ed flight, and landing a heavier-than-air
machine using only its own power.
The Wright brothers' machine rolled
downhill along a wooden rail to pick up
speed before take-off; it had skids, not
wheels, as can be seen in the photo on page
4. Santos Dumont's "14-bis", on the other
hand, was equipped with wheels in direct
contact with the ground and gained speed
only from its own engine-power before it
took off. Unlike the Wright brothers'
machine, it had an undercarriage.
In 1941, when the aeroclub of the United
States proposed that 17 December should
be chosen to mark "Pan-American Aviation
Day", Brazil and many aviation clubs in Cen¬
tral and South America protested on the
grounds that this would have constituted a
slight on Alberto Santos Dumont, the man
whom Thomas Alva Edison dubbed "the
pioneer of the air". The Aeroclub de France,
on the other hand, erected a monument to
this "pioneer of aviation".
Emil de Roure Silva
Graduates' Association
of the Higher War Academy
Niteroi, Brazil
The question of who first conquered the sky
is still unanswered and probably will be so
forever. It ¡s a fact that a number of aviation
pioneers, including Santos Dumont, experi¬
mented with flying machines before and
after the Wright brothers succeeded after
several attempts in staying aloft for 59
seconds, covering 852 feet on the
ground the equivalent of a flight of one
half-mile in still air. Perhaps more than any
other "invention" human flight resulted from
the creative impulse and the daring of pio¬
neers of many countries who learned from
each other's mistakes and successes and
each contributed in his own way to making
aviation what it is today Editor.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
World Water Balance and Water
Resources of the Earth, prepared by
the Chief Administration of the Hydro-
meteorological Service under the Coun¬
cil of Ministers of the U.S.S.R.
(U.S.S.R. Committee for the Internatio¬
nal Hydrological Decade). The results of
studies of the earth's water balance and
water resources, prepared by Soviet
scientists within the programme of the
International Hydrological Decade and
incorporating the latest Soviet and inter¬
national research. ("Studies and Reports
in Hydrology" series, No. 25) Also in¬
cludes the Atlas of the World Water
Balance, which contains 65 maps illus¬
trating the distribution of precipitation,
evaporation and river run-off over the
continental land masses, the world
ocean and the earth as a whole. 1978,
663 pp. (+ 65 maps) 300 F.
Economic Aspects of Special Edu¬
cation. Three case studies on education
for the handicapped in Czechoslovakia,
New Zealand and the United States.
1978, 152 pp. (24 F).
Computers and Social Options is
the theme of Unesco's quarterly Impact
of Science on Society (Vol. 28, No. 3,
1978). Each issue: 12 F; subscriptions
40 F for one year or 66 F for two years.
Human Habitats: from Tradition to
Modernism, theme of Unesco's quar¬
terly International Social Science
Journal (Vol. XXX, No. 3, 1978). Each
issue 23 F; subscriptions 70 F for one
year or 116 F for two years.
OTHER BOOKS
A Primer of Drug Action, by Robert
M. Julien. W.H. Freeman and Co., San
Francisco USA and Reading U.K. 2nd
edition 1978, 288 pp. ($16.80 hardback;
$7.20 softback).
Tactical Nuclear Weapons: Euro¬
pean Perspectives. Published by Tay¬
lor and Francis Ltd., London, on behalf
of Stockholm International Peace
Research Institute (SIPRI), and distrib¬
uted by Almqvist and Wiksell Internatio¬
nal, Stockholm (for Scandinavia), Crane,
Russak and Co. Inc., New York (for
USA), and Taylor and Francis (for rest of
world). 1978, 371 pp. (£10.50).
Gardening for Better Nutrition, an
OXFAM document by Arnold Pacey.
Intermediate Technology Publications
Ltd., London. 1978, 64 pp. (£1.60).
The Role of Women in Rural Zaire
and Upper Volta, by David A. Mitch-
nik. An OXFAM working paper (A re¬
vised version of a paper prepared for the
ILO within the framework of the World
Employment Programme. Available from
OXFAM, Oxford, U.K. 1978, 36 pp.
(50 p.).
Unicef greetings cards
Unicef, the United Nations Children's Fund, is
today active in nearly 100 developing countries,
providing needy children with better nutrition,
improved health care and better educational
opportunities. Most aid is for long-term develop¬
ment, but Unicef also provides emergency relief
when children are endangered by natural or
man-made disasters. The idea was born in 1949
when a 7-year-old Czechoslovakian girl drew a
picture and sent it to Unicef as thanks for the
Fund's help to her village after World War II.
Today Unicef produces cards suitable for many
occasions : birthdays, Mother's Day, birth
announcements and so on, as well as a calen¬
dar postcards and stationery sets. All are now
available at Unicef sales points throughout the
world. The theme of the 1979 calendar, "Focus
on Children in Art", was chosen to tie in with the
International Year of the Child proclaimed by the
United Nations General Assembly for 1979. The
reproductions, from over 40 countries, include
masterpieces by Rembrandt, Rubens, Goya,
Gainsborough and Fragonard, and the cover, a
child'writing on a banana leaf, is a detail from a
Japanese screen. Card shown here features
"Church Bells", a design by the Polish artist
Maria Jas.
Unesco sponsors
Red Cross poster series
As a tribute to the part played by the Red Cross
in contributing to the peaceful development of
nations, thus promoting a new international eco¬
nomic order, Unesco is sponsoring a poster
series produced by the League of Red Cross
Societies on "The Red Cross and World Prob¬
lems". The poster set, accompanied by a back¬
ground document for teachers, contains 6 pho¬
tos showing major Red Cross activities. The pos¬
ters are available (with commentary in English,
French, Spanish or Arabic) free from the League
of Red Cross Societies, P.O.B. 276, 1211
Geneva 19, Switzerland.
Rabies spreads
in Europe
The recorded number of animal rabies cases for
1977 indicates that the disease has gained new
territories in Europe, reports the World Health
Organization. Italy was again invaded and Den¬
mark reinfected for the third time, while the epi¬
demic spread to new areas in Austria, Switzer¬
land, France and the Czech Socialist Republic.
The disease maintained its strongholds in the
German Dem. Rep., the Fed. Rep. of Germany,
Poland and Hungary.
Unesco award
for officials
of 12 National Commissions
At a ceremony held at Unesco's Paris HQ on 27
October 1978, the Director-General, Mr.
Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, presented the Organi¬
zation's . silver medal to 3 chairmen and 9
secretaries-general of National Commissions for
Unesco who had occupied their posts for at least
15 years. At a round table meeting before the
ceremony there was discussion of the draft char¬
ter on the role of National Commissions, which
was to be submitted to Unesco's General Con¬
ference and forms part of efforts to bind the
Organization as closely as possible to its
Member States.
Nineteen new reserves
for Brazil
Brazil is establishing 19 ecological stations
throughout the country covering a total area of
900,000 hectares. In each station ecological data
will be collected and comparative studies made
between these protected areas and those nearby
inhabited by man. Most of the stations will be
ready for scientific work by the end of 1978.
U.N. stamp
honours
General Assembly
The United Nations Postal Administration has
issued a set of stamps on the theme "The United
Nations General Assembly". All Member States
are represented in the General Assembly, the
U.N.'s main deliberative organ, which meets in
regular annual sessions from September to
December and in special sessions when re¬
quired. The stamps are issued in the follow¬
ing values : Sw. Fr. 0.70 and 1.10 and 13 and
18 U.S., cents.
3
o
o
3
o
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Biology
and ethics
Reflection* inspired by a Unoco sympowum
h> Bruno Ribes
A new Unesco series
INSIGHTS, a major new Unesco series focussing on important
themes and critical choices facing mankind today. By creating
INSIGHTS, Unesco hopes to inform a wide public, as well as specia¬
lists, about the contributions of many different disciplines to the
study of world problems.
Biology and Ethics, the second title in the series, examines the
relations between biology and ethics in the light of the new possibili¬
ties opened up by recent developments in the life sciences. In 1975
Unesco held a symposium in Varna (Bulgaria) on biology and ethics,
attended by distinguished biologists and philosophers from many
parts of the world.
In Biology and Ethics, Prof. Bruno Ribes of France reviews their
contributions on such urgent issues as the ethical problems posed
by genetic manipulation the regulation of human behaviour organ
transplantation new directions in research into ethics relating to
biology.
202 pages 38 French francs
To be published shortly
Violence and its Causes
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch-
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-652
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Vertag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahnr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Pans, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/Munchen. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HKI Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A.K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson&Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna -Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub¬
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ra'tutangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish-
mg and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tei Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co , Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P O. Box 286,
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication &
Distribution, P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. Federal Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling
Jaya, Selangor. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street,
Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco
Koerier" Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat
71-75, Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1, For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Poiona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahe.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVTI Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications AIB CE. Fntzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet, Skolgrand 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236. -
TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen
Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sn/j'P.O. Box 402, Bangkok:
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops In London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
- UNITED STATES. Unipub, 345 Park Avenue South, New
York, N.Y. 10010. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
A ticket
to nowhere?
Once the key to a well-paid, satisfying job, a university degree is fast becoming a ticket to nowhere. At the
end of 1976, in France, for example, 25,000 young university graduates, one third of the annual output, were
registered as job-seekers; in Japan, only 70 per cent of the 1976 graduates had found work by the end of the
year; projections of supply and demand for university graduates in the United States suggest that there will
be a surplus of 950,000 over the period 1974-1985. The problem of the "educated unemployed" is also
affecting the developing countries (see diagram page 12).
w
<tp' *$¡t&
^
***.
/
/>
í
pffr i
'.> \
Ê
m.
'"m
t
.. .;, t,
]]>
</page>
</document>
