<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074812eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^^^\ A window op«n on tha world
Courier
JUNE 1977 (30th year)
2.80 French franc*
I 4
RUBENS
IN PRAISE OF BEAUTY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
|v
ms
L
mw *^
~+w
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Belgium
Childhood radiance
An incomparable child-portraitist, Rubens excelled at capturing the fleeting moods and
expressions of childhood in drawings and paintings which glow with life and freshness. This
"Child's Head" is thought to be a portrait of his daughter Clara Serena. The eldest child of
Rubens and his first wife, Isabella Brant, Clara was only 12 years old when she died in 1623.
The portrait is today preserved in the art gallery of the Prince of Liechtenstein at Vaduz,
Liechtenstein.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JUNE 1977 30THYEAR
PUBLISHED IN 16 LANGUAGES
English Japanese Dutch
French Italian Portuguese
Spanish Hindi Turkish
Russian Tamil Urdu
German Hebrew
Arabic Persian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 28 French Francs
2 years: 52 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A. ; (2) N.CR. -
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co.,
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
France
Managing Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu Edition
Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
; Werner Merkli (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
; Maria Remiddi (Rome)
: H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
: Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
page
4 A 400th ANNIVERSARY TRIBUTE TO RUBENS
by Makaminan Makagiansar
6 RUBENS
A PORTRAIT OF THE ARTIST AS A UNIVERSAL MAN
by Roger Avermaete
R
¿5.
8 MANSION FOR A MASTER
Photos
12 RUBENS THE BOOK-ILLUSTRATOR
Photos
14 VIVE LA FEMME!
Photos
17 HELL'S TORMENTS AND EARTHY DELIGHTS
Photos
18 STAMPS TO HONOUR RUBENS
19 FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
23 RUBENS
Emissary of peace in strife-torn Europe
by Frans Baudouin
26 THE THRILL OF THE CHASE
Photos
28 SPINOZA
PHILOSOPHER OF INTELLECTUAL FREEDOM
by Ben Rekers
34 ANTONIE VAN LEEUWENHOEK
FATHER OF MICROBIOLOGY
by Jan Willem Maurits La Rivière
36 UNESCO MEDAL FOR RUBENS YEAR
37 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
38 UNESCO NEWSROOM
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
BELGIUM: Childhood radiance
Cover
This year marks the 400th anniversary of the
birth of Peter Paul Rubens, the great Flemish
painter. To salute the occasion, this issue of
the Unesco Courier is largely devoted to a
study of Rubens' monumental achievement,
not only as a prolific and versatile artist of
genius but as a diplomat who worked
tirelessly for peace. Cover shows a detail
from St. George and the Dragon (today in the
Prado Museum, Madrid) which Rubens
painted sometime between 1606 and 1610.
Photo © Editions Arcade, Brussels
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
RUBENS
A 400th ANNIVERSARY TRIBUTE
w
E celebrate this year the 400th anniversary of the birth of Peter Paul Rubens,
one of the world's most outstanding painters.
The sensuous exuberance, the overwhelming vitality of Rubens, the greatest
exponent of Baroque painting, is a joy for ever for all those who have eyes to see.
Seldom in the history of art have all the good things that enhance the value and
beauty of life been represented with such strength and eloquence.
Through the genius of Rubens, the great traditions of the north and south of
Europe of Dutch and Flemish painting on the one hand, and of Italian painting on
the otherwere to combine in unrivalled masterpieces.
Rubens' inspiration had robust roots in the life of the Flemish people that he
knew from his earliest childhood. And through his artistic skill this people has
become dear to art lovers all over the world. Though he never severed his roots, he
spent long years studying Italian art at the court of the Gonzagas in Mantua and
then in Rome, where he acquired new techniques and became aware of the new
visions of the Carracci brothers and Caravaggio.
It is thus that he was able to reconcile in his person and in his art theirs Nova
of the north and the Buona Pratica of Florence. All that was most traditional and
most modern in the painting of his time found equally vigorous expression in his
work. This towering personality, poised astride two centuries, was the most
accomplished figure of the Renaissance and a herald of modern times.
From Mantua, Genoa and Rome, Rubens brought back not only new art forms,
trends and perspectives, but he was also able to complement his vast knowledge in
different fields, and to acquire, in the six languages he mastered, all the Western
culture of his time.
IMo wonder, therefore, that his house in his beloved city of Antwerp was to
become one of the great schools of painting of all time. Many masterpieces now
hanging in galleries all over the world come from that school.
Man of genius, man of culture, man of education, Rubens was also a man of
peace. It is not surprising, therefore, that he spent a great part of his extraordinarily
active life in the service of international understanding. His intelligence, his charm,
his exceptional knowledge of political affairs and his perfect command of the
major European languages made him a first-rate diplomat.
But though he served different courts, he always acted as a universal messenger
of peace. He fought to protect his country's interests among the tensions of the
great powers of the time. In Madrid, in Paris and in London he was always to
oppose war and to advocate a policy of negotiation and understanding.
The horrors of war are expressed with agonizing reality in his wonderful
masterpiece in the Pitti Palace in Florence, and the blessings of peace are immortalized
with equal eloquence in his great canvas in the National Gallery in London.
Genius of the arts, scholar, fighter for peace: all these qualities make Rubens
dear to all men of goodwill dedicated to serve international understanding.
Makaminan Makagiansar
Unesco's Assistant Director-General for
Culture and Communication
Self-portrait of Rubens, executed some time after
his marriage to the beautiful young Hélène
Fourment in 1630.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
RUBENS
Aportrait of the artist
as a universal man
by Roger A vermaete
THE great Flemish painter Peter Paul Rubens was born
400 years ago, on 28 June 1577. Although known to
contemporaries as "the painter of Antwerp", he was not
born in Antwerp, as was long thought, but in Siegen, a small
town in Westphalia.
A trivial detail, one might suppose. And yet it throws an
interesting light on life in western Europe in the late 16th century.
Jan Rubens, the painter's father, was a rich and cultivated
burgher of Antwerp. An alderman of the city and a Protestant,
he was an opponent of the Duke of Alva, then governor of
Flanders and a notorious slaughterer of Protestants. In 1568
the alderman and his family were forced to flee the dreaded
Duke's wrath.
They settled in Cologne, where Jan Rubens became involv¬
ed in an intrigue which led to his being imprisoned for five years.
On his release he was allowed to live with his family in Siegen.
So it came about that "the Painter of Antwerp's" birthplace was
determined by Europe's religious conflicts.
Jan Rubens renounced his Protestantism and died a Catho¬
lic, and in 1589 his widow, Maria Pypelinckx, obtained permission
to return to Antwerp with her children.
Peter Paul was about 12 years old at the time. In 1590 he
became apprenticed to a well-known landscape painter, Tobias
Verhaecht, with whom he spent two years before going on to
spend two years in the studio of Adam van Noort. After a
further spell of apprenticeship under Otto van Veen, in 1598 he
was accepted as a Master by the Guild of St. Luke, the Antwerp
association of artists and artisans.
It is hard to tell what exactly Rubens learned from his mas¬
ters, solid painters untouched by genius. Tobias Verhaecht was
an unremarkable landscape painter who also depicted Towers of
Babel and scenes from the Apocalypse. It was his misfortune to
work several generations after Bruegel the Elder.
Adam van Noort, whose reputation had a moment of glory
in the 19th century when a number of works were wrongly
attributed to him, was a mediocre artist who belonged to Ant¬
werp's group of "Romanists", painters who had studied in Italy w
and whose work was imbued with the humanist learning of the Y
Renaissance.
ROGER AVERMAETE, internationally known Belgian writer, is the author of an
important study of Rubens' life and work, Rubens et Son Temps (Rubens and his
time), published in French and Dutch versions by Arcade publishers, Brussels, 1976.
A member of the Royal Flemish Academy of Sciences, Letters and Fine Arts of
Belgium, he has published novels and plays as well as art criticism and historical
studies. Tvo of his works, Guillaume le Taciturne /William the Silent) and Rem¬
brandt et Son Temps /Rembrandt and his time) have been awarded prizes by the
Académie Française.
One of Rubens' most remarkable works is an
altarpiece he painted for Antwerp cathedral
between 1611 and 1614. It was commissioned by
the Arquebusiers, an Antwerp brotherhood, for
their side-chapel in the cathedral. Rubens
produced a magnificent triptych whose central
panel was the Deposition from the Cross; on the
left was the Visitation, and on the right the
Presentation in the Temple. The Deposition
established Rubens as the foremost religious
painter of his time and has for over 300 years
been admired for its breathtaking virtuosity.
Painted with a dramatic intensity which is all the
more poignant for its restraint, the Deposition
scene is composed with powerful sweeping
curves that lead the eye directly to the dead
Christ, at the moment after his body has been
released from the Cross and is about to slump
into the arms of St. John. Rubens was
unsurpassed at creating a sense of dynamism
and movement through the use of curves and
counter-curves, but this was the first time that
he had achieved such a powerful effect with such
economy of means.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
*"*
Photo © Bulloz, París
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
> The most interesting of the trio, Otto van Veen, produced
pale imitations of the works of the Italian masters. A cultivated
man with a passion for the art "from beyond the mountains", he
whetted the curiosity of his young apprentice and filled him with
impatience to travel to Italy.
We know little of Rubens' work during this period, except
that he painted an Adam and Eve in Eanhly Paradise (today in
Rubens' House, Antwerp), a conventionally classical work in the
manner of Otto van Veen, and a portrait of a man statedwith
unusual precision to be "26 years old". This work, now in a
private collection in New York, seems to herald later develop¬
ments in the art of portrait painting.
The impact of Italy
In 1600, Rubens set out for Italy, as many Flemish painters
had done before him. To Complete their education, they regard¬
ed a journey "across the mountains" as indispensable, although
for some of them the experience proved fatal. More than one
Flemish painter lost the roots of his originality in Italy. Only
Bruegel the Elder managed to resist the siren-call and emerge
triumphant. As for Rubens, his great achievement was to create
a style that was all his own, reconciling the opposing forces of
North and South.
Hardly had Rubens arrived in Italy (doubtless furnished with
impressive testimonials) than he was taken into the service of
Vincenzo de Gonzaga, Duke of Mantua. Like all Italian princes
of his age, Vincenzo lived in sumptuous style. He was a great
collector and a man of boundless curiosity.
However, it seems that Rubens did not find Mantua an ideal
setting for his work, since he managed to get himself sent to
Rome, ostensibly to complete his studies. The Eternal City was
then the capital of the arts. The great masters of the Renais¬
sance were dead, but a number of brilliant painters still worked
there, including Caravaggio, the Carracci brothers and Guido
Reni. Artistic life in Rome was passionate and turbulent.
In 1603, Rubens was entrusted by the Duke of Mantua with
the task of taking a number of presents to King Philip III of Spain
and to other influential people. Some have claimed that this
was a diplomatic mission. But Rubens thought otherwise and
complained that he didn't even get an opportunity of presenting
the gifts to the King himself. In compensation, though, he was
commissioned to paint an equestrian portrait of the King's chief
minister, the all-powerful Duke of Lerma.
On his return to Italy, Rubens did his utmost to remain in
Rome, although his master, the Duke, demanded his return to
Mantua.
In 1608, on receiving news from Antwerp that his mother
was seriously ill, he packed his bags and left for the North "in all
haste" (he wrote) without waiting for permission from the Duke,
who was away travelling at the time. He said he would soon
be back, but in fact he never returned.
Too little attention has been paid to the fact that a year
earlier Archduke Albert of Austria, Governor-General of the
Spanish Netherlands, had already asked Vincenzo I to grant
Rubens leave of absence to settle some matters in Antwerp and
that the Duke had refused. This may well have been a first,
unsuccessful attempt on Rubens' part to break free from Mantua.
A number of paintings have survived from Rubens' eight-
year stay in Italy. Of the great triptych 77?e Holy Family being
adored by Vincenzo de Gonzaga and his family there still
remains The Baptism of Christ, The Transfiguration and two
fragments of the central painting, which was mutilated in the
18th century. One is in the Academy of Mantua and the other in
the Academy of Vienna.
Other works which have survived from this period are a
triptych painted on slate for the Church of Santa Maria in Valli-
cella. The Adoration of the Virgin by the Saints, a St. George
and the Dragon, a portrait of The Marchesa Brígida Spinola Doria
and other portraits of noblewomen. Some portraits of men have
also survived, such as the curious Moulay Ahmed, today in the
Boston Museum of Fine Arts.
These works all display sound craftsmanship, but none ^
escapes the influences of the great Renaissance masters. Their r
MANSION FOR
A MASTER
When Rubens bought a large house in Antwerp
about 1610, he was a rich man, the most famous
painter in Europe. Commissions were flowing in,
and he was surrounded by pupils and assistants.
He carried out extensive alterations to his new
house before moving in five years later. As an
annex he built a two-storey studio (centre of lower
photo, opposite page) for which he designed an
Italianate façade decorated with statues and
Baroque stonework. Here, in a room over
10 metres long and 8 metres wide, he could work
on as many as three large compositions at once.
The studio was joined to the house by a triumphal
arch (left of same photo), giving onto a garden
with a classical pavilion (detail below). Almost
entirely rebuilt in the 18th century, Rubens' house
was bought in 1937 by the city of Antwerp,
restored to its original state and transformed into a
museum. Opposite page above, Antwerp Town Hall
in. 1609 during the Twelve-Year Truce (see article
page 23), in an engraving by Visscher, a
contemporary of Rubens.
Photo © Almasy, Paris
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
k composition is calm and ordered; the colours lack any personal
touch.
Rubens received a warm welcome from the rulers of the
Spanish Netherlands, who immediately commissioned portraits
of themselves from him. The painter decided to settle in Antwerp
and made his home there for the rest of his life. Commissions
soon began to pour in. He painted an Adoration of the Kings for
Antwerp's Town Hall which made a great impression. Traces of
Caravaggio's influence can be detected in this work.
The Elevation of the Cross which he executed for St. Wal-
burga's Church in Antwerp marks a further stage in Rubens'
development and is still one of his most popular works. Cons¬
tructed along a diagonal, the painting creates an impression of
dynamism and movement, with its astonishingly muscular figures
and its athletic Christ on the Cross. In fact it looks more like a
hymn to life than a death-scene.
In Rubens' next major painting, the Deposition from the
Cross, the effect is less tempestuous and the colours are in gene¬
ral more sombre, although the figures are just as muscular as in
the Elevation and the gloominess of the scene is mitigated by a
fine sweep of red.
Thus Rubens embarked upon his extraordinary career in
Antwerp. He was soon inundated with commissions. There
was a great demand for paintings of religious subjects, reflecting
the spirit of the Counter-Reformation sparked off by the Council
of Trent. The Catholics countered the severity of the Lutherans
and the Calvinists with ¡mages that were more numerous and
above all more attractive. At the same time, the influence of
humanism made it permissible to depict mythological themes.
This was an ideal climate for an artist like Rubens who loved life
in all its multifarious forms, especially men, women, children,
and animals.
The nude triumphant
This love of life found expression in his work through his
exaltation of the nude. The masters of the Renaissance, from
Michelangelo to Titian, had given the nude figure a prominent
place in their work, but none of them ever showed such a mark¬
ed predilection for it as Rubens. The Old and the New Testa¬
ments certainly offered a wealth of subjects, but afforded few
opportunities for painting the female nude. In mythology, on the
other hand, nymphs and goddesses abound, and since in
Rubens' imagination they were never clothed, they provided him
with an inexhaustible supply of models.
PHILOSOPHERS AND CLASSICISTS
This painting, executed around 1612, is entitled "The Four
Philosophers", although not all those portrayed were, strictly
speaking, philosophers. Grouped beneath a bust of Seneca are
(from right to left) the Latin scholar Jan Woverius, the Stoic
philosopher Justus Lipsius, Rubens' brother Philip a disciple of
Lipsiusand Rubens himself. The work, with its background of
Classical ruins, documents the vogue for Greek and Latin learning
in early 17th century Europe.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Gradually there emerged a type of woman, buxom and pale-
skinned, which was to recur so often in Rubens' painting that
people came to believe that it was a representative likeness of
Antwerp women in general. (However, it is known that the
models for the naiads in The Reception of Marie de Medici at
Marseilles were Italian.)
Some of Rubens' vast canvases are crowded with nude
figures. Among them are two Last Judgements depicting clusters
of mingling men and women, and a delightful panel entitled The
Infant Jesus, St. John and two Angels, showing four children,
one of them a cherub with a lamb and a basket of fruit.
Rubens derived constant inspiration from men, women and
children. The nude is everywhere triumphant in his mytholo¬
gical paintings such as Nymphs and Satyrs; Ceres, Bacchus,
Venus and Love; Neptune and Amphytrite; and even the Four
Parts of the World. Obviously it was more difficult to introduce
nude figures into paintings of religious subjects. Christ, and the
Infant Jesus in the Holy Family were the only appropriate occa¬
sions the possible exception of the Adoration of the Kings.
In the latter, however, one of Rubens' favourite subjects, the
crowds thronging the scene and the splendour of the costumes
tend to distract attention from the newborn babe.
Rubens was a competent portraitist, but during these early
years, not a brilliant one, although an exception should perhaps
be made for the portrait he painted of himself and his young
wife, Isabella Brant, whom he married in 1609.
Another much admired work from this period is the painting
known as The Four Philosophers, a portrayal of the scholar
Justus Lipsius with his pupils Jan Woverius and Rubens' brother
Philip on either side of him, and, in the background, Rubens
himself.
Later Rubens was to develop a more expansive manner, but
he had already moved far from the style of his predecessors. To
appreciate this one has only to look back to the portraits of the
16th-century Dutch painter Antonio Moro, with their deep concern
for visual analysis, where truth comes before beauty.
Rubens saw things otherwise. He did not forget the manner
of the Renaissance masters and idealized his models with a subt¬
lety that delighted them. Van Dyck was to learn this lesson and
make his fortune thereby.
For a long time, landscape merely served as a background
for the groups of people which occupy the centre of the stage.
Later, however, it came to occupy a far from negligible place in
Rubens' paintings, bearing as always the unmistakable stamp of
his genius.
It was probably to give free rein to his taste for movement
that Rubens painted a series of hunting scenes: depicting a wolf;
a lion and a leopard; a crocodile and a hippopotamus; a wild
boar; and a lion. These are tumultuous paintings in which men
and beasts are locked in furious combat.
Rubens' horses are always magnificent animals of unrivalled
beauty. In his first equestrian portrait, depicting the Duke of
Lerma astride his mount, the steed is drawn with unequalled
grace. Mane and tail streaming in the wind, Rubens' horses are
involved in countless adventures. They are the main protagonists
in The Battle of the Amazons, a masterly example of perfectly-
balanced composition despite the turmoil of the scene.
In the midst of all this activity, Rubens still found time to
indulge in architecture. He bought a house on the Wapper (a
canal which had once formed part of the moat of Antwerp's
fortifications) and spent three years carrying out alterations to it.
His designs were clearly inspired by the Italian palazzi he had so
admired. He even published a book on Genoese architecture,
Palazzi di Genova, with the declared aim of combatting the
Gothic style which, like Vasari, he thought barbaric. .
People said that his house, together with that of his friend Y
Wealthy and successful, a happy
husband and father, Rubens felt an
increasing need as he grew older to
withdraw from his crowded
professional and social life in
Antwerp. In 1635 he bought a
country retreat, the Château of Steen
(left), a manor in the Flemish
Renaissance style with a moat, a
drawbridge, an orchard and gardens.
In addition he purchased woods and
fields nearby. Here he began to
paint peaceful landscapes, depicting
the lush farmland in all its variety of
light, mood and season. In one of
his most beautiful portrayals of the
countryside around the château
(opposite page), the mellow evening
light strikes through trees onto the
façade and glinting window-panes of
the mansion (far left of painting).
These "sunset years" in the Flemish
countryside also inspired him to paint
the famous scene of peasant revelry
known as La Kermesse. ,
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Almasy, París
Photo © Bulloz, Paris Plantin Museum, Antwerp
RUBENS THE
As well as producing a gigantic output of paintings, for
25 years Rubens supplied the Plantin printing-house in
Antwerp with many designs for title pages and book
illustrations. The Plantin press was founded by
Christophe Plantin (1530-1589), a Frenchman who settled
in Antwerp and became the most celebrated printer of his
time. By 1576 he had 16 presses and was working
virtually on an industrial scale. In 34 years he published
oyer 1,500 works, ranging from anatomical treatises and
atlases to Bibles, Including the renowned "Polyglot
Bible", an ambitious attempt to fix the original text of the
Old and New Testaments on a scientific basis. Rubens
,was a lifelong friend of Balthasar Moretus, Plantin's
grandson, who became head of the press and had
unlimited confidence in Rubens' capacities as an
illustrator. In his work for Moretus, Rubens developed a
new style of book illustration through designs displaying
a wealth of allegorical motifs, symbols, emblems and
L Balthasar Moretus (the grandson of the great printer Christophe
Plantin) was one of the finest in Antwerp. ' Rubens wanted to
furnish it with antique marble statues and to this end he began
negotiations with the English Ambassador, Sir Dudley Carleton.
The resultant haggling between these two equally wily dealers,
each out to get the better of the other, is. a highly entertaining
episode.
In 1619, Rubens painted The Last Communion of St. Francis
of Assist'. Despite the angels thronging the scene, this is one of
his few paintings expressing pain. Not long afterwards, he
received an important commission for 36 ceilings and three altar-
pieces for the new Jesuit church in Antwerp (today the church
of St. Charles Borromeo). The church was gutted by fire in 1718
and all Rubens' work perished in the flames, except for the three
altarpieces.
A helping hand from
van Dyck and Brueghel
A mounting flood of commissions meant that Rubens had
to take on experienced assistants to help him. These were not
mere pupils as has often been suggested; even renowned artists
such as Jan Brueghel and Frans Snyders were happy to under¬
take this sort of work.
Antony van Dyck also worked for a time with Rubens, after
being received into the Guild of St. Luke. This collaboration
between the master and his young rival produced at least one
masterpiece, the Rape of the Daughters of Leucippus. Rubens
and van Dyck also worked together on the cartoons for a tapes¬
try recounting the story of the Roman Consul Decius Mus.
Van Dyck did not stay long in the service of Rubens. Other
assistants took his place. There was never any lack of applicants.
Jan Wildens and Lucas van Uden painted landscapes; Theo van
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Bulloz, Paris Plantin Museum, Antwerp
BOOK-ILLUSTRATOR
figures from Greek mythology.
Although not himself an engraver, Rubens
was instrumental in creating a whole new school of
engraving, working closely with a carefully-chosen group
of print-makers and often correcting the first pulls of a
print with pen or brush. As an illustrator he turned his
hand to a variety of subjects, from treatises on optics to
historical compilations, travel books and philosophical
works. Photos on this double page show (1) the
courtyard of the Plantin printing house in Antwerp, today
the Plantin Museum; (2) a portrait of Christophe Plantin
by Rubens ; (3) Martine Plantin, Christophe's daughter;
(4) printing presses (left) in the Plantin workshop; and (5)
. a title page designed by Rubens for a historical work,
La Reddition de Breda (The Surrender of Breda). It is seen
at various stages of production. Above left, Rubens'
original design; above right, the engraved copper plate;
and below right, as it appeared in the book.
Thulden, Justus van Egmont, Abraham van Diepenbeek and
Erasmus Quellin specialized in figures; Paul de Vos painted ani¬
mals. This list of Rubens' collaborators is far from complete.
Curiously, once these painters set up on their own account they
seemed to run out of inspiration.
Rubens was a hard task-master, but he was perfectly capable
of adapting to the manner of a talented assistant. Adam and
Eve in Paradise, painted in collaboration with Jan Brueghel, has
been called "a masterpiece of understanding between the great¬
est genius and the subtlest talent in 17th-century Flemish
painting".
While never ceasing to paint, Rubens gradually became
involved in other activities. Events were to provide him with an
opportunity of playing a part in politics, in which he was passion¬
ately interested. The Twelve-Year Truce between Spain and the
United Dutch Provinces expired in 1621 and a resumption of
hostilities seemed inevitable.
Rubens was a staunch pacifist, and he set out to promote
peace no easy task at that time. Spain was proud and Holland
was unyielding., The painter sought to use his brilliant circle of
friends and acquaintances to ease his entry into public life. After
the death of the Archduke Albert, in 1621, the Archduchess
employed his services on more than one occasion. He was sent
to Holland to sound out the prospects for peace, but in vain.
Scenes from the life of
a scheming queen
Rubens the artist, on the other hand, was as successful as
ever. In 1622, he was summoned to Paris, where Marie de Medi¬
ci, the Queen Mother, asked him to decorate a gallery in her
newly-built Luxembourg Palace.
The subject was a tricky one. The artist was asked to paint
20-odd episodes from the scheming Queen Mother's none-
too-glorious life. But imagination can help to surmount most
obstacles. A combination of allegory and symbols, with a sprink¬
ling of mythology, provided a brilliant camouflage for history,
and Rubens managed to skirt round a number of embarrassing
episodes (although not quite enough for Richelieu, who ordered
certain alterations).
Thus was created the famous Medici Gallery, today one of
the glories of the Louvre. It is not Rubens' greatest work, and
certain contemporaries criticized him for his excessive and often
obscure use of allegory. Even so, it was a gigantic undertaking,
one that few painters could have brought to completion. It
required two years' work, although it did not prevent him from
completing other works in the meantime, notably his finest ver¬
sion of The Adoration of the Kings (Antwerp).
After completing the Medici Gallery, Rubens returned once
more to Paris to discuss the pictures needed for a second gallery,
whose decoration was to be devoted to the life of King Henry IV.
This project never came to fruition, and only a few brilliant
sketches have survived to testify that the lusty king inspired the
artist better than his scheming wife.
Fortunately, there were compensations: Louis XIII had com¬
missioned the designs for 12 tapestries telling the story of the
Roman Emperor Constantine. At this time, Rubens also made
the acquaintance of the Duke of Buckingham, the all-powerful
favourite of two English kings, James I, and his son Charles I.
He painted a portrait of the flamboyant Duke and cultivated
his company. Their relations were not without political overtones
on either side, and Buckingham, probably eager to win over a
man of such high standing at the Brussels court, paid Rubens a
fabulous price for the collection of statues that the painter had
earlier purchased from Sir Dudley Carleton.
In quest of peace
in Madrid and London
- For several years, Europe had been involved in the bloody
conflict known to history as the Thirty Years' War. Buckingham
was seeking peace with Spain and Rubens embarked on skilfuj
manceuvrings that led to his being summoned to Madrid to pre:
Dare the around for discussions.
rQIS ""¡»luuiiu u»i,umiuiiíi. CONTINUED PAGE 16
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Vive la femme !
Portrait of Isabella Brant (Dijon Museum, France)
Rubens was one of the greatest painters of women and
especially the nude female formwho ever lived. He excelled in
depicting milk-white flesh, glossy curls, graceful gestures,
the hollows and curves of the body. When a widower of 53, he
married the 16-year-old Hélène Fourment. Breaking the news to
one of his friends, he wrote, "It would have been hard for me to
exchange the priceless treasure of liberty for the embraces of an
old woman." He painted many portraits of Hélène, sometimes
playing with her children, sometimes richly adorned, and once
clad only In a fur cloak. She also served as a model for many of
his mythological and religious scenes (such as 77ie Education of
the Virgin, opposite page below, and The Judgement of Paris,
below, where she appears as the naked Venus in centre of
painting). Of his first wife, Isabella Brant, who died prematurely
in 1626, Rubens also painted unforgettable portraits reflecting the
gentleness and serenity which enchanted him both as husband
and painter.
Self-portrait of Rubens painted around 1624 (Windsor
Castle, England)
14
The Judgement of Paris (Prado Museum, Madrid)
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Education of the Virgin
(Musée Royal des Beaux-
Arts, Antwerp)
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
y The Spanish prime minister. Count Duke Olivares, was
unenthusiastic about opening peace negotiations with England,
but Rubens won over Philip IV, who preferred painting to poli¬
tics. At all events, the painter was eventually entrusted with- an
official peace mission to London. Before he left he was given
the honorific title of "Secretary to the Privy Council", since it
was considered unfitting that proud Spain should be represented
by a man who "worked with his hands"
While in Madrid, Rubens spent much of his time painting,
and is said to have produced 30-odd works during his stay. He
also managed to persuade the King to buy the paintings he had
had the foresight to bring with him. In his spare time, he met
and frequently conversed with the young Sevillian, Velasquez,
the indefatigable painter of the Spanish king and his court.
Rubens' visit to England was a personal triumph. The king
commissioned a series of paintings, representing the blessings of
his father's reign, to decorate the ceiling of the great Banqueting
House in Whitehall, and knighted the artist on the eve of his
departure. Diplomatically, the trip was less successful. After a
year and a half's absence, Rubens returned home disappointed.
The records tell us nothing about the work of his studio during
this period.
In the year of his return to Antwerp, he married Hélène
Fourment, then aged 16. His first wife, Isabella Brant, who had
died in 1626, had borne him a daughter, Clara Serena (who died
young) and two sons, the elder of whom was the same age as
his new wife.
This plump, blond young woman was henceforth to appear
in many of his works, as Venus, Andromeda, St. Cecilia, Diana,
one of the "Three Graces" and as a goddess in the Judgement
of Paris. She also posed as plain Hélène Fourment, richly
adorned, with her husband or with her children, or even virtually
naked, as in the painting known as The Little Fur.
It seems that Rubens wished to abandon politics at this
time, for he turned down an offer to return to England on ano¬
ther mission. The next year, however, he was once more in the
thick of things. Marie de Medici had been forced to flee from
France and arrived in Mons, where Rubens was delegated to
welcome her. The Queen Mother's misfortunes led him to urge
Olivares to support armed intervention on behalf of her intrigue-
ridden entourage. The peace-loving Rubens had become over¬
night an advocate of war! However, his petition came to naught,
for Madrid would have none of it. The artist returned to his
brushes and easel, the best thing he could have done.
The last ten years of his life were as prolific as those that had
gone before but his style became increasingly subtle. As in the
past he continued to paint both religious and secular subjects.
The latter became more and more sensual, while his treatment
of religious themes reflects a greater tenderness and tranquility
than his earlier work.
Paintings such as the Offering to Venus, with its angels
dancing about the goddess or perched in the trees above her,
and with its amorously entwined couples, exude Joie de vivre
through their fresh colours, their spirited sense of movement and
the gaiety of the children.
Rubens loved children and they abound in his paintings,
even in such dignified works as the Triptych of St. Ildefons,
which had been commissioned by Archduke Albert and his wife,
who were portrayed on the side panels. Children appear in The
Education of the Virgin, looking down on Hélène Fourment as
the Virgin Mary, and in the Holy Family and the Saints.
These are the paintings of a happy man. His varied expe-
RAVISHED
BEAUTIES
According to a Greek myth, Phoebe and Hilaria,
daughters of King Leucippus of Messene, were
snatched away from their husbands-to-be by
Castor and Pollux, the twin sons of Zeus. Rubens
delighted in such stories, which provided him with
almost inexhaustible opportunities to portray his
favourite subject: the female nude. The Rape of the
Daughters of Leucippus (2.25 m by 2.10 m), painted
around 1619, is not a tragic picture: the maidens,
like the impish cupid clinging to the horse's bridle
at left, do not seem unduly perturbed by what is
going on. Rubens has enclosed the action within
a circular compositional frame (see schematic
presentation above). Within the circle tensions are
expressed through sweeping intersecting arcs and
the scene is organized in a series of rectangles.
(The size of each rectangle is determined by the
"golden section", a canon of proportions which
Rubens had studied intensively in Italy.) To create an
atmosphere of motion and excitement, Rubens has
systematically used contrasting surfaces and
colours. It is remarkable that the same techniques
could create such different effects as the high
tragedy of The Deposition from the Cross (see page
7) and the "comic opera" atmosphere of the
painting shown here.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
riences in public life had not affected his art. When the Arch¬
duchess Isabella asked him to attend negotiations between the
Estates General of the Spanish Netherlands and the United
Provinces, he was confronted by a storm of protest from his
countrymen, outraged by this interference in their affairs. This
time, Rubens had had enough, and he bade farewell to politics.
Staging a mammoth pageant
with an army of
artists and craftsmen
The Archduchess died in 1633 and was succeeded as
Governor General by the Cardinal-Infant Ferdinand. To celebrate
his ceremonial entry into Antwerp, Rubens designed elaborate k
street decorations that are probably unique in the history of art. f
HELL'S TORMENTS
AND EARTHY DELIGHTS
The works shown on this page are characteristic of two
distinct stages in the development of Rubens' art. In 77ie
Last Judgement (right), a great turmoil of figures hurtles
down towards the middle of the picture, whence devils
drag their tortured bodies to the fires of Hell. This
painting, commissioned for a Bavarian church, displays
Rubens' delight in depicting whirling movement, nudes
in abundance and strong contrasts of light and shadow.
Below, La Kermesse, a village carnival painted in the
1630s when Rubens was concentrating more and more on
landscapes and pastoral subjects. In this scene of
uninhibited revelry, harking back to the world of Bruegel
the Elder, Rubens has rediscovered his roots as a
Flemish painter.
i
jl *. r
{Pi »» V
*
W^ mmw *7V Am
r \j* i_i é¿ wÈmm^m^Ë^^^W&^wT^j- * ^r^ - ^flH ^ÊÊ
mmm\W ^ ^vJ r^^fctt ^2mW0+ - v " «1^1 uàmmk i
HJH i t» I^Hl "ZA * 5» mJB
mr^mw^ i m\ lun ^H m^r *
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
As architect, chief designer and impresario of this grandiose
pageant, he marshalled an army of assistants. Among them
were 20-odd painters, including Jacob Jordaens, Cornelis de
Vos, Erasmus Quellin, Theodore Rombouts, Cornelis Schut,
Theodore van Thulden, the two van Balen sons, and six sculp¬
tors, including Quellin, van Mildert and Van den Eynde.
The inscriptions were done by his friend Gevaerts, the poet
and scholar. A multitude of carpenters, painters, gilders, black¬
smiths, drapers, firework-makers, weavers, tinsmiths and glaziers
were also engaged on the colossal undertaking, aimed at turning
the whole city into an immense theatre. Floats were set up in
the streets and no fewer than 11 triumphal arches were erected.
The most resplendent of them was decorated on one side with
12 white stone statues of the emperors of the House of Austria,
and with paintings illustrating their achievements. Decorations
were everywhere and no expense was spared.
The city council wanted to raise new taxes to cover the
enormous costs of this gala occasion, but higher authorities
refused. However, these were mere details; the important thing
was the magnificence of Rubens' achievement. Several sketches
for the reception still survive, in a number of museums, notably
the design for the monumental "Pompa introitus", showing
sculptures and paintings by van Thulden and a text by Gevaerts.
During the same year, 1635, Rubens purchased the château
of Steen at Elewyt, in Brabant, where from now until his death
he would spend part of each year. Steen influenced the deve¬
lopment of his work: he began to use its trees, and sometimes the
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite page: Detail from a painting by
Rubens snowing the artist, his young wife
Hélène Fourment and one of his sons strolling
in their Antwerp garden.
Photo Blauel-Pinakothek, Munich
Centre double page:
The Marchesa Brígida Spinola Doria, a Genoese
noblewoman. Rubens painted this portrait
around 1606.
Photo © National Gallery of Art, Washington D.C, U.S.A.
STAMPS TO HONOUR
RUBENS
Belgium
Paraguay
! 1377
;1,o
MONACO 1»,;
3;j>*dH Pét, '
P.P. R
-'"'' :
UBENS 11573 -1640) '
Monaco
Liechtenstein
Cook Islands
surrounding countryside and its people, in the background of his
paintings. The painter's imagination reached new heights in
romantic scenes such as the Landscape with Ulysses and Nausi-
caa and the Shipwreck of Aenaeas. In these last years he conti- ,
nued to develop, applying his art to what he saw around him.
In some paintings, reality mingles with the imaginary: the château
serving, for example, as the backdrop to a tournament scene.
Gradually, human figures began to dwindle in importance
until they became no more than tiny actors; their presence re¬
mained necessaryartistic tradition demanded itbut the land¬
scape now dominated the entire painting. A light breeze rustles
the leaves; the sky, strewn with light clouds, becomes more
vast; horizons stretch out in the distance.
Gardens of love and peasant frolics
This development also influenced his choice of figures. In
the lavish canvas known as The Garden of Love, well-dressed
figures stroll, sit and flirt outdoors but still maintain an atmosphere
of polite restraint. In the marvellous Kermesse (Carnival), painted
with light, deft brush-strokes, restraint has been cast to the
winds: peasants and their women dance, drink and embrace in
a veritable explosion of joy. This is the work of a painter expres¬
sing himself with total freedom, in full possession of his creative
powers. The time had come to discard the mask. The Peasants'
Dance is a joyful reel, a prelude to the Shepherd Embracing a
Woman in which Hélène Fourment's legs entwined around the
legs of a man leave little to the imagination.
One last major commission arrived from Spain. Philip IV
wanted a series of paintings to decorate the Torre de la Parada,
his hunting lodge near Madrid. The subjects chosen, "Ovid's
Metamorphoses and the Labours of Hercules", were just the
kind of thing to delight the painter, providing him with endless
opportunities to depict the nude.
At the same time, he continued to paint religious subjects,
and his customers went on plying him with commissions. Some
of his works from this late period are outstanding, especially The
Virgin with the Saints, which he planned for his tomb, 777e Road
to Calvary and The Martyrdom of St. Llvinus, painted with
breathtaking energy. His brushstrokes were growing lighter and
lighter, barely skimming the canvas.
As for the dazzling nudes of his last years, many of them
depicting Hélène Fourment, surely they are the best and most
convincing answer to those who, glancing at his last self-portrait,
have assumed that he was an unhappy husband. Nothing could
have been further from the truth. His last known letter, written
CONTINUED PAGE 3«
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
'c.
.
¿
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
>
H
É
m
b!!
Ï
if
h
a
*
'
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
RUBENS
Emissary ofpeace
in strife-torn Europe
by Frans Baudouin
Opposite page above:
Rubens executed this chalk
portrait of his son Nicolas
around 1625-1626. He made
many delightful sketches of
his children and sometimes
used them as models for his
paintings.
Photo © Erich Lessing-Magnum
Albertina, Vienna, Austria
Opposite page below:
Le Chapeau de Paille (The
Straw Hat) is one of Rubens'
most famous and attractive
portraits. It shows Susanna
Fourment, sister of Rubens'
second wife, wearing a
wide-brimmed hat which is
actually made of felt.
Photo © Erich Lessing-Magnum,
National Gallery, London
Right, Peace and War (or
Allegory on the Blessings
of Peace), painted in
London in 1630, when
Rubens was trying to
induce Charles I to make
peace with Spain. In the
background, Minerva,
goddess of wisdom, drives
away Mars, while beneath
her protection the joys of
peace are displayed. A faun
blissfully offers the
gorgeous fruits of the earth
to children and cupids,
while his companions (left)
are laden with gold and
treasures, symbols of
renewed prosperity.
AS a painter whose fame stretched
throughout Europe, Rubens ful¬
filled a mass of commissions
which would have exhausted a lesser
man. And yet, astonishingly enough, he
still found time to take part in the affairs
of State. His correspondence, as well as
other documents, provides ample evidence
of this.
The earliest surviving letter mentioning
public affairs is dated 30 September 1623,
but its contents support the view that he
had been concerned in secret State busi¬
ness long before then. However, it was
through a series of fortuitous events and
circumstances that he came to play an
active part in diplomacy.
At that time, the Netherlands were divi¬
ded into two parts. The largely Catholic
south (corresponding roughly to present-
day Belgium) belonged to the Spanish
crown; in the north was the Republic of
FRANS BAUDOUIN is curator of Antwerp's mu¬
seums of history and art, and secretary of the co¬
ordinating committee for Rubens Year (1977). He is
the author of P.P. Rubens: L' de Toute une Vie
(P.P. Rubens: the work of a lifetime), published by
Fonds Mercator S.A. (Antwerp) and Albin Michel
(Paris).
the United Provinces (the nucleus of
today's Netherlands) which had won its
independence from Spain and whose
representatives met at The Hague.
For many years Spain spared no efforts
to reconquer the United Provinces. How¬
ever, by 1609 the Republic was so well
defended under the determined leadership
of Maurice of Nassau, Prince of Orange,
that Spain agreed to sign a 12-year truce.
The governors of the Spanish Nether¬
lands at this time were the Archduke
Albert of Austria and his wife the Arch¬
duchess Isabella (her Spanish title was the
"Serene Infanta"), whose court was at
Brussels, the capital. When the truce
came to an end in 1621, Jan Brant, a
resident of The Hague and a nephew of
Rubens' first wife, tried to make contact
with the Archducal court.
A close friend of the Prince of Orange,
Jan Brant was among those who had
supported the truce and who were press¬
ing for an agreement with the Spanish
Netherlands. When the Prince seemed in
favour of making peace, Jan Brant was
eager to convey the news to the Arch- k
ducal court. y
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
PORTRAYING
THE MIGHTY
In 1625 Rubens painted this portrait
(top left) of the Infanta Isabella
Clara Eugenia, governor of the
Spanish Netherlands. She is
wearing the habit of a nun, which
she adopted after the death of her
husband, the Archduke Albert, in
1621. Judging from a portrait of her
in court dress which Rubens painted
about 1609, the Infanta had never
been beautiful: here her expression
is one of authority softened by
benevolence. For 25 years she was
a friend, patron and protector to
Rubens, who was deeply moved by
her death in 1633. Top right, the
first Duke of Buckingham, English
politician, flamboyant adventurer
and favourite of King Charles I.
During his diplomatic missions,
Rubens had close contacts with
Buckingham, who was assassinated
in 1628. Below, detail from The
Presentation of the Portrait of Marie
de Medici to Henry IV, one of
21 great paintings depicting the
life of Marie de Medici, the dowager
queen of France. The queen
commissioned this series from
Rubens in 1621 for her sumptuous
Paris residence, the Luxembourg
Palace. Considerable imagination
was needed to present the
quarrelsome queen as the
embodiment of all the virtues.
Rubens solved the problem by
clothing truth with allegory, £
showing the queen in glorious S.
scenes peopled with bevies of |
goddesses, sirens, angels and ä
cupids. In three years he completed s
the series, a masterpiece of |
Baroque art. Here a portrait of J
Marie is shown to her future i
husband Henry IV, who is attended s
by the god Mars. ^
At this point Rubens expressed his
' willingness to act as an intermediary. As
a painter, much-favoured by the Archduke
and the Infanta, he had access to the
Brussels court and could communicate
secret information to influential people
there without arousing suspicions. Rubens
gave an account of his talks with Jan
Brant to another of his relatives, Pierre
Peck (or Peckius), Chancellor of Brabant
and a trusted counsellor of the Infanta.
Rubens' first diplomatic letter was
addressed to Peckius. It deals with the
peace terms the artist had discussed at
Antwerp with Jan Brant, who is referred
to pseudonymously as "el Católico" (the
Catholic). Thus it was through two family
connexions that Rubens became involved
in State business as a negotiator.
From the surviving evidence, it is impos¬
sible. to piece together a detailed account
of the talks between Rubens and Jan
Brant. Because of the highly confidential
nature of the negotiations, many letters
relating to them were undoubtedly destroy¬
ed by the participants. At all events,
Peckius reported on them to the Infanta,
who subsequently passed on the infor¬
mation to her nephew, Philip IV of Spain.
On 11 October 1624, the Spanish king
expressed his agreement with Jan Brant's
proposal that the belligerents should meet
in a conference. Rubens' name is not
mentioned in the letter, but we can assume
that he was responsible for transmitting
the "Catolico's" proposal to the Brussels
court. In 1625, Rubens again refers to
these negotiations, which had probably
been interrupted in the meantime.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
MEN, GODS
AND
SNARLING
TIGERS
These works illustrate two of the
many aspects of Rubens' art.
Above, expressive and realistic
studies of African heads. Below,
graceful group of nymphs and
gods in The Four Parts of the
World. As in so many of Rubens'
works the nudes are resplendent.
In foreground, a snarling tiger
suckles its young and children
play with a crocodile whose
gaping jaws and scaly hide make
a startling contrast with the
creamy skin of its human
companions.
In -1623, Rubens reported on his talks
with Jan Brant to Peckius. Soon, how¬
ever, he had an opportunity to brief the
Infanta herself about them.
On 30 August 1624, the French ambass¬
ador in Brussels noted that the Infanta
had granted several audiences to Rubens,
who was exploring the possibilities of a
truce. He also recorded that Rubens, as
well as making frequent journeys between
the Brussels court and the army camp of
General Ambrogio Spinola, a Genoese
marquis in the Infanta's service, was putt
ing it about that the Prince of Orange was
favourable towards a truce.
A letter Rubens wrote to the Infanta on
15 March 1625 provides further proof
that his standing was now sufficiently
high for. him to approach her directly on
official business.
The scope of Rubens' diplomatic activity,
which had hitherto aimed at establishing
peace between the two parts of the Nether¬
lands, now became European-wide. At the
beginning of 1627 he began to devote all
his energies to promoting a peace treaty
between Spain and England, then at war.
A chance encounter, two years before,
was of decisive importance in extending
Rubens' diplomatic activities to a wider
European stage. While in Paris in the
spring of 1625 to complete his series of
paintings on the life of Marie de Medici,
Rubens had made the acquaintance of
George Villiers, first Duke of Buckingham,
and his agent, Balthazar Gerbier. Bucking¬
ham was an adventurer, a connoisseur, a
collector and a favourite of Charles I.
Gerbier, like Rubens, was a painter and L
diplomat. Y
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Like many Flemish artists, Rubens loved painting animals, and
gave free rein to his taste for excitement, drama and physical
power in tumultuous hunting scenes depicting men and beasts
locked in life-and-death combat. As well as European animals,
he also portrayed lions, tigers, crocodiles and hippoes, some of
which he may have seen and sketched in menageries belonging
to rich noblemen. In The Boar Hunt (below) a boar attacked by
a swarm of hounds and huntsmen is the centre of a whirlpool
of action dominated by a horse's head poised dreamily above the
mêlée. Rubens had a particular fondness for horses, often
giving them expressions that are almost human. The great
French painter Eugène Delacroix (1798-1863) dubbed Rubens
"the Homer of painting" and made a careful study of his
THE THRILL
OF THE CHASE
Photo © Bulloz, Paris Marseilles Museum, France
techniques, especially his use of horses to define a painting's
"lines of force". Delacroix shows something of his debt to
Rubens in 77ie Death of Sardanapolus (detail right).
, In Paris Rubens painted the Duke's
portrait and thus had ample opportunity
to get to know this powerful figure. This
meeting in Paris undoubtedly explains
why Buckingham, when he subsequently
, wished to conclude a peace treaty between
England and Spain, called on Rubens to
act as an intermediary. He dispatched
Gerbier to the Netherlands to sound
Rubens out.
, Rubens played a key role in the ensuing
negotiations. He was summoned to
Madrid by Philip IV to give an account of
his contacts with Buckingham. He left
Antwerp in haste at the end of August
1628 and made the journey to Madrid in
the remarkably short time of two weeks.
Until then Philip IV, his powerful minister
Olivares, and his other Counsellors, had
been sceptical about the negotiations in
which Rubens was engaged. Now they
were impressed by the positive results of
the talks and by the soundness of Rubens'
reasoning.
Rubens' stay in Madrid lasted about
eight months, ending on 29 April 1629,
when he set out for London on a mission
entrusted to him by Philip IV. He called
at Brussels on the way to meet the Infanta,
and paid a brief visit to Antwerp to see his
two sons.
In London, Rubens encountered many
obstacles but finally succeeded in prepar¬
ing the ground for a peace treaty between
England and Spain. His acuteness , in
assessing men and situations, his powers
of persuasion, his skill and tact certainly
made a major contribution to the outcome,
as well as his reputation as a great painter,
for both Charles I and Philip IV of Spain
loved the arts and were delighted by the
presence of Rubens at their courts.
For Charles I he painted an Allegory on
the Blessings of Peace (National Gallery,
London) in which Minerva, goddess of
peace, drives away Mars, god of war.
This was clearly an allusion to the nego¬
tiations which Rubens had carried on with
Charles I and which led to the peace treaty
between Spain and England.
Rubens' mission to London was undoub¬
tedly the high point of his diplomatic
career. Madrid was highly satisfied with
his work in London. There was question
of entrusting him with other missions.
But the artist, who had spent so many
years travelling, now wished to live a
peaceful family life in Antwerp with his
young wife, Hélène Fourment, whom he
married on 6 December 1630. He wished
once more to devote himself entirely to
his art.
"For my part, I should like the whole
world to be at peace and that we should
in a century of gold arid not of iron,"
Rubens wrote. It is not only in his paint¬
ings that we can see the glimmering dawn
of a "century of gold."
Frans Baudouin
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Rubens' skill in creating a luminous quality
when depicting human flesh has been
admired (and envied) by many artists. A
great modern painter of the female nude,
Auguste Renoir (1841-1919), once ruefully
confessed that he needed to use heavily
applied paint to produce effects which
Rubens achieved with the lightest of
brushstrokes. Nevertheless, Renoir's
Mother and Child (right) strikes the same
warm, intimate note as Rubens' Portrait of
Hélène Fourment and her Children (detail
below). See also colour reproduction,
page 19.
VENUS GOES POP
Rubens borrowed the subject of The Toilet of Venus (below left), executed between 1612 and 1615, from the great Venetian
Master, Titian (1477-1547). In the 1960s the painting was given a "pop art" treatment when the American artist Robert
Rauschenberg used it in a work entitled Persimmone.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
SPINOZA
PHILOSOPHER OF
INTELLECTUAL FREEDOM
by Ben Rekers
THREE hundred years ago, on 21 '
February 1677, Benedict de Spino¬
za, the great seventeenth-century
forerunner of modern agnostic thought,
died at The Hague.
The contents of his desk, containing
his last writings, were in accordance with
his wishes taken that very evening to
Amsterdam, where the bookseller Jan
Rieuwertsz made an immediate start on
the printing of the Opera Posthuma (Post¬
humous Works).
Within a few months a translator, Jan
Glazemaker, had produced a Dutch ver¬
sion of these works so as to render their
contents accessible to those who did not
know Latin.
In 1632, when Spinoza was born in
Amsterdam, the country was enjoying a
period of tolerance and great prosperity.
The latter, resulting from successful trad¬
ing with the Dutch overseas colonies, had
its focus in the Beurs or stock exchange
of Amsterdam.
Power in this city was in the hands of
the burgomasters, an oligarchy drawn
from a small circle of patrician families.
The religious tolerance of Amsterdam's
cosmopolitan citizens sprang from their
tradesman's mentality one does not,
after all, question the religion of people to
whom one is trying to sell something.'
During the first 15 years of his life Spi¬
noza had little or no contact with the
Dutch. Even though its members enjoyed
the rights of citizenship, the Jewish com¬
munity, to which Spinoza's family belong¬
ed, lived in isolation in its own quarter of
the city.
Spinoza spoke Portuguese at home and
at school (1). His father ran a highly
successful business trading in products
from the Levant. From the age of five.
Spinoza attended a Jewish school where
he learned excellent Hebrew and scripture.
When aged about 14, he left the school
in order to help in his father's business,
and after the latter's early death Spinoza
ran the business for some years on his
own. He probably had little talent for
commerce, but it is known that he was
delighted to leave school.
At the Amsterdam stock exchange he
made the acquaintance of other young
merchants like himself, such as Jarig
Jelles, Pieter Balling and Simon de Vries,
all of whom were Collégiants (2). Their
piety reflected the simplicity and austerity
of the early Christians and they professed
a religion with pronounced spiritualist
leanings.
The young Spinoza, who was himself
sober and serious-minded by nature, was
attracted to them, and they were to remain
his closest friends throughout his life.
Their ways of thinking were more sympa¬
thetic to him than those of the capitalist-
minded Jewish milieu.
Around this time Spinoza also met
Francis van den Enden, an ex-Jesuit from
Flanders who was now married and living
in Amsterdam. He had opened an excel¬
lent Latin school there, where the sons of
rich merchants could be prepared for their
studies at the University of Leiden.
Spinoza went there to learn Latin, with
the particular purpose of acquainting him¬
self with contemporary European science.
He then began to read Giordano Bruno,
Bacon, Hobbes, Machiavelli and, most
important of all, Descartes, who had be¬
come famous in the Netherlands when his
BEN REKERS, Dutch university teacher, is an
assistant professor at the University of Utrecht. His
study on Arias Montano, the 16th-century -Spanish
Orientalist who directed the translation of the Antwerp
polyglot Bible (see page 12) has been published in
English as Benito Arias Montano 1527-1598 (The
Warburg Institute, London, 1972).
(1) Like many of its neighbours, Spinoza's family
was descended from immigrants of Iberian origin who
had fled the Inquisition.
(2) The collégiants constituted an important movement
of religious dissidence in Dutch Protestantism. From
1620 onwards they set up "colleges" which met in the
village of Rijnsburg near Leiden, where they underwent
rebaptism by immersion. They respected all religious
beliefs since they felt that no denomination could
claim a monopoly of the truth. They did not recognize
any religious services or dogmas, and attached more
importance to love of their fellow beings than to love
of God.
first works were published in 1637, and
for whom there was a veritable passion at
Leiden University.
Van den Enden introduced Spinoza to
the philosophy of scepticism, of which he
was himself an advocate, and in return
Spinoza gave lessons in Hebrew grammar
to the school's pupils, who included the
young intellectuals Lodewijk Meijer and
Adriaan Koerbagh, with whom he became
great friends.
Their nafnes occur in his correspondence
right up to the end of his life, and it was
they who eventually persuaded him to put
his ideas down on paper. They were acti¬
vely involved in publishing his work and
drew on Spinoza's philosophy in their own
writings.
As a result of this contact with liberal
Dutch intellectuals, Spinoza became in¬
creasingly estranged from the milieu of his
birth. However, the leaders of the Jewish
community, who would have been glad to
have had such a brilliant young man to
their credit, tried to win him over, even
going so far as to offer him a thousand
florins in return for his silence.
But in his discussions with the rabbis,
Spinoza refused to change his ideas, per¬
sisting in them with, if anything, greater
vehemence.
By 1656, when Spinoza was 24, the
synagogue had had enough and proceed¬
ed to excommunicate him. He was cursed
to future generations, and no Jew was
allowed to have anything to do with him
or even approach him closer than ten
paces.
History is, however, guilty of a certain
misinterpretation, or at any rate misunder¬
standing, with respect to the much-quoted
text of Spinoza's excommunication. Less
well-known than the actual text is the fact
that such bans were a frequent occurrence
in Jewish communities, often being rescind¬
ed after as little as a week.
In any case Spinoza seems to have been
totally unconcerned by the event, and did
not even bother to defend himself or take
any steps to have the excommunication k
withdrawn. His choice had been made*
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Portrait of Spinoza by an anonymous 17th-century Dutch painter
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
voluntarily. His new circle of friends was
* like a family, with the advantage that they
^hought as he did.
Spinoza's separation from the Jewish
community meant that he could no longer
carry on his business, so he learned to
grind lenses in order to make a living.
There was a great interest in experi¬
mental natural science at this time, espe¬
cially microscopy and astronomy. Through
the work of Descartes, Spinoza had already
come into contact with the investigations
being made in the Netherlands by the
young Christiaan Huyghens, van Leeuw¬
enhoek (see article page 34) and Swam-
merdam, and he knew of the experiments
being carried out by Newton and Boyle in
England. He felt that his occupation had
a promising future.
For another four years Spinoza continu¬
ed to live in Amsterdam, until the fanatical
rabbis managed to persuade the city coun¬
cil to declare him persona non grata. After
this he spent some months at the summer
residence of a rich friend in Ouderkerk,
15 kilometres away from his Amsterdam
friends, who were thus able to pay him
regular visits.
In the mid-17th century Amsterdam was
referred to by foreigners as Irenopolis
(city of peace) or Eleutheropolis (city of
freedom). The city opened its doors freely
to all those who were undergoing religious
persecution elsewhere in Europe: Span¬
ish Jews, French Huguenots and Soci-
nians from Poland could speak, write and
publish there unmolested.
The city council, by reason of its busi¬
nessman's mentality, was tolerant, for
prosperous trade was irreconcilable with
fanatical idealism. Anyone who had ex¬
pertise or good trade contacts to offer
was welcome and of potential use to the
economy.
During his Amsterdam period, Spinoza
learned to value highly the climate of free¬
dom which reigned in the city, and later
sang its praises in the following splendid
passage:... "the city of Amsterdam, whose
enjoyment of this freedom had made it
great and admired by the whole world. In
this flourishing state, this city without a
(3) From chapter 20 of the Tractatus Theologico-
Politicus, 1670, translated by A.G. Wernham in Spi¬
noza's Political Works, (Oxford 1958).
peer, men of every race and sect live in
the greatest harmony, and before they
entrust their goods to anyone, there are
only two things they want to know :
whether he is rich or poor, and whether
he is honest or dishonest. His religion or
sect does not matter, for it has no influence
on the decision of lawsuits. And no sect
whatsoever is so detested that its mem¬
bers (provided that they harm no one,
give every man his own, and live decent
lives) are refused the protection of the
civil authorities." (3)
In 1660 Spinoza moved to Rijnsburg,
where he knew he would find an atmos¬
phere of peace and seclusion in the com¬
pany of the Collégiants. He lived in the
village in a small house for three years,
making optical instruments, reading and
above all writing.
He corresponded frequently with Hein¬
rich Oldenburg of the Royal Society in
London on the subjects of refraction and
Boyle's experimental physics, and received
regular letters containing questions from
his Amsterdam friends Meijer, Balling and
de Vries.
Two scenes of life in Amsterdam in Spinoza's time. Below right, the Stock Exchange, where the tolerant and enlightened Dutch
merchants met not only to talk business but to discuss the latest ideas. In the 1650s, when Spinoza worked for his father, a prosperous
merchant, his duties often took him to the Stock Exchange. It was there that he met and befriended a group of young Protestants
belonging to the "Collegiant" movement (so named because its members were organized in small congregations or "colleges"). Below, an
assembly of Collégiants, who, like the young Spinoza, were critical of existing social and religious institutions.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
They had formed a discussion group
which met weekly in Jan Rieuwertsz'
bookshop, the centre for freethinkers.
Spinoza also received visits from states¬
men and scholars such as Burgomaster
Hudde, who ordered lenses from him, and
probably from the well-known diplomat
van Beuningen, a Collegiant who came to
Rijnsburg every year for a retreat.
Another visitor was the powerful Grand
Pensionary Jan de Witt, who was a mathe¬
matician by training and the author of a
well-known mathematical treatise. De
Linearum Curvarum.
A student from Leiden by the name of
Casearius paid regular visits to Spinoza in
order to have the work of Descartes
explained to him. As a result, a collection
of notes came into being which were also
read by the members of the discussion
group in Amsterdam, who urged Spinoza
to have them published.
He agreed, and the notes became his
first work to appear in print, entitled "Prin¬
ciples of the Cartesian Philosophy toge¬
ther with Metaphysical Thoughts".
His friend Lodewijk Meijer, the doctor
and philologist, wrote a preface to the
book. The corn-chandler. Jarich Jelles,
who in the meantime had sold his business
in order to devote himself to philosophy,
financed the printing.
Jelles did not know Latin, and consider¬
ed that at his age it would be a waste of
time to learn it, and so he paid for a trans¬
lation of the book into Dutch, which was
undertaken by Jan Glazemaker. This and
subsequent translations were of consider¬
able importance in making Spinoza's phi¬
losophy known to a wider public at an
early stage.
During this period Spinoza began to
formulate his own philosophical system,
in the first version of his Ethics, in which
he moved right away from Descartes.
Passages of this began to circulate in
manuscript form and were read and com¬
mented on with eager enthusiasm by his
friends.
Their admiration was so great that the
merchant Simon de Vries, a bachelor,'
named Spinoza as his sole heir, although
the philosopher, whose way of life was
still modest and frugal, only accepted an
annuity of 300 florins. Without a doubt
the generous offers of help to Spinoza and
the interest taken in his ideas from an
early stage were invaluable to his work.
At this point a gradual change began to
form in Spinoza's attitude to life. He felt
that he could no longer allow himself to
share in the Spiritualists' lack of political
commitment. His thoughts had been
turned in this direction by reading Pierre
de la Court's Maximes Politiques pour les
Etats de Hollande, which defended a form
of liberal republicanism. According to de
la Court the system of government was
determined by economic freedom, and
political and religious freedom were close¬
ly linked. The church should not be al¬
lowed to dominate the State.
Spinoza now abandoned isolation and
abstract thought in order to give active
support, through his writing, to the liberal
politics of Jan de Witt. He moved to
Voorburg on the outskirts of The Hague
so as to keep in closer touch with his
friends in the government.
During this period he wrote his Tracta- j
tus Theologico-Politicus, which contained I
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
a fierce attack on the so-called "theocra¬
tic" Calvinist mode of government, and
on the greed for power of the clergy, who
pandered to popular feeling.
Spinoza categorized military patriotism
as one of the basest human passions. He
thought that the most suitable form of
government for the country would be the
rule of an oligarchy composed of a small
intellectual élite drawn from the upper
merchant classes.
In the theological part of the Tractatus
he pointed out that the Bible was only the
work of man, and had been used time and
time again to enslave the people. Spinoza
also indicated various chronological inac¬
curacies in the Bible.
The work was published in 1670, the
author's name only being indicated by the
initials B.D.S.
During this period, Jan de Witt's politi¬
cal power began to wane. A rationalist
politician, he had never curried, favour
with the mass of the people, and now he
was making mistakes, particularly in his
foreign policy towards England.
In 1672 he was suddenly faced with a
joint attack by the French army of Louis
XIV and the English fleet. This year of
invasion became known in Dutch history
as the Rampjaar or year of disaster. De
Witt's fall is partly attributed to his refusal,
during his period in power, to allocate
sufficient funds for Dutch military forces.
This decided his fate: he was lynched by
the mob at The Hague.
When Spinoza, normally so disciplined
in his emotions, heard of his friend and
kindred spirit's brutal murder he was over¬
come with rage. He wanted to go out in
the street to challenge the hateful mob,
and was only dissuaded from doing so
with the greatest difficulty. That night he
wrote a short pamphlet, Ultimi Barbaro¬
rum (the very lowest of the barbarians),
which he posted near the place of the
assassination.
In the same year, the young Prince
William III of Orange was appointed Stad-
tholder and Captain-General of the Army.
He was already much liked by the people,
as a "child of the state". Admiral de
Ruyter was able to make his mark on the
English fleet; and so the disaster-ridden
nation was saved.
On the home front, however, a period
of repression was under way. University
professors who had been won over to
scepticism were dismissed and censorship
was reintroduced. The city councils, which
for years had ignored the condemnations
of the Calvinist synods, were purged. Mili
tary patriotism had prevailed.
Spinoza now belonged to the ranks of
the persecuted, whose spokesman he had
been in his writings. His Tractatus Theo-
logico-Politicus was banned: it is thought,
though not known for certain, that it had
been commissioned by Jan de Witt. In
any case it was denounced by the censor¬
ship as a work "forged in hell by a rene¬
gade Jew and the devil, and issued with
the knowledge of Mr Jan de Witt"
Spinoza's subsequent fear, especially in
a man of such natural caution, is under¬
standable, particularly in view of the fate
of his disciple Adriaan Koerbagh. After
writing a Spinozist work, A Light Shining
in Darkness, Koerbagh had in 1668 been
imprisoned and tortured, and had died in
gaol.
In addition, Spinoza had learned that
his former teacher van den Enden, who
had gone to France, had been beheaded
in 1674 for his involvement in the republic¬
an plot of the Chevalier de RoJ/ian against
Louis XIV.
During the remaining five years of his
life Spinoza lived in a rented room in The
Hague, secluded and disillusioned, work¬
ing on a new Political Treatise and com¬
pleting his Ethics. He received a number
of important visitors, particularly from
abroad where his reputation was already
high, such as a representative of the Prince
de Conde, the French general, and also,
the young Leibniz, St-Evremont, and the
Elector Palatine, who offered him a chair
at the University of Heidelberg.
He refused the offer because of his
desire to complete his life's work in peace
and isolation, and almost achieved his
wish. Unfortunately he left his Political
Treatise unfinished, in the chapter where
after discoursing on the subject of monar¬
chy and oligarchy, he had intended to
deal with the advantages and disadvanta¬
ges of democracy.
Spinoza died of tuberculosis at the
early age of 45. Right to the end of his life,
he applied himself to his writings and
correspondence, often working at night.
Towards the end a doctor friend from
Amsterdam stayed with him, and after¬
wards took the manuscript of the Ethics
back with him to van Rieuwertsz, the
publisher.
The philosopher was buried in the
Nieuwe Kerk (new church) at The Hague,
and his hearse was accompanied by six
carriages occupied by important admirers
whose names have not come down to us.
The house on the Prinsessegracht where
he spent his last years has recently been
restored and opened as a museum.
As we have seen, even during Spinoza's
lifetime he had followers who saw in his
thought the ultimate truth and who, often
simplifying his philosophy, made
extreme and radical deductions from it in
their own writings.
These followers included Lodewijk Meijer
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Opposite page: 17th-century engraving of
a district of Amsterdam. The Dutch
voyages of discovery and the founding of
the Dutch East India Company in the
early 17th century made Amsterdam the
world's major commercial city, and its
policy of religious toleration attracted
waves of Jewish refugees from Spain and
the Spanish Netherlands as well as
Protestants from many countries. Left,
77;e Geographer (1658) a work by one of
the great Masters of Dutch painting, Jan
Vermeer of Delft, who, like Spinoza, was
born in 1632. He died in 1675.
in his Philosophia S. Scripturae Interpres
("Philosophical Interpretation of the Holy
Scriptures")an eloquent titleand also
spiritualist believers such as Pieter Balling
("The Light on the Candlestick") who
modified his philosophy into a vague mys-
ticism, and Jarich Jelles, who in his "Pro¬
fession of the Christian Faith" presented
Spinoza as a kind of evangelist.
These spiritual free-thinkers were of
great value to Spinoza when it was a
question of giving him practical help, but
they were somewhat naïve and only had a
partial grasp of his metaphysics, which
are far more complex than those of
Descartes.
Shortly after Spinoza's death, a minister
from the town of Zwolle, F. van Leenhof,
wrote "Heaven on Earth", an epicurean
work in which he drew on Spinoza's work
to advocate free sexual morals. He was
given a savage sentence in 1712 after a
long trial.
The orthodox Calvinists had been right
in realizing early on that Spinoza's philo¬
sophical system contained dynamite. It is
difficult to be sure whether Spinoza was
essentially an atheist in his Ethics, as
modern interpretations of his work are
greatly at variance.
What is certain is that his pantheism
(Deus sive Natural, his lay rationalism and
his philosophical free-thinking prepared
the way for the crisis of the European
conscience and the Age of the Enlighten
ment. Later on Schelling, Goethe, Schlei-
ermacher and Hegel were to build on his
foundations, and in 19th-century France
his influence on Victor Cousin, Paul Janet
and Ernest Renan was considerable. Ein¬
stein in the 20th century was an admirer
of his work.
	 Many of Spinoza's biographers have
painted a highly sentimentalized picture of
him as a poor spectacle-maker who lived
his life in poverty and obscurity. The truth
is that, along with Huyghens, he was one
of the most famous experts in optics of
his day.
He is often depicted as a dreamy abstract
thinker living in seclusion, whereas he
numbered many influential politicians
among his friends and acquaintances.
Finally, his often-cited excommunication
by the Jewish authorities was a frequent
and relatively insignificant occurrence at
the time.
Recent historical research, in some cases
undertaken on the occasion of the tricen¬
tenary of Spinoza's death, has set out to
expose a number of legends concerning
his life and to distinguish fact from fiction.
Nevertheless, there are still some gaps
in Spinoza's biography. Evidence dating
back to the 17th century, apart from the
biased and unreliable entry in Pierre Bayle's
Dictionary, is confined to descriptions of
him by his contemporaries Lucas and
Colerus. They did not know him perso¬
nally, and were obliged to rely on informa
tion given them by the painter from whom
Spinoza rented a room. There are many
discrepancies in the works of these early
biographers.
The surviving correspondence to and
from Spinoza is scant, consisting of a
mere 84 letters whose texts are often in¬
complete. . Personal news was . regarded
by early scholars as unimportant and was
cut out, so that most of the letters read
more like treatises on philosophy or natur¬
al science. '
Even so, they provide much useful clari¬
fication of the Ethics and also illustrate
Spinoza's kindliness, revealing the patien¬
ce with which he explained his ideas to
the often simple people who wanted to
understand his work.
Spinoza was a highly original thinker
who evolved his philosophical system quite
independently. Yet it should not be for¬
gotten that he was able to work so
successfully partly because he lived in one
of the freest nations in Europe, where the
intellectual climate was salutary and sti¬
mulating and where he was able to find a
circle of friends who could support him
morally and financially.
One might even wonder whether this
modest and cautious man would ever have
committed his thoughts to paper, let alone
published them, had it not been for the
pressure exerted by these friends.
H Ben Rekers
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
VAN LEEUWENHOEK
FATHER OF MICROBIOLOGY
by J. W.M. La Rivière
Some 300 years ago in the 1670s
a vast new world was uncovered
by the ingenuity and perseverance
of a self-made scholar living in the city of
Delft, the Netherlands. The scholar's
name was Antonie van Leeuwenhoek.
He did not sail uncharted oceans, nor
did he cross inhospitable mountains and
deserts. He made his discoveries quietly
at home looking at a candle, armed with a
tiny hand-microscope.
The candle served as a light source for
the illumination of a great variety of objects
ranging from a drop of blood to the wing
of a butterfly. These he studied with his
home-made instrument about the size of a
matchbox, which nevertheless gave a
JAN WILLEM MAURITS LA RIVIERE is professor
of environmental microbiology at the International
Institute for Hydraulic and Environmental Engineering,
Délit, the Netherlands. He is chairman of the Inter¬
national Cell Research Organization (ICRO), of the
International Commission on Microbial Ecology and of
the natural sciences subcommission of the Netherlands
National Commission for Unesco.
magnification of some 270 times with a
single lens.
Having started his career as a draper,
van Leeuwenhoek had been counting the
threads of his wares with a magnifying
glass. Gradually he became so fascinated
by microscopy that he devoted more and
more time to perfecting his lenses arid
bringing them to bear on everything he
could put his hands on.
Thus he turned from a small business¬
man into one of the world's great natura¬
lists, earning what money he needed
through several jobs in the service of the
town of Delft.
He recorded his observations in great
detail and with passionate objectivity in
his famous letters to the Royal Society in
London; the Society eventually elected
him a Fellow in 1680.
His collected letters are now being
published by the Royal Academy of Scien¬
ces of the Netherlands in Doth Dutch and
English, illustrated with his drawings, and
Portrait of Antonie
van Leeuwenhoek
(1632-1723)
by J. Verkolje
annotated in the light of present know¬
ledge. More than 20 thick volumes are
foreseen.
Even today his reports are a delight to
read. On the one hand he leaned over
backwards to remain factual and to refrain
from unwarranted interpretations and
speculations, providing ingenious quanti¬
tative measurements wherever he could.
On the other hand he could not always
restrain himself, a human being possessed
as he was by the elation engendered by
marvels freshly discovered.
On such occasions he let himself go,
giving vent to his excitement, an ex¬
citement easily shared by biologists peer¬
ing through their microscopes today.
Describing, for instance, his observations
on what we now call bacteria in infusions
of pepper in water, he wrote (1676) .
"In the afternoon of the same day, about
3 o'clock, I saw still more animalcules, both
round ones and those that were twice as
long as broad, and besides these, a sort
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
which were still smaller, and incredibly
many of the very little animalcules whose
shape I could not make out this morning.
I now saw very distinctly that these were
little eels or worms..., lying huddled toge¬
ther and wriggling, just as if you saw with
your naked eye a whole tubful of very little
eels and water, the eels moving about in
swarms; and the whole water, seemed to
be alive with the multitudinous animalcules.
"For me this was among all the marvels
that I have discovered in nature the most
marvellous of all, and I must say that, for
my part, no more pleasant sight has yet
met my eye than this of so many thousands
of living creatures in one small drop of
water, all huddling and moving, but each
creature having its own motion. And even
if I said that there were a hundred thousand
animalcules in one drop of water which I
took from the surface of the water, I
should not err."
And in his letter (1693) on the anatomy
of the flea he recorded the following excla¬
mation of his draughtsman: "Dear God,
what marvels there are in so small a
creature." 	-
Because he also observed and described
many other kinds of microbes such as
algae, protozoa and yeasts, van Leeuwen¬
hoek became perhaps best known as the
Father of Microbiology. Nevertheless we
should not forget that he made many more
pioneering discoveries in other branches
of biology as well, including:
the spermatozoids of man (1677); the
circulation of the blood in arteries; the
structure of hair, teeth and bone; the
components of blood, milk and sputum; I
the structure of wood and many other
plant tissues;
the anatomy of insects, worms and
many other animals.
Through his work in botany, anatomy,
histology, entomology, physiology, as
well as that in microbiology, van Leeuwen- |
hoek became a universal forerunner in the |
life sciences, a field of intensive activity ^
for Unesco too, in which the Organization |
closely collaborates with the International |
Cell Research Organization (ICRO), found- ^
ed exactly 15 years ago.
A major segment of this programme is
carried out jointly with the United Nations
Environment Programme (UNEP) and is
directed towards the application of micro¬
biology to the basic human needs in the
developing countries, especially rural areas.
Most microbes less than one-tenth of k
a percent of them can cause disease are Y
PIONEER EXPLORATION
OF THE MICROBE WORLD
Above, a brass microscope, one of 500
made and used by Antonie van
Leeuwenhoek between 1673 and 1723 in
his pioneering studies of microbes. The
tiny lens was mounted between two metal
plates (approx. 40 mm by 18 mm) riveted
together. Objects to be viewed were
mounted on a needle and brought into
focus by adjusting the screw which moved
On
II
!»
5 -o
<sfá: G
the specimen in front of the lens.
15 April 1977 a replica of a van
' Leeuwenhoek microscope was presented
to Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-
General of Unesco by the Netherlands
National Commission for Unesco in
recognition of Unesco's activities in the
life sciences. Below left, van
Leeuwenhoek's drawings of bacteria
from the human mouth. Fig. A is a
drawing "of a motile Bacillus. Below right,
cell of a motile Bacillus seen through a
powerful modern electron microscope.
In a famous letter to the Royal Society In
London, written In 1683, van Leeuwenhoek
vividly described the above bacteria and their
movements: A, he wrote "had a strong and
nimble motion and shot through the water like
a pike"; B "often spin about like a top and
sometimes took a course as shown between C
and D "; E "went ahead so nimbly. . . that I can
compare them to nothing better than a swarm
of gnats or files"; F were "streaks or threads...
which lay disorderly ravelled together"; and
G "bent themselves in curves as they moved. "
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
beneficial and eminently suited to serve as
tools in the production of food, fodder;
fuel and fertilizer, in the recycling of waste
materials and in the production of chemi¬
cals like antibiotics (see Unesco Courier,
July 1975). These are the areas on which
the UNEP-Unesco-ICRO programme of
applied microbiology concentrates its
activities.
But there is one more good reason why
Unesco should join in the celebrations of
the tercentenary of van Leeuwenhoek's
discoveries. At a time when Europe was
seething with conflict, van Leeuwenhoek
quietly conducted his correspondence
with the Royal Society in London across
the barriers of the war between England
and the Netherlands (1672-1674).
This is spelled out in the letter through
which Reinier de Graaf, an anatomist from
Delft, introduced van Leeuwenhoek to the
Royal Society in 1673: "That it may be the
more evident to you that the humanities
and science are not yet banished from
among us by the clash of arms, I am writ¬
ing to tell you that a certain most ingenious
person here, named Leeuwenhoeck, has
devised microscopes which far surpass
those which we have hitherto seen... The
enclosed letter from him, wherein he des¬
cribes certain things which he has observed
more accurately than previous authors,
will afford you a sample of his work...."
The letters in which van Leeuwenhoek
communicated his discoveries to the Royal
Society 300 years ago manifest the univer¬
sality and pervasiveness of scientific en¬
deavour among the nations of the world,
spiritual foundations upon which Unesco
also depends.
J.W.M. La Rivière
RUBENS (CONTINUED FROM PAGE 18)
less than two months before his death, provides ample proof to
the contrary. And his work, it must be repeated, is that of a
contented man.
Rubens died in Antwerp on 3 May 1640. He had been the
: crowning glory of the Antwerp school, which virtually died out
with him. Van Dyck followed him to the grave in 1641, although
' Jordaens, the Antwerp school's last representative of note, sur¬
vived until 1678. After that, the school went into a more or less
final decline. However, Rubens' work continued to exercise
great influence, especially on French artists, from Watteau,
' Boucher and Fragonard, to Delacroix, and even Renoir.
Rubens, a fascinating and many-sided personality, loved
corresponding with the great men of his time, especially with
humanists such as Fabri de Peiresc, the famous Provencal scholar
who, right up to his death in 1637, lost no opportunity to show
his admiration for the painter.
As a result of his formative years in Italy, Rubens was most
at ease when writing in Italian, which he used whether commu¬
nicating with Spanish grandees such as the Archduke and his
wife, or Count-Duke Olivares, or with his French scholar friends.
Sometimes he wrote in Frenchto Buckingham among others
or in Flemish, to some of his colleagues. His letters contain a
liberal sprinkling of Latin phrases.
His prodigious capacity for work enabled him to amass an
impressive fortune, despite the hard times in which he lived. He
was tireless in defending his own interests. For example, he was
greatly interested in engraving, realizing that the circulation of
prints was an excellent means of getting his work widely known.
In addition to obtaining privileges for the distribution of his works
in several countries, he made a close study of engraving tech¬
niques, even giving impetus to a new school of engraving, differ¬
ing from earlier schools in its concern to render subtle gradations
of light and shade.
In his search for the most faithful possible rendering of his
coloristic richness into linear black and white, he helped to
train a galaxy of engravers, including Cornelis Galle, the Bolswert
brothers, Lucas Vorstermans and Paulus Pontius. These engrav¬
ers took the rapid sketches he prepared for his friend Balthasar
Moretus, who had inherited the Plantin press, and completed
them in accordance with his instructions. These sketches became
the sumptuous title pages which lent the books coming off
Plantin's presses their entirely new, pure baroque style.
Rubens was a draughtsman of astonishing skill. When pre¬
paring his portraits, he would make a study of the model from
life, thereby enabling us to gauge just how much liberty he took
when he came to apply the paint. Here too, his powerfully deco¬
rative style helped save his models from banality. What is most
striking in these sketches, which usually served as a guide for the
final composition, is his sureness of touch. . Everything fell into
place at once; there was no need for second thoughts. The
sketches, done on little wood panels, with brush and sepia, with
the occasional underscoring of colour here and there, furnish
striking evidence of Rubens' genius. Even at this stage, every¬
thing was already in its intended place, and the final painting
could be executed to scale from these invaluable documents.
On more than one occasion, as we have seen, the paintings
were done by teams of assistants, with the master adding the
finishing touches. Not that there was ever any attempt to de¬
ceive the client. Rubens graded the prices of his work according
to whether it was entirely "by his hand", as he put it, or simply
supervised or revised by him. ,
In any case, the skill of his assistants was such that specia¬
lists still argue over who exactly did what.
One expert tried to sidetrack the problem by asserting that,
with two exceptionswhich were undeniable on account of
evidence that has survived in Rubens' correspondenceall the
paintings were by the master himself. But this view is untenable.
The fact is, Rubens relied heavily on his assistants, and painted
very few works entirely by himself. This in no way detracts from
his creative genius, one of the greatest in the history of art.
H Roger Avermaeta
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to
the editor
THE ACROPOLIS IN DANGER
Sir,
A short while ago, a terrible photograph
appeared in the newspapers. It showed the
Acropolis, in Athens, trapped in an enorm¬
ous semi-transparent plastic bubble, through
which the famous monuments appeared
dimly, as if seen in a mist.
This "artist's impression" purported to
show the most effective andaccording to
its inventors the easiest way of protecting
the Acropolis from the effects of pollution.
But no one who knows what the Acro¬
polis means to the world, and no one who
has seen for himself the sunlight of Greece
playing on the marble of its monuments,
could countenance such an imprisonment,
even as a last, desperate measure of pro¬
jection.
That is why I was pleased to read, in the
February 1977 issue of the Unesco Courier.
- the appeal by Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
Unesco's Director-General for an inter¬
national campaign to save the monuments
nf the AcrODOlis.
There is hope, then, that the Parthenon,
the Erechtheum,' the Propylaea and the
temple of Athena Nike will be saved, with¬
out recourse to plastic. .
I look forward to reading the Unesco
Courier's forthcoming issue devoted to the
Acropolis. There can be no doubt that by
calling attention again to the site's historic
importance and to the problems of its pre¬
servation, you will alert world opinion, and
make the public even more receptive to Mr.
appeal.
Jean Sam Curtet
Nyon, Switzerland
Editor's note: The Greek authorities have rejected
as unfeasible a plan to cover the Acropolis monu¬
ments with a giant glass dome to save them from
pollution decay.
LEVIATHAN LIVES ON
Sir,
Your January 1977 issue ("Who Owns
the Oceans?") contains a caption on whales
which is misleading.
It is not true to state that "all species of
great whales are threatened with extinction
because of intensive whaling." Indeed, the
only species so threatened is Bryde's Whale
(Balaenoptera edeni), a tropical species
which is taken mainly by nations not party
to the International Whaling Convention.
Nor is it true to state that "no measurable
increase has occurred in the numbers of the
[totally] protected species [of great whales]."
Humpback whales in the North Atlantic
have been protected since 1955, blue wha¬
les since 1960. Humpback whales in the
Northwest Atlantic are numerous, probably
numbering 1500 or more. The number of
blue whales in the same area is not known
accurately, but strandings induced by ice
are now an annual phenomenon in south¬
west Newfoundland.
Rate of increase, clearly, will be a func¬
tion of the residual population at time of
protection and time elapsed since protec¬
tion, and will follow the kind of curve ex¬
pected of an animal population.
Dr. D.E. Sergeant
Member, Whale Research Group,
International Union for Conservation of
Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN)
Ste. Anne de Bellevue
Montreal, Canada
ESPERANTO
AND WORLD COMMUNICATION
Sir,
I am rather surprised that your April 1977
issue about world communication contains
no reference to the international language,
Esperanto, invented by Dr. Zamenhof to¬
wards the end of the last century.
Being completely regular in grammatical
construction, and for other reasons, it is
much easier to learn than any national lan¬
guage. It has the added advantage of being
"neutral", so that its use does not excite
national sensitivities.
R.D.Y. Perrett
Sheffield, U.K.
UNESCO MEDAL FOR RUBENS YEAR
To mark the 400th anniversary of Rubens' birth, Unesco
has issued a commemorative medal in gold, silver and
bronze. The medal (see opposite page) shows on one
side a bust of Rubens, after his self-portrait in the Rubens'
House, Antwerp. On the other is a mother and infant
from a Rubens drawing, "Maternity", in the Louvre,
bearing the inscription "Pietro Pauolo Rubens" in the
style of his signature. During a ceremony at Brussels on
21 April, the first gold medal to be struck was presented
to King Baudouin of Belgium by a delegation led jointly by
Mr. Makaminan Makagíansar, Unesco's Assistant Direc¬
tor-General for Culture and Communication and by Mr.
Felipe Herrera, Chairman of the Administrative Council of
the International Fund for the Promotion of Culture.
Proceeds from the sale of the medal, designed by Serge
Santucci (France) and struck by the French mint, will be
used to assist the training of young artists from develop¬
ing countries.
The medal can be obtained from:
The Philatelic Service of Unesco,
7, Place de Fontenoy,
75700 Paris;
Monnaies et Médailles du Monde,
24, Rue Royale,
75008 Paris;
or from Belgian banks.
Prices are as follows:
Gold 900/1,000, 0 23 mm, 7.5 g
(with chain ring)
455 French francs
500 FF
(3370 Belgian francs)
(3705 FB)
Silver 925/1,000, 0 41 mm, 30 g
(with chain ring)
135 FF
145 FF
(1000 FB)
(1075 FB)
Bronze 0 59 mm, 100 g
(with chain ring)
60 FF
70 FF
( 445 FB)
( 520 FB)
Complete series in a box
(with chain ring)
670 FF
735 FF
(4965 FB)
(5445 FB)
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
New Trends in Integrated Scien¬
ce Teaching, Volume IV: Evaluation
of Integrated Science Education,
edited by David Cohen. (Based on the
proceedings of an international sympo¬
sium held in Oxford, U.K., in 1975).
1977, 199 pp. (38 F).
Communication Policies in Costa
Rica, by Jaime M. Fonseca. 1977,
89 pp. (16 F).
Science and Technology in the
Development of the Arab States.
(No. 41 in Unesco's "Science Policy .
Studies and Documents" series). 1977,
327 pp. (30 F).
The Economics of New Educatio¬
nal Media. A reference book on the
cost effectiveness of different media
approaches to education. ("Educational
Methods and Techniques" series. No. 1).
1977, 200 pp. (36 F).
In-service Training of Teachers in
Sri Lanka, by K.D. Ariyadasa. 1976,
56 pp. (7 F); Examination Reforms in
Sri Lanka, by B. Premaratne. 1976,
49 pp (6 F); Management of Educa¬
tional Reforms in Sri Lanka, by K.D.
Ariyadasa. 1976, 41 pp. (6 F); Integrat¬
ed Approach to Curriculum Deve¬
lopment in Primary Education in Sri
Lanka, by K. Peiris. 1976, 25 pp. (6 F);
Integrated Science in the Junior
Secondary School in Sri Lanka, by
A.M. Ranaweera. 1976, 31 pp. (6 F).
A series of studies on Sri Lanka's major
educational reforms of 1972. Unesco:
International Bureau of Education (IBE)
"Experiments and Innovations in Edu¬
cation" series. Nos. 23, 24, 25, 26 and
27.
A Comprehensive Plan for the
Global Investigation of Pollution in
the Marine Environment and Base¬
line Study Guidelines. (Intergovern-'
mental Océanographie Commission
Technical Series, No. 14). 1976, 42 pp.
(6 F).
An Alternative Pattern of Basic
Education. Radio Santa Maria, by
Robert White. A study on Radio Santa
Maria, which provides an education
service for the rural adult population of
the Dominican Republic. (Unesco: IBE
"Experiments and Innovations in Educa¬
tion" series. No. 30). 1976, 122 pp.
(15 F).
Mediterranean Forests and Ma¬
quis: Ecology, Conservation and
Management. 1977, 79 pp. (14 F);
Human Population Problems in the
Biosphere: Some Research Strate¬
gies and Designs, edited by Paul
Baker. 1977, 82 pp. (16 F); Dynamic
Changes in Terrestrial Ecosystems:
Patterns of Change, Techniques for
Study and Application to Manage¬
ment, edited by R.O. Slatyer. 1977,
30 pp. (6 F) Nos. 2, 3 and 4 in Unesco's
"MAB Technical Notes" series. (MAB
= Man and the Biosphere, Unesco's
international programme of global re¬
search on the interactions between man
and the environment.)
G3 0
Dictionary of
African Biography
The first volume (Ethiopia-Ghana) of the Dic¬
tionary of African Biography was presented to
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow, Director-General
of Unesco, on 19 April 1977 by Professor Ofosu-
Appiah, Director of the Encyclopaedia Africana
secretariat. The first of 20 volumes being
written under the direction of the Encyclopaedia
Africana secretariat in Accra (Ghana) it cont¬
ains 290 biographies of noted African figures
from Ethiopia and Ghana (living persons not
included). Vol. I can be obtained from Refe¬
rence Publications Inc., 218 St. Clair River
Drive, Algonac, Michigan 48001, U.S.A., price
$59.95 per copy. (For orders outside U.S.A.
add $3 per copy for shipping.) The 20-volume
set can also be ordered at a specially reduced
pre-publication price of $49.95 per volume (plus
$3 per volume for shipping costs outside U.S.A.).
Prices subject to change for later volumes if
printing costs increase.
30 years
of international co-operation
in flying
The International Civil Aviation Organization
(ICAO) celebrates its 30th anniversary this year.
A specialized agency of the United Nations
with 136 Member States, its objectives are to
develop the principles and techniques of inter¬
national air navigation and to foster the plan¬
ning and development of international air trans¬
port. It is currently playing an active role in
providing technical assistance for aviation pro¬
jects within the framework of the U.N. family's
programme of aid to developing countries.
Centenary of
sound recording
The centenary of the invention of recorded sound
was celebrated recently at Unesco's Paris head¬
quarters at a ceremony organized jointly by
the International Federation of Producers of
Phonograms and Videograms (IFPI) and the
International Music Council (IMC). The French
U.N. stamp honours
Security Council
UMTtDWmONS WOtlW
iOy80coNsa-n£S£ajwTE
i	»««.--..
This stamp honouring the United Nations Secu¬
rity Council is one of a set issued by the U.N.
Postal Administration on 27 May 1977. It is a
tribute to the work of the body on which the
U.N.'s Member States have conferred the pri¬
mary responsibility for maintaining peace and
security. Designed by G. Hambri (Australia),
the stamp renders the idea of security through
two stylized hands protecting the U.N. emblem, ,
symbol of the universe.
\S\
poet Charles Cros invented a phonograph in
1877, the same year in which Thomas Edison
of the U.S.A. made his first recording. During
the ceremony, Mr. John E. Fobes, Unesco's
Deputy Director-General, drew attention to
Unesco-sponsored conventions and agreements
protecting recordings and facilitating their
circulation, and stressed the importance of re¬
cording in conserving and making known "un¬
written music, so rich in many countries of
Africa, Asia and Latin America".
New catalogue of
U.N. stamps
A new list of U.N. stamps issued during the
first 25 years (1951-1976) of existence of the
United Nations Postal Administration has just
been published. It is available (in English only)
from the U.N. Postal Administration, Palais des
Nations, CH-1211 Geneva 10, Switzerland (price
$0.75).	 :
India's gift to save
Moenjodaro in Pakistan
The Indian government has contributed $50,000
to Unesco's International Campaign to safe-1
guard the 5,000-year-old site of Moenjodaro in
Pakistan, one of the largest known examples of
early Bronze Age town planning. The Interna¬
tional Campaign was launched to raise a mini¬
mum $5 million of the estimated $11 million
needed to preserve Moenjodaro from destruc¬
tion. Total contributions pledged or received
now stand at $650,000.
Dinosaurs and drifting
continents
A piece of fossilized bone, recently discovered _
on the Isle of Wight (U.K.), is believed to be
part of the tail of a giant Diplodocus dinosaur.
A complete skeleton of a Diplodocus was un¬
earthed in Wyoming (U.S.A.) at the turn of the
century. The new find suggests that this pre¬
historic creature also existed in what is now
Europe, and supports the theory that Europe
and America were once joined in a single land-
mass that later split and drifted apart.
Flashes...
The Paris mint has issued a medal to
mark the 300th anniversary of Spinoza's
death.
Schistosomiasis, or snail fever, is ende¬
mic in 71 countries, infecting about 200 mil¬
lion people, reports WHO. The disease is
spreading and its severity Increasing.
The water used by 90 per cent of the
population of the developing world Is either
unsafe or inadequate, or both, reports
UNICEF.
As part of Its "philatelic year" Sweden
is issuing a special stamp to commemorate
the 500th anniversary of Uppsala University.
The U.S. alligator has been saved from
extinction after 20 years of efforts by con¬
servationists and officials, reports U.N.
Development Forum.
UNICEF is helping to sink some 310,000
shallow wells in Bangladesh (from 1972 to
1980) for supplying safe drinking water to
rural communities.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
TWO UNESCO BOOKS ON PAINTING
Catalogue of reproductions of paintings 1860 to
1973 with fifteen projects for exhibitions
1974
343 pp.
40 French francs
Lists high-quality colour
reproductions of more than
1,500 important paintings
produced between 1860
and 1973, chosen by an
international panel of
experts.
Each reproduction
shown in black and white,
along with full details of
original work (date,
collection, museum, etc.)
and reproduction (size,
price, publisher's
address, etc.).
Fifteen projects for
exhibitions based on the
reproductions in the
catalogue.
An illustrated inventory of famous
dismembered works of art-European painting
Unesco
An illustrated inventory
of famous dismembered
«oiks of an
European painting
1974
221 pp., 340 illustrations
70 FF (hardbound)
)
Distinguished European
specialists trace the history
of famous dismembered or
mutilated works of art and
show what has been or
could be done to restore
these works to their
original unity.
Chapters on dismembered
works of Flemish, French,
German, Italian, Russian
and Spanish painting;
European illuminated
manuscripts; and
dismembered tombs and
sculpture in France.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW; Periodicals;
Dominie Pty., Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division 5th floor, 134-136 Flinders St.,
Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain,
Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandlung, Industriehof Stadlan,
Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220 Wien. - BELGIUM. "Unesco
Courier" Dutch edition only; N.V. Handelmaatschappij Keesing.
Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition
and general Unesco publications agent: Jean de Lannoy, 112,
rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 000-0070823-13. - BURMA.
Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552 Merchant Street. Rangoon.
CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine
Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H 1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 11 Soukenicka,
Prague 1. For Slovakia only; Alfa Verlag Publishers,
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava - CSSR. - DEN¬
MARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National' Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency
for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, SF 00100 Helsinki.
FRANCE, Librairie de l'Unesco.' 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Interna¬
tionalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53
Bonn 1, Colmantstrasse 22, C.C.P. Hamburg 276650. For
scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach
800830. Other publications; Verlag Dokumentation, Pössen-
bacher Strasse 2, 8000 München 71 (Prinz Ludwigshöhe).
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - GREECE.
International bookshops. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
Division, Far East Publications Ltd., 5 A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, Wong Chuk Hang Road, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémial
Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok
Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. - ICELAND.
Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate,
Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a,
Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New
Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820
Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub-Depots; Oxford Book &
Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House.
New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry of Education and
Social Welfare, 511 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan, New Delhi 110001. -
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop. Jl. Gadjah
Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 47,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution
Co., 229 Daneshgahe Street. Shah Avenue, P.O. Box 14/1486,
Teheran. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, Avenue
Iranchahr Chomali No 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ.
McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad. . IRELAND.
The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road,
Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachtat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street Je¬
rusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.
Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. - JAPAN. Eastern Book
Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo 100-92. - KENYA. East
African Publishing House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, P.O. Box
2942, Kuwait. - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book Centre, P.O.
Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia. - LIBYA.
Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O.
Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg, MALAYSIA. Federal Publi¬
cations Sdn. Bhd., Balai Berita, 31, Jalan Riong, Kuala Lumpur. -
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30,- bd des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications; N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.). N.V.,
Willemstad, Curaçao. N. A. NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street,
P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721,
Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes
Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag,
Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife. The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University
Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The
Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY.
All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl Johans-
gate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only; A.S. Narvesens
Literaturtjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. - PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore
3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue,
P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. - POLAND. ORPAN-IMPORT,
Palac Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dlas Et
Andrade Ltda, Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMAU DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop
and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Buil¬
ding, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier (single copies) only; Central News Agency P.O. Box
1033, Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook
Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.B. 244 Columbo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118, Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier; Svenska FN-Forbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. - TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030
Dares-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnem Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London. Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill
Station, New York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in
Spanish: Santillana Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington
Avenue, New York, N.Y. 10022. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya
Kniga, Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenije,
Titova C 25, P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
SELF-PORTRAIT OF RUBENS, PAINTED WHEN HE WAS AGED ABOUT 60, A FEW YEARS BEFORE HIS DEATH.
]]>
</page>
</document>
