<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074804eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco CX)llFÍCr A window
Ä:.AiVr;
K^
I
KBBH
ma
::£*@$
O-ù&ik
««S^-^ys?*,-
»«
-"-*&
*^\¡3
. "«.f
e^ *e
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
Egypt
The blessings of the sun
This low-relief sculpture (1.05 m. high) depicts the Pharaoh Akhenaton and his wife IMefertiti worshipping the
sun-disc Atori, which confers blessings on them through its life-giving rays. This Egyptian ruler came to the
throne as Amenophis IV of the 18th dynasty (1567-1320 BC) but in the fourth year of his reign took the name
Akhenaton, which means "He Who Serves the Aton". He abandoned the old gods of Thebes and devoted
himself to the exclusive cult of Aton, hitherto worshipped as one of a number of deities. Carved around 1370
BC, the sculpture is today preserved in the Cairo Museum.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COllIier
JUNE 1978 31st YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 18 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese Dutch
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head. Inc., 111 West 40th Street.
New York, U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia. U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in
Olga Rodel
Managing Editors:
English Edition:
French Edition:
Spanish Edition:
Russian Edition:
German Edition:
Arabic Edition:
Japanese Edition:
Italian Edition:
Hindi Edition:
Tamil Edition:
Hebrew Edition:
Persian Edition:
Dutch Edition:
Portuguese Edition:
Turkish Edition:
Urdu Edition:
Catalan Edition:
Malaysian Edition:
chief
Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Pans)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Werner Merkli (Berne)
Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition:
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Pans.
page
5 ENERGY FOR TOMORROW'S WORLD
by Boris M. Berkovsky
COO
Oí 2
in ,
<2z
8 THE FAST BREEDER
A nuclear reactor that produces more fuel than it consumes
by Wolf Häfele
11 NUCLEAR ENERGY AND THE ENVIRONMENT
Are present safeguards adequate?
by Essam El-Hinnawi
13 FUSION POWER r
by Rende/ S. Pease
16 THE SUN ALSO SURPRISES
The myriad possibilities of solar energy
by A. Ramachandran and J. Gururaja
22 NEPTUNE'S POWER STATION
Ocean thermal energy conversion offers
an inexhaustible and non-polluting energy source
by Richard Arlen Meyer
24 TAPPING EARTH'S FIERY CORE
by Ralph Haenel
26 REAPING THE WIND
27 A COME-BACK FOR KING COAL
by Vladimir A. Kuzminov
29 FARMING MICROBES FOR FOOD AND FUEL
by Jan Willem M. La Rivière and Edgar J. DaSilva
32 THE CASE FOR HYDROGEN ENERGY
by T. Nejat Veziroglu
34 IN BRIEF
2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
EGYPT: The blessings of the sun
Cover
The first photograph of the earth eclipsing
the sun was taken by Apollo 12 astronauts
returning from the moon in November 1969.
Cover shows the amazing interplay of light
seen by the astronauts. The sun, which is
itself an enormous thermonuclear reactor,
has always provided virtually all the energy
used by man, in the form of solar energy
stored in fossil fuels, in the flow of rivers and
in the plants that provide our food. But fossil
fuels, which today meet the bulk of our
energy requirements, are non-renewable and
the race is on to find replacements for them
before thev run out.
Photo © IPS. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Owing to its ease of use and convenience as a vehicle
to carry energy to the consumer, electricity, whether
produced in a coal-fired or a nuclear power station or
by any of the alternative energy sources (solar,
geothermal, wind, tide), is in increasingly high demand.
At present ten per cent of the energy consumed in the
world is in the form of electricity and it is estimated
that this share will increase to twenty per cent by the
year 2020. Below, the camera captures the crystal-like
beauty of an electrical discharge induced in an
experimental laboratory.
For a quarter of a century,
Unesco has been closely
concerned with world energy
problems as part of its scientific
activities. On 16 May 1978, while
presenting Unesco's programme
for science and technology to the
Organization's Executive Board,
the Director-General of Unesco,
Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow,
drew attention to a major project
on the promotion of research
aimed at rational utilization of
conventional and non-
conventional sources of energy.
This project Mr. M'Bow
explained, "deals with the
problems of energy production,
conversion, storage and efficient
utilization. It includes training
activities and support for
research, and is aimed in
particular at ensuring that
conventional sources of energy
such as coal are used more
effectively and at promoting new
energy sources." The energy
issue raises questions of vital
importance for the future of
humanity. This number of the
Unesco Courier attempts to
answer these questions by
presenting an overview of energy
sources available in the world
today and a study of possible
alternatives for tomorrow.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Energy
for tomorrow's
world
Human ingenuity applied to
the natural resources of the earth
can ensure the energy needs
of future generations
by Boris M. Berkovsky
THE world's energy comes from a
number of different sources, which
may be broadly classified in two
categories. The first, which includes fossil
fuels and minerals such as oil, coal, natural
gas, uranium, etc., comprises sources of
energy that are non-renewable. The
second category which includes the winds,
the waves, the tides, the temperature of
the oceans, and the sun, comprises
sources that will continue to provide
energy in virtually unlimited quantities as
long as the earth and the sun exist. And
yet, despite the fact that they are to all
intents and purposes inexhaustible, the
sources of this second category remain
almost untapped.
Most energy is produced today by
burning hydrocarbon fuels drawn from the
world's non-renewable reserves. The
amount of these potential reserves, by
which is generally meant the quantity that
can be extracted by present or conceivable
future techniques, is a matter of some con¬
troversy; this is understandable, if we con¬
sider the enormous difficulties involved in
determining how much fuel Nature has hid¬
den in the earth, and how much of it is or
' will become accessible, and the fact that
different countries use different methods
of estimation.
It is impossible, for example, with
present-day drilling techniques, to drain an
Boris M. Berkovsky of the Byelorussian Soviet
Socialist Republic is a specialist in thermo-
physics who is currently responsible for
Unesco's programme on fundamental scientific
and technological energy problems.
oil well absolutely dry; a considerable
amount remains underground. The estima¬
tion of oil reserves thus depends on the
efficiency of the extracting equipment, and
the improvement of this efficiency is a sub¬
ject of intensive research today in all the oil-
producing countries. The same is true for
coal and natural gas. But some idea of the
potential reserves of such fuels may be
obtained from the following figures.
World Energy Conference statistics indi¬
cate that almost 88 per cent of the world's
potential reserves of fossil fuels are in the
form of solid matter, principally coal. Solid
fuel potential reserves amount to approxi¬
mately 11,200,000,000,000 tons of codi
equivalent (TCE) (1), or enough coal to fill
an enormous cube twice as high as the
world's highest mountain ! This image ser¬
ves to show at the same time that although
these reserves are colossal, they are also
limited. Liquid fuel potential reserves
(mainly crude oil) are estimated to amount
to some 740,000,000,000 TCE, and poten¬
tial reserves of natural gas, to approxi¬
mately 630,000,000,000 TCE
Proven recoverable reserves, i.e. those
whose extraction is already an economi¬
cally feasible proposition, are consid¬
erably smaller, and amount to approxi¬
mately 4,000,000,000,000 TCE for all the
fossil fuels together. The great difference
between potential and proven recoverable
reserves is explained by the fact that
Nature has placed so much of this fossil f
(1) "Ton of Coal Equivalent" (TCE) is used as a unit o1
measurement of energy production or consumption, 1,
TCE being an amount of energy equivalent to that pro¬
duced by one ton of coal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
L fuel in remote parts of the globe, at depths
and in quantities that make its extraction
unjustifiable at present in economic terms.
It should be pointed out that the above
figures are under- rather than over¬
estimated, particularly as far as reserves of
natural gas and of shale and bituminous oil
are concerned.
Let us now compare proven recoverable
reserves with estimated consumption. Bet¬
ween now and the year 2000, the quantity
of energy required by the world will
account for almost 10 per cent of its proven
recoverable fossil fuels; if no other source
of energy is employed, 78 per cent of these
fuels will have been used up by the
year 2050; while a hundred years later
to the most moderate long-
term forecast there will be none left.
Comparison of consumption with poten¬
tial reserves produces a somewhat brighter
picture. By the year 2000, the demand for
energy will have used up only 3.6 per cent
of these reserves, and by 2050 per
cent. A century later, about half of these
reserves will still remain.
These comparisons clearly show that the
world's stock of chemical fuels is quite suf¬
ficient to cover its energy requirements for
at least another hundred years. There is
thus no immediate danger of, as it were,
emptying the coal-bucket. On the other
hand, these reserves of fuel are limited, and
within the foreseeable future there could be
none left. It is possible that our children's
grandchildren might find themselves in a
world drained dry of natural gas and oil.
We should thus lose no time in thinking
about ways and means of producing artifi¬
cial oil or artificial gas, and above all of pro¬
ducing energy in unlimited quantities from
sources which in no way threaten the
environment.
Science is already familiar with sources
and types of energy that are infinitely more
powerful than the old chemical fuels. At¬
omic energy, produced by controlled
chain-reactions involving the fission of
heavy elements such as uranium and pluto¬
nium, is the outstanding example. Then
there is thermonuclear energy, produced
by fusion of light atoms at very high tem¬
peratures such as those which occur inside
the sun. Finally, there is the mind-bending
process known as annihilation, in which
matter comes into contact with anti-matter
to release energy in unheard-of quantities,
and which astrophysicists believe to be the
source of the enormous energy of the so-
called "quasars", or quasi stellar sources.
Simpler chemical physics tells us that the
burning of one gramme of wood produces
enough energy to light up a hundred-watt
bulb for one minute, and that one gramme
of burning coal is enough to light two simi¬
lar bulbs for the same sixty seconds. One
gramme of uranium in a nuclear reactor
produces much more energy enough, in
fact, to light 200,000 bulbs or 20,000 apart¬
ments for a whole hour.
Exciting new prospects are opened up by
"fast breeder reactors", so-called because
they involve fast-moving neutrons, and by
controlled thermonuclear (fusion) reac¬
tions. One gramme of deuterium (an iso¬
tope of hydrogen) in such a fusion reaction
would produce enough energy to light all
the homes of a large modern town for an
hour. The process of annihilation mentio¬
ned above creates fantastic quantities of
energy: one gramme of matter and one
gramme of anti-matter produce the energy
equivalent of 6,000 tons of coal an hour's
lighting for the homes of all the inhabitants
of a country the size of France!
^ ANY experts think that the
HH^^^H utilization non-
I 1 V j I renewable sources of
I I II I energy is limited by ecolo-
I I I I I gical factors. Strange as it
| ^ ^ | may seem, this is not a
H^H^HH matter of pollution of the
^^BB^^HI environment by the solid
matter and poisonous effluents emitted
during the combustion of fossil fuels. Expe¬
rience shows that such pollution can be
handled. The real problem concerns the
overheating of the earth's surface and its
atmosphere resulting from both the pro¬
duction of energy, by nuclear and conven¬
tional power stations alike, and its con¬
sumption.
In accordance with Nature's immutable
laws, all forms of energy known to Man,
whether mechanical or electrical in origin,
end up as heat. And this heat affects the
temperature of the earth's surface and its
atmosphere in a way that can upset things,
as far as the climate is concerned, on a
local or even global scale, depending on its
influence on the natural process of give-
and-take which constitutes the world's
thermal balance.
Certain scientists believe that the maxi¬
mum amount of energy that can be prod¬
uced on the earth in any given year without
catastrophic consequences for its climate
amounts to some 70,000,000,000,000 TCE.
This is obviously much more than we are
producing at the moment but it is not an
inconceivably large amount. We may con¬
sequently say that although there appears
to be no immediate danger of a change of
climate on a worldwide scale, local distur¬
bances, particularly in the vicinity of indus¬
trial centres where large quantities of
energy are produced and consumed, are
already possible, and require some very
careful thought. Of course, the question
whether local disruption of the thermal
balance can affect atmospheric pheno¬
mena on a global scale remains open.
We have so far limited ourselves to the
consideration of terrestrial sources of
energy. But what about the sun ? It is
known that all the vegetation of our planet
absorbs an annual ration of at least
12,300,000,000 TCE of solar energy. The
amount of sunlight falling on a square
metre of the earth's surface theoretically
contains the equivalent of around one kilo¬
watt of energy. In other words, the sun¬
light falling on an area of very approxima¬
tely 100 kilometres square during the
course of a year would be enough to satisfy
all man's requirements at the present time.
The waves of the world ocean contain
almost three times as much energy as the
world is using today in the form of electri¬
city. Almost as much energy can be extrac¬
ted from the ocean by taking advantage of
temperature and salinity gradients and
there is the more immediately obvious
energy in its currents and its tides. There is
energy in the earth's body-temperature
too, and in the fresh waters that run over
its surface.
All of this goes to show that the real
question today is not one of inadequate
resources of energy, but of difficulties
which are mainly of a political and econo¬
mic nature. These difficulties stem from
arbitrary decisions at the level of produc¬
tion and from irrational patterns of
consumption.
How is the situation likely to develop?
The majority of specialists believe that the
way ahead lies through more thoughtful
and careful planning in the production, dis¬
tribution and utilization of energy, through
research designed to improve conventional
methods of energy supply and through the
establishment of a sound basis for the
energy production of tomorrow. Another
extremely important task is the exploitation
of reliable sources of energy that cause the
least possible harm to the environment.
In many circles, the call is for a concen¬
tration of efforts on the utilization of re¬
newable energy that can be produced
"ecologically", and of solar energy in parti¬
cular. Specialists agree that the time has
come to move in that direction, but point
out that it will be many years before such
energy is available in sufficient quantities to
contribute in an appreciable manner to the
satisfaction of mankind's requirements.
Opinions differ concerning the exact
amount of time involved, but concur that it
will be measured in decades, rather than
years.
This conclusion is based on the amount
of time required in the past to replace one
major source of energy by another, i.e.
wood by coal, coal by oil, oil by natural
gas. It is interesting to note that in each
case, the time-span of transition has never
been less than 60 years. It is reasonable to
expect although allowance must be made
for possible scientific and technological
breakthroughs that approximately the
same period will be required for the intro¬
duction of new methods of producing
energy.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The what's watt of energy
1 gramme
of wood
0.0018 kilowatt-hours
Power to light
1 hundred-watt bulb
for 1 minute
1 gramme
of coal
X^r ~
0.0037 kilowatt-hours =
Power to light
2 hundred-watt bulbs
for 1 minute
1 gramme
of uranium-235
= 20,000 kilowatt-hours
1 gramme
of deuterium (1)'
150,000 kilowatt-hours
Power to light
a small town
(60,000 inhabitants)
for 1 hour
Power to light
a large city
(500,000 inhabitants)
for 1 hour
(1) Deuterium, also called heavy hydrogen, is an important ingredient in
the fuel required to produce a fusion reaction. Supplies of deuterium,
which can be easily separated from water, are virtually inexhaustible.
Drawings Mas © Unesco Courier
For this reason, the priority task, in deve¬
loped and developing countries alike, is to
refine the traditional methods. During the
next few decades, the accent must remain
on wood, coal, oil and natural gas, while at
the same time work goes ahead in the
quest for their replacements.
Unfortunately, however, there is no lack
of examples today of futile attempts to
implement projects for producing energy
that are still in an embryonic state, if not
totally misconceived. The attraction of
novelty, coupled with a seemingly simple
method and limitless supplies as in the
case of solar energy creates the illusion
that widespread utilization is just around
the corner, and obstructs serious efforts to
introduce reliable long-term methods of
producing energy as rapidly as possible. It
is probably worth recalling in this con
nexion that in North America more than
half a century was needed before
oilwhich was the cheapest and most effi¬
cient primary source of energy at the
time took half the place then occupied by
coal, and that atomic energy, 35 years after
the earliest experiments, still accounts for
less than one per cent of the world's total
energy.
Energy is a key element of social and
economic progress, and its development is
linked with social and political as well as
scientific and technical problems. But there
can be no doubt that human ingenuity and
good will, applied to the unlimited resour¬
ces of the earth itself, will ensure that
future generations have at their disposal as
much energy as they require, without dis¬
ruption of the ecological balance of our pla¬
net. The energy of tomorrow will be vir
tually inexhaustible or renewable, and will
come for example from thermonuclear
reactions and the sun. And tomorrow must
be prepared today, through well prepared
and soundly backed research and practical
experiment, and through a reasoned com¬
bination of national efforts and internatio¬
nal endeavour.
Unesco and other international organiza¬
tions are making a substantial contribution
to the solution of the world's energy
problems. Unesco's long-term programme
concerning scientific and technological
aspects of these problems provides for
multilateral assistance to the developing
countries, the exchange of up-to-date
experience, the strengthening of internatio¬
nal co-operation and the joint examination
of prospects for development.
Boris M. Berkovsky
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The fast breeder
A nuclear reactor that produces
more fuel than it consumes
by Wolf Häfele
IN principle, and to a large extent also in
practice, the fast breeder reactor can
provide virtually unlimited amounts of
energy. Energy from fast breeders there¬
fore is not just an extension of existing
energy resources; it changes our whole
conception of the energy problem.
The fundamental difference between
fast breeder reactors and today's nuclear
power stations is that the former "breed"
more fuel than they consume. Current
nuclear reactors, the predominant type
being the light water reactor, obtain most
Wolf Häfele of the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many is deputy director of the International Insti¬
tute for Applied Systems Analysis (IlASA) at
Laxenburg (Austria), where he leads IIASA's
research on energy systems and problems of
energy demand. While attached to the Karlsruhe
Nuclear Research Centre he participated in the
design of the first German-built nuclear reactor
(FR2) and later established and led the Centre's
Fast Breeder Project. He is a member of the
Scientific Advisory Committee of the Inter¬
national Atomic Energy Agency (IAEA).
of their energy from slow-neutron fission of
the scarce isotope of uranium known as
uranium-235. Natural uranium consists of
only 0.7 per cent of uranium-235; the rest is
uranium-238 which cannot readily be used
by the light water reactor.
A thousand-megawatt light water reac¬
tor consumes some 5,000 tonnes of natural
uranium during its lifetime. A world total of
a thousand such power stations would
thus consume five million tonnes of natural
uranium, a figure approximating to current
estimates of world uranium reserves.
The fast breeder is fuelled with a mixture
of uranium-238 and plutonium. It makes
use of a fast-neutron fission process during
which there is a net gain of about half an
atom of plutonium for every one and a half
atoms of uranium-238 consumed. Since all
the abundant uranium-238 in natural ura¬
nium can be used as fuel, the fast breeder
reactor produces sixty to seventy times
more energy from a given quantity of ura¬
nium than any other reactor now in use.
Consequently, it will be possible to tap eco¬
nomically uranium resources which today
are too costly to exploit.
At the present time, the fast breeder is
the only technology at hand which offers
the possibility of resolving the problems of
energy resource limitations which will have
to be faced in the coming decades.
In the short term, however, if fast
breeders are to be introduced soon they
will be part of energy systems which are
closely integrated into the present world
economy and will have to show that they
can compete with the available alternative
energy sources. It seems reasonably likely
that they will achieve this goal by the end
of the 1990s.
All new technologies have to establish
themselves through hard economic compe¬
tition, a process which ultimately saves
investment in terms of labour, capital and
ingenuity. Light water reactors have
already been through this process and have
proved to be commercially viable. The elec¬
tricity they produce is usually from three to
six dollars per megawatt hour cheaper than
that produced by fossil fuels. During the
recent cold winters in New England, for
instance, light water reactors assumed the
baseload of electricity production. There
are today some 200 of them in operation
throughout the world, and by the year 2000
it is expected that their installed capacity
will be 1,500,000 megawatts.
All fission reactors produce plutonium or
a uranium isotope, U-233, neither of which
occur in nature. Both isotopes permit
breeding and must be handled with very
great care. Both emit alpha-rays and it is
dangerous for the organism to bear traces
of them.
~>
A light water reactor produces about 170
kilogrammes of plutonium per thousand
megawatt year. The safest way of handling
this plutonium is to put it back into a reac¬
tor after separating it chemically from the
rest of the irradiated fuel.
The fast breeder thus has a role to play in
dealing with the "hot end" of the light
water reactor fuel cycle, and a wide variety
of strategies for combining light water
reactors and fast breeders have been
studied and assessed. From these studies it
appears that the principal role of the fast
breeder in the next few decades will be as a
depository for plutonium. Only later will the
multiplying effect on plutonium stocks
become of prime importance.
The second, or present, generation of
fast breeder reactors uses the mixed oxides
Pu02/U02. The inherent negative Doppler
coefficient thus installed acts like a tran¬
quillizer upon the reactor. In the final analy¬
sis, this leads to a situation where the con¬
trol devices of a fast breeder reactor are vir¬
tually identical to those of a light water
reactor, and the safety features of the fast
breeder reactor can be designed to meet
the same predetermined safety standards
as are applied to light water reactors or any
other reactor.
Today's energy systems will not be ade¬
quate to meet tomorrow's needs, and we
must face the fact that a changeover to
new systems is inevitable. Some studies
seem to indicate that the crucial moment
will come shortly after the year 2000. By
that time, if adequate preparations have
not been made, it will be too late to develop
and deploy the technologies capable of
satisfying such a massive demand. The
problem is one of time: several decades will
be needed and there seems to be no quick
solution.
A new technology must meet three
demands before it can be used on a large
scale: it must be scientifically feasible; it
must be feasible from an engineering point
of view; and it must be commercially .
viable. f
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Nuclear power is one answer to dwindling fossil fuel supplies. Nuclear
reactors create heat by fission splitting apart uranium atoms. The heat
boils water to steam which propels turbines that generate electricity.
The first generation of reactors could only use a minute proportion of
natural uranium as fuel. Today, however, a new generation of "Fast
Breeder Reactors", fuelled by a mixture of natural uranium and
plutonium, create more plutonium than they consume, thus offering the
promise of virtually limitless energy. Below, the gleaming heart of the
U.K.'s 250 megawatt prototype fast reactor, which began to generate
electricity in 1975.
9
'rmtJSx
1**
!SS
;. ïifixrf
*
m +
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
7
Ï-'AV»» »*_
> » _» « é « » «r» * «r
i,««,«»
	,! C -
	
»ii i
IM -
i
I
Public debate on nuclear energy has focussed largely on the environmental and safety
problems involved in operating reactors, handling nuclear fuel and particularly in the
disposal of radioactive wastes. The proponents of nuclear energy point to the excellent
safety record of nuclear power and maintain that reactors are essential in a time of
dwindling fossil-fuel supplies. Others argue that the risks outweigh the benefits and that
no long-range techniques have yet been perfected for the transportation and storage
of nuclear wastes. Above, lead column for transporting wastes from a French reactor.
, The fast breeder has been scientifically
feasible for 30 years. To meet the second
condition, power plants of a scale big
enough to provide electricity for a grid
must be designed, constructed and
brought into operation. In Europe this has
been accomplished during the 1970s. The
prototype French Phénix breeder, with a
capacity of 250 megawatts, went into suc¬
cessful operation in 1974. Shortly after¬
wards, the U.K. 's 250 megawatt prototype
PFR reactor gradually came into operation
and is now at full power. The USSR's 1 ,000
megawatt BN 350 has been used since the
early 1970s, partly for generating electricity
and partly for desalinating sea water. In the
Federal Republic of Germany, the 300
megawatt prototype SNR 300 reactor will
be completed by 1981 or 1982, while con¬
struction work on Japan's Monju pro¬
totype is expected to begin next year.
France has taken the lead in this movement
by starting construction of its second big
reactor. Superphénix, a 1,200 megawatt
power station.
The fast breeder reactor has thus
crossed the threshold of scientific and
engineering feasibility. Other new
technologies solar power, fusion, and
new, large-scale uses of coal will go
through these phases, but the world eco¬
nomy into which they will have to be inte¬
grated will probably be different from that
of today. Because the fast breeder already
exists, there is a great temptation to
evaluate it exclusively in the context of
today's world energy systems. However,
we must look further ahead and not limit
our long-range technological options by
taking only short-term considerations into
acount. This means going ahead with the
development and deployment of the fast
breeder reactor, together with our other
long-range energy options.
Wolf Häfele
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Nuclear energy
and
the environment
Are present safeguards adequate ?
by Essam El-Hinnawi
NUCLEAR energy has been used to
generate electricity on a commer¬
cial scale for about two decades,
and it is estimated that it will constitute
between 11 and 13 per cent of the world's
total electricity generating capacity by 1985
and 20 per cent by the year 2000.
Public concern about the development
of nuclear power has focussed chiefly on
the radioactivity released from the products
of nuclear fission.
However, every stage in the "nuclear
fuel cycle" '- has ' some impact on the
environment from the mining and milling
of uranium, through the manufacture of
fuel elements for reactors, the transport
and processing of irradiated : fuel, to the
management of the wastes produced at
each step in the cycle.
The environmental impact ot. uranium
mining may take several forms. On thé one
hand, land and water may be affected by
spoil, and by 'waste water, (from mine
drainage and in some cases from drilling).
On the other, there are certain occupation¬
al health hazards.
Essam El-Hinnawi of the Arab Republic of
Egypt is research professor of geochemistry and
mineralogy at the National Research Centre,
Cairo. The author of two books and many arti¬
cles on these subjects and on energy,, he was
awarded . Egypt's State Prize for Science and
Technology in 1967. He is chairman , of the
Energy Task Force of the United Nations Envi¬
ronment Programme (UNEP).
Uranium ore contains radium-266. As it
decays, this element gives off the radio¬
active gas radon, which is considered to be
a major cause of cancer among uranium
miners. Nevertheless, it should be noted
that the number of "environmental deaths"
among coal miners (from pneumoconiosis)
is much higher than among uranium
miners.
In the milling process, about 70 per cent
of the total radioactivity contained in the
uranium ore fed to the mills remains undis¬
solved in the form of tailings ground to a
sandlike consistency. Radioactive dust
from unprotected tailings piles may be
spread by wind erosion. Such piles may
also cause, water pollution if they are loc¬
ated too near river banks or if flood water
leaches radium from them and then perco¬
lates down to the groundwater.
- In the fuel fabrication process, the main
potential hazard arises from the toxicity of
the hydrogen fluoride and fluorine used in
the production of uranium hexafluoride.
However, safe methods of handling these
chemicals are now well established in the
fluorochemical industry.
As the' level of uranium enrichment
increases,' so too does the risk of the acci¬
dental agglomeration of sufficient quanti¬
ties of uranium-235 to set off a chain reac¬
tion. Although such accidents are unlikely
to occur,' great' care is needed to ensure
that they never do.
The production of uranium dioxide fuel
elements is now a well-established proce¬
dure which seems to be free of appreciable
hazards. Manufacture of mixed-oxide fuel
is, however, much more complicated.
Hazards arise from the toxicity of pluto¬
nium and from the fact that the "critical
mass" of plutonium dioxide the smallest
amount of material necessary to start a
chain fission reaction is only a few kilo¬
grammes.: However, normal operational
hazards of mixed-oxide fuel production are
not difficult to manage.
' During the normal operation of a nuclear
reactor, radioactive materials are produced
which are for the most part retained within
the fuel elements. Compared to the risks
from gaseous emissions produced by
fossil-fuel-operated plants, the risks from
discharges from nuclear power plants
during normal operation are negligible.
Thermal pollution, however, is consid¬
ered to be more pronounced with nuclear
plants than with fossil-fuel plants. The for¬
mer reject virtually all their excess heat to
the cooling water, while in the latter about
15 per cent of the heat is rejected up the
smoke stack along with combustion pro¬
ducts. In other words, a nuclear power
plant will discharge about 50 per cent more
waste heat to the receiving waters than a
fossil-fuel plant producing the same
amount of electricity.
Public concern about reactor operation
has concentrated on the possibility of an
, accident leading to the release of a consi¬
derable, amount of radioactivity into the
environment. Various types of accident are
possible during the operation of a nuclear
reactor, but many safety devices are incor¬
porated into reactor design, and there are
operating procedures that will automati¬
cally close the reactor down in the case of
any serious malfunction.
: In -addition,' most reactors are placed
inside a containment building,' the purpose
of which is to contain virtually all the
radioactivity that might be released in the
case of a serious accident. However, there
has been some criticism of the efficiency of
these safety measures * (particularly . the
emergency systems for cooling the reactor
core).
' Several studies have been made to deter¬
mine the probability of a major nuclear
reactor accident, using information on the
failure rate of reactors'1 various engineer1
ing components. The most recent of these
studies, generally known as the Rasmussen
report (1), estimates that the probability of |
an accident due to the melting of the fuel in I
(1) "The Reactor Safety Study", was sponsored by the
U.S. Atomic Energy Commission and carried out under
the direction of Prof. Norman C." Rasmussen' of the
Massachusetts Institute of Technology.-
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
the core of a light water reactor is some¬
where in the region of one in 20,000 per
jreactor per year, and that 99 out of 100
core-melting accidents would cause no
early fatalities. It is also predicted that
about one in 170 core-melting accidents
would cause more than 10 early fatalities,
and that only one core-melting accident
out of 500 would cause more than 100 early
fatalities.
The arguments over the adequacy of this
study are extensive and complex. Some
critics have questioned the validity of the
methods used, the estimation of the risks
of accidents, and the factor of human
error. Others have concentrated on the
inadequate consideration given by the
study to the risks of natural hazards (such
as hurricanes or earthquakes), deliberate
sabotage or war.
Because they produce more fissile mate¬
rial than they consume (see article page 8),
fast breeder reactors have attracted consi¬
derable criticism. The intense neutron
bombardment which occurs in a liquid-
metal fast breeder produces changes in the
size of the structural materials which sur¬
round it. This can result in the swelling of
metals used in the construction of the reac¬
tor core. These changes in the tolerance of
the core can affect the coolant flow, and
they might precipitate the overheating of
the core and the melting of the plutonium.
0NOTHER problem which
plagues breeder designers
is fuel handling. Breeders
have the advantage of
generating plutonium, but
retrieving the newly-
created radioactive subs¬
tance necessitates much
more frequent fuel handling than is neces¬
sary in today's reactors. Once the pluto¬
nium is lifted from its birthplace in the reac¬
tor core, it must be transported to a fuel
reprocessing plant so that it can be made
into new fuel elements.
Should an accident occur a major con¬
cern of those critical of the liquid metal fast
breeder reactor plutonium could leak out
of the cylinders during transit. Another fear
surrounding the movement of plutonium is
that some of the material may be diverted
for use by unauthorized parties. Only a
relatively small amount is needed to cons¬
truct a nuclear bomb.
The complete dismantling of a nuclear
power station after its write-off period
(usually fixed at between 20 and 30 years)
will be difficult and hazardous because of
radioactivity induced in the reactor struc¬
ture during its operating life. Bombardment
by neutrons of the materials used to build a
reactor produces a range of radioactive
nuclides. Some of these emit highly pene¬
trating gamma radiation and have a half-life
(the time required for a radioactive subs¬
tance, to lose half of its radioactivity) of
several years.
Experience gained in decommissioning
small power reactors gives some grounds
for optimism about the possibility of totally
disposing of full-size reactors after their
write-off. However, the environmental
consequences of this operation are far from
being sufficiently understood.
The spent fuel elements removed from
reactors during refuelling are the most
intensely radioactive material in the fuel
cycle. The main hazard here is the enor¬
mous amount of gamma radiation emitted
by the decay of radioactive fission pro¬
ducts. The spent elements are removed to
deep tanks of water known as cooling
ponds, and left there for some time. They
must be stored in the ponds in such a way
that the considerable amount of fissile
material present in them (uranium-235 and
plutonium) is prevented from forming a cri¬
tical configuration. After the short-lived fis¬
sion products have decayed to low levels of
activity which takes a few months the
fuel can be reprocessed.
At a fuel reprocessing plant the spent
fuel is chemically dissolved and the residual
fuel material recovered. During this pro¬
cess the major portion of the fission pro¬
ducts, in addition to induced radioactive
products present in the fuel cladding, is
converted into solid and liquid waste mate¬
rial. So far, fuel reprocessing plants have
been the major source of radioactive envi¬
ronmental contamination from the nuclear
industry.
Low-level liquid waste produced during
reprocessing is eventually discharged into
the environment. Improved methods of
storing or disposing of this waste must be
developed. Reprocessing plants also pro--
duce intermediate and low-level solid
wastes. Reprocessing the fuel used in one
year by a 1,000 megawatt light water
reactor would produce from 20 to 60 cubic
metres of such wastes. ,
Until now most waste of this kind has
been buried on land or placed in canisters
and dumped in the ocean. The Nuclear
Energy Agency of the Organization of Eco¬
nomic Co-operation and Development
(OECD) is currently supervising the dispo¬
sal of 7,000 tonnes per annum at a depth of
4,500 metres in the Atlantic Ocean. Other
methods of disposal include deep burial in
abandoned mines or in suitable geological
formations.
It is estimated that by 1990 there will be
20,000 cubic metres of high-activity wastes
arising from the reprocessing of spent fuel.
Such wastes contain over 99 per cent of
the fission products present in the fuel
together with smaller quantities of actini-
des. High-level wastes are at present stored
mainly in liquid form, and some consti¬
tuents will remain dangerously radioactive
for several hundreds of thousands of years.
There is at present no generally accepted
means whereby high-level waste can be
permanently isolated from the environment
and remain safe for very long periods.
Processes for the conversion of high-
level waste to a relatively inert solid have
been : developed. Permanent disposal of
high-level solid wastes in stable geological
formations is regarded as the most likely
solution, but has yet to be demonstrated as
feasible. It is not certain that such methods
and disposal sites will entirely prevent
radioactive releases following disturbances
caused by natural processes or human
activity.
Nuclear fusion is the fusing together
at very high temperatures of two
atomic nuclei. When this happens to
the nuclei of light elements like
hydrogen large amounts of energy
are released. This process provides
the limitless flow of energy from the
sun. Scientists are today
experimenting with lasers to achieve
the high temperatures required to
reproduce nuclear fusion on earth.
Photo shows cables of laser fusion
apparatus at Los Alamos, New
Mexico, U.S.A.
Marine disposal of high-level radioactive
wastes has been extensively restricted by
international and regional conventions
which are binding on many countries with
nuclear power industries. Disposal in
Antarctica is prohibited by treaty.
During the entire fuel cycle, including the
transport of nuclear material, strict vigi¬
lance and care must be exercised to ensure
that such material does not fall into unau¬
thorized hands. An enormous effort is
therefore required, both nationally and
internationally, to Drevent any diversion
of nuclear material or sabotage ofnuclear
installations.
The establishment and implementation
of a physical protection system at the
national level is the primary responsibility of
Governments. At the international level,
the International Atomic Energy Agency
(IAEA) has initiated and implemented a
nuclear safeguards system.
The system established under the Non-
Proliferation Treaty (NPT) of 1968 has a
number of limitations and weaknesses: the
.failure of many states to become parties to
the Treaty; the inability of safeguards to
prevent the transfer of nuclear technology
from nuclear power production to the
acquisition of nuclear weapons compe¬
tence; the fact that many nuclear, facilities
are covered by no safeguards; the exis¬
tence of a number of loopholes regarding
the application of safeguard agreements to
peaceful nuclear explosions, to, materials
intended for non-explosive military uses,
and to the re-transfer of materials to a third
state; the absence, in practice, ' of safe¬
guards for source materials; the practical
problems of maintaining effective checks
on nuclear inventories; the ease with which
states can withdraw from the Non-
Proliferation Treaty and from most NPT
safeguards agreements; deficiencies1 in
accounting and warning procedures; the
absence of reliable sanctions to deter diver¬
sion of safeguarded material.
\ Nevertheless, the', Non-Proliferation
Treaty remains the most widely applied and
most effective international' nuclear safe¬
guards system.
Essam El-Hinnawi
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Mark Animan, Pans
Fusion power
Can we reproduce and harness on earth
the energy of the stars?
by Rende/ S. Pease
FUSION power has all the attractions
of fission power as a replacement
for fossil fuels, and also has a num¬
ber of potential environmental advantages.
The main problem, however, is that fusion
is still in the research stage and will not be
available until the beginning of the next
century.
Rendel S. Pease of the U.K. is director of Cul-
ham Laboratory, a major centre for controlled
nuclear fusion research. He is also chairman of
the International Atomic Energy Agency's Inter¬
national Fusion Research Council.
The research into and building of reactor
plants requires very high technology and
much capital investment. The International
Fusion Research Council estimates that the
cost of research and development will be
$15 billion. However, once (and if) achiev¬
ed, fusion should be very cheap to fuel.
Nuclear fusion is, in simple terms, the
fusing together of two atomic nuclei to
make one slightly heavier nucleus. When
this happens to the nuclei of light elements
(like hydrogen or lithium) large amounts of
energy are released. It is this process which
occurs in the stars and provides the limit¬
less flow of energy from the sun.
Nuclear fusion reactions occur abun¬
dantly only at high temperatures, such as
exist in the centres of stars. To produce
controlled nuclear fusion energy on earth,
the temperatures needed will depend on
the fuel, but even with the fuel we are
working on at the moment, which requires
the least high temperature, this must still
be about 100 million degrees centigrade.
The temperatures are so high that any¬
thing which comes into contact with the
reacting mixture (sometimes called plasma),
will melt. There are two methods, known
as magnetic and inertial confinement, for'
avoiding this. The latter, which is a rela¬
tively recent development (dating from
around 1970), involves storing the reactant
inside a miniature glass pellet, which is i
heated and compressed until the fusion I
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
7 w
Too hot to handle
at a hundred million degrees
Thermonuclear (fusion) reactions can occur only at temperatures
so fantastically high, around 100 million degrees centigrade, that
anything coming into contact with the reacting mixture (plasma)
would melt. The problem facing scientists, therefore, is how to
insulate the plasma from the walls of its container. One way of
achieving this is to hold the plasma in a magnetic field. In the
Soviet-designed, experimental "Tokamak 6" installation (above),
at the Kurchatov Institute of Atomic Energy, Moscow, the fusion
plasma is held in a doughnut-shaped container around which
coils are wound to create a strong magnetic field which stabilizes
the plasma. An electric current flowing through the plasma itself
heats the plasma and produces another magnetic field that holds
it away from the container wall.
<
©
o
£
k reaction occurs and there is a 'micro-
explosion" which is too small to,'damage
the surrounding reaction vessel but large
enough to give useful energy.
While results from inertial confinement
experiments are very promising, magnetic
confinement will probably provide the
quickest route to successful commercial
reactors. It is on this, especially the
tokamak-type confinement system, that
the bulk of research until now has been and
will continue to be concentrated.
The tokamak apparatus is shaped like a
very large American doughnut and the
plasma is held away from the walls by an
extremely strong magnetic field. The
plasma in the doughnut-shaped vessel is
heated by passing through it an electric
current of several hundred thousand am¬
peres. In experimental apparatus, tempera¬
tures of between 10 and 20 million degrees
centigrade are obtained routinely, and sus¬
tained for as long as the current, at present
up to one second.
Thermal insulation is provided by the
magnetic field, although in present appara¬
tus the effective insulation is still not good
enough for a reactor. The properties of
plasmas at 100 million degrees centigrade
are expected to be similar to those at 20
million degrees centigrade. There are thus
excellent prospects that when the larger
vessels and currents required for reactors
are used, the thermal insulation will be suf¬
ficient for nuclear energy production.
The exact relation of thermal insulation
to size and current is to be explored in the
next generation of experiments. These
experiments will also explore the raising of
temperatures towards the required 100 mil¬
lion degrees centigrade, which appears to
be a matter of improving existing tech¬
niques.
Only a very few fuels react fast enough
to be of any use to us. These are deuterium
(heavy hydrogen), lithium, which is conver¬
ted for use into tritium (an even heavier
form of hydrogen), helium 3, and boron.
The last two are involved in reactions
which are beyond our technical capabilities
today, and which we might never be able
to engineer.
In the reactor we are working towards at
present, the fuels are deuterium and tri¬
tium. Four-fifths of the energy released by
the reaction will be carried through to the
reactor wall by neutrons which are released
in the reaction. The neutrons enter a region
containing lithium and heat exchangers,
where they give up their energy and heat
the steam. The neutrons also react with the
lithium to manufacture tritium (which does
not occur naturally), which can then refuel
the reactor. The other one-fifth of the
energy remains in the plasma and keeps it
hot enough for the fusion reactions to con¬
tinue.
This reaction is the easiest to obtain and
also has excellent energy input to energy
gain ratios. Of all the fusion reactions it is
the only one which could occur sufficiently
abundantly in magnetic confinement.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The fuel reserves for deuterium-tritium
reactors are very considerable. Deuterium
constitutes 0.0033 per cent of sea water,
and the sea thus contains what is to all
intents and purposes an inexhaustible
supply of this fuel. Lithium is found in fairly
rich deposits of up to about one per cent
concentration in South Africa and North
America, and in salt lakes and mineral
waters. Using these deposits alone, which
amount to about 10 million tonnes, there is
enough lithium to release energy sufficient
for the next 200 to 500 years at the predic¬
ted rate of consumption, if no other forms
of energy are used.
Lithium is present on average in the
earth's accessible crust at around 0.002 per
cent concentration which equals around
100 million tonnes. If we were to tap only a
small fraction of this by exploiting lower
grade lithium deposits, we would have
enough for a very considerable
period. If, after achieving power stations
based on deuterium-tritium reactions, we
can proceed to design viable reactors
based on deuterium-deuterium reactions
(which is the next very large step), then
we have reserves for another 10 billion
years in the sea.
Not only is the fuel available in limitless
supply, but it is also extremely cheap and
easy to obtain, with a minimum of proces¬
sing. The extraction of deuterium from the
sea will result in very little land despoliation
and will in no way affect the sea.
Because the quantities of lithium re¬
quired are so small, mining operations
would be modest, less that those required
for the running of fission reactors and
vastly preferable to the strip mining neces¬
sary for coal-fired power stations.
The only chemical product of fusion is
helium, which is an inert gas. Thus there
are no reprocessing or dumping operations
of spent fuel or ash to worry about. But
there will be waste heat and some radio¬
activity, so that the siting of fusion reactors
would present much the same problem as
that of fission reactors.
Structural parts from the reactor will
occasionally need to be replaced. They will
have become radioactive and their disposal
will pose a problem. If the metals used are
carefully selected, these parts might have
activity which would last for about 100
years. Tritium is radioactive and will have
to be contained.
The reaction requires such special condi¬
tions that any imbalance in them will auto¬
matically stop the process very quickly.
Moreover, there will only be very small
amounts of fuel (up to about one gramme)
in the reactor zone. Consequently, the con¬
ditions for serious reaction runaway will be
absent.
The International Fusion Research Coun¬
cil (IFRC) has proposed the following time¬
table for research into fusion power. The
next six to eight years must be spent in
acquiring full understanding of the physics
of burning plasmas. After this we should
be able to demonstrate the net energy out¬
put from experimental reactors. This will
take between seven and ten years.
The next step would be the development
of efficient and cost-effective components
for demonstration reactors, which will be
ready in a minimum of 15 years if all the
necessary financial support is forthcoming,
followed by comparison of different reactor
systems.
Only then could the design and cons¬
truction of commercial reactors start. If all
goes well, the first of these may be ready
early in the next century. This programme
depends heavily on the degree of public
and financial support invested in it. We
have the necessary scientific skill and
enthusiasm to make rapid progress, but
progress depends on experiments which
require very expensive equipment. As sta¬
ted above, the IFRC estimate for costs up
to the demonstration reactor stage is $15
billion.
DOTH the time and the cost
of development can be
reduced by international
cooperation. Work on
magnetic confinement has
been completely open
since 1958, and this has
led to extensive and valu¬
able cooperation between the nations.
By 1960, for example, the Euratom coun¬
tries of Western Europe (1) started to work
together on a co-ordinated programme
which the U.K., Ireland, Denmark, Sweden
and most recently Switzerland have since
joined.
Co-operation with the Soviet Union has
been particularly fruitful in this field, and
critical measurements on the Soviet Toka¬
mak T-3 device by a team from the U.K.
which worked for up to a year in the
U.S.S.R.'s principal atomic energy insti¬
tute, proved to be a turning point in toka¬
mak research.
Another example of close international
collaboration in this field ¡s that between
the Soviet Union and the United States,
which has included such areas as the gen¬
eration of very high magnetic fields to pro¬
duce very dense and hot plasmas. The
most important recent example of interna¬
tional co-operation is the setting up of the
Joint European Torus (JET) project at Cul-
ham (U.K.) by the nine Euratom countries
and Sweden.
The purpose of the experiment is to heat
and confine matter to the temperatures,
densities and thermal insulation close to
those required in a controlled fusion reac¬
tor. Construction work on the project will
take about five years and will cost about
$200 million.
The United Nations plays an important
role in promoting international co¬
operation through its International Atomic
Energy Agency, which in 1970 set up the
International Fusion Research Council to
advise it on progress in and co-ordination
of world-wide fusion research.
Countries with substantial research pro¬
grammes report on their work and future
plans annually to the Council, where it is
subject to discussion and comment. This
process enables adjustments to be made to
improve the progress of research. The
Agency also operates small-scale specialist
services to aid the international pro¬
gramme.
The IFRC has published a number of
reports reviewing progress. In the most
recent of these, published this year, the
Council affirmed that the progress of
research is now such that the scientific
basis for building controlled nuclear fusion
devices with a net energy output from
deuterium-tritium reactions is no longer
seriously in doubt.
This conclusion needs to be proved, and
research has to be combined with engin¬
eering development to establish whether or
not technically and economically practical
fusion systems can be realized. The Coun¬
cil has also made detailed recommenda¬
tions aimed at achieving more concrete
International co-operation in the next
stages, and there are encouraging indica¬
tions that their hopes can be fulfilled.
Rendel S. Pease
(1) Euratom, the European Atomic Energy Com¬
munity, was set up in 1957 by Belgium, France,
Italy, Luxembourg, The Netherlands and the
Fed. Rep. of Germany in order to develop
atomic energy for peaceful purposes.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
by A. Ramachandran
and J. Gururaja
A. Ramachandran, president of India's Solar
Energy Society, is Secretary for Science and
Technology of the Government of India, New
Delhi, and director-general of his country's
Council of Scientific and Industrial Research.
J. Gururaja is secretary of India's Solar Energy
Society and director of the new energy sources
section of the Indian Government's department
of science and technology. He is the author of
some 25 studies on thermal engineering.
The sun
also surprises
From refrigeration to desalination
the myriad possibilities of solar energy
THE sun is the source of nearly all forms
of energy on the earth and there is
strong evidence that recent scienti¬
fic and technological progress in the collec¬
tion, storage and conversion of solar
energy will bring the widespread utilization
of this form of energy much nearer. Given
suitable conversion systems it could, at
least ¡n principle, meet the bulk of the
world's future energy demands.
The world's total energy consumption
equals the solar energy received every year
by an area of 22,000 square kilometres a
mere 0.005 per cent of the surface of the
globe. Even if a conversion efficiency of
only 10 per cent were achieved, global
needs could in theory be met from solar
energy falling on less than half the area of,
say, France.
~ln practice, however, the exploitation of
even a fraction of this energy presents a
colossal challenge to both technology and
industry. There are two major problems.
Firstly, although solar energy is abundant
and ubiquitous, its diffuse nature means
that it is expensive to collect and convert.
Secondly, it is not always available, and so
storage is necessary. Thus, cost-effective
technologies for collection, conversion and
storage must be developed.
The possible uses and potential benefits
of solar energy have aroused high hopes.
Grandiose schemes have been aired, such
as putting a few square kilometres of solar
cells in geostationary orbit and beaming the
electricity so generated by microwave to
the earth, and building solar power stations
(in the form of towers) of 100 to 1,000
megawatt capacity. Pilot studies on pro¬
jects of this kind are already underway. In
the industrialized world, it is estimated that
it will take between 20 and 25 years for
such schemes to come to fruition. For
most developing countries; however, such
schemes are an even more distant, and
perhaps unattainable prospect.
Other, simpler applications of solar
energy that seem more feasible in the short
or medium term are water and air heating
systems, distillation, industrial process
heat, small and medium scale power
plants, various systems and devices using
photovoltaic (or solar) cells which convert
solar energy directly to electricity, and a
number of indirect uses such as bio-
conversion and wind energy.
These applications, which are accorded
different priorities in different countries,
call for a variety of technological ap¬
proaches. In the developing world, the
major emphasis is on small-scale solar tech¬
nologies compatible with local skills and
materials, but such constraints do not
usually obtain in the industrially developed
countries.
Specially designed collectors which
absorb and transform the rays of the sun
into energy are a feature of all solar energy
devices. Such collectors fall into two
broad categories focussing collectors and
flat plate collectors, the latter being gen¬
erally used at low temperatures (less than
100 °C). Thermal energy used for heating
buildings (such heating accounts for a
significant proportion of energy consump¬
tion in the U.S.A. and Europe), for drying
various commodities, and for producing
hot water for domestic purposes, can be
provided by flat plate collectors.
Where high temperatures are involved,
focussing collectors are essential. Nearly
all focussing collectors require equipment
for tracking the sun and their surface must
have a high degree of reflectivity. Meeting
these requirements poses complex techno¬
logical problems.
Solar water heaters are already being
widely used in Japan, (where over a million
have been installed), Australia and Israel
(250,000) and are becoming increasingly
popular in the U.S.A. and some parts of
Europe. In the industrialized countries, the
need for domestic heating systems is well
established and its impact on the economy
is an accepted fact. In the developing
countries, however, the priorities have not
yet been fully worked out.
One view is that climatic conditions and
the life style of the vast majority of people
in the developing world are such that
demand from private consumers is relati¬
vely low and that the development of pri¬
vate consumption should not be given pri¬
ority. However, it is becoming increasingly
clear that a wide range of potential uses of
low grade heat exists in countries like
India ¡n rural industries based on agricul¬
ture, in dairy farming, in the chemical,
paper and food Industries, as well as in
public health centres, schools, canteens,
laundries, hotels, restaurants and other
commercial enterprises.
There is an enormous need for plant to
dry various agricultural products such as
rice, corn, groundnuts, copra, tea, coffee,
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
This prototype solar boiler was developed at
Genoa University's botanical research farm on
the Mediterranean coast of Italy. The array of
271 flat round mirrors (each of 0.5 square
metres) focusses sunlight onto a small
superheater boiler suspended from the stalk¬
like arm. Steam from the boiler is used to
operate an electricity generator.
cashews, chillies, grapes and other com¬
modities such as fish. The lack of adequate
drying and storage facilities is largely res¬
ponsible for food losses of between 20 and
25 per cent. Solar driers can be an effec¬
tive substitute for traditional methods.
Solar driers ranging from simple locally
manufactured cabinet driers to big blower-
driven models have been built and tested.
One such unit, capable of drying 10 tonnes
of rice per day, recently came into opera¬
tion on a seed farm near Ludhiana in India.
Preliminary estimates tend to show that the
cost of solar drying is much less than that
of conventional oil-fired systems and that
capital costs could be recovered in less
than five years.
However, only the industrially developed
countries seem likely to develop sufficient
productive capacity in this field, supporting
their efforts by marketing policies and fiscal
incentives. In the developing countries,
the lack of economic structures and manu¬
facturing facilities ¡s hindering the applica¬
tion of solar energy even in sectors where
its use is a viable proposition.
Energy from the sun can be used to cool
things as well as to warm them, and solar
refrigeration is another field in which rapid
progress could be made. It could play a
major role in the preservation of perishable
goods, reducing wastage and bringing eco¬
nomic stability to farmers who often have
to resort to distress selling due to lack of
adequate preservation facilities.
Development of community-size cold
storage facilities should be accorded a high
priority in developing countries. Although
various types of solar absorption refrigera¬
tion units have been made and tested in a
number of countries (the U.S.A., the
U.S.S.R., Japan, France and India) many
financial and technical problems still remain
to be solved. Solar refrigeration is unlikely
to be available on a commercial scale in less
than five years.
In spite of great technological achieve¬
ments, thq development of small engines
for solar energy applications has so far not
yielded positive results. The small engines
now available are expensive. Two kinds of
engine are currently being developed:
prime movers of one to three kilowatts,
capable of driving small irrigation pumps;
and medium-sized (20 to 50 kilowatt) pum-,
ping or power plant units for lifting irriga i
tion water. f
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
r Prototypes of both have been developed
¡n France and the U.S.A., and a few have
even been sold in African countries. One
solar irrigation pump developed in the
U.S.A. can lift some 50,000 litres of water
per minute to a height of over four metres. '
These developments indicate that there
is no dearth of technological potential. At
present costs are high and many systems
are too complex and hence difficult to op¬
erate under rural conditions. Thus al¬
though the development of solar pumps is
a priority target in many developing coun¬
tries, such engines do not seem to be desti¬
ned for widespread use in the near future.
For small capacity pumping of the order of
one kilowatt or so, photovoltaic cells may
prove attractive if costs are brought down.
Bigger units in the 10-to-50-kilowatt
range are more suitable for large farms, but
in developing countries power plants of
this capacity should be developed not only
for Irrigation but for village industries, and
other community activities. Only a few
experimental power plants in this range
(including a 10 kilowatt experimental solar
thermal power plant in India) have so far
been installed. A number of systems based
on a variety of technologies are currently
being studied. Technical and economic
data are not yet sufficient to enable us to
forecast future demand for such units.
The conversion of solar energy Into elec¬
tricity by photovoltaic cells is a particularly
promising technique. The manufacture of
such cells demands a highly sophisticated
technology but systems based on photo¬
voltaic cells are so simple to operate that
they are highly attractive to industrialized
and developing nations alike. . They have
no moving parts, last a long time, and
require little maintenance. Their capacity
ranges from a few watts to several kilo¬
watts. As things stand, however, costs are
still prohibitive for anything other than
highly specialized applications.
Nevertheless, in the last five years there
has been a tenfold drop in the cost of solar
cell electricity, which now ranges from $12
Solar power
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
n orbit
Beyond our atmosphere solar energy is
available in quantities up to 15 times
that which reaches the earth's surface.
The challenge of tapping this virtually
unlimited energy source has stimulated
the imagination and ingenuity of
modern scientists and engineers. Pho¬
tos 1, 2 and 3 show an artist's impres¬
sions of one audacious project for a
satellite solar power station currently
being studied in the United States. The
design calls for a massive solar power
collector, assembled in space, to be sta¬
tioned in fixed orbit some 35,000 km.
above the equator. (Unlike ground-
based solar power systems, the station
would face no energy storage problems
because the sunlight would be virtually
uninterrupted.) From this orbital posi¬
tion it would transmit solar power via a
microwave beam to a vast off-shore
receiving antenna (3) 10 km. in diameter,
on the earth. There the microwave
energy would be converted into electri¬
city and fed into the grid.
The satellite station itself would consist
of a vast array of solar cells (of the kind
now used in spacecraft and satellites)
mounted on two massive rectangular
panels each measuring approximately 6
km. long by 5 km. wide (1). Between the
panels is a circular microwave antenna
some 800 metres in diameter, which
rotates so as to remain always pointed
at the earth receiver. The solar cells
constantly face the sun. The satellite,
which would provide 5,000 mega¬
watts to meet the needs of a
city the size of New York would weigh
some 20,000 tonnes. Elements of a solar
power sky-lab could be transported into
space in the 1980s by the Space Shuttle,
but a much larger "Heavy Lift Launch
Vehicle" would be required to put cons¬
truction materials into orbit for a full-
sized satellite. When the basic materials
were in orbit, assembly would begin.
Photo 2 shows work proceeding on a
solar panel while (beneath it) a utility
vehicle brings more material to the site.
In photo 1 the assembled satellite heads
for its final orbit point, gently pushed by
a solar-electric propulsion system.
Photo 4 shows another project for a
satellite solar power station: a four-
segment array stretching 15 km. across
space. The round disc collects energy
and transmits it to earth in the form of
microwaves.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
/t\ :4x^^H¿S^
~i
û4^-^j^i\
Éj^Éj^fjnwLTjjiiwi » »Mu
A solar-powered water desalination plant
provides drinking water for the sheep of a
State farm in the Turkmenian SSR.
A solar air blower developed at the
Faculty of Agricultural Engineering,
Jabalpur, India. A reflector
concentrates the rays of the sun on to
the blower causing air to be sucked in
through the aperture in the base; the
heated air is blown out at the top of
the blower and directed at the produce
to be dried.
to $20 per peak watt ( 1 ) . This trend is very
encouraging and proponents of photovol¬
taic devices believe, perhaps rightly, that
by the end of the next decade, costs could
be brought down as low as $0.50 a peak
watt. This is also borne out by the results
of massive research and development pro¬
grammes and technological progress in the
United States, the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, Japan, France and elsewhere in the
past few years.
Major recent innovations include the
development of techniques for continuous
production of silicon ribbon suitable for
solar cells, the production of polycrystalline
silicon, improvements in the efficiency and
stability of solar cells, and the development
of Inexpensive wide aperture concentra¬
tors. Photovoltaic systems will thus be a
serious contender for meeting energy
demands at village level, in such fields as
drinking water supply, lighting, community
radio, TV and even small scale irrigation.
(1) Solar cells are generally rated in terms of "peak
power" how much electrical wattage they produce in
direct sunlight.
Another type of drier using a flat plate roof
collector installed at a seed farm near
Ludhiana, India. It has a drying capacity of ten
tonnes of rice per day.
A hundred horsepower solar power plant designed and installed at
Meadi, Egypt, as long ago as 1913 by an American engineer. The
energy obtained is used to power an irrigation system.
A solar power plant at Bouzareah, Algeria. The dish-shaped
reflector tracks the sun as it moves across the sky.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Solar energy can also be used for
cooking, but despite the fact that solar
cookers have been in existence for many
years, their success with the public has
been minimal. Current models ranging
from wooden hot boxes covered with glass
and insulation to parabolic reflectors and
other types of concentrators, all cook
effectively, but none seems capable of
replacing traditional methods in terms of
cost and convenience, and without inter¬
fering with the existing pattern of life.
Another application of solar energy is the
desalination of water. Here small family
size solar stills seem viable and because of
their extreme simplicity and the ease with
which they could be manufactured locally,
they lend themselves to extensive use in
rural areas of developing countries.
Sea water distillation by this method is
already being widely used in Israel and
some other countries. Recently a pilot
scheme producing up to 5,000 litres of
fresh water per day was installed in a village
near Bhavnagar in India, where the water is
extremely brackish. . At first the people
were unwilling to use water from the solar
still (because they felt that some vital ingre¬
dient had been removed!) but their reluc¬
tance was overcome when the word got
round that tea prepared with the water
required 25 per cent less sugar. All the
villagers there are 1,000 of them now
use the water for drinking and cooking.
In the last analysis, it is the storage of
solar energy which poses most problems.
Whatever solution is adopted, storage will
add considerably to the cost of the system.
As far as the future is concerned, inte¬
grated systems using various sources of
energy are an increasingly practical propo¬
sition. The possibility of meeting village
energy requirements by the combined use
of such sources as the sun, wind, and bio-
conversion should be seriously studied and
implemented on a selective basis. The
future trend in developing countries may
well be towards such autonomous energy
systems.
Solar technology is still in its early days,
and teething troubles are Inevitable. Since
it is in financial terms a high-risk activity,
many of the resources for solar technology
development will have to come from
government support and international co- >
operation.
I A. Ramachandran
and J. Gururaja
Model of a projected solar power plant to be erected near Barstow
in the desert region of south-eastern California, U.S.A.
1,800 mirrors will focus the sun's rays on to a tower furnace.
For centuries the Nepalese have dried their crops and herbs in the sun. Today,
according to a study by engineer Gyani R. Shakya, this traditional use of sunlight
should be extended by the widespread use of solar water heaters. Made from locally
available materials by local craftsmen, solar heaters have proved .themselves to be
efficient and economically viable. Already solar energy collectors are to be seen on
the roofs of scores of hospitals, schools, hotels and houses. Above, solar energy
collector being installed on a school roof at Godawari, Nepal.
The hospital of the Faculty of Medicine of Kinki University, Osaka, Japan, is supplied
with hot water by a solar heater which incorporates 1,856 tubular collectors.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Neptune's
power station
Ocean thermal energy conversion
offers an inexhaustible
and non-polluting energy source
by Richard Arlen Meyer
WHEN most people think of solar
energy they imagine heating
panels on roofs of houses and
other buildings. But actually the sun is
where all forms of energy (except nuclear)
originate. Oil and coal were processed by
nature over thousands of years under¬
ground, but they began by combining the
sun's energy with elements already present
in the earth. Solar energy is also the source
of the power of winds, waves and tides,
whose possibilities are now being Inves¬
tigated by researchers as sources of energy
which would not pollute the atmosphere as
do the fossil fuels, coal and oil.
Solar ocean energy, produced by the
process known as ocean thermal energy
conversion, makes practical use of the con¬
tinuous warmth of the seas, where the
sun's energy is conveniently stored 24
hours a day. Ocean thermal energy conver¬
sion takes advantage of the temperature
difference between the warm surface
waters of the ocean and the deep, colder
waters and taps the largest of the earth's ,
solar-thermal storage systems by using
heat exchangers that produce electrical
power.
The idea was first suggested by a French
physicist, Jacques d'Arsonval, in 1881. His
student, Georges Claude, another French¬
man, first demonstrated the concept on a
barge in the Mediterranean and later built a
plant in Cuba, in the late 1920s. These
experiments actually produced electricity,
but the cold-water intake pipes were des¬
troyed by a storm. Since, at that time, oil
Richard Arlen Meyer, U.S. zoologist and
oceanographer, is a specialist in the study of
solar ocean energy and its uses. He is editor and
publisher ot The OTEC Liaison, a monthly news¬
letter on ocean thermal energy conversion
published in Chicago.
was cheap and abundant, the power plant
was never rebuilt. Claude used seawater as
the working fluid in much the same way
that power plants today use steam to gen¬
erate electricity.
Today the United States has the largest
ocean thermal energy conversion pro¬
gramme, with government funding increas¬
ed from $700,000 in 1974 to an expected
$56 million in 1978, but other nations are
also active in the pursuit of solar ocean
energy. Japan has been working intensi¬
vely, since 1973, and a consortium of Euro¬
pean nations and firms is heavily involved
in research. At the largest conference ever
held on the subject, in Miami, Florida in
February of this year, 16 countries were
represented. The industrial countries were
there, officials from third world nations
seeking alternatives to oil, countries bord¬
ering on tropical seas, and even representa¬
tives from the oil-producing countries
themselves, since they know that their
major energy source is being rapidly
depleted.
Solar energy warms the surface water of
the oceans and other large bodies of water
to temperatures much higher than deeper
waters. This cold, deep water is brought up
to heat-exchangers where the temperature
difference is utilized and energy extracted.
Claude's system used warm seawater as
the medium (operating on only a 13°C
temperature difference) but modern scien¬
tists find that the use of other fluids, such
as ammonia, is more efficient. This was
first suggested, in fact, by d'Arsonval.
A prime advantage of ocean thermal
energy conversion is that power plants can
operate around-the-clock, and are non-
polluting. At present, such plants are plan¬
ned for areas surrounded by tropical
waters, but increased efficiency of the heat
exchangers promises a wider range of
potential locations.
The transference of energy from the seas
can be effected in several different ways,
the prime one being to send electrical
power to shore by undersea cable. While
this can be done economically up to 320
kilometres from shore, additional methods
of extracting energy are being studied. On-
site production of energy-intensive pro¬
ducts such as ammonia for fertilizer, as well
as other fuels and chemicals, and large
quantities of fresh water is also being con¬
sidered. Aluminium processing, which
uses great quantities of electricity, could be
enhanced by operating power plants near
the source of its basic raw material, bauxite
ore.
In addition to permanent anchoring of
the plants, either offshore or on coastlines
near ocean areas which have large tem¬
perature differentials, the concept of
"ocean grazing plants" is being developed.
These would be floating factories, that
would move to areas with the greatest tem¬
perature advantages, which change in the
oceans from time to time. Satellites are
already being used to map these locations,
and plot their movements.
By-products of ocean thermal energy
conversion plants make them still more
attractive. In addition to fresh water pro¬
duction, the largest potential apart from
electricity is the likelihood of creating pro¬
ductive fisheries in waters nearby.
The cold water pumped up from the
depths is heavy with nutrients, and re¬
searchers have found that sea life thrives
in such an environment. The Humboldt
Current, a natural cold-water upwelling off
the coast of Peru, produces a fishery that
supplies almost 20 per cent of all the
world's commercial fish. The marlculture,
or aquaculture, aspect of this new source
of energy is being enthusiastically observed
around the world.
While ocean thermal energy conversion
holds great promise as an energy source,
several problems remain. Marine organisms
cling to the surfaces of the heat exchan¬
gers, much as barnacles cling to boat bot¬
toms, but cleaning methods are being
developed to surmount this problem. The
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
In conventional electric power
plants coal, oil or nuclear fuels
generate heat which converts
water into steam. This steam
drives turbine generators which
produce electricity. In the ocean
thermal energy cycle no fuel is
burned and another liquid
medium, ammonia or propane,
is used instead of water.
Diagram below illustrates this
cycle. Ammonia is pumped
round a closed circuit. First it is
heated by the warm ocean
water (top of diagram) so that it
turns into vapour. The vapour
passes through a turbine where
it expands, driving a generator.
Emerging cooler and at a lower
pressure it flows to a cold-water
heat exchanger where it is
cooled further to become liquid
again and the cycle
recommences. Left, an artist's
impression of the surface
platform of an ocean energy
conversion plant. The cold water
pipe extends far below the
surface.
cold-water pipewhich may be as much as
20 metres across will pose transport and
assembly problems of an unprecedented
scale, and engineers are studying safe and
economical methods of solving them. Yet
the biggest questions today are not tech¬
nical, but political. Who would own and
operate the plants? Where can they op¬
erate without infringing on political boun¬
daries? How should they be regulated?
How should they be taxed? It is to be
hoped that this year's International Con¬
ference on the Law of the Sea will find ans¬
wers to some of these questions.
In 1978 ocean thermal research will leave
the laboratories, where efficiency of heat
exchangers, elimination of biofouling and
corrosion, and deployment of plants have
been studied for almost a decade. Late ¡n
1978 or early in 1979 the first mini plant will
be in the water, probably off Hawaii or
Puerto Rico, with a much larger plant
scheduled for 1980. Funding in the United
States and other nations has been increas¬
ing rapidly each year, although of all of the
solar energy options being pursued, solar
ocean energy has probably attracted the
least public attention.
Unlike conventional power plants which
produce pollution of some kind, solar
ocean energy is a clean source of power.
While extensive preliminary studies have
been made to determine the environmental
effects of such power plants, only minimal
objections have arisen. Sea life, while pro¬
tected from the intake openings by
screens, will actually be aided by the
nutrient-rich waters, brought from depths
where little life exists. Researchers have
estimated that, in the year 2000, if all the
power in the world came from solar ocean
energy the surface temperature of the
oceans would be lowered by less than one
degree, since the heat would be conti¬
nuously replaced by the sun.
The world's researchers are pursuing
ocean thermal energy development
because its potential as an inexhaustible,
clean, renewable energy source is tremen¬
dous. One estimate is that 180,000 million
megawatt-hours of power could be genera¬
ted annually from the Gulf Stream along
the "east coast of the United States alone.
This is about 75 times the amount of
power the United States will be using in
1980. Similar coastal areas suitable for solar
energy development could supply a subs¬
tantial share of the world's population with
electric power. With man's ingenuity and
persistence, it is expected that the oceans
will yield what has been stored there for
centuries: clean, inexhaustible energy from
the sun.
Richard Arlen Meyer
Liquid ammonia
"\
£=\ Warm
J^seawater
/29°C
Gaseous ammonia
Turbine
Q
Gaseous ammonia Pump
I
Liquid ammonia
J
Drawing ©RA. Meyer, OTEC
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Tapping earth's
fiery core
mWBm
by Ralph Haenel
Ralph Haenel, chairman of the Federal Repub¬
lic of Germany's commission on geoihermal
energy, is also director of géothermie studies
and deputy director of the geophysical depart¬
ment at the Lower Saxony Soil Research Insti¬
tute (Hanover). A visiting professor at the Berlin
Technical University, he is a project leader with
the Research and Development Group attached
to the European Community's Commission in
Brussels.
GEOTHERMAL energy, in its broad¬
est sense, is the natural heat of the
earth. .The temperature of the
earth rises steadily with increasing depth,
and if just one per cent of the energy con¬
tained in the upper five kilometres of the
continental crust could be tapped, this
would satisfy our energy requirements for
the next 4,000 years.
Unfortunately, it is not yet possible to
draw heat directly from the subterranean
rock layers. So far all that can be used is
the heat transmitted to underground water
deposits by these rocks. Thus geothermal
energy is currently only available in the
form of natural hot water or natural steam.
In 1975, geothermal energy was
supplying electrical grids with 1,191 mega¬
watts, and producing the equivalent of
some 6,340 megawatts for non-electrical
uses, such as the heating of dwellings and
greenhouses an overall geothermal
energy total of some 7,500 megawatts or
the equivalent of the output of seven large
nuclear power stations. In the last decade
the amount of geothermal energy used has
doubled every five years. There is reason to
believe that 15,000 megawatts will be pro¬
duced in this way by 1980; perhaps even
more if the energy crisis leads to increased
exploitation of the earth's natural heat.
So far the use of geothermal energy in
the form of natural steam has been largely
limited to volcanic areas where the surface
shows clear indications of underground
steam, such as geysers, steam or sulphur-
laden vapour escaping through fissures, or
hot springs. Today exploration is being
extended beyond these original sites.
The primary use of geothermal steam is
for the generation of electricity. The steam
emerges either in pure form, as dry steam,
or as a mixture of steam and water known
as wet steam. The wet steam is piped into a
separator, in which the water and the
steam are separated. The steam is then led
into a turbine connected to an electrical
generator.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
mmw
Geothermal hot water cannot be used
directly, since it often contains toxic or
dangerous chemicals. Instead, it is passed
into a heat-exchanger where it heats cold
water which is then used to warm a dwel¬
ling. Heat-exchangers -which can operate
with a relatively high percentage of un¬
desirable chemical content are already on
the market.
The use of geothermal energy derived
from hot water is still very localized, as dell-
very by pipeline to the user is not economi¬
cally viable over distances of more than five
kilometres. But when one considers that
about 40 per cent of all energy used in the
world goes to heat households and provide
them with warm water, this local aspect
takes on added significance. In fact, this is
one promising area for the replacement of
electrical current by geothermal energy.
Geothermal energy can thus only be
used on a large scale if the heat of the earth
can be transformed into electricity, and if
this current can be carried over long distan-
North Island, New Zealand, is
noted for its wide belt of
geothermal activity including
many hot springs, bubbling
mudpools and spouting
geysers. Left, steam surges
skywards at the
Whakarewarewa thermal
reserve at Rotorua, one of the
North Island's major tourist
attractions. Part of this large
geothermal basin is tapped for
steam to generate electricity
and heat homes.
ces and used for a wide range of purposes.
Up to now, however, only natural steam
from sites of comparatively recent volcanic
activity has proved suitable for this sort of
conversion. In most populated regions, it is
unlikely that natural steam suitable for the
production of electricity is available for tap¬
ping. This is. why other techniques of
drawing energy from the internal heat of
the earth on a large scale are now under
examination.
In the forefront of this discussion is the
Hot Dry Rock process which involves dril¬
ling down to high-temperature under¬
ground rock layers. Given a deep enough
bore-hole, temperatures of around 250°
centigrade can be reached. Since the tem¬
perature rises between 3° and 4°C with
every hundred metres of depth, this would
require drilling to a depth of seven kilo¬
metres. At this level, the rocks no longer
contain water: they are dry.
High-pressure water is pumped down
the bore-hole, causing the rock to crack,
producing a fissure stretching over several
square kilometres. A second hole is drilled
down to this fissure, as far away from the
first as possible. At this point, cold water
can be pumped down the first hole, to be
heated to between 200°C and 250°C in the
fissure, and then brought up to the surface
again by the second bore-hole. The reduc¬
tion in pressure during its ascent turns it
into steam, which can then be used to pro¬
duce electricity.
This technique was first tried out in Los
Alamos (New Mexico, USA). It was shown
conclusively that there were no problems
involved in making a fissure of the requisite
size; the difficulty lay in locating this nar¬
row and vertical fissure at great depth with
the second bore-hole. In addition, it has
not yet proved possible to regulate the
speed and quantity of water moving ,
through the fissure, and thus to control
energy production.
In the Federal Republic of Germany, the
possibility of extracting energy by means of
a single bore-hole is under investigation. In
the United Kingdom and Sweden studies
are being carried out on a Warm Dry Rock
technique, designed to tap the geothermal
energy of rocks at lower temperatures than
those called for ¡n the Hot Dry Rock pro¬
cess. In Iceland and the Federal Republic of
Germany attempts are being made to
bypass the creation of artificial fissures by
deep drilling down to natural fissures
already containing water, such as the main
fault deep beneath the Rhine basin in Ger¬
many.
Another recent proposal involves
breaking up large volumes of underground
rock by means of nuclear explosions. The
heat yield would be extremely high, but a
number of questions about this technique
have yet to be answered what would it
cost? What would be its effect on the envi¬
ronment? Would it cause earth tremors?
Successful exploitation of geothermal
energy will depend largely on reducing the
cost of drilling, but drilling costs rise expo¬
nentially with increases in depth. A bore- k
hole three kilometres deep costs in the t
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Volcanic gases spurt from a mini-crater (left) near the mining
centre of Chuquicamata in northern Chile. Lava has solidified
around the vent to form a natural chimney. Above, view of
geothermal plant at Larderello (Italy) in a part of Tuscany rich in
thermal springs and subterranean steam containing boric acid.
Larderello takes its name from a Frenchman, the Vicomte de
Larderel. who exploited its boric acid deposits as long ago as
1818. Today this thermal belt, which extends over some 200 sq.
km., feeds a heavy water plant and several power stations.
y region of $1,450,000, while one reaching a
depth of six to seven kilometres costs some
$9,750,000.
Studies are now taking place in the Uni¬
ted States on a process whereby the rock
layer is neither pierced nor fractured, but
melted. The 1500°C temperature necessary
for this can be provided either electrically or
by means of a small nuclear device
attached to the end of the drilling probe.
An entirely new idea a spin-off from
the Hot Dry Rock concept is to investi¬
gate whether additional energy can be pro¬
duced as a result of heat released by chemi¬
cal reactions. The aim is to set up a chemi¬
cal reaction with the hot rock within the
artifical fissure. The first estimates suggest
that the heat gain resulting from the use of
chemical additives would be of the same
order as the original geothermal energy
present.
It may also prove possible to exploit tem¬
perature conditions in the regions of the
ocean ridges, where upwelling magma
from the depths of the earth are constantly
forming new sub-bcean crust. Hot water
under pressure is also to be found in newly
formed coastal basins such as the Gulf of
Mexico. But in both these cases the condi¬
tions for exploitation would be extremely
difficult and any energy obtained would
have to be carried over long distances to
reach the consumer.
Clearly, a new and massive source of
energy is becoming available, though the
technology to tap it effectively is now in its
early stages. Time will tell whether or not
the subterranean heat bank ¡s a dead end or
a major breakthrough.
Ralph Haenel
Reaping the wind
Don Quixote would have
been dumbfounded by
this modern version of
the windmill with its
rotor 17 metres in dia¬
meter. As well as provi¬
ding energy directly for
grinding and threshing
grain, cutting wood and
pumping water, wind¬
mills are now being stu¬
died as a means of gene¬
rating electricity in areas
isolated from power
grids. This experimental
model, built at the U.S.
Energy Research and
Development Adminis¬
tration's laboratories in
New Mexico, can pro¬
duce 60 kilowatts in a 45-
kilometre-per-hour wind.
Photo © IPS, Paris
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
A come-back
for King Coal
by Vladimir A. Kuzminov
COAL represents 87 per cent of all the
known fossil fuel reserves of our
planet, and this vast store contains
six times as much potential energy as the
world's known reserves of oil.
Scientists have estimated that these
positively identified coal deposits, together
with those that may confidently be presu¬
med to exist, amount to 8,400,000,000,000
tons corresponding to a store of potential
energy twenty-five times greater than that
of the world's oil supplies.
In the unlikely event of mankind turning
its back on all sources of energy except
coal, and allowing for the annual Increase
¡n world energy consumption (which
during recent years has amounted to
about three and a half per cent), and for
unavoidable wastage, there would still be
enough coal to meet requirements for at
least another hundred years. In other
words, despite the fact that for a century
and a half coal has been the principal
source of the world's energy, an enormous
amount remains to be exploited.
The period since the 1950s has seen a
decline in the rates of extraction and utiliza¬
tion, with the result that coal now provides
no more than 30 per cent of the world's
energy, while oil and natural gas have |
taken over Its dominant role. I
Vladimir A. Kuzminov is a Soviet physicist
who specializes in the study of heat and mass
transfer and in world energy problems. He is the
author of two studies and a number of articles
on these questions.
Coal, one of mankind's most precious resources, is sometimes called "buried
sunshine" because the sunlight falling on swamp forests long ago is stored in it.
Most coal began to be formed between 210 and 280 million years ago, during a
time that geologists call the Carboniferous Period, by the slow decomposition
and chemical conversion of immense masses of dead trees and plants. Coal
sometimes bears markings of the plants from which it was formed. On this piece
a part of a fern-like Alethoptera plant can be seen.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
If all the world's known coal deposits
(as assessed in 1974) were piled up,
they would form a cube 21 kilometres
high more than twice as high as the
world's highest mountain. Small cube
(each side measuring 1.8 km) carved
out of upper right corner represents
total world energy consumption for
1975 expressed in terms of coal. Large
cube carved out at left (each side
measuring 13.5 km) shows the amount
of coal that would be needed to meet
all the world's estimated energy
requirements between now and the
year 2050.
Coal has fallen out of favour as a source
of energy, because, in comparison with
substances like oil and natural gas. Its
exploitation involves certain disadvan¬
tages. Coal-mining is a costly process, and
one which is not without risks as far as
human health and the environment are
concerned. Present methods of transport¬
ing coal from pit-head to power station are
labour-consuming and inefficient. Burning
coal emits harmful gases which are hard to
eliminate, as well as particles of gritty
matter, and leaves large quantities of slag.
^Furthermore, coal cannot be used, in its
natural state, as fuel for modern methods
of transport. All these factors obviously
inhibit any tendency to produce more coal
or to use it more extensively. -
On the other hand, some success has
already been achieved in overcoming cer¬
tain of these difficulties ; further research is
in progress, which should lead to a rehabili¬
tation of this age-old, well-tried source of
energy and of raw materials for the chemi¬
cal industry.
The large-scale mechanization and auto¬
mation of mining processes make extrac¬
tion a much less expensive business, and
reduce the health hazard to mine workers.
Underground gasification and hydraulic
methods of seam working make the future
prospects of the mining industry look much
brighter. Problems of transportation from
the mine to the furnace are being solved by
mixing the coal with oil or water and
pumping it through pipelines.
But the most important challenge
remains the improvement of the techno¬
logy of coal use. Radical improvements are
required if the heat-generating capacities of
coal and its potential as a source of energy
are to be increased without undesirable
consequences for human health and the
environment. Ways and means must be
found of ensuring that the replacement of
oil and natural gas by coal does not entail
substantial alterations to heat-generating
equipment.
Specialists believe that the extensive use
of coal in the future will depend on under¬
ground or surface gasification (i.e. its
transformation into methane), and on its
transformation into synthetic oil. Engineers
and scientists in many countries are cur¬
rently devoting considerable efforts to the
improvement of technologies for this pur¬
pose, which are not yet practical or econo¬
mical enough for widespread introduction.
It should be added that the production of
synthetic gas and oil from coal makes the
latter more competitive as a substitute for
natural gas and crude oil in the chemical
industry.
A large-scale return to the use of coal as
a source of energy thus depends on the
solution of a whole series of scientific and
technological problems; but in an age of
outstanding scientific and technological
advance and discovery, with every nation
striving to ensure that coming generations
will have reliable supplies of energy at their
disposal, these problems will all be solved
before many years have passed.
Indeed, solutions to some of them have
already been found and are being applied in
the mining and energy industries.
Soviet successes with underground gasi¬
fication and hydraulic coal extraction are
widely acclaimed while scientists and engi¬
neers in the United Kingdom, the U.S.S.R,
the United States, the German Democratic
Republic, the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, Poland, Czechoslovakia and many
other countries are making great efforts to
perfect the technology of surface gasifica¬
tion and the transformation of coal into
liquid fuel.
The increased production and utilization
of coal as a source of energy open up
favourable prospects not only for the
industrialized countries but also for those
of the developing world, particularly in the
Asian region, which has large reserves.
Coal can provide these countries with a
national supply of energy for social and
economic development, and above all for
their industrialization.
What role will coal play as a source of
energy in tomorrow's world? If it is difficult
to predict its future importance in specific
countries or regions, the analysis of the
potential which it offers in terms of energy
clearly reveals that tomorrow, and for a
long time to come, coal will continue to
serve the development of all mankind.
Vladimir A. Kuzminov
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Farming microbes
for food and fuel
by Jan Willem M. La Rivière
and Edgar J. DaSilva
Jan Willem M. La Rivière of the Netherlands is
professor of environmental microbiology at the
International Institute for Hydraulic and Environ¬
mental Engineering, Delft, the Netherlands. He
is chairman of the International Cell Research
Organization (ICRO), of the International Com¬
mission on Microbial Ecology and of the natural
sciences subcommission of the Netherlands
National Commission for Unesco.
Edgar J. DaSilva, Indian microbiologist, is a
staff member of Unesco's Division of Scientific
Research and Higher Education. He is engaged
in the promotion of the Unesco-ICRO pro¬
gramme on the use of micro-organisms for the
management of the environment.
MODERN agricultural practices are
causing serious environmental
problems through waste gen¬
eration and pesticide use and, furthermore,
absorb large amounts of fertilizer and fossil
fuel energy.
From research all over the world on
seemingly divergent topics, one highly pro¬
mising approach to these problems is emer¬
ging: fully integrated farming exploiting not
only plants and animals but also the enor¬
mous and flexible potential of micro¬
organisms.
Microbes are not only highly efficient at
capturing solar energy, but, equally impor
tant, they can help make room for the pro¬
duction of energy by biological means
because they are ideal instruments for
improving food production and for reduc¬
ing the wasteful use of resources. Last but
not least, they can expand agriculture from
land into water through aquaculture. Thus
integration has in this case a two-fold signi¬
ficance; the integrated use of all types of
living organisms also makes it possible to
integrate food, fodder, fuel, fibre and che¬
mical production into a new type of highly
economic, multipurpose agriculture.
This new agriculture will be character-^
¡zed by a minimum of waste of energy and f
Photo © J W M. La Rivière
From time immemorial plants, which combine energy from sunlight with water and
carbon dioxide to make food, have also served mankind as a source of fuel and building
materials, while animals fed on plants have furnished additional food. This microscopic
blue-green alga, Spirulina placentis, has for centuries provided the people living around
Lake Chad in Africa with supplementary protein. It was also harvested from lakes by the
Aztecs who ate it in dried form as a biscuit.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
, minerals, reduced use of fertilizers and pes¬
ticides, a much larger diversity of crops,
the use of aquaculture, and, most impor¬
tant of all, the utilization of biotechnology
both at household and village level and on
an industrial scale.
Microbes are not newcomers to the
farm. For thousands of years they have
played essential roles, although their
actions were not understood and their
potential was not fully exploited.
Almost all types of living matter can be
converted by special micro-organisms into
a mixture of carbon dioxide and methane, a
clean gaseous fuel which is easily stored
and transported. Besides this process,
known as anaerobic digestion, (so called
because it takes place in the absence of
air), there is the process of alcoholic fer¬
mentation in which carbohydrates are
transformed into the liquid fuel ethanol by
yeasts assisted by other suitable microbes.
In both cases the remaining waste mate¬
rial is rich in minerals that can be used as
fertilizer. Methane or ethanol can be ob¬
tained in this way either from waste mate¬
rial or from living organisms grown for the
purpose on land or in water.
Anaerobic digestion has been used for
half a century on a large scale in industrial
countries as part of the sewage treatment
system.
In remote rural areas in developing coun¬
tries where there is little hope of estab¬
lishing electricity grids in the near future,
biogas production from waste is of great
value. In Asia thousands of small blogas
plants of household to village scale have
been brought into operation over the past
10 years. India and Korea have 30,000
plants each, the People's Republic of China
more than 2,000,000.
The gas is used for cooking, lighting,
pumping, heating and refrigeration. Its use
replaces the old practice of burning dung
which caused local air pollution and wasted
a lot of energy and fertilizer. Since biogas
installations provide a hygienic means of
disposing of waste they have helped
reduce the spread of infectious diseases.
Furthermore, by offering an alternative fuel
to firewood they are counteracting defores¬
tation and its consequent erosion.
Among the land plants, sugar cane so far
holds the record for the highest rate of pro¬
duction per hectare 112 tonnes per year.
Hence this crop was chosen by the govern¬
ment of Brazil as the basis for its National
Alcohol Programme which is now under¬
way and alms at an annual production of 8
million cubic metres of ethanol in the
1980s, to be produced by microbial fermen¬
tation of sugar. Up to 20 per cent of the
alcohol will be used for blending with
petrol, the annual consumption of which
was 15 million cubic metres in 1975. The
rest is to be used as raw material for the
chemical Industry.
This large pioneering programme will
help make Brazil less dependent on oil
imports and will involve large sugar cane
plantations, extraction and fermentation
plants coupled to distilleries fuelled by
bagasse, the waste part of sugar cane.
Only a few of the thousands of known
plants are today used for crops; further
^,S.
TI
^ **'%. - V w^ / Sw«.
iV ^ / 1 -áEflJJ
/ * *Pm-
»
i ^
14 '" -WW- m\ *'É 5
JlflSC,
CO
c % '
Sjp, * i Ben 4'%
c
o \* IkTX !Fi3§£? ^aW.
> ^L JrJr j£
,^0r
¿ I f Wr m\\ mr*^ íJmmw Ï*
<0 ^Êj T ^'L ^ », f
? mwi j ' v " 71iS »
(- mj^ / i ¿ J
.2 MKmi à "kim BL - _ém
"£ \m ï im ^^mr I*^*î
3 ¿mt ^V ?6S
< m\ / .»
© >L \r .1
r ^v _<ß
O *C <r vr:
u 'tu*
m ir
i
U. If -' '
o w
<D
0.
o \i
o
o.
Photosynthesis on photo
The Austrian botanist Hans Molisch (1856-1937) was one of the great pioneers of plant
physiology. Photo of the great scientist, above, illustrates the mechanism of
photosynthesis, which is the ultimate source of all fossil fuels such as coal and oil. In
photosynthesis light is absorbed by a green pigment called chlorophyll. A negative of an
ordinary photo was laid on top of a leaf. The dark patches on leaf at right show where the
sunlight was prevented from penetrating to the chlorophyll. In "print" at left the effect is
reversed, the dark patches showing where the light did penetrate and starch was formed.
screening coupled with genetic and physio¬
logical study will no doubt produce new,
even more efficient, carbohydrate pro¬
ducing plants some of which will be suit¬
able for the exploitation of marginal,
hitherto unused, land. It is also likely that
the versatile fermentation industry which
became dormant after World War II will be
revived to produce, besides alcohol, the
Important chemicals butanol, acetone and
acetic acid, thus alleviating the strain on
oil resources from which they are now
derived.
The same result will be achieved through
increased exploitation of the rubber tree
and the guayule shrub for making natural
rubber. Finally, cellulose, the main compo¬
nent of plants, can now be made Into a
petrochemical substitute through new
effective microbiological methods.
Water cannot be ploughed, seeded and
weeded in the same way as land but its pro¬
ductivity can be much higher. The problem
is how to maintain a culture of water plants
or of microscopic algae in a steady state
without the risk of overgrowth by weeds.
Two different approaches are now rapidly
removing aquaculture from phantasy to
reality.
The first one focusses on the use of
natural weeds that already predominate in
polluted waters, like the water hyacinth,
which infests with its floating mats many
square kilometres of tropical fresh water
and is kept in check by expensive combat
programmes, mostly using pesticides. Tur¬
ning a curse into a crop, the U.S. National
Aeronautics and Space Association labora¬
tories have shown that water hyacinth
grown on sewage in lagoons can yield up
to 374 litres of biogas (containing between
60 per cent and 80 per cent methane) per
kilo dried material when subjected to
microbial anaerobic digestion.
This operation produces not only energy
from waste but also makes minerals in the
waste reusable for fertilizer and, in addi
tion, permits the withdrawal from sewage
of toxic heavy metal. Thus energy produc¬
tion and the struggle against pollution here
go hand in hand.
A further example of the use of water
plants is the farming of the giant brown
kelp, Macrocystis pyrifera which grows up
to a length of 100 metres, and with a daily
elongation of between 15 and 60 cm per
day is one of the fastest growing plants in
the world. It occurs abundantly on the
coasts of California, Mexico and New
Zealand.
The best yields are, of course, to be
expected in zones rich in minerals, that is
where upwelling occurs. General Electric,
with the sponsorship of the American Gas
Association and the U.S. Energy Research
and Development Administration, is now
embarking on a trial project on the Callfor-
nian coast in which kelp is grown attached
to rafts moored to the sea bottom. The har¬
vest of this marine farm will be converted
to methane, food additives and chemicals.
The second approach constitutes an ela¬
boration of one of the oldest and simplest
waste treatment practices, the oxidation
pond or lagoon as used all over the tropical
world. In these systems, bacteria decom¬
pose the waste into minerals which serve
as nutrients for the layer of microscopic
algae that grows on top and, ¡n turn, prov¬
ides the bacteria with oxygen, thus enabl¬
ing them to do their job. Normally, the
resulting slurry of algae is discharged into
the receiving surface water without cau¬
sing serious environmental problems but
still the energy contained in the algae and
their minerals originating from the
waste is lost to human use.
Workers at the University of California at
Berkeley have added to this system the
ingenious process of Harvestable Cell
Recycle. This solves in one swoop the pro¬
blem of the economic harvesting of living
matter and that of maintaining one particu¬
lar alga in a predominant position in the
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
pond. The desired algae can be separated
by a cheap filtration process and returned
to the pond, which is thus constantly
populated by such filtrable algae.
These algae, whose cells contain some
60 per cent of protein, can be harvested
and used as food, animal fodder, and feed
for fish, or (after anaerobic microbial fer¬
mentation) as a source of biogas and
fertilizer.
While this technique started out as a
means of waste utilization, it has also op¬
ened the way to bioenergy farming through
aquaculture on any scale desired: in princi¬
ple one and the same stock of mineral
nutrients can maintain a constant supply of
algae and hence also of methane. In this
way the intensity of the solar radiation and
the available water surface become the sole
determinants of the bioenergy-generating
capacity of an aquafarm. At present capa¬
cities of 80 tonnes dry weight per hectare
per year have been obtained but a further
increase is to be expected.
As mentioned above, microbes can help
plug the drains of present agricultural prac¬
tice by recycling minerals and converting
waste into useful materials. They open the
road towards aquafarming and may render
marginal lands more productive by making
a great variety of plants accessible to
human use. Furthermore, bacteria of the
genus Rhlzobium can fix gaseous nitrogen
from the air and thereby reduce the need
for nitrogenous fertilizer, the manufacture
of which requires much energy (see the
Unesco Courier, July 1975).
In addition, microbes that cause disease
among plant parasites are already used to
replace chemical pesticides for crop protec¬
tion and thus assist in attenuating the envi¬
ronmental hazards of Intensified agricul¬
ture. But perhaps most Important of all,
microbes can help set the world on a
course towards a more vegetarian diet and
thus reduce the agricultural capacity now
used for fodder production in favour of
food and energy production.
Single Cell Protein (SCP) can be manu¬
factured from a wide diversity of raw mate
rials ranging from cellulose, the main com¬
ponent of wood, to carbohydrates like
starch and even mineral oil. Microbes
made to grow on these materials enrich
their nutritive value by adding protein and
vitamins. In addition, they may enhance
durability and palatability. Already hun¬
dreds of such fermented foods are
available.
Exploitation of the microbe's versatile
potential for bioconversion thus provides
the new agricultural capacity for local
needs and changing markets. For ins¬
tance, the same crop of cassava can be
converted at will to blogas, to ethanol, to
SCP or to petrochemical substitutes accor¬
ding to prevailing demands, while in each
case environmental risks are minimized
through full waste utilization.
In building the new agriculture much can
be learned from time-honoured practices
found in developing countries. Using
microscopic algae for food, for instance, is
not really new. People living around Lake
Chad have for centuries obtained supple¬
mentary protein from the alga Spirulina,
and the same type of alga was eaten by the
Aztecs under the name of "tecuitlatl".
Even now a Mexican firm produces two
tonnes of dry Spirulina per day, which is
sold as fodder. The same alga is the major
food for the Tilapia fish and the flamingoes
¡n Lake Nakuru and other African Rift
Valley lakes.
The value of traditional recycling
methods used ¡n the rural areas of Asia is
also being increasingly widely recognized.
Far from being old-fashioned, the night soil
collection and composting systems of
China are models for the future. So are the
Indonesian village ponds in which wastes
are converted to algae which are then
eaten by fish.
At a syposium held in Bangkok ¡n 1977
more than 200 varieties of fermented foods
from all over the world were described. In
most cases they were prepared by traditio¬
nal methods from soybean, rice, yams,
potato, cassava, etc. Rich in proteins, they
can be used as substitutes for meat.
In this respect biotechnology ana
enzyme engineering have much to offer,
and genetic engineering applied to plants,
animals and microbes may not only boost
yields but may also increase the diversity of
renewable resources. Large research cor¬
porations and industries all over the world
are working on various aspects of the
problem.
The International Council of Scientific
Unions (ICSU) and its Scientific Committee
on Problems of the Environment (SCOPE)
have launched programmes on the produc¬
tion of renewable resources. In the U.N.
family, the United Nations Environment
Programme (UNEP) jointly with Unesco
and the International Cell Research Organi¬
zation (ICRO) embarked several years ago
on a project on the exploitation of microbial
resources, with special emphasis on rural
development in developing countries.
Wishful thinking of some five years ago
is now achieving tangible results in terms
of research, development and implementa¬
tion. Many hurdles still remain, but the
new integrated agriculture is definitely
underway.
J.W.M. La Rivière
and Edgar J. DaSilva
Seaweed
for food
and
fertilizer
On the Portuguese coast
a group of women and
children collect seaweed
for use as fertilizer. A
number of seaweed
species are also nutritious
and are considered a food
delicacy in some parts of
the world.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Hydrogen is the most abundant element in our galaxy. It
constitutes about 80 per cent of the volume of the sun and
on earth is present in vast quantities as part of the water
in oceans, ice packs, rivers, lakes and the atmosphere. It
is also the most abundant constituent of interstellar gas.
Photo shows part of the constellation Orion. Dark
projection at centre of the cloud of gas and dust is known
to astronomers as the horse-head nebula. Some scientists
believe that hydrogen is destined to become the all-
purpose fuel of the future.
The case
for hydrogen
energy
by T. Nejat Veziroglu
WORLD demand for energy is today
mainly met by fossil fuels, and
fossil fuels have some very use¬
ful properties. They possess concentrated
energy. They are relatively light for the
amount of energy contained in them. They
are easily transportable and storable. In
fact they can be stored for almost unlimited
lengths of time, without any change in
their properties. However, fossil fuels are
not renewable.
The new energy sources which are now
being considered do not possess all the
advantages of the fossil fuels, although
some of them, such as solar energy,
nuclear fusion energy, and ocean thermal
energy, are almost unlimited in amount.
Some are only intermittently available.
Solar energy, for example, is only available
during the daytime when the skies are
T. Nejat Veziroglu is Associate Dean for
Research of the School of Engineering and
Architecture at Miami University (U. S.A. ) where
he teaches advanced heat transfer, solar energy
and nuclear engineering. President of the Inter¬
national Association for Hydrogen Energy, he
was chairman of the First World Hydrogen
Energy Conference, in Miami Beach in 1976.
clear. Even then, the intensity of solar
radiation changes with time and with the
seasons. Hence solar energy needs to be
stored to meet demand when the sun is not
available.
Some of the new energy sources are
continuously available, but they are too far
away from the consumption centres. For
example, the best ocean-thermal energy
sites are in the equatorial regions. As for
nuclear power plants, more and more of
them are being erected away from the
cities or the consumption centres because
of the potential danger from radioactivity.
None of these new energy sources can
be used as fuel for transportation, with the
possible exception of nuclear energy.
Nuclear energy is being used to power
some ships, but as yet it has not proved
itself commercially. With the exception of
nuclear energy, none of these new sources
exists in transportable form.
The above-mentioned shortcomings of
the new energy sources point to the need
for an intermediary energy system to form
the link between the primary energy
sources and the energy consuming sectors.
In such an intermediary system, the inter¬
mediary energy form or carrier must be
transportable and storable, economical to
produce, renewable and pollution-free, if
possible.
It ought to be independent of the pri¬
mary energy sources used so that, even if
these are changed from time to time, the
intermediary energy system remains intact.
This would have the advantage that the
storage and transmission systems and con¬
version devices running on the interme¬
diary (synthetic) fuel would remain the
same, even though the primary energy
sources might have to be changed.
The above conditions are best met by
hydrogen. Hydrogen is plentiful in the form
of water in our oceans,- lakes and rivers. It
is the cheapest synthetic fuel to manufac¬
ture per unit of energy stored in it. It is
almost pollution-free, and is certainly the
least polluting of all the synthetic fuels
such as methane, methanol and ammonia.
For a given amount of energy, the
weight of hydrogen is about one-third that
of the fossil fuels. But it is bulkier. For a
given amount of energy, it occupies 3.4
times the volume occupied by petrol. Its
lightness, high flame speed and wide flam¬
mable limits when mixed with air (from 4 to
74 per cent) make hydrogen an excellent
fuel. Its high ignition temperature is a
safety factor. It is also non-poisonous.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Photo © IPS, Paris
Hydrogen ¡s a renewable or recyclable
fuel. After being produced from water, it
combines with oxygen to produce energy.
Its combustion product is water vapour
which eventually comes back to earth, in
the form of rain or moisture, to make up
the water used to produce it in the first
place.
Hydrogen can be produced in three
ways: (1) by the direct thermal method (if
water is heated to a high enough tempera¬
ture ¡t will spontaneously split into hydro¬
gen and oxygen); (2) by the thermo-
chemical method (chemical reactions are
induced which split the hydrogen from the
oxygen); (3) by electrolysis (a direct electric
current passing through the water releases
the hydrogen and the oxygen separately).
This ¡s how the proposed hydrogen
energy system would work. A nuclear
power station, situated for safety at a
remote location, a solar furnace, sited to
make the best possible use of solar radia¬
tion, or indeed any other new energy
source, would provide the power to sep¬
arate water Into its component elements
of hydrogen and oxygen.
The hydrogen would then be transported
(via pipelines or super tankers) to energy
consumption centres where it would be
used just as fossil fuels are being used
today. The oxygen produced in the plant
could be either released into the atmo¬
sphere, or be shipped or piped to industrial
and city centres for industrial use, for re¬
juvenating polluted rivers and lakes, and
for speeding up sewage treatment.
Hydrogen is a very efficient energy car¬
rier. For distances greater than 200 miles, it
is cheaper to transmit energy as hydrogen
through pipelines than as electricity via
overhead lines. In addition, the hydrogen
pipelines would need very little right-of-
way and take up no land area. Also, hydro¬
gen is storable while electricity is not.
In the hydrogen energy system, ¡t ¡s envi¬
sioned that hydrogen will be transmitted
from the production plants or the ports, by
means of underground pipelines to
industry, homes and buildings. There,
hydrogen can be directly used for industrial
processes needing heat, and for space
heating and cooking. For example, the
combustion of hydrogen produces steam,
which is used ¡n many industries such as
the paper and chemical industries.
Hydrogen can be used in the smelting of
iron, instead of coal, with untold environ¬
mental benefits. The electricity needs of
industry, buildings and homes, can be pro
duced by means of fuel cells. In the fuel
cells, hydrogen and oxygen combine, and
produce electricity. At present, the con¬
version efficiency is of the order of 60 to 70
per cent. It is expected that this figure can
be improved with further research.
Today hydrogen is from three to four
times more expensive than the fossil-based
fuels. However, studies indicate that as a
result of research and development work
now in progress, the cost of hydrogen will
be brought down while the cost of fossil-
based fuels will increase due to depletion. It
is probable that the cost of hydrogen will
be comparable to those of fossil fuels at the
beginning of the 21st century.
Many scientists and engineers agree that
the hydrogen energy system offers, both
economically and environmentally, the best
link between the new primary energy
sources and the user. It would be better
for the world to start converting to the
clean and , renewable hydrogen energy
system as soon as possible, thus protecting
the environment and enhancing the quality
of life. Once such an energy system is esta¬
blished, it will never be necessary to
change to another.
T. Nejat Veziroglu
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Bookshelf
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
AND PERIODICALS
Water Quality Surveys. A guide for
the collection and interpretation of water
quality data. Prepared by the Internatio¬
nal Hydrological Decade (IHD)-World
Health Organization (WHO) working
group on quality of water. A Unesco-
WHO co-publication. 1978, 350 pp.
(80 F).
Basic Education in the Sahel Coun¬
tries, by M. Botti, M.D. Carelli and M.
Saliba. A study prepared for the Interna¬
tional Bank for Reconstruction and
Development. Unesco Institute for Edu¬
cation, Hamburg. 1978, 130 pp. (8 F).
Elementary School Science is the
major theme of Prospects, Unesco's
quarterly review of education (Vol. VIII,
No. 1, 1978). Each issue 12 F; Subscrip¬
tion rates 42 F (1 year); 70 F (2 years).
Integrated Technology Transfer is
the theme of Unesco's quarterly Impact
of Science on Society (Vol. 28, No. 2,
1978). Each issue 12 F; Subscription
rates 40 F (1 year); 66 F (2 years).
OTHER BOOKS
World Energy Resources 1985-2020.
Executive summaries of reports on
resources, conservation and demand to
the Conservation Commission of the
World Energy Conference. Published for
the World Energy Conference by IPC
Science and Technology Press, Guild¬
ford, U.K. and New York, U.S.A. 1978,
247 pp. (£16 clothbound; £9.50 paper¬
back).
Planning and Plutonium. Evidence
of the Town and Country Planning Asso¬
ciation of Great Britain at the public
inquiry into the proposed uranium oxide
reprocessing plant at Windscale, Cum¬
bria, in summer 1977. Published by the
Town and Country Planning Associa¬
tion, London. 1978, 110 pp. (£2.00).
The Twenty-Ninth Day: Accommo¬
dating Human Needs and Numbers
to the Earth's Resources, by Lester R.
Brown. A survey of the environmental,
food and population problems facing the
world over the next quarter century.
1978, 363 pp. ($3.95 paperback).
Compost, Fertilizer, and Biogas
Production from Human and Farm
Wastes in the People's Republic of
China, translated from the Chinese by
Lee Thim Loi and edited by Michael G.
McGarry and Jill Stainforth. Interna¬
tional Development Research Centre,
Ottawa, Canada. 1978, 94 pp.
Climate and Solar Energy Conver¬
sion. Proceedings of a IIASA (Interna¬
tional Institute for Applied Systems
Analysis) workshop. International Insti¬
tute for i Applied Systems Analysis,
Laxenburg, Austria. 1978, 156 pp.
Brazil's International
Book Biennial
The fifth International Book Biennial organi¬
zed by the Brazilian Book Chamber will be held
at Sao Paulo from 11 to 20 August 1978 in a
pavilion (total area 30,000 square metres) de¬
signed by the famous architect Oscar Niemeyer.
During the Biennial, which is expected to wel¬
come over 700 publishers from all over the
world, there will be seminars, meetings and lec¬
tures as well as other cultural and educational
events. More than 200,000 persons visited the
last Biennial in 1976.
Smallpox:
$1,000 reward
The World Health Organization (WHO) is to
offer $1,000 to any person, anywhere in the
world, who reports an active case of smallpox.
The last confirmed case was reported in Merka
(Somalia) on 26 October 1977. WHO is conti¬
nuing its active search and surveillance program¬
mes until the global certification of smallpox era¬
dication, the target date for which is May 1980.
The Netherlands, the 44th country to provide
financial" aid for WHO's international action to
eradicate smallpox, is to contribute $1 .84 million
to cover the estimated cost of these pro¬
grammes.
China to take part
in global meteorological
experiment
The People's Republic of China has officially
agreed to take part in the first global experiment
of the Global Atmospheric Research Programme
(GARP) which will be launched by the World
Meteorological Organization (WMO) on 1
December 1978 and will last a year. It is expec¬
ted that all WMO's Member States will partici¬
pate in this unprecedented scientific programme
and that many will contribute observation
systems including satellites, aircraft and ocean
buoys. China's decision is particularly important
not only because of its vast area but because it
will put scientific research ships at the Pro¬
gramme's disposal.
The
United
Nations
and
Namibia
The United Nations Postal Administration has
issued a set of commemorative stamps on the
theme "Namibia: Liberation, Justice, Co¬
operation". The U.N. is conducting an interna¬
tional campaign to end South Africa's illegal
occupation of Namibia and in co-operation with
Unesco is helping to prepare for Namibian inde¬
pendence and train administrators for the future
state.
War on locusts
The countries bordering on the Red Sea and
the Gulf of Aden are waging war on swarms of
locusts which have reappeared in the region for
the first time for 16 years. It is feared that they
may migrate towards the Sudan or Kenya.
Insecticides and equipment worth some
$800,000 have been sent by the United Nations
Food and Agriculture Organization (FAO) as part
of its technical co-operation programme.
Modernizing
bullock carts
Indian scientists have developed a modernized
bullock cart on which the traditional wooden
wheels have been replaced with metal ones,
with the addition of bearings and new sup¬
ports. The new design, which is expected to
make transportation easier and ease the burden
of 26 million bullocks, will also reduce wear and
tear on India's roads.
Unesco medal
celebrates
South
America's
Jesuit Route
Unesco has issued a medal to support the international project to safeguard monuments and develop
tourism in those parts of South America which once formed the home of the Jesuit Republic of the
Guarani Indians. Paraguay, Argentina, Brazil and Uruguay, together with Unesco, are restoring build¬
ings put up between 1600 and the mid-18th century along what is known as the Jesuit Route.
Museums will be established, exhibiting art produced by Indian communities organized by the Jesuit
missionaries. The obverse side of the medal shows an 18th-century church bell (now in the Provincial
Historical Museum at Rosario, Argentina) and bears the inscription ORBIS GUARANITICUS (World of
the Guarani) UNESCO 1978. The reverse shows a carving of an angel carrying a maracas (a gourd
rattle) from a church at Trinidad, Paraguay. The medal is the latest in a series issued by Unesco in sup¬
port of its international action to save outstanding monuments and sites (Moenjodaro, Venice, Philae,
Carthage, Borobudur, the Acropolis) and to commemorate famous men (Michelangelo, Rubens, Aris¬
totle). The new medal is available in gold at 500 French francs (550 F with ring for wear as a pendant),
in silver at 150 F (160 F with ring) and bronze at 65 F (75 F with ring). The boxed set costs 750 F. Thé
medals can be obtained from the Philatelic Service, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Two Unesco studies on energy alternatives
186 pp.
65 French francs
A review of the latest research and developments in geothermal energy:
presents the various phases of geothermal work, from exploration and utilization
to geothermal economics and field management
features contributions from experts in New Zealand, the U.S.A., the U.K.,
Japan, Iceland and Kenya
offers clear diagrams and handy conversion tables
292 pp.
140 French francs
A survey of all the known ways in which the
sun's radiation can be converted into power:
provides a full and clear introduction to the
science and techniques of solar energy
focusses attention on the direct conversion
of light into electricity by solar cells
reviews "the latest research and development
Co-published with Butterworths, London, who have exclusive
sales rights in the U.K.
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (Sea list
below; names of distributors In countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch¬
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. - BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd , Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahnr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. onlyl: 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/München. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Capo Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. - HONG KONG. Federal Publications
IHK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Váci u. 22, Budapest V;
A K.V. Konyvturosok Boltja, Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. - ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co., H. F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub¬
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 51 1 C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedia
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomali No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstein's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachtat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. SangsteKs Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. - LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O.J Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Van Dorp Et Co. (Ned
Ant.), N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christ-church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. - NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana.
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Sarah Quaid-e-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda, Livraria
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mah".
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, ¡
Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street,
P O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir 8ookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Fórbundet, Skolgránd 2,
Box, 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 12-236. -
TANZANIA. Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen
Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok:
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY.
Libraire Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
- UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Station,
New York, N.Y. 10016. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Iceland, one of the world's most active volcanic regions, is a land of vast subterranean thermal ac¬
tivity in the form of hot springs and steaming geysers as well as volcanic eruptions. Below, glowing
lava bursting from the crater of Eldfell, near the town of Heimaey when the volcano erupted in 1973.
Geothermal energy the earth's natural heat is today being tapped by Iceland, New
Zealand and a number of other countries, which use natural hot water or steam for conversion
into electricity or as a means of domestic heating. Deep-drilling experiments are now being carried
out with a view to exploiting geothermal energy on an even larger scale. (See article page 24).
m,
]]>
</page>
</document>
