<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074807eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window
open on the world
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
(^
Republic
of Korea
Match of miniatures
These stoneware figurines of a man (8.2 cms high) and a woman (5.3 cms) were fashioned in the 5th or
6th century A.D., during the period of the Silla dynasty in Korea. Silla potters displayed acute powers of
observation and sometimes a puckish sense of humour when creating such clay figurines and sculpted
ceramic vessels. As well as depicting the human form, they also portrayed animals such as rabbits,
dogs, cows, pigs, tigers, tortoises and snakes.
Photo © Kim Tae-byok, Seoul
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
DECEMBER 1978 31st YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 19 LANGUAGES
English Italian Turkish
French Hindi Urdu
Spanish Tamil Catalan
Russian Hebrew Malaysian
German Persian Korean
Arabic Dutch
Japanese Portuguese
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year : 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's Issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering post¬
age. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions
and headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (microfilm
and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms (Xerox).
Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (2) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th Street.
New York. U.S.A.; (3) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mans¬
field Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H.W. Wilson
Co., New York, and in Current Contents - Education,
Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris - France
Editor-in-chief
Assistant Editor-in-chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editor : Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
Edition: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Edition:
Edition
Edition
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese.
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
Edition: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Edition: Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Edition: H.L. Sharma (Delhi)
Edition: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Edition: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Edition: Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Edition: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese Edition: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istambul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Cristian Rahola (Barcelona)
Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Lim Moun-young (Seoul)
Turkish Edition:
Urdu Edition:
Catalan Edition:
Malaysian Edition:
Korean Edition:
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Djamel Benstaali
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
page
~4 SPIRITUAL LANDSCAPE OF TRADITIONAL KOREA
by Chang Byung-kil
11 200 years before Gutenberg
THE MASTER PRINTERS OF KORYO
by Ch'on Hye-bong
Ï3 THE KOREAN ALPHABET-
A GRAPHIC PORTRAIT OF THE HUMAN VOICE
by Lee Kl-mun
14 ORIENTAL OCTET
16 The wall paintings of Koguryo :
A FRESCO OF DAILY LIFE
19 KOREAN PAINTING-
AN ORIGINAL CONTRIBUTION TO ORIENTAL ART
by Ch'oe Sun-u
22 THE UNICORN, THE PHOENIX AND THE FLYING HORSE
Recent discoveries from three ancient royal tombs
by Kim Won-yong
31 IMMORTAL CLAY
The traditional pottery of Korea
by Chong Yang-mo
32 THE STONES OF SOKKURAM
A cornucopia of Buddhist sculpture
in a 1200-year-old temple-grotto
by Hwang Su-young
35 A PRACTICAL APPROACH TO SCIENCE
by Jeon Sang-woon
38 SIX GOOD TURNS FROM THE TURTLE
by Zo Za-Yong
40 PAINTINGS MAGIC AND MUNDANE
Folk art with a wealth of significance for everyday life
by Zo Za-Yong
44 AN AUREOLE OF LEGEND ON A GOLDEN CROWN
by Li Ogg
50 UNESCO'S GENERAL CONFERENCE
~2 TREASURES OF WORLD ART
REPUBLIC OF KOREA: Match of miniatures
Cover
To its own people Korea is best known as
Chosun, often translated as "land of the
morning calm". The Western name, Korea, Is
derived from the Koryo dynasty which ruled
the country from 918 to 1392 (Koryo may be
translated as "high and beautiful"). Although
the course of Korean history has been
strongly influenced by the country's location
between Its two mighty neighbours, China
and Japan, Korean culture has retained a
distinctive quality of its own and numbers
many unique accomplishments in the arts,
science and technology. This issue of the
Unesco Courier examines some of the more
Important facets of the ancient Korean
cultural tradition, thus contributing to
Unesco's activities in recording, interpreting
and preserving the cultures of Asia. Cover
shows portrait of Yi Chae, a scholar-official
of the Yi dynasty, by an unknown 18th-
century painter.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Spiritual landscape
of traditional Korea
by Chang Byung-kil
THOUSANDS of years ago, according
to ancient legend which archaeolo¬
gical research and linguistic studies
seem to confirm, tribes inhabiting the Altai
Mountains started migrating eastwards
across Siberia and Manchuria. Some of
them, believed to be of Tungu origin,
travelled as far as the Korean peninsula.
They liked what they saw and from the
third millennium B.C. they moved into the
peninsula and settled there to become the
dominant ethnic group.
The primitive Korean, a hunter-fisher,
was much bewildered by the way in which
things around him behaved. He wondered
if those things too had spirits as he did.
His attempt to understand and come to
terms with his environment eventually evol¬
ved into a nature-belief that powerful spi¬
rits resided in the natural forces and ani¬
mate and inanimate objects surrounding
. him. Thus when the hunter had to kill an
animal for food, he performed a rite invo¬
king the approval of the totem spirit of the
victim he was going to hunt. And when the
farmers wished for a good harvest, they
held ceremonies which were intended to
propitiate the local gods of field and forest.
For personal as opposed to social needs,
the individual required an intermediary with
the spirit world who could avert or cure'
sickness and bad luck, and assure a propi¬
tious passage from this world to the next
when the time came. Such a priestlike indi¬
vidual, known as a shaman, would be cal¬
led upon to perform the requisite rituals.
The myth of national foundation embo¬
died in Korea's oldest religion, Taejong-
gyo, is comparable to those of other Altaic
peoples.
Taejong-gyo is about 4,000 years old,
and embodies the concept of a triune god:
creator, teacher, and temporal king, whose
name is Hanul. This god took human form
in the person of Tan'gun, the father,
teacher, and king of the Korean people,
CHANG BYUNG-KIL is professor of religion at
Seoul National University. His writings on the
history of Korean religions include an important
contribution to A Handbook of Korea, Seoul,
1978.
who descended from heaven onto the
highest peak in Korea, presumably Mt.
Paektu, in 2333 B.C. Until recent times
Korean calendars and dates were reckoned
from this year.
Tan'gun became the great teacher and
law-giver of the tribes he found living in the
Korean Peninsula, reigning over them for
ninety-three years until he reascended to
heaven.
The tribal communities gradually develo¬
ped into kingdoms. By the first century
B.C., there were three such kingdoms in
Korea, namely Koguryo, Paekche and Silla.
Religious rituals common to these tribal
states included a service directed at propi¬
tiating heaven.
The tribal rituals, conducted by the chief¬
tains, who were regarded as "messengers
of the Heavenly Emperor", were strongly
established among nobles and commoners
alike by the time of the Three Kingdoms
period, but with the introduction of foreign
religions, purity in the practice of Taejong-
gyo gradually declined. By the fifteenth
century, this cult as such had practically
disappeared.
It was during the Three Kingdoms era! 57
B.C. 668 A.D.) that more sophisticated
religions began to flow into Korea from
China. When Taoism, Confucianism and
Buddhism came to Korea, one after ano¬
ther, they were readily accepted and there
was no sense of conflict between them or
of opposition to rites relating to local
nature-spirits.
It is difficult to pinpoint the exact date
when Taoism, as philosophy and religion,
came to influence Korea. Mural paintings
found in Koguryo tumuli near Kangso,
Pyongan Province, show Taoist influence.
Records indicate that the teachings of Lao
Tzu and Chuang Tzu were brought to
Korea in the seventh century A.D., and
that there was some active effort to study
them. Even Buddhist temples were conver¬
ted to Taoist temples as Koguryo's power
began to weaken.
In Paekche too, there was a trend toward
believing in Taoist spirit beings. But the
strongest imprint of Taoist influence can be
discerned in the guiding principles of the
Hwarang elite corps of Silla, who were trai
ned in patience, simplicity, contentment,
and harmonyall part and parcel of Taoist
ethicsalong with the Confucian doctrine
of loyalty, filial piety, righteousness, and
faith, and the Buddhist teaching of com¬
passion.
Although Taoism failed to proliferate as
an independent cult, it nevertheless conti¬
nued to permeate all strata of the Korean
populace.
The most apparent trace of Taoist
influence among the Koreans is the search
for blessings and longevity, the strongest
of Taoist features. One may observe the
indelible Taoist mark in the two Chinese
characters, su (longevity) and pok (bles¬
sings, or bliss, or happiness), which are
used to decorate so many everyday articles
such as spoons and pillow cases. Should
one ask an elderly Korean what constitute
the ultimate blessings, he would most
unhesitatingly answer, "Longevity, happi¬
ness, health, wealth, and the begetting of
children".
At the time Buddhism entered Korea in
the fourth century A.D., the peninsula was
drawing toward the middle of the Three
Kingdoms period, and was about to be uni¬
fied as a single nation under the southern¬
most kingdom, Silla. For geographical rea¬
sons primarily. Silla was the last of the
three to be penetrated by the foreign reli¬
gion. Koguryo, the northern kingdom, was
visited by a Chinese monk named Sundo in
the year 372 A.D., and a dozen years later,
neighbouring Paekche played host to an
Indian missionary, Marnananta, who had
come by way of China.
Silla did not begin to receive Buddhist
influence until about half a century later,
and it was only in 528 A.D. that it became
legal to preach Buddhism openly there,
after the miraculous martyrdom of the
saintly Yi Cha-don.
Meanwhile, the new religion must have
, spread like wildfire in the two northern
kingdoms, apparently under royal patro¬
nage. Many temples and monasteries were
constructed, and hordes of believers con¬
verted. So rapidly and deeply rooted did
Buddhism become in Paekche and
Koguryo, in fact, that by the sixth century
priests, scriptures, and religious artisans
CONTINUED PAGE 9
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
These two granite bodhisattvas ("future Buddhas") discovered near Kyongju,
capital of the ancient Korean kingdom of Silla, were carved some 1300 years
ago. The serenity of Buddhism is inscribed In their kindly, smiling faces.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Deep in meditation, a sage
(above) gazes at flowing
water In a work by Kang Huí¬
an (1419-1465). Calligraphier,
poet and functionary as well
as a painter, Kang Hui-an
visited China where he was
influenced by the Ming
tradition of Confucian art.
The god of longevity, Susong
Noln (right) was one of the
Taoist figures often depicted
by Korean artists. In this ink
painting by the court artist
Kim Myong-guk (1623-1650),
the god's alert and vigorous
features are delineated in a
style characteristic of 17th-
century literati painting.
Colour page
Maitreya
in meditation
According to Buddhist teaching which
spread from India to Tibet, China, Korea
and Japan, bodhisattvas are individuals
destined to attain the Enlightenment of
the Buddha in this or another life. In
Mahayana (Great Vehicle) Buddhism they
postpone their own final entrance into
Nirvana in order to alleviate the sufferings
of others, whom they help by perfecting
in themselves the six virtues of
generosity, morality, patience, vigour,
concentration (in meditation), and
wisdom. Highly revered throughout the
Buddhist world, the bodhisattva Maitreya
is here depicted in a gilt bronze sculpture
dating from around 600 A.D., the period of
the Three Kingdoms In Korea. Features
such as the square jaw and bulging
cheeks suggest that it may have been
made in the south of the Korean
peninsula. The artist has succeeded in
conveying an impression of spontaneity
and grace in a figure which is deep in
meditation.
Photo © Yi, Paris, National Museum of Korea, Seoul
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
n
*y
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
and artifacts were being sent to Japan, for¬
ming the basis of the early Buddhist culture
there. Much of the prestige attached to the
new cult in Korea, and its eventual adop¬
tion as the state religion in all of the Three
Kingdoms may be traced to the Koreans'
high respect for Chinese learning.
By the time Silla unified the peninsula
under one government in 670 A.D. Bud¬
dhism had been established there too as
the State religion, though governmental
systems were already being run along Con¬
fucian lines, with no conflict between the
two.
Royal patronage during this brief Golden
Age of Unified Silla produced a magnifi¬
cent flowering of Buddhist arts and temple
architecture; and the rapid fragmentation
of the kingdom after less than 200 years did
not harm the position of the Buddhist
church either, since the succeeding Koryo
Colour page
Millennial home
of Holy Writ
Located In a remote spot on the beautiful
tree-covered slopes of Mount Kaya in the
southeast of the Korean peninsula, the
temple of Haein-sa is famed as the
repository of the set of thirteenth century
woodblocks used for printing the
Tripitaka, a sacred Buddhist scripture. The
81,240 blocks of the "Tripitaka Koreana"
are one of the most outstanding
monuments of Korean cultural history.
Founded in the year 802 by two monks,
Sunung and Ijong, the temple was built by
King Aeja of the Silla dynasty. The
monarch Is said to have been converted to
Buddhism and ruled his people from
Haein-sa, In whose grandiose setting
monks still carry on the tradition of
worship begun over a thousand years ago.
Photo © Korean Overseas Information Service, Seoul
dynasty which took power in 936 A.D. was
even more enthusiastic in its support of the
imported doctrine.
Out of many famous monks and theolo¬
gians of the Silla era, possibly the most
influential was Wonhyo, though he was
the only clerical leader of that day who did
not study in China. Wonhyo tried to unify
the various sectarian rivalries among Bud¬
dhists, and sought to make the religion
popular and applicable to the daily lives of
the people. He wrote many books, and
legend ascribes to him a brief love affair
with a royal princess the son of their
union being supposedly the scholar who
invented the system of writing Korean in
Chinese ideographs called idu.
During the Koryo dynasty, priests
became politicians and courtiers, some of
them corrupt or worldly in their interests.
When in the thirteenth century the Mon¬
gols invaded Korea, conquering and rava¬
ging the entire nation except for the Han
River estuary island of Kanghwa where the
king and the court took refuge, the Bud¬
dhists took their share in the blame for the
national disaster. From this era may be
dated a definite and rapid decline in Korean
Buddhism.
When Yi Song-gye staged a revolt and
had himself proclaimed king in 1392, his
policy was both anti-Mongol and anti-
Buddhist. All influence of the religion was
removed from the government. Vast
wealth and land holdings of temples were
seized and Confucianism became the State
religion.
Confucianism had, in fact, first become
established in Korea very much earlier.
Confucian texts had entered the peninsula
well before the beginning of the Christian
era and all the Three Kingdoms left records
that indicate the early existence of Confu¬
cian influence. In Koguryo, for example,
there was a central Confucian university
functioning by the fourth century A.D.,
arguing a long and deeply-rooted tradition
already in existence: while the province had
scattered private Confucian academies cal¬
led Kyongdang.
The neighbouring kingdom of Paekche
seems to have established similar institu¬
tions at about the same time: as usual, the
southernmost kingdom of Silla was a little
later in importing the foreign influence. But
when in the seventh century A.D., Silla
conquered and absorbed the others, her
interest in Confucianism and other aspects
of Chinese culture rapidly increased. Dele¬
gations of scholars were sent to China to
observe the workings of Confucian institu¬
tions at first hand, and to bring back volu¬
minous writings on the subject. Though
Buddhism was the state religion of Unified
Silla, Confucianism formed the philosophi¬
cal and structural backbone of the State.
In Korea, Confucianism was accepted so
eagerly and in so strict a form that the Chi¬
nese themselves regarded the Korean
adherents as more virtuous than them¬
selves, and referred to Korea as "the
country of eastern decorum," referring to
the punctiliousness with which the
Koreans observed all phases of the doctri¬
nal ritual.
The overthrow of the Koryo dynasty in
1392 marked the beginning of a Confucian
renaissance. In the fifteenth and sixteenth
centuries, under rulers who were generally
enlightened or themselves scholars, there
was indeed considerable progress in social
reform, modernization, and justice. It was
an era of inventions, culminating in the
development of an exact phonetic system
for transcribing the Korean language, cal¬
led Han'gul (see article page 13).
Confucianism produced a new crop of
philosophers starting in the seventeenth
century called the Sirhak or Practical Lear¬
ning School, whose concern was less aca¬
demic than utilitarian. Perhaps under the
influence of Western ideas filtering into
Korea indirectly via the Jesuit missionaries
then active in China, there arose a new
interest among the literati in such matters
as national productivity and defence, agri¬
culture, trade, and welfare of the general
populace.
Confucianism in Korea meant a system
of education, ceremony, and civil adminis¬
tration. With the passing of the monarchi¬
cal system in the early twentieth century,
only the first function remained important.
However, the deeply ingrained Confucian
mode of manners and social relations is still
a major factor in the way Koreans think and
act.
The tide of Christian mission activity
began to turn toward Korea as early as the
seventeenth century, when copies of
Catholic missionary Matteo Ricci's works in
Chinese were brought back from Peking by
the annual tributary mission sent there to
exchange gifts with the Chinese emperor.
In Korea, the missionaries, especially the
late-arriving Protestants, came as bearers
of modern knowledge in every field, filling a
vacuum which the isolated, indrawn
Korean nation desperately needed filled if it
were to attain that modernization which
might assure its continued independence.
The missionaries arranged for the advan¬
ced education abroad of many of Korea's
young potential leaders, and stood shoul¬
der to shoulder with patriotic resistance
to Japan's encroachments upon Korean
sovereignty.
The Tonghak movement, which arose in
the mid-nineteenth century in response to
many complex social factors, was in a
sense a reaction against Catholicism,
which was called "Western Learning,"
whereas Tonghak means "Eastern Lear¬
ning." It was also inspired by the political
decadence of the period, and the plight of
country people ground under the heels of
city aristocrats or idle rural gentry. In these
respects it was a reform movement, and
also included anti-foreign elements, in reali¬
zation that Korea was threatened by out¬
side domination as well as inner decay.
The founder of the Tonghak movement
Choe Che-u aimed at a religious system, in
his own words, "fusing into one the ethics
of Confucianism, the awakening to nature
taught in Buddhism, and Taoist cultivation
of energy."
Syncretism of this kind continued to be a
feature of almost all later religions, most of
which are Confucian in ethics, follow
Buddhist-type rites and adopt Taoist
methods in religious practice.
Chang Byung-kil
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Kim Tae-byok, Seoul
ANCIENT KOREA AND WORLD HISTORY
Christian
year
Korean history World history
B.C.
2333 Tan'gun founds Ancient Chosun
753 Foundation of Rome
555 Buddha born
551 Great Wall of China
108 Chinese Colony of Lolang established
Kimhae pottery
THREE KINGDOMS (57 B.C-668 A.D.)
57 Silla
37 Koguryo
18 Paekche
A.D. Christ born
372 Buddhism introduced to Koguryo
476 West Roman Empire falls
527 Buddhism sanctioned in Silla kingdom
571 Mohammed born
589 Sui Dynasty unifies China
618 T'ang succeeds Sui in China
660 Paekche kingdom falls
668 Koguryo falls: end of Three Kingdoms
UNIFIED SILLA (670-935)
670 Silla Kingdom unifies Korea
751 Construction of Sokkuram Temple
800 Charlemagne crowned Emperor
907
KORYO DYNASTY (918-1392)
T'ang dynasty falls in China
918 Koryo kingdom founded
935 Silla falls
960 Sung dynasty founded in China
962 Holy Roman Empire founded
980 Avicenna born
1011 Work started on the Tripitaka Koreana
1096 First Crusade
1145 Annals of the Three Kingdoms published
1215 Magna Carta
1231 First Mongol invasion
1234 Metal type for printing used for the first time
1272 End of the Crusades
1274 First expedition to Japan
1275 Marco Polo visits China
1279 Sung Dynasty falls in China
1281 Second expedition to Japan
1368
YI DYNASTY (1392-1910)
Ming dynasty founded in China
1392 Koryo falls, Yi dynasty takes over
1396 Capital moved to Seoul
1443 Korean alphabet invented by King Sejong
(1419-1450)
1455 Gutenberg Bible
1492 Columbus reaches America
1498 Vasco de Gama discovers Cape
route to India
1592 Japanese invasion
The shaman's mask
In ancient Korea the shaman cast out
demons, cured disease and communicated
with the dead. Supernatural powers were
attributed to the masks worn during
shamanistic rituals. (1) Lacquered wood
mask for scaring off evil spirits was
discovered in a 5th-century royal tomb
near Kyongju. It originally had protruding
teeth and two pairs of globular eyes.
Survivals of old shamanistic beliefs still
find expression in colourful Korean folk
dances such as that based on the legend
of Ch'oyong, son of the dragon of the
east. Originating in the 9th century, the
legend was adopted by 13th-century
Buddhists who used it to illustrate the
principle of countering evil with good :
Ch'oyong had resisted the temptation to
kill his wife's lover. Photos 2 and 3 show
masks worn during the Ch'oyong dance.
(2) Mask of a functionary is draped with
leaves and equipped with "ears"
representing traces of a stag's antlers.
Like the symbolic "ears" which adorned '
the crowns of Silla kings, they recall the
antlers attached to the headgear of
Siberian shamans. (3) Mask worn by
another figure in the dance is capped with
a lotus flower, an unmistakable sign of
Buddhist influence.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
200 years
before Gutenberg The master printers
of Koryo
by Ch'on Hye-bong
CH'ON HYE BONG is professor of history and
bibliography and director of the university
library, Sungkyunkwan University, Seoul. He is
the author of numerous articles on ancient
Korean printing techniques.
JOHANNES Gutenberg, a fifteenth-
century German craftsman and
inventor, is widely believed to have
been the first man to produce a font of
movable metal type. This belief is mis¬
taken. This momentous invention had been
anticipated over two centuries before in
Korea, where no less than six distinct fonts
of metal type had been created by the time
the famous Gutenberg Bible was printed.
According to Lee Kyu-bo, an illustrious
man of letters who was also the prime
minister of King Kojong of the Koryo
dynasty, the first book to be printed with
metal type was produced around 1234. In a
book of his own he describes how twenty-
eight copies of a Confucian work entitled
the Sang-jong-ye-mun ("Detailed Text for
Rites of the Past and Present") were pro¬
duced and distributed to various govern¬
ment offices.
This great innovation occurred in a
country where the art of printing already
had a long history. More than seven hun¬
dred years before Gutenberg and five hun¬
dred years before the invention of movable k
metal type, artists under the Silla dynasty f
Two early examples of Korean work in
xylographie (woodblock) printing and the
use of metal type. Above left, the oldest
surviving Buddhist text printed with a °
woodblock, the "Pure Light
Dharani-sutra", dates from the mid-7th
century A.D. It was discovered in a
Korean temple in 1966. Left, two pages
from a Buddhist classic
printed in 1377 with movable metal type.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
, had achieved great proficiency in wood¬
block printing.
Woodblock printing is an art form which
reached a high level of development in
many parts of east Asia, but the achieve¬
ments of Korea in this field are so remark¬
able as to support the view that the most
brilliant accomplishments are often foster¬
ed within the smaller cultures.
Historians acknowledge that the Chinese
invented xylographie (woodblock) printing
between 712 and 756 during the great age
of T'ang culture. At that time Korea's
ruling Silla dynasty was in very close con¬
tact with China as a result of a military
alliance with the T'ang dynasty which had
led directly to the unification of the Korean
peninsula. Therefore it may be assumed
that knowledge of printing using carved
wooden blocks reached Korea soon after
its invention.
The oldest surviving woodblock print in
the world seems to be the Pure Light
Dharani-sutra, a small Buddhist scroll dis¬
covered in 1966 at the Pulguk-sa Temple in
Kyongju. Scholars have deduced that it
was published under Silla patronage
around 751 A.D.
The oldest surviving Chinese woodblock
scroll is the Diamond-sutra, which was
printed in 868 under the T'ang dynasty by
Wang Chieh for the purpose of praying for
the souls of his dead parents. Comparison
of this scroll with the Korean sutra from
Pulguk-sa reveals that the Korean product,
while displaying similar excellence of work¬
manship, unmistakably shows features of
an earlier age.
The art of printing was further developed
in the early years of the Koryo period (918-
1392). The Precious Box Seal Dharani-
sutra, a scroll published by Ch'ongji-sa
Temple in 1007, is a work of exquisite skill
and is undoubtedly the best of all such
works dating from the early years of the
Koryo dynasty.
But the greatest of the Koryo accom¬
plishments in the art of woodblock prin¬
ting, and perhaps in all the arts, is the
monumental 6,000-chapter Tripitaka
Koreana, based on a Buddhist text impor¬
ted from Sung China in 991. This project
was motivated by the desire to enlist the
aid of the Buddha in an attempt to with¬
stand invasion.
The first set of woodblocks, completed
in 1013, was destroyed two centuries later
when the Mongols invaded Korea in 1232.
The invaders ravaged the entire country
except for the island of Kanghwa off the
west coast, where the king and the court
took refuge. It was here that the
government-in-exile began the mammoth
task of restoring the destroyed Buddhist
books. The work went on for sixteen years
and resulted in over 80,000 woodcut blocks
which are today preserved in the Haein-sa
Temple. A precious source for the study
of Buddhism, the Tripitaka has a strong
claim to be considered Koryo's finest pro¬
duct in the arts.
Whatever the truth of this claim, it is
indisputable that the invention of movable
metal type was Koryo's overwhelming con¬
tribution to science and technology. The
technological capability existed by the early
Photo © Jeon Sang-woon, Seoul
Traditional Korean bronze form tray, set
with Chongyu type cast in 1777. The text
¡s a page of the Kukcho pogam (Precious
mirror of the YI Dynasty).
thirteenth century in the form of suitable
papers and inks and in the availability of
sufficient metalworking knowledge. The
need for books to be produced in a number
of copies was driven home when the royal
palace of Koryo, along with tens of thou¬
sands of books in the royal library, was
twice destroyed by fire, in 1126 and 1170.
At the same time China, a major source of
book supply, was preoccupied with wars
which caused a decline in book output.
Further stimuli included a growing scarcity
of wood suitable for making printing
blocks, an abundance of bronze, and the
prospect of reduced costs from using a
type font on many occasions.
And yet the promoters of movable metal
type were initially to be disappointed, for
their innovation did not win general accep¬
tance. To the Koreans a book was both a
store of knowledge and a work of art, and
the unsurpassable beauty and fineness of
detail achieved with wood was to relegate
this new technique to the status of a minor
oddity for the next one hundred and
seventy years.
It was not until 1403 that T'aejong, the
second king of the Yi dynasty, revived the
neglected technique when he initiated the
casting of bronze type for the printing of
Confucian classics and historical literature
with the aim of helping government offi¬
cials to rule wisely. His type font was re¬
vised by his son, King Sejong, the most be¬
loved of all Korean rulers, and there ensued
a series of technological improvements
which by the end of the fifteenth century
resulted in the printing of books as beauti¬
ful as any produced with wood.
Ch'on Hye-bong
The library at the monastery of Haein-sa houses the famous set of
woodblocks inscribed in the 13th century with the Tripitaka Koreana. The
Tripitaka ("The Three Baskets") is the most complete collection of early
Buddhist sacred literature. The Tripitaka blocks at Haein-sa (see also colour
photo page 8) are the oldest and best-preserved of any complete Buddhist
scriptures in the world.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A graphic portrait
of the
human voice
by Lee Ki-mun
The Korean script known as Han'gul was developed by a board of
scholars appointed by King Sejong, who ruled Korea from 1419 to 1450.
Above, statue of King Sejong In Seoul. Left, the word Han 'gui itself Is
made up of the following letters (from left to right and from top to
bottom): .¿-=h h = a |_=n -|=g -=u E = I.
SPOKEN by some fifty million people,
Korean ranks among the twenty
major languages of the world.
Although most speakers of Korean live on
the Korean peninsula and its adjacent
islands, about one million are scattered
throughout the world on every continent.
The origin of the Korean language is as
obscure as the origin of the Korean people.
In the nineteenth century when Western
scholars "discovered" the Korean lan¬
guage, this was the first question that they
raised. These scholars proposed various
theories linking the Korean language with
Ural-Altaic, Japanese, Chinese, Tibetan,
Dravidian, Ainu, Indo-European and other
languages.
Among these, only the theories of the
relationship between Korean and Altaic
(which groups the Turkic, Mongolian, and
Manchu-Tungus languages) on the one
hand and between Korean and Japanese
on the other have continuously attracted
the attention of comparative linguists in the
twentieth century.
Altaic, Korean and Japanese exhibit not
only great similarities in their general struc¬
ture, but also share remarkable common
features such as agglutination (the combi¬
nation or running together of simple or root
words into compounds in which the form
and meaning of the constituent parts
undergo little or no change) and vowel har¬
mony, although the vowel harmony in Old
Japanese has been the object of dispute
among specialists in the field. More¬
over, it has been found that these lan¬
guages have various common elements in
their grammars and vocabularies. Although
much work remains to be done, research
seems to show that Korean is probably
related to both Altaic and Japanese.
LEE KI-MUN is professor of Korean language
and literature at Seoul National University. His
Comparative Study of Manchu and Korean
appeared, in English, in Ural-Altaische Fahrbu-
cher. Volume 30, 1958.
According to early historical records,
two groups of languages were spoken in
Manchuria and on the Korean peninsula at
the dawn of the Christian era: the northern
or Puyo group and the southern or Han
group.
Around the middle of the seventh cen¬
tury the kingdom of Silla conquered the
kingdoms of Paekche in the south-west
and Koguryo in the north and its language
became dominant on the peninsula. As a
result, the linguistic unification of the
peninsula was achieved on the basis of the
Silla language.
After the peninsula was unified, the
Koryo dynasty was founded in the tenth
century and the capital was moved to Kae¬
song in the centre of the Korean peninsula
and the dialect of Kaesong became the
standard for the national language.
When the Yi dynasty was founded at the
end of the fourteenth century, the capital
was transferred to Seoul. However, since
Seoul is geographically close' to Kaesong
this had no significance as far as the deve¬
lopment of the language was concerned.
The Korean script which is now generally
called Han'gul was invented in 1443 by
Sejong, the fourth king of the Yi dynasty,
who called it Hunmin-chongum (the cor¬
rect sounds for the instruction of the peo¬
ple). However, the script was not promul¬
gated until 1446 in a document which was
also called Hunmin-chongum.
The motivation behind the invention of
script was, according to Sejong's
preface in the above book, to enable the
Korean people to write their own language
in their own way. Until the invention of
Hunmin-chongum, only Chinese charac¬
ters were used by the upper classes. There
also seems to have been a secondary moti¬
vation behind the invention of Korean
script, that of representing the "correct"
sounds of Chinese characters.
In inventing Korean script, Sejong and
the scholars who assisted him probably
referred to several writing systems known
to them such as Chinese old seal charac¬
ters, the Uighur script and hP'ags-pa
script, but the system of Korean script is
based upon phonological studies. Above
all, its inventors developed a theory of tri¬
partite division of the syllable into initial,
medial and final, as opposed to the bi¬
partite division of traditional Chinese
phonology.
The initial sounds (consonants) are
represented by sixteen letters of which
there are five basic forms. According to the
explanations of the original Hunmin-
chongum text,
~1 (k) depicts the root of the tongue block¬
ing the throat.
L_ (n) depicts the outline of the tongue
touching the upper palate.
(m) depicts the outline of the mouth.
A (s) depicts the outline of the incisor.
O ( depicts the outline of the throat.
The other initial letters were derived by
adding strokes to the basic letters. No let¬
ters were invented for the final sounds,the
initial letters being used for that purpose.
The original Hunmin-chongum text also
explains that the medial sounds (vowels)
are represented by eleven letters of which
there are three basic forms :
is a depiction of Heaven.
is a depiction of Earth.
I is a depiction of Man.
By combining these three signs the other
medial letters such as ±. (o) and îî (yo) are
formed.
One of the characteristics of Korean
script is the syllabic grouping of the initial,
medial and final letters. However, Korean
script is essentially different from such
syllabic writing systems as Japanese kana.
It is an alphabetic system which is charac¬
terized by syllabic grouping.
After the promulgation of the Korean
alphabet, its popularity gradually increased
to the point, especially in modern times,
where it replaced Chinese characters as the
main system of writing in Korea.
Lee Ki-mun
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Oriental
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The traditional music of Korea shares
much of the common musical background
of Chinese and Japanese music. Yet Korean
music has maintained a number of uniquely
Korean characteristics which give it a place
apart in East Asian culture. These include,
for example, the triple rhythms of Korean
music, as compared with the double
rhythms of Chinese and Japanese music,
and its system of notation (chongganbo).
Korean music, like Korean painting,
reveals two distinct currentsclassical or
court music with its slow elegance and con¬
trolled passion, and folk music with its
lively rhythm and emotional melodic
expression which is comparable to that of
an Indian raga. Court music includes a num¬
ber of different types of music each of
which was used on specific occasions or for
specific ceremonies, for example, banquet
music and ritual Confucian and ancestral
shrine music.
Following a tradition borrowed from
China, musical instruments are classified
according to the eight principal materials
from which they are made: wood, clay,
metal, stone, hide, gourds, silk and bam¬
boo. Instruments representative of each
category are shown on these pages. Wood
is represented twice because the instru
ments traditionally used to start and end a
performance are both made of wood.
(1) Wood: the Chuk is a kind of wooden
trough with a hammer inserted through the
cover; the Chuk is placed at one side of the
orchestra and the hammer strikes the bot¬
tom of the trough, three times to indicate
the start of a performance. (2) Clay: the
Hun is a rounded flute with a blow hole on
top and five finger holes; the pitch depends
upon the width of the flute and the manner
in which the clay is baked. (3) Metal: the
P'yonjong is a set of sixteen bronze bells
hung in two rows on a carved wooden
stand; the bells are identical in size and
shape but of varying thickness of bronze
and are struck with a hammer made of
horn. (4) Stone: the P'yon'gyong is a set of
sixteen jade stone chimes which are also
struck with a horn hammer; pitch varies
according to the thickness of the jade. (5)
Hide: the Changgo is an hour-glass-shaped
drum; the left hand skin is thick and is
struck with the palm of the hand; the thin¬
ner right hand skin is struck with a drum¬
stick. (6) Gourd: Saenghwang is a type of
mouth organ consisting of a small bowl fash¬
ioned from a gourd from which seventeen
slender bamboo pipes, one of which is
mute, of differing lengths protrude; at the
base of each pipe is a thin metal tongue
which vibrates when the performer blows
into the gourd. (7) Silk: the Komun-go is a
six-stringed zither with strings made of silk.
(8) Bamboo: the Hyang-piri is an oboe made
of bamboo with double reeds and eight fin¬
ger holes; it was introduced to Korea during
the fifth century. (9) Wood: the O is an ins¬
trument in the form of a tiger with twenty-
seven indentations along its back; at the
close of a performance the tiger is struck
three times on the head and then a split
bamboo stick is drawn across the indenta¬
tions on its back; the O is always placed at
the opposite side of the orchestra to the
Chuk. M
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The wall paintings of Koguryo
A fresco
of
daily life
THE tombs of kings and nobles,
discovered during recent decades
along the middle reaches of the Yalu
river in the T'ung-kou plain of south Man¬
churia and in the basin of the Taedong
river, near P'yongyang, represent the
height of artistic and architectural develop¬
ment of the ancient kingdom of Koguryo
(37B.C.-668A.D.).
The sites of the tombs were selected by
diviners for their favourable aspects and are
scattered widely over the countryside.
Some fifty of them are decorated with wall
paintings of great beauty which provide
precious information on the beliefs, the
organization and the daily life of the society
of the period. The architectural skill with
which these tombs were built is evidenced
by the design of the vaulting and the
placing of the pillars. Long buried beneath
their protective mounds of earth, the
tombs exemplify the deliberate marriage of
the aesthetic with the functional.
Portrait thought to be of
King Michon, from
tomb No. 3 at Anak,
Hwanghae province.
Photo © Academy of Social Sciences of the Democratic People's Republic of Korea
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
fe'K
i
fe1-^,
^^
äHRSw
ik&>$a
The royal procession, a mural in King Michon's tomb.
The wall paintings, which are in a
remarkable state of preservation, deal with
a wide variety of subjects.
In the "Two Pillars Tomb", two corteges
wend their way along the walls of the
entrance corridor, traverse the ante¬
chamber, finally converging at the far end
of the main chamber where a man and a
woman are seen seated on a dais.
The huge fourth century tomb of king
Michon, at Anak in the province of Hwang¬
hae, comprises four fully decorated cham¬
bers. Its most remarkable mural is a six-
metre-long portrayal of a royal procession.
The king, seated in an ox-drawn carriage, is
escorted by mounted and foot guards and
a host of retainers and clowns, in all 250
figures. Surprisingly, although almost all
these figures represent conventional
categories nobles, functionaries, monks,
servants, jugglers, etc. each figure is dif¬
ferent, and so are the features of each face.
So subtly are the varieties of expression
rendered that it seems as though each
figure was a real man or woman known to
the artists. The same sorupulous attention
to detail can be seen in the portrayal of
weapons, armour, carriages and land¬
scape.
The Koguryo tomb paintings also pre¬
sent a veritable bestiary, including domest¬
ic and wild animals, real and mythological
beasts, the latter representing the points of
the compass. It was also in the kingdom of
Koguryo that astronomers compiled the
first Korean star maps, such as that painted
on the ceiling of the principal chamber of
the Tomb of the Dancers.
An infinite variety of ornamental motifs
adorn the Koguryo tombs; lotus flowers
and honeysuckle tendrils entwine the pillars
and enliven the ceiling panels, testifying to
the rich artistic technique and the inex¬
haustible inventiveness of the anonymous
artists who produce these masterpieces of
a bygone age.
The wall paintings of
the Anak tombs and
the Tomb of the Three
Chambers are rich in
information on a wide
variety of costumes.
Horseman and mounted archer from the
Twin Pillars Tomb, Chinjidong, Pyongang
province.
Honeysuckle design on a ceiling panel of King Michon's tomb.
MORE DRAWINGS PAGE 18
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Decorative motif from one
of the Kangso tombs
Fabulous creatures from
the Anak tombs and the Twin Pillars Tomb
Drawings taken from The Culture of Kokouryo
(1972) © Academy of Social Sciences of the
Democratic People's Republic of Korea.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Korean painting an original
contribution to Oriental art
by Ch'oe Sun-u
DOWN the ages, Korean painting has
been strongly influenced by Chi¬
nese painting, both because of the
geographical proximity of the two coun¬
tries and the long-standing cultural ties bet¬
ween them. Yet Korean artists were not
content with mere imitation. They created
a uniquely Korean art by harmonizing Chi¬
nese influences with their own native
genius.
Korean art goes back to the tomb murals
which were a prominent feature of the cul¬
ture of the ancient kingdom of Koguryo (37
B.C. to 668 A.D.). In its early days, the
kingdom was open to the influence of
north Asian civilization through its contacts
with a number of peripheral tribes, such as
the Huns. But the dominant influence was
that of the north Chinese culture developed
under the Han dynasty (206 B.C. to 220
A.D.) and the Six Dynasties (280 B.C. to
589 A.D.), and the murals of the ancient
Koguryo tombs, both in conception and in
style, drew their inspiration from Chinese
painting of this period.
This tradition had its counterpart in the
kingdom of Paekche (18 B.C. to 660 A.D.).
The murals in the stone tomb in Nungsan-
ni, Puyo, which depict in a refined and deli¬
cate style lotus flower designs, cloud pat¬
terns, and portraits of the Four Gods are an
excellent example of Paekche art. Another
excellent example is the tomb of King
Muryong which was discovered in Kongju
in 1971. The tomb contains delicate lotus
designs and colour representations of the
Red Phoenix and animal deities. A beautiful
landscape painting executed on a brick wall
in a ruined Paekche temple which dates
back to the first half of the seventh century
confirms the notable development of land¬
scape painting during the Paekche era.
The kingdom of Silla (57 B.C. to 668
A.D.) was by far the most conservative of
the three ancient kingdoms as far as paint¬
ing was concerned. Up to 1950 no trace of
Silla painting had been found, but excava¬
tions in recent years have turned up some
exciting findings, notably the birch bark
paintings discovered in Tomb 155 in
Kyongju in 1973. A form of oil painting, it
would seem that the contours were first
drawn rather freely on the surface of arti
cles made from white birch bark and that
the colours were then added.
The Samguk Sagi (Historical Records of
the Three Kingdoms) has an interesting
anecdote about a painter named Solgo
who was active from the middle of the sixth
century to the beginning of the seventh
century. "A painting of an old pine tree
which Solgo executed looked so real that
birds flew into the room to perch on its'
branches. After the passage of time the
colours in the painting began to fade and it
was retouched by an old priest. From then
on, the birds were no longer deceived."
So, even though no actual Silla paintings k
are extant, with the exception of those*
CH'OE SUN-U is director of the National
Museum of Korea, Seoul. He is one of the con¬
tributing authors of Korea, its Land, People and
Culture of all Ages, Seoul, 1963.
Landscape (ink and colour on silk) attributed to the 16th-century
scholar-painter Yi Kyong-yun. With a group of other artists Yi Kyong-
yun introduced into Korea the "Northern School" style of painting
inspired by Chinese art. The crane near the human figure symbolizes
immortality.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Han Sok-hong, Private Collection, Haenam
Self-portrait (ink and colour on paper) of Yun Tu-so, a 17th-century scholar-painter
of the Northern School. One of the few self-portraits to have survived from Yi
dynasty Korea, the face is realistically portrayed with every strand of the beard
being meticulously delineated.
, associated with tombs, one can see that,
by contemporary judgement at least, works
of outstanding artistic merit were being
produced.
There were two schools of painters
during the period of the Koryo dynasty (918
A.D. to 1392 A.D.), one comprising profes¬
sional painters and the other made up of
aristocrats, scholars and literati who re¬
garded painting as a hobby.
Yi Nyong was one of the representative
professional landscape painters of the
Koryo era. Two of his landscapes, one
depicting the Yesong River and the other
depicting the Chonsuwon Pavilion, won
great praise from Emperor Huitsung of
Sung China who was himself an accom¬
plished artist.
Outstanding among the literati painters
of the day were Chong Chi-sang, famous
for his landscapes and paintings of flowers,
Haeae and Hyeho, both Buddhist monks,
who gained renown for their Buddhist
paintings and their bamboo paintings in
Indian ink, and King Kongmin (1351-1374)
who excelled in landscape painting, paint¬
ings of flowers and birds, and portraits.
The division of the painting world into
two schools mentioned earlier was intensi¬
fied under the Yi dynasty (1392-1910). The
professional painters centered their activi¬
ties around the Tohwa-so (Office of Paint¬
ing), a government office which had been
set up in the Koryo era but was reorganized
under the Yi dynasty.
The leading professional landscape
painters during the early Yi dynasty were
An Kyon and Yi Sang-jwa, and the out¬
standing literati landscapist was Kang Huí¬
an. All three painted in the style of the old
Sung academy, showing the conservative
taste of the royal court and the nobility. A
factor in this trend towards conservatism
was the enormous collection of Sung and
Yuan paintings which Prince Anp'yong,
the fourth son of King Sejong, had in his
possession. Prince Anp'yong was a young
man of refined taste and artistic leanings.
Around the middle of the sixteenth cen¬
tury a group of painters, notably Kim Che,
Yi Pul-hae, and Yi Kyong-yun introduced
the Northern School style of painting to the
Korean art world. The Northern School
continued to exert its influence until the
end of the seventeenth century, numbering
among its adherents artists of the calibre of
Yi Chong (1578-1607) and Yun Tu-so
(1668-?)
The eighteenth century saw the emer¬
gence of a number of remarkable painters.
Among them was Chong Son, a landscape
artist, who introduced the Southern
School and thus boldly challenged the con¬
ventional Northern School style. Chong
Son was the first artist to successfully
adapt the Southern School style to paint¬
ings of Korean scenes and this innovation
may be attributed to the awakening of a
new national consciousness, which ultima¬
tely led to the emergence of the Sirhak
school of practical learning, a popular
literature written in Han'gul, and genre
painting based on themes taken from the
daily lives of the people.
Ch'oe Sun-u
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Northern School painting was challenged by the "Southern School"
which contributed to Korean art a host of lively paintings of scenes
from everyday life. Kim Hong-do (born around 1745) was a noted
painter who boldly and wittily depicted the occupations and
recreations of people usually neglected by conventional painters.
Three scenes by Kim Hong-do : The Amorous Look (top right);
Village School (right). Typical Korean musical instruments are
featured in Musicians and a Dancer (above).
Photo © Han Sok-hong, National Museum of Korea, Seoul
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The unicorn,
the phoenix
and the flying horse
Recent discoveries from three ancient royal tombs
by Kim Won-Yong
AROUND the beginning of the Chris¬
tian era, at the height of the early
Iron Age in Korea, the inhabitants
of the Korean peninsula began to form
what might be called village-states in
various parts of the country.
According to Samguk Sagi, the official
history of the Three Kingdoms in Korea,
compiled in the twelfth century, the
Koguryo kingdom was formed on the
northern bank of the Amnok (Yalu) river in.
37 B.C. Twenty years later, in 18 B.C., a
group of political refugees from Koguryo
established the state of Paekche in what is
today the Seoul area on the lower reaches
of the Han river.
Koguryo was renowned for its mounted
archers who harassed the north-eastern
frontier of China across the Liao-ho river in
the Liaotung peninsula. Towards the end
of the fourth century, however, when the
Northern Wei dynasty (386-534) rose to
power in northern China, the Koguryo
kingdom had to change its policy and in
427 moved its capital further south to
Pyongyang. This southward advance natu¬
rally led to friction between Koguryo and
the two southern kingdoms.
The Paekche kingdom remained in the
Seoul area until 475, when it moved its
capital to Kongju in south-western Korea
after being defeated by Koguryo. In 538
Paekche again moved its capital, this time
to Puyo a little further south. Puyo remain¬
ed the capital of Paekche until the kingdom
collapsed in 660.
The State of Saro, or Silla, emerged in
57 B.C. in south-eastern Korea in the valley
of Kyongju, which remained the capital
Fabulous stone animal with a single
iron horn guarded the burial
chamber of King Muryong (501-523)
at Kongju, capital of the Paekche
dynasty.
KIM WON-YONG Is professor of archaeology
at Seoul National University. He is the author of
History of Korean Art, Seoul, 1968.
throughout Silla's thousand-year-long his¬
tory. Silla steadily expanded northwards
and westwards at the expense of Koguryo
and Paekche respectively, and by the
middle of the sixth century had won pos¬
session of the Seoul area, thus securing a
base on the west coast. This expansion
naturally led to battles with its two neigh¬
bours and as a result Silla formed an
alliance with the T'ang dynasty in an
attempt to unify the entire Korean penin¬
sula.
This policy succeeded, and Paekche and
Koguryo fell before the allied forces in 660
and 668 respectively. Silla before unifica¬
tion is usually known as Old Silla, and after
unification as Unified or Great Silla (670-
935).
Many tombs of kings and aristocrats of
each of the three kingdoms have been dis¬
covered near the ancient capitals. In sou¬
thern Korea those of the Paekche kingdom
are clustered around Seoul, Kongju and
King Muryong and the queen who was
buried with him were laid on a bier with
elaborately painted wooden pillows and
foot-rests. Phoenix heads face to face on
each side of the queen's pillow, above.
Below, the king's foot-rest.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Crown, bracelets and jewellery as they
were found in the Great Tomb of
Hwangnam. Barely visible are the lines of
the grid used by archaeologists to record
the exact position of each object.
General view of ancient burial mounds at Kyongju,
capital of the kingdom of Silla (57 B.C. -668 A.D.).
Dwarfing all the rest, the twin mound at right is the
Great Tomb of Hwangnam in which a royal couple
was buried in the late 5th century.
A scene during the excavation of the Great Tomb: the
mound has been removed, revealing the layer of stones
which covered the burial chamber.
Puyo, while Silla tombs are concentrated in
the Kyongju area.
Paekche tombs are stone (very rarely
brick) chambers covered with a mound of
earth. Because access to the burial cham¬
bers was easy, almost all of them were
looted of their contents long ago.
Thus the accidental discovery of the
intact tomb of King Muryong (501-523) in
Kongju in 1971 was an event of major
importance.
At the northern edge of Kongju there is a
brick tomb with mural paintings, probably
dating from the early sixth century. Dis¬
covered in 1933, it had been completely
stripped by robbers. Nevertheless it was
the first Chinese-style brick tomb to be dis¬
covered in Paekche territory, and also the
second Paekche tomb to be discovered
decorated with wall paintings, the first
being a tomb in Puyo.
In early July 1971, a labourer workings
behind the tomb to improve the drainage f
The stones are removed beneath a temporary structure
erected to protect the site.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
around it struck a brick which turned out to
be the left upper corner of the façade of the
tomb of King Muryong. The new tomb was
covered by a low mound which archaeolo¬
gists had previously assumed to be an
earthwork to protect the portion of the
tomb with wall paintings.
The royal tomb, whose entrance faces
south, was constructed by cutting into the
slope of a hill. It consists of a main chamber
and a smaller passageway leading in from
the south (See colour page opposite). A
vertical brick wall was constructed at the
outer end of the passageway. This façade
had an arched doorway which was sealed
with bricks.
A drain, eighteen metres long, was posi¬
tioned at the bottom of the main chamber,
extending as far as the slope of the hill.
Both the main chamber and the passage¬
way are tunnel-shaped and are lined with
hard grey bricks decorated with lotus
designs in relief. The structure is a faithful
copy of contemporary Chinese tombs in
the Yangtze river area.
At the entrance to the tomb chamber,
there is a step down to a recessed portion
of the floor, which occupies approximately
one-fifth of the total area of the main room.
Thus the rear four-fifths of the chamber,
where the royal coffins were placed, give
the impression of being raised. Five small,
onion-shaped niches were set in the walls
to hold porcelain lamps which, when dis¬
covered, still contained the remains of
burnt wicks.
In the middle of the passageway stood a
stone guardian animal with a single iron
horn and carved stylized wings. In front of
the animal were two inscribed stone
plaques placed side by side, each of them
bearing a number of iron Wu-shu coins of
the Liang dynasty (502-557). One of the
plaques bore the name of King Muryong,
along with the dates of his death and of the
deposition of his coffin in the burial cham¬
ber. The other, dedicated to his queen, was
inscribed with the contract drawn up bet¬
ween King Muryong and the Earth Deity
for the purchase of the site for 10,000
coins.
According to the inscriptions the king
died in 523 and was buried in the tomb in
525, exactly twenty-eight months after his
death. His queen died in 526 and was
buried in 529. The king was sixty-two years
old when he died, but the age of his queen
was not given in the epitaph. A molar
tooth, the only organic material in the
queen's coffin, however, was identified as
that of a woman about thirty years old who
had experienced a healthy adolescence.
We do not know whether or not her death
was a natural one.
When Seoul, the first capital of Paekche,
was sacked by the army of Koguryo in 475,
the defeated King Kaero died in the battle.
Members of the royal family, including the
fourteen-year-old Prince Sama, who later
became King Muryong, fled to Kongju. It
was there that he ascended the throne in
501, immediately sending an envoy across
the Yellow Sea to China as a measure of
security against the invading Koguryo.
Paekche enjoyed peace and progress
during the reign of Muryong who, accor¬
ding to the Samguk Sagi, was a tall, hand¬
some man greatly loved by his people. It
24
was only after his death that the title
"Muryong", meaning Military and Peace,
was bestowed on him.
Muryong's tomb may have been an imi¬
tation of a Liang brick tomb, commemora¬
ting the king's close alliance with Liang
China. It is the only Paekche tomb yet dis¬
covered to be identified as that of a known
king, to contain inscriptions of dates and a
full, intact inventory of rich burial objects.
The discovery caused great excitement
not only in the city of Kongju but through¬
out Korea and even in Japan, because
Paekche was traditionally regarded by the
Japanese as the transmitter of an advanced
culture into Japan.
The king's coffin was placed in the east¬
ern side of the chamber with its head point¬
ing to the south; that of the queen occu¬
pied the western side. Both coffins had col¬
lapsed because the planks at each side had
decayed. The heads and feet of the royal
couple had rested on painted wooden pil¬
lows. According to the history of Liang
China, Paekche kings wore a black silk
crown with gold floral ornaments attached
to the back and front. A pair of such orna¬
ments was found near the king's head-
pillow. Both the king and his queen had
once worn, a garment studded with many
tiny beads and gold floral ornaments. The
king also wore gold earrings and a girdle
with a long silver pendant. Two bronze mir¬
rors were in the king's coffin, one near his
head and one near his feet. The latter is
particularly remarkable on account of the
animal figures depicted on it in relief over
patterns of a kind usually found on Chinese
mirrors.
The queen's wooden head-pillow is more
elaborate than that of her spouse. Minia¬
ture portraits of animals and birds were
painted on a red background, and a
phoenix head was carved at each end of
the pillow. The queen wore a gold neck¬
lace, gold and silver bracelets and gold ear¬
rings. A pair of tiny glass figurines in the
shape of a small boy with a shaven head
were suspended from the queen's girdle,
probably as a charm.
The relics from this royal tomb provide
solid clues to the chronology of archaeolo¬
gical specimens and works of art from the
Three Kingdoms period, as well as the con¬
temporary Kofun Period in Japan.
The second major archaeological dis¬
covery in Korea in recent years occurred in
April 1973 when a team of specialists began
excavations in the centre of the Silla ceme¬
tery in the city of Kyongju, the capital of
Silla.
Hundreds of Silla tombs, dating from the
fourth to the eighth century A.D., are still
to be seen in and around the Kyongju
Basin. Although many of them have lost
their covering mounds, some are well pre¬
served with enormous mounds over twenty
metres high and fifty metres in diameter.
The typical Silla tomb consists of an
earth mound enclosing an inner mound of
boulders, which in its turn covers a box-like
wooden chamber containing a coffin and
burial objects. Within a few years of
construction, the wooden chamber col¬
lapsed due to natural decay and the stones
fell into the burial chamber, crushing most
of the tomb offerings.
CONTINUED PAGE 29
Fabulous beasts
from royal tombs
The only architectural remains of the
ancient Korean kingdom of Koguryo are
mound tombs with stone burial chambers
often richly decorated with wall paintings
depicting real or mythical creatures as
well as scenes from everyday life. The
turtle and the snake entwined to form the
so-called creation symbol of the north are
shown in this detail of a mural In the
Great Tomb (6th-7th century A.D.) at
Uhyon near Pyongyang. Portrayed
elsewhere in the tomb are the other
fantastic animals symbolizing the cardinal
points of the compass: the dragon, the
tiger and the phoenix.
Its mane bristling, its long curved tongue
protruding from its mouth, the Heavenly
Horse (near right) bears the dead to the
next world. This remarkable painting
adorns a birch bark saddle flap discovered
in a 6th-century tomb at Kyongju, once
capital of the historic State of Silla. In
Siberia and Manchuria the birch was a
sacred tree whose wood was used for the
shaman's staff. The word tan, meaning a
variety of birch, appears in the name of
the mythical founder of Korea, Tan'gun.
Far right, the tomb of King Muryong, ruler
of the Kingdom of Paekche in the early
6th century. The discovery of the tomb at
Kongju, southwestern Korea, in 1971, was
a major find since unlike most tombs of
its kind it had not been plundered and
contained a rich store of gold, silver and
bronze objects. The tunnel-shaped burial
chamber, 4.20 metres long and almost 3
metres high, is lined with bricks decorated
with lotus designs.
Photos © Kim Tae-byok, Seoul
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
1
*
\-<
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
w
m
I
H
I
H
V
*
-
'ir
4
*
*
*
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
»
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Centre double page
In 1789 the scholar-architect Chong Yag-yong drew the plans of this
pontoon bridge across the Han River at Seoul. Thirty-eight boats were
commandeered and on them were laid a thousand planks; a dozen
other vessels moored on each side of the bridge completed the
construction. Here, a contemporary painting shows the scene as a royal
procession crosses the bridge. The works of Chong Yag-yong
(1762-1836), also known as Ta-san, reflect the influence of an important
intellectual movement in Korea whose adherents are known as the
Sirhak movement had an impact on many sectors of Korean life. The
founder of a royal academy, Chongjo was noted for his love of
the society and nation, such as the promotion of administrative reform,
éducation, industry and technology. Sirhak scholars also carried out
research into the history, geography and language of Korea and
conducted critical examinations of the Confucian Classics.
It was customary for a Korean ruler to pay his respects to his ancestors
several times a year, bearing food and drink to their tombs. In this
painting on a screen King Chongjo, escorted by an entourage of
courtiers and attendants, is shown on the way to the grave of his
father. Prince Sado. During the reigns of Chongjo and his grandfather,
Yongjo, which spanned the last three-quarters of the 18th century, the
Sirhak movement had an impact on many sectors of Korean life. The
founder of a royal academy, Chongjo was noted for his love of
literature and concern for social reform.
Photos © Korean Overseas Information Service, Seoul
Colour page left
Top left, bronze water pourer-or sprinkler with silver Inlay and fittings.
Dating from the 11th or 12th century, it contained drinking water used
in Buddhist ceremonies. The design of willow trees and swimming
ducks is typically Korean.
A woman toys with an ornament in this delicately executed painting
(114 cm by 45.2 cm) on silk by Sin Yun-bok, who portrayed many
humorous and realistic scenes of everyday life in late 18th-century
Korea in works which typify Korean taste and feeling at that time.
A member of the royal house of the Yi dynasty, the 16th-century artist
Yi Am was renowned as a painter of flowers, birds and animals. This
dog with three puppies beneath a tree, far left, is one of the few
authenticated examples of his work.
Photos © Han Sok-hong, Seoul
Covered by a mound 12.7 metres in
height and forty-seven metres in diameter,
tomb 155 at Kyongju is known as the Tomb
of the Heavenly Horse because a flying
horse is depicted on a birch bark saddle flap
found among its burial objects. Study of
the tomb and the goods in it has shown
that they date from the early sixth century.
All the organic material in the coffin has
disappeared, but gold and glass objects
have survived intact. The male occupant of
the tomb wore a girdle and a magnificent
gold crown, the fourth to be recovered
from Silla tombs in Kyongju. Its wearer
must have been a king of the Old Silla
period.
The crown consists of a circlet of cut
sheet gold with three tall uprights at the
front, each with stylized branches like a
tree. The uprights are flanked by two
upright ornaments shaped like antlers. The
tree form and the antler symbols reflect
shamanistic beliefs widely spread across
the Siberian steppe. Strands of comma-
shaped jade pendants are suspend¬
ed from the upright ornaments of the
crown by means of twisted gold wire. A
shimmering effect is added by numerous
gold spangles attached to the uprights. A
pointed cup of cut sheet gold with open¬
work designs was placed outside the. cof¬
fin. Two wing-shaped frontal ornaments
for a cap, made of pure gold, were also
found in the tomb.
A wooden chest at the eastern end of the
burial chamber contained a rich array of
burial gifts including horses' trappings,
vessels of gold, silver, bronze and iron,
lacquerware and pottery. A pair of saddle
flaps for a horse were made of several
layers of birch bark sewn together with lea¬
ther trimming. A galloping white horse
with streaming mane and tail is painted in
the centre, surrounded by a band decorat¬
ed with a floral pattern painted in red,
black, white and green (see colour photo
page 25). Wings sprout from each hoof.
The saddle flap is a prized example of a
unique form of Silla painting; nothing like it
has survived anywhere else in east Asia.
To the east of the Tomb of the Heavenly
Horse is tomb 98, the largest tomb in
Kyongju. It is known as the Great Tomb at
Hwangnam, after the area of Kyongju in
which it is situated. It consists of twin
mounds set on a north-south axis and join¬
ed together at their base. It is twenty-three
metres high and 123 metres long, and was
excavated between July 1973 and October
1975.
The northern mound contained the tomb
of a female, probably the wife of the male
buried in the southern mound. The struc¬
ture of the mound suggests that she had
outlived her husband. She wore a magnifi¬
cent gold crown, a gold girdle, five pairs of
gold bracelets, two necklaces made of
glass beads and gold ornaments. Three
pieces of evidence confirm that the tomb
contained a woman: the fact that there was
no sword in the coffin; the presence of a
large ornamental clay spindle-whorl; and
above all the inscription "Girdle 'for the
Lady" scratched with a needle on the orna¬
mental silver end of a girdle found in the
gift chest. A striped glass goblet probably
manufactured in the Mediterranean region »
was also found. f
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
, The husband of the royal female wore a
gilt-bronze crown and a gold belt with
fewer pendants than the one worn by his
wife. The tomb dates from the second half
of the fifth century, and since Silla had no
ruling queen until the seventh century, it is
puzzling that the male occupant, who
should have been a king, wore a bronze
crown and his wife a gold one.
A huge array of iron weaponry, however,
was found in a pit connected to the hus¬
band's grave, while a late Roman glass
ewer and cup were found inside the gift
chest.
A skeleton identified as that of a girl
around fifteen years old was found outside
the wooden chamber of the male burial.
She may have been killed and thrown into
the pit as a human sacrifice. According to
the Samguk Sagi, King Chiiung of Silla
officially forbade the practice of human
sacrifice in 502 A.D.
Finds from these three royal tombs
throw into relief the lineage and sophistica¬
tion^ early Korean culture, and especially
its genius for metalworking. The discovery
of these spectacular intact burial sites in
Korea can best be seen in perspective
when compared with finds from contem¬
porary Chinese and Japanese tombs. The
artistic riches of these tombs reveal eastern
Asia as a cultural mosaic, in which high cul¬
ture was achieved in a variety of forms
among different ethnic groups.
Kim Won-yong
Intricately worked gold cap (5th or 6th
century) was discovered in the Tomb of
the Heavenly Horse at Kyongju.
Probably worn inside a crown, it
consists of four pieces of gold plate, each
bearing a different openwork design.
Photo © National Museum of Korea, Seoul
Celadon bowl with inlaid decoration of arabesque
designs and chrysanthemums (mid-12th century).
A sprig of foliage from the
plum-tree, symbol of youth
and purity, was placed in this
celadon maebyong vase,
known as the Thousand
Crane Vase because of its
incised decoration of
roundels depicting cranes
flying upwards amid clouds.
Produced in the 12th century,
it is one of the finest
specimens of incised ware
made under the Koryo
dynasty.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Immortal clay
The traditional pottery of Korea by Chong Yang-mo
White porcelain jar with grape design painted in copper
red beneath the glaze. (17th or 18th century).
The introduction of Buddhism in Korea led to the
practice of cremating the dead and burying their
ashes in funeral urns. Stoneware funeral urn above,
dating from the 8th or 9th century, is decorated with
stamped designs and covered with green glaze.
THE history of Korean pottery goes back to neolithic times
which saw the emergence of a form of pottery, fired at a
low temperature, and known as combware from the close,
toothcomb lines with which it was decorated. Then, around 100
B.C., followed Kimhae pottery which was fired at higher tempera¬
tures and from which the toothcomb designs gradually disap¬
peared. During the Bronze Age and at the beginning of the Iron
Age in Korea, black, red and grey pottery appeared.
Great progress was made during the period of the Three King¬
doms. Dark grey in colour, the pottery of this period, though much
finer and lighter than that of earlier days, was neverthless very
robust since it was fired at temperatures of up to 1,200 degrees
centigrade. Pottery from the kingdoms of Koguryo (37 B.C. -668
A.D.) and Paekche (18 B.C. -660 A.D.) is rare, but from the king¬
dom of Silla there remain many fine pieces which were the fore¬
runners of the famous celadons of Koryo. Most of them were reco¬
vered from tombs, some of which contained hundreds of pieces
including cups, vases with rounded bases, statuettes, models of
chariots and animals. Some pieces were decorated with geo¬
metric designs.
The techniques of celadon glazing and of white porcelain manu¬
facture had been brought into Korea from China during the Three
Kingdoms period and advanced techniques developed under the
T'ang dynasty in China reached the south-west corner of the
peninsula during the ninth and- early tenth centuries. Both the cela¬
dons and the white porcelains of the period up to the eleventh cen¬
tury reveal immense technical progress. Workshops and kilns were
under the control of the royal court and systematic experiments
were made with the techniques of the various Chinese schools of
pottery. As a result, Korean craftsmen were able to produce an
enormously varied range of pottery.
During the eleventh century Korean ¿pottery of the Koryo
dynasty was approaching perfection. Contemporary Chinese chro¬
nicles describe Korean glazing in particular as the most perfect of
the day. Gradually the ceramic art of Koryo was throwing off the
bonds of Chinese influence and acquiring an individuality of its
own. With its original shapes and ornamentation of great beauty
and its light, transparent glazes, Koryo pottery reached its apogee
in the middle of the twelfth century. New decorative techniques
were adopted mouldings, metal inlays and various other embel¬
lishments on ever finer clays. This brilliant phase was to continue
until the thirteenth century when decline and decadence set in
with the Mongol invasions, even though the latter brought with
them new techniques.
Under the Yi dynasty, Korean ceramic art experienced a new
resurgence, notably in white and blue porcelains for which grey
clay and kaolin were used. Kilns were supervised by the govern¬
ment of Kwanju, near Seoul, supplying the court and aris¬
tocracy while the regional kilns supplied the lesser nobility and
local administrations. The kilns were situated along an eighty-
kilometre stretch of the river Han and were fuelled by timber from
neighbouring forests, with disastrous consequences for the
environment of the region.
After the Japanese invasion towards the end of the sixteenth
century, Korean ceramic art fell on difficult times. Many Korean
potters were carried off to Japan where they gave a new impulsion
to Japanese ceramic art. In Korea, only white porcelain subsisted.
Later, its quality and style changed and flowers and plants became
part of the ornamentation. Korean pottery of this period, of great
simplicity, originality and beauty, was much appreciated by scho¬
lars and Korean white porcelain would continue to bring beauty
into the lives of many throughout the long, slow decline of the Yi
dynasty.
CHONG YANG-MO is chief curator at the National Museum of Korea,
Seoul. He is a specialist in ceramic art, a subject on which he has written
widely.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The stones of Sokkuram
A cornucopia of Buddhist sculpture
in a 1200-year-old temple-grotto
by Hwang Su-young and promised to build a temple on the spot
where he had caught the bear.
The tradition states that Tae-song was
converted to Buddhism as a result of this
incident and that afterwards he built Pul
guk-sa Temple and Sokkuram Temple, one
in memory of his parents during his former
existence and one in memory of his parents
during his second existence.
Kim Tae-song was born in 700 into the
royal Kim family and served King Kyong-
dok for a period of five years between 745
and 750 as chief minister of state. When he
finally left office in 750 he devoted himself
in accordance with the royal command to
the construction of the two temples. He
personally supervised the actual construc¬
tion work until his death in 774, and the old
IT5"
I :
EMPLES were as numerous as the
stars in the sky and pagodas as
a flock of geese on the wing.'
With these words an ancient chronicle des¬
cribes the spate of building which accom¬
panied the spread of Buddhism in Korea,
where it was introduced from India via
China in the latter half of the fourth cen¬
tury, later to become the State religion.
As temples increased in number there
was a corresponding development in
ancient Buddhist art. The period from the
latter half of the seventh century through
the eighth century is known as the golden
period of Buddhist art in Korea. It was a
period of close contact with India and
China where many young students and
monks went to pursue their studies.
Kyongju was the capital of Korea at the
time and haturally many temples were
constructed there. Of those which survive
today, Pul guk-sa Temple and Sokkuram
Temple are perhaps the most famous. Both
of these temples were built in the eighth
century A.D. on T'oham Mountain which
lies to the north-west of Kyongju. They
were built by the same man, Kim Tae-song.
Tradition has it that during the Silla
Dynasty Kim Tae-song was reincarnated as
the son oT a chief minister of state because
of his merits during a former existence.
When he was a full-grown man he liked to
hunt on T'oham Mountain. During one of
these hunts he caught a bear. When the
hunt was over he spent the night in a
country house at the foot of the mountain.
In a dream during the night the bear ap¬
peared to him in the form of a ghost and
began to attack him. Greatly alarmed, Tae-
song appealed to the bear for forgiveness
HWANG SU-YOUNG is professor of Buddhist
arts and dean of the Graduate School, Tongkuk
University, Seoul. A former director of the
National Museum, Seoul, he is one of the contri¬
buting authors of Korea, its Land, People and
Cultures of all Ages, Seoul, 1963.
Detail of one of the ten disciples of Buddha carved in
relief on the granite walls of the main hall of Sokkuram
temple. The entire figure is 2.18 metres high.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Photo Masakatsu Yamamoto © Kodansha International, Tokyo, Japan
This huge granite Buddha, over 3 metres high, sits on a lotus pedestal at the
centre of Sokkuram temple. The right hand lies palm downward, in the
"calling the earth to witness" gesture, signifying Buddha's activity in
the universe. The left hand is laid palm upwards on the lap, signifying
meditation. A figure of majesty, serenity and peace, the statue is a masterwork
of sculpture of the Unified Silla period.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
records tell us that the State completed the
' project.
We know that Kim Tae-song was a
member of the royal family and we can pre¬
sume that he was very close to the king
himself. We can also surmise that he built
these two temples to honour the king, the
royal family and his own ancestors.
The T'oham Mountain, on which Sokku¬
ram Temple stands overlooking the sea,
formed a natural barrier protecting the
Kingdom of Silla and its capital Kyongju
from foreign invaders, and it became cus¬
tomary to offer sacrifices on its eastern
peak for the prosperity of the nation. The
remains of the fourth king of the Silla
Dynasty, King T'halhae (57 - 79 A.D.), who
was held in popular belief to be the "strong
warrior without a single enemy under hea¬
ven", were transferred there, and he was
venerated as the god of the mountain.
A number of important historical remains
are concentrated in the area where the
waters from T'oham Mountain meet and
flow down into the sea: Kamun-sa Temple,
which was built at the end of the seventh
century for the purpose of protecting the
nation, the tomb of King Munmu, and a
ceremonial rock used by the people for rites
in honour of the deceased king.
The most important of these historical
remains is the tomb of King Munmu.
Munmu reigned in the middle of the
seventh century and was the monarch res¬
ponsible for the establishment of the king¬
dom of Unified Silla. His dying wish was
that after cremation he should become the
Guardian Dragon of the Eastern Sea and a
protector of the nation. It was his hope that
his example would teach the people to hold
Buddhist doctrine in high esteem. The
ashes of King Hyosong (734-741 A.D.)
were also scattered in this area, which is
thought to have been a common burial
ground for the royal Kim family. Another
interesting fact is that Sokkuram and the
main Buddha figure in it face directly
south-east. This is probably no chance
arrangement. One feature that distinguish¬
es Sokkuram from other stone cave tem¬
ples in India and China is that Sokkuram is
man-made. In other words, the builders
were able to site it in the direction of their
choice.
Sokkuram consists of a main domed hall,
a small square anteroom, and a fan-shaped
connecting corridor. The main hall was
constructed in granite and the smaller ante¬
room was built in wood with a tiled roof.
The method of construction follows long-
established Korean tradition in this form of
building, and it is especially noteworthy
that similar temples in India have the same
floor plan.
Eight standing figures carved in granite
adorn the walls of the anteroom. The
solemn-faced Deva kings guard the corri¬
dor. The entrance to the main hall is sup¬
ported by twin eight-sided pillars which are
decorated with lotus designs. In the centre
of the domed hall is the main Buddha
figure, seated on a large circular table, also
decorated with lotus designs, and sur¬
rounded by fifteen other figures including
his ten principal disciples.
The main figure, 3.26 metres tall and in a
sitting posture, breathes a sense of peace.
serenity and harmony, making it one of the
great Buddhist art treasures in the world.
Ten niches are cut into the wall just below
the dome, and these niches hold ten seated
Bodhisattvas. It is noteworthy that with the
exception of the main figure and the ten
seated Bodhisattvas all the other figures
are carved on granite slabs.
Traditionally the main figure was regard¬
ed as the Buddha Sakyamuni, (the "Sage
of the Sakya dynasty") but recent research
reveals that it is in fact Amitabha, the Bud¬
dha of infinite light.
The influence of Buddhist art, stretching
all the way from India, resulted in the cre¬
ation of a great masterpiece in Korea in the
middle of the eighth century. Sokkuram,
though small in area, has been the guardian
for more than twelve hundred years of
priceless art treasures, and the credit for
preserving these treasures must go in
large part to the strong faith and devotion
of so many Buddhist believers down the
centuries.
In our own time the preservation of the
art treasures in Sokkuram has been no easy
task. First of all, a section of the ceiling col¬
lapsed and a large scale operation had to be
mounted to repair the damage. Then in
1960 scholars became aware of a whole
series of problems concerning the conser¬
vation of these art treasures. Unesco pro¬
vided invaluable assistance in seeking solu¬
tions to these problems, and repair work
began in 1961 and continued for three
years. In the years to come stricter super¬
vision will be required, as well as research
into the many aspects of the question of
preserving these unique art treasures.
Hwang Su-young
The figure of Avalokitesvara, the bodhisattva ("Buddha-to-be") of
infinite compassion and mercy, is carved in granite on the walls of
Sokkuram's main hall. He is portrayed with eleven heads, looking in all
directions to save all creatures. The whole sculpture is 2.18 metres high.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
FROM ancient times right up until the
late nineteenth century, Korean
science anJ technology developed
within the shadow of the sophisticated civi¬
lization of the neighbouring giant China.
Yet the science and technology introduced
from China came to a land already techno¬
logically experienced in certain fields. The
men who lived in the Korean peninsula
around the tenth century B.C. had, for
example, already reached a high level in
metal-working and alloy-making. They
knew something about the advanced tech¬
niques of zinc-copper alloy-making, a tech¬
nology that differed from that of ancient
Chinese bronze-making methods.
With this technological tradition behind
them, the Koreans did not simply accept
innovations imported from China. They
modified and adapted them to local needs
and conditions and this often gave rise to
new inventions and discoveries. In metal-
working, for example, this national gift for
assimilation and adaptation was to lead to
the invention, two centuries before Guten¬
berg, of the first movable metal type, in
astronomy to the building in 647 A.D. of
the Ch'omsongdae observatory, the oldest
known astronomical observatory extant in
East Asia, in meteorology to the invention
in 1441 of the world's first rain gauge, in
alchemy and medicine to the compilation in
1433 of the Hyangyak chipsongbang, the
great collection of native Korean prescrip¬
tions.
In 108 B.C. the Han dynasty established
the Chinese colony of Lo-lang in north¬
western Korea and transplanted Chinese
metallurgy there. Under the influence of
Chinese artisans Korean metal-workers, in
the region of the lower Naktong river,
rapidly developed new iron smelting
techniques which were so successful that
even the colonists of Lo-lang and the
Japanese purchased Korean iron.
Ornaments and decorations excavated
from Silla tombs, especially golden crowns
JEON SANG-WOON is assistant professor of
natural sciences at the Sungshin College for
Women Teachers, Seoul. He has written widely
on the history of science and technology in
ancient Korea; his Science and Technology in
Korea: Traditional Instruments and Techniques
was published, in English, by the MIT Press in
1974.
A practical
approach
to science
by Jeon Sang-woon
The oldest astronomical observatory of its kind still extant in the East, the Ch'omsongdae
observatory was built at Kyongju in 647 A.D. Opinions differ as to the use made of this
structure. Some scholars believe that instruments for observing the moon and the stars
were installed on top of the tower, others that it was a dome observatory open to the
sky, while a third theory holds that it was a gnomon used to determine the twenty-four
agricultural seasons by the position and length of the shadow of the sun. Top left, a
Korean Bronze Age radial axe.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
and earrings, show that Korean metalwork-
' ing made great progress in the fifth and
sixth centuries A.D. Under the patronage
of the royal family and the aristocracy,
metallurgy gained momentum in the sixth
and seventh centuries with the flowering of
Buddhist culture, which encouraged the
casting of gilt bronze Buddhist images.
Buddhist bells of incomparable beauty,
which combined the functions of the tradi¬
tional chung bell and the t'o bell of old
China, bear witness to the innovative tech¬
niques developed by Korean artisans under
the Silla dynasty. In producing these bells,
the Silla artisans discovered a new bronze
alloy which was highly acclaimed in the
China of that time and which became so
renowned that it was said that "Persian
bronze is suitable for mirrors, but Silla cop¬
per (bronze) is superior for casting bells".
Astronomy is traditionally one of the first
branchés of science to be developed in
ancient cultures. Efforts to regulate agricul¬
tural production, which was the staff of
national life, combined with the influence
of the ancient Chinese astrological concept
that celestial phenomena were related to
affairs on earth, early led to the develop¬
ment of ch'onmun (heaven study) in
Korea. However, astronomy in ancient
Korea remained essentially subsidiary to
the Chinese mainstream, in spite of occa¬
sional original observations and indepen¬
dent researches.
In addition to their practical importance
for agriculture, astronomy and calendar-
making had special bearing on govern¬
ment. Astronomical charts were symbols
of royal authority, and under the ancient
dynasties the results of astronomical obser¬
vations were recorded in the form of star
maps. In Korea the first of these probably
dates back to the Koguryo period. Star
charts in the Koguryo tombs represent the
constellations, as well as the sun and
moon, on circles, placing the sun to the
east and the moon to the west, and depic¬
ting the four "celestial palaces" centered
on the cardinal points: the Blue Dragon,
Black Tortoise and Snake, White Tiger,
and Red Phoenix.
The armillary sphere was the basic astro¬
nomical instrument of ancient and medi¬
eval times in East Asia. First manufactur¬
ed in China around the second century
B.C., the instrument is believed to have
been brought into Korea sometime bet¬
ween the Three Kingdoms era and the age
of Unified Silla. Instruments similar in prin¬
ciple to the armillary sphere seem to have
continued in use during the Koryo dynasty
era.
The succeeding dynasties of Korea were
extremely sensitive to meteorological and
astronomical phenomena, especially solar
and lunar eclipses. The prediction of solar
and lunar eclipses was a part of the monar¬
chic ritual which augmented the dignity of
the rulers in the eyes of his people. Many,
indeed, are the royal astronomers and
meteorologists who lost their positions or
even their lives because of failure to pre¬
dict such occurrences correctly.
Developments in astronomy during the .
Three Kingdoms era (57 B.C. to 668 A.D.)
are exemplified by the construction of the
Ch'omsongdae observatory. A graceful.
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
bottle-shaped stone tower, nine metres
high, the observatory was built at Kyongju
in 647, the sixteenth year of the reign of
Queen Sondok. Its unusual shape indicates
that it was built in accordance with the tra¬
ditional round heaven, square earth theory
of ancient China.
This observatory, whose shape embo¬
dies Korean aesthetic preferences, is of
particular interest in several respects. First
of all, the tower permitted the measure¬
ment of the sun's shadow, much in the
way of a gnomon, to ascertain the season.
Furthermore, the window facing the south
opens in such a way that at noon on the
vernal and autumnal equinoxes, sunlight
covers the floor inside, whereas sunlight is
completely absent at both solstices.
The Ch'omsongdae was probably the
centre of astronomical activity of the King¬
dom of Silla. It served as the meridian for
astronomical observations throughout the
Silla period and gave the standard point of
reference for measurement of the four car¬
dinal points and directions. The sides of the
square stone slab on top faced the four car¬
dinal points of the compass and diagonal
projections from the corners pointed to the
four intercardinal points ; the window
faced due south. The area surrounding the
Ch'omsongdae was paved with flagstones,
presumably to prevent the erection of
houses and thus secure an open space
in all directions to facilitate unobstructed
observations.
The systematic measurement of time in
Korea is thought to have begun some¬
where around the beginning of the Chris¬
tian era and fragments of a sundial from the
Silla era are still to be seen in the Kyongju
Museum. The decimal sundial developed
during the early years of the Yi Dynasty is
one of the most accurate sundials ever
invented by man.
But the usefulness of sundials is con¬
fined to sunny days and during the Three
Kingdoms era the clepsydra, or water
clock, came to be regarded as a more use¬
ful and reliable time indicator. The first
clepsydras were made in 718.
When, in 1392, the Yi dynasty moved the
capital to Hansong (present-day Seoul),
there arose the need to install a new stan¬
dard clock, and accordingly a kyongnu
(night clepsydra) was installed in 1398 in
the centre of Seoul. Together with the new
clepsydra a belfry was erected to ring the
standard time throughout the royal
capital.
The armillary sphere was the basic
astronomical instrument of ancient
and medieval times in East Asia.
Armillary spheres were introduced
into Korea from China and the
armillary clock reached a high
standard of perfection during the
reign of King Sejong. (1) Detail of an
armillary clock built in 1669 and now
preserved in the Koryo University
Museum, Seoul. It incorporates the
principles of the Western striking
clock as well as features of Chinese
and Arabic clock-making traditions.
King Sejong's reign also saw the
invention, in 1442, of the world's first
rain gauge and in the same year the
first network of rainfall measuring
stations in the world was established.
(2) Korean rain gauge made in 1770
exactly in accordance with the
specifications established in 1442.
Systematic wind observation was
also developed under King Sejong. A
cloth streamer, attached to a bamboo
pole and placed on a stone column,
indicated wind direction and velocity.
(3) Stone anemoscope stand dating
from the 17th century.
Incense sticks or joss sticks were also
used in Korea for measuring time, espe¬
cially in Buddhist and Taoist temples. From
an early period attempts were made to
measure time so that the various rituals and
ceremonies might be punctually perform¬
ed. In the course of their rites, the Buddhist
monks learned that incense sticks burn at a
constant rate. They eventually found
incense sticks to be more reliable for accu¬
rate measurement of time than incense
powder.
Meteorology in the modern sense had its
start in Korea in the early Yi dynasty era
(fifteenth century). Until then a system pre¬
sumably devised in the Koryo era was
used, whereby the depth of rainfall was
gauged, and the statistics thus obtained
were consolidated by the provincial gover¬
nors and reported to the Board of Taxa¬
tion, which periodically recorded the fig¬
ures. At first this practice was not conduc¬
ted at regular intervals but only during the
farming seasons or in times of severe
drought when the method was used to
measure the aridity of the soil.
The first recorded mention of this
measurement appears in the Sejong sillok
(veritable records of the King Sejong era),
bearing the date May 3, 1423: "It rained
tonight, penetrating earth to the depth of
approximately 1 ch'on (about 2.13 cm.)."
Heavy rains and severe droughts alterna¬
ted around the year 1441, rendering
impracticable the conventional methods of
measurement. The difficulties encountered
led to the invention of the more scientific
method of collecting rainwater in a vessel
specially shaped for the purpose of accu¬
rate measurement the world's first rain
gauge.
The second most important meteorologi¬
cal phenomenon for agriculture after rain is
wind velocity and direction. Thoroughly
familiar with the influence of wind on farm
crops, the meteorologists of the Yi dynasty
took special care to observe wind direction
closely. An anemoscope, called a p'ung-
gijuk was set up for that purpose. There is
no clear indication when the observation of
wind direction was actually started, but the
wind gauge was erected in the era of King
Sejong to determine wind direction from
the flow of a streamer.
Wind direction was expressed in one of
twenty-four directions. The wind velocity is
presumed to have been classified, as in the
case of the volume of rainfall, into eight
degrees. For instance, a wind strong
enough to uproot a tree was referred to as
a taep'ung (great wind) and one violent
enough to strip the roof tiles was called
p'okp'ung (violent wind). There are specific
mentions of these two classes of wind.
Although the origins of alchemy are lost
in antiquity, Chinese alchemy, with its
emphasis on physical immortality, was
more closely linked to medicine than to
metallurgy. Alchemy in Korea, as was the
case in China, was associated chiefly with
the "way of the immortals" and was a
branch of Taoist learning. For Koreans, as
for Chinese alchemists, on the whole the
transmutation of base to precious metals
was not important.
Korean alchemy dates back to the fifth
century, when, under the influence of
Taoism, efforts were made to manufacture
an elixir of immortality. But Koreans had a
good deal of chemical and pharmacological
knowledge well before that time. Accor¬
ding to ancient Chinese documents
Koreans produced medicine and poisons
well before the birth of Christ.
There are many folk tales in Korean
about men who spent their lives wandering
deep in the mountains and valleys in search
of several-hundred year-old ginseng. There
is no doubt that these stories have a philo¬
sophical background in Chinese alchemy.
By about the eighth century, the folk
pharmacological knowledge of Silla had
been systematized into an academic disci¬
pline under Chinese influence. Eleven
medicines of Korean origin were included
in T'ao Hung-ching's pharmacopoeia. By
the ninth century another twenty-two
kinds were known to Japan and China.
In the tenth century, Koryo's medicine
was further subjected to the influence of
Indian medicine. With the rise of Buddhism
Koryo was able to build a foundation for
the development of its own pharmacology
CONTINUED PAGE 60
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Turtle base of the now-missing centre
stone of the tomb of King Kim ln-mun at
Kyongju (7th century).
Photo © Korean Overseas Information Service, Seoul
Six good
turns
from
the turtle
by Zo Za-Yong
Prehistoric turtle design on a rock at Pan'gu-dae,
Ulsan, in the province of south Kyongsang.
Photo © KorPan Overseas Information Service, Seoul
Afew years ago a young Korean sailor named Kim Chong-nam
fell overboard late one night while his ship was in mid-
Pacific. For hours he struggled desperately to keep afloat
until he suddenly came up against a huge turtle. He grasped the
turtle's back, hauled himself on to it and lay there for thirteen
hours until he was rescued by a passing Swedish ship.
During the middle of a recent, long, hot summer, another giant
turtle emerged from the sea at Haeun-dae beach near the city of
Pusan and crawled to a nearby tavern. A crowd gathered to watch
it as it dug into the sand and laid its eggs. Interpreting this as a
good omen, the tavern keeper ran to the turtle as it was making its
way back to the water, hung her necklace around its neck and
gratefully sent it on its way back to sea.
The Korean press latched on to both of these "human interest"
stories with fascination, for the turtle is a reptile which commands
strong affection and respect among Koreans. It has always played
a major role in their folklore and traditions, while the wealth of
symbolic meanings associated with it have for centuries inspired
Korean sculptors and painters as well as the creators of folk art and
handicrafts.
The turtle plays six major roles in Korean folklore. First and fore¬
most it is the messenger of the water spirit, just as the tiger is the
messenger of the mountain spirit (1). Sitting astride a huge dra¬
gon, the white-bearded Water Spirit (or Dragon Spirit) lives
beneath the sea in the Dragon Palace and controls all affairs rela¬
ted to water, the sea, rivers, ponds, rain, storms and floods. The
industrious turtle is the only messenger capable of communicating
between the Dragon Palace and the earthly world.
Secondly, the turtle is a sacred animal of good omen, along with
the dragon, the oriental unicorn [Chi-lin) and the phoenix.
Thirdly, it is one of the ten longevity symbols known as the
Sipchang-Saeng, the others being the crane, the deer, the pine,
the bamboo, the fungus of immortality, rock, water, cloud and
sun. Of the three animals in this group the turtle is the only one
believed to live ten thousand years.
As the guardian of the north, the turtle is also one of the four
cardinal direction spirits, along with the blue dragon, the white
tiger and the red bird.
In its fifth role, that of carrier of the eight trigrams, the turtle is
one of the earliest holy animals in Oriental mythology. The trigrams
were magic writings which were supposed to have been carried by
an old turtle to the first man, Pok-Hi [Fu-hsi in Chinese) on the
bank of the Lo Sui River.
(1) These two earthly spirits, together with the various heavenly spirits such as the
Seven Stars, the South Pole Star, the Four Cardinal Stars, the Twelve Zodiac
symbols, the Sun and Moon, the Wind and Clouds, Rain and Thunder, constitute the
core of the Korean shamanistic tradition. Each of these spirits is associated by Korean
people with a sacred animal.
20 ZA-YONG is director of the Emilie Museum, Seoul. He is the author of
The Spirit of the Korean Tiger, 1972, The Life of Buddha, 7575, and
Korean Folk Painting, 1978.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Turtle-shaped celadon wine-flask
decorated with a peony pattern in white
against a dark green background (15th or
16th century).
Photo © Korean Overseas Information Service, Seoul
Finally, the turtle is connected with divination through its hex¬
agonal shell pattern which in ancient times was held to be of mys¬
terious origin. This pattern gave rise to complicated philosophical
interpretations, and a special fortune-telling technique was devised
whereby the shell was heated and the crack-lines thus caused were
analyzed.
Korean history is rich in stories illustrating the attributions of the
turtle. The rescue of the lucky sailor Kim Chong-nam itself has a
historic precedent. During the rule of the Paekche dynasty (18
B.C. -660 A.D.) a monk named Pangje was pushed from a boat by
bandits while he was transporting temple treasures. He was saved
by a mighty turtle that carried him to safety. The story of Chu¬
mong, the founder of the Koguryo dynasty, is a variation on the
same theme. While fleeing from a band of assassins, he came to a
river. At this critical moment the Dragon Spirit sent a multitude of
turtles to form a bridge across which Chumong made good his
escape.
According to one account, the six leaders of the six tribes of
Kaya, who formed a Kaya dynasty (42-562 A.D.), were born from
six huge eggs on "Turtle Mountain". The record states that the
people of Kaya gathered at the Holy Mountain and sang the song
that attracts turtles, and it is usually interpreted that the eggs were
laid by a turtle.
During the Silla dynasty the famous beauty Suro was carried
away by the Dragon Emperor. The story has it that a great crowd
assembled, singing the song of the sea, as a giant turtle brought
her back from the Dragon Palace.
A familiar figure in the visual arts, the turtle also appears in clas¬
sical literature, notably in a number of novels written under the Yi
dynasty, such as "The Story of the Hare and the Turtle" (Pyol-
chubu-ion), "The Voyage to the Dragon Palace" (Kumeo
Sin-hwal, and "The Story of Sim-Ch'ong".
Turtles appear comparatively rarely in classical Oriental painting
but although painting in general seems less important than other
forms of "turtle art", it is invaluable in helping to explain the
symbolic background, for each piece of turtle symbolism is expli¬
citly depicted. In Korean folk painting benevolent turtles are shown
carrying rabbits on their shoulders back to the Dragon Palace and
feature in paintings of Sa-Ryong, the four sacred animals of good
omen.
The sacred book-carrying turtle is often shown in the character
design paintings of the Yi dynasty, referring to the legend of the
turtle which bore the knowledge of the eight trigrams, while the
turtle as guardian of one of the four cardinal directions is found in
the tomb murals of the Koguryo dynasty. The latter symbolism
seems to have died out later as there is little trace of such painting
under the Yi dynasty, and the turtle came to appear most com¬
monly as one of the ten longevity symbols.
However, stone carving is the branch of Korean art in which
turtles are most prolific, especially in the form known as Kwi-Bu,
turtle-shaped stones which form the base of monuments and buil¬
dings. Over a hundred of these turtle stones, dating from the Uni¬
fied Silla period to the Yi dynasty, have survived at the graves of
kings and at Buddhist temples. The base stone is combined with a
dragon cap stone which completes the monument, and the turtle
in this art form may be either the turtle of good omen, the guardian
spirit or the symbol of longevity.
Some turtle stones (like the Sa-Ryong paintings) feature
strange, stylized turtles with dragon's heads. Their significance
can only be understood in reference to the iconography of other
sacred animals with a monster's head such as the chi-lin (unicorn),
the hai-tai, the lion, the white tiger and the dragon. Each of these
figures is portrayed as a real animal such as a deer, a lion, a tiger or
a snake, but is equipped with the monster-mask known as the"
Pyok-sa, whose purpose is to repel evil.
Although this type of turtle art originated in China under the Han
dynasty and was later introduced into Korea during the period of
the Three Kingdoms, many Orientalists claim that it was in Korea
that it attained maturity with the creation of masterpieces such as
those found in the Silla monument of King Muyol.
The influence of the turtle in Korean life and history extends
much further than art and folklore. In the 16th century Admiral Yi
Sun-sin designed a "turtle ship" which is often considered to be
the first ironclad battleship in the world. The turtle motif was
found on a variety of everyday tools and utensils; it adorned the
foundations of buildings, seals, stones in gardens, water tubs and
stone containers. Nearly a hundred magnificent "turtle bottles"
made for royal officials out of soapstone or bronze have survived
from the Yi dynasty, and together with gunpowder boxes, door
locks and fortune-tellers' magic boxes, bear witness to the cherish¬
ed place which this reptile came to hold in Korean life as a symbol
of longevity and good fortune and as a guardian against evil.
Zo Za-Yong
Photo © Zo Za-Yong, Emilie Museum, Seoul
The Taoist Immortal and the turtle, symbol of longevity, as
portrayed in an ink painting by an unknown 18th-century artist.
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Paintings magic
and mundane
Folk art with a wealth
of significance for everyday life
the least appreciated. Korean scholars
regarded painting as a scholarly hobby and
tended to look down on the professional
painters attached to the Tohwa-so, or
Office of Art, who were recruited from the
Chungin, or artisan class.
Conventionally, Korean painting has
been grouped into two major
categories pure painting and "functional"
painting. Yet although there is now no
such thing as a really pure, academic form
of painting, any more than there exists an
exclusively "functional" painting, this clas¬
sification still often dominates the thinking
of artists, art historians, connoisseurs and
art dealers. The traditional Confucian scho¬
lar's scorn of popular paintings that were
colourful and contained folk motifs was at
the basis of this idea that unsigned "func¬
tional" paintings were a low form of art.
"Functional" in this context has a very
wide sense. Among "functional" paintings
were included, for example, those brought
out in accordance with old Korean custom
for specific seasonal festivals, such as New
Year's Day, the first day of spring, and the
fifth day of the fifth month. Old records as
well as those paintings that remain indicate
that most of these paintings included lon¬
gevity symbols, happiness symbols and
by Zo Za-Yong
THE rediscovery and re-evaluation
of a great wealth of long-forgotten
Korean folk paintings has been
one of the most exciting cultural events of
the past decade. These popular works of
art, often treasured family heirlooms, have
remained hidden away in private houses
and it was not until some ten years ago that
they started to be collected and systemati¬
cally studied.
These newly-discovered treasures have
come to be classified rather ambiguously as
"folk painting", but only if we examine the
historical position of the artist in ancient
Korean society does this classification
begin to make sense.
Painting in Korea has always been
closely associated with Confucian scholar¬
ship. A good Confucian had to excel in
three different skills: poetry, calligraphy
and painting. Poetry was the most impor¬
tant skill, while calligraphy was valued as
an art form. Of the three skills painting was
The twelve thousand needle-point peaks of the Diamond Mountains, a
vast massif running downwards from the north central part of the
Korean peninsula to the east coast and one of the three sacred
mountain ranges of Korea, have inspired a great variety of landscape
paintings and drawings. Left, a sketch in which the peaks seem as
though carved from a piece of crystal encircled with a Chinese
ideogram. Below, this painting of the mountains where they reach the
sea could almost be a view of a modern seaside town. Opposite page,
detail from an 18th-century screen over ten metres long. The serried
ranks of pinnacles seem like a ghostly congregation of monks and
priests engaged in some mysterious sacred rite.
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
r. ..
f Ï ' \ f '
i' :
;
. i
l \
: Y '.. V /> . \ Il J
ï
> 7 J
J''
I.
7^( .OJÍ
/'A ; ft
í/VÍ/ ' Y,>
V/í
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
, guardian ¡mages to ward off evil spirits and
in this sense fulfilled a "useful", even
"magical" function.
Thus the old Confucian-oriented Korean
scholars classified virtually everything out¬
side the elitist areas of calligraphy and lit¬
erati or Zen painting, created for the intel¬
lectual diversion of the scholar class, as
folk painting. Yet a great deal of this paint¬
ing was not folk painting at all in the sense
that this term is used elsewhere in the
world, i.e. meaning a simple form of paint¬
ing executed by amateurs and with no refe¬
rence to the rules of any school of art.
Korean folk painting therefore, develo¬
ped as an art of an entire nation, of all clas¬
ses, directly related to a particular life style;
and although in many cases we have no
idea whatever of the individual names of
these painters, we are at least aware of the
type of people in each group. They ranged
from wandering craftsmen to court paint¬
ers, all of whom participated in this popular
art.
The first group consisted of painters
known as "passing guests", wanderers
who travelled from one village to another
producing domestic paintings at individual
households. Of course most of them were
naive peasant craftsmen, but some skilled
artists were found among them, usually
those who had failed to become court
painters.
The second group was made up of
painter-monks. Talented monks who recei¬
ved severe training from a master usually
became professional painters and engaged
in producing various Buddhist ritual paint¬
ings for temples. Those who failed to sur¬
vive the severe regimen often turned to the
life of wandering painter-monks, travelling
from one temple to another and earning
their living by painting murals for temple
walls.
The third group consisted of the court
painters. As far as social position is concer¬
ned, a court painter was the highest rank
obtainable in Korea for an artist. It is often
thought that the works of these men were
only in the classical style, but they were
also hired to decorate palaces and to pro¬
vide ornamental designs.
Folk paintings were to be found in the
royal court, Buddhist temples, Shaman
shrines, Klsaeng drinking houses, altars
and private houses. Some themes were
reserved exclusively for the court while
others were used only in temples, shrines
and upon altars. The remainder were used
by ordinary folk to decorate their homes
and to enrich everyday life.
In a Korean home certain works of art
can be installed permanently while others
are brought out only during certain seasons
or on special occasions. A few themes are
suitable anywhere within the house, but
others are intended to be placed in one par¬
ticular location in order to produce felici¬
tous results. For example, the door paint¬
ing of a tiger to repel evil belongs to the
front entrance, while a painting or print of a
dog is intended for a storage room door.
Screens with representations of flowers
and birds or babies belong to bedroom
walls.
Korean folk painting is often classified in
terms of its relationship to the concepts of
Confucianism, Taoism, Buddhism or Sha¬
manism. This classification is valid when
there is a clear religious identification:
paintings on the theme of Buddha's Life
are Buddhist painting, and of the Taoist
Immortals are Taoist painting; illustrations
of Confucian teaching are Confucian paint¬
ing and of the Mountain Spirit are Shaman
painting. However, at times these religious
motifs are so complexly interwoven that it
becomes impossible to determine to which
specific religion each belongs. The end
result of this is a general impression that in
Korea there is Taoist Buddhism, Buddhistic
Shamanism and Taoistic Shamanism, and
that the thought behind religious ritual
painting is actually the Shamanistic folk
content of each religion rather than its aca¬
demic aspect.
Analysis of Korean domestic paintings
manifesting various symbols reveals a com¬
mon denominator which interlocks these
religious ideas tightly together. This com¬
mon denominator is an inborn desire for
long and happy life and protection against
evil spirits. Thus these works of art are no
more than the Korean expression of a uni¬
versal aspiration. Though there are a cer¬
tain number of paintings which may be
grouped as ethnographic, such ethnic
themes do not characterize Korean folk
painting as much as the universal themes.
A striking characteristic of this painting
is the extent of stylization, which leads to
abstract art, expressing man's dreams,
imagination, symbolism, love, humour,
satire and sense of fantasy. There is no
attempt at realism and there is a filling in of
space in contrast with the aesthetics of
open space typical of classic Oriental
painting.
The second aspect is animism, which is
positively expressed in all kinds of animal,
rock and tree paintings and which is really a
reflection of Shamanistic animism. A third
style, usually referred to as naive style, is
developed by a combination of abstraction
and animism which portrays a genuine,
childlike world where a man's heart is more
important than his name.
The whole range of these paintings deals
with the life of the masses, often in a most
unconventional and unorthodox manner.
Dating back to ancient Korea, some of
these paintings are serious and others are
frivolous; some deal with imaginary things
and others with real objects; some have
religious overtones; some of them were
done by expert hands such as those of pro¬
fessional court painters and others by utter
amateurs.
Whatever the subjects and whoever the
artists, there is one thing common to them
all they are uniquely Korean and insepa¬
rably attached to the actual lives of the
people of the time.
Zo Za-Yong
42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
The imposing majesty of the mountains of
Korea gave rise to popular belief in the
existence of a Spirit of the Mountain.
Among the various ways In which artists
depicted the Spirit the most frequent was
in the guise of an amiable old gentleman
with his arm resting affectionately on his
friend the White Tiger, as in this 18th-
century painting on hemp.
Photo © Zo Za-Yong, Emilie Museum, Seoul
Cascading waterfalls have long been a
favourite theme in oriental art. The words
of the Chinese philosopher Lao-tzu:
"Water is the weakest and most gentle of
things, yet it overcomes the strongest and
the most resistant", seem to be
epitomized in paintings below in which
the power of the dragon, the Spirit of
Water, contrasts with the outward
tranquillity of flowing mountain rivers.
Photos © Zo Za-Yong, Emilie Museum, Seoul
43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
An aureole
of legend on
a golden crown
Ancient bronze ornament from a wooden
staff used by a shaman to lure spirits
down to earth. Birds played a major role
in shamanistic ritual and symbolism and
shamans donned wings or feathers to
equip themselves for their journey to the
spirit world.
Colour page
The luck of
the leaping carp
For Koreans a carp leaping from the
waves was a harbinger of good fortune. It
might herald the birth of a son or presage
some great success in life. The carp was
thought to live for a hundred years and in
old age to turn into a benevolent dragon
which repelled evil spirits. Leaping carp
shown here is a detail from a painting on
rice paper (55 cm. by 95 cm.) by an
anonymous 18th-century Korean artist.
Photo © Zo Za-Yong, Emilie Museum, Seoul
by Li Ogg
ON 24 September 1921, a group of children were playing on
a patch of waste ground in Kyongju, once the capital of
the ancient kingdom of Silla which was founded in the
first century B.C. and later held sway over most of the Korean
peninsula. Suddenly the children noticed a handful of glass beads
lying on the ground. Unwittingly they had stumbled across the site
of a burial mound, once imposingly high but by then considerably
flattened, which contained the tomb of a king who had reigned
sometime around the beginning of the sixth century A.D. Excava- k
tions brought to light some thirty thousand glass beads and a fabu- f
LI OGG is assistant professor at the University of Paris VII and director of
the Centre of Korean Studies at the Collège de France. His Histoire de la
Corée was published in 1969 in the Que Sais-je ? series by Presses Univer-
sia tires de France.
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
s
ñr,
yg
/
'\P^
b»5
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Colour page
Magnificent gold crown bedecked with
comma-shaped jewels of green jade (top
right) was once worn by a 6th-century
ruler of the Silla kingdom in Korea.
Discovered at Kyongju, the ancient capital
of Silla, it incorporates a wealth of
symbolism (see article this page). Also
found in the "Gold Crown Tomb" was the
elaborate gold belt (below) made of 39
openwork plates and 17 pendants. It is
embellished with motifs of a type then
current in China where such belts were
traditionally hung with pendants
representing objects found in every
functionary's saddlebag, such as a sword,
a knife, a whetstone and a flint. Note the
fish-shaped pendant of a kind which in
T'ang China indicated its wearer's rank.
The use of this type of belt may have
originated in ancient times among the
nomads of the northern steppes. Top left,
gold ornament dating from the early 6th
century. It was discovered in the tomb of
King Muryong (see photo page 25) at
Kongju capital of the kingdom of
Paekche.
Photos © Korean Overseas Information Service, Seoul
Photo © Han Sok-hong, Seoul
Photo © Dong-wha Publishing Co , Seoul - Museum of the University of Taegu
These earthenware ducks with human feet date from Ancient Silla times.
Birds acted as intermediaries between the shaman and the spirit world.
L lous hoard of jewellery. The most spectacular find was an exquisite
" golden crown which in spite of its extreme fragility had survived
intact. As a consequence of this discovery the tomb became
known as The Tomb of the Golden Crown.
The crown's design was rich in symbolism which, when deci¬
phered, provided precious information about the shadowy myths
and legends then current in east Asia and about the religious vision
of the universe which prevailed among the ancient Koreans.
The crown takes us back to the age of the shamans, who profes¬
sed beliefs which had reached Korea from the Siberian Altai moun¬
tains and practised magical nature-cults based on an obscure com¬
plicity between men and animals. For the hunters of ancient
Korea, the animal was a tutelary being. To slay a beast was to
make a sacrifice to the celestial being which would allow the hun¬
ter to arrogate for himself the dead animal's physical and spiritual
attributes. Hunting rituals and legends like the story of Chumong,
the founder of the kingdom of Koguryo, strikingly illustrate this
complicity between men and animals.
Legend has it that a daughter of the Lord of the River, a water-
deity, was out walking when she met Hämosu, the son of the
Celestial Emperor and became friendly with him. Later she concei¬
ved and brought forth an egg. The egg was thrown first to a dog
and then to a pig, but neither of them would touch it. Then it was
left on the highway, where the horses and oxen gave it a wide
berth. Next it was placed in a field, where the birds protected it
with their wings. Attempts to crack it proved vain. From the egg
emerged handsome Chumong.
Animals were thus linked to men by deep undercurrents of com¬
prehension which brought into being a whole language of animal
symbolism, of which the Golden Crown of Kyongju (see colour
photo opposite) is a glittering and instructive expression.
For the ancient Koreans, the universe consisted of three worlds:
heaven, earth and the nether regionthe kingdom of the dead
which was also often known as the world of water. A shaman had
to "dominate" these three worlds, often by changing into different
beings, as illustrated in the story of how Chumong's father sought
the hand of the Lord of the River's daughter.
To put the suitor to the test, so the story goes, the Lord of the
River transformed himself into a carp; straightaway Chumong's
father turned himself into an otter and caught the carp. Next the
Lord of the River assumed the form of a stag, but this time his
antagonist turned into a wolf and hunted him down. Finally the
Lord of the River changed into a pheasant, whereupon Chumong's
father became a falcon. By this time the Lord of the River knew for
sure that he was dealing with the Celestial Emperor's son. He con¬
sented to the match and decreed that the marriage should take |
place. I
47
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Mounted archers and their dogs are shown in
hot pursuit of stags, deer and tigers in this
wall painting from the Tomb of the Dancing
Figures, on the T'ung-kou plain, south
Manchuria. For ancient Koreans hunting was
imbued with ritual reflecting the unity of the
world of humans and the animal world.
1
Photo © Aurora Publishers, Leningrad
, The Golden Crown of Kyongju, like the legend of Chumong's
birth, is dominated by two wings. They are attached to the pointed
cap within the crown. They afford protection but they also sym¬
bolize the ascent to heaven. A piece of headgear discovered at
Chunghwa, in the land Chumong once ruled, incorporates a
mysterious three-footed bird which has the same religious signifi¬
cance. But the significance of bird-symbolism on ancient Korean
crowns does not end here. The Wei Che, a Chinese text from the
third century A.D., recounts how among the Han of southern
Korea the dead were made to "fly" using birds' feathers. Mongo¬
lian shamans felt themselves transformed into flying creatures as
soon as they put wings on their backs. Shamanistic priests in Sibe¬
ria and Manchuria also decked out their costumes and head¬
dresses with birds' feathers. A gold and bronze alloy crown dis¬
covered at Yoshino in Japan bears traces which prove that it was
once adorned with wings, thus suggesting that this bird-cult may
have reached as far as Japan.
For the ancient Koreans, birds' wings were not the only means
of ascending to heaven. A flying horse, like the eight-hoofed steed
painted on birch bark (see photo page 25) could also perform the
task.
Were the wings which dominate the Golden Crown meant to
symbolize those of a real bird or of some mythical flying beast?
Might they not have been the wings of a cock, the bird whose role
in Silla mythology was so important that the kingdom was known
as the "Land of the Cock and the Forest"? In the Samguk Yusa, a
thirteenth century Korean text, it is also recorded that the people
of Silla venerated the cock as a god and used its wings for orna¬
mental purposes.
In ancient Korean beliefs the cock symbolized the sun and was
the counterpart of the mythical Stone Age reindeer with golden
antlers which flew across Siberia from east to west.
In Korea the stag, another religious symbol, corresponds to the
Siberian reindeer, and attached to the circlet of gold which forms
the base of the Golden Crown are two antler-shaped projections.
The antler motif can also be discerned in crowns from the king¬
doms of Koguryo and Paekche, although some believe that these
designs are simply floral decorations reflecting the influence of
Chinese art. The people of Paekche, Silla's western neighbours,
believed that a stag taken during a royal hunt was sin or divine,
while a Chinese text describes how the aristocracy of Koguryo, the
State which dominated the north of the Korean peninsula during
the period of the Three Kingdoms, attached gold and silver "ears"
to their helmets. It is possible that the word ears might have
been a copyist's error,, since the Chinese characters for "ears" are
According to ancient shamanistic
beliefs, bird-spirits hold sway in the
Upper World, while the nether
world is ruled by mammals. (1)
Drawing of a Tungus shaman
whose reindeer-costume enabled
him to descend to the Nether
World. By doffing his head-dress he
could also rise to the Upper World.
Similar beliefs are found in Siberian
mythology. (2) Fabulous beast
combining features of deer, eagle
and tiger was found tattooed on
the embalmed body of a chief
buried at Pazyryk in Siberia (5th or
4th century B.C.). (3) Ornament in
openwork gold leaf adorned the
crown of a Paekche queen. It was
unearthed In the tomb of King
Muryong at Kongju.
48
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
similar to those which signify "the horns of a stag". This in turn
calls to mind the iron horns with which Tungu shamans adorned
their headgear, thus evoking the antlers of a stag. Shamanistic
headgear was similarly adorned with iron reindeer antlers among
the Siberians of eastern Ket.
Other, equally venerable animals also figure on the Golden
Crown, from the base of which hang a large number of hook- or
claw-shaped pieces of jade. They recall the bear claws, some real,
some made of iron, which adorned the boots of Tungu shamans,
and probably represent those of wild beasts such as the tiger,
which was worshipped by the people of Ye, north of Silla.
The plant world appears on the Golden Crown in the form of
tiny, metal-shaped plaques. The best example of a floral motif on
an ancient Korean crown, however, is the corolla featured on the
crown of a Paekche queen (see photo page 48). An ancient docu¬
ment also describes how the king and aristocracy of Paekche wore
crowns adorned with gold and silver flowers.
As for the nether world, it is depicted on the crown by the zigzag
pattern, evoking waves, which runs along the circlet.
At the front of the circlet are three tree-shaped uprights. Each
one has three branches which symbolically represent the three
worlds of the Korean cosmogony. The same religious symbolism is
found in Japanese mythology in a head-dress made from the
C/eyera japónica flower. In Korean cults the tree is often replaced
by a post which represents the centre of the earthly world and
makes it possible to communicate with heaven. Among the Sibe¬
rians and the Tungu, this post was sometimes capped with birds.
Ancient Chinese texts record how in the south of ancient Korea a
post was planted in worship of the kuisin or spirits, and a bell and a
kind of drum were fixed to the top.
With its green jade jewels and fluttering gold sequins, the fragile
Golden Crown of Kyongju thus affords a glimpse at the beliefs of a
long-vanished world.
UOgg
49
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[
A practical approach
to science
(continued from page 37)
by combining the local variant of T'ang
medicine which it inherited from Silla and
the pharmacological information it got
directly from Sung China. Koryo estab¬
lished two state-run medical schools and
added a specialization in medicine to the
state civil service examinations which were
inaugurated in 958. In this the government
was following the lead of T'ang China.
The origins of Korean science can be
traced back through the technical tradition
of craftsmen who passed on their practical
experiences and skill from generation to
generation. They devoted themselves to
empirically verifiable phenomena and were
little concerned by theoretical explana¬
tions. The result of attaching importance to
empirical research instead of theory was
that technical developments did not grow
out of systematic experimentation.
It was very difficult for those craftsmen,
who were officials supported by their
government, tó have any opportunity to
follow their own bent because they had to
engage in practical research and manufac¬
ture dictated by government policy. In
addition craftsmen were part of society's
strict class system and were given little
freedom of thought or movement.
Their work was made more mechanical
and less creative than it might have been
because of the lack of social pressures and
rewards for innovation and exploration.
It was only in the seventeenth and eigh¬
teenth centuries that these traditional tech¬
niques acquired a systematic scientific
basis, thanks to the advocates of sirhak, or
practical learning, who rejected the idea of
the superiority of philosophical speculation
and adopted the slogan silsa kusl (verifica¬
tion of truth on the basis of factual studies)
thus opening the way to the introduction of
Western science and the initiation of a
scientific reformation.
Jeon Sang-woon
Unesco's General Conference
Ornamental plaque from an ancient
Korean door lock. The inscription in the
inner circle means, literally, "Ten
thousand years of great peace", a form of
salutation roughly equivalent to "long live
the king". The outer ring inscriptions are
expressions of wishes for happiness,
many sons, health, wealth, honours,
peace and longevity.
THE twentieth session of Unesco's
General Conference, which opened in
Paris on 24 October 1978, ended its
work on 28 November after approving the
Organization's programme for 1979 and
1980. The Conference, which was chaired
by Mr. Napoleon LeBlanc of Canada, voted
a budget of $303 million to carry out the pro¬
gramme, an increase of six per cent com¬
pared with the budget for 1977 and 1978.
"The spirit of co-operation and the desire
for consensus (...) emerge strengthened
from this session of the General Conference
and have even acquired greater signifi¬
cance", declared the Director-General of
Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow in his
final address.
"There can be no doubt," Mr. M'Bow
declared, "that the Declaration [on funda¬
mental principles concerning the contribu¬
tion of the mass media to strengthening
peace and international understanding, pro¬
motion of human rights, and to countering
racism, apartheid and incitement to war]
has been a central theme of the twentieth
session of the General Conference in view
of the place it has occupied in the discus¬
sion. (...) The ovation with which this
Declaration was adopted will without
doubt remain one of the most intense and
moving moments I have experienced as
Unesco's Director-General (...). This happy
issue is all the more remarkable because
the probability of failure appeared so high.
It is an illustration of the triumph of a
patient desire for conciliation which never
flagged".
The Director-General went on to point
out that other important decisions with
ethical implications had been taken and
should not be forgotten, confirming as they
did Unesco's mission in this sphere of
human activity. He stressed the signifi¬
cance of the unanimous adoption of the
Declaration on Race and Racial Prejudice:
"For the first time in the United Nations
system, and even in the history of
mankind's long efforts to extirpate racism
and racial prejudice, the international com¬
munity will dispose of a text which, without
being legally binding, represents a moral
engagement covering all aspects of the
problem."
Mr. M'Bow also recalled with satisfaction
that the statutes of the new Intergovern¬
mental Committee to promote the return of
cultural objects to their country of origin or
their restitution in case of illicit appropria¬
tion had been unanimously adopted.
The Director-General stressed that the
General Conference had "shown a strong
desire to see Unesco step up its action in
the field of science and technology" and
had also manifested "the wish of Member
States to see Unesco maintain and extend
the particular responsibility for science
falling to it within the United Nations sys¬
tem on the occasion of the United Nations
Conference on Science and Technology in
the service of Development".
The Conference, which was attended by
delegations from all Member States (whose
number rose from 144 to 146 with the addi¬
tion of Namibia and Dominica), including
93 Ministers for Foreign Affairs, Education,
Science, Culture, or Communication, was
an opportunity for a high-level expression
of views on concerns in Unesco's fields of
competence.
Throughout the general policy debate, it
was evident, in the words of Mr. M'Bow
that "the establishment of a new internatio
nal economic order is one of the most
important and, doubtless, most far-
reaching, goals to which the Organization's
activities must be directed". The discus¬
sions attested to the desire of Member
States "not to limit the concept of the new
order to the economic level, but to widen
and deepen it with due regard for its social
and cultural dimensions". Delegates were
also agreed that it was up to Unesco to
rectify the imbalance in the fields of
knowledge and information, whose con¬
sequences are still borne by the majority of
mankind. The programme to be carried out .
during the next two years illustrates this
determination.
"Unesco is at the crossroads (...) of all the
creative anxieties of our times", Mr. M'Bow
said. "It seeks to be a laboratory open to all
the intellectual currents converging to form
a new ethic of relations between men and
nations. This goal originates in the realiza¬
tion, as obvious as it is decisive, that the
world has ceased to have a single centre, a
single model for the future, and that it is
seeking new paths of development and a
new planetary order which takes account
of the upsurge of diversity. The vital im¬
perative for all is that this quest should be
carried out through a peaceful process of
reciprocal re-adaptation and of fruitful ex¬
changes between all systems and not
through confrontations based on deepen¬
ed distrust."
The cultures of many countries were
highlighted during the Conference through
a series of exhibitions and other cultural
events featuring internationally-known
artists and groups from the different
regions of the world.
The next session of the General Con¬
ference will meet in Belgradein 1980.
Further reading
on Korea
Arts of Korea, bv Chewon Kim and Lena Kim
Lee. Kodansha International Ltd., Tokyo, New
York and San Francisco. 1974.
Science and Technology in Korea, Traditio¬
nal Instruments and Techniques, bv Jeon
Sang-woon. The MIT Press, Cambridge, Mass.
and London, U.K., 1974
5000 Years of Korean Arts. National
Museum of Korea, Seoul, 1976.
The Arts of Korea, an Illustrated History,
by E. MacCune, Charles Tuttle and Co. Rutland,
Vermont and Tokyo, 1962.
UNESCO TRANSLATIONS
OF KOREAN LITERATURE
The Bamboo Grove, translated by Richard
Rutt. University of California Press, 1971.
Poems from Korea, from the earliest era to
the present. Selected and translated by Peter
Lee. University of Hawaii Press, Honolulu, 1974.
Songs of the Dragons. Translated by James
Hoyt. Korean National Commission for Unesco
(Royal Asiatic Society, Korean Branch), Seoul,
1971.
Virtuous Women (Three masterpieces of tra¬
ditional Korean fiction). Translated by Richard
Rutt and Kim Chong-un. Korean National Com¬
mission for Unesco, Seoul, 1974.
Voices of the Dawn : a selection of Korean
poetry from the sixth century to the present day.
Translated and introduced by Peter Hyun. John
Murray, London, 1960. Paragon Books, New
York.
z>
o
50
]]>
</page>
<page number="51">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Index 1978
January
THIRD THEATRE' (F, Taviani). Sharing the same globe (W. Piatt). Space co-operation
(A. Leonov). Genetic engineering (D. Behrman). Brunelleschi (F. Gurrien). Art treasures:
Walking Buddha (Thailand).
February
WORLD WATER CRISIS. A global challenge (Y. Mageed). Impending water famine (V.
Korzun, A. Sokolov). U.N. Water Conference. Modern cities: an unquenchable thirst?
Strange ways of H20 (M. Bâtisse). Will deserts drink icebergs? (P.-E. Victor). Redrawing
the world's waterscapes (J. Pournelle). Hydrology (R. Nace). Sumatra's swampland
pioneers (G. Francillon). Art treasures: Celtic crucifix (Ireland).
March
CATALONIA'S IMPACT ON MODERN ART. (A. Ctrici). One man's luxury is another
man's need (P. Fensham). Information, please... (Y. Litukhin). Mankind's memory banks
(J. Favier). Painters of medieval Catalonia (colour pages). Education tomorrow (C.
Hummel). Jules Verne (A. Bombard). Art treasures:' Golden helmet (Romania).
April
AVIATION AT AGE 75. (Y. Lambert). High-flying women. Down with decibels1 (E.
Sochor). Destination development (L. Cabrai). Special purpose flying (P. Finn). Safety
first in the air (0. Fritsch). World alert against hijacking (J. Marrett). Flying for thrills (0.
Antonov). The shape of things to come (C. LaFond). Sadriddin Ayni. Art treasures: On
the wing (Fed. Rep. of Germany).
May
BEFORE WE ARE SIX. (H. Dieuzeide). School is other people (A. Fafunwa). What's in a
game? (K. Masoka). Should we re-think the pre-school system? (L. Lurçat). Love is not
enough (B. White). India's mobile crèches (M. Mahadevan). Family and state (A.
Zaporozhets). It's never too early to learn (B. Nikitin). Jean-Jacques Rousseau (M.
Sinaceur). Who teaches the teachers? (D. Fleming). Art treasures: Satirical mask (Zaire).
June
ENERGY FOR TOMORROW (B. Berkovsky). The fast breeder (W. Hafele). Nuclear
energy and the environment (E. El-Hinnawi). Fusion power (R. Pease). The sun also
surprises (A. Ramachandran, J. Gururaja). Neptune's power station (R. Meyer). Tapping
earth's fiery core (R. Haenel). A come-back for king coal (V. Kuzminov). Farming
microbes (J. La Rivière, E. DaSilva). Hydrogen (T. Veziroglu). An treasures: The sun's
blessings (Egypt).
July
THE CULTURAL HERITAGE: RETURN TO THE HOMELAND (G. Fradier). A plea for
the return of an irreplaceable cultural heritage to those who created it (A.-M. M'Bow). A
woman of high degree (M. Remiddi). My years with Tolstoy (D. Makovitsky). Tolstoy: the
struggle towards the light (V. Shkolovsky). 'The Mother', spiritual heir of Sri Aurobindo
(E. Pouchpa Dass). Technical co-operation among developing countries (D. Najman). Art
treasures: Miniature monarch (Greece).
August-September
THE SLAVS. Flowering of Slav culture (D. Markov). The making of the Slav community
(V. Korolyuk). Magic, marriage and merry-making (A. Gura, 0. Ternovskaya and N.
Tolstoy). Hidden splendours of Russian art. The Slavs and Byzantium (D. Angelov and G.
Litavrin). An Arab traveller to an antique land. Tea and sympathy (0. Suleimenov). Kiev
(Y. Asseyev). The Morava school (S. Radojcic). Dubrovnik (V. Vuco). Workmanship in
wood. The common heritage (S. Vollman). Dialogue with the West (I. Belza). From
Copernicus to Korolev (B. Suchodolsky). Arts and crafts of Byelorussia (E. Sakhuta). Slav
post-war literature (A. Flaker). Art treasures: Animal art of ancient Thrace (Bulgaria).
October
TEACHING HUMAN RIGHTS. A new school of law and learning (K. Vasak). Human
rights and the international community (L. Levin). Unesco and respect for human rights.
Education for disarmament (S. Rana). Goya (S. Amon). A voice from the Third World (R.
Coomaraswamy). The right to be informed (A. Lopatka). A challenge for the universities
(T. Buergenthal). The doctors' dilemma (L. Cotte). Chernyshevsky (E. Dnieprov).
Unesco : publisher to the world (E. Wegman). Art treasures: Our Lady of Loderup
(Sweden).
November
50 MILLION UNEMPLOYED. Today's lost generation (P. Melvyn). The right to work.
The manpower situation in European socialist countries. Employment crisis in the Third
World. The multinationals and the Third World. The brain drain. Women at work: a
European profile (E. Sullerot). Workers can be choosers (G. Rehn). Teachers: society's
poor relations. Copyright: the creator's bread and butter (H. de Saint-Blanquat). Unesco,
youth and the right to work. Art treasures: High art from the Andes (Bolivia).
December
KOREA: 'LAND OF THE MORNING CALM'. Spiritual Landscape of traditional Korea
(Chang Byung-Kil). Master printers of Koryo (Ch'on Hye Bong). Korean alphabet (Lee Ki-
mun). Korean musical instruments. Korean painting (Ch'oe Sun-u). Koguryo. Three royal
tombs (Kim Won-Yong). Pottery of Korea (Chong Yang-mo). Temple-grotto of Sokkuram
(Hwang Su-young). A practical approach to science (Jeon Sang-woon). The turtle (Zo Za-
Yong). Folk art (Zo Za-Yong). Golden crown (Li Ogg). Art treasures: Match of miniatures
(Rep. of Korea).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications. Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd. P.O.
Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subs¬
criptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent:
United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
Campbell House, 100 Flinders St., Melbourne IVictona), 3000.
AUSTRIA. Dr. Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuch-
handlung, Industriehof Stadlau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220
Wien. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books International
Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola, Dacca 3.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Han-
delmaatschappij Keesing. Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-OQ70823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H
1M7. - CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makanos 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicnl literatura,
11 Soukemcka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrlr Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris, C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colma ntstrasse 22. For scientific maps only: GEO CENTER D7
Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other publications: S. Karger
GmbH, Karger Buchhandlung, Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2,
8034 Germering/ München. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.,
P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University
Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN.
See United Kingdom. HONG KONG. Federal Publications
(HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street,
Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kónyvesbolt, Václ u. 22, Budapest V;
A K.V. Konyvtùrosok Boltja, Népkoztarsaság utja 16, Budapest
VI. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson&Co., H F., Hafnarstraeti
9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamam Marg,
Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 '
Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Road,
Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 . Sub¬
Depots- Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street, Calcutta
70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications Section, Ministry
of Education and Social Welfare, 511 C-Wmg, Shastri Bhavan,
New Delhi 110001. - INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and
Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Gramedla
Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl. Dr
Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publish¬
ing and Distribution Co., 28, Vessal Shlrazi Street, Shahreza
Avenue, P.O. Box 314/1486, Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for
Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomall No. 300, B.P. 1533, Teheran.
IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI -Rashid Street, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL.
Emanuel Brown, formerly Blumstem's Book-stores, 35 Allenby
Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9, Shlomzion
Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA. Sangster's Book
Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston. -
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box 1728, Tokyo
100-92. KENYA. East African Publishing House, P.O. Box
30571, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National Commission for
Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. - KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait - LESOTHO. Mazenod Book
Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication 6- Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul
Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA. Federal
Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V.
Magnus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddme N V., P.O. Box
200, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. - NEW ZEALAND.
Government Printing Office, Government Bookshops at:
Rutland Street, P.O Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721 Christ-church; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857
Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;
The University Bookshop of Nsukka; The University Bookshop
of Lagos;The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of Zana
NORWAY. All publications: Johan Grundt Tanum
(Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco
Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturjeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Sarah Quaid-e-azam,
P O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. - PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co , 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. -
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-901
WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias Et Andrade Ltda, Livrana
Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. - SEYCHELLES. New
Service Ltd., Klngsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahé.
SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra Leone
Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New Industrial Road, off Upper
Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19. - SOMALI DEMOCRATIC
REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and General, P O. Box 951,
Mogadiscio. SOUTH AFRICA. All publications' Van
Schaik's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Librl Building, Church Street,
P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100
Sir Chlttampalam Gardiner Mawata P O B. 244 Colombo 2.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. -
SWEDEN. All publications A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Forbundet, Skolgrand 2,
Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWITZERLAND. All
publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse. Zurich. Librairie
Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236. -
TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop, P.O B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen
Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok:
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok;
Sukslt Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco,
18 Alexandra Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. - TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. -
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569,
London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops In London,
Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol.
- UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Station,
New York, N.Y. 10016. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga, Trg
Republike 5/8, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenje, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="52">
<![CDATA[
.T"*~ "
The tiger
and the
magpie
This tiger baring its teeth in
vexation at its traditional
enemy, the magpie, was
painted some two hundred
years ago by an anonymous
Korean artist. The tiger, a
familiar figure in Korean
folklore, was one of four
deities that guard the
cardinal points of the
compass, the other three
being the dragon, the
phoenix and the turtle. In
ancient times in Korea a
tiger was sometimes
painted on the door of a
house to ward off evil
spirits, along with a dragon
to bring good fortune.
¡»Hi
RIB
.
]]>
</page>
</document>
