<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074929eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
X
j
r H
I
Women
Tradition and change
Also in this issue:
Folklore
Preservation and protection
Two anniversaries:
Johann Sebastian Bach - Niels Bohr
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
*-,*
v**f
u**
^w»
i
3
A time to live...
Photo © Max Jtin, Switzerland
33 Switzerland
The carnival at Basel
The masquerade has always been a popular
amusement at carnival, itself a survival of
masked festivities dating back to ancient
times. Merrymaking at the Shrove Tuesday
carnival at- Basel, Switzerland, lasts for
three days during which dozens of masked
groups in fancy dress parade through the
streets playing drums and fifes. Above, a
band of fife-players all wearing the same
female disguise. Drummers bring up the
rear of the procession.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
THIS year marks the end of the UnitedNations Decade
for Women : Equality, Development and Peace. At
the World Conference to be held next July in
Nairobi, Kenya, delegates from United Nations Member
States will draw up a balance sheet of the results obtained
and of the problems which remain unresolved the many
forms of discrimination to which women are still subject
both in practice and under the law.
In this issue of the Unesco Courier we present three articles
which deal respectively with the common traditions which
restrict the rights of women in Mediterranean societies, with
the situation in Latin America where women themselves have
given priority to participation in political and social struggles
over the fight to achieve their emancipation and to establish
their "identity", and with the triple oppression as women,
on grounds of "race" and of class to which women are
subjected under the apartheid regime of the Republic of
South Africa.
Also in this issue we commemorate the tercentenary of the
birth of Johann Sebastian Bach, whose music, little appre¬
ciated in his own time, seems to us today to be imbued with
the power of "memory and prophecy". We salute as well the
centenary of the birth of Niels Bohr, a pragmatist of genius
who helped lay the foundations of modern physics.
In a further article we examine a question that preoccupies
a number of Unesco Member Statesthat of the need to
extend to folklore the protection already afforded to other
art forms. Unanimity has yet to be achieved on the appro¬
priate international action required to provide this
protection.
The study we present of Bartolomé de Las Casas, the
"Apostle of the Indians", demonstrates the astonishing
freshness of the thought and actions of this 16th-century
Spanish prelate whose opposition to slavery and insistence
on respect for cultural differences as the basis of liberty and
peace remain of topical interest today.
Finally, as a postscript to our March issue on the urban
explosion, we present a pen portrait of Cartagena de Indias,
which since November 1984 has been included on the World
Heritage List drawn up under the auspices of Unesco. This
old Colombian town and seaport, which for four centuries
withstood the savage assaults of Caribbean pirates, conti¬
nues today to resist the excesses of modern urbanism and to
retain its old-world charm and its soul.
Cover: Photos Eric Valli © ANA, Paris
Editor in chief: Edouard Glissant
April 1985
38th year
Women of the Mediterranean
'A shared destiny'
by Nilüfer Göle
10 Latin American Woman
'An elusive shadow'
by Luisa Futoransky
14 Women under apartheid
'A triple oppression'
by Caroline Flepp
1 6 Johann Sebastian Bach
'Between memory and prophecy'
by Alberto Basso
20 Niels Bohr
A pragmatic genius
by John Gribbin
23 In defence of folklore
by Jean Paul Guibbert
27 Unesco and the Preservation
and Protection of Folklore
28 Bartolomé de Las Casas
The apostle of the Indians'
by Silvio Zavala
32 Cartagena de Indias
'A city with a soul'
by Renata Duran
A time to live...
SWITZERLAND: The carnival at Basel
Published monthly in 31 languages English Italian
by Unesco,
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Macedonian Finnish
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
Swedish
Basque
A selection in Braille is published
quarterly in English, French,
Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N° 4- 1985 -OPI- 85- 1 -421 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Women:
tradition and change
From 15 to 26 July this year a World Conference is to be held
at Nairobi, Kenya, with the aim, firstly of evaluating progress
made in improving the situation of women during the United
Nations Decadefor Women: Equality, Development and Peace
and identifying obstacles to achievement of its objectives and,
secondly, of establishing as a result of this appraisal priorities
and strategies for overcoming these obstacles, especially in the
fields of employment, health and education. United Nations
Member States are being invited to send official delegations to
represent them at the Conference, and intergovernmental
organizations and non-governmental organizations with con¬
sultative status with the United Nations Economic and Social
Council are being invited to send observers. The Unesco
Courier presents on the following pages three articles by women
who express their personal viewpoint on various aspects of the
condition of women today in the different world regions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
'A shared destiny'
Women
of the Mediterranean
Two Turkish women whose different ap¬
proaches to life are reflected in their
dress
"Westernization has been associated
with a degradation of public morality, an
attack on women's honour; and the signs
of this degradation have always been
perceived in the transformation of
women's ways of dressing and the eman¬
cipation of their presence in the public
arena."
Nora Seni (Turkey)
by Nilüfer Gole
RUNNING in filigree through studies
on the situation of women in var¬
ious Mediterranean societies is a
common thread: a desire to seek out the
feminine presence wherever it lies hidden, in
the political and cultural as well as the
religious and urban context. Far from at¬
tempting to analyse the situation of "the
Mediterranean woman" as a stereotype
stamped with the seal of absolute sub¬
servience, they aim to identify the specific
tensions which arise from confrontation
between a particular cultural heritage and a
hegemonic cultural model.
The two dominant aspirations of feminist
movements in the industrialized
countriesthe equality of the sexes and the
search for a specifically feminine
identity find an echo in the perceptions of
women of the Mediterranean countries.
The first of these preoccupations gives rise
to calls for modernization, for removal of
the social, economic and juridical obstacles
that inhibit the expression of women's in¬
dividuality and militate against equality of
opportunity between men and women as far
as rights and career possibilities are con¬
cerned. Equality of the sexes forms part of
the liberal tradition (encompassed by the
rights of man and of the citizen) and enables
women to escape from the confinement of
a world apart, punctuated by childbirth,
and to aspire, like men, to the wider status
of "human beings".
The second aspiration arising from the
female experience, from the sexual
specificity of her body, has become the
ground of battle against male domination.
Here the purpose is not, as in the case of the
demand for equality of the sexes, the break¬
ing down of barriers that stand in the way
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Drawing by the French artist Topor
"Over and above theoretical divergen¬
ces, it is clear that no egalitarian ideology
establishes the principle of equality bet¬
ween men and women as long as It does
not recognize the notion of individual
rights. Most of these ideologies have
restricted themselves to proclaiming
equality between men and denouncing
the forms of domination of which they are
the object, and have disregarded the
domination man Imposes on woman."
Judith Astelarra (Spain)
of the free participation of women in all
spheres of public life. It is above all the
recognition by women of their repressed
femininity, imprisoned by the one-way
language of man, and the desire to give
back to women "their own territory".
Rather than social integration and reform,
what is demanded is a transformation of the
psychological social climate, until now
dominated by male-oriented language; it is
a call for recognition of the difference bet¬
ween the sexes and a rejection of reduc¬
tionist destruction of specificity in the name
of universality.
In the industrialized countries these two
themes of the feminist movement, equality
of the sexes and affirmation of the female
identity, made headway only with difficul¬
ty. The difficulty arises from their very
nature: the dilemma is how to affirm the
female identity, the specificity of woman,
without leaving the way open to claims that
woman is inferior? At the same time, is
there not a danger that affirmation of
women's status as "human beings", of
their participation in "the universal", will
lead to an erosion of the notion of the
specificity of woman? Does not the demand
for both equality and recognition of a
specific identity leave women in a "Catch
22" situation?
This thorny problem also faces the
women of the Mediterranean. The societies
in which they live are exposed to the
onslaught of the hegemonic cultural model
of the industrialized countries, a
homogenizing model conceived in terms of
the Universal, of History, of Progress, as
opposed to regional, national and cultural
specificities. Yet, at the same time, Mediter¬
ranean women are subject to these
specificities which are the source of their
confined situation.
How, in Mediterranean cultures, does
this principle of the equality of the sexes,
which is alien to their cultural model, fit in
with the indigenous culture in which the
identity of and the relations between the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
sexes are based on differentiation, a hierar¬
chical organization and segregation? In
other words, leaving aside national and
religious differences, to what extent is there
a specific Mediterranean culture?
The fact is that the unity of the Mediter¬
ranean is revealed in the broad sweep of its
history, a unity so profoundly experienced
that the peoples of every Mediterranean
shore share the same destiny, with the
Muslim and the Christian Mediterranean
sharing the same life rhythm.
Within this geo-cultural grouping, the
oppression of women is current in both
Christian and Islamic countries. This belies
the widespread misconception that the ser¬
vitude of women on the southern shores of
the Mediterranean springs from Islamic
doctrine; in fact it is a socio-geographical
rather than a religious phenomenon.
The veil and the harem pre-date the
Qur'an, which advocates according women
the rights due to all persons and is thus more
advanced than the code of custom in these
societies. If women are systematically
deprived of their rights in the Muslim and
Christian countries of the Mediterranean,
this is despite the Qur'an and the French
Revolution.
The distinction which designates coun¬
tries of Mediterranean culture as "kinship
societies" and those of "Western" culture
as "societies of citizens" highlights the
crucial importance of family structure in
the former as opposed to the concept of the
individual that characterizes the latter.
Modern culture is individualist in the sense
that the individual is of supreme impor¬
tance, whereas in anti-individualist societies
the highest value is society itself and the
community as a whole.
The norms which govern kinship struc¬
tures also control sexual relationships and
community groupings and are often the
basic cause of the constraints on women.
Some of those who see a direct link bet- ^
Algerian woman
"It is up to us to dismantle the
mechanisms of invisibility, all those pro¬
cesses which impoverish our relationship
with the world, impose silence on the ma¬
jority of women, and bring to the fore a
few of us, under certain conditions, to
legitimize the exclusion process as a
whole."
Fatma Oussedik (Algeria)
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Portrait of a woman of the time of Lalla
Khenata, who was the effective ruler of
Morocco during the reign of her son
Moulay Abdallah (1729-1757)
"It is in the light of history that we can
judge whether the few women who have
managed to infiltrate into political life
constitute a break with the past, of
decisive importance because it is sym¬
bolic in a society in which the essence of
power is masculine, or, whether, on the
contrary, they simply perpetuate the
heritage of the past."
Fatima Mernissi (Morocco)
ween the kinship structure and the oppres¬
sion of Mediterranean women attribute this
not to the practice of endogamy, which is
characteristic of the kinship structure in
these regions, but to the weakening of this
practice due to contact between urban and
tribal societies. In a truly endogamous
group, a woman, in virtue of her status as
a "cousin", is treated with tenderness and
regard. In a "detribalized" society,
however, she ceases to be a "cousin" yet
fails to receive the regard due to a human
being, an individual.
An ethnological analysis of history
reveals the distortions that can arise when
differing social realities come face to face,
a confrontation that sometimes provokes a
defensive attitude on the part of peoples
subject to the hegemony of other cultures
and incites them to seek in the past an "un-
contaminated" cultural identity.
Mediterranean societies are not, by
nature, modern societies in the in¬
dividualistic, egalitarian, liberal sense.
Liberal ideology situates and defines
Western society both in the "public" area
(social relationships) and in the "private
area" (the relationship between the sexes);
when it intrudes on Mediterranean
societies, it not only meets strong resistance
with regard to matters concerning the
"private" area but also creates a duality in
the social sphere. Italy is an example of a
Mediterranean country in which these two
influences cohabit and even have the effect
of creating geographical dichotomy bet¬
ween the North and the South, with the nor¬
thern influence more and more gaining the
upper hand.
The Italian women's movement has thus
developed a new set of values in tune with
a new cultural background. These values in¬
clude: equality at all levels in the relations
between men and women, whether at work,
in politics, and in the home; acceptance of
the woman's identity and her right to make
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
her own decisions regarding sex and mater¬
nity; finally, the notion of the community
of women, the keystone of this cultural
project.
Certain "evolutionist" analysts maintain
that Mediterranean woman is apart, outside
the mainstream of emancipation, and is
destined to go through the same stages as
women of liberal societies as Mediterranean
societies relinquish their cultural heritage.
But this is to succumb to reductionism and
to fail to see the tensions provoked by the
introduction of phenomena related to a
liberal-type emancipation into societies
with more specific cultural backgrounds.
Turkey offers another good example.
Whilst it is an Islamic country and generally
classed as one of the developing countries,
following the modernist tradition of its rul¬
ing élite Turkey adopted the principle of the
equality of the sexeseven before there was
any pressure on it to do sogiving women
legal and political rights (such as the right to
vote, which was granted earlier in Turkey
than in many Western countries) and
established the principle of equal right to
education for boys and girls (the only non-
mixed schools in Turkey are the French
lycées).
The complexity of the situation in which
Mediterranean women find themselves
results, therefore, from the specificity of
their cultural heritage, the impact of a
hegemonic cultural model and the claims of
the feminist movement. The conflict bet¬
ween the sexes thus takes on a particular
coloration in each country as a result of the
interaction and the opposition between
these elements in the religious, political and
cultural fields.
In the political and religious context of
the Arab Mediterranean the question arises
as to whether or not the Islamic cultural
heritage constitutes an obstacle to equality
of the sexes. Must the Arabo-Islamic past
be "mutilated" in order to enable equality
Feminist demonstration in Milan, Italy
"The history of men is the history of a
form of bias. Women, once they realized
this, decided to take back the history, the
life, the space and time that had been
denied to them."
Gioia di Cristofaro Longo (Italy)
of the sexes to be established, or should this
past be sifted and analysed, in which case
might not a' measure of hidden political
power of women stand revealed?
In Morocco, women who have exercised
direct power have been given a dehumaniz¬
ed image, being represented either as
something "monstrous" or as pertaining to
the "sacred". However, the exercise of in¬
direct power via a husband or a son seems
to have been more acceptable to the extent
that it conjured up the image of the devoted
wife or mother.
Analysis of outward signs, such as
physical attributes and clothing, reveals the
extent of the influence that Ottoman rulers
exercised over sexual and ethnic differentia¬
tion. It shows how, in a hierarchical, non-
liberal society such as the Ottoman society,
this accentuation of sexual and ethnic dif¬
ferences, far from ceding to a process of
homogenization and egalitarianism, as was
the case in the "modern" countries, was in¬
stitutionalized and regulated down to
details of dress so that sexual, ethnic or
religious affiliation could be seen at a
glance.
In Spain, the historic partnership bet¬
ween Church and State, due to the strength
of the Catholic religion and the late
development of capitalism there, had
prevented the spread of liberal ideology and
delayed the development of feminism.
Contemporary Spanish feminism only
really took hold from 1975, after the death
of Franco, but without the fully-fledged
social mobilization that occurred in other
European countries. This absence of solidly
based feminism explains why Spanish
feminists associated themselves with certain
political parties so as to obtain a foothold in
a society that had a reserved attitude
towards women's rights. This alliance gave
rise to clashes within the feminist movement
and to debate on such questions as
feminism and political parties, militancy on
two fronts, feminism and the female identi¬
ty and feminism and equality.
Examination of the specific form
domination of women takes in Algeria
comes down to an examination of the
various aspects Algerian women's "in¬
visibility", that is to say, the various forms
of social rejection to which they are subject
as being "Other". It also involves study of
the struggle of those women who have at¬
tempted to escape from this cloak of "in¬
visibility" by acquiring a certain autonomy
in their private lives or by outright
militancy.
One aspect at least of the condition of
Mediterranean women can be defined.
From the situation of Algerian women to
that of Italian women there is a progression
from "silent" action towards conscious,
collective action by women. The "silent"
way is perhaps peculiar to Muslim societies;
nevertheless, outspoken, independent ex¬
pression by women is possible only within
the context of a lay society.
NILUFER GOLE is a Turkish sociologist and
the author of many articles and studies on
women's participation in public affairs, the
discrimination from which they suffer and the
solutions proposed by feminist movements.
This article is extracted from the introduction
she wrote to a study to be published shortly by
Unesco on the situation of women in Mediter¬
ranean countries. Other contributors to this
study are Fatma Oussedik (Algeria), Fatima
Mernissi (Morocco), Nora Seni (Turkey), Ju¬
dith Astelarra (Spain) and Gioia di Cristofaro
Longo (Italy).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Latín American Woman
'An elusive shadow'
by Luisa Futoransky
As it by common accord, the best con¬
temporary women singers of Latin
America seem united In their desire to
rediscover their national folklore and to
spread it, even to other countries and
othercontinents, to revivepopularpoetry
and to create new songs of protest or of
hope that are rooted In social reality.
Their goal Is to achieve a renewal of the
popular music of the continent, to bear
witness to their times and to speak out for
the peoples of their countries. On these
pages we present seven such singers
together with brief excerpts from some of
their best-known songs. Unless the
singer wrote the song herself, the
author's name Is given In brackets after
the title.
Violeta Parra (Chile)
The poor of this world
Know not where to turn their eyes,
So In the undying hope
Of finding there the prize
In this world stolen from them
By their peers, they upward look
to the skies
("Porque los pobres no tienen")
LATIN America is no more a
homogeneous entity than are Africa
or Europe. The very term Latin
America brings to mind a jigsaw puzzle
whose pieces are extremely difficult to fit
together, so varied are the countries of
which it is composed both as regards their
past history and their present situation. Of
course, we still share a common language;
and I say "still" advisedly, since it is no
secret that Castilian Spanish, so long a
powerful bond between the countries of
Latin America, is undergoing an ac¬
celerating process of differentiation, similar
to that which separated the Romance
languages from Latin. Language apart, the
countries that comprise Latin America have
developed along quite distinct lines as a
result of the diversity of their geography
and climate, of the origins of their popula¬
tions and of their political and cultural
backgrounds.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
To attempt to give a global picture of
Latin American women over the past
decade would, therefore, be simply to add
to the sum total of generalizations and pre¬
judices. To launch into a disquisition on
that abstraction the Latin American woman
within the limits of this article would be
more than pretentious, it would be impossi¬
ble. I shall therefore confine myself to of¬
fering a few indications and pointers to
those interested in pursuing this subject.
Try as I would, I could not conjure up a
face, hands, legs, or indeed any kind of por¬
trait of that disjointed doll that bears the
label a Latin American woman. In the win¬
dows of the old-fashioned village shops, at
carnival time, everything was much easier.
There you could see Madame Pompadour,
with powdered wig, a beauty-spot on either
cheek and hooped skirt; or Manola (the
typical Spanish dancer), her red and white
spotted cotton skirt with its ruffles, fitting
tightly over her hips, high-heeled dancing
shoes and with carnations in her hair; or a
grand lady ofthe past, her mantilla, held in
place by a comb, allowing a glimpse of kiss-
curls plastered to her temples, wearing a
crinoline and holding an ever open fanthe
sunshade was an optional extra.
All too quickly, life dissipated the fine
certainties of carnival day, when a person
could be easily identified by his or her ap¬
parel. Falling back thus on my childhood
memories in search of the elusive outline of
this Latin American woman, I found only a
fugitive shadow, a graceful masquerade.
Who is this peasant girl from Oruro, in
Bolivia, whose photograph could be slipped
into a newspaper story on Tibet or Burma,
without anyone being the wiser? What have
a Colombian housewife, a young Mexican
bank employee, an Argentine textile worker
and a Brazilian sweet-vendor in common?
Were we to follow up these questions we
should find ourselves enmeshed in an inex¬
tricable web of theories, ranging from an¬
thropological studies of the first wave of
migration across the Behring Straits to
psycho-sociological analyses of the after
effects of slavery upon the Black popula¬
tions of the Atlantic coast.
I shall, therefore, attempt the more
modest task of examining the context
within which women have found themselves
during the more recent past. As everyone
knows, the last twenty years have been a
difficult period in the history of the conti¬
nent, marked by the rise of authoritarian
and repressive regimes. The growth or the
restriction of democracy has been closely
related to the mobilization of women, since
this is clearly bound up with the evolution
of the labour market and the family
structure.
It should be noted that, as I write these
lines, at least three of these Latin American
countries have returned to the democratic
fold, which gives one hope that, freed from
other constraints, women will be able to
devote their energies to specific problems
relating to the feminine situation.
The women of the Plaza de Mayo, in
Buenos Aires, for example, come to mind.
Soledad Bravo (Venezuela)
Little green bird, how can you say
I should not weep?
Little green bird, how can I stem
the tears that pour?
Alas, alas, I have but one life to live,
Little green bird, and they would
cast me through death's door (...)
Alas, alas, they have removed
my chains,
Little green bird, only to clamp them
on once more.
("Pajarlllo verde"
Venezuelan folksong)
Amparo Ochoa (Mexico)
The curse remains.
We offer the stranger
Our faith, our culture,
Our bread, our money.
Today we go on exchanging
Gold for glass beads
And giving up our treasure
For shining mirrors (...)
We open our homes to them
And we call them our friends,
Yet when an Indian arrives
Worn out by the long journey from
the mountains,
We spurn him and look upon him
As a foreigner in his own country.
("La maldición de Malinche"
Gabino Palomares - Mexico)
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Mercedes Sosa (Argentina)
Each time they wiped me out
I would disappear,
Beside my own funeral bier
Alone I cried,
And in my handkerchief a knot I tied, '
But then it went out of my head
That there were other times I had
been dead
And I went on my way singing...
("Como la cigarra"
Maria Elena Walsh Argentina)
Sara González (Cuba)
How can you say
That a woman is incapable
Of building, thinking
And fighting for life,
When all history proclaims
another truth (...)
("Que dice usted")
Maria Bethanla (Brazil)
I want to give out an unearthly scream
For this is one way to make myself
heard (...)
Father, remove this cup from me,
Father, remove this cup from me,
Father, remove this cup from me,
This cup of blood-red wine (...)
("Caliz"
Chico Buarque Brazil)
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Tania Libertad (Peru)
His tread was light,
His heart was of steel,
And the messenger declared:
The people have awakened (...)
("Pescador de luz"
V. Merino - Peru)
When the armed forces seized power in
March 1976, Argentina sank into economic
crisis accompanied by unemployment and
repression. In 1977, a few mothers of los
desaparecidos (victims of the military who
had "disappeared") began to meet regular¬
ly at the Plaza de Mayo, a square near the
presidential palace, demanding a hearing
which the authorities systematically refus¬
ed. Gradually as many as two thousand
women joined this group. Various forms of
pressure were applied in an attempt to
reduce them to silence, to which they replied
by organizing "lightning" demonstrations
and meetings in churches. In 1979, they
formed an association which was joined by
women from all over the country and which
launched an inquiry into the fate of the hun¬
dreds of children reported missing, children
who had been taken away with their parents
or had been born while their mothers were
in prison.
The association never concerned itself
with the kind of problems normally tackled
by feminist movements but relied instead on
the traditionally accepted role of women to
sanction their message and their protest.
They were united by something that
transcended social differences; this was a
matter of life and death everything else
could wait. Faced with a common social
catastrophe, solidarity and a united front
was the only answer.
It would, therefore, be difficult, a
mistake even, to try to establish a parallel
between the demands of Latin American
women and those of European feminists.
Brazil is another special case. From 1972,
modelling themselves on the mothers'
associations that had been formed in the
suburbs of Säo Paulo, Brazilian housewives
began to take action to improve their living
conditions, in particular to obtain the cre¬
ation of crèches, dispensaries and schools as
well as an improvement in public transport
facilities. Housewives' Associations and
Mothers' Clubs were formed, with the
backing of some sections of the Catholic
Church. From 1978 on, they concentrated
on fighting against the rise in the cost of
living.
Without doubt this movement will go
down in history as one of the most popular
ever, since between May and August 1978 it
succeeded in collecting one million three
hundred thousand signatures to a petition
which it presented to the government. The
demands which aroused such unanimous
support included a price freeze on all essen¬
tial foodstuffs, a wage increase propor¬
tionately higher than the rise in the cost of
living and the immediate payment of a flat
rate bonus to all workers.
Special mention should be made of those
women who, during the last decade, impell¬
ed by the flood tides of history, have ven¬
tured far beyond the domestic front and the
arena of the work place to participate in
liberation movements. To cite but one ex¬
ample, women made up thirty per cent of
the people's army that fought against the
Somoza dictatorship in Nicaragua.
It could be objected that all these are ex¬
treme cases. Yet even if this were true, the
difference as compared with events in other
Latin American countries is only one of
degree. Nevertheless, it must be recognized
that, for many Latin American feminist
groups, the United Nations Decade for
Women acted as a powerful catalyst,
stimulating them to action and laying the
foundations for their success.
This is why the Latin American reality is
so disconcertingit is extremely difficult to
find a common denominator among its
multiple facets.
On the one hand we find women engaged
in the national struggle; on the other we
have women in certain countries still
demanding the most elementary rights in
such matters as divorce, abortion or protec¬
tion from sexual abuse. At all events,
whatever may be our political persuasion,
the situation could well be summed up in
these words of Nora Astorga, lawyer,
mother of five and Nicaragua's deputy
minister of foreign affairs: "I have never
been a feminist in the sense that this is
understood in the industrialized countries.
Our struggle is quite different. Where op¬
pression and exploitation exist we believe
that to liberate women we must first liberate
society".
Respecting the principle that the best way
to illustrate a point of view is to maintain a
judicious balance between the general and
the particular, I return to my personal
memories of infancy and youth which may
provide a yardstick by which to measure
what has been accomplished. The changes
that have occurred in the field of education,
for example, where twenty years ago mixed
schooling would have been unthinkable,
have been enormous. Young girls at school
were taught handicrafts, to play the piano
and to read music; as young adolescents
they progressed to sewing and dressmaking
and, finally, to training as teachers or as
bookkeepers. Entry to university was much
more restricted and some professors could
still be heard to say that "they did not want
students in skirts attending their courses".
Sex education to prepare us for marriage
or maternity was limited to discreet ex¬
amination of an illustration of a cross-
section of the human body in an anatomy
.textbook.
The arduous and often disheartening
struggle to achieve an identity still con¬
tinues. For some women, for example, it
may be the symbolic rejection of the little
word "of", as used in such phrases as "the
pupil of", "the wife of", "the mother
of", "the widow of", "the mistress of",
"the companion of"...
The battle is being fought on many fronts
and the objectives vary widely according to
the specific situation being faced. Each
small step forward is achieved at the cost of
great effort and sacrifice, but also brings
and will continue to bring with it moments
of joy and fulfilment.
Of one thing I am sure; if in twenty years
time I have the good fortune to be able to
reflect once again on what has been achiev¬
ed by that elusive figure the Latin American
woman, I am sure that the balance will be
very positive. In the meantime, for my part,
I am ready to give of my best to ensure that
it will be so.
LUISA FUTORANSKY/s an Argentine writer
whose works include the novel Cuentos Chi¬
nos (Chinese Tales) and several books of poe¬
try, notably Babel Babel, Lo Regado por lo Se¬
co, El Diván de la Puerta Derecha and Partir
Digo.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Women under apartheid
'A triple oppression' by Caroline Flepp
IN the Republic of South Africa women
constitute the category of the popu¬
lation most seriously affected by the
apartheid system. They are subject to a
triple oppression: as women and on the
grounds of "race" and of class.
By adopting the principles of the patriar¬
chal society, the apartheid system has ac¬
centuated the subjection of women. Some
of the rights they had in pre-colonial days,
such as the right to work, which in rural
areas consisted traditionally of gathering
fruit and working the fields, have been
taken from them. In some regions, where it
did not exist before, the White authorities
have even legalized polygamy. In other
regions they have re-introduced corporal
punishment.
Apartheid pushes to its extreme the divi¬
sion of labour between men and women;
men, the producers, are employed in the
White economy, whereas women, the non-
producers, are confined to the Bantustans
(the "States" reserved for the Black
populations), their only right being to
reproduce an African labour force.
To say that they are "confined" is no ex¬
aggeration; they cannot leave the Ban¬
tustans because they are forbidden to take
up residence in the White zones. If they do,
they are liable to a fine or imprisonment. A
woman who enters one of these zones to
visit her husband can only stay for seventy-
two hours. The White authorities fear that
the permanent presence of these women in
the White areas would lead to the installa
tion of a Black urban population that would
then demand permanent residence permits
as well as other rights at present denied to
them.
Apartheid means the systematic destruc¬
tion of the family unit, which forms the
basis of classic capitalist society. In the
Republic of South Africa, a society, it can
never be repeated often enough, unlike any
other, everything is done to prevent the
Blacks from leading a normal family life.
Thus women are looked upon by the
Whites as nothing more or less than
superfluous hangers-on. Half the female
population lives in the Black reserves
among all the other "undesirables" of the
apartheid systemchildren, the sick, the.
elderly and the handicapped as well as those
rejected as trouble-makers, such as militant
union men and strikers.
Most of these women live on money sent
to them by their husbands out of the
miserable wages they earn working in the
White zones. It should be remembered that
Black workers are all treated as bachelors
and are therefore consistently underpaid,
since, according to the curious logic of the
system, the Bantustans are held responsible
for meeting the costs of maintaining their
families.
Exodus from the city, In Pretoria,
Republic of South Africa
Many women, however, receive nothing
from their husbands and sometimes lose all
trace of them. In the Bantustans, the educa¬
tion of the children is undertaken by the
women. In the absence of a hospital system,
the infant mortality rate is one of the
highest in the world with nearly one child in
two dying before the age of five, chiefly
from malnutrition.
In order to survive the women cultivate a
plot of land or work on a White man's farm
for the lowest wages paid anywhere in
South Africa. Otherwise they become
nurses or teachers.
In 1974, a Black nurse earned two-thirds
of the salary of a White nurse. Women
teachers earn ten per cent less than their
male colleagues. Their training is inade¬
quate; in 1978, out of seventy thousand
African teachers, only two hundred and
forty had diplomas.
To escape from this wretched, lonely life,
the women ignore the prohibitions and go
and settle in ghettos near the White towns.
The know that in coming to the towns they
run a big risk of being deported. Of the
three million Africans who have been for¬
cibly expelled from the urban areas the vast
majority are women.
The reason they go to the White areas is
to live with their husbands or to try to find
them. Some of the ghettos in which they
have settled, such as the Crossroads settle¬
ment, near Cape Town, which has a popula¬
tion of some twenty thousand, have surviv¬
ed thanks to the determination of the
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
women. Men and women live there
together, but this is not always possible.
Everything is done to try to separate them.
The Whites have built a number of hostels
for bachelors, but these, in fact, are oc¬
cupied by married couples who have
children. However, the women who live
there are not allowed to keep their children
with them and they have to send them back
to the reserves.
As far as work is concerned these women
have little choice since most of them have
had no education or professional training.
In the mid-1970s there was not a single
African woman judge, lawyer, magistrate,
engineer, architect, veterinary surgeon,
chemist or pharmacist.
The only possibility open to them is to
work for a White family as domestic ser¬
vants. The conditions of work for a
domestic servant in the Republic of South
Africa are tantamount to slavery. They
work sixty hours a week, on average, but
some work as many as eighty-five hours a
week. A third of them work seven days a
week for a pittance.
In the Republic of South Africa a
family Is evicted under the
Group Areas Act.
Furthermore, domestic servants are
housed in huts at the bottom of their
employers' garden and are strictly forbid¬
den to have their husbands and children
living there with them. In the past they were
allowed to keep their children with them up
to the age of three or four, but nowadays
that is strictly forbidden. They are therefore
unable to care for their own infant children,
a particularly cruel predicament for women
who spend their days looking after White
children. On top of all this there is no
legislation to protect them and they are not
permitted to join a union.
Women also work in the textile, food,
dress-making and canning industries in
which there are no fixed hours, no social
security and no guaranteed minimum
wages. Sexism is often sanctioned by
legislation, as, for example, in the textile in¬
dustry where a twenty per cent difference in
"The problem of improving the situation
of women In Africa Is inextricably linked
with the problem of poverty and can only
be resolved if we first tackle the latter (...)
A human being cannot walk very far or
very fast on one leg. How, then, can we
expect half the population of a country to
be capable of ensuring its development?
Yet, in fact, when it is a matter of discuss¬
ing development questions or of taking
decisions on methods of implementing
development projects, women are
generally left out of it..."
Julius Nyerere
President of the United
Republic of Tanzania
wages between men and women is decreed
by law. Women who become pregnant are
liable to instant dismissal and may even be
sent back to a Bantustan. On average,
African women workers earn less than half
as much as their partners and eighty per
cent less than White men.
Suffering from the evil effects of apar¬
theid not only in their daily lives but also in
their very bodies, women took up the strug¬
gle against the system very early on and
their role in that struggle has been very
important.
Their first combat, in 1913, was against
the pass laws which limited their freedom of
movement. This was one of the high peaks
of their struggle when for the first time they
began to organize themselves. A key princi¬
ple was at stake. The women knew that by
being obliged to carry a special pass they
were effectively being forbidden either to
live with their husbands in the White zones
or to work there; in other words, this meant
their seclusion in the reserves. For years
African women refused to carry these
passes which they burnt in public. They
demonstrated in the streets and were beaten
up and imprisoned in their hundreds by the
police.
The movement reached its culminating
point on 9 August 1956. On that day twenty
thousand women, of every "race",
gathered in Pretoria from every part of the
country, despite the dangers of the journey
and transport difficulties, bringing with
them over 100,000 petitions.
Despite this powerful mobilization of
forces, they were eventually obliged to yield
when the government decreed that it was
obligatory to have a pass in order to obtain
a job, to go to hospital, to receive a pension
or to register the birth of a child.
On 1 February 1963, the pass laws finally
came into force, but it had taken the
government fifty years to impose its will.B
CAROLINE FLEPP Is a French journalist and
heads the French Anti-Apartheid Movement.
This article is based on a speech she made on
International Women's Day, 8 March 1985, at
the invitation of the International StaffAssoci¬
ation of Unesco.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
s-.'
.-tí^í?'- ->-
E£^?v*\
A composer ofgenius, Johann Sebastlap
Bach was also a great organist. Organ
works and cantatas predominate In his
output, which grew directly from his ac¬
tivities as organist, Kapellmeister, and
Kantor. From 1703 to 1707, Bach was
organist at the Neuklrche ("New
Church", known since 1935 as the
"Bachklrche") at Arnstadt In Thuringla,
some 40 kilometres from Weimar. At this
period Bach became acquainted with the
art of the great German composer
Dietrich Buxtehude (1637-1707), a
decisive experience In his musical
development, and wrote his first cantata
and possibly his earliest organ works.
This 18th-century German engraving
shows Bach at the organ of the Neu¬
klrche. Virtually nothing remains of this
Instrument except for the console, which
¡s displayed at the Bach museum In
Arnstadt (German Dem. Rep.).
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Johann Sebastian Bach
'Between memory and prophecy'
THE works of Johann Sebastian Bach,
the Kantor maximus, the musician
who more than anyone else left an
indelible mark on the musical life of his age
(which we now call the "Baroque") are to-,
day so widely known, so often performed
and recorded, that the three hundredth an¬
niversary of their composer's birth is an
event for which the public should not be
unprepared.
The course of Bach's industrious life
took him all the way from the lowly posi¬
tion of "chamber musician" to that of
director musices of Leipzig, superintending
the musical activity of what was then a city
with no more than 30,000 inhabitants, after
being an organist, a konzertmeister ("con-
certmaster", leader of a collegium musicum
at a court), a Kapellmeister in charge of a
Kapelle or chapel of musicians, and a Kan-
tor (the official responsible for musical
education in a school and the official com¬
poser of a town or city).
Yet scarcely any trace of his itinerary has
survived. As a brilliant interpreter of im¬
ages which after the Renaissance brought
grandeur to Baroque art, an obstinate
devotee of the past, and a sceptical oppo¬
nent of things modern, Bach had the good
fortune or, from another standpoint, the
misfortune to voice a message which was
somewhere between memory and prophecy
and which could only be grasped by a hand¬
ful of dedicated followers who had been
trained in his school.
--
» *
by Alberto Basso
This community of initiates, which
followed the teachings dispensed by a mind
that was equipped to deal with any dispute
or challenge, subsequently split into small,
silent groups which discreetly made their
way into the musical world of the second
half of the eighteenth century and brought
with them both an outstanding mastery and
the musical heritage bequeathed to them by
the Kantor.
Indeed, these followers, disciples and
apostles were to be the channel through
which one of the fundamental principles
underlying Bach's music was confirmed: its
possession of an extraordinarily powerful
instructive and exhortatory impact. In
other words, it is a music that opens up to
the outside world, dictates exempta to it,
and suggests exercises, practical applica¬
tions and projects.
Emerging as they did in a fascinating
world that was a focus of the clash between
the rational and the irrational, between
science and divine grace, between the ex¬
position of historical fact and faith, Bach's
works did not enjoy the consideration they
deserved among his contemporaries.
Through one of those contradictions that
make historical interpretation so unreliable
and hazardous, the most outstanding figure
SB
5^
of the age which we have become accustom¬
ed to call the Late Baroque, and his un¬
disputed musical leadership, do not occupy
their rightful place in the annals of the
period, indeed can scarcely be said to
feature in them at all.
There was widespread indifference to his
art, because Bach himself was generally,
and even provocatively indifferent to the
new trends. The society of his time thus did
not trouble to transmit to future genera¬
tions documentary evidence about a life
that was dedicated exclusively and uncondi¬
tionally to art.
As a result, his biography is riddled with
gaps. Contemporary sources are few and
far between; information about Bach's
material situation is unreliable and indeed
almost non-existent; psychological data
about him are vague; attempts to establish
definitive dates for many of his works,
especially the instrumental music, have
been vain; it is impossible to calculate how
many of his compositions have been lost;
the contribution made by his meagre
correspondence there are only some thirty
letters extant is very modest; the commer¬
cial impact of his works, which were virtual¬
ly unknown outside Thuringia and Saxony,
was insignificant; and the critical response
they aroused was slight and by no means en¬
thusiastic. In 1737, one of his pupils,
Johann Adolph Scheibe, would tax him
with being a musical anachronism.
Bach's music was forgotten by those who
had lived in close contact with the com¬
poser. His own sons regarded it as odd, as
fit for the museum, and it was unknown to
music lovers of the succeeding generation.
"Officially", it did not exist. This abnor¬
mal silence, which was nevertheless to some
extent justified by historical circumstances,
did not start to be broken until near the end
In 1707 Bach married his cousin, Maria
Barbara Bach. Four of their children sur¬
vived, two of them becoming musicians:
Wilhelm Friedmann (1710-1784) and Carl-
Philipp Emanuel (1714-1788). In 1720
Maria Barbara died and the following year
Bach married Anna Magdalena Wülcken
(or Wilcken), a singer at the court of
prince Leopold of Kothen near Halle (in
what is now the German Democratic
Republic), where Bach was
Kapellmeister. Anna Magdalena bore 13
children, two of whom became musi¬
cians: J. Christoph Friedrich (1732-1795)
and Johann Christian (1735-1782). In
spite of her onerous household tasks she
constantly helped her husband by copy¬
ing many of his scores, singing for him,
taking part In rehearsals and entertaining
visitors. Bach wrote several works tor
her. At the beginning of 1722 he wrote for
hera Clavierbuchleln, left, containing the
first five of his French Suites.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
52,
I
*- IL..5 (X
^ of the eighteenth century when a number of
theorists began to quote scattered
fragments of Bach's works in support of
certain technical approaches and a handful
of music lovers sponsored hesitant and
sporadic private performances of the in¬
strumental music. The German
musicologist and composer Johann
Nikolaus Forkel, in 1802, was the first per¬
son to tackle the problem of Bach's life and
work. This spelt the beginning of the "Bach
Renaissance", and a number of publishers
immediately began to put some of his works
on the market.
In 1829 Felix Mendelssohn, then aged
twenty, presented a recast version of the St.
Matthew Passion, 120 years after its first
known performance, and thereby launched
what might be called the "Bach
phenomenon". Paradoxically, the
"discovery" of the Leipzig musician was
primarily an outcome of the crisis of
Lutheranism which spanned two centuries.
The decisive impetus in the "rehabilita¬
tion" of Bach came from those who, in a
bid to give a new and vigorous lease of life
to Lutheranism, brought back to light the
great treasury of chorales which formed the
lifeblood of the German nation.
Once the Lutheran musical repertory had
been rediscovered and studied, it was only
natural that attention should be focused on
Bach. There was an immediate chain reac¬
tion: a "Bach Society" was founded in 1850
and a year later embarked on the publica¬
tion of the master's collected works. An im¬
portant study by C.H. Bitter was published
in 1865, followed in 1873 and 1880 by two
monumental volumes by another German
musicologist, Philipp Spitta. History is full
of contradictions; once rejected, Bach was
now regarded as a turning point. With him,
one era came to an end and another began.
Indeed, Bach had never lost sight of
history. He took an extraordinarily close in
to 1723, Bach was appointed Kantor of
the Thomaskirche (St. Thomas' church)
in Leipzig, a major German economic and
musical centre, and director musices
director of church music the city. As
well as organizing programmes of sacred
music, he taught music and Latin at the
Thomaskirche school adjoining the
church, where he lived with his large
family. Throughout this longperiod, Bach
wrote abundant church music, especially
admirable cantata cycles. From 1729 to
1740 he also directed the Collegium
Musicum, one of Germany's leading
associations for organizing public con¬
certs, which had been founded In 1 702 by
Georg Philipp Telemann (1681-1767) and
gave a concert each week. He travelled,
performedat concerts outside the city, In¬
augurated organs, visited his children,
and wrote a large number of occasional
works until his death on 28 July 1750.
Above, engraving dating from Bach's
lifetime showing the Thomaskirche In
Leipzig; the school, at the end of the alley
at left, cannot be seen.
terest in the works of others, ancient and
modern alike. He approached them in all
modesty, with the mind of a researcher.
Study was the purpose of his life, and his art
was the expression of a tireless scientific ap¬
plication. His taste for eclecticism and
historical synthesis undoubtedly stemmed
from study. Concepts such as research and
experimentation were part of his innermost
nature. It is significant, for example, that
much of his instrumental work is a product
of both poetry and science.
In view of certain aspects of his artistic
temperament there would appear to be
grounds for believing that he intended to
devote himself to an abstract art, and that
external circumstances alone obliged him to
produce "ordinary" music. In fact, the
real, concrete musical situation never
escaped his attention, ready as he always
was to grasp opportunities to display the
novelty of his thinking and to communicate
his musical findings.
In this respect, Bach made no distinction
between works sacred and profane, bet¬
ween vocal and instrumental music, bet¬
ween theory and practice. The mediums,
styles, materials and situationsin other
words, his working tools were always the
same (and many were the times that Bach
made use of pages that had originally been
conceived for quite another purpose), but
he transformed them with flashes of in¬
tuitive expression, breathing life and poetic
substance into what seems to have been con¬
ceived in the abstract or to have been
capable of adaptation to all uses.
There is naturally an indication of a
moral attitude in all this. Bach's work is
primarily the fruit that ripened in the soul
of a fervent devotee of the Lutheran creed
and not a single page of it can be said to run
counter to that religious experience. Even in
the most popular and fashionable works,
the sheer gravity and severity of his poetics
preclude any alternative interpretation of
the musical text since, in Bach, this is
always determined by a motive of rigorous
speculation and is governed by a persistent
feeling for geometry, the symbol of order
and wisdom, the reflection of a privileged
intelligence and an exemplary human
condition.
The idea that musical space was condi¬
tioned by mathematical principles and that
creativity could be likened to a scientific
pursuit was fairly widespread during the
Enlightenment. Throughout his life, Bach
showed that he was intent on quantifying
the principles of logic and formal abstrac¬
tion and on linking them to the sentimental
and dramatic consistency both of poetic
creation and of the circumstances in which
a work was created. For a long time,
however, he acted as if he were obeying an
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
instinct or an irresistible force of attraction,
perhaps even unconsciously in some cases,
driven on by a modus operandi that was
specific to his time.
Even so, with the passage of time, his ap¬
proach became more refined and his in-
depth analysis of "composition" gave rise
to a burst of speculative energy and to
theoretical conceptions which, when he
came to apply them, went beyond the
bounds of contemporary musical practice.
Accordingly, little by little, Bach drew
closer to what was to be the supreme goal of
his life: the exercise of perfect inner
discipline, control of the imagination, and
the stifling of instinct. At the same time, the
great musician showed that he was retracing
the steps of musical history, as it were, and
was drinking from the pure wellsprings of
polyphony. What he was proposing was
tantamount to a "return to the antique"
which, because it was so singular and indi¬
vidualistic, had absolutely no influence on
contemporary musical developments, and
remained isolated and unique, an enigmatic
reminder of the past, an impregnable bas¬
tion of memory.
The approach to the "new music" Was
gradual, but it became a burning issue in the
last decade of Bach's life. The principle of
construction adopted with the aim of
renewing musical language and its
significance was that of the variation, but
the variation as understood in a totally dif¬
ferent sense from that which later became
established. The material was organized on
the basis of a theme or arbor (trunk), which
was then developed in a series of derivations
and ramifications in accordance with an
organic plan, although this was always link¬
ed to the starting point. At the same time,
the overall architectural structure of the
composition was also a manifestation of an
encyclopaedic approach, in that the com¬
poser aimed at combining in a single entity
the different aspects of a given technique or
a number of seemingly incompatible formal
possibilities.
All Bach's works, including those he
composed before taking up residence in
Leipzig, are authentic proof of an en¬
cyclopaedic culture applied to a given
musical situation. But the principle was
developed further while Bach was working
at the church of St. Thomas in Leipzig, and
especially during his last creative phase.
Even a work like the B Minor Mass which,
in its final version, is contemporaneous
with the Art ofthe Fugue, is the outcome of
an application of the encyclopaedic ap¬
proach to musical doctrine, which reached
its culminating point in the last keyboard
works, by linking them with the common
denominator of the art of the variation, in
an unspoken bid to achieve perfection using
the instruments of a consummate scientia
universalis.
The new and rigorous self-discipline and
the new-found mysticism entailed devoting
the utmost attention to the facts of
Manuscript page of the first part of the
Christmas Oratorio (1734), one of Bach's
most popular religious works. It consists
of six beautiful and melodious cantatas.
"One can sense the man who, each year,
experienced with his children the poetry
of Christmas, " wrote the French doctor
and organist Albert Schweitzer
(1875-1965) of the Christmas Oratorio.
geometry, to order, and to reduction of the
macrocosm and the microcosm within a
symmetrically designed organic system in
which the cabalistic, alchemical and
mathematical disciplines were finely
balanced. Rationalism was impregnated
with magic, occultism and hermeticism,
and the approach to music of a certain type
involved initiatory rites after the manner of
a secret society. Indeed, Bach's ultimate
aim was to gain access to that secret
knowledge, which he only succeeded in
mastering on the eve of his death.
Bach prepared himself for the difficult
art of dying, the ars moriendi of the an¬
cients, by engaging in acts of purification
and exercises in musical asceticism. In the
last ten years of his life he changed beyond
recognition. Perhaps he lost touch with his
old self when his sight failed. Once he had
forsaken his old habits and severed his links
with the outside worldperhaps because,
in his heart of hearts, he no longer believed
in the forms and styles which he had so
fiercely championed in the first ten or fif¬
teen years of his association with the institu
tions of Leipzig Bach withdrew to Mount
Zion, into the solid fortress, the citadel, the
tower, where the only guest was science,
with its virtues as an elect creature and its
luminous and vibrant aura of acquired cer¬
tainties and unexpected developments.
It was a new apocalypse, and hence a
revelation of what is and what has been, a
testimony to prophecy not so much in the
sense of prediction of the future as of a
reading of the past and an interpretation of
the signs through which thought manifests
itself, thought that can also be composed of
pure sounds that are the faithful mirror of
a strict spiritual discipline.
ALBERTO BASSO, Italian musicologist, was
president of the Italian Musicology Society
from 1973to 1979. He is the author of several
books including a history of music and a two-
volume study of the life and work's of Johann
Sebastian Bach. He is at present editing an
eight-volume Dizionario Enciclopédico Univer¬
sale della Música e del Musicisti (Universal En¬
cyclopaedic Dictionary of Music and
Musicians).
¡j, &*if (Plnei.f'ÛTXj
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
NIELS
BOHR
NIELS Bohr, who was born in Copen¬
hagen on 7 October, 1885, was
one of the foremost scientists of
the twentieth century. Before the First
World War, he took the new quantum
theory and used it to construct the first
successful, detailed picture of how atoms
work; in the 1920s, he first extended this
understanding to explain the periodic
table of the elements. Then revolutionary
new developments transformed quantum
theory into the foundation stone of
modern physics, and Bohr was instrumen¬
tal in providing the interpretation of quan¬
tum physics, the Copenhagen Interpreta¬
tion, which is still today the basis for
translating quantum ideas into everyday
terms. He worked on the Manhattan Pro¬
ject, the construction of the first atomic
bomb, but in the 1950s he campaigned to
achieve control of nuclear weapons, and
his efforts to promote the peaceful use of
atomic energy led to his receiving the first
US Atoms for Peace award, in 1957.
Bohr came from an intellectual family.
His father, Christian Bohr, was professor
of physiology at the University of
Copenhagen; his younger brother, and
lifelong friend, Harald, was an eminent
mathematician; and his son, Aage, follow¬
ed Niels both in the directorship of the
Institute of Theoretical Physics in
Copenhagen and as a winner of the Nobel
Prize in physics.
In his early academic career Niels Bohr
displayed thoroughness rather than
brilliance, carrying out a painstaking
measurement of the surface tension of
water in 1906, then moving on to analyse
the behaviour of electrons in metals, a
project for which he received a PhD in
191 1 . It was only after he completed this
work, and moved first to Cambridge and
then, in March 1912, to the University of
Manchester, that Bohr displayed what
became his characteristic approach to
scientific problems.
His particular genius, which was just
the thing required to make progress in
atomic physics in those days, was his will¬
ingness to patch together different ideas,
from different sources, to make an im¬
aginary "model" of the atom (a set of
equations, and a physical picture) that
worked at least in rough agreement with
the way observations suggested that real
atoms worked. Once he had a rough idea
what was going on, Bohr could tinker with
the theories to make the bits fit together
even better, and so work towards a com¬
plete picture. This was just about the only
approach that could have worked in the
second decade of the twentieth century,
for what physicists knew about atoms was
decidedly fragmentary and incomplete.
The electron itself, which we now know
to be a component of the atom, had only
Niels Bohr (right) with Einstein in
Brussels, in 1930. Einstein believed that
there were laws governing the behaviour
of everything in the universe from elec¬
trons to planets and to the end of his life
he was unwilling to accept a central no¬
tion of quantum theory that the precise
movement of a single electron could not
be predicted. "God", he once said, "is
subtle but he is not malicious. " And on
another occasion "God does not play at
dice." To which Bohr is said have
retorted "Stop telling God what to do."
been discovered in 1887, and it was only
in 191 1 that New Zealand physicist Ernest
Rutherford (1871-1937), on the basis of
experiments carried out in Manchester,
suggested that there must be a small cen¬
tral nucleus to every atom, containing all
of its positive charge and most of its mass,
while the electrons formed a cloud of
negatively charged particles around the
nucleus.
Later experiments showed he was
correctthe nucleus is only one hundred
thousandth of the size of the atom.
Typically, a nucleus about 10-13 cm
across is embedded in an electron cloud
10-8 cm across. To put these figures in
perspective, imagine a pinhead, perhaps
a millimetre across, in the centre of the
dome of St Paul's Cathedral (35 metres in
diameter), surrounded by a cloud of
microscopic dust motes far out in the
dome. The pinhead represents the
nucleus, and the dust motes represent
electrons. Atoms are mostly empty space.
But at the beginning of 1912, Ruther¬
ford's picture of the atom was still con¬
troversial. In particular, since opposite
electric charges attract one another,
physicists could not explain why all the
electrons in every atom did not im¬
mediately fall in to their nuclei, releasing a
burst of energy (radiation) in the process.
This is where Bohr came in, naturally
gravitating to Manchester to work with
Rutherford's group as his interest in the
atomic puzzle grew.
The simplest ¡mage of the atom that
emerged from Rutherford's work was
something like the Solar System, with a
nucleus at its heart, in place of the Sun,
and electrons orbiting around it, in place
of the planets. The picture is over-
simplistic, but it was the first step on the
road to understanding the atom.
Everything physicists knew about charg¬
ed particles in orbit said that they should
radiate electromagnetic energy (light, X-
rays or radio waves) and spiral inwards.
So there was an obvious flaw with the
model. Bohr resolved the dilemma by
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
a pragmatic genius by John Gribbin
plucking a totally different idea out of cur¬
rent developments in physics, and stick¬
ing it on to Rutherford's atomic model.
This was the idea, stemming from the
work of German physicist Max Planck
(1 858-1 947) at the turn of the century, that
electromagnetic radiation (light, or the
other forms) could only be emitted or ab¬
sorbed by an atom in discrete units, called
quanta. The automatic bank-note
distributor at my bank in London operates
much the same way. It will only issue me
with money in units of £5. 1 can get £20, or
£45, but I cannot get £1 , or £37, out of it.
Bohr said that the electrons "in orbit"
around the nucleus of an atom could not
spiral gently inward because that would
involve radiating energy continuously.
Quantum theory said that they could only
release certain fixed amounts of energy,
and to do so an electron would have to
"jump", instantaneously, from one "or¬
bit" to anotherrather as if Mars sudden¬
ly jumped into the Earth's orbit. There
were stable orbits, said Bohr, correspon¬
ding to fixed amounts of energy, rather
like the rungs on a ladder. But there were
no in between orbits, and an electron
could not spiral into the nucleus because
that would involve releasing fractional
amounts of energy.
What Bohr did had no right to work. The
whole idea of an orbit depends on
classical physics, Newton's laws; the idea
of electron states corresponding to fixed
amounts of energy (energy levels, as they
came to be called) came from quantum
theory. Making a model which patched
together bits of each theory gave no in¬
sight into what made atoms tick, but it pro¬
vided just enough of a starting point for
Bohr to make progress throughout the
next ten years.
Niels Bohr used to begin his lectures by
saying to his students "Every sentence
that I utter should be regarded by you not
as an assertion but as a question. " He Is
seen here, In 1936, at the Niels Bohr In¬
stitute, Copenhagen, in conversation
with two other Nobel Prlzewlnning
physicists, Werner Heisenberg (centre)
and Wolfang Pauli (right).
That progress continued in
Copenhagen, where the authorities
created a new Institute to entice Bohr
back. He became director of the Niels
Bohr Institute in 1920, developing it into
one of the great scientific centres, where
theoretical physicists came from all over
the world to bounce ideas off one another
and to probe the mysteries of quanta and
the atom. And in the early 1920s Bohr pro¬
duced his greatest single achievement, a
theory of the atom which explained, at
least in broad outline, the whole science
of chemistry.
The Siberian Dmitri Mendeleyev
(1834-1907) had come up with his
classification of the elements in the
1 860s. He showed that these fundamental
substances could be ranked in a table in
order of increasing atomic weight, in such
a way that elements with similar proper¬
ties appeared beneath each other in the
columns of the table. But there was no ex¬
planation of why elements with very dif¬
ferent atomic masses should just happen
to have similar chemical properties, until
Bohr improved his theory of the atom in
the years following the First World War. It
was clear to Bohr, and his contem¬
poraries, that the chemical properties of
atoms depend almost exclusively on the
number of electrons they contain. These
are related to the number of protons
(positively charged particles) in the
nucleus, and therefore to the atomic
mass. But the electrons themselves are
the visible face an atom shows to the
world, the "handles" by which it interacts
with other atoms. So why should an atom
of lithium, which has three electrons, be
very similar chemically to an atom of
sodium, which has eleven electrons, and
potassium with nineteen? Once again,
Bohr produced an imaginary model of the
atom to explain the observations, without
waiting for the fundamental physics to be
worked out.
Imagine the electron "orbits" around
the atom as more like onion skins, nest¬
ling one inside the other, than like the or¬
bits of the planets around the Sun. What
Bohr said, in effect, was that the inner¬
most orbit, or "shell", only has room for
two electrons. He didn't worry why this
should be so; he just chose the restriction
to match the observed patterns of
chemical properties of the elements. The
next shell out from the nucleus, however,
has room for eight electrons. So an atom
which has, say, six protons in its nucleus,
and therefore "needs" six electrons to en¬
sure its electrical neutrality, will slot two
into the innermost shell, and four into the
second shell. But an atom with eleven pro¬
tons (sodium) has two in the innermost
shell, eight in the second, full, shell, and
the last has to go into a new shell, out on
its own. This is very similar to the pattern
for lithium, which has two electrons in its
innermost shell, and, once again, just one
out on its own. And potassium fits the pic¬
ture if we imagine it to have three filled
shells (two, eight and eight electrons
each), with a lone electron in the fourth
shell.
What matters for chemistry is primarily
the number of electrons in the outermost
shell that contains any electrons at all.
Working outward through the shells for
heavier and heavier atoms, with more and
more electrons, Bohr was able to explain
the relationship between the elements in
Mendeleyev's periodic table in terms of
atomic structure, and although he had no
idea why a shell containing eight elec¬
trons should be "closed" to further addi¬
tions, he could use the fact that it was to
explain how atoms combine with one
another.
Bohr proved nothing mathematically
he just knew that things had to be this
Niels Bohr (left) sitting back-to-back with
Ernest Rutherford during a river-side pic¬
nic In 1923, at Cambridge, where he had
gone to receive an honorary Doctor of
Science degree. In 1911, Rutherford had
made the greatest of his many contribu¬
tions to sciencehis nuclear theory of
the atom (see article). It was while work¬
ing with Rutherford at Manchester
University that Niels Bohr developed the
theoretical Implications of the nuclear
model of the atom, combining It with the
quantum theory developed by the Ger¬
man physicist Max Planck.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
way. In his Autobiographical Notes,
published in 1949, Einstein said of Bohr's
work and the early quantum theory "that
this insecure and contradictory founda¬
tion was sufficient to enable a man of
Bohr's unique instinct and talent to
discover the major laws of spectral lines
and of the electron-shells of the atoms
together with their significance for
chemistry appeared to me like a
miracleand appears to me as a miracle
even today".
In 1922, Bohr received the Nobel Prize
for physics for this work; in the same year,
a previously unknown element, whose ex¬
istence had been predicted by his atomic
theory, was discovered, and named haf¬
nium. But it was only in 1926 and 1927
that physicists at last began to put the
quantum theory on a secure footing,
discovering the relationships and laws
which explained why electrons had to
behave in this peculiar manner, why the
numbers allowed in each shell were
limited. That full version of the quantum
theory brought in concepts that still seem
bizarre. No longer could the electron be
thought of as a tiny particle, but rather as
an entity which could be both wave and
particle at the same time. Any experiment
designed to find a particle would indeed
show the electron behaving as a
particlebut set up an experiment to
measure wave properties, and it would
show electrons behaving like waves.
What was "really" going on?
By the late 1 920s, physicists had a com¬
plete theory, a set of self-consistent equa¬
tions, to describe the behaviour of atoms,
electrons and radiation. The only trouble
was it didn't make sense. Once again,
Jb^.df-ftt , z'*
¿
W-'fô-i'jf£c. $-
-MM
# #
tt-Ki
&
i-
*-*f f-nÖ^
iim
** '5*
fr-kè? ïî: -IÜ<
A j~.t H-) .---- *~4 -J, a m t. :
U tLm^t^- ¡. / -*-y
fi^.U/L%~l E_j -*£.')
Jr-fK *
*-*-£, $-**' t
K.*.f =
This document, In Niels Bohr's hand¬
writing, Is a calculation of the rate of
change of radius and frequency of an
electron moving in a circle.
Bohr came to the rescue. It didn't have to
make sense, he said. The only thing we
have direct knowledge of is the outcome
of an experiment, and as long as we can
predict how experiments will turn out,
there is no need to worry about what the
particles (or waves) do when we are not
looking at them. This is a slight over¬
simplification of the philosophy that
became known as the "Copenhagen In¬
terpretation" of quantum mechanics, but
only a slight simplification.
For more than half a century, following
Bohr's teaching, physicists have used the
quantum theory to explain the behaviour
of molecules, including biological
molecules such as DNA, to design
nuclear power stations (and bombs), to
build solid state computers, digital
watches, and lasers. To this day, nobody
"knows" what the particles of the quan¬
tum world are really like, what they are
"doing" when they are not being
monitored by our experiments. But every
experiment carried out in the past half
century has produced results in agree¬
ment with the predictions of the quantum
theory.
Bohr's greatest triumph was un¬
doubtedly his explanation of the periodic
table of the elements; and his pragmatic
approach to the contradictions of quan¬
tum theory, that as long as it works it is not
of overriding importance to know why it
works, influenced a generation of
researchers and still influences many
scientists today. But even after the 1920s
he made major contributions, especially
to the understanding of nuclear fission,
and as one of the prime movers in the
establishment of the European Centre for
Nuclear Research (CERN) in 1952. He
died peacefully in Copenhagen on 18
November, 1962, a few weeks after his
seventy-seventh birthday.
JOHN GRIBBIN, British astrophysicist and
science writer, former member of the Science
Policy Research Unit of the University of
Sussex, England, Is physics consultant to the
magazine New Scientist. He has written many
books on astronomy, geophysics and climatic
change. His most recent book, In Search of
Schrodinger's Cat (1984), deals with the de¬
velopment of quantum physics.
Nuclear Nirvana
For some reason, an atom seeks out a state in which its outer¬
most shell is closed, or full. For an atom like sodium, the easiest
way to achieve this Is to discard its outermost electron, leaving
bare the closed shell of eight electrons beneath; for an atom like
chlorine, which happens to have seven electrons in its outer¬
most shell, the easiest way to achieve chemical nirvana is to find
a spare electron to add to its collection. So sodium and chlorine
eagerly react together. Each sodium atom loses an electron and
is left with a net positive charge; each chlorine atom gains an
electron, and has a net negative charge. And the charged atoms
(ions) then arrange themselves in a crystal lattice, held together
by electric forces. The crystals are those of common salt, that
we sprinkle on our food.
The same end can be achieved in another way. A pair of elec¬
trons can be shared between two atoms, to form a chemical
bond. This happens, for example, when hydrogen and carbon
combine to form methane. Each carbon atom "wants" another
four electrons to complete its outer shell; each hydrogen atom
needs just one electron to fill its only shell, the innermost one,
which only holds two electrons. So four hydrogen atoms sur¬
round a carbon atom in such a way that eight electrons are
shared between them, and each atom has the illusion of existing
in the desired state, with a closed shell of electrons around H.M
Hydrogen
atom
©
Carbon
atom
4 Hydrogen atoms
and 1 Carbon atom...
0
®\V/©
(Shell has room for
1 additional electron)
(Outer shell has room for
4 additional electrons)
Ó
... combine to form
Methane (CH4)
Shared
electrons
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
In defence of folklore
by Jean Paul Guibbert
Design on a playing card from Purl, a
town In the province of Orissa, India,
depicts an Incarnation of the Hindu deity
Vishnu who ¡s shown In the form of a
hybrid creature, Navagunjara, a combina¬
tion of man and beast, bird and snake.
FOLKLORE in its various manifes¬
tations forms part of the heritage
of mankind; enshrining folk
memory and traditions, it constitutes the
living museum of our civilizations.
Transmitted by the oral tradition, in¬
herited and assimilated by imitation or
learning, folklore is volatile and fluc¬
tuating. In other words it is living, which
also means that it can die.
Transposed, adapted, modified,
folklore appears in a variety of guises. It
is a reflection of man, and like man may
be well or ill nourished, rich or poor.
Precious and fragile, prone to loss, ob¬
livion, caricature and, of course, to
plunder, it eludes close definition and its
range is difficult to circumscribe. In
other words it is both highly vulnerable
and hard to defend.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
s
©
Two examples of handicrafts from Benin.
Left, a ceremonial drinking cup fashioned
from a gourd engraved with friezes
bordering a bicycle motif. Right, In the
market at Porto Novo, the administrative
capital of Benin, metalsmiths have
transformed used tins Into sieves by per¬
forating them with traditional decorative
patterns.
Folklore today seems to be in a less for¬
tunate position than art, the protection of
which not so long ago provoked the same
doubts and hesitations. However, this ill-
fortune is also a sign of vitality, for the
resistance and opposition which folklore
arouses suggests that it does mean
something to us and that it does have a
life of its own, in addition to its rarely
mentioned attributes: the poetic and
didactic powers, the symbolic force and
cathartic possibilities, which make
folklore an effective instrument of cre¬
ation, education and the transmission of
values.
It is symptomatic of a growing trend
that Unesco should today be concerned
with the problem of the conservation and
protection of folklore. People every¬
where are coming to feel the heed for
roots, for the preservation of identity.
Without self-knowledge and self-respect
it is impossible to know and respect
others, and the cultural diversity in which
differences are rooted is also through
those very differences the hallmark of
the originality of the entire human race.
The key issue is folklore's right to ex¬
ist, a right which extends further than
recognition that it actually does exist and
raises more technical problems how
should folklore be defined, how should
its various forms be identified and kept
alive? This is why it will be necessary to
act with great flexibility. The machinery
which will have to be created could well
be based on models that have been
adopted for other forms of creative ac¬
tivity; but they will need to be adapted,
and provision will have to be made for ex¬
ceptions and special cases in order to
stimulate folklore as far as possible and
prevent it from becoming ossified. An ex¬
cess of legislation or categorization could
cause irretrievable losses. It is not im¬
possible that a kind of consensus may
spontaneously emerge from among those
concerned with the technicalities of
folklore, scholars and the representatives
of the different interest groups so that ex¬
cessive measures, whatever their nature,
will not be taken.
Opportunities must be created for the
widest public to discover, enjoy and
study folklore. It must also be explained,
put in its context or contexts, compared
and exchanged. Through an approach of
this kind folklore offers great potential
for promoting contact and under¬
standing between different peoples and
cultures.
But there is no doubt, either, that
folklore can be misused or caricatured in
ways which pervert its aims while
exploiting and even degrading its
substance, for its charm and fascination
are well known.
This raises the problem of the protec¬
tion of the rights connected with folklore,
as well as the more immediate concern to
protect folklore collections that exist to¬
day. Here too, it will be necessary to act
with a certain flexibility; otherwise
folklore may be confined within a protec¬
tionist system which would defeat its own
ends. Folklore will thus have to be ad¬
ministered and protected, like all human
property, through laws guaranteeing it
against attacks on its integrity and
authenticity. This all-round protection
will not be possible without purposeful
action on the part of the international
community, which, if its action is to be
fully valid, will have to take account of
the judgements and viewpoints of each of
its members.
Folklore cannot exist without people to
transmit it, and these people must be pro
tected, primarily within their own coun¬
try and community. But their protection
is a matter for universal concern.
Awareness of the issues involved must ex¬
ist both at the national and the interna¬
tional level.
The fact that such concern is felt, and
in many cases has been felt for some time,
in a number of countries which have
already created the necessary mechan¬
isms for the protection of folklore, is a
source of valuable experience which may
help other countries avoid a number of
pitfalls. Co-operation with these coun¬
tries and use of the knowledge they have
acquired may ease the way to the
establishment of various forms of pro¬
spection, collection and indexing of
folklore, as well as the diffusion of all
kinds of background data relating to it.
If the timeliness and even the feasibili¬
ty of establishing a binding international
instrument has been questioned, a ma¬
jority has nevertheless emerged in favour
of a flexible instrument, perhaps in the
form of an international recommenda¬
tion. Unesco's next General Conference
could formulate a number of principles
which States would be invited to adopt in
the form of national laws. Through inter¬
national co-operation and with the sup¬
port of clearly expressed wishes by the
nations, Unesco could contribute to the
establishment of the necessary infrastruc¬
tures, the formulation of a typology, the
training of personnel, the listing of rele¬
vant institutions and the constitution of
an international register of folklore
cultural property.
JEAN PAUL GUIBBERT, French sculptor,
poet and writer, is the author of a number of
studies on art and on the oral tradition. He has
a special interest in the popular and so-called
"primitive" arts and in problems relating to
the preservation and diffusion of, and exchan¬
ges between, the cultures of the world.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The classical repertory of Japanese Noh
theatre Is performed by professional ac¬
tors belonging to five schools which have
been officially recognized since the 17th
century. In 1910 a very ancient form of
Noh was discovered in Kurokawa, an
isolated rice-growing village northeast of
Tokyo. It had survived for centuries, and
is still performed six times a year by two
troupes of talented local actors on an Im¬
provised candle-lit stage (left).
Since it emerged In the early 1960s,
Butoh has become a leading modern
dance form In Japan. Moving with
dreamlike slowness In an atmosphere of
Intense concentration, Butoh performers
plunge Into a world ofshadows, in search
of the sources of life and dance. Butoh Is
largely improvised when executed by
solo dancers whose bodies are covered
with white make-up and who express
through bodily movements the Images of
their inner world. It mayalso be danced to
highly precise choreography, executed
by groups who try to create a universe or
rediscover a language of gestures in¬
herited from traditional daily life.
A piece of painted cotton cloth and a
ceramic bowl made by Peru's Shipibo In¬
dians and decorated with traditional geo¬
metrical motifs, the emblems of the tribe.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
This apple-wood gingerbread mould
depleting Adam and Eve Is part of a col¬
lection of wooden stamps and moulds
made In the 17th, 18th and 19th centuries
at the town of Torun, Poland.
Bottom photo : this 19th-century Cauca¬
sian carpet is from the Karabakh region of
Azerbaïdjan (USSR). The S-shaped
figures symbolize benevolent dragons,
and the diagonal lines, running water.
Below, Liatlf Kerlmov ¡s an ornamental
weaver and designer who has written a
major work on the carpets ofAzerbaïdjan.
j ÍLMI ' ^B ' jH'
mJejBy
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Unesco and the Preservation
and Protection of Folklore
ACTIVITIES for the safeguarding
of folklore were included in
Unesco's Programme in 1 973 as
the result of a communication from the
Government of Bolivia asking that con¬
sideration might be given to the possibili¬
ty of drawing up a Protocol to the Univer¬
sal Copyright Convention which would
govern "the conservation, the promotion
and the diffusion of folklore".
Following a number of preliminary
studies and exchanges of views with the
Committees set up by the International
Copyright Conventions (the Universal
Convention and the Berne Convention) in
order to determine the extent to which
the protection of folklore might involve
copyright, Unesco embarked on a global
study of the protection of folklore which,
if it is to be complete, requires an inter¬
disciplinary effort, and on a study of the
"intellectual property" aspects involved.
The latter is being carried out jointly with
the World Intellectual Property Organiza¬
tion (WIPO).
The comprehensive study of the pro¬
tection of folklore was begun in 1981
when a questionnaire was sent out to
Unesco Member States. Then, in
February 1982, a Committee of Govern¬
mental Experts met at Unesco head¬
quarters in Paris; it did not reach a con¬
sensus on the definition of folklore but in¬
vited Unesco to continue its work aimed
at formulating general regulations con¬
cerning the safeguarding of folklore.
In January 1985 a second Committee
of Governmental Experts met at Unesco
Established In 1981 with the support of
Unesco and its International Fund for the
Promotion of Culture, the an¬
thropological cinema workshop in Cairo
is the first of its kind In the Arab world. As
a centre for training, research and pro¬
duction Its aim Is to preserve and assert
traditional cultural values. Below, still
from a film made In Egypt by the
workshop shows a young potter at work.
headquarters to study the possible range
and scope of such regulations. In its con¬
clusions the Committee proposed that
folklore could be defined as follows:
"Folklore (in a broader sense, traditional
and popular folk culture) is a group-
oriented and tradition-based creation of
groups or individuals reflecting the ex¬
pectations of the community as an ade¬
quate expression of its cultural and social
identity; its standards and values are
transmitted orally, by imitation or by
other means. Its forms include, among
others, language, literature, music,
dance, games, mythology, rituals,
customs, handicrafts, architecture and
other arts."
Concerning the identification of
folklore, the Committee considered it ad¬
visable that systems should be set up to
collect and record its various manifesta¬
tions, and to co-ordinate the classifica¬
tion systems used by different
institutions.
The Committee also concluded that
the conservation of documentation
regarding folk traditions calls for the
establishment of a network of archives,
the standardization of archiving methods
and the creation of museums where
folklore would be represented. To pro¬
vide for the safeguarding of folk tradi¬
tions, it would be advisable to introduce
the study of folklore into educational cur¬
ricula, to guarantee the right of the
various ethnic groups and national com¬
munities to their own folklore and to set
up national folklore councils where
various interest groups would be
represented.
The dissemination of folklore should be
encouraged through organizing regional,
national and international folklore events
and keeping the mass media informed
about them, publishing periodicals, and
creating documentation centres and
libraries specializing in folklore.
As far as the use of folklore is concern¬
ed, the Committee concluded that it
would be useful to call the attention of
the relevant authorities not only to the
"intellectual property" aspects of the
question which are the subject of the
"model provisions for national laws"
adopted in June 1982 under the joint
auspices of Unesco and the World In¬
tellectual Property Organization, but also
to the fact that the protection of folklore
should cover the transmitters of tradition
as well as the materials gathered, and
that measures should be taken to
safeguard against misuse, whether in¬
tentional or due to negligence.
The Committee considered that
Unesco Member States should be invited
to co-operate with the relevant institu¬
tions and organizations and among
themselves, notably to ensure interna¬
tionally that the various interested par¬
ties (communities, or natural or legal per¬
sons) enjoy the economic and moral
rights resulting from the investigation,
creation, performance, recording and/or
dissemination of folklore.
With regard to the nature of possible
international regulations, the Committee
felt that these should not take the form of
an international convention. On the other
hand, there was unanimous agreement
that they might take the form of an inter¬
national recommendation, whereby
Unesco's General Conference formulates
principles that it invites Member States
to adopt in the form of a national law or
in some other way.
To preserve China's outstandingly rich
heritage of traditional folk music and
make It more widely known, the Chinese
authorities have launched a project to
collect popular songs from every pro¬
vince in the country. The resulting an¬
thology will eventually comprise 30
volumes. Unesco 's International Fund for
the Promotion of Culture is supporting
the project by providing the necessary
recording equipment. Photo shows musi¬
cians from Xianghe (Hebelprovince) play¬
ing traditional instruments. In fore¬
ground, a 75-year-old farmer Is playing a
kind of flute, known as Shuang Guan, In a
bowl of water to evoke swans at play.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Bartolomé de Las Casas
The apostle of the Indians'
by Silvio Zavala
Scenes from dally life among the Aztecs
(fishing, weaving, collecting reeds, poun¬
ding maize and cooking tortillas) such as
Bartolomé de Las Casas must have
witnessed many times during his long
stay in Mexico. The drawings are from the
Codex Mendoza, a 16th-century Aztec
manuscript ordered by the first Viceroy of
New Spain, Don Antonio de Mendoza, for
the Emperor Charles V. Drawn by an
Aztec artist, with text by a Spanish priest,
the Codex never reached the Emperor. It
turned up a century later at the Bodleian
Library, Oxford where It has remained to
this day.
NOT long ago, I saw in the window
of a Spanish bookshop a work
entitled "European Anti-colonial¬
ism from Las Casas to Karl Marx".
"Good", I said to myself. "Our hero has
again been summoned to lend a hand, as
always when great causes are at stake".
At first sight it seems obvious that Fray
Bartolomé de Las Casas, the great critic of
Spanish colonialism in the New World,
should have been an opponent of col¬
onialism and that today's anti-colonialist
movement should count him among its
great precursors.
Although he accepted Pope Alexander
VI's bulls of 3 and 4 May 1493 granting the
kings of Spain authority over the West In¬
dies, he interpreted them as conferring
responsibility on the Spanish temporal
power to work for the religious conversion
of the recently discovered peoples while
safeguarding their sovereignty and posses¬
sions in a political structure which he
described as quasi-imperial, maintaining
their freedom and their right to property
and bringing them to the faith as Christ and
His Apostles had preached, by persuasion
and not by force.
After his controversy with the Cordobán
humanist Ginés de Sepúlveda at Valladolid
in 1550-1551, Las Casas was asked "what in
his view it would be legitimate and ex¬
pedient to do". He replied that in places
where there was no danger the appropriate
form of evangelization was that only
preachers, together with those who could
teach the indigenous people good customs
in conformity with the Christian faith, and
those who could speak to them of peace,
should enter such territories. In those places
where danger was to be feared a few for¬
tresses should be built on the frontiers from
which negotiations could be started and
religion would spread gradually and make
headway through peace, love and good
example.
Las Casas added that this and only this
was the intention of Alexander VI's bull
and that of Paul III, that once they became
Christians (the indigenous people) would be
subjected to His Majesty..., not enslaved
nor deprived of their land, but placed under
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
his supreme jurisdiction, with some
reasonable tribute being exacted from them
for the protection of the faith and instruc¬
tion in good customs and government.
In other words, notwithstanding the
religious purpose assigned by him to the
Spanish penetration of the New World, Las
Casas admitted that side by side with the
preachers were those who could teach good
customs to the indigenous population and
discuss peace with them and that instruction
in the faith, in good customs and in govern¬
ment went together. In his History of the
Indies (book III, chapter 102) he asked that
real settlers be sent, "industrious people
who would live by cultivating such happy
lands as these, which would be granted by
their own natural owners and occupiers, the
Indians, and that they would intermarry,
and together would become one of the best
and perhaps most Christian and peaceful
republics in the world, and not to send in¬
discriminately all kinds of profligates who
would rob and destroy them."
Thus, as the French historian Marcel
Bataillon has rightly remarked, Las Casas
did not entirely exclude the idea of coloniza¬
tion but stressed that it should be peaceful
and educational, and that in order to create
a better republic the colonists should be de¬
cent, kindly folk who would not refuse to
intermarry with the indigenous population.
Las Casas thus foresaw the union through
intermarriage which was to be a feature of
the Latin American peoples up to our own
time.
Las Casas assumed that the right to rule
the Indians conferred on the Spanish
monarchs by the Papal bulls became effec¬
tive when the Indians freely accepted the
faith. The former Indian rulers then ceased
to rule in their own right and became
ministers of the Spanish crown. However,
for Las Casas, this rule was not purely
political; it constituted a convenient and
necessary means of spreading the Christian
faith.
Moreover, in a petition of February 1543,
Las Casas proposed that "in order to
establish the royal rights over these peoples
and lands legally and securely, and to en¬
sure that they shall be perpetual and un¬
disturbed, it should be considered whether
the best way to achieve this might not be for
the religious, the king's officers, and learn¬
ed persons nominated by the authorities to
conclude an agreement between the
emperor on the one hand and the Indian
lords and chiefs on the other, so that all
agree freely and voluntarily to be subjects
of his majesty and agree upon the moderate
royal tributes, dues and taxes to be paid to
the king"
Las Casas was opposed not only to the
armed conquest of the Indians but also to
their subjection to the encomienda system
whereby the Spanish crown granted
numbers of Indians as workers to Spanish
settlers known as encomenderos. His ap¬
proach to this problem did not lead to the
abolition of the system but it did lead to its
restriction by royal power and consequently
to better protection for the Indians who
were the victims of it.
In a preliminary study for his treatise De
Regia Potestate, he laid down that "no
State, king or emperor may alienate ter¬
ritories or change their political regime
without the express consent of the in¬
habitants". Here Fray Bartolomé pro¬
claims the right to self-determination, that
the cession of peoples or territories is not
legally possible unless the free consent of
the people or citizens concerned has first
been obtained. Las Casas concluded in his
treatise De Thesauris that "as long as the
people of this world of the Indies and their
kings do not freely consent to the papal
grant in favour of our monarchs, do not
ratify it and surrender possession to them,
they have only a title, that is to say a reason
for obtaining primacy over the said world
and a right to the kingdoms and their
universal supremacy or dominion which is
derived from the title, but have no right
over them". In the absence of this consent,
the kings of Spain lack the most important
right.
Las Casas' doctrine on freedom and
slavery is one of those which has caused the
most controversy between his admirers and
his opponents.
Born in Seville about 1484, Bartolomé de
Las Casas must have been familiar from
childhood with captives brought back from
the Levant, the Barbary Coast, the Canary
Islands and West Africa, who included men
and women with white, black and copper-
coloured skins. In his early experience as a
colonist in the West Indies in the manioc
fields, in places where gold was washed and
livestock reared, he had to do with An-
In 1502, ten years after Christopher Col¬
umbus, Bartolomé de Las Casas, a young
man from Seville, arrived In the West In¬
dies where he became famous forhis pas¬
sionate defence of the Indians against the
excesses of the Spanish colonists. Yet
this man who was to go down In historyas
"The Apostle of the Indians" has also
been described by an eminent 20th-
century Spanish historian as a
psychopath and a fanatic. His strong op¬
position to colonialism was Indeed sur¬
prising at a time when other European
countries, following the example ofSpain
and Portugal, were setting out on the
roadofcolonial expansion, with complete
disregard for the rights of other peoples.
Above, this engraving of Las Casas was
made from his only known portrait, the
work of the Spanish artist Antonio Lara.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
In 1544, at the age of 70, the controversial
Bartolomé de Las Casas received
recognition for his action on behalf of the
Indians when, on the recommendation of
Charles V, the Pope named him Bishop of
Chiapa, in the present-day Mexican State
of Chiapas. Under the terms of his ap¬
pointment this land was declared "pro¬
hibited to the conquistadors". Above,
Maya bas-relief from Chiapas depicts a
woman offering a helmet to the governor
of Yaxchilán. Right, a conchero or dan¬
zante de la conquista (dancer of the con¬
quest), one of a group of Indian dancers
who, during religious festivals at
Querétado, in Guanajuato State, Mexico,
commemorate a battle between Aztecs
and Spaniards which took place at the
time Las Casas was fighting desperately
to protect the Indians of New Spain.
tillean labour: Indian domestic servants and
workers, as well as with Caribs and other in¬
digenous people enslaved in wars and raids
by the colonists.
It was in this environment, after hearing
an uncompromising, courageous sermon
preached in Hispaniola in 1511 by the
Dominican Father Antón de Montesinos
that Las Casas was converted to the cause
of the Indians. The fundamental questions,
as recorded by Las Casas were: "Are these
not men? Should the precepts of charity and
justice not be observed towards them? Did
they not have their own lands and masters?
Have these people offended us in any
way?".
Las Casas campaigned against the
enslavement of the Indians because he did
not admit the justice of the wars waged
against them or the legitimacy of the so-
called ransom whereby Indian slaves seek¬
ing their freedom from their Spanish
masters were forced to enslave another In¬
dian to take their place, since there were
very few slaves among the Indians and the
word slave did not have the same
significance for the Indians as it did for
Europeans.
In Algunosprincipios, a document which
he included in the Tratados, or "Treatises"
published in Seville in 1552, Las Casas
asserted that every man is presumed to be
free unless the contrary is proved. All ra¬
tional creatures are born free, and freedom
is therefore a natural right. Slavery is an ac¬
cident which befalls a human being by
chance. It is a matter for the law of nations.
In the fifth "Treatise" he declares that
"after life itself, human freedom is the most
precious thing and consequently the most
worthy cause to defend, and whenever
anyone's freedom is in doubt, the decision
must be on the side of freedom". Thus, ac¬
cording to Las Casas "His Majesty'is oblig¬
ed by divine precept to order that all Indians
enslaved by the Spaniards be set free.
Bishops must be extremely solicitous and
diligent in seeking this. The religious should
agree amongst themselves in a learned and
saintly manner not to give absolution to any
Spaniard who holds Indian slaves unless he
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
first presents them for examination by the
Royal Tribunal (Audiencia) in conformity
with the New Laws, but they would do bet¬
ter still to resolve this without taking them
before the Audiencia, because of possible
sophistries in the legal proceedings".
As far as the slavery of Africans is con¬
cerned, it must be said that when Las Casas
was in the West Indies, he believed that the
precarious condition of the indigenous
population, who were close to extinction,
could be relieved if they were replaced by
manpower brought from Africa.
In her book Las Casas as a Bishop
(Library of Congress, Washington, D.C.,
1980) Helen Rand Parish confirms that
around 1543-1544 Las Casas was still think¬
ing of bringing two dozen African slaves to
his diocese of Chiapas to help the new
Spanish colonists and the religious by sow¬
ing cassava. She rightly believes that it was
only later, perhaps from 1546 and certainly
by 1552, that Las Casas came to realize the
utter injustice of black slavery and repented
of his earlier opinion.
On 30 June 1560, the archbishop of Mex¬
ico, Fray Alonso de Montúfar, wrote to the
king of Spain that "we do not see why
blacks should be captives any more than In¬
dians since, according to reports, they will¬
ingly accept the Holy Gospel and do not
make war on Christians".
In a famous passage in his History of the
Indies (book II, chapter 58), Las Casas
himself explains that he proposed the in¬
troduction of Blacks in order to alleviate the
condition of the Indians, but later repented
when he saw the injustices committed by the
Portuguese in seizing and enslaving them,
and from then on regarded them as unjustly
and tyrannically enslaved because "the
same reasoning should be applied to them
as to the Indians".
In his opposition both to the enslavement
of the indigenous peoples and of the
Africans, Las Casas has left us two ad¬
mirable definitions, one of his universal
concept of man, the other, which we have
' already quoted, of the fundamental value
of freedom.
In the History of the Indies (book II,
chapter 58), he repeats his famous conclu¬
sion that "all nations of the world are men
and are thus defined once and for all. All of
them possess understanding and will, all
have five external and four internal senses
(...), all take pleasure in what is good and
reject and detest evil, are disturbed by what
is disagreeable and harms them".
Furthermore, he believed in the aptitude
for civilization of all untutored peoples and
in their capacity to contribute to human
progress, because "just as uncultivated
land does not yield fruit but thistles and
thorns, yet contains inherent virtue which
enables it when cultivated to produce useful
and desirable domestic fruit, so there can be
no people in the world, however barbaric or
inhuman, nor any nation which, when
taught and instructed in the manner re¬
quired by the natural condition of man,
especially in the doctrine of the faith, can¬
not produce a plenitude of reasonable
men".
Las Casas' conversion to the anti-slavery
cause was a long and painful process, but
the conclusions he reached are just, and he
Las Casas has often been reproached
with having proposed the introduction of
Blackslaves to replace Indian labour. The
French historian Marcel Bataillon has
shown conclusively that Las Casas was
not the first to suggest this and that, in
any case, the suggestion was never
followed up in practice. Moreover, he
later bitterly regretted his words and in
his Historia de las Indias (Historyof the In¬
dies) he wrote that "the same reasoning
should be applied to them [the Blacks] as
to the Indians". Above, Portrait of a
Black, charcoal drawing by a contem¬
porary ofLas Casas, the great German ar¬
tist Albert Dürer.
left valuable seeds for those who would
later undertake similar campaigns.
When, influenced by the events of the
Napoleonic Wars, the Spanish colonies
began to revolt in 1808, the personality and
work of Las Casas again came to the fore.
His memory helped the insurgents to prove
that Spanish domination was harmful and
must be ended. His writings became bedside
reading for Fray Servando Teresa de Mier
in Mexico, for Simón Bolívar in Caracas
and Jamaica, and for Gregorio Funes in
Córdoba and Tucumán. And his memory
was revived by Juan Antonio Llórente, a
Spanish liberal in exile in France.
In his preface to the 1965 edition of the
Tratados of 1552, Lewis Hanke remarked
that it was topical to commemorate Las
Casas because the principles and ideas he
championed in the sixteenth century are still
being debated at a time when the world is
laboriously seeking an honourable basis for
lasting peace between peoples of different
cultures.
The critical examination conducted by
Las Casas not only led towards a repudia¬
tion of the use of force in subjecting other
peoples and of the evils of slavery and op¬
pression which accompany colonial rules, it
was also applied to his own thinking. This
is clear from the effort it cost him as he
came to insist on the consent of the Indians
as a prerequisite to their evangelization and
conversion and to their submission to the
temporal rule of the Spanish crown. The
same capacity for self-criticism is revealed
in the evolution of his thinking on the
enslavement of the Africans, to the point
where he applied to them the same doctrine
of freedom which he tirelessly defended in
the case of the Indians.
SILVIO ZAVALA, of Mexico, is a specialist in
the history of Latin America with a particular
interest in the Conquest and the Colonial
period. He was formerly director of Mexico's
National Museum of History, president of the
History Committee of the Panamerican Institu¬
te of Geography and History, president of the
International Institute of Philosophy and Hu¬
man Sciences, and a member of Unesco's
Executive Board. His many books on political
philosophy and the history of Latin America in¬
clude Sir Thomas Moore In New Spain, pub¬
lished in English translation.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Bullt between 1753 and 1759 during the
reign of Ferdinand IV ofSpain and named
after him, the fortress of San Fernando
controlled the strait of Bocachlca, the
narrow passage that gives access to the
outer bay of Cartagena. It was built In the
shape of a horseshoe the two points of
which were on the land side with a solid,
seml-clrcular wall facing out to sea.
Above, one of the many turrets In which
lookouts were posted to warn of the ap¬
proach of enemy warships.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Cartagena de Indias
'A city with a soul'
by Renata Duran
TTHE string of tall luxury blocks
stretched along torrid Caribbean
beaches suggests a modern city
meekly submissive to the demands of in¬
ternational tourism. This is only partially
and superficially true. Not far away stand
the steeply rising fortifications of old Car¬
tagena, the city built on the lovely bay of
the same name, on the Atlantic coast of
Colombia, as a magnificent riposte to the
attacks which this region coveted by the
enemies of imperial Spain had to endure
in the seventeenth century.
In the sixteenth century Europeans
were dazzled by the New World and long¬
ed to possess it. The seventeenth cen¬
tury, the age of pirates and privateers
(the latter, unlike the former, obeyed the
laws of the State which granted them
"letters of marque" authorizing them to
seize enemy ships and merchandise),
saw the growth of strongholds whose
ramparts and defences were vastly
superior to those of medieval times.
Solid and massive fortresses were
needed to withstand attack by heavy ar¬
tillery and cannon. The Spanish forts in
America met these specifications. Car¬
tagena was one of the most typical of
them and is, perhaps, the only one to
have survived virtually intact.
Sir Francis Drake, the English sailor and
privateer who fought the Spaniards in the
Gulf of Mexico and ravaged the coasts of
Chile and Peru, suffered a severe defeat
at the hands of the terrorized but valiant
citizens of Cartagena. The man who
would later take on the Invincible Armada
attacked the city a second time, in 1 586,
when he granted it freedom in exchange
for 100,000 ducats, 200 black slaves
and the church bells. On account of this
humiliation the Council of the Indies in
Madrid decided on the complete fortifica¬
tion of the city. For the Spanish empire,
Cartagena, the prey of greedy pirates,
was a vital point for the defence of its
communications with the whole of South
America, and especially with the
viceroyalty of Peru, since it was through
this warehouse and arsenal that all the
treasures of the former Inca empire were
sent to Spain.
Hence the exceptional geopolitical im¬
portance of Cartagena for the Spaniards
and, of course, for their enemies. Hence
too the strategic position of what was
then called "the key to the Indies of
Peru".
The walls of Cartagena, rebuilt and im¬
proved over two centuries, constitute a
piece of military architecture that
resisted repeated assaults by the Dutch,
the English and the French. Treasures of
colonial architecture are conserved
within them. Traces of the original in¬
habitants, many of whom came from An¬
dalusia, survive in the Mozarabic design
of balconies, windows and patios, and in
the language and traditions. Stone-lined
pools and luxuriant gardens surround the
The skyline of the old city of Cartagena
(founded In 1533) provides a backdrop to
the old port through which passed the
treasure of the New World to replenish
the coffers of Imperial Spain.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
inner thoroughfares of a still living city
with moisture and magic.
Cartagena has not suffered from the
excesses of progress. Thanks to its wise
master plan and architects, a substantial
part of the original layout has been
preserved. It is still possible to relive the
moments of the city's splendour. Saint
Peter Claver (1580-1654), the Spanish
missionary to the black slaves of
America, still imbues the city with that
heroic humanism that helped to mitigate
the cruelties of the Inquisition (the place
where its sombre ritual was performed
has wisely been preserved almost in¬
tact). Convents, churches, public foun¬
tains, cobbled alleys, tiny circular plazas
bring to the city an evocative charm.
Even the vaults built here and there in the
city walls have been preserved; they not
only served as shelters for the in¬
habitants during attacks by the English
and French but ironically were later
used by the Creoles when they fought
the Spaniards for independence, having
previously served as prisons for these
self-same heroes.
The forts of San Felipe de Barajas and
San Fernando de Bocachica which
defended the harbour are remarkable for
their original and ingenious design. A
group of fine mansions bears witness to
the magnificence of a port that grew rich
from the merchandise it redistributed
throughout South America.
The city was a rallying point for people
and ideas as well as for goods and ambi¬
tions. In Cartagena, a city with a soul,
blacks, mulattoes, mestizos and whites
lived and still livetogether. The cruci¬
ble of a new world, it has been the scene
of successive experiments in Latin
American integration. The Andine Pact
and the Cartagena Agreement are suffi¬
cient proof of this vocation. During the
colonial period the city succeeded in in¬
tegrating Catholic austerity with a pas¬
sion for adventure; today it combines
fidelity to the past with love of life. Car¬
tagena's vitality greets the visitor at
every step. Its present creativity gives
the lie to those who simplistically identify
conservation with stagnation. It is im¬
possible to escape the bewitchment of
the city's colonial atmosphere and
fortress-like character, but its people are
not drugged by the perfume of its past.
!i.SSSr-i
A typical street In the old town of Car¬
tagena. Corbelled balconies provide
welcome shade and add Interest to the
façades of the houses.
On the contrary it stimulates them to
face the challenges of today.
Cartagena de Indias is a city which has
miraculously resisted the corrosion of
time, the assaults of pirates and smug¬
glers who also tried to sell its soul, and
the indifference of the powers-that-be.
But above all it has survived the more
dangerous assaults of the worshippers of
progress who, insensitive to the charm of
the past, are always ready to demolish a
colonial house and replace it with a
pretentious concrete cube to show that
the city is vigorously facing the future.
Fortunately this wonderful city is also
determined to preserve its past, and the
intelligent expression of this determina¬
tion is, perhaps, the best contribution
Cartagena can make to the year 2000.
RENATA DURAN, Colombian lawyer and
writer, is a member of her country's perma¬
nent delegation to Unesco. She is the author
of two volumes of poems, La Muñeca Rota
(The broken Doll) and, to be published shortly.
Oculta Ceremonia (Secret Ceremony).
Covered balcony with carved wooden
balustrade ¡s a feature of the house of the
Marquis of Valdehoyos, a wealthy mer¬
chant of the 18th century. Recently
restored, this lordlyproperty is one of the
finest examples of colonial architecture
In Cartagena.
oo
It
So
o2
DO
<o
Ql-
OO
CI
ma.
Editorial. Sales and Distribution Offices'.
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.* The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced In microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris ;
(2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcsrd Edition. Indian Head. Inc.. 111
West 40th Street. New York. U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster. Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Brotdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Río de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekín)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Assistant Editors:
English Edition: Roy Malkin
French Edition: Neda el Khazen
Spanish Edition: Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Bibliographie Guide
To Studies OnThe
Status Of Women
Development &PopulationTrends
UNIPUB
A highly informative annotated bibliography
which provides an excellent guide to recent
research and world literature on the status of
women. Apart from published material, the
bibliography covers untranslated works in
local languages, theses, unpublished
documents and up-to-date information on in¬
stitutions undertaking research, and on major
events (meetings, etc.) related to the field of
women's studies.
A useful tool for scholars, planners and policy¬
makers, the bibliography covers three general
regions which are rarely found in a single
volume: the Western industrialized countries,
the Socialist countries, and Third World coun¬
tries. Each regional annotated bibliography
was compiled by women social scientists work¬
ing, teaching, and doing research in the
selected area.
Co-published with the Bowker Publishing Company,
UK, and Unipub, New York, who have exclusive sales
rights in the UK and the USA respectively.
ISBN 92-3-101914-7 (Unesco); 0-89059-002-8 (Unipub);
0-85935-066-5 (Bowker)
284 pages 175 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 175,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-1011, Vienna. BAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R.K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 68, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-113 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 1 1 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava - CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1 , SF-001 00
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 12598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr..H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 800830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon,
P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 1 3-1 5, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 1 49 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi;
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001 .
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 188 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 1 31 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000. ITALY. Licosa {Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 113. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 - 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Christchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1 104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum - Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404.
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications IS) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.CE. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 1 6. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. AM publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rámistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot atso in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road.
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.,
Istiklâl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SWS 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1X 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 1001 7. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor. Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Mica 30/.11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/1 1 , Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
.
a
am
bBMB
hHmM
- «
111
IIP
BHflB
HT
-P&
Stt
: 'if
^
Er
kamil Gok, Turkey's grocer-architect
*'I feel as though, like an octopus, 1 can
stretch out my tentacles in every direction.
I can paint fields, sculpt mountains, carve
«real rocks. When I close m> eyes in
meditation I see all these landscapes
transformed by my hand..." So speaks
Kamil (iok. grocer by trade, but architect
and landscaper at heart. At his village of
Derekoy, in the mountain region of
Rodrum. Turkey, this self-taught sculptor
and painter has created a wide range of
unusual works of popular art and visional}
architecture. Above, view of part of the un¬
completed mausoleum Kamil (iok has built
for himself near the village cemetery.
Turkish sculptor Mustafa Altintas. who
told us about Kamil Gok, feels that the
world should know more about the work of
this "odd-man-out'* of art.
]]>
</page>
</document>
