<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074933eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
NOVEMBER 1986-8 Frtnth francs
I
*mm
mm :
afira
wsVtf
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
<f-¥ f
>4**-
«f, i-i?.
i0 H
*?
r
',<
-
i « '
i
^Sí^f
\*7V
Ai
-* f»«
A time to live . . .
48 Gambia
Land for women
Women living in rural areas are the invisible
farmers of the Third World. In Africa alone they
produce, process and store almost 80 per cent of
food destined for family consumption. Along with
other organizations, the International Fund for
Agricultural Development (IFAD), which was
created in 1977 to increase food production and
income of rural populations in developing coun¬
tries, is co-operating with Third World govern¬
ments and other institutions in projects to im¬
prove conditions for these women. In Gambia,
where the Government had launched a project to
boost rice production, IFAD supported the
women who traditionally grow and harvest rice in
the marshes along the Gambia River (above) dur¬
ing successful negotiations to obtain rights relat¬
ing to the land they cultivate when this land was
redistributed. As a result of land redistribution
and the draining of the marshes, rice production
was increased sixfold, benefiting 15,000 persons
in 40 villages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
A window open on the world
Editorial
THE fresco of mental images peoples create of them¬
selves and the world they live in the main theme of
this issue of the Unesco Courier owes much to the
lessons they have learned from their history. Sometimes this
"popular imagination" focuses on a great man or woman.
Two such outstanding figures are commemorated in the
following pages: the great Islamic scholar and man of faith
al-Ghazäli; and Aleksandr Ostrovsky, the contemporary of
Tolstoy and Turgeriev who was one of the founders of the
Russian theatre, which has made such a notable contribution
to our understanding of the human soul.
The collective imagination is also a product of the interac¬
tion between different ways of perceiving and describing the
world. In this process, a "transfer of images" takes place in
which a community assimilates, sharpens or deforms its
conception of other peoples and civilizations. One illustra¬
tion of this phenomenon, described in this issue by Miguel
Rojas Mix, is the way in which depictions of the American
continent by European artists over the centuries have some¬
times but not always been distorted by projections of
European concepts and values. Likewise,« a comparison
between the cult of filial piety in China and certain religious
practices in the West casts a revealing light on differences
and similarities between two civilizations.
Imagination is inevitably rooted in the world of practical
knowledge. An instrument such as the Japanese abacus can
be used with amazing technical virtuosity as a calculating
instrument; it also opens up far wider horizons of mental
activity which stretch beyond the processes of arithmetic.
Recent developments in brain research are showing a similar
form of interdependence, as they stress the importance of
"co-operation" between the rational and the intuitive func¬
tions of the brain's two hemispheres. In the same strain, it is
now being realized that science and tradition are not mutual¬
ly exclusive, and that the most advanced discoveries of
science can be enriched by the deepest roots of tradition.
Finally, the imagination of peoples also shapes their
future, tracing a design for development which they alone
are equipped to define. Peoples can only advance towards
self-fulfilment when they draw on the vitality of their im¬
agination and the dynamism of their culture.
Cover: Illustrated envelope and stamps have been specially created
for the United Nations Development Programme (UNDP) and
issued at Vienna (Austria) by the United Nations Postal Adminis¬
tration. The envelope was designed by Anka Klausing of the
Alsterdamm School of Art, Hamburg (Fed. Rep. of Germany) ; the
stamps by Thomas Lee (China).
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
November 1986
39th year
*/ y.
4 Al-Ghazâlï:
From philosophy to mystical experience
by Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow
5 The spiritual quest of al-GhazälT
by Abdurrahman Badawi
9 Aleksandr Ostrovsky
Founding father of Russian theatre
by Nelly Kornienko
1 1 Latin America in European painting
One continent seen through the 'I' of another
by Miguel Rojas Mix
16 Saintly sons and daughters
Ancient China's enduring cult of filial piety
by Donald Holzman
20 How Japan reckons with the abacus
by Toshio Sawada
22 Breakthroughs in brain research
by David Ottoson
25 Science and tradition
Two spokes of a single wheel'
by Basarab Nicolescu
29 The human factor in African development
by Jean-Paul Ngoupandé
34 1986: Year of peace/11
2 A time to live ...
GAMBIA: Land for women
Published monthly in 32 languages English Italian Macedonian Turkish Finnish A selection in Braille is published
by Unesco French Hindi Serbo-Croat Urdu Swedish quarterly in English, French,
The United Nations Educational, Spanish Tamil Slovene Catalan Basque Spanish and Korean
Scientific and Cultural Organization Russian Hebrew Chinese Malaysian Thai
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. German Persian Bulgarian Korean ISSN 0041-5278
Arabic Dutch Greek Swahili N° 1 1 - 1986 - CPD - 86 - 1 - 439 A
Japanese Portuguese Sinhala Croato-Serb
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Al-Ghazäh:
From philosophy to mystical experience
/
í
¿**
á1 j&FT *í iff-'* i%
m .
<
©
Portrait of al-Ghazäli by the Lebanese
writer, mystic thinker and poet Gibran
Khalil Gibran (1883-1931), who emigrated
to the United States at the turn of the
century. Gibran's most noted work, The
Prophet (1923), was widelysuccessfuland
has been translated into 34 languages.
AL-GHAZÄLI's whole life seems to
have been guided by his determina¬
tion to restore the faith of the Mus¬
lims to its original purity and vigour. This he
attempted to do by taking up one by one the
challenges with which Islam was then faced,
deriving strength for his great work, which
he entitled "The Revival of the Religious
Sciences", from those challenges themsel¬
ves. In writing this work, he drew most
admirably on all the intellectual resources
provided by the accumulated intellectual
knowledge of his time.
He began by making an exhaustive
study which was to take him ten years of
all the intellectual traditions established
over the previous period, systematically
subjecting them to critical analysis but ack¬
nowledging that each one contained some
measure of wisdom and validity.
The development of his thinking at this
stage seems to have brought him to that
critical point in his life where, having
attained the summit of contemporary learn¬
ing, he began to reflect on the possibility of
acceding to a realm beyond all rational
knowledge leading, through the teachings
of Süfism, to a state of receptivity to the
ultimate divine truth.
He felt that he was invested with one last
mission in life to show his contemporaries
the light which he had so long and so
arduously sought and which had at last been
so fully bestowed upon him. In his eyes, the
mystical experience gave an overall mean¬
ing to the truest intuitions contained in the
various schools of thought of his time, while
breaking through the boundaries within
which each of them was confined.
He thus left us a work of rare breadth and
generosity, testimony to an exacting faith
served by an exceptional intelligence and
dedicated to the teaching of men of his own
generation as well as to the teaching of
generations to follow. In the development
of his thought, knowledge was always
directed towards serving the faith, and con¬
viction was constantly reinvigorated by a
critical spirit.
His influence was and still is very great in
the Muslim world, where he is seen by the
most erudite as one of those exceptional
Muslims whose thinking retains its vitality
and who have fully harmonized their
teaching with their own personal ex¬
perience.
In the West, his influence was consider¬
able although it was some time before the
entire significance of his work was fully
perceived. He was one of the first Arab
authors to be translated into Latin in
medieval Europe, and was first known
there through his book Maqäsid al-Faläsi-
fah ("The Aims of the Philosophers"). This
treatise was translated in Toledo by one
Master Johannes in the second half of the
twelfth century.
His account of Aristotelian logic,
metaphysics and physics, which he based on
an abridged version of Ibn Sïna's "Great
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Encyclopaedia", circulated widely in
Europe during the thirteenth century. By
contrast, his refutation, contained in the
masterly Tahafut al-Faläsifah (translated by
some as "destruction" and by others as the
"incoherence" of the philosophers), was
not known until much later, and even then
only indirectly through the criticism made
of it by Ibn Rushd in Tahäfut al-Tahäfut
(translated in the Middle Ages under the
title "Destructio Destructionis").
In the second half of the thirteenth cen¬
tury, a Catalan preaching friar, Ramón
Martí, who devoted himself to the study of
oriental languages, became acquainted with
several Arabic works by al-Ghazäli and
quoted in particular the Tahäfut and the
Munqidh min al-daläl ("The Deliverer from
Error"). Here, at last, al-Ghazâlï's thinking
appears to have been faithfully reproduced;
but Ramón Martí's works seem to have
been reserved mainly for the use of his
fellow friars.
In 1328, Robert of Anjou, King of Na¬
ples, requested a scholar from Aries, Carlo
Calonymos, to translate the Tahäfut al-
Tahäfut in which Ibn Rushd began by giving
an objective account of al-Ghazâlï's main
ideas and then proceeded to criticize them.
This gave Europe a fresh opportunity to
become acquainted with the real thinking of
al-Ghazäli but for a long time Calonymos'
translation remained practically unknown.
Not until the end of the fifteenth century
and the Renaissance was a new version of
Ibn Rushd's book printed and widely circu¬
lated in Italy. Only then did al-Ghazâlï's
work, and the full significance of his think¬
ing, begin to be known in Europe.
What, today, in general terms, are the
lessons to be learned from his thinking,
even outside the Islamic world? First of all
that al-Ghazâlï can be seen as a unique
witness of an age distinguished by great
intellectual turmoil and by much question¬
ing about ultimate aims in relation to the
realities of social life.
This is certainly where the evolution of
al-Ghazâlï's thinking, which played so im¬
portant a role in the development of West¬
ern thought, can still be a source of inspira¬
tion today.
Al-Ghazâlï reacted to the challenges of
unprecedented intellectual, scientific and
technological development and to its
psychological and social consequences,
both per se and in regard to the faith, by
adopting an approach that was exemplary
in its scrupulousness. Enlightened by the
most progressive knowledge of his time, he
embarked on the path of luminous spiritual¬
ity and intellectual revival which gave to
culture its most creative stimulus.
This article is a slightly shortened version of an address
given by the Director-General of Unesco on 9 Decem¬
ber 1985 at Unesco Headquarters in Paris, during a
symposium on al-Ghazäli.
¡ftp
IssSäDälllüllE
©
* i
The spiritual quest
of al-Ghazâlï
by Abdurrahman Badawi
ABU Hamid al-Ghazâlï, a great
theologian, a penetrating and sub¬
tle-critic of rationalist philosophy
and a mystic with great gifts of psychologic¬
al and moral analysis, was born in 1058 in
Tüs, today called Meshhed, in eastern Iran,
and died in 1 1 1 1 . One of the greatest think¬
ers humanity has ever known, he was hon¬
oured with the title hujjat-al-isläm (Proof of
Islam) for his role as a defender of religion
against the rationalist atheism of the philo¬
sophers and of orthodox Islam against sects
preaching heresy and subversion. The
lucidity of his writings and the beauty of his
prose were such that his works were widely
circulated and won a very extensive reader¬
ship. His masterpiece, entitled Ihyä' 'ulüm
al-dïn ("The Revival of the Religious Sci¬
ences"), was, and is still, a reference work
on the principles and practice of the Muslim
religion.
There were three stages in al-Ghazâlï's
spiritual development: a stage of practical
involvement and political commitment, a
stage of doubt and criticism, and a mystical
stage.
Having received a sound training in case
law and theology from the great masters of
his time, and primarily from the Imam al-
Haramayn (al-Djuwainï), al-Ghazâlï went
to seek favour with the great vizir Nizäm
al-Mulk in Naysäbür. The latter was im¬
pressed by al-Ghazâlï's learning and cogen-
The decorative qualities of the angularand
geometric Küfic style ofArabic calligraphy
has led to its widespread use for religious
inscriptions carved in stone. Above, re¬
production of a Küfic inscription inside a
mausoleum at Isfahan (Islamic Republic of
Iran). Highly stylized into square and rec¬
tangular forms, the calligraphy of this in¬
scription dating from the early 14th cen¬
tury seems to evoke certain trends in mod¬
ern graphic design.
cy in debate, and, as an earnest of his admir¬
ation, he apppointed him in 1091 to teach at
the Nizämiyyah school in Baghdad. One
year later, Nizäm al-Mulk was murdered by
a young Bätinite. The Bätiniyya was a Shi-
'ite sect, the militant branch of the Ismä'ili
sect. During and after the crusades, its
members were known by the name of
hashishi. The activities of the Bätinites
posed a serious threat to the Abbasid
caliphate in Baghdad.
The Caliph al-Mustazhir accordingly in¬
structed al-Ghazâlï to wage war with his pen
against the Bätinite sect. Al-Ghazâlï wrote
a book entitled the Mustazhirt, or The De¬
pravity of the Bätiniyya, in which he re¬
vealed its impostures and unmasked its evil
designs against Islam and its great conspira¬
cy against the State. This work analyses in
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
detail the sect's stratagems to attract well-
wishers and rally them to its cause, for the
Bätinites were skilled at making converts.
At the age of thirty-four, al-Ghazâlï be¬
gan to study philosophy. He then entered a
period of profound spiritual crisis in which
he came to doubt his faith. That doubt was
transient and lasted for only two or three
months. It was more a "dark night of the
soul" than the methodical type of doubt
practised by Descartes, as some scholars
have mistakenly suggested. But that doubt
was a goad which spurred him to subject his
beliefs to unrestricted scrutiny. In Mlzan
al-amal, he asserts the usefulness of such
doubt, for "he who does not doubt, does
not think; he who does not think, does not
see; he who does not see remains in a state
of blindness, perplexity and error".
Being blessed with a positive attitude of
mind, he could not remain in a state of
doubt for very long. Thus we see him enter¬
ing a new phase: that of certainty based on
reason. He had found a new vocation,
which drove him to defend the great articles
of faith against the rationalism of the Isla¬
mic philosophers, including al-Färäbi and in
particular Ibn Sïna (Avicenna).
By way of a prologue to his diatribe
against the philosophers, he wrote for the
layman a clear and easily grasped summary
of the three principles of philosophy: logic,
physics and metaphysics. That summary is
entitled Maqäsid al-Faläsifah ("The Aims
of the Philosophers"). It is a brief and lim¬
pid exposé, unclouded by polemic or per¬
sonal opinions.
This was the prelude to his philosophical
masterpiece, Tahäfut al-Faläsifah ("The In¬
coherence of the Philosophers"), in which
he launches a sustained attack on the
rationalist philosophers. As he states in the
prologue, this book is a refutation of the
ancient philosophers, designed to prove the
falsity of their doctrines, to expose their
contradictions in the sphere of philosophic¬
al theology (metaphysics) and to reveal the
dangers inherent in their opinions.
In this work, he claims that between the
different philosophers there are huge di¬
vergences, and bitter conflicts between the
different systems. He therefore confines
himself as he says to a refutation of the
philosophy professed by the greatest of
them, namely, Aristotle.
According to al-Ghazâlï, Aristotle and
philosophers in general "judge by conjec¬
ture and presumption, and not by verifica¬
tion and certainty" in the field of meta¬
physical theology. He therefore sets out to
In 1095, afterbeing embroiledin a religious
controversy with the Islamic philo¬
sophers, al-Ghazâlï experienced a period
ofdoubt. He wenton apilgrimage to Mecca
and visited Jérusalem, where he began to
write his masterwork Ihyä' 'ulüm al-dln
("The Revival of the Religious Sciences"),
which he completed during a two-year
stay at Damascus. Above, elaborate
mosaics on a golden background adorn
the cupola of the Dome of the Rock, the
shrine built in Jerusalem in AD 691 by the
Umayyad caliph 'Abd al-Malik. The shrine
is built over a flat sacred rock which many
traditions connect with Abraham and
Muhammad. Right, the Great Mosque of
Damascus (Syria) was built in AD 705, also
under the Umayyads, on the site of the
Byzantine church of St. John the Baptist
and of a Roman temple once dedicated to
Jupiter.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
i
111 '
s
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
0flagra.
The modem town of Meshhed, near the
eastern border of the Islamic Republic of
Iran, is an offshoot of the ancient city of
Tüs, the birthplace of al-Ghazâlï, which
was destroyed by the Timurids in 1389. As
the site of the mausoleum of the Imäm AH
Reza, eighth Imam of the Shi'ites (died AD
818), and of the adjoining mosque of Ga-
whar Shäd (15th century), Meshhed is the
Holy City of the Shi'ites and a major pil¬
grimage centre. Above, enamelled tiles
cover minaret and porch of the Shäh
Mosque (14th century).
Below, the four minarets of the Käzimayn
Mosque, one ofthe mostbeautiful in Bagh¬
dad, which became the seat of the 'Abbä-
sid caliphate in AD 750, and was the
greatest religious and economic centre of
the Near East until it was sacked by the
Mongols in 1258. Al-Ghazâlï taught law in
this prestigious city before applying him¬
self to the study of philosophy, then
embarking on the path of Sufi mysticism.
prove the falsity of their ideas in the follow¬
ing fields:
The eternity of the world.
The creation of the world.
The proof of the existence of God.
The attributes of God.
Divine knowledge.
The movement and the prime mover of the
Heavens.
The possibility of miracles.
The immortality of the human soul.
Resurrection and life after death.
After a disputation with the philosophers
on these topics, he concludes with a con¬
demnation of the following three theses:
their assertion that the world is eternal;
their assertion that God does not know
particulars, i.e. the acts of human beings;
their denial of resurrection and eternal life.
"These three theses are wholly incom¬
patible with Islam. Anyone who professes
belief in them is thereby claiming that the
prophets are liars and that they made their
pronouncements only for utilitarian pur¬
poses, using parables for the sake of clarity.
But this is a manifest heterodoxy (kufr)."
{Tahäfut)
As regards the remaining theses, al-Gha¬
zâlï finds similar tenets in the various Mus¬
lim sects; they are therefore not incompati¬
ble with Islam.
Some scholars have claimed that al-Gha¬
zâlï's attacks on the philosophers who had
upheld these three theses struck a mortal
blow to philosophy in the Islamic world.
This allegation is quite false since, during
the century which followed al-Ghazâlï's
death, Muslim philosophy reached its
apogee in Muslim Spain with Ibn Bäjja, Ibn
Tufayl and Ibn Rushd (Averroës), and con¬
tinued to advance in the East with Suhra-
Wardi, Bawwânï and Mulla Sadrá.
Al-Ghazâlï argued with the philosophers
"using their own method, that is, a logical,
rational and rigorous method". But in the
depths of his soul he felt that reason was not
enough to attain the supreme truths of re¬
ligion. He realized that he needed to use
quite another faculty in order to penetrate
directly to the heart of the mystery of being.
In 1095 he experienced another crisis, much
more acute than the first, whereupon he
abandoned his teaching at the Nizämiyyah
school in Baghdad and set out on the pil¬
grimage to Mecca. After (or before) that
pilgrimage, he visited Damascus and Jeru¬
salem. In Jerusalem he began to write his
masterpiece, the Ihyä' ("The Revival of the
Religious Sciences"), which he completed
in Damascus during the two years that he
spent in that city.
After Damascus he returned, in 1097, to
his native town of Tüs, where he had re¬
solved to end his days in mystical retreat.
But the vizir of Koräsän, Fakhr al-Mulk,
son of Nizäm al-Mulk mentioned earlier,
invited al-Ghazâlï to take up teaching once
more. Al-Ghazâlï demurred, but the vizir
was insistent. Al-Ghazâlï therefore began
to teach again, not at the Nizämiyyah of
Baghdad, but at that of Naysäbür, after an
eight-year retreat. However, one year later,
in approximately 1106, he returned to Tüs
in order to devote his time to writing several
mystical treatises, including the Mishkätal-
anwär ("The Niche for Lights"). He also
wrote his autobiography there, Al-Mun-
qidh min al-daläl ("The Deliverer from
Error").
In the Mishkät, al-Ghazâlï draws inspira¬
tion from a verse of the Qur'an which pro¬
claims that "God is the light of the heavens
and the earth", and reveals a vision of a
world structured around the concept of
light. He shows how that divine light suf¬
fuses and sustains the world with its count¬
less rays. The world is accordingly repre¬
sented as a pure crystalline sphere, scat¬
tered with opaque points of matter.
The Munqidh, his autobiography, is a
masterpiece of remarkable psychological
insight. It retraces his spiritual development
and uncompromisingly dismisses jurists,
theologians, Bätinites and philosophers
alike, reaching the conclusion that the only
true Way is that of the mystics. Compared
with the Confessions of St. Augustine, the
Munqidh is more concentrated, but more
precise and structured. It is free of the
grandiloquence and prolixity that we find in
the Bishop of Hippo.
The influence of al-Ghazäli was
tremendous, both in the Muslim world and
in medieval Europe.
Six of his works were translated into Heb¬
rew in the thirteenth century. Some, includ¬
ing the Maqâsid, were even translated
several times. Jewish philosophers influ¬
enced by al-Ghazâlï include Isaac Albalag,
who translated the Maqäsid, Moses of Nar-
bonne, who wrote a major commentary on
the same work, and Jehudah Halevi, who
makes abundant references to the treatise
entitled "The Grounds of Belief" (later in¬
corporated into the Ihyä'). David Yehuda
Léon even goes so far as to claim that
Maimonides drew on the works of al-Gha¬
zâlï as his main source of inspiration.
The Maqäsid was translated into Latin in
the twelfth century by Domingo Gundisal-
vo, a well-known translator of the Toledo
school. The Tahäfut (Destructio philo-
sophorum) was likewise translated into
Latin, together with its refutation (Destruc¬
tio destruction^) by Averroës in about
1325.
What influence did the works of al-Gha¬
zâlï exert over the thinkers of the late Mid¬
dle Ages and the Renaissance? This has still
to be determined. However, we reject the
parallels that have been drawn wrongly,
in our opinion between the method of
approach of al-Ghazâlï and that of certain
modern European philosophers: between
the doubt of al-Ghazâlï and that of Des¬
cartes, for example, and between the con¬
ceptions of causality found in al-Ghazâlï
and in David Hume. These are empty
hypotheses , totally without foundation .
ABDURRAHMAN BADAWI, of Egypt, is a philo¬
sopher and an historian of philosophy. Former
head of the departments ofphilosophy at a num¬
ber of universities in Egypt, the Libyan Arab
Jamahiriya and Kuwait, and a visiting professor
at the Sorbonne, Paris, he is author of over a
hundred publications in French and Arabic,
mainly concerned with existentialism, Greek and
Arab philosophy and contemporary German phi¬
losophy.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Aleksandr Ostrovsky
Founding father of Russian theatre
by Nelly Kornienko
SOMETIME in the autumn of 1849, in
the famous Moscow literary salon of
Countess Rostopchin, an elegant,
fair-haired man of twenty-six read his play
Bankrot ("The Bankrupt") to an audience
of distinguished literary figures including
the great Nikolai Gogol. More readings of
this work, which had opened the doors of
Moscow's salons to its author, were soon
delighting the evening patrons of the city's
cafés and taverns, but the imperial theatres
remained immune to the enthusiasm felt by
the new playwright's first admirers. Tsar
Nicolas I banned the play and had its au¬
thor, Aleksandr Nicolaevich Ostrovsky
(1823-1886) watched by the police. His sixth
play was the first to be staged and all its
successors had problems with the censor.
The author of some fifty plays, Ostrovsky
is the creator of the Russian "comedy of
manners" and the founder of the repertory
of the Russian theatre. He was born and
grew up in the Zamoskvorechye commer¬
cial district of Moscow, away from the city's
major thoroughfares. Destined by his
father for a career in commerce, the young
Ostrovsky's first employment was with the
Moscow civil court. His youthful observa¬
tions of different types of merchants and the
setting in which they lived were to provide
him with material for most of his plays.
In face of obstinate, ignorant, despotic
money-grubbers respectful of the estab¬
lished order, conformists such as Podkha-
liuzin, Bolshov and Kabanikha, he sets
figures on a par with such great characters
of the European drama as Hamlet, Karl
Moor or Laurencia, the creations of
Shakespeare, Schiller and Lope de Vega.
In Dokhodnoe Mesto (1857, "A Profit¬
able Post"), Zhadov champions those who
go "against social customs and conditions. . .
The struggle is arduous and often fatal, but
the glory for those who win through and the
gratitude of later generations is all the
greater. . . . Without them lies and evil would
have proliferated to hide the sun's light
from men". In Les (1871 ; The Forest, 1926),
the tragedian Neschaslivtsev proclaims that
"honour is boundless", and Parasha, in
Gorzhacheiya serdce (1869, "A Yearning
Heart"), asserts for all to hear, "You can
take away all I have but I shall never give up
my freedom	 For my freedom I would go
to the scaffold."
The tragic end of Ostrovsky's finest char¬
acters always springs from their rectitude,
their purity, their nobility of spirit, their
moral integrity and their conviction that
love is the ultimate meaning of life. In this
respect Ostrovsky echoes the preoccupa¬
tions of Dostoyevsky, for whom beauty will
save the world, or the law of love and the
vocation of goodness dear to Tolstoy.
Ostrovsky wished "to put the people on
the right path without harming them". Be¬
cause of the logic of the plot, people who
make their mark in life through hypocrisy
and duplicity often triumph in his plays. But
the real victors are losers like Katerina, who
is incapable of living dishonestly and throws
herself into the Volga, or Larissa, the girl
without a dowry whose fine talent has been
brought to nothing by the vulgarity of life
and who murmurs "Thank you" to Karan-
dychev, her murderer and saviour, before
she dies. Ostrovsky wants a person who
rebels against oppression and arbitrariness,
a free spirit, to become the "law of life".
It should thus come as no surprise that
circles close to the court of the Tsar, suspi¬
cious of culture and the theatre and
apprehensive of new ideas, stopped at noth¬
ing to prevent Ostrovsky's heroes from
being portrayed in the theatre, even though
they might admit that Ostrovsky himself
was not without talent. It was said contemp-
"You alone have completed the edifice
whose foundations were laid by Fonvizin,
Griboyedov and Gogol. It is because of
you alone that we Russians can proudly
say that we have our national theatre. In all
justice, it should be called the Ostrovsky
theatre." This tribute to Aleksandr N.
Ostrovsky was made by the writer Ivan A.
Goncharov, seated at extreme left of this
photo taken in the editorial offices of the
magazine Sovremennik. Seated with him
(left to right) are Ivan S. Turgenev, Alek¬
sandr V. Druzhinin, and Ostrovsky. Stand¬
ing behind them are Leo N. Tolstoy and
Dim¡tri V. Grigorovich.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Scene from a production of The Forest at
Moscow's Maly Theatre where this and
otherplays by Ostrovsky still have an hon¬
oured place in the repertoire. The Forest,
written in 1871, describes the decline of
the Russian aristocracy and the rise of a
new class of merchants, who buy up the
large estates at rock bottom prices and
ruthlessly clear their forests.
With his general's uniform, narrow-
minded outlook and generally decrepit
appearance, Krutinsky, a character in
Ostrovsky's comedy Even a Wise Man
Stumbles, symbolizes the decadent in¬
stitutions of the old Russia. Above, Kru¬
tinsky played in a 1910 production by the
greatactoranddirectorKonstantin Stanis¬
lavsky.
tuously of his plays that they "stank of
sheepskin".
Nevertheless, under the pressure of pub¬
lic opinion , Ostrovsky was elected a Corres¬
ponding Member of the Academy of Scien¬
ces in 1863. Shortly before, on the new
ceiling of St. Petersburg's Maryinsky the¬
atre, his portrait had been added to those of
the classics of Russian satire, Fonvizin, Gri-
boyedov and Gogol.
"The existence of a national theatre is the
sign that a nation has reached its majority,"
wrote Ostrovsky, "just like that of
academies, universities and museums." In
addition to his creative work as a dramatist,
he gave many years of his life to other
activities connected with the theatre. Mos¬
cow's "Little Theatre" (or "Maly") where
he staged many of his plays, was dubbed
"the Ostrovsky house". And only six
months before his death he was appointed
director of the repertory of Moscow's impe¬
rial theatres where in face of considerable
obstruction he nevertheless succeeded in
introducing reforms. His influence on the
history of the theatre was in every respect
enormous.
Ostrovsky's horizons broadened as the
years went by and came to include other
social classes as well as the merchants. In
the 1870s he created a new type of charac¬
ter, the cold, ambitious bourgeois, the Rus¬
sian equivalent of Balzac's Rastignac.
Ostrovsky analyses certain forms of Rus¬
sian behaviour and patterns of thought with
such originality and authenticity that this
"Russianness" slowed down the introduc¬
tion of his work to other countries. In
France, for example, the first performance
of Groza (1859; The Storm, 1898) possibly
his masterpiece, did not take place until
1889.
Around the middle of the nineteenth cen¬
tury the Russian novel of Tolstoy, Dos-
toyevsky and Turgenev conquered Western
Europe, but Ostrovsky's plays remained
unknown there because of the exceptional
translation difficulties involved. In the East
too, interest in his plays only began to
appear much later. In adapted form, his
work enjoyed a certain success in China in
the 1920s, but did not achieve world fame
until the 1960s and 1970s, when plays by
Ostrovsky were performed in over forty
theatres in Delhi, London, New York,
Paris, Milan, Hamburg, Basle and else¬
where. Since then their author's literary
reputation and stature have continued to
grow.
In Ostrovsky's own country, the greatest
directors of the twentieth century have been
attracted to his work. Konstantin Stanis¬
lavsky staged Snegurochka ("The Snow
Maiden", 1872) a poetic masterpiece made
famous by Rimski-Korsakov's operatic
adaptation of it, and "A Yearning Heart".
Vladimir Nemirovich-Danchenko, author
and drama teacher who founded the Mos¬
cow Art Theatre with Stanislavsky, staged
Na vsyakogo mudretsa dovolno prostoty
(1868; Even a Wise Man Stumbles, 1944),
and the great Vsevolod Meyerhold pre¬
sented The Forest and "A Profitable Post".
Two other avant-garde directors, Alek¬
sandr Tai'rov and Yuri Zavadsky, staged
respectively Bese viny vinovatye ("The In
nocent Guilty") and Bespridannitsa (1879;
"The Girl without a Dowry"). Musical
adaptations and experimental versions have
also been performed in the present decade.
Some of Ostrovsky's plays have also been
adapted for the cinema and television.
Among them are Yakov Protazanov's ver¬
sion of The Poor Bride, Vladimir Petrov's
The Storm, and, more recently, Eldar
Riazanov's Gestoki romanse ("The Cruel
Romance"), which was a great success with
the public.
All these productions have made known
a new Ostrovsky who sings a hymn to love
and fidelity.
A man of wide culture, Ostrovsky did
much to bring to the Russian stage dramat¬
ists from other literatures. Among the
works he translated into Russian are the
Asinaria of Plautus, Terence's Hecyra,
Shakespeare's The Taming of the Shrew and
Antony and Cleopatra, Machiavelli's The
Mandrake, and works by Seneca and Cer¬
vantes.
With Nikolai Rubinstein, director of the
Moscow Conservatory, and the actor Piotr
Sadovsky, Ostrovsky created in 1865 the
"Artistic Circle" the first society of artists
in Russia whose members included
actors, writers, musicians and painters. Im¬
pressed by the teachings of the Russian
physiologist and naturalist Ivan Sechenov,
he worked out a theory of acting based on
the idea of reciprocal conditioning between
the actor and his environment.
In the last years of his life, Ostrovsky
spent much of his time on his estate at
Chtchelykovo, in the region of Kostroma,
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
**
T
4 1
The actress Alice Koonen as Katerina in a
1924 production ofOstrovsky's The Storm
(1859). In this interpretation oftheplayas a
"peasant tragedy" Katerina is the per¬
sonification of pride and purity, ready to
lay down her life for the right to be free.
which became for him what Boldino was for
Pushkin, Yasnaya Polyana for Tolstoy, and
Bougival for Turgenev.In this country re¬
treat he wrote more than a dozen of his
finest plays. And it was there, in June 1886,
in his house built high on a hill in the midst
of the countryside he loved, where even the
storms seemed more beautiful than else¬
where, that Ostrovsky passed away. Borne
by peasants on long pieces of drapery
embroidered with traditional motifs,
escorted by faithful friends, Ostrovsky's
coffin was carried through the places from
which he had drawn inspiration to the
cemetery of Nikolo Berezhki.
Today the house at Chtchelykovo is an
Ostrovsky Museum, a place of pilgrimage.
Nothing neither the setting nor the wel¬
come has changed. The visitor almost ex¬
pects to see the master of the house appear
in the clothes he loved to wear in the coun¬
try Russian shirt, wide trousers and high
boots, short grey doublet and wide-brim¬
med hat ready to sit down at his work
table.
NELLY NICOLAEVNA KORNIENKO, of the
Soviet Union, is a specialist in dramatic art and in
the sociology of culture, subjects on which she
has written some 40 works published in her own
country and elsewhere. A former member of the
sociology of culture sector at the Soviet Institute
of Scientific Research into Art, she is currently a
staff member of the Russian language edition of
the Unesco Courier.
Latin America
in European painting
One continent seen
through the T of another
by Miguel Rojas Mix
¿rpi| HE people are blue-skinned and
have square heads." The Euro¬
peans were still disembarking in
the New World when John of Hollywood, a
cosmographer with the name of a film-star,
penned this azure-tinted, geometrical por¬
trait of its inhabitants. At the time when he
wrote or even earlier, with the publication
of the letters of Christopher Columbus an
"imaginary America" began to take shape
through images in which people and the
natural world were continually transmogri¬
fied into the most unusual and fanciful
forms.
Over the centuries, works of art depicting
America were coloured by the spirit of the
age in which they were created. The earliest
of them encompass the entire continent,
but from the eighteenth century onwards
the United States has a separate image.
After that date, we shall refer exclusively to
Latin America.
The first image of America, coinciding
with the classical aesthetic of the Renais¬
sance, was a "fantastic" one. The "Dis¬
covery" (although to avoid Eurocentrism it
would be preferable to talk of "the arrival of
the Spaniards") does not seem to have
made a great impression on Europe. Apart
from travellers' tales and the engravings
illustrating them, there are few contempor¬
ary accounts of the impact made by this
event on the European continent. We are
left with three major literary works: "Des
cannibales", a chapter of Montaigne's
Essays; Thomas More's Utopia; and
Shakespeare's The Tempest.
There are also a handful of allusions and
exotic details in paintings by the great
artists: a name on a map by Leonardo da
Vinci, a plump agave cactus in The Garden
of Earthly Delights by Hiëronymus Bosch
and a sunflower lurking somewhere among
his sketches; a Saimirí squirrel monkey in
St. John on Patmos by Hans Burgkmair the
Elder; and a strange figure of Apollonian
physique, clothed in feathers, used by
Dürer to decorate the prayer-book of Maxi¬
milian I.
And yet newly-discovered America
seemed to be tailored to fit European
dreams. In the New World, all myths found
concrete expression. The "newest of the
new" walked hand in hand with the old.
There, merging and overlapping, were to
be found Eden, the country of Ophir and El
Dorado. Columbus believed that he had
discovered Paradise, and Dürer and
Rubens followed current taste by placing
between Adam and Eve a parrot a bird
which, though undeniably beautiful, seems
to symbolize a sin of frivolity which has
been imputed to America ever since.
Through the landscapes of the New
World wandered creatures from the classic¬
al and medieval bestiaries: giants cohabited
with basilisks, and Amazons, with one
breast slashed off, encountered ster-
nocephaloids, creatures with heads beneath
their shoulders. In addition to these figures
were plants and animals the evocation of
which inspired artists to create a world
where miracles could happen, unhampered
by the mundane restrictions of daily life.
America was to exert an influence, even
if indirect, on the emergence of a series of
themes in European painting. Did the en¬
counter with its pristine natural world con¬
tribute to the discovery of landscape paint¬
ing as a genre? (Dürer was the first Euro¬
pean artist to paint pure landscapes.) We
cannot be sure. What is certain, however, is
that in reawakening the classical opposition
between "techne" (art and technique) and
"physis" (nature), America raised once
again the question of the origins of human¬
ity and fostered in painters a certain taste
for the primitive. And not only for biblical
primitivism many painters have worked
on the theme of Paradise: Cranach, Jan
Brueghel, Titian, etc. but also for classical
primitivism, Orphism and nostalgia for the
Golden Age, which influenced the style of
Piero di Cosimo's works.
Nevertheless, there is little reference in
European painting to the primitive lives of
the inhabitants of America, for the simple
reason that Europe never managed to de¬
cide whether they were barbarians or "no¬
ble savages". Were the indigenous people
of America human beings or animals?
Europeans wondered. Did they have souls?
Should they be enslaved? Should they be
exterminated? And although Bartolomé de
las Casas maintained as long ago as the
mid-sixteenth century that all the nations of
the world consist of human beings, the Puri¬
tan colonizers had very different ideas.
Even in the nineteenth century the poet
James Russell Lowell had a Yankee soldier
in the Mexican War confess that before he
left home he was convinced that Mexicans
were not human beings but a nation of
orang-outangs that could be slaughtered
without a second thought.
In 1637, John Maurice of Nassau, Gov-
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THEODORE GERICAULT (Rouen, 1791 -
Paris, 1824). The Battle of Maipú, gouache,
around 1818. Paris, Bibliothèque
Nationale. This little-known work by Gérl-
cault depicts the meeting between José de
San Martín and Bernardo O'Higgins after
their army had defeated the Spanish
forces at Maipú (8 April 1818) and brought
independence to Chile. Géricault, who
painted his famous Raft of the "Medusa" in
the following year, epitomizes the spirit of
the Romantic painters who championed
"modernity" and the new freedoms, and
closely followed contemporary events in
Spanish America and elsewhere.
ALBRECHTDÜRER (Nuremberg, 1471 -id.
1528). This figure (below) drawn in the
margin of the prayer-book of the Emperor
Maximilian I (1515) is an example of the
way in which the non-European was en¬
visioned by early 16th-century Europe as
radically different from the European, in¬
corporating features from India, Africa and
America.
©
id -. .-ii» . .» miyti
« courts umi>i » W»1»0M«II MM
12
THE MAP OF TEMIXTIAN (Mexico City),
known as the "Cortés Map", incorporates
a schematic map of the Gulf of Mexico (at
left of document), and is the oldest known
map of the island of Tenochtitlán, the site
ofpresent-day Mexico City. It Is attributed
to Hernán Cortés since it appears in the
first Latin edition of the conquistador's
second letter to Charles V, published In
Nuremberg In 1524. This highly Imagina¬
tive piece of work with Its European-style
city buildings may have been a source of
inspiration for Utopian thought. (Its influ¬
ence may be seen in a plan for a Utopian
city dating from around the same time and
attributed to Dürer.) The link between
America and Utopia seems to have been
close; in his book Utopia (1516), Thomas
More learns of the existence of Utopia
from a certain Hitlodeo, who is presented
as a former companion of the Italian navi¬
gator Amerigo Vespucci, from whom the
American continent takes its name.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
^ ernor and Representative of the Dutch
West India Company, took up residence in
Pernambuco. In his entourage were Frans
Post and Albert van der Eeckhout, two
artists who had been instructed to paint
everything that lived and moved and had its
being there. While they were in Brazil, they
produced works that were true to life.
When they returned to Europe, however,
buyers considered their paintings to be in¬
sufficiently exotic and decorative, and to
comply with the taste of the age they were
obliged to invent a Brazil of gaudy jungle
scenes and improbable animals. Such was
the "Baroque image" of America.
This new style loved exuberance and an
exoticism that gave short shrift to geo¬
graphical precision. America now became a
set of decorative motifs and competed in the
salons with "Chinoiseries". Some of the
finest depictions of exotic America date
from this period: the "tapestries of the In¬
dies", large canvases into which are woven
images of Indians, llamas, tapirs, etc. in
short, all the animals and plants with which
America astonished the Old World all
jumbled together with animals and plants
from Asia and Africa. For Baroque, the
exotic has no geographical location, but is
simply "outside Europe".
But America became fashionable for
allegory as well as for decorative exoticism:
she is one of the matrons representing the
"Four Quarters of the Globe". These
female figures were a favourite motif of the
time, because on ceilings and at the heads of
staircases they could give solid expression
to the limitless power-hungry aspirations of
Absolutism and the no less ambitious mis¬
sionary pretensions of the Counter-Refor¬
mation. Giovanni Battista Tiepolo, the un¬
disputed master of this art, produced the
finest representation of America as an
Amazon, with the horn of, plenty in one
hand and a skull at her feet. Rich and
barbaric. Rich, and thus promising bound
less wealth to kings; barbaric, and thus open
to legitimate conquest. The country must
be converted to Christianity and civilized:
profit and its justification fused in a single
image.
This image of America changed in the
nineteenth century with the advent of
Romanticism. The Romantics brought a
spirit of liberalism, and their art expresses
the values of a nascent middle class. Their
themes included the new freedoms, revolu¬
tion, the abolition of slavery, the people,
progress, nature and travel. In America the
Romantics found plenty of grist to their
mill. A series of engravings by William
Blake denounces slavery in Suriname; a
watercolour by Géricault celebrates a deci¬
sive battle for the independence of Chile.
But, above all, such concerns find express¬
ion in the taste for the picturesque to be
found through travel and in the feeling of
wonderment before the rich profusion of
the natural world.
Romantic exoticism is nevertheless dis¬
tinct from that of the Baroque period. It
prides itself on being scientific and attempts
to reproduce the landscapes, animals and
people of the New World with total veri¬
similitude. It is the exoticism of exploration
in the travels of Alexander von Humboldt,
and the literary exoticism of Chateau¬
briand, who describes the Niagara Falls
with a geographer's scrupulous attention to
detail. Humboldt attempts to marry art and
science in "treu und lebendig" (faithful and
lively) representation of reality. This com¬
bination was to be of benefit to both: to art,
since contact with such magnificence in na¬
ture would revitalize landscape painting,
and to science, which was thus able to en¬
rich its stock of images (photography was
still unknown). The spirit of Humboldt im¬
bues most of the German artists who
travelled to America in the nineteenth cen¬
tury: Johann Moritz Rugendas, who jour¬
neyed throughout the continent; Ferdinand
Bellermann, who visited Venezuela;
Eduard Hildebrandt, to whom we owe one
of the most vivid depictions of Brazil in the
mid-nineteenth century; and many others,
including Pissarro.
This great French painter, born in the
West Indies, arrived in Venezuela under
the name of Pizarro. He was twenty-two
years old. His style was in keeping with the
naturalism favoured by Humboldt, but
even at this early date he was determined to
capture the intensity of the light. Was this
naturalism, bathed in the sunlight of the
Caribbean, the first stage of the quest that
would make him one of the founders of
Impressionism? Whistler, another artist
obsessed with light, would leave in one of
his paintings a fleeting record of his brief
contact with South America. At anchor one
night in the world's remotest harbour, he
painted Valparaiso: Nocturne in Blue and
Gold.
Three outstanding painters of the end of
the century had intermittent connections
with America: Manet, who produced a
number of versions of The Execution of
Maximilian; Henri (Le Douanier) Rous¬
seau, of whom it is claimed, on scanty
evidence, that he was in Mexico with the
French army and there discovered the
"tropical" landscape that is unmistakably
his own; and Gauguin, the great master of
modern exoticism, which he portrays as à
refuge from civilization. Gauguin was influ¬
enced by his childhood in Peru. Both in his
pottery and in some of his paintings we find
the shapes of Mochica vases: head-shaped
jars which are self-portraits, and terra-cotta
vases with the uplifted faces of Breton
women, just as in Inca society, where there
were no tables, the clay faces must have
gazed upwards to meet the eyes of their
owners and masters.
At the beginning of the twentieth cen¬
tury, the image of America becomes Janus-
faced. One face is that of the mass media;
~
:>.-
V
\
THEODORE DE BRY (Liège, 1528 - Frank-
furt-am-Main, 1598). Engraver famed for
his 13-part Travels in America published
between 1590 and 1634. The Amazon and
the sternocephalic figure were two of
many fantastic creatures which European
travellers and chroniclers claimed to have
found in Brazil and Guyana, and show how
European myths were projected onto
America. The Amazon is a figure from clas¬
sical mythology and the headless man
appears in a legend associated with im¬
aginary journeys. Headlessness is also a
feature associated with such figures as
Gog and Magog and Antichrist. The
monstrous creature here epitomizes the
Indian's diabolical nature.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
DE BRY, El Dorado. The engraving below
depicts the original myth ofEldorado ("the
glided one"), a name first applied to the
chief of a rich country who according to
legendplastered his naked body with gold
dust before plunging into a sacred lake.
Eldorado later came to mean a whole fabu¬
lous country ofgold which was described
in the 18th century by Voltaire : "Near to a
certain Parima, whose sand was ofgold. ...
There was a city with gilded roofs. ..."
WILLIAM BLAKE (London, 1757- id.
1827). Poet, painter and illustrator of Dan¬
te. Blake also expressed his humanist
vision in his illustrations for John Gabriel
Stedman's Narrative of a Five Years' Ex¬
pedition against the Revolted Negroes of
Surinam (London, 1796). Blake shows In
atrocious detail (right) how slaves were
tortured to death. His work and that of
painters who followed him anticipated the
struggle for the abolition of slavery.
ae-v ,s l
.
-1"" -ö*ä*s»v
m&.
HENRY MOORE (Castleford, 1898 - Much
Hadham, 1986). Like many European
artists, the great English sculptor drew
inspiration from pre-Columbian art. The
Reclining Figure, below, outside the main
building of Unesco Headquarters in Paris,
and other works bearing the same title,
have a strong affinity with effigies of the
Aztec divinity Chac Moot. Opposite page
below, statue of Chac Mool in the Temple
of the Warriors, Chichén Itza, Yucatán,
Mexico.
I
»T
'
\
II I
1 IT t
1 1* J
0-
rr
©
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
m
m
PAUL GAUGUIN (Paris, 1848 - Atuona,
Marquesas Islands, 1903). Above left, Self-
Portrait, stoneware, 1889, Copenhagen
Museum ofDecorativeArts. The same ves¬
sel features in apicture Gauguinpainted in
the same year, Still-life with Japanese
Woodcut (Ittleson Collection, New York).
Like Gauguin's other ceramics, this self-
portrait is strongly inspired by pre-
Columbian Peruvian pottery such as the
anthropomorphic Mochica vase (above
right). Gauguin may have sought self-
realization In exoticism through memories
ofhis childhood in Peru or because of the
Peruvian blood he inherited from his
maternal grandmother.
the other, that of art. The media have
accumulated all the stereotypes that have
represented America throughout history,
together with new clichés born of specific
historical events. The image of parrot-like
frivolity, human degradation in hot cli¬
mates, sloth and childishness has been com¬
pounded by that of machismo, corruption,
the siesta and lust for revolution. Such is the
image put across by the cinema, advertising
and light novels, and often, too, by more
serious literature. The comic strip is largely
responsible for projecting this image,
although it is true that comics are now be¬
ginning to change. The Indian is regarded
with less contempt, and the Western hero
has doubts about his moral superiority. This
may be to some extent due to the influence
of the French social anthropologist Claude
Lévi-Strauss, who altered the concept of
"the savage mind".
The image found in art is quite different.
In the early twentieth century it sought
renewal through the discovery of new rules
of formal expression. When Picasso,
Braque and Matisse drew on African aes¬
thetics to creat modern art, all non-Euro¬
pean art was seen with new respect as a
source of inspiration for the avant-garde.
Many artists became interested in pre-Col¬
umbian art. One was Henry Moore, whose
Reclining Figures irresistibly evoke the sta¬
tue of the Aztec divinity Chac Mool. The
image of twentieth-century art thus came
into being, not merely as a prolongation of
Greek classicism of the aesthetics of Phi¬
dias and Praxiteles but also as the syn¬
thesis' of the creative abilities of all huma¬
nity. Cubism, abstract art, expressionism
and other schools of art owe much to the
sensibility of these "foreign cultures".
Thus over the centuries America has
been depicted in images which do not al¬
ways correspond to reality but tend instead
to reflect European interests and changes in
Europe's idea of itself from one period to
the next. In this context, the non-European
is little more than a mirror. Europe has
projected its own vision of itself whether
classical, Baroque or Romantic onto "the
other". As this vision changed, "the other"
changed too. And so we see an America
that is imaginary in two senses both be¬
cause its story is told in images and because
it is more imaginary than real. As an Indian
says to a European in an illustrated story by
the Italian author Milo Manara: "Everyone
knows that Indians cannot really exist in
your world."
afeé - ' -' -
v..,,. _. . t . ._,. ...
MIGUEL ROJAS MIX, of Chile, is the founder
and former director of the Chilean Institute of
Latin American Art. A former professor at the
Sorbonne, he is currently teaching at the Uni¬
versity of Vincennes, Paris. He is the author of
several published works, including Vera historia
natural de Indias (The True Natural History of the
Indies) and a short history of Latin America for
children.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
I*
Saintly sons and daughters
-r
Ancient China's
enduring cult of filial piety
Drawings show the evolution of3 Chinese
characters from pictorial representation.
Left to right, ideograms signifying "old",
"child" and "filial piety". The latter is a
combination of the first two.
Calligraphy © Hsuing Ping Ming, Paris. Drawings from L'origine
des caractères © Yong Bao Zai, Beijing. 1979
by Donald Holzman
THE desire to reach out beyond our
everyday lives to find some kind of
permanence or absolute meaning
for them seems to be universal, but each
civilization reaches out in a different way.
To study one of the methods the Chinese
have employed to attain to this heightened
meaning of life may teach us something
about the bases of Chinese civilization and
also something about our own.
The Chinese have espoused various
forms of religiosity throughout their long
history. Filial piety is possibly the most
enduring of all these forms. Archaeologists
believe that the burial sites in Banshan,
eastern Gansu, which date from the begin¬
ning of the third millennium BC, show that
the Chinese already celebrated an ancestor
cult at that time. Whether or not we accept
their hypothesis, it is clear that filial piety
was the cornerstone of the most ancient
Chinese royal religion. The worship of the
supreme deity, God on High (Shangdi)
could only be carried out through the
worship of the king's own ancestors who
served as "go-betweens" (peí) to the deity.
Evidence of filial piety is also found
throughout the earliest period of Chinese
history, even though the character for filial
piety, xiao, strangely enough, does not
appear in the earliest writings, the oracle
bone inscriptions. On bronze vessels dating
from as early as 1000 BC, a Chinese scholar
writing in 1974 counted sixty-four inscrip¬
tions containing the word for filial piety, in
contexts showing that the sentiment con¬
cerned living members of the family (pa¬
rents and brothers) as well as ancestors.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
It is hard to appreciate today what it
meant to be "filial" in ancient China; too
few texts dealing with everyday life have
survived to enable us to reconstruct in detail
what it was like to live in a Chinese family
in, say, 1000 BC. However, some ancient
texts do give us glimpses of what Chinese in
that distant past thought of their parents,
providing a picture not entirely different
from that presented by Chinese family life
today. Poem no. 202 in the "Minor Odes" of
the "Book of Poetry" (Shijing), for exam¬
ple, contains a very moving description of
an orphan lamenting the death of his
parents, and the "Book of Documents"
(Shangshu) contains a number of references
to filial piety, the most important (and
probably one of the oldest) being in the
"Announcement to Kang" (Kanggao). The
passage in question not only equates unfilial
children with "the worst criminals", it also
describes unfilial behaviour in emotive
terms, saying that an unfilial son "wounds
his father's heart grievously".
Yet in the earliest stories told about filial
sons and daughters there is something that
non-Chinese find hard to believe or under¬
stand. A story in a very late section of the
"Book of Documents" about the early cul¬
ture hero, Shun, and his barely credible
filial conduct towards his blind father and
his wicked stepmother, is typical of the
stories of filial sons. In one of the very few
works of Antiquity that tell us much about
everyday life, the Zuozhuan ("Zuo's Com¬
mentary" on the Chunqiu), a work that is
generally thought to have been recorded in
written form in the mid fourth century BC
but may contain genuine material from as
early as the end of the eighth century, are
other stories which it is equally difficult to
believe.
It is surely not a coincidence that the very
first story in the Zuozhuan concerns filial
piety. It describes the actions taken by
Duke Zhuang of the state of Zheng who has
done everything in his power to remain filial
to his mother whose treacherous behaviour
towards him would seem rather to merit the
strictest punishment. Yet the commenta¬
tors, beginning with the author of the
Zuozhuan himself, find that his behaviour
-MCW^m zzw&
i%7tt
mt >!*
i
.» l\ I ii' ! J	 WW
II
föS&M :,i£Zíí
hty, . jjyii if. rjjr a «ftTTT
<^Z¿JS^ShA. J | \|VU
was not filial enough! The stories of Jizi
(695 BC) and of Shensheng (659 and 655
BC) both of whom prefer to die rather than
to deny their fathers' exorbitant demands,
are similarly hard to take. In all these stories
filial piety seems to require absolute obedi¬
ence to one's parents.
These earliest examples of the import¬
ance of filial piety are more than confirmed
in the Golden Age of the philosophers.
Every single school of philosophy without
exception, even the iconoclastic Daoists
and the anti-traditional Legalists, accepted
filial piety as a natural, inevitable human
sentiment. The Legalists, indeed, coupled
the virtue with "loyalty" (zhong) and gave it
an importance in the government of the
State that it had never had previously but
that it was to keep until our own day.
Illustration depicts an episode in the life of
a model son, Xue Bao. "His father remar¬
ried and his new wife, taking an intense
aversion to Xue Bao, had him sent away
from the house. Buthe criednightandday,
unable to leave, until they took a stick to
him and he was obliged to lodge in a hut
outside the house. In the mornings he
would go In to sprinkle and sweep, which
angered his father, who chased him out
again. "
Photo from an 1 8th century Korean work on virtuous people from
Chinese history © Musée Guimet, Paris
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
m
^O z H
BK
Drawing of Cao E., a Chinese heroine cele¬
brated for her filial devotion. Her father
was a shaman who drowned while celeb¬
rating the cult of the God of the Waves.
"His body was not recovered, and his 13-
year-old daughter, Cao £., went along the
river wailing and crying night and day
without stopping. Seven days later she
threw herself into the river and drowned. "
Confucius makes filial piety a corner¬
stone of his philosophy, but his remarks on
the subject show that for him this quality
transcends ordinary rationality and should
be treated as something inviolable. It is
generally agreed that Confucius, in his
"Analects" or "Conversations", provided
China, and the world, with some of the
loftiest, most deeply human and appealing
moral insights ever pronounced. But his
dicta on filial piety seem so stiff and doctri¬
naire that they might almost have been
made by someone else, a follower so intent
on keeping the letter of Confucius' teaching
that he lost its spirit.
But I am by no means sure that this is the
case; is it not rather that the very special
role played by filial piety in Chinese
thought in general, and in Confucian
thought in particular, gives to his pro¬
nouncements on the subject a stiff, absolut¬
ist tone quite absent from the rest of his
work? Precisely because the Chinese have
considered filial piety as something "abso¬
lute", something universally recognized as
beyond question, a distinctive form of mor¬
al hero or saint has come into being. De¬
tailed study of this "saint" may reveal some¬
thing important about the Chinese way of
thinking.
The three examples already cited from
the Zuozhuan show men doing very strange
things, leading to suicide for two of them, in
order to respect blindly the sometimes irra¬
tional wills of their parents. Many similar
sacrifices must have been made in the
ancient period, but it is only under the
Empire [after the unification of China in
221 BC] that stories of filial sons and daugh-
Scene from the life of St. Mary Magdalen
de Pazzi (1566-1606), patron Saint of Flor¬
ence who was canonized in 1669. In spite
of a fragile constitution, she lived in great
austerity and attained a high degree of
mysticism. She is shown below at the age
ofeleven when, wearing a crown of thorns,
she spent entire nights flagellating
herself.
2
Photo from an 18th century Korean work on virtuous people from
Chinese history © Musée Guimet, Paris u
©
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
ters become commonplace and are re¬
corded in detail. A chapter is reserved for
them in twenty of the twenty-four dynastic
histories and countless separate collections
are devoted to them, much like the "Lives
of the Saints" that were so popular in
Europe almost until modern times. It may
be that filial piety only became noteworthy
under the Empire when it was institutional¬
ized as an "imperial" virtue, rewarded by
the State with stipends and titles that could
lead to high official posts in the civil service.
The earliest examples of filial extrava¬
gances I have been able to find in the dynas¬
tic histories are taken from the Hou Hon¬
shu, principally from Chapter 39, which is
entirely devoted to filial sons and daughters
and probably dates from the middle of the
fourth century AD.
The Preface to Chapter 39 tells two stor¬
ies about sons who showed filial piety. The
first describes a man who serves as an offi¬
cial only to be able to take care of his
mother, who has no personal interest in the
glory such service might procure for him.
The second tells a story that is so typical that
I shall quote the beginning of it in full:
"At the time of Emperor An [who
reigned from AD 107 to 126] there lived a
man from Runan [southern Henan] named
Xue Bao. ... Studious and sincere, when his
mother died he was renowned for his per¬
fect filial piety during the mourning period.
His father remarried and his new wife, tak¬
ing an intense aversion to Xue Bao, had him
sent away from the house. But he cried
night and day, unable to leave, until they
took a stick to him and he was obliged to
lodge in a hut outside the house. Mornings
Two edifying cases of filial piety are de¬
scribed in a 14th-century collection of
Chinese poems by Gui Ju Jing entitled
Twenty-four Examples of Chinese Piety.
Drawing this page, left shows the Emperor
Wu of the Han dynasty (standing) and his
mother (seated at left). After becoming
Emperor, Wu continued to treathis mother
with the same filial devotion as before.
Whenever she took a medicinalpotion the
Emperor tasted it himself before giving it
to her. Drawing right evokes the story of
another model son. The family of 8-year-
old Wu Weng lived in a region infested with
mosquitoes. Because his parents were so
poor that they could not afford to buy a
mosquito net, Wu Weng slept in their bed¬
room and let himself be bitten by the mos¬
quitoes so that his parents could sleep
undisturbed.
he would go in to sprinkle and sweep, which
angered his father, who chased him out
again. Then he set himself up in a hut next
to the gate of their ward, but never failed to
greet his parents in the evening and in the
morning. After a year or so his parents felt
ashamed and had him come back."
Later, when his father and stepmother
died, he doubled or tripled the mourning
period. Xue Bao is typical of the filial sons
we read about in texts of this time. In fact
his actions seem almost normal when you
compare them with some of the other filial
sons and daughters that fill the pages of the
Hou Honshu.
We learn of four-year-old children who
refused to eat and drink when their parents
fell ill, and of a man who "ate no meat and
drank no wine for over ten years after the
death of his father, and commemorated the
anniversary of his death by fasting for three
days". Some of the stories, such as that of
Yang Zhen (died AD 124), are even more
amazing. A scion of one of the founding
families of the Han dynasty, Yang Zhen
taught school early in life to keep aloof from
politics:
"Fatherless when young and poor, he
lived alone with his mother. He rented
some land to cultivate and thus provide for
their sustenance. Once one of his pupils
tried to help him plant cabbages, but Yang
Zhen pulled them up each time, and re¬
planted them a little further on. The neigh¬
bours called him 'filial'."
Yang Zhen, believe it or not, is here
proving his filial piety by insisting that his
mother's cabbages were planted by her
son's own fingers!
Moving cabbage plants around is a harm¬
less enough demonstration of filial feelings,
but there are many examples of deaths
caused by a desire to give irrefutable proof
of filial piety. The most famous example is
the story of Cao E, who lived near what is
now Shaoxing in Zhejiang. Her father was a
shaman (wu) who drowned on the fifth day
of the fifth lunar month (6 June) in AD 143,
while he was celebrating the cult of the God
of the Waves (perhaps a deification of the |
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
^ tidal bore). "His body was not recovered,
and his thirteen-year-old daughter, Cao E,
went along the river wailing and crying
night and day without stopping. Seven days
later she threw herself into the river and
drowned."
Another filial daughter, Shuxian Xiong
(or Shu Xianluo), drowned herself in
Sichuan, on the other side of China, on the
spot where her father had drowned, and
was found floating in the water with her
father in her arms six days later. Jiang Shi
drowned because he ventured too far out
into the river to fetch drinking water for his
mother who preferred river water to well
water.
The stories showing self-sacrifice, mira¬
cles, cruel persecutions (usually by
mothers-in-law or stepmothers) greeted
with forbearance, useless suicides, extraor¬
dinary examples of brothers who refuse to
leave one another even to sleep with their
wives, except to produce offspring, fill the
pages of the Hou Honshu and are in fact
found throughout Chinese history.
How can these astonishing actions be
accounted for? They are strongly reminis¬
cent of the behaviour of the Christian saints
of late Antiquity and the Middle Ages.
Mortifications, leper-licking, holy anorexia
and other excessive actions were never
deemed excessive enough to prove the
saints' love for and adoration of their
Creator. Is this not a similar phenomenon
to that of Chinese filial piety?
The Chinese woi Id-view, as has often
been remarked, is much more earthbound
than the world-view of the West; imman¬
ence has always been preferred to trans¬
cendence in China, and when the Chinese
reach out towards their "creator" they re¬
fuse to take the metaphysical leap the Wes¬
terner finds normal and look toward those
they know are their true creators, their
parents. "The Book of Filial Piety" (Xiao-
jing), a mediocre document that probably
dates from the very end of Antiquity or
from the beginning of the Imperial era and
has been extraordinarily popular through¬
out Chinese history, says this in almost so
many words. In Chapter 9 we read: "there
can be no greater veneration of the father
than to make him the go-between with
Heaven." The word used for "go-between",
pei, and the context, show that the authors
of the Xiaojing here are referring to the very
earliest Chinese religious practices known
to us, according to which sacrifices were
presented to royal ancestors who, as go-
betweens, interceded and presented to
Heaven their descendants' requests. This is
to give the father a mystical role and to
identify him, if not as God, at least as a
stepping-stone toward God. Thus in this
respect the Chinese are not far from making
gods of their parents, and their actions show
them, like their Western counterparts,
attempting to reach out beyond themselves
to glorify their creators, who are literally
their fathers and mothers.
DONALD HOLZMAN, born in Chicago, USA, is
head of the Institute of Advanced Chinese Stu¬
dies in Paris, and director ofstudies at the School
of Advanced Studies in Social Sciences, also in
Paris, where he is professor of Institutions of
Imperial China.
How Japan reckons with
SURPRISING though it may seem in a
country where many business enter¬
prises are computerized and where
microcomputers are widely used in schools
and families, the soroban or Japanese aba¬
cus is still playing a unique role in Japanese
life as a calculating device and as an educa¬
tional tool.
The soroban was introduced into Japan
from China about 450 years ago. The
Japanese then developed and began to
manufacture an improved version which was
soon being used throughout the country. Chil¬
dren were taught to handle the soroban in
small schools known as tera-ko-ya and it is no
exaggeration to say that the three R's in
Japan became "Reading, Writing and soro¬
ban".
Why, at a time when the price of computers
is falling and their performance is improving,
should the soroban not only survive but form
part of training programmes organized by
some Japanese firms, with one world-famous
computer manufacturer even holding an
annual soroban contest for its employees?
There are several answers to this question.
Firstly, a skilful handler of the soroban is likely
to be a dab hand at immediately spotting
errors in facts and figures, and able to use
mental arithmetic to make the kind of instant
estimates that are invaluable in business
analysis and decision-making. Another plus
for the soroban is that using it helps to develop
the kind of psychomotor skills required for
handling keyboard machines.
Today the use of the soroban is taught in
Using the soroban or Japanese abacus,
this 1 1-year-old schoolboy can solve with¬
in ten minutes twenty addition and sub¬
traction problems involving 5- to 10-figure
numbers, and perform mental arithmetic
calculations on 12- to 13-figure numbers.
At the blackboard, a primary schoolboy
solving multiplication problems by mental
arithmetic.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
the abacus by Toshio Sawada
Japanese primary schools, from the third year
on, and occupies a major part of the curricu¬
lum in higher commercial secondary schools.
A number of features make the soroban a
useful educational tool. By manipulating
beads pupils can actually see the process of
calculation, become familiar with numbers
and enjoy learning to be numerate. It also
helps them to understand decimal notation.
Another advantage, since higher figures are
handled first (see drawings) is that it is easy to
see approximate figures and also, incidental¬
ly, to calculate not only written but dictated
numbers.
Research has shown that handling the
soroban develops certain kinds of mathema¬
tical skills. Japan won first prize at a World
Congress cf Mathematics held a few years
ago. Might further investigation show that this
victory was in some measure due to the con¬
tinuing role of the soroban?
TOSHIO SAWADA, Japanese educator, is a
senior specialist for curriculum in the Vocational
Education Division of the Elementary and
Secondary Education Bureau at the Ministry of
Education, Japan.
Lower beads worth 1 Frame Dots indicating units Column rods Upper beads worth 5
^^^^^^/t>^V^^_^t>^^^^
L	L	L	L/	L	L	/
The soroban is a calculating instrument
consisting ofa rectangular frame contain¬
ing a number of counting beads which
slide back and forth along rods. A cross¬
wise bar divides the soroban into two
parts: the upper part consists of a row of
beads each with a value of 5 and the lower
part has four rows of beads each with a
value of 1. On the crosswise bar, a dot is
marked at every third rod to Indicate the
unit or the decimal point. The rows of
beads to the left have a higher value than
those to the right, and calculations with
numbers of more than two figures are
always done from left to right. The value of
the beads is determined by their position:
they only "count" when they are pushed
towards the crosswise bar.
Two examples of simple arithmetic on the soroban:
A. Addition: 87+52- 139
(1) Put down 87.
(2) Add 50 (from the 52) to 80 (of 87) by
moving the bead worth 5away from the bar
and positioning a bead worth 1 on the rod
to the left. The number shown on the soro¬
ban is 137.
(3) Add 2 to the 7 of the last rod. The
answer is 139.
TEE ^¿5
<^> Bead left in its place or with no value
^^ Bead moved in the course of the calculation
<©> Bead already "counted" or "positioned"
B. Subtraction: 92-35= 57
(1) Put down 92.
(2) Take away 30 (from the 35) from 90 (of
92), leaving 6¿.
(3) 5 cannot be subtracted from 2. There¬
fore borrow 10 from the rod to the left,
which is worth 60. 10-5~- 5. Take away 10
from 60 and add 5 to the rod on the right,
which is already worth 2. The answer is 57.
©
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
An international symposium on the theme "Science and the
Boundaries of Knowledge: the Prologue of our Cultural Past"
was held in Venice, Italy, from 3 to 7 March 1986. Leading
scientists from 1 6 countries attended the meeting, which was
organized by Unesco in collaboration with the Giorgio Cini
Foundation. They agreed on a final communiqué, the "Venice
Declaration", which sets forth their joint observations in five
points, summarized below:
1 . A significant gap exists between the new world-view which
is emerging from the study of natural systems and the values
that continue to prevail in philosophy, in the human and social
sciences and in the life of modern society. We believe that this
discrepancy holds a threat to the very survival of our species.
2. The new and mutually enriching exchange between science
and the different world traditions opens the door to a new
vision of humanity, even to a new rationalism, which could
lead to a new metaphysical perspective.
3. There is a pressing need for truly transdisciplinary re¬
search, through a dynamic exchange between the natural
sciences, the social sciences, art and tradition. In a sense, this
transdisciplinary approach is inherent in our brain through
the dynamic interaction of its two hemispheres.
4. The conventional way of teaching science masks the di¬
vorce between today's science and outdated world-views.
There is an urgent need for new educational methods that
take into account current scientific progress, coming into
harmony with the great cultural traditions, the preservation
and study of which appear essential.
5. Although scientists may have no control over the applica¬
tions of their own discoveries, they must not remain passive
when confronted with the haphazard use of these discoveries.
The magnitude of today's challenges requires a reliable and
steady flow of information to the public and the establishment
of multi- and transdisciplinary mechanisms for the guidance
and even the implementation of decision-making.
The following two articles have been extracted from papers
prepared for the symposium and illustrate some of the points
made in the Venice Declaration.
Breakthroughs in brain research
by David Ottoson
IN the last two decades there has been a
dramatic development in brain research,
only rivalled by the advances in molecular
biology in the early 1 950s and the progress in
physics at the beginning of this century. The
introduction of new biophysical arid bioche¬
mical techniques has made it possible to
tackle problems that until recently were
beyond experimental investigation. All evi¬
dence indicates that these techniques will
open up a world hitherto unknown to us and
give us new insight into the complexity of the
higher functions of the brain. This develop¬
ment is at present progressing at a rapid rate,
but the results already obtained have pro¬
vided us with unprecedented data on many
aspects of the brain involving information pro¬
cessing, perception, brain control of pain,
neurotransmitter actions, brain plasticity, re¬
generation, learning, memory, behaviour and
emotion.
The major breakthrough in our understand¬
ing of the higher functions of the brain was the
discovery of Roger Sperry, Professor of
Psychology at the California Institute of Tech¬
nology, of the functional specialization of the
two hemispheres of the brain. Since the two
hemispheres are anatomically almost identi¬
cal, it had long been generally assumed that in
principle the two brain halves had similar func¬
tions. However, it is interesting to note that as
early as 1861 it was demonstrated by a
French neurologist, Pierre-Paul Broca, that
the centre for speech is localized in the left
hemisphere. When presenting his observa¬
tions to the Société d'Anthropologie in Paris,
he made the now famous dictum: "Nous par-
Ions avec l'hémisphère gauche".
Later observations, particularly on soldiers
wounded in the two world wars, indicated that
the two hemispheres have different functions
also in other aspects, but the functional differ¬
ences between them remained largely un¬
known until the early 1 950s when Roger Sper¬
ry made his pioneering discoveries which
soon received world-wide attention and for
which in 1981 he was awarded the Nobel
Prize in Physiology or Medicine.
Sperry's research thus established that
each of the two hemispheres are specialized,
each having its own specific functional char¬
acteristics. The left hemisphere is analytical,
sequential and rational while the right is syn¬
thetic, holistic and intuitive. The left hemi
sphere is, to quote Sperry, "the more aggres¬
sive, executive, leading hemisphere with con¬
trol of the motor system". This is the hemi¬
sphere that we mainly see in action and the
one with which we communicate. The right
hemisphere is "the silent passenger who
leaves the driving of behaviour to the left
hemisphere". The right hemisphere cannot
express itself in language, is therefore unable
to communicate any experience of perception
or consciousness.
More recently a number of new methods
have been employed for the study of brain
functions which have given us new and excit¬
ing insights into the performance of the brain
in health and disease. One of these tech¬
niques provides for measurements of the re¬
gional blood flow in the brain. With this tech¬
nique it has been demonstrated that at rest in
a quiet room, the cerebral flow is the same in
the two hemispheres. It is interesting to note
that the highest flow is found in the frontal
lobe. Simple visual perception consisting of
opening the eyes results in an increase in the
primary visual area of the cortex, while visual
stimuli which require discrimination tasks are
followed by an increase in other areas.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Tête nucléaire d'un ange (1952), by Salvador Dali.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
e
©
E
Cerebral blood flow measurements have
also provided interesting information on re¬
gional activation of the brain during voluntary
movements in man. When programming a
sequence of movements without actually ex¬
ecuting them, there is a selective increase in a
special area called the supplementary motor
area. During the execution of a movement
there is in addition an increase in another
area, the so-called primary motor area. This
suggests that the command for the movement
is executed by the supplementary motor area,
while the execution of the movement is carried
out by the primary motor area.
Equally interesting are the results of studies
of cerebral blood flow during the focusing of
attention. It is of particular interest from a
clinical point of view that cerebral blood flow
measurements have demonstrated abnormal
patterns of blood flow in mental diseases such
as organic dementia and schizophrenia.
These findings encourage the belief that this
method and other modern approaches to the
analysis of higher brain functions may also
provide a deeper understanding of the brain
mechanisms in mental disorders.
Visual field Visual field
'right/ \ left 1
Still another method, positron emission
tomography (PET), provides a new and
powerful tool for the study of higher brain
functions. In positron emission tomography a
chemical compound is labelled with radioac¬
tive isotope that decays by emitting positrons
with the emission of gamma rays as a result.
The gamma rays are recorded by a circular
array of detectors placed around the head and
a computer reconstructs the distribution of
radioactivity and displays it as a colour-coded
image on a TV screen. With this technique it is
possible to see how different regions of the
brain are activated during various kinds of
mental activities. Thus it has been demon¬
strated that certain regions of the left hemi¬
sphere are activated when a person listens to
someone speaking to him. When listening to
music, regions in the right hemisphere be¬
come active. However, if the patient is asked
to tell what particular piece of music is played
or to say the name of the composer, the
activity shifts over to the left (analytical)
hemisphere.
The famous Russian physiologist Pavlov is
supposed to have said that mankind can be
divided into artists and thinkers. It would be
tempting, in view of the new knowledge that
recent advances in brain research have
brought us, to believe that in artists the right
holistic hemisphere is the dominating one
while in thinkers the left analytical hemisphere
is dominant. However, it is important to
emphasize that the hemispheric differences
are quantitative rather than qualitative in
many aspects and that care should be taken
in classifying individuals or groups as being
dominated by the left or the right hemisphere.
It is equally clear that the brain only reaches
its full potential capacity by the functional
co-operation of the two hemispheres. This
new insight has important implications for the
understanding of higher cognitive functions
and has practical applications in many fields
of social life and most particularly in educa¬
tion. Recent developments in various areas of
brain research provide strong evidence that in
teaching attention should be given to the spe¬
cific functions of the two hemispheres and
both of them should be given the opportunities
to fully develop their inherent faculties.
Most educational systems in the Western
world have until now been directed mainly
towards the training of the left hemispheric
capacities. In view of our expanding know¬
ledge of hemispheric processing it is impor¬
tant that the information provided by brain
research should be integrated into the educa¬
tional system. As our knowledge of the func¬
tions of the brain develops, teaching methods
should be modified to meet the specific needs
not only of the normal individual but also of
those with hemispheric dysfunctions in order
that they may be given the opportunities to
develop the full functional capacities of their
brains.
Corpus callosum region
Language
The study of the functions of the left and
right cerebral hemispheres has made
great progress due to the "split brain"
technique, which consists in cutting the
nerve fibres (primarily the corpus callo¬
sum) which Interconnect the two hemi¬
spheres. In the early 1960s, this surgical
technique was applied to several patients
suffering from severe epilepsy by a team
of specialists led by the U.S. neurophy¬
siology Dr. Roger W. Sperry (Nobel Prize
for Physiology or Medicine, 1981) and led
to a series of remarkable observations of
the functioning ofeach hemisphere separ¬
ately. It proved possible, in particular, to
locate linguistic capacities essentially in
the left brain hemisphere and to establish
that the righthemisphere has superiorabi¬
lities In the field of vision and the recogni¬
tion ofshapes. Thus, in the drawing above,
the "right hemisphere" person (someone
whose left hemisphere is inoperative)
sees the flower, makes the gesture of
smelling it, but cannot say its name.
Diagram above shows how visual fields
and visual centres of the brain are related.
Cutting optic chiasm and corpus callosum
leaves each eye feeding information to
one side of the brain only and eliminates
the normal overlap of visual fields. 1. left
eye-ball; 2. right eyeball; 3. optic chiasm;
4. left hemisphere; 5. right hemisphere; 6.
lateral geniculate body; 7. optic tract; 8.
right-half visual field; 9. left-half visual
field.
DAVID GUSTAV OTTOSON, Swedish medical
doctor, has been since 1984 Special Adviser on
scientific questions to the Director-General of
Unesco. Former head of the department ofphy¬
siology at the Karolinska Institute, Stockholm,
president of the Nobel Committee for Physiology
or Medicine, and honorary professor at the Beij¬
ing Medical University, China, he is a member of
the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences and of
several international medical associations, in¬
cluding the International Brain Research
Organization (IBRO) of which he is Secretary-
General.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Science and tradition
Two spokes of a single wheel'
by Basarab Nicolescu
1
ANY practising scientist knows from ex¬
perience that our representation of the
world is not wholly arbitrary. A scien¬
tific theoretical construction worthy of the
name may be rejected because it does not fit
the observed facts. There is something that
resists. What other name than "reality" can
we give to that something?
To date, two conceptions of "reality" have
dominated our representations of the world.
"Reality" has been seen either as "objective"
(with humanity cast in the role of "master" of
an external reality) or as "subjective", created
by humanity (humanity thus being the only
source of "reality"). These two conceptions of
reality stem, in my opinion, from a single
vainglorious attitude that of viewing human¬
ity as the static and absolute centre of
"reality". There is, however, a third possibility
which seems to me to be consistent with
modern scientific knowledge: "reality" is the
product of the interaction between the world
and humanity, which are two aspects of one
and the same reality. Modern scientists could
testify about this interaction.
The time may be ripe for us to incorporate
the most general ideas of modern science into
our culture. Is it going too far to suppose that
the discrepancy between an outmoded vision
of the world and an infinitely more subtle and
more complex reality (as revealed on the
quantum scale or on the cosmological scale)
is the source of many of the tensions and
conflicts that we witness every day, but on
which we are virtually powerless to act? Is it
not our attitude to reality that will determine, in
the final analysis, the fate of our world? Is
ignorance of fundamental science not one of
the causes of that anarchic technological pro¬
liferation which, although it has many ben¬
eficial effects, may also lead our species to
self-destruction?
Fundamental science is rooted in the
nourishing earth of questions that are com¬
mon to every field of human knowledge: What
is the meaning of life? What is man's role in
the cosmic process? What is nature's place in
knowledge? Fundamental science thus has
the same roots as religion, art or mythology.
It is true that such questions have gradually
Finely sculpted figure on the marble tomb¬
stone of a Greek (4th century BC) evokes
eternal questions of the meaning of life
and man's role in cosmic processes.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
and increasingly come to be regarded as non-
scientific and have been cast into the outer
darkness of the irrational, the preserve of the
poet, the mystic, the artist or the philosopher.
The cause is probably the indisputable
triumph at the material level of analytical,
reductionist and mechanistic thought. Every¬
thing was, apparently, determined, even pre¬
determined. In this universe of false freedom it
was amazing that anything could actually
happen. As witnesses to an absolute, static
and immutable order, scientists could no lon¬
ger be, as in the past, "natural philosophers";
they were obliged to become "technicians of
the quantitative".
Modern science, starting with the advent of
quantum physics at the turn of the twentieth
century, reveals the fragility of such a para¬
digm. Quantum physics has demonstrated
the groundlessness of blind faith in continuity,
local causality and mechanistic determinism.
Discontinuity came in through the front door
that of scientific experiment. Local causality
gave way to a subtler concept of "global"
causality.- "Objects" were replaced by re¬
lationships, interactions and interconnections
among natural phenomena. Lastly, the clas¬
sical concept of matter was replaced by the
infinitely more subtle concept of matter-ener¬
gy. The omnipotence of substance, the touch
stone of reductionists from time immemorial,
was challenged: substance is simply one of
the possible facets of energy.
An unprecedented conceptual revolution
which logically should have led to a new sys¬
tem of values governing our everyday life in
the community began with Planck and Ein¬
stein. However, three-quarters of a century
after the emergence of the quantum image of
the world, nothing has really changed. We
continue to act, consciously or otherwise,
according to the concepts of earlier centuries.
The palpable, experimental discovery of a
scale invisible to the sense organs, the quan¬
tum scale on which the laws are completely
different from those of the visible scale of
everyday life, has probably been modern sci¬
ence's most important contribution to human
knowledge. The new concept which has thus
emerged that of levels of materiality is one
of those that could underpin a new vision of
the world.
The world of quantum events is completely
different from the world to which we are
accustomed.
The unity of opposites seems to reign in this
new world: quantum entities are particles and
waves at the same time. The quantum event is
not separable as an object: the new world is
that of universal interconnection, relationship
and interaction. Discontinuity and continuity
coexist harmoniously (that is to say, "contra¬
dictorily"): energy varies by jumps, but our
visible world nonetheless remains a world of
continuity. The void is "full" it contains,
potentially, all events. The new world is one of
perpetual effervescence, annihilation and
creation, and movement at lightning speeds
beyond comparison with those of rockets.
Energy concentrated on the scale of the in¬
finitely small reaches fantastic values that are
hardly imaginable on our own scale.
But over and above the inadequacy of im¬
ages there is also the inadequacy of logic and
language based on classical realism. Contra¬
diction, a concept that must be taken here in
its philosophical sense of reciprocal construc¬
tion through antagonistic struggle, does not
mean incoherence. It simply means that what
is unified at one level of reality appears con¬
tradictory at another level of reality.
Let us consider in this context the well-
known example of the concept of com¬
plementarity introduced by Niels Bohr in
1927: a quantum particle may be described
approximately in terms of either a classic
particle or a classic wave, but the quantum
particle is neither a particle nor a wave. Parti¬
cle and wave appear to be two com¬
plementary aspects of the quantum particle,
Physicists Max Planck (right, 1858-1947)
and Niels Bohr (1885-1962) were respec¬
tively pioneers in the development of the
quantum theory and quantum mechanics
in the early 20th century. The quantum
theory grew up around Planck's introduc¬
tion into physics of the concept of the
discontinuity of energy. According to this
concept light, which appears to be a
steady stream or a continuous flow, is
actually given off and absorbed in tiny
units called quanta. The theory was de¬
veloped by Bohr and other great physi¬
cists into a system of "quantum mecha¬
nics" which has come to be used to de¬
scribe physical phenomena occurring on
such a small scale that the system of
mechanics deriving from the work of the
17th-century English physicist Isaac New¬
ton breaks down.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Buddhist tradition, like that of other
great world religions, enshrines doctrines
handed down over the centuries "by word
of mouth, ... through the science of sym¬
bols, through writings or works of art,
myths or rites. "Above, graceful hands ofa
moulded clay Bodhisattva or future Bud¬
dha, in the rock-cut caves of Mai-chi-shan,
a major Buddhist site in Kansu Province,
northern China.
Shamanism is the traditional religion of
the Tungus people ofSoviet eastern Siber¬
ia. The central figure is the clan shaman,
left, who is a mystical priest, singer,
prophet and healer. Found in many parts
of the worldbut especially in the Arctic and
central Asia, shamanism is based on the
belief that the world is pervaded by good
and evil spirits whom the shaman seeks to
influence or control by communicating
directly with them.
which is, in this sense, both a particle and a
wave.
Complementarity in this sense, then, in
contrast to the meaning of the word in every¬
day language, denotes the mutually exclusive
aspects of quantum phenomena.
The quantum particle defies representation
by forms in space and in time, for it is obvious¬
ly impossible to make a mental representation
(other than by mathematical equations) of
something which is at the same time both
particle and wave.
This was an unprecedented challenge
hurled by scientific experiment at the very
foundations of our everyday thinking. For ex¬
ample, light behaves experimentally either as
waves or as particles. But the results of scien¬
tific experiments are obtained, by definition,
on our own scale in an unavoidably classical
world that is incapable of conceiving of the
unity of opposites. This separation between
opposites is due to our logic, our language,
and our way of interpreting results on an
infinitely more complex scale than the quan¬
tum scale. On the quantum scale light is one: it
is both wave and particle.
Is there really a connection between sci¬
ence and Tradition? Tradition means all the
doctrines and religious or moral practices
handed down over the centuries, originally by
word of mouth or example, and the handing
down of more or less legendary information
about the past, also initially by word of mouth,
from one generation to another. According to
this definition, Tradition encompasses various
"traditions" Christian, Jewish, Islamic, Bud¬
dhist, Süfi and so on.
Tradition is thus primarily concerned with
the transmission of a body of knowledge
about the spiritual evolution of man, his posi¬
tion in different "worlds", and his relationship
with different "universes". This body of know¬
ledge is necessarily constant, stable and per¬
manent, despite the many forms through
which it is transmitted and despite the distor¬
tions wrought by time and history. Transmis¬
sion is usually by word of mouth, but it may
also be effected through the science of sym¬
bols, through writings or works of art, myths or
rites.
For an impartial researcher, there seems to
be every reason to separate science from
Tradition.
Traditional knowledge is based on revela¬
tion, contemplation and direct perception of
reality. In contrast, scientific knowledge (at
least in its contemporary form) is based on the
understanding of reality through mental pro¬
cesses, through logical and mathematical
constructions. Traditional knowledge presup¬
poses the non-involvement of mental proces¬
ses, through the suppression of ordinary
logical associations, whereas scientific know¬
ledge is possible precisely because the
mental faculty is activated as intensely as
possible.
Traditional research assigns great import¬
ance to the body, sensations, feelings and
faith, while scientific research excludes the
researcher's own body, sensations, feelings
and faith from the field of observation and the
formulation of laws. The only instrument be¬
longing to the human body that is tolerated by
science is the researcher's brain and its inhe¬
rent logical structures that are common to all
researchers. Experimental measuring de¬
vices are assumed to possess an intrinsic
objectivity and a quasi-absolute independ¬
ence of the researcher's own will.
Traditional thought has always claimed that
reality is not linked to time and space: it simply
is. The traditional researcher, through long
and unremitting effort, deliberately annihilates
his own spatio-temporal identity in order to
discover his true being, through dissolution in
that one, all-embracing reality which, to be
known, admits of no separation, no impurity
due to projection in space or time. At the other
extreme, the scientific researcher is obliged to
postulate the existence of a separate objec¬
tive reality which is necessarily defined in
terms of time and space.
Another important difference between sci¬
ence and Tradition resides in the communic¬
able or non-communicable nature of an ex¬
periment. Traditional research claims the right
to engage in experiments that cannot be com¬
municated through natural language. The tra¬
ditional experiment is unique and total, and
transcends ordinary logical categories. A sci¬
entific experiment, on the other hand, is com¬
municable and repeatable. The conditions of
scientific experimentation are defined in as
objective a manner as possible. A scientific
experiment can thus be repeated by any re¬
search team equipped with the appropriate
scientific instruments. Experiment is even
considered to be the supreme arbiter of sci¬
ence. The "argument from authority" does not
exist in science (save as a marginal and tran¬
sient sociological phenomenon). A theory,
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
I ^ v> \ y V A
Science and Tradition "differ in their
nature, methods and final purposes. But
they ... converge toward the same centre:
humanity and human progress." Above,
diagram from 16th-century French treatise
on navigation shows location of the points
of the compass in relation to the parts of
the human body.
"The only instrument belonging to the hu¬
man body that is tolerated by science is
the researcher's brain and its Inherent
logical structures that are common to all
researchers. Experimental measuring de¬
vices are assumed to possess an intrinsic
objectivity and a quasi-absolute inde¬
pendence of the researcher's own will. " In
this drawing by the artist Yôsai (1788-
1873), the Japanese astronomer Kasuga
Ason Manumaro is depicted from the
back, with a map of the heavens to evoke
his scientific calling.
even if it is of the greatest aesthetic beauty or
formulated by the greatest physicist of the
age, is unhesitatingly rejected if it is clearly in
conflict with experimental data.
Traditional knowledge therefore claims a
"right to ineffectiveness" on the level of spa¬
tio-temporal materiality and on the level of the
directly observable material world. Con¬
versely, science is interested essentially in
maximum effectiveness on the level of direct
materiality. It is precisely because of this
effectiveness that the material life of humanity
has been profoundly transformed by the tech¬
nological applications of the discoveries of
fundamental science.
Is there, then, any relationship between
science and Tradition?
Einstein's famous dictum: "The most in¬
comprehensible thing in the world is that the
world is comprehensible" is often quoted. Pa¬
raphrasing these words, it could be said that
the only "irrational" aspect of the world is its
rationality.
It is a constant source of wonder to scien¬
tists in their daily practice to see the harmony
between their abstract, logical and mathema¬
tical constructions and experimental data.
The conformity between human thought and
the intelligence concealed in natural laws acts
as a third factor in the man-nature relation¬
ship, making a ternary entity that exists as a
dynamic and inseparable unit. That confor¬
mity, an independent factor in the man-nature
relationship, explains Einstein's insistence on
the role of intuition as a form of immediate
knowledge in the genesis of great scientific
discoveries. Forgetfulness or ignorance of
this third factor seems to be the source of
contemporary reductionist schools of thought
that proclaim a vulgar, false and static duality.
Traditional experience is, indeed, incom¬
municable, but it is important to realize that
some traditional thinkers feel a need to analy¬
se and explain to others in an intelligible man¬
ner what they experienced at the time of the
experiment. Describing, analysing, ex¬
plaining: these constitute a procedure on
which science is also built.
Is not faith in the structural rationality of the
world the subtle link which binds traditional
thought to scientific thought?
The idea of the unity of opposites and the
role of discontinuity in the genesis of move¬
ment permeates traditional thought. For many
traditional approaches (in both East and
West), the outward manifestation is bound up
with a dynamic process of combat and co¬
operation, annihilation and creation, eternal
movement and eternal transformation, one
might even say "eternal genesis". Is this vi¬
sion of the world not surprisingly close to our
own?
Science and Tradition differ in their nature,
methods and final purposes. But they can be
viewed as two poles of a single contradiction, or
as two spokes of a single wheel, which although
different yet converge toward the same centre:
humanity and human progress.
BASARAB NICOLESCU is a French theoretical
physicist at the National Centre for Scientific
Research (CNRS), Paris. A specialist in the
theory of elementary particles, he is also in¬
terested in the relationship between art, science
and tradition and has published many articles on
this subject in French andAmericanjournals. He
is also the author of several published works,
including Nous, la particule et le monde (1985).
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The human factor
in African development
by Jean-Paul Ngoupandé
WHEN the peoples of the develop¬
ing countries aspire to develop¬
ment, what they really want is to
attain the normal condition of any form of
human existence, whether collective or in¬
dividual, namely to be able to choose their
course, to be responsible for their destiny,
and hence to control all action concerning
their lives. In Sartrian terms, they want to
be able to act instead of being acted upon.
The firm if inarticulate resistance of the
peoples of developing countries to develop¬
ment controlled from abroad is now well
known. It is a commonplace to say that the
only certain result of twenty-five years' de¬
velopment in the developing countries is
that the development graft has not taken. In
the great majority of cases the graft is re¬
jected because the populations concerned
have a basically conflictual relationship
2
©
with "projects". Mr Helmut Eggers, of the
Directorate-General for Development at
the Commission of the European Com¬
munities, noted recently that a review of
experiments carried out over the years in
the field of financial and technical co-opera¬
tion for development, notably for rural de¬
velopment, revealed the "self-evident
truth" that the operations funded were not
viable. As a large number of such opera-
In May 1986 the United Nations General
Assembly met in special session at min¬
isterial level "to consider in depth the cri¬
tical economic situation in Africa". On this
occasion Unesco published a document
entitled Getting to the Roots of the Prob¬
lem, which describes what Unesco is
doing, within its fields of competence, to
help to build African economies on solid
and lasting foundations. The Introduction
to the document draws attention to the
growing acceptance of "a conception of
development which goes beyond the mere
listing of parameters relating solely to
growth and material goods", and which
takes human fulfilment as its ultimate
goal. The document emphasizes that a de¬
velopmentprocess ofthis kind is not feasi¬
ble "unless account Is taken of the cultural
dimension, which in turn implies taking
account of, and even ifneed be transcend¬
ing and integrating into the movement of
innovation, the sociological characteris¬
tics and deep traditional roots of the peo¬
ples concerned." Left, oil-rig worker at
Port Harcourt, theport ofsouth-east Niger¬
ia in the Niger Basin.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
tions do not survive when external funding
comes to an end, their impact on the capac¬
ity for self-development of the rural groups
concerned is insignificant, non-existent or
negative.
This can be verified in the field.
"Development aid" leads to scenes of rack
and ruin: miracles of engineering which are
now abandoned factories; rusting machines
which in some cases need only a fuse or a
washer to work; land recently occupied by a
"project" overgrown with vegetation; the
spectacle of desolation which follows the
departure of the "experts", sometimes giv¬
ing the landscape of a developing country
the strange appearance of an old industrial¬
ized country whereas in fact industrializa¬
tion has only just begun.
The explanation is that since man is fun¬
damentally free, he aspires to be himself,
and it is useless for anyone else to try to
make him happy against his will.
Human fulfilment, the achievement of
freedom in the field of economics, means
being able to choose what one produces, to
know why one produces it, and to know
how it is produced. The cultivation of mil¬
let, corn or sorghum presents no problems
to peasants in the least developed countries
because these are the crops they want, and
because they know thé practical reasons for
growing these crops. If on the other hand
they must be continually persuaded to grow
cotton, tobacco or even coffee, it is because
these crops are imposed on them and they
see no clear advantage for themselves in
growing them. It is significant that the most
stubborn resistance to development con¬
trolled from elsewhere comes from rural
people: they are the ones who have been the
least affected by the great cultural changes
effected by contact with industrial societies,
and they are therefore the ones who aspire
most to be themselves. As they account for
between 75 and 90 per cent of the popula¬
tion in the developing countries, it is clear
that they represent a tremendous force of
inertia.
In the least developed countries, which
are primarily agricultural countries, the im¬
pact of this inertia on production is obvious:
most of the labour force is unenthusiastic
and feels unconcerned by its own work.
And if famine is again invading these coun¬
tries today, in these times of overproduc¬
tion, it is not only because of worsening
climatic conditions. The vagaries of the
weather are nothing new to Black Africa.
Far be it from us to insinuate that there was
no famine in precolonial Africa.
"Despite the development policies which
she has followed, Africa remains the conti¬
nent where per capita income ... is the
lowest ... Everywhere the basic needs of
mankind ... are very poorly met ... In our
opinion, It is much less the theory and the
policies ofdevelopment which are in ques¬
tion than the institutional frameworks in
which they are implemented (instability of
exports, high degree of economic balkan¬
ization and nationalism, excessive facili¬
ties accorded to transnational corpor¬
ations, etc.). In Africa these conditions act
as a brake on growth and lead to increas¬
ing dependence on developed countries
..." (Science économique et développe¬
ment endogène, "Economie Science and
Endogenous Development", Unesco,
1986). Right, drought in Mali, 1983. On the
banks of the Niger River, men hack at the
dried out soil in order to build dams to
capture hoped-for rainwater.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
^ ^
) \T
;
2
©I
~'\) v*
>l
However, as the twentieth century draws
to a close, with the world having achieved
an unprecedented level of technological
progress, no one would suggest that climatic
difficulties alone can explain famine. There
are admittedly civil wars which disrupt pro¬
duction because of insecurity, mass popula¬
tion movements and the depletion of
peasants' reserves in order to feed armies.
But the most important thing in our opinion
is the lack of motivation of peasants to grow
crops and observe production standards
which they have not chosen. Endemic
famine or chronic malnutrition in countries
where there is neither civil war nor extreme
variations in climate, abundantly prove that
the human factor is still crucial.
In a country such as the Central African
Republic the drift from the land occurs
chiefly in regions where the old cash crops
inherited from colonial times are dominant.
These crops are identified in the peasants'
minds with forced labour and the overseer's
whip, even though these came to an end
twenty-five years ago. Cotton-growing
areas have been so drained of labour that
output has been affected, since virtually
none but elderly workers remain. A recent
survey carried out by a Bangui young peo¬
ple's newspaper revealed that the vast
majority of the young would prefer to starve
to death in the capital rather than return to
the countryside.
Food aid also tends to make both con¬
sumption and production dependent on ex¬
ternal factors, and thus removes responsi¬
bility from indigenous producers. Food aid
is closely related to the key problem of
self-sufficiency in food production. Theo¬
retically this is a goal sought by everyone,
but the conditions for achieving it are close¬
ly linked to the mobilization of the rural
world.
Food aid alienates the peasant and places
him in a situation of enforced inferiority,
powerless in the face of his destiny, his
environment, and nature. It will be argued
that such aid makes it possible to save hu¬
man lives which would be inevitably lost
without it. This is true; just as it is also true
that the by no means well-off men and
women in Europe who make the effort to
show their human solidarity are not all in¬
spired by Machiavellian motives. No one
doubts the good faith of donors who have
nothing to do with political or economic
"decision-making" circles. However, food
aid has a serious long-term effect on the
viability of African agricultural production,
which has become accustomed to relying on
the outside world to bridge gaps in output.
Still worse is the harmful effect of this
"In the least developed countries ofAfrica
those responsible for promoting develop¬
ment have been reduced to such a state of
enforced inferiority that theyare caught up
in a vicious circle. If development is to be
achieved, it must be achieved by the Afri¬
cans themselves; but since the Africans
are still suffering from the after-effects of
submission, and have no confidence in
their own human resources, it follows that
the aim of development must be to free
them from this psychological block."
Above, workers in a Tanganyikan diamond
mine, 1948. The country gained independ¬
ence in 1961, and together with the former
Sultanate of Zanzibar formed the United
Republic of Tanzania in 1964.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
African agriculture:
the road to recovery
The Food and Agriculture Organization of
the United Nations (FAO) issued, on the
occasion of its 14th Regional Conference
for Africa in September 1 986, the results of
a far-reaching study on the food and agri¬
cultural crisis in Africa which the FAO initi¬
ated in 1984. The study, African Agricul¬
ture: The Next Twenty-Five Years, pro¬
vides a close analysis of the causes of this
situation and recommends practical mea¬
sures that would make a recovery feasible.
Contrary to widespread belief, drought
is not the only cause of the suffering and
famine which affect so many African coun¬
tries. The problem is rooted in a crisis
which has been undermining agriculture
for over twenty years. Per capita food pro¬
duction has decreased by almost 20 per
cent since 1961 and, although they were
practically self-sufficient ten or twenty
years ago, most African countries are to¬
day incapable of feeding themselves. If
current trends persist, the food situation in
Africa by the year 2010 will be even worse
than it was at the most critical juncture of
the 1983-1985 famine (see Figure 1).
Six factors, according to the authors of
the FAO study, are mainly responsible for
the crisis: a bias in government policy
against agriculture (to which most coun¬
tries devote less than 10 per cent of their
budgets); high population growth rates
(with an urban population growing much
more rapidly than the rural population); a
decline in the rate at which arable land and
harvested area are being developed (see
Figure 2); a lack of technological change,
which is leading to a widespread stagna¬
tion or even decline in crop yields; acceler¬
ated degradation of the environment; an
external economic environment that is
making it more and more difficult for most
African countries to balance their budgets.
Many remedies have been suggested,
including various forms of aid to farmers
V
(notably incentive policies), institutional
reforms and the improvement of infras¬
tructures (roads, railways, ports). Special
attention is being given to the protection
and development of natural resources.
To halt the degradation of agricultural
land, for which man is the main culprit,
action has already been taken in a number
of African countries (including Somalia,
Kenya, Malawi, Senegal, Sierra Leone,
Morocco and Lesotho) in many cases with
highly positive results, suggesting that
under certain conditions African agricul¬
ture could be more productive than it is at
present.
To take one example, on the Mossi
Plateau of Burkina Faso, simple techni¬
ques of water harvesting have enabled
village co-operatives and farmers to bring
abandoned land back into production; in
several villages rice yields have doubled.
This successful experiment, if it was ex¬
tended, would allow the exploitation of
millions of hectares of potential plough-
land in the semi-arid regions of the con¬
tinent.
M
(
©
When they became independent, most
African countries inherited poorly de¬
veloped transport networks designed pri¬
marily to export commodities to the home
ports of the former colonialpowers. Today
African agriculture urgently requires an
efficient infrastructure for supply and dis¬
tribution. Above, working on a railway line
at Ouagadougou, capital of Burkina Faso.
Figure 1
Self-sufficiency if trends continue*
'assuming projected deficits are met by net imports
Figure 2
Trends for arable land development (percentages)
North Africa
^^^"
.:.'. -i
| 1 	
West Africa
- .- ^i^^
j 1
Central Africa
3 [ : r!4 - - J:»:J-!^^^W.: -:Z¿ZZ+y }<:. -.".. - - . /f^
£ | ... n ... . 1
Sudano-Sahel
; ,- y ..- :: v..
£ i	 1
East Africa
-.-,. y- .\; ;-.
f 		 Ï
South Africa
1	 1
North Africa
West Africa
Central Africa
Sudano-Sahel
South Africa
0 0.5
BB11969-1971 F/iS.-fl 1979- 1981 I 12010 [ 1961-1963 to 1971-1973 I I 1971-1973 to 1981-1983
Source: African Agriculture: The Next 25 Years, Main Report, © FAO, Rome, 1986
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
dependency on the creativity of the African
peoples and their determination to cope
with the vagaries of nature.
Increasing numbers of Africans now
think that nothing is more degrading than to
be in permanent receipt of food aid and
believe that Africans themselves should be
able to meet their basic food requirements.
It is understandable to call for international
solidarity when an exceptionally serious dis¬
aster occurs, but the continued showering
of African countries with foreign foodstuffs
can give no cause for satisfaction. It is only
by fully pledging their labour and their re¬
sponsibility, and by being constantly faced
with their responsibilities as human beings,
that Africans will overcome their terrible
century-old handicap of defeatism, of lack
of confidence in themselves and their des¬
tiny.
In the least developed countries of Africa
those responsible for promoting develop¬
ment have been reduced to such a state of
enforced inferiority that they are caught up
in a vicious circle. If development is to be
achieved, it must be achieved by the Afri¬
cans themselves; but since the Africans are
still suffering from the after-effects of sub¬
mission, and have no confidence in their
own human resources, it follows that the
aim of development must be to free them
from this psychological block.
One of the least frequently mentioned
factors of dehumanization is the slave-
trade. Its extent, duration and especially its
cruelty were such that it has left immeasur¬
able psychological after-effects in Black
Africa. In terms of extent and numbers of
victims, its impact affected the entire con¬
tinent; it lasted for more than three centur¬
ies and was characterized by great brutality.
Folk imagery still vehicles the phantasms
born of the shock of this experience. The
slave trade also explains the limited territo¬
rial settlement of populations which for
more than three centuries were continually
forced to flee. This led to the incessant
migratory movements in the seventeenth,
eighteenth and nineteenth centuries which,
in certain regions of Central Africa, histo¬
rians find it impossible to disentangle.
Fear has become a kind of second nature
to people who live in a climate of perma¬
nent insecurity. The continuing oppression
of post-colonial Black African dictatorships
maintained and sometimes increased this
fear.
This then is the post-colonial Black man,
who is now responsible for promoting de¬
velopment: he is traumatized; he has lost
confidence in himself, in his destiny, in his
human capabilities.
Any talk of development which today
fails to take account of this terrible burden
borne by post-colonial Black Africa is simp¬
ly preaching in the wilderness. The impossi¬
bility of achieving economic take-off brings
us back to the most important question: the
human question. Psychological blocks, the
after-effects of traumatism caused by
aggression, oppression and humiliation, are
the first obstacle to mobilization for de¬
velopment. Statistics, projects, plans, bi¬
lateral or multilateral aid have for twenty-
five years come up against this insurmount¬
able wall of human despair.
It is possible to break this vicious circle by
stating the problem of development in a
different way from that defined by econo¬
mists. In economic theory, development
means increasing material production in
order to lead to the liberation of man. To
posit this relationship of cause and effect
between the production of material wealth
and emancipation is to enter a vicious circle.
But by positing development as both mate¬
rial increase and human emancipation, in
our view it becomes possible to avoid this
vicious circle.
By transforming their environment in
order to increase material production and
improve their living conditions, people
transform themselves, and take one step
towards their liberation. Emancipation is
not simply the outcome of the material
results achieved, nor simply a result of the
material wealth provided by development;
it is a part of the very process by which
Black Africans change their material con¬
dition, and therefore goes hand in hand
with the process of material production.
But this is only possible on one vital
condition: that the process of material pro¬
duction should be initiated and conducted
by the Black African himself. This means
that by his own efforts, by trial and error,
the experience he acquires and the progress
he makes, Black African man will gradually
learn to know his own capabilities, and thus
regain confidence in himself when he re¬
alizes that he is capable of creating. It is
from the ordeal of success or failure,
whether immediate or in the long term, that
he will learn, and through that ordeal he will
transform himself.
JEAN-PAUL NGOUPANDE is the Minister of
Education of the Central African Republic and
former head of the faculty of letters and human
sciences of the University ofBangui. The present
article has been extracted from a study "The
Aims of Development in the Context of the Least
Developed Countries ", which was presented to a
specialist meeting on "The Aims of Develop¬
ment", held in Budapest, Hungary, in October
1986. The meeting was one of a series of semi¬
nars on philosophical aspects of development
which Unesco has organized since 1978.
The analysis of developmentprocesses in
different social and cultural contexts is
one of Unesco's major preoccupations. In
November this year an international meet¬
ing of experts is being held at Unesco's
Paris HQ on the theme of "Poverty and
Progress". The meeting, organized by Un¬
esco in co-operation with the United Na¬
tions University, will examine from a wide
range of viewpoints the problems of
poverty, marginalization and exclusion
caused by certain development proces¬
ses. Right, coal-mining village in Bihar,
one of India's leading mineral-producing
States.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
1986: Year of Peace/ 11
MOKarHAPOOHAfl
Scientists and peace
A Conference on the theme "Scientists
on the Problems of Peace and Pre¬
vention of Nuclear War" was held in
Moscow from 27 to 29 May in the context of
the International Year of Peace. Those
attending the Conference included not only
Soviet delegates but also over a hundred
scientists from 44 countries representing all
the continents.
Representatives of Mr. Javier Perez de
Cuellar, Secretary-General of the United
Nations, and of Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow,
Director-General of Unesco, emphasized the
importance' of a conference whose theme, as
the representative of the Director-General of
Unesco pointed out, "epitomizes the struggle
in which mankind is engaged to save our
planet and humanity from a nuclear holo¬
caust."
The ultimate aim of the Conference was to
work towards the total elimination of the nu¬
clear arsenal and other means of mass des¬
truction before the year 2000, an aim which,
like all the initiatives stimulated by the Interna¬
tional Year of Peace, has been warmly wel¬
comed by world opinion. The proposals put
forward by the Soviet Union in order to attain
this objective were spelled out in detail in a
report entitled "For a world free from nuclear
arms in the 21st century", presented by Mr.
Anatoly Dobrynin, Secretary of the Central
Committee of the Communist Party of the
Soviet Union.
After a report on the activity of the Commit¬
tee of Soviet Scientists for Peace and against
the Nuclear Threat, presented by the Commit¬
tee's chairman, Mr. Evgeniy Velikhov, a num¬
ber of study groups examined certain topics in
greater depth, notably "Prevention of the mili¬
tarization of space and international co-oper¬
ation", "Current problems of nuclear disarma¬
ment and the limitation of conventional
armaments" and "Probable consequences of
a nuclear conflict".
New information presented by Mr. Georgy
Golitsyn, a Corresponding Member of the
USSR Academy of Sciences, speaking on
behalf of a large group of Soviet scientists,
brought the "nuclear winter" scenario (see the
Unesco Courier, May 1 985) into clearer focus.
In the event of an atomic war, the discharge of
soot after nuclear explosions into the upper
layers of the troposphere and into the strato¬
sphere would in themselves be enough to
cause serious climatic disturbances.
Sir Frederick Warner (United Kingdom)
presented the results of research into the
environmental consequences of nuclear war,
carried out as part of the ENUWAR project of
the Scientific Committee on Problems of the
Environment (SCOPE) of the International
Council of Scientific Unions. Some 300 re¬
searchers from 30 countries are taking part in
this work.
One speaker, Mr. B. Raushenbakh (USSR)
pointed out the dangers for humanity inherent
in the increasing computerization of the tech¬
nologies of destruction. Mr. S. Gustavsson
(Sweden) stressed the need to develop furth¬
er international legal safeguards with a view to
avoiding nuclear war. Messrs R. Khan (India),
O. Obassanjo (Nigeria), T. Berendt (Hungary)
and I. Ivanov (USSR) emphasized the dis¬
astrous consequences of the arms race,
especially for developing countries, while Mr.
A. Fokin (USSR) drew attention to the fact that
chemical weapons, which are less complex
and costly than the nuclear arsenal, are within
reach of a larger number of countries and that
their banning is all the more urgent. Finally,
Mr. B. Sendov (Bulgaria) recalled that peace
education for the young generation was one of
the keys to future peace.
At the close of the Conference, an "Appeal
to the Scientists of the World" was adopted.
The only way to save humanity, it states, is
that of genuine disarmament and international
co-operation in every field of constructive
action: from space exploration to the exploita¬
tion of the ocean depths, from environmental
protection to the non-military use of atomic
energy, from the solution of the world hunger
problem to the elimination of epidemics and
disease.
nOMTACCCpK 35 é
me mnpABH re nu i st HHAM
OKI »HCrPAWtl (.«.', v
K0MMCCMO
T
ÍI0HTA OOCP k
nOMTA CCCP k 10
MHI0BIK M 6H0C0XPA
. _
nOMTA CCCP
<
©
nOMTACCCP kI
To commemorate the 40th anniversary of
the founding of Unesco, the Soviet Union
has issued a series of stamps entitled
"Unesco Programmes in the USSR". The
three stamps at left are dedicated (in
ascending order) to the intergovernmental
programme on Man and the Biosphere
(MAB), to the International Geological Cor¬
relation Programme (IGCP) carried out
jointly by Unesco and the International
Union of Geological Sciences, and to the
International Hydrological Programme
(IHP). The other two stamps feature (be¬
low) computer science and (above) The
Intergovernmental Océanographie Com¬
mission (IOC).
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 78 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
56 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear '
author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed arti¬
cles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and headlines are written
by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published
in the magazine do not imply official endorsement or acceptance
by Unesco or the United Nations. The Unesco Courier is pro¬
duced in microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco,
7 Place da Fontenoy, 75700 Paris: (2) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100. U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Micro-
card Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield Road, Wooster,
Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille: Frederick Potter
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-
Chief in Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian:
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
34 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C 1 - Novembre 1986
PHOTOCOMPOSITION : Ateliers de l'UNESCO - PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Étampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
International Voluntary
Service campaigns
for Unesco and the Courier
Ever since it was founded on Unesco's initiative
in 1948, the Co-ordinating Committee for Inter¬
national Voluntary Service (CCIVS), based at 1
rue Miollis, 75015 Paris, has been committed to
strengthening international solidarity between
the world's young people and to providing a
forum for those wishing to create a climate
favourable to peace.
The CCIVS is composed of 1 1 0 organizations
which, with their local branches, are present in
more than 100 countries of North, South, East
and West. Through its wide range of activities
and its publications, the Committee plays a lead¬
ing role in promoting many kinds of voluntary
service throughout the world, including work-
camps, intercultural exchanges, literacy cam¬
paigns, training programmes, activities for the
protection of the environment and the cultural
heritage, and for rural development.
As a contribution to the International Year of
Peace, and a follow-up to International Youth
Year, the CCIVS has organized in co-operation
with Unesco, a conference which will be held in
November 1986 in Accra (Ghana) on the theme
of "The Mobilization of Rural Youth for the Prom¬
otion of Peace, Disarmament and Develop¬
ment", as well as the 23rd Conference of volun¬
tary service organizers, the theme of which will
be "Working Together for Mutual Respect, Co¬
operation and Peace".
In order to create direct contact between Un¬
esco and the public, the CCIVS has launched a
campaign, on the occasion of Unesco's 40th
anniversary, for a thousand young people to
subscribe to the Unesco Courier.
The CCIVS has appealed to other non-gov¬
ernmental organizations to commemorate Un¬
esco's 40th anniversary by launching similar
campaigns, in order to collect as many subscrip¬
tions as possible to Unesco publications.
A Unesco best-seller
Study Abroad 1987-1988
The latest (25th) edition of Unesco's popular reference book
detailing opportunities for further study and training
available in more than 124 countries:
ger 2
oad 4-»
îlext 00
1
00
ON
dyabr esa1
o
>
a
1/3 estudi
Lists some 3,700 university and
postgraduate courses in all fields;
Financial assistance offered by
international organizations,
governments, foundations and
universities;
Entrance requirements, study
fees, cost of living and facilities
available to handicapped students.
And for the first time
provides information on:
Opportunities available to those who
are over university admission age
and/or who do not fulfil the required
academic conditions;
Study opportunities offered to adults
who already have practical
experience in their field.
1,348 pages
Trilingual: English/French/Spanish
68 French francs
ISBN 92-3-002337-X
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications. 58a Gipps St., ColÜngwood. Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box
175. 5th floor, Ana House. 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne. Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011. Vienna.
BAHRAIN. United Schools International, Arab Regional Office, P O. Box 726,
Bahrain. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch
edition only: N.V. Handelmaatschapptj Keesing Keesmglaan 2-18, 2100
Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications agent.
Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Intemacionais Ltda, Processing Dept., R
Peixoto Gomide 209. 01409, Sao Paulo SP. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., Central Distribution Centre, 61, Sparks Street, Ottawa ONT K1P 5R1.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box
88, Beijing CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51 -1 13 02. Prague 1 ; Ve
Smeckach 30. P.O.B. 790-1 1 1 -27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Pub-
lishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munk-
sgaard Export-OG, Tidsskriftservice. 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1 970 Kobenhavn
K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications,
No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box
128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2. 01641
Vantas 64. Rautikirja Oy. Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1 , 01641 Vantas
64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco. 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP
12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig. Post¬
fach 140. 71 0 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum. Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides
Entreprises. P.O. Box 141 29, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE John Mihalopouios & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box
10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore,
4 Nikis Street, Athens T 126. Kostarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2
Hippocratous Street, Athens. HONG XONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15. Lock
Rd.. Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre,
Baskerville House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B.
149-H-1389. Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co., H.F.
Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.. Kamani Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2, 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-
500001. Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St.. Calcutta
70016; Scindia House. New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T.. Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie 37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco.
11 88 Englab Ave.. RoslamGiveBuilding.zip Code 13158. P.O. Box 11365-
4498, Teheran. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Bally-
mount Rd., Walkmstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box
1283.71 AllenbyRd., Tel Aviv61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria
Sansoni, S.p.A ), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo
113. KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur
22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd.. 30 Bourbon St.. Port-Louis. MEXICO. DILITSA, Distribuidora
Literaria SA, Apartado Postal 24 448, Mexico DF 06700. N & E Omicron SA,
Bookseller & Subscriptions Agency, Col Condesa Deleg Cuahtemoc, Aparta¬
do Postal 40 075, 06140 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd. des
Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam. NEW
ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P O. Box 14277-Kilbirnie. Wellington;
130 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721, Christchurch; Alma St., P O. Box 857,
Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1104, Dunedm. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286. NORWAY.
Johan Grundl Tanum, P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum -Oslo 1 ; Narvesen A/S, btteraturt
Jenesten. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets Bokhandelen,
Universitetssenlret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco
Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book Development in Asia and the
Pacilic, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O Box 8950, Karachi 29. POLAND.
Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda.
Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan,
Olaya Mam Street. Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SINGAPORE.
Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Rd., Singapore
2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas Publications (Pty) Ltd., Sub¬
scription Service. P.O. Box 42476. Johannesburg. Universitas Books (Pty)
Ltd . P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaiks Bookstore (Pty) Ltd., Libri
Building, 268 Church Street, Pretoria 0001 . Central News Agency Ltd., Group
Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 613. Cape Town 8000. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box 1118. Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco. P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet,
Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-Wilhams AB,
Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25 Stockholm: Esselte Tidsknftscentralen,
Gamla Brogatan 26. Box 62 -101. 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa
Verlag, 5 Ràrmstrasse, Zürich; Librairie Payot. Rue Grenus 6. 121 1. Geneva
11. C.C.P. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey.
Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establish¬
ment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop,
P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO.
National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair, Trinidad W 1.
TURKEY. Hasel Kitapevi A S.. Istiklàl Caddesi, No 469, Posta Kutusu 219,
Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, Agency Sec¬
tion Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008. Nine Elms Lane,
London SW8 5DR. and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester. Birmingham. Bristol; for scientific maps only McCarta Ltd., 122
Kings Cross Rd.. London WC1 X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan Associates-
UNIPUB. Periodicals Department, 10033-F King Highway, Lanham MD
20706. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul Dimitrova 39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladosl. llica 30/1 1. Zagreb; Cankaneva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit. Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Lid., 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
This seventeenth -century Gobelins tapestry was executed from a cartoon by the Dutch painters
Albert van der Eeckhout and Frans Post which had been presented to Louis XIV by John Maurice of Nassau
It shows an Indian on horseback wearing a poncho, a somewhat fanciful flama with claws instead of hooves,
and a dappled horse in an exotic landscape where the vegetation and animal life are typically Brazilian.
Although there were already Blacks in Brazil. the one shown here is not depicted realistically but is a purely
decorative figure of the kind found in many European tapestries of the period. Background information for
the cartoon had probably been assembled during a journey to South America which the two painters made
with John Maurice of Nassau. The tapestry is today preserved at the Mobilier National. Paris
(See article page 1 1 ).
]]>
</page>
</document>
