<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074930eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
What's new
ir\ archaeology?
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live. . . Zlzri
Tender cooks, Iron Age broth
Children who visit the Historical-Archaeological Research
Center at Lejre in Denmark have an opportunity to live, eat
and work as they might have done in the Iron Age. The Cen¬
ter, which was founded to bring children and young people
nearer to their past through practical activities, has a
weaving workshop, 19th-century farm cottages and a pot¬
ters' workshop as well as a school and a cluster of Iron Age
houses. Here, three young pupils are busy preparing and
tasting an Iron Age meal while a fourth works at the loom.
Autopsies performed on the bodies of Iron Age men, remar¬
kably preserved in the peat bogs of Denmark, have yielded
information about their last meals before they died, up to
2,000 years ago.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
A window open on the world
Editorial
ARCHAEOLOGY, the study of man's past through the
material remains of human activity, has come a long way
since it originated among the leisured connoisseurs of
sixteenth-century Europe. Whereas the early excavators, it has been
said, "were little better than grave-robbers", today's ar¬
chaeologists are specialists who investigate the past using forensic
skills buttressed by a formidable array of scientific and
technological expertise.
At the same time, in the late twentieth century the material re¬
mains of the past are more than ever impossible to ignore. They are
uncovered every day by urban development projects and large-scale
engineering works. New nations seeking to establish their own iden¬
tity feel the importance of a heritage which not only defines the past
cultural achievements of their peoples but is also an essential factor
in national development. Paradoxically, an age bent on change has
come face to face with its past.
In this changing climate archaeology has assumed a new impor¬
tance and is itself changing. Its activities are expanding into new
fields (urban archaeology, industrial archaeology, seismological ar¬
chaeology...). New theoretical approaches are being developed,
and new scientific techniques have made it possible to chart the past
of every country more reliably than ever before. The traditional pic¬
ture of the spade-wielding archaeologist is undergoing drastic
modification. A modern archaeologist is part of a multidisciplinary
team and may call on télédétection from space as a means of pro¬
spection, use a computer for such varied tasks as making a three-
dimensional site-map or getting access to the latest archaeological
data, and rely on nuclear physics to analyse his finds, as well as ap¬
pealing to sciences as varied as botany, entomology and even the
study of ppllen, diatoms and fishbones.
All the same archaeology still means spadework, and to prove it
we have chosen to present two major recent excavations in Latin
America and Central Asia. The uncovering in the heart of Mexico
City of the Great Temple levelled by the Spanish after the conquest
in the sixteenth century is one of the most exciting recent events in
Latin American archaeology. Equally enthralling is the discovery
by Soviet archaeologists of a fabulous Bactrian treasure in the heart
of central Asia.
If archaeology today is interdisciplinary it is also, and increasing¬
ly, international. Here Unesco has played a leading role for many
years, largely as a result of international campaigns to save the
world cultural heritage, symbolized in this issue by Moenjodaro in
Pakistan.
Last but not least, in International Youth Year, archaeology can
tap the enthusiasm of a host of amateurs, many of them young peo¬
ple, whose very existence is a challenge to modern archaeologists
wishing to give real meaning to the phrase "democratization of the
past".
Cover : At work on the site of Moenjodaro
Photo © Raoul Zamora, Paris
Editor in chief: Edouard Glissant
July 1985
38th year
4 What's new in archaeology?
by Colin Renfrew
9 Let the past serve the future
by Osaga Odak
12 How science unlocks the secrets of the past
by Tony Hackens
Tell-tale tree rings
Did Philip of Macedón look like this?
The preservation of Pete Marsh
Archaeology from the air
The Nazca enigma
23 El Templo Mayor
The Great Temple of the Aztecs
in the heart of Mexico City
by Eduardo Matos Moctezuma
28 From the Throne of Stone
A treasure-trove of Greco-Bactrian art
by Boris A. Litvinskiy and Igor R. Pichikiyan
32 Moenjodaro
Threatened centre of an ancient civilization.
by Syed A. Naqvi
36 My life as an archaeologist
by Guo Zhan
38 Unesco Newsroom
A time to live...
DENMARK: Tender cooks, Iron Age broth
Photos Unesco
Published monthly in 31 languages English Italian Turkish Macedonian Finnish A selection in Braille is published
by Unesco, French Hindi Urdu Serbo-Croat Swedish quarterly in English, French,
The United Nations Educational, Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque Spanish and Korean
Scientific and Cultural Organization Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. German Persian Korean Bulgarian
Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala N° 7 - 1985 - OPI - 85 - 1 - 424 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
What's new in archaeology?
by Colin Renfrew
OVER the past two or three decades,
archaeology the study of the
human past through the material
remains of human activityhas changed
profoundly in nature. Archaeology was
once widely regarded as some sort of
backward extension of recorded history.
For times when written records were
available it was seen as a useful addition, as
simply some sort of illustration of the writ¬
ten narrative. For the prehistoric period,
prior to the availability of written
testimony, it offered some kind of shadowy
reconstruction of the past, an illiterate
substitute for a proper historical record.
Today, rather suddenly, archaeology,
seems relevant and relevant in a very inter¬
national way. Every continent has its own
rich archaeological record, whether or not it
has its own written records into the remote
past. Moreover we can see more clearly that
what happened in the Americas, for in¬
stance, or in Africa two or three thousand
years ago is just as relevant to our general
understanding of human history as events
occurring at that time in Asia or in Europe,
areas with a longer written record.
Several developments have come together
to create a new awareness that the ar¬
chaeology of all these areas and let us not
leave out Australia and the Pacific is part
of our archaeology, the record of the
history and achievements of our own
species, and a part of the cultural heritage
of our world.
In the first place, the development of new
dating techniques, especially radiocarbon
dating, has allowed the archaeological finds
from every part of the globe to be dated
reliably, without recourse to written
history. The application of other techniques
from the sciences, along with more rigorous
excavation methods, has given the ar¬
chaeologist a whole array of approaches
which he or she can use to investigate past
economies, the development of technology
and early social systems (see article page
12).
Secondly, with the development of what
has come to be called the "New Ar¬
chaeology", research workers have re¬
defined their aims. We are no longer simply
seeking to reconstruct the past, and form
some simple narrative of what happened in
early times. We are trying in addition to
understand why things changed and why
they became what they are. This aim re¬
quires the development of a clearer
theoretical framework for archaeology and
involves the questioning of old beliefs. And
if our goal is to understand how and why
things change, the study of the processes at
work in one part of the world may give us
very valuable insights into those operating
in another. The New Archaeology is
therefore not ethnocentric, or at least it tries
not to be.
Thirdly, with the increased pace of
development in many parts of the world,
both in towns and in the countryside
through the mechanization and intensifica¬
tion of agriculture, many components of
the archaeological record are under threat.
The awareness that this is so has given rise
to "rescue archaeology" as a national
policy in many countries, sometimes refer¬
red to as Culture Resource Management.
This implies both the effort to protect im¬
portant sites against damage, and an
acknowledgement of the need to conduct
systematic excavations at those whose
destruction, cannot be prevented, so as to
learn what we can from them before the site
has been destroyed. Along with the na¬
tional, public investment in rescue ar¬
chaeology has come a deeper awareness of
the significance of the early past for each
nation's own identity. Our past matters: it
is a fundamental part of what we have
become. And archaeology is the only way
we can find out about our early origins.
Up until a century ago, no-one had any
very clear idea of how old the world was,
and very little notion of the antiquity of
humankind. In most countries there were
creation stories, often suggesting that the
first appearance of humankind was the act
of god, or of the gods. But no one could say
with any precision how long ago this
occurred.
It was not until 1859, the same year in
which Charles Darwin published The
Origin ofSpecies, that the antiquity of man
was established. Flint tools were then
shown to have been found together with the
bones of extinct animals, and it was
demonstrated that the animals and the
humans who made the tools must have lived
many thousands of years ago.
Work over the century following these
revelations made many things clear. It was
shown that our species had first emerged in
Africa and that most of the globe had first
been peopled during what is termed the Old
Stone Age, well before 10000 BC. Evidence
for the local origins of farming was found
in several parts of the world. In some of
these areas, early cities developed for the
first time and writing was invented.
But when? To give a precise date to these
developments was extremely difficult. It
was not until the 1950s that progress in
atomic physics allowed new analytical
techniques to come to the aid of ar¬
chaeology. From the application of
potassium-argon dating applied to these
two elements found in rocks of volcanic
origin, we know that the first tool-making
hominids emerged in Africa around two
million years ago. They were not, of course,
very much like modern humans. But even
the earliest hominids, of the genus
Australopithecus, had the human ability of
walking upright, of using the hand to hold
things in a prehensile grasp, of binocular vi¬
sion, and other abilities distinguishing them
from many other species.
By 35,000 years ago, the first members of
our own species, Homo sapiens sapiens are
seen. Modern humankind dates from then
and this date for the appearance of modern
humankind is given to us by radiocarbon
analysis. This technique of radiocarbon
dating is another spin-off from atomic
physics, and it allows any piece of organic
matter (that is to say, material derived from
once living things, whether animal or plant,
and which contains carbon) to be dated in
the laboratory, so long as it is not more than
about 40,000 years old.
For prehistoric Europe, these results have
produced a revolution in our thinking. They
showed that many of the very early Euro¬
pean developments were not derived from
the east Mediterranean area, as had once
been thought. For instance it is no longer
true that the pyramids of Egypt are the
earliest stone-built monuments in the
world. Some of the stone-built tombs of
Europe are earlier, and Stonehenge in
England or the temples of Malta are now
the contemporaries of the pyramids not
their younger relatives.
The broader significance of radiocarbon
dating is much wider even than this. It
means that for the first time, those areas
which did not have an early written history
can have their own secure chronology. We
know now, for instance, that Australia had
a human population, the ancestors of the
modern aborigines, as early as 25,000 years
ago. We can now date properly the early
developments in the Americas, to take
another example. It has been shown that the
origins of the Maya civilization of Mexico
and neighbouring countries date back as
early as 2000 BC. We can now begin to
understand the African iron age, and
recognize properly the true originality of
the terracotta and the bronze sculptures of
Nigeria, some of them dating back to
around 600 BC. I
An extraordinary combination of climatic
and geological conditions has preserved
these footprints of a hominid in petrified
volcanic ash at Laetoli, Tanzania, for /
some 3,600,000 years.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
ri'
/ -
> * £K '. v Ató'*' -w* s ' Àfti 3r '
/:
' ^ ' / * t '
v s'y^* í
' ti
HE" '
v, .U/7
:Xf 'V'/^V **I1
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ó£0' /*
$2
MET- M
Wrt \
' II HtEr ' y-J>M
AS
^T- " ^.Trl
A¿¿F rlSSÍr
:,\
tefc
.**
«S^
-.-:-- .
Above, excavating a tumulus In fair
weather and foul, as depicted in the
Gentleman's Magazine, 1852. Below, a
modern scientific excavation being car¬
ried out at a Palaeolithic site in the Oise,
France.
These are just a few examples of the
many which could be brought forward from
each area of the globe. All of this means
then, that it is now possible to speak in
terms of a world prehistory. For each area
the long sequence of human development
can be built up. As a result of this dating
revolution, each country can have its own,
well-dated prehistory.
Dating techniques represent, however,
only one group of the techniques of ar¬
chaeological science, even though they are
probably the most important. Another line
of investigation is the laboratory analysis of
artefacts stone tools, for instance, or
pottery which can often give clear indica¬
tions of the original source of the material
used. This allows us to learn something of
the trade and exchange of goods among the
early populations and of the system of
distribution of the goods to the areas where
they were used, buried and later discovered
by the archaeologist.
The life sciences too have made their con¬
tribution. From the study of the rubbish of
early societies it is now possible to build up
a very clear picture of their diet, and hence
of their subsistence economy. For instance,
carbonized seeds from rubbish dumps,
when studied by a specialist, can reveal
precisely what food crops were being
cultivated by early farmers. Investigations
of animal bones can indicate which wild
animals were being hunted, and whether or
not domestic animals were being kept and in
what numbers and proportions.
Modern archaeology, it has been said, is
sometimes just the study of poor man's rub¬
bish. This is often quite true! For by study¬
ing these rather modest remains we can
build up a whole picture of the developing
economy of early societies which may tell us
more about life in them than the most
precious objects of gold or jade.
In many ways, however, the most ex¬
citing recent developments in archaeology
have not been those achieved in the
laboratory, in the perfection of dating
methods or the study of the early environ¬
ment. They have come rather, from a
change in outlook, and of philosophy. The
"New Archaeology" began in the 1960s, in
the United States and in Britain, arising
from a dissatisfaction with the assumption
and outlook of the traditional archaeology,
which often seemed to reach conclusions
framed in very simplified historical terms.
Its leading exponent has been Professor
Lewis R. Binford of the University of New
Mexico at Albuquerque, and his great
achievement has been to show that in order
to understand the past it is not sufficient
just to dig up the artefacts of past ages and
to write some intuitive story based on one's
impressions of them.
Instead, our concern should be the study
of culture processthat is to say how and
why human cultures change. We have to ask
much more carefully what is the explana¬
tion for all the differences, the variability
which we see in the archaeological record.
This means that we have to develop a better
theory, a better methodology for ar¬
chaeological interpretation.
Processual archaeologists, then, seek to
understand why things changed, and this
means developing explanations through a
willingness to generalize. It implies the con-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
struction of theories in the same sort of way
that the scientist works when understanding ,
the world of nature. These theories can then '
be assessed, and sometimes they can be
tested against new archaeological findings.
To take an example, we may want to
understand how a particular city came to be
built, and how civilization emerged in an
area whether we are talking of ancient
Rome, or of Moenjodaro in Pakistan, or
whatever. To do this properly we need to
seek some more general understanding of
the processes which lead to increasing
growth and complexity in different human
cultures. We can then study how far the
case of Rome or Moenjodaro fits into the
general picture, and try to examine the
special features of each.
The "New Archaeology" is more op¬
timistic than the traditional approach. It
does not accept the assertion that we cannot
learn through archaeology about the social
organization or the religious life of past
societies as many traditional archaeologists
have asserted. Rather we have to try and
develop sound arguments which will allow
us to interpret the data about these aspects
of society, as well as about diet and about
technology and so forth.
Processual archaeology is very concerned
also to think more carefully about how the
Prehistoric megalithic temple complex at
Ggantija, on the island of Gozo, Republic
of Malta. Modern scientific dating tech¬
niques have shown that some of Malta's
prehistoric stone temples, characterized
by a very skilful use of local materials,
were built before 3000 BC, much earlier
than was once thought. Unesco is co¬
operating with the Maltese Government
on the preservation and presentation of
Malta's important monuments and sites.
archaeological record itself is formed
about exactly how the sites which we dig up,
and the objects which we find in them,
come to be found where they are. The new
field of ethnoarchaeology has developed in
order to investigate these issues. It involves
going out to live in a suitable contemporary
community, which has a way of life that is
in some respects similar to the prehistoric or
historic one that one seeks to understand.
The ethnoarchaeologist studies how the
modern archaeological record in that con¬
temporary society comes about.
Lewis Binford was one of the first ar¬
chaeologists to go and do this. His interest
was in the hunter-gatherers of the
Mousterian period, 40,000 years ago. He
saw clearly that the best way to understand
the archaeological record of those long-
dead hunter-gatherers was to go out and
study in detail the archaeological record of
a living community of hunter-gatherers. He
chose the Nunamiut eskimos of Alaska. He
. lived in a suitable community, taking part in
hunting expeditions. And because he was
not a very good hunter, he did the butchery
for the group. This gave him the opportuni¬
ty of studying how rubbish is discarded in
such a community, and his work has con¬
tributed greatly to the study of early hunter-
gatherers.
The same techniques of study can be ap¬
plied to urban communities also. In Tuc¬
son, Arizona, the "Garbage Project"
under the direction of Professor William J.
Rathje has studied the rubbish discarded by
families in different districts of the city.
Since they do not simply throw rubbish
away, but deposit it in trash cans, the Gar¬
bage Project has had to turn itself into a
rubbish-disposal squad, collecting the gar¬
bage from the trash cans and studying it in
the laboratory. It may sound odd, but the
results are very interesting.
This project illustrates the point that the
techniques of archaeology are relevant to
the material culture of human societies at all
times and places, ancient and modern. The
contemporary archaeologist no longer
thinks in terms of "primitive" and "ad¬
vanced" cultures. The hunter-gatherer of
today or yesterday is as interesting as the
city-dweller: both are part of the rich varie¬
ty of human culture although it must be
admitted that hunter-gatherers have con¬
tributed to it for a hundred times as long as
city-dwellers!
There is another reason why modern ar¬
chaeology really does deserve its place in the
modern world. The traditional archaeology
often explained things in terms of the "dif¬
fusion" of culture. The assumption was
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
"o "o
O -1
il
©I
C Q)
To help him unravel the archaeological
record left by the hunter-gatherers of the
Mousterian period, 40,000 years ago, the
U.S. archaeologist Lewis Binford decided
to study the archaeological record of a
modern community of hunter-gatherers,
the Nunamiut eskimos ofAlaska. In seek¬
ing to understand how hunters perceive
and use their landscape and the kind of
archaeology they create by their actions,
Binford mapped the life of the Nunamiut
community in every detail. Above, line
drawing by Binford of activities he
observed at a Nunamiut killing and
butchering site. Bone splinters discarded
by 2 men (nos. 2 and 3) entered the drop
zone. Larger bones were thrown behind
them In the toss zone.
^ made that the major advances came about
only in one or two areas, and were transmit¬
ted to the barbarian fringe by the "diffu¬
sion" of culture. In recent years, resear¬
chers have come to realize that this was
sometimes a rather colonialist viewpoint,
implying that the interesting developments
came about only in a few crucial, privileged
centres.
Today we see that, to understand the
changes taking place, you have to under¬
stand the processes that are operating local¬
ly in the area under study. It is necessary to
study the changes in social structure, the
developing population, the economy and
technology. Exchanges with other areas,
and the importation of new ideas can admit¬
tedly play and do play a part in that process,
but they are not necessarily of dominant
importance.
To take one example, it was assumed for
many years that the ruins of Great Zim¬
babwe, in the country which today takes its
The Tucson Garbage Project
The brainchild of a group of an¬
thropologists at the University ofArizona,
the Tucson Garbage Project was launch¬
ed in 1973 in order to study the material
culture of a modern city by "excavating"
its garbage, considered as evidence of its
residents' way of life. In the words of the
Project's director, Professor William L.
Rathje, "we believed that assumptions
about the way material culture is related
to behaviour in past civilizations can be
tested in a familiar, on-going society. Se¬
cond, we felt that applying archaeological
methods to such a society can produce
valuable insights into that society itself. "
Below, Rathje's student workers careful¬
ly sort, record and weigh household gar¬
bage for evidence of what contemporary
society buys and how it lives. This at-
. tempt to take a systematic look at modern
society in the United States from the ar¬
chaeological viewpoint is the prototype
ofsimilar studies conducted elsewhere in
the United States as well as in Mexico city
and Sydney, Australia.
name from that monument, must have been
the work of skilled immigrants from the
north, or perhaps the result of contacts with
Arab traders. It simply was not accepted
that they could be the work of the local in¬
habitants, that is to say, of the African
population. Yet today all the evidence (in¬
cluding the radiocarbon evidence) goes to
show that this was in fact the case. We don't
need immigrants, or a trading mission, to
account for the monument, which we can
explain better in terms of the local working
of the society of the time. Just the same is
true of Stonehenge in England which used
to be thought of as the product of contacts
and skills of the Mediterranean world. To¬
day we think of it in local terms. We don't
need Mediterranean colonists to explain it.
This does not mean that we should always
think of each land in isolation. But it does
encourage us to believe that every nation
should encourage the investigation by ar¬
chaeological means of its own past. Today
most countries are proud of their own
cultural heritage, and some of them have
remarkable museums, like those in Mexico
City and in Cairo, to display it.
There is also a growing concern for the
conservation of the cultural heritage.
Unesco is sponsoring a number of projects,
such as its major campaign to save the re¬
mains of the great early city of Moenjodaro
in Pakistan (see article page 32); and most
nations have their own programme for
safeguarding monuments. These are now
seen as international problems. Some of
them will be discussed at the World Ar¬
chaeological Congress, to be held in
September 1986 in Southampton and Lon¬
don (see note page 38). The U.K. national
secretary, Professor Peter Ucko of
Southampton University, is expecting that
representatives from most countries in the
world will attend. They will discuss pro¬
blems of conservation and of interpreta¬
tion, in the light of the newly-emerging in¬
ternational consciousness about our early
past.
Archaeology used to be the pursuit of a
few leisured amateurs, often based in the
more prosperous centres of the industrial
west. Today it is a field of great interest to
many people in every country in the world.
This is partly because it gives each of us an
opportunity to understand more fully our
own national history. But to focus on one's
own nation alone is mere chauvinism. Ar¬
chaeology also offers us the opportunity to
see the early history of each land as one part
of the broader history of the human species
as a whole. And processual archaeology in¬
vites us to try to understand better the
greater diversity of human culture, now and
in the past. This has been made easier both
by the battery of techniques made available
by the sciences, and the rigour and the self-
awareness which have been part of the
"New Archaeology".
COLIN RENFREW is Disney Professor of Ar¬
chaeology at the University of Cambridge and
a Fellow of St. John's College, Cambridge. He
has worked mainly on the Prehistory of Europe
and on the Theory ofArchaeology. Among his
publications are Before Civilization: the
Radiocarbon Revolution and Prehistoric
Europe (London, Pelican Press, and New York,
Cambridge University Press) and Approaches
to Social Archaeology (Cambridge University
Press and Harvard University Press).
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Let the past serve the future
by Osaga Odak
"Pick it up. Feel it. Take it to pieces. Can
you find this? This is the message that the
children in Kenya are given these days
when they visit one of the national
museums." This statement in a Nairobi
newspaper highlights the main objective
of the Nairobi Museum's education
servicesto show that learning can be an
active and enjoyable process. Below,
students handle a cast of early man at the
National Museum, Nairobi.
IN the Third World, application of de¬
velopment theory is directed primarily
towards alleviating human suffering
and enabling people to live relatively com¬
fortable lives. This implies the provision of
better health services, adequate educational
opportunities and proper communications
systems as well as improving agriculture
and moving towards industrialization.
The role of culture (and of archaeology
which is concerned with an aspect of
culture) in development has, however,
generally been neglected. Yet if develop¬
ment is to be meaningful, it has to embrace
all spheres of human activity, including
culture. Cultural intervention in develop¬
ment, it must be stressed, is fundamental to
the stability of the development effort.
Archaeology evolved as a discipline in
Europe. But at the time when it was
developing into a truly scientific discipline
the continent ofAfrica was in the process of
being colonized. The colonists were preced¬
ed by explorers and missionaries who saw
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Africa as a continent inhabited by primitive
peoples who needed to be rescued from bar¬
barism and brought to civilization basically
through the Christian religion.
To the missionaries, African religions
and values were not worthy of preservation
and development. Furthermore, the
religious systems the missionaries imposed
were based on alien cultural systems which
were incompatible with African cultures.
The whole fabric of African culture was
undermined. Shrines were replaced by
churches, mosques and temples, sites sacred
to the Africans were defiled and artefacts
that bore witness to the continent's pre-
colonial technological achievements were
replaced by industrially produced items.
This was the context in which European
and American archaeologists came to
Africa. They came not to save African
culture and history from destruction, but
primarily for their own personal aims and
ambitions. Nevertheless, there were some
positive side-effects since their work,
oriented as it was towards reconstruction of
cultural successions and the development of
general archaeological methodologies and
theories, not only revealed numerous past
cultural achievements and laid the founda¬
tions for future work, but also led to an up¬
ward reassessment of the African cultural
profile.
Cultural consciousness based on tradi¬
tional culture among the colonized was not
encouraged during colonial times even in
countries where the colonists established
organizations dealing with antiquities and
archaeological programmes.
After independence," however, there was
a movement towards what might be termed
a "cultural renaissance". Study of tradi¬
tional culture systems and elements of
cultural disciplines such as archaeology
found their way piecemeal into syllabuses.
However, the lack of a sufficient number of
trained local educationists and the almost
total reliance on foreign experts in the
preparation of educational programmes
resulted, to some extent, in a continuation
of colonial programmes.
As the African countries moved towards
self-sufficiency in manpower, the position
began gradually to change. Efforts were
made to intensify investigation of the
history of Africa, but since there were few
written records in which that history was
reflected, African historians turned to other
sources. Archaeology in particular gained
new popularity as a tool of historical
research and was introduced as an auxiliary
discipline in the history departments of
several African universities.
Nevertheless, the appeal of archaeology
remains limited. This is in part because ex¬
cavation, an essential element in ar¬
chaeology, involves dealing with burial-
grounds, skeletal remains and other sites
and objects associated with certain taboos.
Hence, in ordinary people's minds, to be an
archaeologist is to be a "grave-digger" and
to practise an abnormal profession.
Modernization has also had a negative in¬
fluence. Modern developments in
agriculture, road building and the construc¬
tion of dams and hydro-electric power
plants have destroyed sites once regarded
with reverence and this in turn has en-
Students' quarters at the Centre for
Museum Studies, Jos, Nigeria.
During the International year of Disabled
Persons, 1981, the Tunisian National
Committee of the International Council of
Museums (ICOM) designed a scheme to
use museum facilities to help mentally
handicapped children. Right, during their
first experimental visit to an ar¬
chaeological museum, the National
Museum of the Bardo, Tunis, a group of
handicapped children examine a massive
foot from a statue of Jupiter. Above, a
drawing made after the visit by one of the
children, Khaled Zarrouq. The scheme
proved that the mentally handicapped
could benefit from the stimulus of regular
visits to museums.
couraged vandals to destroy other formerly
sacred places either in the hope of finding
treasure or even just for fun. All this has
created a climate of general disrespect for
traditional culture that has extended to in¬
clude disciplines such as archaeology and
anthropology which study traditional
culture.
Since independence the influence of
foreign archaeologists and of foreign foun¬
dations funding archaeological projects has
continued to display both negative and
positive aspects. Recent advances in the
study of human origins, especially in east
Africa, have, for example, focused world
attention on Africa's distant past. They
have also given outsiders the impression
that African archaeology has no problems
and that work is going ahead smoothly.
The fact is, however, that these studies
refer to periods before the emergence of
modern man. It may be asked, for example,
to what extent the study of human origins
contributes to the understanding of the
history and culture of the modern popula¬
tions of Africa. A government which is con¬
scious of the need to understand the overall
past of its peoples cannot rely almost ex¬
clusively on one aspect of human history,
however important, which is of little direct
relevance to its peoples, whilst ignoring
those areas vital to the promotion of their
consciousness of their cultural identity.
A further problem is that, due to the
shortage of funds from internal sources,
African archaeologists seek and receive
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
financial assistance from foreign founda¬
tions and financing agencies. Although in a
number of cases this has led to ar¬
chaeological work being carried out which
would not otherwise have been done, it also
involves two major negative side-effects.
Firstly, it tends to encourage local
authorities not to provide for ar¬
chaeological work in their development
planning on the grounds that funds will be
available from foreign sources. Secondly,
these foreign foundations and agencies
usually assist only projects they themselves
have selected. As a result local ar¬
chaeologists'; find themselves obliged to
design their research proposals to fit in with
the dictates of the funding agencies. In this
way foreign foundations may influence the
development of archaeological work in a
country without necessarily involving
foreign researchers.
All this highlights the need for coherent,
clear-cut national policies for archaeology
backed by legislation and adequate finan¬
cial resources. Such policies should include
clear guidelines concerning the relation¬
ships between archaeology and other
cultural organizations and disciplines as
well as an element of manpower planning.
An archaeological organization manned
by a sufficient number of local ar¬
chaeologists and inspired by a well-
formulated policy could play a very positive
role. By co-ordinating the efforts of local
and foreign researchers it could prevent
duplication of effort and ensure proper
distribution of research over the different
time periods and different aspects of
archaeology.
Armed with a sound policy and a
knowledge of national priorities, a local ar¬
chaeological organization could relate ar¬
chaeological efforts to national develop¬
ment needs and provide up-to-date infor¬
mation on the country's archaeological
potential. It would also be expected to have
at its disposal detailed documentation on
the country's cultural resources, including
an inventory of archaeological sites and
monuments based on work undertaken
previously together with the relevant data
(field notes, reports, publications and other
unpublished materials) retained at its
documentation centre.
The public has yet to recognize the role
archaeology has to play in modern develop¬
ment and few Africans are attracted to it. It
is not unusual for African countries to have
no more than a handful of professional ar¬
chaeologists, or even just one. The battle
for recognition has not been won even
within academic circles. The problem is to
remove archaeology from the dark corners
of academic elitism and throw it open to the
public.
Young people are currently in the majori- .
ty in Third World countries and, just as the
ultimate solution to illiteracy lies in free and
compulsory education for youth, so also, if
the battle for the recognition of ar¬
chaeology is to be won, it has to start with
them. There is therefore an urgent need to
stimulate interest in archaeology among the
young, to enhance its status within
academic circles and to develop interest in it
among the public at large.
Archaeology provides data which con¬
tribute to the reconstruction of the history
of peoples whose past is not or is only little
reflected in written records. Relics unearth¬
ed at archaeological sites mirror the origin
and development of a people's culture.
Some of the sites excavated could be
developed into on-the-spot museums or
cultural parks.
Archaeological sites, treasures and
artefacts can become symbols which inten¬
sify a people's sense of belonging to a locali¬
ty and to a historical and cultural tradition.
A sense of cultural identity is the basis for
self-awareness and self-realization which
opens up vast opportunities for individual
or group creativity. Accordingly, ar¬
chaeology can play an important role in any
nation's development.
OSAGA ODAK, of Kenya, is a cultural an¬
thropologist who specializes in rock art,
cultural resource management and . ethnic
studies. An Associate Director of the Kenya
Archaeological and Ethnographic Research
Agency (KAERA) and Cultural Research Co¬
ordinator in the Department of Culture of the
Kenya Government, he is also the chairman of
the Kenya National Committee of the Interna¬
tional Council on Monuments and Sites
(ICOMOS).
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
How science unlocks the secrets
of the past by Tony Hackens
ARCHAEOLOGY was born in sixteenth-century Europe as
an offshoot of the scholarly pleasures of the Renais¬
sance. Many early archaeologists were collectors moti¬
vated by an aesthetic interest in Antiquity and a desire to recon¬
stitute the background of events described by ancient writers.
Until the beginning of the twentieth century, generations of
archaeologists set out to rediscover and excavate great sites, to
record the evolution of styles and to retrace the interplay of cul
tural influences according to aesthetic criteria and typology
the study of objects by types.
Today's archaeologist usually lives in a world which is far from
the preoccupations of scholarly collectors or prestige excava¬
tions. He or she is at the centre of a group of specialists from dif¬
ferent scientific disciplines. Working with these specialists and
profiting from methods used in the natural sciences, modern
archaeologists attempt to decipher the messages stored in the
Tell-tale tree rings
In the late 15th century Leonardo da Vinci discovered seasonal
growth patterns in trees. In this century tree-ring dating (den¬
drochronology) has become a science. Each ring produced in a
tree's trunk during its yearly growth is unique. The rings are
wide or narrow depending on the prevailing growth conditions,
and precisely the same long-term sequence of wide and narrow
rings is never repeated, because year-to-year variations in
climate are never the same. By putting together tree-ring pat¬
terns from overlapping living trees and dead wood (see diagram)
scientists construct a tree-ring chronology. Samples of wood
from objects discovered by archaeologists can be dated by be-
/
W 1572 MdKacreol St. Bartholomew
1589 Asiaitmation ol Htnr III
1610 Anamination ol Henr IV
HI
1643 Dnthof Log« XIII
©
1715 Death of Louii XIV
17 89 French Revolution
1804 Coronation of Napoleon I
1852 Loun Napoleon proclaimed emperor
' 11)70 Proclamation of the 3rd Republic
1669 Inauguration of the Eiffel Tower
1914 Firjt World War
ISM Strand World War
ing matched, either visually or using a computer, to such master
chronologies, established region by region.
Because they live to such a great age, the bristlecone pines
which grow in the White Mountains of California have served as
a unique tool in tree-ring dating. Using them, Dr. C.W. Ferguson
of Arizona University has established a continuous tree-ring
sequence which stretches back over 8,500 years into the past
(see back cover). Ferguson hopes that this sequence will even¬
tually reach back at least 10,000 years. This sequence and
others developed in other parts of the world have been used to
"calibrate", or cross-check, dates established using radiocar¬
bon or carbon 14, another important scientific dating method
used by archaeologists.
Developed in the late 1940s, radiocarbon dating is based on
the fact that living organisms absorb radiocarbon from the at¬
mosphere. When they die the carbon disintegrates at a known
rate, and by measuring the amount of it left in a sample ol
organic material such as charcoal or bone, it is possible to deter¬
mine how long ago the plant or animal died. However, when
scientists analysed the carbon 1 4 content of tree rings of known
age they found that although the carbon 1 4 age and the tree-ring
age should have been the same, there were actually con¬
siderable discrepancies. Earlier than 1000 BC the carbon 14
dates give a progressively greater underestimate of the true
calendar date. Why is this so? The reason is that radiocarbon
dating was based on the assumption that the cosmic rays that
created carbon 14 had bombarded the atmosphere at a fixed in¬
tensity, but in fact carbon 14 has fluctuated. Today, tree-ring
calibration charts have been established which convert
radiocarbon years into calendar years. It is amazing to think that
some Swiss lake-villages of the 4th millennium BC can be dated
not by millennia or centuries but down to the year in which the
trees used to build them were felled.
This development had far-reaching consequences for ar¬
chaeology. Many European prehistoric monuments and sites
were shown to be centuries older than previously thought. The
classical theory whereby their origin was due to skills and
motivations which were diffused into Europe from the east was
no longer tenable in the light of tree-ring calibration.
Left, section of an oak felled in the Forest of Fontainebleau in
1952. By counting the tree-rings it was possible to establish the
age of the tree which, because it began to grow around the time
of the Massacre of St. Bartholomew in Paris, in 1572, is known
as the oak of St. Bartholomew.
©
mi; 1 1 trrm
an
Liv,nfj
tu
Dead t rees Dead wood
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
material archives of human activity in the form of multifarious
traces left on a wide variety of materials. Although they may not
tread in the footsteps of Schliemann at Troy and Mycenae, or
those of Lord Carnarvon in Egypt, nor experience the excitement
of discovering tombs overflowing with precious objects and
jewellery, they perform an equally valid humanist task as they
use the latest scientific techniques to recapture aspects of the
life, environment, landscape, economy or technology of the past.
To excavate is to destroy, and once destroyed the archaeologi¬
cal heritage unlike naturecannot grow again. These seem¬
ingly commonplace observations underlie the mission of the
archaeologist, who must identify the slightest hint of past human
activity, analyse every facet of the information it can yield by
using every available method, and evaluate his or her interpreta¬
tion through reasoning which may later be tested with the
computer.
The following text, with accompanying boxes and illustrations,
attempts to provide a highly simplified and selective account of
some of the complex scientific techniques being used today by
archaeologists in prospection, excavation, analysis, dating and
preservation.
WHERE TO EXCAVATE. One problem a field archaeologist
faces is that of knowing where to dig. Sometimes the study of old
documents and literature is helpful: in other cases clues must be
found from the air or on the ground. The use of aerial photo¬
graphy in archaeology (see page 1 8) goes back to the beginning
of the century, when photos were taken from a balloon above
Ostia, the port of Rome. Its systematic application has made it
possible to study the layout of towns before beginning to exca¬
vate, to locate traces of Roman roads and villas and to observe
systems of land management. More recently télédétection from
satellites has vastly expanded the scale of possibilities for aerial
prospection.
On the ground, the use of electrical resistivity to detect buried
walls and ditches is now widespread. In making a resistivity sur¬
vey, an electrical current is passed through the ground to mea-
These 3 drawings of the site of ancient Troy reflect some of the
changing techniques and approaches in field archaeology since
the last century. Top, a cross-section drawn in 1879 and publish¬
ed by Heinrich Schliemann. It shows the accumulation of debris
to which the great German archaeologist often referred as a ma¬
jor obstacle to his search for Homeric Troy. Middle drawing is a
diagrammatic section of a deposit at Troy by Carl Biegen, who
directed the University of Cincinnati's research at Troy from
1932 to 1938. Biegen 's major interest was the analysis of
stratigraphical sequences in different parts of the artificial hill of
Troy. Bottom drawing is a recently published section showing
not only stratigraphy but the sampling of soil in the different
layers. This is done to help reconstruct the environment at dif¬
ferent periods.
©
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
)> sure the resistance of the soil, which is affected by moisture.
Metal detectors are being widely used by treasure hunters in
some countries where, when used indiscriminately and irrespon¬
sibly, they have caused havoc to the archaeological heritage.
Recently US and Swedish technicians have developed a radar-
truck capable of recording structures buried to a depth of four
metres in certain terrain such as peat.
EXCAVATION. When they come to excavate, the most impor¬
tant method used by modern archaeologists is to study the strati¬
graphy of a site, the arrangement of archaeological deposits in
superimposed layers or strata. The earliest excavations at Rome
in the sixteenth century and at Pompei and Herculaneum in 1717
were above all a harvest of objects from the soil, and Schliemann
himself admitted that he had dug through (and destroyed) many
recent levels before reaching the "interesting" Trojan levels. He
was not alone in acting in this way. His drawings give some idea
of the superposition of strata and remains, but he made no pre¬
cise visual records which can be interpreted without reference to
his reports.
The next generation of archaeologists made abundant
records, drew vertical and horizontal sections, and covered the
site with a grid of squares of standard size in order to "read" the
way in which the strata were superimposed, to analyse their rela¬
tionship with the levels of soil on which people had lived, and with
layers of building and destruction. A meticulous description was
made of every trace revealed during the methodical removal of
earth, often using precision instruments to locate the exact posi¬
tion of each vestige.
The present generation of archaeologists takes large numbers
of samples while excavating samples of earth, pollen, and
charcoal. In this way it is possible to deduce from the ruins of a
building what the building was actually like, to reconstitute its
environment, and to identify the occupation of those who lived in
it. Analysis of the isotope Carbon 13 in bones and tissue can pro¬
vide evidence of the diet of prehistoric men, and the study of
insect finds can help indirectly to identify their occupations. Stra¬
tigraphy now makes use of a range of scientific disciplines,
among which the earth sciences play an increasing part.
Top photo: analysis of a small Byzantine
cross being carried out by proton-
induced X-ray emission (PIXE), at the
Laboratoire d'Analyses par Réactions
Nucléaires, Namur, Belgium. The cross is
bombarded with protons from a "proton
gun", inducing X-rays whose
characteristics are measured by X-ray
detectors at each side of the cross. The
analysis showed the relative content of
gold, copper, iron and silver. Photo,
above, shows the non-destructive nature
of this test : a member of the Namur team
uses the same method on his own teeth.
Did Philip of Macedón
look like this?
In 1977 Professor Manolis Andronicos of
the University of Thessaloniki discovered
three royal graves at Vergina in
Macedonia (see Unesco Courier, June
1979). It seemed possible that King Philip
II of Macedón (382-336 BC), the father of
Alexander the Great, might have been
buried in the biggest tomb, but proof was
lacking. In 1981 Richard Neave of Man¬
chester University, Dr. John Prag of the
Manchester Museum and Dr. J.H.
Musgrave of Bristol University began to
co-operate with Professor Andronicos in
examining the skull in question and
reconstructing the dead man's ap¬
pearance. Casts were taken of the bones
of the skull, in fragments after cremation.
It proved difficult to fit the bones
together, and study showed that this dif¬
ficulty was largely due to injury and con¬
genital deformity. "In short," Dr. Prag
has written, "the left side of the dead
man's face was markedly
underdeveloped and the right side
overdeveloped, to compensate for this."
Plastic surgeons also noted injuries to the
right eye-socket which, they concluded,
could only have been caused by a missile
from above. Portrait heads of Philip show
an injury to the right eye which was ap¬
parently sightless, and a 1st century BC
author noted that "he had his right eye
cut out when he was struck by an arrow
while inspecting the siege engines and
the protective sheds at the siege of
Methone." This account, Dr. Prag notes,
"tallies exactly with the injury we noted
on the skull from Vergina. It provided the
proof that Andronicos has always been
hoping for and appears to have silenced
the sceptics." The team which
reconstructed the head used the same
techniques as those used by the police to
identify unknown decomposed bodies.
Measuring pegs were inserted at different
points on the skull to establish the
thickness of soft tissue, muscles were
modelled, and then superficial layers
added. The details of the scar were based
on an almost identical injury received
some years ago by a Canadian
lumberjack.
1. Reconstructed skull
showing injury to right
eye
2. Plaster cast of the
finished head
3. Wax cast of the
reconstructed head
with hair, beard and
skin colour
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
THE ANALYSIS OF ARCHAEOLOGICAL FINDS. Since the
end of the Second World War great strides have been made in
the analytical techniques used by archaeologists. Objects may
be analysed to discover how they were made, what they were
made of, and where those materials were obtained. The Lydian
stone or touchstone was the earliest method used to determine
the proportion of precious metal contained in an object. It pro¬
vides remarkably precise results. The metal to be assayed is rub¬
bed on the touchstone which is then exposed to a reactive agent
whose colour changes are evaluated.
In the third century BC, Archimedes used the concept known
today as specific gravity to solve the problem of whether or not
King Hieron of Syracuse's crown was made of gold or of an alloy
of gold and silver. According to the story, it occurred to him one
day as he stepped into his bath and saw the water overflow that
the excess of bulk caused by the introduction of alloy could be
measured by putting the crown and equal weights of gold and sil¬
ver separately into a vessel of water and measuring the differen¬
ces of overflow. Each of these techniques is still used today.
In chemical analysis techniques a sample has to be taken from
the object being analysed, and in the case of precious objects
this is often undesirable. Spectrographs analysis, which suc¬
ceeded "wet chemistry", investigates the chemical nature of a
material by examination of its spectrum. Using this technique
only a single point may be examined in each object, and if a
sample is taken it is destroyed and the experiment cannot be
repeated. The ¡deal remained a method of analysis which did not
destroy the object being analysed.
The next step towards non-destructive analysis was to
bombard objects with X-rays which cause no damage and simply
provoke other rays whose diffraction or energy levels are
characteristic of different materials. This analysis is confined to
a microscopic layer of atoms on the surface of an object. A
specimen which is not homogenous will thus deceive the analyst
as to its true nature. The X-ray method requires a profound
knowledge of series of objects so as to avoid hasty generali¬
zations made from surface analyses.
Dating prehistoric sites
In an experimental study which could
open up fascinating possibilities for
future work on human evolution and ar¬
chaeology, Swedish scientist Svante
Pääbo recently succeeded in extracting
and cloning (reproducing identical copies
of) a DNA sample from the 4,500-year-old
mummy (right) of an ancient Egyptian boy
who died at the age of one. DNA (deox¬
yribonucleic acid) is the master molecule
of life and carries the hereditary instruc¬
tions that determine the nature of a living
organism, and information on DNA se¬
quences can give us a clear picture of a
population's genetic identity. Informa¬
tion on the DNA sequences of ancient
Egyptian mummies could, therefore, tell
us not only about the relationships bet¬
ween members of the Egyptian royal
families, but also about population
movements in ancient Egypt. It should be
pointed out that, despite sensational
rumours, it is not possible using these
techniques to reconstitute a functional
gene, and even less a living human being,
from such DNA sequences.
Methods Materials Range of time
Thermoluminescence Ceramics
burned rocks
(silex,
sandstone,
granite)
stalagmites
0 to several
hundreds of
thousands of
years
Comments
Dendrochronology Wood 0 to 7,000
Carbon 14 Organic
remains
(wood,
bones)
shells
0 to 40,000
Uranium- Stalagmites 10,000 to
thorium ratio bones
shells
250,000
Electron spin
resonance
Stalagmites
bones
1 ,000 to several
million years
under
development
Fission tracks Volcanic
glass,
minerals rich
in uranium
0 to several
hundred thousand
years
Potassium-argon volcanic larva 1,000 to
1,000 million years
Amino-acids Bones under
development
Chart (0 Centre des Faibles Radioactivités, Centre mixte CNRS-CEA, Gif-sur-Yvette, France
Certain dating methods are more appropriate than others,
depending on the approximate age of the site and the materials
available. Whenever possible it is advisable to use several
methods and to compare results.
Rome has embarked on a far-reaching
project in which the conservation of the
antiquities in its historic centre is an in¬
tegral part of the wider canvas of modern
city planning. The protection of marble
and bronze monuments and statues
disfigured by air pollution was a priority
step. Right, statue of Marcus Aurelius
undergoing treatment at the Central In¬
stitute of Restoration.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The use of more penetrating rays has made it possible to elimi¬
nate both the disadvantages of destructive analysis and the
superficial character of X-ray analysis.
Nuclear analysis using neutrons either produced from a re¬
actor or an accelerator has greatly extended our knowledge of
ancient metalwork, as well as helping to identify recent forgeries,
through establishing the respective content of certain elements
and identifying the sources of metals in ancient coinage by what
are called the "geological fingerprints" of their original mines.
But one field of nuclear analysis is particularly fruitful: that of the
proportion of isotopes of certain bodies determined by mass
spectrography. The proportions of Oxygen 16 and Oxygen 18 in
ancient marble are characteristic of different deposits, and it is
much safer to identify the origins of Greek marble artefacts using
this method rather than by an "experienced" judgment of the
grain and the colouring of the veins. The application of this
method to lead is even more widespread, since lead is so exten¬
sively used in building and glass. It has been possible to identify
deposits of lead from ancient Spain to Iran with considerable
certainty.
Finally, analyses are carried out to find out more about the
nature of ancient technologies. The electron probe micro-
analyser provides an enlarged image on a screen of responses
recorded when electron beams bombard a surface. This method
has been used to determine whether gilding was done with mer¬
cury. Detailed and repeated analyses can be carried out, even on
cumbersome objects, using Proton Induced X-ray Emission
(PIXE) apparatus in which protons strike a small area of the
object and provoke X-rays whose characteristics are measured
by X-ray detectors.
DATING. The Carbon 14 dating method invented by Willard F.
Libby is today part of the dating arsenal of many archaeologists.
An accurate measurement of the proportion of Carbon 14 con¬
tained by a given sample makes it possible to estimate its age
"BP" (Before Present, i.e. before 1950). Extensive research
revealed that Carbon 14 dates were in some cases erroneous
In many countries today treasure hunting
using metal detectors is a popular out¬
door hobby. Archaeologists preoccupied
with the problem of the erosion of the ar¬
chaeological heritage and damage to
sites have strongly criticized treasure
hunters on the grounds that they are only
interested in objects and that by remov¬
ing objects from their context they
destroy valuable information about the
past. At the same time many ar¬
chaeologists are also aware of the danger
of a "comprehension gap" between them
and the public and feel that it is important
to try to mobilize the enthusiasm of
treasure hunters for the buried heritage
and reconcile their hobby interests with
the scientific investigation of the past.
Georadar is an electromagnetic method
of site investigation which has been
developed to map geological structures
and which also has applications for ar¬
chaeology. Electromagnetic energy is
transmitted into the ground from a unit on
Graphic
Recorder
Power
Supply
Tape
Recorder
Pulse
Transmitter
Receiver
Transmit
Receive
Selector
Antenna
iround. \
urface \ \
Transmitted
Pulse
Target
the surface. On its way through the soil
part of the energy is reflected when it
meets an interface between two materials
of differing electrical properties (such as
soil and bedrock, or soil and an ar¬
chaeological object) while the rest pro¬
ceeds to greater depths (see diagram). By
measuring the time between the transmit¬
ted and reflected signals it is possible to
survey the different layers of soil and rock
and the location of buried objects. The
reflected signals are displayed on a
cathode ray tube and on a graphic
recorder, providing a continuous profile
of the subsurface. Below, the radar
system in field operation. The antenna is
mounted on a boom which can be raised
or lowered by a winch inside the vehicle.
The graphic record of the reflected
signals is a close approximation to the in¬
terfaces that would be seen in the wall of
9
dip jwr*2^^j Baa«
BHaMBaaaHMBB^HPrfl
a trench dug along the path taken by the
radar apparatus. Below, "radargram" of
a Bronze Age road in a Danish bog. The
oak road, slightly inclined, was based on
sand. The depth of the road surface was
approximately half a metre.
Oak road
'
G round surface
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
because of wide fluctuations of cosmic rays in the past. Carbon
14 dates have been adjusted after confrontation with dates pro¬
vided by other methods such as thermoluminescence and den¬
drochronology (see box page 1 2).
Thermoluminescence is based on the phenomenon that rays
from radioactive elements in the soil and cosmic rays accumu¬
late in the crystalline materials of pottery and that when the mate¬
rials are heated this energy is liberated and emitted in the form
of light. The quantity of energy and thus of light is proportional
to the length of time during which they have been accumulated.
The system acts as a kind of clock which starts at zero when the
material is heated to a certain temperature. (In the case of pottery
this is when the pottery was baked.) The quantities of light invol¬
ved are infinitely small, and photomultipliers are needed to make
them visible and measure them. Nevertheless, the accumulation
is significant for long periods of over 1,000 years, and this
method is of inestimable value above all for periods earlier than
50,000 years. In very ancient civilizations lacking any written or
typological references, such as the prehistory of Brazil, or the
Jomo culture of Japan, or the oldest cultures of West Africa, ther¬
moluminescence has become accepted as a pioneer dating
method. For space reasons it is not possible to include all dating
methods such as magnetic dating and new nuclear methods now
being developed (see chart page 15).
COMPUTERS AND MATHEMATICAL TECHNIQUES. The
possibilities opened up to archaeologists by access to big
archaeological data banks are virtually limitless. This would
replace cumbersome paper files and the consultation of annual
bibliographies which often inevitably appear with delay. We
should have literally at our fingertips information about objects
and monuments, sites and current research which we could call
up at will. But the danger is that of the tower of Babel. Computer
languages and software must be compatible, yet even in a field
with a concise and international language such as numismatics
different teams have different aims and equipment. Views and
experiences are being exchanged but not yet, automatically at I
The preservation of Pete Marsh
The body of a man was discovered in a
peat bog at Lindow Moss south of Man¬
chester (UK) in August 1984 and taken to
the British Museum for analysis and
preservation. The body had been
mutilated by an excavating machine but
its upper half, including part of the
digestive tract and much skin and hair,
were still intact after preservation in peat,
partly decayed plant matter that gives off
a preservative acid, absorbs moisture and
excludes oxygen. Radio-carbon dating
showed that the corpse of "Pete Marsh",
as the man was nicknamed, was about
2,500 years old. A team of scientists in¬
cluding specialists in forensic science,
dermatology, anatomy, microbiology and
botany immediately began to investigate
the remains and a portrait of Pete Marsh
emerged. He is estimated to have been
1 67 cm tall, aged between 20 and 30, with
mousey-coloured hair, red moustache,
beard and sideburns, and immaculately
trimmed fingernails. He had come to a
violent end by garrotting. Further study of
the body has been carried out by X-ray,
and computerized images of its insides
have been taken with a nuclear magnetic
resonance scanner. Using newly
developed genetic engineering tech¬
niques, researchers are also proposing to
extract genes from the corpse and
"grow" them in the laboratory. Before
being put on public display, Pete Marsh is
being "freeze-dried" (lyophilized) using a
technique which involves freezing the
water content of the body which is then
placed in a vacuum chamber where its ice
crystals vaporize.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
any rate, information and data themselves. Too many data banks
are closed systems reserved for the privileged who have access
to them. Distance questioning is rarely possible. However, tens
of thousands of images can already be recorded on a video disc,
and theoretically the major photo libraries could become accessi¬
ble like those museums which have published illustrated micro¬
fiches of their holdings.
Computerization has also made it possible to carry out com¬
plex reasoning through simulation in short spaces of time, and
to catalogue, record and relate masses of data at great speed.
Interdisciplinarity is thus a keynote of archaeology today. It
should not be limited to the use of costly new methods. Archaeo¬
logists also call increasingly on the expertise of geologists, soil
scientists, botanists and others working in long-established disci¬
plines. It is not possible here to make acomplete list of the
sciences nowadays involved in the reconstruction of the past, but
such a list would include the study of shells, diatoms and
fishbones, mining and ore processing techniques, the study of
glass and paper, not to mention the whole field of underwater
archaeology.
TONY HACKENS, of Belgium, is Professor of Classical Archaeology,
Numismatics and Technical Methods in Archaeology at the Catholic
University of Louvain-la-Neuve, and a research associate with the
Center for Old World Archaeology, Brown University, USA. He is Vice-
President of PACT, the European Expert Group for Physical, Chemical,
Mathematical and Biological Methods in Archaeology, Council of
Europe, Strasbourg. He is also scientific rapporteur for the inter¬
disciplinary post-graduate schools of sciences in archaeology held at
the European University Centre for the Cultural Heritage, at Ravello,
Italy.
Archaeology from the air
Aerial photography has become a major
tool of modern archaeology and each
year leads to the discovery of large
numbers of new sites which are often in¬
visible at ground level. Buried traces of
human activity can affect plant growth for
thousands of years, and these dif¬
ferences in vegetation can be observed
from the air. Interpreting aerial photos is
a highly specialized task; the image
changes as the light changes at different
times of day and at different seasons, and
varies with the state of the vegetation and
other factors. Buried sites may be reveal¬
ed as soil-marks (traces of differently col¬
oured or textured soil) or crop-marks.
Drawing above shows how crop-marks
develop. The vegetation is taller over the
buried ditch but stunted above the stone
foundations. Photo gives a rare oppor¬
tunity to see why crop-marks appear. The
dark soil of a silted up Iron Age ditch can
be seen at the edge of this gravel pit. The
barley above it is taller as a result of the
extra depth of soil and moisture. Remote
sensing technology using devices
mounted on spacecraft and aircraft which
can "sense" on wavelengths that cannot
be detected by the human eye or by con¬
ventional photography seems bound to
affect radically the way in which ar¬
chaeological reconnaissance is planned
and carried out. As yet the potential of
this technology for archaeological
research has only begun to be tapped.
The Nazca enigma
Immense patterns made of furrows or ditches are etched into
the barren Nazca desert almost 500 km southeast of Lima,
the capital of Peru. They are so vast that they cannot be seen
from ground level, but when viewed from the air they unfold
into a fantastic bestiary of semi-naturalistic monkeys, long-
necked birds, a spider, a lizard, dogs, fish and whales, sur¬
rounded by zigzags, spirals, star-shapes, rectangles and
trapezoids. The lines, scored by moving aside lines of rocks
to expose the lighter alluvial soil beneath, are named after
and widely attributed to the Nazca culture which flourished
in the area from around 200 BC to 600 AD.
What was theirpurpose? Eversince the discovery of the Naz¬
ca display over 40 years ago by Dr. Paul Kosok, this has been
a perplexing archaeological mystery. Many theories have
been put forward, some far-fetched. Did the lines indicate a
space-port built by or for extra-terrestrial beings? Did they
have a ritual significance, with torchlight processions
winding along the pictograms on ritual days? Were they a
star map of the ancient heavens, "the world's largest
astronomy book," in Dr. Kosok's phrase? Did they contain
symbolic information for transmission to later generations?
Although many different interpretations have been made of
the individual components of the Nazca display, today many
scholars agree that it has social, political, economic and
religious implications of some kind.
Ever since the Nazca lines were discovered, astronomer-
mathematician Dr. Maria Reiche has devoted her life to stu¬
dying them andattempting to establish correlations between
them and astronomical occurrences. She has specially
recorded some of her conclusions for the Unesco Courier.
"The perfect proportions of these figures, some of them 200
or 300 metres long, suggest that they might have been made
in order to be seen from the air. They could represent con¬
stellations which, as in other ancient cultures, were con¬
sidered to be divinities. These constellations characterize
the different epochs of the year according to their visibility
at night. The most important time of the year was always
December because it was then that water was expected to
flow in the drier rivers and people prepared for this event by
making ploughs... In Nazca this water-announcing constella¬
tion was the Big Dipper. When afraid the water would not ap¬
pear, the people would draw on the ground an image of the
water-bringing divinity, that is the constellation which
always appeared at the same time as the water, so big that
the divinity could see itself from high up and be reminded to
send water again. For several reasons the Big Dipper is
depicted as a monkey. The spider can be considered to
represent Orion."
Not all archaeologists agree with Dr. Reiche's theories, but
they pay tribute to her determination to preserve the fragile
Nazca lines for posterity, so that even if their mystery is
never fully explained they will remain among the most
beautiful creations of human ingenuity.
Right, 90-metre-long Nazca humming Bird seen from the air.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
' n ////
97/
/
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
IMIM""
-JL
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
¿m
- &
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Centre colour pages
Top left: Archaeological digs carried out
in China from 1974to 1979 at a number of
sites of the ancient kingdom of
Zhongshan, in present-day Hebei Pro¬
vince, south-east of Beijing, have made a
major contribution to our knowledge of
this period of Chinese civilization (from
the 6th to the beginning of the 3rd century
BC). Some 20,000 objects were
recovered, most of them from two great
royal tombs. Several musical instruments
testify to the importance accorded to
music during this period. Kongfuzi (Con¬
fucius) considered music to be essential
to the good government of a State. King
Cuo ofZhongshan (died 3 14 BC) seems to
have shared this view. A carillon of
musical stones and a complete carillon of
14 bronze bells (our photo) were
discovered in his tomb. Hung in descen¬
ding order on a lacquered wood frame,
the bells had no tongues but were struck
by a small mallet. This is one of the very
few complete carillons that have ever
been found.
Photo ©Foreign Affairs Bureau of the Ministry of Culture,
Beijing
Bottom left: Coloured frieze from the
Temple of the Eagles, part of the Great
Temple complex in Mexico City (see arti¬
cle this page).
Photo Alex Webb © Magnum, Paris
Top right: Ruins of Moenjodaro in
Pakistan. Advanced concepts of city
planning were used in this centre of a
brilliant culture that flowered in the Indus
Valley 5,000 years ago.
Photo © Raoul Zamora, Paris
Bottom right: Masterpiece of micro-
jewellery from a Scythian kurgan (burial
mound) in the Ukraine depicts a griffon
with a pendant in the form of a bunch of
grapes.
Photo © Institute of Oriental Studies of the USSR Academy
of Sciences, Moscow
Opposite page
Above: Charged with expressive power,
this extremely rare miniature ivorybust of
Alexander the Great wearing a lion helmet
dates from the 3rd century BC. It was
unearthed in a monumental temple ex¬
cavated by Soviet archaeologists in the
Tajik SSR (see article page 28).
Photo © Institute of Oriental Studies of the USSR Academy
of Sciences, Moscow
Below: Bearded head in the style of the
Nok civilization ofNigeria. Since most ob¬
jects of the Nok civilization were found at
alluvial sites in which stratigraphy is im¬
possible because of landslides, there is
little certain archaeological data about
them. The use of carbon 14 and ther¬
moluminescence dating techniques (see
article page 12) proposed a period for the
Nok civilization ranging from 500 BC to ±
500 AD.
Photo © Université Catholique de Louvain. De Grunne
Collection
El Templo Mayor
The Great Temple of the Aztecs
in the heart of Mexico City
by Eduardo Matos Moctezuma
ON the night of 21 February 1978,
workers of the Light and Power
Company were digging on the
comer of Guatemala and Argentina
Streets in the centre of Mexico City. After
breaking the thick concrete surface and
penetrating about two metres down, they
encountered a hard stone which put a
stop to further progress. On removing the
clay adhering to it they found that the
stone was covered with a series of reliefs,
and decided to suspend operations until
the next day. A telephone call to the Office
of Salvage Archaeology of the National In¬
stitute of Anthropology and History led to
the despatch of a team of archaeologists
to identify the find. On 23 February it was
established that on part of the stone was
a piece of sculpture showing a face in pro¬
file with adornments on the head.
Salvage operations continued until the
27th under the supervision of the ar¬
chaeologists. An enormous monolith,
3.25 metres in diameter, was uncovered.
Its upper surface bore a sculptured
representation of a decapitated, naked
woman, whose arms and legs were
separated from the torso. Clearly this was
Coyolxauhqui, a lunar deity and sister of
Huitzilopochtli, the Aztec god of war who,
according to legend, killed his sister in
single combat on the hill of Coatepec.
This discovery marked the start of the
1 Great Temple Project. From the outset it
was planned in three principal phases.
This enabled us to apply the theory and
methods that would give us a clearer pic¬
ture of the chief temple of the Aztecs or
Mexicas, who settled on the little islands
in the lake of Texcoco around 1325 and
later became subject to the lordship of
Azcapotzalco, before achieving in¬
dependence around 1428. They then .
became an expansionist community and
: conquered large areas of central America,
until in 1 521 they succumbed to the domi¬
nion of the Spaniards who under Hernán
Cortés conquered Mexico during the six¬
teenth century and destroyed the Aztec
city of Tenochtitlán, and with it the city's
Great Templeel Templo Mayor.
The project was carried out in three ^
phases.
Below, the Coyolxauhqui Stone, 3.25
metres in diameter, whose accidental
discovery in 1978, in the heart of Mexico
City, was to lead to the comprehensive
excavation of the ancient Aztec Great
Temple of Tenochtitlán. The stone
depicts the dismembered body of the
goddess Coyolxauhqui, a moon goddess,
who, according to myth, was defeated in
battle, slain and dismembered by her
brother Huitzilopochtli, god of war and of
the sun.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The first phase consisted in assembling
all available information about the Great
Temple, both from historical sources and
from reports of previous archaeological in¬
vestigations, either on the site or on near¬
by sites. On the basis of this information,
a general plan covering both theoretical
and practical aspects was drawn up.
The second phase consisted of the ex¬
cavations proper, which were begun on 20
March 1978 and completed in November
1 982. Suitable techniques were employed
to ensure adequate control of the excava¬
tion process, the area being divided up in¬
to 2-metre-square grids. The site was also
divided into three sections, each supervis¬
ed by an archaeologist and his assistants.
Support units included a team of restorers
with a field laboratory, as well as
biologists, chemists, geologists and other
specialists from the Department of
Prehistory. There were also photographic
laboratories, a design section and a sec¬
tion for controlling the excavated material.
The third phase comprises the study
and analysis of the material recovered in
the preceding phase. After four years'
continuous work, the first two phases
have been completed, and we are now
engaged on the third phase which will
take longer.
We shall now summarize the results of
nearly five years of excavations and of the
investigations currently being carried out.
Architecture Until a few years ago
the chief sources of information about the
Great Temple were the accounts of
sixteenth-century chroniclers. Now,
thanks to archaeology, we have the tem¬
ple before our eyes, and we can see that
in fact the chroniclers' descriptions cor¬
respond very closely to what they saw or
to what the indigenous people told them.
Thanks to archaeology we have also been
able to learn about very early periods in
the temple's history, of which even the
last generations of Mexicas knew nothing.
The main façade faced west. The tem¬
ple stood on a vast platform, with a base
of four elements, including two stairways
leading up to two sanctuariesone on the
south side dedicated to the tutelary war
god Huitzilopochtli, and another on the
north side to Tlaloc, the god of water, rain
and fertility.
For various reasons the temple was
repeatedly enlarged. For instance, the city
of Tenochtitlán suffered from flooding,
which made it necessary to raise the level
of its buildings, as well as from structural
faults due to the instability of the terrain.
Again we know from historical sources
that certain rulers ordered a new temple to
be raised on top of the existing one, so
that different construction Epochs are
Plan © Scientific American, New York
superimposed upon each other. We now
know that the temple was enlarged on all
four sides at least seven times. There
were also four enlargements of the main
façade.
We shall now briefly describe each of
these construction Epochs, except for
Epoch I, which was located inside Epoch
II and was in a state of such deterioration
that it would be pointless to describe it.
The Roman figures indicate total
enlargements on all four sides and, if
followed by a letter, enlargements of the
main façade only.
Epoch II This structure is notable for
the fact that its upper part is remarkably
complete. We can see remains of the two
stone sanctuaries with some of the stucco
(mixture of sand and lime) which covered
them. Facing the entrance to the sanc¬
tuary of Huitzilopochtli is the sacrificial
stone. On the top step, in line with this
stone, is a head with a glyph, or carved
pictograph, of two rabbits above it, cor¬
responding to the year 1390.
Inside the sanctuary a platform runs
from north to south, in the middle of which
there is a small altar on which an image of
the deity must have been placed. On the
Tlaloc (north) side there is a chacmool
polychrome stone sculpture of the divine
messenger responsible for carrying the
offering into the sanctuary. The pillars at
the entrance to the sanctuary are still
decorated with mural paintings of black
and white circles (perhaps depicting the
god's eyes) on blue and red bands. Below
these are alternating vertical black and
white bands. Inside can be seen the plat- ^
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
* V
The great temple of Tenochtitlán
The Templo Mayor, or Great Temple of
the Mexicas, the people of the Aztec city
of Tenochtitlán, was a monument to the
power of the Aztec empire. Shrines
dedicated to Tlaloc (the god of water, rain
and fertility) and to Huitzilopochtli (the
god of war and of the sun) crowned the
temple reflecting the dependence of the
economy of the Mexicas on agriculture
and on tribute collected by conquest. Ex¬
cavation revealed seven major epochs of
construction (indicated by Roman
numerals on plan, opposite page). The
earliest epoch to be excavated, Epoch II,
dates from about 1390 AD and was found
almost intact. The last construction
epoch, Epoch VII, was razed to its founda¬
tions by the Spanish conquistadores.
Above, a view of the site from the south¬
west corner of the façade. The Coyolx¬
auhqui Stone can be seen (centre of
photo) surrounded by a metal framework.
In the foreground a sculptured snake
(often used as a symbol of Huit
zilopochtli) flanks the stairway leading to
the war god's shrine. Further to the left
along the façade are two sculptured frogs
(not easily visible on this photo). Frogs
were often used to represent Tlaloc the
rain god. Left, artist Ned Seidler's draw¬
ing depicts the complexity of the edifice.
Facing west, the temple rose to a height
of some 60 metres, with twin stairways
leading up to the double shrines. Ex¬
cavating a major site in the centre of a
major modern city is no easy task and it
was even more difficult in Mexico City
where the water table is only four to five
metres below street level. City traffic
often slowed the work down and thirteen
buildings had to be removed before ex¬
cavation could begin. However, the urban
location had some advantages.
Specialists, including city planners, ar¬
chitects, soil scientists, ethnologists,
historians, ornithologists and ich¬
thyologists were available for advice and
many students volunteered their help.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Plundering the past
The looting of archaeological sites and
the Illegal export and import of cultural
property has become a booming
worldwide business worth an estimated
3,000 million dollars a year. The principal
victims of the art traffickers are the
developing countries who often lack the
resources to introduce effective controls.
Not only are priceless artefacts being
lost, but whole pages of history are being
erased by the robbers' indiscriminate
destruction of archaeological sites.
Unesco has taken the lead in the fight to
eliminate this illicit trade, notably through
the establishment of the Convention on
the Means of Prohibiting and Preventing
the Illicit Import, Export and Transfer of
Ownership of Cultural Property (1970)
and the Convention for the Protection of
the World Cultural and Natural Heritage
(1972). Photo shows part of an exhibition
of artefacts that had been illegally ex¬
ported from Ecuador and which were
recovered after a six-year legal battle in
the Italian courts. Heldin Quito, Ecuador,
in May 1983, the exhibition was entitled
Ecuador Recovers an Important
Fragment of its Cultural Memory.
form on which the image of the god must
have stood. This Epoch is mostly earlier
than 1428, the year when the Mexicas
became independent of Azcapotzalco.
Epoch III To this Epoch belong well-
made stairways, and the facings of the
steps of the base are still upright. Eight
sculptures of standard-bearers were
found in recumbent positions on the steps
of the stairway on the Huitzilopochtli side.
These figures may have adorned the
edifice, but when a new construction
Epoch was begun they were collected and
ceremonially placed on the stairway
where they were discovered. On the back
wall of the platform, on the Huitzilopochtli
side, is carved the glyph "4 Reed", which
corresponds to the year 1431.
Epoch IV This Epoch, with its addi¬
tions, is one of the richest in decorative
elements. The main platform was
decorated on all four sides with braziers
and serpent heads. The braziers on the
Tlaloc side are adorned with the face of
the god, while those on the Huitzilopochtli
side bear a knot, a symbol of the warrior
deity. Various offerings were found below
the braziers and serpents.
Epoch IV b is an addition to the main
(west) façade which was very rich in
decorative elements. It consists of the
vast platform on which the Great Temple
stands. This platform had a continuous
perron, at both ends of which enormous
serpents with undulating bodies and huge
heads were unearthed, still bearing some
of the paint which originally covered them.
The stairs leading to the platform are inter¬
rupted only by a small altar flanked by two
frogs standing on the stone flags of which
the altar is constructed. This altar is in line
with the middle of the stairs that once led
to the upper part of the temple dedicated
to Tlaloc. On the Huitzilopochtli side, op¬
posite the stairs leading to the sanctuary
of this god, a two-metre-wide stone block
decorated with serpents forms part of the
top of the platform. The base formed by
the remains of the two stairways which led
to the upper part includes four serpent
heads, one at each end and two in the
middle, marking the junction of the two
halves of the temple. In the middle of the
platform, on the Huitzilopochtli side, is the
place where the monumental stone
sculpture of the god's sister, Coyolxauh¬
qui, was found.
Chronologically, we believe that Epoch
IV corresponds broadly to the reign of the
Aztec ruler Moctezuma I, because the
glyph "1 rabbit", equivalent to the year
1454, is carved on the back part of the
platform on the Huitzilopochtli side.
Coyolxauhqui and the serpents may have
been added during the reign of Axayacatl.
Another glyph on the south side of the
edifice, with the symbol "3 house", cor¬
responds to 1469, the year in which Ax-
ayacatl's reign began.
Epoch V All that has been
discovered of this period is the stuccoed
main platform and part of the stone floor of
the ceremonial precinct.
Epoch VI This is the last Epoch but
one. Its vestiges consist of part of the main
platform. A wall of the main west façade is
decorated with three serpent heads.
Epoch VII This is the last Epoch of
the Great Temple and the one the
Spaniards saw. All that remains of it are
part of the slab floor of the ceremonial
precinct, some traces of the temple site,
and part of the platform on the north side.
Offerings During nearly five years of
excavations, some 7,000 objectsthe re¬
mains of almost a hundred offerings
were unearthed. These offerings were
found in three distinct places in stone
cists whose sides and bottoms bore
traces of stucco, inside movable stone
boxes with stone lids, and actually in the
fill of stone and earth covering a construc¬
tion Epoch.
It may be said that, as a general rule,
the manner in which objects were placed
in the offerings was not haphazard but
premeditated,.conforming to some kind of
symbolism which has still to be inter¬
preted. In other words these objects and
their positions correspond to a language.
Thus in some offerings certain objects oc¬
cupy the lower position, while others are
always found higher up. We also noticed
that the objects were placed facing in a
certain direction. Both the offerings on the
west (main façade) side as well as those at
the back of the temple faced the spot
where the sun sets, whereas those found
in the middle of the edifice, in its northern
and southern façades, were facing north
and south respectively.
Offerings 7 and 61 , located towards the
middle of the edifice on the south side and
on the north side, respectively, contained
the same arrangement of objectsat the
base, seashells facing north to south;
above them, crocodiles; and at the top,
seated deities which we thought to be
representations of Xiuhtecutli, an ancient
fire-god, centre of the universe and of the
hearth. To the right of these gods was a
coral, and to the left an earthenware vase
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
bearing an effigy of the god Tlaloc.
Perhaps this arrangement means that the
shells represent the sea, the crocodiles
the earthly level, and Xiuhtecutii and
Tlaloc the heavenly level. The same ar¬
rangement is found in offerings 1 1 and 17,
the first located in the main façade bet¬
ween the two serpent heads marking the
junction of the temples of Tlaloc and Huit¬
zilopochtli, and the second at the back
where the two edifices are joined. Both
are placed in stone-walled cists and, apart
from being very similar in their contents,
the objects are arranged in a similar order.
Some of the objects unearthed were of
purely Mexica origin; others came from
tributary areas. The former include
sculptures of seated ancients wearing on¬
ly the "maxtatl" or loincloth and a head¬
dress with two protuberances. They are
thought to represent Xiuhtecutii. Others
are effigies of the god Tlaloc sculpted in
"tezontle" (volcanic stone) and in other
kinds of stone. There are also representa¬
tions of coiled serpents, serpent heads
and rattlesnakes carved in obsidian,
stone braziers with knots, and, of course,
the magnificent representations of
seashells which are real works of art
although, like the Coyolxauhqui and ser¬
pent heads adorning the temple façade,
they did not figure among the offerings.
Interesting objects from the tributary
areas figure in greater numbers among
the offerings from Epoch IV onwards
(around 1454) when the Mexicas were in
full expansion. They include a large quan¬
tity of masks and figures in the Mezcala
style (from what is now the State of Guer¬
rero), of various types and sizes, alabaster
pieces from the Puebla region repre¬
senting deer heads, arrows and seated
deities. There are two magnificent orange
ceramic funerary urns from the Gulf
Coast. Inside them were the remains of
burnt bones, necklaces, and other ob¬
jects. The great variety of seashells,
fishbones, sawfish bills and corals come
from the Gulf and Pacific coasts. So do
the crocodiles and jaguars, which may
have come from Veracruz or Tabasco.
Another group of objects can definitely
be attributed to societies very much
earlier than the Mexica. Such are the
Teotihuacán masks, which can be dated
around the year 400 AD, and an Olmec
mask. Pétrographie analysis has shown
that the latter originated in the area now
occupied by the States of Puebla, Oaxaca
and Guerrero. It is believed to be the
oldest object discovered (800 BC).
We can say that most of the objects
represent Tlaloc or symbols associated
with him, including such objects
associated with the sea as canoes and
fishes. But there are also objects
associated with Huitzilopochtli, a god who
is only represented symbolically, in the
form of braziers with a knot, skulls, "tec-
patl" sacrificial knives with eyes and teeth
of conch shell and, generally, objects from
tributary areas, the spoils of military con¬
quest. All this confirms our thesis of the
existence of an agricultural and warrior
people who depended for their
sustenance on both agriculture and
tribute.
EDUARDO MATOS MOCTEZUMA, of
Mexico, is general director of the Centro de In¬
vestigaciones y Estudios Superiores en An¬
tropología Social at Tlalpán. Before beginning
the excavation of the Great Temple in Mexico
City, which he describes in this article and
which was carried out under his supervision,
he had done extensive fieldwork on the pre-
Columbian sites of Mexico.
EAGLE WARRIOR. Nearly two metres in
height, this pottery statue of a soldier of
the eagle order is one of the most
remarkable finds made at the Great Tem¬
ple. There were two main ocders of Aztec
soldiery, the eagles and the jaguars.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
From the
Throne of Stone
A treasure-trove of Greco-Bactrian art
by Boris A. Litvinskiy
and Igor R. Pichikiyan
In this silver bridle ornament depicting
the gorgon, the monster ofancient Greek
mythology has been transformed Into a
sweet maiden. The object is an illustra¬
tion of the synthesis of Greek and Indian
art known as the Gandhara style. The
discovery of Indian silver coins and of
many ivory objects in central Asia shows
the existence of economic links between
Bactria and India in the 1st century BC.
Finely wrought ivory sword-sheath,
above, belongs to a spectacular treasure
found by Soviet archaeologists at Takhti
Sanghin in central Asia. The treasure has
illuminated some dark corners in the
history of the ancient land of Bactria, im¬
portant as a meeting place for east-west
overland trade and as a centre of artistic
crosscurrents. The sheath is decorated
with a relief carving of a Hon seizing a
deer. The lion 's head is depicted frontally
with tightly clenched teeth while the deer
is shown in profile, its legs bent in sub¬
mission (detail, above right). The carving
is thought to be an allegorical depiction of
a victorious conqueror, king or god, and
his submissive subjects. Beneath the lion
is a highly stylized scene showing a feline
predator attacking a wild sheep. Typical
of Achaemenid Persia, the sheath dates
from the early 5th century BC and is
276 mm long.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
OVER a hundred years ago, in 1878,
three Bukhara merchants en route
for India halted in the oasis of
Kobadian (in the south of what is now Ta¬
jikistan), where they bought a mass of ob¬
jects and coins from an "old fortress", on
the promontory at the confluence of two
rivers. The objects and coins fell into the
hands of Indian jewellers, then those of
English collectors and finally, known as the
"treasure of the Oxus", ended up in the
British Museum in London.'
The objects comprising the treasure of
the Oxus are of superb artistic quality. They
made it clear that ancient Bactria, whose
territory covered what are today the
southern regions of Tajikistan, part of
Uzbekistan and the north of Afghanistan,
held the promise of major historical and ar¬
tistic discoveries. The laconic remarks of
ancient authors about the wealth and power
of the Bactrian kingdom were confirmed.
Descriptions of the site where the treasure
of the Oxus was discovered suggest that it
lay among the ruins of a city at the con¬
fluence of two rivers, the Vakhsh and the
Piandj, which meet to form the Oxus (Amu
Darya). The Techik-Tach mountain range
runs close alongside the western bank of the
Vakhsh. An ancient caravan route once
passed through the narrow valley. Ar¬
chaeologists have explored this site many
times and have found traces of two ancient
cities: Takhti Kuvad ("Throne of Kuvad")
and, five kilometres further north, Takhti
Sanghin ("Throne of Stone") where ex¬
cavations in 1928 and 1956 did not yield in¬
teresting results.
In 1976, the archaeological mission to
southern Tajikistan organized by the In¬
stitute of Oriental Studies of the USSR
Academy of Sciences, the Academy of
Sciences of the Tajik SSR and the Her¬
mitage Museum, Leningrad, decided to
begin new excavations at Takhti Sanghin.
Our aim was not, of course, to locate the
site where the treasure of the Oxus had been
found. Takhti Sanghin's location near an
old caravan route, its powerful fortifica¬
tions, and the scattered remains of ancient
columns, together with our intuition as ar¬
chaeologists, were enough to convince us to
begin work again on its ruins. We pitched-
our tents and erected our portable chalets.
Dozens of Tajik students and specialists
from Moscow got down to work.
The central part of the ancient city the
citadelwas rectangular (165 by 237
metres). It was surrounded by a six-metre-
high wall, with sturdy towers at each cor-
9.Q
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
ner, and a deep ditch. Two walls running
from the mountains towards the river, 500
metres north and south of the citadel, mark¬
ed the limits of the city.
A monumental building has been ex¬
cavated on a hill in the western part of the
citadel. It was almost certainly a temple,
since it contained a votive stone altar
dedicated to Oxus. At the centre was a vast
white hall with four columns. It was enclos¬
ed on three sides by two lines of galleries.
To the east (where the great main entrance
stood) was a colonnaded portal.
The architecture of this massive building
(the walls of the hall were four metres
thick), which we called the temple of Oxus,
suggests that it was built in the late fourth
or early third century BC. Its plan recalls
that of Persian fire temples; it is built of
local materials; its columns, pilasters, altars
and other details of the stonework are in
Hellenistic style.
Offerings were brought to the temple and
left in specially excavated ditches or in other
receptacles. Later, they were piled in cor¬
ners of the corridors which were subse¬
quently blocked up and became secret
treasuries.
We had the pleasure of discovering these
treasures. As the five metres of fill were
removed, hundreds of works of the hitherto
little-known Greco-Bactrian art appeared
before our eyes: bronzes with a dark green
patina, gleaming white alabaster sculptures,
glittering gold. We also unearthed many
carved ivory objects. In ten seasons of ex¬
cavations, 5,000 specimens have been
unearthed and restored.
Above all we were delighted to discover
works of art dating from the sixth-fourth
centuries BC, the period when the
Achaemenid dynasty ruled in Persia, which
recall those of the treasure of the Oxus. An
ivory scabbard for a short sword is ex-
A striking example ofcultural synthesis in
central Asia over 2,000 years ago, this
votive stone altar is surmounted by a
bronze figurine of a Silenus playing a
double flute. Carved on the base is an in¬
scription which reads, "After making a
vow, Atrossok dedicates it to Oxus."
Although the inscription is in ancient
Greek, the two names cited in it are of Ira¬
nian origin. It is thought that Atrossok,
who dedicated the altar with its Greek in¬
scription and Greek figure to the localgod
Oxus, may have been a Bactrian official of
a fire cult.
. pressively decorated with a relief carving of
a lion holding a deer between its outstretch¬
ed paws (see photos on preceding double
page). In size and shape (276 mm) it forms
a pendant to a scabbard from the Oxus
treasure.
Other works of art from Achaemenid
Persia whose manufacture recalls pieces in
the treasure of the Oxus have also been
discovered in the temple. They include a
rhyton (a drinking cup) the extremity of
which depicts a crouching lion, and a
horseman's sword-hilt topped by a griffon.
More than fifty gold plaques have also been
found.
The objects belonging to the next
chronological period (late fourth-early
second century BC) initiate the extremely
interesting and until recently unknown
Hellenistic period of Bactrian culture. In
date and place of manufacture (Asia Minor,
Bactria, the Scythian steppes) they are akin
to specimens in the treasure of the Oxus.
Clay and alabaster sculptures, the pro¬
totypes of which are found in the plastic
schools of Asia Minor, are purely
Hellenistic works of art. Besides many por¬
traits of Greek and Oriental sovereigns
wearing diadems, we have unearthed
sculptures of maidens (kore) depicted in im¬
petuous movement and a statue of Apollo
(the "Apollo of Takhti Sanghin").
A special place among all these
discoveries is held by a miniature ivory bust
of Alexander the Great, a new addition to
the rare Hellenistic effigies which have
come down to us of the warrior king who
was depicted by Lysippus, Leochares and
other great artists. Alexander's effigies on
coinage are probably based on a monumen¬
tal statue, which has not survived, in which
Lysippus depicted him as Heracles wearing
a lion mask with the paws crossed on his
breast. The iconography of the ivory por¬
trait of Takhti Sanghin in which Alexander
is shown frontally is taken from this same
model. Because of certain differences from
the coinage, in which Alexander is generally
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Hunting scenes carved on the side of an
ivory casket illustrate the costume,
weaponry, horses' trappings and riding
skills of the Yueh-chih, conquerors of the
Greco-Bactrian kingdom (late 2nd-early
1st century BC).
shown in profile, this portrait is unique (see
colour photo page 22).
The discovery in the heart of central Asia
of this "masquerade" in which Alexander
is depicted with the attributes of Heracles is
particularly important because Alexander-
imagery played an important role in Greco-
Bactrian art, just as it did in Buddhist art
and in the art of Gandhara, in what is now
northwestern Pakistan.
Another work of the highest quality is an
original depiction of a combat between
Heracles and Silenus, an extremely rare
subject in the plastic art of Antiquity, which
adorns a Greek ceremonial sword.
Among the many reliefs embellishing the
Greek sword scabbards is a fantastic depic¬
tion of a female creature with the tail of a
fish, horse's hooves and a bird's wings. One
might think that an ancient Greek sea
divinity had been transformed into a
nymph-follower of the god of the river
Oxus. This image dating from the second
century BC, the period when the Greco-
Bactrian kingdom collapsed, is a proof of
the Hellenization of Bactrian culture and of
an important measure of the influence of
Antiquity in Greco-Bactrian art.
Probably from the same period is a
hemispherical gold plaque with a relief im¬
age of three panthers in a circle; each biting
the one before it (the "Round of the Pan¬
thers"). This is a fine example of the
"animal style" characteristic of Scytho-
Siberian art.
The abundance of objects made of ivory,
a rare and extremely costly material, is
evidence of close economic and commercial
relations with India, which are also borne
out by the extremely rare oval and rec¬
tangular punched coins which were struck
in India from the fifth to the second century
BC when the dynasty of Nanda and the
Mauryas held sway. Other ivory objects
found in the temple are incontestably works
of Gandhara-Indian style.
The hypothesis concerning the cultural
and artistic contacts which may have existed
between the Parthians and the Bactrians has
been put forward many times. The Takhti
Sanghin sculptures and almost seventy
silver coins, imitations of drachmas of the
Parthian king Phraates IV (36-2BC), sup¬
port this conjecture.
Some of the objects we have unearthed
attest to permanent relations with the
Scythian-Siberian world. Apart from the
gold plaque described above there is a
bronze disc with an image ("the Scythian
holding 2 horses by the bridle") and several
thousand bronze and iron arrowheads
which must have been brought to the temple
as offerings.
The discoveries at the temple of Oxus
thus reveal with precision the components
of Greco-Bactrian art: these elements are
Oriental (original), Hellenistic (secondary)
and that of Gandhara (a result of the Greco-
Indian synthesis).
Most of our finds have analogies with ob¬
jects in the treasure of the Oxus and in the
metropolitan Iranian art of the
Achaemenid period. There are many
reasons to think that the treasure of the
Oxus is organically related to the temple of
Oxus, that it is part of the temple treasure.
Exploration of Takhti Sanghin is going
ahead hand in hand with that of other Bac¬
trian monuments. On the opposite,
southern bank of the Amu Darya in
Afghanistan where the Kocha Darya flows
into it, our French colleagues have brought
to light an entire Greek city the ruins of
which are known as Ai Khanum. The ob¬
jects from Ai Khanum and those discovered
at the temple of Oxus complement each
other and give a fair idea of Greco-Bactrian
culture, its origins and extensions.
From a vast amount of material, science
has been able to shed further light on the
role of local tradition in the genesis of the
Hellenistic Bactrian culture. Study of this
material has informed us about the many-
sided relationship between the peoples who
had inhabited this region and various an¬
cient civilizations (from India to the
Mediterranean). The works of art
discovered in the temple of Oxus and
reintegrated in the cultural treasure of
humanity brilliantly illustrate the extent
and intensity of these links.
The synthesis of these civilizations was
not confined to the field of material culture.
On the right bank of the Oxus lived people
who spoke and wrote Greek and worship¬
ped the Hellenic gods; a syncretic Greco-
Bactrian culture was created there. A Greek
theatre and gymnasium, and other
specifically Hellenic buildings, have come
to light at Ai Khanum.
The literary, scientific and philosophical
writings of Greek authors were, it seems,
widespread in Bactria even at a later period.
It is possible that elements of this culture
survived the fall of the Kushan empire.
This is for the time being no more than a
hypothesis. It is highly important to con¬
tinue research, for the discovery of even
faint traces of ancient cultural traditions
which may have survived to the Middle
Ages would throw a new light on the genesis
of the science and philosophy of the Muslim
east.
BORIS A. LITVINSKIY, Sower specialist in
the cultures of central Asia, is a corresponding
member of the Academy of Sciences of the
Tajik SSR and director of the department of
historical and cultural relations between the
Soviet and the non-Soviet Orient at the In¬
stitute of Oriental Studies of the USSR
Academy of Sciences. Among his many
published works are "The Tombs of
Ferghana" (4 vols., 1972-1978) and "Tepai-
shah. Culture and Contacts of the Bactria of
the Kushans" (1983) written in collaboration
with A.V. Sedov.
IGOR R. PICHIKIYAN, Soviet archaeologist,
is a scientific collaborator with the Institute of
Oriental Studies of the USSR Academy of
Sciences. A specialist in the problems of the
art and ancient history of central Asia, he has
published over 100 studies on the culture of
this region.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
OENJODARO
Threatened centre
of an ancient civilization
by Syed A. Naqvi
An Incomparable monument to a great
civilization that flourished in the Indus
Valley some 5,000 years ago, the vast
ruins of the city of Moenjodaro are
located in the Sind Province of present-
day Pakistan, some 400 kilometres north
of Karachi. Sometimes referred to as "the
Manhattan of the Bronze Age ' ' because of
its extraordinarily modern, scientifically-
planned layout, Moenjodaro, even at the
height of its splendour, has always been
at risk from flooding by the Indus.
Preserved for centuries beneath a protec¬
tive layer of soil, the excavated city (the
excavations began in 1922) now faces
two additional threats: a rising water table
and corrosion by salts. Since the 1960s,
Unesco has been collaborating with the
Government of Pakistan in preserving
this outstanding site. With the aid of
Pakistani experts, Unesco has establish¬
ed a master plan for the work ofpreserva¬
tion, launched an international fund-
raising campaign and included Moen¬
jodaro on Its World Heritage List. Above,
a view of the site of Moenjodaro
dominated by a Buddhist stupa of more
recent construction.
MOENJODARO, a metropolis of the
five-thousand-year-old Indus
Valley civilization in Pakistan,
presents the earliest example of town-
planning and a setting for the future. Even
in the limited area laid bare by the ar¬
chaeologist's spade, it is like walking
through a fossilized embryo of Manhattan.
In the lower city, we find the crisscross
grid-iron system of street layout, a broad
boulevard over nine metres wide, running
north to south and crossed at right angles
by somewhat smaller east-west streets.
The blocks of residential houses between
are served by narrow lanes.
The prime considerations in planning
the houses were safety and comfort.
Avoiding the risk of heavy traffic on the
main streets, the doors of the houses
usually opened on to the side-lanes. In¬
terior courtyards provided light and air,
and windows were screened with grilles of
terra-cotta or alabaster. The thickness of
the walls of the houses in Moenjodaro
proves the existence of at least two-
storey-high structures. Most houses had
stairways that led either to the second
storey or to the roof, often used in
Pakistan and elsewhere in the East as a
cool sleeping place in summer. Besides
other basic amenities, many houses also
had wells for water supply which were lin¬
ed with brickwork and had protective
revetments at their head to prevent ac¬
cidents to children and domestic animals.
The grid layout and residential architec¬
ture are not the only indications of the
perception and care that went into the
planning of Moenjodaro. Never before,
and not until Greek and Roman times,
was so much attention paid to sanitation
and civic facilities. The water-discharge
sluices from the houses first collected the
refuse in small cesspits lined with bricks
at the base of the walls, from which the
dirty water was led through conduits to the
main drains which ran along the streets
below pavement level and were covered
with sturdy bricks. This drainage system
was connected to the larger sewerage
outlets, also covered at the top, which
finally led the dirty water outside the
populated area.
A few hundred metres to the west of this
densely built part of the city, excavations
have revealed some most conspicuous
monuments located on an artificial hill
some seven to fourteen metres high. The
Great Bath, a highly complex brick struc¬
ture, symbolizes a triumph of engineering
at that time. The pool, 1 1 .9 metres long, 7
metres wide and 1.9 metres deep, was
made watertight by an inner facing of
bricks set on edge in gypsum mortar
which was laid over a layer of asphalt 2.5
cm thick trowelled on to double brick
walls. The floor sloped to an outlet that led
in turn to a corbelled arched drain. This
corbelled arch was one of the earliest
achievements of architectural engineer-
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
U a*
:»-
Sfc
Photos © Raoul Zamora, Paris
ing, spanning an opening without using
wooden beams. (The possibilities of span¬
ning wider openings were extended later
on by the discovery of the keystone, and
in our times developed still further with the
use of reinforced concrete.)
A second architectural feature is the
podium of the great Granary situated on
the western flank of the mound. The
podium, made of solid brick square-
shaped platforms separated by a gridiron
of straight and narrow passages, is
thought to have been covered by a floor of
wooden boards, and probably the
superstructure was also made of wood. It
has been suggested that it served as a
State Treasury to which bullock carts
brought sacks of grain from farmers, since
in those days coins had not yet been
minted. A quantity of charred grains of
wheat collected from the excavations puts
the nature of the building beyond any
doubt. A third important building in this
area is the Pillared Hall. It has twenty
pillars and encloses a small courtyard,
and probably served as the centre of
administration.
The purpose of some of Moenjodaro's
sophisticated structures is one of the
many questions that still remain
unanswered about the city. The discovery
in 1922 of so complete and advanced a
metropolis came as an immense surprise
to the archaeologists who never had any
inkling that such a full-fledged civilization
existed in the Indus Valley as far back as
2500 BC. It was not until 1920 when ex¬
cavations started at Harappa, about 640
kilometres north of Moenjodaro, that the
existence of a whole network of such
"modern" ancient cities was suspected.
When Harappa, the mother city of the
Indus Valley , civilizationbecause of
which this civilization is also known as the
"Harappan culture" was discovered in
the second half of the nineteenth century,
it was found to be already robbed of its an¬
cient burnt bricks by the engineers laying
the railway line between Lahore and
Multan and, of course, by local villagers
hunting for easy building material for their
own houses. Since then, archaeologists in
the Indian sub-continent have located
nearly 1,000 other Harappan sites. They
show a remarkable similarity of cultural
deposits and cover an astonishing
geographical spread, from the Arabian
Sea to the foothills of the Himalayas and
from the eastern border of Iran to the
vicinity of the Ganges Valley. This area
was much larger than the combined size
of contemporary cultures in Mesopotamia
and the Valley of the Nile.
What was the mainstay of the life of the
Indus Valley people in that remote past?
The archaeological evidence shows that
they were primarily farmers, growing
grains, vegetables and cotton, and cattle
husbandry was central to the farm
economy. Their life-style was simple but
The Great Bath is undoubtedly the most
spectacular building of Moenjodaro. Built
like most of the city's buildings in brick,
the 12-metre-long bath itself was made
completely watertight by the application
of a layer of bitumen between two layers
of brick pointed with lime mortar. The
sloping floor of the bath was equipped
with an ingenious draining system.
A seal found at Moenjodaro. At top is an
example of the pictographic writing of the
Indus civilization. So far all attempts to
decipher this writing have failed.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
not lacking in rich goods. They used cop¬
per and bronze for some tools and
weapons, and occasionally worked gold
and silver with other materials into the
beads for their jewellery. Among the
beads some were skilfully fashioned out of
rare semi-precious stones such as agate,
carnelian and lapis lazuli. At the same
time, the bulk of their artifacts consisted of
bone, shell, faience, flint, clay, and other
locally abundant materials. Their han¬
diwork in more vulnerable organic
substances has not survived, and we are
left to guess what kind of furniture they us¬
ed or what varieties of textile patterns they
preferred. The remains of the dyers'
workshop at Moenjodaro and certain pat¬
terns depicted, on dresses worn by
sculptured figures do, however, suggest
that they liked colourful clothing, often
embroidered or printed.
A further striking aspect of this ancient
civilization was the extent of standardiza¬
tion. In architecture, building bricks were
of standard size, 27.94 cm in length, 1 3.42
cm in breadth, and . 6.35 cm thick.
Drainage and sewer systems were stan¬
dard in pattern. The private houses were
generally standardized in their plans and
dimensions and only special structures,
possibly public buildings, were treated
differently but within the framework of the
city plan. Above all, the existence of strict¬
ly controlled weights and measures
throughout the Indus Valley civilization
distinguishes it from other contemporary
civilizations.
The King-Priest. This 18-cm-high
statuette, carved in steatite and dating
from about 2500 BC, is one of the few
sculptures in stone found at Moenjodaro.
The people respected the rule of law
which helped them to develop an
egalitarian society on such a vast scale
about 5,000 years ago, an achievement
unparalleled in the history of mankind. By
inference, therefore, the Indus Valley
possessed an efficient mechanism of con¬
trol, means of communication and
transportation and an administrative
framework free of such grandiose struc-
Movement of salts into the ruins
°0,D06ff
'Drawing Unesco
A. Salt-impregnated water
rises from the water table
by capillary action.
B. Salty water also
infiltrates through
surrounding earth and
débris which has yet to be
cleared away.
C Dust-laden winds carry
salts and deposit them on
bricks. Rain helps the salts
penetrate the brickwork.
D. Accumulated salts
within the bricks erode the
walls.
Eaten away by salts, the walls of Moen¬
jodaro are slowly crumbling into dust.
The salts are absorbed from the water
table which has risen considerably as a
result of the rise, through silting, of the
river bed of the Indus and of irrigation in
the surrounding plains. The water table,
which in 1922 was at a depth of about 8
metres, has risen to between 1.52 metres
of the surface in October and 3.66 metres
in May. The water impregnates the brick
walls by capillaryaction and in other ways
(see diagram) thus beginning a con¬
tinuous cycle of saturation, evaporation
and crystallization of the salts which
causes the walls to disintegrate. Control
measures envisaged include the lowering
of the water table, by pumping or drain¬
ing, and the complete excavation and ex¬
ternal cleaning of the walls coupled with
leaching out of the accumulated salts.
tures as forts, palaces or great temples
serving as centres of authoritarian rule. It
was here in those ancient times that a con¬
cept of some kind of Government of the
people, by the people, for the people was
evolved, laying the seed of democratic
rulesa cherished goal of us all today.
Of course the proof of this inference lies
in the results of further research into the
socio-cultural pattern of the Indus Valley
civilization and particularly the decipher¬
ing of its enigmatic script which appears
on seals and sealings discovered in the In¬
dus Valley. The epigraphists and
linguistic experts of the world have made
many attempts to decipher this script in
the last sixty years. An account of their ef¬
forts would make a long tale of trials and
errors. The net gain of their researches so
far has been recognition of nearly 350 dif¬
ferent pictographs and the fact that the
script was written from right to left. But in
the absence of long texts even the use of
computer technology has not yielded any
positive results and one can only hope for
a day when a bilingual inscription will be
discovered making it possible to unravel
the mysteries of the Harappan culture in
the same way as the Rosetta Stone did in
Egypt and the Behistun inscription in Iran.
A further insight into the skill of the
people is provided by a wide range of
utilitarian, recreational, artistic and cult
objects made of baked clay, stone,
metals, ivory, conch shell, faience and
other substances. A whole range of pot¬
tery types, most wheel-turned, presents a
multitude of forms, sizes and decorative
features. Amongst the innumerable terra¬
cotta toys, miniature bullock carts with
solid wheels are particularly striking. Such
carts are being used even today around
Moenjodaro. Here we also find the begin¬
nings of a chess-board designed on brick
tiles, with gamesmen made of agate or
ivory.
Who were the founders of this far-
reaching, long-vanished civilization?
Scholars believe that the people of the In¬
dus came down into the valley from the
foothills of the mountains to the west. Of
the early Harappan sites, recent
discoveries at Mehrgarh in Baluchistan,
southeast of the Sulaiman and Kirthar
ranges, show an unbroken sequence of
cultural evolution from the sixth millen¬
nium BC to the mature Harappan culture.
As to the end of this highly developed
civilization around 1500 BC, several
theories have been put forward by ar¬
chaeologists. Some of them attribute it to
the Aryan invaders who swept over the In¬
dus Valley about that time, others con¬
sider it due to a tectonic shift in the
coastline of the Arabian Sea affecting the
entire ecological system of the Valley.
However, further research is needed to
shed light on the causes of the sudden
demise of this great civilization.
The ancient remains of Moenjodaro are
now on the World Heritage List as a monu¬
ment of universal interest and Unesco has
launched an international campaign for
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
their preservation. When . excavations
started at the site in 1922, the structural
remains were in excellent condition. Soon
after they were afflicted by the plague of
waterlogging and the leprosy of salinity.
These two diseases, combined with the
menace of erosion by the River Indus,
posed a grim threat to the very existence
of Moenjodaro. This complex problem re¬
quired not only huge finances which were
beyond the resources of the Government
of Pakistan but also technical know-how
of a multi-disciplinary nature.
At the request of the Government of
Pakistan, the General Conference of
Unesco adopted a resolution at its seven¬
teenth session, authorizing an interna¬
tional campaign for the preservation of
Moenjodaro. In January 1974, the
Director-General of Unesco launched an
Appeal for international solidarity, stating
that " By the generous provision of money,
equipment and services, governments,
public and private individuals will not
merely be helping to save a precious
record of man's past, they will also be
demonstrating and strengthening that in¬
tellectual and moral solidarity on which
true peace must be founded".
Since then, over US$4 million have
been received in the Unesco Trust Fund
from Member States and private sources.
The Government of Pakistan, from its own
resources, has already invested about
US$6 million for the execution of the
Master Plan, which includes schemes for
groundwater control, conservation of
structural remains and the training of the
River Indus, at a total estimated cost of
US$19 million.
The first phase of the groundwater con¬
trol scheme, which envisaged fourteen
tubewells, collector and disposal drains,
and a pump house, has already been
completed. Work on the conservation of
structural remains has also advanced
considerably. The amount required for the
implementation of the River Training
scheme, about US$9 million, has yet to be
collected and work on this project has not
yet begun. The Director-General of
Unesco has, therefore, addressed a
second Appeal to the international com¬
munity urging that "This challenge is
commensurate with the responsibility we
all bear for our common history, to which
Moenjodaro is a moving testimony we
cannot and must not allow to disappear."
SYED A. NAQVI, internationally known ar¬
chaeologist and museologist, was head of the
National Museum of Pakistan, and then
General Director of Pakistan's Department of
Archaeology and Museums. He has excavated
at many Pakistani sites including Moenjodaro,
Taxila and Mansura. In July 1973 he joined
Unesco's Division of Cultural Heritage, which
he has headed since January 1982. He has
been directly responsible for the successful
campaigns for Nubia and Borobudur, as well
as supervising all Unesco's activities for the
preservation of the cultural heritage. Among
his studies on archaeology and ancient art are
The Muslim Art (1966), Gandhara Art (1967)
and 1,400 Years of Quranic Calligraphy
(1973).
Most of the houses atMoenjodaro had in¬
terior wells to provide water for cooking
and washing. Looking at first sight more
like chimneys after excavation of the soil
around them, these wells testify to the
continual rise in the ground occupation
level and provide archaeologists with a
convenient time and depth scale. The in¬
habitants of the city were obliged to add
fresh layers ofbrick at regular intervals to
raise the tops of the wells above the level
of the ground. Some wells have been
found to go right through entire rooms of
earlier houses.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
My life as an archaeologist
by Guo Zhan
WHEN I entered Beijing University
in 1973 to study archaeology, a
whole new world opened up for
me. I received a rigorous training in how to
excavate and carry out archaeological
surveys. Our teachers taught us not only
how to unearth specific parts of ancient
ruins but also principles of excavation work
on large archaeological sites. As fieldwork
I took part in the excavation of the Qin
Dynasty E-fang Palace Ruins in Shanxi, of
Stone Age ruins at Hong Hua Tao in the
middle reaches of the Yangtse River, and
worked on the site of the ancient capital of
Qi City State of the Spring and Autumn
period in Linzi, Shandong Province. Look¬
ing back now, I realize that these ruins
where we beginners were allowed to work
were not of the greatest importance, and yet
working on a real archaeological site gave
me practical experience and awakened in
me a deep interest in my studies.
Apart from fieldwork, we also studied
classical Chinese, ancient Chinese
characters, the ancient history of China,
major archaeological themes from each
period of Chinese history, photography,
cartography, the history of ancient ar¬
chitecture, the history of the different na¬
tionalities, philosophy and political science.
When I graduated in 1976, 1 was assigned
to work in the Science and Technology
Research Institute for Relics Protection af¬
filiated to the State Relics Administration
Bureau. The Institute is chiefly concerned
with the conservation of all kinds of
historical remains using modern
technology, and the preservation and
maintenance of ancient monuments. Along
with some other staff members I was given
the job of launching a brand-new subject:
seismological archaeology. (First of all, we
archaeologists working along the Yangtse
River provided hydrological data relating to
the last 2,000 years as reference material for
the construction of hydrological projects.
Chinese archaeologist Guo Zhan (second
from right) and his colleagues during a
survey of part of the Great Wall in 1976.
The 2,400-kilometre-long Wall is largely
the work of Qin Shihuang, the first
emperor of China (221-210 BC), although
parts of it date back to the 4th century BC.
It was substantially rebuilt later, especial¬
ly in the 15th and 16th centuries.
We thus opened up another new branch of
science, hydrological archaeology.)
In 1976, an earthquake in Hebei Province
literally flattened the city of Tangshan.
Hundreds of thousands of people were in¬
jured or lost their lives, and the after-shocks
threatened the safety of Beijing and another
great city, Tianjin. What were the
possibilities that Beijing would be
devastated by an earthquake in the very
near future? This was a question of nation¬
wide concern.
Research into earthquakes must be based
on an examination of the earliest possible
historical documents. In this respect China
is fortunate because all over the country
there are documents and steles from ancient
times bearing records of seismic activities.
Together with the many ancient
monuments which have survived earth¬
quakes, these were valuable materials for us
to study. The varying degrees of damage
sustained by ancient monuments in dif¬
ferent parts ofTangshan due to differences
in the magnitudes of the earthquakes pro¬
vided evidence which we were able to pro-
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Unesco Courier, Chinese edition
This immense tomb in Qinghai province,
western China, Is that of a Turfan
aristocrat. During excavations which
began in 1983 a large amount of silk
fabrics, fragments of engraved bamboo
slips and other articles have been un¬
earthed. Situated in an oasis in the
Sinkiang Uighur Autonomous Region,
Turfan was an important staging post on
the northern branch of the Silk Road (see
the Unesco Courier, June 1984, issue on
"Great Trade Routes").
cess scientifically. Seismological ar¬
chaeology had begun.
Between 1976 and 1979, my colleagues
and I travelled extensively in disaster-hit
Tangshan, on both sides of the Great Wall
in northern China, in Beijing and Tianjin,
and completed our research. The results of
our efforts were compiled in a book entitled
"Seismic Archaeology in Beijing" which
has won wide acclaim from our fellow pro¬
fessionals. From this experience I learned
about the many-sidedness of archaeology
and its close links with other branches of
science.
In 1979 I took a graduate course in the
history of the Yuan Dynasty at the
Academy of Social Sciences. This opened a
new page in my archaeological career and
ended my work in seismic archaeology.
When I finished the course, only two places
really attracted me; one was the Institute of
Historical Research, the other was my
former place of work, the State Relics
Bureau. Here I could do both research and
conservation work. I decided to go back.
And so I joined the Relics Department,
which takes part in drawing up and enforc¬
ing laws concerning historical relics and in
administration related to relics and their
protection, and is involved in ar¬
chaeological work throughout the country.
I had developed a strong interest in ancient
religions during my post-graduate studies.
My new post provided me with oppor¬
tunities for contact with ancient religious
remains and was ideal for carrying out
research in this field.
I feel strongly that a patriotic ar¬
chaeologist should not only undertake
serious research into historical problems by
himself; he should help a wider audience
the whole nation to understand the im¬
portance of archaeological work so that
they can take part in the protection, study
and appreciation of our common historic
culture.
I am wholeheartedly devoted to my ad¬
ministrative work and research into sub¬
jects that interest me. In the past three years
I have visited ancient ruins on the three
gorges of the Yangtse river, surveyed the
Lama relics in Tibet, and visited Egypt.
This year I was appointed deputy director
of our Relics Department, a new honour
that spurs me to make greater efforts in my
work so as to fulfil the historic mission
bestowed on our generation.
Like myself, young archaeologists of my
generation are growing up. Before the
founding of the People's Republic, there
were few archaeologists in our country. In
the first years of the young republic, several
famous archaeologists, including some
from abroad, set up a training course for
future archaeologists. In 1955 an ar¬
chaeological department opened at Beijing
University. Its graduates became the main
force for undertaking archaeological work
in the new China. Now we of the next
generation have become pillars of ar¬
chaeological work throughout the country.
Many of us have been promoted to director¬
ships of museums and are leaders of ar¬
chaeological teams. Our modernization
drive is accelerating research and excava¬
tion work on ancient ruins. Heavy respon¬
sibilities have been placed on the shoulders
of young archaeologists.
Today many other universities are setting
up archaeology departments. With the
development of the economy and the rise in
living standards and levels of culture,
greater demands are being made on ar¬
chaeologists. Present numbers are insuffi¬
cient. The new situation also calls for
deeper professional knowledge. A course
run by the State Relics' Administration
Bureau to train leaders of archaeological
teams recruits only college graduates with
three years of working experience. Only
those who pass the examination at the end
of the course are qualified to lead excava¬
tion work.
The most professional archaeological
periodicals in China are "Archaeology"
(published by the Archaeological Research
Institute of the China Academy of Social
Sciences) and "Relics" (published by Relics
Publishing House). Other publications are
edited by local museums and research
institutes.
The scope for the study of archaeology is
widening. In the past, because of the lack of
professionals, the emphasis had been laid
on periods before the Qin and Han
dynasties. However, as China develops and
exchanges with other countries increase,
there is a growing interest in contemporary
relics and in the artifacts of our minority
nationalities.
GUO ZHAN, of the People's Republic of
China, is Deputy Director of the Relics Depart¬
ment of the State Relics Administration
Bureau. He was one of the compilers of
"Seismic Archaeology in Beijing", published
by Relics Publishing House, 1985, and is the
author of several historical studies.
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO NEWSROOM
In youthful hands, a future for the past
Each year, large numbers of young peo¬
ple show their concern for the cultural
heritage by taking part in archaeological
excavations as volunteers or by joining
voluntary work camps organized to
repair or restore historic buildings or
sites. Each year since 1980 Unesco and
the Paris-based association Jeunesse et
Patrimoine ("Youth and Heritage") have
issued a leaflet providing information
about voluntary work camps and interna¬
tional courses for training camp leaders
in various countries. This year's leaflet
lists work camps in the following coun¬
tries : Argentina, Australia, Austria,
Belgium, Canada, Czechoslovakia,
Finland, France, German Democratic
Republic, Hungary, Ireland, Israel, Italy,
Morocco, Netherlands, Norway, Poland,
Portugal, Spain, Syrian Arab Republic,
Tunisia, the United Kingdom. The train¬
ing courses are designed to enable par¬
ticipants to set up or run voluntary
restoration camps in their own countries.
Students are instructed in a range of
restoration and conservation techniques,
Photo Dominique Roger Unesco
from stone dressing to paving and roof¬
ing. For further information and to
receive the leaflet, please write to:
Jeunesse et Patrimoine, 9 Avenue
Franklin D. Roosevelt, 75008 Paris,
enclosing a stamped addressed envelope
(postage paid for 50 grammes) for
France, or an equivalent international
reply coupon. Above, restoration of the
columns of the Roman theatre at Bosra in
the Syrian Arab Republic.
Violence of Nature and of Man
During the 1 21 st session of the Unesco
Executive Board, the Director-General of
Unesco, the Chairman and members of
the Board expressed their sympathy for
the families of the thousands of victims
of the recent cyclone and floods in
Bangladesh and their solidarity with the
Bangalee people and Government. The
Director-General outlined the various
steps he had taken in aid of the victims of
the disaster.
The Chairman and members of the
Board and the Director-General also
deplored the violence that resulted in the
tragedy at the Heysel stadium, Brussels,
on the occasion of the final of the Euro¬
pean Cup, when 38 spectators lost their
lives. Mention was made of Unesco ac¬
tion designed to encourage fair play in
sport.
World
Archaeological
Congress
The World Archaeological Congress to
be held in Southampton and London from
1 to 7 September 1 986, is the 1 1 th Con¬
gress of the International Union of
Prehistoric and Protohistoric Sciences
(U.I.S.P.P.) sponsored by Unesco. Fur¬
ther information may be obtained from
the UK National Secretary, Professor P.J.
Ucko, Department of Archaeology,
University of Southampton, Southamp¬
ton S09 5NH, England. (See article
page 4).
International
Simón Bolívar Prize 1985
On the recommendation of the Prize
Jury, following its meeting at Unesco
headquarters in Paris from 1 3 to 17 May
under the chairmanship of Mr. Arturo
Uslar Pietri (Venezuela), the Director-
General of Unesco, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, has decided to award the Inter¬
national Simón Bolívar Prize 1 985 to the
Contadora Group (Colombia, Mexico,
Panama and Venezuela).
The award is being made in recognition
of the efforts of the Contadora Group to
find a pacific, negotiated solution to the
extremely serious problems now facing
Central America. Established by Unesco
in 1 978, the Simón Bolívar Prize was first
awarded jointly in 1983 to King Juan
Carlos of Spain and Nelson Mandela, the
African National Congress leader im¬
prisoned in South Africa.
In announcing the award Mr. M'Bow
also associated himself with the special
tribute paid by the jury to Prince Talal Bin
Abdul Aziz AI Saud, of Saudi Arabia, for
his exemplary humanitarian action for
development in general and for the
world's needy children in particular.
The Prize was presented at a ceremony
held at Unesco headquarters in Paris on
20 June.
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Offices:
Unesco, 7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 68 French francs. 2 years (valid only in
France): 1 20 French francs. Binder for a year's issues:
52 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be
reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from the
UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three voucher
copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles reprinted must
bear author's name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon covering pos¬
tage. Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and
do not necessarily represent the opinions of UNESCO or those
of the editors of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and
headlines are written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boun¬
daries on maps published in the magazine do not imply offi¬
cial endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the United
Nations.
The Unesco Courier is produced In microform (microfilm and/or
microfiche! by: (Il Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris ;
(2) University Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100.
U.S.A.: (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1
West 40th Street, New York. U.S.A.: (4) Bell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road. Wooster, Ohio 44691. U.S.A.
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Howard Brabyn (Paris)
Roy Malkin
French: Alain Lévêque (Paris)
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Jorge Enrique Adoum
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov (Paris)
Arabic: Sayed Osman (Paris)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Rajmani Tiwari (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: Hossein Razmdjou (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra llgazer (Istambul) .
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwa
(Dar-es-Salam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Vitomir Sudarski (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Pekin)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Inger Raaby (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larranaga (San Sebastian)
Braille: Frederick Potter (Paris)
Research: Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
38
BRODARD GRAPHIQUE. COULOMMIERS - Dépôt légal C 1 - Juillet 1985 - IMPRIMÉ EN FRANCE (Printed in France)
PHOTOCOMPOSITION CHRISTIAN PAGNOUD - 6/8, rue des Épinettes - 75017 PARIS - PHOTOGRAVURE DAWANT - 13, rue des Arquebusiers - 75003 PARIS.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Two recent Unesco books on archaeology I
In 1979, as part of its programme on
the study of Asian cultures, Unesco
launched a series of surveys on the
archaeological sites and objects which
have been excavated in Asia during
the last 20 or 30 years and which are
considered to be of great historical
and cultural value. The first two titles
in the series are :
Recent Archaeological Discoveries in the
Republic of Korea, a survey of eleven
important excavations and discoveries
undertaken since 1961, ranging from the
Palaeolithic Age to the seventeenth" century.
1983 104 pp. illus. 80 French francs
ISBN 92-3-102001-3
Recent Archaeological Discoveries in the
People's Republic of China. Some of the.most
outstanding archaeological discoveries made in
China over the past 30 years.
1984 116 pp. illus. 90 French francs
ISBN 92-3-102241-5
RECENT
ARCHAEOLOGICAL
DISCOVERIES IN
THE REPUBLIC OF KOREA
KIM WON-YONG
Th« Cerm« lor East A«lan Cultural Studies
VMM
RECENT
ARCHAEOLOGICAL
DISCOVERIES IN
THE PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF
.
CHINA
TOE INSTITUTE OF ARCHAEOLOGY
ACADEMY OF SOCIAL SCIENCES
PEOPLE'S REPUBLIC OF CHINA
' '
^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^^ ' ' '"^
Th« Ccntr* (or East Asian Cultural StudMfe
BMMt
Both co-published with the Centre for
East Asian Cultural Studies, Tokyo
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58A Gipps Street, Colling-
wood Victoria 3066; Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd.
P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NSW. Periodicals: Dominie Pty.
Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-
agent: United Nations Association of Australia, P.O. Box 1 75,
5th floor. Ana House, 28 Elizabeth Street, Melbourne Victoria
3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31,
A-101 1, Vienna. RAHAMAS. Nassau Stationers Ltd., P.O. Box
N-3138, Nassau. BANGLADESH. Bangladesh Books
International Ltd., Ittefaq Building, 1, R,K. Mission Rd., Hatkhola,
Dacca 3. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies
Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64, Bridgetown.
BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V.
Handelmaatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, P.O.
Box 91, Gaborone. BURMA. Trade Corporation No. 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Que. H3H 1M7.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export
Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. CYPRUS. "MAM",
Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1 722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L., Spalena 51-1 13 02, Prague
1 ; Ve Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790 - 1 11 - 27 Prague 1 (Permanent
display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1 Soukenicka, Prague 1 . For
Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893
31 Bratislava CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG
Tidsskriftservice 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco
Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb Street, Cairo. ETHIOPIA.
National Agency for Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, Keskuskatu 1, SF-00100
Helsinki 10; Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2,
01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris, CCP. 1 2598-48. GERMAN
DEMOCRATIC REP. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier (German,
English, French and Spanish editions): Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3 .-For
other Unesco publications: Karger Verlag, Germering/München.
For scientific maps only: Geo Center, Postfach 600830,
Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University
Bookshop of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon,
P.O. Box 1, Legon. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
HONG KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd.. 5A Evergreen
Industrial Mansion, 1 2 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book
Co., 13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. Hong Kong Government
Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville House, 22
Ice Street. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport - ABT, P.O.B. 149 -
H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson & Co.,
H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd.,
Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038; 1 7 Chittaranjan
Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 7001 6; Scindia House, New Delhi; *
Publication Unit, Ministry of Education and Culture, Ex. AFO
Hutments, Dr. Rajendra Prasad Road, New Delhi 1 10001.
INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl. Oto
Iskandardinata III, Jakarta; Indira P. T., Jl Dr Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co.,
28, Vessal Shirazi Street, Enghélab Avenue. P.O. Box 314/1486,
Teheran; Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco. 1 188 Enghlab Av.,
Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158, P.O. Box 11365-4498,
Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al Rashid Street,
Baghdad. IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd,
Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A. B.C.
Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv
61000- ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A.)
Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101
Water Lane, Kingston. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Mona, Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo
3-chome Bunkyo-ku Tokyo 1 13. KENYA. East African Publishing
House, P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd.,
Quran House, Mfangano Street, P.O. Box 45245, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box
Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd,
POB 2942, Kuwait; for the Unesco Courier; Farafalla Press
Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait. LESOTHO. Mazenod
Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod. Lesotho, Southern Africa. LIBERIA.
Code and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LIECHTENSTEIN : Eurocan Trust Reg. P.O.B. 5 9494 Schaan.
LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication & Distribution,
P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAWI. Malawi Book Service,
Head Office, P.O. Box 30044 Chichiri, Blantyre 3. MALAYSIA.
University of Malaya Cooperative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. KEESING BOEKEN B.V., Joan Muyskenweg,
22, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam. NETHERLANDS
ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., P.O. Box 200, Willemstad,
Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O. Box 5344,
Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace. P.O. Box 1721 Chrtstchurch;
Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street, P.O. Box
1 104, Dunedin, Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Wellington.
NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The University
Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum,
P.O.B. 1 1 77 Sentrum Oslo 1 , Narvesen A/S; Subscription and
Trade Book Service. P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O.
Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional
Office for Book development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi
Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. PHILIPPINES.
National Book Store, Inc. 701, Rizal Avenue, Manila D-404,
POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No. 7.00-068 WARSAW.
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do
Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES. National Bookshop, P.O. Box
. 48, Mahé; New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131,
Mahé. SIERRA LEONE. Fourah Bay, Njala University and Sierra
Leone Diocesan Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Federal
Publications (SI Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Road,
Singapore 2261. SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern
Book Shop and General, P.O. Box 951 , Mogadiscio. SOUTH
AFRICA. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata P.O.B.
244 Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications A/B.C.E. Fritzes Kungl,
Hovbokhandel, Regeringsgatan 12, Box 16356. 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Forbundet,
Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams, Box 30004-S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte
Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 - 101 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag. 5
Rämistrasse. Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva
1 1 , CCP. 1 2-236. Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle,
Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchàtel and Zurich. TANZANIA.
Dares Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam.
THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402; Bangkok: Suksapan Panit,
Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok; Suksit Siam
Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
Street, St. Clair, Trinidad, W.I. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.,
Istiktäl Caddesi, N° 469, Posta Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istambul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 7145, Kampala.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, H.M.S.O., P.O.
Box 276, London, SW8 5DT, and Govt. Bookshops in London.
Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for
scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Road,
London WC 1 X 9 DS. UNITED STATES. Unipub, 205 East
42nd Street, New York, N.Y. 10017. Orders for books &
Periodicals: P.O. Box 1222, Ann Arbor, Ml 48106. U.S.S.R.
Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Moscow, 121200. YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, P.O. Box 4227, Aden. YUGOSLAVIA.
Mladost, Mica 30/1 1 , Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitarjeva 2,
Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664
Lusaka. ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67 Union
Avenue, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
'
r J
M
á il
Lu
Trees
that rewrote
history
This gnarled tree trunk protruding
from rocky debris over 3,000
metres up in the White Mountains
of California is an ancient bristle-
cone pine (Pinus Longaeva). The
bristlecone pine is the world's
oldest known living tree. By coun¬
ting the distinctive ring patterns
that are produced in a tree trunk
during each year of its growth, one
bristlecone pine specimen was
found to be about 4,900 years old.
By fitting together tree-ring pat¬
terns from living trees and dead
wood, scientists have established a
system for dating archaeological
remains which has led to the re-
evaluation of some traditional theo¬
ries about the development of
ancient cultures.
]]>
</page>
</document>
