<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="074925eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
JULY 1987-9 French IÍWK»
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Keeping in touch
Mentally handicapped children have special needs but first and fore¬
most they are children and they share all the needs and emotions of
childhood. In the past it was often felt that these children were in¬
capable of learning or of any form of independence, but it is now
known that all children can learn if taught in the right way. The de¬
velopment of communication skills plays an important role in help¬
ing disabled children to become as independent as possible and find
a place as young adults in the community. Above, a mentally handi¬
capped child engrossed in learning to use the telephone.
56 Japan
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
The International Conference on Drug Abuse and Illicit Trafficking,
organized by the United Nations and held in Vienna in June 1987,
marked a new chapter in attempts by the world community to combat
the problem of drugs. In recognition of the importance of the
Conference, the articles which open this number of the Unesco Courier
are devoted to different aspects of the drug question including the key
role of the prevention of drug abuse through education, one of the
activities which Unesco has been carrying out in this field for over
fifteen years.
Action on behalf of the disabled is another important field in which
Unesco is co-operating in efforts to achieve goals set by the United
Nations, in this case through the encouragement of educational
activities to help the integration of disabled young people into schools
and society at large. To draw attention to the importance of such action
in fostering the personality development of disabled children and
enabling them eventually to participate in society to the fullest extent,
we publish a case study from Portugal which incorporates the testimony
of two visually handicapped children who talk frankly about their lives.
Also in this issue , the nature of the writer's responsibility in the
preservation of peace is analysed in an article by the secretary of P.E.N,
the international association of writers, who examines the process
whereby words can be used to create false pictures ofwhat he calls the
"hereditary enemy", and suggests ways in which writers can destroy
these dangerous myths.
New light is shed on the history of urbanization by an article which
recreates the historical and cultural context which saw the birth of
al-Kufah, the prototype of the Islamic city, and proposes a new
approach to the place of cities in Arab Islamic civilization. Also in this
issue we look at some of the latest developments in the field of artificial
intelligence research and especially the astonishing horizons being
opened up by the development of the fifth generation computer.
Finally , 1987 marks the bicentenary of the birth of a maj or figure in
cultural history, Vuk Stefanovic Karadzic. As a tribute to Karadzic, the
father of Serbo-Croat literature who preserved treasures of the folk
tradition , reformed the alphabet , and won a European reputation
during his lifetime, we publish a profile of him and a short selection of
extracts from his works.
Cover: Photo Jean-Eric Pasquier © Rapho, Paris.
Back cover: Map of Medina (Al-Madîna , Saudi Arabia) one of the chief holy cities of Islam.
It is taken from Description ofMecca and Medina, a Persian manuscript (AH 982/AD 1574)
by Mohyi Lari. Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
July 1987
40th year
Learning to live
by Nicole Friderich
Unesco and drugs
7
'A perverse logic'
by Jean Baudrillard
10
How should we attack the drug problem?
by Giuseppe di Gennaro
14
The new world of artificial intelligence
by Domenico de Gregorio
16
The search for a thinking computer
by Norihisa Doi, Koichi Furukawa
and Kazuhiro Fuchi
20
The city-builders of Islam
by Mohammed Allai Sinaceur
25
Fighting words
The myth ofthe 'hereditary enemy'
by Jean Blot
29
Society and the disabled
30
Breaking down the barriers for visually
handicapped children
by Maria Adelaide Moreira de Moráis Alves
32
Vuk Stefanovic Karadzic
Profile of a great scholar
34
A world congress on copyright teaching
by Yves Gaubiac
A time to live
JAPAN: Keeping in touch
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 33 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
Thai
Vietnamese
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N°7-1987-CPD-87-l-447 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
In response to growing international concern about the problem ofdrugs,
the General Assembly of the United Nations convened an International
Conference on Drug Abuse and Illicit Trafficking (ICDAIT) to meet in
Vienna (Austria) from 17 to 26 June 1987, on the initiative of the
Secretary-General of the UN, Mr. Javier Pérez de Cuéllar.
The goal of the Conference was to generate national, regional and interna¬
tional action to combat the drug problem in all its forms and define future
activities on issues such as preventive education, illicit demand reduction,
law enforcement, eradication of illicit sources of raw materials, and
rehabilitation of drug abusers with emphasis on their integration into
society. Some 2,500 delegatesfrom governments all over the world attended
the Conference, together with over 300 representatives ofnon-governmen¬
tal organizations, in order to confront all the aspects ofthe drugproblem in
the world context.
The priority goal of Unesco's activities relating to drugs is prevention
through education andpublic information. The importance ofefforts in the
field of preventive education, encouraged by Unesco, is evoked in the
following article by Mme. Nicole Friderich, who was for many years
responsible for Unesco's programme of education concerning problems
associated with the use ofdrugs. The two other articles on the drugproblem
published in this issue present divergent, ifnot conflicting, analyses of this
highly controversial subject. While Mr. Giuseppe di Gennaro, Executive
Director of the United Nations Fundfor Drug Abuse Control (UNFDAC),
condemns the activities of the traffickers and producers of illegal drugs,
whom he sees as the propagators ofthe "drug culture", French sociologist
Jean Baudrillard takes the view that systematic repression is an incomplete
and even dangerous response to the social problems associated with drugs,
especially in the industrialized countries. Preventive education as advo¬
cated by Unesco may constitute at least a partial response to the concerns
expressed by these contributors.
The logo of the International Conference
on Drug Abuse and Illicit Trafficking de¬
picts the motto of the Conference, "Yes to
life, No to drugs", in the 6 official United
Nations languages.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
- *
H
t*M L¿
i
Learning to live
by Nicole Friderich
PERSEVERANCE is a quality shared
by all concerned with the problem of
drugs. The men and women
involved in law enforcement do not let
themselves be disheartened by the fact that
only between 10 and 15 per cent of the illicit
drug traffic is intercepted as a result of their
work. They continue their efforts, seek new
methods, draw benefit from modern tech¬
niques, and realize the importance of active
co-operation with those who are engaged in
scientific research into the different drugs,
treat drug users, or attempt through educa¬
tion to limit the harm caused by drugs and
prevent drug abuse.
The scientists who study the chemical
composition of legal and illegal drugs and
their physical and psychological effects
(about which in many cases we still know
very little), therapists, doctors and
psychologists, are continuing their work
and in some cases making essential
discoveries, such as that of endorphins a
decade ago.
Neither these specialists nor social work¬
ers allow themselves to be discouraged by
the fact that their devotion only achieves a
"cure" in 30 per cent of treated cases of
dependence on so-called hard drugs or on
alcohol, which may be put in this category.
They reflect on experiments that have been
carried out, learn from their failures as well
as their successes, compare their results,
improve their methods, and unflaggingly
help those who are trying to free themselves
from the grip of drugs. Organizations such
as Alcoholics Anonymous, whose members
have succeeded in overcoming their depen¬
dence on certain substances, support and
encourage those who have been unable to
do so, and consider that their work should
be a continuing effort. The families and
friends of drug users often search unremit¬
tingly for a solution, sometimes ready to
"Nothing if not constructive, the role of
educators, teachers, parents and youth
leaders is to help the young and less
young to develop their character and
strengthen their intellectual, emotional
and moral resources, to learn to learn and
to learn to be."
believe in a miracle; their task is a hard
one.
Educators, teachers, parents and youth
leaders are playing an active role in these
joint efforts. Their co-operation is sought
by everyone, from therapists to enforce¬
ment agents and government authorities,,
since the importance of their preventive
efforts is appreciated. Nothing if not con¬
structive, their role is to help the young and
less young to develop their character and
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
strengthen their intellectual, emotional and
moral resources, to learn to learn and to
learn to be.
Professional educators have been trained
to do this; they understand the theory and
practice of teaching, psychology and techni¬
cal skills. Family members have usually not
had such an initiation. In their day-in, day-
out task of bringing up young children, pos¬
sibly not their own, to live a life which in
many cases they hope will be better than
theirs, they rely on their personal experi¬
ence, their love, their moral or religious
principles.
Efforts, notably those carried out by
Unesco, to encourage all those involved in
education in the broadest sense to take part
in what has been called preventive educa¬
tion, are already bearing fruit. Those con¬
cerned with education have become aware
of the role they can play and have spared
neither their efforts nor their good will.
Most of them have volunteered their help
but have often asked "What can we do?"
One of the first tasks has been to show
them the preventive effects of what they
were already doing: character training, the
development of a critical approach, deci¬
sion-making capacities, respect for princi¬
ples, and understanding of psychological
mechanisms; and, of course, the transmis¬
sion of knowledge of the nature and the
effects of certain substances which are
already studied as part of some school
programmes or which have a domestic use.
It has also been necessary, and this is an
essential task, to demystify the idea of drugs
as magical and evil substances which have
incomprehensible effects and are totally
alien to their experience. Many parents and
educators have come to understand the
problems more fully after thinking honestly
and frankly about the use of legal drugs
which they take or see others take. Why do
people smoke, drink, take tranquillizers,
stimulants and medicines which give them a
sense of well-being? Are they seeking
energy, relaxation, pleasure, an escape
from stress? The phenomenon of depen¬
dence is not unfamiliar to those who have
watched someone try to stop smoking or
drinking, or have witnessed the anguish of a
person deprived of his or her usual sleeping
pill or tranquillizer.
Educators have thus become more fully
aware of what they already knew and have
defined what they want to find out. They
are not by any means seeking an
encyclopaedic knowledge of the world's
countless drugs (new drugs to cure illness
appear every day and each one is potentially
beneficial or dangerous). But they do wish
to be fully informed about the substances
used in their own countries and environ¬
ments, products which certain groups or
younger generations know more about than
they do from their own experience,
however biased or incomplete such "knowl¬
edge" may be.
Parents and teachers have also made it
clear that they want to know how to act in
time, before it's "too late". They have
asked to be informed about the signs and
symptoms of drug taking and quickly
realized that the most important thing they
can do is to be attentive to the difficulties
which seem to be faced by young or older
people in their family or school. They have
also asked for help in forming relationships
with those in distress and in making contact
with those who are at risk of turning to
drugs (or to other expedients).
Techniques for opening up channels of
communication have been put forward to
educators and they have developed others
for themselves. Some have discovered the
importance of active education methods,
pupil participation and learning by doing.
This has had a beneficial effect on their
teaching as a whole. The efforts made by
educators to confront an immediate prob¬
lem have committed them to action and in
some cases encouraged them to adopt less
theoretical approaches.
But their work has not always been
crowned with success. Their methods, some
imported from other cultures or borrowed
from other contexts, have not always been
effective. In some cases quick and easily
quantifiable results were expected. "Eval¬
uations" have been made without taking
into account the objectives which had been
set and which could have been achieved
with the means available. The authorities,
in some cases, and, very often, those who
agreed to finance preventive education
experiments, have insisted on rapid and
spectacular results forgetting that the
education of a human being takes years and
that people are free agents and, have
attempted to apply to prevention strict cost-
benefit criteria.
Far from being discouraged, parents and
educators have continued their work. They
have formed groups, shared their discov¬
eries, experiences, disappointments and
successes. They have exchanged their
ideas and the role of an organization like
Unesco has been of inestimable value in this
respect. This role is still developing. In all
the world regions, in situations where the
pattern of drug use varies widely, a growing
number of initiatives in favour of preventive
education are being taken. Experience and
innovation are complementary. No one
ever claims that a definitive solution has
been found. Problems are being patiently
solved as and when they arise.
Educators, families and youth leaders
will continue their work. They will not
abandon their efforts to prevent drug abuse
since in the final analysis their motivation is
love for those in their care and whom they
wish to help through education to "learn to
live".
Unesco
NICOLE FRIDERICH is a consultant in the field
ofpreventive education at Unesco Headquarters
in Paris and in various countries. She was for
many years responsible for Unesco's pro¬
gramme for equality of educational opportunity
for girls and women, and from 1972 to 1983
headed Unesco's section for education concern¬
ing problems associated with the use of drugs.
She is a co-author of a new Unesco book, Edu¬
cating Against Drug Abuse.
Unesco subscribes to the definition of a drug
formulated by the World Health Organiza¬
tion (WHO) as "any substance that when
taken into the living organism may modify
one or more of its functions." This definition
does not designate those who are dependent
on drugs as either "abnormal" or "crimi¬
nal", and has the advantage of being equally-
applicable to "legal" substances (tobacco,
medicines, alcoholic beverages) and to those
such as heroin or LSD which are proscribed
by law.
Unesco turned its attention to the prob¬
lems of drug abuse in 1970, in response to an
appeal from the General Assembly of the
United Nations. It was decided that the most
valuable contribution Unesco could make
would be in the areas of education, the social
and human sciences and communication.
The financing, directed primarily towards
operational projects, was entrusted to the
United Nations Fund for Drug Abuse Con¬
trol (UNFDAC).
Unesco's programmes relating to drugs
were drawn up in the early 1970s for the
industrialized countries. Fifteen years later,
at the request of the developing countries,
which had begun to be affected by the grow¬
ing market in legal and illegal drugs, these
programmes were expanded and strength¬
ened in order to intensify the "struggle
against trafficking and the illicit use of
drugs", and to promote "education for the
prevention of drug abuse".
The principles governing Unesco action
on drugs were defined in 1972:
concern was to be directed towards both
illicit drugs and those which are socially
acceptable (such as tobacco and commonly
used medicines);
drug problems were not to be looked on as
problems specific to youth, if only because it
is mainly adults who tend to abuse "legal"
drugs and tend to be the producers of both
"legal" and "illegal" drugs;
a distinction would be made between
action within educational systems and public
information hi a wider context.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
v?#
6A perverse logic'
and drugs
Unesco was soon active in a number of
world regions. In several Asian countries, its
education and prevention programmes have
been integrated into those of other United
Nations agencies. Certain projects aimed at
finding alternative activities to the cultiva¬
tion of the opium poppy fall into this cate¬
gory. In Latin America and the Caribbean,
where certain countries produce cocaine and
cannabis, action is aimed primarily at pre¬
vention. In Africa, where until the mid-
1970s the problems of drug abuse were
almost non-existent, large sectors of the pop¬
ulation were exposed to the fluctuating drug
market. Under Unesco auspices, representa¬
tives of six African countries met at Lomé
(Togo) in 1976, in order to devise systems of
preventive education. Soon afterwards,
working groups were set up in twelve coun¬
tries, and courses in methodology were
organized in Gabon in 1981 and in Kenya in
1983.
Among current projects:
two pilot programmes are being launched
in Senegal and Ghana: the first stage began
with the distribution of a questionnaire to
assess the extent of drug abuse in both for¬
mal and out-of-school education;
the publication (in English and French)
on the occasion of the United Nations Inter¬
national Conference on Drug Abuse and
Illicit Trafficking (Vienna, June 1987), of a
book entitled Educating Against Drug
Abuse (see inside back cover);
the production of an audiovisual montage
on Young People and Drugs for those con¬
cerned with teaching young people in danger
of becoming dependent on drugs;
the analysis of audiovisual messages and
assessment of their impact on drug preven¬
tion campaigns;
continuing co-operation with non-gov¬
ernmental organizations, particularly with
some sixty international youth organiza¬
tions.
by Jean Baudrillard
DRUGS in general no longer form
part of the shared values and sym¬
bolic rituals of modern industrial
societies, which are dedicated to deferred
gratification and ulterior purposes which
call for a calculated sacrifice of time and
energy. The use of drugs, on the other
hand, always implies an immediate mental
process and the attainment of a kind of
utopia. All schools of thought (including
religious thought) which have favoured the
immediate attainment of utopia have been
declared heretical and condemned as such
through the ages.
Traces of this long-standing condemna¬
tion linger on in our own vision of modern
drugs and of the occult power they derive
from their ancient symbolic virtues. They
simultaneously fascinate, repel and terrify,
and their ambivalence is virtually definitive,
posing a problem that Western reason finds
insoluble; they "dope" bodies and brains
and have the same effect on our judgment
of what they are.
Drugs were long held and are still held
in current analytical thinking to be "ano-
mic", in Durkheim's sense of the term,1 like
a certain type of suicide which is itself char¬
acteristic of the social structures of indus¬
trialized countries. Such phenomena are
residual, marginal, beyond the pale of the
law, outside the overall pattern of organiza¬
tion and the value-system of the group.
Peripheral though they are, they do not call
in question the principle of law and values
as such, and it is not unknown for laws and
values to absorb and integrate them.
Today, the status of drugs seems to me to
be totally different, along with other speci¬
fically contemporary phenomena which I
shall call, not anomic, but anomalous. By
this I do not mean something marginal, the
expression of an imbalance or the organic
deficiency of a system, but the result of an
excess of organization, of an excessive con-
1. The term anomie, as coined by the French social
scientist Emile Durkheim (1858-1917), denotes the con¬
dition of a society or a social group which results when its
members are deprived of norms or standards of be¬
haviour and of ideals which give meaning to their aspir¬
ations. Editor
cern with balance, regulation and rationa¬
lization in a given system. Such a phe¬
nomenon, seemingly extraneous, conflicts
with the workings of the system, for no
apparent reason, but in fact it is a conse¬
quence of the very logic of the system , of the
excessive logic and rationality of a system
in this case society in the industrialized
countries which, having reached a certain
level of saturation, secretes antibodies
which express its internal diseases, its
strange malfunctions, its unforeseeable and
incurable breakdowns in a word, its
anomalies.
In such systems this is not the result of
society's inability to integrate its marginal
phenomena; on the contrary, it stems from
an overcapacity for integration and standar¬
dization. When this happens, societies
which seem all-powerful are destabilized
from within, with serious consequences, for
the more efforts the system makes to orga¬
nize itself in order to get rid of its anoma¬
lies, the further it will take its logic of
over-organization, and the more it will
nourish the outgrowth of those anomalies.
A Finnish poster in favour of "Good
human relations without drugs"
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
JA ;
© ".'i, . - ». -.A
' - -- '-* '.
v ..-r
"AI/ drugs, hard or soft, including tobacco,
alcohol and all modern variants, are a
means of exorcism: they exorcise reality,
the social order and callous indifference."
is
I©
A naively rationalist (educational and
therapeutic) conception of these systems
must be discarded (and this applies not only
to social systems but also to cybernetic and
computerized systems). In the past, the ex¬
istence of anomic peripheries prompted the
system to become even more rationalized,
but today it is the over-rationalization of the
system which causes and strengthens ano¬
malous developments.
This "perverse" logic must be taken into
account and a distinction must be made
between drug-taking connected with econo¬
mic and social underdevelopment (as it still
is in developing countries or, in the case of
alcohol, in underprivileged classes) and
drug-taking linked to the saturation of the
consumer society. The latter type began to
emerge in the 1960s in the industrialized
countries, as both the apogee of consump¬
tion and a parody of it, as an anomaly which
challenged a world that had to be escaped
from because it was too full, not because it
lacked something. Perhaps there is a lesson
here for developing societies, which are still
ambivalent in terms of their organization.
In these countries, then, we are dealing
with drug use of what might be called a
"second order" which should not be con¬
fused with the other type, for neither its
limits, nor its characteristics nor, obviously,
its prevention, will be the same. In particu¬
lar, we must consider the problem of drugs
in connection with all the "second order"
phenomena which are contemporary with it
and which follow the same "anomalous"
logic. We must look at the various types of
"second order" violence, which do not stem
from straightforward delinquency or
aggression, but from a reaction against the
excessive tolerance of industrialized society
and the over-protectiveness of the social
fabric. Terrorism certainly belongs to this
type. It is a form of response to the omnipo¬
tence of modern States, which secrete it no
longer as historical violence, but as anoma¬
lous violence, which, moreover, they can¬
not suppress, except by turning themselves
into States which are even more powerful,
more controlled and more coercive, there¬
by perpetuating the vicious circle.
We must take account of such types of
"second order" pathological phenomena as
AIDS and cancer, which are not traditional
diseases due to the organic deficiency of
bodies exposed to an attack from outside,
but a consequence of the destabilization of
over-protected bodies (over-protected by
all our hygienic, chemical, medical, social
and psychological prostheses), which there¬
by lose their immunity and become a prey to
any virus. Just as there is apparently no
"political" solution to the problem of ter¬
rorism, for the time being there seems to be
no biomedical solution to the problem of
AIDS and cancer and for the same
reason. These are, in fact, anomalous
occurrences, turning with savage, reactive
violence against the political or biological
over-control of the body, whether it be the
social or the individual organism.
Such phenomena spring from a "darker
side" of human experience. Drug use and
abuse form part of this syndrome. The exist¬
ence of this darker side and the behaviour
resulting from it may be deplored but its
symbolic necessity cannot be denied . As the
French writer Georges Bataille has shown,
the darker side ("La part maudite") plays a
fundamental role in most societies, in ways
which may be more or less explicit.
One thing is certain: a society that
attempts to purge itself entirely of this dar¬
ker side runs a very great risk. Such a desire
nevertheless forms part of the rationalist
paranoia of the social systems of industrial¬
ized countries. The negative aspects of this
darker side are, admittedly, important and
should not be ignored, but they should be
set against the far more serious loss that
might result from its destruction. Such an
act would generate cancers and viruses that
would be far more malignant and would not
even have the charm of malediction to re¬
commend them.
This is the crux of the ambiguity and the
paradox of drugs: in some countries drug-
taking is a symptom of the collective loss of
immune defences or of the individual loss of
symbolic defences a situation in which
some societies become vulnerable to terror¬
ism, drug addiction and violence (but also
to depression or to fascism). And it is ob¬
vious that the only solution would be to
restore those immunities and those symbo¬
lic defences. But in the West we also know
that we live in a system which is tending, in
the very name of science and progress, to
destroy all natural immunities and to re¬
place them with substitute systems of artifi¬
cial immunity.
Why should we expect such a system to
change direction? And now we see the use
of drugs from another, exactly opposite,
angle: while it is part of the immune de¬
ficiency syndrome, it is itself a defence.
Better defences may exist, but it is possible
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
to speculate (for we must respond to such
an insoluble state of affairs with paradoxical
hypotheses) that the use and abuse of drugs
may be a vital and symbolic reaction,
however despairing and suicidal it may
seem, against something still worse.
Without by any means yielding to the
temptations of the over-optimistic ideology
in the West during the 1960s and 1970s
concerning the "expansion of conscious¬
ness", there are grounds for thinking, much
more prosaically, that this is not only an
impulse to flee from the objective process of
brutalization that life in some societies may
be, but a collective movement of avoid¬
ance, a shared reflex of flight from the
universal standardization, rationalization
and regimentation which undoubtedly con¬
stitute, in the long term, a much more se¬
rious danger to society and to the human
race. We know that individuals use neurosis
as an effective protection against madness;
similarly, it is possible to use, not absolute
good, but relative evil, as a defence against
absolute evil. The Church has coped with its
heresies in the same way, by treating them
as necessary (from its point of view) aberra¬
tions, as harmful offshoots (but offshoots
nevertheless). A Church which no longer
generates heresies or which has stamped
them all out begins to wither, just as a body
which no longer produces any kind of
offshoots, including those which work for
its destruction, is a dead body.
That said, drug-taking in the industrial¬
ized countries is no longer in its intensive
phase, the phase sustained by euphoric or
glorifying rhetoric, whether subversive or
suicidal. It is in its extensive phase: while it
is spreading and gaining ground, it is in the
process becoming less virulent for society.
It is no longer a more or less subversive type
of anomy, but an anomaly which is becom¬
ing institutionalized.
How should we react to this process of
familiarization? Should we fight it even
more strenuously? A hard new anti-drug
philosophy (now that there is no longer any
philosophy of drugs) may seem problema¬
tic. In this state of precarious balance, or
imbalance, of the immune system of society
and of the individual, where drugs play an
ambiguous role, such an approach intro¬
duces a rigid moralizing element, a rigid
dichotomy between law and anomy which is
no longer appropriate for the delicate man¬
agement of anomalies (this rigidity is,
moreover, itself highly ambiguous, since it
is often a disguise for political strategies in
which drug-taking, like any other form of
delinquency, is used as an easy alibi).
It is imperative to realize that the prob¬
lem of drug-taking must be approached
with sensitivity, and (because it is an ambi¬
guous problem) with strategies that are
themselves ambiguous. The best form of
prevention is to introduce a symbolical ele¬
ment into the social strategy, a difficult
undertaking which involves flying in the
face of today's excessive rationalization and
Giving young people help and support is ±
an essential part of a preventive approach %
to the drug problem.
social organization. Lack of a ready-made
solution does not spell failure, and we must
at all costs avoid clear-cut, unilateral
strategies of denunciation, whereby one
kind of society takes complacent refuge in
its own hypocrisy. Drug-use is a question to
which there are no glib answers. Nor should
too hasty a distinction be drawn between
drug use and abuse: no one could trace
clearly the unstable boundaries between
them.
All drugs, hard or soft, including tobac¬
co, alcohol and all modern variants, are a
means of exorcism: they exorcise reality,
the social order and callous indifference.
But it should not be forgotten that, through
drugs, society itself exorcises certain forgot
ten powers, certain drives, certain inner
contradictions. Exorcism is production for
the sake of rejection. Society produces this
effect, and society condemns it. Failing the
ability to stop producing it (which is consi¬
dered desirable), society should at least
cease to condemn it.
JEAN BAUDRILLARD, French sociologist, is
professor of sociology at the University of Paris
X-Nanterre and scientific director of IRIS (Socio¬
economic Research and Information Institute),
Paris IX-Dauphine. His publications in English
are The Mirror of Production (1975) and For a
Critique of the Political Economy of the Sign
(1980).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
How should
we attack the
drugproblem? At<
by Giuseppe di Gennaro
THE increase in drug dependence
among young people is creating
exacting new problems for educa¬
tors, who need to grasp the true nature and
scope of the phenomenon in order to carry
out their duties.
The non-medical use of drugs has always
existed, but in forms which have little in
common with drug dependence among
young people as we know it today.
Historical and anthropological research
has shown that in the past drug-taking was
almost always confined to adults. Adoles¬
cents were never involved. Drugs were
taken sporadically for mystical, religious or
ritual purposes, and only by certain groups
and in certain circumstances. The impor¬
tant thing about the practice and purpose of
these forms of drug taking was the absence
of dependence.
Later, when morphine, heroin and
cocaine began to be used, there were cases
of addiction among adults, but until the
mid-1960s the numbers involved were so
small that the phenomenon never reached a
socially significant scale and on the whole
attracted little attention.
It was not until the late 1960s that drug
abuse began to make inroads among young
people and children and eventually became
a world problem, as uncontrollable waves
of epidemic proportions swept from con¬
tinent to continent.
It is therefore both mistaken and dan¬
gerous to assume that the present situation
is simply the continuation of the past. It is
mistaken because only today have drugs
become a culture which everyone must
face. It is dangerous because it makes peo¬
ple less vigilant and encourages passivity
and acceptance. We expect that the damage
will be limited and that the community will
continue to take things in its stride as it has
done over the centuries.
Educators must take stock of the dangers
that drugs represent for children and ado¬
lescents today, foresee possible future
developments, understand the causes of the
situation and the forces underlying it, and
introduce appropriate remedial measures
into the educational process. This is an
arduous task, as can be seen from the per¬
sistence and increasing gravity of drug
dependence in spite of the determination of
many educators and the hard work they
have done in the last twenty years.
The subject has been exhaustively dis¬
cussed. Whole libraries of books have been
devoted to it, written by specialists in every
branch of knowledge; research has been
carried out by highly qualified authorities
and organizations; innumerable con¬
ferences and meetings have been held, both
local and international; but the guidelines
for reliable and effective educational
defence measures have still not been clearly
and unequivocally defined.
It is thus vital to continue our efforts to
understand the situation and deal with it
more effectively. The purpose of this article
is to stimulate critical reflection about cer¬
tain widely held beliefs. There is a risk that
such beliefs may be considered to be abso¬
lutely true, although they are not, and be
taken, wrongly, as a basis for educational
theory and practice, now and in the future.
These beliefs all stem from the assump¬
tion that drug dependence among young
people is due to factors caused by the
changes and tensions of modern society. In
accordance with this assumption various sit¬
uations have been singled out and blamed
for the spread of drugs. An exhaustive list of
these situations would be extremely long
and is unnecessary for our purpose. We
shall merely point out certain widely
accepted allegations.
The first comes under the heading of
i
\
\
I
1
\
!
This French poster is a stiff from a short
f/7m produced for showing on TV and in
cinemas as part of an anti-drug campaign.
Intended for 10- to 13-year-olds, the film
was made to encourage young people to
resist approaches from drug-pushers.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
»«8**
"youthful protest". It has been maintained
that young people at a certain stage refused
to be dominated by the adult culture, which
in their view was entangled with profit-mak¬
ing and the status quo, and reacted against
the idea of being excluded from the con¬
struction of the future society in which they
would have to live. This reaction turned
into confrontation and struggle, and the
anger that in some countries culminated in
the disturbances of 1968 was accompanied
by the development of a general attitude of
rejection of adult behaviour and values.
Drug abuse was essentially a deliberate
insult and provocation on the part of young
people towards adults.
The correlation between the spread of
drug dependence and youthful protest
seemed convincing because the connection
appeared to be logical and because the two
phenomena occurred at the same time.
Youthful protest lost its impetus within a
few years and was inevitably followed by a
general feeling of defeat, resignation and
disengagement from society. This second
phase was also accompanied by drug depen¬
dence. Specialists have stressed the impor¬
tance of detachment and the flight from
reality in drug abuse, and have proposed
another causal hypothesis without paying
much attention to the fact that it is the
antithesis of the first.
Meanwhile, in some societies an extreme
form of consumerism was developing at a
time of general social well-being and at
the same time drug dependence among
young people assumed greater proportions.
Again the two phenomena were seen by
some to be related; this paved the way for
the theory that drug dependence was due to
well-being and excess. It was only later that
underdevelopment, poverty and drugs
came to be associated, and sparked off a
search for other causes.
Various theories continued to be put for¬
ward. Some assertions were so general as to
be irrefutable since they were impossible to
verify empirically. One was the claim that
drug dependence is the result of the collapse
of traditional values.
Other theories based on the simultaneous
occurrence of spreading drug dependence
and certain forms of social change were
refuted by the observation that the same
social conditions did not always give rise to
similar phenomena. One of the most impor¬
tant of these theories claimed that there was
a relation between the loosening of family
ties and drug dependence. This theory, of
course, originated in highly industrialized
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ft has been suggested that the spread of
drug dependence is due to the loosening
of traditional family ties. However, some
doubt was cast on this theory when drug
dependence was observed among young
people in a context of stable family struc¬
tures. Above, Family Group (1945-1949) by
the British sculptor Henry Moore.
countries, where the family has been
affected by the demands made by the level
of organization and by the tensions of indus¬
trialized society.
The family and especially the parents
were blamed for this tragedy. Today, many
people question their culpability, having
seen situations in which the epidemic of
drug-taking on the part of young people has
appeared in a context characterized by
social and economic immobility and the sta¬
bility of family structures.
Lastly, the idea that there is a causal link
between unemployment and drugs has
recently been disproved by the spread of
drug dependence among workers.
Logically enough, whenever one of these
theories was put forward, those concerned
with the prevention and treatment of drug
dependence took action against the sup¬
posed causes of the phenomenon. In con¬
sequence, for more than twenty years we
have seen a feverish succession of prescrip¬
tions and measures intended to tackle a
wide variety of different "causes". Every¬
one agrees that education is an essential
tool in combating drug dependence, above
all as a means of prevention. However, it
has lost its bearings and is now at the centre
of a heated argument that is fed by alternat¬
ing aetiological "credos".
The inability of the family and the school
to perform their respective educational
functions has been castigated by the suppor¬
ters of these different theories, who main¬
tain that certain factors are the cause or at
least contribute to the cause that corre¬
sponds to their particular theories. The fol¬
lowing remarks are intended to help these
two great forces which are under accusa¬
tion the family and the school to
rediscover their bearings and to perform
their difficult task successfully, each in its
own sphere of responsibilities and each
applying its own methods.
Although family upbringing and school
education have much in common as regards
their dynamic and their aims, there are
important differences between them.
By family upbringing we mean the natu¬
ral process by which parents and other
members of the family nucleus transmit to
their children a number of messages, by
word, action and behaviour. Such messages
give, more or less directly, an indication of
what "should be" in other words, guid¬
ance for living and an idea of the behaviour
that is expected of young people.
School education, on the other hand, is
an institutional process designed to inte¬
grate the process of family upbringing. In
school education trained professionals
transmit messages which are meant to
inform their pupils and influence their
behaviour by means of the values and ideals
that they assimilate.
The process of family upbringing is
largely unconscious, and in the mechanism
whereby messages are transmitted and
received the emotional or affective element
is usually more potent than the intellectual
or cognitive element. School education, on
the other hand, is a conscious process,
although the emotional or affective element
may play an important part in it.
The two educational processes, for all
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
their differences, have one thing in com¬
mon: they interact with a series of influ¬
ences originating in the circumstances of the
young person's life. It is clear that the effect
of identical educational processes will vary
as a result of different external influences. It
is generally realized that the influence of
friends, or the "peer group", is extremely
powerful in this respect, especially at cer¬
tain stages of adolescence.
If the influence of the peer group conveys
the values of an alien or hostile culture, it
will encourage and strengthen attitudes of
confrontation and opposition to the
authority of parents and teachers, together
with rejection of the culture to which the
family and the school owe allegiance.
Instead of being a part of the growing-up
process, when adolescents assert their own
personalities and attempt to throw off the
bonds of parental authority, this stage may
on the contrary become an opportunity for
messages from alien and hostile cultural
sources to enter their minds. The young
person's personality becomes a battle-field,
in which the more powerful influences can
be expected to prevail.
How does the peer group transmit the
messages of the drug culture while the
school and the vast majority of families
belong to a different culture? To answer this
question, we need to know where the drug
culture comes from and what sustains it.
The idea that young people themselves
create the drug culture because of weak¬
nesses in family upbringing and school edu¬
cation is thoughtless and superficial. Relia¬
ble research findings now indicate that the
drug culture is the outcome of shrewd
manipulation by the many persons who
work for the barons of the drug traffic.
Preventive education against the abuse of
legal or illegal drugs is at the heart of
Unesco's action against drug depen¬
dence. Below, schoolchildren in Singa¬
pore examine the diseased lung of a dead
smoker.
These powerful figures possess very consid¬
erable financial resources and highly effi¬
cient and far-reaching organizations. Just as
the great fashion centres and the producers
of other consumer goods create and impose
a culture that aspires to the acquisition of
such products, so those who control the vast
drug market create and impose a culture
that leads inevitably to drug abuse and the
spread of drug dependence. In this market,
young people are not active agents; they are
conditioned customers.
If this is true, it is false and unjust to
blame the family or the school, and it is
pointless to look for causal factors among
social phenomena or tensions. Drug depen¬
dence springs from the drug culture, which,
in its turn, is created by drug traffickers and
their battalions of propagandists.
The family and the school should realize
this; they should stop feeling guilty and
should understand that, in the present state
of affairs, if they wish to protect young peo¬
ple they must do more than generate and
transmit traditional positive influences.
Drug abuse will not be beaten unless the
drug culture is beaten too, and this means
waging a determined struggle against illicit
drug production and trafficking and against
the powerful criminal syndicates that grow
rich in this way. .
Of course the family and the school have
a role to play, but their efforts will be inade¬
quate if not fruitless unless government
institutions and the resources of the com¬
munity are mobilized to defeat those
responsible for the scourge of drug
dependence.
Drug taking is no recent phenomenon, and
drug abuse has been resisted throughout
history. In an episode from the Sirat
Baybars, a folk account of the life of
Baybars I, a 13th-century Mamluk Sultan
of Egypt and Syria, Baybars attacks cor¬
ruption, crime, prostitution and hashish
smoking in the Cairo slums. Above and
below, details of cover illustrations from 2
volumes of a new French translation of
this vast work of some 36,000 pages.
GIUSEPPE DI GENNARO, Italian jurist, has
been Executive Director of the United Nations
Fund for Drug Abuse Control (UNFDAC) since
1982. He was previously Chairman of the UN
Commission on Narcotic Drugs and frequently
served as a UN consultant. In his own country he
has been a judge, and occupied various high-
level posts in the Italian Ministry of Justice. He is
the author of numerous anieles and reports on
drug problems, criminology and other legal
matters.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The new world
ofartificial intelligence
THE days may soon be past when a pes¬
simist could say that a computer, for all
its capacity for rapid calculation, was a
"high-speed idiot" because it could not "rea¬
son". We are now moving into the age of
"intelligent machines" and of "artificial intel¬
ligence" a discipline that has an important
place in informatics.
Artificial intelligence is a branch of informa¬
tics which studies the theoretical bases, meth¬
odologies and techniques which make it pos¬
sible to design hardware and software
systems capable of performing tasks which to
the non-expert would seem to belong
exclusively to human intelligence. The aim of
artificial intelligence research is to produce
systems which behave intelligently and inter¬
act with the world outside them just as human
beings do.
In practice, the results of research into artifi¬
cial intelligence are now becoming part of our
everyday lives. Artificial intelligence systems
are acting as advisers and experts in such
fields as lexicological analysis, medical diag¬
nosis and genetic engineering. There are
robots which have the power of perception
and visual recognition and the ability to
behave rationally in unfamiliar circumstances,
terminals which converse in natural lan¬
guages, either in speech or writing (though
there are limits to their abilities in this sphere),
systems that solve problems and demon¬
strate theorems.
Every two years, specialists meet to
exchange information at the International
Joint Conference on Artificial Intelligence
(IJCAI), which is usually held in a leading
world centre for study in this field. The first
conference was held in Washington, D.C., in
1 969, and since then conferences have taken
place in London, Stanford, Tbilisi, Cambridge,
Tokyo, Vancouver, Karlsruhe and Los
Angeles. This year the Conference is being
held in Milan, in recognition of work done in
Italy in this field of advanced research. It will
take place from 23 to 28 August, in the Centro
CongressLMirafori.
The philosophy of IJCAI is based on the
belief that contemporary thought has suc¬
ceeded in unifying the concept of culture; the
old idea that scientific culture and humanistic
culture are two different things has been dis¬
carded. The culture of our day should there¬
fore be characterized by the synthesis of
these two forms of mental activity.
Artificial intelligence is thus claimed to be
the supreme example of an interdisciplinary
subject, as was made clear at a symposium to
prepare for the IJCAI Conference in Milan,
held at the St. Vincent Cultural Centre (Italy)
on 21 February last. The work of the sym¬
posium, entitled in an allusion to Beckett's
play, "Waiting for Robots: the immediate
future of artificial intelligence", could perhaps
be summarized by saying that two fundamen¬
tal questions are being asked in this field: how
far and how soon will robotics be able to take
the place of man; and will man ultimately be
rivalled, if not completely outstripped, by
machines.
Mr. Basilio Catania, the director of the Turin
Telecommunications Research Centre and
Laboratories, a leading Italian research
institution in the field of artificial intelligence,
pointed out that man possesses muscle
power, faculties of perception, and intel¬
ligence. Over the centuries, man has con¬
stantly aimed to extend these capacities. His
first success in enhancing his muscle power,
the invention of the wheel, was followed by
many others and culminated in the harnessing
of the atom. He enhanced his faculties of per¬
ception by inventing increasingly efficient
tools, leading to the development of the elec¬
tron microscope, the radio telescope, and
television.
In the sphere of human intelligence, one of
the most significant steps forward was the
invention of the pocket calculator, the pro¬
totype of the complex modern machines
which make it possible to increase man's
mental capacity and will do so to a still greater
degree in the future. Artificial intelligence sim-
Some key words in artificial intelligence
The expression artificial intelligence was formulated for the first time in 1956 by John McCarthy of
Stanford University (United States).
This new discipline proposes to overcome the current limits of informatics in certain areas, improving
and extending the performance of computers. Its purpose is not to "simulate" human intelligence but to
"emulate" it, since there is no basis for excluding the possibility that some manifestations of human
intelligence, problem-solving, for example, can also be provided by adopting methodological approa¬
ches that are not necessarily anthropomorphic.
Within artificial intelligence, an Expert System is a system capable of automatically solving problems
of a certain type, proposed by the users of the system. An Expert System is the result of the collaboration
of two designers, the "knowledge engineer" who develops the algorithms (the sequences of instructions
for solving a particular problem) necessary to construct the solution and the structures suitable for
receiving the base information, and the "problem expert" who furnishes the body of facts and deductive
rules, called the knowledge base of the Expert System.
Industrial exploitation of Expert Systems will Increase with the use of fifth generation machines (see
article page 16) which are currently the subiect of intensive research. The Expert System is directly
embedded In the electronic architecture of these machines, which are created with the most advanced
technologies of microelectronics, such as Very Large Scale Integration circuits, which present a million
transistors on a single silicon chip.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
by Domenico de Gregorio
ply enables man to "extend" his own intel¬
ligence, as It were, by providing a "prosthesis"
to help him perform various functions.
We must, however, beware of thinking of
the future of these "prostheses of intel¬
ligence" as a collection of anthropomorphic
robots: a car may be regarded as a prosthesis
of legs, but it is not the same thing.
One of the most advanced fields of artificial
intelligence research has led to the con¬
struction of what are known as "connection
machines", in which a large number of tiny
calculators, instead of working sequentially,
work on various pieces of information at the
same time which is what happens in the
human brain and combine the results. This
was the field selected for the EEC project on
"Basic research in adaptive intelligence and
neurocomputing".
The great scientific discoveries of the twen¬
tieth century, such as the splitting of the atom
and, more recently, genetic engineering, have
conferred on man enormous powers which
can be used for good or ill. Artificial intel¬
ligence, too, may be used for good or ill. The
availability of vast amounts of information
which can be analysed in a fraction of a sec¬
ond can be a source of financial and political
power and can thus be open to all kinds of
abuse. But artificial intelligence can also bring
many advantages. It may help to provide more
rewarding occupations for millions of people,
increase productivity and take some of the
drudgery out of work.
Advances in the field of artificial intelligence
will soon produce "fall-out" which may have
surprising and awe-inspiring consequences
such as giving sight to the blind. A project now
underway at Rockville, Maryland, Is currently
examining the possibility of using about a hun¬
dred thousand micro-electrodes, associated
with nerve cells In the embryonic phase of the
visual cortex, to connect with the visual struc¬
tures of the brain and give sight even if only
rudimentary sight thanks to a microscopic
telecamera implanted in a pair of spectacles,
completely by-passing the eyeballs and the
optic nerve.
While the opportunities opened up by artifi¬
cial intelligence can be expected to create
new and more satisfying kinds of work, prob¬
lems are bound to arise, ranging from the
revaluation of certain categories of work and
those who do it, to problems connected with
privacy and the security of information, which
may have Important legal implications.
©
:
'
1
1
-
1
. Vr;A/. - ';
0^H
i wÄu^Sk
rJjMre& H
¿$ËA h?
W
WmÊ
**Áta¿ «*#**' vv I HÔk
£.: 2»
i m __
t : ^m
5 mtm f!
*--i H !T B * M H#^H
ft a
*
DOMENICO DE GREGORIO, Italian journalist
and specialist in mass communication, is man¬
aging editor of the Italian edition of the Unesco
Courier. He has taught at the Italian Advertising
Institute (University of Rome) and is the author of
a number of studies on information science,
notably Metodología del periodismo (1966,
"Methodology of Journalism") and L'lnforma-
zione, teoha ed evoluzione storlca (1981, "Infor¬
mation, Theory and Historical Evolution").
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The search for a thinking computer
As part of an unparalleled long-term re¬
search and development effort, computer
scientists in a number of countries are
today trying to bridge the gap between the
limited computer intelligence that exists
now and something approaching human
capacities. One of many obstacles in this
search for a machine as intelligent as man
lies in the limitations of conventional com¬
puters which perform their operations one
step at a time. The search for a solution to
this problem has led to the development of
"parallel processing" systems which
operate on thousands of data elements at
once. In the computershown above tens of
thousands of processors co-operate on
the processing of a single task.
WITH few exceptions, all present com¬
puters are von Neumann compu¬
ters, so called after John von Neu¬
mann, one of the scientists whose work was
seminal in creating and developing these
machines. The von Neumann computer is
characterized by data and programs that are
stored together (stored program) and pro¬
grams that are executed sequentially
(sequential control). In the von Neumann
computer, everything to be done must be
defined In advance in the form of procedure.
The program describes procedures in a lan¬
guage the computer can understand. In the
program, the procedure is called an algorithm.
This system presents no problems for numeri¬
cal computation and routine clerical process¬
ing, since procedures can be pre-defined for
this kind of work.
However, most activity requiring human
intelligence is characterized by the need to
accommodate strategies flexibly to the
demands and complexity of a particular situa¬
tion. Using the example of language, which is
the basis of intelligent activity, the meaning of
a word may vary with the situation In which It is
used. The meaning of a word also changes in
relation to surrounding words. The meaning of
a sentence also depends on the object of the
sentence and circumstances of use.
Consequently, when one tries to write a
program to analyse the meaning of a word in a
sentence, all cases in which the word can be
used must be considered. However, the num¬
ber of cases will be colossal, and even if all
cases could ever be listed the program would
never be completed in a reasonable time. In
other words, such a program would have very
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
little practical value because of the excessive
processing time.
It is clear that computers must perform intel¬
ligently and flexibly in the applications
required by the society of the 1990s. The
problem is how to develop a computer with
this capability. A first approximation to solving
this problem can be found in artificial intel¬
ligence research. But because of the limita¬
tions described, the results of artificial intel¬
ligence research cannot be put into practical
use with existing computers.
Stated simply, the goal of artificial intel¬
ligence research is that computers should
perform in an identical or similar manner to
human intelligence.
This research takes two approaches: one
models the mechanism of human intelligence;
the other attempts to achieve human intel¬
ligence in the computer by processes that are
not necessarily the same as actual human
intelligence, the emphasis being on the result.
Major themes of current research in artificial
intelligence are:
1) Proofof theorems. Conclusions are made
based upon axioms and inference rules. The
computer can be an aid in proving theorems,
but this field has not developed to the point
where computers can automatically prove
theorems that human beings cannot.
2) Games. Studies aim at methods of choos¬
ing the best move in all game situations and
strategies for winning the game. This field has
developed a number of methods of finding the
best of all possible moves and thus has
helped to solve problems.
3) Robots. Research and development in this
area is mainly aimed at controlling manipula¬
tors to perform skilful work, developing sen¬
sors, and developing high-level languages to
describe work environments and commands.
4) Vision understanding. The aim here is to
make it possible for computers to recognize
faces, scenes, photographs, etc. A variety of
¡mage analysis methods have been
developed. As a result, computers can now
recognize complicated scenes on condition
that knowledge on the subject be input pre¬
viously. However, a general method of coping
with a wide range of objects has not yet been
developed.
5) Natural-language understanding and
voice recognition. How to make computers
understand sentences and speech in natural
language, e.g., in Japanese, English or
French, is the focus of this field of study. There
are already some experimental systems that
can understand English or Japanese when
objects are limited. However, as the number
of objects increases, the number of words and
sentences required increases even more,
necessitating common sense and inference
rules. Thus, much further study is required.
6) Knowledge engineering. Research in this
area aims at storing experts' knowledge and
automatically finding the answer to a given
problem. The system used for this purpose is
called an expert system (see box page 14).
Efforts have been made to apply this to medi¬
cal treatment, machine design/maintenance/
repair, and education.
What are known as "fifth generation" sys¬
tems are being designed to overcome the
shortcomings of the present-day computer.1
In particular, research is concentrated on
knowledge information processing.
Computers of the past and present genera¬
tions have simple hardware architecture and
implement complex functions through soft¬
ware. In 1 982, the Japanese Ministry for Inter¬
national Trade and Industry initiated a project
to develop computers capable of forming the
basis of an advanced information society in
the 1 990s. In this project, it was decided to use
technologies that are essentially different
from those of the past.
In other words, the ultimate form of fifth
generation computer should be oriented to
knowledge information processing and
achieved on the basis of revolutionary theo¬
ries and technologies. The fifth generation
computer is a knowledge information pro¬
cessing system that, overcoming the tech¬
nical limitations of conventional computers,
implements the intelligent conversation and
knowledge base inference functions required
in the 1990s. Its applications are expected to
be more extensive than those of conventional
computers.
The four basic functions the fifth generation
computer must achieve are:
1) Problem solving and inference func¬
tions. Logical deductive inference and induc¬
tive inference to solve a given problem, includ¬
ing guesses based on incomplete knowledge.
2) Knowledge base management func¬
tions. Acquisition, storage, and utilization of
various kinds of knowledge required in the
inference process.
3) Intelligent interface functions. External
interfaces that use natural language (sen-
1. Computer "generations" have been defined by
the components used:
Generation Approximate period Component
1 1946-1958
2 1959-1964
3 1965-1977
3.5 1978-1983
4 1984
Vacuum tube
Transistor
Integrated Circuit (IC)
Large Scale Integration (LSI)
Very Large Scale Integration (VLSI)
Tomato talk
In the widening field of artificial intel¬
ligence, computers are being asked to
solve an array of real-life problems rang¬
ing from the diagnosis of illness and the
prescription of treatment, to exploration
for minerals. "Expert systems" are pro¬
grams which help the computer to mimic
the behaviour of human experts when
tackling these problems. The questions
and answers below are part of a computer
dialogue between a tomato-grower and
"TOM", an expert system In plant patholo¬
gy developed by Alain Bonnet, a French
specialist in artificial intelligence, and
Dominique Blancard, a researcher In plant
pathology.
TOM: Age of plant?
User: Adult.
TOM: What variety?
User: Vemone. ...
TOM: Have you noticed yellowing, withering or drying of the
leaves (not to be confused with spots on the leaves)? Generally,
this yellowing affects the lower parts of the plant, and only affects
a few plants at first.
User: No. ...
TOM: Have light brown or greyish spongy galls been observed on
the roots, concentrated at soil level?
User: Yes.
TOM: Are these symptoms by any chance more noticeable In the
wettest parts of the plot?
User: No.
TOM then gave "his" diagnosis of possible diseases.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Hands that "see"
Advanced computer technology has made it possible to endow
robots with "sight", a sense of touch, and in some cases the
ability to respond to voice commands and make basic decisions
about the situations they encounter. Photo above shows "Maga¬
li", an apple-picking robot developed in France. Artificial vision is
an essential component in Magali, whose arm is guided to the
fruit by a television camera associated with a microcomputer. In
robot vision systems a computer analyses an ¡mage, converted
into digital form, fed into it from a television camera and directs
the robot to perform a specific task when it "detects" certain
features that have been programmed into its memory. Below, a
computer-controlled hand developed at the Massachusetts Insti¬
tute of Technology (MIT). The hand is capable of picking up an
egg without breaking it. Each finger can make 40 movements a
second. Covered with a plastic skin equipped with sensors, the
hand can "recognize" different materials such as metal, plastic
and wood, and instantaneously measure the temperature of ob¬
jects that it touches.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
tence, voice), graphics, and images, and can
converse naturally.
4) Intelligent programming functions.
Functions to automatically convert a given
problem to efficient computer programs.
To achieve these functions, various tech¬
nologies of hardware architecture, software
engineering, and artificial intelligence are
being studied and developed.
The first task for achieving knowledge infor¬
mation processing and fifth generation com¬
puters is the selection of the programming
language best suited to describe intelligent
activity by the computer. To select the lan¬
guage, it is necessary to understand the fun¬
damental mechanism of the intelligent activity
to be described. It should be noted that the
present computer is a machine developed to
model the fundamental mechanism of numeri¬
cal computation: that is, the four rules of
arithmetic.
In fifth generation computer systems, logic,
in particular predicate logic, was selected as
the principle of intelligent activity. Logic is gen¬
erally regarded as the universal rule of
thought. Of numerous types of logic, predicate
logic is most closely related to our daily lan¬
guage. This means that anyone can handle
predicate logic, although it may seem difficult
at first because of its rigour.
Of course, predicate logic alone cannot
account for all intelligent activities; it is cer¬
tainly, however, the most powerful logic for
description.
The basic mechanism of logic is inference.
Inference is a rigorous procedure for acquiring
unknown information using known informa¬
tion and knowledge. Inference plays a central
role in our understanding of meaning, whether
or not we are conscious of its use. The basis of
intelligent activity is to possess knowledge
and make inferences.
Inference is made according to inference
rules. The most fundamental inference rule is
the syllogism. A syllogism is a form of reason¬
ing as follows: A is B; B is C; therefore, A is C.
One method of having the computer make
inferences automatically is to incorporate this
inference rule in the hardware, and this is the
approach of the project on fifth generation
computer systems.
The method of describing a program log¬
ically and executing it by inference is called
logic programming. Predicate logic programs
allow parallel processing, which resembles
the process of obtaining unknown quantities
in a system of simultaneous linear equations
concurrently. One objective of the fifth gener¬
ation computer systems project is to achieve
parallel processing directly by hardware. In
other words, the project aims at developing
computers that can perform symbol-crunch¬
ing computation at high speed. For this rea¬
son, the final form of the fifth generation com¬
puter will be a parallel inference machine
consisting of a number of element processors.
The research and development of fifth gen¬
eration computer systems involves many
unknown factors and great risks. For this rea¬
son, the research and development period
spans ten years and is divided into three
stages three years for the initial stage, four
years for the intermediate, and three years for
the final stage.
Fifth generation computer systems could
be applied to any area that requires problem
solving and inference functions.
To take the example of medical treatment,
countless applications can be listed: auto¬
matic nursing systems monitoring serious
cases through the night and giving treatment
support when the patient's condition changes
suddenly; systems to help analyse X-ray films
or tomograms and diagnose the area for treat¬
ment; systems to help determine the name of
the illness or prescribe medicine based on
various check data; systems to devise duty
schedules for nurses and systems to decide
menus. When studies in natural-language
understanding advance further and machine
translation at higher levels becomes possible,
or when people place international calls to
speakers of another language, both parties
may be able to speak in their own tongue. In
education, more effective educational sys¬
tems can be expected, in which one will be
able to judge the optimum way- of giving
instructions to each individual. Present com¬
puter aided instruction (CAI) systems cannot
do this.
Needless to say, these applications will
occur not only through the achievements of
research on fifth generation computer sys¬
tems but also through research In artificial
intelligence that makes clear the models and
mechanisms of intelligent functions. Thus,
continued research Is very important.
The goal of the fifth generation computer
systems project is to create a knowledge infor¬
mation processing system that can help peo¬
ple solve problems in their exploration of the
unknown, and significantly extend the scope
of their Intellectual activity. This will have
an immeasurable impact on industry and
society.
NORIHISA DOI, of Japan, is a professor at the
Institute of Information Science at Kelo Univer¬
sity, Japan. His co-authors, KOICHI FURUKA-
WA and KAZUHIRO FUCHI, also Japanese, are
respectively assistant director and director at the
Research Centre of the Japanese Institute of
New Generation Computer Technology. All three
are closely involved in research In artificial intel¬
ligence, operating systems and software en¬
gineering. A longer version of this article is
appearing in an issue of Unesco's international
quarterly Impact of Science on Society (No. 146,
1987) entitled "The Third Industrial Revolution".
Using a computer and an expert system, s
this researcher can compose music "after &
the manner of" the great composers. Only f
African music presents problems. °-
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The city-builders of Islam
by Mohammed Allai Sinaceur
F'
jOR a Muslim ... the term 'Mother
Nature' defies translation. The
Muslim is no ecologist. ... Islam
took root in regions where nature is, gener¬
ally speaking, hostile to man. ... Its ideal is
the artificial world the city, the irrigation
system, the garden, which is introduced into
the home and represented in the design of a
carpet. The poetry of Islamic urban culture
speaks not of virgin landscapes but of the
flowers of the garden. ..."'
These words of the Islamist Josef van Ess
are a reminder of the value that the city
holds as we would expect of a great civi¬
lization for Islam, and above all for
Arabs. In the Islamic context, the con¬
notations of terms such as "city",
"urbanity", "urbanism", even "civility",
are so similar as to make these words vir¬
tually interchangeable. The city is the art of
living together. Islam, then, it might a priori
be concluded, is a founding, constructing
and urbanizing, rather than a conquering
civilization. Whereas relations between
other cities, as, for example, in ancient
Greece, were marked by rivalry, among
Islamic cities there existed a sense of mem
bership of an urban society with a shared
culture and way of life.
To understand this phenomenon we need
to examine the genesis of the Islamic city,
provided that we can find an example that is
sufficiently ancient and representative.
What better prototype could there be than
Al-Küfah (Iraq), the first city of Islam,
whose birth was recently related in a book
by the Tunisian historian Hichem Djaït?2
But first, a little historical background.
Küfah was founded in AH 17/AD 638, dur¬
ing the early years of the rise of Islam, five
years after the collapse of the kingdom of
the Lakhmids during the reign of Khosrow
II. Symbol and centre of the new Arab
sway, Küfah was constructed near al-Hîra,
the Lakhmid capital which for three cen¬
turies had dominated the region and whose
power and functions Küfah was eventually
to take over. The Islamic empire was
founded, and a decisive step forward in
human progress, the abandonment of
nomadism in favour of sedentary life, was
initiated.
Küfah drew its strength from the relative
financial autonomy of the new province. In
selecting its site, Caliph 'Umar I is said to
have decreed that no bahr (river) should
separate it from Medina. The first Islamic
city outside Arabia had to be in direct spa¬
tial contact with the homeland. This prere¬
quisite was later applied to other towns.
Only conditions that suited their camels,
said Caliph 'Umar, were right for Arabs
zones open to the steppe and in uninter¬
rupted contact with pastoral life.
Such, indeed, was the position of Küfah,
remote yet in contact, on the border of
steppe and cultivated land, and thus a focal
point of interchange and complementarity.
The first city of Islam, Küfah symbolized its
spirit: a civilization of borders and links, of
transition and mediation; for, in terms of
human geography, the role of Islam has
been to provide the "bridges", the
"railheads", the "termini" which link the
towns of the desert to the huge cities of the
North.
Some historians relate that, at the found¬
ing of the city, a site was marked out by
shooting arrows from a central point at
which were located the masdjid (mosque)
and the palace. Town-planning was born
20
1. Le christianisme et les religions du monde ("Chris¬
tianity and the Religions of the World") by Hans Küng
and Josef van Ess, Editions du Seuil, Paris, 1986.
2. Al-Küfa, naissance de la ville islamique ("Al-Küfah,
Birth of the Islamic City") by Hichem Djaït, Editions
Maisonneuve and Larose, Paris, 1986.
Right, the city of Aleppo (Arabic Halab) in
Syria as depicted In a miniature from
Nâsùh al-Matraki's Itinerary, a AH X /16th
century AD manuscript describing the
campaigns of Sultan Sulaymän the Magni¬
ficent Aleppo was a Hittite, Assyrian and
Hellenistic site before becoming one of the
great cities of Islam. The citadel, sur¬
rounded by a moat, Is built on a huge
mound In the centre of the city.
Left, map of Küfah at its apogee (AH 100-
120/AD 718-738) during the Umayyad
period
1 1 || : tribal plot (qatr a)
II : street (sikka)
i i : residence of an aristocrat (dar)
From Al-Küfa, naissance de la ville islamique by Hichem Djait,
Editions Maisonneuve & Larose, Paris, 1 986
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
m
r
!
t
I ; u
JE
N
>
i i
h j .. , i . , .
! ! A'ili « - "I1
as - -
tr pi r v^.^LDH
- 	 - : i^-;J it-x' ^ri^:.-IS , - AU
£ JlMí.] '»
Ni
ill - m&àÉM»
.il ,1m nu a r-î rëFitïS it
Z^áS
n ri * -
I
V
V~ Lj_,-	j_i	 t i-
'
-
te _i
e^*
&. .
.'li km*
s>
its jLLi H i i
un
» ?
û./ ' F; ' ^1
m rm
I ï
| r 1.-1	__	JB... î
HA-n
^w I .
, » «t»j^'"r:"
1 1 * * r y.c
il 1 1
I* Ia Al
\ i i
II
MMMmMÍ
1 inrli i ir^HJ'-j l 1 Lrutfüip *
i ; I ii r|
! i
0
cru*
rvt'i * #
i'i'in
iri^n [ ':rr,
M^-'! ' - *
iTT
I Uli
1 i Al
* .s
1
I
! » * j
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
ffluT
when the construction of permanent, mud-
brick buildings began. Considering that the
mosque was the first building to be marked
out and built at Küfah, that 'Umar I decreed
that houses should be limited to three
rooms and should not be too high, that
roads should be clearly defined and that
land should be allotted to the tribes in con¬
formity with the regulations, it is clear that
town-planning (takhtït) and civilization
(tamsir) went hand in hand, at the same
pace and on the same wave of progress, with
the aim of establishing a defined and
ordered space to which the Umayyads were
later to add the seal of truly monumental
constructions tuned to the harmonies of
other disciplines.
What was the source of this organiza¬
tional plan, of the juxtaposition of mosque
and palace? What were the origins of the
süq (market-place) which surrounded this
monumental complex and was built in such
a way as to respect both the plan and the
exigencies of the terrain? What precedent
was there for the immense public area
which, in 'Umar's day, could hold 4,000
horses? Every trace, every scrap of infor¬
mation must be examined if the impetus
that gave rise to the founding of this and
other Islamic cities is to be understood. We
must scrutinize everything that scholarly
erudition and comparative research can
reveal about that matrix of urban con¬
struction which is Küfah.
Küfah marked the advent of Islam the
mediator, the inheritor, the innovator. The
city itself was heir to a rich legacy, drawing
much from Babylon, the Mesopotamian,
oriental model, and from the cultural
heritage preserved in the twin city of
Seleucia on the Tigris/Ctesiphon, the Par¬
thian capital. As in these cities, the central
palace-mosque complex was a distinctive
feature, a veritable urban unit; however, in
Küfah this central unit never became an
isolated citadel as in Babylon, or later, in
Baghdad (Iraq), the circular city of the
'Abbäsids. If in later cities the palace was
moved to the outskirts, the mosque and the
market remained where they were, surviv¬
ing all transformations, specific and unvary¬
ing in location and status, the symbol of
centrality, the heart of the city.
Another heritage, another choice! Could
the Greek or Hellenistic city have influ¬
enced Küfah? The Greeks and the Romans
built their standard pattern cities in their
colonies, just as the Arabs built theirs on
the borders of Arabia. It is difficult to detect
any evidence of influence from this quarter.
Greeks, Romans and Arabs each assimil¬
ated and enriched foreign traditions, as
does any "torch-bearing" civilization.
The first Küfah was destroyed by fire,
perhaps because its builders had not suffi¬
ciently respected local environmental con¬
ditions. Those who rebuilt the city learned
from their first urban venture in the condi¬
tions of a new land, drawing inspiration
from their patrimony of ideas, but building
on the basis of their experience of their
surroundings. Legatees like the Persians,
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
's¡¿>
ff"""". 9^-.
i» f 	
III
Houses in the old city of San'à', capital of
the Yemen Arab Republic. Since 1986 the
old city of San'à' has been included on
Unesco's World Heritage List.
synthesizers like the Romans, the Arabs
were also innovators both in that, for them,
the act of founding a city was the outcome of
a reasoned project, and that in erecting a
structure they drew on the traditions of the
Arab city and on their own Arabian culture.
The Arabs had, indeed, experienced city
life long before they founded cities. In
founding Küfah they had behind them a
wealth of experience gained, it would seem,
in the north of the Arabian Peninsula. Long
before the coming of Islam, perhaps before
the development of written Arabic,
cuneiform inscriptions bear witness to the
existence of a whole Arab culture. This
ancient identity reached its zenith during
the first three centuries of Islam under the
enlightened impulsion of a universal faith
which led to the creation of cities, of a State,
of an Empire. Thus Arabism, in a non-tribal
sense, became co-extensive with Islam,
vehicle of universality.
The identification of Arabs with nomad¬
ism, so marked in the writings of the great
Arab historian Ibn Khaldun, is a com¬
paratively late phenomenon. Were the
formerly a sedentary people who
became nomads by accident? The answer is
a definite yes. For the Arabs, then, the city
is perhaps an environment regained which
became more and more clearly defined as
the Islamic era approached. With the
advent of Islam the Arabs found their his¬
toric destiny as builders and citizens. "On
the whole," wrote the French Islamist
William Marcáis, "the spread of Islam ...
found its expression ... in an extension of
urban life."3 However, the Arabs' cultural
background and bedouin roots, strength¬
ened by proximity to the desert-refuge,
gave them a spirit of resistance, a marginal
quality which left them open to the appeal
of nomadism, of a way of life more in tune
with nature than with culture. They
3. "L'islamisme et la vie urbaine", in Articles et con¬
ferences by William Marcáis.
Editions Adrien-Maisonneuve, Paris, 1961.
to ..
Î5
0-
E
1
m '
2|
©^
«j V
flj
* 1
fn the süq, the old market, of Marrakesh,
Morocco.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
remained the greatest romantics of history
with a throbbing, irrepressible nostalgia
for, and innate identification with, the spirit
of nomadism.
Thus it was through Islam, revealed as it
was in an urban setting, that the Arabs were
able to fulfil their destiny as citizens. This
they accomplished all the more easily, defi¬
nitively, thanks to the examples of at-Tä'if
(in what is now Saudi Arabia), Yathrib
(pre-Islamic Medina) and Mecca. These
men, who had become nomads, knew that
the city too could defend itself, have its
share of culture, and be the symbol of unity.
The city, arising from some inner well-
spring of Arabism, was the fruit of the ter¬
ritorializing activities (paradoxical in these
nomads-by-accident who had become
nomads by temperament) of the tribes for
whom the city at times became the site and
primary source of innovation and the focus
of the urge to come together and to unite.
Küfah, then, drew on skills from many
sources, including those of the Yemen
which had already been tested out in the
Hejaz region in the heart of the Arabian
Peninsula, as witness the jabbänät (tribal
burial grounds) and the dur (houses) of the
nobles. Mecca provided a model of the
notion of the centre and of its pre-emi¬
nence. Even the marking out of the centre
of- Küfah by means of arrows was a
memento of the ritual involving arrows
practised in Mecca. More than this, the
notion of founding the city, of urban plan¬
ning, drew its inspiration and took as its
model the actions of Ibn Kilab Qussayy (a
5th-century prince of Mecca), ancestor,
builder, town-planner and architect.
At-Tä'if, too, provided another urban
model with its fortifications and city walls.
Finally, Medina offered the first example of
a twin central complex with its juxtaposition
of the house of power and the house of God ,
although, in the time of the Prophet,
authority was exercised from the mosque
itself.
It was only when the lessons of all these
models had been fully assimilated that the
new Islamic city arose on the fringes of the
desert. More than a polis (city), it was a
politeia (a whole social and political order).
It was a focal point at which life gathered
and then radiated outwards, flowing along
its streets and avenues. It encompassed the
areas earmarked for each tribe where they
could build their dwellings. Above all, it
was organized to meet economic needs,
with sites allocated to economic activity, the
sûqs which were a direct reminder of
Medina where the Messenger of God had
himself organized them, separating com¬
merce from prayer, market from mosque,
thus putting an end to the traditional, age-
old, oriental muddle. It was by this action
that the süq, until then a sort of fair, became
a distinctive feature of urban life.
All this is a far cry from the sententious
pronouncements of Orientalists anxious to
demonstrate, by their assessments of the
Islamic city, that the city in the full sense of
the term is really an exclusively European
phenomenon. How can' Küfah, with its
planned space, its urban sub-units, its politi¬
cal and religious centre, its well laid out
avenues and streets, be considered a hap
hazard construction? One should talk
rather in terms of an overall master-plan.
The rationale is so profound, especially in
the harmony achieved between human and
institutional needs, that the original outline
long remained, despite the later separation
of vocational and functional institutions, so
evident in the palace-city: "A universe of
courtyards, houses, public baths and
strange doorways, decorated in an extraor¬
dinarily rich style [such as] appeared in the
tale of 'The City of Copper' from The Thou¬
sand and One Nights."4
MOHAMMED ALLAL SINACEUR, director of
Unesco's Philosophy Division and professor of
the sociology of development at Hassan II Uni¬
versity, Casablanca (Morocco), was formerly a
research officer at the French Centre National de
la Recherche Scientifique. He has written widely
on philosophical problems and on the history of
mathematics.
4. La formation de l'art islamique ("The Making of
Islamic Art") by Olcg Grabar. Editions Flammarion,
Paris. 1987.
r
Try 0- * I £* A4
Aerial view of the medieval city of Bozrah
(Syria) shows its maze of narrow streets,
massive citadel and the east-west road
which was once the main thoroughfare.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Fighting words
The myth of the 'hereditary enemy :
IN his essay "The Writer's Profes¬
sion",1 Elias Canetti (Nobel Prize
for Literature, 1981) quotes an
anonymous author who wrote, a week
before the outbreak of the Second World
War: "... everything is over. If I were
really a writer, I would have to be able to
prevent the war!"
Canetti's immediate response is not
unlike my own reaction and that of many
others to the Slovene P.E.N. Centre's
proposal to create a "writers for peace"
committee: "an example of the blustering
that has discredited the word writer and
filled us with mistrust as soon as a mem¬
ber of the guild beats his breast and comes
out with his colossal intentions."
But Canetti then has second thoughts
and causes me to follow suit. In the sad¬
ness of the poet's statement, in its admis¬
sion of failure, there is the affirmation of
a responsibility the sincerity of which can¬
not be doubted. Canetti admits that a
situation in which war becomes inevitable
can be created through "words, deliber¬
ate and used over and over again, mis¬
used words", and then goes on to ask: "If
words can do so much why cannot
words hinder it [war]?" And he adds
and here too I think he is speaking
directly to us writers "It is not at all
surprising that a man who deals with
words more than other people do will also
expect more of words and their effect."
Of course wars have always originated
in conflicts of interest. However, even
this statement of the obvious should be
analysed, since the term interest is as fath¬
omless as life itself. Was it really in the
best interests of the Greeks to send their
heroes en masse to sack Troy and retrieve
Helen, even if the beauty of the princess
should be seen as an image for strategic
positions and trade monopolies? Can
there be any doubt that he who argues
most eloquently and persuasively will
always win his case?
1. "The Writer's Profession", in The Conscience of
Words by Elias Canetti, translated from German by
Joachim Ncugroschcl, André Deutsch. London. 1986.
by Jean Blot
Photo © International P.E.N, London
The logo of International P.E.N. (Poets and
Playwrights, Essayists and Editors, and
Novelists), a world association of writers
founded in London in 1921, which today
has over 10,000 members from all conti¬
nents and around 90 centres worldwide.
More recent events demonstrate that
"interests" are not necessarily related to
obvious factors. I have never been able to
get anyone to explain where the interests
of William II's Germany lay in the First
World War, of which it was to a large
extent the cause and architect, although I
have been assured that competition
between German and Serbian pork had
something to do with it.
Who would ever agree to lay down his
life for a pig or to sell more pork? Sub¬
stitute gold, oil, roads or rivers for this
perhaps unjustly despised animal, and
the question remains just as scandalous.
To mask interests, to present them in
such a way that they appear vital and that
people will agree to risk their lives to
defend them, a vast operation of verbal
camouflage is needed to transform reality
into emotion, passion, enthusiasm. Such
a task calls for the gifts of the poet and
writer.
Wars have always been preceded by
vast battalions of words. As writers, we
have a nebulous influence over the vested
interests that lie at the root of conflicts,
but over the battalions of words which
precede, mask and transfigure these
"War, my children, serves to defend our
Interests," reads the caption to this car¬
toon published during the First World War
in a 1915 issue of the Italian newspaper
Avanti.
interests, our control is direct, our
responsibility is great. It is all the greater
since in the past our talents have often
been used in the interests of belligerence.
War precedes peace in the sense that the
fear that underlies it and of which it is the
projection and the theatre precedes cour¬
age. In the infancy of the species and of
the individual, the stranger immediately
inspires dread. The poet and writer is a
child of depths and origins. He is most at
home on very ancient ground. Myth suits
us better than enlightenment.
If vested interests must wear a mask in
order to arm and deceive those who serve
them, their first ally will be the atavistic
fear of the other, of the stranger. Those
who serve such interests will mobilize this
archaic fear and direct it along lines which
suit them. Since experience alone shows
that the world is habitable, the unknown
is felt as a threat.
We thought men were white. But
here's someone who is yellow or black.
We thought men were small and thin . But
here's someone who's tall and fat. We
thought men had turned-up noses. Here's
someone with an aquiline nose. This
hooked nose, this belly, this stature, this
swarthy skin are bound to mean trouble
for me, since, in my inexperience, they
Photo © All Rights Reserved
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
frighten me! From my fear I project the
evil they have in store for me.
And what's more, these nightmarish
creatures, whom later, slightly reassured,
I shall regard as caricatures of humanity,
speak no human language. Can these
grunts really be a language? And if they
do attempt to speak in human language,
by which I mean the language that / speak
and understand, they violate, deform and
destroy it. In the violence they inflict on
my language I see the hatred which moti¬
vates them and which they will soon be
venting on me. Thus in Balzac there are
whole pages of mimicry of Jewish or Ger¬
man accents; they are not crimes but per¬
haps they should be considered as
offences of war and racism. The person is
hated through his accent, and through
him the human group to which he
belongs.
Bo'dy, language, accent. Every custom
or habit is impregnated with values con¬
sciously or unconsciously held. These val¬
ues express and sustain the identity of the
group and the individual who belongs to
it. Who am I but a man who does not eat
pork? If another man eats pork in my
presence, is he trying to show me his iden¬
tity or to attack mine? It boils down to the
same thing. For the wine drinker, the
beer drinker is suspect. Eating habits are
rooted in the depths of the psyche.
The English reputation for coldness
owes much to the fact that English people
only shake hands on exceptional occa¬
sions; the French reputation for sensual
or sexual excess to the fact that the
French kiss in the street. All these factors
and many more will be taken up by vested
interests when they need to mobilize one
group against another, to describe an
enemy who is both frightful and des¬
picable since everything about him
what he drinks, eats, his clothing, his
behaviour proves that he does not
belong to humanity.
So far I have only spoken of inex¬
perience. We should not forget the
manipulation of experience. For cen¬
turies, in a relatively stabilized world,
peoples have lived side by side, but pro¬
foundly isolated by mutual incomprehen¬
sion of their respective languages,
customs and values. Each conflict, in
spite of the disappointment bred by its
outcome, almost as great among the vic¬
tors as among the vanquished, in spite of
the immediately evident absurdity of its
result, prepares and heralds the next.
Experience confirms my obscure intui¬
tion that the stranger is dangerous. I
thought I had unmasked an assassin. And
that's exactly what he is. My share in the
crime is all the more quickly forgotten, if
it is not concealed, since the people
around me, starting with writers and
poets, are talking only of heroism. They
will translate vague intuitions into words,
images and verses, and populate the
unconscious with the features of the
hereditary enemy. If I have doubts, I shall
find certainty in their work.
If we writers have done much to create
the hereditary enemy and exclude him
from humanity, to prove that he kills and
to justify killing him, we can do as much
to destroy the myth. It is up to us, and we
alone possess this power, to make the
stranger a familiar figure , to eradicate the
fear which he naturally provokes.
The process of identification dear to
the novelist is of great importance here. It
is for us to reveal the hereditary or poten¬
tial enemy from the inside, as if we were
what he is. Is it really possible, on reading
Tolstoy, to believe for a second that a
Russian only removes the dagger from
between his teeth when he wants to
knock back a glass of vodka? That a Ger-
-
i
V
!
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
"Can there be any doubt that he who
argues most eloquently and persuasively
will always win his case?" Above, public
meeting in Paris, 1954.
"If we writers have done much to create the
hereditary enemy ... we can do as much to
destroy the myth. " Left, Fight with Sticks, a
work (c.1820) by the Spanish artist Fran¬
cisco Goya (1746-1828).
man is nothing but beer, sausage and bay¬
onets when we read Werther or Elective
Affinities? The literatures of countries
other than our own can play an immens^
role; it is our duty to make them better
known. The conflicts which divide us
doubtless remain. But they have become
human conflicts to which human solu¬
tions must be found.
The role played by our own literatures
is even more important. Norman Mailer's
novel The Naked and the Dead enabled
me to imagine for the first time what it
was like to be a young Japanese during
the war in the Pacific. The Lover, by the
Israeli writer Abraham B. Yehoshua,
gave me an idea of the feelings a young
Arab could have about the Israeli
bourgeoisie.
But so far I have only discussed the
simplest issue, the type of conflict which
we rightly think of as belonging to the
past. Modern wars, whether local or the
total war which we dare not even imag¬
ine, have or will have different founda
tions: racial wars, class wars, ideological
wars. Today it is easy to reconcile the
French and the Germans, the British and
the Americans. We only talk so openly
because the divisions between them are a
thing of the past. But who will dare
explain the Capitalist to the Bolshevik,
the proletarian to the bourgeois, and vice
versa? Who will dare proclaim, in the
conflict that divides them, their opposing
and equal humanity? The one excludes
the other from humanity. It is behind this
verbal mirage that the reality of war
announces itself. An impossible task,
perhaps. But if we refuse to shoulder it,
we can no longer talk of writers for peace.
Let us begin with the basic issues. Paci¬
fists and non-pacifists both wish for
peace. It is only the ways and means of
maintaining peace that divide them.
Some consider that peace can only be
assured by a balance of weaponry. Others
are in favour of a calculated risk and
believe that partial disarmament in a sit¬
uation of overarmament may bring about
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Unesco poster depicting a detail from The
Pigeons of Saint Mark, oil on canvas (1949)
by the Portuguese-born painter Maria
Elena Vieira da Silva.
a general movement of which peace, and
all peoples, will be the beneficiaries. The
choice of means divides them, but the
goal is the same. This must be proclaimed
time and time again.
It would be a mistake to forget that the
unanimous clamour for peace is a recent
phenomenon. Elias Canetti has pointed
out that humanity must fear the experi¬
ences that it has not yet had, the setbacks
it has not yet faced. He suggests that it is
easier today to exterminate an entire
population than it is to burn a single per¬
son on a fire in a public place. This is why
the apocalyptic experience of Hiroshima
and Nagasaki should not be forgotten.
There is another instinct, the instinct of
the survival of the species. It has
awakened, it reveals itself in a way which
is often confused and odious. We must
listen to it, express its mystery, capture
this spring of hope where it rises in the
depths of night, and use it to irrigate our
works and our inspiration. Other inclina¬
tions which come naturally to writers are
favourable to our project. War is only
possible in the abstract. It is for writers to
depict the horrors of war as concretely as
possible and to see that they are not con¬
cealed. Another natural inclination
comes to our aid. Men and women of
sensibility, we take more pleasure than
most in diversity. This delight in the
diversity and wealth of the human species
should be captured and communicated in
a spate of joy which will soon wash fear
away.
JEAN BLOT is the pen name of the French writer
Alexandre Blokh, who is Secretary of Internation¬
al P.E.N, a world association of writers. Critic,
essayist, translator and specialist in Russian
literature, he is the author of a number of novels
including Les cosmopolites (7976, "The Cosmo¬
politans") and Gris du ciel (1981, "Sky-Grey"). In
1986 he published the first biography of the
Swiss writer Albert Cohen, and Ivan Gontcharov
ou le réalisme impossible ("Ivan Goncharov or
Impossible Realism"). The above article is an
edited and abridged version of an address that
he gave last year in Bled, Slovenia (Yugoslavia),
during a meeting of International P.E.N's Writers
for Peace Committee, on the theme of "The
Hereditary Enemy".
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Emblem of the United Nations Decade of
Disabled Persons (1983-1992)
Society and the disabled
IN the last twenty years and especially
since 1 981 , the International Year of Dis¬
abled Persons, the integration of dis¬
abled young people into the ordinary educa¬
tion system has become widely accepted and
is now a prominent goal of educational plan¬
ning in many countries.
This undeniable change in attitudes and
behaviour towards disabled people is playing
an essential role in their integration into work¬
ing life and into the societies to which they
belong. This integration is based on the fun¬
damental principles of equality of access to
education and the full participation of all per¬
sons, including the disabled, in social life and
in national development. It is one of the objec¬
tives of the World Programme of Action con¬
cerning Disabled Persons which was adopted
by the General Assembly of the United Na¬
tions in 1982. Unesco is co-operating with
other specialized agencies of the United Na¬
tions system in implementing the Programme,
which was included in Unesco's Second
Medium-Term Plan (1 984-1 989). The integra¬
tion of disabled young people into ordinary
schooling is already being carried out in many
Unesco Member States on a long-term basis,
to the benefit of both the disabled themselves
and of the education systems in these coun¬
tries, which thereby become more flexible.
Integration contributes to the acceptance of
"differences", promotes mutual tolerance and
respect and encourages the democratization
of education.
The concept of "handicap" has been great¬
ly modified in the last two decades. It is now
distinguished from that of "impairment" or
"disability" and is defined as a disadvantage
for a given individual, resulting from an impair¬
ment or a disability, that limits or prevents the
fulfilment of a role that Is normal, depending
on age, sex, social and cultural factors, for
that individual. Handicap is therefore a func¬
tion of the relationship between disabled per¬
sons and their environment. It occurs when
they encountercultural, physical or social bar¬
riers which prevent their access to the various
systems of society that are available to others.
Thus, handicap is the loss or limitation of
opportunities to take part in the life of the
community on an equal level with others.
This new concept of what it means to be
handicapped highlights the relative nature of
differences between the performances or sta¬
tus of disabled people and those of others,
and draws attention to the fact that these gaps
may be reduced, if not removed, by appropri¬
ate action on the disabled person's physical,
psychological, educational and social en¬
vironment, and by measures to make him or
her as self-reliant as possible.
From an educational point of view, the in¬
tegration of disabled people requires specific
measures, and above all that account should
be taken of the special situation of each hand¬
icapped child or adolescent. The nature and
importance of the disability should be eva¬
luated, along with the possibilities of educa¬
tion and of developing" individual aptitudes,
following the strategy best adapted to each
case. The breaking down of barriers within
institutions, the setting up of multi-disciplinary
educational teams and the use of varied
teaching methods are required.
Integration into ordinary education takes
different forms in different countries, some¬
times even within the same country, depend¬
ing on requirements and on the facilities
available. Nevertheless all these forms are a
response to the same overriding concern: to
encourage the development of each child's
personality and to ensure his or her eventual
integration into adult society. In the article
overleaf, a specialist describes the integration
process in Portuguese schools today and pre¬
sents in their own words the testimony of two
visually handicapped children.
The integration of disabled children into the ordinary education system is a goal being
pursued in many countries. Alia Zureikat, a young Jordanian girl afflicted with cerebral
palsy, attends an ordinary school in Amman. According to her teachers, Alia, here seen
holding her younger brother in her arms, is a highly motivated and enthusiastic pupil
whose level in some subjects is higher than the class average.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Breaking down the barriers
for visually handicapped children
by Maria Adelaide Moreira de
Moráis Alves
Catia Susana when aged 8
THE social and educational integration of
visually handicapped children and young
people in schools forming part of the ordi¬
nary education system is today the policy of the
Special Teaching Division of the Portuguese
Ministry of Education and Culture, which is
responsible for the education of the disabled.
Since the beginning of the 1970s, the Division
has followed the lead taken by other countries,
notably the United States.
As a result, blind and amblyopic1 children who
were formerly educated in private institutions or
boarding schools (where State intervention was
minimal), cut off from society and separated from
their families, now have an opportunity to attend
ordinary schools.
The first step in this direction was the creation
of salas de apoio, or support classes, in primary
and secondary schools in the main cities of Por¬
tugal. In these cities were the boarding establish¬
ments where the blind and amblyopic pupils
completed four years' primary education before
entering the secondary schools where support
classes had been created. They continued to live
either in the boarding schools or at home. The
support classes were staffed by specialized
teachers who provided pupils and subject teach¬
ers with teaching materials and advice on
changes in the curricula necessary to cater for
the type and degree of disability suffered by each
pupil.
1. Amblyopia: dimness of vision without apparent
change in the eye structures. Editor.
However, this system soon proved to be inad¬
equate. The support classes were few, and the
numbers of visually handicapped pupils in them
constantly increased until they came to form
"colonies" within the schools. The visually hand¬
icapped young people stuck together and sel¬
dom mixed with the other pupils during recrea¬
tion periods or in their free time. There was no
real social integration.
Moreover, in order to attend these secondary
schools, pupils from other cities and from rural
areas had to be separated from their families and
friends. When these pupils returned home after
completing their studies, they were treated as
outsiders. They felt uprooted; they had no
friends; they had lost touch with their community
and had great difficulty in fitting back into it. Many
of them, especially those from rural areas,
refused to return. They could not face the pros¬
pect of going back to the humble homes where
they had been born and living among those
whose culture and habits were now quite dif¬
ferent from their own.
One pupil from a village once said something
which shocked me and impelled me to do all I
could to change the system. "You bring us here,"
he said, "to turn us into birds with clipped
wings."
It was urgent to solve the problems stemming
from the young peoples' isolation from their fam¬
ilies and from society. This could only be done by
creating the conditions for "full-scale integra¬
tion", so that visually handicapped pupils could
go on living with their families in their home
environment and attend local schools like other
children and teenagers, use the same public
transport facilities, play the same games, and
experience the same pleasures and the same
problemsin short, be a part of the community.
After the necessary legislation had been pre¬
pared, it soon became clear that legislation in
itself was not enough. A much more difficult
problem had arisen. It would be necessary to
change the attitudes of teachers who, through
feelings of uncertainty or mistrust, through preju¬
dice or because they were unwilling to put them¬
selves out, refused to accept visually handicap¬
ped pupils or, when they did, left them on the
sidelines.
This was the mid-1 970s, and the struggle was
a hard one. Today, with few exceptions to the
general rule, the integration of the visually hand¬
icapped in Portugal can be said to have become
a reality.
Today pupils are integrated into ordinary
schools as early as possible, and are provided
with support from specialized teachers. Each
pupil can be given back-up teaching two or three
times a week, depending on the gravity of the
handicap and the level of instruction. The teach¬
ers periodically advise the parents about their,
children's education and other activities that may
contribute to their balanced development. They
also alert parents about the need for regular
medical attention.
We cannot claim that everything is perfect:
indeed, we are only too aware of our limitations,
including a shortage of specialized teachers, the
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
lack of facilities to produce teaching materials,
and lack of funds to purchase better equipment.
However, we believe that it was necessary to
choose the lesser evil, and the sheer pleasure of
seeing our children and young people grow up
within their families, be accepted by their fellow
pupils, display the same abilities and the same
limitations, and become fully-fledged members
of the community, strengthens our conviction
that we are on the right track.
Boarding schools and special schools have
not disappeared. They will continue to exist,
especially for the more severe cases of multiple
disablement calling for more constant attention
and the use of a wider range of techniques.
These establishments are working with the sup¬
port teachers in the integrated education system
on developing training methods and organizing
vacation courses.
The following remarks illustrate how the
approaches described above have affected the
lives of two visually handicapped Portuguese
children who are integrated into schools in the
ordinary education system.
Catia Susana was born with severe malforma¬
tions in both eyes involving the degeneration of
the iris and the cornea. At the present time, she
can just about perceive the light. She lives with
her parents and elder brother in Santarem, a
town some 90 kilometres from Lisbon. At three
years of age, she attended nursery school just
like any other child and at six went on to the
primary school in the area where she lives. She
is now in her third year and was nine years old in
June. It is clear that she is fully integrated into the
school from the way she talks about it and her
friends:
"The teacher is good and amusing and
teaches well. She is kind, but since I'm a chatter¬
box she is always telling me to be quiet. She has
separated me from the others, but she has put
me next to a boy called Rodrigo, and we are
always talking to each other. I read to him what I
have written and we talk about all sorts of things.
"I learned typing in my second year, so as to
be able to write without seeing. I already know
how to type, but I can also write in Braille.
"I go to school with my mother, but I some¬
times go on my own, with my stick. I know the
area well and when I go down the street, I guide
myself by the curve of the houses. In the after¬
noon, when I come out of school, I go home with
my girlfriends and we play with dolls, or else I
read my stories to them until my mother comes.
At other times, I go to a local shop where there Is
a little dog I like very much, and I also go to visit
my old nurse. I don't go out at rush-hours, but If I
am a bit late, I ask somebody to help me cross
the street."
Catla's parents have learnt to accept her dis¬
ability and lavish affection on her, without show¬
ing either overprotectiveness or rejection.
Catia's intellectual development is superior to
the norm for her age, perhaps because she has
always received encouragement. Her mother
says, "When she was very young, I tried to teach
her by reading her all the stories I could lay my
hands on and by giving her detailed descriptions
of illustrations in the books." This may explain
Catia's enthusiasm for reading and writing.
She says: "My favourite subject is Portuguese
language and then grammar. ... I write whenever
I can, both at school and at home, in prose or in
verse, depending on my mood." Her mother
says: "Reading is her world," to which Catia
adds: "Books make my mouth water because
there are so many marvellous stories to read."
Catia spends her free time with her parents
and with other friends of her age, goes to the
beach or on walks, or stays at home reading,
writing or playing with her dolls. She also goes
swimming and has already had music lessons.
She began by being very enthusiastic because
she was very fond of music, but she ended up by
losing interest in the lessons because "the
teacher was too demanding". Catia is a very
determined child: she is a perfectionist and
hence she loses interest in anything that she
cannot succeed at right from the start. What
more could be expected of a nine-year-old
child?
I asked her to think of a message for children
all over the world. She pondered for a moment
and then wrote the following words: "THE SUN.
When the sun shines brightly, it makes the blond
hair of some children shine too, like the coins
they need to live. The sun is a playful figure who
gives life to all children and all hearts and brings
them together, whether they are red, white, black
or yellow. In every country, if the sun shines, then
hearts, hands and arms join together to turn the
world's children Into flowers that will form great
clusters of love and friendship."
Renato Jorge is totally blind. His premature
birth and very low birth weight account for the
many health problems he had in his early years.
He lives near Lisbon with his parents and grand¬
parents. He is now twelve years old and is in his
sixth year at the Vasco da Gama de Melecas
college. He is a happy, high-spirited child who
expresses himself easily and precisely.
"Before I came to the college, I was at three
other schools. The first of these was rightly called
the 'Inicio' (the 'Beginning'). I only stayed there a
month because I still felt very ill and it was hard
for me to be away from my parents. I had prob¬
lems fitting in. Then I spent a year with my grand¬
mother, but my parents dropped in to see me
whenever they could. When I was four, I went to
the A-da-Beja school for two years. From then
onwards I remember things better.
"When I was six, I went to the Antonio Feli¬
ciano de Castilho Institute in Lisbon, which was a
school for children and young people with eye¬
sight problems. The teachers and my school-
friends were very good to me and really helped
Renato Jorge, aged 12
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
me to 'grow' because I was very frail and back¬
ward. At the Institute, I had two women teachers
who were not only kind to me but were very good
at teaching, and aroused my interest in lessons. I
spent a lot of time playing with my friends and
those who could still see and those who were
blind used to play tricks on one another.
"My mother took me to school every morning
and collected me every afternoon. There were
fewer people at the Institute than at the college
where I am now. It was a family affair, whereas
my present school is very large. That is the only
difference between them, since both of them are
equally good. I feel happy in the college where I
am now. I like everything about it. The curriculum
is well organized and I like the way the teachers
treat me.
"I responded at once to the very first lessons
because the teachers, who had never had a blind
person in their classes before, taught me just like
the pupils who had their sight. I have never felt
that they make the slightest distinction between
me and the others. When they write^n the black¬
board, they dictate out loud what they are writing
and sol have no problem in taking notes. I enjoy
all subjects, although I have more difficulties with
visual education. However, the teacher makes
adjustments when there are things in the curricu¬
lum that I cannot cope with. My favourite subjects
are history and natural science. I have always
been fond of history because I like to understand
why we have reached our present situation,
good or bad.
"My schoolfriends are very nice. Whenever
somebody has a birthday, he invites the others.
A great idea! In my free time, I do judo, take
music lessons and go on bicycle rides. I have
also done some horse-riding. I had to drop It
because I did not have enough time, but plan to
take it up again. At weekends or during the long
vacation, I go out with my parents and friends. I
have many friends- of my own age with whom I
can play, but I also very much like talking to older
people because I am always trying to improve
my Portuguese and acquire more knowledge.
They can teach me the things they have learnt
from their own experience.
"At home, I help my mother to dust the house
and my father to mend the fence or the cart if
necessary."
Renato made this long statement almost with¬
out a break, displaying admirable self-assurance
and equanimity. Whenever he referred to his
parents or to other members of his family, he did
so with great affection and with a smile on his
lips. My final question was whether he too would
like to send a message to other young people.
He replied without hesitation as follows:
"I should like to say to the readers of this article
that if they are disabled, or if they have children
who are disabled, they should take life as it
comes, as I do. If they do that, they may succeed
in overcoming their problems more easily. That
is my family's motto and we have had plenty of
problems to contend with."
That is the message of courage and hope
which visually handicapped Portuguese young
people wish to address to the world. By their
example, these young people teach us to face
life with optimism and to fight for our ideals.
MARIA ADELAIDE MOREIRA DE MORÁIS
ALVES is a Portuguese educator who is re¬
sponsible within her country's Ministry of Educa¬
tion for the basic education of visually handicap¬
ped young people. She has organized many
seminars and training courses to help teachers
overcome the problems of integrating disabled
children into the ordinary education system and
regularly takes part in national and International
meetings and workshops devoted to the educa¬
tion of handicapped children.
irait oí snov
Vuk Stefanovic Karadzic
Profile of a great scholar
The bicentenary of the birth of the Serbian writer and
scholar Vuk Stefanovic Karadzic, who made an out¬
standing contribution to the culture of Yugoslavia, is
being celebrated as an occasion of international sig¬
nificance on 6 November 1987. To honour the memory
of this great figure, we publish below an account of his
life and achievements together with short extracts
from his works.
FATHER of Serbo-Croat literature,
great reformer of the Serbian lan¬
guage and spelling system, founder
of Serbian Romanticism, linguist, eth¬
nographer and historian, Karadzic played a
pioneering role in the cultural history of
Yugoslavia.
Born into a farming family at Trsic (Ser¬
bia) in 1787, he attended local schools but
was largely self-taught. In 1813 he took
refuge in Vienna and lived there, except for
a few short absences, until his death in
1864.
In Vienna he met a Slovene scholar,
Jernej Kopitar, who encouraged him and
introduced him to such leading European
writers and thinkers as Johann Wolfgang
von Goethe, Jacob Grimm, Leopold von
Ranke and Friedrich Engels. Karadzic's
first collection of epic poems, published in
1814, brought him to the attention of an
educated readership. In addition to his
many other activities, he devoted his life to
the collection and publication of works
from the Serbian oral literary tradition,
notably in "Serbian Folk Tales" (1821),
"Serbian Folk Sayings" (1836) and, above
all, the multi-volume "Serbian Epic Poems"
(1814-1866).
His efforts to record and preserve the
treasures of oral literature formed part of
his struggle to gain acceptance for the spo¬
ken language as the language of literary
expression, and to create an alphabet which
would be adapted to Serbian phonetics and
would obey his dictum: "Write as you
speak, read as it is written." Karadzic sim¬
plified the spelling system so that each
sound corresponded to a single letter,
finally devising an alphabet of thirty letters
that is one of the most scientific and logical
in the world today.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Preserving the oral heritage
His linguistic works include the first Ser¬
bian grammar which was reviewed by
Goethe and a "Serbian Lexicon" (1818), a
Serbo-Germanic-Latin dictionary which
did full justice to the rich vocabulary of
popular speech. The second edition (1852,
reprinted in 1934) remains a classic
reference work.
The translation of the New Testament
into the popular idiom that Karadzic com¬
pleted in 1847 laid the foundations of the
Serbo-Croat language, which was to
become the common tongue of the Serbs
and the Croats.
Karadzic was a revolutionary figure who
sought to bring about the political and spir¬
itual awakening of his people through
books. As well as his efforts to create a
national language and a new spelling sys¬
tem, he produced a body of historical and
ethnographic works, which, especially in his
"The Serbian Revolution" (1829) and
"Montenegro and the Montenegrins"
(1837), are dominated by his realistic vision
of social relationships and by his sense of
perspective.
During his lifetime Karadzic achieved a
European reputation. In 1823 he was the
guest of Jacob Grimm in Kassel and of
Goethe in Weimar; the same year he
received an honorary doctorate from the
University of Jena. In 1824 he became a
member of the Turin Society for Antiquities
and, in 1825, of the Göttingen Learned
Society. In 1842 he was awarded a gold
medal for his scholarship and literary
achievements by the Russian Academy of
Sciences. He became a corresponding
member of the Viennese Academy in 1848,
the Berlin Academy in 1850 and the St.
Petersburg Academy in 1851. He was
also a corresponding member of the Paris-
based African League for Combat Against
Slavery.
Karadzic owes his greatness not only to
the originality of his ideas and thé tenacity
with which he expressed them, but also to
the links he made between the traditions of
his people and international culture: as a
thinker he made a major contribution to the
spiritual unity of mankind.
Article and selection have been compiled from material
provided by Marija Biäof, author of Vuk Stefanovic"
Karadiié Bicentenary 1787-1987, a quadrilingual
(English, French, German and Russian) brochure pub¬
lished in Belgrade
Article and selection have been compiled from material
provided by Marija BiSof, author of Vuk Stefanovié
KaradzióBicentenary 1787-1987, a quadrilingual
(English, French, German and Russian) brochure pub¬
lished In Belgrade
Yugoslav postcard showing the thirty let¬
ters of the Serbian alphabet as devised by
Karadzió, in upper and lower case. The six
boxed letters are those which he added to
correspond to sounds In the spoken lan¬
guage which formerly had no graphic
equivalent. His signature appears below
the alphabet.
Write as you speak, read as it is written.
(Preface to the "Serbian Grammar", 1814)
As long as the spoken word of the people is
pure and unaltered, literary language
should not be distinct from the language of
the people. Why should it be different?
Don't we see people in our time discarding
the literary language of the past in order to
write in the language of the people as it is
today? ... Please God that we should be
able to write books in the way that the peo¬
ple speak ...
(Correspondence, 1845)
I am convinced that my efforts and my task
will be appreciated by all our writers and
authors who love the language of the people
and respect it as the most precious posses¬
sion of the people, for whom they wish hap¬
piness and progress. On the other hand, I
have not tried to please those who, while
speaking the Serbian language, heap abuse
on it and claim that it is worthless and no
more than a tainted language, the speech of
swineherds and horse-traders.
The greatest outcry will be raised against
the spelling system. But here too I hope that
all our writers will be on my side, all those
who are familiar with language and writing.
And they will see that this is the most appro¬
priate way to write the Serbian language.
(Preface to the "Serbian Lexicon'.', 1818)
A man with nothing else to do could easily
devote his whole life to bringing together all
our folksongs, our stories, our tales, our
riddles, our customs and our words. And
when he came to think he had finished the
task, he would see that he was only just
starting. ... These works of folk art must be
collected before they are altered or even
stifled by new, more "enlightened"
fashions.
Songs, riddles, folktales, these are a highly
accomplished form of popular literature, to
which there is nothing to add. They should
simply be collected and their purity should
be scrupulously respected. And when tran¬
scribing these tales, it is certainly advisable
to think of the construction of the words
(not, I repeat, according to one's own taste,
but following the genius of the Serbian lan¬
guage) so as to avoid any form of excess,
and to'succeed in such a way that cultivated
souls can read them and uneducated folk
can listen to them ...
(Preface to "Serbian Folk Tales", 1821)
Our folksongs can all be divided into epic
poems, sung to the accompaniment of the
guzla, and women's songs, sung by women
and girls but also by men, most often youths
singing in unison. More than the women's
songs, the epic poems are intended for a
public, hence the utmost importance of
their text.
(Preface to "Serbian Epic Poems", 1824)
Our Serbian folksongs do not come from
parchment manuscripts, they were col¬
lected from the warm lips of the people;
they are not old because they have never yet
been recorded in writing, but they will cer¬
tainly live to a ripe old age ...
Jacob Grimm
(Review of the third volume of "Serbian Epic
Poems", 1823)
Mother and daughter
Aie, aie, aie, mother, a monk is wakening
me,
He is wakening me, kissing my eyelids!
Must I kiss him, oh my mother?
Kiss, my daughter, do not be damned !
When your mother was the same age ,
Before dawn, she had embraced nine,
And your father, he was the tenth,
And she had woven three lengths ofcarpet!
(Traditional poem collected by Karadzic and
published in "The Red Duke" [erotic folk
poems], Prosveta publishers, Belgrade, 1979)
A 5 B r 4 "B E >K 3 H
a 6 b r a h e hî 3 h
m J K Jl Jb M H H) o n p
! J K ./I Jb M H H, o n p
1 C T
E
lt\ y 4> x u h ¥ in
ÎË c m Ji
c
ra
Z
>
v>
y $ x it q V UI.
>
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A world congress on copyright teaching
by Yves Gaubiac
UNESCO is holding a World Con¬
gress on Copyright Teaching and
Information in Paris in September
1987 in order to mark the thirty-fifth anni¬
versary of the Universal Copyright Con¬
vention, which was signed on 6 September
1952 and the secretariat of which ¡s
provided by Unesco.
The theme of the Congress, which is
directly related to Unesco's mandate in the
field of education, has been chosen because
many infringements of copyright are due to
lack of information and knowledge.
The provision of information and educa¬
tion about copyright is an indispensable
part of any effort to ensure that copyright is
respected. The idea of literary and artistic
property is not universally shared. There is
no basic reflex relating to justice and equity
for creators. Education and training are
needed in order to create this reflex. Once
¡n'circulation, created works are often seen
as common property which can be freely
used. Works should certainly be circulated
as widely as possible, in order to satisfy
people's legitimate desire to enjoy the crea¬
tions of the mind. But the use of a work
without its author's consent and in the
absence of any remuneration is harmful to
creative activity since it deprives authors
and their rights holders of the financial
resources necessary to create and invest in
the production of new works.
Copyright is recognized in the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights of 10 Decem¬
ber 1948, which states that "Everyone has
the right to the protection of the moral and
material interests resulting from any scien¬
tific, literary or artistic production of which
he is the author".
Copyright is now an accepted right. It
should be more widely known if it is to be
more widely respected.
YVES GAUBIAC, of France, is a consultant with
Unesco's Copyright Division.
Bookshelf
The Education of Children and Young People
who are Mentally Handicapped, by Dorothy
M. Jeffree. 79 pp., 1986; Working together,
Guidelines for partnership between profes¬
sionals and parents of children and young
people with disabilities, by Peter Mittler, Hel¬
le Mittler and Helen McConachie. 63 pp.,
1986; Testing and Teaching Handicapped Chil¬
dren and Youth in Developing Countries, by
David Baine. 63 pp., 1986. Nos. 1 , 2 and 3 in a
new series of "Guides for Special Education"
published by Unesco. The guides, which are
available free, are intended for teachers, pa¬
rents and community workers. Their aim is to
stimulate discussion on basic knowledge,
methods and techniques relevant to the educa¬
tion of disabled persons, and offer practical
advice for action in this field. Nos. 4 and 5 in
the series, Education of Deaf Children and
Young People, by the Centre for Total Com¬
munication, Copenhagen, Denmark, and
Language and Communication in the Educa¬
tion of Handicapped Pupils, by A. Labregère,
will be published later this year.
Terminology of Special Education. Revised
edition 1983. 167 pp. Quadrilingual: English/
French/Spanish/Russian. (30 French francs)
Constructive Education for Special Groups:
Handicapped and Deviant Children, by W.D.
Wall. 144 pp., 1979 (35 FF). Co-published
with George G. Harrap & Co. Ltd., London,
who have exclusive sales rights in the United
Kingdom.
Case Studies in Special Education: Cuba,
Japan, Kenya, Sweden. 195 pp., 1974 (24 FF)
Economic Aspects of Special Education:
Czechoslovakia, New Zealand, United States
of America. 152 pp., 1978 (24 FF)
The Present Situation and Trends of Research
in the Field of Special Education. Four studies:
Sweden and other Scandinavian countries,
USSR, USA and Uruguay. 306 pp., 1973 (28
FF)
International Yearbook of Education, Volume
XXXVIII1986. Primary Education on the
Threshold of the Twenty-first Century, pre¬
pared for the International Bureau of Educa¬
tion by José Luis García Garrido. 276 pp.,
1986.
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue , and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
. captions and headlines arc written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1 ) Unesco, 7
Place dc Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S. A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. , 11 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691 , U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief: Olga Rodel
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
NedaelKhazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian: Nikolai Kuznetsov
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)-
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
34
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) -Dépôt légal :C1 -Juillet 1987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Unesco publications on drugs
Drugs demystified
by Helen Nowlis
j drugs
mmm-
ISBN 92-3-101231-2
108 pp.
3rd edition, 1982
20 French francs
Published in ten languages, Drugs
Demystified is essential reading for all
parents and educators. Contents include:
Drugs and their effects
Drug use and drug users
The social context
Strategies for prevention
Educating against drug abuse
Preventive action against the abuse of legal and illegal drugs
concerns everyone, especially parents, teachers and those who
are closely involved with vulnerable persons and groups.
Illustrating the theoretical approach with specific examples,
Unesco has compiled this new publication which describes
attempts in different parts of the world to solve problems
associated with the use of legal and illegal drugs.
Also described are various approaches to prevention work
which have been developed as a result of international
co-operation.
ISBN 92-3-102479-5
86 pp. 42 FF
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collmgwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian
Division, 328 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung
Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools
International, Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726, Bahrain. BARBADOS.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64,
Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: Internationale
Drukkerij en Uitgeverij Keesing, Keesinglaan 2-20, 2100 Deurne-Anrwerpen.
CCP 000-001 2775-68. French edition and general Unesco publications agent:
Jean de Lannoy, 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internacionais Ltda, Processing Dept.. R
Peixoto Gomide 209, 01409, Sao Paulo SP. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road. Ottawa, Ontario K1B 3W8. STORES: 61 Sparks
Street, Ottawa. 21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. SALES OFFICE: 7575 Trans Canada
Hwy. Ste. 305, St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1 V6. CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51 -1 13 02, Prague 1 ; Ve Smeckach
30. P.O.B. 790-1 1 1-27 Prague 1 (Permanent display) ¡Zahranicni literatura. 1 1
Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag. -Publishers, Hurbanovo
nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tids-
skriftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Hart
St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box 128, SF-00100
Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641 Vantas 64. Rauti-
kirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1, 01641 Vantas 64. FRANCE.
Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Pans. CCP 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig. Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Oeutscher Unesco-Kuner
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides Entreprises, P.O.
Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE John
Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O. Box 10073, 541 10
Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore, 4 Nikis Street,
Athens T 1 26. Kostarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2 Hippocratous
Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-1 5, Lock Rd., Kowloon.
Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre, Baskerville
House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389.
Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjdrn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bom¬
bay 400038; 1 7 Chttaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai. Mount Road,
Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Rd., Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001 .
Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St., Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1 1 88 Englab
Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 1 31 58, P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498, Teheran.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Rd., Walkin-
stown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd.,
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv 61006A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283. 71
Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (übreria Commissionaria Sanso-
ni. S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 501 21 Florence. JAPAN.
Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El Correo de la
Unesco, Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle, Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British
Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Pol-
chowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1 000 AD
Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 14277-
Kilbirnie, Wellington; 130 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1 721 , Christchurch; Alma
St., P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Princes St., P.O. Box 1 1 04, Dunedin. NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of lie; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O: 286.
NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum. P.OB. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1; Narvesen
A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets
Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blmdern, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No.
729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI
ARABIA. Dar al Watan, Olaya Mam Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building,
Riyadh. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Re Ltd. Times Jurong, 2
Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas
Publications (Pty) Ltd., Subscription Service, P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg.
Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaik's
Bookstore (Pry) Ltd., Libri Building, 268 Church Street, Pretoria 0001 . Central
News Agency Ltd., Group Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 613, Cape Town
8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner
Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box 2943, Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Forbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm: Wennergren-
Williams AB, Nordenflychtsvagen 70. S-104, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidskrift-
scentralen. Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101 , 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, COP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne,
Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.,
40-42 Charoen Krung Road, Siyaeg Phaya Sn, P.O. Box 402. Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9. Rajdamnern Ave.. Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair.
Trinidad W 1 . TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesí, No 469, Posia
Kutusu 219, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office,
Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008, Nine Elms
Lane. London SWS 5DR. and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta
Ltd., 122 King's Cross Rd.. London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan-
UNIPUB. Periodicals Department, 4611-F Assembly Drive, Lanham, MD
20706 4391 . USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrov»39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, llica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
