<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="076585eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WW//
\\v\v
-
i \ \ \ v
y
tf:' »", '
n» iÉ^ hiÉtaii^^^j,^-,^.^^.^.
- * »*V *-^ y
ta» .
-»*,	 .^ '*
* TV , *.* * ' *' '^ * f
VO
irtft
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
A time to live . . .
59 Egypt
The staff of life
Smiles of satisfaction light up the faces bf these Egyptian village women
as they complete the time-honoured ritual of baking bread . In many parts
of the world bread has been a staple of human diet for some twelve
thousand years. The first bread, made in Neolithic times, probably
consisted of crushed grain, moistened with water and baked by being laid
on heated stones and covered with hot ashes. It is to the ancient Egyp¬
tians that we owe the invention of the bread oven and the discovery of the
fermentation process in wheat dough that makes possible the baking of
light aerated bread.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
One of the highlights of 1987 has been the publication of Our Common
Future, the report of the independent World Commission on Environment and
Development, commissioned by the United Nations. "The environment," says
the report, "is where we all live; and development is what we all do in
attempting to improve our lot within that abode. The two are inseparable."
The report goes on to say that "the changes in human attitudes that we
call for depend on a vast campaign of education, debate and public
participation. This campaign must start now if sustainable human progress is
to be achieved."
In this issue of the Unesco Courier we hope to further that campaign by
publishing extracts from a forthcoming report on Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) Programme, entitled Man Belongs to the Earth, in which a
serious attempt has been made to marry strict scientific accuracy with a style
accessible to the general reader.
The extracts published here do not by any means cover the entire range of
MAB activities. In particular, forests are deliberately not mentioned since we
shall be devoting a future issue of the Unesco Courier to this subject.
The extracts do, however, underline the message of the World
Commission on Environment and Development that development and
conservation of the environment, far from being incompatible, are inextricably
linked.
The year 1987 also marks the 150th anniversary of the birth of the
Georgian writer and poet llya Chavchavadze and the 100th anniversary of
the birth of Les Kurbas, founder of Soviet Ukrainian theatre. To conclude this
issue, we publish articles on the life and work of these two men, each of
whom played their part in the enrichment of world culture.
Cover: Man's partnership with nature and the progress being made along the road to
sustainable development are symbolized by this view of farmland near Ruijin, in the grain-
rich province of Kiangsi, in the middle Yangtze region of China.
Photo Georg Gerster © Rapho, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
October 1987
40th year
Man and the Biosphere
Sustainable development
by Bernd von Droste
4
The urban maze 8
Food for thought 12
Return of the griffon 13
Nature and culture 16
Painting the future 18
Islands at risk 20
Pirates, parasites and population
A case study 23
Information please 24
The canopy raft 25
Mountain challenge 27
Lake Baikal 30
The poetry of llya Chavchavadze
by Gaston Bouatchidzé and
Edouard Glissant
31
Les Kurbas, founder of Ukrainian
theatre
by Nelly Nicolaevna Kornlenko
32
Food for all The 'Paris Appeal'
by Yannis Coutsocheras
34
A time to live ...
EGYPT: The staff of life
The environmental section of this issue was
compiled in association with Malcolm Hadley,
of Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences,
and Howard Brabyn, science writer and former
editor of the English edition of the Unesco
Courier.
The Courier
A window open on the world
English
French
Spanish
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 33 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
German
Arabic
Japanese
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Korean
Swahili
Croato-Serb
Bulgarian
Greek
Sinhala
Vietnamese
ISSN 0041-5278
N°10-1987-CPD-87-l-450A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Sustainable development
by Bernd von Droste
Conservation and development are
two sides of the same coin
A quarter of a century has passed
since American biologist Rachel
Carson sat down to write The Silent
Spring, a book which was to become a
watershed in the brief history of ecology.
The graphic picture she drew of a world in
which, as a result of the indiscriminate use
of pesticides, the song of birds at spring¬
time would be lost for ever, captured the
imagination of the public. Suddenly there
was a new awareness of the intricate rela¬
tionships that link living organisms and their
environment, of man's oneness with nature
and the extent of his influence over it.
More importantly, perhaps, The Silent
Spring drew attention to the fact that there
were limits to the absorptive and regenera¬
tive powers of nature; whilst man had
always manipulated his environment, he
could no longer use it as an unfailing,
bottomless sink for pollutants and man-
generated wastes.
It is difficult today to believe that we
should still have needed to be reminded of
these seemingly self-evident facts. After all,
as far back as Aristotle's day, Theo-
phrastus, his disciple and successor as
head of the Lyceum in Athens, had written
at length about the inter-relationships
between organisms and their non-living
environment, and the idea of the unity of
organisms and environment has long been
a part of many religions.
For centuries, however, botanists and
biologists, geologists and demographers,
went their separate ways, and it was not
until the latter part of the nineteenth century
that the German zoologist Ernst Haeckel,
Right, a stretch ofthe GreatBarrierReefand,
above, a close up view of part of the most
remarkable coralformation in the world. The
Reef is inscribed as a World Heritage site.
tt
@
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
T "V
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The Simen Nationalpark and World Heritage
site, Ethiopia
the man who coined the term oekologie,
once again stressed the importance of "the
relation of the animal both to its organic as
well as to its inorganic environment".
Strangely enough, Haeckelian oekologie
was overshadowed rather than enhanced
by the Darwinian revolution and,
throughout the early part of this century,
ecological research was based on the
scantiest of theoretical foundations. It was
not until 1942, when R.L. Lindeman
developed his theory of the hierarchical
trophic (food chain) structure of eco¬
systems, which laid emphasis on the flow of
energy through ecosystems, that ecology
started to become an organized modern
science.
The subsequent development of compu¬
ters and of new techniques, such as label¬
ling with radio-isotopes, stimulated studies
of both energy and nutrient cycling through
ecosystems, and, as a result, the eco¬
system, as a functional unit made up of
interacting biotic (living) and abiotic (non¬
living) components through which energy
flows, became one of the unifying concepts
of ecology and the focus of much ecological
research.
This was a great step forward, but it was
not enough. The multidisciplinary approach
to research came up against serious diffi¬
culties. The research time span for a bota¬
nist studying crop succession, for example,
could be a matter of months, whereas that
required for, say, a forester, or a biologist
concerned with population dynamics, could
run into decades. Similar problems arose
over the size of the ecosystem under study.
Furthermore, despite Rachel Carson's
warning, there remained a tendency to look
at ecosystems from the "outside" and thus
to overlook the vital feature of man's impact
on ecosystems.
Two events were to help change all this:
the launching, in 1971, of Unesco's Man
and the Biosphere (MAB) Programme, and
the United Nations Conference on the
Human Environment, held in Stockholm in
1.972, both of which stressed the role of
man as a major environmental force.
The MAB Programme went further; it
stressed the need for an integrated, inter¬
disciplinary rather than mu/f/'-disciplinary
approach and brought the social sciences
into ecological research as an equal part¬
ner with the natural sciences. As a result,
the past fifteen years have seen the imple-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
mentation of a wide range of pilot projects
throughout the world, the building up of
research facilities in the developing world,
the accumulation of an impressive quantity
of environmental data and the forging of an
exciting new research tool an interna¬
tional network of biosphere reserves.
Underlying all this work was a new con¬
cept of fundamental importance the con¬
cept of "conservation for sustainable
development". In other words, ecologists in
MAB were no longer saying "Stop doing
that or you will destroy the environment".
Rather they were saying "Try doing this and
you can enjoy the benefits of development
and conserve the environment".
Nevertheless, as a Scientific Advisory
Panel pointed out to the International
Co-ordinating Council of MAB at Its ninth
session held in Paris in October 1986, a
number of theoretical and practical prob¬
lems remain.
One major problem has been the tend¬
ency to disregard the evolving nature of
ecosystems. We have tended to look at
ecosystems as the outcome of evolution
rather than as being constantly subject to
evolutionary processes. Disturbance in an
ecosystem may well be a moulding, driving
force in an evolutionary sense rather than a
destructive force.
In turn this attitude tends to colour our
approach to environmental "conservation"
or "restoration", words which seem to imply
a return to a pre-existing state, when we
should perhaps be thinking in terms of
achieving a new equilibrium equally if not
more beneficial to man.
On the more practical side, the Panel
proposed to build on past achievements in
a number of ways. It suggested that:
fuller use should be made of data from
the biosphere reserve network in the
development of comparative studies of
ecosystem functioning, such as the com¬
parative study now being undertaken on
the improvement of tropical soil fertility
through biological processes.
increased emphasis should be given to
approaches for handling the management
and re-development of ecological
resources degraded by man.
research on the changing relationships
between economic driving forces and ecol¬
ogical systems should be intensified.
greater use should be made of sophisti¬
cated modern risk assessment methods to
provide guidance for policy-makers con¬
cerning investment and resource use.
expert systems should be established
which could offer decision-makers rapid,
easy access to relevant information from
the vast wealth of ecological research data
already accumulated.
Finally, the Panel emphasized the com¬
plexity and increasingly global extent of
man's impact on the environment, in par¬
ticular where environmental disturbance is
concerned. What once were local incidents
of pollution confined to one watershed or air
basin now tend to involve many nations, as
witness the Chernobyl incident and the
growing problem of acid rain.
All this underlines the fact that the MAB
Programme itself is an evolving system,
and this implies not simply change, but also
the selection of successful trends and the
elimination of undesirable or ineffective
components.
The opening chapter of Our Common
Future, the recently published report of the
World Commission on Environment and
Development (often referred to as The
Brundtland Report, after its Chairman, Gro
Harlem Brundtland, Prime Minister of Nor¬
way) contains these words:
"Humanity has the ability to make
development sustainable to ensure that it
meets the needs of the present without
compromising the ability of future genera¬
tions to meet their own needs. ... Technol¬
ogy and social organization can both be
managed and improved to make way for a
new era of economic growth. The Commis¬
sion believes that widespread poverty is no
longer inevitable. Poverty is not only an evil
in itself, but sustainable development
requires meeting the basic needs of all and
extending to all the opportunity to fulfil their
aspirations for a better life. A world in which
poverty is endemic will always be prone to
ecological and other catastrophes."
It is the proud aim of Unesco's Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) Programme to do all
In its power to ensure that such catastro¬
phes do not occur.
BERND VON DROSTE is Secretary to the Inter-
national Co-ordinating Council tor the Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) Programme and Directorol
Unesco's Division of Ecological Sciences.
The GalapagosArchipelago, Ecuador, is both
a MAB biosphere reserve and a World
Heritage site.
Left, the Durmitor National Park and MAB
biosphere reserve, Yugoslavia
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The urban maze
No single thread has yet been found that
can guide us through the tortuous labyrinth of the city
IN a famous phrase recorded by his biog¬
rapher James Boswell, that peerless
eighteenth-century man of letters Sam¬
uel Johnson once declared that "when a
man is tired of London, he is tired of life, for
there is in London all that life can afford".
This was less a panegyric of London per
se than an affirmation of the fact that cities
are the melting-pot ot ideas and invention,
market-places for the exchange of informa¬
tion and centres of learning, the fount of
human culture and creativity in short, that
cities are the sine qua non of civilization.
For the medieval peasant, city life held an
additional attraction residence in a city for
a year and a day brought emancipation
from serfdom. "Stadtluft macht frei" (City
air brings freedom), declared Emperor
Henry the Fifth in drawing up the charters of
the cities of Speyer and Worms. And even
today, this same desire to escape the pov¬
erty and servitudes of rural life remains the
major driving force behind the explosive
expansion of many cities in the developing
world.
Dome of polluted
air (photochemical
smog, heat inversion
and changes in
the microclimate)
Deterioration of the
landscape (changes
in vegetation, erosion
construction)
8
Importation
of energy
Exportation
of materials
Groundwater
Sewage Polluted coastal water
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Concentrated
in birüsof prey
<4 Touba, Senegal
Accumulation
in polar ice caps
Right, a descriptive risk assessment model
illustrating what occurs when DDT is used in
a developing country and is recycled through
terrestrial and aquatic ecosystems.
^Tlunningof cgpshells-
/ reproductive lailurc in birds
-¿L~
Persists in soil half life or 10 years
Long tenu storage in sediment
Affects learning
processes. Alters
natural behaviour.
Abnormal growth
After Whyte and Burton, Environmental Risk Assessment, 1 980
©
©
Chang an jie Avenue, Beijing, China
Left, a qualitative input-output model show¬
ing the energy and materialsflows involved in
the metabolism of the city ofBarcelona.
To the ecologist, however, a city may
appear to be a very artificial system. It is
true that the sites of man's earliest fixed
settlements, such as the rich valleys of the
Fertile Crescent, were chosen for their
favourable environmental conditions, but
with each new technological advance the
city-dweller became increasingly divorced
from his "natural" environment until, today,
man is able to use almost any environment
for town living. Indeed, as Soviet space
experiments have shown, man can now live
for months on end in a totally artificial,
wholly man-made environment.
What is a city?
In these circumstances, the question arises
as to whether the ecological approach is
applicable to urban systems. What, indeed,
is a city? Is it an organism, and, if so, is it a
"parasite" with the natural environment as
its host? Is a city an organism within an
environment, or itself an entire ecosystem?
Urban ecologists are thus still seeking to
establish their discipline on a firm theoreti¬
cal basis, while at the same time being
swamped with demands for advice from
politicians and city bosses on how to handle
the horrific problems resulting from the
urban explosion.
The threat of massive failure of cities,
through resource depletion, disease and
famine, which has always existed, seems
more menacing than ever. In the general
confusion about the nature of the urban
phenomenon, ecologists have perforce
adopted an ad hoc approach.
As a result, urban ecology has come to
include a heterogeneous ragbag of study
topics. These range from studies of energy
and materials flows and the use of ecologi¬
cal indicators to measure urban environ¬
mental quality, to traditional and experi¬
mental building forms and the carrying
capacity of urban systems and ecological
support systems.
In practice, most urban studies under¬
taken within the MAB framework have
focused on one aspect only, such as the
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ill lu III in IH »¡Tin^iesa, 1 "^tfYrÄR1 T^MVl
» - V
» * -1 ! j
Mv "" li f
m. i& ' X-
" M| I
distribution of flora and fauna within urban
areas, or the human ecology of children in
the city.
One study, which explicitly aimed to inte¬
grate city-wide studies of energy, food and
water flows with a bio-social survey of indi¬
vidual quality of life and human adaptation
(Hong Kong), was unable to demonstrate
how a change in one level affected the
other, even though it seemed reasonable to
suppose they must be interlinked.
Although many of these case studies
have succeeded in providing a valuable
scientific basis for handling urban planning
problems specific to particular cities, the
original objective, of setting up an interna¬
tionally agreed comparative data set for
urban systems so that case studies could
be contrasted and compared so as to
provide answers to common, process-
oriented questions, has been virtually
abandoned.
This is because, owing to the sheer
speed and magnitude of the urban explo¬
sion, the problems themselves are chang¬
ing, both in scale and in nature, almost as
fast as the necessary data can be collected
and collated.
Under these circumstances it has been
well-nigh Impossible to establish agreed
data collection standards, and without stan¬
dardized units of measure and similar
descriptive parameters the individual stud¬
ies are doomed to remain no more than
Isolated case studies.
The way ahead
Today, a critical point has been reached in
the development of ecological approaches
to urban systems. No single thread has yet
been found that can guide us through the
tortuous labyrinth of the city.
The auguries, however, are good. In the
fifteen or so years since MAB was launched
a wealth of experience has been gained
and an impressive store of research data
acquired. The advent of the new generation
of micro-computers means that it is now
possible to make speedy and effective use
of these data to make comparative analysis
a reality and to realize the full potential of
systems analysis. Furthermore, introduc¬
tion of the technique of risk assessment
offers new horizons for urban ecology.
Comparative analysis
The option here is, in part, to go back to
basics and take up the work begun a
decade ago in setting up a comparative
data set for urban systems. The time is now
ripe to develop and agree a detailed, inter¬
national framework for data collection
which will include: (a) common parameters
for describing urban systems, and (b) the
variables required for specifying key sys¬
tem relationships. This is a prerequisite for
development of valid comparative analysis
of urban systems.
There remain considerable difficulties. It
may not be easy to formulate common
parameters that will encompass the older
cities with their history of slow, organic
growth and many modern cities which are
rapid, ad hoc, one might almost be tempted
to say "artificial" creations.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Systems analysis
With the arrival of the latest generation of
micro-computers, the full potential of sys¬
tems analysis as applied to urban systems
can now be realized. The work done ¡n con¬
structing input-output matrices and plotting
metabolic city flows can now be incorpo¬
rated into policy-oriented decision models.
These models will allow policy-makers to
assess the consequences for an eco¬
system of proposed actions, whether the
specific proposals be about green spaces, -
housing or transport.
In this connection, a state-of-knowledge
report is at present being prepared by a
joint working group* to assess the status
and potential of integrated economic ecolo¬
gical models for understanding urban sys¬
tems. These models provide rapid, graphic
feedback and are one important way of put¬
ting existing results into the policy arena.
Risk assessment
Although risk assessment methods were
originally developed for technological and
Left, city centre of Frankfurt, Federal
Republic of Germany
"New Construction", one of the entries in an
international photo competition organized in
connection with the United Nations Con¬
ference on Human Settlements (HABITAT),
1976, in Vancouver, Canada.
chemical risks, such as nuclear power and
heavy metals, risk assessment ¡s essen¬
tially an application of the ecosystem
approach. It translates Information about
ecosystem relationships into probability
statements about likely harm and inte¬
grates these with social value judgments
about the acceptability of risk to provide a
basis for policy-making.
Risk assessment, then, whilst not a pan¬
acea, provides a general paradigm for look¬
ing at urban vulnerability and resilience
from the perspective of decision-making
under conditions of uncertainty. It is eco¬
system thinking within a management
framework.
The balance sheet
The biennium 1985-1986 saw a re-exam¬
ination of basic principles and a subtle
re-shaping of the practical approach to
problems of urban ecology along the lines
suggested above. These trends are
reflected ¡n the practical achievements of
the period.
The next milestone in the evolution of an
integrated ecological approach to cities
may well be the development and use of
"expert systems" and inclusion of the
decision-making process as part of the
ecological system to be studied.
of MAB, the International
Council of Scientific Unions (ICSU), the Scien¬
tific Committee on Problems of the Environment
(SCOPE), and the International Federation of
Institutes for Advanced Study (IFIAS)
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
The role of MAB
in urban systems
research
Foodfor thought
Is one answer to hunger, under-employment
and poor quality of life among the urban poor
to be found in our own backyards?
Concern about urban development centres
on the sustainability of urban systems, both as
suitable habitats for mankind and in terms of
their ecological and support systems.
With its worldwide research network, MAB
is uniquely well placed to carry out compara¬
tive studies of the environmental and social
effects of rapid urban expansion. The data
already acquired from case studies of such
widely differing cities as Kuala Lumpur,
Rome, Barcelona, Sao Paulo, Mexico City,
Beijing, Frankfurt-am-Main, Dakar, Khar¬
toum and Lae (Papua-New Guinea) provide a
firm scientific basis for the development of
guidelines for planners and decision-makers
faced with problems of rapid urban growth in
other parts of the world.
The change from a mainly rural to a pre¬
dominantly urban habitat for the majority of
the world population demands major
psychological and physiological adjustments
at both the individual and the community
levels.
Many MAB projects contain a strong social
science input to ensure that the vital social,
psychological and physiological aspects of
"total environment" are not overlooked.
Involvement of all sections of local popula¬
tions^ local personalities, women's and youth
groups, decision-makers, etc. as well as
on-the-spot training of local technicians, is also
an integral part of most MAB projects.
Cities are in many ways dangerous and
"unnatural" biological habitats for mankind,
yet they are the "natural" homes of human
culture and creativity.
Conservation in itself is not enough; it must
also contribute to the development and the
improvement of man's relationship with his
environment. In seeking to ensure a viable
future for cities as the major human habitat,
MAB is fulfilling one of its most fundamental
objectives.
IN a notable passage in his satirical work
Candide, the French philosopher and
writer Voltaire declared "Il faut cultiver
notre jardin" (We must cultivate our
garden), a phrase that might well have
been adopted as the motto of a remarkable
research project undertaken by the Centro
de Estudios Urbanos y Regionales
(CEUR), Argentina, and backed by the
United Nations University and Unesco/
MAB.
Voltaire, of course, was referring to the
Individual, spiritual garden which each of us
must cultivate if we are to become self-
reliant and realize our full potential. A report
on the first stage of the project, published in
1 986 under the title Agricultura Urbana y
Periurbana en el Gran Buenos Aires
(Urban and Perl-urban Agriculture in
Greater Buenos Aires), goes a step further
than Voltaire. After detailing the results of a
thorough evaluation of the economic, social
and environmental consequences of urban
and peri-urban agriculture for self-con¬
sumption ¡n the Greater Buenos Aires
region, it comes to the conclusion that the
literal cultivation of back gardens, unused
building lots and green spaces on the out¬
skirts of our great cities might offer some of
the urban poor a way of escape from the
trap of hunger, under-employment and
wretched living conditions.
The report points out that, at com¬
paratively low cost, urban gardening for
self-consumption could have the following
desirable effects:
Make quickly available to the section of
the population in greatest need a supply of
highly nutritive food which the normal work¬
ings of the food market denies them.
A cultivated backyard plot in a workers' barrio in Greater Buenos Aires
Increase the real Incomes of poor urban
families.
Make use of urban resources now lying
¡die (vacant land, some household wastes,
the unused working capacity of the under¬
employed).
Provide opportunities for re-cycllng
urban wastes in soil reclamation projects
for the provision of new gardens.
Improve the quality* of life in the most
deprived urban areas.
Inculcate a sense of pride, self-reliance,
community spirit and liberty by offering the
urban poor an opportunity to act positively
on their own behalf.
For local authorities faced with the huge
expenditures required by traditional
Improvement schemes, the urban garden
proposal offers an effective, low-cost
opportunity to improve rapidly the lot of the
urban poor for whom they are responsible.
It has been estimated that, on average, a
plot of land of 40 or 50 square metres would
be sufficient to provide a family of, say, two
adults and four children with all their needs
in fresh vegetables and other green
foodstuffs. The labour input needed to
achieve this would amount to the equiv¬
alent of one and a half days work a week
which could be shared by all the members
of the family.
It might be objected that, as has some¬
times been the case with imports of food for
famine relief in Africa, the Introduction of
new sources of food supply would distort
food markets to the detriment of rural
farmers.
This objection melts away under closer
scrutiny. Standard methods of stimulating
food production rarely benefit the hard core
urban poor, who remain outside the normal
food market chain because they simply
have not the resources to enter the market
as buyers.
Brazil, for example, has become the
world's third largest exporter of meat, after
the United States of America and the Euro¬
pean Community, yet 25 per cent of its pop¬
ulation still lives at the poverty line and does
not benefit from the country's increased
meat production. India and China have
recently become net exporters of cereals,
yet it is far from being the case that every¬
one living in those countries ¡s adequately
nourished.
Clearly, urban gardening for self-con¬
sumption is not a panacea for all the ¡lis of
modern urban life. However, if combined
with other initiatives being studied within
the larger framework of the CEUR project
on Alternative Strategies for Improving
Food and Energy Availability in Cities, ¡t
offers more than a glimmer of hope for the
millions of urban poor now held in the icy
grip of poverty.
o
©
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Return of the griffon
z
J"
f
w
I
The griffon vulture is one of several species
being re-introduced into the Cévennes Biosphere Reserve
in southern France
THE road from Nîmes to Florae, head¬
quarters of the Cévennes Biosphere
Reserve, winds into the southern
highlands of the French central mountains.
Skirting terraced hillsides and deep
ravines, with jagged mountains looming
above, it seems to be leading the visitor
back into another age, when life was harsh
yet man was still in close communion with
nature.
Geologically and ecologically diverse,
the Cévennes region is an ideal site for a
biosphere reserve. Spread over some
300,000 hectares, it Includes a granitic
massif to the north, a schist zone ¡n the
centre, a schist and granite mountain to the
south and a limestone plateau to the
west.
Mont Lozère, the northern granitic mas¬
sif, is 40 kilometres long and 15 kilometres
wide, reaching 1 ,700 metres at its highest
point. The central schist valley is slashed by
valleys opening towards the Mediterranean
basin. Aigoual, the composite mountain to
the south, ¡s a high zone cut by an important
hydrographie network. The sedimentary
plateaux of Causse de Sauveterre, Causse
Mejean and Causse Noir, to the west, are
rolling regions bounded by deep canyons.
The geology, geographic location and
great range of elevations mean that many
kinds of vegetation are present, including
sub-Mediterranean and Mediterranean for¬
est, Atlantic forest, middle European moun¬
tain forest, shrub and grass moors and rock
vegetation. In general, the flora is sub-
Mediterranean.
The Cévennes contains 50 species of
mammals, 1 50 species of birds, 30 species
of reptiles and amphibians and 20 species
of fish. Rare or threatened species include
the golden eagle (Aquila chrysaetos), the
peregrine falcon (Falco peregrinus), and
the eagle owl (Bubo bubo). Attempts are
being made to re-Introduce some species,
including griffon, beaver and capercaillie.
Already a dozen or more great griffon vul¬
tures can, from time to time, be seen in
majestic flight against the dramatic back¬
drop of the mountain slopes.
The Interest of the Cévennes as a bio¬
sphere reserve lies not only in its rich flora
and fauna but also ¡n the character of its
diverse landscapes, where the natural and
the cultural heritages are intricately mixed.
The region shows many signs of human
occupation dating back centuries. The orig¬
inal forest was destroyed in Roman times to
provide firewood for the great pottery kilns
of Banassac and La Graufesenque. This
deforestation led to the development of an
architecture of superimposed vaulting
capable of supporting heavy roofs of lime¬
stone tiles.
Traditional rural architecture, dating back
to the seventeenth century, ¡s based mainly
on local geological materials (schist, gra¬
nite, limestone) which are still the basis of
today's buildings, such as the elèdes, used
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The Cévennes
Biosphere
Reserve and
National Park
Inhabitants are encouraged to respect tradi¬
tional building styles and methods (right and
below). Any additional cost involved is borne
by the National Park.
Biosphere reserve functions
Biosphere reserves can be
envisaged as geographic
"hubs" for conservation of
landscapes containing the
characteristic ecosystems ofa
given biogeographic region
and for ecological monitor¬
ing, research, education,
demonstration and training
relating to the wise use of
these ecosystems. Right, a
schematic zonation of a bio¬
sphere reserve. In this zona¬
tion the core area is strictly
protected. The buffer zone
can be used for regulated,
non-destructive activities and
is strictly delineated. The
transition area covers other
biosphere reserve functions
including such activities
as experimental research,
traditional use, and re¬
habilitation.
Key (both diagrams)
ER = Experimental Research
TU = Traditional Use
RA = Rehabilitation
TA = Co-operation
(Transition Area)
XX = Human Settlements
Facilities for: R = Research
E = Education
T = Tourism
M = Monitoring
Diagrams source: M. Bâtisse, 1986
WET^F '
I
o
©
for drying chestnuts, and the magnaneries,
where silkworms were once raised.
The schistose area of the Cévennes ¡s a
difficult area for human settlement because
of its steep slopes. For centuries people
have climbed these slopes carrying the soil
that each Mediterranean storm washed
down into the valleys. Patiently and with
great effort they built terracing and hamlets
on the mountain sides.
This long and extraordinary Interplay
between man and nature was recognized
by the French authorities and led, in 1970,
to the creation of the Cévennes National
Park. Like other French National Parks, the
Cévennes Park has a central zone, ¡n which
some 600 people live, where Park officials
have extensive statutory powers (supervi¬
sion of hunting, building licences, traffic,
etc.), and a peripheral zone ¡n which they
can advise and attempt to influence the
communities within the zone to conserve
natural features.
In the field of architecture, for example,
the park administration asks farmers to
respect traditional building methods and
pays the difference between the cost of a
contemporary construction and a tradi¬
tional one.
As far as agriculture is concerned,
environmental planning helps farmers to
improve their profits without damaging the
environment. Farmers also sometimes
work directly for the Park under special con¬
tract, at times when they are not too busy
¡n their own fields, on such projects as
clearing undergrowth to prevent forest
fires and restoring communal buildings ¡n
the villages.
The similarities between the objectives of
the Cévennes National Park and those of
the MAB International biosphere reserve
network are evident, and ¡n 1984 the Park
was designated a biosphere reserve.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
A rocky landscape typical of parts of the
Cévennes
Arid and semi-arid zones
This has enabled it to deal more effec¬
tively with a number of ecological problems.
For example, the boundaries of the Park
had been established on the basis of
administrative and political demarcations,
which rarely coincide with ecological limits.
As a biosphere reserve, Its new boundaries
have been drawn up according to such cri¬
teria as geological patterns and vegetation
distribution.
Furthermore, scientific objectives are
often better defined in a biosphere reserve
and are related directly to human uses. In
addition, the Park now has access to the
vast MAB data base compiled from
research undertaken in biosphere reserves
all over the world.
Within the framework of the MAB Interna¬
tional network of biosphere reserves, a suit¬
able policy ¡s being developed for the
environment outside the central zone of the
National Park.
The objectives of the Action Plan for Bio¬
sphere Reserves have been enthusi¬
astically adopted and this was reflected in a
workshop on the Implementation of the
Action Plan for Biosphere Reserves in the
Mediterranean Region, organized by the
French MAB Committee and held at Florae
in September 1986. Some fifty specialists
from eight countries (Algeria, Egypt,
France, Italy, Portugal, Spain, Turkey and
Tunisia) attended, including representa¬
tives from two other French biosphere
reserves: Fango, in Corsica, and the
Camargue.
A recurrent theme of the Florae work¬
shop was that consideration of the human
element was vital to the understanding and
better conservation of Mediterranean land¬
scapes. Biosphere reserves like the
Cévennes can give a lead in testing ways of
conserving landscapes that have long been
shaped by the hand of man.
Arid and semi-arid zones, lands of highly
variable and sparse rainfall, cover one-third of
the surface of the globe.
The boundary between "arid" and "semi-
arid" may at the risk of over-simplifica¬
tion be taken as the division between places
where rainfall farming is possible, even though
with great variance from year to year, and
those where it is impossible to be certain of a
crop in most years.
The transition from extremely arid to sub-
humid regions is gradual and, except where it
coincides with a distinctive feature such as a
mountain range, is best delimited by a band of
varying width. Within this variable band the
rainfall is highly irregular, falls in contrasting
dry and humid periods, and on average is less
than 600 mm in summer or less than 400 mm in
winter humid periods.
Climatic conditions give rise to very dif¬
ferent situations. It is possible to distinguish
between arid and semi-arid regions on the basis
of rainfall, but it is also very important to con¬
sider the duration of the rainfall and the dura¬
tion and timing of the dry season. It is evident,
for example, that the problems of irrigation, of
dry farming and of the movement of livestock
differ greatly as between the northern fringes
of the Sahara (where the rain falls in winter and
is connected with the fronts and depressions of
the temperate zone) and the southern fringes
(where the rain falls in summer and is linked to
the shifting of the inter-tropical convergence
zone).
Not only precipitation registered by rain-
gauges has to be taken into consideration.
There are many coastal arid and semi-arid
regions (in Chile, Mauritania, Morocco, etc.)
which benefit from the condensation of dew
(attributable to greater humidity of the air in
these parts). And while evaporation is always
difficult to measure and calculate, it is evident
that thermic conditions vary widely from one
arid region to another (with all the resulting
repercussions on the life of human populations
and on vegetation).
The presence of allogenic rivers (rising in
non-arid regions) may radically modify the
hydrological conditions which largely deter¬
mine the development of a region. They have
often made it possible to extend irrigated areas
considerably.
The nature of the flow of these rivers (degree
of irregularity, high-water period, etc.) exer¬
cises a considerable effect. The flow of the Nile,
for example, which is governed mainly by trop¬
ical precipitation, is very different from that of
mountain rivers of higher latitudes, which are
affected by the phenomena of snow retention
combined, sometimes, with karst retention.
Furthermore, conditions for the use of surface
and underground water resources differ as
a function of topography and of geological
features.
Soil conditions are very variable, depending
upon the distribution of the parent rocks. Silty
soils are more propitious in certain respects
than sandy soils, yet like sandy soils they are
vulnerable to erosion, hence the importance of
soil fixation, conservation and restoration.
The position occupied by the arid and semi-
arid regions in the countries concerned
(whether they form a marginal, an important
or an essential element in the national econ¬
omy) obviously affects the attention govern¬
ments pay to them and the investment, private
or public, that is available for their develop¬
ment.
The approach to development problems will
differ greatly according to whether or not tra¬
ditional populations and civilizations exist, and
also to what part nomads, semi-nomads and
sedentary peoples play in a country. The avail¬
ability of mineral or power resources is another
decisive factor.
Thus the great variety of natural parameters
and the diversity of socio-cultural and histor¬
ical backgrounds makes it extremely difficult
to elaborate general models for development.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
->
/
.^
Photo J.D. Lajoux © Rapho, Paris
A priceless heritage of universal value
Nature and culture
The World Heritage emblem symbolizing the
interdependence ofcultural and naturalprop¬
erties. Tassili n'Ajjer, Algeria, famedfor its
rock paintings (above), is both a World
Heritage site and a biosphere reserve.
THE Convention for the Protection of
the World's Natural and Cultural
Heritage, more commonly known as
The World Heritage Convention, was
adopted by Unesco's General Conference
in November 1972 and came Into force in
December 1975 after ratification by twenty
nations. As of mld-1987 there are 247
natural and cultural sites on the World
Heritage List and the Convention has been
ratified or accepted by 95 States.
The Convention marks a new departure
in international co-operation, setting up a
system whereby the international com¬
munity can participate actively ¡n protecting
those parts of the natural and cultural
heritage that are agreed to be of great uni¬
versal value.
Traditionally, the preservation of cultural
heritage and the conservation of nature
have been regarded as two quite different
problems, with responsibility for the protec¬
tion of important cultural or natural sites
being considered as lying exclusively with
the country ¡n which they are located.
The Convention breaks hew ground by
linking together the protection of the
cultural heritage and the natural heritage
and in providing a permanent legal, finan¬
cial and administrative framework for inter¬
national co-operation in ensuring this pro¬
tection. It also introduces the new concept
of a "World Heritage" of natural and
cultural properties of universal value which
transcends all political or geographical
boundaries.
The underlying philosophy which
brought the Convention into being is that
there are some parts of the world's natural
and cultural heritage that are so excep¬
tional and of such scientific importance to
the world that their conservation and pro¬
tection for present and future generations is
a matter of concern not only to individual
nations but to the international community
as a whole.
Countries that are most richly endowed
with artistic, archaeological, palaeontologi-
cal, biological or ecological "treasures" are
not, however, always the most prosperous
and may have difficulty in providing ade¬
quate protection to this endowment.
Through the World Heritage Fund estab¬
lished under the Convention, any nation,
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Inclusion of natural properties of
universal value on the World Heritage List
Under the World Heritage Convention, the
natural heritage is defined as:
Natural features consisting of physical and
biological formations or groups of such forma¬
tions which are of outstanding universal value
from the aesthetic or scientific point of view;
Geological and physiological formations and
precisely delineated areas which constitute the
habitat of threatened species of animals and
plants of outstanding universal value from the
point of view of science or conservation;
Natural sites or precisely delineated natural
areas of Outstanding universal value from the
point of view ofscience, conservation or natural
beauty.
Criteria
A natural heritage site, following the definition
above, which is submitted for inclusion in the
World Heritage List, will be considered to be of
outstanding universal value for the purposes of
the Convention when the Committee finds that
it meets one or more of the following criteria
and fulfils the conditions of integrity set out
below. Sites nominated should therefore:
1. be outstanding examples representing the
major stages of the Earth's evolutionary-
history;
2. be outstanding examples representing sig¬
nificant on-going geological processes, biolog¬
ical evolution and man's interaction with his
natural environment; as distinct from the
periods of the Earth's development, this
focuses upon on-going processes in the develop¬
ment of communities, of plants and animals,
land-forms and marine and freshwater bodies;
3. contain superlative natural phenomena, for¬
mations or features, such as outstanding exam¬
ples of the most important ecosystems, areas of
exceptional natural beauty, or exceptional
combinations of natural and cultural elements;
4. contain the most important and significant
natural habitats where threatened species of
animals or plants of outstanding universal
value from the point of view of science or con¬
servation still survive.
In addition to the above criteria, the sites
should also fulfil the following conditions of
integrity:
(a) The sites described in 1. should contain all
or most of the key interrelated and inter¬
dependent elements in their natural relation¬
ships; for example, an "Ice Age" area would be
expected to include the snow field, the glacier
itself and samples of cutting patterns, depo¬
sition and colonization (striations, moraines,
pioneer stages of plant succession, etc.).
(b) The sites described in 2. should have suffi¬
cient size and contain the necessary elements to
demonstrate the key aspects of the process and
to be self-perpetuating. For example, an area
of "tropical rain forest" may be expected to
include some variation in elevation above sea
level, changes in topography and soil types,
river banks or ox-bow lakes, to demonstrate
the diversity and complexity of the system.
(c) The sites described in 3. should contain
those ecosystem components required for the
continuity of the species or of the objects to be
conserved. This will vary according to the indi¬
vidual cases; for example, the protected area of
a waterfall would include all, or as much as
possible, of the supporting upstream water¬
shed; or a coral reef area would be provided
with control over siltation or pollution through
the stream flow or ocean currents which
provide its nutrients.
(d) The area containing threatened species as
described in 4. should be of sufficient size and
contain the necessary habitat requirements for
the survival of the species.
(e) In the case of migratory species, seasonal
sites necessary for their survival, wherever
they are located, should be adequately pro¬
tected. The Committee must receive
assurances that the necessary measures will be
taken to ensure that the species are adequately
protected throughout their full life cycle.
Agreements made in this connection, either
through adherence to international con¬
ventions or in the form of other multilateral or
bilateral arrangements, would provide this
assurance.
Each site should be evaluated relatively, that is,
it should be compared with other sites of the
same type, both inside and outside the State
Party's borders, within a biogeographic
province or migratory pattern.
institution or individual can contribute to the
protection of the heritage in countries
where national resources are insufficient.
Signatories to the Convention undertake
to help in the identification, protection, con¬
servation and preservation of world
heritage properties. They recognize that
the identification and safeguarding of those
parts of the heritage which are located on
their own territories is primarily their own
responsibility and agree to do all they can,
with their own resources and with any inter¬
national assistance they can obtain, to
ensure adequate protection. They agree,
amongst other things, to "adopt a general
policy which aims to give the cultural and
natural heritage a function in the life of the
community and to integrate protection of
the heritage into comprehensive planning
programmes".
The Convention ¡s administered by the
World Heritage Committee, composed of
twenty-one States elected at a General
Assembly of Member States held every two
The Ngorongoro Conservation Area (right),
United Republic of Tanzania, and the con¬
tiguous Serengeti National Park, are World
Heritage sites. Combined they form a single
biosphere reserve.
years. The Secretariat is provided by
Unesco and a number of its officials are
also members of the Man and the Bio¬
sphere (MAB) Secretariat, in particular
those concerned with biosphere reserves.
While the aims of, and criteria for selec
tion of World Heritage sites (see above)
and biosphere reserves are different, far
from being incompatible they are comple¬
mentary. Indeed, twenty-five World
Heritage natural sites also form part of the
MAB Biosphere Reserve Network.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The pictures on these two pages give an
illustration of the Visual Impact Analysis
Method and the results obtained. They show
the locality of Dybäck on the south coast of
Sweden and its development from Mesolithic
forest.
Right: Mesolithic landscape of Dybäck. The
Baltic Sea level was then about 4 metres above
the present level. The animals shown are all
species that have been identified in excavation
material. The existence of the human settle¬
ment was inferred from a large number of
finds in and around the estuary. The vegeta¬
tion was closed forest, densest in the wetter
areas, thinning out to a shrub ofoak and pine
along the coast. The hydrology is based on
topography, evidence of peat in some areas
and the evidence of 18th and early 19th cen¬
tury maps.
.... iilB^^s.,
JA¿rí
*V~.-
«Sr
-¡ ... - - , *,-* ' ' ¿¿TL*?' _
.*- f
;
iViiîi
Painting
the future
Using 'Visual Impact Analysis',
Swedish MAB scientists and
artists are charting future changes
in their country's landscape
*+JH
TOWARDS the end of 1986, the
Riksdag, the Swedish Parliament,
was the setting for an art exhibition
with a difference.
Consisting of a series of attractive water-
colour landscapes, the exhibition was
designed to bring home to the nation's
leaders the visual impact that their deci¬
sions could have upon the Swedish land¬
scape.
The watercolours were, however, much
more than an artist's personal impression
of what might lie ahead. They were the fruit
of a serious scientific research project
which started ¡n 1 978 under the aegis of the
Swedish National MAB Committee and the
Committee of Future-oriented Research
(both under the Swedish Council for Plan¬
ning and Co-ordination of Research).
The Swedish landscape has undergone
major changes since 1940. Approximately
a quarter of all agricultural land has been
taken out of production and has reverted
naturally to forest or been planted with con¬
ifers. Rapid urbanization, road building, the
construction of recreational housing and
the development of Industrial sites along
What will thefuture bringfor this landscape?
Two visualizations are presented here the
two energy scenarios, "Nuclear Sweden" and
"Solar Sweden".
Right: "Nuclear Sweden" in 2015. Picture
shows a nuclear power station with four 100
MW reactors. Location and configuration are
based on the Barsebäckplant and information
supplied by Sydkraft AB. The road is as pro¬
jected in long-term roadplans. Land use out¬
side the immediate vicinity of the power sta¬
tion is assumed not to be radically altered.
18
as
**_ *Çi:-*-»'v. .- _
A
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
*---v
-
¿e/r: Dybäck in 1980. The landscape is domi¬
nated by the agricultural activity ofthe Manor
(centre right of picture) with its pattern of
large consolidated fields. In the middle dis¬
tance, left andfar distance the pattern ofagri¬
culture is dominated by smallerfarms laid out
in the land reform of1824. A summer housing
development can be seen along the shore
above the fishing village ofHörte, which was
constructed in 1937.
the coast have also contributed to this
transformation.
The object of the Swedish MAB study
was to develop a method of Visual Impact
Analysis and to test it on a number of
localities in Sweden, using scenarios pro¬
duced by others, so that it could be incor¬
porated Into the planning and decision¬
making process.
The first step was to select from a num¬
ber of previously completed future studies
dealing with forestry, energy and agricul¬
ture those scenarios that were sufficiently
detailed to enable their visual impacts to be
deduced with reasonable precision.
Four such future studies were deemed to
fulfil these conditions: two alternative
energy scenarios, "Nuclear Sweden" and
"Solar Sweden", presented by a project
group of the Secretariat for Future Studies;
a "High-Yield Alternative" for Swedish for¬
estry, produced by a government commis¬
sion on the future of Swedish forestry;
and an alternative agricultural scenario
produced by the Swedish Agricultural
University.
The Visual Impact Analysis method is
divided into three basic stages: (a) the
analysis of a scenario and its application to
a given locality; (b) the Integration of
information Into instructions for the pro¬
duction of pictures; (c) the production and
successive modification of a series of visual
impact pictures.
Once a locality has been chosen, a thor¬
ough study of all the background material is
made Including a historical reconstruction
of the development of the landscape. Infor¬
mation on the geology, hydrology, past and
present vegetation and land use of the area
is gathered and a search is made in local,
regional and national archives for maps
and other documentary evidence.
Specialists from a wide range of disci¬
plines are consulted concerning the back¬
ground material and reconstructions and a
series of aerial and ground photographs
are taken and drawings made at different
times of the year.
Field studies are made and checked
against maps and other documentary evi¬
dence and all this background material is
integrated into a series of maps and trans¬
parencies and superimposed on the aerial
-.-;.
ÇKi*W
¿ n¡
-ru.
'*
>... , . -'-
"" '
©
photographs. Similar methods are used in
elaborating the "portraits of the future".
The degree of confidence that can be
placed in these reconstructions varies, of
course, with the type of evidence available.
With regard to the future projections and
Visual Impact Analyses, the assumptions
of the respective scenarios are followed
whenever these are explicit.
None of them involves technology or
practices that are not now current and they
all assume a "surprise-free" future. In the
forestry alternatives, for example, normal
and orderly forest development after plant¬
ing is assumed.
A master perspective is used for each
locality for the production of a complete
series of pictures. The time of the year ¡s
also held constant.
The artist draws preliminary pictures
from the background material and the mas¬
ter perspective ¡s produced by watercolour
on a drawing. In fact, acrylic paint is used
for these "watercolours" so that changes
can be made later if necessary.
The pictures are then reviewed by a num¬
ber of the experts who were consulted on
the background material as well as by other
independent experts. On the basis of their
assessments the original pictures may be
modified or new ones made.
Left: "Solar Sweden" in 2015. Wind power
development with a station of4 MW wind tur¬
bines. Height about 100 metres, blade length
80 metres. The configuration follows
guidelines for location proposed by the
National Board for Energy Source Develop¬
ment. Cables are laid underground, but this
would not be the case in less favourable soil
conditions.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Islands
©
The world's five billionth (5,000,000,000) inhabitant, Matej Gaspar (pronounced Matey
Gushpar) is greeted by United Nations Secretary-General Javier Pérez de Cuéllar, above. The
baby is pictured in the arms ofa nurse at a hospital in Zagreb, Yugoslavia, where he was born
early in the morning of 11 July 1987.
The day of five billion
Born at 7.00 am on Saturday 11 July,
1987, Matej Gaspar was the symbolic
focus of worldwide celebration of the
day the world population reached a
total of five billion (5,000,000,000).
The date, too, is symbolic since nobody
knows exactly when thefive billion total
was actually reached. What we do
know is that the number of human
beings is now growing at a rate of 150
every minute, 220,000 a day, 80 million
a year. At this rate, according to the
1987 State of World Population
Report, published by the United
Nations Fundfor Population Activities
(UNFPA), we will reach six billion by
the end of the century, seven billion by
the year 2010, and eight billion by the
year 2022. Most ofthis growth will take
place in the developing countries. It is
estimated that world population will
finally stabilize at around ten billion in
about a century from now.
IS Paradise an Island? The ancient
Greeks believed that the spirits of their
dead heroes inhabited the Elyslan
Fields in the Isles of the Blest, far away to
the west beyond Calpe and Abyla, the Pil¬
lars of Hercules.
Centuries later, searching for Paradise,
the Irish monk Saint Brendan (484-578)
sailed far Into the Atlantic Ocean, where he
came upon an island of unsurpassed
beauty and fertility which he believed to be
the "Promised Land of the Saints". Saint
Brendan's sacred Island remained clearly
marked upon most maps for over a thou¬
sand years. Even today most travel agents
have at least one "island paradise" on their
books with which to tempt clients anxious
"to get away from it all".
Is Hell an Island? For millions of Africans
sold Into slavery, the Island of Gorée off the
coast of Senegal, near Dakar, where they
were held before being transported across
the Atlantic, was the gateway to Hell, and
few names so readily evoke the notion of
Hell on earth as that of Devil's Island.
Paradise or Purgatory, Heaven or Hell,
islands leave no one indifferent, least of all
scientists. It was no accident that Darwin's
momentous The Origin of Species was the
outcome of a voyage to the Galapagos, the
Islas Encantadas, the "Enchanted Isles" as
they were also called, for by their nature
islands offer the scientist special oppor¬
tunities for research. As Darwin wrote of the
Galapagos in his Journal on 8 October
1835, "The archipelago is a little world
within itself...", and 'The natural history of
these islands is eminently curious and well
deserves attention".
Echoes of these words can be heard in
those written almost a hundred and forty
years later by a group of experts gathered
in Paris, in 1973, to outline the scientific
content of the MAB project on The Ecology
and Rational Use of Island Ecosystems:
"Islands offer an exceptional opportunity to
study, under relatively controlled condi¬
tions, the entire spectrum of ecological,
demographic, economic and social factors
that influence population/environment rela¬
tionships. This is particularly true as popu¬
lation/environment systems on islands are
small and easily modelled, and can at the
same time be representative of larger sys¬
tems." The final sentence of the above dec¬
laration not only re-introduced the notion of
the Island as a microcosm, Darwin's "little
world within itself", it also explains why
MAB Island research is concentrated on
small islands. The 1973 meeting of experts
defined "small" as meaning having a sur¬
face area of 1 0,000 square kilometres or
less.
Briefly stated, the objective of MAB
island research is to promote sustainable
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
at risk
development of small islands and rational
management of their natural resources.
A number of primary research themes
have been selected as being necessary for
the achievement of this objective:
the management of environmental
resources by Island populations;
the Impact of external forces on islands,
in particular the effects of tourism;
the impact of the introduction of alien
plants and animals on island ecosystems;
the impact of migration;
the impact of agrochemicals on island
environments and societies;
the ¡slander's perception of his or her
special social and natural environment.
Implementation of these general lines of
island research within MAB has been
largely shaped by the situation and prob¬
lems of each specific island or island group.
The South Pacific was the focus of initial
island research work in MAB, followed by
studies in the Caribbean, Mediterranean
and other regions.
Experience from a selection of these
projects provided one of the basic Inputs to
an inter-oceanlc workshop on sustainable
development and management of small
islands, held in Puerto Rico in November
1986.
Organized by the US-MAB Directorate
on Caribbean Islands, the workshop was
sponsored by the MAB Committees of the
United States and Canada, Unesco, UNEP
and UNCTAD.
The thirty invited specialists who took
part came from five ocean basins and nine¬
teen countries, from cultures as diverse as
those of Australia, Barbados, China, Fiji,
France, Hawaii, Japan, Malta, St. Lucia and
Yugoslavia, and from disciplinary back¬
grounds ranging from anthropology, ecol¬
ogy and economics to geography and
sociology.
This diversity among the participants
attending the workshop mirrored the very
wide diversity to be found amongst Islands.
Quite apart from the major division between
continental islands (those that are unsub-
merged parts of the continental shelf) and
oceanic islands (those that rise from the
floors of the ocean basins), there is a world
of difference between the very small
Islands of the eastern Caribbean, the
Pacific and the Atlantic, and, for example,
Puerto Rico (8,897 square kilometres),
Jamaica and Fiji.
Islands are to be found in every latitude
and in all climates. They occur singly, in
groups, in archipelagos and in island arcs.
There are high islands of continental rock,
high. volcanic islands, raised limestone
islands, coral atolls and sand cays. They
may be populous or uninhabited, indepen¬
dent States or politically part of a conti¬
nental State, richly or poorly endowed by
nature.
Underlying this diversity, however, is the
fundamental fact that small islands are in
several respects specialized and rather
fragile environments. They have a much
higher proportion of endemic species than
most continental regions, are subject to the
action of the sea on all sides, and have only
small fresh water catchments so that rain¬
fall and eroded material are constantly
being lost to the sea.
Island peoples have often evolved cul¬
tures that are distinct from those of conti¬
nental peoples and to which they feel a
©
Tahiti, the largest island of the Windward
Group of the Society Islands, French
Polynesia
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
strong allegiance. At the same time they
are very vulnerable to the effects of outside
economic, technological and social forces
which can disrupt both their natural and
cultural environment.
Because small islands have only a lim¬
ited range of exploitable resources, the
options for ecologically and economically
sustainable development are restricted.
Ultimately an island's natural
resources its water supply, soil, wildlife,
forests and fisheries will determine its
capacity to accept and sustain develop¬
ment.
Moreover, on a small island the margin
for error is small. Even a comparatively
minor miscalculation over the acceptable
level of forest exploitation, for example,
could seriously endanger the water supply,
diminish animal wildlife, and result in
excessive soil erosion and sedimentation
with , consequent adverse impacts on
estuarine and marine resources. Even
quite a small upswing in population can
have devastating ecological and social
effects.
Much is still unknown or unclear regard¬
ing the mechanisms that regulate the rela¬
tionships between man and a limited
environment, yet without a thorough under¬
standing of the resources available for
development and the vulnerability of island
resource systems to human activities, sus¬
tainable development will remain a hit-
or-mlss affair.
Furthermore, ecological change can
both cause and result from economic and
. cultural changes. Effective resource man¬
agement must therefore strive to establish
an equilibrium between economic con¬
straints, ecological imperatives and the
social and cultural dimensions of each
island society.
Poster by the French designerA ndré François
for the exhibition lies (Islands), held at the
Centre Georges Pompidou, Paris, from 24
June to 23 September, 1987
Twenty key issues in island
Islands have many problems in common with
certain continental areas. Yet at the same time
they provide a special case in development,
largely owing to specific characteristics of their
natural resources, their economies and their
cultures. The developmental opportunities and
constraints with which small islands (10,000
square kilometres or less, population 500,000
or less) are faced were thrown into relief at a
MAB inter-oceanic workshop on small islands,
held in Puerto Rico in November 1986, at
which twenty key issues, briefly stated below,
were determined and discussed:
/. Sustainable development. Islands have a
smaller capacity to absorb environmental
impacts than larger areas. It is essential for
islanders to understand and implement strat¬
egies of sustainable development.
2. Diversity of islands. Found in every latitude
and clime, islands vary from quite large popu¬
lous areas to tiny sand cays. With their small
size, limited resource base, susceptibility to
storm damage and drought, atolls exhibit
many of the problems of small islands in their
most extreme form.
3. Open, specialized economies. Openness and
specialization are the hallmarks of an island
economy. In many cases dependent upon the
export of one or two specialized crops, small
islands are often obliged to import many con¬
sumer goods, including food.
4. Private sector involvement. The private sec¬
tor has much to contribute to development pol¬
icy. Transnational and local companies have a
major responsibility with regard to waste man¬
agement, toxic materials control and energy
conservation.
5. Distortions in island economies. Island econ¬
omies are subject to distortions due to socially
or politically motivated transfer payments of
various kinds. The significance and effects of
these distortions have not always been fully
recognized.
6. Transport. Many small islands have serious
external transportation problems. For island
groups there is often a problem of maintaining
an adequate outer-island transport service.
7. Demographic issues. Small islands are sub¬
ject to cycles of rapid demographic change
that go far beyond those related to natural
birth and death rate balances (see Salina case
study, opposite page).
8. Employment. Small population size and
migration mean that the fine balance between
manpower supply and demand is easily
upset.
9. Decision-making. Integration of scientific
concepts into managing island environments is
often given low political priority. This stems
partly from a lack of information available to
decision-makers.
10. Natural resources. Natural resources, on
which sustainable development ultimately
depends, are among the most vulnerable sec¬
tors of island economies.
11. Forestry. Conservation of forest cover is
essential for small islands for watershed pro¬
tection and as a guarantee against soil
erosion.
12. Land management. Land-use problems on
islands largely result from the conflict between
change and development and traditional sys¬
tems. In many cases loss of traditional forms of
land ownership is increasing the fragmentation
of landholdings.
13. Water. Only the largest and wettest high
islands have ample resources of water, and
even on some of these there are seasonal
shortages.
14. Energy. Many islands depend almost
totally on imported fossil fuels, although use of
wood and charcoal continues. Solar energy is
already important on some islands and biogas
digesters are in use in a few areas.
15. Conservation. Small islands are often the
site of rare but fragile ecosytems, many of
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A CASE STUDY
development
Pirates, parasites
and population
which are in danger of disappearing through
lack of conservation policies. The introduction
of exotic species represents an additional threat
to native wildlife species.
16. Coastal and marine ecosystems . An island's
coastline is often its most valuable region, but
unregulated industrial and tourist develop¬
ment projects are liable to cause irreparable
damage. Pollution from mining and forest
activities are causing extensive damage to
coastal areas and marine life in some high
islands of the western Pacific.
17. Fisheries. Island fisheries in the tropics and
the Mediterranean are mainly small-scale and
conducted on artisanal lines. In tropical
islands, fishing for export is often hampered by
problems of storage and marketing.
18. Agriculture. Island agriculture systems
range from subsistence farming to the produc¬
tion of export cash crops. The fall in demand
for sugarcane and copra has been a serious
blow to certain island economies.
19. Industry. The smallness of islands is a
severe constraint on industrial development.
There is, however, some scope for value-
adding semi-manufacture.
20. Tourism and allied services. Climate and
beaches are islands' main tourist attractions,
but tourism as a major industry requires
investment in infrastructure. Military use of
strategically placed islands is comparable with
tourism in its economic effects.
Above, the Greek island ofHalki, to the west
of Rhodes, is one of a dozen small islands in
the Mediterranean that are working together
to solve their environmental problems with a £
helping hand from Unesco's Man and the "-_
Biosphere Programme. Right, the island of =|
Salina, in the Aeolian Archipelago, is one of @
the sites studied as part ofMAB research on s
the ecology and use of small islands. £
SMALL islands throughout the world
have experienced cycles of rapid
demographic change. This may be
due to the Impact of outside forces beyond
their control or to the fact that their econo¬
mies are based on a single specialized crop
at the mercy of disease and the caprices of
the market.
Pirates and parasites were the cause of
the vicissitudes of Salina, a small island
lying to the north of Sicily in the Aeolian
Archipelago. ^
For centuries, fear of pirates in the Archi¬
pelago was such that only Lipari, with its
powerful fortifications, had a stable popula¬
tion, while Salina and the other Aeolian
islands remained virtually uninhabited.
Even Lipari finally succumbed. In the
Aeolian islands they still commemorate the
terrible siege of July 1544, when Khayr-
ad-Din, the Barbary pirate better known as
Barbarossa (Red-beard), seized the for¬
tress and carried off into slavery some
9,000 inhabitants, almost the entire popula¬
tion of the island.
Salina remained largely unsettled until
the arrival of the French and British fleets in
the Mediterranean, and a campaign by
Admiral Nelson, finally eliminated the pirate
scourge.
Already ¡n the mid-eighteenth century, as
pirate power started to decline, the Bene¬
dictine order, a considerable landowner in
the area, had begun leasing its lands on
Salina on favourable terms to a number of
private entrepreneurs. The latter brought in
landless immigrants from other islands of
the archipelago, as well as from Genoa,
Naples and Sicily, to work the vineyards
that had been established on terraces on
the volcanic formation, about 900 metres
above sea level.
The vineyards of Salina specialized in
Malmsey, a wine much in demand in
England. Trade prospered and the farmers
were able to buy their lands. By 1860,
Salina boasted 8,000 Inhabitants, most of
them engaged ¡n the cultivation of grapes
and the production and shipping of wine.
At the end of the century, however, an
infestation of the Phylloxera parasite des¬
troyed the vineyards on Salina. Earnings on
the island dropped sharply and, lacking the
capital to survive during the period required
to restore the vineyards, local families
began to emigrate in large numbers to
Argentina, the United States and, later, to
Australia. In a relatively short time, the
population fell to under 2,000.
Although the vineyards were rehabilita¬
ted prior to the Second World War, the
population has only recently risen to a total
of 2,300.
Salina's period of economic develop¬
ment lasted only about sixty years. Its rapid
settlement was based on a specific oppor¬
tunity to take advantage of an existing mar¬
ket to earn a good living.
Rapid emigration followed the Phylloxera
infestation. In the absence of long-term cre¬
dit with which to restore their vineyards, and
in view of inducements offered to emigrate
to other areas where land was made availa¬
ble at low cost, many farmers took the easy
way out, even though it meant leaving their
native island and, in some cases, their fami¬
lies as well.
For Salina, dependence upon a single
product led first to rapid population growth
and then, following a natural disaster, to
rapid emigration a clear example of the
risk involved for a small Island of basing its
economy on a single specialized crop.
l-Z^-j- - .
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The most accurate, up-to-date
research data will be worthless
unless they are presented with
the end user's objectives in
mind
Information please
IN a tribute to the greatest scientist of the
seventeenth century, Alexander Pope
wrote:
Nature and Nature's laws lay hid in night;
God said, "Let Newton be!" and all
was light.
Somewhat more than two centuries later,
in a light-hearted pastiche of Pope, Sir John
Collings Squire paid his own wry tribute to
the greatest scientist of the twentieth
century:
It did not last: the Devil howling "Ho!
Let Einstein be!" restored the status quo.
The two couplets are of more than merely
anecdotal interest. They highlight the tre¬
mendous volume and complexity of scien¬
tific advance in the 229 years between the
publication of Newton's Principia Mathe-
matica (1687) and of Einstein's The Foun¬
dation of the General Theory of Relativity
(1916).
Publication of scientific information
increased ¡n parallel with scientific
advance. Beginning with two journals that
started publication in 1665 (the Journal des
Scavans and the Philosophical Transac¬
tions of the Royal Society of London), the
number of scientific periodicals has grown
enormously. Estimates of the present num¬
ber of such journals vary from 25,000 to
100,000 (the wide variation being due to
differing opinions as to which publications
qualify as scientific journals).
To publications such as these must now
be added an overwhelming mass of report
literature (the periodic reports often
required by organizations sponsoring
research), papers published by informa¬
tion-exchange groups, newsletters,
reviews and abstracting services,
reference books, handbooks and manuals.
For the scientist struggling to cope with
this rising flood of information, with which
he must contend if he is to keep abreast of
his subject, the immediate solution has
been to narrow his field of interest by
increasing his degree of specialization.
This in turn has contributed to the fragmen¬
tation of the major disciplines Into ever
smaller subject areas, each with its own
specialized data bases, newsletters,
periodicals, and so on. The net result has
been a greater and greater amount of in¬
formation accessible to fewer and fewer
specialists.
This is not to suggest that there is, or ever
will be, too much scientific information
available. There is a striking parallel to be
made between an apparent information
glut and the "food mountains" that have
grown in the West at a time when two-thirds
of the world population is either mal¬
nourished or under-nourished.
Part of the food problem is that in many
cases the surpluses produced in the West
are unsuitable, ¡f not indigestible, to those in
need of food elsewhere.
The problem is somewhat similar with
scientific research data. Decisions are
made every day throughout the world which
will affect the lives of millions of people, in
complete disregard of scientific facts, sim¬
ply because those facts are not available to
decision-makers in a form which they can
apply, or to the people who will be affected
in a form they can understand.
To go back for a moment to Newton; the
apocryphal story that his theory of gravity
came to him when he was hit on the head by
a falling apple while resting under ah apple
tree was related to the everyday experi¬
ence of ordinary people. Because of this
they gave credence to his assertion that the
Universe was regulated by simple mathe¬
matical laws.
Einstein, whose theory of relativity rel¬
ated to events outside the direct experience
of almost the entire population of the globe,
was less well served by a limerick
published ¡n the magazine Punch in
December 1923:
There was a young lady named Bright,
Whose speed was far faster than light;
She set out one day
In a relative way,
And got home the previous night.
Fortunately, two events have occurred
which have gone a long way towards
resolving the information dilemma.
The first, paradoxically, was the emer¬
gence of yet another scientific specializa¬
tion ecology, which originated as an off¬
shoot of biology. By definition ecology ¡s
basically the study of relationships, of eco-
systems, and, although it took some time to
break their ingrained habits, ecologists
found themselves working in teams made
up of scientists from different specialities
and therefore obliged to communicate
between each other, to think in terms of
other disciplines, other time scales, other
objectives than their own. Horror of hor¬
rors they even had to work with special¬
ists from the social sciences, which many of
them did not consider to be "real" sciences
at all.
The second event was the arrival en
masse of cheap, readily available compu¬
ters capable of handling huge quantities of
data flexibly and at great speed.
Suddenly the sum of human knowledge
as related to a particular problem has
become available at the price of a few
strokes of the keyboard instead of hours,
months or years of painstaking sifting
through reams of paper.
Suddenly the prospect is in sight of being
able to ask such questions as: "What would
happen ¡f we were to cut down 1 00 hectares
of forest in West Africa?" and to get a reply
which covers not only the forestry aspects
of such an action but the economic, social,
human, wildlife and public health effects
as well.
As one of the world's major International
ecology programmes, Unesco's Man and
the Biosphere (MAB) Programme has
played its part ¡n this evolution. A com¬
puterized documentation system for MAB
has been set up through an agreement with
the Centre International de Documentation
Agronomique pour les Régions Chaudes
(CIDARC), at Montpellier, France.
Research data on all of the 250 or so bio¬
sphere reserves are available on computer
at the Conservation Monitoring Centre, in
Cambridge, England, and a Biological
Diversity Program to develop detailed com¬
puterized inventories of the biological
resources of biosphere reserves following
a standard protocol is being developed in
co-operation with the Smithsonian Institu¬
tion, in Washington, D.C.
More importantly, perhaps, MAB has
tried to convince scientists that, to be effec¬
tive, information must be presented in a
usable form that takes into account the tra¬
ditional knowledge, skills, and cultural,
social and economic imperatives of those
to whom it is being imparted.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
m
7pt.
. -^
WÊÊÊÊÊM
aiv-fc^.ï
The canopy raft
SATELLITES, aircraft, ultra-light air¬
craft and tethered balloons all
enable photographs and measure¬
ments to be taken from above the forest
canopy. Something else is needed,
however, for taking measurements and
samples from within the canopy, hence the
use of walkways and vertical towers at MAB
research stations such as Sakaerat (Thai¬
land), Tai (Ivory Coast), and Dimonlka-
Mayombe (Congo).
Another approach is to climb up into the
canopy, either using the trunk as a means
of support or directly into the branches from
the ground or from a neighbouring tree.
Abseiling is among the devices borrowed
from rock-climbing that have been used in
scaling up and down the forest profile, but
this is definitely not a technique to be
recommended to the uninitiated or the faint¬
hearted.
Recognition of the shortcomings of these
methods led to the idea of using a hot air
balloon as a method for studying the forest
canopy. The idea was the brain-child of
Francis Hallé, a botanist who has long been
interested in the architecture of tropical for¬
est ecosystems, Dany Cleyet-Marrel, an
aeronautic designer and owner of the bal¬
loon, and Gilles Ebersolt, a young balloon
enthusiast and constructor.
The Radeau des Cimes (canopy raft), as
it was baptized by its French inventors, is
31 metres long by 22 metres wide and con¬
sists of inflatable rubber cylinders con¬
nected by a sort of net trampoline made of
PVC-covered Kevlar. Weighing 750 kilo¬
grams, the raft serves as the nacelle for the
hot air balloon of 3,000 cubic metres to
which it is attached by twelve cables.
Once airborne, the raft skims downwind,
just a few metres above the forest canopy.
The two-man crew of pilot and scientist use
a guide-rope to orient the raft and to land it
on top of the canopy. Once the raft is landed
and secured, the balloon is deflated and
folded away and the scientific work can
begin. Liaison with a ground team ¡s estab¬
lished by means of a caving cable, which
enables other scientists to have access to
the canopy.
Initial results have been promising. After
trials with a helicopter-landed, 12 by 12
metre prototype raft ¡n the Forest of Pllat, in
France, in October 1 985, the first field trials
in the tropics took place in October 1986 in
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
French Guyana, in the region of Montsin-
ery. Samples were taken of trees, lianas
and parasitic plants, which were then con¬
served using a method perfected by the
British Museum of Natural History in
London. Ultra-violet lamps and interception
nets were among the methods used for col¬
lecting insects, particular emphasis being
given to two groups of beetles. Other obser¬
vations and sampling concerned epiphytic
plants, ant gardens and atmospheric
pollen.
If all goes well, a second set of trials, to be
held in late 1 987 at the MAB project site of
Makokou, in Gabon, will seek to associate
other scientific disciplines in addition to
those that took part in the first series med¬
ical entomology and parasitology, bio-
climatology and mammalogy, ornithology
and floral biology.
First, however, a number of improve¬
ments need to be made in the basic opera
tion of the canopy raft. These include an
increase in upward force, improvement of
visibility through the nets, Improvement of
access from the soil, improvement of night
use and the addition of a directional move¬
ment capability. At a post-trial meeting held
in Paris in December 1 986, the feeling was
that these various improvements should all
be technically feasible, although a fair
amount of financial sponsorship would be
required.
It might well be asked what was the role
of Unesco/MAB in all this. In truth, it was
very modest moral support plus a few
thousand dollars. But, as in other similar
instances, the small amount of financial
support from Unesco (¡n this case a joint
effort with UNEP, the United Nations
Environment Programme) was "put up
front". It was made available at the very
early risk-taking stage of the project. This
"pump-priming" support was useful to the
leader of the project, Francis Hallé, in
attracting more substantive funding from
public and private sources such as the
French Ministry of the Environment and
National Research Council, the Office for
Scientific Co-operation Overseas
(ORSTOM), the national petroleum com¬
pany (Elf/Antargaz), and a national televi¬
sion channel, Antenne 2.
Already the initial success of the canopy
raft has had considerable coverage in
newspapers and magazines, both ¡n
France and abroad. In addition, one film, for
the scientific audience, has just been com¬
pleted and another, for a more general
public, is in the making. Francis Hallé and
his team hope that this publicity will help to
attract further support for this novel way of
entering the enchanted, unknown world of
the forest canopy.
African Mountains Association created
at Addis Ababa Mountains and Highlands Workshop
The need for research and development strat¬
egies, resource management and food security;
man's role in changing the mountain environ¬
ment in Africa; processes and consequences of
change until the end of the century these were
among the issues taken up at an international
workshop held in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, from
18 to 27 October, 1986.
The workshop was attended by scholars
from ten African and seven non-African coun¬
tries. Some thirty -six papers were presented on
a range of topics covering the characteristics of
African mountain ecosystems, land use,
environmental problems in general and soil
erosion and conservation in particular. Both
in the papers and during an extensive four-
day field excursion, practical responses to
solving environmental problems were
demonstrated.
The close inter-relationship between
environmental degradation and rural poverty
was a central theme for discussion. The general
feeling of the workshop was that while the sit¬
uation was critical in many regions there was
also room for optimism.
Reflecting both this optimism and also the
feeling that there was a serious need for
remedial action, the workshop concluded with
the creation of an African Mountains Associa¬
tion. The new Association intends to maintain
close working contacts between the partici¬
pants and to enlarge progressively into an
effective force for research and action, and will
work closely with international programmes
such as MAB.
A first step will be the publication of the
proceedings of the workshop. Participants felt
that the collated papers and field demonstra¬
tions would constitute the most important body
of literature now available on African moun¬
tain and highland ecosystems.
The participants also unanimously adopted a
series of resolutions which address issues of
resource development in African mountain and
highland regions.
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Deforestation, erosion,
population pressure, migration
and social change all threaten
the equilibrium of mountain
ecosystems
Mountain
challenge
IN Hindu mythology, a mountain is the
centre of the universe and the axis of
the world. This mythical golden moun¬
tain, Mount Meru, is the abode of the gods
and the Himalayas are its foothills. It
extends down into the nether regions of the
Earth as far as ¡t reaches up into the heav¬
ens. On Mount Meru, say the Hindu scrip¬
tures, "there are rivers of sweet water run¬
ning, and beautiful golden houses in which
live the spiritual beings, the Deva".
From Fujiyama to Olympus to Sinai,
every high mountain has been looked upon
with awe and reverence by those who live
within its shadow. Indeed, so strong has
been this instinctive sense of the sacred
nature of mountains that even the plains¬
men of Mesopotamia felt the need to con¬
struct artificial mountains, the "ziggurats",
in an attempt to reach upwards to the
gods.
Perhaps this is because each one of us
has his own interior mountain to climb, to
enjoy and to revere. Even today, when men
have stood upon the summit of Mount Ever¬
est, the challenge and the reverence
remain. A mountain must be climbed,
revered and preserved, in the famous
mountaineering phrase, "because it's
there".
Strangely enough, for all our natural
Interest in mountains, there is no standard
geological definition of a mountain. The
most we seem able to say of them is that
mountains are landforms that rise promi¬
nently above their surroundings, generally
having steep slopes, a relatively confined
summit area and considerable local
relief.
View of the ziggurat at Ur (modern Tall
al-Muqayyar), Iraq. These pyramidal, step¬
ped temple towers were a characteristic
feature of the cities of ancient Mesopotamia
from about 2000 BC to 500 BC. They are
thought to have given rise to the story of the
Tower ofBabel.
I -*i _a_I ^~r~^-; V^-
Zi V ;" -4j^-^i
\ ~t -t _r-j-rj
m * ,_-. i I i i. 1 . I...
t- 	1 .±_z^TrZLrz.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
A Nepalese village in the Himalayas Yet even if only areas above 1,000
metres in altitude are considered to be
mountainous, the mountain regions of the
world are vast in extent.
Some 10 per cent of the world's popula¬
tion actually live in mountainous areas and
approximately 40 per cent or more depend
on mountain resources, whether for miner¬
als, timber, agriculture, water, energy or
recreation.
Because man's impact on mountains is
mainly in rather than above the vegetation
belt, the mountain ecologlst tends to think
of mountains as areas, at all elevations,
where there is significant ecological dif¬
ferentiation in the vertical sense, and where
there are continuous interactions between
the ecological belts at different altitudes,
including, ¡n particular, interactions associ¬
ated with human activities, since man is the
most important factor for change in most
mountain ecosystems.
How great is man's impact on the moun¬
tain regions of the world? For centuries
highlanders have lived ¡n partnership and
equilibrium with nature, creating some of
the most harmonious landscapes in the
world. Today, however, the world ¡s shrink
ing, and from the Alps to the Andes the
pressures of population growth and move¬
ment and the demands of development are
placing this equilibrium in danger. Two
MAB research studies have shown how this
has come about.
For many centuries, human habitation in
the central Andes was concentrated mainly
in the altiplanos, or high plateaux, with set¬
tlements spanning the range from isolated
rural communities to large urban centres.
The adjacent downslope areas were more
sparsely settled, particularly the tropical
forest areas In the lowlands adjoining the
Andes. During this century, and especially
since the 1950s, there have been great
movements of population to the urban
areas in the mountains, to the lower altitude
areas and, above all, to the coastal towns
and cities.
Emigration from the highland areas
results in part from growing population
pressure on a limited resource base and in
part from a real or expected better quality of
life ¡n other areas. For a variety of social and
political reasons the patterns of land exploi¬
tation established in the altiplanos after the
Spanish conquest remained static and,
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
bacterial, viral, parasitic and microbial^
infections against which they have no*
natural immunity.
In the Alps, population movement has
been in two directions. The traditional
mountain populations are abandoning
some of the higher altitude areas, while
adjacent lower areas are becoming com¬
paratively crowded. But the main cau.se for
concern is the transformation of what was
formerly a relatively stable agricultural and
pastoral system, due to seasonal inflows of
people from outside the area on such a vast
scale that the carrying capacity of these
areas may well be exceeded.
These Inflows are made up of summer
and winter tourists and weekend visitors
from the densely populated neighbouring
regions. To these must be added owners
of second homes, who often become per¬
manent residents upon retirement. Many
traditional villages, Alpine pasturelands
and, indeed, whole valleys can no longer
meet the demands of this additional popu¬
lation for avalanche-safe building land,
water, roads, energy supplies, ski-lifts
and ski-runs.
Agriculture, too, is very much affected
not only in tourist areas but throughout the
Alpine region. New attitudes towards agri¬
cultural work and rural life are as important
as the Increasingly marginal profitability of
agricultural and pastoral use of steep and
isolated mountain lands in provoking the
abandonment of certain areas or the
appearance of such phenomena as under-
grazing. As fewer and fewer pathways for
the herds remain available, the old practice
of transhumance (the moving of livestock
from winter to summer pastures) is disap¬
pearing in the western Alps. One side effect
of this abandonment of grazing land is that
changes in the vegetation cover create sur¬
faces more conducive to avalanches.
The direct effects of the massive
increase in the number of skiers over the
past fifteen years must also be taken into
account. Aerial photographic surveys have
shown how much the impacting of snow by
thousands of ski descents every winter hin¬
ders the run-off of water in the spring. Vege¬
tation is destroyed by the cutting edges of
skis and it has been found that along the ski
runs the insect population ¡s decimated and
the number of earthworms per square
metre along some trails has been reduced
from 130 to ten.
These are but two examples of the prob¬
lems facing mountain regions throughout
the world as a result of population pressure,
social change and the needs of develop¬
ment. Even the mighty Himalayas are not
untouched. In Nepal, for example,
deforestation and erosion, coupled with an
influx of adventure-seeking tourist-
trekkers, are taking their toll.
To Edward Whymper (1840-1911), the
artist and mountaineer who was the first
man to climb the Matterhorn, an uncllmbed
mountain was "an affront to man's con¬
quest of nature". Today, man's spoliation of
the mountains he has revered for centuries
will, if left unchecked, become the ultimate
affront to nature.
Aboard the famous mountain train from
Cuzco to Machu Picchu, Peru
when faced with rapid population growth,
the capacity of the highland areas to sup¬
port ever-Increasing numbers was soon
stretched to the limit. The result was over¬
use of land, particularly over-grazing, a
decline in productivity and a consequent
increase in emigration, especially among
the younger and more dynamic people.
Migration on the scale experienced in the
Andes over the past two decades has
affected the environment through over-use
in some areas and under-use in others.
Today, for the first time, the down-slope
areas below the altiplanos are being mas¬
sively exploited. Unfortunately, lack of
sound agricultural practice is leading to
accelerated erosion of the soil which not
only affects the productivity of these areas
directly but also has a negative effect on
lowland areas.
Migration is putting serious pressure on
the housing and health services and other
amenities in the urban areas, especially ¡n
the coastal towns and cities to which the
population flow Is greatest. The health
problems are enormous since the altiplano
populations arriving in the humid low alti¬
tude areas are especially vulnerable to
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Lake Baikal
The world's deepest lake holds one-fifth of the fresh water
on the surface of the Earth
LAKE Baikal, the world's deepest lake,
contains ¡n Its basin more than
23,000 cubic kilometres of fresh
water. This represents about 20 per cent of
the world's fresh water reserves and 80 per
cent of the total surface fresh water
reserves of the USSR. This is about the
same amount as is contained in all the five
North American Great Lakes put together.
The lake, into which 336 rivers and
streams flow, is home to some 2,600 spe¬
cies of plants and animals. Three-quarters
of these species as well as eleven
families and sub-families and ninety-six
genera are endemic to the lake.
Scientists at the Siberian branch of the
USSR Academy of Sciences, based at the
Limnologlcal Institute at Irkutsk, have been
studying Lake Baikal for many years and
have obtained a wealth of data on such
aspects as water inputs, nutrient flows,
sedimentation rates, trophic relationships,
benthlc and littoral fish communities, prod¬
uctivity of phytoplankton and Zooplankton,
and the effect of vertical stratification of the
water column on the distribution of organ¬
isms of all trophic groups. Quantitative
measures of biomass and productivity
include an estimated average total net
weight biomass of invertebrates of 750,000
tons, of which 40 per cent is comprised of
300 benthos.
Research has highlighted the dynamic
nature of the Baikal ecosystem and the
intricacy of the interactions between the
lake and its surroundings. Pollution through
water recycled by industrial (particularly
cellulose) plants is a major threat to water
quality, which in turn ¡s crucial to the plant
and animal communities living in the lake.
One cubic metre of re-circulated water from
a cellulose plant, normally diluted in more
than 1 ,000 cubic metres of lake water, is not
capable of supporting life. When it is con¬
sidered that some of the larger cellulose
plants are re-clrculatlng more than 300,000
cubic metres of water per day (water con¬
taining highly toxic components which,
even at low concentrations, may affect the
life and behaviour of living organisms), the
importance of the threat to the Lake Baikal
ecosystem can readily be appreciated.
It is in this context that Dr. G.I. Galazy
and fellow scientists from the Irkutsk
Institute have mounted a sustained public
education campaign to inform the Soviet
people about the uniqueness of Lake
Baikal, of the importance of its biota and of
the present and projected effects of human
activities on the lake.
Public awareness about these issues
has been raised throughout the Soviet
Union by a concerted programme involving
the press, television and radio and calling
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The poetry
of llya Chavchavadze
by Gaston Bouatchidzé and Edouard Glissant
on the skills of journalists, science writers
and other communications specialists.
At the same time, government officials
have been regularly informed about the sit¬
uation, and this whole process has trig¬
gered a change in attitudes towards the
economic policy in the Baikal drainage
basin and the conservation status of the
lake ecosystem.
In April 1986, as a result of these efforts
to change public opinion and policy, the
Lake Baikal Region Biosphere Reserve
was approved by the MAB Bureau as a new
addition to the international network of bio¬
sphere reserves. And on 2 April 1987, the
Government of the USSR Issued a new law
concerning the protection and redevelop¬
ment of Lake Baikal and Its surroundings,
as well as plans to close the cellulose
industry ¡n the area within the next five
years. The whole process is instructive of
how scientists' observations and under¬
standing can be put to good use in chang¬
ing policy, and underscores the role of
scientists in initiating and providing the
basic information for educational pro¬
grammes for the public at large.
Gaston Bouatchidzé: The work of llya
Chavchavadze (1837-1907) fits naturally
into the literary tradition of Georgia, the
origins of which can be traced back to the
fifth century. The poetical works which pre¬
ceded and paved the way for his own
include, first and foremost, The Knight in
the Panther's Skin by Shota Rustaveli
(twelfth century), the Davitiani by David
Guramishvili (eighteenth century) and the
poetry of the romantic Nikoloz Baratashvili
(first half of the nineteenth century).
However, the period spanned by the life of
llya Chavchavadze coincides with a unique
chapter in the history of the country. The
poet sets out to be its chronicler, and both
his poetic inspiration and his craft are influ¬
enced by this, being shaped by the dictates
of the author's views, if Rustaveli is the
master of epic and philosophical poetry, a
virtuoso of richly musical and varied verse,
Guramishvili the craftsman of the most
wide-ranging poetic metre and of con¬
structions that are both brilliant and strik¬
ing, and Baratashvili the lyricist of suffering
and melancholy, the poetry of llya
Chavchavadze is outstanding in its deliber
ate purity of form and transparency, in
keeping with his generous breadth ofvision.
Clarity and directness of impact are the
essential characteristics of his work.
Edouard Glissant: The poetry of
Chavchavadze does, indeed, have the
power and refinement to be found in all
literature which strikes a strong popular
chord and marks a new departure. In this
respect it is reminiscent of the French six¬
teenth-century poets such as Jean de
Sponde or Jean-Baptiste Chassignet. At the
same time, it is almost symbolist in its musi¬
cal qualities, and speaks, besides, with the
perfectly controlled voice of modernity.
Here we find a lyrical encounter between
personal feeling and collective destiny.
G.B.: I should like, in this connection, to
Still from the 1958 Soviet film "The Widow
Otarova", which was adapted for the screen
from llya Chavchavadze-'s 1887 novel describ¬
ing the misery of serfdom and the decline of
the feudal system.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
recall the variety of llya Chavchavadze's
writings: the poet in him is closely seconded
by the prose writer, and the publicist goes
hand in hand with the militant humanist and
organizer of various aspects of community
life. This means that the same, or similar,
themes run through his work, and, as it
were, resonate in sympathy with the preoc¬
cupations of the century, and in particular
those of writers such as Pushkin, Victor
Hugo and Tolstoy. Those themes include,
for example, humanism (including the
demand to abolish the death penalty),
social justice, truth at all costs, fervent
patriotism and the need to educate and
enlighten the people.
E.G.: Such poetry is remarkably relevant
today. I am thinking of the quotation from
Leibniz that Chavchavadze chose as an
introduction to his poem Mother Georgia:
"The present, born of the past, in turn
begets the future." Historical memory, with
all its light and shade, is the background to
all identity, particularly in the present age,
when different cultures and civilizations
impinge on one another. Poetry throughout
the world needs both the universal and the
particular. Here again, I think that
Chavchavadze affords an instructive exam¬
ple. Moreover, the "tone" of the language is
The Poet
/ do not sing for singing's sake,
As does the bird upon the tree;
Nor was it for sweet sounds alone
That God created me.
God chooses me; the people shape
And temper me for my vocation,
And I commune with God, that I
May rise and lead my nation.
My heart burns with a holy flame
That all my strength I may employ
To serve my people faithfully
In sorrow and in joy.
O let my people's suffering
Be branded on my soul, I ask
And let my heart, through good and ill,
Be equal to its task!
If in my heart the spark divine
Will kindle fire to banish fears,
Then I will raise my people up,
And I will dry their tears!
Pavlovsk,
23 July 1860
Poem
The soulless life is not
A gift that falls like rain:
What merely lives and dies
Returns to dust again.
A soul that yearns to act
Lights up our path, our goals,
And makes them Infinite
Like He who gives us souls.
Blest is the man whose life
With noble deeds doth shine,
For, mortal, he shall drink
Of the immortal wine.
St. Petersburg,
1860
audible through the translation. But I sup¬
pose that, as in the case of Pushkin, much of
the melody is necessarily lost?
G.B.: In this respect I might offer for com¬
parison my previous experience as a transla¬
tor of Georgian poetry into French. In
translating Rustaveli's The Knight in the
Panther's Skin (to be co-published by
Publications Orientalistes de France and
Raduga of Moscow in 1988), I kept to the
single rhyme of the quatrains and tried, as
far as possible, to transpose the music of the
verses. On the other hand, in the case of a
modern poet, Galaktion Tabidze, whose
"Skull with Artistic Flowers" will be
published this year in Tbilisi in a bilingual
(Georgian-French) edition, I dispensed
with rhyme in order to keep more closely to
the poet's variations of rhythm. With llya
Chavchavadze the problem was primarily
one of maintaining the structures suited to
his form of poetic expression, and rendering
his tone, which is both sober and vigorous.
E.G.: That sobriety reveals both the grace
of a language and the charm of the poet. I
hope that the translations which will appear
in the different language editions of the
Courier will make our readers want to
become better acquainted with the poetry
of Chavchavadze.
Night
When the feverish din of the busy day is
hushed,
And the droning voices of Evil at last are
still,
And, cradled beneath the sky, the village
sleeps,
Then, southern night! on you 1 gaze my fill.
(1857-1861)
Poem
My hopes are crushed and all my dreams are
fled
All lost, all gone. I am alone again.
The arrow loosed from love's despairing
bow,
Piercing my heart, surrendered me to pain.
Cursed by our meeting, in an ill-starred
hour.
Where was this paragon of virtue bred?
And you, my heart, erstwhile subdued and
calm,
What force was this that made you raise the
dead?
All that I amis hersshe is not mine.
And she holds out, adoringly, to sate
Another's thirst, her heady cup of love,
While I can only rail against my fate.
To whom shall I confide my tale of woe?
The door is barred, and I am left outside.
My sickness has no cure, and there can be
No words to comfort me, when hope has
died.
(1877)
Translated into French from the Georgian by Gaston
Bouatchidzé
GASTON BOUATCHIDZE, of the USSR, is a
doctor of philology specializing In French lan¬
guage and literature. A member of the Union of
Writers of the Georgian SSR, he teaches at
Tbilisi State University.
Les
Kurbas,
¡founder of
lUkrainian
theatre
Portrait ofLes Kurbas taken in 1913
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
by Nelly Nicolaevna
Kornienko
THE worldwide interest currently
being shown in Les Kurbas (1887-
1942) is by no means fortuitous. As
the end of the twentieth century
approaches, people are beginning to feel
the need for a "Renaissance personality", a
leader in the arts and a philosopher. Kurbas
was such a personality. He was an actor,
playwright, translator, stage and cinema
director with original ideas about the func¬
tion of the theatre. A disciple of
Melpomene, the Muse of Tragedy, his
greatest claim to fame is that he evolved a
strategy of culture. That is why his ideas on
aesthetics continue to interest people nearly
half a century after his death.
The name of Les Kurbas, founder of
Soviet Ukrainian theatre, figures among
the greatest in the history of dramatic art
Konstantin Stanislavsky, Vsevolod
Meyerhold and Yevgeny Vakhtangov,
Max Reinhardt, Edward Gordon Craig
and Bertolt Brecht.
Kurbas was born in Galicia (then part of
the Austro-Hungarian empire), into a fam¬
ily of well-known Ukrainian actors, the
Yanovichs. Educated at the universities of
Vienna and Lvov, he studied several lan¬
guages, including English, so that he could
read Shakespeare in the original; Nor¬
wegian, in order to understand Ibsen; and
Sanskrit, because he was particularly inter¬
ested in the East. Thus he came to his
national culture in the spirit of a
reformer.
He established a Youth Theatre in 1917,
with the intention of producing plays drawn
from different cultures throughout the
world. This quite exceptional and successful
experiment in theatre work lasted until
1919. Enthusiastic audiences wearing
sweaters and leg-warmers (it was the time of
the Civil War and the country was in a state
of economic dislocation) saw various
plays a brilliant production of Oedipus
Rex, the first of Sophocles' works to be
performed on the Soviet stage; Zhulavsky's
fanciful, impressionistic Yola; Shev-
chenko's expressionistic masterpiece Jan
Huss; intellectual plays such as Lesya
Ukrainka's In the Thicket; one of the
national folklore theatre's colourful Christ¬
mas productions; and, later on, plays by
Shakespeare, Molière, Schiller, Hugo,
Crommelynck and Grillparzer.
Kurbas brought Ukrainian theatre to the
forefront of Soviet and European cultural
life. As early as 1925, at the World Fair in
Paris, the design for one of his productions
won a gold medal for the Soviet Union.
Osip Mandelstam, major Soviet poet and
literary critic, who was anything but compli¬
mentary about the theatre, showed great
insight when he said that Kurbas would be
renowned as the founder of Ukrainian
theatre.
Much of Kurbas' work in the theatre was
based on the idea that "man is a micro¬
cosm", as postulated by the eighteenth-cen¬
tury Ukrainian philosopher Grigori
Skovoroda. Skovoroda's teaching on the
"inner man", the value of the spirit and the
worth of the human personality, had a
marked influence on productions at the
Berezil Theatre in Kharkov, where Kurbas
did most of his work. In many of his produc¬
tions, images inspired by Skovoroda were
used to symbolize the unending search for
spiritual truth.
Kurbas, like Vakhtangov, was an artist of
the Revolution. He regarded the theatre as
a model of society and a forum for the dis¬
cussion of public questions. His vision of a
theatre of "transfiguration", in which the
world could be, as it were, re-created, was
profound and idealistic. A firm believer in
the ethical power of art and the insight it
provides, he thought it was possible to
change society through the artistic and
moral life of the theatre.
But it is unorthodox ideas of this kind that
leave their mark on history, especially when
they are put forward by someone who is
completely disinterested. Thanks to Kur¬
bas, something of Craig's dream about a
school to study the art of the theatre was
realized. He established the Berezil Artists'
Society comprising an extensive network of
theatrical workshops, the prototype of the
new Soviet Ukrainian theatre which pro¬
duced shows ranging from drama and opera
to variety, circus, reviews and musicals as
well of the many theatre research institutes.
The political plays produced by Kurbas at
the Berezil Theatre between 1922 and 1926
included Keiser's Gas, Shevchenko's Haid-
amaks ("Ukrainian Soldiers"), Sinclair's
Jimmy Higgins and Shakespeare's Mac¬
beth. These performances were vivid,
striking studies of extreme psychological
and social experiences, very avant-garde
compared with other contemporary
productions.
Much can be learned from Kurbas' con¬
ception of the theatre. What was true in his
time is true today. The Polish experimental
theatre director Jerzy. Grotowski's search
for the "sacral life of the human spirit", the
British director Peter Brook's vision of a
new kind of culture, the subtle combination
of irony, farce and insight found in the films
of the Italian director Federico Fellini, the
tragic symbolism of the Swedish director
Ingmar Bergman all these recall the
Soviet experiments and, in particular, Kur¬
bas' theatre of "transfiguration". The mys¬
terious nature of his productions gives a
feeling of timelessness to his conception of
humanity. Their interplay of the serious and
the farcical, the eternal and the mortal, the
lofty and the base, is reminiscent of baroque
art; everyday life is interpreted by reference
to the fantastic. Kurbas' aesthetic ideas
brought to theatre a new and dynamic form
of realism based on fantasy, with an infinite
capacity to reveal the complexities of the
world and the absurdities of daily life.
NELLY NICOLAEVNA KORNIENKO, of the
Soviet Union, is a specialist in dramatic art and in
the sociology of culture, subjects on which she
has written some 40 works published in her own
country and elsewhere. A former member of the
sociology of culture sector at the Soviet Institute
of Scientific Research into An, she is currently a
staff member of the Russian language edition of
the Unesco Courier.
Scenefrom Jimmy Higgins, a strikingly inno¬
vative stage version of the American writer
Upton Sinclair's anti-war, humanist novel
(1919), produced by Les Kurbas in 1923.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
»ir.
In the May 1987 issue of the Unesco Courier reference was made
to a proposal by the Greek poet and politician Yannis
Coutsocheras, that the basic food products necessary to humanity
' should not be subject to market forces. In view of the importance
of the question, we publish the following text by Mr. Coutsocheras.
Food for all -
The 'Paris Appeal'
by Yannis Coutsocheras
'- ar¿~
TODAY'S so-called age of affluence is
also an age of paradox. The mounting
wave of individuals and peoples driven
to despair by famine is reaching alarming pro¬
portions.
The brunt of this unacceptable state of
affairs is borne primarily by the children of
developing countries, where 1 5 million people
starve to death every year and 50 million more
are undernourished and suffer from the
serious physical and psychological con¬
sequences of malnutrition, such as inability to
attend school or to work.
Dire poverty is the rule in the population
groups and peoples devastated by famine.
Meanwhile quantities of foodstuffs that the.
market cannot absorb are being destroyed.
The scientific advances that would make it
possible to produce enough food to feed a
population much larger than that of the world
today are not being applied for fear of a drop in
prices. Moreover, astronomical sums are
being wasted on the arms race in order to
prepare for a war which will never take place,
since It is acknowledged that total war would
mean universal suicide. Such poverty is
a source of ever-growing despair, where
bitterness breeds hatred, revolt, violence
and war.
Free access to staple foods in order to guar¬
antee the right to life is a fundamental require¬
ment. The conception of human rights which
has evolved over the years to include the right
to health, the right to education and the right to
work, seems to be lagging behind with respect
to the basic right to life.
In 1975, as a member of the Parliamentary
Assembly of the Council of Europe, I pre¬
sented a proposal calling for universal free
access to basic foodstuffs; subsequently, so
that this ideal might be achieved by degrees, I
restricted my proposal to children, wording it
as follows: "In order to safeguard the lives of
all children, certain basic food products
should not be subject to market forces, and
each child should be entitled to a free
ration."
This proposal has been adopted by various
organizationsthe Council of Europe (1 980),
the Greek Parliament (1 984), Unesco (1 985),
the International Association of Democratic
Lawyers (1986) and by many distinguished
figures. It meets with approval and support
wherever it is put forward, since it is consid¬
ered to be effective and capable of implemen¬
tation without delay.
The onus is on intellectuals to take the first
step and, unswayed by religion, culture,
Threshing grain in Lebanon
nationality, political convictions, race or
colour, to rise up against injustice and make a
joint effort to bring this shameful situation to an
end; so that we may never again read such
headlines as "Rampant famine" or "Rising
world toll of famine and malnutrition", and
never again be told that hunger now afflicts
730 million people.
With this end in view, a group of dis¬
tinguished persons from various countries
has recently set up a Provisional Committee in
Paris to make preparations for 16 October
1 987, World Food Day, when a meeting will be
held at Unesco Headquarters to launch the
"Paris Appeal" for the early withdrawal of sta¬
ple foods, in particular children's foods, from
the arena of market forces. The appeal will go
out to all governments and will be taken up by
news agencies and the media to bring the
campaign to the attention of the world. Subse¬
quently, political will must come to the fore,
since without it nothing can be done.
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco. 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox). Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100
U. S.A. ;(3)N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
I lead. Inc. . 1 1 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S. A.; (4) Belland Howell Co., Old Mansfield
Road. Woostcr. Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief:
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
NedaelKhazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian:
Arabic: Abdclrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstcin
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducrct
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
A II correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: SeiichiroKojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian. Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papagéorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
34 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C1 - Octobre 1 987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A..Z.I. route dEtampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
PUBLICATIONS
Only One Earth video series of three
55-minute introductory programmes and
eight 30-minute case studies, linked to the
publication of Our Common Future, the
report of the World Commission on
Environment and Development. Three lan¬
guage versions planned (English, French,
Spanish). Co-produced by Unesco, the
British Broadcasting Corporation and
North-South Productions, UK, 1987.
Man: The Key to Conservation, slide-tape
package consisting of 55 colour slides,
20-minute cassette, and brochure. (MAB
audio-visual series 3, bi-lingual English/
French.) Unesco, 1986.
InfoMAB, periodical on the work of
Unesco's Man and the Biosphere (MAB)
Programme. The World Heritage Con¬
vention, reference map and list of recorded
World Heritage Sites. Unesco, 1986. MAB
Urban and Human Ecology Digest, by Brian
Spooner. Unesco, 1986. (These publica¬
tions available free of charge from Unesco's
Division of Ecological Sciences.)
Ecology in Action, an exhibit of 36 colour
posters (120 cm x 80 cm) with drawings,
photos and diagrams, accompanied by a
users' guide and a descriptive note, which
presents a synthesis of some of the main
problems of land use, resource manage¬
ment and man-environment relations.
MAB/Unesco, 1981.	
Living in the Environment: A Sourcebook
for Environmental Education, edited by
K.M. Sytnik. UNEP/Unesco, 1985. (Avail¬
able free of charge from Science Teaching,
Education Sector, Unesco.)
Fishes of the North-Eastern Atlantic and
the Mediterranean, edited by P.J. P. White¬
head, M.-L. Bauchot, J.-C. Hureau, J.
Nielsen and E. Tortonese. 3 vols., Unesco,
1985-1987.
Man's Dependence on the Earth: The Role
of the Geosciences in the Environment, edi¬
ted by A.A. Archer, G.W. Liittig and I.I.
Snezhko. UNEP/Unesco, 1987.
Ecology in Action, resource kit.
Heinemann Educational Books/Unesco,
1987.
World Prospects: A Contemporary Study,
by John Molyneux and Marilyn Mac-
Kenzie. Prentice-Hall Canada Inc., Scar¬
borough, Ontario, 1987.
Parks, an international tri-lingual quar¬
terly (English, French, Spanish) for man¬
agers of national parks, historic sites and
other protected areas, published by Science
and Technology Letters on behalf of the
International Union for Conservation of
Nature and Natural Resources (IUCN),
with the support of Unesco. (Vol. 10, No. 3,
1985, on Unesco's MAB Programme.)
t/5
u
i-
3
O
u
s
«
a
u
3
«
resources
A quarterly in English, French, Spanish,
Russian and Chinese, which provides inter¬
national news and information on Unesco
programmes concerning environmental
activities, natural resources research and
conservation. This recent issue, for exam¬
ple, featuring on the cover the Cévennes
Biosphere Reserve in southern France,
contains articles on the development of the
biosphere reserve concept, on water
resources management, and on design for
energy-conserving cities. Each issue also
includes bulletins on Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere (MAB) Programme, the Inter¬
national Hydrological Programme (IHP)
and the International Geological Correla¬
tion Programme (IGCP), plus book reviews
and other news items of general interest.
Annual subscription 60 French francs
Single issue 18 FF
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
In local currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33. Brookvale 2100.
NSW; Periodicals; Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia, Victorian
Division, 328 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000. AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung
Gerald and Co.. Graben 31. A-1Û11, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools
International, Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726, Bahrain. BARBADOS.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64,
Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: Internationale
Drukkerij en Uitgeverij Keesing, Keesinglaan 2-20, 2100 Deurne-Antwerpen.
CCP 000-001 2775-68. French edition and general Unesco publications agent:
Jean de Lannoy. 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internacionais Ltda. Processing Dept., R
Peixoto Gomide 209, 01409, Sao Paulo S P. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd., 1294 Algoma Road. Ottawa, Ontario K1B 3W8. STORES: 61 Sparks
Street, Ottawa. 21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. SALES OFFICE: 7575 Trans Canada
Hwy. Ste. 305, St. Laurent, Quebec H4T 1 V6. CHINA. China National Publica¬
tions Import and Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena51-113 02, Prague 1; Ve Smeckach
30; P.O.B. 790-1 1 1 -27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni literatura, 1 1
Soukenicka. Prague 1 . For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Publishers. Hurbanovo
nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava-CSS R. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-OG, Tids-
skrrftservice, 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn K. EGYPT (ARAB
REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications, No. 1 Talaat Harb
St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. P. O. Box 128. SF-00100
Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641 Vantas 64. Rauti-
kirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1, 01641 Vantas 64. FRANCE.
Librame de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP 12598-48.
GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710
Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF
GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides Entreprises, P.O.
Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE John
Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O, Box 10073, 541 10
Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore. 4 Nikis Street,
Athens T 1 26. Koslarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2 Hippocratous
Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15. Lock Rd., Kowloon.
Hong Kong Govt. Information Services, Publication Centre. Baskerville
House, 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kurtura-Bush import-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389,
Budapest 62. ICELAND. SnaebjÖrn Jonsson and Co.. H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate. Bom¬
bay 400038; 17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road,
Madras 2; 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma
Gandhi Rd-, Bangalore 560001; 3-5-620 Hyderguda. Hyderabad-500001.
Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 17 Park St., Calcutta 70016;
Scindia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37.
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1 188 Englab
Ave., Rostam Give Building, Zip Code 13158. P.O. Box 1 1 365-4498, Teheran.
IRELAND. The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd.. Baliymount Rd., Walkin-
stown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL Literary Transactions, Inc.. Co Steimatzky Ltd.,
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv 61006A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71
Allenby Rd., Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sanso-
ni, S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 501 21 Florence. JAPAN.
Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Faralalla Press Agency. P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue. Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-11. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El Correo de la
Unesco, Actipán 66, Colonia del Valle, Mexico 12, DF. MONACO. British
Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte Cario. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Pol-
chowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe. P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD
Amsterdam. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 14277-
Kilbirnie, Wellington; 1 30 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1 721 , Christchurch; Alma
St., P.O. Box 857, Hamilton; Pnnces St., P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin. NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of Ife; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286.
NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo V, Narvesen
A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad. N 0602 Oslo 6; Unrversitets
Bokhandelen. Universitetssentret. Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo 3.
PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam. P.O. Box No.
729. Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for Book De¬
velopment in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box 8950,
Karachi 29. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI
ARABIA. Dar al Watan. Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building,
Riyadh. SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2
Jurong Port Rd., Singapore 2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas
Publications (Pty) Ltd., Subscription Service, P.O. Box 42476. Johannesburg.
Universitas Books (Pty) Ltd., P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaik's
Bookstore (Pty) Ltd., Libri Building. 268 Church Street. Pretoria 0001 . Central
News Agency Ltd., Group Overseas Periodical Div. P.O. Box 61 3, Cape Town
8000. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner
Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box
1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box 2943, Paramaribo- SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN
Förbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104. 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-
Williams AB, Nordenftychtsvagen 70, S-1 04, 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidskrrft-
scentraten. Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -1 01 . 20 Stockholm, SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Ranmstrasse, Zurich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 121 1,
Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle. Berne,
Vevey. Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment. University of Aleppo. Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.,
40-42 Charoen Krung Road. Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402. Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9. Rajdamnem Ave.. Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND
TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair,
Trinidad W 1. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklal Caddesi, No 469, Posta
Kutusu 219. Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office.
Agency Section Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008. Nine Elms
Lane, London SWS 5DR, and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Belfast. Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta
Ltd.. 122 King's Cross Rd., London WC1X 9DS- UNITED STATES. Beman-
UNIPUB, Periodicals Department, 4611-F Assembly Drive. Lanham. MD
20706 4391 . USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Ihca 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba,
Zoprtarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit. Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
K- ^
v
llya Chavchavadze, a great Georgian poet who was born 150 years ago (see article).
This norlrait, by Guigo Zaziachvili, is today preserved in the Museum of Georgian Art,
Tbilisi (USSR).
]]>
</page>
</document>
