<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="076517eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
-ja*?*
'l¿*ñ& Z
r -ça
m*-
r , ->i
' »*Vl
SP
ff i
A ífrae ío /ft;e
58 Brazil
The candomblé cult
Modem Brazil has been shaped by a process of
racial and cultural intermingling which began
during theperiodwhenforms ofbaroque art and
architecture importedfrom Portugal were being
adapted to the Brazilian environment. Black
slaves transported from Africa were compelled
to accept the Catholic faith, but preserved in
modified form many of their ancestral beliefs
and rituals. Some of the syncretic cults and
rituals which arose from this fusion of cultures
stillhold sway in parts ofBrazil. One of them is
practised by members of the candomblé ritual
groups which first appeared in the 19th century
in the city ofSalvador, formerly Säo Salvador de
Bahia de Todos os Santos, the capital ofAfro-
Brazilian culture. Above, four women members
of a candomblé group at prayer before an altar
in the lavishly gilded baroque church of Säo
Domingo, in Salvador.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial n:::
The baroque age in western Europe began sometime around 1600 and lasted until
the mid-eighteenth century. It saw the flowering of a culture which, although it
developed mainly in the Latin countries, spread to eastern Europe and above all
took root on a grand scale in the Spanish and Portuguese colonies of South
America, where an important hybrid form of baroque art emerged.
Baroque culture was the product of an age marked by profound economic and
social crisis during which the pomp and ceremony associated with absolute
monarchies and the Counter-Reformation could not conceal signs of depression in
a Europe whose religious beliefs had been shaken by the Lutheran Reformation and
by the first conquests of rationalism and modern science.
This acute sense of crisis, which would last until its extinction a century and a half
later by the optimistic humanism of the Enlightenment, shaped many of the .
characteristic features of baroque art and literature: disenchantment, a sense of the
illusory nature of the world of appearances, a theatrical conception of life, an acute
awareness ofpassing time and of the certainty and finality of death, a taste for
artifice and display, and, in art, for exaggerated, "expressionist" forms. But
paradoxically enough, such depressive tendencies triggered off an explosion of
sensuality and whetted an appetite for life and enjoyment which is revealed in the
dazzling exuberance of the baroque visual arts and the prodigious universe of sound
which is baroque music.
The baroque art and culture of seventeenth- and eighteenth-century Europe also
flourished in the Spanish and Portuguese colonies of America, where in time it
underwent a transformation. Models imported from the Iberian peninsula were
gradually adapted, subtly modified and given an original imprint as the process of
ethnic and cultural intermingling overflowed into art. Latin American baroque
would eventually find full expression in such magnificent creations of folk art as the
church ofTonantzintla in Mexico, the "Sistine Chapel" of colonial art.
Some critics consider that the Baroque is not only a European and Ibero-
American phenomenon but a " cultural constant" which recurs throughout the
history of art. It is undeniable that outside Europe and the Americas, in such
different cultural regions as Persia, China, Japan and Kampuchea, forms of
expression closely related to baroque sensibility have appeared. It is also significant
that a century like our own, a century of crises, upheavals and vacillating beliefs,
should feel an affinity with certain seventeenth-century forms of art and culture.
Perhaps it is justifiable, then, to consider the Baroque as a category of aesthetic
sensibility and thus recognize its global dimension.
This number ofthe Unesco Courier does not claim to paint a complete picture of
the immense world of the Baroque . What we have tried to do is to show some of its
most characteristic manifestations and some of its finest achievements.
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
September 1987
40th year
An age of exuberance,
drama and disenchantment
by Peter Skrine
Three great domes
by Giuho Carlo Argan
The musical offering
by Alberto Basso
Spain: An art of gilt and pathos
byJulián Gallego
Baroque as a world philosophy
by Edouard Glissant
Sculpture, theatre of the sublime
by François Souchal
The stately heritage of Portuguese
baroque
byJosé-Augusto Franca
Italy: The great illusionists
by Arnauld Brejon de Lavergnée
LatinAmerica: 'A new form of self-
expression'
by Leopoldo Zea
The Angel with the Arquebus
by Miguel Rojas Mix
Brazil: The triumph of O Aleijadinho
by Augusto C. da Silva Telles
10
11
14
18
20
27
30
34
36
39
CentralEurope: The art of persuasion 42
by Christian Norberg-Schulz
Baroque in the Slav countries
by Georgii Gatchev
46
A time to live...
BRAZIL : The candomblé cult
Cover: The Glorification ofUrban VIII's
Pontificate (1633-1639) painted by Pietro da
Cortona on the ceiling of the main hall of the
Palazzo Barberini in Rome (see article page 30 and
colour pages).
Photo© SCALA, Editions Mazenod, Paris
Back cover: detail of mouldings on the ceiling of
the church of Santa Maria Tonantzintla (c. 1 700),
near Puebla, Mexico (see article page 34).
Photo Kai Müller© CEDRI, Paris
The Courier English
French
Italian
Hindi
Turkish
Urdu
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Finnish
Swedish
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
A window open on the world
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 33 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
German
Arabic
Persian
Dutch
Korean
Swahili
Bulgarian
Greek
Vietnamese
ISSN 0041-5278
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala N°9-1987-CPD-87-l-449A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
An age of exuberance, drama and
disenchantment
BY PETER SKRINE
WHAT does Baroque mean? There
are many overlapping definitions.
To some scholars and art histo¬
rians who have written well about it,
Baroque signifies a mode of European paint¬
ing, a style of architecture, a cultural phe¬
nomenon which found its most effective
expression in the fine arts and the applied
arts. To them, and rightly so, it is above all
something visual.
But to many other scholars and literary
historians, Baroque means an attitude to life
which arose out of that great revival of
cultural energy and aesthetic values known
as the Renaissance, from which it was sepa¬
rated by the deep spiritual and religious
crises which are associated with the Protes¬
tant Reformation.
As a result, baroque literature, which
flowered in the 1620s and 1630s and reached
its zenith around 1660, is characterized by
sharp contrasts and antitheses: its authors
delight in the sensual beauty of things and
are fond of describing them in opulent, even
flowery, detail, but they are also capable of
brooding darkly on the deeper mysteries of
life and eternity. Its playwrights extol heroic
valour and steadfastness, but enjoy the colli¬
sion between such virtues and the passions of
the heart, which they evoke with extraordin¬
ary vigour, eloquence and verve. These
qualities may be seen in the plays of the
German baroque poet Casper von Lohens-
tein (1635-1683) and even in those of his
French contemporary Jean Racine (1639-
1699).
The baroque attitude to life found elo¬
quent expression in literature and music as
well as in architecture and painting. In all
these arts it manifests itself most obviously
in a dynamic relationship between underly¬
ing control of form, a strong desire to create
a sense of movement, and a delight in orna¬
mental detail. In countries where it has left
strong and indelible traces, there is a natural
tendency to rate it highly and to describe the'
finest products of seventeenth-century art
and literature as baroque without further
definition. This is often the case in Italy,
Spain and the Latin-American countries,
and in Austria, the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many, the German Democratic Republic,
and Czechoslovakia.
In England and France, however, there is
a deeply ingrained and understandable reluc¬
tance to accept the term. Indeed, all coun¬
tries with strong Protestant Christian tradi¬
tions, like England and the United States,
tend to regard the Baroque as a typically
Roman Catholic phenomenon, as something
alien to their own culture. The case of
France, however, reveals how complex the
situation really is, for there the Baroque
coincided with what the French are justly
proud of calling their "classical age", which
rightly or wrongly they see as its antithesis.
The Baroque developed at different speeds
and different levels of intensity in different
places. Some areas of art and literature might
be more affected by it than others and some¬
times, too, it could coalesce more or less
naturally with indigenous traditions and
ways of being. Italy, already the home of the
Renaissance, played a large part in its emer¬
gence and its radiation to other parts of
Europe. But should we locate its sources
there alone? There are also valid arguments
for seeing the Baroque as the expression of a
state of mind and an attitude to the world
which arose simultaneously in many dif¬
ferent parts of Europe and which even had
counterparts in other, more distant places
such as the Iran of Shah Abbas (1587-1629),
the China of the early Ch'ing Dynasty and
the Japan of the great dramatist Chikamatsu
(1653-1725).
But let us stay in Christian Western
Europe. There two significant factors were
perhaps more responsible than any others
for the rise of the Baroque. One was the
emergent concept of absolute monarchy, the
other was the popularity of play-acting and
theatre. Europe had not witnessed these
things on such a scale since the emperors and
vast amphitheatres of the ancient Roman
Empire, one thousand years before. When
absolutism and the theatre came together,
and powerful seventeenth-century sov¬
ereigns commanded that splendid perfor¬
mances of plays be given in their magnificent
new palaces, the Baroque was more strik¬
ingly in evidence than anywhere else
except in the ceremonies and imposing
buildings of the Roman Catholic church.
The Church's claim to universal spiritual
authority and its highly-developed sense of
occasion made it a generous patron of
baroque artists, musicians and poets. It
would be impossible to overstress the
importance of royal prestige, spiritual values
and dramatic display in Europe's baroque
achievement.
A pervasive image captures the baroque
age's view of the human condition and its
love of the theatrical : the world as a stage. To
the English speaker this image recalls Shake¬
speare because it occurs in his comedy As
You Like It. But the same notion can be
found in all the major literatures of Europe.
The rich seaport of Amsterdam opened its
municipal playhouse in 1638; over its door
could be read a couplet by the great Dutch
poet of the age, Vondel, which proclaimed
"The world's a stage: each plays his role and
gets his just reward".
Meanwhile in Holland's political and
CONTINUED PAGE 7
The baroque period has been called "the golden
age of the clock-maker's art", and an acute
awareness of time slipping by is a recurrent
theme in great works ofcontemporary literature
such as Shakespeare's plays and the sonnets
of the Spanish poet Francisco Quevedo. Above,
L'habit d'horlogère, an early 18th-century en¬
graving showing a pendulum clock, an inven¬
tion of the baroque age.
Baroque art is characterized by a sense ofactiv¬
ity and movement which contrasts with the
order and restraint ofclassicism. To escapefrom
the rigidity of orderly rectangular areas inher¬
ited by the Renaissance from Greco-Roman
Antiquity, baroque architects often used twisted
columns, the mostfamous examples ofwhich are
those designed by the Italian architect, sculptor
andpainter Gian Lorenzo Bernini (1598-1680)
for the bronze baldacchino or canopy (right)
over the high altar in St. Peter's basilica, Rome.
The dramatic 34-metre-high baldacchino was
commissioned by Pope Urban VIII and built
between 1624 and 1633 beneath the great dome
designed by Michelangelo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
M?
rttfj V
11* 41
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
The world's a stage
"All the world's a stage", says a character in
Shakespeare's comedy As You Like It, and the
Spanish dramatist Calderón de la Barca entitled
one of his early works El Gran Teatro del
Mundo (The Great Theatre ofthe World). Such
theatrical images of the human condition per¬
vade the baroque age, which saw an extraordin¬
ary flowering of the dramatic arts, the magnifi¬
cence of Roman Catholic Church ceremonies
and the pomp of absolute monarchies. In addi¬
tion to Shakespeare and Calderón, other great
17th-century dramatists ofwestern Europe were
Corneille, Racine añd Moliere in France, and
Lope de Vega in Spain. Baroque stage sets were
designed, and new forms of theatre machinery
were developed for the staging of spectacular
productions. Above, decor by the Italian stage
designer Giacomo Torelli for a production of
Corneille's musical tragedy Andromède. Left, a
scene from a performance of Calderón'splay La
vida es sueño (Life is a Dream) at a French
drama festival.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 4
commercial rival, Spain, Vondel's contem¬
porary Calderón de la Barca was writing his
famous masterpiece El Gran Teatro del
Mundo, the play which gives the image of the
world as a stage its supreme baroque inter¬
pretation: for here God Almighty is himself
the author of the play which is produced on
the stage of our human world after the cur¬
tain of chaos has risen. This play is acted
extempore by the various men and women to
whom its parts are given: ambitious king and
beautiful woman, overworked peasant and
bullied beggar, wise religious person and
complacent rich man, they may be stereo¬
types, yet they are caught up so realistically
in the act of living that they seem to come to
life before our very eyes. Of course their
performances turn out less well than God
had hoped, and divine Grace, the prompter,
has a very difficult task with such all-too-
human actors. But fortunately God is also an
indulgent author and spectator. The climax
of Calderón's play, like the massive Spanish
altarpieces of the period, confronts its spec¬
tators with the timeless message central to
the Christian faith: the sacrifice of Christ
and mankind's redemption as seen through
the eyes of a post-Reformation Spanish
Roman Catholic poet with a truly baroque
imagination.
Baroque men and women were always
conscious that the eyes of God and the world
were upon them. But this did not lead to self-
consciousness in the modern post-Romantic
sense. Instead it fostered a sense of self-
esteem and an awareness of the importance
of cutting a figure in the world, of projecting
an image as meaningful as those conveyed by
the painting, sculpture and drama of the
period. Maybe the painted portraits of the
Baroque, like its stage productions and the
descriptive passages in its profuse pastoral
and courtly romances, did not seem as unre¬
alistic to their contemporaries as they per¬
haps now seem to us.
Like painted portraits, baroque palaces
reflect their builders' views of themselves.
They are panegyrics in stone, and their pur¬
pose was to extol the virtues and victories of
those who lived in them. In order to laud
their names and magnify their deeds,
baroque princes also required the services of
writers, who were usually ready to place
their talents at the disposal of their patrons
and to praise them in fulsome odes, light-
hearted wedding poems and sonorous epi¬
taphs, all written to order. Financial reasons
certainly had a part to play in this, but one
senses the presence of profounder and more
compelling motives. There are times when
the balance between meaning and hollow
bombast, triumph and despair, is so finely
caught that the desire of baroque artists to
exalt great men and their achievements can
strike us as a heroic show of defiance and
a bold attempt to drown their sense of
insecurity.
A note of disenchantment was present in
the Baroque right from the start. Its fond¬
ness for play-acting and for the metaphor of
the stage reveals its deep-seated awareness
that appearances are all illusion. Its flam
boyant praise of great men and heroes as in
the plays of the French Corneille, the
English Dryden and the German
Gryphius may just have been an attempt to
postpone the oblivion that must finally
engulf all things, even the greatest. Amidst
all the colour, glitter and extrovert joy of
living so characteristic of the baroque
period, there was a darker and more search¬
ing side to its literature. "Chaque instant de
la vie est un pas vers la mort," the Roman
emperor Titus realizes in the last act of Cor-
neille's late tragedy The et Bérénice
(1670).
But when the play is over, what then? The
people who inhabited the baroque world
could never entirely forget that life is pre¬
carious and short indeed in comparison to
the certainty and finality of death: "Death,
in itself, is nothing; but we fear to be we
know not what, we know not where," says
the Indian hero of John Dryden's heroic
play Aureng-Zebe (1675).
War, famine and plague were common
occurrences for people then: for instance the
Thirty Years War devastated the German-
speaking areas of Europe between 1618 and
1648, and plague ravaged London and many
other cities in 1665. A few years later, Hans
Jakob Christopher von Grimmelshausen, a
German soldier who had served in that war,
produced one of the masterpieces of baroque
prose fiction, a novel called Simplidssimus,
which has been translated into many lan¬
guages and which expresses its author's first¬
hand experience of prosperity and adversity
in a fascinating fusion of narrative forms and
styles ranging from the picaresque tradition
of the Spanish satirical novel of low life to the
fashionable courtly romance in which the
hero's adventures finally turn out to have an
underlying design and purpose.
In various parts of Europe men were gaz¬
ing heavenward at the mysteries of a universe
which was growing daily vaster thanks to the
newly invented telescope, and trying to
comprehend the harmonies which they
knew must underlie it. Kepler's scientific
emphasis on elliptical motion, and his obser¬
vation that the heavenly bodies can form
constant patterns despite the fact that they
are never static, have many features in com¬
mon with the restless movement, the ellipti¬
cal shapes and the formal designs which
underlie all baroque architecture, art and lit¬
erature. The recognition of fundamental
laws and transcendental order made it possi¬
ble for them to accept that this brief and
fragile life of ours, this vale of tears, is a mere
illusion, yet prevented them from lapsing
into dark despair at the inevitable fact of
mortality. Even in the delightful innocent
pastoral world of Arcadia, peopled with
pretty nymphs and love-lorn shepherds,
which baroque writers never tired of evok¬
ing, death could never be entirely ruled
out.
But it was not of death, perhaps, that
baroque writers most complained, but of
Time, under the fatal shadow of whose
wings all things decay and wither. The cen¬
tury which saw the invention of the pen
dulum clock and the balance-spring mecha¬
nism in watches was growing more and more
aware of the passing of time of time mea¬
sured not just in seasons, months and days,
but in hours, minutes and even seconds. The
pressure which all modern people know
came as something of a shock to the seven¬
teenth century. To own an hour-glass or
pocket-watch was a first step towards the
acute consciousness of fleeting time which
quickly became a major preoccupation of the
period. It became a frequent theme for
poets, and in some more thoughtful writers
it was to engender a feeling of metaphysical
dread.
But the acute awareness of rapacious time
forever slipping by and taking with it all the
things we love and value most; the universal
sense of the vanity of all earthly things which
poets and preachers reiterated in all the
cultural languages of Europe; the tomb
always waiting just around the corner as a
reminder that flesh is mortal and that man is
dust: all this paradoxically led to an extraor¬
dinary capacity for living and enjoying life.
This paradox is to be found at the heart of
countless baroque poems in which poets
encouraged men and women to gather
rosebuds while the summer lasted, to love
one another and to be in love, and to appreci¬
ate the colourful masquerade of life. Their
knowledge that it would all end like a dream
served to put life in perspective and to
enhance its value for those on whom fortune
smiled. Famous examples are to be found in
all the literatures of Europe: in John Donne
and Herrick, in the French poet Ronsard's
admirers Hooft and Opitz in the Nether¬
lands and Germany, and in the complex and
Pain and suffering are frequently portrayed in
religious drama, painting and above aü sculp¬
ture of the baroque age. Spanish baroque reli¬
gious carvings are particularly notable for their
sometimes macabre depictions of Christ, the
Virgin Mary and other figures of the Passion
story in paroxysms ofgrief. Below, the severed
head of St. John the Baptist (c. 1625) by the
Cordobán sculptor Juan de Mesa (Seville
cathedral).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The works ofShakespeare (left), while not strict¬
ly speaking baroque, often reflect the spirit of
the age in their explosive violence and in their
preoccupation with appearance and reality and
with dramatic illusion. The SpanishpoetLuis de
Góngora y Argote (centre) was a master of a
highly ornamental, labyrinthine style which be¬
came known as "gongorism". Like its Italian
equivalent "marinismo" (named after the Ita¬
lian Giambattista Marino), it echoed contem¬
porary trends in the plastic arts. Engraving,
bottom left, is the frontispiece illustration of a
17th-century edition of Simplicissimus, a'mas-
terwork ofbaroqueprose by the German writer
Grimmehhausen.
jfoaiiUT.mnriT i tnuiram u ""VrrT
'3
.'¡."-vii.- ,Vr r tr: "*
MWm
sophisticated verse of Marino in Italy and
Góngora in Spain.
Despite its emphasis on the transience of
all earthly things, baroque culture produced
works of literature which can attain
unparalleled vitality and intensity. But this
only becomes fully evident if one can under¬
stand the meaning of the words in which
baroque poems, plays and novels are writ¬
ten and sometimes their hidden meanings,
too ! Otherwise, the rich interplay of images,
metaphors and conceits which baroque
writers delighted in inventing may some¬
times seem to readers today to amount to
nonsense.
Only in performance can baroque plays
and operas capture our whole attention and
enthral us with their sights and sounds, their
appeal to ear and eye, the mind and the imag¬
ination. Yet performances are rare, and most
of them have to take place in the imagina¬
tions of sympathetic readers or of listeners to
recordings. Only when we are actually
standing in the baroque churches and palaces
which can be found all over Western Europe
and in many of its former overseas colonial
possessions can we come to appreciate the
powerful claims that the Baroque makes on
us.
Modern readers and spectators may think
that much is fake: they may find it as hard to
relate to the far-fetched metaphors and florid
sentiments expressed by baroque love poets
as to the exaggerated poses of carved and
painted statues. But sometimes, even now,
we can still register the impact of a love
sonnet or a funerary ode, a heroic tragedy or
a deftly turned comedy, and marvel at the
audacity with which these artists three cen¬
turies ago reflected a world not yet deprived
of its sense of delight and wonder and gave
expression to Europe's last comprehensive
vision of a universe not yet bereft of its
divinity.
PETER SKRINE, of the United Kingdom,
teaches German language and literature at the
University of Manchester, and specializes in the
poetry and drama of the seventeenth century. He
has written many articles on these and other sub¬
jects and is the author of a book on seventeenth-
century literature and culture in Europe, entitled
The Baroque (Methuen, London and New York,
1978).
Rubens
the magnificent
While baroque art did not take root in the
northern Netherlands, it blossomed in the south
(what is now Belgium) above all in 17th-century
painting. Baroque art is at its most luminous and
sensual in the work ofPeterPaulRubens, which
celebrates life in all its forms. Through Rubens,
who knew Italy well and paid a long visit to
Spain, Antwerp became a centre ofthe artsfrom
which a taste for baroque painting spread
throughout Europe. Right, The Last Judgment
(1616), a work by Rubens which is today pre¬
served in Munich. Compared with the work
which inspired it, Michelangelo's Last Judg¬
ment in the Sistine Chapel, Rubens' painting
appears typically baroque by virtue of the ex¬
aggerated dynamism of its figures and the vio¬
lent effects of contrast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
*
'#'
tf
#
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Three great domes BY GIULIO CARLO ARGAN
St. Peter's basilica, Rome, with the colonnade
designed by Bernini flanking the square
St. Paul's cathedral, London The church of St. Louis des Invalides, Paris
IF Roman Baroque is the representation
of a religious and political ideal, French
Baroque is the representation of an
exclusively political ideal, and English
Baroque that of a civic and social ideal. The
diversity of the ideological content of
French, English and Italian Baroque is strik¬
ingly illustrated by a comparison between
the three famous domes of St. Peter's in
Rome, the church of St. Louis des Invalides
in Paris, and St. Paul's cathedral in London.
The first is clearly the archetype. In the
thinking of its architect, Michelangelo, later
followed and given a wide allegorical sweep
by Bernini in his conception of the colon¬
nade flanking St. Peter's Square, the dome
was ta be identified with the body of the
church, to be the image of the head of Chris¬
tianity and of the celestial vault which ideally
covers the whole ecumene (the world). In
Bernini's design, the wings of the colonnade
are like the arms of a figure whose head is the
dome.
Resting on a double drum, Jules Hard-
ouin Mansart's dome in Paris rises in sov¬
ereign isolation above a flat façade divided
by columns into geometrical panels: its mass
and its ornate decoration dominate the
whole building, supported on a perfect
architectural arrangement just as the sov¬
ereign power was supported by the hier¬
archical order of the State of which it was the
summit.
Christopher Wren's dome in London is
related, through the Italian architect Sebas¬
tiano Serlio, to Donato Bramante's original
plan for St. Peter's. It rests on a vast edifice
with which it is so little articulated that it
requires a cylindrical base. It is like a build¬
ing incorporated into another building and
only distinguished from it by the stylized
elegance of the drum and the curvature of the
dome. This dome is more of a symbol than
an image of power; and its function is purely
formal, like that of the sovereign in the
English political structure of the late seven¬
teenth century. Without going so far as to
see a deliberate political allegory, it must be
remembered that the form of a dome tradi¬
tionally symbolizes authority or power and
that such a political intention is surely at the
origin of Michelangelo's dome and inspired
the domes of Mansart and Wren.
GIULIO CARLO ARGAN, Italian art histor¬
ian, is a professor at the University of Rome and
was mayor ofthe aty from 1976 to 1979. He is the
author of many works on art history, urban plan¬
ning and methods of criticism, including the book
from which this article is taken, Immagine e per-
suasione. Saggi sul barocco (1987) and, published
in English, The Renaissance City (Braziller, New
York, 1969).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The musical offering BY ALBERTO BASSO
Opera, one of the most characteristic forms of
baroque musical expression, originated in Italy
with Orfeo, L'incoronazione di Poppea and
other landmark works by Claudio Monteverdi.
The first significant French operas were written
by the Italian-born musician Jean-Baptiste
Lully, whose influence extended throughout
Europe. Above, "The Fall ofPhaethon ", a stage
design by Jean Bérain the Elder for Lully 's
musical drama Phaeton.
IN music, the term baroque has been
used to describe a certain concept of art,
a stylistic idiom, but also a method of
composition built on a specific component,
the basso continuo. Described in simple
terms, such compositions consist of a
melodic line and a continuous accompani¬
ment in a set form. This type of composition
is quite different from that of the preceding
period, when the emphasis was placed on
polyphony, that is, music in which there are
several parts of equal importance.
The starting point of the new epoch is
usually taken as the year 1600, when the
Italian melodramma (opera) came into
being, and its end is generally considered to
have come with the death of Johann Sebas
tian Bach in 1750. The history of music
underwent extraordinary changes in this
century and a half during which forms that
were to exist for hundreds of years were
"invented", and the structure of harmony
was established on foundations that lasted
into much later times.
As the Renaissance drew to a close, one
outstanding event dominated the musical
world, and later had a far-reaching effect on
the development of style in literature, in the
pictorial arts, in architecture and even in
social life. This was the rise of opera, the
logical evolution of the revival of the art of
theatre which was ushered in by the Italian
courts and was the outcome of the Renais¬
sance desire to recreate classical Antiquity
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
and actualize Hellenistic civilization. Opera
originated in Florence, but acquired various
characteristics of style and expression in
Rome, Venice and Naples. It was the most
effective vehicle of the new musical culture
in Italy, and rapidly won recognition in
other countries, where it almost always
retained its original character, except in
France where it developed independently
and was known as tragédie lyrique.
Claudio Monteverdi, Luigi Rossi and
Francesco Cavalli were the leading expo¬
nents of this new genre in the early seven¬
teenth century, while later Jean-Baptiste
Lully (the Florentine who was the father of
French opera) and Alessandro Scarlatti came
to the fore as creators of two different kinds
of musical theatre that persisted throughout
almost the whole of the eighteenth century.
The operatic style that prevailed was that
of Scarlatti, which was taken as a model even
by German masters such as Handel and
Hasse. Opera was originally a "serious"
genre, but later it assumed a comic form as
well, and became either a theatrical produc¬
tion in its own right or a kind of humorous
interlude performed between the acts of a
larger production (as in the case of the inter¬
mezzo, the undisputed master of which was
the Italian composer Giovanni Battista Per-
golesi). In other countries opera gave rise to
entertainments in which spoken dialogue
and singing were combined (the English
masque, the Spanish zarzuela, the French
opéra-comique, the German Singspiel),
which supplanted the traditional Italian pat¬
tern of recitative and aria.
This same pattern also dominated other
forms of vocal music, above all the oratorio,
the authentic expression of the devotional
spirit of the Counter-Reformation which
has all the characteristics of a spiritual opera
without scenery. At least, this is the case
with the most typical, vernacular form of
oratorio, such as the splendid works of
Stradella and Alessandro Scarlatti, for those
written in Latin (mainly associated with
Carissimi) were more ecclesiastical in
spirit.
Unlike oratorios, which usually relate
biblical events or the lives of the saints, Pas¬
sion music centres on the death of Christ and
often uses the words of the Gospels. The
finest examples are the Passions of Bach, but
other great settings were written by
Heinrich Schütz and later by Handel (who
was also a master of the oratorio) and by
Georg Philipp Telemann.
Opera in miniature, the chamber cantata is
a typical expression of Italian vocal music.
The thousands of examples of this genre sug¬
gest that its popularity exceeded even that of
the madrigal in the sixteenth century. One or
two recitatives and arias were enough to
create a cantata, and the only instrument
required, as a rule, was a harpsichord to
provide the accompaniment. From Car¬
issimi to Rossi, from Cesti to Stradella, from
Pasquini to Scarlatti and Handel, the cantata
remained in vogue throughout the baroque
period, even in French musical circles,
which constantly resisted the Italian style.
Indeed, the opposition between Italian style
and French taste was one of the most
persistent and pervasive features of the
baroque era.
As for sacred music intended for use in the
liturgy, masses and motets continued to be
composed, although at a rather sluggish rate.
The great masters of sacred music belonged
to the Roman and Venetian schools (Benev-
oli, Bernabei, Caldara, Gasparini, Legrenzi)
and then the Neapolitan school (Scarlatti,
Durante, Leo), later being drawn from the
Germanic countries, (Biber, Kerll and Fux)
and France (Charpentier, Lalande and Cou-
perin). In England, remarkable services and
anthems were written for the Anglican'
Church by composers who were also noted
for their secular music, such as Gibbons,
Tomkins, Lawes, Blow, and above all Pur-
cell, who inspired even Handel.
But it was in the Protestant Church music
Developed to a high degree of technicalperfec¬
tion, the harpsichord and the organ were, with
the violin, the favourite instruments ofbaroque
composers. In the work ofGirolamo Frescobaldi
in Italy andJohann Sebastian Bach in Germany,
organ music reached its peak, while in France
François Couperin "the Great" won fame as the
composer of music for the harpsichord. Eight¬
eenth-century engraving, left, shows the decora¬
tion of the organ in Weingarthen Abbey in
Swabia (Fed. Rep. of Germany) built by Gabler
in 1750. Below, "A Lady Playing a Spinet", an
engraving by Bonnart (c. 1685). An early
keyboard instrument of the harpsichordfamily,
the spinet was widely played in the 16th and
17th centuries, especially in England.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
From Monteverdi to Bach
which sprang from the Lutheran Reforma¬
tion that the baroque period revealed a new
sensibility. The sacred cantata, more often
called a sacred concerto or simply a concerto
(as if to emphasize that it was the descendant
of the Italian concerto ecclesiastico, a com¬
bination of voices and instruments), came to
play an essential role in worship, and
inspired a constant creative effort from com¬
posers. The words were taken from the
Scriptures, often from the readings pre¬
scribed by the liturgical calendar for feast-
days, and the music took over that extraor¬
dinary vehicle of artistic and religious feel¬
ing, the chorale.
Schein, Scheidt and Schütz (the three great
Ss of the history of German music) laid the
foundations of an edifice that was to include
composers such as Buxtehude, Pachelbel,
Tunder, Weckmann, Böhm, Theile, and
above all Bach and Telemann (the latter
wrote almost 1,600 liturgical cantatas).
Bach, however, was the great exponent of
the religious cantata. (He is thought to have
written some 300, a third of which are lost.)
His works, which span the whole baroque
period, constitute an unrivalled repertory of
the vocal and instrumental techniques used
to express the emotions aroused by sacred
texts and religious festivals.
Some of the greatest works of instrumen¬
tal music, whether for a solo instrument or
an ensemble, are associated with the baroque
period. Pride of place went to keyboard
instruments (harpsichord, spinet, virginals,
clavichord and organ), with a repertoire that
was often interchangeable. The work of the
Italian school of organists reached its peak
with Girolamo Frescobaldi, whose organ
music and style influenced the whole of
Europe. One of his most distinguished
pupils, Johann Jakob Froberger, spread
throughout the Germanic countries a mes¬
sage that was heard above all by the masters
of the southern school, whose greatest figure
was Pachelbel. The northern school, on the
other hand, was more vigorous and pro-
Shown above are portraits of some of the great
composers who contributed to the flowering of
baroque music, which began with Monteverdi
in Italy at the beginning of the 17th century and
ended in the first half of the 18th century with
Bach. 1. Claudio Monteverdi (1567-1643), com¬
poser of operas, madrigals and sacred music,
whose work had a seminal influence on modem
music. 2. François Couperin (1668-1733), the
French master of the harpsichord, as depicted in
an anonymous portrait at the Palace of Ver¬
sailles. 3. Johann Sebastian Bach (1685-1750),
one of the greatest musical geniuses ofall time,
(engraving afterapainting by Gebel). 4. George
Frederick Handel (1685-1759), another great
German composer, who spent much ofhis life in
England (engraving after a painting by G.F.
Schmidt). 5. The Italian composer Alessandro
Scarlatti (1660-1725). His son Domenico, a
harpsichord virtuoso, livedfor manyyears at the
Spanish court, and taught Antonio Soler, the
leading Spanish baroque composer. 6. Henry
Purcell (1659-1695), the English composer who
in his short life wrote some of the finest lyrical
music of the age.
1 . Photo © Cournat © Rapho, Paris
2. Photo © Ciccione-Bulloz, Paris
3. Photo © Bulloz, Paris. Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
4. Photo © Bulloz, Paris. Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
5. Photo © Roger Viollet, Paris. Museo Cívico, Bologna
6. Photo © Edimedia, Paris. British Museum, London
duced more illustrious figures, notably Bux¬
tehude. It claimed as its progenitor a Dutch
master, Sweelinck.
Toccatas, fantasias, preludes, Capriccios,
ricercars and fugues proliferate in the key¬
board music of the time. Dance rhythms
were adapted into suites incorporating styl¬
istic, metrical and dynamic variation. The
Lutheran liturgy gave scope for the develop¬
ment of another genre, the choral prelude for
organ, which extended the range of that
instrument by providing it with a repertoire
of incomparable splendour, which will for¬
ever be associated with the name of Bach.
Among the illustrious names linked with
the harpsichord are those of Frescobaldi and
Michelangelo Rossi, and later Pasquini,
Alessandro Scarlatti and his son Domenico,
Couperin and Rameau, Bach and Handel.
But the harpsichord was also used to accom
pany instruments on which the melody was
played, especially the violin, the repertoire
for which culminates in the sonata and the
concerto, the two great ideal forms of the
baroque period, whether composed as
church music or as chamber music. Later,
the development of the concerto followed
two paths: that of the concerto grosso (in
which a group of solo instruments is heard in
contradistinction to the whole orchestra, the
tutti), and that of the concerto solo (in which
a single instrument accomplishes impressive
feats of virtuosity).
Arcangelo Corelli was the forerunner of
generations of violinists, but with him were
the greatest exponents of Italian eighteenth-
century instrumental music Vivaldi,
Albinoni, Geminiani, Locatelli, Tartini,
Torelli, Marcello. Hundreds of works for
solo instruments or groups are evidence of
an incomparable vitality which was felt in
every country in Europe, for their compos¬
ers bore the Italian style far beyond the bor¬
ders of Italy.
Meanwhile, new musical forms were
being developed. The symphony and over¬
ture vied with each other in a field teeming
with ideas, and compositions gradually
became increasingly complex and more
heavily orchestrated. The basso continuo
acquired a personality of its own, as several
themes were introduced into the fabric of the
music, which was composed in accordance
with dialectical principles. From then on the
rich, mannered baroque style began to give
way to the elegant and graceful style galant.
ALBERTO BASSO, Italian musicologist, was
president of the Italian Musicology Society from
1973 to 1979. He is the author of several books
including a six-volume history of music and a
biography of Johann Sebastian Bach. He is at
present editing an eight-volume Dizionario encic¬
lopédico universale della música e dei musicisti
("Universal Encyclopaedic Dictionary of Music
and Musicians").
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
An art ofgilt andpathos BY JULIAN GALLEGO
Above, the monumental baroque façade known
as the Obradoiro, which was added to the
romanesque cathedral of Santiago de Compost-
ela (Spain) in the 18th century. Gothic and
plateresque (Spanish Renaissance) elements are
also found in the cathedral.
IT should be said at the outset that
religion played a fundamental role in the
development of Spanish Baroque. We
shall not go into the question of the meaning
of the term baroque, still less consider
whether, as the Spanish critic Eugenio d'Ors
has claimed, it is a cultural constant, recur¬
ring throughout the history of art in dif¬
ferent periods and forms, in alternation with
classicism.
In his book Principles of Art History, the
Swiss art historian Heinrich Wölfflin
broadly defined "classical" and "baroque" as
static and changing forms of art respectively.
In another influential book, Baroque, the
Art of the Counter-Reformation, by Werner
Weisbach, the Baroque is seen as a passio¬
nate reaction against Renaissance paganism.
Some specialists have recently suggested
that there is an intermediate style known as
Mannerism, which did not commit the
rhythmic and decorative excesses of the
Baroque but did reject the balance of the
Renaissance in an endeavour to achieve
heightened emotional effects (the most
renowned example of this style is perhaps
Michelangelo's LastJudgment, in the Sistine
Chapel, Rome). Some scholars consider that
Mannerism is the true art of the Counter-
Reformation, and the Spanish critic José
Camón Aznar has suggested that the term
"mannerist" should be replaced by "tren-
tine" (after the Council of Trent, which cod¬
ified the principles of the Counter-Reforma¬
tion).
The monastery of San Lorenzo del
Escorial, one of the outstanding monuments
of Spanish architecture, is an example of this
style. It was built near Madrid between 1563
and 1584 on the orders of Philip II. Its archi¬
tects were Juan Bautista de Toledo and Juan
de Herrera, the latter of whom gave his name
to the "herrcran style". Characterized by
austerity, clarity of line and volume, and an
attachment to regular, geometrical forms,
the style of the Escorial was to influence the
development of Spanish architecture
throughout most of the seventeenth century,
and remained a model until it was supplanted
in the eighteenth century by the highly orna¬
mental "churriguercsque" style, which took .
its name from that of a family of architects,
the Churrigueras.
Most ecclesiastical buildings in the Span¬
ish baroque style were built to rectilinear
plans until well into the eighteenth century,
and innovations were confined to ornamen¬
tation. Many churches were built to a plan
derived from that of II Gcsù in Rome, the
mother church of the Society ofJ esus, which
had been founded by the Spaniard Ignatius
Loyola. The plan of II Gcsù is cruciform,
and there is a dome above the crossing of the
transepts and the nave. On each side of the
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
nave there is a row of chapels. There are also
examples of vast oblong churches, whose
architectural sobriety contrasts with their
abundant, showy decoration, in wood and
plaster, sometimes stone and metal. Iron¬
work is rich and abundant, and the chapels
usually have wrought-iron gates. The deco¬
ration of the upper part of the church may
take the form of stalactite-like shapes and
other ornamental relief carvings of the type
described technically as "Grotesque". In
some cases these are vestiges of the mudejar
style of Muslim Spain (al-Andalus) which
lasted from the eighth century until the end
of the fifteenth century.
The lower part of the walls is often cov¬
ered with altarpieces in the form of a tri¬
umphal arch with richly decorated columns
and pediments. The largest altarpiece, in the
apse, is a monumental structure which
reaches to the vaults and is usually entirely
covered with gilt and polychrome painting.
In the church of San Esteban in Salamanca is
a massive altarpiece designed by José de
Churriguera (1668-1725). It has six huge
twisted "Solomonic" columns, modelled on
a column in Rome which was supposed to
have been part of Solomon's temple; this
form became famous when Bernini used it
for the baldacchino, or ornamental canopy,
over St. Peter's tomb (see photo page 5).
Supports of this kind (which sometimes sup¬
port nothing) bring dynamism to porches,
chapels and shrines, of which there are many
remarkable examples in Andalusia. They
display the influence of the new architecture
from Latin America, for while Spanish mod¬
els were dominant in Spain's American colo¬
nies, they were influenced by the taste and
craftsmanship of the indigenous peoples
(especially in Mexico and Peru) and gave rise
to a colonial Baroque whose luxuriant orna¬
mentation and colours in their turn influ¬
enced the Baroque of metropolitan Spain.
The great Spanish court architect was
Pedro de Ribera (c. 1683-1 742), whose work
showed a pronounced taste for the theatri¬
cal. As supports he used "estípites", highly
decorated pilasters of irregular shape, which
had been introduced into Madrid architect¬
ure by José Ximénez Donoso (1628-1690).
Thus, although the Bourbons succeeded the
House of Austria as rulers of Spain, the clas¬
sical baroque style of Versailles was not
adopted at the Spanish court until the royal
palace in the Alcazar (the style of which was
more or less herreran) was destroyed by fire
in 1734 and was replaced by the Palacio de
Oriente, the work of the Italian architects
Filippo Juvarra and Giovan Sacchetti, in
which there is less typically baroque orna¬
mentation. The outstanding example of this
transition to classicism is the architect Ven-
Right, the Baptism of Christ by El Greco (1541-
1614), the great Cretan artist who settled in
Toledo. Baroque sensibility is apparent in the
dramatic upward movement and bold elonga¬
tion ofnaturalforms characteristic ofEl Greco 's
late works.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
tura Rodríguez (1717-1785), who
redesigned the Paseo del Prado, which made
Madrid one of the great European capi¬
tals.
In Andalusia, the vitality of the Baroque
left its mark on churches, monasteries and
convents, and palaces, in which fantasy and
elegance are combined in the use of multi¬
coloured materials such as brick, various
kinds of stone, glazed tiles, carved wood,
forged iron-work, shutters and stucco. Of
special interest are tall, decorated bell-tow¬
ers such as that at Ecija, and elegant bell-
gables, examples of which are found in
Seville and Cadiz. Inside the highly deco¬
rated churches there is often a window at a
certain height in the altarpiece, through
which can be seen a high chapel or niche
where a holy image is presented for worship.
Most of the external decoration was in por¬
ches and cornices; walls were left as
unadorned brick or stone, or were regularly
whitewashed to offer a striking contrast with
the deep blue of the sky.
In Spanish towns and cities a labyrinth of
medieval streets often leads to magnificent
church porches or to a plaza mayor, one of
the great squares which, throughout the
peninsula, are the focal point of civic life and
festivities. The churrigueresque great square
in Salamanca is a notable example. Some of
these squares are veritable museums of dif¬
ferent architectural periods and styles,
brought together and unified by baroque
urban planning. One example can be seen at
Santiago de Compostela, where the cathe¬
dral, which was given the monumental
The monastery ofSan Lorenzo delEscorial, built
near Madrid between 1563 and 1584 on the
orders ofPhilip II, provided a model for much
17th-century Spanish architecture. In the next
century the influence of its austere classicism
gave way to the highly ornate baroque churri¬
gueresque style. Below, the Patio of the Kings,
with the façade, a tower and the dome of the
monastery church.
baroque façade known as El Obradoiro by
Fernando Casas y Novoa in the eighteenth
century, is an extraordinary amalgam of
romanesque, Gothic, plateresque and classi¬
cal styles.
Through the combined effect of sculpture
and architecture, churches became sacred
theatres opening on to the splendid pro¬
cessions that took place outside. Wood carv¬
ing was the principal form of sculpture,
together with clothed polychrome statues
which were intended to create a lifelike
effect. The seventeenth-century school of
Valladolid, one of the masters of which was
Gregorio Fernández, produced sober, natu¬
ralistic works, full of intense emotion. The
people were thus helped to relive Christ's
Passion and death in the Holy Week pro¬
cessions. The Andalusian school was more
expansive and exuberant. Its polychromes
are brighter, and are combined with rich
materials. In Seville, Juan Martínez Mon¬
tañés (1568-1649) and Juan de Mesa (1583-
1627) were noted for the brilliant colours
and expressive gestures of their works, and
in Granada Alonso Cano (1601-1667),
Pedro de Mena (1628-1688) and José de
Mora (1642-1724) painted works of great
poignancy. The subjects most frequently
treated are scenes from the childhood and
Passion of Christ and the motherhood and
sorrow of the Virgin Mary.
The eighteenth century saw a trend
towards greater movement and elegance and
more brilliant colours, both in the decora¬
tion of wood (covered with gold leaf, which
was covered in its turn with oil-painted
embellishments), and in the clothing of stat¬
ues with embroidered garments. To
heighten the illusion that they were real and
to intensify the sense of drama, statues were
fitted out with eyes of crystal, artificial eye¬
lashes, and hair. Pedro Roldan (1624-1700)
and his daughter Luisa, "La Roldana" (1 656-
1704), introduced the new style to Seville,
carving widely-admired statues such as that
of the Virgin of Macarena. Smaller statues
The baroqueperiod in Spanishpainting came to
an end with Juan de Valdés Leal (1622-1690),
whose works are charged with tension and dra¬
ma. Above, Valdés Leal's The Wedding at
Canaan, now in the Louvre Museum, Paris.
were executed in terra-cotta, a technique
employed with great elegance by José
Risueño of Granada (1 665- 1 757). In Murcia,
Francisco Salzillo (1707-1781), an artist of
Neapolitan descent, was renowned both for
his Nativity figures and for groups of elegant
and expressive sculptures which could be
carried in the Easter procession.
The baroque period is the Golden Age of
Spanish painting. The Andalusian school,
which was naturalistic in the Italian style,
emerged at the beginning of the seventeenth
century with Pacheco and Herrera, and
filled the churches with huge canvasses. The
successors of El Greco (1541-1614) worked
in Toledo. They did not reach the ecstatic
mannerist heights of the Cretan master,
whose last works, in their depiction of ver¬
tiginous upward movement, verged on the
Baroque. Francisco de Zurbarán (1598-
1664), from Extremadura, painted pictures
for altars and cloisters that were imposing in
their archaic sobriety, their tactile and
almost architectural effects, and their pious
gravity.
Italian influence can be seen in the painters
of the Valencian school, who were in con¬
stant contact by sea with Naples. Outstand¬
ing among them are Francisco Ribalta (1551-
1628) and especially José de Ribera, known
as "el Españólelo" (1591-1652), who,
though he went to live in Naples and died
there, influenced painters all over Spain by
the powerful realism and beautiful colours
that were the hallmark of his work. He sent
his striking paintings of saints and martyrs
back to Spain. His example was followed in
the next generation by a pupil of Pacheco,
Diego Velazquez (1599-1660), who became
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
painter to King Philip IV. In paintings such
as "The Maids of Honour" and "The Spin¬
ners", he displayed a technical skill and a
conception of atmosphere and light that
were completely new and difficult to match,
although his successors Mazo, Carreño,
Rizi and Claudio Coello are worthy repre¬
sentatives of the School of Madrid which he
founded. The artist who most nearly
approached him was his friend the sculptor
Alonso Cano, who was also an excellent
painter and architect. Both these baroque
painters shunned exaggerated attitudes and
dynamic movement in favour of serene, clas¬
sical perfection, although there is no lack of
energy in the play of light and the boldness
of the brushwork.
Two Andalusian artists of genius brought
to an end the great period of Spanish baroque
painting: Bartolomé Esteban Murillo (1617-
1682) in Seville, and Juan de Valdés Leal
(1622-1690) in Córdoba. These men were
near-contemporaries but differed totally in
their approach. Murillo had a natural grace
that had a wide appeal. He wanted to make
the sacred relevant to his own day; and he
had exceptional technical powers, although
his works convey an impression of sim¬
plicity. This was the antithesis of the ten¬
sions, gesticulations, and exaggerated move¬
ments of Valdés Leal, which could,
however, lead to outstanding results in such
paintings as The Chariot of Elias, in the
monastery of the Carmelitas Calzados at
Córdoba, a work in which he approaches the
Romanticism of Delacroix.
JULIAN GALLEGO, Spanish historian and art
critic, is a professor at the Complutense University
of Madrid. He is an elected member of the San
Fernando Academy ofFine Arts, Madrid, a corres¬
ponding member of the Hispanic Society ofAmer¬
ica, New York, and a member ofthe International
Association ofArt Critics. His many publications
include Visión y símbolos en la pintura española
del siglo de oro ("Vision and Symbols in Spanish
Painting of the Golden Age"), Diego Velazquez,
and studies on Francisco de Goya and on the
history of art.
The last phase ofSpanish baroque architecture,
known as churrigueresque, is characterized by
the use ofspiralling forms and ornamentation of
a lavishness only surpassed in Latin America.
The huge altarpiece by José de Churriguera in
the Dominican church of San Esteban, Sala¬
manca (above), is typical of this ornamental
style.
Baroque polychrome sculptures of scenes from
Christ's Passion and Crucifixion are found in
many Spanish churches. During Holy Week
processions they are carried through the streets.
Left, a group ofPassion sculpturesfrom Zamora,
a city northwest ofMadrid.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Baroque as a worldphilosophy
BY EDOUARD GLISSANT
THE baroque style made its
appearance in the West at the very
moment that a certain idea of
Nature that it was homogeneous, harmo¬
nious and comprehensible was gaining
ground. Rationalism refined this concept
which fitted in well with its growing ambi¬
tion to dominate reality. It seemed, more¬
over, that Nature could be artificially
reproduced, imitation of reality going hand
in hand with knowledge of it.
Imitation of Nature as an objective
assumes that, underlying outward
appearance and inherent in it, there is a "pro¬
fundity", an unassailable truth, artistic
representations of which approximate more
closely as they systematize their imitation of
reality and discover its rules. The revolution
represented by the introduction of perspec¬
tive during the quattrocento can thus, per¬
haps, be seen as part of the search for this
profundity.
It was against this current that the baroque
"diversion" began to make itself felt.
Baroque art was a reaction against the
rationalist claim to penetrate the mysteries of
the known in one single, incisive, uniform
movement. The stone with which baroque
art disturbed the rationalist pool was an
affirmation that knowledge is never fully
acquired, a fact that gives it all its value. Thus
the techniques of baroque art were to favour
"breadth" to the detriment of "depth".
In its historical context, the baroque
diversion thus presupposes a new heroic
quality of knowledge, resolutely turning its
back on the goal of attempting to epitomize
the substance of the world in a series of
representative (or imitative) harmonies. On
the contrary, baroque art or style was to turn
to contrast, to circumvolution, to prolifera¬
tion, to everything that contradicted the soi-
disant oneness of the known and the
knower, to everything that exalted quantity
repeated to infinity and totality eternally
renewed.
In its historical setting, therefore, baroque
art is a reaction against a natural order, natu¬
rally proffered as evidence. When the con¬
ception of Nature evolved, at the same time
that the world was opening up to Western
man and that science was bringing the splen¬
did ordering of Nature into question, the
thrust of baroque art was itself also to
become generalized, ceasing to be no more
than a reaction. Baroque art, the art of
expansion, was itself materially to expand.
The first manifestation of this expansion
was undoubtedly to be seen in Latin-Amer¬
ican art, so close to Iberian and Flemish
' Baroque, yet so intimately interwoven with
indigenous elements, daringly introduced
into the baroque concert. These elements
were no longer seen to enter as revolutionary
disfigurements of reality, but as inputs of a
novel kind. No longer simply the negation
of a concept, baroque art has given its sanc¬
tion to a new schema (soon to be a new
concept) of Nature, to which it is attuned.
Cross-fertilization is the determinant of
this evolution, and the pursuits of baroque
art are at one with the dizzying adventure of
cross-fertilization of cultures, styles and
tongues. With the generalization of this
cross-fertilization, the Baroque has finally
achieved its "natural" condition. It
announces to the world the growing contact
between a diversity of "natures". It is in
sympathy with this world movement and is
no longer content to be merely a reaction
against a philosophy or an aesthetic. It is the
sum and result of all aesthetic theories, of all
philosophies. In short, Baroque is neither an
art nor a style, but a being-in-the-world.
The modern scientific view of reality coin¬
cides with and confirms this expansion of the
Baroque. Science does, indeed, assert that"
reality cannot be defined in terms of outward
appearances and that it has to be examined
"in depth", but it also accepts that knowl¬
edge is never wholly acquired and that it
would be absurd to claim that its essentials
can be grasped at a single stroke. Science has
entered the era of the uncertainty principle,
retaining, nevertheless, a form of rationalism
which henceforth abjures paralysing,
mechanical, once-and-for-all dogmatism.
Its conceptions of Nature are "expanding",
becoming relative, problematical. It is mov¬
ing, that is, in the selfsame direction towards
which the Baroque tends.
Similarly, human nature is no longer
thought of in terms of a clear-cut, universal
model. The concept of being-in-the-world
implies the sum total of all types of being-
in-society. There is no unique, recognized
model. All human cultures have had their
classical periods, eras of dogmatic certainty
from which they must all emerge together.
In this sense the "profundities" revealed by
science, psychology and sociology counter
triumphantly the metaphysical "profun¬
dity" emphasized by Western classicism
alone. Herein lies the very key to the univer-
salization of the Baroque.
One might, then, sum up by saying that
there has been a "naturalization" of the
Baroque, not simply as an art form or style,
but as a way of living out the diversity-unity
of the world; that this naturalization takes
the Baroque out of the limited context of
Counter-Reformation flamboyance, of
revolt against the constraints of a tradition,
to give it a universal quality as the embodi¬
ment of "interrelating"; and that, in this
sense, the Baroque of history foreshadowed,
in astonishingly prophetic fashion, the
upheavals that mark the world of today.
Finally, a recent characteristic of contem¬
porary art, defined by Walter Benjamin as
"technically reproducible art", seems to
confirm this movement towards universal-
©
ization. The ability to make exact copies,
made possible by modern techniques, has
changed the whole course of future develop¬
ment of the arts. Not only has the con¬
ception of Nature become relative, the
notion of the metaphysical oneness of a mas¬
terpiece has been swept away. In the present
state of diversity, not only does a work of art
combine profundity with expansion, it is
itself subject to a fundamental expansion
which, thanks to increasingly perfected
methods of reproduction, adds infinitely to
its significance.
EDOUARD GLISSANT, of Martinique, is the
author of many volumes of poems, novels and
essays, including La lézarde, L'intention poétique
and Le discours antillais. He has also published a
play, Monsieur Toussaint. In 1967 he founded the
Institut Martiniquais d'Etudes at Fort-de-France.
Since 1981 he has been editor-in-chief of the Un¬
esco Courier. His latest novel, Mahagony, has just
been published.
Although the notion of the Baroque is primarily
associated with a specific period in the cultural
history of the Christian West, the 17th and 18th
centuries, some writers have wondered whether
it could not be applied in afar wider context to
describe a surge ofvitality, movement and emo¬
tional force of the kind which periodically
causes an upheaval in the arts. The Spanish
critic Eugenio d'Ors has suggested that the
Baroque may be an essential component of in¬
telligence and sensibility, a "stylistic constant"
which recurs throughout history. Such a thesis
could help to explain the affinities that can be
observed between Western Baroque and other
forms ofartistic expression that have appeared
at different periods in countries far distantfrom
each other. 1. 13th-century Gate of Victory in
the temple complex of Angkor Thorn, Kam¬
puchea. 2. Church ofthe Sagrada Familia (Holy
Family), Barcelona, by the Catalan architect
Antonio Gaudt, begun in 1883 and never com¬
pleted. 3. Tomb built for himself by Ferdinand
Cheval, French postman and self-taught artist
famed for the "Ideal Palace" he built (after
seeing it in a dream) between 1879 and 1912 at
Hauterives, Drame, France. 4. Colourful car¬
nival scene from Trinidad and Tobago (West
Indies). 5. The Cuban poet and novelist José
Lezama Lima (1910-1976) who, like many
Latin American writers, considered himself a
baroque author, and claimed affinities with the
Spanish baroque poet Góngora.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The baroque impulse
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Sculpture, theatre of the sublime
BY FRANÇOIS SOUCHAL
The genius of Bernini, the supreme artist of
baroque Catholicism and the man who made St.
Peter's basilica the prestigious centre of the
papacy in Rome, was expressed with thegreatest
intensity in his work as a sculptor. Above left,
The Ecstasy of St. Theresa (1644-1652) in the
Cornaro chapel in the church of Santa Maria
della Vittoria, Rome, a dramaticportrayalofthe
mystic rapture of a 16th-century Spanish nun.
Bernini sought above all to express movement in
sculpture, often with a dynamism which infused
religious fervour even into works on mytholo¬
gical themes such as Apollo and Daphne (1622-
1625) in the museum of the Villa Borghese,
Rome (above right).
PROJECTING matter into space,
delimiting its presence there, the
sculptor's art is both defiant and sym¬
bolic. Drawing its vitality from a constant
state of tension with the architecture that
provides both its frame and its support, it has
to assert its identity within its environment,
and derives from this necessity a measure of
its dynamism and its dignity. Essentially,
primordially, an act of artistic creation,
sculpture also bears a message: its image of a
divinity, a sovereign or simply of a man is
never entirely gratuitous.
At the close of the sixteenth century, the
sculptor's unremitting struggle with nature
had led him into an impasse. Michelangelo,
assailed by doubts, left his statues
unfinished. Mannerism turned in on itself,
caught up in convolutions of its own mak¬
ing, a serpent swallowing its own tail. In this
atmosphere of introspection, the only possi¬
ble outcome was escape or asphyxia. West
ern art, as it had so often in the past, rose to
the challenge. Gathering new strength in the
process, it would give consummate expres¬
sion to the civilization that emerged from the
great conflicts of the sixteenth century.
Although this civilization was restless and
precariously balanced, it lasted for two hun¬
dred years.
It would be absurd, spurious even, to
attempt to list in order of importance the
different modes of artistic expression that
characterized this baroque civilization.
However, its great master was unquestiona¬
bly the sculptor Gian Lorenzo Bernini
(1598-1680), an artist who was perhaps
unsurpassed in the skill with which he
instilled living movement and the force of
illusion into his works. The personality of
Bernini is so overwhelming, so fascinating,
that it is tempting to see him as the person¬
ification of the magic spell that Baroque was
to cast over all Europe for generations.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
However, it should not be forgotten that
Bernini himself was plagued by contradic¬
tions; he was an ardent, passionate man, but
one who took Antiquity as his yardstick and
never ceased to be haunted by the great
vision of classical harmony. Nor is it possi¬
ble to overlook the forces of opposition
which were inspired by rivals such as the
Italian Alessandro Algardi and the Fleming
François Duquesnoy, and which, through a
concern for simplification have been identi¬
fied with an "anti-Baroque" and con¬
sequently "classical" movement. But sim¬
plification can often lead to a degree of
misapprehension, if not to outright error. It
is not false to say that one of the riches of
sculpture in this period lies in the dialectical
tension between Baroque and classicism. It
is equally true that Baroque was a complex
art whose very complexities undeniably add
to its riches. And perhaps it is an example of
an art form that contained deep within itself,
embedded in an awareness of its own limita¬
tions, the reasons for its eventual decline and
demise, firstly because it is an art that
depends on immediacy, on capturing move¬
ment at the crucial moment, and secondly
because it is a theatrical, self-contemplating
art, and is thus sometimes charged with
almost unbearable emotion the emotion of
pathos rather than tenderness.
Let us look first at Bernini's famous sculp¬
ture The Ecstasy of St. Theresa, which
provoked such sardonic laughter on the part
of the French scholar Charles de Brosses
(1 709-1 777). In this work in a side-chapel of
the Roman church of Sta. Maria della Vit-
toria, Bernini has arrested the flight of the
golden arrow in the split second before it
pierces the heart of the saint and mystic,
capturing, in the same split second, the
expression of ecstasy that illuminates her
features. Meanwhile, at the crucial moment
in this celebration of Christian spirituality,
the members of the Cornaro family, to
whom the chapel belonged and who are por¬
trayed on each side of the composition in
niches that bear a remarkable resemblance to
boxes in an opera-house, gossip away in sub¬
lime indifference to the beatific vision that is
taking place before their eyes.
In its force of contrast, ambiguity, illu¬
sion, illusionism even, this is undoubtedly a
masterpiece of baroque sculpture, simul¬
taneously expressing intense religious fer¬
vour and the worldliness of a society that
lived as if it were on stage and believed that
theatre was more real than life itself. In this
work of art in which stage effects figure
prominently, light falls mysteriously from a
hidden source, softened by coloured filters,
and lends its own glory to the wonderful
group that occupies space with such
assurance and such power (of fascination
rather than persuasion) that the question of
domination by or subjection to its architec¬
tural framework does not arise.
Nor should it be forgotten that Bernini
was also outstanding at the staging of funeral
scenes and spectacular ceremonies. His
sculpture was designed to entrance the spec¬
tator. Even when he takes a subject from
classical mythology, as in the Apollo and
Daphne at the Villa Borghese in Rome, the
transformation (in this case of the nymph's
nubile body into a laurel tree) is designed to
provoke stupefaction, a shudder of amaze¬
ment. This is why the baroque sculptor
found equal fulfilment in depicting Christian
miracles and Ovidian metamorphoses: both
reflected the same appetite for the mar¬
vellous.
The taste for the supernatural was
expressed with particular gusto in the Ger¬
manic world, the home of Bernini's most
faithful disciples and a place where Nature
and reality had already in the past been sub¬
jected to violent distortions in the name of
art. In the church at Rohr, the painter Cos-
mas Damián Asam and his brother, the
sculptor Egid Quirin Asam, boldly staged (a
theatrical term, again!) one of the Christian
mysteries, The Assumption of the Virgin. In
this work executed in plain and polychrome
stucco, the Mother of Christ is suspended in
midair, in defiance of the laws of gravity.
The gestures and facial expressions of the
Apostles gathered around the open tomb
reveal a variety of reactions to this new chal¬
lenge to reason. They are actors in a tragedy,
playing their roles with passionate convic
tion. And we feel, as we do before the works
of Bernini, how these great baroque sculp¬
tures reflect an authentic sincerity and inten¬
sity of faith, a piety that proceeds not from
introspection but rather from a warm and
outgoing desire to communicate, from an
impulse towards charity, from confidence in
God's infinite goodness and in divine grace
(here is the language of mysticism again!).
Baroque sculpture did not, however, limit
itself to the depiction of superbly performed
great moments of sacred theatre. True, it is a
product of religious fervour, and is the last
sacred art worthy of the name in the Chris¬
tian West. But baroque society was also the
reflection of a system of government of a
monarchical system that was more or less
absolute according to the traditions and pat¬
tern of development of each State. And
baroque sculpture, if it served the Church,
The Ganges, a detail of Bernini's Four Rivers
Fountain (1647-1670) which adorns the centre
of the Piazza Navona in Rome. Bernini, Borro-
mini (the architect of the Piazza Navona) and
Guarini were the great trio of Italian baroque
architects.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
: &m
© Baroque at Versailles
The 17th century in France is often seen as the
age of classicism. The French painters of the
period, including the greatest of them, Nicolas
Poussin, seem to have been largely untouched by
baroque vehemence. Even the Palace of Versail¬
les, the masterpiece of the reign of Louis XTV
designed by Jules Hardouin-Mansart, Louis Le
Vau andAndré Le Nôtre, appears at first to be a
classical work by virtue of its plan, with its
buildings and gardens reflecting a concern for
geometrical balance far removed from baroque
sinuosity. Nevertheless, Charles Le Brun, who
was commissioned to decorate the palace by
Louis XTV in 1674, enriched it with many baro¬
que scenic elements. Above, The Chariot of the
Sun fry Jean-Baptiste Tuby. This gilded bronze
sculpture in the Bassin d'Apollon, in thegardens
of the palace, was executed from a plan by Le
Brun.
also served this monarchical and aristocratic
society, providing a necessary setting for the
ceremonial and liturgy of kings and princes.
On the façades of palaces, on the walls of
reception rooms, lining the paths that led
through parks and gardens, forming the cen¬
trepiece of ponds and fountains, baroque
sculpture proclaimed the virtues of a politi¬
cal system that would only begin to crumble
much later, under critical assault from the
philosophers of the Enlightenment.
Baroque sculpture adapted itself equally
well to each of the two prevailing codes of
expression: Biblical Christian iconography,
and mythology as it had been formed by
writers such as the Italian Cesare Ripa (1560-
1645) into a more or less coherent symbolic
system. With the exception (by no means
absolute, however) of portraiture, allegory
is sovereign and ever-present in baroque
sculpture. Mythological figures are enrolled
as actors to give some kind of demonstra¬
tion. Sometimes, too, allegory is given form
and movement without the support of
mythology.
The French tend to reject the epithet
"baroque" as a description of the great sculp¬
tures that adorn the park of Versailles. But
what could be more profoundly baroque
than this universe of marble and lead, repre¬
sentation of a veritable political cosmogony?
It is true that the performers in this particular
drama are somewhat less exuberant than
their Italian or German counterparts.
Restraint is a feature of French theatre. And
more intellectual concerns are evident in this
remarkable commission dating from 1674,
the product of the imagination of the painter
Charles Le Brun and of the talent of the
sculptor François Girardon and his disciples
and rivals. The completed work depicts an
astonishing tetralogical system: the four sea¬
sons, the four humours, the four times of the
day, the four forms of poetry, and so on.
This is an eminently baroque attempt to
sum up the world of knowledge and knowl¬
edge of the world. The mode is secular, but
the ambition is equal to that of the great
religious compositions. Here once again is
the ambiguity of baroque sculpture herald
of the irrational and the pathetic, yet a
staunch defender of comprehension and
rhetorical unification, despite its excesses
and emotional turbulence and thanks to its
transcendent spirit and its pursuit of the eter¬
nal. Baroque sculpture is the most deter¬
mined attempt to give expression to the pas¬
sion that moves men and lifts them to the
sublime.
FRANÇOIS SOUCHAL, French art historian
and museum curator, has been professor of the
history of art at the university of Lille since 1969.
He is a member of his country's Historic Monu¬
ments Commission and the author ofmany articles
on baroque sculpture and architects. Among his
published works are three volumes in English enti¬
tled French Sculptors of the 1 7th and 1 8th Centur¬
ies (Faber & Faber, 1977-1987).
COLOUR PAGES
Colour page right
Above left: head of a thief, detail of a
polychrome wooden statue (1796-1799) carved
by Antonio Francisco Lisboa, known as O Alei-
jadinho (the Little Cripple), for the Way of the
Cross series in the sanctuary of Bom Jesus de
Matozinhos at Congonhas do Campo, Brazil.
(See article page 39.)
Photo © SCALA, Florence
Above right: Presentation of Christ in the
Temple (1641) by the French artist Simon Vouet
(1590-1649). Vouet was one ofthefirst artists to
introduce an Italianate baroque style ofpainting
into France, along with Charles Le Brun, de¬
corator of the Palace of Versailles.
Photo © D. Genet, Editions Mazenod, Paris. Louvre Museum
Below: the great ceiling fresco in the Palazzo
Farnese, Rome. The fresco, on mythological
themes, was painted between 1597 and 1604 by
Annibale Carracci (1560-1609). This master¬
piece of 17th-century Italian art was a major
influence on the development ofbaroque paint¬
ing and decorative arts. (See article page 30.)
Photo © SCALA, Florence
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
'**
^gj'c k
B^JE
^
.
sc
.1
i i 3
«y> jsi
.XV
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
mil^ji
- V*i-£.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
I
mi ._
t
x!¡,
H é
-
/(
nlW
A-
r
W T
y
i\ "*&
v
;
<H
%
A
v
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
v»'/«-.
2®SÍ
S* ~r 4
/'3S
. * "' v.. V it; -\
V
fir'
M
k
F » .»
1 r
»#
î*ft >#i Li
.A* J î |f
f l'
IÍ«***''
M
K
wm
^s,
"t/;
k-1 \
r
\/ L
L.-'
mw
^
«
^
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Centre pages
Above left: the decorative structure known as El
Transparente ("The transparent"), executed by
Narciso Tomé in the ambulatory of Toledo
cathedral, Spain, between 1721 and 1732. Like
the Obradoiro, the façade of the cathedral of
Santiago de Compostela, it is an example of a
highly ornamental, dynamic baroque addition
to a building of a different style, in this case
Gothic. (See article page 14.)
Photo © Mas, Barcelona
Below left: high altar and upper nave of the
church of St. John Nepomuk (1733-1746),
Munich, Fed. Rep. of Germany, by the brothers
Cosmos Damián Asam (1686-1739) and Egid
QuirinAsam (1692-1750). (See articlepage 42.)
Photo © A. Hornak, London
Centre: Triumph of St. Ignatius (1685), a ceil¬
ing fresco by the Jesuit priest Andrea Pozzo
(1642-1709) in the rhurch of St. Ignatius in
Rome. In this masterpiece of illusionism, Pozzo
creates above the real structure of the church a
grandiose trompe-1' architectural setting
opening on to the heavens, where the founder
of the Jesuit order is welcomed. (See article
page 30.)
Photo © Scala, Florence
Above right: St. Bonaventura Lying in State
(1629) by Francisco de lurbarán (1598-1664).
The works of this Spanish painter, who had
many commissions from monastic orders, are
imposing in their sobriety andprofoundsense of
mysticism. (See article page 14.)
Photo © RMN, Paris. Louvre Museum
Below right: theatrical attitudes and gestures
infuse a powerful sense of movement into this
Assumption (1718-1722), executed by Egid
Quirin Asam for the choir of the monastery
church of Rohr (Fed. Rep. of Germany). The
work of the Asam brothers marked a high point
in Central European baroque sculpture and de¬
coration. (See article page 20.)
Photo © Toni Schneiders, Lindau, Fed. Rep. of Germany
Q
LU
O
©
I
i
I
HOL
' _ 111
The stately heritage
of Portuguese Baroque
BY JOSE-AUGUSTO FRANCA
Colour page left
Above: interior ofthe church ofthe Third Order
of St. Francis, Salvador, Brazil. With its gilded
sculptures and mouldings, this early 18th-cen¬
tury church is typical of Brazilian and Portu¬
guese architecture. (See article page 39.)
Photo Moisnard © Explorer, Paris
Below left: the "Angel with the Arquebus"
(Peru). This typical figure of Andean baroque
art is here shown in an anonymous 18th-
century painting of the Cuzco School. (See arti¬
cle page 36.)
Photo © Rojas Mix, Paris. Manuel Mujica Crallo Collection
Below right: glazed andpainted tile or azulejo
from the stairway of the pilgrimage church of
Nossa Senhora dos Remedios (1750-1760),
Lamego, Portugal. The azulejo is an essential
decorative feature in Portuguese architecture
and is also widely found in Spain and Brazil.
Photo S. Marmounier © CEDRI, Paris
PORTUGUESE Baroque did not
really come into its own until the
young King John V (1706-1750), his
coffers filled with the recently discovered
treasures of Brazil, determined to make a
symbolic affirmation of his power with the
ambitious project of the monastery-palace-
church of Mafra, on the construction of
which, from 1717, all the resources of the
kingdom were to be concentrated.
J.F. Ludwig (known as Ludovice in Por¬
tugal), a Swabian goldsmith and architect
who had spent some time in Italy, drew up a
series of plans for Mafra, each more gran¬
diose than the one before, which were
inspired by St. Peter's, Rome, and by the
Roman architecture of the Italian architect
Carlo Fontana and his school. The monu¬
mental construction, said to be "greater than
the kingdom", is undoubtedly one of the
finest examples of the whole series of
Germano-Italian monastery-palace-church
complexes.
Manor houses and palatial family seats such as
that of the Mateus family at Vila Real, above,
display the elegance ofPortuguese 18th-century
secular architecture.
Just two years after work was started at
"Mafra, John V summoned the Piedmontese
architect Filippo Juvarra to Lisbon and
asked him to draw up plans for a royal palace
and a patriarchal church. Frustrated by the
length of time completion of such a building
operation would take, the king decided
instead to enlarge and embellish the palace
that Philip II of Spain (who was also king of
Portugal) had had built after 1580 on the
banks of the Tagus.
The Hungarian Carlos Mardel proposed a
series of elegant monumental fountains to
adorn the capital. Meanwhile, in 1747,
Mateus Vicente, a Portuguese architect
trained at Mafra, began work on a country
residence for the king's younger brother, at
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
o
©
Queluz, near Lisbon. The façade of this
building, in which hints of Rococo could
already be discerned, was the country's sec¬
ond major example of southern Baroque.
Shortly before his death, John V ordered
the superb chapel of St. John the Baptist,
designed by Luigi Vanvitelli in a style which
foreshadowed the classical revival, to be
brought from Rome and installed in the
Jesuit church of St. Roch. Like the
patriarchal church, this chapel became a ver¬
itable museum of religious jewellery and
plate supplied by Roman workshops.
John V acquired his tastes from and shared
his orders between Rome and Paris, the'
"Eternal City" supplying his needs in the
religious field while Louis XV's capital met
his secular requirements. Two Frenchmen,
the illustrious silversmith Thomas Germain
and the great scholar and collector Pierre
Jean Mariette, were official suppliers to the
Portuguese crown. The latter supplied the
patron-king with a huge collection of
engravings, lost, unfortunately, in the earth¬
quake of 1755, which destroyed John V's
capital and all its riches, five years after his
death.
The city, which rose again rapidly follow¬
ing this catastrophe, thanks to the
"enlightened" policies of the Marquis of
Pombal, reflected the latter's rational, bour¬
geois taste rather than the Baroque of the
preceding generation.
In the north of the country, however,
where the old landed nobility was
entrenched, far from the court, a different
form of Baroque developed which made use
of the exceptional plastic qualities of granite.
The Tuscan Niccoló Nasoni (and later his
disciple Figueiredo de Seixas) was the most
influential architect of Porto, where he set¬
tled in 1725. The church of the Clérigos
(1731-1749), whose graceful tower was to
become the emblem of the city, and the
Freixo and the Sao-Joao-Novo mansions,
are among the buildings that typify the late
baroque style specific to this part of the
country, a style that with its rococo touches
is somewhat reminiscent of that of Central
Europe.
Towards the middle of the century, at
Braga, not far from Porto, the architect A.
Soares erected three important monumental
buildings the church of Falperra, the
Town Hall, and the Raio mansion whose
façade is the most intricately worked of all
Portuguese civic architecture of the period.
Indeed, country houses and manors (solares)
were the field of predilection for sculptural
late Baroque. In the homes of the Lobo-
Machado family (at Guimaräes), the Mal-
heiro (Viana do Castelo) and the Mateus
(Vila Real) the varied range of Portuguese art
of the period 1730 to 1770 finds its most
original expression.
In the Azores, in Madeira, in India,
Macao and especially, in Brazil, Portuguese
baroque architecture took root and left its
mark.
Although Portuguese painting and sculp¬
ture of this period are of only secondary
interest, in spite of the import of paintings
and statues by the finest Roman artists to
decorate Mafra, two decorative creations
gave an original stamp to Portuguese
Baroque azulejos (painted faience tiles)
and talha (gilded carved wood).
The talha of the altars, spreading out
along the walls, provided the ideal décor for
the "all-gold" church, both a practical and a
Right, peristyle of the palace-monastery of
Mafra, epitome of Portuguese Baroque which
flourished in the 18th century during the reign of
KingJohn V, who built Mafra near Lisbon in a
bid to match the Escorial ofPhilip II of Spain
(see photo page 16). Above, the façade of the
church of Santa Casa da Misericordia at Viseu.
Churches of this kind were copied with varying
degrees of accuracy in Brazil, a Portuguese col¬
ony until the early 19th century.
semantic proposition fundamental to Por¬
tuguese Baroque. The talha harmonized
with the plain blue on a white background of
the azulejos which tiled the walls of cloisters,
staircases, rooms, even the vaulted ceilings
of churches, replacing pictures and tapes¬
tries. The religious themes and scenes from
daily life that they depicted were copied
from imported engravings and were framed
with painted, trompe l'oeil imitations of rich
architectural mouldings.
Thus, from the monumental carved stone
of Mafra to the scintilla of gilded carved
wood and the thousand reflections of
painted tiles, Portuguese Baroque, erected
to the glory of John V, was a celebration of
both the sacred and the sensual.
JOSE-AUGUSTO FRANCA, Portuguese histo¬
rian and art critic, is a professor at the New Uni¬
versity of Lisbon and an associate professor at the
University of Paris III. He is president of the
International Association of Art Critics and a
member of the International Committee for the
History of Art. He is the author o/Une ville des
lumières: la Lisbonne de Pombal (1965).
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
.ílp
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The great illusionists BY ARNAULD BREJON DE LAVERGNEE
*G
, OUNTER-REFORMATION
art", "the Jesuit style" ... these
' are but two of the countless des¬
ignations that have been applied to baroque
art. After a period of austerity which coin¬
cided with the end of the Mannerist school,
ideas changed, the Church became less rigid
in its attitude towards artists and there was a
general resurgence in all the arts. Painting,
sculpture and architecture combined to give
birth to a new conception of the handling of
space. Rome witnessed the genesis of a spec¬
tacular style, spread by the Jesuits and
The Crucifixion of St. Peter (1600-1610), oil on
canvas by Caravaggio, below, is today pre¬
served in the church ofSanta Maria del Popólo,
Rome. In his short life (1573-1610) Caravaggio
paved the wayfor baroquepainting through his
emphasis on heightened emotional tension, his
dramatic use oflight and shade, and his realistic
depictions of religious themes.
backed by the Church, which encouraged a
visual approach to the teaching of dogma.
The painted ceilings of Roman churches are
the masterpieces of this illusionist art, a tri¬
umph of the wondrous and of decorative
effervescence.
The seventeenth century ushered in a new
kind of painting. The Italian critic Luigi Sal¬
erno expressed its guiding principle in these
words: "The image is no longer just a matter
of line or colour; the artist wants to convey
something which goes beyond lines, colours
and perspective and which strikes the view¬
er's feelings and imagination." To stimulate
the imagination, the artist attempted to
break down the barrier between the viewer
and the work of art and to give his painting a
"non-finite" aspect.
The Bolognese painter Annibale Carrac-
ci's purpose seems to have been to bring the
figures in his paintings closer to the space
occupied by the viewer by creating the illu¬
sion that his paintings were a continuation of
real space. The revolution introduced by
Caravaggio, it would appear, was the sancti¬
fication of everyday life. A few years later it
was Bernini's turn to complete the process
and with him the frontiers between art and
life were finally eliminated. What, then,
were the stages in this artistic revolution
which accompanied the development of the
baroque style? Everything happened in
Rome, in the space of three generations.
Annibale Carracci and the new style. In
1595, Annibale Carracci (1560-1609) arrived
in Rome at the invitation of Cardinal
Odoardo Farnese. In addition to many easel
paintings, he created one of the great master¬
pieces of seventeenth-century Italian art
when he painted the ceiling vault of the gall¬
ery of the Palazzo Farnese (1597-1609) for
which he took as his theme the Triumph of
Love (Amor omnia vincit). Against a back¬
ground of highly complex trompe l'sil arch¬
itecture (imitation vaulting, imitation of the
wooden frames that usually surround paint¬
ings, imitation bronze and marble statues on
which a golden light plays), Carracci
unfolded mythological scenes that are inven¬
tive, joyful and dynamic, in accordance with
the criteria of "ideal beauty". The decorative
scheme of the ceiling of the Farnese gallery
was so richly inventive that it influenced ceil¬
ing decoration for generations and left its
mark on both classical and baroque artists.
We must turn to the Swiss art historian
Heinrich Wölfflin (1864-1945) for an expla¬
nation of the baroque style, which he dis¬
tinguishes from the classical style on the fol¬
lowing five counts:
the classical style is linear, stressing the
limits of the subject which it defines and
isolates. Baroque style is pictorial and its
subjects have a natural relationship with
their surroundings;
the classical style is a construction of
planes, whereas baroque art is built in depth;
Classicism is a closed system, the Baroque
is open;
the unity of the classical style is a com¬
position of clearly distinct elements, the
unity of the baroque style is an indivisible
unity;
Classicism aims above all for clarity
whereas the Baroque is less concerned with
its personages as individuals than with their
inter-relationships.
In its strict sense, the word Baroque (from
the Portuguese word barroco, used to
describe a pearl that is crudely or irregularly
shaped) applies to an architectural style cre¬
ated in Rome at the beginning of the seven¬
teenth century arid which spread later to
other countries. Gradually the word came to
be applied to other arts (such as sculpture,
painting, music and poetry). Although its
dates vary from country to country, there is
general agreement in situating the baroque
period as a whole between the beginning of
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
f*Vj
"\
\
M y-
F
.1 j
r *
I9H
the seventeenth century and the first half of
the eighteenth century.
Giovanni Lanfranco (1582-1647) was one
of the first adepts of the new style. Fasci¬
nated by the diffused luminosity and the
daring handling of space in the frescoes of
Correggio (1494-1534), Lanfranco devel¬
oped some new experiments in his own
frescoes use of contrasting light and shade
to obtain greater expression, a taste for bold,
dynamic compositions, and spectacular
effects and illusions.
One of the first major commissions he
received from the Roman clergy was for a
fresco of imposing dimensions on the theme
of the Assumption ofthe Virgin, for the dome
of the church of S. Andrea della Valle (1 625).
Splendour and unreality; the Baroque
comes of age. Pietro da Cortona (1596-1669)
was the first truly baroque Italian artist. The
Bernini of painting, Pietro da Cortona was
the artist of the Church triumphant (his
career spanned six pontificates) and of abso
lutism. He was the originator of a style of
painting that was to be followed by Le Brun
but whose aesthetic would be more fully
understood by Luca Giordano and Tiepolo.
The grandiose plans of Pope Urban VIII
(Maffeo Barberini), to make of Rome a
worthy capital, were carried through by sev¬
eral leading artists including Bernini and
Pietro da Cortona. In one of Pietro's major
works, the frescoed ceiling of the Palazzo
Barberini (1633-1639), the trompe l'iil
architectural features and sculptures merge
into the main body of the work to give a
"total painting" effect and this gives a unity
to the complex allegories depicted. In the
central section, Divine Providence,
enthroned on clouds above Chronos and tbe
three Fates, receives a crown of stars from
the hand of Immortality and displays the
Barberini coat of arms.
Following on from the professions of faith
of Carracci and Caravaggio, we see the last
of the three fundamental currents of seven¬
teenth-century Roman painting taking
The great age ofItalian baroque painting came
to an end with the Venetian artist Giovanni
Battista Tiepolo (1696-1770). The elegance,
spirit and lightness of touch of Tiepolo's work
influenced much 18th-century painting, espe¬
cially in Spain where Tiepolo spent much ofhis
life. Above, The Meeting of Antony and
Cleopatra, a fresco from the Palazzo Labia in
Venice.
shape. With its splendours and unreality, its
riot of colours and forms set free in space,
this is a style which speaks to us in a language
close to that of Bernini. Within a setting of
trompe l'eil architecture, a host of symbolic
figures spill out against wide open blue skies
in a ceaseless undulation of flowing drapery
and golden ringlets. Heraldic arms, garlands
of flowers and dancing cherubs enliven the
representation of an ideal world in which
earthly glories receive their highest accolade
in a free and happy rapprochement with the
symbols of Catholicism triumphant and of
classical mythology.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Spectacular painted ceilings in 17th-century
Roman churches andpalaces reveal the fondness
8 ofbaroque artistsforfantastic, illusionist effects.
| Left, The Triumph of the Name ofJesus (1662-
\ 1683), a ceiling fresco painted by Giovanni
5 Battista Gaulli, known as Baciccia, in the
íá church ofII Gesù in Rome. Carved andpainted
© figures blend with imitation and real
S architectural structures to create an extraordin-
f ary trompe-l'oeil effect.
Remarkably, the shapes and forms are not
confined within the frame which appears
behind imitation stucco atlantes over which
the figures enthroned on the clouds freely
spread. The frame is an integral part of the
painting, giving a profound sense of spatial
unity which is underlined by the warmth of
the Venetian palette. The renewal is total and
complete, with forms that seem to engender
each other spontaneously.
Some thirty years later, in his last great
decorative work, the fresco (Vision of St.
Philip Neri during the Building of the
Church, 1664-1665) for the vault of the nave
of the Chiesa Nuova, Pietro da Cortona cre¬
ated a new form of illusionism. The impor¬
tance of this work needs to be underlined
since it influenced most of the decorative
work for church naves in Rome and its sur¬
roundings throughout the eighteenth cen¬
tury. With its daring foreshortening, its
original di sotto in su (upward movement)
and, above all, the way in which the mar¬
vellous and the divine are presented as if they
are part of everyday life, this fresco remains
unmatched. The new ambition of the artists
of the middle years of the century was to
make the fantastic seem credible.
Naples was, perhaps, the second great
artistic centre of the seventeenth century in
Italy. From Caravaggio to Luca Giordano, a
whole range of experiences clashed only to
combine, often with very original results. At
the heart of baroque creativity, Luca Gior¬
dano's prolific, impetuous inventiveness laid
the foundations of eighteenth-century Euro¬
pean painting. A felicitous poetic streak and
tender humanity free of all bombast, set him
apart from the other great Italian decorative
artists. His fresco in the gallery of the library
of the Medici-Riccardi palace, in Florence
(1682-1683), that great, luminous fable, was
born of a fusion of many influences and
experiments (Venetian art, the message of
Pietro da Cortona...). On the themes of the
Apotheosis ofHuman Life and of the Life of
Thought, Luca Giordano carried through a
rigidly established, allegorical, symbolic and
mythological programme with a supreme
liberty of invention to produce a unified
composition that was both balanced and
daring.
Gaulli and Andrea Pozzo: illusion carried
to perfection. In Rome, some extremely
important decorative works were created at
the end of the century. From 1680 to 1685
the Genoese artist Giovanni Battista Gaulli
(1639-1709, also known as Baciccia) trans¬
formed Il Gesù, the Counter-Reformation-
style mother church of the Jesuit order,
built during the previous century by
Giacomo da Vignola, into a baroque church
with a nave fresco on the theme of the Tri¬
umph of the Name ofJesus.
Stimulated by Bernini, Gaulli at II Gesù
propagated Bernini's ideas, amply illustrat¬
ing his revolutionary pictorial concepts.
Baroque artists were always seeking to intro¬
duce an element of illusion and at II Gesù it is
to be found in the plasticity of the painted
figures, mingled with the stucco figures, and
in their movement beyond the architectural
framework on to the coffering of the vault¬
ing and into the real space of the church.
Here for the first time can be seen the com¬
position characteristic of late baroque
frescoes, in which the juxtaposing of the
darker areas is of greater importance than the
distribution of the figures. Since some of the
stucco figures are painted and some painted
figures have been placed where stucco fig¬
ures would have been expected, it is no
longer possible to distinguish painting from
sculpture. Gaulli gave his paintings a strong
relief effect, influenced by Bernini's sculp¬
tures, and this, coupled with his vigorous
distribution of light and shade, makes even
compositions as vast and as well-peopled as
the Gesù frescoes clear and legible. As well
as imparting a certain mystic quality, the
divine light builds and organizes the entire
composition.
It has often been remarked that the great
artisans of baroque art active in Rome came
from northern Italy. Andrea Pozzo (1642-
1709), a native of Trento, confirms the rule.
The vault fresco of the church of St. Ignatius,
begun in 1668 by Pozzo, himself a Jesuit
priest, extols the glory of the founder of the
Jesuit order. Above the real architectural
structures of the church, he painted, with
brilliant trompe l' effect, the walls and
arcades of another great temple which opens
out on to infinite heavens peopled with
groups of angels, of the blessed and of alle¬
gorical figures. With the vault of the church
of II Gesù, painted by Gaulli, this is, per¬
haps, the most solemn and the most forth¬
right celebration of the splendours of the
Church in the entire decorative output of
seventeenth-century baroque art.
Illusionism, the trompe l' effect sought
by Gaulli and Pozzo, gives rise to a merging
of pictorial space and real space. With Gaulli
some of the painted figures are projected into
the real space of the church occupied by the
viewer. Pozzo, on the other hand, doubles
the real space of the church by the creation of
a painted space. At the centre of his fresco
Pozzo added a vanishing point around
which his ceiling was organized. Thanks to
this innovation, the effects of painting
mingle with those of architecture. As for
Gaulli, he had recourse to sculpture. This
development was to triumph during the
eighteenth century. The power of the colour
arid the studied virtuosity beguile the view¬
er's eye with their prestige, but stir no emo¬
tion in the soul. They are beautiful paintings
and their technical prowess is seductive, but
they do not lead the mind on to meditation.
Painting has become a feast for the eyes. The
beauty of reality is revealed, but not the
secret inner anguish of the soul.
ARNAULD BREJON DE LAVERGNEE,
French art critic and historian, is a curator at the
Louvre Museum, Paris. He has organized exhibi¬
tions on baroque artists and has written several
catalogues for the Louvre and other French
museums. He is the author ofhi peinture italienne
du 17e siècle (1979; "Italian Painting of the 17th
Century ") and of many articles on classical and
modern artists.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A new form ofself-expression' BY LEOPOLDO ZEA
THE term baroque refers to forms of
cultural expression orginating in a
distinctive conception of life and
humanity. The Renaissance, basing itself on
a distant Greek past and turning away from
the Christian view of man, had evolved a
new ideal and a new idea of mankind.
Renaissance man rejected the heritage of
medieval man, the creature and servant of
God, and wished to sever all connections
with the immediate past. A new start was to
be made. Man should be the architect of his
own destiny, as the French philosopher
René Descartes would later insist.
The Baroque in Europe was therefore
associated with a certain rationalism. It was
more than simply an aesthetic phenomenon.
Its striking diversity, variety of ideas and
involution of forms reflect an attitude to life
that was consonant with Jesuit rationalism
and the dialectic of Spinozism. As an artistic
phenomenon, it gave rise to a number of
different forms of expression, among which
Spanish Baroque appears to have been the
origin of baroque art in general.
Across the sea lay America, the object and
the instrument of the dreams of imperial
Spain. In the sixteenth-century controversy
about whether or not Indians should be con¬
sidered as human beings, the ideas of the
Spanish historian and theologian Juan Ginés
de Sepúlveda prevailed over those of the
Dominican missionary to the Americas,
Bartolomé de Las Casas. The result was that
the indigenous people of Latin America were
regarded as homunculi something less than
human beings and as such only fit to be the
servants and slaves of those who were con¬
sidered supreme examples of the human
race.
With their status as human beings called
into question, forced to reproduce exactly
the models imposed on them by the domi¬
nant culture, the people of the Ibcro-Amer-
ican colonies gradually became aware of
their identity. "What am I," they asked, "a
man, or a homunculus?"
In the sixteenth century, the creóle culture
of Latin America was a mere copy, and
sometimes a poor one, of metropolitan mod¬
els. Of course, in the following century the
models came from an Iberian peninsula that
was aware of its decline. The Baroque was an
expression of that awareness, and the spirit
of Spain was manifested in it. And this kind
of artistic expression, with its characteristic
diversity, was to enable Latin American peo¬
ple to manifest their disputed identity, albeit
unconsciously. Thus appeared the mar¬
vellous products of Latin American baroque
art, with its proliferation of contorted lines
which expressed the originality of those who
had fashioned them. Outstanding examples
of this art include the little church of
Tonantzintla, in Puebla (Mexico), in which
cherubs and saints are shown with Indian
faces; and the flowers and offerings which
appear in other baroque works of art
throughout Latin America.
But what is the true status of these works?
Since they are not faithful reproductions of
baroque models, should they not be consid¬
ered simply as mediocre copies?
If they are considered to be poor copies, it
is because they do not closely resemble the
original; they differ from the model. Despite
the painstaking efforts of the copyists, the
copy was a distortion of the model. In time,
their failure to execute faithful copies was to
be the undoing of these artists; they were
Left', 17th-century portrait of the Mexican
poetess Juana Inés de la Cruz (1648 or 1651-
1695), one of the great figures of baroque litera¬
ture in the Spanish language. Her works include
religious and secular plays and poetry, notably
an outstanding series of love sonnets.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A remarkable example of Mexican colonial
baroque architecture, the church of the Jesuit
college ofTepotzotlán, above, was built between
1760 and 1762, at a time when decoration was
beginning to proliferate but was still executed
with the lyrical freshness characteristic of local
artists. (See also back coverfor the decoration of
the church ofSanta Maria Tonantzintla.) Statue
of the Virgin, above right, in the Museo del
Virreinato, Tepotzotlán, exemplifies the
gracefulness of Hispano-American sculpture.
The devil's horns beneath the Virgin's feet, a
typically Spanish feature, symbolize victory
over Evil.
excluded from the colonial system, and even
became subversive of it.
In Latin America, the Church was the
only channel through which culture could
reach the people, and, repressive though it
was, it set out to investigate the nature and
true situation of the people in that part of the
world. Like the sixteenth-century Fran¬
ciscans, the Jesuits, from the seventeenth
century onwards, aimed to find out more
about the art forms that were characteristic
of Latin American people and their environ¬
ment.
In the eighteenth century, conscious or
unconscious attempts at reconciliation
begun in the baroque period took the form
of a new, rationalist approach, which tried to
bring together the imported and the indi¬
genous, the internal and the external. An
effort was made to reconcile the dominant
culture with the specific nature of the people
who were subjected to it, and to make the
anachronistic nature of that culture compati¬
ble with the new forms of cultural expression
that had replaced it in Europe.
Such conciliatory and casuistical attitudes
placed the old colonial order in a difficult
situation. Eighteenth century colonialism
claimed to be enlightened. It tried, albeit
despotically, to lead its Latin American sub¬
jects along the path that the new nations
were treading the path of progress for all
peoples and it came up against the Society
of Jesus. Enlightened despotism proved to
be at variance with the Jesuits' eclectic, con¬
ciliatory attitude, which had already made it
possible for the theocratic system to be
accepted in countries such as Paraguay. In
the end, the attempt made in the baroque
period to reconcile the irreconcilable jeopar¬
dized the system which it was supposed. to
reinforce.
After their exile in Italy, a group of Mex¬
ican Jesuits made it their business to study
the situation of Mexico and of Latin America
in general. As a result of their investigations,
the characteristics of the region, instead of
being seen as worthless, came to be regarded
as the basis for a new form of self-expres
sion. They also drew attention to the rights
of certain peoples to be themselves, not
merely skilful copyists of alien cultural
ideas. From such a view to subversion was
but a step. The outcast became a rebel.
The "mediocre copy" was actually a
means of self-expression. When the people
of Latin America realized this, they began to
forge their own identity. It was then that
they had to try to reconcile the seemingly
irreconcilable. To the question, "Who are
we? Spaniards or Indians?", they answered,
with Simón Bolívar, "We are Americans!"
LEOPOLDO ZEA, Mexican philosopher and
essayist, is professor ofthephilosophy ofhistory and
the history of ideas in America at the Autonomous
National University, Mexico City. Much of his
writing is devoted to the analysis and the history of
Latin American culture. Among his works pub¬
lished in English are The Latin American Mind
(1963) and Latin America and the World (1969),
both published by the University of Oklahoma
Press.
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
The Angel with the Arquebus BY MIGUEL ROJAS MIX
ONE of the most typical figures of
Latin American baroque art is that
of a dandified angel with swan's
wings and a broad-brimmed hat with a
feather in it. He is richly clad in a garment
with lace ruffles and a greatcoat with a gold
and silver lining, and he holds a heavy
arquebus.
Although found only in Andean painting,
the "Angel with the Arquebus" is a
supremely representative feature of the
baroque art of Latin America, which is at
once a magnificent and theatrical form of art,
and also a style whose purpose was to induce
the Indian to accept the power of God and
the king and, through religion and force of
arms, to make him part of colonial society.
One of its most common themes was the
system of mestizaje, or ethnic intermixture,
in which people were placed in castes
according to their origin and the colour of
their skin.
Baroque art in Latin America has left an
indelible mark on the individual and on the
course of history. Even today, many writers
consider themselves to be baroque writers.
In fact, baroque art is the art of the New
World. The mixture of Iberian (in which
there was already an Arab element) with
Indian and Black elements produced a dis-
*Wr
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
E
<
©
Left, portal of the church of San Francisco, La
Paz, Bolivia, an outstanding example ofAndean
Baroque. Construction began in 1743. The de¬
coration with anthropomorphic and animal
motifs is typical of Latin American "churri-
gueresque" architecture. Above, façade of the
Jesuit church, known as La Compañía, in
Quito, Ecuador. Completed in 1765, the church
incorporates twisted columns and other Spanish
and Italian features. The interior is decorated
with magnificent gilded wood carvings in local
style.
tinctive style which some have called Indo-
Hispanic, some creóle (criollo), or mestizo.
In accordance with its regional characteris¬
tics, it has also been called "Andean
Baroque" and "Poblano Baroque" (after the
Mexican town of Puebla).
A proselytizing art, Baroque was the
"Bible of the poor", the gospel conveyed to
the Indian's mind by images. While the Prot¬
estants preached simplicity and modesty,
used no images and made no attempt at evan¬
gelization, the Council of Trent (1545-1563)
took a stand against pagan images, extolled
the Eucharist, the Virgin and the Pope,
advocated evangelization and the cult of the
saints, and laid down rules to the effect that
the saints should be portrayed in a setting
suggestive of martyrdom and ecstasy. As late
as 1782, instructions were still being issued
for artists which repeated the Council's
resolutions concerning iconography and set
forth detailed rules on the degree of nudity
that was permissible for each saint, the age at
which he should be depicted and the attitude
in which he should be shown.
The baroque style was a perfect way of
conveying to the Indians the idea that they
should accept their new destiny. Classical art
is an art of moderation and balance, an art
that is concerned with general principles,
and seeks what is universal. Its characters are
rhetorical figures. Baroque art is the
opposite; it expresses what order and mod¬
eration cannot express emotion, grief,
ecstasy and faith. Its representation of
mystical feelings is close to everyday life,
and its examples are taken from actuality. Its
Christs are sacred actors in a human tragedy.
Carved in wood painted the colour of flesh,
with real hair, eyelashes and eyelids, with
glass eyes and real clothing, they are more
like characters in a waxworks exhibition
than sacred images. In the "Christ of Sor¬
rows", the subject most frequently treated in
Latin America, sorrow is dramatized in a
paroxysm of grief. The figure is covered with
blood (made of scarlet cochineal and pitch)
so that the viewer almost feels the pain of the
wounds, and the face and body are distorted
by deep suffering. The convincing realism of
this pain, which is in no sense symbolic, was
intended to show the Indians that their trials
were as nothing compared to the suffer¬
ings of Christ.
In its early period, Latin American
baroque art was thoroughly European in
character. Most of the sixteenth- and seven¬
teenth-century paintings are by European
artists who worked for the New World, or
copies of engravings brought from Europe.
Yet even then there was a certain intermix¬
ture of styles. The plans of the cathedrals
were of Roman or Spanish origin, but they
were considerably modified in the course of
execution. And of course the "plateresque"
or Spanish Renaissance style was a product
of the intermixture of the mudejar style and
late Gothic.
The second period of Latin American
Baroque began when local artists emerged.
Although ideas and works of art continued
to be imported, certain changes and the
emphasis placed on certain themes reveal a
growing independence. Because of the pre¬
vailing taste for pictures that told a story, a
touching story, with an element of fantasy,
art of this period is often called "primitive"
art. The wood carvings known in the
Náhuatl language as tequitqui reveal the sen¬
sibility of the Indian. The combination of
realism and abstraction in these carvings
shows the persistence of pre-Columbian
ideas.
Iconography was also modified by the
Black sensibility. Baroque art (and especially
rococo art) used the Black as a decorative
feature. In Europe he was a figure holding a
lamp, or, in tapestries, a counterpoint to the
white horse whose reins he held. In Latin
America Blacks were at first depicted as
sumptuously liveried servants or as figures
wearing motley. In both cases they added a
picturesque note. As sensibility is a form of
narcissism, an African element was bound to
appear in Latin America to lend dignity to
the popular image. Its failure to do so would
have been an act of self-abnegation by the
artists themselves, who were mestizos,
mulattoes or Blacks. Thus African gods slip¬
ped surreptitiously into the cult of the saints,
and in many cases a darker complexion, ren¬
dered by the mixture of wax and paint used
to depict the flesh of the Virgin or the angels,
was enough to make them recognizable as
Blacks from Brazil, Colombia or other
regions with a large African population.
The Latin American element in baroque
art did not, however, simply consist of mod¬
ification or stylistic exaggeration. The ultra-
baroque or churrigueresque style nowhere
reached such a pitch of ostentation as it did in
Latin America, especially Mexico, but many
of the motifs that artists in the New World
began to use were quite different in spirit:
decorative forms such as masks with Aymara
or Quechua faces, known as indátides, or the
delicately gilded frames with carvings of
macaws, capybaras, monkeys and other
creatures, in settings of papayas, pineapples
and banana trees. Such motifs were depicted
with a "flat" technique, as if the artists
refused to accept the illusion of volume and
space known to Western art.
Other highlights of Latin American
Baroque are the screens that are distinctive
features of churches in the New World, but
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The work ofAndean sculptors in Peru, Ecuador
and Bolivia ranges from imitations of Spanish
religious sculpture to depictions of local themes.
Above, detail ofa crucifix by Gaspar de Sangur-
ima in the monastery of the Immaculate Con¬
ception, Cuenca, Ecuador. Christ is portrayed
in the realistic style typical ofSpanish sculptors,
with a stream of blood flowing from His side.
Right, Peruvian statue of the baby Jesus dressed
as an Indian, viith cap and poncho.
whose filigreed carving recalls mudejar taste;
other creóle saints as well as the Angel with
the Arquebus; Matamoros images, in which
Indians are portrayed instead of Moors, and
which should really be called Mataindios in
Latin America; depictions of the Magi in
which colonial artists include not only a
Black king, but sometimes a mestizo and an
Indian, so that the subject becomes a meta¬
phor of race; the guitar-playing sirens beside
the doors of San Lorenzo de Potosí, in
Bolivia, and in the choir of San Miguel de
Pomata, in Peru; the creóle Virgins the
morenas (Black women) or mamacitas (little
mothers) as the Indians call them. In the
church of San Juan on the shores of Lake
Titicaca, the child Jesus is shown wearing a
poncho and a cap like those the Aymara
children in the district wear, and to avoid
any possible confusion is labelled with the
inscription "I am Jesus". Innumerable
painted panels show Incas in gala dress,
while others show impoverished Indians.
And of course there are many specifically
colonial characters and themes, such as Santa
Rosa de Lima (1 586-161 7), a saint much por¬
trayed by eighteenth-century painters, and
the "Christ of the Earthquakes", who is ven¬
erated in the cathedral of Cuzco and in many
other Andean churches, a Christian way of
exorcizing the fears of a people that has
always felt threatened by the gods of
Nature.
Baroque art in Latin America is not a mere
transposition of Spanish or Portuguese art.
It is a hybrid art. And it embraces more than
two cultures, for along with the Spanish tra¬
dition it received the Arab heritage in the
form of the mudejar style. It is said that the
Indian contribution is shown in a preference
for a range of pure colours and in the use of
abstraction in the portrayal of figures. But
the Black influence can also be seen, both in
the dark complexion of angels and Virgins
and in the syncretism of African gods with
the traditional Christian saints. A mar¬
vellously enriched style emerged from all
these influences, the style of an art that was
fundamental to a new world. Such is the art
we know as "Latin American Baroque".
MIGUEL ROJAS MIX, of Chile, is the founder
and former director of the Chilean Institute of
Latin American Art. A former professor at the
Sorbonne, he is currently teaching at the Universi¬
ty of Vincennes, Paris. He is the author ofseveral
published works, including Vera historia natural
de Indias ("The True Natural History of the In¬
dies") and a short history of Latin America for
children.
38
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
The triumph of O Aleijadinho
BY AUGUSTO C. DA SILVA TELLES
ARCHITECTURE and the other arts
practised in Brazil in the sixteenth
and seventeenth centuries or
imported there from Europe were merely
the transposition of what was then being
done in Portugal.
Early buildings such as the parish church
of Olinda, in the State of Pernambuco,
which later became a cathedral, the Jesuit
Church of Grace in the same city, and the
many religious houses, chapels, churches,
colleges, monasteries and convents built by
the Jesuits, Franciscans, Benedictines and
Carmelites along the coast, all shared a styl¬
istic sobriety and simplicity in the decora¬
tion of façades and other architectural ele¬
ments.
These features were still found in seven¬
teenth-century architecture and in the build¬
ings erected as part of the reconstruction
campaign that took place at the end of the
Above, façade of the Carmelite church in the
Pelourinho district ofSalvador (State ofBahia),
a major centre of Brazilian colonial art (now
included on Unesco's World Heritage List).
Left, fresco painted on the wooden ceiling ofthe
church ofNossa Senhora do Rosario, Persepolis,
State of Goias.
Dutch occupation of the Northeast (1630-
1653), although in the second half of the
century volutes, pinnacles and other decora¬
tive features, in some cases large, bold and
elegant, began to appear on porches, pedi¬
ments and bell-towers. These were the first
signs of the coming of the Baroque. Exam¬
ples can be seen in the Franciscan monas¬
teries at Olinda and Igarassú (State of Per¬
nambuco), and in the church of the Jesuit
College, now the cathedral, at Salvador
(State of Bahia).
But the most notable form of baroque
expression in Brazil was the art of talha,
decorative gilded and polychromed wood
carving, which was practised on altarpieces
in chapels and churches, and spread to the
walls and ceilings of high altars and to trans¬
epts, and in many cases to the nave and side-
chapels as well. Gilded and polychromed
decorative carving thus covered most of the
interior of the churches; surfaces were
ornate, full of movement, and colourful.
The first distinctively baroque carvings in
Brazil date from the end of the seventeenth
century. The columns of concentric arches
were executed in spiral or "Solomonic" form
and covered with vine-leaves, pelicans or fig¬
ures of angels, while walls and roofs were
intersected by carvings that framed painted
or low-relief panels. Notable examples are
39
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Ouro Preto, an old city in the Brazilian State of
Minas Gerais (now included on Unesco's World
Heritage List), is a showcase of Brazilian ba¬
roque art. Outstanding among the city's many
baroque monuments is the church ofSt. Francis
ofAssisi, the work of the great mulatto sculptor,
architect and designer Antonio Francisco Lis¬
boa, known as O Aleijadinho (1730-1814), who
was born in Ouro Preto. Right, view ofthe nave.
Far right, the stairway, terrace andfaçade ofthe
sanctuary ofBom Jesus de Matozinhos, at Con-
gonhas do Campo, Minas Gerais, Aleijadinho's
masterpiece. For the sanctuary, built between
1796 and 1799, he created a series of
polychromed wood carvings representing the
Last Supper and the Stations of the Cross (see
also the head of the thief reproduced on colour
page 23) and the soapstone statues of the twelve
Old Testament prophets which line the stair¬
way.
the carvings in the monastery of Sao Bento
(Rio de Janeiro), in the main side-chapel of
the Cathedral (Salvador), and in the Gilded
Chapel of the Third Order of St. Francis at
Recife (Pernambuco).
Later, however, in the 1730s, altarpieces
and other decorative carving in churches
underwent a definite change. The aim was to
create a sense of movement by breaking up
lines and surfaces. Canopies, massive carved
figures and voluted pilasters appeared, of the
kind which can be seen in the church of Sao
Francisco da Penitencia in Rio de Janeiro.
From then on, as in Portugal, the new
forms evolved by the Borrominian school
(which took its name from the Italian archi¬
tect Borromini) began to influence plan and
volume. Walls were given a sense of move¬
ment through the use of elongated polygonal
plans, oval plans, or plans formed of over¬
lapping ovals, while a strong vertical thrust
was the dominant feature of the façades.
Among the churches built in this style are
the Gloria do Outeiro (Rio de Janeiro),
which stands on a hill beside the bay and
whose plan is based on two elongated and
juxtaposed octagons, the church of Säo
Pedro dos Clérigos in Recife, the high façade
of which is an exceptionally powerful exam¬
ple of baroque movement, and the church of
Conceicäo da Praia, in Salvador.
Another church in the same style is the
parish church of Our Lady of Pilar, in Ouro
Preto (State of Minas Gerais), which is
unique in that its polygonal nave is an auton¬
omous structure of carved and gilded wood
inserted into a building whose plan is rec¬
tangular.
The church of the Third Order of St.
Francis, in Salvador, which dates from the
first half of the eighteenth century, is an
outstanding example of baroque art. With
its façade entirely covered with sandstone
carvings, in the manner of Spanish
American churches, it is unique in Brazilian
architecture.
In the second half of the eighteenth cen-
40
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
&j/,.
tury both architecture and decorative wood
carving began to be influenced by the rococo
style. In Bahia and Rio de Janeiro States,
Rococo appears notably in highly ornamen¬
tal gilded carvings, such as the sculptures in
the nave of the church of the Third Order
Carmelites in Cachoeira and the sacristy of
the Carmelite convent in Salvador and, in
Rio de Janeiro, the sculptures in the chapels
of the Santissimo Sacramento, and the
shrines in the Benedictine monastery and in
the chapel adjoining the church of the Third
Order Carmelites. This chapel was built by
Mestre Valentim (Valentim da Fonseca e
Silva), the outstanding architect, wood-car¬
ver and sculptor in Rio de Janeiro of that
time.
In the Northeast, around Recife and
Olinda, baroque and rococo influence
brought animation to the structure of
façades. The church of the monastery of Säo
Bento, in Olinda, and the Carmelite basilica
in Recife are notable examples of the archi¬
tecture of this period in northeastern Brazil.
But it was in the State of Minas Gerais that
the baroque and rococo movement in Brazil
had the most comprehensive impact on arch¬
itecture, especially in the work of the great
architect and sculptor Antonio Francisco
Lisboa (1730-1814), known as O Alei-
jadinho (the Little Cripple) in church
façades, plans, volumes, carvings, and the
use of space. Because of the geographical
situation of Minas Gerais and because there
were no convents or monasteries of the regu¬
lar orders in the region, architects building
parish churches and churches for fraternities
and tertiary orders were not directly exposed
to Portuguese influence and could thus
produce forms of architecture, sculpture
and decoration which were to some extent
original.
Of special interest in this period are the
Franciscan churches in Ouro Preto and Säo
Joäo del Rei and the Carmelite church in
Ouro Preto. These buildings share certain
common features. Their plans consist of
curves and straight lines which are not
arranged in series but create lines and points
of tension, while porches carved in steatite
(soapstone) bring dynamism to their façades
and constitute the focal point of the com¬
position.
In the Franciscan church at Ouro Preto,
the transept, with carved soapstone pulpits,
opens on to the high altar whose retable of
polychrome and gilded wood echoes the
dynamics of the façade and joins with the
vault and sides to form a unhy.
The supreme example of Brazilian
Baroque is Aleijadinho's masterpiece, the
sanctuary of Bom Jesus de Matozinhos, in
Congonhas do Campo, also in Minas
Gerais. This magnificent example of the arts
of architecture, sculpture and landscape,
now included on Unesco's World Heritage
List, stands on a hill-top overlooking broad
valleys. Life-size soapstone statues of the
twelve Old Testament prophets stand on
parapets lining the stairway leading to the
church, creating an extraordinary impres¬
sion of rhythm and movement. On the slope
in front of the church, preserved in chapels
of more recent construction, are the poly¬
chromed wood carvings, also by Alei-
jadinho, which are known as "The Way of
the Cross", and include seven impressive
figures of Christ.
AUGUSTO C. DA SILVA TELLES, Brazilian
architect and historian, is a professor in the Faculty
ofArchitecture and Town Planning at the Federal
University, Rio de Janeiro, and technical consul¬
tant to Brazil's Ministry of the National Historical
and Artistic Heritage. He is vice-president of the
International Council of Monuments and Sites
(ICOMOS) and consultant to the International
Centre for the Study of the Preservation and Res¬
toration of Cultural Property; Rome (ICCROM).
Among his published works are an atlas ofhistoric
and artistic monuments in Brazil, and many arti¬
cles which have appeared in Brazilian and Portu¬
guese periodicals.
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
-
cu
O
ptí
D
tí
<
oí
H
z
tí
V
The art ofpersuasion
BY CHRISTIAN NORBERG-SCHULZ
DURING the eighteenth century,
the landscape of Catholic Central
Europe became saturated with
religious monuments: roadside crucifixes,
statues of the "bridge saint" John Nepomuk,
calvaries (mostly in combination with a via
crucis), pilgrimage churches, and a multitude
of new monasteries. The architecture of the
epoch was thus closely related to the
environment, which it sought to transform
into a "sacred landscape" which everywhere
should remind man of the "true faith".
In accordance with this aim, the works of
art and architecture in question have an exu¬
berant and persuasive character. The man¬
ifest religious ecstasy of the figures is echoed
in the flame-like towers of the churches, in
the interior of which heaven becomes visible
in the illusionary paintings of the vaults.
Even the palaces of the aristocracy have a
similar expression. Being rulers "by God's
grace", princes also had to present the basic
axioms of faith.
In general, we may say that baroque art
and architecture is a product of the Counter-
Reformation, the basis of which was the
esprit de système of the seventeenth century,
that is, the belief that the world may be
understood as a system deducible from a few
immutable a priori dogmas. According to
counter-reformatory policy, these dogmas
ought to be presented as vividly as possibly.
At the Council of Trent it was decided that
"The Bishops shall carefully teach this: that,
by means of the Stories of the Mysteries of
our Redemption, portrayed by paintings or
other representations, the people are
instructed and confirmed in the habit of
remembering, and continually revolving in
mind the articles of faith".
Persuasion thus became the basic means of
achieving the participation needed by the
system. The most famous example of this
approach can be found in the "Spiritual
Exercises" of St. Ignatius Loyola, which
aimed at an imitation of Christ by means of
imagination and empathy. And the Jesuits in
fact made an essential contribution to the
diffusion of baroque art.
Imagination as a means implies that the
world is transformed into a "theatre" and
that the church is intended as a teatrum sac¬
rum where the articles of faith are enacted.
Hence the expressive and illusionary charac¬
ter of baroque art. Following the principles
laid down at the Council of Trent, baroque
art and architecture were born in Rome, the
centre of the Catholic Church. In architect¬
ure we may distinguish between two cur¬
rents: the truly theatrical one, developed by
Bernini, where architecture serves as a splen¬
did but conventionally ordered background
to the "stories" told by illusionary painting
and sculpture, and the "architectural" one,
invented by Borromini, where space itself is
set into motion and becomes a means of
emotional expression. Borromini's more
original treatment of architecture as such
was further developed by Guarini, who in
numerous projects for Theatine churches
defined space as a system of interdependent
cells which seem to be subject to a movement
of pulsation. In fact, Guarini considered the
pulsating, undulating movement a basic
property of nature.
As a manifestation of the Counter-Refor¬
mation, Central European Baroque has a
double face. Firstly, it aims at persuading the
people, and from the very beginning it there¬
fore assimilated local traditions and beliefs to
become part of the world of daily life. It also
had to express the power of those who were
the guardians of faith, that is, the bishop and
the prince, who in Central Europe were
.42
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Left, interior and vault of the Niklaskirche (the
church of St. Nicholas) in the Little Quarter,
Prague, Czechoslovakia. Begun in 1703 by the
architect Christoph Dientzenhofer and com¬
pleted by his son Kilian Ignaz, it has been de¬
scribed as "one ofEurope's most beautiful chur¬
ches".
Below, façade of the Karlskirche (St. Charles'
church) in Vienna (Austria) built between 1715
and 1737 by the architectJohann Bernhard Fis¬
cher von Erlach. Austriaplayed a leading role in
theflowering and diffusion ofCentralEuropean
Baroque.
often one and the same person. Therefore,
the Central European Baroque is popular as
well as grandiose, and aims at communicat¬
ing with "everybody".
The architecture of the Counter-Refor¬
mation was introduced into Central Europe
by the Jesuits before the end of the sixteenth
century. It was only after the Thirty Years
War (1618-1648), however, that building
activity gained full momentum, and the main
works of Central European Baroque stem
from the eighteenth century. Travelling Ital¬
ian architects and craftsmen played an
important role at the outset, and the names
of Lurago, Caratti, Carlone, Martinelli,
Zucalli, Alliprandi, Broggio and Santini
have found their place in architectural his¬
tory. Soon, however, local architects took
over, such as the Vorarlberg masters, who
aimed at a synthesis of local and Italian traits.
This aim was supported by the counter-
reformatory movement, which wanted a
locally rooted, generally understandable art.
Thus, quite early, we find the introduction
of medieval motifs and structures in the
basically classical language of the Baroque,
such as the wall-pillar, which is a late-
Gothic kind of buttress placed inside the
church.
Austria played a primary role in the
development of Central European Baroque,
due to the leading political position of the
country after the defeat of the Turks near
Vienna in 1683. Both of the main Italian
currents were present; the Berninesque one
found its spokesman in Johann Bernhard
Fischer von Erlach (1656-1723), who is
known as the creator of the grandiose
Karlskirche in Vienna (1715-1737), where a
synthesis of the eras of Solomon, Augustus,
Christ and the Austrian emperor is
expressed by means of historical quotations.
This is a truly "theatrical" architecture, with
a rich symbolic content. The Borrominian
current was introduced by Fischer's rival,
Johann Lucas von Hildebrandt (1668-1 745),
who in several churches made use of
Guarini's method of grouping spaces. His
main work, however, is the charming and
picturesque Belvedere palace in Vienna
(1714-1722), built for Prince Eugene of
Savoy, the defeater of the Turks.
A more popular baroque architecture,
mainly centering its attention on religious
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
Photo © C. Norberg-Schulz, Oslo
buildings, was developed in Bohemia by
Christoph and Kilian Ignaz Dientzenhofer.
Christoph (1655-1722) migrated to Prague
from Bavaria in 1686, and in his new country
achieved a highly ingenious synthesis of
Guarini's spatial organisms and the Central
European wall-pillar system. Owing to the
skeletal character of the latter, Christoph's
churches may be characterized as "open"
compositions which in a particularly fas¬
cinating way express the dynamism and
infinite quality of baroque art. Christoph's
son Kilian Ignaz (1689-1751) further
developed the ideas of his father, and in
numerous works realized an ars com¬
binatoria of interdependent spatial cells,
thus bringing the intentions of Borromini
and Guarini to their logical conclusion. One
example of the art of the Dientzenhofers is
the great church of St. Nicholas in the Little
Quarter in Prague, initiated by Christoph in
1703 and completed by Kilian (1737-
1753).
A third member of the Dientzenhofer
family, Christoph's brother Johann (1673-
1726), brought the principles of the Bohe¬
mian Baroque to Franconia, where we find
one of the most accomplished works of the
period, the monastic church of Banz (1710-
1719). Johann Dientzenhofer also inspired a
follower, who is generally considered the
most important architect of the Central
European Baroque: Johann Balthasar Neu¬
mann (1687-1753). The work of Neumann,
who was equally active in ecclesiastical, sec¬
ular and military architecture, is excep
tionally rich and varied. His great churches
of Vierzehnheiligen ( 1 742ff. ) and Neresheim
(1747ff.) combine the "open" spatial groups
of the Guarini-Dientzenhofer tradition with
a central, dominant rotunda, indicating that
around 1750 baroque dynamism started to
give way to a more static, classical con¬
ception of space.
The same holds true of the works of two
other important late baroque masters,
Johann Michael Fischer (1691-1766) and
Dominikus Zimmermann (1685-1766). In
Zimmermann's pilgrimage church at Wies
(1744-1754), the Central European Baroque
is consummated in a Gesamtkunstwerk
("total art work") of rare beauty, which
achieves an exuberant expression of rejoicing
and fulfilment.
After the powerful manifestation of faith
of the Central European Baroque,
Enlightenment took over, and a new epoch
in European history began, aiming at analy¬
tic understanding rather than synthetic
truth.
Today, however, a keen interest in the
Baroque is again being felt. Its "open" and
dynamic forms have a basic affinity to mod¬
ern art, and its emphasis on expression and
"happening" rather than ideal order, is cer¬
tainly related to some aspects of contempo¬
rary life. Although its aims and social back¬
ground were different, we may therefore
learn much from the Baroque, and the works
of the Borromini school in particular have
had a liberating effect on many present-day
architects.
Above, the interior of Dominikus Zimmer¬
mann's pilgrimage church (1744-1754) at Wies
in Bavaria (Fed. Rep. of Germany), a triumph
of Central European Baroque. High altar in the
form ofthe "tree oflife", right, wasproduced by
Bartholomäus Steinle for the church of Stams
monastery (Austria).
CHRISTIAN NORBERG-SCHULZ, Norwe¬
gian architect and art critic, is dean of the Oslo
School ofArchitecture, Norway. He has lectured at
major universities in Europe, the UnitedStates and
Japan, and is a member ofacademic associations in
several countries. Among his works published in
English are Late Baroque and Rococo
Architecture (Faber & Faber, London, 1980),
Meaning in Western Architecture (Rizzoli Inter¬
national Publications, New York, 1980), and
Architecture: Meaning and Place (New York,
1987).
E
O
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
V
ír^
,k '
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Baroque in the Slav countries
BY GEORGII D. GATCHEV
RUSSIA was no exception to the rule
whereby the baroque style was
transmitted from country to country
by itinerant artists and craftsmen. Among
the baroque artists who worked in Russia
was the French sculptor Etienne Maurice
Falconet, who executed the equestrian statue
of Peter the Great in Leningrad, while the
Italian architect Bartolomeo Francesco
Rastrelli was the country's most brilliant
exponent of baroque architecture. Il Gesù,
the famous Jesuit church in Rome, was a
source of inspiration for many churches in
the Ukraine as well as in Latin America.
With its formal complexity and technical
refinements, far removed from the spon¬
taneity of Rousseauism or the Romantic
taste for simplicity and naturalism, baroque
art lent itself to this form of transmission. In
the seventeenth century, mathematical dis¬
coveries crossed frontiers in the same way,
just as they do today, in a kind of scientific
and technological internationalism.
The characteristics of Slav Baroque are
linked to the historical and cultural tradi¬
tions of the different regions in which the
Slavs had settled. The Baroque left a very
strong imprint among the Catholic Slav peo¬
ples of Poland and Dalmatia, just as it did in
Protestant, Germanic Bohemia. Its influ¬
ence was less marked among people of the
Orthodox faith in the Ukraine, Byelorussia
and Russia, and was felt least of all by the
Serbian and Bulgarian peoples under Otto¬
man domination.
In creative terms, the Slav contribution to
European Baroque is more evident in litera¬
ture than in the fine arts. In the sixteenth
century the Polish poet Mikolaj Szarzynski
(1550-1581) expressed the anguish of man's
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution
Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues : 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
VtlH3KMTrU Cf^X iflj-CTJ rMtri. Aoif-.T». i.
~Em Mdtí-rifil, r'lAAHí^
isolation in the world and the tragic need for
spiritual choice imposed by the conflict
between Reformation and Counter-
Reformation.
Osman, an epic work by the Croatian poet
Ivan Gundulic (c. 1589-1638), presents a
completely different vision of reality, evok¬
ing the cultural and religious confrontation
between East and West through a wealth of
images from the external world.
One aspect of baroque culture, common
to the vast majority of the Polish nobility
and known as "Sarmatianism", had echoes in
Hungary, Romania, and in the Ukraine.
Polish contacts through wars and trade with
Turks, Crimean Tartars and Persians led to
this rather unusual synthesis of eastern and
western elements, which was expressed in
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by : (1)
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris ; (2)
University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691 , U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief:
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian:
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research : Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations : Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion : Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions : Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Left, baroque inspiration can be seen in this
calligram by the Russian poet Simon Polotzki
(1629-1680). Entitled "The Eagle ofRussia", the
heart-shapedpoem is dedicated to the TsarAle¬
xis on thé occasion of his 30th birthday.
Photo taken from Le baroque dans les civilisations slaves,
Moscow 1982 © Nauka Publishers
interior decoration, costume, manners and
the art of oratory. Court theatre was also
influenced by the Baroque, notably the plays
of Ursula Radziwill, who had married into
the Polish royal family, which was of
Lithuanian origin. In her "Tale of Prince
Adolf", for example, borrowings from clas¬
sical mythology and mannered French liter¬
ature are transformed into a magnificent
"primitive" art form.
Notable aspects of Byelorussian and
Ukrainian painting are the unique seven¬
teenth- and eighteenth-century funerary
portraits on metal, a.nd parsuni (a corruption
of "person") art, inspired by icon painting.
While the painters used some processes
favoured by baroque artists (contrast of light
and dark, effects of perspective), they
refused to idealize their subjects: beauty
spots, scars or deformities were meticu¬
lously painted, in an attempt to immortalize
the flesh, which though doomed to decom¬
position concealed a soul bound for eternity.
GEORGII DMITRIEVITCH GATCHEV,
Soviet historian and art critic, is a researcher with
the Institute ofSlavonic and Balkan Studies ofthe
USSR Academy ofSciences. His many publications
include "Creation, Life, Art" (1980) and "The
Image in Russian Artistic Culture" (1981).
Non-Headquarters editions
German : Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian : Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil : M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian : H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu : Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan : Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
46 IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed In France) - Dépôt legal : C1 - Septembre 1 987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
INTERNATIONAL
SOCIAL SCIENCE JOURNAL
N°112
REGIONAL SCIENCE
Theory and policies
Regional science : retrospect and prospect.
An interview with Walter Isard
The region as a geographical,
economic and cultural concept
Paul Claval
Regional policies : experiences and prospects
Antoni Kuklinski
Regional and world economic development and the world
economic crisis
Walter B.Stöhr
Sunbelt versus frostbelt : a case for convergence theory?
Bernd Hamm and Martin Lltsch
High technology industry and regional development : a
theoretical critique and reconstruction
Allen d. Scott and Michael Storper
French regional policy In the early 1 980s
G.B. Benko
György Enyedi
Open forum
A comparison between the Chinese and Western models of
philosophy
Liudingshan
The Social Science Sphere
Social Science In Ireland
dohn A. dackson
In recent years there has been an upsurge of Interest In ethnic
studies, as a response to a real increase In the significance ol
contemporary etnnic phenomena. The articles ¡n this Issue
analyse these phenomena, which concern practically all socie¬
ties, from various perspectives.
nature and
resources
Provides international news and information about
Unesco programmes concerning environmental activities,
natural resources research and conservation. Issues
soon to be published include such topics as : water
resources and energy ; environmental geology ; land
development in the tropics.
Annual subscription 60 FF
Single issue 18 FF
Vol. XXII, N° 4,
Oclobcr-Dcccmbcr 1986
ConflicLs of resource use on the Lake Kariba environs
by C. II. D. Magadza
Taming the floods : environmental aspccLs of floodplain
development in Africa
by C. A. Drijver and M. Marchand
BULLETIN OF THE MAN AND THE BIOSPHERE
PROGRAMME
"Die tropical humid forests of the Indomalayan Realm Seminar on
soil fauna in áfrica
The conflict of conservation and survival
Agroforestry in humid forestry zones in Africa
European seminar on nature protection
Human impact on tropical upland forests
Tropical forest management
Rainforest regeneration in Mexico
Analysis of lowland dipterocarp forest
BULLETIN OP THE INTERNATIONAL
HYDROLOGICAL PROGRAMME
The International Hydrological Programme and IAHS
by John C. Rodda
IAHS celebrates 150th issue of its publications
The XXIst International Course in Subterranean Hydrology
Groundwater conference in Malaysia
BULLETIN OF THE INTERNATIONAL GEOLOGICAL
CORRELATION PROGRAMME
Unesco training course for micropaleontologists
Mineral exploration (Paris, France )
Mining exploration and exploration geophysics (Delft,
Netherlands)
Geochcmical prospecting methods (Prague, Czechoslovakia)
Fundamental and applied Quaternary geology (Brussels, Belgium)
Summer course on earth sciences : crystallography, mineralogy
and mctallogeny (Madrid, Spain)
Course on gcolhcrmal energy (Kyushu, Japan)
impact
I of science on society
No.146.
The third industrial revolution
No-one can deny that all our lives are being affected by the
introduction of the computer and related Information systems.
In this issue of Impact we take a look at this revolution and the
fundamental changes It Is bringing to the world of work.
Separate articles are devoted to data retrieval, computer-aided
design and manufacture, integrated management of production
processes, robotics, fifth-generation computers, and novel
educational systems to prepare our children for the new
information age. A special introductory chapter describes a
major new Unesco initiative In the field of informatics.
THE NEW INDUSTRIAL REVOLUTION
The Intergovernmental Informatics Programme
André Danzin
The third industrial revolution : an economic overview
Rahat Nabi Khan
The technical database : storage, recovery and utilization of
industrial and engineering data
David A. Blackburn
Computer-aided design : a powerful tool at the disposal of the
designer
Jean Sequeira
Mechanics, electronics and computer science : their
integration in manufacturing
Bruno I. Rebaglia and Sergio Sartori
Robots : their present-day use and prospects for the future
Elisabeth Filemon
Fifth generation computer systems and their Impact on society
Norihisa Doi, Koichl Furukawa and Kazuhlro Fuchi
The engineer and the modern technological revolution
Christo Boutzev
The twenty-first century corporation
Roger B. Smith
The growing influence of microelectronics and computer
technology in China
Liu Fengglao
Education for an information age
Blagovest Sendov
Science reports horn the regions
Research in palm oil
P. Parameswaran
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
Institute of Higher Studies in International Relations
Founded in 1948
ILERI offers to students and young executives the opportunity
to pursue studies in International Relations in the fields of law,
economics, diplomacy, commerce and languages.
The faculty is composed of university professors, and senior
officials in international relations. The Diploma, awarded after
the four-year study program, gives access to French doctorate
programs as well as American MBAs.
Admission to first year is subject to the equivalent of the French
Baccalauréat. Admission to second year is subject to successful
completion of two years of French university (or equivalent).
Admission is granted only after close examination of the
student's academic record, followed by an interview.
Institute of Higher Studies in International Relations
Private Institute of Higher Studies
12 Rue des Saints-Pères, 75007 Paris
Tél. (1) 42 96 51 48
Secretary's office open Monday through Friday from 9 a.m. to 12 a.m.
and from 2 p.m. to 6 p.m.
EXHIBITION
Unesco Courier
40 years of cultural action
^
Georges Pompidou Centre, Paris
9 September-5 October 1 987
]]>
</page>
<page number="49">
<![CDATA[
!.-*-
y r- v
m
A baroque mise
\V
tV
Conceptions of the Baroque
According to one theory, the term baroque
stems from the Portuguese word barroco,
which is used to describe a rough or imper¬
fectly shaped pearl. In the 18th century it
was being used to denote (in architecture)
"a paroxysm of the bizarre" or "the height
of absurdity", and to describe music that
was "laden with dissonance" (Jean-Jacques
Rousseau). More generally it designated
forms of artistic expression "in which the
rules of proportion are not observed and
everything is represented according to the
artist's whim" (Pernety, Dictionnaire por¬
tatif de peinture, sculpture et gravure,
Paris, 1757).
"Baroque architecture speaks the same lan-
- guage as the Renaissance, but in a barbarie
11 dialect." (Jacob Burckhardt, // Cicerone,
í 1860.)
! "A noble art form with a rural base, pro¬
duced by seigneurial landed societies, in
contrast to classical art which is associated
with the bourgeoisie." (V.-L. Tapié, Baro¬
que et classicisme, 1957.)
"A palatine and urban art, springing from a
Catholic and monarchical society which is
both aristocratic and bourgeois." (G.
Bazin, Destins du baroque, 1970.)
"The Baroque is a permanent element of
sensibility which continually changes its
appearances throughout the history of
j?& art." (E. d'Ors, Lo barroco, 1936.)
/ Words and expressions commonly associ-
\ 2 ated with baroque art include: exuberance,
extravagance, exaggerated forms, rejection
of straight lines, contorted forms, gesticu¬
la lation, declamation, free forms, "forms
7 that fly" (E. d'Ors), exploding space, dise-
r quilibrium, asymmetry, diagonal dyna-
- mism, effects of depth, evanescence, illu-
1Ï sionism, trompe-1'til, art of movement, art
Ä of excess.
Further reading
Renaissance and Baroque, by H. Wölf-
flin. Cornell University Press, U.S.A.,
1967; Collins Publishers, London, 1984.
Principles of Art History, by H. Wölf-
flin. Dover Publications, New York, 1949.
Der Barock als Kunst des Gegenre¬
formation (1921; "Baroque, the Art of the
Counter-Reformation"), by W. Weisbach.
L'art baroque, by Y. Bottineau. Edi¬
tions Mazenod, Paris, 1986.
The Story of Art, by E.H. Gombrich.
Phaidon Press, London, 1957.
Baroque, the Age of Exuberance, by D.
Scarisbrick. Orbis Publishing, London,
1973.
Building the Escorial, by G. Kubier.
Princetown University Press, U.S.A.,
1981.
Baroque and Rococo in Latin America (2
vols.), by P. Kelemen. Dover Publications,
New York, 1951, 1967.
The Story of Architecture in Mexico, by
T.E. Sanford, W.W. Norton & Co., New
York, 1947.
The Art and Architecture of Russia, by
G.H. Hamilton. (Pelican History of Art),
Penguin Books, Harmondsworth, U.K.,
1954.
Art and Architecture in France, 1500-
1700, by A. Blunt. (Pelican History of
Art), Penguin Books, Harmondsworth,
U.K., 1953, 1981.
Baroque Art and Architecture in Central
Europe, by E. Hempel. (Pelican History of
Art), Penguin Books, Harmondsworth,
U.K., 1965.
Baroque, by J.R. Martin. Penguin
Books, Harmondsworth, U.K., 1977.
Baroque and Rococo Art, by A.C. Sew
ter. Thames & Hudson, London, 1972.
English Baroque Architecture, by K.
Downes. A. Zwemmer, London, 1966.
Italian Baroque and Rococo
Architecture, by J. Varriano. Oxford Uni¬
versity Press, U.K., 1986.
The World Atlas of Architecture, G.K.
Hall & Co., Boston, Massachusetts,
U.S.A., 1984.
Some baroque masterpieces
Façades: S. Carlo alle Quattro Fontane,
Rome, by Borromini, and the Palazzo
Carignano, Turin, by Guarini.
Sculpture: The Ecstasy ofSt. Theresa, Sta. **
Maria della Vittoria, Rome, by Bernini; '
i The Way of the Cross series by Aleijadinho aSh/,
at the sanctuary of Bom Jesus de Mato-
zinhos, Congonhas do Campo, Brazil.
Decoration: El transparente by Narciso
Tomé (Toledo cathedral, Spain) and the
¡façade of San Francisco Acatépec, Mexico;
church interiors: the church of St. John
Nepomuk, Munich, and the church of Sao
Domingo, Salvador, Brazil; Assumption of
the Virgin, by E.Q. Asam, Rohr monas¬
tery, Fed. Rep. of Germany (decorative
carving); ceiling of the church of Santa
Maria Tonantzintla, Mexico.
Palaces and castles: Nymphenburg and
Würzburg (Bavaria, Fed. Rep. of Ger¬
many); Stupinigi (Piedmont, Italy).
Painting: ceiling fresco, Palazzo Barber¬
ini, Rome, by Pietro da Cortona; vault of II
Gesù, also in Rome, by Gaulli.
"Ephemeral" architecture: triumphal
arch of the Carrefour de la Fontaine Saint-
Gervais, Paris, erected to mark the arrival
of Marie Thérèse of Austria, queen consort
of Louis XÍV of France, 26 August 1660.
Depictions of this and many other
"ephemeral" baroque works of art con-
,' structed of non-durable materials can be
Í found in contemporary engravings.
X"V
<S£s
>
SL'-Jff
<#
y
&4
i
1
"I"
- Pi
"M
>.W»
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="50">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
