<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="076565eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
i?,
Archaeology
under water
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Roller-skating around the Mediterranean
Five young roller-skaters with an impressive sporting achieve¬
ment to their credit being welcomed by the Director-General of
Unesco, on their arrival at the Organization's Paris Head¬
quarters on 9 September 1987. They had set off from Monaco on
13 July and roller-skated for 5,000 km in the summer heat, along
often difficult routes through Italy, Tunisia, Algeria, Morocco,
Spain and France. They skated some 90 km each day, except for
one daily stage when they covered 216 km and set a world
record. This exercise in friendly co-operation between young
people was organized under the auspices of Unesco's Inter¬
national Fund for the Development of Physical Education and
Sport (FIDEPS), as the first in a series of international sporting
and cultural events designed to further the objectives of the
Fund.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
Almost forty-five years ago, the French explorer Jacques-Yves Cousteau
and the engineer Emile Gagnan invented the aqualung (Scuba) , a
self-contained underwater breathing device, and opened up a new era in
the exploration of the ocean floor. Before the aqualung, divers were
weighed down by heavy, cumbersome equipment which severely limited
their underwater stamina and work capacity. With the aqualung vast
areas of the sea floor became accessible to human curiosity to marine
biologists, to photographers, and to archaeologists.
Since that time underwater archaeology has made great strides. A
number of spectacular discoveries, excavations and rescue operations (a
selection of which are described in this issue) have captured the
imagination of a wide public. Meanwhile, away from the limelight, great
progress has been made in the development of underwater archaeology
as a discipline on a par with land archaeology. This is a science which
brings together not only professional and amateur archaeologists but
sports divers, geologists, architects, surveyors and marine historians, as
well as the geophysicists and electronic engineers who help to search the
seabed and pinpoint remains through the use of remote sensing
equipment. Underwater archaeologists are today adding to our
knowledge of the past in many ways. Ancient wrecks are "time-capsules"
which, when scientifically studied, can provide a microcosmic picture of
life in the civilizations which produced them. On a larger scale, the
collection, collation and interpretation of a growing mass of data
accumulated from individual wrecks and underwater sites which are often
not spectacular in themselves are throwing new light on ancient
technologies and patterns of trade, changing sea levels, ancient
settlements and migrations, helping us, in short, to understand human
use of the sea and lakes over several millennia.
This issue presents a selection of reports on the activities of underwater
archaeologists working in different world regions, in different marine
environments, on different types of site, using different methods, on
projects of different scales. The reports cover not only investigations of
marine shipwrecks, but of submerged inland sites, as well as harbours,
cities and even a vast landmass, now located underwater as a result of
various kinds ofnatural occurrences. Finally, two articles reflect
Unesco's concern about the protection of archaeological sites and the
need for action to combat the looting of underwater sites and the growing
illegal traffic in archaeological treasures.
Cover: A ghostly ship looms out of the past in this side-scan sonar image
of the wreck of an early 19th-century Great Lakes sailing vessel with masts
still standing. Sound pulses reflected from 70 metres down show the ship,
which sank in 1813, in black, casting a white acoustic shadow that outlines
her masts.
Photo Gary Kozak © Canadian Center for Inland Waters, Klein Associates, Inc.
Back cover: A diver surveys a hull at a wreck-site off the coast of Gabon.
Photo Xavier Desmier © CEDRI, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
November 1987
40th year
Plunging into the past
Underwater archaeology, a new scientific
discipline with a wide popular following
by Nicholas Flemming and Mark Redknap
An international survey of
the underwater heritage
The Mediterranean,
an underwater museum
Between 50 and '100 new sites
located each year
by Anthony I. Parker
The Madrague de Giens wreck
A Roman freighter yields its secrets
by André Tchernia
Ten great discoveries
Technology and the marine
archaeologist
by Charles Mazel
Fair copies
Modern replicas of ancient vessels
11
12
15
23
Law and the underwater heritage
by Lyndel V. Prott and Patrick I. O'Keefe
24
The amphora war
Looting of ancient shipwrecks is
widespread. How can it be stopped?
Jewels from the Crown
A 17th-century man-of-war
in the Baltic
by Lars Einarsson
Herod's great harbour
by Avner Raban
Beringia
A prehistoric 'intercontinental highway'
between Asia and America
by Nikolai N. Dikov
25
26
30
32
Reports from 6 countries
Spain: Exploring a 'ships' graveyard'
The Netherlands: Archaeology in muddy
waters
Italy: The Lazzaretto wreck
Norway: Amateurs are welcome
Mexico: Sacred wells and Spanish galleons
Sri Lanka: Coins and cannon
35
Apollonia, a model port of Antiquity 38
The Courier English
French
Italian
Hindi
Turkish
Urdu
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Finnish
Swedish
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English ,
A window open on the world
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 33 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
German Persian Korean Bulgarian Vietnamese
Scientific and Cultural Organizatioi Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala N°ll-1987-CPD-87-l-451 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Underwater
archaeology,
a new scientific
discipline with a wide
popular following
Plunging into
THE origins of underwater archaeolo¬
gy can be traced back to the time,
about a century ago, when a handful
of intrepid archaeologists began to use hel¬
met diving methods or employ sponge di¬
vers to look at submerged ruins and wrecks.
These methods were used on perhaps a
dozen sites in all until the end of the Second
World War, when the aqualung, a self-
contained underwater breathing device in¬
vented by the French explorer Jacques-
Yves Cousteau and the engineer Emile
Gagnan, made it possible for scientists and
explorers to work cheaply and easily in
waters up to 50 metres deep.
Hundreds of books and magazine articles
have now been written about underwater
archaeology. In particular, in the last thirty
years a number of underwater excavations
have received massive publicity (see page
12). These finds, surveys and excavations
have been vitally important, and have
furthered the art and discipline of underwa¬
ter surveying, stratigraphy, and the inter¬
pretation of ancient seafaring. Such major
wreck excavations which have produced
well-preserved artefacts form the high
points of underwater archaeology.
However, to present another review of
the high points of the last thirty years might
suggest that underwater archaeology has
become intellectually and spiritually dead,
living off the grandeur of its achievements.
The truth is that underwater archaeology
has been spreading like wildfire. There are
now many thousands of underwater sites
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
the past by Nicholas Flemming and Mark Redknap
known throughout the world, ranging in
age from 45,000 years to a few decades,
from Stone Age quarry sites in Tasmania to
American War of Independence gunboats;
from the floor of the Mediterranean to
Alpine lakes and sinkholes in Mexico and
Florida. Hundreds of professional
archaeologists spend at least part of their
time supervising underwater sites, whilst
thousands of amateur diving archaeologists
assist the professionals in many dozens of
countries.
Many developing countries now support
scientific work on underwater archaeologic¬
al sites ranging from the seventeenth-cen¬
tury Portuguese vessel off Mombasa
(Kenya), and trade centres dating from the
ninth to the twelfth century off Malaysia, to
pre-European craft off Korea and
Thailand, and early ports and wrecks off the
southeast coast of Sri Lanka (see page 37).
This increasing awareness of the cultural
importance of archaeological sites in the
maritime zone by governments and institu¬
tions is extremely encouraging.
The vast number of sites which are now
known provide professional archaeologists
with vital new opportunities. Whilst the
sites are not all of equal value, and some are
mundane, the accumulation of data means
that experts can search for correlations,
evolution and trends through time, spatial
patterns and differences, links and causes.
Instead of treating artefacts only as objects
of beauty or technical achievement, the
archaeologist can start to interpret them as
parts of culture, trade, economics, politics,
and patterns of living. Obviously the
archaeologists working on the earlier ex¬
cavations used comparisons with land sites
to make such tentative deductions, but the
sheer accumulation of information now
means that much more sophisticated analy¬
sis can be attempted on the basis of com¬
parison between underwater sites.
These vast assemblages of similar under¬
water sites of similar ages mean that we can
start to understand how peoples and cul¬
tures related to the sea or lakes in each
millennium and century. That is a grand
objective. As the number and variety of
sites has increased, the age barrier has been
pushed further back in time.
In the 1950s the earliest known shipwreck
was the Gelidonya Bronze Age ship at 1200
BC (some others were earlier than about
200 BC), and the earliest known harbours
about 600 BC. The age of ship finds has only
been pushed a little way back, with the
discovery in 1982 of the fourteenth-century
BC ship near Kas off the coast of southern
Turkey (see page 12), but the number of
known ships older than 2,200 years has
increased significantly, filling the gaps.
The age of known harbours and coastal
occupation sites has been extended drama¬
tically, first with Bronze Age harbours
(1500 BC) found in the late 1960s and early
1970s in Greece and Israel; then with
Neolithic and Mesolithic settlements
(5,000-10,000 years old) found in the Baltic,
and off the coasts of Greece, Turkey, Israel
and the United States; and most recently
Palaeolithic artefacts, found in the North
Sea, and off the coast of France, Italy and
Greece, ranging in age from 10,000 to
45,000 years. We are now in a position to
consider studying the whole sweep of the
evolution of human culture in its relation to
the sea over the last 40,000 years.
During the last Ice Age, from approx¬
imately 120,000 to 5,000 years ago, the sea
level was lowered as much as 150 metres, as
so much water was locked up in the form of
ice in the great ice caps on the continents.
As a result, most of the continental shelves
of the world were dry, and Palaeolithic
tribes could walk from Siberia to Alaska,
from continental Europe to Britain, from
the Soviet Union to Japan, and most of the
way from Asia to Australia. Today under¬
water archaeology is contributing to
our knowledge about these prehistoric
migrations.
f
m»
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
High standards of stratigraphie recording
are now considered routine underwater. In
the 1950s, Professor George Bass
pioneered the techniques which enabled di¬
vers to maintain the same standards of re¬
cording as would be expected on land, pro¬
ducing accurate descriptions of deposits and
using grids to produce precise site plans.
Over the decades, improvements in electro¬
nic positioning, sonar imaging, and the use
of underwater survey equipment and tape-
recorders for fast on-site data collection,
have improved the procedures, and made
work faster. But the objective is always the
same: to record the three-dimensional
structure of a deposit, whether a wreck or
an occupation site, so that the sequence of
accumulation of artefacts and natural debris
can be understood. This time-sequenced
accumulation can then be unscrambled in
reverse, so as to get as close as possible to
the conditions and mode of use of the arte¬
facts at the moment before deposition.
The stories presented on the following
pages are a small selection of the many
hundreds of underwater archaeological re¬
search projects at present underway in
many countries. They range from large ex¬
cavations centred on major museums to the
excavations of modest wrecks by amateurs.
They are typical of projects in the 1980s.
Above all, they show a healthy level of
energy, dedication to detail, and stimulat¬
ing response to new ideas.
Where does underwater archaeology go
from here? Firstly, we should perhaps be
cautious and cast doubt on the theory that
underwater archaeology has reached
maturity. Conflicts between amateurs and
professionals, between souvenir hunters
and archaeologists, between treasure-sal¬
vors and those concerned with presenting
and preserving the past for the benefit of
present and future generations still create
continuous problems. Nor have legislation
and attitudes really evolved to contain the
conflict. A great deal of educational effort,
in the broadest sense, is needed to bring
order.
The World Confederation of Underwa¬
ter Activities (CMAS) is currently carrying
out a survey of the underwater cultural
heritage in an attempt to meet the need for
an overall assessment of the present state of
underwater archaeology and for greater ex¬
change of this information (see box). Ques¬
tionnaires on both marine cultural re¬
sources and inland underwater sites have
been sent out by CMAS to 151 countries.
Information on national inventories de¬
scribing the numbers of underwater and
marine artefacts in various countries, have
been received from Europe, Africa, Asia
and the entire Mediterranean littoral. The
survey aims to produce a consultative docu¬
ment including specific recommendations
for increased support for research.
There is a growing awareness that the
underwater archaeological heritage belongs
to the population at large, to the nation, to
the community and that nobody has the
right to destroy it or exploit it for private
gain. If a wreck or city is too expensive to
excavate and preserve in the dry, then it
should be left and protected underwater. In
parallel with principles applied on land in
many countries, if social priorities demand
the construction of a harbour, motorway,
barrage, or oil well, then preventive
archaeology should be carried out first.
Another important trend in underwater
archaeology today relates to co-operation
between amateurs and professionals. It has
been suggested that tens of millions of peo¬
ple have an interest in archaeology, that
there are two million or so sports divers, a
few hundred professional archaeologists,
and a few tens of professional treasure hun¬
ters. Many professional underwater
archaeologists stress that their work would
be impossible without amateur assistance.
Since there are now sports diving federa¬
tions in over sixty-five countries, and most
Photography is an essential tool for the
underwater archaeologist who, like the ex¬
cavator of any archaeological site, must
record the locations of finds and make an
accurate survey of the site. Stereophotog-
rammetry is today widely used to produce
accurate site-plans from stereoscopic
photos taken at different points along a
frame. Right, a diving archaeologist sets
up a camera mounted on a boom ready for
stereophotogrammetry. Since it is gener¬
ally impossible to encompass the whole
area being excavated in a single photo,
archaeologists fit a number of photos
together like a jigsaw puzzle to give a
general impression of the site. Below,
photomosaic of the wreck of the 1 7th-cen-
tury Swedish vessel Kronan in the Baltic
(see article page 26). The main problems in
photography under water are that light,
colour and contrast are lost with increas¬
ing depth.
of them show serious interest in underwater
archaeology, it is not surprising that the
number of new sites reported to the author¬
ities should be increasing rapidly. In the
Mediterranean, for example, most known
ancient wrecks are from areas where there
are the most sports divers, in the south of
France. Similarly, most Neolithic sites have
been discovered off the coasts of Denmark,
Israel and Florida, where sports divers and
professionals have combined to search for
them. Since sports diving is rather expen¬
sive as a hobby, it tends to spread progres¬
sively to more and more of the developing
countries as they increase their level of
technology and raise the economic standard
of living. We can therefore expect a steady
increase of new data from the coasts of Asia
and Africa in the coming years.
NICHOLAS C. FLEMMING, of the UK, is presi¬
dent of the Scientific Committee of the World
Confederation of Underwater Activities. He has
many years experience in archaeological diving
on submerged terrestrial sites, and is the author
of many articles and books on the subject. He is
the co-editor (with P.M. Masters) of Quaternary
Coastlines and Marine Archaeology, Towards
the Prehistory of Land Bridges and Continental
Shelves, published by Academic Press, London
(1983).
MARK REDKNAP, British archaeologist spe¬
cializing in Roman and medieval pottery, is
secretary of the Archaeological Committee of the
World Confederation of Underwater Activities.
He has excavated widely both under water and
on land.
te
a
m
o
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
pHH
i^^B
^¿
5
a-
E
n
©
An international
survey of
the underwater
heritage
The Scientific Committee of the
World Confederation of
Underwater Activities
(CMAS) is currently carrying out an
international survey of the underwa¬
ter cultural heritage. The survey,
which is being prepared with Unesco
support, will review marine cultural
resources and inland underwater
sites, mechanisms for their protec¬
tion, shipwreck data bases and under¬
water cultural heritage inventories,
ways of disseminating results, and the
priorities for underwater archaeolo¬
gical research. The survey is designed
to record submerged archaeological
remains without giving away their
locations.
CMAS, which has also produced an
International Code ofPractice for Sci¬
entific Diving, is an international non¬
governmental organization which
groups national bodies concerned
with the training and safety of non-
military and non-commercial divers
involved in the fields of sport, photo¬
graphy, science, conservation, medi¬
cine, and the technology of diving
equipment. Its Scientific Committee,
established in 1970, includes repre¬
sentatives from bodies concerned with
professional diving and has Commis¬
sions on biology and conservation,
technology, geology and archaeology.
Already a number of sites of im¬
portance for marine archaeology have
been included on Unesco's World
Heritage List of properties of out¬
standing universal value. These sites
are covered by the system of protec¬
tion and international co-operation
organized by the World Heritage
Convention adopted by the General
Conference of Unesco in 1972 (see the
Unesco Courier, October 1987). They
include the Great Barrier Reef (Aus¬
tralia), where a number of shipwrecks
of historical interest are known, in¬
cluding that oiHMS Pandora (see col¬
our pages) which ran aground there in
1791. Also on the List are the island of
Gorée (Senegal), the great classical
cities ofCarthage (Tunisia) and Leptis
Magna (Libyan Arab Jamahiriya),
and the ruins of Kilwa Kisiwani and
Songo Mnara (United Republic of
Tanzania), whence merchants once
controlled a large proportion of trade
in the Indian Ocean.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The Mediterranean,
an underwater museum
Between 50 and 100 new sites
located each year
by Anthony J. Parker
8
THE formative cultures of European
history, especially the far-reaching
"Roman Empire, grew up around the
Mediterranean Sea. They were thus in¬
volved with seafaring, fishing and seaborne
commerce from the earliest times. Even in
the seventh millennium BC, finds of obsi¬
dian and fish-bones in prehistoric settle¬
ments in Greece show that the sea was not
an insuperable barrier.
In the classical period, cities such as
Athens or Rome could not have survived
without a regular supply of food and raw
materials from overseas, brought by hun¬
dreds of sailing ships. An observer, gazing
out over the Mediterranean from a cliff or a
mountain top on a summer day some time in
the last two centuries before Christ or the
first two centuries of the Christian era,
would have seen the blue sea dotted with
sails.
The Mediterranean, though effectively
tideless, and enjoying good visibility and
calm weather for much of the summer, can
still hold dangers for sailing ships. There are
many low, sandy coasts which lack naviga¬
tion marks and natural havens; there are
also rocky, mountainous coasts where ships
can be held up by contrary winds, or over¬
whelmed by squalls. Mediterranean cur¬
rents, too, though they are scarcely noticed
by modern, powered ships, are strong
enough, if combined with other hazards, to
place a small sailing ship in danger.
The magnetic compass was unknown to
the classical world: ships navigated the
Mediterranean by looking out for land¬
marks such as mountains, or by watching
the stars at night. A sudden storm could
therefore endanger the ship, not just if it
were to be overwhelmed or made to leak,
but by blotting out the sky or the horizon so
that the ship sailed unawares into danger.
Small wonder, then, that there were
many shipwrecks in classical Antiquity. The
actual total number of ships lost is un¬
known it must run into scores or hundreds
of thousands but the dangers of sailing
(especially outside the best months of the
year) were well known, and are mentioned
by many writers, both Greek and Latin.
Today, almost 1,000 shipwrecks of the clas¬
sical and medieval periods have been disco¬
vered in the Mediterranean and the Black
Sea; nearly all of these have been found by
aqualung divers in the last forty years.
This body of information, which is con¬
tinuing to grow at the rate of between fifty
and a hundred new sites every year, offers
great opportunities to archaeologists and
historians to find out more about the com¬
merce and economy of the ancient world.
There are, of course, plenty of difficulties.
The shipwrecked cargoes which survive for
divers to discover do not, for the most part,
include perishable goods such as corn, tim¬
ber or cloth, which were certainly among
the most important items of trade; not all
wrecks are well preserved; some areas have
not been thoroughly searched; all too many
sites have been inadequately excavated, re¬
corded, studied or published; and many
divers are concerned only with collecting
souvenirs or even making a profit out of
selling their finds.
The special qualities of classical ship¬
wreck sites are double the overall view
and the detailed insight. Since almost no
statistics referring to seaborne trade survive
from Antiquity, the hundreds of lost ships,
even though they are individually very
varied, can supply a kind of statistic. No
master ever chose deliberately to wreck his
ship, destroy his cargo and risk his crew's
lives: shipwrecks are essentially a hapha¬
zard selection from the voyages which were
made, though we do not (and cannot) tell
whether the selection is really a meaningful
sample.
The areas where shipwrecks have been
found is one such statistic. The map on page
9 shows how they have been reported from
most parts of the Mediterranean, but that
the distribution is decidedly uneven. Many
coastal areas, and most of the deep sea,
have no wrecks at all; conversely, some
areas, such as the south of France, which
has one-fifth of all recorded sites, bulk dis¬
proportionately large because diving is
popular in this area, there is a State under¬
water archaeology service, and most of the
known sites have been published.
Another statistic which can be derived
from the shipwreck reports is the periods at
which voyages were most frequent. The
great majority of known Mediterranean
shipwrecks date from the Hellenistic and
early Roman Empire periods. Knowledge
HP
of prehistory, and even of the colonizing
and archaic centuries of Greek and Phoeni¬
cian navigation, remains surprisingly un¬
documented. On the other hand, the statis¬
tics clearly show the revival of Mediterra¬
nean commerce in the sixth century AD. In
the medieval period (after the Arab con¬
quest of the seventh century AD) there
were many changes in seaborne commerce,
and so it is not surprising that wrecks of
these centuries have rarely been reported.
In order to collect general statistics of this
kind, one has to take into account all man¬
ner of wrecks, both well-preserved, where
the ship's cargo and a good part of her hull
lie on the sea-bed much as they came to rest
on the day she sank, and mere scatters of
broken pottery, often ground into tiny
pieces by the waves and mingled with the
remains of other cargoes lost at the same
hazardous spot. Nor are all the published
reports of wrecks of equal value: in fact,
over a quarter of all recorded sites have
been published only in very summary
terms, such as "A Roman wreck two
kilometres out to sea...". Figures and dia¬
grams can reduce this very varied material
to order for the historian, but there can be
no doubt that it is well-preserved and fully-
excavated wrecks that with their grouping
of cargo, nautical equipment, personal pos-
CONTINUED PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Surveying the site of a 4th-century-AD
Roman wreck in the Mediterranean
Ancient shipwrecks in the Mediterranean and the Black Sea
0° 1tf 20" 30" tc
I '-V->
^.-/ L>^
***~i îÏ -gfeti:.
A< y^ l^T ^
X p+!!* \ - ? - ^
~1- 4** L\ * TK, - Í \
%*' S * ^-l^ y ^u 7
JP o- . /*» I f^' ea Vf -40"
! *^ÏT ti .\>...^ kv l~&
/I"* Sitó- BSI "^
* r^« iL? *1^¿V"^
! ^^^ ¿/" -C' ' .AT* e^. ;-^vfe^/>,.-^'
ï i-- átï5 Í^*3
.£- ' zfc t -¿ . .;
®
>
NUMBER OF SHIPWRECKS
1
2-4
5-12
0 13-24
£ 25-66
^x
3 ^"""^ ''"""'"^L* » - 5Î
3
C ~^^^ # ^^\S-«>t
3 lrf
es i i
ti
© 1 '^2L ir
§
3
' ' 0" 	 10" 2D" 30" ¿ff
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 8
sessions and hull timbers offer real gains to
archaeology.
The people and objects on board a ship
make up a very special group in any society,
but we rarely have similar opportunities on
land to catch a glimpse of people and arte¬
facts frozen in the midst of their daily life.
This "time capsule" aspect of ancient ship¬
wrecks never fails to enthral divers, as
weed, encrustation and sand are delicately
stripped from the underlying deposits. Just
one example could be cited the Byzantine
wreck of Yassi Ada, excavated by George
Bass and Fred Van Doorninck, where the
captain, Georgios, had meals cooked in a
tiny stone-floored galley in the stern while
his quite small ship sailed on with her cargo
of anise-flavoured wine, slopping about in a
job lot of second-hand jars. One could
name many more details, and many other
wrecks, which together make up a vivid and
ever-growing tapestry of life in the ancient
world.
Gathering the threads of this tapestry,
however, involves more than merely diving
and collecting artefacts. Wreck-sites can
only be understood if they are meticulously
excavated, fully recorded on site, if the
finds are carefully catalogued and con¬
served, and most important of all if
enough time, effort and money are spent on
making a thorough study of every aspect of
the site. The Yassi Ada wreck is one of a
mere handful of excavated wrecks which
have been anything like properly studied
and published.
In the Mediterranean, as elsewhere,
wrecks are threatened with destruction
from commercial development and casual
looting. Portable artefacts such as amphor-
Datum 2
Î0
I
10
Approximate position
of looted concretion _
+ Datum 1
t « t i L r
Scale in metre»
+
Test pit
Amphoras salvaged m 1981
(approximate positions)
* « 3m x 2m »xcavation frame
Wood
as are hard to protect by legislation and
policing, and often the only way to save, a
site from destruction is to excavate it as
soon as possible.
There are some wrecks, however, which
are easier to protect, at least from casual
depredation, and they are also often spec¬
tacular sites on which to dive. These are the
remains of marble and building stone car¬
goes. At Rome the demand for fine stone
with which to construct or finish off build¬
ings had to be met by importing marble and
granite from Greece, Turkey, Egypt and
other distant parts of the Empire. Natural¬
ly, some stone-carrying ships failed to reach
their destination, and their cargoes lie lost
and abandoned along the sea-routes of the
Mediterranean. To swim under water
among the great blocks of stone is an aes¬
thetic and an evocative experience.
Let us hope that these sites can be left as
they are, with some protected status and
with a guardian boatman in charge, to serve
as exciting and instructive underwater
monuments which tourists (with aqualungs,
snorkels or even glass-bottomed buckets)
can view, just as (in another dimension)
they might visit the Colosseum or the Parth¬
enon on land.
ANTHONY J. PARKER, of the UK, is lecturer in
Roman archaeology at Bristol University. He is
the author of a forthcoming comprehensive re¬
view of pre-16th-century wrecks in the
Mediterranean.
Drawing at left is an example of site-map¬
ping as practiced by underwater
archaeologists. It shows the wreck of a
small Roman merchant ship which ran
aground on the beach of Randello, on the
south coast of Sicily, around AD 300, while
carrying a cargo of sardines preserved in
brine and stored in amphoras. Almost
1,700 years later, in 1982, the wreck was
excavated by a team of archaeologists
from British universities, with the help of
the man who found it, Dort. Giovanni
D'Andrea, and the assistance of the Sici¬
lian authorities. Analysis of fish-bones in
the amphoras revealed that the sardines
had "been processed in a permanent, pro¬
fessional fish-factory", writes Dr. Anthony
Parker. "The clay and shape of the
amphoras point to the Sado estuary of
Portugal as the place where this was done;
in the ruined Roman town of Troia, at the
mouth of the estuary, batteries of fish-
salting tanks can still be seen. The salt¬
pans of the Sado are traditionally re¬
nowned for the fine flavour of their salt,
and a century ago the fishermen of the
area were recorded as using boats and
nets for catching sardines in a way which
is extraordinarily like not only what we
know of Roman fishing in general but also
what can be inferred from the Randello
sardine bones."
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
A Roman
freighter
yields its secrets
The Madrague
de Giens
wreck
by André Tchernia
FOR eleven years, from 1972 to 1982,
diver-archaeologists of the
Archaeological Institute run jointly
in Aix-en-Provence (France) by the Uni¬
versity of Provence and the National Centre
for Scientific Research (CNRS), pitched
camp each summer in a pine wood over¬
looking the sea on the southern shore of the
Giens peninsula, some thirty kilometres
east of Toulon.
A Roman wreck had been discovered
near the little fishing port of La Madrague
de Giens in 1967, and since it was lying at a
reasonable depth 18 to 20 metres and
had not, like so many others, been pillaged
by looters, it was chosen as the site of the
first truly scientific underwater excavation
carried out in France on a considerable
scale. Three years of work were planned:
little did we know, at the time, that the
wreck would prove to be one of the two or
three largest ancient ships whose remains
have ever been found under the sea.
The method adopted is easier to describe
than it was to implement, given the nature
of our equipment and changing conditions
at sea. It meant extricating the objects care¬
fully and completely using an air pump,
without moving any one of them before its
position had been recorded; attaching
clearly visible numbers to all the amphoras
and other important objects; carrying out a
stereoscopic photographic coverage of the
area explored; raising to the surface the
objects thus identified, and continuing to
probe, level by level, as far as the hull.
Lastly, we carefully examined the hull itself
and dismantled parts of it in order to deter¬
mine how it had been constructed.
The ship was wrecked some time around
70-60 BC. It was carrying a cargo of wine
from Italyto be precise, from the region
of Terracina: we know the location of the
workshop where most of the amphoras in
the cargo were manufactured. It measured
nearly 40 metres in length, and could carry
7,000 or 8,000 amphoras, which gave it a
tonnage of 350 to 400 tons: a respectable
capacity for any traditional sea-going vessel
as late as the nineteenth century.
Part of the cargo of amphoras carried by
the Roman merchantman wrecked off the
south coast of France near La Madrague
de Giens.
But we did not find so many thousands of
amphoras on the sea-bed. Firstly because,
on its last voyage, the ship was not fully
loaded with wine. An extra cargo, consist¬
ing of crates of black glazed pottery, had
been packed on top. Secondly, and above
all, because we were able to establish that
divers probably professionals had come
to salvage the sunken cargo shortly after the
wreck, and had raised to the surface at least
half of the amphoras. There were two con¬
sistent pointers to this. The wreck is strewn
with large stones; a geological study has
shown that they very probably came from
the peninsula itself, or from the opposite
coast adjoining the town of Hyères. These
are the stones used by skin divers in order to
plummet more quickly to the sea-bed, as
sponge divers have done for centuries
throughout the Mediterranean.
Furthermore, scrutiny of photographs
and plans produced during the excavation
reveals beyond a shadow of doubt that,
despite the displacement of the cargo dur¬
ing and after the wreck, while three layers
of amphoras are still in place on the port
side, there is only one layer to starboard. In
some places there are even holes in the
cargo, and one or two isolated amphoras
have remained embedded in the volcanic
sand which, to aft, was used both as ballast
and to hold the amphoras in place, whereas
those next to them were hoisted on board
the boat used as a base by our predecessors
in Roman times.
Studying the hull called for the most spec¬
tacular measures. In order to examine the
keel and take samples from it, it was neces¬
sary to dig a tunnel under the hull and to use
underwater chain-saws. The fragments re¬
moved were taken apart and studied trenail
by trenail on land, then reassembled exactly
as before and returned to their place in the
wreck.
The most important finding was the con¬
firmation that the strongly curved hull pro¬
file and the depth of the keel would certain¬
ly have prevented the ship from drifting
very much and would have enabled it to sail
to windward. The elaborate form of the hull
would have compensated for the large, non-
specialized sails of ancient ships and given it
speed. Forward, an inverted stem and a
bobstay piece added the finishing touches to
the ship's nautical qualities.
Patrice Pomey drew up a detailed plan of
the hull and superimposed it on a much
later picture of a ship represented on a
Tunisian mosaic. The proportions are ex¬
actly the same: the upward sweep fore and
aft begins at exactly the same point, and the
bilge pump and the masts are in the same
positions. From this we must draw three
important conclusions: that this mosaic,
and probably many others, represent
ancient ships with much more realism and
accuracy than might be supposed; that the
missing parts and the sails of the Giens
wreck must have been similar to those on
the mosaic; and that this type of ship was
built to a virtually identical pattern for more
than three centuries.
Five years after the end of the excavation ,
an exhaustive study of the results is still far
from complete. Further observations will
be made. It is a pity that no other way of
preserving this great sailing ship of Antiqui¬
ty could be found than covering it with sand
again and leaving it buried where we had
found it.
ANDRE TCHERNIA, of France, is assistant
director of the sciences of man and society at the
National Centre for Scientific Research (CNRS).
In 1967 and 1968 he served as France's first
director of research in underwater archaeology.
With Patrice Pomey he directed, under the au¬
spices of the CNRS, the excavations of the Mad¬
rague de Giens shipwreck from 1972 to 1982. 11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Ten great discoveries
One of the Riace statues shortly after being
recovered from the sea
Photo Giansanti © Sygma, Paris
ITALY
The Riace warriors
In August 1972, a Roman skin-diver disco¬
vered two large bronze statues representing
human figures near Riace on the Calabrian
coast of southern Italy. He immediately
informed the archaeological authority for
the area, and the statues, about 2 metres
high and weighing over 150 kilos, were reco¬
vered from the sea-bed and brought back to
land. Authentic examples of classical Athe¬
nian art, it is thought that they may have
belonged to a group of 11 statues intended
to decorate the temple at Delphi. Some
specialists believe that they are the work of
the great Greek sculptor Phidias who, with
his pupils, carved the frontispiece and
friezes of the Parthenon in Athens. After
some 2,000 years of immersion, the restora¬
tion of these masterpieces of 5th-century-
BC Greek art proved a long and painstaking
job. The statues were X-rayed to provide a
picture of their internal structure and the
thickness of their different parts in order to
choose appropriate restoration materials.
Research revealed that metals other than
bronze were used for certain parts of the
statues. The teeth and eyelashes of one of
the figures are in silver, lips are of copper,
ivory was used for whites of the eyes and
vitreous paste and amber for the iris. The
statues are now preserved at the Magna
Graecia Museum in Reggio di Calabria,
where they were shown to the public for the
first time 7 years after being discovered.
(See Unesco Courier, November 1981)
On this double page and overleafwe present a selection of discoveries and achievements of
underwater archaeology in the last two decades which have attracted widespreadpublicity and have
contributed to the growingpopular interest in the underwater heritage.
P
Map Jack Kelly, courtesy Archaeology Vol 38, 4 I
Archaeological Institute of America 1 985
TURKEY
'Metal biscuits with ears'
This was how a young sponge diver des¬
cribed the objects he had spotted lying on
the sea-bed, in the autumn of 1982, less than
100 m from his home village of Kas. For the
experts from the Bodrum Museum of
Underwater Archaeology, this image re¬
called the copper ingots recovered in 1960
from a shipwreck at nearby Cape Gelidony-
a. The US archaeologist George Bass and
his team from the Institute of Nautical
Archaeology of Texas A & M University,
who had studied the Gelidonya wreck, im¬
mediately launched plans to excavate the
site, which has pushed back knowledge of
the shipbuilding techniques of Antiquity as
far as the Bronze Age. The copper ingots
found in the Kas wreck resemble an ingot
depicted in an Egyptian tomb at Thebes
dating from 1350 BC (copper was combined
with tin to make the bronze from which the
era takes its name). The discovery of a
miniature seal, no larger than a button, with
markings similar to those used by ancient
Greek merchants, suggested the origin of
the vessel. Among the finds in the wreck are
many precious objects in gold, pottery,
amphoras from Canaan, Mycenae and Cyp¬
rus, as well as cobalt-blue glass ingots, the
earliest glass ever found, probably intended
for making jewellery or goblets. The wreck
is still giving up its rich cargo, and the
remains of the hull will perhaps supply vital
information on the type of ships in use at the
time of the Trojan Wars.
Photos © Deutsches Schiffahrtsmuseum, Bremerhaven,
Fed. Rep. of Germany
FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF
GERMANY
Conserving the Bremen Cog
When the harbour at Bremen on the Weser
estuary in the Fed. Rep. of Germany was
dredged in 1962, engineers uncovered a
14th-century merchant vessel or "Cog" pre¬
served in the mud (top). The wreck was
rescued with a view to research and conser¬
vation. The raising of the Cog, the Wasa and
the 5 Viking ships from Roskilde Fjord
confronted museum conservators for the
first time with the problem of preserving
huge objects made of waterlogged, soft, old
wood. Scientists discovered that such tim¬
bers could be protected against the distor¬
tions caused by shrinkage which would in¬
evitably occur as they dried by impregna¬
tion with a water-soluble wax, polyethylene
glycol (abbreviated PEG). After the Cog
had been reconstructed from some 2,000
pieces of timber (a task which took 7 years) ,
a conservation tank was built around it so
that it could be immersed in a PEG solution
(above). Today visitors to the German
Maritime Museum at Bremerhaven can see
the resubmerged vessel through windows in
the tank, where it will be immersed for
many years. Controlled drying will then
take place and the tank will function as a
huge controlled climate chamber.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Map Reinhardt and Cavanagh, courtesy Archaeology
Vol. 37, 1 © Archaeological Institute of America 1984
JAMAICA
Port Royal a submarine
Pompeii
Shortly before noon on 7 June 1692, the
bustling life of Port Royal (Jamaica) ended
in a violent earthquake and tidal wave.
Within minutes, nine-tenths of the great
Caribbean trading centre lay beneath the
waters of what is now Kingston Harbour.
Since then many divers have explored its
ruins, but not always with the controls and
documentation demanded by modern
archaeology. In 1978 a plan of collaboration
between the Government of Jamaica and
the Institute of Nautical Archaeology of
Texas A & M University was established,
and a thorough research programme was
initiated. There are hundreds of submerged
buildings to be excavated, offering a wealth
of architectural data and artefacts, and
work will continue for years to come. A vast
quantity of brass, pewter, silver, iron, glass,
pottery and wood objects have already been
brought to the surface to be restored and
studied . The X-ray of one find , an encrusted
watch, has revealed the time at which the
earthquake struck.
UNITED KINGDOM
Tudor life at sea
On a calm summer day in 1545, as a French
invasion fleet lay at anchor off Portsmouth,
King Henry VIII's flagship, Mary Rose,
sailed into her final battle. Probably as a
result of poor handling and overloading, she
heeled over and sank, so close to the shore
that the king, watching her go down, is said
to have heard the cries of the drowning,
sailors. On 1 1 October 1982, 437 years later,
the surviving starboard hull structure of the
700-ton vessel was raised to the surface (see
drawings) and towed into Portsmouth har¬
bour as the climax of a great rescue opera¬
tion which had begun in the late 1960s when
maritime archaeologists located the wreck.
A survey and exploration programme was
carried out by volunteer divers, scientists
and archaeologists until 1979, and then the
contents of the ship were removed and its
structure fully recorded. Divers brought up
17,000 artefacts representing almost every
aspect of Tudor life at sea. The internal
structural timbers of the hull were disman¬
tled and taken ashore. After being raised in
a protective steel cradle, the Mary Rose was
taken to a special dry dock in Portsmouth
dockyard. Today visitors can view the hull,
like a giant cutaway model towering to the
height of a 4-storey building, and watch the
work underway to replace many of the tim¬
bers removed during the years of underwa¬
ter excavation (top right). When this work is
complete long-term conservation can begin.
The hall in which the ship is preserved is
kept at 95 % humidity. The hull is sprayed
with chilled water to prevent degradation
and uncontrolled drying.
Photo © Mary Rose Trust, Portsmouth, UK
The hull ready for lifting with wires attached
to tubular steel lifting frame
The hull in suspension from the lifting frame
being transferred underwater to a support
cradle
The cradle with the hull ready to be lifted into
the air and placed on a barge to be towed
ashore
uw^Ti
MEXICO
The sacred well of Chichén-Itzá
Underwater archaeology began in Mexico
with the exploration of the cenote (sacred
well) of Chichén-Itzá (left), a freshwater
well with a diameter of 68 m and a depth of
22 m to the surface of the water, itself 14 m
deep. The Mayan civilization, a highly de¬
veloped pre-Hispanic culture of Meso-
America, worshipped water deities, and vo¬
tive offerings were thrown into the well in
their honour. The first, unsuccessful,
attempt to explore it was made in 1881 to
1882 by the French antiquarian Désiré
Charnay. In 1904, Edward H. Thompson,
the first United States consul to Yucatán,
organized two seasons of diving work to
dredge the well, recovering archaeological
treasures (jade figures, stone sculptures,
gold and copper discs, remains of human
skeletons), which went to the Peabody
Museum in Harvard University, USA.
Other salvage attempts were carried out at
later dates. The most recent explorations
took place in 1967 to 1968, under the direc¬
tion of Dr. Pina Chan, of the National Insti¬
tute of Anthropology and History, Mexico.
The team employed various methods, such
as lowering the water level almost 4 m and
chemically clarifying the water. The divers
used the most advanced techniques, and all
the artefacts recovered, which will be pre¬
served in museums in various parts of the
country, will be studied and classified by
specialists from the Institute.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Full-scale replica of a Viking ship from
Roskilde Fjord
Photo © Viking Ships Museum, Roskilde
DENMARK
Viking dragon ships
Five Viking sailing ships scuttled over 900
years ago at the entrance to Roskilde Fjord,
near the village of Skuldelev in Denmark,
were discovered in the late 1950s during
underwater excavations organized by the
Danish National Museum. In 1962, a coffer¬
dam was built round the site which was
pumped free of water so that the wrecks
could be excavated as if on land. After
lengthy conservation treatment the ships
were painstakingly reconstructed. The re¬
mains were those of 2 warships of different
size, 2 merchant ships, and a smaller vessel,
perhaps a ferry or a fishing boat. The larger
warship seems to have been at least 30 m
long with provision for 26 pairs of oars. Such
a longship, designed for speed and man¬
oeuvrability, could have carried up to 60
warriors as well as its crew, and would have
been a pillar of Danish maritime power a
thousand years ago. One of the merchant¬
men is almost certainly a knarr, a type of
broad-beamed ocean-going craft which was
described in the Icelandic Sagas and formed
the backbone of Viking trade. The Roskilde
find provided archaeologists with a unique
opportunity in northern waters to study
ships built at the same time but for different
purposes.
A diver examines a Neolithic site (4000 BC)
in Lake Zürich.
Photo © Dr. Ulrich Ruoff, Zürich
SWITZERLAND
Lake-floor archaeology
The archaeological wealth of lakes and
other inland underwater sites is much less
well known than that of sites located in or
near the sea. In Switzerland and its neigh¬
bouring countries important discoveries
have been made from lake settlements built
on piles and dating mainly from the
Neolithic period and the Bronze Age (from
the end of the 5th century to the beginning
of the 1st century BC). In the last 20 years
excavations in Lake Zürich, one of the most
important centres of these lacustrine set¬
tlements, have brought to light Stone Age
and Bronze Age axe helves, ladles, flint
knives, looms, archery bows, wooden
boxes, scraps of netting and textiles, balls of
yarn and other finds providing valuable in¬
formation about prehistoric technology.
Four years ago the ground plan of a late
Bronze Age house was discovered at a spot
where volunteer divers had previously
found a collection of small Bronze Age
vessels. Today this cultural heritage is in
great danger due to construction work on
the shoreline, dredging to accommodate
shipping, and increased wave erosion in the
shore area as protective reeds are removed.
The preserved and reassembled hull of the
2,300-year-old Kyrenia Ship
Photo © M.L. Katzev, Arlington, Vt., USA.
Kyrenia Ship Project
CYPRUS
The Kyrenia wreck
Discovered by a sponge-diver, a 4th-cen-
tury-BC amphora carrier lying in about 30
m of water near the harbour town of Kyre¬
nia, Cyprus, began to be surveyed and exca¬
vated in 1968 by a team led by Michael L.
Katzev of the University of Pennsylvania.
Thus began a programme of conservation
and research which has continued for
almost two decades and culminated in the
building of Kyrenia II, a full-scale, sailable
replica of the ancient Greek merchantman
(see page 23). The Kyrenia Ship, writes
Katzev, "represents the best preserved hull
of the Classical Greek period ever found.
About 60 per cent of her total area and more
than 75 per cent of her representative tim¬
bers survived to be recorded in meticulous
detail. Five years went into raising the hull
piece by piece, preserving it in polyethylene
glycol, then mounting it for exhibition in a
handsome sandstone gallery of the Crusad¬
er Castle at Kyrenia". Its cargo included
some 400 amphoras, as well as crockery,
millstones, iron ingots, and the remains of
nearly 10,000 almonds.
SWEDEN
Raising the Wasa
In 1961, the Swedish warship Wasa was
raised from the bottom of Stockholm har¬
bour, where she had sunk at the start of her
maiden voyage in 1628. This huge vessel,
displacing about 1,300 tons and measuring
70 m from stem to stern, was apparently
unstable and capsized in 35 m of water. She
was remarkably well-preserved: she had not
suffered damage from long service at sea,
she had not run aground, and, lying at the
bottom for three centuries, she had not
been damaged by ice or currents nor attack-
Richly decorated stern of the Wasa. In the
middle, the Swedish national coat-of-arms.
ed by wood-destroying marine organisms.
The wreck, rediscovered in 1956 by an
amateur marine archaeologist and histor¬
ian, Anders Franzen, is an outstanding
testimony to 17th-century naval
architecture and life in Sweden. An unpre¬
cedented rescue operation was mounted
which lasted from 1957 to 1961. The sal¬
vaged ship was housed in a special hall
where the correct temperature and humid¬
ity could be maintained, and sprinklers
were installed to prevent premature drying
out of the wood. Treatment of the water¬
logged timbers was carried out by a system
of pipes and nozzles by which every part of
the ship was sprayed for more than 10 years
with a solution of polyethylene glycol
(PEG). By the late 1970s, more than 6
million people had already visited the
museum to see this major addition to
Sweden's cultural heritage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Technology and the marine
archaeologist by Charles Mazel
/ "pyAVY Jones meets the com-
* I I puter." "High Tech Treasure
M-J Hunt." These headlines from
articles on recent finds of important ship¬
wrecks are signs of the growing role of
sophisticated equipment in the location and
excavation of historic underwater sites. The
privateer De Braak, lost in 1798 with a
fortune in treasure reported aboard, was
found just off the shore of Lewes, De¬
laware, USA, by side-scan sonar. The site
of what is probably the pirate vessel
Whidah, sunk on the outer shore of Cape
Cod in 1717, was located by magnetometer.
In both cases, precision navigation played a
vital role.
The applications of technology go far
beyond the search phase of any project.
Sites must be excavated carefully, with pre¬
cise mapping and recording of the locations
of all objects found. Underwater work
raises difficulties unlike those encountered
on land. Besides the obvious problem of
breathing, there are limitations in com¬
munications, visibility, and movement, to
name a few. One of the early tasks of mod¬
ern marine archaeology was to develop
tools whose performance would match or
exceed those being used at land sites. That
goal generally has been achieved.
Just because a search or site mapping
operation uses all the latest electronic giz¬
mos and computer-controlled whatsits does
not mean that it is going about the project in
the right way. Proper technology should not
be confused with proper technique. Tech¬
nology is just the hardware, electronic or
otherwise, that is used for the job. Tech-
©
nique is the way in which that equipment is
used.
The question of technique should come
into play as soon as a project is conceived.
One factor in the initial planning of a job is
the selection of the appropriate technology.
And, even if the proper equipment is selec¬
ted, all efforts may fail if it is not used
properly. For example, running a sonar
search with inadequate navigational control
is poor technique and could lead to failure.
The right way to go about a project is to a)
succeed, and b) spend as little money and
time as possible in doing so. Both too much
and too little technology can be a problem.
Without proper technique, success be¬
comes a matter of luck. Proper selection of
tools and methods is playing an increasingly
important role in finding shipwrecks and
other sites and in carrying out the excava¬
tion and providing documentation.
The role of research as the first phase in
any search project cannot be overempha¬
sized. The inexpensive hours spent in librar¬
ies and archives can save many expensive
and difficult hours searching on the water.
A survivor's report that "the wreck is lo¬
cated in two fathoms of water, two leagues
south of the river mouth" may sound like a
good lead until the researcher learns that a
"league" has meant different things in diffe¬
rent times and places, and the river mouth,
not to mention the position of the beach
itself, may have moved a great distance in
the time since the original disaster. A se¬
rious student of the art will learn much
about the history of how one measures
time, distance, and position.
The most commonly used instruments for
searching in the oceans are the side-scan
sonar, the sub-bottom profiler, and the
magnetometer. These generally can be
called high tech. Other methods, just as
good, fall under the categories low tech, no
The manned deep-water submersible
Alvin, of the Woods Hole Océanographie
Institution (USA), with its mother ship,
Atlantis II. In 1986 Alvin explored the
wreck of the Titanic 4,000 metres beneath
the North Atlantic. Much advanced tech¬
nology is available for marine archaeology
but its use on a routine basis is often
limited because of prohibitive costs.
m
i
.émr	,
alia
**>
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ï
CO
o
16
tech, and plumb luck. The great majority of
finds have resulted from methods as simple
as talking to local sponge divers, or spend¬
ing long hours in a small boat with a hand-
operated coring device.
Side-scan sonars and sub-bottom profil¬
ers are acoustic devices that use sound
waves to produce a hard-copy, graphic re¬
cord of the sea floor and underlying
sediments. Both instruments are portable
and utilize battery power. They can be
operated from small boats, thus making it
possible to mount search operations in diffi¬
cult or remote locations.
In the side-scan sonar, a torpedo-shaped
"towfish" transmits pulses of high-frequen¬
cy sound (50 to 500 kilohertz) out to both
sides. The pulses are transmitted in a nar¬
row beam in the horizontal plane, giving
good resolution, and a broad beam in the
vertical plane, providing wide coverage.
Sound is returned to the sonar from the
texture of the sea floor and by reflections
from targets. The returns from successive
pulses are printed side by side on the paper
record, producing a very detailed view of
the sea floor, similar to an aerial photo¬
graph. A side-scan can produce an image of
the sea floor more than 300 metres out on
both sides of the tow path.
Side-scan sonar produces a detailed
graphic image of the surface of the sea floor.
Areas of rock, sand, mud, or other material
can be distinguished. If an archaeological
site leaves some visible trace on the sea
floor, it can be found by side-scan sonar. If a
wreck is relatively intact, the sonar image
may be clear enough to allow identification
from the sonar record alone. In some cases,
indirect indications, such as a difference in
material type, may be enough to point to a
site location even if no portion of the wreck
itself is exposed. A side-scan sonar unit
cannot detect sites that are completely
buried beneath the sea floor. Extremely
rocky or irregular bottoms can make it hard
to interpret sonar returns.
The sub-bottom profiler utilizes low-fre¬
quency sound (3.5 to 12 kilohertz) to pene¬
trate bottom sediments. A pulse of sound is
directed vertically down into the bottom.
At each interface between different types of
sediment layers some of the sound energy
continues on and some is reflected. As the
device is towed along, a cross-sectional view
of the sea floor is generated, showing the
different layers and the underlying bed¬
rock. If there are buried hull remains, they
can show up as a localized reflection below
the bottom.
A sub-bottom profiler can be used to
locate sites that are completely buried.
Drawing shows 4 methods of geophysical
surveying under water. (1) The proton
magnetometer detects variations in the
earth's magnetic field, which is distorted
by objects of a ferrous nature such as
cannon, iron shot or steel hulls. (2) Side-
scan sonar detects variations of projec¬
tions above the sea-bed. A "fish" towed
behind the boat transmits a fan-shaped
beam of acoustic energy perpendicular to
its path, and rock outcrops, sandwaves,
wrecks and other projections are recorded
on a continuous graph (see front cover).
(3) The sub-bottom profiler is an acoustic
transmitter which sends out into the sea¬
bed sound pulses which bounce back
from underlying strata or buried objects.
All 3 devices, when used simultaneously,
can detect objects lying on or below the
sea-bed and distinguish ferrous and non-
ferrous anomalies, thus helping
archaeologists to distinguish early timber
structures from later metal wrecks. (4)
Another system is the Remotely Operated
Vehicle (ROV). Equipped with low-light
videos and cameras, such highly man¬
oeuvrable unmanned submersibles are
connected to a mother vessel by a cable
through which they receive electricity and
commands from their human pilot and
transmit pictures and data.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
A mosaic of X-ray photos of a concretion
helps to guide a technician in the process
of chipping off the overlay from iron arte¬
facts recovered from a 16th-century ship¬
wreck off the coast of Texas, USA.
Since it looks directly down, it covers only a
narrow path underneath the search vessel.
This makes it an inefficient tool for general
searching. The sub-bottom profiler can be
used effectively to help define the site limits
and geology once the primary location is
found by other means.
In some cases, a magnetometer should be
used either instead of or along with a side-
scan sonar or sub-bottom profiler. The
magnetometer is a passive device that mea¬
sures the strength of the local magnetic
field. It has been the primary search tool for
treasure hunters and others looking for
Spanish vessels in the New World, where
most wrecks are broken up and buried in
sand or coral.
The spinning Earth behaves much like a
bar magnet, with a north and south magne¬
tic pole. At any point on the Earth there will
be some natural magnetic field strength,
influenced by the local geology. Concentra¬
tions of ferrous material such as iron
anchors, cannon, or ships' fittings will al¬
ter that field, producing what is termed a
magnetic anomaly (or variation). It does
not matter whether the iron material is
buried or exposed. The shape and size of
the anomaly give clues to the mass of iron
producing it and the depth of burial.
The unit of measurement of magnetic
field strength is the gamma. The Earth's
natural magnetic field ranges from 30,000
to 60,000 gammas, depending on the loca¬
tion. Modern magnetometers can detect
anomalies in the local field of less than 1
gamma. Although there are several types of
magnetometer available (cesium, rubi
dium, flux-gate), the one most commonly
used for marine search applications is the
proton precession magnetometer. These
units are relatively small, simple and
robust, and are well suited to field oper¬
ations.
A magnetometer consists of a sensor, a
chart recorder, an interconnecting cable,
and a power supply. The units are portable
and are easily adapted to virtually any
search vessel. The sensor is generally towed
behind the search vessel, although for some
shallow-water operations magnetometer
sensors have been mounted on a boom on
the bow of a small boat or even suspended
from a helicopter. A boat that is not made
out of steel is preferred, but any vessel can
be used if there is enough cable to get the
magnetometer out of the of the
vessel's own magnetic field.
The strength of an object's magnetic field
decreases with the cube of the distance from
the object. This means that the magneto¬
meter sensor must be towed relatively close
to the object in order to detect it, depending
of course on the amount of metal involved.
As a rough guide, a large steel wreck can be
detected at a range of 120 to 180 metres, a
site with scattered iron anchors and cannon
at 80 to 100 metres, an isolated iron cannon
at 30 metres, and an individual small iron
object at 3 to 5 metres. Skilled operators are
able to use magnetometer readings to put a
marker buoy directly on top of the source of
an anomaly.
Magnetometers are useful for finding any
site that has iron structures, artefacts, or
associated minerals. Since it does not mat¬
ter whether or how deeply the material is
covered, magnetometers are particularly
appropriate for locating vessels that are
buried or located in areas that are unfavour¬
able for sonar searching.
Magnetometers are not able to detect
non-ferrous materials, so it is necessary as
part of the research process to determine
whether and how much of such material
may be on a site. Bronze cannon, for exam¬
ple, cannot be detected.
With all these search tools, it is vital to
have precision navigation. That is the only
way one can know that the entire search
area has been covered with a reasonable
degree of accuracy. It is also needed to
return to any contacts found with the search
instruments.
The future is already here in terms of
available technology. Computers, sub¬
mersible vehicles, satellite mapping systems
and the like, are in widespread use. It is
their application to marine archaeology that
is somewhat lagging. In large measure, this
can be attributed to the prohibitive cost of
using these systems on a routine basis.
The major change in search technology is
likely to be an increasing success rate for
site location. The basic technology is in a
relatively advanced state of development.
Continued advances will be made in select¬
ing the best equipment for a job and car¬
rying out the search properly. As the equip¬
ment and techniques are refined, they will
play an important role in site identification,
as opposed to simply site location.
Aerial and satellite imaging, whether by
photography or multi-spectral imaging, will
be more widely used. Satellite images have
already disclosed previously unknown reef
structures and sandbars that might contain
shipwreck sites. Shipwrecks can sometimes
be seen in high-altitude photographs.
Photography using optimized film/filter
combinations could maximize water
penetration and bottom contrast.
Pulsed lasers are being used ex¬
perimentally, to make hydrographie
measurements from aircraft. As the tech¬
nology advances, it will become possible to
survey large areas of the bottom at pre¬
viously unheard-of rates. Anomalies will be
found that are caused by shipwreck sites.
The possibility of finding shipwrecks in
deep water has been recognized since the
1960s. Under the right conditions, wood
and other organic materials suffer little de¬
terioration at great depths.
The future will see continued progress in
the ability to locate such sites. More impor¬
tantly, technology will provide the means to
investigate such sites more efficiently. Un¬
manned, remotely operated vehicles have
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
already performed television and photo¬
graphic inspections of several sites. One-
atmosphere diving "suits" now commonly
used in the offshore oil industry provide the
archaeologist with direct access to sites at
ever-increasing depths, with no danger of
decompression sickness.
Improvements also continue to be made
in the ability to document sites rapidly and
accurately. New film and camera technolo¬
gies make it easier to obtain high-quality
photographs for documentation.
A new mapping system is currently
undergoing field trials. It promises to great¬
ly reduce, the time needed to make,
measurements. The system uses acoustic
signals to replace measuring tapes. The
diver holds a wand-like device wherever he
wants a measurement. When he pulls a
trigger, acoustic pulses travel out to receiv¬
ers at carefully surveyed locations. The
travel time of the pulses is converted into a
distance measurement by a computer on the
surface, which then calculates the location
of the point in space. To achieve the neces¬
sary accuracy of less than a centimetre, the
system must continually measure and adjust
for the speed of sound in the water. The
equipment is compact and portable. The
system is so fast and accurate that the diver
can sign his name on the computer screen
simply by holding down the trigger and
"writing" with the wand.
As computers become smaller, cheaper,
and more powerful, they are increasingly
being used in the field of underwater
archaeology. This is not to say that
archaeologists have not been using com¬
puters. University mainframe computers
have been used for a number of years for
archaeological database management
storing, sorting, analysing and displaying
information on artefacts and sites. The data
are brought in from the field on standard
reporting forms. Recently, however, more
and more archaeologists have been taking
either terminals or small computers into the
field so that data can be sent back to the
mainframe computer over telephone lines
on a daily basis.
With the advent of portable, battery-
powered microcomputers, field uses are
starting to go far beyond simple cataloguing
tasks. Underwater measurements can be
entered into the computer on site to be
converted into useful co-ordinates for im¬
mediate plotting or display on a graphics
screen. This provides both on-the-spot
error checking and a tool for site planning.
The role of computers as an integral part of
archaeological fieldwork is one that should
show rapid development in the next few
years.
CHARLES MAZEL, of the USA, is an ocean
engineer who is technical director of the non¬
profit Maritime Archaeological and Historical Re¬
search Unit, based in Maine. He is presently a
consultant on ocean survey and electronics pro¬
jects and is developing new equipment for under¬
water photography. This article was first pub¬
lished in Oceanus magazine (vol. 28, no. 1,
Spring 1985) published by the Woods Hole
Océanographie Institution, Massachusetts.
Colour page opposite
A sunken ship is a "time capsule" of life at
sea, frozen at a moment in the past.
These 3 photos show a silver pocket watch
recovered by Australian archaeologists
from the remains of HMS Pandora, which "
foundered on Australia's Great Barrier
Reef on 29 August 1791 with the loss of 35
men. Pandora had been sent to Tahiti in
1790 by the British Admiralty to capture
the mutineers who had seized HMS Bounty
the previous year and "bring them to con¬
dign punishment". She went down on her
return voyage to England with 14
mutineers manacled inside a deckhouse
cell.
The watch, thought to have belonged to
the ship's surgeon because it had a
second hand useful for taking a patient's
pulse, was brought up in a wet container.
An X-ray showed that most of its works
were still intact. It had stopped at 12 min¬
utes and 20 seconds past 11. Pandora
sank at 6:30 A.M. and so the watch may
have been stopped by the shock of impact
when the ship hit the reef the night before
or by rising waters when she began to fill.
Remarkably preserved, the watch was
conserved and restored by Jon Carpenter,
conservator of the Pandora expedition,
and rebuilt nearly to working condition
(below right) by an antiquarian watch¬
maker, Hugh Whitwell.
Photo © Patrick Baker/Western Australian Maritime Museum
Photo © Jon Carpenter/Western Australian Maritime Museum
Photo © Jim Brandenburg, Minneapolis
Centre colour pages
4
6
9
12
2
7
10
13
3 14
Photos on this double page spread show
some of the processes and techniques of
underwater archaeology today, from sur¬
veying and excavation to conservation.
1. Laying down the line. Before excava¬
tions can take place, an accurate survey of
the site is made to record archaeological
material and the environmental situation.
Site planning before and during excava¬
tion is usually done with the aid of a site
grid made using poles or line (see also
photo page 28).
2. Making measurements. Detailed site
plans often involve measuring the posi¬
tion of objects by taking the distance at
right angles to the main grid line. The diver
at right is carefully noting the distances.
3. By swimming along lines strung be¬
tween two fixed points, divers can inspect
the sea-bed for archaeological material.
Intensive surveying and plotting with re¬
covery of selected items for dating evi¬
dence can identify new sites worthy of
further investigation.
4. Underwater vacuum cleaners called air¬
lifts are commonly used to remove sedi¬
ment from the site. They come in all sizes.
The equivalent of the wheelbarrow on
land, they should only be used to remove
sediment and not the evidence embedded
in it.
5. The rim of a pot gradually appears as
divers carefully remove the topmost layer
of sediment with a vacuum hose. The di¬
ver's hand is the most sensitive working
tool of all.
6. Drawing underwater is done with an
ordinary pencil on a sheet of underwater
drawing film. Meticulous records need to
be made of archaeological sites under wa¬
ter just as on land, since all archaeology is
destructive. Once the excavation is com¬
plete the only record is that produced on
paper and film.
7. Stereophotogrammetry (making plans
by computer from stereophotographs)
may be used to produce a 3-dimensional
record of parts of a site or even of com¬
plete hulls.
8. Underwater archaeologists are not soie-
ly concerned with shipwrecks. They also
explore sites once occupied by prehistoric
man in inland waters or submerged on the
continental shelf. Here, divers record data
and prepare to recover a mastodon tusk
from a North Florida river.
9. Archaeologists and divers working at
great depths face the danger of decom¬
pression sickness, commonly known as
"the bends", which can kill or paralyse.
Photo shows a submersible decompress¬
ion chamber (SDC) used at Yassi Ada (Tur¬
key) in the late 1 960s by George Bass and a
team from the University of Pennsylvania.
By allowing four divers at a time to de¬
compress, the SDC permitted longer daily
dives.
1 0. A diver uses a pneumatic saw to cut off
a piece of the hull of a wreck off Gabon for
study ashore.
11. Air-filled bags are used for raising
heavy objects to the surface.
12. Deep water sites are now becoming
accessible thanks to technological de¬
velopments in the field of off-shore en¬
gineering. Here, a diver clad in a revolu¬
tionary "wearable" submarine. Such
equipment circumvents decompression
problems.
13. The Bremen Cog. Reassembly of this
medieval ship from about 2,000 pieces of
waterlogged timber took 7 years.
14. Inside the hull of the Sohar, a full-size
replica of a medieval Arab ship (see photo
story page 23). The workmen are using
mops dipped in vegetable oil to preserve
the coir (rope made of hand-twisted coco¬
nut fibres) used to lash the ship's timbers
together.
1 . Photo © M. Little; 2. Photo © Charles Hood; 3. Photo © Jon
Adams; 4. Photo © Nils Aukan, Stavanger, Norway. 5. Photo Bill
Curtsinger © 1987 National Geographic Society/Photo Resear¬
chers; 6. Photo Xavier Desmier © CEDRI, Paris; 7. Photo Claude
Rives © MARINA-CEDRI, Paris; 8. Photo © James Dunbar,
Florida Bureau of Archeology; 9. Photo Flip Schulke © Rapho,
Paris; 1 0. Photo Xavier Desmier © MARINA-CEDRI, Paris; 1 1 .
Photo © M. Little; 12. Photo Emory Kristof © 1983 National
Geographic Society, Washington, D.C.; 13. Photo © Deutsches
Schitlahrtsmuseum, Bremerhaven, Fed. Rep. of Germany; 14.
Photo Bruce Foster © Tim Severin-Sindbad Voyage
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
i
T
M
\
WM
*
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
1
Bt'è
\ "V
- : J.: \-\
* -
a.
VAÄ
3NÈ j
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Fair copies
Modern replicas
ofancient vessels
The sea trials of full-scale replicas of a num¬
ber of ancient ships have successfully de¬
monstrated the seaworthiness of early craft
as well as contributed to our knowledge of
naval construction techniques and the art of
navigation. (1) In 1987, for the first time in
over 2,000 years, a trireme of the Greek
navy cut through the waters of the
Mediterranean. The trireme, a reputedly
invincible, fast and manoeuvrable warship
with three tiers of oarsmen on each side, was
fundamental to the naval strength ofAncient
Greece. The modern replica, named Olym¬
pia, was built in a Greek naval shipyard to a
design by a team of British researchers. As
no remains of a trireme have ever been
found, the designers relied on descriptions
by classical writers, surviving illustrations
of the ships, and experience gained from
other ancient shipwrecks. The warship, 37
m long and over 5 m broad, displaces 1.5 m
ofwater for 45 tons weight and is armed with
a bronze ram at the bow. She soon showed
her paces, reaching a speed of 7 knots in her
first sea trials, propelled by a crew of almost
200 rowers. Use of the trireme will lead to a
better understanding of the tactics employed
by the Ancient Greek fleet. The Sohar (see
colour page left) is a replica of an 8th-cen-
tury Arab trading ship or boom. In this
vessel, with a crew including 8 Omani sea¬
men, navigator Tim Severin made a 7-
month voyage of almost 10,000 km, from
Muscat to Canton, following the route of
Sindbad, the legendary Arab sailor and hero
of The Thousand and One Nights. (2) Tim
Severin uses an early Arab navigation in¬
strument, the kamal. A wooden rectangle
pierced by a knotted string, the kamal is a
kind of sextant for calculating latitude from
the position of a selected star above the
horizon. (3) The Kyrenia II, an authentic
replica of a Greek merchantman which went
down off Kyrenia (Cyprus) 2,300 years ago,
is the culmination of a 20-year research
programme carried out on the wrecked ship
under the direction of the Institute of Nautic¬
al Archaeology (INA). The Kyrenia Ship
(see also page 14) is the best preserved vessel
of its period yet found. Thanks to knowledge
gained during the long and painstaking re¬
construction of the ship, which can be seen
today in the city of Kyrenia, a replica was
built in a Greek shipyard, using ancient
techniques. The 14-m-long Kyrenia II has
already made several successful voyages.
Colour page left
Above: Sohar
Photo Richard Greenhill 0 I Tim Severin-Sindbad Voyage
Far left: a Roman warehouse in the west¬
ern dock of the submerged harbour of the
ancient city of Apollonia, Libyan Arab
Jamahiriya (see page 38).
Left: central quarter of Apollonia and the
harbour
Photos © André Laronde
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Law and the underwater heritage
by Lyndel V. Prott
and Patrick J. O'Keefe
*****
24
AN international consensus is de¬
veloping that States should take
special steps to ensure the protec¬
tion of their underwater heritage. Apart
from international agreements by which
States have undertaken actively to ensure
the protection of the cultural heritage
generally, such as the European Conven¬
tion on the Protection of the Archaeological
Heritage; Unesco Convention for the Pro¬
tection of Cultural Property in the Event of
Armed Conflict; Unesco Convention on the
Means of Prohibiting and Preventing the
Illicit Import, Export and Transfer of Own¬
ership of Cultural Property; Unesco Con¬
vention Concerning the Protection of the
World Cultural and Natural Heritage; OAS
(Organization of American States) Con¬
vention on the Protection of the Archaeolo¬
gical, Historical and Artistic Heritage of the
American Nations, there is also a Unesco
Recommendation which deals specifically
with the underwater cultural heritage. This
is the Recommendation on International
Principles Applicable to Archaeological
Excavations (1956). It applies to "any re¬
search aimed at the discovery of objects of
archaeological character" whether on land
"or on the bed or in the subsoil of inland or
territorial waters of a Member State".
The Recommendation includes some de¬
tailed provisions on the control of excava¬
tions, the admission of foreigners for
archaeological work, the keeping of a cen¬
tral register of important sites, the forma¬
tion of collections, disposal of finds, rights
and duties of the excavator, documentation
of excavations and the suppression of clan¬
destine excavations. The Recommenda¬
tion, according to the Constitution and
Rules of Procedure of Unesco, obliges
Member States of Unesco to implement it
and to report the methods taken to give
effect to it. European and other States
bordering the Mediterranean should also be
aware of a major initiative of the Council of
Europe to strengthen legal protection of the
underwater cultural heritage in the Euro¬
pean and Mediterranean areas.
In studying all these materials, States
may not only feel a responsibility or an
obligation to legislate promptly on this
issue, but will also find guidance as to the
type of provisions that should be included.
There are two legislation schemes which
have been very widely used to provide
permanent legal protection: these are, first,
the extension of general antiquities legisla¬
tion to underwater finds and, second, the
drafting of special legislation solely to cover
submarine antiquities (meaning those
under the sea) or other antiquities under
water where these are significant. Certain
schemes have been based on the extension
of other types of legislation to cover the
underwater cultural heritage: most of these
appear to have some disadvantage.
The major advantage in having specific
legislation on the underwater cultural herit¬
age is the practical one of easy accessibility.
For the most part, those who do damage to
shipwrecks are divers, fishermen or em¬
ployees of oil or cable-laying companies
involved in underwater operations. Many
of these have little legal knowledge.
Divers, both amateur and professional,
and particularly those interested in ship¬
wrecks, are often said to be of independent
character, resourceful and sceptical of au¬
thority. They come from a variety of back¬
grounds, from the highly educated to the
lowly. Nevertheless, they have a common
tendency to regard what they find under
water as their own, a product of their skill
and effort and something that only they can
work on, by whatever means they consider
fit. It is important to seek their co-operation
and not to arouse their resentment.
On the other hand, fishermen in most
cases do damage by dragging their nets
along the sea bottom, scattering surface
remains and obliterating sites, as well as
raising objects in their nets. In recent years,
the surveying and trenching of the sea floor
for pipelines or cables has led to the unin¬
tentional discovery of many wrecks. It is
important that such finds be reported and
identified, and requirements to that effect
should be written into every national permit
system.
Philippines law provides that any
accidental discoveries made "in the course
of agricultural and engineering works,
mineral and marine explorations" shall be
reported and further work immediately sus¬
pended. Norway and Thailand have also
expressly created a duty to report for such
operators. In all cases, the best protection
of the underwater cultural heritage lies in
education and in persuasion of the diver,
fisherman, oil worker or cable layer of the
cultural value of what is found or noticed.
This will be done most easily if reference
can be made to a single piece of legislation
which is easily accessible physically and
associated by name: one in which rights and
duties are set out concisely, without ambi¬
guity or the need to refer to other legal
provisions.
The extension of general antiquities leg
islation to the underwater cultural heritage
is an alternative which has been adopted by
some States which already have compre¬
hensive legislation on land antiquities (e.g.
Greece and Turkey). There is no legal
reason why the cover provided by general
antiquities legislation should not be as
strong: the advantages of specific legislation
are, as we have mentioned, practical ones.
There are a number of other States that
have not made the extension specifically
" but whose system of classification and pro¬
tection would be suitable to cover impor¬
tant finds. Such an extension of existing
legislation would not, however, ensure
accessibility and publicity. Nor is this pat¬
tern of action helpful where general anti¬
quities legislation is not so well developed.
Although many States have comprehen¬
sive legislation to protect the underwater
cultural heritage, and even those that do not
have other legislative weapons in hand to
protect them from the spoliator, the cultu¬
ral authorities should not become com¬
placent. Many will recognize that there are
much stronger provisions that could be
and should be included in their national
legislation. This is an urgent task for all
national cultural authorities in countries
where the underwater cultural heritage is
under threat. There are two other impor¬
tant tasks which would increase legal pro¬
tection: one, the signing of international
agreements on this subject; the other, the
requiring of all those working on the sea¬
bed for any purpose to observe and report
finds of interest. The best level of protec¬
tion will be achieved by a judicious blend of
strong legal provisions and an effort to
make people everywhere aware of the incal¬
culable value of the cultural inheritance of
man.
LYNDEL V. PROTT is Reader in International
Law and Jurisprudence at the University of Syd¬
ney, where her husband, PATRICK J.
O'KEEFE, is Senior Lecturer in Law. They are
co-authors of a report for the Council of Europe
on legal protection of the underwater cultural
heritage (1978), and are currently engaged on a
majorproject to collect, analyse and comment on
national and international laws on the protection
of the cultural heritage round the world. The
results of their research will eventually be pub¬
lished in 5 volumes, the first of which, Law and
the Cultural Heritage, appeared in 1983
(Professional Books, Abingdon, UK). The above
article is an extract from "Law and the underwa¬
ter heritage ", a chapter which they contributed to
Protection ot the Underwater Heritage, a collec¬
tive work published by Unesco in 1981.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Looting of ancient shipwrecks is widespread.
How can it be stopped?
IE
The amphora war
MORE than 2,000 years ago, Greek
and Roman galleys sailed the
Mediterranean Sea loaded with
goods for trade or soldiers for conquest.
Today, off the coasts of Italy, Spain, and
France, hundreds of these ancient ship¬
wrecks, sunk for centuries, are being pi¬
rated by clandestine salvagers and deep-sea
divers. In the past twenty years in France
alone almost 400 shipwrecks from the
Greek and Roman eras have been found.
All but three had been pillaged before being
discovered by the authorities.
The statues, art works, precious metals
and amphoras found on these ships supply
an international market of private buyers.
The publicity surrounding the volume of
this trade, soaring prices, the aggressive
promotion by auction houses, and con-
- tinued record-breaking sums have done
much to promote this illegal traffic. And it
has led to violence. Rival gangs are known
to have burned each other's boats, and over
twenty divers, some very experienced, have
been found dead due to dangerous clandes¬
tine working conditions in deep water or
outright murder. In the South of France
they call it the Amphora War.
For hundreds of years, men tried to in¬
vent ways of getting to sunken ships with
little or no success. With the invention of
the scuba tank, a practical solution was
found.
It was one of the inventors of the scuba
tank, Jacques Cousteau, who excavated the
first ancient ship from the sea floor. In 1954,
diving down 60 metres off the Grand Con-
gloué island in the Mediterranean near the
city of Marseilles he found an ancient Ro¬
man shipwreck sunk in the second century
BC. Two thousand amphoras were disco¬
vered on the ship. Cousteau's divers simply
raised them to the surface and drew no
plans of the site, but this first expedition led
to the birth of underwater archaeology.
On land, wholesale plundering of ancient
artefacts had been going on since the eight¬
eenth century. Today, treasure hunters
spend more time searching under the sea
than on land.
In France, the police responsible for en¬
forcement of the laws protecting under¬
water archaeological sites are under the
authority of the Customs Service. With a
fleet of 20 boats, 12 helicopters and 3 aero¬
planes, the Customs agents regularly patrol
the areas of known underwater archaeolo¬
gical sites. Aircraft Spottings are reported
to patrol boats that are equipped with radar
and armed with sub-machine guns. But. as
Commandant Rivière, head of Customs
from the Mediterranean coastline from Ita¬
ly to the Spanish border and the island of
Corsica, has pointed out, "... The fight to
prevent the pirating of underwater wrecks
is only a small part of our activity because
our main job is aimed against drugs and
terrorists. T|
"Guarding underwater archaeological
wrecks is very difficult because there are a
lot of wreck sites and it is impossible to put a
Customs officer on every site, and if you are
not there to catch someone red handed
bringing up an artefact, then most probably
the pirate cannot be prosecuted."
The major problems facing the preserva¬
tion of ancient shipwreck sites are the ex¬
pense of an excavation, the tedious weeks at
sea, around-the-clock security to protect
the site from pirates, and the health dangers
of decompression from repeated deep-wa¬
ter diving. Since diving can be done only
seven months a year off the coast of France ,
unfinished excavations must be buried in
hundreds of tons of sand to protect them
from pirates during the winter months, and
then painstakingly uncovered the following
year before new work can begin.
m
This text has been extracted from the script of a
new video programme entitled Amphora War. A
Unesco-Cross Communications Europe co-pro¬
duction, the 26-minute video reviews the ques¬
tion of piracy of amphoras and other artefacts off
the coast of southern France and the measures
being taken by Unesco for the protection of the
underwater heritage. For further information
about the video, which exists in English and
French versions, please apply to: Division of
Audiovisual Productions, Unesco, 7 Place de
Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Investigation of a 17th-century man-of-war in the Baltic
by Lars Einarsson
T
| HE Swedish man of war HMS Kro-
nan ("The Royal Crown") was lost
in battle off the coast of south-east
Sweden on 1 June 1676. Her keel had been
laid in 1665 and she had been launched in
1668, entering service four years later in
1672. The first three-decked ship built in
Sweden, she displaced 2,140 tons. Her
length was 55 metres, and she carried 126
cannons. At the time of the disaster her
crew consisted of approximately 850 men.
In the mid-seventeenth century, Sweden
was a great power with the general strategic
ambition of controlling the Baltic Sea and
the shores around it, thus creating a closed
inner sea a "Mare Claustrum". In 1675
the Swedish provinces on continental
Europe were attacked by Brandenburg. In
the same year, war broke out between
Denmark and Sweden, and in the spring of
1676 the Swedish navy set sail for the south¬
ern Baltic in order to find and destroy the
Danish fleet which was ravaging the Swed¬
ish islands.
The first battle between the enemy fleets
was fought between the islands of
Bornholm and Rügen during the night of 25
May. In spite of the Swedish superiority in
numbers, the Danes escaped, and were a
few days later joined by a Dutch squadron.
The Dutch became a Danish ally to prevent
Sweden gaining total control of the
Baltic.
The Swedes had acted in confusion dur¬
ing the battle, and consequently the king
ordered the fleet to seek battle closer to the
Swedish mainland, hoping that a possible
disaster could be avoided if the ships could
seek refuge in Swedish ports.
On the morning of 1 June 1676, the Swed¬
ish fleet, over sixty ships strong, was sailing
northwards in a southwesterly gale along
the coast of Oland. Off the village of Hul-
terstad, the Svärdet ("The Royal Sword"),
the flagship of the second squadron, fired a
gunshot either as a signal to call the fleet
closer together, or as a request to turn
against the enemy who were closing up from
behind.
Without responding to the Svärdet's shot,
the Kronan turned with the wind without
taking in sail. Suddenly, the ship heeled
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Jewelsfrom the
Crown
over and began to capsize. The crew tried
desperately to pull the guns in through the
gunports, but in vain. The ship capsized,
and shortly afterwards was shaken by an
explosion in which the starboard side was
blown to pieces. Within a few minutes, the
Kronan had sunk with the loss of 800 lives.
Only forty men survived the disaster.
The wreck of the Kronan caused total
confusion in the Swedish fleet. Only a few
ships remained to continue the battle,
among them the Svärdet, which fought
heroically for several hours before being set
on fire by a fireship. The result of the battle
was disastrous for the Swedes: the loss of
the two largest ships in the Swedish navy
and 1,500 seamen.
In the 1950s, Anders Franzen began a
programme to find twelve Swedish men-of-
war sunk in the Baltic in the sixteenth and
seventeenth centuries. Franzen had real¬
ized that because of climatic and other natu¬
ral conditions, the Baltic is a treasure-house
for the underwater archaeologist.
First of- all, the Baltic is within the con¬
tinental shelf area and only parts of it are
Pieces of richly carved woodwork are
among the most notable finds made dur¬
ing excavations of the Kronan. Left, a cher¬
ub from the admiral's quarters photo¬
graphed as it lay among the wreckage.
Above left and right, another wooden cher¬
ub from the Kronan.
deeper than 100 metres. Both the coastal
waters and large areas of the sea bottom are
accessible for ordinary diving up to a
depth of 50 metres. Secondly, wood-des¬
troying organisms such as shipworm
(Teredo navalis) are less prevalent than in
warmer, saltier waters such as the
Mediterranean. In fact the whole of the
Baltic is free of damage by shipworm.
In 1956, Franzen discovered the Wasa in
the waters of Stockholm harbour where she
had sunk at the start of her maiden voyage
in 1628. After an unprecedented rescue
operation the Wasa was raised from the
sea-bed and towed away to a museum site in
1961 (see page 14).
In 1980, after making a systematic survey
including the use of side-scan sonar, proton-
magnetometer and low-light television,
Franzen and his team discovered the Kro¬
nan just over 6 nautical miles off the east
coast of Oland, at a depth of 26 metres.
The first sight which met the divers was
that of a broken wreck, not a Wasa. But the
sediments of the site would later prove to
contain thousands of artefacts originally be¬
longing to the crew, representing a seven¬
teenth century in miniature encapsulated
and deep frozen at noon on 1 June 1676.
In 1981, archaeological investigation of
the Kronan began, supervised by the Kal¬
mar County Museum. The investigated cen¬
tral area of the wrecksite is divided into
twenty squares of 10 metres a side. The
squares comprise a system of co-ordinates,
each corner being marked with a white
cross and identified with a letter-number
combination. These codes are needed to
Right, artist's impression of the Kronan.
The drawing, by Admiral Jacob Hägg, was
made in 1906. 27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
describe the location of a recovered object
and are also helpful in photographic and
search-work.
A further refinement in excavation is the
use of a portable plastic grid, divided into
squares. The grid as a whole is fitted into
the general system of co-ordinates before
excavation is begun, and then makes the
work of describing the location of recovered
artefacts easier. This method is used in
combination with triangular measuring and
has proved to be efficient at this stage of the
excavation.
The actual excavation work is done with
an airlift, a sort of underwater vacuum
cleaner. It uses compressed air to draw up
the sediment, thus revealing objects and
parts of the ship, by preventing everything
from being obscured in a cloud of mud. The
divers pick up the objects recovered in this
way, while the sediment, sand and gravel
drawn up with the compressed air are sieved
on deck, so that smaller objects are also
recovered.
Important aids in the underwater docu¬
mentation process are waterproof sketching
equipment, underwater cameras and
perhaps most important an underwater
video camera. Documenting the excava¬
tions with low-light video is a very conve¬
nient method of obtaining maximum input
of immediate visual information at a re¬
latively low cost. Communication between
divers and the surface is carried out by diver
telephone.
Excavating and documenting the port side
of the Kronan, which lies flat on the sea¬
bed. The plastic grid divided into squares
enables the location of objects to be pre¬
cisely recorded. Upright forms in back¬
ground are broken deck-beams.
The divers use only dry-suits, meaning
they wear insulating overalls under their
diving suits and remain dry. This prevents
the diver from being exposed to the cold
waters of the Baltic, which seldom exceeds
8°C at this depth. This is a most important
safety measure.
Diving time at a depth of 26 metres with
compressed air is relatively limited. Each
diver does two descents a day, with an
effective diving time of from 50 to 70
minutes, depending on whether decom¬
pression in water is being used.
When the excavations began in 1981, the
first method used was to dig test-pits in
strategic areas of the wreck-site, in order to
determine the area of the find and the ship's
constructional elements. The archaeolog¬
ists immediately realized that a tremendous
number of artefacts were preserved in the
sediment and, thanks to the wood-preserv¬
ing conditions of the Baltic, noticed the
remarkable richness of the exposed parts of
the ship. Kronan clearly offered a unique
opportunity to study life on board a big
seventeenth-century battleship.
In 1984, after three seasons of excava¬
tions, a new method succeeded the test-pit
Plate and jugs from the Kronan
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
method. Continuous, systematic excava¬
tion starting from identified constructions
on the port side began. The choice of
method was based on the knowledge
obtained from the previous tests, which led
to a theory concerning the deterioration
process and the present state of the wreck.
At the time of the disaster, Kronan was
heading north in a strong south-western
gale. The ship turned with full sails, heeled
over on her port side, capsized and turned
around in the wind. This is proved by the
ship's position on the sea-bed. The great
explosion in the powder-storage room must
have blown the entire starboard side away,
since this was the direction of the shock-
wave. The vessel probably broke athwart-
ships at this stage, forward of the main
mast, which explains the absence of the
bow. Thus, approximately two-thirds of the
length of the port side, from the stern for-
"ward, is preserved.
After the explosion, Kronan sank rapid¬
ly. When she reached the sea floor, she
immediately rested on her port side. This is
indicated by in situ findings of internal port
side sculptures, originally decorating the
walls of the admiral's quarters, astern on
the upper gun-deck. The sculptures were
originally nailed to the wall with iron nails,
which rusted away soon after the ship¬
wreck. The sculptures still remain in their
original positions.
One consequence of this must be that the
external sculptures of the port side stern
castle are also likely to be still in their
original positions, embedded in the anaero¬
bic, glacial clay. We hope that future ex¬
cavations will prove this.
Since she was the first three-decked ship
ever built in Sweden, Kronan is likely to
show unique constructional details. Some
interesting features have already been
This carved wooden head was placed on
the sterncastle of the Kronan to frighten
the enemy.
observed. However, the outstanding asset
of Kronan is the tremendous richness of the
artefacts found on her. As of 1986, approx¬
imately 15 per cent of the area of the wreck-
site had been excavated. More than 12,000
artefacts have been salvaged. They range
from everyday utensils, personal belong¬
ings, weaponry, navigational instruments,
sculpture, and musical instruments to a
medicine chest and the largest find of gold
coins ever made in Sweden.
Perhaps the most interesting finds are the
sculptures which are in remarkably good
condition. One can still see in detail how the
artist has shaped the piece of wood with his
tools. The relatively gentle conservation
process of freeze-drying ensures that the
original features of the wooden sculptures
remain. The reconstruction of the sculptu¬
ral features of the Kronan is one of the
greatest achievements of the investigation.
Since the excavation began, a Kronan
exhibition has been open to the public at the
Kalmar County Museum. More than
200,000 people have seen the exhibition so
far.
Apart from the main archaeological pur¬
pose of the Kronan investigations, the site
has also become a melting pot for interna¬
tional underwater archaeology. Each year
marine archaeologists from different coun¬
tries and institutions are invited to take part
in the work and exchange experiences. The
Baltic in general, and Kronan in particular,
offer a unique opportunity for underwater
archaeological work under extremely good
conditions.
LARS EINARSSON is curator of the Kalmar
County Museum, Sweden, and chief
archaeologist of the Kronan project.
The Convention on the Law of the Sea
and marine archaeology
Adopted on 30April 1982 by the United
Nations Conference on the Law of the
Sea (by 130 votes to 4, with 17 absten¬
tions) the Convention on the Law ofthe
Sea lays down rules for all parts and
virtually alt uses ofthe oceans. Articles
149 and 303, the texts of which are
given below, relate specifically to
archaeology.
Article 149
Archaeological and historical objects
All objects of an archaeological and
historical nature found in the Area*
shall be preserved or disposed of for
the benefit of mankind as a whole,
particular regard being paid to the
preferential rights of the State or
country of origin, or the State of
cultural origin, or the State of histor¬
ical and archaeological origin.
Article 303
Archaeological and
historical objects found at sea
1. States have the duty to protect ob¬
jects ofan archaeological and historic¬
al nature found at sea and shall co¬
operate for this purpose.
2. In order to control traffic in such
objects, the coastal State may, in ap¬
plying article 33**, presume that their
removal from the sea-bed in the zone
referred to in that article without its
approval would result in an infringe¬
ment within its territory or territorial
sea of the laws and- regulations re¬
ferred to in that article.
3. Nothing in this article affects the
rights of identifiable owners, the law
of salvage or other rules of admiralty,
or laws and practices with respect to
cultural exchanges.
4. This article is without prejudice to
other international agreements and
rules of international law regarding
the protection of objects of an
archaeological and historical nature.
* Article 1
Use of terms and scope
1. For the purposes of this «invention:
(1) "Area" means the sea-bed and ocean floor
and subsoil thereof, beyond the limits of
national jurisdiction;
" Article 33
Contiguous zone
1. In a zone contiguous to its territorial sea
described as the contiguous zone, the coastal
State may exercise the control necessary to:
(a) prevent infringement of its customs,
fiscal, immigration or sanitary laws and reg¬
ulations within its territory or territorial sea;
(b) punish infringement of the above laws
and regulations committed within its terri¬
tory or territorial sea.
2. The contiguous zone may not extend
beyond 24 nautical miles from the baselines
from which the breadth of the territorial sea is
measured. 29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
o
©
*
o
Ancient Caesarea, now submerged beneath the Mediterranean,
was an amazing feat of engineering
by Avner Raban Herod's great harbour
30
/ tOW King Herod observed a
* f^^l place near the sea, which was
A. ^ very proper for containing a
city, and was before called Strato's Tower.
... and what was the greatest and most
laborious work of all, he adorned it with a
haven that was always free from the waves
of the sea. ... The king, by the expenses he
was at, and the liberal disposal of them,
overcame nature and built the haven larger
than at Piraeus and it had towards the city a
double station for the ships. It was of excel¬
lent workmanship: and this was more re¬
markable for its being built in a place that of
itself was not suitable to such noble struc¬
tures, but was brought to perfection by
materials from other places, and at very
great expense. This city is situated in
Phoenicia, in the passage to Egypt, between
Jaffo and Dor, which are lesser maritime
cities and not fit for havens, on account of
the impetuous south-west winds that beat
upon them, which rolling the sands that
come from the sea gainst the shores do not
admit of ships lying in their station; but the
merchants are generally forced there to ride
at their anchors in the sea itself. So Herod
endeavoured to rectify this inconvenience,
and laid out a compass towards the land as
might be sufficient for a haven, wherein the
great ships might lie down in safety; and this
he effected by letting down vast stones into
twenty fathoms of water, most of them
being fifty feet in length, and nine in height
and ten in breadth, and some still larger.
But when the haven was filled up to that
length, he enlarged that wall which was thus
already extant above the sea, till it was two
hundred feet wide; one hundred of which
had buildings before it, in order to break the
force of the waves; but the rest of the space
was under a stone wall that ran around it.
The name of Pilatus (Pontius Pilate), the e
Roman procurator who tried Jesus Christ, |
is carved on this stone found at Caesarea, g
It may once have been affixed to a temple. J
On this wall were very large towers. ...
There was also a great number of arches
where mariners dwelt. There was also be¬
fore them, a quay (or landing place), which
ran round the entire haven, and was a most
agreeable walk to such as had a mind to that
exercise; but the entrance or mouth of the
port was made on the north quarter, on
which side was the stillest of the winds of all
this place. ... At the mouth of the haven
were on each side three great Colossi sup¬
ported by pillars, where those Colossi that
are on your left hand as you sail into the port
are supported by a solid tower; but those on
the right hand are supported by two upright
stones joined together, which stones were
larger than that tower which was on the
other side of the entrance."
These words were written almost 2,000
years ago by the Jewish historian Josephus
Flavius and constitute what may be the most
detailed description of an ancient harbour.
In 1975 this hidden wonder of ancient hyd¬
raulic technology began to be studied by the
Centre for Maritime Studies of the Uni¬
versity of Haifa, and since 1980 the project
has been carried out by the Caesarea
Ancient Harbour Excavations Project, with
the participation of the universities of Col¬
orado, Maryland and Victoria (British Col¬
umbia). Every summer, over one hundred
diving volunteers from all over the world,
directed by a large staff of marine
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
3**
-w**&
Opposite page: artist's reconstruction of
the ancient harbour of Caesarea. Above:
highly ingenious techniques were used to
construct the reinforced parts of the
breakwaters, which were anchored with
concrete blocks, some weighing 50 tons.
Wooden forms were towed into position
(centre), then sunk (above right) and pack¬
ed with waterproof mortar (above left) be¬
fore being paved with stone. A rubble bar¬
rier (far left) protected the seawall.
archaeologists, diving technicians, marine
engineers and architects take part in what
may be the largest underwater excavation
of its kind.
Though the work is far from being com¬
pleted, it has already yielded scores of data
that not only verify Josephus' testimony but
add surprising facts about the standards of
harbour technology of that time. Not only
was this the first protected basin to be artifi¬
cially encompassed by free-standing
breakwaters not based on any headland,
natural bay or off-shore reefs, but those
structures were so designed that their inter¬
nal side was properly protected from the
splash of breaking storm waves to
accommodate mooring facilities for their
entire length.
The main breakwaters were built in a
unique combination of carefully laid huge
ashlar blocks fastened with iron clamps
(held by molten lead that was poured into
grooves at the edges of the ashlar blocks
when they were already in place under the
water) and artificial hydraulic conglomer¬
ate that slowly solidified within double
walled wooden caissons that were lowered
to their proper position by the careful addi¬
tion of a specially blended mixture of hyd
raulic concrete made of lime, red soil, and
volcanic pumice, in between the double
wooden walls.
In order to save building material in the
construction of the submerged part of the
breakwater (the total volume of the under¬
water base must have been around 200,000
cubic metres) the caissoned blocks and the
ashlar walls were installed only at the exter¬
nal, internal, midsection and cross-sections
of the breakwaters, with hollowed compart¬
ments of 20 x 30 metres left for the sea to fill
with wave-carried sand. In this way, after a
few years, the filled sections could be paved
and built on.
Other sophisticated measures were taken
in order to prevent what seems to be the
constant problem of all modern protected
basins along this coastline, silting up and
the deposition of sand. This natural process
was prevented by the creation of a constant
current through the harbour entrance. This
current was initiated by a series of channels
through the stem of the main breakwater.
These channels would have an opening just
above the highest tide, so there would be
only an inflow of silt-free water generated
by each incoming wave-front. The flow in
the channels could be controlled by sluice
gates to satisfy the demand for an efficient
washing current.
The archaeological proof that this system
was properly working was deduced from the
thin layer of fine silt with Herodian pottery
sherds all over the harbour bottom which
represents a sandfree basin during the time
when the harbour was intact and func¬
tioning. The same kind of layer, with an
abundance of clay vessels and other small
finds dating from the Roman period, was
found just outside the harbour entrance. It
was over 1.5 metres thick and had been
swept there by the outflowing current.
Technologically, the Caesarea project is
the culmination of twenty-five years of
marine archaeological exploration and re¬
search. It encompasses land and underwa¬
ter excavations and includes sampling of
bio-species, minerals and sediments for
laboratory analysis. The results will contri¬
bute to knowledge of ancient environ¬
mental changes, land-sea relations,
ancient marine engineering and harbour
technologies.
AVNER RABAN is Executive Chairman of the
Centre for Maritime Studies at the University of
Haifa. 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
/
Q
LU
O
©
Beringia
32
During the last 2 million years, vast accu¬
mulations of ice covered extensive parts of
the Earth and melted again about 20 times,
each Ice Age lasting around 100,000 years.
Each time that the ice sheets reached their
maximum extent, the additional volume of
water extracted from the ocean was about 40
million cubic kilometres. This resulted in a
drop in sea level of about 100 metres.
Archaeologists have been aware for several
decades that the lower sea levels during the
Ice Ages created a larger living space for
Stone Age tribes of the Palaeolithic (over
10,000 years ago), and that migrations be¬
tween continents and islands were promoted
by the creation of "land bridges" or narrow
straits. Marine archaeologists are now
studying submerged prehistoric sites on the
continental shelf and have established
beyond doubt that human occupation did
take place below the present sea level. Study
of "land bridges" may shed new light on one
of the most important (and still poorly
understood) processes of human history, the
colonization of the Earth's continents by
early man after his evolution in East Africa
1.5 million years ago. In the following art¬
icle, a Soviet specialist, Nikolai N. Dikov,
describes one of these land bridges, the
ancient landmass known as Beringia which
in prehistoric times stretched from Siberia
to Alaska.
A prehistoric
'intercontinental highway'
between Asia
and America by Nikolai N. Dikov
UNLIKE the mysterious Atlantis, Be¬
ringia actually existed. Like Atlan¬
tis, it was submerged by the sea.
This happened gradually about 10,000 years
ago, as the huge glaciers of the last great Ice
Age melted. The level of the Pacific Ocean
rose as much as 200 metres at that time, and
the vast depression between Chukotka and
Alaska was inundated. Since then, the wa¬
ters of the Bering and Chukotkan seas and
of the Bering Strait, which joins them, have
intermingled here.
The honour of making the definitive dis¬
covery (in the 1960s) of this huge land-mass
which is now under water belongs to the
U.S. geologist David M. Hopkins, although
the actual term "Beringia" was first used by
a Soviet palaeozoologist, Petr P. Sushkin,
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
View of the globe showing connections
between the continents at times of low sea
level during the Ice Ages, and the general
directions of human migrations over mil¬
lions of years.
in 1925, and as long as 200 years ago a
Russian academician, Stepan P. Krashenin-
nikov, had a general idea that there was
some such land route between Asia and
America.
Subsequent scientific investigations con¬
firmed the existence of Beringia and en¬
abled us to chart the course of its rivers and
lakes and to get an idea of what its climate
and its fauna and flora must have been like.
It was a flat plain, woody in the south, and
with tundra and steppes in the north, where
herds of mammoths and bison, wild horses
and reindeer grazed.
Curiously enough, Beringia appeared
above water more than once during the Ice
Ages, when much of the world's water be¬
came concentrated in sheets of ice and as a
result extensive shallows along the coasts
(shelfs) became dry land. Glacial and in¬
terglacial periods alternated, and when the
temperature rose, the ice melted and a strait
appeared between Asia and America,
where there had previously been dry land.
At the beginning and end of the Ice Ages,
each of which lasted several thousand
years, there was a fairly wide bridge of land
between the west and east parts of the sheet
of ice. In these periods, too, there was a
direct route by which animals and people
could migrate from Asia to the interior of
America, which was covered with glaciers.
The main interest that Beringia holds for
archaeologists lies in the question of the
original settlement of America from Asia.
In the L'ilt that has accumulated at the
bottom of the sea, archaeologists expect to
find tracks of Stone Age men who passed
through on their way from Asia to America.
Underwater operations are to begin very
soon, but for the time being intensive
archaeological prospecting and excavation
work is being done on the approaches to the
submerged land of Beringia, in Chukotka,
Kamchatka, and Alaska. These investiga¬
tions are giving us1 some idea of the stages in
the migration of populations through Be¬
ringia and of the nature of their culture.
They are also helping us to work out our
strategy for the underwater archaeological
searches that are to be undertaken, which
will take account of the topographic and
stratigraphie characteristics of the ancient
sites that have been discovered in the im¬
mediate approaches to Beringia.
Systematic searching was begun by the
author of this article in 1961, after he had
worked out a programme for archaeological
investigations in the north-east with a view
to solving the problem of the peopling of
America. The excavations carried out so far
have revealed a large number of
Palaeolithic sites in Kamchatka and Chu¬
kotka, which are now the basic source of
information for our study of the peopling of
America through Beringia.
Every year brings fresh evidence that this
region, which was subsequently cut off from
the centres of ancient civilization, was at
that time not a backward, outlying part of
the world but one of its great highways
which, with Beringia, formed a wide bridge
between what are now Asia and North
America.
Data obtained by Soviet and U.S.
archaeologists enable us to distinguish, with
different degrees of precision , four stages in
the peopling of Beringia.
The first stage is as yet in many respects
hypothetical, but logically necessary. It
appears to correspond either to the penulti¬
mate Ice Age, known as the Ziryansk Ice
Age (70,000-50,000 years ago) or to the
beginning of the last Ice Age, known as the
Sartansk Ice Age (28,000-20,000 years
ago). This is the stage to which we may
attribute both extremely ancient relicts that
have been found in America, including
roughly chipped pebbles, and what appear
to be prototypes of these ancient relicts
which have been found at sites in the Soviet
Far East in Chukotka and elsewhere.
The second stage, which is also largely
hypothetical, corresponds to the period be¬
tween 14,000 and 20,000 years ago when
Sartansk glaciation was most extensive and
Beringia itself reached its maximum size.
At this stage, its tundra-steppes, which
were populated with megafauna, were a
single natural zone, cut off from its sur¬
roundings by glaciers to the west and east
and by the relatively warm Pacific Ocean to
the south.
In this closed-in region it was probably
some time before there was any differentia¬
tion between the two cultural zones the
continental zone, where huge mammals
were hunted in the tundra-steppes, and the
north Pacific zone, near the coast, where
hunters, öf whom little is known as yet,
exploited the sea's resources in a sporadic
fashion. Technologically, this was still
a united zone with a relatively uniform
culture.
The third stage, which is quite clearly
defined, corresponds to the dispersal to the
western approaches of Beringia, in Kam-
G
Z
Z
©
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
w
BP
View of the excavations (foreground) of
the Ushki Palaeolithic site in Kamchatka.
Around photo, stone implements un¬
earthed on the site.
34
chatka, of the early Ushki culture, which is
dated around 13,000-14,000 years ago and
possibly earlier, judging by palaeo-magne-
tic dating. From this period on we can make
fairly definite assertions about the cultural
connections between Asia and America by
way of Beringia and also, perhaps, about
population migration, when we think of the
astonishing resemblance of Ushki stemmed
bifacial stone points for missiles to those
found in sites in the State of Washington, in
the north-west of the USA.
This was the last period when cultural
connections and perhaps population migra¬
tions were possible entirely over dry land,
because up to the beginning of the thir¬
teenth millennium Beringia was not divided
by a strait. The north-west coast of North
America could also be used to get from
Beringia to America, which was covered
with glaciers, for at that time the glaciers
had somewhat diminished in volume and
were no longer a hindrance to population
migration along the Pacific coast, particu¬
larly for populations which engaged in hunt¬
ing, fishing and gathering, as in the early
Ushki culture.
The fourth and much more clearly de¬
fined stage corresponds to the very end of
the Sartansk Ice Age (12,000,-10,000 years
ago). It is connected with the further ero¬
sion and ecological reconstruction of Be¬
ringia the broadening of the strait be¬
tween Chukotka and Alaska, the gradual
swamping of the tundra-steppes and the
reduction of the diversity of species and the
number of megafauna. The main flow of
migration to Beringia did not pass by the
north route in the direction of Yakutia
(although this cannot be entirely excluded)
but by a south Pacific route in the direction
of the northern part of what is now the
Soviet Far East.
Here there came into being a new culture
which was based on fishing and bison-hunt¬
ing and could readily adapt to the new
ecological conditions. This was the Late
Ushki culture, which has been extensively
studied in Kamchatka. It is characterized by
large settlements, at the largest of which
some thirty dwellings have already been
excavated. These dwellings are quite diffe¬
rent from the large double tents of the early
Ushki culture.
There are also marked differences in
stone implements. As well as the bifacial
leaf-shaped non-stemmed points of mis¬
siles, forms of ornament much favoured by
the Aleutians and the Eskimos have been
found. A domestic dog burial has already
been found, that of a dog like a husky. It is
one of the most ancient burials in the
Palaeolithic. Wedge-shaped cores are com¬
monly found. They are yet another indica¬
tion that there is a certain affinity between
the Ushki culture and the Denali culture in
Alaska, where the latter played its part in
the formation of the proto-Eskimo Aleuts.
When the proto-Eskimo Aleuts reached
the southern part of Beringia, they de¬
veloped sea hunting more and more inten¬
sively. A factor that facilitated this was the
considerable diminution in the size of Be¬
ringia (starting about 12,000 years ago). A
strait gradually appeared, and boats had to
be used to reach the eastern side.
The Palaeolithic sites in Chukotka may
be seen as intermediary stopping places on
the way from Kamchatka to Beringia and
beyond it to America. The same wedge-
shaped cores and bifacial weapon points
have been found in them as in the Late
Ushki culture in Kamchatka and the Denali
culture in Alaska. This shows that popula¬
tion movement direct from Chukotka to
Alaska took place 12,000-10,000 years ago,
when Beringia began to get considerably
smaller, until finally there was a strait where
it had once been.
Underwater archaeologists working in
the submerged land of Beringia can expect
to make fascinating discoveries. They can
use the latest diving equipment available on
vessels such as the Academician Nes-
meyanov, which is registered at the Far East
Department of the USSR Academy of Sci¬
ences. This vessel is equipped with the latest
apparatus including a system for the adap¬
tive training of divers and remote control by
television communication. It can carry out
underwater operations at a depth of up to
300 metres.
As to the method of carrying out under¬
water investigations, what we have said
about the pattern of the distribution of
ancient sites in the parts of Beringia that
were not submerged suggests that it would
be advisable to begin possibly by drill¬
ing near the mouths of the river beds that
have been found on the shelf. The success of
these investigations is bound to be of great
international scientific importance.
NIKOLAI NIKOLAEVICH DIKOV is a corres-
ponding member of the USSR Academy of Sci¬
ences and director of the archaeology, history
and ethnography laboratory of the North-East
Scientific Research. Institute of the Academy's
Far East Department. He is the author of 7
monographs, including "Ancient Culture of
North-East Asia" (2 volumes) and over 150 sci¬
entific papers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Reportsfrom 6 countries
SPAIN
Exploring a 'ships' graveyard'
In August 1987, during an extensive under¬
water archaeological operation off the
"Coast of Death", Galicia, a team of 20
archaeologists discovered the wreck of a
ship which had taken part in a naval expedi¬
tion sent by King Philip II of Spain against
England. Many of the ships, which set sail
from Seville and Lisbon, were wrecked in
October 1586 during a violent storm off
Cape Finisterre. The archaeologists made
600 individual dives and spent a total of 800
hours under water at a maximum depth of
25 metres. The excavation and recovery of
some of the remains, which were located
with the aid of magnetometers and un¬
covered by airlifts, was no easy task since
the artefacts had fused together and were
covered with concretion. The wooden
wreckage had distintegrated, but it proved
possible to recover a large anchor, some
stone projectiles, a large quantity of small
arms ammunition, and numerous coins
(left), as well as pottery and personal acces¬
sories. Work in this veritable "ships'
graveyard" is to continue for several years.
Manuel Martín-Bueno
Professor of archaeology,
University of Saragossa.
Director of the "Finisterre 87" expedition
THE NETHERLANDS
Archaeology
in muddy waters
If beauty is in the eye of the beholder,
maritime archaeology in The Netherlands
cannot be called beautiful. Eyesight is often
superfluous to the diver, who is confronted
with absolute darkness or a shimmering
opaque green micro-world in which the
shapes and features of structural remains
and differences in soil texture can be felt but
can hardly ever be seen. Practically blinded,
the diver feels his way and digs like a mole
although his method of excavation differs
greatly from the one followed by that des¬
tructive creature.
The survey of a shipwreck discovered
near the harbour of the medieval town of
Medemblik illustrates how underwater
archaeologists in The Netherlands work in
such conditions. Maximum visibility on the
©
site was about 0.5 metres. An accurate
drawing of the remains protruding from the
bottom was prepared in the following way.
Pins were set out in a rectangle, the longitu¬
dinal side of which was parallel to the main
axis of the ship. The pins were spaced exact¬
ly 3 metres apart. They were connected by
strings, thus forming a grid. This grid was
simply an aid for orientation, no measure¬
ments being taken from the lines. Trilatera-
tion measurements were taken from each
set of two pins (see drawing bottom right).
The measurements and all other data were
recorded by speaking into a tape recorder.
A pencil was only used to note certain speci¬
fic details. In this way trilateration was car¬
ried out in confined areas, approximately
square in shape and the resulting drawings
were fitted into a general plan which pro¬
vided an "overview" of this barely visible
site.
Next, three trial trenches were dug per¬
pendicular to the main axis in order to
establish the midships, forward and aft sec¬
tions of the hull, and to provide a relatively
clear picture of the construction of the ship.
With little work done on site a maximum of
information was retrieved.
The find is of great interest from the point
of view of shipbuilding techniques and tra¬
ditions. It combines features of the mediev¬
al cog with distinct differences in construc¬
tion. The underwater survey and trial ex¬
cavation have shown that the ship dates
Left, plan ofthe wreck-site, with (below) sections
ofthe trial trenches.
z
from between the Middle Ages and modern
times a transitional period for the building
of big ships.
There are no plans for extended excava¬
tion of the site. Its importance has been
assessed and it can and will be kept as it is,
an object for scientific research in the dis¬
tant future. Why, it might be asked, wait so
long if the site is so interesting? There are
good reasons for this.
Firstly, much of the scientific research on
sites in the reclaimed land of the Zuiderzee
and on ships such as the Bremen Cog has
not yet been published. Only when it is shall
we get a clear picture of what is known and
of the gaps in our knowledge. Only then will
it be possible to formulate up-to-date
hypotheses which can be tested on sites that
have been preserved and protected.
Another reason is that there are many
more sites than can be tackled scientifically
at present. Whenever protection is feasible
we should thus limit our curiosity to a good
survey.
Thijs J. Maarleveld,
Co-ordinator of underwater archaeology,
Government of The Netherlands
Below, trilateration measurements being carried
out on the Medemblik wreck. All information was
spoken into a tape recorder.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Top, detail of coin bag with 4th-century-
AD Roman coin.
Above, fishbones preserved in resin.
Photos © C.R.A.S.A., Sardinia, Italy
ITALY
The Lazzaretto wreck,
Sardinia
The Underwater Archaeology Research
Centre of Sassari and Alghero (CRASA) in
Sardinia is an association of scuba divers
which works in close collaboration with the
Sardinian archaeological authorities and
employs the scientific expertise of a profes¬
sional underwater archaeologist during ex¬
cavations.
Its most important operation has been the
complete excavation of the remains of a
small Roman round ship which sank in the
fourth century AD at Lazzaretto cove near
Alghero. The wreck lay about 40 metres
offshore at a depth of only 2.5 metres. Ex¬
cavations were carried out for 2 seasons in
June 1985 and June 1986.
Although the archaeological work has
only just finished, we may already begin to
draw some conclusions. The ship was
loaded with preserved fish (in brine or
dried) and garum (fish sauce) stowed in
amphoras produced in northern Africa or
southern Spain. One important find was a
number of coins in a leather or cloth bag
completely transformed by concretions.
This small bag must have been affixed to its
possessor's waist. One of the coins became
detached from the rest and left a perfect
impression on the concretion , enabling us to
conclude that it is afollis, struck during the
reign of the Emperor Licinius and issued in
AD 315-316. The shipwreck was caused by a
southwesterly gale, but we cannot exclude
an act of piracy.
Edoardo Riccardi
Scientific Director, Lazzaretto project
	 ZT
A diver positions a measuring scale during
excavation of the wreck of an 18th-century
Dutch freighterfound by sports divers offthe
coast of Norway. Each year sports divers
locate many new archaeological sites.
NORWAY
Amateurs are welcome
Ever since its birth in the early 1960s,
Norwegian marine archaeology has de¬
pended heavily on the participation of
amateur divers, and the museums co-oper¬
ate closely with the Norwegian Diving
Association. Local diving clubs have
formed marine archaeology groups whose
members specialize in such fields as under¬
water photography, drawing, and sur¬
veying. The museums contact the groups
when they need assistance. Projects are
usually carried out during the summer holi¬
days and the divers are unpaid, although
they receive compensation for the use of
their personal diving equipment as well as
travel and lodging expenses.
One important wreck that has been sur¬
veyed and worked on by amateur divers is a
medieval hulk dating from about AD 1450 ,
which has been found in southern Norway.
Its cargo seems to have consisted of flag
stones, sarcophagus lids, and round copper
ingots. Fossils in the limestone flag-stones
indicate that they came from a quarry out¬
side the town of Tallin in Estonia. The
wreck was excavated by sports divers under
the supervision of the Norway Maritime
Museum during 1986 and 1987.
Torstein Ormoy,
Norwegian Diving Association
MEXICO
Sacred wells
and Spanish galleons
Although objects were being recovered
from the sacred well of Chichén Itzá as early
as the end of the 19th century (see page 12),
it is only relatively recently that systematic
exploration began of Mexico's important
underwater heritage of pre-Hispanic votive
offerings and other objects in inland waters
and its maritime colonial heritage of Span¬
ish vessels and their cargoes. In 1980 a
Department of Underwater Archaeology
was created as part of the National Institute
of Anthropology and History (INAH), the
federal institution with responsibility for the
Hauling aboard a 16th-century iron cannon,
Bay of Campeche, Mexico
protection, investigation and conservation
of the country's archaeological heritage.
One important project undertaken by the
Department began when a group of U.S.
sports divers who were exploring the Cayo
Nuevo reef in the Bay of Campeche disco¬
vered several iron cannon and an anchor, as
well as a bronze cannon with 16th-century
inscriptions and emblems which particularly
attracted their attention. In 1979 the INAH
began work on the site with the Institute of
Nautical Archaeology at Texas A & M Uni¬
versity, and since then other objects have
been retrieved from this 16th-century ship¬
wreck and the remains of an 18th-century
wreck have been located. The 16th-century
bronze cannon is today preserved in a
museum in the city of Campeche.
Half Moon Spring in San Luis Potosí
State, a spring into which offerings were
thrown in pre-Hispanic times (above all be¬
tween AD 600 and 900) is the site of another
project sponsored by the Department. Un¬
fortunately, the spring's popularity with di¬
vers has encouraged looting, and thousands
of objects have been removed without any
control or record.
In 1984 the Department launched a pro¬
ject on "Aids to pre-Hispanic navigation on
the east coast of the Yucatán peninsula".
The aim is to locate and analyse offshore
structures such as lighthouses which might
have aided navigation in pre-Hispanic
times.
Finally, the Department has embarked
on the preparation of an atlas of all Mexico's
submerged sites of archaeological interest,
both inland and at sea.
Pilar Luna Erreguerena,
Department of Underwater Archaeology,
National Museum of Anthropology,
Mexico City
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
SRI LANKA
Coins and cannon
Owing to its geographical position in the
Indian Ocean, centrally situated in the sea
lanes linking the Near East and the East
Indies, Sri Lanka has been an important
landfall for seafarers ever since ancient
times, when it was known as Taprobane to
the Greeks and Romans, Serendib to the
sea-farers of old Arabia, and the "land with¬
out sorrow" to the Chinese. The great
Chinese traveller Cheng Ho made several
visits to the island in the early years of the
fifteenth century as part of his explorations
of the "Western Oceans".
There is no doubt that there are wrecks in
Sri Lankan coastal waters dating from the
period of European expansion into South
Asia. An expedition to the Great Basses
reef in the early 1960s, the first real attempt
at the archaeological exploration of a wreck
off southern Sri Lanka, produced finds in¬
cluding some 350 pounds of silver coin, a
bronze cannon and flintlock pistols. Post-
X
expedition analysis established that the
coins came from Surat, the cannon may
have been British, and the ship may have
been built in Southeast Asia. More recent¬
ly, important studies have taken place on
the traditional Model Paruwa or sewn
boats, drawing attention to the need for
research on the ethnographic material relat¬
ing to the Sri Lankan maritime heritage.
In late 1986 an exploration of two re¬
ported wreck sites was organized as part of a
feasibility study on the marine archaeolo¬
gical potential of Sri Lanka. The first took
place in Galle harbour, 115 km south of
Colombo. Galle, dominated by the massive
ramparts of the Portuguese and Dutch fort
in which the city is contained, is bounded on
the east by Mount Rummaswela, which has
a perennial fresh water spring. Folklore re¬
lates that this fresh water source was used by
vessels in Antiquity. A scatter of artefacts
including local and imported pottery was
found. The second site, approximately 2 km
west of Colombo, was identified by local
divers some years ago, at a depth of 20
metres, and was assumed to be the location
of two jettisoned cannon. The 1986 survey
identified two more cannon and it has been
suggested that they are probably of a seven-
lili
m
pasaos *
A sea-going vessel of a kind which would
have plied the Indian Ocean in the 8th or 9th
century AD. Detail from a low-reliefcarving
at the Buddhist temple-sanctuary ofBorobu-
dur (Indonesia).
teenth-century type used for merchant ser¬
vice. These limited explorations showed
that a coherent maritime archaeology prog¬
ramme is called for, and as a result a joint
"Sri Lanka Maritime Heritage Project" be¬
tween the Sri Lanka Department of
Archaeology and the University of London
has been prepared.
Prasanna Weerawardane
Department ofArchaeology,
Sri Lanka
The Bodrum Museum of Underwater
Archaeology, Turkey, houses important
displays of the remains of five scientifical¬
ly excavated shipwrecks from Antiquity.
Below, 1 :20 scale diorama of the excava¬
tion of a 4th-century-AD Roman shipwreck
at Yassi Ada (near Bodrum, in south-west
Turkey), carried out during the late 1960s.
Several modern underwater search tech¬
niques were used for the first time during
this excavation.
Below right, this Chinese celadon jar
(Ch'ing-pai lype) with carved dragon hand¬
les is thought to date from the 14th cen¬
tury. It comes from a shipwreck off Shinan
(Republic of Korea) that has been exca¬
vated and studied since 1976 by
archaeologists from the Cultural Prop¬
erties Preservation Bureau, Seoul. Ex¬
amination of artefacts found on the wreck,
notably almost 9,000 pieces of celadon
and around 4,500 porcelain objects,
should throw light on the history of
Chinese porcelains and of international
sea trade in the Middle Ages. Right,
Chinese coins (Chi-dai T'ung-bao) found
at the Shinan site. They were minted in the
early 14th century and were legal tender in
Japan and other countries in the region, as
well as in China. The finds confirm that this
ancient Far Eastern shipwreck is perhaps
the richest ever found, both in terms of the
value of the cargo as well as for the in¬
formation it provides on traditional naval
construction techniques in this region.
©
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Apollonia,
a modelport ofAntiquity
RECENT discoveries made in the
submerged ancient harbour of
Apollonia (see colour page 22) by
the French Archaeological Mission to the
Libyan Arab Jamahiriya were featured in
an exhibition held at Unesco's Paris head¬
quarters from 3 to 15 June 1987. The exhibi¬
tion, produced by Unesco's Division of
Cultural Heritage, also highlighted the re¬
sults of major projects for the study, safe¬
guard and presentation of the Libyan Cultu¬
ral Heritage carried out as a result of co¬
operation between Unesco, the Depart¬
ment of Antiquities of the Libyan Arab
Jamahiriya, and the Archaeology Depart¬
ment of the University of Manchester
(UK).
Located on the northeast Libyan coast,
Apollonia has been described as "a text¬
book example of an ancient harbour." It
was the port, and originally a dependency,
of the great inland city of Cyrene, which was
founded around 631 BC. In the first century
BC, it became a city in its own right. Today
the ancient harbour installations are sub¬
merged because of subsidence that has
occurred all along this part of the Libyan
coastline.
The harbour was formed of two linked
sandstone islets joined to the shore by natu¬
ral breakwaters. Today these islets are 300
metres offshore. An extraordinary range of
buildings and other structures has been dis¬
covered, including the best preserved set of
slipways in the Mediterranean, a well-pre
served piscina or fish tank, and the remains
of warehouses including grain-storage silos
cut into the rock.
The French Mission, directed by Profes¬
sor André Laronde and working in co-op¬
eration with the Archaeological Service of
the city of Aries, has carried out a systema¬
tic survey of submerged structures and
wrecks and other material recently located
in the eastern dock. The wreck of a mer¬
chant ship, originally about 25 metres long,
has been discovered. Apart from its
wooden structure, the wreck has also
yielded ship's tackle and the remains of a
cargo have been found nearby.
Another wreck contained terra-cotta
bowls with ornamentation in relief, known
as "Megarian" ware, which come from the
coast of Asia Minor, together with Rhodian
amphoras for transporting wine. The
stamps on the handles make it possible to
date this material and consequently the
whole cargo to about 180 BC. Underwater
exploration has also produced an abund¬
ance of undecorated ceramic ware, most of
it locally made, which gives an idea of the
accessories of everyday living. A bronze
candelabrum head from the beginning of
the Roman period bears witness to trade
with southern Italy in the first century BC,
while a gold coin (solidus) from Constanti¬
nople shows that trading relations were still
being maintained at the time the Arabs
arrived in Libya.
Acknowledgments
We regret that owing to a last-minute
technical error, the September issue of the
Unesco Courier devoted to the Baroque was
printed without a note expressing our
gratitude to the French art critic and former
Unesco staff member Michel Conil Lacoste
for his help in preparing that issue. The
Editors also wish to acknowledge their
indebtedness to Le Baroque, a monumental
work by the French author Yves Bottineau,
published by Editions Mazenod, Paris,
1986.
38
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request . Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A. ; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. ,111 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief:
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian:
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: AzizahHamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: DaoTung (Hanoi)
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Dépôt légal : C1 - Novembre 1 987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes. 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Forty years of cultural action
The Unesco Courier, which was first pro¬
duced in 3 languages, is now published in 34
languages worldwide, in addition to Braille
editions in 4 languages. In the early days, its
circulation was a few thousand; today hun¬
dreds of thousands of copies are printed and
the magazine is read by over 3 million people
of all ages and on all continents. In its forty
years of existence the Unesco Courier has won
for itself a unique position on the internation¬
al cultural and publishing scene. In the words
of its Editor-in-Chief, Edouard Glissant, "the
editions of the Courier produced in 34 lan¬
guages not only represent an outstanding
publishing achievement, they constitute
above all an irreplaceable instrument for mu¬
tual enrichment and international under¬
standing, without being either bland or par¬
tisan".
To mark these "40 years of cultural action",
the Courier's Paris staff organized an exhibi¬
tion about the magazine which was held at the
Georges Pompidou Centre, Paris, from 9
September to 5 October 1987. A series of
display panels retraced in words and pictures
the history and achievements of a magazine
which, in the words of Unesco's Constitution,
has always sought to "construct the defences
of peace in the minds of men" by developing
understanding between peoples and cul¬
tures.
The exhibition, which will later tour France
and other European countries, was accompa¬
nied by a series of films about Unesco's work,
one of which has as its theme the cover
designs of the Courier. On 10 September four
writers associated with Unesco and with the
magazine took part in a poetry reading at the
Pompidou Centre: the Arab poet Adonis,
deputy permanent representative of the Arab
League to Unesco; the Martinican poet
Edouard Glissant; the French poet Alain Lé¬
vêque, senior editor of the French edition of
the Courier; and Henri Lopès, Congolese
novelist and Unesco's Assistant Director-
General for Culture and Communication.
A fortieth anniversary issue of the Unesco
Courier will be published in 1988.
Group photograph taken at Unesco's Paris Headquarters on 23 April 1987
during a meeting of Editors of the Unesco Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
fei
^^H
m^é
]]>
</page>
</document>
