<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="076667eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
DECEMBER 1987 9 French Irancs
JAPAN
TODAY
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
The dance of life
60 Japan
Suspended from ropes like spiders dropping down their silken threads,
these exponents of Japanese butö dancing are members of the "Sankai
Juku" troupe photographed during a performance in the United States.
Butö is a dance form in which the moment of birth is recreated, with the
ropes as symbols of umbilical cords. The dancers, whose virtually naked
bodies are covered with rice-flour and paint, are being slowly lowered to
the ground from the top of the building by men who pay out the ropes to
which they are fastened. As they descend, to the strains of eerie,
supernatural music, they express in movement the reactions of a new¬
born child. An exploration of the sources of dance and of life itself,
butö has become a leading dance form in Japan since it emerged in the
early 1960s.
Covers: Collage of Japanese motifs and crumpled paper composition evoking the Japanese flag have been specially designed for this issue by the
Japanese artist Ado. who also executed the ideogram "Japan" reproduced on the opposite page and elsewhere in the issue.
Photos © Ado / Thf Um'\co Courier
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
Expo '70 the Osaka Universal Exposition of 1970 marked a
turning point in the history of modern Japan. It symbolized the
country's renewed prosperity and reasserted its position in the
world . With hindsight it can also be seen as the culmination of a
period of massive technological achievements, triumphant
modernization and major city-planning projects. The oil crises of
the 1970s would act as a brake on economic expansion, and the
production system and social life in general would evolve towards
greater diversification and individualism.
The following years saw the development of new trends in art
and architecture, in industrial design and literature, given wide
publicity by the media, whose power heralded the development of
a veritable "communications society". On the international scene
today, after a long period of absorbing Western science ,
technology and ways of thinking, Japan appears as a pioneer of the
scientific revolution of the late twentieth century, and is making a
distinctive contribution in many fields of creative activity: At
home, the inconveniences of urban life are a reminder that there is
a price to pay for accelerated growth.
We have tried in the following pages to give a picture,
necessarily incomplete, of a changing country as it seeks to chart a
course for the future and to understand the cultural factors that
underlie its extraordinary economic success. As well as the
intrinsic fascination of Japan its social and economic systems, its
technology and its culture perhaps this picture also reveals
achievements and problems inevitably associated with the growth
of industrial civilization.
Federico Mayor Zaragoza elected Director-General of Unesco
Mr. Federico Mayor Zaragoza, of Spain, was elected Director-General
of Unesco for a 6-year term by Unesco's General Conference on 7
November 1987. He succeeds Mr. Amadou-Mahtar M'Bow of Senegal,
who was Director-General since 1974.
Mr. Mayor, who has taught biochemistry at the University of Madrid
and at the University of Granada of which he was Rector, served as
Deputy Directon-General of Unesco from 1978 to 1981 before becoming
his country's Minister of Education and Science.
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
December 1987
40th year
Signs of a new individualism
by Masakazu Yamazaki
10
Aiming high
Japan 's demanding education system
by Kazuo Kurimoto
14
A 'communications society'
An interview with Yozo Shiozaki
16
The art of making light work
by Motoko Ishii
18
Colours to whet the palate
by Jun'ichirö Tanizaki
21
Cities at one with nature
by Augustin Berque
24
The changing home
Tradition and modernism in domestic architecture
byMarcBourdicr
26
A large foreigner in search of space
bv James Kirkup
31
The high tech explosion
bvShigeruKimura
34
Confucius and capitalism
bv Michio Morishima
38
The Japanese and Western music
by Luisa Futoransky
41
Home thoughts from abroad
A Japanese writer in Paris reflects on his country's
postwar literature
byTokuyoshi Hiraoka
44
Two contemporary writers
bv Dominique Palme
A time to live...
JAPAN:Thedanceoflife
The Courier English
French
Italian
Hindi
Turkish
Urdu
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Finnish
Swedish
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
A window open on llw world
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque French, Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 33 languages Russian Hebrew- Malaysian Chinese Thai
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational.
German Persian Korean Bulgarian Vietnamese
Scientific and Cultural Organization Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek
ISSN (XI4 1-5278
7. Place de Fontenoy. 757(1(1 Paris. Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala N" 12- 1987-CPD-87- 1-452 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Signs of a new
individualism
The State, the family
and the company in Japan today
Right, a happy couple in a Tokyo park. A
decline in the birth-rate and the ageing of the
population (the Japanese longevity rate is
among the world's highest) are major recent
demographic trends in Japan. People are also
spending less time at the workplace and in the
family, and life-styles are becoming more
diversified.
1 . In the mid-19th century, in response to foreign press¬
ure. Japan ended over two centuries of isolation and
opened its ports to international trade. In 1 868. a strong
central government was restored, under the symbolic
authority ol the Emperor Meiji. This was a turning point
in Japanese history. The Unesco Couner published a
special issue in September-October 1968 to com¬
memorate the centenary of the Meiji Restoration.
by Masakazu Yamazaki
IT is generally agreed that the 1970s
were a crucial decade in contemporary
Japanese history, but it is less easy to
define their precise significance. The pre¬
ceding decade of the 1960s, by contrast,
left a clear-cut impression on all of us as a
time of dramatic change.
In the 1960s, the fruits of economic
growth were just beginning to be visible,
and the theme of growth was the central
concern both for those who sought to pro¬
mote it and for its opponents. Increasingly,
people felt that Japan had recovered from
the isolation following its defeat in the Sec¬
ond World War and that the postwar era
was over. "Internationalization" emerged
as a key goal for the new era.
The 1970s, by contrast, were a period
without heroic slogans, and the decade left
no memorial in the form of a major festival
or celebration. People began to talk of the
1970s as "an age of uncertainty", a phrase
borrowed from the title of a book by John
Kenneth Galbraith.
The changing image
of the State
One of the most notable changes that
took place in this period was the decline in
the ¡mage of the State. Of course, the State
has by no means lost its role as a func¬
tioning political system. But the 1970s saw
a rapid diminution of the State in individual
perception.
During the hundred-year process of
modernization and industrialization that
began with the Meiji Restoration of 18681,
the State was perceived as an immeasur¬
ably powerful force in determining national
attitudes. For the Japanese, modernization
dramatically changed the concept of the
nation, which ceased to refer simply to an
ethnic community, as it had in pre-modem
times, and came to describe an instrument
of collective purpose.
The State was greatly reinforced by its
use as an instrument of collective purpose
during the process of modernization. In
particular, modernization heightened peo¬
ple's feeling that their lives were dedicated
to the achievement of national goals. This
tendency reached its apogee during the
1960s when Japan moved into second
place in the market-economy countries in
terms of GNP.
The 1960s were also a decade of
remarkable achievements in foreign policy.
People were stirred by the success of the
negotiations for the return of Okinawa. The
1964 Tokyo Olympics and Expo 70 were
also national events, orchestrated by the
State before a world-wide audience. And
the people were able to witness these
events via the new nationwide medium of
television. If the 1960s were a time of
clear-cut goals, it was because the State
itself had clear objectives and played a
leading role in managing great national
events.
If we look more closely, however, we find
that the Japanese State was permitted to
follow such a dramatic course of action and
pursue a single goal with such fervour
because Japan was still a minor nation. In
the Meiji era, when Japan was an industri-
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
ally backward State, and in the late 1 940s,
when it was a country defeated in war, the
national goal of "catching up and over¬
taking" was almost entirely a domestic
concern.
An invisible limit in this process of ex¬
pansion was reached in the 1960s when
Japan's GNP reached the level referred to
above. Though a certain degree of eco¬
nomic growth would be tolerated subse¬
quently, dramatic advances would no long¬
er be possible in the international context.
As it turned out, the first oil crisis braked
Japan's economic growth during the
1970s, but it is reasonable to assume that
even if the oil crisis had not occurred,
something else would have happened to
curb the soaring growth rates of the
1960s.
Ironically, the peaking of Japan's nat¬
ional strength during the 1960s eventually
robbed the country of the opportunity for
bold action during the 1970s. The most
significant outcome was that the State lost
its fascination for the people and no longer
provided stimulation for their day-to-day
activities or encouragement in their lives as
individuals. The State ceased to be a
"combat force" working towards a major
objective and became instead a "technical
force" concerned with maintaining a del¬
icate balance among countless minor
problems. It was no longer an arena for
great celebrations but the realm of day-to¬
day administration.
The local community
Of course, the full implications of this
change were not apparent at the time. One
extremely symptomatic development,
however, was the sudden appearance of
the vogue phrase "the local era" at the
close of the 1970s. Local magazines be¬
gan to be produced for people living in
specific areas. The development of these
magazines, a revolutionary phenomenon
in the history of Japan's highly centralized
publishing industry, was paralleled by
growth in the circulation of local newspa¬
pers and in the number of young people
listening to local radio stations. These may
seem to be minor changes, but when it is
remembered that during the 1960s the
"The surplus in the work force stimulated the growth of the service industries, strengthening the
concept of consumption without production. " Below, the Tokyo Stock Exchange, one of the
world's leading financial centres.
\qsa&&&£K
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
I [-f i-, MM W»r»l»l
"The number of new publications increased
steadily throughout the 1970s. The range of
specialized and educational publications also
widened..." The Japanese are avid readers and
their practice of reading wherever and when¬
ever they can is so widespread that it has a
special name, tachi yomi (reading standing
up). Below, a young man browsing in a book¬
shop selling computer magazines.
"The State ceased to be a 'combat force' work¬
ing towards a major objective and became
instead a 'technical force' concerned with
maintaining a delicate balance among count¬
less minor problems. It is no longer an arena
for great celebrations but the realm of day-to¬
day administration. " Above, the traffic control
centre at police headquarters in Tokyo,
where 8 million vehicles ply through the
streets each day.
information media were almost totally
dominated by national television, it be¬
comes clear that a highly significant
and subtle shift had occurred in popular
interests.
New kinds of citizens' movements, led
by local government, also began to appear
throughout Japan in the 1970s. Tradition¬
ally, citizens' groups were formed on the
basis of political or ideological ties and
formed a mirror image of national politics.
But these new groups were much more
closely linked to the interests of their own
communities. Many were cultural in nature
and engaged primarily in recreational or
educational activities. Some went a step
further and sought to "promote local
development through "cultural.'» indus¬
tries". Community colleges, environmental
groups, civic choirs and local craft
groups all took on new significance and
began to serve as nuclei to encourage
residents to identify more closely with
their community.
Today we are seeing the emergence of a
milieu in which the individual, in the course
of his or her daily life, can relate to. the
group while maintaining a certain distance,
identifying with it on a more rational, multi¬
valent basis. In other words, people are
becoming more individualistic in their atti¬
tudes to everyday living and the individual¬
istic aspects ol society in general are
being strengthened. Seen in this light, the
changes that have, occurred in the
¡mage of the State are part of a wider trend.
A number of other symptomatic develop-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
ments occurred during the 1970s, perhaps
by historical accident. All these changes, at
least externally, have served to move
Japanese people in the direction of greater
individualism.
More time to spare
The most important groupings in modern
Japan apart from the State are probably
the company and the family. Over the past
decade, both these institutions have un¬
dergone a quiet but nevertheless extre¬
mely far-reaching alteration.
In the 1970s, probably for the first time
since the Meiji Restoi^tion, the amount of
time that the Japanese spent in their work¬
places or with their families declined.
According to data published by the Min¬
istry of Labour, the six-day working week
was in force in 71 .4 per cent of workplaces
in 1970. By 1980, this figure had plummet¬
ed to 23.7 per cent, indicating a threefold
increase in the percentage of companies
letting workers have at least one free Sat¬
urday per month. Even more remarkable is
the fivefold increase in the number of com¬
panies adopting a five-day-week. Statistics
for the same period relating to the number
of paid holidays indicate a decline in the
percentage of companies allowing be¬
tween 1 and 14 days from 57.7 per cent to
25.1 per cent, while the percentage of
companies allowing 15 days or more
doubled.
Another widely reported phenomenon of
the 1970s is the dramatic reduction in the
amount of time married women spend on
housework and the proportionate increase
in the amount of free time at their disposal.
The main reasons for this trend are be¬
lieved to be the spread of electrical ap¬
pliances during the 1960s and the in¬
creased availability of child-care facilities.
The 1970s also saw the beginning of a
rapid upsurge in the service industries,
particularly the restaurant business, which
played a major role in accelerating what
has been called the "externalization of
housework". It was in this period too that
the nuclear family, the trend for which be¬
gan after the Second World War, became
the general rule, and the birth-rate
declined.
An ageing population
The ageing of the population is a major
change which is perhaps the most widely
discussed issue of recent times in Japan.
Its most direct impact can be seen in the
decline in the relative importance of the
workplace and the home. By 1976 Japan's
average life expectancy had climbed to 72
years for men and 77 for women. The
statistics are continuing to edge upward,
and the Japanese now rank among the
world's longest-lived peoples. This means
that a man who starts work at 20 and
retires at 55 is likely to spend less than half
his life in the communal milieu of the work¬
place. By the same token, even if a woman
has her first child in her mid-twenties and is
in her mid-fifties before the last of her
children leaves home, she will still devote
far less than half her life to the family. For
Japanese. of both sexes, this implies a
K * 4j ^m
"A threefold increase in the percentage of
companies letting workers have at least one
free Saturday per month" look place in Japan
between 1970 and 1980. Above, swimming
pool complex that can accommodate up to
30,000 people, at Körakuen amusement park
in central Tokyo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
8
more diversified range of relationships out¬
side the workplace and the family, as well
as more time spent alone.
The problems faced by middle-aged and
elderly people vary from person to person;
they are not amenable to solution by politi¬
cal action at group level or by across-the-
board government measures. An increase
in the number of elderly persons in the
population is thus more likely to encourage
the development of a society characterized
by diversification of perceptions, ideas and
life-styles.
The influence of this change will prob--
ably be felt most strongly in various forms
of fashion. We are unlikely to see the
emergence of major trends, either in ideol¬
ogy or in styles of dress, with the potential
to affect the whole of society. Even today, it
is possible to perceive a tendency toward
diversification in women's fashions and
popular music, and it is difficult to pick
out trends that characterize the era as it
was possible to do in the 1960s.
The shift towards consumption
Production and consumption have al¬
ways been two sides of the same coin:
neither can exist without the other. Yet
ever since industrialization began in the
seventeenth century, the principles that
have determined the fundamental patterns
of modern society have been drawn almost
exclusively from human relationships in
the area of productive activities.
Though the supremacy of production re¬
mains largely intact, a subtle change in
social values seems to have taken place in
the last decade. The most important factor
underlying this change has been affluence,
as symbolized by the emergence during
the 1960s of the saying "consumption is a
virtue", but the change is perhaps more
directly attributable to the energy crisis of
the 1970s and the introduction of elec¬
tronics technology.
The energy crisis forced consumers to
economize, but far more important was its
dampening effect on the creed of mass
production. Previously, the goal of incen¬
tives to consume had been to boost pro¬
duction, but now consumers were en¬
couraged to be more judicious so as not to
overstimulate production. Meanwhile, the
development of energy-efficient industries
and the automation of factories through
electronics produced a surplus in the
working population and also permitted the
production of goods better adapted to the
consumer market. The surplus in the work
force stimulated the growth of the service
industries, strengthening the concept of
consumption without production.
The 1970s were thus a period when the
social value of consumption steadily began
to increase. This, in itself the first such
change in three centuries, was accompa¬
nied by changes in the fabric of consumer
behaviour. Consumers began, first, to se¬
lect goods according to more individual
preferences and, second, to demand direct
personal services rather than material
goods.
Changes in the publishing industry typify
this trend. The number of new publications
increased steadily throughout the 1970s.
The range of specialized and educational
publications also widened in such fields as
philosophy, the social sciences and the
natural sciences. Along with the increase
in small-format paperback books, this
seems to contradict critics who talk of the
decline of reading and the spread of ig¬
norance. What we are seeing here, espe¬
cially in the case of magazines, is a typical
manifestation of the trend towards the pro¬
duction of small quantities of a wide range
of goods. This phenomenon is not merely
the effect of the relaxation of social ties but
a sign that the Japanese are beginning to
develop strong personal tastes.
The boom in cultural services
Perhaps even more significant is the fact
that people have begun to seek services in
the cultural sphere. People are demanding
a change in the way society treats them,
and the current boom in the service indus¬
tries is a symptom of this phenomenon.
Restaurants, hotels, travel agencies,
sports clubs, adult education courses, art
galleries, museums and theatre have
all begun to attract large numbers of
patrons; so have medical facilities and new
religions.
These facilities provide not the basic
physical necessities for survival but forms
of intellectual and emotional satisfaction, in
other words, "cultural services" in the
broadest sense of the term. They take
the form of the direct provision of services
from person to person, eliminating mech¬
anical means of transmission wherever
possible.
In the arts, for example, the spread of
reproductions and multivolume art series
has been paralleled by an increase in the
number of people interested in original
woodblock prints. In education, radio and
television broadcasts now compete with
well-attended lectures at community col¬
leges. This apparent shift in the trend of
cultural services from secondhand to first¬
hand experience may prove to be an im¬
portant transition in terms of the broad
perspective of cultural history.
Affirmation of identity
In pre-industrlal societies the majority of
people were treated as "nobodies". In the
industrialized democracies, all people are
respected equally, but since everyone is
treated in the same way, people have sim¬
ply become "anybody".
Today, however, many people are af¬
firming their identity, and societies capable
of responding to this affirmation are com¬
ing into being. Until now, Japanese society
has provided for this need in the context of
the family and in the small groups that form
within companies. People are treated as
individuals by their families and their col¬
leagues and superiors. The consensus is
that groups of this type function better in
Japan than in the Western countries and
that they have played an important role in
maintaining the psychological stability and
diligence of the Japanese people.
No doubt this view is still valid today, and
it is extremely unlikely that we will see a
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
dramatic decline in the role of the home or
workplace group. What is certain is that
opportunities for self-affirmation can no
longer be limited to these two areas.
People are beginning to seek a wider
range of opportunities for recognition in
society at large. Many such opportunities
are likely to be provided by places where
cultural services are purchased as com¬
modities, as well as in such mutual-service
contexts as discussion groups and volun¬
teer organizations.
In conclusion, we can deduce that the
various social changes that have occurred
since the 1970s stem from the emergence
of new aspirations concerning the self and
individualism. And although the overall pic¬
ture is still not clear, it is probable that the
individualism of the future will be totally
different in nature from that of the era of
industrialization. We can expect to see the
individualism of maturity, of flexible and
aesthetic interests and enlightened self-
expression, instead of the goal-oriented
individualism of competitiveness and rigid
beliefs.
MASAKAZU YAMAZAKI, Japanese educator,
teaches at Osaka University and is a former
guest professor at Columbia University, USA.
He is the author of several books, including a
study of contemporary art. This article has been
adapted from a text published in August 1983 in
the Japanese monthly magazine Chüö Köron.
Audacious architecture
"People have also begun to seek cultural services. Restaurants, hotels, travel agencies, sports clubs,
adult education courses, art galleries, museums ... have all begun to attract large numbers of
patrons. " Three examples of modern Japanese architecture are shown here: 1. The roofgarden of
Spiral, a Tokyo building designed by Fumihiko Maki for a clothes manufacturing company as a
centre for cultural as well as business activities. 2. Parabolic stainless steel roofs of the Fujisawa
Municipal Gymnasium, some 30 km from Tokyo, also by Fumihiko Maki. 3. The Museum of
Contemporary Art in Los Angeles, USA, designed by Arala Isozaki, is an audacious blend of
architectural styles using geometric elements.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Aiming high
Japan's demanding education system
by Kazuo Kurimoto
Below, students at a graduation ceremony at
one of Tokyo's technological universities.
Japan has a large, highly developed system of
higher education which each year produces a
massive output of well-trained graduates.
THE Japanese economy grew through¬
out the 1970s until it eventually
came to account for 10 per cent of
world economic activity. It is often said that
education played a major role in this eco¬
nomic expansion. What is the nature of this
contribution? What is the current state of
Japanese education, and what problems
does it face?
In Japan, primary education, which lasts
six years, and the first three-year stage of
secondary education in middle school, are
compulsory and free, and enrolment is
close on 100 per cent. As all the members
of every class move up into the next grade
together, there is no such thing as bright
children skipping a year, nor do slower
pupils "fail" or have to repeat a year.
The second stage of secondary educa¬
tion (three years of high school) is not
compulsory, but enrolment is about 97 per
cent of the eligible age group.
Thirty-six per cent of the young people
who complete the twelve years of primary
and secondary education go on to study at
universities or junior colleges. A further 1 2
per cent proceed to higher education in
specialist schools or colleges. Thus half of
the relevant age group go on to institutions
of higher education; and practically all of
these students complete their education at
these institutions.
About half of Japanese young people
enter working life after finishing twelve
years of education; the other half do so
after undergoing some form of higher edu-
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Juku, private tutoring establishments where
children are helped to improve their school
results and older pupils are coached for uni¬
versity entrance examinations, are widely pa¬
tronized as a complement to the "official"
education system. Right, a juku teacher
reprimands a pupil who does not know his
arithmetic.
cation. Virtually all of both groups acquire
specialist or professional skills from in-
service training, under something like an
apprenticeship system, in the organization
which they have chosen to enter on com¬
pletion of their school and/or college
education.
Broadly speaking, then, only half of the
education which Japanese children re¬
ceive as they progress to adulthood is at
school, college or university. The other half
consists of studies they pursue on their
own when they have become fully-fledged
members of society, or as part of their
training within the enterprise or organiza¬
tion to which they belong.
In-house training
In Japan a person is not assigned once
and for all to carry out a specific function at
the workplace. After acquiring a variety of
skills and experience within an organiza¬
tion, employees move on to more special¬
ized or managerial types of work. In Japa¬
nese companies, work is not organized so
that people are hired from outside and
dismissed when they are no longer re¬
quired. The general rule is that a fixed
number of new employees, who will consti¬
tute the bottom layer of the personnel
structure of the organization, are taken on
every year and trained in the necessary
skills, or switched to different work, as
occasion may require, within that person
nel structure. In addition to the major role
of the organization in providing education
and training, employees are highly motiva¬
ted to study on their own account.
Society expects the school system to
produce individuals with the basic skills
they will need as members of the orga¬
nizations they will eventually join, together
with the ability and aptitude that will enable
them to benefit by future training at work.
People do not believe that the function of
schools is to turn out ready-made special¬
ists who can be useful at work without any
further training after they have been
hired.
The key to social status
At the beginning of 1987, a report was
published on the results of joint research
carried out by Japanese and US special¬
ists on education in Japan and the United
States. The Japanese team focused on
education in the USA, and the American
team concentrated on Japanese educa¬
tion, and their conclusions were published
simultaneously. In their analysis of Japa¬
nese education, the US educationists
made the following points:
Japanese society is highly education-
oriented. Success at school is synony¬
mous with success in life, the only route to
social and economic status.
Japanese education produces striking
results, which are the product of co-oper
ative effort by parents, children and teach¬
ers. The education system is reinforced by
historical and cultural tradition, by a close
relationship between employers and edu¬
cation, by the availability of preschool edu¬
cation and, at the primary and middle
school levels, by supplementary out-of-
school education.
The nine-year period of compulsory ba¬
sic education is well balanced and of high
quality. Both the average levels of aca¬
demic achievement and the rates of at¬
tendance throughout primary and second¬
ary education are very high.
Japanese education also motivates pu¬
pils to succeed at school; it teaches them
how to study efficiently, maintains an effec¬
tive learning environment, promotes edu¬
cation of the whole person, and provides
effective careers assistance to high school
graduates.
But, according to the US report, Japa¬
nese education is not perfect. It is too rigid,
too uniform. There is too little opportunity
for choice; hardly any attention is paid in
schools to the needs of, and differences
between, individual pupils. An associated
problem is that when it comes to employ¬
ment an individual's academic record is
given too much weight.
Why is it that Japanese society is so
education-oriented, and parents are so in¬
tent on the education of their children that
they send them to juku, private coaching
establishments, for extra lessons after
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
school hours? The reason seems to lie in
the structure of Japanese society.
A 'selection machine'
It is generally accepted that there are no
ethnic divisions within Japanese society,
and regional divisions have diminished as
a result of rapid urbanization and the pow¬
erful impact of the mass media. Also, the
widespread destruction of homes and the
means of production in the Second World
War, together with the subsequent land
reform, meant that the nation was forced to
make a new start at a time when rich and
poor alike were all in equal straits, with
disparities in wealth reduced to a lower
level than almost anywhere in the world.
People were no longer so clearly con¬
scious of a division between "upper" and
"lower" classes; and a kind of classless
society emerged, in which everyone thinks
of himself or herself as middle-class.
With 120,000,000 people forming a sin¬
gle vast group without linguistic or ethnic
differences, with few variations in regional
culture or vertical class divisions, social
mobility is extremely easy for the able
individual. On the other hand, people fear
that if they do not succeed against the
competition, the fall will be limitless.
In this homogeneous society, virtually
the only social identity the individual can
acquire is that derived from education, and
the academic record, including the names
of the schools children have attended, is
an important factor in determining their
career and lifestyle when they reach
adulthood.
As pointed out above, 97 per cent of
young people attend high school, and 48
per cent go on to higher education. Japan
has 5,000 high schools with 4,600,000
students, 500 junior colleges with 400,000
students, and 460 universities with
1 ,800,000 students. With a school, college
and university system on this scale, the
future employers of graduates from these
institutions have to adopt a method of se¬
lection. Some decide to limit their intake to
graduates of specific institutions, which
means that graduates of other universities
are automatically excluded from joining
leading companies and other organiza¬
tions that may otherwise have been their
first choice. In effect, the university en¬
trance examination serves as a first stage
of the examination by which employers
select their new recruits. The entire school
system thus acts as a kind of "selection
machine" for sorting out children's future
potential.
Private lessons
and study groups
The ability to get into a university or
some other institution of higher education
is of crucial importance for a child's social
and economic future. Consequently young
people push themselves to the limits to
pass the entrance examination of the uni¬
versity which offers the best conditions. In
order to prepare their children for university
entrance examinations, parents must first
get them into a high school with a partic¬
ularly good reputation. This means going
to a good middle school first and so the
competition escalates. Many parents send
their children to juku to help them obtain
good marks in the fiercely competitive en¬
trance examinations that exist at every
stage of Japanese education. The chil¬
dren, afraid of being overtaken by their
classmates, are eager to attend these ex¬
tra classes.
The State school system does not sanc¬
tion either the skipping of grades by gifted
children or "failure" on the part of slower
children. Classes are not streamed so as
to separate the able from the less able
pupils. There is thus a wide variety of
attainment within a class; the bright chil¬
dren are not fully stretched, while the
weaker pupils cannot keep up. The bright
children find satisfaction in the lessons
offered by juku which specialize in prepar¬
ing high-fliers for entrance into "elite" uni¬
versities, while other juku cater for those
who find it difficult to keep up with the
ordinary school curriculum, which they
supplement by revising basic subjects in a
way that these children can understand.
As well as the "academic" juku catering
for different levels of attainment, there'are
juku which provide training in the use of the
abacus, or teach brush calligraphy, not to
mention the opportunities for learning af¬
forded by private "studios" offering instruc¬
tion in a variety of skills such as painting,
piano-playing or swimming. Nor is it only
primary and middle school children who
make use of these opportunities. Japan
now has an enormous variety o\juku, "stu¬
dios" and "study circles", which are used
by people in every walk of life. Working
adults and students attend driving schools,
computer programming schools and ac¬
countancy schools, in addition to working
or pursuing their academic studies. Young
men and women belong to a wide range of
"study groups", not only for such activities
as cooking, swimming and tennis, but also
for traditional subjects which predate the
introduction of the modern school system,
such as the tea ceremony, flower arrange¬
ment and handicrafts.
Together with the wide variety of "stu¬
dios" and "study circles", the purely aca¬
demic juku form part of a traditional "pri¬
vate", or unofficial, educational system.
This unofficial system seems to have
evolved spontaneously behind the
scenes, as it were, of the public and official
system, with its uniformity, excessive sup¬
pression of individuality, and lack of
freedom of choice as a means of contrib¬
uting to the development of the
individual.
Japanese education today compels chil¬
dren to devote long hours to study. The
result is that they are deprived of opportu¬
nities to play freely, and to think or test
things out for themselves as individuals,
away from the group. In the competition for
marks In the tests which are an integral
part of school life, the original aims of
education become distorted. It is hardly
surprising that some cannot stand this
fierce competition, and find an outlet for
© Japanese companies provide a wide range of
| in-house training schemes which give their
employees the opportunity to learn new skills
and acquire a high degree ofprofessional mo¬
bility. Left, a workman whose post has been
abolished because of automation is retrained
as an engineer.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
Photo Richard Kalvar © Magnum. Paris
their inability to adapt to test-dominated
education in violence on school premises
or in absenteeism. Both teachers and par¬
ents are fully aware that this kind of educa¬
tion is injurious to children's intellectual,
social, emotional and physical develop¬
ment. However, the system is so en¬
trenched that the minority of educationists,
teachers and parents who would like to
reform it have little chance of success.
Education has now become a major so¬
cial and political issue. A third reform is
being planned, on a scale comparable with
the introduction of a modern school system
in 1872 and the reforms of 1946, the aims
of which were equality and expansion of
educational opportunity. This is in line with
the needs of Japanese society as it rapidly
becomes more "internationalized" and in¬
formation-oriented, and of an economy
and society which is currently in the
process of breaking out of a system of
standardized mass production.
Winning admission to a good university is a
major hurdle for Japanese young people
hoping to achieve social status and material
rewards. Above, prayers inscribed on
wooden tablets have been placed in a Tokyo
shrine by students anxious to succeed in their
examinations.
KAZUO KURIMOTO is a Unesco staff member
specializing in educational administration and
management.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
An interview with Yozo Shiozaki
A 'communications society'
A Unesco Courier interview with
Mr. Yozo Shiozaki, President of
Dentsu France S.A., a subsidiary
of Japan's largest communications
agency, Dentsu Incorporated,
on the part played by the media
in cultural life.
14
Which are the dominant media in Japan
today?
Of the four "mass media" newspapers,
magazines, television and radio the most
powerful is television. There are two chan¬
nels run by the State-owned Japan Broad¬
casting Corporation (NHK), and five com¬
mercial networks. Of the 39 million
households in Japan, 99.7 per cent own at
least one TV set, and the average individu¬
al watches three to five hours daily. Japa¬
nese people are also avid readers. Five
newspapers are read nationwide, two of
them (Yomiuri Shimbun and Asahi Shim-
bun) by over 7 million households each.
Japan's newspaper circulation figures are
among the highest in the world, and read¬
ership is very stable because of the high
percentage of subscribers, who have their
papers delivered to the home. Until the
1970s, newspapers tended to publish arti¬
cles on mainly political and economic top¬
ics written for a predominantly male read¬
ership. But recently more editorial effort
has gone into home life, women's pages,
sport and entertainment. Over 2,000
monthly and 70 weekly magazines are also
published. Radio, which was forced into
the background in the early days of televi¬
sion, has made a comeback with the in¬
troduction of commercial stations, nearly
half of which operate around the clock,
especially in urban areas.
Above, two stills from a publicity film for a
Japanese publisher, announcing the simulta¬
neous publication in 12 countries of a set of
encyclopaedias on the animal world. The
film was awarded the Grand Prix at Cannes
International Advertising Festival 1987.
A forest of shimmering neon signs towers
above street level in the Ginza district of To¬
kyo, left.
What is the role of the media in cultural
life?
The contribution of the media has changed
along with social developments and now
includes the conception and co-ordination
of cultural events as a link between private
industry and the public. For example, as a
communications agency we were one of
the major promoters of both the 1 964 To¬
kyo Olympics and of Expo 70 in Osaka.
More recently, we played a major role in
organizing, producing and promoting the
1985 International Exposition at Tsukuba
on the theme "Science and Technology for
Man at Home", which was sponsored by
the Japanese Government and twenty-
eight private corporations. The mass pub¬
licity given to this event encouraged some
20 million people to visit the displays, and
they found that high tech developments
were perhaps not as remote from their
daily lives as they had thought.
Which other activities attract private
sponsorship and extensive media pro¬
motion?
The first official sumo wrestling tournament
outside Japan, for example, which was
sponsored by a television network in 1 986.
The Japanese people were delighted that
a sumo tournament should take place
abroad, because the sport is very close to
the roots of their national identity. Probably
everyone in Japan watches the wrestling
bouts which are broadcast on the State
television network every day during tour¬
nament seasons. It's a spiritual sport, more
akin to the mind than to the body. Similar
coverage is given to baseball, as the Yomi¬
uri actually owns the "Giants", a famous
baseball team in Japan. A year ago the first
concert hall in Japan to be devoted to
classical music was opened in the centre
of Tokyo, sponsored by a beverage manu¬
facturer and distributor. Other cultural and
educational activities which attract spon¬
sorship are theatre and cinema perform¬
ances, art exhibitions, courses for the pub¬
lic, creation of green spaces in cities,
publishing, scholarships and international
exchanges, to name but a few. The activ-
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
¡ties of Japanese companies abroad are a
new trend in this booming phenomenon.
Another good example of such commercial
enterprise is a series of events entitled
"Close-up of Japan", sponsored by a large
Japanese group. In an attempt to introduce
Japan's modern culture to other countries,
this programme was held in San Francisco
in 1983, London in 1985, and Paris in
1987.
Have the Japanese people now
achieved a lifestyle which reconciles
the influence of Western culture with
their own traditions?
By and large, yes. At the end of the Second
World War, Japan in many respects was
indeed learning from the West, particularly
from the United States, about education,
culture, business ways, and so on. Now
things have definitely changed. The Japa¬
nese are striving to express their own iden¬
tity in culture, fashion and many other
fields and I have a feeling that perhaps this
new identity is in a small way beginning to
influence the West. Up until now perhaps
Japanese people were too involved in eco¬
nomic affairs, in pushing up their GNP, to
do much else, but if they want any kind of
self-fulfilment they now have to divert
some of their attention from economic af¬
fairs into building up their cultural heritage.
They have made a strict reappraisal of
their lifestyle and they wonder whether
materialism, the mere fact of owning
things, of consuming things, is going to be
enough to bring them happiness.
Do you consider that Japan is the lead¬
ing communications society today?
If you consider the technical aspects, such
as press readership, TV watching habits,
the number of telephones or computers,
Japan certainly is as much an information
and communications society as, for exam¬
ple, the United States. But it is also true
thai-Japan has just started privatizing its
telecommunications systems, and there is
still plenty of room for development. Our
company, for example, is now working on
advanced software for cable and satellite
broadcasting, and this year we have set up
a new subsidiary, the "Dentsu Institute for
Human Studies". One of the first themes
that this Institute will be working on is
"Searching for the Identity of Japan". A
symposium on this subject was organized
recently, as one of the numerous activities
to be developed in the future. We are in the
throes of a major upheaval in society. Per¬
haps the Japanese people were the first to
see this and to search for ways to cope
with it, and perhaps in this respect they can
be said to be holding the mirror to show
the world what the twenty-first century
may be like.
Left, a Yokozuna (grand champion) of sumo. This ancient style of
wrestling, thought to have originated in Japan nearly 2,000 years ago,
has close associations with the Shinto religion. Today sumo is a mass
spectator sport, at which several hundred specially selected athletes
make their living. Six major championships are held annually, attract¬
ing immense crowds and massive media coverage.
Characters from a Japanese cartoon film,
Come Down from the Tree, Bunna, which
was created for the celebrations marking the
30th anniversary of Japan's admission to the
United Nations in 1956. The modern fable on
which the film is based, by the well-known
Japanese writer Tsutomu Minakami, relates
how Bunna the frog learns of the interdepen¬
dence of all living beings.
Photo © Tokyu Agency International, Inc.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
From moonbeams to lasers
The art of making light work
Above and right, traditional lamp of the Edo
period (17th-19th centuries) known as an
ariake lamp or night-light. The word ariake
designates the pale moon which can be seen at
dawn and, by extension, dawn itself.
by Motoko Ishii
LIGHTING devices of great beauty,
using handmade paper, were de¬
vised at an early date in Japan. A
flame produced by burning a candle or
lamp oil was screened by a paper shade so
as to diffuse a soft light equally In every
direction. Chöchin, collapsible lanterns
with a paper shade stuck over a bamboo
frame, and andon, standing lanterns with a
similar paper-covered frame, in this case
Japan has many Shinto and Buddhist sects,
and it is possible to practise several forms of
beliefsimultaneously. Below, the Sanctuary of
the Shinji Shùmei-kai Shinto sect at Shiga.
Lighting heightens the majesty of the site, add¬
ing to the atmosphere.
made of thin strips of wood, were devel¬
oped and widely used in the Edo period
(1603-1867).
Many of these traditional means of light¬
ing were highly ingenious and well-
designed. Examples are the Odawara chö¬
chin,'1 a portable lamp tha» could be folded
so as not to take up sps^e on a journey, the
ariake andon (night-light), the light of which
could be reduced by covering it with a
wooden cube with apertures in its panels
shaped like the crescent moon, or the
tsuji-zndon (crossroad lanterns), covered
with a tiny roof, that were placed at cross¬
roads and street corners to help people
find their way.
Not only Japan but other Far Eastern
countries such as China and Korea have
from ancient times shown a special appre¬
ciation of moonlight. On the nights when
the moon was full people came together to
drink saké and celebrate the beauty of the
moon, and many fine poems describing
such scenes have survived in both Japan
and China. I believe that this traditional
love of moonlight underlay the develop¬
ment of the beautiful lighting devices that
were produced in Japan during the Edo
period.
With the arrival of Western civilization in
the Meiji period (1868-1912), gas and elec¬
tric lamps made a dramatic impact. Many
people were astounded by the brilliant light
of the arc lamps that were installed in
Tokyo's famous Ginza district in early Mei¬
ji, an event commemorated in ukiyo-e
prints of the time. Electric lighting spread
rapidly from the late 1880s onwards, but
for cost reasons most houses had only one
lamp in each room, suspended from the
centre of the ceiling. The oil lamps of the
Edo period, which stood on the floor and
could be moved to wherever was conve¬
nient, disappeared altogether, and for a
long period "one room, one light" was the
standard practice.
Innovations were introduced into Japa¬
nese lighting after the Second World War.
In the black-out during the war years, with
their constant air raids and drastic short-
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
ages of food and other supplies, the Japa¬
nese experienced both physical and spiri¬
tual darkness. They saw a symbol of peace
in the bright white light of the fluorescent
lamps that began to be manufactured soon
after the war.
First used in industry, which was then
struggling to get back on its feet, these
lamps came into domestic use in the
1950s. The number of households choos¬
ing this form of lighting for the family room
known as the chanoma (dining/living area)
grew steadily, and one product of this peri¬
od was the circular fluorescent lamp
(called the "Circline"2 in Japan), an al¬
ternative to the conventional straight
fluorescent tube which is unique to Japan
and is still in widespread use.
The spread of fluorescent lighting raised
the illumination levels of offices, factories,
stations, banks and all kinds of public
buildings until they were high even by inter¬
national standards. Lighting techni¬
cians aimed at a shadow-free illuminated
space in which the light was bright and
evenly balanced. In this they had support
from industry, whose first priority was
to increase production, and also from
architects.
The 1970s saw a second wave of in¬
novation, initiated by Expo 70, the In¬
ternational Exposition held at Osaka In
1970. Eighty-five pavilions were erected
on a 351 -hectare site at Senri, a suburb of
Osaka. Seventy-seven nations took part in
Expo 70, which attracted an astonishing
number of visitors some 64 million. One
of the Expo's most popular attractions was
the beauty of its illuminations at night.
I was commissioned to design the light¬
ing for five sites at Expo 70 the Electric
Power Pavilion, the Art Gallery, the Takara
Beautilion, the roof of the Housing Capsule
in the "Symbol Zone", and the Japanese
Garden. My proposals involved rejecting
the concept of uniformly and brightly lit
space which had until then been the guid¬
ing principle of lighting in Japanese archi¬
tecture, in favour of the idea of a more
"animated" space using both light and
shade with a moderate level of brightness;
a form of lighting that would form a link
between people and architecture.
In the Electric Power Pavilion, a variety
of different light sources were used
throughout the building, and a programme
was devised for continuous blinking on and
off and for modulating each source. In the
Art Gallery a wave-like effect was attempt¬
ed, by setting clear bulbs into the glazed
framework of the large foyer and alternat¬
ing different circuits in the vertical direction,
the variations in light intensity making it
appear as if the space were "breathing". In
the Japanese Garden, on the other hand,
the effect we aimed at was that of a tran¬
quil, gentle light. In all these sites no effort
was spared to create new, experimental
forms of architectural lighting. Expo 70
was the scene of many other such experi¬
ments, which found wide acceptance.
Interest in lighting as a source of enjoy¬
ment and of beauty, as distinct from its
merely functional role, has grown in Japan
ever since. I have been involved, with lead¬
ing architects such as Kenzö Tange, Yosh-
inobu Ashiwara and Kiyonori Kikutake, in
numerous design projects including hotels,
Created in 1976 for an insurance company,
this chandelier (diameter 6 metres) is made of
specially processed aluminium panels with in¬
candescent mini-bulbs, mercury-vapour lamps
und fluorescent tubes. It was designed so that
the light level can be varied at will, not only for
aesthetic reasons but to save energy.
1 . Odawara: a city in the Kanagawa department, some
80 km from Tokyo. The lamp described here was
invented in the 16th century by Jinzaemon. a native of
Odawara.
2. Like many other terms in modern Japanese, this
word (originally a trade name) is based on a very free
adaptation of English words, in this case "circular line".
Editor. 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
theatres, embassies and commercial
buildings.
In the mid-1970s the Japanese econo¬
my, which for some time after Expo 70 had
appeared to be in good shape, was hit by
the dramatic rise in oil prices. The profes¬
sion of lighting design was directly affected
by the oil crisis. Chandeliers were switched
off, as were all the light bulbs in ornamental
lighting brackets beyond the number need¬
ed to provide a bare minimum of light.
Even the spectacular neon illuminations in
the Ginza district went dark. For those
involved with lighting, like myself, it was a
heartbreaking time.
By the end of the 1 970s, however, Japan
had recovered from the oil shock. While
due regard was still paid to the need to
save energy, bright lights reappeared in
shops and offices. Incandescent lamps
with a high power consumption were re¬
placed in many cases by HID (high in¬
tensity discharge) lamps, and cold cathode
tubes and neon lighting became increas¬
ingly popular.
With the 1980s came a general prefer¬
ence for greater balance in lighting design.
Another trend can be seen in the growing
number of buildings requiring special
forms of lighting, particularly religious
buildings.
The Shiga Sacred Garden of the Shinji
Shümei-kai, a Shinto religious body, was
completed in 1983. At the centre is a sanc¬
tuary to the movement's founder.
Within the vast internal space, which is
40 metres high, a diffused light, mostly
from concealed sources, creates a sense
of solemnity and awe. The lighting here
plays a similar role to that of an atmo¬
sphere of appropriate temperature and hu¬
midity.
On the night of the ceremony marking
the completion of the sanctuary, I put on a
laser beam show in the plaza in front of the
building. One of the greatest discoveries of
the present century, the laser beam is a
powerful, artificially "bunched" or nar¬
rowed ray of light beamed in a single direc¬
tion. Using laser beams as a medium for
"free composition", we succeeded that
night in giving light a new form of expres¬
sion in endowing light with an existence
of its own, independent of architectural
space.
My current task is to create hew forms of
light in all kinds of architectural space,
using different light sources and a variety
of control techniques. At the same time, I
hope to revive the traditional Japanese
sensibility to lighting, with its special feeling
for the beauty of moonlight.
Colours to whet the pal
JAPANESE cuisine, it has been
claimed, is a feast not only for the
taste-buds, but also for the eyes; in
a case like this, I would even be tempted
to say: not just a feast for the eyes but,
better still, for the spirit! A contemplative
state of mind is induced by the quiet har¬
mony between the glow of candles flicker¬
ing in the gloom and the reflections in the
lacquerware. Some years ago, the great
writer Söseki1 celebrated in his Kusa-mak-
ura2 the colours of the yökan? and in a
sense these colours are also, surely, aids
to meditation. Consider their cloudy sur¬
face, semi-translucent like jade, the im¬
pression that they convey of drawing sun¬
light into their very substance and holding
in their depths a tremulous glimmer like a
dream; consider the deep harmony of col¬
our tones, and their complexity; you will
not find these in any piece of Western
confectionery. To compare them to some
cream or custard would be superficial and
naive.
Now take a lacquer cake dish and set
upon it the subtly-tinted harmony of a
yökan, place it in the shadows so that its
colour is scarcely discernible and you will
find that its power of focusing contempla¬
tion is even stronger. And when at last you
carry to your lips this cool, smooth sub¬
stance, you will feel as if part of the dark¬
ness of the room, solidified into a morsel
of sweetness, were melting on the tip of
your tongue, and in this yökan which is,
after all, rather insipid you will discover
an unusual depth that enhances its
taste.
In all the countries of the world, efforts
have doubtless been made to create
pleasing colour combinations with food,
tableware and even the walls in the back¬
ground; at any rate, if Japanese dishes
are served in surroundings that are too
well-lit, or in crockery that is predomin¬
antly white, they lose half their attraction.
Take the red misoA soup, for example, that
we eat every morning; look at the colour of
it, and you will have no difficulty in under¬
standing that it was invented in the dark
houses of a bygone age. One day, when I
had been invited to a tea party, I was given
a serving of miso, and when I saw that
murky, clay-coloured soup that I had al¬
ways eaten without paying it much atten¬
tion when I saw it by the soft glow of
candlelight, lying like a calm pool in the
curve of the black lacquer bowl, I discov¬
ered that it had real depth and the most
appetizing of hues.
Shôyu,5 a sticky, glistening sauce, also
gains much from being seen in the shad¬
ows, and is perfectly at home in darkness,
especially if one follows the custom of the
Kyoto region for seasoning raw fish, or
pickled or boiled vegetables, and uses the
thick variety called tamari. Similarly, white
miso, töfu,6 kamaboko,7 steamed sweet
potato cakes, white fish all white foods,
in short, are not shown off to advantage if
their surroundings are brightly lit. Rice,
above all: the very sight of it, served in a
shiny black lacquer box placed in a dark
corner, is aesthetically pleasing and at the
same time it whets the appetite. Flawless
rice, cooked to perfection, heaped in a
black box and giving off hot steam as soon
as one lifts the lid, every grain gleaming
like a pearl: there is not a Japanese alive
who can remain indifferent to this offering
of sheer goodness. All this goes to show
that our cuisine is meant for a shadowy
setting and has an enduring bond with
darkness.
Jun'lchiro Tanizaki
Extract from In'ei raisan (1933; "In Praise of
Shadows") by Jun'ichirö Tanizaki (1886-
1965).
1 . Söseki. Natsume Söseki (1867-1916), one of the
greatest Japanese novelists of the early 20th cen¬
tury.
2. Kusa-makura, "The Three-Cornered World" (a
poetic expression meaning literally "the grass
headrest", associated In classical literature with the
notion of a journey), a novel by Natsume Söseki,
published in 1906.
3. Yökan. jelly-like confectionery similar to crystal¬
lized fruit. The basic ingredients are bean paste
with added sugar and agar-agar seaweed, fla¬
voured with fruit: chestnut, persimmon, plum,
etc.
4. Miso, a purée of fermented soya beans, boiled
and mashed, with added salt and yeast. It is a basic
ingredient for a soup that is always served for
breakfast.
5. Shôyu, a brown sauce with a fermented soya
base, the essential condiment used in Japanese
cooking.
6. Tôfu. a whitish curd obtained from soya beans
that have been crushed and boiled, then strained
and thickened with a coagulent. Töfu is used in
many dishes, but it can be eaten alone, with various
condiments.
7. Kamaboko, a firm pâté made from the flesh of
certain white fish, steamed and then dried. Slices of
kamaboko are found in a variety of dishes. Editor.
18
MOTOKO ISHII studied industrial design at To¬
kyo University of Fine Arts before specializing in
the new field of lighting designand installation,
in which her work at the 1970 Osaka Exposition
attracted widespread attention. She has won an
international reputation for such projects as the
lighting of the Okinawa Ocean Expo '75 and of
several pavilions at the Tsukuba International
Exhibition in 1985, and has been invited to work
in many countries.
Colour page right
"The beauty of a Japanese room is created solely by the relationship between shadow of
varying opacity, and does not depend on accessories or fillings... We delight in this delicate
clarity derivedfrom changing outer light, fixed to the surface of twilight-coloured walls, barely
preserving a last vestige of life. " (Junichiro Tanizaki). Photo shows detail of a tea-house built
at Osaka in 1985 by architect Tadao Ando. With its simplicity and purity ofform, it is faithful
to the Japanese aesthetic tradition.
Photo © Mitsuo M;ilMiok:i,'77ir Japtm Ardjiwit. Tokyo
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Cities a
THE urban tradition which arose in
Western Asia and spread across Eu¬
rope has handed down to us the im¬
age of a town or city standing out sharply
against a rural or natural background. Mod¬
ern urban development has blurred this con¬
trast by extending suburbs into the country¬
side and increasing the number of green
spaces in towns, but this trend has not gone
so far as to obliterate the antithesis that
Europeans unconsciously establish between
the town and nature. The city is still at one
pole, the symbol of a constructed and artificial
environment, and it is towards the opposite
pole, that of the natural world, that owners of
country cottages and holiday-makers are
constantly drawn even if that symbolic pole
is often, in reality, scarcely less artificial than
the town they leave behind them.
However, this typically European pattern is
not universal. In particular, it does not fit
Japan. Japanese towns and cities, if only
because they have never been systematical¬
ly enclosed by ramparts, have never been as
cut off from their rural surroundings as those
of Europe or China. Differences in population
density between town and country have, like¬
wise, always been relatively slight.
But the crucial factor is probably the signif¬
icance of towns and cities for Japanese peo¬
ple in the relationship between nature and
culture. Towards the end of the ancient peri¬
od (3rd to 7th centuries AD), the association
between towns and civilization was partic¬
ularly strong in Japan, since both had been
simultaneously introduced from China. How¬
ever, as a result of the relative suddenness of
their introduction, the urban phenomenon
and civilized manners (urbanity) were super¬
imposed on an indigenous view of nature
which was deeply animistic, and which repre¬
sented the cultural order and the natural or¬
der as a continuum. This strong inclination
was to exert a twofold influence on Japanese
urbanity: symbolically, on urban manners,
through the expression of a refined feeling for
nature in poetry and in architecture, and eco¬
logically, on the material components of the
Colour page left
urban environment, and in particular the cen¬
tral role that vegetation would play. Over the
centuries and right up to the present day, the
Japanese town has always given expression
to nature.
The courtly and the natural
The brilliant civilization of the Heian period
(8th to 12th centuries) revolved around the
Royal Court in Kyoto (then called Heian). This
was a time of flowering in the arts and litera¬
ture which produced the Genji monogatari,' a
masterpiece of world literature. Just as the
English word courtesy is derived from
"court", so the Japanese language would
describe elegant manners and delicacy of
taste by the word miyabi, derived from miya
meaning "royal palace". The word miyako
("capital", i.e. Heian) has the same origin.
And yet this homology points to a radical
difference of outlook. In English, words such
as "politeness" (from the Greek polis: town or
city), "civility" (from the Latin cives: citizen of
Rome) and "urbanity" (from the Latin word
urbs) suggest primarily relationships between
people in the artificial environment of town or
city. "Courtly" originally referred to the lan¬
guage of lovers. Miyabi has a quite different
connotation; it concerns not the essentially
polite or politic (from polis) relations between
human beings, but the sensitive and aes¬
thetic relationship of human beings with
nature.
Indeed, miyabi of which the Genji monog-
atari has left us a detailed description was
particularly apparent in the art of expressing a
feeling for nature in poetry, in dress or in
gardens. The criterion by which the town-
bred or civilized person was judged was his
or her capacity to fully appreciate cicadas, the
moon, or maple trees
Gardens and tea pavilions
By the closing years of the Heian period,
this expression of feeling for nature had be¬
come stylized. It was given a new lease of
life, however, by the experience of solitude in
"The basic model of a Shinto sanctuary ... is a wooden building sunounded by trees. On the
one hand, this sacred wood (chinju-no-mori) symbolizes the mountain forest, in the depths of
which is the fountain-head of divinity ... On the other, it is an ecological representation of
primeval nature, for since their vegetation must not be cut down, the chinju-no-mori have
become relics of the forest of shining leaves which once covered the plains of Japan. " I'holo
shows a Shinto temple at Kyoto.
I'holo Ï homas Hopkcr (£: M.iiMiiun. Pun*.
nature
by A ugustin Berque
the mountains, as is borne out by the poetry
of Saigyö,2 who deliberately abandoned the
life of the capital. New aesthetic values were
emerging which apparently had nothing to do
with the town: on the contrary. For example,
in his Höjö-ki,3 Kamo no Chömei gives a
blueprint for the hermit's life, in the precarious
shelter of a hut measuring "ten foot
square" only one-tenth of the size of the
house in Kyoto that he had left behind.
Two or three centuries later, in the Muro-
machi and Momoyama periods (14th to 16th
centuries), these supremely anti-urban mod¬
els would reach their highest form of expres¬
sion in the city, in the tea pavilion (chashltsu)
and the little garden leading to it (roji). By
virtue of its small size and the materials of
which it is made, the chashltsu is an urban
metaphor for the mountain shelter, a symbol
of the precariousness of life in this world.
Similarly, the roji is, with its stepping stones,
reminiscent of the harsh and rugged moun¬
tain track which leads to the pure realm of
Buddha-hood.
These forms of expression themselves
profoundly influenced the aesthetics of the
Japanese house, especially the seventeenth-
century warrior dwellings (büke yashiki) of
the capital of the shogun, Edo (the future
Tokyo). These dwellings served in their turn
as the prototype of the small detached
houses, each with its garden, in which many
of the inhabitants of Tokyo live today.
Life in the midst of nature has thus been
the inspiration for the ideal dwelling in the
world's biggest city and, to an even greater
extent in Japan's provincial towns, where
there is not such a shortage of space.
1. The Genji monogatari ("The Tale of Genji"), a
masterly novel in the classical Japanese tradition, was
written at the beginning of the 1 1 th century by Murasaki
Shikibu, a lady of the Heian Royal Court at Kyoto.
Packed with intrigue and character studies, the novel is
a remarkable evocation of aristocratic court society
written with an acute "sensitivity to things", in the words
of the 1 8th-century literary scholar Motoori Norinaga.
2. The Buddhist priest-poet Saigyö (1 1 1 8-1 1 90), one of
the most popular poets in Japan, was a great master of
the waka, a traditional Japanese poetic form of 31
syllables. His many works, inspired by his solitary
wanderings, expressed a love of nature and devotion to
Buddhism.
3. In Höjö-ki {The Ten Foot Square Hut, 1970), the
court poet turned Buddhist monk Kamo no Chömei
(1155-1216) gives a series of brief accounts of the
disasters that had befallen Kyoto during his lifetime,
followed by a contrasting description of the natural
beauty and peace of his hermit's life. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
I
22
Ikebana, the art of Japanese flower arrange¬
ment, has highly developed conventions and a
complex symbolism. It began as a religious
ritual in which flowers were offered to the
Buddha, and, like the traditional Japanese tea
ceremony, is a combination of beauty and
austerity. In the words of one master of the art,
ikebana must "with a little water and a flower¬
ing branch, evoke flowing streams and vast
mountains" . Ikebana is still widely taught.
Earthquake resistant skyscrapers of concrete,
steel and glass dominate Tokyo's Shinjuku
business quarter, right.
Wilderness and sacred groves
All these forms of dwelling owe much to
Buddhism, and through Buddhism (among
other channels) to Chinese civilization. Nev¬
ertheless, the unique expression of the indig¬
enous animist heritage lives on, in partner¬
ship with the Shinto religion. The holy places
of Shinto range from a rock in a remote valley
to a sanctuary in the middle of Tokyo, and
from the bough of a tree to a sacred enclo¬
sure of several hectares: they are to be found
on every scale throughout Japan. Yet all have
one feature in common: they refer to nature,
which they express both symbolically,
through the mythology attaching to the divin¬
ities worshipped there, and ecologically,
through their vegetation.
The basic model of a Shinto sanctuary
(jinja), both in the towns and in the country¬
side, is a wooden building surrounded by
trees. On the one hand, this sacred wood
(chinju-no-mori) symbolizes the mountain for¬
est (yama), in the depths of which is the
fountain-head of divinity; the value attached
to depths (oku) is also expressed in the archi-
Ü	i
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
tecture of religious buildings. On the other
hand, it is an ecological representation of
primeval nature, for since their vegetation
must not be cut down, the chinju-no-mori
have become relics of the forest of shining
leaves which once covered the plains of Ja¬
pan (except in the North-East).
It is true that the sacred woods have not
been preserved as fully as they might have
been. Many have been nibbled away by mod¬
ern urban development. Nevertheless, in the
heart of the biggest cities they still keep
Japanese culture firmly rooted in the natural
world which was there before towns existed.
The heart of nature
Despite its love of nature, Japanese socie¬
ty has been unable to prevent, in our time, a
serious deterioration of its natural heritage,
particularly from an aesthetic point of view.
This development is only superficially a para¬
doxical one. Among its causes are the Japa¬
nese people's lack of interest in politics, in
other words, in the principles governing the
régime under which the deterioration in ques
tion took place. This is an attitude which, as
we have already seen, expresses a very
ancient and very deep-seated tendency in
Japanese culture.
All the same, the deterioration of the envi¬
ronment has aroused local protest in the form
of the so-called "residents' movements"
(jùmin undo) which proliferated in the late
1960s and eventually succeeded in introduc¬
ing strict legal measures for environmental
protection. Since then, partly as a result of
technological changes and the slow-down of
the economy, less damage is being caused
and there has been a corresponding slacken¬
ing of activity in the residents' movements.
The focus of interest has shifted towards
amenities, which are seen mainly in terms of
greenery. The Tokyo city authorities, for ex¬
ample, are currently implementing a pro¬
gramme to double the amount of green areas
in twenty years. In addition to these ecolog¬
ical improvements to the urban setting, many
inhabitants of Tokyo take out a symbolic
passport to the wilderness by purchasing
honorary citizenship in northern municipal¬
ities such as Hokkaido, which are there
by able to finance the preservation of their
forests.
The theme of nature thus tends to distract
attention from more specifically urban, and
thus even political, problems, such as what is
to be done with the large areas of public land
in the middle of Tokyo, that are being auc¬
tioned off piecemeal to replenish public
funds. The destiny of the heart of the city is
clearly of little interest to the suburban com¬
muters who, every evening, travel back in
their millions to their little houses in a green
setting.
A sense of place
The urban phenomenon is so closely
bound up with the highest values of European
society, such as democracy and civilization,
that it is difficult for a European to imagine
that towns can express other values, or even
that such values can be expressed in other
ways than by towns. However, these conno¬
tations are by no means universal: many
societies (some of which originated in Europe
itself) are untouched by them. Japan is one of
these societies.
The material similarities between the ways
in which human dwellings are clustered to¬
gether in towns and cities throughout the
world tend to disguise the fact that conurba¬
tions differ from one another just as human
societies do.
Instead of confining ourselves to formal
comparisons, and expatiating on the relative
lack of public forums or political debate in
Japanese towns and cities, it would be more
profitable to remember the underlying pro¬
pensities of the culture in question, and to see
that the Japanese counterpart to the Europe¬
an public forum the arena of political dis¬
course, identifiable by its colonnades and
belfries may well be none other than the
sacred grove a place that offers a way back
to primeval nature, typified by the trunks and
foliage of ancient trees; and we should re¬
member that, in both cases, the society in
question is doing no more than giving urban
expression to its own first and guiding princi¬
ple: in one place, the Word; in the other,
Nature.
AUGUSTIN BERQUE, of France, is professor of
cultural geography at the Ecole des Hautes
Etudes en Sciences Sociales, Paris, where he
has also been director of research on modern
Japan. He is currently French Director of the
Maison Franco-Japonaise in Tokyo. Among his
published works on Japanese themes are Vivre
l'espace au Japon (1982) and (as co-author) La
qualité de la ville: urbanité française, urbanité
nippone, 1987. 23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The changing home
Tradition and modernism in domestic architecture
FOR decades the traditional Japanese
house has exercised a fascination on
many architects, and today it gets
plentiful coverage in interior decoration mag¬
azines and art publications.
By Western standards it is not a comfort¬
able place to live in. It is cold in winter and the
people who live in it sit on the bare floor on
mats (tßtami). For the investor it lacks the
reassuring durability of stone. Nevertheless,
because of its design, method of construction
and aesthetic philosophy, it is a rare example
of a complete, complex system.
Because of the wood of which it is built and
the subtle series of transitions between it and
the outer worldthe gardenit stands in
close relation to nature. Because of its
thatched roof, cob walls, and the fact that it is
built on piles, it can stand temperatures of
about 40° accompanied by over 80 per cent
humidity in summer, and its flexible construc¬
tion enables it to absorb earthquake tremors.
With its sliding partitions it can be adapted to
any occasiontwo rooms can be converted
into one by drawing back four paper doors or
fusuma. It is the spatial expression of a form
of social and family organization in which
hierarchical relations between individuals are
strictly governed.
But all this is becoming a thing of the past.
After evolving gradually over many centuries,
the traditional Japanese house is now
scarcely more than a memory in the big cities
like Tokyo and their dormitory suburbs. Pro¬
found and rapid changes in construction
methods and the consequent appearance of
new types of individual and collective dwell¬
ing have revolutionized traditional living hab¬
its since the Second World War.
There are many reasons for this change. It
by Marc Bourdier
Heavy modern furnishings and fittings seem
an encumbrance in the traditional Japanese
house with its characteristic simplicity and
flexible use ofspace. The practice ofallotting a
specific function to each room and separating
rooms with concrete walls instead of mobile
screens makes the amount of living space seem
smaller.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
is not due only to Western influence, although
the latter is responsible for the appearance of
the bed in 42 per cent of Japanese homes,
where it coexists with the traditional bedding
(futon) which is put away in a cupboard (oshi-
ire) every morning after exposure to the sun.
A bed takes up. a lot of space in a small
apartment (the average area of a Tokyo flat is
58 m2).
Chairs, which were not found in Japanese
homes before the war, have also come from
the West. Nowadays table and chairs of
Western type can often be seen in one room
and the traditional low table and cushions in
another. This duality can be explained by the
relatively low ceilings of mass-produced
dwellings as well as by force of habit. The
volume of a room is perceived differently
depending on whether one is seated on the
floor or on a chair. Likewise, more people can
be accommodated on cushions around a low
table than on chairs around a Western-style
table.
Nevertheless, most of the changes in Ja¬
panese living habits are of local origin.
Whereas in the past people would sleep, eat
or study in the same room, in modern dwell¬
ings each room is assigned a single purpose.
This is due to the concern for better hygiene
which grew up in pre-war Japan and led to
the idea that people should sleep and eat in
different rooms.
The inventors of this idea expected that
there would be a big increase in the surface
area of mass-produced dwellings after the
war. But they were wrong. Partly because of
the concentration of the population in big
cities, the average surface area of rented
apartments is now 43 m2. All the rooms are
small and each has only one function. If they
communicated with each other as in the past,
their smallness would be tolerable. But the
use of reinforced concrete in the construction
of apartment blocks has brought an increase
in the number of walls in the living area,
instead of the mobile partitions found in the
traditional wooden type of dwelling. More¬
over, the new building code which came into
force in the 1 950s requires that small wooden
houses be capable of resisting earthquake
tremors and not merely absorbing them as
before. Here again one of the technical solu¬
tions has been to increase the number of
solid walls.
Nowadays Western visitors to a Japanese
home will probably find their eyes drawn to
certain typical features and habits which
seem to have survived, such as taking off
one's shoes in the hall and walking on tatami
mats in certain rooms, or the traditional cor¬
ner alcove (tokonoma). which now accommo¬
dates the television set instead of the floral
arrangement (ikebana) as in the past. Such
"exotic" features hide the fact that these
concrete dwellings, which are heated in win¬
ter and air-conditioned in summer, are a
source of previously unknown inconve¬
niences and. as recent surveys have shown,
are a source of stress to people of rural
origin who have been accustomed to a diffe¬
rent way of life.
Japanese housing and life style may not
have become completely Westernized, but
they have undergone a considerable trans¬
formation.
The traditional Japanese house (above) is a
fragile dwelling which blends into its natural
surroundings. Its occupants can experience the
rhythm of the changing seasons and feel the
sense of "impermanence" which is fundamen¬
tal to Buddhism. Translucent sliding outer
panels diffuse light and open directly on to a
garden which is a composition designed to he
seen, like a picture, front inside the house.
MARC BOURDIER, French architect, is a mem¬
ber of a team ol specialists engaged on a Fran¬
co-Japanese co-operative research programme
on the quality of the urban environment in To¬
kyo. He is the author of several published works,
including "Housing Production and Living Con¬
ditions, the First Subsidized Housing in Japan.
1924- 1942 "and "The Problem of Urban Housing
in Japan ". 25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
A large foreigner
in search of space
by James Kirkup
M
A crowd of rush-hour passengers being packed
into a subway train by an attendant
| OST Japanese subway and com¬
muter trains have their seats in
the form of long benches on each
side of the carriage. They are quite com¬
fortably upholstered in hard-wearing
green, red or blue plush. I suspect that the
reason for such seating arrangements is to
allow as many people as possible to stand
during the rush hours, which in the big
cities seem to last all day long. People
queue up quite docilely on the platforms
facing the sign on the opposite platform,
just above the tracks, indicating exactly
where the train doors will open automat¬
ically: and Japanese trains always stop
exactly in the correct place.
26
But as soon as the doors open, there is a
general stampede to enter the cars and get
a seat. Passengers who want to get off
sometimes have difficulty in doing so, and
have to fight their way out against the solid
mass of those desperate to get on. Small
children, perhaps trained by their parents,
are expert queue-jumpers who insinuate
themselves into the trains before less
quick-footed grown-ups and bag whatever
empty seats there may be. Nor do they
intend to give them up to their elders and
betters. Each carriage has a few seats
marked "Silver Seats" ostensibly for Ja¬
pan's rapidly-ageing silver-haired popula¬
tion, but these signs are never observed.
This kind of behaviour, in a people re¬
nowned for politeness, used to puzzle me.
Where are the exquisite manners of the tea
ceremony and the grand social occasion,
the almost Quaker-like self-effacement of
the audience at the Nô theatre or of the
practitioners of Zen meditation? But now I
understand that all this rushing and push¬
ing to get the last vacant seat on the
subway is a national characteristic owing
its existence simply to the lack of space in
Japan for each individual. A subway seat,
to most Japanese, represents a bit of that
precious space that has to be conquered
and hung on to by hook or by crook: if you
don't seize it, someone else will.
Japanese people have the enviable gift
of being able to sleep anywhere, at any
time of the day. One can observe this
unique ability especially in trains: someone
will grab a seat, fold his arms, lower his
head and at once drift off into the Land of
Nod. No one ever disturbs a sleeper, even
though he may be taking up more space on
the seat than an individual is entitled to.
Quite often such sleepers abandon their
heads on the convenient shoulders of the
stranger sitting next to them: when this
happens to me, I am very happy, for I
consider it a privilege to support a sleep¬
er's head in a land where foreigners are
often kept at arm's length. Some young
Lack of space is a persistent problem for
Japanese society and living quarters are often
cramped. Right, photomontage of a modern
prefabricated apartment block.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
people, not as shameless as the children
sprawling on the seats, pretend to sleep in
order to avoid giving up their hard-won
space to some feeble old lady or gentle¬
man hanging hopefully over them from the
white plastic rings dangling like gymnastic
equipment from the roof of the carriage.
But there is another, subtler reason why
young people do not willingly give up their
seats to the elderly and the infirm. On the
rare occasions when I have seen a young
man or woman do so, usually abruptly,
without grace, the unusual action draws
astonished looks from the other passen¬
gers and no Japanese likes to attract
attention. Moreover, the old lady to whom
the seat Is offered will not accept it with a
simple bow or word of thanks: instead she
will make quite a performance of it, bowing
and smiling repeatedly at this now highly
embarrassed youth and uttering a flow of
very high-class expressions of gratitude
and long formula phrases of noble-sound¬
ing politeness before allowing herself final¬
ly to accept the offer and settle herself,
straight-backed, on the very edge of the
seat, continuing to nod and smile at the
young man who is trying to move as far
away from her as possible in the packed
train. If he cannot move, and is stuck in
front of the beneficiary of his well-bred
behaviour, the old lady may insist on carry¬
ing his sports bag or attaché case on her
knees. Many a youth has got off the train at
the next stop in order to escape such
attentions from the delighted senior citizen,
resolving, as he waits for the next train to
his destination, never to give up his seat to
anyone again.
Those who are unsuccessful in obtain¬
ing a seat try to obtain the next best
thing a steel pole, handle or strap to hold
on to. The white plastic rings, often grubby
with newsprint, are also expressions of
desired territory, and some people insist on
hanging on to two of them, one in each
hand, in order to assert their territorial right
to a modicum of personal space. And they
hang on to their plastic rings to the very last
moment, even after the train has stopped
at their destination, when they finally de¬
cide reluctantly to let the ring go: I have
often been struck sharply over the nose by
one of these suddenly-abandoned rings as
I follow its former possessor off the train.
The Japanese go on about their lack of
space all the time. The unfortunate term
"rabbit hutches" has been applied by
Western critics to the exiguous space of
houses and apartments in Japan, to the
amusement of the Japanese, who believe
there is a rabbit, not a man, in the moon.
Space is at a premium because of the
abnormally high price of available land for
building, a price that has recently been
reaching dizzying heights. Yet Western
critics seem to forget that in the West, too,
there are many people living in conditions
worse than any rabbit hutch, living entire
lives in a single hotel room or bed-sitter or
caravan.
The Japanese at least make the very
best of what little space they have in their
houses. A six-mat tatami room can be
made to look quite spacious if the only
furniture in it is one small low table, and if
the seats, in the form of five (never six) flat
square cushions are neatly stacked in a
corner. The only other objects in such a
traditional room, still found in even the
most modern "manshuns" or apartments,
might be a hanging scroll and a flower
arrangement. True luxury is the sense of
uncluttered space.
Unfortunately, many houses and apart¬
ments now have several "Western-style"
rooms with wooden, carpeted floors, and
such rooms are usually overflowing with
cumbersome Western furniture, pianos,
organs, sideboards and all the latest la¬
bour-saving devices and electronic gad¬
gets. Such rooms, with their furniture
draped in antimacassars, look curiously
Victorian In their un-Japanese clutter of
bibelots and étagères and bird-cages.
There is hardly space to swing a cat.
The Japanese are being urged to buy
more Japanese products in order to reduce
the very high level of their savings, help the
languishing economy and regulate the bal¬
ance of payments.
But they have no more room in which to
put new purchases, unless they throw out
perfectly good items that the latest prod¬
ucts have made slightly out of date. Not far
from the spacious apartment I, as an extra-
large foreigner, am allowed to occupy,
there is a small graveyard of used TV sets,
washing machines, refrigerators, radios,
computers and piles of other still quite
usable junk cast out by this throw-away
society desperate to find space for the
never-ending flow of new products. Poor
foreigners can often be seen scavenging
among all this valuable rubbish, retrieving
items for their own crowded apartments or
for sale or barter in the second-hand shops
that have at last begun to be popular.
My own three rooms, living room and
kitchen contain only the minimum of mod¬
est furniture, but my space is awash with
books, magazines and all the scribbled
chaos of a poet's life. I have tried offering
all my manuscripts and notebooks to Japa¬
nese university libraries, but they, too, are
short of space and have trouble in accom¬
modating even a fraction of the thousands
of books and periodicals published in Ja¬
pan every month. Ordinary household
trash is collected twice a week, but one
cannot put out anything bulky, so about
once every ten days there is a special
bottles-and-cans collection, all carefully
sorted and graded.
Traditional arts like the tea ceremony
and flower arrangement are elegant and
beautiful attempts to impose temporary or¬
der and spaciousness on chaos and
crowding. And even in the rush hour I have
often observed gracious manners on the
packed trains, as when someone seeing
that people are not sitting quite close
enough together will stand in front of those
seated and give an appealing little bow,
whereupon the others will squeeze togeth¬
er to make room for another. I have
learned this technique myself. But only too
often, when a space has been made for
me, I find I am too big for it a somewhat
embarrassing situation but one which ap¬
peals to the good-natured sense of humour
of the Japanese. At such moments, I rather
enjoy the lack of space: but it's awful if my
neighbour kindly gets up to give me his
own precious room on the bench. I can
only bow my thanks and sit with lowered
head on the edge of my seat until the next
stop.
JAMES KIRKUP, a British poet and translator
who has lived in Japan since 1958, is professor
of comparative literature at Kyoto University of
Foreign Studies. He is the author of many prose
works on Japan and the Far East and of many
volumes of poetry, the most recent of which is
The Sense of the Visit (Sceptre Press, 1984).
Much of his work has been translated into Japa¬
nese. With the contemporary Japanese com¬
poser Minoro Miki he created the first kabuki
opera, An Actor's Revenge, the most recent
production of which was in April 1987 at Mun¬
ster, Fed. Rep. of Germany.
Colour page right
A form ofJapanese popular theatre created
at the beginning of the 17th century, kabuki
(from ka = singing, bu = dancing, and ki
= acting) contains elements of theatre, op¬
era and music hall. All the roles, including
female roles, are taken by men. Poster
below left is by a well-known Japanese
graphic artist, Tadanori Yokoo (born
1936). ¡l advertises a kabuki dramatization
by Yttkio Mishima o/Chinsetsu yumihari-
zuki (Crescent Moon: The Adventures of
Tametomo) an adventure tale by Bakin
(1767-1848) performed in Tokyo in 1969.
Top left: the hero of Kagekiyo. a kabuki
play which tells of the struggle of a legend¬
ary 12th-century figure. Taira no Kageki¬
yo, against a mortal enemy of his family.
Top right: a dramatic moment in Ichinota-
ni Futaba Gunki (Chronicle of the Battle
of Ichinotani), an 18th-century kabuki
tragedy. To control his feelings after his
son's death, Sagami grips a piece ofpaper
between his teeth. Bottom right: presenta¬
tion of men's winter fashions by the leading
Japanese couturier Issey Miyake, Tokyo,
1984, took place in a setting designed by his
an director, Tomio Mori.
Photo © Tadanori Yokoo. Tokyo
Photo Bun Glinn © Magnum. Paris
Photo Mike Yamashita © Rapho. Paris
Photo Claude Charlar © ANA. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
IH! »*
/
M 0*
J"
i :
i-*-1
k t
$
M
1
m
«
M
.- . 1
<3*
'r '
^
^
» ¿U^*-*
¥,
J gflft
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
1 «frV
1 %^ «h
MV \^k
m 'Jt--Jï , {
a ftuirX
^
fe
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The high tech explosion
Technological ingenuity,
Japan's home-grown raw material
Three examples of Japanese mastery of minia¬
turization technology. Left to right: an electric
razor, a transistor radio and a camera which
also serves as a key-ring. by Shigeru Kimura
Colour page left
Top: Japan's MOS1 maritime observation
satellite which was successfully launched in
February 1986 by the Japanese Space
Agency. Centre: using cubes, spheres, tri¬
angles and other geometric forms, Japanese
architects created a science fiction setting in
their designs for the pavilions at Expo '85,
an international exhibition held in 1985 at
Tsukttba, 50 km north of Tokyo. Over 20
million people visited the exhibition, the
main theme of which was "Dwellings and
Surroundings and Technology
for Man at Home". Bottom: Japanese tech¬
nicians purify silicon, thin wafers of which
are the starting point for the manufacture of
integrated circuits used in many types of
electronic systems.
Pholo James (¡ritlitlis © Maenum. Paris
Photo Keisuke Ktimaean © Rapho. Pans
Pholo Claude C'harlier © ANA. Paris
IT was not until the 1980s that the high
level of Japanese science and tech¬
nology began to attract worldwide at¬
tention. Up till then, the United States could
boast of its supremacy in these fields; but
at the beginning of the present decade
Japan overtook the USA in several fields:
steel-making, cars, numerically controlled
machine tools, industrial robots and in¬
tegrated circuits.
Imitation and creativity
How is it that Japan has made such
rapid technological advances? Various
reasons can be adduced, the first of which
is the determined adoption by Japanese
engineers of the latest technology avail¬
able in other countries.
Dr. Masaru Ibuka, founder of the Sony
Corporation, is a case in point. When he
was In the United States in 1952, looking
for ideas that might lead to new devel¬
opments in technology, he heard that
Western Electric, Inc. had decided to allow
other companies to make use of its transis¬
tor patent. Dr. Ibuka at once began nego¬
tiating with Western Electric with a view to
obtaining the right to use the information
disclosed in this patent. At that time his
company was very small and little known.
Its achievements in developing tape re¬
corder technology were highly thought of,
however, and no obstacle was raised to his
acquiring the right to use the patent in
question.
During the negotiations, the Western
Electric executives asked him what he pro¬
posed to use transistors for. When he re¬
plied that he wanted to see if he could use
them to make a miniature radio, the Amer¬
icans advised him to give up the idea: the
transistors would be expensive to produce,
and even if he were to succeed in making a
radio with them, they assured him, it would
be no match for the ordinary valve radio,
either technically or cost-wise, so he would
be wasting his time.
Undeterred, Dr. Ibuka returned to Tokyo
and set to work with a small team of re¬
searchers to develop his idea in a lab¬
oratory that was little more than a shack.
Two years later, in the winter of 1954, the
sound of the first transistor radio was
heard. It was badly affected by static, but at
least it was a radio. This transistor radio
was subsequently exported all over the
world, and became very popular.
Until 1949, the metal teeth of the zip
fasteners made by Yoshida Kögyö Ltd.
(YKK), today the world's biggest zip manu¬
facturer, were implanted in their cloth edg¬
ing by hand. In 1950, however, the com¬
pany imported an automatic implanting
machine from the United States. The ma¬
chine was secondhand, but Company 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Japan, which today produces over half the world's output of computer
microchips, has an outstandingly successful electronics industry.
Above, computer components in an "electronic bazaar" in Tokyo's
Akihabara district, which specializes in the sale of electrical and
electronic equipment through outlets ranging from market stalls to
chain-stores employing over 1,000 people.
32
President Tadao Yoshida took it apart,
studied it in detail, and added a series of
improvements, till finally he succeeded in
producing a version which was far superior
to the original. The company reached 'its
present position as the world's number one
producer of zip fasteners in 1960.
It is often said that the Japanese are
very good at imitating other people's ideas,
but short on originality or creativity. But
there is no doubt that without originality
without creative thinking neither that first
transistor radio nor the improved zip fas¬
tener machine would have been possible.
After the Second World War, Japan found
itself lagging behind in science and tech¬
nology. By first assimilating scientific and
technological advances that had been
made overseas, and then adding its own
unique ideas to the expertise thus ac¬
quired, Japan was able to produce finished
products of outstanding quality, and
thereby to win a high reputation in world
markets.
Japanese originality can also be seen in
the small home video recorders, now found
throughout the world, that were developed
by two Japanese companies, and in the
fact that 98 per cent of the facsimile ma¬
chines in use worldwide were made in
Japan.
Catching up the first priority
Until about a century ago, Japan was no
more than an underdeveloped country in
the remote Far East. In science and tech¬
nology, it lagged far behind Europe and the
United States.
The Japanese government of that time
sent many students to study in Europe and
in the United States. Between 1868 and
1874, some 550 of these students went
overseas; a considerable number, in an
age in which Atlantic and Pacific crossings
were made in small ships.
The government also invited many sci¬
entists and technical experts from other
countries to teach in Japan. Some of these
teachers, who came from the United King¬
dom, France, the United States, Germany,
The Netherlands, Switzerland and Italy,
were more highly paid than Japanese Cab¬
inet Ministers. Between 1868 and 1889
2,299 foreigners were thus employed.
In addition, the government very quickly
recognized the importance of education,
and began to introduce a system of uni¬
versal education as early as 1871. While
only 35 per cent of children of eligible age
were attending school in 1875, by 1905 the
rate had risen to 96 per cent.
Thanks to a combination of traditional
values, talent and government policies, by
the 1920s Japanese science and tech¬
nology had already caught up with Europe
and the United States in several fields. The
Japanese had, for example, discovered
new pathogens and established the theory
of mesons.1
In the Second World War, however, the
fruits of this scientific and technological
research were lost. Once again Japan had
no alternative but to start from scratch and
learn from other countries. Thirty-five
years after the War, the Japanese led the
world in a number of areas.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Japans MU radar systems are among the
world's most advanced technological equip¬
ment for studying the Earth's upper atmos¬
phere. A very large MU installation has been
developed at Shigaraki (province of Gifu, on
Honshu island) by Kyoto University's Centre
for Studies of Super High Atmospheric Elec¬
tric Waves, in order to carry out meteorologi¬
cal studies and other scientific research. The
facility has 475 3. 5 -metre-high antennae stand¬
ing 4.5 metres apart in hexagonal groups
(above).
The problems ahead
But as the 1980s draw to a close, the
skies are not cloudless for Japanese sci¬
ence and technology.
In 1957 Japan became the world's lead¬
ing shipbuilding nation, and maintained
this lead for many years. But recently the
Republic of Korea has mastered the most
advanced technology in this field, and can
now build excellent ships more cheaply
than Japan, with the result that Japanese
shipbuilding companies are facing hard
times.
In steel manufacturing technology too,
the Republic of Korea has caught up with
Japan. Lower Korean wages mean that
Japan cannot compete with Korean manu¬
facturing costs, and Japanese steelmakers
are being forced to curtail their oper¬
ations.
The Republic of Korea has also Intro¬
duced car production technology from Ja¬
pan, and is now manufacturing cars which
are as good as, but cheaper than, the
Japanese product.
If this trend continues, it may well be that
countries such as the Republic of Korea,
Taiwan, Hong Kong and Singapore will
overtake Japan in the 1 990s, just as Japan
has been overtaking the United States in
the 1980s.
The people of a country such as the
United States, rich in natural resources,
are not likely to be pushed into extremes of
poverty by technological decline. But Ja¬
pan has virtually no oil, coal, or any other
raw materials of its own. Until now the
Japanese have imported raw materials
from overseas, and used their technologi¬
cal capacity to transform them into manu¬
factured goods for export. With their export
revenues they purchase essential com¬
modities such as oil, food and animal
fodder.
Japan cannot abandon this trade in
manufactured goods all at once. No effort
must be spared in formulating research
and development programmes relating to
the manufacture of high tech products that
cannot be easily imitated by competitor
countries.
The Japanese government is encourag¬
ing original inventions and discoveries
through such initiatives as its Project lor
the Promotion of Creative Science and
Technology, and it is fortunate that Japa¬
nese parents are so closely concerned
with their children's education. The
average level of education certainly
compares favourably with that of other
countries.
There is no doubt that Japan will contin¬
ue to produce top level scientists and tech¬
nologists whose work will help to improve
the lives of many people throughout the
world.
1. Elementary particles. Editor
SHIGERU KIMURA is assistant administrator of
a satellite broadcasting company, Eisei Chan-
neru. A specialist in the history of science, he
was formerly a journalist with the Tokyo daily
Asahi Shimbun, where he was head of the
scientific department and director of research.
He is the author of several published works,
including Japan's Science Edge: How the Cult of
Anti-Science Thought in America Limits U.S.
Scientific and Technological Progress, Universi¬
ty Press of America. USA, 1985. 33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A cultural explanation
for Japan's economic
performance
Confucius and capitalism
by Michio Morishima
^^^ 1. Max Weber. Gesammelte Autsätze zur Rehgionso-
ziologie ("Collected Writings on Religious Sociology".
34 1920)
WHY did "modern capitalism" not
emerge in other times and other
places than modern western
Europe? The German sociologist Max
Weber (1864-1920) believed that modern
capitalism was not automatically produced
by the development of science and tech¬
nology, and that behind its emergence lay
also the emergence of rational, anti-tradi¬
tional ways of thinking among human
agents. Weber asked why there had been
such an enormous historical difference in
this respect between the Orient and the
Occident. To answer this question he
made a magnificent comparative study
covering Europe, the Middle East, India
and China, and concluded that there were
religious factors in the modern West which
favoured the rise of capitalism, while such
factors were absent in other civilizations.
'Sublimated empiricism'
Weber considered that Confucianism,
ike Protestantism, is a highly rational reli¬
gion, but that there is an important differ¬
ence between them. "As against the ac¬
commodation to the world found in
Confucianism we find in Puritanism [or
Protestantism] the task of reorganizing the
world in a rational manner."1 Puritanism
alone fostered modern natural science and
promoted the spirit of capitalism. In China,
not only were natural science and tech¬
nology absent, but also natural law and
formal logic. China, therefore, failed to
achieve a shift from empirical to rational
techniques. "Everything remained at the
level of sublimated empiricism."1
Weber's comparative study of world reli
gions may be regarded, as he himself
perceived, as a massive integrated at¬
tempt to clarify the cultural background,
spiritual backbone and materialistic conse¬
quences of Western civilization. From a
different point of view, however, it may be
seen as part of the overall task of estab¬
lishing the proposition that the economic
performances of various peoples or na¬
tions are unstable and influenced by the
slightest change in their ethos. Only that
part concerning Christianity was complet¬
ed by Weber himself, who left unfinished
the parts relating to other religions such as
Confucianism, Hinduism, and Buddhism.
The instability (or knife-edge) thesis is
based on the observation that Catholics
and Protestants, who share the same Bible
but interpret it differently, are significantly
different in their modes of worldly beha¬
viour. Weber sees the essential disagree¬
ment between the two as lying in the fact
that Protestantism removes the barrier be¬
tween layman and clergy by discarding the
division of Christian ethical precepts into
praecepta and consilia, while Catholicism
sticks to this dualism. For all Protestant
denominations "the only way of living ac¬
ceptable to God was not to outbid worldly
morality by monastic asceticism, but solely
through the fulfilment of the obligations
imposed upon the individual by his position
in the world. That was his calling "'
Rationalism and austerity
The Protestant interpretation of the Bible
thus produces the concept of a job as a
"calling", a task set by God, by which
secular life (and hence economic activity)
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
.
vYQ -senvi-
Photos Louis Frédéric © Rapho, Paris
is connected with the will of God. A job
becomes a duty, and this kind of outlook on
work is, at least at some stage of history,
necessary for the establishment of the cap¬
italist régime and its take-off for economic
growth. The Protestant Reformation was a
breakthrough by which asceticism, hitherto
confined to the monasteries, was released
into the outside secular world. People be¬
gan to act ascetically and rationally. The
rational utilization of capital was carried out
and the rational capitalistic organization of
labour was implemented. Protestantism
thus contributed to (or is congruent with)
the establishment of an efficient economic
system.
No such instability argument concerning
China, India and Japan is found in Weber's
works. He only concludes that neither Con¬
fucianism, Hinduism nor Buddhism is suit¬
able for promoting the spirit of capitalism;
each contains some significant factors
which militate against the emergence of
capitatism. He comes nearest to the knife-
edge proposition when he says: "The Chi¬
nese in all probability would be quite capa¬
ble, probably as much as if not more capa¬
ble than the Japanese, of assimilating
capitalism, which has technologically and
economically been fully developed in the
modern culture area."1 In my book Why
has Japan 'Succeeded'?, however, I have
carried out further investigation into the
subject and developed, for the sake of
comparison between China and Japan, an
argument which is parallel to the one which
Weber made with respect to Catholicism
and Protestantism.
In my opinion, between China and Japan
there is prima facie no significant differ-
CONTINUED PAGE 36
The Meiji Restoration in 1868 and the sub¬
sequent abolition of feudalism brought Japan
into the modern age through a rapid pro¬
gramme of industrialization and development.
Within a few decades Japan could compete
with the Western powers in economic and
military terms. The three 19th-century Japa¬
nese prints above give some idea of the extent
of the change: left, view ofa street in Edo (now
Tokyo) in the early ¡800s, by the great master
of the woodblock print, Ulagawa Hiroshige
(1797-1858), depicts a town untouched by
modern change. The two prints on this page,
"The Train from Takanawa to Tokyo" (c.
1875) and "The Azumabashi Bridge" (1887),
are both by Hiroshige HI (a pupil of Hi¬
roshige) and show the inroads being made by
industrialization and Westernization on the
traditional Japanese scene. The art of the Japa¬
nese print reached perfection in the 18th and
19th centuries in the work of such great artists
as Kitagawa Utamaro, Katsushika Hokusai
(creator of the famous "Thirty-six Views of
Mount Fuji"), and Hiroshige himself. Japa¬
nese prints became very popular in 19th-centu¬
ry Europe and exercised great influence on the
Impressionists and other painters.
One possible explanation for Japanese eco¬
nomic success may lie in the specific Japanese
interpretation of Confucian principles. Left,
an 18th-century ivory netsuke, a richly carved
small toggle used to attach objects to the sash
of a kimono. It depicts General Kuan-yü, a
Chinese hero (2nd and 3rd centuries AD)
considered by the Japanese to embody such
Confucian virtues as courage and loyalty. The
netsuke art form flourished in Japan during
the Edo period (1603-1867).
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
t!Ä
IL I
36
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 35
ence in ideological layout. They are primar¬
ily Confucianist countries. Buddhism came
to Japan not directly from India but always
through China, and Shinto which is gener¬
ally thought of as a religion truly indigenous
to Japan, was, even in its ancient primitive
form, deeply Influenced by Chinese
Taoism. Indeed it has been suggested that
Shinto might even be nothing other than a
Japanese version of Taoism. In spite of
this, Japan succeeded in easily assimilat¬
ing modern capitalism, while China contin¬
ued to be exploited by imperialists from the
West and Japan. This paradoxical situa¬
tion can be resolved only by viewing it in
the light of instability theory.
Company loyalty, a
Confucian virtue
It is noticeable that whereas the Chinese
interpretation of Confucius' doctrines is in¬
dividualistic and humanistic, the Japanese
version is nationalistic and militaristic. This
contrast arguably has existed ever since
Confucianism first came to Japan in about
the sixth century. This is not surprising
because the Japanese have suffered at all
times from a sense of inferiority vis-à-vis
the powerful Chinese empire, leading them
to be, throughout their history, closely
banded together and aggressive.2 After
two centuries of isolation which lasted until
1859, Japan came under pressure from
the West. In this crisis the intelligentsia,
who had been educated in the Japanese-
Confucian manner, succeeded in unifying
the country and finally established a new,
powerful modern government. A national¬
ist-capitalist economy was eventually es¬
tablished, based on a seniority system,
lifetime employment, the loyalty of employ¬
ees to their company, and the share-hold¬
ing system, which fully suits the ethos of
Japanese Confucianism.2
For the establishment of modern West¬
ern-style capitalism, there are two precon¬
ditions: the nation-State and the civil soci¬
ety. For the capitalist mode of economic
behaviour to prevail, an administrative or¬
ganization must be established, which se¬
cures the continuance of the régime. There
must be a strong government which en¬
forces rational law in order to enable each
member of society to calculate the conse¬
quences of his activity objectively and
quantitatively. The government must have
professional bureaucrats, administrative,
judicial and military.3 It is very much due to
the nationalistic Japanese form of Confu¬
cianism that Japan, which had been
marked by many class and regional divi¬
sions, was easily unified into a nation in a
relatively short period of about twenty
years, although there were obviously other
favourable factors, such as insularity, Ja¬
pan's awareness that the Philippines had
fallen into the hands of Spain and that
China was under constant attack from
Western countries. Whatever the reasons,
by 1890 Japan already had a powerful
modern government with officials recruited
from among ex-samurai and new universi¬
ty graduates.
It was, however, very difficult for Japan
to fulfil the other precondition for capital¬
ism, the establishment of a civil society. In
contrast to Christianity, according to which
everyone is equal in the sight of God,
Confucianism promotes a collectivist ethic
and the ethics of functional role expecta¬
tion,4 both of which maintain and strength¬
en the hierarchical character of the society.
Therefore, the elements of a civil society
were not well developed in Meiji Japan,
and it is evident that this strong nation with
its weak civil society was not suited for
competitive capitalism of the Western type.
It created a different type of production
system,4 though this can be, and is, in¬
cluded in the broad category of capitalism.
In this economy, the "invisible hand" is
more visible, since the government always
takes the initiative and plays the role of
helmsman of the economy. Efficiency has
been established by collaboration rather
than competition, and the idea of class
antagonism has not been widespread
among trade unionists.
The rise of 'Confucian
capitalism' in the East
We may say that by virtue of the emer¬
gence of Japan, capitalism ceased to be
monochromatic. Moreover, as the capital-
2. Michio Morishima, op. cit., 1982
3. Max Weber, Wirtschaftsgeschichte. Abriss der uni¬
versalen Sozial- und Wirtschaftsgeschichte. 1927
(General Economic History, tr. F.H. Knight)
4. J. Hirschmeier and T. Yui, The Development of
Japanese Business 1600-1973. 1975
5. J.A. Schumpefer, Capitalism. Socialism and Democ¬
racy. 1943
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Company loyalty, one of the pillars ofJapan's
social consensus, does not prevent employees
from defending their interests, sometimes vig¬
orously, in negotiations with their employers.
The sense of "belonging" to a company is
reinforced by the widespread ringi system, in
which written proposals submitted from below
are examined by senior executives who take the
final decisions. Left, trade union and manage¬
ment representatives of a large Japanese
photographic materials company at the nego¬
tiating table.
The integration of employees into a company
is encouraged by working relationships based
on confidence and on the conception of the
company as a "big family". Communal holi¬
days and outings are organized such as the
picnic in the park at cherry-blossom time,
right. Each year in early April, the Japanese
press and television give daily coverage to the
northward advance of the "blossom from".
ism of the West, which may be called
Protestant capitalism, declines because of
its very achievements, its very success, as
the US economist and sociologist Joseph
Schumpeter (1883-1950) has pointed out,5
so the rise of Confucian capitalism in the
East becomes more apparent. The attain¬
ment of an economic optimum via individu¬
alistic economic competition, which is said
to be the most important raison d'être of
the free enterprise system, is neither the
main purpose nor the prime function of the
Japanese economy. In this context, collab¬
oration between workers for the benefit of
the firm is a more important subject for
analysis than competition among workers
vis-à-vis the firm. In Japanese society,
competition prevails, not so much among
adults, but mainly among children, who are
selected and allocated to various -firms
according to the diplomas they have re¬
ceived in the educational rat race. Once
they have been allocated to a firm, it is very
difficult for them to move, especially from a
small firm to a big one.
In addition, within Japanese society
there is a wide gulf, in wages, fringe ben¬
efits, productivity, risks and profits, be¬
tween big business and the small busi¬
ness-subcontractor sector. Compared with
Western firms Japanese big business op¬
erates in a very bureaucratic way, in ac¬
cordance with the ringi system ("proposal
submission from below and deliberation at
the top") instead of Western planning and
decision-making by top management.
Moreover, newly industrialized countries
such as the Republic of Korea, Taiwan,
Hong Kong and Singapore are all dom
inated by Confucianism. For the analysis of
these new capitalist societies, a new eco¬
nomic model emphasizing collaboration,
group consciousness and nationalism
should be formulated.
These countries have developed by
penetrating foreign markets, and home de¬
mand is not very important for their eco¬
nomic growth. Even for Japan, which has a
fairly large domestic market, domestic de¬
mand is not the main motive force behind
development. The failure of a civil society
to develop is thus not a serious handicap to
economic growth in these countries. It was
possible for them to achieve economic
expansion despite poor home demand and
to embark on a forced march of rapid
growth to catch up with the West.
MICHIO MORISHIMA, Japanese economist,
has been Sir John Hicks Professor of Econom¬
ics at the London School of Economics since
1984. The ideas presented in this article are
discussed in greater detail in his book Why has
Japan 'Succeeded'? Western Technology and
the Japanese Ethos, Cambridge University
Press, UK, 1982.
Although Japan has a substantial domestic
market, its industrial growth has been primar¬
ily sustained by exports. Right, cars for export
ready to be loaded aboard ship. 37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
The Japanese
and Western music
38
UNTIL recently, one of the many dis¬
paraging clichés used by critics
when speaking of the appearance
of Japanese artists in the front ranks of the
world art scene, was that they were "im¬
itators". They forgot that, to the Japanese,
the work of Western artists often seems to
suffer from a lack of maturity and to be
contaminated with the virus of excessive
originality.
In Shinto, a religion which still has con¬
siderable influence on everyday life in Ja¬
pan, there is no clear-cut distinction be¬
tween the divine and the human, which are
linked by a principle of continuous animis¬
tic generation. In the words of the Japa¬
nese composer and musicologist Akira
Tamba, "The living man's god is his de¬
ceased ancestor and, when he dies, he in
turn will become the protective deity of his
descendants." It is easy to appreciate,
therefore, that Japanese artists do not sub¬
scribe to the idea of individual intellectual
ownership with which Western creative art¬
ists are sometimes obsessed. Masters of
traditional Japanese music, painters, cal-
ligraphers and actors all share the knowl¬
edge which they have acquired and devel¬
oped throughout their lives with their pupils
who, in turn, hand down this common stock
of culture to their own successors ...
However relevant they may be, these
observations are not sufficient in them¬
selves to explain why Japan, after the
terrible turning-point in history represented
CONTINUED PAGE 40
by Luisa Futoransky
Western classical music is highly popular in
Japan today, and leading Japanese exponents
such as lite celebrated conductor Seiji Ozawa
often top the bill at concert halls all over the
world. This enthusiasm can be traced back
over a century to the Meiji Restoration, which
marked the opening of Japan to the West.
Above, a Japanese print produced in 1887 bv
Kanenobo depicts young people dressed in
European style taking a singing lesson.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
.2 ¿¿c
. à
'Living National Treasures'
Each country has its own way ofpaying tribute to those who enshrine its
culture, and Japan is no exception. The country honours its most
outstanding living artists and craftsmen by conferring on them the li'le of
"bearers of intangible and important cultural properties". Recipients of
the honour are granted an annual allowance to enable them to work,
exhibit and transmit their arts and skills to young apprentices. They are
venerated and known affectionately as Ningen Kokuhö. ' Living National
Treasures". Five of them are shown here. (1) Fumiko Yonekawa is the
leading exponent of the koto, a kind of zither originally found in China.
The instrument is over 2 metres long and has 13 strings made of spun silk
or nylon. (2) Toyozo Arakawa, one of Japan's most celebrated crafts¬
men, has revived ancient pottery techniques and creates magnificent
ceramics on his farm deep in the countryside. (3) Kako Moriguchi has
been making beautiful kimonos for the last 50 years using dyes and
techniques dating from the 17th century. It may take up to 6 months to
make a kimono. (4) Eislürö Abe is one of the few surviving Japanese
masters of the 1 , 300-year-old art of making paper by hand. He works
'done at home, collecting the wood he uses as raw material and personally
supervising ¡he kiln. (5) Lacquerwork is the speciality of Gonroke
Matsuda. He uses powdered gold sprinkled from a flute-like tool, the
tsu-tsu. as well as the shells of quails' eggs. When decorating a box with
floral motifs, he may use up to 650 shells.
I !
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 38
The shamisen (below), a 3-stringed plucked
lute, is a traditional instrument which is often
used to accompany the koto, or zither. Al¬
though the passion for Western music persists,
recent years have seen a revival of interest in
Japan's traditional music. This has stimulated
the production of typical Japanese instruments
such as the shakuhachi (bamboo finie), the
koto and the shamisen. More and more Japa¬
nese children are learning to play these in¬
struments.
by Hiroshima and the end of the Second
World War, having started virtually from
scratch as far as Western music is con¬
cerned, should have become the leading
manufacturer of top-quality musical instru¬
ments; nor why the Japanese have be¬
come increasingly involved in the enter¬
tainment business and popular music; nor
why, in classical music, Japanese instru¬
mentalists, conductors and soloists should
have come to occupy a leading place in the
world's concert halls.
There can be no doubt that Japan has
superimposed European ways on its own
models, especially in the arts and in educa¬
tion. The reasons for this are bound up with
sociology, philosophy and cultural policy,
and lie beyond the scope of this article.
What is clear, however, is that Western
music has gained such a foothold that in
popular parlance it has become synony¬
mous with "music" in general. As a result,
when the Japanese wish to refer to tradi¬
tional music, they feel compelled to add the
word "Japanese", in order to avoid misun¬
derstandings.
This does not mean that the practice of
traditional music and interest in it have
disappeared altogether. Following a period
of apparent eclipse at the end of the 1 960s,
as a result of the craze for jazz, rock and
other musical forms which were taking the
world by storm, the study of traditional
instruments such as the shakuhachi, the
koto and the shamisen has been steadily
gaining ground in recent years, as is borne
out by the number of such instruments
being manufactured and sold. However, in
terms of public concerts and other events,
traditional Japanese music accounts for no
more than 10 per cent of musical activities
in Japan, although it should not be forgot¬
ten that such music has always been
"semi-public" in the sense that it is primar¬
ily based on the close relationship between
master and pupils and that traditional con¬
certs are usually attended by groups of
friends and connoisseurs. Unlike other cul¬
tural events, they attract a faithful following
which does not need to be prodded by
advertising, and is not a prey to the vicissi¬
tudes of fashion.
Any attempt to study the interest
aroused by music in Japan would be in¬
complete if no allowance was made for the
leading role played by women. Although
this phenomenon is not confined to Japan,
it is an acknowledged fact that, in the
middle and upper-middle classes, the
study of music used to, and to some extent
still does today, bring social prestige. Japa¬
nese custom required young women of
marriageable age to round off their educa¬
tion by taking lessons in flower arrange¬
ment, the tea ceremony, calligraphy or
traditional dancing, or else by learning to
play a traditional instrument. This formed
the beginning of a close relationship be¬
tween master and pupil which lasted for
the rest of the master's life.
With the increasingly rapid pace of
Westernization in the 1950s, more and
more people began to learn to play the
piano, violin or harp. However, the surpris¬
ing thing was that young people were not
content with occasional private lessons.
The taste and passion for music assumed
such proportions that veritable musical uni¬
versities began to flourish. Today. Japan
has about 150 institutions, including con¬
servatoires, academies, universities and
US-style colleges offering high-quality mu¬
sical instruction. Some of them are vast
institutions with their own nursery schools,
orchestras, opera groups, summer camps,
and primary and secondary schools.
Statistics recently published show that
some 10,000 young people with higher-
grade diplomas, roughly 90 per cent of
them women, enter the music market
every year. Some of them become teach¬
ers at the universities where they them¬
selves studied: many others teach in small
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
local conservatoires or simply pass on their
love of music to their children. However,
more and more of them are keen on pursu¬
ing their studies in the leading European
centres in the hope of launching an in¬
ternational career. Rising living standards
have enabled an increasing number of
Japanese families to send their children to
study in Europe, where school fees are
often much lower than in Japan. More than
300 Japanese pupils are studying music or
singing in Vienna alone.
The proverbial Japanese qualities of
consistency, hard work and constant In¬
tellectual curiosity, coupled with submis-
siveness to one's teachers, also help to
explain this phenomenal musical success.
It should come as no surprise that in the
Federal Republic of Germany, for exam¬
ple, there are currently more than 250
Japanese musicians occupying permanent
posts in orchestras.
Quite apart from the undoubted quality
of Japanese artists, one of the reasons for
the number of Japanese on the internation¬
al orchestral and operatic scene lies in the
shortcomings of Japan's cultural infras¬
tructure which is unable to absorb the large
number of good professionals coming onto
the market. There are few regular orches¬
tras and only two or three of them are
subsidized by local municipalities.
Until only very recently, plans for orga¬
nizing a national opera company had not
materialized. Owing to the very high cost of
staging opera, it is understandable that
such an outstanding opera group as Niki-
kai, in addition to depending on private
sponsorship, should have three casts for
each production. For the right to take part,
each member of the company is required
to sell a large number of tickets. Hence,
there are obviously good reasons why tal¬
ented young people should compete
fiercely for a place on the international
scene. Yet again the old adage that "no
man is a prophet in his own country" is
shown to be valid the world over.
I shall let the Japanese musicologist
Mamoru Watanabe have the last word on
the Japanese passion for Western music.
In one of his books on the subject, he
indulges in an ironical jest when he asks:
"Why do the Japanese like European mu¬
sic? ... Why shouldn't we? It is beautiful
music and it is natural for us to like it."B
LUISA FUTORANSKY, Argentine writer, edited
and presented a Spanish-language radio pro¬
gramme for the international service ol NHK. the
Japanese nation-wide broadcasting company,
between 1976 and 1980. when she also taught
opera at the Tokyo music academy Musashino
Ongaku Daigaku. Among her recent publica¬
tions are a novel. De P a Pa (1986). and a
volume of poetry. La sanguina (1987).
Shóhei Ôoka (boni 1909) first became known as a writer through works such as
F'uryo-ki (1948: Prisoner of War. 1967), which were based on his wartime
experiences. He is also the author of essays and novels, notably Kaei (1958-59) a
tenderly-drawn portrait of a woman. In Yônen (1973; "Childhood Years") and
Shoiien (1975; "Years of Youth"), he has written about his early life with his
characteristically direct style and sharp sense of observation. Above, a scene from
Kon lchikawa'sfilm Nobi (1959; l-'ircs on the Plain) adapted from a short story with
the same title (1953). in which Ôoka denounces the horrors of war.
Home thoughts from abroad
A Japanese writer in Paris reflects
on his country's postwar literature
THERE is a subtle and unexpected
pleasure to be derived from reading
the literature of one's homeland
while in Paris, a cosmopolitan city thou¬
sands of kilometres from Japan, surround¬
ed by people of another culture, hearing
only a foreign language and reading only
newspapers written in that language. From
this perspective, Japanese writing seems
mildly exotic, remote in time as well as in
space, and for that very reason has a
striking if paradoxical freshness. Distance
brings a certain detachment. Yet it is after
all the literature of one's own country, and
a feeling of frustration is unavoidable, com¬
bined with relief at not being involved a
combination of responses not easy to
explain.
Reading the same books in Tokyo, one
immediately pictures each writer's face,
hears his tone of voice, conjures up his
distinctive gait, the idiosyncrasies of his
speech or his drinking habits, not to men¬
tion the gossip that surrounds him. and the
part that his work has played in one's life.
His writing comes across as the voice of a
fellow-inhabitant of a familiar world. Here in
Paris, however, this "aura" is swept away,
or filtered out, and only the voice of. the
by Tokuyoshi Hiraoka
writing is heard, like a call from another
world.
Take the following extract from a piece
by Yutaka Haniya in an issue of the journal
Bungakukai ("Literary World"), which has
just reached me.
"If we really penetrate into and concen¬
trate on those of his masterpieces now
available to us, they will not yield up their
astonishing series of intellectual revela¬
tions, which are linked together like the
model built by Watson and Crick to repre¬
sent the "double helix" structure of DNA
and we will never get out of the maze of his
books until we lift our mental awareness to
the point where we unconsciously find our¬
selves climbing step by step to heights
within ourselves whose existence we had
never suspected."
These lines are from an essay in mem¬
ory of that unorthodox genius. Tatsuhiko
Shibusawa, who died not long ago. How
strikingly applicable they are to Haniya
himself, who began his Shiret ("The Spirits
of the Dead"), a monument to waking delu¬
sions, just after the Second World War.
and forty years later is still painstakingly at
work on this same novel. But that is not all.
What is important is the unique "voice".
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
42
that characterizes not merely Haniya's
novels, which are few, but his many critical
articles, collected essays, travel sketches,
and even his countless koshimaki' recom¬
mending other writers' work. A shiver of
excitement runs through us as we catch
the characteristic note of this voice, one
not easy to reproduce in translation, as of
an electrical pulse from some remote cor¬
ner of the universe.
From Haniya and his immediate contem¬
poraries in the "first postwar school" of
writers right up to Masahiko Shimada, who
is still in his twenties, the evolution ol
modern Japanese literature has been
closely connected with the revolutionary
movement, aiming at the transformation of
Japanese society. In Yasahii Sayoku no
tame no Kiyükyoku ("Divertimento for a
Tender Left"), the novel which first brought
him to prominence, Shimada caricatures
the naivety of the peace movement, which
he sees as a childish game. He employs,
for example, the device of writing sayoku
(left-wing), that sacred catchphrase of the
postwar years, not with ideographs but
with the simple phonetic letters that chil¬
dren use before they have mastered the
"adult" system of writing. But behind this
portrayal, nevertheless, there is clearly an
awareness of the passionate sincerity of
the young men and women who were in¬
volved in violent clashes with the police in
the struggle against the Japan-US Security
Treaty in 1960 and the unrest on university
campuses in 1970. When Yutaka Haniya,
Ken Hirano and other writers who had
survived the war and its aftermath,
launched Kindai Bungaku forty years ago,
they drew a clear line between art as a
servant of revolution and the Communist
Party as such. But they still believed in the
political effectiveness of literature, and in
the end failed to differentiate between "ar¬
tistic revolution" and "revolutionary art".
This left them open to attack by the "na¬
tionalist" school, and their influence de¬
clined. Haniya's Shirei. with its insistence
on "permanent revolution", despite this
background he has lived through, towers
W J
i
WT>'2r ¿à
JlrÉlEBr / -^
^BBPRJSfcSBfiHr- ^^"3
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
Left, a still from the film Ekimae ryokan (1958), directed by Shirö
Toyoda and based on a novel by Masuji Ibuse (born 1898). Ibuse's
prolific fictional output consists almost entirely of stories, such as
Tajinko mura, (1939; Tajinko Village, 1971) and Yöhai taichö (1950;
Lieutenant Lookeast, 797/), which are highly popular in Japan and
describe with dry humour Japanese urban and rural life. Ibuse was
awarded the Noma Prize, one of Japan's highest literary distinctions,
for his longest novel, Kuroi ame (1966; Black Rain, 1969) in which he
drew on eyewitness accounts of the Hiroshima catastrophe. In 1982, he
published his autobiography, Ogikubo füdoki ("Topography of Ogi-
kubo").
Below left, a scene from Kon ¡chikawa's film
Enjö (Conflagration. 1958) based on the novel
Kinkakuji (1956; The Temple of the Golden
Pavilion, 1958) by Yukio Mishima
(1925-1970). The novel tells the story of a
young Buddhist monk who burns down his
house of prayer because he -is obsessed by its
beauty. A prolific writer whose works ranged
from an autobiographical novel. Kamen no
kokuhaku (1949; Confessions of a Mask.
1958) and other fiction such as Shiosai (1954;
The Sound of Waves, 1956) to plays including
Kindai nögaku shü (1956; Five Modern No
Plays. 1957), Mishima committed public ritual
suicide a few days after completing a vast
4-volume epic, Höjö no umi (1965-70; The
Sea of Fertility. 1971-74). Brilliant, full of
contradictions, his work reflects the conflict
between Western influence and traditional Ja¬
panese values.
amid the darkness, his "voice" continuing
to haunt his readers' inner world.
Among the noted writers who did not
belong to the Left, Shöhei Ooka, a disciple
of Stendhal, himself experienced life in a
prisoner of war camp. His massive Reite
senki ("Record of the Battle of Leytel"),
written as a tribute to his comrades who
died during their pitiable flight from a victo¬
rious enemy, contains an outstanding
analysis of modern war. Another major
figure was Yukio Mishima. Mishima never
abandoned his right-wing, ultra-national¬
istic ideology; he lived the life of a star,
fascinating and baffling the mass media,
until, like a coiled spring snapping back to
its original position, he committed seppuku
(ritual suicide) out of grief over the state of
his country.
More noteworthy is the major talent of
Masuji Ibuse, whose position is some¬
where between the so-called "I novel" writ¬
ers (who find their reality in the faithful
depiction of the details of their everyday
lives) and the "pure literature" school, typ¬
ified in his younger days by Hideo Ko-
bayashi. Among Ibuse's many works, all
distinguished by their stylistic elegance
and a highly individual sense of humour, is
his long novel Kuroi ame (1966; Black
Rain. 1969), in which he deals directly with
the Hiroshima atomic bomb. What led him
to write it, he has said, was a sense of
unbearable frustration during the Vietnam
War at the newspaper reports of the
seemingly unending stream of American
reinforcements.
Whatever their stylistic differences, Ja¬
panese writers are extremely serious-
minded. One manifestation of this serious¬
ness is a sense of justice and fairness.
Today Kenzaburö Oe seems to be the sole
spokesman of this trend, which may, how¬
ever, also take the form of a devotion to
"pure literature". This approach can be
traced back to the "ethics" which all Japa¬
nese children were taught in elementary
schools before the war, and, to go back
further, to the Confucian code of morality
which has been deeply rooted in the minds
and hearts of Japanese intellectuals ever
since the days of the Tokugawa Shogun-
ate. which turned the teachings of Confuci¬
us and Mencius into what was virtually a
State religion. But the primary question
with which this Confucian ethic, unlike
Christianity, is concerned is "how best to
get through life?", not "what is life for?".
Junnosuke Yoshiyuki, Shdsaku Endo.
Shötarö Yasuoka and others of the so-
called "third wave"? of postwar writers,
rejected what they saw as over-intellec-
tualism. denied that literature could have
any effect on politics, and were fond of
characterizing themselves as "poor stu¬
dents", "dropouts" or "bad boys". Yet now
CONTINUED PAGE 45
A master of narrative, Yasushi lnoue (born
1907) is the author of many novels whose
screen versions have added to his popularity as
a writer. The film made in 1963 by Shirö
Toyoda from lnoue's novel Yüshü Heiya tells
the story of a beautiful middle-class woman
who suffers in her search for true love (above),
lnoue is also noted as the author of brilliantly
imaginative historical novels such as Aoki
Ökami (7960; "The Blue Wolf) and Fütö
(1963; "The Storm") set in ancient or medieval
times in China, Mongolia and other countries
on the Silk Road. He has won many literary
prizes and plays a leading role in Japanese
cultural life.
1 . A koshimaki (literally "loincloth") is a small strip of
paper wrapped round the dust cover of a new book,
with a short recommendation by a well-known writer or
specialist.
2. A term used to designate chronologically the third
group of Japanese writers to emerge after the Second
World War. The first group began to make their name in
1945-1946; the second appeared around 1950. The
"third wave" authors appeared on the literary scene
around 1952-1953. 43
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
In 1961, Nagisa Öshima adapted for the cinema Shiiku (1958; The Catch, 1959), a
collection of stories which had brought its author, Kenzaburö Oe (born 1935), a
major literary award, the Akutagawa Prize. Written in luxuriant, baroque prose,
novels such as Man'en gan'nen no futtoböru (1967; The Silent Cry, 1974) reflect a
preoccupation with Japanese history and politics. Öe's relationship with his mental¬
ly handicapped son has also played an important role in his work, notably in
Kojinteki-na taiken (1964; A Personal Matter, 1969) which has been translated
into many languages. He has published collections of stories, including Reintsuno
kiku onnatachi (1982), which contains experimental and autobiographical writing
focused on the image of a mythical tree.
CO
<5
-^
'i_
CS
o
Q.
E
S
c
o
o
o
Yutaka Haniya (born 1910), novelist and critic, has a special place
on the literary scene of modern Japan. From the early 1930s to
the end of the Second World War, he followed a path similar to
that taken by many left-wing Japanese intellectuals: clandestine
political activity, arrest and imprisonment (for over a year, in
1932-1933), then silence during the war years. While in prison
Haniya read the Critique of Pure Reason, and this encounter with
Kantian philosophy was a crucial experience for him. From it grew
his fascination with a logic which could defy the limits of reason. In
1945 he decided to devote his life to literature, and with a few
friends launched Kindai Bungaku ("Modern Literature"), a period¬
ical which for over twenty years would play a decisive role both in
ideological debate and in bringing important literary works to
public attention. His own long novel Shirei ("The Spirits of the
Dead") is certainly a literary milestone. This still unfinished work,
the first volume of which was published in 1948 and a second in
1976, is an attempt to describe in a five-day scenario the exist¬
ential quest of several characters who feel they are caught in a
mental trap, or in Haniya's own words, to "test the extent of the
vast and unique phoneme resounding from one side of the
cosmos to the other". After making a name as a novelist, from
1955 onwards Haniya attracted attention as an essayist and
through his forthright opinions on literature and politics expressed
in such works as Genshi no naka no seiji (1960; "Politics in the
Field of Hallucination"), a reflection on the origin and nature of
political power; Kage-e no sekai (1966; "The World of Chinese
Shadows"), an autobiographical account of his inner life up to the
age of 35; and Yami no naka no kuroi uma (1 970; "Black Horses
in the Gloom"), a collection of nine short stories, which are
variations on a theme: thought in dreams, thought in darkness,
thought in mirrors. These stories, in which highly abstract philo¬
sophical reflections are transformed by the power of the author's
imagination and poetic vision, reveal the same originality which
distinguishes "The Spirits of the Dead".
Kenji Nakagami (bom 1946) was the first writer of the postwar
generation to be awarded the Akutagawa Prize, for a short story
published in 1 975 entitled Misaki ("The Cape"). Still only 30 years
of age, he had reached a watershed in his work. Until then he had
chronicled the lives of the uprooted in stories which had been
published from 1966 onwards in various literary magazines and
portrayed young provincials who had, like himself, gone to live in
Tokyo in the mid-1 960s. His work since 1 975 has tended to focus
on the search for roots. Through his main character, a young man
called Akiyuki, Nakagami depicts the complex relationships of a
family community in his own region, the Kii Peninsula, where a
web of ancient beliefs and superstitions still keeps the living in
close contact with the dead. The sequels to Misaki, Karekinada
("The Sea of Dead Trees") published in 1977, and Hösenka
("Balsamine") published in 1980, which shows how events affect
the women of the family, form a trilogy, although the same main
character also appears in Chi no hate shijö no toki ("Supreme
Hours on the Edge of the Earth"), published in 1983. Not the least
important aspect of Nakagami's contribution to contemporary
literature is that his realistic accounts of the lives of the buraku-
min, ' from which he came, have helped to break the taboos which
oppress this despised group of people.
1. Burakumin (literally "people from the hamlets") is the name given to
groups such as tanners and certain kinds of butchers who were ostracized
by Japanese society during the Edo period, often because ol religious
taboos. A law was passed in early Meiji which abolished all discrimination
towards them, but the prejudices remain, especially as regards employ¬
ment or marriage prospects.
DOMINIQUE PALME, of France, is a writer and translator spe¬
cializing in Japanese language and literature. She is the author of
an essay on Japanese poetry, "Chansons pour l'enfance, un
poète japonais, Kitahara Hakushù" (1932; "Songs for Childhood:
Kitahara Hakushù, Japanese Poet").
44
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
CONTINUED FROM PAGE 43
they find themselves members of the pres¬
tigious Selection Committee for the Ak¬
utagawa Literary Prize, and even of the
Japan Arts Academy, which makes it look
as if they have now become the guardians
of "pure literature". In terms of what they
really stand for, probably even Yasushi
lnoue, who is widely spoken of (especially
in the West) as a candidate for the Nobel
Prize for Literature, is not a "pure litera¬
ture" writer.
Not only this group, but also the "I novel"
writers, have a latent propensity to classify
work into what is and what is not "pure
literature", much as at one time it was
usual to distinguish between what was and
what was not "progressive". The Kyöfüki
("Tale of a Mad Wind") of Jun Ishikawa, a
writer of astonishing imaginative range and
force; the Hako otoko (1 973; The Box Man,
1980) of Köbö Abe, who has an interna¬
tional reputation as an avant-garde novel¬
ist; the Shiki ("Four Seasons") of Shin-
ichirô Nakamura a dazzling picture-scroll
of love and lust: none of these comes
within this category of "pure literature",
because in none of them is the question
"how to live?" asked.
This is the kind of literary landscape that
I see as I look back at Japanese literature
from abroad a landscape that appears to
me in this way because I too am concerned
about my country, take an interest in poli¬
tics, and am a believer in "pure literature".
From behind this literary perspective,
though or superimposed upon it come
the "voices" of such writers as Haniya and
the much younger Kenji Nakagawa. Other
voices, those of Atsushi Mori, Nobuo Koji-
ma, Meisei Götö and Minako Oba, are less
easy to "place" within this broad perspec¬
tive; which paradoxically adds to their
appeal.
In Japan it is well understood that there
is a clear division of territory between the
two most prestigious literary awards, the
Akutagawa Prize and the Naoki Prize, the
former being concerned with "pure", and
the latter with "popular", literature. The
members of the Akutagawa Prize Selec¬
tion Committee sometimes award the
Prize to really original work such as Yosh-
ikichi Furui's Yöko, Ryü Murakami's Kagiri-
naku tömei ni chikai buru ("Almost Trans¬
parent Blue"), or the woodblock print artist
Masuo Ikeda's Egekai ni sasagu ("Offering
to the Aegean Sea"). But whenever this
happens, some members of the Commit¬
tee object even to the point of resigning, on
the ground that the style is too unorthodox
or the ideas are too bold. This is always
followed by a sharp reaction, and before
long the stress is once more on the impor¬
tance of completeness or "roundedness"
in candidate works, rather than on their
originality. Future potential is no longer
taken into account; and the Prize then
tends to go to collections of short stories,
unpretentious and small in scale, but with a
due measure of sabi3 and a pleasantly
readable style not unlike that of the Com
mittee members themselves. This is how
devotion to "pure literature" manifests
itself.
Throughout the 1960s, when this sit¬
uation was a dominant factor in the literary
world, the new "prize-winners" who ap¬
peared on the scene year by year were all
in their forties or fifties, and voices were
raised to deplore this "ageing" of Japa¬
nese literature. Then Ryü Murakami's sud¬
den emergence ended this apparent state
of saturation. A group of talented young
writers, all in their early thirties Kenji Na¬
kagami, Michitsuna Takahashl, Masahiro
Mita, So Aono, Haruki Murakami, and
Wahei Tatematsu came on stage close
behind him.
Of all the work published by this group,
Kenji Nakagami's fine novel Karekinada
("The Sea of Dead Trees"), depicting the
day-to-day existence of a tough youth
struggling to make something of his life
within the context of a complex family
structure in the remote district of Kumano,
sandwiched between the mountains and
the sea, is probably the only one to have
acnieved full acceptance by the literary
establishment. There is a "Roots" ele¬
ment the tracing of one's origins in this
story, though it is not so prominent as in
Yasuoka's Ryuritan ("A Tale of Wander¬
ings in a Strange Country"). Like Yoshiyu-
ki's Suna no ue no shokubutsugun ("A
Cluster of Plants on the Sand"), it is haunt¬
ed by the horror of incest; and it has many
of the specific qualities beloved of the
"pure literature" school especially the
lovingly detailed descriptions of the daily
life of ordinary country people with neither
education nor property. It is filled with sun¬
light and the sound of wind, the love of
flowers, and the smell of sweat; with a
sense of oneness with nature.
"When he started work, Akiyuki at last
felt the sun soaking into his body. A film of
sweat made a second skin, sensitive to the
light breeze. His shadow stretched out
over the soil as he dug into it with his pick.
He scooped the soil up with a spade. He
felt the sound of his breathing, as it rose
from within his hollow body that was made
only of arms, stomach and muscle, res¬
onate with the soil as the air rose from it,
smelling of the sun-roasted earth. The air
was breathing. The mountains were
breathing."
But when one reads from the vantage
point of "abroad" the successive variations
on his theme that Nakagami builds up
"Now he would work. He dug with his pick,
lifted the soil with his spade. The pick was
Akiyuki. The spade was Akiyuki." "He ac¬
cepted the sun. He was steeped in its light.
Akiyuki melted into the sunlight. He be¬
came the trees, the stones, the air. Stand¬
ing, Akiyuki trembled, like a blade of
grass" what comes across primarily is
not the feeling of a lyrical scene depicting a
young labourer in love with his work, but a
particular music, of the kind which I sus-
77¡t' novels of Köbö Abe (born 1924) are fantastic parables of social life. One of
Abe's main themes is the alienation of modern man in an anonymous and stifling
world. In Tanin no kao (¡964; The Face of Another. 1966). adaptedfor the cinema
bv Hiroslti Teshihagara in 1966 (below), the hero is an industrialist who is rejected
bv his wife after being accidentally disfigured, and secretly undergoes plastic surgery
in an attempt to fashion a new identity and win her back. Abe established his
reputation in Japan in 1951 when his collection ofstories Kabe won the Akutagawa
Prize. The publication «/'Suna no onna (1962; The Woman in the Dunes. 1964)
brought him international recognition. His latest novel, Hakobune Sakuramaru
("The Ark of Sakura") is mainly set in a nuclear shelter.
3. Quiet, elegant simplicitya quality traditionally much
esteemed in Japanese literature. Editor.
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
pect writers of "pure literature" most de¬
test: Rock 'n' Roll, with its powerful, relent¬
less beat ... Not only passages like these,
but also the intentional build-up of scenes
which are of basic importance for the hero,
make it quite clear that this novel was
"composed" (using the word in its musical
connotation) in a highly intellectual man¬
ner. And reading the sequel, Hösenka
("Balsamine"), which depicts the troubled
life of the young man's mother, seen from
her point of view, I was suddenly reminded
of William Faulkner. In his sun-baked Ku-
mano, with its abundance of legends and
of tales of blood, Nakagami has created a
world as vivid as Faulkner's Yoknapataw-
pha County. No other critic seems to have
made this particular point. Who knows
perhaps this too is a spin-off from reading
one's own literature abroad.
TOKUYOSHI HIRAOKA, who has taught since
1370 at the Waseda University, Tokyo, has
published two collections of short stories, "The
Vanished Chimney" and "Eating the Rose", as
well as many articles of literary criticism and
translations of French authors into Japanese.
This article was written during a sabbatical year
which the author spent in Paris.
Unesco's Literature Translations Series
A selection of modern Japanese works
ABE, Köbö: Inter Ice Age 4 (Dai yon kampyo-ki), trans,
by E. Dale Saunders, A. Knopf, New York, 1970, Cape,
London, 1971 ; The Man who Turned into a Stick (Bö ni
natta otoko), trans, by D. Keene, University of Tokyo
Press, 1 977; The Woman in the Dunes (Suna no onna),
trans, by E. Dale Saunders, Seeker & Warburg, London,
1963, C. E. Tuttle, Tokyo, 1967.
ENDO, Shüsaku: Tfte Sea and Poison (Umi to
dokuyaka), trans, by M. Gallagher, 1972; When I Whis¬
tle (Kuchibue wo fuku toki), trans, by Van C. Gessel,
1 979; Wonderful Fool (Obaka san), trans, by F. Mathy,
1 974; The Samurai (Samurai), trans, by Van C. Gessel,
1982; all published by Peter Owen, London.
INOUE, Yasushi: The Root Tile of Tempyö (Tempyö no
iraka), trans, by J.T. Araki, Univ. of Tokyo Press, 1 975.
KAWABATA, Yasunari: The Lake (Mizuumi),\rans. by
Reiko Tsukimura, Peter Owen, London, 1977; Snow
Country (Yukiguni), trans, by E. Seidensticker, Knopf,
New York, 1956, Seeker & Warburg, London, 1957.
MISHIMA, Yukio: The Sound of Waves (Shiosai),
trans, by M. Weatherby, CE. Tuttle, Tokyo, 1981;
Spring Snow (Haru no yuki), trans, by M. Gallagher, C.
E. Tuttle, Tokyo, 1974; The Temple of the Golden
Pavilion (Kinkakuji), trans, by I. Morris, C. E. Tuttle,
Rutland, Vt., USA & Tokyo, 1972, 1981.
Sauvez les enfants du monde,
achetez les cartes de viux,
jeux et cadeaux unkaf <f*
UNICEF Greeting Cards
Artists and museums from many countries have
again contributed an attractive and varied range
of designs and paintings to this year's UNICEF
Greeting Cards, which are on sale at UNICEF
sales points throughout the world.
Proceeds from the sale of cards, gifts and sta¬
tionery help UNICEF (the United Nations Chil¬
dren's Fund) to finance its programmes for bring¬
ing improved health care, nutrition and sanitation
to millions of needy children in the developing
countries of Africa. Asia and Latin America. The
sale of a single card provides the funds to vaccin¬
ate 4 children against diphtheria, whooping cough
and tetanus or to protect 10 children from blind¬
ness caused by malnutrition.
This year's selection of UNICEF Greeting
Cards features a series by modern artists, includ¬
ing 5 abstract designs bv Wassilv Kandinskv.
An ideal gift for the festive season
Unesco Desk Diary 1988:
'The World Heritage'
The 54 superb colour photographs in :
this diary show a selection from the
world's cultural and natural heritage
sites.
M4pagcs, 17x23.6 cm, ISBN 92-3-002483-X
Trilingual: English/Frcnch/Spanish
Price: 60 French francs (in France only)
Co-published by Unesco and Incafo. Madrid
How to order:
The desk diary can be ordered through the
national distributor of Unesco publications
in your country (sec list opposite page), who
will indicate the price in local currency, or in
case of difficulty, from the Unesco Press.
7. Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Paris. Orders to
the Unesco Press should be accompanied by
a cheque or money order in French francs or
the equivalent sum in US dollars.
1988
UNESCO
li Run mm IK- \LmiJkiI
I I I'.riniiKKjio Munilutl
The Courier JU
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco. 7 Place dc Fontenoy. 757(10 Paris.
Subscription rates
I year: 90 French francs.
Hinder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus dale of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent loihe
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an internalional
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S. A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc., 1 11 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief:
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Mallcin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
NedaclKhazcn
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian:
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringelstcin
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
All correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German : Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Azizah Hamzah (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papagcorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: DaoTung (Hanoi)
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) -Dépôt légal :C1 -Décembre 1987
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
Unesco Courier Index 1987
January
IN SEARCH OF PARTNERSHIP. Is the international community a myth ? (R.-J.
Dupuy). Twenty years of cultural co-operation (E. Pouchepadass). Cities without
limits (R.M. Salas). The world's homeless millions. Women on the sidelines (A.M.
Diop). The "new poor" (G. Sarpellon). Domination and deprivation (N. van Khoa).
Class, caste and power (A.S. Patel). An open book (I. Petryanov-Sokolov). Games,
sports and traditions. Treasures from an ancient Chinese tomb (Wen Ruitang).
UNICEF at forty.
February
ALPINE EUROPE. In harmony with nature (L. Lienert). When men and mountains
meet (J. Schaller). The great transalpine routes (B. Parisi). The Walser (P. Zinsli).
Grenoble (P. Frappât). The Alpine culture of Slovenia (M. Kmecl). Getting to the top
(P. Meyer). Horn of plenty (B. Bachmann-Geiser). Song without words (M. Müller).
The ranz des vaches (G. Métraux). The ALPEX experiment (R. Newson). Lakes and
glaciers ol the Alps (H. Löffler).
March
BIOTECHNOLOGY, AGRICULTURE AND DEVELOPMENT. The new biotechnolo¬
gies (J. C. Senez). The Green Revolution. The gene revolution (B. Dixon). Tomatoma-
tion (Koichibara Hiroshi). Hybrids for the year 2000 (R.G. Butenko and Z.B. Shamina).
Grains of hope (E.C. Wolf). The rediscovery of traditional agriculture. Rusitec the cow.
Rhizobium, the farmer's Mr. Fixit (E.J. DaSilva, J. Freiré, A. Hillali, S.O. Keya). A
challenge for the developing world (A. Sasson).
April
TRAVELLERS' TALES. The traveller and his quest (J. Brosse). The earthly Paradise
(C. Columbus). In search of the Amazons (C. de Acuña). The first men on the Moon
(N.A. Armstrong, E.E. Aldrin). Mass to the sound of gunfire (F. Magellan/Anlonio
Pigafetta). Saved by the Indians (J. Cartier). Festivities in the Friendly Islands (J.
Cook). A Russian on the coast of Alaska (G. Shelikhov). The swimming postman (A.
von Humboldt). Reflections on solitude (A. Nikitin). Scholar Gypsy (G. Borrow). How I
became Gustavus Vasa (O. Equiano). Long nose, white skin and "honey mouth" (M.
Park). Island fling (V. Segalen). How Buddhism came to Karnasuvarna (Xuan Zang).
A visit to the regent of Tibet (R.-E. Hue). The mystic way (F. oddïn 'Attär). Diplomats
under surveillance (Fukuzawa Yukichi). Vive la différence! (Yuan Zuzhi). Dance-floor
democracy (D.F. Sarmiento). A Chinese general in Paris (Chen Jitong). An Indian poet
visits an English parson (R. Tagore). Paris on-Thames (J.-K. Huysmans). The
obedience due to princesses (Ibn Batutah). Into the heart of Africa (R. Caillié). Psychic
sports (A. David-Néel). Thoughts from the roof of the world (J. Myrdal).
May
FOOD AND CULTURE (I. de Garine). A grain revolution (T. Ndoye. M. M'Baye). Of
maize and meat (P. Petrich). Beneficial beans ? Reflections on the potato (N.M.
Joaquin). The ones that get away (J. Durnin). (Table) manners makyth man (Naomichi
Ishige). The meal is the message (R. DaMatta). China's health food tradition (Li
Ruifen). Paradise lost (P. Camporesi). Food aid and food habits (J. Shoham, B.
Stainier).
June
LIFE IN EXTREME CONDITIONS. Survival (F.Z. Meerson). It's tough at the top (G.
Antesena, M. Paz-Zamora, E. Vargas). Travelling light (O.G. Gazenko). The time of
our lives (M. Siffre). The desert as a way of life (H.A. Sidikou). Hunter-gatherers of the
tropical forest (L. Palade). The sea within us (D. Behrman). Stress in the modern world
(L. Levi). Solo to the Pole (J.-L. Etienne). Marathon Man (B. Berntsen).
July
EDUCATION AND DRUGS. Learning to live (N. Friderich). Unesco and drugs. "A
perverse logic" (J. Baudrillard). How should we attack the drug problem ? (G. di
Gennaro). The new world of artificial intelligence (D. de Gregorio). The search for a
thinking computer (Norihisa Doi, Koichi Furukawa, Kazuhiro Fuchi). The city-builders
of Islam (M.A. Sinaceur). Fighting words (J. Blot). Society and the disabled. Breaking
down the barriers for visually handicapped children (M.A.M. de Moráis Alves). Vuk
Stefanovic Karadzic. A world congress on copyright teaching (Y. Gaubiac).
August
MEDICINE AND HEALTH. The notion of health (P. Gigase). "Let the days come in"
(J.F. Garcia Ruiz). Does wealth equal health ? (D.-C. Lambert). A chance for every
child (M. Rey). Complementary medicine (S. Fulder). Plant therapy in the fight against
cancer (Xing Sishao). Overdose (G. Peters). A grand old age (E. Beregi). Tomorrow's
medicine (Y. Villedieu). The challenge of AIDS. Automation and microsurgery (S.
Fedorov).
September
THE BAROQUE. An age of exuberance, drama and disenchantment (P. Skrine).
Three great domes (G.C. Argan). The musical offering (A. Basso). Spain: An art of gilt
and pathos (J. Gallego). Baroque as a world philosophy (E. Glissant). Sculpture,
theatre of the sublime (F. Souchal). The stately heritage of Portuguese baroque (J. -A.
Franca). Italy: The great illusionists (A. Brejon de Lavergnée). Latin America: "A new
form of self-expression" (L. Zea). The Angel with the Arquebus (M. Rojas Mix). Brazil:
The triumph of O Aleijadinho (A.C. da Silva Telles). Central Europe: The art of
persuasion (C. Norberg-Schulz). Baroque in the Slav countries (G. Gatchev).
October
MAN AND THE BIOSPHERE. Sustainable development (B. von Droste). The urban
maze. Food for thought. Return of the griffon. Nature and culture. Painting the future.
Islands at risk. Pirates, parasites and population. Information please. The canopy raft.
Mountain challenge. Lake Baikal. The poetry of llya Chavchavadze (G. Bouatchidzé,
E. Glissant). Les Kurbas (N.N. Kornienko). Food for all (Y. Coutsocheras).
November
ARCHAEOLOGY UNDER WATER. Plunging into the past (N. Flemming. M. Red-
knap). An international survey of the underwater heritage. The Mediterranean, an
underwater museum (A.J. Parker). The Madrague de Giens wreck (A. Tchernia). Ten
great discoveries. Technology and the marine archaeologist (C. Mazel). Modern
replicas of ancient vessels. Law and the underwater heritage (L.V. Prott. P.J.
O'Keefe). The amphora warlooting of ancient shipwrecks. Jewels from the "Crown"
(L. Einarsson). Herod's great harbourancient Caesarea (A. Raban). Beringia (N.N.
Dikov). Reports from six countries. Apollonia, a model port of Antiquity.
December
JAPAN TODAY. Signs of a new individualism (Masakazu Yamazaki). Japan's
demanding education system '(Kazuo Kurimoto). A 'communications society'(Yozo
Shiozaki). The art of making light work (Motoko Ishii). Colours to whet the palate
(Jun'ichiro Tanizaki). Cities at one with nature (A. Berque). The changing home (M.
Bourdier). A large foreigner in search of space (J. Kirkup). The high tech explosion
(Shigeru Kimura). Confucius and capitalism (Michio Morishima). The Japanese and
Western music (L. Futoransky). Postwar Japanese literature (Tokuyoshi Hiraoka).
Two contemporary writers (D. Palmé).
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco periodicals
AUSTRALIA. Hunter Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collingwood. Victoria 3066;
Publications: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale 2100,
NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of Australia. P.O. Box
175, 5th floor, Ana House, 28 Elizabeth St., Melbourne. Victoria 3000.
AUSTRIA. Buchhandlung Gerold and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna.
BAHRAIN. United Schools International, Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726,
Bahrain. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop, Cave Hill
Campus. P.O. Box 64. Bridgetown. BELGIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch
edition only: N.V. Handelmaatschappi| Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18. 2100
Deurne-Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications agent:
Jean de Lannoy. 202 Ave. du Roi, 1060 Brussels. CCP 000-0070823-13.
BRAZIL Publicaçoes Técnicas Internacionais Ltda, Processing Dept.. R
Peixoto Gomide 209, 01 409. Sao Paulo SP. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co.
Ltd.. Central Distribution Centre, 61. Sparks Street. Ottawa ONT K1P 5R1.
CHINA. China National Publications Import and Export Corporation. P.O. Box
88, Beijing. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51 -1 13 02. Prague 1 : Ve
Smeckach 30, P.O.B. 790-1 1 1 -27 Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura, 11 Soukenrcka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Pub-
lishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6.893 31 Bratislava-CSSR. DENMARK. Munk-
sgaar/j Export-OG, Tidsskriftservice. 35 Norre Sogade. DK-1970 Kobenhavn
K. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for Unesco Publications,
No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, P. O. Box
128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalainen Kirjakauppa Oy, P.O. Box 2, 01641
Vantas 64. Rautikirja Oy, Subscription Department, P.O. Box 1 , 01641 Vantas
64. FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris. CCP
12598-48. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchhaus Leipzig, Post¬
fach 140, 710 Leipzig, or from Internationalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R.
FED. REP. OF GERMANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher
Unesco-Kurier Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57. D5300 Bonn 3. GHANA. Fides
Entreprises. P.O. Box 1 41 29, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE John Mihalopoulos & Son SA. International Booksellers. P.O. Box
10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki. G C Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore.
4 Nikis Street. Athens T 126. Koslarakis Brothers, International Booksellers, 2
Hippocratous Street. Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-15, Lock
Rd.. Kowloon. Hong Kong Govt. Information Services. Publication Centre,
Baskerville House. 22 Ice St. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushlmport-ABT, P.O.B.
149-H-1389, Budapest 62. ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co.. H.F.
Hafnarstraeti 9. Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamam Marg, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 400036; 17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2: 5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh, Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Rd.. Bangalore 560001 ; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-
500001. Sub-depots: Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 17 Park St., Calcutta
70016; Sandia House, New Delhi. INDONESIA. Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam
Ratulangie37, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco,
1188 Englab Ave.. Rostam Give Building, Zip Coda 13158. P.O. Box 11365-
4498, Teheran. IRELAND. The Educational Company ol Ireland Ltd., Bally-
mount Rd., Walkinstown, Dublin 12. ISRAEL. A B.C. Bookstore Ltd.. P.O. Box
1283,71 AllenbyRd., Tel Aviv61000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria
Sansoni. S.p.A.), Via Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence.
JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku. Tokyo
113. KOREA. Korean National Commission (or Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64,
Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co.. Ltd, POB 2942. Kuwait; for the
Unesco Courier: Farafalla Press Agency, P.O. Box SAFA 4541, Kuwait.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22. Grande-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic St.. Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd.. 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. DILITSA, Distribuidora
Literaria SA, Apartado Postal 24 448. Mexico DF 06700. N & E Omicron SA,
Bookseller & Subscriptions Agency. Col Condesa Deleg. Cuahtemoc. Aparta¬
do Postal 40 075, 06140 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library. 30 Bd. des
Moulins, Monte Carlo. NEPAL. Sajha Prakashan Polchowk. Kathmandu.
NETHERLANDS. Faxon Europe, P O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam. NEW
ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box 14277-Kilbirnie, Wellington;
130 Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721, Chnstchurch; Alma St., P.O. Box 857,
Hamilton; Princes St, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin. NIGERIA. The University
Bookshop of He; The University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286. NORWAY.
Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum-Oslo1;NarvesenA/S, Litteraturt
Jenesten, P.O.B. 6125 Etterstad, N 0602 Oslo 6; Universitets Bokhandelen.
Universrtetssentret, Poslboks 307 Blmdern. Oslo 3. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book
Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3: Unesco
Publications Centre. Regional Office for Book Development in Asia and the
Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box 8950, Karachi 29. POLAND.
Ofpan-lmport. Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie
Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda.
Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan,
Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SINGAPORE.
Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd. Times Jurong, 2 Jurong Port Rd., Singapore
2261. SOUTH AFRICA. American & Overseas Publications (Pty) Ltd., Sub¬
scription Service, P.O. Box 42476, Johannesburg. Universitas Books (Pty)
Ltd.. P.O. Box 775, Pretoria 0001. Van Schaiks Bookstore (Pty) Ltd.. Libri
Building, 268 Church Street, Pretoria 0001 . Central News Agency Ltd., Group
Overseas Penodical Div. P.O. Box 61 3, Cape Town 8000. SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop. P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.-
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Frjrbundet.
Skolgrand 2. Box 150 50 S-104. 65 Stockholm; Wennergren-Wilhams AB,
Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104. 25 Stockholm; Esselte Tidsknftscentralen.
Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101, 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa
Verlag. 5 Rámistrasse, Zurich; Librairie Payot, Rue Grenus 6, 121 1, Geneva
11, CCP. 12-236; Librairies Payot also in Lausanne, Basle, Berne. Vevey,
Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zurich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establish¬
ment, University of Aleppo. Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop.
P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road. Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan
Pamt, Mansion 9. Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok. TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO.
National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair, Trinidad W 1.
TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S.. Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469, Posta Kutusu 219.
Beyoglu, Istanbul. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Orfice, Agency Sec¬
tion Publications CTR, Periodicals Section-Room 008, Nine Elms Lane,
London SW8 5DR, and H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast,
Manchester. Birmingham. Bristol; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122
Kings Cross Rd., London WC1X9DS. UNITED STATES. Bernan Associates-
UNIPUB, Periodicals Department, 10033-F King Highway, Lanham MD
20706. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost. Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba,
Zopitarjeva 2, Lubljana; Nolit, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre. Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
