<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="077050eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
^BliTheCourier
JANUARY 19M - 9 French Irincs
|riCieft "*
1
i
1
i
WÊÈ
i^ SI
THE CIRCUS
An international art
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
. I » ."
I Mexico
Learning
together
1988 marks the opening of the World Decadefor Cultural Development proclaimed by the General
Assembly ofthe UnitedNations andplaced under the auspices ofthe UnitedNations and Unesco. The
Decade, which will end in 1997, was proposed at Unesco's World Conference on Cultural Policies
(Mexico City, 1982) which strongly supported the idea that "culture constitutes afundamentalpart of
the life ofeach individual and ofeach community". The two main objectives ofthe Decade, in which
Unesco will be playing a leading part, are to place greater emphasis on the cultural dimension in the
development process and to stimulate creative skills and cultural life in general. As part of the
Decade, the Unesco Courier this month launches a newfeature on "Peoples and cultures". Above,
two young pupils and their teacher in a village school in Mexico's Chiapas State. Later this year we
shall be publishing a special issue entirely devoted to the World Decade for Cultural Development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
The Unesco Courierofíers its best wishes for 1988 to the readers of its 34
language editions throughout the world.
January 1988
41st year
For many people young and old, the word circus evokes memories of a
fantastic world of thrills and laughter, of the hilarious antics of colourfully
costumed clowns, the dexterity of the jugglers, the agility and split-
second timing of the acrobats, tightrope walkers with nerves of steel.
But perhaps because in some languages the word has pejorative
overtones the circus is all too often considered as a minor form of show
business and its claims to an artistic pedigree are disdained.
Yet the circus is an art in its own right, a many-faceted art with its own
history and originality. Everyone who has ever watched from a ringside
seat knows that the circus, unlike some other forms of art and
entertainment, is based not on illusion but on risk. At the circus there is,
literally, no room for concealment ; the preparations for each number
take place before our eyes.
The circus as we know it today originated in eighteenth-century
England as an offshoot of the art of horsemanship. Later its range
widened to include a broad variety of disciplines and complex forms of
dramatic and lyrical expression . The poetry of the circus and the symbolic
image of the clown captivated and inspired painters and writers. At the
same time the circus became an international art as artistes from different
countries learned from each other and performed together beneath the
Big Top.
But the universality of the circus is also, and perhaps above all, due to
its fraternal nature. There is no fighting in the circus ring except for
laughter; no victims, except those caused by accident. Laughter, the
language of the circus, is universal, and so are the emotions of admiration
and trepidation to which it moves the audience.
This issue of the Unesco Courier is thus devoted to a supremely human
art. It does not cover all the crafts and disciplines of the sawdust ring, nor
does it analyse the problems which the circus is facing today. Instead it
describes the conditions in which the modern circus was born and seeks to
explain its undying popularity and eternal youth.
The Big Top 4
The modern circus, an international art
by Anthony Hippisley Coxe
The 'Hundred Entertainments' 8
China's 2,000-year-old tradition of acrobatics
by Huang Minghua
The art of the impossible
A repertoire constantly renewed
by courageous, versatile artists
by Lucien-René Dauven
10
The Little Top
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
14
Self-portrait of a clown
by Leonid G. Engibarov
16
The profession of laughter
An interview with Anatoli Martchevski
23
Schools for artistes
by Monica J. Renevey
24
The freedom of the ring
by Annie Fratellini
27
The circus on celluloid 29
'As American as apple pie'
The art of the circus spectacular
by A.H. Saxon
30
The rubber man
by Alfred Mikhail
34
A topsy turvy world
by Manuel Pereira
35
Peoples and cultures 2
MEXICO: Learning together
Cover: Composition with Five Clowns, 1953, (162
x 130 cm). by the French painter Fernand Léger
(1881-1955). Private collection, Geneva.
Photo Held © Artephot. Paris. SPADEM. 1 987
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
Back cover: Chinese acrobats of the Beijing
Circus during a performance at Unesco
Headquarters, Paris, in 1981
Photo Unesco/MichelClaude
The Courier English
French
Italian
Hindi
Turkish
Urdu
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Finnish
Swedish
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English.
A window open on the world
Spanish Tamil Catalan Slovene Basque
French. Spanish and Korean
Published monthly in 34 languages Russian Hebrew Malaysian Chinese Thai ISSN 004 1-5278
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational.
German Persian Korean Bulgarian Vietnamese
N°l-1988-CPD-87-l,453 A
Scientific and Cultural Organization Arabic Dutch Swahili Greek Pashto
7. Place dc Fontenoy. 75700 Paris. Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The Big Top ^
The modern circus, an international art by Anthony Hippisley Coxe
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
MORE than 16,000 books are
known to have been written about
the circus: that is the surprising
total of entries in Raymond Toole Stott's
monumental circus bibliography Circus and
Allied Arts. Historians say that the modern
circus was invented in 1768 by Philip Astley
at Halfpenny Hatch, near Westminster
Bridge, London, and it seems highly prob¬
able that it was Astley, a former cavalry
sergeant-major trained as a rough-rider,
who first found that by galloping in a circle,
while standing upright on his horse's back,
centrifugal force could help him keep his
balance. After all, most of the trick riders
who appeared in the middle of the eight¬
eenth century started as riding masters,
steeped in the traditions of the rectangular
manège.
But did Astley trace the first ring in Lon¬
don, and did this take place in 1768?
In his Memoirs, published in 1830, Harry
Angelo writes that "Corporal Astley as¬
tonished the common people of Wilton ...
when one day his horse galloped in a circle.
With Astley upon its back, standing upon
his head...." That event took place some
130 kilometres west-south-west of London;
and since he was still a corporal the date
must be circa 1761.
Of course one trick rider does not make a
circus, but the reason why other showmen,
such as jugglers, stilt walkers, acrobats and
rope dancers, all found the ring an ideal
place in which to perform, can be readily
appreciated. Unlike the actor, musician,
singer or dancer, the circus artiste does not
interpret; he demonstrates some aspect of
physical prowess. But that demonstration
of agility or balance or dexterity must be
believed. In the circus arena there are eyes
all round to see that nothing is faked.
Hippodramas, trick riders and clowns
Small wonder then that such a spectacle
was immediately appreciated all over the
world; except in the United Kingdom, its
birthplace. Here Astley and his rival
Charles Hughes thought that by adding a
stage to the side of the ring they could
double the attraction. But the Spectacle of
Actuality is killed if it becomes associated
with the Spectacle of Illusion. If you know
that a certain role is being played by an
actor, you must have lingering doubts about
the rope dancer's performance; is the rope
really much thicker than it looks? Might
there not be some unseen wires which help
him keep his balance?
This misalliance produced a hybrid form
of entertainment, equestrian drama. It did
not survive for long in continental Europe.
Nor did it find favour with the tenting circus
proprietors in the United Kingdom. They
wondered why on earth they should make
travel more difficult and expensive by cart¬
ing round a lot of unnecessary scenery,
costumes and "props".
Halfway between hippodramas such as
"The Battle of Waterloo" and the straight¬
forward trick riding in the ring, came scenes
on horseback performed with the greatest
success by Andrew Ducrow. He was the
first great international star of the circus.
Yet of the score or more roles which he
enacted on the back of his horse "Indian
Hunter", "Chinese Enchanter", "Tyrolean
Shepherd", "Jack Tar" and so on only one
is still seen today: "The Courier of St.
Petersburg", in which the countries through
which a courier would ride on his way to
Russia are represented by horses which pass
beneath him as he straddles two more. It is
easy to see why this survived while all others
failed. It requires much more riding skill
agility and sense of balance than acting
ability.
Perhaps one other riding act can be
traced back to Andrew Ducrow. Although
Billy Bell is usually given the credit for
inventing the bareback or Jockey act, in the
1870s, I believe that it can be traced back to
"Le Jockeis (sic) Anglais" performed by
Ducrow in the 1820s.
Be that as it may, the Jockey act was the
one at which the British excelled. Apart
from Bell, Wilkes Lloyd, Adolph Wells,
Hubert Cooke and John Frederick Clarke
all achieved international fame. Clarke was
the greatest of all Jockey riders. Nobody
took up the £1,000 challenge which he
Erecting the Big Top. The Cirque Grock,
Cannes (France), 1954
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
Below, poster featuring the English white-
faced clown Foottit (1864-1921), who intro¬
duced a number of innovations into the
clown's repertoire. When performing at the
Nouveau Cirque in Paris he created a
famous double act with a Cuban artiste,
Chocolat (Raphaël Padilla, 1868-1917),
which established the classic partnership be¬
tween the clown and his stooge, the auguste.
His innovations in make-up were also widely
imitated.
NOUVEflU GRAND CIRQUE
ARl S
E
0)
CO
5
<u
oí
CD
É
©
.F 9
CLOWN FOOTTIT
H.HOUCK1
Above, "Astley's Amphitheatre" in London
as depicted in an early 19th-century print by
Auguste Pugin and Thomas Rowlandson.
The Amphitheatre was built by the British
horseman and acrobat Philip Astley (1742-
1814), one of the great figures in the history
of the circus and reputedly the first man to
think of staging shows in a ring.
issued. He was born in 1869 into a circus
family whose founder is said to have been
the model Charles Dickens used for Sleary
in Hard Times.
Today, that circus is utterly forgotten. It
was not a large show. The three partners,
Powell, Foottit and Clarke, reckoned their
share was worth £500 each. In the middle of
the last century it would travel almost 4,000
kilometres in 32 weeks, visiting some 200
towns and taking £8,500-£9,000 in ticket
sales.
Yet that one little show was the cradle of
three of the most famous circus performers
the world has ever seen. John Frederick
Clarke was one. His cousin Ernest Clarke
was the first man to turn a triple somersault,
from bar to catcher, on the flying trapeze.
The third performer, Foottit, was destined
to become famous as a clown.
Clowns have always been an integral pan
of the circus. In a spectacle of physical
prowess which produces a mental reac¬
tion such as wonder, astonishment,
apprehension or admiration in the au¬
dience, a complementary note is needed a
mental concept which produces a physical
reaction in the audience that of laughter.
And like the Jockey riders, many British
clowns achieved more success in continen¬
tal Europe than in their native land. The
two outstanding examples are John Price
(whose splendid portrait by Renoir is now
in the Kröller-Müller collection in The
Netherlands) and Foottit, who with his
Black partner Chocolat became the toast of
Paris at the Nouveau Cirque and was im¬
mortalized by Toulouse-Lautrec.
The epitome of style
Meanwhile, in France and Germany
another aspect of riding had come to the
fore. This was La Haute Ecole, or The High
School of Equitation. I still find an écuyère
riding side-saddle, wearing a habit, top hat,
veil and a bunch of violets in her but¬
tonhole, the very epitome of style. And no
doubt this view was shared by most mem¬
bers of high society at the end of the last
century. The Jockey Club had its private
box at the circus in Paris; while in St. Peters¬
burg the stables were specially scented so
that the aristocratic patrons would not be
offended by the smell.
The circus was better appreciated by the
aristocracy in continental Europe than in
the United Kingdom where , in spite of royal
patronage, High School was rather despised
by the upper classes. They preferred fox¬
hunting. The interest in dressage is a very
recent phenomenon.
Another aspect of working with horses,
at which the French and Germans were
more adept than the British, was the Lib¬
erty act of riderless horses. Ernst Renz,
Eduard Wulff, Albert Carré and, above all,
the Schumanns had superb troupes of
beautifully matched horses, trained to
perfection.
Daring feats on tightrope and flying trapeze
So for 150 years the horse dominated the
circus scene. But although it never lost
pride of place, in the middle of the last
century another influence was making itself
felt. Jules Leotard's invention of the flying
trapeze and Blondin's feat of crossing
Niagara Falls on a tightrope focused the
attention of the public on the individual
performer, working without animals. The
aerialist and rope dancer were followed by
jugglers such as Paul Cinquevalli. Each of
these disciplines eventually threw up the
outstanding acts of all time, the Codonas on
the flying trapeze, Con Colleano on the low
wire, the Wallendas up aloft and Enrico
Rastelli as juggler. Their actual feats may
now have been surpassed, but not their
sense of style.
By the end of the last century, wild anim¬
als were introducing an exotic note to the
circus. Animal dealers such as Carl Hagen-
beck of Hamburg were responsible. He is
usually given credit for introducing the
"gentling" system of animal training, but I
believe the tradition is much older than
that, stretching back into prehistory. Wild
animals had been exhibited in the
menageries throughout the nineteenth cen¬
tury. The wagon cages lined the walls of the
tent surrounding the public. The great in¬
novation came when the wagon cage, open
bars all round with all shutters removed,
was dragged into the centre of the circus
ring. The next step was to build up the big
cage in the ring itself.
And this brings me to the latest influence
on the spectacle of the circus: the growing
importance of apparatus. This movement
started in nineteenth-century Russia, and I
believe that it was the amazing artistry of
their ordinary gymnasts on apparatus such
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
In the early days of the circus, displays of
equestrianism dominated the scene. Below,
the celebrated British trick rider Andrew
Ducrow (1793-1842) as "Jack Tar", in one of
his many scenes on horseback.
The Clown (1868), by the French painter
Auguste Renoir, is a portrait ofJohn Price, a
member of a family of noted English circus
artistes and one of the first "musical"
clowns. Star performers at the Cirque Loyal
in France, John and William Price are
thought to have created the act in which two
clowns play the violin while performing
acrobatics and contortions.
as the Roman Rings and horizontal bars
that forced the circus to find a more spec¬
tacular presentation. So instead of perform¬
ing on a beam, the outside edge of a giant
moving semaphore arm was introduced.
The high wire could no longer remain hori¬
zontal; it had to take on an oblique angle
before our eyes.
Dressing for the occasion
That phrase "before our eyes" reminds
me how important a role apparatus and
accessories perform in the circus. Pierre
Bost, in Le Cirque et le Music Hall (1931),
has pointed out that whereas in the variety
theatre the curtain rises to reveal the appar¬
atus already set up, in the circus the compo¬
nent parts are brought in piece by piece and
assembled before our eyes. One of the mo¬
ments of delight for the aficionado is to
watch an almost insignificant little man in a
dressing gown and clogs adjusting the align¬
ment, checking the level, testing the ten¬
sion, and, when satisfied, leaving the ring
only to throw off his dressing gown and
make a magnificent entry, arm upraised in
salutation, for all the world as if he was
appearing for the very first time.
After such evidence of authenticity,
would it not be absurd for the ring-boys to
cover the apparatus with artificial roses to
make it look like a pergola? Yet I have seen
perches supposedly disguised as palm trees,
and more than one aerial act has introduced
a phoney aeroplane, which apart from look¬
ing silly also distracts by its noise.
This is over-production, which can also
be seen in the costumes performers wear.
They should be designed to enhance the
act. Ever since Con Colleano made his
entrance in Mexican trousers, wire walkers
have copied him. They seem oblivious to
the fact that, once on the wire, he ripped
these trousers off as he turned a
somersault to appear in the knee breeches
of a bull-fighter, so that his magnificent
footwork could be properly appreciated.
Tights and leotards still show aerialists to
their best advantage, because there is no¬
thing to hinder one's appreciation of their
movements through the air, or of the fasci¬
nating foreshortened view of the human
form seen from an unfamiliar angle.
In a High School act it is the unity of horse
and rider that needs stressing. Therefore
the formal classical costume, or the uniform
of Le Cadre Noir, are ideal. Yet I have seen
riders dressed in the red, white and green
frills and flounces, ribbons and bows of
Hungarian peasants, which immediately
established a disunity between horse and
rider. Because I want to see performers
look their best, I do not like seeing dogs
dressed up in crinolines. It merely detracts
from their natural attributes.
I am sure that by now many readers will
think I have gone too far adopted a much
too purist approach. What, you may well
ask, of the rococo band wagons with their
sun-burst wheels, the "oompah" music of
the befrogged and shako-ed band, the
spangles, the elaborately ornate show
fronts with their parades ...? Is not all this
"circus"?
Of course it is. It is the picture-frame
which surrounds the painting, but it is not
the painting it holds. It is a splendid setting
for the spectacle, but it is not the spectacle
itself. What I have tried to do is to get down
to the fundamental principles on which the
circus is built; why it appeals to everyone all
over the world, regardless of age, income
group, rank or class the one truly inter¬
national entertainment where nations are
united.
ANTHONY HIPPISLEY COXE, of the United
Kingdom, has written many articles and books on
the circus, including A Seat at the Circus (Evans
Brothers, London, 1951, Archon Books, Ham-
den, USA, 1980). His extensive collection of
circus memorabilia is preserved in the Theatre
Museum, London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The 'Hundred Entertainments'
China's 2,000-year-old tradition of acrobatics
THE art of Chinese acrobatics dates
back nearly 2,000 years, to the Han
dynasty. Combined with music and
dance, the "Hundred Entertainments", as it
was called, was a major form of amusement
for the ruling classes.
In a work known as the "Prose of the
Western Capital", the scientist and man of
letters Zhang Heng (AD 78-139) vividly
describes the acrobatic art of his time, from
rope dancing and hand standing to juggling,
pole climbing, and balancing on balls. A
stone painting (photo 1) dating from the
Han dynasty, which was found in the ances¬
tral temple of the Wu family in Shandong
Province, depicts a performance that com¬
bines acrobatics with folk dancing.
In the T'ang dynasty (618-907), a special¬
ized "Training Workshop" was established
at the imperial court to train acrobats, musi¬
cians and dancers and to organize shows
comprising up to a dozen types of acrobatic
acts. The T'ang poet Bai Juyi described
some of these, such as "Dual-Sword Danc¬
ing", "Seven-Ball Jumping", "Rope Walk¬
ing" and "Long-Pole Tricks".
During the Sung dynasty (960-1279),
acrobatics gradually went out of favour at
the imperial court, but gained ground as a
form of popular entertainment. "Memories
of the Eastern Capital", by the Southern
Sung writer Meng Yuanlao, records over
one hundred different acrobatic acts.
In the Yuan (1206-1368) and Ming (1368-
1644) dynasties, many acrobatic skills and
techniques were introduced into drama and
opera. The so-called "Lotus Drama" in¬
cluded wire-rope walking, rope dancing,
hand standing, turning somersaults on a
ladder, jar-balancing, lasso tricks and
jumping through fiery or sword-studded
hoops.
China's first national acrobatic group, the
Acrobatic Troupe of China, was created
soon after the founding of the People's Re¬
public in 1949. Inspired by this group, local
troupes were formed all over the country.
Household utensils such as the rice bowl
are among the "props" used by Chinese
acrobats. Balancing a "pagoda" of bowls on
the head has long been part of their reper¬
toire. A picture on a tile unearthed in a Han
tomb in Nan-yang, Honan Province, de¬
picts an acrobat standing on one hand with a
stack of bowls on his head. In the 1950s, a
famous acrobat named Xia Juhua created a
new act which involved balancing a pagoda
of bowls while standing on one hand, and
supporting another stack of bowls between
her feet, thus combining acrobatics and cal¬
listhenics. Her innovation inspired a wide
variety of other "Pagoda of Bowls" acts
(photo 2).
Spinning plates on bamboo poles is
another graceful art which goes back to the
T'ang dynasty and is still practised today
(photo 3). Rope walking and dancing also
have a long history. A huge mural in a Han
tomb in Yinan, Shandong Province, depicts
three girls jumping, dancing and standing
on their hands on a thin rope with four
sharp knives, points uppermost, on the
ground below. Today, in addition to rope
walking, wire walking is practised, either on
a tightly-strung, slack or sloping wire. The
tight-wire walkers specialize in somersaults,
the slack-wire walkers in juggling, clowning
and sword-fights, and sloping-wire perfor¬
mers slide or walk up and down a 10-metre-
long wire strung at an angle of 40°.
The game of diablo, long popular with
Chinese children, has been successfully
turned into a circus act. All kinds of varia¬
tions have been added to the game, which
basically involves whipping a spool (the
"devil") into the air and catching it again
using a cord. The "Two-person Diablo
Game", and "Swinging Around the Body",
as performed by two Chinese acrobats,
Wang Guiying and Wang Shuying, have
added a new dimension to the traditional
game.
The Lion Dance is a beautiful and typical
example of an art form, known as "Mask
Entertainment" in ancient times, in which
people imitate or are disguised as animals.
ë ^
"\ àI;* ><-.
v h¿ mak
1 rsrjî .jr^^^
^T-/& r<V|
1 J>fcl»i#"' -
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
by Huang Minghua
Bai Juyi, in a description of the Lion Dance
as performed in the T'ang dynasty, wrote
that the dancers wore carved wooden masks
on their heads with gilded eyes and silver-
plated teeth. In recent variations of the
Lion Dance, up to four lions balance on a
ball, sometimes combined with work on a
seesaw (photo 4).
As bicycles are a very common means of
transport in China, the skills of trick cyclists
can be readily understood and appreciated
by Chinese audiences. Although bicycle
acrobatics only began at the beginning of
this century, the technique developed
rapidly, with the emergence of many diffe¬
rent collective balancing (see back cover)
and other trick cycling and unicycling acts.
In the 1950s, the acrobat and trick cyclist Jin
Yeqin introduced his "Clown on a Bicycle",
which never fails to captivate audiences
with its humour and wit.
Juggling with the feet is another ancient
balancing skill which is still practised. Wu
Zimu, a Sung dynasty writer, describes
artistes juggling bottles, plates, urns and
clocks with their feet. Peng Shiwang of the
Ch'ing dynasty (1616-1911) recounts how
an acrobat used his feet to juggle an eight-
year-old child, a table, a wooden hammer
and a nine-runged ladder. One of the hun¬
dred paintings produced by a Beijing artist
to illustrate Ch'ing dynasty customs depicts
one acrobat juggling a ladder with his feet
while another balances on top (photo 5).
While people, ladders, stools and chairs
are still used by foot jugglers, new acts have
been invented using even more props:
known as "heavy-weight juggling" with a
table or an urn, or "light-weight juggling"
with tubes or wooden plates.
Chinese acrobats have adapted valuable
techniques from other art forms in order to
develop new shows, some of which incorpo¬
rate dance poses modelled on images from
Buddhist frescoes in the cave temples at
Tun-huang, Kansu Province. From sporting
events they have borrowed the pole climb¬
ing technique (photo 6); other shows have
been developed from work on thé exercise
rings and the horizontal bar; while spring¬
board jumping, introduced into China in
the 1930s, has evolved into a series of com¬
plicated and highly skilled acts, where a
leap from the springboard can take an
acrobat to the top of a six-high human
pyramid, turning a backward somersault on
the way.
HUANG MINGHUA, of China, is a member of
the Association of Chinese Acrobats and deputy
editor-in-chief of "Modern Acrobatics" maga-
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The art of the impossible
A repertoire constantly renewed
by courageous, versatile artists
by Lucien-René Dauven
UNLIKE the circus itself, which can
only establish itself in a new country
by diversifying to adapt to a new
public, the arts of the sawdust ring have
developed in approximately the same way
all over the world, owing to the proverbial
mobility of the "travellers" and the deter¬
mination of all artistes to outshine their
rivals. Since the beginning of the nineteenth
century, there has been a steady stream of
exchanges from one circus to another. A
Franconi Circus number much applauded in
Paris would be seen the following season in
London, Copenhagen or St. Petersburg.
Jules Leotard of Toulouse, who invented
the flying trapeze at the Cirque Olympique
in Paris, and who was unknown before he
made his Paris debut, had already worked
all over Europe when he decided to go to
New York. This was the crowning glory for
a young man who had been improbably
lionized during the Second Empire and
who, impervious to ridicule, styled himself
the "Antinous of the Trapeze".
The animal trainers who came on the
scene around 1830, and the daredevils who
appeared later, are not the only outside
artistes to have been accepted by the circus.
Other examples include the trick cyclists,
adopted by the circus in the heyday of the
velocipede. But experience has shown that
although such artistes can contribute to the
success of a show, they are not indispens¬
able: the essential features of a circus are
still those which made its name when it
began to establish itself as an entertainment
in its own right: horses and acrobats.
In the last century, the circus was called
the "temple of the horse" by its most lyrical
chroniclers, and was primarily a celebration
of women trick riders and side-saddle
equestriennes elevated to the rank of prin¬
cesses. Lovers of horsemanship knew when
to applaud at the right moment. The horse
has vanished from everyday life, and con¬
noisseurs have become rare, but equestrian
acts, ranging from voltige and other forms
of trick riding, to High School and
"Liberty" horse displays, have lost none of
their prestige. They are eagerly awaited,
appreciated, applauded and often cheered.
Just as it is possible to love painting without
©
-^ Walking the high wire, Lagny (France),
1960
ever using a brush, it is possible to admire a
trainer without knowing that chambrière is
the name given to the long whip that he
throws on the ground as he enters the ring,
in order to show the audience that he does
not need it in order to win obedience from
his "pupils".
Equestrian spectaculars
The history of the equestrian arts of the
circus has been punctuated by major turn¬
ing points (such as the introduction of High
School riding around 1820) which can be
dated to within a year or two, depending on
the historian describing them. Although cir¬
cus horsemanship developed rapidly in the
second half of the nineteenth century, it had
Poster announcing the first appearance of
Jules Leotard (1838-1870), the inventor of
the flying trapeze, at the Cirque Napoléon,
Paris, in 1859. At first Leotard worked with
a layer of mattresses below him, the equiva¬
lent of today's safety net.
CIRQUE NAPOLEON
ra_- I ***t«*l *"» Hlk»-J«.. .ihiir.
. MliKft M i-it*rn /OP
DEBUT . Gywuii^Bt TmImsiib LEOTARD fils
MERVEILLES
CYMNASTIQUES
h :. COURSE AUX TUPES* ww h tau Ma ira
LES 2 VIRTUOSES
LE TOURBILLON
l'IYIIIIUII IUIIMM
FANTAISIES CHINOISES
*«l 1K1I l' KIKIM 14 KM
L* PASSE DjUJPËfÎt CERCLE
II, a. n *ii4» <» <
i% riJim m t i »»(tu i -.
il «INvtt-l
©
begun long before in Astley's
Amphitheatre (see article page 4), with bur¬
lesque scenes acted out on horseback, early
versions of comedy acts, and above all with
the dressage interludes which gave the vol¬
tige riders time to get their breath between
two exercises. The first trained performing
horses were not required to do very much,
but as soon as they were gathered in the
ring, they became the distant and unwitting
forerunners of the splendid equestrian spec¬
taculars that are still the pride of the big
circuses.
Carousels, with as many as sixty horses in
the ring, are no longer fashionable, and
nowadays acts with a group of twelve, or
sometimes twenty-four, Liberty horses,
faultlessly performing complicated man¬
oeuvres, have come close to perfection. The
time-honoured traditional repertoire con¬
tinues to be enriched by new routines
smoothly linked under the invisible gui¬
dance of the trainer, who gives orders by
gestures and movements so discreet that
they go unnoticed by most of the audience.
Some recent inventions such as the cloud of
white mist from which the Lipizzaner horses
of the Swiss trainer Frédy Knie gradually
emerge, and the circling of the ring by a
rearing stallion, a finale of rare beauty in¬
vented by the late Alexis Gruss, Senior, are
on the way to becoming classics.
Daredevils on horseback
In the circus, High School has a spectacu¬
lar side unsought in the riding school. Using
training methods that are criticized by mas¬
ters of academic equestrianism, outstan¬
dingly talented écuyers, starting with Fran¬
çois Baucher and his pupil James Fillis,
adapted their art to the restricted area of the
ring and invented new airs such as the pas
espagnol, the galop en arrière and many
others which are still popular today. Circus
horsemanship is different from formal
equitation. It is more showy, but it also
shuns facility, and today boasts high-class
artistes, men and women, who are elegant
riders of splendid horses trained with rigor¬
ous precision. Unfortunately, there are too
many others who turn High School in the
ring into a shameless parody.
Voltige acts are military in origin, but
voltige as practised by circus tumblers on
horseback soon became quite different
from that taught in the barracks. The tradi¬
tional vaults and jumps of voltige were com-
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Alexis Gruss, Junior, and his brother Pat¬
rick, French horsemen and acrobats, leap to
land astride a horse in their "double Jockey"
act, during a performance at the trad¬
itional-style Gruss Circus in Paris. In this
form of voltige act the rider combines
acrobatics with feats of balance on a bare¬
back horse, circling the ring in an anti¬
clockwise direction.
bined with acrobatic feats, and the two
disciplines were already merging when, to¬
wards the middle of the nineteenth century,
two novelties from the United States spread
through Europe: voltige à la Richard, which
was performed bareback without saddle or
bridle, and so-called "Epsom Jockey"
work, a mixture of all known types of vol¬
tige in which the rider leaps off the horse
and vaults on again, landing in a standing or
sitting position. Pride of place, however,
still went to exploits performed actually on
horseback.
Acts became more varied when they were
performed by two or three riders working
together, and when troupes of six to eight
people formed amazing human pyramids
straddling four or five horses trotting neck
and neck. But the store of new tricks was
running out. Although we do not know for
sure where, when and by whom the first
backward somersault from horse to horse
was performed, this exploit was undeniably
more than fifty years old in 1930 when it was
performed by the Franco-Chinese horse¬
man Chotachen Courtault in the ring of the
Cirque Medrano in Paris. It was hailed as a
novelty ... for a time.
There may be fewer trick riders in the
circus than in the past, but the best of them
stand comparison with their predecessors.
There are reasons to doubt whether any
new acts will be devised. In recent years,
novelty has lain primarily in a welcome
return to tradition. Alexis Gruss, Junior,
for one, has vividly revived such long-
forgotten numbers as the "Courier of St.
Petersburg", in which the rider, standing
astride two horses, allows twelve horses to
pass between his legs, snatching up their
long reins ás they pass. This number was
created by Andrew Ducrow in 1826 (see
article page 4) , and had not been performed
for some thirty years.
Leapers and tightrope walkers
Although equestrian acts delighted the
elegant audiences who brought the circus
into fashion, directors soon realized that the
general public, who provided most of the
takings, was less interested in these acts
than in acrobats, leapers and tightrope
walkers, The tumblers of yesteryear,, now
known as artistes "of strength and agility",
soon came to the fore. Many of them be¬
came famous, including Leotard, the clown
Auriol (who could turn a somersault and
land with his feet in his slippers), Blondin,
the tightrope walker, and Risley, who gave
his name to an act in which one or more
performers, lying on their backs, juggle the
smaller members of the company with their
feet (see photo bottom left, centre colour
page).
They all had their imitators, intent on
doing better than their models. Such rivalry
did not exist in the days when professionals
preferred to avoid one another and met
only by chance when they were on the road,
and it accounts for the remarkable develop¬
ment of the art of acrobatics as practised by
the finest circus performers. But this prog¬
ress would probably have been less remark¬
able arid less swift had it not been for the
training that has always been compulsory
for circus folk.
Circus training calls for will-power, pa¬
tience and courage (which the animal train¬
er Gilbert Houcke used to describe as the
three essential qualities of the good crafts¬
man), and for the future acrobat it entails a
long, hard apprenticeship. Before specializ¬
ing at all, he or she must achieve complete
mastery of acrobatic jumps and balancing
acts on the ground. It takes several years'
practice to be able to perform a standing
somersault correctly, or to maintain a hand¬
stand for two minutes. But once an artiste
possesses these skills, the sky's the limit,
and he or she can aspire to excel not just in a
single discipline, but in several, or even in
all. This versatility accounts for the con¬
tinual renewal of acrobatics, which is more
noticeable today than it was in the last
century.
Acrobats who spend years learning an
'impossible' trick
"In acrobatics, the last word is never
spoken, and the nee plus ultra never
attained," wrote Georges Strehly, profes¬
sor of philosophy at the Sorbonne and
historian of acrobats, in 1903. His implicit
tribute to the artistes of the last century is
just as valid today. Since modern acrobats
cannot perform any more extraordinary
movements than those invented by their
predecessors, they combine their tricks with
others borrowed from different disciplines.
Nowadays, jugglers perform not only on
the ground, but standing on their heads on a
tightrope or upright on a galloping horse.
Tumblers use stilts and are thrown into the
air from a springboard; contortionists vary
their dislocationary movements with hand-
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The most critical moment of a breathtaking
act. Perched on a monocycle balanced on a
globe, the young Chinese juggler Fu Xiuyu
performs a feat which won her the City of
Monaco Prize at the 12th Monte Carlo Cir¬
cus Festival in 1987.
to-hand interactions between partners, and
some acts amaze even the most jaded
audience.
Perched on a tall monocycle and pedall¬
ing with one leg in order to keep her balance
on the top of a large wooden globe, which
would begin to roll at the slightest false
movement, the young Chinese acrobat Fu
Xiuyu places four bowls along her free leg,
and then flips them all into the air. The
bowls fly in different directions and then,
stacking neatly into one another, land in a
fifth bowl that she has previously placed on
her head. These are joined shortly after
wards by a teapot and lid, flung into the air
in the same way. The feat seems almost
impossible. But some day will another
artiste make it even more complex by
adding an extra difficulty? It is tempting to
answer: "Why not?". In the circus, as in the
sports stadium, records exist to be broken.
And they always are broken.
The list of recent inventions that bear
witness to the incredible virtuosity and in¬
ventive abilities of acrobats would be a long
one. They dream of performing an impossi¬
ble trick. It will perhaps take them years to
do it, but they will succeed, and sometimes
they will even be outdone by a colleague
who has stooped to faking. Some very im¬
pressive numbers that win the loudest ap¬
plause are of questionable value, because
they consist of tricks that the performer
cannot attempt unless he has first hooked to
his belt the safety rope or "lunge" that will
save his life if he misses his catch. In some
cases, the lunge provides the acrobat with
aid, more or less visible, which deprives the
supposed star turn of any interest.
Fortunately, there are many other num¬
bers which deserve wholehearted enthu¬
siasm, even if they are less impressive and
their merits are apparent only to those
members of the audience who know the real
thing when they see it. Fearlessness is part
of the game, but no one goes to the circus
hoping to see a fellow human mutilated in
the ring. Safety precautions which do not
diminish the quality of acrobatics are thus
to be commended. However, if numbers
involving deception cannot be excluded, at
least let us hope that they are few, and save
our respect (and applause) for acrobats who
are wedded to their art and whose motto
might be: "I am less flashy, but I don't
cheat."
'A happy dream'
Is the art of acrobatics declining or
developing? No acrobat will answer that
question.
The growing complexity of the acts, the
use of new apparatus and the replacement
of one technique by another have depleted
the ranks of those working in the less spec¬
tacular disciplines, which are closest to pure
acrobatics, and which require only muscu¬
lar strength and a keen eye.
But the circus is first and foremost a
spectacle. No voltige rider catapulted up¬
wards by two people clasping each other's
hands has ever reached the fourth level, i.e.
landed on the shoulders of the third man in
a three-man column . But if the same voltige
rider is propelled by a seesaw, which gives a
powerful artificial thrust, he can somersault
and reach the fifth or even the sixth level.
Which of these tricks has the greater merit?
It is difficult to judge, because it is undeni¬
able that the second has a bigger impact
than the first. The trend may be regretted,
but it should not come as a surprise.
One thing is certain, however: if the
achievements of the past cannot be com¬
pared to those of the present, the latter are no
less valid than the former. Acts that were
considered impossible at the beginning of the
century, such as head-to-head balancing
without a protective pad, have been per¬
formed, and no longer surprise anyone; En¬
rico Rastelli surpassed jugglers who, accord¬
ing to Strehly, would never be rivalled; and
the forward somersault on a tightrope, the
virtually exclusive master stroke of Con Col-
leano in the 1930s, features in the repertoire
of all good specialists. One of them, Luis
Muñoz, performs it in the "lay-out" or fully
extended position, and no longer "balled-
up", with his arms hugging his knees to his
chest, like all his predecessors.
Riders, animal trainers and acrobats: in
the ring, all remain eternally young, and
thanks to them the circus is still, as Heming¬
way wrote, the only show that gives the
audience the feeling that they are living in a
happy dream.
What better reason could there be for
loving the circus?
LUCIEN-RENE DAUVEN, French journalist,
writer and contributor to the revised edition of
Henry Thétard's La merveilleuse histoire du cir¬
que, has been the editor since 1959 of Le cirque
dans l'univers, the quarterlyjournal of the Paris-
based Club du Cirque, ofjxhich he is president.
The Editors wish to express theirgratitude to Mr.
Dauven for his assistance in the preparation of
this issue.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
The Little Top
by Jorge Enrique Adoum
Latin America is justly famous for the
quality of its big circuses, but it is the
poignant world of the small-time circus
rather than glamorous Big Top spec¬
taculars that inspired this evocation by
the Ecuadorian novelist and poet Jorge
Enrique Adoum.
THE Argentine poet Raul González
Tuñón penned the following descrip¬
tion of the character whose name
figures in the title of his book Los poemas de
Juancito Caminador: "He was a pitiful
negro, who worked in a circus. All circuses
are poor, but this one was poorer than the
poor. He had planned a 'magic act', in
which he placed a skull on a table, with a
lettuce leaf beneath its one remaining jaw¬
bone. Behind it, where the audience could
not see, there was a rabbit eating the leaf,
v and this gave the impression that the skull
was doing so. When the rabbit died, he lost
his job. I don't know whether he just didn't
think of buying another rabbit, or whether
he couldn't afford to buy one."
The universal symbol of the circus the
tent means poverty to the Latin Amer¬
ican. Whenever the tent is mended or
patched, ten new gaps appear, and when it
rains the audience have to use their umbrel¬
las. These gaps would be a godsend for the
bare-foot children who cannot afford to pay
the entrance money, were it not for the
local police who, either because the mana¬
ger or owner of the circus has greased their
palms or because they are always ready to
do anything that stops the poor from doing
what they want, prevent them from enter¬
ing what for them is paradise.
The Ecuadorian writer Raúl Vallejo once
wrote a story called "The World's Most
Patched-up Circus Tent" and a similar tent
appears again and again in "The Triple
Jump", a collection of texts by his compat¬
riot Iván Egiiez. But the image of poverty
evoked by the circus tent is best captured by
the Chilean poet Alfonso Alcalde: "The
lion's coat was so worn that some friends
had patched it up with bits of socks and old
shirt-sleeves. There were patches of every
colour yellow, with purple or green
stripes, or red circles. When the lion was
pleased, it wagged its tail, which was tied up
with string."
That is when there is a lion. For exotic
animals, the main attraction of a circus, are
very expensive. They have to be imported
from Africa or bought in European mar¬
kets; transport has to be paid for; a suitable
environment must be created for them; they
cost a fortune to feed. (When one of these
Pablo Picasso, circus-lover and a frequent
spectator at the Cirque Medrano in Paris,
painted many canvases on circus themes,
especially during his "Rose Period". His Girl
on a Ball (1905), left, is today preserved in
the State Pushkin Museum of Fine Arts,
Moscow.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
"real" circuses came to town, the street
urchins, who had somehow found out in
advance, used to catch stray dogs and sell
them as food for the wild animals.) And so
these little circuses, which try their luck on
the outskirts of big cities, dwarfed by Ferris
wheels and merry-go-rounds, are proud
when they can show off an elephant or a
bear in much the same wretched state as
Alfonso Alcalde's lion, animals which the
big circuses sell off because they can no
longer stand on their feet.
The village circuses are even poorer and
virtually sedentary, although they may
travel short distances in a truck where the
performers sleep beside their belongings
so much for the nostalgic image of a caravan
of covered wagons where "Gypsies" live
(for we always regarded the circuspeople as
Gypsies, perhaps because of the fortune¬
tellers) with their children who never know
for sure which country they were born in.
Such village circuses are happy if they can
produce a wild cat of some kind. The tamer,
a kind of poor man's Tarzan in a makeshift
uniform, usually has his eye on an eques¬
trienne in a rival circus that has horses,
while also setting his cap at the mulatto
trapeze artiste, who is nearly always the
owner's daughter-in-law or concubine. He
is remarkable for his stature rather than his
skill; he makes a great noise when cracking
his whip in order to conceal his failure to
overcome the animals' obstinate refusal to
obey him.
The other animals the circus keeps are
small, tame monkeys, inevitably dressed up
as babies, which squeal as they jump, clam¬
ber up high and turn somersaults, and "per¬
forming dogs" dressed up as clowns, Gyp¬
sies or ballerinas, depending on their sex.
The dogs' main activity is walking around
with a hat in their jaws, collecting money
from the audience, who are seated on
planks placed on trestles. The money they
collect is a kind of gratuity over and above
the entrance fee or the price of a bag of
candied peanuts made by the women in the
troupe. (Sometimes a bigger dog, dressed
in a tawny-coloured skin, serves as a tiger.)
And in at least one village in the Andes
there are hens with skirts or cloaks and even
neckties, whose act consists of running
madly round the sawdust-covered ring.
The performers, who are usually mem¬
bers of one family (to avoid splitting up the
takings) are much the same as in any circus.
There is the female contortionist and the
bearded lady, the sword-swallower, the
knife-thrower who more often than not
misses the target, and the magician who
pulls many a scarf and bunch of flowers out
of his painted cardboard hat, but never a
rabbit which would be enough for the
family dinner ... or could have kept Juan-
cito Caminador in his job. The tightrope
walkers and acrobats are particularly
courageous since they know that the
trapeze is a dubious piece of apparatus
patched up with odd bits of wire, that the
tightrope was bought second-hand at the
frontier, and that there is no safety net to
protect them from a sudden return to earth .
Some new additions to the repertoire
indicate concessions to modernity: "Super¬
man and the Seven Dwarfs", "Franken¬
stein's Coffin", and "The King of the Jun¬
gle" (who stands in for the tamer when the
latter is dismissed by the owner or his son
for making advances to the trapeze artiste),
the hunchback who swivels round on his
Two Colombian aerialists, members of the
Los albarracines troupe, performing at the
Cirque d'Hiver, Paris
hump, and the dwarf who dances on his
head. Until recently fakirs were another
attraction . An exotic figure if ever there was
one, the fakir was locked up with a snake in
a glass-topped chest, where he fasted for
thirty days. Some members of the audience
thought that this was an inordinate length of
time and yelled, "Some people will do any¬
thing rather than work !", obliging the
police commissioner to certify personally
that it was not a hoax.
The band, recruited from local musi¬
cians, enlivens the show with tunes of ineff¬
able gloom. It's the same band that strikes
up in the square late on Sunday afternoons
after playing at the Sunday morning foot¬
ball match in the same square (sometimes
there is only one team and the players wear
ordinary clothes) and at bullfights where
there are no spangled costumes and no
matadors, and the bull careers round the
square, knocking over the Indians and mes¬
tizos who have been drunk since the night
before. A band which, wherever it plays,
pours out the melancholy of villages hud¬
dled in the hollows of the cordillera and
covered with a veil of dust that protects
them from the drizzle. The grocer plays the
cornet, the chemist the trombone, the
muleteer the flute, the lawyer's clerk the
saxophone, and the barber the clarinet. The
butcher's boy beats the drum, consoling
himself for his humble destiny with the
knowledge that the death-defying leap
would be impossible, or at least not so
exciting, were it not for the roll of his drum.
In the poorest circuses of all, the problem is
solved by the cassette-player, a marvellous
substitute for the gramophone, with its re¬
cords that used to get broken after every
performance.
Here, as everywhere, the clown is the
person who most fully expresses the way
things are in communities that are victims of
the system. He also expresses his own situa¬
tion as a victim of the circus, for he does not
belong to the family which owns it. They
exploit him, for as well as clowning he has to
drum up business, collect the entrance
money, put away the props and sweep up
after the show. Here more than anywhere,
the clown is what the American writer
Henry Miller called "fate's pawn".
Although some people prefer to see him as
the village idiot, the shoe-shine boy in the
market, or a stammering beggar, rather
than, like them, the victims of others or
of fate.
In big, well-equipped international cir¬
cuses, the clown's attire has to "look" torn,
his hat and shoes must "suggest" a tramp's
outfit. But in our sort of circus, both in
everyday life and on the night when there is
a show, the clown (in remote villages an
artisan or peasant, in the city an itinerant
who goes from circus to circus), has his
elbows and knees showing through holes in
his shabby old clothes whose patches are
not part of the costume , but marks of pover¬
ty. Slapped in the face, kicked about, spat
at, the poor wretch is a compendium of the
mistakes and stupidities of humanity. He
walks like a blind man, bumps into walls,
can't grasp explanations, doesn't hear what
people say to him. He is a blockhead made
fun of and exploited by another blockhead,
because it takes two to represent society
and the system. The other blockhead blows
him up and then deflates him, plays tricks
on him, fills his hat with water, and pulls
away his chair so that he sits down with a
bump. And the children laugh. After all,
why shouldn't they laugh at the misfortunes
of this hapless wretch if it helps them get
even with a life in which there is little to
laugh about? And even the adults laugh
because some of them see their own like¬
ness in the clown. For everyone knows that
the other chap, the rascal, the bully, the
villain, never makes people laugh.
Such are the images of gloom and poverty
evoked by the kind of circus that does not
come to town headed by a parade of acro¬
bats riding exotic animals, while the big
band plays. During the interval it's imposs¬
ible to buy a photo of a pretty girl walking
on a ball bigger than she is (for one thing the
girl who performs this act isn't pretty; for
another, balls are so expensive that she has
to use an empty barrel smelling of liquor).
There is no printed programme. Sometimes
there are no tickets; you just hand over your
money at the entrance and walk in. But the
main thing is that such circuses bring poor
people a fleeting moment of happiness on a
Sunday afternoon. For next morning, when
the farce of the system starts all over again
they too will have to contend with cuffs,
kicks and shabby treatment, and perform
their own leaps into the void and their own
balancing acts as they move forward along
an unsteady and endless tightrope.
JORGE ENRIQUE ADOUM, Ecuadorian writer,
has published several volumes ofpoetry, includ¬
ing an anthology, No son todos los que están:
Poemas (1949-1979), a novel, Entre Marx y una
mujer desnuda, and two plays, La subida a los
infiernos and El sol bajo las patas de los caballos
(published in English as The Sun Trampled be¬
neath the Horses' Hooves).
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
64 -
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Self-portrait of a clown by Leonid G. Engibarov
I trained at the Moscow Circus School,
where my teacher was Yuri Petrovich
Belov, a young director passionately
interested in the art of the clown. We cre¬
ated my character together. Inventing a
character is the trickiest of all the problems
facing a clown. An actor on the screen, on
the stage or even in music hall is in a very
much easier position, because his character
is described in writing by an author, where¬
as the clown creates his own character.
All sorts ofquestions had to be answered.
For example, should my character wear a
clown's make-up? We considered in turn
the make-up and masks worn by the
greatest comic artistes that we knew. What
ideas could they give us for the figure that
we were creating? We were particularly
drawn to the white face of Grock, the great
Swiss clown. I found this make-up, similar
to the classical mask of Pierrot, very
attractive.
On mature reflection, we nevertheless
decided against a variant of this type of
mask, which strongly emphasizes the sad
eyes of the person acting the clown. But
before deciding on the make-up, it was
necessary to work out the personality of my
character. Who was he?
At Belov's suggestion, we gave free rein
to our imagination and carefully noted
everything that occurred to us in connection
with our character, whom we called
Lionia Engibarov, since I had decided that,
initially, he would be loosely based on
myself.
Our Lionia was a youth of eighteen or
nineteen, whose life had followed a similar
pattern to my own. Like me, he had been
born in Moscow. He did not have very
pronounced national characteristics, but
was clearly of Eastern origin. We strove to
understand his personality, his likes and
dislikes, his view of the world, his tastes, his
inclinations and everything that made him
an individual in his own right. We gave him
a child's curiosity and thirst for knowledge,
both of which would very often lead him
into scrapes.
Here we already had material for comic
misunderstandings. But we had to give
much more emphasis to the character's
comic side. I was determined that Lionia
should be a very modest person. He per¬
forms the most complicated circus feats
without turning a hair. We thought and
events proved us right that there was
strong comic potential in this.
Lionia's personality gradually took
shape. Here was a comic hero who made
people laugh without malice. We agreed
that he should be a sort of gallant knight,
@ -4 Left, the great Swiss clown Grock (Adrien
s Wettach, 1880-1959) waits to go into the ring
I at Toulon, France, 1954
always ready to fly to the rescue of ladies or
underdogs. Even if Lionia did not look like
a tough guy, he had a certain strength of
character.
Finally we had to fit him out with clothes.
It was essential that his costume should not
be a hindrance to juggling or acrobatics,
and so it had to be functional. But it also had
to express the character's personality.
Lionia wears his father's outsize shoes, a
feature that we borrowed from our beloved
Chaplin. His trousers and the braces that
hold them up were an idea of my mother's.
"Dressed like that, he'll look a real scally¬
wag," she said.
Then we spent a long time looking for a
shirt, and finally opted for a striped singlet
that makes him look even thinner than he
is. We tried out several dozen types of
headgear, from caps to berets, before de¬
ciding that what suited Lionia best was the
most ordinary type of hat, bought across the
counter. We tied a silk scarf around his neck
and put a slapstick in his hands to show
clearly that he was a clown, and we decided
that he would enter the ring walking per¬
fectly normally.
The image continued to develop as we
worked. The young fellow still had to
mature, not physically, but psychologically.
However, if my invented character was to
mature, I had to develop spiritually as an
artiste. To be a brilliant juggler and capable
Leonid Engibarov (below) believed that "the
clown always does everything seriously. Of
course, that's not to say that he doesn't want
to be funny. On the contrary, his aim is to
make people laugh. But the true comic does
this without trying to raise a laugh at any
price."
of doing handstands is not enough, nowa¬
days, to make a clown worthy of the name.
The artiste must, as the Czechs say, be
"drawn out of himself. In the way that he
handles a character, the artiste gives im¬
mediate, perceptible expression to the way
he relates to it. And this is precisely what I
want: the audience must always be aware,
underneath Lionia's comic guilelessness, of
my own personal reactions to what happens
to him.
I have often been asked why I never
speak in the ring. It is not because I can't but
because the circus is primarily a visual spec¬
tacle. It seems to me that people go to the
circus to "watch" a performance and not to
"hear" one. I am silent also because I am
very fond of mime. I love its language,
wordless yet so remarkably expressive.
The subject of a circus mime must be
simple, like a children's fable, without
being unduly "primitive". A true fable is a
fount of wisdom; its meaning can always be
clearly grasped. A person performing a cir¬
cus mime must aim at the same kind of
clarity. As a rule, I create my own inter¬
ludes and scenes. How do I get the ideas for
my comic turns? There is no hard-and-fast
rule. It varies according to the circumstan¬
ces. However, I always start by writing a
little story for my character. I imagine all
sorts of adventures that he might have, and
I place him in a wide variety of situations.
I sometimes feel that I have "said it all"
and used up all my ideas. Only fresh emo¬
tions can help at such a time, whether ex¬
perienced directly in life or through the
mirror of art. When such moods descend on
me, I spend a lot of time strolling around, I
travel and I voraciously watch films and
shows. Not necessarily comedies. Grieg and
Beethoven are as indispensable to a co'mic
artiste as Charlie Chaplin, Buster Keaton or
Fernandel. I let myself be guided by my
curiosity. I listen to music whenever I can. I
go to exhibitions and art galleries, and visit
painters in their studios. I have a craving for
poetry. I leaf through my collection of char¬
acter sketches and caricatures.
One day I happened to hear a blues sung
by that incomparable Black American
singer Louis Armstrong. I was moved by
the poignant sadness of the melody. Almost
against my will, a subject for a little story
crept into my mind: the story of a sad
acrobat. He has known so many failures
that even when he has become an artiste of
great prowess, dexterity and talent, he can¬
not believe in his own success. And this lack
of confidence makes him very touching. I
fleshed out this theme with the help of a few
tricks and stunts.
. Lionia walks towards the audience with
his head bent, his hands in his pockets. He
gives the traditional salutation and then, to
the slow tempo of this sad blues, he starts to
go through a complicated routine. At the
end, he walks towards the ring doors, as
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
"Having chosen to make mime my life's
work, I assembled a collection of themes for
pantomimes and sketches." Above, En¬
gibarov strikes a pose in a mime sequence
entitled The Crocodile.
dejected as ever. The ringmaster urges him
to come back and take a bow. But the young
man still cannot believe that his art can give
pleasure to anyone, and he shakes his head.
Then the audience warmly applauds Lionia,
to encourage him. And when he appears for
the next turn, happy and beaming, the audi¬
ence bursts into even louder applause.
It always gives me great satisfaction as an
artiste when I succeed in mastering a new
genre or in performing an original trick. But
I never, never do a number in the ring just
for its own sake. I always make sure that
each trick is woven into a story that matches
my character.
One day, somebody told me about skip¬
ping with a rope, not in the usual upright
manner, but lying down. I decided to prac¬
tise this trick, which greatly appealed to me.
But for a long time I was unable to work it
into an act, since I could not think of a
suitable pretext. Skipping ropes and urchins
go very well together, I reasoned. But how
could I bring in skipping lying down?
And then I had an idea. The ringmaster is
annoyed when he sees that rascal Lionia
skipping during the performance, and takes
away his rope. But Lionia has another in
reserve. The ringmaster confiscates that
one, too, and then a third. This walking
embodiment of discipline finally gets really
angry and forces the kid to turn out his
pockets. But Lionia acts stupid and pre¬
tends not to understand what he is supposed
to do. I get as much as I can out of the
business of emptying my pockets, first the
right, then the left, according to Chaplin's
principle of milking a gag for the last drop of
laughter. The audience watches the scene
closely, and it does not occur to anyone that
I may have another rope ... in my hat. This
is a wonderful surprise for everyone.
But what a pity the rope is too short.
What is to be done? I heave a disappointed
sigh, and then I hit on the solution: I stretch
out on the floor and start to skip lying down.
When the ringmaster rushes towards me yet
again, I quickly knot the rope around my
heck like a tie. My whole attitude seems to
be proclaiming: you can't touch me, it's
only my tie. Then I march out with my nose
in the air.
Improvisation is another way of creating
an act. I have a very soft spot for our
wonderful clown Karandash, who is famous
for his improvisations. And although I con¬
sider the best "improvisation" to be the one
that can be rehearsed beforehand, I am
willing to improvise if the opportunity
arises.
One day, when I was working one of the
many interludes in the programme, the
ringmaster whispered in my ear: "Spin it
out." This meant that there was a problem
behind the scenes and that the audience had
to be kept amused. I had neither my slap¬
stick nor my hat, both useful props in such
cases. But I noticed that the props manager
had placed a microphone on the ring fence,
ready for the next number.
As I walked towards the microphone, I
had no idea what I was going to do. But as
soon as I had it in my hands, an idea came to
me and I burst into an impassioned speech
... which did not have a single word in it. I
suddenly realized that the microphone was
not working. I tapped it and blew into it.
Meanwhile I was desperately thinking:
"What next? What next?". "Step on the
wire", the voice of inspiration suddenly sug¬
gested. Remembering the illusionist's trick
of distracting the audience's attention by a
false movement, I raised the microphone as
if to hold it closer to the light, and thus
made the audience look up, while in the
meantime I surreptitiously trod on the wire.
From then on it was all plain sailing. To my
great surprise, I had discovered what was
wrong.
I shifted my foot and tapped again on the
microphone: everything was working! I
took up the stance of an orator. And sud¬
denly I was overcome by stage-fright. I
opened my mouth, but no words came. In a
panic, I shot a glance at the ringmaster. He
gave an encouraging sign. I signalled to him
that I was afraid, and on a sudden impulse I
held the microphone to my heart like a
stethoscope. The rest followed naturally: I
started to tap gently on the microphone
with one finger, and the whole circus heard
the rapid "toc-toc" of my racing heart. Then
I had the idea of testing the ringmaster's
heart. It was beating to quite a different
rhythm, at long intervals: "boom ... boom
Colour pages
Colour page opposite
A "spec" or pantomime in progress during a
recent season of Ringling Bros, and Barnum
& Bailey, America's largest circus (see
article page 30)
Photo © AH. Saxon, Fairfield, Conn., USA. All Rights Reserved
Centre colour pages
(1) A clown in brightly coloured costume
decked out with badges entertains a young
member of the audience at the annual
clowns' convention at Bognor Regis (UK).
(2) A troupe of Egyptian artistes at a drama¬
tic moment in a Risley Act, in which perfor¬
mers lying on their backs juggle smaller
members of the company with their feet. (3)
The Palacios, Mexican flying trapeze
artistes in action at the Benneweis Circus
(Denmark). (4) The Diables Blancs, a troupe
of European funambulists whose skills won
them an award at the Monte Carlo Interna¬
tional Circus Festival. (5) Martine Gruss
leaps the garters in a classic pad horse act.
(6) Rearing Lipizzaner horses of the Swiss
National Circus under the direction of
Marie-José Knie. The white-coated Lipiz-
zaners, bred as early as the 16th century in
Austria, are particularly suited to High
School exercises.
1 . Photo Jeremy Nicholl © Impact. Paris
2. Photo © Sylvie Mercier, Paris
3. Photo © Sylvie Mercier, Paris
4. Photo © Sylvie Mercier, Paris
5. Photo © MONKA
6. Photo Weiland © Rapho, Paris
. . . boom". The audience burst out laughing.
And at that moment we received the signal
that behind the scenes everything was now
in order.
Later, I developed and improved on what
had come to me by chance. I concentrated
on showing my anxiety about the irregular
rhythm of the ringmaster's heartbeat. I am
dismayed as it begins to beat more and more
slowly and finally stops. In desperation, I
look everywhere for his heart, placing the
microphone over various parts of his body.
But in vain. I shake his head to and fro, peer
into his eyes and burst into despairing sobs.
Then, with a smile, the ringmaster suggests
that I should look for his heart on the left,
and when the microphone finds it and I hear
it beating perfectly normally, I am filled
with childlike joy.
LEONID GEORGIEVITCH ENGIBAROV
(1935-1972), of the Soviet Union, was one of the
first modern clown-mimes. A skilled juggler,
tightrope walker and acrobat, he also performed
in films, pantomime and music hall, in sketches
that he had written himself. This article is an
edited version of a contribution to "The Art of
the Clown", published in 1969 in the USSR.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
<
« -w> )
^î
. ^
/
Mäff'i
f V;'
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
>_ *S£
m^ÊMtmiiiÊnmft^ ~*
MjTÄ"
S.
I
m-
NT:
I
m
m
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
>J
\
i.
v
Miff
*
£
ii
I
*
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Last winter, Soviet clown Anatoli Martchevskigave this ringside interview
to the Unesco Courier while touring France with the Moscow Circus.
A juggler and acrobat as well as a clown, the talented Martchevski (born
1948) is a man ofmanyparts whose activities in the arts rangefrom directing
films to writing children's books.
The profession
of laughter
Have you wanted to be a clown ever since
you were a child?
Since even before I was a child !
Why were you attracted to being a clown?
It's one of the most human professions
there is. The clown is the personification of
laughter. But it's a kind of laughter which
doesn't belittle human dignity. A clown
doesn't lose his dignity when he makes the
audience laugh. People see him as their
equal or as someone they can identify with.
He has become the hero of a show.
When you say "audience", are you thinking
mainly of children?
Children are the most honest and genuine
audience. Through them, you can test the
quality of an act and work out exactly how
to make your entrance. Adults, on the
other hand, react in terms of their pre¬
conceived ideas about the world.
You don't have a red nose, you don't wear a
grotesque costume ... you have hardly any
make-up. How would you define the type of
clown you play?
In the Soviet Union it's known as the mod¬
ern clown, to distinguish it from classical
comic figures such as the auguste and the
white-faced clown. For us the clown is first
and foremost an artiste who comes into the
ring to express his own personality to the
public. He does not represent a fictional
character. Nor is he a traditional type. It's
his real self, an individual human being,
that emerges from behind his make-up.
Is the modern clown, as you see him, very
different from the auguste?
Yes, each has a particular psychology and
sense of humour. Auguste is the archetype
of the character for whom nothing goes
right: he is in thrall to the bossy, intellectual
and rather narrow-minded white-faced
clown. But I don't want to play auguste as in
the past, in the classical manner. I'll keep
his outward appearance, the "mask", as
well as his kindness and love of mischief,
but I'll add my own inventions. I should like
to create a blend of the classical and modern
art of clowning. My "rose" act can be per¬
formed as an auguste, for example. But that
would mean mixing up different types of
clown. If I play a modern clown, then it's
me, Martchevski, with no disguise, but if I
play auguste, then it's auguste acting and
not Martchevski.
< Colour page left
The Soviet juggler Serguei Ignatov works
with as many as 11 rings, a world record
Photo © Sylvia Mercier, Paris
Will you always be a clown?
Yes , because I want always to be a man . For
me there is no difference between the clown
and the man. I am the same person now,
talking to you, as I am in the ring.
How did you become a professional clown?
By chance. Big circuses didn't visit the little
Ukrainian town where I grew up. I was
eighteen when I first went to the circus, but
I became an amateur circus performer while
I was still at school. It was my passion. First
I worked as an acrobat and trick cyclist in a
small outfit known as the "Circus on Stage".
But at the same time I was preparing to go
to technical college to train as an engineer.
Then came the day when I had to fill in for a
clown who couldn't come on tour...
What happened?
I saw the eyes of the audience as they
laughed, I heard their laughter and their
applause. It was irresistible. It's like when
you know a funny story and you're longing
to tell it to somebody. You're already
laughing about it and you enjoy it just as
much as the person you tell it to. It's this
need to share, to make people laugh, to
make them react, to bring them some
warmth and a positive feeling, which drives
me on. So I decided to become a profession¬
al clown.
Is this encounter with the public always
crucial for you?
Yes. Of course, audience reactions can vary
from town to town, and from country to
country. The age range of the spectators is
different every night and that affects the
nature of the show. We're used to it, that's
how things are. With an audience that loves
the circus, the experience is very fruitful;
it's like two people communicating frankly
and openly. In one way or another, every
actor on stage, every person in real life,
always wants some form of contact. Well,
that's what I offer: knowing how to give,
being receptive to others. And that's how I
want to live.
In photo sequence, right, taken at a Paris
performance during the Moscow Circus's
tour of France in 1986-1987, clown Anatoli
Martchevski burlesques the act of weightlif-
ter Valentin Dikul, who had preceded him in
the ring. Dikul is a bearded colossus who
juggles weights of 50 to 500 kg as if they were
feathers. After finding other uses for the talc
which the weightlifter had rubbed on his
hands to give him a better grip, Martchevski
gravely tries to lift barbells whose weights
are balloons. In this parody sketch, Mart¬
chevski returns to one of the clown's tradi¬
tional sources of inspiration.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Schools for artistes
by Monica J. Renevey
Rapt spectators at the Grand Cirque, Palais
des Sports, Paris, 1957
THE Swiss sociologist Jean Ziegler
claims that the circus is "the last
surviving trace of an ancient, ex¬
istential and esoteric form of knowledge".
There are only two ways of perpetuating
this knowledge and the unique, ancestral
art of the circus: transmitting it from gen¬
eration to generation within the family, or
teaching it in a circus school.
Great circus dynasties such as the Knie,
the Gruss, the Togni, the Althoff and a few
other families have practised the first
method. But, as we shall see, a Gruss and a
Fratellini also founded the first circus
schools in France. Conversely, it is quite
common in countries such as the USSR and
Poland to find third- or even fourth-genera¬
tion circus artistes who are learning their
skills at the State circus school, but who also
benefit incalculably from the experience of
their fathers, of members of an older gener¬
ation. In the past, too, a boy would some¬
times be lured away by the glamour of the
sawdust ring and "oompah" music and,
leaving his family and his village, would be
lucky enough to find a "master" who would
agree to teach him all the tricks of the trade.
Let us pay a brief visit to some of the
circus schools that exist today in different
parts of the world. First stop will be the
famous Moscow Circus School, followed by
its counterparts in Poland, Hungary, the
Democratic People's Republic of Korea,
and Cuba. Next we will head for France,
which boasts three big circus schools, and
then look at a few isolated but interesting
cases, such as the Big Apple Circus in New
York, Canada's Cirque du Soleil, and the
acrobatic troupes of China.
In 1919, Lenin signed a decree on the
"nationalization of theatres and circuses" in
the Soviet Union. At that time there were
very few Russian artistes, and their Western
counterparts, who were far more numer¬
ous, became the first instructors of the new
generation of Soviet circus performers. The
Moscow School was inaugurated in 1927 as
the "School for Circus Arts", and its first
pupils graduated in 1930. One of them,
Mikhail Nikolaievich Rumiantsev (1901-
1983), later became world famous as the
clown Karandash (literally "pencil", in
Russian). The Soviet Union is undeniably
the hardest place in which to learn to be a
clown, because of the very high standards
required in the examinations. A Soviet
clown must be not only a perfect mime
but also a rope dancer, a walker on the
slack wire, a good juggler and an excellent
acrobat.
In addition to the famous Moscow
School, the USSR has two more official
circus schools organized along the same
lines. One is at Kiev, in the Ukraine, and
the other is at Tbilisi, in Georgia. About a
hundred teachers (sixty of them full time)
instruct 300 pupils. The age of admission
ranges from fifteen to twenty, and the
course lasts four years. Every year, three
selective examinations (medical including
general bearing and presence, physical apti¬
tudes and musical ability) weed out all but
seventy-five pupils.
In the first year, eclectic forms of
teaching and practical work enable the
teachers to assess their pupils' general abili¬
ties and, above all, their individual gifts.
Pupils are encouraged to go on only if they
are capable of reaching a very high level.
Specialization takes place in the second
year, and the third year is spent refining and
polishing. The fourth and final year belongs
to the chosen few who are considered to be
worthy representatives of the Soviet circus.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Those who are not chosen will play "small
parts", as long as they pass the two final
examinations, one in their own discipline
and another in philosophy, for in the USSR
a circus artiste is something more than a
muscular, spangled figure capable of land¬
ing accurately to within the nearest mil¬
limetre on his partner's feet, or of making
animals perform without seeming to give
them any orders. The circus artiste is always
part of a vast and carefully planned pro¬
gramme inspired by a long-term philosophy
of the performing arts.
In the last few years, all the circus profes¬
sionals who meet annually at the Monte
Carlo Festival have been saying that "the
wind is blowing from the East". The new
trend in the circus, which combines har¬
mony of gesture, beauty of performance
and strength of feeling, has sprung from
Soviet circus philosophy.
The director of the Leningrad Circus,
Valentin Kuznetsov, like other Soviet cir¬
cus school authorities, feels that "technical
skill alone is a thing of the past. The overrid¬
ing aim is now to communicate an emotion
to the audience. In the Soviet Union today,
a circus performance is planned as if it were
a piece of drama, with a prologue, action,
and epilogue. The almost theatrical
sequence of the acts is of paramount im¬
portance, but the progression must be sus¬
tained by a heightening of emotion. This is
where the entrée clown, typical of the
USSR, comes in. The whole programme
hinges on him; he is the hub of all the
action ..."
The art of clowning has also changed; the
clown now tries to get people to smile rather
than laugh. Considerable subtlety is re¬
quired, and in addition to his physical pro¬
wess the artiste must be able to understand
the psychology of different types of au¬
dience, know all about the joys and sorrows
of everyday life and possess great emotional
versatility.
Nearly all the other socialist countries of
Eastern Europe have circus schools, but the
standard achieved by their graduates is in
most cases lower than that of their Soviet
counterparts. The main reason for this is the
lack of support for circus arts and artistes on
the part of many local authorities.
In Poland, the winter quarters of circuses
and of the school are in Julinek, 30
kilometres from Warsaw, on a former great
estate in the beautiful forest of Kampinov-
ski. Only pupils who have passed their
secondary school leaving certificate and are
under the age of twenty-one are allowed to
enrol for the two-year courses held at the
school, which was founded in 1967. In the
first year, a wide range of disciplines are
taught, including anatomy and biomecha¬
nics. Preparation for individual acts takes
place in the second year, which also in¬
cludes paid training periods with Polish cir¬
cuses. In order to get the most out of
Balanced on a knife edge. A spectacular feat
based on the strength of the jaw, as per¬
formed in Paris by the Circo Americano, a
big Italian circus.
Poland's artistic potential, some directors
are trying to extend the courses and make
them more intensive, and, above all, to
lower the age of admission to sixteen.
Cuba and the Democratic People's Re¬
public of Korea have each founded a circus
school on the Soviet model. In Cuba, which
has four circuses, there is a four-year
course, and pupils often finish their training
in Moscow, while the national circus and
school founded in Pyongyang in 1952 pro¬
vides four years of basic training after which
the pupils begin to polish their acts. One
typical Korean acrobatic number uses the
seesaw (a piece of apparatus that can be
seen in parks all over the country); recently
Western audiences have had the opportun¬
ity to admire a young acrobat in a tight-
fitting kimono turn backward somersaults
after being launched in this way.
Back in Europe, the Budapest Circus
School follows the Moscow pattern, except
that its organization is patriarchal (many
families today have been in the circus for
four or even five generations). All the
teachers are former artistes or gymnasts.
Like its counterparts for drama and dance,
the Hungarian Circus School accepts pupils
at eleven years of age and offers an eight-
year course. The first half of the course is
spent studying basic disciplines and general
culture, up to the level of the school leaving
certificate. The second half provides profes¬
sional training, with three years devoted
primarily to acrobatics, followed by spe¬
cialization. The School may modify an act
to suit the aptitudes of a pupil or even to
take account of market demand. It is open
to Westerners and has already awarded
diplomas to French and Swiss pupils.
The Gruss Circus School, founded in
Paris in 1972 by Alexis Gruss Junior and the
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
In the Soviet Union, circus artistes are as
popular as film stars and sporting heroes,
and there is strong competition for admis¬
sion to circus schools. Above, a young
Muscovite tries his hand at clowning, made
up as Oleg Popov, the internationally known
Soviet clown.
One time-honoured way of becoming a cir¬
cus performer is to belong to one of the great
circus dynasties. Below, Achille Zavatta, a
famous auguste, leaves the ring with his son
Franck.
actress Silvia Monfort, was also "patriar¬
chal". It was housed in a former theatre
whose high-ceilinged rooms were particu¬
larly suitable for practising trapeze acts.
The pupils studied basic subjects for one
year and then prepared their act for two
years before performing in their own old-
style Circus. With their small tent pitched in
the heart of Paris and the school right next
to it, the Gruss family were pioneers in
revolutionizing circus arts in the West.
Also in Paris, Annie Fratellini and Pierre
Etaix founded the National Circus School,
open to all young people between the ages
of sixteen and twenty-five (see article page
27). There are even beginners' classes for
six-year-olds. Basic disciplines are taught in
the first year, and then technical problems
(erecting and dismantling apparatus, light¬
ing) are tackled, and training periods are
arranged in a travelling circus. After three
years, the pupils can think of preparing a
professional number.
Since 1986, France has also possessed the
first professional circus school in the West
organized on Eastern European lines, the
High School (of the National Centre) of
Circus Arts, at Châlons-sur-Marne. Pupils
from France and other countries are re¬
cruited from the age of sixteen on by com¬
petitive examination. The course consists of
two two-year stages. The first is designed to
encourage the expression of individual and
group potential and to guide the pupils
towards a suitable line of specialization.
Specialized work begins in the third year,
and in the fourth year acts are worked out
and polished. A circus performer's diploma
is awarded at the end of the course. The
basic disciplines taught for three years in¬
clude acrobatics, dance and music; the cir¬
cus techniques include trapeze-work and
trick riding; and the general subjects taught
range from anatomy and physiology to
show business management and labour
legislation. There were 370 entrants for the
first examination: twenty-five passed, and
nineteen of these continued into their
second year. The school is directed by Guy
Caron, a Canadian who is a former pupil of
the Budapest School.
Each of North America's few circus
schools flourishes in the shadow of a circus.
In 1983 Guy Caron set up a private circus
school in Canada, which works closely with
the Cirque du Soleil, of which he is also
artistic director. Here, too, in keeping with
modern trends, great importance is
attached to choreography. In the United
States, the giant Ringling Circus has a
"Clown College" where the art of comedy is
taught. American clowns, with their custard
pies and monstrous tooth extractions, are in
a class apart.
New York's Big Apple Circus and its
school, the New York School for Circus
Arts, Inc., are ten years old. The School,
run by Frenchman Dominique Jando,
offers a course for children between the
ages of nine and thirteen, organized jointly
with the Manhattan Harbor School, which
provides two hours a day of circus training
and options for more advanced instruction.
When the Big Apple Circus acquires its new
building, it plans to organize courses for
thirteen- to sixteen-year-olds and to create
a professional training school.
In China, there are no Big Tops. Circuses
are usually stationary and have troupes of
acrobats which are the equivalent of circus
schools. Foremost among these is the
Acrobatic Troupe of China, which was
formed in 1950 as the Zhonghua Troupe,
and has inspired a number of other groups
including the Troupes of Shanghai, Chong¬
qing, Shenyang, Wuhan and the Troupe of
the Guangzhou Soldiers.
China today has some 130 professional
State troupes, with over 11,000 artistes.
Conjuring and voice imitations are two
highly popular specialities. Anyone who
works in show business can join the Asso¬
ciation of Chinese Acrobats, which was
founded in 1981. Its woman president is a
former acrobat, Xia Juhua, who is also a
Deputy to the People's Congress. It is not
surprising that China should produce circus
acts of high calibre, since quality is con¬
nected with the respect accorded to artistry,
and circus artistes in China and the Soviet
Union enjoy high social status.
MONICA J. RENEVEY, of Switzerland, is an
animal trainer turned reporter, writer and publi¬
cist. She is the chiefauthor and editorofa French
encyclopedia on the circus, entitled Le grand
livre du cirque (Bibliothèque des Arts, Geneva,
1977). Among her many publications and articles
on the circus are II circo e il suo mondo (Laterza,
Rome, 1985) and J'aime le cirque (Walt Disney
Productions, Paris, 1986).
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The freedom of the ring
by Annie Fratellini
"If an art is to survive, it needs a school."
Above, a young trapeze artiste trains at the
National Circus School founded in Paris by
Annie Fratellini and Pierre Etaix.
FRATELLINIit's our real name-
means "little brothers" in Italian.
Gustave, born in 1842 in Carrara,
was the first member of the family to join
the circus, just as one might join a religion.
He had four sons: Louis (1868-1909), Paul
(1877-1940), François (1879-1951) and
Albert (1886-1961). When the eldest died,
the remaining three formed a trio that be¬
came famous "the Fratellini Brothers".
My father Victor, son of Paul, was an
acrobat. He taught me acrobatics, the con¬
certina and the saxophone. He gave me a
new musical instrument an accordion, a
vibraphone, a violin, a piano for each
birthday. I learned to play them all. I made
my first appearance in the ring at the Cirque
Medrano in Paris , at the age of twelve. I had
to balance on a rolling blue globe, trundling
it forwards while I played the saxophone.
But by the time I was twenty, I wanted to
forget about the circus. It was a family my
family that I rejected wholesale. I left the
circus and went into jazz, singing, music
hall, drama and films. Why? Mainly be¬
cause it had not lived up to my expectations.
The circus of my childhood wasn't the circus
as my parents had known it.
The memories that I cherished were
those of Grandfather Paul the auguste
with the top hat and the monocle. But I had
to learn all the circus disciplines without
sharing in its magic and mystery. It was
wartime. The circuses were silent. I had to
break free, and for fifteen years I turned my
back on the circus.
What gave me the idea of setting up a
circus school? Originally it must have been
Paul, my grandfather, who gave me this
desire to widen my horizons. He had a
remarkable collection of books, and was
interested in the theatre, music, painting
all the arts. With him I listened to Beeth¬
oven, Wagner, Puccini and Verdi. He
talked to me about life at the Cirque Medra¬
no, where the three Fratellini brothers
worked from 1909 to 1925. In 1920 they
gave the first performance of Jean Coc-
teau's sketch Le buufsur le toit, with music
by Darius Milhaud. Musicians such as
Milhaud, Jean Wiener, Henri Sauguet,
Georges Auric and Erik Satie; writers
Cocteau, Raymond Radiguet, and Colette;
painters, such as Georges Rouault, Fer¬
nand Léger, Pablo Picasso and many
more all used to come to the Cirque Med-
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Berthe Judet, Paris
rano, and would gather in the Fratellinis'
dressing-room after the show.
My life took a new direction in 1968 when
I met Pierre Etaix, a terrific fan of clowns
and of the Fratellinis. He persuaded me to
return to the ring. Fernand Léger used to
say, "A ring means freedom: it has neither
beginning nor end". Pierre Etaix was the
white-faced clown. I was the auguste. Three
years later, we went on our first tour with
the Pinder Circus.
I abandoned everything in order to re¬
turn to my origins. My daughter Valérie
(born in 1960, the child of a previous mar¬
riage to the film-maker Pierre Granier-De-
ferre), who had kept away from the circus,
decided to become a trapeze artiste. Where
could she train? There were no more cir¬
cuses in Paris. Medrano was dead, and the
Cirque d'Hiver was being used for other
types of show.
If an art is to survive, it needs a school.
Where there were schools, the circus was
alive and well. This was an observable fact.
Encouraged by the then Minister of Cul¬
ture, Jacques Duhamel, we first of all
founded the National Circus School Asso¬
ciation in 1971 . Then, in 1974, we were able
to establish the school in a Paris youth
centre.
It was an instant success. I had expected
about twenty young people: 600 turned up.
We had to organize classes. I was deter¬
mined that the teachers should be artistes
themselves, the best in their field, real pro¬
fessionals who also wanted to teach. I
wanted the school to be wide open and
generous in its approach , without any initial
weeding-out of applicants. Selection would
occur naturally. My aim was to instil in all
the young beginners the same high stan¬
dards and the same respect for work well
done.
In 1977, we pitched our circus tent on a
piece of land adjoining the La Villette park
in Paris. Circus arts have to be learned in a
clearly defined space, a particular place.
Since we received very little in the way of
subsidies, we had to fight to prove that the
craft of the circus was necessary. In that
year our school became the first technical
education establishment to award a Profes¬
sional Circus Diploma (circus tent equip¬
ment assembler), and the circus became
officially part of French education in 1985.
The school provides two types of
teaching: artistic and technical. On the
technical side, pupils learn how a tent can¬
vas is put together, how king poles, quarter-
"Make-up isn't a disguise; it helps to bring
out your personality." Above, Annie
Fratellini, one of the few female clowns,
prepares for her renowned auguste act.
poles and all the rest of the equipment are
manufactured. Next they learn to read a
tent plan, lay out a tent and build it up.
They also study joinery, metal work, elec¬
tricity and sound systems. After three years
they take an examination.
In the artistic disciplines, dancing and
acrobatics are compulsory. After three
months, pupils choose from among the fol¬
lowing options: fixed trapeze, flying
trapeze, tightwire, juggling, basic music,
equestrian voltige, clowning and trampo¬
line. Having passed through the school, the
pupils can then take their first steps in pub¬
lic, learn to set up an act, choose a musical
accompaniment and a costume, regulate
their lighting and participate in the prepara¬
tion of the show.
It was for these pupils that we created the
Fratellini Circus, which is attached to the
school. An exhibition on the clowns in my
family travels with it on tour. Thus, at the
end of the road, I offer my pupils my
memories, linking the past with the future.
If an art is to continue, its roots must be well
planted. At the end of this training the
pupils can embark on the artiste's life equip¬
ped with all the qualities of a true profes¬
sional, or they can choose something else.
The intake is international: we have
pupils from other countries besides France.
Annie Fratellini's "auguste shoes", which
once belonged to her grandfather, Paul
(1877-1940), one of the famous trio of
"Fratellini Brothers" who made their name
at the Cirque Medrano in Paris.
A circus whose artistes are all from the same
country is not a real circus; diversity is
essential, in nationality as well as in perfor¬
mance. And during the school holidays we
go on tour with the pupils. Since 1975 our
Big Top has visited 200 towns, we have
toured in England, Belgium, Italy and the
United States, and have welcomed 1.5
million spectators.
At present, 360 young people are attend¬
ing the school; 200 children from the age of
eight upwards come to learn on Wednes¬
days and Saturdays. It takes at least three
years at the Circus School to learn acroba¬
tics, which is the foundation for all other
disciplines. Learning on the job is indispen¬
sable, and those who stay are those who
have what it takes to practise the art of the
circus at a high level. Out of 300 pupils
between the ages of eight and twenty, 5 per
cent succeed.
Thus we have trained a new generation of
artistes who can be seen in a number of
establishments. Circuses with schools, such
as the Big Apple Circus in the United States
and the Cirque du Soleil in Canada, have
grown up in the light of our experience.
For twelve years, our circus has been
battling against difficulties. For the circus is
nothing if not fragile. To those who do not
like it, the effort that it requires may seem
futile. We "build up" put up the circus
tent we work, and we go on our way. And
we say to ourselves, "So much labour for so
little reward". But our reward is the plea¬
sure we give to the audience. We relive the
legend of the "travellers", the strolling play¬
ers of the olden days: we set our own scene
in which to present a world of dreams and
magic. The circus entails, above all, hard
work, and a team; team-work. It is a craft,
and must be exercised with sensitivity. I am
gratified that so many young people are
attracted to it.
The circus is regarded by most people in
show business, whether in the theatre,
dance or the cinema, as a school second to
none. It is, after all, at the heart of all forms
of show business, and this explains its influ¬
ence and its continued existence. I wanted a
school, a ring: "A circus for the future."
ANNIE FRATELLINI, ofFrance, is a member of
a famous circus family. From early training as an
acrobat she has gone on to be a singer, musician,
and actress. She has appeared in films by Louis
Malle, René Clair, Pierre Granier-Deferre,
Federico Fellini and Pierre Etaix. Since 1974 she
has run the National Circus School in Paris,
which she founded with Pierre Etaix.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
MR
The circus on celluloid
£5 -'
-"
The circus has been a fertile source of in¬
spiration for the cinema, from the early
films of Louis Lumière and Georges Méliès,
which featured artistes such as Little Tich
(Harry Ralph, 1868-1928) a forerunner of
the famous figure of the tramp invented by
Charlie Chaplin, to the animated cartoon
films of Walt Disney, notably Dumbo (1941),
and spectacular productions like Cecil B.
dcMille's The Greatest Show on Earth
(1952). From the 1920s on, circus themes
began to attract some of the world's leading
film-makers. (1) A scene from The Circus
(1928) by Charlie Chaplin. (2) The Marx
Brothers' comedy At the Circus (1939). (3)
Der Himmel über Berlin (1987; Wings of
Desire) by Wim Wenders.(4) Cycklarnas
Aftom (1953; Sawdust and Tinsel) by Ingmar
Bergman.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
'As American as apple pie'
by A.H. Saxon The art of the circus spectacular
LIKE its European ancestor, the circus
in the United States began with ex¬
hibitions of trick horsemanship, to
which clowns, acrobats and tightrope per¬
formers were quickly added. Its founder
was the British equestrian John Bill
Ricketts, who had previously performed in
English circuses and who, in the 1790s,
established permanent circus buildings of
his own in Philadelphia and New York City.
Ricketts and his small troupe also toured
cities in the USA and Canada, often erect¬
ing temporary wooden arenas along their
route.
Meanwhile, in a parallel development,
other showmen had begun taking around
the country small collections of exotic anim¬
als brought to these shores by enterprising
ships' captains. There were no public zoos
in the United States at this time. Conse¬
quently, it was through such exhibitions
that most Americans had their first view of
lions, camels, elephants and other non-
native animals. The menagerie owners,
whose "caravans" quickly grew to impress¬
ive sizes, established permanent buildings
in such cities as New York, where they
exhibited their animals during the winter
months. When the weather was warm, they
continued to tour, and they soon hit upon
the idea of exhibiting under canvas tents,
thereby eliminating the need to erect
boarded enclosures or lease existing build¬
ings wherever they went. Beginning in the
1820s, this innovation was adopted by
American circuses.
'Big Tops' that could scat 10,000
With these portable tents that could easi¬
ly bè erected or taken down in a few hours,
they were free to roam wherever they liked,
even to the smallest towns in the hinter¬
lands, where they often gave single perfor¬
mances, then moved on in time to exhibit in
the next town on the following day. From
the introduction of the tent dates the true
beginning of the American touring circus,
which later in the nineteenth century ex¬
panded into "tented cities" of astounding
dimensions consisting of "big tops" cap¬
able of seating 10,000 or more spectators;
separate tents for menageries, sideshows
and other attractions; dressing tents and
Roll up! Roll up! Before the show, a young
performer encourages the public to come
and see the "crocodile-woman". Lagny
(France), 1959.
dining-room or "cook tents" for artistes and
employees; not to mention additional tents
for stabling the hundreds of draft horses
that pulled the circus wagons, for black¬
smiths and veterinary surgeons, and for va¬
rious other purposes.
By the mid-nineteenth century, too, a
number of circuses had linked up with
menageries, whose animals were no longer
simply exhibited in cages, but were now
featured in the increasingly elaborate street
parade that advertised the arrival of the
circus in a town, in processions and races
(between camels, elephants, and even
ostriches ridden by monkeys) inside the
circus tent itself, and in separate numbers of
their own. Among these last was the sensa¬
tional act by the celebrated American lion
trainer Isaac Van Amburgh, who first en¬
tered a cage with his "big cats" in the 1830s
and shortly thereafter, as the first American
circus performer to gain an international
reputation, appeared with them in various
European cities.
There is no such thing as "pure" circus,
and since the early days of Philip Astley in
London and Antonio Franconi in Paris, the
circus has traditionally been a mixture of
diverse entertainments: of tumbling and
rope walking which date from Antiquity, of
trick horsemanship performed in open
fields by eighteenth-century riding masters,
of clowns whose roots are traceable at least
to the Commedia dell'Arte, of pantomimes
and even theatrical spectacles, in which '
animals often took part, performed on huge
scenic stages in permanent circus buildings
and theatres.
'The Greatest Show on Earth'
In the United States, another accretion
occurred in the late nineteenth century,
drawn from the hippodromes of Henri Nar¬
cisse Franconi and Phineas T. Barnum in
New York City (built in 1853 and 1874,
respectively). These establishments were
huge arenas sometimes open to the air,
sometimes roofed with canvas or glass
that had been popular for some years in
Europe and were a conscious attempt to
recreate the ancient Roman "circus" and its
"games". This was not the circus as we
know it today, but rather the great oval
course over which races, à la Ben Hur, were
run. In the United States, such arenas fea¬
tured races between Roman chariots, be¬
tween male and female jockeys on indi¬
vidual horses, representations of stag hunts
with real stags and full packs of hounds in
pursuit, besides steeplechases, foot races
and related attractions. The oval hippo¬
drome track and the kinds of entertainment
peculiar to it were also adopted by the
American circus but not before another
important development had taken place.
.As in Europe, American circuses were
originally one-ring affairs, an arrangement
that remained the norm until the 1870s. At
the beginning of that decade the great
showman P.T. Barnum, then in his sixties,
entered the field and, within a few brief
years, created what he proudly termed
"The Greatest Show on Earth". The size of
his main tent or Big Top was so large that
many spectators had difficulty seeing, stood
up in their seats and crowded to the ring¬
side, and consequently interfered with the
view of others. At the beginning of his
second season in 1872, therefore, Barnum
and his partner William C. Coup decided to
add a second ring, in which acts were per¬
formed simultaneously with those in the
first in effect making their enterprise into
a "double circus". At the same time they
added to their establishment an oval hip¬
podrome track, encompassing the two rings
and running around the arena immediately
in front of the spectators' seats; and races,
spectacular processions and triumphal
drives in a carriage by the famous showman
himself became standard features on this
vast expanse. The arrangement proved so
popular that nearly every circus in the coun¬
try soon added a second ring.
The three-ring circus
To go one better than these competitors
and further increase the size of their tent, in
1881 Barnum and his new partner James A.
Bailey added a third ring, thereby complet¬
ing the evolution of what is perhaps the
most distinctive characteristic of the Amer¬
ican circus: the "three-ring" format. In fact,
even this term gives but a faint idea of the
multiplicity of entertainment such a show
presents, since besides the three rings and
hippodrome track, Barnum added two
large platforms or "stages" between the
rings for acts requiring a firm surface, such
as trick cycling or roller-skating, while
above the arena high-wire artistes and as
many as three trapeze troupes might per¬
form at the same time! When Barnum took
his huge show to London during the winter
of 1889-1890, British spectators, still accus¬
tomed to the traditional one-ring circus,
hardly knew what to make of it. It was
bewildering, overwhelming, apt to give
spectators "fits of indigestion", critics
wrote. Yet nearly all agreed it was a mag¬
nificent spectacle.
Since the days of Barnum, at least, "spec¬
tacle" has remained another distinctive fea¬
ture of American circuses. On the great
hippodrome track itself, elaborate proces¬
sions, featuring horses, elephants and all
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
the human artistes, are given to this day;
while traditionally, at another point in the
programme, all of these forces, gorgeously
costumed, participate in a mammoth panto¬
mime or "spec", as it is termed, whose
theme may be based on some nursery tale or
historic event, and whose action occupies
all three rings in addition to the track.
In Barnum's day there was sometimes
even a raised stage over 100 metres
wide at one side of the arena, on which
grandiose pantomimes like Nero, or The
Destruction of Rome were performed. This
particular production, which was given in
1889 and 1890, employed a cast of over
1,000 actors and dancers, a full orchestra
and choir of 100 voices, and nearly all the
animals belonging to the establishment, be¬
sides scenery depicting the interior of
Sir Edwin Landseer painted the portrait,
above, of the American lion tamer Isaac A.
Van Amburgh (1801-1865) with his big cats
while they were performing in the United
Kingdom in the late 1830s. Note the compa¬
ratively small, rectangular cagel The cir¬
cular "big cage" used by circuses today only
began to appear at the end of the 19th
century.
An early poster for the Ringling Brothers
Circus, one of the great itinerant American
circuses of the early 20th century. The cir¬
cus, under the name of Ringling Bros, and
Barnum & Bailey, is still performing today.
Below, Barnum & Bailey Circus poster
(1887) for an act by a dwarf elephant, "Tom
Thumb", named after one of Barnum &
Bailey's most famous attractions, the midget
"General Tom Thumb" (real name Charles
Sherwood Stratton). Phineas T. Barnum
(1810-1891) and his partner James A. Bailey
(1847-1906) are depicted at left.
»«
V
WORLD'S
GREATEST
&HOW&
Tm
Invincible
monar.cn
or Tm amusement World.
AMERICAS
LARGEST. (jRMIDEbT. MOM PROW.«
AMUSEMENT INSTITUTION.
CE <ft
= c
3.<3
II"
ma
D
II
< r
©a
o x>
CLCÛ
'-OsiGirUtfAMousiOniy Diminutive.Dwarf Clown Elephant'Tom Thumb''
J&Eä TOSAVE WHOM J U M BO SO NOBLY SACRIFICED HIS OWN LIFEi^S*»* ^SSSäwt
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Nero's palace, the Circus Maximus, and
Rome itself, which spectacularly "burned"
at the end, of course, amidst a glorious
apotheosis celebrating the DAWN OF
CHRISTIANITY!
Bigness sheer size for the sake of size
has traditionally been another goal of
American circuses, the expressions "one-
horse show" and "one-elephant circus"
generally being terms of derision. In Bar-
num's day again, which is sometimes refer¬
red to as the "golden age" of the American
circus, as many as forty trained elephants
might participate in the programme, while
the menagerie tent itself often rivalled or
actually outshone the finest zoos in the
country. "Freaks" human prodigies like
the celebrated midget Tom Thumb (dis¬
covered by Barnum) and Chang and Eng,
the famous Siamese Twins abounded in
the sideshow or "museum" department,
which also displayed a profusion of auto¬
mata, illusions and curious inventions.
Three special trains for a single show
To Americans, especially those living in
rural areas, the day the circus came to town
was a major event. For here, crammed into
the space of a few brief hours, was enter¬
tainment enough to last a year, beginning
with a spectacular street parade that fea¬
tured blaring bands and beautifully carved
"tableau" wagons; gorgeously costumed
riders atop richly caparisoned mounts; up to
forty horses pulling a single, colossal band
wagon; elephants ambling along with pic
turesque howdahs on their backs; while
other animals lions and tigers, monkeys,
giraffes, even serpents behind plate-glass
windows were drawn along in their own
special wagons; and at the very end (in case
of explosion!) another American invention,
the steam organ or calliope, whose raucous,
ear-splitting notes could be heard
kilometres away.
To transport these immense shows to all
the cities throughout the United States and
Canada, Barnum and his contemporaries
soon abandoned horse-drawn wagons, fit¬
ted out their own special railway trains, and
devised new methods for quickly loading
and unloading them. Indeed, so marvel¬
lously efficient did this operation become
that it was not unusual for a circus like
Barnum's to unload early in the morning,
Above, a restored "Elephant Wagon" be¬
longing to the AI G. Barnes Circus parked
on a lot at Milwaukee, Wisconsin, USA.
Top, a once-familiar scene reconstituted in
1985: the circus train arrives in an American
town.
Balancing and juggling act performed by the
young American artiste Anthony Gatto
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
set up its tents and give its street parade and
as many as three complete performances,
reload in late evening and travel overnight
hundreds of kilometres to another town, to
begin all over again the following day.
The circus artistes and labourers (whose
one day off was Sunday) slept aboard the
trains, and the logistics and careful advance
planning required by such an unrelenting
schedule may easily be imagined. No less
than three separate trains were needed to
carry all the employees, animals, tents and
paraphernalia belonging to Barnum's
establishment. Garishly decorated "adver¬
tising cars", attached to regular trains and
carrying press agents, billposters and so on,
preceded the show by several weeks in
order to publicize its coming. Other special
agents also travelled in advance to arrange
for the rental of the circus lot, the delivery
of food and fodder for the circus employees
and animals, and anything else that might
be required. When Barnum's partner and
successor James A. Bailey toured the
United Kingdom and continental Europe at
the end of the nineteenth century, again
using special trains modified to the speci¬
fications of the circus, military officers from
all the countries through which the show
passed were sent to observe these precise
operations and were later said to have put
what they learned to good use during the
First World War.
A college for clowns
In the present century the American cir¬
cus, while retaining many of these tradi¬
tions, has continued to be influenced by
contemporary developments. With the one
notable exception of Ringling Bros, and
Barnum & Bailey the lineal descendant of
Barnum's show nearly all circuses now
move by motor transport. The circus parade
has been entirely abandoned, although
many of its handsome chariots and ornately
carved wagons have been lovingly restored
and may still be admired at the Circus
World Museum in Baraboo, Wisconsin.
The Big Top and three-ring format continue
to flourish; but here again the Ringling
show, the largest in the country, proves to
be an exception. At the end of its 1956
season this renowned circus gave up playing
under canvas and ever since has performed
in the modern, enclosed sports arenas that
are now found in virtually every North
American city. Besides saving considerably
on expenses, this arrangement permits the
circus to exhibit for up to eleven months
each year (in fact there are two Ringling
shows, the "Red" and the "Blue" units),
while spectators are more comfortably
accommodated than they formerly were.
Of the dozens of other circuses that criss¬
cross North America each season, un
doubtedly the most interesting and elegant
is the Big Apple Circus, a show that exhibits
in a single ring, employs a tent that seats
only around 1,600 people, and deliberately
attempts to emulate "European" tradi¬
tions. With its headquarters in New York
City, supported by subventions from both
the municipal and State governments, this
non-profit organization also runs a school
for training future circus artistes. For the
past few years, at its winter quarters in
Florida, the Ringling show has also run a
special "college" for clowns.
Unlike the situation found in several
European countries, circuses in the United
States the reputable circuses that give
their patrons a fair return for their money,
that is are generally in sound financial
condition. For despite the advent of the
movies, television, and a host of competing
entertainments in the twentieth century,
the circus, to use a popular expression,
remains "as American as apple pie".
A.H. SAXON, of the United States, is the author
ofover a hundred books, articles and reviews on
the theatre, circus and popular entertainment.
Among his publications, which have been trans¬
lated into several languages, is The Life and Art
of Andrew Ducrow and the Romantic Age of the
English Circus. He is currently working on P.T.
Barnum: The Legend and the Man, a biography
of the famous showman.
The rubber man by Alfred Mikhaïl
THE Egyptian acrobat and contortion¬
ist Sabir Hamid Rammah is one of
the stars of his country's National
Circus. His virtuosity has earned him an
international reputation. He is known as
the "rubber man" because his movements
are so graceful, supple and precise that his
body seems boneless.
He does not belong to one of the old
circus families, some of which were already
travelling from town to town and village to
village in the Arab countries before the
seventeenth century. Accompanied by their
menageries, they put on shows foi mawalid
festivals (anniversaries of the birth of the
Prophet or of a Muslim holy man).
Rammah comes from a bedouin family
which settled at Giza. Most of the family
were tailors. From early childhood he was
noted for his agility and dexterity. At the
age of thirteen, he left his family to work as
an acrobat in Alexandria, a cosmopolitan
city which welcomed visiting foreign perfor¬
mers. A meeting with one of them, a Ger¬
man acrobat, led Rammah to polish his own
act. Then, in 1950, he accompanied a trio of
German acrobatic dancers when they went
home.
On returning to Egypt two years later,
Rammah had developed a new style in
The Egyptian contortionist Sabir Hamid
Rammah
which he filled out his act with clowning. He
worked in casinos and in schools which
organized festivals and other spectacles, as
well as in various private circuses.
In 1964 the Egyptian National Circus
gave its first performances, which were
34
highly popular. "A competitive spirit drove
us all to excel," Rammah explains, "and we
did our utmost to surpass ourselves. In our
troupe we had first-rate performers such as
the trapeze artiste Dakhli Amin. He would
leap from the flying trapeze with a sack over
his head, perform three backward somer¬
saults and catch his partner's hands in mid¬
air. Other notable acts were that of the
juggler, Farouk Rachid , and the Ben Abbas
tightrope walkers."
Thanks to a policy of exchange visits with
circuses in other countries, Rammah has
worked with a number of circuses. In 1974
he won a international acrobatics competi¬
tion in Tokyo.
Today Rammah works with the Egyptian
National Circus in one of their permanent
Big Tops, at Giza, on the banks of the Nile.
Among the show's many attractions apart
from acrobatics, are trained animals (as
many as fourteen big cats at a time), trapeze
artists and jugglers.
Rammah's passion for his art is so strong
that he would like to die in the ring in the
middle of his act. Thus he would have given
his entire life to the circus, to his very last
breath.
ALFRED MIKHAIL, of Egypt, heads the
documentary films section of the Egyptian televi¬
sion service. His own work for television includes
films on the Suez Canal (1975), shadow plays
(1983), and Verdi's opera Aida (1987).
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
A topsy turvy world by Manuel Pereira
"Might not the word 'circus' come from
Circe, the sorceress in Homer's OdysseyV
Above, "Circe changing Odysseus' com¬
rades into swine", by the Amsterdam-born
engraver and print-dealer Jaspar de Isaac
(died Paris, 1654).
w
rHAT is the etymological origin of
the word circus? Common sense
suggests that it comes from "cir¬
cular", an allusion to the traditional shape
of the circus ring from the Roman Coliseum
to the Big Top of today. I would suggest
another explanation. Might not the word
circus come from Circe, the sorceress in
Homer's Odyssey who changed Odysseus'
comrades into swine? The Latin word cir¬
censes, describing the circus games, makes
this hypothesis even more tempting, for
what were the sorceress's tricks but circus
acts before their time?
More prosaically, Pliny tells us that when
the Romans first caught a giraffe in Africa
they thought it was a cross between a camel
and a leopard because it had a spotted coat.
They supposed it to be an animal capable of
fighting the gladiators in the arena, and
there the harmless creature was killed,
amid applause.
The stories of Circe and of the giraffe
have one point in common zoological
confusion. Men are turned into pigs, gir¬
affes are thought to be wild beasts. In both
cases the natural order of things is inversed
to produce an exciting spectacle. This de¬
sire to turn things upside down is the ess¬
ence of the circus. What is an acrobat but a
man who imitates a bird? What is a clown
but an unreal being whose absurdity can
make us laugh or cry? The behaviour of a
tamed lion is as human as that of the
gladiators in Vespasian's day was bestial.
The bearded lady, the spider woman, the
35
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Fools and jesters were often depicted by
15th- and 16th-century European artists.
Above, detail of a jester and his bauble
drawn by the German artist Hans Holbein
the Younger in the margin of a 1515 copy of
In Praise of Folly, by the Dutch Humanist
Erasmus.
frog man, Siamese twins, the sword-swal-
lower all the biological freaks, whether
real or fake, that occur in the history of the
circus can be traced back to Homer's Circe
and Pliny's giraffe.
The circus is the world back to front.
. Whatever is unusual, eccentric or disturb¬
ing, whatever is, so to speak, a challenge to
us, has always found an ideal refuge there.
Moreover, this is not a purely European
phenomenon; circuses are found all over
the world. The museum of freaks that the
Spanish conquistador Hernán Cortés disco¬
vered in Tenochtitlán was Moctezuma's pri¬
vate circus; and Marco Polo tells us with
amazement how in another part of the
world the Great Khan had a huge lion
trained to kneel at the foot of the throne
when there was a festival at the palace.
In every court, in every land, from China
to Spain and from the time of the Mongol
emperor Kubla Khan to that of the Spanish
king Alfonso X (The Wise), there have
always been astrologers and necromancers,
clowns and acrobats, performing animals,
jugglers and minstrels. Every court has
been a kind of circus ; one need only think of
the extraordinary garments people wore at
masked balls, the attire of the lansquenets
(German mercenaries) or the Burgundians
with their huge puff sleeves and cockscomb
hats. The historians Johan Huizinga and
Jules Michelet both give detailed descrip¬
tions of fashionable gatherings where the
guests could watch puppets fly through the
air and devices that made a sound like roll¬
ing thunder, dwarfs riding bears and huge
Moors riding elephants, the statue of a
woman with wine flowing from her breasts
and that of a boy urinating rose-water, and a
pie containing twenty-eight musicians.
Leonardo da Vinci constructed a mechan¬
ical lion to amuse the guests at a banquet
at the château of Clos-Lucé, where he was
lodged by François I.
Tragedy and comedy are often mingled in
the circus. The death of Aeschylus, for in¬
stance, is a circus turn in itself. An eagle
caught a tortoise and flew up into the sky,
then dropped it to break its shell, where¬
upon it fell on the sleeping poet's head. A
comic accident, even though it cost the life
of the great Greek tragedian. The tortoise
transformed into a projectile might have
been one of Circe's tricks, but it is also like
an Eleatic aphorism or a Chaplinesque gag.
The blood-stained bullring is the only
survival of the Roman circus, for bullfight¬
ing is basically a circus game which goes
back to the mythical Minotaur of Crete.
The bullfighter is to the gladiator what the
bull is to the lion. That is why there are so
many bulls, tumblers and harlequins in
Picasso's paintings; they are all part of the
same obsession. And the bullfighter's cos-
"Bullfighting is basically a circus game
which goes back to the mythical Minotaur of
Crete ... That is why there are so many bulls,
tumblers and harlequins in Picasso's paint¬
ings; they are all part of the same obses¬
sion." Below, The Picador, a wash drawing
by Picasso.
©
36
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
-*
Grimacing masks by the Belgian artist
James Ensor (1860-1949), in an oil painting
entitled Intrigues.
tume is reminiscent of the clown's get-up
and his flour-white face.
Fortunately, the only reminders of the
bonfires that blazed at the time of the In¬
quisition are the straight]' acket and the cowl
worn by the condemned. And there is a
curious resemblance between these gar¬
ments and the attire of the figures of Pul-
chinello painted two centuries later by
Giandomenico Tiepolo. The conical cap is
the same as the dunce's cap once worn by
restless and rebellious children. Even today
clowns often enter the ring wearing this
unjustly derided headgear. Just as the
alchemist's cap became the Phrygian bon¬
net of the French Republic, so the conical
cap of the heretic became the cap of the
clown. Once more tragedy is inextricably
linked with comedy.
But in any case the grotesque is always a
-dominant feature of the circus, whose entire
imagery is contained in grimacing cathedral
gargoyles and in twelfth-century illumin¬
ated bestiaries, perpetuated in the works of
Gaudi and Borges respectively. The circus
is Gothic, Romantic, Baroque and sur¬
realist. It is certainly not classical, for its
spirit is too mischievous for serenity. It is
predominantly Faustian to the extent that it
seems to have become a favourite theme of
German literature.
Nietzsche, in Thus Spake Zarathustra,
chose the acrobat walking the tightrope as a
symbol of domination. The superman is a
tightrope walker: "He is a lightning flash;
he is a madman", as Nietzsche puts it. This
is a variation of the exploit of Icarus, or of
Goethe's Faust the flight to the imposs¬
ible. The theme recurs in Rilke; the fifth of
his Duino Elegies is a tribute to trapeze
artistes who catch each other in mid-air.
This circus tradition in German literature
can be traced from Thomas Mann's Mario
and the Magician to Günther Grass's Tin
Drum, and includes Heinrich Boll's The
Clown.
In the Middle Ages, the very idea of the
circus seemed destined to disappear. Para¬
doxically, however, the Angel of the Ex¬
traordinary survived extermination. The
liturgical drama of the Church and the secu¬
lar ritual of the courts were, ultimately, a
kind of circus. And between these two cere¬
monies was the irrepressible street festival,
the carnival, that was to be seen every¬
where. There was much circus in trie
medieval carnival, as can be seen in Pieter
Brueghel the Elder's Fight Between Carni¬
val and Lent. Hiëronymus Bosch and
Albrecht Dürer also painted pictures of car¬
nivals and circuses inspired by the fifteenth-
century humanist Sebastian Brant's allegor¬
ical poem The Ship of Fools. And these
same fools, with their caps and bells and
their asses' ears, waving their baubles and
banners, are figures from the medieval
French satirical plays known as Sotties, half¬
way between buffoons and clowns. Eras¬
mus was probably thinking of them when he
wrote In Praise ofFolly. Bosch takes up the
same theme in The Conjurer who plies his
trade at a fair, and in The Cure of Folly,
which depicts a surgeon wearing a funnel
for a hat, and a nun with a book on her
head. Pure circus.
In the seventeenth century the Flemish
painter David Teniers the Younger often
painted pictures of festivals in which the
villagers chose a mock king, with a card¬
board crown; this was a satire on authority.
From then on the country fête became a
common theme in painting, from Rubens'
Kermesses, to Watteau's fêtes galantes,
which contain echoes of pantomime,
Goya's Burial of the Sardine, in which the
painter mocks obscurantism, and James
Ensor's brightly coloured masks.
In a period when laughter was suspect
and weeping was thought to be in good
taste, the god of laughter lurked in disguise
on religious feast-days such as Christmas
and Epiphany, turning up in medieval mir¬
acle and mystery plays, in festivals and
when folly was tolerated, at the carnival,
which later crossed the ocean to America, ,
where the Day of the Kings was celebrated.
The drum-playing and the Yoruba dances
which the Negro slaves took to the New
World were other manifestations of the
spirit of the circus, which is the impulse
towards the Dionysian paganism that Savo¬
narola attacked at the height of the Renaiss¬
ance with his "burning of the vanities".
Tournaments also had something of the
circus in them. Equestrian pageants which
might be described as a sport with erotic
overtones, they were the last survivals of
the horse-races and gladiatorial combats of
37
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Antiquity. The spirit of the circus can also
be glimpsed in medieval miniatures, in the
fairy-like damsels with their hoods and wide
veils, who wander among round tents
adorned with coloured pennants, forerun¬
ners of the Big Top. Perhaps the best-
known example of this spirit is to be found
in the famous unicorn tapestries in the
Cluny Museum, in Paris, one of which de¬
picts a lady, surrounded by birds, rabbits,
monkeys, dogs and lions, coming out of a
multicoloured tent. She is wearing a feath¬
ered turban which makes her look like a
sultan's wife, or a snake-charmer worthy of
The Thousand and One Nights.
The Cluny tapestries, like flying carpets,
transport us to the imaginary circuses, float¬
ing animals and fantastic Gypsy caravans of
Marc Chagall's paintings. It would be in¬
teresting to study the development of the
tent from the studded medieval pavilion of
the Battle of Roncevalles to the Big Top in
Ingmar Bergman's film Sawdust and Tinsel.
I suspect that Gypsies played a substantial
part in if. Even today, in the streets of
Madrid, the Gypsies shake their tam¬
bourines around a bear dancing on a barrel,
and fortune-tellers read the hands of
passers-by in the Paris Flea Market. Any
Gypsy has the circus in his blood because he
is an outsider and because both his clothing
and his way of life are exaggerated, out of
the ordinary.
Exaggeration is the key word. Arcimbol-
do, with his heads made up of plants, Rabe¬
lais with his erotic humour, his eschatolo-
gical jubilation and his insatiable greed,
Brueghel and Bosch with their diabolical
fantasms all these were faithful to the spir¬
it of the circus in the best possible way,
unconsciously. And isn't it appropriate that
a misshapen dwarf, Henri de Toulouse-
Lautrec, should have produced a series of
circus paintings? His self-portrait is a true
caricature of a clown, with its exaggerated
mouth, pathetic spectacles, squashed bow¬
ler hat, and nose like an aubergine from an
Arcimboldo head. Everything in the work
of Toulouse-Lautrec, the aristocrat who
lived with outsiders, recalls the circus,
whose secret mysteries are revealed only to
artists and children.
The circus has obvious links with the
cinema, and vice versa. As early as the
eighteenth century, the magic lantern was
an attraction at French fairs. In its early
days, the cinema drew inspiration mainly
from the scenic and dramatic wealth of the
circus, the cabaret and the music-hall. The
ambiguity of the circus may be its weakness
or its strength: neither an art nor a sport,
neither Athens nor Sparta, for ever vacillat¬
ing in the no-man's-land between aesthetic
fervour and muscular skill.
In the declining days of their empire, the
Romans asked their emperors for "bread
and circuses". Today, civilized societies set¬
tle for "bread and cinemas" or, worse still,
for "bread and television". The fantasms of
the circus live on in video-clips and even in
advertisements. They startle us in the
streets with punk hair-styles and clothes, or
when rock concerts resound through a
space several times the size of the Coliseum ,
amid coloured lights, clouds of smoke and
shrieks. Not only are the singers disguised
as clowns, marquises or Martians some
call themselves "Prince" or "Queen", a re¬
minder that the clown Coquinet, the jester
of Burgundy, was once appointed minister
by his prince. Long before that, Caligula
had proclaimed his horse a consul. History
is full of tightrope walkers.
There are craters in the moon which,
from afar, look like open-air circus rings.
Perhaps, one day in the not too distant
future, an intergalactic troupe will appear in
one of them. Perhaps indescribable won¬
ders will then be seen, as in the films of
Steven Spielberg, who is in many ways close
to the circus. Holography and laser beams,
computer science, optical fibres and quan¬
tum mechanics will perhaps make it possi¬
ble to change Pliny's giraffe into Aeschy-
lus's tortoise. Perhaps such a fantastic trick
will give free rein to the concentrated
liberty of the circus.
MANUEL PEREIRA is a Cuban novelist and
journalist whose novels El comandante veneno
and El ruso have been translated into several
languages. His reports on Nicaragua have been
published under the title Cró-Nicas. He is cur¬
rently a member of Cuba's Permanent Delega¬
tion to Unesco.
Bookshelf
Circus and Allied Arts. A World Biblio¬
graphy (4 vols), by Raymond Toole Stott,
1958-1971.
A Seat at the Circus, by Anthony Hippisley
Coxe, Evans Brothers, London, 1951,
Archon Books, Hamden, Conn., USA,
1980.
The Life and Art of Andrew Ducrow & The
Romantic Age of the English Circus, by
A.H. Saxon, Shoestring Publishers, Ham¬
den, Conn., USA, 1978.
Pictorial History of the American Circus, by
John and Alice Durant, A. S. Barnes and
Company, New York, 1957.
The History of the Circus, by Nicolas Bent-
ley, Michael Joseph, London, 1977.
Circus!, by Alan Wykes, Jupiter Books,
London, 1977.
A History of the Circus, by George
Speaight, Tantivy Press, London, A.S.
Barnes & Co., San Diego, 1980.
La merveilleuse histoire du cirque, by
Henry Thétard, 1947, reissued with chapter
by L.-R. Dauven, Julliard, Paris, 1978.
L'acrobatie et les acrobates, by Georges
Strehly, Charles Delagrave, Paris, 1900,
reissued by Mme. S. Zlatin, Paris, 1977.
Le grand livre du cirque, edited by Monica
J. Renevey, Bibliothèque des Arts,
Geneva, 1977.
The Courier nmf
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy , 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S.A.; (3) N.CR. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc. , 11 1 West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691 .U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief:
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: RoyMalkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
Neda el Khazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian:
Arabic: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringclstein
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat, George Ducret
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
A II correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Mcrkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul Manaf Saad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebcsibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: DaoTung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Scham (Kabul)
38
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) - Depot légal : C1 - Janvier 1 988
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
i
K
"What do you say to the public at the end of the show?" The Cirque Medrano, Paris, 1954
"What d'you say to the public, my dear Mimile? You say goodbye, of course."
"Wrong, Boulicot. You never say goodbye to the public,
you say here's to the next time!"
Dialogue between two French clowns, Emile Recordier (1890-1946) and Alphonse Boullicot (1878-1957), known as "Boulicot"
Histoire illustrée des cirques parisiens d'hier et d'aujourdhui, Paul Adrian Publications, Paris, 1957 (out of print)
Where to renew your subscription
ALBANIA. 'Ndermarrja e perpjes se librif. Tirana. ARGENTINA. Librería et
Correo de la Unesco - EDILYR. SRL, Tucumán 1685, 1050 Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Books only:: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33,
Brookvale 2100, NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O.
Box 33. Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agents: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street, Melbourne 3000.Hunt.er
Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collingwood, Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional, Arab Regional Office, P.O. Box 726, Bahrain; The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co., AI Mutanabi St.. PO Box 156, Manama. BANGLADESH
Kanm International. GPO Box No; 2141. 64/I Mampuri Para. Tejgaon.
Farmgate. Dhaka. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64. Bridgetown. BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy, 202
Ave. du Roi. 1 060 Brussels. BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundaçâo Getúlio Vargas. Serviço del Publicaçoes,
caixa postal 9.042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 18B, Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000;
Books only: Imagem Latinoamericana, Av. Paulista 750, 1 andar, caixa postal
30455, Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus, Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6, Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9), 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing Co. Ltd., 1294
Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K1 B 3W8. (Stores: 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa.
21 1 Yonge St.. Toronto. Sales office: 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305, St.
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre, PO Box
123, Limbe. Commission Nationale, BP 1600, Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S.A., Departamento de Importaciones, M. Luisa Santander
0447. casilla 10220. Santiago; Editorial 'Andrés Bello", Av; R. Lyon 946,
Casillo 4256, Santiago de Chile; Dipublic, Antonio Varas 671 , 2o piso, casilla
14364, Correo 21 . Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Export Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura). Carrera 3A. n° 18 / 24, Bogota; Books only: Librería
Buchholz Galería, Calle 59. No; 13-1 3. Bogota. CYPRUS. 'MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avene, PO Box 1 722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L..
Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Publishers.
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava; PNS-UED. Jindnsska 14, praha 1;
Slovart, Gottwaldovo Nam 6, 805 32 Bratislava. DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 1 4th
October Corporation, PO Box 4227, Aden. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG. Tidsskriftservice, 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco, Avenida Bolivar. No; 402, esq
Hermanos Deligne, Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre, No. 1 Talaat Harb St., Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco, PO Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. P. O. Box 128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen
Kirjakauppa Oy. Koivuvaarankuja 2 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. Periodicals only: Unesco CPD /
V-1 . rue Miollis. 7501 5 Paris. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port, Postfach 140, Leninstrasse 16, 7010, Leipzig. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier; Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb. Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3; UNO-Verlag, Simrockstrasse 23,
D-5300 Bonn 1; S. Karger GmbH, Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9. Postfach 2
D-8034 Germenng / München. For scientific maps only: Geo Cerwer, Postfach
800830. 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Books only: Presbyterian Bookshop
Depot Ltd., PO Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd.. PO 7869, Accra;
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon. PO Box 1 . Legon. Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises, P.O. Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA. International Bookstore, 4 Nikis
Street, Athens; John Mihalopoulos & Son SA, International Booksellers. P.O.
Box 10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco, 3
Akadimias Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-15 Lock
Road, Kowloon; Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., Tokwawan, Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section, Hong Kong;
Periodicals only: Beaconsfield House 6th floor. Queen's Road Central, Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT, P.O.B. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62.
ICELAND. SnaebjÖrn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg. Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038;
17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a. Anna Salai. Mount Road, Madras 2;
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd.,
Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-agents:
Oxford Book and Stationery Co.. 17 Park St., Calcutta 7001 6; Scindia House,
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers. 29,
Jl , Oto Iskandardinata 111, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37.
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1188 Englab
Ave.. Rostam Give Building, P.O. Box 11365-4498. Teheran 13158.
IRELAND.Periodica/s on//: The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., PO Box
43A, Walkmstown, Dublin 1 2; Books only: TDC Publishers, 1 1 North Frederick
Street, Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions, Inc., c/o Steimatzky Ltd.,
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv; A.B.C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd..
Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni, S.p.A ), Via
Lamarmora 45, Casella Postale 552, 501 21 Florence; via Bartolini 29, 201 55
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalla, 001 00 Rome. JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona. Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc., 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency. PO Box 375. Amman. Penodtcals only: Jordan
Book Centre Co. Ltd., PO Box 301 , AI Jubeiha, Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House, PO 30571. Nairobi; Africa Book Services Ltd. Quran
House. Mangano Street, PO Box 45245. Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co.. Ltd, POB 2942, Kuwait; Periodicals only: Farafalla Press
Agency. P.O. Box SAFA 4541 . Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A. Naufal
et Frères, BP 656. Beirut. LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, PO Mazenod.
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets, PO Box
590, Monrovia: Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.. PO Box 286, Monrovia.-
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg; Periodical: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 1022, Luxembourg. MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office. PO Box 30044, Chichiri. Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop. Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1. MALTA. Sapienzas. 26 Republic St., Valletta. MAURITANIA GRA.LI.-
CO.MA., 1 rue du Souk X, Avenue kennedy. Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco, Actapán 66, Colonia del Valle, Apartado postal 61 164,
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins. Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. übraine 'Aux belles images', 282 ave. Mohammed-V.
Rabat; Librairie des écoles, 1 2 ave, Hassan-ll, Casaglanca; Société cherifien-
ne de distribution et de presse, SOCHEPRESS, angle rues de Dînant et St.
Saëns, BP 13683, Casablanca 05. MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
e do Disco (INLD). avenida 24 de Julho. 1 921 r / d 1 ° andar, Maputo. NEPAL
Sajha Prakashart Polchowk. Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing. Boeken B.V., Hogehilweg 13, Postbus 1118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals: Faxon Europe. P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V., PO Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao. NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbimie, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of Nsukka;
The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zaria. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen. Universitetssentret. Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo
3; Periodicals only: Narvesen A/S, Litteraturt Jenesten, P.O.B. 61 25 Etterstad,
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency. 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam.
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre. Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and the Pacific. 39 Delhi Housing Society. P.O. Box
8950, Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional. Apartado
7571. Zona 5. Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc.. 701 Rizal
Avenue. Manila. POLAND. Orpan-lmport, Palac Kultury I Nauki, Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export-Import, Plata Scienteii, no. 1, PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan. Olaya Main Street. Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building. Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd., Kingsgate
House, PO Box 131. Mahé: National Bookshop, PO Box 48, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College, Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN ARAB JAMAHIR¬
IYA. General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and Advertising, Souf
Al Mahmoudi St., PO Box 959, Tnpoli. SOMALIA. Modern Book Shop and
General. PO Box ùàô, Mogadiscio. SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa Libros SA, aparta¬
do 1 223, Castelló 37, Madrid 1 ; Ediciones Liber, apartado 1 7. Magdalena 8.
Ondárroa (Vizcaya); Donaire. Ronda de Outeiro. 20, apartado de correos 341 .
La Corurla; books only: Librería Casteils, Ronda Universidad 1 3 y 1 5, Barcelo¬
na 7; Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya, Palan Moja, Rambla de los
Estudios 1 1 8, 03 002 Barcelona. SRI LANKA. Lake House Bookshop, 1 00 Sir
Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo 2. SUDAN. AI Bashir
Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SURINAME. Suriname National Com¬
mission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943, Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A / BC.E. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel. Regenngsgatan 12, Box 16356, S-103 27 Stockholm
1 6; For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN Förbundet, Skolgrand 2. Box 1 50 50
S-104, 65 Stockholm; For periodicals only: Wennergren-Williams AB. Nof-
denf lychtsvagen 70. S-1 04, ¿5 Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla
Brogatan 26. Box 62 -1 01 , 20 Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse. Zürich; Librairies Payot in Geneva Lausanne. Basle, Berne,
Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and Zürich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books
Establishment, University of Aleppo, Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.,
40-42 Charoen Krung Road. Siyaeg Phaya Sri. P.O. Box 402. Bangkok;
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok; Suksit Siam Com¬
pany. 1 71 5 Rama IV Road. Bangkok; ROEAP. PO Box 1 425, Bangkok 10500.
TRINIDAD AND TOBAGO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra
St., St. Clair, Port-of-Spain. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevi A.S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No
469, Posta Kutusu 21 9. Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO
Box 7145, Kampala. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba. PO
Box 15408, AI Am. Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office.
PO Box 276, London, SW8 5DT; H.M.S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh,
Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham, Bristol; Third World Publications, 151
Stratford Road, Birmingham B1 1 1 RD; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd..
122 King's Cross Rd., London WC1 X 9DS. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA.
Bernan-UNIPUB, Periodicals Department, 461 1 -F Assembly Drive, Lanham,
MD 20706 4391. URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho,. S.A., Maldonado 1092,
Montevideo. USSR. V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova39, Moskva
113095. YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/1 1. Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba.
Zopitarjeva 2. Luciana; Nolit, Terazije 13/ VIII, 11000 Belgrade: periodicals
only: Jugosorvena Kniga, PO Box 36. YU 1 1001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664, Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
V
^ir
]]>
</page>
</document>
