<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="077733eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
2 Cameroon
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Editorial
All human societies, past and present, have coexisted with populations of
animals of one or many species. This issue of the Unesco Courier explores
some of the many dimensions of the relationships which have arisen from
this coexistence at different times and in different cultures. The articles on
the following pages may raise more questions than they answer, since
human attitudes to the animal world have been so diverse, and so often
replete with mystery, paradox and ambiguity. The very question "What is
an animal?" produces answers which differ from one culture to another,
and definitions of animality, whether "folk" or "scientific" , reveal much
about the ways in which the definers see themselves. The lovable animal of
one culture may be the unwanted pest of another. Modern industrial
society may seem no stranger to ambivalence in this field when it lavishes
affection on pets yet tolerates the cruelty of intensive forms of conveyor-
belt husbandry. And even when modern man is most seemingly benign to
his fellow creatures, his activities have such a far-reaching impact on the
environment that the survival of many animal species is being jeopardized
by the destruction of their habitat.
The earliest surviving record of the man-animal relationship can be
found in prehistoric rock art . Creation myths of some early societies speak
of a golden age when "gods, animals and people lived together and
communicated as equals in a common language" , perhaps reflecting a
balanced and in a sense almost egalitarian relationship between hunters
and animals. Such societies killed what they needed to survive, and usually
did not exceed the capacity of the environment to replenish the resources
they had taken. Then came a revolutionary change: with the transition
from hunting to pastoralism and the development of animal husbandry,
certain animals were domesticated and came under human control. This
was the beginning of a process which still goes on today.
The man-animal relation can be seen from many standpoints. Our
species has used animals symbolically to embody a range of qualities, from
innocence to dark unruly forces; we have involved animals in religious
practices; our feelings about animals have been vividly expressed in the
visual arts, literature and folk tales, and in anthropomorphic cartoon
animals. Man has studied animals scientifically and used representations of
their society in attempts to understand his own; he has explored the
boundaries of communication with animals. And while engaging in these
multiple activities he has felt a diversity of emotions: fear and admiration,
cruelty and affection, familiarity and distance, reflecting a complex
relationship varying from friendship to hostility and uneasy truce .
Cover: A Lapp working in a corral with his reindeer herd
Photo Alexander© Rapho, Paris
Back cover (inset): Bronze Age rock carvings at Tanum, Sweden (c. 1500 BC)
Photo Candelier-Brumaire © Artephot, Paris
Editor-in-chief: Edouard Glissant
February 1988
41st year
Man and animals
by Marc-Olivier Gonseth
Grandfather bear
Hunting rituals in early Eurasian cultures
by Viktor A. Shnirelman
11
People and pets
by Erika Friedmann
14
A horse named Hans
The search for a'talking animal'
by James Serpell
18
Why wildlife matters
by Richard Fitter
22
The wolf a man-made scapegoat
by Daniel Dubois
24
The last refuge of the giant panda
byPanWenshi
26
The monkey and the leopard
An Africanfolk tale
28
Animals in Islam
by Abdelhamid S. Hamdan
31
The private life of the vampire bat
. . . and othersurprising examples
ofanimal behaviour
by Marian Stamp Dawkins
Peoples and cultures
CAMEROON: Hitting the high notes
The Courier
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 34 languages
by Unesco
The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
7, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Malaysian
Korean
Swahili
Macedonian
Serbo-Croat
Slovene
Chinese
Bulgarian
Greek
Finnish
Swedish
Basque
Thai
Vietnamese
Pashto
Japanese Portuguese Croato-Serb Sinhala
A selection in Braille is
published quarterly in English,
French, Spanish and Korean
ISSN 0041-5278
N"2-1988-CPD-88-l-454 A
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Man and animals
n
*<
EACH culture thinks about animals
differently and classifies them in
ways which define the possible rela¬
tionships between man and those other spe¬
cies which share his physical and symbolic
environment. The modes of classification
vary from period to period and place to
place, but they usually lead to the dif¬
ferentiation (or to the association within
general groups) of human beings, gods,
plants, animals, stones, and spirits.
Generally speaking, the natural sciences
are not fundamentally distinct from indige¬
nous and popular forms of knowledge; they
develop as a result of a continual process of
"conceptual tinkering". Thus, in order to
distinguish plants from animals and to
accommodate organisms which were diffi¬
cult to classify, in the nineteenth century it
was found necessary to create a kind of
halfway house or intermediate category,
that of the "protists", from which the bac¬
teria were later extracted and assigned to a
separate kingdom, that of the procaryotes.
It is almost as difficult to establish a tax-
onomical difference between man and ani¬
mals. One specialist, Jacques Goimard, has
summed up the problem in these terms:
"even the latest scientific thinking, in spite
of appearances, has not completely aban¬
doned the attempt to define a specific quali¬
ty which differentiates animals from plants
and, above all, from human beings. The
animal might be defined as a non-human.
But all attempts to solve this problem are
unsatisfactory: none of the proposed
criteria is acceptable, except possibly that of
upright posture, which is the least meta¬
physical ... of all." The difference is not
biological but essentially cultural and
perhaps metaphysical.
The French anthropologist Claude Lévi-
Strauss has pointed out that "the Navajo
Indians, who proclaim themselves to be
'great classifiers', divide living creatures
into two categories, depending on whether
or not they have the gift of speech. Beings
without speech include animals and plants".
Once the frontiers have been defined,
relations can be established and com¬
munication can begin.
4 A woman gathering honey is depicted in this
reproduction of a painting (c.10,000/8000-
c.3000 BC) in the Araña cave, near Bicorp,
Valencia (Spain). Prehistoric rock art pro¬
vides the earliest record of man's reactions
to the animal world.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
by Marc-Olivier Gonseth wmmu
Many of the deities of ancient Egypt had
animal forms. One of the oldest was the
sky-god, Horus the falcon, who is depicted
with a human body in this low-relief carving
on the walls of the Nubian temple of Kalab-
sha. Other sacred animals in ancient Egypt
included the ram, the bull, the ape and
the cat.
Shamanism and the supernatural
The shamanic experience, in which anim¬
als sometimes appear as messengers or in¬
termediaries, may constitute the most pro¬
found relationship that a human mind can
have with the animal world. The ethnolog¬
ist Emmanuel Désveaux has described
how, among the Indians of Big Trout Lake
in Canada, at puberty a child is taken to a
remote spot where he settles down alone at
the top of a tall tree, on a platform that the
Indians liken to an eagle's nest , and fasts for
several days. He experiences hallucinations
that enable him to make contact with super¬
natural entities (opawakanuk) , which be¬
long to the animate world as it is perceived
by the Indian mind, and which to us corres¬
pond to real animals, to mythical animals,
and to supernatural creatures that haunt the
forest. After this initiation, the child adopts
towards the different animal species an indi¬
vidual system of rituals which include food
taboos, verbal taboos and rituals governing
the treatment of meat or bones after con¬
sumption.
On these occasions the Indians form rela¬
tionships which they keep up throughout
their lives. They also seek to create others,
so that the power they receive from super¬
natural agencies increases as they grow
older. When the men are too old to hunt,
they can exercise their specific powers in the
community through another ritual known
as kosapashikan (long-distance sight), in
which the Indian summons his opawakanuk
Scene from a fresco in the cultural centre of
the Hopi Indians at Albuquerque, New Mex¬
ico (USA). It was executed in 1978 by the
Indian artist J.D. Medina.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
^ Richly adorned with animal motifs, this
wooden prow of a boat was carved by an
artist of the Douala people of Cameroon.
This tiny bronze figure of a pelican feeding
its young is an ornamental weight produced
by a metalworker of the Baoulé people of the
Ivory Coast. It was once used for weighing
gold dust and nuggets. West African crafts¬
men fashioned a variety of such weights
depicting animal figures and scenes. Each
one corresponded to an ancient unit of
weight based on the seeds of certain plants
and was designed to illustrate a proverb or
transmit a message.
into a hemispherical shelter and entrusts
them with certain missions. This is a
"psychic process common to all indi¬
viduals", and lasts from the earliest initia¬
tion to the onset of old age. "In this sense, it
can be said that shamanism ... permeates all
activities, every moment of the Indians'
lives. The opawakanuk, essentially animal
spirits, are the vectors through which the
shaman accomplishes his extraordinary
tasks beyond place and time".
Clean and unclean
Pork, which is the object of absolute
prohibitions in Jewish and Muslim
societies, is a case which illustrates the
importance of the classifications which
underlie the culture and identity of human
groups.
Whether or not a group consumes certain
animal species is of fundamental importan¬
ce. Someone who eats or does not eat a
specific kind of meat, in a specific way, in
specific circumstances, is often considered
an outsider.
In her famous book Purity and Danger
the British anthropologist Mary Douglas
analyses the food prescriptions given in
Deuteronomy and Leviticus and notes that
"in general the underlying principle of
cleanness in animals is that they shall con¬
form fully to their class. Those species are
unclean which are imperfect members of
their class, or whose class itself confounds
the general scheme of the world". Thus the
pig is excluded by Hebrew tradition be¬
cause, not being a ruminant, it conflicts
with the following rule: "Whatsoever parts
the hoof and is cloven-footed and chews the
cud, among the animals you may eat" (Levi¬
ticus 11, quoted by Douglas). This prescrip¬
tion also excludes the camel, the rock bad¬
ger and the hare (which are not cloven-
footed). It would be hard to find a clearer
instance of the importance of categories of
thought in social practices.
Restrictions are also imposed on the eat
ing of pork in societies where it is widely
consumed. The reasons given for this are
essentially "dietary" and relate to the often
deplorable production conditions as well as
to latent anxieties about the status of the pig
as an omnivorous, scatophagous and sup¬
posedly dirty animal.
Animal eaters and animal lovers
The pork processing industry is unfortu¬
nately not the only one which sometimes
causes concern. The conditions in which
other animals than pigs are mass produced
for consumption are often scandalous and
contrast strongly with the sometimes exces¬
sive care lavished on domestic animals.
Another problem is related to the con¬
sumption of animal protein, the production
of which is extremely costly in terms of
energy (it takes between 5 and 20 kg of
plant protein to produce 1 kg of animal
protein). Levels of consumption vary wide¬
ly in different parts of the world. Whereas
the majority of people do not eat meat or
only eat meat on high days and holidays, for
a small proportion of the world's population
every day is a feast. The adoption of "carni¬
vores" as companion animals is an addition¬
al boost to the excessive consumption of
meat.
Hunting and rearing animals for their fur,
fishing of the great sea mammals, and other
examples of the massive exploitation ofwild
animals by "civilized" man have had spec¬
tacular consequences such as the trans¬
formation of lakes and forests into
aquariums and vivariums, and the increas¬
ing rarity of certain species.
The contemporary French artist François-
Xavier Laianne with his "Flock of Sheep".
The work, 6 examples of which were pro¬
duced, consists of 24 lifesize "sheep" (16
headless). Materials used include copper
plating, cast aluminium, wood, steel and
sheepskin.
»SaJ,
mM
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
One writer, Philippe Roger, has related
the disappearance of animal species to a
question of classification which led to the
"elimination of animality in the decades
between Darwin and Freud". Roger points
to the sacred character of all animals as the
dominant characteristic of very ancient
times, and suggests that it may have been
reinforced by Christianity. He notes that
medieval bestiaries still emphasize the
strangeness of animals and sees the "ra¬
diant" animality expressed in the bestiaries
as lasting until the time of the eighteenth-
century French naturalist Buffon, who him¬
self stressed "the radical difference between
the two worlds" by asserting "that man is of
a different nature, that he alone is in a class
apart".
Unfair game?
Any discussion of the extermination of
animals leads inevitably to the question of
hunting and its significance. Animals which
are highly valued for their fur, skins or ivory
are pitilessly and systematically hunted in
some parts of the world. The pretexts for
expeditions in which risk and the exercise of
virility are the backdrop for all kinds of
excesses, or decimated in quasi-industrial
fashion by groups organized along com¬
mando lines, these species are today so
seriously threatened that a strict and
perhaps partially inoperative regulation has
been drawn up to protect them.
The relationship between hunter-gather¬
er peoples and animals is (or was) generally
of another kind. Emmanuel Désveaux tells
how, before the arrival of the missionaries,
the Indians of Big Trout Lake were each
given the name of a different animal spe¬
cies. As a result of this process, a profound
relationship could be established between
the future hunter and the future quarry. A
specific ritual also marked the first capture
of a given quarry.
The practices described above are far
from being universally accepted, and va¬
rious organizations and individuals have
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The anthropomorphic rodent Mickey
Mouse is one of the most famous animated
cartoon characters created by the American
film-maker Walt Disney (1901-1966). He
made his film debut in Steamboat Willie
(1928), the first animated cartoon with
sound, and later starred in over a hundred
short productions. Left, a Mickey Mouse
figure takes part in a Washington, D.C.,
parade.
contributed to the debate on the protection
of animals, again raising the question of
where the frontiers of humanity should be
drawn. Jurists are also being asked to give
their opinion on animal rights and to formu¬
late legal provisions for the protection of
animals. Which animals should be protec¬
ted and to what extent? How can human
beings be persuaded or forced to respect
measures for animal protection?
Man-animal projections
Projections of human characteristics onto
animals and vice versa have given rise to
two apparently contradictory ways of think¬
ing. The first is that adopted by Walt Disney
and other creators of cartoon animals
whose attitudes, reasoning powers, attri¬
butes, anxieties and preoccupations are un¬
equivocally human. Perhaps this massive
output of anthropomorphic perceptions
and projections has further confused our
thinking about the relationship between
man and animals. Urbanization and the
industrialization of agriculture have dis¬
rupted the relationship between man and
animals and led to totally different por¬
trayals of the latter.
The reverse form of projection, from
animal to man, is often misused by scientific
and popular ethology (life is a jungle, man
is wolf to man, the strongest devour the
weakest, the female is subjected to the
male ...)
Here again we encounter demarcation
problems. Colette Guillaumin notes that "if
a common animal nature makes it possible
to make man, whenever the need arises, by
turns a chimpanzee, a wolf or a Scotch
grouse, no attempt is made to explain the
wolf in terms of the grouse or the chimpan¬
zee in terms of the wolf. This reveals at least
one thing: ethology describes the animal but
explains man. The reference point is man
and not animal social behaviour as such: the
animal is the mask that conceals, albeit
inadequately, the project of justifying ...
man. ... In spite of appearances, we are not
so far from the universe of La Fontaine or
Aesop, incapable of not projecting our 'pas¬
sions', of not peopling the world with con¬
structions engendered by our relations with
each other".
This remark seems particularly relevant
to species that are close to man (biological
proximity in the case of mammals; analogic¬
al proximity in the case of social insects),
but the further one goes from the human,
the less possible the transfer.
Experimentation with animals rests in
many cases on the same difficulties of trans¬
position, since man is the only guinea pig on
whom medicines destined for his fellows
can be reliably tested.
There is one field in which the animals we
think of as wild and even ferocious still
enjoy a little autonomy: in our individual or
collective fantasies and in the stories in
which they feature, wolves, tigers and hye¬
nas join the hybrids and monsters of our
imagination dragons, centaurs, were¬
wolves, yetis and other "alien" creatures
to define the imaginary limits of our
humanity.
Perhaps we have lost our feeling for the
"right distance" between ourselves and
animal species, a distance that can enable us
to communicate with animals without over-
sensitivity or cruelty and can at the same
time stimulate our symbolic imagination.
By coming too close to certain species, by
scandalously exploiting others, and by re¬
jecting animals which are hard to accept in
the sanitized capsules in which we live,
could we be fomenting dangerous problems
in our own minds and in the world at large?
The above article has been adapted from Des
animaux et des hommes ("Animals and Man"), a
book published by the Museum of Ethnography,
Neuchâtel (Switzerland) as a commentary on an
exhibition with the same title which was held at the
Museum in 1987. In the last thirty years the
Neuchâtel Museum of Ethnography has won a
reputation for its innovative exhibitions. Since
1 981 it has presented a series ofstriking exhibitions
designed to stimulate reflection on cultural relativ¬
ism through the unexpected juxtaposition of arte¬
facts from different cultures.
MARC-OLIVIER GONSETH, Swiss ethnologist,
was a staff member of the Neuchâtel Institute of
Ethnology from 1983 to 1987. He is currently
engaged on research among the Ifugao people of
the Philippines.
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Grandfather bear
by Viktor A. Shnirelman
'¥'
| ROM the innermost parts of the
Earth, from end to end, runs the
Myandash-pyrre, the wild rein¬
deer. His track is that of the sun; he runs
towards it. He is white, and his coat is more
silvery than the snow. He holds his black
head high, with his antlers back, and he flies
on invisible wings. His breath is that of the
untrammelled winds; they bear him along
on his flight ..."
In such poetic terms Lapp legends de¬
scribe the golden-antlered deer, which is a
protector and guide. Many of the peoples of
Northern Eurasia believed until recent
times that their good fortune depended on
the spirits that protected animals. The
Yakuts thought of a spirit as a fantastic wild
beast with the head of a dog, the hooves of a
cow, and long ears that hung down. Other
peoples believed that success in hunting
depended on the good will of the bear that
ruled over the reproduction of animals.
Others again thought that the world was
controlled by two does, from which both
wild and domesticated reindeer originated.
Another spirit of nature that people be¬
lieved in was the mammoth, which wan¬
dered about under the Earth, heaving it up
to produce hills and mounds.
Sometimes these spirits were thought to
be cosmic beings. Traces of this belief can
still be found among some of the Slav peo¬
ples; for instance, the Poles call the Polar
Star the "Elk Star", and in the north of the
Soviet Union the Great Bear was known as
the Elk until a short time ago.
All of this takes us back to the remote
past, when nature was peopled with super¬
natural beings on whose will the fate of
human beings depended. Hunters had to
pacify the spirits and observe certain pro¬
hibitions and prescriptions under the spirits'
watchful eyes. Preparations for the hunt
were surrounded by mystery. The hunters
were allowed to say little about it, and were
A bear in a sacrificial posture is shown in this
buckle from the Urals (4th-5th century AD).
In ancient times the hunters of Siberia and
North America treated the animals they
hunted with great consideration. Before
shooting an arrow at a bear, they addressed
it in friendly and persuasive tones as "old
man", "grandfather" or "lord", and later
when it was dead begged it not to take
revenge.
Hunting rituals
and animal worship
in early
Eurasian cultures
<
©
prohibited from referring to the game they
wanted to catch.
The quarry had to be treated with re¬
spect. Many of the peoples living in Siberia
and North America called the bear "old
man", "grandfather", "lord" or "sacred ani¬
mal". Before shooting a bear, they would
speak to it in a friendly fashion, to persuade
it not to resist. When the Ostyaks lured a
bear out of its lair, they would say, "Don't
be angry, grandfather! Come home with us
and be our guest." When they had killed the
bear they would beg it not to resent their
action and take revenge on the hunters.
They even tried to escape blame for having
killed it.
One Lapp legend tells how the reindeer
took pity on hungry men, and suggested
that they should kill him. Since then, people
had hunted reindeer, and had not wanted
for food. But the legend goes on to say that
the sacred reindeer had warned men to
spare the females and the leaders of the
herds in autumn; otherwise the hunting of
the wild deer would stop. By controlling
their hunting, the Lapps saved these anim¬
als from thoughtless extinction, in so doing
providing for their own future.
The ancient hunters also believed in cer¬
tain magical ways of ensuring the fertility of
wild animals. Many of the tribes of North¬
ern Eurasia and North America believed it
was forbidden to break the bones or the
skull of the principal animals they hunted.
They carried them into the depths of the
taiga, or hung them on trees, believing that
this would restore the creatures to life.
Others reconstituted the skeleton of a bear
they had killed and eaten and, after carrying
out certain rites, took it away into the taiga.
But even these precautions did not satisfy
the hunters' of old, and they called on the
shamans, who acted as intercessors with the
spirits. It was the shaman's duty to tell
people where and when they should hunt or
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Openwork bronze plaque of intertwined
fantastic animals dates from the second half
of the first millennium AD. It was discovered
in the region of Perm in the Urals.
the Tuvinians sold their cattle, they pulled
out a few of the animals' hairs and burnt
them. In this way they tried to prevent their
good luck from leaving them along with the
animals.
The war-horse was a favourite figure in
Turko-Mongolian epics. It was more than a
horse; it had magical properties. It had
wings, and could fly through the air; its
flight was like that of a falling star. It bes¬
trode the clouds and outstripped the birds;
only magic could bring it to a halt. The
war-horse played its part in campaigns; it
was the protector, guide, counsellor, healer
and saviour of its master. Sometimes a mare
was the horseman's nurse, and in such cases
he was considered to be the foster-brother
of his horse. If a batyr lost his horse, he lost
his strength.
Certain features of the cult of the horse
(horses were born from sea-spray and, like
winged deer, could fly through the air) sug¬
gest that there was once a cult of sacred deer
among the ancient Indo-European peoples
which, when horse-breeding began, be¬
came a cult of the horse. Even today, the
motif of a deer's antlers can be seen in the
folk art of some parts of Europe. The Celts
Bronze cult object (5th-10th century AD)
from the Perm region is shaped in the form
of a man standing on an animal's back.
fish, and also to treat the sick and forecast
the weather.
Each shaman had an animal that was his
double; it protected him and was in close
contact with him. Many people thought that
the shaman was descended from this ani¬
mal, or had been nurtured by it. He often
identified himself with it. Bronze plaques
that have been found in the valley of the
River Kama and in the Perm region of the
USSR, made by metalworkers living in
those parts in the period between the sixth
and twelfth centuries AD, show the shaman
wearing a ritual garment made of animals'
skins and birds' feathers.
The shaman sometimes wore a "crown"
with a deer's antlers on it, and shoes that
were like a deer's hooves. Among the
Ostyaks, the shaman-bears had the muzzle
of a bear fastened to their brow. On the
wolf's festival day, the shamans of the
Chukchi wore a mask made from a wolf's
muzzle. It was thought that an animal's vital
force was in its muzzle, and that the shaman
became as powerful as the animal by wear¬
ing this sort of mask. When the shaman was
in a trance he behaved as if he were an
animal he growled like a bear, leapt like a
deer, and so on.
One Yakut legend tells of a shaman who
stole the magical hairs of the elk, a divinity
that protected wild animals. He strewed the
hairs on the tribal hunting ground, and they
turned into game. The Nganasan people
thought that the Earth Mother was a female
elk, and that they had been created from the
hairs of her coat.
Among Turkic-speaking nomads, belief
in the miraculous powers of animal hair is
linked with horses. In their epic tales the
batyr (a powerful lord, or warrior) often
gets out of a difficult situation by setting fire
to horse-hairs, which turn into horses.
When the horses' hair was clipped, in the
spring, the Buryats held a ceremony for the
burning of the hair of white horses, which
was unquestionably a fertility ritual. When
Costume of a shaman of the Mansi people of
Siberia (9th-15th century AD). Details such
as the antlers on the headdress evoke the
close relationship between the shaman and
the animal world.
<S
10
worshipped a deity which had a deer's
antlers, and Artemis, the Greek goddess of
the hunt, was shown surrounded by does. A
drawing of a winged creature with antlers
has been found in a Scythian burial-ground
in the Altai region of Siberia.
The transition from the worship of the
deer to that of the horse was a slow process,
and for a long time the horse was regarded
as the reincarnation of the deer. The Hit¬
tites and the Celts disguised horses as deer,
and according to ancient Vedic documents,
Aryan groups decorated the head of a sac¬
rificial horse with the golden antlers of a
deer. In the Pazyryk kurgans (burial
mounds) in the Altai, the remains of horses
have been found which have deer masks on
their skulls (see the Unesco Courier, De¬
cember 1976). The Scythians put special
frontlets on their horses' heads, making
them look like deer with winged antlers.
Among the Turko-Mongolian peoples,
too, deer were replaced by horses as cult
animals. We do not know exactly when and
where this took place. But in recent years
Soviet archaeologists working in the south¬
ern regions of the European part of the
USSR have discovered a whole stratum of
cultures dating from the fourth millennium
BC, when people hunted wild horses and
had begun to tame them. About the same
time, a cult of the horse grew up, evidence
of which can be seen in statuettes of horses
and ossuaries of horses' skulls and bones
found in ancient settlements and burial
grounds. In the same period, in the Euro¬
pean steppe, stone sceptres began to be
fashioned in the shape of horses' heads,
perhaps to symbolize the power of a chief.
VIKTOR ALEKSANDROVICH SHNIRELMAN
is a staff member of the Miklukho-Maklaya
Ethnography Institute of the USSR Academy of
Sciences, where he specializes in the history of
early societies. He is the author ofstudies on "The
Origins of Cattle-Raising" and "The Classifica¬
tion and Differentiation of Cultures".
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
People and pets
by Erika Friedmann
Photo © Edouard Boubat, Pans
PET keeping is virtually ubiquitous
among human groups. People have
kept domesticated animals for at
least 10,000 years, and have captured,
tamed and kept wild animals as com¬
panions, without breeding them, for con¬
siderably longer. Although the initial im¬
petus for domestication is unclear, the first
breeding of animals, in the Mesolithic
period, was probably associated with
favourable environmental changes in speci¬
fic areas which dramatically increased the
availability of food. According to the
archaeological records, dogs were the first
and cats the second domesticated pets.
The importance of pet animals in modern
industrial society is repeatedly demons¬
trated in the popular press, movies and
books. Pets, and dogs in particular, are
often characterized as man's "best friend".
From a symbolic perspective, pets may well
represent the lost relationship of the mother
to the infant; that is complete and total
devotion, love, and adoration. They can
help bridge the developmental transitions
from infancy to childhood; from depend¬
ence to independence; from isolation to
social integration at varying times and
stages in our lives. While the relationship
between people and their pets may be a
symbol for the relationship of a mother to
an infant, the species difference constitutes
a fundamental distinction, providing emo¬
tional continuity without negating our indi¬
viduality.
Prior to the last decade there were few
scientific studies of the benefits of interac¬
tions between people and pets. Freud rec¬
ognized the unique and important role of
pets in people's lives: "It really explains,"
he wrote, "why one can love an animal ...
with such an extraordinary intensity; affec¬
tion without ambivalence, the simplicity
free from the almost unbearable conflicts of
civilization, the beauty of an existence com¬
plete in itself ... that feeling of intimate
affinity, of an undisputed solidarity."
However, his warm regard for them was not
expressed in a clinical interest. Most in¬
formation about the value of pets to their
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
people was based upon anecdotal informa¬
tion, compilations of personal stories of the
amazing devotion, intelligence and restora¬
tive powers of individual pets or particular
breeds, without the support of systematic
scientific investigation.
In the last ten years the common belief
that "pets are good for you" has gained
scientific support. Pets decrease owners'
loneliness and depression by providing
companionship, an impetus for nurturance,
and a source of meaningful daily activities.
They also decrease owners' anxiety and
stress levels by providing ccr.tact comfort, a
relaxing focus for attention, and a feeling of
safety. In addition, a pet can help its owner
improve or maintain physical fitness by pro¬
viding an impetus for exercise. While most
researchers into the effects of animals on
health have concentrated on dogs, there is
considerable evidence that other pets are
equally beneficial.
Loneliness may cause or worsen illnesses
and can even lead to death, and the com¬
pany of a pet can promote health by ame¬
liorating the pathological effects of lack of
contact with family members or close
friends. Pets can be particularly beneficial
to elderly people, who are especially
vulnerable to loneliness and isolated from
their families and friends. They act as com¬
panions to their owners, many of whom
consider their pets to be family members,
talk to them frequently as if they were
people, and think their pets are sensitive to
their moods.
In the course of a study of the social,
The tradition of keeping domesticated cats
as pets is thousands of years old. In ancient
Egypt, anyone who harmed a cat was
punished and when a pet cat died its master
shaved off his eyebrows as a sign of mourn¬
ing. Below, a modern cat-lover and his
companion.
psychological and physiological factors
affecting the survival of patients with coron¬
ary heart disease (severe chest pain or heart
attack), pet ownership was related to one
year survival. Only three of fifty-three pet
owners died within one year of admission to
a large urban university hospital while
eleven of thirty-nine non-pet owners co¬
vered by the study died in the same period.
As expected, the best predictor of survival
was the severity of the illness. The combina¬
tion of pet ownership and physiological
severity was better at predicting survival
than was physiological severity alone.
Furthermore, pets benefited everyone, not
just those who were living alone, unmar
ried, or widowed. The researchers con¬
cluded that the effects of pets on health
were distinct from the effects of other
people.
Pets can also lead to increased compan¬
ionship by facilitating interactions with
other people. They provide hospitalized or
institutionalized persons with important
links to friends and relatives in the outside
world. Many pet owners seek daily informa¬
tion about their pets during their own hospi¬
talization.
Frequently people who live alone or lose
reciprocity in their relationships with others
become depressed, feel unneeded, and lose
self esteem. These feelings lead to increases
"In early childhood pets provide a connec¬
tion to the natural world and are in¬
strumental in teaching respect for other liv¬
ing things." Below, a playful dog and its
master dwarfed by a high-rise block in the
Paris region.
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A
Above, a young Gypsy and his 4-legged
friend. Sometimes thought of as confined to
wealthy Western societies, pet-keeping
appeals to a wide variety of cultures
throughout the world.
in the psychological and physiological re¬
sponses to the challenges of daily life which
in turn lead to diminution of the body's
ability to fight infections and resist disease.
By lessening these feelings, pets can de¬
crease the impact of problems, disappoint¬
ments, deaths of friends, and other stressful
events.
Caring for a pet can also improve self
image and facilitate caring for oneself. In
one survey of senior citizens in the United
States, pet owners felt significantly more
self-sufficient, dependable, helpful, self-
confident and optimistic than non-pet
owners. A social worker in Edinburgh
(UK) even used the incentive of caring for a
pet to induce elderly clients to take better
care of themselves. She gave several of her
clients, who relied on open fires to warm
themselves in winter, pet birds which re¬
quired warm environments. None of those
who were given pet birds and instructed to
maintain higher house temperatures for
their pets experienced hypothermia that
winter. Since hypothermia is a major cause
of death for the elderly in Edinburgh, the
pets undoubtedly contributed to their own¬
er's health.
There is growing recognition of the im¬
portant positive role of the sense of touch
throughout the human life cycle. Pets pro¬
vide a crucial source of touch for individuals
who would otherwise be without this sen¬
sory input. Touching an animal decreases a
person's anxiety and stress levels. Touching
a pet, as well as being a means of expressing
affection, has a beneficial effect on owners'
cardiovascular systems. People rarely pet
an animal without talking to it, so it is not
possible to assess the independent effects of
the two activities. Researchers have re¬
ported that talking to and petting a compan¬
ion animal arouse the owners' cardiovascu¬
lar system less than talking with people.
This lends credence to the non-threatening,
supportive nature of the bond between hu¬
mans and companion animals.
Pet animals provide a sense of calmness
and security. People may be more willing to
go for walks, to leave their homes, or to visit
friends when their pet accompanies them or
guards their homes in their absence. Recog¬
nizing the pleasant aura presented by their
inclusion, advertisers and even politicians
often use pets to help create desired moods.
Both scenes and people in them are per¬
ceived as more friendly and less threatening
when an animal is included than when no
animal is present.
When animals are present, people tend to
focus their attention on them, especially in
stressful situations. This focus of attention
outside the self can cause decreases in stress
levels similar to those experienced during
more conventional forms of stress reduction
such as transcendental meditation or pro¬
gressive relaxation. Watching fish swim in
their tank has been as useful as hypnosis for
reducing anxiety and pain during dental
surgery. This type of observation of the
natural world also can be useful in lowering
blood pressure.
Caring for a pet can promote health by
giving people responsibility, providing time
orientation, and encouraging them to de¬
velop a more varied life-style. Taking re¬
sponsibility for a pet can be especially im¬
portant to patients whose activities are
limited due to chronic diseases, handicaps,
or social isolation.
In early childhood pets provide a connec¬
tion to the natural world and are in¬
strumental in teaching respect for other
living things. For slightly older children, the
responsibility of a pet may be instrumental
in developing self-esteem, self-confidence,
and independence.
Pets serve multiple functions at many
points in the life cycle from early childhood
through mature adulthood. Once contact
with an animal is established, it is easier to
enter into relationships with other people.
ERIKA FRIEDMANN, of the United Stales, is an
associateprofessor ofhealth and nutrition sciences
at Brooklyn College of the City University ofNew
York. She has published over 40 scientific articles,
a number of which examine the physiological
effects of keeping pets.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A horse named Hans by James Serpell
If-
The search for
a 'talking animaP
Arecent study in the United States
revealed that three-quarters of all
books and stories written for chil¬
dren are either about animals or contain
animals as important central characters. In
the vast majority, animals are endowed
with essentially human thoughts and feel¬
ings and, more often than not, they are able
to talk.
Although obvious to anyone who has
ever browsed through the average child's
bookshelf, these findings are nevertheless
intriguing. After all, why should adults writ¬
ing for children evidently assume that their
readers will identify more readily with
animal characters than with human ones?
And what is the point of encouraging chil¬
dren to imagine that animals can talk when
every child will eventually discover that
they cannot? At least not in the sense that
humans talk. The more one thinks about it,
the more curious it seems.
While this notion of animals and people
talking to each other is doubtless peculiar, it
is far from being a recent or a Western
invention. It is older and more widespread
than literature itself. The creation myths of
indigenous peoples throughout the world
hark back to a time beyond memory a
time such as the "dreamtime" of the Austra¬
lian aborigines when gods, animals and
people lived together and communicated as
equals in a common language. Even the
biblical account of creation implies a state
of harmonious coexistence between Adam
and Eve and the non-human denizens of the
Garden of Eden. And Noah, we are told,
was able to communicate sufficiently well
with doves and ravens that he could send
them out on search missions.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
^ "The notion of animals and people talking to
each other ... is older and more widespread
than literature itself. ... Noah ... was able to
communicate sufficiently well with doves
and ravens that he could send them out on
search missions." Left, Noah's Ark depicted
in a woodcut executed in 1564 by the Swiss
painter and engraver Jost Amman.
Long reputed for their intelligence, playful-
ness and friendliness to man, dolphins are
mentioned in the works of Aesop, Herodotus
and other early writers, often as a child's
mount or the rescuer of someone lost at sea.
For centuries many sailors regarded the pre¬
sence of dolphins leaping around their ship
as a sign that their voyage would be smooth
and happy. Right: "Cupid astride dol¬
phins", detail from a 2nd-century-BC
mosaic on the Greek island of Delos.
Indeed, as late as the Middle Ages in
Europe, the ability to communicate with
animals was regarded as a sure sign of bud¬
ding sainthood. According to legends,
many of the early Christian saints possessed
a special rapport with the birds and beasts.
The nature mystic, St. Francis of Assisi, for
example, preached sermons to rapt audi¬
ences of birds, and was able to tame wolves,
sing duets with nightingales, and still the
chattering of swallows or the croaking of
frogs. In this modern age of scientific objec¬
tivity, such stories seem quaint and fanciful.
Yet, ironically, the concept of people talk¬
ing to animals and vice versa continues to
flourish as never before.
The recent revival of interest in such phe¬
nomena began with a horse called Clever
Hans. Hans belonged to a retired school¬
teacher, Wilhelm von Osten, around the
turn of the century in Germany. Convinced
that his horse was exceptionally intelligent,
von Osten decided to teach it to solve sim¬
ple mathematical problems using the same
techniques he had used to teach children.
Hans far exceeded his expectations and
proved to be exceptionally gifted. When
asked to solve a simple problem, for exam¬
ple six subtracted from eleven, the horse
would give the correct answer by tapping
five times on the ground with his right fore¬
leg. Only rarely did he make serious errors.
Once the news of von Osten's clever
horse reached the rest of Europe, Hans
became a notable sensation. Visitors
poured in to see the horse perform, and
most of them went away convinced that
Hans was an equine genius. Even those who
suspected trickery, including many eminent
scientists, were baffled to discover that the
horse could still answer people's questions
correctly when his trainer was out of sight.
His fame spread, and Clever Hans rapidly
became a household name.
Sadly, it was not to last. Two professors
with the names of Stumpf and Pfungst were
determined to prove that Hans was a fraud.
They designed a series of experiments, in
the first of which two people agreed on a
problem they would ask the horse. One of
them would whisper the problem in the
horse's ear, and then retire from view be¬
hind a screen. In this test, where both ex¬
perimenters knew the right answer, Hans
usually solved the problem correctly. In the
second test, however, one experimenter
thought up a problem without telling the
other, and he then whispered it to the horse
and retired as before. In this situation,
Hans was apparently unable to give the
correct answer.
Further investigations revealed that Hans
was, indeed, very clever, but not in the way
that people had thought. Hans's skill lay in
his ability to detect the minute and subtle
variations in people's posture and facial
expression whenever he solved a problem
correctly. To get the right answer, all Hans
needed to do was to continue tapping on the
ground until he received the appropriate
signal to stop from his mystified audience.
Everyone, including the disillusioned von
Osten, had been fooled because they were
unaware that they had been transmitting
any signals to the horse (in humans, non¬
verbal messages of this kind are transmitted
unconsciously). They had drastically under¬
estimated the animal's powers of percep¬
tion and, as a result, had fallen into the trap
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
of assuming that Hans actually understood
the problems he was solving.
In reality, Clever Hans was not particu¬
larly exceptional. Talking animals, or at
least animals with amazing powers of
understanding, had been known about for
centuries. Clever Hans was, however, the
first such animal to be subjected to detailed
scientific scrutiny, and his eventual "expo¬
sure" cast a shadow of scepticism over all
subsequent phenomena of this kind.
It took the scientific world many decades
to recover from this ignominious piece of
self-deception and, when news of talking
animals resurfaced again in the early 1960s,
it involved not horses, but dolphins. It had
long been recognized that marine mam¬
mals, such as dolphins, were intelligent and
highly trainable creatures which could be
taught to perform astonishing tricks for
public entertainment. But in 1961, a book
entitled Man and Dolphin was published
containing far more exciting observations.
The author, John C. Lilly, was a neuro¬
logist who had been conducting experi¬
ments on the brains of live dolphins, focus¬
ing particularly on their vocal behaviour.
Despite early setbacks (many of his ex¬
perimental animals died under anaesthe
tic), Lilly succeeded in training dolphins to
vocalize on command, and he noticed that
some of his animals spontaneously pro¬
duced passable imitations of human speech.
This finding, coupled with the fact that
dolphins possess exceptionally large and
complex brains, inspired Lilly to make the
optimistic prediction that "within the next
décade or two" humans would establish
two-way communication with another
species, probably a marine mammal.
Lilly's book attracted considerable media
attention and stimulated a number of futur¬
istic novels and films. More surprisingly,
perhaps, his arguments were so convincing
that research on human-dolphin com¬
munication began to attract considerable
government funding. Alas, despite these
efforts, Lilly's talking dolphin never mater¬
ialized. Within a decade it was apparent
that the spectre of Clever Hans had simply
reappeared in an unfamiliar disguise, and
the entire programme of research was dis¬
continued.
Evidently undaunted, the scientific com¬
munity once again shifted its attention, this
time to focus on anthropoid apes. As our
nearest living relatives, apes have long been
the objects of special fascination, and the
idea of teaching them to speak was far from
new. The earliest experiments in this direc¬
tion, conducted by various people between
1896 and the 1940s, were, however, largely
unsuccessful. In 1947, for example, a young
American psychologist and his wife
adopted a month-old infant chimpanzee
called Vicki, and brought her up as their
"daughter". Vicki was reared as a child for
six years until her death, and subjected to
an intensive programme of language
training. Despite this, she learned only four
words papa, mama, cup and up which
she whispered rather than spoke. It was
concluded that apes were incapable of ac¬
quiring human language, if only because
they lack the necessary vocal apparatus to
pronounce words effectively.
In spite of these early negative results,
talking apes hit the headlines again in the
1970s when Allen and Beatrice Gardner at
the University of Nevada began teaching a
young chimpanzee called Washoe Amer¬
ican Sign Language (a system of hand sig¬
nals devised for the deaf). After four years
of intensive training, the Gardners claimed
that Washoe had acquired a vocabulary of
132 different signs which she could combine
together into apparently meaningful "sen¬
tences". Owing to the particularly close
relationship which existed between Washoe
and her trainers, however, it was difficult to
rule out the so-called "Clever Hans effect".
In other words, the Gardners may have
unwittingly provided Washoe with non-ver¬
bal cues when she gave the correct or ex¬
pected hand signals. Even when Washoe
signalled some spontaneous request, such
as "give me drink", it was not clear that she
understood the meanings of her signals in a
symbolic or abstract sense, as a person
would. It was possible that she had simply
learned to associate a gesture or a series of
gestures with a particular desired result.
These objections to the results of
"Project Washoe" and other more recent
sign-language studies have led to the inven¬
tion of increasingly elaborate and sophisti¬
cated techniques for exploring the linguistic
ability of apes. Artificial languages using
coloured plastic chips as "word analogues",
and computer keyboards made up of dis¬
tinctive geometric symbols have been de¬
vised to eliminate human interference and
the Clever Hans effect. Chimpanzees have
even been trained to communicate with
each other using such artificial languages.
Studies of this kind have revealed that
chimpanzees can be trained to understand,
in abstract, the meanings of the symbols
they use. In other words, they can acquire
"Chimpanzees can acquire ... the use of
arbitrary symbols to represent objects,
states or events. As yet, however, research
has provided little evidence that they are
able to organize these symbols according to
recognizable rules of grammar or syntax. In
short, their conversational abilities are
strictly limited." Left, a chimpanzee learn¬
ing the hand signal for "tickle" at the Insti¬
tute for Primate Studies in Norman, Okla¬
homa (USA).
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
the rudiments of semantics, or the use of
arbitrary symbols to represent objects,
states or events. As yet, however, this re¬
search has provided little evidence that
chimpanzees are able to organize these
symbols according to recognizable rules of
grammar or syntax. In short, their conver¬
sational abilities are strictly limited.
Perhaps because apes lack the ability to
pronounce human words, scientists are now
exploring the linguistic capacities of other
more "talkative" species. Most people
assumed that talking birds, such as parrots,
merely mimic sounds at random and are
incapable of using speech in appropriate
contexts hence the phrase: to learn some¬
thing "parrot fashion", meaning to imitate
things without understanding them.
After several years of careful instruction,
however, researchers at one university in
the United States have succeeded in train¬
ing Alex, an African grey parrot, to learn
verbal labels for more than twenty different
objects, such as paper, rock, cork or water.
He also knows five different colours, four
different shapes, and various commands,
such as "want", "come here", and "you
tickle me".
More to the point, Alex is able to com¬
bine these words intelligently to identify,
request or refuse more than fifty different
items, even some which were not included
in his original training. Alex is a long way
from being able to hold a conversation with
his trainers, and many scientists argue that
he is just another example of associative
learning and the Clever Hans effect. Yet his
"For the time being, talking animals anim¬
als capable of holding conversations with
people or with each other must remain the
subject of myths and children's literature.
... But one need only observe a shepherd and
his dog, or a skilled rider and his horse, to
realize the extraordinary level of shared
communication which exists." Above, "con¬
versation" between a man and his horse in
Romania.
achievements already rival those of the
signing chimpanzees, and Alex is only a
parrot.
For the time being, talking animals
animals capable of holding conversations
with people or with each other must re¬
main the subject of myths and children's
literature. All our efforts to educate our
non-human relations have failed to produce
a single individual that is capable of acquir¬
ing language. This does not, of course,
mean that people and animals are unable to
communicate. One need only observe a
shepherd and his dog, or a skilled rider and
his horse, to realize the extraordinary level
of shared communication which exists. But
there is a fundamental difference between
this, and the kind of communication that
goes on all the time between people.
Language, with its abstract symbols and
grammatical rules, is apparently unique to
human beings. We alone acquire it with
ease and apparent spontaneity; so much so
that when a person does not acquire lan¬
guage during normal development we are
immediately concerned that something is
seriously wrong. We need language in order
to cope with the complex social and mate¬
rial world in which we live. It is apparent,
however, that animals do not need it. They
manage their lives efficiently and effectively
without.
But, if all this is true, why have people
devoted so much time, effort and resources
to the idea of talking to animals? What
would we actually gain from the exercise? It
would certainly be interesting (and doubt¬
less ethically disturbing) to know what
animals really think and feel. Or to be able
to ask them direct questions concerning
their lives. But we have never, in fact, come"
close to achieving this sort of dialogue.
Perhaps our true motive is a simple desire to
make contact; to be united once again with
our own animal origins.
Human language and self-awareness
effectively isolate us from the rest of the
animal world. As Adam and Eve dis¬
covered, the price of self-knowledge was
eviction from the Garden of Eden. Yet in
myths, fairy-tales and children's literature,
and in our more recent interactions with
clever horses, signing chimpanzees and
talking parrots, we seem to cherish the per¬
sistent, if forlorn, hope that this isolation is
only temporary.
JAMES SERPELL is a senior research associate
in animal behaviour at the University of Cam¬
bridge (UK). He has written numerous articles on
animal behaviour and relationships between peo¬
ple and animals and is the author ofa recent book,
In the Company of Animals: A Study of Human-
Animal Relationships.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Why wildlife matters
Photo Norman Myers © WWF, Gland, Switzerland
"If all the beasts were gone, men would die
from great loneliness of spirit, for whatever
happens to the beasts also happens to the
man. All things are connected. Whatever
befalls the earth befalls the sons of the
earth." These words were written by an
Indian chief, Seathl, in a letter to the Presi¬
dent of the United States in 1855. Above, a
herd of African elephants. Poaching for iv¬
ory is a serious threat wherever elephants
are accessible, and in Africa elephant num¬
bers have declined considerably in recent
years.
IN this age of technology, of computers,
television, supersonic aircraft and nuc¬
lear power stations, why should wild
animals and plants matter to us any longer?
Surely they must now go into the ash-can of
history, along with bows and arrows, wood
fires and horse transport?
On the contrary, it is a matter of life and
death, in every sense of the phrase, that
animals and plants should continue to exist.
For every day of our lives, every man,
woman and child in the world depends on
them for vital parts of their welfare.
Animals and plants contribute to human
welfare in three main ways. They provide
much of the material basis of human life:
almost all our food, much of our clothing,
and in many parts of the world still most of
the material for building and of the fuel for
heating and lighting our dwellings. In addi¬
tion, they provide the knowledge that is
essential for maintaining this material basis,
and indeed for preventing a widespread
return to more primitive conditions. Not
least, they contribute significantly to our
enjoyment of our environment, both in our
daily recreation and in our wonderment at
both the beauty of the natural world and at
the mysteries of the universe.
It was recognition of the importance to
mankind of the genetic resources repre¬
sented by animal and plant species, both
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Htter
Photo J. Esser © WWF, Gland, Switzerland
wild and domesticated, and alarm at their
widespread destruction, that eight years
ago led the International Union for Con¬
servation of Nature and Natural Resources
(IUCN) and the World Wildlife Fund
(WWF) to produce the World Conservation
Strategy (see the Unesco Courier, May
1980). This has three primary objectives:
(1) to maintain viable stocks of all animal
and plant species (it must be ail because we
still know so little about the value of the
great majority of species; it is only quite
recently, for instance, that the value in the
treatment of cancer of a little-known Mada¬
gascar plant, the periwinkle Catharanthus,
was discovered);
(2) to maintain large enough stocks of
species already known to be of value to
. man, so that they can be cropped, harvested
or otherwise enjoyed indefinitely; and
(3) to maintain pure air and water and
fertile soil.
, Though all three aims of the World Con¬
servation Strategy are plain common sense,
they are widely disregarded by both govern¬
ments and individuals, thanks to our pre¬
sent social and institutional arrangements.
How are we to overcome this widespread
neglect and manage the world's animals and
plants, both wild and domesticated, on a
sustainable basis, i.e. so that they continue
to be available for our benefit?
The two main threats to species, which
have led to the extinction of some and se¬
vere reductions in the numbers of many
others, are overexploitation and habitat
destruction.
Historically, overexploitation, both legal
and illegal, has been the more important. In
the last century, overhunting exterminated
the passenger pigeon in North America and
nearly exterminated the bison there too. In
the present century, systematic poaching
for their horns and ivory has almost exter¬
minated the black rhinoceros and severely
reduced elephant numbers in Africa.
Moreover, overhunting of the great
whales, especially in the southern oceans,
despite the efforts of the International
Whaling Commission (IWC) set up espe¬
cially to prevent this, has reduced almost all
stocks throughout the world to the level of
commercial extinction. Since their hunting
is now forbidden, the whaling industry has
in effect committed suicide. Marine fish
stocks throughout the world have also been
steadily overexploited so that many of them
are no longer available for human consump¬
tion. The world's last great reservoir of
plentiful fish stocks is now in the Antarctic
and sub-Antarctic. Will current efforts
through the Antarctic Treaty be too little
and too late to save these too?
But today widespread habitat destruction
The vicuña (Lama vicugna), a ruminant re¬
lated to the llama, lives in the high Andes. Its
exceptionally fine and warm wool was highly
prized in North America and Europe, and so
many vicuña were slaughtered that the spe¬
cies was threatened with extinction until
Peru took protective measures to save it in
the 1960s.
is by far the most serious threat to both
animal and plant species, especially in the
great rainforest belt of the developing
world. Here the burgeoning human popula¬
tion makes constantly increasing demands
for timber and cultivable land. "More peo¬
ple and less swamp", as an elderly Floridan
pithily explained the decrease of the cougar
in his district. Ten hectares of virgin tropical
forest are estimated to be disappearing
every minute. At this rate of clearance
hardly any of the surviving 2 to 3 billion
hectares will remain outside national parks
and other protected areas by the end of the
century, now only a dozen years away.
Pollution is an almost equally important
factor. Chemical wastes from both industry
and agriculture, as well as from the activi¬
ties of individuals such' as automobile
travel, are steadily impairing the quality of
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The African northern white rhino (Cer-
atotherium simum cottoni) lives under threat
of extinction because of hunting for its horn.
By the early 1980s it was estimated that its
numbers had been reduced to fewer than 700
animals. The biggest population of northern
white rhinos today live in Zaire's 500,000-
hectare Garamba National Park, which in
1980 was included on Unesco's World Herit¬
age List as a natural property of outstanding
universal value.
The Arabian oryx (Oryx leucoryx) was once
common throughout the desert areas ofAra¬
bia, Syria and Mesopotamia. By 1972 it had
become extinct in the wild through intensive
hunting. Fortunately, before that happened,
a few had been captured and used to build
up breeding herds. In 1980 the oryx was
successfully reintroduced in Oman.
air, soil and water. The most dramatic effect
is that of acid rain , due to a "chemical soup"
still not fully understood, which is des¬
troying both forests and freshwater fish
stocks throughout the northern hemi¬
sphere.
To stop overexploitation, we must reg¬
ulate cropping and harvesting. This calls for
both licensing of individual hunters, some¬
times with specific bag limits, and quotas for
commercial harvesting. The problem is al¬
ways enforcement, as witness the universal
existence and increasing audacity of
poachers even in national parks, and the
dismal record of the whaling industry.
The accurate estimation of stock size is
another problem. The IWC has its own
scientific committee to do this for whales,
and IUCN has set up a Conservation Moni¬
toring Centre (CMC), to create an accurate
data-base for all species. The Centre is also
responsible for the Red Data Books, brain¬
child of Sir Peter Scott, which summarize
key information about endangered species.
So far the chief weapon against habitat
destruction has been the creation of nation¬
al parks, nature reserves, wildlife refuges or
other protected areas. But can enough land
be set aside in this way in the next ten or
twelve years to save the many thousands of
species that today face certain extinction
from rainforest loss alone? The number of
species so threatened may indeed be mil¬
lions, if the latest estimates of the world's
invertebrate species an incredible 30 mil¬
lion are correct.
The two bodies which bear the brunt of
the responsibility for saving species are
IUCN and WWF. They share a headquar¬
ters in Switzerland and are greatly helped
by the United Nations Environment Prog¬
ramme (UNEP), which strongly supports
and grant-aids IUCN. Birds are covered by
the International Council for Bird Preserva¬
tion (ICBP), headquartered in the United
Kingdom and currently grant-aided by
WWF.
IUCN operates through six commissions
of scientific experts: the Species Survival
Commission (SSC), the one mainly con¬
cerned with species conservation, works
through a network of more than 90 special¬
ist groups, to which nearly 2,000 zoologists
and botanists all over the world voluntarily
contribute their expertise. Among the most
active groups are those covering African
elephants and rhinos, antelopes, cats, pri¬
mates, crocodiles, marine turtles, dragon-
flies and orchids. The Trade Group is re¬
sponsible for IUCN's input into the impor¬
tant Convention on International Trade in
Endangered Species (CITES). The SSC
also has close links with ICBP, which has its
own series of working groups, such as those
for parrots, flamingos and bustards.
Two other relevant IUCN commissions
are those for Ecology (general habitat prob¬
lems, pollution) and National Parks and
Protected Areas. Unesco's Man and the
Biosphere Programme also plays a vital
part in preserving habitat for species, as do
such international conventions as the World
Heritage Convention, and the Ramsar Con¬
vention on Wetlands of International Im¬
portance.
Many non-governmental organizations
belong to IUCN, and some are active in the
species conservation field in their own
right, notably the Bombay Natural History
Society, the Fauna and Flora Preservation
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Illicit trade
in threatened species
Society of London, the Frankfurt Zoologic¬
al Society of the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many and the New York Zoological
Society.
Unlike IUCN, WWF and ICBP operate
largely through national organizations or
sections, ICBP's network being consider¬
ably the more extensive world-wide. WWF
is primarily a fund-raising body, and in¬
creasingly tends to raise funds for its own
programmes and projects.
So where do we go from here? How can
this array of national and international
bodies help to achieve our aim, the con¬
servation and sustainable use (which in¬
cludes non-consumptive uses, such as bird-
watching and whale-watching) of animal
and plant species?
More, and usually a lot more, of what we
are already doing seems to be the answer.
First we must set aside and manage properly
adequate areas of habitat. This includes
ensuring that big development projects take
account of the need to conserve genetic
resources.
We must also ensure that all wild popula¬
tions that are harvested are not over-
harvested. This means both cracking down
on poaching everywhere, not just in pro¬
tected areas, and properly enforcing the
CITES trade regulations. Finally, and most
important of all, we must carry with us not
only the decision-makers, politicians and
administrators, but also villagers and
townsfolk all over the world. Without their
goodwill, and their realization of where
their own real long-term interests lie, every¬
thing will be lost.
RICHARD FITTER, British naturalist and au¬
thor, has been a member of the Species Survival
Commission of the International Union for Con¬
servation of Nature and Natural Resources
(IUCN) for 24 years and is currently chairman of
its Steering Committee. His 29th book was Wild¬
life for Man, a source-book on species conserva¬
tion for the World Conservation Strategy, and his
30th, a field guide to the north-west European
countryside in winter, will appear in September
1988.
The green turtle (Chelonia mydas), found in
tropical seas, is overexploited for its meat,
its eggs and its shell, used to make tourist
souvenirs. Turtle populations have been sev¬
erely reduced and in some regions have dis¬
appeared completely. Right, baby green
turtles.
THE international wildlife trade, worth
billions of dollars annually, has been
responsible for massive declines in the
numbers of many species of animals and
plants. The scale of over-exploitation for
trade aroused such concern that an interna¬
tional treaty was drawn up in 1973 to protect
wildlife against such over-exploitation and to
prevent international trade from threatening
species with extinction.
Known as CITES, the Convention on In¬
ternational Trade in Endangered Species of
Wild Fauna and Flora entered into force on 1
July 1975 and now has 96 member countries.
Enforcement ofCITES is the responsibility of
these countries, which are required to ban
commercial trade in an agreed list of cur¬
rently endangered species and regulate and
monitor trade in others that might become
endangered. Governments are also required
to submit reports, including trade records,
to the CITES Secretariat in Switzerland.
The wildlife trade involves a wide variety of
species, both as live specimens and as pro¬
ducts. Millions of live animals and plants are
shipped around the world each year to supply
the pet trade and to meet the demand for
ornamental plants. Furskins, leather, ivory
and articles manufactured from these mate¬
rials are all traded in large quantities.
CITES provides protection for species in
two main categories, "most endangered spe¬
cies", and "other species at serious risk".
Among those listed in the former category are
all apes, lemurs, the giant panda, many
South American monkeys, great whales,
cheetah, leopards, tigers, Asian elephants,
all rhinoceroses, many birds of prey,
cranes, pheasants and parrots, all sea turtles,
some crocodiles and lizards, and giant
salamanders.
Included in the second category are species
which might become endangered if trade in
them is not controlled and monitored. Inter¬
national trade in these species is permitted
with proper documentation issued by the gov¬
ernment of the exporting country. The list
includes all animal species in the following
groups which are not already in the first
category: primates, cats, otters, whales, dol¬
phins and porpoises, birds of prey, tortoises,
and crocodiles, as well as many other species
such as the African elephant, fur seals and
birds of paradise.
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The wolf-
a man-made scapegoat by Daniel Dubois
IN the beginning man made a pact with
nature. All animals, not only domestic
but also those that were thought to be
dangerous, were held sacred, and to kill and
eat them was regarded as murder and
punishable. Save on rare occasions when
the whole tribe participated, the use of their
flesh was forbidden.
Thus it came about that small groups or
clans of men concluded quasi-religious
pacts with such animals as the bull , the hare ,
the lion, the snake, the eagle and the scor¬
pion. The wolf was one of these animals.
The clan that chose the wolf made him their
totem. He became their brother, their
name and emblem, their ancestor, the re¬
vered animal which it was forbidden to kill
or eat, the tribe's guide and protector who
never attacked its members. He was a full
member, as it were, and had to respect and
share in all the rights and duties of his
brother-men.
This fundamental pact or primitive taboo
was reflected in a mandatory rule "thou
shalt not kill". This pact applied to men as
well as to their brothers the wolves, and
it is still observed between the wolves
themselves.
Mythology has been described as a dilu¬
tion of totemism which occurred when man
abandoned his pact with nature and trans¬
ferred his trust to new gods. But in many
instances man gave his totem animal to his
gods for a companion, or even deified the
animal, as in Ancient Egypt, where the wolf
Because of its fearsome reputation the wolf
has more than once been wrongly accused of
crimes it did not commit. When the noto¬
rious "Beast of Gévaudan" terrorized part
of southern France in the 18th century,
claiming over 100 lives and wounding 30
people, an enormous wolf was thought to be
the culprit. Today much of the evidence
seems to suggest that the atrocities were
caused by human hands. Above, contem¬
porary depiction of the Beast of Gévaudan.
was worshipped at Lycopolis, the city of the
wolves, capital of the nome of Lycopolite,
the homeland of Plotinus, now called
Assiout. In ancient Greece, Apollo, the god
of day and light, was also a wolf-god. A
bronze wolf guarded his altar in the temple
of Delphi.
Mars-Ares, the Roman god of war, had a
wolf for his emblem, and sometimes
changed into a wolf by donning a wolfskin.
It was his seduction of the vestal virgin Rhea
Silvia that led to the creation of Rome. She
was punished by drowning and her children ,
Romulus and Remus, were in danger of
certain death in the marshy waters of the
Tiber when they were rescued by a she-wolf
near Mount Palatine. Later, Romulus kil¬
led his brother and built his city on the
mountain where the she-wolf had reared
them. From that day Rome adopted the
wolf as its totem and paraded its famous
standard, decorated with the wolf, through¬
out the Roman world.
Further north the Scandinavian wolf-god
Odin (Wotan to the Germans) reigned,
assisted by the wolves Gere and Freke, who
never left his side. There is no trace of fear
of the wolf in any of these legends at the
most a kind of respect. It could not have
been otherwise, since the wolf was man's
brother and often his protector.
Some Christian saints, especially her¬
mits, lived without fear amongst the anim¬
als of the forest. Examples of wolf-loving
saints abound, but we shall mention only a
few. Among the Slavs there was a tradition
that Saint Peter was the wolves' shepherd
and that on 17 January he assembled them
all and distributed food supplies to them for
the coming year. In eastern Europe, Saint
George, patron of wild beasts, was accom¬
panied by wolves who were called his
hounds and were his favourite companions.
The blind Saint Hervé had a faithful wolf to
guide him. Saint Francis of Assisi made a
friendship pact with the wolf of Gubbio.
The pact was respected, and thanks to it the
reformed wolf was fed by the people of
Gubbio for the rest of his life.
Then, suddenly, everything changed.
From being a god or companion of the gods,
a friend or familiar animal of the saints, the
wolf gradually became a despised and hated
beast, an evil animal earmarked for destruc¬
tion. He became the enemy and supreme
insult the Devil; the werewolf, Satan's
henchman, Hell's procurer. What is the
reason for this hatred, which still survives in
our subconscious, even though the wolf is
now only found in fairytales, comic strips,
advertisements, and films of the fantastic?
If we do not know exactly what hap¬
pened, we can at least try to understand the
reasons for this turnabout. It is strange that,
although prehistoric man accurately repre¬
sented many animals on the walls of his
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
*c
-*~<rcZ í 1/Vi
^"Wolf man" Werner Freund, a former keep¬
er at Stuttgart Zoo, has bred a pack of 20
wolves in a specially made enclosure at Mer-
zig, in the Saar forest, Fed. Rep. of Ger¬
many. He lives among the animals, playing,
eating and even sleeping with them.
The wolf has been persecuted unremittingly
for centuries and has all but disappeared
from many of its former haunts, at least in
Western Europe, where only a few isolated
specimens continue to lead a precarious ex¬
istence. Below, a European wolf cub.
cave-dwellings, he very rarely represented
the wolf. And yet we know that the wolf
existed at that period, since many wolves'
remains have been found in deposits of
bones. Pierced eyeteeth of wild boars and
wolves, probably used as pendants or com¬
ponents of necklaces, have also been found,
especially in children's tombs. To the
eyeteeth was attributed the power to pro¬
tect from disease and the evil eye, a power
later found in magic and popular medicine.
Clearly, therefore, our hunter-gatherer
ancestors were not afraid of the wolf.
The transition to livestock rearing and
agriculture brought man and wolf who
occupied the same territories and had simi¬
lar modes of behaviour into deadly con¬
frontation. The wolf fell victim to steppe
and forest clearances, and, driven into
smaller and smaller areas where prey be¬
came ever scarcer, he became dependent on
man for his survival. In the West he chiefly
attacked livestock, an abundant and easy
prey. Sometimes hunger or rabies forced
him to emerge from his lair and attack his
persecutor, man. Hence the hatred and
fear, sharpened further by wars, invasion
and famines.
Henceforth the two enemies waged an
unceasing war on each other in which man
spared no effort as a hunter, setting traps
and snares, and using poisons and all kinds
of weapon. At a very early date man de¬
cided to exterminate the wolf because of the
wolf's damaging effect on the economy. No
account was taken of the wolf's important
and necessary ecological role, nor of his role
in medicine, for many parts of the wolf have
been used in the materia medica.
In Western Europe, the Emperor Charle¬
magne institutionalized the extermination
of the wolf when he established the
Louveterie or wolf-hunt. He had his vassals
appoint two officers in each fief, whose duty
was to hunt down the wolf. The system was
repeatedly modified and finally abolished
by Louis XVI on 9 August 1787 as an eco¬
nomy measure.
Napoleon I re-established the Louveterie
and placed it under the supervision of a
Grand Veneur or Master of the Imperial
Hounds. Everywhere, the Lieutenants de
Louveterie were big landowners. Many of
them were members of the nobility and
played an important role in local politics. It
was not until 1971 that this legalized surviv¬
al of feudalism was finally abolished by an
act of parliament.
The wolf is now totally extinct in Ireland,
the United Kingdom, France, Belgium,
The Netherlands, Denmark, the Federal
Republic of Germany, the German Demo¬
cratic Republic, Switzerland, Austria and
Hungary. The species is virtually extinct in
Norway, Sweden and Finland and is en¬
dangered in Bulgaria, Czechoslovakia,
Italy, Poland, Portugal and Spain. Today it
is only in the snow-bound wastes of Alaska,
Canada and the USSR that the wolf is at
home.
Has fear of the wolf or rather the wolf
psychosis disappeared? Whenever a
strange, ferocious animal is mentioned,
someone will bring up the wolf and his
misdeeds, his ferocity, cruelty and man-
eating proclivities. During the Middle Ages
this fear was nurtured by tales of fantasy
told around the fire on long winter nights,
and later in cheap news-sheets which seized
upon accidents and attacks by wild animals;
as well as by the civil and religious author¬
ities.
Nowadays the wolf seems to have lost his
power to frighten, and soon fear of the wolf
will be only a myth, perhaps less because
of his disappearance than because we have
acquired a better understanding of his
behaviour.
DANIEL DUBOIS, French ethnozoologist, is a
staff member of the laboratory of ethnobiology
and biogeography at the Natural History
Museum, Paris. He is co-author, with Daniel
Bernard, of L'homme et le loup (2nd edition,
1987) and has published articles in a number of
periodicals. He is currently working on a book
about people and trees.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Helping
an endangered species
to survive
in its natural habitat
i
V
J&
o
'&***ât
Photo G.B. Schaller, © WWF, Gland, Switzerland
The last refuge of the giant panda
by Pan Wenshi
GIANT pandas, with their unique
black and white fur and adorably
clumsy behaviour, are today an en¬
dangered species whose fate is worthy of
general concern, for they are a treasure not
just of China but of the whole world.
Though the origins and taxonomical de¬
tails of the giant panda are still being de¬
bated, its evolution has been clearly defined
after scientific study of fossils unearthed at
hundreds of spots in China, eastern Burma
and northern Viet Nam.
The giant panda already existed three
million years before the anthropoid apes
evolved into humans. At that time there
was only a small number of them living in
what is now South China's tropical and
sub-tropical jungle where the giant apes
ruled. Judging from the fossilized teeth of
the giant pandas in those times, their diet
was almost the same as it is today, but their
average size was only half that of a grown
panda today.
Some 750,000 years ago, giant pandas
began to spread northward, over the Qin-
ling Mountains which extend across the
western half of China, all the way from the
Pearl River and the Yangtze River basins in
the south to Zhoukoudian in the mountains
southwest of Beijing in the north. It was at
this time that the giant panda population
reached its peak. The pandas also grew in
size, averaging about one-eighth bigger
than those of today.
In this early period of their evolution,
they not only flourished in the tropical and
sub-tropical jungles of the south, but also
adapted to the mild-to-cool climate of the
northern forests.
The giant pandas suffered their first set¬
back some 18,000 years ago when the last
Ice Age began. Their kingdom north of the
Qinling Mountains was swept out of exist¬
ence while their numbers in the south
dwindled. The real knock-out blow,
however, did not come from nature, but
from the most intelligent of all living crea¬
tures human beings.
The fast-growing human race in the last
few millennia has slowly but irresistibly
forced the giant pandas to retreat from the
fertile land in the lower mountains of south¬
ern China into the deep valleys on the east¬
ern skirt of the Qinghai-Tibet plateau.
Today, giant pandas are found only in six
separate locations in the mountainous west
of China. In one of these locations, an area
of some 1,650 square kilometres on the
southern slopes of the Qinling Mountains,
are no more than 240 giant pandas. The
largest of the six locations, in which some
350 pandas live, spreads out over 13,300
square kilometres of slopes on the Minshan
Mountain on the border of Gansu and
Only about one thousand giant pandas today
survive in nature, all in 6 small blocks of
high bamboo forest in western China. The
panda exists almost entirely on a diet of
bamboo.
Sichuan provinces. The now-famous
Wolong Nature Reserve, surrounded by the
Qionglai Mountains in Sichuan Province,
accommodates about 250 giant pandas over
an area of 10,425 square kilometres. The
southern limit of the giant pandas' living
space is along the three mountain chains of
Daxiangling, Xiaoxiangling and Daliang-
shan, where some 100 of the rare animals
hide in bamboo thickets scattered over an
area of 3,300 square kilometres. All told,
there are now less than 1,000 giant pandas
in a combined area of 28,725 square
kilometres.
How have the giant pandas managed
to survive so far? Scientists from Beijing
University have reached the following con¬
clusions after studying the natural history
of the giant pandas living in the Qinling
Mountains.
In their hard-earned coexistence with the
human world over thousands of years, the
giant pandas have improved their capacity
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Zhen-Zhen ("precious" or "rare treasure"),
an elderly female panda, shows no fear as
she visits the panda studies centre estab¬
lished in the Wolong Nature Reserve
(Sichuan Province) by the Chinese Ministry
of Forestry and the World Wildlife Fund.
to endure the environmental changes
brought about by human civilization. But as
the changes became quicker and more radi¬
cal, the giant pandas could no longer keep
up the pace and were eliminated in large
numbers. However, there were times when
civilization affected the natural environ¬
ment less dramatically, and the giant pan¬
das were thus able to survive. An example
of this can be found on the southern slopes
of the Qinling Mountains.
Over 2,000 years of attempts to cultivate
the mountain slopes have yielded practical¬
ly nothing because of the harsh climate at
such a high altitude. This natural barrier
protected the giant pandas from human in¬
terference, because people stayed in the
warm temperate and sub-tropical areas be¬
low 1,400 metres. The temperate and cold
temperate forest climate above that height
has therefore become the last shelter for the
Qinling giant pandas.
Unfortunately, however, the giant pan¬
das are being deprived of their last natural
habitat as a result of irrational deforestation
prompted by the pressing needs of 1,000
million people. Today the giant pandas of
China are threatened with extinction. The
shrinking forests, the increasing failure of
the animals to multiply because of close-kin
mating within separate small groups and the
widespread starvation caused by the
periodic flowering of the bamboo which
forms their diet and which dies after blos¬
soming all these factors have worsened
the giant pandas' already serious plight.
Nature can no longer keep the giant pan¬
das alive. It is up to us to help them to
survive. Since China is the only country in
the world where giant pandas live in the
wild, the Chinese Government has taken
strict measures to protect them and is doing
all it can through legal protection and edu¬
cational programmes to help people to
realize the importance of helping these
endangered animals.
Nature reserves have been declared in 20
per cent of the areas where giant pandas
live. A panda studies centre was jointly
established by the Chinese Ministry of
Forestry and the World Wildlife Fund in
1980. Located in the Wolong Nature Re¬
serve, the centre has carried out compre¬
hensive studies into the life of the giant
pandas and worked out measures to protect
them in their natural habitats.
In 1984, scientists from Beijing Universi¬
ty made detailed observations in the Qin¬
ling Nature Reserve, hoping to find a way of
creating an ideal forest community that
would not only provide the giant pandas
with a comfortable living environment but
also yield more timber. They hope that their
work will help to ease the discord between
the giant panda and man and point the way
to harmonious coexistence in the future.B
PAN WENSHI, of the People's Republic of Chi¬
na, teaches biology at Beijing University. He is the
author ofmany studies on the giant panda, includ¬
ing a forthcoming book about the natural habitats
of the giant pandas of the Qinling Mountains.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The monkey and the leopard
An African folk tale
Africa is a mine of proverbs and folk
tales which were transmitted from gen¬
eration to generation by word of mouth
at village gatherings. Many of these
stories feature animals and communi¬
cate a message which is expressed with
humour and eloquence. "The repertoire
of folk tales seems to be ... a kind of
'unwritten Bible' bequeathed to poster¬
ity by the ancestors," notes the Camer-
oonian writer Gabriel Evouna Mfomo,
a specialist in his country's oral tradi¬
tion. The following story has been taken
from Soirées au village ("Village Eve¬
nings"), an anthology of Cameroonian
tales collected and translated into
French by Gabriel Evouna Mfomo
(Karthala publishers, Paris, 1980).
Photo A.B.Y. © Jacana, Paris
ONE day the leopard set out on a
hunting expedition. He was very
hungry, because for many nights he
had not tasted so much as a mouthful of
game. He padded softly through the forest,
his eyes glaring, his tail between his legs and
his tongue hanging out. Suddenly he fell
into a pit carefully covered with dead
leaves, which was used as a trap. He was
dumbfounded, and did not know what to
do. Should he cry out? But if he did, he
would hasten the arrival of the hunter, who
would bear him afar off and come to dis¬
patch him. He thrashed around in the bot¬
tom of the pit, springing from one side to
the other. But there was no way out!
Breathless with trying, he began to howl.
For, as he said: "Can I die in silence when I
have a voice to shout for help? Who knows?
Perhaps a brother from the tribe of quad¬
rupeds will hear me and come to rescue
me."
On the contrary! As soon as an animal
saw the leopard at the bottom of the pit, it
ran away as fast as it could, saying "What!
The leopard? Who can come anywhere
near him without risking his life? Let him
find his own solution: we all have our own
problems!"
The quadrupeds passed by in single file,
avoiding the trap: the leopard was left to his
fate in the hole.
Meanwhile, Ahem-koé, the white-nosed
monkey, was sitting on a branch of an
umbrella tree, partaking of a golden fruit
and pulling faces as he did so. He heard the
leopard's lamentations. He leaned forward
and peered into the undergrowth, but could
not descry the owner of the voice that
seemed to be issuing from the bowels of the
Earth. The monkey straightened up, lost his
balance and let himself fall to a lower level,
where he landed in a bush. He listened
carefully: real groans were emanating from
the pit. He was worried.
"What's the matter now? Who can be
groaning like that?"
He alighted on the ground, and what did
he see? A leopard, covered in mud from
head to tail, groaning at the bottom of the
pit.
"O leopard, son of my father, what are
you doing there?" asked the monkey.
The leopard spoke.
"O monkey, O son of my father, I entreat
you in kinship's name: save me! I am at
death's door! Above all, I am afraid of the
owner of the trap. If he were to find me
here, it would certainly be all up with me. O
monkey, my brother, have pity and pull me
out of the pit!"
Ahem-koé paused for a moment to think.
He was familiar with the leopard's charac¬
ter. He wanted to clear up a suspicion:
"If I pulled you out, wouldn't you be
likely to catch me?"
The leopard swore an oath:
"Never! What? Who ever dreamed of
doing such a thing?"
The monkey replied:
"Let us be clear about this. If we come to
an agreement, you give me your word of
honour."
The leopard confirmed:
"I swear it by the ancestors: Have no fear,
son of my father. Rescue me."
Still doubtful, the white-nosed monkey
wanted to be quite sure:
"Ah, but, leopard! Are you not saying
this simply because your life is in danger?
Can it really be you who is saying these
things? All the animals know how you tend
to behave. Have you ever spared an ani¬
mal's life?"
The leopard swore repeatedly that he
would mend his ways. Ahem-koé invoked
the wisdom of tradition:
"Our ancestors said: 'Death is easily
given.' They added: 'It is easy to treat an
illness, but not someone's character, be¬
cause the character sticks to its owner!'"
The leopard burst into tears. He begged:
"White-nosed monkey, son of my father,
try to pull me out of this hole and I swear to
you that the clan of the monkeys and the
clan of the leopards will form a lifelong
alliance!"
The monkey gave in.
"O leopard, you have pledged your word.
We shall see!"
Thereupon, he cut a long stick which he
laid across the pit. He sat on it and let his tail
dangle within the leopard's reach. The
leopard grabbed it and, in the twinkling of
an eye, he was out of the pit. The monkey
was still recovering his breath and was
about to ask the leopard how long he had
been in the hole when he noticed a sudden
change in the attitude of the leopard, who
was, indeed, devouring him with his eyes.
The monkey trembled inwardly; he began
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photo Verzier © Jacana, Paris
to shake all over. Timidly, he stammered:
"But why, O leopard, are you looking at
me like that? Can you never restrain your
fury?"
The freed leopard then spoke as follows:
"White-nosed monkey, have you never
learned that one person's happiness is
another's misery? Have you not learned
that the willing horse got the worst of the
bargain and has to carry human beings on
his back and be beaten by them? As for you,
true enough, you pulled me out of the pit.
But do you now expect me to starve to death
when you are right there in front of me?
You have decided to help me: let me eat
you, then!"
Ahem-koé found himself face to face
with a ferocious carnivore, with glaring
eyes, protruding tongue, tail held low,
threatening teeth and steely claws. The ter¬
ror of the forest! "So it is true," thought the
little acrobat. "The leopard has decided to
gobble me up!" He was still trying desper¬
ately to think of some means of escape when
the leopard abruptly interrupted his
thoughts:
"White-nosed monkey, have you never
heard that the lenient never prosper?"
As best he could, the monkey strove to
keep the discussion going in the hope of
postponing the evil moment. He thought
that he was saved when, walking around the
trap, a long procession of quadrupeds filed
past on their way home. As each one passed
by, he explained his dispute with the
leopard, hoping for an impartial judge¬
ment. But they were afraid of the leopard.
After all, was it not preferable that one
should die for the sake of them all? The
verdict against the monkey was unanimous:
they urged him to let himself be eaten by the
leopard. The great cat became dangerously
impatient and was no longer willing to con¬
tinue the discussion. He quoted at his victim
one last proverb from the wisdom of the
ancestors: "Prolixity is a sign of poverty!".
And he was about to spring at the primate
when all of a sudden along came the
.tortoise, laden, as always, with his heavy
shell. The antagonists called upon him to be
their final judge.
"O tortoise, son of my father," began the
monkey. "Something unbelievable has hap¬
pened to me today! I rescued the leopard
from the pit, son of my father, this pit that
you see here. And he swore not to harm me.
But as soon as I had rescued him, he saw me
as nothing but a defenceless prey. Please:
you at least can give a clear verdict. If I am
in the wrong, I will allow myself to be
eaten."
The tortoise clapped his hands in asto¬
nishment.
"Do you mean to say," he asked the
monkey, "that you managed to pull the
leopard out of the hole? Impossible! Where
did you get the strength?"
"I am not lying," answered the monkey.
"Here is the leopard himself. Ask him."
"O leopard," inquired the tortoise. "Is
the monkey telling the truth?"
"Of course what he says is true," growled
the leopard. "But that is not the point. I am
telling the monkey this: I am hungry and Í
have nothing else to eat!"
The tortoise reassured him:
"You are quite right, son of my father.
However, when I investigate a case, I do
not like to rely on hearsay; I always prefer
to have direct evidence. So this is my point
of view. We are all here, the monkey, the
leopard and myself. Here, too, are the pit
and the stick. Can you show me how you
proceeded? On your side, O leopard, you
have nothing to fear. The monkey cannot
run away. I am here to guard him."
With a bound, the leopard vanished into
the pit.
The tortoise called the monkey:
"White-nosed monkey!" he said. "Have
you never heard that a carrier of frogs will
one day carry a toad? Have you never heard
that if you kiss every tree, then one day you
will kiss a thorn tree? That if you keep
catching flies, then eventually you will catch
a bee?"
Safe and sound once more, the monkey
made the following pronouncement:
"The leopard is what he is. And Ahem-
koé is still Ahem-koé! I shall never regret
having helped someone!"
The tortoise turned to the leopard, half-
stunned at the bottom of the pit:
"Stay there in peace, son of my father.
And never forget this: our character is our
salvation; our character is also our down¬
fall!"
Naa, na hm!
Copyright © Editions Karthala, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Animals in Islam
by Abdelhamid S. Hamdan
THE two most important nights in the
Islamic year are Laylat al-Qadr (the
night of the determination), when
the Qur'an was revealed, and Laylat al-
'Isrä' wa al-Mi'räj (the night of the noctur¬
nal journey from Mecca to Jerusalem of
Muhammad, the Prophet of Islam, and of
his ascension to heaven).
How was this miraculous nocturnal jour¬
ney from Mecca to Jerusalem accom¬
plished? How could the Prophet have co¬
vered the distance so quickly? Many histo¬
rians and commentators on the Qur'an tell
us that on that night the Prophet travelled
on an animal called al-Buräq, which trans¬
ported him at such a miraculous speed that
"in a single stride it disappeared from
view". The commentators refer to this
mount as a kind of horse, described as "an
animal halfway in size between a mule and a
donkey". Some of them add that it was
white with a long back and ears. The con¬
cept of al-Buräq was later developed and
given figurative representation. At a later
stage it was even given a human face.
Al-Jähiz (died 869), a noted Arab writer
on animals, wrote in his Kitäb al-Hayawän
("Book of Animals") that there is some¬
thing marvellous about a spider because it
knows how to spin a web without receiving
any training. According to tradition, a spi¬
der saved the Prophet Muhammad at a
moment of great danger during his hijrah
(migration) from Mecca to Medina. He had
taken refuge in a cave with his travelling
companion, Abu Bakr. Perceiving a
spider's web at the entrance to the cave, the
Qurayshites who were pursuing them aban¬
doned their search because a man could not
have entered the cave without destroying
the web. The spider is thus mentioned in the
Qur'an and lends its name to the 29th sürah
(chapter).
In Arabia, the cradle of Islam, certain
domestic animals such as the horse, the
camel and the goat played an important role
in the lives of Muslims, who attributed to
' them the qualities and defects of men. The
cock, for example, was said to be generous,
the lizard deceitful, the lion courageous,
and the bustard stupid. Moreover, a num¬
ber of Arab and Turkish tribes bore animal
names, such as Asad (lion), Kalb (dog) or
Quraysh (shark). Popular superstition attri¬
buted magical powers to certain animals
which were seen as the embodiment of evil
spirits. The metamorphosis of animals into
human form occurs both in folk tales of
fantasy and among the miracles performed
by saints. Some animal species have patron
saints who often take the form of the anim¬
als they protect.
A number of animals were, and still are,
associated with the practice of magic, and
many Arab scholars have written at length
about how to interpret the appearance of
certain animals in dreams. The desert was
populated with fabulous animals such as the
ghul (gorilla), which was also the animal
form assumed by jinn (spirits) when they
wanted to approach human beings.
In pre-Islamic Arabia, jinn were the
nymphs and satyrs of the desert. They rep¬
resented that side of nature which was un¬
subdued and hostile to man. They figured
prominently in popular literature, especial¬
ly in the first part of The Thousand and One
Nights where they often transform them¬
selves into animals such as monkeys, cats or
dogs in order to act in a hostile manner
towards human beings.
As for the ghuls, although these fabulous
animals were capable of constantly chang¬
ing their guise and appearing to travellers in
the most attractive forms, they could always
be recognized by their asses' hooves. This
ability to change form and colour became
proverbial.
Other fabulous animals, mainly birds
such as the 'anqa, rukh ("roc") and
simurgh, frequently appear in folk tales.
The 'anqa, which resembled the phoenix,
was associated with the Ashäb-al-Rass, a
pre-Islamic people who fell victim to this
bird, which became a scourge. The prophet
Hanzala ben Safwän is credited with having
put an end to the 'anqa s ravages. After the
coming of Islam the 'anqa was identified
with the simurgh, which plays a role in
Iranian mythology.
Animal tales in the folklore of certain
parts of the Islamic world, especially in
North Africa, form an important part of the
oral tradition. The central role is often
played by the jackal (Ibn Äwä), half wolf,
half fox.
Zoology was never a very popular subject
with Islamic scientists, and, despite the
translation in the 9th century of Aristotle's
Historia animalium by Yahyä ben al-Bitrik,
h The simurgh, a fabulous bird which appears
? in the allegorical poem The Conference ofthe
i Birds by the Persian Sufi mystic Farid addin
m 'Attär (d. c. 1220). Drawing is based on a
i detail from a 15th-century illustrated manu-
o script of the poem.
Illustration from a manuscript of Kalila wa-
Dimna, the Arabic version of a collection of
Indian animal stories designed for the
education of princes and attributed to Bid-
pai, a legendary Indian sage. It shows a
dialogue between the King and the Bird
Fanza in which the King says, "We have
betrayed you and you have taken revenge so
that we are now even. Come back to us and
have no fear." "No," says the Bird. "I will
never come back to you."
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
uy
S* ú\ué¿&h&^>ks^Jk&^*
.
^^¿m^j^m\^w^w^
Photo (£ BOtiotheque National«. Ptnt
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
The constellations of the Centaur and the
Lion as shown in The Book ofFixed Stars, by
'Abd ar-Rahmän as-Süfí (903-986). Follow¬
ing ancient Greek tradition, the author
represented the constellations by animal or
human figures or by objects.
it occupies a rather insignificant place in the
various theoretical classifications of the sci¬
ences. It formed an integral part of the
physical and natural sciences, and al-Fârâbï
associated it with the study of the soul. This
is probably largely due to the absence of
organized research and specialized works of
a genuinely scientific character. The
monumental work on animals by al-Jähiz
referred to above is a religious work, not a
book on zoology, and it consists largely of
literary references enriched by oral tradi¬
tions. The same can be said of the Hayät
al-Hayawân (c. 1371) by ad-Damïri (died
1405) which does not offer any new classifi¬
cation, merely reproducing that of al-Jähiz.
{^WA&itrf ¡ ft JE*
v
f
. a
r
")
Physicians and naturalists were in¬
terested in animals, but the only branches of
zoology that were thoroughly and systema¬
tically studied were hippology, hippiatry
and ornithology as applied to the training of
falcons for hunting.
Many animal species figure prominently
in pre-Islamic Arabic poetry, and camels,
horses and other animals continued to be
described in Arabic poetry after the coming
of Islam. Charming verses were written ab¬
out domestic animals, especially goats, cats
and birds. In later centuries the crow and
the lion remained favourite subjects of
poetry, the former symbolizing the sadness
of separation, the latter strength and audac¬
ity ideas dear to Arabs.
Where prose is concerned, the Kalila wa
Dimna, an Arabic translation of a collec¬
tion of Indian animal fables known in
Europe as The Fables of Bidpai, was a
revelation for many people. The original
Indian work was intended to teach wisdom
to princes by means of fables told through
the mouths of animals. This new literary
genre enjoyed great popular success, soon
became part of the Arab and Islamic liter¬
ary heritage, and inspired many writers and
artists.
Representations of animals are not a
prominent feature of art in Islamic coun¬
tries, because of the aniconic and abstract
decoration characteristic of Islamic civiliza¬
tion. Each species is treated differently, in
accordance with ideas derived from liter¬
ature, from daily life, or from their symbolic
and magical significance.
As early as the Ummayad period, animal
figures were being employed for their de¬
corative qualities and to glorify the reigning
power. Animal motifs such as lions and
birds of prey appeared frequently on royal
furnishings and were used to symbolize
royal grandeur.
This taste for animal motifs later became
ever more pronounced, reaching its peak in
Iran, Iraq, and Egypt, and later in Ottoman
Turkey, where scenes from daily life (hunt¬
ing, animal rearing and training) were fre¬
quently portrayed.
Muslim painters and miniaturists also
depicted animals, but in quite a different
spirit, producing highly stylized interpreta¬
tions which were not devoid of accuracy or
even of realism.
ABDELHAMID S. HAMDAN, Egyptian special¬
ist in the history of¡slam, is the author ofa number
of scientific studies on Islam and is currently
editing a series ofArabic manuscripts on history,
science and mysticism.
©
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The private life of the vampire bat
by Marian Stamp Dawkins
Photo C.V.V. © Jacana, Paris
...and other
surprising examples
ofanimal behaviour
THERE is a tendency among many of
us to think that the human view of
the world is the only one. We be¬
come so wrapped up in our own concerns
that we may fail to notice that there is
another point of view. We may think that
the suburbs of our towns are divided up into
postal districts or sharply delineated by the
boundary between our property and our
neighbours'. But cats will divide up the
same area quite differently and small birds
such as great tits see it divided into territor¬
ies, to be fiercely defended against other
great tits, with little regard as to where
humans put their arbitrary lines of own¬
ership.
Blood-eating vampire bat of tropical Amer¬
ica (Desmodus rotundus, actual size 6-9 cm.)
The study of animal behaviour is,
perhaps more than any other branch of
biology, a window into other worlds, the
worlds of species that may be very different
from our own, and it has provided some
astonishing revelations into the private lives
of the animals concerned. Who would have
thought that vampire bats would be willing
to give each other food when they were in
Continued on page 33
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
1
y-
s
^
*
Study of vervet monkeys in Kenya's
Amboseli National Park showed that the
monkeys have different alarm calls for their
3 main predators, leopards, eagles and
snakes. Each type of call elicits a response
appropriate to the kind of predator with
which the call is associated. When the monk¬
eys hear a "leopard" call, they run for the
nearest trees; an "eagle" call causes them to
look up at the sky and head for dense scrub;
and a "snake" call has them standing on
their hindlegs peering into the long grass
around them.
©
4 Termite tower blocks
Termites build brilliantly designed "air-con¬
ditioned" nests which provide the climate
suited to their needs. The nests begin as
underground chambers and swell above
ground as the termite population grows,
eventually forming a mound up to 6 metres
high. The large population means that the
air has to be regularly purified. High humid¬
ity and temperature are also critical for
survival. The termites achieve climate con¬
trol by an elaborate system of air ducts
inside the mound through which body heat
and carbon dioxide are Filtered to the outside
walls and cool fresh air is channelled back to
the base.
2
©
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Continued from page 31
need, and also remember which bat had
done them a good turn in the past? But,
unlikely though it sounds, G.S. Wilkinson
has shown that these bats seem to realize
which of their fellows are in danger of
starvation and then give them blood meals if
they are. There is a catch, however. A bat is
more likely to provide food for another one
if, in the past, the starving bat has given
food to it. An unhelpful bat is therefore less
likely to get help itself when the need arises.
Just as unexpected were the insights into
monkey society that Dorothy Cheney and
Robert Seyfarth found when they started
watching vervet monkeys in the Amboseli
National Park in Kenya. One of the first
things they noticed was that the monkeys
make different alarm calls depending on
what sort of predator they have seen . If one
monkey has seen a snake, it warns the
others by giving a call that makes them look
down onto the ground; if it has seen a
leopard, it gives a second sort of call that
makes the others run into trees; and if it
gives the "eagle alarm" call, the other
monkeys look expectantly up into the sky.
The monkeys clearly have the ability to
"tell" each other what is going on.
More recently, the same workers have
shown that vervet monkeys are also con
noisseurs of each others' family relation¬
ships. A monkey that has recently been in
an aggressive interaction with another one
is more likely to threaten the kin of that
second monkey than before. The monkey
apparently notices who are the close associ¬
ates of the individual that is bothering him
and then takes it out on them just because
they are members of the same family!
The parallels between a group of animals
"talking" to each other about things going
on in their environment and having a de¬
tailed knowledge of each others' family re¬
lationships may be a little too close for
comfort to those who like to see a very sharp
dividing line between our own species and
any other animal. But if there is one thing
that the study of animal behaviour teaches
us, it is that the dividing line, although it
may be there, is not nearly as sharp as we
might like to think it is.
One area in which we humans tend to
think that we stand quite apart from other
animals, for example, is that of choosing a
mate. In fact, in farming, dog-breeding and
all sorts of other situations, we assume that
the animals do not care who they get as a
mate just as long as it is the right species and
that we can direct them to whatever partner
we choose. Our desire for bigger and better
bodies or more milk rides roughshod over
any preference they might have. And yet
when we look at what animals do when left
to choose mates on their own, we find that
not only are they often extremely fussy, but
that their choices, particularly those of
females, are based on the most pragmatic
considerations of social status and material
wealth in their partners.
Female spotted flycatchers (small migra¬
tory birds) have a strong preference for
males that arrive on the breeding grounds
early in the spring and set up their territor
ies before trie other males arrive. These
early arrivals tend to be the older males so
the females are apparently choosing
mature, well-established males as their
partners. However, by cleverly manipulat¬
ing the numbers of nest-boxes available in a
given area at any one time, R. Alatalo and
his colleagues in Sweden were able to show
that it was not the male himself the females
were going for, but his territory. What the
females really wanted was a safe place to
nest and this, in their view, meant an area
full of tall trees with high nest sites well out
of harm's way. If such a territory was de¬
fended by an older male, a female would
choose him, but if the territory belonged to
a younger male, he would do just as well. It
A fox investigates radio tracking apparatus
used to study foxes.
\
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
was the resources and nature of the territory
that mattered, not the male himself.
Even more mercenary are the female
hanging flies studied by Randy Thornhill in
the United States. These females simply
will not mate at all unless presented with
food. The larger the gift of insect food, the
longer the male is allowed to copulate and
the more eggs he fertilizes. The transaction
is as basic and straightforward as that.
It is clear, even from these few examples,
that the lives of many animals are of great
complexity and in some ways seem to pro¬
vide echoes of what we find in human
beings. But are we right to draw such paral¬
lels and, even if we wanted to, which anim¬
als should we look to? Do we look to our
closest living relatives, the monkeys and
apes? If so, do we see ourselves as baboons
with their male dominance hierarchies and
harems where the male disciplines his
females by biting them on the back of the
neck?. Or should we look to chimpanzees
with their promiscuous, much more egalita¬
rian society based on political alliances be¬
tween brothers and close relatives? If we
really want to draw fruitful analogies,
perhaps we should look even further afield.
After all, ants are one of the few kinds of
animal to go in for organized warfare in the
way that humans do.
In view of the enormous range of ways in
which different animals run their lives,
there are perhaps only two conclusions we
can draw with any certainty when we com¬
pare animals to humans. The first is that the
human view of survival, the choice of mate,
the rearing of young and the complexities of
social relationships is not the only one. We
share this planet with millions of other spe¬
cies whose lives, if we just take the trouble
to look into them, are full and rich in their
own right. There are other pairs of eyes
besides human ones looking out onto our
world and knowledge of that fact should
surely affect the ways we treat other species
and respond to them. It is arrogance indeed
to see our own species as the only one of
importance and, although it may dent our
human pride a little, perhaps we do have to
acknowledge that the study of animal be¬
haviour shows up parallels and similarities
in areas we might have thought were
uniquely human.
The other conclusion is essentially hope¬
ful. Most biologists believe that all animals
evolved by the process of natural selection,
which, on the face of it, appears to be a
ruthlessly selfish struggle for survival. We
might expect, therefore, to see "Nature red
in tooth and claw", as the fittest struggle to
survive and those unsuited to their environ¬
ments lose out in the competition for life.
Instead, what do we find? We find co¬
operation and collaboration, caring and
feeding of others. We find parents looking
after young, we find animals warning each
other of danger, we find even those hated
animals, vampire bats, feeding each other
when one of their number is in danger of
starvation. From the essentially selfish
struggle to survive and reproduce has
evolved co-operation and mutual aid be¬
cause these, in the long run, give both par¬
ties an advantage.
For many animals, to belong to a group
that aids them or feeds them when they are
in need gives them a better chance in life
than leading a solitary existence, even
though group membership may be at the
price of sometimes giving aid and protec¬
tion to others in return. Co-operation can
pay off. It may be co-operation born of
self-interest, but it is co-operation never¬
theless. Surely our own species, troubled
with conflict and competition, can take
some comfort in that.
MARIAN STAMP DAWKINS, British ethologist,
is Fellow in Biological Sciences al Somerville
College, Oxford, where she teaches animal be¬
haviour. Her research, carried out at the Depart¬
ment ofZoology in Oxford, is on the use ofanimal
behaviour to promote animal welfare. She is the
author o/Animal Suffering: the Science of Anim¬
al Welfare, which examines ways in which animal
suffering can be assessed, and Unravelling Anim¬
al Behaviour, an account of current problems in
ethology.
Bookshelf
Speaking of Apes: A Critical Anthology of
Two-Way Communication with Man,
edited by Thomas A. Sebeok and Jean
Umiker-Sebeok. Plenum Press, New York
& London, 1980.
Animal Communication: Techniques of
Study and Results of Research, edited by
Thomas A. Sebeok. Indiana University
Press, Bloomington, Ind. , USA, 1968.
Des animaux et des hommes, edited by
Jacques Hainard and Roland Kaehr.
Museum of Ethnography, Neuchâtel,
Switzerland, 1987.
Animal Architecture, by Karl von Frisch.
Hutchinson, London, 1974.
Purity and Danger: An Analysis of Concepts
of Pollution and Taboo, by Mary Douglas.
Routledge & Kegan Paul, London, 1966.
How to Save the World: Strategy for World
Conservation, by Robert Allen. Based on
the World Conservation Strategy prepared
by the International Union for
Conservation of Nature and Natural
Resources (IUCN), Kogan Page, London,
1980.
Life Sciences and Society, edited by
Raymond Daudel and Nicole Lemaire
D'Agaggio. Proceedings of an international
colloquium on discoveries in the biomedical
and social sciences and their impact on the
evolution and understanding of society.
Elsevier Science Publishers, Amsterdam &
New York, 1986.
nal
The Courier
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues: 62 FF
The Unesco Courier is published monthly.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the
editor. Signed articles reprinted must bear author's
name. Non-copyright photos will be supplied on
request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be
returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of Unesco or
those of the editors of the Unesco Courier. Photo
captions and headlines are written by the Unesco
Courier staff. The boundaries on maps published in
the magazine do not imply official endorsement or
acceptance by Unesco or the United Nations. The
Unesco Courier is produced in microform
(microfilm and/or microfiche) by: (1) Unesco, 7
Place dc Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2) University
Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor, Michigan 48100,
U.S. A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard Edition, Indian
Head, Inc., Ill West 40th Street, New York,
U.S.A. ; (4) Bell and Howell Co. , Old Mansfield
Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Assistant Editor-in-chief:
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
Editors:
English: Roy Malkin
Caroline Lawrence
French: Alain Lévêque
NedaelKhazen
Spanish: Francisco Fernandez-Santos
Russian:
Arabic: Abdclrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille:
Research: Violette Ringclstcin
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Scrvat
Promotion: Fernando Ainsa
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
A It correspondence should be addressed to
the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Non-Headquarters editions
German: Werner Mcrkli (Berne)
Japanese: Sciichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian: Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram BabirSharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew: Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morrcn (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefra Ilgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul ManafSaad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: PaikSyeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing)
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksancn (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: DaoTung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
34
IMPRIME EN FRANCE (Printed in France) -Dépôt légal :C1 -Février 1988
PHOTOGRAVURE-IMPRESSION : MAURY-IMPRIMEUR S.A., Z.I. route d'Etampes, 45330 MALESHERBES.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Forpeople who care about
the rest ofthe world. . .
TheCourier
The only magazine in the worldpublished in 34 languages
A monthly magazine, each issue
usually devoted to a single theme
Stimulating and informative
coverage from a wide range of
viewpoints
A window open on the world
A meeting-place for different
outlooks and cultures
A valuable source of ideas and
information on currentissues such
as development, new technologies,
human rights, and the cultural
heritage
A powerful instrument in the
service of international solidarity
and understanding
Annual subscription
1 2 issues : 90 French francs
Forthcoming issues include:
Printing and publishing. . .
from movable type
to the microchip
Forests
New light on Ancient Egypt
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the National Distributor in your country.
(See list below; names of distributors in countries not listed, along with subscription rates
in local currency, will be supplied on request.)
ALBANIA. 'Ndermarrja e perpjes se librif, Tirana. ARGENTINA. Librería el
Correo de la Unesco - ED1LYR, SRL, Tucumàn 1685, 1050 Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Books only:: Educational Supplies Pty. Ltd , P.O. Box 33,
Brookvale 2100. NSW; Periodicals: Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale 2100, NSW. Sub-agents: United Nations Association of
Australia. Victorian Division, 328 Flinders Street. Melbourne 3000-Hunter
Publications, 58a Gipps St., Collmgwood, Victoria 3066. AUSTRIA. Gerold
and Co., Graben 31, A-1011, Vienna. BAHRAIN. United Schools Interna¬
tional, Arab Regional Office. P.O. Box 726, Bahrain: The Arabian Agencies
and Distributing Co., Al Mutanabi St.. PO Box 156, Manama. BANGLADESH
Karim International. GPO Box No; 2141. 64 /I Manipuri Para. Tejgaon.
Farmgate, Dhaka. BARBADOS. University of the West Indies Bookshop,
Cave Hill Campus, P.O. Box 64. Bridgetown. BELGIUM. Jean de Lannoy, 202
Ave duRoi, 1060 Brussels BOTSWANA. Botswana Book Centre, PO Box 91
Gaborone. BRAZIL. Fundaçâo Getúho Vargas. Serviço del Publicaçoes,
caixa postal 9.042-ZC-05 Praia de Botafogo 188, Rio de Janeiro (RJ) 2000:
Books only Imagom Latinoamericana, Av. Paulista 750, 1 andar, caixa postal
30455, Sao Paulo CEP 01051. BULGARIA. Hemus, Kantora Literatura,
boulevard Rousky 6, Sofia. BURMA. Trade Corporation no. (9), 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renoul Publishing Co. Ltd.. 1294
Algoma Road, Ottawa, Ontario K1 B 3W8. (Stores: 61 Sparks Street, Ottawa,
21 1 Yonge St., Toronto. Sales office: 7575 Trans Canada Hwy. Ste. 305, St.
Laurent, Quebec H4T 1V6. CAMEROON. Cameroon Book Centre. PO Box
123. Limbe. Commission Nationale. BP 1600, Yaounde. CHILE. Editorial
Universitaria S.A., Departamento de Importaciones, M. Luisa Santander
0447, casilla 10220. Santiago; Editorial 'Andrés Bello", Av: R. Lyon 946.
Casillo 4256, Santiago de Chile; Dipublic, Antonio Varas 671 , 2o piso, casilla
14364, Correo 21, Santiago. CHINA. China National Publications Import and
Expon: Corporation, P.O. Box 88, Beijing. COLOMBIA. Instituto Colombiano
de Cultura (Colcultura). Carrera 3A. n° 18 / 24, Bogota; Books only: Librería
Buchholz Galeria, Calle 59, No; 13-13, Bogota. CYPRUS. 'MAM', Archbishop
Makanos 3rd Avene, PO Box 1722. Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S N.T.L..
Spalena 51-113 02, Prague 1; For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag.-Publishers.
Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava; PNS-UED, Jindnsska 14. praha 1;
Slovan. Gottwaldovo Nam 6, 805 32 Bratislava DEM. REP. OF YEMEN. 14th
October Corporation, PO Box 4227. Aden. DENMARK. Munksgaard Export-
OG, Tidsskriftservice. 35 Norre Sogade, DK-1970 Kobenhavn K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC Librería Blasco. Avenida Bolivar, No: 402. esq
Hermanos Deligne, Santo Domingo. EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). Un¬
esco Publications Centre, No. 1 Taiaat Harb St., Cairo. ETHIOPIA. Ethiopian
National Agency for Unesco, PO Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa. P. O. Box 128, SF-00100 Helsinki. Suomalamen
Kirjakauppa Oy, Koivuvaarankuja 2 01640 Vantaa 64. FRANCE. Librairie de
l'Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy. 75700 Pans. Periodicals only: Unesco CPD /
V-1 , rue Miollis. 75015 Pans. GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Buchex-
port, Postfach 140. Leninstrasse 16, 7010, Leipzig. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Courier: Mr. H. Baum, Deutscher Unesco-Kurier
Vertrieb, Basaltstrasse 57, D5300 Bonn 3; UNO-Verlag, Simrockstrasse 23,
D-5300 Bonn 1; S. Karger GmbH, Verlag Angerhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2
D-8034 Germering / München. For scientific maps only: Geo Center. Postfach
800830, 7000 Stuttgart 80. GHANA. Books only: Presbytenan Bookshop
Depot Ltd., PO Box 195. Accra: Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., PO 7869. Accra;
The University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape
Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, PO Box 1 , Legon. Periodicals only:
Fides Entreprises, P.O. Box 14129, Accra. GREAT BRITAIN. See United
Kingdom. GREECE. Eleftheroudakis SA, International Bookstore. 4 Nikis
Street. Athens: John Mihalopouios & Son SA, International Booksellers, P.O.
Box 10073, 541 10 Thessaloniki. Greek National Commission for unesco, 3
Akadimias Street, Athens. HONG KONG. Swindon Book Co., 13-15 Lock
Road. Kowloon; Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., Tokwawan, Kowloon; Hong
Kong Government Information Services, Publication Section, Hong Kong;
Periodicals only: Beaconsf ield House 6th floor, Queen's Road Central, Victor¬
ia. HUNGARY. Kultura-Bushimport-ABT. P.O.B. 149-H-1389, Budapest 62.
ICELAND. Snaebjorn Jonsson and Co., H.F. Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longman Ltd., Kamam Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay 400038:
17 Chitaranjan Ave., Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai, Mount Road, Madras 2:
5-9-41/1 Bashir Bagh. Hyderabad 500001 (AP); 80/1 Mahatma Gandhi Rd.,
Bangalore 560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda, Hyderabad-500001. Sub-agents:
Oxford Book and Stationery Co., 1 7 Park St., Calcutta 7001 6; Sandia House.
New Delhi 11 0001. INDONESIA. Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29.
J1, Oto Iskandardmata 111, Jakarta; Indira P.T., Jl Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37,
Jakarta Pusat. IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1 188 Englab
Ave., Rostam Give Building. P.O. Box 11365-4498, Teheran 13158.
IRELAND.Periodica/so/i/y:The Educational Company of Ireland Ltd., PO Box
43A, Walkmstown, Dublin 1 2; Booksonly: TDC Publishers. 1 1 North Frederick
Street, Dublin 7. ISRAEL. Literary Transactions. Inc., tío Steimatzky Ltd.,
P.O. Box 628, Tel Aviv; A B C. Bookstore Ltd., P.O. Box 1283, 71 Allenby Rd.,
Tel Aviv 61 000. ITALY. Licosa (Librería Commissionaria Sansoni. S.p.A ). Via
Lamarmora 45. Casella Postale 552, 50121 Florence; via Bartolmi 29. 20155
Milan; FAO Bookshop, via délie Terme di Caracalia, 001 00 Rome. JAMAICA.
University of the West Indies Bookshop, Mona, Kingston 7. JAPAN. Eastern
Book Service Inc.. 37-3 Hongo 3-chome Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113. JORDAN
Jordan Distribution Agency, PO Box 375. Amman. Periodicals only Jordan
Book Centre Co. Ltd., PO Box 301 , Al Jubeiha, Amman. KENYA. East African
Publishing House, PO 30571, Nairobi: Africa Book Services Ltd. Quran
House. Mangano Street. PO Box 45245, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd. POB 2942, Kuwait; Periodicals only: Farafalla Press
Agency. P.O. Box SAFA 4541 . Kuwait. LEBANON. Librairie Antoine A. Naufal
et Frères, BP 656, Beirut. LESOTHO Mazenod Book Centre, PO Mazenod,
Maseru. LIBERIA National Bookstore, Mechlin and Carey Streets, PO Box
590, Monrovia: Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd.. PO Box 286, Monrovia.-
LUXEMBOURG. Books only: Librairie Paul Brück. 22. Grande-Rue, Luxem¬
bourg; Periodical: Messageries Paul Kraus, BP 1022, Luxembourg. MALAWI
Malawi Book Service, Head Office, PO Box 30044, Chichiri, Blantyre 3.
MALAYSIA. University of Malaya Co-operative Bookshop, Kuala Lumpur
22-1 1 . MALTA. Sarpienzas, 26 Republic St.. Valletta. MAURITANIA GRA.LI.-
CO.MA., 1 rue du Souk X, Avenue kennedy, Nouakchott. MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30 Bourbon St., Port-Louis. MEXICO. Librería El
Correo de la Unesco, Actipán 66. Colonia del Valle, Apartado postal 61 164,
06600 Mexico DF. MONACO. British Library, 30 Bd. des Moulins, Monte
Carlo. MORROCCO. Librairie 'Aux belles images', 282 ave. Mohammed-V,
Rabat; Librairie des écoles, 12 ave, Hassan-ll, Casaglanca; Société chenfien-
ne de distribution et de presse. SOCHEPRESS. angle rues de Dînant et St.
Saens, BP 13683. Casablanca 05. MOZAMBIQUE. Instituto National do Livro
e do Disco (INLD), avenida 24 de Julho, 1921 r / d Io andar, Maputo. NEPAL.
Sajha Prakashan Polchowk, Kathmandu. NETHERLANDS. Books only:
Keesing, Boeken B.V., Hogehilweg 13, Postbus 1 118, 1000 BC Amsterdam.
Periodicals: Faxon Europe, P.O. Box 197, 1000 AD Amsterdam.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. Van Dorp-Eddine N.V.. PO Box 200, Willem-
stad. Curaçao, NA. NEW ZEALAND. Government Publishing, P.O. Box
14277-Kilbirnie, Wellington. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of lie; The
University Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286;The University Bookshop of Nsukka;
The University Bookshop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello University Bookshop of
Zana. NORWAY. Johan Grundt Tanum, P.O.B. 1177 Sentrum - Oslo 1;
Universitets Bokhandelen, Universitetssentret, Postboks 307 Blindem, Oslo
3; Periodicals only: Narvesen A/S, Litteralurt Jenesten, P.O.B. 61 25 Etterstad.
N 0602 Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65 Shahrah Quaid-i-azam,
P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3; Unesco Publications Centre, Regional Office for
Book Development in Asia and the Pacific, 39 Delhi Housing Society, P.O. Box
8950. Karachi 29. PANAMA. Distribuidora Cultura Internacional, Apartado
7571, Zona 5, Panama. PHILIPPINES. National Book Store Inc.. 701 Rizal
Avenue, Manila. POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kultury I Nauki. Warsaw; Ars
Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.7. 00-068 Warsaw. PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrade Ltda. Livrana Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. ROMANIA.
ARTEXIM Export-Import, Piata Scienteii, no. 1, PO Box 33-16, 70005
Bucharest. SAUDI ARABIA. Dar al Watan. Olaya Main Street, Ibrahim Bin
Sulaym Building, Riyadh. SEYCHELLES. New Service Ltd., Kmgsgate
House, PO Box 1 31 , Mahé; National Bookshop, PO Box 48, Mahé. SIERRA
LEONE. Fourah Bay College, Njala University and Sierra leone Diocesan
Bookshops, Freetown. SINGAPORE. Righteous Enterprises, P.O. Box 562,
Kallang Basin Post Office, Singapore 9133. SOCIALIST PEOPLE'S LIBYAN
ARAB JAMAHIRIYA. General Establishment for Publishing, Distribution and
Advertising, Souf Al Mahmoudi St., PO Box 959. Tripoli. SOMALIA. Modern
Book Shop and General, PO Box ùàô. Mogadiscio SPAIN. Mundi-Prensa
Libros SA, apartado 1223, Castelló 37, Madrid 1; Ediciones Liber, apartado
17, Magdalena 8, Ondárroa (Vizcaya): Donaire, Ronda de Outeiro, 20,
apartado de correos 341, La Coruña; books only: Librería Castells. Ronda
Universidad 13 y 15, Barcelona 7; Librería de la Generalität de Catalunya.
Palan Moja. Rambla de los Estudios 118, 08 002 Barcelona SRI LANKA.
Lake House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata. P.O.B. 244,
Colombo 2. SUDAN. Al Bashir Bookshop, P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SURINAME. Suriname National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box 2943,
Paramaribo. SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Regenng-
sgatan 12, Box 16356, S-103 27 Stockholm 16: For the Unesco Courier:
Svenska FN Förbundet, Skolgrand 2, Box 150 50 S-104, 65 Stockholm; For
penodfca/son/y.Wennergren-WilliamsAB, Nordenflychtsvagen 70, S-104, 25
Stockholm; Esselte Tidskriftscentralen, Gamla Brogatan 26, Box 62 -101, 20
Stockholm. SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich: Librairies
Payot in Geneva Lausanne, Basle, Berne, Vevey, Montreux, Neuchâtel and
Zürich. SYRIA. Aleppo University Books Establishment, University of Aleppo,
Aleppo. TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030. Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd.. 40-42 Charoen Krung Road,
Siyaeg Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402, Bangkok; Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Ave., Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road,
Bangkok; ROEAP, PO Box 1425. Bangkok 10500. TRINIDAD AND TOBA¬
GO. National Commission for Unesco, 18 Alexandra St., St. Clair, Port-of-
Spam. TURKEY. Haset Kitapevt A S., Istiklâl Caddesi, No 469. Posta Kutusu
21 9, Beyoglu. Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop. PO Box 7145, Kampa¬
la. UNITED ARAB EMIRATES. Maktabat al Maktaba, PO Box 15408, Al Am,
Abu Dhabi. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, PO Box 276, London,
SWS 5DT; H.M. S.O. Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham. Bristol; Third World Publications, 151 Stratford Road, Birming¬
ham B11 1RD; for scientific maps only: McCarta Ltd., 122 King's Cross Rd.
London WC1X 9DS. UNITED STATES OF AMERICA. Bernan-UNIPUB.
Periodicals Department, 461 1-F Assembly Drive, Lanham, MD 20706 4391
URUGUAY. Ediciones Trecho. S.A., Maldonado 1092. Montevideo. USSR.
V/O Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga, Ul. Dimitrova 39, Moskva 113095.
YUGOSLAVIA. Mladost, Mica 30/11, Zagreb; Cankarjeva Zalozba, Zopitar-
ieva 2. Lubljana: Nolit. Terazije 13/ VIII, 11000 Belgrade; periodicals only:
Jugosolvena Kniga, PO Box 36, YU 11001 Belgrade. ZAMBIA. National
Educational Distribution Co. of Zambia Ltd., P.O. Box 2664. Lusaka.
ZIMBABWE. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 1 Norwich Union Centre, Harare.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
</document>
