<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078148eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Jí m
JANUARY
19 5 6
(9th year)
Price : 9d. (U. K.)
40 francs (France)
.'-"»*"
, gg&o¡tf<aM'!ji
ïïl
/
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TOWARDS NEW HORIZONS. A last
wave as a ship leaves Bremerhaven,
Germany, carrying refugees to a new
life across the seas. But the elderly
woman on the dockside symbolizes a
problem that remainsthe resettlement
of 350,000 refugees still left in Europe.
Copyright Yvan Dalain
-
^00*
,1*,*«CS*?mi
1 Wfc ' ' '
mm ##
- ma ¿mS*,"*'.U»^, «¿JS***
:^ÎFS*»"
J*»*;^rw *«£:
-*~*^Sfe^to^Jy * "-. ..,#s»s<
*«****> <#..
'tina?" ..,.. 	
. -*-l¿á3SKL
y****,». . , * tK«-*:
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
JANUARY - 1956
9th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 EDITORIAL
4 NOBEL PEACE PRIZE FOR U.N. REFUGEE OFFICE
5 MIRACLE AT TINOS
Isolation ends for island refugees
10 THE UPROOTED
40,000,000 refugees: a staggering world problem
By James Douglas
16 MODERN 'FLYING DUTCHMEN*
Sailors "chained" to their ships
By Louise de Béa
17 THE SAGA OF FRIDTJOF NANSEN
Great explorer, champion of refugees
18 BIGGEST MIGRATION IN HISTORY
Millions on the march between India and Pakistan
21 GOOD NEIGHBOURS 'DOWN UNDER'
Welcoming New Australians to the Island-Continent
By H.B.M. Murphy
23 EXODUS IN REVERSE
Refugee farmers revive a dying French village.
OTHER ARTICLES AND FEATURES
26 THE STEEL AXE THAT DESTROYED A TRIBE
Upheavals in the life of an Aborigine people
By Alfred Metraux
28 A MISSION GOES TO THE DEVIL...
... to build a school in Liberia
By Daniel Behrman
30 PAINTING WITH WAX AND FIRE
Artists and scientists probe secrets of encaustic art
By L. and G. Attinelli
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
35 A WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
Table of contents for 1955
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organi¬
zation
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
U:S.A. : Henry Evans
Individual articles not cop/righted may be reprinted from THE UNESCO
COURIER but must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted
from UNESCO COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's
name. Prints of non-copyright photos are available on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an inter¬
national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE UNESCO
COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE UNESCO COURIER : 8/-: S 2.00 or 400
French frs or equivalent (U.S. edition $ 2.50) (MC. 55.1 98. A)
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
COVER PHOTO
This old man is one of the 350,000 re¬
fugees in Europe who have not yet found
a place or a country where they can
establish themselves permanently. Some
I 20,000 of these refugees are living in
camps in Germany, Austria, Italy and
Greece. International protection is ex¬
tended to all by the Office of the
U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees.
UNATIONS
T
he Oxford English Dictionary defines a refugee as:
"One who, owing to religious persecution or political
troubles, seeks refuge in a foreign country", and adds
that the word was first applied to the French Huguenots
who came to England after the revocation of the Edict of
Nantes in 1685. Two years later, John Evelyn in his Diary
spoke of the "poor and religious refugees who escaped out
of Prance in the cruel persecution."
The problem therefore has a long history. Since the
17th century the world has seen successive waves of people
driven from their countries through religious or political
persecution. It is still with us today.
Between the two World Wars the classic definition of a
refugee was a person who "had sought refuge in a terri¬
tory other than that in which he was formerly resident as
a result of political events which rendered his continued
residence in his former territory impossible or intolerable."
But the Second World War and post-war political develop¬
ments rapidly out-dated this description and made a new,
more topical definition necessary.
In July 1951 the Convention Relating to the Status of
the Refugee was adopted at a conference attended by
28 States. This Convention which is the most compre¬
hensive codification of the rights of refugees so far
attempted on an international level, laid down that the
"status of refugee" would apply to a person who "owing
to well-founded fear of being persecuted for reasons of
race, religion, nationality, membership of a particular
social group or political opinion is outside the country of
his nationality and is unable or, owing to such fear, is
unwilling to avail himself of the protection of that
country" (and who for similar reasons)... "is unwilling to
return to it."
But behind all this legal phraseology looms the tragic
human problem of the men, women and children who are
today without roots and without work. Whatever the
definition applied, it is important to remember that the
refugee is first and foremost a human being. As Dr. G.J.
van Heuven Goedhart, the United Nations High Commis¬
sioner for Refugees, has said: "We should never fail to see
him behind our documents, papers and discussions. We
should always be aware of him as a man who, in his little
bundle with which he crosses the ' border, carries a
-tremendously important decision the decision to leave
everything which was dear to him and walk into an
unknown Tuture with a deep confidence in freedom, and
in the reception which he will have in the free world. The
refugees are looking for shelter, work and the chance to
live decently. They are valuable, . courageous and in¬
dustrious human beings."
The problem today is world-wide. There are certainly
no less than 30 million, and there may be as many as
40 million refugees in the world. The solution of this
human tragedy is a task of staggering magnitude.
At this time, when the Office of the U.N. High Commis¬
sioner for Refugees has just received the Nobel Peace
Prize for its work, the Unesco Courier has made an
assessment of the refugee problem as it stands in 1956.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE NOBEL
PEACE PRIZE
Honours work of
U.N. Refugee Office
The Nobel Peace Prize for 1954 has just been awarded to
the Office of the United Nations High Commissioner for
Refugees, headed by Dr. G.J. van Heuven Goedhart
of the Netherlands. On December, 10, 1955, the High
Commissioner spoke at the prize-award ceremony in
Oslo. Below are some passages from his speech.
Gerrit Jan van Heu¬
ven Goedhart, of the
Netherlands, is an LL.D.
of Leyden University.
Before the Second
World War he was
editor of two well-
known Dutch news¬
papers. In 1941 he went
" underground " and
edited the then illicit,
"HetParool".ln1944he
escaped to Great Bri¬
tain via Belgium, France
Spain and Gibraltar and
shortly after his arrival
in London was appoint¬
ed Minister of Justice
in the Netherlands Gov¬
ernment-in-exile. After
the war he resumed
the editorship of "Het
Parool" which post he
held until 1950. Dr. van Heuven Goedhart has
represented his country at U.N. conferences and
was Vice-Chairman of thé Netherlands Delegation
to the 4th and 5th sessions of the U.N. General
Assembly. He was appointed U.N. High Commis¬
sioner for Refugees for a three-year term with
effect from January 1 1951. Upon expiry the term
of office was renewed by the U.N. General Assem¬
bly for a further five years.
\ \ hat have refugees got to do with peace? Many
people may have asked themselves this question on
hearing that the Nobel Peace Prize had been awarded
to an international office working on behalf of refugees.
The answer, according to the U.N. High Commissioner,
can be found in the life of Alfred Nobel himself. There
were, he said, very definite links between Nobel's ideas
and those which are at the root of any constructive
refugee programme.
"My colleagues and I my¬
self," said Dr. van Heuven
Goedhart, "are very much
aware of the fact that it is
not the first time that the
existence of such a link
seems to have been recogniz¬
ed by the Nobel Committee
of the Norwegian Storting in
its deliberations regarding
the award to be made.
Forty-three years after the
death of Nobel in 1895, the
Nobel Prize for Peace was
awarded to the Nansen Office
for Refugees. That happen¬
ed eight years after that
great Norwegian, Fridtjof
Nansen, died, but during his
lifetime the Nobel Committee
had already given proof of
its awareness of the "indivi¬
sibility of a reasonable no¬
tion of peace" by awarding
in 1922 the Nobel Prize for Peace to Nansen personally.
"Peace has been rightly described as much more than
just the absence of war. It is rather a state in
which no people of any country, in fact no group
of people of any kind, lives in fear or in need. Real peace
is therefore an ideal to be pursued by mankind, relentlessly
and with unflagging perseverance, but at the same time
an ideal which mankind can never realize to the full
extent. Alfred Nobel certainly was aware of the indivisi¬
bility of peace and of its all-embracing character. I would
4
WHAT IS THE OFFICE OF THE U.N. HIGH
COMMISSIONER FOR REFUGEES? It is
not a specialized agency but part of the
United Nations itself. Established at the
end of 1950 by the U.N. General Assembly,
the Office originally had a mandate for
three years since extended to the end
of 1958. The High Commissioner is assist-
ted by a Deputy, Mr. James M. Read,
of the United States, and an international
staff numbering 130, working at the Geneva
headquarters and in 14 branch offices.
Eleven of these offices are located in
Europe and one each in the Middle East,
Latin America and North America. Joint
offices with the Intergovernmental Com¬
mittee for European Migration are also
maintained in Hong Kong and Shanghai.
like on this sixtieth commemoration of his death to pay
tribute to his memory.
"During its five years' lifetime our office has had to
fight on at least two fronts. On the one hand there was
the necessity of convincing the governments that there
was still an unsolved refugee problem of considerable
magnitude left after the International Refugee Organiza¬
tion closed its doors. On the other hand there was the
necessity of persuading the
governments to make contri¬
butions to the United Nations
Refugee Fund, which is the
financial basis of the four-
year programme for per¬
manent solutions for refugee
problems and for emergency
aid to needy refugees.
"Given the fact that today
there are, mainly in Europe,
but also in the Near and Far
East still hundreds of thou¬
sands of refugees who so far
have not been able to find a
solution to their difficulties
there can be no doubt about
the necessity of a programme
such as the one we are in the
process of carrying out.
"But whereas we may say
that the first battle to get
recognition of the fact that
the problem still existed and
that something had to be done about it has been won,
the second oneito obtain the necessary contributions for
the carrying out of our four-year-programme is still
undecided.
"So far the response of governments to our appeals for
funds has been disappointing. It is therefore for this
reason that we are deeply grateful for the encouragement
given to our Office through the award of the Nobel Prize
for Peace, encouragement which will also affect the
governments themselves:".
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
AT TINOS
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
Copyright Ernst Haas, Magnum
F
OR the past five or six years
125 refugees of Greek stock from
Eastern Europe have been living in the
refugee centre on the Greek Island
of Tinos. Soon they will all have been
resettled elsewhere with homes and
jobs thanks to the special Nobel
Peace Prize Project which has just
been announced by the Office of the
U.N. High Commissioner for Refu¬
gees. The Nobel prize money
about $35,000 recently awarded
to the Refugee Office will be used
to close down this isolated centre.
For the refugees this will indeed
seem a miracle The island of Tinos,
however, is celebrated for another,
very different, miracle. Every year
thousands of pilgrims come to pray
for good health before the Holy
Ikon, discovered on the island In 1 822.
Above, a Greek priest mounts Cathe¬
dral steps with aged and crippled
pilgrims. Left, all eyes are turned
towards the Holy Ikon The story on
the following pages by a chance visi¬
tor to Tinos conveys something of
the former despair and hopeless¬
ness felt by the island refugees.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
MIRACLE
AT TINOS
(Continued)
REFUGEE RATIONS
Soup, bread, an onion
and a handful of olives.
A daily living allowance
equivalent to 20 U.S.
cents is also provided.
.¡km
:
V / 1**b|
ip¿frnWrnZ^** ^0uWS
UÂdM
j^^r
UNREF
JL ihey all want to go to America, all 200 of them.
They have been here now seven years. They haven't got
anything to do and we can't do anything with them."
"Who are 'they'?" asked Ronald Doyle, an American
photographer who had just arrived on the Greek island
of Tinos.
The owner of the Hotel Poseidon made a movement
with his chin towards the house on the other side of the
street.
"In that building refugees. God help them. We
haven't enough work for our own people on this island,
let alone for these foreigners."
After he had unpacked his bags and washed his hands,
Ronald walked on to the balcony and looked out. On the
other side of the street he saw the boy who had helped
him to carry his bags up from the port leaning against a
wall, obviously waiting for him to appear. He gave
another look at the harbour then went inside, picked up
his photographic equipment, gave a quick glance at the
prospectus about Tinos and left the hotel.
The boy joined him without a word and Ronald gave
him his 'flashgun to carry as if it had been agreed
between them.
They walked up the long cobbled road, arrived in
front of the cathedral, climbed the steps
and went in. It was dark inside and they
had to wait until their eyes got used to
the gloom.
Suddenly Ronald noticed a girl in
prayer. She looked very attractive with
her dark hair, wide eyes and soft curving
lips. She was poorly dressed, but there
was an air of dignity about her that
impressed him.
As she left, Ronald followed her. He
was wondering whether he might take
some photographs of her to illustrate life
on the island, but when he reached the
exit he saw her run swiftly down the hill
and disappear into a busy street.
As they returned to the hotel, the young
boy, whose name he had discovered was
Peter, took Ronald by the hand.
"Please, mister, you see my 'father and
mother ?"
Ronald smiled his agreement. He felt
the boy wanted his earnings to be given
to his parents. They turned into the
backyard of the refugee centre. It was
mealtime. Men, women and children,
carrying tin plates and bowls with thin
soup, some onions, olives and bread,
crossed from the central kitchen to the
kitchen to the main building.
The photographer gave a closer look
at the food. It didn't seem much to
live on.
The boy and the man climbed the stairs to the second
floor and walked down a long corridor. The boy opened
a door: a man of about 50 was standing near the table,
ready to go out with bowls and plates. The mother was
busy with a baby of a 'few months old in a little cot near
the door. A girl of about seven was looking out of the
window. Everybody turned to stare at the visitor.
The boy spoke in a Slav language. The man put down
his bowls and plates and came forward with outstretched
hands.
"Mr. America, welcome," he said. "I am Vladimir Papa-
poudos." He offered a chair but Ronald shook his head.
"I am sorry, I cannot stay", he explained. "'I am expect¬
ing a telephone call at the hotel."
At that moment the door was flung open and a man
aged about 35 burst in. He had long black hair that
needed cutting, and a stubbly beard. His shirt was
collarless and there were stains on his coat. He gripped
Ronald by his tie and started shouting furiously in a mix¬
ture of languages. Ronald thought he heard him say
"espion, espion" but everyone was talking at once, and
Peter's 'father and mother were tugging at the man. The
stranger suddenly sat down and put his head in his hands.
"He thought you were secret agent because you photo¬
graph his sister," explained Mr. Papapoudos. "He afraid
for his parents, but we explain you American ; it is all
right now." "My friend Sternen," he added, "speaks no
English. He speaks French. He is our doctor."
You won't make the headlines
At this moment the door opened and Mrs. Papapoudos
came in carrying food from the central kitchen.
Father Papapoudos insisted that Ronald should eat
with them, but he shook his head.
"I must go now," he said. "They are telephoning me
from Athens."
On one of the staircases Ronald saw a notice board with
old, torn announcements from the International Refugee
Organization, and a little type-written letter flapping in
the wind saying : "The Representative of the United
Nations High Commissioner for Refugees will call on the
27th of this month." It was typed in three languages :
English, French and Greek.
The following day as Ronald came down to breakfast
he saw Mr. Papapoudos with three men standing in the
hotel hall. They greeted him. One was the President
of the Refugees' Association and the others were members
of the Committee. The President spoke good English. He
explained that everybody in the centre had been very
excited when they heard that an American journalist had
"' -fc
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
come to Tinos to take photographs. Young Peter had told
them that the American was working for a big paper and
now everyone was hoping that he would publish articles
about them in the American press so something would
be done to help them.
Ronald felt embarrassed. He invited the men to have
breakfast with him and while they ate, he tried to
explain to them that he had come to Tinos on a special
mission for a tourist and geographical paper. Even if
he took photographs of the refugees he wasn't certain
that any newspaper would print them.
"You see," he said, "the papers only buy a story when
it is about a disaster."
"But isn't this a disaster?" asked the President. "We
have been seven years on this island and unless somebody
takes us away we must die here. We haven't even enough
money to go and look for work in Athens!"
Ronald did not know what to answer. He allowed him¬
self to be guided round the island by the four men. Out-
DOUBT AND DESPAIR, here so clearly written on the faces of these refugees has now
been effaced. For over six years they have longed for a real home and a chance to work.
They were called the "forgetten men of Tinos," but soon they will be leaving the island where
they have waited so long. Some will be resettled overseas, some will find sanctuary in
homes for old people, but all will leave the island and years of isolation behind them.
side the town one of the two members of the Committee
took up a handful of earth.
"I was a farmer once," he said, "and I would love to go
back to the land, but here, on this island, there is no land
free. If there were, several of our families could make
a living out of it."
When the group passed the fishing boats in the
harbour, another man broke the silence. "Now and then I
am allowed to go out with them," he said, "in the tourist
season when there are people who will buy our fish.
Mind, if I had my own nets and could hire my own boat I
think I could make a living."
"Why don't you?" asked Ronald.
"Where could I get the money?" retorted the refugee.
"Couldn't you raise a loan?"
The men laughed without mirth. "Without security?"
they asked. "You don't know the banks."
As they returned they saw Sternen. By him sat the girl
Ronald had seen in the cathedral.
The President who, by this time, had talked himself
into a state of excitement, gripped Sternen by the arm
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
and said "We are all useless here, cut off from the world."
He pointed. "Look at him a doctor, a surgeon. He may
not work. He may not go away. Look at his sister. She
has TB. They thought they would be going to America
once but now that is out of the question too..."
"Why?" asked Ronald.
"Because that is the way of the world" said the Presi¬
dent. "If you are not healthy or if you are too old, you
cannot go. All of us want to live in America or Canada
or anywhere, but all we can get is promises and nothing
ever happens."
"But is there no one who will help you?" asked Ronald.
"Surely there must be. What about this Representative of
the United Nations High Commissioner?"
"He takes notes and makes plans," said the leader, "but
he has no money, and what can you do when you haven't
any money?"
"How do you live, then?" asked Ronald.
Father Papapoudos, who had kept silent all this while,
now spoke. "We get food from the Government," he said.
"They pay for light and fuel and the
High Commissioner also gives us some¬
thing." He turned out his pockets. "But
we never have a penny in our pocket, we
can never buy a cigarette, we can never
buy a glass of wine. And we must always
wear the old clothes that people send us."
Woman without a future
The faces of the men looked tense,
even threatening.
"Is there nothing you can do to
help yourselves?" asked Ronald.
"There is something we do," said the
President. "Better come along." They
walked through the streets of the old
town and stopped near the Cathedral
where a woman sat selling embroidered
table runners and carved model ships.
"It pays for the milk for the babies and
our old people, but we haven't got enough
thread or material to make a business out
of it," said the President.
In the middle of the street, he suddenly
turned round. "Will you help us now?"
he asked.
"Let's go to the Centre," said Ronald
With great, hurried steps the President
led the group back down the street to the
refugee centre.
They went and sat in the room occupied
by Katia and her brother, Sternen. "You
see," Ronald explained to them, "with
photographs, it is like with a film. You
have got to take the story of a few people.
By telling their story, the public is made
to feel that the needs are not only those
of a few but of many." Turning to Katia,
he said, "I will tell your story and I will
photograph it to make the people see It
happening to you as if it were happening to themselves."
The girl nodded her head.
"What do you want me to do?" she asked.
"I want you to re-enact your life here since you came
to Tinos."
"That was years ago," said Katia. "We came here a few
weeks after we arrived in Greece. We were told that this
was the only place where there was still room left. Even
so, we found the refugee centre packed and we had to
share a room with another family.
"The first week we came here we met Mrs. Korianovi, a
social worker from a voluntary agency, to whom we gave
all our particulars. I was a student; Sternen was a doctor.
I spoke fluent English; he spoke fluent French. We were
willing to do any work as long as we could remain
together. We filled in forms and we waited.
"I thought I would use the waiting time to give English
lessons to the children in the camp, but even
the grown-ups came, all of them hoping that (Cont'd on
one day they would be able to leave. next page)
UNREF
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
MIRACLE
AT TINOS
(Continued)
'Post Office' says the sign on the
wall of this whitewashed building
in Tinos in reality the "provi¬
sional" camp where 125 refugees
have lived crowded together for
years. Their hopes of leaving it
will now be realized thanks to the
money from the Nobel Peace Prize.
J J
"There was Mr. Zamanov, his wife and his mother.
Mr. Zamanov's mother was too old for emigration and he
didn't want to leave her behind, but he had never told her
that this was the reason, and old Mrs. Zamanov came to
listen to me and to try to speak English. She spoke lightly
of 'when we are in America' and I think it hurt me most to
see that old woman speaking about a future everyone knew
she didn't have.
"There was also Miss Domnavico who couldn't emigrate
because she was an unmarried mother. There was Profes¬
sor Zuliakus who couldn't go anywhere because no country
seemed to need a philosopher; and there was Pravdec
who was a plumber who didn't know why no country
wanted him. They were good students and yet, as time
went by, I began to wonder... what use was I to them,
teaching a language in which they could say 'I want to
go to a new country', when no country seemed to want
them.
Damning X-Ray shadow
ffjT was about two years after we came to Tinos that,
-I one day, Mrs. Korianovi called us into her office.
She seemed excited and very happy. A doctor in
Chicago had agreed to sponsor us. The American Consul
was working on our papers and soon we would hear from
him. Indeed, a few weeks later we were called to Athens
for an interview. We signed the papers and then went
to see a doctor for a final medical check-up.
"I'll never forget that day. We had been waiting for
the X-ray picture. We went to see the doctor in high
spirits. The doctor asked me to sit down and pointed
to a light shadow on the negative on the viewer. 'I am
afraid I have rather bad news for you' he said. 'Do you
see this? It's a patch on the lung.' It wasn't active TB,
he told me-nothing, in fact, that couldn't be put right
with rest and good food but it was sufficient to prevent
the visa being given. Stemen and I were heartbroken. I
told Stemen to go to America alone but he wouldn't do it
and I felt very badly about it. We even quarrelled, but
Stemen wouldn't budge. I think that is what hurts me
most. Because of me, there is no future for Stemen."
The next day was the 27th of the month the day when
the U.N representative was due to visit the Island. In
the morning, as Ronald was crossing the quay he saw
the President boarding a boat and talking to a group of
men. The group landed. The leader held up his hands.
"You all know the Representative of the United Nations
High Commissioner," he said. "He wants to say a few
words."
The representative stepped forward.
"This time I have come with a Selection Mission from
two European countries," he said. "The High Commis¬
sioner has made an appeal to close the camps, and a fund
has now been established with which we hope to help
many of you. We are trying to place as many of you as
we can in other countries. To start on our work, will all
of you come for an interview this afternoon?"
"We shall proceed by alphabetical order" said the Presi¬
dent. "Everyone should go back to the camp and get his
papers.1"
The refugees lined up outside the hotel formed a pathe¬
tic picture, each man and women clutching some papers
in their hands. Tense expressions were on their faces,
and few words were spoken. The President acted as
doorman and ushered one family in after the other.
Ronald watched them for a moment and then became
aware that neither Katia nor Stemen was there.
Ronald walked across the street into the empty build¬
ing, along the corridor, looking into each empty room
with its poor contents. Finally, he found the brother
and sister in their room. Katia was standing near the
window looking out. Stemen was lying on his bed
smoking one of the cigarettes Ronald had given him.
"What are you doing here?" asked Ronald. "Why
aren't you downstairs?"
Katia turned round. She looked at him for a long time.
"You know I have TB."
Stemen went on smoking. He didn't say anything.
"That is no reason," said Ronald. "You should go
downstairs and meet these men. What have you got to
lose?"
Katia shook her head.
"I have filled in enough forms!" she said.
"But don't you understand?" shouted Ronald. "If you
won't go Stemen won't go, and if he doesn't go, you will
both lose your chance of ever leaving this damned spot.
You have no right to be so selfish."
UNREF
REFUGEE STUDENT was a young girl when she arrived in Tinos. As
she copies the maps of the Americas, her mind is already far from the
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N' 1. 1956
Stemen got up and looked at him.
"Va-t'en get out!"
'Va-t'en" he said.
But Katia ran forward and held Stemen by his arm.
She looked at Ronald. "You are right/' she said, "We
should go down".
It was now the turn of Katia and Stemen.
"I want you to understand" said the Representative of
the High Commissioner, "that we are trying to help you,
that even if we cannot help you this time we may perhaps
be able to do something later on. These two gentlemen"
he pointed to the two men sitting on either side of him
"are from the Ministries of Labour of two different
countries, and the gentleman on your left is a doctor. We
want to find out whether there is a chance for you to start
life here in Greece or whether we should concentrate on
getting you to another country. From your flies we've seen
that Miss Staminova needs hospital treatment. We will
try to arrange it for her either here in Greece or abroad.
What I want you to do now is to answer truthfully the
questions these gentlemen are going to put to you. Is that
understood?" Both Stemen and Katia nodded.
In the evening Katia and Stemen were both in their
room. Stemen sat on the bed. Katia had her elbows on
the table. They didn't speak. There was a knock. The
door opened and two men came in with smiles on their
faces. One, who had been introduced to them as the
doctor, called a friendly "Hello, doctor" to Stemen and
went to stand in front of the table. He looked at Katia
and took a little St Christopher medal from his pocket
which he placed before her.
"This is what we give to travellers in our country", he
said, "before they set out on their journey. May it bring
you good luck on your trip."
Tears of happiness filled Katia's eyes as she looked at
this symbol of a new future.
John Defrates
island. For pious Greeks, Tinos is an island of pilgrimage. They visit
it to pray before its Holy Ikon for relief from sickness and infirmity.
Round-The-World Report
rjELf help schemes under which refugees build their
own homes are being supported by governments, volun¬
tary agencies and the U.N. High Commissioner's
Office. Loans in the form of land and materials are
given to refugees who have to repay them to a revol¬
ving fund on a ten or twenty year basis. Current
plans provide for rehousing of 3,000 refugees. Out of
1,000 loans already granted only three per cent failed
to repay the money.
w,
ith the co-operation of churches in several Euro-
peau countries, the "World Council of Churches Refu¬
gee Service placed over 400 aged, sick and tuberculous
refugees in homes and institutions during 1954. A
special effort is being made by unref to aid this class
of refugees. Its 1955 programme aimed to help settle
1,000 refugees in homes, hospitals and sanitoria at a
cost of $500.000.
A
IBOUT 16,000 refugees from Europe were resettled
overseas in 1954, 10,000 of them in the United States
and Canada. But 8,000 new refugees arrived in West¬
ern Europe during the same period. Some 14,000
refugees of European origin on the mainland of China
are seeking new homes in other countries. The most
destitute are being helped from unref funds. In
the Middle East, isolated groups of European refugees
total several thousands. Many are living in the great¬
est distress.
T
.his year a Dutch selection team will be visiting
refugee camps in Austria to select families for reset¬
tlement in the Netherlands where they will be given
furnished houses and jobs. This is a combined opera¬
tion of the Netherlands Government, the European
Migration Committee, and the U.N. High Commis¬
sioner's Office.
R.
Iefdgee projects in the U.N. Refugee Fund Program¬
me for 1955 included the settlement of workers in
crafts, trades and agriculture, vocational training,
housing, aid to university students, life insurance for
aged refugees and many other forms of aid and relief.
In Austria, 196 families were rehoused and 313 refugees
were given vocational training during the first half of
1955. In Italy over 1,000 received medical care and in
Germany 306 families were rehoused.
Ü
_ NDER the .1951 Convention on the Status of Refu¬
gees, provision was made for the issue of a travel
document an internationally-recognized refugee "pass¬
port". Most countries insist on visas for these "pass¬
ports" but recently the Benelux countries (Belgium, the
Netherlands and Luxembourg) agreed to "waive visa
requirements for refugees travelling within their
borders. The Council of Europe has now suggested
that all its 'member states follow the Benelux lead.
T
he total of Jewish refugees living in European
campshundreds of thousands immediately after the
warhad been reduced (in Germany, Austria and
Italy) to 17,000 by 1951. Today only 1,465 remain in
refugee camps, and it is hoped to close the last camp
in Germany by the end of this year. Most of these
refugees have been resettled in Israel. Others have
gone to the U.S.A. and other countries. In just over
five years permanent homes were found for 275,000
Jews by the American Joint Distribution Committee
Inc., one of the largest voluntary agencies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
IRO
THE UPROOTED
40,000,000 refugees:
a staggering world problem
by James Douglas
THE OLD ONES. For the
elderly refugees (above) there is
little possibility of emigration and
a new start in life because of their
age. But other opportunities exist
for them and sometimes they have
to make difficult decisions. "Togo
or not to go?" is a problem clearly
reflected in the expressions of these
old people. Valuable work on
behalf of aged refugees has been
done by the large voluntary agen¬
cies, both national and international.
Church groups of all denominations
have come forward with funds,
active, devoted workers and moral
support in the cause of the refugees.
Here, with his back to the camera,
(on right) is one such worker, Father
Braun of the French voluntary
agency, the Little Sisters of the
Poor, talking to some of "the old
ones" in an Austrian refugee camp.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N1* 1. 1956
an's inhumanity to man", said Burns,
W / "makes countless thousands mourn" and
l\ /I this is a fact as old as history itself.
i w What else can explain the presence
today of 30 to 40 million men, women
and children scattered throughout many
lands in camps and settlements far from their own
homes and families in short the world's refugees.
This is a pressing problem which our generation is
attempting to solve. These men and women have faced
up to a future which at best is a question mark and at
worst a miserable existence eked out by charity. They are
people who have had the courage of their convictions and
who have found, each in his or her own way, freedom
of speech, of religion and of political convictions. They
have a right to new jobs, new homes and a new way of
life, and also, in their new-found freedom, to some of the
rights and dignities for which they made a sacrifice.
Just after the announ¬
cement of the Nobel Peace
Prize award to the Office
of the U.N. High Commis¬
sioner for Refugees, (see
page 4) a unesco courier
special correspondent was
given an exclusive inter¬
view by the U.N. High
Commissioner, Dr. van
Heuven Goedhart, in Ge¬
neva. Asked how he saw
the position of the refugee
today, and what he
thought of the possibili¬
ties for the future, Dr.
van Heuven Goedhart had
this to say:
"'The refugee is not a
man to be pitied but one
to be admired. He has had
the courage to abandon
his home, and sometimes
his family, for something
in which he believes
freedom. He is an exam¬
ple to every one of us.
Refugees have been called
'forgotten people' but I
want them to be --iorgot-
ten' in an entirely diffe¬
rent way as ordinary citi¬
zens . living together with
their families and having
permanent jobs. It is my
first concern to see that
the refugees are really
'forgotten.' in this way.
* "There are today some
seventy thousand refugees
living in 200 official
camps in Europe without
any regular work. Within
' three years these camps
will be closed, and the
projects and plans for my
office in 1956 are a means to achieve this end."
Although, as the High Commissioner remarked, emer¬
gency aid and relief supplies still have their uses, the
important question today is to find permanent solutions.
This is an immense problem one which has been des¬
cribed as the largest single human issue of our time.
In 1945 the crux of the refugee problem lay in Europe
with Germany as a nerve centre. Since then events have
created refugees by the million in Asia and the Near and
. Middle East. The partition of India, wars in China and
Korea the creation of the State of Israel, the partition of
Indo-China have all led to the displacement from their
homes of millions of people. The refugee problem in 1956
is one that is world-wide in scope. It is a tragic fact that
the vast majority of these refugees, some of whom are
known in technical parlance as "national refugees", are
not by international definition refugees at all, however
displaced, homeless and destitute they may be. They do
not benefit from international aid and protection and
have to rely in the main on the assistance given to them
by their own governments and by voluntary and other
relief agencies.
Falling within this class are the 11 million refugees
'OLIVER TWIST' LOOK on the
far better than any words the hun
who have arrived in Western Germany (and who are
at present arriving at the rate of approximately 1,000 a
day the majority being young men and women under 25).
Then there are some 670,000 Chinese refugees now
living in Hong Kong who as yet have not been placed
directly under international protection; the two million on
Formosa; and the 12 million which India and Pakistan are
trying to absorb. Korea's homeless amount to almost
five million, and quite recently the figure for refugees in
South Viet Nam came to nearly one million including
soldiers and their families.
These are just a 'few of many examples which show
that the world refugee problem has assumed a size and
complexity which might well baffle any international
agency, no matter how large. But, however the term
refugee is defined, the problem is one demanding interna¬
tional action. As M. Jacques Vernant states in his
book on "The Refugee in the Post-War World" : "It is by
attempting to harmonize
the sometimes conflicting
interests of the countries
of first asylum and those
of permanent resettle¬
ment; by acting, if not as
referee, at least as coun¬
sellor to those states and
to the refugees them¬
selves; by promoting In
every possible way the
gradual assimilation of
the unemployed refugees
and their integration in
more prosperous coun¬
tries; by smoothing the
process which normally
ends in naturalization it
is in these ways that the
international authority
set up for this purpose
can best do its work."
If we put on one side for
a moment the millions of
so-called "national" refu¬
gees, we are still faced
with a refugee problem.
The remainder numbering
about one million in Eur¬
ope and several thous¬
ands in the Middle and
Far East are refugees by
definition and so fall
within the mandate of
the Office of the U.N.
High Commissioner for
Refugees. These refugees
do receive international
protection and are the
concern of the High Com¬
missioner's Office. Falling
into another category are
the 900,000 Palestinian
Arab refugees who are
fed, clothed, trained and
educated through the
work done by the United Nations Relief and Works Agency
and unesco (see the unesco courier n" 7 1955; U.S. Oc¬
tober 1955, for full details of what u. n. and unesco are
doing).
Again in a somewhat different category are the Spanish
Republican refugees in France who now number about
150,000, the majority of whom have French work permits
and are in regular employment.
As the U.N. High Commissioner has said, it is a sobering
and distressing thought that in 1956, eleven years a-fter
the end of the Second World War, there are still between
100,000 and 120,000 refugees living in government-main¬
tained and unofficial camps in Austria, Germany, Greece
and Italy. Some people have been living in tents, shacks
and barracks for ten years, and none have regular work.
These people are the crux of the European refugee
problem. Why are they still there after the immense
efforts made to solve this very problem by various interna¬
tional agencies since the end of the war? Some by reason
of ill-health or lack of skill cannot be re¬
settled overseas, some cannot find regular work (Cont'd on
in the vicinity of the camp and so never next page)
have enough money to establish themselves
1 1
ATP
pinched face of this little girl reveals
ger and misery she has lived through.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
THE UPROOTED (Continued)
ENDLESS WAITING. For these refugees in
Germany, life for years past has been a succession of
endless queues. Again and again they have lined up
for interviews, food and clothing, medical examin¬
ations and for a dozen other reasons. At selection
centre (right) relief and pleasure show on faces of
those chosen for emigration. Below, others wait
to complete applications to emigrate to Canada,
England, North Africa, Venezuela or Brazil.
IRO
elsewhere, and some through years of inactivity and
disappointment have given up hope and are incapable of
struggling to improve their situation.
If we still keep within our limited definition of the word
refugee it is instructive to examine the situation today
in some countries oí Europe and the Far East. In Austria
there are 160,000 refugees of whom some 32.000 live in
80 official camps maintained by the Austrian Government
and a further 30,000 in unofficial camps. Many thousands
are Volksdeutsche who have been found regular employ¬
ment and can now if they choose become Austrian citi¬
zens.
The total of refugees in Austria who have no regular
work comes to approximately 40,000. Foreign refugees in
Germany now number 220,000 of which 30,000 are living in
official camps maintained by the Federal German Govern¬
ment. The inflow rate for non-German refugees is about
100 a month.
Greece has around 14,000 refugees of whom 2,700 are
living in camps and refugee centres. In October 1955
there were still 1,500 refugees in the Trieste camps and
other camps in Italy housed a further 3,000.
The overall picture for Europe is that of 350,000 refugees
who, in refugee terminology "have not been assimilated".
This polite phrase disguises the fact that these men and
women do not have regular work, have little money and
are often dependent on international charity. In camps,
towns and villages they are living in conditions which
sometimes border on destitution. They are today still
unable to resume the kind of life they once knew in their
homelandsi a life which has become now a rapidly fading
memory' taking some of them back fifteen years or more. .
Among them are found 15,000 sick and disabled and
another 15,000 children who were born "'refugees". Many
of these people, and particularly those in the camps, are
affected by the blight of enforced idleness. They have in
many cases reached the lowest point of human existence
where they are dependent on charity for anything that
is not strictly a necessity, and for a great many things
of an emergency nature which are.
Turning to the Middle East, there are still 9,000 refu¬
gees scattered throughout Egypt, Syria, Iraq and the Le¬
banon, who rely primarily on international aid. In China,
14,000 European refugees are living in Shanghai, Harbin
and Tientsin. Some 6,000 of these already have visas for
other countries but through political difficulties the rate
of egress is painfully slow. Some of the more needy cases
rely entirely on international help for their immediate
needs.
Minor miracles are routine
This thumbnail outline of the world refugee problem
in very generalized terms is disheartening and
depressing. But after painting the picture in its
gloomiest colours it is now only fair to turn the page and
examine what constructive work is being accomplished in
finding new jobs and new homes for the mdlions who
have sacrificed their all. Fortunately men of goodwill are
at work on this problem and are accomplishing some
minor miracles.
The chief U.N. Agency at work on the refugee problem
is the Office of the U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees
(unhcr) brought into existence by the General Assem¬
bly of the United Nations in 1950. This Office now has
a mandate from the Assembly which runs until the end
of 1958. It has 14 branch or sub-offices located through¬
out Europe, the Middle and Far East and in the Ame¬
ricas, but although the work accomplished by the High
Commissioner's Office is world-wide in scope, it is
limited in a sense to three main types oí aid: 1. Inter¬
national protection for refugees; 2. Promoting perma¬
nent solutions; 3. Administering emergency aid.
Money for operational work comes from the U.N. Re¬
fugee Fund which is entirely dependent on the generosity
of governments, voluntary organizations and private do¬
nors. To work effectively, the High Commissioner's Office
has to maintain close relations with inter-governmental
and voluntary agencies concerned with the refugee pro¬
blem. Thanks to this, much of the practical work of
resettling and integrating refugees has been successful.
The action might be summed up as follows. The High
Commissioner's Office (unhcr), promotes the solutions
for refugees and negotiates with the governments while
the inter-governmental and voluntary agencies do most
of the work on the spot. It is they, in the main, who
move the refugees to new homes, pay for their passages,
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
pre-select them for possible immigration and see that
they have the means to travel. This of course is a gene¬
ralization but gives an idea of the type of co-operative
partnership which exists and without which few posi¬
tive results could be reached.
Without in any way detracting from the essential work
carried out by unhcr the efforts made on behalf of the
refugees by religious organizations in all parts of the
world must be stressed. The Lutheran World Federa¬
tion, the National Catholic Welfare Conference, the
American Jewish Joint Distribution Committee Inc., the
World Council of Churches, the ymca, the Friends'
Service Council and the American Friends' Service
Committee and others all play important roles. There
are many thousands of people today living in new lands
with new prospects before them who would still be
refugees had they not been aided by these organizations.
Vital work has also been done by the Inter-Govern¬
mental Committee for European Migration which,
although it is primarily concerned with migration,
nevertheless works in close harmony with unhcr in
helping to resettle refugees. Between 1952 and mid-
1955 this Committee resettled no fewer than 131,000
IRO
refugees of which 76,600 were refugees falling directly
within the mandate oí the High Commissioner. In terms
of migrants and refugees the Committee in the same
period resettled a total of 383,000no mean achievement.
In other spheres the work of the League of Red Cross
Societies, the Council of Europe, the United States
Escapee Programme, the International Labour Organi¬
zation, the Organization for European Economic Co¬
operation and the U.N. Commissions concerned with
specific problems in Korea and Palestine should not be
overlooked. Many other smaller national organizations
both of a governmental and voluntary nature also per-
valuable work in the refugee field. The problem
is world-wide in scope and world-wide action is being
taken to meet it.
' Magna Carta ' for the refugee
Here then are some of the international and national
agencies. In what ways are refugees provided
with new opportunities through their help? This
has become a complex subject, and the layman who
thinks that resettling the refugee in another country is
the only answer would be completely wrong.
First of all, the refugee must be in a position to benefit
from international protection and such protection lies
within the competency of unhcr. A refugee cannot get
help 'from his consul, he has no passport or travel
documents. He is far worse off than other aliens who
are protected by their governments when they are
abroad, unhcr, therefore, tries to safeguard the
refugee's rights by promoting international agreements
with governments.
The most important of these is the Convention on the
Status of the Refugee, drawn up in 1951 and already
ratified by 15 countries. Under this Convention the
country to which the refugee goes is obliged to issue him
with travel and identity documents. The Convention also
contains many other clauses which are designed to
safeguard the refugee's rights.
Once the refugee is accepted in a country a place must
be found for him in the community. Mention has been
made earlier in this article of permanent solutions.
These can be simply classified as: repatriation to his
own country; emigration and resettlement in another
country and integration by means of a regular job in the
country to which he had, fled.
No emigration after forty-five
Under the permanent solutions category there are
many difficulties with which to contend. A refugee
may be too old to emigrates the age limit is 45; he
may be offered repatriation but for political or other
reasons may not wish to accept it; he may be medically
unfit or he may lack any useful skills. All these points
have to be carefully examined by the field worker who
is trying to find the best solution.
Integration of the refugee in the country in which he is
living has recently become of increasing importance.
Various projects now being implemented by unhcr and
the voluntary agencies fall in this category. Ic ,.
They include: housing settlements vocational C-0"* a on
training, loans and credit facilities for set-
next
ting up 'small business and, most important P°Se-)
RISEN FROM THE ASHES. Riziani, a destroyed
and abandoned Greek village, now lives again.
New houses have been built on the ruins and are
occupied by resettled refugees. With their own
homes to live in and their own land to till the refugees
have set to work, helped by the Greek Government
which built 40 houses and provided livestock, food
and seeds. Refugee family (upper, left) stores its
first corn crop around the bed. In refugee centres
others put their skills to use (lower photos). The
6 1-year old painter has been waiting in a Trieste camp
for years for a chance to emigrate. Dressmaker has
managed to live since I 950 by doing hand-embroidery.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE UPROOTED
(Continued)
EUROPE'S CAMPS MUST GO!
of all, establishment in regular work either in towns or in
the country. No fewer than 118 different aid projects of
this nature have been, or are being put into operation by
unhr under its Refugee Fund programme.
Under this programme between May and November 1955,
6,000 refugees in Europe, the Near, Middle and Far East,
received assistance. Houses for 287 families are now
under construction and work on 306 will start shortly.
Vocational training has been given to 435 refugees and
scholarships to 120. Help and advice on jobs has been
aiforded to more than a thousand and a like number will
profit from loans and credits. All this work falls directly
or indirectly within the integration category and although
these numbers may not appear vast in terms of the total
number of refugees, there can be no doubt that what has
been accomplished in a little more than six months is a
worthwhile achievement.
Many significant results are also being achieved in re¬
settling refugees in countries overseas. In an eight-
month period in 1955- some 7,000 refugees were resettled
overseas irom camps in Germany and Austria, 266 from
Migration Committee has meant that the total now in
the Trieste camps only numbers 1,500. On January, 1953
there were 5,000.
Much valuable work has also been done for those
refugees who, by reason of ill-health, cannot be resettled
or found regular work. The Scandinavian countries have
been particularly generous in accepting a number of these
cases. A six-man Norwegian selection team has just
completed visits to camps in Munich, Trieste and Naples.
They selected 75 refugee families for settlement in
Norway, many of whom were suffering from tuberculosis.
Once in Norway they will have the benefit of specialized
medical care and attention. Denmark has also accepted a
number of severely handicapped refugees who have been
living in penury in Shanghai for years past.
Apart from the efforts made to integrate or resettle
those refugees living in the European refugee camps there
has been a recent development in attempts to alleviate the
torpor and frustration of camp existence. This scheme,
known as Camp Adoption, has achieved some useful
results. As the High Commissioner for Refugees said in
THE WANDERING KALMUKS. One
of the most remarkable Odysseys any group
of refugees has ever experienced is that of
the Kalmuks who in the 17th century fled
westward from their homes in the Chinese
province of Sinkiang to settle in the
lower Volga region. Though conquered
by the Russians towards the end of the
18th century they continued to live as a
community until the Revolution of 1917
when they lost some of their numbers in
migrations to Bulgaria, Yugoslavia and
Czechoslovakia. In the Second World
War they formed special cavalry units tb
fight against the Nazi invaders, but when
the Kalmuk territory was over-run, many
Kalmuks were deported to work in Ger¬
many. It was here that the remnants of
the group once made up of tens of thou¬
sands were re-united, though at the end
of the war they numbered less than 800
men, women and children. Today, a
small group of the Kalmuk community
lives in Ingolstadt Refugee Camp, Bavaria.
Above, a priest stands by an altar in a
temple set up in a camp barrack room.
UNATIONS.
Greece and 345 from Shanghai. The majority of these
refugees went to the United States but large numbers also
went to Australia and Canada. These impressive refugee
movements were carried out as a joint operation between
unhcr and the Committee for European Migration.
Among the voluntary agencies, the World Council of
. Churches reports that more than 1,000 refugees were
moved to new homes during the month of October 1955.
Remedies for boredom and frustration
Perhaps one of the most impressive resettlement
campaigns was that carried out in the Trieste refugee
camps. In a twelve-month period between October
1954 and October 1955, 2,403 refugees were resettled, the
majority going to Australia, the United States and Chile.
This considerable effort on the part of the voluntary
agencies working in collaboration with unhcr and the
14
his report to the tenth (1955) session of the U.N. General
Assembly, "The improved morale and living conditions in a
number of camps in Austria, Germany and Greece today
bear tribute to what can be achieved by generous and
resourceiul action undertaken by local communities in
other countries."
No fewer than 42 refugees camps have so far been
adopted by groups and communities in the United
Kingdom. In the Netherlands the movement is spreading
and in Denmark public-spirited citizens have already
adopted two camps and are considering adopting four
more. A camp at Augustdorf, Germany is being helped
under the Unesco Gift Coupon Plan. Here a school for
over 100 Latvian children Will shortly be receiving text¬
books, physics and chemistry teaching apparatus and
school furniture bought with coupons donated by people
in Denmark and the Netherlands.
Camp adoption has meant that refugee craitsmen now
have tools with which to work, gardeners have been
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
UNREF BARE EXISTENCE of people living in an unofficial barracks camp for refugees in Austria, is symbolized by small
boy slaking his thirst at a tapsole water supply in the barracks. Soon many refugees will move into new housing
projects similar to one above being completed near Salzburg. Similar projects exist in Germany.
supplied with seeds and tools, women have been given
sewing machines and children have received toys. Camp
adoption has meant that 38 refugee children in a Greek
camp, who were in a tubercular or pre-tubercular condi¬
tion, were able to go to Switzerland for four months and
receive medical attention free of charge from the Swiss
Red Cross Society.
These measures are of course of an emergency relief
nature but their importance ior the well-being of the
refugee camp inmates is considerable.
These in broad outline are some of the positive steps
which are now being taken to solve the refugee problem,
but as the figures quoted show, much still remains to be
done. The prime necessity for any solution lies in the
dissolution of the camps. Until these disappear there can
be no permanent solution.
No dreamboats for a land of plenty
The mere promise of resettlement overseas is not by
itself sufficient as it has been found that refugees
will cease doing constructive work if they are under
the impression that all they have to do is to wait for a boat
which will transport them to a magic land of opportunity
where gold will automatically fall into their laps. It is
not enough to create economic opportunities for refugees
without the adequate social advice they need to profit
from the opportunities made available. Every step has to
be taken with the utmost care if permanent solutions
which really are permanent are to mean anything.
To achieve any results at all money is needed, and
whether this money goes to the U.N. Refugee Fund, to the
voluntary agencies or to any of the other bodies working
in the refugee field, it is always put to the best possible
use. In a humanitarian crisis of this kind people are
generous. A magnificent response was made by the
people of the Netherlands to an appeal for funds launched
by the U.N. High Commissioner. They spontaneously
decided to give one hour of their wages to the refugees
with the result that one million dollars was contributed.
This campaign was conducted on a purely voluntary basis.
Everyone participated from members of the Dutch Royal
Household to the workers in the factories and on the
farms. Money 'for the U.N. Refugee Fund has also, of
course, come from governments. In mid-November, 1955,
the total amounted to 1,624,482 dollars, but in the words
of the U.N. High Commissioner, "So far the response... has
been disappointing."
If funds are forthcoming there is litle doubt that
within the next few years the refugee camps in Europe
will be dissolved, and thereby one of the most tragic
legacies of the aftermath of the Second World War will
have been removed. The refugee picture at the beginning
of 1956 is still grim and depressing. It is a challenge
which can only be met and conquered by determined and
co-ordinated international action.
LEFT BEHIND. The case of handicapped refugees has recently been
given special attention by the U.N. High Commissioner's Office. Some
European countries, notably the Scandinavian states, have shown
their willingness to accept physically handicapped refugees.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE NANSEN SAGA
For the second time in its history, the Nobel Peace Prize
has been awarded to an organization working on behalf
of refugees the Office of the U.N. High Commissioner for
Refugees. The previous occasion was in 1938 when the award
was made to the Nansen International Office for Refugees,
named after the famous Norwegian explorer, Fridtjof Nansen,
himself a Nobel Peace Prize winner in 1922. The following
article tells something of Nansen's life as an explorer and of the
great humanitarian work he did for the world's refugees.
In the year 1882, a 21-year old Norwegian completed his
studies at Christiania University and set out on a
sealer to collect zoological specimens in the Arctic.
This was the first of many later and greater voyages un¬
dertaken by Fridtjof Nansen whose name was to become
famous both in the field of Arctic exploration and in
refugee work during and after the First World War.
Nansen made an amazing Arctic journey in 1888 when
he was only 27 years old. He set out to cross island of
*«a
!P*
34P-
Norwegian Embassy, Paris
DIFFICULT PROGRESS. To travel 500 yards by sledge demanded
an enormous effort from Nansen and his colleagues. Pictured here is
Nansen's base camp in I 894, about 300 miles short of the North Pole.
Fridtjof Nansen, a name famous not
only for voyages of Arctic exploration
but inseparably associated with the
Nansen Passport. This gave offi¬
cial status to thousands of refugees.
Copyright Eneret Wiese - Oslo
Greenland on skis
though many authori¬
ties had declared this
achievement impos¬
sible. He left with a
party of four and
succeeded in making
the crossing from east
to west.
During this trip an¬
other far more ambit¬
ious plan was germin¬
ating in his mind an
expedition to the
North Pole. At that
time no man had
reached the Pole and
Nansen had his own
very particular ideas
on how this should be
attempted. He believed that the currents of the Arctic Sea
would carry a ship north from Siberia across the Pole and
then south to Greenland. This was no idle dream as
Nansen had examined driftwood on the coast of Green¬
land, which he was certain had come from Siberia.
Nansen interested the Norwegian Government in his
plans and a special type of vessel was built capable of
withstanding the terrible pressure of the grinding ice
floes. She was named the Fram (Forward) and on a
June day in 1893 she lay alongside the quays of Chris¬
tiania which were crowded with thousands of people who
had come to wish Nansen luck in his attempt.
By September the Fram was frozen in the ice pack and
just as Nansen had predicted she drifted northwards until
March 1895. Then, nearly two years after their departure
from Norway at a latitude of 85° 5' north, Nansen and one
of his colleagues Lt. Johansen took their sledges out for a
final bid to reach the Pole. By April 7 1895 they were
within 272 miles of the Pole 184 miles farther north than
any man had ever been before. But ice conditions forced
them to turn back and they made their way to Franz
Josef Land where they passed the winter. In 1896 Nansen
arrived back in Norway, and the Fram reached port
shortly afterwards.
This dramatic voyage made Nansen a famous figure
both in Norway and abroad. He was honoured by many
European countries and he lectured in Europe and in the
United States. In 1905 he played a leading part in the
MODERN
'FLYING
DUTCHMEN'
by
Louise de Béa
The polyglot seagoing fraternity
manning . the world's merchant
navies today numbers thousands
of refugee seamen in its ranks. Some
were once regular crew members on
ships of their native countries who
sought freedom by "'jumping ship"
while in a foreign port. Others found
countries willing to give them refuge,
but after a spell in a refugee camp
they preferred to return to sea.
Most are men without countries and
without identities and thus condemned
to lives which recall the ancient story
of the Flying Dutchman who was
doomed to sail the seas eternally. But
this legendary captain was allowed to
return to port from time to time to
search for a maid whose love could
release him from his fate, whereas
these are refugee seamen whose world
ends at the bottom of a ship's gang¬
plank. Without identity papers they
can never set foot ashore.
These men are prisoners on board
ship and there are plenty of case
records of refugees who have sailed
round the world for three or four years
without ever being able to land.
Two years ago the Netherlands
authorities, acting for the Office of the
U.N. High Commissioner for Refugees,
made a survey of refugee seamen serv¬
ing on ships docking in Dutch ports.
This brought to light some startling
facts. Out of 550 refugee seamen only
220 had papers allowing them to return
to the countries where their ships were
registered. A further 124 were entitled
to return to some other country, and
59 had documents which had either
expired or were not valid for return to
the issuing country. The remaining
147 had no valid documents at all they
were men who, officially, did not exist.
These men thus still lack the protec¬
tion prescribed by Article 11 of the
Convention on the Status of Refugees (11
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
negotiations which led to the peaceful separation of
Norway from Sweden. His efforts in the field of diplo¬
macy were rewarded by his appointment as Norway's
first Minister to Great Britain. He held this post until
1908 when he was appointed Professor of Oceanography at
the University of Christiania.
Nansen however, was not content to rest in the peace
and calm of University life and between 1910 and 1914
he made a number of scientific voyages of discovery in
the North Atlantic. This work was suddenly interrupted
by the outbreak of the First World War. Norway remain¬
ed neutral' but Nansen busied himself with relief work and
thus started a new chapter in his career which was to lead
to the Nobel Peace Prize award in 1922.
In the latter part of the war Nansen set up an office
to help the thousands of Russian refugees in Asia Minor.
Later he was in charge of the repatriation of German and
Russian prisoners-of-war and in the years immediately
following the war he became internationally-known for
his relief work in famine-stricken Russia. This work won
for Nansen the Peace Prize award.
Following the First World War Europe faced a refugee
problem of a magnitude such as had never been seen
before. Nansen took the initiative in attacking this
problem and with the approval of the Council of the
newly-created League of Nations a conference attended
by delegates of 48 Red Cross Societies and 12 governments
was held. This led to the setting up of the High Commis¬
sion for Refugees with Nansen at its head, and the new
office immediately set out to provide an identity certificate
for the thousands of Russian and Armenian refugees.
The Nansen Passport, as it was known, gave these stateless
refugees an officially-recognized existence.
Nansen continued his work for refugees and also
represented his country at the League of Nations. In 1925
he conducted the negotiations which resulted in the entry
of Germany into the League. But although Nansen was
deeply involved with the work of the League his taste of
adventure was still very much alive, and just before his
death in 1930 he was planning a Zeppelin flight over the
Arctic regions.
In the same year (1930) it was decided to set up the
Nansen International Office t for Refugees. This office
did much valuable work and i'n 1938, the year that it was
closed, it received the Nobel Peace Prize for the direction
of relief activities. Thus ended one period of great
humanitarian work for the world's refugees, the chief
architect of which had been Fridtjof Nansen.
FAST IN THE
ICEPACK. The
famous Fram with
Nansen in front
sitting on his ice
yacht before leav¬
ing base Polhavet
I during his great
Arctic voyage of
18 93-1896.
Norwegian Embassy,
Paris
adopted by an international confe¬
rence in 1951.
In September 1955, an eight-nation
conference at The Hague recommended
that refugee seamen should receive
international protection under the
Status of Refugees Convention and
that they should be allowed to serve on
ships of any nationality and be allowed
to go ashore without let or hindrance.
The recommendations will be put into
concrete form by a second conference
due to meet early this year.
The tragic human aspect of the
problem is brought home by the follow¬
ing case, typical of many others with
which the U.N. High Commissioner's
Office has had to deal. The seaman
concerned arrived in Genoa in 1949, but
his ship left again before the question
of his documents was settled. Just
over'a year later he disembarked again
at Genoa and since he did not have
any papers he was put in prison. Then
he was transferred from one refugee
camp to another and his efforts to
emigrate failed on health grounds.
He left Italy illegally for Austria
where he was arrested and expelled to
Germany. He was ordered to leave
Germany and embarked on a British
ship in August 1952. Disembarking at
a Belgian port he was put in prison and
then expelled to Germany. In 1953 he
was allowed to embark on an Italian
ship and the Italian authorities agreed
to issue a travel document. It was
difficult to contact him as he was
sailing from port to port. Finally he
was found at -Port Said, but before his
travel papers could be prepared his
ship had sailed again. Since then all
trace of this man has been lost.
Norway, one of the world's great
maritime powert, has been one of the
first countries to implement the re¬
commendation regarding seamen in the
Convention on the Status of Refugees.
As a first step it has provided all re¬
fugee seamen serving in Norwegian
ships with a special record of service.
In 1953, the Norwegian Government
also agreed to accept 50 refugee seamen
for service in the merchant marine on
the understahding that they would be
given internationally-recognized travel
documents and residence rights in Nor¬
way.
If other governments were to follow
the Norwegian example this would go
a long way towards solving the
problem. But what is still required is
a general internationally-adhered-to
issue of travel documents to refugee
seamen which give them the right to
go ashore.
Ui "In the case oí refugees regularly serving as
crew members on board a ship flying the flag of a
Contracting State, that State shall give sympathetic
consideration to their establishment on its territory
and the issue of travel documents to them or tem¬
porary admission to Its territory particularly with a
view to facilitating their establishment in another
country."
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N' 1. 1956
Govt, of India
A SLOW-MOVING STREAM OF 7.000,000 REFUGEES FLOWED FROM PAKISTAN TO INDIA (ABOVE) AND MORE THAN 4.000,000 CROSSED THE NEW BORDERS IN THE OPPOSITE DIRECTION (BELOW).
THE BIGGEST MIGRATION IN HISTORY
Pakistan Embassy, Pa Copyright Almasy
Sadness and exhaustion mark the faces of two elderly refugeesMoslem and Hindu(above)
who have been uprooted from their ancestral homes and holdings. Below, weary refugees who
have come from East Pakistan rest in the shade of a buildingand await the next move.
Copyright Almasy
The world's biggest mass migration in recorded his¬
tory took place in 1947 when the State of Paki¬
stan was carved out of the sub-continent of India.
Predominantly Moslem areas in the north and east
were separated from the rest to form the new state of
Pakistan. Hastily-drawn boundary lines left millions
of Hindus and Sikhs in Pakistan and millions of Moslems
in India.
Religious feuds which had been simmering for some
years burst into frenzied rioting, killing, looting and
arson. People who found themselves on the wrong
sides of frontiers had to leave their homes and property
without any notice and trek in convoys, sometimes 150
miles long, to run the gauntlet of marauding bands,
cross rivers in flood over two narrow bridges alongside
people of the other community coming from the opposite
direction, and face hunger, pestilence and disease. The
loss of life1 and property ran into astronomical figures.
The problem of resettling refugees was the first that
the Governments of India and Pakistan had to face
after their newly won freedom. The magnitude of the
task could be better appreciated if we visualized the
problem which would face the United States and Unit¬
ed Kingdom Governments if the entire populations of
London and New York were suddenly ordered to change
places within one month, and found both the cities in
complete discorder.
The Indian and Pakistan Governments have a credit¬
able record in tackling their refugee rehabilitation.
Scores of camps housing more than 70,000 men, women
and children were set up. An immense operation to
redistribute land of an area as large as France was
carried out.
Exchange of urban property was arranged. Uprooted
people were taught new trades. New townships
were built, and, above all, the morale o'f the re¬
fugee population kept up by infusing enthusiasm for
the new nations they were helping to build by their
sacrifice.
In eight years India has resettled over seven
and a half million and Pakistan over four and a half
million refugees. This is an example which other coun¬
tries with similar but infinitely smaller problems could
emulate,
Pakistan Embassy, Paris
I8
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Korea : 300,000 war widows and 125,000 orphans
When fighting in Korea was at its fiercest and people fled from the combat
areas or abandoned their ruined homes, the number of refugees rose to
5,000,000. In the first summer of the war men, women and children
crowded dusty roads, carrying what they had been able to save, like the
farmer (left) who also has his wife perched on his heavily-laden back. When
winter came, refugees packed open trucks of freight trains (above) heading
south and away from the fighting. Since the Korean Armistice, the Govern¬
ment of the Republic of Korea, the U.N. Korean Reconstruction Agency,
the Korea Church World Service and other voluntary agencies have still
been faced with the problems of millions of homeless. There are at least
300,000 war widows and 125,000 orphans and abandoned children.
UNATIONS
Indo-China : Operation 'Red Gross parcel' aids Viet-Nam
Foa, Saigon
Since the Armistice in Indo-China halted the decade-long war and led to
the partitioning of Viet-Nam, a million refugees from the north have poured
into South Viet-Nam. Emergency aid has been sent to these people by
national Red Cross Societies in 23 countries, and a few months after the
start of relief operations, the South Viet-Nam Red Cross had distributed
more than 200,000 parcels. Although South Viet-Nam should eventually
be able to absorb the refugees, the sudden inrush has created serious
feeding and housing problems. According to observers, conditions in
many camps are deplorable. Shelter, food, and equipment are lacking
despite aid from the Government, Churches, Red Cross and other agencies.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N1* 1. 1956
GOOD NEIGHBOURS 'DOWN UNDER'
Welcoming New Australians to the Island-Continent
B
f
k. i
l mt\\f^X^k
Jr^^" ^j j't~¿
fj
i
B
Jl
V * ltfÉ
^ . . ^H
V ,'- ^H
\'- k^m\
m^m^r^f V
W* ".Vf
t'W^
	 KILOMETRES
	 a 3QO toa ' h
1^	
MILES H
by
H. B. M.
Murphy
ETWEEN 1947 and 1950 Australia admitted
155,000 European refugees taken from camps in Germany,
Italy and Austria. From the Australian point of view the
purpose of this migration was to increase the manpower
available both for defence and for the newly-developed
industries. The great majority of the refugees were under
contract to do unskilled labour for a period of two years,
and fitness for such labour was the prime criterion in
their selection. After the two years they were to be free
Australian Official Photos
to take what employment they pleased except where
some statutory obstacle existed, as with the professions
and to apply for citizenship in the normal way, although
it was expected to take five years for such citizenship to
be completed. Australian public opinion was strongly
in favour of encouraging the newcomers to apply for
citizenship, and strongly against permitting them to form
their own communities. lnthefollowingarticle,Mr. H.B.M.
Murphy discusses some refugee resettlement problems.
Australia with nearly 3,000,000
square miles of territory has
room and to spare for the
Continent of Europe (drawn to
the same scale in map, above).
For its ever-growing industries
and vast wheat and sheep-
farming lands Australia needs
more workers. Many European
refugees have thus found new
homes there under mass immi¬
gration programmes. This flow
was halted in I 95 I, but started
again after the Australian
Government decided to increase
the total immigration target for
1 954-55 to 115,000. Left,
party of over 800 refugees from
camps in Germany are welcomed
on arrival at Melbourne, by Aus¬
tralian Minister of Immigration.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
GOOD NEIGHBOURS
(Continued)
By the time that I
visited Australia at
the end of 1950 the
recruitment
of immigrants from re¬
fugee camps was almost
at an end and the recruitment of Dutch, German and
Italian labour was beginning to take its place. On the
other hand relatively few of the refugees had finished
their two years' contract; and hence the subject of
refugee immigrants was not much in the public eye. I
travelled on a immigrant ship, and followed the same
shipload through until the majority had been found work,
but my main observations were made on people who had
been from 6 to 18 months in the country.
On arrival in Australia the initial reaction of the immi¬
grant was usually good. This was to be expected from
the type of letter one had seen sent home to Europe, and
officials confirmed my own impression. In general, there
was a conscious willingness to start working, to mix with
Australians rather than with fellow refugees and a feeling
of satisfaction at their impressions of the standard of
living, the employment position, and the appearance of
the country. Very few of the refugees refuse the type of
work first offered them, and in my experience more are
prepared to grab the first job they can get rather than
wait and choose between two or three possibilities, as is
usually permitted.
Most workers went into unskilled labour, as had been
forecast in their contract, and about half of them into
the various branches of public constructional work, a fact
which had been less accurately forecast and which was
not so much part of the Government's plan. The demand
for foreign workers had been mainly in the heavy indus¬
tries and in the countryside, but trade union opposition
and the unsuitability of the refugee for lonely country
life forced a diversion of this labour to the more essential
of the secondary services, a development which was
economically not very sound, since the country's primary
production might not have been enough to carry this
after the boom in wool was over.
However, such considerations did not worry the
individual D.P.who saw no reason to regret having escaped
work which he was not well trained to undertake, being
usually too little or too well educated for it. Roads, rail¬
roads, waterworks, gasworks and hospital service are all
characterized by the relatively large amount of unskilled
labour which they can use labour where no great amount
of manual aptitude, such as is required in ironworks or
mines, is demanded and hence the refugee was usually
fairly content in such employment, not feeling that the
work was beyond him.
A shovel for the surgeon
The Government's declared policy on the use of the
immigrant's previously acquired skills was to take
as much advantage as possible of these, despite
the fact that the individual was contracted irrespective
of them it would seem to be the sensible road to fol¬
low. The application o-f this policy, however, was very
patchy. I came across many instances of it being com¬
plied with, of diplomas (science) being scrutinized and
accepted, of draughtsmen being taken from the labour
squad into the office, etc.
But I also heard of many instances where it seemed
to be forgotten or in some cases disregarded, untrained
men being sent to a shoe factory while cobblers in the
same camp were refused, builders found doing other work
at a time when the labour exchange denied having a free
builder on their books, a throat surgeon who hoped to
resume his career being allotted to roadmaking while
another physician who asked to be put into some other
occupation was being sent against her will to act as camp
doctor. Thus whether an immigrant was able to follow
his prior occupation was largely a matter of luck and the
personality of the employment officer.
The penniless state of all refugees (those who brought
some savings with them soon spent them there on making
their life more bearable) and the difficulty of finding and
paying for reasonable accommodation out of current earn¬
ings meant that those who were able to do so very soon
started looking for supplementary means of income from
which to accumulate a little capital.
Hence most immigrants were keen on overtime work and
to have their wives working, and a remarkable number
of them managed, against all labour custom, to take two
jobs àt once, dashing from a day shift in controlled
employment to a night shift elsewhere, taking weekend
employment or running their own allotments. This natur¬
ally often resulted in neither job being done properly,
but at that time of full employment the State gained
by such industriousness, however much union and work¬
ing class objections to the practice made its officials
disapprove. Later, however, these supplementary jobs
made trouble' with the employment officers, who could
not understand why a man should object to being moved
from one job to a similar one in another location and
so believed it was only stubbornness when the refugee
resisted such a move.
Too scared to go on strike
Thus, redirected labour was usually found both by
employment officers and by supervisors to be less
satisfactory than raw labour sent direct 'from the
reception camps or left in the same area, although this
cause for unsatisfactory work did not seem to be as widely
realized as it should have been and was often not taken
into account in opinions given me on the working qualities
of the refugee.
Apart from this type of problem, the incidence of
unsatisfactory behaviour among the refugees was quite
low, and they mostly seemed too afraid of being sent back
to Europe to take part in even as safe an activity as an
Australian-organized union protest or strike. The truly
anti-social individual, such as one meets in any commun¬
ity and such as were apparently much in evidence among
ex-concentration camp refugees, were presumably present
but did not seem to be .giving much trouble.
Australianization of the refugee started in Europe from
the moment he was provisionally selected. In the resettle¬
ment camps, at sea and again in the reception camps in
Australia, he was taught English mixed with Australian
history and social customs under a unified and specially
adapted scheme which continues to be widely available to
him, though no longer compulsory, wherever he may find
himself later. These courses struck me as being intellig¬
ently devised and energetically undertaken, lacking only
that training for democracy which after spending so long
under autocratic rule refugees so urgently required, but
which is difficult to put into an official syllabus because
of the political interpretations involved.
The programme would seem to complement the initial
conscious desire of most refugees to forget their past and
to become Australian as soon as possible, and it deserved
to succeed. Yet at the time of my visit all sources agreed
that the progress in learning English was slow, compared
with expectations, that the attendance at classes after all
.facilities had been made available was exceedingly poor,
and that contact between the immigrants and Australians
was very slight. It would seem a clear illustration, on
both sides, of the frustration of conscious intentions by
unconscious motivations. Only three of the 30 to 40
refugees with whom I spoke, the great majority of whom
had been in the country more than a year, had satis¬
factory private contacts, as evidenced by having an
Australian home where they felt confident of a real wel¬
come. And this was the case although my selection was
not a true cross-section but was rather biased on the side
of intelligence and stability.
Since there is no sponsorship system for the majority
of refugee immigrants to Australia and hence no
individual with whom they can feel personally linked,
nearly all have to depend for their free-time contacts
with Australian life on the communal efforts of State,
church and voluntary organizations, or on an extension
of contacts in work The State does very little directly
beyond the educational programme mentioned above. It
runs a newspaper for immigrants, a newspaper for societies
and individuals interested in helping the immigrant, and
has produced two propaganda films; but none of these
seems to reach the wide public, and hence although there
was some effort to educate the refugees to understand
Australian habits, little was done to explain the refugee to
the Australian beyond saying what nice people they are.
More specific welfare services for the refugee however,
are avoided as part of a deliberate policy
which, while giving him most of the privileges (Cont'd on
of an Australian and thus perhaps helping him page 2S)
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr I. 1956
Copyright Meyer, Carpentras.
CRUMBLING WALLS were practically all that remained of La Roque-sur-Pernes, a tiny village
nestling on a sunny hillside in Southern France (above). Life was brought back to this decaying
hamlet by refugees from camps in Austria who set about building new homes for themselves.
EXODUS IN REVERSE
Refugee
a dying
farmers revive
French village
BLACKSMITH, MOTHER
AND SCHOOLGIRL
the newcomers to La Roque-sur-
Pernes have now become well
integrated into the local French
community.
»
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
THE PROVENCAL
VILLAGE THAT
ALMOST DIED
UNTIL a fev/ years ago, La Roque-
sur-Pernes was a dying village.
Abandoned houses and farms were
crumbling Into ruins, stables and barns
were empty and most of the fields lay
fallow. The exodus of farmers and agri¬
cultural workers to the towns of southern
France had. reduced the population from
400 to less than 80. It looked as If the
village would soon disappear from the
map of France.
But the exodus from this sunny Pro¬
vencal village went Into reverse In 1950
when ten families of refugees whose ances¬
tors originated from this part of France
arrived bringing new blood and new life
back to La Roque-sur-Pernes.
This first group of refugees had been
working as farm labourers in Alsace,
hoping some day they would once again
own small farms. Later, a second group
of eleven families came directly from
camps in Austria. A French voluntary
aid organization bought houses and land
for them, the cost to be repaid out of the
profits from their farming. Funds were
provided from a Ford Foundation grant
administered by the Office of the U.N,
High Commissioner for Refugees.
The French Government was especially
interested in the experiment because it
pointed the way to halting the exodus
to the towns- and restoring prosperity
to regions which had once been rich and
fertile. It gave funds and granted chil¬
dren's allowances and free medical care
to the settlers. The Vaucluse Depart¬
ment authorities loaned a truck, improved
the roads leading to the village and pro¬
vided a teacher for the village school.
Some farms were immediately habitable,
but others needed repair. Here the
refugees showed they were as good .
builders as they were skilled farmers.
One farmhouse was completely rebuilt
In two months without any outside help.
By the end of 1954, over 200 acres of
land had been brought back into cultiva¬
tion and fruit trees, vines, cereals, market
produce and beets planted. Direct grants
were made for the purchase of seeds, farm
tools, a tractor and building materials.
Titles to houses and land, at present vested
in the French voluntary authority super¬
vising the settlement, will finally revert
to the settlers on repayment of the origi¬
nal loans.
Today La Roque-sur-Pernes is a thriving
community and the former refugees are
firmly settled in their new homes. They
have received help, but their success in
bringing back prosperity to abandoned
lands is largely due to their own efforts.
Their example suggests a single, practical
solution for two serious problems how to
resettle refugee farming families and how
to combat the rural drift to the towns.
Copyright Meyer, Carpentras.
HARD-WORKING refugee families turned over long-fallow fields and planted fruit trees, vines,
cereals and beets. The new settlers will own land and buildings after repayment of initial loans.
UNATIONS.
APT FARMERS, the refugees soon brought land back into cultivation. Some even went on work¬
ing after sunset by the light of lanterns. Above, mid-day meal break during the cherry harvest.
UNATIONS.
VILLAGE SCHOOL was about to close in 1950there was not a single child of school age
in the community. Today 20 out of class of 25 are children who come from refugee families.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
GOOD NEIGHBOURS
(Continued from page 22) NEWCOMERS IN A QUANDARY
to feel himself as one, gives him no services which would
permit him to feel himself as something special or would
allow Australian electors to grumble about unnecessary
expense.
Locally, the commandants of camps have sometimes
organized entertainments and clubs to which both new¬
comers and nearby residents are invited, thus incidentally
enriching the usually poor social life of the nearest small
town, but that is the most direct approach made.
Blame for lack of contact must not be laid too
thoughtlessly on the local voluntary organizations. They
were doing as much as they would do for any Australian-
born person moving into their area, probably more. It is
true that a different approach, one that the isolated
Australian had ¡never had a chance to learn, was needed
in such cases, but it was also true that the refugee
immigrant too often made no adequate attempts at contact
from his side. I was given story after story of functions
being arranged for them and the newcomers not appear¬
ing; of working conditions being softened for them and
yet being rejected or abused; of sulkiness, quarrelling and
other forms of misbehaviour, both at organized gatherings
and in private contacts.
The refugee immigrant saw the problem differently.
Such organized assimilation and get-together activities as
we have mentioned should have been needed only for the
more bashful among them. In most countries of Europe
they could so they thought have adjusted themselves
easily enough to the local population, no matter how little
they knew of the language. But in Australia, so the story
went, there was no social life to get into, nor any true
friendliness on individual contact.
The common picture was that the refugee would join
the local sports club, go drinking, attend dances and
functions, and in general be moderately welcome.
Certainly, few of them experienced anything like real
host'lity. But after a couple of invitations to home, to
drink, to play tennis, duty seemed to have been fulfilled
on the Australian's part, and although relations might
remain perfectly cordial there was no deepening of the
contact or extension through it to other contacts.
There is some truth in both points of view, and some¬
thing left out by them both as well. The general culture
' o'f Australian society is more distant from that of Europe
or America than is commonly recognized. A discussion
of it is outside the scope of this article, since we are here
concerned with the refugee side of assimilation, not the
other. Briefly, however, it may be said that the pioneer
tradition had engendered a belief in self-sufficiency and
a scorn for those social functions which attempt to do
for the individual what he should be capable of doing for
himself. Hence the social life of Australian towns is
remarkably simple. To that extent the refugees' complaint
is true social life of the complexity found in central
Europe does not exist.
Not prepared for pioneering
But it is also almost certainly true that if the refugees
had found a society of the complexity and richness
of Europe, they would still have had difficulties in
adjusting and would still have shown abnormalities
in their behaviour. The self-sufficiency which Aus¬
tralian culture believed in was just the state of mind
which the refugee, rootless and emotionally shaken by past
events, could least attain to. The self-sufficiency of the
pioneer is. based on the principle that the individual can
control his relations with his environment, and Australian
history in post-pioneer days has never met a situation
which really challenged that ; but the whole existence of
the refugee is an epitome of the contrary theory, namely,
that the individual is a toy in the grip, of uncontrollable
forces. Hence the newcomer needed not only emotional
strength to become more self-sufficient, but also had to
assume implicitly for the foundations of Australian
culture were never explicit for him a philosophy which
their whole recent life belied.
Faced with this quandary the natural tendency was to
resist assimilation, or at the least to make no positive
efforts towards it. Occasionally this resistance showed
itself as a hostility or even (in 1953) in a demand to be
sent back to Europe, bad though that was recognized to
be. More commonly the wish to co-operate was there,
but the will to do it was frustrated by unconscious or
unrecognized forces. I remember one young Yugoslav
couple, both working, both making reasonable money,
living . privately with an old, ex-Yugoslav, Australian.
They wanted to learn English; their old landlord was
strongly encouraging them to do so; and there was an
English class two streets away. And yet they never went
to it. Their personal contacts were not too bad since
they had, in their landlord, one good friend; but learning
English meant accepting the change of life and the
change of personality which their resettlement both
offered and demanded. In their talk with me it was clear
that this change was being resisted.
Leadership taken by extremists
In my own experience such a feeling was to be 'found
less commonly at that time than at the time of reset¬
tlement, but it undoubtedly appears in the majority
of refugees at some time or another and when it does it
is a major factor in his appearance or behavioui . In
Australia there can be little doubt that while the refugee
immigrants were adjusting themselves quite rap.dly to
their new economic conditions they were, at the time of
my visit, resisting quite strongly those aspects of the assi¬
milation programme which appeared to them to threaten
their original integrity
In relieving the strains which assimilation was imposing
at that time, the societies run by the refugees themselves
could only give limited help. In the first place, they
were anything but united. All the traditional trends of
European politics seemed to have their counterparts in
the groups and organizations which the exiles had
developed. In the second place the Government's declared
intention of promoting assimilation and preventing parti¬
cularism made it difficult for them to operate and tended
to restrain anyone but the extremists from seeking leader¬
ship among them.
The situation in Australia, then, whereby refugee
immigrants are found to be adjusting more rapidly to the
economic than to the social environment, is not an unex¬
pected or unusual one. The thing that gives it
significance in the present context is the declared policy
of the Australian Government and people to press for
assimilation within one generation and to obstruct any
attempts which might be made to form local colonies of
immigrants speaking the same language.
The difficulties which the refugees were having in
accepting the change of personality which goes with
assimilation, and in making local contacts, could be easily
handled and hence would be of little importance if they
were allowed to form their own communities, as in some
other countries. (As it was, they remained largely in their
own communities in camps, but every effort was made
to ensure that no community spirit or sense of permanence
was developed.) The psychological effect of the present
policy, however, appears to be making the refugee feel
even more isolated than he had felt before resettlement,
and it was not linking him to any group whose ethics he
could be expected to adopt.
Economic rewards were sufficient, and probably will still
be even in a time of recession, but emotional rewards for
conforming behaviour did seem to be inadequate, and in
consequence it appeared possible at the time of my visit
that much personal or social breakdown was liable to
occur among these people in the near future.
This article has been taken from a recently-published Unesco
study in the Population and Culture series entitled "Flight and
Resettlement" (Price: 8 3.50; 19/6; 950 fr.). Mr. Murphy's
observations are based on a visit made to Australia at the end
of 1950 and should not, therefore, be taken to indicate that
conditions have in no way changed since that time. The New
Australian movement and various vocational training schemes
have, without doubt, helped considerably to integrate the refugee
immigrant in the Australian community. However, many of
the social adjustment problems mentioned are still unsolved-.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
As an anthropologist sees it
A STEEL AXE THAT
DESTROYED A TRIBE
In a previous issue of the Unesco Courier (No. 7
1955; U.S.A., Oct. 1955) Dr. Metraux described how
the thirst for iron and steel tools among the Indian
tribes of Latin America led to bloodshed and war¬
fare. Here he tells how steel axes completely upset
the lives of an Australian aboriginal community.
To give a tribe of Australian aborigines steel to
replace the stone axe heads which they had used
since the earliest times would seem to many to
be a very modest step forward along the path of
economic advancement. But with primitive peo¬
ples the possible effects of the smallest changes made in
their way of life have to be weighed carefully in case the
results produced are entirely opposite to those intended.
A book recently published under the title of "Human
Problems in Technological Change" (edited by Edward H.
Spicer) includes a fascinating account by an experienced
ethnographer, Lauriston Sharp, of the upheavals which
occured in the life of an Australian tribe when, through
the generosity of missionaries, stone axes were exchanged
for steel ones. The tribe was the Yir Yoront, inhabiting
the west coast of the Cape York Peninsula, in the middle
of dry bush country with so little to recommend it that
26
there had been no white penetration until quite recently.
The Yir Yoront were scattered in small nomadic groups
over a huge tract of land. Almost all their activities were
connected with hunting and food-gathering. The stone
axe was the most important implement among their pri¬
mitive tools, essential for procuring and cooking food,
building their scanty shelters and keeping warm; it was
in fact, the very foundation of all their technical skills.
The stone axe was not only the principal tool but also a
factor making for social cohesion.
It was comparatively easy for the Yir Yoront to make
axes. Any man knows which branches are suitable for
making the handle, and where to get the gum and fibre
binding to hold the head in position. Their only difficulty
was to obtain stone axe-heads for an implement which
was easily damaged and often had to be replaced. These
axe-heads came from a distant part of the country,
inhabited by unknown tribes who traded them for spears
tipped with sting-ray spines, in whose production the
coastal tribes naturally specialized.
Trading relations were therefore established between
the regions supplying the two kinds of raw materials, and
the Yir Yoront used to play a very active part in this
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N' I. 1956
trade. Trading, like the manufacture of axes, was a male
monopoly. It gave rise to a network of partly commercial
and partly political relations, in which each group played
a clearly defined part. At the great initiation ceremo¬
nies, "buyers" and "sellers" used to meet and, combining
business with religious ceremonial, exchange axes for
spears. The profits to be made in this way were one of
the attractions of these festivities.
Although the men were the owners of the axes, these
were most often used by the women, who had to borrow
them from their husbands, fathers or uncles in conformity
with traditional rules. In the same way, young men who
had no trading partners were obliged to apply to their
elders whenever they needed an axe, which thus became
a symbol of virility, dominance of the male, and the
prestige of age.
The social function of the axe was also reflected in the
supernatural world and the myths of the people. One of
the clans forming the tribo the Sunlit Cloud Iguana
clan had, among its totems, the stone axe. Although this
clan's Ancestors were supposed to have been the discov¬
erers of the tool, the clan had no monopoly of the manu¬
facture of axes. On the other hand, it had the privilege
of symbolically representing the use of the implement in
the religious festivals.
This fact is also of some importance as, in the belief of
these tribes, everything taking place in their world had to
be an exact reproduction of the activities and incidents
which marked the life of their Ancestors when the world
was new. The present life is simply a repetition of the
mythical life of yore. With the function of the axe thus
. defined in its cultural and social context, it becomes easier
to understand the changes brought about by the advent
of steel.
In the course of recent years the Yir Yoront received
large numbers of steel axes, generously
distributed to them by missionaries,
either in return for work done on the
mission station, or as gifts to win over
the tribesmen. The missionaries
expected the implements to bring
about a rapid improvement in the
natives' living conditions. Even groups
living far from the mission stations
soon obtained axes for themselves
by barter.
In short, the steel axe quickly drove out the stone. But,
contrary to all expectations, it did nothing to improve
the welfare of the Yir Yoront. They gained by the change
in one way ; their work became easier and they had more
leisure than they had ever known. They used it, however,
not for enriching their lives, but for sleeping "an art at
which they were past masters." Had that been the only
result of the introduction of metal, there would be no
cause for regret. Unfortunately there were much more
serious consquences ; the steel axe shook the social
structure of the Yir Yoront to its foundations.
In the first place, the trading system which linked the
different groups was entirely disorganized. The bonds of
by
Alfred Metraux
friendship and
partnership be¬
tween i n d i v i-
duals of differ-
ent groups
ceased to have
any basis.
Goods no
longer flowed
from the coast
to the interior,
and vice versa.
The price the
tribes paid for
the axes was
their indepen¬
dence. They all
became depend¬
ent on the mis¬
sionaries, whose
principles for
distributing the axes must have appeared completely ir¬
rational and incomprehensible to the tribes.
The men were no longer the unquestioned masters of
the axes; their position was usurped by women and
adolescents, who acquired rights of property which had
formerly been considered an adult masculine prerogative.
The old men were particularly affected by this "technolo¬
gical revolution". Their dignity and age placed them at
a disadvantage in relation to the young men, who hired
themselves out as labourers or thronged the missions
when axes were being given away, and they thus came to
depend on the women and the young men, and so lost
their prestige and authority. For the first time, the word
"axe" was used with a feminine possessive a revolution
in the linguistic sphere as well.
The initiation festivals became less
exciting, since those who used to
come to them in search of stone axe-
heads were no longer drawn by the
need or prospect of a good bargain.
The political situation also changed.
In the past, relations between indi¬
viduals had been strictly governed by
the bonds of kinship, age and sex.
The tribe had no chiefs in the sense
in which we understand the world. Collective under¬
takings were organized in accordance with long-establish¬
ed tradition. When the tribesmen sought work in the
missions or on farms in order to get steel axes in return
for their labour, they had to submit to the European sys¬
tem of work. Foremen were put in charge of gangs and,
for the first time in their history, the Yir Yoront had
"bosses".
It was, however, in the sphere of sentiments and values
that the steel axe caused the greatest number of changes.
The destruction of the bonds of dependence and the
customary relationships very soon had repercussions on
the moral sense of the tribe. The idea of property was
weakened, and thefts and other offences became more
frequent.
Hitherto, the Yir Yoront had had a mythology which
provided answers for all eventualities. Whenever any
slight change occurred in their traditions, they added a
new episode to their myths so that the innovation became
a part of the traditional background. . With the steel axe,
such a re-adaptation was impossible.
Efforts were indeed made to attribute it to a clan whose
totems included the white ghosts, with which the white
men were associated; but the Sunlit Cloud Iguana clan
itself had already appropriated the honour of counting
this wonderful new implement among its totems. This
was only one of countless examples of the confusion
introduced by this technical change.
Today, the tribe is going rapidly downhill. The totem
system has been swept away by innovations which could
not be reconciled with it. With it have gone the religious
traditions and the cultural and social order which used to
hold the tribe together and provided the reason for
existence.
Far from bringing security and well-being to the Yir
Yoront, the steel axe has been primarily responsible for
their decline and may well lead to their ultimate
extinction.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
MISSION GOES TO THE 'DEVIL'
TO BUILD A SCHOOL
£3»n SS¿'##
4\ 4J ^jii
SPIRIT DANCER, Jobai, the local devil (actually, a mask of raffia,
shells and mirrors), visits the Klay Fundamental Education Centre.
mt,
FARMERS DOUBTED when experts proposed to
plant rice in local swamplands. They were amazed
by Daniel Behrman
If schools are now mushrooming in back-country villa¬
ges and hamlets of the West African republic of Li¬
beria, a great deal of credit should go to the bush
doctor of Dimeh and the devil of Belinga.
Dimeh and Belinga are both villages in the Klay district,
thirty miles west of Liberia's capital, Monrovia, where Li¬
berian educators and an international technical assis¬
tance team from unesco are working on a fundamental
education project to raise living standards.
Not only have 19 schools been opened in the Klay dis¬
trict itself, but more than two dozen new schools are now
being operated throughout Liberia by 46 men and women
who graduated
this year from
Liberia's Na¬
tional Funda¬
mental Educa¬
tion centre at
Klay.
The story of
julep (Joint
Unesco -Liberia
Education Pro¬
ject) was told
recently by
Marcel de
Clerck, a Bel¬
gian educator
who has return¬
ed to Paris af¬
ter completing
a technical as¬
sistance mission
for unesco in
Liberia. In the
Klay district, he
worked with
Roger Garraud
of France and
Srinovasa Rao
of India, the
two other mem-
PROUD FATHER is T.S. Koffa of Kran tribe bers of UNESCO'S
and a graduate from the Klay centre. He has team. The CO-
named his son after M. de Clerck, Unesco director of JU-
Technical Assistance expert. When christened, LEP is Dr. Na-
boys are carried four times round the house. thaniel V. Mas-
28
CHIEF'S DAUGHTER, Maima
Zwannah, is a pupil at theAmiina
fundamental education school.
saquoi, Liberia's Assis¬
tant Secretary of Public
Instruction.
The devil came to
Unesco's aid two years
ago when Mr. de Clerck
managed to convince the
members of Belinda's
Jobai Society (Jobai is
the name of a" spirit
commonly called a devil)
that their village needed
a school and that Jobai
should help. He did his
convincing by talking to
the devil' in appearance
a mask about waist-high
adorned with shells and
mirrors and covered with
raffia. During their con¬
versation (through a tri¬
bal *"interpreter") the
devil danced, but how it
danced is a secret which
no Jobai Society member
dare reveal. In the end, Belinga became the second vil¬
lage in the Klay district to build its own fundamental
education school.
As for the bush doctor, Boima Zina, he is one of the
3,000 members of a health co-operative launched by Li¬
berian educators and members of the unesco team in the
district. A payment of ten cents a year entitles members
to free care at a clinic at Amiina.
"We have the co-operation of the bush doctors and
this is extremely important", commented Mr. de Clerck,
"You see, they send us patients whom they have not been
able to cure*and sometimes, we send them patients".
He recalled the case of a woman with phlebitis who had
been treated by Dr. Paul Meyer, the Liberian government's
official doctor who visits the Amiina clinic every Monday
when anything from 80 to 100 patients may be awaiting
him. Dr. Meyer told his patient that she had to keep her
leg raised for 15 days, but she did not listen to him.
"So then we called on Boima Zina"fsaid Mr. de Clerck,
"He told the woman that she was sick because of an evil
medicine on the floor and she agreed to ¡keep her foot
off the floor for 15 days".
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
when swamp rice harvest proved to be twice
as plentiful as their own dryland plantings.
NEW GRADUATES leaving the Klay Fundamental Education Centre were the first group to complete
the course in July 1955. These young men will train rural workers for Liberia's education centres.
Last August, Boima Zina gave the Liberia-UNEsco team
a helping hand in its fight against infant mortality. He
called a meeting of chiefs and local notables at the villa¬
ge of Dimeh and, upon his recommendation, they institut¬
ed a thrice-weekly class for village midwives.
In addition to working in health and education, the fun¬
damental education team at Klay has also attacked the
basic problem of increasing food production in the dis¬
trict's villages. Local farmers traditionally have raised
"dryland rice" by burning clearings and planting one
crop, then moving on to another clearing.
But land is becoming scarce, for at least an eight-year
growth of vegetation is required before burning produces
sufficient ash to fertilize a crop. In these villages, the
months from June to October are known as "hunger time"
because not a
grain of rice is
to be had and
families must
subsist for food
on manioc.
However, the
Klay district is
covered with
swamps. Last
spring, the Li¬
beria-U n e s c o
team at Klay
called in the
services of Mr.
Yartu, a young-
agricultural ex¬
pert from Sierra
Leone working
for the Liberian
Government, to
show how crops
of swamp rice
could be raised.
As trainees at
the Klay centre
dug canals and
built dikes for
the future rice- JOBAI'S INTERPRETER is the only person
fields, funda- able to understand the mysterious devil
mental educa- language. As he dances he holds a secret
tion became a charm to protect Jobai from other devils.
MOSLEM PRIEST, Kimael Malik,
veteran teacheratthe Amiinaschool.
He is also adviser on Moslem affairs.
standing joke in the
villages where local
farmers could not decide
whether the experimen¬
ters intended to plant
rice on the dikes or in
the canals.
When young shoots of
paddy began to rise
above the swamps, how¬
ever, the farmers chang¬
ed their minds. Yields
from the swamp rice de¬
monstration farms prov¬
ed to be double those of
the old method of plant¬
ing dry rice in clearings.
Improving living con¬
ditions in the Klay dis¬
trict is only one side
of the fundamental edu¬
cation centre's task. Its
main job is to train rural
workers for fundamen¬
tal education schools
throughout Liberia and graduates of its first class are
now scattered all over the country.
The Liberian government had adopted a policy of
paying these workers among the highest salaries in rural
Liberia and their word carries weight in their commu¬
nities. "'I was amazed myself when I heard about one of
our graduates in the Bopolo district", said Mr. de Clerck.
"When he arrived, he called a meeting of the local chiefs
and, after he had explained his programme to them, they
donated 15,000 acres of land to help him carry it out."
Mr. de Clerck, a former professor at Ostend, is one of
unesco's veteran technical assistance workers. Before
going to Liberia, he completed a two-year mission in El
Salvador, Central America, where he aided in a funda¬
mental education campaign covering a district of 4,000
inhabitants.
In his opinion, there are no secrets to his trade. "It is
just a question of confidence", he said, "You have to live
with the people you are trying to help and you have to
live with them long enough for them to forget that you
are an outsider."
Unesco Photos : De Clerck, Garraud, Rao.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
PAINTING
WITH WAX
AND FIRE
Copyright Studio Roger Viollet.
Copyright Studio Yves Hervochon.
Artists and scientists
delve into the lost
secret of encaustic
painting a long
forgotten art technique
by
Lucio and Giuseppe
Attinelli
WIDE-EYED BEAUTY of a young woman (left)
was captured by an encaustic painter over seventeen
centuries ago. Portrait, believed to depict a member
of the family of Pollius Sotor, Archon (magistrate) of
Thebes is on wood and was found in a necropolis at
Fayoum, Egypt. Bacchante (above) was executed as
an encaustic on marble by a contemporary French
painter, Helen Mai, who seems to have re-discovered
methods used by ancient painters. Encaustic fresco
(opposite page), depicting two women playing with
a goat, was found at Pompeii. Painted in the first
century A.D., it is now in the Louvre Museum.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
When volcanic dust and ashes
rained down upon the town of
Pompeii, life there expired.
But the stones of Pompeii have lived
to tell its story, and, more amazing
still, a strange type of painting resist¬
ed the heat and dust to provide later
generations with a fascinating glimp¬
se of an art which might be said to
have disappeared with the Roman
Empire.
Through the centuries many at¬
tempts have been made to find the
secret of this durable painting,
known as encaustic. Only recently
Italian scientists gave the most
exhaustive chemical tests to samples
of encaustic art from Pompeii
without discovering the secret of the
ancient formula. It looked as if it
would remain locked in mystery.
A Greek word for it
What in fact is this encaustic
painting which is, in its way,
the forefather of all modern
forms of painting? Its origins go back
to the dawn of European civilization.
Homer spoke of the ships with red
bows and Ovid has described* a ship's
stern painted and decorated with
burnt colours. Here, perhaps, is one
part of the secret, for the word en¬
caustic is derived from the Greek
egkaustikos meaning "burnt". All we
know is that the encaustic painters
used heated or liquid wax applied to
wood and stone in such a way that
they could be washed, scrubbed,
heated or left in the burning rays of
the sun without suffering damage.
Perhaps the most complete des¬
cription of this ancient form of paint¬
ing is found in Pliny. He has describ¬
ed three methods, all of which were
apparently in general use by the Ro¬
mans. The first, and most common
of these, he calls the spatula method.
In this a mixture of resin, wax and
colour was heated and applied to the
surface with a spatula. . This techni¬
que was probably used in Pompeii and
Herculaneum.
The second, used on polished wood
and ivory, consisted of saturating the
wax with colour and then applying
the "'paint" with a stylus. Roman
ships were usually painted by means
of the third method whereby liquefied
wax was applied to the planks with
a brush. This surface set so hard
that it was completely impervious to
effects of sun and sea water. How¬
ever, all three forms produced paint¬
ings of a nature far more durable
than anything which has been seen
since.
During the excavations at the
Graeco-Roman necropolis at Hawara
in Egypt portraits were found in
The Unesco Courier. Nr 1. 1956
which the vitality of expression and
the perfect state of preservation gave
eloquent testimony of their resistance
to the ravages of time. The dura¬
bility of wax, and its power to with¬
stand the effects of the atmosphere
were therefore well-known to the an¬
cient Greeks, Romans and Egyptians.
Pillaged portraits
It is this amazing resistance of an¬
cient encaustic paintings which
has spurred archaeologists and
others to try and discover their hidden
secret. Much of their research has, un¬
fortunately, been frustrated by wilful
vandalism. Such a case occurred in
Egypt in 1887 when an ancient ne¬
cropolis was pillaged by Bedouins
searching for salt on the desert's edge.
Everything was either burnt or
destroyed with the exception of some
portraits found in the mummy wrap¬
pings, which, according to ancient
Egyptian custom, depicted the de¬
funct person. These portraits were
sold and eventually found their way
to Vienna.
The scene at this necropolis has
been vividly described by a French
historian, Dr. Fouquet, who saw the
ground strewn with mummified
skeletons. At each mum- (Cont'd
my's head was a small on next
board on which was en- PaSe)
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Art of wax and fire
(Continued)
graved the name, quality and place
of birth. On the mummy casings
themselves were encaustic paintings
on wood, the majority of which were
in a perfect state of preservation.
The decline of the Roman Empire
saw also a decline in the art of en¬
caustic painting. But, later, with the
triumph of the Church it re-appeared
in Constantinople. Eusebius, the Pa¬
triarch of Constantinople, in 339 A.D.,
has described a vast encaustic paint¬
ing showing the Emperor Constantine
hurling a dragon (symbol of the
Church's enemies) into the waves.
After centuries of splendour, en¬
caustic art finally died out. Perhaps
it was thought too difficult and too
involved for the newer painters in
tempera and oils who were then
starting to come to the fore.
Delacroix dabbled
It was not until the eighteenth cen¬
tury that revival of interest
became apparent. In 1755 the
Paris Académie des Inscriptions
opened a competition to probe the
mystery of encaustic art. Work done
by two French painters, Caylus and
Bachelier, for this competition was not
crowned with success, although it did
have the effect of re-awakening pub¬
lic interest in this lost art form.
In the 19th century Delacroix and
his pupils experimented with wax .
painting but without the applica¬
tion of heat. Despite this they achiev¬
ed some significant results, and a good
Illustration of the work done can be
seen in the painting now hanging in
the French National Assembly show¬
ing Attila with his Huns withdrawing
across the ravaged plains
of Italy.
Tentative experiments
were also made in Italy,
but nearer our own times
a painter of great origi¬
nality, Henri Cros, after a
prolonged study of the
classical sources, produced
several paintings of wood¬
en horses. Although the
colours do not have the
brilliancy of true encaus¬
tic painting they do bear
some resemblance to it.
Unfortunately his work
was brought to an end by
his sudden death.
Today, a French paint¬
er, Helen Mai, living in
Paris, has attacked the
problem with renewed "
vigour. Piecing together
the fragments of informa¬
tion available from cent¬
uries-old documents, she
experimented and tested
a variety of chemical
combinations over a pe^
riod of many years.
Through her research and study she
has evolved a formula which, to judge
by her paintings, seems to correspond
to the work done by the encaustic
painters of ancient times.
The similarity between her paint¬
ings and the classical Roman works
is indeed striking.
One of her works, La Bacchante, an
encaustic painting on marble, for
example, shows traces of firing, and
suffers no damage when repeatedly
washed, scrubbed and brushed with
soap and water.
Among Helen Mai's other encaustic
paintings is a series on wood on the
Comedia dell'Arte and a Road to
Calvary specially done for a church
in N.W. France.
Although Helen Mai has not yet re¬
vealed the secret of her technique,
her achievement may well serve to re¬
vive interest in the lost art of en¬
caustic painting.
BAYEUX TAPESTRY SCENES
(left) were reproduced on stone
and on canvas as encaustic paint¬
ings by French artist Helen Mai.
(Tapestry depicts events in Anglo-
Norman history during llth
century). Contrasting subject, an
impish Scapin (stock character
from the Italian Commedia dell'
Arte) above, is also by Helen Mai,
Copyright Studio Yves Hervochort.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. N1* 1. 1956
Letters to th d i t o r
Sir,
As I regularly read the Unesco Cou¬
rter, my attention was drawn by the
pictures on page 32 of No. 5 (1955) :
"Unesco in Pictures" (Learning to
"hear" with their eyes). I read, in refer¬
ence to the Institute for Deaf Mutes
at Bandung, that it was "the only one
of its kind in Indonesia". There are in
fact two, and a third is being bu'lt.
Besides the Institute at Bandung there
is also an Institute at Wonosobo (Cen¬
tral Java) which up till now educated
children of both sexes. In November of
this year the boy pupils will move to a
new building, also at Wonosobo. The
Wonosobo Institute is under the direc¬
tion of the Reverend Sisters and the
newly-built one will.be directed by the
Brothers of Charity, who are well-
known in Belgium for their institutes
for deaf-mutes (L'Institut Royal des
Aveugles et des Sourds-muets, at Brus¬
sels and l'Institut Royal des Sourds-
muets at Ghent.)
The new building is not only projec¬
ted for deaf-mute children of primary-
school age, but also older boys who are
taught a profession (shoemaking, print¬
ing, weaving, etc.) so that when they
leave school, they are able to find their
own way in human society.
The new project cannot be financed
by the Brothers themselves, so the build¬
ing costs are partly borne by the Indo¬
nesian Government which really under¬
stands the necessity of this charitable
work. But as for the educational ap¬
pliances, the machinery, the tools, the
installation of electricity, the direction
of the school would certainly appreciate
help.
D. Baak.
Brothers of Charity,
2 Djalan Bruderan,
Purworedjo, Indonesia.
Sir,
We noted with regret that in the re¬
cent issue of The unesco courier devo¬
ted to women the name of our League
was om'tted from the list of women's
organizations working with Unesco...
You did, however, include the World
Union of Women for International Con¬
cord to which we are affiliated (without
being dependent on it). We were in
fact instrumental in bringing to the
union's attention the work accomplish¬
ed by Unexo and the support which it
merited. The fact that much work is
done on the national or local level in
no way implies that we are not working
on the human plane...
Leontine Roux.
General Secretary,
International League of Mothers
and Women Teachers for the
Promotion of Peace,
Clermont-Ferrand, France.
Editor's Note : By a regrettable error, the
International League of Mothers and Women
Teachers for the Promotion of Peace was
omitted from the list of women's organiza¬
tions on page 40 of onr issue \'o. 11, 1955,
and also the names of two more organiza¬
tions The International Council of Women
Psychologists, C/o Ur. Harriet T. O'Sheu,
Psychology Department, Bürde University,
Lafayette, Indiana, U.S.A. and the Interna¬
tional Council of Social Democratic Women,
8, Motcomb St., London, S.W.I. , Gt. Britain.
Sir,
As Chairman of the Unesco Club in
the Orns Department Teachers' Train¬
ing College, I want to congratulate
you on the unesco courier which
makes continual progress. It is interest¬
ing and within everyone's reach, and is
always full of valuable information. I
have just received the Issue on "The
Conquest of the Desert" (No. 8/9 1955
: U.S. November 1955). Congratulations!
You are doing good work; keep it up.
R. Navailh.
Teachers, Training College,
¡\lencon, Orne, France.
Sir,
I have received a copy of the unesco
courier of June (U.S.A. edition)
"PuppetsMagic World in Miniature"
with a great deal of pleasure. I am not
sure to whom I am indebted for this,
but I would like to congratulate you on
this most interesting issue and to thank
you very much for its receipt.
Cecil Stavordale.
Stavordale Marionettes
Finchley, London.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Unesco's National distributors from
whom the English, French and Spanish
editions of the UNESCO COURIER
can be obtained are listed below.
ALGERIA. Editions de l'Empire, 28,
rue Michelet, Algiers.
ARGENTINA. Editorial Sudamericana
S.A., Alsina 500, Buenos Aires.
Inter-Prensa, Florida 229, Buenos Aires.
AUSTRALIA. Oxford University Press,
346, Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
AUSTRIA. Wilhelm Frick Verlag, 27
Graben, Vienna 1.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15, rue du Tilleul, Ganval
(Brabant).
BOLIVIA. Libreria Selecciones, Avenida
Camacho 369, Casilla 972, La Paz.
BRAZIL. Livraria Agir Editora, Rua
México 98-B, Caixa Postal 3291, Rio de
Janeiro.
CAMBODIA. Librairie Albert Portail,
14, Avenue Boulloche, Phnom-Penh.
CANADA. University oí Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5112, Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, Colombo I.
CHILE. Libreria Universitaria, Alameda
B. O'Higgins 1059, Santiago.
COLOMBIA. Libreria Central, Carrera,
6-A No 14-32, Bogota.
COSTA RICA. Trejos Hermanos,
Apartado 1313, San Jose.
CUBA. Unesco Centro Regional en el
Hemisferio Occidental, Calle 5 No. 306
Vedado, Apartado 1358, Havana.
CYPRUS. M.E. Constantinides, P.O.
Box 473, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd.,
30, Ve Smeckach, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6, Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
DOMINICAN REPUBLIC. Libreria
Dominicana, Mercedes 49, Apartados de
Correos 656, Ciudad Trujillo.
ECUADOR. Librería Científica, Luque
233, Casilla 362, Guayaquil.
EGYPT. La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency,
P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FORMOSA. The World Book Company
Ltd., 99, Chungking South Road, Sec¬
tion I, Taipeh, Taiwan.
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, 19, Ave¬
nue Kléber, Paris, 1 6\ CCP. Paris
12598-48.
Sales & Distribution Division, 19, Ave¬
nue Kléber, Paris, 16'.
FRENCH WEST INDIES. Librairie
J. Bocage, rue Lavoir, Fort de France,
Martinique.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerscrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HAITI. Librairie « A la Caravelle »,
36, rue Roux, B.P. I 1 I, Port-au-Prince.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149,
Budapest 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I.
17, Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13.
36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots :
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi.
Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Himalaya
House, Hornby Road, Bombay I.
INDONESIA. G.CT. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Jakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road, P.O. Box 4101, Tel-
Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Cas el la Pos¬
tale 552, Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99,
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Torî-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous & Co., Dar
ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O. Box 66, Am¬
man.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
LEBANON. Librairie Universelle, Ave¬
nue des Français, Beirut.
LIBERIA. Momolu Kamara, 69, Front
& Gurley Streets, Monrovia.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand'Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26, Kings-
way, Valletta.
MEXICO. Libreria y Ediciones Emilio
Obregon, Avenida Juarez No. 30, Mexico
D.F.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni-
jhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100, Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60, The Mall.
Lahore.
Ferozsons : Bunder Road, Karachi.
Ferozsons : 35, The Mall, Peshawar.
PANAMA. Agencia Internacional de
Publicaciones, Plaza de Arango No. 3,
Apartado 2052, Panama, R.P.
PARAGUAY. Agencia de Librerías de
Salvador Nizza, Calle Pte. Franco No 39/
43, Asuncion.
PERU. Libreria Mejia Baca, Jirón Azan-
garo 722, Lima.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
PORTUGAL. Publicacoes Europa-Ame-
rica Ltda, Rua das Flores 45, I, Lisbon.
PUERTO RICO. Pan American Book
Co., P.O. Box 35 I I, San Juan 17.
SPAIN. Librería Científica Medinaceli,
Duque de Medinaceli 4, Madrid.
Ediciones Iberoamericans, S.A., Pizarro 19,
Madrid.
SURINAM. Radhakishun & Co. Ltd.
(Book- Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36,
Paramaribo.
SWEDEN. A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaten 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5,
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva.
TANGIER. Paul Fekete, 2, rue Cook.
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TUNISIA. Victor Boukhors, 4, rue
Nocard, Tunis.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469,
Istiklat Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3, Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569, London. S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Nuional Agency
for Internacional Publications, 500, Fifth
Avenue, New York 36, N.Y,
URUGUAY. Unesco Centro de Coope¬
ración Científica para América Latina,
Bulevar Artigas 1320-24, Casilla de Cor¬
reo 859, Montevideo.
Oficina de Representación de Editoriales,
18 de Julio, 1333, Montevideo.
VENEZUELA. Librería Villegas Vene¬
zolana, Av. Urdaneta - Esq. Las Ibarras,
Edif. Riera, Apartado 2439, Caracas.
VIET-NAM. Librairie Nouvelle Albert
Portail, 185-193, rue Catinat, B.P. 283,
Saigon.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije 27M l, Belgrade.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
J.APPING NATURE'S
RESERVOIRS: The first group
of civil engineers and geologists
from the Institute of Hydrogeo-
logy, Istanbul, Turkey, which
was created in 1952 with the
help of Unesco's Technical
Assistance Mission to Turkey,
is now taking part in an all-
out plan to develop Turkey's
underground water resources.
Teams consisting of a geologist
and a civil engineer have gone
to the country's ten principal
river basins to carry out inten¬
sive water prospecting and to
make plans for the fullest ex¬
ploitation of this resource.
TREASURES OF THE
NILE: Egypt is setting up a
special research centre for
studying Ancient Egyptian
art and civilization. In res¬
ponse to the Egyptian Go¬
vernment's request for aid in
forming a local and complete
collection of archives for this
purpose, Unesco is sending
Mrs. Desroches-Ncblecouit,
Curator of Egyptian Antiqui¬
ties at the Louvre Museum,
to Cairo as chief of mission.
The centre's first task will
be to plan the preservation
of important monuments
such as the Temple of Abu
Simbel in Nubia, which may
be threatened if a proposed
new dam is constructed there.
NiI EW LIFE FOR OLD
MASTERS: Rome has been
chosen as the site for a new
international centre for the pre¬
servation and restoration of
paintings, sculptures, ancient
monuments and other "cultural
property" by Unesco's Executive
Board. The Centre will make
available the latest world-wide
developments in giving ancient
works of art a new life. It will
also make suggestions on top
priority preservation work and
prepare a programme of re¬
search work to be carried out
on an international level. When
agreements with the Italian
Government have been con¬
cluded Member States of Unesco
will be asked to participate in
the work of the Centre.
ENERGY FROM THE
SUN: Seven hundred scien¬
tists from 30 nations met
recently in Phoenix, Arizona
U.S.A., for the world's first
Symposium on Solar Energy.
The sun's rays have already
been harnessed for the pro¬
duction of electrical energy,
for irrigation and refrigera¬
tion, for cooking and the dis¬
tillation of sea water, but
only a fraction of their im¬
mense potentialities is being
used. Statistics quoted by
34
delegates showed that, alth¬
ough the initial cost of solar
energy installations is heavy
their operation is extremely
economical. Solar plants cculd
provide an additional source
of cheap power, particularly
in under-developed countries.
Dr. Bessel Kok of the Ne¬
therlands stated "the' pro¬
duction of our farms and
forests could be increased in
theory from ten to twenty-
fold" if better use were made
of the sun's power.
s<'CIENCE IN SCHOOLS:
Seventeen British industrial
concerns have contributed one
and a half million pounds ster¬
ling to establish a fund for the
advancement of science teaching
world's leading host country
for foreign students is the
United States with 33,833
students, "Study Abroad" re¬
ports. France ranks second
with 9,329 students, and the
United Kingdom third with
8,619 students. In Latin
America, Mex.co heads the
list with 2,039 foreign stu¬
dents, while in Asia Japan
leads with 3,768 students.
More than 24 per cent of
the students who go abroad
study the humanities, 17.7
per cent go in for medicine,
15.1 per cent for engineering,
14.7 per cent for the social
sciences and 11.9 for the
natural sciences. Leading
donor country is the United
States with 17,356 fellowships
offered to foreign students,
«ATOMS FOR PEACE' AGENCY
APPROVED BY U.N. ASSEMBLY
The United Nations General Assembly recently gave unanimous
approval to the setting up of an International Atomic Energy Agency.
It also recommended that a second international technical confer¬
ence similar to the "Atoms for Peace" Conference, held in Geneva
last August, should fake place in two or three years' time. News
of progress in using atomic power for peace has come recently
from four European countries. At Marcoule, in France, the first
of three reactors being built by the Atomic Energy Commission
will start producing power early this year to operate an electricity
plant. An atomic reactor is being built inside a mountain at Halden,
Norway. By next year it will be supplying steam to a pulp and
paper plant. About one third of the electric current needed for
the Brussels Exhibition in 1958 will be provided by an atomic
reactor constructed in Belgium. After the exhibition, the reactor
will generate power for Belgium's railway system. In Western Ger¬
many, the first industrial atomic power plant will be built as
soon as the Atomic Energy Law is passed by the Bonn Parliament.
in schools. Aim of this fund is
to provide an adequate flow of
qualified scientists and techno¬
logists into British industry.
STUDY ABROAD: More
than 50,000 fellowships and
scholarships offered to for¬
eign students by institutions
in over 100 countries and
territories are listed in the
1955-1956 edition of " Study
Abroad" published by Unes¬
co. This new seventh edition
of "Study Abroad" also in¬
cludes a report on Unesco's
third annual survey of for-,
eign student enrolments in
universities and institutions
of higher education through¬
out the world. The survey
shows that, in 1954, 125,000
students were studying in
foreign countries. The
followed by France with 5,491
and Egypt with 3,588. Other
chapters of "Study Abroad"
which can be obtained from
Unesco House, Paris, or
through Unesco distributors
(see opposite page) price:
S2. 00; 10/6& or bJO French
francs, deal with the fellow¬
ship programmes of the u*. n.
and its specialized agencies,
and general guidance to
students.
NiI EW AFRICAN UNIVER¬
SITY: A new university, to be
known as the University of the
Belgian Congo and Ruanda-
Urundi, is to be established with
headquarters at Elizabethville.
Various schools and faculties
will be set up throughout the
region according to special local
needs. An autonomous institu
tion, the new university will
have the same rights and pri¬
vileges as those in Belgium.
WAR ON ILLITERACY:
Bolivia and Ecuador have
joined Costa Rica and Nica¬
ragua in a large scale cam¬
paign to wipe out illiteracy
within their borders. The
campaign, launched by the
Organization of American
States, aims at establishing
100.000 reading centres . in
twenty Latin American re¬
publics. "Popular libraries"
will be set up in 1,500 com¬
munities of Bolivia and
Ecuador. More than 3,000
centres being set up in Costa
Rica and Nicaragua have
already received libraries of
textbooks.
BiÍETTER FISH CROPS:
The private life of the fish îxom
the egg to the frying pan re¬
cently had the sp:tlight turned
on it in Java, Indonesia, at an
international course run by
the U. N. Food and Agriculture
Organization, the Indonesian
Government and the Indo-Paci-
fic Fisheries Council. The course
offered advanced training in
taking stock of inland fishery
resources and putting them to
the best possible use. Indonesia
was selected as the site because
. inland fishing is one of its main
industries. Many Indonesian
farmers are "fish-farmers", rais¬
ing crops of fish in ponds, lakes
or rivers.
BOOM IN EDUCATION:
One of the world's fastest
growing educational systems
has been taking shape in
Libya during the past four
years with help from Unes¬
co's technical assistance mis¬
sion to that country. Unesco
aid has covered teacher train¬
ing, physical education, arts
and crafts, manual train¬
ing, demonstration schools,
rural and adult education.
A men's teacher training
college in Tripoli now has an,
enrollment of 921 students
compared with 88 in 1951.
This year 292 women teacher
students started the course
compared with 28 in 1951.
Enrolment in boys' and girls'
P'imary rchools has also shot
up during this period. Libya
is a country with little natu¬
ral wealth, and the Libyans
know that the skills of their
people constitute their largest
untapped resource. The de¬
sire for education is so great
that even kindergarten clas¬
ses, opened for 30 pupils,
receive hundreds of requests
for places.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
A dwinüow open on
the world' in 1955
No. I. (U.S.A.-April)
FORGOTTEN SHADOWS
, The birth of the cinema
The cinema and its origins	J. Guerif
Newsreel cameramen of yesterday
The cinema todaya world picture	 J.Douglas
Dreaming with open eyes (Audience reaction) 	 W. D. Wall
Magic shadows (Photo story of cinema history)
Other Articles
Knife and brush painting in ancient China	 Chou Ling
20th century Gullivers (Measuring the universe)	 A. Gille
No. 2. (U.S.A.-May)
AWAKENING CONTINENT
Latin America in new perspective
Land-hunger on top of the Andes	 A. Metraux
Brazil's polygon of drought E. Aubert de la Rue
"Los Úneseos" in Latin America D. Behrman
( I) The Mayans modernize
(2) Don Quixote of the radio
(3) Boom town on the Pan-American Highway	
On looking into a Mochican urn	 J. Carrera Andrade
No. 3-4. (U.S.A.-June)
PUPPETS
Magic world in miniature
How do they get away with it ?	 M. Kurtz
"Shakes v. Shav" (A G.B.S. puppet play)	 J.Douglas
Crefalito (Popular puppet teacher) G. A. Gomez
Indian- cavalcade	T. S. Satyan
Puppets of the Far East R. Dhunjibhoy
Japan's "Bunraku" puppet theatre
My name is Mr. Punch G. Sigisbert
Strange tales from the puppet world	
Puppets, source of literary inspiration J. Chesnais
Puppets in Russia, Turkey, Italy, Czechoslovakia & France	
Other Articles (U.S.A.-July)
Sirs-el-Layyan (Education in an Arab village)	 G. Fradier
Ghost village comes to life (Work campers in action)	
Munich's youth library	 B. Gnauck
The four-handled jars (Deciphering a lost tongue)	 D. Gillie
Is good health a world threat ?	 J. V. Manevy
Stamp of Friendship (U.S. edition only)
No. 5. (U.S.A.-August)
EXPLORING THE OCEANS WITH SCIENCE
Science and the sea
Strange facts about Neptune's realm	 F. Le Lionnais
Hunting the whale	D. Gunston
Migrating mammoths P- Budker
Bread from the sea C. Drummond
Fish in myth and legend J. Marabini
Other Articles
The Greek Meteora (Rocks "hung in the air")	 G. A. Sotiriou
Sugar bowl in the date palm (New Iraq industry) 	 G. Fradier
No. 6. (U.S.A.-September)
TWISTED IMAGES
How nations see each other
Pictures in our heads	O. Klineberg
An Englishman takes a look at Americans	 D. W. Brogan
Better understanding through foreign languages	 H. Kerst
A French village sums up foreigners	 L. Bernot & R. Blancart
Stereotyped images in cartoons G. Gadoffre
Other Articles
The Sudan	A- shaw
I 955: Big year of decision for T.V	 H. Cassirer
Art Renaissance for Ecuador's Indians	 L.Linke
Youth volunteers across the face of India H. P. Müller
No. 7. (U.S.A.-October)
SCHOOLS IN THE SAND
Saving half a million Arab refugee children
Exiled in the desert	M. Winter
Please give us schools F.Walter
Magna Cum Laude refugee students	
Other Articles
Chinese Opera B. Gargl
Masterpieces you can now buy	 J. Leymarie
Jungle Indians with an axe to grind A. Metraux
Korea's thirty million textbooks
No. 8-9. (U.S.A.-November)
CONQUEST OF THE DESERT
One-fourth of the earth (Unesco and arid lands)	 J. Swarbrick
Conquest of the desert	B. T. Dickson
Science safari in the U.S.A
Harnessing power from desert winds	 E. W. Golding
Jules Verne setting (France's solar factory) D. Behrman
The Camelfacts and fables	 B. & K.'Schmidt-Nielsen
Art in the Sahara J. Gabus
Food crops without soil J.W.E.H. Sholto Douglas
Probing nature's arid land mysteries	 H.I.S. Thirlaway
Rain "made to order"
Invoking the rain gods
The myth about the tropics	 W.S.S. Ladell
A desert steeped in fog G. de Reparaz
No. 10. (U.S.A.-December)
THE UNITED NATIONS
A frank appraisal
Dear Jenny (A father writes about the U.N.)	 H. Abraham
42nd Street and First Avenue (60 Nations on I 8 acres)	
The U.N. from A to Z (Pocket dictionary)
Stamps from many lands (Salute to the U.N.)
Other Articles
Chance of a square meal (F.A.O. Anniversary report)	
The atomic future today	G. Wendt
No. II. (U.S.A.-January 1956)
ARE WOMEN INFERIOR BEINGS?
The changing outlook in politics,
employment, society and the home
Women on the march	A. Myrdal
Are women the inferior sex ? A. Montagu
The long road from the plough	 E. Almasy
The "white cap" day (Swedish student celebrations)	
Anti-feminism and Eve's inhibitions M. Duverger
The march to the polls
Custom versus the law
Women in primitive society	 A. Metraux
The hand that rocks the cradle L. Noblet
The vanishing veil A. H. Hourani
Five-star figures from the past G. Cabrini
No. 12. (U.S.A.-February 1956)
HAPPY NEW YEAR AROUND THE WORLD
A voyage by "magic carpet" to the
festivals, rites and customs of many lands
New Year gods and torchlight processions	 G. Cabrini
Rituals and symbols of time reborn M. Eliade
How the gift idea started	 C. Levi-Strauss
New Year cards down the ages F. Christiaen
Festival of the Dayak head-hunters
Happy New Year in Bali
Living ghosts of the Incas A. Metraux
India: land of many calendars	 K.Singh
Colourful fairs of Assam and Bengal
Elephants made elegant for the feast
Lobsters for a long life in Japan S. Kimura
Night of the goats and gilded ploughs	 E. Falck
Lanterns, gongs and fireworks	 Lin Yutang
Tug-of-war with Himalayan spirits
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Courier i "^Courier
çp**
ftfH-'*
. ORGOTTEN
SHADOWS
rlh of the (
JiCouiier
EXPLORING .t£¿£
THE OCEANS i./9%
WITH SCIENCE / ÏWBr
M*.~°^m 1
WL ¿ff¿ 1
1
*** s
t» ï J
Il MC
Ha * hûm tu* il» H
I fhÇetSBI-*. Courier
CONQUEST
OF THE
DESERT
Samisiisj pttt
Um m t wind
Prss »ni mm «(
artificial rais
witfioM seil
itrttj«, rieh «ri
Ml
.wgiff«Jief«1
TWISTED1 '
ARE WOMEN
INFERIOR
BEINGS ?
THE CHANGING
OUTLOOK IN
-politics
-education
-employment
-society
-the home
rs
V
r
b
ira
HAPPY
NEW YEAR
AROUND
THE WORLD
A voyage hy
magic carpet
to the festivals
rites S customs
of many lands
A YEAR'S SUBSCRIPTION
8 / - ; 400 French francs or Jfl.00
]]>
</page>
</document>
