<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078175eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
a M
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
M liM
OCTOBER 1960 (13th year) - Price : 1/-stg. (U.K.) - 30 cents (U. S.) - 0,70 NF. (FRANCE)
THE EXECUTIVE BOARD OF UNESCO
NOTING with deep concern the recrudescence of manifes¬
tations of racial hatred, anti-Semitism and discrimination,
which have occurred in various regions in recent months,
particularly in the Union of South Africa, leading to
serious social disorder and loss of life
RECALLING the terms of the Universal Declaration
of Human Rights and of the Constitution of Unesco,
which condemn all discrimination against any person on
grounds of race, religion or sex
CALLS upon the governments of all Member States to
take all steps in their power to combat every form of
racial discrimination, anti-Semitism, violence and hatred
whfch may occur within their territories.
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
L'**-*»
% %
H*»'
BEWILDERED AND TERRIFIED
with S.S. sub-machine guns point¬
ing at him, this little boy is march¬
ed with other, Warsaw Jews to
death in a Nazi extermination camp.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
îer
OCTOBER 1960
1 3 T H YEAR
Contents
No. 10
4 RACISM, THE SOCIAL CANCER OF OUR TIME
6 RACE, PREJUDICE AND EDUCATION
By Cyril Bibby
13 A LOOK AT MODERN ANTI-SEMITISM
By Léon Poliakov
18 MEIN KAMPF
21 THE RACIAL LANDSCAPE OF LATIN AMERICA
By Alfred Metraux
24 X-RAY OF THE RACIST MIND
By Marie Jahoda
28 FRANK CONVERSATION AT AN EMPTY TABLE
By Khushwant Singh
29 THE CINEMA SAYS NO ! TO RACISM
By Louis Marcorelles
32 THE DIARY OF ANNE
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7«, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Alexandre Leventis
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Celia Bertin
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 60.1.151 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.); 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7«.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
1?
H^^ ACISM has been called the social cancer of our time. It gnaws away slowly and
insidiously until it invades the whole organism of society and erupts in violence
and death.
In the years immediately following the Second World War it may have seemed that racism
was definitely on the decline. Racial hatred had logically led from discrimination to acts of indes¬
cribable horror and death camp massacres carried out on an industrial scale. The shock and
repulsion that swept the world so discredited the doctrine of racism that it dared not show
itself cynically and blatantly as it had done before.
The struggle against Hitlerism had had its own logic too. One could hardly battle racism
and still practice it, even indirectly. And so, in the countries united against Nazism many bar¬
riers of discrimination and prejudice tumbled and a spirit of greater tolerance marked rela¬
tions between the different races.
But the cancer of racism was by no means extirpated.
Human memory is short, and the gruesome past slips or is pushed easily into oblivion. The
death camps of yesterday have apparently not been sufficient to put an end to the doctrine that
one race is superior to another. The older people in many countries have forgotten them; the new
generations barely know they existed. Furthermore, ten years of fanatical racism sowed dra¬
gon's teeth around the world and one cannot tell when they may germinate and lead to a terri¬
ble harvest.
Today, the excesses of racialism are universally decried and condemned, but the racist out¬
look or attitude which is at the root of these excesses and makes them possible is still with us.
It is all the more dangerous since ours is the century of the great awakening and accession to
indépendance of the coloured peoples of the world who have long been its victims. Instead of
being accepted as normal and foreseeable, the mistakes and hesitations made by the newly-
independent peoples as they pass through the trying initial periods of autonomy are interpreted
in racist terms by certain people as proof of racial inferiority. In its turn, the racism of the
white man has given rise to a reaction among coloured people which, rightly or wrongly, is des¬
cribed as "counter-racism".
Many public and private organizations, both national and international, have sensed the dan¬
ger of latent racism in the world and have taken steps to combat it. Through science and edu¬
cation the twin means at its disposal Unesco has been at grips with the problem since the
first years of its creation. (The Unesco Courier too has devoted several past issues to racism.)
Last year and again this year racism became front page news once more. An epidemic of
anti-Semitism in many countries and the massacre of negroes in South Africa set off a wave
of world protest culminating in the condemnation of such acts by the Human Rights Commis¬
sion of the United Nations. At Unesco, where feelings ran high, the Executive Board in a spe¬
cial meeting voted a strongly-worded resolution (see partial text on cover) denouncing racial dis¬
crimination, anti-Semitism, violence and hatred, and called on governments and Unesco to cam¬
paign against these evils and to propagate "the doctrine of the total equality and kinship of all
men and women everywhere."
If racism is to be eliminated as an active ideology of our time we must know more of the
terrain on which it develops. One thing we do know: the place where preventive measures can
be most effective is in the school and in the home. That is why Unesco has set out to inform
both the teacher and the general public of the basic facts established by modern science.
Neither anthropology, nor biology nor for that matter any science offers the slightest
justification for racist dogmas, which are based on discredited scientific notions or emotional
irrationalism. The full facts still need to be placed before every person so that the social cancer
of racism may one day be eradicated.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
Courtesy Cahiers du Cinema
CRY, MY BELOVED COUNTRY
MASSACRE AT SHARPEVILLE. This Is the picture that shocked the world last March when nearly 100 Africans were killed
and over 200 wounded at Sharpeville, South Africa, as police opened fire on a crowd protesting against the rule which forces Africans
to carry passbooks. Top photo is from "Come Back Africa", a film which spotlights the lot of the Negro in South Africa.
© United Press, London
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
TWO LITTLE ROCKS. White and Negro children leaving
school arm In arm at Llttlerock, California, (left) contrast
strikingly with Negro students in Little Rock, Arkansas, escor¬
ted from classes under protection of Federal troops. Little
by
Cyril Bibby
5
, M ti(
here are very few places, even in
lands with a proud history of tolera-
. tion, where beneath the smooth
surface there is not some undercurrent of racial prejudice.
The Negro has the same rights of admission to hotels in
Britain as any other person, but he may frequently find
that all their rooms are "already occupied." The Algerian
may be a citizen of France, but his path will be harder
than that of a fellow-citizen of lighter hue. The Jew may
distinguish himself in an American university, but certain
student fraternities will be closed to him. And, con¬
trariwise, the Gentile may be held in low esteem by the
Jew, and the European despised by the very African or
Asian on whom he himself looks down.
One of the difficulties in any discussion of race rela¬
tions is that of definition. From a purely academic point
of view, it might be better to wait until biologists and
anthropologists and sociologists have produced a unani¬
mous definition of "race" but the matter is not simply
an academic one. Racial prejudice and discrimination are
present and urgent evils, and racial tension and friction
have mounted menacingly in our own generation. More¬
over, a firm belief in something which is not a fact is
itself a fact, and there can be "racial prejudice" against
a group which is not a "race". We cannot, therefore,
delay action indefinitely while awaiting definition.
Perhaps an extreme case of this difficulty relates to the
Jewish people. They certainly do not constitute a race
in any proper sense, and it might be argued that anti-
Semitism should not be considered in the same context
as colour prejudice; but, despite the objective differences
between them, these two phenomena have many subjec¬
tive features in common. Nevertheless, it should be stated
explicitly that the joint treatment here of anti-Semitism
and colour prejudice must not be taken to imply that the
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
W-T/V
Rock was in the headlines just three years ago when Arkansas
resisted the historic U.S. Supreme Court decision calling for
the Integration of Negro and White children in schools. Negro
children now attend and leave classes unescorted. Despite
Photos © Planet News, London
other headline-making racial strife, progress has been made
in U.S. school integration. According to a recent report,
racial segregation, once the rule in the South, has now ended
in almost one quarter of the southern school districts.
distinction between Jew and Gentile is of the same nature
as that between Negroid and Caucasoid and Mongoloid.
All too often, when society is faced with a problem of
human behaviour or social relations, there is a tendency
to assume that its solution can be left to the schools.
Teachers, generally speaking, are conscientious people
with a sharp sense of social obligation, and they are
usually prepared to play their part in any urgent social
task. But their part in eradicating racial prejudice,
although important, is only a part ; and the school can
be wholly successful only if Society at large plays its
part also.
What the child does not know, and what even many
educated adults do not seem to know, is that it is quite
impossible to mark off mankind into a few simple and
clearly delineated groups on the basis of physical
differences.
The concept of "race", originating in a recognition of
obvious physical distinctions between different human
groups, has been developed by anthropologists as a device
for classifying populations. And, as often happens when
a concept is extended beyond its original range, this deve¬
lopment of the idea of race has produced many difficul¬
ties. Some anthropologists distinguish few "races", others
distinguish many: and it is hard to find two anthropolo¬
gists who completely agree in their classifications. More¬
over, the popular idea of racial classification is so out of
touch with the biological facts of human variation that
some people would prefer to abandon entirely the use of
the word "race" in connexion with the human species.
Unfortunately the word seems too well established for
abandonment; and alternatives such as "ethnic group" or
"genetically distinguishable populations" are too cumber¬
some for general acceptance into common speech. Thus,
the teacher had better turn his efforts to showing his
pupils how to use the word "race" more exactly and to
freeing their minds of the prejudices which the word so
often carries with it.
The teacher of biology, dealing in the ordinary course
of his lessons with species and their varieties, might well
consider the main divisions of mankind. The native Afri¬
can and the native European, the native of China and
the aboriginal native of Australia, differ sufficiently to
warrant their being placed in distinguishable subgroups
of the human species; and, providing that one does not
imagine that the boundaries between them are hard and
fast, these great subgroups may be not too inaccurately
called "races". Children are not ostriches, and honest
recognition of biological variation is not intolerance.
The teacher should explain that there is no biological
warrant at all for such terms as "the Aryan race", "the
British race", "the Jewish race", "the Arab race" and so
on. "Aryan" is a linguistic term for a hypothetical early
language, "British" is a political term for a particular
group of nations sharing certain historical traditions and
constitutional forms, "Jewish" is a socio-theological term
for people with an ancient religious tradition and with
recognizable customs, "Arab" is an ecological term for
those who lead or have comparatively recently led a par¬
ticular type of seml-nomadic life in the Middle East.
None of these are "Races" in any proper biological sense:
indeed, to speak of an "Aryan race" is as great an abuse
of words as to speak of a "black-skinned language", and
this should be made clear to children.
Similarly, the "Jewish race" is a myth. There are people
called Jews, and these people 'are sometimes recognizable
as such, but that does not make them into a race.
Style of dress, type of gesture, habits of hygiene, turns
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
RACE, PREJUDICE & EDUCATION (Cont'd)
of speech all these things, dependent on social envi¬
ronment rather than on biological heredity, combine to
facilitate recognition of the members of a cultural group.
And that is, primarily, what Jews are: a cultural group
sharing a common religious tradition, a common sacred
language, and a great wealth of common customs. There
are characteristically Jewish gestures, a characteristically
Jewish pattern of family life, certain characteristically
Jewish occupations and cultural Interests, but there is no
Jewish race.
The teacher, therefore, is on safe ground in correcting
any of his pupils who speak of a "Jewish race". One may
properly speak of "the Jewish religion" or of "the Jewish
people", but never of "the Jewish race".
Nor is this a purely pedantic point. It is partly because
the word "race" has been so loosely used in the past,
sometimes to denote biological groups and sometimes lin¬
guistic groups or religious groups, and because inexact
use of language encourages inexact ideas of all kinds, that
mankind has been led into racial prejudice and discrimi¬
nation. Intolerance and cruelty and exploitation are
things too ugly to be willingly accepted by most decent
people: they have to be wrapped up in an ideological
dressing which will disguise their ugliness, and muddled
ideas of race have often provided such a dressing.
At various times the French, the English and the Ger¬
mans have all been claimed as "Aryans," and in Nazi Ger¬
many the myths of an "Aryan race" and a "Jewish race"
were twin strands in an elaborate pattern of prejudice,
discrimination, cruelty and finally mass-murder. The
teacher who persuades his pupils to use the word "race"
exactly, is helping them also to see the world about them
more clearly. Moreover, an understanding of how loosely
and inaccurately the word "race" is often employed may
well be the first step to the exertion of some rational
control over the emotional feelings which the word so
often arouses.
JL, ic
eachers will often find that their pu¬
pils have fixed and oversimplified
ideas (stereotypes, as they are called)
about race. They may imagine, for example, that all Neg¬
roes and only Negroes have "woolly" hair, or that all
Chinese and only Chinese have "slanting" eyes or that all
Scandinavians are tall and blond and blue-eyed. We need
not be surprised that children in ethnically uniform areas
hold such ideas, for their personal contacts provide no
evident corrective to the verbal and visual over-simplifi¬
cations which impinge on them from all the media of
mass communication. It is, however, a little more surpris¬
ing that children living in cosmopolitan cities, which count
people of all colours and ethnic origins among their citi¬
zens, may also have similar false stereotypes.
Evidently, social barriers may be almost as effective
obstacles to understanding as those of geography, and the
distance from Park Avenue to Harlem may in this sense
be as great as that from Berlin to Addis Ababa. Even
where children of different colours and different ethnic
origins sit in the same classroom, the scales of prejudice
may still so obstruct the pupils' vision as to prevent them
from recognizing what is plain there for them to see.
It is similarly easy to make false generalizations about
"racial character" on the basis of observed or Imagined
behaviour, and we may find many of our pupils with false
ideas of this kind. Thus, the European child may believe
that Negroes are lazy and violent in nature, the Gentile
child may imagine that Jews have natures mercantile and
mean, while the Jewish child may take Gentiles to be
crude and unimaginative. The child of the colonial settler
may assume that the natives are naturally unintelligent
and servile, while the child of the native may imagine
that the settlers are naturally harsh and overbearing.
Without denying that peoples vary in many ways and,
Indeed, while emphasizing that such variation may be a
source of great cultural richness the teacher can do
much to make his pupils aware of the unreality of most
stereotypes. "Racial character" is a concept which courts
confusion: the sooner children can be freed from it, the
better.
The idea of "race" is a very complex one, with elements
belonging to biology, psychology, sociology, anthropology,
geography and history; and it is quite impossible to give
any short account of it without running the risk of dan
gerous over-simplification. However, it is possible to clear
away fairly quickly some of the lumber of myth and
fallacy which obscures the essential facts. The major
fallacy which bedevils any proper understanding of the
situation is the simple but false idea that mankind can
be split into a number of quite distinct divisions characte¬
rized by clear-cut biological differences. Naturally, if a
school uses atlases which include population maps based
on the Blumenbach or similar system of "black, brown,
yellow, red and white races", the teacher will need to
point out their utter fallaciousness.
In fact, the biological classification of our species is a
matter of great complexity. If skin colour is taken as a
criterion, the natives of Africa and Australia fall in one
group and those of Europe in another; but, if hairiness of
body be the criterion, the European falls with the abori¬
ginal Australians, while the African must be placed in a
group apart. Use cephalic index as a guide, and one finds
long-heads and short-heads mixed up together the whole
DIFFERENT DOES
COI, London
NIGERIAN STUDENT Oladotun Okubanjo was recently
elected chairman of the Students' Union at the Ealing Technical
College, London, which has a student body of 8,000. Here
he presides over meeting of Union's Executive Committee.
Today there are more than 26,000 Commonwealth students
in Britain, including 8,000 from Nigeria, and 4,000 from India.
world over; use blood-group distribution, and yet other
affiliations are indicated.
A classification of mankind by one biological criterion
does not correspond with the classification which results
from using another criterion; and it is impossible to say,
of any one particular criterion, "This is the right one".
Recognizing this, anthropologists take account of all these
characteristics in combination; and, even then, it is still
very difficult to decide to what ethnic group some indi¬
viduals belong.
Racial prejudice is not inherent in the nature of hu¬
manity but emerges and gathers strength only in certain
social conditions. It Is, of course, a common observation
that members of any "in-group" tend to be prejudiced
against the members of an "out-group" conquerors
against conquered, old residents against newcomers, one
neighbouring tribe against another-^but this does not
mean that intergroup tensions are unavoidable. It is also
a fact that colour prejudice may be exhibited by those
whose skins are yellow or brown or black, as well as by
those whose skins are white, but this does not mean that
colour prejudice is innate. Indeed, infants of different
religions and different colours will commonly play unself¬
consciously together, only learning prejudice gradually
from their elders.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
Although today few will be found to justify the grosser
forms of racial discrimination and exploitation, there is
still a fairly widespread feeling that "coloured" people
are in some way inferior to "white" people. And such is
the power of the preconceptions of the predominant group
that many "coloured" people themselves share this idea
of their inferiority. It is a feeling rather than a belief,
vague and ill-defined rather than clear-cut and definite,
based on prejudice rather than on reason. There is, in
fact, no very useful sense in which it may legitimately be
said that one ethnic group is inherently superior to
another.
The teacher has many opportunities to clarify the
muddied waters of popular belief. It is true that, during
recent centuries, the "pink" peoples have in general
reached a higher level of civilization (certainly of techno¬
logical achievements) than the browns and yellows and
blacks, but history shows that it has not always been so.
The English child, learning about the invasion of his land
NOT MEAN INFERIOR
USIS
FIRST DAY AT SCHOOL for Robert Brooks, a little Negro
boy, and one of the 3,600,000 six-year-old U.S. children who
were enrolled In the first-grade classes of the nation's schools
this year. Studies by U.S. psychologists show that white and
Negro children place less emphasis on race after they have
lived and played together in classrooms and summer camps.
by the legions of Julius Caesar, is usually told that his
forebears were stained with woad and roughly clad in
animal pelts, but he may be surprised to learn that Cicero
advised Atticus not to buy British slaves since "they are
so utterly stupid and Incapable of learning".
European children, and those of European descent,
might learn that during earlier centuries, when the lands
that are now Germany and France and Scandinavia were
backward and ignorant, there was a brilliant flowering of
Hellenistic culture in the North African city of Alexandria
and that in the Arab States the lamp of learning burned
brightly. In the "Middle Ages", Marco Polo travelled the
territories of Tartary and chronicled the wonders that
met his eye, and West Africa had its Ghana kingdom so
admired by Arab voyagers. Before the fifteenth century,
the African State of Benin was producing its little master¬
pieces of bronze and ivory; in the sixteenth, one of the
great centres of Moslem culture was the University of
Timbuktu; in the seventeenth, across the globe in China,
there was the exquisite civilization of the early Manchu
dynasty.
Cultural achievement at any one moment in history is
no evidence of innate superiority, but depends upon all
sorts of economic, social, political and geographical con¬
ditions. The idea that only the "white" peoples are capa
ble of high culture cannot withstand for a moment the
ineluctable facts of history: the teacher who presents the
facts to his pupils need scarcely draw the moral, for it is
manifest. Moreover, it is quite unjustifiable to assess the
level of a culture by reference solely to its technical
achievements.
Unfortunately, the textbooks used in schools do not
commonly consider questions of this sort: more often,
they tell whatever redounds to the credit of the country
in which they are written. No objective teaching of his¬
tory can exclude consideration of the enslavement of
- Africans and the exploitation of Asians by the powers of
Europe; nor, if it is to avoid one-sidedness, can It fall to
indicate that in earlier days Africans enslaved each other,
and Asians exploited Asians. But this is no reason for
failing to disclose the darker side of European dominance.
The good teacher will not allow himself to be circum¬
scribed by narrowly national books, and there are publi¬
cations available which will help him to teach history
more impartially.
Geography books, too, may be misleading. Not uncom¬
monly they imply, and in some cases explicitly state, that
one so-called "race" is superior to another. Especially is
this the case with textbooks used in the schools of a
colonial power, where the natives of an African colony
may be described as "child-like" and as having been
"uncivilized until the more energetic and intelligent white
man came".
In European schools, there is a tend-
v ency for textbooks to imply the infer-
.. iority of the Amerindians and Austra-
loids whom the Europeans decimated, of the Negroids
whom they once enslaved, and of the Asiatics whom they
in the past exploited. Similarly, some of the textbooks
commonly used in United States schools give inadequate
Information on ethnic matters and do little to promote
racial tolerance. They sometimes present a picture of
"the American way of life" which implies that it is
"white", Protestant and middle-class, and which omits all
reference to segregation and discrimination.
Nor is it only the text that may mislead in this way:
the camera can lie very effectively if its lens is suitably
pointed. Thus, if the only photographs of "Blacks" in a
geography book show them with mud-matted hair and
skewers through their noses, while the photographs of
"Whites" depict them in elegant linen and fine footwear,
an impression of Negro inferiority is almost inevitably
given.
Meanwhile, the commercial cinema misleads many a
child: on the screen, Negroes tend to appear either as
bloodthirsty warriors or as lovable children, Orientals
either as sinister plotters or as sleek sophisticates, and
non-Europeans generally as menial servants. All too
often, unfortunately, teachers tend to turn up their noses
at the local cinema and thereby abandon their pupils to
Its distorting influence. If teachers would make a habit
of discussing with their children the "fllm of the week",
they would find many an opportunity of correcting false
Impressions.
People may differ in all sorts of ways, but difference
is one thing and superiority is another. Red hair is
different from black hair, but is neither superior nor
inferior to It the two are different, but of equal status.
The same could apply to some mental differences. More¬
over, the teacher whose daily life is spent with children
of very different physiques, intellectual abilities and tem¬
peramental characteristics, and who yet tries to treat
them all as individual human beings with equal rights to
his care and consideration, will need no convincing that
the condemnation of racial discrimination does not
depend upon any proof that all ethnic groups have Iden¬
tical physical or mental or emotional endowments.
Very often, the warmly hero-worshipping mind of ado¬
lescence will be less vividly impressed by sustained and
reasoned argument than by striking individual examples
of physical, intellectual, temperamental and moral great¬
ness in people of different ethnic origins; and there will
be many opportunities in the school to mention examples
of outstanding achievement by members of various ethnic
and so-called "racial" groups.
Yet not too much should be made of this "'eminent
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
RACE, PREJUDICE & EDUCATION (Cont'd)
Ignorance, reservoir of racial prejudice
individuals" approach to the matter. In the first place it
is a simple fact that thus far in history there have been
comparatively few Negroes of the highest culture, and
many of them have been of mixed Negroid-Caucasoid
ancestry. Second, and more important, to overstress that
there are great Negroes and Asians' and Jews may seem
to imply that racial tolerance should be dependent on
such greatness, which is going a long way to grant one
of the very premises of racial bigotry.
It may, moreover, make some children of minority
groups feel that they must win acceptance in the school
by distinguishing themselves in some way, and thus pro¬
duce either excessive strain or objectionable aggressive¬
ness. In the case of the Jewish people in particular, their
history is so studded with human greatness that there
may be danger in stressing what is, for some Gentiles,
already an unconscious source of envy and resentment.
If, however, there Is evidence in the classroom of damag¬
ing Ignorance on this point, the teacher should certainly
quote one or two cases to illustrate Jewish ability.
I t has been remarked that "every
people has a right to have its scound-
. reis", and this puts the question in its
proper perspective. When a Jewish financier cheats his
shareholders or a Negro soldier rapes a girl, the words
"Jewish" and "Negro" are likely to figure prominently in
newspaper headlines; when the offenders are Gentile or
White, their ethnic affiliations are usually not mentioned.
This circular process of labelling the group with the
offences of a few delinquent members, and then labelling
the members of the group with the attached delinquen¬
cies, is responsible for the maintenance of much group
prejudice; and it is no more honest to seek to parallel the
process with the achievements of a few persons of
distinction.
The important thing is for our pupils to learn to judge
each individual as an individual neither owning the glory
nor bearing the shame of other individuals in his group.
And, most essential, the whole day-by-day conduct of the
school should be directed towards building up better ways
of thinking and feeling in general, so that the pupils
learn to think straight and feel charitably when con¬
fronted with any individual or group different from
themselves.
It is sometimes supposed that young children are
always free of racial prejudice, but this attractive picture
of childhood innocence scarcely corresponds with the
facts. From the very earliest days infants are imbibing
the implicit assumptions of the society in which they live;
and, if the social environment is one of racial discrimina¬
tion, it will be difficult indeed for a child to grow up
without taking it for granted that such a state of affairs
is part of the natural order of things.
In some ways, racial prejudice and discrimination today
play the same social role as did the persecution of the
Christians and Jews in Imperial Rome, the crusades
against the infidels in medieval Christendom, the inquisi¬
tion of heretics and the burning of witches. All such
attacks have these things usually in common they pro¬
vide a means of distracting the attention of the oppressed
from the defects of their oppressors, they offer the oppor¬
tunity of direct or indirect material gain, they serve to
"smear" a whole group of people indiscriminately and so
aid charlatans and witch-hunters in their nefarious
designs, and they provide a socially acceptable outlet for
feelings of frustration and aggression.
The early Christians of Rome were falsely accused of
obscenity, ritual murder and disloyalty, and the group-
prejudices of our own time are nourished by charges no
less false. If Jews can be blamed both as the internation¬
al capitalists and as the international communists for
intergroup prejudice knows no logic the common people
may be diverted from careful inquiry into the causes of
the calamities which befall them. If Negroes can be
stereotyped as stupid, a good excuse is provided for keep¬
ing them out of the skilled jobs desired by the "white"
workers.
10
If all Europeans can be labelled as "white devils", they
can more easily be cast out from Asian lands. If the
entire people of an African or Asian region can be cha¬
racterized as "terrorists", some sort of justification may
be provided for denying them self-government and the
protection of normal legal process.
Not only are fear and frustration potent sources of
aggression, but the situation may be aggravated by
feelings of inadequacy or guilt. One reason why anti-
Semitism so flourished in Germany may have been that
the German people, prevented by their late achievement
of nationhood from establishing a worldwide empire like
Britain's, found reassurance in the assertion of their
"Aryan" superiority. One reason why the Englishman,
racially tolerant at home, so often develops racial pre¬
judice in Africa and Asia, may be that there he represents
a dominant minority group and fears the potential rebel¬
lion of the subservient native majority a situation which
today exists very clearly in South Africa. One reason why
many "'Whites" from the Southern states of the U.S.A.
are so virulent in their expression of racial prejudice is
probably that, deep down, they feel guilty about the way
in which the Negroes have been treated.
Wherever erroneous stereotypes based on simple igno¬
rance betray themselves in the child's comments, the
teacher can supply the corrective in the form of further
Photo © Keystone
SWASTIKA-LIKE Crossed Circle is symbol of a
small racist fringe group in Britain which last year
staged a "Keep Britain White" meeting in Trafalgar
Square, London. (Above and top right, opposite page).
information. And, wherever such stereotypes are per¬
petuated by a pupil's refusal to recognize the facts, the
teacher can gradually open his eyes for him and gently
wash away the scales that cover them. There is,
admittedly, no certainty that what the teacher does in
the school to encourage an enlightened attitude to inter¬
group relations will have a permanent effect on pupils'
behaviour once they leave school.
But this is no reason for not performing the task that
lies to hand: after all, it is a commonplace in education
that we are uncertain what permanent effects this or that
element in schooling may have, but we do not for that
reason close down our schools. And in any event, con¬
trolled experiment has shown that it is in fact possible
to change children's racial attitudes quite considerably
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
Photo © Keystone
KEEP BRITAIN WHITE proclaims poster at London meeting protest¬
ing immigration of Negro British subjects from W. Indies and Africa.
Photo © Keystone
ANTI-NEGRO RIOTS like one seen here in Notting Hill, London
have often been the work of irresponsible Teddy boys and girls.
by means of carefully devised educational procedures in
the school.
The teacher will often find that his pupils' prejudices
have complex origins which are difficult to trace. For two
or three centuries the Western world has been washed by
the waves of racial and religio-racial discrimination, and
its waters have seeped into the very fabric of our social
thought. Thus, it will often be the faint whisper of pre¬
judice, rather than its strident clamour, which the
teacher with a sensitive ear will detect, and it Is a
whisper not easily stilled.
The blatant lie can be exposed as plainly false and the
crude political discrimination denounced as manifestly
unjust, but the delicate denial of human fraternity which
takes the form of not-quite-tfriendship is too subtle a
thing to be conjured away easily. Only by patiently
correcting month by month each minor manifestation of
prejudice, and by demonstrating year by year a genuinely
all-embracing acceptance of humanity, can the teacher
hope finally to free his pupils of this more tenuous type
of discrimination.
I
Photo © Keystone
BLACK AND WHITE can live together in harmony proclaims Lon¬
don picket group following of violence in which a Negro was killed.
t is important that the teacher should
provoke genuine discussion not for¬
mal debate, which often tends to
confirm speakers in their views and makes their abandon¬
ment a matter of loss of prestige encouraging the pupils
to express all points of view quite openly and freely. Any
too obvious or premature disapproval of undesirable opi¬
nions may lead to their repression, but will not secure
their eradication; and it is a poor service to ethnic under¬
standing merely to suppress views, leaving them still
potent and liable to break out with renewed virulence
after the child has left school.
Moreover, it must be remembered that the child who
exhibits prejudice is as much in need of help as the child
who is subjected to it, should be treated by the teacher
with the same sympathy and understanding, and in some
cases may actually need protection by the teacher from
the indignation of classmates who resent all racial pre¬
judice. The securer a child feels, the less emotional need
he will have to indulge in discrimination: and the teacher
must therefore take care, while indicating unambiguously
his own tolerance, not to appear to reject the prejudiced
pupil.
Each child's self-respect must be built up in every
possible way, and this can only be done if the teacher
tries to enter into the mind of his pupil, no matter how
much he may disapprove of its distortions and confusions
and contradictions. It is a painful process, as any honest
teacher will recognize from his own experience, to give
up prejudices behind which one has sheltered for years,
and we must not be surprised if our pupils offer uncons¬
cious resistance to efforts at their enlightenment. Any
sudden and ruthless stripping away of a child's protective
covering may in the long run do more harm than good;
and the teacher should seek to be not a bulldozer, to
demolish his pupils' illogicalities by brute force of argu¬
ment, but rather a lightning conductor by which their
emotional tensions and their accompanying prejudices
may safely leak away.
There is in the modern world altogether too widespread
a tendency to uniformity and conformity in all things,
and we are in danger of losing sight of the enormous
human potentiality for idiosyncrasy and originality. We
do not know what combinations of desirable character¬
istics, what possibilities of cultural diversity, may not
await us in a world which ceases to measure all men by
the yardstick of "white" ways but which, instead, encou¬
rages peoples of all pigmentations to develop to the fullest
their own innate qualities and to combine in the forma¬
tion of fresh mixtures. Teachers should not seek to mini¬
mize ethnic differences or to pretend that they do not
exist, but rather to emphasize the uniqueness of each
individual human person and to encourage children to
appreciate the value of human variation.
One element in racial prejudice is sometimes of an
aesthetic nature: the child brought up to admire Greek
statues and the paintings of the Italian Renaissance is
often conditioned against skins that are not white and
locks that do not flow. If, therefore, art teachers were
sometimes to deal with visual and plastic representations
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
RACE, PREJUDICE & EDUCATION (Cont'd)
of other physical types, it might do something to erode
racial prejudice. Once a person ceases to say, "I can't
tell one Japanese from another" or, "All Negroes look
alike to me", and instead begins to appreciate the beauty
of an almond eye and the delicate sleekness of an ebony
skin, he is on the way to overcoming any repugnance to
"yellows" and "blacks" which may have soaked into him
from the atmosphere around.
It is not unknown for children to agree in classroom
discussions that racial discrimination is wrong and racial
prejudice irrational, and even to learn in community study
a good deal about the factors influencing race relations,
and none the less to continue in their daily lives to exer¬
cise discrimination and display prejudice in all sorts of
little ways. There is a Chinese proverb which may be
approximately rendered, "If I hear, I forget; if I see,
I remember; if I do, I know"; and it is in action against
racial wrongs that children really learn racial Tightness.
Once a child has actually committed himself by assert¬
ing his friendship for a schoolmate of different colour,
once he has argued with his playmates that a child
hitherto racially rejected should be admitted to their
games, he has become emotionally involved in the struggle
for racial equality and has innerly identified himself with
those who insist on racial tolerance.
T-
pr
JLoi
hus. If the teacher can, without ever
essing any individual to the point
of resentment, encourage his pupils
not merely to talk about but actively to take part in a
programme of non-discrimination, he may achieve
something which no amount of mere moral exhortation
can bring about. Before many years have passed, the
pupils of the secondary school will be adult citizens of the
community, and while at school they should learn ethnic
equality not merely by precept but in practice.
It Is essential to remember that children, like their
elders, are reluctant to act alone. The individual with the
courage to flout the herd is a priceless asset to a commu¬
nity, for without such individuals a society ossifies. It is,
however, unrealistic to expect most pupils to adopt a
line of action distasteful to their closest friends; in the
main, a child's attitudes and acts are those accepted by
his playmates and classmates, his "peer-group." Recog¬
nizing this, the teacher who wishes to alter behaviour
will normally seek to influence the whole group rather
than an individual in isolation.
Yet the child is not constrained absolutely by his peer-
group: the behaviour of respected adults can set a most
effective example. If teachers seem to contract out of the
social situation, pupils can scarcely be blamed for doing
likewise. If teachers demonstrate by their actions their
concern for social righteousness, pupils will be encouraged
to do the same.
Finally, therefore, the teacher should have the temerity
to exercise his citizen rights. All too often, in many
lands, teachers tend to be somewhat retiring spending
their evenings and weekends with a few choice friends,
themselves not infrequently teachers too. Only rarely do
they join in the casual conversations of the local café or
public house, take part in politics and local government,
engage in friendly argument with miners and shopkeepers
and engineers. But those who remain within ivory towers
can do little to influence the affairs of the great world
outside, and the teacher who wishes to help his pupils
to a life full and rich and free must be prepared to share
in the shaping of the society in which they will live it.
GUIDEBOOK TO RACE
The above article is based on chapters selected from "Race, Preju¬
dice and Education" by Dr. Cyril Bibby, lecturer at the Institute of
Education, London University, and at the College of St. Mark and
St. John, London. Dr. Bibby discusses the reasons for racial prejudice
and what can be 'done about it. He gives the biological facts about
the divisions and variations of mankind, traces the growth of racial
discrimination and discusses the tangled emotions behind it. His
manuscript, which was commissioned by Unesco, was revised in the
light of comments by twenty-six experts from places as far apart as
Mexico, Poland, Canada, Germany and India. Published by Heinemann,
London, price 7/6.
12
Photos © Keystone
GERMAN YOUTH DEMONSTRATED EN MASSE against a
series of anti-Semitic incidents which occurred early this year.
Right, assembled before a synagogue In Berlin, ten thousand young
people vow to fight against any revival of anti-Semitism. The
demonstration followed a long night procession by young Germans
through West Berlin to protest "Against Racial Hatred" (banner,
above). Similar demonstrations took place in East Berlin where
young marchers (below) carried banner marked "Down with anti-
Semitism". The first racist incident occurred in Cologne on Christ¬
mas Eve when swastikas were smeared on a new synagogue that
the West German Chancellor had helped to dedicate three months
earlier. This was followed by an outbreak of similar incidents
not only in Germany, but also in other European countries and in
the United Statesoften the work of delinquents or cranks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
Keystone
A LOOK AT MODERN
ANTI-SEMITISM
Anti-Semitism is a highly complex phenomenon.
The term itself contains a double ambiguity.
Firstly the majority of Jews do not belong to
the "race" so defined (few writers still speak of a "Semi¬
tic race" anyway; if one does exist, its representatives par
excellence would be the Arabs). Secondly it reduces to
terms of racial conflict, a hostility whose roots are to be
found quite elsewhere.
That this animosity exists cannot be denied, and down
the centuries it has even been marked by an intensity,
and above all, a constancy, never attained by any of the
other conflicts between confessional, ethnic or national
groups. The age of the wars of religion gave way to the
age of tolerance; the great "hereditary enmities" were
succeeded by cordial alliances; anti-Semitism alone
remained faithful to itself, seemingly as durable as the
Jewish people themselves.
So strange and so intense a phenomenon had necessa¬
rily to be rooted in a doctrinal system and buttressed by a
by Léon Poliakov
Author of "Breviary of Hatred" & "A History of anti-Semitism"
strong belief, nourished on the teaching of leading think¬
ers. Accordingly, for centuries anti-Semitism was "the¬
ological" conceived to be (the expression of the divine
will, whose commands the persecutors of the Jews
believed themselves to be obeying by word or act until in
the 19th century, it became "scientifically" justified in
the eyes of its protagonists, thanks to some current
anthropological theories firmly believed both by well-
educated individuals and by the general mass of the
people.
Today, however, we are faced with a new situation
since the Churches of the various denominations are
almost unanimous in condemning any manifestation of
anti-Semitism, even expressed verbally, and since racial
theories, after a triumphant heyday from the time of the
Count de Gobineau down to the Nazi anthropologists, are
now universally rejected by scientists and are doomed to
share the oblivion of such once popular theories as inter¬
stellar ether or spontaneous generation. Before examining
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
MODERN ANTI-SEMITISM (Cont'd)
FNDIRP
ROUNDED UP LIKE CATTLE In 1942, Jewish people In Nazi-occupied Paris were herded into the Velodrome d'Hiver, a vast sport
arena, to await deportation in sealed trains "to the east". Parisians managed to warn and hide a small number but In two days alone,
July 16 and 17, nearly 13,000 children and adults were arrested in Paris. Similar round-ups were made in all the countries of Europe.
any conclusions to be drawn from this, we should look
more closely at the nature of both theological and scien¬
tific anti-Semitism and see how they fell into disrepute
and disuse.
Theological anti-Semitism dates back to early Christian
times, when the first Christian Churches seemed to be
nothing more than a dissidence from the Judaism to
which they were opposed. The story of the Crucifixion
as told in the Gospels, and the cry attributed to the
Jews: "May his blood be visited upon us and upon our
children" led to the conclusion that the Jews, by causing
Jesus to be crucified, had judged and condemned them¬
selves!
And indeed, from that time on, the Fathers of the
Church, powerless to convert the Jews, elaborated a
doctrine which laid down that, having committed the
crime of deicide, the Jews were condemned to eternal
punishment and, like Cain, must wander over the world
bearing witness by their abasement and servitude to the
truth of the dogmas and the triumph, of Christianity.
This is what Professor Jules Isaac has called "the teach¬
ing of contempt".
Consequently, the status of the Jews, which was on
the whole good in Roman and barbarian Europe, deterior¬
ated as that same Europe became Christianized and
learned to read. The great turning point was the period
of the earliest Crusades, when first great massacres of
Jews took place, against a background of religious exal¬
tation of the masses, it was then that the tales of ritual
14
murders committed by the Jews, profanations of the
Host, poisoning of wells, and other similar legends, were
spread. From then onwards, when an epidemic, famine
or other calamity occurred, the Jews served as scapegoats:
from time to time the people rose up and massacred them,
whilst the princes alternatively extorted wealth from
them to fill their own treasuries or sent them into exile.
In these circumstances, the Jews in the end became the
chief pariahs of Europe.
The situation at the time of the Renaissance may be
summed up in the wry witticism of Erasmus: "If it
is the role of a good Christian to detest the Jews, then
we are all good Christians", which is borne out by the
ferocious anti-Semitism tirades of a Luther or the im¬
placables decrees of the Popes of the Counter-Reforma¬
tion. The Jews remained in this miserable state until
the XVIIIth century; a strikingly expressive trace of it
is still to be found in the usage of all European languages,
in which the very word Jew, in addition to its intrinsic
meaning, has a second derived meaning which is always
perjorative.
It required the effort of reflection accomplished by the
philosophers of the Age of Enlightenment to understand
that these conditions were not due to some divine male¬
diction but to the status to which Christian society had
relegated the Jews. These ideas finally led to decisions
and actions: between 1789 and 1848, in all the countries
of Western Europe, the Jews were emancipated and
became "full citizens", attaining equality of rights with
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
Auschwitz museum
MOUNTAIN OF BOOTS AND SHOES at Auschwitz bears silent witness to the extermination of some 6,000,000 Jews in S.S.
death camps. Nazism made birth a crime punishable by death. Jews, half-Jews, quarter-Jews died for no other reason than their
descendency, and innocent men, women and children were put to death, after enduring indescribable mental and physical torture.
Catholics and Protestants. Their emancipation was not
accomplished without struggles; it raised constant po¬
lemics and objections from those nostalgic for mediaeval
Christian times, and it shocked certain Jews themselves;
but in a society which had become secularized, it was
impossible to re-establish the ghettos and a discrimina¬
tion based on the old theological anti-Semitism.
Needless to say, the age-old prejudice against the Jews
did not on that account disappear as if by magic. It
even found new stimulus as a result of the social ascen¬
dency of the Jews, who themselves were impatient to
"compensate" for their former abasement. Thus, new
jealousies and grievances were added to the old Christian
prejudices; and yet, what justification could be found
for holding anti-Semitism to be according to the will of
God, in a society in which the Jews were no longer
socially degraded and in which the new tendency was to
explain the course of events no longer as decrees of
Providence but as the laws of nature?
Science had become a new goddess, all of whose mys¬
teries men sought to discover too hastily; as far as the
species homo sapiens was concerned, since the time when
Linné had divided men into "Europeans, white and.hard¬
working", "Asiatics, yellow and long-suffering", "Afri¬
cans, black and weak-willed", and "Americans, red and
hot-tempered", systems of classification in which physical
characteristics were paired with mental ones and the
latter with virtues and vices, became too numerous to
count.
Therein lay the origins of "scientific anti-Semitism":
in the vast amount of literature that the XlXth century
devoted to these questions, it was taken for granted that
the Jews were a "race" and discussion turned upon the
question whether it was a "good" or "bad" race; that '
was also the approach adopted by many Jewish writers
themselves.
The political exploitation of "scientific anti-Semitism"
by the Nazis, the teaching of hatred succeeding the
teaching of contempt, and the massacre of six million
innocent human beings which followed, are facts still
fresh in the memory of all. It is also important to stress
the fact that the persecution of a defenceless minority,
especially if prolonged, does not remain merely a series
of unilateral actions; it provokes a whole chain of reac¬
tions and attitudes that transform it into a vicious circle,
the dialectics of which consist In fostering and poisoning
the conflict.
From this point of view (to quote but one example),
the very natural adherence of Jews to ideologies and
parties that were not anti-Semitic, which meant, gene¬
rally, to those that were "leftist" or "progressive", pro¬
duced accusations such as "all Jews are revolutionaries",
"Communism is a Jewish doctrine", and to their defa¬
mation as "destructive elements" attacks which could
not fail to increase their solidarity both with the camps
in question and among themselves. Hence the original
solution of the "Jewish problem", proposed by dreamers
in the XlXth century and put into practice by realists
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
MODERN ANTI-SEMITISM (Cont'd;
in the XXth: the Jews should turn their backs upon an
uncompromisingly inhospitable Europe and create a
Jewish State on the very site that was formerly the legen¬
dary Jewish fatherland.
If neither theological nor scientific anti-Semitism are
no longer accorded the status of coherent doctrines, it is
because Christian thought on the subject has profoundly
changed, and developments in anthropology prevent the
arguments of the racialists .from being taken seriously.
But the change has been accelerated to a remarkable
extent by a sort of grandiose experiment in vivo.
The crimes committed under Hitler showed the extent
to which all anti-Semitism was anti-Christian leading as
it did to the negation of all ethical values. As for the
"racial characteristics" attributed to the Jews, the State
of Israel, itself ethnically a miniature Tower of Babel,
and a country in which the Jews have shown themselves
to be both sturdy labourers and good soldiers, was from
that point of view an excellent practical lesson. In those
conditions, it is difficult to imagine from what pulpit a
doctrinal anti-Semitism could be preached and what
authorities it could find to support it. The general
outcry which followed the recent "epidemic of swastikas"
has shown the sensibility of public opinion to the danger,
and the intensity of international reactions.
Nevertheless, as a prejudice one which rarely dares to
call itself by its real name anti-Semitism is still very
widespread in all the countries of Western . civilization.
Even those tragic events which revealed its odious and
wanton cruelty, have also helped to stimulate its persis¬
tence here and there.
Hitler's "teaching of hatred", practised on a mass
scale for twenty years in Germany and for four years
throughout all occupied Europe from France to the Cau¬
casus, has left traces in innumerable minds. The massa¬
cre of millions of innocent martyrs, even though it
aroused so much indignant compassion and made the fate
which befell the Jews the very symbol of injustice, also
succeeded precisely for that reason in arousing mixed
feelings among certain people. It is rather like the
Athenian who hated Aristides because in the eyes of his
fellow-citizens Aristides was a just man^and above
reproach.
We have here an example of a process similar to that
well-known to psychiatrists: the revolt against the laws
of social life is very liable to choose as a target men or
groups who are the incarnation of justice, as well as
being inoffensive, and who therefore can be attacked
without risk.
In a sense, Jews stimulate aggressiveness of that kind
by the mere fact of their existence, or to the extent that
they remember better than anyone the horrors of Hitler's
racialism, the sufferings they endured, the relatives who
disappeared and the homes that were devastated. There
are some whose peace of mind is disturbed by the Jews
on this account.
M
I ^m ATERiALLY, there still exist throughout the
A -^L.world numerous hotbeds of anti-Semitism.
Most of tnose who less than twenty years ago, close at
hand or from afar compromised with Hitler or were in
sympathy with him, and especially those who were puni¬
shed after the war as a result, are still impregnated with
the virus of hatred. More or less clandestine centres of
anti-Semitic propaganda still exist in all the five contin¬
ents. A crank called Einar Aberg, a citizen of tolerant
Sweden, for example, floods the whole world with crude
pamphlets in which he accuses the Jews of hatching a
world-Wide conspiracy to subjugate the "Aryan" nations
(where he gets his funds remains a mystery) ; and there
are similar centres in Cairo, Buenos Aires and elsewhere.
So even the Jewish tragedy of the last war has raised
a shower of counter-reactions on which anti-Semitic
prejudices continue to feed. It is worth noting in this
connexion that Jewish attitudes, which formerly played
their part in the vicious circle of anti-Semitism, are of
very limited importance, and as regards present-day
Germany it has become possible to speak, justifiably, of
"anti-Semitism without Jews." In most other countries
the Jewish "emancipation problem" has long since been
solved.
In addition, the former anti-Jewish theological teaching,
16
although in principle abolished in the present day, is still
perpetuated in many old manuals or catechisms, many
local traditions and festivals, or in family recollections.
So we find that the famous "Mystery of the Passion" at
Oberammergau in Bavaria, which is performed every ten
years, is to keep to its traditional text in 1960, a text
which is largely concerned with the role of the Jews, who
are depicted as a treacherous and odious people, justly
incurring divine punishment.
T
t is probably far from the intention of the organi-
J^-zers of Oberammergau to spread anti-Semitism,
but a spectacle of that kind, lasting several days and
drawing hundreds of thousands of spectators, cannot
fail to leave traces of it here and there. (Psychologically,
it is interesting to note in this connexion that of the
ten principal actors in the 1940 production, only the one
who played the part of Judas was not a member of the
Nazi Party (1).
Here is another example of the persistence of out-of-
date conceptions: in a third-grade class in a Paris lycée,
the teacher asked the girls to explain the text of the
first scene of Racine's.."Athalie", in which the action takes
place several centuries before Christ. In this scene,
Racine puts into the mouth of Abner, leader of the Jews,
the following lamentation: "Even God has abandoned
us; Formerly so jealous of the honour of the Hebrews
He looks down unmoved upon their fallen grandeur
His mercy in the end grown weary..." One girl in the
class commented on the passage as follows: "The Jews
had been punished", said Abner, "because they had
crucified Jesus". Behind this "howler" made by a pupil
whose background was in no way anti-Semitic, can be
seen the persistence of the notion of deicide, and in a
more general sense, the idea of a merited punishment of
the Jews.
So we see the number and variety of the factors of all
kinds that contribute to the persistence of an anti-
Semitism which more often than not, lacks the courage
to name itself aloud: like a certain French journalist, for
instance, who begins an article with anti-Semitic impli¬
cations, by stating "I am not anti-Jewish, but...".
Can a prejudice which has been thrown overboard and
condemned ex cathedra by all the philosophies and poli¬
tical doctrines of our time, still be full of evil conse¬
quences? The inquisitors who burned Jews in former
times, and even the fanatical Nazis who exterminated
them, would themselves have been ready to die for their
ideas; inasmuch as men endowed with reason do not risk
their lives for their prejudices, it looks as though the
massacres and pogroms of Jews belong to the past, even
if there still subsist throughout the world many tensions
and injustices due to anti-Semitism.
Moreover, it is considerably easier to fight against a
superstition than against a system of faith, and that
important task is primarily the duty of teachers and edu¬
cators, who, after revising their textbooks, must then
uproot the superstitions and myths which continue to be
handed down from father to son; it is a worthwhile task
of international co-operation that will take two or three
generations, but it is no longer the superhuman one it
would have been in the past.
In all that I have said here, I have spoken only of the
territory of so-called Western Christian civilization. The
fact is that elsewhere, in India, China and Africa south
of the Sahara, anti-Semitism was and still is unknown.
As regards the countries of Islam, where formerly the
majority of the Jews lived, to speak of anti-Semitism
there would be, both an error of meaning and of fact,
since in -an anti-Semitic system the Jewish minority
serves the dominating majority as its chosen scapegoat,
whereas in Islamic territory the fate of the Jews was
never worse than that of the "law abiding" Christians,
who were more numerous. Generally speaking, contrary
to the idea spread of Islamic fanaticism, Moslem tradition
implied a fairly extensive v respect for the beliefs of
others. As for the present Israel-Arab conflict, with its
political and economic aspects, it must be regarded from
quite a different angle, which does not come within the
scope of this article.
(1) Cf. A. Graham Davis, "Passion at Oberammergau", Commentary,
March 1960.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
R. Caloz
i Keystone ,
ARBEIT
MACHT
FREI...
Labour brings freedom (Arbeit Macht
Frei) which the Nazis, with mons¬
trous cynicism, had inscribed in
letters of iron above the gate to the
Auschwitz Concentration Camp
(above) found an echo early this year
in the swastika crudely scrawled with
chalk on the wall of the Dachau
Concentration Camp (left). This
was one of a series of anti-Semitic
incidents which aroused indignation
In Germany and around the world.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
A film produced in Sweden and now being shown in nu¬
merous cinemas of the German Federal Republic is draw¬
ing record attendances of young people most of whom never
saw Adolf Hitler. The film called "Mein Kampf", after the
notorious book Hitler wrote, was assembled from authentic
documentary films and newsreels of the Nazi regime and
shows the horror of Hitler's ruthless "Struggle". The photos
on these pages are taken from one of the most poignant se¬
quences which the Nazis filmed in the Jewish ghetto of War¬
saw. Only some of the less gruesome are published here.
(Note Jewish star of David on streetcar in photo opposite).
It is reported that Goebbels ordered the film made as an anti-
Semitic propaganda film but never dared release it, fearing
perhaps that the sight of all the cruelties inflicted by the S.S.
on the Jews of Warsaw might have a boomerang effect.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
LIGHT & SHADOWS IN THE RACIAL
LANDSCAPE OF LATIN AMERICA
by Alfred Metraux
Nowhere in Spanish-speaking America do race
relations display the rigidity and harshness we
have come to associate with the term '"ra¬
cialist". However, it is not true to say as one often
does that no form of racial prejudice and discrimination
is to be found in the countries of Latin America which
have large non-white populations.
In this article I shall speak only of relations between
whites, Indians and mestizos, particularly in the Andean
region, where despite rapid change, inter-group relations
have remained stationary and outdated.
Racial intermingling began with the Spanish conquest
and colonization, and persists to this day. Except for
one or two countries where the population is chiefly of
European stock, the Indian constitutes a substantial
ethnic component of the population. In Central America,
Ecuador, Peru and Bolivia, racial mixture is so widespread
and of such long-standing that it is impossible to use
anthropological criteria to distinguish one ethnic group
from another.
Physical traits are the only criteria used and accepted
by scientists in classifying races. But in the Andean
countries different physical traits are distributed in such
a way throughout the whole population that to use them
would only lead to the most absurd conclusions.
Can one justifiably classify as Indians persons who
indignantly deny even the remotest connexion with any
Indian group? For, even if the texture of their hair, the
form of their nose or the colour of their skin is indeed
Indian, they have nothing in common, either socially or
culturally, with this group. Conversely, there are people
among the Indian population whose features are those
of the white race.
When physical traits are in total contradiction with a
person's social status, and are not accepted as valid either
by him, or by his social group, then by what outward signs
can we recognize an Indian? His language, perhaps?
Certainly, a man who speaks only an indigenous language
is very probably an Indian, though there are exceptions.
In Peru, some non-Indian groups speak Quechua in pre¬
ference to Spanish, while certain Indians such as those
of the Cajamarca region no longer speak any language
Copacabana is not only the name of a famous beach in Rio-
de-Janeiro. It is also a pilgrimage town In the Bolivian High¬
lands, near Lake Titicaca and the Peruvian frontier toward
which Indians from the Andean countries converge twice a
year to the music of Pan-Pipes, drums and tambourines.
Photos show Indian women at a mountain-top sanctuary.
Photos © Yvan Dalain
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
RACIAL LANDSCAPE OF LATIN AMERICA (Cont'd)
but Spanish. There remain the cultural peculiarities
type of clothes worn, social organization, economic
activities, etc. But here the distinctions between Indians
and mestizos are by no means clear-cut.
Consequently, one finally has to use a kind of tautology:
"An Indian is a man who recognizes himself as such and
who belongs to a community which prefers to speak a
native language, whose material and spiritual culture are
largely^ composed of indigenous elements and who feels
that his community is isolated from those of mestizos or
white men" (Alfonso Caso).
In most countries, with large Indian populations, the
Indian occupies the lowest levels of the social pyramid.
Not only is he poor and illiterate, but his language,
traditions and customs continue to Isolate him from the
rest of the nation. Thus, the Indians represent a group
culturally apart within the larger community.
Despite the misguided efforts of past colonial
administrators, the Indians of Spanish Amer¬
ica have not been imprisoned behind the social barriers
of caste, although cultural 'differences, ignorance of Span¬
ish and geographical isolation can give the impression
that they live in a closed! world from which there is no
escape. But even in countries where movement up the
social ladder is weakest, there is a constant '"passing"
from the Indian to the mestizo group, and from the latter
to that of the '"whites." There are no constitutional or
legal obstacles to social advancement and since public
opinion attaches more value to social symbols, racial fea¬
tures are in no Way insuperable barriers for those who
seek to improve their status.
An Indian has only to speak Spanish, to change his
clothing and to leave his community in order to pass as
a mestizo. In exceptional circumstances, he can become
a member of the bourgoisie by entering one of the liberal
professions, and, with the help of politics, even rise to
power. The history of Latin America offers many examples
of such ascensions perhaps the best proof that racialism
in the strict sense of the term, is superficial and in no
way deeply-rooted.
Recent economic progress, road development, the begin¬
nings of industrialization, education and many additional
factors, have had a decisive influence on race relations.
Thousands of Indians have settled in the towns where
they form a miserable proletarian group which neverthe¬
less is losing its Indian characteristics by adopting the
appearance and behaviour of the mestizo. Thus, by this
process of absorption we find that although the Indian
population is increasing numerically it is paradoxically
diminishing in general in comparison with other ethnic
groups.
The Indian is not dying out, but he is slowly merging
with the nation. For example, there are villages in Chile
which a century and a half ago were referred to in
documents as "native" communities; today, though
they remain free of any inter-mixture, they are consi¬
dered pure Chilean and "white".
From this very brief outline it might be assumed that
the countries conquered and colonized by Spain are free
of any form of racialism. Nevertheless, many common
attitudes and casual remarks frequently overheard show
that this is not so. Many intellectuals and politicians
suffer from what, for want of a better phrase, I might
call "'racial pessimism". I have noticed that many other¬
wise intelligent and perceptive individuals have a ten-
22
dency to lay the blame for everything that is criticized
in their countries on "the heavy burden of Indian blood".
For some, the country's future depends on the elimina¬
tion of the Indians and their replacement by European
immigrants.
Even in countries where the Indian has disappeared,
the name is still used as an insult, and "Indian blood"
is invoked to explain the reason for a person's dis-
agreable character. Vulgarity is also easily interpreted
as "Indian blood" coming to the fore.
"Racial pessimism" is also revealed by the shame cer¬
tain leading circles feel over the existence of Indians in
their country. When their presence cannot be denied, an
attempt is made to minimize their importance. Official
statistics often reflect this.
But scorn for the Indian is not limited to the upper
classes. It appears with even more virulence among the
mestizos who are closest to the Indians and it is not
infrequent to find it even among the Indians themselves.
Nothing is more ludicrous than to hear an Indian cook
call her kitchen attendant an "ignorant Indian".
But let us beware of appearances. Latin-American
"racialism" differs from that found in other parts of the
world. It is the expression of scorn for the customs and
manners of classes considered to be ignorant and uncouth
rather than a systematic isolation of groups having dif¬
ferent physical appearances. Very often, opinions which
can easily be interpreted as evidence of intolerance or
racialism are mere expressions of scorn for rural or urban
populations whose continuing way of Ufe has little in
common with the standards set by the nation. However,
since social hierarchy and racial origin follow an almost
identical pattern, it is easy and tempting to draw racia¬
list conclusions.
Finally, the racialist theories of the 19th century helped
to confirm the ruling classes in old prejudices inherited
from the colonial era.
An intellectual counter-current dating from the Mexi¬
can Revolution (1910-1917) has done much to reduce the
more or less conscious racialism of the élite groups. This
movement, which finds as much expression in art as in
politics, has been called indigenismo, and opposes opti¬
mism to the traditional racial pessimism.
r;
H* AR from being a national burden, the Indians
JL. are seen as a rich source of vitality and talent.
People of the soil, they have inherited its spirit, and are
the custodians of its most authentic values. For the ind¬
igenistas, the most urgent task is integration of the Ind¬
ians into the rest of the population. Inspired by the
example of Father Bartolomé de Las Casas, the great
16th-century pioneer, the indigenistas urge the study of
Indian cultures and the preservation of their artistic and
even social traditions. Such has been their enthusiasm
that it has almost led to an inverted form of racialism.
In matters of race relations, Latin America thus offers
us a blurred picture, full of shadows and light. There
can be no doubt that the solution of the problem lies in
the integration of the Indian into the rest of the nation.
This is happening spontaneously and it is what the Indian
himself wants. Education could speed up the process.
However, the steps governments take on behalf of the
Indians will ultimately depend on the abandonment of
certain prejudices which often serve economic and poli¬
tical interests and are hardly reconcilable with the rapid
development of these ancient lands of the Indians.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
NEGRO JEWS are found in various parts of the world. In the U.S.A. they maintain synagogues in New York,
Brooklyn, Chicago, Philadelphia and Cincinnati. The largest community lives in Harlem, N.Y. and numbers
nearly 5,000. Photo shows Chief Rabbi Wentworth Matthew (left) preaching a Sabbath sermon in Harlem syna¬
gogue. The more observing adherents follow modified Orthodox ritual including Kosher food preparation.
The children are taught Hebrew. Most American Negro Jews are believed to be the descendents of converted
slaves born in the homes of Jewish planters. In the West Indies, Spanish and Portuguese Jews often intermarried
with Negroes and congregations of Negro Jews still exist in Jamaica and the Virgin Islands. Another community
of Negro Jews lives on the Loango coast of West Africa, not far from the Portuguese island of Sao Thome where
2,000 Jewish children were shipped in 1493 during the Inquisition. Negro Jews are also found in Madagascar,
and North Africa. The Falashas or Abyssinian Jews, though not considered originally African, claim descent
from Menelik, son of King Solomon and the Queen of Sheba. Not to be confused with Negro Jews are the Black
Jews of India, so-called to distinguish them from the White Jews living In the same towns. The colour of their
skin, however, is dark brown, not black. (For Chinese Jews, see The Unesco Courier, February Issue 1957).
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
X-RAY OF THE RACIST
by Marie Jahoda
Photos Ian BeTy © Magnum
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
T
n contrast to other forms of violence between
individuals, the ultimate justification of racial
-^^»- violence is given in terms of who the victim is
rather than what he has done. Physical violence against
an individual because of his race often meets with
a curious condonement and silent approval from other
members of the aggressor's race, even though they
themselves do not engage in it. And even where racial
violence is officially frowned upon, there are many who
admit to a sympathetic understanding of acts designed
to humiliate a member of another race, of discrimination
against him, or of the expression of wholesale dislike for
the members of another lace.
In Brazil, Jamaica, Cuba and Hawaii, for example,
several races live without signs of overt conflict. Yet it is
a comment on the general state of affairs that these few
examples should be so well known as exceptions to the
Photo Werner Bischof © Magnum
A COUNTRY DIVIDED. South Africa today is a country
divided against itself. The government's "apartheid" (apart¬
ness) policy and the racial segregation decrees through which it
is applied have provoked riots at home and condemnation abroad.
Using such criteria as the shape of noses, kinkiness of hair, the
apartheid system classifies Negroes, mixed-blood Negroes and
Asians by race, then allocates to each a rigid, underprivileged
place in society in which residence, travel, employmentand
even drinkcan be determined by government officiais. Photos
show: opposite page, top, white South Africans hold mass meet¬
ing in support of apartheid policy; bottom, Negroes demons¬
trate as armoured car stands by. In protest against apartheid,
signs like that above have appeared in hotels in Asian countries.
rule. What is the meaning of racial antagonism for those
who feel it?
There exists a large body of research on the reasons
people give for their dislike of various racial groups. If
one asks certain people in the United States of America,
for example, to explain their antagonism to Negroes, the
odds are that they will use one or more of the following
phrases: they are inferior, they are lower class, they are
low in intelligence, they force out the whites, they are
lazy, sloppy, dirty, immoral, oversexed, troublesome,
childish, they have a bad smell and carry diseases.
If one inquires why Jews are disliked, one learns that
they have all the money, control business, are capitalists
but also communists, are clannish but also intrude on
other people's affairs, are smart, intellectuals, think
themselves better than others, work too hard but never
do manual labour, and are noisy, bad-mannered and
emotional.
Before one takes this array of statements as data for
an interpretation of the state of mind of the person who
makes them a question must be faced: are these perhaps
realistic descriptions of what the majority of Negroes and
Jews are like? The question is crucial. For if these
descriptions are broadly speaking accurate, racial anta¬
gonism must obviously be interpreted differently than if
they are figments of the imagination.
There is every reason to believe that groups which do
not intermingle freely with members of other groups,
which have traditions of long standing, their own way of
bringing up children and special social institutions, norms
and values will develop common characteristics. The fact
of belonging to a group which is the target of strong
racial antagonism must be assumed to be a particularly
weighty influence on the behaviour and character of
members of that group.
It is conceivable that many Negroes are lazy because
the assertion of white supremacy denies them the fruit
of industriousness; that some crave for sex relations with
white women because the white community has establish¬
ed a taboo against such relations, a symbol of their
alleged inferiority against which they rebel. Equally, it is
possible that centuries of persecution have made some
Jews clannish while others try to enter the Gentile world
in an effort to escape their fate.
T
here is a steadily growing body of evidence to
^ show that inadequate reality-testing is charac¬
teristic of many who feel hostile to racial outgroups.
A drastic demonstration of this was given by Professor
E.L. Hartley who included in a study of racial anta¬
gonism three non-existent groups whom he called the
Danireans, the Piraneans, and the Wallorians. A large
proportion of those who disliked Negroes and Jews also
expressed a dislike for these fctitious groups and advo¬
cated restrictive measures against them.
The idea that racial antagonism is determined from
within rather than by adequate reality testing is support¬
ed by Robert Merton's argument that the very same
qualities which are given as reasons for disliking another
racial group the "out-group" as the sociological jargon
terms it are often highly appreciated when found in a
member of the "in-group."
In comparing current beliefs about Jews and Japanese
in the United States with those about Abraham Lincoln
he says: "Did Lincoln work far into the night? This
testifies that he was industrious, resolute, persévérant and
eager to realize his capacities to the full. Do the out-
group Jews or Japanese keep these same hours? This
only bears witness to their sweatshop mentality, their
ruthless undercutting of American standards, their unfair
competitive practices. Is the in-group hero frugal, thrifty
and sparing? Then the out-group villain is stingy,
miserly and penny-grinding," and so on.
Several psychoanalytically oriented studies have taken
the problem a step further by actually investigating the
nature of the experience with members of the disliked
group. In some cases it was found that the antagonism
persisted without any personal contact whatsoever. In
others, the antagonistic person maintains that his judge¬
ment is based on direct experience with members of the
disliked group; yet his descriptions of such contact are
bare of all individual characteristics; it is as if he had
met not an individual human being but the incorporation
of his idea manifesting only the allegedly typical qualities.
But perhaps more interesting are -those who were able
to evaluate the individuals whom they met correctly
without letting such an experience interfere with their
general judgement of the group. In a study of army
veterans by B. Bettelheim and M. Janowitz one man was
quite explicit on his general dislike for Jews, and then
continued: "There was one Jewish fellow in our outfit
whom I liked especially, he wasn't like the ordinary run
of Jews, that's why I remember him."
This is a typical case of the notorious remark "Samp
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE RACIST MIND (Cont'd)
COUNTERFEITERS OF REALITY
of my best friends are Jews, but..." Even more remark¬
able is the case of a man included in another study who
when not quite in control of himself would call an
opponent "dirty Jew" and generally complain that Jews
take advantage of others. His first contact with Jews
occurred in childhood when he established a friendship
with a Jewish boy and his family which lasted for years.
As an adult he had several Jewish friends. His anti-
Semitism existed notwithstanding such friendly contacts.
In these cases reality is assigned the place of exception;
the rule is established by untested preconceptions.
It is claimed by most who defend their prejudices that
adequate reality-testing has led them to assert the
inferiority of certain races. This may be a logical
possibility. It is, after all, conceivable that a man may
meet a whole series of exploiting Jews or unintelligent
Negroes. These qualities exist in all races sufficiently
often to make such a chance occurrence possible. Granted
this logical possibility, the arguments used in the defence
of prejudice give little support to the idea that it is often
based on such statistical misfortune in encounters with
people belonging to another race. Let us examine some.
In the stupendous dilemma in which the Union of South
,
îr If?
imr, i ü.»*
United Press International
FIRE HOSES are turned on a crowd of Whites and Negroes following
recent sit-in lunch counter demonstrations in Chatanooga, Tennes¬
see. A movement against food service segregation in department stores
and other establishments has been spreading through the American
South in recent months, and has been marked at times by violence.
26
Africa finds itself with regard to its racial problems one
might expect the apartheid policy to be based on the
assertion of adequate reality-testing. But this is not the
case. Gwendolen Carter says in summarizing her sober
and extensive studies: "They [the Nationalists] admit,
somewhat reluctantly, that there are more highly de¬
veloped Africans: . . . Beyond this, there is something
irrational, but none the less compelling, in the Nationalist
attitude toward non-Europeans, an instinctive distaste,
even horror at the thought of being associated with them
on equal terms	 The most extreme example of this
sentiment is bound up with the phrase: Do you want
your daughter to marry a Native?"
"One of the most surprising features of Nationalist
arguments is the frequency with which they justify
apartheid measures on the ground that they are necessary
for preserving an acute colour sense. In other words,
it almost seems as if Nationalists fear that close proximity,
rather than intensify distaste, may blur the differences
felt between Europeans and non-Europeans. . ..
"But the fear of a white minority lest it lose its
distinctive identity is a sentiment which may override
more mellow considerations based on personal experience.
European South Africans, and Afrikaners in particular,
are often devoted to individual Africans with whom they
have an easy and mutually satisfactory relationship, but
this is very different from the attitude they hold towards
Africans in the mass, who somehow tend to take on the
worst features of savagery and unreliability of the most
drastic stories about Africans they have ever heard."
This account of the irrational elements in the idea of
white supremacy captures the way and even the language
in which some white Southerners in the United States
express their antagonism against Negroes.
1*
H ^Between the two lists of stereotyped beliefs
J^^^r about Negroes and Jews there is a significant
difference. While the Negroes are called lazy, dirty and
oversexed, that is without control over their instincts, the
accusation against the Jews that they control industry,
.have all the money, are ambitious and push aheadgo
in the opposite direction: they have too much control.
These two types of accusation correspond to two types
of neurotic conflict: the conflict which arises when man
cannot master his instinctive drives to fit into rationally
and socially approved patterns of behaviour; and the
conflict which arises when man cannot live up to the
aspirations and standards set by his conscience. In such
conflicts, shame over one's untamed nature or guilt over
one's unachieved standards impede the functioning of
the ego and, in severe cases, the conflict becomes para¬
lysing.
This parallel between the content of racial stereotypes
and the basic conflicts of man is not fortuitous. Here,
it is worth noting that under the National-Socialist
regime in Germany, where the Jews were the major target
for out-group hostility, the stereotyped beliefs about them
combined what the existence of two target groups on the
American scene permits to be separated.
Ample evidence for this latter type was found in a study
using detailed case histories of persons under psycho¬
analytic treatment who also happened to be anti-Semitic.
One of these patients, for example, disliked the Jews
because they were "emotional and untamed" but also
"shrewd, capable and industrious." The life history of
this man showed that he, too, was shrewd, capable and in¬
dustrious, but unable to experience any warm emotion.
This inability was actually one of the reasons which
made him look for help in psychoanalytic treatment.
There it emerged that very early in life this man had
found himself in a conflict of loyalty to an overstrict, rig¬
idly joyless mother and a happy-go-lucky father who
spsnt little time at home, perhaps not surprisingly con¬
sidering the atmosphere of gloomy righteousness which
pervaded it. For the little boy the conflict between the
parents presented itself as an irreconcilable dichotomy
between being happy and being good. Under the dominant
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
HAWAII has been called a laboratory of human relations. The mingling of numerous peoples, notably from Asia but also from
Europe, the Americas and Oceania is one of the most remarkable features of the 50th State of the U.S. where the colour bar and
racial prejudice are practically non-existent. Photos above show some of the women of Hawaii. From left to right
they are: pure Chinese, Nippo-Portuguese, Dutch-Hawaiian, girl of Chinese descent, Hawaiian-American, Sino-Hawaiian.
influence of his mother he chose the path of goodness and
success, trying valiantly to suppress, as she did, all tender
and warm feelings. Yet the suppression did not wholly
succeed, and as a result he suffered from loneliness and
emotional emptiness in an outwardly successful life.
The culturally prevalent stereotype to the effect that
Jews manage to combine emotions with success was a
fearful reminder to that man that he had built his life
on a false premise. By despising the Jews for the com¬
bination of qualities that he had denied himself, he tried
to defend his own unsatisfactory device of a way of life.
Since he could not satisfy his own longing for emotional
warmth, the burden was easier to carry if he found emo¬
tionality in others despicable.. He acted like a thief who
joins the crowd shouting "Stop thief" in an effort to divert
attention from himself.
For him, it would have made little psychological sense
to rationalize his anti-Semitism by accusing the Jews of
being capitalists, communists, or bad-mannered. Neither
would it have made sense to hate Negroes or Catholics,
for the very combination of qualities which he needed to
hate in order to make bearable their absence in himself,
are not easily attributed to either of these groups.
Since it is often reality which threatens to destroy the
defensive bulwark of the prejudiced person, it is reality
which he tries to manipulate so that it will better fit his
psychological needs. Thus, prejudiced persons use what¬
ever social power they have at their disposal to create
conditions which compel the target group to become as
the stereotype prescribes. A vicious circle is set in motion,
an example of what Merton has called the "self-fulfilling
prophecy".
In some southern parts of the United States, for exam¬
ple, the Negroes are rejected because they are lower class
and uneducated. Because they are so regarded, oppor¬
tunities for advancement and better education are denied
to them; as a consequence many Southern Negroes do
indeed suffer from low status and low educational level,
thus apparently justifying the original act of discrimi¬
nation.
Much the same could be said about the apartheid poli¬
cies in South Africa: while the native populations are
rejected because of their different culture, the means of
reducing the difference are nevertheless eschewed. In¬
stead, all policies are designed to intensify the difference.
It may well be, however, that South Africa is about to
demonstrate that such manipulation of reality does not
constitute an effective support for the psychological
defence mechanisms at play. For the inexorable fact of
the South African economy is that it depends largely on
African labour, thus requiring contact between the races
which apartheid aims to destroy.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
FRANK CONVERSATION AT
AN PTY TABLE
by Khushwant Singh
The Coffee House in the Delhi Uni¬
versity Campus was jammed. There
was a long queue of students waiting
for seats and as soon as anyone got up someone would
dash to take his chair. I paid for my cup of coffee and
looked around for a table. There didn't seem any hope
of getting one and I decided to gulp down my beverage
standing by the bar as many others were doing.
I suddenly caught sight of an empty table in the far
corner of the room empty in as much three of the
four chairs were unoccupied and the fourth was
taken by someone who had hidden his face behind a
newspaper. I threaded my way through the crowded
room, guarding my precious cup of coffee from the noisy,
gesticulating mob of boys and girls.
"Are these seats taken?", I asked, as politely as I could.
The man lowered his newspaper for a second and replied
with a gruff "No." He was a Negro.
I took my seat and began to sip my coffee in silence.
Something about the man's attitude and the empty seats
in a cafe with a queue waiting to find places made me
uneasy and curious. After a polite cough, I opened the
conversation.
"Are you studying in Delhi University?"
The man lowered his newspaper again and replied as
offensively as before. "'Yes I am. Do you want to see
my identity card?"
Before I could protest he had fished out his student's
card and placed it on the table. He was from Ghana and
as dark as they come. I put out my hand to him. "I
didn't mean to be rude: I just wanted to talk. I have
never met anyone from Ghana before. My name is Singh.
I am a professor at Aligarh."
He took my hand gingerly and mumbled his name. My
opening gambit was another faux pas. "How do you like
being in India?"
"Do you really want to know?" he asked, mincing every
word. "The truth, the whole truth and not just propa¬
ganda!"
He told me of the few months he had
been in Delhi; of the hospitality
extended by Indian boys and girls to
"white" (and occasionally "brown") foreign students, but
denied to Negro students; of the cold aloofness of the
majority of Indians towards him and his fellow Africans;
of the indifference of waiters in cafes to serve Negro
patrons; of the crowded coffee house and empty seats
around a table where a Negro happened to sit.
His words stung like slaps on the face. Weren't we the
nation who more loudly than others proclaimed the equa¬
lity of races and read holier-than-thou sermons to the
South African whites and the Little Rock Americans?
"But our government..." I protested.
"I said nothing against your government", he inter¬
rupted impatiently. "It is your government that has
invited me and hundreds of other Africans to study in
Indian Universities. It gives us good scholarships. We
are invited to meet the President and the Prime Minister.
And your Vice-President, Dr. Radhakrishnan, has asked
28
me to tea more than once. Sometimes the Vice-Chan¬
cellor and the Professors also ask us to their homes. But
it is always an occasion a sort of "African occasion" as
a duty that has to be performed. The students who
don't have to do it, never ask us. They seldom mix with
us and even avoid sitting near us." Didn't I see for
myself?
The Indian Constitution has abolished race and caste
distinctions but the Indian people are still a long way
from abolishing prejudices based on race and colour for
our caste-system is essentially based on colour complexes.
The Sanskrit word for caste is Varna which literally
means colour. Varna goes back to the times when the
fair-skinned Aryans invaded India over three thousand
years ago.
The first lot of invaders did not bring their women and
there was a certain amount of intermingling of the Aryan
and the dark negroid Adibasi (aboriginal) who the Aryan
had subjugated. Then more Aryans came with their
women and families. The aboriginals were pushed out
into the jungles and reduced to servitude. To exploit
the situation to their best advantage, the Aryans devel¬
oped the caste system based on occupation and' the
"purity" of race.
On the top were the Brahmins who had
the monopoly of learning. Next came
the Kshatryas or the warriors who
defended the society. The third group were the
Vaisyas or the traders. The fourth were the Sudras or the
workers. And the fifththe old aboriginalwas reduced
to doing the most unpleasant jobs like scavenging, skinn¬
ing dead animals, and given no status in society by
being declared an untouchable.
This system which had its apologist in Manu developed
a rigidity which made intermarriages between the dif¬
ferent castes almost impossible. There is enough evidence
to prove that the basis of the division was colour. Even
to this day the Brahmins and the Kshatryas are lighter-
skinned than the Vaisya and the Sudra. And the
Untouchable is dark and negroid.
Prejudices die hard. The Indian Government has made
valiant efforts to wipe out the caste system. All temples
have been thrown open to "untouchables". In villages
where the lower castes were not allowed to draw water
out of wells belonging to the upper castes, there are
governing bodies (Panchayats, with at least one member
elected from the "untouchables") whose duty it is to
see that no discrimination is practised by one caste
against another, and if there be any case, to get the aid
of the police to rectify it.
The law comes down heavily on the discriminator.
Government action and rapid industrialization has begun
to break the caste edifice but it will be a long time before
the colour complex is erased from the Indian mind. Pick
up any daily newspaper and turn to the matrimonial ads.
You will see that in nine out of ten the one quality that
an Indian male demands of his prospective wife is that
she should be fair, and the one thing that a father will
advertise (if he can) about his unmarried daughter, is
her light skinor keep silent on the subject of looks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
THE YELLOW STAR. "Stars" is a memorable anti-racist film made by a combined German-Bulgarian production team. Its
story concerns a German soldier in Bulgaria during the last war, who is ordered to round up the Jewish inhabitants for depor¬
tation. He falls in love with one of thema young Jewish schoolteacherand his eyes are opened to the injustice of racial hatred.
THE CINEMA SAYS NO!
TO RACISM
by Louis Marcorelles
B"^ iLM makers have long realized that the cinema
B is more than mere entertainment and that
JtL*. it can be a powerful weapon to influence
public opinion. In the 1940-1941 period there is no space
here to discuss pre-war films a number of deeply sig¬
nificant films appeared, such as "Grapes of Wrath" and
"Citizen Kane." But it was not until 1945 that a syste¬
matic study was made of some of today's key problems
anti-Semitism and the status of the Negro, for example.
Then, in rapid succession, films like "Crossfire," "Gentle¬
man's Agreement," "Home of the Bravé" and "Pinky"
' showed that Hollywood had begun to face the serious
problems of our time in earnest.
Another ten years went by before really significant films
on these subjects began to be made and before producers
emerged who were capable of exploting to the full the
themes they had chosen. Among these producers two
stand out: a Frenchman, Alain Renais and an American,
George Stevens.
Before winning international recognition and an award
at the Cannes Film Festival with his first full length
feature, "Hiroshima mon amour", which has since receiv¬
ed world-wide attention, Alain Renais had produced two
shorter films which creajted quite a sensation. In "Les
Statues meurent aussi" (Statues also die), a strongly pol¬
emical film, he showed the deterioration of Negro culture
after contact with the white civilization. At one parti¬
cularly dramatic moment he showed Negro musicians
playing the drums and immediately following this came a
scene of white policemen clubbing other Negroes.
Renais' "Nuit et Brouillard" is certainly the starkest,
most uncompromising film ever made on the Nazi death
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
THE CINEMA SAYS NO ! (Continued)
Cahiers du Cinéma Collection
DRAMA, PSYCHOLOGY AND RIDICULE are three ways in which the cinema has attacked racial prejudice. Left, "Pyra¬
mide Humaine", a new film by French anthropologist-producer Jean Rouch which tells how a young Parisian girl tries to improve
race relations between Negroes and whites in an African secondary school. In an American film, "The Defiant One", two convicts,
camps. And he undescored its message in the closing
moments by calling on all of us to see that such atrocities
never occur again.
"Hiroshima mon amour" tells a pathetic love story, but
over and above this it describes the encounter of two
civilizations against the backdrop of the Bomb. The story
of the two lovers would have been less moving, or rather,
their love would not have had the same significance had
the girl not been French and white and the man Japa¬
nese. After the film's release, the producer was agreably
surprised to find that the public accepted as perfectly
natural a situation that no other film had hitherto dared
to describe. We can perhaps go a step further and say
that the film's message strikes home harder because the
bomb was first dropped on a non-white nation. Since
the fllm is concerned with the drama of man's incommu-
nicability, the racial problem naturally received the chief
emphasis.
In "Giant" and "The Diary of Anne Frank", George
Stevens approached racism and anti-Semitism in the
Hollywood mannerthat is, a tendency to overembellish-
ment but no lack of courage. Richard Brookes, a younger
American producer, known for his liberal outlook, sought
to show the relationships between people of different races
and backgrounds, in "Blackboard Jungle", "The Last
Hunt" and "Something of Value".
A recent film dealing with this question is "The Defiant
One" made two years ago by director-producer Stanley
Kramer. It tells the story of an escaped convict, a white
man, who sacrifices his chance of freedom to save a
fellow escapee, a Negro, whom he had previously hated.
There is perhaps a weakness in these films in that they
concede too much to sentimentality and fail to trace back
problems to the basic causes.
30
Inasmuch as the films which deal with racial problems
demand absolute honesty from their producers and to the
extent that producers refuse to compromise with the
subject, such films run the risk of a cold reception from
public authorities and certain cinemagoers. Two films of
this kind which immediately come to mind are the Ger¬
man-Bulgarian co-production "Satrs-Sterne" (Stars),
made by Konrad Wolf from a remarkable scenario by the
Bulgarian, Angel Wagenstein, and "Come Back Africa",
produced by the American Lionel Rogosin. Despite their
frankness, and passionate conviction, and the Gha festival
awards they gained, neither of these films was successful,
at least in Europe.
Their styles are as different as the techniques used by
each producer. Whereas "Satrs-Sterne" was based on an
elaborate scenario, "Come Back Africa", because of the
almost clandestine conditions in which it was shot, is
almost entirely a work of improvisation. Each, in its own
way, is a noteworthy testimonial the first on anti-Semi¬
tism in Nazi Germany and the second on anti-Negro
racism in the Union of South Africa in 1958.
Rogosin has used a kind of journalistic approach, striv¬
ing to give us a maximum of hard-hitting facts and
images. In his anxiety to impress the spectator and to
win his sympathies, the producer has sometimes been
driven to extremes in simplification. The limited means
he had at his disposal are also reflected in the awkward¬
ness of certain sequences. Here we are not dealing with
a technically perfect film (nearly all Hollywood films are
"technically perfect" but this does not prevent them from
sometimes being boring). No, this is a sort of cry from
the heart which says: "This cannot and must not be
allowed to go on".
"Satrs-Sterne" is obviously a much more subtle produc-
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October I960
a Negro and a white man, break out of prison while chained together. Their initial feelings of hatred and distrust are even¬
tually replaced by understanding and real friendship. In "The Great Dictator", Charlie Chaplin stigmatized hatred and brutality
by ridicule. Right, Chaplin and Paulette Goddard, as two Jewish citizens, are pursued by stormtroopers of a racist dictator
tion and owes a great deal to the scenario "a la Brecht"
written by Wagenstein. We see a typical German soldier,
on occupation duty in a small Bulgarian town, gra¬
dually becoming conscious of the true meaning of the
Nazi system. The film is doubly successful in that it not
only shows the step-by-step awakening of a man's
conscience, but also the suffering of a whole people arbi¬
trarily oppressed, as seen through the eyes of a young
Jewish girl.
In Czechoslovakia and Yugoslavia, several films
equally sincere, but perhaps less skillful have dealt with
the subject of racial persecution, thus bringing these
problems before a wide public. In France, Claude Ber-
nard-Aubert brought to the screen an indictment of the
destructive effects of strife between whites and Negroes
in an imaginary country. More significant was anthropo¬
logist Jean Rouch's, "Moi, un Noir," a half-fictional, half-
documentary film. Rouch filmed a plot improvised by
Negroes from the Ivory Coast and then recorded as a
sound-track commentary the freely expressed views of
one of the actors. One of Rouch's achievements was to
reveal some of the feelings which grip the often uprooted
peoples who have suddenly been brought into contact
with the white civilization and whose ways and ideas they
try clumsily to imitate.
Rouch was bitterly attacked by the Negro elites of these
same lands and accused of making a caricature of the
less fortunate of their countrymen. The proper answer
to these criticisms was that the rather eccentric
characters depicted in '"Moi, un Noir" were not present¬
ed as Negroes, but as the handiwork of a white civilization
which until recently tried to impose its standards nearly
everywhere. These same critics would probably have been
less severe had the fllm made by a Negro. And here we
come up against one of the important problems of world
film-making in the next decade. Until now, as far as
we know, no fllm on Negro problems and with a cast of
Negro actors, has yet been made by a Negro producer.
Looking beyond the problem of film production and the
growing attention that must be given, not only to the
Negro film industry of the future, tout also to the fllm
industries in embryo of Asia and Latin America, we have
also to consider the equally important question of dis¬
tribution. Film distributors display just as much inertia
as the general public. Western fllmgoers, in particular,
still reject things that are outside the ordinary run of
their way of life and traditions. They often spurn films
which do not feature their favourite stars or in which
civilizations, often thousands of years old, confront them
with (for them) unfamiliar problems.
Naturally, we should not go to the other extreme and
automatically agree to run films simply because they have
been made by a small country and with a minimum of
technical equipment. Even a recognized masterpiece like
the Indian film, "Pather Panchali" ran into difficulties in
Paris and New York.
Today the cinema is no longer the harmless distraction
that certain unimaginative business men still persist in
considering it to be. It demands on all levels from its
creators to the viewing public an increased sense of res¬
ponsibility. Its development on truly international lines
implies the removal of the last traces of racism from our
world. In any case, I do not believe that today's young
generation, whatever the difficulties facing them, will res¬
pond as was once the case to a call to hatred from
unscrupulous leaders. The world is changing and the
cinema must undoubtedly follow this evolution. In the
words of the French critic, Léon Moussinac, "It was born
to speak the message of human unity".
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
P'»¿ )o ce*\ {-oleo , z ¿Ä-&
ík ^e Zok w^w^ewN,
eCr^ Ka^b °^ r\acxy
Keystone
One day in June 1942 a little Jewish girl, hiding with her parents in occupied Amsterdam, received a
notebook for her 13th birthday. For two years she kept a diary which stopped three days before her
family was arrested by the Nazis and she was sent to the concentration camp of Bergen-Belsen where
she died in March 1 945. (Two months later the camp was liberated by British troops.) In her last entry
on July I 5, 1 944, she wrote: "I have not abandoned my hopes even if they appear absurd and unattainable.
Despite everything, I believe that at the bottom of their hearts people are not wicked... 1 continue to
believe in the innate goodness of man." Anne's "Diary of a Young Girl" is one of the most moving stories
of the last war. Spirited, modest, witty yet simple, it deserves to be read at least once by every young
person. Translated into 20 languages, the Diary has been made into a film and has been staged success¬
fully for years. Over 30 troupes once presented the play simultaneously in Germany. Below, Anne (in circle) in a Dutch school, aged seven. Next to
her picture, above, Anne wrote: "This is a photo as I would wish myself to look all the time. Then I would perhaps have a chance to go to Hollywood."
Photo Taken m 1936 by Alg, Holl Fotopersbureau, Courtesy " Elle " Paris
THE DIARY OF
ANNE FRANK
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. October 1960
Letters to the Editor...
EARLIEST 'ESPERANTO' STAMP
Sir,
Both philatelists and Esperantists
will have been pleased to see in your
April issue, M. Pierre Girot's in¬
teresting letter listing some of the
stamps which have been issued by
various countries in honour of Dr.
Zamenhof and his language. A col¬
lection of "Esperanto on Stamps"
however should begin with the two
Russian stamps issued in October 1925
in honour of Dr. A.S. Popov, the
pioneer of wireless telegraphy. These
stamps bear, above the portrait of
Dr. Popov, the Esperanto words
"Inventisto de Radio, Popov" (In¬
ventor of Radio). This is the first
instance of the use of Esperanto on
postage stamps. The latest Esperanto
issue comes from Bulgaria and shows
a portrait of Dr. Zamenhof and the
green star emblem of the Esperantists.
C. W. Hill
Wolverhampton, England
GODS OF THE NILE
Sir,
Perusing your
magnificent special
issue of February
1960 on "Save the
Treasures of Nu¬
bia" I was struck
by the plate of
"Two Nile Gods"
decorating "two
thrones of the co¬
lossi of Rameses II
on the facade of
the Great Temple
" at Abu Simbel."
I am, unfortunately, no student of
Egyptology but sorcery does sometimes
come my way and I would be greatly
obliged if you could get one of your
experts to say whether they are dugs
under the inner arms of the gods and,
if so, do they have any significance?
P. J. Quinlivan
Port Moresby, Papua
Ed. note: In answer to this letter,
Madame Christiane Desroches-Noble-
court, Curator of Egyptian Antiquities,
Louvre Museum, Paris, has given us the
following information: The god of the
Nile or rather the spirits symbolizing the
Nile is often represented by two figures:
the spirit of the southern waters having
a lily headdress and that of the noithern
waters a papyrus. These two spirits
fiequently figure in scenes where the
Pharaoh is entrusted with the rule of the
country. In this ceremony, the spirits
wreath around a large hieroglyphic
symbol {representing the trachea and the
lungs) the floral emblems of the two
provinces, thus conferring on the king
supremacy over the whole land. The
king must first and foremost assure the
sustenance of the country: this is, only
possible when the harvests are abundant
and, thanks to the irrigation of the land
by the flooding of the Nile, bring pros
perity. The spirit of the Nile, either
alone or evoking the two regions, or
again shown on a frieze bearing offerings
which correspond to the names or
provinces, is always depicted as a
powerful figure, the abdomen often well-
rounded and protruding and supported
by a boatman's leather belt. The torso
is always uncovered and only the collar
bones are covered. Finally, this generous
spirit, as the nourisher of Egypt, is
endowed with an ample bosom, nearly
always poitrayed as two heavy breasts.
On the reliefs, because of the special
characteristics of Egyptian draughtsman¬
ship, only one of these breasts can be
seen in the same way that only one eye
and one ear are represented. Neverthe¬
less, we are sure that they had tno
bi easts, thanks to plastic representations
preserved in museums (for example, the
two monumental statues of the Nile
spirits dating from the Hyksos period,
now in the Cairo Museum).
DANGERS OF ALCOHOLISM
Sir,
I noted with interest that a reader
asked if it would be possible to have
an article on Alcoholism. I, too,
would very much like to see something
on this subject as it seems too few
people realize the dangers of such and
the good work being done in many
countries to fight this disease. It
seems too few people understand what
are the causes and effects of Al¬
coholism, and how it can be con¬
trolled. I am sure an article on this
would be a great education and
-warning to your readers.
I must also compliment you on the
fine magazine and in particular the
high value of the articles in it, which
give me a bird's eye view of the many
and different peoples and their
cultures.
Robert B. Burns
Grafton, New Zealand
HANDIWORK OF ALL MEN
Sir,
Like you I deplore the fact that
so many people are familiar only with
their own civilization and refuse to
recognize that thousands of years ago
people in different parts of the world
created great civilizations whose in¬
fluence spread around them. I believe
that "civilization" is the sum total of
all civilizations, that is, it is drawn
from the multifold efforts made down
the centuries by men all over the
world to improve living conditions,
to learn more about the world in
which they live, to study its natural
laws, to discover more about mankind
and its spiritual aspirations and to
translate all these things into works
and masterpieces.
Today we live on a shrinking world :
continents are crossed in a matter of
hours and radio flashes news around
the world in an instant. People must
get to know each other better and
like each other more. Would it not
therefore be a good idea to produce
a book (or if one already exists, simply
to make it easily accessible) in which
all peoples would describe the part
they have played in creating the
world's civilization. They would tell
of their inventions and discoveries, of
the awakening of their minds, feelings
and consciences, and they would
describe the masterpieces they had
sired and the poems they had written.
The descendants of those who
created the great civilizations of anti¬
quity must rid themselves of their
inferiority complexes and no longer
view with envy the glory of their
ancestors. It is normal for centuries
of inspired creative work to be
followed by centuries of repose. But
I believe this is a temporary situation
and that the day will come when,
with strength renewed, the heirs of
the ancient peoples, will rediscover
themselves and their genius and will
create new marvels in every field
scientific, literary, artistic and social.
Louise Cadoret
Nantes, France
WHAT'S IN A NAME?
Sir,
I was much interested in "The
Story of Place Names" in your April
number. With regard, however, to the
remark, "the Canary or Dog Islands,
so named by Columbus, because of the
wild dogs he found there," may I
point out that the name "Canaria"
was actually current in Pliny's days
(Natural History VI, 37, "Canariam
vocari a multitudine canum ingentis
magnitudinis") ? A reference to this
will be found in my book "Key to the
Names of British Birds" (Pitman,
1954) under Serinus canarius serinus.
R. D. Macleod
Etchingham, England
Ed. note: Our reader is correct. The
Romans learned of the existence of the
Canaries through Juba, King of Maure-
tenia, whose account of an expedition to
the islands, made about 40 B. C, was
preserved by the elder Pliny. This Ro¬
man author mentions "Canaria, so-called
from the multitude of dogs of great
size."
Sir,
In connexion with your article on
"The Story of Place Names" I thought
you might like to know that in the
Department of the Somme there is a
small village (143 inhabitants) called
'"Y". Any stranger seeing the signpost
indicating the name of this place might
think that is showed two roads forking
and that someone had forgotten to put
on the names of the places to which
they led. In the Somme too, I think
we have the longest place name in
France : Saint-Quentin-Lamotte-Croix-
au-Bailly.
Abbé Maurice Pillion
Gamaches, France
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Ne
THE UNESCO
PHILATELIC SERVICE
tfi UNITED NATIONS 0
< _______________
NATIONS UNIES
The latest commemorative stamps
to be issued by the United Nations
Postal Administration honour the
Fifth World Forestry Congress and
mark the fifteenth anniversary of the
United Nations itself. Above, the
forestry stamp issued on August
29 opening date of the World
Forestry Congress, in Seattle, U.S.A.
and printed in two denominations:
4 cents (dark blue, dark green, two
shades of blue-green and orange);
2 cents (dark blue, dark green, two
shades of yellow-green and orange).
Below, the stamp commemorating
the Fifteen Anniversary of the U.N.,
which is to be issued on U.N. Day,
October 24. This, the fourth U.N.
Commemorative stamp of 1960, is
being issued in 4 cent and 8 cent
denominations and a souvenir sheet,
value 12 cents, is being issued at
the same time. These stamps can be
obtained from the Unesco Phila¬
telic Service which has stamps and
first day covers issued by many
Member States to commemorate
important events in the history of
Unesco and the U.N. As the agent
in France of the U.N. Postal Adminis¬
tration, Unesco's Philatelic Service
stocks all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. Information on
Items available, their price and the
methods of payment, will be sentón
request by Unesco's Philatelic Ser¬
vice, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7*.
LENIN, SHAKESPEARE WORLD'S
MOST TRANSLATED AUTHORS
Lenin is the world's most-translated author. Shakespeare is in second place follow¬
ed by Jules Verne. Next come three Russian greats Tolstoy, Dostoievsky and
Gorki. This information comes from a panorama of the world's translations in
more than 200 languages provided by the current (eleventh) édition of Index
Translationum (1) published annually by Unesco. The latest Index comprises
translations published in 64 countries, mostly in 1958, the total of 29,213 being
well above the figure of 27,978 reported in 1957 in the previous edition.
As in the past, Lenin tops the list with 209 translations, most of them in the
languages of the U.S.S.R. Shakespeare, as runner-up, has 127 translations and
Jules Verne 107. Authors translated more than 60 times during the year inclu¬
ded Simenon, Engels, Marx, Agatha Christie, Alexander Dumas père, Earl Stan¬
ley Gardner, Zola and A. J. Cronin. An equally varied list is found in the
"more than 50 times" group: Turgenev, Conan Doyle, Hemingway, Dickens, Mau¬
passant, Steinbeck, Chekhov, Andersen, Pearl Buck, Jack London, Victor Hugo,
Mark Twain and Somerset Maugham.
On the basis of countries publishing translations, the U.S.S.R. remains in first
place with a total of 4,458 translations into all its languages, but this figure is
below that of the previous year (4,608). Then come Germany (showing
a marked increase with 2,513 as against 2,041), Czechoslovakia (translations into
Czech and into Slovak), Japan, France, the Netherlands, Rumania and Sweden,
all of them countries publishing more than 1,000 translations.
Information listed in the Index Translationum was supplied to Unesco by national
libraries or Unesco National Commissions in various countries, as well as by
publishing or bibliographical institutions.
(1) llth edition. Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7°) Price : $18.50 ; 92/6 (stg) ; 65 NF.
E:
QUINZIEME AHME mm
îXPLORING THE SEA: Scientists
and government representatives from 34
countries meeting in Copenhagen recently at
Unesco's invitation have agreed to place the
whole subject of oceanography on an inter¬
national footing. They recommended that
Unesco set up a permanent intergovern¬
mental océanographie commission to orga¬
nize joint action by states and international
bodies. In a unanimous declaration, the
Copenhagen Conference stated: "Because
the high seas are of value to all mankind
it is appropriate that their scientific study
for peaceful purposes be undertaken in con¬
cert by the international community of na¬
tions." (See "The Ocean's Secrets", The
Unesco Courier, July-August, 1960.)
NEW ASSISTANT DIRECTOR-
GENERAL FOR UNESCO: Mr. Alvin
Roseman, of the United States, has
taken up his duties as an Assistant Di¬
rector-General of Unesco. Born in
Cleveland, Ohio, Mr. Roseman has held
many U.S. Government posts and was
latterly Regional Director at the Inter¬
national Co-operation Administration in
Washington, in charge of United Sta¬
tes economic and technical aid to coun¬
tries in the Far East. He is now one
of three Assistant Directors-General of
Unesco, the other two being Mr. Jean
Thomas of France and Mr. Malcolm
Adiseshiah of India.
w,ARSAW SCHOOL HELPS NU¬
BIA: The pupils of the Zmichowska Girls
Secondary School in Warsaw have recently
heen helping to publicize Unesco's Inter¬
national Campaign for the Preservation of
the Monuments of Nubia. Using photo¬
graphs and articles taken from the special
Unesco Courier issue on Nubia (February
1960) they presented the history and geogra¬
phy of Egypt and Nubia to the rest of the
school, interspersed with facts about the
help needed to save the Nubian monuments
threatened by the waters of the new Aswan
Dam.
CROSS-CHANNEL POWER EX¬
CHANGE: Preparations are being made
to lay the cross-Channel cable which
next year will link the national electri¬
city systems of France and the United
Kingdom. The scheme has been made
possible because peak periods in electri¬
city consumption in the two countries do
not coincide due to differences in cli¬
mate, hours of work, mealtimes and
other habits. Power will be transferred
by submarine cable to meet peak hours
on either network, thus making it pos¬
sible to use each country's generating
capacity to full advantage.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TWO NEW UNESCO BOOKS ON RACE
Two new books have appear¬
ed in the series "The Race
Question in Modern Science".
RACE RELATIONS AND
MENTAL HEALTH by Marie
Jahoda is largely based on
thetheoretical statements and
findings of modern psycho¬
logy and of psychoanalysis.
$0.50, 2/6 stg., 1,75 NF
In THE JEWISH PEOPLE
Professor H. Shapiro exam¬
ines "the biological and an¬
thropological history of the
Jewish people from their
genetic origins through the
Diaspora to modern times.
He concludes that few other
peoples have had so varied
a biological history as the
Jews ; they have contributed
something of their genetic
heritage to more different
peoples than any other group
and have in return absorbed
an equal number of new
genetic strains.
$0.70, 3/6 stg., 2.50 N F
ts-sS?
by Marie Jahoda
relations
and ^eïltal
health
unesco
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaî, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 1 3/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
16, rueMarcq, Bruxelles, C.C P. 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei 151,
Antwerp.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd, 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librarla Alberto Sanchez Veloso
O'Reilly y Villegas, Havana - Librería Eco¬
nómica, Pte Zayas 505-7 Apartado I 13,
Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd.. 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. E|nar Munksgaard Ltd ,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P.O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy, Paris, 7«. C.C.P. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb fur Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, 1; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata"
Djalan Nusantara 22, Diakarta
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée. Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street. Tel-Aviv (l£ 4.-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 9 I
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings ( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, 135, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Ni¡-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & C- (Ned Ant ) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 1 00 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. CM. S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhiornet, Lille Gren-
sen, 7, Oslo. (N. kr. I 0)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. ~- Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. " RUCH " ul. Wiloza Nr. 46
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50), other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. - Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich. ,
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva C.C P.
1-481 I. (Fr. S 7).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S E.l.( I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 3.00.) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York. 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaj'a Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïgi,
Terazije 27/1 I. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
'Wfc
SOUTH AFRICAN
BONFIRE
Negroes near Johannesburg burn their
passbooks, symbol of racial discri¬
mination in S. Africa. Failure to pro-
ducethepassonrequesteven in cross¬
ing the street means fine or impri¬
sonment. Momentarily rescinded,
passbook rule is now reinstituted.
Photo Ian Berry © Magnum
V.
...",
]]>
</page>
</document>
