<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078193eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
SEPTEMBER 1962 (15TH YEAR) - PRICE 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) - 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
., *
^»í~****^
..m the Dolore* Olmedo Phillip* Collection, Mexico. Photo © Gisèle Freund.
n A linn All A fir llrVIA All AIIT This terra-cotta figure of a warrior holding a lance and shield from Ix-
rANUKAMA Jr Mt A liAN AK I tlan> Mex'co, was produced by the Pacific Coast Civilization that flou-
l niiviiniun wi iriLfllunil mil rlshed between 300 and 1250 A.D. It is one item in a rich collection of
Mexican art, dating from pre-Columbian times to the present day, which is now being shown in Europe. This travelling
exhibition has already visited Belgium, Switzerland, the Federal Republic of Germany, the Netherlands, Austria, the
U.S.S.R., Poland, France and Italy where it has been seen by many people. It will shortly be shown in Yugoslavia.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
Contents
No. 9
SEPTEMBER 1962
15TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
Tankers on the high seas.
The pollution of the oceans
through the discharge by
ships of fuel oil waste and
contaminated water ballast
has become a major world
problem. At a recent confer¬
ence in London, 40 nations
adopted measures to reduce
the fouling of the seas and
shores and the consequent
destruction of birds and
marine life. (Story page 10).
Photos (top) Esso (bottom) Spirale
Pag«i
4 MUSIC ON A STRING
The story of the violin family
by Claude Marly
10 DANGER ! OIL-POLLUTED SEAS
International action for a growing menace
by David Woodward
14 THE OCEAN UNDER A MICROSCOPE
A teeming world within the waters
by L. Howell-Rivero
17 PATTERNS OF ECONOMIC CHANGE
" The Anatomy of Underdevelopment " (Pt. II)
23 GERHART HAUPTMANN : DRAMATIST OF THE OPPRESSED
by Karl Ruhrberg
27 HOW TO BE AN AMATEUR ARCH/EOLOGIST
Digging up history as a hobby
by Beatrice de Cardi
31 JODO KUMAMI
King of storytellers for Kyoto's children
by Muneharu Kitagaki
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(H.C 62.1.1 72 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7\ France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
It is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English. French. Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re*
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unetco Courier le Indexed monthly In The Readert' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilton Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; I 0/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
The violin and the melodious sounds which
virtuosi extract from it are familiar to us all.
But casting off the blinkers of habit, let us take a fresh
look at this modest wooden case. How extraordinary it
is that a few plates of thin wood, and the friction of
horsehair on four strings should be able to produce the
quivering strains which lead and dominate an orchestra,
the powerful and moving voice that holds large audiences
in thrall. The miracle of the violin is indeed a miracle
of human art and ingenuity, which has never yet been
fully explained by science.
When the great Italian violin-makers of the sixteenth
and seventeenth centuries constructed models of string¬
ed instruments which have never since been rivalled,
they received no help from acoustics, a science which did
not then exist. Yet, by a process of trial and error,
repeated experiments and empirical research, and thanks
to the kind of Intuition which rewards tenacious effort,
they managed to achieve remarkable results and to
create sounding-boxes that correspond in every way to
the laws of modern acoustics.
The making of a stringed instrument is more than a
matter of technique. There are so many subtle rela¬
tionships between its component parts, between the
choice of the wood and the way in which it is worked,
between the capacity of the resonant box and the
thickness of its wooden plates, and between the wood and
the varnish, that no formula can be a guarantee of
success.
The instrument-maker's personal talent is all-impor¬
tant; his experience and skill cannot be conveyed in writ¬
ten Instructions, but must be passed on from man to man
in the course of a long apprenticeship. As a matter of
fact, this is unfortunate, because the old instrument-
maker's art is in great danger of being lost.
The quality of stringed instruments, of which violins,
violas and violoncellos are the most important, depends
primarily upon the wood of which they are made: epicea
excelsa for the upper part or belly, .maple for the back
and the "ribs" which form a violin's sides, ebony for the
finger-board, and Guiana "bees' wood" or Pernambuco
wood for the bow. Epicea, a variety of pine, is found in
Switzerland; maple is scattered through some valleys
of Central Europe. The wood must be compact and fine¬
grained, without knots, but with the "ripples" which
make the varnish shimmer.
Exposure, soil and climate have as much influence on
a crop of wood as they have on vines; the wood must be
cut "di quarto", that is, not longitudinally, but from the
bark to the heart, like the lith of an orange; only the
central part of the trunk not too near the roots, where
the wood would be too damp, or too near the top, where
the sun would have dried it out is considered satis¬
factory; and, lastly, the part exposed to the south is
held to be the best. All these prescriptions give an idea
of the care taken by stringed-instrument makers in
choosing their raw material.
The work of a master violin-maker is done entirely by
hand, and by the same craftsman, except for the bow,
The Indian ravanastron is
believed to be the oldest of
instruments played with a
bow. It may have travelled
to Arabia to become the
rebab (1). The rebab was
perhaps the father of the
rebec, reconstituted versions
of which are shown here (2),
though this mediaeval strin¬
ged instrument may be a
descendant of earlier Wes¬
tern ones. .Most widely-used
bowed instrument of the
Middle Ages was the viol.
Shown here are three "love
viols" from Germany and
Italy (3). The instrument ma¬
kers of the Tyrol and Cremo¬
na, in northern Italy, trans¬
formed the viol into violins
I ike this Stradivarius(4) dating
from 1724. This v¡olin(5)once o
belonged to Johann Strauss. £ V
THE
ANCESTORS FROM THE EAST
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
MUSIC
ON
A STRING
by Claude Marly
Young gipsy fiddler
i Goldner
Carved head decoration
on a "Viola d'Amore",
literally "love viol", made
by Nicolas Lupot (1758-
1824), a craftsman who
has often been called
"The French Stradivarius".
© Marcel Arthaud.
executed by a skilled bow-maker. Despite the simplicity
of its outline, a violin is composed of 83 to 85 parts, all
of which must be fashioned with the utmost care.
The violin-maker, with the help of a mould, cuts out
the back, which is generally made of two pieces glued
together so that the graining of the wood corresponds.
He fines down the arch of the belly so as to give it the
necessary convexity, forms the curve of the ribs with
a hot iron, calculates the size of the neck, which he fits
to the instrument, uses a penknife to cut the sound-
holes in the belly S-shaped holes which give the Ins¬
trument its resonance and elegance mounts the pegs
and bridge.
Lastly, with a little tool inserted in the sound-holes,
he fixes that essential part of the instrument which the
Italians and French call the soul and the Germans the
voice of the violin. This ls a wooden cylinder, designed
primarily to keep the belly firm under the pressure of
the strings; but It also seems to Influence resonance of
the Instrument, since a millimetre's difference In Its
position ls enough to alter that resonance.
Up to this point, however, the violin ls still unfinished;
It awaits Its finest adornment the famous "varnish", so
much appreciated by the connoisseurs, which enhances
the instrument's elegant curves and enables the light to
play on the grain of the precious wood. The purpose
of the varnish ls to protect the violin against the ravages
of time and climate; It ls highly Important because, even
though a bad violin cannot be Improved by a good
varnish, a bad varnish can "muffle" an excellent violin.
Unfortunately, the famous varnish of Cremona which
combined depth with transparence and gave the
CONT'D ON PAGE 7
VIOLI
CELTIC OR ARAB ORIGIN ?
FAMILY TREE
MUSIC OF THE MIDDLE AGES FOR VIRTUOSOS TOKEN OF REMEMBRANCE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
MUSIC ON
A STRING
(Cont'd)
In the early days of the
Renaissance, there were two
groups of stringed instruments
in Europe: vielles, which were
once used to accompany trou-
bador songs (and later evolved
into organistrums, or large
hurdy-gurdies) and the nobler
family of the viols, bowed
instruments whose gradual
modification no doubt pro¬
duced the violin, the most
Important of modern stringed
instruments. The legendary
name of Stradivarius domi¬
nates this branch of Instru¬
ment-making, which demands
great manual skill and a
perfect ear for tone. Below,
a well-known French violin
maker, Emile Français, in his
Paris workshop. Left, violins
drying after being varnished.
Varnish protects a violin but
can also affect its resonance.
Photos © Goursat
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
A lost secret of the Cremona craftsmen
Instruments their Inimitable golden or reddish tortoise-
shell colour, ls a lost secret. No chemical analysis has yet
revealed its composition. Some plants in the Tyrolese
woods are said to have produced a gum which, collected
In special bags, supplied the vlolln-makers of Cremona
with the main Ingredient of their oil varnish.
The last person able to secure these bags of gum
appears to have been Carlo Bergonzi, disciple of
Stradivari, who bought the master's workshop after his
death. Once the trees yielding It had been felled, this
gum could no longer be found, and the varnish has never
since been the same. However, time, which mellows
the tone of old Instruments, has probably also given their
wood its Inimitable patina.
Strings are quite, or almost, as delicate a matter.
Those used by the Italian craftsmen were produced in
the central and southern parts of the peninsula, especially
in Naples; the gut was derived from the intestines of
seven or eight-month-old lambs. This gut was left to
soak for a long time In alkallnized water before being
dried and twisted. It was believed that the exposure
of the pasture-lands, the season at which the lambs
were slaughtered and the kind of water used influenced
the quality of the strings and especially their resistance.
In fact, that resistance ls extraordinary, considering
that the four violin strings are subjected to a total
tension of over 50 pounds. 	
Thus we see what subtle alchemy of plant and animal
matter and what intuitive, meticulous craftsmanship
are needed in order that wood, gut and horsehair may be
transformed into that great, enchanting voice, with Its
infinite modulations, which by another miracle of human
genius, can be heard today in every home.
The first stringed instrument was a gift of nature, a
tortoise-shell converted into a sounding-box by a few
strings stretched across It. That ls why the lyre retained
the name of chelys In Greek and testudo In Latin. And
according to classical tradition, the first stringed-ins¬
trument maker was Orpheus, who replaced the Unen
threads of the lyre with strings made from the Intestines
of animals.
Stringed Instruments are found among primitive
peoples: the Negro viol of Nyasaland has a bow made
of two strips of willow, one straight and the other curved.
But musicologists generally agree that the earliest
ancestor of the violin ls the ravanastron, which has all
the same features: resonant box, neck, bridge, pegs,
strings made of gazelles' Intestines and bow. This Ins¬
trument ls said to have been Invented over five thousand
years ago by Ravana, king of Ceylon, a ten-headed giant.
It ls still sometimes seen In India, In the hands of certain
mendicant Buddhist monks.
The story goes that the ravanastron, transported from
India to Persia and thence to Arabia, became the Arabian
rebab, which, in Europe, engendered the rebec, a small,
three-stringed bowed Instrument played by the ministréis.
On the other hand, Breton bards before the Moorish
Invasion used a bowed Instrument called the crwth,
which was an Improved version of the rebab. Was the
latter Imported Into the East by the Crusaders? Or did
they bring It back from Palestine? Or else, as ethno-
musicology would seem to testify, did the various forms
of bowed stringed Instruments make their appearance
as Independent Inventions In different countries?
At all events, by the beginning of the Renaissance in
Europe, there were two groups of stringed Instruments:
vielles, which, alter being used to accompany troubadour
songs, evolved Into organistrums, or large hurdy-gurdies,
worked by a handle and employed for dance music or for
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
THE VIOLIN CURIOSITY SHOP
Viol with five strings
copied from an ins¬
trument In a paint¬
ing by Cimabue,
the 13th century
Florentine artist.
Photos © Arthaud.
Viol with three
strings reconstitut¬
ed according to a
13th century sculp¬
tured figure in
Chartres Cathedral.
Violin marked with the mono¬
gram of Antonio Stradivari
Stradivarius in Latin -»the most
celebrated of the great violin-
makers of Cremona (1644-1736).
Photo © Goursat.
The names of the different kinds of viols are as musical as
the sounds they make: viola d'amore (love viol), viola di
gamba (placed between the knees for playing), vloletta
marina (for which Handel wrote pieces), viola di bordone,
viola pomposa (said to have been invented by Bach; his VI
suite for violoncello was actually written for the viola pom¬
posa) and viola bastarda which at first had 6 or 7 strings
and later, fitted with 14 strings, became the "English violet".
Almost all the great violin concertos (for example, those of
Mozart, Beethoven, Paganini, Brahms, Tchaikovsky, Lalo,
etc) are written in D.
One of the most strange-looking of all musical instruments
was the tromba marina (marine trumpet) which was very
popular in Germany from the 14th to the 17th centuries.
It has been suggested that one part of its name came from
the use made of it for signalling in the British Navy.
Tho octobassc, an
immenso strlnped
double-bass, 10 feet
high Invented by tho
19th century French
Instrument maker,
Jean - B. Vuillaume.
THE INCREASING USE OF STRINGS IN THE ORCHESTRA
HAYDN BEETHOVEN WAGNER STRAVINSKY
(as used in his 78th
Symphony)
4 Basses.
4 Cellos.
4 Violas.
8 First Violins.
6 Second Violins.
(as used in the 5th
Symphony)
8 Basses.
8 Cellos.
10 Violas.
1 4 First Violins.
1 2 Second Violins.
(as used in "Parsifal")
10 Basses.
1 2 Cellos.
1 2 Violas.
18 First Violins.
1 8 Second Violins.
(as used in the "Rite
of Spring")
10 Basses.
12 Cellos.
13 Violas.
18 First Violins.
1 8 Second Violins.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
MUSIC ON A STRING (Cont'd)
Masterpieces from
a prison cell
the entertainment of drinking parties; and the nobler
family of the viols, bowed instruments which may or may
not have been derived from the vielle. The gradual
modification of early viols doubtless produced the violin,
the most important of modern stringed instruments. '
The first violins are generally attributed to Gasparo
da Salo, who, together with Maggini, founded the famous
school of Brescia in Lombardy. Yet a few years before
Salo's birth in 1533, Francis I of France was already
travelling with eight violin players in his train. There
was probably an uncertain period during which various
modifications of the viol were called violins, although
the proportions of the violin had not yet been established.
Such hesitation is evidenced by the fact that the French
word violon means "large viol", whilst the Italian violino
means a small-sized viol.
The Brescia school later seemed primitive in comparison
with that of Cremona, founded in the seventeenth
century by the Amatl dynasty, the most famous member
of which, Nicola, lived to be eighty-eight (1596-1684)
and was the master of Stradivarius. His small violins,
with their strong voice and brilliant, transparent varnish,
were already masterpieces.
Astrange legend surrounds Giuseppe Guarnieri
(1683-1745), known as "del Gesù", because,
in order to distinguish himself from the other violin-
makers of the family, he adopted a label on which his
name was followed by the three letters I.H.S. (Iesus
Homlnum Salvator) surmounted by a cross. His violins
have acquired such a reputation that a "del Gesù" has
become a common expression. It was, for instance, on a
"del Gesù", which he donated to his native city of
Genoa, that Paganini played.
The story is that, despite his pious nickname, Guarnieri,
who only began his career as a violin-maker at the age of
thirty-eight, produced his best instruments while in
prison. Some of them are called "prison violins" or
"the servant-girl's violins", in memory of the goaler's
daughter who is supposed to have supplied him with the
material he required.
The greatest and best-known of the violin-makers of
Cremona was Stradivari Stradivarius in Latin whose
name has become synonymous with the finest and most
valuable violins. He lived to be ninety-three and had
two wives and fourteen children, only two of whom took
up the craft. Starting as a pupil of Nicola Amati, he began
to sign his instruments, using his own label from 1670
onwards, and had very soon surpassed his master.
After this first thirty-year period, known as the
"Amitized" period because of the influence of Amati's
models, he developed his own style through passionately
keen and unremitting labour; and It was to remain
unrivalled. He designed his model with sober grandeur,
the height of the vaulting was reduced, the volume of
air in resonating bodies methodically refined, the thick¬
nesses accurately calculated and the exact intonation of
the woods ascertained. The Magginls had a veiled, mel¬
ancholy voice, the Amatis a soft, silvery one; but Stra¬
divarius was the first to be able to combine strength
and sweetness, vigour and tenderness.
The Cremona master chose his woods with the greatest
care and tried to use the same piece for the back and
the ribs. His backs were often in one piece. He rounded
off angles lovingly and decorated them with faultless
profiling. His angles were cut In an elegant manner
all his own; the paraph of the sound-holes was exquisitely
fine. His varnishes were Incomparable, thoroughly
resistant, sometimes amber-coloured, sometimes tending
towards a russet shade called rossino, and always highly
transparent.
The whole of Stradivari's long life (1644-1737) was
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Goursat
For almost three centur¬
ies, French violin makers
have been carrying on
the great traditions they
inherited from the crafts¬
men of Italy. In the small
town of Mirecourt, on
the borders of Lorraine,
veteran violin makers
like this one examining
a finished instrument
(above) still hand on the
secrets of their craft to
new generations. Left,
a violin back is prepared
and (below left) finished
parts are fitted together.
The work of making and
assembling well over 80
parts for each violin Is
done entirely by hand.
When meticulous skill
and loving care have
done their utmost, the
result is an Instrument
worthy of concert artists
like the Czech violinist,
Alexander Plocek (right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
MUSIC ON A STRING (Cont'd)
Stradivarius inspires
French violin village
devoted not only to making instruments violins, viols,
violoncellos, double basses, lutes and pocket-violins but
also to research and experiment. Those who knew him
have described his tall, lean, figure. He always wore a
white cap a woollen one In winter and a cotton one in
summer. While working, he wore a white leather apron
and, we are told, "since he was always working, his
costume hardly varied". Corelli may have given him
advice for the perfecting of a violin ;but no virtuoso could
advise him about the violoncello, then considered as an
instrument of secondary importance, and yet his 'cellos
are the best ever made.
Artists such as Boccherini, Tartini, Kreutzer, Kramer,
Lafont, Rode, Pugnani and Sarasate made the sound
of Stradlvarlous violins famous. Some of these, the
"Rode", the "Messiah", the "Dolphin" and the "Dawn"
are considered to be the Cremona craftsman's master¬
pieces. Henceforth, the power and range of stringed
instruments made it possible for them to leave the
drawing-rooms of the aristocracy and reach an in¬
creasingly wide public In theatres and big concert halls.
Although Stradivarius was to give the violin its final
form and style, the instrument had already been known
and even popular In France, England and Flanders since
the middle of the Sixteenth century. Violin-makers
worked In those countries; in Paris, they fashioned the
instruments under the supervision of musicians and were
sometimes classified with braziers. The following century
witnessed the appearance in France of great violin-
makers, such as Nicolas Lupot, who made a very careful
study of the Stradivarius proportions, and Médard, who
set up his workshop at Nancy.
A GROWING THREAT to wild creatures, including
seals, penguins and graceful seabirds like those above on
the South American coast, is widespread oil pollution.
The International Conference on the Prevention of
Pollution of the Sea, convened, by the Inter-
Governmental Maritime Consultative Organization
(I M CO), ended on April 13, 1962, with the signing of
the Final Act of the Conference by representatives
of 40 nations. These countries represent over two-
thirds of the world's shipping tonnage and well
over half the oil tanker tonnage. A number of other
countries sent observers to the Conference.
POLLUTION is due chiefly to tankers washing out stor¬
age tanks before taking on a new load or through ordinary
cargo ships replacing the fuel they burn by water ballast,
and later discharging this contaminated water. Below,
petrol tankers take on oil at Kuwait on the Persian Gulf.
T;Hus France inherited from Cremona. Paris
violin-makers are all grouped in the "Euro¬
pe" quarter, but it ls, above all, the small town of Mire¬
court, on the borders of Lorraine, which has long
specialized in the art of stringed-Instrument making. The
first historical document concerning Mirecourt violin-
making dates from 1637 and ls a contract binding an ap¬
prentice to his master. For over three centuries, therefore,
the people of Mirecourt have been teaching or learning
how to cut, adjust, assemble and varnish stringed-instru¬
ments with the famous "Italian sonority".
There Is a historical explanation of this tradition.
When the Dukes of Lorraine, great patrons of the acts,
went to stay in their castle at Ravenel a few walls of
which are still standing they brought with them their
musicians and, in particular, their violin-maker, named
Tywersus, who had worked in Cremona. Tywersus taught
the craft to a few inhabitants of the village near the
castle, and they transmitted their knowledge to their
descendants.
In 1732, the violin-makers of Mirecourt received their
charters as a corporation from Francis II, Duke of Lor¬
raine. Today, workshops of instrument makers survive
at Mirecourt alongside modern industry; the work is
done by hand, skilfully and lovingly, and with respect
for Renaissance traditions.
There are other centres of the art in Austria, the
Netherlands and Italy, where high quality violin-making
is by no means dead, as well as in other European
countries. But heavy competition comes from mass-
produced work; the instrument market is quickly satur¬
ated, and apprenticeship is long and difficult at a time
when young people are faced with openings in less
exacting and more lucrative trades.
Will the master violin-maker of today find disciples
to whom they can bequeath their knowledge? It is to be
hoped so, for the perfection of these resonating bodies
is one of music's secret weapons, and Instrumental
music henceforth accessible everywhere, a joy and
10 comfort to all, as well as a common language has an
even greater and more vital part to play in modern times
than in the past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
DANGER !
OIL-POLLUTED
9 EL tf\ 9 by David Woodward
Antonio Quintana, Chile
On the shores of the seven seas, from the
Antarctic to Florida and all along the West
coast of Europe, the pollution of the sea by oil fuel
has for years been an unmitigated nuisance to all
those who look to the seashore for their pleasure or
for their livelihood.
Oil, washed up on the beaches, and left behind by the
receding tide, is at the least unpleasant. It spoils the
enjoyment of swimmers and holiday makers, ruining
their clothes and their shoes. If these conditions prevail
over any length of coastline, the dispirited holiday maker
can pack up and go home, or if he is lucky during the
holiday season find somewhere else to go; but thousands
of people whose livelihood is provided by the seaside,
suffer a loss of trade as well as damage to the carpets
and furnishings of their hotels or lodging houses.
Inshore fishermen suffer, for It ls Impossible to wash
fish covered with oil. Lobsters do not breed. And even
the most thoughtless must deplore the plight of sea birds
whose feathers have become coated with oil and have
thus been deprived of their power to swim or to fly.
Unless they receive highly skilled help, such birds arc
doomed to a miserable end by starvation. As an Indica¬
tion, it is calculated some quarter of a million sea birds
perish In this manner every year around the coasts of
Great Britain alone.
CONT'D ON NEXT PACE
Ci Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
POLLUTED SEAS (ü»>W
Messages in plastic bottles
dropped by the thousand in the
In the Antarctic the plight of seals and penguins
covered with oil has touched the hearts of even the
tough whaling men. Dr. Harry R. Lillie, a former surgeon
to an Antarctic whaling fleet, said in a newspaper
interview:
"I have found half-grown seals covered In a sticky tarry
mess, their eyes bloodshot with irritation; and penguins
hopelessly clogged, waiting for a slow death."
Dr. Lillie added that he had spent a lot of time cleaning
up the birds on board the factory ship:
"I must say with respect to the whaling crews, they
were generally little concerned with the .suffering of
harpooned whales, but I never found any of the men
around me who ever felt that our butter supply was too
good to be used to clean up oiled penguins."
The fact that pollution has become a major problem is
due to the enormous growth of oil fuel used throughout
the worlda fifty-fold increase in the last 40 years, and
almost all this oil is carried about the world in tankers.
S ir Gilmour Jenkins, President of the IMCO
Conference which met in April, told the
meeting:
"Last year 500 million tons of oil were carried across
the seas and ooeans of the world. If we assume that only
a very small proportion, say one part in a thousand, of
this vast amount found its way into the sea in the form
of persistent waste, we get the terrifying total of half a
million tons."
This oil, for the most part, is the sludge left behind in
the tanks of the ships after they have discharged their
cargo. The tanks are washed out by sprays of hot water
and pumped into the sea. And there it floats. Man has
always used the sea as a vast cesspit, for such various
commodities as sewage, unwanted high explosives and
atomic waste. But the oily waste is persistent and may
well stay in the sea for ever.
A secondary source of this oil is the practice of oil-
fuelled merchant ships replacing the fuel which they
burn during a voyage by water ballast. Later, the water
ballast, now contaminated by oil, is pumped out, and
another addition is made to the pollution of the high seas.
To deal with the whole problem two approaches are
being tried. One is to limit the areas of the sea in which
oily waste may be pumped overboard. The other is the
use of machinery on board ship, known as separators,
which remove the oil from the waste water or the provi¬
sion at ports of plant to receive the tank washings. These
are both fairly expensive proceedings. A separator also
may cost between £500 and £1,000 ($1,400 and $2,800).
At one large port for oil tankers, the plant to receive tank
washings has cost some £300,000 ($784,000). At the same
time, the period spent in getting rid of the washings must
be cut to an absolute minimum. Every day's delay to a
big tanker can easily cost as much as $1,000.
Athird source of oil on the sea, happily much
rarer, is through accidents, when a ship is lost
and her oil tanks perforated, or when the oil fuel must be
jettisoned to free the ship from a position of danger. As
one example of the damage that may be caused under
such circumstances, there is the case of a tanker which
ran aground at the mouth of the river Elbe, and lightened
herself by pumping overboard 6,000 tons of oil. An
enormous floating island of oil was thus released, which
slowly drifted about the North Sea. Oil islands like this
usually last for some 50 miles before they break up and
patches float away, but the record is held by an oil island
which appeared in the Red Sea and covered a distance
of 500 miles before it began to dissipate.
As for the oil island from the Elbe, some of it came
ashore on the island of Sylt, where the authorities spent
vast sums of money to get rid of it. A little further to
the north, six miles of beach on the island of Fanoe, off
Esbjerg, were covered with oil. The Danes tried spraying
it with sawdust and then attacking it with flame throwers,
but the oil survived, and the sand that it had contaminat¬
ed had to be bulldozed into open trenches.
Another example of the difficulty of getting rid of the
oil was provided by a tanker which was in collision in the
Solent, off Portsmouth, in England, a couple of years ago.
Two months later the authorities of that town were still
trying to clean up the mess. An enormous tonnage of
oily shingle had to be taken away and four thousand tons
of clean shingle brought in to take its place.
Among recent experiments made to get rid of oil which
has accumulated in this way has been a Danish attempt
Photo Rank Organization
12
OIL-FOULED BEACHES are a major headache for swimmers, holiday makers and local authorities.
Freeing them of the slimy, black oil that sometimes comes ashore is a major operation. Below left, clean¬
ing up an oil-polluted beach at Portsmouth, England. At Rampen, Germany (below right) an oil "island"
that drifted in with the tide had to be ploughed into the sand to a depth of three feet before it was clear.
I Dr. H. Ecke
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
i RS PCA OIL CAKED SEABIRD Is one of countless thousands that each year pay the penalty of years of
unchecked oil-dumping at sea. They are tossed up In flocks of thousands (a quarter of a million are
believed to perish around the coasts of Great Britain each year) feathers too matted by oil to fly.
to impregnate the oil with a powder which would cause
it to sink. Some fully effective remedy of this sort may
eventually be devised, but it will always be expensive;
the logical way of dealing with most of the oil In the sea
is to prevent its deliberate discharge and to encourage the
wider use of facilities ashore. This, in fact, was what the
IMCO Conference did.
The world's conscience had already been aroused
by the oil pollution problem before 1962. An Inter¬
national Convention on Pollution of the Sea by
Oil was drawn up at a conference held In London
during 1954 and was later ratified by 17 nations, Including
many of the largest shlpowning countries. Scientific
investigation was undertaken and, in some cases, was
followed by legislative action.
To start with, it was necessary to plot the ocean
currents which carry the oil. For that purpose, aircraft
dropped thousands of plastic envelopes Into the sea.
Inside each envelope was a message inviting the finder to
say where the envelope had been found. And a piece of
cork which made certain that the envelope floated. Two
vessels of the International force of weather ships dropped
an envelope overboard every day of the year 1954 at noon.
The results of all this research were plotted by the
British National Institute of Oceanography.
S OME governments also took legislative action.
'For example, the United Kingdom Introduced
the Oil in Navigable Waters Act which forbade British
ships to discharge oil within 50 miles of the coast. But
national measures could not be successful by themselves ;
it was clearly necessary to persuade all nations owning
large merchant fleets to adopt the same kind of measures.
This was the background to the IMCO Conference of 1962
where a number of resolutions were unanimously adopted
which aim at increasing the effectiveness of the earlier
measures and at strengthening them through a new Con¬
vention. Many delegates emphasized the Importance of
mineral oils to man, but deplored his casual approach to
the fouling of seas or shores and the destruction of birds
and marine Ufe.
The new Convention has considerably increased the
areas of the sea In which it ls forbidden to discharge oil.
Formerly fixed as any area less than 50 miles from the
coast, this zone has now been increased in many parts
of the world.
Discharge is now completely forbidden in the North Sea
and the Baltic; the 50-mlle limit has been superseded by a
limit of 100 miles off the North-Eastern coast of North
America, the Mediterranean, the Red Sea and the Persian
Gulf as well as the west coast of Canada, the Atlantic
coast of Spain, the coast of Portugal, the Arabian Sea,
the Bay of Bengal and Australian waters.
Three years after the ratification of the agreement by
the Soviet Union and Rumania, the Black Sea and the
Sea of Azov will become a zone in which discharge of
oil ls completely forbidden. These arrangements are
probably rather more than a halfway house to an eventual
ban on the discharge of oil anywhere at sea.
Clearly the seas of the world will not become suddenly
cleaner as a result of the April Conference or the new
Convention. But« useful progress has been made. Much
will depend on the* oil companies which control a large
share of the world's tanker tonnage. And, as William
Graham, Acting Secretary-General of IMCO, said, "no
truly successful result can be achieved without the active
co-operation of those directly responsible for operations
on board ship and ashore which may cause oil pollution."
David Woodward is a documentary writer-producer for
the British Broadcasting Corporation, London.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE OCEAN
UNDER
A MICROSCOPE
by L. Howell-Rivero
T
I o
he sea is populated by myriads of microscopic
rganisms known as plankton. The vast major¬
ity of these marine biota are so small that if we were
to take a glass of sea water and look at it with the naked
eye, we should only see after close examination a series
of dots which might make the water appear muddy.
Viewing a sample under a strong magnifying glass, how¬
ever, we should see that these dots consist of living bodies.
Their composition is very varied; some of them are
unicellular plants (phytoplankton) , others are animals
(Zooplankton); they also include microscopic animals and
other marine animals in their larval state.
14
STRANGELY-SHAPED DIATOMS are a form of
phytoplankton from the ocean which have a shell of
pure silica crystals. How these tiny organisms extract
the silica from sea-water solutions is still a mystery.
ONE-EYED CYCLOPS is a minute animal of the
copepod family found in parts of the Baltic Sea. Cope-
pods are an important food for the sea's edible fish.
These organisms are clearly of very great importance,
since phytoplankton is at the origin of what is known
as the food chain; it derives its own nourishment from
the nutrient salts in the sea-water, uses sunlight as a
source of energy and in turn acts as food for Zooplankton
and other marine animals further up the scale. Thus,
the productivity of a given zone can be deduced from
the quantity of nutrient salts and plankton it contains.
There are many features of this microscopic world
which claim our attention and cause us to marvel at the
wisdom of Nature. Among the phytoplankton, for
instance, there is that group of microscopic algae, known
as diatoms, which have a shell of pure silica crystals with
varied and fantastic shapes. How do these tiny organisms
extract the silica from the different sea-water solutions
to make their shells?
In other microbiota, such as the foraminifera type of
Zooplankton the shell is calcareous like that of sea-shells;
here the question ls how can the soluble carbonate of
lime be made to create such insoluble shells ?
These are some of the mysteries to which Man must
find the answer if he is to take up Nature's challenge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
In spite oí their mysterious origin, these minute orga¬
nisms provide clues to the history of our planet since,
as their shells settled in the depths of the sea throughout
the ages, they became part of the radiolarlan, foraml-
niferous and other types of ooze layers.
If we recall the theories concerning the marine origin
of petroleum deposits, we shall see why the study of
foraminiféra in the different geological strata of our
planet is one of the basic means of determining the
possible location of "black gold".
Let us turn, however, to the great planktonic mass
formed by other marine animals In their larval state;
a vast and fascinating world lies before us when we
consider the changes and metamorphoses that some of
them undergo before they become the creatures we are
accustomed to see, such as oysters, sea-urchins, lobsters
and all kinds of fish.
Certain species of common oyster which, when full-
grown, are sedentary and are found attached to the roots
of coastal plants such as the mangrove, move about freely
when in their larval state until they find a suitable
place to cling and develop Into the commercial form which
can later be eaten by Man. During this short larval
period, they live of phytoplankton and move by means
of a crown of fronds, reminiscent of helicopter blades.
The larval state typical of certain sea molluscs which
scientists call "veliger larva" reveal a number of varied
and interesting structures. One of the most fascinating
subjects of zoological research ls that of the development
of these structures.
We have all seen sea-urchins and star-fish on beaches
or have felt their sharp spikes In our feet. They again,
Photos © L. J. Uporte, Paris
In their larval state, bear no resemblance to the fully-
grown species. In the case of star-fish, for instance, a
small bl-symmetrical organism is transformed on meta¬
morphosis into a creature with radial symmetry.
Even when its animal organisms can move of their own
free-will this does not prevent plankton from being
carried away by the great ocean currents, which thus
distribute the different marine species over wide areas.
A typical example ls provided by the marine lobster
in the Caribbean. The adult species ls found on the
coral sea-board of the whole area washed by the same
set of currents, which also ensure its distribution by
carrying the larva; away.
Here again, we encounter a great difference between
adult and larval forms. The larva; of lobsters look
like transparent spiders with long legs and no feelers.
At birth, each is about the size of a full-stop on this page.
As they grow, the features associated with the adult
lobster gradually begin to appear and the larval charac¬
teristics are lost. When they are hardly more than an
inch long, they select the coastal stretch where they will
turn into the lobsters that will subsequently be eaten.
There are many varieties of fish which undergo con¬
siderable transformations from the time they are born
until they become full-grown. We shall consider the two
most outstanding examples.
The first is the eel. This fish, which lives in European
and American rivers, migrates to the distant Sargasso 15
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE SEA has many tiny animals that glow in the dark and,
when very abundant, make the waters luminescent. Here
is Noctiluca scintillons, photographed by electronic flash.
ZOOPLANKTON of the forminifera type. From depo¬
sits of their calcareous shells in sediment geologists can
reconstruct the history of the waters in which they lived.
UNDER A MICROSCOPE (Cont'd)
The plaice with the roaming eye
16
Sea to spawn; its larvae then begin their return journey
to their respective continents during metamorphosis.
At first these transparent, planktonic organisms are very
minute, and when they reach the river mouths they are
scarcely two inches long; at this point they are sometimes
caught and sold as canned "fry". Scientific research has
established the relationship between the larvae and the
adult of this species, but there are many other species
which have yet to be investigated.
The other example worthy of note is that of the plaice
or sole. Everyone must have noticed that their eyes are
on the same side of their bodies. But they were not born
like that. As tiny creatures In their larval state, they
are bi-symmetrical and have the shape of a normal fish,
with one eye on each side of the head.
By one of Nature's quirks, one of their eyes moves
over to the other side, with the result that the head bones
become twisted; it is in this way that the peculiar features
of the fully-grown fish are produced. However, does one
eye in particular move from one side to the other? Here
again, Nature challenges us to discover the design behind
her apparent capriciousness. In some species, it is the
left eye which moves, in others it is the right eye, and
in yet others, this movement is unpredictable.
We can therefore see the enormous problem facing the
scientists who wish to learn about marine life; in order
to catch these mlcrobiota, they have to make use of such
special methods and techniques as plankton nets; after
the plankton has been caught, it has to be studied not
only for itself, but also for its possible long-term
practical value.
The reader may ask: What can plankton be used for?
Is there any special justification for the efforts made to
catch and study it? What benefits does it bring to Man?
Science is attempting to give a satisfactory answer to
these questions.
The relationship between nutrients and phytoplankton
is a guide to the economic potentialities of an area and
hence to areas where fish of commercial value may be
able to exist in abundance. In addition, there are species
of Zooplankton which reveal the presence of fish of
commercial value. Lastly, plankton itself provides food
for many different kinds of fish. This makes us wonder
whether Man himself could not use plankton for food.
Although it is reasonable to expect the time and effort
devoted to marine research to be justified by practical
applications, the research in itself is valuable in so far
as it reveals that Man is making an effort to learn more
about the natural phenomena surrounding him, their
causes and effects, and about the organisms living in a
given medium. Perhaps one of the most interesting and
least known of such fields ls that of microscopic sea-life.
Former professor of Ichthyology at the University of
Havana, Luis Howell-Rivero is now the Oceanography
specialist at the Unesco Latin American Science Cooper¬
ation Office, Montevideo, Uruguay.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The anatomy of underdevelopment (Part 2)
PATTERNS OF ECONOMIC CHANGE
All countries are in some respects underdeveloped for all are still in
the development process. But broad distinctions can nevertheless be
made between the different levels of development that have been ach-
ieved. These different characteristics are analyzed in the following arti¬
cle, the second of a series whose publication began in the July-August
issue of The Unesco Courier. They are taken from a new study produced
by the United Nations as part of the World Campaign Against Hunger.
Industrialization, or the opportunity for all to
partake of its benefits, is essential to economic
progress. It is not, however, an end in itself. Schools,
hospitals, museums, art galleries, theatres are built not
for their own sake, but to serve specific purposes, and fac¬
tories are no exception. They are indispensable tools in
the struggle to raise living standards among the less for¬
tunate of the world's people. This is a fundamental objec¬
tive of the United Nations and the sole purpose of
the technical assistance programmes.
Factories, mines, power stations, transport undertakings
and so on are symbols of the economic development by
which this raising of living standards can be achieved.
Economic development must go hand In hand with
the production of more food, the improvement of
health, the spread of education and the promotion
of social welfare and human rights. It will help
to put more money into the pockets of the people who
need it. Without that increase in spending power, the
people In the "underdeveloped" countries cannot know
freedom from misery and want.
The most striking difference between the developed
and the underdeveloped countries lies, as we have seen,
in the standard of living attained by the majority of
their people In other words, In the extent to which
the national income is distributed through wide strata
of the population. It is, however, possible to attempt
some more exact definition of the term underdeveloped.
An underdeveloped country might be described as one
in which the natural and human resources arc used for
economic purposes to only a very limited degree. The
trained personnel, the capital and the administrative
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
World Bank
Economic growth, symbolized by Industrialization, leads to greater employment and Increased
Incomes for workers. The foundations for progress of this kind In the world's less-developed
countries have often been laid thanks to international aid. The World Bank (International Bank
for Reconstruction and Development) for instance, has already awarded development loans totalling
5,000 million dollars, Including nearly 800 million dollars for different countries In Africa.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
UNDERDEVELOPMENT (Coned)
Innovations that changed history's course
machinery necessary to make proper use of them are
partly, of wholly lacking. Such a definition is no more
than rough and ready. The word "resource" Itself needs
clarification. We might say that, in the economic sense,
a resource only becomes a resource when it can be put
to an appropriate use. Until that time, the richest
resources are valueless in themselves.
If we look back over the long history of mankind, we
see a period, perhaps lasting up to half a million years
or more, during which the food gatherers and hunters of
the Palaeolithic, or Old Stone Age, wandered countless
times across what was later to be recognized as rich
arable land without being able to make the slightest use
of it. It was probably not more than ten thousand
years ago that the first Neolithic farmers, by sowing
and harvesting grain, discovered the possibilities inherent
in such land. Thanks to this innovation, they took
to living in settled communities and so changed the
course of human history.
We can find plenty of examples nearer our own time,
In fact, the more complex civilization has become, the
more intense has been the search for new resources or
new uses for old resources. Coal was occasionally used
in the Middle Ages, but its real value as a natural
resource was discovered only when the factories of the
industrial revolution created a demand for fuel which
could not be met by the diminishing woodlands of late
eighteenth and early nineteenth-century England.
At a further stage in the industrial revolution,
oil began to taJke the place of coal as a fuel
and the vast deposits lying under the Middle East,
Central America, Texas, the Caspian Sea area and
elsewhere acquired immense economic importance for the
industrialized civilization of the twentieth century.
During the last few years, several countries have discov¬
ered that their deposits of uranium have tremendous
value. Only a generation ago, little attention would
have been paid to them. Because resources become
resources only when a use Is found for them, it follows
that new discoveries may at any moment reveal value in
hitherto neglected materials or new uses for resources
already being exploited. Even the most highly developed
countries may therefore possess natural resources which
still contribute nothing to their economic life.
As long as this is the case and as long as those coun¬
tries continue the search to improve their techniques
and to use the sum total of their natural and human
resources to better purpose, even advanced countries
are still in the process of development, or are technically
underdeveloped. Moreover, as the easily accessible
supply of certain minerals begins to fail under the heavy
demands of industry, new sources are constantly being
turned to account by technological research. An exam¬
ple would be the extraction of magnesium from the sea,
now a considerable Industry in the United States.
It looks as if two great steps forward will be taken
shortly when automation and atomic energy begin to
play a leading part in industrial life. Automation, which
is merely an extension of the use of machines to replace
workers and of electronic equipment to replace brains, is
beginning to revolutionize industrial prospects. Perhaps,
when the economically advanced countries of today look
back, fifty years hence, from the early atomic-automation
era, they will regard their present condition as having
18 been very "underdeveloped" indeed.
Bearing these facts in mind, we can still list certain
characteristic features which distinguish the countries
that have not yet set out upon the road of economic
progress or have advanced only a little way along it.
Generally speaking, most of the people living In such
countries get their livelihood from agriculture of a pri¬
mitive kind, which yields them only a bare subsistence
and little or no surplus for exchange purposes.
Industries tend to be few and their level of output
per worker is very low, as a result of the low level of
capital per worker. Transportation facilities are gene¬
rally inadequate. Such countries tend to have widespread
underemployment, illiteracy, poor housing, low nutri¬
tion and health standards and an acute shortage both
of educated people and of teachers.
It is broadly true that the economically un¬
derdeveloped countries mostly lie in the hotter
regions of the earth's surface. Many of them have
experienced colonial status, the traces of which have
often been left on the national economy. In many of
the less developed countries, an industry extracting one
specific local raw material or product has long had a
preponderating place. This may be a mineral or a vege¬
table product such as rubber, coffee or cocoa. Fluctua¬
tions in the price of such commodities on the world
market tend to make the economic life of the country
concerned unstable, and this economic instability is
another characteristic shared by many of the underde¬
veloped countries.
It would be difficult to say how many of the world's
Inhabitants live in the underdeveloped areas, because
we have seen that there is no precise definition of the
term underdeveloped. It is obvious, however, that much
of Asia, Latin America, Africa and the Middle East would
be covered by any normal use of the term "economically
underdeveloped area." These regions comprise between
them some 75 per cent of the world's population.
As only a small fraction of their inhabitants enjoy a
standard of living which could be described as high or
even adequate, and, as some people even in the more
developed areas are living on the subsistence level, prob¬
ably three-quarters of the world's men and women are
at present condemned to a Ufe of grim poverty and often
of bitter hardship.
Economic development is the means by which those
material hardships can be reduced and by which poverty
can be attacked at its root.
T hree stages in the process of economic dev¬
elopment have been distinguished. At first,
communities are primarily agricultural and mostly self-
supporting. Next, a network of commercial and exchange
activities is developed. Then follows the Introduction of
manufacturing industry.
The beginnings of exchange in an agricultural society
usually concern a surplus of local products, such as salt
or fish. When markets begin to take shape, commo¬
dities specially produced for sale acquire increasing
Importance. As money becomes more generally used,
there ls greater specialization both in producing and in
selling goods.
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The construction of highways and railroads is opening up the road to economic development In many countries, making possible 19
increased trade and the export of raw materials. These sections of railroad line are for a new section of railway being constructed
in the Republic of Congo which will transport manganese ore mined in the neighbouring Republic of Gabon to the African coast.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
UNDERDEVELOPMENT (Cont'd)
HELICOPTERS
LINK JUNGLE
BUILDING SITES
Near Bacoumba in the Republic of Gabon,
helicopters help to construct an aerial
cableway, 45 miles long, which will carry
manganese ore to a new 180 mile railroad
link. Men, equipment and cement are flown
(left and right) over the dense forest to the
almost inaccessible pylon sites. Far right
and below, iron girders are flown to a jun¬
gle clearing in which pylons will soon rise.
The slow emergence of industries
This type of society remains more or less self-contained,
but it includes the elements of an exchange of com¬
mercial economy, the promise of bigger things to come.
It ls typical of much of contemporary Africa and also of
parts of Latin America and Southeast Asia.
By organizing a system of trade, such societies take
the first step leading from the subsistence agriculture
stage to that of industry. There is, however, no ela¬
borate transformation of materials, no use of complex
machines and no employment of specialized wage earners
in a common place of work. Nevertheless, the emergence
of better transportation and the Increasing sale of goods
open the way to further specialization.
At first individuals, then organized groups,
devote themselves entirely to secondary occu¬
pations away from the land, such as the transformation,
preparation or carrying of raw materials. This early
commercial stage with its simple industries grows out
of the subsistence agriculture phase. Later, and general¬
ly much later, comes the stage of more complex
manufacturing industry, with the use of machines on an
ever-increasing scale, an increasing specialization of
many workers and the creation of more and more elabo¬
rate administrative and financial techniques to keep pace
with heavier economic demands.
Industry first appears with the processing of primary
products. Grain is milled, leather is tanned, wool or
vegetable fibres are spun, ores are smelted. These pro¬
cesses obviously call for the next level of industrial
development, when materials are transformed and not
merely processed. The grain so milled is turned into
bread, the leather into footwear, the cloth into wearing
apparel, the smelted ores into ploughshares, horseshoes
and other metal goods.
20 At this stage, goods are still produced for immediate
use by the person who buys them. The major differ¬
ence between this phase and the next, more complex,
stage of large-scale industry is that capital equipment
now begins to be produced not to satisfy immediate
consumer demand, but to help in the future production
of such goods over a long period of time and with far
more elaborate marketing facilities in mind.
Civilizations do not pass through these phases in
clearly defined historical periods. Human history is an
untidy phenomenon. It allows for much disorder and for
the existence side by side of processes of varying age and
efficiency. The so-called Industrial civilization of our
time is distinguished by a tremendous emphasis on the
third, or machine-dominated stage.
The railroad, the steamship, the Internal-combustion
engine, flight, atomic power, electronics, all of them
Western discoveries or inventions, have vastly broadened
the horizon of man's possibilities. Their advantages are
now becoming available by degree to countries which
have never experienced the preliminary stages of indus¬
trial progress.
As a result, our contemporary world presents the pic¬
ture of an economically advanced minority of peoples
on the one hand and, on the other, a highly diversified
group of peoples who make up the majority of mankind
and who, at varying stages of economic underdevelop¬
ment, are seeking to narrow the broad gap which separ¬
ates them from the economic leaders. It may be
possible perhaps to distinguish various categories among
these underdeveloped countries and the distinction will
help to make clearer both their economic problems and
their potentialities.
(a) First there are societies in which there has as yet
been practically no autonomous economic growth. Most
of the people wrest a meagre livelihood from the soil as
subsistence farmers. A very elementary marketing
system exists, but the exchange of products is on too small
a scale to allow any real division of labour into different
skills and crafts, and thus the incentive to progress is
lacking.
Great areas of Africa would be typical of this phase of
CONT'D ON PAGE 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
22
UNDERDEVELOPMENT (Contd)
The increasing importance
of government intervention
economic development, as would a territory like New
Guinea, hardly affected as yet by outside civilization. In
such regions, the people themselves lack all the essential
means to promote their economic growth. They must
be helped to modify the pattern of subsistence agriculture.
A more complex exchange system must be introduced . to
promote buying and selling and the manufacture or
preparation of products.
In these simply constituted economic societies (personal
and tribal relationships, like the indigenous languages,
are often far more complex than any In the "civilized"
world) this will always require both technical assistance
and capital from outside to get the static economy moving.
(b) The second category is more common In the
contemporary world. Here, we are dealing with under¬
developed countries where foreign enterprise, capital and
management, have Introduced themselves Into a rela¬
tively simple economic society and have caused a rapid
evolution in certain sectors. This situation Is to be seen
In a number of ex-colonlal countries such as Indonesia
and Malaya.
Here, valuable raw materials like rubber and tin have
been exploited through foreign technical skill and capi¬
tal. As a result, a few highly developed industries have
been set up to obtain and export such raw materials.
The coming of these industries has introduced, in part
at least, a commercial economy into the country
concerned. This has brought with It an elaborate
exchange mechanism and has provided commercial em¬
ployment for some of the local population.
Meanwhile, the primitive agricultural economy
goes on as before over the country as a whole.
The scale and complexity of local industries which may
arise to process raw materials on the spot will vary ac¬
cording to the nature of the product removed and
exported with foreign help. If this is a mineral, the local
processing plant is likely to be more complicated than in
the case of a vegetable product like sisal, for example,
which is grown and processed in Tanganyika. Much more
complex are the copper refineries in Katanga and Nor¬
thern Rhodesia and the oil refineries of the Middle East.
(c) A third category of countries differs from the rest
mainly as a result of Internal, rather than external, eco¬
nomic factors. How far will domestic demand encourage
industrial enterprise? We have seen above how the par¬
tial economic development of an underdeveloped country
may be stimulated by demand from abroad for a parti¬
cular raw material or product. Where this foreign
demand is absent, economic growth will occur only when
a local demand for goods exists.
This demand, in turn, will depend upon the way in
which income is distributed among the people and the
tastes of potential customers. If only small numbers of
the population can afford to buy consumer goods, they
may prefer imported articles. Local manufacturers will
then receive little encouragement to enter the field and
there will be as little impulse to extend the industria¬
lization process. A number of Latin American countries
are in this situation.
At this point a word must be said about the important
factor of government intervention. Government inter¬
vention has tended to increase markedly in our time. It is
World Bank
LACK OF TRUCKS in Iran encourages dangerous
overloading which, in turn, causes road surfaces
to break up and turn to powder. Iran's plan of
economic development now includes the reconstruc¬
tion and widening of existing highways and the
construction of some 1,500 miles of new highways.
particularly noticeable in countries which have recently
gained their political independence and which And them¬
selves faced with the great task of raising the living
standards of their people with a minimum of delay.
This task requires some degree of central direction.
Essential data about natural resources, both natural and
human, have to be centrally collected and assessed.
Plans must be centrally drawn up for the development of
these resources, as part of an overall national programme
of economic and social development. Priorities must be
centrally established, official encouragement must be given
to projects and industries which are likely to promote
the welfare of the people as a whole, and technical assis¬
tance and foreign loans must be applied for through
recognized government channels.
This government intervention ranges from encoura¬
gement and advice, as seen, for example, in community
development projects sponsored by the authorities in
India and elsewhere, to actual direction by the state in
the U.S.S.R., the countries associated with her and in the
mainland of China. The methods applied to achieve
economic development will reflect the prevailing idelology.
But it should be borne in mind that the conditions favour¬
ing spontaneous economic growth are present only in a
small measure in the underdeveloped countries and,
without some degree of government action, no substantial
progress could be expected In the foreseeable future.
(To be continued)
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
GERHART HAUPTMANN
DRAMATIST OF
THE OPPRESSED
by Karl Ruhrberg
GERHART Hauptmann, the German poet and
playwright, was born a hundred years ago. on
November 15, 1802, at Salzbrunn, in Silesia. He died on
June 6, 1946, at ten minutes past three in the afternoon,
in his house at Agnetcndorf (Rlesengcblrgc). The conci¬
liatory attitude shown by the occupying troops to the most
representative dramatist of the defeated country, Imme¬
diately after the war when suspicion, bitterness and
hatred were the order of the day bore consoling witness
to the Indestructible power of the spirit and to the
strength of the love that breathes through every page
and line of Hauptmann's work.
Hauptmann's writings found a response throughout the
world, partly because he vigorously championed the rights
of oppressed peoples. Travelling in Italy at the age of
twenty, he had been profoundly shocked to discover the
wretched condition of the poorer classes, particularly In
Naples. He never forgot his experience, and It was
reflected In his plays, where he gave expression to his
sympathy for the poor and for underdogs In general.
Alfred Kerr, the dramatic critic, who devoted a lifetime
to commenting on Hauptmann's development and ex¬
plaining his Intentions, declared that the basic sentiment
In his writings was longinglonging for a better world,
where all men would be brothers, all class and racial
prejudices forgotten.
That ls the Impression left by his descriptions of misery,
destitution and fear. This was what made him a great
writer. All acsthetlcal considerations and discussions as
to the strictly literary merits of his enormous output
(even the first section of which, omitting fragments,
variants and preliminary drafts fills 17 volumes) are over¬
shadowed by it.
I
) AFP. Paris Gerhart Hauptmann in the grounds of his home at
Agnetendorf, in the Riesengebirge mountains of Silesia.
n March, 1945, Hauptmann, then 82 years, of
. age, returned from Dresden to his house at
Agnetendorf. His Journey coincided with the Allied air¬
raids that reduced the former capital of Saxony to a heap
of rubble, two months before the end of the Second World
War. The advocate of compassion and love among men,
the poet who stood for a secularized Christianity, focused
on the things of this world, was profoundly afflicted by all
the suffering he had been forced to witness. "Anyone
who had lost the power to weep would recover it amid the
ruins of Dresden," he declared, only a few weeks before
Germany's final defeat.
He was deeply distressed by the horrors he had seen, but
his grief was passive and resigned. He made no attempt
to stir up resistance to the powers of darkness that had
brought disaster on the world. "I am nearly 83 years
old" he said, "and I come before God with a prayer
which has no power In It, alas, but It comes from the
heartthe prayer that God may show greater love to men
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
GERHART HAUPTMANN (Cont'd)
Last German 'Prince of Poets'
than hitherto, that he may transform them and enlighten
them for their own salvation."
This submissive attitude was not due merely to
Hauptmann's great age, it was part of his nature. He
was a Socialist, but not a militant one, he believed that
nothing could change the course of destiny. He was no
utoplan reformer, he had no taste for moralizing or
polemics. His plays depicted the grim world of the poor,
the outcast, the oppressed and rejected; but they also
showed that there could be beauty even in ugliness, nobi¬
lity even in cramped and petty circumstances and that
even the most despised members of the community had a
destiny to fulfil. He made no demands, however; his
attitude was one of hope and despite his pessimism of
confidence.
He did not aspire to be a stormer of barricades, and
this helps to explain his reserved attitude while Hitler
was in power, for which he was much criticized. In
spirit he was strongly opposed to National Socialism and
to the brutality of the dictators who showed him reluctant
respect because he was a great national figure; and in
1937 he wrote a requiem entitled "Finsternisse" (Tene-
brae), based on Tolstoy's "Power of Darkness", for his
Jewish friend Max Pinkus. But he made no open resis¬
tance; he preached love and brotherhood, but not rebel¬
lion. So his International reputation as a committed
champion of the proletariat is partly due to a misconcep¬
tion.
This is already made clear in his first play, "Vor
Sonnenaufgang" (Before Sunrise), which was produced in
Berlin in 1889 and caused a scandal by its unvarnished
portrayal of a family of alcoholics. The original title of
this play was "Der Säemann" (The Sower), and as the
word indicates, the Sower was the forerunner of a new
world. His name in the play was Loth, and in some res¬
pects he shows a marked resemblance to Hauptmann
himself. Loth, an enlightened prophet of Socialism,
irrupts into the drab world of profiteers, petty tyrants
and their victims, in a mining district in Upper Silesia,
and falls In love with Helene, a girl who has kept her
simplicity, freshness and purity, in an environment of
corruption, drunkenness and immorality.
Ihe talk between Helene and Loth is one of the
most beautiful love scenes in German dramatic
literature. But Loth is afraid Helene may have inherited
undesirable qualities from her father, who has become
a victim of drink, so he leaves her, and she commits
suicide. This denouement reveals the fundamental weak¬
ness of the central figure and of the play as whole. But
it also illustrates the untenable philosophical attitude
of nineteenth-century Europe and its blind faith in
science in this case taking the form of a conviction
that the theory of heredity is infallible.
Hauptmann was a passive observer, not an accuser,
much less a rebel. In this he differs from the militant
socialist writers, such as Maxim Gorki and Bertolt Brecht.
It is understandable that the first collected edition of his
works should have appeared not In Germany, but In
Russia, where it was published in 1902-1905. This also
shows that Hauptmann's writing's were in fundamental
accord with the spiritual situation of his own day, not
in Germany alone, but throughout the world.
Gerhart Hauptmann became a legend during his own
lifetime (he won the Nobel Prize in 1912), largely owing
to his forceful personality and his physical resemblance
to Germany's greatest poet, Goethe. He revelled in the
role of the last German Prince of Poets, which rather
paradoxically devolved upon him as the champion of the
poor In drama; his personality had a powerful streak of
the actor in it, to which Thomas Mann paid a somewhat
24 equivocal literary tribute by portraying him, with a
mixture of respect and irony, as Mr. Peeperkorn in his
novel "Der Zauberberg" (The Magic Mountain).
Together with Brecht, of whose "epic drama" his "nar¬
rative" plays, with their informal style, were to some
extent the forerunners, Hauptmann was the most pro¬
lific and important German playwright of the century.
His success during his own lifetime far exceeded that of
any other dramatist, even Schiller. For several decades
he dominated the German stage, and even theatres in
other countries still keep his work in their repertory.
His epic writings have attracted comparatively little
attention, though they include some ambitious efforts
such as "Bahnwärter Thiedel" (Thiel the Signalman),
"Der Ketzer von Soana" (The Criminal of Soana), "Der
Narr In Christo Emanuel Quint" (Christ's Fool, Emma¬
nuel Quint), "Till Eulensplegel", "Der grosse Traum"
(The Great Dream) and above all "Griechischer Frühling"
(Grecian Spring). There can be no doubt that Gerhart
Hauptmann reached the loftiest standard of his gene¬
ration; he touched its most responsive chord, and this
alone would fully justify his fame.
S ince the war, little has been heard of him,
either in Germany or abroad. Only a few of
his plays are still acted, and those not very often, and
there is practically no discussion of his work in literary
circles. There are several reasons for this. Hauptmann's
plays are not "literature" in the strict sense of the term.
As a boy he wanted to be a sculptor, and this ambition
left its mark on his writing. He simply changed from one
medium to another, using words instead of stone and
bronze. He wrote in a local idiom (Silesian and Berlin).
The characters in his plays are shown "in the round".
Their facial expressions, movements and gestures, even
their silences, are as important as the words they utter.
They stem from the visual imagination of a man who used
his eyes, who thought in pictures. Hauptmann was not
a philosophical writer, and he was the very reverse of
a rationalist. He wrote in a semi-hypnotic state, sunk
in meditation. To borrow a term from modern psycho¬
analysis, "something" wrote inside him, and much of his
output was enigmatic, sybilllne.
So in his enormous output the sublime is juxtaposed
with the commonplace, enduring values with topical
ephemera, realism with romanticism. Not all his writ¬
ings were carried to the ultimate perfection of form, and
their literary quality ls very unequal. Incompleteness,
unfinished sentences, have their own significance, as in
the conversation of Thomas Mann's Mr. Peeperkorn,
whose words take on meaning from his personality and
whose regal gestures raise his stammering utterances to
the unattainable level of impenetrable cosmic mysteries.
Gerhart Hauptmann's plays only come to life
when they are acted, it rests with the audience
to put the finishing touch to them. The written lines
are not enough. This is one reason why the literary
commentators have hitherto shunned the gigantic figure
of this last of Silesian mystics.
There ls another reason for their avoidance of him,
however, the fact that his work has an unusually wide
stylistic range. It includes all the movements that arose
during his long life, and there were a great many of
them. The plays range from naturalism, with its
attempt to show the world and its inhabitants as they
really are, to neo-romanticism, which won its greatest but
briefest theatrical triumph in "Die Versunkene Glocke"
(The Sunken Bell) ; from social dramas such as "Die
Weber" (The Weavers), which deals with the abortive
uprising of the Silesian weavers in the 1840's doomed
to end in resigned surrender to the four Atrides plays,
with their sombre retelling of an ancient tale of doom,
which make up a belated testament, influenced by the
inhumanity of his own day.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Flammarion, Paris
GERHART HAUPTMANN. HE WAS BORN ON NOVEMBER 15, 1862 AND DIED ON JUNE 6, 1948.
Interspersed with these are pieces like "Der Biberpelz"
(The Beaver Coat), a delightful comedy about a theft in
Berlin; the moving legend of "Hanneles Himmelfahrt"
(Hannele Ascends to Heaven), in which an unreal dream¬
world breaJîs into a poverty-stricken environment; the
tragedy of "Florian Geyer", the chivalrous peasant
leader, which "penetrated to the very heart of German
discord"; the tragedy of the artist, "Michael Kramer":
"Die Ratten" (The Rats), a poignant tragicomedy whose
characters are broken-down artists, proletarians and anti¬
social elements, and which is perhaps Hauptmann's best
play; "Rose Bernd", a tragedy of infanticide, based on the
period of German genius; an original version of the
Hamlet story called "Hamlet In Wittenberg", which vied
with Shakespeare and caused much controversy; and
many other works.
Hauptmann's most poetical play is a fairy-tale, "Und
Pippa Tanzt" (And Pippa Dances), set amid a community
of glass-blowers and in which the eternal powers Eros,
the spirit, and youthfind poetic embodiment In the cha¬
racters of the girl Pippa, the malevolent glassblower
Huhn, Wann, the gentle sage who ls an earthly Incar¬
nation of God, and the travelling journeyman, Michel
Hellrlegal.
Thus, In nearly all Hauptmann's plays, the plot centres
on love. It may be humiliated, scorned and wounded,
but It cannot be destroyed. Hauptmann knows that
people do not love one another enough. "Nobody has had
enough love", moans Rose Bernd, driven to crime and
disaster by other people's cowardice and selfishness; and
August Kell, once her betrothed, speaking "solemnly,
from the depth" utters the closing words of the tragedy:
"Poor girl what she must have suffered!"
A specialist and writer on theatrical questions, Karl 25
Rührberg is a director of the "Deutsche Oper am Rhein"
theatre, at Düsseldorf-Duisberg .
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Grave Mound near Amesbury in southern England comes to light under the careful digging of archae-
26 ologists and volunteer helpers, in foreground two students record the position of a skeleton with the
help of a string grid. The area of Amesbury is very rich in remains of prehistoric man, among the"
best-known of which is Stonehenge, the greatest surviving megalithic structure in the British Isles.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Students working on an excavation site
In Rhodesia learn to use a surveyor's level
to contour the area before digging begins.
HOW TO BE AN AMATEUR
AKvH àMLULUvld I by Beatrice de Cardi
T
Austin D. Underwood
he amateur field worker is no new phenom¬
enon in British archaeology. ' His contribution
to research dates back to the 18th century when, as a
gentleman of leisure, an appreciation of classical antiqui¬
ties led him to record and collect relics of the past which
he observed in the countryside around him.
By the 19th century, the emphasis lay firmly on collect¬
ing, the antiquary perhaps reflecting the materialism of
the age In his acquisitive attitude which saw in fieldwork
little more than a legitimate means of enriching private
collections. Barrow after barrow was dug with rarely a
thought to the circumstances of Its burial beyond the
excavated urn. Narrow as the horizon may appear, it
evoked widespread public interest, particularly as it
coincided with the broader consideration of man's evolu¬
tion proposed by Darwin. The spate of county archaeolo¬
gical societies founded in the middle of the century is
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
AMATEUR ARCH>COLOGlST (Cont'd)
From teen-agers
to septuagenarians
but one expression of the trend which led in turn to the
establishment of museums maintained at public expense.
The rapid growth of museum collections, with their
assembled wealth of artifacts, made possible the applica¬
tion of methods used in related branches of the natural
sciences and produced the typologies and chronological
framework upon which much of British prehistory has
been built up. The credit for this research rests largely
with the amateur and the museum archaeologist.
There were in fact few professionals In other fields of
archaeology until the close of the century, when the
State, lagging somewhat behind public opinion, accepted
a limited responsibility for the preservation of ancient
monuments and a nucleus of Civil Service archaeologists
was formed in 1882 with General Pitt-Rivers as the first
Inspector of Ancient Monuments of the Ministry of
Works.
The establishment of the Royal Commissions to survey
and record historical monuments followed in 1908 and
provided further openings for the professional.
T
28
he gulf between the amateur and the profes¬
sional archaeologist was already becoming
apparent as the pace of specialization quickened in the
1930's. World War II completed the process. The
leisured classes, who were once the mainstay of the
archaeological societies, found they had neither the time
to keep abreast of current thought nor the resources to
devote to archaeology. The societies in turn were faced
with serious financial problems: navvy labour for
excavation was often beyond their means and increased
printing charges made it difficult to maintain the high
standard of publication which had prevailed before the
war.
At the same time there was more urgent need than ever
before for extensive fieldwork. Agricultural and urban
development, were threatening field monuments with
destruction in all parts of the country and the commercial
exploitation of the river gravels and ironstone was
devouring the archaeology of whole regions at a rate
which made recording and examination well nigh
Impossible for the small body of professional archaeolo¬
gists to tackle single-handed, especially as many of them
had heavy teaching and other commitments. The State
has, as a result, assumed a greater responsibility for
large-scale excavation but much still remains for the
societies to do. It is here that the amateur can help,
provided he is prepared to acquire the requisite skill in
field techniques.
It is hard to generalize about present-day amateurs.
Their age may range from 16 to 70 and their background
is as varied. The retired colonel, the doctors of divinity
or medicine, town councillors and engineers, biochemists
and school-teachers, housewives, students and school¬
children can all be found working side by side upon an
excavation. Some may be members of an archaeological
society; others may be students attending an adult edu¬
cation course. A few may have no clear idea what led
them to spend their spare time tolling in a trench apart
from the general fascination which archaeology now
appears to hold for many people.
The present popularity of the subject undoubtedly
owes much to television. Broadcast series such as The
Arch introduced in 1946, have also had an effect
as the sale of 55,000 copies of a British Broadcasting Cor-
^ííjMWKmPKL-. v:
DIGGING UP HISTORY, in the Zambezi Valley, Rhodesia,
students of the Third Livingstone School of Archaeology (above
and right) set to work on a Later Stone Age mound. A specialist
in prehistoric rock art (above) shows a student how to recognize
a Stone Age scraping tool. Delicate and thorough searches call
for small tools like trowels and brushes which students (right)
are using inside each of the marked squares that have been
allocated to them. Below right, excavations at Earlswood Long
Barrow, near Salisbury, England. The word barrow (grave
mound) has been incorporated in many place-names in Britain.
poration pamphlet on Roman Britain proves. Excavations
provide an even greater attraction.
The discovery of a Roman temple in London drew a
patient queue of 30,000 visitors and 60,000 persons found
their way through the suburbs to watch the foundations
of Nonsuch Palace being uncovered in the space of less
than two months recently. Archaeology is news to the
daily press and popular magazines which turn unprompt¬
ed each spring to inquire about forthcoming excavations
from the Council for British Archaeology.
The Council was formed in 1944 to promote and co-or¬
dinate archaeology in the British Isles. It received State
recognition five years later in the shape of a small annual
subsidy. The Council was alive to the dangers of popu¬
larizing archaeology and realized that an outlet should be
provided for the growing public interest in fieldwork.
The obvious remedy was to organize training-schools for
the serious amateur and to put those who simply wanted
an archaeological holiday in touch with the director of
an excavation where their help would be welcomed.
The latter was easy enough to arrange. A brief quest¬
ionnaire to professional archaeologists likely to be
digging usually produces requests for helpers on between
70-80 sites during the season. Last year such sites in¬
cluded Bronze Age barrows within sight of Stonehenge,
Iron Age farmsteads and hillforts, . and many Roman sites
towns, temples, villas and forts in all parts of the
country. A small expedition went to Orkney and adjacent
islands to search for evidence of Scandinavian settlement
in the form of pagan burial-mounds. Work will continue
in the mediaeval towns of Winchester and Southampton,
on castles, priories, manors and on the site of long
deserted villages. Town, country or even uninhabited
island, there is something for all tastes.
Details of these sites are circulated to prospective
volunteers in the form of a Calendar of Excavations,
issued monthly from March until the end of the digging
season in September for an annual fee of 5s. The volun¬
teer selects whichever site appeals to him and writes to
the director to askJf he may help. When the Calendar
first appeared in 1950 it had a modest circulation of
CONT'D ON PAGE 30
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photos L. Titchener (Q Northern Khodrsij Information Drjit
Austin D. Underwood
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
AMATEUR ARCH/EOLOGIST (Cont'd)
Women ideal for uncovering skeletons
67 copies. Within a matter of months it had increased
threefold, and subscribers now total over a thousand and
Include students In America and on the Continent.
The success of the Calendar lies largely in the fact that
it meets the needs of both excavators and volunteers with
a minimum of correspondence or formality. The archaeo¬
logist can appeal for helpers of all kinds: trained super¬
visors, photographers, surveyors, a soil scientist or even a
cook-caterer ,and his chances of finding them are good.
The volunteer, on the other hand, is told as much as
possible about the site; its nature, period and location.
In particular, he ls warned of projects which are only
suitable for those with previous field experience and his
attention ls drawn to sites where beginners would be
given elementary training. Women as well as men are
welcomed on most sites, particularly where a delicate
touch ls needed in uncovering skeletons. And no distinc¬
tion is made unless primitive living conditions In some
Isolated spot demand it.
When the site lies near a village, the volunteer is
usually expected to find his own accommodation. In the
case of a popular holiday resort, difficulties may arise but
the organizer of the dig will usually provide a list of likely
lodgings or may even arrange a camp.
The degree of organization on these sites varies greatly.
A primary qualification of any excavation Is that it
should be disciplined. The director must have some assur¬
ance that his helpers will spend at least a week with him
if not longer, and that they will arrive on time each day.
Where the temptation of sand and surf is likely to prove
too strong, some directors, wisely recognizing the frailty
of their helpers, adjust their hours of work to allow for
a swim In the middle of the- day. Nor are such amenities
as the local pub equipped with darts-board overlooked.
Once on the site, the volunteer will be shown how to dig
and use a trowel, and the necessity for removing the soil
layer by layer will be explained to him. He will also be
told about the purpose and general progress of the work
so that he may understand developments beyond the
limits of his own trench. Heor she will be expected to
share heavy manual jobs and on the larger excavations
may even have to take a turn as guide-lecturer in show¬
ing visitors round the site..
Many amateurs return each season to the same
site acquiring confidence from their familiarity
with the stratigraphy. It is, however, difficult to gain a
thorough grounding in all aspects of fieldwork on an
ordinary excavation. The archaeological problems of the
site must take precedence over training and all too often
the director may be working against time.
Volunteers with long-term aspirations in archaeology
usually prefer to attend a training-school, returning in
successive seasons until they have acquired the back¬
ground and technical knowledge needed to work on their
own. The majority of amateurs can devote their energies
to only such limited objectives as the rescue-excavation of
sites threatened with destruction. Even so, they need an
understanding of the basic principles of excavation and
their practical application in recording stratification, the
registration of associated objects and field survey.
The past decade has seen a notable Increase in the pro¬
vision of such training facilities. In Scotland a Field
School of Archaeology was established in 1947 under the
auspices of four Scottish universities and the C.B.A. region¬
al group. Its purpose was to build up a cadre of trained
field workers to tackle emergency excavation when
needed. Ten years later, of the 171 students who had
30 received training, seven had become professional archaeo¬
logists or museum officials. Eight had conducted excava
tions on their own account and 32 had acted as assistants
on sites in Scotland and elsewhere.
The students were drawn from a wide range of occupa¬
tions which included the professions, the Forces, the Civil
Service, journalism, broadcasting, science and Industry.
Thirty-seven were teachers and it is interesting to note
that the majority used archaeology to a greater or
lesser degree in their work.
Similar groups of trained field workers are being built
up in other regions. The University of Durham has for
a number of years used the site of Corstopitum (Cor-
bridge) on Hadrian's Wall as a training-school for stu¬
dents and amateurs. The University of London is asso¬
ciated with Verulamium (St. Albans). In the east Mid¬
lands, the University of Nottingham's Department of
Adult Education has held eight successive summer schools
on the Romano-British town and neighbouring villa site
of Great Casterton, Rutland.
Ei xperience on these sites has shown that
i ideally the training-school should be envisaged
as an integral part of a more prolonged theoretical course
which could best be provided by means of university
extension or adult education lectures during the winter
months. Now, thanks to public demand, tutorial courses
can be followed in many parts of the country.
Extensive as are the facilities provided on the training-
schools, it sometimes happens that they do not meet the
requirements of the active but inexperienced members of
a local society who may wish to work on a site in their
own locality. If there is no archaeologist of suitable expe¬
rience among their ranks, such a project can best be pur¬
sued by inviting a qualified archaeologist to advise and
direct their activities. Unless he is a person with both
means and leisure, his visits are likely to be restricted to
a minimum, especially if the local society is unable to
meet his travelling expenses.
The Carnegie Trust has recently provided a solution to
this problem by making grants to meet the fees and
expenses of qualified archaeologists willing to direct
projects undertaken by societies and recommended by the
C.B.A. The Trust will also provide funds for the
purchase of tools and expensive items of equipment,
which reverts to the C.B.A. when the society no longer
needs them.
Since the project was initiated in 1958, it has been
possible to train over 200 members of some 28 archaeo¬
logical societies. Excavation was entailed in the majority
of cases, but several societies have embarked on long-
term field surveys. These included surveys of early
settlements in Northumberland and Devon, the tracing of
Roman roads in Flintshire, and the recording of early
domestic architecture in several regions.
The provision of so wide a range of training facilities
for the amateur as distinct from the student who intends
to make archaeology his profession has been one of the
most interesting developments of the postwar period.
Its full effects cannot yet be gauged and much will depend
upon the ability of the local societies to move with the
times and provide for more active participation in field-
" work than has hitherto been customary. Herein lies their
best chance of survival. There is much work to be done
both in field survey and by excavation in all parts of the
country and it is through his local archaeological society
that the amateur can most usefully contribute to research.
Beatrice de Cardi is a Fellow of the Society of Antiquaries
and Secretary of the British Council for Archaeology,
London.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
»^ - &MMMMLAÛ. ^bBb^bB MMdMM
^^bW^ * ^to_^H CI
- cn^BBvBB ^^.vVBBm
* *^ : :> ¿r > ^tn^^M^^BBB LBB ^fej ^% ^ Bk
JODO KUMAMI
"*'**t am^mmm KVj flt^^S B^Bw King of story-tellers
daWta^A^MMMM \Wm* ¥ ' AiBaB^B for Kyoto's children
á$FíO-5
6y Muneharu Kitagahi
On December 31, 1959, an old man of 77 died
peacefully In Kyoto, the ancient capital of
Japan. With his death, a familiar figure disappeared
from the city]s streets. For some fifty years, passers-by
had been accustomed to see Jodo Kumami riding around
in his tricycle wheelchair pulled by two dogs, a con¬
spicuous sight with his long hair and moustache which
made 'him look somewhat like a Chinese physician or
a fortune-teller.
Jodo Kumami was a story-teller and a friend of chil¬
dren for whom he organized many activities at a time
when few people thought of providing playgrounds or
arranging excursions for youngsters in the city. He was
born in 1882, son of a poor family In Osaka, and after his
parents' death, was brought up by his brother in Ako, a
town famous in Japanese feudal history. Burns on his
legs crippled him for life at thirteen, when he acciden¬
tally upset a lighted oil lamp. Being unable to walk,
however, seems to have spurred his Imagination and
obliged him to develop other talents.
His first ambition was to become an artist. He went
to Kyoto to study under a master and, while he earned
a meagre living by drawing designs for kimonos, he began
to make up fairy tales to entertain his neighbours'
children. As they told their friends about his stories,
more and more children flocked to him. Finally, his
small room would not hold them and he had to hire
a large public meeting hall.
About this time, he organized the Kyoto Fairy Talc Club
which held regular meetings for boys and girls and pub¬
lished a monthly magazine in which his stories appeared.
But he did not confine his activities for children to ln-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Jodo Kumami (1882-1959)
became accidently crippled
at the age of 1 3. Afterwards,
for some fifty years of his
life he was a familiar figure
in the streets of Kyoto.Japan,
riding in his wheelchair.
ï¿in ¿K "
cvÄtiV**1
.
m
to s '
- . - mJt*
31
Unesco photos
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
JODO KUMAMI (Cont'd)
The magic of 'once upon a time'
venting stories for them ; he also arranged baseball teams
and excursions and organized summer camps.
By now, he was well-known as a story-teller and a
familiar figure In Kyoto. Children loved him, and called
him "Sense!" (master). They used to push his wheel¬
chair for him and In exchange he gave them drawings
illustrating scenes from his stories.
To commemorate the tenth anniversary of the Kyoto
Fairy Tale Club, Kumami organized Kyoto's first story
competition for schoolchildren in the Town Hall in 1920.
More than ten schools took part in the competition, which
was sponsored by a leading Japanese newspaper. On an¬
other occasion, the Club launched a fund-raising cam¬
paign for Lieutenant Shlrase's Antarctic expedition, an
event which opened up vistas of a new world in the
children's imagination. When Britain's Prince of Wales
visited Kyoto in April 1922, the Club gave him a set of
dolls made by master dollmakers of Kyoto to illustrate
the famous fairy tale of the Tongue-Cut Sparrow.
When it came to money, Jodo Kumami, like many
artists, was impractical. From time to time, financial dif¬
ficulties forced him to close the Club. One evening, when
he had been evicted for not paying his rent, an eight-
year-old girl who had listened to his stories found him in
the street and brought him home. Her parents, who owned
32
a hotel, approved their daughter's generosity and allowed
him to stay for a year.
Kumami wrote many tales, but lack of money prevented
him from collecting them in book form, and in the course
of time, the manuscripts were scattered and lost. Usually,
the stories began with. "Once upon a time." They
had simple, dramatic themes, and the chief characters
were ants, butterflies, dragonflles, rats, mice, rabbits and
goldfish.
Public recognition of Jodo Kumami's activities for
children only came a few years ago, and by then his
name meant little to the rising generation of Japanese
youth who prefer radio, television and cinema to story¬
telling. In 1953, the old man who had given joy to
hundreds of youngsters, was presented with a motor-
driven wheelchair by the Mayor of Kyoto. But even this
brought him no luck. He soon crashed it into a streetcar,
and was seriously injured. He was not at home in the
world of modern machines any more than he was in
the world of modern entertainment. When he got well
after his accident, he again went back to using his old,
trustworthy, dog-powered tricycle-chair.
When he fell ill in 1959, one of his friends asked a
nearby primary school to send some schoolchildren to
visit him. The request was granted, and a group of boys
and girls brought musical instruments to console the for¬
gotten storyteller with a concert. It was only a half-
hour visit, but Kumami was excited to tears, and re¬
marked that he was so happy that now he was ready
to die.
In Kyoto there are still many grown-up people who
cherish a childhood memory of Kumami Sensei. But out¬
side of Kyoto, and among young people and children even
there, he is almost unknown. One Japanese writer of
children's books calls his work old-fashioned. Neverthe¬
less his tales are deeply implanted in the minds of hun¬
dreds of people doctors, university professors, bankers,
merchants, housewives who listened to Jodo Kumami
when they were small.
Because he became an almost legendary figure in the
lives of people familiar with his stories, he has been
compared to Hans Christian Andersen. The two had
much in common: both came from poor families and
spent a poverty-stricken childhood, and both became
story-tellers. But there are differences. Andersen had
opportunities to attend school, while Kumami had none.
Andersen had the advantage of travelling all over Europe
to Rome and to London but Kumami was a cripple and
never went beyond the city of Kyoto. Andersen met
Charles Dickens, and was helped by King Frederick VI
of Denmark, but Kumami had no such distinguished
friends. And, unlike Andersen, Kumami had no opportu¬
nity to publish his fairy tales. Recently, however, efforts
have been made to bring him recognition. Fairy tales
never really die ; and for young children, the world around
there is still magic in the words: "Once upon a time..."
Professor Muneharu Kitagaki is a member of the faculty
of Doshisha University, Kyoto.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WHY NOT COMPROMISE?
Sir,
Although I have been a subscriber
io The Unesco Courier since the
May, 1956 issue, this is my first
correspondance. Despite my unfor¬
givable incommunicativeness, the fact
that I have continued my subscription
since 1956 should indicate my satis¬
faction; but the fact that I write now
is to indicate a dissatisfaction and
offer a placative suggestion. My dissa¬
tisfaction lies with your "new editorial
policy of publishing a greater variety
of articles" instead of devoting
"whole issues" to one theme (April,
1962); my suggestion is a compromise:
devote some issues to the one-theme
approach, and some to the multi-
theme approach. Some themes, such
as conservation, ethnology, the sea,
are in themselves so pregnant with
diverse matter that Unesco could only
perform an abortive service by editing
only one or two articles per theme; on
the other hand, there are a number of
other subjects that are relatively
confined in scope so as not to require
extenuated treatment. Exactly what
subjects should be thrown in your
diversity pot to make a rich stew for
your diversity readers I leave to you;
but please! do not fall into that either-
or fallacy. Your Unesco fare is
broad enough to make a variety of
editorial approaches, not just the one
approach of squeezing "variety" in
every issue.
Tom Kloepping
New Jersey, U.S.A.
Ed. Note: We should be interested
to know what other readers feel.
Please send us your BRIEF comments.
TRAFFIC LIGHTS THAT 'THINK'
Sir,
I have viewed with interest your
"From the Unesco Newsroom", for
several years now, and have found
it one of the high points of each
issue. I wish to point out however
that in it (March 1962), I saw to my
astonishment that there appeared an
article on the "new" idea of mechanic¬
ally controlled "thinking" traffic
lights in Leningrad. Living in one of
the worst cities as far as traffic
problems go in the world, we have
been forced to try everything, and
have had in operation for many years,
a great number of these "Thinking"
traffic lights. They are now so
commonplace here, that nearly every
major street has them sprinkled at
crowded intersections.
Andrew Getz
Los Angeles, U.S.A.
LIFE-SAVING BLOOD
Sir,
In your interesting magazine and
particularly in the May, 1962 issue
(Two Faces of World Health) you
frequently refer to causes of death in
the economically-developed countries:
road accidents (subject of a special
i^sue last year), accidents at work and
cardiovascular diseases which in
Europe and North America have
become "killers of modern times".
I think you would be in line with the
¡îims of Unesco if you reminded your
readers of the role nowadays played by
blood. It is needed for daring heart
operations, used in the treatment of
severely-burned people and also in
the case of "blood poisoning" which
sometimes occurs in young babies
because their parents have opposing
rhesus factors in their blood. Every¬
one should know to which blood group
hi- belongs and many more people
ihould offer to donate a little of their
blood once or twice each year. If this
was done, we should certainly be bet¬
ter protected against the afflictions of
prosperity.
L. Balzy
Paris, France
TEMPLE OF UNDERSTANDING
Sir,
Perhaps your readers will be
interested to know that the Temple
of Understanding as mentioned in the
November 1961 issue of The Unesco
Courier continues to grow apace!
At the request of many Embassy
friends in Washington, a lower or
cultural half has been added to the
plans for the building. The six wings,
representing the six major world
religions will be duplicated below in
order to represent Art, Science, Music,
Philosophy, Literature and Archi¬
tecture. These wings will centre on
an auditorium to be called the Hall
of Nations where the cultural activities
of visitors from abroad may be per¬
formed. This is to broaden our
theme that Truth is indeed a diamond
of many facets.
If any readers are interested in
knowing more about "Project Under¬
standing" we warmly welcome their
inquiries. Letters should be sent to
Box 191, Greenwich, Connecticut,
U.S.A.
Judith Ilollister
New York, U.S.A.
DOLLS GO TO SCHOOL
Sir,
I was so intrigued by the article,
"Ping-Pong Dolls go to School"
(February 1962) that I showed it to
the teachers in the nursery schools of
Rostov who, in turn, were interested
in this way of using Lilliputian
"teachers" to bring lessons alive.
I should like to receive from Madame
Poinsart-Chasson, its originator, full
details of this particular aspect of
"active" methods of education.
I would like to add that thanks to the
publication of a letter I sent to
The Unesco Courier in 1959 on the
subject of frost-resisting vines, I had
replies from America .Japan, Belgium,
Sweden, Norway, Denmark and
France.
I. S. Ailkov
Rostov-on-Don, U.S.S.R.
SEEKING THE CAUSES OF WAR
Sir,
Has Uní sco ever sponsored a
study of history, by scholars of all na¬
tions, with the object of discovering
the causes of war and the conditions
recessary for peace? Even if nothing
new is discovered, the published
findings of such research should
emphasize, for world leaders and
people alike, the need to build peace
upon a firm foundation.
Similarly a Unesco publication of
the lives of those who have devoted
themselves to the pursuit of peace,
could be of value. Provided the lives
of these people carried the same ele¬
ments of courage and adventure as
the heroes of war, they could prove
a great inspiration to all.
Peter A. Walker
Victoria, Australia
Ed. Note:
Unesco's studies relating indi¬
rectly to the causes of war and
the promotion of peace begin in 1947
with studies of international tensions,
many of which have been published.
These include "Tensions that Cause
liar", "How Nations See liai h
Other", "Ways of Life" studies,
covering Australia, Norway, Swit¬
zerland, and South Africa, ami studies
dealing with the question of racial and
ethnic minorities (The Race Question
In Modern Science). Since 1956
emplxasis has been placed on studies
< tlie positive aspects of improving
international relations rather than
conducting research into the negative
aspects of such relations which tend to
hing about war. Study projects have
included: social aspects of economic
development (urbanization, conse-
cjuences of technological change),
Human Rights (race questions, chang¬
ing situation of women) and, more
particularly, questions of peaceful co¬
operation and international under¬
standing.
THE LIKEABLE EMPEROR
PENGUIN
Sir,
The article on "The Emperor Pen¬
guin, Monarch of Antarctica" (May
1962) gave me special pleasure. The
originality of the subject, the excel¬
lence of the text and the striking
photographs illustrating it should have
satisfied even the most demanding
readers, to judge from the opinions
1 heard expressed around me. Thanks,
too, to Jean Prévost, the author, for
having given us such a pleasant intro¬
duction to a little-known member of
the animal world.
J. Tripier
Asnièrcs, France
ERRATUM
The three photos which appear¬
ed on page 25 of the June 1962
issue of The Unesco Courier,
illustrating the article on Paul
Geheeb, are by Yolande Custer.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New:
MEDICAL SCHOOL BY RADIO:
Family doctors in Australia will find
it easier to keep abreast of new develop¬
ments in medicine thanks to a "radio
medical school" which is to be started by
the University of New South Wales, in
Sydney. The courses, to be broadcast by
the University's own medium-wave trans¬
mitter, have been widely requested by
doctors.
rS.SH. HAS 381,000 LIBRARIES:
This was the figure, covering all
types of libraries, revealed by the most
recent 'census, and on their shelves was a
total of 1,900 million books. Largest is
the Lenin Library in Moscow with
21,200,000 books, but more than 100
libraries have more than half a million
books each. Scientific, technical and
specialist libraries in the Soviet Union have
20 million readers.
T.B. STILL A PROBLEM IN
EUROPE: Tuberculosis is still a
threatening disease in Europe, reports the
World Heath Organization. Death rates
have dropped sharply since the war, but
the decline in newly detected cases
annually has been less marked. Hope
that tuberculosis would be eliminated by
"miracle" drugs has been undermined by
the fact that the tubercle bacillus is
acquiring resistance to these highly efficient
agents. New methods of attack will now
have to devised.
YOUTH BUILDS FOR YOUTH: An
International Village named for
Henri Dunant (founder of the International
Red Cross) is being built at Varazze, on
the Italian Riviera, by and for young
people. Apprentice masons, electricians,
carpenters and gardeners from technical
schools in Switzerland are devoting time
from their own holidays to help build five
modern blocks of buildings of this holiday
centre for young people.
MORE GIRLS IN SCHOOL: A survey
carried out by Unesco for the U.N.
Commission on the Status of Women
regarding opportunities for girls in ele¬
mentary education in 82 countries and
territories has revealed a spectacular rise
in the number of girls attending school.
But schooling for girls is still a serious
problem in many countries, and the U.N.
Commision has urged the U.N. Economic
and Social Council to recommend to all
U.N. member states to provide equal
educational rights and facilities for boys
and girls alike.
CAST YOUR TREE... The cherry trees
which bring thousands of visitors to
Washington, the U. S. capital, each spring
were a gift from the people of Tokyo
fifty years ago. The parent trees in Tokyo,
however, disappeared through blight and
damage after World War II. Now, thanks
to a gift of 40 grafts from the trees in
Washington, young cherry trees have again
bloomed on the Arakawa Embankment in
Tokyo from which Washington received the
original gift.
34 1%Ï EK0NG FLOOD STUDIES: Thanks
!» to assistance from the U.N. Special
Fund, a special study for the eventual
construction of a flood control dam on the
Mekong River Delta will be carried out
by .Unesco. The study will reveal the
effect the dam would have on flood control,
sylviculture, fisheries, navigation and power
production in Cambodia and Vietnam.
FRANZ HALS IN HAARLEM: The
100th anniversary of the creation of
the Franz Hals Museum in the city of
Haarlem, The Netherlands, has been cele¬
brated by a large-scale exhibition of" the
Dutch master's works many loaned by
museums and galleries in other countries
which ends on September 30.
INTERNATIONAL POSTER CON¬
TEST: An international jury has now
awarded prizes in the Unesco Poster Contest
on international understanding and co¬
operation, for which a total of 124 designs
were submitted through the intermediary of
Unesco National Commissions. As no
design fulfilled all the requirements for the
award of a first prize, the jury awarded two
second prizes of $500 each to Mr. Morteza
Tabrizian of Iran and Mr. Stanlislaw
Zagorski of Poland. The third prize of
$300 was won by Mr Pau Macia i Pons
of Spain.
WARSAW'S BOOK FAIR: The 7th
International Book Fair was held
in Warsaw's Palace of Culture and Science
recently, when in addition to many Polish
publishers, 140 foreign exhibitors, represent¬
ing some 2,000 publishers and booksellers,
set up their stands. Exhibitors included
the United Nations, Unesco, the Food and
Agriculture Organization, and the Inter¬
national Atomic Energy Agency.
UNESCO PHILATELIC
SERVICE
Shown above is a stamp recently
issued in 2 and 6 rial denomina¬
tions by Iran in honour of the
15th anniversary of Unesco. As
the agent in France of the U.N.
Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all the
U.N. stamps and first-day covers
currently on sale as well as many
stamps, like the one shown
above, issued by Unesco member
states to commemorate important
events in the history of Unesco
and the U.N. For prices and
further details write: The Unesco
Philatelic Service, place de Fon¬
tenoy, Paris (7e).
DANGERS OF RADIATION: The
increasing number of radioactive
products now being used constitute a
growing health problem and call for the
organization of radiation protection
services, the training of personnel and
promotion of research. These problems
were reviewed at a recent conference
sponsored by the World Health Organiza¬
tion in Düsseldorf, which considered
aspects ranging from existing laws and
regulations and control measures to the
supervision of contamination in man's
natural surroundings in air, water, soil
and food.
GUIDES TO U.N. FAMILY: A new
Study Guide Series of five books on
the United Nations and related agencies
specially designed for teachers, group
leaders and students is being published
by Oceana Publications, Inc., of Dobbs
Ferry, New York. Material was prepared
by the Unesco Youth Institute in close
co-operation with the U.N. and specialized
agencies. The first four volumes are
entitled "World Peace and the United
Nations", "Food for Life Food for
Thought", "Improving Living Conditions"
and "Pooling Skills for Human Progress".
The fifth volume to be published in the
Autumn, is entitled "International Co¬
operation". The books should be ordered
through Oceana Publications Inc., Dobbs
Ferry, New York, U.S.A., and not through
Unesco.
LANGUAGE TEACHING AIDS:
Language teachers in countries other
than English-speaking ones may also be
interested in a selective list of materials
for use by teachers in modern foreign
languages in elementary and secondary
schools which has been prepared and
published by the Modern Language
Association of America. The list, which
covers material in French, German, Italian,
Modern Hebrew, Norwegian, Polish, Por¬
tuguese, Russian, Spanish and Swedish, can
be obtained from the Modern Language
Association Foreign Language Program
Research Center, 70 Fifth Avenue, New
York 11, N.Y. price $1.00 each.
Flashes...
Ghana and Canada recently joined the
Universal Copyright Convention, __ under
which 42 countries have now agreed to
grant foreign works the same protection
accorded works by their own nationals.
A sea as big as the Sea of Azov (14,500
square miles in area) has been discovered
deep underground between the Dnieper and
Molochnaya Rivers in the Ukraine.
The World Health Organization reports .
that of 1,420 million people exposed to u
malaria before 1955, 317 million (22%) §
now live in areas where malaria has been £
eradicated. Eradication programmes are in z
progress in areas with 710 million in- ^
habitants. £
o:
<M\ Switzerland recently became the 49th z
state to adhere to the UNESCO-sponsored .
Convention on Protection of Cultural 5
Property in the Event of Armed Conflict. <
High peaks between McMurdo Sound %
and Beardmore Glacier in Antarctica have <
been mapped by helicopter. Radio signals
between a surveyor landed by helicopter S
on mountain peaks and "master units" 20 §
miles away enabled distances between the ¡j
two points to be calculated with a margin ¿
of error of about six inches. 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO ART SLIDES
A collection of colour transparencies to make known to the public masterpieces of world art which,
in spite of their importance for the history of art and for the understanding of the genius of tho nation
which created them, are all too often unknown. Most of the slides are based on the Unesco World
Art Series Albums, with which readers of The Unesco Courier are already familiar. Tho slides,
produced for Unesco by Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire in Paris, are of top quality and rea¬
sonably priced. They are presented in a plastic case for ready projection, each series containing thirty
transparencies, in mounts 5x5 cm, and an explanatory booklet with text and titles in French, English
and Spanish. The very high standard of colour reproduction makes these slides valuable not only
to teachers and lecturers but also to art lovers everywhere.
Series now available :
1. EGYPT: Paintings from Tombs and Temples.
2. YUGOSLAVIA; Mediaeval Frescoes.
3. INDIA : Paintings from the Ajanta Caves.
4. IRAN: Persian Miniatures, Imperial Library.
5. SPAIN: Romanesque Paintings.
6. NORWAY: Paintings from the Stave Churches.
7. MASACCIO: Frescoes in Florence.
8. AUSTRALIA: Aboriginal Paintings from Arnhem
Land.
9. CEYLON: Paintings from Templo, Shrine and
Rock.
10. NUBIA: Masterpieces In Danger.
11. U.S.S.R.: Early Russian Icons.
12. MEXICO: Pre-Hispanic paintings.
To be published shortly :
13. JAPAN: Ancient Buddhist Paintings
(late 1962).
14. CZECHOSLOVAKIA: Romanesque and
Gothic Illuminated Manuscripts (late
1962).
15. GREECE: Byzantine Mosaics (early1963).
16. ISRAEL: Ancient Mosaics (early 1963).
Art education slides :
These sets of slides, and the accompanying
text, illustrate contemporary concepts and
methods of art education in different parts
of the world.
1. Play - Explore - Perceive - Create.
2. Three-dimensional art for the ado¬
lescent.
Prices vary according to country, but do not
exceed the equivalent of S10 in local
currency.
Ih
SPECIAL AGENTS FOR ART SLIDES
Argentine : Editorial Sudamericana S.A., Alsina 500,
Buenos Aires. v
Australia : Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, Mel¬
bourne C. I.
Belgium : Louis de Lannoy, 22, place de Brouckère, Brussels.
Denmark : Mellemfolkeligt Samvirke, Kronprinsessegade 32
(4), Copenhagen.
Finland : Kuvanauha Oy, Alkutie 51, Pakila.
France : Unesco, DPV, 7, place de Fontenoy, Paris (VIIe).
Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire, 44, rue du Dra¬
gon, Paris (VIe).
Rousseau, 6, place Chapou, Cahors (Lot).
Germany : Dr. Lucas Lichtbild, 1, Berlin-Lichterfelde-West,
Fontanestr, 9A.
India : National Education and Information Films Ltd.,
National House, Tulloch Road, Apollo' Bunder, Bombay I.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35 Allenby Road and
48 Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv.
Italy : Casa Editrice Bemporad-Marzocco, Via Sclpione
Ammirato, 35-37, Florence.
Japan : Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6, Tori-Nkhome, Nihonbashi,
P.O. Box 605, Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
Netherlands : C.P.L.I., Postgiro 15476, Amsterdam (O).
Norway :Johan GrundtTanum Bokhandel, Karl Johansgt. 41,
Oslo.
Spain : Librería Científica Medinaceli, Duque de Medinceli 4,
Madrid 14.
Sweden : Pogo Produktion AB, Fack 4 52, Solna 4.
United Kingdom : Educational Productions Ltd., East
Ardsley, Wakefield, Yorks.
U.S.A. : Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third Avenue,
New York 22, N.Y.
Switzerland : Films Fixes Fribourg S.A., 20, rue du Romont,
Fribourg.
IMPORTANT
ART SLIDES In countries where there is no special agent, application should be made to the
National Distributors for Unesco Publications.
UNESCO PUBLICATIONS AND SUBSCRIPTIONS TO THE UNESCO COURIER Please see the
list of National Distributors in the last number.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
From the Gobelins Museum. Photo © Bulloz, Paris.
MUSIC
The viol and the guitar figure in this fragment of
a 15th century tapestry, "Concert at the Fountain
of Youth", believed to have been executed for
Pierre de Rohan, a Marshal of France. The pres
ervation, down the centuries, of the cherished
skills and traditions of stringed-instrument cons¬
truction have made this ancient art a modern one
too (see article, " Music on a String ", .page 4).
]]>
</page>
</document>
