<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078141eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
B m
% w
\
Il \
^
y
1954
Price: 15 cents (U.S.)
Sevenpence (U. K. )
30 francs (France)
UNESCO |
ARCHIVES *
In this issue
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
PRINCIPAL
AGRICULTURAL PRODUCTS
¿J Bananas 1 Sugarcane 0 Coffee
0 Cacao $ Cotton W Tobacco
f Sisal r Coconut *P Oil Palm
fr Pine Hardwood *H Cattl.
/S ATLANTIC
f OCEAN
j Gu/f
( of Mexico
iL c\
v/ ft^n Bahamas
Û \
-¿-^^-O^^w Haiti
Cuba V^>¡j*
Jamaica Dominican
*"X Republic
) Caribbean Sea
PACIFIC
OCEAN
1L -
-^ Lemongrass (essential oil)
Black symbols indicate present areas of production.
Gray symbols indicate areas where expansion ¡s possibl
Areas which can be developed by irrigation From:
Surface water Underground water
Road, all weather, hard-surfaced (asphalt)
Road, all weather, loose-surfaced (gravel)
Road, dry weather, dirt
Railway, 3'6" gauge
OCEAN
Department boundary
0 10 20
1 I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
TheCourier
NUMBER 2- 1954
7th YEAR
CONTENTS
PAGE
3 AT ONE STROKE
4 MESSAGE BY PAUL EUGENE MAGLOIRE
President of the Republic of Haiti
5 FROM SLAVERY TO NATIONHOOD
Haiti's stormy history.
By Alexandre Leventis.
8 KALEIDOSCOPE
Aspects of Haitian culture.
By Jean Price-Mars
10 CHARTERS AND TRUE. FREEDOM
Constitutional liberty and its application.
By Dantes Bellegarde.
12 HAITI AND THE UNITED NATIONS
Plans for greater prosperity.
By Jean F. Brierre.
14 HAITI TODAY
In text and image.
OTHER ARTICLES AND FEATURES
18 THE GROWTH OF OUR CITIES
Three hitherto unpublished maps and the story of a
century and a half of urban development. By Charles
Morale and Jacques Bertin.
22 TV PASSPORT TO EUROPE
Eight countries link up their programmes.
By Henry R. Cassirer.
24 HAWAII: RACIAL CROSSROADS OF THE PACIFIC
The Islands of racial harmony.
By Harry L. Shapiro.
26 SCIENCE CHRONICLE
It was colder when we were younger.
By Gerald Wendt.
28 HISTORY BOOKS AND THE VIKINGS
A new look at the "bloodthirsty nomads
of the North". By Marcel Vanhamme.
29 ASSIGNMENT: SOLOMON ISLANDS
A teacher's unusual experiences.
By H. W. Gaudin.
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Brief notes on education, science, culture.
Published monthly by
The Department of Mass Communication of the United Nations
Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France.
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler.
Associate Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton
French Edition: Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition: José De Benito
*
Individual articles not copyrighted ma/ be reprinted from THE COURIER but
must be accompanied by the following credit line: "Reprinted from UNESCO
COURIER". Signed articles reprinted must carry the author's name.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied by an intep-
' national reply coupon covering postage.
Signed articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of THE COURIER.
Annual subscription rates of THE COURIER: 6/-, or S 1.50 or 300 French frs.
MC. 53.1 79. A.
UNESCO COURIER . K» 2 - 1954
This month's theme :
HAITI, 150 YEARS
OF INDEPENDENCE
*n the park before the Haitian national
capitol at Port-au-Prince stands a mem¬
orial tû Toussaint Louverture, a detail
of which shows a chained Negro slave
paying homage to the man who helped
liberate Haiti. François Dominique
Toussaint adopted the name Louver¬
ture, " the opening. " It is popularly
considered symbolic of his opening the
door to freedom for the slaves.
(Photo copyright Rapho-Guillumette).
One hundred and fifty years ago there occurred an event
'which remains unique in the annals of world history.
Against all odds and to the amazement of all nations, a
people of slaves rose up in revolt and achieved both
emancipation from degrading servitude and national indepen¬
dence.
Many are the countries that have resorted to arms to win their
independence, and on numerous occasions slave peoples have
risen up to Win their emancipation. But there is no example,
apart from Haiti, of a people who achieved both in one single
stroke.
It is these unusual circumstances and this great example of a
struggle for human rights that have prompted the Editors of
The Courier to devote a large portion of this issue to Haiti, in
place of the monthly theme devoted to an important world
problem in education, the arts or science.
Haiti has many claims upon the attention of the world: it was
the first independent Negro state in the modern world ; it was
the second free state in the Western Hemisphere ; it has
answered the question often posed in the past whether a nation
ruled by blacks could long endure ; it has emerged from a long¬
standing isolation to join the comity of nations, welcome the aid
of foreign experts, pursue a policy of enlightenment in educa¬
tion, public health improvement, soil conservation, and agricul¬
tural and general economic development. Haiti is today open
to the dynamic influences which accompany a changing
economy.
As Haiti's President, Paul Eugène Magloire has firmly put
it : "Haiti has shown by its struggle for liberty and progress
that the black race and small nations can... achieve a status
equal to that of any other human group. Haiti has given the lie
to those who pretend that certain races are unfit for liberty,
equality and self-government."
When in 1947 Unesco launched its world-wide campaign for
belter standards of living- through a combined altack on ignor¬
ance, poverty and disease, it was Haiti that ofl'ercd one of
its most desolate areas the Marbial Valley as a testing
ground. Here, by trial and error, new educational techniques
and methods were evolved and new paths broken, through
the combined efforts of the United Nations and its Specialized
Agencies working directly with Haitian officials and the Haitian
people. This was one of the UN's earliest large-scale joint
efforts of its kind, and in a sense served as a forerunner of the
idea which was later to develop inlo the- expanded programme
of technical assistance to the underdeveloped nations of
the world.
Haiti is a land of many contrasts. It is a land of poverty, and
faces enormous problems of education, health improvement and
rural development. But it is also a happy land. Her people
wear a gay and smiling countenance, love to sing and dance and
laugh. Although poor in worldly goods, the peasants have three
priceless possessions : freedom, a home and a plot of land.
Time and the exuberance of both the land and its people have
healed many of the deep scars of slavery, devastation and vio¬
lence which darkened Haiti's history for so long. Today the
hard-won peace and freedom are beginning to bear fruit and
give promise of great progress in Haiti in the futu:e.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
tvo
tV«tvts
*&£& co-<att^^V
ec?üc
Ca^oí
^ et*»
'fice ~"° -ííi ft.
5 Of
have
xx
\\stte Ott
,attc ^e
otte'^Aep^à!^ee^s
ate
to
ttte
co^
, «Oft
^PtoveJ*0^ seTi^e fo. r^ai-ew
«SS§Ä*
The stamp shown below ¡s one ot a seri
commemorating the I50ch anniversary of the
independence of Haiti. It carries the por¬
traits of Jean-Jacques Dessalines, first head of
the Haitian State and of Paul Magloire, Haiti's
President since 1950. For this issue of the
Courier on Haiti, President Magloire has sent
the special message published on this page.
satistoil til L° the r "'"¿en ~"r o#P 0/
i*a£?*<»e~iiiip,
*****
y of
That ,
eprr
Ve »redete
'ens
Go ^''
%h has
the
aj*
**** £¿ ^ta *8'<<.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
From Slave
Colony to
Nationhood
UNESCO COURIER - N° 2 - 1954
by Alexandre Leventis
THE CITADELLE LAFERRIÈRE was the most
massive of the fortresses built by King Henri I
(Henry Christophe). Like the prow of a ship, its
great bastions sweep upwards from the rocky
summit of the mountain, beneath walls which
tower to a height of 240 feet. (Photo copyright
Denise Colomb, Paris.)
WHEN George III, King of England,
asked one of his admirals to de¬
scribe Haiti to him, the admiral
crumpled a sheet of paper into a ball
and, holding it out to his sovereign to
see, said, "'There it is, Sire". The story
may not be true, for it is also told of
Puerto-Rico, with Queen Isabella asking
a Spanish admiral to describe it. All the
same, it fits the facts; seen from the air
the island appears a mountainous mass
furrowed by valleys running in every
direction. Indeed, there is a Haitian
saying, "Behind : the mountains there
are other mountains" and the name
"Haiti" in the language of the Arawak
Indians means "mountainous country"
or "high land."
Christopher Columbus, dazzled by the
beauty of the. landscape when, for the
first time, he saw the wonderful bay
which he named St.Nicholas, exclaimed,
"Es una maravilla!" (It is a wonder!),
and described it thus in writing to his
patrons Isabella of Castile and Ferdi¬
nand of Aragon.
The great navigator had set out from
Palos in Andalusia with three caravels
and ninety-eight companions on August
3, 1492, and on December 6, after having
landed at the Bahamas and at Cuba, he
sighted the large island which the In¬
dians had told him existed to the east.
"Everywhere there you find gold and
untold treasure", they said.
Gold was, in fact, one of the presents
given to the sailors from the Santa Ma¬
ria, the Pinta and the Nina by the In¬
dians of Arawak stock who inhabited the
island. Welcomed with open arms,
Christopher Columbus and his men had
no difficulty in taking possession of the
island in the name of the Queen of Cas¬
tile. Columbus called it "La Isla Espa¬
ñola", whose Latinized form "'Hispa-
niola" was later adopted in English.
LIKE A GRIM CYCLOPS, the fortress of King Henri dominates land, sea and sky from its rocky promon¬
tory called Bonnet à PEvêque (Bishop's Bonnet). It was armed with 365 weighty bronze cannon dragged
by hand up a winding mountain trail. It once held enough provisions to supply 10,000 soldiers during a
year's siege. (Photo Haitian National Tourist Office.)
Small of stature, the Arawáks were a
sedentary and peaceful people. Al¬
though they were skilled weavers of
cotton and lived by hunting, fishing and
agriculture, they went about almost
naked. Columbus described them as
"gentle beings, hospitable... curious and
merry, walking. in beauty..." These In¬
dians were already playing a form of
football using a ball 'made of crude
rubber which they called a bastos, and
which they hit mostly with their knees.
On the whole they were cheerful peo¬
ple, who when not keeping up their
gaiety by singing did so just as effect¬
ively by drinking onycou, - a beverage
made from fermented fruit juice. The
gods they worshipped were the sun, the
moon, the sky, the stars, and they were
so fond of mameys, a succulent island
fruit, that their conception of paradise
was a place where one did nothing but
eat mameys all day. When the Span¬
iards landed there, Haiti was divided
into five small kingdoms governed by
"caciques", who combined the roles of
political and military chieftains, priests
and doctors.
Christmas Day 1492 was a disastrous
one for Columbus. His flagship Santa .
Maria drifted onto a coral reef in Acul
Bay and was wrecked. But this paved
the way for the founding of the first
American colony. "Because it is certain"
wrote Columbus In his Journal, '"that if
I had not run aground here, I should
have kept out to sea without anchoring
in this place... Neither would I have left
people here on this voyage".
This first colony was founded near
what is_ now the town of Cap Haïtien
and a "fortress was built with salvage
from the Santa Maria. When Columbus
set sail for Spain in January 1493 he left
behind 42 colonists. But when he
returned in November of 'the same year
bearing the titles of Admiral and Viceroy
of the Indies, with seventeen ships and
1,500 volunteers attracted by the thought
of gold and adventure, Columbus found
the fort destroyed and the colonists slain.
However gentle and hospitable the
Arawaks may have been, they objected
to being pillaged and had finally taken
counter measures.
This time the "Admiral of the Ocean
Seas" established a settlement further
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
With scythes, pitchforks and torches
to the east, 25 miles from the 'present
Dominican town of Puerto Plata, and
later, near a gold mine, at the spot
where the town of San Domingo stands
today. In dealing with the chieftains he
resorted alternatively to the sword and
to negotiation (with a preference for
force). Then he ran into trouble from
another quarter: when his companions
realized that their hopes of riches to be
had just for the taking, were unfounded,
they began to make exhorbitant demands
and Columbus could not prevent them
from enslaving the Indians. Finally the
"High Admiral" was forced to seek help
in Spain; but he failed, and in the end
died in destitution in Valladolid on May
20, 1506.
By that time there were only 60,000
Indians left in the Isla Española, a
twentieth of what there had been fifteen
years earlier. The colonists' treatment
of the remaining Indians became so
harsh that Bishop Bartolomé de Las
Cases, horrified by the oppression of the
Arawaks, appealed to the Spanish Court
on their behalf. As a result in 1517 four
thousand Negroes were sent from Guinea
to work for the settlers.
But this did not save the Indians from
extermination. In 1533 when Henry,
"last chieftain of Haiti", abandoned the
struggle for independence, the Spaniards
offered him sanctuary near the city of
San Domingo. He settled there with 600
followers the sole survivors of the
"gentle and hospitable" Indians who had "
welcomed Christopher Columbus some
forty years earlier.
Similar ill-treatment goaded the
Negroes to revolt and "...as they were
captured they were hanged from the
nearest tree, so that the road was lined
with their swinging bodies".
But the Spaniards were no longer the
undisputed masters of the Island.
French, English and Dutch privateers
began to set up bases on its largely
uninhabited north-west coast from
which to prey on the Spanish galleons
and caravels sailing the Caribbean Sea.
Their main base was the small island of
Tortuga (The Turtle), legendary hide¬
out of the filibusters or freebooters
(words derived from "flyboat", a fast,
light boat).
Between raids these pirates developed
a characteristic way of life economic,
political and social on Tortuga. They
often came over to the mainland to shoot
wild cattle and boar which they roasted
whole over a wood fire on a barbecue
THE MAJESTIC RUINS of Sans Souci, the most
magnificent of the nine royal palaces and eight
chateaux built by King Henri. It is said to have
been modeled after the palace of Frederick the
Great. Its main floor was cooled by a mountain
stream which flowed through conduits beneath
it. (Photo Haitian National Tourist Office.)
frame called a boucan (hence the name
"buccaneers").
Among this company of privateers,
filibusters, 'buccaneers and pirates the
French came to outnumber the others, so
that at the signing of the Treaty of.
Ryswick in 1697, France claimed and
Spain ceded the western third of the
Island.
Bertrand d'Ogeron, the first Governor-
General of Saint-Domingue, /the new
French colony, showed himself a great
administrator and also, in bringing girls
out from France as wives for the settlers,
an astute psychologist. To provide
manpower for the development , of the
plantations he organized the importation
of 'the African Negro slaves at the rate
of 20,000 to 30,000 a year.
Colour and caste
AS the colony grew prosperous espe¬
cially with the arrival of new
immigrants from France in the
1720's, there came into being a class
system in which whites, mulattoes and
Negroes were distinguished not only by
the colour of their skin, but by their
social standing. Negro slaves, naturally,
did not figure in this system.
Properly speaking it consisted of three
groups 'known as grands' blancs, petits
blancs, and gens de couleur. The first of
these categories embraced the important
whites owners of large plantations,
wealthy merchants and state officials.
The second covered all other whites of
the colony shopkeepers, artisans, small
planters with only a few slaves, little
people busily engaged in social climbing,
and shiftless whites largely slipping
downhill. The 28,000 gens de couleur
included all free persons who had Afri¬
can blood in their veins.
. This society, where love of money and
of pleasure held sway, was beset by every
kind of prejudice, but chiefly those of
colour and caste. - As the free coloured
people flourished, so also did the jeal¬
ousy of the' petit blancs against them. As
for the Negroes, they were the slave
labour and often served as mere beasts
of hurden.
«First of the blacks'
FOR many years tiny fires of discon¬
tent smouldered in the colony. The
fall of the Bastille in France in
1789 helped to fan them into a larger
flame. Like the grands blancs the freed
mulattoes sent their children to Paris for
an education. Working through a hu¬
manitarian group called the Society of
Friends of the Blacks, some of these
students, and particularly a young mu¬
latto, Vincent Ogé, were influential in
getting the French National Assembly to
pass a decree in March 1790 granting
political and civil rights to freedmen.
But the Assembly left the actual inter¬
pretation of the decree to the colonial
authorities.
Returning to Saint-Domingue, Ogé
joined a friend, Chavannes, a freedman
like himself, and sought in vain to have
the decree enforced. Both were ultimate¬
ly arrested, tried and condemned to be
broken on the wheel. The torture of
Ogé and Chavannes in 1791 gave the
smouldering revolt two martyrs and the
signal for insurrection. It quickly
spread to the proportions of a massacre.
Slave gangs ran riot, setting fire to one
plantation after another. Half the rich
northern plain was laid waste in a few
days. The blacks then turned on their
masters. The massacre of the whites
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N° 2 - 1954
HAITI (Continued.)
He had been a slave for nearly
fifty years when t.'.e insurrec¬
tion of the slaves broke out In
Saint-Domingue In 1791. In
the next eleven years he be¬
came one of the most talked-
of men In the world. Self-
educated, he was to show high
military talents and political
astuteness. By 1797 he was
supreme leader In Salnt-Do-
. mingue. He was eventually
captured and imprisoned in
France where he died in 1803.
Wordsworth wrote a moving
sonnet to him for strengthening
human faith In "man's uncon¬
querable mind."
From childhood Dessalines
rebelled against his life as a
slave. Punishment for disobe¬
dience merely hardened his
resolve tofightagalnsthls mas¬
ters. At the head of the army
of Saint-Domingue he helped
Toussaint to repulse the Span¬
iards and expel the English.
After Toussamt's fall, Dessa¬
lines led the Haitians to final
victory and independence. Ap¬
pointed Governor-General for
life, he took the title of emperor
in 1804. He was killed in an
ambush in 1806 before the ad¬
ministrative reforms he planned
were achieved.
The son of freed slaves, Chris¬
tophe was born In the English
West Indies and became one of
Toussaint's leading generals.
After the death of Dessalines
he was elected president, but
refused to accept the office,
considering It to be merely
an honorary one. He therefore
proclaimed himself king and
reigned in the north until his
death In 1820. He ruled with
iron discipline but he was
an able administrator. He
established schools, built
roads, developed agriculture
and industry, promoted arts
and sciences.
ALEXANDRE PETION
In the first uprisings Pétlon
became famous for his calm
courage and chivalry. Later he
opposed Toussaint, was exiled
to France but returned to |oln
Dessalines and ensure final
victory and independence. He
became Haiti's first president,
gave sanctuary and aid to Bo¬
livar In his struggle for Latin
America's emancipation, estab¬
lished the basis of Haiti's edu¬
cational system, and was the
founder of Haitian rural de¬
mocracy by creating land re¬
forms. At his death the entire
nation mourned the "little
father" they had lost.
which followed is comparable in horror
only to the butchering of the Negroes
which followed the suppression of this
first rebellion.
Whites and mulattoes were sharply
divided in their loyalties, the former
seeking to hold on to their privileges, the
latter inclined to favour the abolition of
. slavery if only for the sake of their own
safety. Some of the more die-hard
colonists blindly called 'on the English
then at war with France for support,
and the situation was further compli¬
cated by the fact that the Spanish
hostile to both the French and the
English were supplying the rebels with
arms and poised on the eastern border.
Three commissioners had been sent
from Paris to restore order. On August
29, 1793, one of them, Sonthonax, pro¬
claimed the abolition of slavery in the
north in order to pacify the rebels and
win support against the invading armies
of Spain and England. The decree was
later extended to the western and
southern regions of Saint-Domingue.
The French would probably have "been
defeated if help had not come from a
black ex-slave, Toussaint Louverture,
who offered his troops to the French
General in the colony and finally drove -
the English and the Spaniards but of
Saint-Domingue.
"The First of the Blacks" as Toussaint
was called had been a slave for over 40
years before the insurrection and lived
only eleven after it, but in that short
space of time he became one of the most
talked of men in the world.
By 1797, Toussaint had become the
supreme leader in Saint-Domingue, his
authority disputed by only one rival, the
mulatto General Rigaud whom he
quickly vanquished after a brief conflict.
By the time Napoleon came to power two
years later he had achieved independ¬
ence from France in all but name.
He had taken' over most of the
functions of government from the
French; under him anarchy and massa
cres had come to an end. Saint-Domin¬
gue was making its own laws, main¬
taining its own army, and negotiating
treaties with foreign powers. A
committee of seven white planters and
three mulattoes drew up a new consti¬
tution abolishing slavery and making
Toussaint Governor-General for life.
Napoleon was infuriated at the me¬
teoric rise of the "gilded African" as he
called Toussaint, and resolved to crush
him. He sent the largest fleet and most
powerful expeditionary force that had
ever crossed the Atlantic to Saint-Do¬
mingue. The war of independence had
begun.
Birth of a nation
AFTER three months of furious
fighting, marked by epic moments
of heroism by Toussaint's officers
and men, both sides were exhausted and
a truce agreed upon. Shortly afterwards
Toussaint was invited to a conference.
In the course of a meal he was seized,
bound and swiftly shipped off to France.
Haiti never saw him again. Less than
a year later, in April 1803, he died of
cold and starvation in a dungeon high
in the mountains near the Franco- '
Swiss border.
The fall of Toussaint was followed by
the Terror,, with rebels .executed en
masse. These executions were answered
by guerilla warfare and then by a full-
scale uprising led by Jean-Jacques Des-
salines, Henry Christophe and Alexandre
Pétion. Armed with everything from
scythes to rifles their troops fought sa¬
vagely. But the French army which had
been largely consumed in the battle
against Toussaint was now also being
destroyed by disease. In four months
18,000 soldiers and 50 Generals were
wiped out by yellow fever. The French
commander, Leclerc fell ill and died.
On November 15, 1803, white authority
on Saint-Domingue was ended forever.
And on the first day of January 1804,
Dessalines solemnly proclaimed the
former colony of Saint-Domingue inde¬
pendent and the first independent Negro
State in the world assumed its former
name of Haiti.
The Haitian nation, however, still
remained to be built. But built on
what? On Independence Day the nation
was nothing but' a "'herd of slaves who
had suddenly acquired their freedom".
No more than 350,000 people remained
out of the 530,000 who had lived in
Saint-Domingue in 1792. Nothing was
left of Haiti's past wealth and prosper¬
ity. The rich plantations had dis¬
appeared in the smoke of the incendiary
torch during the fierce scorched-earth
war of liberation.
The whole structure of the nation had
to be built, new institutions established,
morale, ambition and the desire to work
affirmed. "The master does not work;
to be free is not to work", was the ter¬
rible gospel bequeathed by the colonial
system to the freed Negroes. ,
For over twenty years, until Haitian
independence was officially recognized
by the French in 1825, Haiti remained in
complete isolation constantly fearing the
possible return of the French. This
kept the whole nation in arms and
seriously retarded efforts at organization.
It is hardly surprising therefore that
under such circumstances the unity of
the Haitian people was not achieved
immediately and that several decades
were needed to complete the work begun
by Dessalines on 1 January, 1804.
.As one of Haiti's great historians has
pointed out, "there is certainly not one
among the modern states which started
under such adverse conditions. But the
Haitian nation no longer presents the
aspect of the amorphous mob 'of 1804.
It has created its own institutions and
today it possesses all the elements which
will give it a definite opportunity to de¬
velop. It has planters, skilled workers,
industrial workers, traders, and an intel¬
lectual class of its own. "
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
KzjékMâqbe
by Jean Price-Mars
CULTURAL ASPECTS
OF LIFE IN HAITI
AMID the tremendous birth pangs
of the new world which was
engendered by the ideological
movement of the eighteenth century and
found expression in two revolutions
the American Revolution of 1774 and the
French Revolution of 1789 some of the
strangest, most paradoxical and most
unexpected events occurred in the West
Indies.
Saint-Domingue, the wealthiest and
most flourishing of the French colonies,
rebelled against France. And after a
struggle which lasted 14 years, amid ruin,
destruction and catastrophe, its people
declared their independence.
But who were these people ?
Were they the owners of the plan¬
tations where sugar-cane, coffee and
indigo were plentifully produced ? Were
they the rich aristocrats, the pompous
bourgeois, the arrogant government
officials who had set up sugar factories,
rum distilleries, coffee factories and tan¬
neries and were drawing enormous
profits from them ? Were they the rank
and file of the comparatively poor the
labourers, tradespeople or craftsmen "
bitterly resentful of their subordination
to the privileged classes ? Were they,
in short, the members of the European
minority, which totalled over 30,000 ?
Not at all. Those embarking upon this
incredible adventure were the amor¬
phous mass of 600,000 black slaves who
had been brought from Africa in the
course of three centuries of slave trad¬
ing, to be used as tools in promoting
the colony's prosperity. The outstand¬
ing fact about their existence was that
they were regarded, not as human beings
whose individual merits served to
reinforce those of the rest of the com¬
munity and so increase its collective
value, but as mere instruments, whose
only useful purpose was to contribute to
the development and exploitation of
France's wealthiest overseas possession.
Real wealth
it was that while, according to
Mr. Barbé de Marbois, the last Fi¬
nancial Administrator of Saint-Domin¬
gue, the total wealth of the colony
amounted in 1790 to 1,487,840,000 livres
tournois equivalent, as calculated
by an economic expert in 1938, to
5 275,537,487,50 (gold standard) the
chief item in this impressive total was
the market value of the Negroes, enter¬
ed in the same account at 1.137.500.000
livres tournois, or, S 210,648,506.25.
Jean Price-Mars is a former di¡ilomat and one
of Haiti's leading liistorians, ethnographers and
sociologists. He is the author of "Ainsi parla
l'oncle", a remarkable booh on Haitian life and
other works surveying the intellectual and cultu¬
ral achievements of Haiti.
It is therefore clear that the real
wealth of San Domingo resided in the
economic power of its slave population.
It was, in fact, at once the condition and
the consequence of the slaves', existence.
When, in 1790, those slaves rose up and
demanded the unconditional restoration
of their former status as free men, they
were, in our opinion, initiating the
greatest revolution the world had ever
seen a revolution whose success
depended upon the savage annihilation
of everything that could serve as a
reminder of the former system of slavery.
No virgin soil
"P UT the destruction was only of a
JJ material nature. For in any event
this new society was born under the spi¬
ritual sign of Western civilization, of
which France was at that time the most
brilliant representative ; and to that
civilization it was indissolubly bound.
From its former mother country it
borrowed, as occasion arose, a super¬
structure of language, political consti¬
tution, administrative organization,
manners, customs, and so on. The
result was a phenomenal feat of socio¬
logical mimetism accomplished by a
magnificent effort of adaptation and
redemption to which Michelet, that seer
among historians, paid tribute by refer¬
ring to the new nation as "black
France".
Can it be said however, that this deli¬
berate transmutation took the form of
complete "integration"?
By no means. And we may be glad of
the fact.
For such a course of events would have '
been contrary to reason. We must
remember that we are dealing here with
human beings and that human willpower
alone is not always enough to bring about
change simply because it is wanted or
needed. Besides, the Negro community
of Saint-Domingue which in 1804 became
the State of Haiti, did not consist of
homogeneous elements brought across
the Atlantic en bloc with no past and
no history. Thus this was no virgin
soil for experimentation providing -a
convenient foundation for whatever
artificial structure the fancy of would-
be nation builders might conceive.
It consisted of men scattered through¬
out the length and breadth of the
colony, men so shackled by their fate of
servitude that they could not even
maintain daily contact and thus agree
on a measure of concerted action.
Moreover, these men were descended
from many different Negro races, ele¬
ments of which had . been brought to
Saint-Domingue by slave traders who
had operated along the entire western
coast of Africa.
In the land of their slavery they had
. all, it is true, been subjected to the same
physical and moral suffering, which
ultimately led them to unite their
demands in a single outburst of rage.
That was the miracle resulting from the
revolutionary era which provided' the
atmosphere, the opportunity and the
moment. But was it not to be feared
that, victory once gained, tribal differ¬
ences would revive ?
This did not happen, because the
members of the community, whatever
their origin, were unconsciously linked
together by another factor, which acted
as a catalyzer of activities and move¬
ments the similarity between their
religious beliefs, of which animism was
the common denominator. It inspired
their actions and outlook and though
hidden in the depths of the collective
consciousness, penetrated even into the
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 - 1954
ceremonies of the other religion the
Catholic, Apostolic and Roman faith
which had originally been forced upon
the community and later became its
official creed.- As though religious
belief were a mental attitude which
could be decreed by officialdom. The
result was that between the real outlook
of the people and this officially expres¬
sed "conformism" there remained a
discrepancy in time certainly the most
arresting and fascinating of all the prob¬
lems presented by the society based on
the former slaves of Saint-Domingue.
This problem has not yet been solved,
despite the '"Bovarysm" displayed in
orthodox circles.
The more rigidly conventional quarters
refuse to admit the existence of this
duality, closing their eyes to everything
save the semblance of a Western culture,
more in line with their plans and their
conception of' greatness an Ulusory
conception, because they judge civiliza¬
tions according to a "'scale of values".
But the problem exists, and has reper¬
cussions in every sphere of social Ufe.
And it is because sociologists, ethnogra¬
phers, historians and psychologists have,
in recent years, endeavoured to identify
it in the many different externalizations
of our community life that they have
ended by engendering a real literary,
scientific and artistic renaissance move¬
ment in Haiti.
They looked into Haitian folklore and
found, to everyone's surprise and delight,
a whole galaxy of works which reflected,
and stUl reflect, the different aspects of
our culture. Dancing, music, poetry, the
story, and works of science all this
belongs to the choicest harvest of the
people's talents.
It would be tedious and pointless to Ust
these works and their authors here ;
still less is it our intention to suggest
any order of merit for them. We merely
wish to stress the extent to which our
intellectual heritage takes shape in the
externalization of a culture that is pecu¬
liar to ourselves and characteristic of our
society.
We would mention only a few examples
of this. In the first place, could any¬
thing be more truly Haitian than that
special quality of rhythm in our music,
which imprints upon it the indelible
mark of the Negro spirit ?
As we wrote some 20 years ago, "'There
is no denying that even the slightest of
our gestures reveals this expressive
sense of rhythm. Rhythm in walking, to
the "stroke" of arms and shoulders, Uke
that of oars driving a boat forward.
Rhythm in the crushing of grain in
(Continued on page 32)
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
HAITI (Continued)
*
CHARTERS AND
TRUE FREEDOM
by Dantes Bellegarde
HAITI'S CAPITAL, Port-au-Prince is the
country's chief port and commercial centre.
Situated against a crescent of wooded moun¬
tains, the city faces the emerald-blue Gulf of
Gonave. Into the city on market days
come peasants, like the old, pipe-smoking
woman (above), to sell their produce.
(Photos Haitian Tourist Office).
THE proclamation of Haiti's in¬
dependence, on 1 January 1804, was '
not merely the birth of a new
State, but resounding affirmation of the
principle of human freedom through the
abolition of slavery, and a decisive vin-
Dantes Bellegarde, ili¡)lumul, educator, author,
is nue uf Haiti's most distinguished scholars. He
is Ihr author of numerous u-oiks on the history
>// his couiitri/. 'mctudinij "Haiti and its Peo/ile",
and "I'll llndirii I'm le".
10
dication of the idea of racial equality
through the triumphal entry of a Negro
people into the comity of civilized
nations.
Born of the courage and enterprise of
the slaves of Saint-Domingue, and
drawing its inspiration from the prin¬
ciples of the French Revolution, the State
of Haiti was bound to adopt the demo¬
cratic system. Its social policy was
defined and proclaimed at a very early
stage. The Haitians claim for both the
"Preliminary Declaration" of the 1805
Dessalines Constitution and the "Gener¬
al Provisions" of the 1806 Republican
Constitution, a place alongside the Eng¬
lish "Magna Carta" and the Bill of
Rights, the American Declaration of In¬
dependence, the French Declaration of
the Rights of Man and the Amerioan Bill
of Rights.
The 1805 and 1806 Declarations
together form the Charter of Haitian
freedoms, proclaiming those conceptions
of liberty, equality and fraternity which
are the hall-mark of our democratic
civilization. It is astonishing to see how
faithfully these three great ideas the
very essence of democracy are reflected
in three of our national heroes. Tous-
saint-Louverture personifies liberty. Des¬
salines stands for equality, for in leading
Haiti to independence he was affirming
the right of a black people to rank as an
equal with all the other nations of the
world. Alexander Pétion represents
fraternity which today we call social
justice because in founding the Re¬
public he appealed to all Haitians to
participate in the government of their
country, for the common good; and
because, in helping Simon Bolivar to
liberate the Spanish colonies- in the
Western hemisphere, he ensured the
abolition of slavery in Spanish America,
and gave the first disinterested example
of inter-American solidarity.
Since the proclamation of the Republic
in 1806, the form of its government has
never been seriously challenged. History
does, it is true, record the "imperial"
designs of Soulouque in 1849; but none
of our subsequent Heads of State was
tempted to :emulate the grotesque
behaviour of this man who reigned as
Faustin the First.
All our constitutional Charters and
we have had a great many have re¬
spected the republican principle.
Creaking machine
"pVER since 1816, Haiti has adhered to
-*-* the representative system, with uni¬
versal suffrage and separation of powers.
It has a House of Representatives,
a Senate and responsible Ministers in
. fact, all the components of an up-to-
date political structure. .Our Constitu¬
tion embodies all the principles proclaim¬
ed in the French Declaration of the
Rights of Man civil' equality, freedom
of thought and conscience, freedom of
the press, the right to property, the
right to freedom of assembly and asso¬
ciation, freedom of teaching, the right
to education free of charge, and invio¬
lability of domicile and correspondence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 1954
PORT-AU-PRINCE was founded by the French in 1749 but two earthquakes and a icore of devastating
fires have left little of the original French colonial city. Among the city's imposing public buildings are the
Palace of Justice (above) and National Assembly (below). (Photos Haitian Tourist Office and Denise Colomb.)
The legislator has striven to protect
these rights by all the necessary guar¬
antees.
Are these guarantees effective in
practice? It would be hypocrisy to claim
that they are.
The machinery set up by our various
Constitutions has never really cor¬
responded to reality, because the public
does not, in practice, pay sufficient
respect to constitutional principles.
Except at a few junctures in our history,
our institutions have functioned un¬
evenly; the machine creaks, the springs
groan, and principles are sometimes
" curiously deformed in the process of
their application. .
This is not to imply that the Haitian
people are incapable of self-government.
Such a conclusion could be reached by
no one at all familiar with the history of
the political development of nations.
Those versed in the secrets of the
militant policy of certain States that are
regarded as the most advanced and
democratic in the world know what often
lies behind the deceptive façade of
parliamentary institutions. The point _
in favour of the Haitian people is this:'
the democratic instinct is- so firmly rooted
in them that it has enabled them to
resist all attempts at absolutist govern¬
ment made throughout their stormy
history.
To this resistance must be ascribed
most of those violent reactions which we
are pleased to call revolutions. The
Haitian people may undergo the tyranny
of a dictator for long periods, but they
.will never accept it.
The experience of over a century has
convinced the Haitian people that, in
order to guarantee the internal pro¬
tection of human rights, it is not enough
merely to embody noble democratic
principles in the country's Constitution.
Public opinion and customs must be
strong enough to impose respect for
those rights, and their impartial ap¬
plication must be guaranteed by in¬
stitutions that" are firmly established.
The first of these institutions is the
Law, which, to ' be effective, must be
administered by persons of real com¬
petence, complete independence and
absolute integrity. Those responsible for
prejudicing human rights are usually
persons who fail to understand that
'freedom stops at the point where the
next man's freedom begins'. Such
attacks on the rights of others should be
tried by courts which are open to all
without distinction; the law must be the
same for everyone, and the courts must
enjoy the confidence of all, plaintiffs and
defendants alike.'
Privileges abused
T T often happens that the Executive,
-* with armed forces at its disposal,
takes action which infringes the free¬
dom of the individual and other funda¬
mental human freedoms. There must
be honest, independent judges to con¬
demn such acts. And in cases where the
Legislative itself abuses its privileges
.and passes measures contrary to consti
tutional law or international treaties,
such measures must be proclaimed in¬
valid on the ground that they infringe
the Constitution.
In principle, a country's Constitution
and the laws deriving therefrom are
confined to determining the rights and
duties of .that particular country's
nationals. But ideas have so progressed
that a purely "national" approach in this
matter is no longer possible; it is the in¬
ternational rights of man that now have
to be established.
Haiti, a signatory of both the Act of
Chapultepec and the San Francisco
Charter, was one of the first to ratify
these two international instruments.
The Act of Chapultepec gave birth to the
Organization of American States, and
the San Francisco Charter to the United
Nations. It was under the aegis of these
two great organizations to which, from
the outset, Haiti has belonged that in¬
struments such as the American
Declaration of the Rights and Duties of
Man, signed at Bogota on 2 May 1948,
and the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights, issued at Paris on 10 December
1948, were adopted.
The international treaties and con¬
ventions to which Haiti has subscribed
have added, to the traditional rights and
obligations recognized by all Consti¬
tutions, a number of new duties, in¬
cumbent upon the modern State by
reason of mankind's social evolution.
(Continued on page 32)
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
HAIT
AND
The League of Nations at Geneva
though founded upon a sincere de¬
sire for peace, could not prevent the
destruction of peace. Born out of war, it
foundered in war. Bringing together
men of goodwill from every country and
race, it was yet unable to prevent private
egoism and partisan intolerance from
entering its counsels. Designed to
smooth off awkward corners, clear up
misunderstandings and establish a pro¬
visional code of law, but lacking the
means of implementing its decisions, it
went from one compromise to another,
undermined by unsated imperialism and
revivals of Caesarism which doomed
magnanimous resolutions and impas¬
sioned speeches to oblivion.
The United Nations Organization as
conceived and created at San Francisco
looking out over the Pacific with its
frightful memories of Hiroshima yet
undimmed is, like its predecessor, a
product of victory.
It should be recognized, however, that
United Nations is far better equipped
to deal with the problems that confront¬
ed the League at Geneva than ta settle
some of those of the new world.
What this new world exactly is has not
yet come to light. Yet it speaks through
different voices in all the languages of
Jean F. Brlerre is<one of Haiti's noted writers
and poets. For several years he has followed
closely the work of the United Nations and jiarti-
ciiluilij the Technical Assistance ¡iroyramme of
Ihr I iiitrd Rations in Haiti.
.the earth; Mrs. Vijaya Pandit, President
of the United Nations General Assembly,
knows it and supports its cause ; it uses
dialects which few can understand and
none can properly translate ; it is there,
alive and strong, despite barbed wire and
interdicts, taboos and disparagement.
The United Nations must take care not
to be surpassed by the clear and simple
aspirations often voiced from its plat¬
form by speakers who may lack the
international reputation of an - Eden,
Stassen, Churchill or Bidault, but who
brush aside prejudices and out-of-date
ideas and speak a new language, searing
as a flame, startling as a cry, announcing
a new future at our gates, a future that
may astound many but cannot be
questioned or ignored.
All the '"underprivileged" in the
world, whatever their" race, colour or
-culture, realize the undeniable truth of
Pearl Buck's statement which should
preface every history book that the
world possesses enough wheat, food and
agricultural resources in general to
prevent any man going hungry. The
United Nations knows it so well that in
the economic sphere it has its own
Technical Assistance organ a body of
people who are experts in all branches
of its activity, a "'brains trust" selected
from among specialists throughout the
world, who have a wide knowledge of
population, feeding and natural
resources problems and who know men's
reactions to drought and want, their
reactions in the presence of birth and
death.
THE UN
By Jean F. Brierre
In an address to the Haitian people,
delivered on 24 October 1953, the repre¬
sentative of the United Nations in Haiti
defined the rôle of Technical Assistance
as follows :
"In the economic and social field, the
rôle of the United Nations is to discover
how best to improve the standard of
living, establish greater justice for all
and promote a better use of natural
resources, so as to create the interna¬
tional atmosphere requisite for the
maintenance of peace and co-operation
among men."
This clear-cut statement, no longer is
a mere wish but a concrete policy. As
Mr. Seynès, France's representative at
the United Nations, authoritatively said,
"the programme of Technical Assis¬
tance... has done more than any other
programme to bring the message of the
United Nations not only to governments,
but to the whole world." For it is
obvious, even to the uninitiated, that in
political matters the peoples are surpris¬
ed to receive messages from the 'great
Federation of Nations which they cannot
understand because, amid the painful
realities of the moment, such messages
do not explain the exact meaning of the
battle which the United Nations is
assumed to be waging against man's
most terrible enemies.
Technical Assistance on the other
hand, which is financed by voluntary
contributions from member states,
implies respect for "the minimum obli¬
gation contracted by the States in
signing the San Francisco Charter.""
m
av:
*4>
W W&
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N° 2 - 1954
»-
"For the first time in the history of the
world", Mr. Seynès points out,
struggle against poverty and hunger has
been recognized as an international
responsibility, and the Technical Assis¬
tance programme is the first attempt
effectively to discharge that responsibi¬
lity."
We no longer ask, today, what are the
real causes of poverty and hunger. We
simply affirm that the programme of
technical assistance for the nations of
the world is an immense step towards
an exact knowledge and an appropriate
solution of the great problems- of our
civilization. And in Haiti we have seen
it in action in many fields.
Marbial. A great deal has been written
about the Unesco pilot project in the
Marbial Valley. It has been denounced
,more often than defended in our country
where, in the past, experts have often
been regarded with legitimate suspicion.
Many people have asserted that Marbial
was a failure, without taking the trouble
to go and see it with their own eyes and
to discuss the question scientifically.
As the word "pilot project" indicates,
Marbial was an experiment. In a given
community one of the poorest and
most heavily afflicted by ignorance,
poverty and soil erosion it was planned
to establish contact with the people and
to help them to understand and solve
their problems.
A preliminary enquiry conducted by a
true friend of our people, Alfred Metraux,
and by Haitians of undisputed merit
such as Dr. Jeanne Sylvain, E. Berrouet
and Mrs. Jean Combaire, resulted in a
report of real scientific value entitled
"Making a living in the Marbial Valley "
which should have been widely circulat¬
ed, not only to give an idea of what has
been achieved in this region, but to
accustom the Haitian to taking thought
for his own people by revealing to him
this sombre, unknown figure of the
peasant who is too often victimized by
disease, poverty and ignorance.
When men who were yesterday ignor¬
ant and uneducated can today meet
and discuss their community problems ;
when one of them can direct the pro¬
ceedings at a co-operative meeting, as is
done anywhere in the world ; when a
whole community realizes and then
combats the dangers of erosion or of
microbes ; when it decides to build a
road and starts work on it in no lan¬
guage can that be called a failure, for
the people of Marbial have emerged
from the experience regenerated. Some
mistakes, admittedly, were made. A
pottery project was begun in an area
where there was no clay, and a firing
oven was bought without regard to the
local type of electric current. Yet
Marbial has provided a lesson. It has
supplied leaders for the locality and for
the rest of the territory.
Rural industries. Ours is a country
where refuse has never been utilized and
has served merely to pollute the air. At
the request of the Haitian Government,
a United Nations expert is now planning
the construction of a plant for the
conversion of refuse into manure. The
benefit that our agriculture would derive
from such a project is obvious.
The work done by Mr. Glen Lukens
These drawings were done by Alix Roy for a
special "Artisans Calendar" produced by the Audio-
Visual Unit of Haiti's Dept. of National Economy.
and Miss Laura Nadal, for the develop¬
ment of handcraft skills should be men¬
tioned. The former, a ceramics expert
whose high professional standards are
known to me personally, has trained
others to replace him, both at Lafond
and at Jacmel ; and many peasant
families are today using baked clay
utensils made by their children at the
Lukens School.
Miss Nadal, a wickerwork and weaving
expert, has, besides passing on her own
skilled techniques, stressed the market-
- ing problem and the importance of high
quality and standardized products. She
has made her pupils alive to the question
of gross cost and profit, and instructors
trained by her are now capable " of
calculating cost prices.
The development of industries based
on local fibres should infuse new blood
into the people's economic life.
Tanning. The skins prepared by the
Jacmel peasants are now among the best
in Haiti. Soaking, softening, milling,
unhairing, finishing and dressing have
all been taught scientifically. Some of
the most valuable work has been that
done by Mr. René Azémar. The ins¬
truction he gave with the aid of tools
and hides found locally, has produced
tangible results. It is to be hoped that
the services of those who have benefited
from this instruction will be employed
for the good of the community.
Reforestation. The acute problem
of erosion has been attacked with in¬
creasing success by M. Vinton Burns in
collaboration with the Department ot
(Continued on page 32)
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Harri today
About 50 miles to the southeast of Cuba, and ranking next in
size among the islands of the West Indies, lies tropical Hispaniola.
Its territory is shared by Haiti and the Dominican Republic (see
map page 2). Haiti's population is estimated at about 3,000,000,
or about 295 persons per square mile, a density greater than that
of China or India, or any other republic in the Americas. About
83 % live in rural areas, noncentrated on the most productive
slopes, valleys and plains. ' About 90 % of the people are Negroes,
the remaining 10 % are mulattoes.
Cric? - Crac! - 'Shall I tell you a story?'
THE Haitians are great story tellers. When a group
gathers and a story is about to begin, the teller says,
"Cric?"that is, "Shall I tell you a story?" and the reply
comes back, "Crac!"or, "Go ahead, we're listening". There
are thousands of "Cric? Crac!" folk-tales current in Haiti
today. The most popular characters of these are simple-
minded Boqui and his inseparable companion, clever Malice.
These stories are told in colourful Creole, a language derived
from French and where words are often doubled with
charming effect. Thus, ioun bel, bel femme an extraordinarily
beautiful woman; U té ben, ben malade he was very gravely ill;
U mâ'ché, l'mâ'ché, l'mâ'ché kept on walking and walking.
Few countries possess a richer folklore heritage than Haiti's
which goes back thousands of years to Africa.
Haitian folklore is especially rich in proverbs.
Here are a few :
fer couper fer You need iron to cut iron, or, great needs
demand great remedies.
Tit cochon tit sang little pig has little blood, or, from each
according to his means.
Others are: "Rotten teeth are strong only on rotten bananas";
"Experience is the staff of the blind." One Haitian was heard
to say, "Nègue riche li mulatte; mulatte pauv' li nègue" the
rich Negro is a mulatto; the poor mulatto is a Negro." This
is a profound comment on an important social problem in
Haiti even today.
Zombi tales are another important aspect of Haitian folklore.
The belief in the possibility of producing the appearance of
death indirectly through plants and drugs, is very widespread
among the Haitian masses. But even houngans the Vodun
priests assert that the practice is absolutely impossible.
African slaves had brought with them from Africa their pri¬
mitive beliefs and superstitions, some of which were later incor¬
porated into a cult called Vodun or Voodoo. The coexistence
of Catholicism and Vodun in Haiti and the frequent sensational
accounts of Vodun practices by unscrupulous foreign commen¬
tators have produced varied reactions in Haitian writers.
Some such as Georges Sylvain gave historical reasons for its
continuation. Others, like the great writer and poet Jacques
Roumain have attempted to explain it in terms of the Haitian
peasants' isolation, the inaccessibility of church and school.
It would be difficult to deny that Vodun contains a mixture of
charlatanism and superstition.
The End of. Yaws
OF Haiti's health problems, one authority has written:
"It would probably not be far from the truth to say that
for two centuries the majority of Haitian Negroes have
been afflicted to a greater or lesser degree with malaria,
hookworm, and yaws, either singly or together. Next to these
dire diseases comes a group which seems to have affected
from a tenth to one half the population; tuberculosis, dysentry,
enteritis and granular conjunctivitis."
Camille Lhérisson, one of Haiti's leading doctors, said some
years ago: "People do not die of hunger, but rather of the
diseases which accompany malnutrition."
During the past two decades, there "has been a strengthening
of the health services, new hospitals, clinics, and dispensaries
have been opened and better use made of existing ones and
water supplies have been improved.
(Continued on page 16)
I) D. H. Toy/or Ottawa; 2,3) D. Colomb, Paris; 4) Haitian Tourist Office.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N' 2 - 1954
WOMEN OFTEN TRANSPORT THE
MOST INCREDIBLE LOADS BALANCED
ON THEIR HEADS.
L
BOB
2 ;-4J-'
A HAITIAN COMBITE, THE TRADITIONAL CO-OPERATIVE OF NEIGHBOURHOOD PEASANTS, GATHERS TO BUILD A NEW HOUSE.
HANDICRAFT INDUSTRY IS EXPANDING. GOODS PRODUCED STRAW HATS, SISAL HANDBAGS, FURNITURE, CARVINGS ETC.
AT THE FOOD MARKET, RICE, MEAL, BEANS, ARE PILED ON MATS. . USUAL MEASURING DEVICES ARE TIN CANS OR BUCKETS.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
HAITI TODAY (Cont'd)
Today, therefore, the rural people are learning that " even
though there may not be a dispensary or a doctor within easy
reach there is much they can do to prevent diseases. They
are being shown how to drain swamps where malarial mosquitos
breed. Fundamental education lessons teach them elementary
health precautions as applied to food, water, the prevention of
infection and the disposal of refuse. They are made to realise
too that a full stomach does not necessarily provide sufficient
nourishment to maintain good health.
In the past two years the greatest victory over disease has
been the almost complete wiping out of the loathsome running-
sore disease of yaws. ~ This has been achieved during a nation¬
wide campaign, in which the World Health Organization co¬
operated, by giving one single injection of penicillin to more
than 2,600,000 people. If similarly effective action could be
taken against malaria and hookworm, a major obstacle to
Haiti's' progress would be removed.
The Vanishing Soil
HAITI is primarily an agricultural country. Because of the
mountain-and-plain character of the land and the varying
rainfall and water supply, agriculture has developed in
fairly distinct zones: coffee is cultivated on the humid mountain
slopes ; sugar-cane in all irrigated plains; bananas in the plains
and well drained slopes; cotton on the semi-arid plateaus and
plains. However, the Haitian farmer is extremely poor, much of
the land is worn out and the earth has been "bled to the bone".
Erosion, small-holdings and over-population these are the
three main and closely interrelated causes for -the decay of the
rural areas. An extreme, but by no means rare case is the
Valley of Marbial, in the south of Haiti, where Unesco set up a
fundamental education pilot project. In a report on conditions
in Marbial, published in 1951, this is what the anthropologist
Dr. Alfred Metraux, had to say: "The earth in a land deforested
and converted into savanna, has become a brittle substance.
Exhausted by two harvests a year and stripped by erosion, the
soil of Marbial is dying. With every rainy season, hundreds of
tons of humus are swept down by the rivers to the sea. 'That is
our life ebbing away', say the peasants as they watch it go." ,
But since that report was written a change has taken place
in Haiti. - In Marbial, the peasant has found that his precious
top soil need not be swept down the mountain during the rainy
season. He has been shown how to terrace the land; how to
alternate rows of food-bearing plants with rows of grass to
hold down the earth. To replace the lost trees he has been
given seedlings which are cultivated in nurseries and then
planted on the denuded hillsides. - The efforts to save the soil
and increase its yield which have been made in Marbial are
also taking place in other parts of Haiti as part of the five year
development plan, stressing agriculture, which was announced
by President Magloire in 1951. Technical aid has been given by
the U.N. Food and Agriculture Organization.
The most ambitious feature of the plan is the damming of
Haiti's biggest (and only main) river, the central Artibonite,
and the irrigation of some 80,000 acres that are now dusty desert
in the dry season and muddy lakes during the rains. It is
planned to distribute the controlled waters of the Artibonite
through canals so as to better the lives of 160,000 peasants. The
main plan of the Haitian Government also calls for agricultural
schools, the co-operative use of tractors, a farmers' bank, re¬
forestation grain storage and the construction of roads to link-
farmers with the markets.
Knowledge to Reshape a Land
SINCE the declaration of. independence, Haiti has attempted
to organize a complete educational system but efforts have
been hindered by lack of funds and the shortage of
teachers. Illiteracyestimated at 80 to 90 % still casts a
gigantic shadow over the peasant masses. Vocational edu¬
cation, so important for training skilled workers, is a relative
newcomer in the educational system.
Until recently there was a great difference between urban and
rural education. Urban schools, modelled after French edu¬
cation and using imported textbooks, were little adapted to
local requirements; rural schools, run by the" Department of
Agriculture, have sought to link curriculum to peasant life and
(Continued1 on page 33)
A TYPICAL RURAL HOUSE IN HAITI. HAS ONE ROOM, BARE.
FINE HAND-MADE EMBROIDERY FOR SALE IN PORT-AU-PRINCE MARKET.
Credits: 1,2,3 H.D. Toy/or, Ottowa ; 4) Haitian Tourist. Office ; 5) UN.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 - 1954
DIRT FLOOR, WOOD FRAME AND A THATCHED ROOF. HAITI NEEDS MORE SCHOOLS, -MORE TEACHERS,. A MORE MODERN CURRICULUM
.A TYPICAL FOLKLORE DANCE. HAITIANS DELIGHT IN SINGING AND DANCING. SUGAR-CANE IS ONE OF THE CHIEF EXPORTS. FINE QUALITY RUM IS MADE FROM CANE JUICE-
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 - 1954
MULTIPLYING CITIES
THE SWIFT-CHANGING MAP OF URBAN DEVELOPMENT
by Charles Morazé
HAT is civilization,? A strange question it may seem to
ask in connexion with the three maps published here
for the first time. But is it really so strange and
unrelated? Is it not true that most of the magnificent and
fascinating objects of the past that draw millions of ordinary
people to museums every year have come from sites which bear
the marks of organized communities?
Even when an archaeological site of ancient objects is dis¬
covered in an area now totally desert or completely rural, it
always points to a city, a centre of human activity, a converging
point of trade or some social grouping.
No one would deny that agriculture and work on the land
have always occupied an enormous and indispensable portion
of human activity and continue to do so today. But urban
centres have been so singularly important in the development of
human intercommunication, in the elaboration of such great
instruments as languages, systems of numeration, calendars, the
tools of countless trades, and in the creation of works of art
(whether for religion or just for the sake of plain beauty) that
Charles Moraré ¡s a member of the faculty of the Institute of Political
Studies, university of Paris.
one can well ask if the history of the development of cities is
not practically synonymous with the history of the development
of civilizations. Centres of religion, centres of art, centres of
learning and politics, these all bear the characteristic stamp of
city life.
Have cities always had the same importance, and can their
importance be gauged by their size or population ? Who would
venture to say that because Detroit, Lyons and Odessa have
more inhabitants they are more important than was the little
city of Athens at the foot of the Parthenon ?
The three maps showing the growth of the world's cities give
us, therefore, no more than a tiny glimpse of a long history, and
even this is quite narrow and restricted. Yet there is much that
these maps can tell us with their round dots charting the surface
of our planet in the short span of 150 years.
Leaving to one side the nature of urban influence on civili¬
zation which would make a fascinating study in itself, there is
one major thing that stands out at a glance ; the tremendous
increase in the number of cities in the past century and a half.
In my opinion' this is a revolutionary development and marks a
stage in man's history as important as were the metal age and
the alphabet at the dawn of civilization. For huge conglom¬
erations, tentacular cities expanding at amazing speed pose
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE CHANGING MAP
OF CITY
DEVELOPMENT
(Cont'd)
THE NEW PERSPECTIVE. Air
view of New York reveals new
urban "façade". Here is no indivi¬
dual building, street or neighbour¬
hood, but the whole city, and with
it a revelation of its composition. It
is typical of the unplanned town of
"the 19th and 20th centuriesa
jumbling-together of industrial,
commercial and residential struc¬
tures. The smoke of its factories
reduces the sunshine by almost
40 per cent. Greater New York
comprises today I 2 million people,
the largest population of any urban
region in the world. (World Wide)
STAGES OF URBANIZATION
THE URBAN NUCLEUS.
In most cases the village
formed the urban nucleus.
It is situated harmoniously
within the landscape. Roads
connect it with other villages
and with farms more or less
evenly distributed through¬
out the country. Popu¬
lation distribution was far
more satisfactory than it
became in the industrial era.
«
J**i > >-*
*&*
3 .«f£<Sfc )
¿TjL
i nt
-"V!
'vi
_
THE EARLY INDUS¬
TRIAL TOWN. Factories
are being erected partly near
the railway line, partly near
the river wherever the
landowner pleases. People .
of the surrounding villages
and farms are flocking to
the city, and with the de¬
population, of the surround¬
ing countryside grows the
overpopulation of the city.
Reproduced from " X-ray the
City 1 " Copyright by the author,
Dr. Ernest Fooks Published by
The Ruskin Press, Melbourne.
THE RAILWAYS COME.
Railroads have caused one
of the most revolutionary
changes in urban develop¬
ment. The growth of urban
population of the last century
follows closely the develop¬
ment and growth of the
means of modern transpor¬
tation: the railroad, the mo¬
tor car and truck, the aero¬
plane, and of water traffic.
,>*'
^ S : &
"A<Ko^V ^
problems of so complex a nature that
only the most evolved techniques can
hope to solve them.
To take only one example, an incred¬
ible concentration of foodstuffs is required
to keep alive the mass of city dwellers
squeezed into a tiny sterile area : swift,
sure highways are needed to siphon agri¬
cultural products into the towns and
permit the farmer to sell his surplus; the
. cities in turn must produce articles
which will attract the farmer in ex¬
change for the food he supplies. Thus
the growth of cities goes hand in hand
with a tremendous general development,
implying advances in agriculture, indus¬
try, commerce, inventions with their
roots reaching out into science and all
fields of human experience.
It is also true that certain cities have
expanded so rapidly that they seem to
have forgotten the need for beauty, and
the unprecedented growth of urban
developments generally has therefore
given rise to a whole series of new prob¬
lems of aesthetics, such as town
planning, slum clearance, etc.
Thus the three maps offer many possi¬
bilities for study. They show that a new
era which began at the end of the 18th
century has' opened in the history of
town development. It is a pity that no
similar maps exist of earlier centuries
for these would enable us to get a better
picture of the evolution of the world's
"cities and the rise and decline of certain
cultural centres. But such maps are no
easy matter to draw up, and would pro-
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER N» 2 - 1954
bably show no major development in any
way comparable to that of the past
150 years. They would show clearly
when certain cities were great in the
past "even though they have diminished
in size and importance in recent times.
Thus, Baghdad was no more than a
small town of a few thousand inhabi¬
tants in 1800 yet in the great age of
Islam, it was one of the largest and most
fascinating cities in the world. The same
is true of Samarkand, or Ispahan and
many of the mighty cities which once
dotted the great routes leading from the
East to the West through Central Asia.
It is doubtful whether the" ancient
cities of America could rival these in
splendour, except perhaps the extraordi¬
nary remains of Chitchen-Itza, in Yuca¬
tan, or Cuzco, in. Peru. Nevertheless,
subject to these reservations, the map
for 1800 would give us a fairly accurate
picture of the relative density of cities
several centuries ago, if we ,'merely make
a few additions in the White areas and
a few deletions in some of the black
areas (particularly in Western Europe).
The spread of urban settlement is a
recent phenomenon, and may be briefly
analysed as follows : there are two great
zones of city development to the West
and East of the Europe-Asia land mass.
This is indicated on the 1800 map by the
different shading used for the two zones,
black for the west and grey for the East.
The cities, in fact, differ very consider¬
ably in type. The cartographer has used
different symbols because, while Europe
in 1800 already had some rudimentary
statistics, there was nothing on the same
scale or of the same significance in the
East.
As early as the 18th century, Europe
had begun to take an interest in the prob¬
lems of population trends which was
to lead to the periodic censuses now
considered so essential. But though pre¬
cise figures are lacking, certain Eastern
cities must have been much larger than
the great capitals of Europe. Pekin, the
city of cities, or Tokyo, must have been
more densely populated than London or
Paris.
An 18th century French traveller tells
us that China had seven cities larger
than Paris. But, while in the West these
cities were still young and expanding
rapidly and more or less systematically
with the development of a new industrial
economy, the great cities of the East
were already ancient. They consisted of
a number of different quarters carrying
on a variety of distinct activities, so that
they were more like conglomerations of
large villages than cities proper. In cen¬
tral Eurasia, there must have been large
floating urban populations following the
king from city to city, moving along the
roads of religious pilgrimages or the
great highways of commerce.
We should also note that, between the
Far East, which apparently was mari¬
time, and the extreme West, which cer¬
tainly was, the towns in the central part
of Europe and Asia were essentially conti¬
nental, indicating that the desert and
the land routes were, then, more reliable
channels of civilization than the sea
routes. But by 1800, maritime trade be¬
gan to change ' the emphasis and thus
the distribution of important cities.
The old inland route city of Trichinopoly
in southern India thus saw Madras rise
and prosper on the east coast.
This development of large-scale world
trade, which also accounts for the estab¬
lishment of Batavia, Singapore, Hong
Kong and Honolulu on the Asian sea¬
board and in the Pacific was coupled
with the amazing growth of cities and
the urban way of life in Europe. For,
while Europe shipped people, capital and
its economic skills to every corner of the
world, its own cities multiplied, espe¬
cially along the broad corridor running
from densely populated England to the
head of the Adriatic. The Rhine valley
was transformed into a gigantic tho¬
roughfare of towns, criss-crossed by
powerful railroad Unes, postal and tele¬
graph services, which speeded business
transactions and encouraged competition
and even bitter rivalry.
From Europe, the great upsurge of
cities spread across the Atlantic. In 1800,
as the map shows, the only great metro¬
politan centre on the American conti¬
nent was Mexico City. By 1900 it had
lost its proud place (if not its historical
prestige), to the mighty cities blackening
(Continued on page 33)
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
PARIS TV AUDIENCES have
recently been getting an entirî^r^
new view of their city's museums
through a series of imaginative
programmes entitled "Jewels of
Paris" in which music, opera,
folklore, ballet and poetry have
brought museum exhibits to life
in an exciting way. Later this
year when a planned international
TV - relay network comes into
operation it will be possible for
people of eight, European coun¬
tries to exchange programmes and
to get to know one another
better. Photos on this page were
taken during a TV gala programme
staged in the- Louvre Museum at
the foot of the Winged Victory of
Samothrace." Through telecasts of
this kind, countries linked by TV
will be able to share their art
treasures with their neighbours.
(Photos Télévision Française.)
One evening in July, 1952, we
were relaxing in the sitting
room oí one of those two-
family brick houses which are
so typical of London's residential dis¬
tricts. Everything was there, the aspi¬
distra plant in the bay window, the
plush-covered easy 'chairs and, of
course, the television set. The pro¬
gramme for the evening: A visit to
Paris. The cameras took us first to the
studio of a painter in the artist district
of Montmartre. Then came a visit to
the Louvre. We saw the statues of
Michelangelo and religious sculptures
of the Middle Ages. To close the visit,
we went down into one of the "caves",
so characteristic of Paris student life,-
where young people danced to the
vibrating rhythm of jazz, and long¬
haired femmes fatales sang of the lives
and loves of Old Paris.
When we turned the set off, we
kneW that we had witnessed an his¬
toric event. We had caught a glimpse
of a new way for man to communicate
with man, across the barriers of lan-
THE CAMERA focuses on sculptures at the Guimet
Museum of Asian Art in Paris. In this French TV
programme actors helped to give movement and
meaning to museum exhibits. A camera coverage
of Chinese figurines, for example, faded into a
Chinese girl telling one of her country's 18 th
' century fables. (Photo Télévision Française).
guage and of frontiers. European tele¬
vision has come a long way since this
beginning, and international communi¬
cation is taking on a new reality as
plans for future co-operation are put
into practice.
Breaking a barrier
What struck us most, as we
watched the broadcast from
the Louvre, was the ability of
television to overcome lan¬
guage barriers. Here we saw two
commentators, an Englishman and a
Frenchman (for the programme was
seen simultaneously in France), who
alternately described the Works of art.
If this had been ' radio, the English
audience would have felt itself com¬
pletely shut out while the French com¬
mentator spoke. But in television,
viewers 'appreciated having more time
to look at the sculptures without having
to listen to the commentary. While
there was some criticism of this
method as being too cumbersome, the
broadcast left no doubt that pictures
can form a bridge between' nations
where sound alone would have failed.
The next step forward was taken in
June 1953 when the Coronation cere¬
monies were broadcast from London
simultaneously to four countries on the
Continent, to France, Belgium, the
Netherlands and Germany. A million
French people watched an English
Queen being crowned. Once more
everything became easy to understand
because Frenchmen were doing the
commentary to the picture, the same-
picture seen by television audiences in
England, Holland and Germany and
accompanied by commentaries in each
of their languages.
The temporary relay network which
made this broadcast possible was the
fruit of long preparations and- con¬
siderable engineering ingenuity. The.
principal difficulty was that the broad¬
cast standard in the participating
countries differs basically. A televi¬
sion picture in England is made up of
405 lines. But in France the picture
consists of 810 lines, while the Nether¬
lands and "Germany have 625 lines.
It had been thought that these differ¬
ences would constitute insuperable
obstacles to international television
broadcasts, just as different railroad
gauges make it impossible for trains
to travel from one system to the other
without special adaptation.
But engineers succeeded in "convert¬
ing" .the broadcasts. The first suc¬
cessful conversion took place between
England and France across the Chan¬
nel in 1051. The second step Was the
broadcast of a week's programmes'
from Paris to Great Britain, climaxed
by the July 14th celebration held in
1052. The third step was the multi-,
national relay of the Coronation cere¬
monies from England to the Continent
in 1953. . And the fourth step will be
the two-way exchange of programmes'
between Great Britain, -France, Bel¬
gium, the Netherlands, Germany, Swit¬
zerland and Italy, and possibly Den-'
mark, planned for June 1954.
How others live
Here is an ambitious goal : the
' establishment of a permanent
(and very costly) relay network
which links in two-way com¬
munication eight countries speaking
between them six different languages,
using four different definitions of the
television picture and having young
television organizations, many of which
are" only learning how to produce pro¬
grammes for their own audience, let
alone for other countries.
The eight countries will each pro¬
duce one programme designed to give
a picture of their own country, and all
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 - 1954
of them will during the same period
carry broadcasts of the international
football championship games which
will be played in Switzerland. A new
approach will be tried out this time to
overcome the language difficulties. In
none of the broadcasts will there ap¬
pear people who speak in their own
tongue directly to the camera. In¬
stead, the programmes will be narrated
What interests viewers in these coun¬
tries is to see the life of Madame Du¬
pont or Mr. Smith, the way they make
both ends meet, what they can buy on
the market, what amusements they
enjoy, how they bring up their child¬
ren, how they work in railroad sta¬
tions or factories, in fashion salons or
on farms. And then, of course, view¬
ers want to see the best shows each-
Mît
S .*-..!" .-A? *£S
by unseen commentators whose words
will be translated into the language of
the country receiving the broadcast.
And what do these countries Want to
show to each other? Are they setting
up such an elaborate network only for
the broadcast of national ceremonies
and spectacular events? Whether you
talk to British or French, to German or
Dutch producers of television program¬
mes, you always get the same answer :
we want to see how other people live
and show them a slice of our own life.
f
m *
country can produce, the .best enter¬
tainment. There is going to be a Eu¬
ropean competition for the applause of
the European viewer.
The French television audience had
a taste of this new feature of interna¬
tional television When "Cafe Conti¬
nental", a BBC television show, was
broadcast as part of the programmes
carried during the Coronation period.
In this programme English viewers
have seen, for instance, German acro¬
bats and Austrian dancers, Dutch ma
gicians and French singers, as well as
British entertainers. The entertainers
are introduced by a French girl who
lives in London and Whose French
accent is loved by English viewers.
This show is good television in Eng¬
land. But it is also good entertain¬
ment elsewhere. In fact, it drives
home, in its own way, that peoples are
not so different whatever _ their lan¬
guage.
Pooling Programmes
Tins international exchange serves
a double purpose. Not only does
it seek to promote better under¬
standing between nations, but it
meets the serious problems which each
individual European country finds in
trying to produce an adequate number
of good programmes for its own
audience. Everywhere there is a
shortage of money, a shortage of
artists and a shortage of good ideas
and scripts. Europeans point out
that television has developed success1
fully in- the United States on what
amounts in fact to a continental scale.
They hope that similarly the great
human and artistic resources of
Europe will aid them in making a
greater success of television on this
continent.
Television is going to teach us much
about the other fellow and about our¬
selves, and not all that we will learn
will be favouiable or welcome. But
such is life and such are the relations
between individuals' and nations. If
television gives us a chance to find Out
more about others, to' adjust ourselves
better to them, to learn that underneath
the differences there is an even great¬
er community, it will have contributed
its share.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Racial
Crossroads
of the Pacific
by Harry L Shapiro
Race mixture has had a
field day in Hawaii.
Polynesians, aU kinds '
and degrees of Europeans
and Americans, Puerto Ri¬
cans, Chinese, Japanese, Ko¬
reans, Filipinos, not to men¬
tion smaller contingents of
other populations, have met
here and produced a bewil¬
dering array of hybrids. The
extraordinary fact about all
this extraordinary in the
light of conditions in many
other areas of race mixture
is the relative absence
¿j here of friction, prejudice or
Ü social rejection.
There is no colour bar in
Hawaii and no legal disability
based on race, although
contact between the same
races elsewhere has given rise to them. Why, one might ask,
has Hawaii become the seat of such an amicable arrangement?
The answer it seems to me, lies in the history of the Hawaiian
islands and in their relation to the imperialism of the Western
World.
When Captain Cook discovered the islands in 1778, he found
' them populous and administered by a strong feudal-like system.
He made no attempt to claim them for Britain: in fact he was
murdered by the natives and his expedition withdrew. 'By the
time Vancouver and subsequent expeditions reached Hawaii,
the islands had become consolidated or were rapidly becoming
so under the rule of Kamehameha I.
Thus, in the early nineteenth century, when European powers
were seizing every scrap of unclaimed territory to which they
had access, the Hawaiian islands were able to resist these ma¬
neuvres, since they were governed by a strong monarchical
government capable of maintaining its hegemony over the
islands. There was no political vacuum inviting imperial
Professor Harry L. Shapiro is Chairman of the Department of Anthropo¬
logy, American Museum of Natural History, New York. He is one of the
leading authorities in the United States on race 'mixture und the author of
the rolnine "Race Muture" just published by Unesco. {Pnce: $.¿j, 1/6, 75 fr.)
pom which the article on this pai/e is taken.
24
Photo New York Times
expansion. Of course, the balance of power in the Pacific played
a part in preserving Hawaiian independence, but where a strong
centralized native government was lacking, as in the Society
Islands, the Marquesas and in many other island archipelagos,
these succumbed to French or British control.
When, therefore, Americans and Europeans began settling in
the Hawaiian islands in the early years of the nineteenth
-century, drawn there by commerce, adventure or missionary
enterprise, they were legally foreigners whose advancement and
prosperity depended on the goodwill of the Hawaiians. To own
and hold land in that feudal society required permission and
special dispensation or possibly marriage with a daughter of a
chief. To pursue missionary work with any hope of success,
the Hawaiian chiefs and royal family had to be won over tact¬
fully and their acquiescence sued for with the respect exacted
by a ruling class.
From the very beginning of this contact with the 'Western
World, therefore, the Hawaiians were in the position of autho¬
rity. Never having been conquered, they remained the masters.
Their chiefs and kings continued to be persons endowed with
power and entitled to the respect and evidence of homage that ,
their traditions demanded. Such a situation created a pattern
of relationship to which the Americans ¡and Europeans had to
conform. And racial tolerance toward the Hawaiian had neces¬
sarily to become an accepted social and official pattern. -
Since the potential and actual wealth of the islands the
land remained in the hands of the native famiUes, intermar¬
riage was frequently 'an economic advantage that brought a
social position to the white man which he might not otherwise
easily achieve. Has children, therefore, would acquire status and
prestige in the beginning not so much from their white ancestry
as from the status and land
they inherited from their
native mothers. Enough of
such marriages took place to
entrench halfcastes firmly in
the upper social and econo¬
mic levels of the population.
With the native race en¬
joying social and economic
dominance, miscegenation
with it could not lead to the
social rejection of the -half-
caste since to do so would
also imply an intolerable re-
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
jection of the Ha¬
waiian as such. , -
' Moreover, the half-
caste had family
connexions With a
rising class7 of
Whites. Thus race
mixture in Hawaii
very early acquired
an - official ac¬
ceptance and, pub¬
licly at least, lpd
to no social seg¬
regation. This
pattern, was ex-,
tremely important
for the far more
numerous offspring
of mixed marriages on lower levels of Hawaiian society, as it
fixed the terms of social tolerance under which they existed.
Later, when Chinese and Japanese labourers for the plan¬
tations began to be imported in large numbers, they entered a
situation where racially at least, official tolerance was
the accepted mode. Social prejudice and economic resentment
against these newcomers did develop and at times became quite
acute, but it could not'degenerate into a crude, open, racial form
since that would have involved the Hawaiians and the part-
Hawaiians. The pattern of racial tolerance had to be -expended
to include all the various races that were joining and mingüng
with the Hawaiian population.
When, in 1900, the Hawaiian Kingdom came to an end and
the islands were annexed by mutual agreement to the United
States, 'the tradition of racial tolerance, established for over a
century, was firmly enough implanted in the HawaUan way of
life to withstand continental influences stemming from diffe¬
rent attitudes. This, at any rate, 'was true up.to World War II,
before the large-scale migration of mainland population . in
connexion with wartime activities took place. Some hints have
come through that the
sudden increase of
settlers conditioned to
another tradition has
to some extent affected
the situation described
above, but these may
merely be reflections
of difficulties from
re-adjustement rather
than indications of a
fundamental change.
While the picture
drawn here of con¬
ditions in Hawaii repre¬
sents an unusually
benign resolution of a
complex Tacial situa¬
tion, it should not
be taken to. imply that
race or race mixture
does not exist as a
factor at all in Ha¬
waiian life. That they
do is obvious from any
careful consideration of
that Ufe.
It must be remem¬
bered, first of all, that
the various racial
groups that entered the
islands as labour re¬
cruitments, came main¬
ly in fairly considerable
numbers. As such, they were settled on plantations where they
naturally tended to form cultural isolates, separated from
Hawaiian Ufe by its unfamiliarity. and by barriers of language.
Moreover, their own tendency was to reproduce in this alien
land the familiar elements of their own culture with all its va¬
lues. Later, as the members of these labour groups were able to
free themselves from plantation Work and to establish
themselves in such urban centres as Honolulu, they generally
settled in tight residential sections where they could continue to
enjoy the cultural security that . close association with one's
fellows gives.
Thus some continuity of racial and cultural identity was
maintained. For the most part it is a voluntary type of segre¬
gation which -has, however, tended to break down to a large
UNESCO COURIER . N» 2 - 1954
degree as acculturation and economic , prosperity permitted.
These racial and cultural entitles serve, as long as they persist,
to act as nuclei for their 'respective groups and to keep alive
some of the traditions brought to the islands. While they contin¬
ue to exist, they also keep alive a social centre that affects the
contacts of their group and their marital patterns.
That some cohesion still exists along these lines is evident
from the in-and-out mariage rates of these racial groups. It is
a fairly general pattern that the immigrants tend to marry
within their own group when partners are available. But, with
continued residence in HawaU, they aU show an increasing
inclination to marry outside the group. The rate with which
this occurs varies from group to group and depends, apparently,
on a number of factors too complicated to go into here.
The outmarriages, however, lare not random, but follow pat¬
terns distinct for each group. To some extent these outmar¬
riages are reflections of opportunity but also of a variety of
cultural and possibly racial attitudes. The striking thing,
however, is that each group reveals a stronger inclination to
marry half-caste Hawaiians than any others when they do
marry outside their own circle. Thus the Chinese are more
likely to marry mixed Chinese-Hawaiian, while the Whites show
an equally per¬
sistent trend to-
w a r d Caucasian-
Hawaiian mixed
bloods in prefer¬
ence to any other
group.
The mixed Ha¬
waiians, thus, by a
steady growth
through pri¬
mary crosses, ' by
intermarriage with
"pure" racial
groups and by their
own high natural
increase, are ex¬
panding at a more
rapid rate than
any other major
contingent of the
population. And
although it is unli¬
kely that all the
groups will be dis¬
solved into one ra¬
cially mixed popu¬
lation in the very
near future, the
present trends
suggest that the
mixed bloods are
destined to become
one of, if not the,
major group in
Hawaii.
"If race mixture enjoyed complete acceptance in the modern
world, its offsprings would ultimately be absorbed by the society
into which they were born and consequently no problem would
exist," says Professor Shapiro, in his study "Race . Mixture",
which has been published by Unesco in the series "The Race
Question in Modern Science". Such, however, is not the case,
and one of the world's racial problems arises from the fact that
mixed bloods very often form a special class and an unabsorbed
element in the populations where they exist. But there are
modern instances of racial mingling that has neither led to a
rigid social stratification nor to any significant friction, preju¬
dice or social rejection, in the article above, Professor. Shapiro,
has described an interesting case in point.
Drawings by Tambi Larsen token from " The Children '
other island territories in the Pacific.
a book on Hawaii .an
ARCHIVES
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
IT WAS COLDER
WHEN WE WERE YOUNGER
RECEDING GLACIERS in Greenland, Alaska, the Alps
and elsewhere are an indication that the average world
temperature is increasing. The base of the Swiss Alpine
glacier shown in the centre of this photo is at. an altitude
of about 6,000 feet. Glacier on left is receding rapidly.
Its base is nearly 1,200 higher. (Photo Swissair.)
THE changes in climate that people
think they experience are seldom
real. Extremes of heat or cold, of
drought or rainfall, occur at intervals,
many years apart. Because those of
childhood seem most dramatic they are
longest remembered, and we are easily
tempted to compare present average
weather with the remembered extremes.
These extremes, however, can be
expected to recur, and do not constitute
a lasting change.
Nevertheless it is now quite certain
that the average temperature of the
inhabited parts of the earth has risen
about 2°F (1°C) 'within the past 100
years, with most of that change since
1890.
This seems a very small change but it
is important. If the average tempera¬
ture of the earth should drop by only
4°F (2°C) ,the glaciers would again
advance from the Poles and eventually
cover large parts of Canada, Northern
Europe and Asia. On the other hand, if
the present process of warming con¬
tinues to the end of this century, the
melting of Arctic ice will cause a rise in
the sea-level that may be troublesome
on many sea-coasts. Over a longer
course of time, this slow rate of change
would transform the earth.
It has happened often in. past ages.
The earth is at least 2,000 million years
old and in that time the temperature
has gone up and down repeatedly. For
about 99 per cent of its existence the
earth was much warmer than now and -
tropical conditions prevailed over most
of the surface. The coal deposits in
England, in Siberia and Alaska, and even
on the Antarctic continent, are the
remains of luxuriant tropical vegetation,
long since extinct. At intervals of about
250 million years there have been relati¬
vely short periods, only a few million
years long, of intense cold when glaciers
covered a large portion of the continents
of the earth. Only ten to twenty
SCIENCE CHRONICLE
by Gerald Wendt
thousand years ago vast sheets of ice
extended from the North Pole down into
Germany and France, and covered all of
Canada and the northern part of the
United States.
We are still in the period ofwarming up
after the last glacial age. In Greenland,
in Alaska, in the Alps and elsewhere the
glaciers are still receding because the
snow that falls in the short and rela¬
tively mild winters does not make up for
the melting of ice during the long, warm
summers. In Spitzbergen the average
winter temperature has risen 18°F
(10°C) since 1910, and the harbour is now
open 200. days .a year. Where records
have been kept the facts are beyond
question. In Philadelphia, the rise in .
temperature has been 4°F (2°C) in the
past century. In Montreal, Canada, in
Britain and in Scandinavia, the increase
has been about 2°F (1°C) since 1850.
The future of many lands depends on
whether. this change will go on and for
how long it.will continue. No one knows
because no one can be sure (why such
changes take place. They may be due
to conditions on '.the sun and a fluc¬
tuation in the amount of heat that
reaches the earth. Or - they may be
caused by a shift in the tilt of the
earth's axis. But there is no definite
evidence for either of these two possibi¬
lities. Most experts agree that they are
caused by changes in the earth's
atmosphere, for which two principal
possibilities have been suggested.
One of these is a change in the activity
of the earth's volcanoes. A really large
volcanic eruption, such as that of the
island of Krakatoa in the East Indies in
August of 1883, throws enormous quan¬
tities of fine ash many miles into the
sky and winds carry the ash to all parts
of the earth to dim the sunlight. After
the eruption of Krakatoa, astronomers at
the Montpellier Observatory in France,
noted a 10 % decrease in the ;amount of
sunshine. For about three years the
thin cloud of volcanic ash apparently
prevented the full strength of the sun
from reaching the earth's surface. The
eruption of Krakatoa, however, was the
last of the great eruptions. So the air
may be clearer now and the sunshine
brighter and hotter. It is possible,
though not very probable, that volcanic
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
ash in the air is the cause of periods of
cooler weather.
Nearly a century ago the British
scientist John Tyndall suggested that
the cause is to be found in the increase
or decrease of carbon dioxide gas in the
atmosphere. This theory was recently
developed by Professor Gilbert N. Plass
of Johns Hopkins University in a radio
broadcast.
Normally, the air contains 0.03 per cent
carbon dioxide. This gas acts somewhat
like the glass roof of a greenhouse
because it is .transparent -to the direct
rays of the sun and lets them strike the
earth and there change into radiant heat
waves. These rays are absorbed by the
carbon dioxide just ',as they are by a
greenhouse roof. They do not. escape
into empty space but remain to warm
the air and thus the earth itself. .
Tons of Co2
INCREASES in the amount of carbon
dioxide in the, air would therefore
result in a warmer climate. And the
fact is that direct measurements of the
carbon dioxide content of the atmos¬
phere tend to show that the. amount has
increased by about 10 per cent during
the past 50 years. That would nicely
account for the increase in the average
temperature.
But the question then becomes: what
causes the carbon dioxide to vary?
There are several possibilities. Green
plants absorb carbon dioxide from the
air and water from the earth and under
the action of sunshine combine them to
make sugars, starches and cellulose and
thus to build their structures. About a
million million tons of carbon dioxide
are thus taken out of the atmosphere
every year in the life process of growing
plants.
But this is not a total loss because the
plants, and the animals that feed upon
them, eventually die and decay and in
decaying the carbon dioxide is reformed
and escapes back to the atmosphere. If
this decay does not occur, as in the
formation of coal where the plants are
buried and protected from decay then
the growth of plants results in a gradual
loss of carbon dioxide from the air.
But only some ten million tons of carbon
dioxide are thus buried in the earth
each year and lost to the atmosphere. It
is a comparatively small amount and
cannot be an important factor.
Weathering rocks
ANOTHER influence on the carbon
dioxide content of the air is geolo¬
gical. The weathering of rocks
and their conversion into soil is to a
large extent an attack upon the rocks
by carbonic acid, the weak acid that
forms when carbon dioxide dissolves in
water. The result is a slow change of
the rocks from silicates to carbonates.
This process takes about 100 million tons
of carbon dioxide from the air every
year. But this process is balanced by
another geological process. Hot springs
and volcanoes pour large quantities of
carbon dioxide into the air, approximate¬
ly 100 milUon tons a year. Thus the
' two geological processes normally count¬
eract each other.
But neither of them is steady. Both
change with the conditions of the earth's
surface. In periods of the 'earth's his¬
tory long ago huge mountain ranges
were raised" so that the surface was
higher and more rugged than now. This
exposed new "rock to weathering and in
such periods the rate of removing carbon
dioxide from the air is greatly increased,
j This means that the heat rays from the
earth can more easily escape into empty
space and the average temperature falls.
The records of the earth's history show
that periods of mountain building were
followed by periods of glacier formation
a few milUon years later.
On the other hand, in those periods
of the earth's history when the land
was generally flat and marshy and
there was less weathering of the rocks,
carbon dioxide tended to accumulate and
the weather during such periods was
tropical. The rise and fall of the average
temperature may thus well depend on
the relative rates at which carbon
dioxide is removed by weathering or is
supplied by springs and volcanoes.
It is interesting that this change in
the carbon dioxide content would also
affect -the amount of rainfall. A cloud
sheds its rain when there is a consider¬
able - difference of temperature between
its lower and upper surfaces. With less
carbon dioxide, the upper surface of the
cloud cools more quickly and thus in¬
creases the rainfall. Periods of low
carbon dioxide are both cooler- and
wetter. Periods of high carbon dioxide
are hotter and dryer.
But there is one new factor that would
increase the carbon dioxide content of
the air. It is an effect of man's activity:
the burning of coal and oil. The carbon
dioxide produced by combustion is much
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 - 1954
larger than is generally reaUzed. The
burning of one ton of coal produces
about two and a half tons of carbon
dioxide. It is estimated that each year
six thousand million tons of carbon
dioxide are poured into the atmosphere,
chiefly by industrial plants. This is a
much larger amount than from any
other cause. If all this additional carbon
dioxide stays in the atmosphere it alone
could account for a temperature rise of
2°F (1°C) in a century. Strange as it
may seem, this is very close to the rate
at which the temperature is actually
rising now. » Thus man himself may be
responsible for the changing climate.
If this is so, and if no other process
appears to counterbalance it, then the
climate of the earth will become contin¬
ually warmer and possibly also dryer
for the next few centuries. This, in turn,
means that crops such as grain, or
grapes which could formerly be grown
only in> southern areas, will become
available much nearer to the Arctic.
Already in Finland and Scandinavia,
farmers are ploughing fields that had
lain under the ice for centuries. In
Canada and Siberia, the area of perma¬
nently frozen ground is retreating
toward the Pole at the rate of a hundred
yards to several miles a year. Time was
when Greenland and Iceland supported
a flourishing culture and grapes could
be cultivated in .England. Such times
are likely to return and vast areas of
Canada, Alaska and Siberia may become
available for food production.
VOLCANIC ACTIVITY is one suggested cause for changes in the
world's climate. After the gigantic eruption of the East Indian island of
Krakatoa in 1883 scientists in France noted a 10% decrease in sunshine
apparently due to the thin cloud of volcanic ash which stopped the full
strength of the sun from reaching the earth. Since then there- have been
no great eruptions so the air may be clearer and the sunshine brighter
and hotter. (Photo American Overseas Lines).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
a new look at the 'Barbaric Nomads of the North'
by Marcel Vanhamme
>
iEW passages of
history have made
a greater im¬
pression on the ima¬
gination of schoolchUd-
ren than the inroads
of the Vikings, thanks
largely to the writers of
history textbooks. Hun¬
dreds . of these books
have . dwelt upon the
terror aroused through¬
out Europe by the
"bloodthirsty Norsemen", and "'the
barbaric nomads of the North", wearing
their strange winged helmets and
pursuing their booty with a single-
minded cruelty and ferocity. Such im¬
pressions, surely calculated to strike the
imagination of the young, are often in¬
tensified by citing the petition: "From
the fury - of the Norsemen, deliver us,
good Lord."
The Vikings, or "'Children of the
Creeks", did undoubtedly spread terror
among the harassed people torn by the
dissensions that followed the death of
Charlemagne, but the picture of them
given by the history books is not only
unfair: it is only half the story.
Considering the general standards of
the time, the geography and climate of
the Northern . countries go far toward
explaining the piracy practised by the
Vikings. But these wild sea-rovers,
driven to their trade, in part, by the
difficulties of existence in their part of
the world, came from countries with a
civilization of their own. Serious
historians know this, but not all of the
writers of textbooks. So, to give a truer
and more fitting picture of ancient
Norway, a joint committee of Norwegian
and Belgian history teachers met in
Oslo in 1952 and drew up a series of
recommendations for the authors and
publishers of school books. These were
designed to secure a less biased pre¬
sentation of historical events affecting
the two countries.
These experts had been present at the
seminars organized by " Unesco at
Brussels in 1950 and at Sèvres in 1951
dealing with improvement of textbooks,
and were therefore aware of the
accomplishments of the Scandinavian
countries, among others, in improving
standards of history teaching on the
basis of joint consultations.
One result of the Belgian-Norwegian
agreement has been the presentation of
an important exhibition in Brussels in
February of Norway's finest examples of
ancient, mediaeval and popular art.
This exhibition, presenting "A Thousand
Years of Viking Art", offered the general
public and crowds of schoolchildren a
practical lesson which enabled them to
correct the false impressions they may
have gained from the over-coloured
accounts in certain books.
The exhibits made it clear, even to the
most superficial observer, that the
Marcel Vanhamme is professor of history at the
Ecole Normale of the City of Brussels.
statements contained in many text¬
books, which suffer from excessive
generalization and over-abridgment, are
in conflict with the facts.
-Students have been amazed at the
treasures yielded up by the famous
tumulus of Oseberg, about two miles
from the coast south of Oslo, discovered
by a farmer in August 1903. Professor
Gabriel Gustafson of the University of
Oslo-, identified the tumulus as a royal
tomb dating from Viking times (750-1050
A.D.). It was in fact the last resting
place of Queen Assa, known to us from
the sagas, who was the grandmother of
Harald Fairhair and died in 850.
The tomb was in disorder; this was
probably deliberate, with a ritual pur¬
pose, to prevent the dead from dis-
THE VIKINGS, as many history books depict them: "They were
ruthless invaders. They stole into peaceful communities, killed,
plundered and burned, and then sailed away as quickly and silently as
they had come". Such accounts, historians tell us, are unjust because
incomplete. They urge a closer look at Viking life.
Exhibitions of this kind, which allow
children to "see .history for themselves"
are becoming more and more common."
This seems to be one of the clearest
applications of modern ideas on edu¬
cation, which moves ever farther from
the exclusive dogmatism of the written
word once so characteristic of it.
Thousands of boys and girls, for
example, have travelled great distances
to Tournai, the "Cradle of the French
Monarchy", as Louis XTV called the
Royal City, to see an exhibition of
Merovingian art treasures.
Three eventful centuries have passed
since the memorable day when Adrien
Quinquin, a labourer chanced to drive
his pick into the site of the forgotten
tomb of Childeric. It contained fabulous
treasures, including
three hundred golden
bees from the royal robe
and two hundred gold
coins from the king's
purse. " Unfortunately
these priceless historical
treasures were stolen
and only about twenty
items were recovered,
including two bees - and
the famous mounts from
the scabbard of the
sword, considered
essential to a knowledge
of the art öf the period.
Some, specialists think
the Merovingians had
not the skill to make
such jewels and believe
that they must have
called in Byzantine
artists specially, unless
the latter had opened a
workshop at Tournai.
Other archaeologists
think the Franks could
have made them.
turbing the living. Archaeologists dug
out what was left of an oak-built ship,
70 feet long by 16 feet wide. The galley
had 30 new oars, 13 feet long, and an
improved form of rudder, 9 feet. long,
which could be drawn up by the crew
when saiUng in shallow water. The
mast must have stood some 42 feet high.
A great number of luxuries and articles
of common use were taken from this
ship, including superb, finely carved
state chariots, sleighs, and hundreds of
objects which throw light on the
everyday life of the Vikings.
Exhibits include a replica of the ship's
prow, a twelfth-century wooden .Ma¬
donna, beautiful boxes for the safe
keeping of papers, fine wood-carvings, a
section of the famous twelfth-century
tapestry of Baldishol, jewellery, weapons
and tools, all of faultless workmanship,
and scenes, depicting, folk life and
traditions.
How very far from the truth Augustin
Thierry was when he said, in his History
of the Conquest . of England by the
Normans, that the Scandinavians were
not interested in .the arts!
Many people have
been surprised to find such a high
standard of art among peoples whom
they have too often been taught to
regard as untutored "barbarians" with
no appreciation of beauty."
The recent discovery, at Vix, a few
-miles from Chatillon-sur-Seine, of the
tomb of a sixth-century Celtic princess
or priestess, has once again brought -up
' the question of the relations of the
Northern countries with the Medi¬
terranean world. The tomb contained a
number of imported articles, mainly
Etruscan and Greek, the most surprising
, being the - wonderful bronze bowl,
weighing over 460-lbs and standing over
5-feet high. It has a frieze of soldiers,
surrounding chariots drawn by four
horses. The Vix treasures have been
on show at the Louvre Museum.
These great exhibitions on art and
history help visitors to a better under¬
standing -of the inter-dependence of
civilizations and, by practical dem¬
onstration, correct many errors instilled
into children's minds by the old-
fashioned approach to teaching or by
out-dated textbooks.
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
VILLAGE MOUN¬
TAINEERS on Ma-
laita Island perform
one of their tradi¬
tional dances (above).
When . Mr. Gaudin,
newly appointed act¬
ing Director of Edu¬
cation in the Solo¬
mons, first visited
the island in 1949
he found the people
distrustful of "edu¬
cation". Village feast
(below) is being held
on Vella Lavella Is¬
land, some 300 miles
to the north west of
Malaita. (Photos COI).
ASSIGNMENT:
SOLOMON
I SLA N D S
by
H. W. Gaudin
UNESCO COURIER - N« 2 - 1954
When Mr. H.W. Gaudin, a New Zea¬
land teacher, set off in a small motor
vessel in 1949 to take on the job of Acting
Director' of Education in the British
Solomon Islands, he knew very little
about either the territory or its peoples.
But he quickly became familiar with the
islanders and their way of life. He found,
in fact, that educational problems were
indivisible from many other island pro¬
blems linguistic, cultural, economic and
social.
Mr. Gaudin's experiences, published
below, are taken from a recent issue of
the "Newsletter for New Zealand Teach¬
ers Serving in' the Pacific".
ONE of my first assignments after
arriving in Honiara, the capital
of the Solomons group, was to tour
the neighbouring Island of Malaita,
where it was hoped to show the people
that the ' Government really. was trying
to do something for them by building a
school there. When I arrived in the
Protectorate some of the school buildings
were already complete, but there were
no teachers and no pupils. Did I say no
pupils? Well, that is not quite correct.
By superhuman efforts five boys had
been brought together. It had proved
impossible to get a single other candidate
from any part of the Solomons.
But I had a job to do, so a doctor and
I boarded a small vessel, the "Nelly",
he to do something for the yaws and
malaria, and I to see what could be done
to help with the education of the
Malaitans. The doctor did his best to
look at the diseased ones and I did mine
to look at the uneducated ones. To tell
the truth it was not too easy to have a
look at either, for the people were so
opposed to government that' they
thought they would be hurting it by
refusing to have their diseases healed
by a government doctor. They preferred
to die in the bush rather than to come
down and see the doctor. As for this
new "education" idea, they distrusted
that too.
At the beginning of our tour, on the
first sign of our ship coming, a series of
warning fires would spring out from"
each spur on the mountains, running
further and further into the distance,
telling every good tribesman that a
- government ship was on the way. As
that usually meant that the District
Commissioner with all his policemen was
on the way to arrest tax-evaders, the
men merely took to the bush till all was
clear, and only the "marys" (womenfolk)
remained to greet us.
However, I did manage to get a few
, of the chiefs from the bush when they
found that there were no police aboard,
and I got promises of boys for my school.
Not that I put much faith in promises
there had been a lot of promises given
one way and another in the past. Still,
at the end of a three weeks' tour, things
had begun to look up a little, and there
seemed a chance that the new govern¬
ment school would have at least a
nucleus of pupils. And so it turned out.
King George VI School, as it was
eventually named, was a residential
school for about 130 pupils, and was
designed to produce boys for training
colleges. The boys were to come from '
the better mission schools and to have
a knowledge of elementary spoken
English and the other normal subjects
of a school of this type.
A curriculum was provided in which
the following were the main studies:
English, Arithmetic, Writing, Reading,
Social Studies, Nature Study, Music and
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Assignment: Solomon Islands (Cont'd)
EDUCATIONAL SERVICES in the Solomons
were almost entirely those of missionary schools
until a government experimental school was
Physical Education. English was a
necessity. In the Solomons, according
to one anthropologist, there are 50
languages as different as English and
French. In the school, out of the first
20 boys there were 12 different lan¬
guages. There was no adequate printed
material in any of these languages, so
we were forced to teach in English.
Once the King George VI School was
established I had to see what could be
done about other educational matters,
and" problems hit me in the eye from
everywhere. What languages are you to
teach the junior and the senior schools?
What about the ilUterate adults? Will
the adults really be enthusiastic about
their children going to school while they
themselves remain ignorant? Won't
they be jealous even though they profess
the reverse? And what will the men
think of any idea to educate the women
when it will certainly mean that they
will have to take over duties formerly
performed by women?
There also had to be an - Education
Regulation promulgated in the Solomons
so designed that it would satisfy all
authorities concerned. "Which of ' the
problems was most urgent? , A lingua
franca? Women's education? Adult
education? Economic education? The
Education Regulation?
As soon as the Education Regulation
had been hammered into shape not
without many struggles and concessions
on all sides I" decided that the best
policy for the infant Education Depart¬
ment was to establish a nucleus of better
government schools and to prosecute a
programme of Mass Education. Mass
Education is a technique whereby in the
cheapest and quickest way backward
areas are given a. minimum standard of
education in various aspects of social
life literacy, health and economics are
the three facets of the one problem.
The facet I was interested in, of course,
was literacy. Here is how I went about
my programme.
I decided that the principles of Mass
Education as being now carried out in
all backward colonial areas would -be
applicable to the Solomons with certain
modifications. To shorten the story I
will take you with me on tour to one of
the Mass Education Pilot Schemes which
I helped to inaugurate in the Solomons.
My aim was to bring literacy in the
native tongue to the adults of the area.
The Agricultural Department had
schemes of rice-growing and so on to
Improve the material well-being of the
MELANESIAN STUDENTS impressed Mr. Gau¬
din, who began the first mass education campaigns
in the Solomons, by the speed with which they
learned to read and write their language. Mission
school (left) is established on Gela Island. Contact
with Solomons by white men was first made by
explorer Alvari de Mendana who sighted landfall
at Santa Ysabel Island in I 568. He was convinced
he had discovered an El Dorado, the "Isles of King
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
opened on Malaita Island in 1950. The boy
completing a drawing of an island canoe is a third
year student ata missionary school on Ugi Island.
people so that they could afford the
luxuries of education that they desired;
the Medical Department had plans for
maternity annexes and elementary
hygiene ' to lower the horrid infant
mortality rate of 50 per cent. But I
" won't deal with anything but the facet
I was mainly concerned with.
We loaded all our paraphernalia onto
our ship. We took food for four or five
weeks, our bedding, and my precious
rifle that I used for getting fresh meat
pigeons. Then, late at night so as to
have a calm crossing, we set out from
the war-torn shores of Guadalcanal for
Malaita. Along the coast we steamed to
the village of Hauhui situated in one of
the wildest 'parts of a wild island, among
the depressed and dwindling Areare
tribes. My wife came too, and so did
Peter, aged 11, on the theory that a little
Solomon". After this, no Europeans visited the
islands for two centuries: Village "green" (right)
is at- Kia, on - Ysabel Island. (Photos COI).
real education in an Areare village
wouldn't hurt him and it didn't either.
At Hauhui we unloaded the ship, for
the coast is open and the ship cannot
stay off-shore to serve as a base; then
it steamed off; we were alone on the
wildest island of the Solomons with no
European nearer than several hours
steaming. We couldn't speak a word of
the language. We had come to give the
natives that mysterious "'something"
-that the District Commissioner had been
filling their ears with for months now
Mass Education.
They all know the word. They had
been told that . Mass Education was
something that would help them, but
that they would first have to help
themselves and pay either with money
or work towards it, although, goodness
knows they have little enough to give in
the way of money. But we did expect
labour from them labour for the new
school, labour for the maternity annexe,
labour for the new rice field rice, that
wonderful food they like so much, but
never grow although the climate is quite
suitable.
We had to teach these people parti¬
cularly the older ones to read and write
using the "'each one teach one" techni¬
que used by some of the more successful
organizers of Mass Education projects in
other Colonial areas. The idea is that
as soon as a man knows, say, the letter
"a", he is to teach this to another man
who is more ignorant than he is, and
so on by a cumulative process.
That night by the light of the ubi¬
quitous kerosene pressure lamp, seen
everywhere in the less populous parts of
the colonial empire, in the palpable
blackness of the equatorial night the
villagers, silently on bare feet, padded
into the "church" that was to be the
centre of our activities.
" Marys " join the class
At the inaugural campaign the vil¬
lagers were avid to learn and were
prepared to sit by the hour, working
fiercely all the time. All reading was to
be done in the native tongue of the
village, a dialect of the Areare language
spoken, as is normal in the Solomons, by
only a thousand or two people. There
were only about 19 sounds that I could
distinguish, and probably only 18, as the
"1" and the "r" which they professed to
be able to distinguish were interchange¬
able. Probably a skilled linguist would
have distinguished more, but whether
that would have made the learning easier
I doubt.
Just as in English, the', people soon
learned to distinguish the look of the
work and did not bother about the indi¬
vidual letters. But here is a fact that
will amaze those who have never
attempted to make adults start from
scratch and learn to read in less than
a week the more able members of the
group were able to read simple words in
their own language, which is completely
phonetic, and these were using the "each
one teach one" technique to instruct
their neighbours.
. The women were there too. This was
a minor triumph, as women normally
took little part in .the social life of the
village, and it had .taken a long time to
persuade the men that -it was a good
thing for the "'marys" to be educated.
When the women did get into class they
were jso fiercely proud of the honour that
they were considerably better students
than the men, in spite of the fact that
they usually had babies hanging round
their necks in a sort of shawl. The only
time they stopped working was in the
UNESCO COURIER - N° 2 - 1954
brief moment it took to soothe the baby
when he cried: to soothe it in the
age-old way. No false modesty here.
In a very short time there were enough
people in the village who could read
words in their own language slowly and
it. was now time to produce something
interesting for them to ' read. This
problem was not nearly so formidable as
might be imagined. To be sure I did not
know the language nor did any avail¬
able white person ; nor for that matter,
was there much use in trying to learn
the multitudinous languages of the
Solomons, and there was no printed
matter available in Areare. But some of
the men spoke pidgin and so did I.
Dog chases cat
To get a story I merely drew a picture
of, say, a dog chasing a cat up a
tree, and showing it to one of the
more intelligent men, (the women didn't
usually speak pidgin) asked him to relate
the story in language "blong him". This'
I wrote down phonetically, and in no
time had plenty of simple "'stories".When
these stories were tested on another
member of the tribe, who could repeat
to me in pidgin what I had told him in
his own tongue. I had checked that the
sentence was correct. While all this was
goins on mv wife was busy making
suitable drawings and reproducing the
whole thing on a "'Fordigraph" dupli¬
cator.
On the momentous night when these
simple stories were first issued to the
class there was a hushed gaso as the
implications struck home, and then a
steadily erowing roar of voices as
evervone in the room started to read
aloud, or to help his more ignorant
neighbour.
For the first time in their history these
people had read a storv in their native
language. The psychological effect
seemed enormous, as these adults, who
an their lives had admired the occasional
villager who had been to a mission
school and learnt to read a -few words in
English from the Bible, realized that it
was possible, in fact fairly simule, for
them to learn 'to read in their own
tongue. They were visibly excited.
In a month the majority of the adults
could read slowly in Areare, and,
although writing progressed more
slowly, all could draw the nineteen
letters of the alphabet, and in that way
slowly make words. The more able
students even wrote letters and stories.
Melting stone-age
In my considered view the only hope
of making this under-privileged peo¬
ple melt into the European culture
which 'is fast enveloping its stone-age
one, is to get a basic minimum of literacy
instilled into the people, particularly the
adults. It is little use expecting the
young generation to accomplish much in
a village ruled entirely by the older and
completely ilUterate generation.
First of all let the people be able to
read and write, at least in their own
tongue. This is not a long business, at
any rate the reading part of it, and then
it will be easier to bring to the villages
propaganda so that the old agricultural
methods will be improved; so that that
modern marvel, the hoe, will take the
place of the digging stick ; so that
schools and hospitals will be built by
community effort, and money subscribed
for their operation ; in short, so that the
peoples of under-developed areas may
make haste to join the new culture.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Kaleidoscope
(Continuée/ from page 9)
wooden mortars, to the accompaniment
of a melancholy chant. Rhythm in the
'work songs' sung by the groups of
peasants, the combites, as their picks
strike down in unison into the rich soil,
preparing it for the coming seed time".
All this, surely, forms part of the law
and essence of our Negro life.
Again, could anything be more typi¬
cally Haitian than the passion for
dancing shared by the great mass of the
population, in town and country alike
for ths religious dances of voodoo and
for the secular dances of the rara (1),
the mahi and the congo ?
Even the least observant onlooker is
struck by the infectious delight displayed
by the spectators during the sacred
dances in which, as we have written
elsewhere, "the gods may, on occasion,
usurp the bodies of mortals and borrow
their voices to proclaim, with delirious
excitement, their right to share in the
ecstatic performance". Dances of en¬
chantment, where the frantic beating of
the drums and the deafening clamour of
voices communicate to the spellbound
audience the madness of crazy, fantastic
motion. Hypnotic dances, where the
performers are so agile and supple that
their bodies seem jointless. Exhausting
dances, where intoxication of sound,
combined with' Bacchic uproar of the
"possessed", smites the quivering, dust-
enveloped audience with what would
appear to be mass dementia.
Another thing too, must be recognized
as an expression of the collective spirit
the new manifestations of "primitive"
painting and sculpture which, thanks to
the initiative ' of the American, Mr. De
Witt Peters, have won recognition as part
of our spiritual heritage.
The work of the Haitian primitive
painters has developed along extraord¬
inarily realistic, and zestful lines, bright
colours and simplicity of design im¬
parting- a special feature to this fresh
evidence of the Haitian people's marked
artistic gifts.
All this establishes the dazzlingly
varied nature of Haitian culture, which
even the most superficial observer cannot
ignore and in which the tourist seeking
"local colour" cannot but delight.
In my- Father's house ,are many
mansions, said the Nazarean.
(I) Peasant carnival.
Haiti and the U. N.
(Continued1 from page 13)
Agriculture. His knowledge of the Hai- .
tian and his respect for human values
have enabled him to talk with the pea¬
sants and convince them of the need,
not only for themselves but for their
children and their children's children,
to prevent the soil from disappearing
beneath their feet. It is obvious to aU
who travel about the country that im¬
portant work has been done, not only
by the State but through the voluntary
and clear sighted help given by indivi¬
dual people.
Fish breeding-. For some time now
fish breeding ponds have existed more
or less throughout the country. Some
are on private property, but everyone
who has the necessary means will soon
be able to take part in the fish breed¬
ing programme, if the experts' advice
about the nature of the land is followed.
Only salty land, unsuitable for cultiva¬
tion, is used for fish ponds. Specimens
of fish, sent to us from Africa and Israel,
have been able to adapt themselves to
local conditions. Living as we do on the
edge of an ocean abounding in fish, we
should' benefit from the advice of a
fishery expert, who could also assist us by
introducing new methods of curing.
' Again, we should consider introducing,
even as a school subject, practical pro¬
cesses for preserving meat, fruit and
food in general.
Whether on questions of grain storage
and methods of silo building, of estab-
Ushing a school for hotel keeping, of
technical training, stockbreeding, audio¬
visual education or statistics, there
are certain methods of approach which
must be observed. Everything must be
seen, discussed and considered on a
Haitian scale. Where a carpenter is to
be trained, it is unnecessary, for example,
for an apprentice to start by learning to
operate an electric saw, which he wiU
rarely have occasion to use. In building
a silo, there may in a given region be
reasons economy, transport, etc.
for using easily avaUable material. In
rural education, the teacher must be able
to chat with a man who is said to be
tricky, backward and superstitious but
whose conscience and dignity are very
much alive; whose mind is ready to show
appreciation, and his heart to give
affection.
Charters and Freedom
(Continued from page il)
Meeting at the "'sacred city" of
Gonaives in November 1950 for the great
task of giving the Haitian people a
democratic Constitution "'safeguarding
its rights and freedoms", the Constituent
Assembly, followed the liberal ' tra¬
dition of lour, first legislators land
endeavoured to model the new Consti¬
tution, so far as possible, on the demo¬
cratic ideal - proclaimed in Abraham
Lincoln's famous words: "Government
of the people, by the people,- for the
people."
The Assembly granted Haitian women
the right to vote and drew up detailed
regulations on such matters as marriage,
- the family, children, family property, the
provision of education at all levels, the
protection of agricultural and urban
workers, rural public order, rural branch
banks and banks for urban workers,
social security, pubUc health and poor
law administration.
The Constitution of 25 November 1950
now in force is designed to give
the Haitian people a tool for the
building of a free, peaceful and prosper¬
ous civilization based on collaboration
between the social classes and co-op-
- eration between the nations. It gives the
Government a legal and social pro¬
gramme for transforming Haiti into a
modern State. As the Message from the
Constituent Assembly to the Haitian
people stated: "'the State must seek
to improve public health, raise the
living standards of all sections of the
population, and organize an educational
system based on the principles of liberty,
morality, civic responsibUity and human
solidarity and providing equal oppor¬
tunities for aU, so that every individual,
according to his gifts and merits, may
share in the advantages offered by his
national community and enjoy the
benefits of the intellectual, literary,
artistic, scientific and technical progress
made throughout the world."
The Government of Mr. Paul E. Ma-
gloire has, since December 6 1950, been
striving earnestly for the implementa¬
tion of this programme which is so com¬
pletely in line with the United Nations
Charter. In this task it relies on the full
collaboration of the United Nations.
City Development
(Continued1 from page 2/)
the Eastern sea-board of the United
States and spreading inland as far as
Chicago.
Meanwhile great Atlantic and Pacific
ports were being established on the
coasts of South America with the arrival
of increasing settlers from Europe. On
the coasts of Africa, too, the same was
happening. First, Cape Town was built
by the white man as a beacon of beauty
to shipweary seamen, then, perhaps as a
consequence of the deplorable slave-
trade, the Negro constructed the gigan¬
tic town of Abeokuta in Nigeria a
typical example of the rise of urban
development in the "Dark Continent".
At the same time, old Islamic cities, such
as Aleppo, maintained their position or,
like Cairo, revived. But the impact of
neighbouring Europe makes this less
surprising.
The changes are important therefore
between 1800 and 1900. But what a dif¬
ference there is when we come to the
next fifty years. ! The 20th century is
marked by a veritable profusion of urban
development despite "the havoc wrought
by the two most terrible wars mankind
has ever known.- In spite of all the
destruction, the map presents the 20th
century as constructive, as if the increase
in destructive power were but the reverse
side of man's new capacity for buUding.
What is particularly striking is the
enormous eastward expansion of the
European city belt. The great Russian
cities date back only to the 19th century
but, in the 20th, they developed into a
series of great conglomerations strung
otit along the major routes crossing Sibe¬
ria, and in a sense are the modern
northern equivalents of the towns on the
ancient southern routes of Central Asia.
The three maps published on the cen¬
tre pages are part of a series which
will be used to illustrate a new history
of mankind.
The preparation of this history
has been entrusted by Unesco to
the International Commission for a
Scientific and Cultural History of Man-
kind. The Commission considers the
three maps as still in the "working docu¬
ment" stage, and they are therefore
being circulated to specialists in different
parts of the world for possible revision
and completion.
Similarly, for the text of the History,
the Commission is publishing the "Jour¬
nal of World History", a quarterly review
in English, French and Spanish edited by
Professor Lucien Febvre of the famed
College de France.
The History of Mankind will seek to
present the scientific and cultural story
of the world, free from national bias, and
show the efforts of the men and peoples
who fashioned the tools of modern
society.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER - N» 2 - 1954
results aré not immediately apparent. A closer look reveals
striking changes. For the first time, peasants have feelings
of pride and dignity as they sign their own names. The toil
and austerity of life is slowly alleviated as they learn new
techniques of irrigation, soil conservation, planting and eco¬
nomics. As health fundamentals are explained to parents,
fewer children die and energy is no longer sapped by disease.
The protection of law and the rights of the citizen are made
known. Men begin to understand that knowledge gives them
power to control their way of life. Mechanization, only possible
with a literate population, is within grasp. A new energy
knowledge is reshaping the face of the land. .
HAITI TODAY(Contd from page 16)
problems. Unesco and other U.N. agencies are helping Haitian
authorities in an effort to surmount the formidable obstacle the
country faces to eradicate ilhteracy, provide vocational training
and improve the economic and social retardation of its rural
areas. For the major educational problem in Haiti remains
that of the rural school. An agricultural country, depend¬
ing almost exclusively on its production of coffee, sugar,
bananas, cotton, and similar crops for subsistence, Haiti is
compelled to try to intensify its agricultural effort through
educating the peasants in modern methods of cultivation and
soU conservation. "
Until the problem of rural education is satisfactorily solved, fa People's Art Reborn
Haiti seems destined to remain a desperately poor country. r
The converse of this statement is also true, for Haitian eco¬
nomics and education are inextricably linked. Progress has
been made in recent years but the facts remain that four out
of five peasant children never attend school; that teachers'
salaries are inadequate; that many school buildings are hope¬
lessly unsatisfactory; that equipment and textbooks are often
unobtainable.
Only in recent years has real attention been paid to the pro¬
vision of schools. The present five-year plan calUng for an
additional 327 elementary, 12 secondary and 15 professional
schools cannot meet the full needs of the people. But to have
established this goal and appropriated $ 5,000,000 is a tremendous
stride forward in the battle against illiteracy.
Education is compulsory for children of seven to fourteen
years but the law is rarely enforced. The reasons: A shortage
of schools; the dispersion of rural communities; the crowding
of existing schools ; a serious teacher shortage.
Moreover, the language problem continues to plague Haitian
educators. The official language of the RepubUc is French,
but all Haitians understand, and most Haitians speak, Creole.
Creole is now becoming a written language for the first time,
but there are four different spellings and a great lack of
textbooks for teaching it.
Another major problem has been the transformation of the
teaching methods and subject matter. Today such subjects
as health, sanitation and home economics are being given
equal emphasis with the three R's. Schools in both urban
and rural areas serve as adult centres in the evening. Students
may range in age from 12 to 75.
What have these efforts achieved so far? Superficially the
DURING the past decade Haiti has achieved fame by a
veritable explosion of artistic talent which has amazed
critics from New York to Paris and beyond. The ori¬
ginal exponents of this art were simple men. They included
a cobbler, a taxi-driver, a voodoo priest, a book-keeper, a
carpenter and a tailor, aU of them making a scant living, but
with one thing in common. They were able to translate their
sorrows, their beliefs, their joys, their patriotic and emotional
experiences into pictures of powerful simplicity, .utter sincerity
and enchantingly decorative effect.
The man responsible for bringing together all this talent,
guiding it and revealing it to the world was an American, De
Witt Peters. When he founded the Centre d'Art, at Port-au-
Prince in 1944 this American painter had only a slight interest
in the Haiti's contemporary "primitives". Then, foUowing an
exhibition in which the works of three of the "popular" paint¬
ers were shown, he began to follow and encourage their work
more closely. From this has grown a powerful movement of
popular art in Haiti in which the names of men like Hector
HyppoUte, a former voodoo priest, Philome Obin, Louverture
Poisson and Wilson Bigaud stand out.
Haiti has produced an interesting body of Uterature, parti-
îularly in the field of poetry. Haitian poets have been influenced
by French styles, but their rich local colour gives their poetry
a distinctively .national character. Oustanding poets are
Jacques Roumain, Léon Laleau. The MarceUn brothers Pierre
and PhiUppe Thoby won fame in 1943 when their peasant novel
Canapé-Vert was awarded first prize in a Latin American Novel
Contest and was translated into English.
3i
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco Newsroom
M. ERIPATETIC JAPANESE
ART : Unesco has organized
travelling exhibitions of 17th to
19th century Japanese wood¬
prints. These are now touring
14 countries in Europe, Asia and
the Americas.
BARGING INTO CLASS :
Holland has set up 10 schools
and 21 special classes on the
country's network of water¬
ways to cater for children of
bargemen who are "passing
through".
ic SCREENS FOR FARMERS:
TV Clubs in rural France are
experimenting with television
as an aid to better farming.
Programmes prepared by
Unesco, the French TV net¬
work and Education and Agri¬
culture authorities are being
tried out on rural audiences,
and results are being follow¬
ed closely.
w HERE'S TEACHER? The
teacher shortage in the United
States is growing according to
lamic Research, Psychology,
Fine Arts and Library Archi¬
ves are also to be established.
SiSiamese centre: a
"Thailand-Unesco Fundamental
Education Centre" is to be set up
in Ubol, Thailand, following a re¬
cent technical assistance agree¬
ment. Four specialized agencies
and the TJ.N. will co-operate in
the project. They will survey
social and economic conditions,
train local educators and field
workers in health, agriculture,
tion by 7 states contributing
75 per cent of CERN'S bud¬
get will bring the Convention
into force.
The European Organisation
for Nuclear Research was set
up under Unesco's auspices
last year to proceed with the
construction in Geneva of an
international laboratory for
nuclear research and to de¬
velop co-operation between
existing laboratories in theo¬
retical studies. The research
will be of a non-military na¬
ture and none of it will be
secret.
M SLAMIC GIVE AND
TAKE: Pakistan and Turkey have
signed a ten-year cultural agree¬
ment. Pakistanis and Turks will
now learn more about each other
through exchange lectures, films,
translations of books and folk
songs.
* ARABIC RAISED DOTS:-
The first Braille lending li¬
brary in the Middle East is
being created as part of a new
rehabilitation centre for the
blind of this region recently
set up near Cairo by Egypt
. and the U.N.
Country teachers:
The problems of preparing rural
teachers for their jobs is the sub¬
ject of a new Unesco book, "The
Training of Rural Teachers",
with detailed studies written by
educators from Brazil, Gold
Coast, India and Mexico. The
book is inspired by Unesco's con¬
cern with rural education, - the
fight against illiteracy and the
spread of compulsory primary
education .generally. Price:
$ 1.25; 7/6r 350 fr. frs.
NO MORE TAXES: The
United Kingdom has joined 16
other nations in applying the
Unesco-sponsored internation¬
al agreement which abolish¬
es ~ import duties on educa¬
tional, scientific and cultural
materials such as books, news¬
papers, magazines, works of
art, music scores and articles
for the blind.
w OMEN ADMITTED: Wo¬
men's rights in Jordan have
marked a new step forward with
the opening of the first women's
teachers' training college at Ra¬
mallah, near Jerusalem.
HELP HAS NO NATIONALITY. The International Work Camp Move¬
ment is growing. Volunteers are now active in the Greek Ionian islands
(photo) struck by earthquakes last August and in the Netherlands
following last year's floods. Others are at .work on projects in India,
Pakistan, Algeria, Italy and elsewhere. Seventy organizations, whose
work was co-ordinated by Unesco after the last war, now sponsor the
movement in 35 countries.
M
the International Bureau of
Education. Over 1,500,000 child¬
ren entered school last autum
requiring a total of at least
116,000 new teachers to meet
both the increase in enrollment
and replace retiring teachers,
but less than half were avail¬
able.
EDUCATION BUDGET
UP: Pakistan will spend
£130,000,000 on education at
all levels from primary school
to universities according to a
new six - year development
plan. Special centres for Is-
home industries, social welfare
and rural education and prepare
new teaching materials.
ATOMS FOR PEACE:
The Government of the Unit¬
ed Kingdom, is the first to.
ratify the Convention setting
up a European Organization
for Nuclear Research (CERN),
approved last July by 12 Unes¬
co Member States. The im¬
portance of CERN and the
peaceful uses of atomic ener¬
gy were dealt with in a major
portion of the December 1953
issue of the Courier. Ratifica-
EXICAN LOUD SPEAK¬
ERS: Mexico has launched a
scheme to develop audio-visual
"aids for class use. Every school
will have a projector and radio
by 1955 according to the plan.
CINEMAS ON WHEELS:
Mobile cinemas now pay reg¬
ular calls to seven hundred
villages in Norway. Twen¬
ty-eight of these are touring
the countryside permanently, '
four by boat and the others
by car. In two years
1,200,000 people have attended
20,000 shows.
Translation acade¬
my: The State of Madhya Pra¬
desh, m India, has decided to
set up a translation academy
which will translate important
books from other languages into
Hindi and Marathi. A sum of
100,000 Rupees (about $20,000)
has been set aside for the project
from state funds.
FILM. HISTORY: As part
of its Fourth Centenary cele¬
brations, Sao Paulo is now
holding an international Film
Festival. Unesco is participat¬
ing -with a photographic
exhibition tracing the history
of the cinema from its first
intimation, in the drawings of
Leonardo da Vinci, to its la¬
test manifestation in the cine¬
mascope, invented by Profes¬
sor Henri Chrétien. Publi¬
cations connected with Unes¬
co's programme for films are
being displayed at the exhi¬
bit. A selection of films from
many countries is being
shown during the Festival
week, and the Unesco film
"World without End" is in¬
cluded in the programme.
Unesco's National Distributors from whom the
English edition of THE COURIER can be obtained
are listed below Other Unesco Distributors are
listed in the French and Spanish editions of THE
COURIER.
Australia : Oxford University Press, 346,
Little Collins Street, Melbourne.
Austria : Wilhelm Fnck Verlag, 27, Graben,
Vienna I.
Burma : Burma Educational Bookshop, 55 1-3
Merchant Street, P O. Box 222, Rangoon.
Canada : University of Toronto Press, To¬
ronto.
Ceylon : Lake House Bookshop, The Asso¬
ciated Newspapers of Ceylon, Ltd., Co- .
lombo 1
Cyprus : M. E. Constantinides, P.O.B. -473.
Nicosia.
Denmark : E|nar Munksgaard Ltd., 6 Norre-
gade, Copenhagen.
NATIONAL DISTRIBUTORS
Egypt : La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9, Adly
Pasha Street, Cairo.
Finland : Akateeminen Kirjakauppa 2, Kes-
kuskatu, Helsinki.
Formosa : The World Book Company Ltd.,
99, Chung King South Rd, Section I, Taipeh.
France : Sales Division, Unesco, 19, Avenue
Kléber, Pans- I 6e.
Germany : Unesco Vertrieb für Deutschland,
R. Oldenbourg, München.
Greece : Elefthéroudakis, Librairie Interna¬
tionale, Athens.
Hong Kong : Swindon Book Co., 25 Nathan
Road, Kowloon.
India : Orient Longmans Ltd. Bombay, "Cal¬
cutta, Madras : sub-depots : Oxford Book
& Stationery Co , Scindia House, New
Delhi; Rajkamal Publications Ltd., Himalaya *
House, Bombay 7.
Indonesia : G.C.T. van Dorp & Co. NV.,
Djalan Nusantara, 22, Djakarta.
Iraq : McKenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
Israel : Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Al-
lenby Road, Tel-Aviv,
Jamaica : Sangster's Book Room, 99, Harbour
Street, Kingston ; Knox Educational Services,
Spaldings.
Japan ; Maruzen Co, Inc., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, Tokyo.
Jordan : J I. Bahous and Co., Dar-UI-Kutub,
Salt Road, Amman.
Malayan Federation and Singapore : Peter
Chong and Co., P.O. Box 135, Singapore.
Malta : Sapienza's Library, 26, Kingsway,
Valletta.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout 9, The Hague.
New Zealand : Unesco Publications Centre,
7 De Lacy Street, Dunedm, N. E. 2.
Nigeria: C.MS Bookshop, P.O. Box 174,
Lagos.
Norway : A/S Bokh jornet, Stortingsplass 7,
Oslo.
Pakistan : Ferflzsons Ltd., Karachi, Lahore,
Peshawar.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co., Inc ,
I 104 Castillejos, Quiapo, Manila.
Surinam : Radhakishun and Company Led ,
(Book Dept.), Watermolenstraat 36, Para¬
maribo.
Sweden : A.B.C E. Fnztes Kungl Hovbok-
handel Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16.
Thailand : Suksapan Panit, Arkarn 9, Rçj-
Damnern Avenue, Bangkok.
Union of South Africa : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Ltd., P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United Kingdom : H M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
U.S.A. : Columbia University Press, 2960
Broadway, New York.
U
Z
<
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
SUBSCRIBED YET?
Take advantage NOW of our new
reduced rates for a year's subscription :
6/- instead of 10/6; #1.50 instead of
2.00; 300 francs instead of 500 fr.
The COURIER is a non-profit publication of Unesco with regular
readers in more than 70 countries. It seeks to serve as a window opening
on the world of education, science and culture through which the school¬
teacher in particular and other readers in general can look out on to
wide global horizons. Each month it presents by text and image, features
which are both informative and thought-provoking, and devotes a section
to an authoritative treatment of an important world problem and shows
how it is being dealt with nationally and internationally.
Some themes recently studied in The Courier : The Jigsaw Pattern
of the World's Languages and New Techniques in Foreign Language
Teaching; Peaceful Uses of Atomic Energy; Children's Art and Educa¬
tion; The Fraud of Racial Doctrines; Public Libraries and Education;
Pushing Back the World's Desert Frontiers; TV A Chance and a
Challenge for Education; Geography Teaching and International Under¬
standing; World Paper Famine; Cinema and International Understanding.
GROUP SUBSCRIPTIONS : Special group subscription rates are
available for teachers, students and educational bodies for copies supplied
to one address at the following discounts : 25 copies -5 % ; 50 copies
10 %; 100 copies 15 %; 200 copies 20 %.
NOTE : Subscriptions to The Courier can be paid in local currencies
to Unesco National Distributors.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE SAME STREET
AFTER 50 YEARS
This is how one of the main streets in Sao Paulo, Brazil, looked in I 900 and how it looked in I 952.
The phenomenal growth of Sao Paulo probably the fastest growing city in the world is now fairly
well known. What is relatively less known is the amazing increase in the number of cities all over
the world in the past I 50 years. For a story of this remarkable growth and a series of hitherto
unpublished maps on this subject, see centre page. (Photos copyright "O Estado de Sao Paulo").
]]>
</page>
</document>
