<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078194eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
WINDOW OPEN THE WORLD
mam
iHni-mtiniir-^ÉKii »it i; CE 1,-STG. (U.K.1 <HMHaJÍ*¿ (U.S.) - 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
¿m y --:^:<:ilm-
- " »in. - * ' ""
\~ *
; «ÜB»!«
FRESCOES RISING FROM THE SAN
Archaeological excavations carried out in Su¬
danese and Egyptian Nubia during the past
two years have yielded spectacular discover¬
ies of the greatest historical and artistic im¬
portance. Over twenty countries have thus
far sent expeditions into this area which will
soon be flooded by the waters of the Nile.
Here frescoes from a buried Christian church,
unearthed by Polish archaeologists, are seen
as they emerge from the sand for the first time
in almost a thousand years. (Story page 18)
*-
Je**
*>
CO G. Gerster, Zurich
S"
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1962
15TH YEAR
Contents
No. 11
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
This strange contraption is
one of a number of new
musical Instruments invented
by two young Frenchmen in
recent years. The instru¬
ments create sounds Impos¬
sible to achieve on ordinary
musical instruments and
exemplify present efforts to
explore new horizons in the
world of music. (See page 12.)
© Almasy
Page
4 SOCIETY CALLS THE TUNE
From troubadour to juke-box
by Peter Lengyel
8 MUSIC SKETCH BOOK
14 IN DEFENCE OF SCIENCE-FICTION
by Arthur C. Clarke
18 DIGGING FOR HISTORY
Excavations in Nubia I 96 I -62
by Rex Keating
26 UNICEF GREETING CARDS
28 RISE AND FALL OF GREAT CIVILIZATIONS
The anatomy of underdevelopment (Pt. Ill)
30 WORLD PIONEERS OF TECHNOLOGY
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 62.I.I74 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition :
German Edition
Arabic Edition :
Japanese Edition
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
Jane Albert Hesse
: Arturo Despouey
Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Abdel Monvim El Sawi (Cairo)
: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box S69, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
SOCIETY CALLS
THE TUNE
by Peter Lengyel
A:LL art reflects the complexity of the society
.which produces it. Music, perhaps the most
spontaneous of the arts, is no exception and we shall
examine here how musical taste and production are
related to social structure. Can one learn anything about
a culture by listening to its music? I believe that one
certainly can, and that the reverse also holds true: one
needs to know something about a culture before really
appreciating its music.
The history of music goes back to the various folk
idioms, which are the collective and mainly anonymous
characteristics of certain cultures, or of stages in their
evolution. Their origins are not commonly known with
any precision, though the effects of certain recorded
events can often be clearly distinguished.
Thus typical elements of North African origin in Spanish
folk music are a relic of the Moorish occupation of Spain,
just as the diffusion of certain modes and phrasings of
Mediterranean origin to other parts of Europe bear
witness to the passage of the troubadours and trouvères,
those wandering minstrels of the Middle Ages who,
Peter Lengyel is in charge of projects on economic and
4 social development in the Department of Social Sciences
of Unesco. For many years he has studied the shifting
place of music in social life through the ages in Europe.
fanning out from Provence, came to be greatly admired
for their accomplishment in distant parts.
Folk music is essentially traditional and mostly un¬
written (except when collected and noted by scholars):
like the great Gothic cathedrals or the ancient sagas and
myths, it is the result of an accumulation of artistic effort,
most of the individual contributions to which are hard
to distinguish from each other. No doubt there were
important musical Innovators who exercised an incisive
influence in their day, but their names are lost and it
is probable that they were not particularly honoured in
their lifetime, for the folk audience did not take a sophis¬
ticated interest in art for art's sake.
On the contrary, folk pieces tend to be short and specific
to common situations: they might be dances, ballads,
songs for festive or special occasions (banquets, lullabies,
work songs, dirges), hunting calls or military marches.
Also, they are generally intended for performance by the
voice or on selected and usually simple instruments, widely
available and none too difficult to play.
Melody and rhythm, rather than harmony and timbre,
are their outstanding features: "abstract" music, long
compositions in complex form and music which calls for
considerable technical equipment (whether in the shape
of instruments or performing skills) has little or no place
in folk music.
Folk musicians rarely had the benefit of formal musical
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Left, concert in an 1 8th
century drawing room.
Right, jazz drummer Lionel
Hampton in action. Jazz, a
music in which improvisa¬
tion plays a major role, has
been called a new folk idiom,
reflecting as it does many
aspects of our time and
appealing to the most di¬
verse audiences. The ab¬
stract and "learned" classical
music of two centuries ago
was written for the plea¬
sure and appreciation of a
cultured minority audience.
Jean-Pierre Leloir
training other than that which might be handed down
from father to son, nor were they acquainted with a
repertory beyond the traditional one. These limitations
gave them a simplicity and constancy which their less
naive successors could not validly claim. Thus the folk
musician strove to encompass the entire gamut of his
listener's emotional experience in the only terms available
to him. If many cultures never really moved beyond the
folk stage in their musical expression, this is an index
of their continued homogeneity, separateness and cohe¬
sion. Undisturbed in patterns of living and basic values,
they reflected such simplicity in their art.
In Europe, as in several other parts of the world, notably
in Asia, however, increasing social differentiation brought
with it the rise of "learned" or "classical" music. This
was distinguished from folk music by being addressed to
minority audiences, giving expression to increasingly
singular emotions or abstract sentiments and being the
product of composers schooled in certain established
conventions and techniques. Also, classical music is
mostly written, leaving a decreasing amount of latitude to
the performer's fancy and introducing a formal distinction
between the creative artist (the composer) and the
executing artist (the player or singer), which is rare in
folk music.
The rise of classical music owed a great deal to the
patronage of churches and courts, both of which used it
to enhance their prestige and as a commonly acceptable
vehicle to convey uncommon concepts. In Europe, the
earliest school of classical composers were the Poly-
phonists, who flourished from the 10th to the 17th
centuries and whose art, as the name suggests, lay in the
combination of several voices singing different but super¬
imposed melodic lines simultaneously.
Since they were chiefly in the service of the church, the
works of prominent Polyphonists, such as Byrd in
England, Orlandus Lassus and Josquin dès Près in
Flanders, Victoria in Spain and Palestrina in Italy, were
typically couched in the form of masses, anthems and
motets. Their most important output for profane use
were the madrigals, written for amateur domestic
performance, of which large collections by various masters
are known to us today.
From the combination of several voices singing different
parts, the logical development was to have these parts
performed by instruments, or by voices and instruments
together. It is to this art that the succeeding school of
European classical composers the Contrapuntalists
devoted itself. By this time (the second half of the 17th
and the 18th century), two other important developments
were also taking place.
Firstly, great strides were being made in perfecting
instruments through inventions (keyboard instruments),
refinements (string instruments) and technical improve-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
SOCIETY CALLS THE TUNE (Lonfd)
Orchestras for kings, dukes and generals
ments (wind instruments) which not only allowed for
hitherto unknown flights of virtuosity in performance but
also encouraged the exploration of novel timbres and
effects through orchestration.
Secondly, increasing attention was paid to the formal
aspect of music as the "learned" tradition took hold:
simple two-section (binary) or three-section (tertiary)
pieces were supplemented by compositions cast in the
more complicated form of fugues or airs with variations.
Such evolution, in turn, reflected the increasing
complexity of European society and the widening of
audiences and sources of patronage. While the Polypho-
nists relied chiefly on the church for support, and to a
lesser extent on the courts and on educated amateurs, the
Contrapuntalists already had wider profane outlets
including increasingly wealthy aristocratic circles and the
rising middle classes.
Johann Sebastian Bach successively held posts as a
choirboy, violinist in a princely band, town organist, chief
court musician and cantor of the municipal school of
Leipzig. George Frederick Händel speculated in public
entertainment with his operas and made a career in
Germany, Italy and England.
Most of the Contrapuntalists tried their hand at many
kinds of music choral, instrumental, orchestral, stage,
military, ceremonial, sacred frequently in response to
commissions. They were artisans who responded to new
demands: in the widening field open to them, they be¬
came acknowledged masters of a versatile trade with
enlarged horizons for themselves and for their art.
U;p to this stage, the folk and "learned" tradi¬
tions of music in Europe tended to diverge.
Learned composers became men of the world who mixed
with the upper classes, had access to kings, dukes, popes
and generals, and formed as well as shared their tastes.
Folk musicians remained obscure, playing to the common
people in what came to be regarded as a crude and rustic
manner; they did not have great orchestras or choirs at
their disposal, nor were they challenged by the theatre,
the pomp of state and religion and the demands of
talented amateurs. Their idiom was unsuited to the
expression of lofty abstractions, like charity and humility,
patriotism and loyalty, and they could not compete with
their grand colleagues. This state of affairs carried over
into the next important period of * European musical
history, the Classical epoch.
It is true that Haydn introduced German, Hungarian
and Slav folk melodies into his music, sometimes for light
relief, sometimes with deliberate expressive purpose, while
Beethoven gave full symphonic treatment to peasant
dances and Schubert derived the lied (or art song) from
traditional German patterns. Yet these were but episodes,
paralleled by attempts to present popular music to
sophisticated audiences, such as the ballad operas of the
18th century, amongst which the Beggar's Opera by Gay
and Pepusch achieved enduring fame.
It was the Romantics of the 19th century who, after an
fi excess of courtly and ecclesiastical discipline, suddenly
discovered the as yet untapped sources of folk music
which lay all around them and provided material as rich
and diverse as it was colourfully attractive to mixed
audiences removed from the traditional life.
"Nationalistic" composers, working the vein of folk
music and incorporating it into their personal styles,
flourished everywhere: Mussorgsky, Borodin, Tchaikowsky
and Rimsky-Korsakov in Russia, Smetana and Dvorak in
Bohemia, Chopin in Poland, Liszt, and later Bartok and
Kodaly in Hungary, Grieg in Norway, de Falla, Granados
and Albeniz in Spain, Vaughan-Williams in Britain, and
more recently, Enesco in Rumania, Villa-Lobos in Brazil,
Copeland and Gershwin in the U. S.
T here was even a considerable amount of
fascination with the folk music of foreign
countries. Bizet's Carmen, undoubtedly the most popular
opera ever written in the Spanish idiom, is the work of
one Frenchman, based on a story by a second which, in
turn, was adapted as a libretto by two others. Tchai¬
kowsky wrote several pieces incorporating popular Italian
airs, as did Mendelssohn, "who also used Scottish tunes.
Brahms' Hungarian dances are famous; so are Dvorak's
New World symphony and his American quartet, incorpor¬
ating Negro themes.
There now occurred a period of convergent development.
While folk music was being studied, recorded and worked
up by "learned" composers, classical music was also to
some extent passing into the popular domain. The
operetta is a typical example of musical entertainment
which, while cast in a version of the "learned" idiom,
appeals to the taste of a public that is not necessarily
sophisticated in its musical tastes.
Those who flocked to applaud Offenbach's excellent
comedies, or the endlessly tuneful light operas of Johann
Strauss might not have been able to tell Berlioz from
Rossini, nor cared to do so. But they were equally
strangers to pure folk music being, for the most part, city
dwellers and members of an industrializing, specializing
society, . increasingly cosmopolitan, increasingly eclectic,
decreasingly linked to their own traditional sectors.
Without being particularly conscious of the
process, the pace-setting elites and their
crowds of imitators, had gradually been made familiar not
only with elaborations of their home folk materials, but
also with exotic elements originating, perhaps, from
Africa, the Far East or Polynesia. The process was,
incidentally, two-way, for it also acquainted audiences in
Tokyo, Cairo or Rio de Janeiro with the musical fashions
of Paris, Vienna and Milan.
At the same time, however, true folk music itself began
to decline, for it was assailed with increasing strength by
an international idiom (the amalgam of several folk tradi¬
tions, plus an infusion of "learned" styles) which caught
the imagination of millions all over the world. Thus,
some of the lieder of Schubert, arias by Mozart, Verdi and
Puccini, a few instrumental or orchestral pieces as well as
a host of airs and dances, from "John Brown's Body'' to
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
1 Ad
%
9 3i %
_J^
f___j__l
HP*
: -»if1
1 v.
*A
. _s
<**
* *
^
%
#
«
ft
1 I % ai ib
«?% 1 ^^^H^
(y __K-"""
\f ^Nä
£ * 7
1y
_____	
* } i
PHILOSOPHY OF MUSIC. Today, musicians as well as
sociologists are preoccupied with the meaning of music and its
future. Above, Olivier Messiaen, the eminent French composer
surrounded by his pupils at the Paris Conservatoire Nationale
de Musique, where he lectures on the philosophy of music.
Samuel Goldwyn Productions-Columbia
© Pans-Match
STEEPED IN FOLK TRADITIONS. The Romantics of the
19th century suddenly discovered the untapped sources of
folk music. Composers in many lands have since worked this
vein and incorporated it into their personal styles. One
example is George Gershwin's opera, "Porgy and Bess" (recently
brought to the screen, and a scene from which is shown below)
whose music is steeped in American Negro folk traditions.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Drawing, above, by Russian artist
Larionov shows Serge Prokofiev,
at the piano with composer-
conductor Igor Stravinsky, (glass
in hand) and Serge Diaghilev, foun¬
der of the famous Ballets Russes.
Niccolo Paganini (right)
composer and one of
the world's greatest vir¬
tuosos of the violin.
Enrico Caruso (left). Self-
portrait by the great
Italian 'tenor who was
also a skilled caricaturist.
<j
e _
sst .
IK
N
IT O '
': I
Ui_t
ft noti. C«-KfV*l*» ;-it ML
C*fU út'í.f J»t»*E i*j,pAf*M.n\r
MUSIC
SKETCH
BOOK
All drawings courtesy of the André Meyer Music Collection, Paris.
Reproduction prohibited without prior authorization.
8 Musical puzzle invented by Charles Gounod
which shows that in a given scale arrangement
the same note is found in 1 30 different tones.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Arturo Toscanini (Italy)
4
Dimitri Shostakovitch (U.S.S.R.'
*
4j*
\
Bêla Bartok (Hungary) Leonard Bernstein (U.S.A.)
CELEBRITIES DRAWN BY AN ARTIST-MUSICIAN
Musician and artist, B. F. Dolbin is an American of Austrian birth now living in
New York, who is well-known in America for his drawings and caricatures of
celebrated musicians and composers such as the six reproduced here. He has also
done hundreds of portraits of great modern figures in the theatre, art, and science.
Arnold Schcenberg (Austria) Hector Villa-Lobos (Brazil)
STRAVINSKY
BALLET
SET
Scene from " Les
Noces " one of the
ballets written for Dia-
ghilev's Ballet Russe
company by Igor Stra¬
vinsky, Its premiere
was given in Paris in
1923 when this draw¬
ing was made by Na¬
thalie Gontcharova,
who was responsible
for the setting, the
curtain and costumes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
SOCIETY CALLS THE TUNE (Cont'd.)
The many faces
of modern jazz
"Auprès de ma blonde," from the tarantella to the tango,
passed into the international cultural patrimony.
Folk music, in the old-fashioned sense of the term,
flourishes, if at all, only in regions still shielded from the
mainstream of modern life, though mixed forms of it
naturally continue to evolve everywhere, and with
specially creative vigour in countries with mixed popula¬
tions, such as Brazil or Israel.
Yet the victory of any single "learned" or semi-learned
idiom of music is far from complete. For with the emer¬
gence of an international audience, there also arose an
Industry which sought to cater to as wide a consensus of
its tastes as possible. It is often argued that the products
of this industry "pop" songs, dance music, film music,
etc. are hopelessly debauching contemporary musical
standards by throwing out immense quantities of a
commercial product hastily stitched together from worn
and disparate patches.
A captive public, exposed to such music wherever it goes
at the factory, In airports, over television, in restaur¬
ants, at parties, in cars is having its testhetic responses
blunted by a sort of journalese of sound which panders
to fashionable fads and exploits the most banal, superficial
and conventional reactions of the listener, deliberately
avoiding anything that might conceivably displease at
first hearing.
The situation today strikes many critics as one where
people face only the choice between the remote, in-
J. Gome, Paris
MUSIC EVERYWHERE. Wherever they go today people have
access to music. Music is brought to them constantly by radio, TV,
records and loudspeaker systems. "Pop" songs blare out from juke
boxes like this one (right) in a Parisian cafe with its teen-age
audience. To feed juke boxes, gramophones in the home and disk
jockeys on the radio, millions and millions of records are being
produced. Above, a gramophone factory worker separates recording
plate from matrix with which records will be mass-produced.
tellectualized and difficult work of serious composers and
the half-baked, half-heard leftovers which constitute the
background to daily activities. One consequence of what
has been called "the appalling popularity of music" is to
make the effort at communicating something that is at
once artistically valid and widely accessible an increasingly
delicate task.
BALLET DECOR BY DALI. Ballet with its themes of drama, fairy-tale, fable and life has offered a rich medium
for musical expression. Since the time of Lully, the 17th century French composer, often considered as the first
to make an art of ballet music composition, many great musicians have combined their efforts with those of
choreographers and artists to produce spectacles enchanting equally to eye and ear. Below, a Salvador Dali
painting for a backdrop used in a modernistic ballet "Sentimental Colloquy", first produced in New York in 1944
by the Ballet International Company, with music by Paul Bowles and choreography by André Eglevsky.
4 /<**;
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Alm?^y-Vauthcy
There is also the opinion which asserts that an entirely
new folk idiom has recently arisen, one that is a character¬
istic of our age, and as good an expression of its quality,
as the folk music of earlier, more circumscribed and
simpler cultures. This is jazz. Born of a cross-current of
influences Spanish, French, African, English, Creole,
Protestant hymns, military marches in a country which
is itself a melting-pot of cultures, jazz certainly transcends
frontiers with amazing ease, and seems to mirror current
moods in the most distant places.
Its element of improvisation has about it something of
the tentative, episodic and rapid features of modern life.
Then, too, the interpénétration of jazz and "learned"
music appears significant: if Haydn used folk tunes, a
Milhaud, a Kurt Weill or a Stravinsky turn as naturally
to jazz, while the ideas of Bartok, Ravel, even of Scarlatti,
are not absent from Its "progressive" examples.
A'ttractive though it sounds, there are object-
. ions to this thesis. For jazz itself is com¬
partmentalized: it has its "learned", "'naive" and
"commercial" branches, each appealing to a different
audience. Those who appreciate the first and second
varieties overlap significantly with the audience for class¬
ical music, which is hardly true for the fans of the com¬
mercial variety, strangers to connoisseurship in any shape.
Furthermore, jazz only expresses part of the total range
of experience within the cultures of which it is a product.
It does not even aspire to express them whole, or to
encompass many of their refinements and complexities.
Thus jazz has a layered structure, precisely reflecting that
of modern industrial communities. One extreme is shoddy,
the other esoteric while the middle ground is strewn with
soiled remnants.
If we now try to explain what is going on in sociological
terms, we may say that, as societies have become more
similar to each other at comparable levels, so they have
been further differentiated internally. The arts have
followed suit. People in comparable situations resemble
each other more closely, In their ways of life, their
mentality and their emotional make-up which governs
taste, while being cut off more completely from those
whose experiences are essentially dissimilar, even If they
happen to be neighbours.
While this has no doubt always been the case to some
extent, its repercussions today are much greater than
ever before, more rapid in their impact and on the whole,
more deliberately organized. Despite certain appearances,
there is a lot of spontaneous segregation in the world
based not on force and prejudice so much as on the
perfectly legitimate desire to pursue one's own interests
and one's own temperamental preferences, which has led
to dependence upon indirect and roundabout means of
contact rather than on physical propinquity.
What, in these circumstances, Is likely to be the future
of music? If one can venture a guess on the basis of
visible trends, I should say that music will again tend to
become somewhat anonymous, something of a collabora¬
tive product and that the remaining free-lancers will be
mainly concerned with the technological exploration of
the frontiers of sound.
Why? Because Interest in, and sympathy for the isolat¬
ed person and his problems is declining, displaced by
interest in groups, in associations and in identifiable mass
movements. Also, the percentage of musical participants
(i.e. amateur or professional performers) is declining in
comparison to the total number of "spectators" (i.e.
listeners).
The patronage for music is now in the hands of the
controllers of the great institutions the radio, the cinema,
recording companies, the state itself who are forced to
think in terms of wide public responsibility and the
economics of mass production and marketing. What
is more, the unparalleled accessibility of the standard ^.
CONT'D ON PAGE 13
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
SOCIETY CALLS THE TUNE (Cont'd.)
EXPLORING
NEW FRONTIERS
OF SOUND
In the past half century there have
been many attempts to extend the
frontiers of the world of music. Musi¬
cians have experimented with "concrete
music" and new tonal forms of music,
and even explored the possibilities of
new musical instruments. Photos here
show the recent efforts of two young
Frenchmen, François Baschet, a stringed
instrument maker, and Jacques Lasry,
who have invented startlingly new
types of instruments which bear strange
names such as the "pneumatic guitar",
"echo screen", "crystal organ" and the
"lameliphone". The crystal organ exists
in three tonal ranges, one of which,
the deep crystal, is shown on left. It
has three sounding boards made of
steel or duralumin connected to small
crystal rods which the player rubs
with wetted fingers. The instrument
has been used to play revolutionary
compositions and classical masterpieces.
12
Two hands moving
along a small forest
of rods conjure
sounds from the so¬
prano crystal organ
that are short and
non-resonant.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
y#>
All photos © Almasy
This strange assembly of metallic domes and "lifebuoys"
(above) called "l'homme" (the man) is a new kind of per¬
cussion instrument which produces sad, drawn-out tones.
Left, the workshop where Baschet and Lasry have experi¬
mented with and built their extraordinary new instruments.'
François Baschet inflates a pneumatic guitar (right). One of
the simpler instruments he has devised, it has attracted
many amateur musicians and soon may be mass-produced.
Future dimensions of music
repertory encourages the use of music quite freely to
match the whim of the passing moment. How often do
we not twiddle a knob, or change a record, because we
don't feel like Rachmaninov in the morning, or because
Wagner happens to overwhelm us over tea?
Taking such logic a step further, one can ensure a steady
flow of suitable sound by assembling it functionally
(Music for Expectant Mothers, Relaxing Tunes, Gay
Melodies, the Rhythms of Productivity). Thus one elimi¬
nates the personal projections and tensions which
composers reflect in successive sections of their works, to
obtain a homogenized quantity varied at the behest of
the listener alone. From becoming an art which carries
the listener beyond himself, music is already largely
converted into one which the listener manipulates, so we
may expect its patrons to make the consumer's job even
easier.
By the same token, composers, instead of seeking a style
of their own to give as great a range as possible to what
they Individually wish to express, may endeavour to
discover new sound-combinations (not necessarily made
by instruments) to tickle the fancy of auditors in moods
not yet scaled by the output of their predecessors.
Already, this is the orientation of what is known as
musique concrète.
The vision of squads of sound-engineers turning out
music in response to preferences revealed by opinion polls
and sample surveys is perhaps repulsive. But is it, in
fact, any worse than the possessed genius trying to make
headway against indifference, or the master craftsman
executing a composition to special order?
The whole history of Western music is one of conflict
between the innovators and the conservatives, between
those who reached out for something beyond the already
achieved, and those who were automatically outraged by
any infringement of the established rules of their day.
Possibly, in the coming decades, this conflict will take a
different shape: tension between those who stress music
primarily in its personal and dimension, and
those who develop it along lines of utilitarianism and1_
therapy. Which would be perfectly in accord with the
wider tensions to which modern societies are subject.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
IN DEFENCE
OF SCIENCE-FICTION
by
Arthur C.
Clarke
On September 27 in New Delhi, the Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of Science
was awarded to the British science and science-fiction writer, Arthur C. Clarke.
As tenth winner of this award, Arthur Clarke was also the first interpreter of the
space age to be so honoured. The prize-giving ceremony was held to coincide
with a meeting of the Indian National Commission for Unesco and thus took place
for the first time in the country of Kalinga Prize founder, Mr. B. Patnaik, of the
Orissa Legislative Assembly. Below we publish Arthur Clarke's address delivered
in New Delhi, in which he describes his award as a tribute to his particular field
of writing science-fiction. The idea that artificial satellites might one day be
used for relaying radio and television (now become reality with Telstar) was sug¬
gested by Arthur C. Clarke as early as October 1945 in an article "Extra-Terres¬
trial Relays", published in Wireless World.
14
Universal International
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Paramount 19 54
Long before rockets and artificial satellites went into orbit around the
earth science-fiction writers had already reached the moon and other
planets, travelled to the heart of the earth and explored time. Though
such forward-looking stories have sometimes evoked their share of
scientific scoffing, some have, in fact, become reality. Novels and films
have helped to spread the ideas of spaceflight as in "Conquest of Space'-
(above) and of possible futuristic mishaps as in "The Incredible Shrinking
Man" (left) who gradually diminished to the size of a microbe.
I N addition to the pride I
personally feel on receiving
the Kalinga Prize, I would like to
think that it Is a tribute to the field
of literature in which I have specia¬
lized science-fiction. Although at
least four of the earlier prize-win¬
ners have written some science-fic¬
tion (1), it has been only a minute
and incidental portion of their output.
I can claim that it is a major part
of mine, for I have published just
about as much fiction as non-fiction.
Many scientists, I am sorry to say,
still look down on science-fiction and
lose no opportunity of criticizing it.
For example, they often point out
that ninety percent of science-fic¬
tion is rubbish ignoring the fact
that ninety percent of all fiction is
rubbish. Indeed, I would claim that
the percentage of competent writing
in the science-fiction field is probably
higher than in any other. This is
because much of it is a labour of
love, written by enthusiasts who have
considerable scientific knowledge and
who are often themselves practising
scientists.
What role does science-fiction
(1) Ed. note: Julian Huxley ("The
Tissue Culture King"); Bertrand
Russell (stories from his collection,
"Satan in the Suburbs"); George
Gamow ("Mr. Tomkins in Wonder¬
land" and "Mr. Tomkins Explores the
Atom"); Ritchie Colder ("Forbidden
City").
actually play in the popularization
of "science? Though it often serves
to impart information, I think its
chief value is inspirational rather
than educational. How many young
people have had the wonders of the
universe first opened up to them, or
have been turned to a scientific
career, by the novels of Verne and
Wells? Many distinguished scientists
have paid tribute to the influence of
these great masters, and a careful
survey would, I believe, reveal that
science-fiction is a major factor in
launching many youngsters on a
scientific career.
It is obvious that science-fiction
should be technically accurate, and
there is no excuse for erroneous
information when the true facts are
available. Yet accuracy should not
be too much of a fetish, for it is
often the spirit rather than the
letter that counts. Thus Verne's
From the Earth to the Moon and
A Journey to the Centre of the Earth
are still enjoyable, not only because
Verne was a first-rate story teller,
but because he was imbued with the
excitement of science and could com¬
municate this to his readers. That
many of his "facts" and most of his
theories are now known to be incor¬
rect is not a fatal flaw, for his books
still arouse the sense of wonder.
It is this sense of wonder that
motivates all true scientists, and all
true artists. We encounter it in the
writings of such scientific expositors
as Fabre, Flammarion, Jeans, Rachel
Carson, Loren Eisley, as well as many
of my precursors at this function;
and we meet it again in all scientific
romances that are worthy of the
name. Any man who can read the
opening pages of Wells' The War of
the Worlds or the closing ones of
The Time Machine without a tingling
of the blood is fit only for "treasons,
strategems and spoils."
The cultural impact of science-
fiction has never been properly recog¬
nized, and the time is long overdue
for an authoritative study of its his¬
tory and development. Perhaps this
is a project that Unesco could spon¬
sor, for it is obvious that no single
scholar will have the necessary quali¬
fications for the task. In one field
in particular that of astronautics
the influence of science-fiction has
been enormous. The four greatest
pioneers of spaceflight Tsiolkovsky,
Oberth, Goddard and von Braun all
wrote science-fiction to propagate
their ideas (though they did not
always get it published!).
In spreading the ideas of space¬
flight, science-fiction has undoubtedly
helped to change the world. More
generally, it helps us to face the
strange realities of the universe In
which we live. This is well put in an
article recently sent to me by a
science-fiction "fan" who also hap¬
pens to be a Nobel Prize winner
Dr. Hermann J. Müller, whose disco¬
very of the genetic effects of radia- ^5
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE-FICTION
ON THE SCREEN
The fantastic imagination of science-fiction
writers of yesterday and today is illustrated in
scenes from films shown here, from left to
right : "The Invisible Man" and "The Time
Machine", both by H. G. Wells, "Satellitein
the Sky" and "Earth vs. Flying Saucers".
Transposed to the screen, in recent years this
"literature of a changing world" has made an
even wider impact on the man in the street.
Universal Pictures
Literature of a changing world
tion has inadvertently inspired much
recent science-fiction and made
"mutant" a modern bogey-word.
To quote Dr. Müller (Science-Fic¬
tion as an Escape: The Humanist,
1957, No 6.): "The real world is
Increasingly seen to be, not the tidy
little garden of. our race's childhood,
but the extraordinary, extravagant
universe descried by the eye of
science ...If our art.. .does not explore
the relations and contingencies im¬
plicit in the greater world into
which we are forcing our way, and
does not reflect the hopes and fears
based on these appraisals, then that
art is a dead pretence	But man
will not live without art. In a scien
tific age he will therefore have
science-fiction."
In the same paper, Dr. Müller
points out another valuable service
that this type of literature has per¬
formed. "Recent science-fiction," he
writes, "must be accorded high credit
for being one of the most active
forces in support of equal opportuni-
Science-fiction has encouraged the cosmic viewpoint, quickly making those who read
it realize the absurdity of mankind's present tribal divisions. In the film "This Island
Earth" (below) two inhabitants of a distant planet named Metaluna outside our solar
system return home in their spaceship with two hostages after visiting the earth. Universal International 1956
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
ig) Warner Brothers
M.G.M.
ties, goodwill and co-operation among
all human beings, regardless of their
racial and national origins. Its
writers have been practically unani¬
mous in their adherence to the ideal
of 'one free world'."
That, I think, is inevitable. Anyone
who reads this form of literature
quickly realizes the absurdity of man¬
kind's present tribal divisions.
Science-fiction encourages the cosmic
viewpoint; perhaps this is why it is
not popular among those literary
pundits who have never quite accept¬
ed the Copernican revolution, nor
grown used to the idea that Man
may not be the highest form of life
in the universe. The sooner such
people complete their education, and
re-orientate themselves to the astro¬
nomical realities, the better. And
science-fiction is one of the most
effective tools for this urgent job.
For it is, pre-eminently, the litera¬
ture of change and change is the
only thing of which we can be cer¬
tain today, thanks to the continuing
and accelerating Scientific Revolu¬
tion. What we science-fiction writers
call "mainstream literature" usually
paints a static picture of society, pre¬
senting, as it were, a snapshot of it,
frozen at one moment in time.
Science-fiction, on the other hand,
assumes that the future will be pro¬
foundly different from the past
though it does not, as is often ima¬
gined, attempt to predict that future
in detail. Such a feat Is impossible,
and the occasional direct hits of
Wells and other writers are the result
of luck as much as judgement.
But by mapping out possible
futures, as well as a good many
impossible ones, the science-fiction
writer can do a great service to the
community. He encourages in his
readers flexibility of mind, readiness
to accept and even welcome change
in one word, adaptability. Perhaps
no attribute is more important in
this age. The dinosaurs disappeared
because they could not adapt to their
changing environment. We shall
disappear if we cannot adapt to an
environment which contains space¬
ships and thermonuclear weapons.
Sir Charles Snow ends his famous
essay Science and Government by
stressing the vital importance of
"the gift of foresight." He points
out that men often have wisdom
without possessing foresight. Per¬
haps we science-fiction writers some¬
times show foresight without wisdom;
but at least we undoubtedly cío have
foresight, and it may rub off on to
the community at large.
Before concluding, I would like to
take this unique occasion of the first
Kalinga presentation on Indian soil,
to speak about the promotion of the
scientific outlook in the East. Though
this task is important enough in the
West, it is even more desperately
urgent here. Two of the greatest
evils which afflict Asia, and keep
millions in a state of physical, men¬
tal and spiritual poverty, are Fana¬
ticism and Superstition. Science, in
its cultural as well as its technolo¬
gical sense, is the great enemy of
both; it can provide the only weapons
that will overcome them and lead
whole nations to a better life.
For Fanaticism is incompatible
with the open-minded, inquiring
spirit of science with the readiness
Columbia Pictures
to accept the discipline of external
reality, even if it conflicts with one's
personal hopes and beliefs. The
motto of the fanatic is "Don't con¬
fuse me with the facts I've made
up my mind." This is the exact
antithesis of the Scientific Outlook.
As for Superstition most of us can
remember, though too many people
have already forgotten, the events of
last February 5. On that date a
natural and inevitable grouping of
the planets (that has happened about
twenty times since the days of the
Kalinga empire!) caused needless
fear to millions. How many lakhs
if not crores of rupees were then
expended to ward off astral influen¬
ces? And most of that money was
spent by families who could ill
afford it.
That was a spectacular example of
the evils of superstition, but there
are countless others unnoticed by the
world. Recently, not far from my
home in Ceylon, a villager was bitten
by a snake. He could get no medical
treatment, because the date was
inauspicious; and so he died.
Two years ago Monsieur Jean Ros¬
tand, referred to India as "that
great nation which welcomes the
future without rejecting the past."
That is a good policy for any nation
as long as it realizes that there are
things in the past that must be
rejected. Science, which after all is
only common-sense raised to the
n'th degree, can tell us what to pre¬
serve and what to reject. Heed its
voice if not for your own sakes,
then for the sake of the lovely, dark-
eyed children of Asia and Africa,
who are born in millions every year
and die in millions the next. Their
only hope of a better future lies in
Science combined with Wisdom and
Foresight. I shall be happy indeed *-j
if any writings of mine have helped
towards this goal.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
1 ,,:'-,
DIGGING
FOR HISTORY
An account of excavation
in Nubia during 1961-62
by Rex Keating
-^ A
J\
BRILLIANTLY-COLOURED FRESCO¬
ES as fresh as the day they were executed
1,000 years ago were found several months
ago on the walls of a Christian church at
Faras in Sudanese Nubia. Here, Professor
C. Michalowski, leader of the Polish Expe¬
dition examines one of the most remark¬
able of these murals. It depicts the crown¬
ed figure of the Archangel Michael protect¬
ing Shadrach, Meshach and Abednego
from the flames of the fiery furnace into
which they were cast by King Nebuchad¬
nezzar. Below, another of the murals at
the Faras excavation site is brought to light.
>T»- *"V
?5£*r* **^? - y 4ifeí¿ ¿$5***
18
G. Gerster, Zurich
small felucca traces an erratic course through
kthe broken waters of the Second Cataract. It
swings perilously close to a big rapid named Kabuka,
whose roar fills the air with sound and then slips to safety
under the lee of a rocky islet.
From it springs a young man, Hans Nordstrom. He is
an archaeologist and member of the Unesco Mission to
Sudanese Nubia which is engaged on an archaeological
survey of sections of the Cataract area on behalf of the
Sudan Government. The islet, Shahgil, is one of many
which give to the Cataract its well-merited name "The
Belly of Stone".
On many of these islands are the remains of churches
and settlements dating from the twilight of Christianity
in Nubia; some conceal traces of the much earlier Meroitic
civilization, as on Gumnarti where in 1962 the survey team
led by Dr. W. Adams found and excavated a Meroitic
village.
But Shahgil is a tiny Island, too small for habitation,
and Nordstrom had little hope of its surrendering
anything more than had the score of similar islets over
which he had scrambled fruitlessly during the last few
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
weeks. He was about to climb down from the summit to
the boat when his trained eye was attracted to a crevice
about five metres above the present high-water level of
the Nile. A quick examination convinced him that he
had stumbled on a neolithic "fishing industry" site.
Beneath a sand deposit was a layer of fish bones and
potsherds some twenty centimetres deep and a thick layer
of ash. The bones were large, similar to those of the
big Nile perch of today. This it seems was no habitation
site but a camp to which the fishermen returned
seasonally to fish the big rapid nearby. The fish thus
caught they smoked on the spot and removed the flesh,
leaving the bones behind when they departed for their
homes on the mainland.
Those fishermen casting their nets around six thousand
years ago lived on the threshold of recorded history and
the discovery may establish a bridge between Neolithic
Sudan and pre-historic and archaic Egypt. One of
Egypt's archaic kings, Djer of the First Dynasty, has left
an inscription the oldest in Nubia yet found on the Hill
of Sheikh Suleiman not a dozen miles from the Neolithic
fishing camp.
This shadowy sovereign, as the inscription records, sent
a military expedition to Nubia, around five thousand years
ago. Thereafter the mists of time and superstition close
in over Nubia for centuries and do not clear until the
intrepid Princes of Elephantine, guardians of Egypt's
southern frontier with Nubia in the Sixth Dynasty of the
Old Kingdom Period, led their expeditions from Elephan¬
tine where now stands modern Assuan, up-river into the
"Land of the Ghosts" as they fearfully termed the awe¬
some territories to the south. This was around 2 400 B.C.,
and the great caravan captains of that era established
trade links with inner Africa which became vital to
Egypt's economy and which were to endure, with minor
interruptions only, for the next two thousand years.
The tales of their exploits are graven on the walls of
their .tombs overlooking Elephantine Island where they
can be seen to this day by any visitor who takes the
trouble to climb the steep cliff to the row of sepulchres
that pierce the rock-face. To these men, then, has gone
the credit for opening up the road to that stretch of the
Nile which today is known as Nubia, and beyond. Or so
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
NUBIA 1962 (Cont'd)
Blast furnaces in the 'Land of the Ghosts'
it was believed, and this belief is reflected in every pub¬
lished work on early Egyptian history.
Then an archaeologist's wife taking her dog for its
evening walk along the banks of the Nile noticed some¬
thing in the sand which must lead to a revolutionary re¬
assessment of Egypt's early relations with Nubia. What
Mrs. Emery had seen was a concentration of copper slag,
and it led in the winter of 1961-1962 to the discovery by
Professor W.B. Emery, who leads the Egypt Exploration
Society's Expedition at Buhen opposite Wadi Haifa, of
a fully-fledged Egyptian industrial town.
It was a town devoted to the smelting of copper, and
the excavators found mortars and stone hammers, and
crucibles with pieces of pure copper that had splashed
over the edges, still lying where they had fallen some
forty-six centuries ago. They found the moulds and
finally uncovered the blast furnaces used for smelting
the copper.
IosT important though, were the pieces of in¬
scribed pottery which were unearthed and the
many clay sealings of the type used to secure the bindings
around papyrus documents. These sealings demonstrated
that the town was in official contact with Egypt and bore
the names of kings of the Fourth and Fifth Dynasties in¬
cluding those of the builders of the Pyramids of Gizeh, near
Cairo. So that when the first stone of the Great Pyramid
was laid, Egyptian vessels were loading pure copper ingots
at the quays of an Egyptian town deep inside Nubia. And
all this was taking place at least two centuries before the
first of the great caravan captains of the Sixth Dynasty
was born.
Not least among the tantalizing vist&s opened by this
discovery is the whereabouts of the source of the copper
ore which is of very high quality. The Egyptians, an in¬
tensely practical and conservative people, always worked
their copper as near as possible to its source, a source
which must have been considerable since the furnaces
were worked for at least a hundred years. Copper is a
valuable commodity; will the mines be located and if
found will they prove to be still rich in yield?
At the very end of the 1962 digging season, Professor
Emery cut a trench across the whole town-site and came
across buildings one below the other down to a depth
of four metres. The large size of the mud-bricks in the
lowest levels provided a clue to their date, which may
extend back to the Archaic Period to the First and
Second Dynasties. Next season's digging at Buhen
promises exciting revelations.
To add point to Professor Emery's revolutionary findings
is the discovery, made also in 1962 by the Franco/Argen¬
tine Expedition led by Professor J. Vercoutter, of an
Archaic Egyptian cemetery not twenty miles from Buhen
containing sealings of the First Dynasty.
All in all, therefore, it now looks as though the
Egyptians had a strong foothold in Nubia possibly five
hundred years earlier than the historians tell us, and that
they lost control of the territory so completely that by the
time of the explorers of the Sixth Dynasty Nubia had
20 receded into legend.
In the first weeks of this year, on top of a rocky hill
ten miles north of Buhen I watched some twenty Nubian
workmen with ropes and wooden beams heave and strain
at a great rock lying buried in rubble. The rock stirred
and excitement mounted until with a mighty heave it
lifted out of the hole, teetered for a moment, then toppled
down the side of the hill amid shouts of delight.
he hill, called Sidi Qurnein, stands some two
hundred yards from the west bank of the Nile
and its flanks merge into a desert which stretches across
an entire continent to the Atlantic, three thousand miles
away. Here there can be no life save that bequeathed by
the river surging north to the distant Mediterranean.
This is the spot where in the sixteenth century B.C., a
prince, Prince Amenemhet, of what is now called Debeira,
chose to excavate his tomb, and here, three thousand
five hundred years later a group of archaeologists from
Scandinavia re-opened it. When the great stone fell it
revealed the top of a shaft cut vertically in the rock to a
depth of twenty-two feet and at the bottom was a passage
leading off into darkness. This is the moment which
provides the field archaeologist with his greatest thrill;
will the tomb be intact or will the ancient robbers have
got in first?
The passage was forty feet long and its floor was
covered with pottery vases, among them a plaque inscribed
with the figure of the goddess Nut and several canopic
jars bearing the name of Amenemhet's brother, Djehuty-
hotep, Prince of Teh-khet, whose tomb is across the river
on the opposite bank. The burial chamber was empty
but several small objects left behind by the robbers
hinted at the richness of the original burial.
he really valuable find was in the tomb chapel
a little further down the hill where Professor
Säve-Söderbergh, who leads the Scandinavian Joint Expe¬
dition, found leaning against the wall of the shrine, the
finest stela yet discovered in Nubia. On the grey granite
are the names and titles of Prince Amenemhet and the
beautifully incised hieroglyphs are filled with yellow
paint as fresh in colour as the day it was mixed.
Prince Amenemhet and Djehuty-hotep were Nubians
who had become so Egyptianized that there was nothing
in their names, titles and form of burial to distinguish
them from true Egyptian grandees of the Eighteenth
Dynasty, living around 1500 B.C. The brothers illustrate
the final stage In the long process of Egyptian domination
of Nubia, a process which had begun about a thousand
years earlier, in the period when the Princes of Elephan¬
tine of the Sixth Dynasty were leading their expeditions
south into the Land of the Ghosts.
This was the time when a mysterious people, known to
archaeologists as the "C-group" to distinguish them from
their predecessors the "A" and "B-group" peoples,
appeared in Nubia, possibly from the south or west. They
were a people well-organized and skilled in the art of
war and were almost certainly the enemy against
whom the Egyptian kings of the Twelfth Dynasty built
CONT'D ON PAGE 22
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
0. Gnri^eî, Zurich
CATHEDRAL IN THE DESERT. Under
-a giant mound of Sand at Faras, Polish
^ have discovered the remains I
of what was once the greatest centre of,
'Christianity in this part of Nubia. Atl
M one end of its cathedral they uncovered
- the tomb (entrance shown in foreground)
r of Bishop Johannes, Its probable founder
and first bishop who died in the year 606.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
NUBIA 1962 (Cont'd)
Thirty tombs unearthed per day
around 2000 B.C. the line of protective fortresses along
the length of the Second Cataract, fortresses which even
today can excite wonder by their sheer strength and
ingenuity of design.
Yet within five hundred years of their arrival in the
area this formidable people apparently vanished from
Nubia without trace. Intensive excavation of their
cemeteries, however, during the 1962 season has solved
the riddle of their fate. The area of Debeira, where the
Danes, Finns, Norwegians and Swedes of the Scandinavian
expedition were at work is particularly rich in C-group
remains.
Working against timefor all these cemeteries are
doomed to be swallowed by the flood waters of the High
Damand using the latest tools of field archaeology, the
Scandinavians were clearing and recording up to thirty
graves a day. The clearance of several C-group ceme¬
teries was also undertaken by the Spanish Expedition
under the direction of Prof. Blanco y Caro.
he thousands of objects recovered and the
design of the tombs themselves have revealed
how over the centuries the C-group culture was peacefully,
yet inexorably, absorbed by that of the Pharaohs, so that
by 1500 B.C. the native princes of Debeira have become
culturally indistinguishable from Egyptians.
Unfortunately the early C-group people, who were great
cattle breeders, seem to have had no written language
so that all that is known of their customs derives from
their curious circular graves. Buried outside several such
graves, near Faras, which lies just on the Sudan side of
the frontier with Egypt, Hans Nordstrom found a number
of ox skulls.
This was a common practice among the early C-group
people, but what made the Faras skulls interesting was
that the tip of each left horn had been bent downwards
and forwards artificially. This custom of bending down
the left horn of cattle is known from tomb paintings to
have been practised during the Old Kingdom Period
around 2500 B.C. and much later during the Meroitic
around 600 B.C. What is remarkable is that the Nilotic
peoples of the Southern Sudan the Dinkas and Shilluks
follow the custom to this day; it is, they say, a tradition
that came to them a very long time ago.
Houses of the C-group people are extremely rare so
there was excitement when In 1962 three C-group dwellings
were found by the Scandinavians and a fourth by the
expedition of the Oriental Institute of Chicago. So, pains¬
takingly, the field archaeologists working in Nubia are
piecing together the history of this enigmatic C-group
people. They have discovered what became of them,
how their culture was completely absorbed by that of
their great northern neighbour, but have yet to solve the
riddle of the origins of the C-group.
Buhen was the military headquarters of the Second
Cataract area and nerve-centre of the dozen or so fort¬
resses built around 2000 B.C. to keep the C-group people
in check. Five hundred years or so later Queen Hatshep-
sut and the Pharaoh Thutmose III built a stone temple
inside the citadel of the old fortress. Today it is the finest
temple in Sudanese Nubia and is one of the monuments
22 scheduled for removal to safety before the flood waters
close over it. Professor Emery, working on behalf of the
Unesco-Keating
Egypt Exploration Society, hopes to start work on this
rescue operation at the end of this year.
Moving inscribed and painted walls and columns which
have been weakened by exposure to thirty-five centuries
of burning sunshine and bitter nights, is an extremely
tricky business and Professor Emery proposes to take a
leaf out of the ancient builders' book. To dismantle the
temple he will in effect reverse the process they used in
building it.
The temple will be filled with sand and the stones
manhandled by local Nubian workmen straight onto the
cushioning surface without the necessity of lifting. As
each course of stone is removed so the level of sand "will
be correspondingly reduced until the temple pavement is
reached. This method will obviate the use of machinery
which, apart from being difficult and expensive to get to
Nubia, could damage the extremely friable sandstone.
The area beneath the existing temple is practically
the only part of the fortress which has not been systema¬
tically cleared, and immediately the temple has been
removed Professor Emery will start digging down to the
original foundations of the citadel. He may uncover a
second templeor find nothing of interest!
Another temple threatened by the forthcoming flooding
is Kalabsha, largest in Nubia after Abu Slmbel. It is a
Graeco-Roman edifice thirty-five miles south of Assuan.
Unlike Abu Simbel which can only be protected in situ,
Kalabsha will, despite its great size, be dismantled stone
by stone and responsibility for this most delicate oper¬
ation has been assumed by the Federal Republic of Ger¬
many. Festooned in scaffolding, the temple today is
being systematically taken apart for reconstruction
elsewhere in Egypt.
Five miles upstream from Buhen and on the island of
Meinarti is a large mound believed to conceal another
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
DIAMOND DRILL IN
TEMPLE. In the Great
Temple of Abu Simbel
tests have been made
to check strains in the
rock during preparatory
studies of the plan to
encase the entire temple
in a concrete block and
raise it 200 feet up the
side of the mountain
from which it is hewn,
thus saving it from the
invading waters of the
new Aswan Dam. Right,
diamond-tipped drill
operated by a Swedish
engineer cuts holes in
the temple walls. The
drillings will be used to
house Instruments for
measuring the internal
pressures in the rock.
Left, high over Sudanese
Nubia an automatic cam¬
era is used for a large
scale aerial archaeological
survey. With this all-
seeing eye, scores of
hitherto unsuspected ar¬
chaeological sites have
recently been discovered.
Unesco-Keating
of the Twelfth Dynasty fortresses. The mound was, by
the way, used as a gun platform during the River War
against the Dervishes towards the end of the nineteenth
century. Meinarti will be excavated by the Egypt Ex¬
ploration Society when their work at Buhen is completed.
Nother of the fortresses, Mirgissa, some ten
Lmiles south of Meinarti, is to be excavated
next year, by the Franco/Argentine Expedition. Already
the foundations of an Egyptian town of the period have
been located on the banks of the river below and when
this is dug it may well reveal valuable indications of how
the inhabitants of a Nubian garrison town lived some
four thousand years ago.
At Serra, a mile or so inside the Sudan border with
Egypt, is yet another fort and in 1962 it was cleared down
to the foundations, and the layout of the fortifications
was thoroughly examined and recorded, by the Expedi¬
tion of the University of Chicago's Oriental Institute,
directed by Dr. Keith B. Seele.
Inside the fortifications awaiting excavation next season
are several interesting buildings of early Christian date.
They are contemporary with the large Christian town
across the river on the west bank. Here the University
of Ghana Expedition under Professor P. L. Shlnnie has
uncovered an astonishing complex of buildings. What
started as a mudbrick church around the seventh century
of the Christian era grew over the next eight hundred
years into a large town with layer upon layer of buildings
so numerous that, according to Professor Shinnie, it would
need at least ten seasons to clear it.
Nothing could Illustrate more vividly than this town
the intensive occupation of Nubia during Christian times,
from its conversion under the Emperor Justinian in the
sixth century to its final eclipse by Islam in the fourteenth
century. Indeed only a few miles down-stream from
Shinnie's "dig" is Faras, ancient capital of Nobatia, the
northernmost of the three early Christian kingdoms of
Nubia and the Sudan.
Here under mountains of sand lie dozens of ancient sites
covering an area of some five square miles, and here
during 1961-1962 the Polish Expedition led by Professor
C. Michalowski has been making spectacular discoveries.
The huge mound on the river's edge at Faras, on which
the expedition's members have been concentrating, has
now been revealed as nothing less than a great church
and associated buildings, containing brilliantly coloured
frescoes as magnificent as they are wonderfully preserved.
The tombs of at least eight of the Bishops of Faras (its
ancient name was Pachoras) have been found, the earliest
being that of Johannes who died at the age of 82 in the
year 606 and who was probably the first bishop of Faras.
Beneath the church are the stones of a temple built by
the Pharaoh Thutmose III two thousand years earlier and
below that, possibly, another Middle Kingdom fortress.
Nearby is a fortress of the Meroitic period, not yet dug.
Truly, Faras is a field archaeologists' paradise!
When Christianity came to Nubia there was living there
another of those alphabetically Identified cultures, in this
case the '"X-group" people. Like the C-group, their
origins are unknown and they have left no written lan¬
guage. The unrobbed tombs of their kings were dis¬
covered at Ballana and Qustul some fifteen miles north
of Faras on the Egyptian side of the border.
That was in 1931 and W. B. Emery assisted by L. P.
Kirwan cleared scores of tombs which yielded a fantastic
quantity and variety of valuable objects. In 1961 Emery
did it again, finding two large unrobbed tomb magazines 23
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
NUBIA 1962 (Cont'd)
Footprints 15 centuries old
in an X-group cemetery at Kasr Ibrim, north of Abu
Simbel.
X-group cemeteries are common in Nubia and several
were dug by most expeditions in the 1962 season, but the
huge tumulus-graves were usually found plundered. A
number of bodies came to light, however, in many cases
rather too well preserved by the bone-dry sand of Nubia
to be comfortably handled.
In one of these cemeteries the Unesco mission found in
a trench alongside one of the tumuli thirty-six neatly
stacked baskets abandoned or forgotten by the labourers
who made the mound some fifteen hundred years ago.
They were perfectly preserved and look very much like
the baskets one can buy nowadays in Wadi Haifa market.
In a grave nearby were several pieces of bread.
This X-group cemetery is on a plain consisting of a
deep deposit of greyish sand intermixed with shells,
clearly the alluvial deposit of an ancient river. The
deposit slopes upwards towards the surface and while
digging another of the graves, Nordstrom found below
the top stratum of sand a number of footprints of adults,
children and camels, following what appeared to be a
path in the direction of the river which nowadays Is at
least a kilometre away.
The footprints were about a metre below the surface and
Nordstrom followed them down for about six metres to
where they disappeared under the next lower alluvial
deposit. The footprints being beneath the graves show
that the people and animals who made them lived at the
very beginning of the X-group period or immediately
before it.
The footprints were no more than half a dozen miles
from the Neolithic "fishing industry" described at the
beginning of this article, yet in time they are separated
by fifty centuries and more. This seems a tremendous
weight of years and, in truth, it very nearly spans the
whole of man's recorded history. But to the pre-histor-
ians and geologists of the Columbia University Expedi
tion led by Dr. Ralph Solecki and Dr. Rhodes W. Fair-
bridge, a figure such as this is insignificant.
Surveying the east bank of the river from the Second
Cataract down to the frontier in 1962, they found number¬
less artifacts, "workshops" and habitation sites indicating
that in Palaeolithic times this reach of the Nile was
heavily populated. All these remains among them were
two fossilized skeletons, probably of homo-sapiens came
from the tops of eroded hills that stand in the desert a
mile or so back from the Nile.
hese hills are really' terraces and are all «that
remain of the ancient plateau down through
which the Nile has cut its way for around one hundred
and fifty feet. Fossil soil and mineralized roots of plants
led the geologists in the expedition to the conclusion that
the present bed of the Nile is no more than 25,000 or
30,000 years old, and that the surrounding desert is an
even more recent feature of the landscape.
The pre-historians visited Abu Simbel, which lies twenty
miles or so down-river from the Egyptian/Sudan frontier,
and on the hills above the temple they found many Stone-
Age artifacts.
There is reason to believe that the mountain of Abu
Simbel was regarded as a holy-place long before the
masons and sculptors of Rameses II fashioned the rock-
face into two of the most splendid temples to come
down to us from the past. In 1962 I made a pilgrimage to
this shrine of Rameses, my second in two years. But how
changed was the scene when I stepped onto the beach in
the first light of dawn !
A pneumatic drill flung back echoes from the cliff face
and to its din was soon added the roar of diesel engines.
Nor was this all. The narrow strip of beach was packed
with men, women and children laden with cameras, and
drawn up at the water's edge were the three large tourist
steamers that had brought them to see the temples.
Ç) R. Keating
'
24
GRAVEYARD FIND by Scandinavian archaeo¬
logists near Debeira (left) is one of many which
help specialists to reconstruct the life and customs
of Nubian peoples who left no written history.
In this grave were the bodies of a woman and a
child. Specialist here is removing a gold mask
from the woman's skull. Below, a cache of baskets
discovered in a cemetery on the shores of the
Second Cataract of the Nile by a Unesco Mission.
Left by workmen who built the tomb 1,500 years
ago, baskets look much like those that can still
be bought in nearby market at Wadi Haifa.
Nordstrom-Unesco
-ííÜE
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
"
R. Keating PRINCE'S TOMB. At Debeira West (above) Sudanese workmen, watched by Professor T. Save
Söderbergh, leader of a joint Scandinavian expedition, heave and strain at a great rock blocking the
burial shaft leading to the tomb of Prince Amenemhet, a 16th century B.C. Nubian ruler.
Nearby, barges and lighters were unloading timber,
scaffolding and masses of other equipment. Rows of
tents lined the bottom of the cliff and among them
technicians and workmen were already astir. Truly Abu<
Simbel had undergone a metamorphosis in the two years
since the Nubian Campaign started.
I went into the Great Temple and there in one of the
innermost chambers was an even more startling intrusion
from the twentieth century. At one end of the narrow
rock-cut chamber an ultra-modenx. piece of machinery
was filling the place with sound, so that one could imagine
that the very figures of the gods staring down from all
sides were trembling with the vibrations of the diamond-
tipped drill. Bending over it, in the glare of a spotlight,
was a young Swedish engineer, seemingly oblivious of the
wild incongruity of the spectacle.
The machine was cutting smooth cylinders of sandstone
from walls, ceiling and floor to make way for sensitive
instruments. With these a group of mining engineers
from Sweden were to measure the vital forces which
exerting pressures within the mass of rock hold the
temple in balance and which, if disturbed haphazardly,
could bring about its collapse.
The lifting of such great masses of rock, the larger
that containing the temple of Rameses weighing around
a quarter of a million tons, to a height of two hundred feet
and more, represents a feat of engineering that is breath¬
taking. Yet for two years now, men representing a score
of disciplines and as many countries have converged on
the temples and have probed and surveyed, analysed and
calculated.
The science and technology that can put a man into
orbit and fling rockets at the moon is more than equipped
to preserve even so fragile a monument as Abu Simbel.
The world's technical resources stand ready, only the
funds are needed to launch the most spectacular' rescue
operation of our time.
Rex Keating of Unesco's Radio Section has devoted
many years to the study of the history and archaeology of
ancient Egypt. He has travelled widely in the Sudan and
in Egypt and other countries of the Middle East where he
lived for many years. Mr. Keating has led several Unesco
radio missions into the areas of Nubia to be flooded by
the Nile and again visited Nubia earlier this year to
gather material for the above article. His profusely
illustrated book, "Twilight of the Gods" on the same
subject is to be published this month in the United King¬
dom by Rupert Hart-Davis Ltd. (42/-) and in the U.S.
by Harcourt, Brace and World, Inc. (About $ 7.50).
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
Macaws and Toucan...
with South American children
Pigeons... and
children of Venice
FESTIVAL OF BIRDS
In a series of five paintings about
two of the most fascinating inhabi¬
tants of our planet children and
birds Roser Agell, a young Spanish
woman has created UNICEF greet¬
ing card designs that are gay
and brilliantly colourful. Each
design in "The Festival of Birds"
captures perfectly the delight
taken by youngsters ¡n winning
the trust of their feathered friends.
UNICEF
Peacock... and
Indian children
Cardinal and Chickadees...
with North American children
Flamingo and Crowned Crane...
with African children
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
'
'fëmutâtâ
CEREMONIAL DANCE by the young Brazzaville (Congo) artist, François Thango
GREETING CARDS
Through its programmes to help govern¬
ments meet the urgent needs of their
children for medical care and adequate
food, UNICEF (United Nations Children's
Fund) is currently reaching 60million children
and their mothers. The opportunity to
have a personal share in these programmes ' .
given by UNICEF greeting cards which have
raised nearly $5 million since they were
put on sale in 1950. In 1961-62, 21.5
million cards were sold in over 1 00 countries.
This year it is hoped to increase this figure
to 25 million. The 1962/63 cards comprise
1 2 designs (some of which are reproduced
here) by seven artists. Representative of a
new group of African painters, known as
the Poto-Poto (a district in the city of
Brazzaville, Congo) school are Raphael
Mounkala (Blessing of the Hunt) and François
Thango (Ceremonial Dance). A teen-age
artist, Garya Mahmoud, of Egypt, has con¬
tributed "Joy of Living", a detail from one
of her weavings. U.S. artist Arnold Blanch
has contributed two designs, "The Herald "
and "The Pilgrims" and another U.S. painter,
octogenarian Leo Schutzman has donated
"Winter Carnival ". Swiss artist, Max
Hunziker is represented by "Compassion",
symbolizing the United Nations. Finally,
Roser Agell of Spain, well-known for her
murals, frescoes and paintings, has designed
a series of five under the title "The Festival
of Birds" (see opposite page). UNICEF cards
come in boxes of ten~at $1.25 (U.S.A);
7/6 (U.K.) and 5 NF (France) per box
each box sold can provide enough DDT to
protect five children from malaria for a
year or one child with a daily glass of milk
for eight months.
For further information, orders, etc.,
write UNICEF Greeting Card Fund, 1 3
Heddon Street, London W.1 ; United Na¬
tions Association in Canada, Committee for
UNICEF, 280 Bloor Street West, Toronto 5,
Ontario (Att. Mrs. G. Richards); U.S. Com¬
mittee for UNICEF, POB 22, Church Street
Station, New York 8, N¡Y. (Att. Miss Olga
Gechas) or UNICEF, Service des Cartes de
Vrux, 24, rue Borghèse, Neuilly-sur-Seine,
France.
THE PILGRIMS
by Arnold Blanch (U.S.A.)
WINTER CARNIVAL by
U.S. artist Leon Schutzman
JOY OF LIVING by 16 year old
Garya Mahmoud (Egypt)
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The anatomy of underdevelopment (part 3)
THE RISE AND FALL
OF GREAT CIVILIZATIONS
The Western world has not always a full understanding of the past
achievements in science and technology of other peoples who, how¬
ever, did not experience the scientific and industrial revolution that
has given birth to the modern technological world. Some of the
former accomplishments of these peoples along with the problems
raised by traditional attitudes in the transition from a rural culture
to a machine-conscious urbanized society are discussed in this, the
third article in a series which began publication in our July-August
issue. They are taken from a new study produced by the United
Nations and shortly to be published under the title "Aspects of Under¬
development: The Background to Freedom from Hunger."
28
he question has often been asked why certain
areas of the globe isaw the rise of "modern"
scientific and technological knowledge and others did
not.
It is a commonplace that the fundamental discoveries
which made civilization possiblefire-making, tool-
making, agriculture, building, calculating, writing, money-
were all apparently made outside the area which has
given us the marvels of modern science. Nor were the
mathematical and scientific concepts upon which modern
industrial society rests, themselves of Western origin, as
is so often believed.
Before the Christian era, peoples such as the Egyptians,
the Babylonians, the Chinese, the Hindus and the Greeks
all made important contributions to human thought and
to practical engineering. It is likely that today's world
has inherited only a fraction of the vast store of
knowledge accumulated by earlier peoples. Much may
have been lost, like the marvellous art of the gem carvers
which disappeared with the Roman Empire, after more
than 2,000 years of achievement, or like the stained glass
techniques of Chartres and the Sainte Chapelle, which are
the despair of modern craftsmen. If this is the case, we
shall never know how often we tread in the footsteps of
some daring, but forgotten, thinker whose papyri
parchments or clay tablets have returned to dust.
However that may be, the modern Western world has
not always a full understanding even of those achievements
of other peoples about which no doubt exists.
Few save professional archaeologists realize the scale on
which the peoples of the Ancient East carried out such
engineering projects as irrigation schemes. In the
Twelfth Dynasty of Egypt, the Pharaoh Amenemhet III
brought much of the Nile Valley under cultivation, causing
its waters, when they reached a dangerous flood level, to
be diverted into the escape reservoir of a depression in
the Fayyum which his engineers converted into an artifi¬
cial lake of great dimensions. At about the same time,
the Babylonians brought the river Euphrates under
control and caused its waters to flow into artificial ponds
covering 650 square miles, in which the water stood
twenty-five feet deep during the flood season.
For scores of generations, the Chinese worked their
miracles with jade, bronze, ivory and silk in almost
complete isolation from the cultures of Europe. Mean¬
while, they were inventing the mariner's compass,
gunpowder and printing and making other discoveries far
in advance of the rest of the world, while the Great Wall
which they were building still remains, in the second half
of the twentieth century, the largest work erected by man
on this planet.
Very early in recorded history, India's craftsmen
developed a variety of marvellous skills. Ancient Rome
was a market for Indian fabrics so delicate that it was
said they were invisible when moistened and laid on the
ground. Across the Atlantic, the Aztecs of Central
America evolved a calendar which has been called more
accurate than our own. The precursors of the Incas in
the high Andes built walls of huge dressed stones, so
skillfully laid without cement that, after nearly twenty
centuries, it is impossible to insert a knifeblade between
them. Later the Incas themselves constructed a road
system along the high Andes, many hundreds of miles in
length, which is still one of the engineering marvels of
the world.
NOT one of these astonishing cultures produced
I what we understand as an industrial revo¬
lution. From the time of the Greeks, some of the finest
products of China and India found their way to Western
markets but, unlike our machine civilization, the cultures
which found such perfect expression in them exercised
little influence on other peoples.
The Arabs, during a relatively brief but brilliant flower¬
ing, bequeathed to Europe much of the inherited science
of Ancient Greece and made fundamental contributions of
their own in the fields of chemistry (an Arabic word) and
mathematics. The figures now used in calculation by
Western scientists, financiers and village schoolchildren
were brought to Europe from India by Arab mathemati¬
cians, and displaced the clumsier Roman numerals.
No one can say with confidence why the impulse of
Arab science and learning withered, for we are here
dealing with the little understood problems of the rise and
fall of civilizations. What is certain is that the spirit of
inquiry and experiment first fostered by the Ionian Greeks
later passed, by way of the Arabs, to various European
peoples, and that the birth of the "modern" technological
world was entirely a European phenomenon.
It looks as if the world is now entering upon a phase
in which non-Western peoples are about to be drawn once
more into the field of scientific and engineering progress.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
@ Almasy ENGINEERS FOR INDIA. India boasts one of the most modern institutes of technology in Asia with the
recent completion of the Indian Institute of Technology in Bombay shown here. Established with the help
of U. N. Technical Assistance funds, the institute can accommodate up to 2,000 students. Nine hundred
students and 150 trainees are already taking courses. Unesco has spent since I955 nearly $1 million
on specialists, $3 million to provide scientific equipment and $200,000 for scholarships. Nineteen
Unesco specialists are working on the staff. The institute will be officially inaugurated later this year.
With the great stress now being laid upon the training of
research workers and engineers and the vast increase in
the pool of human talent which the spread of education
will open up outside the Western world, it is tempting to
speculate on the immense advances which the next
hundred years may witness.
As the impulse of the Moslem thinkers waned, a deep
stirring began in eleventh and twelfth-century Europe.
New ideas, new ways of thought and possibilities of living
continued to present themselves, until the life of the
Western European peoples was affected in 'all spheres,
from the conditions on which a tenant farmer held his
acres to the technique of portrait painting.
Then, in the fifteenth-centuryand still more in the
sixteenthcame the great explosion. Henry the Navi¬
gator began the patronage of seafarers which was to lead
to Columbus, Vasco de Gama, Magellan and the new maps
of an unsuspected world. Giotto had shown the way, but
now came Leonardo da Vinci and Michelangelo. The rare
personal touches which a mediaeval memoir writer
allowed himself blossom into the ironic self-exploration of
sr Montaigne. Cervantes writes the first great novel- of
Europe, though not of the world, and Shakespeare
gathers up in himself the resources of an age, and of
every age. Bacon and Descartes lay the foundation of
modern thought. Rembrandt for the first time puts all
experience into the lights and shadows of an aging face.
Nothing quite like this was happening in the other
cultures of the world. Europe's intellectual and spiritual
experiments at this time were associated with changes in
Western man's relation to his fellow citizens, in which
economic elements played an important part. Especially
in England, society was moving from a static condition
centred on the country gentleman into a dynamic phase
in which the merchant was working and working with
grim persistence toward supremacy. The great explorers
of the fifteenth and sixteenth centuries we're advance
guards of commerce. Columbus won support, and sailed,
because he believed that he could open a more profitable
route for trade with India.
One immediate result of the discovery of the New World
was a flow of gold and silver into the treasuries of Europe.
Economic historians have shown how this new supply of
the precious metals released fresh energies in many
departments of European life. It did more than help to
finance new merchant ventures and to pay for more goods
offered for sale. It led to the endowment of numerous
public institutions such as schools, which opened the doors
of learning and opportunity to many, and so helped to
cultivate the resources of Europe's most gifted minds.
Shakespeare's grammar school at Stratford-on-Avon was
endowed in this way about a century before his time.
There is reason to think that a good many inventors In 29
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
UNDERDEVELOPMENT (Cont'd)
Revolutions in
farming & industry
mediaeval Europe may have worked secretly and kept their
discoveries to themselves, for fear of persecution as
wizards. With the dawn of the "modern world" new
discoveries of all kinds became fashionable and rewards
were attached to those that had money-making possibili¬
ties.
By the eighteenth century, even provincial clergymen in
England were inventing new appliances for the spinning
and weaving which were so prominent in the early stages
of the industrial revolution. Such inventions held the
promise of bigger profits for mill owners and merchants,
and this was the best way to secure a hearing In a world
where manufacturers and investors of capital were coming
rapidly to the fore.
In seeking an explanation for the rapid growth of the
factory system in England around 1800, we shall find no
more important cause than the rise, over the previous five
centuries, of an enterprising and increasingly prosperous
commercial class. These new merchants or businessmen
began to emerge with the shift from subsistence agricul¬
ture to an economy of exchange. They formed a new
middle class with certain very distinct qualities. Work
for its own sake gradually became a fetish, and thrift,
leading to a steady accumulation of capital, was regarded
as an essential part of the good life. The English diarist
Samuel Pepys, writing in the 1660's, continually dwells on
his growing capital. He could not know that he was the
unacknowledged mouthpiece of a new age.
he industrial revolution In England found
ready to hand rich natural resources like coal
and iron, a large merchant class eager to seize the new
opportunities for profit, ample capital to pay for the new
factories and machines and an abundant supply of very
cheap labour, consisting largely of women and children
uprooted from the countryside and almost unprotected by
the law.
New inventions placed at the disposal of the merchant
class provided railway and steamship facilities for the
rapid transportation of raw materials to their factories,
and of manufactured goods to their customers. The
Royal Navy guaranteed their safe passage and Lloyd's
insured them against loss.
In spite of all these advantages, the English industrial
revolution could hardly have succeeded unless a revolu¬
tion in agriculture had taken place first. This agricultural
revolution in Western Europe, led to the growing of more
wheat through enclosure of common land, to the rotation
of crops, to the winter feeding of cattle and to other
improvements in efficiency. It was less spectacular than
what happened soon afterwards In the factories, and it
is much less vivid in our minds. Yet the two movements
were Intimately connected.
Before any large-scale economic development can take
place in an underdeveloped country, the output and
efficiency of Its agriculture must be increased. The
growing populations of the cities and industrial areas must
be fed, because they are not self-supporting, as are the
villagers. The country-dwellers must also be able to
produce more food in order to earn higher incomes by
selling surplus produce, or they will be unable to buy goods
from the factories, and the industrialists will be without
an essential market. It was fortunate for the nineteenth-
century England that these technical changes on the
farms had largely taken place by the time the first
factories were being built.
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
ENGINEERING
The Spanish Conquista¬
dores who arrived in Peru
in the 16th century found a
civilization already highly
advanced. The empire of
the Incas had an extensive
network of well-built roads,
a remarkable irrigation
system. Using stones of
considerable weight, Inca
engineers perfected an
amazing method of build¬
ing construction, but were
ignorant of the wheel.
ASTRONOMY
The ancient Mayas, in the first
centuries of our era, were
highly skilled astronomers.
Through their celestial obser¬
vations and mathematical cal¬
culations they worked out a
complex calendar which is con¬
sidered more exact than the
present-day Gregorian one.
Buffalo Museum of Science
(g) Giraudon, Paris
A History of Technology
Oxford University Press
WEAVING
More than 4,000 years ago in
Peru cotton was grown and
woven into such striking pat¬
terns as that of this poncho
from Narca (opposite). Cotton
was not raised until the year
500 B.C. in the Nile Valley.
Early Egyptians cultivated and
spun only linen and hemp.
Collection Cleveland Museum of Art
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
WORLD PIONEERS
OF TECHNOLOGY
This 16th century map of the
voyages of Magellan shows only
a few of the vital contributions
which many of the so-called
"underdeveloped" countries have
made in the past to the techno¬
logical and scientific development
of today's industrialized society.
N*^"*-
THE COMPASS
It was largely thanks to the
compass that Portugese and
Spanish explorers found dis¬
tant lands in the 15th century.
But Chines^ sailors were the
first to navigate with a magne¬
tic needle in the 7th century.
© Builoz, Paris
IN I AG, Paris
Z?fl
PRINTING
The oldest known printed document dates from the 8th
century in China. Chinese paper was first manufactured
in 105 A.D. Printed impressions were made from engrav¬
ed plates until 1041 when, centuries before Gutenberg,
the Chinese Pi-Chang invented the first movable type.
SHIPBUILDING
Egyptian sailboats cruised the
Mediterranean in 1500 B.C.
Under Rameses II Egyptian sail¬
ors voyaged by canal from
the Nile to the Red Sea. Size¬
able naval squadrons from
Egypt penetrated the Indian
Ocean in 1200 B.C., probably
as far as Sumatra, in ships
220 feet long with large crews.
"A History of Technology"
Oxford University Press
METALLURGY
Mining of copper, silver,
and gold and the making
of glass was current in
Mesopotamia and Egypt
6,000 years ago. Iron was
not discovered until 1,000
years later in the same
countries. Above, an iron
axe decorated with copper
and gold (1300 B.C.) found
at Ras Shamra in Syria.
MEDICINE
The world's first med¬
ical treatise dates back
to 2700 B.C. under the
Chinese Emperor Chen-
Nong (opposite). Some
thousand years later
the Babylonian King
Hammurabi decreed a
series of laws governing
the practice of medi¬
cine and surgery. By
the year 500 Indian
scholars had identified
700 medicinal herbs.
" La Médecine chinoise, " Ed. Dacosta, Paris
:m-
MATHEMATICS
Mathematics owes much to the
Orient. The formula of Pytha¬
goras' theory is found on Meso-
potamian clay tablets dating
back to 1770 B.C. In 400 A.D
India produced one of the early
mathematical treatises, the
"Surya Siddhanta," and during
this period gave the world its
first recorded works on algebra.
Yale University
tS
m
i'ír':¡, \;\\ , ... r,
Vinlrs'.'y*' ,'óái
WRITING
Three thousand years before
Christ the Sumerians had an
alphabet of 500 to 600 charac¬
ters one hundred of which
were phonetic. Tablet-writing
in Mesopotamia (opposite) pro¬
gressed steadily to cuneiform
letters. By 1300 B.C. the libra¬
ry of the Hittite capital, Hat-
tusa, held texts in 8 tongues.
Oriental Institute, Chicago
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
UNDERDEVELOPMENT (Cont'd)
Can ancient values survive a machine age ?
But even the agricultural revolution at home would
not have sufficed to feed the rapidly growing popula¬
tion, which was concentrating more and more on work
that did not produce food. Just at this moment,
another fortunate circumstance came to the help of the
manufacturers and businessmen. Broad farmlands were
being opened up in North America, Argentina, Australia
and New Zealand from which ample supplies of wheat,
meat and dairy produce were to flow to the crowded cities
of the United Kingdom in return for her eagerly desired
manufactures.
The historian cannot explain why European thought
took the direction it did at the dawn of "modern" times
or precisely why the industrial revolution occurred just
when it did and how it did. Nevertheless, he has no
difficulty In pointing out the contributing factors at which
we have glanced, factors that help to explain why
progress was so rapid. When we turn to the problem of
economic development in our contemporary world, it Is
obvious that conditions differ in many important respects
from those we have been considering.
Many of the underdeveloped countries of today do not
possess the raw materials required for industrialization.
Still more important, few of them have undergone the
long preliminary period of social change which took place
in England before the industrial revolution began there.
In particular, most of these underdeveloped countries have
never seen the emergence of a powerful mercantile class
with the enterprise, the experience and the accumulated
capital, as well as the broad international connexions,
which the businessmen enjoyed in England, the centre
of a world-wide empire.
In some of today's underdeveloped countries, the small
educated class has tended to despise commercial and
industrial pursuits, while lack of education and capital
has prevented the mass of people from using trade as a
means of substantially improving their condition.
Perhaps most fundamental of all is the different
philosophy of life obtaining in many of today's under¬
developed countries. The success of Western technological
civilization has depended upon the willingness of large
numbers of men persistently to devote their energies to
the acquiring of material goods and social prestige
symbols. The habits of industry, thrift, accumulation of
capital and shrewdness in the far-sighted employment of
it opened the doors of society, while earning the plaudits
of moralists. As the twentieth century advanced, the
désire for possessions and security has been Intensively
stimulated, lower and lower down the social scale, by all
the resources of professional advertising.
I T would be a mistake to suppose that, even in
the West, man has always been eager to make
this effort. In fact, lack of discipline and absenteeism
were among the most serious obstacles to economic pro¬
gress in the early factory age. A contemporary observer,
Andrew TJre, in his Philosophy of Manufacture (1835)
remarked: "The main difficulty of the new industrial
system did not, to my apprehension, lie so much in the
invention of a proper self-acting mechanism.. .as in train¬
ing human beings to renounce their desultory habits of
work and to identify themselves with the unvarying regu¬
larity of the complex automaton... Even at the present day,
when the system is perfectly organized and its labour
lightened to the utmost, it is found nearly impossible to
convert persons past the age of puberty, whether drawn
from rural or from handcraft occupations, into useful
factory hands."
Long ago, Aristotle said in the Nicomachean Ethics:
32 "We busy ourselves in order that we may have leisure"
and it has been pointed out that the Greek language has
only a negative Word for "job" or "business"asxolia,
literally "the lack of leisure." The Latin equivalent for
"business" is neg-otium or "absence of leisure." The
German for work arbeit comes from a Middle High
German word, arebeit, which had the meaning of
"hardship" or "distress."
We have contemporary evidence to show that it took
much effort and not a little brutality to create in the
early factory workers the habits of unremitting attention
and regularity that machinery demands, habits which, in
the fields and the artisan's shop, can be less rigid and
exacting, thanks to the relief afforded by varying tasks,
seasonal changes, weather conditions, traditional religious
festivals and folk ceremonies.
If the discipline of industry took a long time to assert
itself in the West, obstacles of a still deeper nature may
hinder its development elsewhere. Compare the outlook
which is now typical of many Western societies with the
traditional attitudes of a civilization like that of India.
There, renunciation and the conquest of desire are
principles deeply admired. Matter is the great illusion
and desire the root of all evil, a force which draws man
into a material world with which his real self can have
no affinity, and to which his genuine interests would
never bind him. From the standpoint of this ancient
culture, the stimulation of material desires and the crea¬
tion of means to satisfy those desires are in the highest
degree vanity and foolishness.
here are, of course, many underdeveloped
countries in which these views are not held,
or are restricted to certain spiritual teachers and their
disciples. Few Indians would today see an irreconcilable
conflict between the Hindu religion and an effort to im¬
prove standards of living. The existence in non-
industrial societies of such traditional attitudes before
the great mystery of life and a widespread reluctance to
submit for long to the monotony of' industrial labour
should however be noted.
Critics of the West have pointed out what they believe
to be a certain selfishness and superficiality in the atti¬
tudes which have made "Western Industrial civilization
possible. They see in Western man a desire to "have"
rather than to "be," and they compare this unfavourably
with the more communal, less individualistic and
acquisitive state of mind that prevails in much of Asia
and Africa. There, at least in many rural communities,
personal aggrandizement tends to be condemned as a
motive for human conduct. Sharing with one's fellowis is
taken more readily for granted and time is something to
be enjoyed, rather than used, like a song by firelight that
enriches companionship, even if it leaves the coffers as
empty as^-ever. Such attitudes could perhaps restore to
the "acquisitive society" a dimension of human warmth
which it has, to some extent, lost. In any event, they
cannot be overlooked if we seek to compare the mentality
of today's underdeveloped countries with that of industrial
England or America.
In the attempt to move from an earlier, rural culture
into the mobile, machine-conscious, urbanized, technolo¬
gical society, the "less developed" countries may risk
losing precious social values consecrated by tradition and
also art forms which satisfy as manufactur¬
ed goods can never do. Only economic development and
industrialization can reduce the material sufferings and
insecurity of the less privileged peoples, but respect for
these social and artistic values may still be a guiding
principle both of those who are seeking to diversify their
economies and of the experts from industrialized
countries who go among them, sometimes without fully
realizing what treasures an "underdeveloped" culture may
conceal.
(To be continued.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
SPECIAL ISSUES
Vs. VARIED ISSUES
Sir,
As you have asked for readers'
views on a single or multi-subject
policy for your magazine here are
mine.
Being partial to a full and adequate
treatment of subjects, I naturally prefer
by far the one-theme issues of which
you have already given us some
magnificent examples. Scientific
discoveries, artistic treasures and
literary masterpieces are not too
numerous to prevent your making
individual mention of each of their
authors and of presenting in a single
issue their lives, the history of their
works and, above all, the objective
and competent judgment of their
contemporaries.
Marcel Faelli
Dampremy, Belgium
Sir,
I agree with your correspondent
Tom Kloepping (Sept. issue) that
The Unesco Courier has lost some
of its unique flavour and carries less
weight since it ceased to concentrate
on the various aspects of one special
subject.
Ellen Bosanquet
Falmouth, England
Sir,
It would be a pity if you ceased
to publish issues devoted to one theme.
These are the numbers of The Unesco
Courier that I treasure the most.
Paulette Vassel
Suresnes, France
Sir,
You are making a big mistake
when you devote your magazine to
a single subject and adopt a dry and
official style of presentation. This
could make the subjects dealt with
more difficult to understand and act
as a brake on the expansion of your
publication.
P. F. Oloviaguine
Shardjou, U.S.S.R.
Sir,
I prefer greatly whole issues devoted
to one theme : it makes the issue
more authoritative and worth keeping
for reference. The Unesco Courier
in its old form was in an outstanding
class of its own and I was always
recommending it to friends and to
educational institutions.
Cyril Harrison
Birmingham, England
EDUCATIONAL
BUT NOT BORING
Sir,
As a fifteen-year-old schoolgirl, I
first came into contact with The
Unesco Courier when I wrote to the
Foreign Office for information about
the Aswan Dam. This was for a
school competition project which I
hid entered .
The Foreign Office sent me an issue
of The Unesco Courier, partially
devoted to Abu Simbel. With its aid
I won the project, and decided to
subscribe to the magazine.
-Since that time -I -have been entirely
satisfied with the articles, which I
find to my delight vary widely. I
feel that, although I hope to continue
on to further education on the side of
the arts, my education could not be
complete without some knowledge of
science, people, ancient civilizations
etc. which the magazine deals with
admirably.
I wish that other people of my own
age group knew about it. It is educ¬
ational, without being boring, unlike
so many textbooks.
Deborah Parker
Wirral, England
NEW WAYS IN ASIAN MUSIC
Sir,
I agree wholeheartedly with
Alain Daniélou "Music of the
Orient", June 1962 issue, that inter¬
national music education is a worth¬
while step towards the understanding
of other cultures and that this is best
accomplished today by means of
recordings and radio. I must however
take exception to several of his state¬
ments.
Music is a form about which we
are all most subjective but, who can
say that "new forms and innovations
in Asian music destroy the meaning" ?
Should we not think of them as addi¬
tions rather than destructions? A
new face doesn't mean that the heart
is gone.
As a student of the instrument pic¬
tured in the hands of Ravi Shankar
I feel that some mistake must have
been made in the captioning. Though
it is true that India's stringed instru¬
ments have been lumped together as
"vinas", the instrument shown is best
known throught the world as the
"sitar". It is indeed difficult to des¬
cribe these instruments because of the
wide variation in each type but a
careful look at the photograph will
show that this one has twenty frets,
seven main strings and thirteen sym¬
pathetic resonating strings on a fin¬
gerboard of teakwood.
P. Estabrook
Bombay, India
Ed. note : Professor Daniélou (who
did not write our captions) says :
"The instrument is a Indian Sitar.
It has four main strings, two or
three drone strings, and 13 sym¬
pathetic strings tuned to the various
notes of the mode and that help to
increase the resonance of the ins¬
trument. These cannot he called
drone strings. The number of frets
is usually 20.
On the photograph of an Indian
painting next to that of Ravi Shankar,
the instrument is an Iranian sehtar
(not an Indian instrument). The
musician may be Persian or Indian."
LITERACY IN SWITZERLAND
Sir,
The use of statistics is always some¬
what questionable as one never knows
how the figures have been arrived at.
New evidence of this is given in the
pages of your June 1962 issue where
we read how illiteracy has been ra¬
pidly reduced [to 3.5%] in Cuba un¬
der Castro, and you then place Cuba's
illiteracy on a par with Switzerland
and other countries. On this basis,
Switzerland would have 20,000 illite¬
rates which is certainly far from the
truth.
Franz Koller
Benken, Switzerland.
Ed. note: Our reader is correct. Illi¬
teracy is practically non-existent in
Switzerland and cannot be put on the
same level as that of Cuba. The
parallel with Switzerland was drawn
by the Cuban Ministry of Education
in a report communicated to Unesco
which indicated that Cuba's illiteracy
percentage was 3.5 %.
HAZARDS OF SPACE DISEASE
Sir,
Anent the letter from Mr. George
R. Schäfer in your May issue.
Speaking of the two-way problem of
disease-causing agents in space ven¬
tures, and perhaps of interest in
connexion with your forthcoming
special issue on the Conquest of Outer
Space, note is made of the fact that
two years ago I published a short item
in the American journal "Science"
[vol. 132, p. 1569 (I960)] stating that
it was time to begin investigations into
the production of germ-free humans.
Of course, it would be out of the
question to take a human infant and
raise it germ-free; however, the notion
seems entirely feasible for adults who
have developed a full complement of
anti-body and other defense mecha¬
nisms, so that they could be returned
to their natural environment with a
minimum of danger.
As for "space disease" brought
back to earth, it appears that an im¬
portant gap will have to be filled.
Namely, the gathering of extra¬
terrestrial infectious agents (which in
all probability exist) by specially-
designed, unmanned vehicles, and
bringing these back to earth for
"space bacteriology" and like exami¬
nations having the aim of developing
or using present disease countermeas-
ures.
It is not inconceivable that "space
disease" could provide a major hazard
for manned expeditions.
Jack DeMent
Portland, Oregon, U.S.A.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
INTERNATIONAL TV BY TELSTAR:
For the first time, on September 17,
an intercontinental TV programme was
transmitted by the communications satellite
Telstar. It was a U.N. programme, honour¬
ing the memory of Dag Hammarskjold,
former U.N. Secretary-General, Count
Folke Bernadotte, U.N. Mediator for
Palestine and others who died in the cause
of peace, and was seen by audiences on
both sides of the Atlantic. It included
ceremonies at U.N. Headquarters, New
York, Unesco Headquarters in Paris and
at Dag Hammarskjold's tomb in Uppsala,
Sweden.
KENE MAHEU CANDIDATE FOR
DIRECTOR-GENERALSHIP: The
Executive Board of Unesco, after meeting
in Istanbul in September, announced its
decision to submit for the approval by the
General Conference of the Organization
which opens in Paris on November 9, the
nomination of Mr. René Maheu, Acting
Director-General, to the post of Director-
General of Unesco.
GIFT COUPONS HELP UNRWA: Over
$170,000 to aid UNRWA Arab
Refugee Camps and Schools (See The
Unesco Courier, October 1962) has been
raised in the past ten years by schools,
organizations and individuals in twelve
countries and donated through Unesco
Gift Coupon Scheme projects. This aid
came from Australia, Belgium, Canada,
Denmark, France, Germany, Italy, the
Netherlands, Norway, Sweden, the United
Kingdom and the U.S.A. Unesco's current
project (GCP N° 324) invites contributions
for provision of science teaching equipment,
domestic science materials, school libraries
and youth centres.
HONEY IN THE DESERT: Experiments
have now shown that bees can live
happily, busily, and profitably in the Kara
Kum and Kizyl Kum deserts of Uzbekistan
U.S.S.R. thanks to the thorn and wild
desert grasses which blossom in summer.
Many collective farms are now setting up
apiaries in these areas, but to protect busy
bees from heat prostration, their hives must
be set up under tents which are kept
sprinkled "with water.
SAVING THE ORYX: An expedition
recently set out for the Rub al Khali
desert of southern Arabia in search of spec
imens of the Arabian oryx, a rare, long-
horned species of antelope which man has
almost succeeded in wiping out. In the past
there were large numbers in the Middle East,
but they have been progressively hunted
down. An aerial survey earlier this year
revealed only seven specimens surviving.
The Fauna Preservation Society in London
with the support of the World Wildlife
Fund sent the present expedition to capture
the remaining animals and fly them to a
place of safety, probably somewhere in
Africa.
AGAINST DISCRIMINATION IN
EDUCATION: The U.S.S.R. has
become the seventh country to ratify the
Convention Against Discrimination which
was adopted in 1960 by the Unesco
General Conference. Designed to promote
equality and justice in access to education,
the Convention defines discrimination as
including any distinction "'based on race,
colour, sex, language, religion, political or
other opinion, national or social origin,
economic condition or birth."
S|~ï ULTURAL PASSPORTS': The Hague
^ Art Foundation in co-operation with
the city authorities is now issuing "cul¬
tural passports" to young people aged
between 15 and 20. These passports
provide entry to exhibitions, art galleries
and museums and enable the holders to
enjoy theatre, music, ballet, opera and film
performances at reduced prices.
VOLTAIRE'S LIBRARY: A detailed
description of Voltaire's library, which
was purchased by Catherine II of Russia
after the death of the great 18th century
philosopher, has now been given in a book
published by the U.S.S.R. Academy of
Sciences. Voltaire's many notes, on the
margin of his books, are rich material
for research. Especially noteworthy are
letters he received from the Russian scien¬
tist Mikhail Lomonosov.
WORLD CAMPAIGN AGAINST
MALARIA: Over 90 postal author¬
ities are now taking part in the vast
philatelic campaign, "The World United
Against Malaria", launched by the World
Health Organization last April. Proceeds
34
THE UNESCO PHILATELIC SERVICE
NATIONS UNIES
their price and methods of
Philatelic Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris (7e)
The United Nations has chosen U.N. Day, 1962, on
October 24 to commemorate its operation in the
Congo with the issue of a new stamp (left). As
the agent in France of the U.N. Postal Administration,
Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks all the United
Nations stamps currently on sale. It also has stamps
and first day covers issued by many Unesco member
states to commemorate important events in the
history of Unesco and the U.N. (Inauguration of
Unesco's Headquarters, Human Rights Day, Unesco's
15th Anniversary). Information on items available,
payment will be sent on request by the Unesco
from the stamps will be used to advance
the WHO campaign to eradicate the
disease that threatens 1,300 million people
today. Already 764 million people are
covered by malaria eradication program¬
mes.
FREEING KNOWLEDGE FOR ALL:
New Zealand and Gabon are the latest
countries to join the Unesco Agreement
on the Importation of Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Materials which
exempts these materials from import duties.
So far 39 countries have joined the
Agreement which is part of Unesco's
programme to promote "the free flow of
ideas by world and image."
SCHOOLS AT SEA: Over 600 senior
boys and girls from secondary schools
in France and Britain recently went on
a cruise to Morocco, Senegal and Gambia
on a ship specially fitted out as a kind
of floating school. During their trip they
met African youngsters of their own age
and joined in many festivities and
excursions.
LIBRARIES FOR DEVELOPING
LANDS: To help member states set
up libraries which can buttress their
educational systems, Unesco has organized
a series of conferences in recent years.
Recently it has been participating in three
regional seminars organized for the benefit
of developing countries: On the develop¬
ment of libraries in Africa (held in
Nigeria), of university libraries in Latin
America (in Argentina) and on co-operation
between libraries and documentation
centres in Arab countries (in Cairo).
IN THE STEPS OF ALEXANDER: A
team of German film producers, techni¬
cians and actors has recently been follow¬
ing a route taken over 2,000 years ago
by Alexander the Great on his way to
India, through Macedonia, Turkey, Iran and
Afghanistan. The expedition will make a
full-length documentary film of Alexander's
campaigns for eventual screening on
European TV networks.
Flashes...
:| Asia's educational problems are brought
home by the situation in India where there
are 46 million children of school age a
number equal to the total population of
France.
| Oceanographers are making ever greater
use of highly developed fixed buoys (un¬
manned research vessels) to measure ocean
currents and temperatures. Thirty such
stations could produce eight million
temperature measurements annually.
H Ceylonese fish catches have doubled
since 1956, when nylon nets were intro¬
duced in Ceylon by a specialist adviser
sent by the U.N. Food and Agriculture
Organization.
I Twelve countries (the latest of them
being Ghana) have joined the International
Computation Centre in Rome set up under
UNESCO's auspices.
| Africa's present cattle population (about
114 million head) could be doubled if
trypanosomiasis (sleeping sickness) which is
transmitted to man and animals by the
tsetse fly in tropical Africa, were eradicated.
In the past three years, 1,540 work.-, of
fiction totalling 181 million copies have
been published in the U.S.S.R. They
included books by writers of 68 countries
and translations from 45 languages spoken
in the U.S.S.R.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Binders for your
collection of
THE UNESCO COURIER
We offer subscribers a special binder for
their copies of THE UNESCO COURIER hold¬
ing a year's issues of the magazine. Hand¬
somely produced in halfcloth with the spine
in an attractive blue and the title (in English,
French or Spanish according to the edition
to which you subscribe) and Unesco colophon
embossed in gold, these convenient and
attractive binders, costing $2.50; 12/6stg. ; or
6 NF, can be ordered from UNESCO Agents.
The Unesco Courier
will make a New Year's
gift for which your friends
and relations will thank
you throughout the year
' i
"^Courier
FREEDOM FROM
HUNGER
A unique, modestly-priced
international periodical
read by one and a half
million people every month
One Year's Subscription only
10/ - (stg)
$ 3.00
7 NF
See list of sales agents below
lûCourïer
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
theNational Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzat, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Sch. 60.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A.,
16, rte Marq, Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only : Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckách, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Norregade,
Kóbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de "Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris, 7«. CCP. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, (German ed only)
Bahren- felder-Chaussee I 60, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asal Ah Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxfords Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Dehli 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti, D|alan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Alienby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv ( I £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
( I 0/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O.Box 286, Monrovia
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand -Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
RiverValley Rd., Singapore. MALTA. Sapienza's Library
26 Kingsw y, Valetta. (10/-). MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS. N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Wellington, and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch, Dunedin ( I 0/-).
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR-
WAY. For the Unesco Courier only: A. S. Narvesens Lit
teratur-Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks 115 (kn
I 3.20) Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grense.
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Cor.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
LIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., I 104 Castille¬
jos, Quiapo, P.O. Box 620, Manila. POLAND.
" RUCH " ul.Wiloza Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda, Livraria Portugal,
Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA & NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A/B CE. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse
Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. «Courier» only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suks apan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O., Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue, New York, 22, N.Y. (S 5.00.) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoilo-
venska Knpga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
, à
SCIENCE-FICTION AS LITERATURE
This year's Unesco Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of Science has gone to Arthur C. Clarke, a writer who has
made his name in science-fiction. In the article on page 14, Mr. Clarke comes to the defence of science-fiction as
a new form of literature worthy of attention and stresses the role it has played in arousing interest in science in
young minds. Photo here shows a scene from " Forbidden Planet", an American film in which a science-fiction
flying saucer sets out from Earth to explore a planet circling the star Altair in the Constellation of the Eagle.
iïivj,	
]]>
</page>
</document>
