<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078160eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ON THE WORLD
SIGHTLESS SCULPTORS
(page 16)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TWO ROSETTES
WORLDS APART
Ultra-modern instruments enable
scientists to penetrate an infinitely
small world and an infinitely large
world beyond each end of the region
of space directly accessible to our
senses. At the extremities of this
chain are found, on the one hand the
particles of matter some of which
make up the nucleus of the atom,
and on the other hand the galaxies
and galactic systems. Photo right
is rosette-shaped diagram of the
cristal beryl obtained by X-ray
diffraction method which permits
science to determine geometrical
arrangement of atoms in crystals.
Below, a view of the Rosette Nebula,
which forms part of our Milky Way,
taken with Schmidt telescope at Mt.
Palomar, California. (See page 20 for
story 40 Jumps through Universe.)
Laboratoire de Mineralogie, Sorbonne. Paris
USIS
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
A WINDOW OPEN OH TNI WOULD
MAY 1957 I Oth YEAR
No. 5
CONTENTS
PAGES
3 EDITORIAL
4 'WALKABOUT* IN AUSTRALIA'S BUSH
A bedtime story that really happened
by Axel Poignant
I I ZOOS THROUGH THE AGES
"Parks of Intelligence"
by David Gunston
14 A WOMAN'S LIFE IN AN AFRICAN VILLAGE
PART II:
Business affairs, extensive liberty, bringing up a family
by Claudie Hauferlin
16 SCULPTURE BY THE BLIND
by Bertha Gaster
20 FORTY JUMPS THROUGH THE UNIVERSE
A fantastic voyage into space
21 I. Into the macrocosmic world
28 II. Into the microcosmic world
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, 19 Avenue Kleber, Paris 16, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavarlani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemln
Circulation Manager
Jean Groffier
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English.
French, Spanish and Russian. A small Japanese version is published in Tokyo
and a Danish version in Copenhagen. The United States of America edition
is distributed by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 152. West 42nd
Street, New York 36. N.Y., Pennsylvania 6-0851. Second-class mail privileges
authorized at New York, N.Y. M.C. 57. IA-II2
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
credit is given to THE UNESCO COURIER and two voucher copies are sent
to the editor. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless accompanied
by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent the opinions of
UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S2.50 ; 8 - ; 400 French franc» or equivalent.
Printed in France
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
COVER PHOTO
James Thornton, a blind American
Negro, moulds his own bust in the
sculpture workshop at the San Francisco
Centre for the Blind. Sculpture courses
for the sightless started seven years ago
by a young teacher, Jeanne Kewell, have
shown remarkable results. (See "Sculp¬
ture by the Blind", page 16).
i*> Imogen CLnnin¿ham
For many millenia, man's knowledge of the external
world was limited to what he could detect with his
senses. Living in a purely natural environment, he
found his place therein, like the other animal species.
Man's senses, however, are not always better than those
of animals: certain insects can see ultraviolet light; the
bat can hear ultrasonic vibrations, dogs have a more
highly developed sense of smell. So it is not because he
has a sensory system superior to those of animals which
has enabled man to conquer a privileged place for himself
in nature. It is his ability to reflect upon the plain evi¬
dence of his senses, to analyse it, to compare various pieces
of information with one another, and to interpret the
result with his mind.
Among our senses, those which enable us to appreciate
the arrangement in space of all the objects of the world
around us, give us more valuable information than do the
others. Thanks to this idea of arrangement in space we
can attribute larger or smaller dimensions to objects.
Many animals of course possess the idea of space and
have some knowledge of the sizes and distances away of
various other animals, plants and objects in their environ¬
ment. But this knowledge is confused and cannot be
raised to the status of a science because the animals have
no idea of measuring lengths or distances by a voluntary
experimental act.
There are many species of animals which can count,
but there is not a single one which has the faculty to
measure. Thus even in the field of medium distances (such
as the size of his own body, distances between himself
and other objects) man has, since remotest antiquity,
had a great superiority over animals in his ability to
measure.
But it is only in the past few hundred years, with the
invention of the microscope and telescope and other ins¬
truments of measurement, that man has made his most
prodigious bound forward. Today, the electron microscope
permits us to see details one hundred times smaller than
ever before. In bacteriology it has provided valuable
information about the structure of viruses and bacteria;
in metallography it has made possible extensive study of
metallic surfaces and crystals. The 200-inch Mt. Palomar
telescope, on thé other hand, has extended man's vision
of the universe up to 720 million light yearsthe distance
of the furthest galactic cluster yet observed.
During this pursuit of fresh knowledge, into the regions
of both the extremely small and extremely large, man has
not only encountered unknown and marvellous phenomena
which have enriched his conception of the universe, but
has also been able to transform his own existence by
entirely new means developed in the process.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
'WALKABOUT' IN AUSTRALIA'S
"*«?V*'itÄ.
~*
All photos pages 4 to 1 0
(Ç Axel Poignant 1957
A BEDTIME STORY THAT
REALLY HAPPENED
On Millingimbi Island off the
coast of Arnhem Land in north¬
ern Australia live groups of
aborigines, tall and slender people
who are great hunters and fishermen.
Especially indulgent towards their
children (piccaninnies, as they are
called in Australia), the aborigines
delight in telling them stories around
the camp fire at night. They tell
of their ancestors, of how the world
was made, and of all the legends
associated with their culture.
The youngsters listen wide-eyed to
the stories and, like children all over
the world, quickly identify them¬
selves with the heroes and heroines.
Children on Millingimbi Island like
Nullagundi and his sister Rikili,
really re-live the adventure of two
children lost in the bush. The story,
set in their own familiar surround¬
ings may be intended to interest and
amuse them but it is also teaching
some of the hard facts of life, show¬
ing them how to stay alive in country
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
BUSH
by Axel Poignant
fe
In Arnhem Land on the North Coast of Australia, there live two aboriginal children, Nullagundi and his sister Rikili. One day while
their parents were away hunting, the children decided to go off into the bush by themselves. When night came they were lost, but
with the resourcefulness of aboriginal children they found food and water and built themselves a shelter for the night. Next day
their parents set out to look for them and the family was soon reunited. Here is their adventurea bedtime story told to aboriginal
children around the campfire, but one that really happenednow recounted by a photographer.
where an inexperienced white man
would perish in a few days.
The lessons are driven home in a
practical way when the children go
"walkabout" (long trips across
country) with their parents. On
these walkabouts the children are
taught all the skills necessary for a
life in the bush : how to find food
and water, how to hunt and fish, how
to build a bark canoe, how to weave
a basket and make a spear. Younger
children go food gathering with the
womenfolk who teach them how to
track animals and to read the signs
of the bush. Sometimes, as in the
photo story on these pages, the chil¬
dren decide to take off on a minor
walkabout of their own.
The boy in the story, Nullagundi,
is tall for his ten years. He has
already learned most of these things
and soon he will undergo the initia¬
tion rites which will make him a
man. As soon as these ceremonies
begin life becomes very different for
a boy. He may no longer speak to
his sister or many other women who
are closeley related to him. Taboos
are imposed on him. There are foods
he may not eat and his whole beha¬
viour is strictly controlled. His nine
year-old sister Rikili, on the other
hand, just goes on growing up. Rikili
has already been promised in mar¬
riage and she will be claimed by her
husband as soon as she is old enough.
The aborigines of Arnhem Land are
among those peoples whose lives and
cultures have remained the most
primitive, the closest to those of
their far-off ancestors. These bush-
men, as they are called, depend solely
for their living on hunting, fishing
(where possible) and food gathering.
Until 1788 aborigines had been
occupying the entire continent of
Australia undisturbed for many cen¬
turies. They are thought to have
numbered some 300,000 at the time of
the first white settlement in Austra¬
lia. Today there are some 60,000 full-
blood aborigines and about 25,000 of
mixed blood. They are mostly
nomads found in tribes scattered over
the Northern Territory, the north of
Western Australia and northern
Queensland. Many roam vast reser¬
vations. Others, no longer tribal, live
in organized camps where medical
services and schools are provided by
the Australian Government. Others
live in normal contact with the white
man and work at various trades.
Aborigines have contributed in no
small measure towards Australian
life. Pastoral industries could not
have developed without their help.
One of the most remarkable aspects
of the aboriginal is his art, a truly
primitive and still living art. Unesco
devoted an album in its World Art
Series, "Aboriginal Paintings-Arnhem
Land" to this art on bark and stone.
(See THE UNESCO courier, N° 11, 1954).
Today the Australian aborigines are
not only diminishing in numbers but
are also losing their primitive beliefs
and customs because of their greater
contacts with Western civilization.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
AUSTRALIAN «WALKABOUT* (Cont'd)
, LET'S HAVE A
SPEAR FIGHT'
Nullagundi and Rikili met their
friends on the beach and decided to
play the "spearfight" game. The
boys tied soft bark round the
points of their spears, and as they
threw them at each other, the
girls stood between them as "peace¬
makers" and tried to deflect
the flying spears. (The aboriginals
use spears for hunting and at the
peace-making ceremonies which
often precede the corroborées, or
big feasts). The game ended as
one of the boys pretended to be
killed, and the girls wept over him.
WHAT ABOUT
A WALK?
Rikili got tired of playing games
and suggested a walk in the forest.
The two children sneaked off into
the bush, taking care that their
grandmother didn't see them.
Soon Rikili was thirsty, but all
the water holes were dried up so
Nullagundi "tapped" a paperbark
tree. He cut into the tree with
his spear and soon water was
dripping into the bark cup they
had made. It tasted slightly brack¬
ish, but they were too thirsty to
notice. (When these photographs
were taken there had been no rain
for a good two years and water
was. very hard to find anywhere).
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
*
-.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
AUSTRALIAN «WALKABOUT* (Cont'd)
CATCH
A GOANNA
BY ITS TAIL...
Goanna (lizard) meat is an abori¬
ginal delicacy. But these lizards
dart into rocks or hollow logs the
moment they hear humans around.
By pulling hard on the goanna's
tail Nullagundi drew it from its
hiding place and quickly killed it.
Rikili proudly held the trophy of
the chase. Rubbing two sticks to¬
gether until they smouldered, her
brother made a fire with dried
grass and branches. The goanna
was soon cooked and in no time
the children had gobbled it down.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
LOST IN THE FOREST The long walk, the hunt, the meal... all that took some time, and suddenly. the
sun was setting. Nullagundi and Rikili had first of all wandered aimlessly, then
they had hunted for something to eat and a place to cook it. When it began to
get dark they had no idea how far they had come or where they were. Rikili was frightened and began to cry. But her
brother was not dismayed. He built a shelter of sticks and bark and made a small fire to keep them warm during the night.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
'WALKABOUT'
AUSTRALIAN
(Continued)
STORY WITH A
HAPPY ENDING
When the mother and father return¬
ed from their hunt they were very
worried by the two children's dis¬
appearance. Early next morning they
set out in search of them and soon
found the trail the children had made
a footprint, sometimes a
broken branch or grasses bent back.
From time to time they stopped to
call out... and finally Nullagundi heard
them. That evening a big corroborée
was held in the camp to celebrate the
children's return. The story had a
happy ending and the children's
"walkabout" taught them still another
lesson about aboriginal skills and lore.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Moy 1957
Zoos through
the ages
by David Gunston
Since early times men have kept wild animals in
captivity, although not always for the same
reasons. Animals have been kept as objects of
curiosity, wonder and amusement as well as 'for
observation and profitable study. At various times
they have been used for thrills in sport and specta¬
cles.
Today, apart from travelling menageries and the
captive performing animals of the circus, all the older
forms of the practice have been superseded by
zoological gardens a comparatively recent develop¬
ment. The one thing that has not changed is the
curiosity excited by the spectacle of wild creatures in
captivity which is as strong today as ever before.
Nowadays, however, the aspect of sensationalism has
been more usefully turned in an educational direction,
as exemplified by the zoological garden, or the "zoo"
as people have been calling it for the past century.
As far as we can tell the very earliest zoo existed in
the advanced civilization of Ancient China. There
the first emperor of the famous Chou dynasty founded
a collection of animals about 1100 B.C. We have no
record of what creatures it contained, but 'from its
title, "a park of intelligence", we gather that its
objects were obviously educational and scientific and
probably corresponded to those of modern zoos. This
is all the more remarkable because at that time very
often the only reason for keeping animals was for
their religious associations which gave them elevated
rank among the denizens of the earth.
This was an attitude widely prevalent in Egypt,
where the cat was reverenced as also were calves,
baboons, crocodiles and many other creatures regarded
as animal deities.
Ancient Egyptian drawings and designs abound in
animals and birds. But the Egyptian practice was
one of pet-keeping rather than the assembling of
caged collections a pet-keeping carried to excess.
Many o'f these creatures lacked for nothing and had
picked slaves to look after them. From the many
mummified remains discovered in tombs we know
that after their death such animals were buried with
ceremony and ritual.
The peoples of Ancient Greece and Rome were well
accustomed to seeing a variety of wild animals, but
these were nearly always brought to Europe and
maintained with care solely for the role they were to
play in the arenas, to be slaughtered either by other
beasts or in combat with gladiators. Thus, the people
of Rome saw camels, elephants, leopards, lions,
antelopes, rhinoceroses, crocodiles, hippopotamuses
and ostriches, and even the giraffe, which was after¬
wards not to be seen again in Europe until 1827.
Paul Almasy 19 57
The Roman Emperors could always maintain large
collections of wild beasts. As these animals existed
in far greater numbers than they do today, there was
little difficulty in restocking the collections after the
bloody combats attended by thousands of citizens.
Vast quarters were built for the beasts within the
precincts of the Coliseum, often only a few yards from
the prisons oí the Christians and others who had
incurred disfavour. These hapless victims were
thrown to the lions regularly, the beasts having been
kept hungry to ensure lively "sport". Fights between
gladiators and lions were a favourite spectacle; we
read of Commodus who slew more than a hundred
lions in as many single struggles. Sometimes certain
animals leopards, lions and tigers apparently tame
and pampered with food and attention, wandered
freely amid the palaces and garders. It is said that
Nero had a pet tigress called Phoebe which sat with
him at banquets and was occasionally used to rid the
court of unwanted guests or those who displeased the
Emperor. It is also recorded that Heliogabalus
entered Rome in a chariot drawn by four panthers
and four tigers later set loose in the palace.
Thus throughout the Roman era animals provided
entertainment for people and nobles alike. Towards
the Middle Ages, however, animal collections were to
be found only in the entourage oí feudal potentates,
princes, dukes and barons, for they alone could afford
to maintain the animals in proper quarters. The
keeping of animals was often a form of hobby among
the rich from whose collections our own zoos of today
directly derive.
Throughout Europe the rare visit of some cheap
travelling menagerie of the lowest form, or perhaps
some unusual pet, a showman's monkey or a
performing bear, were the only chances the average
poor person had of seeing wild creatures from
different lands. The pandering to empty sen¬
sationalism only began to disappear when the
collections of the privileged grew both in numbers
and in scientific status, and were thrown open to the
public ior its edification and amusement.
Kings had the most extensive collections for they
were often presented with live captive animals ty
rulers of other lands, explorers and the captains of
ships visiting strange parts. The first zoo in England
seems to have been founded by Henry I at Woodstock
early in the 12th century. It included lions and
leopards. This collection was later transferred to the
Tower of London where it formed the basis of the
menagerie which in its turn was to be the
original nucleus of the present Regent's Park.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
I I
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ZOOS (.Continued) The keeper of the lions: a court gentleman
This transfer of the first English collection to the
Tower of London, where there was ample room and
safe accommodation for the increasing numbers of
wild animals being presented by foreign rulers, took
place in the reign of Henry III, in the early thirteenth
century. The collection was presided' over by an
official of the Crown and it seems the Sheriffs of the
City of London and of the counties of Bedford and
Buckingham were ordered to finance the complete
menagerie, including the keepers. Henry III added
an elephant and a white bear to his collection, as well
as three leopards symbolizing those on the royal
coat of arms which he had received from the Em¬
peror Frederick as a token of friendship. In 1252 it
is recorded that the sheriffs of London were ordered
to pay fourpence a day for the maintenance of the
white bear and its keeper. A year later it was deemed
advisable to provide a muzzle and a chain for this
animal while it was washing or fishing in the Thames!
The menagerie at the Tower grew throughout the
reigns of the next three sovereigns, and orders still
preserved show that sixpence a day was the usual
allowance for each leopard or lion, with three-half¬
pence as the keeper's wages.
We know very little of the actual conditions under
which these collections were housed, but they do not
appear to have been at all bad; and the animals
thrived as a rule. By the time oí Henry VI the
menagerie had risen in official status, for the keeper
of the lions was a rank held by a gentleman of the
court, with a iee of sixpence a day and as much again
for the maintenance of every lion or leopard in his
charge. It is obvious that the royal menagerie was
held in high esteem, for the corresponding allowance
for human prisoners in the Tower was a penny a day.
Henry Ill's elephant was a gift from the King of
France about the year 1255. It was the first live
elephant to be seen in England and accordingly
attracted vast crowds of sightseers on its arrival. A
document still extant describes how the Sheriff oí
Kent was ordered to proceed to Dover in person in
order to see how the animal might most conveniently
be brought to London, and if necessary to arrange for
a ship to convey it in. Shortly afterwards the
Sheriffs of London were commanded to erect with
all speed, in the Tower, an elephant's house, forty feet
in length and twenty ieet wide, strongly built, but
adaptable to other uses should the need arise. This
prudent touch is typical of the age when the keeping
of wild animals was still very much a novelty.
Similar collections were being built up in Europe.
In France, Phillip VI had a fine collection by 1333,
and Charles V maintained menageries at Couflans,
and at the Tournelles in Paris. Later, Louis XI
formed a zoo at Plessis-les-Tours in Touraine and
after his death this was re-established at the Louvre
in Paris and enlarged with a number of animals
brought specially from North Africa. This establish¬
ment was done away with by Henry III but in due
course a collection was built up again, first by
Henry IV, then by Louis XIII at Versailles where the
Menagerie du Parc was ultimately founded by
Louis XIV. This collection was quite a good one and
received many different species from Cairo. It was
kept in order for more than a century, affording
much scope for naturalists and anatomists until its
eventual decay and final destruction during the
Revolution in 1789.
In Germany, the Elector Augustus I started a zoo
at Dresden in 1554; one of the lion keepers was killed
there by a particularly savage beast.
Outside Europe zoological collections were being
formed in South America, although nothing oí their
existence was known until centuries later. In the
middle of the fifteenth century, King Nezalhualcoyotl
had zoological gardens in Mexico. At the beginning
of the next century the Aztec ruler Moctezuma II
kept large collections of wild creatures, including
serpents, fish, jaguars and ocelots, feeding the
carnivorous animals on the plentiful wild turkeys of
that part oí the world. Cortez reported finding
extensive aviaries and fishponds at Iztapalapan.
From now on the keeping of menageries and zoo¬
logical collections became more widespread. Much
of the initiative came from monarchs who vied with
one another for the interest or rarity of their
collections. Charles II of England kept a large
assortment of birds in cages at Birdcage Walk (as it
is still known) in London. After the menagerie in
the Tower was opened to the public," James I started
a small private one in St. James's Park. Here, away
from the eyes of his subjects, he kept 'flying squirrels
brought back from Virginia by Sir Thomas Dale,
sables from Russia, gyrfalcons from Iceland, five
camels, an elephant from the King of Spain (which
had four attendants and was given six bottles erf wine
daily in winter), and strangest of all, a cream fawn,
for which a woman was hired as a wet nurse.
The collection at the Tower became a centre of
great attraction, wild animals still being considerable
rarities for the populace. In his Diary, Pepys records
a visit in the 17th century there "to see the lions".
Not long afterwards a separate, privately-owned
collection of animals was kept in the Strand. This
was Pipcock's menagerie, later taken over by Cross,
who founded his own zoo in Surrey. One of the in¬
mates was Jack, a trained mandrill which smoked a
pipe and drank spirits. Cross's collections were
housed under a glass dome, and he studied the
longevity of captive carnivores. In 1731, the news
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
?
;
1 h
^ '- .
*
mfc
A ZOO BORN OF THE FRENCH REVOLUTION
Mid-nineteenth century engravings show monkey house (opposite page) and two views of bear pit at the Museum of Natural History, Paris.
Before the French Revolution this "King's Garden", founded by Louis XIII, was already being widely used for studies of the natural sciences,
and in particular of botany. Buffon, the famous 1 8th century naturalist, worked there for half a century. A menagerie was added in I 793
when Bernardin de St. Pierre, the famous author, managed to prevent the destruction of the animals in the royal menagerie at Versailles. From
that once magnificent collection there remained only a handful of beasts, including a kind of African antelope, a crested pigeon, an Indian rhino¬
ceros and an African lion. These five survivors of the revolutionary upheavel were the first boarders at the Museum of Natural History, as the
former King's Garden was named. The present Paris Zoo was opened at Vincennes on the eastern edge of the French capital in 1935.
that a litter of lion cubs had been born at the Tower
created a great sensation.
In 1735 an elaborate plan for a zoo for the Duke of
Savoy and Piedmont was drawn up, idealistically
indicating seven enclosures in a fan-shaped pattern,
laid out artistically with avenues of trees and with
only low walls separating the groups of bison, lions,
ostriches, wild goats and so on. . This does anticipate
much of the modern zop lay-out, and the Mappin
Terraces in Regent's Park, London, are not very
remote from this early idea.
By 1793 the French established a Museum of
Natural History in Paris, and Buifon's idea of having
a menagerie attached took shape in what still sur¬
vives as the Jardin des Plantes. The original
collection contained many valuable species and
boasted a lion and a dog living amicably together.
Although a great number of travelling and well-
patronized menageries were coming into vogue the
trend was towards the scientific keeping of wild crea¬
tures under more natural conditions, supported and
encouraged by the growing interest in natural history
museums and zoological societies.
Thus it was that Regent's Park gardens were
founded by the Zoological Society of London in 1826.
The collection from the royal menageries at the
Tower, together with certain deer, emus and ostriches
from Windsor Great Park were transferred to modern
conditions in London. Here were installed some 297
mammals, 637 birds and 18 reptilesnearly a
thousand creatures. By 1839 there were more than
twice as many.
The serious modern zoo had been born, and its like
appeared all over the world. The Phoenix Park Zoo
in Dublin was formed in 1830, and almost from the
start it achieved a reputation for the successful
breeding of lions. Bristol followed with the 'formation
of the Clifton Zoo in 1835, Manchester with its
privately-owned Belle Vue Zoo in 1836, Amsterdam
Zoo, owned by the Society Natura Artis Maglstra, in
1838; a large menagerie at Antwerp in 1843; the
famous and also privately-owned Tiergarten of Berlin,
1844 ; and some years later the gardens at Edinburgh.
Within the next twenty years or so, first-class zoo¬
logical gardens sprang up throughout the world. We
find zoos being established in such widely separated
places as Melbourne, 1857; Philadelphia, 1859; Co¬
logne, 1860; Hamburg, 1863; Copenhagen, 1859; Mos¬
cow, 1864; Calcutta, 1875; Cincinatti, 1875; and New
York, 1889 and 1890. In addition zoos were laid out
in Vienna, Rio de Janeiro, Hanover, Bombay, Tokyo,
Chicago, Detroit, San Francisco, Brussels, Buenos
Aires and countless other places, and the growth has
continued right up to the present.
By 1886, Regent's Park was a favourite and
fashionable London resort. Its population has not
diminished. It pioneered the use of radiant heat,
artificial sunlight and modern ventilation, amenities
now found in almost every large zoo. Almost all of
the zoos established in the nineteenth century sur¬
vive and flourish today, although several in Europe
were devastated during the war.
After a long and arduous history, zoos have now
come fully into their proper role which is to educate
the public, and especially young people, by inculcating
a love of and a kinship with natural creatures. This
is probably their greatest achievement.
_l ;
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A woman's life in an African village (Part m
Ministère de la France d'Outre-Mer
GOD OF THE FORGE and of fire in Dahomey, named
Gou, is shown here with headdress bearing symbols of
the metal-working trade.
D
uring the two years she spent in
Dahomey, Claudie Hauferlin, wife of an
ethnologist, was brought face to face with
the two Áfricas that exist side by side today
new Africa undergoing the birth pains
of modernization, and traditional Africa with
its polygamous families, minor rulers and
sorcerers. In the new Africa, where women
have won the right to vote, they have also
become printers and journalists, doctors
and magistrates. In the old Africa women
too have important roles as guardians of
traditions, for they cling, far more than do
the men, to ancestral rites and customs.
In the first part of her article, "A Woman's
Life in an African Village", (THE UNESCO
COURIER, March, 1957), Claudie Hauferlin
depicted the traditional Dahomey family
lifethe quarrels between wives, the songs,
marriage customs and social etiquette. Here
she shows us her friends in the village of
Mitro as astute and independent business
women, enjoying a larger measure of free¬
dom, as women, than is commonly believed,
and bringing up their families.
BUSINESS AFFAIRS
EXTENSIVE FREEDOM
RAISING A FAMILY
by Claudie Hauferlin
<t 1957
Few of the women of Mitro the nearest village to my
home in Dahomey cook meals very often for their
husbands, but as the Dahoman market is exactly like
an open-air restaurant, the husbands are in no danger
of starving. Bosi, a young woman with whom I spent
much time, is typical of the majority of wives in this
respect.
Her household chores include little cooking and not
much sewing, but on the other hand she often does
washing. Here in Dahomey, it is not considered em¬
barrassing to wear torn clothes. While it would be un¬
seemly to appear in a soiled pagne (half-skirt), a torn
garment is a sign of mourning or of straitened circumstan¬
ces, but never a proof of negligence.
Bosi rises early, about five o'clock, and washes and
dresses in her "bathroom" one of the little outhouses
made of dried, interwoven palm leaves which lean against
the side of every hut in the village. She sees to her
children and cleans out the hut. (The cleanliness of the
Southern Dahomey villages is striking; the women, with
brooms made of palm branches, seize every occasion of
sweeping in and around their huts). There are always
children to be washed and some laundry to be dried. Mo¬
thers rub their offspring vigorously with soap, and sluice
them down with water several times a day. At
Porto-Novo, they even install themselves with their tubs
on the pavements. Yet there are no taps in the houses;
water has to be fetched from the river or the well, which
is not always near, and carried back on the head in jars.
Since Dahoman women hardly ever have to cook, they
are able to devote time to trade in fact, "business" is
their main occupation. On the market place at Mitro,
Bosi sells akasa, a starchy maize paste, resembling
maizena, which, in Dahoman cooking, is as important as
the potato in some European cooking. She takes up her
stand at the market from 8 a.m. onwards or else, with her
basket on her head, goes round from tata to tata, display¬
ing her wares. (A tata is the group of houses of a single
family surrounded by mud walls.) At about 4 p.m. she
goes home where she finds plenty to do until the evening:
preparing the akasa for market, carrying maize to be
ground at the mill, making palm-oil for home use, and
paying various visits to kinsfolk in mourning, to her
mother, to a friend who has just had a baby, or to a
newly-married fellow trader.
Night falls swiftly in Africa; at 7.30 p.m. it is already
dark. For an hour, with lanterns flickering in every hut,
the whole village, looks like a Christmas tree. At 9 p.m.
everyone is asleep and the only sounds are the drone of
insects and the deep-throated croaking of the bull-frogs.
Sometimes, the harsh sound of the night-guards' horns
haunts the village until dawn. On such nights, no woman
would venture outside or even dare to peer curiously
through the window; for the task of policing the district
at night falls to a secret masculine society, known as the
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Zangbeto, and no woman is allowed to see what goes on.
One evening, Bosi, who had stayed late at a distant
market, met the night-guards as she reached Mitro. She
was fined, and recounting her adventure to me next day,
she added in a whisper: "If things were still as they used
to be, I should be dead now."
All the women of Mitro are traders. Tavi, the richest
of my women acquaintances, has a stall with a very
strange mixture of wares: pencils for schoolchildren, reels
of cotton, fish hooks, talcum powder, antimony for the
eyelids, and cigarettes. Videhu sells small piles of leaves,
which are used here as wrapping paper. As for Henrietta,
she takes her stand at the market with some frying palm-
oil and sells piping hot maize fritters to the passers-by,
inviting them to come and sample her "delicious crisp
fritters."
I spent a great deal of time at the market. An African
market is a place where news is exchanged quite as much
as goods. The Mitro market, held every other day, is one
of the busiest in the region; it is a meeting-place for the
people of the nearby plateau and those of the river.
Women who come from distant villages to buy or sell, set
out at two or three o'clock in the morning with forty to
fifty pounds of merchandise on their heads and their
babies comfortably asleep attached to their backs. They
return home about five o'clock in the evening.
As soon as she used to see me, Laly Yemadje, an old
fetisher-woman with whom I often
sat, would unwind the Madras hand¬
kerchief round her head to make me
a cushion. We would exchange smiles,
gestures and the few French or Gun
words which we both know: "Alors, ça
va?" (Well, everything all right?)
"Dagoe, dagbe." According to Daho¬
man etiquette, any conversation must
be prefaced by a long series of compli¬
ments and good wishes. With the
help of my interpreter, questions and
answers followed in quick succession:
"How are you?" "I am very well"
"How is your husband?""Very well,
you." Every member of the
family is mentioned .
Then came the good wishes: "May
you have continued good health",
"May your children be strong and
healthy", "May your business pros¬
per", etc. To every wish, Laly Yem¬
adje replied "ami", rubbing the palms
of her hands together. In her turn,
she hoped that I would have many
children, that my husband would be
made a governor or earn a larger
salary to which I answered "ami",
rubbing my hands. Here, silence is
certainly not golden. Patiently, the
family is enquired after again and
more good wishes are expressed.
When you receive a visitor in your
own house, etiquette does not require
that you stay to keep him company, but it does demand,
that you come back from time to time to say: "Please
make yourself comfortable."
When I first arrived in the village, Laly Yemadje was
selling maize. Although there is a whole series of recepta¬
cles for measuring cereals accurately, Laly Yemadje, like
all maize vendors, prefers to use baskets a little smaller
than the standard size. She presses her arms round the
basket, squeezing the maize up into a dome. Thus the
customer, impressed by the overflowing pyramid, always
has the feeling that he is getting more than his money's
worth and is better served here than elsewhere. As for
the vendor of fritters or croquettes, she does not raise her
prices at times when maize or manioc are scarce, but gives
smaller portions for the same price, which the customer
notices less.
Women are not obliged to stick to one kind of trade.
If Henrietta is in mourning for a few weeks and cannot
go near the fire or do any cooking, she collects wood and
chops it up for sale as firewood; Bosi does not hesitate to
give up her akasa trade temporarily in order to speculate
on maize. She keeps an eye on the price of cereals, finds
out how things are with the farmers who sell them and
cleverly takes advantage of the slight differences between
the harvest on the plateau and that in the valley. As for
Laly Yemadje; after dealing in maize for a few months
Ministère de la France d'Outre-mer
One of the wives of the head chief of Porto
Novo shows off her magnificent jewellery.
The Unesco Courier. Mo/ 1957
she turns to selling palm-oil. This is the great trade of
women one of the most profitable, but also the one which
is the most severely threatened by the establishment of
oil factories. These concerns buy directly from the men
who own the palm-plantations and the women are thus
in danger of losing an entire source of earnings. For them
it is a potential catastrophe.
The profits that a Dahoman woman makes from her
business are administered by her alone in other words,
she benefits from similar rights to those which women
enjoy, for example, In England, under the Married Wo¬
man's Property Act. The receipts from the market often
do not amount to much fifty to one hundred francs a
day but they are regular and, moreover, a woman's right
to keep and to dispose of her earnings as she pleases, gives
her a privileged position in the country's economic system.
A woman is thus able to keep herself if her husband
does not fulfil his duty to feed his wife. And husbands
are often slack about that "He used to keep me when I
was young," Videhu told me, "but now he seldom gives
me any money." Bosi and Tavi who have "'good"
husbands admit that they sometimes contribute to the
household expenses, especially during that period of bridg¬
ing the gap between harvests when food prices rise.
They all told me, too, that they lend money against
interest. Women are often the bankers of the family, and
sometimes even of the entire village, where they control
practically all of the trade. They
earn less money than men, but they
earn it more regularly and it is to
them that the men turn when in need
of funds; often, in fact, men in debt
obtain loans from the women by
pledging their future harvests as
security. This whole financial bal¬
ance is now, of course, threatened by
Industrialization.
Tavi uses her money to make herself
attractive. She showed me her ward¬
robe one day; it contained twenty-
six skirts for special occasions and
ten everyday ones. "If they are
shabby", she said, "I give them to
my grandmother".
Bosi, the most thrifty, confided to
me that she is putting money aside
in the hope of buying herself a palm-
plantation one day; that is exception¬
al, because palm-plantations belong
to men and when a woman possesses
such land she tries to hide the fact
that she is the owner.
Henrietta, before her marriage,
used her earnings to set up her future
home; but now she puts some aside
so that she may one day be able to
open an ironmongery business. When
I questioned Videhu, she threw up
her hands in despair and said: "I have
only the skirt I'm wearing. Money?
I never have any I don't know where it goes. I'm sure
that someone has cast a spell on me!" Remarks like these
are very common: you do not manage your affairs badly,
but you have enemies who send you bad luck. One day,
I asked a schoolboy how he had done in his examinations
and he replied: "Badly! An uncle of mine has a spite
against me."
One day, Laly Yemadje said to me: "When I have given
a customer credit and she does not pay up, I go to see her
and flatter her, but above all I do not get angry with her,
otherwise she would buy nothing more from me." Few
women, however, are as patient as Laly Yemadje. Fre¬
quent disputes take place during which the defaulting
customer often puts on an offended air. Insults to the
family and warnings of impending diseases follow there
is no lack of pursuasive arguments. "Personally," said
Bosi, "I warn all my friends if one of my customers is in
the habit of not paying for the goods that she buys on
credit. The word goes around and in the end the woman
is forced to change markets because no one will sell her
anything any more." One morning, I saw
a shabbily-dressed man arrive at the mark¬
et; he strode round it several times, shout- Cont'd on
ing volubly and making threatening ges¬
tures. "One of the vendors has given him
some money", my interpreter explained, "to
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SCULPTURE BY
THE BLIND
by Bertha Gaster
Seven years ago eleven people sat
down in a San Francisco art
class to do the impossible.
Plunging their hands into masses of
wet clay for the first time in their
lives, they set out to make sculptured
portrait busts of themselves. And
they were blind.
It was Jeanne Kewell, a young and
gifted art-teacher from the California
School of Fine Arts who first con¬
ceived of sculpture as a method of
helping the sightless to use their
hands and find a valuable emotional
outlet. Her original group of stu¬
dents, chosen from the San Francisco
Centre for the Blind with no regard
to talent or manual dexterity, caught
fire from her enthusiasm. They
learnt and carried out all the ne¬
cessary technical processes for them¬
selves, from the initial mixing of the
clay to the hollowing out of the mo¬
dels before firing. For nine months
they worked, patting, pressing, mould¬
ing the clay, and at the end of the
year the doors of the California
School of Fine Arts opened on an
exhibition of eleven completed clay
and terra cotta self-portraits made
by eleven sightless men and women.
Three of the eleven were blind from
birth; others went blind later.
Others again could still distinguish
light from darkness, but these latter
removed their glasses so that "all of
the students might be on a more
equal footing". There could be no
mirror for them, no gauging of dis-
16
tance and relationship with pencil or
thumb. They built their figures
slowly in wet clay, feeling their own
bone structure, shape of feature,
details of hair and expression, finger¬
ing the fold of flesh and curve of lips,
forcing out of the clay, it seems, not
only the likeness of their features but
also some visible expression of an
emotional attitude; for the astonished
public could not only clearly reco¬
gnize the extraordinary physical
resemblances, but also the suggestion
of profound feeling built into the
terra cotta and clay. What the artists
said about their own work is very
revealing. "I lived in a world of ideas
and sounds", said Leonid Malarevsky,
a former accountant who lost his sight
during the war, "and sculpture
brought me back to the world of di¬
mensions". Said Elsie Northern: "I
get at the open window in the morn¬
ing and look up and wish that I could
do something worth while". Even
more moving were the words of Louise
Bixler: "T wanted to portray the
sagging feeling in a person when they
can scarcely bear any more... I didn't
think of the head as just a chunk of
clay, but I thought here, under here,
is my heart... I was thinking of what
life had made of me."
After the West Coast exhibition the
busts were shown at the Brooklyn
Museum in New York, and later at a
private art gallery, arousing enorm¬
ous interest and a great deal of dis¬
cussion. Some critics pointed out the
high degree of manual dexterity and
tactile awareness in these works;
others related a certain monumental-
ity and austerity in the portraits to
the art of other periods, such as early
Egyptian art, when expressive quali¬
ties were counted of greater impor¬
tance than visual ones. Others again
claimed that memory played the
predominant role, and insisted that
strict representationalism had been
the aim, and Che lack of pictorial
detail was more a limitation of sight
than a deliberate choice of form.
Since that time the experiment has
expanded and the particular value
of sculpture for the blind become
more widely recognized.
In Amsterdam, for instance, at an
exhibition of the work of the English
sculptor Henry Moore in the Stedelijk
Museum, the director invited several
blind people to visit it and tell him
what they thought of the different
works. Patting, stroking, passing
their hands over the curves and
angles, over the forms of this sculptor,
their first reactions were much the
same as the sighted public. The
shapes did not feel like bodies and
heads, they thought. But some of
them, returning again and again,
liked them more and more. As one
of them said, "It is better when you
come to understand that Mr. Moore
isn't imitating life but telling you
about it. It is the same with music."
Jeanne Kewell, in the meantime,
had been extending her work to the
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Moy 1957
I LIKE TO RIDE ON THINGS... "...especially on
boy's shoulders... I like horses... I got six at horre," said
the author of this "Horse and Rider." Aged 1 I when he
modelled this work, he became blind at seven.
£, Bob Hollingsworth 1957
education of blind children. A class
of eighteen ranging roughly in age
from nine to thirteen, with one girl
of seventeen among them, was cho¬
sen, again without regard for artistic
leanings. "The sighted child", says
Jeanne Kewell, "learns through visual
exploration and initiation. The blind
child does not. Through sculpture"
she claims, "he can come to know the
intimacy of objects, formulations,
concepts, and ideas". The eighteen
children, therefore, were given the
clay to play with and handle, chose
their subjects and began to model,
no one child working for more than
a total of thirty-two hours over a
four-month period.
What subjects did they choose ?
The little girl whose family group had
been separated through illness and
death modelled families the dog
family, the bird family, in smooth
rounded shapes. Others chose single
animals, birds, cats, dogs, horses all,
be it observed, domestic animals they
may once have seen. The child
with no visual memory, blind from
birth, made a rough unrecognizable
heap representing a bird, in a nest
curiously suggestive of the walls of a
room; children who had been studying
King Arthur in English class modelled
knights in the clay. «They were hor¬
rible men, I think", said one, "you
can hear the blood".
Extraordinarily powerful in its
sense of opposing forces is the horse
and rider modelled by an eleven-year-
old boy, blind since seven. "I like to
ride on things" he said, adding "I
like horses especially". Unbearably
poignant is "The Solitary child"
three figures at the playground
bench, two together at one end, one
small immobile form seated alone at
the other. The blind nine-year-old
who made it gave a name to the child
sitting spart. It was his own. And
there are the two solid featureless
figures modelled by a thirteen-year-
old girl. Her brief explanation of them
may well stand for all these children
struggling in blackness "She says
take me out of the dark, dark dun¬
geon. He is signalling to go".
Whether the theories of aesthetic
values propounded by some of the cri¬
tics are valid, time alone will tell.
But of the healing and releasing pro¬
perties of this form of activity for the
blind, in this new method of expres¬
sion and appreciation, there can be
little doubt. The faceless
figure with bound hands
cries "Take me out of the
dark, dark, dungeon"
Jeanne Kewell has opened
a door.
î u
A BIRD IN ITS
NEST. A little girl
aged eight and blind
from birth expressed
her conception of a
tiny bird in its nest.
Through the creative
work of her hands
she has given a new
dimension to her life.
© Bob Hollingsworth
1957
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
SCULPTURE BY THE BLIND (Continued)
Blind youngsters often choose as subjects for their sculpture the domestic
animals which are familiar companions and which they may have seen
sometime in the past. Two animal forms (above) were made by a boy
aged I I who had been blind for four years. Below, cat studies. Left,
M"85
t '7\b o
«
1
V
c
i
r,
<
ft
'.;
i
í
l
4
0^'^^L
1
V
^8
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. May 1957
à JA
t
X
*1
Í'
Q
i
J
fi
ft*
H .\
t: ^ 'îfWÇ*'^ Ak
' {
|
*
f a .,
i
£3â$4I « i^
HL' j
r
© Bob Hollingsworth 1957
THREE-LEGGED RACE was depicted In clay by a
totally blind I 2-years-old girl who had run in this race
at school Field Day. About this event another child
said: "Do you know how blind people run ? There Is a
big old wire at the end of the rope. You take hold ofthat
. rope and start running real fast, and he counts the sec¬
onds; once I did it In nine point eight on the 50 yard dash."
a boy (the sculptor himself, aged I I) carrying a cat; centre, a curled up
cat modelled by a nine-year-old girl, visually handicapped at the age of
two; right, an attacking cat made by a partially blind girl of nine. "They
move quietly," she said, "and are sneaky. Kittens are not as fierce."
Photos © Bob Hollingsworth 1957
,-
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
by
Kees Boeke
Text and illustra¬
tions copyright by
the author. Repro¬
duction prohibited.
FORTY JUMPS
THROUGH
THE UNIVERSE
On the pages that follow, we Invite our readers on an imaginery and fantastic journey through space
the world of the infinitely large and the world of the Infinitely small. Our voyage will be un¬
dertaken In a unique fashion, by a series of 40 jumps in the direction of a straight line perpendicular
to the horizon. In the first part of the voyage each jump will be on a scale ten times smaller (In the
second part on a scale ten times larger) than the preceding one until we have reached the two extre¬
me limits of size of our Universe. Forty Jumps Through the Universe, or "Cosmic View", as its author
terms it, has been devised by Kees Boeke founder and former director of the Werkplaats Children's
Community at Bilthoven, Netherlands, a pioneer "comprehensive school" created in 1926. The
school is now associated with the International Federation of Children's Communities founded with
the aid of UNESCO. Forty Jumps Through the Universe reveals In a novel and fascinating fashion
the different orders of magnitude of the Brobdingnagian and Lilliputian worlds around us, and
can serve as a stimulating complement to the UNESCO pamphlet "Man Measures the Universe"
(see inside back cover for details concerning this pamphlet and free offer to subscribers).
IT is important for us human beings who are living together on
our little planet to widen our sphere of interest. We are too
often inclined to consider our immediate surroundings as our
"world". For some of us it may be the house in which we live,
for others our village or town, for many our country. For the
few it is the continent, for fewer still the whole earth. But even
this horizon is too limited. We must develop a truly cosmic view
if we are to become free from the narrow provincialism, the chau¬
vinistic outlook, which is such a hindrance to a truly human atti¬
tude, and therefore one of the great dangers which beset mankind.
In order to develop this cosmic view, and thus as a help in
education for international understanding, the material which fol¬
lows has been devised (1). In the hands of a teacher who has
this wide outlook and interest, it may help children and young
people to realize their relative position in the great and mysterious
whole of the Universe.
At school we are introduced to a great many different spheres
of existence, but they are often not connected with each other.
It is therefore of value in our education to supply ourselves with
the means of developing a wider and more connected view of the
strange world in which we are placed.
This series of illustrations, published for the first time in the
pages of the unesco courier, originated years ago in a school
in the Netherlands, the "Werkplaats Children's Community" at
Bilthoven, where a group of children under my guidance drew
the original pictures which form its basis.
I began this project with them because I realized the importance
of developing a "sense of scale" and I therefore proposed to the
children to draw the same objects in different scales, using the
units of the "metric system".
When we started to make the pictures, we at once saw that it
looked as if we were going right up into the sky, so that we saw
the objects from ever increasing heights, smaller and smaller, where¬
as at the same time a constantly increasing area around them
was included in our view. We also noticed that the imaginary
jump we had to make to see the next picture at a ten times smaller
. (1) It will shortly be published in book form under the title "Cosmic
View : Forty Jumos through the Universe" (John Day Company, 62 West
ASth Street, New York 36, New York, U.S.A.). Price : $2.95. It will then
also be published in the Netherlands in Dutch.
scale had to be ten times higher than the one before, and we
soon found that we had started on a tremendous journey of
exploration, for we began to wonder what we would discover if
we kept on going up in the same way.
In undertaking such a plan, it was first necessary to decide on
the date and time of day, for we had to know where the sun would
be at that moment. With the group of children in Holland, we
assumed that the moment of observation in each case would be,
and would remain, the 21st of December 1951, at noon. We
knew that the sun would then be in what is called the "'Winter
Solstice", and that it would stand in the south.
We chose as our object to start with a little girl sitting in a deck
chair in the courtyard in front of the school building, and facing
south. When we started on our project, we hardly suspected what
our self-imposed task, which seemed so simple, would lead to.
The first 26 pictures are the record of such an imaginary journey
up into space.
The question then arose : what should we see, if instead of
decreasing the scale, we should increase it each time in order to
plunge into the world of the infinitely small ? To find this out,
we had to go back to the original picture of the little girl sitting
in front of the school. We then began a second journey of
exploration, which proved to be as full of marvels as the first,
and which is shown in the second half of this story in pictures on
page 28.
In our jump upwards into the heavens (Numbers 1 to 26) each
illustration is on a scale ten times smaller than the one before it.
This means that every centimetre (or inch) in a drawing is equiva¬
lent to a ten times larger distance, than the drawing preceding it.
Thus the first picture is on a scale of "one to fifteen", that is, one
centimetre portrays what in reality is 15 centimetres. In the
second picture, one centimetre represents ten times the distance or
a length of 150 centimetres, and so on until the centimetre in illus¬
tration 26 stands for a real length of unimaginable magnitude.
1 cm = 10 millimetres or 4/10 inch. Thus a centimetre in one
view simply becomes the same number of millimetres in the next.
In our jump downward into the microcospic world (Numbers 0 to
minus 13) the reverse is true, and each photo is on a scale ten
times larger than the one before it until in the final illustration
each centimetre stands for a real length of unimaginable tinyness.
Under each photo the scientific degree of scale is indicated.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier, May 1957
1 ' One centimetre in picture = I 5 centimetres in reality.
OCHILD AND CAT. Our voyage Into the universe begins with
this simple photograph of a girl holding a cat. This is what we
are going to look at as we move straight up into the sky at noon on
December 21, 1951. Cat is used merely to compare sizes of living
creatures as they would occur In later domains of scale. It is assumed
we look down on scene from a height of S metres (I 6 x/2 ft), or 33 cm
on this scale. Smallest humans are pygmies: average 1. 45 m (4.80ft).
Tallest: Patagonians and Lake Chad Africans (1.84 m; 6.07 ft).
-* One cm = ISO cms. Drawings by EN do Bouter
OTEN TIMES SMALLER. The small square in the centre of this
second illustration is the miniature image, reduced ten times, of the
preceding picture. Near the child with the cat we can see the compar¬
ative size of two automobiles and the front part of a blue whale, the
largest animal the world has ever known. The giant blue whale meas¬
ures up to 34 metres (I 00 feet). Diplodocus was about 25 m (82.5 ft)
long. Certain Américain sequoias have attained heights of 83 m
(274 ft), some marine algae lengths of 100-200 m (330-660 ft).
I i I cm = 1,500 cm = 1 5 metres.
©WHALE IN A SCHOOL. We now look down from a height of
500 meters (1,640 ft) on a U-shaped building (I) the Werkplaats
Children's Community at Bilthoven, Netherlands. In the courtyard
Is the small square which corresponds to the previous illustration. We
now can see the whole whale (2), and the two cars are still visible (3)
but the little girl (4) is practically invisible. The long building (5)
is typically Dutch: It is a large bicycle shed for the numberless bicycles
on which the children from the surrounding area come to school
I cm ' 15,000 cm = ISO metres.
O CHILD HAS VANISHED. It is surprising that already in this
fourth image the child which filled the greater parte**/ the first picture
has completely disappeared. We must not forget that each time we
jump upward we rise ten times higher than we were in order to produce
an image ten times smaller than the one before. The wavy line reaching
the child represents, symbolically, a radio wave of the Hilversum Sender,
enabling us to compare Its wave length with the other objects In this
illustration. We are at a height of 5,000 metres or 5 km (3 miles).
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
FORTY JUMPS (Continued)
i	1 I cm- 1,500 metres.
OUTRECHT AND BILTHOVEN. We have now jumped to a
height of 50,000 meters or 50 kilometers (3 I miles). We notice
the second effect of the jumps we are making: not only do all things we
see become smaller each time, but the area also Increases tenfold.
Picture is not the complete field of vision of what the eye could encom¬
pass at this height. Above Illustration covers a square with sides
15 kilometers long (9.3 miles). Bilthoven (I) is a suburb of Utrecht
(2) fourth largest town of the Netherlands, located in centre of country.
1 v i * y
IV * 1
7 1
7
8 A
\
rt y
]_ \ (jJ\ ) Y ' :$j .v\- "V^-N-
/ ^vT-^^-i 'A&
/emtls
I 6V_
V \ ¿r "v^-^-
9 J~^^--^
I ru^~~~-V *À	f* ^-s^"*"*^
l¥~^^*^*^
&-£^' m'i\ **-** \
/~?V.
XT
' Tl
r4
I cm = I 5,000 metres = I 5 kms.
©CENTRAL NETHERLANDS. Our sixth |ump shows the cen¬
tral part of the Netherlands. Small square contains Bilthoven and
Utrecht. Holland's principal towns: Amsterdam (I), The Hague (2),
Rotterdam (3), and rivers Rhine (4) and Meuse (5) are now visible.
Bay In north (former Zuyderzee) is now a lake named after the river
Yssel (6), an arm of the Rhine which flows into It. In the Yssel Lake
new land (7) is being reclaimed by the use of dykes (8) and water-
pumping apparatus. In right centre, town of Arnhelm (9) is seen.
1	' I cm= I 5,000 kms.
O PLANET. Even more than in previous drawing the Earth now
shows up as the planet It is, spinning in anti-clockwise direction on
its axis in empty space. The sun, to the south, casts Its shadow towards
north. Two dotted lines mark limits of this shadow or "umbra" (I), as
otherwise they could not be shown against the blackness all around.
Other dotted line shows path of earth, moving from right to left. Many
distant stars would be visible but are omitted here and in following
drawings to concentrate attention on our "immediate surroundings".
22
H I cm» 150,000 kms.
«\ EARTH AND MOON. Readers will probably have noted that
r the shaded part of the earth in the two previous Illustrations was
clearly lighter on left side. The cause Is clear In this picture. Here
we see not only the earth (I) its path (2) and umbra (3) but the path
of the moon (4) around the earth. The actual position of the moon
on December 21 1951... when our Imaginary series of jumps through
the universe takes placeis shown at (5). It is now clear that as the
moon was on the left, night on earth was lit up there by Its reflected light.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
i	1 I cm = I 50 kms.
O 1 5 COUNTRIES. Whereas picture 6 gave part of a country
with its towns, this one shows a portion of a continent (Europe)
with a number of its countries. Actually 15 countries are wholly or
partly visible. The map further shows three seas: North Sea, the
Baltic and Adriatic, and a portion of the Atlantic. The spherical shape of
the earth becomes visible: a parallel of latitude demonstrates this, but
the curvitude is so slight, that the map can yet be thought of as flat.
' ' I cm = 1,500 kms.
O THE EARTH. Now we can see five of the six continents. Only
Australia is not visible. The northern part of the globe is in shad¬
ow since the picture was taken on December 21 at noon. The sun
was then in the South, and daylight did not reach further North than
the polar circle. The shaded area is lighter than it should be in order
to show the visible portions of North America and northeast Asia.
The North pole (I) and the equator (2) as well as the meridians and
parallels of latitude for every IS0 are shown as series of dotted lines.
-n I cm = 1,500,000 kms. -h I cm = I 5 million kms.
®INTO OUTER SPACE. Shape of moon's orbit in previous
picture appears to be a circle. In reality it is an ellipse, but slight
difference Is only visible in the position of earth which is in the focus
of the ellipse and hence not in the centre. Dotted curve in preceding
drawing shows moon's orbit as it would actually appear from our
imagined observation point. Difference cannot be distinguished in
picture above which shows the earth (I), the moon and its orbit (2),
earth's umbra (3) and orbit (4). Latter is seen as slightly curved.
©VENUS IN VIEW. In our I 2th jump we have risen 500 million
kilometres from our starting point. The tiny circle (I) is now
the moons' orbit. The earth has become invisibly small but its position
is marked by a dot although this is much too large. The earth's orbit (2)
is now seen to be clearly curved. Under it the orbit of the planet Venus
(3) has come into view. No other planet approaches so near to the
earth. The ancients atfirst believed Venus was two planets alternatively
visible : Vesper, the evening star, and Lucifer, the morning star.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
FORTY JUMPS (Continued)
I cm
©
50 million kms.
SUN COMES IN. The sun (I) has now come into the picture.
The dot denoting it and of course that showing the earth (2) are
much too big. Inside the earth's orbit are the planets Mercury (3)
and Venus (4). Outside It are Mars (5) and Jupiter (6) with their
orbits. The position of the planets in this and the following drawings
is that which they occupied on December 21, 1951. Apart from the
sun and the planets we see part of the orbit of Halley's comet (7),
which comes into our "neighbourhood" once every seventy-seven years.
-i I cm = 1,500 million kms.
©OUR SOLAR SYSTEM. Whole Solar System now is in view.
Sun and planets Mercury, Venus, Earth and Mars are reduced
to tiny circle (I) but other planets and orbits are clearly seen: Jupi¬
ter (2), Saturn (3), Uranus (4), Neptune (5) and Pluto (6). Pluto's
orbit at one place is Inside that of Neptune's. Entire orbit of
Halley's Comet is now visible with its position in 1951 (7). It will
be near Earth again In 1986. Elliptic nature of planets' orbits is
noticeable only for Pluto. Light on this scale would travel I cm per hour.
I cm = 1,5 million million km*.
©SOLAR SYSTEM A PIN POINT. This seems like a most
uninteresting picture; it contains no more than a tiny white dot
In the centre of a black square. Yet the spot stands for our whole Solar
System (the sun along with all the planets, comets, asteroids and meteor¬
ites which move around it... and their orbits!). Numberless stars, we
see at night, may possibly have similar satellites moving around them.
On this scale our SolarSystem would beonlya little more than a tenth of
a millimetre in diameter, and light would travel 6.3 cm in a year!
24
©
I I cm = about 1.5 light years.
OUR NEAREST STAR. For the first time we now show another
star besides the sun. The Solar System is the point (I). The
dot (2) is the double star Alpha Centauri, the nearest visible star to
Earth' It is about 25 billion miles (in U.S. trillion miles) or 4 light
years away, (i.e. light travelling at I 86,000 miles a second takes 4 years
to cover the space). A jet plane going 700 miles (1,120 km) an hour
would take almost a million years to reach it. From our observation
point here looking down the sun is closer to us than Alpha Centauri.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
-) I cm = I 5,000 million km.
©SHRINKING SOLAR SYSTEM. Here whole "Solar System",
with the sun and all the smaller bodies which move around it,
has been reduced to a circle a little over I cm. These pictures really
give a wrong impression of what the Solar System would look like,
as all the orbits are shown. What would be seen would be only sun
as a small star and near It the planets, which themselves give no light,
but are lit up on side facing sun. Only a powerful telescope would
make them visible from present distance of 500,000 million kms.
-i I cm = I 50,000 million km.
©SOLAR SYSTEM A PIN-HEAD. We have now come to a
height of 5 million million kilometres above the horizon of the
village in Holland from which we started. It would have taken light
more than 6 months to cover that enormous distance from the earth,
travelling at the rate of 299,800 kilometers ( I 86,000 miles) per second.
As we have imagined that we made our trip without spending any
time, this means that if we had a marvellously good telescope we could
at this point see what happened on our little earth over six months ago !
I	' I cm = about I 5 light years.
©36 NEIGHBOUR STARS. Apart from sun and Alpha Centauri,
36 stars are now shown, all visible with naked eye from Earth and
all less than 50 light years from sun. Circle marks distance of 50 light
years from sun. Sun would no longer be visible without a telescope,
for star of its magnitude is barely visible with naked eye from dis¬
tance of more than 55 light years. Present point of observation:
500 light years away. Stars marked 3 and 4 might have been shown
in the previous drawing. The stars are identified in next caption.
1 cm = about I 50 light years.
AJJv 5,000 LIGHT YEARS AWAY. Stars in photo 19 are here
*mr shown from distance ten times removed, now 5,000 light years
from Earth. Best known are identified. Sun is at (I), then Alpha
Centauri (2), Beta Hydri (3), Delta Pavlonl (4), Castor (5), Pollux (6),
Capella (7), Procyon (8), Sirius (9), Arcturus (10), Altair (I I), Wega
(12). Seen from Earth, Sirius is brightest of all stars and relatively
near our planet: 51,000,000,000,000 miles or 6.5 light years. The
star Arcturus is 33 light years from Earth, Castor is 47 light years away.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
FORTY JUMPS (Continued)
I cm = about 1,500 light years.
¿J\ BEYOND SOLAR SYSTEM. We have now jumped so high
y¿V that we have come right out of the complex of stars to which our
Solar System belongs, and which we can see on a clear star-lit night as
a strip right across the sky: the "Milky Way" or "Galactic System".
It contains thousands of millions of stars. Our sun ¡s a very unimportant
one and is located not In centre but on outskirts as seen above. In
tiny square sun and Its 37 neighbour stars have become a tiny dot.
i i I cm *= about I 5,000 light years.
©THE MILKY WAY. We now see whole galactic system or
"Galaxy". It Is a "Spiral", a circular disk with protruding spiral
arms and bulging centre. We see it partly tilted, hence as an ellipse.
In small square we recognize a rather irregular spiral, near which our
Solar System is situated. Other spiral arms can be seen. Below on
right ¡s a nebulous body, the Great Magellanic Cloud, a much smaller
galaxy, far behind our "Milky Way". White dots around galaxy are
some of the 100 ör more clusters of stars which surround it.
©
I cm = about I 5 million light years. I parsec = 3.26 light years.
MORE WORLDS. Countless galaxies and clusters of galaxies
are known to be spread out in all directions around our "Local
Group". In previous drawings only a few galaxies were shown but
were put in their correct positions. Here no more than a general
sketch can be given of the numberless worlds surrounding them. Each
galaxy or stellar nebula is isolated in space by an almost complete vac¬
uum extending for one or two million light years. Bridges of matter
between certain galaxies have, however, been discovered in recent years.
26
' I I cm = 150 million light years.
©STILL MORE WORLDS. Some thousand million galaxies are
visible with present telescopes, the furthest 2,000 million light
years from Earth. Galaxies are not fixed in position relative to one
another; they are moving away from each other at varying speeds.
According to one theory the Universe Is continuously expanding.
Clusters of galaxies, above, have been placed arbitrarily. What is
shown is certainly very much less than what actually exists, in the Immen¬
sity of the Universe, for the galaxies would be much nearer to each other
and they would continue far beyond the confines of the present picture...
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
I cm = about I 50,000 light years,
®200 MILLION YEARS TO ROTATE. Inside small square
we see our Galaxy (I) and Great Magellanic Cloud (2). Outside
are Small Magellanic Cloud (3) and two galaxies relatively "near"
Milky Way: the "Sculptor (4) and Fornax (5) Systems. Many other
galaxies would be visible but are omitted to centre attention on "our
nearest neighbours". Galaxy Is whirling in clockwise direction, its
spirals trailing; once around in 200 million years. Yet this movement
gives Solar System terrific speed of 216 km (135 miles) per second.
©
i I cm = about 1,500,000 light years.
JUST A 'LOCAL GROUP'. Galaxies tend to draw together
in groups, some small, others hundreds or even a thousand strong.
Our Galaxy belongs to a small group, called the "Local Group". Ellip¬
soidal in shape, its larger axis is 2 million light years long. Nearest
galaxies to ours were shown in previous photo. The Magellanic Clouds
are respectively 150,000 and 170,000 light years from sun. Among
more distant galaxies, Messier 3 1 Cluster (6) the Great Spiral
Nebula in constellation Andromeda is 1,600,000 light years from sun.
FROM MACROCOSM TO MICROCOSM
How far these countless millions of worlds continue outside the large square of illustration n° 26 is
not known. All these worlds seem to be rushing away from a centre somewhere, and therefore
from each other. Their speed seems to increase the further away they have proceeded on their
ways. It seems also that space is curved, but how it is curved is not yet known, nor do we know
if the Universe has a "radius". As all this is still so vague and uncertain, we end our imaginary journey
into these infinite expanses of space and turn back, to go through all the stages we passed on our flight
upwards. Let us attempt to picture to ourselves what it means each time the small central square extends
and extends as we come nearer and nearer to the Solar System, which must be there in the centre... until
at last the small square has grown to the size of the large one, and what we then see is to be found on
the previous drawing. It is clear that on this return journey the height from which we view the pa¬
norama decreases each time tenfold from station to station. When we have returned to the original
picture of the little girl in her chair, which we reproduce again on the next page, the height of our point
of observation has again become only 5 metres, and when we continue in the same way to the next
picture, it will be one tenth of this, that is only 50 centimetres.
We shall see, when we pursue our campaign of exploration, that on this journey we can go
through only half the number of stages we passed on the first expedition. We shall reach the unknown
after 13 of them whereas in the journey upwards we counted 26 jumps. But who will say what wonders
are hidden beyond the limits of man's investigations of today?
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
FORTY JUMPS (Continued)
i
-
-H I cm = I 5 cm in reality.
OPREPARE TO PLUNGE. We now begin the second part of our
adventure, this time plunging downward into the world of the
infinitely small. Our jumping off point is once again the girl with her
cat. One of the things we have wanted to find out has been: in how
many of the domains of scale are living creatures known to occur ;
Thus far we have found them only in photos numbered I, 2 and 3.
From now on we shall continue to look for representatives of the
living world in all succeeding scales. Unusual creatures and objects will
be assembled on the hand of the child to help us compare their sizes.
©
I cm in picture = 1.5 cm in reality.
HIND LEGS UP. We are now looking down from a height of
'50 centimetres (20 in.). The first living creature we meet is an
Anopheles or malaria mosquito. We can tell this from the way it
sticks up its hind legs. We also notice a little cut in the girl's finger.
In the centre of the tiny square we may be able to distinguish a minute
white spot. It is a grain of salt. We will note that, contrary to our
upward flight Into the heavens, in our downward plunge each square
in the centre will be ten times enlarged in the following image while
the tiny square within ¡twill be 100 times enlarged two pictures later.
-* I cm = 1.5 x I0-J cm.
©THE MICROBE SCALE. Height from which we are looking
down on skin has now been reduced to five-tenths of a millimetre,
or 500 "microns" to introduce the microbe scale. A micron is one-
thousandth of a millimetre. Living creatures here are bacteria: coll ( I)
diphtheria (2), tubercle bacillae (3) and pneumonia bacteria (4). Bacte¬
rium in inset can now be recognized as a typhoid bacillus (5) such
as human beings may "carry" unknowingly for a long time. Its
flagella are clearly shown and will be magnified separately in inset.
On this scale height of salt crystal (6) would be over 30 cm. (I ft).
I cm = 1 . 5 X I 0-* cm = 1.5 micron.
©VIRUS OBSERVED. Fourth jump has taken us Into a world
so minute that electron microscope is needed to get an idea of
shapes of living creatures. Diphtheria bacillus is at (I). We see sau¬
sage-shaped coli bacterium (2) being attacked by tiny bacteriophages (3).
A smallpox virus has now come into view (4). We note how keratin
of the skin curls up (5) before falling off. Extreme thinness of gold
leaf is shown at (6). Wave lengths of red (7) and violet light (8) are
symbolically represented. Inset shows typhoid bacillus (9) with flagella
( 1 0). Height of salt crystal on this scale would be over 3 metres ( I 0 ft).
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. May 1957
;^%,j0f{ir,
s/l\ %ß- 6 5
©INVISIBLE WITH EYE. Minimum distance an object must be
from human eye to be seen clearly is 25 cm. ( 1 0 in.). We have
here reached 5 cm. (2 in.) and with a magnifying glass can distinguish
the furrows in the skin. Small organisms at (I) are water mites and
bacteria. In bottom right corner inset there is a bacterium still too
small to be seen. In wound we see a section of epidermis and above it
grain of salt. Mosquito now appears like huge monster: large com¬
pound eyes are at (2), feelers (3), jaws (4) and proboscis (5) stinging
child. We see flexible sheath (6) bent in curve as it touches skin.
I cm = 1.5 x 0.01 cm = 1.5 x I O-' cm.
©INSIDE THE SKIN. We should need a microscope to see this
picture, taken from a height of only 5 mm. (2/ 1 0 of an inch). One
of the water mites seen on previous drawing is a cyclops ( I). In section
of the skin we note the horny keratin layer (2) on top. Under it the
Malpighian Layer (3) with its numerous pigment cells, and the opening
(pore) of a sweat duct (4). Under that lies the Corium (5) with its
nerve endings or papillae (6), small blood vessels (7) and fat cells (8).
Only point of penetration of mosquito's proboscis into skin is shown
here (9). In inset, we can just see the bacterium as a tiny dot (10).
-* I cm = 1 . 5 x I 0-5 cm = 0. 1 5 micron. I cm = 1.5 X I O." cm = 0.01 5 micron.
©MOLECULES' APPEARANCE. On upper layer of keratin (I)
viruses are crowded together as they often are on skin. One of
the largest is small pox (2). A bacteriophage of medium size (3) is
shown very distinctly from electron microscope observation merely
to give size and shape for it would not be likely to lie there by
itself. Many molecules could be shown. Two starch molecules (4) are
represented in the above Illustration. Inset shows the helical
structure of flagellum (5) as given by electron microscope. Height of
salt crystal on this scale: 30 metres (100 ft) or length of blue whale.
©HIGHER THAN EIFFEL TOWER. This scale has a magnifi¬
cation of more than 600,000. The electron microscope can no
longer give us clear images here, for at most it has magnified 100,000
times. Yet we know that living creatures exist on this scale. Shown
are infantile paralysis virus (I) already visjble in -5, and hoof and
mouth disease virus (2) about smallest known to now. Molecules
of air are visible as dots (3). Electron micro-photograph shows
flagellum (inset) composed of three strands. Height of salt crystal on
this scale would be over 300 metres (990 ft) or taller than Eiffel Tower!
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
FORTY JUMPS (Continued)
I cm = I . S X I 0-' cm = 0.00 1 5 micron.
©MAGNIFIED 6 MILLION TIMES. Though magnification is
now over six million times, X-ray diffraction method permits dis¬
tances of successive layers of sodium (I) and chlorine (2) atoms in lat¬
tice of salt crystal to be accurately shown. Yet on this scale height
of salt crystal would be 3 kms (1.8 miles). Oxygen (3) and nitrogen
(4) molecules are moving about as "air" at approximate distances
shown. Nitrogen molecules are slighter larger and over 3 times more
numerous. Inset shows one of strands of flagellum, though only
hydrogen atoms are given. Dotted lines (5) show limits of molecules.
3
m
m *
2 %
w
i.
a
fi /
I cm = 1.5 x 10-'= 0.00015 micron = 1.5 Angstrom.
©INTER-ATOMIC DISTANCES. Distances between atoms are
now so tiny they are measured by a new unit: angström (A) one
ten-thousandth of a micron or a hundred-millionth of a cm. Sodium
(I) and chlorine (2) atoms of salt crystal are clearly indicated. Darker
grey area indicates greater probability of finding an electron. As to
oxygen molecules (3) moving in air, their speed at 10° is 470 metres
per second. In the image that speed would seem I 09 times greater, i.e.,
more than one hundred times the speed of light! In inset, only
hydrogen atoms are again shown. Incorneraquarterofahydrogenatom.
' ' I cm = 1.5 X I 0-" cm = 0.0015 Angstrom.
A SALT 18,000 MILES HIGH. This is now the third jump we
^mw have made since seeing the atoms from the outside in " 8" and
we are still In the seemingly endless emptiness of the inside. Chances
of meeting an electron are again 100 times smaller. Wave length of
gamma ray has increased to 5 cm. Grain of salt, which was only half a
millimetre when we saw it in real existence on the girl's hand, has
now become an unthinkably huge cube with sides of more than
30,000 km (almost 20,000 miles). This is 350 times the height of Mt.
Everest! Nucleus of sodium atom is 0.7 mm, that of hydrogen 0.2 mm.
i i I cm = 1.5 x I 0-" cm = 0.00015 Angstrom.
©PROTONS AND NEUTRONS. Nucleus of sodium has grown
to appreciable size. Proton or nucleus of hydrogen atom is shown
in inset. Atoms consist of electrons whirling round a nucleus composed
of protons and neutrons. Hydrogen atom, simplest of all elements,
has single electron revolving about nucleus of one proton. Helium
atom has 2 electrons; sodium I I ; uranium 92; centenium 100. Dimen¬
sions here are 100 million times smaller than wave length of light.
Electrons and protons are electrically charged particles detectable by
Geigercounterand Wilson Cloud Chamber. Neutrons have no charge.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. May 1957
0.1 5 Angstrom.
©X-RAY WAVE LENGTH. As darkness of grey denotes prob¬
ability of finding an electron, shading of the Sodium atom filling
most of area of the picture and of hydrogen atom in inset is lighter than
in photo 8, for area is now only one-hundredth in size. Nucleus of
sodium is in center. Its size on this scale is only 7 micron. Twelve
electrons are whirling round this nucleus at speeds of about I 000 km
per second in reality, which would seem 1, 000 million times more on this
imagined magnified image! Wavy line drawn shows wave length of finest
X-rays on this scale. Quarter of a hydrogen atom is visible in the inset.
jj)
m = 0.01 5 Angstrom.
WRIST WATCH GAMMA RAY. Colour symbolizing probable
presence of an electron is even a lighter grey than on previous
drawing because area depicted here is again 1 00 times smaller. Dotted
line coming from left shows wave length of a typical "gamma ray"
(wave length 5 mm) such as is emitted from a wrist watch. On this
scale girl in picture n° I would have a height of about 10 million kms
(6 million miles)! Salt crystal would now be over 3,000 km high (almost
2000 miles). Sodium nucleus would be one-thirtieth of a millimetre,
the hydrogen nucleus or "proton" one-hundredth of a millimetre.
A,
-i I cm=l.5x I 0-1J cm = 0.00001 5 Angström..
©WEIRD PENETRATING POWER. In this last picture we
see the nucleus of sodium atom but cannot even guess how the
12 protons and I I neutrons of which it is composed are placed. Inset
shows proton or nucleus of hydrogen atom. A weirdly powerful
gamma ray from cosmic radiation comes into the picture from left.
Smaller particles than protons or neutrons, such as mesons, have recently
been detected. Looking back on our series of 40 pictures we find that
in only ten of them (Nos. I to 3 and 0 to is life known to exist.
In other scales there may, however, be forms of life as yet unknown.
.ND so our journey ends at the nucleus of the atom, thai
mysterious, utterly small and incredibly powerful centre of
energy which only recently has unveiled some of its secrets
to mankind. Whereas at the end our first journey we stood
in awe before the imposing greatness of the dimensions of the
Universe, and felt as nothing in comparison to their immen¬
sity, the conditions are now completely different. True, we
feel as much awe and reverence when we attempt to think
of the miracles of dynamic power which are hidden in these
domains of the smallest existing entities, but our own dimen¬
sions are now indescribably colossal compared with what wc
see. Thus in the last drawing a man's height on that scale
would be of the nature of 10 thousand million kilometres,
that is about the diameter of the Solar System! If we add
to that the thought, that man is beginning to control and
use these limitless nuclear powers, it is clear that unthinkable
possibilities are within his reach. When we thus think in
cosmic terms we realize, that, if he is to become really
human, man must combine in his being the greatest humility
with the most careful and considerate use of the cosmic powers
of which he can dispose.
The problem, however, is that primitive man at first tends
to use the power put in his hands for himself, instead of
spending his energy and life for the good of the whole growing
human family which has to live together in the limited space
of our planet. But now it is a matter of life and death for
the whole of mankind that we learn to live together and that
our children be educated in a spirit of tolerance and mutual
respect, regardless of differences of birth or upbringing, of
nationality or race, of creed or conviction.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
WOMAN'S LIFE
(Continued from page 15) How free is the African housewife?
come here and publicly denounce a customer who hasn't
paid her debts!"
The Dahoman woman is free, far -freer than is
commonly imagined in Europe she is free to go out (and
even to travel), free to carry on her business as she thinks
best and to do exactly as she likes with the money she
earns.
Bosi and Henrietta were born at Mitro, but Videhu and
Tavi lived in neighbouring villages before they were
married; and Se Kande, the Chief's wife, is from Porto-
Novo. These women often visit their families. From time
to time, Tavi, piling a few skirts, crockery, provisions
and gifts on her head, sets out with her children on foot,
or in a lorry if she is lucky enough to find "a lift". Her
visits to her native village last a week or two. Once she
was away nearly two months: "My mother was ill, so I
looked after her", she explained. One of Henrietta's
friends made up her mind one day to visit some of her
relations in Nigeria... the other side of the world 'for a
little village girl. Another set out for Natitingu, a
Northern town some four hundred miles away, to see her
daughter.
For the three religions
tolerance is de rigueur
But though the Dahoman woman is free, she has to
conform to a very severe traditional code of morality.
iOne day I found Tavi in bed with a high fever; she
accepted the quinine tablets which I offered her, but said,
"I am going to see the witch-doctor to 'find out what gave
me the fever". It is never by chance that one is laid low
by sickness. Fever is either a punishment for having
forgotten to make some offering, or a sacrifice demanded
by an ancestor, or, again, a penalty for having offended
the gods. In such circumstances, a doctor is all very well,
but a witch-doctor is still better. There are remedies
medicinal plants to soothe a stomach ache, bring down a
fever or a swelling and relieve pain but, most important
oí all are the purifying baths and penances prescribed by
the witch-doctor.
The Dahoman woman lives with a sword of Damocles
over her head the possibility that she may be punished
for a sin, even unconsciously committed, by seeing one of
her relations become sick or even die. One day, I asked
after a fisherman whom I had not seen for a long
time. Bosi told me with a confidential air: "His body is
swollen, he is very ill", and she added: "Perhaps it is
because of his wife." This woman was reputed to be
and, according to tradition, when a woman is
unfaithful to her husband he is always warned of it
because he falls ill. "Time was when the gods killed the
woman", said an old fetisher-woman regretfully. If the
invalid Is to recover, the misdeed must be confessed and
the name of the seducer revealed.
So far as the punishment of adultery, theft, scandal-
mongering or disrespect is concerned, Dahoman morality
is a private code, designed to keep the family intact; the
principal punishments are sickness or sterility, which, as
they strike the individual, show that he or she has
offended against society.
There are other obligations and other things forbidden.
The school-teacher's wife explained to me that every
family, probably for reasons connected with its distant
antecedents, refrains from eating certain foods. Tavi
does not eat eels, Videhu does not eat snails and Bosi does
not touch certain vegetables. When she gets married, a
woman never forgets to ask an old aunt for her husband's
"'diet sheet", so that she will not run the risk of serving
him with types of food forbidden in his family.
The gods may forbid those who worship them to eat
certain foods. Thus Videhu, a fetisher of serpent-
worship, eats no fish that is smoked and rolled around a
stick because its form suggests a coiled snake.
Henrietta's sister-in-law, Mary-Jane, is a Roman
Catholic but her husband worships the vodun. She had
her last child baptised but all the others, who are dead,
were not Catholics: "As all the other children died, I had
this one baptised", she informed me. And (she must have
acquired tolerance in her family) she added: "In anj¬
ease, the witch-doctor had told me to do it." I met a
fetisher woman whose two sons were Animists, one of her
daughters a Protestant and the other a Roman Catholic;
and when I asked the reason for this diversity, she
replied with some such words as "One mustn't put all
one's eggs in one basket!" In the village, religious
differences do not lead to quarrels and, in a tata,
Moslems, Christians and Animists get on very well
together.
Although Christians and Moslems may refrain from
taking part in the religious ceremonies, ancestors continue
to be universally hallowed. Before they drink, Henrietta
and Bosi, like their fetisher friends and kinswomen, never
forget to sprinkle a few drops on the ground "for oui-
an cestors". While Tavi's children wear greegrees on their
wrists, Bosi's three children have devotional medals, and
Animata hangs round her little daughter's neck a sachet
containing a few verses aï the Koran. They believe that
scapulars and verses of the Koran have the same value
and function as greegrees to ward off sickness and
death, the two disasters which haunt Dahoman women.
And there is some justification for their fears: Bosi's baby
died of a fever in three days, and Mary-Jane has lost
three children. There are very -few women at Mitro who
have never lost any children and I have met some who
have seen four or five and even as many as seven of their
babies die.
In these African villages where three religions coexist
the old Animist religion, Mohammedanism and Christia¬
nity great tolerance reigns among the people. When
Henrietta's old uncle died, part of the family sacrificed
the traditional chickens, while cousins from the town
sprinkled the body with holy water. Tavi, who is very
particular about her appearance, once enumerated the
occasions on which a "smart" woman likes to dress up;
in addition to religious festivals and traditional
ceremonies, I was astonished to hear her a devotee of
thunder-worship mention Christmastide. "For my Chris¬
tian kinswomen and friends, it is a festival", she
explained, "so I too put on my best clothes, and go to
church to see what the ceremony is like". One day, a
high dignitary of a local religion told me that he was a
Roman Catholic. Seeing my amazement, he gave me a sly
smile and said: "After all, I wasn't born in Rome!"
I saw the finest example of this tolerance one day when
I was invited to a big local wedding. The young couple,
who had been married the day before according to local
custom, called at the Civil Registry Office in the early
morning, were married in the Roman Catholic church at
ten o'clock and then, about midday, received a blessing
from the Moslem Imam. As one guest, who was toasting
the couple, told them: "You'll run into terrible difficulties
if you ever try to divorce!"
Herb-tea prepared
by ' those who know '
About one year after her marriage, Henrietta had her
first child. Throughout her pregnancy, she followed
the advice of her mother, of elderly aunts and of
other old women, and wore round her hips a greegree cord,
which is supposed to protect the child; she drank herb-
tea, carefully prepared by women "who know" and avoided
going near too hot a fire; but she continued to work and
carry burdens. No word was spoken, in her hearing, of
her pregnancy and no plans or preparations were made
for the child, in order not to tempt Providence. Death,
they say, is always lying in wait and its attention is easily
attracted. Many women have refrained from telling me
how many children they have, or else have told me in a
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
whisper, so as not to arouse the interest of Death, or of
jealous women "friends" who would rejoice in their
decease.
Henrietta gave birth to her child in her hut, assisted by
the village matrons. Only about a third of the village
women go to the clinic for their confinement. "The
clinic is twelve and a half miles away from here", the
school-teacher explained to me, "and it is not always
easy to go there; besides, the women here calculate their
period of pregnancy very roughly". Se Kande, one of the
wives erf the village Chief, waited over a month at the
clinic for the birth of her last son; and two of her sisters,
who had gone with her to help prepare her meals, stayed
with her throughout that period. Near to the clinics I
have often seen women, surrounded by children, cooking
on a portable stove for a relation who is in hospital.
Patients whose families live nearby have their meals
brought to them every day.
Alihossi, the little girl
' who was born on the road '
For Se Kande, this absence from home was no handi¬
cap, since, being the Chief's wife, she does not go in
for trade; but for the other village women it is a
serious matter to stay for several weeks at the clinic, doing
and earning nothing. "And on top of that", said
Bosi, "one is never sure of being able to get one's custo¬
mers back afterwards". Nevertheless, when she was
expecting her little girl, Bosi decided to have her baby
at the clinic and to go there at the very last minilte.
Indeed, she left it so late that the child was born in a
ditch, a few miles from Mitro. The little girl was thus
called "Alihossi", or "she who was born on the road".
In Dahomey, one's name is almost a curriculum vitae.
It describes one's birth, events in the family during one's
mother's pregnancy, and anything unusual that happened
when one was born. One of Videhu's children is called
told lies" because, when he was born, his family
was in the throes of a quarrel involving slander.
So many names here recall to mind that infant
mortality is the great scourge of the countryside. One
child is called Kudunukpo, or "Death has taken my
children"; another is called Yemalo, or "'He who is no
longer awaited". As for Se Kande's baby, his name is
"It is Death's fault", because, before he was born, Se
Kande had lost her three children, one after the other.
Her last-born has special tattoo marks on his cheeks and
wears copper bells round his ankles, so that his little dead
brothers may not come to fetch him.
Roman Catholics give their children the name of the
saint's day on which they are born. Henrietta's son is
called George because he was born on April 23. Had he
been born the next day, he would have been called Gaston.
One day I saw a man, who had just become a father,
looking very crestfallen. He said to me: "My child was
born last Sunday what am I to do?" It was Septua¬
gésima Sunday!
Christians also have several African names which are
given to them seven or nine days after their birth, during
the ceremonies succeeding the confinement. These
traditional ceremonies still take place at Port-Novo, in
modern and old-fashioned families alike; they are
accompanied by a great deal of pomp. Sugared almonds
(the traditional sweetmeat offered at French christenings)
may not yet have appeared on the scene, but the custom
of displaying all the "birthday presents" is becoming
increasingly common. One day when I went to see the
newborn son of the wife of a Porto-Novan official, I
found the baby dressed in pink garments and lying amidst
embroidered cushions and bowls overflowing with tins of
talcum powder, bottles of scented oil, cakes of soap and
eau-de-cologne.
Henrietta's son, George, is a member of his father's
family. That is what is meant by the expression "a child
belongs to his 'father". If Henrietta divorced, she would
take her son with her, but would later send him back to
his father. For it is from his father that he will later
receive his lands and titles; when he is of an age to marry,
again it is his father who will give him his first wife by
helping him to pay the dowry.
The Unesco Courier. Moy 1957
In the towns, modern young women are beginning to
consider this custom unfair, and several have said to me:
"We should at least like to keep our daughters with us."
In the village, however, the women considered my
questions on this subject out of place. This rule, perhaps,
surprises us; yet it is responsible for the strength or* the
African family, for it keeps the men in the same place
and thus ensures the family's continuity.
In reality, the link between the child and its mother is
a very strong one. I am always struck by African
children's affection for their mother, and also by the
tenderness of their relationships. Completely naked, with
little rounded stomachs and rolling their large inquisitive
eyes, they are adorned with multi-coloured pearl necklaces
and bracelets. There are never any "washed-out" looking
children. I went to see Henrietta's son the day after his
birth and found the baby asleep. He was hardly browner
than if he were slightly sunburnt, and I exclamed: "He's
a little vovo, a little white boy!", for newly-born Africans
all have fair skins. There was general laughter and my
interpreter said: "You'll see him in a few weeks and
he'll be completely black."
Henrietta's friends came to visit her, almost all of them
with a child hanging in a cloth on their backs. The
babies were dressed in their best clothes and, with their
faces smeared with talcum powder, looked like little
pierrots. The women chattered and, whenever a child
started to cry, its mother would sit down, lift up her
muslin blouse, undo the cloth, catch hold of the baby
under the armpit and pull it round on to her knees to
give it the breast. Children are reared in this way up to
the age of two or even three. This lays the foundation of
children's affection for their mothers; a child who later
joins his father never forgets his mother, and will help
her and often house her in her old age.
I seldom hear children cry. Is it because their mothers
seldom scold them and they are not always being told,
"don't touch this", "don't do that", "don't pick your nose",
or "hold yourself straight"? A child's mother -feeds him
when he is hungry and puts him to sleep when he is tired
and he doesn't seem any the worse for it. An African
child is relaxed and free and appears thoroughly happy.
He does not know what loneliness means. Agossu, Bosi's
eldest child, has a host of small cousins in the tata with
whom he can play; he also has his neighbours and as
many friends of his own age as he could wish. They
dance in a ring and together build little bamboo cages or
make whistles. A little ten-year-old cripple, his legs
wasted away by a mysterious disease, makes miniature
lorries out of bamboo sticks. He forgets nothing, not even
the spare tyre, which is made out of a dried 'fruit, round
and flat like a fig.
Solving the great problem
of an empty continent
Agossu, who is already seven years old, does not spend
all his time playing. His mother asks him to do
little jobs for her. He often goes to market to buy
one or two francs' worth of peanuts. "He is learning the
value of money" Bosi said, and added : "When you take
him to France, he will already know how to count"; she
winked as she said this, for Agossu's trip to Europe was
a standard joke between us. From time to time, his father
takes him into the fields where he hoes the furrows with
a little hoe just the right size for him. He is already
treated like a little man. Helen, his cousin, who is six, is
also learning to work. She has a little jar with which she
goes to fetch water from the marigot, and a miniature
palm-broom to sweep out the hut (or pretend to). On
market days, her mother entrusts her with manioc cro¬
quettes which she carries on a tray on her head, selling
them from door to door.
A child is always wanted and always expected with joy.
To have a large family is one of the reasons invoked in
defence of polygamy. In a farmer's family, children are
a guarantee that labour will always be available. They
are also a guarantee that the dead will continue to be
revered. Lastly, as every African vaguely feels, even in
thickly populated areas, to have children is to help solve
the great problem of Africa how to populate an almost
empty continent, and give it vitality.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
L etters to the Edit or
The Editor of the unesco courier has received the following letter from
M. Jean-Pierre Cabouat on behalf of the French National Commission for
Unesco :
Sir,
I have today received the April issue of the unesco courier devoted to
problems of food in the world. I am shocked by the photographs published
on pages four and five illustrating the posthumous article of Professor André
Mayer.
Indeed, the procedure which consists, in order to emphasize a contrast,
in publishing side by side two photographs, one of which constitutes a
caricature of reality, seems to me unworthy of the cultural level and of the
objectivity which should be maintained by the magazine. It should, in any
case, be absolutely proscribed in a large-circulation periodical published by
an international and inter-governmental organization working for the
brotherhood and closer relations between peoples. In this regard, the
illustrations used for this article seem to me to be of such a nature as to
arouse, in inexperienced minds, more a sentiment of hostility than a desire
for brotherhood.
Jean-Pierre Cabouat
The Editors of the Unesco courier wish to assure M. Cabouat and all other
readers that if these photographs have given rise to any such interpretation they
are the first to express their regrets.
Sir,
Hearty congratulations for your
January number! No issue until now
has been so beautiful, so well written
and presented as the arresting work of
Masaccio and the Perisan miniatures.
They have revived the fairy dreams of
my childhood. I spent a whole evening
admiring both the finesse of the printing
and the perfection of the colours and
not once did this tire me.
When I was at Montserrat (about 100
miles from Barcelona) I remember seeing
the Black Virgin which you reproduced
(page 20), but covered with huge jewels
and emeralds... Before reaching the
monastery little is left connected with
the name of Ignazio de Loyola I was
surprised by the unbelievable strange¬
ness of the site: a pile of gigantic
columns, and sometimes extraordinary
shapes which seem to have been care¬
fully sculpted in the mountain side.
On enquiring I was told: "'It is the
erosion of the winds and waters". This
explanation did not satisfy me, and the
allusion you make to the "many legends
which have grown up around the
extraordinary site" has aroused my
curiosity. Why not publish an article
on this subject? I am sure it will
interest your readers.
Certainly many striking and curious
legends must still exist in various parts
of the world, in Africa and in Central
America, in Rhodesia and Mexico, in
Peru and Asia Minor. These legends
have their roots in the most distant anti¬
quity, and something about them would
be sure to interest your readers. It
might also put professional and amateur
archaeologists and writers (such as P.
Hermann, M. Briou etc.) on the track
of important discoveries or lead to
studies on these oral traditions
transmitted from generation to gene¬
ration.
Helene Herzmann
Paris, France
Sir,
I ami an invalid (total deafness) who
like other invalids has had his share of
suffering on this earth, unesco must
certainly deal with the conditions of
invalids, and I should like to read
something about its efforts in the
columns of the unesco courier.
Pierre Levoisin
Lagny, France
editor's note : An issue on this subject
is being planned for a later dale. Reha¬
bilitation of the physically handicapped is
the responsibility of the United Nations in
New York, and the World Health Organi¬
zation. A conference of all international
organizations dealing with the physically
handicapped is convened periodically by
the U.N. Dept. of Social Affairs, unesco
maintains contact with various international
bodies dealing with this subject and advises
on specific educational problems. Unesco
has given special attention to handicapped
children and the international standard¬
ization of Braille for the blind. UNESCO's
Gift Coupon programme includes projects
for aiding the handicapped. See special
issue of UNESCO courier on blind, March
1952 as well as April 1952, Nocember-
December 1956. For other subjects see
analytical indexes.
Sir,
I am writing to say how much 1
enjoyed the January issue. Today
international relations are strained by
political beliefs on all except cultural
and sporting levels. This magazine
helps to create international under¬
standing as well as being interesting in
itself.
(Miss) Cosima Bayne
Victoria, Australia
Sir,
Your August 1956 issue, "Buddhist
Art and Culture" (English edition July
1956) is one of the finest presentations
of Buddhism that I have ever had the
pleasure to encounter. The issue is a
gem. The day Nations begin to extend,
genuinely, this attitude of Buddhism
and, apparently, the unesco courier,
instead of threats..., two-thirds of the
world's troubles will be on the way out.
(Miss) Terreden Dickinson
New York U.S.A.
Sir,
Your magazine deserves praise; I be¬
lieve it is very human, and in these
times the message of Men of Good
Will. But, frankly, I don't find the ma¬
gazine gay. Don't you think that the
smile also reflects love and fraternity
between peoples. Why do you always
publish grave, tortured faces and take
life in such an infinitely dramatic
way ?... I should like to see faces where
the eyes are lit up despite the injustice
of men. Mine is only a modest point
of view compared to your very intelli¬
gent and educated readers, but I think
you would reach a wider public if your
magazine relaxed the working man and
housewife more.
M. Amand
Champagne, France
Sir,
I sometimes have the impression that
too much space is given in your pages
to the countries of the Far East. It
is true that our knowledge of them is
too small, but these countries do not
always have sufficient knowledge of us
either. I should like to see future is¬
sues devote a regular place to the edu¬
cational systems of the various countries
of Europe and America.
L. Cosentini-Frank
La Cibourg, Switzerland
Sir,
I have the greatest pleasure in reading
the unesco courier which .keeps
me in touch with the whole world
through the work and benevolent genius
of unesco. My warmest compliments
and sincerest wishes that this humani¬
tarian work may continue.
L. C. Kleinbeitz
San Francisco, U.S.A.
u
z
<
CE
z
<
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
man
measures
the
universe
scientific exhibition
organized by unesco
FREE TO SUBSCRIBERS
MAN MEASURES THE UNIVERSE is
the fourth travelling scientific exhibition
organized by UNESCO. Inaugurated in
Paris in 1954, it has been seen so far by
more than a quarter of a million visitors
in Oslo, the Hague, Madrid, Ghent, Brussels,
Liège and Warsaw. The exhibition is now
touring Poland and is currently on view to
visitors in Cracow.
Devoted to the techniques and instru¬
ments used to measure length and distance,
from the infinitely small to the infinitely
great, the UNESCO exhibition deals with
a fundamental subject which is the root not
only of knowledge but also of scientific
method. The great I 9th century physicist.
Lord Kelvin, said that "to measure is to
know". It is through the introduction of
measurement into observation and experi¬
ment, that science has, in fact, been able to
make its most striking advances, and it is
the measurement of lengths which provides
the key to all other measurements.
The exhibition tells the story of the units
of measurement used in the different orders
of magnitude: the human scale (metre),
the microbial (the micron), the virus and
very large molecules (the millimicron),
the atomic scale (angström), the inter¬
atomic scale, the geographic (kilometre),
the solar system (astronomic unit), the
interstellar (light-year) and the inter-galac-
tic (the parsec).
The UNESCO COURIER is pleased
to announce that copies of the UNESCO
pamphlet "MAN MEASURES THE UNI¬
VERSE" describing the exhibition in detail,
are now offered free of charge to subscri¬
bers. Since only a limited number of copies
is available, subscribers will be served on
a "First come first served" basis. Write to:
DPV Service, UNESCO, I 9 Avenue Kléber,
Paris I 6, France.
WHERE TO SUBSCRIBE
Unesco's national distributors from
whom the English, French, Spanish
and Russian editions of the UNESCO
COURIER can be obtained are listed
below.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzal, Press Dep¬
artment, Royal Afghan Ministry ol Educ¬
ation, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 303 Flinders Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria.
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V.
BELGIUM. Louis de Lannoy, Editeur-
Libraire, 15 rue du Tilleul, Genval (Bra¬
bant). 80 Belgian francs.
CANADA. University of Toronto Press,
Toronto 5.
Periodica Inc., 5090 Avenue Papineau,
Montreal 34.
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
ni Ceylon Ltd., Lake House, P.O. Box
244, 100 Parsons Road Colombo I.
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh.
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Libreria Económica, Calle
O' Reilly 505, Havana.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd.,
6 Nörregade, Copenhagen K.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Unesco Sales Section,
19 Avenue Kleber. Paris, 16'. CCP.
12598-48, Unesco Bookshop, Paris.
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb für Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2.
Sub-Depots : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., Scindia House, New Delhi; Rajkamal
Publications Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay 1.
INDONESIA. G.C.T. Van Dorp & Co.,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission lor
Unesco, Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
P. O. B. 4 154, Tel-Aviv.
ITALY. Libreria Commissionaria San-
soni, Via Gino Capponi 26, Casella Pos¬
tale 552. Florence.
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 99
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
lor Unesco, Ministry of Education, Seoul.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SIN¬
GAPORE. Peter Chong & Co., Post
Office Box 135, Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta.
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church.
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos.
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass 7, Oslo.
PAKISTAN. Ferozsons : 60 The Mall,
Lahore ; Bunder Road, Karachi and
35 The Mall, Pashawar.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Ciiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
REPUBLIC OF IRELAND. The
National Press, 1 6 South Frederick St..
Dublin.
SWEDEN. - A/B CE. Fritzcs, Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgaicn 2, Stockholm
16.
SWITZERLAND. - Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40 rue du Marché, Geneva.
5.20 Swiss francs.
TANGIER. Paul Fckcte, 2 rue Cook,
Tangier.
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
UNION OF BURMA. Burma Educa¬
tional Bookshop, 55 1-3 Merchant Street,
P.O. Box 222, Rangoon.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724. Pretoria.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 152 West 42nd St, New York,
36, N.Y,
U. S. S. R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovcnska Knjiga
Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
Alex Poignant
A VANISHING C1VI ISA! ION Cut off from *ne rest of the world and untouched by
/-\ VMMUl lll-iVJ V.I V ILIJMI IWIN outside influences for untold centuries, the aborigines of
Australia are one of the few peoples of the world whose lives and cultures are still fairly close to the Stone
Age. But as they come more and more into contact with the modern world, the aborigines abandon their
beliefs and customs and today, scientists are observing and recording every aspect of this vanishing culture
before it disappears for ever. (See page 4 for photo story of the aborigines of Arnhem Land, northern Australia.)
]]>
</page>
</document>
