<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078176eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
m
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m 1 1ra
NOVEMBER 1960 (13th year) - Price : 1/-stg. (U.K.) - 30 cents (U. S.) - 0,70 NF. (FRANCE)
**
m*ék
. ^^^p$k-
""
0
<"**
v ^. \
.iéÊÊ&- friiy*
\
9_h
VV ^x
.i%
A NEW
MAGNA CARTA
FOR CHILDREN
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
wgm
s y. ; y.'
= :"-
. - ;; -
H_P" '
¡SS& :
Hüi»ll
«$¡8
-*»
«IP
>yyy
\c?
(71
c
* ^ í^í
LO
4 s$
THE HEN WITH
THE GOLDEN CHICKS
(See page 28)
im- ! At
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
NOVEMBER 1960
1 3 T H YEAR
Contents
No. Il
COVER PHOTO
The United Nations has un¬
animously adopted and pro¬
claimed a Declaration of the
Rights of the Child "to the
end that he may have a happy
childhood and enjoy for his
own good and for the good
of society the rights and
freedoms herein set forth".
© Paul Almasy, Paris
Page
4 ASIA'S VICIOUS CIRCLE
Special report by Georges Fradier
(I) 3 Rs for 130 MILLION CHILDREN
I I (2) THE LITTLE WORLD OF ASIA'S TEACHERS
15 DECLARATION OF THE RIGHTS OF THE CHILD
A new Magna Carta for children
22 CHILDREN WE NEGLECT
The mentally handicapped
23 UNICEF GREETING CARDS
Chagall & Tamayo say Happy New Year
24 CRUSADER FOR PEACE AND YOUTH
The Story of Jane Addams
By Pauline Bentley
28 THE HEN WITH THE GOLDEN CHICKS
Masterpieces of an ancient Rumanian treasure trove
By Emil Condurachi
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
Alexandre Leventis
Associate Editors
English Edition :
French Edition :
Spanish Edition :
Russian Edition :
German Edition
Ronald Fenton
Célia Bertin
Amparo Alvajar
Veniamin Matchavariani
: Hans Rieben
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York. N.Y. (M.C. 60.1.152 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S VICIOUS CIRCLE
A special report by our correspondent GEORGES FRADIER
Richard Lannoy, London
The problem of schooling in the countries of Asia is a vicious circle. The countries are poor because they are not properly
educated and they cannot build schools because they are poor. Asia's people are now determined to break this vicious circle.
One of the crucial issues of our time is the edu¬
cational future of the children of the world. For
the children of Asia, Latin America, tropical Africa
and the Arab states of the Middle East this is a prob¬
lem which, in magnitude and complexity, ranks
with those of hunger, sickness and poverty.
The extension of school facilities to all children
has always been a basic concern to Unesco.
International regional studies and conferences
sponsored by the Organization led to the launching
of a major Unesco project in 1957 for the extension
of primary education in Latin America. Since then,
surveys and inquiries have been made by Unesco
into the needs of Asia, Africa and the Middle East.
Preliminary investigations for each area were
completed last year and considered at meetings of
Ministers and Directors of Education from each
region, held in Karachi, Addis Ababa and Beirut
at the end of 1959 and early this year. The reports
they adopted are of special importance in connexion
with the long range efforts being planned and have
also made possible the formulation of proposals
for Unesco action which are being considered at
the eleventh session of Unesco's General Confer¬
ence which opens in Paris later this month.
Georges Fradier, special correspondent of The
Unesco Courier, travelling through Asia, Africa
and the Middle East, has had a first-hand view of
their educational resources, problems and projects.
Below we present his first reporta striking picture
of the educational problems and plans of Asian
countries whose populations total 800 million.
Further reports, on Africa and the Middle East, will
appear in future issues of The Unesco Courier
and the whole broad outline of the school situation
in the three regions will be reviewed in "Asia,
the Arab States and Africa: Education and Pro¬
gress", a forthcoming Unesco publication.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
W7
^^f^M E live in an age which has grown ac-
^F W customed to huge figures. Miles, tons,
T T dollars and roubles are calculated in
terms involving more and more strings of zeros. Applied
to human beings such figures are lifeless and without
meaning. Thus when we speak of children we must think
of them one by one, remembering that in each and every
case a promise, a future, an opportunity and an irrepla¬
ceable life is at stake.
Here we are dealing with 130 million ir/eplaceable
children from 15 Asian countries about half of whom
are denied a basic opportunity (1). They are denied the
opportunity of obtaining an education, of escaping from
the narrow confines of inherited toil ("You don't know
anything so you can do the same work your father did"),
of understanding something of what goes on outside the
village, the factory or the home; they are denied the
opportunity of choosing their own careers or their own
opinions, of going through life with some degree of
awareness and understanding .
In Korea, for example, all children between the ages
of 6 and 12 go to school (much as in Western Europe about
1880) ; in Thailand almost all children go to school from 7
to 14. But in Vietnam, in India, in Pakistan, Indonesia
and Iran, only 5 out of every 10 children are lucky enough
to be taught the 3 Rs; out of 10 village children, 5 go to
school and 5 work in the fields; out of every 10 children
in the industrial suburbs, 5 spend their days in the class¬
room and 5 in the streets.
If we take these 15 Asian countries as a single unit, out
of every 10 children, 5 will never read a newspaper or a
letter or the history of their own countries. They will
never read a single line of any of the masterpieces of
"'world" literature, so named because they were conceived
and written for the benefit of all.
These 5 children, boys or girls, picked at random from
each group bf 10, wil grow up, live and work very much
like their illiterate parents before them. But not quite
like them. . Life will be even harder. Our civilization is
based on the written word. As that civilization develops
(1) Afghanistan, Burma, Cambodia, Ceylon, India, Indonesia,
Iran, Korea, Laos, Malaya, Nepal, Pakistan, Philippines, Thai¬
land, Vietnam.
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
and spreads, Illiterates will be increasingly faced with a
difficult and Isolated existence, sometimes fearful and
secretive, sometimes jeering and rebellious, the same
existence as that led by the few complete Illiterates still
sometimes found in the large cities of the Western world.
The average number of Asian children condemned to
illiteracy is 5 out of 10; but in Afghanistan, in Laos or
Nepal, the number is as high as 7 or 8 in 10. In any
event, something like 65 million children in 15 Asian
countries are in this situation, despite the fact that tre¬
mendous progress has been made in these countries in
recent years.
Between 1950 and 1956, for example, the number of In¬
dian children in classrooms rose from 18,294,000 to
25,947,000; in Laos the number of schoolchildren increased
three-fold and in Iran and Malaya it almost doubled.
Undoubtedly these increases were offset by the over-all
increase in population, but they do reflect an unprece¬
dented effort on the part of the States concerned: 9,000
new schools built in Burma since 1950, 3,000 in Malaya
and 9,000 in the Philippines in 4 years, and more than
80,000 in India between 1950 and 1956. In the 15 countries,
primary school enrollment rose from 38.7 million in 1950
to more than 66 million in 1960.
When we take into account the teacher training that
had to be given and the salaries that had to be provided,
then it is safe to say that so much action in so short
a time was never taken during the 19th century (except
perhaps in the case of Japan) when today's "developed"
countries were introducing coanpulsory education. Yet
despite these remarkable (and costly) advances, Delhi,
Rangoon, Karachi, Teheran and the other eleven capitals
realize that these are merely the first steps on a long
and difficult road.
The governments of these countries have solemnly pledg¬
ed themselves to provide all children with a practical,
solid and useful education. They have even set them¬
selves a deadline: compulsory primary education every¬
where within 20 years.
Thousands of schools have been opened. But dozens
of towns and thousands of villages are still without
schools. In most cases the reason is simply lack of money.
Most of these States have been independent for less than
1 5 years ; whatever education systems they inherited, they
Steven Trefomdes, Boston, U.S.A.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S VICIOUS CIRCLE (Cont'd)
3 Rs for 130 Million Children
have had to give priority in this period to the building
up of the elements necessary to independent States: eco¬
nomic development, means of defence, the maintenance
of public order. Inevitably, educators were asked to wait
a little longer. In fact some countries still seem to find
themselves in an impasse, and then what is the use of
proclaiming compulsory primary education when adequate
schools to receive the children cannot be built.
It is not unreasonable to expect a child to walk one
mile to school or even a .little more in very sparsely
populated regions. Thus at least one school is needed
for a zone of 3 to 5 square miles. In Korea, Pakistan,
¿Thailand and Malaya, however, there is only one school
for 7, 8 or 10 square miles; in Burma and Nepal, one for
23 square miles or more; in Iran one per 75 square miles.
These figures, moreover, are approximate and relate to
average areas. In actual fact most schools are grouped
around the towns. In India, the average individual area
served by each primary school is 4.2 square miles. But
India is essentially a land of villages and its 840,000 com¬
munities, most with less than 500 inhabitants, have, hard¬
ly more schools than electric power lines. The Indian
authorities estimate that they will need to build 180,000
schools before 1962 to provide a school within one and
half miles of each child's home.
Educationally speaking, then, there are groups of still
more under-privileged children in the under-privileged
regions and many of them are country children. Millions
of Indian, Afghan, Pakistani and Iranian boys are con¬
demned to remain illiterate simply because they are the
sons of peasants or village craftsmen. Education will be
available for their counterparts in the cities and towns,
but they will have to wait for adult education classes,
when these' are set up one day.
Another under-privileged group is not limited to rural
areas. In many cases the fact of being a girl is a barrier
to primary education not on an official ' basis, of course,
but in actual fact, just the same. In none of the 15
Asian countries are there as many girls in schools as there
are boys. In India, Pakistan and Iran girls represent less
than 50% of the school population; in other countries
where only 10 to 12 per cent of children attend school,
for every 10 boys able to read there is only one girl.
But the problems of rural education and education for
girls form only one aspect of a whole complex of factors
which puts a brake on the development of primary edu¬
cation. Differences in the progress that has been made
between one State and another are (partly due to vari¬
ations in educational policy and to the extent to which
people show an interest in their children's education. To
understand these differences, we need to take into account
diversity of material, social, cultural, political,
demographic and economic conditions.
Outstanding among the material fac¬
tors is .the multitude of little villages
already mentioned. India has 443,000
communities of less than 200 people. In Nepal, out of
28,770 villages or hamllets, 24,429 have less than 50 inhabi¬
tants; in Iran, 40,000 villages are scattered over an area
four times that of Great Britain; in Burma, 23,621 com¬
munities out of 32,000 have less than 500 inhabitants.
In all these countries, the vast majority of the people
live in tiny communities dispersed among the islands or
in the forests, clinging to the mountain sides, hidden
away in all but inaccessible valleys or clustered around
oases in the desert. When one considers the problem of
providing these thousands and thousands of communities
with schools, of equipping the schools, of finding the
teachers, paying their salaries and providing them with
somewhere to live, it is not hard to understand why even
the most enthusiastic advocates of compulsory primary-
education sometimes become disheartened.
Industrialization and urbanization growth are already
affecting the picture, drawing village people into towns
or creating new towns. Apart from this, it should be
possible to group villages in twos or threes and supply
one school for the group. Elsewhere, assuming that there
are suitable roads, it might be possible to use itinerant
teachers. In still other places, central boarding schools
might be set ¡up. There is no shortage of paper solu¬
tions. In practice, however, it has so far seemed more
advantageous and more urgent to try to meet the needs
of towns which are also short of schools.
What about the social aspect of the problem? There is
the complex situation of huge countries populated by sep¬
arate communities which are racially distinct and whose
customs are often markedly different. There are also the
mental or geographical barriers which continue to divide
the communities and castes. Most Asian countries, too,
possess some communities cut off from the national life
in general and living in inaccessible or wild regions.
There are probably enough priests,
shamans and wisemen among these
nomadic hunters and farmers to
provide for the traditional teaching for initiations and
crafts. But one is not likely to find among them literate
persons of the type most suitable to contribute to a natio¬
nall education programme. The "tribal populations'" may
toe scattered, but collectively they represent millions of
human beings and hundreds of thousands of children.
But the most important social factor here is the status
of women. Imagine a country where virtually all the
women are illiterate. Outside the home, no-one seeks
their opinion on the country's present or its future* their
task is to maintain the old traditions. But a country
wishing to advance and anxious to improve its living
conditions will have a hard road to travel if half the
population must be carried as a dead weight; and that is
what women have become through being deprived of the
elementary means of understanding and adjusting to
new things.
And, in the final analysis, it is on the women that so
much social progress depends. Once they have won the
right to education, women demand other rights: to parti¬
cipate in social, economic and finally political activities
from which they were previously excluded. Women, in
fact, know better than men how to combat poverty and
slums, unjust working conditions, and bad health and
hygiene conditions as well as ignorance in all its forms.
Once emancipated they demand enough new schools not
only for their sons but also for their daughters.
In this respect, there are some striking differences bet¬
ween one Asian country and another. In some regions,
women have long enjoyed a great measure of freedom and
there is no feeling or situation that prevents their educa¬
tion. In others, reformers still have an uphill fight to
convince the population as a whole .that it would be fair
and reasonable to provide schools for girls. In a few
countries .there will soon be as many girls at school as
boys. But others will have to make heavy sacrifices to
achieve as much, their task made all the harder because
in general the countries in which few girls now go to
school are also those most opposed to the idea of co¬
educational schools; thus these countries will have to
find as many women teachers as men.
Yet even in India and Korea where the disproportion
between the sexes is by no means the most marked, men
teachers outnumber women teachers by 5 to 1; elsewhere
the ratio is as much as 10 to 1. At the other end of the
scale there is Ceylon with almost as many women as men
teachers and the Philippines which stands out among
other Asian nations because it has more women than men
teachers.
It may seem surprising to talk of cultural barriers to
the progress of education. But the fact is that culture
has not always nor everywhere been linked with the idea
of general education given by teachers. On the contrary,
in many civilizations the most important knowledge and
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
BRICKLAYERS
IN SHORT
PANTS
Photos Unesco-P.A. Pittet
Few children have ever been asked to help build their own school. But in Indonesia it is a case of
needs must, and village folk and their children have made themselves responsible both for finding
the material and for building schools. Thus they contribute their share to the effort of the govern¬
ment which provides all funds for education. No special taxes or local rates are imposed for educa¬
tion. Top left, the headmistress and a teacher give working instructions to the children; right,
youngsters hard at work breaking up bricks. Scaffolding behind is of bamboos collected by the
children. Above, young masons carry their bricks to the building site on a "stretcher".
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S VICIOUS CIRCLE (Cont'd)
WRAPPED IN YELLOW SHAWLS. Indian boys at a Benares school (run on the ancient Vedic principles of
the Hindu religion) study under the supervision of a bearded teacher called a Brahmachari. Their studies include
Sanscrit and religious subjects, but they also follow the modern curriculum and enter for the normal State exami¬
nations. Shawls bear Sanscrit script with the word MA or Motherfor the Mother Goddess. Cultural traditions
of certain Asian countries have always encouraged the development of what we today call primary education.
Richard Lannoy
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
SOLEMN-FACED children on
their way to school pause for a
moment on the Cabantcharuk
Road near Djakarta, the capital
of the Indonesian Republic.
Photos Unesco-Pierre Pittet
ARCHAEOLOGIST from
France and boy from Bali study
some well-weathered stone figu¬
res inspired by stories from the
Ramayana, the Hindu epic poem.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S VICIOUS CIRCLE (Cont'd from page 6)
the most useful, whether for this world or another, 'was
not the sort that could be passed on by a schoolteacher
to young scribes and future merchants. And a peasant,
able to recite from memory the noblest passages from
ancient epics and hymns, is unlikely to be overimpressed
by the business of writing.
Elsewhere, however, cultural traditions have always
encouraged what we call primary education. In Burma,
for instance, the religious tradition has for centuries been
a true intellectual tradition as well. Here, custom has
long decreed, that young boys should spend a certain
period in a monastery or temple. Guided by a master,
they learn the arts of reading and writingconsidered as
sacredwhile studying the doctrines and rules of
Buddhism. Obviously the development of primary educa¬
tion presents no social or psychological difficulties in a
country where the remotest village has always piously
sent its small monks to school. But then not everyone is
Burmese...
On the other hand, millions of Asian students, when
they hear about education in other lands, can under¬
standably be expected to remark, with some regret, "Not
everyone can be Russian, or English or Italian.9' For there
aire, fortunately, a great many children in the world who
do all their lessons in their own language, that of their
homes and the streets of their city, the same language
whether at work or play. These children don't realize
their good fortune. In Asia such duck is almost exception¬
al. Either the mother tongue is not the same as the
national language or this language is inadequate for even
slightly advanced studies, and so before long still another
language must be learned.
between 1956 and 1966: in 10 years it will have topped
527 million.
Because of the relatively short life-span in Asia, there
are many more school-age children in proportion to the
total .population than is the case in Occidental countries.
For this reason the burden of education grows Increas¬
ingly heavier. The great problem is where and how to
find the necessary funds. Advisers may suggest how each
of the difficulties confronting education should be met.
But they have little to propose for the most formidable
obstacle of all mass poverty.
Because they are poor and cannot provide clothes and
other necessities, people don't send their children to
school, or, children are taken away from school before
they have finished their education, either to help at
home or to earn a little money. But the impoverishment
of the people has still graver consequences: taxes have to
be kept low and this seriously limits the State's income;
what is available is devoted by priority to the activities
considered most essential.
This fundamental obstacle to educational progress is,
in fact, a vicious circle. The people of these countries
cannot build a sound educational system because they
are poor and they remain poor because they are not
properly educated. The government is short of money
to finance national education because its income is limited
by the low living standards of the people and these, in
turn, cannot be raised precisely because of the inadequate
system of education.
It is this vicious circle which the Asian countries have
determined to break.
Here then are some of ,the difficulties
confronting children in simple pri¬
mary education. At least half their
time is spent in learning languages which often have no
connexion with each other and which do not even use the
same alphabet. The resulting organizational prob¬
lems are naturally immense. Sometimes a school must
be started for each linguistic group; at best, teachers
must be specially trained, Schoolbooks have to be speci¬
ally prepared, and it is difficult for a publisher to produce
a reading primer on a large scale and at a low price:
the schools need twenty different books in 20 different
languages using a variety of types.
Yet despite all these huge problems, let us suppose that
the nations of Asia now had all the books they needed
and had managed to build enough schools and to train
enough teachers. Let us imagine that the present
problem of primary education had been miraculously
solved in every country, from Manila to Tabriz. Would
ministries of education be able to relax and simply super¬
vise the smooth working of the educational system? No!
the problem would be as great as before. The task would
no sooner be completed than everything would have to
be started again from the beginning. For while the
authorities might have effectively provided for the educa¬
tion of 130 million of today's children, in 20 year's time-
To illustrate the educational problems posed by the rate
of population increase, we may take as examples, two
countries of very different sizeIndia and Ceylon. By
1961 the population of Ceylon is expected to reach
10,390,000. Ceylon's birth rate is 40 per 1,000 and, thanks
to improvements in hygiene and medicine and victories
over- malaria, the mortality rate has dropped to 10 per
1,000. Today the population increase stands at 2.9 per
cent.
This means that in 10 years the population will number
15 million, and that in 20 years an island as large as
Belgium and the Netherlands combined, but without any
resources other than agriculture, will number more than
20 million inhabitants. Already Ceylon must plan to
provide educational facilities for 890,000 new school¬
children by 1968, simply to maintain the number of
children attending school at the present proportion of
70 per cent of those of school age.
In India it is expected that the birth-rate will drop to
32.9 per thousand within 10 years (as against 41.7 per
thousand in 1955, and as compared with the then U.S.S.R.
rate of 25.6 per thousand and the TJLS.A. rate of 25 per
thousand). At the same time the death-rate is expected
to drop from 26 per 1,000 to less than 14. . On this basis
the population of India will have increased by 86 million
Bathtlme for the children of a fisherman In the Philippines. But when they
are older will there be schools for them to go to ? The education authorities
are making a sustained effort to replace the 85% of schools which were des-
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
The Little World of Asia's Teachers
Aivisit to a few ."'ordinary" schools in
the East inspires not only sympathy
.for the teachers, but also admiration
for these poorly but neatly dressed men and women, who
are at their schools from an early hour each day. Two
things about the average school strike one immediately:
it is too small for its purpose and it is forbiddingly austere.
It may be a straw hut built by the village council or a
group of small mud houses or, more often, a "modern"
building of bricks and cement, which means it is even
less attractive with its treeless courtyard and its dusty
school garden.
A glance round the classroom offers a neat but bleak
perspective of benches, a dais and a single window. There
is nothing to relieve the bare walls; not even a map or
a picture. But the teacher is not likely to be conscious of
this emptiness; his own home is just as austere, and even
the best furnished living-room in the neighbourhood
probably has nothing but a calendar or a religious print
by way of ornament. A classroom with a blackboard, a
few chalks and a sponge is relatively well-off.
The teacher has probably never heard of visual and
audio-visual aids to teaching. If you mention these
things to him, he will probably nod and smilingly tell you
/
Unesco-P.A. Pittet-
troyed during the last war. To meet any sudden Increases In enrolment
or when typhoons have damaged school buildings, they also build
"temporary" schoolhouses of light materials such as softwood and bamboo.
that they are not yet available in that part of the world.
Here, in fact, even the basic equipmentmaps, wall
charts and large sheets of drawing paper are all difficult
to come by, if indeed the school has any sort of paper
other than perhaps the portrait of the Chief of State
which hangs in the headmaster's office. A radio? Yes!
one would be useful, but there is no mains electricity so
it would have to be a battery set. And anyway there is
no one to look after it or to repair it if needs be.
And here are the children a hundred or so, apparently
of all ages between 7 and 14, squeeze themselves onto the
narrow benches. How still and well-behaved they are;
just as quiet in the stifling summer heat as they are in
the monsoon season or in the chill cold of winter.
They work hard on the whole, the teacher tells you,
or at any rate they are eager to learn, but after a few
hours they get tired and their attention wanders. "The
trouble is," he adds, "that some of them don't get enough
to eat. They come from poor families. If only we could
help to feed them." (School canteens are practically non¬
existent in Asia. Among the exceptions: Ceylon, where
each child receives a cup of milk and a bread roll each
day; Korea, where in many schools children are given
powdered milk, supplied, as in Ceylon, by American funds;
the Philippines, where a cheap meal is available; Madras
State, where subsidies enable school committees to serve
meals an experiment which the State intends to develop
until 30% of schoolchildren will be getting one meal a
day in 1966.
As to the children's health, all the teacher can tell you
about it is that on the whole it is good as good as can
be expected. There are no files to supply further informa¬
tion and no doctor to look after the children, although
nearly all the countries are trying to expand their medical
services.
Tihe next thing that strikes you are
the obvious differences in size
and apparent maturity among the
children in the classroom. You are not mistaken; they
are of all ages. Some are perhaps brighter than others
and each year they go on to a higher class until they
finish the school programme. But these are not the
majority.
"'There are always some who stay in the class for
another year," says the teacher; "that is something that
really plagues us in this school." It is also the constant
headache in many other primary schools thoughout Asia.
Far too many children stay for one, two or even three
years in the first class, eventually struggle into a more
advanced one, then become discouraged and give up.
The children who "stick" in the same class for several
years and those who give up altogether are symptomatic
of more deep-seated ills: irregularity of attendance,
ineffective teaching and the unsuitable orientation of the
school programme.
As for the other symptoms, the teacher will sometimes
admit that the lessons he gives, as well as those of his
colleagues could, in principle, be improved. (An inspector
will tell you how difficult it is to overcome the placid
resistance of teachers who have been trained according
to old-fashioned methods.) But to improve teaching
takes time. The programme has to be carried out as
well as may be, mostly without guidance; there are few
inspectors and these confine their activities to inspecting.
The school programme is packed with subjects; nothing
has been forgotten. First come languages (generally at
least two have to be learned and in some countries as
many as five). Then come arithmetic, history, geography,
object lessons and elementary science; next the arts and
manual work, such as agriculture; drawing, singing,
dancing, sports and gymnastics; and what some
countries consider a basic subject religion or civics and
ethics. "It is a great deal for one man to cope with,"
says the teacher. It is. also a great deal for the children
to cope with, and they too are likely to lose themselves
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ASIA'S VICIOUS CIRCLE (Cont'd)
15 nations plan a school revolution
in this labyrinth of subjects, loosely related to each other
and still less related to the local life.
Nowadays, however, some countries do encourage the
use of active methods: "projects" or practical tasks are
carried out in the community schools of the Philippines,
"co-ordinated education" in India's new schools, and
"interest centres" form part of the programme in some
Laotian schools. Usually, the good pupils learn everything
by heart, and unfortunately they are not alone in thinking
that this is the best way of passing examinations.
Active methods which make demands on intelligence
rather than memory and which aim at developing
initiative and a spirit of co-operation should be applied by
teachers having a broad general culture and proper peda¬
gogical training, which are not required to the same
extent when traditional methods are used. They also
require much more classroom material pictures, photo¬
graphs, equipment of all kinds and, above all, plenty of
books.
These same methods encourage children to choose their
own reading matter. This very idea is enough to make
the teacher of our "ordinary" school anywhere in Asia
raise his hands to heaven. Choose what they would like
to read? Why, he himself has only a handful of books
and his pupils have to make do with the unique textbook
which serves them throughout one year a textbook
sometimes shared by two or three children. One reason
for this terrible shortage is that during the past ten years
it has been necessary .to translate into national or local
languages books which were only available previously in
English, French or Dutch. Another is that Asia is short
of paper. Finally, however cheap the textbooks may be,
there are always people and communities for whom they
are too dear.
These then are the conditions in
which the teacher each day carries
out the job entrusted to him by
society, in the hope that from the classroom will emerge
younger generations less shackled to a particular destiny
and better fitted for the tasks of their time. And perhaps
before his day is over, the teacher will have run an adult
education class or .stopped by at the town hall where he
acts as secretary. Finally, he will be free to go home,
a home in all probability devoid either of .comfort or
charm.
For teachers are still poorly paid in some Asian countries
less well paid than other civil servants of similar
status. And the teacher's social condition depends very
largely on his economic situation. Nor is it merely a
question of his personal well-being: at a time when
compulsory primary education is coming into its own, the
teacher must have an adequate standing in society. If
he is treated as an unimportant, minor official, it will be
all the harder for him to create the respect and desire for
knowledge which Asian countries are seeking to inculcate
in even the remotest villages.
The educational picture of Asia is changing all too
rapidly for it to be summed up briefly. The important
fact which stands out is that the peoples and
governments are resolute in their determination to
vanquish the many obstacles to educational progress. A
veritable revolution lies ahead for the under-equipped
countries and their largely illiterate populations. But it
will be a peaceful and calculated revolution which, in some
countries, has been planned to the last detail.
In India, for example, educational projects are drawn
up by the governments of the different States and co¬
ordinated in an over-all plan by the Ministry of Educa¬
tion. India's Third Five-Year Plan (1961-66) which has
just been completed, aims at making primary education
compulsory for all children from 6 to 11 and at increasing
the school population to 54 million. The final goal for
India is free and compulsory primary education up to the
age of 14. In Pakistan, the government has set up a
National Education Commission which recently published
a complete report on education at all levels.
12
Plans have also been .drawn up by ministries or
planning councils and commissions in Afghanistan,
Burma, Cambodia, Ceylon, Korea, Iran and Viet Nam. In
some countries, recently created planning and statistical
departments are still not properly equipped for their job.
But the need to methodically plan the extension and
reform of primary education is now universally recognized.
This was apparent when representatives of Asian States
met at Karachi this year at the UNEsco-sponsored
conference which produced a work plan designed to
ensure "universal, free and compulsory education in Asia."
The first of the 15 objectives in this remarkable pro¬
gramme is to ensure at least seven, year primary educa¬
tion for all children within the next 20 years. It is a
tremendous task and must be carried out stage by stage.
Thus, the second aim is to raise the number of primary
school pupils to 11 per cent of the population in 1965,
to 14 per cent in 1970, to 17 per cent in 1975 and,
eventually, to 20 per cent in 1980.
Five objectives concern teachers: there should be one
teacher for 35 pupils. All teachers should have a good
secondary education plus at least two years' professional
training. Within five years enough training colleges and
special courses are to be established to produce the
qualified teachers which the development programme
requires. Teacher training colleges will have specialized
instructors in the proportion of 1 for 15 student teachers.
In its budgetary provision, the plan envisages the
increasing of recurring expenditures to 10 dollars per pupil
in 1965, to 12 dollars in 1970, to 16 in 1975 and to 20 in
1980.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
With Its 90 million inhabi¬
tants spread out over the
world's largest group of
islands, Indonesia needs to
train a vast army of teachers.
Right, students in a handi¬
crafts class at a teacher-
training college; below, op¬
posite page, preparing a silk
screen for the production
of charts at a Teaching
Aids Centre in Bandung.
Photos Unesco-Pierre Pittet
Schools to be built must have classroom areas calculated
on the basis of 1 square metre per pupil; enough equip¬
ment, furniture and teaching materials for these schools
must be provided and adequate administration and inspec¬
tion services created. Accomodation must be found for
50% of the teachers. More money must be spent to raise
the level of instruction in teacher training colleges: 125
dollars per year per pupil in 1965, rising to 200 dollars in
1980. Last, but not least, the plan emphasises the urgent
need to produce books, for teachers and pupils alike.
What is the real significance of this plan and what will
it cost?
B Y 1980 it is estimated that the total
population of these 15 Asian countries
will have reached 1,185,000,000. This
means .that in 20 years time these countries should
be ready to provide 7 years' primary education for 237
million children (compared with 4 or 5 years currently
provided for 60 to 65 million).
A vast army of teachers will be needed to cope with
this teeming school population. The bulk of the colleges
where they will be trained are still to be built and staffed.
When they are operating, it is calculated that these
schools will have to train 286,000 teachers each year by
1965, 388,000 before 1970, and 599,000 each year between
1975 and 1980, when primary education in the 15 countries
will be needing the services of about 6,770,000 men and
women teachers.
The total cost has been estimated at $ 56,217,000,000
spread over 20 years. It sounds like a frightening amount
of money, but in point of fact it is only enough to pay
for a modest project: to provide for Asian children during
the next 20 years means of education that are today
considered inadequate for Western children.
Furthermore its full achievement will cost these
countries annually 5 dollars per head of population. This
is about the same as is now being spent in Ceylon on all
levels of education and probably less than one-tenth of
expenditure on primary education in the West. Compared
with the Asian plan to spend 20 dollars per pupil by 1980,
Venezuela currently spends more than 100 dollars.
In a unanimous recommendation, the Karachi
Conference suggested specific ways of raising money for
the plan: reforms making possible an increase in primary
education allowances; levying of taxes suited to local
conditions; special loans; appeals for voluntary contribu¬
tions from local committees. .
But the Conference insisted equally strongly on the
need for outside aid. If we have to rely solely on our
own national resources, said the delegates, we might just
as well give up the plan. In this case, compulsory
primary education for Asian children might become a
reality sometime in the 21st century. But the children
of Asia connot wait until then, and the delegates at
Karachi refused to consider such a possibility.
In their final recommendation, they declared, in part:
"The main method of ensuring this aid (outside financial
support) consists in bilateral and multilateral arrange¬
ments between the countries of the region and the
economically developed countries, and a further effort in
this direction should be made in the near future. It is
to be hoped that Unesco will offer its good offices to
encourage this assistance and, given the growing goodwill
of countries throughout the world, there is reason to hope
that the amount of such assistance will greatly increase
before long. The meeting also feels that Unesco should
encourage the creation of an international fund for
primary education designed to complete the bilateral and
multilateral agreements..."
Unless action is taken now, hundreds of millions of
children will still lack education ten years hence. It is
not these children who are to be pitied, but the adults
they are to become. Ignorance today will be misery
tomorrow. That is why the problem of education is one
confronting clear-thinking and responsible citizens of
every country on earth. On the solution of this problem
depends not only the future progress of Asia, Africa, Latin
America and the Middle East, but the prosperity and peace
of the whole world.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
DECLARATION OF THE RIGHTS
OF THE CHILD
The United Nations General Assembly, on November 20, 1959, unanimously
adopted and proclaimed a Declaration of the Rights of the Child, setting forth
those rights and freedoms which the international community has agreed
every child, without any exception whatsoever, should enjoy.
Many of the rights and freedoms proclaimed were already mentioned in the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights adopted by the General Assembly in
1948. It was, however, thought that the special needs of the child justified a
separate declaration.
Like the Universal Declaration, the Declaration of the Rights of the Child sets
a standard which all should seek to achieve. Parents, individuals, voluntary
organizations, local authorities and governments are all called upon to recognize
the rights and freedoms set forth and to strive for their observance.
This year, Human Rights Day on December 10 has been set aside by the
United Nations and its agencies to mark the first anniversary of the adoption
of the Declaration of the Rights of the Child.
The full text of the United Nations Declaration of November 20, 1959, is repro¬
duced on the following pages together with a special photo-reportage by Paul
Almasy. All photos copyright.
PREAMBLE
Whereas the peoples of the United Nations have,
in the Charter, reaffirmed their faith in fundamen¬
tal human rights and in the dignity and worth of
the human person, and have determined to promote
social progress and better standards of life in larger
freedom,
Whereas the United Nations has, in the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, proclaimed that
everyone is entitled to all the rights and freedoms
set forth therein, without distinction of any kind,
such as race, colour, sex, language, religion, politi¬
cal or other opinion, national or social origin, prop¬
erty, birth or other status,
Whereas the child, by reason of his physical and
mental immaturity, needs special safeguards and
care, including appropriate legal protection, before
as well as after birth,
Whereas the need for such special safeguards has
been stated in the Geneva Declaration of the Rights
of the Child of 1924, and recognized in the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights and in the statutes of
specialized agencies and international organizations
concerned with the welfare of children,
Whereas mankind owes to the child the best it has
to give,
Now therefore,
The General Assembly
Proclaims this Declaration of the Rights of the
Child to the end that he may have a happy child¬
hood and enjoy for his own good and for the good
of society the rights and freedoms herein set forth,
and calls upon parents, upon men and women as
individuals, and upon voluntary organizations, local
authorities and national Governments to recognize
these rights and strive for their observance by legis¬
lative and other measures progressively taken in
accordance with the following principles:
PRINCIPLE 1
The child shall enjoy all the rights set forth
in this Declaration. Every child, without any
exception whatsoever, shall be entitled to
these rights, without distinction or discrimina¬
tion on account of race, colour, sex, language,
religion, political or other opinion, national or
social origin, property, birth or other status,
whether of himself or of his family.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE RIGHTS OF THE CHILD (Continued;
PRINCIPLE 2
The child shall enjoy special pro¬
tection, and shall be given opportuni¬
ties and facilities, by law and by other
means, to enable him to develop phy¬
sically, mentally, morally, spiritually
and socially in a healthy and normal
manner and in conditions of freedom
and dignity. In the enactment of
laws for this purpose, the best inte¬
rests of the child shall be the para¬
mount consideration.
PRINCIPLE 3
The child shall be entitled from his
birth to a name and a nationality.
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
PRINCIPLE 4
The child shall enjoy the
benefits of social security. He
shall be entitled to grow and
develop in health; to this end,
special care and protection shall
be provided both to him and to
his mother, including adequate
pre-natal and post-natal care.
The child shall have the right to
adequate nutrition, housing,
recreation and medical services.
PRINCIPLE 5
The child who is physically, mental¬
ly or socially handicapped shall be
given the special treatment, education
and care required by his particular
condition.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE RIGHTS OF THE CHILD (Continued;
PRINCIPLE 6
The child, for the full and
harmonious development of his
personality, needs love and
understanding. He shall, wher¬
ever possible, grow up in the
care and under the responsibility
of his parents, and, in any case,
in an atmosphere of affection
and of moral and material secu¬
rity ; a child of tender years
shall not, save in exceptional cir¬
cumstances, be separated from
his mother. Society and the pub¬
lic authorities shall have the
duty to extend particular care to
children without a family and to
those without adequate means
of support. Payment of State
and other assistance towards the
maintenance of children of large
families is desirable.
PRINCIPLE 7
The child is entitled to receive
education, which shall be free
and compulsory, at least in the
elementary stages. He shall be
given an education which will
promote his general culture, and
enable him, on a basis of equal
opportunity, to develop his abili¬
ties, his individual judgement,
and his sense of moral and so¬
cial responsibility, and to be¬
come a useful member of
society.
The best interests of the child
shall be the guiding principle of
those responsible for his educa¬
tion and guidance; that respon¬
sibility lies in the first place with
his parents.
The child shall have full
opportunity for play and recrea¬
tion, which should be directed
to the same purposes as educa¬
tion; society and the public
authorities shall endeavour to
promote the enjoyment of this
right.
18
"3
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE RIGHTS OF THE CHILD (Continued)
, 0.-"
Í1 .
« Ik
PRINCIPLE 8
The child shall in all circumstances be among the first to receive protection and
relief.
PRINCIPLE 9
The child shall be protected against all forms of neglect, cruelty and exploitation.
He shall not be the subject of traffic, in any form.
The child shall not be admitted to employment before an appropriate minimum
age ; he shall in no case be caused or permitted to engage in any occupation or
employment which would prejudice his health or education, or interfere with his
physical, mental or moral development.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
PRINCIPLE 10
The child shall be protected from practices which may foster racial, religious and
any other form of discrimination. He shall be brought up in a spirit of understanding,
tolerance, friendship among peoples, peace and universal brotherhood, and in full
consciousness that his energy and talents should be devoted to the service of his
fellow men.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The Mentally Handicapped
CHILDREN
WE NEGLECT
i
$.
mJÈÊÊt*
jB bF jAVBb
» iL 41
wÊÈts^- ^ i
Unesco - David Seymour
An inquiry carried out among
71 countries by the Internation¬
al Bureau of Education leads
to the conservative estimate that at
least four per cent of the world's chil¬
dren are (mentally handicapped. In
the relatively few countries where
statistics exist the figures are stagger¬
ing almost a million in Japan, over
250,000 in France (or nearly five per
cent of the school age population),
six per cent in Uruguay, four per cent
in Peru, two per cent in Yugoslavia
and Poland.
Most of these millions of unfor¬
tunate children are potentially educ¬
able, but unless they receive special
education they will become a burden
on society, sometimes useless and
often dangerous tragic misfits who
constitute a problem for their families
and communities.
Yet today, in the middle of the 20th
century, special education for the
mentally handicapped is reserved for
a privileged minority and hundreds of
thousands of potentially useful citi¬
zens are lost to themselves and to the
world.
It was to focus attention on then-
plight that the International
Conference on Public Education,
organized by Unesco and the Interna¬
tional Bureau of Education, meeting
in Geneva last summer, chose as a
major discussion theme the organiza¬
tion of special education for mentally
deficient children. The basis for its
discussions was the world-wide in¬
quiry mentioned above. This com¬
parative study, however, was not
concerned with the whole problem of
mentally deficient children, but was
confined to those considered as "educ¬
able" or "recoverable."
"So long as a child can be taught
to read, he can be made into a useful
member of society," Mr. César San¬
telli, of France, told delegates from
77 countries at the Geneva Confer¬
ence. "But the problem of special
education for mentally deficient
22
children is one which is always being
put aside in favour of seemingly more
urgent ones," he added.
Obviously, said Mr. Santelli, coun¬
tries grappling with the problem of
stamping out illiteracy among their
"intelligent" population and putting
them all in school have little time for
dealing systematically with their
mentally handicapped. Even the ad¬
vanced countries where illiteracy is
no longer a problem lack sufficient
specialized institutions and qualified
teachers to deal with the difficult
cases.
In only a dozen countries of the
71 covered by the inquiry does educa¬
tional legislation stipulate that spe¬
cial education it to be organized and
that it is obligatory for mentally
deficient children to receive instruc¬
tion. In a further 12 countries, men¬
tally deficient children are 'liable for
compulsory schooling in the same way
as other children.
Where special institutions do not
exist, educable mentally deficient
children must usually attend the
ordinary school. But when classes
are already overcrowded, it is pratic-
ally impossible for the teacher to give
enough time to the mentally deficient,
who more than any other children,
need direct contact and individual
attention. They are inevitably neg¬
lected, waste their time, often disturb
their fellows, have to repeat the class
and when they reach school leaving
age, they depart without having
learned anything much.
If it is easy to pick out immediate¬
ly children who are seriously sub¬
normal cases of idiocy or imbecility
the educable mentally deficient
child is at first sight more difficult to
identify. Cases of slight deficiency
are often confused with slow learners,
whose intelligence may be developed,
whereas the mentally deficient suffer
from a lesion of the brain which may
be more or less serious, but which is
unfortunately incurable.
It is important therefore to detect
such children at an early age. Psy¬
chological and IQ tests combined with
medical examinations and enquiries
into family environment enable
mental deficiency to be diagnosed
and thus save the time of teacher
and class as well as giving the child
himself a chance to improve with
special education.
When once it has been established
that the child is mentally handi¬
capped rather than backward or
lazy, practical teaching based on
manual work, games and exercises
will help him to co-ordinate his
movements and to gain self con¬
fidence one of the prime require¬
ments for a normal life. Group acti¬
vities and teamwork help the child to
adjust to society and learn to live
with others; memory, suitably train¬
ed, will often help him to compensate
for lack of intelligence.
U I t has often been noted that
I there is a relationship between
delinquency and mental defi¬
ciency," 'Mr. Santelli told the Geneva
Conference. "This makes it all the
more important to give these children
a sound moral training, and also to
equip them with the means of earn¬
ing a living. They should be guided
towards jobs they can do and em¬
ployers should be discreetly convinced
that mental deficients can often carry
out certain work more conscientiously
than their more gifted brothers. A
list of specially suitable trades and
jobs in industry should be drawn up
on the basis of experiments and an
attempt made to keep these jobs open
for them."
Apart from the shortage of money,
qualified, teachers and special schools,
one of the main obstacles in the way
of the mentally deficient is their own
parents. They are often unwilling to
admit their children are unlike others
and they have to be taught to over¬
come their pride and to understand
that with proper education their chil¬
dren can be made useful members of
society.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
CHAGALL AND
TAMAYO SAY
HAPPY
NEW YEAR
Achain of human solidarity forged toy the United
Nations Children's Fund (Unicef) today spans 86
countries, helping to protect millions of children from
three deadly dangers: sickness, hunger and ignorance.
Unicef's chain now girdling the world is composed of gay
and artistic greeting cards.
From the obscure beginnings of a German wood-cut
print bearing a New Year's message about 500 years ago,
greeting cards have become an almost universal tra¬
dition and within this framework, the Unicef cards have
become a tradition in themselves.
Ten years ago Unicef brought a new concept to the
custom, by seeking out. the works of famed artists as
designs for cards which would bring the joys and needs
vttfWté
¡32 ¿¿¿¿i Hrí^**«
The Unesco Courier. November I960
S jñ
ALPINE GAMES, a UNICEF Greeting
Card design by Swiss artist Aloïs Carigiet.
of children to people throughout the world. Since then,
Unicef's gallery of contributors has grown to include
many great names in world art.
Among this year's contributors is Marc Chagall, vision¬
ary painter and Biblical illustrator, always close to the
world of children and to the folklore of his native
Vitebsk. In "Glad Tidings" he has affirmed his faith in
the work of the United Nations and has symbolized the
strength of maternal care and affection.
Another master of modern art, Mexico's Rufino Tamayo,
has contributed an abstract design, "Poetry of Flight",
whose soaring movement expresses his concept of the
efforts of the United Nations towards peace.
Switzerland's Alois Carigiet, has created two appro¬
priate designs entitled "Alpine Games". Both "Bells"
and "Sledding" are as crisp and gay as the snow and the
happy children they depict.
As an illustrator of children's books, Adolf Zabransky,
the Czech artist, has gained international fame in the
field of romanticism. The five designs he has made for
Unicef are entitled "Tales of Many Lands." His legends
GLAD TIDINGS, a Unicef Greeting Card design fay Marc ChajîII.
and fairy tales portrayed in fascinating colour are: from
Holland, "The Legend of St Nicholas"; from Denmark,
Hans Christian Andersens's "The Ugly Duckling"; from
India, "The Epic of Ramayana" ; from Korea, " The Jade
Slipper" and from Brazil, "Snow White and the Seven
Dwarfs."
Ettore de Grazia of the United States breathes life,
colour and motion into a favourite subject of ins Lidian
children and the Arizona desert. As the children danca
in a circular motion, the desert around them seeais also
to rotate in a whirlpool-like motion.
Unicef greeting cards come in boxes of 10, offering to
people everywhere an easy way to remember their Mends
in the festive season while helping sick and hcngiy
children throughout the world.
Each box sold makes it possible for Unicef to snpply
vaccine to protect 50 children against tuberculosis. Hts
boxes provide enough antibiotics to cure 15 children off
that blinding disease, trachoma. Ten boxes pay fear
enough penicillin to save 120 children from the crippling
effects of yaws.
From a modest beginning of 130,000 in IS 50, Xtac»
Greeting Cards sold more than 14 million last year and
provided enough money to protect six million eMldren
against malaria for a year, or enough vaccine to immunise
75 million children against tuberculosis.
Through planned universality and variation of art,
people in 86 countries are every year given glimpses of
other cultures and new approaches to art. In this sense
these cards are both educational and conducive to better
understanding among peoples.
All Unicef cards are available with Seasons Greetings
in the five official languages of the United Kations
English, French, Spanish, Russian and Chinese, or witti
inside pages blank for use as gifts or personal stationery.
They are packaged ten to a box with matching envelopes»
at $ 1.25 (U.SA.) ; 7/6 (U.K.) ; and 5 NF (France) per
box.
For further information, orders, etc., write to any of the
three main Unicef Offices: Greeting Card Fund, Unicef,
United Nations Building, New York ; Greeting Card Fund,
14-15 Stratford Place, London W.l ; Service des Cartes de
Viux, 23, rue Borghèse, Neuilly-sur-Seine, France.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
JANE ADDAMS
crusader for peace
an d you th
by Pauline Bentley
In 1860 there was born
in the village of Cedar-
ville, among the rich
and open countryside of
Illinois in the United
States of America, a deli¬
cate, bright eyed little
girl whose childhood
was haunted by a dream.
She dreamt that only
she remained alive in
the world and that upon
her alone rested the res¬
ponsibilities of making
a waggon wheel which
would get the world
started again. In the
daytime she would go to
the village forge and
watch from the doorway
as the blacksmith work¬
ed, asking him questions
and trying earnestly to
memorize the process of wheel-making.
She never told anyone of this dream until she wrote
of it years later in her autobiography, and in time it
slipped into its place among childhood memories, but
looking backward from today it could appear prophetic;
that small dreamer grew up to be Jane Addams whose
whole life was in fact dedicated to "making wheels and
getting things started".
By the time she died in 1935, Jane Addams was a world
figure, famous for her achievements in social reform and
her work towards international peace. Her work was
manifold and its legacy still enriches us today; she founded
the famous Hull House settlement in Chicago, and in an
age when any kind of social work was totally unorganized,
she and the handful of ardent helpers she gathered round
her helped to set the pattern of present day formal socio¬
logical investigation. Their efforts brought better living
and working conditions to the under privileged and
oppressed, without reservation of class, creed or race,
particularly to the children and young people who were
their first concern, and the gradual expansion of their
influence enforced civic legislation which changed the
social fabric of the time.
To the causes she championed Jane Addams brought a
penetrating intellect which never failed to take into
account any opposing viewpoint, a quietly brilliant gift of
oratory and authorship, and an unfaltering integrity which
established her as one of the outstanding public figures
of her time. In private life she radiated a compassionate
and gentle serenity which endeared her to those whom
she inspired. She was honoured by the love of the people
among whom she lived and worked as well as by numerous
civic and academic distinctions, and in 1931 she received
the final accolade when she became the first American
woman to be awarded the Nobel Peace Prize.
The driving force behind all her endeavors was the
24
conviction that only understanding between people, bet¬
ween groups and societies and nations, could ensure peace
and progress and to develop such understanding was her
main ambition:
Its roots as her basic inspiration seem to have sprung
from her own character and also from the lessons of her
childhood.
Her mother died when Jane was two, and she grew up
closest to her father. John Addams was a friend of the
young Abraham Lincoln. Jane adored him and eagerly
absorbed from him the Lincoln traditions of tolerance
and liberty ; she was much struck as a child to find him
one day dazed with grief at the news of the death of the
Italian liberator, Mazzini. From her father's reaction to
the loss of this stranger, whom he had never even known,
Jane learnt something she prized all her life "a sense
of the genuine relationship which may exist between men
who share large hopes and like visions even though they
differ in language, nationality and creed."
She began early to question the inequalities of society,
when as a little girl her father took her into the nearest
town and she saw for the first time the squalor of city
poverty. "The horrid 'little houses so close together"
worried her into resolving that when she grew up she
"would build a big house among .the horrid little ones so
that people could come and visit her." Twenty years later
she was to do exactly this when she opened Hull House
in the Chicago slums, but like so many great altruists, she
found the path from wide-eyed idealism to its final reali¬
zation was anything but straightforward.
I n 1881, her father died and though she tried
to smother her grief by concentrated medical
. study at Philadelphia, her health broke down
under the strain. The spinal disorder with which she was
born necessitated an operation, leaving her physically and
nervously exhausted, and for her health's sake she was
advised to travel in Europe. The next few years passed
for her in spiritual confusion and depression. The careless
round of pleasure and enjoyment which seemed to be
expected of a young woman of her type seemed to her
futile and her education only a burden to her direct
understanding of the sufferings which she glimpsed on
her travels.
In the journal she kept during these years she notes
her bitter resentment at the wretched poverty of a London
midnight street-market selling rotten food and the impulse
in Germany which sent her flying to remonstrate with a
brewery overseer regarding some oppressed women labour¬
ing for him. These experiences and her own feeling of
inadequacy before them filled her with an unformulated
desire to take action.
Her purpose, as yet shadowy and indistinct, was "to rent
a house in a part of the city where primitive and actual
needs are found." This idea simmered until 1888 when, in
Madrid, Jane voiced it to her travelling companion and
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
Photo © Max Stein, courtesy Philadelphia Inquirer
A SOCIAL PIONEER, Jane Addams was involved with practically every great cause and reform movement in the United States.
She was champion of the poor, pioneer in health, welfare and social work, instigator of child-labour legislation, and winner of
the 1931 Nobel Peace Prize. Above (on extreme right) she campaigns for women's voting rights at a New York meeting in 1912.
old college friend, Ellen Gates Starr. She realized that if
she was to do more than just dream, she must put her
idea to the test at once. The time of preparation had
given way to the days of action.
Losing no time, she left at once for England, where she
sought help and advice from Samuel Barnett, the English
clergyman who had four years previously founded the first
of all settlements, Toynbee Hal in London. She then
hurried back home to look for '"her big house among the
horrid little ones."
She found it in Chicago, where rapid industrial expansion
and alternating waves of boom and slump had made
the city one of the gaudiest as well as the most wretched
in America. Fortunes from railroads, meat-packing and
shipbuilding were being made while the most abject
poverty remained untended by any kind of civic legislation
and nowhere more so than in the nineteenth ward of the
city, which was largely given over to the emigrants from
all over Europe who, through bewilderment and poverty,
found themselves exploited as cheap labour.
Here, on Halstead Street, surrounded by sweatshops,
tenements and filthy alleys, Jane Addams discovered Hull
House, a fine old mansion degenerated into half drinking
saloon, half warehouse. With the care and enthusiasm of
new young housewives, she and Ellen Starr furnished it
and in September 1889 opened it "to provide a centre for
a higher civic and social life; to institute and maintain
educational and philanthropic enterprises and to inves¬
tigate and improve the condition of industrial Chicago."
From the beginning, Jane Addams found the claims of
the children of Halstead Street her first attention. A
kindergarten and nursery came into being almost im¬
mediately and a Boy's Club grew up rapidly. Remembering
the unhurried joys of her own countryside childhood
games she opened a playground at Hull House and later
agitated for the first civic playgrounds and parks where
the city children could at last play in .peace and in safety.
Great place was given to the force of Art in education;
arts and crafts classes were soon started with a studio
and music school and a new world opened to children who
had never before known of its existence.
One of her foremost concerns was the relationship bet¬
ween first and second generation immigrants; she saw
how the more rapidly Americanized children tended to
despise their elders, and she gathered these old people
together to give exhibitions of their native skills in weav¬
ing, spinning and cooking, and so on. These meetings
became a feature of Hüll House, giving new dignity to the
older immigrants and earning them a new respect from
their children. At the same time, she took up the cudgels
for the children when their parents acquiesced too readily
in their being employed in ways far too harsh for their
age.
When the immigrant children at a Hull House Christ¬
mas party refused sweets saying they "couldn't face them"
after working 14 hours a day in a sweet factory, Jane
Addams started investigating the whole question of child
labour to find that children of .five were Working in the
glass and textile industries. With Dr. Alice Hamilton and
Florence Kelley, who came as residents to help her in
Hull House, she started to work on this question,
continuing, against bitter opposition and even attempted
bribery, to combat it until, finally, after fourteen years,
in 1903, the first Child Labour Laws were passed in
Illinois.
Another of the Hull House residents, Julia Lathrop,
became head of the first Children's Bureau in Washington
and was also concerned with Jane Addams in the question
of the many juvenile delinquents spawned by poverty and
ignorance in the city. Their work led to the formation of
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
r
the first Juvenile Court in America, a Juvenile Protective
Association, and later initiated the use of psychology in
the treatment of young criminals.
For three years Jane Addams worked on the Chicago
Board of Education trying to instil her ideas into the
factions which at that time composed it. "Our schools
must give the children better and truer standards for
judging life. Life does not ask whether a man can read'
or write so much as it asks him whether he can use
whatever faculties have been given him... To find a native
talent in a man, woman or child, and then see that it is
exercised, is one of the greatest objects of all social
work..."
Il
ON THE WALLS of the Riverside Church in New York stand
figures honouring two great humanitarians of the modern age :
Jane Addams (shown in photo above) and Dr. Albert Schweitzer.
26
n the first year, 52,000 people came for help or
advice to Hull House; in the second, thousands
.a week were coming and it is said Jane Addams
never refused to see any one of them. With her devoted
team of residents, she minded toaJbies, kept house, orga¬
nized new buildings as they were needed, maintained
finances entirely from her own pocket, or with the help
of generous friends, and wrote and lectured increasingly.
She published 9 major works in 30 years which established
her as an authority on social enquiry and leave an inde¬
lible record of her as a humanitarian.
She learnt patience and tenacity "Premature reforms
fail. Doctrinaire reforms fail. Reforms to be effective
must be rooted in and routed through the social conscious¬
ness. One does good, if at all, with people, not to people."
Jane Addams never lost sight of her guiding principle,
the simple understanding between people, but she was no
bigot; her effectiveness lay often in her balanced ability
to see all sides of every question; she tackled what lay
before her with humility and the wish, not the certainty,
to foe right. Walter Lippman once described her as "in¬
habiting reality", and Jane Addams was indeed no
theorist: she admired the inspiration of a Tolstoï, and
visited him at Yasnaya Polyana, in 1895, but she believed
fundamentally in action, in "'pushing vigorously but
kindly through and beyond all difficulties."
At the end of ten years' work at Hull House she had
grown immeasurably as a citizen and both she and the
settlement were world famous. The one building on
Halstead Street had become a huge establishment, with
training workshops as well as studios, a theatre, an art
gallery and a country club for summer recreational acti¬
vities.
Complete racial, religious and political tolerance
distinguished Hull House; it later earned Jane
Addams the (reputation of "dangerous radi¬
calism" and a good deal of .abuse, but for the moment
her star was set high and in the first decade of the 20th
century she achieved an almost imperial status in Ame¬
rica, with 14 academic honorary degrees and many prizes
to her credit.
Neither fame nor calumny deflected her from her work;
she handed all the money she made to the settlement and
went on to continue and enlarge her activities. Her
upbringing and background ensured her support of
Women's Suffrage and as the first world war approached
she became increasingly aware of their traditionally
pacific role in history. Her tenet of mutual understanding
and neighbourliness expanded into a confirmed inter¬
nationalism which inspired her finest work her work for
world peace.
In 1904 she was principal speaker at the National Peace
Societies' convention in Boston; in 1907 she published her
book "Newer Ideals for Peace" which was received en¬
thusiastically. She took part in the first National Peace
Congress ever held in America and supported Theodore
Roosevelt as the first President to use the World Court
at the Hague in an international dispute.
At the outbreak of the European war in 1914 she plung¬
ed wholeheartedly into the work for continuous mediation
of neutral powers to bring about peace. As a means to
this end, she accepted the chairmanship of the Women's
Peace Party which was to develop into the historic
Women's International League for Peace and Freedom,
dedicated "'to uniting women in all countries who are
opposed to any kind of war, exploitation and oppression,
and who work for universal disarmament and for the
solution of conflicts by the recognition of human solida-
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November I960
rity, by conciliation and arbitration, by world co-operation
and by the establishment of social political and economic
justice for all, without distinction of sex, race, class or
creed."
She presided over the Congress of Women in 1915 at the
Hague and accepted, with Dr. Aletta Jacobs of Holland, the
mission to interview leading statesmen of a world at war.
They were received courteously at top level in 12 capitals
and were told that neutral action to bring about an
honourable peace would be welcomed. Jane Addams
returned to Washington and handed to President Wilson
the report and resolutions of the Congress, some of which
in a modified form were embodied in .the famous 14 points.
America's entry into the war did not deter her from
her pacifist work, although public opinion turned bitterly
against her. She lost the support of even her family and
many of her Hull House colleagues, but she maintained
the League's decision to continue working for peace
wherever possible. Hull House continued to be a sanc¬
tuary for all shades of opinion and she defended cons¬
cientious objectors and harrassed immigrants.
generation facing the Depression. She was by this time
over 60 and increasingly beset by ill health which often
forced her into hospital but she never stopped her work
for Peace.
In 1931 she presented to President Hoover in Washing¬
ton a petition for disarmament signed by 200,000 Ameri¬
can women but had to refuse appointment as delegate to
the Geneva Disarmament conference the next year be¬
cause of ill-health.
She was waiting for an attack of bronchitis to clear up
before she could undergo a major operation which had
been recommended, when she received news that with
Dr. Nicholas Murray Butler she had been awarded the
Nobel Peace Prize for 1931. The day it was formally
presented in the presence of the Swedish Court, Jane
was in hospital in Baltimore; so she never heard the
address honouring her as '"the foremost woman of her
nation... the spokesman for all peace-loving women of the
world."
The Peace prize money she promptly handed to the
Women's Independent League for Peace and Freedom and
HULL HOUSE, one of America's
pioneer social settlements, was foun¬
ded . by Jane Addams in Chicago's
West Side slums. Here, for most of
her life, she strove against injustice
and unkindness, against dirt and di¬
sease, against greed and dishonesty
in public office, against intolerance,
bigotry, ignorance and war. Even in
her late years, she continued to take
a special interest in the myriads of
children who have found the key to
a new world in Hull House (left).
As soon as the war ended she again presided at the
Second Women's Peace Congress held in Zurich in
1919, supporting the League of Nations and forseeing the
dangers inherent in the Versailles Peace Treaty. After
an extensive tour with the Friends' Service Committee
through war-stricken Europe, she returned to travel the
length and breadth of America to plead for food for the
children and the starving people of all nations, irrespective
of their war-time allegiances.
Her attitude and her stand against military training of
any kind earned her personal vilification, but the Women's
International League grew and she presided at its confe¬
rences in Vienna, Washington, Dublin and Prague where
in 1929 she forced through her own resignation. During
the post-war years she travelled the world, presiding at
the Pan-Pacific Women's Union and speaking all over the
Far East.
When women were given the vote she turned her at¬
tention to what she called the humanization of justice in
which she included the Negro question, the immigrants
Quota Act, Old Age Pensions, and the needs of the younger
as far as her health would let her, she continued her work
for "'peace and bread".
Four years later she died, mourned by the simple people
of Chicago whom she had benefitted, and honoured by
famous men and women the world over.
This year her centennial is being commemorated by a
75,000 dollar grant from the Fieild Foundation Inc., for a
training school for settlement house workers, and by the
creation by the League and .the Office of the U.N. High
Commissioner for Refugees, of a "Jane Addams" house
for 32 refugee families in the refugee village of Spital on
the Drau in Austria. To these great and fitting ceremonies
in her memory there could be added the echo and example
of her own credo:
"I believe so firmly in this great world at peace, ready
to come into being as our wills turn toward it, that I must
needs go about this present world of disorder and darkness
like an exile doing such feeble things as I can -toward the
world of my desire. Nothing could be worse than the
fear that one had given up too soon and left one effort
unexpended which might have saved the world."
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
THE HEN WITH THE GOLDEN CHICKS
by Emil Condurachi
Director, Institute of Archaeology of the Academy
of the Popular Republic of Rumania
Among the
most treasured
possessions of
the Rumanian
National Anti-
qui t ies Mu¬
seum in Bu¬
charest is a
collection of
twelve works
of art in gold
which has
become known as "The Hen with
the Golden Chicks.'' The name has
come from a group of magnificent
bird-shaped clasps contained in the
collection which comprises in all
twelve objects, some worked in solid
gold and embellished with engraved
or carved designs, others in gold leaf
filagree work adorned with precious
stones set in gold.
Together they compose an inesti¬
mable treasure as much by their
beauty and value as by the light they
throw on the past history of the
Rumanian people and of Europe, and
in particular the little-known period
of the great tribal migrations be¬
tween the 4th and 7th centuries A.D.
Like every treasure worthy of the
name this one has an exciting story
behind it. One day in 1837 two Ru¬
manian peasants were working in a
quarry at a tiny village called Piet¬
roasa when they suddenly unearthed
a fantastic treasure in gold. One by
one they drew from the ground
26 cups, vases, clasps and other gold
objects, many of them decorated with
precious stones.
For a whole year they kept then-
discovery a secret until they met an
Albanian stone-cutter and decided to
sell him the entire treasure trove for
4,000 piastres. The Albanian decided
that it would foe easier to sen the gold
if he broke up all the objects and
disposed of them one by one to diffe¬
rent jewellers. Some he smashed up
with an axe, scattering the precious
stones with which they were studded,
and he split a solid gold tray into
four parts, all of which were later
recovered and reassembled.
Fascinated by the gold, he threw
away all the precious stones as well
as some chips of gold which were
later found by some village children.
Thus the rumour spread through the
village that a treasure had been
discovered and this, in turn, reached
the ears of the authorities. An in¬
vestigation was made, but it was not
until five years later, in 1842, that
Taken from "The Treasure
of Pietroasa" by Alexandru
Odobescu, Paris, 19 00
careful searching enabled 12 of the
original 26 objects to be recovered.
But the chequered history of the
"Hen with the Golden Chicks" did
not end on the day in 1842 when the
treasure found its way, into the
collection of the National Antiquities
Museum in Bucharest. In 1868 it
disappeared in mysterious c i r-
cumstances and was badly damaged
by" those who stole it.
Fortunately, a young Rumanian
archeologist, Alexandru Odobescu,
had spent several years studying the
treasure and delving into its origins.
The drawings and reproductions he
had had made of the objects enabled
them to be reconstructed and restored
when they were eventually recovered.
Nor was this
the last ad-
venture for
the Pietroasa
treasure. In
the Autumn of
1916 it was
evacuated
from the Mu¬
seum in Bu¬
charest to save
it from the
armies invading Rumania, and was
taken to Russia along with other
works of art. Later, it was handed
back to the Antiquities Museum by
the Soviet Government.
The total weight of the objects
now preserved in the Museum is
44 pounds, and the fact that there
were originally a further 14 objects,
which were never recovered after the
peasants had sold them, shows that
this was undoubtedly one of the
largest treasures of its kind ever
discovered in Europe.
There are differences of opinion as
to the origin of the collection. Some
historians, like Alexandru Odobescu,
believe that the treasure belonged to
the Visigoth king, Athanaric, who in
378 A.D. fled from the Hun invasion.
According to this version, Athanaric
took refuge in the region of Pietroasa
and there buried his most precious
possessions, hoping that a change in
fortune would enable him to recover
them sometime later.
Other scholars, however, maintain
that the treasure belongs to a later
CONT'D ON PAGE 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
HEN WITH THE GOLDEN CHICKS (Cont'd)
Taken from "The Treasure of Pietroasa", by Alexandru Odobescu, Pans, 1900
GOTHIC PANTHEON OF THE GODS
One of the most remarkable pieces of the Pietroasa treasure is a beau¬
tifully worked shallow dish, or patera, dating from the 2nd or 3rd
century A.D. Ten inches in diameter, it is decorated with a statuette
surrounded by sixteen figures of gods, Graeco-Roman in style, several
of which are reproduced here. Above, left to right: the third of the
Gothic Fates holding in her left hand the scissors with which, like her
Greek counterpart Átropos, she cuts the thread of human life; a young
man, naked and carrying a mantle draped over one arm and a whip
in his other hand, is probably the Germanic Castor; woman dressed
in a flowing robe, a pail in one hand and a porringer in the other, is
another of the three Fates; statuette of the Gothic Earth goddess
(seen also in centre of dish, below). Opposite page, top: the Gothic
Mars fias a raven on his shoulder; bottom: holding a lyre and with a
mythological animal, the hippogriff, at his feet, is the Gothic Apollo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
period and is not connected with the
flight of the Visigoths. They point
out that Athanaric would have been
ill-advised to bury what was the
royal treasure or even the sacred
treasure of the nation in a region he
was going to have to abandon
completely.
But the objects themselves do have
many things to tell us of their origins
and purposes. Archaeologists agree
that they do not all belong to the
same period, and the techniques used
to make them, their shape and their
ornamentation all indicate that they
came from different workshops.
There is no doubt that the tray-
shaped patera encircled by divinities,
Graeco-Roman in style, is the work
of an artist from one of the Greek
settlements to the south of what is
now the Soviet Union
The same applies to a pitcher with
a long, straight handle, the lip and
rim adorned with carved leaves. This
is similar in all respects to the multi¬
tudes of Greek "cinachoiai" made of
silver or terra cotta. The date of
these works can be fixed approxi¬
mately as the middle of the 3rd
century A.D.
The filigree
objects adorn¬
ed with col¬
oured stones,
on the other
hand, date
from the 4th-
6 th centuries
A.D. Objects
such as these,
embellished
with garnets,
turquoise, topaz and other precious
stones are the work of Oriental
craftsmen.
In the 3rd and 4th centuries, such
works of art and the precious stones
decorating them came mainly from
Sassanide Persia; and the Eastern,
Iranian style spread everywhere and
became greatly in demand among the
chiefs of the tribal aristocracy and
the rich merchants established on the
northern shores of the Black Sea.
This explains the great numbers of
objects made by this technique, which
was later to become characteristic of
German workshops.
From one end of Europe to the
other, all the royal treasures of the
Visigoths, Ostrogoths, Vandals, Bur-
gundians and Lombards contained
works of art fashioned in the ancient
Persian style.
Not all the mysteries of the
Pietroasa treasure have yet been
resolved. But as artistic and histori¬
cal testimonies of the ancient story
of the Rumanian people and that of
mediaeval Europe as a whole, the
"Hen with the Golden Chicks" has
served asan touchstone of rare value.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
HEN WITH THE GOLDEN CHICKS (Cont'd)
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. November 1960
Letters to the Editor...
WANTED! MORE BOUBAS
*
»
ft «
*
KtfWft ¿y
Sir,
The article in The Unesco Cou¬
rier of September about the drawings
of Bouba and his friends I thought
so very interesting that I showed it
to my pupils at school and we talked
a long time about it. They asked me
if we could send drawings to children
in Africa too something which I have
wished for a long time but which
I've not realized until now! As I teach
at a Primary School, the first and sec¬
ond class, my pupils are too young
for correspondence but I think that
just by exchanging drawings they will
know more about children in Africa.
It's only very difficult where I can
get in touch with teachers from schools
there and so I write to you. I hope
very much that you can help me in
this, maybe by giving my address to
teachers in some African countries?
My project is to exchange drawings
in all varieties which can be exposed
in the classrooms then. As most
teachers in new African countries
speak French, I tell you that I can
write in that language too.
Miss Riny Spykhoven
Kriuslaan 208 bv
Amsterdam (0)
Netherlands
YOGA AND HEALTH
Sir,
As a regular reader of The Unesco
Courier I am especially interested in
the issues that deal with health
services. In our day, when all
mankind is making a tremendous
effort for peace and progress, the
preservation of health is a subject of
the greatest importance. I was much
impressed by your issues that dealt
with the fight being waged to preserve
animal and vegetable life, the purifi¬
cation of the atmosphere and achieve¬
ments in the field of medicine.
It is well-known that the physical
exercises of the Indian yogi are one
of the miracles of human invention.
They are regarded as an unusual
science that preserves health and
lengthens life, a science based on
thousands of years' experience. Un¬
fortunately, the articles that I have
been able to get hold of express
different opinions on the subject. I
should like to see The Unesco Cou¬
rier print the opinions of authoritative
scientists on yoga.
A. Chetverikov
Gory, U.S.S.R.
'PEN FRIENDS' FOR AN INDIAN
Sir,
After reading "Seven Million For¬
gotten Indians in the Land of the
Incas" which appeared in the The
Unesco Courier, the schoolchildren
belonging to our Spanish Olub decided
to "adopt" an Indian child who knew
Spanish well enough to correspond
with them. The Olub intends to tell
this child all about our way of life
and culture over here.
Madame Pivano
College Neyret, Lyons, France
WHO INVENTED RADIO VALVES 1
Sir,
In view of its unique position it is
most important that all information
given in the Courier should be fac¬
tual. It is surprising therefore to see
that in the September 1959 issue you
state that the inventor of the thermio¬
nic valve is Lee de Forest. This
claim has been made in the U.S.A.
but it is not supported by the facts.
The inventor was actually Dr. Fleming
of University College, London.
W.A. Maw
Templestowe, Vic, Australia
Ed. Note : The idea of the radio
valve (tube) can be interpreted broadly
or narrowly. In the former case, and
applying it to the valve as we know it
today, Lee de Forest is certainly the
inventor. However, in the narrow
interpretation, it is true that Dr. I.A.
Fleming produced the first vacuum
tube. This was the diode valve with
two electrodes the filament and the
plaie. It was only brought into use
for radio after Lee de Forest had im¬
proved it by introducing a grid bet¬
ween the filament and the plaie, thus
producing the triode valve and giving
it the power of amplification it need¬
ed for its general use in radio.
'GUIDE' MAPS IN THE 'COURIER'
Sir,
If you assume that The Unesco
Courier is "skimmed through" by
readers in too much of a hurry, then
artistic maps like that of Nubia pub¬
lished in the February issue are quite
adequate. If, however, you believe
that a good proportion of your readers
go through the magazine attentively,
you must admit that the inclusion of
detailed maps would be a great help
to them.
R. Rocherolles
Sceaux, France
DON'T TAKE THE MONUMENTS
Sir,
I feel that it is up to every country
to contribute, as far as its means
allow, towards the conservation of
Nubia's monuments and to the ar¬
chaeological investigations in those
areas which are soon to be inundated
for ever.
But I also think that the monuments
which are to be dismantled and remov¬
ed should not leave the country.
Taken from their natural setting and
transported to Europe or America,
they would lose a great deal of their
inherent charm. The country which
contributes towards the transfer of a
monument should not take it out of
Egypt, despite the facilities to do so
which are being offered, but should
leave it elsewhere in the country
alongside other historic and artistic
works. Thus this help would take
on its full measure of disinterestedness
and chivalry.
José Navarro Alcazar
Sucina, Spain
F.R.N.S. 3 & THE TRIPOD FISH
Sir,
I should like to point out an error
in your issue of July-August (The
Ocean's Secrets) concerning the French
bathyscaph F.N*R.S. III. The cap¬
tion with the photo of the tripod fish
on page 23 has a serious error of fact
in it, the effect of which could be
detrimenitail to the scientific work
accomplished during the past six years
by the French bathyscaph F.R.N.S. III.
The caption states: "This tripod fish...
was photographed from the bathy¬
scaph "Trieste" off Guam... 7,000
mètres under the surface." The photo
in question was in fact, taken by me
from the F.N.R.S. III in September
1954, off Toulon in the Mediterra¬
nean, at a depth of 2,200 metres. A
correction published by you would set
the record straight and would also
prevent possible errors with respect to
assertions that this fish has been found
at a depth and in waters where so far
it has not been identified.
Commander G. Huot
Commandant, Bathyscaph
F.R.N.S. HI and French
Navy Bathyscaph Group Nr.43,
Toulon, France
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco
.International council of
sport and physical education:
An International Council of Sport and Phy¬
sical Education, whose aim is to bring
about the co-operation of athletes, educa¬
tors, physical education instructors, mem¬
bers of the medical profession, psycholo¬
gists and sociologists, has been established
in Rome following the 1960 Olympics. The
Council came into being at a meeting
which brought together some 100 represen¬
tatives of international physical education
associations, international sport federations,
government agencies and institutions. The
meeting was addressed by Mr. René Maheu,
Deputy Director-General of Unesco, who
stressed Unesco's interest in all efforts to
link sport to education and to culture.
MASACCIO'S FRESCOES ON
COLOUR SLIDES: The new series of
Unesco Art Slides, the seventh to be
issued, is devoted to works of one of
the great painters of the Italian Renais¬
sance: Tomaso di Giovanni Guidi,
better known as Masaccio. The works
are frescoes from the Brancacci Chapel
of the Church of Santa Maria del Car¬
mine, and from the Santa Maria Novel¬
la Church in Florence, painted about
1426. The price of the complete set
of 30 colour slides is $ 10 (maximum)
or the equivalent in other currencies; a
20% discount is granted to educational
and cultural institutions. Orders may
be placed directly with the distributors:
Publications filmées d'Art et d'Histoire,
11, rue Carvès, Montrouge, Seine,
France.
Ëj ANGUAGE LABORATORIES':
In many U.S. colleges, high schools and
even in private industrial firms "¡language
laboratories'" have now been installed.
Pupils sit in semi-sound-proof glass-pan-
nelled booths provided with earphones. A
tape-recorded lesson is played, and the tea¬
cher may dlustrate it with slides or other
visual aids. Textbooks and exercises are
prepared for each tape. During pauses,
pupils repeat the phrases they have heard.
The teacher may tune in and correct pro¬
nunciation and inflexion and give help to
students needing it most without holding
up the rest of the class. Students, it is
claimed, make faster progress and have
more chance to develop conversational
ability. However, the system does not
replace the teacher who is needed to explain
linguistic structure, correct errors and to
prepare good master tapes.
ADULT EDUCATIONA WORLD
NEED: The second World Conference
on Adult Education organized by
Unesco recently brought together at
McGill University, Montreal, Canada,
the representatives of about 50 coun¬
tries and over 40 international non¬
governmental organizations to discuss
the many problems ~which educators
34
and governments face in this field.
The declaration which they adopted
unanimously sets down the principles
on which adult education should be
based in coming years. It concludes:
"We believe that adult education has
become of such importance for man's
survival and hoppiness that a new atti¬
tude toward it is needed. Nothing less
will suffice than that the people every¬
where should come to accept adult edu¬
cation as a normal and that Govern¬
ments should treat it as a necessary
part of the educational provision of
every country.
Si»HOW WINDOW OF EVOLU-
TION: A travelling exhibition now tour¬
ing Latin American contries, illustrates
the history of the Galapagos Islands and
the role played by the unique species of
animals and plants found there in the
theory of evolution. The display, prepar¬
ed jointly .by the International Union for
the Protection of Nature and Unesco, aims
to spotlight the efforts now being made to
preserve this "Noah's Ark" of strange forms
of life. A second copy of the exhibition
is circulating in Europe and, after being
shown in Belgium, is to open in Prague.
TEACHING TEACHERS OF JOUR¬
NALISM: Professors of journalism
and specialists in journalistic education
from Europe, Africa the Middle East
and Asia are attending the fourth annual
course of instruction which has begun
at the International Centre for Higher
Studies in lournalism, at Strasbourg.
This centre was set up in 1957 through
collaboration between Unesco and the
French Government. Professor-pupils
generally attend it on fellowships for
higher training. This year, sixteen
fellowships have been awarded by
Unesco. The Strasbourg Centre,
however, is only part of a broader enter¬
prise. Following a XStitsco-convened
conference in Quito, Ecuador, a similar
Latin American centre has now opened
its doors at the Central University of
Ecuador.
f^ ENTRE FOR CULTURAL EX¬
CHANGE: An Orient-Occident Cultu¬
ral Exchange Centre has now been opened
in Paris by the Congress for Cultural Free¬
dom an independent international organi¬
zation in which are grouped universities,
writers, scientists and artists. The new
foundation meets one of today's basic
needs: efforts must be made to overcome
the intellectual barriers which prevent a
full understanding between the Orient and
the Occident. It will thus work to spread
mutual knowledge and perhaps help to pro¬
vide deeper spiritual and intellectual under¬
standing. The distribution of literary
works and the exchange of translations will
be part of its functions "and it has also the
special role of helping to facilitate meetings
and discussions between those who represent
current movements in the philosophy, arts
and science of the Orient, on the one hand,
and of Europe, Africa and America, on the
other. The Centre (Centre d'Exchanges
Culturels Orient-Occident) is situated at
104, Boulevard Haussmann, Paris-88.
; NO MORE CANING: Corporal
punishment, already abolished in other
types of schools, is now being completely
abolished in Swedish primary schools.
Special instruction may be given to help
badly behaved pupils to fit into school
life. Marks for behaviour and neatness
will not be entered in the final marks
which children receive when they leave
school.
TFiREE FLOW TREATY AIDS 1,000
MILLION: Nearly 1,000 million people
are benefiting from a UNESCO-sponsored
Agreement which exempts books, newspa¬
pers, educational films and many other in¬
formation materials from import duties.
The Agreement adopted ten years ago by
Unesco's General Conference, is now
applied by 32 countries and has also been
extended to over 40 non-self-governing ter¬
ritories. Reviewing the progress made
through this treaty, M. René Maheu, Dep¬
uty Director-General of Unesco, recently
declared: "The customs revenue which
States forego in applying the Agreement,
amounts to millions of dollars annually.
This is evidence of the willingness of govern-
ernments to promote intellectual co-opera¬
tion between peoples by aiding the develop¬
ment of education, science and culture. I
hope that before long the Agreement will be
universally applied.
MUSIC AND MENTAL HEALTH:
The works of famous composers who at
one period or other of their lives suffer¬
ed from mental disturbances, were fea¬
tured in a concert broadcast recently
over the Belgian radio network to mark
World Mental Health Year 1960. The
programme included compositions by
Robert Schumann, Mussorgsky, Hugo
Wolf, Chabrier, and Ravel. The concert
was designed to prove that former men¬
tal health patients can produce works
of real artistic merit. It is hoped that
the idea will be extended to other fields
of artistic creation as a means of fight¬
ing the prejudice from which such for¬
mer patients often suffer.
M. EACHERS-A-PLENTY: While
most countries are desperately short of
teaching staff, in Spain a ' recent competi¬
tive examination for primary school tea¬
chers produced 14,120 candidates to fill
4,506 posts. Meanwhile enrolment in tea¬
cher training colleges is steadily increasing.
In the past three years, the number of
teacher-trainees has risen from 10,000 to
17,000 for male students and from 18,000
to 26,000 for female students.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Announcing
A NEW GERMAN EDITION
The Unesco Courier is proud to announce the launching of a German
edition, published in Berne, Switzerland, under the auspices of the Unesco
National Commissions of Austria, the Federal Republic of Germany and
Switzerland. The first issue dated September 1960 has now appeared.
Subscriptions to the "UNESCO KURIER" in Austria, Germany and
Switzerland only should be sent to the following addresses:
AUSTRIA: Subscription S 50.-. Single issue S 5.-. Subscriptions to:
UNESCO-KOMMISSION, Mentergasse 11, Wien VII.
FEDERAL REPUBLIC OF GERMANY: Subscription DM 10.-. Single issue
DM -.80. Subscriptions to: UNESCO-KOMMISSION, Komódienstrasse 40,
Köln. (Postscheckkonto 3711.)
SWITZERLAND: Subscription 8 S. Fr. Single issue -.80 S. Fr. Subscriptions to:
UNESCO-KOMMISSION, Schwanengasse 7, Bern (Postscheckkonto 111/
414). - HALLWAG AG, Nordring 4, Bern (Postscheckkonto 111/414),
and the National Distributors in Switzerland (see below).
In countries other than Austria, Germany and Switzerland the subscription rate for the
German edition will be the same as that of our other language editions.
Current subscriptions can only be transfered to the German edition at the time of renewal.
For the English, French, Spanish and Russian language editions in the above three countries,
and for the German edition of the "UNESCO KURIER" in all other countries, please continue to
send subscriptions to the National Distributors of UNESCO publications listed below.
WHERE TO OBTAIN UNESCO PUBLICATIONS
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaî, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I, Victoria. (A. 13/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Sch.
37.50.)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier:
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, C.C.P. 338.000. (fr. b. 100.)
Other publications: Office de Publicité,
I 6, rue Marcq. Bruxelles, C.C P. 285-98;
N.V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei I 5 I,
Antwerp.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. ($ 3.00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd , 99
Chungking South Rd., Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa).
CUBA. Librarla Alberto Sanchez Veloso
O'Reilly y Villegas, Havana - Librería Eco¬
nómica, Pte Zayas 505-7 Apartado I 13,
Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd ,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D.kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P O. Box I 20, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateemmen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Paris, 7«. C.C.P. 12598-48
(7 NF.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg K.G.,
Unesco-Vertrieb fur Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 145, Munich 8. (DM. 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P.O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 13; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/ I Asaf Ali Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I; Sub-Depots:
Oxford Book & Stationery Co., I 7 Park
Street Calcutta 1 6, (Scindia House,
New Delhi); Rajkamal Prakashan Private
Ltd., Himalaya House, Hornby Road,
Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. Bappit Pusat "Permata"
D|alan Nusantara 22, Diakarta
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd.,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlac Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (l£ 4-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central. Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co ,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd., Times House, 135, River Valley Rd.,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta. ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.)
NETHERLANDS. N.V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (fl 6)
NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES.
G. CT. Van Dorp & O (Ned Ant.) N.V.
Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackthorne Road, Christ-
church. (10/-).
NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A.S. Bokhi'ornet, Lille Gren-
sen, 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd., Unesco Publications House,
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony, Lahore.
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. Tl-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc., 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620, Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46
Warsaw. 10 (Zl. 50.)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andradi Ldi,
Livraria Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. ( I 0/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50), other publications
A/B CE. Fritzes, Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Rämistrasse, Zurich.
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. C C P.
1-236.
"Courier" only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-481 I. (Fr. S. 7).
THAILAND. Suksapan Panic, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi. Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street, Pretoria (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I { I 0/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N.Y. ($ 3.00 ) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaj'a Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
HELP THE WORLD'S CHILDREN by buying greeting cards which UNICEF is selling this year.
The proceeds will protect millions of youngsters from hunger and sickness. (See page 23)
Three of the ten different designs are shown on this page. Above, "Los Ninos", an impression
of Indian children dancing a joyous round in the desert, by American painter Ettore De Grazia.
THE JADE SLIPPER, a kind of Oriental version of
"Cindrella" from the folk tales of Korea, is one of a
series of designs by Czech artist Adolph Zabransky
based on five children's stories. Here, pretty Kon-Gi
is seen with her white pigeons which help her to thwart
the evil schemes planned by her step-mother.
THE EPIC OF RAMAYANA is to Indian mythology
what the llliad is to that of Greece. This design shows
the Princess Sita in the fateful moment when she sees
the golden deer. This epic story from India is another
of the "Tales of Many Lands" designed for
UNICEF cards this year by Adolph Zabransky.
]]>
</page>
</document>
