<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078133eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
MIHI«
DECEMBER 1962 (15TH YEAR) - PRICE 1 -STG. (U.K.) . 30 CENTS (U.S.) - 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
m
IB > í&M&a
l-íf^lfl^^
IS ART
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
EARTHLINGS
IN THE SPACE AGE
From an artificial satellite in orbit an
eye, human or electronic, sees no poli¬
tical frontiers and no differentiation of
races. Today as man embarks on the
conquest of space, we should not lose
sight of the immense unsolved human
problems which deny to untold millions
on our planet the most elementary of
human rights. This, as Ritchie Calder
reminds us on page 4, is something to
ponder seriously as1962drawsto its close.
¿VW
u V>
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
PO' OMN ON r«l HOalfl
rier
DECEMBER 1962
15TH YEAR
Contents
No. 12
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
Sculptured heads, detail from
a bas relief depicting an
episode from the Hindu
epic, the Ramayana, were
carved over 1,000 years ago
In a gallery of the Temple
of Shiva, near Djakarta,
Indonesia. They are among
the masterpieces of world art
chosen to Illustrate the
theme of "The Human Face"
In a 14-volume series of art
portfolios to be entitled
"Man Through His Art" (p. 11).
Unesco-Cart
Page
4 EARTHLINGS IN THE SPACE AGE
By Ritchie Calder
8 RODIN AND THE CITIZENS OF CALAIS
By Rainer Maria Rilke
11 MAN THROUGH HIS ART
A new series of educational art portfolios
12 THE DEADLY SALT OF THE EARTH
Lands poisoned by man
By Daniel Behrman
17 SAMARKAND THE FABULOUS
20 THE HIDDEN FACE OF THE CINEMA
A special world-wide report
By Paul Léglise
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
35 THE UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1962
(M.C. A3. 1.175 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except In |uly and August when
it Is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re<
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unetco Courier it Indexed monthly In The Readcrt' Guide to
Periodical Literature publithed by H. W. Wilton Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
As the year 1 962 draws to a close, The Unesco Cou¬
rier submits the following article to the contemplation
and reflection of its readers. The article is the inaugu¬
ral address that Ritchie Calder delivered in November
1 961 after his appointment to the Chair of Internation¬
al Relations at the University of Edinburgh. Winner
of the Unesco Kalinga Prize for the Popularization of
Science, Ritchie Calder is well-known to our readers
for the many articles we have published in past issues.
EARTH
sixteen times a day,
a man-made satellite
can circumnavigate the earth
By his own ingenuity, Homo sapiens, the
Earthling, has shrunk his world to the dimensions
of a very small planet. In the arrogance of our
conceit, which puts Man and his brain at the very
centre of the universe, we have never been quite
convinced by the astronomers when they have tried
to tell us how insignificant the world is in the
immensities of Space. But now the Space
Engineers, and the Astronauts, beating the bounds
of our global parish, have reminded us how relatively
small it is.
In the spirit of new adventure, one may regard
the world as a departure-platform for fugitives to
the moon or a launching pad for escapades to other
planets or even beyond our solar system, into other
universes. But the EarthUngs who cannot so escape
must recognize that on its relatively limited surface,
3,000 million people today, 4,000 million in twenty
years' time, and 6,000 million or 7,000 miUon forty
years from now, wiU have to contrive to Uve and to
work together. Or by the neglect of wisdom or
the abuse of human ingenuity, to die together.
An eye, human or electronic, in an artificial
satellite in orbit, sees no poUtical frontiers; no
ideological curtains; and no differentiation of races.
It might see H-Bombs going off as the signals of
tensions. It might see the smoke of industrial
cities, distinguishing the highly-developed, from the
underdeveloped, countries; but, in general, it would
see a globe of which only three-tenths was land and
seven-tenths covered by oceans; mountain ranges
reduced to wrinkles; evidence of surviving forests;
tawny expanses of hot deserts which cover a fifth
of its surface and cold deserts which cover another
fifth. It might with difficulty distinguish the
pattern of cultivation, of arable or cropped lands,
which accounts for only one-tenth of the land-
surface. That is the nature of humanity's famUy
estate of which, at the moment, we are the
improvident stewards.
T:he world is not just
the relic of a cosmic incident
It provides the biosphere, the Uving-space, for
the evolutionary process which, we Uke to think,
had its consummation In Man.
But with a wisdom which we have not demons¬
trated convincingly so far, we must recognize that
that biosphere and that evolutionary process include
other species with which we can coexist or which
we can stupidly destroy. Stupidly because our
relations with these other species are a condition
of our own survival.
A lump of soil no bigger than a football contains
a micro-organic population greater than the human
population of the world. That micro-organic popu¬
lation includes the germs and fungi which evoca¬
tively suggest disease or danger but which, in other
forms, are indispensable to our existance. In the
same way, we think of insects as deserving insec¬
ticide and other creatures as deserving pesticide,
but in the process we can kill those which are
essential to our ultimate needs.
For example, in order to get margarine, we
cleared big areas in Tanganyika of brush and tsetse
flies which it harboured, but in the process we got
rid of the bees which were needed to pollinate
alternative crops.
Similarly, for our short-term, and short-sighted,
needs we have destroyed the vegetation cover. We
have cut down forests the Sunday edition of one
American newspaper consumes in a single year the
yield of a forest area half as big again as that of my
native county of Angus. We have damaged the
vegetation cover in other ways, preventing the
absorption of water by the natural sponge through
which it seeps into the underground springs. As a
result the scouring rains sluice the soil off the hills,
cause floods and eventual erosion.
In the Ufetime of the United States, over two
hundred and eighty million acres of arable, crop
and range land have been destroyed more than ten
times the productive acreage of the United King¬
dom.
In the 1930's there was
the apocalyptic warning
when the midday sun
of New York was blotted out
by the dust of the Dakotas over a thousand miles
away. But only five years ago, the airliner on which
I was flying to Winnipeg could not land because at
noon we had flown into night. When we finally
broke through it was to find the city and everything
in it covered with khaki mud, spread by the rain
which had enabled us to land.
The "night", the pall which had blotted out the
sun, was dust. At 8,000 ft. the dust had been that
of Texas 1,500 miles away. At various levels, the
samples were from Oklahoma, Nebraska and the
Dakotas. The heavy particles nearer the ground
were those of Manitoba itself. We had been caught
in the cUmax of a dust storm which had whipped
topsoil from the middle of a continent.
Only slowly and recently have we come to
recognize that wild animals are not something with
which mankind is at war but a part of the balance
of Ufe, which is delicately adjusted. Recently, I
was at the Arusha Conference, in East Africa,
caUed by the International Union for the Conser¬
vation of Nature, under the sponsorship of Unesco
and the Food and Agriculture Organization. It
was an emergency meeting because so many new
states are becoming independent and the natu¬
ralists of Europe and America were afraid that the
Africans might decimate the game animals by
slaughter and destroy their habitat by immature
husbandry and indiscriminate cattle-raising.
It was gratifying, and at the same time humbling,
to find that the Africans themselves were tradition-
aUy more aware of the role of wild Ufe in their
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
LINGS IN THE SPACE AGE
by Ritchie Calder
own ecology than the white man has hitherto
shown in his intervention in that continent. The
African recognized that in the precarious nature of
the savannah lands, big game and even the tsetse
fly were a decisive factor.
Nearly four million square miles of the African
continent are held in fief by the tsetse fly. Because
of the fatal diseases which its bite produces in man
and his domesticated animals but does not produce
in the wild animals, the tsetse has preserved great
tracts which might have been destroyed by shifting
cultivation and by over-grazing.
It was suggested at Arusha that a monument
ought to be raised to the tsetse fly as "The Saviour
of Africa" and it was Africans who insisted that
before modern methods to remove the tsetse were
employed, their people must be trained to husband
well this legacy of land.
More than that, Prime Minister Nyerere of Tan¬
ganyika, volunteered the Arusha Manifesto pledging
his government, with the endorsement of all Afri¬
cans present, to preserve the wild life and their
habitat "for their children's grandchildren."
This kind of wisdom, this recognition of a world
we share, not only with other people but with other
creatures, has not been conspicuous in those nations
which we call advanced, or scientific.
In the past, civilizations have developed in loca¬
lities or regions. They have flourished and decayed
but always another civilization could succeed them.
Today, ours is a global civilization. It Is not
bounded by the Tigris and the Euphrates; it is the
whole world. It is a closed community so interde¬
pendent that every mistake we make is exaggerated
on a world scale.
For the first time in history, man has the power
of veto over the evolution of his species. We share
the biosphere. Into that we have injected, in the
past sixteen years, man-made radioactivity. Ele¬
ments which did not exist in nature have been
indiscriminately scattered over the face of the earth,
to combine in all living things.
Today there is not a child
in the world that does not have
radiostrontium in its bones
At least to some degree. The amounts may be
insignificant and the possible effects may be emo¬
tionally exaggerated and medically in dispute.
Much is unproven, much is unknown. But that only
emphasizes that men, on defective evidence or in
positive ignorance, are recklessly tampering with
the biosphere on which the present and future of
their race depends.
We have had plenty of reminders of the dangers
of neglecting Claude Bernard's warning to his
fellow-scientists a century ago "True science
teaches us to doubt and in ignorance to refrain."
Radiostrontium was overlooked in the calculations
of the possible effects of H-bomb testing, because
the mechanism by which radioactive krypton decays
into strontium-90 had not been taken into account
and because the mechanism of stratospheric storage
I
and the reappearance of radioactive particles in the
atmosphere had not been realized.
Nature, with grim Irony, brinßs the radioactive
chickens home to roost. Nuclear tests may be made
In remote places the Marshall Islands, Christmas
Island, the Sahara, behind the Urals or In the
Arctic, but the radioactivity will reappear in the
countries which originated such tests as, well, of
course, as countries which were not party to them.
Whether exploded near the Equator or beyond the
Arctic Circle, the radioactive garbage of those
bombs will be swept into the Jet streams of the
Radioactive Forties, the latitudes which include the
United States, Britain, France and the Soviet Union.
This, with all the emotional and political over¬
tones which it produces in international relations,
is another reminder that wc all share one biosphere
and of the global risks of tampering with it.
t took Homo sapiens
at least 200,000 years to
multiply and reach the present
figure of 3,000 million
It will, on present trends, take less than forty
years to double that figure. There ls no way, short
of cataclysm, man-made or otherwise, by which the
figure can be less than 4.000 million by 1930. It may
be more but it cannot be less.
In the lifetime of the younger politicians of today
the Demographic Revolution, which takes no
account of political Ideology, will have completely
changed the pattern of world politics. Whereas at
the beginning of this century, there was one Euro¬
pean to every two Asians, by the end of this century
the ratio will have become 1 to 4and here the
term "European" includes the entire Soviet Union.
Latin America will, in the twentieth century, have
Increased its population tenfold and the remaining
continents will have increased fourfold.
As the experts of the United Nations said In The
Future Growth of World Population "Wc are swim¬
ming against the tide of evolution but having disco¬
vered how to increase the flood, we have not aLso.
through biological science, the means of arresting
it." In the next twenty years, we have Inescapably
therefore to contrive to provide board and lodging
for a least another 1,000,000,000 people.
In fact. It means that. In political wisdom as well
as decent humanity, we have to double the present
food supply because more than half the world's
population is undernourished and the pressures
upon the governments of new states are to provide
proper nourishment.
I have. In the past fourteen years, been among
the wandering Bedouins in the desert, the Dyaks of
Equatorial Borneo, the Eskimos in the Arctic, the
peoples of the hinterlands of Latin America and
Africa and Asia. In one way or another their lives
and their destinies have been consciously touched
by scientific and technological achievement.
Many of them have acquired their freedom
there are nearly twice as many nations In the U.N. 5
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
EARTHLING'S IN THE SPACE AGE (Cont'd)
as there were when it was founded. But when the
intoxicating effects of political Independence wear
off, there is the mornlng-after-the-nlght-before.
People are apt to wake up and discover that free¬
dom has been robbed of its meaning; that they are
Just as hungry, or more hungry; just as poor, or
more Impoverished; just as sick or more disease-
ridden, and just as frustrated in their seeking for a
better way 'of Ufe.
But there is a new factor in their frustration:
they know that the wit of man can produce more
food and that disease is not the will of the gods
but can be cured by means available to man and
that there are so many things which they knew
they wanted but now know they need.
Through the limitedfinancially that isacti¬
vities of the U.N. agencies, of the U.N. expanded
technical assistance fund and now of the special
fund and by the much more lavish examples of
bilateral aid, people have been shown what is scien¬
tifically and technically possible. But it is not
enough to show them.
To demonstrate what might be done to people
who have not the means to do it is just tantalizing.
It is just "window-shopping"walking along
Princes Street with nothing in your pocket and with
plateglass between you and the things you have
been taught to want.
The peoples of the- emerging
countries have not the means
to go shopping in the
supermarket of science
Prof. P.M.S. Blackett has termed it. They
cannot even afford the bargain basement.
We say, and are emphatically right in saying so,
that the object of this kind of assistance is to help
people to help themselves throwing them a rope
with which to haul themselves out of the morass
of poverty. But this is no Indian rope-trick the
rope has to be tethered to something, and a winch
would help to haul them out more quickly. As it is,
the rope is slipping.
After ten years of this new social philosophy by
which governments acknowledged that they were
responsible, not only for their own people, but for
other, less fortunate peoples as well, the gap between
the prosperity of the highly-advanced countries and
the poverty of the countries struggling for develop¬
ment has not closed it has widened. The rich
countries are richer and the poor countries are
poorer despite the thousands of millions which
have been spent on aid.
The explanation is not that this aid has been
squandered although some of it has, because it
was given for the wrong motives and applied in the
wrong ways or because the recipients themselves
have misused it.
But the true explanation was that of the late Dag
Hammarskjold. He pointed out what the phrase
"You've never had it so good" meant in reverse
in the underdeveloped countries.
"A fall of only 5 per cent in the average of their
export prices is approximately equivalent to the
entire inflow of capital which they receive not only
from International Bank Loans but from all other
public and private loans and government grants."
The prices of some staple primary products of
those countries to the advantage of the richer
countries which buy them have dropped, not 5 per
cent, but from 10 to 47 per cent! One cannot disso¬
ciate that from the political consequences.
Such circumstances have, in this closely inter¬
dependent world, global repercussions. This was
very succinctly put by Mr. Ernest Bevin when, as
Foreign Secretary, he was trying to convince an
audience of Lancashire housewives that foreign
affairs were kitchen politics. It was at the time of
a worse-than-usual fat shortage. He said:
"You complain because you can't get fish suppers
in Lancashire. Why can't you get fish suppers?
The Fleetwood trawlers are bringing in the fish and
there's plenty of potatoes. But the fish-fryers can't
fry. And why can't they fry? Because there's
trouble in Burma and because we haven't got things
straightened out in Slam. And because of all that
India can't get rice from these countries. And
because India has to grow more food for its own
people, we can't get groundnuts from India. And
because we can't get groundnuts from India, the
fish-fryers can't get the oil. And you can't get your
fish and chips."
Governments, when the markets skid, cannot
"lift themselves by their own bootstraps" or, if
they do it is by duress. In the meantime their
peoples ' will endure the Misery-Go-Round of
Poverty.
Sick people cannot work to procure, or earn, food.
So they are undernourished, and because they are
sick and undernourished they remain ignorant,
because the sick and hungry cannot learn how to
Improvise or improve their condition. And because
they are sick and hungry and ignorant, they remain
poor and endure squalor, and because they Uve like
animals they breed Uke animals.
With more mouths to feed, there is less food for
everyone. And so the roundabout of wretchedness
goes on. Democracy is a word which echoes mean-
inglessly in empty bellies.
Dr. Sen, the Director-General of F.A.O., has
launched "The Freedom from Hunger Campaign."
He might not have had to do so if his predecessor,
Lord Boyd Orr, had not been frustrated in his
efforts to set up a World Food Board, fourteen years
ago. It would have taken politics out of food and,
food out of politics; in the phrase of former Mayor
Fiorello La Guardia of New York, "It would have
taken human lives off the ticker-tapes." It would
have ensured that food would get into the bellies of
people who need it and that farmers would not
suffer from over-production.
Per capita until this year we have had, globally,
enough calories, even for the increasing world popu¬
lation. But that, too, is grossly misleading. What
is important is not per capita but per stomach and
more than half the world's population have not
enough to eat, and, short of death from starvation,
have never had food adequate for well-being.
By 1960 the total world stocks
of surplus grain had reached
the incredible figure
of 125,000,000 tons
Enough to provide the full calorie needs of
450,000,000 people for a complete year. Or an extra
200 calories a day to the Asian population for more
than three yearsas Dr. Norman Wright, Deputy
Director-General of F.A.O., points out in the
valuable British Association symposium published
as Hunger: Can It Be Averted?
No one should be so foolish as to think that the
distribution of those vast surpluses, even if it were
possible would solve the problem of hunger. Reliev¬
ing immediate stresses, yes. By distribution through
such agencies as Unicef, yes. By turning food into
currency, yes. Supplies of food can be made avail¬
able to governments to help present needs and the
proceeds can be used by a government to help its
own agriculture to increase its yields in future
years. That is .the only permanent solutionto
enable countries and regions to produce their food
requirements.
It can be done. We do not need to imagine food
artificially produced by photosynthesis. The scien¬
tific know-how already exists. The knowledge we
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
have got, applied with wisdom, can increase the
yields from existing acreages. By plant-breeding we
can extend the food-growing acreages into what
seemed inhospitable regions.
The Unesco Arid Zone Committee has done
remarkable work in showing how deserts might be
developed. I have no doubt, having been in the
Arctic seeing whether it might become part of our
habitable world, that production, if need be, can be
extended there.
As far as those oceans which cover seven-tenths
of our globe are concerned, we are at the cave-man
stage.
At sea we hunt our food
and do not husband it
Sea-farming and sea-ranching
are perfectly feasible
The great international survey of the Indian
Ocean, sponsored by Unesco, In which 25 survey
ships of 15 nations are taking part, will not only
tell us a great deal about that birthplace of the
monsoons but also about its biological possibilities
and its food prospects.
The World Health Organization and the United
Nations Children's Fund have done a great huma¬
nitarian work in conquering disease and relieving
suffering. It is not too much to claim that, with
their very considerable help, modern medicine, with
scientific drugs, such as penicillin, has saved more
lives in the last ten years, than have been lost in
all the wars in human history. Drugs are the in¬
struments of death-control and, as such, have part
responsibiUty for the rising tide of population.
But reverting to our Misery-Go-Round, I would
remind you that ill people cannot produce, or earn,
food. Well people can. In rice-growing regions, the
critical, and very manual, functions of transplant¬
ing and harvesting rice coincide with the malarial
seasons. Three out of five may be sick of the fever.
ReUeved of malaria, there will be five pairs of hands
and the yields will be increased. Malaria control
extends acreages by recovering land from the mos¬
quito and clearing malarial jungle for cultivation.
Yet even this work is in hazard. Malarial control,
through modern insecticides, has freed hundreds of
millions from the fever. But the mosquitoes are
developing insecticide resistance and are multiply¬
ing and what was endemic malaria may become
epidemic malaria. It is a race between Man and
the Mosquito.
It means malaria eradication, not just control.
If, by modern drugs which are available, the para¬
site of malaria can be removed from the blood of
humans before the resurgence of the mosquitoes,
there wiU be no disease for the mosquito to trans¬
mit. It is perfectly feasible. What is needed is the
will and the financial support of governments for
the World Health Organization's Campaign.
Recently, the United Nations held in Rome a
conference on "New Sources of Energy." Ironically,
atomic energy was never mentioned. The new
sources were the oldest of all sun, wind and geo-
thermal energy, the heat in the crust of the earth.
It was a "Do-it-yourself" conference telling the
developing countries how they might contrive,
improvise, and adapt methods of harnessing the sun
and the winds to their domestic and industrial
needs.
We found that geothermal energy has immense
possibilities. We have thought of it, up to now, as
the self-evident showings the geysers, the bubbling
mudpools and the gases escaping from rock fissures.
Such sites have been usefully developed for power
and the production of electrical energy In Iceland,
CaUfornla, New Zealand and Italy.
But it has been shown that drilling into the geo¬
thermal structures, of which these are just the
obvious manifestations, will give temperatures even
twenty times as high as the open leaks. It Is pos¬
sible to tap oil as required develop power units to
suit requirements, which, of course, ls Just what
developing countries need. They have to have
power-units with which their Infant industries can
grow upas our Industrial Revolution did. from
factory steam engines to the industrial conurbations
with huge generating stations.
Now here Is an Interesting fact: the First Indus¬
trial Revolution derived from access to fossil fuels
coal In the first Instance, and then oil and natural
gas. But, as the World Power Conference has con¬
sistently reminded us, there ls a geographical and
geological "joker" In this. Over nine-tenths of all
the accessible coal and eight-tenths of the proven
oil Is north of Latitude 20 N.
So the countries outside that zone, Including mast
of the countries we now call underdeveloped, could
have no role In the First Industrial Revolution
except the one they had as the providers of food
and raw materials for the workers and factories
of the fossil-fuel countries.
But if we look at the configurations of geother¬
mal energy, we can Identify It with the great vol¬
canic arcs. From Kamchatka, through Japan, the
Philippines, Indonesia, the South Pacific Islands, to
New Zealand. From Alaska, down the west coast of
Canada and U.S.A. to Mexico, Ecuador, Peru and
Chile, to Terra del Fuego. From Iceland, via the
great range of submarine volcanoes, through Tris¬
tan da Cunha, round the Cape of Good Hope.
Another down the Great Rift from Ethiopia, through
Uganda, Congo, Kenya, Tanganyika and Mozam¬
bique.
Then there is a geothermal region from Italy
through Greece and the Middle East to Afghanistan.
Note that nature has provided geothermal energy in
places where it failed to provide fossil fuels. With
U.N. help countries are to look for this source of
energy which, by default of atomic energy, may
speed their development.
For the first time in history,
Man, the Earlliling, has
the power of veto over
continuing evolution
He can exercise that veto by the nuclear destruc¬
tion of the race, or, by default In handling the pro¬
blems of starvation, prove that Malthus was right.
He can ambitiously reach out to the farther
planets, but his species as such must survive on the
surface of the earth, subsist from the nine Inches
of top-soil which feeds, clothes and shelters him or
from the seas from which he emerged hundreds of
millions of years ago.
All the majesty of his mind can be dethroned by
his stomach. Man can feast like Bclshazzar and
Ignore the writing on the wall. He can spend
£40,000 million a year on the defence of peace and
Ignore the real content of the peace he Is supposed
to be defending. He can say, "My group, at least,
shall survive"', and like the locust-men of Attila',
Genghis Khan and Tamerlane and Hitler, try to
wrest lebensraum at other people's expense.
He can split the atom and release the power of
matter and use this, his greatest discovery, to poi¬
son the goodness of his earth and destroy his
species. He can outboast the Ancients, who in the
arrogance of their material success built pyramids
as the gravestones of their civilizations, for Modern
Man can throw his pyramids into Space and they
may orbit eternally round a planet which died of
his neglect.
Or he may choose to use his science and his
wisdom to co-operate with all his kind in the 7
peaceful enrichment of his Earth and of the people
who live on it.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
A general view (above) and details of "The
Citizens of Calais" by Auguste Rodin, who made two
originals, one for Calais and the other for London,
and authorized seven originals to be cast in bronze.
These are now on view in Tokyo, Philadelphia,
Basle, Copenhagen, Belgium, in an American pri¬
vate collection and in the Musée Rodin in Paris.
RODIN AND
by Rainer Maria Rilke
In 1347 six burghers of Calais volun¬
teered to give their lives to save
their beseiged city, and though they
were eventually spared, the event
has gone down as one of the most
glorious examples of the spirit of
self-sacrifice in history. Five hun¬
dred years later, in 1895, Auguste Ro¬
din chose the theme for one of his
greatest works in bronze, and in
1903 the poet Rainer Maria Rilke
wrote a moving description of this
immortal scene. Rilke's text and the
group scene above are reproduced
in the first volume, War and Peace,
of a new art series entitled Man
Through His Art appearing early next
year (see page 11). The Unesco
Courier presents the Rodin and Rilke
works in this issue not only for their
intrinsic beauty but as an example
of the struggle for Human Rights to
mark the 14th anniversary this month
(December 10) of the adoption of the
Universal Declaration of Human
Rights by the U.N. General Assembly.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photo* C Dominique Lajoux
THE CITIZENS OF CALAIS
he most supreme instance of Rodin's power
of exalting a past event to the height of the
imperishable, whenever historical subjects or forms
demand to live again in his art, is found perhaps in "The
Citizens of Calais".
The suggestion for this group was taken from a few
passages in the chronicles of Froissart that tell the story
of the City of Calais at the time it was besieged by the
English king, Edward the Third. The king, not willing
to withdraw from the city, then on the verge of starv¬
ation, ultimately consents to release it if six of its noble
citizens deliver themselves into his hands "that he may
do with them according to his will." He demands that
they leave the city bareheaded, clad only in their shirts,
with a rope about their necks and the keys of the citadel
in their hands.
The chronicler describes the scene in the city. He
relates how the burgomaster, Messire Jean de Vienne,
orders the bells to be rung and the citizens to assemble
in the market-place. They hear the final message and
wait in expectation and in silence. Then heroes rise
among them, the chosen ones, who feel the call to die.
The wailing and weeping of the multitude rises from
the words of the chronicler, who seems to be touched for
the moment and to write with a trembling pen. But he
composes himself once more and mentions four of the
heroes by name; two of the names he forgets. He says
that one man was the wealthiest citizen of the city and
that another possessed authority and wealth and "had
two beautiful maidens for daughters"; of the third he
only knows that he was rich in possessions and heritage,
and of the fourth that he was the brother of the third.
He reports that they removed all their clothing save
their shirts, that they tied ropes about their necks and
thus departed with the keys of the city and of the citadel.
He tells how they came to the King's camp and of how
harshly the King received them and how the executioner
stood beside them when the King, at the request of the
Queen, gave them back their Uves. "He listened to his
wife", says Froissart, "because she was very pregnant".
The chronicler does not continue further.
For Rodin this was sufficient material. He felt immedi¬
ately that there was a moment in this story when some¬
thing portentous took place, something independent of
time and place, something simple, something great. He
concentrated all his attention upon the moment of the
departure. He saw how the men started on their way,
he felt how through each one of them pulsated once more
his entire past life, he realized how each one stood there
prepared to give that life for the sake of the old city.
Six men rose before him, of whom no two were alike,
only two brothers were among them between whom there
was. possibly a certain similarity. But each of them had
resolved to live his last hour in his own way, to celebrate
it with his soul and to suffer for it with his body, which
clung to life.
Rodin then no longer saw the forms of these men.
Gestures rose before him, gestures of renunciation, of
farewell, of resignation. Gestures over gestures. He
gathered them together and gave them form. They
thronged about him out of the fullness of his knowledge,
a hundred heroes rose in his memory and demanded to
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
RODIN (Cont'd)
be sacrificed. And he concentrated this hundred into six.
He modelled them each by himself In heroic size to
represent the greatness of their resolution, modelled them
nude in the appeal of their shivering bodies.
He created the old man with loose-jointed hanging
arms and heavy dragging step, and gave him the worn-
out walk of old men and an expression of weariness that
flows over his face into the beard.
He created the man that carries the key, the man who
would have lived for many years to come, but whose life
is condensed into this sudden last hour which he can
hardly bear. His lips are tightly pressed together, his
hands bite into the key. There is fire in his strength and
it burns in his defiant bearing.
He created the man who holds his bent head with both
hands to compose himself, to be once more alone.
He created the two brothers, one of whom looks back¬
ward while the other bends his head with a movement
of resolution and submission as though he offered it to
the executioner.
He created the man with the vague gesture whom
Gustave Geffroy has caUed "Le Passant". The man moves
forward, but he turns back once more, not to the city,
not to those who are weeping, and not to those who go
with him: he turns back to himself His right arm is
raised, bent, vacillating. His hands open in the air as
though to let something go, as one gives freedom to a
bird.
This gesture is symbolic of a departure from all uncer¬
tainly, from a happiness that has not yet been, from a
grief that will now wait in vain, from men who live some¬
where and whom he might have met sometime, from all
possibilities of tomorrow and the day after tomorrow;
and from Death which he had thought far distant, that
he had imagined would come mildly and softly and at
the end of a long, long time.
This figure, if placed by itself in a dim, old garden,
would be a monument for all who have died young.
Hus Rodin has made each of these men live
again the last concentrated moment of life.
Each figure is majestic in its simple greatness. They bring
to mind Donatello and, perhaps, Claux Sluter and his
prophets in the Chartreuse of Dijon.
It seems at first as though Rodin had done nothing
more than gather them together. He has given them the
same attire, the shirt and the rope, and has placed them
together in two rows: the three that are in the first row
are about to start forward, the other three turn to the
right and follow behind. The place that was decided
upon for the erection of the monument was the market¬
place of Calais, the same spot from which the tragic
procession had formerly started. There the silent group
was to stand, raised by a low step above the common life
of the market-place as though the fearful departure were
always pending.
The City of Calais refused to accept a low pedestal
because it was contrary to custom. Rodin then suggested
that a square tower, two storeys high and with simply-
cut walls, be built near the ocean and there the six
citizens should be placed, surrounded by the solitude of
the wind and the sky. This plan, as might have been
expected, was declined, although it was in harmony with
the character of the work.
If the trial had been made, there would have been an
incomparable opportunity for observing the unity of the
group, which, although it consisted of single figures, held
closely together as a whole. The figures do not
touch one another, but stand side by side like the
last trees of a hewn-down forest united only by
the surrounding atmosphere.
From every point of view the gestures stand out
clear and great from the dashing waves of the
contours; they rise and fall back into the mass of
stone Uke flags that are furled. The entire impression
of this group is precise and clear. Like all of Rodin's
compositions, this one, too, appears to be a pulsating
world enclosed within its own boundaries.
Besides the points of actual contact there is a kind
Archaeological Survey of Ind
'Love & Marriage'
of contact produced by the surrounding atmosphere
which diminishes, influences and changes the character
of the group. Contact may exist between objects far
distant from one another, like the conflux of forms
such as one sees sometimes in masses of clouds,
where the interjacent air is no separating abyss, but
rather a transition, a softly-graduated conjunction.
To Rodin the participation of the atmosphere in the
composition has always been of greatest importance. He
has adapted all his figures, surface after surface, to their
particular space and environment; this gives them the
greatness and independence, the marvellous complete¬
ness and life which distinguishes them from other works.
When interpreting nature he found, as he intensified
an expression, that, at the same time, he enhanced the
relationship of the atmosphere to his work to such
a degree that the surrounding air seemed to give more
life, more passion, as it were, to the embraced surfaces.
When Rodin concentrates the surfaces of his works
into culminating points, when he uplifts to greater height
the exalted or gives more depth to a cavity he creates
an effect like that which atmosphere produces on monu¬
ments that have been exposed to it for centuries. The
atmosphere has traced deeper lines upon these monu¬
ments, has shadowed them' with veils of dust, has
seasoned them with rain and frost, with sun and storm,
and has thus endowed them with endurance so that
they may remain imperishable through many slowly-
passing dusks and dawns.
The effect of atmosphere, which is the monumental
principle of Rodin's art, is wonderfully achieved in "The
Citizens of Calais." These sculptural forms seen from
a distance are not only rounded by the immediate
atmosphere, but by the whole sky; they catch on their
surfaces as with a mirror its moving distances so that
a great gesture seems to Uve and to force space to parti¬
cipate in its movement.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
© The National Galle
Three great works of art in the volume " Love
and Marriage ", one of a series of 14 art portfolios
to be published under the title " Man Through
His Art ".From left to right : Standing couple
Courtesy of The Art Institute of Chicago
on the façade of Caitya Hall, Karle, Bombay
(Ist century B.C.) ; Wedding portrait of Giovanni
Arnolfini by Jan Van Eyck (1434) ; American
Gothic, a painting by Grant Wood (1930).
'MAN THROUGH HIS ART
HROUGHOUT the ages, from the time he dwelt in
caves to the present day, man has beep impelled to
an artistic expression and across the long tapestry or his history
he discloses in his art the same inspirations prompting his
painter's brush or sculptor's chisel.
The great themes of his art admit no frontiers; they vanquish
both time and conflict, providing a perfect basis for the introduc¬
tion of one culture to another.
On this basis a series of art portfolios called "Man Through
his Art" is being prepared by an international group of scholars
and art historians working within the framework of Unesco's
Major Project for the Mutual Understanding of Eastern and
Western Cultural Values.
"Man Through his Art" is sponsored by the World Confede¬
ration of Organizations of the Teaching Profession (W.C.O.T.P.)
and will be published with the collaboration and financial aid of
Unesco. It has received a research grant from the Rockefeller
and other foundations in the United States, and many of Unesco's
national commissions those of India, U.S.A., Sweden, Federal
Republic of Germany, Cambodia, Spain, Ghana and the United
Kingdom have also co-operated to make the project possible.
The complete series will appear over a seven-year period in
14 folios on 14 separate themes: War and Peace, Music, Nature,
Man at Work, the Human Face, Festivals, the Vision of Bliss, Love
and Marriage, Charity, Death, Man and Beast, the Family, Dreams
and Fantasy, and the Experience of God.
The first two portfolios, War and Peace, and Music, are sche¬
duled to be published early in 1963. The immense theme of
war and peace ranges from works of art from the modern period
to 3,500 B.C. Saharan rock paintings (the Archers of Tassili)
through the heroic epics of ancient India and Greece (the Maha-
barata and Homers Iliad), and the Chinese Buddhist cavo painting
"Meditation before the Setting Sun" expressing visually the
Chinese saying that "Peace comes through a man's ability to
listen not only with the ear but with the mind, not only with the
mind but with the spirit."
Each portfolio will have 20 reproduction plates (12 1/4" by 9",)
16 in full colour and 4 in black and white. The plates will be
detachable for display in classrooms, adult education and commu¬
nity centres, and a text prepared by eminent scholars will
combine information about the approach of different cultures to
each theme with a detailed analysis of each work of art chosen.
The volumes seek to reveal to the modern 6tudent not only the
multiformity of the world's civilizations and the inter-relationship
of their artistic expression but man's fundamental similarity of
response within them.
Within the shrinking bounds of our world today we live in the
immediate presence of other civilizations and our understanding
of them has become indispensable to the discovery of our own
identity. The editors of the "Man Through His Art" series hope
that the recurring themes of man's creative history will bridge past
and present and link the people of the world in better under¬
standing.
All orders and enquiries should be directed to WCOTP, 12, rue dc
Ponthieu, Paris, who are responsible for making arrangements for the
publication of editions in all languages or (for the U.K.) to Educational
Productions' Ltd., East Ardsley, Yorkshire, England (publishing agent
in the U.K.). Provisional price for the U.K. edition £1; France about
15 NF. Other editions at comparable prices.
NO ORDERS SHOULD BE SENT TO UNESCO, PLEASE.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO SURVEYS
A SPECIAL
ARJD-LAND PROBLEM
^pP!
Y. Bagrianski, U.S.S.R.
Milos Hrbas, Prague
From as far as the eye can see a silver ribbon of
water flows down a newly excavated drainage canal
in the Soviet Socialist Republic of Uzbekistan.
THE DEADLY
Tashkent is one of those names on the map
that ring with adventure. Long before clumsy
galleons set out for new worlds, it throbbed with life along
the main artery of trade between East and West. It was
one of the great caravan halting places of Central Asia
on the silk route from China to Europe. Here, travellers
halted on their journeys, exchanged their goods and their
ideas and, perhaps, learned that what they had in common
outweighed what set them apart.
Recently, I watched Tashkent live through another such
adventure. The setting was a modern, rambling city of
1,000,000, the capital of the Uzbekistan Socialist Republic
in the Soviet Union. The camel caravans had been
replaced by jet airliners and plodding donkeys had given
way to trams and trolleybuses, but that atmosphere of the
caravanserai as an international meeting-ground could
still be felt.
This time, the travelers were scientists and the treasures
they were exchanging were knowledge. From twenty-
five countries, 300 of them had come to Tashkent to take
stock of a little-known problem that is one of most dan¬
gerous enemies facing man in his struggle to wrest new
land from desert and semi-desert regions the world over.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
"i* ' Il
A burst of water from a high-pressure hose being operated In the
Uzbekistan desert and a sand dune disintegrates and is washed away.
SALT OF THE EARTH
by
Daniel Ilehrman
They met In a symposium on the influence of irrigation
upon secondary-sallnization of soils, organized by the
Academies of Science of the Soviet Union and Uzbekistan
with the co-operation of Unesco.
In addition to this symposium, Tashkent also played
host to a group of twelve Unesco fellows studying problems
of irrigation and salinization under differing conditions.
Their course in the Soviet Union followed stays In the
United States and France.
Why this concern with salinization? To the non-
specialist, with whom I had a great deal in common until
the problem was patiently explained to me, saline waters
belong In the sea and the "fight against salinization" im¬
plies efforts to convert the oceans Into reservoirs of
unlimited supplies of water for drinking, industrial and
agricultural purposes.
The Tashkent symposium, however, was interested only
in saline soils and saline ground water. True, this water
is not very saltywhen used for Irrigation, it contains
only from 0.5 to 2 grammes of minerai salts per litre
(1,000 grammes) as compared to an average of 35 gram
mes per litre in the sea. But if it ls not handled carefully,
it can play havoc.
The extent of this havoc was quickly brought out at the
Tashkent meeting. It opened with a statement by Prof.
G. A. Mavllanov, the director of the Uzbekistan Institute
of Hydro-Geology, in which he estimated that 30 per cent
of the 12,000,000 hectares now irrigated in the Soviet Union
are sallnized to the point where they require reclamation
to some extent. Dr. Luna Leopold, chief hydraulic en¬
gineer for the United States Geological Survey, put it to
me in another way: In the U.S.A. to-day, every new acre
of land brought in by irrigation Ls offset by the loss of
another acre rendered partially barren by secondary-sali-
nization. This figure, he believes, holds true for arid zones
thoughout the world.
Now the meaning of the Tashkent symposium was
beginning to be driven home: in these arid lands where
every acre of new soil represents both a huge economic
investment and a marshalling of engineering and scientific
skills, modern man is literally sowing his fields with salt.
Yields drop, plants wilt, whitish slime oozes into
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE DYING GROUND
White patches covering ground
between date palms (left) are salt
deposits brought to the surface
by evaporation of moisture from
water-logged soil at Lahore, Pakis¬
tan. Salts poison the soil, stunting
nearby vegetation. Soil specialists
(right) doing research work in
Uzbekistan are almost hidden by
dust clouds swept up by the search¬
ing wind from the eroded ground.
West Pakistan Water and Power
Development Authority, Lahore.
SALT OF THE EARTH (Cont'd)
Lands by man
u
furrows to turn land into a waterlogged salty mass, grey
outcroppings of salt blotch the surface in pools even
walls and foundations of buildings are attacked by a man-
made curse of the earth.
The blight ignores political boundaries. As speaker
after speaker took the rostrum in Tashkent, I learned that
It strikes in the Central Valley of California, the cotton-
fields of Uzbekistan, the Valley of the Euphrates in Iraq,
the Polygon of Drought in northeastern Brazil, the Indus
Plain in Pakistan... Temperate zones cannot afford to relax
fully, either: the danger lurks whenever Irrigation is used
to supplement scanty rainfall.
A question flashed into my mind as I listened to this
toll: what about the ancients? How were they able to
Irrigate for centuries or even millenia without suffering
from salinization? This question came naturally after
Dr. Mustafa M. Elgabaly, director of the Land Reclamation
Institute of the University of Alexandria in the U.A.R.,
told how salinization has appeared in Egyptian soil
only within the past century after 5,000 years of irrigation.
Here, I had unwittingly found the crux of the problem.
Ancient civilizations learned from trial-and-error to
Irrigate with water of low salt content on soils with good
natural drainage. Even so, it is believed that saliniza¬
tion was one of the causes for the decline of the great
ancient civilization of Mesopotomia. In some cases in
history a set of fortunate circumstances enabled irrigation
to be carried out without excessive dangers of salinization.
For instance, around oases, where land was irrigated for
thousands of years, belts of salt-resistant date palms
provided biological drainage by drawing the salt from the
soil.
Modern man, however, cannot rely on such exceptional
conditions when he seeks to stretch the cultivable surface
of the -earth. He must run the risk of using water with
a high mineral salt content when no other new supplies
are available. He must cultivate land where nature has
not provided the soil with drainage.
That is where the trouble begins. The two main causes
of secondary-salinization (scientists use this term to dis¬
tinguish man-made salinization from the problem of
naturally saline soils) are too little water... and too much
water.
Modern irrigation systems tend to stretch their water
supplies over the largest possible area of land. In dry
years when water resources drop, there is not enough
left for leaching that is, for flushing salts out of the
upper layers of the soil where they accumulate when
evaporation removes water from the earth but not its
salts. The leaching process is extremely important: it is
also used in making naturally saline soils fit for cultiva¬
tion.
Too much water can be even worse. It may come from
over-irrigation when farmers prefer the prospect of high
short-term yields to the long-term warnings of scientists.
It also Is caused by seepage from unlined irrigation canals
(losses of water in transport can run as much as 50 per
cent in old systems).
he combination of the two raises the sub¬
surface water table at a rate often as high
as three feet a year. When this ground water table rises
to the point where roots can suck it up through capillary
action, plants commit slow suicide and rich land becomes
a soggy swamp.
Like the common mortal who is neither a soil scientist
nor a hydrogeologist, I had always thought that making
arid land productive was simply a matter of bringing
water in. But the Tashkent symposium was much more
interested in getting water out.
It would be an exaggeration to say that, after four
days of meetings and seventy-five scientific papers, the
problem of salinization was solved. We have been
spoiled by the miracles of modern science in which a
wonder drug can wipe out a pestilential disease over¬
night or a discovery in petrochemistry can revolutionize
the objects in our everyday lives. But soil, water and
agriculture do not lend themselves to such dramatic test-
tube treatment. The conditions under which scientists
must work here are as varied as the waters and the soils
of the earth itself.
The Tashkent meeting made one point clear: this is
not one of those problems where wastage of natural
resources is an inevitable consequence of progress. On
two different occasions, I heard an American and a Soviet
scientist state flatly that irrigation per. se is not the
culprit. When properly performed, it can reclaim waste
land. The fight against salinization is a delicate and
complex process: it might be compared to adding and
draining exactly the right amount of water, according to
its qualities, while tending a flowerpot except that the
flowerpot in question usually measures a few hundred
thousand acres.
This flowerpot analogy was underlined when Prof. Pierre
Chouard of the Sorbonne, director of the phytotron out¬
side Paris where plants are studied under artificial envir¬
onments, told of a fascinating small-scale experiment in
the Sahara. There, fruit and vegetables are grown in
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
In the shadow
of Tamerlane's tomb
r^frSïn,
"-m
large plastic containers filled with sand and equipped
with "plumbing" to assure drainage of highly-saline
water. While this method ls suitable only for desert
stations where its high cost is still lower than the price
of bringing in food by road or air, it came as a welcome
Interlude among reports of gigantic drainage projects.
Throughout the world, the scale of these projects ls
nearly as great as that of irrigation dams and canals. In
certain regions, porous tile drainpipes are laid by auto¬
matic machinery at depths from ten to fifteen feet below
the earth's surface and they carry excess water into
collector canals in a network comparable to that of a
city's sewage system. Elsewhere, tube wells may have
to be drilled to depths as great as 300 feet (100 metres)
to pump out this excess water and lower the subsurface
water table out of the range of plant roots.
But how much land can be drained by a given number
of tube wells or a given length of horizontal drains?
Which plants resist salinity best? At what point accord¬
ing to the mineral salt content of irrigation water should
preventative steps be taken? And how can crops be
irrigated so as to maintain high yields, conserve water
and prevent re-sallnlzatlon all at the same time?
hese were some of the questions asked and
often answered at Tashkent both in and out
of the symposium. As any scientist who has ever
attended such an international meeting can tell you
some of the most valuable work of a symposium is done
outside official working hours. Tashkent Itself was
fertile soil for such encounters.
Despite its industrial growth represented by textile
factories feeding on irrigated cotton fields almost at Its
gates, It has wisely clung to its character of an oasis city.
Every street and avenue is lined by shady trees whose
roots bathe in omnipresent irrigation canals, a minor
pedestrian hazard until you get used to them. With Its
squares, parks and fountains, present-day Tashkent is
still on a human scale propituous for walking and talking.
Over shashllk or pilaf In a restaurant, drainage could be
discussed. On the balcony of a hotel room in the cool
desert night, an equation could be thrashed out. We even
saw people of four nationalities working in the shadow
of Tamerlane's tomb during a trip to Samarkand.
Men and women who had been faces behind printed
namecards became real with the help of generous Uzbek
hospitality. The mixtures with the experiences of two
dozen countries as its ingredients, began to bubble.
A very wise gentlemen, Prof. Alexel Silln-Bekchurin,
told me: "I think that the outstanding feature of our
symposium is that it ls being held in the desert where
irrigation and its problems are a reality."
They were able to contribute three decades and more
of experience in Central Asia to the symposium. One
such veteran at Tashkent was Dr. Boris (Dlmetreyevitch)
Korjavln, director of irrigation and reclamation planning
for Central Asia. This canal builder ls a weathered oak
of a man with a gleaming, smooth-shaven head rooted to
a powerful neck, and a face seamed by a ready smile. He
could tell of changes: when he came to Tashkent in 1925,
occasional camel caravans still passed through the city.
"Irrigation was easier then, too", he said almost wist¬
fully. "We still had plenty of good land without any
salinization problems."
In those days, the problem was machinery. Canals were
dug by hand and Dr. Korjavin recalled how the Great Fer-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
SALT OF THE EARTH (Cont'd)
The Indus river in a computing
ghana Canal of Uzbekistan was opened In 1939 in a
fantastic plck-and-shovel Olympic: 160,000 men dug 320
kilometres of canal In 45 days, moving 18,000,000 cubic
metres of earth. "Two years ago", he commented, "we
had to widen the canal to double its capacity. We didn't
move a single cubic metre of earth by hand."
Women have had a hand in this work as well.
Soviet women scientists can be startling at
least, I was startled when I learned that a quiet lady
in a cool print suit and a summer hat had spent fifteen
years of her life trekking through the deserts of Turkme¬
nistan, Uzbekistan and Kazakhstan. Prof. Helene Lobova
of the Soil Institute in Moscow crossed them first by
horse and then by car.
"I chose the career of soil scientist because I wanted to
visit the Orient", she admitted. "But I quickly found that
this science is bound up with the relation between man
and nature. The nature of the soil can explain many things
in the life of a people and scientists can often learn from
the people of the desert. Farmers in Central Asia have
always used sand from old walls to improve the texture
of takyrthe clay-like mosaic soil found in some of our
deserts. Today, we know that the only way to change the
texture of this soil is to add sand to it, but on a much
larger scale."
Conditions have changed for scientists in Central Asia.
When Dr. Vladimir (Mlkhallovltch) Borovsky came to
Khazakhstan in 1934, soil samples still had to be sent to
Moscow or Leningrad for analysis, but he is now vice-
director of the Soil Institute of Khazakhstan at Alma Ata
where 250 scientific collaborators are working with him.
His home was originally in Leningrad, "the best town in
the whole country and not just because it's my town" yet
his life to-day in Alma Ata is a full one composed of work,
music, walking for relaxation (20 miles on a Sunday) and
scientific writing.
He ls a warm, stocky man with blue eyes, grey hair, a
gentle manner and that purely Russian gift for smiling
broadly while smoking a cigarette (that is, while clenching
the cardboard tube of a papyroska between his teeth). Over
a glass of tangerine soda at a little oasis of a stand out¬
side the symposium, he told me that he believed in world
co-operation by scientists to fight what he called "a war
on salinization." In this respect, he has high hop'es
for an International manual on irrigation and drainage
sponsored by Unesco and the U.N. Food and Agriculture
Organization. "People all over the world are working on
this problem," he said. "This manual will enable us to
learn their ideas and contribute our own."
,uch an exchange took place at the scientific
'caravanserai of the symposium, particularly
with the help of mathematics as an international tongue
to topple hurdles of language and nationality. In this
respect, extreme interest was stirred by Prof. Harold A.
Thomas Jr. of Harvard University when he described the
use of a digital computer to study the feasibility of using
tubewells to drain the waterlogged Indus Plain in West
Pakistan.
Prof. Thomas is a slight, bespectacled man of fifty with
a boyish aspect that belies his age. He was almost
dwarfed by the rostrum as he reported on a United States
project to aid Pakistan in combatting widespread sali¬
nization afflicting this region.
In this project, a mathematical model of the Indus
Plain was constructed at Harvard University, incorpor-
16 ating such data as river flow, rainfall, drainage, ground
water flow as well as economic factors on the basis of
available information. As a result, a fifty-year cycle of
the Indus could be run through a digital computer in two
minutes, and scientists were able to choose the best of
100,000 possible solutions to the problem. The mathem¬
atical model showed that tubewells could be used to drain
the plain and that the area drained by each could be
nearly tripled, resulting in a huge cut in reclamation costs.
"At home, we like to say that the Punjab's five-fanged
river is now flowing dry at Cambridge in the Harvard
computer", Prof. Thomas told me. "We expect very
shortly that a river will flow in a Tashkent computer."
Dr. Vassil Kabulov, vice-director of the Uzbekistan
Institute of Mathematics, reported that Soviet mathemat¬
icians are now using computers to forecast ground water
regimes, to estimate seepage from reservoirs and canals
and solve other irrigation problems. He was one of fifty
scientists who met with Prof. Thomas in an informal
shirt-sleeved working party on computers organized on
the spur of the moment. There, Prof. Thomas turned
over his data and received more he now intends to use
the research on cotton irrigation carried out by Dr. S.N.
Ryzhov of Tashkent State University as an additional
element in his computer studies.
¡ rvE-AND-TAKE ran through this entire sympo¬
sium like a bright thread, representing what
Prof. N.A. Kenessarin, vice-director of the Institute of
Hydrogeology of the Uzbekistan Academy of Science,
called the "eagerness" of all nations to advance research
for the benefit of arid lands.
On and off the symposium floor, the channels of
communication were open. Dr. Leopold was able to help
Dr. S. P. Raychaudhuri, of the Indian Planning Commis¬
sion in New Delhi, on a common problem: what to do
when, silted river channels rise to the point where they
hinder drainage. In turn, at Tashkent the Indian scientist
was asked for details of his own studies on the movement
of chemical nutrients from rocks through clay to plants.
The need for such channels was strikingly brought out
when Prof. Abdul Rassool Kamaliddin, director of the
Arid Zone Research Institute at the University of Bagh¬
dad, met Dr. V. R. Volobuev of the Azerbaijan Institute
of Soil Science and Agricultural Chemistry. They learned
that, working separately in Iraq and the Soviet Union,
they had arrived at almost the same equation to govern
the flushing out of mineral salts from the soil.
This free interchange was stressed at the close of the
symposium by Dr. Victor A. Kovda, former head of the
Salinity Laboratory of the Soil Institute in Moscow and
now director of Unesco's Department of Natural Sciences.
It brought out, he said, that highly-salinized waters (up
to 6-8 gr/1) can be safely used for irrigation purposes
under conditions of active drainage.
It also brought out that the problem of forecasting and
controlling de-sallnization can be solved only by an
integration of all methods, he declared, and the electronic
computer is an invaluable tool for such an integration.
But it is not a panacea.
"The use of computers", Dr. Kovda warned, "depends
upon their programming and this programming requires
extremely detailed knowledge of natural processes. In
other words, the use of computers to solve irrigation
problems means even deeper research into nature".
Then Dr. Kovda summarized the spirit of the Tashkent
symposium as well as its scientific lessons when he
concluded :
"We are all working with ground water, a hidden ocean
beneath the surface of the earth. Our meeting has shown
that this ocean links the scientists who are trying to
extract its. secrets."
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
tri* .' i ? * .«' '-
r
SAMARKAND
FA
E
BU LOU
Milos Hrbas. Prague
Capped with a bright, blue-green tiled cupola, the Gur Emir (above) is one
of the most striking monuments of Samarkand, an ancient city renowned for
the beauty of its 14th and 15th century architectural and decorative treasures.
Tamerlane and one of his grandsons, Ulug Beg, are buried within. Tamerlane's
tomb was opened for the first time in 1941 and examination of his skeleton proved
that, as it had been told, he was lame.
It was to Timur (the iame Timur) commonly known as Tamerlane whose
empire finally spread from northern India to Asia Minor, that Samarkand, capital
of the kingdom of Transoxiana owed its legendary splendour. For Tamerlane,
whose ruthless cruelty became a black legend recounted down the centuries,
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
4
I- *V*" jUlÍ* í" '1 »V - -Ö 1-" '"""
J|«b| ^$$ -Ir1
J , . ' ¿ ; Pv
i';tó¿IA ' r-i
SAMARKAND
(Cont'd)
18
and who devastated entire regions during his 35-year reign (1370-1405), embellished
his capital with care and affection.
His son, Shah Rukh and his grandson, Ulug Beg, as pacific as he himself
had been warlike, in their turn made Samarkand a brilliant centre of Persian
culture. It was already a very ancient city for its name first appears in accounts
of Alexander the Great's expeditions. After the Islamic conquest it became
a metropolis famous for its gardens, canals and fountains. It was well-known
as a centre of paper-making. In 1220 A.D. it was sacked by Ghengis Khan.
Ulug Beg, a patron of science and the arts, was passionately interested in
astronomy and built an observatory on a hilltop, close to his capital. His mea¬
surements of the astronomical year made in the 15th century are said to differ only
by one minute from the calculations made four centuries later.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Intricately carved designs (above)
decorate walls of mausoleums out¬
side Samarkand, burial place of
Tamerlane's family. Tiles are col¬
oured yellow, lilac and turquoise.
Immense tiled walls of the Babikha-
nim Mosque, erected in 1388 by
a Chinese wife of Tamerlane, tower
above the streets and colourful
bustling bazaar of Samarkand.
Photos Milos Hrbas, Prague
Ruined towers of Tamerlane's pal¬
ace in Samarkand still testify
to the city's former magnificence.
After 1 369, Tamerlane and his suc¬
cessors enlarged and beautified it
The kingdom of Khiva once held the keys of the mighty Oxus River (Amu
Darya) in Central Asia. Changes In river's course have brought desert condi¬
tions. The palace of the Khan (below) recalls Its capital's ancient glories.
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
American director Joseph Mankiewicz. (20th Cent. Fox) Chariot race scene from the film "Ben Hur". (MGM)
THE HIDDEN FACE
il
THE CINEMA
20
With this issue, The Unesco Courier begins the exclusive
publication of a series of articles on some of the lesser-
known aspects of the cinema industry, based on a world
survey undertaken by Paul Léglise. M. Léglise takes us on
a voyage into the hidden problems of production, distri¬
bution and financing of feature and documentary films of
all kinds, including the impact of TV on the film industry.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
From the WHO "film "To Your Health". (WHO photo) Japanese actresses at Tokyo Film Festival (< Almasy)
LONG queues winding down the streets outside
the box office ; a mystifying or suggestive
title at the entrance to draw in the crowds ; a famous
star's name or photograph haloed in a blaze of lights ;
a torrent of publicity pouring forth the star's dally
adventures reaU embellished or Imaginary. Rain or
shine, the queue waits patiently to pass Inside for two
or three hours on an evening or a weekend. This, for
the great majority of the general public, ls the stereo¬
typed façade of the cinema.
Yet behind the façade sits the cinema manager adding
up his takings. He sees his customers fleeing the bustle
of the city on their days off. He knows the T.V. pro¬
grammes will keep other old "faithfuls" at home tonight.
He is delighted of course with his Sunday week-end
crowds, but the week ls aLso made up of working days,
and his empty seats cannot be seen by the passerby in
the street outside. Besides, all cinemas arc not located
on the Champs-Elysées, in Piccadilly, near the Via
Véneto or on Broadway.
Not so long ago, various pundits rase to voice alarm
at the effects of the cinema and lost no time brandishing
interdictions and the cutting scissors. Then along came
the public finance experts who set about estimating what
cinema taxes could be levied on the thousands eager for
entertainment.
Fortunately the detractors of the cinema have come
to a better understanding of the positive contributions
the cinema can make, and now realize that a new
approach Ls needed in order to promote the production
of films specially suited for young people. This trend ls
also reflected In the new attitude of government finance
officials who now recognize the economic and cultural
Importance of the cinema for their countries, and are
gradually lowering the barriers raised by their prede¬
cessors against the free circulation of films. Today we
find the State giving its financial help to promote the
development of national film Industries.
The man who Ls the qualified Intermediary between
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
The new undocile
the cinema and the public Is the manager of the cinema
theatre. Although he is only one part of the cinema world
everyone in the huge industry watches the rise and fall
of his box-office takings. For regardless of the form of
social or economic system the cinema operates under,
money remains the arbiter of film subject matter. A film
must please those who finance it and who decide what
they think is the public's taste. But it must also please
the audience itself, the real cinema audience, that is.
Once the most docile of creatures, the cinema public is
changing and Is showing increasing discrimination in the
type of films it is willing to accept. With the help of a
new type of film critic who is both lively and hard-hitting,
with the emergence of film clubs which foster a deeper
understanding of the cinema as an art, the passive
audience is being transformed into devotees of the film
"cinéphiles". People now go to the cinema to see the
work of a particular director, and actually follow the
trends of different "schools" of film makers. The cine¬
ma in fact ls becoming a more difficult profession to work
in and thereby Infinitely more exciting and rewarding.
Furthermore, the cinema ls no longer confined to the
public theatre. We now find It in the school, in the factory,
in fairgrounds, exhibitions, hospitals, museums, and many
other hitherto unsuspected places. We find it in the
Isolated village of the African bush, and In meetings of
specialists and great scientists. It is a working and
research Instrument for education, science and culture
where it has proved its value in every corner of the globe.
In the conception, production and distribution of a film
a whole series of complicated operations are involved.
Artistic values, cultural factors, economic considerations,
technical principies and industrial requirements all
overlap and clash. This makes the behind-the-scenes
life of the cinema no less fascinating than the flurry of
its outer bustle, superficial, artificial and publicity-
inspired as it so often is. Besides, the one explains the
other.
Let us try to penetrate behind the halo of
mystery which often prevents the general
public from grasping the fundamental problems of the
great film Industry. The film enthusiast may perhaps
regret that there will be no examination here of the
films of a Hitchcock, René Clair, Antonioni, Chukhrai,
Satyajit Ray, Kurosawa, Norman McLaren or Jiri Trnka.
But we shall not have much occasion to mention their
works except to indicate their production costs or box-
office takings.
Some readers may be disappointed too to find no
description of the studios and the actors at work or an
explanation of how the camera can express an idea or
feeling.
Our purpose, however, is to demonstrate to those inte¬
rested in the cinema that it is equally important to know
the underlying factors that regulate the production and
distribution of films. Here too the role of the cinema
devotee could be as decisive as it has been up to now in
moulding public taste.
Let us not forget that the economic and organizational
problems confronting the cinema today bear within
them the seeds of the great renewal of tomorrow and that
this depends on how these problems are ultimately
solved.
A Brigitte Bardot film and an industrial film on the
manufacture of steel are exactly the same when we look
at them in terms of the general techniques of film pro¬
duction. Where they differ is in the number of persons
employed, the means and capital engaged, and the
methods of production used.
It takes more than a camera and a few reels of film
to make a film. There must first be the nucleus of a
scenario, a "synopsis"; or at least an idea. Sometimes
the producer buys a title. It may be the title of a popular
song or the title of a book. One French producer once
22 bought the title (and nothing more than the title) of
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
MGM
SYNTHESIS OF ART
AND INDUSTRY
Towering backdrops, an army of "extras",
powerful arc-lights, batteries of cameras and
sound recording equipment, engineers, elec¬
tricians, carpenters, painters all under the
command of a producer are the character¬
istics of a "superproduction" like the one
being shot here. In a production of such
mammoth proportions even a sequence
lasting only a matter of minutes in the finished
film may cost several hundred thousand dol¬
lars. Skill and talent sometimes earn success
for far more modest productions. One recent
example is the Japanese production, "The
Island" in which Kaneto Shinto tells the day-
to-day life story of two peasant farmers on
an island (right) who have to transport every
drop of water for their field from the far-off
mainland. The story is told without words. The
film cost only $33,000 to produce, but has
already earned more than $110,000 abroad.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Kindai Ei|a K/okai, Cocinor-Marccau Filmi
> N, i
«^
s^g*
0 t* .*
V^Sj*^* -¿-- ' «
OBSf
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
A full day's work: 2 minutes of finished film
a famous detective novel series for 600,000 francs ($1,200).
The scenario comes later, depending on the director and
the cast.
The producer then roughs out his plan of production
costs while the scenario writer and director work out a
shooting script. This is a kind of analytical blueprint of
the whole operation. It enumerates all the camera shots
(close-ups, medium and long shots), the timing and
camera movements (tracking and panning) and details
of direction (set arrangements, actors moves, the posi¬
tion of people and objects on the sets, etc.) as well as
the commentary or dialogue.
At this point the literary aspect of the cinema ends
and the technical side of production begins, while the
financial side of production continues for it starts
from the moment that the idea for the film has been
accepted.
Several days in the studio under powerful arc lights,
or on exterior location depending on the whims of the
sun, require the hiring of teams of technicians which
vary in their multitude according to the size of the pro¬
duction (the director, cameraman, continuity girl^ sound
engineer, set designer, make-up man, etc... and their
assistants) to say nothing of the cast (stars, other actors
and extras, etc.)
There are too many people Involved in the production
of a film to list them all. Great Britain regularly employs
4,000 persons in the production of feature films alone,
and it ls estimated that 25,000 to 35,000 persons work in
film production in the U.S.A. The Japanese film industry
lists 120,000 employees, 18,000 for the production and
distribution of feature films, 82,000 for film exhibition.
But are these figures complete? Are extras and other
persons called upon included? Music in a film for ins¬
tance means a composer, an orchestra, a recording studio
staff. Do they always figure in these statistics?
Every sequence shot is printed on negative film, with
very often several prints of some takes. In France, a full
day's work produces an average of two minutes of the
final film. The film is then developed and printed on
positive film preferably in well-equipped laboratories as
near the studios as possible. After this comes the editing,
the mixing of image and sound, optical effects for
transitions between shots (known as wipes, fade-ins, fade-
outs, and dissolves, etc.) then titling, the making of dupli¬
cate negatives, and the running off of the final positive
prints... Annual footage processed in French laboratories
for instance amounts to 72 million metres.
So we see that to call film-making an industry is no
idle use of the word. Before even the smallest of films
can be envisaged all the financial and technical require¬
ments of a big industry come into play. That is why
24
*ÜSí
r~iU<!-r<ci
Quite apart from their basic aim which is to encourage the public to buy someone's
products, publicity films occupy a special place in the film world. They offer young
producers the opportunity to display creative originality. Some of them are minor
masterpieces of the film-maker's art. Through application to publicity films animated
cartoons have, in particular, found ways to perfect techniques and discover new ones.
Cinéma et Publicité, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
CINEMASCOPE
INVENTOR'S
NOTEBOOK
The film industry has reacted to the
prodigious growth of television by
a vigorous search for innovations.
One of the most far-reaching de¬
cisions, designed to retain public
patronage of the cinema, has been
the introduction of wide screen
projections. This opened the
way, in 1953, to the development
of a technique invented years
earlier by a Frenchman, Henri
Chrétien. The result was the
birth of Cinemascope. Reprodu¬
ced on the right is a page from
the notebook of Professor Chré¬
tien, inventor of the Cinemascope
lens and camera, with the follow¬
ing annotations.
I.Shot taken with a normal ca¬
mera.
II.Shot taken from the same
point with the same camera and
lens, but now fitted with a Hyper-
gonar: the shot is distorted hori¬
zontally and the breadth of the
field of vision is doubled.
III.Previous shot projected by
a normal projection apparatus
fitted with Hypergonar which has
restored all objects to their true
proportions.
,.t -u. t <f{ " y
'flu. 'Jlua it- kt*A A«*¿ 4**fi-^Ä *'*" ''" d
íucum' ifyíUf, »tsUê i**iL (U. S'Hy/.aj'h'*: *
d*M ¿W^«^, ö&s* zU diùitL *
20lh Century fox
another important person in film-makingthe ever-
present, formidable film producer keeps his eye on
production from the first moment to the last. It is he
who fixes the budget of the film and sees that It ls
adhered to. The budget is based on the film's profitability,
or returns, that is, on the estimated money it will bring
In. The budget commands the greatest respect, for even
in the world of the cinema a Maecenas is a rare bird.
In fact its real Maecenas is the public, twelve thousand
million patrons each year in more than 175,000 cinemas
around the world ; and this does not include what the
trade calls non-theatrical (that ls, non-commercial)
showings which would triple or quadruple the figures.
It is no easy matter therefore to forecast what the public
interest will be. What is more, each film has its own
public. There are not many films like Gone With the
Wind which had an audience of 70 million spectators. And
yet it is the overall returns of an average film which
condition the budget of a new film.
The financing of films is dealt with by each country
in its own way. Without going into details of the mecha¬
nics of financing, the problem in the Socialist economies
and in the major American companies is relatively simple.
In both cases the anticipated returns of a new film are
estimated and the financial risks spread over several
films. The budget is then fixed and the required funds
are drawn upon as needed.
In a Socialist economy film organizations operate like
a government ministry possessing a special budget for
the production of educational and Information films.
They order a film on a particular subject, grant the appro¬
priate budget, have the film made and control every phase
of its execution. Profitability is assessed not for each film
individually but on the basis of the total returns of all
national and foreign-made films shown in the country.
With the major American films financing is more
speculative. Backing ls usually assured by commercial
banks or large industrial concerns. In turn the leading
film companies themselves (which control production,
distribution and cinema circuits) Invest most of their
capital outside the film industry.
Thus in both systems the risks are greatly diminished
by being widely spread. Future film production in both
cases depends more on the graph of national cinema
attendance generally than on the success of their own
films.
When an independent company decides to launch Into
film production, the problems of financing arc a matter
of much graver complexity. The risks involved are infi¬
nitely more serious since any single set-back, like the
Illness or death of the leading players or of the director
In the middle of shooting, or the public's cool reception
to the film once It Is released, can spell complete disaster.
Some of these risks, such as accidents, illness, bad
weather, the loss of film by fire, are of course covered by
Insurance ; and insurance companies often allow pre¬
miums to be paid after the release date of the film. Des¬
pite this, an independent company has to be prepared for
heavy expenses and must find the needed credit.
In France, for example, the 1951 total Investment in
the different branches of the film industry amounted
to 3.5 thousand million Francs (over $7 million) for a
production total valued at about 5 thousand million
Francs (over .* 10 million). This investment represented
66 per cent of the value of France's total film production
for the year, and was a national record for all industries
(the steel industry came second with only 37%.)
Where does this backing come from? First, there are
the contributions by the producer, then from private
sources, and loans from banks. Some banks specialize in 25
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
Low-cost films vs. de luxe superproductions
film-financing loans. In Italy, for Instance, an indepen¬
dent branch of the Banca Nazionale del Lavoro finances
up to 60% of production costs, and in Brazil the Bank of
the State of Sao Paulo grants credit of up to three million
cruzeiros upon presentation of an early-stage "cutting-
print" of a film costing on an average 5 to 7 million
cruzeiros.
Other sources of financing backing are the large
developing and printing laboratories as well as techni¬
cians, artists and film distributors and exporters. Note
should be taken of the important role played by the
distributor In financing film production, either by ad¬
vancing credit against future box-office takings or by
covering the cost of general release prints and advance
publicity. The conditions laid down by the distributor
for the leasing and exhibition of a film will vary according
to the degree of his financial participation in production.
The State too finances the production of private films,
and this is now becoming an increasingly frequent
practice. Apart from the subsidies and loans accorded
for the making of cultural films (particularly documen¬
taries) there is a growing tendency on the part of the
State to use the proceeds of special taxes on cinema
tickets, and levies on the footage of films being shown in
cinemas, to give financial support to films it wishes to
promote, and thus mould public taste.
This is now being done in Denmark, Portugal, Egypt,
Argentina, France, Italy, Brazil, Greece and other coun¬
tries. The funds are used for the granting of subsidies,
loans and advances on box-office takings, or for the
awarding of big prizes for completed or projected films
which by virtue of their quality or the ideals they espouse
do honour to the nation's cinematographic output.
When people refer to the film-producing countries they
generally have in mind full-length or feature films,
Regrettable or not, let us follow this custom.
The number of 35 mm. feature films produced each
year throughout the world for public screening runs to
about 3,000. No exact figure can be given since tabu¬
lating methods vary widely from country to country. In
the United Kingdom for example, a feature film must be
over 3,000 feet In length, while in Italy it cannot be less
than 6,500 feet.
Consequently, the national figures given below should
be interpreted with caution, particularly since there is
often no way of telling if certain co-productions have
been counted twice in two different countries. The
figures used here will be those provided by the Interna¬
tional Federation of Film Producers (1959 figures).
siA leads the other continents with 1,580 films
i produced annually, or more than half the
total world cinema production. Japan (493 films), India
(310) and Hong Kong (240) are the world's three largest
producers. These are followed in Asia by South Korea
(109) and mainland China (80). Burma, Thailand and the
Philippines each produce about 50 films a year.
The United States occupies fourth place in the world
with 187 films, or half of the total annual production in
the Americas: Mexico (84), Brazil (40), Argentina (23).
Europe produces 950 films a year: Italy (167), France
(133), U.S.S.R. (about 130), Great Britain (123), Federal
Republic of Germany (106), Turkey (60), Czechoslovakia
(35), Eastern Germany (27).
Sixty films are produced in Africa, 50 in the United
Arab Republic alone. If most people are aware of the
world-wide distribution of American films, it is not
always realized that the cinema of Asia too is a thriving,
dynamic industry which reaches wide audiences.
Although the bulk of its production is geared to meet
the tastes, customs and culture of the people of Asia,
Japanese films have been enthusiastically received in
Europe, and Indian films are finding a growing public
in African countries.
How can we explain the amazing development of film
26 production in Japan? In their book, Le Cinéma Japo¬
nais, Shinobu and Marcel Giuglaris tell us that "The
film industry is designed to make money and is not pro
tected by the State. Five large film corporations each
possess their own studios and production equipment, their
own financing methods and distribution chains, their
own cinema theatres, stars and technicians. A sixth
large group specializes in films for export.
Each of the first five groups produced a film a week in
1955 at the modest cost of 18 to 25 million yen ($50,000 -
$70,000) and made a return of 50 to 70 million yen ($150-
200,000) within a month from national receipts alone.
Thus, according to Giuglaris, one month's production time
and only one month's exhibition brought the producer,
after deduction of all expenses and exploitation costs,
a net profit of over 100%.
The low production cost of Japanese films is explained
by the fact that the actors are not paid astronomical
salaries, that there are no trade union rules decreeing
a minimum number of technicians per film, and that long
sequences with fixed cameras are a standard technique,
thereby greatly reducing the number of shots.
I n addition to these films made for home con-
I sumption, there are those made for foreign
screening which, especially since the success of Rashomon
are allocated a higher budget, though Rashomon "itself
was made for only 15 million yen.
If we remember finally that there are 7,400 cinemas
in Japan 66% of which show nothing but Japanese films
with a seating capacity for over 3 milion people, and
that more than 1,000 million spectators attended the
cinema in 1959, then is not difficult to understand the
enthusiasm of this nation for moving pictures and the
development of the Japanese film industry to meet it.
The United States offers a well-known example of the
concentrated importance of a film industry under a free
economy. Eight major corporations dominate the film
business. They release 60 to 70 per cent of the total
volume of feature films produced, and through their their
own distribution and exhibition outlets account for up to
85 to 90 per cent of America's gross box-office receipts.
In addition, their Influence extends abroad where their
subsidiaries or affiliated companies often enjoy a predo¬
minant position with regard to distribution and film
booking. As the French economist, Professor Henri Mer-
cillon has written: "Hollywood has taken over the field
of entertainment for a whole sector of the world."
Alongside a host of "B-pictures" made at medium cost,
Hollywood turns out a substantial number of high-budget
films which follow certain aesthetic standards that
flatter the public's taste. Such films feature big-name
stars and are released with an advertising build-up
commensurate with their cost. The de-luxe superproduc¬
tions call for gigantic installations and organization, and
it would seem could only be filmed by or in Hollywood.
Yet now a drive is being made to outdo Hollywood and
the Cecil B. de Mille technique by Italy's Cinecitta studios
outside Rome which are churning out elaborate spectacles
based on a formula of mythology and ancient history.
With its superproductions, America at any rate has hit
the box-office jackpot on the world's markets.
Thus though their production techniques are funda¬
mentally different, both Japan and the United States
are the world's leading film countries. It is interesting
to note, however, that both industries are characterized
by a high degree of concentration of their economic
structures.
In other free economy countries, and for that matter
in Japan and the United States as well, one finds a wide
variety of film producing companies in existence. These
range from the individual craftsman who produces and
directs his own films to the giant industrial complexes
with their multifold technical, commercial and adminis¬
trative services.
To attempt, under these circumstances, to record the
number of film companies operating In the world, or
even by country, becomes a statistician's nightmare. The
diversity of companies in terms of capital, staff, volume
and type of production, access to national and foreign
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Photo» i*) Alma*/, Parí»
BOUNTIFUL JOURNALISTS
A three-masted sailing vessel spe¬
cially built for a new version of
the American film, "Mutiny on the
Bounty" sets out across the waters
of the English Channel with 80 jour¬
nalists and photographers on board
(see photos). The launching of a
feature-length film is usually the
occasion for a vast publicity cam¬
paign. In the case of de-luxe super-
productions the need for a rapid
turnover of the huge amounts of
capital involved leads to campaigns
being started while the film is still
under production. The budget for
publicity can run to as much as
7% of the total production costs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Photo United Artists - Cahiers du Cinéma
SUSPENDED
ANIMATION
The Soviet film, "An Unsent Letter",
which recounts the adventures of a
group of geologists in the Siberian
"taiga", is distinguished by the remark¬
able shots of cameraman Sergei
Uroussevsky, a technician who seeks
always to work in real-life surround¬
ings. On right he is seen suspended
with his camera above the ice-floes
of a swirling river. Left, operating on
an indoor film set, the camera poised
on the end of a massive "boom"
follows the actors up a stairway, in
John Huston's film "Moulin Rouge".
CINEMA (Cont'd)
Pioneer role of independent companies
28
markets, makes it well nigh impossible to lay down any
common yardstick.
Furthermore, certain countries have special regulations
governing the establishment of film companies. In Italy
a company cannot be set up for co-production operation
if its capital fund is under 30 million lire. In France a
professional licence is required which is denied persons
with a police record or firms of limited capital (less than
$10,000 for the production of feature films; and less
than $2,000 for short films). Records show that in 1961,
as many as 617 feature film companies were in existence
in France and 960 short film companies, but the output
figures show only 145 feature films and 326 short films
actually produced during the year. Thus it. is quite
obvious that the number of really active producing
companies is much smaller than the impressive official
list would imply.
The situation is no different in other countries. Even
in the United States, the example par excellence of film
concentration in the hands of a few corporations, the
figures show 181 producing companies. These may be
accounted for by the fact that certain firms having once
produced a film under more or less accidental circum¬
stances retain the title of film-producer as ornaments
on their commercial letter-heads.
In fairness, however, it should be added that many
companies specialize in educational, technical and in¬
dustrial films, or in 16 mm. production, two and three
minute advertizing films as well as films for T.V. This
output represents a marginal fringe of the main cinema
industry, and official production statistics do not normally
Include them in their figures. Nevertheless it is a dyn¬
amic, bustling branch of the film industry the importance
of which ls rarely suspected because of its complex
operations.
To get back to feature films produced for commercial
circuits, a further word should be said about the many
independent producers and their stimulating effect on
the industry. In fact, if the cinema is constantly being
enriched as a form of art and entertainment in various
countries (and indeed on the world market generally)
much of the credit is due to the push and competition
created by the independent film companies. In their
efforts to establish a reputation, the enterprising in¬
dependents have not hesitated to break with the trad¬
itional approach of the big film corporations and have
pioneered new forms of cinema expression.
In the Socialist economy countries nationalization of
the film industry is the rule, production being planned
and financed by a ministerial department. Apart from
the director, all production technicians are attached to
a given studio and receive regular salaries.
In Poland, the Barrandow studios alone employ 1,800
persons regularly, while In Czechoslovakia at least, all
actors are hired for a specific film. In Yugoslavia,
persons engaged on the creative side of film making were
formerly employed on a regular salary basis, but in 1951
film production was decentralized and a new basis of
worker-management adopted, leading to an Increase in
the number of film producing companies in the country.
As a result film directors and other creative personnel
have been recognized as members of the liberal profession
with the right to sign separate contracts with film
companies. But most technical and administrative per¬
sonnel remain on permanent contract to a given
company.
Up to now we have been dealing only with feature films,
but if we were to consider the footage processed in all
the world's film laboratories, separating feature film foot¬
age from all other types (excluding amateur and TV
footage) the figure would certainly be startling and
prompt us to want to revise our current methods of tabul¬
ating world film production.
The plain fact is that present world statistics do ill
justice to the short film. Admittedly, there is no
universally accepted definition of how short a short film
should be. Finland says less than 2,000 feet, the U.K 3,000,
France 4,250, Portugal 5,900 and Italy less than 6,500 feet.
But it would be a serious mistake to underestimate the
continued growth and expansion of the short film, its
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
PholO Soviet ierren
richness as a medium of expression, and the important
place it occupies in the world today. A very conservative
estimate of the total number of short films produced each
year gives us a figure running into several scores of
thousands!
The short film is not often made by the large feature
film companies; it is usually left to the small, artisan-
type producer since it involves a much smaller expend¬
iture. For example, the average short film made in France
in 1961 cost 51,000 New Francs ($10,000) as compared with
1,370,000 Francs ($275,000) for the average feature film.
But unless it is subsidized the chances of a short film
recovering its production costs are much slimmer than
for the more expensive feature film. Even those films
produced for commercial cinema showing are very rarely
aimed exclusively at this market, except for featurettes
of the "curtain raiser" type such as short comedies or
dramas, or light variety shorts and musical briefs, or
documentaries considered to be of broad general interest.
Just as often they are aimed at the non-commercial
market, assuming they were not originally produced
chiefly for non-commercial distribution. Of course, certain
types of short films, like the technical, scientific and
educational films, never aim at anything but a non¬
commercial screening, and some are even produced only
in 16 mm.
When a short entertainment film is commissioned by
public or private backers who are not primarily interested
in getting their money back there is no real problem; but
there is a serious problem when we turn to the short
experimental film, independently produced. Here financ¬
ial backing is much more difficult to come by since such
films do not find a ready market. The experimental film
is thus in danger of disappearing for lack of financial
support or exploitation possibilities.
Luckily, many governments are showing concern for
this problem and are taking steps to remedy the situation.
The production and distribution of such films are being
encouraged by the offer of subsidies, loans, special film
prizes and tax concessions; in certain countries the double
feature has been completely banned, and cinemas are
required to include short films in all programmes.
We should not forget that short films, be they docum¬
entaries, animated cartoons or featurettes, offer the film
world unusual scope for creative originality, and that It
Is from this branch of the industry that the great film
makers of tomorrow arc likely to come. Like the full-
length feature, the short film too now boasts its own
"schools" and outstanding directors whose masterpieces
are in no way inferior to the feature film classics.
The special problems confronting short film production
have been recognized not only in the free-economy count¬
ries but in the Socialist States where significant measures
have been adopted to encourage new films. Thus In
Czechoslovakia while 80 per cent of the short films
produced are State-ordered, the remaining 20 per cent
are made up of freely-produced films proposed by art
councils set up In Czech studios.
Of the many types of short films turned out annually
for non-commercial use. the educational film ls finding
an increasingly important market. Educational films arc
often produced directly by government bodies or else are
commissioned and financed by the State. The French
Centre audio-visuel de l'Ecole normale supérieure de
Saint-Cloud, near Paris, exclusively devoted to films for
schools, is an interesting example. It undertakes comp¬
arative studies of audio-visual techniques in classrooms,
advises film makers and directors as well as teachers,
organizes film seminars, and produces its own experi¬
mental films in its own studios. Most French educational
films, however, are privately produced though State
commissioned and supervised.
In certain countries all educational film production Is
in the hands of private enterprise and no State control
is exercised. This is true of the United States where
educational productions are made by the large film com¬
panies and by several independent organizations. The
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Confd)
30
Boom
in co-productions
unusual thing about these producers is that frequently
they are actually specialized branches of book publishing
firms. Textbooks, In fact, include references to films
which are specially adapted to or can appropriately be
used in conjunction with one chapter or another of the
textbooks in question. In Japan an Educational Film
Producer's Association groups 80 of the country's most
active companies, about a dozen of which account for
roughly one third of all educational and industrial film
production (approximately 200 school and adult education
films were produced In Japan in 1958).
In the past few years, however, there have been signs
of the government's growing interest in promoting better
educational films. Production and distribution remain
free of government control but an audio-visual education
section has been set up in the Japanese Ministry of Educ¬
ation to encourage the use of films in schools, and a
selection committee created to help teachers and adult
education leaders to choose appropriate films. In addi¬
tion, an annual educational film festival in Tokyo is spur¬
ring the production of better educational films.
Closely associated in certain ways with the educational
film are the various industrial films which play an im¬
portant part in professional training and are used in
"refresher" courses for executives and specialists in in¬
dustry. To cite the case of Japan again, of the 768 techni¬
cal films produced In 1958, 200 were concerned with
education proper while the majority of the remaining
568 dealt with industry.
HREE other types of specialized films, all highly
distinctive, deserve mentioning here: the
newsreel, the advertising film and the television film.
The newsreel is unique in that it appears at regular,
relatively brief intervals, and deals with various subjects
directly connected with current events. With the advent
of television, however, it is being forced to consider a
change of pace. Unable to compete with daily TV pro¬
grammes in presenting the spot news of the week as it
formerly did the cinema newsreel is rapidly tending to
become a kind of illustrated magazine featuring specific
events of the day in analytical capsule form.
The status accorded the newsreel varies from country
to country. In some it is entirely a private, commercial
affair (Argentina, Austria, Belgium, Colombia, Fed. Rep.
of Germany, France, Ireland, Israel, Italy, Japan, Nether¬
lands, Peru, U.K., Uruguay, etc.) ; in others it is regarded
as a public service or is nationalized (India, Norway, Por¬
tugal, Spain, the Socialist economy countries, etc.)
We shall not say much about the advertising film, which
is extensively used in fairs and exhibitions as well as in
public cinemas during intervals, except to point out that
many film people have made their cinema debut in this
branch of the industry and that it has proved a rich
medium of expression for the animated cartoon, and an
exceptionally good vehicle for perfecting and renovating
the style and technique of the animated cartoon generally.
As for television films, though broadly speaking both
TV films and films for the cinema use identical recording
techniques their production methods are radically differ¬
ent. TV films are rarely conceived as single units but
are usually produced (at least for commercial television)
as package programmes comprising 13 films for showing
over a 13 week period.
TV films require special adaptation of the frames to
the small television screen and also present particular
editing problems. Furthermore, in a TV film the per¬
formers act out their roles from beginning to end, follow¬
ing the script as in a play, unlike cinema actors who are
filmed in unconnected "takes". Nonetheless there is no
denying that cinema and television films.have much in
common..
Although TV companies often produce their own films
yet at the same time private film corporations are also
National Film Board of Canada
SCIENCE ON THE SCREEN. The National Film Board of
Canada has won international renown for the quality and scope
of its short film productions. Above, a shot from a film on the
subject of cancer. This drawing shows a multicellular growth.
Ministry of Information, New Delhi
THE METRIC SYSTEM. India has recently adopted the
metric system. To help explain this innovation to the man
in the street, an animated cartoon showing its uses was
produced in 1960 by the Government Films Division.
H Vz
Film Export, Prague
BIG HEADS FOR SMALL SCREENS. The tendancy to
exaggerate the size of the head in relation to the boby is a
feature of American cartooning, especially since the arrival of
television. The small TV screen calls for means to accentuate
character and expression. The figures under the drawings
(above) show the approximate head to boby proportions used by
artists who draw three well-known animated cartoon characters.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
CARTOONS
AND PUPPETS
FOR LAUGHS
OR LEARNING
The short film has known an
immense growth and expan¬
sion in all its forms during the
past 15 years. This has come
about not only to meet the
needs of television and publi¬
city, but also because of the
pressing demand for educa¬
tional films. The annual pro¬
duction of short films has been
conservatively estimated as
running into several scores of
thousands. As photos on these
pages demonstrate, animated
cartoons and puppets can be
used as effectively to teach
serious lessons of many kinds
as for light entertainment.
From "The Technique of rim Ann ll Pir«, I r.nrti.
DOLLS AND LEGENDS. The screen has brought fame to dolls used by
the Czech film-maker Jiri Trnka. Painter and illustrator of children's books,
Trnka was the producer of a Unesco film entitled "Fable for Friendship".
Above, a scene from one of Trnka's puppet films "The Song of the Prairie".
called in (in the free economy countries) to produce
others. This example of collaboration, at least as far as
specialized film production is concerned, is a hopeful sign
indeed, particularly since relations between the two
industries have not always been of the best.
In fact at the Tangiers Conference called by Unesco
in 1958 to further international co-operation between the
cinema and television industries one could not help not¬
ing the bitterness of the cinema people towards their
television "juniors". They complained that the fees paid
by TV stations for commissioned films were too low (relat¬
ively speaking that is) and that they could rarely cover
their production costs from TV broadcasting channels
alone.
In time solutions acceptable to both sides will certainly
be found. As it is, films produced by public or national¬
ized services are nowadays widely diffused through the
cinema and on TV. In the near future, co-productions
resulting from co-operation between these two media will
no doubt point the way to a new and profitable opening
for films.
In their search for greater profitability, feature film
producers are today being drawn increasingly to the solu¬
tion of international co-productions. The past already
offers good examples of this trend: Cavalcade which had
a marked effect on the distribution' of American films in
British cinemas and Henry VIII, which opened the door
to the American market for some major British films.
The formula offers obvious material benefits. Endowed
with dual nationality the co-production can skirt many
obstacles to film distribution in its "parent" countries.
Its financial advantage is that production costs are
shared.
Viewed in terms of international co-operation the
arrangement also has much to commend it. Professional
actors and film-makers of different nationalities apply
skill and effort to a common end. Technicians and
creative workers get to know each other better and this
in turn helps to stimulate better understanding between
the people of their countries.
The co-production method has nevertheless come in
for some sharp attacks from groups concerned with
preserving the integrity of national expression. Art, say
these critics, is an expression of national culture and
when two countries combine their artistic efforts in an
artifical alliance the result may be a hybrid product which
satisfies neither the ideas and feelings of the spectators
in the two natioas nor those of foreign audiences which
prefer films offering authentic cultural backgrounds that
differ from their own.
But criticism of this kind must not be pushed to absurd
lengths. For every strictly national topic that would be
unsuitable for co-production treatment, there arc many
others which deserve to be handled in thLs way.
How do co-production arrangements work in practice?
Many forms exist but the most common is based on an
equal reciprocity covering two films. Let us suppo.se that
the first of these films is a Franco-Italian production.
The French company will foot the major part of the
cost while the Italian partners will be required to find
not less then 30% of the total estimated outlay. French
technicians and actors will outnumber Italians. After
this film Is completed a counterpart Italo-Frcnch prod¬
uction will be made in which the proportions of the
financial, technical and artistic contributions will be
reversed.
Arrangements of this kind are usually covered by an
official inter-governmental co-production agreement such
as existed between France and Italy In the example just
given. The films produced benefit from privileges norm¬
ally reserved for nationally produced films In both
countries State financial aid, tax concessions, quota
privileges and other advantages designed to aid a national
film industry. A joint commission decides which films
qualify for these benefits before production begins and
also supervises the working of the agreement. In 1961,
83 feature films were co-produced by France and Italy
in this way.
In another and more simple type of co-production
usually outside the scope of official agreements foreign
capital is used to finance production, or alternatively,
foreign technicians and actors participate in a film pro¬
duced with local capital.
In such cases the film does not always benefit from a
dual nationality status. The resulting loss of privileges
may in some measure be compensated for by a more
profitable distribution of the film In the country which
provided the technicians and cast.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
CINEMA (Cont'd)
Films for schools of all nations
Nowadays there Is a much greater use of foreign cap¬
ital for film production because of increased restrictions
on the export of film-showing -receipts. Large amounts
of capital earned by foreign films are now "frozen" in
some countries. Unable to export their profits, foreign
producers have been using them to finance co-productions
locally. Countries where this happens benefit in two
ways: films made with "frozen" funds often provide
employment for local labour and technical staffs, and the
films themselves are likely to have a wider distribution
abroad through the participation of a foreign co-producer.
Co-productions of this type have nevertheless disturb¬
ed the technicians' trade unions. In the United States
the problem of what the American trade journal Variety
has called "runaway" film production has attracted
much attention. The question has been raised and
discussed by the Labour Commission of the House of
Representatives. U.S. trade unions affirm that 509 films
made between January 1949 and November 1961 were
financed from U.S. sources.
Turning to educational films we find that co-production
has been tried out experimentally on quite a large scale
although on very different lines from those already
described. The overall problem here ls obviously not the
same. Basically each country tries to produce a number
of educational films corresponding to the needs and
content of its school programmes. Through consulations
and exchange of information between the various na¬
tional educational film services, a wasteful duplication of
effort such as the possibility of several countries produc¬
ing a film on exactly the same subject is avoided. Inter¬
national co-operation in this connexion benefits all
concerned.
Joint agreements sometimes lead to the production of
a series of films (physical and general geography and the
history of science have been three examples) each film
being made by a different country. Eventually each
producer country supplies to the other partners in the
project the material needed for making prints of its film,
free of all dues and charges. Thus each country receives
several films for the cost of one production.
An example of an even more ambitious development in
educational films is offered by the film, "Climatic Regions
of Europe", produced by the International Educational
Film Council. Four countries agreed to make sequences
presenting Europe's different climatic conditions: the
German Federal Republic for continental climate, the
United Kingdom for oceanic climate, France for the
Mediterranean climate and Sweden for the Arctic. An
introduction in animated cartoon form was made by
Denmark and the entire operation co-ordinated by Swed¬
en. Contributions towards the cost of the project were
made by Unesco and by the members of the Inter-
(1) {"Film Production By International Co-operation". No. 34 in the
Vnksc.o series. "Report.* and Pa/iers on Mass Communication" ,
Pans l!)li2.)
national Educational Film Council in proportion to each
country's share in the council's budget.
An account of these experiments and of several others
a co-production with the United Nations and two co-pro¬
ductions with broadly cultural themes (The Open Window
and December, The Children's Month) has been given in
a Unesco booklet (1). This publication will be of immense
value to future educational film-makers since its authors
explain at length the mechanics of co-operation and with
admirable candour deal fully with the problems they met
and the mistakes they made.
Increased international co-operation of this kind will
do much to open the way and smooth the path for future
educational films. This became clear at the Unesco-
sponsored meeting in Kuala-Lumpur, Malaya, in Aug¬
ust 1961, which brought together the heads of national
audio-visual aid departments in countries of South and
East Asia. Guided by the results of the experiments
already described, these specialists agreed to carry out a
joint production programme of films on human geography
and natural science, as well as other projects.
Since it combines both art and industry, the cinema
needs technicians, specialists and creative workers in
many fields. The "on the job" training of the early days
has now been replaced by highly skilled and specialized
instruction in schools specifically created for this purpose.
Most of these training schools, affiliated under an Inter¬
national Liaison Centre for Cinema and Television Schools,
are in Europe Potsdam-Babelsberg, Madrid, Paris,
Athens, Budapest, Lodz, Rome, Prague, Moscow, Vienna,
Munster, Kiel, London and Amsterdam and in several
universities of the United States. Others are operating
In La Plata, Cairo and Taipeh.
Professional training given in these centres covers the
creative roles in film-making (directors, actors, art
directors), the administrative (associate producers) and
the technical (operators, sound engineers, laboratory
technicians etc.).
In addition there are audio-visual training centres where
teachers learn to prepare or to make use of the multi¬
fold items of equipment now employed in today's visual
and sound information media, equipment which has prov¬
ed of much value in the classroom.
Tomorrow's cinema is already taking shape in such
schools and centres.
(To be continued)
This survey was undertaken by Paul Léglise, at the request
of Unesco's Free Flow of Information Division of the Depart¬
ment of Mass Communication and carried out under the
auspices of French National Commission for Unesco. Mr. Léglise
is head of the cultural and short films service of the Centre
National de la Cinématographie Française in Paris. He is the
author of several works on the cinema including, "Methods of
Encouraging the Production and Distribution of Short Films
for Theatrical Use", published this year by Unesco.
UNESCO CREATES KALINGA FILM PRIZE
32
I InESCO has instituted an award of £2,000 sterling for
" a feature-length film contributing "most effectively to
public appreciation of an outstanding achievement in
education, science and culture, resulting from international
co-operation." To be known henceforth as the Kalinga
Film Prize, the first award, for 1961-62, went to "In the
Bay of the White Bears", a Polish film by Jaroslav
Brzozowski about polar research during the International
Geophysical Year. A French film, "Le Grand Secret" by
Gerald Calderón received special mention.
Like the Kalinga Prize for the popularization of science
created in 1951, the new award is a donation from
Mr. Bijoyanand Patnaik, Chief Minister of the State of
Orissa in India, and one of the directors of the Kalinga
Foundation, set up to give full support to economic
development and social and cultural progress in Orissa.
Films were submitted by Australia, Belgium, Finland,
France, Japan, Mexico, Poland, Singapore, the United
Kingdom and the U.S.S.R., and were viewed by an inter¬
national jury appointed by Unesco, comprising Mr. F. L.
Ammannati, President of the Centro Sperimentale di
Cinematographia, Mr. Boris Milev, Permanent Delegate of
Bulgaria to Unesco, Mr. Leopoldo Torre Nilsson, film
director in Argentina and H.R.H. Prince Prem. Purachatra,
President of the Mass Communication Committee of the
National Commission of Thailand for Unesco.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
SECOND LANGUAGE FOR ALI	
Sir,
Your June issue (Antennas Across
The World) highlights the appalling
handicap of language.
This is the point in history, where,
in considering this vast communica¬
tion system for the world. . . Telstar,
television, radio, etc.,... we should
here make one concerted move for a
second language common to all peo¬
ple of the world. With Unesco pre¬
paring so admirably for the spread of
mass media communications by 1975
to the world's illiterate millions, could
not Esperanto, that' proven inter¬
national language be that medium ?
A simple solution would be one
year's tuition in Esperanto for all child¬
ren of the world, when they, our
future leaders in every walk of life,
would be able to communicate readily
with each other without interpreters,
electronic brains and the like. Espe¬
ranto asks no country to give up its
own language but merely to use it as
a second one.
E. D. AHcn
DunedJn, New Zealand
... SUCH AS ESPERANTO
Elstara sinjoro:
Ricevu mian humilan, sed sinceran
kaj tutkoran gratulon pro la ci durao-
nata numero "El correo" -rev uo.
La terura problemo, kiun oni ko-
mentadas ka; samtempe studas am¬
piélese en tiu interesega revuo, lasos
sendube grandan influon en ciujn per-
sonojn, kiuj tutlande legos gin.
Certe ke tiu ci numero, "La luktado
kontrau la malsato", kauzigos profun¬
dan impakton en ciujn konsciencojn.
Mi certigas ci tion medidante la vor-
tojn de Tibor Mende, kiuj aperas en
aparta loko sub la titolo: "La humilla¬
ción".
Ankau gratulojn pro la altega kul¬
tura kaj humana nivelo de via Revuo
kaj pro la senlaca agado de Vi kaj
viaj kunlaborantoj por tiom bêla kaj
dankinda misio, celante la vekadon
kaj felocon de Homaro.
Kun antaudankoj, salutas Vin atente.
J. Vêlez
Barcelona, Hispanio
ELUSIVE SCHOLARSHIPS
Sir,
Under General Assembly Resolu¬
tion 845 Section (EX) of the United
Nations' Charter, member states of
the U.N. undertake to provide scho¬
larships to students resident in non-
self-governing territories to enable
them to study in the scholarship-
awarding countries.
I know many people in British Cen¬
tral Africa including Nyasaland who
applied for these scholarships but in
each case they were told: "Your appli
cation has been transmitted to the
appropriate authorities of your pro¬
posed country of study and a copy
has been sent to the Permanent Mis¬
sion of the United Kingdom to the
United Nations for observation . . .
You may rest assured that any deci¬
sion on your application will be com¬
municated to you as soon as it is made
known."
The decision on the application is
communicated on the Greek Calends.
This results in a waste of time; a
waste of postage stamps and above
all, the student, fails to go to another
university because he is waiting for the
decision to be made known and does
not, whilst waiting, apply elsewhere
for a scholarship. Surprisingly
enough, during my recent tour of
Universities throughout the length and
breadth of Europe, I never met any
student from underdeveloped coun¬
tries who claimed to be at University
on Unesco scholarships. Arc the
Unesco scholarships bogus? I'leasc
elucidate.
L. M. Kwapata
London, Kurland
Ed note: Unesco is not competent
to answer our correspondent's criticism '
of scholarships administered by the
U.N. and not by Unesco. As regards
Unesco scholarships, although there
are some available ¡or students from
underdeveloped countries, the majority
of awards are for persons already well
established in their careers to spend
relatively short periods obtaining com¬
parative experience in several coun¬
tries. The number of Unesco scho¬
larships is very small compared with
the demand and, in fact, represents
far less than 1% of the world total
in any one year.
IN DEFENCE OF FERTILISERS
Sir,
In reply to Michel Lambert's letter
(Are We Poisoning Ourselves?) in your
July-August issue, I should like to
point out that we cannot grow enough
food if we simply leave Nature to do
all the work. Yields of about 15 hun¬
dredweights of wheat per acre and
six pints of milk or so per cow are
simply not enough to provide a proper
diet for everyone. We do not "poi¬
son" the earth by using chemical fer¬
tilizers. We improve it and also the
quality of the harvests won from it.
Pierre Guillon
Crépy-en-Valois
AID WHERE AID IS NEEDED
Sir,
This is by way of a note of con¬
gratulation on the excellent. July/Au¬
gust issue ("Freedom from Hunger").
I have read it with great interest in¬
deed, and thought that I should send
along a few words of praise for a
good job very well done.
Just for your interest, I am a mem¬
ber of the Royal Canadian Air Force
Association, and last year our Asso¬
ciation adopted as a national project
that Wings and individuals should take
on the support of underprivileged chil¬
dren through the Canadian "Save the
Children" Fund, or like organizations.
J am happy to report that already we
have adopted some 43 children, and
we hope to double this number this
year. We realize that this is but a
drop in the bucket, but is at least a
step in the right direction, and brings
home to our membership the great
need of people in less fortunate cir¬
cumstances. Through such know¬
ledge wc hope that the Canadian pub¬
lic will become better informed and
increase our already considerable
effort in aid to other countries in
need.
G. K. Tenfold
Don Mills Ontario
Cunada
CYBERNETICS & LINGUISTICS
Sir,
As linguists we arc particularly inter¬
ested in the latest achievements in
the theory of information, especially
the development of mechanical means
of translating information from one
language to another; we arc also in¬
terested in problems of transmitting
and preserving information on a world
scale and in the possibilities offered
by cybernetics for the solution of theo¬
retical problems in linguistic research.
Your journal has already published
several articles on this subject, in par¬
ticular, the article on the deciphering
of the ancient Maya manuscripts by
Soviet scientists (March 1962). Wc
should like to sec an issue devoted Io
the problem of cybernetics taken as a
whole.
Wladimir S. Vasliunln
Nikolai V. Nikolaycv
Moscow, U_S-S.lt.
A GESTURE FROM THE CLASS
Sir,
After reading in your magazine the
appeal for help in saving the monu¬
ments of Nubia I talked about this
problem to the class in which I (each
the history of the East and of Greece.
The pupils decided to contribute
towards the protection of the Nubian
temples from their pocket money. I
am therefore enclosing a cheque for
25 New Francs raised by this collec¬
tion. This is obviously only a minute
sum compared with the total cost of
the undertaking, but I feci that the
gesture of these young French second¬
ary school boys shows the interest
that has been aroused by Unesco's
initiative.
F. Bcdarida
Paris
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New:
UNESCO ASKS AID FOR IRAN: The
earthquake which devastated an im¬
mense area of Iran early last September
had a disastrous effect on the country's
developing economy. Altogether some
12,000 people were killed, 30,000 were
injured and a further 90,000 made home¬
less; 150 villages were razed to the ground
and 110 schools destroyed.' The priority
efforts of Iran's government have there¬
fore been directed to providing medical
care, food and shelter for the victims. In
view of the extent of this disaster, Unesco
has appealed to its national commissions
to alert people in their countries to Iran's
need of help and to ask governmental and
private organizations to give assistance so
that the Iran Government may carry out
a programme of educational and cultural
rehabilitation in addition to the priority
tasks it has already undertaken.
COMPUTER vs. LITERARY RIDDLE:
Using an electronic computer, two
Harvard University mathematicians recent¬
ly identified the authorship of 12 essays
believed to have been written by the Amer¬
ican statesman, Alexander Hamilton, and
by James Madison (4th president of the
United States) which were published anony¬
mously in 1787 and 1788. The mathe¬
maticians fed information on the frequency
of key words in the essays and in the known
writings of the two men, and from the
results, identified Alexander Hamilton as
the author of 11 of the essays.
BOOSTING AFRICA'S HIGHER EDU¬
CATION: An Inter-African confer¬
ence on higher education organized by
Unesco at Tananarive, capital of the Mal¬
agasy Republic recently adopted a plan
destined to strengthen and develop 32 Afri¬
can universities. The plan forsees an
expansion of students in higher education¬
al institutions of 31 African countries
from the present figure of 31,000 to
274,000 by 1980. To meet this increase
7,000 non-African and 14,000 African pro¬
fessors will need to be recruited during the
next 20 years.
F LYING DOCTORS FOR AFRICA:
A flying doctor service of the kind that
has operated in Australia for the past 34
years is now being organized to work from
bases with dispensaries throughout Nor¬
thern Nigeria. The Australian Govern¬
ment recently presented the African service
with a pedal wireless "transceiver" a mod¬
ern equivalent of the equipment first devis¬
ed for the Australian service. In Austra¬
lia, the Flying Doctor Service now oper¬
ates from 13 bases to cover about two
million square miles and records more than
10,000 radio calls to its clinics in a year.
IfARITIME MUSEUM ATTRAC-
iWM. TION: Visitors to the Stockholm
museum which houses the 17th century
Swedish warship "Wasa", salvaged last
year from the waters of Stockholm har-
34 bour, have broken all museum attendance
records in the Swedish capital: in 5 months
entries exceeded 250,000. A Swedish na
val specialist recently stated that examina¬
tion of the "Wasa," which foundered on
her maiden voyage in 1628, showed that
faulty design was not the cause of the dis¬
aster, as had hitherto been believed.
GLACIERS IN RETREAT: The Franz
Joseph Glacier in New Zealand's
South Island retreated 300 feet between
1960 and 1961 according to the New Zea¬
land Geological Survey, and during the
past ten years this great river of ice moved
back 3,500 feet. The retreat of the Franz
Joseph and the neighbouring Fox Glacier
is due to lighter rain and snowfall during
this period.
STAMPS AGAINST HUNGER: Dr B.
R. Sen, Director-General of the U.N.
Food and Agriculture Organization has
appealed to all member countries to make
a special issue of stamps in support of the
Freedom-from-Hunger Campaign (See The
Unesco Courier, July-August 1962). He
has suggested that World Freedom-from-
Hunger Week, to be observed in the last
week of March 1963, would be an appro¬
priate time for the release of these special
stamps.
rP-TO-DATE SCARECROWS: Mod¬
ern technology has found more effi¬
cient ways of protecting crops from raider
birds than the use of the traditional scare¬
crow with his battered hat and ragged gar¬
ments. In Australia, following research
into the significance of different bird calls,
recordings made of warning signals given
by certain birds have been amplified over
loudspeakers in the fields and have effec¬
tively scared birds away from the crops.
FOR BETTER SCHOOL BUILDINGS:
A world-wide network of centres deal¬
ing with educational building, linked by an
international centre, has been proposed by
educators and architects from 59 countries
meeting in London at the International
Building Conference, organized by the
U.K. National Commission for Unesco.
The Conference recommended that the In¬
ternational Centre should be operated by
Unesco which has already set up school
construction centres in Khartoum, for Afri¬
ca, and in Bandung, for Asia and Oceania.
EDUCATIONAL BOOKS ON
DISPLAY: On the occasion
of the 12th Session of the Unesco
General Conference (November 9 -
December 12, 1962) an inter¬
national exhibition of educational
books for use in » the developing
countries is being held at the Palais
de la Découverte in Paris under
the joint patronage of the French
and United Kingdom National
Commissions for Unesco. Seven¬
teen countries and 200 publishers
are represented and 3,500 books
displayed. The exhibition is open
from November 14 to December 12.
COMPUTER SKIPPER & NO CREW:
Down the broad river Dnieper in the
U.S.S.R. sails a diesel ship, the "Laborato-
ria," skippered by a computer and with a
crew of automatic machines. She man
vres accurately on turns and avoids shoals.
Depth finders and other instruments flash
information to the computer which imme¬
diately issues orders. The "Laboratoria"
is being used by research workers of Kiev
colleges, hydrologiste and radio specialists
to study widely varied systems of ship au¬
tomation.
WORLD TYPOGRAPHY MUSEUM:
A major event during celebrations
marking the 2,000th anniversary of the
founding of Mainz in the Federal Republic
of Germany, was the dedication of the
World Museum of Typography to one of
the city's most famous men, Johannes Gu¬
tenberg. The new museum englobes the
former Gutenberg Museum and includes
the reconstructed 15th century typography
workshop of Gutenberg alongside an ultra¬
modern automatic book printing machine.
In the biographical note on Mr. Rex
Keating (Digging for History) in last
month's issue the title of Mr. Keating's
book was erroneously given as Twilight
of the Gods. The correct title is Nubian
Twilight.
Flashes...
| An international fleet of océanographie
research ships will survey the fishery re¬
sources of the tropical Atlantic next year
under a plan approved by the 44-nation
Intergovernmental Océanographie Commis¬
sion which met at Unesco House in Paris.
fl Schools in the U.S.S.R., from primary to
university level opened their doors to about
40 million students at the start of the 1962-
63 school year. The period of obligatory
education has now been increased from
seven to eight years in the Soviet Union.
Algeria has become the 107//i member
state of Unesco. A short time before,
UNESCO's Executive Board approved a
$200,000 emergency assistance programme
for Algeria to be used to provide teachers
for secondary and technical education.
Import duties on radio, film and televi¬
sion equipment, scientific instruments and
other information materials have been re¬
duced by 16 nations at the Tariff Confer¬
ence of the GATT (General Agreement on
Tariffs and Trade) held recently in Geneva.
Malaya is to have its first national news
agency through the combined efforts of its
newspapers, radio broadcasting organiza¬
tions and other information enterprises
following a Unesco meeting in Bangkok on
the development of national news agencies
in the Asian region.
At least $80 million will be needed to
develop public libraries in Africa bet¬
ween now and 1970 according to library
specialists from 28 countries at a seminar
organized by the Government of Nigeria
and Unesco at Enugu, Eastern Nigeria.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
TABLE OF CONTENTS THE UNESCO COURIER 1962
January
ANTARCTICA, INTERNATIONAL LAND OF SCIENCE. Frozen
continent of many paradoxes The two faces of Antarctica Antarctica.
International Land of Science Discovery, exploration, adventure and
courage Trail blazers of Antarctica Amundsen and Scott Living at
70 degrees below zero Of sunspots, magnetic rings and polar lights
Journey into the inaccessible Unique species threatened by man.
February
THE RUINS OF NEMRUD DAGH. 2,000 years ago East met West
at the shrine of Antiochus I Frederick Douglass, American fighter
for freedom The Incas of today Ping-pong dolls go to school
Australia's giant ' eye ' on outer space Little-known masterpieces of
Bulgarian art.
March
THE AWAKENING AFRICAN CINEMA. The art of seeing a
film Africa : The awakening cinema Tomorrow's weather The
story of the metric system Computer deciphers Maya hieroglyphs.
April
TWO FACES OF WORLD HEALTH. A special report: The
challenge of disease and poverty; Hazards of progress and prosperity
An S.O.S. from cableman to fisherman words and things
Students abroad in search of knowledge.
May
THIRSTY LANDS, PAST AND FUTURE, The thousand faces of the
'desert' Strategy of scientific co-operation When the Sahara was
a blooming garden The Emperor Penguin, monarch of Antarctica
The lost hymns of Georgia Modern Japanese fiction Reminiscences
by a friend of Tagore.
June
ANTENNAS ACROSS THE WORLD. 2,000 million people without
access to news Global facts and figures A scientist looks at popu¬
larization Kalinga Prize goes to space-age writer Paul Geheeb :
Search for a new humanism Bold reformer and a school for mankind
Music of the orient Latest panorama of world's translations.
July - August
FREEDOM FROM HUNGER. World campaign against hunger
The challenge of hunger Famine, the greatest scourge of history
Hidden hunger Maps of hunger Food taboos and prejudices
The food destroyers Food and people The first victories - A world
strategy for surplus stocks The anatomy of underdevelopment (Pt I)
Waking the sleeping lands.
September
DANGER : OIL-POLLUTED SEAS. Muslcon a string -Growing threat
of oil pollution from the sea The ocean under a microscope The
anatomy of underdevelopment (Pt 2) Gcrhart Hauptmann, dramatist
of the oppressed How to be an amateur archrloglst Jodo Kumaml,
king of storytellers for Kyoto's children.
October
NATURE'S HIDDEN LANGUAGES OF SMELL. Karl von Frisch
on the surprising Uses of smell sense by animals Rameses" mysterious
encounter at dawn Niko Pirosmani Building a future for young
Arab refugees Will the Indian Ocean reveal its secrets ?
November
NEW HORIZONS IN MUSIC. Society calls the tune - Music sketch
book In defence of science-fiction Digging for history Unicef
greeting cards The anatomy of underdevelopment (Pt 3) World
pioneers of technology.
December
MAN THROUGH HIS ART. Earthlingj In the Space age Auguste
Rodin and " The Citizens of Calais " Man Through His Art The
deadly salt of the earth Samarkand the fabulous The hidden face
of the cinema.
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU-
RIERtin any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. PanuzaT, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C'., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckach, Prague 2. DENMARK. Einar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nórregade,
Kóbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7-. C.C.P. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only)
Bahren-felder-Chaussee 1 60, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, C.C.P.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura. P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ali Road, P.O. Box 3 86, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakli, Dialan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 3 5, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv(1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA, Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd.. Times House,
River Valley Rd., Singapore MALTA. Sapienza's Library
26 Kingsway. Valetta. (10/-). MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des Moulins.
Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS. N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9. The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office
Wellington, and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch, Dunedin (10/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR
WAY. For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvtsent Lit
teratur-T|tneste, Stortingsft. 4, Oslo, Potlboks 115 (kr
1 3.20) Others publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grentt.
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. Th« West-Pak Publishing Cor.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D F. (Balboas 3-). PHI¬
LIPPINES. The Modern Book Co.. 508 Rizal Avenue
Manila. POLAND. RUCH " ul. Wiloia
Nr. 46. Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL.
Dias & Andrada Lda, Livrana Portugal, Rua
do Carmo 70. Lisbon. RHODESIA t, NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A/B C.E. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Frcdsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Rlmistrasse
Zurich. Payot, 40. rue du Marché, Geneva. C.C.P.
1-236. " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz, 1, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers. Geneva. C.C.P. 1-4811. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA, Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
.SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria and for the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency. P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office. P.O. Box 569. London, S.E I. (10/-). UNITFD
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue. New York, 22, N.Y. ($ 5.00) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaia
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
venska Knjlga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
SHOOTING IN THE CAPITOL
Film-making today is an itinerant occupation. Camera
crews seem to arrive and set up their equipment al
anywhere, just as they have done here beneath the 288
high dome of the Capitol, seat of the U. S. Congress, in
Washington. The occasion was the shooting of scenes
from the film, "Advise and Consent", by producer
Preminger. The story of the hidden face of modern
making, from production and its problems to the pro
jection of the finished product on the cinema screens o
the world is described in a special report on page 8
]]>
</page>
</document>
