<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078276eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
May 1972 (25th year) - U.K.: 13p North America : 50 cts - France: 1.70 F
Q
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
ARGENTINA
Pre-Columbian 'Humpty Dumpty'
In Argentina's northwestern provinces of Catamarca and La Rioja, in the Andes, have been found strange
sculptures, many of which antedate the 7th century A.D., weird wooden totems, pottery cups, bronze objects
with mysterious designs. They are a question and an answer on how men lived in America long before Christopher
Columbus. Above, an extraordinary vase or perhaps funeral urn (now in the La Plata Museum, Buenos Aires)
dating from about 1000 A.D. This squat stylized human figure, light brown with black painted geometrical
designs and facial markings, was found at Belem, in Catamarca province. It strangely recalls the Humpty
Dumpty of nursery rhyme fame. The pre-Columbian potters of South America are renowned for the ingenious
and imaginative forms they gave to their earthenware figures.
Photo © Instituto Di Telia, Fondo Nacional de las Artes, Buenos Aires
2 M\mx
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
«to Courier
MAY 1972
25TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 12 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: £1.30 stg.; $5.00
(North America); 17 French francs or
equivalent; 2 years :£ 2.30 stg.; 30 F. Single
copies : 1 3 p stg. ; 50 cents : 1 .70 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew and Persian. For list
of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER," plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Con¬
tents - Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7», France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Olga Rodel
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Francisco Fernández-Santos (Paris)
Russian Edition : Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition : Kartar Singh Duggal (Delhi)
Tamil Edition : N.D. Sundaravadivelu (Madras)
Hebrew Edition : Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
Persian Edition : Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Howard Brabyn
French Edition : Philippe Ouannès
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research: Zoé Allix
Illustrations : Anne-Marie Maillard
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief
Page
1972
International
Book Year
8
16
19
23
27
28
30
34
37
11 TOOLS OF A NEW TRADE
13 17 MAJOR WRECK SITES
IN THE MEDITERRANEAN
14 100 SITES ALONG THE COASTS OF FRANCE
SEA GOD FROM CAPRI'S BLUE GROTTO
THE NEW WORLD
OF UNDERWATER ARCHAEOLOGY
Diving into the past
by Mark M. Barinov
THE TRIALS OF AN UNDERWATER
ARCHAEOLOGIST
by George F. Bass
UNDER THE ICY SEAS OF NORTHERN EUROPE
By Ole Crumlin-Pedersen
FOUR PAGES IN FULL COLOUR
BURIED TREASURE
BENEATH THE SPANISH MAIN
by Mendel L . Peterson
THE ENIGMA OF THE BAHAMAS
THE DROWNED CITY OF PORT ROYAL
Excavating underwater ruins in Jamaica
by Robert F. Marx
THE SACRED WELL OF CHICHEN-ITZA
by Pablo B. Romero
THE ARCHAEOLOGIST IN DEEP WATER
by Wif/ard Bascom
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Pre-Columbian "Humpty Dumpty" (Argentina)
UNDERWATER ARCHAEOLOGY
This 6 ft. 10 in. bronze statue of
Poseidon, god of the sea (or possibly
Zeus, overlord of ancient Greek
gods), was recovered from a sunken
vessel near Cape Artemision, in
eastern Greece (see pages 12-13).
One of only two bronze
originals existing from the fifth
century B.C., the statue Is now
in the National Museum in Athens.
Underwater archaeology is a rapidly
growing field of research and
is giving new dimensions to man's
efforts to explore his past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Sea god
from the Isle of Capri
Above, archaeologists gently raise a marble statue
through the waters of the famous Blue Grotto on
the isle of Capri in the Bay of Naples. It is seen
emerging from the waters in the photo right. The
statue, badly eroded by sea water and covered
with marine incrustations (photo above right) was
discovered in 1964 and later found to be a Roman
sculpture of a sea divinity or triton, dating back
2,000 years. It is believed to have been part of a
huge sculptural group decorating the walls of the
Grotto. Underwater exploration in the Bay of
Naples has produced a rich harvest of ancient
stonework and works of art, and has brought to
light the remains of a vast architectural complex.
With its coastline stretching for over 4,000 kilo¬
metres and its history going back for millenia, Italy
is a treasure house for the underwater archaeologist.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The past 25 years have witnessed the development of a new branch of archaeology
in which the waters of the seas, lakes and rivers are being systematically explor¬
ed by the underwater archaeologist. To meet the growing demand for infor¬
mation on this subject, Unesco has just published a book entitled "Underwater
Archaeology A Nascent Discipline" in the series Museums and Monuments.
Although primarily intended as a practical working tool for the specialist in the
field, this highly readable and absorbing book is certainly destined to become one
of Unesco's "best sellers", of interest to a wide and popular audience (see price
and other details on inside back cover). The book is divided into two major parts:
Part I focuses on, the major achievements in underwater archaeology and the
sites and wrecks excavated; Part II examines the main problems facing archae¬
ologists today, the new techniques used, diving "saucers" and other submarine
apparatuses, as well as underwater photography, photogrammetry, etc. An
appendix to the Unesco book gives examples of recent legislation on effective
measures for the protection of sites and wrecks. Much of the material publish¬
ed in this issue is directly taken from or inspired by this new Unesco volume.
The new world
of underwater archaeology
DIVING INTO THE PAST
by Mark M. Barinov
WICERO wrote that in his
time towns and cities were situated
around the Mediterranean Sea like so
many frogs sitting round a pond. In¬
deed, life in the ancient world was in¬
separably linked with the seas, rivers
and waterways.
Traces of the ancient world are being
found in coastal seas and at the bot¬
tom of the larger lakes and rivers
ships that never reached their destina¬
tions, or towns and ports that have
been swallowed up as a result of
alterations in sea level.
Underwater archaeological sites
such as these may well prove to be of
greater interest than land sites, since
the greater part of the relics and
monuments of cities such as ancient
Rome, Moscow, Paris and Delhi, for
example, have been obliterated by
MARK M. BARINOV Is well known in the
Soviet Union as a writer on archaeology and
other scientific subjects. In 1968, he led an
underwater archaeology expedition to Lake
Svetloyar, in the central Volga basin, to
investigate the legend of the lost city of
Kitezh, described in his article. He is the
author of seven books for the general reader
on scientific questions and numerous articles
published in the U.S.S.R. and other countries.
later construction, making the archae¬
ologists' task extremely difficult.
But the discovery of an ancient
sunken ship is a great event for ar¬
chaeologists. A ship is a world in
itself and everything from the cargo to
the nails in the planking is a valuable
document of the past. Moreover, a
ship and its cargo make up a complete
unit of the past, an ensemble that tells
us much more about an era than a
number of separate discoveries.
Under certain conditions, silt and
water are reliable preservatives and,
after cleaning, equipment, weapons
and utensils recovered from sunken
ships are often found to be as good
as new.
In the Mediterranean, with its favour¬
able natural conditions and clear
waters, sunken ships are the number
one target of underwater explorers.
Yet such exploration and salvage of
ancient ships and cargoes for their
archaeological interest is not new.
In 1907, Greek sponge divers came
across the wreck of a 1st century B.C.
ship lying in 40 metres of water off the
Tunisian coast near Mahdia. It proved
to be one of the ships of the Roman
expedition, led by Sulla, which
captured Athens in 86 B.C. Return¬
ing from the Greek city, heavily laden
with the spoils of war, including temple
columns and bronze statues, it was
blown off course and sank (see centre
pages).
Subsequent underwater archae¬
ological expeditions have recovered
enough objects from this wreck to fill
six rooms of the Bardo Museum In
Tunis and much of the cargo still lies
on the sea floor.
In the Black Sea, where maritime
conditions are far more rigorous than
in the Mediterranean, Soviet under¬
water archaeologists have concentrat¬
ed on the search for sunken cities.
One of the best known of these spe¬
cialists is Profesor V. Blavatsky, an
eminent archaeologist who, although
well over middle age, "took the
plunge" in 1957 and became a novice
underwater archaeologist. Another is
B.G. Peters who, while a student of
Prof. Blavatsky, completed a deep-
sea diving course, mastered the use
of the aqualung and became the first
Soviet scuba diver-archaeologist.
For a number of years now, these
scientists with a group of fellow
archaeologists and students, have been
carrying out important exploratory
work at the bottom of the Kerch Straits,
which link the Black Sea with the Sea
of Azov, and in the area of the Dnie¬
per-Bug estuary, probing the sites of
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
DIVING INTO THE PAST (Continued)
The legend of the lost city of Kitezh
the ancient Greek city-colonies of
Fanagoria and Olvia.
After several summers spent work¬
ing under water they have succeeded
in establishing the boundaries, con¬
tours and area of the city of Fanagoria
which was submerged many hundreds
of years ago. Using the simplest
equipment aqualungs and a suction
dredge they have brought up material
evidence of the city's existence, in¬
cluding pieces of pottery and other
household utensils.
The great lakes of the U.S.S.R. also
hold secrets that underwater archae¬
ologists are attempting to wrest from
their depths. A few years ago, an
amateur expedition, made up of spe¬
cialists from various fields with a
common interest in underwater
archaeology, and headed by General
G.N. Karaev, set out from Leningrad
for lake Peipus.
Intrigued by the mysteries of the
past, they decided to explore the site
of the famous Battle on the Ice in
which, the Russian prince Alexander
Nevsky defeated the Teutonic knights
in 1242.
The battle was fought on the frozen
waters of Lake Peipus and ancient
chronicles record that many of the
combatants fell through the ice to a
watery grave. Underwater exploration
by general Karaev's expedition re¬
vealed traces of the battle ancient
weapons and armour.
Students and teachers of the Mos¬
cow Aviation Institute have become
spare time underwater archaeologists
whose aim is to find the lost treasure
of Napoleon. Legend has it that Napo¬
leon took with him on his hasty re¬
treat from Moscow, in 1812, a vast
caravan laden with priceless treasures.
The caravan never reached France.
The legend mentions a lake along
the route taken by the remnants of
La Grande Armée, and the young ex¬
plorers from Moscow have examined
lake after lake, so far without success.
Whether they will ever find the treas¬
ure, or indeed, whether it ever exist¬
ed, is a matter of conjecture. What is
certain, however, is that under the
most difficult conditions they have
developed new methods of underwater
research, including a means of pene¬
trating up to eleven metres of silt.
This alone is ample reward for their
efforts.
6
EaVEN more intriguing is the
story of the search for the "lost city"
of Great Kitezh. Shortly before the
Tartar-Mongolian invasion of Russia,
nearly eight centuries ago, the grand
duke of Pskov, Georgi Vsevolodovich,
travelled down the Volga with his
soldiers establishing fortified towns or
castles along the way to protect the
Russian people from the raids of
the nomads.
After founding the city of Little
Kitezh, known today as Gorodetz, he
turned away from the banks of the
Volga to travel through the forest
beside the quiet river Kerzhenetz. One
hundred kilometres from the Volga, he
ordered trees to be felled and the city
of Great Kitezh arose on the shores of
Lake Svetloyar, in the central Volga
basin.
Shortly afterwards Russia was in¬
vaded by Batu Khan. His army travel¬
led along the Volga capturing Little
Kitezh and burning it to the ground.
Batu Khan forced a prisoner to divulge
the secret of the trail that led to Great
Kitezh, and a few miles from the city
encountered duke Georgi and his
small detachment.
Not a single Russian soldier sur¬
vived the unequal battle that ensued;
but Batu Khan never succeeded in cap¬
turing Great Kitezh, for the town with
all its inhabitants had vanished.
Local legend gives three "explana¬
tions" of the disappearance of Great
Kitezh. In the first, God made the city
invisible; in the second, Kitezh cover¬
ed itself with earth and became the
hills now seen near Svetloyar;
according to the third, the city sank to
the bottom of the lake.
The legend has stirred the imagina¬
tion of generations of Russians and
inspired artists, poets and composers,
including Rimsky-Korsakov who wrote
the now famous opera, "The Legend
of the Invisible City of Kitezh."
A few years ago, I undertook to org¬
anize a combined research operation
on the Kitezh legend, under the aus¬
pices of the "Literaturnaya Gazeta". I
gathered together an expedition com¬
posed of scientists from various fields
in the hopes of discovering some
kernel of truth behind the legend, and
perhaps even of finding the mysterious
city itself.
In the autumn of 1968, we set out for
Lake Svetloyar. The archaeologists in
our group explored the lake shore for
traces of the city; scuba divers examin¬
ed the lake basin and studied the bot¬
tom; geologists, hydrologists and other
specialists determined the age and
source of the lake; and folklore ex¬
perts probed the recesses of local
folk memory, collating everything that
people knew about Kitezh, the lake
and the events of the past.
This first expedition revealed that
Lake Svetloyar is relatively young and
was formed as a result of three land
cave-ins, one of which dated back pre¬
cisely to the time of Batu Khan's inva¬
sion. Our scuba divers discovered
tree trunks on the bottom that had
once been part of the forest, thus
definitely confirming that the lake had
been formed as a result of a natural
catastrophe, but thick silt prevented
them from searching for traces of a
sunken city. Radioactive carbon analy¬
sis substantiated the dating of the
cave-in.
The following year we returned with
a sonic-geolocator, an instrument
specially designed by a Leningrad
scientist, which not only measures the
depth of water down to the bed of a
sea or lake, but' also identifies the
nature of underlying geological layers.
In an ordinary fishing boat we care¬
fully quartered the lake to plot a sonic
cross-section of the bottom. In the
northern part of the lake we discover¬
ed an oval-shaped formation which
seemed to suggest the presence of
some kind of enclosed structure.
Another year passed and, in 1970,
five test borings in the indicated area
pierced ten metres of silt to bring up
pieces of wood which bore tracesof
human activity.
Did we find Kitezh? This question
can only be answered after a further
expedition by underwater archaeolo¬
gists using powerful modern equip¬
ment.
ROFESSOR B.A. Kolchin,
another well-known Soviet archae¬
ologist and a specialist of the Slavonic
Middle Ages, believes that Lake limen,
which lies just south of the city of
Novgorod, could well conceal a large
number of wrecked ships of Norman,
Slavonic, Viking and Greek origin.
The lake once formed a junction of
waterways connecting Scandinavia
and the Slavonic world with Greece
and Rome. Though the lake is only
eight to ten metres deep, it is noted
for its fierce squalls and sudden
storms in which many vessels must
have come to grief. Here is a chal¬
lenging task for a future expedition.
Underwater archaeology is a young
science whose practitioners need the
combined abilities of athletes and scho¬
lars. Prof. Blavatsky believes the time
is ripe for setting up a special Institute
of Underwater Archaeology staffed by
scientist-diving specialists. The Insti¬
tute would need a fleet of specially de¬
signed ships and the latest underwater
exploration equipment. "As a new
branch of an old science, underwater
archaeology is directly dependent on
technological progress," he says.
Many astonishing secrets are wait¬
ing to be revealed by the pioneers of
this new science. As Philip Diolé, of
the French Museum of Natural History,
in Paris, has told archaeologists:
"Learn how to divel The future of your
science lies under water."
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Photo © "Chant du Monde", Paria
In search
of sunken
cities
of ancient
Russia
Soviet archaeologists have ex¬
plored sunken cities in the Black
Sea, ancient settlements on the
Baltic and historical sites in
lakes and rivers during the past
15 years. From the bed of Lake
Peipus, southwest of Leningrad,
they have recovered ancient
weapons and armour from the
epic battle fought on the ice in
1242 by a Russian army led by
Prince Alexander Nevsky which
defeated an invading, force of
Teutonic Knights. Above, pre¬
lude to battle, a scene from
"Alexander Nevsky", the 1938
film of the famous Soviet direc¬
tor Sergei Eisenstein. One ex¬
pedition investigated the ancient
legend according to which the
city of Kitezh sank beneath Lake
Svetloyar, in the central Volga
basin, 800 years ago. The story
inspired many artists, poets and
composers, including Nikolai
Rimsky-Korsakov, whose opera
"The Legend of the Invisible City
of Kitezh" was first produced In
St. Petersburg in 1907. Left, the
sunken city of Kitezh depicted
on the cover of a French record
of the opera.
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
The "Asherah", a 2-man, electric-powered, research submarine,
named after a Phoenician goddess of the sea, was built for the
University of Pennsylvania Museum in 1964. The first submarine
specially designed for archaeology, it is 16 ft long, weighs four
and a half tons and can dive to over 500 ft to investigate and
photograph sites of suspected wrecks. Twin cameras can be
mounted on the front bar for mapping of sites. A closed-circuit
TV camera can also be mounted to give the crew a view of the
objects found directly below the craft.
The trials
of an underwater
archaeologist
by George F. Bass
8
a decade of direct¬
ing underwater archaeological excava¬
tions in the Mediterranean, I returned
last year to "dry-land" archaeology,
where I had first received field
training as a student. It was the first
time that I had directed an excavation
on land, and I found the difference bet¬
ween the two types of digs enormous.
Within two or three days after arriv¬
ing at Gravina di Puglia, in southern
Italy, we had acquired shovels, wheel¬
barrows, brushes, knives, notebooks,
surveying equipment, artist's supplies,
and wooden trays and plastic basins
for collecting and cleaning pottery
fragments.
We rented housing for our staff of
about a dozen people (mostly archae¬
ology students), established a photo¬
graphic darkroom, set up tables for
sorting and cataloguing our finds, and
obtained a minibus to get us from this
headquarters to the site and back each
day.
Finally, we rented a portion of the
GEORGE F. BASS Js one of the world's most
experienced underwater archaeologists and
a pioneer of techniques for locating and
excavating underwater sites. Associate Pro¬
fessor of Classical Archaeology at the Uni¬
versity of Pennsylvania and Associate Curator
of the University Museum's Mediterranean
Section, he has directed almost annually
since 1960. the Museum's underwater excav¬
ations off the Turkish coast the first
complete excavations of ancient ships In the
Mediterranean. Dr. Bass has written many
studies on aspects of underwater archaeology
and Is the author of "Archaeology Under
Water" (London and New York, 1966) also
published as a Pelican paperback by Penguin
Books, London (1970).
farmer's field we wished to dig, hired
a few workmen, marked off and sur¬
veyed our first trenches, and began
to excavate. All of the preparations
had taken less than a week.
I could not help contrasting this with
the beginnings of each campaign in
Turkey, where we had carried out all
of our underwater excavations. Design,
construction, and shipping of equip¬
ment had begun many months before.
Selection of a staff, including special¬
ists in diving, mechanics, electrical
engineering, photogrammetry, and the
physiological problems of diving, as
well as in archaeology, photography,
drawing, and conservation, had taken
the better part of a year. Because
each staff member would be able to
work for only an hour or less each
day on the underwater site, we needed
many people, usually 30 or more.
Once in Turkey, the job of getting
up to ten tons of equipment through
customs began. Crates arrived from
America, England, France, Germany,
and Italy. Each shipment presented its
own individual problem. The cable for
an underwater television system might
inadvertently be unloaded in Istanbul,
while the TV camera and monitor
would arrive in Izmir. It often took
weeks to recognize and solve such
problems, while the rest of the equip¬
ment sat idle.
The shipping of our research sub¬
marine Asherah required special per¬
mission from the United States Depart¬
ment of State as well as from the
various concerned ministries of the
Turkish government, but once in Turkey
there remained the problem of getting
an 8-ton crate to an isolated spot on
the coast where we planned to use it.
Simply getting the submarine un¬
loaded in an area where there were
no large cranes took weeks. Then, as
once happened, a box containing a
necessary spare part costing only
$5 was delayed in shipment, and
the submarine, costing tens of thous¬
ands of dollars, was useless for
additional weeks.
We tried to have every conceivable
spare part for our sonar, television,
diving equipment, and submarine, but
this proved impossible. On a land
excavation almost any necessary item
may be purchased or rented locally,
but very few of the components for
specialized underwater work are made
in the countries where we have dived;
further, spare parts for equipment made
in different countries are usually avail¬
able only from those countries."
Meanwhile, our mechanics began to
put in operating condition the twenty-
seven pieces of machinery which had
been in storage over the winter:
electric generators, high-pressure com¬
pressors for filling air tanks, medium-
pressure compressors for air hoses,
outboard motors, bilge pumps, pumps
for our water jets, an air-conditioner
for our recompression chamber. Their
engines were fuelled by gasoline,
kerosene, or diesel. Maintenance of
radios, depth-finders, metal detectors,
and underwater telephones were left
to the electrical engineers. And the
captains and crews of the three boats
we hired were responsible for their
own equipment.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Photo © University of Pennsylvania Museum, U.S.A.
Our fifty-foot diving barge was over¬
hauled, launched, towed several miles
up the coast to the shipwreck site, and
anchored directly above. This pro¬
cedure required calm weather; often
we had to wait days or even weeks
for the right conditions.
We dynamited away part of the
rocky coast nearest the wreck so
that we might unload and set up our
four-man, double-lock recompression
chamber weighing three tons along
with its air bank and compressor.
We lowered our submersible de¬
compression chamber into the water
and attached it to five tons of metal
ballast we had built up on the sea bed-,
then we connected the air hose and
telephone line and ran them to a com¬
pressor and speaker on the nearest
land. This job, so simply described,
took days of heavy manual work.
Our underwater telephone booth was
lowered, set in place, and levelled next
to the wreck site; its lines and hoses
ran to a compressor and telephone on
the barge above.
Most of the work described so far
was done by past staff members who
knew enough Turkish to discuss the
most complex mechanical problems in
local machine shops, and who knew
how to dive. Meanwhile, we were
teaching our new staff members simply
how to dive.c Once, out of 25 divers,
only ten had dived before (except for a
short course in a swimming pool I had
required all to take beforehand); by
the end of the summer each was
diving twice a day to work in 140 feet
of water.
I could continue but I think' my point
is made. Even with careful planning,
never once in ten years were we able
to begin actual excavation during the
first month of one of our underwater
campaigns. It usually took an ad¬
ditional week or two to dismantle all
of the equipment at the end of each
season.
Since most of us were teachers or
students, working only in our summer
vacations of slightly more than three
months, it is obvious how extremely
inefficient a major underwater excava¬
tion can be. We have given as
much thought to overcoming this in¬
efficiency as to the archaeology itself.
After ten years of experimentation, we
have at least partially solved some of
the problems which faced us.
I OST wrecks known in the
Mediterranean were located accident¬
ally by sponge divers, sport divers, or
fishermen. Purposeful search patterns
swum by divers, even around danger¬
ous and therefore promising areas, are
too limited by both time and depth
and the deeper the divers go, the less
time they can spend under water.
Thus we turned to various technical
aids. We searched for wrecks down
to a depth of 300 feet by towing a
television camera a few feet above the
sea bed from a fishing boat in which
we sat staring at the television screen.
In spite of the great clarity of the
picture we received by this closed-
circuit system, the method proved in¬
effective because such a small portion
of the sea bed was visible at any one
timej we would have taken months to
search thoroughly an area only a few
square miles in size, even if we could
have navigated precisely enough to
ensure complete coverage of the area.
Staff members, towed at the same
depth in a one-man observation cap¬
sule, called a Towvane (something like
a diving bell with wings), could look
around through a wrap-around, 360°
plexiglas window and see more, but
the range of visibility was still too
restricted. Further, this method placed
a man into the always hazardous world
beneath the waves, which the television
method did not do.
Greater range was gained by turning
to side-scanning sonar. Our sonar
device, towed behind a small fishing
boat, sent sound waves to the sea bed
600 feet on either side of the search
path. On the boat, recorders showed
small dark spots whenever sound
waves bounced back from something
protruding from the flat sea bed; in
each case the spot might indicate
either a rock outcrop or the cargo of
an ancient ship. Now, however, with
the areas restricted and defined, it was
efficient to bring television into play,
lowering it onto each anomaly for
identification.
First, however, it was necessary to
bring our boat directly above whatever
the sonar had detected. For this we «
had, during the search, stationed three M
students about a mile apart on shore,
sighting on our search boat through
transits. Each had a handi-talkie radio.
CONTINUED PAGE 15
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
10
SDC. This submersible decom¬
pression chamber is a steel
sphere, over 6 ft. in diameter,
which 4 divers can enter through
a bottom hatch. Inside they can
make notes or contact the sur¬
face crew by telephone during
the long periods needed for
decompression.
METAL DETECTOR. Based on
mine-detector principle, this appa¬
ratus indicates presence of metal
by a sound in the operator's
earphones or on a dial near the
handles. Used to find Roman
wreck off Turkish coast and In
archaeological search off Cyprus.
(See also photo above).
TOWVANE. Steel observation
capsule towed behind a trawler.
Pilot has a 360° view through a
plexiglass window and can con¬
trol the capsule by operating side
fins or vanes. Has been used
down to depths of 300 ft Useful
for searching In clear water over
a flat seabed.
TELEPHONE BOOTH. Plexiglass
hemisphere, 4 ft. in diameter, Into
which fresh air is pumped from
the surface. Four divers can
stand Inside, dry from the chest
up, and talk to each other or to
the surface crew. Also provides
an emergency air supply. (See
also photo above).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
A
Drawings on these pages show the under¬
water archaeologist's tools. Above, accurate
mapping of a wreck is made much easier by
the use of an iron grid and piping placed
over the site, dividing it into small numbered
squares. The frame can also be used to
support photographic towers, and divers can
lie across the frame when excavating, keeping
knees and fins away from delicate artifacts.
m m
t
\- öS kSH
5*hP^(f ~'* -V
PHOTO TOWER. 15 ft. high, it
rests on a horizontal scaffolding.
Stereoscopic photos can be taken
either by moving the camera bet¬
ween fixed points on its cross
bar at top of tower or by moving
the whole tower between photo¬
graphs. Photos are used to
make stereo maps of the site.
WATER JET. High pressure
water - jets are used to clear
sand etc. from wrecks. Recoil-
less nozzles on these underwater
"fire hoses" prevent the operator
being pushed backwards by the
force of the jet. Can damage
artifacts unless handled with the
greatest care.
AIR-LIFT. A simple pipe to
whose lower end air Is pumped
from the surface. Air bubbles
rising through the pipe suck
water and sand through the pipe
to reveal hidden portions of a
wreck. Rails can be added to
ease the diver's work in mani¬
pulating the heavy pipe.
AMPHORA CARRIER. Silt-filled
amphoras found In most ancient
Mediterranean wrecks are heavy
and difficult to handle. A simple
raft attached to a balloon which
is then inflated by an air hose
can lift as much as half a ton
of cargo to the surface. Basket
seen here carries 20 amphoras.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
1. KYRENIA. In 1967, the remains
of five ships were located off the coast
of Cyprus. The most promising wreck,
that of a 4th century B.C. amphora-
carrier, was lying In 30 metres of
water near Kyrenia. The hull had been
sheathed In lead to protect it from ship-
worms the earliest known use of this
technique. Excavations by a University
of Pennsylvania Museum team recov¬
ered hundreds of amphoras and other
objects, and the vessel was raised In
sections for reassembling and preser¬
vation in Kyrenia castle.
2. ANTIKYTHERA. Discovered in 1900 by
Greek sponge divers, this wreck achieved world¬
wide fame when helmeted divers raised a number
of bronzes, including the "Antikythera Youth",
thought to be an original by the Greek sculptor
Lysippos. Dated at between 50 and 80 B.C., the
wreck also yielded up a decorated bronze bed,
36 marble statues, a gold earring in the form of
Eros playing the lyre, glass vessels, the gears
from an astronomical Instrument and amphoras,
cups, pitchers, jugs and cooking-pots.
Photo © Pennsylvania University Museum,
National Geographic Society
The bottom of the Mediterranean has
been called " the greatest remaining
treasure-house of information about
the ancient world." Already, scores of
ancient shipwrecks, representing near¬
ly every period of antiquity, have been
found in the Mediterranean. Many have
been photographed or briefly described ;
others are known only from finds made
by fishermen. On these pages, George F.
Bass, an experienced underwater archae¬
ologist in Mediterranean waters, and
author of the article on page 8, describes
briefly some of the more noteworthy of
the wrecks which have been studied in
detail, through mapping, salvage or
actual excavation, between 1900 and
1968. The material is condensed from
the author's article published in Unesco 's
new book " Underwater Archaeology ".
12
9. SPARGI. New mapping
techniques for underwater ex¬
cavation, Including the use of a
grid for identification and re¬
cording, developed following
the operation at Albenga In
1950, were used in the excava¬
tion of a 100 B.C. Roman
amphora carrier that had sunk
In 20 metres of water between
the island of Spargi and Sardi¬
nia. The ship, about 35 metres
long and nine metres wide, was
sheathed in lead held in place
by copper nails. It carried some
3,000 amphoras, of which 300
were raised, as well as many
dishes, bowls and pitchers.
10. 11. MARZAMEM1. Two wrecks were
found off the coast of Sicily in 1958-1959.
One, lying In six metres of water not far
from Marzamemi, contained decorative
stonework for an early Christian church,
Including an ornate marble pulpit. The
ship, sailing from Constantinople or some
Aegean city, about 500 A.D., was perhaps
bound for Italy, Sicily or North Africa
where the church was to be erected. The
second cargo ship, lying at about the
same depth near Marzamemi, contained
fifteen huge blocks of coarsely worked
building stone from Greece, dating from
the third century A.D.
12. 13. SAN PIETRO AND
TORRE SGARRATA.
Searching for evidence
about Roman commerce
in marble, granite and
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
3. ARTEMISION. A masterpiece of 5th
century B.C. Greek sculpture, the
famous bronze statue of Poseidon or
Zeus (see front cover) came to light
with the discovery of one of its arms
In 1928 by a Greek sponge diver near
Cape Artemision on the northern coast
of the Greek Island of Euboea. The re¬
mainder of the statue was later recov¬
ered together with a bronze jockey
and parts of a galloping horse of the
Hellenistic period. It is thought that an
entire cargo of about the time of Christ
still lies beneath the sand.
4. 5. METHONE. The cargoes are oii
that remain of two wrecks off Cape Spitha,
near Methone, the ships themselves having
been eaten away by shipworm and broken
up by waves. The first cargo consisted of
fragments of about 16 granite columns,
broken before shipment and probably from
a destroyed building. Pottery fragments
suggest that the ship went down In late
Roman times. Four granite sarcophagi with
lids and a few ballast stones are all that
rerrjain of the second wreck which dates
from the 2nd or 3rd century A.D.
Photo © Guido Ucelll
6. 7. LAKE NEMI. Two enormous
Roman ships, each more than 230 feet
long, sank In Lake Neml, 16 miles
from Rome, In the 1st century A.D.
An unsuccessful attempt was made
to salvage one of them In 1446. In
1535, a diver wearing a crude wooden
helmet inspected the wrecks, and in
1827 an 8-man diving bell was used
to explore them. A large scale sal¬
vage operation was begun in 1928.
Pumping lowered the water level by
70 feet (photo above); 4 years later, the
ships, now high and dry, were re¬
moved to a museum. These "floating
palaces" were equipped with heated
baths and their decks were paved
with mosaics and coloured marble
slabs. Both ships were destroyed
during World War II .
B. ALBENGA. The wreck of a Roman ship
lying in 44 m. of water, near Albenga in north¬
west Italy, was first investigated in 1950 after
a fisherman had brought up amphoras in his
nets. A grab, directed by observers In a
diving bell, brought up over 1,000 complete or
fragmentary amphoras and dishes, bowls, stor¬
age jars, jugs and cooking-pots, presumably
from the ship's galley.
porphyry, a University of
Pennsylvania team mapped
a 3rd century cargo of
22 unfinished sarcophagi
off San Pietro, south-east
of Taranto, in 1964. In¬
vestigation of another
wreck near Taranto, at
Torre Sgarrata, revealed
18 sarcophagi and 23
roughly-hewn blocks. The
planking, frames and part
of the keel were raised.
Pottery, tiles and coins
date the wreck to the late
2nd or early 3rd century.
14. MAHDIA.
A 1st century B.C.
wreck was dis¬
covered in 1907
by sponge divers,
and some of Its
cargo, consisting of parts of buildings
stone bases, capitals and marble
columns and statues, was salvaged
by helmeted sponge divers between
1908 and 1913. Well preserved bronzes,
including the figure of a herm signed
by Boethos of Chalcedon (see centre .
colour pages), figurines of dancing
dwarfs, and busts were recovered.
Wearing aqualungs, an expedition led
by the French underwater exploration
pioneers, Jacques-Yves Cousteau and
Philippe Tailliez, cleared mud from the
wreck In 1948. This marked the start
of "aqualung archaeology" which made
scientific excavation possible for the
first time.
15. CAPE GELIDONYA. A wreck, dating
back to around 1200 B.C., was discovered
by Turkish sponge divers near Cape Gelidonya,
In south-west Turkey in 1958. Two years later,
the vessel was . completely, excavated by a
team from the University of Pennsylvania
Museum and the London University Institute
of Archaeology. The cargo consisted of about
one ton of metal, including some thirty-four
large copper ingots, smaller ones and traces
of tin Ingots. Mixed with the ingot fragments
were hundreds of broken bronze tools being
transported for their scrap value. Objects
found on board suggest that this was a Syrian
ship which had taken the metal aboard in
Cyprus before sailing westwards.
16. 17. YASSI ADA. 3,533 individual dives were made during
the excavation, between 1961 and 1964, of a 7th century Byzan¬
tine wreck at Yassl Ada, near Bodrum, in south-west Turkey (see
back cover). This wreck provided an opportunity for a unique
efficiency study of underwater archaeological methods. Finds
included probably the largest dated hoard of Byzantine pottery
plates, cups, pitchers, bowls, cooking-pots, lamps and the ship's
water jar. Lying only a few metres away, in slightly deeper
water, was another wreck whose cargo of amphoras Is thought
to date from the fifth or sixth century.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
A gem of 4th century B.C. Greek art, this magnificent
bronze statue was discovered embedded in the river Hérault
in the centre of the southern French town of Agde. Though
the city Is now 4 kilometres (3 miles) from the coast, as
early as the 6th century B.C. it was a busy Mediterranean
port, and the statue comes from an ancient shipwreck.
The harbour later became silted up, leaving the town high
and dry far from the seashore. The "Ephebe of Agde",
as the statue is known, now stands In the Louvre in Paris,
facing the celebrated "Winged Victory of Samothrace", but
it will eventually grace a specially-built museum at Agde.
ENGLISH CHANNEL
**
Aber- !<
Ildut Treompan
cf S
Brest . .
Rors-Liogan
Saint-Mathieu
Camaret
FRANCE
Penmarc'h
Loctudy
Courreaux de Groix Er-Lanic
Quiberon
Cardinaux
1
Belle-Ile
ATLANTIC OCEAN
Estuary of the Gironde
100 underwater sites
off the coasts of France
The two maps on this page
show how the coasts of
France, from the English
Channel and the Atlantic
Ocean to the shores of the
Mediterranean and those
of Corsica, are dotted
with underwater archaeo-
FRANCE
s
c
a* i f i
Ï3 (D t -Ï ^
*# i « J
cf $Js (o?
S n° f, «° "9 V
* I * §
( « -O C :? P 3
) <a? P £ Ô5 » S «
f a» fc -S <> i? ¿F«
X. 'l?-5 «JÍÍ a.
' *«'J'Si' *'S'ff
RatSnneau #¿f <£
Le Frioul m~,C?.°, "
¡P Cr>^
P iL. *¿ o .*= a> cd
r -J CO #0 ¡I" -C
' »a et 1> O 3
11/5
1* VJ Marseillan-Plage
1
? .?c? le?* i "
* w j? 1 ? # Caco
? 5 | d ¿ï Bianco
Pomégué -j «o ¿ ¿i^» «, -S i Centuri
a o «
V 0, ü
,C to . i w
a ff s £
' ff o
,*> 5 -O
tt
1
tt ^ c _. Capo Corso
ft- .»,. * Saint- Florent
,-u >. Z ? * s
d Hyères o,, o |_ de Gargalo
.. -j.aj i» Porto
/-J ? CORSICA
^/
"OS s
t? j> ~- -* jjAjaccio
w Favone
"7të-t=r .... .9 Porto-
-4 m # Port-Vendres MEDITERRANEAN SEA a>v^^^B- Capo di Muro g Vecchio
1 A ^talBBBr 1. Bruzzi ! Maestro-
1 ¡X Z Cap Bear £ Maria
1 T
5
ft.
CapSperone Cavallo
Balise du Prêtre Perduto
W 1. Lavezzi Gavetti
logical sites. About a
hundred, explored during
the past 20 years, are
described by the French
underwater archaeologist
Denis Fonquerle, in Unes¬
co's new book, "Under¬
water Archaeology". Off
the coast of Brittany, ob¬
jects ranging from prehis¬
toric tools and weapons
to cannon from naval and
pirate vessels of the 18th
century have been found.
From the Mediterranean,
richest hunting ground of
all, thousands of ampho¬
ras and pottery vessels
that once served the thri¬
ving trade in wine and oil,
ancient bronze or stone
statues, ingots of copper
and lead, stone anchors,
mosaics and enormous
numbers of everyday
objects have been salvag¬
ed. At Grand Congloué,
on the Mediterranean, ex¬
cavations directed by Yves
Cousteau and Yves Glrault
have recovered over 6,000
items. At one site on the
coast near Agde some
1,300 objects were brought
up from a wreck dating
from the Bronze Age.
Maps reproduced from "Underwater Archaeology*
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
TRIALS OF AN UNDERWATER ARCHAEOLOGIST (Continued from page 9)
2.000 bicycle spokes for a single wreck
Every two and a half minutes, on a
given radio signal, each transit operator
radioed the bearings he was reading
at that moment on the mast of the
boat, and these bearings were used
by a fourth student, on board, who
plotted each position of the boat and,
therefore, the course of the search.
Thus it was possible to return, directed
by radio messages from the transit
operators, to the same spot again and
again.
In this manner, we found three
wrecks nearly 300 feet deep in a few
days. It is impossible, for physiological
reasons, to work so deep breathing
compressed air, and we do not yet
have the equipment or expertise to
dive with the required mixture of
helium and oxygen. When we do,
however, we should approach these
wrecks in the same way as we have
approached those previously ex¬
cavated.
1 O begin the detailed
records and plans which must follow
each stage of an excavation, a site
should be first measured and photo¬
graphed. Normally the cargo, if of
wine jars or stone blocks, will need
to be cleaned of sea growth with
scrubbing brushes to allow more
detailed mapping.
Much of the cargo and all of the
preserved wood of the ship, however,
will still lie invisible beneath sand or
mud, unless the wreck lies on bare
rock (which immediately indicates that
little or none of its wooden hull will
have been protected from shipworms).
Metal detectors and diver-operated
core-samplers can often determine the
extent of the wreck under the sand, as
can simple metal probes; a proton
magnetometer will, additionally, show
deposits of iron.
Once the size and orientation of a
wreck is known, it is a good idea to
build a rigid, level frame or grid over
the . entire site, dividing it into two-
metre squares. This should be as
close above the wreck as possible,
held up on legs; it can accomodate
slopes and mounds by being stepped.
It can be made of angle-iron and pipe,
or, in order to avoid attracting metal
detectors, of plastic irrigation tubing.
This "scaffolding" serves a variety
of purposes. Pairs of excavators can
be assigned to specific squares, identi¬
fied by numbers and letters, to which
they can return again and again, thus
ensuring continuity of effort. Divers
can also lie across the framework
while excavating, keeping their knees
and fins away from fragile remains.
Lastly, and this was its original pur¬
pose, the frame proves an aid in
mapping, either as support for photo
graphic towers or as a reference for
artists.
We now retain our framework mainly
for the first two reasons, since we
have found a faster method of mapping
than with photo towers. We float a
bar horizontally about 15 feet above
part of the site (the ends of the bar
are buoyed by air-filled oil tins, and
kept level by wires running to concrete
blocks below). On the bar are a
series of marks an equal distance
apart. We hang a special camera on
gimbals from the bar so that it points
straight down, and then slide it along
the bar, taking a picture at each of the
marks.
Each two photographs forms a stereo
pair, allowing us to view the wreck in
three dimensions. Further, knowing
the focal length of the camera, we can
use these pairs to make accurate three¬
-dimensional maps of the site by aerial
survey techniques. This requires a
specially ground lens for our camera,
various measured controls on the sea
bed, stereoscopic mapping equipment
on land, and a knowledge of aerial
mapping techniques, but the method
proves remarkably efficient since it
requires a minimum of diving time. A
more sophisticated version of the
method entails taking the photographs
with a pair of cameras mounted on
the bow of our two-man submarine.
Once objects have been mapped in
their original positions, essential for
the eventual reconstruction of the ship,
they may be removed and taken to the
surface. Commercial lifting balloons
of plastic or rubberized canvas, filled
with air on the sea bed from an air
hose or tank, easily raise to the sur¬
face baskets or trays of artifacts
weighing many pounds or even tons.
Once on the surface, objects may be
towed ashore or winched onto a boat.
After the visible cargo has been thus
mapped and removed, it is time to
dig through the sand or mud into the
next layer. For this picks and
shovels being impractical under water
a suction tube, called an air-lift,
may be used.
This is very easily made: tie a
concrete block to around 30 feet of
PVC irrigation pipe four to six inches
in diameter (this plastic tubing is manu¬
factured in every Mediterranean coun¬
try I have visited). Stick the lower
end of an air hose, supplied with air
from a compressor on a boat or barge
on the surface, into one end of the
tube and give the other end an upward
shove. The air inside the tube will
then rush toward this raised end,
floating the entire tube into a nearly
vertical position; the correct length of
rope between the tube and the con¬
crete block, however, will keep the
tube at an angle so that sand and mud
sucked up through it will fall away
from the excavation area. The suction
is caused by the rush of expanding air
going up the pipe.
Heavy air-lifts of metal, reinforced
rubber, or thick plastic used by us, and
most underwater archaeologists in the
past, are completely unnecessary and
impractical. Catch baskets, which
filter out sand but trap small artifacts
inadvertently sucked up by the air-lift,
may be attached to the top of the tube,
but this creates problems of balance.
Wood remains are best excavated
by hand, with the air-lift held just above
to suck away the cloud of obscuring
mud which occurs during excavation.
To keep pieces of wood in their exact
positions until accurately plotted,
sharpened bicycle spokes can be
driven through them into the sea bed,
holding the soft wood in place (we
have used over 2,000 spokes on a
single wreck). Wood fragments, as
well as all artifacts, should be labelled
with numbered plastic tags so that
once raised to the surface they can
be matched with underwater photo¬
graphs and drawings.
of the work described
will require a good number of divers.
The complete excavation of a modest-
size shipwreck about 65 feet long, we
have found in two instances, takes
about 1,200 man-hours on the sea bed;
and each of our divers can dive
normally less than an hour per day,
in two dives. An excavation is
obviously not something which can
be done by two divers on spare
weekends, although this is too
commonly believed by some amateur
divers.
We dive from a 50-foot-long flat
barge, which holds all of our equip¬
ment as well as up to two dozen divers.
These always work in pairs, for safety,
and use either Scuba breathing
apparatus (using compressed-air tanks)
or, especially for longer dives, hookah
or narghile equipment (using hoses
from surface-based compressors).
With the latter method, the diver al¬
ways wears a small tank with its own
regulator for emergency. Additionally,
we leave extra tanks and regulators at
convenient positions on the wreck.
Perhaps our most useful safety
device was actually designed to facilit¬
ate communications between divers,
and between divers and surface col¬
leagues. This Is our "telephone
booth", a plexiglas hemisphere four
feet in diameter, on four iron legs
which keep the top of the transparent
dome about six feet high.
Fresh air is constantly pumped .i r
through a hose from the surface to 1 J)
this plastic bubble, which also contains
a telephone connected to the diving
barge. At a depth of 140 feet, it is
CONTINUED PAGE 38
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
Left, 14th century merchant ship (known as a cog) on seal of
the Baltic seaport of Stralsund (German Dem. Rep.). A similar
vessel (1400 A.D.) was raised recently from the Weser river
near Bremen harbour.
Photo © Roger Vlollet, Paris
Under
the icy seas
of
northern Europe
by Ole Crumlin-Pedersen
16
I HE North Sea, the Baltic,
and the rivers emptying into them, have
served for thousands of years as
major trade routes in northern Europe.
The traffic was as heavy as in the
Mediterranean, and countless ships
have sunk In these waters. But clim¬
atic and natural conditions make
archaeological investigation here
entirely different from what it is in
the Mediterranean.
The North Sea and the Baltic are
within the continental shelf area, and
depths in excess of 100 metres occur
only at the northerly end of the North
Sea and the Skagerrak, and in parts
of the Baltic. Not only the coastal
waters but large areas of the sea bot¬
tom are accessible for ordinary diving
up to a depth of 50 m.
Wood-destroying organisms are less
prevalent than in warmer, saltier waters
such as the Mediterranean. Ship-
worm (Teredo navalis) does not resist
consistently low temperatures and
OLE CRUMLIN-PEDERSEN, of Denmark. Is
director of the Institute of Maritime Archae¬
ology at the Danish National Museum, Copen¬
hagen. A naval architect, he has been tech¬
nical director since 1957 of the Skuldelev
project for the excavation and recovery of
five ancient Viking ships In Roskilde Fiord,
Denmark. He is director of the Viking Ship
Museum, opened at Roskilde In 1969 to
house the salvaged vessels. This article is a
condensation of the chapter 'Wrecks in the
North Sea and the Baltic', from Unesco's
new book 'Underwater Archaeology"
requires a salinity of 0.9 per cent to
thrive. In waters with a low saline con¬
tent, its attack diminishes as the sali¬
nity of the water diminishes, ceasing
entirely at a concentration of 0.7 per
cent. Hence the whole of the Baltic
is free of damage by shipworm.
Neither can coral-forming organisms
survive under such conditions, so that
wood and other organic material
present are often extraordinarily well
preserved, even when unprotected by
sedimentary deposits. Thus in many
parts of this area conditions favour
the preservation of wrecks.
Shipwrecks occur in considerable
numbers, especially along the major
sea routes, for example off the island
of Anholt in the middle of the Kattegat
at the entrance to the Baltic, and they
make up the largest group of finds.
Between 1858 and 1881 alone, 125
ships were wrecked on the shoals
surrounding this island, and numerous
older wrecks have been found off its
shores.
In the Netherlands, the draining of
the Zuider Zee also uncovered many
wrecks. Within the Noordoostpolder,
the 540 sq. km. section now drained,
156 wrecks, dating from the twelfth
century to the twentieth, have been
recorded.
However, the wreckage of ships is
not all that can be recovered from the
North Sea and the Baltic. On the
Schlei in Schleswig, the remains of a
harbour have been found near the
CONTINUED PAGE 18
Drawing from "Wasa",
by E. Clauson and A. Franzen
© Nordiska Uppslagsbocker, Stockholm
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Staten9 Sjöhistoriska Museum, Stockholm
RAISING THE 'WASA'. In 1961, Swedish salvage engineers raised the warship "Wasa" from the bottom of Stockholm
harbour where it had sunk at the start of its maiden voyage in 1628. Above, the "Wasa" is towed away on a huge
concrete pontoon to a specially prepared museum site. During the unprecedented rescue operation of the "Wasa", lasting
from 1957 to 1961, divers tunnelled passages under the hull for lifting cables, and pontoons raised the 700 ton vessel
from the mud (drawing left). An arduous series of 18 lifting and dragging operations brought the "Wasa" into shallow
water. Divers plugged every hole in the hull, and as pumps emptied the ship at the rate of 7,500 gallons a minute,
it rose slowly to the surface and was towed to a dry dock.
VIKING DRAGON SHIPS. Underwater excavations at
Skuldelev, in Roskilde Fjord, Denmark, in 1957 brought
to light five Viking ships deliberately sunk nearly ten
centuries ago to block the entrance to the fjord. To
uncover the site, a coffer dam was built round the
ships and the area pumped free of water. Above,
reconstruction of one of the vessels, a 16-metre trad¬
ing ship. A Viking warship also found at Skuldelev
Is similar to the 1,100 years old "drakkar" or dragon
ship (photo left) unearthed in 1880 at Gokstad, near
Oslo Fjord, Norway. It had served as the grave
of the Viking king Olaf, who died in 880.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
18
UNDER THE ICY SEAS (Continued)
Viking settlement of Hedeby and, in
Danish waters, defences in the form
of barriers across channels have been
located in many places, e.g., sunken
stone-filled ships (the Skuldelev ships
in Roskilde Fjord) or long rows of
posts.
Shifts in the level of land and sea
have also submerged valuable archae¬
ological material. In the Early Stone
Age (9000-7000 B.C.) most of the North
Sea, the coastal waters of Denmark
and the western Baltic were all part
of the North European continent, but
by about 5000 B.C. Denmark had
roughly the same waters as now.
Since then, a tipping process has
taken place about an axis running
through Denmark, with a resultant
upheaval in Norway, Sweden and
northern Denmark, whereas subsi¬
dence in southern Denmark and north¬
ern Germany resulted in the submer¬
gence of neolithic burial-grounds and
settlements.
Traces of Stone Age settlements
have been found in many places off
the coast of Denmark. No methodical
examination has yet been made, but
there is every reason to believe that
underwater archaeology will open up
fresh perspectives here, since the
earliest Stone Age coastal settlements
that are today unknown can be
found at depths of from 20 to 30 metres
in Danish waters.
Only in recent years has more sys¬
tematic investigation of archaeological
material in the North Sea and Baltic
areas been undertaken. But the sal¬
vage of objects of historical interest
was begun as early as 1847, when a
diver from a Danish salvage company
found the wreck of a fifteenth-century
ship off Anholt. His finds included
eight wrought iron cannon which were
acquired by Danish museums.
The first true archaeological under¬
water investigation in Denmark took
place in 1943 when the Director of the
National Museum, Dr. Poul Norlund,
together with a professional diver,
examined the wreckage of a medieval
cog in Kolding Fjord.
Because conditions for the preserv¬
ation of wrecks are more favourable in
the North Sea and the Baltic than in
the Mediterranean, important ship finds
have been brought to light which show
how difficult it is to say where the limit
lies between archaeology above and
below water.
The actual salvaging of the Wasa,
the Swedish warship that sank in
Stockholm harbour within minutes
of setting off on its maiden voyage
in 1628, took place in deep water;
the hull was subsequently excav¬
ated, after it had been brought to
the surface. The Zuider Zee excav¬
ations show that wrecks can be suc¬
cessfully excavated on dry land as
they were in the short space of time
after completion of the drainage and
before the ships' timbers began to
rot.
Photo W. Ruoff. Zurich (Switzerland).
Photo © Dimitn Rebikoff
#>.^^a
Photo © Flip Schulke
Black Star. New York.
COLOUR PAGES
Opposite
SUNKEN VILLAGE. These wooden piles emerging from the
bed of Lake Zurich, in Switzerland, mark the site of a Stone
Age village that once stood on the lake shore. A 3.80 m.
deep trench dug into the lake bottom by underwater archaeo¬
logists revealed one Bronze Age and four Stone Age layers
(two visible on left of photo). Material recovered from this
and other European waters pottery, bone and wood tools,
fabrics and wickerwork, often remarkably preserved throws
new light on the Neolithic and Bronze Age cultures.
EMERALDS, INGOTS AND PIECES OF EIGHT. Part
of one of the largest underwater coin hoards ever
found (bottom left). They came from the wreck
of a Spanish treasure ship that went down near
Freeport in the Bahamas not far from the Florida coast,
about 1628. Right, "pieces of eight" and a magnifi¬
cent emerald-encrusted cross recovered from the
Spanish galleon "San José" at Islamorada Key in the
Bahamas. These crudely minted, angular coins were
chiselled from a flat bar of silver Top left, gold ingots
also salvaged from the "San José".
MASTERPIECES OF SCULPTURE FROM THE DEPTHS
Centre pages
ARCADIAN GOD. Greek sponge divers discovered the wreck of a 1st century
B.C. ship off the Tunisian coast, near Mahdia, in 1907. The vessel had set out
from Athens filled with booty following the sack of the city by the Roman
dictator Sulla in 86 B.C. One of many works of art recovered was this head
of Pan, god of shepherds and flocks, whose cult originated in Arcadia and
spread to Athens in the 5th century B.C. Now in the Bardo Museum in Tunis.
Photo Desjardins © Réalités. Paris
MARATHON BOY. Head of a full length bronze statue netted by a
fisherman in Marathon Bay, Greece, in 1925. Standing 4 ft. 3ins. high,
the statue of this handsome youth is thought by some experts to be an
original work of the great 4th century B.C. Greek sculptor Praxiteles.
Photo National Museum. Athens (Greece)
MASTERPIECE SIGNED 'BOETHOS'. One of the finest bronzes
found in the Mahdia wreck was this bronze herm, which bears the
signature of the 2nd century B.C. sculptor Boethos of Chalcedon.
Herms, square pillars surmounted by busts of the god Hermes, were
common in Athens where they were used as milestones, signposts and
boundary-marks. This rare signed work of the Hellenistic period is in
the Bardo Museum, Tunis.
Photo Desjardins © Réalités. Paris
THE PHILOSOPHER. Recovered from a ship that went down off the
island of Antikythera, midway between Crete and the southern coast of
Greece, this powerful head is thought to be the portrait of a 3rd century
B.C. philosopher. Divers reported seeing fragments of the draped body,
but only the head was recovered.
Photo National Museum. Athens (Greece)
Page 22
NYMPH EMERGED FROM THE WAVES. Like this lovely woman's
head, many of the marbles recovered from the Mahdia wreck off the
coast of Tunisia, show the effects of 2,000 years of immersion in sea
water and the ravages of marine organisms. Only those parts that
became covered by a protective layer of sand survived more or less
intact. The head is now in the Bardo Museum, Tunis.
Photo Desjardins © Réalités. Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
;*¿l
-
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
BURIED TREASURE
BENEATH
THE SPANISH MAIN
by Mendel L. Peterson
I HE early shipwreck sites
in North America are to be found along
the great Spanish treasure route which
ran from Spain to the Caribbean and
returned to Europe by way of the
Florida Straits.
During the later voyages of Colum¬
bus, the Spanish realized that the sea
and air currents of the North Atlantic
flowed in a clockwise direction. Utiliz¬
ing these currents, ships leaving
Spain for America would sail down the
west coast of Africa to the Cape Verde
Islands. Here they caught the trade
winds which blow steadily westward.
After a voyage of two weeks or so, they
would make a landfall north of Trini¬
dad and enter the Caribbean Basin.
At the height of Spanish power in
the New World, the fleet was organized
in two major convoys: the fleet of
galleons, which served the port of
Cartagena and, indirectly Porto Bello
and South America, and the Flota
which served the port of Vera Cruz and
the Viceroyalty of New Spain (Mexico).
As the combined fleet entered the
Caribbean, the galleons would leave
the company of the Flota and proceed
to Cartagena. Here they would stay
while the merchant ships and small
escort vessels proceeded to Porto
Bello, and its fair.
At Porto Bello, merchants from Peru
MENDEL L. PETERSON historian and spe-
cialist on maritime questions, has explored
many historic underwater sites in the Florida
Straits, West Indies and Bermuda since 1952,
as part of a research programme on naval
history. He was formerly Curator of the
Department of History at the United States
National, Museum, in the Smithsonian Institu¬
tion, In Washington D.C. Dr Peterson has
written numerous articles on naval history
and on the study of coins and medals. This
article Is a condensation of the chapter
"Wreck Sites in the Americas", from Unes¬
co's new book "Underwater Archaeology".
and New Grenada exchanged gold,
silver, emeralds, hides, dyestuffs and
other natural products of the New
World against the manufactured goods
of Europe brought over by Spanish
merchants.
When the fair, which lasted a month
or so, was over, the merchants re¬
turned to the galleons at Cartagena,
the products of the New World were
loaded, and the ships prepared for the
journey home.
Meanwhile the Flota went on to Vera
Cruz where a similar fair took place.
Here, as in Panama, the goods of the
mother country and Europe were ex¬
changed for the wealth of America and
for such precious products of the Far
East as silk and porcelain.
After the fair at Vera Cruz, the Flota
loaded and set sail up the coast of
what is now Texas but was then called
Florida, into the Gulf of Mexico and
down the west coast of Florida past the
dry Tortugas into the port of Havana.
This course was necessary to avoid
head winds.
The galleons from Cartagena and
their convoy rejoined the Flota here.
When ready, the combined fleets sailed
up the Florida Straits, speeded along
on the three-knot Florida current until
they cleared the northern Bahamas.
Here they steered north-east and came
close to Bermuda. Taking a last fix
on those islands they set course for
the Azores and Spain, helped on by
the prevailing westerly winds.
With the beginning of English ex¬
ploration and colonization in North
America a new route came into use.
The English chose to face the head¬
winds of the central Atlantic rather
than sail the long route to the Carib¬
bean and up the Straits of Florida
through waters patrolled by hostile
Spanish ships.
This route led directly from the coast
of Portugal to North America by way
of Bermuda. The English, of course,
used the same westerly winds as the
Spaniards in returning to Europe. As
trade developed between the expand¬
ing English colonies in North America
and the mother country, shipping in¬
creased along this northern route, and
so did the number of shipwrecks.
Finally, with the establishment of
French, English, Dutch and Danish
colonies in the Caribbean Basin, more
shipping was added to the stream and
shipwrecks from many nations began
to pile up in the Florida Straits and
Bermuda.
After the United States had become
independent, the already vigorous sea
trade redoubled, with a vast increase
in shipping along the Atlantic, Pacific
and Gulf coasts of the new republic.
These four-and-a-half centuries pro¬
duced innumerable shipwrecks along
the coasts of North America, and the
Bahamas and Bermuda.
The earliest major Spanish fleet
disaster occured on the Texas coast
near what is now called Padre Island.
In 1553 most, if not all, the New Spain
fleet bearing the silver and natural
products of the Viceroyalty was smash¬
ed by a violent hurricane. Only one
or two survivors returned to Mexico
to tell of the disaster.
East of the Florida Straits lie the
hundreds of islands comprising the
Bahamas archipelago. The Spaniards
did not establish posts in these islands,
which became the lair of freebooters
and privateers who preyed on the
Spanish ships sailing up the Florida
Straits.
In the spring of 1966 three American Vj
spear fishermen discovered an ancient
wreck site on the western side of
Highborn Key island, in the Exuma
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
BENEATH THE SPANISH MAIN (Continued)
The Caribbean: graveyard of countless galleons
24
chain. The site was marked by sand-
encrusted cannon, anchors and iron
fittings from the hull and rigging of the
ship, so well camouflaged that they
looked like a natural reef.
Lead cannon shot with iron cores
were found, and small iron fittings. The
cannon were not disturbed until a full-
scale expedition could be sent. The
next winter and spring the site was
explored, with the help of a grant from
the National Geographic Society, by
the discoverers (Tucker and Canton of
Bermuda) and the author. All metallic
remains of the ship's battery and fit¬
tings were salvaged, and Tucker made
accurate drawings of the guns, fittings,
and traces of ship timbers found under
the ballast.
The sharp lines of the timbers and
the armament, consisting of two bow-
chasers and 13 swivel guns, indicate
that this was probably a pirate ship
or privateer of about 200 tons that
took refuge at Highborn Key after
being damaged by storm or enemy
action, and finally sank while riding
at anchor. The wrought iron, breech-
loading guns, firing lead ball, date the
site at 1560-1580. Historically the site
is important for the survival of a com¬
plete battery of guns and ship's fittings
from this early period.
1 HE other side of the straits
the coast of Florida is even richer
in sites than the Bahamas. This
"western flank of the gateway from the
Caribbean and Gulf of Mexico was
a lee shore when the violent tropical
storms blew up from the south-west
and, as early as the 1570s, numerous
wrecks had already been noted.
On at least three occasions, major
fleet disasters occured on the reefs
and beaches of Florida. In 1662, sev¬
eral ships of a Spanish fleet were
wrecked there and, in 1715 and 1733,
entire fleets were lost.
In 1950, the pioneer Florida under¬
water explorer Arthur McKee, Jr., be¬
gan to investigate a large site some
three miles off Plantation Key in 10 m.
of water. Subsequent investigations,
and checking with an eighteenth
century chart, suggested that the wreck
was that of the capitana (flag-ship) of
the Spanish fleet of 1733, which had
sailed from Havana on Friday, July 13
and was struck by a violent tropical
storm the following Sunday. Eight
ships were driven on to the reefs.
The spot was marked by the ship's
ballast, a high pile of basalt and granite
cobbles. On the ballast lay several,
guns, encrusted in coral and sand.
There were also numerous fragments
of Spanish redware jars.
During a six week investigation of
the site, over two seasons, a significant
collection of artifacts was recovered,
including fragments of Spanish cer¬
amics and Chinese porcelain from the
Manila galleon trade, tools, weapons
and cannon and fittings from the ship's
hull and rigging. Personal effects
found included pewter bowls, silver
forks, religious medals, silver stat¬
uettes and fine Spanish Majolica ware
fragments.
After the salvage, McKee recovered
some silver pieces of four and eight
reals of the crude earlier coinage now
being shipped out for the last time,
and a few of the very rare new milled
pieces of eight, first struck in the New
World at the Mexico City mint in 1732.
Some timber remains were observed
under the ballast, but systematic
excavation was not possible and no
drawings were made of the wooden
fragments on the site.
Several years later, some hundred
miles further north, another underwater
explorer, Kip Wagner, following clues
of coins washed up on the beach and
a notation on a chart in Bernard
Roman's Natural History of Florida
published In the 1770s, discovered the
site of the capitana of the 1715 fleet
like that of 1733, was destroyed
in a violent tropical storm.
Wagner and his associates recover¬
ed the usual ships fittings, ceramic
fragments, anchors, cannon, objects of
personal use and small arms and a
vast treasure of silver and gold which
included gold coins of hitherto un¬
known Mexico City mint issues; these
were of the greatest interest to numis¬
matists studying the early coinages of
Spanish America.
The most spectacular piece of jewel¬
lery was a magnificent gold chain from
which hung a golden dragon, with ruby
eyes, containing a gentleman's groom¬
ing accessories ear-spoon, toothpick,
and beard-plucker. Other jewellery
included pendants and crucifixes.
Among the more important dis¬
coveries on the site were unbroken
Chinese porcelain curs and bowls of
the late 17th century K'ang Hsi period
(the first ever recovered from an Amer¬
ican site); they had been preserved
by some miracle when the ship broke
up in the surf.
A letter written by the admiral of
the fleet (who supervised the salvage
of some of the other ships) describes
the capitana as breaking up in the
heavy waves just offshore where the
water was so turbulent that divers
could not reach the main treasure of
the vessel.
Magnetometer surveys during the
latter phases of the exploration prove
that the ship was scattered over a wide
area, and yet these fragile porcelain
vessels survived to supplement our
knowledge of the Manila galleon trade
through which fine goods from the
Far East were brought into the Spanish
treasure route to Europe. No large
portions of the ship's hull were found.
B ERMUDA, to the north¬
east, was the last important American
signpost on the road home. Here
Spanish pilots tried to get an accurate
picture of their position before setting
out across the trackless waters which
lay between them and safety in Seville.
Sailing too close to the island, ships
frequently ran aground on the sharp
coral reefs which extend into the sea
for distances of up to 20 km. Bermuda
thus became a graveyard of ships but
a rich mine for the underwater
archaeologist.
The first and richest find so far was
the site discovered by the underwater
explorer Tucker in 1950, from which
ship's guns and a few artifacts were
raised. Five years later, Tucker and
Canton returned and, within ten days,
they had recovered the most important
deposit of sixteenth-century material to
come from any site.
This marked the beginnings of under¬
water exploration in Bermuda. The site
yielded tools, heavy and light weapons,
navigators' instruments, including mer¬
cury hour-glasses of very sophisticat¬
ed workmanship, a magnificent Dutch
bronze mortar and a pewter clyster sy¬
ringe, perhaps the oldest known. Fit¬
tings from the ship's hull, which was
smashed to bits in the disaster, add to
our knowledge of contemporary ship
construction.
A surprising discovery was the
beautifully carved staff of office of an
Indian chief, and black palmwood bows
and arrows, souvenirs no doubt. Fine
pewter, bearing French touch marks,
and fine ceramics, including a Majolica
ink-well in the form of a lion mask,
belonged to officers or passengers.
The treasure itself consisted of a
gold bar, two gold ingots, two parts
of gold bars and another smaller gold
ingot, pearl-studded buttons, numerous
silver coins of the reign of Philip II,
CONTINUED PAGE 26
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Roger Vlollet, Paris
Perilous
homeward
voyage
Apart from storm and hurricane, hidden coral reefs and other natural hazards, the Spanish
treasure fleets returning from the New World faced attack by pirate ships and enemy squad¬
rons on the long voyage back to Spain. Above, contemporary engraving of a Spanish
treasure fleet trapped by the Dutch squadron of Admiral ,Pieter Pietersen Heyn off Cuba
in 1628. Below right, divers recover a gold Aztec mask from the wreck of Heyn's own
ship the "Van Lynden" which sank off the Bahamas in 1628. Below left, a magnificent
Aztec gold pectoral recovered from the same wreck. The total value of this cargo has been
estimated at around £750,000.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
BENEATH THE SPANISH MAIN (Continued)
26
and the most magnificent object taken
from the ocean in modern times: an
emerald pectoral cross, a breath-taking
masterpiece. The emeralds are of the
finest quality, seven of them represent¬
ing the seven last words of Christ on
the cross. A small chamber in the
back of the cross once held a relic,
organic in nature judging by the stains
on the gold.
No remains of the hull were found
large enough to be measured and
studied. The ship, not yet identified,
may be the San Pedro.
Eight years after his first discovery,
Tucker made another on the south¬
western reefs of the island: the San
Antonio, which sank in September
1621. The brief records in the Bermuda
archives indicate that the ship had
sunk by the bow, and that the crew
and passengers had got ashore safely;
the Bermudans had salvaged the cargo
and recovered the guns, the Spaniards
finally getting back to Spain, without
their cargo and personal possessions.
From the cargo, traces of leaf
tobacco, thin sheets of tanned and
dyed leather, indigo dye, traces of
cochineal, tortoise shell and lignum
vitae (an American hardwood) were
found. Jewellery recovered included
gold earrings set with crystal and
seed pearls, a beryl ring, a gold
nugget, gold buttons and a perfect one-
carat emerald set in a plain gold ring.
Another ring was set with three stones
garnet, crystal and emerald. There
was a gold medal of the Virgin Mary
and the Virgin of Guadeloupe. Hun¬
dreds of single tiny gold links for a
chain were found, unsoldered, scatter¬
ed about the timbers of the ship.
It is believed that this chain was
used as a form of currency, the links
of a measured weight and purity being
left unsoldered for easy separation.
Another form of money was found:
cowry shells, in thousands. These
little shells, were being brought to
Spain for use in the slave trade with
West Africa, where the cowry was
much sought and highly valued.
Pieces of eight, struck at the Potosi
mint in Upper Peru and bearing the
titles of Philip II and Philip III, furnished
a first dating index. The circumstances
of the actual sinking could be deduced
from the position of the ballast. Tim¬
ber remains led to the Identification of
the vessel. This site has furnished
important details of the armament and
fittings of a Spanish ship of the period,
her cargo, and life aboard during the
voyage to Spain.
As the English began to establish
settlements, Bermuda became a station
on the direct route to North America
from Europe. The island was settled
by Europeans accidentally when the
Sea Venture was wrecked there in
1609 on a voyage from England to
Virginia.
Three other early English shipwrecks
two within a year of each other
have been discovered and explored.
The Eagle, bound for Virginia with
settlers and supplies, crashed on the
coral heads to the north-east of the
islands in 1659 and went down in a
deep ravine among jagged coral out-
croppings. The Eagle was compara¬
tively small.
Much larger was the Virginia Mer¬
chant and much more tragic her loss.
With almost 200 aboard, she was
caught by a severe storm even before
clearing Bermuda, dashed on the rocky
coast and, striking an off-lying coral
head, was broken to bits and scattered
along the rocks. Only twelve people
survived. Some of the guns, ordnance
stores, ship fittings and personal be¬
longings of the crew and passengers
have been found.
The most recently discovered early
English shipwreck is that of the War¬
wick, sunk in Castle Harbour by a
severe northern gale in November
1619. The ship was partially salvaged
at the time, but her location was for¬
gotten. In the summer of 1967, an
expedition found the site in deep mud.
Many other wrecks exist to the north
of the Straits of Florida, including that
of the American civil war blockade-
runner Modern Greece which was sunk
off the coast of North Carolina. It has
been estimated that off the coast of
New Jersey alone some 5,000 wrecks
of all types remain.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
!
* a2
'Mef
5f
fc: Ä1-
É
. iah» ^r
lv7 *jT*9h
*S ^4&S?S
* ^BP" ^%r*L
*v ". v
V
r5 ;ib "fe v JLJ^HV.
ft 1
.**
X J.^A¿&
The enigma
of the
Bahamas
The discovery In 1969 of a series
of huge stone blocks resembling a
"wall" or "pavement" In the sea off
the Island of North Bimini, in the
Bahamas, has puzzled specialists and
sparked off an international contro¬
versy as to their origin. (Above,
stereoscopic mosaic of the blocks,
first located by the underwater explo¬
rer and photographer Dlmitrl Rebi-
koff). Some believe these stones to
be man-made structures; others iden¬
tify them as a natural limestone for¬
mation lying on a larger stratum of
rock. Dimitri Rebikoff has since
discovered another "wall", similar and
parallel to the first and linked, as
are the first blocks, to an alignment
of stone some 600 metres long.
Carbon 14 tests on nearby submerg¬
ed peat layers give a date of about
5000 B.C. This has led to speculation
that the "wall" is part of a man-
made prehistoric site. Man-made or
natural formation, the stones of the
Bahamas remain an enigma. Left,
aqualung divers following the line of
blocks give an idea of their size
(some are five metres square and
from 30 to 60 cm. thick).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
The drowned city
of Port Royal
by Robert F. Marx
28
Shipwrecks are not the
only source of data for the marine ar¬
chaeologist working in the Caribbean.
Ringed almost completely by an earth¬
quake belt, it has provided another
type of underwater site: the sub¬
merged town.
Two of the three recorded James¬
town, off the Island of Nevis, and
Orangetown, off the Island of St. Eus-
tatius sank as the result of the same
earthquake on April 30, 1680. The
couple of hundred buildings of
Jamestown, the main sugar port, lie in
from 3 to 10 metres of water, covered
now by about one metre of sand. Of
the 150 buildings in Orangetown, a
smugglers' base located on a bluff
overlooking the sea, about a third top¬
pled into the sea, In depths of from
7 to 20 m.
Neither town came anywhere close
in size and importance to Port Royal,
in Jamaica, the third earthquake vic¬
tim. In four decades, thanks to pri¬
vateering and the contraband trade
with the Spanish colonies, it had
become the most important trading
centre in the Caribbean and possibly
in the whole New World.
Shortly before noon on June 7, 1692,
there were three strong earth tremors,
quickly followed by a tidal wave. With¬
in minutes, nine-tenths of the city's
2,000 buildings, many two and three
storeys high, had either sunk or slid
into the sea, and over 2,000 persons
perished. No accurate estimate is
available of the material losses.
Apart from the number and variety
of sites, the Caribbean has two other
ROBERT F. MARX, specialist in maritime his¬
tory and marine archaeology, particularly of
the Spanish colonial period in the Caribbean,
directed the mapping and excavation of the
sunken city of Port Royal, Jamaica (1965-68).
He has discovered and explored a number
of Mayan archaeological sites and 'cenotes'
(sacred wells) as well as many wrecks in
the Caribbean and off the coasts of Spain.
This article Is a condensation of the chap¬
ter, "The Submerged Ruins of Port Royal,
Jamaica", from Unesco's new book "Under¬
water Archaeology".
advantages for marine archaeology.
First, an enormous wealth of sources
is available, mainly in Spanish
archives, to aid in locating and identi¬
fying sites and furnish information
about the artifacts recovered. Sec¬
ondly, the working conditions are
extremely favourable. The clarity of
the water in most areas facilitates
location, and photography in situ or
as an aid in mapping.
Most sites are in shallow waters.
These can be rough on an exposed
reef, but there are no strong tides
or, in most places, even currents, and
no danger to divers of nitrogen narco¬
sis or the "bends". Uniformly warm
temperatures and fine weather permit
work to continue throughout the year
even in the hurricane season, weeks
of complete calm are common.
Port Royal offers the most exten¬
sive and important underwater site in
the western hemisphere. Salvage op¬
erations began there on the very day
it sank beneath the sea in 1692, and
continued for many years.
In January 1966, the Jamaican gov¬
ernment began a long-term, proper
excavation of the site which is expect¬
ed to continue for many years. It was
my good fortune to be selected to
direct the project, and I spent the
first four months of 1966 making a
thorough survey.
This indicated that the site measured
some 140,000 square metres in depths
of from 1 to 20 m. of water with
75 per cent in less than 10 m.
The composition of the bottom
sediment varies greatly. On average,
below the silt there is a 1 to 1.8 metre
deposit of hard packed mud and dead
coral fragments; below this deposit,
the sediment is about 70 per cent black
sand and 30 per cent coarse gravel.
A variety of excavation tools were
tested: two types of "prop-wash",
several types of water and air jets, hy¬
drolifts and air-lifts. Our final selec¬
tion was a 10 cm. diameter air-lift, with
a screen to prevent any artifacts larger
than a small coin from going up the
tube. We found that all the other
excavation tools, and even larger-
diameter air-lift tubes, could damage
artifacts.
The sediment is pumped to a barge
where it passes through a fine-mesh
screen and small objects (beads,
musket balls, pins, etc.) are recovered.
Larger artifacts are recovered on the
bottom and sent up in buckets.
A minimum of three divers are re¬
quired on the bottom: one to hold the
air-lift tube, one to send or carry arti¬
facts to the surface, and one to send
up bricks and other debris which are
too large to pass through the screen
on the air-lift tube.
Visibility rarely exceeds 30 to 60 cm
before the day's excavation starts.
Once pumping begins, it is reduced to
a few centimetres (around the mouth
of the air-lift tube) or zero. This makes
the work more difficult, as everything
must be done by touch.
The sophisticated horizontal and ver¬
tical control method used by land ar-
CONTINUED PAGE 38
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Above, contemporary drawing of the 1692 earthquake that brought
disaster to the great Caribbean trading centre and pirate lair of
Port Royal, Jamaica. Within minutes of the first tremor, 2,000
men, women and children had died and nine-tenths of the city's
2,000 buildings had disappeared into the sea. Major underwater
excavations at Port Royal began in 1966. More artifacts have
now been recovered than from all the wreck sites explored in
the Caribbean during the past two decades. Below left, diver
brings up a bucket of Items recovered from the drowned city,
while an air-lift spouts sand and water. Debris brought up by
the air-lift is retained by a huge sieve in the centre of the barge.
Below, two drawings, dated 1622, of salvage operations in Carib¬
bean waters. Left, Spaniards attempting to recover a small
vessel; right, primitive scoop used by early salvage engineers.
CD
O
CO
E
to i
*o ^^" 1
3 1 V
'
to
C
'¥ 1 Sil
© * ^^^"** "^w* ^ W*
O)
o
o
o.
^^ S^Ö***
4 'Jj-
r \sS^,f¿>¿*
«síSP
H
4*
.*
	L
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Drawing © from the book "Chlchen-ltza and Its Cenote of Sacrifice"
by Alfred M. Tozzer, Peabody Museum, Harvard University, U.S.A.
by
Pablo Bush Romero
The sacred well
of Chichen-ltza
30
1^ OTT ED throughout the
Maya country of the Yucatan Peninsula,
in Mexico, are thousands of wells
called cenotes. The Mayas used some
of the wells only as sources of water,
but others they considered sacred.
The best known of the Mayan sacred
cenotes is the well of Chichen-ltza, a
great city whose name means "the
mouth of the well of the Itza".
The cenote of Chichen-ltza, a "well
of sacrifice" into which human beings
and objects of all kinds were thrown
as offerings to Chac, god of rain and
water, was first explored by Edward H.
Thompson, a U.S. consul, between
1904 and 1907, in the first planned
underwater dig.
The edge of the well is 27 metres
above the water, 16 to 18 metres deep,
under which lie some 10 metres of silt
and mud. With a diameter of roughly
PABLO BUSH ROMERO, Mexican explorer,
traveller and author, founded the Exploration
and Water Sports Club of Mexico (CEDAM)
and its later development, CEDAM Interna¬
tional. He is a member of the Explorers
Club of New York and the Underwater World
Federation. He led several underwater re¬
search expeditions to Mayan sites In Mexico,
Including the famous sacred well of Chichen-
ltza in the Yucatan peninsula. His books on
underwater exploration in Mexico and wildlife
in Mexico and Africa have been published In
Spanish and English, including "Under the
Waters of Mexico". This article Is a conden¬
sation of the chapter "The Sacred Wells of
Chichen-ltza and other Freshwater Sites In
Mexico", from Unesco's new book 'Under¬
water Archaeology".
60 metres and walls slanting inwards,
the well is difficult to descend.
Most of the objects recovered by
Edward Thompson went to the Pea-
body Museum of Archaeology and
Ethnology in Harvard University,
U.S.A. Some of the artifacts, traced
to their place of origin, indicate that
the Mayas traded with Aztec tribes as
far north and west as the Valley of
Mexico, and as far south as present-
day Colombia, Costa Rica and Panama.
Objects brought up include symbolic
figures carved in jade (now preserved
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
Photo © René Burrl - Magnum, Paris
From the dark, mysterious depths of the sacred
well of Chichen-ltza, Mexico, (left) divers have
recovered a unique hoard of artifacts which has
given a comprehensive view of the aesthetic life
of the Mayas. Right, a broad, paved avenue
leads from the well to the main pyramid temple
of the city. Above, in the foreground, sculptured
wall of the main pyramid temple with view onto
the "Temple of the Warriors".
Drawing by Tatiana Proskounakoff 0 Peabody Museum, Harvard University, U.S.A.
in the Peabody Museum, which has
perhaps the world's greatest collection
of Mayan jade), stone sculptures, gold
and copper discs, remains of skeletons,
darts and dart throwers, heads of
arrows and spears made of flint and
other kinds of stone, bits of ancient
fabric and bells, pendants and other
items cast, engraved or beaten in gold.
Many of the supposedly gold objects
were of low grade alloy, containing
more copper than gold, and most of
the jade or gold objects were brought
up in fragments. They had apparently
been purposely broken, but in such a
way that heads and features were left
intact. ' Believed to have life, they
were "killed" by being broken before
being thrown into the well as offerings.
Thompson's writings indicate that he
had not recovered more than a tenth
of the contents of the well.
About half a century later, in 1954,
the Exploration and Water Sports Club
of Mexico, of which I was a director,
sent a scuba diving team to Chichen-
ltza to continue the work begun by
Edward Thompson. But it was soon
decided that recovery operations were
impossible with scuba equipment alone
because of the poor visibility and
difficulties with artificial lighting.
A second attempt was made by the
club in 1960-61 under the direction of
the National Institute of Anthropology
and History of Mexico and with the co¬
operation of the National Geographic
Society, in the U.S.A. Many artifacts
were recovered, but after four months,
operations were again suspended.
In 1967, the Mexican underwater
explorers with archaeologists from the
National Institute resumed work at the
well, this time with a group of American
associates. The idea was to pump the
well dry or get the water chemically
pure and crystal clear. Pumping low¬
ered the water-level about 5 metres,
but no further. The alternative was
then tried. Pumping was stopped and
the water was allowed to come back
to its original level (it was not possible
with the equipment on hand to pump
and filter at the same time).
An analysis of the water showed that
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
SACRED WELL
OF CHICHEN-ITZA (Continued)
it was worse than in a New York
sewer. Nevertheless, when the chem¬
ical treatment was finished and the
water filtered, it was possible to see
clearly for more than five metres and
the water was drinkable.
Work was resumed with modified
air-lifts which could to some extent
control the force of the water going
up to the screening tables. The mud
was lifted in layers, and all objects
larger than a button were brought up
by the divers. The work lasted two
and a half months.
All kinds of artifacts were re¬
covered: two beautifully carved
wooden stools, several wooden buck¬
ets, about one hundred jars and vases
of different sizes, designs and periods,
fabrics, gold Items, rings, bells, objects
made of jade, rock crystal, copal (in¬
cense), rubber, coral, bone, mother-of-
pearl, horn, amber, copper, quartz,
pyrite and onyx, human and animal
bones, grinding stones, five stone
jaguars and two stone serpents.
The expedition showed that it is
possible to clear and purify the water,
and that an air-lift properly handled
and controlled can be used to dig
underwater sites in cenotes. When
the air-lift disturbs the mud, taking
away the visibility, it can be lifted
about 20 to 30 cm. and very soon takes
away all the mud and particles in sus¬
pension, making it possible to see
again in a short time.
A preliminary study of the human
bones found revealed that there were
many more sacrifices of children than
adults a ratio of more than 50 per
cent children as against all others.
Other sacred Mayan wells have also
yielded up their treasures. From 1956
to 1965, E. Willys Andrews, Director of
the National Geographic Society,
Tulane University research programme
at Dzibilchaltun, near Chichen-ltza,
explored the 55 metres deep Zlacah
cenote with the help of divers from the
Exploration and Water Sports Club of
Mexico.
During the first three working sea¬
sons hundreds of artifacts were
brought up, including a surprisingly
large number of pottery vessels. Most
of the small objects some exquisitely
carved were apparently thrown in as
cult offerings.
In Guatemala, too, several lakes
have been explored and Mayan arti¬
facts recovered, and plans are being
made to investigate several wells at
Chincultic, in the Mexican state of
Chiapas.
On top of the Xinantecatl volcano,
near Toluca, about 100 kilometres from
Mexico City, are two lakes, the Lake
of the Moon and the larger Lake of the
Sun. From the second lake, 4,215
metres above sea level, underwater
explorers have recovered dozens of
copal (incense) offerings, some in the
shape of volcanoes with twin and
single peaks. The Lake may contain
an Aztec treasure hoard and is
scheduled for further exploration.
Left, this gold pendant from the well at Chichen-ltza, symbolizes a flute-playing
bird-god. A projecting nose covers the entire width of the face and the rows
of spirals flanking it are believed to represent wings. The style suggests
the work of Quimbaya Indian metalworkers in Colombia where the pendant was
probably made in the 16th century A.D.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
CH1CHEN-ITZA
GOLD DISCS
Ten decorated gold discs,
recovered from the sacred well
of Chichen-ltza, Mexico, record
incidents in the struggle between
the Yucatan Mayas and the
invading Tula-Toltec people. The
discs were torn into small
fragments (left) before being
thrown into the well and only one
has been recovered complete.
About ten inches in diameter,
the discs had an inch-wide border
pattern encircling a central
decoration which was usually
divided horizontally into three
segments, with the scene of action
depicted in the middle, a sky
deity 'above, and an earth monster
below. Above right, Mayan
warriors attempt to escape on
rafts or by swimming from their
Tula-Toltec pursuers in the canoe
seen at right This disc is
unusual in that it has no earth
monster at the bottom. The sky
deity is pictured with outstretched
arms against a background
representing a two-headed dragon with wide-open jaws and protruding, curling tongues.
Below, enlarged drawings of two sky deities. These always contain a serpentine element with
usually a human figure entwined in the coils or issuing from the mouth of the snake or dragon.
Photos and drawings © from the book 'Chichen-ltza and Its Cenote of Sacrifice", by Alfred M. Tozzer, Peabody Museum, Harvard University, U.S.A.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
by
Willard Bascom
The archaeologist
in deep water
34
A^LL kinds of ships from the
earliest crude vessel to the most
modern supertankers have had a dis¬
concerting way of getting into trouble
on the high seas and suddenly sinking.
They sink for many reasons, often with
all hands, far from shore.
The hulks may have landed in
shallow water which we will define as
less than 200 metres or perhaps they
came to rest on the continental shelf,
or even in the abyss. Each sunken
ship is a neatly packaged collection of
artifacts representing the culture of its
time. Since these marine disasters
have been going on steadily for 4,000
years, the accumulated record of the
history of civilization is now spread for
our choice on the floor of the sea.
Archaeological techniques for the
examination of old ships in water less
than 30 metres deep are well develop¬
ed. But ship hulls in such shallow
graves have been largely destroyed by
wave action, sand abrasion, chemical
changes, marine borers and divers.
The destruction has usually been so
complete we have come to think of
shallow water wrecks as mounds of
amphoras, piles of ballast stones, and
scattered cannon. Only beneath the
mud or sand does one find wood in
\he form of bottom ribs and planking.
Often the associated artifacts have
been scattered around over half a kilo¬
metre and buried deep in the sand by
great waves over hundreds of years.
These shallow wrecks have en¬
couraged us by providing much in¬
formation; they also urge us on by
raising questions about the parts that
are missing and holding out hope that
we can find better preserved examples.
There may be many ancient wooden
ships in reasonably good condition
WILLARD BASCOM began his career as a
mining engineer, but switched to oceano¬
graphy in 1945 as a research engineer at the
University of California, Berkeley, and later
at the Scrlpps Institution of Oceanography,
La Jolla, California. After joining the U.S.
National Academy of Sciences In 1954, he org¬
anized and directed the first phase of the
Mohole Project to drill in deep water through
the earth's crust (see 'Unesco Courier', Oct.
1963). He has written many scientific and
technical studies and Is the author or editor
of "A Hole In the Bottom of the Sea",
"Waves and Beaches' and 'Great Sea
Poetry', for the general reader.
lying on the deep-sea floor of the
Mediterranean.
The weather in the Mediterranean is
known for sudden violent change, and
the old ships could not respond rapidly
nor sail into wind very well. In the
Aegean, the early mariners feared the
"meltem", a northerly afternoon gale,
known in the Adriatic as the "bora",
which brings winds of 60 mph and
more. It would be very easy for a ship
to be blown offshore and sunk in a
sudden squall.
The ancient ships were generally
small (less than 40 metres long) and
made of wooden planks held edge to
edge. If the planks came apart, the
weight of cargo and ballast would take
a ship down in a few minutes. Many
vessels were not completely decked
and in heavy weather they could take
water over the sides and quickly
founder or capsize.
Pirates were the scourge of shipping
for many centuries: they doubtless
sank many of the vessels they caught.
Fire was also a frequent cause of loss
coals would fall from a galley stove
as the ship pitched, or a carelessly
held torch would start a blaze. War¬
ships, subject to all these hazards, also
had a chance of being rammed in battle
or scuttled after capture.
What happened to the ships that
sank in water deeper than 200 metres?
They must have settled rapidly to the
bottom (the velocity depending on the
weight) where they landed upright (be¬
cause of the drag of the masts and
rigging) on a sea floor made of mud,
ooze or fine sand. Probably the
Impact would not be very damaging to
a hull. Once on the bottom the hull is
protected from most of the things that
would destroy it in shallow water.
In water over 200 metres deep, wave
action at the bottom is virtually nil. In
most places the current is of low
velocity, not capable of rearranging the
bottom materials. It is dark at those
depths, and photosynthesis, required
to sustain plant growth, is not possible.
The temperature is near-freezing so
that chemical reactions proceed very
slowly. And of course man, until now,
has not been able to reach these
depths and disturb the site. Deep
water is a perfect place for old ship
storage almost.
The largest unknown in this con¬
sideration of whether old wooden
wrecks survive in deep water is the
question of whether marine borers con¬
sume them. The evidence is not clear
and the answer is perhaps.
If, for example, the ship was badly
infected with shipworm when it sank,
these creatures may have survived the
increased pressure and finished their
work. But teredos (shipworms) do not
ordinarily live at depths as great as 200
metres. The most likely destruction
will have been caused by a borer clam,
xylophaga, which attacks wood down
to 2,000 metres. Since samples of
very old wood have been found on the
deep sea bottom, these creatures are
not universal and we are left with hope.
Or perhaps there are other, unknown,
biological attackers.
Variations in the survival of wood
are probably caused by differences in
salinity, oxygen, nutrients, metallic ions,
currents, or just accident. In the
reducing environment that exists in
some marine depressions and in the
Black Sea, one would expect wood on
the sea bottom to survive very well.
I F the ship survives the
borers, will it soon be covered with
sediment? In deep water the sea dust
usually accumulates very slowly. The
mid-ocean sedimentation rate is as
little as one or two millimetres per
thousand years; in the central basins
of the Mediterranean it is about 10 cm.
per thousand years. In intermediate
depths (200 to 2,000 m), except near
large river discharges, an average
might be 20 cm. per thousand years.
Thus, in such depths, the general out¬
line of even a very old ship will not be
greatly changed by that blanket of
sediment.
The net effect of the above argu¬
ments is that there is good reason to
believe that somewhere on the deep
sea floor wooden ships are well pre¬
served for very long periods of time.
Certainly they are in better condition
than those found in shallow water.
Wrecks in shallow water have
generally been found accidently by
sponge divers, fishing boats, or sports
divers. But to locate vessels sunk in
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
deep water, other leads are needed.
In the Mediterranean, useful inform¬
ation can be gleaned from statistics
based on knowledge of the ancient
ports and cities, the location of trade
routes, the nature of the old ships and
their cargoes.
It is believed that there were over
300 active ports in the Mediterranean
by the 4th century B.C., and that during
the first millenium B.C. some 150,000
ships were built. Other calculations
suggest that as many as 15,000 of
these vessels foundered many in
deep water.
If the total length of the trade routes
in the eastern Mediterranean were
6,000 nautical miles (1 nautical mile
equals 1.9 kilometres) and the average
width 10 nautical miles, there is a
reasonable chance of one sunken ship
in every four square nautical miles
along these routes.
By selecting specific areas where
ships were known to get into trouble,
it is possible to improve the chances
considerably. There are numerous
high-probability sites in the straits be¬
tween islands, between islands and
mainland, and at major "jumping off
points", where ships left the security
of nearby land and set out into open
waters.
Such sites exist between the Pélo¬
ponnèse and Crete, east of Crete to
Rhodes and Turkey, between Italy and
Yugoslavia, between Tunis and Sicily,
around Malta, near Gibraltar, and along
the coasts of Lebanon, Israel and
Cyprus.
Somewhat more is known about the
losses of military ships in the same
period, and there are more fixed points
to guide estimates. There are literally
hundreds of historical references to
sea battles in which astonishing
numbers of ships were involved.
For example, at the battle of Cape
Ecnomus, Sicily, in 255 B.C., 250
Roman ships faced 200 Carthaginian
vessels. Only 16 ships were lost in
the battle, but in a storm off Camarina,
on the southern Sicilian coast, shortly
afterward, 250 of the remaining ships
were wrecked. When Anthony and
Cleopatra met Augustus at Actium in
37 B.C., about 100 ships of the 900
engaged were lost.
Ships that sank much later than the
CONTINUED NEXT PAGE
Right, impression of a specially
designed archaeological research
vessel, the "Alcoa Seaprobe"
designed by Dr. W. Bascom,
making a sonar search of the
sea bed. An instrument pod,
lowered through the ship's cen¬
tral well, contains forward and
side-scanning sonars that can
sweep a pathway 400 to 800
metres wide. Projections, such
as rocks or the wreck of a ship,
reflect sound waves better and
produce a darker spot on the
record. The sea bed pattern,
below, was recorded by side-
scanning sonar apparatus during
a survey voyage by another
research vessel.
Drawing Willard Bascom
- 	 aaal
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
DEEP SEA ARCHAEOLOGY (Continued)
Exploring ancient wrecks at 1,000 fathoms
36
ancient ones may be even more in¬
teresting. For example, in 1571 the
Battle of Lepanto was fought between
a fleet of 300 ships from Venice, Spain
and the Papal States and a 273-ship
Turkish fleet, not far from Actium, just
over 1,600 years after the fleet of
Anthony and Augustus fought there.
Another 100-odd ships went down, this
time with a very different array of arti¬
facts.
,So the obvious first place to look
is In the Mediterranean along trade
routes that have been travelled for
thousands of years. Although that sea
has a maximum depth of over 4,500
metres, the major part of these ancient
pathways traversed waters less than
half that depth, within easy reach of
the system about to be described.
It is nearly ten years since I reached
this conclusion and devised a method
for systematic searching, inspection
and the recovery of heavy objects.
The system was awarded a U.S. Patent
in 1965 and with few changes has been
developed into a beautiful new ship
completed in late 1971: the Alcoa Sea-
probe. Now the technology is in exist¬
ence.
1 HE Alcoa Seaprobe looks
much like a deep ocean drilling ship
indeed it is capable of drilling
but instead it uses its semi-rigid pipe
to lower a pod containing sensors into
the depths. These sensors include
two sonars, television cameras and
photographic equipment. When these,
are moved along a short distance
above the bottom they transmit infor¬
mation about a wide swath of bottom
up a cable to instrument watchers in
the control room above.
It is not necessary to send men
down; the pod at the tip of the pipe
extends their vision into the depths.
From the surface they can inspect
objects on the bottom, dusting away
sediment with propellers. Items of in¬
terest can be photographed and per¬
haps recovered with scoops and grasp¬
ing devices.
The Alcoa Seaprobe Is 75 metres
long, 17 metres wide, and draws 4
metres. It is propelled by two vertical-
axis manoeuvering propellers which
can exert thrust to move the ship in
any direction, including skewed and
sidewise. The ship is all-electric with
its power plant forward and quarters
for 50 men aft. It is built of an alumi¬
nium alloy to demonstrate the excellent
marine properties of that material.
The ship is steered by a console on
the bridge which manually or automat¬
ically controls the propellers in such a
way as to hold the ship in position
above a point on the bottom in deep
water. This capability, called "dynamic
positioning", was invented by the
author and associates in 1959, and is
the key to doing precise work on the
bottom in water too deep for anchor¬
ing.
In the centre of the ship is a rect¬
angular opening to the sea 4 metres by
12 metres, called a "well". Directly
above it is an aluminium derrick that
can lift up to 400,000 kg (200 metric
tons working load).
The derrick and pipe-handling system
is capable of lowering or recovering
drill pipe at an average rate of about
0.25 metres per second to a depth of
6,000 metres (although only 2,000
metres of pipe will normally be
aboard). The pipe is ordinary oil drill¬
ing pipe 11.5 cm. in diameter, handled
in "doubles". 20 metres long.
Pipe has the advantage that the pod
and the tongs at its tip can be oriented
and that sea water can be pumped
down the inside at high pressure to
operate hydraulic devices at the
bottom. In order to ensure that the
lower tip of the pipe remains close
beneath the ship, the lower end of it
is weighted with 20 tons of very thick-
walled pipe.
The power-information cable bet¬
ween ship and pod is secured to the
outside of the pipe with special clips
and stored on a huge reel on deck.
More pipe can be added or removed
quickly as the depth changes and the
cable length is readily adjusted.
As with any searching system, pre¬
cise navigation is required so that there
is a clear record of where the ship has
been at every moment. Then any
object found can be refound.
The ship's position can be determin¬
ed closely enough by one of the elec¬
tronic navigation systems. But careful
searching out of sight of land requires
local references such as taut-moored
buoys supporting radar transponders
(combined transmitter and receiver) or
bottom-mounted sonar transponders.
A systematic search is then conducted
relative to these fixed points and the
ship's position is plotted at short inter¬
vals of time as it moves back and forth
along parallel pathways.
Once the navigation markers are
installed we are ready to search. The
pod is lowered to a position 20 to 50
metres above the bottom and the ship
moves slowly forward at less than one
metre per second. The sonars send
out high frequency (177.5kh) pings of
sound, one looking at the bottom
directly ahead, the other scanning each
side to a distance of at least 200
metres (twice that in some circum¬
stances).
The side-looking sonar sends and
receives sound pulses in such a
fashion that objects that rise above
the bottom, like a ship or a pile of
ballast stones, reflect the sound and
produce a dark spot on the record.
Since the sea floor immediately beyond
is in the sonic shadow and does not
reflect sound, that part of the record
remains white.
Thus each ping produces a line on
the record and as the pod moves for¬
ward a sound picture of the bottom
develops. The approximate size of
bottom objects can be determined.
Because the side-looking sonar
beam must strike the bottom at a small
angle in order to be effective, it does
not see objects on the bottom directly
beneath the pod. Therefore the for¬
ward-looking sonar, which works in a
similar fashion, is used to get inform¬
ation about the centre of the pathway.
When a ship-like object is detected
with the sonar, it is necessary to verify
it with television and to determine its
approximate age and value. For this
the pod is lowered into television range
(about 10 metres above the bottom) at
the position plotted for the wreck. The
sea dust can be blown away with
water jets and the hulk inspected and
photographed. The amount of work
to be done will be determined by its
value relative to other wreck's which
could be studied.
If there are artifacts to be recovered
an appropriate tool or device will be
attached beneath the television. It
may be a net, a grasping mechanism,
or a large pair of tongs. Major pieces
of a ship, heavy cannon, anchors, stone
columns, etc., can be recovered as well
as small items. Probably it will be
possible to make reasonably good
maps of the wreck from the photos
and observations.
IIT also may be possible to
raise entire small wrecks In one or
more lifts. Large wooden ship struc¬
tures thus recovered would immediately
be placed in fresh water in a prepared
barge so as to prevent their deterior¬
ation while they are being studied and
exhibited.
With the search method described
here it should be possible to examine
30 square kilometres of bottom per
day. The examination of wrecks and
other objects will take the bulk of the
time but it should be very rewarding.
So it seems that a great treasure
house of information about the ancient
world the bottom of the Mediterra¬
nean is almost within our grasp. In
the New World, examination of 300
year-old wrecks will begin this year.
Hopefully we will learn how well wood
survives, how to identify and study old
wrecks, and how to salvage major
items.
If that is successful the next step will
be to organize similar exploration work
in the Mediterranean. M
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
Norman E. Borlaug's defence of DDT
We have received many letters from readers after the publication of
Norman E. Borlaug's article. "In Defence of DDT", in our February 1972
issue. Pursuing our policy of objectivity we devote this month's letters'
page to readers' views on the subject.
AGAINST ALL EXCESSES
Sir,
The "Unesco Courier" has given
spectacular prominence to the address
on DDT delivered by Dr. Norman E.
Borlaug at the Food and Agriculture
Organization in Rome. The striking
cover of the February issues dazzles
the reader with references to the Nobel
Peace Prize and the "Green Revolution"
(still a highly controversial subject
though too often presented as a univer¬
sal panacea for the problem of food
production) and suggests that Dr. Bor¬
laug's defence of DDT is infallible and
has Unesco's support.
You are sure to have certain reactions
from readers. Here ¡s one from the
Unesco regional ecologist for Africa,
Dr. K. Curry Lindahl.
"I regret," writes Dr. Curry Lindahl,
"that the "Unesco Courier" is helping.
Dr. Borlaug to spread ideas so lacking
in balance and restraint, since everyone
will believe that Unesco fully shares
his views on this question. I sincerely
hope that this is not the case. The
whole problem is admirably clarified in
that part of Unesco's programme, "Man
and the Biosphere", which deals with
the use of pesticides and fertilizers in
land and water ecosystems. I hope a
future article will help to counterbalance
Dr. Borlaug's extremist views.
"In my book, 'Conservation for Sur¬
vival' ", adds Dr. Curry Lindahl, "I make
a critical analysis of forecasts on the
Green Revolution and its possibilities
for feeding the future world population.
The forecasts are pure fantasy."
As for myself, I can well understand
Dr. Borlaug's attitude for he must be
exasperated by the excesses, incoher¬
ence and irresponsibility of those who
want to ban DDT at all costs. But in
his desire to emphasize the positive
role played by DDT in solving some of
the difficult problems of health and of
food production, he goes to the other
extreme, since sensationalism appears
today to be the best means of obtaining
a wide audience through the mass
media. I do not believe that extremist
attitudes, even though they have a great
ability to stimulate people, will advance
the truth which is necessarily more
complex and more nuancé.
M. Bâtisse
Director, Natural Resources
Research Division, Unesco, Paris
We would remind readers that each
issue of the "Unesco Courier" states,
on page 3: "Signed articles express
the opinions of the authors and do not
necessarily represent the opinions of
Unesco or those of the Editors of the
'Unesco Courier'." The Editors have
always been opposed to sensationalism
and were in no sense guided by it in
publishing Dr. Borlaug's text. Editor.
CALAMITOUS SIDE-EFFECTS
Sir,
"Minute amounts of pesticides such
as DDT have been found to inhibit
photosynthesis in marine algae by 75
per cent." This quote is from the
"Unesco Courier" (August 1970). In
highly fertilized fields, Swedish scientists
have found crops containing 13 times
more nitrate than the safety limit allow¬
ed for potable water. Should we risk
losing the rich harvests of the oceans
in order to gain a surplus of grain
which might well contain unacceptable
amounts of nitrates as well as residues
of pesticides, and be lacking in vital
trace elements not present in the ferti¬
lizers into the bargain?
In a year when the United Nations
is sponsoring a conference on the
Human Environment, your February 1972
cover story is in defence of DDT. How
wonderful it would be if we could go
on believing that DDT is as marvellous
as we first had come to think I Refer¬
ring to the calamitous side-effects of
durable pesticides, synthetic detergents
and the internal combustion engine,
René Dubos, in your January 1969 issue,
pointed out what we all have to admit,
that "most of the environmental prob¬
lems which now plague technological
civilization derive from discoveries and
decisions made to solve other problems
and to enlarge human life."
However, in your March 1969 issue,
Gene Gregory was given space, to
explain the opportunities for investment
in developing countries in supplying kits
of new "miracle seed" varieties along
with the fertilizers and insecticides upon
which their fruition is dependent. "This
novel distribution concept presents a
special challenge to abilities of inter¬
national corporate enterprises to develop
the joint marketing facilities." In your
issue of June 1971 the same business
consultant was privileged to write the
cover story praising the wonders of
modern chemistry, these Including DDT.
The Green Revolution must come to
rely on plant breeds resistant to pests,
not on breeds relying on the massive
application of pesticides. And the
"Unesco Courier" must be far more
consistent and responsible in its cover¬
age of these grave not controversial
matters, pitting the views of 2,200
environmental scientists (July 1971 issue)
against those of a single expert in
plant breeding.
Gloria Newton
Ulf Christensen
Tenk selv - Think for Yourself
Oslo, Norway
WE ARE NOT HYSTERICAL
Sir,
Norman Borlaug's defence of DDT
seems to be based on a concern for
justice and humanity, yet leaves one
with considerable misgivings.
There is no doubt that if all today's
increased agricultural output, made
possible by scientific research, were
really devoted to humanitarian instead
of speculative ends, Norman Borlaug's
idea for setting up international gran¬
aries of food reserves would have been
put into practice long ago.
Those who defend the environment
are not composed exclusively of "hyster¬
ical" propagandists opposed to the
use of DDT and other pesticides and
chemical fertilizers. Among them are
those who see nature being despoiled
by the spread of wastes of every kind;
who watch a flood of harmful products
(deodorants, cleaning products and so
on) Invading the shops. And quite often
public health authorities seem tó close
their eyes to this situation. Should
environmentalists who condemn this
serious state of affairs be called "hyster¬
ical"?
I am very much afraid that statements
such as that of Norman Borlaug only
serve to encourage those who unscru¬
pulously disregard the social problems
plaguing us today and enable them to
justify their actions in the name of
technological progress while the real
problems are swept under the carpet.
M. J. Goldman
Clichy, France
ALTERNATIVES TO DDT
Sir,
In the face of such a global problem
as the effects of DDT and other pesti¬
cides, one can only regret that Norman
Borlaug gave such a controversial tone
to his article.
In the short term, according to the
World Health Organization, the banning
of these products would be catastrophic
for mankind, an opinion with which
many of those who seek to defend
nature would agree. But to claim that
only the "hysterical environmentalists"
are worried about the long term effects
of pesticides is quite ridiculous.
Norman Borlaug scarcely touches on
the use of biological control of insect
pests, and then merely to hold it up
to ridicule. Yet surely an integrated
campaign using natural predators and
a genetic control of insect pests would
help to limit the harmful effects of an
exclusively chemical attack.
Other institutions besides WHO have
carried out significant research on this
question, for example, the French
National Institute of Agronomic Res¬
earch. Why not publish some of their
findings?
P. Kergadallan
Val d*Yerres Nature
Defence Committee
Brunoy, France
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
TRIALS OF AN UNDERWATER ARCHAEOLOGIST (Continued from page 15)
comforting to know that in case of
emergency one can swim just a few
feet away and stand inside the "booth",
dry from the chest up, and breathe
fresh air.
I have emphasized the time limitation
placed on divers. This is due to the
fact that the longer one stays at any
depth, the more compressed air is
being absorbed into the body. This
gas (air) can come out of solution
and form bubbles, causing what is
commonly known as "the bends", if the
diver rises too rapidly to the surface.
To avoid the bends, which can be
crippling or fatal, the diver must
ascend slowly, in stages, following
schedules that control his ascent rate
depending on how deep he has been
and how long he has stayed down.
To work for an hour at the depth we
have most recently been excavating,
140 feet, would require a total time of
over an hour and a half spent in rising
to the surface, or decompressing. This
hour and a half is more time than we
are willing to spend in open water
following each dive especially as we
dive twice a day, six days a week, for
months at a time.
To allow greater decompression
times, making longer working dives
possible, we built a submersible de¬
compression chamber. This is a steel
sphere more than six feet in diameter,
filled with air through a hose. Up to
four divers can enter through a bottom
hatch. Once inside, they can talk,
read, or take notes in relatively dry
comfort while being raised slowly to
the surface.
There are many, many other prob¬
lems. Conservation of material
raised from the sea, for example, is
a complete subject in itself. But most
problems are solved by following two
principles.
The first principle is that safety
comes before all else. After directing
about 8,000 dives to between 100 and
150 feet, I have gained an increasing
respect for the suddeness of possible
accidents, including diving sicknesses
such as the bends and air embolism.
This concern has led us to design such
safety devices as the telephone booth,
submersible chamber, and special
diving rigs. I would not now want to
be responsible for a single dive with¬
out a physician and a first-rate re
compression chamber (for treatment
of bends or embolism) at hand. When
we began in 1960 we had neither. We
were very lucky.
The second principle is that the
work must be done by archaeologists,
assisted by divers and other special¬
ists. The excavation of a seventh-
century Byzantine shipwreck took us
four summers of diving. Its study,
however, has already taken me and
half a dozen colleagues eight years,
and it is still not quite ready for
publication. But already we know how
the ship was built and what she looked
like, and how this contributes to the
history of naval architecture.
Slowly we have pieced together the
history of the ship: when and where
she was built, who sailed on board and
how they lived, her last route, and
when and how she sank. All this
has taught us much about the mech¬
anics of Byzantine trade and about
life at sea thirteen centuries ago. How
much more meaningful this is than a
simple collection of wood and pottery
and metal artifacts in a museum.
George F. Bass
THE DROWNED CITY OF PORT ROYAL (Continued from page 28)
38
chaeologists and by George Bass on
some of the Mediterranean sites (see
article page 8) was ruled out by the
lack of visibility and by the nature of
the sediment in which cave-ins are the
rule rather than the exception. Al¬
though most of the artifacts are re¬
covered from the first 3 m. of sedi¬
ment, we excavate to 5 m. and occa¬
sionally find artifacts in the lower
sediment.
Horizontal control is maintained by
marking with four buoys the square to
be excavated and each day recording
the position of the top of the air-lift
tube whenever important objects are
recovered and brought up. Vertical
control is maintained by establishing
the depth of water, and noting the
depth that the air-lift tube is down
each time that artifacts are brought
up for tagging.
Excavation began on the site on
May 1, 1966 and has since gone on
continuously, six days a week. We
have systematically excavated a rec¬
tangular hole 133 by 50 m. to an
average depth of 5 m. Only three intact
brick buildings have so far been un
covered, but hundreds of fragments of
brick walls and thousands of brick¬
bats have been located.
On the basis of old maps and
property records, we estimate that the
area excavated contained from thirty
to forty buildings. By checking
owners' initials on pewter and silver
artifacts with the old property records,
we have been able to identify many of
the sites. Most were private homes,
but we also found two taverns, a car¬
penter's shop, a cobbler's shop, a
pewterer's (or silversmith's) shop, the
fish and meat markets, and two turtle
crawls. In this same area we located
two shipwrecks dating from the 1692
earthquake and another dating from a
hurricane in 1722.
Excluding treasure, more artifacts
have now been recovered than from all
the wreck sites worked in the Carib¬
bean over the past two decades. Over
20,000 iron objects have been recover¬
ed most still await a suitable method
of preservation. Other finds include
2,000 glass bottles, 6,500 clay smok¬
ing pipes, and over 500 pewter or sil¬
verware items.
Two large hoards of Spanish silver
coins were found: the first in a wood¬
en chest bearing a brass keyhole
plate with the coat-of-arms of Philip IV
of Spain, the other under a fallen wall
believed to be part of a pewterer's or
silversmith's shop.
Yet, after almost two years of op¬
erations, we have not excavated even
five per cent of the site, and many
years of work' remain. It is to be
hoped that Port Royal will eventually
be used as a training centre for
students of marine archaeology.
Unfortunately, there is both very little
official interest and little financial sup¬
port; at the moment, only the Mexican
and Jamaican Governments are spon¬
soring projects.
In the Caribbean, as elsewhere, mar¬
ine archaeology is still in its infancy
as a discipline. The techniques are
still experimental and there are few
really expert archaeologists. Yet, com¬
pared with the Mediterranean, and
considering the opportunities it offers,
the Caribbean has attracted less than
its share of archaeological effort.
Robert F. Marx
z
<
<
(J
z
<
o
Lai
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Just published by Unesco
An exciting volume that will appeal to both
the general reader and the specialist.
UNDERWATER
ARCHAEOLOGY
A nascent discipline
£3.30 $11 44 F
£4.50 $15 60 F (clothbound)
164 illustrations
in black and white
A few titles from the 27 chapters in this 306 page book :
Ancient Wrecks (Frédéric Dumas), The Salvage of the
Swedish Warship Wasa (Anders Franzen), Wrecks as
Ancient Monuments (G. D. van der Heide), History of
Underwater Photography (Dimitri Rebikoff), The Uses
of Sonar (Donald M. Rosencrantz, M. Klein, Harold E.
Edgerton), Submersibles in Underwater Search and Pho-
togrammetric Mapping (George F. Bass, Donald M.
Rosencrantz).
IN THE
MINDS
OF
MEN
UNESCO
1946-1971
319 pages
£1.20 $4 16F
A provocative
account
of Unesco and
its work during
the past 25
years by
15 international
authorities :
Gian Franco Pompei, Charles Franke/, Lionel Elvin, Victor
A. Kovda, Jean d'Ormesson, Prem Kirpal, Malcolm S. Adi¬
seshiah, William A. Eteki-Mboumoua, Juan Goméz Millas,
Mohi El Din Saber, Afilio Dell'Oro Ma¡ni, Hanna Saba,
Sarwat Okasha, Alva Myrdal, René Maheu.
Where to renew your subscription
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AUSTRALIA. Publications : Educational Supplies
Pty. Ltd., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale, 2100, NS ; Perio¬
dicals: Dominie Pty. Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brook¬
vale 2100, NSW. Sub-agent. United Nations Association
of Australia, Victorian Division, 4th Floor, Askew House,
364 Lonsdale St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. AUS¬
TRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Arbeitgasse 1-7,
1051, Vienna, (AS 110). BELGIUM. Jean De Lannoy,
112, rue du Troné, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. (220F
beiges) BURMA. Trade Corporation N' (9), 550-5S2
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Information
Canada, Ottawa, (Ont.) (» 5,00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244
Colombo 2. (Rs 20). CYPRUS. Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L., Spalena 51, Prague 1
(permanent display); Zahranicni literatura 11 Soukenicka
Prague 1. For Slovakia only : Nakladatelstvo Alfa, Hurba-
novo nam. 6 Bratislava. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard
Ltd., 6. Norregade, 1165, Copenhagen K. (Dan. Kr. 27.00)
EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF). National Centre for
Unesco Publications, N" 1 Talaat Harb Street,Tahrir 1 Squa¬
re, Cairo; Librairie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo.
(IL.E. 35) ETHIOPIA. National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND, Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki (Fmk. 13.90).
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7-9, place de Fontenoy,
75-Paris-7*. C.C.P. 12598-48 (17 F). GERMANY. All
publications : Verlag Dokumentation, Postfach 1 48,
Jaiserstrasse 1 3, 8023 München-Pullach. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld. CCP. 276650 (DM 16).
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O.
Box 195, Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box
7869, Accra; The University Bookshop of Ghana,
Accra; The University Bookshop of Cape Coast, The
University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1, Legon.
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE.
Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade, Athens; Librairie
Eleftheroudakis, Nikis 4, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 1 3-1 5, Lock Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Akadémiai Könyvesbolt, Vici u. 22,
Budapest V; A.K.V. Könyvtirosok Boltja, Népkóztirsasig
utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn Jonsson
& Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard Estate, Bom¬
bay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; 3/5 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1 ; Sub-
Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co. 17 Park Street,
Calcutta 16 and Scindia House, New Delhi; Publications
Section, Ministry of Education and Youth Services,
72 Theatre Communication Building, Connaught Place
New Delhi 1. (Rs. 18,75). INDONESIA. Indira P.T.,
Dj'l. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Djakarta. IRAN. Iranian
National Commission for Unesco, 1/1 54avenue Roosevelt,
B.P. 1533, Teheran. IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop,
Al-Rashid Street, Baghdad; University Bookstore, Uni¬
versity of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad. IRELAND.
The National Press, 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge,
Dublin 4. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48, Nachtat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv; 9, Shlomzion Hamalka Street
Jerusalem. (24 I.L.) JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Stores
Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane, Kingston.
JAPAN. Maruzere Co. Ltd., P.O. Box 5050, Tokyo
International 1 00-31 (Y 1 ,440). KEN YA.The E.S.A. Ltd.,
P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi. KOREA. Korean National
Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd., P.O. Box
2942, Kuwait. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for
Development of Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 34-
35, Tripoli. LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg. MALAYSIA.
Federal Publications Sdn Bhd., Balai Berita, 31, Jalan
Riong, Kuala Lumpur. MALTA. Sapienza's Library,
26 Kingsway, Valletta. MAURITIUS. Nalanda Com¬
pany Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (Rs. 17,45).
MONACO. British Library, 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-
Carlo. NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff,
Lange Voorhout, 9, the Hague, (fl. 14). NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G. C T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned
Ant.). N. V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl. 7.80).
NEW ZEALAND. Government Printing Office,
Government Bookshops at : Rutland Street, P.O. Box
5344, Auckland; 130. Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721,
Chriscchurch; Alma Street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton;
Princes Street, P.O. Box 1104, Dunedin; Mulgrave
Street, Private Bag, Wellington (I 3.00). NIGERIA.
The University Bookshop of Ife, The University Bookshop
of Ibadan, P.O. Box 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka, The University Bookshop of Lagos. The Ahmadu
Bello University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All
publications : Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers) Karl
johansgate 41/43, Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S.
Narvesens Litteraturjeneste, Box 61 25, Oslo6(K.23,00).
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 G.P.O., Lahore;
Showrooms : Urdu Bazaar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree,
Highway, G/6-1, Islamabad. Pakistan Publications Book*
shop, Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi; Paribagh, Dacca.
PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Ave¬
nue, P.O. Box 632, Manila D-404. POLAND. All
publications : ORWN PAN Palac Kultury i Nauki,
Warsaw. For the Unesco Courier only : RUCH, ul.
Wronia, 23, Warsaw 1 0. PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade
Ltda, Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon (Esc. 1 05).
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Sdn Bhd., Times
House, River Valley Road, Singapore 9. SOUTHERN
RHODESIA. Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd.. 67 Union
Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1 1 1 8, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications:
A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2,
Box 16356, 10327 Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier : Svenska FN-Forbundet, Vasagatan 1 5, IV
10123, Stockholm 1 Postgiro 18 46 92 (Kr. 18).
SWITZERLAND. All publications : Europa Verlag,
S Rämistrasse, Zürich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1211, Geneva 11, CCP. 12-236 (Fr. S. 1 6.-). TAN-
ZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-
Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9,
Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (71.00 baht). TURKEY.
Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala.
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications: Van Schaik's
Bookstore (Pty). Ltd., Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies)
only: Central News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham, Bristol (£1,30).UNITED STATES. Unesco
Publications Center, P.O. Box 433, New York, N.Y.
10016 ($5). U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga, Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zaluzba Slo¬
vénie Mestni Trg. 26, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
FISHING UP THE PAST
Piloted by an underwater archaeologist, an ancient amphora
for storing wine, oil or food rises to the surface near Yassi
island, on the south-west coast of Turkey. Encrusted with
orange sponges, it was recovered from the wreck of a late
Roman cargo ship, excavated under water by an expedition
from the University of Pennsylvania, U.S.A. This archaeolo¬
gical site, one of scores recently explored in the Mediter¬
ranean, was first mapped with the aid of a two-man sub¬
marine (see article page 8).
Photo i Flip Schulke - Black Star, New York
]]>
</page>
</document>
