<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078210eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
Bum.H \ ^B m
m ML' " *> - ^B
^ fc, ^BEx**i^ ^1 fiai
l-^^.va, * -/B Bk; ^1 Bbr-ç&tvV.
Global Developm
TURNING
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
YOUTH WITH A PURPOSE
Sir,
It was a real pleasure for me, a
16-year-old, to read your special issue
on youth (July-August 1965). It showed
quite clearly that young people are
now building a world they will one day
Inherit not destroying it. Youth, in
fact, is often criticised because it
shows an awareness of problems that
earlier generations preferred to disre¬
gard because they were unwilling to
disturb the existing order of things.
Thank you for showing us the true
¡mage of youth in 1965.
Didier Uriot
Lomme, France
FIRST THINGS FIRST
Sir,
I admire your magazine and parti¬
cularly its excellent lay-out. But I
wish you would publish fewer articles
on the arts and letters. Instead please
tell us more about the major problem
of hunger in the world and the plight
of millions of poverty-stricken people.
Your first concern should be to cam¬
paign against hunger and all its
causes and against everthing that
contributes to an exhaustion of the
world's soil; articles on beautiful minia¬
tures, mosaics, architecture and
painting should take second place.
Antoine de Römer
Montreal, Canada
WOMAN WITH THE STYLUS
Sir,
Thanks to an illustration accompa¬
nying the article, "Ancestors of the
Ball-Point Pen", by Luigi Pareti (May),
I have at last solved the mystery of a
portrait which I received as a wedding
present nearly 20 years ago. Your
caption identifies it as a mural painted
at Pompeii in 70 A.D., depicting a
young Roman woman holding a stylus.
I have always been intrigued by the
young woman in my painting and am
delighted to have discovered her ori¬
gin thanks to your help.
I especially like your issues devoted
to art, archaeology, ethnography,
ancient civilizations and all humanistic
questions.
Françoise Mutschier
Ferney Voltaire, France
RADIO PIONEERS
Sir,
Your article on "Telecommunications
1869-1965" (May) states correctly that
the invention of radio will always be
associated with such names as James
Maxwell, Heinrich Hertz, Oliver Lodge,
Alexander Popov, Guglielmo Marconi
and Lee De Forest. In my view two
French scientists, Edouard Branly and
Gustave Ferrie, also belong in this list
of radio pioneers.
Marceau Cauchy
Paris, France
Ed note : Edouard Branly (1844-
1940) was responsible for many deve¬
lopments in the application of elec
tricity to telecommunications, including
the "coherer" a -sensitive detector of
electric waves, later used by Marconi
in long-distance radio transmissions.
Research and discoveries by Gustave
Ferrie (1868-1932) also contributed to
the development of radio.
BOOKS, FILMS & CHILDREN
Sir,
I read with great professional
interest the article based on Wilbur
Schramm's book, "The Effects of
Television on Children and Adoles¬
cents" (Feb ). I agree with the author's
views. I think the problem has to
be considered on the highest social,
educational and political levels. An
information medium as persuasive
as television can, if properly handled,
become an instrument of immense
good, but if wrongly used it can do
irreparable harm.
There are two other information
media books and magazines and the
cinema which, like certain television
programmes, can have grave psycho¬
logical effects on a child. Unesco
should make a study similar to
Mr. Schramm's, but devoted to publi¬
cations and to the cinema.
J. Mallas Casas
Barcelona, Spain
Ed note: A Unesco study, "The In¬
fluence of the Cinema on Children and
Adolescents" , was published in the
form of an international bibliography in
1961 (No 31 in the Unesco Reports and
Papers on Mass Communication). An
article based on this report appeared
in the March 1961 issue of The Unesco
Courier.
UNDER THREE FLAGS
Sir,
International Co-operation Year
comes when much effort is needed to
establish the United Nations as the
effective voice of mankind. A few
privileged astronauts can travel In
private space craft, but the rest of us
make up the crew of the biggest space
capsule, the earth itself.
It is widely agreed that loyalty to
the locality harmonizes with loyalty to
the larger unit of government, whether
it is called state, region, province, or
prefecture. In spite of occasional
conflicts, loyalty to a province or can¬
ton is usually seen as compatible with
loyalty to a nation. In a space cap¬
sule, the long-range welfare of
any one nation obviously depends
upon the welfare of the entire
globe. Conversely, the welfare of the
world suffers if any one nation has an
economic collapse. We know, too,
that warfare in any part of the world
carries with it the threat of nuclear
destruction In all other parts as well.
It follows then, that loyalty to any
nation must be compatible with loyalty
to the long-term welfare of the entire
family of man.
Men and women of good will can
strengthen the celebration of Interna¬
tional Co-operation Year by making the
public in all countries aware of the
circles of loyalty on which
support for the United Nations de¬
pends. On United Nations' Day (Octo¬
ber 24) and similar holidays they can
fly three flags together : those of their
city or state, of their nation, and of
the United Nations.
William Thorn
Wilkes-Barre, Pa. U.S.A.
THE TREASURES OF MASADA
Sir,
Masada, one of the most inacces¬
sible and interesting archaeological
sites in Israel, is now yielding its cul¬
tural treasures to both scholar and lay¬
man. This is being accomplished by
the combined efforts of Israelis and
an international group of volunteers,
especially young people, from 28 na¬
tions.
Of the important finds so far
unearthed two, I believe, deserve spe¬
cial attention. One consists of some
more scrolls of the same type as the
famous Dead Sea Scrolls. The newly
found scrolls include portions of Deu¬
teronomy and Ezekiel and add in¬
valuable material to the tricky prob¬
lem of their dating. The other impor¬
tant find is the synagogue. Its remains
are an important contribution to the
history of synagogical architecture and
constitutes a link between the archi¬
tectural influences of the times and
later developments in the art of build¬
ing synagogues and churches.
The literary description of the fall of
Masada by Josephus is now corrobo¬
rated by archaeological evidence.
Even his description of the mass sui¬
cide, which its defenders committed
rather than surrender to the Romans,
has been found to be true.
Some new Israeli stamps (See
above) have been issued to mark the
importance of Masada.
David Ariel
Assistant Permanent Delegate
of Israel to Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
iNOOw orín on THt wenoi . i A WI D W g i « i«» n w« i. -
Courier
OCTOBER 1965 - 18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO,
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg.; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2years:27/-stg.;18F. Singlecopies1/6-stg.;
30 cents : 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French. Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international reply
coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
tne opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Pans)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German . Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
Page
10
12
20
24
27
15
TURNING POINT
The gigantic effort of the Ü.N. Development Decade
frank appraisal in four parts
By U Thant
NEW STRATEGY FOR DEVELOPMENT
By René Maheu
TECHNICAL CO-OPERATION
IN A WORLD OF CHANGE
By David Owen
THE GREAT REVOLUTION
Towards a universal society
By Walter Lippmann
SCIENCE, A NEW SOCIAL FORCE
By Mikhail Millionshchikov
UNESCO METAMORPHOSIS
OTHER FEATURES
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
COLOMBIA
Developing the fabulous valley of the Cauca
PHILIPPINES
Life returns to "Death Valley"
AFGHANISTAN
A country 90% unexploited
THE NEW CEDARS OF LEBANON
Restoring one of nature's ancient treasures
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
Cover photo
We are now at the mid-point of the Uni¬
ted Nations Development Decade. What
progress has been made by countries
striving to free themselves from the bur¬
dens of economic underdevelopment and
what major obstacles have, they still to
overcome? The Unesco Courier devotes
this issue to these vital questions and
to the multiple aspects of international
technical co-operation. Every day sees
new furrows being ploughed in a world¬
wide process of economic development.
Ci FIAP-Antonio Grau Cloquell
Villafranca del Panadas. Spain
v . "
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
TURNING POINT
The United Nations Development Decade is 5 yrs old.
How has it fared ? U Thant gives a frank answer
For the past five years the world community has been engaged in a global
adventure unprecedented in history: the United Nations Development De¬
cade which has now reached its mid-point. How far has this gigantic effort
actually succeeded, what have been the major difficulties and disappoint¬
ments and what are the prospects for the remainder of the Decade during
the 1960s? To these questions, which none of us whatever our country öf
origin can afford to ignore, the Secretary-General of the U.N. offers a frank
appraisal in the challenging analysis published below.
by U Thant
Secretary General of the United Nations
4
HE idea of a Decade of Development, launched
and sustained by the United Nations, is design¬
ed to remind us of a number of things. First, the process
of development itself the process whereby, at different*
times and at different speeds but with complete irrever¬
sibility, the whole human race is adapting to its use the
modern instruments of science and technology. This
process involves all mankind from the commuter in mod¬
ern Megalopolis to the herdsmen on the Saharan fringe.
The United Nations Development Decade seeks to stim¬
ulate our imagination so that we may become aware of
the increasing interdependence of the whole process the
growth, underneath the vicissitudes of day-to-day politics,
of a substratum of economic and social experience which
is more or less common to all the nations of the earth.
Above all, it tries to dramatize the stark fact that the
gap in resources between the fully modernized nations and
their still developing neighbours is tending to widen, leaving
some two-thirds of humanity below the poverty line, turn¬
ing the developed societies, whether or not they realize
it, into a privileged élite.
The concept of the Decade is essentially a focus for
action, action fd lessen the gap, to speed up the proces¬
ses of modernization, to release the majority of mankind
from crippling poverty, to mitigate the tensions and hosti¬
lities which must flow from the world's vast inequalities in
wealth, to restore solidarity and hope.
The U.N. General Assembly has emphasized the need for
increasing the transfer of resources to developing coun¬
tries by expressing the hope that the "flow of international
assistance and capital should be increased substantially
so that it might reach as soon as possible approximately
one per cent of the combined national incomes of the eco¬
nomically advanced countries."
The launching of the Development Decade represents a
new departure In international economic relations. By
agreeing to co-ordinate action with a view to attaining a
5 per cent growth rate in developing countries, governments
in fact extended the concept of sustained and expanding
demand from the domestic economy to the world at large.
The adoption of a target for transfers of resources to
developing countries in terms of a proportion of the national
incomes of developed countries showed that the concept
of shared resources is beginning to enter the philosophy
of States in relation not simply to their own citizens but to
other States as well.
Today, halfway through the Development Decade, how
has the General Assembly's initiative fared? Many of the
basic facts remain as tough as ever. The harsh fact' per¬
sists that many of the poorest economies have continued
to grow most slowly, the growth in developing countries
as a whole slowed down; at the same time the growth rate
in the economically advanced market economies has acce¬
lerated. The gap between the per capita incomes of the
developing countries» and those of the developed countries
has also widened during the 1960s; between 1960 and 1962
the average annual per capita income in the developed
market economies increased by almost $100 while that in
the developing countries increased by barely $5.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The annual flow of international assistance and capital to
developing countries was substantially larger in the early
years of the Development Decade than in the second half
of the 1950s. However, more recently the net flow has
virtually ceased to increase and progress towards the 1 per
cent goal for resource transfer to developing countries was
halted.
Two-thirds of the world's population living in the less
developed regions of the world still share less than one-
sixth of the world's income. In 1962 annual per capita
income in these regions averaged $136 while that of the
population of the economically advanced market economies
in North America and Western Europe averaged $2,845 and
$1,033, respectively.
These abstract figures do little to convey the realities
which underlie the gaps in income. In spite of dramatic
improvements in the prevention of disease which over the
last decade have added ten to twenty years to the expec¬
tation of life in the developing countries, their average
still falls by as much again behind life expectancy round
the North Atlantic. In particular, the tragic death of small
children weighs far more heavily upon the developing lands.
In the most highly developed countries, the mortality rate of
children up to five years of age varies from 4.5 to 6.3 per
1,000. Yet in Latin America, the rates are five to ten times
higher and in Africa, higher still.
One reason lies in the disparities in medical services ;
in North America, Western Europe and the U.S.S.R. where
there is generally one doctor for fewer than 1,000 inha¬
bitants compared with one for 6,000 in India, 32,000 in
Afghanistan, 39,000 in Mali and approximately 96,000 in
Ethiopia. Failure to invest adequately in the control of
disease and the promotion of health, together with a lack
of coverage by health services of large segments of the
population where disease is endemic, has led in many
parts of the world to a deterioration of standards of health
and sanitation.
NOTHER reason for the difference in mortality
rates certainly lies in disparities in diet. Men
and women in North America and Western Europe eat
on the average about 3,000 calories and 80 to 90 grammes
of protein a day. In Latin America, outside Argentina, the
average falls to 2,400 calories and some 70 grammes of
protein; in Asia to 2,100 calories and 50 grammes a level
still below prewar standards; in Africa the protein consump¬
tion is lower still. But these abstractions give no true
sense of the gap between the steaks and chocolate, the
salads and fruit of diets in the developed countries and the
bowl of rice, with little variety beyond a change of sauce,
which makes up, day in, day out, the food of most Asians.
Inadequacies in diet and medical care are made
more intolerable for about 1,000 million people by the des¬
perate standards of housing which they are forced to
endure. The major cities of the developing continents all
have their densely crowded shanty towns in which 20 to 30
per cent of the city's inhabitants may be living without
water, without sewers, without roads. And out in the
countryside the shacks of day labourers, landless men,
untouchables and rural unemployed only seem a little less
miserable because of their larger ration of light and air.
The misery of much of the developing world ¡s a progres¬
sive misery. It threatens to grow worse in the second
half of the Decade. On present showing the numbers of
unemployed and men and women suffering from hunger
and malnutrition will be markedly greater in 1970 than
today. It Is in the poorer countries that the highest growth
rate of population is found. In most of Asia and Africa it
is over 2 per cent and rapidly approaching the 3 per cent
level. In some of the Latin American countries it is higher.
On present showing there simply is not in prospect a
growth in agricultural production sufficient to accommo¬
date this rising flood of people. The world's agricultural
production is growing by under 3 per cent per year, and
the growth rate is much lower in some critical areas. The
continuance of traditional methods in farming has often
been the main obstacle to any significant increase in food
production.
APID migration to the cities has further com¬
plicated the problem. The rate at which this
migration has taken place has often far exceeded the rate
at which urban employment opportunities have been increas¬
ing, with the result that unemployment is rising in many of
the developing countries.
To give one striking example: in 1955 the Indian esti¬
mate of unemployment was some 5 million. By 1961 it had
grown to 8 millions. Even if the planned production targets
for 1966 and 1971 are fulfilled, the Indian authorities esti¬
mate that unemployment will still rise to 12 million and
14 million in these two years respectively. A particularly
disturbing feature in these situations is the degree to which
unemployment will fall most heavily on young people. In
Indonesia, 50 per cent of the urban unemployed and In
Ceylon 80 per cent are under 25 years of age.
This phenomenon of urban unemployment may not in
theory be worse than the semi-employment and under¬
nourishment of the villagers. But in the countryside
family and clan give some support. There is a little more
spare food; in some regions, there may be hunting and fish¬
ing on the side. The city reduces the new migrants to
the rawest struggle for survival. Yet it is to the cities they
come in a flood which far surpasses in speed the general
growth of population. Cities grow, the world over, by
about 4 per cent a year. Some of the greatest cities grow
at twice that rate. About 5,000 newcomers a week move
into Rio de Janeiro. The capital cities of tropical Africa
have doubled in little more than a decade.
The problems that spring from the dynamism of growth
in population, coupled with the added dynamism of urban
expansion, are propelled forward by yet another dimension
of dynamic change the change in people's expectations.
This factor is no doubt inescapable in an open world of
total communication where the richer nations give a daily
demonstration of what can be achieved in terrestrial pros¬
perity. But it compels the governments of the developing
lands to undertake policies and projects which, in the short
run, tend to complicate their already formidable difficulties.
In a world where new drugs dramatically reduce morta¬
lity from such old enemies as yaws or leprosy or tubercu¬
losis, people clamour for the medical help that sends the
population leaping still further ahead of food supplies. In
a world of hope and upheaval, the young men seize the new
means of transport designed to open up the countryside to
stream away from the farms before there is room for them
In the cities and before the farms are producing a surplus
of food.
In a world now aware of education as the gateway
to advance, parents demand village schools which the
youths often leave with barely a primary education to seek
unskilled jobs in urban centres just the jobs which a more
sophisticated industrialization is beginning to abolish.' No
government of a developing country can escape these
dilemmas. But as the Development Decade advances, the
impact of all these dynamic forces of explosive change is,
on balance, to make their difficulties more complex and
their prospects more daunting still.
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
55»Ti3ïS5jg(£2S?»
á"
PIf 1
:'-
v^gi
COLOMBIA'S
FABULOUS
VALLEY OF
THE CAUCA
Like many developing nations,
Colombia is a country of striking
contrasts: on the one hand cities
and whole regions (like Bogota, the
capital, right) on a par with any
found in the most industrialized
countries of the world; on the other
hand, vast areas waiting for full
development. Top left, the Servicio
Nacional de Aprentisaje, a voca¬
tional training school in Bogota,
built some years ago with U.N.
technical aid. The ultra-modern
pilotis support the business training
section attended by 2,000 young
men and women. Lower left, rafts
of "guadua" logs float down the
Cauca River near Cali. The valley
of the Cauca is one of the richest
and most fertile of all South Ame¬
rica, but much of it is still unexploit¬
ed. In 1963 Colombia with the help
of the World Bank undertook an
extensive survey of coal deposits
in the valley and with FAO help set
up an agricultural training centre.
Photos O Paul Almasy, Par
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TURNING POINT
IN DEVELOPMENT
PART mm
B1 UT there is no place for despair. Even if the
	 'distance between the developed -and the de¬
veloping countries sometimes seems unbridgeable, the
developed are themselves proof that such chasms can be
crossed, such disparities reduced to a more tolerable level.
After all, the first decades of technological change inside
the advanced economies produced conditions which closely
resemble the divisions and difficulties of the modern world
economy.
In the United Kingdom, for example, in the middle of the
nineteenth century, after some fifty or sixty years of rapid
economic growth, society was so divided between rich and
poor, so diverse in opportunity and affluence, so alien in
class and culture that it resembled not so much a unified
community as two nations separate in wealth, separate in
understanding, indeed, almost as separate in contact and
sympathy as are the two segments of the modern world
the rich "North" and the still poverty-stricken "South"
below the Tropic of Cancer.
But a century has passed and conditions in the deve¬
loped countries have changed dramatically. The slums
have largely vanished. Good health is all but universal.
Educational horizons widen steadily. Entire communities
have made the transition to the standards of middle-class
comfort. It has taken time, but the chasm has been
crossed. It can be crossed again.
The analogy is imperfect, no doubt, but it can be a source
of hope and guidance. In many fundamental ways the pro¬
cesses of economic and social development, precipitated by
technological change, resemble each other, in spite of the
great variety of cultural and national backgrounds against
which they work. The methods by which today's fully mod¬
ernized societies overcame their internai obstructions are
now part of the vital information available to developing
societies as they struggle with their own problems. Some
of the steps taken in the now developed societies are rele¬
vant to the much wider context of development in general.
I
8
N the nineteenth century, a stream of disco¬
veries and inventions, coupled with increasing
sophistication in their application pushed back the limits
imposed by materials and skills. The nuclear and chemical
revolutions of our day with their promise of almost limitless
power and almost unlimited substitutes are only the last in
a sustained series of physical liberations from the oid
restraints.
This greater technical elbowroom helps to explain the
success of another type of adjustment the ability of the
mass of the workers to capture a much larger share of the
economy's production. Once higher purchasing power
became a fact, it was clear that better technology could
accommodate the larger wage bill by increasing output per
worker and that the bill itself had become a vital element
in sustaining market demand.
Meanwhile, changes in governmental policy also under¬
lined the importance of sustained demand and increased its
effectiveness. Through their fiscal policies, governments
both lessened the income gap and reinforced market
demand. At the same time, the proportion of taxation
spent on schools, health and better housing led to sharp
increases in skills and working capacity and thus hastened
the growth of productivity.
The expansion and adaptation of science and technology ;
defensive, collective action by poor nations to increase
their earnings in the world market; enlightened action by
the developed élite to see that sharing in fact occurs; direct
transfers of resources from rich nations to poor to increase
their skills and education, their health, social assets and
ability to help themselves; and finally, a general effort to
extend the concept of sustained and expanding 'demand
from the domestic economy to the world at large all these
factors can, by analogy, play their part in lessening the gap
between rich and poor nations, in sharing more fully the
new patrimony of technology and affluence and in creating
a modern'world society. And, in essence, this is what the
Decade of Development is all about.
When the United Nations itself was set up twenty years
ago, it was designed, apart from its strictly political pur¬
poses, as a centre for harmonizing international efforts
towards world-wide economic and social improvement but
not as the sole instrument by which that effort should
directly be made. Responsibility in particular fields was
divided among the United Nations and a number of autono¬
mous international agencies.
WITH the Development Decade, co-operation
among international organizations has become
of critical importance. A rural resettlement programme is
likely to require not only the crop specialists whom the Food
and Agriculture Organization can provide, assistance from
the International Labour Organization in such matters as
surveying the manpower potential and providing for training
for rural employment, from the World Health Organization in
the public health aspects of the scheme, from the United
Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural Organization in
the provision of school and out-of-school educational faci¬
lities, but also from the United Nations itself in regional
planning, the provision of social services, the development
of community organization and local government at the area
of settlement. Furthermore, it may benefit from food sup¬
plied by the World Food Programme, and the United Nations
Children's Fund may provide equipment and medical sup¬
plies. If capital as well as technical assistance is needed
to carry out the scheme, the government may wish also to
bring the International Bank or its affiliate, the International
Development Association into the picture.
Another vital factor has been the inception and growth,
from 1949 onwards, of the Expanded Programme of
Technical Assistance. This is a central pooling of govern¬
ment contributions designed to provide, financial resources
(nearly 500 million dollars in the first fifteen years) which
the United Nations and the agencies could use to meet
the priority needs of developing countries for expert
assistance, fellowships and equipment for demonstration
and training purposes.
The Special Fund, a partnership between over 100
Governments and the family of United Nations agencies,
represents a new dimension of co-operation. Since its
inception in January 1959, it has assisted more than 500
high-priority projects in some 13Ö low-income countries
and territories involving over 1,000 million dollars of which
approximately 60 per cent has been provided by the
recipient countries.
The Special Fund has concentrated its efforts on four
major activities : surveys of available resources and their
economic potential for development ; strengthening or
establishing applied research institutes which define
industrial and agricultural potentials, promote better use
of local materials and improve production techniques ;
establishing training institutes which produce engineers,
technicians, planners, managers, industrial instructors, and
secondary school teachers ; building economic planning
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Three dramas of underdevelopment:
(1) exploding populations (2) rising unemployment
(3) mushrooming shantytowns
units which will focus and co-ordinate national and regional
development efforts. The Fund has also provided advanced
education or technical training for over 70,000 nationals
of seventy-four developing countries.
The work of the Expanded Programme and the Special
Fund shows how much relatively modest amounts of
multilateral assistance can contribute in helping developing
countries to make their natural resources more available
for productive use, and to put those resources to work
for the benefit of their people. The efforts will certainly
be intensified if, as the Economic and Social Council
recommends, the two programmes are fused in a single
United Nations Development Programme.
A striking example of the new unified approach is
provided by the World Food Programme under the
joint sponsorship of the United Nations and the FAO.
The World Food Programme is a true child of the Develop¬
ment Decade, having begun operations only in 1963. Its
finance $100 million for the period 1963-1965 which maybe
increased to $250 million in the three-year phase is made
up of voluntary contributions in cash, food surpluses and
services such as shipping.
In addition to giving emergency help in times of disaster,
its major work is the longer task of promoting economic
and social development through the provision of surplus
food required in development projects as diverse as
irrigation, afforestation and road construction. Much of its
work and that of the Food and Agriculture Organization
has received signal support from the Freedom from Hunger
Campaign which, under the leadership of FAQ, has raised
over $220 million and drawn 165 states and territories into
action since 1960 in the interests of better diets and more
productive farming.
HE growing co-operation between the Inter¬
national Bank and other organizations within the
United Nations system in development work is another
source of increasing efficiency. The Bank, like every other
agency concerned with growth, has become more and more
aware that the springs of rapid development lie in the
farms where output and skill must rise if there is to be a
food surplus for the cities, in diversified, industrial growth,
and in education It is therefore beginning to look in these
new directions and its first step has been to reach special
partnership arrangements 'with the Food and Agriculture
Organization and with Unesco and to devise ways in
which Bank money up to a level of some $400 million
can be channelled into its subsidiary, the International
Finance Corporation for investment in industrial ventures.
The United Nations and its agencies, by establishing
patterns of co-operation, agreeing on priorities and working
out policies for putting them into effect, can help govern¬
ments to co-ordinate their own activities and decisions.
There are opportunities for inter-governmental co-ordin¬
ation at other levels.
The governing body of each agency is itself a centre
for inter-governmental co-operation. Some agencies the
Universal Postal Union, for instance, or the International
Telecommunication Union are by the very nature of their
work intergovernmental throughout their entire operations.
Over a wider area, a body such as the U.N. Social
Commission can be the sounding-board for the world's
dilemmas for example, its chaotic urbanization, its run¬
away growth in population as well as its aspirations
and ensure that they and the policies they call for are
brought primarily and with due weight to the governments'
attention.
The United Nations Regional Commissions in the
developing continents in Asia and the Far East, in Latin
America, in Africa have become active centres of co¬
ordinated strategy. In Latin America, the Economic
Commission for Latin America has been a leading
influence in the movement to set up a free trade area
and to back it with agreed policies on industrial
deployment. In Africa, the Economic Commission for
Africa has been instrumental in setting up the African
Development Bank and has helped to launch inquiries
into the possibility of an African Payments Union.
An instance of how far this type of regional co-operation
may go can be seen in the steadily increasing integration
of Central America. Since the signing of the General
Treaty on Central American Economic Integration in Guate¬
mala in December 1960, trade has almost doubled and
currencies have become completely convertible.
Two other examples of inter-governmental co-operation
deserve particular mention. Missions supported by the
Special Fund have surveyed the Senegal and the Niger
River Basins in Africa and assisted the riparian States
in drawing up draft treaties for joint use and development
of the river's resources. In the Far East, a much more
ambitious scheme is in hand to survey and develop the
whole of the Lower Mekong River Basin.
The Mekong project covers not only the uses of the
river in irrigation, in power, in navigation and flood
control but also the administrative structures needed to
exploit all these possibilities and the kind of economic
and social development needed if people are to take full
advantage of them.
More than twenty countries, beside the riparian States
Laos, Thailand, Cambodia and the Republic of Viet-Nam
the United Nations and most of the specialized agencies,
three private foundations and a number of business firms
have all been concerned with the preliminary surveys
and not all the political vicissitudes of the region have
deflected the four local Governments from co-operation
in this field. The tragic juxtaposition of the scheme with
the fighting in South-East Asia and the hope that con¬
ceivably it might provide the context of a constructive
peace only serve to heighten its significance.
Y own definition of an inspired choice is a man
or more, has unlocked the doors of skill and
output, confounded the gloomy prophets of inherent physical
limitation and so fantastically increased man's power io
produce that, in developed economies, to sustain sufficient
demand is more the problem than to mobilize sufficient
supply. This technology is, naturally and inevitably, one of
the developing nations' chief hopes for the successful
achievement of modernization and for any considerable
bridging of the gap between rich and poor.
The poor nations are, in some ways, infinitely better
placed than the pioneers of an earlier century. In the
first place, they have a hundred years of other nations'
experience upon which to draw with some degree of
clarity. One forgets how much earlier technological ad¬
vance was based on uncertain experiment and lucky guess.
Above all, one forgets the mystery in which the whole
process of modernization was shrouded. The early entre¬
preneurs tried out new processes, tested the market, made
a profit or perhaps were ruined and all the time they
CONT'D ON PAGE 30
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
NEW STRATEGY
FOR DEVELOPMENT
IT is no longer necessary to prove that education is one
of the basic factors, if not the basic factor in develop¬
ment. Man is both the instrument and the end product of development,
and his education is now a subject that has assumed increasing weight
even in economic studies. If we compare 1965 with 1960 we find that
this is perhaps the major innovation in thinking on development and in
the strategy for development adopted by international organizations.
I am convinced that this fact, now that it is universally acknowledged
and affirmed, should be the major factor in shaping the future policy of
these international organizations in the second half of the U.N. Develop¬
ment Decade.
WITHOUT scientists, engineers and technicians at all
levels no country can call itself free. This raises the
whole problem of scientific and technical education, from secondary
school study to basic research carried out at the higher institute level,
taking in every type of technical training whether in or outside univer¬
sities and schools or within the framework of industry and agriculture.
"HE idea of education no longer has to be promoted.
The motivation for it exists already and springs from
deep within the hearts of the great masses of humanity. This demand
for education has not been created by international organizations or by
governments. On the contrary, to many it must seem like some surging
wave that threatens to sweep everything before it unless it is channelled
in time into new paths where its vast potentialities can be rationally
exploited. The need, the passion, for education is such that it is turning
into an irresistible clamour of world-wide dimensions sparked by the
triple cry for national development, national freedom and respect
for the dignity of man. So strong and far-reaching is this demand that
many nations be they highly developed or not, newly independent or
established for centuries now find themselves face to face with a host
of formidable problems which are no longer just technical or even eco¬
nomic and financial in nature but also political.
René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
(Passages from an address to the U.N. Eco¬
nomic and Social Council on July 9, 1965)
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
s
' \
\j>
*\
ç
Giant hydro-electric installation under construction at Furnas
on the Rio Grande (Brazil). Photo: World Bank-J.R. Nonato.
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Fifteen years ago, the first day of July 1950, marked the beginning of the
largest and most far-reaching undertaking in international technical co-opera¬
tion: the United Nations Expanded Programme of Technical Assistance.
The Expanded Programme reaches this anniversary mark in a year of special
emphasis on international responsibilities and action to help meet the problems
of a world in which not only the political security but also the economic and
social well-being of mankind as a whole has yet to find its proper balance.
In the first place, the fifteenth year of the Expanded Programme is also being
celebrated as the twentieth anniversary of the founding of the United Nations
itself. Secondly, this is also International Co-operation Year: and the Expanded
Programme stands out as an example of harmony of purpose and action in the
midst of diversity. Thirdly, the year 1965 marks as well the mid-point of the
United Nations Development Decade; and the Expanded Programme, with its
close partners the United Nations Special Fund and the regular programmes of
the United Nations and the associated specialized agencies constitute together
one of the most important direct contributions of the organized international com¬
munity to economic and social progress in the countries which stand most
urgently in need of development.
Finally, the year brings a prospect of a new and closer association of the
Expanded Programme and the Special Fund already recommended by the Eco¬
nomic and Social Council and awaiting action by the General Assembly in a
single United Nations Development Programme.
The Unesco Courier has asked Mr. David Owen, Chairman of The United
Nations Technical Assistance Board, to recall the early days of the Expanded
Programme and to give an account of its growth and progress. We are happy
to present his article below.
o
o.
Ó
x
12
TECHNICAL
CO-OPERATION
A WORLD
OF CHANGE
by David Owen
Excutive Chairman
U. N. Technical Assistance Board
WO documents that stand like milestones In
the history of international assistance to the
developing countries are before me as I write these lines.
One is the first, the other the latest, of the Annual Reports
of the Technical Assistance Board to its governing body,
the Technical Assistance Committee of the United Nations
Economic and Social Council. Almost exactly fifteen years
lie between the first and last of these pages and what
a world of change and progress these years have encom-
passedl
"The basis for operations under the Expanded Programme
Is now firmly established... the financial support pledged
by governments at the Technical Assistance Conference
now paves the way for the actual launching of this major
undertaking of the family of the United Nations." So we
wrote in our first report, under the date of July 4, 1950.
What we meant, in simpler terms, was that we now at
least had money in pledge, If not yet In the bank to the
amount of some $20 million; and we also had the machinery
agreed methods and procedures of co-ordination among
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
mm mWM
One of the first Egyptian women to train as a specialist in industrial hygiene, this student of the Higher
Institute of Public Health in Alexandria is measuring gas toxicity given off in rayon textile manufacture.
The World Health Organization helped the U.A.R. to equip the Institute. In 15 years, U.N. specialized
agencies have sent 859 experts to the U.A.R. and granted over 1,000 fellowships. Over 580 U.A.R. ex¬
perts have gone to other countries. FAO, Unesco, ILO and the International Civil Aviation Organization
this year are taking part in 15 large-scale scientific and technological Special Fund projects in the U.A.R.
the founding members with which to convert that money
Into expert advisers, fellowships and equipment asked for
by developing countries to help them attack their problems
of economic and social development.
Oddly enough, and for the first and last time, we found
ourselves at that moment with resources far more plentiful
than firm' requests for assistance. These were so few,
Indeed, that the Technical Assistance Board was able, as
a body, to scrutinize and almost to savour many of them
individually. With no small sense of anticipation, and even
of excitement, we agreed also to send a few exploratory
missions Into the field In order to find out precisely what
kinds of assistance the countries needed most.
We were, in short, feeling our way into the barely-
explored ' realm of co-ordinated International technical
assistance: indeed, "pragmatic" was the expression that
we applied In that first report to the nature of our approach.
But by the time and It was only a matter of months
that the requests for assistance came pouring in and that
our commitments to provide experts and fellowships
mounted in each case into the hundreds, we felt that the
Expanded Programme was substantially in operation.
And indeed it was, by comparison with the scale of
international assistance previously available. But to turn
from the first report of the Technical Assistance Board to
the latest is to rediscover how far we had yet to go in
developing the Expanded Programme, as it has come to
be called, and to recognize, with some grounds for pride,
how much has been accomplished.
Fifteen years ago the United Nations family looked out
on a group of over 100 underdeveloped countries and
territories which were suffering from a lack of capital,
generally unfavourable trade opportunities and a serious
shortage of technical and administrative skills and expe¬
rience. The International organizations were in no imme¬
diate position to provide the first two ingredients, and so
they concentrated their energies and the resources to 'be
made available by the voluntary contributions of Govern¬
ments, on the ingredient which they could effectively
mobilize: the exchange of knowledge, skills and experience,
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
WORLD OF CHANGE (Cont'd)
32,000 fellowships for training abroad
to organize a civil service or the management of an air¬
port; to run a demonstration farm or a model school; to
train industrial apprentices, nurses and weather forecasters.
Our principal medium of assistance to the countries in
need of it was to be the assignment of "experts", and
this seemed to me at the beginning to be fraught with
perils. Could we assemble, from our various member
countries, large numbers of men and women with sufficient
personal and professional qualifications to fulfill our prom¬
ises to requesting governments? Even one poorly chosen
expert could discredit in an entire country the conception
of international assistance, and we would be running this
risk some hundreds of times a year.
It happened in fact that these fears were intensified
almost immediately by an extremely unfortunate selection
of one of our first appointees. He turned out, however,
to be an exception to a record which we and the thousands
of professionals and technicians concerned can hold up
with no little pride. There have been more than 14,000
appointments in the intervening years: agronomists
recruited and sent out by the Food and Agriculture Orga¬
nization; malariologists by the World Health Organization;
educational planners by Unesco, atomic energy specia¬
lists by the International Atomic Energy Agency; and so
on through the hundreds of particular fields of economic
and social development covered by our participating organ¬
izations (1). I do not think that these agencies would
claim a consistent level of excellence among all their
appointments, but from my own knowledge I can say that
we have had a minimum of embarrassment (and virtually
none of a political kind despite an almost universal range
of nationalities), adequate standards of competence and
a fair share of inspired choices.
I Y own definition of an inspired choice is a man
(or woman) who can function effectively in the
face of delay, resistance or inertia, adjust his objectives to
what can reasonably be accomplished, and gain the con¬
fidence and friendship of the people with whom he works.
This is especially difficult at the grass roots, but hardly less
so in the government offices and institutions where more
than half of our experts can be found. These are the
planners, the statisticians, the fiscal advisers, the admi¬
nistrators, and all the many others whose conditions of
work do not conform to the heroic mold, but whose advice
can seriously affect a country's progress in a given sphere.
I am thinking, for example, of one of our economists
in Libya whose advice was eagerly sought and followed
in establishing national priorities; the experts in Ghana who
helped to plan and analyze a major country-wide census; the
multi-national team that is helping Singapore to industria¬
lize; and the people all over Africa who are drawing up plans
for or demonstrating improvements in education, agriculture,
medical services and the like. It is one of the ironies of
the first fifteen years of the Expanded Programme that
these kinds of assistance have won the least public atten-
j . (1) In addition to these four, there are the U.N., the International
J4 Labour Organization, the International Civil Aviation Organization, the
International Telecommunication Union, the World Meteorological
Organization, thé Universal Postal Union and the Intergovernmental
Maritime Consultative Organization.
tion because they are undramatic and because their suc¬
cess, when it happens, happens without fanfare.
The other principal form of technical co-operation under
the Expanded Programme has been the fellowship award
the means given to the technician, the teacher, the
administrator, the factory foreman or the trade unionist
in a developing country to obtain further training away
from home. There have been 32,000 such awards In the
last fifteen years, and they have, I believe, left a higher
degree of professional and technical polish at many levels
in many developing countries. I have met cabinet ministers
who referred proudly to earlier periods of training under
international auspices, just as I have met railway foremen
and factory supervisors who did their jobs better, or took
over jobs of greater responsibility, when they returned
from abroad.
T the same time, we have learned to regard
Lthe fellowship aspect of technical co-operation
as a secondary means of achieving national development.
We have accumulated much evidence that the primary
means is the creation of institutions, those locally or region¬
ally based facilities which can ensure the creation and the
perpetuation of skills without draining a country of its scarce
and non-expandable supply of trained men and women.
Most government officials have come to share this view,
which is reflected in the number of requests for Expanded
Programme assistance in establishing teacher training
colleges, scientific research institutes, schools for public
administration, for social workers, for medical personnel,
and especially for all grades of vocational instructor and
supervisor.
The Programme does not run these schools or assemble
entire faculties, any more than it builds dams or maintains
farms. But our experts do provide the support in the plan¬
ning stage and in the organization and administration of the
institutions, and often fill key positions on the staffs until
these institutions can train their own replacements. As a
result, we can point to such facilities as the Higher School
of Nursing in Alexandria, Egypt, where 124 young nurses
have already graduated, to the Libyan vocational and
clerical training centre where the graduating list since
1953 has reached over 650, to the Indian Institute of
Technology at Bombay, the Central American School of
Public Administration and the Middle East Technical Univer¬
sity in Ankara, Turkey. In these cases and several others,
the International family can reasonably say that without
technical co-operation the facilities might not have existed
at all.
They would certainly not have existed, of course, if they
had not also received the adequate support of the receiving
governments. In the light of present-day knowledge of
the possibilities as well as the limitations of technical
assistance, this statement may appear self-evident. It was
not necessarily as self-evident when technical co-operation
was still a little tried and somewhat Messianic concept.
We were so preoccupied then with our own machinery for
giving aid that we sometimes tended to take it for granted
that the developing countries would have the Institutional
capacity to absorb the assistance.
In fact, a basic symptom of underdevelopment was the
absence or inadequacy of just those facilities and services
that could guarantee the effectiveness of technical assis-
CONT'D ON PAGE 16
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Ufe returns to
'Death Valley'
Until ten years ago the fertile but
malaria-ridden high plateau of Tabuk,
north of Luzon in the Philippines,
was known as "Death Valley". Mala¬
ria was driving farmers away from
the area in which there are 23 vil¬
lages. As a result of a campaign
waged by Philippine health teams in
co-operation with the World Health
Organization, the farmers have
returned. Tabuk is now called the
"rice granary" of northern Luzon.
International co-operation has thus
also contributed to the world-wide
Freedom from Hunger Campaign
launched by the Food and Agriculture
Organization.- FAO and WHO have
joined with Philippine specialists ' in
a wide range of co-operative pro¬
jects ranging from virology and food
and drug administration to fisheries
development and animal husbandry.
Philippine doctor stops to chat with
Tabuk farmer and son while carry¬
ing out a health check-up in the area.
Below, typical village on the Tabuk
plateau. Anti-malariá team can be seen
crossing fields in foreground. -Left,
farmer's wife and children who
have recently returned to their village.
Photos WHO-Paul Alrnasy
4
£*«*«*
:% WmM \\wWk
'" xtàhfr&£'-ï-22i2
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
An arid and mountainous country and the ancient meeting place of
Greek and Indian cultures, Afghanistan has a population of 12 million,
fully 90 % of which is concentrated in the country's fertile plains and
valleys. Only one-tenth of Afghanistan's land is really exploited. Its
economy still largely depends on agriculture and animal husbandry,
although the government is now beginning to develop the wealth of
the subsoil (oil, natural gas, coal and iron). In 1964 nearly 950,000
dollars were provided for Afghanistan's development under the U.N.
Expanded Programme of Technical Assistance, and between 1959 and
1964 the U.N. Special Fund contributed over 10 million dollars. A more
recent Special Fund project, the higher teacher training college, in
Kabul, was opened in April 1965. Unesco is helping Afghanistan to
develop primary, secondary and technical education and in co-operation
with Unicef it has set up a teacher training academy. Unesco spec¬
ialists have also helped to modernize physics programmes and teaching
materials at Kabul University.
MMMMMMMMMMM
WORLD OF CHANGE (Cont'd)
AFGHANISTAN :
a land 90 % unexploited
Left, photo-reproduction apparatus pro¬
vided by Unesco in use at the audio¬
visual centre in Kabul (Afghanistan).
The centre prints textbooks and maps.
Below, pipe-laying in a Kabul suburb-
part of a new public works programme.
The ILO ¡s helping Afghanistan to plan
for full employment as well as to im¬
prove its vocational training facilities.
ILO
National effort counts most
16
tance: national machinery for co-ordinating assistance; an
economic and social development plan with built-in priori¬
ties; an adequate legislative and administrative framework;
and, not least, a nucleus of technicians and administrators
who could be assigned as counterparts to the international
experts.
The absence of all or some of these affected not only
the Expanded Programme but also the endeavours of all
those governments and organizations which ventured
independently into the new field of economic aid, and it
tried the mettle of many persons involved. I recall the
case of a most distinguished mining engineer whom we
had assigned to an Asian country. More than six months
of his allotted year were allowed to pass without any
support from the ministry which had eagerly sought his
services. Just as we were about to move him to another
country, however, his work caught the interest of quite
another branch of the government, and he was on his
way to a successful assignment.
But cases such as' this demonstrate the flexibility of the
individual rather than the solution of the basic problem. This
was left to be solved and is moving slowly towards solu¬
tion with every passing day by the administrative maturing
of governments, by their accumulation of experience in deal
ing with and making use of all kinds of external aid and also,
I firmly believe, by the efforts by which the United Nations
and its agencies are helping governments in those very
directions.
Under the Expanded Programme, for example, new pro¬
gramming procedures were adopted in 1954 which put the
burden of establishing priorities for development on the
receiving governments themselves and which encouraged,
and indeed virtually obliged them to set up central co-or¬
dinating units to arrange their requests for assistance
according to national development priorities. Working with
these units are the resident representatives of the Tech¬
nical Assistance Board and the field representatives of
the agencies, who are able to guide governments in their
choice and use of' foreign assistance, the former in terms
of overall policy, the latter on the technical substance of
projects.
Moreover, the Expanded Programme has had an effect
on national planning and co-ordination, particularly in the
newer countries, by the very nature of the assistance which
is offered: not only, as I have mentioned, by the emphasis
given to training, but also by providing expert advice in
all areas of economic and social planning and administra¬
tion. From the very beginning, I felt that this delicate and
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Afghans report for
work on a section
of the Asian High¬
way now under cons¬
truction between
Kabul and Kandahar.
crucial area of assistance is a natural focal point for an
international (and therefore disinterested in character) pro¬
gramme, and it has been gratifying to .see this confirmed
by the requests of many governments for assistance of
this kind.
We have grounds for being satisfied that the Expanded
Programme has proved itself to be a substantial and useful
instrument for economic and social development. We
remind ourselves constantly, however, that it is an instru¬
ment and that, like all instruments, it must be used pro¬
perly to produce measurable results. Technical co-operation
cannot work wonders by itself. It was never meant to do
so. In the enormously complicated task of building the
economy of a nation, it is that nation's own strenous efforts
on Its own behalf which count first. Those efforts may
bear fruit more or less quickly depending upon the availa¬
bility of capital (from within and without), the opportunities
for profitable foreign trade and a dozen other vital and
interlocking factors, of which provision of skills is only
one, however important. It is always difficult and some¬
times presumptious, therefore, to try to measure the
contribution of the Expanded Programme or any other
avenue of technical assistance to the overall development
of a given country.
It was said fifteen years ago that ours was a programme
not for years but for decades and this has turned out
to be, if anything, an understatement. Looking at some of
our work, I must frankly confess that it has often taken
longer to achieve worthwhile results than we might ori
ginally have believed. I am not thinking so much of such
classic cases as that of an expert whose recommendations
on the reorganization of a country's civil service languished
on a shelf for four years, until a new administration dusted
it off and made it national law. I am thinking rather of the
stubborn resistance of the problems of poverty, disease
and ignorance their capacity, .indeed, to grow as well as
to survive. In the rapidly increasing population of the
developing countries as a- whole, these evils are capable
of blighting even larger numbers of lives now than when
we began our concerted attack on them fifteen years ago.
We can be satisfied that national and international efforts
have together prevented the toll from being even greater
and have opened for many thousands of people opportu-
nitids as well as hope for economic and social improve¬
ment. But we have far to go before we can be satisfied
that enough has been done to create such opportunities
and to justify such hopes.
Generous though our governments have been in contri¬
buting to this cause their donations through the Expanded
Programme alone total the equivalent of five hundred million
dollars for 15 years their earnest desire to see the burdens
of underdevelopment lifted for the sake of a decent and
peaceful life for all mankind has yet to be matched by the
resources needed for the purpose. The growth of the
Special Fund, and the proposed merger of the two program- ^_
mes in a combined United Nations Development Programme, | /
gives us reason to hope that these resources will increas¬
ingly be made available in the years ahead.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE NEW CEDARS
OF LEBANON
"Wail, O fir tree; for the cedar is fallen; because the goodly
ones are destroyed: wail O ye oaks of Bashan.- for the
strong forest is come down." This biblical lamentation
(Zechariah XI; 2) will soon be valid no longer for today the
famous cedar forests of the Lebanon are rising again.
Civilization after civilization ravaged these forests for
shipbuilding and countless other uses. Two world wars
ushered in the last stages of their decline with timbers
being used as fuel and for railway sleepers. Only four
small groves survived on the arid stony wastes of the
mountains. Today these mountain areas are being reno¬
vated under Lebanon's "Green Plan". Thousands of young
trees have already been planted on their slopes and mil¬
lions of others will follow under the reforestation project
which the Lebanese Government is carrying out with the
help of the FAO and the U.N. Special Fund. Surveys of
the soil, water, vegetation and livestock resources have
been completed. The dual aim of this campaign is to im¬
prove the lot of the mountain farmers and to restore one
of Lebanon's ancient and celebrated natural beauties.
^
XT
\m
l»MW>MI
All along the Lebanon
range terraces are
being carved from the
rocky hillsides to re¬
ceive millions of young
trees cedar and pine.
Using aerial stereo¬
scopic photographs,
a forestry expert plots
the contour lines for
the reforestation areas.
"fai&i
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
3*4
THE
GREAT
3to s.
REVOLUTION
by
Walter
Lippmann
u^^
*" rP*Mm
^V^^^^S
L **A\
% 2
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
To mark International Co-operation Year 1965, eminent
men from different parts of the world were invited this
year by Secretary- G enera/ U Thant to speak at the
United Nations Headquartors on some of the great
problems of our time. Here we present the text of the
address delivered by Walter Lippmann, the American
journalist and commentator, author of some 25 books
mostly on international affairs, and twice winner
of the coveted Pulitzer Prize for Journalism. For
another text in this same series see page 25.
I AM naturally beset with memories and
emotions, for I am old enough to have seen the
beginnings of the League of Nations. Indeed, as a young
man and as a journalist and as a subordinate official,
I followed as closely as I could the evolution of that first
attempt in this century to organize a universal society.
I saw it founder in the upheaval which led to the Second
World War. But I saw something else. In the darkest
days of that war, there was an almost universal assumption
that, when the fierce Insurrection had been defeated, the
interrupted task of organizing the universal society could
and must be resumed.
I hope I have learned something from this experience.
This is my only excuse for addressing you in this place.
Thus, for one thing, I have learned to think of the two
attempts to organize the universal society as a single and
continuous chapter in the history of mankind. It cannot
be an accident, it cannot be mere coincidence, that the two
attempts have occurred so closely together in this century.
There have been many wars in other centuries, great
wars for the hegemony of the world, poisonous civil wars,
bloody national wars, savage wars of religion. But in
these long and violent centuries, only an occasional
Utopian thinker dared even to conceive the construction
of an organized international society. Even when men
dared to dream, their dreams were limited. For they never
entertained the idea that an international society could and
must be universal, embracing all the continents on the
globe and all peoples of the human race.
The concept
of a universal society
ET, in our time, that Utopian idea has become
part of the political calculation of the practical
statesmen in all the governments. They took it seriously,
though perhaps not with full comprehension, after the First
World War. They took it seriously during the Second
World War, again not realizing what universalism would
mean when there were as many nations as are now repre¬
sented in the General Assembly. Now, statesmen must
take universalism seriously.
I ask myself why the idea of a universal society has
become a practical consideration in this century and only
in this century.
I think there is an answer to this question. I think, too,
that the answer will help us to understand why the first
attempt, that of the League of Nations, failed, and why
the second attempt, this attempt of the United Nations
today, is threatened, and what must be done to prevent
it from failing. I put it in this way because we can do
ourselves no good by proceeding on a false optimism.
A universal society is inevitable. But there is no certainty
that this, our second attempt at a universal society, will
be the last attempt. What I have to say does, I believe,
offer hope for the future. But it is hope only for those
who are induced by it to make a far greater effort for
peace than the governments concerned today have as yet
begun to make.
The old regime
of mankind
I ask your indulgence if I go back to the original
question, which is why in this century, and in
this century alone, there is a general assumption that it is
possible and necessary to organize a universal society.
The feeling that it is possible proceeds from the fact that
modern war has become a universal calamity, that therefore
a universal society is necessary, and that necessity is the
mother of invention.
The great historical fact is that this century has wit¬
nessed the consummation of a phase in human evolution
that began in the eighteenth century. In these two cen¬
turies there has been proceeding at an ever-increasing
tempo the dissolution of the ancestral order in which men
have lived and have acquired their habits, and the dis¬
appearance of the old régimes which were built on this
ancestral order.
The old régime of mankind consisted of a hierarchical
society, bound together by usage and custom and presided
over by royal and imperial authority. Obedience was a
duty which must not be questioned and a habit which must
not be broken. In this ancestral order, wars between the
royal and imperial authorities were normal, and the intervals
of peace lasted only as long as the balance of power among
them remained stable.
This ancestral order was struck its first and fatal blow
in the eighteenth century. In almost all of the Western
Hemisphere, the imperial and colonial system was over¬
thrown and destroyed between 1775 and 1820. Elsewhere
it survived, though it was being eroded from within. It
survived until the beginning of the twentieth century.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
THE GREAT REVOLUTION (Cont'd)
The First World War destroyed the imperial system in
central and eastern Europe and In the Middle Eastin the
Europe of the Hohenzollerns, the Hapsburgs, the Roma¬
novs, and of the Ottoman rulers. It left behind, and
apparently Intact, the imperial system in Asia and Africa.
After the First World War, the liquidation of the old
régime produced a vacuum of governments in the great
region between the Rhine River and Vladivostok, between
the North Sea and the Persian Gulf. There were no
legitimate successor governments in this great region and
in these lands when the League of Nations was founded.
Now, it ¡s a fact of human experience that men cannot
endure for long being governed by a power that they do
not accept as legitimate. There was, therefore, a fierce
turbulence produced by fanatical upstart tyrannies, strug¬
gling for survival and for domination.
The League of Nations presided over an immense revo¬
lutionary struggle. It could not control that struggle. It
could not compose that struggle. The failure of the League
of Nations has much to teach us today. The primary and
supreme lesson is that it failed because it could not make
peace and nobody else was able to make peace. In the
creation of a universal society, it is not enough to have
a covenant to which all swear allegiance. It is not enough
to set up machinery of consultation, concilation, mediation
and arbitration which is available to all. There must be
also a basic situation that is acceptable to all who might
have the power to disturb it.
The universal society must have a foundation, and that
foundation can be made up only of peace settlements
which are accepted by all the nations capable of over¬
throwing the settlement. A universal society can do much
to keep the peace if, and only if, first of all peace has
been made. For if peace has not been made by the belli¬
gerents, the foundations of a universal society are insecure.
The history of this cruel and bloody century is one of
recurring cycles of war and revolution. In this cycle the
old régimes and the old landmarks are swept away and
old habits uprooted, and new wars are engendered in the
disorder which ensues. The Second World War carried
much further what the First World War had begun. It
liquidated the feeble, interim successor régimes which
existed in the unpacified regions of Europe and the Middle
East. The Second World War demolished the imperial
system In India, in Indo-China, in Indonesia. In Africa, it
demolished the colonial system from the Mediterranean
down to Angola, South Rhodesia and the Union of South
Africa.
I
The lesson of the
League of Nations
22
F the lesson of the League of Nations teaches
us that peace settlements must be the found¬
ation of the universal society, then the world we look out
upon offers us no reason for complacency and for self-
congratulation.
After the two world wars and the revolutions which
followed them, there is still no peace settlement in Central
Europe, there Is still no peace settlement in Eastern Asia.
There are only the armistice lines of the Second World
War which divide Korea, which divide the Japanese islands,
which divide China, which divide Indo-China. There is
no peace settlement in Africa, no peace which under the
aegis of the United Nations could then be kept in order.
The future of the United Nations is bound up with the
agonies and the hopes of a great historical process. This
process is the dissolution of the ancestral order of power
and authority under which mankind has been accustomed
to live. An anarchy of emptiness has followed this dissolu¬
tion. Amidst violence and frustration and disappointment,
we are living through the attempts to create in this vacuum
a new and acceptable order.
During the past two centuries, almost every government
on earth has been altered radically by revolution: for the
old principle that a legitimate authority derives from tra¬
dition and is carried on by usage and custom, there has
been put in its place the modern and revolutionary principle
that legitimate government rests on the consent of the
governed and that this consent comes from their freedom
to choose and from their capacity to make a choice.
This fundamental revolution in human affairs is the
environment within which the United Nations works. We
can reach some measure of the depth and scope of this
revolution when we look about our world. The two great
wars have not yet been settled and concluded. Stable
governments have not yet been established in all the new
national states nor in all the older national states. We
must not be surprised, and indeed, perhaps we should not
even be downhearted, at realizing that the change from
government by tradition to government by consent is
perhaps the most unsettling change in the political history
of mankind.
The fact that amidst this accumulating disorder there
have been two attempts to organize a universal society is
evidence that man's hopes are wiser than his fears. For
there would be little reason to think that a world society
exists or is being created if we listen only to the official
statements and look only at the front pages of the news¬
papers. The official statements provide little more than
an overpowering dissonance and discord in which all the
issues are irreconcilable.
Practical politics
of preventing war
HE practical politics of preventing war in this
generation turn on the fact that as nuclear
science has produced weapons of annihilation, weapons
which in terms of human endurance are absolute weapons,
war between nuclear powers can no longer be an instru¬
ment of their national policy. This will still be the case even
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
© H.W. Silvester. Lioux-Vaucluse (France)
if, as is most probable, a considerable number of states
acquire nuclear weapons. For no nation can risk the use of
these weapons anywhere because, having those weapons,
it is subject itself to fearful retaliation. However, the acqui¬
sition of these weapons does not mean that a state has
added enormously to its power and influence. For in the
act of becoming a nuclear power, it has also made itself a
target, a target for the nuclear weapons of other states.
Therefore, the prospect of averting great war by mutual
deterrence is a reasonably good prospect. But that does
not mean that violence and disorder are disappearing from
the world. We know that they are not. For the technique
of war is changing. In the First World War we had the
massacre of conscript armies. This was succeeded in the
Second World War by attacks with fire bombs and nuclear
bombs on the civilian population in the cities. Nowadays,
wars are for the most part revolutionary wars, guerrilla
wars, little wars fought by small numbers of men with little
weapons and with terrorism and propaganda.
It Is difficult to imagine a treaty to put an end to revolu¬
tionary wars directed against unstable societies. Our
objective must be to contain these little wars, to Isolate
them, to immunize them, to neutralize them, so that they
do not inflame the rivalry of the great nuclear powers.
Is that all? No, I am sure it is not. For we must look
beneath the surface of the events of the day. When we
look beneath the surface, we shall see that there is under
way what we may call the Great Revolution, and it is upon
this Great Revolution that- we must rely to bring about
peace and stability on which eventually the universal
society can flourish.
What is the Great Revolution? It is a radical change in
the human condition. It ¡s a product of man's advancing
knowledge, his knowledge of how to control the material
conditions of his life on earth.
We are still only at the beginnings of this, the most
fundamental of all the revolutions and, in a sense, perhaps
the response to the revolutions which destroyed the ances¬
tral order and the old régime. The knowledge on which
this Great Revolution is based is a unique experience in
man's long history. Thus, already we know in theory and
in practice how to produce plenty in place of famine. That
marks a sharp break in the history of mankind. Fifty years
ago this knowledge did not exist. We know, too, how to
bring fresh water out of the ocean and to make the deserts
flourish. We know how to control conception and the wild
growth of population which threatens to nullify any pro¬
gress we make in improving the material conditions of life.
Therefore, we no longer have to be afraid that medicine
will save too many lives. We no longer have to rely on
epidemics and famine to keep the population from over¬
running the earth. We know that there need no longer be
any fear of a shortage of power anywhere on earth.
The conquest
of poverty
T the same time, we have at last begun to
Mearn how local and national and regional eco¬
nomies can be managed, how they can be brought under
human control and no longer left to the capricious play of
invisible forces. The art of managing the economy is
perhaps the youngest of all the arts. But as it Is perfected,
it is one of the most promising revolutions in the human
condition. For the sucessful management of the developed
economies should produce a rate of growth in the production
of wealth which can wipe out the material causes of social
conflict. At the same time, it should produce such ample
surplus that there will be quite sufficient capital available
to prime the pump in the less developed regions ot the
earth.
The modern age differs from all the ages that have gone
before in that the conquest of poverty has for the first time
become a rational object of policy for all states. This has
come about because of a conjuncture of discoveries and
inventions arising from new knowledge, from the sciences 09
and the arts which have to do with the conscious and deli-
berate regulation of human affairs the regulation of the
growth of population and the planning of its environment.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
24
THE GREAT REVOLUTION (Cont'd)
We are still a long way from the time when this knowledge
is perfected. We are even a long way from the time when
all governments will know how to use it. as it is being
perfected and will have the will to do so. We are still a
long way from the time when it will be the common sense
of all mankind. But undoubtedly the knowledge has begun
to exist, it has been applied, it is being tested and proved,
and we are dealing with something that exists, not with
something vaguely imagined.
The existence of this knowledge carries with It a certain
guarantee that it will not be lost and forgotten unless
civilization itself is destroyed. The knowledge is not the
secret of one man or of one country or of one ideology.
It is the common property of all men who wish to use it
and can learn to use it. Because this knowledge exists,
it will be applied. And being applied, it will by trial and
error be perfected more and more. Many of the superficial
revolutions in human history have come and gone and
been forgotten. But a revolution in man's knowledge of
the nature of things is, at least in modern times with
modern methods of keeping records, irreversible, and on
that thesis, I believe we can found our faith in the future.
Men have never before had reason to believe that the
conquest of poverty or the attainment of social peace ¡s a
possible and practical object of statesmanship. In this
half-century these objectives have in fact become just
that practical politics in the work-a-day world. The Great
Revolution is undercutting and undermining the dominant
ideological issues of this era. The Cold War will not be
settled by the victory of capitalism or of communism. On
the contrary, the Great Revolution will transcend the Cold
War because it will enable the pioneer societies to do
what neither capitalism nor communism has been able to
do for them, which is to move towards a standard of living
which is better than any that can be attained by a struggle
of classes.
The promise
of the Great Revolution
ND so, in conclusion, let me say that I have
Confidence in the future of the universal society
because it can now have a positive vocation, an affirmative
purpose, which can embrace and engage all the Interests
of men. This vocation and purpose is the conquest of
poverty and the making of social peace by carrying out the
promise of the Great Revolution.
From this vantage point we can look back over the half-
century during which there have been these two attempts
to organize an international society for the enforcement
of peace. Looking back, we can say that peace as such
has not been enough. Men will not make peace the
absence of struggle and conflict their paramount ¡deal.
For they have other Interests, some of which they cherish
more than life itself.
If the universal society is to live and flourish, It must
have some more interesting thing to do than to stand by,
and now and then to intervene in some quarrel when it
breaks out. Defence is a primary and indispensable func¬
tion of any organized society. But not defence alone. No
less indispensable is the promotion of the welfare of the
members of the society. This is true of all organized
governments, and it is true of the United Nations.
While the United Nations must do what it can to influence
the powers to make peace, while It must do what it can to
keep the peace, while it must rally its whole power and
influence to avert big war, it will not live by peace alone.
That is too grey an horizon. The horizon should be vivid
with splendour and hope. The masses of mankind from the
poorest to the richest are preoccupied above all else with
the problem of living with this Great Revolution which
brings the promise and the prospect of the fulfilment of
their hopes.
With these promises and these prospects of the Great
Revolution, the United Nations must Identify Itself.
A treaty without precedent in
modern diplomatic history, the
Antarctic Treaty, signed in
1959, made this vast ice¬
bound continent into an inter¬
national land of science where
nuclear explosions and any
kind of military activity are
prohibited (See The Unesco
Courier, Jan. 1962). Here, a
helicopter sets down on the
ice pack alongside a Japanese
observation ship taking part
in the large-scale Antarctic
research programma of the
International Geophysical Year.
Japanese Government photo
UM^:
SCIENCE
A NEW
SOCIAL
FORCE
by Mikhail Millionshchikov
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
*- V- ,
HE time has now come to enhance the role of
reason in the life of human society. In the world
of today there are various social systems; reason must
help us find ways for states with different social systems
to coexist on peaceful terms.
Nowadays, attempts to urge the "acceptability" of ther¬
monuclear war as an instrument of policy, and calls to
continue competing in means of mass destruction, are not
meeting with their previous success. It has become pos¬
sible to take practical steps which have made the danger
of world-wide thermonuclear war somewhat more remote:
among them, the Moscow Treaty banning nuclear weapon
tests in three environments, the United Nations resolution
calling upon states to refrain from placing weapons of
mass destruction in orbit in outer space, the curtailment
of the production of fissionable materials for military pur¬
poses and some reduction in the military expenditures of
the great powers.
If events could continue on this course it would afford
special satisfaction to peace-loving people; it would prove
that reason is capable of controlling the destructive poten¬
tial of the elemental forces which they themselves have
discovered and released. However, many factors still hang,
like the sword of Damocles, over mankind. One such
factor is the threat of thermonuclear catastrophe far from
eliminated still, and aggravated by the growth of the nuclear
arsenal and the heavy burden of the arms race. Another
is colonialism and racism; another, poverty, hunger and
disease; another, the illiteracy of hundreds of millions of
people; and yet another, the obstacles, still to be overcome,
in the way of a broad development of international trade and
of economic, scientific and technical co-operation.
In order to bring about a substantial improvement in
the situation, the appropriate course would be to follow
the example of the scientists, who achieve success when
they steadfastly seek bold new solutions to the problems
confronting science, and when they do so in an atmosphere
of co-operation instead of enmity. This atmosphere of
honest, mutually advantageous, workmanlike co-operation
and trust should also prevail in the relations among
peoples.
Lenin, the founder of the Soviet State, said that
the best way to celebrate an anniversary was to concen¬
trate on the problems still to be solved. Observance of
the International Co-operation Year will fittingly mark the
twentieth anniversary of the United Nations only if it really
moves mankind forward towards the solution of the prob¬
lems confronting it today.
When man becomes aware of the mortal danger that
hangs over him, all the other cares and wants that beset
him recede into the background. Security that Is the first-
priority problem whose solution is the vital prerequisite
for the solution of all the problems confronting mankind.
We have spoken of this matter so often In recent years
that the real meaning of these words Is gradually slipping
from our grasp; we are coming to regard them as a psycho¬
logical and political cliché, bereft of content. And yet
the real danger that threatens mankind, that threatens its
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
SCIENCE, A NEW SOCIAL FORCE (Cont'd)
For a greater unity of mankind
very existence, has never been as great as it is In our
time.
In the past two decades mankind has acquired the capa¬
city to destroy itself not once but many times over. Lest
this potential should turn into nightmare reality, all reason¬
ing people must find a settlement for the disputes which
divide them. We cannot, we dare not forget that in the
nuclear era the conditions in which human society exists
have undergone drastic change, and that a catastrophe
of .unprecedented dimensions may be unleashed unless
people who do not understand the changes that have taken
place in the world fundamentally alter their behaviour and
their way of thinking.
From the standpoint of the inherent logic of social deve¬
lopment and scientific and technical progress, a world
thermonuclear catastrophe is not inevitable. Yet the accu¬
mulation of weapons of mass destruction continues. The
danger of their being triggered off is growing.
I
26
|N the circumstances, scientists bear a special
responsibility. Representing the highest inte¬
rests of scientific and social progress, they must, I feel,
co-ordinate and pool their efforts with the efforts of all men
of goodwill in the noble cause of eliminating colonialism
once and for all and preventing a thermonuclear war. It is
now generally recognized that the surest way to solve this
problem is through general and complete disarmament
under strict international control. Only in a disarmed world
free from wars can science in its turn become completely a
constructive instead of a destructive force. The Pugwash
Conference of scientists Is doing what it can in the struggle
to prevent a nuclear catastrophe, not to mention the efforts
for peace that the World Council of Peace and many other
organizations are making.
Scientists and people in public life throughout the world
should work out an agreed programme for safeguarding
international security through disarmament. It seems to
me that one of the possible ways of achieving such a
programme might be to have an international year for the
preparation of disarmament. The implementation of such
a programme would undoubtedly assist in removing many
technical and political obstacles both to partial and to
general and complete disarmament. It might be agreed
to continue such efforts until suitable inter-governmental
agreements place disarmament on a solid foundation. At
the same time, this would place the entire question of
international co-operation in the scientific and political
spheres alike on a new plane, which is especially Important,
as in present conditions scientific co-operation Is insepa¬
rable from and determined by political co-operation, although
in turn exerting an increasing influence upon it.
HE unity of mankind in our time is evident from
the unity and close interdependence of the vital
problems facing people wherever they may live. Nowadays
scientific and political problems alike are indissolubly linked
with economic problems. The development of International
co-operation in the economic field by every possible means
lays a solid material foundation for the development of
political, scientific and technical co-operation. Here Inter¬
national trade should be the main avenue of approach. In
our day and age, trade not only drives out war and streng¬
thens peace, which In Itself promotes scientific and tech¬
nical progress, but directly accelerates such progress by
disseminating licences, patents, new types of products and
new technological processes. New independent states are
appearing on the international scene, and their peoples
are uprooting colonialism, destroying the economic and
political positions of foreign monopolies, altering the old
colonial structure of their economy and creating a new
structure. The time is not far distant when these countries
will no longer play the role of mere suppliers of agricul¬
tural and industrial raw materials for the world's markets,
a role bequeathed to them by the colonial era.
The development of international trade free from discri¬
mination and artificially erected barriers would provide a
sound basis for the establishment of friendly relations
among countries and would help to preserve and streng¬
then peace, confidence and mutual understanding among
peoples. For that reason, it is a matter of profound
concern to men of science that the International Co-opera¬
tion Year should consolidate the positive results achieved
by the United Nations Conference on Trade and Develop¬
ment and give a powerful new impetus to the development
of international trade.
At the same time, however, no single one of the various
possible areas of development of International co-opera¬
tion can claim a monopoly or can serve as a panacea.
Man's economic, political and scientific problems consti¬
tute a single interdependent system. As a consequence,
their solution also must be universal in scope, and must
be based on effectively co-ordinated international co¬
operation in all these spheres. From this angle, the first
important task Is to determine correctly, the basic and
primary link in the chain of problems confronting us.
lCIENCE has an increasing number of positive
political achievements to its credit; it is becom¬
ing an increasingly active social force of our time.
In the light of the experience gained, I would emphasize
that the development of international scientific co-operation
makes an appreciable contribution to the cause of peace.
A direct result of the fulfilment of the Antarctic programme
of the International Geophysical Year was the conclusion
in 1959 of the Antarctic Treaty, which proclaimed a sixth
of the earth as the first demilitarized zone and thereby
laid down the principle of reducing militarism's sphere
of action ¡n the world.
An International Year of Preparation for Disarmament
would also be a significant contribution to the cause of
international co-operation and would be fruitful both poli¬
tically and scientifically. There is no doubt that such a
heartening example would provide a strong stimulus for
further steps in that direction; and this is of vital impor¬
tance, for the International Co-operation Year is to usher
in a period of broad and many-sided efforts to bring
mankind closer to a world without weapons and without
wars, a world in which scientific and technical progress
will seek only the good of mankind and will help to create
conditions fit for human beings to live In.
By becoming a direct productive force, science Is creat¬
ing material and spiritual values on an unheard-of, gigantic
scale. Science Itself must also see to it that those values
are not destroyed. In our era science is called upon to
revolutionize not only the economic, social and political
life of society, but also its very way of thinking. By
penetrating and dominating all spheres of social activity,
scientific reason, as the most highly organized and most
disciplined mode of thought, can and must help to find
a rational solution for the problems of mankind.
MIKHAIL MILUONSHCHIKOV is a vice-president of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Science and acting president of the Kurchatov Institute
of Atomic Energy. He has taken an active part in the International
Pugwash Conferences on Science and World Affairs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
I
METAMORPHOSIS
Bachofen, Geneva
To be called a "developing" country is a badge of honour
because it means that a nation has undertaken to lift itself...
out of the stage of economic underdevelopment and to do
in a few decades what in earlier history has usually taken
centuries.
Wilbur Schramm
in "Mass Media & National Development" *
THE years since World War II
might well be called the age of
international action a time during which
nations have pooled their efforts as never
before to solve problems too great for
single countries to overcome alone. Much
of this joint action has been taken through
a partnership of governments and their
peoples working together through the Uni¬
ted Nations and its specialized agencies
under programmes of technical co-opera¬
tion.
Technical co-operation for development
has been an important element of Unesco's
programme since 1946 when Unesco itself
was created. The launching in 1950 of the
U.N. Expanded Programme of Technical As¬
sistance brought about a tremendous in¬
crease in the breadth and scope of these
activities.
In the course of the past fifteen years
101 developing countries have joined with
Unesco In co-operative technical efforts
and have benefited from the skills and
* Published by Unesco-Stanford University Press,
1964. (t6.00 ; 301- 21 F).
experience of 3,000 Unesco technical
missions carried out under the aegis of the
U.N. Expanded Programme. In addition to
this, 3,824 senior and junior technicians,
scientists, specialists and officials were
granted fellowships abroad to enable
them to keep abreast of the latest technical
advances in other parts of the world.
It would be a great mistake to assume
that experts come only from the more
developed countries ; half of the countries
receiving aid are also supplying experts
to assist in the development of other lands.
India, the United Arab Republic and Brazil
to cite only three countries have sent many
experts to serve abroad.
By the end of 1964 Unesco had provided a
total of sixty million dollars worth of co¬
operative technical aid in the form of expert
missions, fellowships for study abroad and
technical equipment.
Unesco has committed itself so whole¬
heartedly to development that, in the words
of its Director-General, René Maheu,
addressed to the U.N. Economic and Social
Council in Geneva on July 9, 1965 : "this
now accounts for some two-thirds of all
budgetary and extra-budgetary resources of
the Organization."
"More important still, it has involved
Unesco to an increasingly greater extent
in operational activities and has thereby
brought about what amounts to a veritable
metamorphosis in the working methods and
immediate priorities if not in the spirit and
ultimate objectives of Unesco. This meta¬
morphosis has been so profound that one
is perfectly justified to speak of the birth
of a new Unesco, markedly different from
the Organization of the early years when
Unesco was basically an.agency for intellec¬
tual co-operation."
Unesco's programme of technical co¬
operation for development has laid special
emphasis since 1960 on three major fields:
development of education; development of
the sciences; development of the mass
media.
To make the fullest use of their human
and material resources, the developing
countries need not just money and mach¬
ines to forge the tools for economic and
social betterment but people who are prop¬
erly trained to use these tools, whether
they be simple lathes or complicated
equipment to operate large-scale industrial
plants.
When the U.N. Expanded Programme was
launched in 1950 Unesco had substantial
but nevertheless limited information on the
educational needs of the developing coun¬
tries and how it could best co-operate in
meeting these needs.
As a first step it sent out teams to survey
the educational situation and potential, as
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
METAMORPHOSIS IN UNESCO (Cont'd)
$60,000,000 for technical
missions, fellows & equipment
28
in Afghanistan, Burma, Libya, Thailand and
the Philippines. These surveys were not
only of great value to the countries but
enabled Unesco itself to work out a co¬
ordinated programme of technical aid and
co-operation, and set up urgent priorities.
Thus during the first five years of
Unesco's technical aid programmes rural
fundamental education was given priority
attention in development programmes initi¬
ated by a host of countries notably Cam¬
bodia, Ethiopia, Indonesia, Jordan, Korea,
Thailand, Sudan, and national fundamental
education centres were created by govern¬
ments with Unesco's help in order to train
various types of fundamental education
workers. In other countries (e.g. Afgha¬
nistan, Bolivia, Morocco, Tunisia) Unesco
experts helped in the setting up of national
fundamental education services, often inclu¬
ding facilities for producing inexpensive
educational materials.
Specialists co-operated with Unesco
member nations in the preparation of text¬
books for adults, literacy teaching, agricul¬
tural education, production or vernacular
language literature, women's education and
and rural handicrafts instruction. Other
Unesco experts collaborated in the launch¬
ing of fundamental education programmes
in Indonesia, Iraq, Libya, Paraguay and Peru
in co-operation with other U.N. agencies.
During this period Unesco gave special
emphasis to the development of regional
programmes for training fundamental edu¬
cation workers, especially in Latin Ame¬
rica, where the Regional Fundamental Edu¬
cation Centre for Community Development
(CREFAL) was opened at Patzcuaro, Mexi¬
co, in 1950 and also through the Arab
States Training Centre for Education for
Community Development (ASFEC) which
was established at Sirs-el-Layyan, U.A.R. in
1952. These two centres have since pro¬
vided many hundreds of trained workers for
the expanding national programmes.
ANOTHER major priority area which
emerged during the 1950s was
the field of primary education, in which
Unesco sent numerous advisers to many of
its member nations on a wide-range of
missions which included: advice in rural
education, teacher training, research in
teaching methods, use of audio-visual aids,
educational surveys, textbook production,
child psychology, establishment of model
schools and educational administration.
Particular attention was focused on Latin
America where a major project on the ex¬
tension and improvement of primary edu¬
cation was established at the end of 1956.
This major effort by the countries of Latin
America has brought together national
resources, supplemented by assistance
under Unesco's regular programme as well
as under the U.N. Expanded Programme.
Its purpose was to help the co-operating
states to come nearer to the goal of provi¬
ding education for all children of primary
school-going age.
Considerable growth in the third five-year
period of the Expanded Programme (the
early 1960s) coincided with the attainment
of independence by many countries, espe¬
cially in Africa.
Unesco co-operated closely with these
member nations in the programming of
educational development and the training
of their nationals. Regional training centres
were established in Santiago (1962), at New
Delhi (1962) and at Dakar (1964).
Regional conferences of ministers of
education and other officials responsible
for economic development plans were also
held to study the problems of education in
relation to economic and social develop¬
ment. The first such meeting, financed out
of technical aid funds, took place at the
end of 1950. It was held in Karachi and
it produced what came to be known as the
"Karachi Plan" which has been modified
since by subsequent meetings of ministers
from the Asian countries concerned.
WHILE major efforts in the fields of
fundamental education, primary
education and educational planning have
been prominent in the technical assistance
activities carried out by Unesco under the
Expanded Programme, other important fields
have also been covered. These include
secondary education, curriculum develop¬
ment, higher education, promotion of
education for girls and women, school build¬
ing construction and educational research
in teaching methods and materials, etc.
Regional centres have been established in
Addis Ababa for the production of primary
and secondary school textbooks and in
Yaounde for textbook production. In addi¬
tion, regional school building research cen¬
tres have been established in Khartoum,
Mexico City and Bandung (the last named
centre is being re-established in another
location).
In teacher training, a pattern of co-op¬
eration has developed whereby Unesco, in
conjunction with Unicef, has set up in-
service training courses under the Expand¬
ed Programme so as to improve the quality
of primary school teaching, and has given
technical advice on numerous projects in
the field of primary school inspection and
administration.
The end of the first five-year period of
co-operation was marked by a new trend
in which isolated activities gave way to
larger projects planned in the context of
broad long-range educational development
programmes.
In the fields of libraries, museums, read¬
ing materials and documentation, regional
centres have been established and regional
and country missions have been carried
out with assistance from the U. N. Expanded
Programme.
During Unesco's early years, its Science
Co-operation Offices based in Latin Ame¬
rica, the Middle-East, South Asia and
South-East Asia, had established firm
working relationships with the scientists of
their own region. It was felt, however,
that they were lacking information on
The world water shortage is so serious
that Unesco has this year launched a
Hydrological Decade a vast co-operative
programme of research into water prob¬
lems. Since 1962 Tunisia has studied the
use of saline water to irrigate its parched
lands. Above, water flowing in this canal
is used by a Tunisian experimental farm.
Right, construction of concrete bins for
growing and irrigating plants. Water
flowing from bins into the large pits
(foreground) will be measured to deter¬
mine loss from evaporation in the soil and
transpiration by the plants. Tunisia . is
carrying out this research in co-operation
with the U.N. Special Fund and Unesco.
Photos Unesco-Dominique Roger
developments in science in other parts of
the world. Thus, as soon as the Technical
Assistance Programme was started, a plan
was drawn up to establish, in several
member nations, centres of scientific and
technical documentation.
THE aim of these centres was to
collect the most important scien¬
tific periodicals and documentation publish¬
ed in the world, and to make them available
in a convenient and rapid way to the
scientists of the country or the region
concerned. The duration of the project
under the Expanded Programme was limited
to five years. The first centre was estab¬
lished in Mexico, and was followed by
others in India, Yugoslavia, Brazil, U.A.R.,
Pakistan, Uruguay, Philippines, Indonesia,
Thailand, Cuba and Korea. Unesco still
co-operates in running centres in Thailand
and Korea.
Scientific teaching and research have
also been developed and reinforced under
the programme, mainly in existing and newly
created universities. Unesco experts have
advised on curricula and on laboratory and
field experiments for students, on seminars
for university staffs and on the introduction
of new methods and new equipment. Dur-
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
ing the last fifteen years, universities of
32 different countries were modernized and
developed under this scheme.
Another area of activity under the
Expanded Programme relates to the
creation of scientific instruments centres,
where specialized laboratory equipment is
made and repaired. The natural outgrowth
of such a centre has led to testing and
standardization of apparatus and construc¬
tion of equipment for schools. Both types
of projects are now developed under the
Special Fund programme.
Unesco has also been associated with
the reform of higher technical education in
two ways: by granting fellowships to key
administrators and professors from techni¬
cal universities or faculties of engineering
who were later to be responsible for orga¬
nizing a new programme (in Mexico and
Yugoslavia for example); and by helping
new institutions such as the large regional
Indian Institutes of Technology and the
Middle East Technical University.
Technical aid missions have also been
concerned with the efforts of governments to
lay down á national scientific policy. Alge¬
ria, Iraq, Kenya, Lebanon, Madagascar and
Morocco have received experts in this field
as part of the Expanded Programme of
Technical Assistance.
Missions have also been carried out in
the social sciences (political science, public
administration, economics, and the social
effects of industrialization and technical
change). Regional social science centres
have been established in Brazil and India.
ALTHOUGH Unesco has been
providing assistance in the deve¬
lopment and use of mass communication
facilities since the beginning of the
Expanded Programme of Technical Assis¬
tance, such aid was entirely concentrated
for the first ten years or so on the educa¬
tional use of the media. From the start, a
small but steadily increasing portion of
Unesco's programme was devoted to such
projects as the establishment of school
broadcasting services, of educational film
services and the setting up of national
audio-visual centres. One example was the
setting up of the Latin American Educational
Film Institute in Mexico.
A major change occurred after the U.N.
Economic and Social Council had asked
Unesco in 1959 to undertake a general
survey of information resources and needs
in the developing countries. Accordingly
in 1960, 1961 and 1962, Unesco organized
three large-scale regional meetings on the
needs of information media in Asia, Latin
America and Africa. In 1961, the Economic
and Social Council invited the Technical
Assistance Board, the Special Fund and
other appropriate agencies to assist the
less-developed countries in expanding and
strengthening their national information
media, and a new programme field was thus
established for action under the Expanded
Programme of Technical Assistance in which
Unesco was invited to play a major role.
While continuing its, by now, traditional
assistance in establishing audio-visual ser¬
vices for education, Unesco has therefore
been able to meet new requests in the field
of mass communication proper. It has, for
instance, provided expert services in the
establishing of national news agencies, in
developing the press and in launching tele¬
vision. The volume of these activities is
still not large in absolute figures, but it
was this sector which showed the largest
proportional increase in Unesco's 1965-66
programme, requests received from its mem¬
ber countries showing a 36% increase
above the previous period.
Within the overall framework of mass
communication development, Unesco has
given priority to the training of professional
personnel, and to a large extent this has
been most fruitfully accomplished through 9Q
the organization of regional training courses
and through assistance in the establishment
of training institutes.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
TURNING POINT bV u Thant (cont'd from p. 9)
were unwittingly changing the face of the earth. The very
phrase that was used, "the Industrial Revolution" is a
symbol of the inadequate estimate of what in fact was
happening. Industry played only one part in the remaking
of a whole society by the uses of reason, calculation,
analysis, cost-consciousness, improvement, experiment
and feed-back.
Today, with hindsight we can better interpret what has
been happening. In fact, the whole idea of development
as a dynamic process, the factors which make for trans¬
formation, the policies which can accelerate it lie at the
very root of the concept of a "Decade of Development".
It is therefore hardly surprising that the United Nations
and the specialized agencies have undertaken special
studies and experiments dealing with the process of
development itself.
A second advantage in the developing world is the
sheer scale of information now available in every field
connected with development. There is not an area of
knowledge or action in which remarkable experiments
have not been carried out experiments which can be
freely studied and may be of crucial help. In the critical
fields of agriculture, for instance, well-known and straight¬
forward changes in the use of fertilizer, better seed, new
tools and plant protection can produce as much as qua¬
druple yields from the land. The developing world might
well despair if it had used up all the available technology
and was still undernourished. The vastness of potential
innovation is the best guarantee of progress and the
task of transferring knowledge of it is correspondingly
urgent.
At a level which escapes the headlines and therefore
takes place almost in anonymity, a phenomenal increase
has occurred over the last fifteen years in the process
of humanity educating itself. If the first change in any
revolution is to change the way in which people think,
the whole world today is mined with explosive change
change in the whole dimension and dissemination of human
knowledge, in the power that goes with it, in the
expectations to which it gives rise.
URING the Development Decade, the tempo of
all this exchange of information and experience
has been increasing. So have the attempts of the United
Nations family to look ahead and study its material dynamic¬
ally. For instance, the United Nations itself has published
its "Long-term Economic Projections for the World Eco¬
nomy." The Food and Agriculture Organization has put
out projections for agricultural commodities up to 1970, and
is engaged on an ambitious Indicative World Plan for Agri¬
culture. Meanwhile Its Third World Food Survey has made
calculations of food needs up to the year 2000 which
suggest that while food supplies in general must triple, the
increase needed for the poor countries is over 200 per
cent higher still.
A wide variety of papers studying the likely development
of international trade to the end of the sixties were pre¬
pared for the United Nations Conference on Trade and
Development held in 1964. Thus, the developing govern¬
ments are being offered more than simple current data.
Along with this increase in the fund of knowledge
available has gone an increase in internationally aided
research of all kinds and in the search for new sources of
natural wealth. In promoting scientific research in a great
variety of fields Unesco has played a central role. In
1961 the United Nations convened a Conference on New
Sources of Energy which provided the first world-wide
exchange of existing knowledge and experience in solar
energy, wind power, geothermal and tidal energy and consi¬
dered means of bringing techniques relating to these types
of energy into wider use. The United Nations has carried
out extensive studies in the development of water resour¬
ces. Panels on the use of nuclear energy in desalinization
are held by the International Atomic Energy Agency twice
a year. The United Nations is holding an interregional
seminar on the economic aspects of water desalinization
later this year. It has also been actively engaged with
other agencies in the investigation of ground-water
resources for domestic, agricultural and industrial uses In
regions where lack of water has been preventing economic
development.
ET the present position of the developing
nations, confronted with the vast surge of
modern technology, is not all gain. Since much of the
technology has been designed for other societies at other
times, it does not always fit in with the present needs of
emergent States. Worse, it may even involve them in
contradictions which more developed societies have avoid¬
ed. The most notorious and difficult of the contradictions
is the tendency of modern measures of health to bring
about a very sharp increase in population before any other
factor in the community food production, educational
development, savings, industrial development has become
really dynamic.
This is not the only contradiction. A very large part of
today's productive technology is geared to the needs of
societies in which labour tends to be scarce and capital
abundant. A modern refinery can cost over $60 million,
yet employ only 300 people. This is an extreme case but
the trend is general. Automatic looms, combine harves¬
ters, road laying machinery, earth-movers, power shovels
the inventions of sophisticated technology dispense with
the only resource which all the developing countries have
in abundant, indeed over-abundant, supply their man¬
power offering instead machines which swallow up their
meagre savings. And just those areas of the economy
which seem to promise the most certain road to growth,
wealth and Independence the heavy industrial sector
which, via the magnetic appeal of the United States and
the U.S.S.R. fascinates the new economies are precisely
the sectors in which capital investments are highest and
the returns longest to mature.
A similar disproportion bedevils other fields. For
example, virtually the entire expenditure of the world in
commercial research takes place in the developed nations.
It is designed to cut costs and increase competitiveness
in the developed sector. Some substitutes made possible
by the chemical revolution for instance plastics and
rayon are cheaper than natural substances. Where the
difference in price only slightly favours primary producers,
manufacturers in developed countries often prefer substi¬
tutes which are under their control and beyond the vicissi¬
tudes of politics and weather. A new cheaper chemical
Insecticide could ruin in a year one of the chief standbys
of peasant farming ¡n East Africa pyrethrum. Binder
twine made as a by-product of petro-chemicals could
threaten to knock out the other sisal. There are no flows
of research money on anything like the same scale to
increase the competitiveness of primary products or to
diversify their use. Technology, used overwhelmingly as
a tool of developed societies, can turn into a potent instru¬
ment of disruption elsewhere.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Developing nations represent only 4 ¥b
of the world's export of manufactured goods
(and of this figure one quarter comes from Hong Kong alone!)
These risks lay at the basis of the United Nations deci¬
sion to summon a Conference to be prepared and run
with the co-operation of a number of the agencies, on the
Application of Science and Technology for the Benefit of
the Less Developed Areas. It met in Geneva in 1963 and
decided both to follow-up this first initiative and to take
positive steps to get more brains and money into research
oriented towards developing needs. An Advisory Com¬
mittee was established which began to meet in 1964 with
the aim of picking out, from the vast potential supply of
problems and possibilities, the most urgent points for
"concerted attack".
It was naturally not difficult to define major areas of
primary interest more and better food, improved health,
new techniques and education, urban planning, the better
use of natural resources and methods of industrialization.
The trouble is that such a list tends to be virtually cotermin¬
ous with human existence and it is now the Advisory
Committee's more difficult task on which it has, in fact,
embarked to pick out in each category points of "attack"
where the chances of a breakthrough are great and the
advantages of making one very wide-spread.
One such instance is clearly large-scale desalinization
of water for agriculture, for which" the best hope lies in
utilizing nuclear energy, another is the provision, from a
multitude of sources, of more protein in ordinary diets,
both by producing synthetic protein and by conserving
available proteins by a variety of methods ranging from
cold-storage chains to food irradiation.
I N the relations between rich nations and poor
I nations, the market they share is the world¬
wide market of international trade, and the higher earnings
the poor nations must seek is a higher proportion of the
gains made in international commerce. The share of deve¬
loping countries in world exports declined steadily from
nearly one third in 1950 to only slightly more than one-fifth
in 1962. One of the major targets of international action
must be at least to restore the proportions they previously
enjoyed.
The underlying pattern of the world market has not
changed very much over the last century. It was brought
into being by the developed nations' need to look over¬
seas for food, minerals and tropical materials, to invest
the necessary capital to produce them in mines and plan¬
tations, in transport and harbours, to recoup the investment
out of the sale of the exported materials and pay for
whatever local balance remained with their own export
of manufactures.
This pattern of trade left little capital in the local eco¬
nomy, led to virtually no modernization outside the sector
concerned with foreign trade and therefore did not set
in motion local forces of diversification and growth. Inter¬
national trade, outside the developed core made up largely
of North . Atlantic States, continued to rest on the
exchanges between strong, modernized and developed
communities on the one hand and, on the other, weak
economies dependent, very often, on a single product.
Intensification of trade could only occur between develop¬
ed economies and virtually the whole organization of the
trade remained in Western hands.
To this day, about 66 per cent of world trade is en¬
grossed by the developed market economies. They control
94 per cent of the world's shipping and virtually all its
insurance. To a very considerable degree, they still control
the processing of the materials underdeveloped nations
account for only 4 per cent of the world's exports of
manufactures and even this percentage is very mislead¬
ing. Nearly a quarter of these exports are provided by
the one fabulous source of Hong Kong.
Since most of the developing nations were still colo¬
nies at the end of the Second World War, and the
independence of the majority was not achieved until the
early sixties, it was only in the last few years that the
attention of the international community has been drawn
to the unbalanced patterns of world trade. The develop¬
ing countries had increasingly begun to realize a certain
common interest in formulating their common grievances
against existing arrangements and seeking redress for
them. The United Nations was a natural forum for their
activity for it was at meetings of the United Nations and
its related organs and subsidiary bodies that many of
the ideas which were beginning to engage the serious
attention of the developing countries in the economic
sphere, were initially broached. And the culmination of
this pressure by the developing countries was the conven¬
ing in Geneva in the spring of 1964, of the United Nations
Conference on Trade and Development, itself the most
important event so far of the United Nations Decade
of Development.
The developing nations' three main headings of dissatis¬
faction are the uncertainty and instability of export
incomes; the difficulty of access to developed markets
for some raw materials and for any more diversified and
processed exports; and the structural bias of the whole
market towards the interests of the rich. Between 1950
and 1962, the unit value of exports from developing coun¬
tries to developed countries fell by 5 per cent in compa¬
rison with 1955 the figure was 12 per cent. Incidentally,
this decline was enough, in the case of Latin America,
to wipe out the effect of all the imports of public and
private capital during the fifties.
The United Nations Conference on Trade and Deve¬
lopment led to the establishment of institutional machinery
within the United Nations to deal with problems of trade
and development on a continuing basis. This» in itself
is a landmark in the history of international organization.
N O single idea has more profoundly shaped the
modern economy than the belief that all citizens
have the right to share in its resources and opportunities.
Whether the policy is predominantly realized by the transfer
of wealth through taxation from rich to poor as in the
market economies, or by budgetary provisions as in centrally
planned States, the consequences tend in the same direc¬
tion towards a community in which the' wealth created in
it is so divided that the vast majority of the people have
the education, the skills, the environment and the kind of
income needed to lead a satisfying life.
Since the war, there has been some evidence to suggest
that this concept of shared resources is beginning to
enter the philosophy of States in relation not simply to
their own citizens but to other States as well. During
the fifties, the flow of financial resources from developed
to developing countries steadily increased.
To meet the needs of developing countries several new
multilateral lending agencies have been established, both
within and outside the United Nations framework, in the
late 1950s and early 1960s. These include the International
Finance Corporation and the International Development
Association, the African Development Bank, the Inter-Ame¬
rican Development Bank and the Central American Bank
of Economic Integration and the Development Fund of the
European Economic Community. Preparations are also
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
TURNING POINT
IN DEVELOPMENT
(Cont'd)
32
under way for the setting up of an Asian Development
Bank. With the increase in multilateral lending facilities,
the establishment of the United Nations Special Fund and
the expansion of activities under United Nations technical
assistance, the proportion of resources which are being
provided to developing countries through multilateral
channels has increased from around 6 per cent of the
total in the late 1950s to over 10 per cent in 1963.
The need for external assistance is not confined to
long-term development capital. Developing as well as
developed countries need "working capital" to underpin
international trade. Between 1960 and early 1965 the
International Monetary Fund made available $5,600 million
to forty-three members, thirty-two of them developing
States. It has also started to operate a modest scheme
to compensate primary producing countries for fluctuations
in export receipts.
T the mid-point of the Decade one cannot say
that the future of this essential financing is
secure. In spite of the increase in the flow of long-term
capital since the mid-1950s, the target set by the General
Assembly according to which resource transfers to develop¬
ing countries are to rise to 1 per cent of the national incomes
of developed countries has not yet been attained. In fact,
the levelling off in the flow of funds to developing coun¬
tries since 1961 has set back progress towards the target.
It is as though such programmes had lost the élan
of a new venture before they had acquired the respec¬
tability of old usage. The words are spoken, the gestures
are made, but the sense of clear commitment seems
elusive. The richer nations of the West, a little bemused
by the quick easy success of the Marshall Plan among
a group of essentially already developed nations, have
tended to approach the whole problem of development with
an unrealistic time scale. Put in the aid, mobilize the
resources and, within a decade, the young economies
should be well on their way to self-sustaining growth. So,
in the crudest terms, ran the hope. But even the most
favoured of the developed nations the United States
took eighty years to reach industrial maturity. Even the
most ingenious Japan took at least forty for its first
revolution and, since the war, fifteen for its second.
The nations which seek to develop their economies
today face all the old dilemmas of rapid transition how
to modernize static farming, how to squeeze savings from
a poor pre-industrial population, how to choose those
industries which actually produce a surplus, how to finance
the new skills needed to produce more capital before
the capital exists to divert to the schools. But they face
even tougher problems as well the population explosion,
urbanization beyond control, unfavourable trade patterns
and inappropriate technology.
The United Nations has already produced a very large
volume of information on the explosive nature of the
world's expansion in population. The censuses it inspired
have shown, throughout the developing world, even a higher
growth rate than had been expected. The World Popu¬
lation Conference, to be held in 1965 (1), will no doubt
underline with new urgency the degree to which, in the
developing continents, the decline in mortality and growth
in population, by preceding the modernization of the eco-
(1) The conference took place from August 30 to September 10 in
Belgrade Editor.
The 'beer, boots and bricks' phase
of early industrial development
nomy, now impedes that process. Yet modernization alone
can provide food and income for the growing millions.
The Conference will make inescapably, dramatically
clear that the situation carries with it a potentially ine¬
vitable risk of disease, starvation and social collapse.
Governments can therefore be urged, with even greater
energy, to give proper priority to the slowing down of
population growth rates and the adoption of acceptable
methods of control.
So far, the United Nations has chiefly concentrated on
drawing attention to population factors in the context of
economic and social development by means of scientific
evaluation and analysis of data.
It is now going to expand the scope of its work so
that it includes questions connected with policies which
are designed to influence the size, structure and change
of the population. In Asia and the Far East, as a result
of a decision of the Economic Commission for Asia and
the Far East in 1964, United Nations activities have been
extended to include family planning and this year a United
Nations team was sent to India to review the family plan¬
ning programe and to make recommendations for acce¬
lerating it within the five-year economic plan.
The population problem of the developing countries,
however, is not merely one of too rapid increase in the
total numbers it is vastly accentuated by massive shifts
of population from the countryside to the burgeoning cities.
The great cities of the affluent world themselves suffer
from overcrowding, social disorder, pollution and traffic
congestion. But in the developing world, the worst aspect
of the urban dilemma is again one that the developed
world to some extent escaped the massive movement
of rural migrants into the cities ahead of any real chance
of their earning a living. The most conspicuous problem
is the acute shortage of housing resulting in overcrowd¬
ing, the growth of "shanty towns" and a chronic shortage
of community services and facilities.
HE United Nations has set targets for housing
in the developing countries based on a standard
of ten new dwellings for every 1,000 inhabitants. So far
only two new dwellings for every 1,000 inhabitants have
been built in many developing countries even though these
countries have allocated 15 to 25 per cent of their total
investment in capital formation to residential construction.
The United Nations has made studies of urbanization
in various regions Africa, the Middle East. It has call¬
ed conferences on such issues as new towns and on urban
development, planning and policy. It has assisted in the
preparation of national physical plans, including master
plans for cities. It has helped in resettling shanty town
dwellers. Now the Social Commission has adopted a
proposal suggesting that a full-scale inter-governmental
programme for joint investigation of the problem should
be launched, and areas set aside for studies and experi¬
ments in regional solutions which seem essential if unwieldy
movements of internal migration are not to throw intole¬
rable strains on young and still unstable economies. There
¡s the germ here of the kind of world process of confront¬
ation and education that has occurred in the field of trade;
but what is also needed is action and investment on a
scale hitherto quite unknown.
Recognition of these deeper difficulties should help to
educate and reassure those in the developed world who
despair too soon, who fear that because the developing
nations have not made a decisive break-through to growth
and economic independence in ten years, they never will.
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
PART 3
HE slow but real progress of development has
attracted less public attention than its occasional
spectacular mishaps. Indeed, the public has been largely
ignorant of what has been learned in the last fifteen years
in the field of development and of how much, in region after
region, is beginning to go modestly well.
The first point to make is that the developing world, for
all its frustrations, is in motion. National incomes are
rising and most agricultural economics have made some
break from traditional farming. The beginnings of industrial
growth are to be found on every side. This is not yet the
recipe for "take-off" but it is a considerable advance on the
stagnation of the twenties and the thirties.
This new dynamism has sprung in part from the fact
that quite a number of the developing countries have been
investing their resources in the right things. And one
reason for this is the increasing relevance of the advice
they receive from experts supplied by governments, uni¬
versities, foundations, and, to a greater and greater degree,
the United Nations and the specialized agencies, partly
through their own budgets, but more substantially through
the voluntary contributions of governments to such under¬
takings as the Special Fund and the Expanded Programme
of Technical Assistance.
NLY ten years ago, the general tendency was
to agree that savings made up the critically
scarce factor in static economies. Pour in the needed
stimulus, add to the foreign exchange reserves, get the
World Bank to put in some infra-structure and the economy
would begin to stir. In some economies the strategy was
not far wrong. After ten years they needed no more
exceptional assistance. But in other communities, the effect
of capital aid without much wider modifications of policy
was rather like splashing water on to leached soli. It
simply washed off.
Much of the progress that has been made since and
which »the Decade of Development seeks to dramatize
is concerned with producing a better soil in which the
assistance can germinate. A few examples of this better
developmental husbandry will illustrate the point. There
can hardly be a realistic plan for expanding a country's
infra-structure transport, power, and so forth unless an
inventory of its resources and their whereabouts has been
established. In this field of pre-investment surveys, the
Special Fund has taken the lead.
But the greatest potential resource of any country are
its human resources. Trained men for administration, for
education, for public health and medicine these, too,
belong to the stage of pre-investment since no investment
can succeed without them. Here, aided by increasing
resources from the Special Fund and the Expanded Pro¬
gramme, the United Nations family is setting up institu¬
tions for administration, managerial and industrial training
and is supporting universities and technical colleges.
However, far more is needed than the higher cadres.
Underdeveloped countries are by definition short of all the
intermediate skills as well. A welcome decision has just
been taken by the International Labour Organization govern¬
ing body as a contribution to the Development Decade,
to open this year the Turin International Centre for Advanc¬
ed Technical and Vocational Training. To relate interme¬
diate skills to the probable needs of each particular eco¬
nomy, . new techniques have been evolved, particularly
the techniques .of manpower surveys and educational
planning to which the International Labour Organization
and Unesco respectively have made a signal contribution.
And clearly within the context of any educational plan,
no single item is more urgent than teaching the teachers.
In this field Unesco with the help of the Special Fund
has taken the initiative in planning and establishing
teacher-training colleges and the International Bank,
recognizing the productivity of education, has begun to
provide credits for educational projects which involve the
direct development of education itself both in terms of the
number of students in schools and the content of the
educational programme. Unesco's recently' started pilot
programme for universal literacy represents an imaginative
new approach both to increasing productivity and to the
wider enjoyment of elementary human rights and dignity.
No less significant an insight in postwar developmen¬
tal strategy is the new priority accorded to agriculture.
Unless production on the farms on which the great bulk
of the people still live begins to go up, there is no sur¬
plus for saving, no surplus to feed the towns, no surplus
to keep pace with rising population and keep down costly
imports of food, no agricultural raw materials to feed into
industry, above all, no rise in farm income to provide an
expanding market for the nascent industrial system.
There is no conflict between the priorities of farming
and industry, and the need to re-emphasize farming springs
not from any desire to "keep developing economies depen¬
dent" but simply to counteract the glamour of factory
chimmeys which may all. too often be smoking above pro¬
ducts which no one in the community can afford to buy.
Wherever the agricultural sector has been jolted into
movement in Taiwan, for instance, or increasingly in
Pakistan the reasons tend to be the same. Access to
water, access to the new technologies of fertilizer and
improved seed, ample credit for the farmers, inducements
to work and produce more in the shape of land owner¬
ship or secure tenancy, co-operatives to give advantages
of scale and some control over marketing, quick access
to the urban market, reclamation of land through malaria
eradication these are the recipes and it is in these fields
that the relevant international agencies, with the Food
and Agriculture Organization at the centre of the picture,
are at work. Moreover, each element is seen more and
more as a part in a fully concerted policy.
«EVELOP1NG countries themselves have tend¬
ed to give special attention to the industrial
sectors in their development programmes. In this field the
question of priorities is of particular importance and
difficulty. Each country has its own particular endowment
of resources and its own local needs and skills. Up to a
point, the first efforts in industry usually substitute local
products for imports. This is the "beer, boots and bricks"
phase through which most economies pass. But whatever
the background of the economy, one need is clear expert
advice in selecting the types of industry that are likely
to prosper.
Private foreign investment has an important role to play in
industrial development, particularly if, in return for tax and
tariff concessions most developing governments offer, the
firms are ready to train local people at all levels of skill and
look for local participation in the enterprise. While skill bot¬
tlenecks in developing countries do impose some limitations
on their capacity to make effective use of additional foreign
investment, new projects in which foreign capital can be
fruitfully absorbed are constantly being revealed and creat¬
ed with the expansion of education and training. The Unit¬
ed Nations family is doing its best to help developing
countries to identify these projects.
33
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
TURNING POINT
IN DEVELOPMENT
(Cont'd)
We know how much still remains to be done
but we also know what we can do
In addition to these problems, a new and formidable
one the full dimensions of which are only gradually
becoming apparent looms ahead: this is the problem of
the growing indebtedness of the developing countries,
and the limits that this imposes on their ability to utilize
the credits which may be available to them.
According ,to International Bank estimates, the public
and government-guaranteed debts of thirty-seven develop¬
ing countries rose from $7,000 million in 1955 to $18,000
million in 1962, interest payments increased nearly fourfold,
and amortization payments were more than tripled. By
1963 the servicing of the external debt absorbed over
13 per cent of the export receipts of these countries.
In response to the increasing debt servicing difficulties
of the developing countries the United States took the
tnitiative of providing development loans at low interest
rates and on easy repayment terms, and other countries
gradually eased their own lending terms. The developed
countries also co-operated in setting up the IDA as a
"soft-loan" subsidiary of the International Bank.
PART 4 Conclusion
34
HERE have been some clumsy beginnings and
uncertain efforts. But the activity, the effort,
the learning, the striving, the aspiration are fully as impor¬
tant as the inevitable delays and mistakes. After such
energetic beginnings, it would be tragic and foolish indeed
if the effort of assistance were now permitted to falter.
The United Nations does not exist apart from its
member governments and in the last analysis governmental
decisions will determine the tempo of its activities over
the rest of the Development Decade. One of the chief
reasons for today's uncertainty is that it reflects a general
crisis in the world's political relationships. It is true that
this has not yet impaired directly the United Nations work
of development. But it has impaired the atmosphere. It
has lessened goodwill and confidence. Yet the paradoxical
truth is that the U.N.'s development work can be one of
the world's chief instruments in lessening political friction.
But development, which should be one of mankind's
great constructive tasks is often bedevilled with suspicion
and misunderstanding, owing partly to the memories of
the colonial era and the persistence in some cases of
economic dependence.
It is for this reason that the question has been raised
whether a larger emphasis on the use of international
or multilateral agencies in the work of development might
not permit the vital task to go forward in an atmosphere
less charged with political tension. For instance, in the
recent governmental study of France's aid programme
which is the world's largest in relative terms of national
income it was recommended that the percentage chan¬
nelled through multilateral agencies might be raised from
12 per cent to 25 per cent. There are cogent reasons
for such proposals. The United Nations and its related
agencies comprise rich States and poor States and enjoy
the advantage of having representatives of both on their
governing bodies and on their staffs.
But perhaps the strongest argument for giving the
international agencies a larger share in the work of
development lies not so much in immediate questions of
effectiveness or efficiency but in the deeper question of
the kind of world community the nations are to live in.
At this point it is necessary to return once more to the
experience inside developed countries. When these coun¬
tries confronted as does the world today the vast
inequalities of wealth and opportunity which coincided with
the deployment of the new resources, they^did not try to
bridge the gap solely by private person-to-person giving
and philanthropy. The decisive change was the decision
that citizens as a matter of right and social justice should
begin to share more fully in the steadily increasing
resources of their community.
Clearly, if in the world community which science and
technology are moulding into an inescapable unity, the
same principles are applied, the case is very strong for
an attempt to base an increasing proportion of international
assistance of all sorts in trade, in technical aid, in capital
transfers, in compensatory finance upon international
institutions and upon an agreed international formula or
standard of obligation such as the target of 1 per cent
of national income. What is formulated as a universal
obligation is more likely to obviate misunderstanding and
possible recriminations. What is given in the name of
citizenship has the best chance of creating responsible
citizens in return. This at least has been a large part
of the experience of developed society in its domestic
aspect. It is still the only working experience upon which
the world can draw in fashioning its own common life.
Reason and vision together tell the nations that they
have entered into an uncharted phase of the world eco¬
nomy. Although over -^120,000 millions are being spent on
arms each year, this arms burden has not prevented eco¬
nomic growth in the developed world at an annual rate of 5
to 6 per, cent. How much more could be achieved for
the benefit of the whole world if even a part of these
vast efforts could be redirected from producing the instru¬
ments of death to producing the instruments of growth
and work and lifel Roads and dams, water and fertilizer,
steel and machines, houses and cities, skills and welfare
all these could provide an economic stimulus equal to
that of arms production, all could therefore be as simply
and as easily afforded by the richer States.
But development need not wait for disarmament, and it
must not. The greatest task of the United Nations Decade
of Development is to convince governments and peoples
that they have the means to wipe out mass poverty with
its attendant miseries and dangers, and to stir them to
use those means to the full. We have seen how much
remains to be done, at this mid-point of the Decade,
to achieve even the modest targets set.
Who, then, can deny the compelling urgency of apply¬
ing our efforts more purposefully, more vigorously and
with a more coherent strategy? Whether we shall succeed
is still doubtful, and in that measure so is the future of
man. But there is no doubt whatever about what can
be done. If we have courage and constancy of purpose,
a better world for all is within our reach.
H
From "The United Nations Development Decade at Mid-point" ,
an appraisal presented by the Secretary-General to the U.N. Economic
and Social Council m July, 1965.
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
ARMS COSTS SOAR: The world now
spends $180,000 million annually on
arms according to a survey prepared for
an international conference on the economic
aspects of disarmament held in Oslo. Arms
spending has thus soared 50% above the
$120,000 million estimate made by the United
Nations in 1962 (See The Unesco Courier,
Nov. 1964.)
I NTERNATIONAL EXCHANGES: Basic facts
' on the aims and programmes of over 5,300
organizations are given in Unesco's Hand¬
book of International Exchanges. In its 960
pages, this quadrilingual (English, French,
Russian and Spanish) handbook lists over
4,000 international exchange opportunities in
education, science, culture and mass commu¬
nication.
JAPAN'S PEACE CORPS: Japan is setting up
a peace corps of young men and women
to work as teams in developing countries of
Asia and Africa. Volunteers are chosen for
their skills in such fields as farming, forestry,
fishing, medicine, engineering and education.
TEACHERS FOR AFRICA: A new Unesco
booklet, "Teachers for Africa", lists some
3,600 teaching posts available in Africa during
1965-66. Vacancies In secondary, technical
and teacher training schools and in univer¬
sities are covered by the booklet which
can be obtained from Teaching Abroad Ser¬
vice, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris T.
UNESCO CENTRES IN ASIA: Unesco's
eight regional centres in Asia have been
achieving their twin objectives of promoting
intra-Asian co-operation and of attaining the
special technical purposes for which each of
them was set up. These are the findings
of a special evaluation commission set up
by Unesco's Director-General to survey and
assess the work of the centres.
TEACHING MACHINES: The University of
Pittsburgh (USA) is making a world sur¬
vey of the use of programmed instruction
and teaching machines on behalf cf Unesco.
Results will be published as a World Direc¬
tory of Programmed Instruction Activities, and
From the Unesco New
Unesco also hopes to publish a monograph
on the subject.
RADIOACTIVE HAZARDS: The Interna¬
tional Atomic Energy Agency in Vienna is
expanding its programme of international gui¬
dance on methods of protection against ha¬
zards from radioactive materials used in in¬
dustry of other fields. The programme, run
in co-operation with other UN agencies, in¬
cludes specialized training courses and
information and advisory services.
COIL STUDIES IN BRAZIL: Scientists re-
cently carried out a 1,500-mile soil inven¬
tory in Brazil's Acre Territory and Mato
Grosso State. Travelling in jeeps, the team
set out to investigate the food-growing
potentialities of this relatively unexplored
area.
ADLAI STEVENSON: In a message of con¬
dolence sent to the U.S. Secretary of
State on the death of Adlai Stevenson,
Unesco's Director-General, Mr. René Maheu,
wrote: "Adlai Stevenson's outstanding con¬
tribution to international co-operation and
peace through his work in the United Nations
and his lifelong championship of human
rights and deep concern over the major prob¬
lems of humanity will long be remembered
with gratitude."
WORLD CONGRESS ON ILLITERACY:
The World Congress of Ministers of
Education on the Eradication of Illiteracy
convened by Unesco opened in Teheran on
September 8. Initiated by the Shah of Iran,
the congress is part of the world literacy
programme adopted by the Unesco General
Conference in November 1964.
EDUCATIONAL FORECAST FOR ASIA:
Unesco specialists and Asian consultants
working together at the Unesco Regional
Education Office in Bangkok, recently used
a computer to forecast and simulate the
future growth of educational systems in Asian
countries. They did so by producing an
"Asian Educational Model" which, as new
information is fed into it, will continue to
provide educationists with a picture of short
and long-term results of national policies and
other factors in educational growth.
CLAVONIC STUDIES: The Government of
Poland is offering ten university fellow¬
ships for Slavonic studies in the fields of
Polish history, Polish philology and Sla¬
vonic philology for the 1966-67 academic
year. The fellowships are intended for mem¬
ber states of Unesco and will be awarded
under Unesco's sponsorship to applicants
selected from among candidates presented by
the governments concerned.
INDIAN OCEAN EXPEDITION: The Interna-
I tional Indian Ocean Expedition co-sponsor¬
ed by Unesco and the Special Committee
on Oceanic Research in which 25 countries
and 40 research vessels have taken part is
now in its final phase. During the past six
years over 150 scientific cruises have been
made during which the hottest, saltiest water
in the world's oceans has been investigated
and vast geophysical studies have produced
maps of the ocean's floor. A recent meeting
of scientists in Bombay discussed the find¬
ings of the expedition's meteorological
research which may be of vital economic
importance to countries affected by weather
generated over the Indian Ocean.
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; namei of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
11 2, rue du Trfine, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Rangoon.
( ). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
($ 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2.(Rs. 13/50). CHINA. World Book CoLtd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51 , Prague 1 (permanent display) ; Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 1 7).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja¬
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
elder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road. Ko'wloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Bellard Estate, Bombay 1:17 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1 ; 3 6a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco. Ministry of Education, for New Deihi3.
(Rs.7). INDONESIA. P.T.N. " Permuta-Nusantara " c/o
Dept.of Commerce, 22,DjalanNusantara,Djakarta. IRAQ.
Mackenzie'sBookshop,Baghdad.IRELAND.The National
Press, 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (1 5/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605Tokyo Central, Tokyo
(1 ,200 yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous& Co., Dar ul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (1 0/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd.,Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9 ; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 0/-). MONACO. British
Library 30 Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9, The Hague, (n. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V., Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104)(15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Oslo, Postboks
115 (17.50 kr.).' PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia. 23, Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda. Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelc 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI
Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWE¬
DEN. All publications : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbo¬
khandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescorädet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 211, Geneva 1 1.CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York,
N.Y. 1 001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Kn-
¡ïg, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
NEVif TOWN
BORN
IN GHANA
WHO-Paul Almasy
Outstanding among the major development projects achieved by Ghana since indepen¬
dence are the giant Volta River hydroelectric power plant, which began operation in
September, and the new port at Tema Africa's largest man-made harbour. A new
town with modern homes for over 80,000 people (above) has already sprung up in the
port's hinterland. Tema has also acquired an extensive industrial complex, including a
huge aluminium smelter, an oil refinery, a steel works and a fish processing plant.
]]>
</page>
</document>
