<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078247eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
ûA: H(JM*Ñ fa&m -WAÍ-
ow open on the world
Courie
October 1969 (22nd year) -U.K.: 2/-stg - Canada : 40 cents - France : 1 .20 F
the heritage of non-violence
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
BW -
\ 1
- fl i Tr fl
TBS**
Photo © Moravské Museum, Brno
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
O
Puzzling masterpiece
This ornament of uncommon design, recovered from an ancient
tomb at Brno (Czechoslovakia), puzzles archaeologists. Fourteen
centimetres high and 12 across, it dates from the 2nd century
B.C. Some specialists believe it was used to decorate a wooden
vessel; others think it enhanced a double yoke for draught-
animals. Whatever its original purpose, the grace and beauty of
this masterpiece in bronze are apparent from every angle (see
photo right).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The,
UNESCO Courier
OCTOBER 1969
22ND YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
THIRTEEN EDITIONS
English Japanese
French Italian
Spanish Hindi
Russian Tamil
German Hebrew
Arabic Persian
U.S.A.
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e
Annual subscription rates: 20/-stg.; $4.00
(Canada); 12 French francs or equivalent;
2 years : 36/-stg. ; 22 F. Single copies : 2/-stg. ;
40 cents ; 1 .20 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when it ¡s bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi, Tamil, Hebrew and Persian. In the
United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M. Stationery Office,
P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Con¬
tents - Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy Paris-7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition: Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Georgi Stetsenko (Paris)
German Edition: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Takao Uchida (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edition: Annapuzha Chandrahasan (Delhi)
Tamil Edition : T.P. Meenakshi Sundaran (Madras)
Hebrew Edition : Alexander Peli (Jerusalem)
Persian Edition : Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Photo Editor: Olga Rodel
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be eddressed to the Editor-'m-Chlef
13
20
22
26
28
31
33
34
MOHANDAS KARAMCHAND GANDHI
By Raja Rao
LANDMARKS IN AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
By Olivier Lacombe
THE HERITAGE OF NON-VIOLENCE
By René Habachi
MARTIN LUTHER KING :
'WE SHALL OVERCOME'
THE WAY OF BAPU
By Humayun Kabir
ONE OF KARL JASPERS'
LAST COMMENTARIES: GANDHIJI
By Karl Jaspers
GANDHI ON STUDENTS AND POLITICS
By Malcolm S. Adiseshiah
GANDHI'S VIEWS ON EDUCATION
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Puzzling masterpiece (Czechoslovakia)
Cover photo
The portrait of Mahatma Gandhi
is by the Indian artist Sri
Suraj Sadan, of New Delhi.
The background silhouette on front
and back cover is adapted from
woodcut by another Indian
artist, Nandlal Bose. Both artists
designed Indian stamps of Gandhi
issued to commemorate
his centenary. The graphic
presentation of our cover
is the work of Georges
Hautenne, Paris.
3
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
GANDHI
'Generations to come will scarce
believe that such a one as this
ever walked upon the earth.'
EINSTEIN
0,
4
I nee upon a time there was
a sage and king, Sri Krishna. Of
the Yadava clan, he ruled from Dwa-
raka, the seaport on the tip of Kathia-
war, the peninsula of western India.
He ruled the country in wisdom and
splendour. And one day, as he sat
in state, his chamberlain announced
that a poor Brahmin was at the palace
gate, claiming to be an old class-fellow
of the king. Sudhama was his name.
"Please ask the guards to let him
in," proclaimed the king, and when the
Brahmin came, he himself washed the
visitor's feet with hot and cold water,
smeared them with unguents and em¬
bracing his friend, accepted with joy
a handful of puffed rice his friend
had brought as a gift. And taking
him into the inner courts, asked him
many questions and fed him and
honoured him, as one should an old
and dear friend.
RAJA RAO is a noted Indian author who
was educated in India, England and France.
He is a follower of the Advaita Vedanta
school of philosophy derived from the Vedas
(the sacred books of Hindu scriptures). He
writes in English, but his work is character¬
ized by the traditional Indian mood and style.
His publications include "Kanthapura", 'Cow
of the Barricades and Other Stories", "The
Serpent and the Rope", "The Cat and
Shakespeare" and many short stories.
by Raja Rao
Sudhama was so happy, he spent
the whole day with Sri Krishna, took
his dinner, and while he was going
in a royal carriage back home to his
small town, some distance from Dwa-
raka, Sudhama remembered what he
had come for. His wife having teased
him, exasperated him, had finally driven
him to go and seek help from his
celebrated friend, King Sri Krishna.
She had grudgingly given her hus¬
band a handful of puffed rice they
were so poor as offering to his host.
But in his joy Sudhama had forgotten
the mission on which he had been
sent. He had even forgotten he was
riding in a royal carriage back home.
But when he returned to his village
such was its magnificence, his own
house had gone up in splendour with
marble walls, and cool courtyards, and
flowering shrubs entwining around the
windows, and his wife richly attired
stood at the door, to receive him with
humility and true devotion. He had
never asked and he had been given.
Such was Sri Krishna's gift to Sudha¬
ma, the Daridranärayäna, the poor-
man-god.
And since that day the village was
called Sudhamapuri, the City of Sud¬
hama, which with the accretion of
time, became Puri, and since it was a
port (bunder) it was called Porbunder,
whose kings like their cousins from
all over India, claimed their descent
from the sun or the moon and more
recently from the families of Sri Rama
(the hero of the epic, the Ramayana)
or of Sri Krishna (the hero of the
great epiG, the Mahabharatha see
Unesco Courier, December 1967).
And it is in the Gita, a part of the
Mahabharatha, that Sri Krishna said
to Arjuna, the hero: Act, but be not
attached to the fruits of action.
Porbunder is an ancient city men¬
tioned even by the Greek and Roman
traders and, since its houses were
all in marble, white stone cut fresh
from the hills behind, that the monsoon
rains had cemented century after
century, it was called the white city,
and in one of those solid marble
houses with decorated wooden doors,
and high terrace pavilions, was Mohan¬
das Karamachand Gandhi born, on
October 2, 1869.
His father was Prime Minister of the
state of Porbunder, like his own father
was, and generations five in all had
served their princes with honesty and
with devotion. Scrupulous' in their
dealings, they would bend not even
before the King if injustices were done,
and Mohandas Gandhi's grandfather,
Ota Gandhi, had to pay for it once.
Having sheltered an honest man (the
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Brian Brake - Rapho
state treasurer) against the extravagant
Queen-regent, the house was shelled
with cannon and marks of that royal
ill-temper live to this day.
Also, when Ota Gandhi left Porbun¬
der and went to his home town in the
state of Junagadh, the Prince there
asked him to be his Prime Minister.
In answer Ota gave the Prince his left
hand. "Why this?" "Because, sire,"
said Ota, "my other hand is pledged
to Porbunder." Such is the traditional
integrity of the Gandhis.
Mohandas' mother was a religious
Hindu woman who loved her fasts,
gifts to the monks and her prayers,
and taught her children obedience to
their elders, tolerance in religion, and
purity of conduct.
She used to take her children
especially Mohania her youngest to
the story-tellings (Kathas) where some
episode from the legends was chosen
for recital, like that of Prahalada who
defied his heretic father and proved
the existence of God God surging
before them from a common pillar or
of Harishchandra, the King, who gave
up his kingdom for the truth, sold his
wife as a charwoman, and himself
became guardian of a crematorium.
Young Mohandas wiping his tears
wondered why he and everybody could
not live like Harishchandra.
When he grew up and went to
school, first at Porbunder, and later at
Rajkot (whither his father had now
been invited to set the affairs of that
state in order), Mohandas was ever
eager for the truth. Having once refus¬
ed to copy from his teacher the exact
spelling of the English word "kettle"
a British inspector of education was
visiting the Alfred High School he
was despised by the teacher, and his
life made difficult.
Yet Mohania was not such a model
Hindu boy. He had class-fellows who
spoke of other things than books, and
made suggestions that the world out¬
side was very, very different. In fact,
the English ruled India because they
ate meat; there was even doggerel:
Behold the mighty Englishman,
He rules the Indian small,
Because, being a meat-eater,
He is five cubits tall.
So Mohania with his brother started
eating meat by the riverside, in hiding.
However, because of the fact that
money had to be stolen and so an
untruthful act committed, he decided
he would eat meat only when he grew
up and was Independent like his
father.
Another day, his companion took
him to a brothel, and he had such
compassion for the harlot that he ran
out a coward. This visit was even
worse for Mohania was already mar¬
ried. He had been married, when he
was thirteen, to Kasturba, who was of
the same age and had been his fiancée
since he was five years old.
The discovery of woman at such an
early age and the raging passion he
had for her made him forget his moral
and intellectual aptitudes and even to
listening to the monks and learned
men who came to visit his father, or
simply hear that great philosophical
epic, the Ramayana of Tulsidas read
out.
And, on the night his father was
very ill, Mohania left the bedside of
the invalid to find the sumptuosities
of his wife's body, and when they
called him it was too late; his father
was already dead. This shook him to
the very depths of his moral found¬
ation.
His brothers, though kind and good,
could, however, never become Prime
Ministers of Porbunder; they did not
have modern education, and now that
the British were installed in India,
unless one were at least a barrister
one would never become Prime Minis¬
ter.
Hence, much against the wishes of
his mother and wife and of his whole
community, the family decided to send
Mohania to London so that he might
become a barrister. The only condition
was that, to keep himself from the
evils of Western civilization, he had
to take a vow: never to touch meat or
wine or female of any type.
Though excommunicated by his
community for "going across the dark
waters", he sailed to London (Sept.
1888) and spent almost three years in
that extraordinary atmosphere of Vic¬
torian England where Socialists were
vying with Imperialists in sincerity,
vegetarians with anti-vivisectionists,
atheists with theosophists, and contra-
ceptionists with anti-contraceptionists.
He desperately tried to become an
English gentleman, taking lessons in
elocution and ballroom dancing and
learning that elegant speech, French,
but, having failed in the attempt, he
gave them all up and devoted himself
to economic living, Latin, and the study
of law.
IOHANDAS' vegetarianism
led him to extraordinary adventures in
which he met eccentric and compas¬
sionate Englishmen and women who
believed that this slight change in diet
would lead mankind to a new millen¬
nium, and perhaps to the true god. He
was elected to the committee of the
London Vegetarian Society, but he was
so shy that he could hardly ever make
a speech, though he attended their
meetings assiduously.
After a brief visit to Paris, where
the great exhibition was being held,
having visited the Eiffel Tower and
eaten at the restaurant there, . he
returned to London, took his degree,
and sailed back to India (1891).
But there was nobody in India to
offer him a Prime Ministership. He
could not even earn enough money as
a lawyer to look after his needs he
was too honest to employ touts and
thus, in misery and sorrow, when a
firm in Porbunder which had connex¬
ions with South Africa invited him as
legal consultant, he jumped to the
occasion and sailed off to Durban,
capital of Natal, in April 1893.
South Africa at that time was a
palimpsest of races, historical periods,
and adventurers from every nation.
The hardy, religious Boer lived, as it r
were, on the outskirts of the Zulu J
universe, while the British manipulated
the world to better business, roads
and railways, and a growing gentle-
CONTINUEO ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
GANDHI (Continued)
6
men's democracy. But as slavery was
abolished and somebody was needed
to do the hard work, indentured
labour was brought from India the
coolie and being neither white nor
black but poor and brown, nobody
knew where to place him.
Thus, travelling to Pretoria on his
legal work, Gandhi, then twenty-three
years of age, was pushed out of the
train at Pietermaritzburg the most
"creative" moment of his life. Shiver¬
ing in the cold at the station and
utterly friendless he could either go
forward and so into the unknown and
suffering, or return to India and to
some minor legal activity. He chose
to go forward, for with his faith in
the truth, he refused to be humiliated.
Travelling further on a stagecoach
toward Pretoria, he was hit by a white
bully, but he refused to answer back
in the same manner. In fact he decid¬
ed he would never appeal to a court
of law for any personal grievance.
Later, walking on a pavement in Pre¬
toria, he was kicked off by the guards,
as the pavement was reserved for the
whites, and he again refused to go
to the courts of law to defend himself.
Seeing the humiliating situation of
the Indian the coolie and being now
called a coolie barrister, he taught
English to the Indian barber and the
trader, and defended the coolie against
his white masters (the coolie was his
Daridranärayäna).
Gandhi also wrote letters to the
legislatures, sent petitions to the Im¬
perial Government in London and
created Indian political and cultural
organizations, and in very few years
made the problem of the Indian in
South Africa an imperial and an inter¬
national question.
And in the process, by a series of
spiritual understandings based on the
Sermon on the Mount and later on
the Bhagavad Gita of Sri Krishna and
of moving human adventures, he
discovered Satyagraha: that is to say,
the Force that is born of Truth and
Love, or non-violence. His final aim
was not liberation of the coolie, or of
India, but of man from his own bon¬
dage: to attain Moksha. And with this
as philosophy, and with the techniques
of non-violence, he fought for the
rights of Indians in South Africa.
Yet when the whites were in a painful
predicament during the Boer War he
organized a Red Cross team and
served in the most dangerous battle
zones. Again, when the Zulus rose in
rebellion he nursed the howling and
wounded Zulus, and whites.
He discussed Christianity with the
Christians, Islam with Muslims, and
chided the Hindus for their sloth, their
filth and their incompetence. When
he left South Africa in 1914, he had
successfully carried on his non-violent
campaign against Smuts, achieved
every specific objective he had in mind,
and thus proved to the world the
unique humanity and efficacity of
Satyagraha.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 8
LANDMARKS IN AN
EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
On the following pages we present, in the form of a picture album, some
of the memorable episodes in the life of Mahatma Gandhi. The accomp¬
anying text is by the French Orientalist, Olivier Lacombe. Professor of
Comparative Philosophy at the' Sorbonne and Director of the Institut de
Civilisation Indienne, in Paris, Olivier Lacombe has written widely on the
culture and philosophy of India, and is the author of "Gandhi, ou la Force
de l'Ame" (Gandhi, or the Power of 'Soul Force') published by Ed. Plön,
Paris, 1964.
l'A*
Gandhi In India, aged 7.. ...aged 17.
1. IN LONDON
REDISCOVERY OF HINDUISM
lOHANDAS Karamchand Gan¬
dhi was born on October 2, 1869, at
Porbandar, a port on the south-west coast
of the Kathiawar peninsula in western
India, and capital of a principality in which
several members of his family, including
his father, had held the office of Prime
Minister.
He died in New Delhi on January 30,
1948, in his 79th year, by the hand of a
Hindu extremist.
Three great periods mark the course of
his life: a period of preparation only remote¬
ly connected with his future mission, set
in India and England, which ended in 1893
when he was 24; a South African period
(1893-1914) when Gandhi forged his
"method" and tentatively practised it In
a marginal area of the Indian diaspora;
and a period of fulfilment (1915-1948) when
he perfected his method in India itself,
applying it on an increasing scale until
its message was carried beyond the front-
tiers of the vast nation he had fathered.
Like so many educated Indians, Gandhi
had first to master and reconcile the dual
cultures of East and West which disputed
possession of his heart and mind. It is
easy to imagine how closely the world
of his early childhood was bounded by
the Hindu tradition. He belonged to a
"caste" family which ranked third in the
tiers of the rigidly graded Hindu society
("Gandhi" means "spice merchant"), though
the family's status was certainly improved
by the political and administrative functions
entrusted to some of its members.
Gandhi was 16 when his father died.
Two years later he left for England, against
the orders of his caste, which excommu-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
by Olivier Lacombe
Law student in London, aged 20.
Lawyer in Johannesburg (South Africa), aged 40.
nicated him. While in Britain (1888-1891)
studying to be a barrister, he not only
improved his acquaintance with Western
culture, but also rediscovered the Hindu
faith in which he had been nurtured.
He had never read the "Bhagavad Gita",
the "Song Celestial", which wais later to
become his daily solace. It was revealed
to him in the English translation by Sir
Edwin Arnold, which he read in conjunction
with the Sanskrit original. The same
English poet and writer unfolded to him,
in "The Light of Asia", the spiritual epic
of Buddha.
Gandhi's reading transfigured his quasi-
instinctive fidelity to the creed of his
forebears, but at the same time, he studied
the Bible; the Sermon on the Mount with
its precept that evil should not be resisted
by evil impressed him deeply.
2. FIGHT AGAINST RACISM
IN SOUTH AFRICA
After his return to India in 1891, Gandhi
went to South Africa as representative
of a firm of Indian lawyers, and arrived
in Natal at the end of May 1893. The
humiliation and discrimination to which he
was at once subjected, because of his
nationality and colour, was an experience
that changed the course of his life. He
resolved to champion the rights of his
fellow countrymen in South Africa, victims
of prejudice and Intolerance.
Sensing in Gandhi a peace-loving but
indomitable force, coupled with a lucid,
shrewd and inventive mind, they welcomed
him. Nor were they mistaken, for his
promotion of what he conceived to be the
public good was bold, steadfast and per¬
severing, yet always attuned to the possibi
lities of the moment. He knew that discre¬
tion was the better part of valour.
In 1894, he proposed the formation of
a permanent organization to watch over
the interests of Indians. Created the same
year, it was named the Natal Indian Con¬
gress, after the Indian National Congress.
In 1904, he helped to start a weekly
magazine, "Indian Opinion", at first contri¬
buting funds and writing articles. But later
he took complete charge and poured all
his savings into the venture.
It put a timely weapon in his hand as
the. situation worsened and the campaign
against Injustices Inflicted on the coloured
peoples was intensified.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
GANDHI (Continued)
Like Smuts and Rhodes (and more
like Rhodes than Smuts), Gandhiji
believed in the importance and integrity
of the British Empire. It was the first
attempt man seemed to have made of
some sort of human commonwealth.
Therefore, Rhodes believed the whole
world should be painted red, whereas
for Gandhi, the Empire implied a sense
of a universal brotherhood, something
Tolstoyan that was emerging out of the
sorrow-beleaguered world.
In fact Gandhiji had already written
to Tolstoy (1909) about the experiences
of non-violence in the Transvaal, and
Tolstoy had replied, "May God help
our dear brothers and co-workers in
the Transvaal," and had sent every
encouragement to the Satyagraha
movement.
But soon Tolstoy died, and the
Germans and the British (the French
and the Russians) all quarrelled over
the body of some royal heir murdered
in Serbia, and Gandhi, true subject of
the British Empire, offered to raise a
volunteer army for the imperial needs,
despite his disbelief in war violence.
But Gandhi's health demanded his
return to India, and Gokhale, the great
leader, was pressing Gandhiji to give
his life to Indian politics at home. At
the Town Hall in Bombay, Gokhale had
declared: "Gandhi has in him the
marvellous spiritual power to turn ordi¬
nary men into heroes and martyrs."
T,
8
_ HE war came and went;
Indians fought in Flanders, in the
Middle East; great promises were
made to them by British statesmen, but
when peace came and the world was
being looked at anew, Britain had no
desire to lose India. There was unrest
and wide-spread repression. Now
violence flared up. Gandhi pleaded
again for a fairer perspective, respect
for their promises made. But the
British were unwilling to listen.
Meanwhile, during the war he had
turned to the poor Indians on the
indigo plantations of Behar who were
treated no better than the indentured
labourers in Natal (he was always for
Daridranärayäna), and with his indubit¬
able honesty and his meticulous
gathering of facts, he showed how the
poor labourers in Champaran were
more or less slaves.
The gentlemen among the English
(both in South Africa and in Great
Britain) sided with him. Truth always
had this power, Gandhiji said, and
each time he tried he found there was
no monolithic adversary. He had no
enemies, only adversaries. And the
adversary was always a system, never
a man. And each time one English¬
man took your point of view, the
adversary's case looked less self-
sustaining.
Then with the backing of the Indian
National Congress, of which he had
by now become the undoubted head,
he launched his first movement of
non-co-operation, the Hartal, when
shops closed, workers would not work,
and offices were deserted. Some¬
times violence broke out here and
there and he suddenly asked his
followers to stop and pray. We were
not yet ready for Satyagraha.
Once again Hartals and Satyagraha
would start. Such was the enthusiasm
in India that wave after wave of the
non-violent revolution shook the
country. The British were unprepared
for this, just as Smuts was. Some¬
times here and there once again vio¬
lence broke out. The country was not
yet mature for a spiritual and material
regeneration.
Now he would try Satyagraha in a
small area (Bardoli) of some 140 vil¬
lages and prepare the country with
this rigorous experiment in non-violent
non-co-operation. It began as a great
success and the country was wild with
enthusiasm. When in Chowri Chowra
some brutal policemen were killed,
against the advice of most of his
followers and with the indignation of
the majority against him, he stopped
the fight. India was not yet ready
for Swaraj independence. We would
fast and we would pray and prepare
ourselves anew.
The British however could not let
him go so simply. They arrested him,
but when the judge had to pronounce
sentence he made a statement that was
to honour the British tradition. "Even
those who differ from you in politics
look upon you as a man of high ideals
and noble and even saintly life." He
was condemned to six years imprison¬
ment. But if he were released, said
the judge, no one would be happier
than himself. Gandhiji was released
some two years later on medical
grounds.
As long as there is a single Satya-
grahi there is never a defeat. This is
the essence of Gandhism. And since
he was there the one at least, Satya¬
graha would continue. For this one
needs much austerity, integrity and
prayer. He had already established
the Ashram (hermiíage) of Sabaramathi
near Ahmedabad, and there he prepar¬
ed workers for a future fight.
He would never seek an opportunity.
The opportunity would have to seek
him. Then with truth and non-violence
he would go to his "non-violent" war.
The heart of the adversary would one
day melt, our suffering would change
him, and the commonwealth of man
could still be founded.
Meanwhile he preached for the unity
of the Hindus and the Muslims. Even
in South Africa most of the leadership
was Muslim while the rank and file
were Hindu. Here in India they would
fight like brothers.
He had now lost faith in the British
Empire. Britain had come to bleed
India; she had taken away our man¬
liness. And so when the moment came
he launched his salt-Satyagraha
(March, 1930), marching to the sea with
his closest followers, and then with
CONTINUED ON PAGE 10
AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
(Continued from page 7)
3. BEGINNINGS
OF ASCETICISM
AND
NON-VIOLENCE
The centre of the conflict shifted to
Johannesburg, and Gandhi's method began
to take shape. A Sanskrit word, "Satya¬
graha" (satya: truth; agraha: firm grasp)
was coined for it.
Clashes with the authorities became more
serious. Between 1906 and 1914, Gandhi
was arrested six times, sentenced to pris¬
on four times and actually kept in jail
for more than a year. But he finally
triumphed. The principal Indian demands
were conceded and confirmed by the
Indians' Relief Act in July, 1914, shortly
before Gandhi left South Africa.
The Gandhi who had worsted the South
African government in a prolonged struggle
Gandhi in 1899, during the
Boer War in South Africa,
seen here (x) with members
of the Indian Ambulance Corps
which he organized and
trained.
Photo PIB. New Delhi
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Gandhi, at 45, shortly before
leaving South Africa. For years
he had practised a strict
personal asceticism, and
had forged and successfully
applied his method of
non-violence. Imprisoned
several times in South Africa.
had meanwhile profoundly transformed his
personal and family life, his wife Kasturbai
having joined him in South Africa in 1896,
together with their two young sons and
a nephew. Gandhi's private life was now
interwoven with his public activities, to
which it gave strength and purity, draw¬
ing in return encouragement and inspiration.
His longing for a simple ascetic life and
his urge to share his existence with the
poorest of his fellows led him to forsake
the city and its artificialities for the rural
or semi-rural settlements he had founded
the Phoenix and Tolstoy farms where he
was free to practise his bent and gift for
teaching.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
(Continued from page 9)
Gandhi and his wife, Kasturbai,
on their return to India in 1915.
4. FIRST CAMPAIGN
EMANCIPATION OF
The First World War broke out when
Gandhi was returning to India via London.
He landed in Bombay on January 9, 1915,
when he was 45. He was already a moder¬
ate, non-violent revolutionary, and destined
to become still more so. He was a man
of uncompromising stands and stern
ideals. His search for the absolute often
seemed to be a search for the impossible,
yet he was always ready to seize any
realistic opportunities. He wa», in his own
words, "a practical idealist".
Moreover, while eschewing strictly poli¬
tical functions of any kind, he frequently
entered the political arena. In his eyes,
religion merged Imperceptibly into ethics,
and ethics into social and political life,
and the key to the human problems he
wished to solve was often to be found in
the realm of state decisions.
After a voyage of reconnaissance across
the length and breadth of India, Gandhi
founded the Satyagraha Ashram at the
gates of Ahmedabad, on May 25, 1915.
Like the settlements he had started in
South Africa, it was to be a place of retreat
where he could teach, plan his campaign,
pray, write and study.
At first the settlement housed about 25
people, men and women of all age«. Some
came from the Phoenix and Tolstoy farms
in South Africa, others from different parts
of India. Gandhi also took in, on an equal
footing, a family of Untouchables, which
caused trouble within the ashram and rais¬
ed a storm outside. But otherwise, how
could India's foreign masters be required
to show respect for human dignity in their
dealings with Indians, if the Indians them-
IN INDIA:
THE UNTOUCHABLES
selves denied it to certain of their own
people?
Gandhi thus found himself in open conflict
with the traditional organization of Hindu
society, the caste system. He approach¬
ed the question as a moral rather than a
social problem.
Gandhi was not basically opposed to
the caste system as such. He was aware
of the services it had rendered in the past
and recognized the value of a social order
based on the respective duties of its mem¬
bers rather than on the clash between
their respective rights. But he never ceas¬
ed to denounce the abuses, aberrations and
harshness that had deformed it. He de¬
manded a radical reform of its principles
and practice.
The contempt shown to the Untouch¬
ables was particularly abhorrent to him. He
found a new name for them: Harijans
(Children of God). He desired to eman¬
cipate and rehabilitate them within the
Hindu society which had wronged them.
He would be satisfied with nothing less.
In 1915, with the world plunged into
war, Gandhi refrained from using Satyagra¬
ha as a weapon against the British Empire.
The first non-violent campaigns he launch¬
ed on Indian soil were directed against the
indigo planters at Champaran in Bihar, for
their abusive treatment of tenant farmers,
and against the owners of the Ahmedabad
spinning mills whose employees were un¬
derpaid and overworked. But Gandhi co¬
operated with the Empire. By his loyalty
and generosity, he hoped to compel the
loyalty and generosity of the British people,
whom he respected, and indeed loved.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 12
10
GANDHI (Continued)
more and more as they joined him on
his pilgrim march, he would finally sit
by the sea and break the government
monopoly on salt.
Salt was the poor man's food, the
need of Daridranärayäna, and the
government made the poor, who were
almost starving, pay for this pittance of
salt that the sea gave to man as free
as air or water. And this Satyagraha
was already a bigger movement than
the one before, spreading rapidly
through the whole of India.
Arrested again and released, he was
invited to London for discussions. He
failed to get what he asked for, and
on his return was arrested again. And
when the government wanted to give
the Untouchables a separate represent¬
ation he fasted, and as the fast was
prolonged the government became
ever so worried, for if he died there
would be a bloody revolution. The
government gave in. The Untouchable
problem was left for the Congress to
resolve.
For the moment he withdrew, as it
were, from politics to prepare himself
and the country for what was to come.
But soon Hitler was making his pre¬
parations for the war. The Jews were
being persecuted. Japan was arming
herself for an Asiatic dominion.
Gandhi wanted, at least for practical
reasons, that India should be made
free, that she too could play her part
in international affairs and maybe bring
some weight on the side of peace
among the warring nations. For he
was not fighting for Indian freedom
he was always fighting for Moksha,
liberation, of which India's freedom
and the welfare of all mankind would
be an Integral part. But the British
were in no mood for such an under¬
standing.
And when Hitler marched into
Poland, Gandhiji begged the British to
let him go to plead with Hitler, and
again when Japan attacked at Pearl
Harbour, he again pleaded with the
government to let him talk to the
Japanese. Churchill was in no mood
to listen to this "naked fakir".
But disaster after disaster shook
the British in Malaya, in Burma, and
then again in the West. Rommel was
almost at the door of India. Disaster
made the British in India evermore
arrogant. But Gandhi would not hurt
the British in their hour of need. Yet
the British would not understand,
caught as they were between the
Germans and the Japanese.
"Quit India", he told them in his
famous speech at the Congress
(August 1942), and leave India to the
anarchy of God. Churchill arrested
him and his lieutenants, Pandit Nehru
and the President of the Congress,
Maulana Azad, one of the greatest
Muslim theologians of our time. And
the news of Gandhiji's arrest and the
arrest of all the important Indian
leaders created such a revolutionary
situation in the country that for six
months there was the biggest mass
upsurge in India since the revolution
(or the "Mutiny") of 1857. Railway
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Gandhi refused to
enter any temple
which denied
admission to
Untouchables.
After years of
struggle and
fasting in support
of their
emancipation,
he saw the ban
lifted In hundreds
of temples.
Photo shows the
temple of Madurai
in the State
of Madras.
lines were lifted, telegraph wires cut,
government offices sabotaged, all in a
non-violent manner, and to this day it
is difficult to know how many people
were shot in the "Quit India" move¬
ment.
But the success of the allied forces
in Europe and the new shape of things
to come suddenly turned in favour of
India. The "Quit India" movement (in
which hardly half a dozen Europeans
were killed) had sapped the integrity
of the British Government so that
when the Indian Navy mutinied against
the British, and with the British soldier
wanting to get back home (in any case
he had no quarrel with the Indians),
Britain decided to give independence
to India.
But to which India, for by now Jinnah
and the Muslim league had become
powerful. They felt that in a majority
Hindu state they would be an important
but helpless minority. Gandhiji and
Nehru pleaded with the Muslim League
leaders. The irony was that Maulana
Azad, the great Muslim theologian,
was the President of the Congress.
But politics is not reasonable ever.
Gandhiji himself was willing to give
the whole of India to Jinnah, his old
friend, if he so desired. The British
however sent Mountbatten, cousin to
the King, as Viceroy of India. India
would at last be independent. But
what India; not Gandhi's India.
Thus when independence came
Gandhiji was trying to quell the Hindu-
Muslim massacres that had started at
the time of the division of the country.
He walked among the Hindus to pro¬
tect the Muslims; he walked into
Pakistan to give courage to the Hindus.
Death was no fear to the Satyagrahi.
In fact that would be the right death.
He preached love from hamlet to
hamlet, going on foot over rickety
bamboo bridges, sleeping in poor peo¬
ples' huts and having his prayers said
morning and evening (Hindu hymns,
texts from Sri Krishna's Gita, and
Muslim prayers) and preaching the
necessity and the efficacy of love.
Finally, coming to Delhi (for the
government badly needed his pre¬
sence) he preached universal love
evening after evening from the Ram¬
lila grounds. His wife had already
died in prison. He looked a lone,
gaunt figure, misunderstood and
sorrowful.
The government heard of conspir¬
acies to kill him the Hindus were
incensed at his defence of the Mus¬
lims but he refused all form of pro¬
tection. He had just gone on a fast
for a better treatment to be given to
Muslims and to Pakistan by the govern¬
ment and the Indians. A young Hindu
intellectual who respected him but
thought his speeches were dangerous
to Hindu India, knelt one afternoon
while Gandhiji was going to his
prayers and shot him. "He Ram" (O
God), he cried; and died to his truth.
"Generations to come, it may be,"
said Albert Einstein, "will scarce be¬
lieve that such a one as this ever in
flesh and blood walked upon this
earth."
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
r
AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
(Continued from page 10)
5. IMPRISONMENT,
FASTING,
STRIKES,
MASS
DEMONSTRATIONS
The years 1918-1919 brought a de¬
cisive reversal of Gandhi's policy: co-opera¬
tion with the Imperial Government in
New Delhi gave place to non-co-operation.
The immediate cause of the break was the
passing of emergency laws that prolonged
certain wartime restrictions. Gandhi and
some of his followers denounced the laws
as unjustified and incompatible with the
dignity of free citizens, especially in time of
peace.
The new leader of the Indian nationalist
movement for without seeking in any way
to be its head, Gandhi was soon recognised
as such kept two aims clearly in mind:
to maintain at all costs the strictly non¬
violent nature of his campaign, despite the
wavering faith of even staunch disciples and
the indiscipline among rank and file; and
never to lose sight of the goal of political
freedom for India, which, as was now
realized, would not readily be granted.
To achieve the first aim, the most deter¬
mined "civil disobedience" refusal to bow
to injustice or to co-operate with its perpe¬
trators did not, in Gandhi's view, justify
the use of violence. The revendication
of legitimate rights through self-sacrifice
and self-purification, acceptance of blows
and imprisonment, and abstention from all
violence to people or property, he affirmed,
alone would bring about true, unblemished
national independence.
Non-violent strikes, mass demonstra¬
tions, fasts of protest took place year after
year until the ultimate goal was attained.
Between 1918 and 1948, Gandhi undertook
at least 15 long fasts: three lasted for 21
days and two he vowed to continue inde¬
finitely until his death from starvation if
his demands were not met There were
times when the situation eased, but even
then Gandhi never relaxed his vigilance.
To the Indian National Congress and the
entire nation, Gandhi had become a re¬
spected leader to whom they gave enthu¬
siastic support. But not everyone under¬
stood the absolute necessity of Satyagraha.
Gandhi had the courage to disown and
even to call a halt, on the brink of vic¬
tory, to the revolutionary élan of his fol¬
lowers, which was marred by serious vio¬
lence, in February, 1922.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 14
Arrested on many occasions,
Gandhi spent more than five
years In prison in India and
South Africa, went on hunger
strikes and led non-violent
mass movements throughout
India. Here, he visits political
prisoners in a jail near Calcutta.
Photo © Snark International
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
THE
HERITAGE
OF
NON-VIOLENCE
by René Habachi
SUNCE the death of
Gandhi violence has spread across
the world In so many different forms
that we often fail to recognize them
as such. The violence of mind-
conditioning as well as economic
violence; the subtle pressures exer¬
cised by broadcasting, press and the
flood of advertising along with the
spread of open violence with resort
to arms and weapons; the agitation
brought about by the consumer society
of rich countries or the misery of the
poor nations. These are all facets of
our present-day world which led the
Brazilian advocate of non-violence,
Don Helder Cámara, to say, "There are
semblances of order and semblances
of peace which conceal flagrant in¬
justice and threats to peace."
And then, suddenly, a shudder of
doubt sweeps over us: are we not
all living in a state of violence? Are
we not exerting it on others? Are we
not all accomplices in some deep-
rooted violence that stealthily Invades
the fabric of life, lying hidden until the
moment when it suddenly erupts to
spread death and disaster?
To this general onset of violence,
RENE HABACHI of the Lebanon is a member
of Unesco's Division of Philosophy and was
formerly professor of philosophy at the
Lebanese, French and American Universities
in Beirut. He is the author of various works
on philosophy including one on the Middle
East entitled 'Orient, quel est ton Occident?"
(Orient, what is your Occident!) 1969; 'La
Colonne Brisée de Baalbek" (The Broken
Column of Baalbek) 1968; "Une Philosophie
pour Notre Temps" (A Philosophy for our
Time) 1962; and 'Pour une Pensée Méditer¬
ranéenne" (A Revival of Mediterranean '
Thought) 4 volumes, 1956-60.
Gandhi, paradoxically, would have
responded by non-violence. But not
by weak compliance or resigned paci¬
fism. Non-violence is at the extreme
pole of violence; it is a form of vio¬
lence inverted. It implies the same
force as violence but something addi¬
tional to transform it into moral force
so as to counteract violence:
"I seek entirely to blunt the
edge of the tyrant's sword, not
by putting up against it a sharper-
edged weapon, but by disappoint¬
ing his expectation that I would
be offering physical resistance."
(Young India, Oct. 8, 1925).
Non-violence Is thus the spirit and
freedom's last recourse after which
only brute force is possible with final
victory going to the most ruthless.
Gandhi speaks to a world which is
still human, which the spirit has not
yet deserted, because "faith in man¬
kind" is his ultimate message.
For his faith in mankind he paid
with his life. Yet is not this non¬
violence in the face of death, this
triumph of free decision which is inse¬
parable from non-violence, itself proof
that faith in mankind is justified? When
those whose lives are a spiritual
example are cut down by blind vio¬
lence, they kindle a flame that grows
Into a reservoir of light for the sombre
hours when man begins to lose faith
in himself.
Non-violence has so little in com¬
mon with a strategy of withdrawal
that its first act is to test the strength
of the adversary. Of what use,
Gandhi asks, is the non-violence of
the helpless? "Forgiveness," he wrote
in -1920, "is the adornment of the
soldier but not of the coward . . .
where there is only a choice between
cowardice and violence, I would advise
violence." (Hind Swaraj, August //,
1920). And "I would risk violence a
thousand times rather than the emas¬
culation of a whole race." [Hind Swa¬
raj, August 4, 1920). And then again:
"I cultivate the courage to die
without killing, but for the man
who does not have this courage,
I would wish him to cultivate the
art of killing and being killed,
rather than flee shamefully from
danger." (Hind Swaraj, Oct. 2,
1920).
So he who would practise non¬
violence must first be capable of
measuring the strength of violence,
and thus equipped must be ready des¬
pite everything to run the full gauntlet
of non-violence, even if it kills him.
Is not the serene strength of unarmed
force the height of courage?
When non-violence succeeds, what,
then, is the secret of its power? It Is
this: non-violence refuses to lump
together the adversary and the force
he uses or the Injustices he commits.
It respects even the flicker of under¬
standing and freedom that still remains
within the adversary unshackled by
violence. Non-violence thus turns the
adversary's attention to his better self,
to his responsibilities, to the values
that are not Irretrievably lost.
In other words, non-violence is a
road to lost truth which previous acts
of violence had masked or muzzled
under the cloak of faits accomplis or
simulations of peace. 1 Q
Gandhi's life was a search for truth
which was dearer to him than all else.
Truth was his Religion: "Truth is God,"
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
(Continued from page 12) 6. GANDHI'S SALT MARCH
Although disappointed in his own sup¬
porters, and harshly treated by the author¬
ities, the Mahatma never lost heart. Two
periodicals, an English-language weekly,
"Young India", and "Navajivan", a Guja-
rati weekly, placed themselves at his dis¬
posal. In articles which he wrote for each
issue, he explained the true significance of
his doctrine and his action: not only to
do away with existing wrongs, but to build
with patience and devotion a truly just so¬
ciety, in which he himself gave the lead by
founding the Village Industries Association
and two new ashrams at Wardha and
Segaon.
Outstanding events not yet mentioned
were the declaration of the "War of Inde
pendence" on March 12, 1930, followed
immediately by the famous "salt march",
an inspired protest against the govern¬
ment salt monopoly, regarded as a symbol
of oppression; Gandhi's part in the Round
Table Conference (London, 1931); his ex¬
tended fasts on behalf of the Untouchables
(1932-33); and his approval of the 1937
provincial elections.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 16
HERITAGE OF NON-VIOLENCE (Continued)
14
he writes (Young India, Dec. 31, 1931).
For him, only non-violence, personified
as a single-minded militant who has
killed the spirit of violence within him,
is capable of retrieving truth if it is
lost to sight, or of revealing truth if it
is still to be discovered.
This is the high ambition inspiring
"Satyagraha", literally: the grasp of
truth. The French orientalist Louis
Massignon, who knew Gandhi per¬
sonally and became one of his sup¬
porters, translated the definition in
concrete terms as a "civil campaign
for truth". Its only weapon is "Ahimsa",
refusal to injure, respect for others.
Thus the aim of the Satyagrahi is
truth; his method, non-injury, the posi¬
tive aspect of which is love and com¬
passion. The end and the means are
so closely interwoven that Satyagraha
cannot be cunningly turned to other
purposes as a mere strategic device
or tactical manoeuvre.
The Satyagrahi must be sincere, and
must breathe the air of non-violence
and compassion. He must therefore
submit to a strict discipline and a long
apprenticeship. This is "Bramashar-
ya" the discipline of all the senses,
asceticism.
The inclination to violence must be
destroyed by fasting, chastity, silence
(Gandhi imposed total silence on
himself every Monday), wearing the
simplest clothing (hence the adoption
of the loin-cloth, and the. "spinning-
wheel campaign" to spin the cotton for
this garment), and meditation in the
"Ashram"v the places of retreat which
Gandhi founded in South Africa and
India.
Thus, before the militant engages
in an external campaign of non-vio
lence, his efforts are turned inwards
upon himself. How can truth be re¬
quired of others, if it is not first
demanded of oneself? Unclean hands
cannot rekindle the sources of light.
By these exacting, even unforeseeable
demands the Mahatma (or Great Soul)
awakened a whole nation to the ways
of the spirit and at the same time to
political freedom.
Can Gandhi's message hope to find
a response in our present world torn
as it is with violence of every kind?
Some people have sought to deny
Gandhi's message any current validity
on grounds that what historical cir¬
cumstances made possible yesterday
is no longer applicable today. Bri¬
tish liberalism and "fair play" enabled
Gandhi to enter politics because of
his reputation as a mystic. The mora¬
lity of a nation traditionally protestant
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The "Salt March" of 1930
was Gandhi's first great
battle in the struggle that
was to lead to Indian
independence. On March 12,
he left the village of
Sabarmati (left) and, for
24 days, trekked on foot
(right) the 240 miles to
the west coast at Dandi,
his followers soon swelling
to many thousands. At
Dandi, he picked up some
sea salt In a symbolic
gesture, encouraging all
Indians to defy the British
salt monopoly laws. This
action recalls the incident
in the American struggle
for Independence, when
the citizens of Boston
in 1773 protested British
taxation without
representation by throwing
whole cargoes of tea from
British ships Into the
harbour. Gandhi was once
asked by Lord Irwin,
Viceroy of India, to have
a cup of tea during a
conference. "Thank you,"
said Gandhi, taking a paper
bag from a fold in his shawl,
"I will put some of this
salt Into my tea to remind
us of the famous Boston
Tea Party."
could not turn a deaf ear to Gandhi's
appeal to the conscience of his own
people as well as to that of the
servants of the Empire. And so this
sage, armed with his English university
degrees and wearing the simplest gar¬
ments, soon found himself introduced
into Buckingham Palace. But this
situation has gone forever.
It has also been pointed out that
when India was part of the closely knit
British Empire, the impact of non-vio¬
lence through economic and political
non-co-operation could be extremely
effective, whereas in the relatively open
world trading pattern of today such
passive resistance would not get very
far. The loss of one economic market
could be made good elsewhere, while
the principle of the full sovereignty of
the modern State would prevent any
foreign interference in internal affairs.
Resistance could thus be crushed by
violent means, as happens only too
often. Non-violence therefore, these
advocates say, would never have a
chance.
But this reasoning tells only half
the story. It overlooks the fact that
the disappearance of the closely-knit
imperial system may turn out to be an
advantage instead of a handicap for
non-violence. Today, when news is
broadcast about trouble in one country
it often creates a mass movement of
sympathy and solidarity in other lands,
and national public opinion, quickly
transformed into international and even
world opinion, soon makes the force of
its protest felt on perpetrators of in¬
justice (not always, unfortunately, and
the result can take an opposite turn
with a clamp down more severe than
before). Nevertheless, we can all
recall examples which prove that
resistance in one area has a good
chance of arousing mass support
abroad and thereby modify the abuses
of power either directly or indirectly.
Since any national event can now
have world-wide repercussions, non¬
violence, too, has taken on interna¬
tional importance, particularly within the
framework of the United Nations. The
atom bomb of violence can be dis¬
armed only by the ultimate weapon of
peace. It is only on the highest levels
of the human conscience that the
spirit of aggression can be trans¬
formed into a spirit of conciliation.
Pacifism at any price and moralism
at any cost being Utopian or even dan¬
gerous, Gandhi that "practical idea¬
list," as he described himself would
not have disclaimed the principle of
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
IS
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE
(Continued from page 14)
7. 'QUIT INDIA!'
During the Second World War, India
wished to share in the war effort on a
strictly equal footing with the Dominions.
Gandhi was at first inclined, as in 1914-18,
not to oppose the arming of the country,
but government policy caused him to
change his views. In October 1940, he
launched a campaign of civil, non-violent
resistance to participation in the war. On
July 14, 1942, Congress voted a resolution
calling on the British to quit India.
At the end of the war, negotiations were
resumed between the British authorities
and the Indian nationalists, with Gandhi
playing a decisive, though unofficial part.
On August 15, 1947, India acceded to full
Independence.
But the conflict between Hindus and
Moslems, often stifled but always latent,
flared up again at that moment with tragic
consequences.
CONTINUED ON PAGE 18
In 1942, Gandhi and other Indian
leaders were arrested for having
openly called on the British to quit
India. Gandhi's watchword
remained "non-violence", but
peaceful demonstrations by his
followers were broken up with
tear gas bombs (photo right).
HERITAGE OF NON-VIOLENCE (Continued)
16
equilibrium so magnificently expressed
by Pascal:
"Justice without might is help¬
less; might without justice is
tyrannical. We must then combine
justice and might, and for this
end make what is just strong, or
what is strong just."
What this means is that the interna¬
tional community must have an inter¬
national force worthy of the justice
it wishes to defend. But this is only
the first step towards international
Satyagraha, and only seeks to keep
violence in check rather than to elim¬
inate it. Hence we must go further
still.
General disarmament would be a
practical demonstration of non-viol¬
ence. By rejecting the possibility of
an aggressive gesture, it would short-
circuit any lurking thoughts of armed
intervention, and compel the nations
to discuss their differences. Here, the
acceleration of nuclear disarmament
would no doubt be a first step in the
right direction. But does the elimin¬
ation of the means of violence do
away with the fundamental causes of
violence? So we must go further still.
Adopting Pope Paul Vl's maxim,
"Development is the new name for
peace," could not science and tech¬
nology be pressed into service to re
duce the existing inequalities, instead
of allowing the gulf to widen and
condemning half the world to helpless
resignation? What kind of democracy
is possible in national or international
affairs with power on one side facing
misery on the other? Power is a temp¬
tation to violence, and misery a temp¬
tation to acts of desperation.
The offensive in the "new name of
peace" must now take the initiative,
and face the problem of humanity in
distress squarely and frankly. The
best brainpower of the developed
nations should be put to work drafting
appropriate plans for the future deve¬
lopment decade. We should not wait
for the shadow of world disaster to
loom over us before acting. We would
thus be forced to adopt the method of
non-violence, in order to head off the
explosion which is building up in the
"Third World" as a result of its growing
misery and poverty. And since helping
others always brings its own rewards,
the big consuming societies would
thus be delivered of the weight which
chains them to their wealth. Over-
consumption is as alienating and
dehumanizing as undernourishment
itself.
This effort which has already begun
in the United Nations (but too timidly
and often frustrated by Internal contra
dictions) would be given a new impetus
if undertaken in the name of non¬
violence. Here we are not dealing
only with the Declaration of Human
Rights or the defence of these Rights
which is severely hampered by the
jealous sovereignty of States. It would
be an "international experiment in
truth," in the Gandhian sense; a world
movement of fellowship, that is,
"Ahimsa".
Can we expect the Member States
of the United Nations to be suddenly
imbued with this spirit of non-violence?
Will the voice of Gandhi be heard
without other voices around the world
joining his? That is why it is so vital
that we have disciples of non-violence
who, while fulfilling their civic duties,
resist violence, oppose injustice and
call upon all men to transform their
own inner disarmament into an invin¬
cible shield.
There is Martin Luther King whose
life tragically recalls that of Gandhi.
He asked his followers to subscribe
to a "Commitment Blank," with its ten
commandments echoing the principles
of Ahimsa and Brahmasharya:
"2. Remember always that the
non-violent movement . . .
seeks justice and reconcilia¬
tion not victory.
5. Sacrifice personal wishes in
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
m
ÜAL L iiJU
¡à ''%
t ' r
order that all men might be
free.
6. Observe with both friend and
foe the ordinary rules of
courtesy.
9. Strive to be in good spiritual
and bodily health.
10. Follow the directions of the
movement and of the captain
on a demonstration."
Then there is Don Helder Cámara,
the Brazilian priest and leader of the
movement "Action, Justice and Peace"
who, like Martin Luther King, invokes
the Gospels to call for justice by the
principle of constructive resistance.
"Action, Justice and Peace was
not created to disarm the revolt
of the oppressed, but to help to
invest the revolt of us all, the
protest of us all, with a courag¬
eous, positive meaning, a lofty
and constructive meaning.
"Action, Justice and Peace was
not created to be an indifferent
movement, adaptable and adaptive
because we know that God abhors
the half-hearted. It aims to be,
and with the grace of God it will
be, the violence of the pacifist."
And here is Gandhi's direct disciple,
Acharia Vinoba Bhave, whose writings
and work are recorded in "The Revo¬
lution of Non-Violence",- now going
from village to village in India to win
over the rich to his "Land-gift" move¬
ment which calls for a redistribution
of land for the benefit of rural families.
In every village he has been creating
"Peace Brigades" to awaken the peo¬
ple to the need for social co-operation.
"All land, like air and water,
belongs to the Almighty. If the
land is properly distributed,
the present state of dissatisfaction
will be transformed into an age
of goodwill, of brotherly love and
co-operation."
Whether inspired by Christ or
Gandhi (who was himself deeply
influenced' by the Sermon on the
Mount and echoed its words on the
banks of the Ganges), the disciples
of non-violence emphasize the inter¬
dépendance of States and peoples,
and consider their national revolution
part of the movement of universal soli¬
darity. In a speech at Calcutta in
1925, Gandhi declared:
"For my own part, I do not want
the freedom of India if it means
extinction of England or the
disappearance of Englishmen. I
want the freedom of my country
so that other countries may learn
something from my free country,
so that the resources of my
country might be utilized for the
benefit of mankind."
This universal approach is no mere
ideal; it is upheld to be a living
experience, the result of man's Intelli¬
gence, feeling and love:
"My religion has no geographi¬
cal limits. If I have a living faith
in it, it will transcend my love for
India herself. Isolated indepen¬
dence is not the goal of the world
states. It is voluntary interde¬
pendence. There is no limit to
extending our services to our
neighbours across State-made
frontiers. God never made those
frontiers."
If we think of the man of tomorrow
homo planetarius we cannot help
recalling that Gandhi's non-violence
not only sought to break the shackles
that paralyze man but to open new
avenues for his progress:
"There is no limit to extending-
our services to our neighbours
across State-made frontiers. God
never made those frontiers."
Science overshadowed by fear is
a destructive force. Science backed
by non-violence could be creative.
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
AN EXTRAORDINARY LIFE (Continued from page 16)
8. AN ASSASSIN'S BULLET
The Moslem League would not accept
the idea of the powerful Islamic minority
about a quarter of the population being
governed by the Hindu majority.
Sick at heart, Gandhi and his companions
had to agree to the "vivisection" of the
country, and August 15, 1947, marked both
the liberation of India, vainly imagined to
be "indivisible", and its partition into two
separate nations: the Indian Union and
Pakistan.
These hopes and disappointments were
accompanied by a tragic sequence of riots,
violence and brutality. Gandhi, who had
always worked for understanding between
At 77, Gandhi went barefooted from
village to village in the regions ravaged
by conflict between Hindu and
Moslem (below).
The day of Indian independence,
Gandhi was in no mood for
jubilation. He fasted and worked for
peace between the two communities.
the two communities, was tormented by the
setback to his efforts. He would not stand
by while evil stalked the land and, although
aged 77, he set out on foot across the
areas ravaged by misery and hatred to
act as peacemaker, well knowing that his
life was a target for fanaticism.
On January 30, 1948, an extremist Hindu
who could not understand Gandhi's chival¬
rous attitude to the Moslems remaining In
the Indian Union, and regarded him as a
traitor, shot him dead. Thus Gandhi paid to
the cause of non-violence, which he
upheld as a universal ¡deal within the
reach of all, the supreme sacrifice of his
own life.
The division of India into two independent nations
in 1947 began perhaps the greatest migration of
peoples in modern history. Countless mi/lions of
refugees fled from violence, carrying their few
possessions in creaking bullock carts.
I
to
il
I
New Delhi,
January 30, 1948:
on the spot where
Gandhi has been
shot only a few
moments before,
his companion,
and Prime
Minister of India,
Jawaharlal Nehru
breaks the news
of his death to a
hushed crowd.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
a
í¿S** í
r.v'»i
Jh*
*^ ». m -** . . _ +& -* ato
I
É
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Life Magazine - Grey Villet
Before Martín Luther King organized his now famous boycott
of city buses in Montgomery, Alabama in 1956, Negroes
could only occupy rear seats in public buses and had to give
up their places to white passengers when buses were
crowded. King called for the bus boycott when a Negro
woman was arrested for refusing to yield her seat For months
on end, buses ran virtually empty (above) and Negroes
walked many miles to work (ab\ve right) rather than face
discrimination. Late In 1956 the U.S. Supreme Court declared
segregation in public transport illegal. Almost overnight,
Martin Luther King, until then a virtually unknown Negro
clergyman of Montgomery, became the foremost American
fighter for civil rights. In August 1963, his movement for racial
justice held the famous Freedom March, the largest civil
rights demonstration In U.S. history, when 200,000 black and
white marchers filled the park between the Lincoln Memorial
and the Washington Monument in the U.S. capital (below).
MARTIN LUTHER KING:
WE SHALL
OVERCOME'
Photo © Life Magazine - Robert W. Kelley
""
I
äÜ5fc ;-
m
HS
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
L,
Martin Luther King (centre of photo above) leads a 50-mile civil rights demonstration march from Selma
to Montgomery, Alabama, in 1965. On his right is Ralph Bunche of the U.N., and Nobel Peace Prize
winner. The Rev. Ralph Abernathy, who took the place of Dr. King after his assassination at Memphis
in 1968, marches on right of Bunche. Below, a huge portrait of Martin Luther King is carried by
crowd at his funeral.
.Ike Mahatma Gandhi in India, Mar¬
tin Luther King in the United States chose the
way of non-violence in his struggle against
injustice. He too urged his followers to
eschew violence at all cost under the slogan
"We shall overcome".
Martin Luther King, winner of the Nobel
Peace Prize in 1964, accepted the dangers
of non-violent resistance in his struggle for
racial equality. "The way of non-violence
means a willingness to suffer and sacrifice,"
he said. "It may mean going to jail... It
may even mean physical death. But if phy¬
sical death is the price that a man must pay
to free his children and his white brethren
from a permanent death of the spirit, then
nothing could be more redemptive." Twenty
years after Gandhi, on April 4, 1968, he too
was cut down by an assassin's bullet.
He was deeply inspired by the example of
Gandhi and expressed his indebtedness in
these words: "Before this century, virtually
all revolutions had been based on hope and
hate. The hope was expressed in the rising
expectation of freedom and justice. The hate
was an old expression of bitterness towards
the perpetrators of the old order. It was
the hate that made revolutions bloody and
violent. What was new about Mahatma
Gandhi's movement in India was that he
mounted a revolution on hope and love, hope
and non-violence. This same new emphasis
characterized the civil rights movement in our
country dating from the Montgomery bus
boycott of 1956 to the Selma movement of
1965." (See photos above.)
Martin Luther King saw his struggle as
part of a broader, universal resistance against
injustice. "The problem is not a purely racial
one, with Negroes set against whites," he
said. "In the end it is not a struggle against
people at all, but a tension between justice
and injustice. Non-violent resistance is not
aimed against oppressors but against oppres¬
sion. Under its banner consciences, not
racial groups, are enlisted."
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
THE WAY
OF BAPU
by Humayun Kabir
..lOHANDAS KARAM-
CHAND GANDHI was born at a
time when the West like a Colossus
bestrode the entire world. Not only
were western powers politically domi¬
nant, their supremacy in the economic,
cultural and intellectual fields was
equally unquestioned. India and in¬
deed the whole of Asia and Africa
suffered from the loss of political
independence, economic buoyancy and
spiritual energy.
In India, the last attempt of the
Mogul Emperor and his adherents to
revive past glory was defeated after
the revolt of 1857. Turkey was looked
upon as the sick man of Europe and
its empire was in the process of
rapid disintegration. New burdens
had been imposed upon China after
her defeat in the Opium War. Japan
had received a rude awakening from
the incursions of the emerging United
States. Russia was pushing her
frontiers into the heartlands of Asia
and pressing east and south in search
of an opening into the warm seas.
The imperialism of the western world
was active on all sides and, for the
first time in recorded history, many
Asians and Africans had begun to feel
as if there was something pre-ordained
in the supremacy of the West.
Before Gandhi died, this mood of
despondency had vanished. In its
place was a new expectancy and hope,
eager, confident and at times impatient.
All countries of Asia and Africa stirred
with a new life and claimed their
rightful place in the mansions of Man.
Not a little of the credit for this
22
HUMAYUN KABIR, the distinguished Indian
writer and educator, died in August, 1969.
Professor Kabir held several ministerial posts
in the Indian government, and was the author
of many works of philosophy, poetry and
short stories, as well as several books on
Gandhi. The article published here appears
in "Mahatma Gandhi: 100 Years", a collection
of essays published in New Delhi by the
Gandhi Peace Foundation to mark the
centenary of Gandhi's birth. Professor
Kabir's works include: "Men and Rivers",
'The Indian Heritage", "Education in New
India", "Science, Democracy and Islam", and
"Immanuel Kant".
transformation belongs to Gandhi.
He was chiefly instrumental in restoring
the self-respect of the Indian people
and making the ordinary man feel a
new sense of dignity. The awakening
of India evoked a new thrill from far-
flung regions of Asia and Africa.
Rarely has a member of a subject
nation achieved such position and
prestige in his contemporary world.
Within ten years of his death,
imperialism was everywhere on the
retreat.
Gandhi's revolutionary significance
for the world lies in his success in
releasing the energies contained in the
endurance and patience of the Indian
people. The Indian masses had sub¬
mitted to wrongs and suffered hard¬
ships against which a more active
people would have revolted long ago.
Their passivity and inertia had been
regarded as a source of weakness by
friends and foes alike. Even Indian
leaders held that the character of the
Indian masses ruled out the possibility
of an open and active revolution.
Gandhi was not blind to the
fatalism and passivity of the Indian
people but found for them a new
political function by turning them into
reserves of hidden power. Instead of
an aggressive and militant struggle,
he built up a movement of non-
co-operation in which the passivity and
endurance of the Indian masses were
turned into sources of strength and
energy. As the Indian masses moved
forward to political action, the static
forces inherent in the Indian character
became dynamic. The people regained
their self-respect and this was in
itself a restoration of the values of
spirituality.
Gandhi was one of the leaders of the
new challenge to Western domination
but did not deny the values the West
had brought to the human heritage.
The scientific revolution in Europe had
opened to man a new world of
immense possibilities. On the material
plane, it had led to an unprecedented
development in technology which
promised freedom from hunger and
disease. On the political plane, its
finest expression seemed to be
liberal democracy in the Nation State.
On the intellectual plane, it gave rise
to rationalism and held out the
hope that all human ills would be
resolved through the spread of
education. Europe was full of the
spirit of expansion, buoyancy and faith.
Wherever Europe led, the rest of the
world followed.
Gandhi recognized the contribution
of science to the solution of human ills,
but protested against the materialism
which was following in its wake. He
felt that Europe had fought for political
freedom but connived at economic
slavery of the worst type. The machine
in its simpler forms might be essential
to human well-being but the way
Europe had used machinery had
reduced men to near slaves.
GlANDHI saw that the tradi¬
tional modes of western thought had
led to a dead end and sought a way
out of the prevailing political and social
impasse through his experiments with
truth.
The abuse of the machine had
led to the concentration of wealth
and the growth of a soulless industrial
civilization. Gandhi sought an escape
from both these evils by his emphasis
on the autonomous and self-contained
village as the unit of society. In such
small units, the human relationship
between individuals cannot be ignored.
Impersonal relationships replace human
contacts when the social unit grows
so large that individuals can no longer
know each other as persons. The
stress on human relationship would on
the one hand ensure against the
danger of licence or anarchy and on
the other provide conditions for the
growth of individual freedom. The
small village community would thus
avoid the risk of dictatorship of the
State and anarchy of Statelessness.
Gandhi was keenly aware of the im¬
portance of the economic independence
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
of the individual. Without economic
independence, political independence
becomes a mockery and democracy
a mere farce. Undue concentration
of wealth undermines the economic
independence of man and yet follows
almost inevitably from large-scale
production under private proprietory
rights.
Gandhi's analysis so far is almost
the same as that of the socialists.
His solution is however very different.
The socialist remedy is based on the
elimination of private property while
retaining large-scale industrial units.
Gandhi sought the solution in the
dispersal of industry which would
automatically limit the accumulation of
wealth in the hands of individuals.
The difference in the socialist and
the Gandhian solution is not difficult
to understand. It is derived from the
difference in their attitude to the
individual.
Gandhi held the individual to be of
supreme importance. Any imposition
on his freedom was therefore to be
avoided as far as possible. Equality
which is the basis of economic
independence must therefore be
achieved through peaceful and non¬
violent methods.
Socialists hold that political liberty
may be and has often been achieved
through bloody revolution. In Gandhi's
opinion only the form but not the sub¬
stance of freedom can be achieved
in this way. The results of a violent
revolution are always liable to be lost
by a more violent counter-revolution.
Besides, those who have taken to the
sword have more often than not
perished by the sword.
It was because of his awareness of
this danger that Gandhi urged that
the economic and political freedom of
man must be attained without resort
to violence. All violence is, according
to him, born of hate and hence the
only way of resolving human conflicts
is through a conquest of hatred.
Gandhi's attitude to violence makes
his message of special significance to
the modern age. The fact that he
developed his philosophy, not by
denying current trends of thought, but
by drawing upon various elements in
them and forming a new combination
compels both attention and respect.
He was an inheritor to the liberal
tradition and regarded personal liberty
as one of the greatest values of life.
An Indian Punjabi village.
At the start of the 20th century,
80 per cent of India's population
lived in the country's
700,000 villages, which Gandhi termed,
"The true face of India."
With the philosophical anarchists he
believed that the State should interfere
as little as possible with the individual.
He also believed in the tradition of
collectivization inherent in socialist
thought.
He imbibed all these teachings but
gave a new turn to everything he
learnt. He believed in personal liberty
but felt that rights accrue only from
the performance of duties. He was in
favour of decentralization but not in
favour of the abolition of the State.
He pleaded that the good things of life
must be shared but he was not
prepared to advocate the use of
violence for achieving this end.
Religious teachers have from the
earliest times preached that man
cannot live by hate. Practice of non
violence has however in the past been
mainly the concern of the individual.
Gandhi for the first time showed the
efficacy of non-violent action by groups.
He was a successful politician and
cannot be dismissed as a visionary.
His advocacy of non-violence as an
instrument of political action has
therefore aroused interest throughout
the world and made the most diverse
groups attempt to use it for solving
their problems.
Technology has unified the world
today by overcoming the barriers
created by time and space. In ancient
times an idea could travel only as fast
as man could move. Till the middle
of the last century, this could not be
more than two hundred miles a day.
Today a man can go round the world
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
THE SAGE
OF THE
SPINNING
WHEEL
In the context of his efforts
to improve conditions in the
villages of India, Gandhi is
perhaps best known (and has
often been criticized) for his
cult of the spinning wheel.
For Gandhi, hunger took pri¬
ority over independence, and
the aim of his campaign to
revive hand spinning and
hand weaving was to put
bread Into the mouths of
millions of landless farmers.
These neglected crafts reviv¬
ed and transformed hundreds
of villages. At the same
time, the boycott of foreign
fabrics, which he urged, gave
India greater autonomy over
its own production of cotton.
Gandhi himself set the exam¬
ple by spinning for several
hours each day, even while
In prison. Left, Gandhi seat¬
ed beside his spinning wheel,
which he regarded as a sym¬
bolic bond between all who
practised the craft and a
means to self-reliance and
self-respect. It Is often stat¬
ed that Gandhi was opposed
to mechanization and indus¬
trialization, but this Is not
completely true. In 1921, he
wrote: "I would favour the
use of the most elaborate
machinery if thereby. . . pau¬
perism and resulting Idleness
be avoided."
Photo Margaret Bourke-White, Life Magazine © Time Inc
24
THE WAY OF BAPU (Continued)
in less than two hours. An idea can
be flashed simultaneously throughout
the world. Even twenty years ago all
these were beyond the scope of man's
wildest imagination.
Mountains and oceans no longer
divide man. He travels over both and
launches into outer space. Technolo¬
gical unification of the world demands
economic, political and cultural unity.
Such unity can however be achieved
only by safeguarding the diversity and
autonomy of the constituent units.
Modern technology has created
conditions where war can and must be
discarded. In ancient times, nations
fought one another for pastures and
living room. Later they fought one
another for raw materials and markets.
They lived under a constant fear that
without political control over territories,
they would face starvation and death.
The development of science and
technology has for the first time
eliminated that fear. Today everybody
can be assured the necessities of life.
This is feasible provided the energies
of man are directed to productive ends
and the wealth so produced distributed
equitably among all members of
mankind.
Conflict or war for assuring survival
is therefore no longer necessary. On
the contrary war today threatens the
very existence of man. Weapons of
destruction have been fashioned which
can destroy not only the warring
parties but the entire world. The
U.S.A. and the U.S.S.R. have enough
atomic weapons to destroy themselves
and everybody else. Today, any
large-scale war may become global
and lead to the annihilation of man.
Science and technology have created
conditions where mankind must feel
and act as one or perish.
Major powers have withdrawn from
the brink time and again because of
their realization that a full-scale global
war will destroy mankind. There is
today a balance of terror which
maintains an uneasy peace.
This is some gain but there is still
lack of realization that violence within
the community may pose an equal
threat. One reason is that no
internal conflict today remains wholly
internal. There are so many affilia¬
tions within and among nations that
an internal conflict in one place may
and does attract interference from
outside.
The Spanish civil war began, as a
conflict between two Spanish groups
but soon developed into a rehearsal
for the second world war because of
intervention by major powers. Vietnam
is a cruel reminder that great nations
cannot refrain from interfering in the
affairs of less powerful states. In
western Asia, the problems can be
resolved if the Great Powers do not
intervene. There can thus be no
assurance for the future unless
violence, internal and international, is
eliminated.
Human conflicts began when Cain
repudiated his responsibility for his
brother. Today the logic of events
has compelled an increasing number
of men and women throughout the
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Bern, Paris - Rune Hassner
world to realize that everyone must
accept responsibility for everyone else.
Gandhi's major contribution is an
attempt to put into practice non-violent
programmes for fighting evil. Even
politicians who are averse to the use
of force do not generally rule it out
as an instrument of policy. Gandhi
declared that the method of persuasion,
whether in internal or external affairs,
is the only human and civilized way
open to man. He wanted to rule out
resort to physical force and substitute
in its place the use of moral pressure.
The essence of his method is non¬
violent resistance to evil. He believed
that this must begin with action by
the individual to influence other indivi¬
duals. Such a programme would ease
tensions both within an individual and
among individuals.
International tensions are very often
the reflection of intra-national tensions
just as tensions within society are often
due to tensions within the individual.
Every individual who resolves his in¬
ternal tensions becomes an integrated
personality. He then becomes a
dynamo of power and radiates energy.
Gandhi's answer to the problem of
violence, internal and international,
was to train a body of men and women
who would have no internal tensions
and would help to resolve tensions
within society. Once tensions within
society are reduced, international
tensions will automatically diminish.
Searching for causes, Gandhi
concluded that injustice and inequality
among individuals and nations are the
basic causes of tensions and hatred.
The State seeks to reduce causes of
internal tension by assuring equality
of all in the eye of law. Progressive
taxation to reduce inequalities in wealth
is intended to serve the same purpose.
The growing contacts among nations
demand the application of similar
methods to ensure justice and reduce
glaring inequalities. It is a paradox
of the modern age that the more the
world is coming together through
technological advances, the more
barriers are being set up by Nation
States to prevent the free intercourse
of men.
The world is irresistibly impelled
towards unity today but two conditions
must be satisfied before a world order
can emerge. The first is the guarantee
of full cultural autonomy and freedom
to even the smallest constituent unit
of mankind. One of the most fascinat¬
ing developments in the last fifty years
has been the emergence of giant
powers accompanied by an insistent
demand for greater autonomy by
smaller and smaller constituent units.
The second condition is the creation
of a body of enlightened opinion
throughout the world. Civil authority
gained in power as its impartiality was
increasingly recognized. The world
authority will also acquire greater
acceptance by assuring justice and
equitable consideration for all.
Gandhi was a revolutionary who
sought to transform human nature
itself. He was also a realist and knew
that people would judge his recipes by
their results. He therefore began
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE WAY OF BAPU (Continued)
with the individual and sought to
change him first. He believed that the
smallest beginning may lead to the
most far-reaching consequences.
Gandhi's technique is therefore
suited for operation by small groups
and through programmes,. which are
initially modest. He rejected the
theory that ends justify the means and
believed that the means are just as
important as the end. When the
individual acts according to this
principle he achieves not only personal
excellence but also changes the course
of history by adoption of pure methods.
The supreme example of Gandhi's
faith in non-violence and the im¬
portance of the individual is found in
his own thought and action in the last
days of his life.
The years 1937-47 were years of
stress and strain in India. As political
independence drew nearer, the clashes
of interest among different sections
of the people reached a new intensity.
India became free, but at the cost of
her unity. The transition to freedom
was marked by violence and murder
on a large scale.
Gandhi stood firm against the rising
tide of communal bitterness and
passion. After helping to assuage
tempers at first in Noakhali and then
in Bihar and Calcutta, he came to
Delhi where communal riots had
broken out in the aftermath of the
partition of India.
26
ITH characteristic courage,
Gandhi faced the fury of the mob and
preached the message of reconciliation
and friendship. His prayer meetings
became a source of strength and
solace to countless men and women
in the capital and outside.
Passions had become so inflamed
that some misguided men tried to
prevent these meetings but in spite of
opposition, threats and attacks he
continued fearlessly. There had been
a murderous attack on him in Calcutta
In September 1947. There were
further attacks in Delhi and continuing
threats. Nothing however could daunt
him. With exemplary courage and
patience, he pursued his chosen path
of understanding, compassion and
brotherhood.
There was a stamp of greatness on
everything he did from the time he
opposed tyranny in South Africa, but
perhaps even Gandhi had never
reached the heights he achieved in
his last six months. A new sweetness
and strength welled out of all his
words and action. Everyone who came
in contact with him came away a purer
and better man.
ONE OF
KARL JASPERS'
LAST
COMMENTARIES:
GANDHIJI
by Karl Jaspers
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
IT was not by force of arms
but by non-violence founded on right
that Gandhi liberated India from British
rule. His action was political inas¬
much as he had to deal with the
authorities in power, but his politics
took an approach of unprecedented
character.
In a world which made a pretence
of living according to right and morali¬
ty, Gandhi tore off the mask of
hypocrisy. He focussed attention on
the sway of violence in society not
only in his analytical writings (others
had done so long before him) but
above all in his daily life by exposing
himself to violence and openly suffer¬
ing under it.
Gandhi's strength lay in his readi¬
ness to endure all the consequences
of his actions from the ruling author¬
ities and in his ability to instil this
readiness to suffer in the Indian
masses. He amazed the world and
inspired the Indian people by his
unwavering method of non-violent
struggle against violence.
Gandhi was a man who sought to
achieve the impossible: politics based
on non-violence. His success was
extraordinary. Did the impossible thus
become possible?
Gandhi repudiated all physical
violence. Imprisoned many times dur¬
ing his lifetime, his very life threatened,
he finally died the victim of assassin¬
ation. But was he opposed to all
forms of violence? This, I think, is the
fundamental point. As sincere and
explicit as Gandhi was when he declar¬
ed that he wanted to convince his op¬
ponents, convert them and reach
agreement with them, in point of fact
he deliberately had recourse to moral
compulsion. His personal capacity
for suffering, with its tremendous
Left, all the worldly possessions left
by Gandhi, "the Great Soul in beggar's
garb", as the poet Tagore once called
him: dinner bowls, wooden fork and spoon,
three porcelain monkeys, his diary,
prayer-book, watch, spittoon, paper knives
and two pairs of sandals. They are kept
in the house in New Delhi in the garden
of which Gandhi met his death.
repercussions on the endurance of
the Indian people, itself became a form
"violence" which ultimately drove the
of English out of India.
We are reminded of the ancient
Indian theory of the power of ascetics.
By the unparalleled self-mortification
they inflicted upon themselves, they
accumulated a magic power which
gave them mastery over all things.
Even the gods feared the power of
these ascetics.
The self-discipline which Gandhi im¬
posed upon himself was no doubt the
result of a kind of violence exercised
on his inner self. But this self-violence
or compulsion is not limited only to
oneself, for he who inflicts violence
on himself is equally prepared to have
it apply to others. For Gandhi, the
force of moral pressure is one of the
factors of action and accounts for
no small part of the response he
achieved.
If Gandhi's method of non-violence
could not actually do away with
violence but only shift it elsewhere,
he nevertheless achieved his political
success without physical violence even
though a few individual followers of
his resorted to a minimum of physical
violence which he disapproved of.
Did not Gandhi thus discover a
political method by which right can
overcome might? To grasp the full
import of this success we must under¬
stand what makes it such a unique and
remarkable experience.
History teaches us that obedience
can indeed be achieved by exterminat¬
ing other men and spreading destruc¬
tion, as the Athenians did at Samos,
the Romans in Palestine, the medieval
Church in Provence and Cromwell in
Ireland. Whenever it is exercised with¬
out restraint or scruple, power turns
absolute, be it by deliberate policy or
in the name of divine revelation.
People who were once proud of their
freedoms find themselves swept away
by this tyranny.
On the paramount question how far
is a ruling power prepared to go when
its authority is gravely threatened, the
English had their answer ready: better
get out than resort to terror. Gandhi
was always free to speak in public.
Even when he was jailed he was
allowed to act. English liberality and
their concept of legal rights made it
possible for Gandhi to develop the
full scope of his activities. Thus Gan¬
dhi's accomplishments owe as much
if not more to the English approach
to politics as they do to Gandhi's own
ideas.
But the extraordinary fact remains
unique perhaps in history that here
was a man who created an instrument
of political action from an idea that
transcends politics, and whose entire
life was a constant illustration of this
conviction.
Gandhi was the theoretician of his
own action. His politics is rooted in
religious principles transcending poli
tics. It is grounded in the action of
the inner self which leads to Satya¬
graha, the tenacious clinging to Being,
to Truth. Gandhi himself set the
example of this principle. Outward
resistance must stem from the active
power of Love, Faith and Sacri¬
fice. The person who lives by Satya¬
graha must adhere to Truth, Chastity,
Courage, Will to Sacrifice. He must
cheerfully accept all suffering inflicted
upon him, not passively, but as a
"Warrior of Truth". The Satyagrahi
practices mental and spiritual discipline
just as the body is exercised in the
handling of weapons. He lives in
self-purification.
GlANDHI also differed from
the holy ascetics in that all his life was
a permanent search, a never-ending
quest for self-purification with an
awareness of his own guilt. He
scorned all efforts tending to make of
him a saint, and this became one of the
great preoccupations of his life as he
strove to resist the tide of Indian
darshan-seekers who wished to deify
him. Such misrepresentation, he felt,
could only hurt the cause he sought to
advance.
By his spirit of self-sacrifice he
showed that a "supra-political" idea
could be converted into a force for
political action. Here lies the great¬
ness of Gandhi in our times. For him,
politics was not only inseparable from
ethics and religion but was constantly
and totally nurtured by them: Better
to die, better to let "an entire people
be wiped off the map" than to sacrifice
the purity of the soul.
Gandhi has become the unique
example in our day of the moral and
religious politics of the man who lives
for undisguised truth. Humiliated in
South Africa because of his race, in¬
spired by his Indian origins though
educated in England, this man was
driven by his love for a free India
which would regain its dignity, by a
readiness for suffering and a spirit of
unlimited sacrifice. At the same time,
he never lost that feeling of inner guilt
which is the spark which spurs one
on to greater determination.
Today we face the question: how
can we escape from physical violence
and war, and avoid the holocaust of
nuclear weapons? Gandhi, through his
action and words, has given us the
true answer: only political values that
transcend politics itself can provide the
force that will save us. It is inspir¬
ing that this answer is offered us today
by an Asian.
KARL JASPERS, born at Oldenburg, Germany
in 1883, was one of the great philosophers
of modern times. His work, spanning almost
three-quarters of a century, has had a
profound influence on contemporary thinking.
He died at Basel, Switzerland in February,
1969. The article above is one of the last
he wrote and appears m "Mahatma Gandhi:
100 Years".
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
GANDHI
ON STUDENTS
AND POLITICS
by Malcolm 5. Adiseshiah
Deputy Director-General of Unesco
GjANDHI's views on politics
in educational institutions are a subject
which is topical for India and all mem¬
ber countries of Unesco. It is the
burning issue today in all countries.
In one year alone, the college year
1967-1968, there were student riots
and student uprisings in 56 out of 80
of Unesco's member countries which
have universities. (The other 45 do not
as yet have universities.)
1 would summarize Gandhiji's views
on the subject of politics in educational
institutions under four slogans:
Educational institutions are political
institutions;
Educational institutions must parti¬
cipate in moments of national poli¬
tical crisis;
Educational institutions must not
participate in party politics;
Educational institutions must be¬
come educational institutions.
Educational institutions
are political institutions
The ancient aphorism, education is
that which liberates, is as true today
as it was before, wrote Gandhiji in the
March 10, 1946 issue of Harijan. This
comment possibly best summarizes his
view with regard to politics in educa¬
tional institutions. For him, educa¬
tion was training of all kinds, starting
28
MALCOLM S. ADISESHIAH is Deputy Di¬
rector-General of Unesco, which he ¡oined in
1948. Born in the State of Madras, he was
educated in India and Great Britain.
Before joining Unesco, he headed the Depart¬
ment of Economics at the University of
Madras and had been lecturer in economics
at the University of Calcutta. At Unesco he
has been especially concerned with problems
of economic development in Asia, Africa and
Latin America.
with the training of one's own charac¬
ter, with a view to serving mankind.
Equally, liberation meant freedom from
all forms and shades of servitude
internal and external.
If politics is the art of serving man¬
kind with a view to its attaining the
rights and freedoms which later came
to be enshrined in India's constitution
and in the United Nations Charter
namely, the universal respect for and
observance of human rights and funda¬
mental freedoms for all without dis¬
tinction as to race, sex, language or
religion, then educational institutions
are political institutions, in an etymo¬
logical sense.
Schools and colleges educate their
members, students and teachers, in
the science and art of liberation. Edu¬
cation is the science, liberation is the
art. Education is learning and training,
liberation is eradicating and freeing.
In educational institutions, a member
learns about himself and the world
around him and acts on liberating from
enslavement himself and all those
around him, who are similarly enslav¬
ed. In this sense, Gandhiji visualized
educational institutions as political in¬
stitutions, in the highest sense of the
political vocation.
Educational institutions
must participate in moments
of national political crisis
In the heyday of non-co-operation,
students and teachers were invited to
leave their schools and colleges. Some
professors and students who respond¬
ed to the Congress call have remained
steadfast and gained much for the
country and themselves, wrote Gan¬
dhiji in his revised issue of the con¬
structive programme which he first set
forth in 1941, and finally published
from Poona on November 13, 1945. In
the life of a nation, there are the rare
but awesome moments of national cri¬
sis, demonstrated in India when Gan¬
dhiji and the Congress called on
students and teachers to leave their
educational institutions to participate,
in the national struggle.
Occasions like the present do not
occur in everybody's and but rarely in
anybody's life, he said, addressing the
All-India Congress Committee at its
Bombay session in 1942, on the eve
of its adoption of the Quit India reso¬
lution addressed to the British. Here
is the mantra that I give you: Do or
Die. In all fights for freedom the
world over the students have made
very large contributions, he said.
At these moments of a nation's life
and death, politics becomes charged
with a sacred mission, and is the staff
of all life everywhere in society.
Educational institutions being in so¬
ciety, participate in and partake of
the politicization at these times of all
of social, public and private life. Such
participation must always conform to
the twin absolutes of Satya and Ahim¬
sa (1). There is no place for Himsa (2)
of any kind in the deep and total in¬
volvement of the student and teacher
in the national movement. When the
final heat of the struggle comes,
declared Gandhiji, students and
teachers will leave their institutions
and if need be, sacrifice themselves
for the freedom of their country. Such
sacrifice is total because it is non¬
violent.
Gandhiji expressed in the same
Poona statement his deep regret at
any form of non-participation of educa¬
tional institutions in these moments
of national political crisis. He traced
such non-response to the false and
unnatural lure offered its members by
current education. In so inviting edu¬
cational institutions to play their part
in national political crisis, Gandhiji was
in effect not denying to the students
and teachers what Harold Laski terms
the ultimate right of every citizen
the right to revolt. This ultimate and
precarious responsibility which every
individual citizen carries but carries
only as an individual citizen, not as a
teacher or a student, is for each per¬
son, in his solemn moment of solitude,
a matter of personal conscience.
And conscience is a tricky thing.
(1) Truth and non-violence. (2) Violence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
While it could gird us with courage,
it could equally make cowards of us
all. It might lead us to say, with
Gandhiji: leave me to God and chaos;
or it might equally lead us to declare
with him that we might be committing
a Himalayan blunder. On no account,
however, warned Gandhiji, may they
(the participants) use coercion against
dissenters or against the authorities.
Ahimsa is the mark of political parti¬
cipation when it emanates from the
conscience.
Educational institutions
must not participate in
party politics
Students must not take part in party
politics, Gandhi said. They are
students, searchers, not politicians.
They may not resort to political strikes,
They must have their heroes but their
devotion to them is to be shown by
copying the best in their heroes not
by going on strikes, wrote Gandhiji
in no uncertain terms in that same
constructive programme of November
1945, on the question of the involve¬
ment of educational institutions in day-
to-day politics.
This directive is quite unambiguous
and seems to speak directly to the
members of educational Institutions to¬
day who go on strike, march in pro¬
cessions, burn trams and buses, stone
railway trains and injure helpless old
men, women and children travelling
on them. These political demonstra¬
tions of students and some teachers
are said to be a protest to language,
State boundaries or other party poli¬
tical issues.
Should educational institutions and
their members be involved in this kind
of party not national political activi¬
ties, with their invariable accompani¬
ment of violence? Gandhiji's answer
is a clear and resounding NO. My
own answer when I was a member
of the University of Madras was NO,
and my answer now as a Unescan is
still NO.
Active political involvement and par¬
ticipation in day-to-day political life is
not the function of schools and col¬
leges. These institutions have not
been created for that purpose. They
have no specialized competence or
vocation in the field of political action.
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
Photo © H Cartie'-Bresson Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
30
STUDENTS AND POLITICS (Continued)
As Gandhiji pointed out, the func¬
tions of schools and colleges are
essentially learning: their members are
seekers and searchers after truth, in
the process of learning the qualities of
tolerance, compassion, equality and
justice. How can you seek and search
for truth, when you march around in
processions shouting slogans? How
can you learn tolerance when you
carry a knife or a steel tipped stick
at demonstrations and stab your
opponent? How can you become
compassionate when you spend the
day halting trains and stoning their
helpless passengers? How can you
learn equality if your school, or college
strike formula is based on the con¬
viction that while all Indians may be
equal, you are more equal than those
who refuse to strike or are from an¬
other State, language or political
group ? Where is the concept of
justice that you are imbibing leading
you, when you set fire to other people's
property, buses, trams and houses?
I S it not precisely to enable
colleges and schools and their members
to carry on their functions as seekers
of truth and learners of the human
values that they are in this country and
in all countries endowed with special
privileges and an autonomy of thought
and action at this formative stage of
the school and college life of the
student? Is one evidence of this
truth, when it is contravened through
students participation in party politics,
not found in the fact that such parti¬
cipation is almost always marked by
violence and counter-violence?
I realize how difficult inaction is at
school and college, when one is im¬
bibing the tenets of truth and personal
integrity and sees corruption and
falsehood all around: when one's head
is filled with concepts of justice and
sees only injustice around; when the
classics on freedom are being studied
while at the same time various forms
of petty tyranny in government munici¬
palities and village councils are at
play all around; when the absolute of
non-violence which is uncompromising¬
ly proclaimed confronts what Herbert
Marcuse calls our basically totalitarian
society which employs subtle tech¬
niques of violence on "the outsiders",
among whom are the students.
For one thing party political man¬
oeuvres rarely relate to these values.
For another, there is no alternative for
the student and teacher. They are like
the astronauts and cosmonauts, only
in an even more critical position. They
must be involved in their training fully.
Gandhiji felt that this may require
an additional one year in college.
They must be soaked and fitted to
the last Inch in the process of learning
and in the ability to think for them¬
selves.
This they need in order to face all
contingencies in life, if disaster to
themselves and even more to the mil¬
lions who will come to depend on
them in the future is to be averted.
That is the price of the privileged
position of educational institutions
discipline, which is at the same time
a call for patient learning and intensive
self-education.
Let me make clear that I am not
trying to divorce education from the
community, to make colleges and edu¬
cational institutions ivory tower in¬
stitutions living apart from social and
national realities. Nor am I suggest¬
ing that all learning takes place only
at school and college. All I am saying
is that the learning process starts
where it is supposed to in education¬
al institutions.
Society today involves education In
a profound crisis both in concepts
and systems. In terms of concepts,
education is not conforming to what
you read or are taught but learning
to think for yourself which is the
basis of divergence and dialogue; not
learning to conform but learning how
to disagree and debate in a civilized
manner.
In educational institutions, we can
apply this concept of learning on a
full-time basis. In terms of systems,
its inherited assumption that life can
be divided into two stages that of
acquiring knowledge (as in filling a
storage tank) and that of giving it out
(as when the storage tank taps are
opened), is now shown to be false.
Equally false is the hope that by
emptying the taps at school and col¬
lege, we can fill them later In life.
Education is no longer preparation
for life. It is part of life. Education
is no longer the gateway to society.
It Is the centre of society. Education
cannot be grounded in national realities
only, if they are nostalgic rather than
prospective. Education and work are
no longer in conflict: work and life
no longer devour each other. All work
and no play does not make Jack
a dull boy. Education is work: it is
part of working time and production.
Education is play: it is the coming
life of leisure.
This means that we can neglect
learning at any stage of life only at
our peril. To waste the early years of
school life playing politics involves
learning which will have to be un¬
learned later. For learning ¡s a con¬
tinuous and continuing process. One
is always learning something, the three
Rs or vocational skills, human values,
or inhuman desires, self-education or
mis-education. One can be busy with
good works or idle as the Devil's
workshop.
To neglect the discipline of learning
to think and reason while at school in
favour of party political activities in
the hope of acquiring such learning in
later life is to turn adult life from
a full, rich life of learning into a vast
psychiatric ward, a sad correctional
educational Institution, a kind of moral
and spiritual jail. If such are the issues
GANDHI'S
VIEWS
ON
EDUCATION
at stake, then educational institutions
cannot afford the luxury of becoming
the playboy or plaything of party po¬
litics.
Educational institutions
must become educational
institutions
But this Gandhian prohibition of
party politics entering educational in¬
stitutions is posited on a certain and
definite view of schools and colleges
I refer now to some of his educa¬
tional obiter dicta. Education does not
mean a knowledge of letters but it
means character building it means a
knowledge of Dharma (1), he wrote
on March 25, 1939. A student means
one who is hungry for learning learn¬
ing is knowledge of what is worth
knowing about. Persistent question¬
ing and healthy inquisitiveness are
the first requisites for acquiring learn¬
ing of any kind. Education must be
a new type for the creation of a new
world. I would revolutionize college
education and relate it to national
necessities. The aim of university
(1) Duty.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
In my opinion what we have reason to deplore and be
ashamed of is not so much illiteracy as ignorance. This is
not to say that I would not provide a knowledge of the
alphabet. I value it too much to despise or even belittle
its merit as a vehicle of education.
The primary need of those who are come of age and are
following an avocation, is to know how to read and write.
Mass illiteracy is India's sin and shame and must be liqui¬
dated. Of course the literacy campaign must not begin
and end with a knowledge of the alphabet. It must go
hand in hand with the spread of useful knowledge.
The old idea was to add a handicraft to the ordinary
curriculum of education followed in the schools. That is
to say, the craft was to be taken in hand wholly separate
from education. To me that seems a fatal mistake. The
teacher must learn the craft and correlate his knowledge
to the craft, so that he will impart all that knowledge to
his pupils through the medium of the particular craft that
he chooses.
Take the instance of spinning. Unless I know arithme¬
tic I cannot report how many yards of yarn I have produced
on the "takli,", or how many standard rounds it will make
or what is the count of the yarn that I have spun. I must
learn figures to be able to do so, and I also must learn
addition and subtraction and multiplication and division.
In dealing with complicated sums I shall have to use sym¬
bols and so get my algebra. Even here I would insist on
the use of Hindustani letters instead of Roman.
Take geometry next. What can be a better demonstration
of the circle than the disc of the takli? I can teach all
about the circle in this way, without even mentioning the
name of Euclid.
Again, you may ask how can I teach my child geogra¬
phy and history through spinning. Some time ago I came
across a book called "Cotton - The Story of Mankind". It
thrilled me. It read like a romance. It began with the
history of ancient times, how and when cotton was first
grown, the stages of its development, the cotton trade
between the different countries and so on.
As I mention the different countries to the child, I shall
naturally tell him something about the history and geo¬
graphy of these countries. Under whose reign the differ¬
ent commercial treaties were signed during the different
periods. Why has cotton to be imported by some coun¬
tries and cloth by others? Why can every country not
grow the cotton it requires? That will lead me into eco¬
nomics and elements of agriculture. I shall teach him to
know the different varieties of cotton, in what kind of soil
they grow, how to grow them, from where to get them,
and so on.
Thus takli spinning leads me into the whole history of
the East India Company, what brought them here, how
they destroyed our spinning industry, how the economic
motive that brought them to India led them later to enter¬
tain political aspirations, how it became a causative factor
in the downfall of the Moguls and the Marathas, in the
establishment of the English Raj, and then again in the
awakening of the masses in our times. There is thus no
end to the educative possibilities of this new scheme. And
how much quicker the child will learn all that, without putting
an unnecessary tax on his mind and memory.
I am elaborating the instance of spinning because I know
it. If I were a carpenter, I would teach my child all these
things through carpentry.
What we need is educationists with originality, fired
with true zeal, who will think out from day to day what
they are going to teach their pupils. The teacher cannot
get this knowledge through musty volumes. He has to
use his own faculties of observation and thinking and
impart his knowledge to the children through his lips,
with the help of a craft. This means a revolution in the
method of teaching, a revolution in the teacher's outlook.
Why should a child waste seven years on learning a
craft when his real profession is going to be something
else, e.g. why should a banker's son, who is expected to
take to banking later on, learn spinning for seven years?
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
education should be to turn out true
servants of the people who will live
and die for the country's freedom,
wrote Gandhiji in Harijan on July 31,
1937.
I cannot help contrasting the Gand-
hian doctrine of education with India's
educational system today. Not that
Gandhiji was unaware of the defects of
education in his day. Writing in the
Hind Swaraj in December 1939, Gand¬
hiji concludes somewhat drastically
that whether you take elementary
education or higher education, it is
not required, in so far as it does not
make men of us. It does not enable
us to do our duty, he said.
Gandhi laid repeated emphasis on
duty, on Dharma, as the purpose of
education. In fact when Unesco invit¬
ed him in 1947 to define human rights,
he replied in a letter dated May 25,
1947, written from Bhangi Colony, New
Delhi: "I learned from my illiterate but
wise mother that all rights to be
deserved and preserved come from
duty well done."
And today India's educational insti¬
tutions seem to have slipped further
down the ladder of mediocrity and
futility. Wastages, drop-outs, repeat-
ings and inefficiencies seem to be their
hallmark. Repetitious, uninspired teach¬
ing, prescriptions of predigested and
erroneous bazaar notes as texts, over¬
crowded classrooms and lack of time
for reflecting and for what Gandhi
called inquisitive questioning with the
resultant cramming as the learning
technique have become a part of In¬
dia's schools and colleges.
The examination systems inhibit
thought (one university professor told
me recently that no student who ever
tries to think in an examination hall
will ever complete his paper) and act
as superficial classification machines.
There is also the lack of relation be¬
tween what is taught and learnt in the
college and the four-fold educational
ideal repeatedly stressed by Gandhiji,
the search for truth, the doing of
one's duty, the building of character
and the meeting of the national de¬
mands for development. Here the
spectre of educated unemployment
haunts the final year student.
Add to all this the moral confusion
and material corruption which seem to
be creeping into educational adminis¬
tration crowned by an atmosphere of
terrible boredom and horrible unreality.
Is this a fair picture of educational
institutions?
If it is so even in part, then is
it surprising that schools and colleges
instead of being centres of living to
learn together and learning to live
together are becoming the seed-bed of
student revolt and student violence?
Is it surprising then that day-to-day,
partisan and party politics are now
part of educational institutions? Is it
not then time that we instantly and
urgently implement the recommenda¬
tions of the Education Commission,
which are aimed at reforming and re¬
structuring India's education system
and providing machinery for all
student grievances so that they may
be examined fairly and met fully?
And so, is not the Gandhian call
more insistent and more relevant to¬
day than ever if our life, personal
and State, social and national, uni¬
versal and International, is not to be
completely lost In chaos and destruc¬
tion so that India's schools become
once more institutions of learning and
its colleges and universities become
once again centres for the pursuit of
truth and the promotion of develop¬
ment? Is it not then time to begin?
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
GANDHIS VIEWS ON EDUCATION (Continued)
The boy under the scheme of basic education does not
go to school merely to learn a craft. He goes there to
receive his primary education to train his mind through
the craft. I claim that the boy who has gone through the
new course of primary education for seven years, will make a
better banker than the one who has gone through the seven
years of ordinary schooling. The latter when he goes to a
banking school will be ill at ease because all his faculties will
not have been trained.
Prejudices die hard. I will have done a good day's
work if I have made you realize this one central fact that
the new education scheme is not a little of literary edu¬
cation and a little of craft It is full education up to the
primary stage through the medium of a craft. Therefore,
to go back to what I began with, if the teacher takes up
the craft in a scientific spirit, he will speak to his pupils
through many channels, all of which will contribute to the
development of all his faculties.
Useful, manual labour, intelligently performed, is
the means par excellence for developing the intellect A
balanced intellect presupposes a harmonious growth of
body, mind and soul. That is why we give to manual
labour the central place in our curriculum of training here.
Character building has the first place, and that is
primary education. A building erected on that foundation
will last.
True education of the intellect can only come through
the intelligent use of the body ... for the development
of the mind and body must go hand in hand with a cor¬
responding awakening of the soul; by spiritual learning
I mean the education of the heart.
I would revolutionize college education and relate it to
national necessities. There would be degrees for mechan¬
ical and other engineers. They would be attached to the
different industries which should pay for the training of
the graduates they need.
I am a firm believer in the principle of free and com¬
pulsory primary education for India. I also hold that we
shall realize this only by teaching the children a useful
vocation and utilizing it as a means for cultivating their
mental, physical and spiritual faculties. Let no one con¬
sider these economic calculations in connexion with educ¬
ation, as sordid, or out of place.
But as a nation we are so backward in education that
we cannot hope to fulfil our obligations to the nation in this
respect in the given time during this generation, if the
programme is to depend on money. I have therefore
made bold, even at the risk of losing all reputation for con¬
structive ability, to suggest that education should be self-
supporting.
There is nothing essentially sordid about economic cal¬
culations. True economics never militates against the
highest ethical standard, just as all true ethics to be
worth its name must at the same time be also good econo¬
mics. An economics that inculcates Mamman-worship,
and enables the strong to amass wealth at the expense
of the weak, is a false and dismal science. True economics,
on the other hand, stands for social justice, it promotes
the good of all equally, including the weakest, and is
indispensable for decent life.
32
Whatever may be true of other countries, in India at
any rate where more than eighty per cent of the population
is agricultural and another ten per cent industrial, it is a
crime to make education merely literary, and to unfit
boys and girls for manual work in later life. Indeed,
I hold that as the larger part of our time is devoted to
labour for earning our bread, our children must from their
infancy be taught the dignity of such labour.
Our children should not be so taught as to despise
labour. There is no reason why a peasant's son after hav¬
ing gone to a school should become useless, as he does
become, as an agricultural labourer. It is a sad thing that
our schoolboys look upon manual labour with disfavour,
if not contempt.
What kinds of vocations are the fittest for being taught
to children in urban schools? There is no hard and fast
rule about it. But my reply is clear.
You cannot instruct the teachers in the needs of villagers
through a training school in a city. Nor can you so inter¬
est them in the condition of villages. To interest city-
dwellers in villages and make them live in them is no
easy task. I am finding daily confirmation of this.
Then as to primary education, my confirmed opinion is
that the commencement of training by teaching the alphabet
and reading and writing hampers their intellectual growth.
I would not teach them the alphabet till they have had
an elementary knowledge of history, geography, mental
arithmetic and the art (say) of spinning. Through these
three I should develop their intelligence.
The question may be asked how intelligence can be
developed through the takli or the spinning-wheel. It can
to a marvellous degree if it is not taught merely mechanical¬
ly. When you tell a child the reason for each process,
when you explain the mechanism of the takli or the wheel,
when you give him the history of cotton and its con¬
nexion with civilization itself and take him to the village
field where it is grown, and teach him to count the
rounds he spins and the method of finding the evenness
and strength of his yarn, you hold his interest and simul¬
taneously train his hands, his eyes and his mind.
This method does not exclude a knowledge of history and
geography. But I find that this is best taught by transmit¬
ting such general information by word of mouth. One
imparts ten times as much in this manner as by reading and
writing. The signs of the alphabet may be taught later
when the pupil has learnt to distinguish the wheat from
the chaff and when he has somewhat developed his or
her tastes. This is a revolutionary proposal but it saves
immense labour and enables a student to acquire in one
year what he may take much longer to learn. This means
all-round economy. Of course the pupil learns mathe¬
matics whilst he is learning his handicraft.
I am not opposed to education even of the highest
type attainable in the world.
The State must pay for it wherever it has definite use
for it.
I am opposed to all higher education being paid for from
the general revenue.
It is my firm conviction that the vast amount of the so-
called education in arts, given in our colleges, is sheer
waste and has resulted in unemployment among the educat¬
ed classes.
I claim that I am not an enemy of higher education.
But I am an enemy of higher education as it is given in this
country. Under my scheme there will be more and better
libraries, more and better laboratories, more and better
research institutes. Under it we should have an army of
chemists, engineers and other experts who would be real
servants of the nation, and answer the varied and grow¬
ing requirements of a people who are becoming increasing¬
ly conscious of their rights and wants.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
LEARNING JOB FOR LIFE
Sir,
Nowadays, with human knowledge
expanding at an incredible pace, self-
education has become a continuing
process throughout life. As a Chinese
proverb puts it: "Studying is like rowing
against the current. If you stop rowing
you are carried backwards."
That is why I was drawn to the
"Unesco Courier", which is as good
as an encyclopaedia and to my mind
one of the best magazines published
in Russian.
Here are some suggestions for
future issues which I think would
interest readers: Important world pri¬
zes, including the Nobel Prizes and
some of their winners; Outstanding
women of the world; Children's art;
History of the world's encyclopaedias;
The future of civilization; Outstanding
educators of the world; Folk wisdom
(proverbs and sayings from different
countries); Freud and Pavlov.
Vladimir Tuchtaev
Leningrad, U.S.S.R.
LUNAR LAPSUS
Sir. .
In your article on communications
on the moon (March 1969) the diagram
on page 29 gives the speed of the
moon in its orbit round the earth as
34,000 kilometres per hour.
If we consider the moon's orbit as
circular, with a radius of 384,000 kilo¬
metres (the mean distance from the
moon to the earth) the following
calculation: 2tt.384.103/28.5 X 24,
shows that the speed of the moon is
about 3,400 kilometres per hour, not
34,000.
Prof. Geremia Delia Nora
Taranto, Italy
We are indebted to our reader for
correcting this typographical error,
perhaps the slip of a moonstruck
proof-reader Editor.
NAIVE ILLUSIONS
Sir,
As a South African citizen I feel I
must reply to the naive illusions of
G.M. Barbier and Paul La Reste of
France (Letters to the Editor, January
1969). I cannot understand how people
living in a state once occupied by Hitler
can support a policy based on racial
discrimination.
South Africa's Government has pass¬
ed over 200 laws which discriminate
against non-White people. Apartheid
has not led "to the creation of Negro
states." Even civil servants and candi¬
dates for the Transkei's so-called
"Parliament" have been banned by
the Pretoria Government against the
will of the Transkei "Government".
Even if Apartheid leads to the crea¬
tion of "Negro states", they will never
result in Whites and Blacks sharing
South Africa's resources equitably. For
analogy, imagine if the poorest two-
thirds of France's population was forc¬
ed to live in an underdeveloped 13 per
cent of France (say the Jura Alps and
Brittany). These people would have
their vote for the French Parliament
taken away, and would not even be
allowed to have their wives with them
if they sought work in the cities
because there was not enough employ¬
ment for them in the Jura and Brittany
"reserves". They would be forbidden
to use nearly all public toilets, beaches,
cinemas etc., and would have only one-
tenth as many educational facilities as
the wealthiest Frenchmen.
A reader
Cape Town, South Africa
This reader has asked us not to
publish his name Editor.
UNFORGETTABLE FRIENDS
Sir,
In May 1968, my husband and I
returned from a round trip of some six
weeks on a Spanish boat, which went
from Southampton via Spain, to South
America, Trinidad and Jamaica.
We travelled tourist class, and found
ourselves the only "white" people
among some 400 passengers of many
interesting hues. Living deep in the
English countryside, we had met very
few West Indian people, and this exper¬
ience proved to be one of the most
exciting and rewarding ones of our
lives. We lived with our friends, ate
with them, and thus found ourselves
deeply involved in their lives and loves.
I have never found such friendliness
in my life. Wherever you went, you
were met with a large smile. One
could not feel alone or unhappy. It is
this warmness I cannot forget.
Use Majer-Williams
Cheltenham, U.K.
PLANETARY MANAGEMENT
Sir,
Your January 1969 issue on the
global environment was excellent in
underscoring the (literally) life-and-
death importance of planning that en¬
vironment to make it habitable. None
of your writers, however, pointed out
the inexorable conclusion to which
the need for such world-wide planning
leads. Failure after failure to get all the
communities and industries in a given
area (such as near a lake or river)
voluntarily to abide by anti-pollution
norms for that area should have taught
us that environmental planning on the
world level at which level one must
deal with some 150 nations and innu¬
merable special-interest groups re¬
quires a world government capable of
enforcing the rules laid down by such
planning.
J. Chrys Dougherty, IV
Austin, Texas, U.S.A.
Sir.
Your issue "Can We Keep Our
Planet Habitable?" (January 1969) de¬
serves the highest praise. As a tea¬
cher of terminal secondary classes
(whose curriculum now gives quite an
important place to ecology) I have been
reading salient passages from this
issue to my pupils.
Geneviève Denis
Toulouse, France
'STATE OF MANKIND' ADDRESS
Sir.
At a recent meeting of the Voice of
Women, Canada, the following suggest¬
ion was made: "That the Secretary-
General of the United Nations issue a
"State of Mankind" address once a
year, and that this address should be
broadcast over the entire world on all
available media with simultaneous tran¬
slations, and that the address be print¬
ed and made available to all school
children."
I think this is an excellent suggestion.
It could be done on United Nations
Day, October 24, and all programmes
on radio and television on that day
could be given over to films and
documentaries on the work of the
various U.N. agencies.
I would like to know if this idea
appeals to readers of the "Unesco
Courier", and if so, what steps should
be taken to implement it.
K. Joan Wright
Vancouver, B.C.
Canada
THE GOLDEN RULE
Sir.
Congratulations for publishing "The
Golden Rule" (Unesco Newsroom,
December 1968) presenting examples
of the ideal of the Common Brotherhood
of Man, expressed in the world's faiths
and embodied in the Universal Dec¬
laration of Human Rights.
The following are from the faiths of
the world not included in your exam¬
ples:
Bahai: "Regard not that which bene¬
fits yourself, but hold to that which
benefits mankind."
Jainism: "A man of religion should
treat all beings as he himself would
be treated."
Sikhism: "As thou deemest thyself,
so deem others. Then shalt thou
become a partner in heaven."
Dr. D.R. Saggar
Dundee, U.K
PEACE RESEARCH PIONEER
Sir,
I should like to call your attention to
Norman Alcock, who in 1961 left his
position in nuclear physics research to
found the Canadian Peace Research
Institute. Starting with $20,000 from
his own savings, his aim was to raise
$4 million to finance scientific study
into the causes of war and the means
of preventing it.
I can recall this tremendous under¬
taking at the time but, because of
apathy, I and many others have for¬
gotten about this great internationalist
and his continuing efforts on behalf of
peace.
I feel that Norman Alcock's efforts
and achievements should be reported
in the "Unesco Courier" in the hope
that his work will be stimulated, and
in turn will stimulate more people of
like mind.
Stuart Craig
Willowdale, Ontario, Canada
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Investment in education
The World Bank has lent a record total
of more than $81 million during fiscal year
1968-1969 to finance educational develop¬
ment in 10 countries in Africa, Asia and
Latin America. The Bank plans to in¬
crease lending for education threefold over
the next five years. Under the World
Bank/Unesco Co-operative Programme, the
funds help to build, equip and expand
schools, colleges and universities.
More protein, more wool
Sheep grow up to three times more
wool on protein rich diets. The problem
is to get protein through the sheeps' first
three stomachs (where microbes ruin most
of it) and into the fourth stomach, where
it can be digested. Australian scientists
have devised two methods: they chemi¬
cally modify protein to make it microbe-
resistant or cover it with plastic which
does not decompose until it reaches the
fourth stomach.
Automatic weather station
With the present shortage of meteoro¬
logists and the increasing need for up-to-
date weather information, a recent British-
designed automatic weather recording
station should be a boon to global meteor¬
ology. It can operate unmanned for three
months, registering rainfall, humidity, wind
speed and direction, air, soil and water
temperatures, barometric pressure, solar
radiation, and water level and flow.
Life in a cold climate
The people of the Soviet Union spend
almost 6,000 million rubles ($6,600 million)
each year on winter clothing furs, winter
hats, felt high-boots, overcoats, and woollen
suits. Fifty million tons of fuel are used
to heat houses and factories each winter,
and Moscow alone needs 120 snow loaders,
500 five-ton lorries, 150 big mechanical
sweepers, 185,000 tons of sand, and 150
mechanical sand throwers to keep its
streets clear and safe.
In the steps of Bolivar
The Colombian Civic Organization for
Literacy has launched a programme to
eradicate illiteracy along the liberation
route taken by Bolivar 150 years ago. The
campaign began at Arauca, the first town
freed by Bolivar (on June 4, 1819) on his
sweep from Venezuela through Colombia.
The operation has been named "The
Second Liberty" freedom from ignor¬
ance. Eighteen towns are involved in the
project with a total population of almost
180,000, of which it is estimated more than
45,000 adults are illiterate.
OVANES TUMANYAN
BARD OF ARMENIA
(1869-1923)
This year's centenary of the birth of Ovanes Tumanyan, often called the father
of modern Armenian literature, is being celebrated by Armenians throughout the
world, and particularly in the Soviet Union where four million copies of his works
have been published in 18 languages. For his ability to embody in his work the
national sentiments, ideals and culture of the Armenian people Tumanyan has been
compared to Goethe in German literature, Pushkin in Russian, Mickiewicz in Polish,
Shevchenko in Ukrainian, and Tagore in Indian.
Above all, Tumanyan brought literature closer to the life and hearts of the Armen¬
ian people; in works such as the poem Anush, the short novel Gikar, and The Song
of the Ploughman, he depicted the spiritual life of the Armenians, their national
characteristics and quest for freedom, while his famous quatrains, dealing with
philosophical subjects, have been compared to the Persian classics of Omar
Khayyam, Khagani, or Hafiz. In his famous poem, David of Sasun (1), a modern
interpretation of a 1,000 year old Armenian folk epic, and The Capture of Tmkberd,
he expressed his ideas on beauty, immortality, patriotism and the power of love.
And he introduced to Armenian readers, through his remarkable translations, the
works of Pushkin; Byron, Lermontov, Schiller, Longfellow, Mickiewicz, de Musset,
Goethe and others.
Through all the turbulent events that occurred during his lifetime strife in the
Caucasus, the slaughter of the Armenians in Turkey, World War One, the Revolution
and Civil War in Russia Tumanyan campaigned unceasingly, often at great per¬
sonal risk, for reason, humanism and brotherhood among nations.
(1) Daredevils of Sassoun, an English translation by Jean Surmelian of the original
epic, has been published by George Allen & Unwin, London, in the U.S.S.R. series
of the Unesco Collection of Representative Works.
International baccalauréat
for 1970
The first international baccalauréat exam¬
ination will be held next year with 100
candidates from four schools: the U.N.
School in New York, the International
School in Copenhagen, the National College
in Beirut and the Iranzamin in Teheran. It
has been accepted as a university entrance
qualification by France, Norway, Sweden,
Switzerland, Canada, Australia and the
U.S.A., and by most U.K. universities.
Five-nation development
of River Plate Basin
Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Paraguay and
Uruguay jointly are to develop the power,
transport and other resources of the
1.3 million square-mile River Plate Basin.
Half of the Basin is in Brazil and nearly
the whole of Argentina's and Paraguay's
populations, and half that of Uruguay live
there. The region's hydro-electric poten¬
tial is estimated at 100,000 million kilowatts,
and Brazil has already begun work at
sites on three rivers the Parana, Para-
naiba and Rio Grande which should be
producing power in five years time.
'Mahatma' a film biography
Twenty thousand photographs, 30,000
letters, 100,000 film extracts and 50 hours
of recorded voice-tapes have been drawn
on to make a 5i hour film biography of
Gandhi, enttled "Mahatma". A copy was
recently presented to Unesco by India's
National Committee for the Gandhi Cente¬
nary. The "film is available in seven of
India's languages and English.
34
FIRST U. N. STAMPS ISSUED IN EUROPE
This month, United Nations stamps are being
issued for the first time in Swiss denominations.
Previously, all U.N. stamps bore only U.S.
values. The new stamps, valid for mailing only
from the Palais des Nations in Geneva, are in
eight denominations: 5, 10, 20, 30, 50, 75 cen¬
times and one and three francs; 20 and 30 cen¬
time postal cards and a 65 centime airletter are
also available. For further details, write to
U.N. Postal Administration, Palais des Nations,
CH-1211. Geneva 10, U.N. Postal Administration, 1st Avenue, New York 17, U.S.A.,
or the Unesco Philatelic Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-78. As agent in France
for the United Nations Postal Administration, Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks
all U N. stamps and first day covers currently on sale.
Flashes... %
Zambia's Flying Doctor Service plans
to provide a nation-wide network of medi¬
cal care, using 50 airstrips and clinics.
Czechoslovakia, assisted by the U.N.
Development Programme, has Inaugurated
a $6.6 million computing research centre in
Bratislava.
Some 1,300 Unesco Clubs in 35 coun¬
tries are helping to promote the ideas of
Unesco for international understanding and
co-operation.
Twenty thousand student volunteers are
to teach adult illiterates at 2,000 centres
In a nation-wide literacy campaign in
Burma.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just republished by Unesco
ALL MEN
ARE BROTHERS
LIFE AND THOUGHTS OP
MAHATMA GANDHI
AS TOI.ll ^^^
IN HIS OWN WOIDS
CENTENNIAL KEPtlNT
2nd edition 1969 196 p.
Paper : $4.00 24/- 14.00 F
Cloth : $6.00 36/- 21.00 F
ALL MEN ARE BROTHERS
Life and thoughts of Mahatma Gandhi
as told in his own words
To mark the centenary of the birth of Mahatma Gandhi
(October 2, 1869), Unesco has brought out a new edition of
the selection of Gandhi's writings it published in 1958.
Compiled and edited by Krishna Kripalani, the selection is
designed to appeal to a wide public and make better known
the different aspects of Gandhi's personality and writings.
An introduction written by Professor Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan,
at the time Vice-President of India and later President, outlines
the main features of Mahatma Gandhi's philosophy and his
influence in promoting international friendship and understanding.
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzal, Pre» Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Publications : Educational Supplies Pty Ltd, P.O.
Box 33, Brookvale, 2 100 NSW; Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Limited, Box 33, Post Office, Brook¬
vale 2100 NSW Sub-agent United Nations As¬
sociation of Australia, Victorian Division, 4th
Floor, Askew House, 364 Lonsdale St., Melbourne
(Victoria), 3000. ($ 2.75). AUSTRIA. Verlag
Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(AS 82) BELGIUM. AU publications: Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-We-
tenschappelijke Uitgeverij Belgiëlei 147, Antwerp, I. For
The Unesco Courier (1 70 FB) and art slides (488 FB) only:
Jean de Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP
3380.00. BURMA. Trade Corporation N'(9), 550-
552 Merchant Street. Rangoon. CANADA. Queen's
Printer. Ottawa. Ont. ($ 4.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, SirChittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244,
Colombo, 2. (Rs 12.50) World Book Co.
Ltd., 99 Chungking South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop
Makarios 3rd Avenue. P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.. Spalena 51, Prague 1
(permanent display); Zahranicni literatura 1 1 Soukenicka
Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard, Ltd.,
6, Norregade, 1145, Copenhagen K. (Dan. Kr. 19.00).
ETHIOPIA. National Commission for Unesco P.O.
Box 2996, Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 11.90).
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (12 F). GERMANY. All
publications: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145,8 Munich, 80. For the Unesco Kurier(Germanedonly)
Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 1 60, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 12). GHANA. Methodist Book Depot
Ltd., Atlantic House, Commercial Street, POB 1 00, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens; Librairie Eleftheroudakis, Nikkis 4, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co.. 13-15 Lock Road,
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kónyvesbolt,
Vid u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtirosok Boltia,
Népkóztarsaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebiörn Jonsson & Co., H.F.. Halnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd., Nicol Road, Ballard
Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 1 3;
36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; 3/5 Asaf Ali Road, New
Delhi 1 ; Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 1 6 and Scindia House. New Del¬
hi: Indian National Commission for Unesco, att. The Libra¬
rian, Ministry of Education, "C" Wing, Room N" 214,
Shastri Bhawan. New Delhi 1. (Rs. 13.50). INDONE¬
SIA. Indira P. T., D¡l. Dr. Sam Ratulangie 37, Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for Unesco, 1/154
Avenue Roosevelt, B.P. 1 533. Teheran. IRAQ. McKen-
zie's Bookshop, AI- Rashid Street, Baghdad; University
Bookstore. University of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad.
IRELAND.The National Press, 2,Wellington Road.Balls-
bridge, Dublin, 4. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly
Blumstein's Bookstores, 35 Allenby Road and 48 Nahlat
Beniamin Street, Tel-Aviv IL. 12.50. JAMAICA. Sang-
ster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O.Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston. JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., P.O. Box 5050,
Tokyo International 1 00-3 1 . JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous
& Co., Dar-ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait
Bookshop Co., Ltd., P.O. Box 2942, Kuwait. LIBERIA.
Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286.
Monrovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of
Publication & Distribution, P.O. Box 261, Tripoli.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. (F.L. 170). Federal Publica¬
tions Sdn Bhd., Balai Berita, 31 Jalan Riong, Kuala Lum¬
pur. MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kingsway, Valletta.
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port Louis. MONACO. Britisn Library. 30,
Bid. des Moulins. Monte Carlo. NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff. Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 10). NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G. C.
T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Cura¬
çao. N.A. (NA fl 5.25). NEW ZEALAND. Govern¬
ment Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland
Street. P.O. Box 5344, Auckland; 130 Oxford Terrace,
P.O. Box 1721,Christchurch; Alma Street, P.O.Box 857
Hamilton ; Princes Street. P. O. Box 1 1 04, Dunedin ; Mul-
grave Street, Private Bag, Wellington. ($ 2.1 5) NOR-
163 56 Stockholm 16.
Svenska. FN.
101 23. Stockholm, 1
SWITZERLAND.
WAY. All publications: A.S. Bokhjórnet, Akersgt 41-Oslo
1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Litteratur-
Jeneste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. The West-Pak
Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publication House, P.O.
Box 374 G.P.O., Lahore ; Showrooms: Urdu Bazar, Lahore,
and 57-58 Murree Highway, G/6- 1, Islamabad. Pakistan
Publications Bookshop, Sarwar Road, Rawalpindi ; Paribagh.
Dacca. PHILIPPINES. The Modern Book Co., 928.
Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box632, Manila.- POLAND. All publi¬
cations: ORWN PAN Palac Kultury, iNauki, Warsaw
For the Unesco Courier only: "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23,
Warsaw 1 0. PORTUGAL, Dias & Andrade Lda.Livraria
Portugal, rua de Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115.
Apartado 1 91 2. Hato Rey. SINGAPORE. Federal Pu¬
blications Sdn Bhd., Times House, River Valley Road , Sin¬
gapore 9. SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
(PVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue. Salisbury. SUDAN.
AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118, Khartoum.
SWEDEN. All publications : A/B CE. Fritzes Kungl.
Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2,
For the Unesco Courier
Forbundet Vasagatan 1 5-IV
Postgiro 18 46 29 (Kr. 1 8)
All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse,
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211,
Geneva 11, CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only :Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
12-4811. (Fr. S. 12). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
(37.50 baht).TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala. SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications: Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty). Ltd.,
Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Central
News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesburg.
- UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester,
Birmingham and Bristol. (20/-). UNITED STATES.
Unesco Publications Center, P.O. Box 433, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5). U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga.Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zaluzba Slovenije.
Mestni Trg. 26, Ljubljana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
AlAIm1
~^»h BT^B- *" ^Lff BT AB " ^if BB
BjwVt*fl
BaVJKWvB
H ^B< ' tJB
Bfir\rfl
lliHi f flfl^ ilnMl ï|h Hfla** V If flM\B
jj^L 'amé V
If/tvl ffibtl
'
IftVrfl
Hbb ~^«l
B ' V
rfcl
1ÏÏIÎ «rflflvfl «fl\B Hy «fl\fl
"~ ^í1
R
AB; ~^Wbb '^II ~^JB
KU
BB* - tJBI ~^vl BTflÊ< " ^bI
t^r*fl
B*/iwfl B'/Vrl FMIB'/twfl
ifflÏl flflXB Húé^vV )]flk\B ffM\i ¡¡SIJIM
KSIRU Î?»B»AIW RU K^awJ
HlrO*'l
LV bv ^K»^rfAfl Ifcl
BB _ W BB
B*/\vfl Bfir\Wfl IfiV^I Ifivhl
LV eW^Sifl
Bv/tVrl
dikxfjllj|iHflM
IIAvl If«1 ^¡hW V BT BV '*flW"l
MyI
Kil *^m \W RU RU
BJ^7j>t'fji*BB
LwjB< '^wl Iftól l/#l
BIBB- ' yBB
|f|^|
Br BB> " tJBB
wm\B
^L iflW* 1
Hlixl
BY >Hk 'éfl^'l
filin
RU
B<__vwJ ff flfl\B IfJb\1
BjL '..flu« * H BM 'a^Éji l/#l ff/tSl
jBL 'Aj'I
If/i9l
^íw*fl
B'/ivfl
flRXB r^^XVIfMj «MB [¡M lliln If flB\B
BU RU
IJf/jSl If/iSl T»i BTBB' ' ajbb
Bfir\rfl
BB> '^vl
bIa\?b
Tiffll
BBVtitfl
]]>
</page>
</document>
