<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078286eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m UTTiH
MARCH 1962 (15TH YEAR) - PRICE : 1/-STG. (U.K.) - 30 CENTS (U.S.) - 0.70 NF (FRANCE)
M*..
" flk^i
»
i»pw^
******** mm m «IHlMtHlOK« *»Ml*
>U*J?»
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
COMPUTER DECIPHERS
MAYAN SCRIPT
One of the world's ancient scripts, that of the
Maya people, has been transcribed on this card
into the world's most modern script: the punch-
ed-hole symbols of the electronic computer.
How Soviet scientists succeeded in deciphering
this hitherto incomprehensible hieroglyphic lan¬
guage is described in the story on page 26.
Novosibirsk Institute of Mathematics, U.S.S.R.
m &
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
No. 3
MARCH 1962
15TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
COVER PHOTO
This boy is a Bororo Peuhl,
a pastoral nomad people of
Africa. He watches over
large herds of cattle and one
day will lead a herd in search
of fresh pastures and water.
When he does and returns
home he will be considered
a man and can marry the girl
of his choice. A beautiful
documentary has been made
on the Peuhls (see page 13).
From "Nomades du Soleil" by
Henry Brandt published Jointly
by © Editions Clairefontaine
and Guilde du Livre, Lausanne.
26 COMPUTER DECIPHERS MAYA HIEROGLYPHS
. Cryptogram technique solves linguistic enigma
By Felix Shirokov
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M.C. 62. 1. 167 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : H^iis Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Shaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German
Arabic and Japanese. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H. M
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Readers* Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates: U. S. $ 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00
New Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30
cents (U.S.) ; 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
THE ART
OF SEEING A FILM
by J.M.L. Peters
For persons of all ages but perhaps more so for the
young, the best protection against the faults and ex¬
cesses of films and television is the awakening, deve¬
lopment and proper training of the critical faculties.
This is not criticism for its own sake but so people can
be more selective in the films the/ see and also under¬
stand them better. Film teaching is already common
practice in the schools of a number of countries. The
Unesco Courier strongly recommends "Teaching About
the Film " by J.M.L. Peters, a book just published by
Unesco, the Introduction of which is reproduced below.
MORE TO IT THAN MEETS THE EYE. The meaning of a film picture is
usually not identical with the object or situation represented by it. The scene
below from Robert Wise's "The Set-Up" does not merely represent a boxer
who has just knocked out another. It "says" something "The winner domi-
These days many educational authorities, as
well as parents, seem to have it on their
consciences that they ought to "do something about the
film." They often appear to envisage some form of inter¬
vention, or interference, from the sphere of education
into that of the cinema.
The arguments in favour of such action stem mainly
from the conviction of many adults, including many
educators, that motion »pictures are a danger to young
people. Their view is that even though most Ulms do not
overtly express ideas and opinions which might be consi¬
dered morally bad, and even though sympathy is not
actually expressed for gangsters and other villains,
nevertheless the cinema may form a bad emotional envi¬
ronment or intellectual climate for the young and
immature.
Certainly the world shown by many films is not a true
reflection of reality. It is often a world where, for
example, family life, work, culture and religion appear
supremely unimportant. Rarely is family life depicted
as being important in itself; it offers only a framework
for the actions of the principal characters on the screen.
Similarly, many Alms give the impression that work is
an unimportant part of man's life. Only very seldom is
the relation of the film hero or heroine towards their jobs
of any importance for the development of the film story.
As for cultural values, it can surely be said without
offending anybody that art, science, technical and social
progress are not the main concerns of many film makers
4 nor of the persons who play a leading part in their films.
Thus it is no exaggeration to say that »many films are
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
K. van der Groep
nates the whole situation, the loser's defeat is absolute." In this picture from
"Notorious", Alfred Hitchcock has used lighting and perspective to create
a dramatic relationship between the girl and the cups of coffee and the
shadow of the hand in foreground gives a threatening effect to the whole.
likely to induce the inexperienced and uncritical onlooker
to believe that life is made up largely of crime and sex.
The actions of the leading characters are often motivated
by the desire for social success, wealth, prestige or author¬
ity.
Sex and romance, crime and adventure, swashbuckling
heroics and personal achievement are the predominant
themes of a great many films. The sentimental element
is over-emphasized at the expense of reasonable argu¬
ment. Problems are solved in a way designed to satisfy
the onlooker's emotional wishes rather than the claims
of his intellect.
Physical advantages strength or beauty are generally
presented as more desirable than brains or character.
The social situation of »man (and woman) as depicted by
the movies also differs considerably from reality. The
heroes of the screen generally have "romantic" profes¬
sions or jobs; they may be cowboys, dancers, singers,
actors, sporting champions, detectives, officers in the
armed forces. But the office stool is not valued very
highly. Indeed, a large percentage of the characters on
the screen are already apparently so rich that they do
not need to work at all.
Similarly, the surroundings most frequently shown in
films are the prairie, the theatre (behind the scenes as
well as from the stage), the racecourse and boxing ring,
the luxury flat, the night-club frequented by gangsters,
the glamorous outpost of empire not the wash-tub, the
factory or the poor apartment.
Yet since (It is argued) one cannot prevent or counter¬
act these "hidden dangers" solely by means of negative
measures, such as film censorship, one has to do some¬
thing positive. However, what Is meant here by "posi¬
tive" has often in the past turned out to be still rather
"negative" ; young people, It has been said, ought to be put
through a process of being "disillusioned" about their
film experiences.
As early as 1933 the American Professor Herbert Blumer
wrote that one ought to teach young cinema-goers not to
involve themselves too deeply In the action of a film or
in the problems of its heroes, In order not to lose their
critical detachment towards »the film Itself.
Young people, he thought, had to learn to develop what
he called "adult discount" .that Is, they should cultivate
aloofness in order to remain consciously the spectators
and to avoid becoming sympathetic participants.
I myself think that nowadays we see more clearly that
one may develop a critical attitude towards the cinema
without at the same time becoming so detached that a
film experience in which one participates as a deeply-
engrossed spectator is forfeited.
As was remarked by Professor Edgar Dale twenty years
after his compatriot Blumer: pedagogically speaking it
would be no small loss, and seeing a film would be a less
rich experience, if one were to cultivate such an emotional
detachment among young people.
What Lord Radoliffe wrote in The Problem of Power is
worth recalling at this point: "The spread of education
has given most people the apparatus of criticism; what
it has not always given them is the knowledge of how to c
use their machine for an end that is not merely trivial or
destructive. Yet criticism is essentially a method of
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
MAGIC OF LIGHT
Basically each film pic¬
ture owes its power of
expression to a combin¬
ed use of visual and
sound effects. Among
these, lighting has an
important role. This is
illustrated by two shots
from "Variations on a
Film Theme" in which
the same face, under
different lighting condi¬
tions, has its expression
completely transformed.
ART OF SEEING A FILM (Cont'd)
Don't be bluffed by glitter & glamour
appreciation. It has no necessary connexion with the
awful luxuries of contempt or condemnation."
Therefore, the cultivation of a critical attitude means,
In a sense, "self-immunizing". The spectators must not
be bluffed by the glitter of a picture and Its stars, nor by
the refined techniques of film production. In this respect
the advice that "one ought to learn to Withdraw from
the suggestive power of the film" can have real meaning.
It really comes down to this: where a worthwhile film
is concerned, the film experience of the young spectator
should certainly be allowed to be deep; the depth of his
impressions, however, should not primarily be due to the
glamour of the stars, the fabulous production costs, or
technical novelties and trickery.
To offer a protection against this type of spurious
appeal is a negative postulate of film education: the need
for critical evaluation and assimilation is a positive de¬
mand.
In American literature on the subject, film education is
mostly referred to as "motion picture discrimination",
and in that term I think both the above meanings (of
withdrawing from the suggestive power of the film, and
of critical evaluation and assimilation) are present. How¬
ever, in the so-called Wheare Report of 1950 (1) which
could be regarded as the English charter of film-teach¬
ing the dangers of the film and the necessity of arming
young people against those dangers were given priority.
The view that the film may be also a new form of art
In Its own right has been late in coming to the forefront
of pedagogical studies and of film educational practice in
most countries. It is remarkable that, generally speak¬
ing, the teaching of appreciation of the film as art must
still be first defended with the argument that the best
way to protect young people against the moral dangers of
the cinema is to cultivate their film aesthetic taste.
Yet changes have been coming over this scene.
Whereas In England the view was held for
many years that film education had to be art education
in the first place, many members of the Socie»ty for Edu¬
cation in Film and Television (formerly called the Society
of Film Teachers) have, for instance, for a long time past
been concerning themselves with aspects of the film
other than its aesthetic ones, »that is, with social, ethical
and cultural values.
What has happened in England has also happened in
other countries where film education has become an
accepted notion, and in other circles besides those pro¬
fessionally interested in the subject. But let us not be
carried away: right up to the present there has remained
a strong and active body of opinion upholding the oppos¬
ing viewpoint that -film education can have nothing to
do with social or moral values.
Sometimes one even hears the opinion expressed that a
discussion about moral or social problems inspired by a
feature film does not rightly belong to the domain of
(1) Home Office, "Report of the Departmental Committee on
Children and the Cinema", London, HM.S.O., May 1950.
film-teaching but to the sphere of the teaching film (that
is, visual aids). Here lies a common misunderstanding.
There are, of course, points of contact between film
education and the use of film as a visual aid in teaching,
but a very essential difference Is that in film education
one always comes back to the film; the film, however,
regarded not merely as an aesthetic object, but also as a
social institution, as a means of mass entertainment
having special effects and influences on the cultural and
spiritual level of the people, a medium for communication
of ethical, religious, and other spiritual values.
As things stand, the film only very seldom qualifies as
being wholly a form of art. Most often it is something
like the newspaper, or a form of public amusement such
as a fair or a sports meeting.
Of course, one may take the view that one
cannot be bothered with this type of film
thereby excluding from one's Interest the major part of
film production. This may be a legitimate attitude for
the private Individual, but in my opinion it is not a valid
one for the educator to adopt. For the latter cannot get
away from the fact that many non-aesthetic or extra-
aesthetic elements in the film represent an Important
part of the normal world In which young people live.
This has nothing to do with the use of films as teaching
aids; it simply means that one ought to teach young
people how to integrate the experiences they have ac¬
quired from a film Into their own lives.
To the average member of the average cinema audience,
the film seems to have a similar function to the novel or
the stage play. All these "media" offer him an opportu¬
nity to participate in another life, the life of other people,
in other surroundings and circumstances, in other regions
of the world.
The cinema screen, the covers of a book, the theatre
curtain are alike the doorsteps to a second world, where
he can lead a second life perhaps in some respects a
"double life". But the reading of a book can be com¬
pared only to leading a second inner life, because the
world described in words is »an inner world, which we can
perceive with our spiritual eye only.
But the film not only represents reality almost true to
nature but also places the spectator emotionally right in
the centre of the life that is going on within this reality.
Let us examine this phenomenon a little more deeply, by
citing an illustration which may seem a trifle homely but
which is nevertheless very much »to the point.
One day when we were still at school, the physics
teacher entered our classroom. He put a mirror on the
demonstration table and placed a burning candle before
the mirror. And then we made a "scientific" discovery
about something which we had probably seen a hundred
times already: we found out "scientifically" that the
candle we were seeing in the mirror and the candle
before the mirror were Identical.
We also heard the scientific term for this: the candle
before the mirror was called In physics a real object, the
one in the mirror was a virtual object. For the rest,
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
VISUAL LANGUAGE
Each separate picture in a film can be given
special meaning depending on how the spec¬
tator stands, so to speak, both mentally and
spatially, in relation to what he sees on the
screen. This "positioning" is done by the
camera (distance, height, angle, position and
movement all play their part). It can be objec¬
tive (the spectator is a mere observer), or
subjective (he identifies himself with a person
or persons on the screen) ; or intermediate
between these two. The sequences below from
Carol Reed's film "The Fallen Idol" show the
three techniques. (1) We look with the boy
through a window and see a couple quarrelling
(intermediate objective-subjective). (2) A "re¬
verse-angle" shot. We see the boy face-to-face
(objective). (3) We witness the quarrel
as though we are looking on through the eyes
of the boy (complete identification-subjective).
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ART OF SEEING A FILM (Cont'd)
From the other side of the mirror
there was almost no difference between the two candles,
except for this major one we could touch the real candle,
the virtual one we couldn't.
This school experience has been recalled to make clear
what Is meant when we say that the film confronts us
with reality in a "virtual" way. When we are truly fasci- »
nated by a film it seems indeed to reproduce reality more
or less true to nature, apart from the fact that we cannot
touch this reality; that is to say, we cannot experience it
physiologically.
There are still other similarities between the experience
of looking In a mirror and seeing a film. When we look
into a mirror, we find ourselves physically in a room in
which the mirror in question hangs on the wall. Yet at
the same time we are in some way "virtually" again
present in the room on the other side of the glass, In the
room that is reflected by the mirror. The furniture and
other objects in the real room, we see from the reflected
room. In a sense, we have stepped over into the room
of the mirror and from there we perceive our environ¬
ment.
In much the same way, like Alice through the Looking
Glass, we experience the people and things on the cinema
screen from the space (it may be a street, the interior of
an aeroplane, or a living-room) in which they happen at
that moment to be situated. If, when a film is being
made, a certain scene is shot in a living-room, where
some people are talking with each other, then the specta¬
tor sees this scene from' the same point of view as the
camera saw it from when shooting the scene.
And if the same scene Is taken from several angles, the
spectator will see the scene successively from those differ¬
ent angles. Though he is, physically, sitting down in
his chair In the cinema, he finds himself at the same time
virtually in the room where the film actors are, and
Indeed moving about in it. He sees the action on the
screen from time to time through the eyes of the actors.
Thus there is a kind of two-way traffic between the
spectator and the film, and as a result we are often stron¬
gly involved In the events of the film, even though we
still remain mere "onlookers". For, of course, we have
to limit our activity to mere looking and we cannot inter¬
vene in any real sense In what Is happening on the
screen.
And here we come across another facet of this pheno¬
menon. Again, a homely illustration: If we are eye¬
witnesses of a car accident, our activity will probably not
be restricted merely to looking but, will take some form of
practical action.
Seeing a similar accident, just as serious, depicted on
the cinema screen, we omit all such action, however
strongly we are emotionally affected by this scene. (And
we may be very strongly affected, because the. film maker
will possibly have shown us the scene through the eyes
of the driver or of the victims.)
Now in such a case, where there is no escape valve for
our inner urge for what can be called motor activity, this
activity turns inwards and our emotional reactions
become all the stronger.
Such emotional participation consists mainly of two
mutually connected processes which are, of course, usually
called "projection" and "identification". In this pheno¬
menon, on the one hand, the spectator, attaches his own
tendencies, feelings and character traits to the actors on
the screen he "projects" them into the actors and, on
the other hand, the spectator thinks himself into the
spirit of an actor and his role to such an extent that he
identifies himself with him and feels and thinks like him.
On the one hand the spectator loses himself mentally
in the screen; on the other, he incorporates the world of
the film into his own person. And again we can apply
the term "virtual" to these processes, for there Is no real
contact with the people on the screen and there Is no
such relationship between the spectator and these people
as there would be in reality because the "glass of the
mirror" stands between them.
The conclusion to be drawn from this exposition Is that
seeing a film can be a "virtual physical" and a "virtual
mental" participation in the life of other people in ano-
HOW TO ANALYS Fl L
Environment and action
1 . Where does the action occur?
2. Is the scenery familiar or
exotic?
3. Is the locale treated fully,
superficially?
4. Is description realistic and
of general interest?
5. Why does it interest you?
6. What arethechief situations?
7. Is an "exciting pursuit" a
sensational feature or an
essential element of the
action?
8. What is the chief theme;
what are secondary ones?
9. What is the genuine relative
importance of these themes?
10. How does the action develop?
The characters
11. What kind of people are the
main characters?
12. Why do you find them attrac¬
tive or displeasing?
13. Are appearance or character
stressed most?
14. How much do these influence
the action?
15. Are the professions of the
characters fairly represen¬
ted?
16. Does an attractive or dis¬
pleasing character come out
as "winner" or "loser"?
17. Is the character of the main
roles "genuine"?
18. Which professions are de¬
picted favourably?
19. Are main characters' occu¬
pations presented more fa¬
vourably than in real life?
20. How do the main characters
behave?
21. Should we approve or reject
their behaviour?
22. Does it deviate from social
or moral standards? Is it
nevertheless justifiable?
23. What are the main charac¬
ters' motives egotism, al¬
truism, idealism, love, self-
sacrifice, desire for money,
success, authority?
24. How do these motivations
become apparent?
Ideas in the film
25. Does the film have an ob¬
vious or hidden tendency?
26. Does it make propaganda
for any belief or cause?
27. What moral does it »make?
28. Can we agree with these
views?
29. What ideas are advanced
about cultural, social, other
standards and concepts?
30. Does the film use proper
arguments to defend or reject
certain views?
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Scene from The World, the Flesh and the Devil, made by Roland MacDougall. In general the aim of all
film-makers is to carry the spectator into another world. We must therefore know how to "liberate"
ourselves from the suggestive effects of a film and its emotional impact. Only thus can we analyse
lucidly the action and the behaviour and ideas of the characters and benefit fully from films we see.
ther world. Or, to put it another way, to see a film is
to lead a second (virtual) life In a second (virtual) world.
For some persons this experience can be as real as
normal daily life, apart from its "virtuality", so to speak.
However, from this very virtuality It derives its own
charm, its appeal, its magic. We cannot "touch" it, but
neither can it "touch" us: it happens to us and we go
through It, but without any risk.
It is impossible as yet to state In detail, or even to
foresee completely, what will be the educational conse¬
quences of regular and repeated excursions into this so-
called "second world". But one thing is certain: a new
pedagogical situation has been created.
The situation in which youth is now growing up is
completely different from that of fifty years ago, as a
result of the fact that young people are, as we have said,
living in two worlds. They are not subjected to the geo¬
graphical, social and cultural isolation which was the
rule for former generations.
Much earlier than before, In a much more direct and
far-reaching manner, the young people of today are con¬
fronted with views, traditions and standards different
from those of their home environment. And they are
also confronted with what can only be described as a new
"language".
Some educationists for instance, professor Louis Stiick-
rath in the Federal Republic of Germany have stressed
the point that film, before being a work of art (or a me¬
dium for entertainment,- a visual newspaper, and so on)
is a new language, a new means of understanding and,
along with that, a new means of gaining knowledge.
In our culture, which until recently was mainly a book-
and-word culture, our mental life and the all-important
process of communication between human beings have
been primarily a matter of discursive thinking and rea¬
soning. Whatever is to be communicated to us by other
people by means of books and words, or whatever we
ourselves want to communicate to others, has to be ana¬
lyzed, so to speak, in a logical-rational way; it has to be
broken down and placed within the grammatical catego¬
ries of the sentence-construction.
But with the development of film language as a new
species of the general genus "language", a non-dlscurslve
means of communication has been put at our disposal.
This not only presents us with new laws of thinking and
reasoning but also leads our minds to other ways of
acquiring knowledge.
The film language opens up to our minds a new dimen¬
sion; perhaps a dimension that, in different respects,
mee>ts the needs of modern life better than verbal lan¬
guage alone is able to do. If this is indeed so, then the
incorporation of this new language Into our film educa¬
tional activities should not be merely supplementary, but
the most fundamental thing of all.
Thus it quickly becomes clear why of recent years in
almost every textbook for the teaching of English in the
United States of America there is a chapter on the film.
In that country, perhaps intuitively, they have realized
that language-teaching can no longer be limited to verbal
language alone, but has to be expanded to cover teaching
about communications in general, and that film-teaching
should not be just a part of general art education and
social and moral education but also a part of the teaching
of general communication theory. -
From this point, it is only a short step to recognition
of the fact that film education is itself just a part of an
educational process related to all the mass media of
communication and especially to the mass medium which
is most closely associated with film, namely, television.
This again presents new tasks for educators, of which
not the least important is the need to teach young people
that there are other means besides film and television
for passing leisure time in a useful and agréable way.
JAN M. L. PETERS is director of the Netherlands Film Institute
and Film Academy. He was formerly director of the Nether¬
lands School Film Services and secretary of the Institute of
Film and Youth.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Cinémathèque Française, Paris
ACCENT ON THE EXOTIC. For many years, films on
Africa showed little more than the exotic side of the so-called
Dark Continent. It is only recently that film producers have
begun to look at the more human side of Africa. Above, a
scene from Trader Horn (193 1). Below, Donald Swanson's
Magic Garden (1950), a minor musical masterpiece telling
of the amazing adventures of a Negro youth in Johannesburg.
10
Today a new African cinema is coming into being, which
is adding something new and significant to the cultural
and artistic life of this continent. The importance of
this development was underlined at an international
round-table discussion held last year in Venice on " Afri¬
ca and Contemporary Civilization ". At this gathering
Unesco presented several studies on the cinema in
Africa. The article below is an edited and abridged
version of a study by jean Rouch, in which the
French film producer traces the development of the
cinema in Africa and looks at some of its new trends.
This subject will also be dealt with in future issues.
T;he cinema made its debut in Africa in the
very first years after its invention. A vaude¬
ville magician managed to steal one of the first "theatre-
graph" projectors from the Alhambra Palace theatre in
London in 1896 and used it to introduce motion pictures
into South Africa. It is interesting to note that South
Africa still employs the turn-of-the-century word "Bio¬
scope" to describe a cinema theatre.
In West Africa the first motion picture projections go
back to 1905 when mobile cinemas began showing ani¬
mated cartoons in Dakar and in surrounding villages.
It was also during this period that explorers first began
to use motion picture cameras in the course of their
travels. The French Film Library (Cinémathèque Fran¬
çaise) in Paris possesses several »catalogues by Georges
Meliès which make mention of the first films made in
Africa.
Since this early pioneering period the cinema has
witnessed quite an extensive development in Africa.
Tropical Africa, however, has remained one of the most
under-developed regions as far as film showings are con¬
cerned, and the world's most retarded continent in the
field of film production.
While Asia and South America have »been making films
for years (in fact Japan, India and Hong Kong are now
the world's three leading feature film producers, ahead
of the U.S.A. which has dropped to fourth place), tropical
Africa has as yet to turn out its first full-length feature
picture. As the French film historian Georges Sadoul
recently wrote: "Sixty-five years after the invention of
the cinema, not one truly African feature-length film has
been produced to my knowledge. By that I mean a film
acted, photographed, written, conceived and edited by
Africans and filmed in an African language."
Now, at a time when a true African cinema Is
about to be born, I think it is worthwhile to
take stock of what has been done, what is now being done
in Africa and to examine the new trends of African
cinema.
The first films shot in Africa were frankly "exotic."
They showed the strangeness of the continent, viewed as
a land of "savages" and "cannibals." The African was
portrayed as a wild creature whose behaviour was in¬
tended to provoke laughter when it did not border on the
pathological. With the end of the first World War came
the stereotype of the childish, good-natured native.
The first noteworthy film about tropical Africa was
probably Croisière Noire (Negro Cruise), made by the
Frenchman Léon Poirier during the first motor-car trip
across Africa from north to south in 1924-25.
The basic theme of the film was the epic automobile
adventure, but parallel with that it showed the most
representative aspects of the people encountered en route.
Though the team was pressed by time the film men
proved their ability both in choosing and seeing their
subjects. The scenes they shot are now dated but never¬
theless remain priceless documents on Africa and the
history of its cultures.
Cahiers du Cinéma, Pans
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
THE AWAKENING
AFRICAN CINEMA
by Jean Rouch
There can be no doubt about the sincerity and good
intentions of the authors of this film. And yet two facts
stand out sharply today. The unit simply did not under¬
stand the world they were filming and which they
»glimpsed only scantily. Second, even when they had
more time on their hands during long halts, their
approach was that of the "let-us-look-at-the savages"
type with scenes of platter-lipped women, details of cer¬
tain »circumcision rites, or aspects in the life of pygmies.
Although photographed with a maximum of objectivity
the scenes remained cold, if not ironical. They had none
of the human warmth which we find in the earlier or
contemporary films made by Robert Flaherty such as
Nanook of the North or Moana.
The same can be said of most of the exotic films of the
time when Western cameras were discovering the rest of
the world with Marco Polo-type lenses, or just about. The
situation worsened in later years when we find the camera
portraying Africa as a continent of barbarism and cruelty,
although it must foe admitted that Africa was not the
only region to undergo such treatment. Asia, South
America, Greenland were brought to the screen with
paltry sequences of savage dances, guitar strummers and
primitive hunters.
But this period also gave us Trader Horn which created
a sensation by showing an African devoured alive by a
crocodile (it was never learned whether the scene was
faked or an accident) and especially Sanders of the River
starring Paul Robeson. Sanders of the River was one of
the first good talking pictures to be made on Africa and
was quite a success in tropical Africa.
The late 1920s also saw the appearance of the first true
documentary films about Africa. André Gide had gone
to the Congo in 1926 and had taken with him Marc Alle-
gret who returned to France with Voyage au Congo
(1928). In 1938 the African specialist Marcel Griaule pro¬
duced two anthropological films in the he-art of the con¬
tinent, using sound track with 35 millimetres. Au Pays
Dogon (In the Land of the Dogons) showed the daily life
»and religion of the Dogons. More important was Sous
les masques noirs (Under the Negro Masks) a film relating
the funeral rites and customs of a Bandiagara cliff village
in what is today the Republic of Sudan.
Two years before, Jean d'Esme had filmed La Grande
Caravane in eastern Nigeria which told the story of a
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Cahiers du Cinéma
A recent feature fil m on tropical Africa is Jean Rouch's " La Pyramide Humaine " (The Human Pyramid) whose
action is set in a secondary school at Abidjan, capital of the Ivory Coast. Below, a scene being filmed.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
LIFE AMONG THE PEUHLS. For half
a year the Swiss film-maker Henry
Brandt lived the life of the Bororo Peuhls,
a noble nomad people of the Niger.
Wandering with them and their herds of
cattle across the savannahs, he came
to understand their ways and to love
them. From his sojourn has come a
film of extraordinary beauty and human
warmth, "Nomades du Soleil" (Nomads
of the Sun) and a book of the same title
from which these photographs are taken.
AFRICAN CINEMA (Cont'd)
1950 the great turning point
caravan journey to obtain salt. The same year G. H.
Blanchon produced a short film in Guinea, Coulibaly à
l'Aventure. Though completely ignored, it deals with one
of the most important »problems of West Africa the
migration of young people from the savannahs to the
cities »on the coast. This could have been one of the most
valuable documentaries to come out of Africa if the film
had not been ruined by an exasperating commentary.
It is only after the second World War that we find a
valid African cinema developing both in documentaries
and in feature films (1).
The last war indirectly helped the development of Afri¬
can cinema, for during this period army field services had
to use portable film equipment, thus permitting 16-milli¬
metre film, previously reserved for amateurs, to prove its
worth.
The 16-millimetre movement was born Immediately
after the war and took hold particularly in France.
French youth, emerging from the Occupation, from the
armed forces or the Resistance, was seized with an Irresis¬
tible wanderlust. The Musée de l'Homme, the anthro¬
pological museum of Paris, became a magnet for young
Frenchmen eager to discover the world for themselves
and thirsting for adventure.
Thanks to these young men probably the first real
archives of recorded African music were assembled on
tape and film. It was this more than anything else which
* made it possible to add authentic musical sound tracks to
African films without resorting to outlandish and wholly
inappropriate exotic music.
Certain folack-and-white 35-millimetre films made at
this time, such as Danses Congolaises, Au Pays des
Pygmées, and Pirogues sur l'Ogooué, have remained the
first top-quality images and sound recordings made In
tropical Africa. These films are documentaries but they
constitute exceptional records of the traditional dances of
the Congo, the daily life of the Babinga pygmies, and
canoe transportation on the Ogowé River in Gabon.
The year 1950 marks a turning point in the growth of
African cinema. The films produced in the preceeding
years had shown that the era of the cheap exotic film
of prewar days was ended, and showed that there was a
great need to learn more about Africa if the cinema were
really to be used as a medium for telling spectators of
other cultures about it. From 1950 until today African
cinema has revealed five main tendencies.
1. EXOTIC AFRICA: apart from the Tarzan films, in
which Africa is only a mere pretext for the locale, a
number of producers continue to work the vein of the
"cannibal" and the "dance of the witch doctors." Here,
as in prewar days, Africa is only a stage setting and the
Africans themselves miserable extras.
(1) Note should be taken of a religious film, S"urs Noires
(Negro Nuns), shown in Paris in 1935 and in which the actors
spoke Zulu. In the 1930s German film-makers made a number
of films on Africa as part of the world-wide documentary series
of EFA and Tobis films. From these perhaps came some of the
sequences for Melodies of the World, by Walter Ruttman in
Germany.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
PEUHL LOVE SONG
Every maiden casts longing eyes at my herdsman
with his Dangadela ox and Ruadduru cattle.
He has gone off to the salt hole with his herd.
The first bird in the sky to bring me tidings of his
return shall have my joyful thanks.
Dear parents forgive me for being so madly in
love.
If I should be separated from him for long,
1 would be like a woman in mourning; I would let
down my hair;
For the first time the Peuhls will see a woman
baptising her infant with her own hands, so great
her happiness to have borne his child,
I shall call my baby girl Inna Ibba.
On our first outing we shall place her on the ox,
and how proudly I shall lead it by the halter.
Only Inna Ibba shall sit upon the ox. At the salt
hole, when we meet Bogue, herself enamoured of
my beloved, her face will drop.
Though her father may offer him many cattle, she
will not have my beloved.
He cannot be bought. He needs a true Peuhl
woman able to charge a bundle with speed upon
the ox.
Every evening we shall whisper together like two
newlyweds, until the morning star rises on the
horizon.
Photos from the book "Nomades du Soleil" by Henry Brandt,
© La Guilde du Livre and Éditions Clairefontaine, Lausanne.
2. ETHNOGRAPHIC AFRICA: here we find film¬
makers and anthropologists attempting clumsily at
times to portray the most authentic aspects of African
culture. The Influence of the ethnographic film has gone
beyond the domain of scientific research, and has already
greatly modified the approach of a large number of
commercial films made In Africa.
In the field of the pure anthropological film the work
of the Belgian Luc de Heusch deserves special mention.
An anthropologist turned film-maker, de Heusch has
attempted to use -the motion picture as a supplementary
tool in his scientific research. Though unpretentious,. his
films (such as Fêtes chez les Hamba, 1955) are conceived
and executed with great care, and still remain as existing
and authentic records of the cultures of the Congo prior
to the disorders of the Independence period.
By contrast, Henry Brandt of Switzerland Is a film¬
maker who turned to anthropology to make a film in
Africa. In the 1950s Jean Gabus, director of the Ethno¬
graphic Museum at Neuchatel, Switzerland, led an anthro¬
pological mission to the Niger to study,a nomad savannah
people, the Bororo Peuhl herdsmen.
He later sent Brandt to the area where he spent half a
year alone with the herdsmen. Brandt, using 16-millI-
metre, returned with a colour film of extraordinary
beauty and a sound track with musical recordings of
remarkable quality and authenticity. Jean Gabus had
told him that his purpose was not to amass "museum
documents" but to foster understanding and respect of
other men ("faire comprendre et respecter d'autres
hommes." )
His film, entitled Les Nomades du Soleil (Nomads in
the Sun) and completed in 1956, is now considered a
classic, although it has never been shown commercially.
(Commercial distribution is now being arranged and the
film will soon be shown in European cinemas Editor.)
At first these experiments were not very well received
in scientific circles. When an ethnographic film
committee was set up at the Musée de l'Homme to teach
anthropology students cinema techniques certain ethno¬
graphers raised the cry that more attention was being
paid to "picture chasing" than to scientific research.
Despite such protests an important school of ethnogra¬
pher-film makers specializing in Africa has now grown
up and as a result the making of ethnographic films is
being taken very seriously by the professional film world
itself.
In 1951, the professional film maker Jacques Dupont
turned out a really magnificent documentary, La Grande
Case (The Long House) which he shot in Western Came¬
roon, and Pierre-Dominique Gaisseau, another profes¬
sional, went off to Guinea to make a group of films,
including Forêt Sacrée (Sacred Forest), Naloutai and Pays
Bassari (Bassarl Country).
3. CHANGING AFRICA: films which attempt to show
traditional Africa in contact with the modern world and
the problems this raises (anthropologists call this "accult¬
uration." )
Here, the cinema faces the same problems as does ^3
African sociology, principally that of ignorance ignor¬
ance of the traditional cultures which are now undergoing
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ALSO DIE',
say Alain Resnais and Chris
Marker In a new French
documentary. Their highly
debatabletheme: masks and
statues are vanishing from
modern Africa and their
purpose is being lost. Our
museum pieces are thus be¬
coming meaningless relics.
Cinémathèque française
rapid change. This is no small handicap and it Is evident
in many films (mostly of the pro-national documentary
type) where we find the old dying cultures disdained and
ridiculed and little effort being made to understand
them.
The first film on acculturation in Africa was the French
documentary, Coulibaly à l'Aventure, made in 1936, and
already referred to. Fourteen years were to pass before
this subject was to be brought to the screen again. In
1950, a young student at the Institute for Advanced Cine¬
matographic Studies (IDHEC) in Paris, named René Vau-
tier, produced a clandestine film in the Ivory Coast on
the struggles of a new political party then under attack
by the colonial administration. Shot in 16-millimetre
black-and-white with a makeshift sound track, the film,
called Afrique 60, was banned in Africa and France and
has been shown only on film library circuits.
Another banned film was Les Statues Meurent Aussi
(Statues Also Die) made by Alain Resnais and Chris
Marker. It was made up of sequences filmed in European
museums dealing with Africa and supplemented by footage
from film archives on which they did an extraordinary
job of editing.
The theme was that the statues of Negro art in our
museums are denatured because their true meaning is
lost to us, and that the new African art influenced by the
West is completely decadent. (An edited version of this
violent film is scheduled to be released shortly-Editor.)
This was the period when African students at IDHEC
began to make their first films in Europe (they were then
unable to operate In their own countries.) A group consist¬
ing of Paulin Vieyra, Jacques Melokano, Mamadou Sarra
and Jarlstan (the cameraman) produced what is probably
the first film ever made by Africans. Called Afrique sur
Seine (Africa on the Seine) it portrayed the life of African
Negroes in Paris. Unfortunately the editing and sound
track were never finished.
Since 1950 films dealing with the theme of changing
Africa have been produced in practically every country
of tropical Africa. But in most of them (such as Paysan
14 Noir Black Peasant, L'Homme du Niger Man of Niger
or even Sanders of the River) Africa's traditions are
viewed as archaic and unworthy of surviving alongside
Western culture which is almost invariably taken as syno¬
nymous of progress.
But three films, I feel, merit special praise. One of
them Men of Africa, was shot in East Africa, and describes
the rivalry between educated Africans and the more
primitive forest pygmies; Carlos Vllaredobo's C'était le
Premier Chant (The First Song) In which a young French
official tries to better the lot of a bush village community
reduced to proverty by drought and lack of initiative ; and
The Boy of Kumasenu filmed by Sean Graham and the
Ghana Film Unit in 1952. It is the story of a boy fisher¬
man who abandons his lagoon village for the big city only
to come face to face with crime and corruption and
narrowly escapes becoming a delinquent himself.
Two films made by Claude Vermorel In Gabon and
Guinea belong in a class apart. In Les Conquérants soli¬
taires (Solitary Conquerors) and La plus belle des Vies
(Best Way of Life,) Vermorel takes the opposite view on
cultural change showing a European so taken by African
cultures after getting to know them that he adopts their
ways.
The political struggles for independence also inspired a
number of films but very few, I feel, can be considered
worthwhile.
4. THE TRUE AFRICAN CINEMA IN EMBRYO. The
films mentioned thus far were all attempts by foreigners
to bring their own impressions and interpretations of
Africa to the screen. But soon certain film producers
began to feel that this was not enough, that a further
step had to be taken to banish the exotic completely and
to bring cinema audiences into direct contact with the
people of Africa be they traditional or modern. This was
to mark the first stage of the true cinema of Africa yet
to come. And here again the modest ethnographic film
was to play an influential role.
The first film of this kind came to us from South Africa,
where as early as 1948 a South African pastor, the
Reverend Michael Scott, produced a 16-millimetre film,
Civilization on Trial, which showed the reaction of the
Negro himself to racial segregation. A minor masterpiece
was later achieved by Donald Swanson, of Great Britain,
with his Magic Garden which recounts the unbelievable
adventures of a Johannesburg thief. In similar vein is
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
First films made by African Negroes
Sean Graham's Highlife (renamed Jaguar) which he
filmed in Ghana.
A much graver message that of the very victims of
racialism was soon to come from South Africa when
Lionel Ragosin, of the United States, filmed Come Back
Africa in 1959. It is perhaps justifiable to ask whether
this film is not Ragosin's own cry of despair against Apar¬
theid rather than that of South Africa's Negroes. But
whatever the director's role may have been the fact is
that in his film it is the voice of Africa which speaks and
he is no longer master of what he has unleashed.
For several years I have attempted to work in the same
spirit. When I filmed Les Fils de l'Eau (Sons of the
Water,) a traditional ethnographic picture, I did my best
to avoid the trap of exoticism. Flaherty had shown me
one way of setting up a documentary. As a director he
arranged and built up a series of scenes from real life,
divorcing them from their alien background thus render¬
ing them accessible to audience the world over. But no
one can hope to equal Flaherty's success in making the
Eskimo Nanook, a real friend of people who had never
even seen an Eskimo.
I therefore decided to try another way by letting
Africans speak for themselves and putting on film their
spontaneous comments on their life, their work and their
opinions. In 1954-55 I tried this method with Jaguar,
letting three young Nigerian emigrants tell the story of a
more-or-less Imaginary journey to Ghana. (This film is
still unedited.)
In 1957, I carried out the same experiment in the
Ivory Coast with Moi, un Noir (I am a Negro.) I showed
a poor Abidjan stevedore, a silent film I had made on his
daily life and asked him to improvise a commentary on it.
The result was amazing. The stevedore, Robinson, was so
stimulated at seeing himself on the screen that he
Improvised an extraordinary monologue in which he not
only reconstructed the conversations filmed but comment¬
ed on them and even criticized himself and his friends.
5. AFRICAN CINEMA BY AND FOR AFRICANS.
I think we have now gone as far as we can working along
these lines. No matter what we attempt neither Ragosin
nor Graham nor myself will ever be Africans, and our
films will always be films on Africa made .by foreigners.
I am not implying that there is anything really wrong
with this, and it will certainly not stop us from continuing
to make African films.
But it is time for a Changing of the Guard. In fact it
has already started with the technical training of African
film-producers. Paulin Vieyra, the first African to study
at the Institute for Advanced Cinematographic Studies,
has been teaching in Dakar for the past several years. He
has made a film, slightly clumsy though it may be, called
Un homme, un idéal, une vie (A man, his ideal and life)
about the frustrations of a fisherman from the coast of
Senegal who defied tradition by installing a motor in his
canoe.
The film does not pass judgment on African traditions,
it simply states them, depicts them. And when in one
scene the trees of the forest speak and take part in the
council of the village elders, there is not even a hint of
mockery.
Lack of funds have prevented the film from being
completed, but Vieyra has other plans; he is no longer
alone. To mention only French-speaking Africa, it is to
him and his colleagues, Blaise Senghor, Tlmité Lassari,
Thomas Coulibaly, Jean-Paul N'Gasza and others that we
must look for the films we all so eagerly await.
JEAN ROUCH is Secretary-General of the Committee for
Ethnographic Films at the Musée de l'Homme, Paris and Direc¬
tor of the French Institute for Tropical Africa, Niger.
Tony Saulnier
WRITTEN IN THE SAND. Decorative design is allied to beauty of gesture in this move¬
ment captured by Pierre Gaisseau in " Forêt Sacrée" a film about the Toma people of Guinea.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
TOMORROW'S WEATHER
Will artificial satellites give us the right answers ?
by Daniel JSehrman
Artificial satellites able to measure the sun's
heat beyond the earth's atmospheric inter¬
ference, and electronic computers working in conjunction
with a "mathematical model" of the earth, are among the
means by which science hopes to solve one of the world's
most stubborn mysteries: the climate.
This was brought out by a recent symposium on changes
of climate particularly as they affect arid lands which
drew 100 scientists from thirty-five countries to Rome on
the Invitation of Unesco and the World Meteorological
Organization.
But the mystery is a long way from a solution. While
scientists can tell us the exact position of Mars 500 years
from now, they are still unable to produce absolutely
reliable forecasts about next week's weather. As for the
climate next year or in the next decade, a problem of vital
interest to agriculture, these are impossible to predict.
The symposium certainly refuted a good many explana¬
tions which have been advanced for recent changes in the
weather. Generally speaking, world temperature averages
grew steadily higher from the 1850's to the 1940's, and this
warm spell has opened Arctic ports, enabled Iceland to
16
*
«w.- m
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
CYCLONES SEEN FROM SPACE. The remarkable photos on these two pages show two cyclones as they
look from a height of 400 miles. They were taken by the U.S. weather satellite "Tiros". Above, cyclone
cloud formation in the Pacific, 800 miles off southern California. Opposite, another cyclone moving some
300 miles north of New Zealand. Both extend over hundreds of miles of the earth's atmosphere. The
"eyes" and spiral cloud bands of tropical cyclones, such as hurricanes and typhoons, have been studied by
means of radar and aircraft photographs, but a picture of a complete typhoon structure as seen from high
levels had never before been taken until "Tiros" snapped the one north of New Zealand. Such photographs
help to explain both fair and foul weather situations, how storms mature and finally dissipate themselves.
grow barley, melted permanent ice in the Scottish High¬
lands and lured a steady run of codfish to the coasts of
Greenland. These warm years, with their economic
implications, have led to a number of theories, notably
one that man is changing the weather by burning fossil
fuels and releasing millions of tons of carbon dioxide into
the atmosphere.
Unfortunately for the theoreticians, this rising tempe¬
rature curve levelled off around 1940 and has now dipped.
Temperature averages have dropped (only half a degree
Fahrenheit, to be sure) in the Arctic and just about every¬
where except for the United States, Western Europe and
the Pacific Coast of Asia.
People who blame colder weather on air pollution or
atomic explosions get no support from climatologlsts.
Changes of climate in the past have been far greater than
any we are witnessing today and they were brought about
without the relatively limited influence of man.
One fact clearly brought out by the Rome symposium
is that, generally speaking, the study of cllmaie is still a
process of hunting for the missing pieces of a puzzle, it
has not yet reached the stage where the puzzle can show
any definite pattern.
A number of scientific disciplines are engaged in collect¬
ing these pieces. Meteorology, oceanography, geography,
hydrology, geology, glaciology, plant ecology, paleobotany 17
and archeology were among the specialized branches
represented in Rome.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
TOMORROWS WEATHER (Cont'd)
Is the heat from the sun growing weaker?
The first requirement for a preview of the future is a
clear view of the past. Weather récords have only been
kept systematically for about 150 years a split-second
compared to the geological time over which the great
changes of the earth's climate have occurred. This
explains why many climatologists are studying ancient
chronicles and classical literature for more clues to the
weather of the historical past. A British delegate to the
symposium told how he is now reading through ships'
logs compiled at the end of the 17th century.
Beyond the limits of written records, the archeologist
has a contribution to make. Here, methods of dating
finds by measuring their radio-active carbon content have
proved valuable; this system of dating is also used to
determine the age of fossil tree-ring samples (the tree
rings themselves can indicate wet or dry years).
Fossil pollen is also an important clue to weather. The
symposium in Rome heard a French paleobotanist report
that, on the basis of pollen finds, he estimates the Sahara
desert to have advanced northward 1,500 miles in 4,000
years. The Sahara, now in the driest stage of its arid
history, once supported a Mediterranean type vegetation
and a grazing economy.
This trip through the past takes the climatologist into
geological time. Here, he encounters the Ice Ages which
are the biggest single factor in our weather. As one
leading meteorologist pointed out, we are still living in an
Ice Age. Ice on the earth's surface is not a "normal"
condition. We still have the mountain glaciers and the
polar ice masses which appeared during the Ice Ages.
Only the continental glaciers have disappeared.
Scientists are the first to admit how far they still are
from solving the mystery of climatic changes. Dr. R. C.
Sutcliffe, director of research in the British Meteorological
Office, put it this way: "There is still no basic theory as
to why the climate changes. We are in the same stage
as pre-Newtonian astronomy: we observe phenomena but
we have not worked out laws to explain them."
Electronic computers have a part to play in determining
these laws, if they exist (there are mathematicians who
will tell you that the earth's climate in the recent past
is like a big roulette wheel running on the law of proba¬
bilities!). In the United States, however, computers are
already being used with a mathematical model of the
earth though this "earth" is a uniform land mass without
oceans.
Artificial satellites will be able to settle a controversy
over the influence on the climate of changes in solar radia¬
tion. Whirling high above the atmosphere, the satellites
will decide if the intensity of the sun's heat is actually
changing or if variations recorded on earth are the result
of other factors.
T;hough they seek some of the basic causes of
weather in places as far away as outer space,
climatologists also place great stress on minor fluctua¬
tions which may not seem important statistically but
which can make an enormous economic difference to
agriculture in semi-arid regions.
Dr. Robert O. Whyte, head of FAO's plant production
and protection division, pointed out that farmers in the
2,500 mile African dry belt from Dakar to Khartum
assume a risk of crop failure once every ten years. If
this rate should rise to two or three failures in a decade,
then the face of the region will change.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
At the final meeting in Rome, Mr. C.C. Wallen, Deputy
Director of the Swedish Meteorological and Hydraulic Ins¬
titute, outlined some of the problems that are to be
tackled by future international research.
"It is true that the clue to the cause of changes in the
earth's climate might be found in studi-es of the heat
balance by itself," he said, "but it must be admitted that
it would be even more interesting to know also how a
certain change in »the heat balance would influence the
general circulation and ultimately the climatic elements.
No doubt the new possibilities with electronic computers
in the statistical treatment of changes in the general
circulation on one side and data obtained from satellites
will play a dominant role in the future development of
studies of causes of climatic changes as related to the
general circulation.
"On several occasions during this symposium, the
significance of climatic changes for vegetation, fauna and
man's activity has been referred to. Most meteorological
scientists dealing with the problem have, of course, no
particular reason to consider this aspect. However, in the
last fifteen years geographers interested in the relation
between man and nature, as weil as international
organizations working for the benefit of mankind, have
shown a growing interest in this side of the problem. As
mentioned, the implications for vegetation, fauna,
agriculture, fishery and sea trade of the "recent climatic
fluctuations" have been enormous."
"In connexion with its arid lands programme,"
Unesco has become Increasingly interested in climatic
fluctuations in arid and semi-arid parts of the world.
Many of those areas, where we are now trying to extend
settlement and agriculture, are considered by many to
have been set out and used for dry-farming or irrigated
in ancient times.' A highly interesting aim of future
development within the field of climatic fluctuations will,
therefore, be an attempt to establish the changes of the
margin of the arid and semi-arid lands which have
occurred in historical and prehistorical times.
"The interrelation between true changes of climate
caused by extra-terrestrial influences or large-scale
fluctuations in the general circulation of the atmosphere,
on the one side, and, on the other, the influence of man
on natural vegetation and soil erosion conditions, which
may seem as caused by a true change in climate, is a basic
problem that we have to face in dealing with all practical
consequences of climate fluctuations in both ancient and
recent times.
"In order to investigate this interrelation, it is first of all
essential to know the present climatic situation and the
way in which natural vegetation, agriculture and climate
are related to each other. The joint Unesco-FAO-WMO
project to study »the agroclimatlc conditions of semi-arid
parts of the Near and Middle East will give a firm basis
to the understanding of the agroclimatlc conditions in
that part of the world.
"I
I feel that this project should be followed up
1 in at least one pilot area within the region
by a contemporary study of the climatic development
and man's influence upon climate by reforestation and
irrigation. This is a long-term project which has to go
on for a considerable time, but It will be the only possi¬
bility of obtaining an idea of the order of magnitude of
the changes caused by man in relation to those caused by
true fluctuations in climate."
In these semi-arid lands man wields an important
influence over microclimates and much further study Is
needed on the effects of deforestation, grazing, and irriga¬
tion. Once conclusions can be reached from such data,
then the meteorologist will be able to Indicate the actual
odds Involved in large-scale land development pro¬
grammes on the fringes of the arid zone. Steps are already
being taken in this direction to designate land for agri¬
culture, grazing or lying fallow on the basis of climato¬
lógica! findings.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE STORY
A centuries-old battle
against chaos
by Mme Luce Langevin
20
"FOR ALL TIMES and all peoples", says the
inscription on this medal by which France in
I 799 planned to mark the introduction of the
metric system. In fact it only became the
country's legal and compulsory system of
measurement in 1840. The metric system
has now been adopted by about I 00 countries.
Although little recognized as such, one of the
greatest contributions of the French Revolu¬
tion to Europe and to science throughout the entire world
was the metric system," wrote the American chemist,
S. French.
To appreciate the full force of this remark, we should
bear in mind the almost unimaginable confusion in the
weights and measures used throughout the world before
the French Revolution.
It was In France more than anywhere else that the
inconsistencies were greatest. Measures varied not only
from province to province but often from town to town,
and the same name frequently applied to different
measures.
Let us take a few examples from the French Encyclo¬
paedia of the eighteenth century.
The definition given for the foot is "a measure of all
articles of commerce." The "King's foot" or "Parisian
foot" equalled 12 inches, or 144 lines (since there were
12 lines to an inch.) But, so we are told, there Were
120 lines to a foot at Rouen, 150.30 at Dole, 128.27 in the
city of Strasbourg, and 130.90 in the area surrounding
Strasbourg.
There was similar confusion in regard to another
measure of length the aune (ell), which was used for
cloth and which varied not only from region to region but
also according to the kind of cloth being measured. In
Paris, for instance, there were 3 feet 7 Inches 8 lines, 1. e.
524 lines, to the aune for linen, 526.40 lines for woollen
fabrics and 527,50 for silks. At Lille, there were 305, and
at Saint-Malo, 597 lines to the aune.
Another measurement of length, the toise, Is cautiously
described as "a measure of size differing according to the
place where it is in use." The "Parisian toise equalled
6 "king's feet".
In addition to the foot, the aune and the toise, there
were various other measures in use, including the Parisian
perche (18 feet) and the French perche (22 feet). The
nautical league was common to France, England and the
Netherlands (maritime connexions between the three
countries were then close), but the land league was diffe
rent in each province, and the farther one went from the
centre of France the longer It became.
Square measures and measures of capacity were still
more confused than long measures. The word arpent, for
example, which was an old Gaulish measure, was used
for an area measuring 100 square perches; but in the case
of the Parisian arpent the perche equalled 18 square feet
and, in the case of the French arpent, 20 square feet.
Speaking of another measure, the journal the area
that a farm labourer could plough in a day the great
chemist Lavoisier, who was at that time a fermier général
(a financier, responsible for the collection of taxes), said:
"It is a frightening thought that, in the subdivision of
Péronne alone, which is comparatively small, there are
17 different journaux."
The "dry measures" boisseau, rasiere, setier, muid and
CONT'D ON PAGE 22
THE ENGLISH YARD was established by King Henry I
in 1101 as the distance from the point of his nose to the tip
of his second finger. Drawing shows monks checking this
royal measure. Britain has not yet adopted the metric
system but its meteorological services are now to publish
centigrade temperature figures alongside Fahrenheit ones.
British and U.S. scientists have long used metric measures.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
OF THE METRIC SYSTEM
SIXTEEN MEN MAKE A
'ROOD'. A 16th century
German treatise describes
how to establish the length
of a "rood" (today the
English rod, pole or perch
1/2 yards in length).
"Stand at the door of a
church on Sunday and bid
16 men to stop, tall ones
and small ones, as they
happen to leave at the end
of the service. Make them
put their left feet, one
behind the other, and the
length thus obtained shall
be a right and lawful rood
to measure and survey the
land with, and the 16th
part of this measure shall
be a right and lawful foot."
Drawings from "Mass und Gewicht" by H.J. Von Alberti, Berlin. 1957
TO EVERY MAN HIS MEASURE
Thousands of different measures and
weights used in ancient Egypt have been
identified. The hieroglyphics at left
represent two measures of distance.
Hand denotes a measure of five fingers
width. Below it is a sign for a "small
span" the width of 12 fingers.
"Man is the measure of all things,"
said Protagoras, the first of the Sophist
philosophers. From far off antiquity to our own times the
human body has been used to define units of measurement-
finger, hand, cubit (from elbow to middle finger tip) foot and
yard.
Sometimes man has fixed his measures in terms of his physi¬
cal prowessthe length of a bow shot, the distance his voice
would carry. In Tibet peasants once used a "cup of tea"
measurement. This was the distance which a man carrying
a scaldingly-hot cup of tea could run before the tea cooled off
to a drinkable temperature.
In 16th century France, Jean Fernel, a reputed court dcctor,
mathematician and astronomer, used a mechanical distance
recorder of his own invention to establish the distance from
Paris to Amiens. Fernel fitted his device on a horse (above)
¿Zfftír.
but it worked equally well on a man. It was activated by each
step taken and a bell tinkled after a certain number of paces
had been covered. This pedometer created a sensation in the
16th century and was remarkably accurate. It is believed that
similar devices were used in Alexandria 1,500 years earlier. 21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
METRIC SYSTEM (Cont'd)
Europe's weights varied from city to city
sac which were used for grain, and the "liquid measures"
barrique, pot, pinte, chopine and feuillette which were
used for liquids, varied incredibly both from region to
region and according to the commodity being measured.
In old French measures of weight, however, things were
less chaotic. The "marc weight" or pound was used
more or less everywhere throughout the kingdom; so was
the half livre or marc, and the quarteron which was a
quarter of a livre. These weights were in the form of
goblets which fitted into - each other and made a pile,
called "Charlemagne's pile." It weighed 50 marcs al¬
together.
Yet France was not the only country where the situation
was so chaotic. The system of weights and measures
was fairly complicated, too, in the other countries of
Europe, though to a lesser degree than in France.
In England, for example, the yard was not the only
measure of length there was also the pole, the English
ell (3 feet 9 inches) and the Flemish ell (2 feet 3 inches).
There were two standard yards, one deposited with the
Royal Society in London and the other with the Court of
the Exchequer, but there was an appreciable difference
between the two which seems to have passed unnoticed
until 1791.
In the United Kingdom there were two different
measures of weight, accord¬
ing to the commodity being
measured. Troy weight was
used for gold, silver, precious
stones, medicines and seeds.
The pound avoirdupoids was
used for metals, wool, fibre,
leather, groceries and bread.
One hundred Paris livres or
Amsterdam pounds corres¬
ponded to 109.9 London
pounds avoirdupoids, 166 Ve¬
netian pounds and 146 Ro¬
man pounds.
The most widely used long
measure, the aune (ell), also
varied in value from one
country to another.
The origin of this variety
of measures, which was
common to all the countries
of Europe, is to be found in
the institution of the feudal
system.
When the countries of
Western Europe were part of
the Roman Empire, they all
used the same system of
weights and measuresthe
Roman systemwhich had been imposed on them, and
whose standards were kept on the Capitol in the temple
of Jupiter. Later, Charlemagne realized that a uniform
system of measures was an invaluable aid in maintaining
the unity of his vast empire. The measure of length,
namely, the "king's foot" and the weights of Charle¬
magne's pile were kept in the Imperial Palace.
But after the death of Charlemagne the empire was
split into small states, principalities and fiefs, each lord
being absolute master of his own lands. He thus fixed
measuring standards exactly how he wished and this
right was one of his most cherished prerogatives as he
could modify it to his own advantage. Each fief thus
gradually became a small independent economic entity.
Nevertheless the economic development in this feudal
society, which saw the improvement of craftsmen's
techniques, the appearance of the first manufactured
goods, urban development which led to a greater exchange
of goods between town and country and great journeys
of exploration by land and sea, led to a tremendous
expansion of markets.
At the time of the Renaissance in Europe, whenever a
peasant left his own village or a merchant traded with
«p cities other than his own, he found he was dealing with
different weights and measures. This was the situation
existing in France on the eve of the Revolution. The
Musée du Conservatoire National des Arts et Métiers, Paris
THE PILE OF CHARLEMAGNE was the 8th century mea¬
sure of weight of the Holy Roman Empire used in France as
late as the 19th century. The 15th century version shown
here consisted of I 3 copper weights (left) nesting in each other,
On the right the decorated case which held the weights.
bourgeoisie which ran the country's economy needed a
unification of measuring standards to encourage business
and trading which by now was being carried out on an
entirely new scale.
"The idea of standardizing" weights in France is poss¬
ibly as old as the monarchy itself," one French historian
has written. From the 13th century on, numerous royal
decrees were promulgated in an effort to standardize
weights and measures. But the only success achieved
was that the "marc weight" pound was adopted through¬
out the country for the minting of coins.
In the 17th century a council for reform set up by
Colbert was defeated by the complexities of the problem.
The following century Necker also studied the question
but had no more success in finding an answer to it.
Nevertheless the movement towards reform was gath¬
ering momentum and the basic principles of the metric
system were being more and more widely accepted among
scientists, philosophers and economists.
The need for universally accepted, consistent and
accurate measures also corresponded to the new require¬
ments of science and especially of physics. In the
hands of men like Galileo, Descartes, Huygens and New¬
ton, physics had made sudden and rapid progress and was
now a real science. If the figures arrived at in measuring
objects were to be of any scientific value, the units used
by scientist had to be clearly
defined and absolutely con¬
stant. Standard scientific
measurements were there¬
fore essential.
The time unit the second
had been fixed long before,
because of requirements of
astronomy and its practical
use in navigation. But every
scientist had long made do
with measures of length and
weight which were his own
personal property, approxi¬
mating as near as possible to
the Châtelet toise or the Pa¬
risian marc. With the rudi¬
mentary techniques for mea¬
suring available at that time,
the measures reproduced
from the standards varied
considerably.
After Huygen's famous
study of clocks and the iso-
chronism of oscillations,
scientists and philosophers
gradually came to the con¬
clusion that they should take
as the unit not an arbitrary
length such as one related to the human body such as
the toise but an invariable, universal length of which
nature itself would ensure the constancy.
In 1670, Christopher Wren put before the Royal Society
in London the proposal that this constant unit should be
the length of a pendulum which swings once in half a
second. The same year, the Abbé Picard, an astronomer
of Lyons who was renowned for measuring the arc of the
meridian in France, determined the length of the pend¬
ulum which swings once a second in Paris, and put
forward a proposal that "the length of the pendulum
swinging once in one second might be called the rayon
astronomique; one-third of this length would be a foot
and twice this length would be the universal toise.
But the experiments conducted by the astronomer
Richer at Cayenne, French Guiana, in 1672 showed that
the length of a pendulum which swings once a second is
shorter at the equator than in Paris. This, therefore
could no longer be regarded as a universal measure. But
the idea of using the pendulum was not abandoned.
In the eighteenth century, this unit was still used by
some scientists, including some of the members of the
Royal Society in London, Jefferson in the Unites States
and La Condamine in France. La Condamine was
requested by the Académie des Sciences to measure the
arc of the meridian in Peru.
CONT'D ON PAGE 24
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
A historic moment:
CASTING METAL FOR THE OFFICIAL METRE
On May 13,1874, a casting of 250 kilogrammes of
platinum-indium metal was made (above) at
the Conservatoire des Arts et Métiers, in Paris.
From this alloy international prototypes of the
metre and the kilogramme were to be made,
but tests revealed slight impurities. A new
and purer alloy was cast in London and from
this 30 metric bars were drawn. The same
alloy was adopted for the standard kilogram¬
mes. These international metric standards are
today stored with infinite precautions in the
International Bureau of Weights and Measures
near Paris. Left, the end of an X-shaped proto¬
type metric bar and, right, the international
kilogramme under its protective glass covers,
with, alongside, tongues used for handling it.
A pioneer among the world's interna¬
tional organizations, The International
Bureau of Weights and Measures came
into being in 1875 after the Convention
on the Metre was signed by 18 coun¬
tries. These States agreed to set up
the Bureau as a permanent institution
in Paris, the birthplace of the metric
system. Right, delegates to the Second
General Conference on Weights and
Measures (1895) came from 15 Euro¬
pean countries and from Mexico and
Japan. At the most recent of these
conferences in October 1960, delegates
from 33 countries adopted a new
method of determining the length of
the metre (see photograph page 25).
Photos Courtesy Int. Bureau of Weights and Measures
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
METRIC SYSTEM (Cont'd)
Reform born of the French Revolution
On his return, in 1748, he had cast a bronze rod the
same length as the second-pendulum at Del Quito and
sealed it in marble with the inscription: "A natural unit
may it become universal!" In his report to the Acad¬
emy, La Condamine stressed both the need to adopt the
decimal division and the need to choose "a fixed,
constant measure, taken from nature itself, and one that
Is verifiable in any century."
La Condamlne's plan was not the only one put forward
by scientists. Another natural unit related to the size
of the earth also had its ardent supporters. The idea
first came from the Abbé Mouton who in 1670 suggested
that the unit adopted should be the sixtieth part of one
degree of latitude, i. e., of the arc of one minute, which
be called the mille. The centuria and "decuria were to be
multiples of the mille, and the decima and céntima
submultiples of lt.
He was the first to propose the adoption of the decimal
division and stress its importance, and the remarkable
system of measures that he suggested contains the germ
of our entire metric system as it is today.
It was not until the Revolution that the material, social
and political conditions necessary for this reform came
into being. The question was raised in the Constituent
Assembly in 1790. Talleyrand rejected the toise and the
livre. "It Is not enough," he declared, "to adopt one unit
of weight and one unit of length instead of many. . . the
system must be perfect it must be based on a constant
model, found In nature, to which all nations would be
able to resort."
The scientists had proposed two different natural units.
Of these Talleyrand favoured the length of the pendulum
with a swing of one second, at "the mean latitude of the
civilized world," 1. e., 45 degrees, rather than the unit
based on the length of the meridian. So as to win the
confidence of the peoples, he advocated that new
measurements should be taken "solemnly" and in colla¬
boration with the Royal Society of London. This
collaboration was facilitated by the fact that on Janu¬
ary 13, 1790, John Miller had proposed, In the House of
Commons, the introduction of a standardized system of
measures based on the length of the pendulum swinging
once a second in London.
T1 1
24
alleyrand's plan was adopted by the Consti¬
tuent Assembly, and the Decree of May 8, 1790
Is the first statute concerning the reform, which thus
seemed to be on the point of realization not only in France
but also in England and the United States. Moreover, plans
already existed for co-operation on this subject between
the Royal Society in London and the Academy in Paris.
In the United States, the standardization of weights
and measures had been decided upon in 1787 when the
Constitution of the Union came into being; the length of
the second-pendulum at the mean latitude of the United
States (38 degrees) had been selected as the unit. Jeffer¬
son, favourably disposed to the French philosophers,
persuaded Congress to agree to the length of the pendu¬
lum at 45 degrees latitude and to follow closely the work
being done in France and England.
For political reasons, however, the standardization of
measures between these three great countries was not to
come about. A few days after the decree was promul¬
gated, the plans were upset by a threat of war between
England and Spain France being an ally of Spain. On
November 30, England announced that the arrangement
was "impracticable."
"It is much more natural," stated a report of the
French Academy, "to measure distances from one point
to another in terms of a quarter of the earth's great
circles than in terms of the length of a pendulum."
The proposal put forward by the Academy was approved
at once, and, on March 30, 1791, the scientists' choice
prevailed. The unit of length, which was defined as the
ten-millionth part of a quarter of the earth's meridian
and was called the "metre," was adopted as the basis of
the metric system.
However, all sorts of difficulties arose in connexion with
the Implementation of the project. The work which the
academicians had estimated would take two years was
far from completed when the fixed date was reached In
1793. The production of the measuring Instruments
needed by the various commissions was considerably
hampered by the» poor quality of scientific equipment
available in France.
After the Revolution, France tried to give fresh Impetus
to the manufacture of measuring instruments, but the
commissions had in fact to wait nearly two years before
they could begin their work.
Even when the technical difficulties involved in the
production of equipment had been overcome, other disap¬
pointments awaited the scientists. The Revolution had
many enemies, both in France and abroad. France was
rent by the counter-revolution and threatened by Invasion
at the time when Delambre began, starting from Dun¬
kirk, to measure his assigned section of the meridian.
Harassed by the suspicions of the people and the local
authorities, he was continually forced to have his in¬
structions verified; sometimes even his Ufe was in danger.
In Spain, his colleague Méchain was encountering other
difficulties. Spain had agreed to collaborate in the work
on triangulation, but It refused to allow Méchain to return
to France once the two countries were at war.
On December 21, 1792, the working out of a detailed plan
for reform was given to the Comité d'Instruction Publique.
On May 29, 1793, Borda, a member of the Commission
appointed by the Academy, announced the general outline
of the system proposed by the Academy. The principle of
the basic relations between the units of long measure,
square measure, cubic measure and measures of capacity
and weight was the decimal system. The length of
the metre, calculated from the results of the measure¬
ments of the meridian carried out by the Abbé Lacaille
in 1740, was selected as the basis of the system pending
the completion of the geodesic operations.
The new measures the metre, the gramme and the litre
and the new monetary unit, the franc, were to have
become compulsory on January 1, 1794. By that date,
however, France being at war, nothing was ready. Owing
to difficulties in applying the law, it was decided to in¬
troduce the new units gradually.
The metric system was actually established by the Law
of 18 Germinal, year III of the Revolutionary calendar
(April 7, 1795) which determined its final nomenclature
and prescribed the practical steps to be taken for the
Introduction of the new weights and measures throughout
the Republic.
In September 1798, it was to Talleyrand, at that time
Minister of Foreign Affairs, that fell the task of issuing
invitations to this first international congress on weights
and measures. Denmark, Spain, the Swiss, Dutch, Ligu-
rian, Roman and Tuscan Republics, and the Kingdom of
Sardinia sent representatives to Paris to acquaint them-
Unesco
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
Courtesy Int, Bureau of Weights and Measures
ACCURATE TO 1,000 MILLIONTH
Up until 1960, the precise length of the metre was fixed
as one ten-millionth part of the distance between the
North Pole and the Equator (shown at left with earlier
measurements, based on parts of the body). But scien¬
tists needed more precision and on October 14, 1960,
adopted as a new unit the wavelength in vacuo of the
orange light emitted by the gas Krypton 86 when an
electric current is passed through it. The new standard
can give an accuracy of one thousand millionth of a
metre. Above, the special lamp containing Krypton
gas with which the metre can now be determined
200 times more accurately than by the previous method.
selves with the work that had been done and to attend
the official Inauguration of the new system.
The rules employed in measuring the bases were com¬
pared, geodesic and astronomical operations were proved,
calculations were checked and the value of the kilo¬
gramme was finally established.
Le Corps Législatif, meeting in solemn session in Paris
on June 22, 1799, received a commission consisting of
French and foreign scientists who handed over two bars
and two cylinders of platinum to the representatives of
France and requested the legal recognition of these
standards as the basis of the new system.
This meeting was of great economic and scientific im¬
portance. Not only was France about to achieve the
standardization of measures and bring order out of chaos,
but the presence and approval of foreign scientists gave
the new measures the universal acceptance which was the
ambition of those who had promoted the metric system.
The Dutch delegate, Van Swinden, was deputed to sub¬
mit the report to the Assembly. The closing words of the
report were: "Lastly, we hope that this excellent metric
system will be adopted by all the nations in the world."
This hope was far from being fulfilled in the next few
years. In France Itself, there was a tendency to cling to
the old names and the old customs a tendency inherent
in the very nature of the French economy, which, In rural
areas, was particularly inaccessible to outside Influences.
Finally, the metric system became legally compulsory in
France only as from January 1, 1840.
In 1872, the International Commission for the Metre,
which brought together representatives of 29 countries,
laid the foundations for an International metric system
and established Its standards, taking as a basis the re¬
markable standards established for the Republican units
by the masterly technicians Fortin and Lenoir.
In 1899, all the countries of Europe, except
Great Britain and Russia, had adopted the
system. It was instituted in Russia immediately after the
Revolution of October 1917. England, which In 1789 came
so near to co-operating with France in the international
standardization of measures, stIU clings to its old units
the pound, the foot, the yard and every scientist
knows the difficulties resulting from the use of the
English system in calculations.
The influence of the metric system throughout the
world has promoted commercial and scientific relations
between the peoples. The first systematic attempts at
international scientific collaboration date from the
introduction of this system. It was for the purpose of
inaugurating the metric system that the first Interna¬
tional scientific conferences were held and the first inter¬
national Institutions set up, suoh as the International
Bureau of Weights and Measures, at Sèvres, which has
been in operation since 1875 and whose members meet
every six years, offering an excellent example of world¬
wide co-operation, Inspired by science.
On October 14, 1960, delegates from 32 countries attend¬
ing the 11th Conference on Weights and Measures 'In
Paris, enthusiastically and unanimously adopted a new
definition of the metre corresponding more closely to
scientific needs.
According to this new "natural and indestructable"
standard, the metre is defined as the length equal to
1,650,763.73 times the wavelength in vacuo, of the orange
emission Une of the element Krypton 86.
The history of the establishment of the metric system
brings out clearly the constant and fruitful interaction
which takes place between science and technology.
The introduction of the metric system by the revolu¬
tionary Assemblies, and in particular by the Convention
shows how scientific knowledge became part of the life
and the economy of society. It is also the first example of
scientific rationalization by society itself.
Luce Langevin, agrégée de l'Université (Physics), is an honorary
member of the staff of the Lycée Fénelon, Paris, and now
lecturer in science at the Université Nouvelle in Paris. This
article is an abridged version of a study published in Unesco's
Quarterly "Impact of Science on Society", Vol. XI (1961) No. 2.
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
One of the world's great civilizations, the Mayan, vanished
from pre-Columbian Central America in the I Oth century
A.D. When the Conquistadores arrived 600 years later
they saw only a few vestiges and ruins of their glorious past.
Amazing architects and artists, the Mayas built numerous
cities throughout their empire, some of which are still
being uncovered from the tangle of jungle which has hidden
then for centuries. The unique character of Maya art comes
from the treatment of the serpent which has left its mark
on all the civilizations of Central America and southern
Mexico. Above, copy of a relief found at Chichen Itza, Yuca¬
tan (Mexico) representing the famous "Plumed Serpent" with
human head. Below, a small temple at Pelenque, in Mexico.
26
Soviet mathematicians have succeeded in deci¬
phering the hieroglyphic script of the ancient
Mayas of Mexico and Central America with the
help of modern electronic computing machines.
Last year at a session of the All-Union Mathe¬
matical Congress, historians and linguists and
hundreds of other people packed the assembly
hall of the Leningrad Mining Institute to hear a
famous Soviet mathematician, S.L. Sobolev, an¬
nounce the deciphering achievment in a special
paper. Dr. Sobolev is Director of the Soviet Insti¬
tute of Mathematics, Siberian Division, of the
Academy of Sciences of the U.S.S.R., who was in
charge of the work on the Maya manuscripts. The
article below tells the fascinating story of the
Maya manuscripts, why electronic computers
were used, and how the deciphering was done.
When Europeans first reached Central America
they discovered on the Yucatan Peninsula the
highly-developed civilization of the Mayas. The Mayas
had built awe-inspiring cities and possessed their own
system of writing. ActuaUy it was the only system of
writing »ever invented by any of the aboriginal inhabitants
of America. The Maya priests possessed astronomical
observatories very much like those of Ulugh Beg In Cen¬
tral Asia, the huge stone edifices of which were designed
for the study of the sky with the naked eye. (1) The
calendar constructed by the Maya priests was, despite
its Intricacy, more accurate than our present Gregorian
calendar. How many centuries' observation must have
gone into »the production of such a calendar!
The Europeans, however, showed no Interest in the
Maya calendar; the Conquistadores destroyed the Maya
state and hurried the Maya books; Maya idolatry was
replaced by Christianity, Mayan young men were sent to
Catholic schools, and in a very short time the secret of
the Maya system of writing was forgotten, no one could
read the old manuscripts and, indeed, very few of them
were left to read.
(1) Ulugh Bey (1394-1449) a grandson of Tamerlane, founded about
1420 a splendid observatory at Samarkand. Under his patronage
astronomical tables were drawn up which constitute one of the great
legacies in astronomy that the Hast has bequeathed io the West.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Cryptogram technique used
to solve linguistic enigma
COMPUTER DECIPHERS
MAYA HIEROGLYPHS
by Felix Shirokov
Lecturer, Moscow Power Institute
i i i i in i n m
u it
m u it
mi it.
Ill mi II II i I
II IUI HU H I'
. I II IUI IUI H <
I I II IUI I" U "I
Novosibirsk Institute of Mathematics, U.S.S.R.
Soviet scientists using cryptogram -deciphering techniques and modern electronic computers have cracked the Mayan script. Photo shows two perfo¬
rated cards used in the operations. Computers took only 40 hours to do the job for which the human brain would have needed thousands of years.
Only three manuscripts have been preserved; they are
now in museums in Madrid, Dresden and Paris. The
Paris codex was in a bad state from the time of its
acquisition and the Dresden codex was badly damaged
during the Second World War and may be considered
as non-existent; fortunately this »manuscript had been
published and research workers are able to use a printed
copy. There are also a number of inscriptions on stone,
done in a special "lapidary" script. These, taken
together, constitute the sources of our knowledge of the
Maya system of writing.
The language of the Mayas, on the contrary, is well
known. There exist two Maya-Spanish dictionaries the
Motul and one compiled by Brasseur de Bourbourg. The
Maya words in these dictionaries (there are about 10,000
in the Motul) are transcribed in accordance with the old
Spanish spelling.
There are also some texts in the Maya language, such
as the Chilam Balam books of chronicles and prophecies
written by Maya priests using the same Spanish alphabet.
The scribes had not much idea of how to break up
phrases into their constituent words and the Chilam
Balam books contain some very lengthy word-monsters.
Furthermore, since the sounds of the Maya language
were different from those of Spanish, the scribes used
combinations of letters for each sound. It is not known,
however, exactly what sounds these letter combinations
were intended to represent.
The Chilam Balam books are based partly on original
Maya documents and describe events that took place at
the time of the colonization of the country. Lastly, there
are about a million people in Guatemala and Honduras
who speak a Maya language that differs very considerably
from that spoken four hundred years ago owing to the
changes that have taken place since the Spanish conquest.
Diego de Landa, second Archbishop of Yucatan, compiled
a book entitled Report on the Affairs of Yucatan (1566).
He believed the Maya symbols to be the letters of an
alphabet and reproduced them as such in his book.
Scholars have since tried to read the Maya manuscripts
by using de Landa's alphabet but have always been
unsuccessful. The "alphabet" actually bore little
resemblance to the symbols in the manuscripts and,
furthermore, it has been shown that the Maya system of
writing is not alphabetic.
Many years devoted to deciphering the Maya writings
have produced some results; symbols indicating dates
have been identified, individual words have been read,
and, finally, a Leningrad scholar Y. V. Knorozov, has
succeeded in reading whole phrases; Knorozov proved that
the Maya script is hieroglyphic and that the symbols may
27
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
COMPUTER DECIPHERS MAYA HIEROGLYPHS (Cont'd)
A gigantic crossword puzzle
represent a sound, a syllable or a whole concept (ideo¬
gram).
Such was the situation when three young scholars of
the Institute of Mathematics, Siberian Division of the
Academy of Sciences, tackled it; the three mathemati¬
cians were E. V. Yevreinov, Y. G. Kossarev and V. A. Usti¬
nov, »all working at the Novosibirsk Institute of Mathe¬
matics.
On the one hand there were the hieroglyphic manu¬
scripts (the mathematicians used the Madrid and Dresden
MSS) in which each character might depict any one of
the "elements" of the language a sound, a syllable or
a word. On the other hand there were the Chilam Balam
books and the dictionaries from which the elements of the
language were known. The hieroglyphic symbols had to
be correlated with these language elements and for this a
process of mathematical substitution was necessary; in
other words, for the manuscripts to be readable the
symbols had to be replaced by the language elements they
represented. There are altogether some 400 hieroglyphs
in the manuscripts, about a half of which had not been
identified when the mathematicians hegan their work.
S ucH a substitution is not difficult in principle.
All you have to do Is to sit down and try out
all possible substitutions in all possible combinations until
you strike the correct one. Unfortunately this is impossi¬
ble in practice because the number of possible substitu¬
tions is such that all the people on earth, all those
living In the past, the present and the future, would
never complete the task. And to find the solution by
guesswork would be as improbable as getting an ape
armed with a typewriter to write Alice in Wonderland.
This is where the electronic calculator, the modern,
rapidly functioning »computing machine come into the
picture. This electronic secretary was given the job of
solving a unique crossword puzzle that contained several
thousand words in an ancient language. But before the
solution could be found the appropriate data had to be
fed into the machine.
The Maya manuscripts were the work of different
scribes living at different times and the hieroglyphs
looked different when drawn by a different hand. The
first thing, then, was to identify individual hieroglyphs.
In this the Novosibirsk group received considerable help
from Y. V. Knorozov.
The scholars adopted an entirely new principle; instead
of trying to discover the meaning of separate symbols they
tackled the text as a whole. The statistical method, the
basic method used by the Novosibirsk scholars, can be
applied only »to a complete text. Furthermore, the
correctness of the "substitution" would be guaranteed
only when a text was readable and understandable as a
whole and in connexion with drawings accompanying it.
The entire mass of words constituting the Maya
language was arranged in a number of sequences that
would enable any word to be found from any of the letters
it contained, initial, medial or final; this is actuaUy what
we do when we are solving a crossword puzzle when some,
of the letters of a word are known we fill in the others
according to those already in the squares.
The Motul dictionary and the entire Chilam Balam
text (about 60,000 words) and the symbols for calendar
dates were also arranged in order and codified; Maya-
Russian glossaries were compiled for such subjects as the
animal and vegetable kingdoms, crafts, deities (with
ritual, sacrifices, etc.), astronomical and chronological
terminology and, lastly, the words most frequently
occurring.
It was possible to hazard a guess at the contents of the
Maya manuscripts from the drawings on them and the
thematic glossaries helped the search for the necessary
words. All this mass of material was recorded on
perforated cards and magnetic drums, the computing
machine's auxiliary memory. The hieroglyphic characters
were then analyzed in the same way. Finally, the
drawings in the manuscript were broken down into
elements and codified. The whole material thus obtained
was then processed statisticaUy.
Y ou will remember how in Poe's story, The
Gold Bug, William Legrand found his gold
bug wrapped in a piece of parchment on which was
written a cryptogram compiled by William Kidd the
buccaneer. It began.
53TT + 305))6*; 4826)4 -T .)4 T )
You will also remember that Legrand counted the
number of times each symbol occurred in the cryptogram
and arranged them in descending order of frequency.
Legrand assumed that Captain Kidd would not be
capable of compiling a complicated cryptogram, and
therefore decided, that each symbol in the cryptogram
would represent a letter of the English alphabet. Legrand
knew that the letter "e" occurs more frequently than any
CONT'D ON PAGE 31
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photos Novosibirsk Institute of Mathematics
PEOPLE OF THE CALENDAR
Soviet scientists E. Yevreinov, Y. Kos-
sarov and V. Ustinov compare Maya
manuscripts with the deciphering
results obtained by their computer.
Manuscripts were found to be priestly
books. Fragment, right, describes
how the gods of good and evil made
their fires. Left, a fragment from a
Maya priestly calendar indicating
when the maize god, the god of death
and other gods fired pottery. The
Mayas were amazing astronomers and
mathematicians and produced the
most precise calendar known to this
day. Scholars have long known that
the Maya monuments do not contain
a single ornament, relief or frieze
that is not connected with some date.
There is no other case In the world of
such subordination of architecture to
the calendar. The Mayas used not one
but two types of notation for their
numbers. These systems were deci¬
phered many years ago. Shown
above right are: glyphs with varying
human heads and bar-and-dot numerals
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
MAYAS VISIT THEIR ANCESTORS
Since the middle of the 19th century archaeologists have
been uncovering the remains of Maya cities in the tropical
forests of Guatemala, El Salvador, Honduras and Mexico.
The descendants of the Mayas still speak dialects resem¬
bling the language of their ancestors. Here, an Indian
family visits a museum in Guatemala City where many of
these treasures made by their forebears reliefs, sculp¬
ture and stelae are preserved. Whether the sudden
collapse and disappearence of the remarkable Maya
civilization was caused by wars, destructive epidemics or
a natural disaster of some kind is still a complete mystery.
Photos © P. Aimasy
30
F l.í
f Ml j*À
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
COMPUTER DECIPHERS MAYA HIEROGLYPHS (Cont'd)
From Poes gold bug to the seven of diamonds
other in the English language and is followed in descend¬
ing order of frequency by a, o, i, d, h, n... This gave him
the clue.
The symbol "8" was the most frequent in the crypto¬
gram and Legrand therefore identified it as the letter
"e". Then he guessed the definite article "the" and
so on, filling in the missing letters on the basis of those
already identified until he had the whole message: "A
good glass in the bishop's hostel in the devil's seat forty-
one degrees and thirteen minutes..."
The Maya priests were probably no more efficient as
"cipher clerks" than the bold Captain Kidd and it was
assumed that their hieroglyphic "cryptograms" were
compiled by the same method. The Novosibirsk mathe¬
maticians therefore decided to try and solve them by the
"Edgar Allan Poe" method.
In any language, be it Russian, Spanish or Maya, every
language element (sound, letter, syllable, etc.) occurs with
a frequency typical for the given language. An English
text written in a phonetic alphabet, say that of Bernard
Shaw, would be easy to decipher. It would only be
necessary to find the frequency of occurrence of all the
symbols used and compare it with the known frequency
of English sounds.
^>
tmKm
I
&3
The Novosibirsk mathematicians used their
electronic computer to find the frequency of
letter combinations in the Maya language as revealed by
the Chilam Balam books. Then the computer found the
frequency of occurrence of the hieroglyphs in the Madrid
and Dresden manuscripts. After that, there remained
only the job of correlating the frequencies. But here
they came up against a snag.
Let us imagine that Captain Kidd, instead of terrorizing
the Caribbean on his buccaneering trips, took a devoted
interest in entomology. Any tiny insect would then have
had greater significance for him than the sordid yellow
metal. He might even have written a Treatise on Gnats
and enciphered it. The combination of letters "gn,"
which is not typical for English, would have occurred very
frequently in the cryptogram and would have upset
William Legrand's statistical picture, even if Legrand
himself had been profoundly interested in insects; the
"gnat effect" would have provided greater difficulty for
him.
The Novosibirsk scholars came up against a similar
"gnat effect" in their work; the hieroglyphic manuscripts
and the Chilam Balam books belong to different epochs
and deal with different subjects.
The simplest hypothesis was that one hieroglyph
represented a pair of letters in the Maya language (had
each character represented a letter the script would have
been alphabetic). This was the working hypothesis
adopted by the mathematicians. The frequency of
occurrence of the hieroglyphs and that of the »pairs of
letters, however, simply refused to coincide the symbols
could not be directly identified with the letter pairs.
Could their working hypothesis possible be wrong? No!
the cause of the trouble was the specific nature of the
texts. Let us try to show by an example what the
mathematicians had to do.
Let us take a pack of 52 playing cards and
i arrange it by suits in the order spades, clubs,
diamonds, hearts, with the cards in each suit proper
sequence from ace to king. This we shall call the "nor¬
mal" order of the cards. Then let us shuffle each suit
separately and replace the cards with the suits in the
same order. The pack will now be arranged in a "spe¬
cial" order that will not differ very greatly from the
"normal" order. The cards have been shuffled by suits,
that is, within a relatively small group of cards; we may
guarantee that the seven of diamonds (card 33 in the
"normal" sequence) will not be in the first place but
will lie somewhere between the twenty-seventh and
thirty-ninth card.
In a specific text (as opposed to a "normal" one) there
is also a shuffling of letter combinations that disturbs the
normal order of frequencies. But, as we saw from the
playing »card example, the displacement is within fairly
small limits. The frequency of a pair of letters does not
change very greatly. Even in the Treatise on Gnats the
"gn" pair would not occupy first place in the frequency
list (diamond cards remain within the range of the
diamond suit).
The mathematicians took advantage of this fact and,
Instead of comparing individual characters with the
31
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
COMPUTER DECIPHERS MAYA HIEROGLYPHS (Cont'd)
Easter Island writing future target
individual pairs of letters, began to compare groups of
each. To be more precise they found which hieroglyphs
occur most frequently, the overall frequency of the first
two most frequent, the overall frequency of the first three,
and so on. They then did the same for the pairs of
letters.
In this case they found a marvelous coincidence. The
frequencies of the letter combinations in the Chilam
Balam texts almost completely coincided with the
frequencies of the hieroglyphic symbols. Half the words
in the Chilam Balam texts (frequency 50 per cent) began
with one of seventy pairs of letters, and half the
hieroglyphic groups in the Madrid and Dresden
manuscripts began with one of seventy-three hieroglyphs.
According to the working hypothesis the meanings of the
seventy-three symbols should be found among the
seventy letter combinations.
The same work was done for other groups in the Chilam
Balam texts and the hieroglyphic manuscripts, for
instance, for the final pairs of letters, the computer being
used for all these operations.
In this way, step by step, identifying and comparing,
using the computer to analyze the thematic glossaries and
calculate frequencies, the three Novosibirsk mathemati¬
cians deciphered the Madrid and Dresden manuscripts in
full. They employed only forty hours of the computer's
working time and even of that forty hours a considerable
amount of time was used up in setting the machine to
programmes of work.
Thus the key to one of the greatest puzzles in world
history was found.
The scholars are now preparing a three-volume report
on their work. The first volume will contain the Madrid
and Dresden manuscripts with an alphabetical translitera¬
tion in the Maya language and translations into Spanish
and Russian. The second volume will contain a complete
catalogue of the symbols and the third, une programmes
for the computer and the results of the mathematical
analysis.
The manuscripts proved to »be »priests' boàks of auguries,
prophecies, etc. To the left there are dates from the
Maya 260-day cycle (the Maya "year" contained thirteen
months and the "month" twenty days which gives a
cycle of 260 days).
This differed from another Mayan calendar, a true
calendrical year of 365 days, admirably calculated by the
Mayas and divided into 18 months each of 20 days and a
supplementary five-day month. For each day of the
sacred calendar there is a description of the activities of
the deities the gods fire pottery, make idols, decorate
temples, tend bees and crops (in other words they engage
in the same activities as the Mayas themselves). The
Mayas, following the recommendation of the priestly
books, planted trees, fired pottery, etc., at propitious times.
The extensive Maya pantheon contained good and evil
beings. There were the gods of the winds black, yellow,
white and red; the Lord of the Skulls and the young
maize god (maize was the chief Maya crop) ; the kindly
god of the North Star and the malevolent yellow jaguar.
There was even a goddess allotted to people who had been
hanged, for the Maya people believed that beyond the
grave there existed a special paradise for these
unfortunates...
Here are some examples from the translation:
The young maize god fires pottery from white clay;
The god of death, the destroyer, fires a pot;
The god of the North Star fires a pot;
The yellow jaguar fires a pot.
There are some phrases that sound very modern,
although the Mayas no doubt pu7, a different meaning
into them; the legend to one of the drawings reads:
"The woman's burden is the god of war."
The work on these manuscripts has been completed but
there are other systems.of writing that have not yet been
»deciphered. A special group of philologists in Novosibirsk
contemplates working on the Rongo-Rongo inscriptions
from Easter Island.
The use of mathematical methods and computing
machines in the most diverse fields of science and culture
is typical of our age. This amazing piece of work on the
Maya manuscripts is only the beginning of the applica¬
tion of mathematics to the study of linguistics and
history.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
TAGORE IN SWITZERLAND
Sir,
I read with great pleasure your fine
issue on Rabindranath Tagore (Decem¬
ber 1961). However, I was sorry that
no mention was made of Switzerland
among the reports of celebrations held
around the world to mark the 100th
anniversary of the poet's birth.
Switzerland had a place in the life
of Tagore for it was here that he
met Romain Rolland in 1926 (he had
already visited Switzerland in 1921
and spoken in Geneva and Basel) and
our country thus had a reason to join
in celebrating the centenary. A
Tagore exhibition was held in May
1961 at the National Library in Ber¬
ne, homage to him was paid by
Swiss radio stations and many arti¬
cles appeared in the press.
We owed it to ourselves to comme¬
morate the centenary of this great
citizen of the world and we did so,
perhaps »more modestly than other
countries, but with equal fervour.
Eric Deschudres
Editor in Chief
"Coopération," Basel
SOUTH AFRICA & THE BANTU
Sir,
I have seen many articles on what is
being done for education in the North
African Black States but have looked
in vain for any article or photo¬
graphs on what is being done in the
Republic of South Africa for the na¬
tive Bantu. Separate development is
condemned in almost every country
in Europe and of »course by the Afro-
Asian block, without any one of them
taking the least trouble to find out the
real state of affairs here. Is it not
your duty to enlighten them and so
establish a better relationship between
the South African Republic and the
rest of the world?
It is the money of the white tax¬
payer of the Republic which has been,
and is being used in the building of
hospitals, churches, schools, universi¬
ties, houses, and recreational centres
for the Bantu population, and now
has given them their own homelands.
There is a »constant stream of for¬
eign natives into the Republic be¬
cause of better living conditions and
higher wages than in the neighbouring
states.
D. A. Jooste
Potchefstroom, S. Africa
TWO CITIES WITH A TALE
Sir,
The story of the rebirth of War¬
saw which appeared in the Japanese
edition (May 1961) of The Unesco
Courier was most interesting.
I am a citizen of Hiroshima
which, as is well known, was the
first city to be attacked by a nu¬
clear weapon in the last war. I
was much impressed by the pictures
in your magazine which compare
Warsaw of 1945 with that of 1961.
Hiroshima too has recovered remark¬
ably since the war. I hope the
world will learn how the atom-
stricken people have rebuilt their city
and how they enjoy their peaceful
life now. The same thing may be
said of the other old Japanese city of
Nagasaki whose people also experi¬
enced the atomic tragedy. I wish The
Unesco Courier would take up the
story of the two Japanese cities.
Go Kawaguchi
Hiroshima City, Japan
FROM NORTH OF THE BORDER
Sir,
Your article about Fridtjof Nansen
(November 1961) is prefaced by the
words "a man »must and shall be
valiant, he must march forward and
quit himself like a man." Thomas
Carlyle. Carlyle was born in a village
near Dumfries in Scotland, called
Ecclefechan. He was a »Scot and not
English as stated in the article. After
all, Nansen proudly remembered and
celebrated his nationality in the
wastes of the Arctic.
Gordon Murray
Glasgow, Scotland
THE PICASSO DEBATE
Sir,
Under the title of "Letters to the
Editor" in the last months I could
view unfolding a "silent" debate about
Picasso's art. These letters urge me
to raise a question for the ardent de¬
fenders and opponents of this critical
art: Is there an art Picasso's at all?
It is abacking and astonishing of
course. But this feeling of astonishing
in the spectators is it equal to the
artistic effect? I can't believe so.
What does Picasso want to express
to man I think every artist wants to
say something for the spectators, the
world in general and in special, with
the characteristic language of his own
art by these sometimes formules, de¬
formed or distorted figures ?
Has Picasso visions? Maybe he is
suffering from some soul-sickness in
this case I can understand. One who
is suffering from serious soul or nerve
disease used to see the spherical forms
as angulars, the whites as blacks and
so on. If it were so I could under¬
stand, but the ardent followers of the
Picasso's line are protesting against
this.
Maybe there is a tendency to re
lapse the spiritual claim of grown-up
men into the level of 3-4-year-old chil¬
dren? The writer of this letter has
3 and 4-year-old children of his own
also and the creations of th»ese young
men remind me of some of Picasso's
pictures excuse me, the great artist!
Against this are protesting the faithful
defenders of this "art."
Maybe Picasso's pictures and figures
are a glove into the face of little
bourgroisie and snobs? But hélas!
What makes these nightmare matters
artistic creations? There is a debate
about this problem a couple of
decades already, but nobody could
say the truth... I should like to have
an answer besides "Mme. Camelin
likes" or "Mr. Cherkosova dislikes"
Picasso.
Dr. Alexander Hegediis
Pecs, Hungary
A PLEA FOR SURVIVAL
Sir,
It has become almost laughable for
us to express our horror at the insane
man of our various heads of
government in seeing these directed
towards an almost inevitable mass sui¬
cide. Many have gathered to pro¬
test.. .but their pleas have remained
inarticulate, for those to whom they
were addressed paid them no heed.
Aggressive policies continue.
Perhaps, as long as there are nation¬
al orientations, each government
within its own specific rationale is
helpless to do otherwise. To them
the problem appears to be a choioe
between Eastern and Western systems,
and fear, distrust and, ultimately,
hatred are the consequences. Never¬
theless the people whom these
governments are supposed to repre¬
sent see it as a problem primarily,
and most urgently, of survival.
They have not the vested interests
that would make intelligible to them
endless, meaningless hitches to agree¬
ments among leaders. Thus what they
see is the insanity of a threat to hu¬
man existence for the sake of ends
they don't understand and benefits in
which they have no share. And there
is small consolation in knowing that
they are being killed by their own
radio-active fallout and not that of the
"opposite" side.
It seems pointless addressing our¬
selves to or through our governments.
There remains only one way of mak¬
ing ourselves effectively heard, and
that is by affirming our friendship
for all people who, similarly, have re¬
mained politically mute but whose
plea, as ours, is for survival in a hate-
less, radiation-less world.
We address ourselves directly to
you.
Veronica and Brian Maltby
Sydney, Australia
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
BRAZIL'S CHILDREN'S CITY' :
About 150 miles from Brasilia, the
new capital of Brazil, another town is
being built which will provide a home for
22,000 homeless boys and girls orphans
ranging in age from one to seventeen years.
They will be grouped in "families" of six
children in separate homes and under the
care of a married couple. Covering a site
of over 1,700 acres, the Children's City
will have schools and training colleges of
all kinds, and also museums, theatres and
libraries.
ARTS AND CRAFTS TRAIN: Two
bright blue railroad coaches carrying an
unusual load recently set off on a year¬
long trip around the U.S. State of Ken¬
tucky. One coach contains exhibits of
arts and crafts from all over the U.S.A.
paintings and sculptures, hand-woven
textiles, pottery and ceramics, silkscreen
work, etchings, and examples of wood
and metal work. In the second coach,
visitors are invited to try their hand at
woodcarving, ceramics, etc. for which
tools are provided. The project was
conceived by the . Museum of Louisville,
Kentucky and has been supported by other
U.S. museums and organizations.
AFRICA'S EDUCATION CENTRE :
A Unesco Regional Centre for Educ¬
ation in Africa, which is staffed by Unesco
specialists, has been opened in Accra,
Ghana. It will provide documentation
and information, gathered from nearly
every country in Africa, on school curri¬
cula, syllabuses, health provisions, use of
recreation time, technical and vocational
training, and every aspect of teacher-pupil
relationships. A special textbook unit
will assist African authors and publishers
in preparing and producing new textbooks
and teaching materials. The operation of
the Accra Centre is part of Unesco's
emergency programme for the development
of education in Africa which has a $4
million target figure.
0 ELECTRICITY FROM THE SEA:
Soviet engineers plan to produce electricity
by using the action of tides in the Barents
Sea. The power station they are to
build will be an experimental one with
a capacity of 1,200 kws, located at
Kisleguba, northwest of Murmansk. Tide
levels in the Barents Sea can have differ¬
ences of up to 35 ft. In slack periods
turbines will be kept working by water
from a reservoir.
103 MEMBER STATES: Unesco has
now 103 member states, the latest to join
being the Islamic Republic of Mauritania.
Two other countries »Cyprus and Ire¬
land became Unesco member states in
1961, and on October 25 the Syrian Arab
Republic which had originally joined in
November 1946, resumed its place as an
individual member state.
SM Y FAIR LADY' & THE BRITISH
MUSEUM: Strange as it may
seem, the success of the musical comedy,
"My Fair Lady" directly interests the
British Museum. This Museum as well
as the Royal Academy of Dramatic Art in
London and the National Gallery of Ireland
are the chief beneficiaries of the estate of
the late Bernard Shaw. For the past three
years each of these institutions has received
about £260,000 chiefly provided by the
royalties from "My Fair Lady," the musi¬
cal adaptation of "Pygmalion".
ONE-FIFTH OF MEXICO'S BUDGET
FOR EDUCATION: Mexico will spend,
2,400 million pesos ($ 200,000,000) on edu¬
cation this year This sum represents 20 %
of the national budget and is the highest
which the country has ever alloted to edu¬
cation. The main aim is to keep education
in step with the country's economic develop¬
ment.
NEW ROLE FOR THE WOMEN OF
PAKISTAN: Women are to serve
as members of Pakistan's Legislative
Assembly. This decision, taken under the
country's new constitution, was announced
by General Mohammed Ayub Khan,
President of Pakistan, when he inaugurated
a recent conference in Karachi on the role
of women in national economic deve¬
lopment.
GABON'S SCHOOL RECORD: The
Republic of Gabon can now boast Africa's
highest percentage of school-age children
actually in the classroom a total of 80 %.
One hundred and forty new schools or
classrooms have been opened, bringing the
number of schools to 470 with 1,400
classrooms accomodating 60,000 pupils.
TRAFFIC LIGHTS THAT 'THINK':
Automatic traffic lights which regulate
the flow of vehicles electronically have
been installed in Leningrad. For a conti¬
nuous stream of traffic the "thinking"
lights change every 50 seconds, but when
there is no traffic in one direction, the lights
remain green for cars approaching from
another. The electronic device controlling
the lights is able to decide which vehicle
has priority and which should stop, and can
also count cars passing through the cross¬
roads.
A PUPPET ODYSSEY: Two young
Frenchmen, Philippe Genty and Serge
George, have left Paris by car on a round-
the-world trip of an unusual kind. With
their three puppets Alexander, William
and Zizi, they are carrying out an enquiry
into the art of puppetry in 36 countries
on four continents.
WTNIVERSITIES OF S.E.ASIA: A study
*^ of the role of universities in the deve¬
lopment of countries in South-East Asia is
to be made by Unesco and the International
Association of Universities with financial
aid from "the Ford Foundation. The study
will be carried out in Burma, Cambodia,
Indonesia, Laos, Malaya, the Philippines,
Singapore, Thailand and Viet Nam.
WORLD FILM DIRECTORY : Unesco
has been preparing for publication an
international directory listing agencies and
organizations concerned with educational,
scientific and cultural films throughout the
world. A first edition in five separate
geographical sections was published in
1952-52 and this is now being brought
up to date and supplemented.
»TNESCO TO CARRY OUT PROJECTS
FOR U. N.: Nine projects in educa¬
tion and scientific research, amounting
to 88,065,000, have been approved by
the Governing Council of the United
Nations Special Fund with Unesco as their
executing agency. These are to be carried
out in Japan, Mali, Nigeria, Pakistan, the
Republic of the Congo (Brazzaville), Senegal,
Tunisia, Uganda and Venezuela. Govern¬
ments of these countries will more than
match international aid in their own
contributions which will total more than
$21 million. Fields covered in the projects
include earthquake engineering, training
of teachers and engineers and research on
use of saline water in irrigation.
GIANT GROWTH OF RADIO & TV :
In the past 13 years since the United
Nations General Assembly adopted the
Universal Declaration of Human Rights,
including the right to knowledge and infor¬
mation radio and TV have made giant
strides. The number of radio transmitters
has inoreased from 5,450 to 11,670 and
receivers from 161 million to 366 million.
The number of countries operating regular
TV programmes grew from 4 to 65 in the
same period, and there are now 100 mil- u
2lion television receivers compared with
four million in 1948.
THEY HAVE IT TAPED: "Friendship
Tapes" recorded by schoolchildren of
the Province of Saskatchewan, in Canada,
present music and folksongs and informal
chats about the sights, sounds and activities
of children's life in that western Province.
These are then exchanged with tapes made
by children in schools in regions ranging
from the Pacific, to Europe and Asia. In
this way children can compare notes about
34 such things as Christmas celebrations in
such widely differing places as sunny Aus¬
tralia and snowbound Saskatchewan.
GOING ABROAD THIS YEAR?
Then get your copy of "Vacations Abroad 1962". Just pub¬
lished, this Unesco international repertory gives you full infor¬
mation on: vacation courses, summer schools, study tours,
youth hostels, summer camps and voluntary work camps.
Price: $1.25, 6/-, 4.50 NF
CE
z
<
o
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
JUST PUBLISHED
More and more, modern man and particularly
modern youth, lives " visually ". Film and tele¬
vision, as the most popular and powerful means
of mass communication and recreation, are gra¬
dually taking over the place formerly occupied
solely by books and by other written or spoken
material.
The main purpose of this book Is to arouse an
active interest in film-teaching among education¬
al authorities and teachers, but its practical
examples and suggestions, and especially its
chapters on film language, the appreciation of
the film as a work of art, and critical assimilation
of film content, make it a model handbook on
film-teaching. (See article page 4.)
120 p.,28 pages of illustrations.
Cloth : $4.00 20/- 14 NF
Paper: $3.00 15/- 10.50 NF
ere to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C. Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 50.-). BELGIUM. Office de Publicité S.A.,
16, rte Marq, Brussels. CCP 285.98. NV Standaard-
Boekhandel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier ( 100 FB) and art slides only : Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
1 00 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section I, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
Librería Económica, Pte Zayas 505-7, Apartado 113,
Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckách, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, 6 Nörregade,
Köbenhavn K. (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 120. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinski.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris. 7». CCP. 12598-48. (7 NF.).
GERMANY. For the Unesco Kurier, Vertrieb Bahren¬
felder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 (DM 8). Other Publications: R. Oldenbourg
Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich, GHANA.
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asai Ali Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, I ; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia House, New Delhi.
(Rs. 6.70). INDONESIA. P. N. Fad|ar Bhakti,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The Nacional Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 35, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv ( I £ 5.-).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Yen 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LUXEMBOURG.
Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND SINGAPORE.
Federal Publications Ltd., Times House, River Valley
Rd., Singapore. MALTA. Sapienza's Library,
26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-). MAURITIUS. Nalanda
Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-Louis.
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). - NETHERLANDS. N. V.
Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fl. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G.C.T.
Van Dorp 8c Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemsud, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications Centre,
I 00 Hackthorne Road, Christchurch. ( I 0/-). NIGERIA
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR¬
WAY. For the Unesco Courier: A.S. Narvesens Littera-
tur-Tjeneste, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Postboks II 5 (kr. 13.20
Other publications. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Grensen
7, Oslo. PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co.
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado
de Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-).
LIPPINES. Philippine Education Co. Inc., I 104 Castille¬
jos, Quiapo, P.O. Box 620, Manila. POLAND.
RUCH " ul.Wiloza Nr. 46, Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50).
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda, Livraria Portugal,
Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. RHODESIA & NYASA-
LAND. The Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SWEDEN. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); other publications A/B CE. Fritzes
Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse
Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. «Courier» only: Georges Losmaz, I, rue des
Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-481 I. (Fr. S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O., Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco
Courier: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033, Johan¬
nesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I. (10/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 801 Third
Avenue, New York, 22, N.Y. (5 5.00.) and (except
periodicals): Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja
Kniga, Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslo-
venska KnjTga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
From " Ultimo Incontro ", directed by Gianni Franciolini
The cinema has a tremendous emo¬
tional impact on young audiences
everywhere. The fascination of super-
productions, the excessive admiration
for film stars and the myth built up
about the screen " idol " all are contri¬
buting to the uncritical surrender of
young people to films. How can these
young people learn to be more discri¬
minating about the films they go to
see, and how can they learn to look
at a picture with discernment and
enough detachment to avoid becom¬
ing so emotionally involved that it
warps their outlook? The story pub¬
lished on page 4 offers some answers.
From " The Naked City " directed by Jules Dassin
]]>
</page>
</document>
