<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078285eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
W OPEN ON THE WORLD
l*i i¿'W»t
THE RUINS
NEMRUD
2,000 years ago
East met West
at the shrine
of Antiochus I
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
ANT EYE
ON THE COSMOS
This giant radio telescope in south-eastern
Australia, in operation since last October, is
the world's most powerful and second in
size only to Jodrell Bank near Manchester,
England. It is capable of receiving signals
from distances in the universe which are
beyond the range of any instrument, radio or
optical, at present in existence. See page 26.
Australian News and Information Bureau
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
FEBRUARY 1962
15TH YEAR
Contents
No. 2
PUBLISHED IN
EIGHT EDITIONS
Page
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
American
Japanese
4 NEMRUD DAGH
Mountain-top sanctuary of gods & kings
By Pauline Bentley
12 FREDERICK DOUGLASS, AMERICAN FIGHTER
FOR FREEDOM
Human Rights for all regardless of colour or sex
By Benjamain Quarles
15 THE INCAS OF TODAY
Descendents of a glorious past on the high plateaux of the Andes
By Alfred Metraux
22 PING-PONG DOLLS GO TO SCHOOL
Lessons come alive with Lilliputian "teachers"
By M. M. Rabecq-Maillard
26 AUSTRALIA'S GIANT «EYE1 ON OUTER SPACE
A new radio-telescope scans the universe
By Selwyn Speight
COVER PHOTO
This giant stone head of
Antlochus 1, King of Com-
magene, now lies among the
ruins of the mountain-top
shrine he erected 2,000 years
ago at Nemrud Dagh, in
present-day Turkey. Through
his Greek mother, Antlochus
traced his descent from Alex¬
ander the Great and his fea¬
tures as depicted on this
sculptured head strongly re¬
semble those of his great
forebear. (See story page 4)
© Ara Guler, Istanbul
29 LITTLE-KNOWN MASTERPIECES OF BULGARIAN ART
Revealed by a new Unesco album of colour reproductions
By A. Vassilev
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M. C. 62.1., 166 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Amin Shaker (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
»Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July end August when
it is bi-monthly ( I I issues a yeir), in English, French, Spanish, Russian, Ger¬
man, Arabic and Japanese. Sales and distribution: UNESCO Publications
Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860 (sole
distributors of the American edition). Second-class mail privileges authorised
at New York, N.Y.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted Irom THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions ol UNESCO or those of the editor» of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier if indexed monthly In The Reader«' Guide to
Periodical Literature.
Annual subscription (an/ edition): $ 5.00; Single copies:
50 cents.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
NEMRUD DAGH
for 2,000 years the colossal
statues of an East-West
sanctuary have guarded the
secret of an Anatolian king
TWENTY CENTURIES AGO, Antiochus I,
King of Commagene raised a mighty monument
to himself and his gods atop Nemrud Dagh (Mount
Nimrod) in the Anti-Taurus Mountains of present-
day Turkey. The colossal statues of Antiochus
and the deities worshipped by his Greek and
Persian ancestors still stand, but most have been
decapitated. Fallen heads of Herakles (on left)
and Zeus (right) are twice the height of a man.
by Pauline Bentley
S(EVEN thousand feet high in the Anti-Taurus
mountains of Turkey stands Nemrud Dagh, the
mount of Nimrod. On this parched and stony summit
there has lain for the past 2,000 years one of the great
monuments of antiquity, a sanctuary which by its beauty
outstandingly exemplifies the amalgam of East and West,
of Persian, Greek and Anatolian cultures. It was raised
in the first century of our era by Antiochus I, King of
Commagene, to be a "holy common room of all the Gods"
and a palace of pilgrimage for his people.
Hewn from the mountain »rock, the sanctuary consists
of three terraces levelled on the summit and decorated
with mighty statues of the King and his Gods which
tower on their bases to the height of a five-storey building.
Portrait reliefs of the "heroic company of the King's
ancestors" grace the terrace walls; above these and
the statues too, Antiochus I caused the rock chippings to
be piled into a tumulus, a great man-made false peak
rising in perfect symmetry for 150 feet on the mountain
top. Is this the King's burial chamber? Archaeologists
believe the rocky cairn to be his tomb, »but so far it has
defied exploration.
Today Nemrud Dagh looks out over an arid land from
which the ferment of civilization has long since seeped
away, but 2,000 years ago the little Kingdom of
Commagene spread in a rich and fertile vista at the foot
of the Anti-Taurus mountain chain from Cilicia to the
Euphrates River. It was a tempting, miniature buffer
state between the great powers of its world. To the
South and East lay the Parthian Empire, northwards the
Roman Protectorates of Cappadocea and Armenia, and on
the Aegean seaboard sprawled the Roman Provinces.
Well may both Rome and Persia have cast longing eyes
upon this kingdom which the Roman Consul Strabo once
described as "exceedingly fertile, though small."
Relatively little is known of its history, but it is recorded
that Antiochus I made treaty with the Roman General
Pompey in 64 B.C., preserving its frontiers until it was
finally absorbed into the Roman Empire under Vespasian
in 72 A.D.
Meanwhile, into Commagene poured the differing
cultures of Persia and of Greece to mingle with the
richness of Anatolian history. The capital city, Samsat,
the Samosata of today, commanded one of the epic
crossing-points of the Euphrates; the whole kingdom lay
astride the ancient trade routes of the Orient and the
West, among lands bearing two of the world's seven
wonders. . .the Temple to Diana at Ephesus and the fort of
Helicarnassus built in memory of the Anatolian ruler
Mausolus whence comes the word mausoleum. In these
4 regions Xenophon led his 10,000 to their fatal meeting
with the Persians and the Apostle Paul trod his dusty way
from Tarsus. Around Edessa, some fifty miles from
CONT'D ON PAGE 6
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
¿Mm
fJjß&
Ara GOler, Istanbul
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
THRONE ROOM OF THE GODS. Overlooking
two vast terraces on "the topmost ridge of my
kingdom" Antiochus I assembled these 29-feet high
colossi. These deities, whose multiple names reflect the
Greek and Persian cultures from which they sprang, in¬
clude a sun god (Apollo-Mithra-Helios-Hermes), the
Commagene fertility goddess (Fortuna), the father of
the gods (Zeus-Ahuramazda), thegod ofstrength(Hera-
kles) and Antiochus. Only Fortuna has kept her head.
Ara Güler
Is Antiochus I buried here?
Nemrud Dagh, there may sometimes still be encountered
a blonde and blue-eyed people, perhaps descended from the
Frankish Knights of the first Crusade who later passed
this way.
The stir of history has all subsided and time and erosion
have done their work. The Turkish Government are
now launching a land-reclamation programme which is
already showing some results in their effort to restore the
region to its former fertility, but so remote and desolate
did it become across the centuries that it was not until
1882 and 1883 that Nemrud Dagh first fell to the
archaeologist.
Reports written then on the sanctuary by Turkish and
German archaeologists in turn fired the enthusiasm of an
American woman geologist, Theresa Goell (1). After 14
years of research work and two preliminary visits she led
her first expedition there in 1953.
Even now the way to the sanctuary is far from easy;
then, it was accessible only by narrow winding donkey
tracks. The old processional way of Antiochus I leads
(1) A personal account by Theresa Goell of her investigations
at Nemrud Dagh was published in "National Geographic."
(Vol. 119, No. 3, March 1961.)
I
i -.»
BETWEEN TWO CONTINENTS. The small
though rich kingdom of Commagene lay astride
trade routes linking Orient to Occident. Gate¬
way to the sacred monuments of Antiochus is
this well-preserved Roman bridge of Septimus
Severus (left) on aformer royal processional route.
ROARING LION (right) carved from sandstone
guards a relief on the west terrace, depicting
Antiochus I and the sun god (Apollo-Mithra).
Lion looks down over barren slopes and valleys
of once prosperous Commagene. Today, through
drought and erosion, much of it is wasteland.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
NEMRUD DAGH (Cont'd)
MAN-MADE MOUNTAIN PEAK.
Crowning Mount Nimrod (right) is
a giant tumulus ISO feet high, raised,
stone by stone, on the orders of
Antiochus I as the crowning monument
of his sanctuary. This may well hide
the tomb of the monarch, but all
attempts to dig into the mound have
been thwarted by avalanches of stones.
Photos © Ara Guler
^ammtff K f. » Un
from the remote village of Esikartha, reached by crossing
the river by the marvellously preserved Roman Bridge of
Septimus Severus, itself a relic of great beauty (see
opposite page).
To the south, lies Karakus, the tomb of the Royal ladles
of the dynasty of Antiochus. Their tumulus is guarded
by a limestone eagle, symbol of Zeus, standing on a neo-
Doric column. The tomb appears to have been pillaged
but there are still traces of 18 columns, once with statues
on them, of which only two now stand.
Beyond, »lies the Anti-Taurus chain, dominated by
Nemrud Dagh, with its symmetrical, man-made peak
rising sharp and clear against the sky, but to the traveller
from Esikartha the sanctuary itself remains completely
hidden from view during his journey. He must toll
upwards on an hours-long arduous climb from the ancient
Anatolian village with no glimpse of his goal to spur him
on until it suddenly bursts forth in complete and
breathtaking splendour high above him.
The havoc wrought by time, weathering and casual
vandalism cannot mar the sudden revelation of the white
cone of stones »glittering in the still and »blazing light,
silently guarded by the immense statues still sentinel
in their mutilation and displacement.
The Goell expedition settled to the examination of the
sanctuary on the rocky terrain which made encampment
a painful hazard and working conditions a matter for
sheer ingenuity. In the rigorous hardship of a climate
swinging between a daytime 130° and an night-time
freezing point; without nearby water or shade; in dust,
hall, freak torrential rainstorms and at the mercy of an
occasional marauding bear, they surveyed the shrine,
clearing It with difficulty of debris. There was no room
on the summit to put this and it liad to be carried
painstakingly down the mountain in wooden litters.
It soon became obvious that Nemrud Dagh warranted
more than one season for its thorough exploration.
Theresa Goell and her team spent five years' dedicated
work there, helped by the sponsorship of the American
School for Oriental Research and with the aid of the
Bollinger Foundation and the American Philosophical
Society. Far from being the crude product of some seml-
barbarian monarch as had been suggested, the beauty of
the shrine established It as one of the glories of the
Hellenistic world.
Not only the sculptured figures of Antlochus and hLs
Gods with their attendant eagles and lions, but also their
sandstone relief portraits cut into the walLs running the
length of the East and West terraces show the purity of
form and line of the great classical tradition.
The ceremonial heart of the shrine Is the Persian fire
altar on the East Terrace. Earlier expeditions had
described a "mighty stairway" to It, but the Goell expedi¬
tion revealed this to be a double podium cut Into the rock
with inscriptions indicating reliefs cut In its walls.
Majestically facing the fire altar, with the tumulus of
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
lb-
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
NEMRUD DAGH (Cont'd;
Mountain-top terrace
of a king & his gods
FALLEN HEADS OF DEITIES litter the west terrace of Nemrud
Dagh (right) giving it the appearance of a huge open-air studio of some
monumental sculptor with, as a back-drop, the bleak eroded slopes
of the Anti-Taurus mountains. Though now shattered by earthquakes,
erosion and vandalism, the deities still seem marvels of engineering
skill. Upon their platform, they rose as high as a five-storey building.
FACE OF ZEUS pitted and scarred by weather and erosion (below)
now stares sightlessly from the west terrace. Other decapitated head
In rear is that of Antiochus I who built and endowed the sanctuary.
Headdress worn by Antlochus shows his paternal links with Persia.
LION HOROSCOPE (be¬
low) was found on east
terrace. Though a similar
one was discovered 70 years
earlier, new information has
been drawn from stars and
other engravings. These
markings on this relief of
a stylized lion give the date
of the horoscope as July 61
or 62 B.C. possibly
when the shrine was built.
a,.2L' A. . >? v'-.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
.
&' V
Photos O Arj CUler
TOMB OF THE ROYAL LADIES
of the dynasty of Antiochus Is at
Karakus which lies to the south of
Nemrud Dagh. The burial tumulus
here is guarded by a limestone eagle
(right) symbol of Zeus, standing on a
neo-Dorlc column. At Karakus there
are also traces of eighteen columns
that were once crowned by statues.
£
m&
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
NEMRUD DAGH (Cont'd;
>2*T^
Ara Güler
GUARDIANS OF THE SHRINE, these eagle and lion heads keep a faithful
vigil over the monuments and statues of Nemrud Dagh as they have done
since craftsmen hewed them from the] mountain rock twenty centuries ago.
The eagle was a familiar motif in ancient Anatolian and Mesopotamian art.
Heritage of both Greece and Persia
10
rock chippings at their back, there still sit, though shaken
and dismembered by earth tremors, an imposing array of
25 to 29-foot high statues reflecting the hybrid culture
from which they spring.
First comes the Sun God, Apollo-Mithra-Helios-Hermes ;
then the Commagene Fertility Goddess Fortuna; next to
her the Father of the Gods, the "Thunder Shaker," Ahura
Mazda-Zeus. Next to him sits Antiochus I himself,
flanked by the Hero God of strength, Herakles-Artagne-
Ares. All the statues, except the Goddess Fortuna have
lost their heads across the years, the mighty head of
Apollo Mithra being discovered when the Goell expedition
were clearing a trench on this terrace to copy inscriptions
cut into bases of the statues.
These Inscriptions give a history of the sanctuary
"I, Antiochus," reads part of them, "have raised this
place to my own glory and that of my Gods." They show
he endowed the shrine with Royal estates, staffed it
with priests and musicians and decreed "everlasting"
monthly ceremonies there. The 10th day of each month
commemorated his accession to the throne, and the 16th,
his birthday.
An important discovery by the Goell team on the East
terrace was a "lion horoscope" similar to the one
discovered on the West Terrace in 1882 which gained fame
as the first known Greek horoscope. Professor Otto
Neygebauer of Brown University, Boston has identified the
19 stars scattered on and near its body and the conjunc¬
tion of the three planets Jupiter, Mercury and Mars,
giving the date of the horoscope as July 61 or 62 B.C.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
© Ara Güler
BEARDED HERAKLES (foreground) and handsome Apollo are two heads
broken off from the mighty statues at Nemrud Dagh, two members of a ruined
pantheon of the gods. Standing on the court of the west terrace, they look like
giants who have been buried to the neck in the rocky soil of the mountain sanctuary.
This may be taken as the possible date of the shrine's
foundation and has been of very great value in the dating
of other Hellenistic monuments.
Among other valuable discoveries was the sculptured
head of Antiochus, some 16 feet (5 metres) high, lying
amidst the fallen heads of his gods and guardian animals
on the West Terrace. It Is of calm and striking beauty,
and bears a strong likeness to Alexander the Great, from
whom Antiochus claimed descent on his mother's side.
The head wears a Persian headdress to remind us that he
also claimed descent from the Aechemenid dynasty of
Persia, through his father.
The relief portraits on this West Terrace show him,
adorned with the lion emblem of royalty and guarded by
a sandstone lion statue, facing Apollo-Mithra as an equal.
for Antlochus I claimed not only descent from the rulers
of Greece and Persia, but considered himself Immortal.
One of the inscriptions in the sanctuary reads "the
topmost ridge" of the kingdom "is the one in closest
proximity to the heavenly throne of Zeus."
It was this Inscription and the discovery of a rock core
under the east side of the tumulus which encouraged
Theresa Goell's conviction that Antiochus I lies buried
under the tumulus he raised. Excavations were started
but they resulted only in avalanches of stone which made
continuing impossible. Twenty centuries after its erection
the shrine of Nemrud Dagh has been brought before us
by description, photograph and film but its final enigma
remains unsolved: the great pile of rock upon its summit
keeps Its secret still.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
FREDERICK DOUGLASS
STILL A YOUTH, Frederick Douglass
began his campaign for the abolition of
slavery. He was himself an escaped slave
from a plantation in the State of Maryland.
by Benjamin Quarles
All photos Frederick Douglass
Historical Association
D uring the four years from 1961 to 1965,
the United States is observing the one hun-
dreth anniversary of a hard-fought war between two
sections of its country, the North and the South.
According to the man who was President when the war
broke out, Abraham Lincoln, one of the great goals of
the struggle was to give to America "a new birth of
freedom." To no group in the United States did these
words mean more than to its Negroes. And to no person
did these words mean more than to Frederick Douglass.
Frederick Douglass, the most prominent American
Negro of the nineteenth century, devoted his life to
extending the boundaries of freedom for his fellow man.
He believed that everyone was entitled to liberty: "Man
was born with it," said he. And so for half a century,
from 1845 to 1895, he made himself a spokesman for the
oppressed and downtrodden.
Douglass was devoted to the cause of freedom because
he knew what it was not to be free. For he had been a
slave. In 1817, when he was born, slavery Was a well-
established institution in the southern section of the
United States. Slavery had deep roots in America, going
back almost to the time when the British founded the
American colonies, beginning with Virginia in 1607.
When the United States became an independent nation
in 1783, it seemed as though slavery was doomed to die a
natural death. But ten years later, a machine was
invented, the cotton gin, which made it possible to
separate the seeds from the fibre. In America and in
Europe there was a great demand for cotton. To meet
this demand a labour supply was nec»sssary. Negro
slavery was the answer to this need.
In being born a slave, Frederick Douglass was like
12 hundreds of thousands of other Negroes In the United
States. But no other slave was destined to become so
well known. From such humble beginnings as his, very
few Americans ever went so far. The key to his success
was his striving for freedom, for himself and for others.
As a young slave on a plantation in Maryland, Douglass
was not satisfied with his lot. He held imaginary conver¬
sations with himself, asking himself these questions:
"Why I am a slave? Why are some people slaves, and
others masters? Was there ever a time when this was not
so?"
To prepare himself for freedom, Douglass wanted to
learn the alphabet. His masters tried to prevent him from
learning how to read and write, but Douglass was not
easily discouraged. His first »pennies were secretly spent
in buying spelling books and in paying other boys to help
him to understand them.
In 1838, after twenty years in bondage, Douglass escaped
from his master and settled in the North, where slavery
no longer existed. For three years at New Bedford,
Massachusetts, he worked as an unskilled labourer, taking
any job he could get sweeping chimneys, sawing wood,
driving a coach or waiting on table He had a growing
family to support, having married a few days after his
flight from his master.
But his responsibilities as a husband and a father did
not prevent him from taking an interest in the activities
of the abolitionists. These were a group of men and
women who were dedicated to the overthrow of slavery,
which they considered the greatest evil under the sun.
They were opposed to slave-ry for two reasons: for what
it did to the slave, and for what it 'did to such civil
liberties as freedom of speech and trial by jury. In
Massachusetts these reformers were led »by two able men,
William Lloyd Garrisson, editor of The Liberator, and
Wendell Phillips, one of the greatest orators of the
nineteenth contury.
In August 1841 the Massachusetts abolitionists held a
meeting at New Bedford, and, Douglass, to his surprise,
was asked to say a few words. He was nervous, but he
spoke with deep feeling, telling of his recollections of
slavery. His listeners were impressed by his story and his
manner of telling it, and they urged him to join their
ranks as a lecturer and agent. The young Negro gave his
consent, thus taking a step he never regretted.
SiChooled by the abolitionists, Douglass soon
became one of their prize speakers. His
imposing physique, his finely formed head, his flashing
eyes and the rolling thunder of his voice, all fitted him
for the public platform. "In listening to him," wrote a
contemporary, "your whole soul is fired."
Slavery also felt the weight of the Douglass pen. Within
four years after he had joined the abolitionists, he had
developed a forceful prose style, direct and vivid. His
"Narrative of the Life of Frederick Douglass," which he
published in 1845, became a best seller on two continents,
being translated into French and German.
This book was a bitter condemnation of slavery, and
it could not fail to stir up sympathy for those In bondage.
"I never saw my mother," ran one of the opening
sentences, "to know her as such, more than four or five
times in my life; and each of these was very short in
duration, and at night."
Following the publication of his "Narrative," Douglass
crossed the Atlantic, going to the British Isles. There for
nearly two years he denounced American slavery before
large and sympathetic audiences. His success abroad was
great; British admirers raised money to purchase his
freedom from his former master, and to enable him to
start a weekly newspaper of his own.
In addition to speaking and writing, Douglass took part
in another of the organized forms of action against
slavery the underground railroad. This was the name
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
A SLAVE WHO BECAME
FREEDOM'S TRUMPET
' r s
IN LATER LIFE, a renowned orator, writer and lecturer, Douglass saw
his own people freed ( I 863). In I 877 he became U.S. Ambassador to Haïti.
given to the practice of assisting runaway slaves by
providing them with food, shelter and money, as they
made their ' way to Canada. Himself an escaped slave,
Douglass was strongly in sympathy with those who made
the dash for freedom. The fees from many of his lectures
went to aid fugitives. '
His home in Rochester, New York, was a headquarters
for runaways. When he went to his printing shop in trie
mornings, it was not unusual for him to find fugitives
sitting on the steps, waiting for him. Such runaways
traveled at nightduring the daytime their abolitionist
friends hid them from prying eyes. Douglass knew where
to take them, to a sail loft, to an out-of-the-way barn,
or to the quiet home of a trusted sympathizer. When
darkness fell, Douglass sped them on their way toward
the Canadian border.
Douglass's Interest in freedom included woman's rights,
a movement in which he was one of the pioneers. In the
America in which Douglass came to manhood, the women
did not stand equal to the men In the eyes of the law,
being denied the right to make contracts, to testify in
court, and to vote. Douglass opposed these unfair
restrictions. His weekly newspaper, The North Star, In
its first issue on December 3, 1847, carried on its masthead
the words, "Right Is of no sex."
Seven months later, at Seneca Falls, New York, the
woman's rights movement in America was formally
launched. At this historic meeting, Douglass took a
prominent part, being the only man to do so. Many
of the delegates to the convention were hesitant about
asserting that women should have the right to vote, but
in a stirring address that changed many minds, Douglass
pointed out that political equality was vital to the
women's cause.
With the coming of the war between the North and
the South in the spring of 1861, Douglass bent his efforts
13
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
Human rights for everyone
regardless of colour or sex
s»
to urging President Lincoln to liberate the slaves. To
Douglass the war was a crusade for freedom, and he tried
to impress this point of view on Lincoln on his two visits
to the White House. The Negro leader was overjoyed
when, on January 1, 1863, Lincoln issued the Emancipation
Proclamation, declaring free the slaves in the South. It
was, said Douglass, "a day for poetry and song."
Too old to shoulder a gun himsef, Douglass »became a
recruiting agent, traveling through the North urging
Negroes to join the army. The first two recruits he
signed up were his own sons, Lewis »and Charles. As a
recruiter and as a lecturer supporting the Nothern cause,
Douglass continued his labours until the South laid down
its arms in April 1865.
After the war, Douglass was destined to hold three
public offices: President Hayes appointed him as Marshal
of the District of Columbia in 1877; President Garfield
appointed him as Recorder of Deeds for the District of
Columbia in 1881; and President Harrison appointed him
as United States Minister to Haiti in 1889.
Between these last two appointments, Douglass spent
one year traveling In Europe and the Near East. He took
in all the sights, making it a point while in Paris to see
the tomb of Lafayette, the general who had helped
America win her independence. "This patriot has two
countries of his own," said Douglass, and therefore his
burial plot was "doubly sacred ground." Douglass was
especially glad to make the acquaintance of such a
champion of human liberty as the eighty-one-year-old
member of the French Senate, Victor Schoelcher, who in
1848 had framed the decree that freed the slaves in the
French colonies.
But whether abroad or at home, whether in office or
out of it, Douglass never lost his deep concern for human
freedom. He never stopped speaking and writing on
behalf of the underdog. Those who were discriminated
against at the polls or in the job market could depend on
him to cry out for them. He viewed the lot of the Negro
not as a race struggle, »but as a human struggle. He hoped
that the day would come when everyone in America would
have equal opportunity, regardless of differences in
ancestry, sex, religious beliefs, or skin color.
Douglass did not live to see that day; he died in 1895.
But to the making of a free America he gave his best and
his all. Such devotion to liberty left its mark on his
generation, and it has its lessons for our own troubled
times.
BENJAMIN QUARLES, professor of history- at Morgan State
College, Baltimore, Md., U.S.A., is the editor of the autobiography
of Frederick Douglass {Belknap/Harvard University Press, 1960),
and the author of "The Negro in the Civil War".
DRIVE TO PRESERVE
DOUGLASS' HOME
AS SHRINE
14
In this white brick house at Cedar Hill in Anacos-
tia, a section of Washington D.C., Frederick Doug¬
lass spent his last years. Here, surrounded by
his papers and books and copies of his abolitionist
newspaper, The North Star, he died on February 20,
1895. By 1961, this once beautiful home was run¬
down with unkempt grounds and in dire need of
repair. The National Association of Coloured
Women's Clubs (N.A.C.W.C.) launched a nation¬
wide campaign in February 1961 for 850,000 to restore
Douglass' home to its original state and preserve
it as a national historic shrine. In response to
this appeal, the President of the United States
wrote the President of the N.A.C.W.C, Mrs. Rosa
L. Cragg : " Frederick Douglass is a part of the
legend of America. As a successful fighter for
freedom a century ago, he can give inspiration-to
people all around the world who are still struggling
to secure their full human rights... " The National
Association of Coloured Women's Clubs numbers
100,000 women in 1,500 clubs in 40 states. It was
organized in 1896, just one year after Douglass
died. Through its national headquarters in Wash¬
ington D.C., the Association is a national clear¬
ing house for nonpartisan information and works
for better race relations and international under¬
standing. N.A.C.W.C. state federations either own
or have helped start facilities for under-privileged,
handicapped or delinquent youth in most of the
Southern states. Proceeds from an N.A.C.W.C,
drive for Unesco Courier subscriptions are to be
used to restore Douglass' home to its former state.
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
THE INCAS OF TODAY
by Alfred Métraux
No civilization ever dies completely. Even If its
creators disappear, they hand on to their suc¬
cessors some part of their own experience. Thus, as long
as there are people who identify themselves with the
original culture, no external pressure has the power to
erase it. The Indians of the Andes, whose ancestors were
subjects of the Incas, offer us the most striking example
of this fact.
Four hundred years have passed since the day Novem¬
ber 16, 1532that Pizarro and his hundred and fifty com¬
panions, treacherously seizing the Inca monarch Ata-
hualpa at Cajamarca, destroyed the greatest Empire ol
the New World.
During these four centuries, life has been hard for the
Peruvian Indians and they have experienced many
changes of fortune. Their economy has been uprooted,
their social order transformed and their religion reduced
to the status of dubious and unpalatable beliefs. Despite
these ruthless changes and the desperate poverty Into
which they fell, the people have preserved part of their
cultural heritage almost Intact. The old Inca civilization
is not dead. Its roots are still healthy, and It may well
one day produce new shoots. Under a European veneer,
there still survive Institutions, patterns of behaviour and
beliefs which the white man has been unable to tamper
with and spoil.
The outward signs of the highly developed civilization
so admired by the Conquistadors when they penetrated
into the Andes disappeared a few years after the collapse
of the Inca Empire. The highways, bordered by low walls
and shaded by trees, were abandoned or broken up. Sus¬
pension bridges were neglected, the palaces and even the
towns were destroyed. The marvellous organization of
this State, which has been called a "socialist" one, suf¬
fered the same fate. The State granaries were pillaged,
the relay system of communications was Interrupted, and
the inhabitants were obliged to settle afresh in towns
and villages of European type.
Thirty years after the conquest, the population of the
Empire was reduced by half, If not by two thirds. Yet
15
CONT'D ON PAGE 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
INCAS OF TODAY (Cont'd)
MARKET DAY in a tiny village on the high Andean plateau of Peru brings together Quechua Indians with
their livestock and vegetables from the surrounding countryside. In the mountains of Peru and Bolivia, the
16 Indians have retained much of their ancient systems of social organization, including the ayllu in which small
groups of families united by a common origin, soil and creed, joined forces to work the. land. Today, how¬
ever, these descendants of the Inca Empire are modernizing and developing their farming methods.
Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
^*
Jl^^*^fc&.
. 	 ;
fit' |V
1 7m
** 9 > V
ft- ». u
l'f)1
mv
k ?
Photos © Pierre Verger RELIC OF THE PAST Is this taclla, a metal-pointed staff used for breaking the soil. Indians who live on the
mountain slopes still use this method but those deep In the valleys use ploughs drawn by oxen, the women
following to break up the earth clods. Left, Indian boy, carrying his baby brother, rests against a village wall.
these misfortunes did not break the Indian spirit. Whilst
it seemed probable in the eighteenth century that the
Andean Indians would, in their turn, disappear very soon,
the Century which followed has produced an expansion
of such magnitude that today there Is a population oí
almost six million within the borders of the ancient
Empire, from southern Colombia to central Chile. In this
expanding Indian population, the precursory signs of a
great renaissance are perceptible. The time is therefore
ripe to see what they have retained of the glorious civili¬
zation of their ancestors.
Let us first consider language, which is an instrument
of culture. The language of the Incas, called Quechua,
is still spoken by nearly five million people, although
some Indian groups have adopted Spanish. Yet some
mestizos (men and women of mixed blood) and even white
men have made Quechua their native tongue. Today,
Quechua is more widely spoken in South America than
it was when the Inca Empire was at the height of its
glory. It was imposed by the Spanish missionaries on
tribes which, though formerly under Inca domination,
had maintained their own national tongues. These same
missionaries spread it to the tribes of the Amazon region
and thus the language of the Incas conquered territories
which had never seen the armies of the Empire.
Along with the language went a whole folklore of a
wealth which Is only just beginning to come to light.
Many an old myth, thought forgotten forever, has sur¬
vived in the memory of the country people. Patient
research may enable us to discover the vestiges of legend¬
ary cosmogonies and cycles assumed to have been lost
beyond recall.
In the mountains of Peru and Bolivia, the Indians have
remained faithful to their ancient social structures. The
ayllu, or small groups of families united by a common
origin, soil and creed, which formed the multiple cells
of the Empire of the Incas, have resisted all efforts to
disperse them. They became the nuclei of the "commu-
nldades," which succeeded in regaining a legal status
and around which the life of the Indians was reorganized.
Although, today, the "communities" no longer carry
out an annual distribution of collectively-owned lands,
they continue to exploit common land and refuse to sur¬
render any property belonging to the community. Mutual
assistance between families is still a strict obligation;
each must help in tasks performed for the common good
and must take part In religious rites honouring the pro¬
tective Saints who replaced the pagan gods. They defend
the frontiers of their community as fiercely as they did
in the old days, when the Incas had not yet incorporated
DANCING MASKS are frequently ceremonial trappings
which long ante-date the Indians conversion to Christianity. 17
The many festivals of the Catholic liturgy have served as
a pretext for rich and varied forms of religious expression.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
INCAS OF TODAY (Cont'd)
18
Europeanized clothing
& centuries-old fabrics
them in a single state. Village patriotism is still ardent.
As in the past, it finds expression In a rivalry which
should be turned to good account.
Some of the "communldades" have taken the initiative
of modernizing themselves, but without renouncing their
old system of organization. Many of them have founded
extremely prosperous agricultural co-operatives and large
amounts of communal money are deposited in banks.
This is a very modern aspect of the old community spirit
of the ayllu of four centuries ago.
On the other hand, economic life has greatly changed
since the Conquest. To the flocks of llamas and alpacas
which the Indians put to graze on the puna, or high pla¬
teaux, sheep have been added and most families own a
bull or a cow, and often mules or donkeys.
Nowadays cheese has become a basic food item whereas
formerly the Indians knew nothing of milk products.
Maize and potatoes are still staple. foods, but barley, corn
and beans are now grown wherever the climate allows.
On the mountain slopes, as in the days of the
Incas, the Indians are still to be seen breaking
up the soil with the taclla, a metal-pointed staff. Deep
in the valleys, however, the old Roman swing-plough,
drawn by oxen is followed by women whose task is to
break up the clods of earth with stone mallets. Although
the plough may be Spanish, the festival atmosphere at
seed-time with the songs and dances of the labourers, is
essentially Indian.
Travellers tend to imagine that the Indians of today, in
their picturesque costumes, outwardly resemble their
ancestors. In fact, this is not true at all. The native
costume has changed considerably since the Sixteenth
century. In appearance, a present-day Indian woman
would only be distinguishable from a Spanish peasant by
the wide, brightly-coloured belt round her waist and the
shawl covering her shoulders, held in place by a silver pin
on the breast.
As for the men's costume, it is entirely Europeanized:
trousers, waistcoat, jacket and felt hat. The woollen
bonnet and the poncho, which are generally considered
to be Indian survivals, were unknown before the Colonial
period. However, as in the days of the Incas, the women,
whether seated or walking, never stop their spinning.
Their spindle has not changed: it is a wooden stick,
weighted by an earthenware spindle whorl. The loom
has not altered, either, with the passing of time ; It always
consists of two wooden bars, one of which is attached to
the weaver's waist, and the threads of the warp are
stretched between them.
The designs of the woven fabrics of today recall those
embellishing the materials found in tombs. When I
was in the Indian village of Chlpay, the Indians were
astonished that I was collecting old and very dirty
fabrics, not realizing that the specimens they were exa¬
mining, and which they thought I had bought from one
of them, had actually come from prehistoric tombs.
Nevertheless, even in a sphere where traditions die hard,
Spain has left Its mark. One of the favourite designs
with which the Indians decorate their tissues is none
other than a stylized version of the two-headed eagle of
the Hapsburgs.
Despite the merciless suppression of idols and Idolaters
by the Spanish missionaries, the Indians, outwardly good
Catholics, have by no means abandoned their prayers
and sacrifices to the ancient Andean deities. These are
still worshipped on the mountain peaks, where strange
structures suggest equally strange rites. On the hill¬
tops, the motorist passes cairns, each surmounted by a
cross, to which the Indians, seeking an escape from
weariness and a means of placating the local spirits, make
CONT'D ON PAGE 21
,,
- me.--
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
. *-y* . ... - _
^ - ' - .
-;^r' .BLEAK ROAD TO TOWN.- Against a pano>anta of eroded
pinnacles at rbck^these -Indian women lead their mules and
-TU '" sheep to"a mar^el^towiVhigh/jn the Bolivian plateau La Paz.
r^ mUTi i *^» *~ ». i - T^ - w :»W
M - * ii" . Vai
**.-« . **~!" -A
19
« " .
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
Photos © Pierre Verger
MIGHTY RAMPARTS of fortress
near Cuzco in the Peruvian Andes
(above left) proclaim architectural
and building skill of the ancient Incas.
Using manpower on a vast scale, the
Incas raised their walls and buildings
with stones of prodigious size weighing
many tons. No mortar or other bind¬
ing material was used and such was
the Incas' skill in cutting and fitting
the blocks together that even today
a knife blade will not slide between
the joints. (Above right), mountain-
girt ruins of another Inca city, Macchu
Picchu, which remained unknown to
the outside world until 1911. Since
then, rich archaeological discoveries
have produced a revealing picture of
the remarkable civilization whose
empire spread over much of western
South America. Many present-day
Indians in Bolivia, Ecuador and Peru
(like those on left, wearing diversi¬
fied headgear and ponchos) are des¬
cended from the Incas. In moving
photo (right) a Peruvian Indian father
greets his daughter. Woollen garments
are woven in ancient Inca designs,
but man's hat is of Spanish origin.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
INCAS OF TODAY (Cont'd)
ktgßf"
i«3flttia1>»«-.-
On the high plateaux
of the Cordillera
ritual offerings of stones or quids of coca. Among the
deities of the Inca Panthéon, only the Earth-Mother, the
Pacha-Mama, and the Llghtnlng-God have kept all their
prestige. The Indian cherished the Pacha-Mama above
all supernatural beings, and In the prayers which he
addresses to her, he Identifies her with the Virgin, calling
her "Santa Maria Pacha-Mama."
There Is no church or chapel so poor as to lack a
statuette of Santiago (Saint James), the warrior saint,
patron of Spain and the Conquistadors. Portrayed as a
seventeenth-century knight, In cape and feathered hat,
he brandishes his sword and crushes the devil under his
horse's hooves. For the Indians, Santiago Is the lord of
lightning Apu-illiampu. It Is In his honour that llamas
are sacrificed at places struck by lightning. Human
beings who arc struck by lightning and survive are,
moreover, called "sons of Saint James," and are Invested
with mystical powers which turn them Into magicians and
sorcerers.
In addition to these great deities, the Indians
continue to worship countless spirits, dwelling
In the mountains, rivers, pools and lakes. Houses are
placed under the protection of a spirit which takes the
form of a wild cat or a hawk, and receives blood sacrifices.
The religion of the Incas does not hide Its face In
shame In remote valleys or the hamlets of the high plat¬
eaux. It stalks boldly abroad In the large towns of the
Interior. Thus, one sees blackish stains on the walls
of modern houses In the capital of Bolivia: traces of
blood-oiferlngs made to the local god and to the Pacha-
Mama. Similarly, at the entrance to the towns, quids of
coca are stuck to the walls of the outlying houses; these
are propitiatory offerings made by the Indians to the gods
worshipped by ancestors before they came to live among
the white men.
The many festivals of the Catholic liturgy have .served
as a pretext for rich and varied forms of religious express¬
ion. The date of the popular festivals which corres¬
pond to those of the great ceremonies of the Inca Empire
have given secondary festivals primary Importance. In
this way, Corpus Christi has replaced the inti-raymi, the
great festival of the Sun-God. The Feast of the Invention
of the Holy Cross (May 3), which coincides with the agri¬
cultural celebrations once held at the beginning of the
harvest, is a pretext for dancing and rejoicings which the
nature of the feast Itself docs not Justify. The costumes
of the religious brotherhoods for the cult of the saints
are often simply survivals of the trappings worn by the
dancers of the pagan age.
The Indians have not forgotten their ancient sovereigns.
They speak of a mysterious personage called Inca-ri, who
founded Cuzco and was murdered by a rival. "Ills head,"
they say, "was burled at Lima. For some years past, it
has been growing a new body, and soon Inca-ri will come
back and bring good fortune to the Indians." It is in
this naive and mythological way that the Indians express
their obscure hope of seeing better days.
Whilst everywhere else In South America the Indian
tribes are doomed to extinction or will merge with the
remainder of the population, there is still, in what was
once the Empire of the Incas, In Ecuador, Peru and Boli¬
via, a vital element which must be reckoned with. In
some of these countries it represents over half the
population. These people, as they become more educated,
look to their glorious past and discover in it grounds for
their confidence in the future.
ALFRED METRAUX, noted anlhropologiil, is in charge of
"Human Rights" in the Department of Social Sciences of
Unesco. His newest book, Les Incas (Editions du Seuil, Paris)
will he published this spring. He is a frequent contributor to
The Unesco »»Courier.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Modern scientific discoveries, the appearance
of new nations on the world political stage
and the internationalizing of economic or social problems
all these have made a radical impact on school curricula
which are becoming progressively more cumbersome and
indigestible.
Faced with the painful necessity of cramming more and
more knowledge into young heads, educators have been
resorting to new pedagogical methods. Some of these
"new" techniques, many people will be surprised to learn,
were actually used centuries ago the homework of the
children of the French royal family was printed long
before the virtues of a school printing press were recog¬
nized. Others, however, are quite original and one of
these is the »method used »by a French educator, Mrs. P.
Poinsart-Chasson, to teach her pupils a wide range of
subjects.
Mrs. Poinsart-Chasson, who studied under Jiri Trnka
and Hermlna Tyrlova (two famed Czech puppet masters)
is now an official of the French Ministry of Public Health.
But she has always been an artist and an educator by
vocation and she became a convinced believer of "active"
methods of teaching long ago. Determined to make
lessons attractive, she had the idea that dolls, so beloved
by little girls the world over, might serve as friendly links
between children and school subjects like history, geo¬
graphy, hygiene, civics and others.
One fine morning (mornings are always fine in fairy
tales and this story has some overtones of fairy enchant¬
ment about it) she arrived at St. Anne's school in Mar¬
seilles, to try out her idea, with the approval of the
school's headmistress.
She took a ping-pong ball from her bag and, with a
few strokes of a brush, transformed it into a little round
92 face similar to those of Trnka's marionettes. Then,
continuing her demonstration, she showed wide-eyed
little girls that this face could wear a number of exprès-
PING-PON
GO TO SC
sions. In turn, the ping-pong ball became gay, sad,
amazed, frightened and hilarious. /
A few fragments of rabbit skin glued in the right places
lent red hair or black mustaches to these faces. A sponge,
nipped in by a stout thread in its middle, produced a
reasonable image of a slim-waisted young lady. The same
sponge, pinched slightly in the back was then transformed
into a portly gentleman. After that, wire could be used
to connect heads to bodies. Soon, under the guidance of
Mrs. Poinsart-Chasson, pupils became skillful enough to
create expressions themselves and to concoct dolls that
were gay or melancholic.
Then Mrs. Poinsart-Chasson reached the second stage
of her experiment. She read to her pupils a Chinese story,
"The Wise Man's Sigh" and suggested that they might
illustrate it by building scenery and reproducing its
characters. The girls enthusiastically began to work.
But soon they realized that they had to know how the
Chinese dressed, what food they ate, where this food
came from, what sort of houses they lived in, how they
decorated these houses, how they lived and so forth.
Soon, an intensive hunt for books, magazines and
newspaper articles about China had begun. Pupils
brought Mrs. Poinsart-Chasson a tremendous variety of
documents and materials for making costumes and
scenery. Some girls became so enthusiastic about their
research that they used .spending money to buy art books
instead of sweets.
Then, in October 19, 1958, their work was done and the
dolls made their bow at the Regional Educational Docu¬
mentation Centre in Marseilles. This exhibition was so
successful that the French television network made a
documentary film about it (the film was half-animated)
which was shown on TV screens in France. It is easy
to imagine the pride of its authors, and also the enthu¬
siasm with which twenty-one little French girls between
twelve and fourteen started to work on a second film, this
one aimed at fighting alcoholism and entitled "Dolls Go
to School in Good Health."
A new teaching method was born. Like many others,
its first aim is to arouse the interest of pupils, but what
really distinguishes it is the immediate appeal it makes
to the ever-awake imagination of children. Of course,
many educators in France and elsewhere had already
accepted the smiling presence of dolls on hitherto dark
and unattractive classroom d»esks. Implicitly, then, they
have given official recognition to dreams, accepting the
existence of that irrational and marvellous world which
awakens a child's creative powers to a point few adults
suspect.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
G DOLLS
HOOL
by
Marie M. Rabecq-Maillard
Curator, Museum of the History of Education
National Institute of Pedagogy, Paris
At the National Pedagogical Institute In Paris, for
example, exhibitions had already been held on the theme
of Christmas, in which kindergarten children gave free
rein to their imagination. One exhibit in which they
reconstructed the picturesque Rue Mouffetard, a busy
shopping centre on the Left Bank in Paris, with Its old
houses and shops and its bustling crowds, revealed remark¬
able artistic talents which amazed grown-ups and won
the admiration of leading French poets.
Both in Paris and in Marseilles, children had created
dolls and exhibited marionettes. But, behind the remark¬
able work of the little kindergarten youngsters, the
shadowy impression of the baton and the inspiration of
an orchestra leader could still be felt. The children had
remained in their own little universea delightful one too.
Mrs. Poinsart-Chasson, however, had gone further by
enabling children to participate In an adult world and by
raising them to a higher level while still allowing them
to express themselves freely.
Nor had anyone else in France thought of using manual
work to approach each subject on the curriculum. Civics
and dry and theoretical ethics became alive. Mrs. Poln-
sart-Chasson's pupils produced a short film on antl-
alcohollsm and succeeded in making adults thinkand
perhaps in convincing themby such hard-hitting slogans
CONT'D ON NEXT PACE
DRESSMAKERS AT WORK: Four young girls put the finishing touches on the clothes designed for a collection
of their colourful dolls which help to illustrate lessons in history and geography in a way not found In textbooks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
PING-PONG DOLLS (Cont'd)
Lessons come alive
with Lilliputian 'teachers'
as: "Little glasses of wine grow up Into big glasses of
tears."
You really have to know your history and geography if
you want to ¡dress Chinese characters, and illustrate their
homes, their ways of life and their customs. Sewing,
drawing, modelling, embroidery and sculpture often
tedious for children who feel no aptitude for them
became fascinating because they were part of the film
production.
Besides, those few hours devoted each week to manual
work gave a child a chance to express a hidden persona¬
lity, rich in all kinds of possibilities but often suffocated
by timidity or environment. The character chosen by a
child is already quite revealing. The face a child gives
to a doll often resembles its own face. In Mrs Poinsart-
Chasson's method, there are opportunities for self-
expression which have enabled real talents to be
recognized.
Thanks to this method, too, a child comes into contact
with such techniques as sound-recording or stage direction
which may not be "in the school programme", but which
certainly awaken Interest because they are very much
in the news. This means that education can shed its
abstract and bookish nature. The child plunges Into a
real world apparently reserved to adults and, therefore,
all the more attractive to a young mind.
At the same time, working as a team develops a sense
of community living. Hunting for materials and evaluat¬
ing them »sharpen a taste for research and a critical sense:
here, the search is for precise, accurate information.
Then, too, there Is that development of taste, ingenuity
and inventlvemess which are the obvious offshoots of the
method used by Mrs. Poinsart-Chasson. No doubt others
before her have proved the value of focussing children's
interest. Ever »since St. Jerome, educators have said that
teaching should be attractive. While she deserves credit
for bringing dolls into schools and, with the dolls, a great
part of the realm of childhood with its marvels and its
colourful and charming visions, she struck out in a new
direction by enabling her pupils to participate in the very
conception of demonstrations which, up until now, have
often been too abstract.
When will we have an international exhibition to bring
together all the world's dolls in a children's dance of
friendship?
FULL RANGE OF FACIAL EXPRESSIONS
on plngpong dolls was captured by a young girl
of twelve who painted this set shown below.
Cal
24
Amused Stern Angry Hurt
>
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
A PING PONG BALL attached to a wire (above) becomes the head of doll with a little paint and rabbit
fur (right). Above left, the indispensable materialswire , pliers, scissors, glueand the dolls them¬
selves in various stages of development. Left, a young boy concentrates attentively on creating a doll.
_____! «
V Wl*\m\.
T^kmmmnm « ^mmmm^km^M. MM\
'¡WESSEN
%ÏW
A -jJjJùm
A CHINESE FAIRY TALE will incorporate these two dolls, above left. To faithfully copy costumes, hairdos and
facial expressions, the children had to read and study and think about Chinese customs, costumes, and life. The.
finished product shows their research time was well-spent. At right, dolls help to teach a history lesson. This
scene from ancient Gaul shows a sod hut and a Gaul verifying the vertical lines of the home he has built.
All photos courtes/ P. Poinsart-Chasson
Contemptuous Disgusted Afraid Admiring Doubtful
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
AUSTRALIA'S
GIANT EYE ON
OUTER SPACE
by Selwyn Speight
All photographs Australian
News and Information Bureau
TINIEST CREVICES in the dish structure
of Australia's giant radio telescope were
sprayed with aluminium paint to stop rust
forming which interferes with reception.
HIGHASAN 18-STOREY
BUILDING and 210 feet
across its parabolic dish, the
telescope here swung into a
horizontal position makes a
space-age umbrella for a
grazier and his flock of sheep.
Apowerful radio "eye" designed to look ten
times as far into the universe as has ever
been possible before, has now come into operation ' in
south-eastern Australia thus opening a new chapter in
the exploration of outer space. A' huge radio-telescope,
of the steerable "dish" type, it is the most efficient and
versatile instrument of its kind in existence, able to scan
vast expanses of the cosmos.
The instrument, a glittering giant, stands on the plain
near the town of Parkes, about 200 miles west of Sydney.
The structure overall is as high as an 18-storey building,
and its movable saucer-shaped aerial system which forms
its effective "eye" measures 210 feet across.
The new telescope has »been built for the Australian
Commonwealth Scientific and Industrial Research
Organisation (C.S.I.R.O.)' at a cost of about £800,000 (half
of which has been provided by the Rockefeller Foundation,
the Carnegie Foundation and private donors in Australia) .
There is only one other comparable instrument in
existence: the big radio telescope at the Jodrell Bank
Experimental Station of Manchester University, in
England. The English instrument is slightly larger 250
feet across the -dish but the Australian one, according to
its design specifications, will be more precise and powerful.
Although its position on the earth's surface enables it to
examine part of the northern sky, its main task will be
to search the southern heavens. Together, the two great
radio-telescopes open up a new era of scientific investi-
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
gation and research into the structure of the universe.
In the exploration now going on within the solar system,
the new Australian radio-telescope can play a significant
part (as the English one already has). If an "instrument
probe" is sent to land on the moon, and if the device
reports back by radio, the Parkes Instrument almost
certainly will be better, able than any other to pick up
these weak signals. If, during the next few years, similar
probes are sent to Venus or Mars, or to any other planet,
the best information may well come through Parkes.
However, this is not the principal task for which the
C.S.I.R.O. instrument was conceived and designed. Its
main purpose is simply to look further and more clearly
into the universe than has ever before been possible.
The essential role of a radio telescope is to detect the
strength and source of radio waves which reach the earth
from outer space. Some idea of the scale over which the
instrument has to work the distances and times can be
grasped from the following information given by Dr. E.G.
Bowen, chief of the Radio-Physics Division of C.S.I.R.O.,
and one of the world authorities in his field: he was a
member of the British team which developed radar in
World War II.
A radio wave, Dr. Bowen explained, goes round the
world seven times in a second. It would take eight
minutes to reach the sun; 100,000 years to go across our
local galactic system; and more than a million years to
reach the nearest external galaxy. It would take up to
5,000 million years to reach some of the distant radio stars
we are watching.
To call the telescope a radio eye is not straining a
metaphor. The Instrument "secs" a band of waves in the
electro-magnetic spectrum.
To be efficient, to "see" the picture clearly and In sharp
focus, the radio eyes must not only be very precise, but
also very big, the bigger the better, within practical limits,
and the Australian Instrument is getting near the limit
with existing structural materials and techniques. The
instruments are most useful when they can look in any
desired direction, just as human eyes do.
The design of the C.S.I.R.O. giant has thus been a major
engineering problem. The great steerable "dish" which
forms the effective eye must be able to watch and keep
watching automatically whatever is under observation
a galaxy, the sun, the planets, the moon, or a man In
space. To do this, It must move very smoothly and
exactly, compensating automatically for the spinning of
the earth on its own axis and for the earth's orbit round
the sun, and compensating also for the movements of the
object being watched. It must also be able to scan
continuously a given portion of the sky, noting anything
of interest.
The big dish must be strong enough to withstand the
fiercest gales, and stiff enough to keep an almost perfect
parabolic shape. It must shed rain without trouble and
withstand the corrosive effects of the weather.
27
CONT'DON NEXTPAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
GIANT EYE (Cont'd)
Probing the secrets
of the universe
Another problem faced by the engineers and
manufacturers a London firm and a German factory in
Augsburgwas to control the direction Of the big dish very
precisely. The solution adopted was to place a small
master control device at the centre of motion of the whole
telescope. The small master can be "aimed" at any one
"part of the sky or made to track any celestial object with
a high order of accuracy; and the big dish is a "slave"
ingeniously linked to it and controlled by it.
The radio signals collected by the dish are reflected on
to one point, a small receiving aerial, at the focus of the
dish, and then amplified by electronic means so that they
may be examined. To avoid losses in transmitting these
faint signals, a special preliminary amplifier has been
placed at the focus in a cabin supported high above the
dish by three tubular steel legs.
This posed a physical problem for the designers: how
to give easy access to the aerial cabin from the ground.
The answer was not only ladders, but a lift big enough for
one man; it will work inside one of the tripod legs. But
the lift itself posed problems: most lifts have simply to
run up and down; this one has to run in almost any
position.
The telescope, which stands in central New South Wales,
on a bare and level plain in the Goobang Valley, about
15 miles from Parkes, is to be only one component in the
whole complex of radio astronomical devices planned for
the area. The C.S.I.R.O. has chosen a site which it hopes
will become, for several decades, the chief centre for this
kind of work in the southern hemisphere.
The area near Parkes had some obvious advantages. It
was comparatively free from radio interference (as
hampering to radio astronomers as a city's bright lights
are to optical astronomers) and it had few weather
extremes (severe weather variations can also have serious
effects).
Here, eventually, will be a big range of radio-physical
instruments intended for the study of the heavens, with
ancillary equipment, and installations of many kinds
workshops, living quarters for the permanent staff, a
small airfield (a landing strip is already in operation).
A second and smaller radio telescope (60 feet across the
dish), which can move over miles of rail track, will work
with the big one.
The fact that Britain and Australia have taken the
lead in radio-astronomy is, in Dr. Bowen's opinion, the
result of radar experience and training during the war.
"The Russians and the American," he said, "have put a
great deal of effort into nuclear research, into research
into rockets and putting vehicles into space." Neither of
these two countries possesses the most efficient equipment
for picking up signals for the rockets they are using in
space probes. Thus the collaboration of all concerned,
thanks to achievements which complement each other, will
remain an essential element for progress in the explora¬
tion of space.
Australia's radio-telescope is the only one working in
the Southern Hemisphere. In the Northern Hemisphere,
other radio-telescopes are due to come into operation,
like the one at Nançay in France whose first stage of
construction has now been completed. These new instru¬
ments are being designed to carry out specialized tasks.
Questioned about the problems which the new radio-
telescope may help to solve, Dr. Bowen had this to say:
"We don't know whether the universe is bounded or
whether It reaches to infinity in every direction; whether
it has a beginning and will have an end, or whether it has
a perpetual existence; whether there are intelligent beings
on other planets... There are any number of theories and
hypotheses about these things but very little evidence of
a factual kind. These are the ultimate problems we are
trying to solve... We hope that with the giant radio-
telescopes ours and otherswe'll get some way towards
the answer."
HUGE DISH of radio-telescope Is three-quarters of an acre in size and able to receive radio waves from the outer¬
most fringes of the universe, 5,000 million light years away. The "dish" rests on a rotating turret supported by
a massive concrete tower and can be pointed at any area of sky. Diagram, right, shows parts of the telescope.
28
Inner part of dish, 54 ft.
in diameter used for
very short wave lengths
Height, 186 ft. 6 in.
above ground level
Elevation Rack
moves telescope
vertically.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
LITTLE-KNOWN MASTERPIECES
OF BULGARIAN MEDIAEVAL ART
by
Assené Vassilev
The religious frescoes executed
in Bulgaria from the 12th to the
15th Centuries to decorate small
chapels or country monasteries
have survived although secular
painting from the same period,
whose existence is mentioned by
contemporary chroniclers, has
unfortunately vanished with
time. Today, a " Unesco Art
Album " has given us an oppor¬
tunity to judge these rare marvels
and to appreciate the evolution,
in all its subtle turnings, of
an art form strongly marked by
Byzantine influences but still
expressing its own originality.
Striking mosaic figure of St. Theo¬
dor now in the Preslav Museum.
Official Bulgarian photo
T;owARD the end of the 7th century, the Proto-
Bulgarians, coming from the East, entered the
Balkan peninsula and founded their nation between the
Danube and the Balkan mountains. The first Bulgarian
empire encompassed all the Slavic tribes living in the
region. From then on, a new culture was superimposed
upon old traditions inherited from the Thracians, the
Greeks and the Romans. The Proto-Bulgarians were
remarkable goldsmiths and skilled sculptors. As for the
local Slavs, their mastery of decorative themes textiles,
embroideries or wood-carvings was to exert a deter¬
mining influence upon Bulgarian art itself.
The first Bulgarian kingdom preceded the Carollnglan
dynasty whose empire later spread to the frontiers of
Bulgaria.
Monuments of the culture created between 681 and 1081
(the date of the Byzantine conquest of Bulgaria) were
destroyed during subsequent centuries, particularly during
the period of Turkish domination. Nevertheless, a large
number of objects, unearthed during the past 100 years,
point to the great achievements of the Bulgarians,
wnether in architecture or ceramics. In addition, des¬
criptions by contemporary writers give us an idea of the
Bulgarian capital and Its cultural apogee during the
Upper Middle Ages.
From documents, we learn that, as early as the 9th
century, the palace at Pliska, the first Bulgarian capital,
was decorated with frescoes. Later, the capital was
moved to Preslay and, according to contemporary ac¬
counts, the splendour of this city, which existed until
the end of the 10th century, dazzled all foreigners. Build¬
ings were decorated with carved stone and painted wood¬
work. Palaces with their varl-coloured marble were
Incomparably beautiful.
Virtually nothing remains of the works of art of this
era palaces, churches, frescoes and wooden icons
because Preslav was destroyed and burned in 967. At the
Patellna monastery, painted enamelled tiles dating back
to the 10th century have been found with the image of St.
Theodor. A large number of kilns and fragments of 29
ornamental tiles bearing traces of human faces lead us
to believe that Bulgarian painting was already highly
CONT'D ON PAGE 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
THE NATIVITY OF THE VIRGIN. A I Sth century frieze from the Monastery of Krem i kovts. As a
composition it is typical of the Bulgarian 14th century tradition; it reveals a more realistic, popular style:
the earrings and hair styles are those worn by the women of I 5th century Bulgaria and the distaff with
which the little girl is spinning is exactly the same as that used until recently by Bulgarian peasant women.
30
THE ARCHANGEL GABRIEL (left) detail from
a mural at Boyana entitled "The Annunciation".
DETAIL FROM JUDAS' BETRAYAL, from the
monastery of Zemen ( I 3 50). This work shows a strong
folklore influence, contrasting strongly with earlier works.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
The frescoes of Boyana, executed in I 259 in Bulgaria, occupy a special place In I 3th century European painting
as examples of developed art of portrait painting. Above, Princess Dessislava, who, with her husband, Prince Sabas-
tokrator Kaloyan, founded the Boyana church. Below, the emaciated face of Saint Ephraim, monk and ascetic.
Second only
to Byzantium
developed. However, it is impossible to retrace its various
stages during the period of the first empire.
At the beginning of the 11th century, Bulgaria came
under Byzantine domination. She recovered her indé¬
pendance only in 1187. Though the influence of Byzantine
art was felt more strongly, Bulgarian artists continued
to follow their 10th century traditions. Later the casting-
off of a foreign yoke gave national Bulgarian art a strong
stimulus. Tirnovo, the capital of the second empire,
became the second-ranking cultural centre of the Balkans
behind Constantinople. Its art schools contributed to the
development of the nation's art. Thanks to Bulgarian
painting of this period, we have a more precise grasp of
religious painting in Byzantium. Frescoes from the 13th
and 14th centuries surpass the general level of Byzantine
art. It must also be noted that they offer some purely
national traits.
Despite barbaric devastation during the Ottoman
conquest, some paintings escaped destruction. Among
them were the justly celebrated frescoes of the church at
Boyana; and frescoes from the chapel at Berende, the
rock chapels of Ivanovo and the church at Zemen. All
dating from the second Bulgarian empire (1187-1396),
31
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
All photos C Un-esco, Album : Bulgaria, Mediaeval Wall Paintings
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
BULGARIAN ART (Cont'd)
Avant-garde painters
of the 13th century
they are among the masterpieces of medieval art in the
Balkans.
The Boyana frescoes are remarkable because of the
innovations which a Bulgarian artist brought here to
Byzantine art. Their style enables us to state that they
preceded the new concepts of the first period of the
Italian Renaissance. The master artist of Boyana,
working in the 13th century, broke away from the tradi¬
tions of painting in his time to create remarkable works
whose execution was technically perfect. Various images
of Christ, the angel In the "Annunciation," the "Descent
into Hell," the "Last Supper," the "Crucifixion," "Christ
Among the Doctors," the "Ascension" and several other
compositions, including images of St. Euples, St. Eustrate,
St. Damlen, St. Ephraim and various saintly warriors and
deacons are painted so realistically and so sensitively that
they cannot be compared to anything executed during
this era. National elements, borrowed from daily
Bulgarian life, were used to bring out religious subjects.
Here are also found four portraits: Kaloyan, the local
feudal lord; Dessislava, his wife; King Constantine and
Queen Irene. The anonymous artist, trained in some
studio at Tirnovo, succeeded remarkably in expressing
the individual characteristics, physical as well as spiritual,
of his subjects. These portraits stand as true master¬
pieces not only of art in the Balkans but of European
art in the 13th century.
F1 OLLOwiNG the Boyana frescoes (1259) , Bulga¬
rian painting continued to develop for 150
years until the conquest of Bulgaria by the Turks in 1396.
Some very interesting frescoes from the 13th and 14th
centuries have »been preserved in several rock chapels near
Ivanovo on the banks of the Russenski-Lom, one of the
branches of the Danube in eastern Bulgaria. The compo¬
sition of these scenes is remarkable and their colours, in
which gilded ochre predominates, have a charm of their
own. Though the artist followed Byzantine style, his
original talent and his new conception of painting are
revealed in his treatment of forms and in his achievement
of a third dimension through gradual shading of colours,
as well as in his expression of subtle psychological mean¬
ings. Among various compositions whose subjects were
taken from the life of Christ, we should mention "Judas
Throwing the Thirty Pieces of Silver," "Players Mocking
Christ" (a very rare subject in religious iconography), the
"Kiss of Judas," and "Christ Before Ann and Caiaphas."
Also worth noting are two scenes from the life of St. John
the Baptist the judgement and the beheading.
Frescoes in the Zemen monastery in the valley of the
Struma also date back to this same period, the 14th
century. Here, all the walls of the church were decorated
by frescoes. The forms of bodies and faces were brought
out by outlines and the artist did not attempt to stress
a third dimension. Light, pleasant colours and well-
executed details make this style particularly attractive.
Certain scenes are unknown in iconography for example,
the forging of the nails used in the Crucifixion. Gripping
portraits are to be found of the donors; Deyan, a local
lord, and his wife Doya. They have not been stylized in
the same manner as the religious compositions and
darker colours were used.
With the Renaissance, the decline of the mystical and
religious ideals of the Middle Ages became marked, but
nothing was to alter the basic characteristics of Bulgarian
painting although architecture evolved considerably
during the period of Turkish domination. Up to the 18th
century, that strange balance between skilled composition
and realistic detail achieved by painters during the
second empire continued to guide Bulgarian artists.
© Unesco, Album : Bulgaria Mediaeval Wall Paintings.
The deacon Lawrence. One of a row of saints
painted at the foot of the walls of the Boyana
Church, set beneath scenes of the Life of Christ.
32 UNESCO WORLD ART SERIES ALBUM, " BULGARIA : MEDIAEVAL WALL PAINTINGS ", (NEW YORK
GRAPHIC SOCIETY, 95 EAST PUTNAM AVENUE, GREENWICH, CONN., U.S.A.) PRICE $18.00.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WHAT ABOUT THE WHALE?
Sir,
In The Unesco Courier I read how
many valuable and interesting sp»ecies
of birds and other forms of wild life
have become extinct through the fault
of man, and that measures have now
been undertaken to protect wild life
on a world scale. I should like to
know how at a time when Norway,
a country poor in natural resources, is
greatly reducing her whaling industry,
other countries that are rich in natural
resources are engaged in whaling on a
tremendous scale which may lead to
the extinction of some varieties of
these mammals since they do not breed
very rapidly and are already greatly
reduced in number. What has world
scientific thought to say about whaling?
Trokhim Korzun
Guiva, Zhitomir Region
Ukrainian S.S.R.
THE H. G. WELLS SOCIETY
Sir,.
An H. G. Wells Society has recently
been .founded, composed of persons
interested in the life and work of this
distinguished author, who are anxious
to encourage a wider understanding of
his writings and ideas. The Society
publish»es a bi-monthly journal, "The
Wellsian", has local branches in Lon¬
don and Manchester, and intends to
carry out an ambitious programme of
study, research and dissemination of
the works of one who made such an
outstanding contribution to modern
thought. I would be most grateful if
any of your readers who may be inter¬
ested in the Society would kindly
contact the undersigned, from whom
further details can be obtained.
J. R. Hammond
39, Rugby Road, West Bridgford
Nottingham, England
CIVILIZATION REDUCED TO SIZE
Sir,
Professor Nougier's "yardstick"
"Homo Sapiens is Ten Minutes Old"
(The Unesco Courier, March 1961), is
interesting. Of more immediate con¬
cernió those with Unesco's ideals at
heart is the application of this same
"gimmick" to "Homo Sapiens' " own
history.
James Harvey Robinson, in his "The
Mind in the Making" (Travellers Li¬
brary), compresses the history of civi¬
lization into fifty years. ' Again there
is the long induction period 49 years
when man was merely a wandering
hunter. Robinson's summary of the
»last six months concludes: "Within
the last few hours they would have
learned to sail in the air and beneath
the waters and have forthwith applied
their newest discoveries to the prose¬
cution of a magnificent war on the
scale befitting their high ideals and
new resources".
He was, of course, referring to the
first world war!
A graph showing the history of
civilization compressed in this way
would doubtless interest and, perhaps,
terrify your readers!
D. A. Spencer
Loudwatcr, England
ESPERANTISTS HELP UNESCO
Sir,
The Esperanto movement is today
contributing greatly to Unesco's
Major Project for the development of
mutual appreciation of cultural values
between Orient and Occident. The
Universal Esperanto Association sends
speakers to talk about their countries
and cultures in other countries of both
the Orient and Occident. A programme
comprising Esperanto translations of
25 literary works »five each from
Europe, Asia, Afri-ca, North America
and South America is under way,
and a work by Tagorc has already
appeared. Local groups of Esperantists
have organized evening meetings
dealing with different countries ' of
Ocxident and Orient (In the' French
town of Angers, last winter's pro¬
gramme covered 10 countries of the
Orient). The 1961 Universal Esperanto
Congress held in London included a
special international cultural week on
the theme "Orient-Occident". Finally,
long-established contacts by corres¬
pondence between the two world
areas been intensified.
G. Perra
Lyons, France
The number of letters received by The
Unesco Courier each day (photo shows
only one of four daily mail deliveries)
makes it increasingly difficult to reply to
all of our correspondents. Please keep
writing to us but do try to be brief !
PLASTIC SURGERY AIDS
VICTIMS OF LEPROSY
Sir,
I was very interested to read your
article on "World Leprosy Day" by
Raoul FoIIereau (January 1961). I
myself am interested in the surgical
rehabilitation of leprosy patients and
I should like to point out the fallacy
of an unfortunate remark made in the
last paragraph of the article. It says
that "The crippled and maimed. 'Iliose
whose faces, for example, will pcr-
manantly bear the mark of the dise.i.sc,
need special homes set up in the
form of small village where they will
live together, with »every measure being
taken to case their lot and help them
forget the past. Though the damage
done to them can never Ik repaired,
they remain none the less human
beings; and society which came too
late to their aid, owes them ¡us respect
and a friendly helping hand".
I should like to point out that
Dr. Paul Hrand, of Vcllore, has been
reconstructing the deformed hand in
leprosy for over fifteen years and that
I have been doing icconMruction i/f
the face in leprosy for over three
years. It is almost always possible to
completely reconstruct the face
however badly deformed the patient
may be.
N. II. A nlla
Itombay, India
A TRIPLE REQUEST
Sir,
As a teacher, I want three things
from Tin; Uni.sco Courier more
statistics covering world facts, c. g.
percentage increase in production,
population and books 1959-61; issues
devoted entirely to one topic, e.g.
Archaeology, the Far North; and
better writers, or an instruction to the
contributors not to pad their articles
with verbiage.
John C. dc V. Roberts
London, England
WORLD'S BEST HOPE
Sir,
I have found Tur. Unesco Courier
absorbing and informative but mostly
I have found it cncx>uraging. Being
unable to believe or trust most of the
international news I have seen, heard
and read, I have read your magazine
eagerly and hungrily. Every issue,
whatever subject it covers, has given
me hope that through scientists, men of
letters and people of good will, this
crazy, mixed-up world may yet grow
together in peace and understanding.
I pass my copies on to my brothers.
I would like to think a copy or two
was being sent to every secondary
school and university in every land.
Informed, educated people seem to be
our best hope for a good world.
Olive M. Cobban
Ontario, Canada
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
EXTRA TIME TO SAVE ABU SIMBEL
THE agreement on operations to lift the temples of Abu Simbel in Egyptian Nubia
out of reach of the waters of the Nile once its level has been raised by the
completion of the new Aswan High Dam need not be concluded until November 1,
1962, instead of January 1 of this year as previously stated. This means that
Unesco has nine more months in which to guarantee to the United Arab Republic
international participation in the cost of the project. However, certain preliminary
studies of the Abu Simbel project must be made before that date.
This decision was announced by Unesco's Executive Board during its 60th session in
Paris last December. It was also stated that, in response to Unesco's appeal asking
governments to contribute sums on the scale of their participation in Unesco's ordinary
budget, 18 countries have indicated their willingness to contribute in some form
or other. They are: Cyprus, Ecuador, France, Greece, Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Lebanon,
Libya, Luxembourg, Monaco, The Netherlands, The Philippines, Poland, Saudi Arabia,
Tunisia, Venezuela, and Yugoslavia. In addition, Qatar and the Holy See, which are
not members of Unesco, have offered financial assistance.
During the Executive Board session, pledges given by Morocco and Italy were also
announced. The Italian Government has promised a contribution much larger than
the $1,450,000 which Unesco had proposed as its share. Further, the United States
have indicated that, aside from the sum of $4,000,000 already voted, a proposal to
appropriate $6,000,000 to ensure the safety of the temples on Philae will de discussed
by Congress, when work round the island begins.
Individual contributions to save the monuments of Nubia may be sent to Unesco,
Place Fontenoy, Paris-7e, or to a bank in your own country, the name of which can
be supplied by your National Commission. Cheques should be made payable to
Unesco (Nubia Account). Donations may be made in any currency.
Burmese bookworms are
GIRLS: In Burma, girls are keener readers
than boys according to survey on reading
interests carried out recently. Nearly
twice as many girls as boys read a daily
newspaper regularly, it was found, and
girls do more general reading too. The
Burma Translation Society made the
survey in connexion with Unesco's pro¬
gramme for the production of reading
materials in Burma, Ceylon India, Pakis¬
tan and Iran.
TELEPHONING VIA OUTER
SPACE: Telephone calls and telegraph
messages relayed from a satellite more
than 22,000 miles above the earth are
planned by US. scientists carrying out
space flight research. A 50-1b experi¬
mental space craft is to be launched
this year in an orbit synchronized with
the rotation of the earth, that is, it
will circle the earth every 24 hours.
The satellite will carry equipment to
re-broadcast the messages it receives
instead of bouncing them back as in
past experiments.
ft INTERNATIONAL PLAYWRIGHTS
CONTEST: A contest for playwrights,
organized by the International Theatre
34 Institute (set up under Unesco's auspices
in 1948) is now under way on a grand
scale in Latin America. Firstly, national
competitions will select one play in each
of nine participating countries: Argentine,
Brazil, Chile, Colombia, Cuba, Mexico,
Peru, Uruguay and Venezuela. An inter¬
national jury will then select the best
among the nine finalists later this year.
Mexico is offering a prize of 10,000 pesos
($800). The top prizewinner will have
his work translated into several languages
and it will be offered for production to
theatres throughout the world.
PEACE TREATY 4,500 YEARS
OLD: The world's oldest known
peace treaty, a chunk of baked clay
shaped like a rugby ball and covered
with tiny cuneiform signs was recently
on display at an exhibition of Yale
University's Babylonian Collection in
New Haven, US.A. The treaty ended
500 years of border warfare between
the Sumerian states of Lagash and
Umma.
S-» TAPLE FOOD WITH A HISTORY:
A museum which traces the history of
man's staple food, bread, from the earliest
civilizations to the present day has been
set up at Ulm, Germany. Its collection
includes books and documents on the
history of bread-making and equipment
used in its preparation. It also displays
works of art in which bread is the central
theme.
UNESCO SCIENCE BESTSELLER:
Two new editions, in Singhalese and
Tamil, have recently been issued of
Un»esco Source Book for Science
Teaching which, since it was first
published in 1956, has become one of
Unesco's best sellers. The handbook
aims to help science teachers in all
parts of the world by showing them
how to improvise scientific apparatus
from simple everyday objects. It has
already appeared in eight languages and
is due to be published in 15 more.
Ii IGHTNING CALCULATIONS :
Two impressive performances have just
been chalked up by Euratom electronic
computers. Scientists fed the text of the
Lord's Prayer in 150 languages to a
machine which, within a few minutes,
classified the versions according to
linguistic and geographical categories.
Philologists had taken several years to
make the same classification. Another
machine rapidly described how trade was
conducted in 1900 B.C. in Cappadocia
(today a province of Turkey).
NEW YORK'S DRIVERLESS
TRAIN: The first completely automatic
passenger train in the United States
is to run under the streets of New
York on the city's subway. Carrying
150 people it will shuttle between Grand
Central Station and Times Square. It
starts and stops and doors open and
close without any driver or conductor
operating the controls. The train
receives orders through electric impulses
transmitted through the rails.
ft HE BIGGEST 'MILK ROUND':
As a practical way of celebrating Inter¬
national Milk Day, sponsored by the
United Nations Children's Fund (UNICEF)
milkmen working for dairies all over the
United Kingdom raised money by making
a house-to-house collection on their rounds.
This will be spent on dried milk powder to
be sent to undernourished children in
many countries. A similar campaign was
organized by the milkmen of Ireland.
LEARNING FROM TOYS &
GAMES: A fascinating exhibition
which highlights the educational role of
toys and games down the ages is on
view (until March 10) at the National
Pedagogical Institute in Paris. Entitled
"Toys and Games of Other Days", it
has been organized by the curator of
the Museum of the History of Education,
Madame M.M. Rabecq-Maillard (au¬
thor of the article on page 22). Among
the many antique objects and curiosities
loaned by museums in Germany, Hol¬
land, England and France are chess
pieces that belonged to Charlemagne,
Louis XV's toy elephant, and some
playing cards used by Louis XVI.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published : 1962 Edition
Study
Abroad 1962
\Ct\t)
Zl, DB KOTAL'
U-.-A mu in ml . |.,u
ne-rVOiiw, Fruuv
tllcalinn fruti»çtuhcf v
nationale* »et «*mi-
i individuell..
iiiiralMo t b) jirt.-
Vomm^iir« ri
' »de n*eJlfi*lir et
ilturrl de Knviui-
déjfc »J
iZ auf? I
S. de 103K.
^ranger
4 Knu.iL-
nourrifilr
Hlllu.ir-i (H r -,
«¡yin«, y I»
/» ^J"" 't"'1 *»-
V , o' y -
I teuton .f 4,>'.'".. * K'i^Ü ¿S **0.*'-t
pat». Kr dará |»rrt
rit tldir n mil »ropolu
irlai-uiti.fia» i ..i.
cultura l.ii|H.(ii< »
4 (ubre matoa del vi
il'i.li Nueva Orieii
I -eni.it. de verano
1A Juillet
I 7.
M Attach«
aade île
»candidat t¡tTJalistc* dea out*-
:??.
Ï.O
fe*
_...pi and aira.
compí/ed by Unesco
->.
rhouiondi of opportunltlei
for itudy ami travel abroad
Uva and «tud»/ In an/
one of 115 countr/ei and
terr/toriei from
2 weel.» to 7
« Io« eruaifHiatuw.
	4 VUUnHalu o un tetado
'uJvakfitr, conferido por un« »eat-iieU
' 'unal. A au irgréao »al Krua.li«-,
rvk:io»
International
Documents Service
New York
I 1 añu a.awtéiiil'-o
t No -U-UrtnkuMÍo.
! ni\. imUd Ci-nti
Driiuilam-r-ntO »de
ralea. Quilo.
fVNIVKHSMiAI) DU
» í'o 1>M. i'uen-M, Ko.
í-caa unlvrnUtarW
" 'rttc-adeh « mm*
NOW YOU CAN GO ABROAD TO STUDY
Many countries now provide funds for Amer¬
icans to study abroad. This unique book
lists over I 00,000 scholarships and fellow¬
ships at leading universities throughout the
world. More than 800 pages cover a wide
choice of academic subjects. Programs des¬
cribed range from two weeks to eight years.
Complete with lists of organizations offering
practical advice and help. Excellent classi¬
fications system lets you find all details easily.
(Compiled by UNESCO experts In education).
Ui
This handy guidebook contains all the information
you need to take advantage of international
educational opportunities.
ORDER FROM THE UNESCO PUBLICATIONS CENTER
80 I Third Avenue
New York 22, N.Y.
INTERNATIONAL DOCUMENTS SERVICE
Columbia University Press
2960 Broadway, New York, 27, N.Y.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
DESCENDANTS OF THE INCAS
Centuries have passed since the mighty Inca Em¬
pire has vanished, but Indians of the high plateaux
of the Andes (like these two Bolivian women) still
preserve the physical features, the language, cus¬
toms and beliefs of their ancestors. They prove
that no civilization really dies If there are people
who maintain the original traditions, (see page IS)
© Paul Almaay
,
A
**
]]>
</page>
</document>
