<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078356eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
WINDOW OPEN ON THE WORLD
m mura
SEPTEMBER 1963 (16TH YEAR) -PRICE 1/-STG. (U.K.) -30 CENTS (CANADA) - 0.70 F (FRANCE)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
\
FAMILY FESTIVAL. A mother places tiny lamps
before the family shrine in an Indian home. India,
a land of 400 million people with many languages,
artistic patterns and religions, is an unfamiliar
spectacle to Occidental eyes. But its rich cul¬
tural and religious heritage has much to offer the
Westerner who will look beyond the superficial
veil of the exotic. (See article on page 4)
© Richard Lannoy
-V "V
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Contents
No. 9
SOW OMN ON TMf 1*0» to
rier
SEPTEMBER 1963
16 TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER PHOTO
Frank J. Malina at work In
his studio near Paris. His
paintings, using artificial light
and real movement, have
brought a revolutionary new
vision to art by translating
the accelerated rhythm of our
time into novel aesthetic
forms. See photo story page
18 and article page 12.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
Page
4 BLINDFOLDED TRAVELLER IN NEW DELHI
Advice to a young man from the West
By Georges Fradier
12 MOVEMENT AND LIGHT IN TODAY'S ART
New dimensions in painting and sculpture
By Frank Popper
18 MALINA: ARTIST-SCIENTIST OF THE SPACE AGE
24 TRACKING THE HURRICANE
Science helps to fight a world-wide scourge
By E.R. Yarham
WHEN FLIGHT WAS SILENT
The balloon agea vanished era of air travel
By David Gunston
33 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
34 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
(M. C 63 1., 183 A)
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*. France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Veniamln Matchavariani (Moscow)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shln-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July and August when
it is bi-monthly (I I issues a year) in English, French, Spànnh, Russian. Cernían.
Arabic, Japanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H.M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus data
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : IO/-stg. ; $3.00 (Canada) ;7. 00
French Francs or equivalent. Single copies l/-stg. 30
cents ; 0.70 F.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
A// correspondence shou/d be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
BLINDFOLDED TRAVELLER
IN NEW DELHI
by Georges Fradier
This article has been written by Georges Fradier as
a letter to a young man from the West, Joris van W.,
who is visiting India. Replying to the young man's
complaint that he was bored and disappointed by
a performance of the Indian epic, "Krishna Leela",
Georges Fradier explains that he has only himself to
blame. Lack of curiosity and indifference have pre¬
vented him from sharing in a unique cultural experience.
THE CELESTIAL FLUTIST. In all lands,
simple or idealized images of legendary heroes
and divinities who embody in themselves the
basic values of a culture are passed down
from generation to generation through poetry,
epics and folk tales. In India the legends
surrounding Krishna, a youthful and lovable
Incarnation of Vishnu, have won him a special
place in the affections of the people. Left,
a folk mural of Krishna the flute-player. Right,
an image of this celestial musician whose exploits
have inspired innumerable songs and dances.
ear Joris,
'To find oneself in Delhi, or New Delhi on a March
evening, as I'm sure you must have felt though you
didn't say so in your letter, is an experience prized by all
its inhabitants, rich and poor alike, and still more by the
Western tourists for whom it must be little short of a
miracle. Such evenings are indescribable; those who have
known them try to convey their impressions by words
like soft; warm; sweet and scented air; starry skies;
rustling palm trees...
But all these words are inadequate, for who can say
for instance that the tall palm fronds in the gardens of
wealthy New Delhi homes stir the emotions more than a
few leaves glimpsed in the humbler and still more peace¬
ful sidestreets beyond the Kashmir Gate. And who can
say why the soft air so often mentioned should be as
palpable at nightfall among all the backfiring motorcycle
taxis in Connaught Circle as in the velvet solitude of
the Lodi Gardens.
Winter is over and the pitiless summer is still a few
weeks off. The lawns and other open spaces are not yet
swarming with the crowds who escape from the old blocks
of flats without balconies or air-conditioning to find a
night's sleep. You can wander alone between the Red
Fort and the Great Mosque where the fields are still green
or in the Ramilla Gardens bathed in moonlight and
caressed by the soft night breezes.
You must surely have fallen under the spell almost too
powerful for people in our part of the world cast by
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Photo« © Richard Lsnnoy
nature which at this time of the year becomes a sheer
delight with the same fresh yet uneffusive spontaneity
we find in the welcome extended by the Indian people,
whom you describe as the most hospitable in the world.
Unless you were ill in bed, all this must have given you
renewed pleasure in life and added reason for living.
Such are the delights or illusions bestowed by February
and March in northern India where musicians from time
immemorial have sung of them with matchless fervour.
And so these spring evenings or nights might even be
described as cultural values.
In India spring has been given a more exalted place
than, perhaps, in any other part of the world. In Europe
it makes you hum an air by Mozart or a "pop" tune or
it brings to mind a Botticelli figure. Here it has been
embodied in divine legends that for three thousand years
have been the never-failing inspiration of poets, sculptors,
painters and even philosophers.
Since you already had some knowledge of its literature
when you set out for the East, I feel I can speak to you
of the Ramayana, an epic which is comparable only with
the Iliad in the lasting influence it has exerted on the
thinking of a whole people. I want to talk about it to you
(because of your March evening in Delhi) as I imagine
you know your way about Hndu mythology and are not
content, when you visit temples with their crowds of
tourists, merely to admire the statues without any idea
of what they represent. Just picture a tourist in Ghent
who, on the grounds that he is an agnostic, sees no more
than lines and colours in the Retable of the Lamb.
When presented with an eíílgy of the Hindu Trinity,
you of course can put a name to the three faces of
Brahma, Vishnu and Shiva. You have grasped that
Vishnu symbolizes perpetual life the sheer will to live.
He is the power that holds the world together. But for
him everything would disintegrate, and when sleep over¬
takes him the universe shrinks to nothing. He is the
hope of all mortal things; and so the Hindus will tell you
that he Is the god of all religions. That is why, every
few hundred or thousand years, when the world seems
threatened with collapse, he comes down in bodily form
to give it new strength and life. You could never re¬
member all the many forms of his successive incarnations.
But the two most famous and most splendid of these
Rama and Krishna have to do with your night in March.
The landscape and seasons in India cannot have
changed much since these incarnations which are suppos¬
ed to have occured a few centuries apart, in relatively
recent times, at the beginning of the "age of conflict".
I wouldn't feel too remote from them though. Rama for
instance is the "Charmer" who must be familiar to you
from Indian literature and the sensitive people who have
welcomed you, for all classes of society feel a very deep
devotion to this god incarnated as a prince.
The story of Rama not only extols the finest feelings
especially loyalty and faithfulness to one's word but is
also an inexhaustible source of inspiration for essayists
and story-tellers, It is roughly comparable with the part
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
BLINDFOLDED TRAVELLER (Cont'd)
Krishna's flute calls from the forest
played by Don Quixote In Spain. Many a scholar in
India and beyond its borders regards it as the origin of
the tale of Prince Charming in Western legend, where
the hero overcomes countless natural and supernatural
obstacles before being reunited with his beloved.
In India she is Sita whom you must have seen in the
many prints and plaster images on sale in the bazaars.
In one she is depicted holding a lotus flower, covered In
jewels, sitting on Rama's left knee; Rama has a serene
smile on his face, set off by a resplendent necklace and
ear-rings, with his hand ever ready to his bow. Behind
him is his brother, the chaste and valiant Lakshman,
also armed. Reposing at their feet is Hanuman, the
monkey king, who triumphed over the evil spirits of
ancient Ceylon.
NI ow that I mention this semi-divine animal, so
devoted to Rama, you must wonder if Indian
children have the same feelings about monkeys as the
youthful visitors to the London, Hamburg or Antwerp
Zoos. Almost inevitably, monkeys should conjure up in
the minds of Indians the army of Hanuman, just as a
reader of the Little flowers of St. Francis is reminded by
birds of the great saint, or a lover of poetry cannot help
reciting Baudelaire when he sees cats. Are these com¬
parisons too far-fetched? But I only meant to bring
home to you the diversity of each people's bestiary. By
the process of mental association, animals, too, can
acquire the significance of cultural values.
The story goes that Rama having sworn to have one
wife only, promised to be reincarnated later so as to
satisfy the passions he had kindled in his followers. And
so he appeared as Krishna, the dark, comely god of love,
all-fulfilling. We find him for Instance in the miracu¬
lous forest of Brindaban not for from the Jumna, a
paradise which for all its appeal to the senses is the most
Innocent that ever sprang from man's imagination. One
March evening in Delhi the spirit of Krishna was present;
though you may never have read a line of the Bhagavata
Purana you were assuredly in Brindaban.
In your letter you say: "Last night I was invited to an
open-air performance called Krishna Leela; I thought it
was never going to end. To begin with I was bored to
death by the pompous speeches with their mixture of
patriotism, learning and philosophy, and then by the
music, which at first I found disquieting and then terribly
monotonous. The performance was a kind of ballet or
historical pageant with lovely costumes but incomprehen¬
sible bits of folk dancing.
There was too much pantomine and an unending succes¬
sion of gods and evil spirits, persons and tableaux with
no apparent connexion between them. It must all have
been based on folklore. But does it mean anything
today? Has it a message to bring? Who can say?
Anyhow it put me to sleep?"
y dear boy, I'm twenty years older than you
I so can't tell you as bluntly as I should that
you're an utter fool. If you were my age, I wouldn't
mince my words. Good luck and your kind hosts brought
fabulous cultural treasures within your grasp one March
evening.
India, which is almost as vast as Europe and has as
large and as varied a population, has other, many other
treasures besides. But this Is one of the most fascinating
aspects of a heritage which belongs not merely to the
past but keeps on growing; and it is one of the most sti¬
mulating aspects of that heritage. Your talk of endless
speeches and a performance based on folklore shows that
it was all completely lost on you.
When the Oberammergau peasants vowed in the 17th
century to play the Passion from time to time a tradition
they have adhered to down to the present daywas it
6 nothing mere than folklore? If despite the flood of
tourists you managed to attend this performance it would
never occur to you to think of it merely as a stage piece
on the same level as a production of Parsifal or the Flying
Dutchman. Instinctively you apply other standards; you
will immediately feel absorbed and for several hours you
will Identify yourself with the actors as a Christian and
even as a Bavarian.
The ballet you watched less solemn, with less ritual
and less spontaneity could not of course be equated with
the Passion or even the mediaeval Mystery Plays which
could be made into a first-rate spectacle in any modern
theatre. But at both the Mystery Plays and the Krishna
Leela, the public's reactions are much the same charged
with emotion and with no trace of surprise. You yourself
would have no difficulty in feeling at one with the spec¬
tators, and in understanding and experiencing the same
emotions, provided that you too were first familiar with
the story brought to life In the acting and dancing.
I suppose that the choreographer had to rest content
with a mere allusion, towards the end of the ballet, to
the part played by Krishna as an adult in the feudal,
cosmic war in which a host of princes of the same blood
destroy one another. Krishna spends his childhood in the
fields and woods among cowherds and milkmaids. The
little prince is entrusted at birth so as to escape the
massacre of the innocents to a family of kind, wealthy
farmers and waxes in strength and mischief rather than
wisdom.
There are endless stories about all the pranks played
by this spoilt child, but everyone is delighted with them,
being powerless to resist the charm of this divine boy
who, after getting into the most terrible mischief, turns a
disarming smile on his nurses and later on his friends.
He has any number of girls among his playmates, and
they are ready to put everything aside work, family, the
past and presentto follow him or just to go looking for
him in the forest. (Later on he was to acquire lawful
wives by scores and then by hundreds, ending with a
grand total of sixteen thousand eight hundred and eight) .
Like all who come into contact with Krishna
as a child or a young man, they have mo¬
mentary visions of his divinity, seeing him in a flash as
Vishnu. Usually the transfiguration passes as it came,
their worship or ecstasy fades in the light of not-quite-
common day; his adoptive parents return to their toil, a
warrior to battle, girls begin dancing and vanish into the
darkness, summoned by a flute. Please never tell me
again that you found that flute monotonous.
In your neglect of the peculiar qualities of the Krishna
story you closed your eyes to the exceptional talents of
the dancers performing before you. Some figures of the
dance had a "merry peasant" atmosphere, a colourful
liveliness you must have enjoyed; for capering in a circle,
hands on hips, to a simple measure, has an unfailing
charm, and the most universally familiar themes of our
century are those of folklore, with its pottery, textiles,
basket-work and ballets.
The round dances have their rightful place of course in
a fairy-tale that was born of the people and still belongs
to them. But in the "classical" dances, products of a
supremely refined art you seem to have perceived only
conventionality and symbolism. True, their technique is
conventional, like that of the Bolshoi Theatre and Covent
Garden.
The masters who teach them in schools such as the
Bharatiya Kala Kendra at Delhi are the direct heirs of
those who formerly brought renown to the courts of
princes or emperors. Incidentally, their learning is the
more precious for being ephemeral; the classical tradition
and the kathak style had nearly vanished from Repub¬
lican India, and are preserved only through the gener¬
osity of unusually devoted and wealthy patrons.
This is the most difficult of all styles of dance, but the
long years of remorseless discipline that are required in
order to master it confer an incredible freedom. Try to
spend a few hours, a few days if possible, among these
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
THE
> OF
DANCE
© Richard Lannoy
India's dances are an expression of every aspect of life and even symbolize life Itself:
Siva, who represents both creation and destruction, is also Lord of the Dance. He is
often depicted surrounded by an arch of flames (destruction) and holding a small drum
(the rhythm of creation). Above, an 8th century A.D. figure of Siva in the famous
rock-hewn underground temples of Ellora, in Hyderabad, southern India.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Chasing a demon (Kathakali)
Photos ID Richard Lannoy
STORIES TOLD
WITH THE HANDS
India's rich heritage of dances ranges from
religious and traditional temple dances (Bha¬
rata Natyam) and dance dramas (Kathakali)
down to simple folk dances. Its five major
schools of classical dance are the Bharata
Natyam, the Kathakali and the Mohili Attam
in southern India, and the Kathak and the
Manipuri in the north. In these dances the
gesture language of the fingers follows rules
that are as strict as they are subtle. These
gestures, through which the audience follows
the story narrated by the dance, offer to the
performer a means of expression as eloquent
as the spoken word. Right, opposite page,
a pose from a Bharata Natyam dance depict¬
ing Siva stamping on the demon of ignorance.
Some examples of the finger movements, or
"mudras", are seen in these photos With their
infinite variety of combinations they are used
to interpret dramatic works, poetry, prose and
songs. Audiences in India find the basic
meanings of this symbolic language easy to
understand and connoisseurs can follow
even the most delicate shades of meaning.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
BLINDFOLDED TRAVELLER (Cont'd)
No longer a foreigner
singers and musicians, in their school. You will have an
opportunity, perhaps unrivalled elsewhere, of watching
performers of all ages in a display of virtuosity, with an
incomparable mastery of their art and control of their
limbs.
Take your seat in the unadorned hall, resonant with
the unchanging drone of the tambura, the basic single-
stringed Instrument. The dancer bows to you, stands
motionless for a moment, then clicks her Angers lightly
to the tabla player's tones which grow more and more
irresistible. She comes forward and bends as though to
kiss the feet of the guru, who is seated at your side. She
waits silently for an instant, about to begin her dance.
She begins... When, at a sign from the guru, she stops,
you do not know whether she has been dancing for half
an hour or an hour. She could have gone on all day,
with more and more intricate steps, seemingly improvised,
never weary, never frenzied, never mechanical but on the
contrary with increasing physical control and ever¬
growing rapture.
Her grace, skill and tireless vigour will no doubt
I teach you more about the Dance, with its ca¬
pacity for beauty and indeed for ecstasy than you could
ever learn from any ballet performance. In any case I
hope that this dancer with her technical mastery over
every least gesture and expression, from flashing eyes to
the musical tinkle of rings as her bare feet tread the
marble floor, will restore your feeling for the wonders of
the Krishna Leela, which evaded you the other evening.
And this will probably reveal to you before long the
Krishna of the poets. Your recollection of that dancer
so completely "traditional", though born about 1940 is
bound to be a help as you turn the pages of the Gita
Govinda, the "Song of the Herdsman", written by Jaya-
deva eight hundred years ago, and then the variations,
differing in their depth of mysticism and in their inge¬
nuity, composed between the fifteenth and eighteenth
centuries by a dozen lyric poets from Princess Mira Bai
to Bihari Lai and Kali Das. Translations are not hard
to come by.
You will find it even easier to appreciate certain sets of
engravings and reproductions, for the loves of Krishna are
the great Inspiration of Indian painting and the producer
of what you took to be a "folk" ballet used the old Pun¬
jabi painters as his guides. They used to illustrate ma¬
nuscripts of which Krishna was the hero; but even quite
lately he was the favourite theme of Jamini Roy in Bengal
and of George Keyt in Ceylon. So to familiarize yourself
with Krishna you need not delve into the past, for he
has not suffered the fate of Apollo and Orpheus who are
now relegated to schoolrooms on the classics.
The Krishna Leela is proof of this. Its Ingenuousness
left you cold. Its ardour a mingling of sensuality and
religion disappointed you. Its wealth of poetry bored
you. You are of course at liberty to attribute this frustra¬
tion to accident, long-winded speeches, or even the fact
that it was too dark to read the programme. Why not?
But when you are told of the worthy 18th century mathe-
matican who went to a Racine tragedy and asked, as he
left the theatre, "What does it prove?" it is not Racine
you find pitiable.
he sole purpose of that dancing, singing and
mime based on the Krishna legends was to
give you pleasure; neither the choreographers nor the
dancers were trying to convey abstract truths, to teach
you local history, or to thrust doctrines down your throat.
The divine legend they acted out is probably meant to
announce that life is worth living and that the world can
10 shake off its terrors; but that is the burden of all music
and dance of all art, most likely though they preach
only to the converted.
You do not invariably close your eyes and ears to beauty
and imagination. But this time you were unable to
escape from yourself and your habits, to forget your em¬
barrassment, which was that of a foreigner clinging des¬
perately to his foreign standards.
Finding yourself unmoved by the magnificent scenery
and costumes, you might perhaps have whiled away the
performance by pretending to be a historian of races and
religions; a dignified amusement, as a substitute for the
message you hoped to find. You would then have noted
for instance that Krishna (and Rama too) always has a
very dark skin, shown by some painters as midnight blue,
and that he is not a Brahman but an aristocrat, a warrior.
You would have pondered over the disputed question of
his Dravidian origin with the conflicts and exchanges it
implies In Vedic times, and the fact that even in more
recent centuries the Aryans have not entirely driven out
the ancient population whose races and languages still
predominate in southern India. It is to these multiple
influences that Indian culture owes its richness and com¬
plexity. Such considerations are by no means idle and,
I repeat, they would have passed the time for you. But
frankly, they are utterly remote from the Krishna Leela,
which offers nothing but delight.
It is true that to understand its joyous language you
need to know the sort of things I have been telling you
here, and a little more as well. Nothing would have been
easier. Quite apart from books, you had only to ask one
or another of your friends in Delhi; not necessarily the
most learned of them. A few hints, recollections or
anecdotes would have put you on the right track.
Indeed, the tone in which people talked to you of Krish¬
na's legends, if not of his worship, would itself have put
you in the right mood for the performance. Then you
would have been ready to understand not only the
sequence of scenes and episodes you now find puzzling,
but the deeper meaning of this tremendous story which
unfolds itself simultaneously on earth and on the super¬
natural plane and piles up a glorious heap of absurdities
as a firm foundation for the triumph of life and love.
h or you to come away in a cold and rather con¬
temptuous mood from a performance that
delights an entire nation is not, in your opinion, a very
serious matter. It is only a pity for you yourself. Go
to see the Krishna Leela again; or, if it is given while
you are there, to the Ram Lila; but try to give it your
full attention. Allow yourself to be moved. Enjoy the
story right through, try to judge the dancers and musi¬
cians by their own standards, in the light of what they
are trying to do and express.
I am not suggesting that this will automatically make
India, with its history, its civilization and its daily life, as
familiar to you, as intelligible, as crystal-clear as your
own native town. It isn't as easy as that. But I promise
you that you will feel a bit less of a stranger there. In
coming to understand such an important element in its
culture you will have moved into a new dimension of
intelligence and sensitivity, even if you have not pene¬
trated very deeply into modern India or the Hindu
doctrines.
Unless you become an Indian, however awkwardly, at
theatrical performances and concerts, for want of any
better opportunity, you will never cease to wonder, with
the foolishness common to all impatient travellers, "how
anyone can be Indian". If this temporary conversion
strikes you as impossible, I really cannot see why you
should stay any longer in India. You see what I mean,
I hope: become an Arab when you go to Lebanon. And
let us hope that the Indians will transform themselves
into Swedes, Italians and Greeks when they have the
chance.
This text is taken from Encounters and Celebrations, a study
on the mutual appreciation of cultural values in Orient and
Occident by Georges Fradier, shortly to be published by Unesco
in English, French and Spanish.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
(Q Richard lannoy
RAMAYANA
SPECTACLE
These children have put on traditional costumes and masks with grotesque features
for their parts in a performance of the Ramayona. This great Indian epic, dating back
over 2,000 years, tells the story of Rama, a "Prince Charming" who overcame a
thousand and one obstacles to win his beloved Sita. Today, as in the past, the legendary
adventures of this hero captivate audiences in India and other Asian countries.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
12
Vardanega
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
MOVEMENT & LIGHT
IN TODAY'S ART
by Frank Popper
KINETICS - The science of the motion of
bodies as produced by the forces acting
upon them. Motion involves the ideas of
space and time. We measure space by the
time which a body takes to move from
one part of space to another. Heraclitus
was the first to insist on the fact of
movement as constituting the most
characteristic aspect of the universe.
Dictionary of Philosophy
and Psychology
by James Mark Baldwin
an's Ideas about movement have varied
I considerably through the ages. In turn he has
feared it and has longed to halt its flight; he has wished
to take part in it, then to analyse It, and finally to make
use of it. Ever since prehistoric times the artist has tried
to give visual expression to movement, and seeking ways
to represent it, he has been torn between the urge to arrest
each changing scene that met his eye and the wish to
breathe new life into the vision he had Just set down.
Increasing powers of analysis brought greater knowledge;
fresh materials became available for the artist's use, and
movement began to find expression In new ways.
So we should not be surprised today to witness the emer¬
gence of Kinetic art, i.e. the use of mechanical, or "visual"
and "natural" movement, and to find others who are
reviving the sporadic studies of a few pioneers, such as
the American, Thomas WllfieJ, the Hungarian, Laszlo
Moholy-Nagy and the Russian composer, A.N. Scrlablne,
CONT'D ON PAGE IS
Galerie Denise René SCULPTURE, REVOLVING AND HYDRAULIC. Today's search for new artistic expression
is reflected in these sculptural works of transparent plastic, incorporating light and movement,
produced by artists from Latin America. Left, detail of a work by Gregorio Vardanega, "Synchronistic
Development of an Infinite Circle". This recent work is one of the descendants of the suspended
constructions created about 1920 by a pioneer of kinetic art, the Soviet artist, Alexander Rodchenko.
Above, two phases of " Hemisphere of Water", by Gyula Kosice, photographed in motion. In his
"hydraulic sculptures", Kosice obtains striking effects from the refractions of colours through
water. Vardanega (born in Italy) and Kosice (originally from the Carpathian Mountains) represent
the two main lines of artistic research which have done much to develop kinetic art In Argentina.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
ART, MOVEMENT & LIGHT (Cont'd)
14
Robert Doisneau, Paris
MOBILE FRESCO BY A
CYBERNETIC TOWER.
At the Palais des Congrès in
Liège (Belgium), Nicolas
Schöffer offers the visitor
a grandiose spectacle called
" Forms and Light ". Behind
the vast, glass facade of
the building (above right)
is a huge (16,000 square
feet in area) semi-trans¬
parent plastic screen on to
which variable coloured
images are projected. The
rhythm and movements of
the' images forming this
mobile fresque can be varied
and controlled by commands
recorded on tape and are
synchronized with a sound¬
track playing electronic
music. To the right of the
palace rises the " Cybernetic
Tower ", (detail left) a metal
sculpture 170 feet high.
Schöffer's Tower is control¬
led by an electronic brain
sensitive to atmospheric
changes, and it is these
which regulate the move¬
ments of the sculpture's
64 mobile blades or vanes.
© Alexis, Brussels
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Search for a new dimension
all of whom made a very direct use of light in art to give
an impression of actual movement.
Scriabine had rays of coloured light projected as an
accompaniment to his symphony, Prometheus, and
Wilfred designed an instrument he called the Clavilux;
by "playing" on its keyboard he cast moving shapes and
colours on a screen. In our own day the most important
work with light and real movement is being done in
painting by an American, Frank J. Malina, and in
sculpture by a Frenchman, Nicholas Schöffer.
Nuclear fission, cybernetics and the whole range of
scientific discoveries are making a deep impact on the
outlook of the average person; their effect on the artist
is no less marked. And it is against this background of
modern science and its relationship to the basic preoccu¬
pations of art, that it is interesting to examine the new
role played by light and movement.
What actually are the latest developments in this field
of art? What objections to their work do these artists
have to face? And how are these criticisms answered?
Apart from works which make use of artificial light and
movement, there are today three distinct trends in which
the element of time is a paramount factor.
The first uses mechanical movement for various pur¬
poses. The aim is to convey the idea of a machine in
operation, using light solely to illuminate and emphasize
the functioning of the mechanism.
This mechanical or mechanistic trend, which tries to
be both amusing and poetic, has a fairly recent history
of some Importance. Francis Plcabla, a French artist,
visualized what he called "irrational machines." Another
Frenchman, Marcel Duchamp, actually built some in
1913. He constructed his first "ready made" a bicycle
wheel mounted on a stool and followed it up with
various pieces of "high precision optical apparatus," as
he called them, such as the "rotary hemisphere." Man
Ray, the American photographer, was also constructing
"ready mades" at this periodamong them a mobile
arrangement of coat hangers; while two Russians, Vladi¬
mir Tatlln and Naum Gabo, Included mobile elements in
their constructions.
MONG other great pioneers of mechanical
Lmovement, we of course find Alexander Calder,
of the U.S.A. Calder, though, first used mechanical pro¬
pulsion in his Circus and in the toys he designed before
producing his "Mobiles" sculptures made up of suspend¬
ed metal plates and wires, which are delicately poetic yet
amusing at the same time. More recently, Jean Tlnguely,
of Switzerland, has been trying to advance beyond the
mechanics of science to a new kind of "metaphysics,"
Illustrated by the titles of his constructions Métaméca-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
ART, MOVEMENT & LIGHT (Cont'd;
Electronics enters the world of art
nique, Métamatic, Relief Métamécanique Sonore. A Bel¬
gian, Pol Bury, uses a concealed motor to give slow move¬
ment to his three-dimensional constructions made of wood
metal and other materials.
The second trend is based on the movement of the
spectator's eyes, either by the manner of looking at the
work (the eye is guided) or by changing position before
it and so causing the eye to move. A Hungarian-born
French artist, Victor de Vasarely, and a Venezuelan, J.R.
Soto, are reviving a long-standing tradition that leads us
back to the linear and perspective trompe l'kil works of
the Renaissance and Baroque periods.
Vasarely began his study of the subject before the war,
by experimenting with transparent plaques which slid In
grooves. He became the leader of a movement known as
Chiétisme Plastique. His designs are usually constructed
with simple elements diverging lines or geometrical
figures skilfully repeated, cut out and superimposed.
These may be black and white or polychrome; it is their
juxtaposition which gives them depth and creates a
three-dimensional effect. The spectator's change of posi¬
tion when looking at a picture gives the work yet another
dimension duration. These qualities relate Vasarely's
work to architecture, to which it may indeed belong.
By the play of specially wrought metallic shapes
suspended before a fluted background, Soto achieves a
poetic effect of great subtlety. Similar trompe l'iil effects
are achieved by Francisco Sobrino and the Frenchman,
Yavaral, with plexiglass and vinyl wire.
The third trend is exemplified by artists who, though
working In a similar vein to those just mentioned, use
natural elements such as air, water and fire to achieve
actual motion.
One group, employing here light and ingeniously
suspended materials, obtains movement in the same way
as Calder does with his "Mobiles" by using air as the
motive force. Thus, J. Le Parc, of Argentina has built
structures made of tiny metallized plastic plaques which
move with the air and shimmer with light. Another
Argentinian, G. Kosice, introduces the force of water into
his "hydraulic sculpture," while the Frenchman, B. Au-
bertin uses matches in his "fire pictures" to produce a
real "firework display." In addition to these three main
16
Ultra-modern devices
are used by Nicolas
Schöffer to impart
movement to his
sculptural composi¬
tions. Left, part of
the electro-mechani¬
cal equipment operat¬
ing the cybernetics
system which controls
the movements of
Schöffer's "Tower"
at Liège, Belgium.
The apparatus seen
here varies the orders
given to the control
system and thus en¬
sures a spectacle of
the greatest variety.
Q Doisneau-Rapho, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
trenas mention might be made of the work of the Greek
sculptor, V. Takis, and his use of the magnet and its
power of attraction.
Thus far, reflected or refracted light have played a
limited role. Before going on to consider artists who have
used it more deliberately, let us look at some of the
criticisms levelled at this new form of art.
The main objection is voiced by lovers of painting, art
historians and by painters themselves. They maintain
that the sudden introduction of movement into a picture
destroys the subtle balance which exists in every well-
harmonized composition. Movement can only be adequa¬
tely expressed, they say, by the general rhythm of a
picture, by the lines of force or the vibration of the
fields of colour; and only thus can the feeling for beauty,
the artist's sensitivity remain unimpaired.
Many persons have also found it extremely difficult to
accept as legitimate art some of the latest trends in
sculpture. According to Moholy-Nagy, the art of sculpture
has evolved from a block like the pyramids to modelled
sculpture (both solid and hollow) and so on down to
contemporary forms in which the sculpture is perforated,
suspended in the air, and finally endowed with movement
as in kinetic sculpture.
he most traditional works of art draw their
vitality from the various internal rhythms
connected either with subject or with form. Yet this
same rhythmic interplay is the guiding principle of pre¬
sent-day kinetic art. The artist tries to achieve a satis¬
factory combination of the rhythm of the moving object
(mechanical rhythm) with the rhythm of human per¬
ception (psychological rhythm) and the aesthetic rhythm
(our appreciation of the work of art).
Another more sweeping type of criticism denies any
connexion between scientific and artistic invention. Or,
in other words, scientific inventions such as cybernetics
and electronics cannot be used to create works of art
and, by the same token, artistic creation can have no
bearing on the widening of human knowledge.
Obviously, present-day research in science takes place
on a scale vastly different from that in art. Setting up
a scientific laboratory demands vast resources and great
discoveries are often the result of collaboration between
several scientists, even whole teams of scientists. All the
same, one can hardly imagine that a scientist, even a
highly specialized one, could wholly ignore the sense of
the aesthetic, since he must have it to picture the complex
physical phenomena of our universe as well as the aesthe¬
tic needs of mankind to which his work is dedicated.
s for the artist, it is equally clear if we agree
Lthat artistic creation is partly a conscious pro¬
cess that a scientific understanding of the means he
employs, of the world around him and of his own per¬
sonality can hardly fail to enrich the artist's art. But it
would be going much too far to say that scientific inven¬
tion and artistic invention are one and the same process.
Yet the artist and scientist have often been combined
in one person: Leonardo da Vinci was an illustrious
example of this, and so were all the great figures of the
Renaissance. Very few artists could lay claim to universal
knowledge nowadays, of course, but some who are working
on kinetic art are actually carrying out scientific experi¬
ments. Their theoretical knowledge is such that, with
the help of specialists, they are able to use the most
modern techniques in composing their works.
The art of the cinema has already outgrown these
difficulties. The cinema welcomed every invention that
CONTD ON PAGE 20
Light, movement, depth and
colour are all used by sculptor,
Nicolas Schoffer, an Innovator
in the field of " lumlno-
dynamlc " art forms. Shown
here are three phases of
his work, "Chronos". (1)
" Chronos " immobile. (2)
In movement. (3) At full
speed. Now it Is a complex
interplay of light and shadow.
Photoi Yvei Horvocllon, Pirii
METAMORPHOSIS
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Malina
MALINA : ARTIST-SCIENTIST OF THE SPACE AGE
i
18
CEPHEUS. One of a series of
lumidyne paintings of the constella¬
tions of the Zodiac, 25 by 25 cms.
Other constellations in this same
group are shown on page 20.
n 1954 Frank J. Malina brought a new vision to art
when he introduced electric light and movement
into painting. We present here a few examples of his
mobile electro-paintings, though admittedly still photo¬
graphs in black and white cannot do justice to the works
which are based entirely on the continuous movement of
shapes and forms and the changes and inter-reactions
of various colours. It is no accident that all the examples
shown are interpretations of heavenly bodies in outer
space or artistic expressions of scientific phenomena.
For Malina is a rare combination of great scientist and
artist. A U.S. aeronautical engineer and geophysicist,
he designed and launched America's first successful
high-altitude rocket (the WAC Corporal) in 1945. He
directed Unesco's first humid and arid zone research
programmes from 1947 to 1953 when he resigned to devote
himself completely to art. After the launching of the first
astronaut he agreed to devote a portion of his time again
to scientific work, and is now director of the International
Academy of Astronautics and permanent representative
to Unesco of the International Astronautics Federation.
In his art Malina has sought to find new methods and
forms of expression and a new rhythm characteristic of
our modern age. By choosing his themes in the world
of science he has tried to focus attention on the interplay
between science and art in our time. To Malina, " move¬
ment is a fact, an aspect of modern life, and it would be
like tying our hands behind our backs not to use this
important element in the plastic arts. " Science, he says,
offers us a new vision of the universe generally unseen
by the naked eye, but it is up to the artist to translate this
vision into rhythmic, aesthetic terms.
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
NEBULA II is a striking example of Frank Malina's kinetic art of our space
age. This large painting measures 200 by 100 centimetres and was produced
early in 1961. The background is painted in deep cerulean blue ; the nebulae
are masses of vibrating, fluid light in yellow and white, animated bycountless
minuscule undulations. The whole effect is one of extraordinary beauty,
giving the observer an impression of looking into interstellar space.
Biü^*~'' "'PPllfflB
I'1 "
Hi---' ^K/~ '''^3
. ;
;
kuálÉll
E,.,!.'!
a^K^'1 >Kn
; |3
B? '^I BIBÉ^' BMíPÜg -r^^BB: 9
^IgSBIfn -I^K^ "'fjf gtf~T:- .: igft MBj B^R
1
Bfcr-- g|~_., J BF i^i
1Ü - "^ Ls 11
© Paul Almasy, Part*
PATHS IN SPACE. Detail of un¬
completed work of cover photo. Malina's
revolutionary paintings are usually
composed of four planes : first, a
source of artificial light (electric bulbs
and fluorescent tubes) placed behind
revolving discs or " rotors " painted
in patterns with opaque or transpa¬
rent oil paint ; a tiny motor operates
the rotors. In front of the rotor is
placed the " stator ", a fixed trans¬
parent plaque on which is painted
the basic composition. The completed
painting, combining movement, colour,
and design, appears on the final
plane, a translucid diffusing screen.
Thus, blue on the rotor passing a
yellow area on the stator is seen as
green on the diffusing screen. The
work of art is enclosed in a frame
and is then ready for hanging on a wall.
POLARIS (1957). Here the North
Star is shown at upper right along¬
side large orbit in motion within
which is depicted an orbital flight
of man around a planet. Squares
in centre slowly change their colours
with the Plough (Big Dipper) appear¬
ing in yellow every two minutes.
Marc Vaux, Parii.
1 PLUS 2 TRIANGLES. One of Malina's early kinetic paintings
produced in 1955 and based on a mathematical theme. Here artificial
electric light and blue, orange and green painted triangles are diffused
and seen in motion appearing and disappearing through a wire mesh.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE HEARTBEAT OF A
FROG. One day in 1956
Malina was reading a scien¬
tific article on the workings
of a frog's heart and was
struck by the graphic design
of its heartbeat. Shortly
thereafter he produced this
artist's interpretation of the
phenomenon incorporating
artificial light. The painting
illustrates a point often made
by Malina that our universe
contains many landscapes
and designs undreamed of
by many observers and
artists and which offer rich
subject matter for art today.
Boigontier-USIS
ART, MOVEMENT & LIGHT (Cont'd)
Unseen rhythms of our universe
20
could be of use to it, "and based its aesthetic theory on a
precise relationship established between light and time.
Movement as the technical principle of films, the move¬
ment of the camera, and many other kinetic features are
of great importance here.
Pioneers of abstract film-making, such as the American
Hans Richter, and the Swede, Viking Eggeling, and their
successors, have often taken the movement of forms as
the central theme of their work. Motion picture cartoons
from the earliest down the present day, are all related to
our subject. So are drawings made directly on films like
those of Len Lye, of New Zealand, and Norman McLaren,
of Canada, and the work of a still younger generation.
Another contribution was the film, Le Ballet Mécanique,
the work of the French artist Fernand Léger, which
brings us back to painting.
Frank Malina, the American painter and scientist, has
introduced light and movement directly into his pictures
and in this respect three aspects of his highly original
work deserve special consideration.
Malina's compositions are ingeniously constructed.
After experimenting with an electronic system, he finally
devised an electro-mechanical technique for his "electro-
paintings." The basic composition is painted in various
colours on a fixed transparent plaque (the "stator" ) while
one or more elements ("rotors") which are also painted,
are moved by an electric motor. Light, from lamps
incorporated in the construction, Is cast on a semi-
transparent screen.
Here, an interesting attempt has been made to establish
a real correlation between Science and Art. A glance at
Malina's career may help to clarify this point. He was a
brilliant aircraft engineer, and before the war had made
a special study of rocket propulsion. He directed the
development of the first successful American high-
altitude rocket, and as such was one of the pioneers of
astronautical development. Later Malina extended his
field of research to geophysics.
It is not surprising that the forms of his electro-
paintings should be akin to those of coral, radiolaria,
diatoma and crystals photographed through the micro¬
scope. This kinship with the physical universe is even
more marked in the case of stars and galaxies.
I n purely artistic terms, the work of Malina
I evokes the art of stained glass. The artificial
light he sets behind the screens of his pictures is a sub¬
stitute for the changing sunlight to which Gothic stained
glass owes part of its miraculous quality.
The way in which he divides his space, the intensity of
his black-circled reds and blues, and the ever-changing
rays of light all transform a picture by Malina into a
kind of animated stained-glass window. Unlike stained
glass windows, however, Malina's pictures are enclosed in
frames and are hung on walls like traditional paintings.
Malina's third important contribution to kinetic art is
his co-ordination of rhythm whether physical, human or
aesthetic by the use of continuous movement of coloured
forms.
Movement in Malina's pictures may be compared to
atomic, biological or astronomical rhythm. Psychologi¬
cally speaking, these movements express the speed of time
as it is lived, not as it is shown on the clock face. They
bring us closer to life and to human movement than to the
prodigiously rapid movement of the universe which is
something our minds cannot grasp.
The investigation of human perception has not yet
been carried very far in the aesthetic sphere ; but even
so, the transposition of the rhythm of life into aesthetic
rhythm is a particularly interesting feature of Malina's
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
work. His essential purpose in trying to break away from
traditional methods of painting, is to create a new rhythm,
demanding the sustained attention of the spectator.
This experiment has a certain relationship to music.
Indeed, in Malina's latest works recorded music is linked
to a mechanical and electrical source, so that its varia¬
tions influence the intensity, while the movement of the
coloured forms keeps time with the music.
One needs to see some of his one hundred kinetic pic¬
tures, such as Changing Times in the Lyons Museum, or
Orbits III in the Musée d'Art Moderne in Paris, in order
to appreciate at its true value Malina's contribution to art.
He has achieved a synthesis of art and science by evolving
a new method for the direct transmission of coloured
light, accompanied by continuous movement in which
different rhythms combine to create a harmonious whole.
Nicholas Schöffer, the sculptor, works with the same
concern for light, movement, depth and also colour. His
sculptures are metallic structures in which curved and
angular elements are arranged horizontally and vertically.
His most recent works are placed behind large, semi-
transparent screens, on which synchronized variable
Images are thrownformed by the shadows and rellcctlon.s
of the revolving sculpture and the colours cast by a
mobile disc. The source of light, though placed outside
the sculpture, plays an important part. SchotTcr uses a
kind of organ to project and vary his chromatic composi¬
tions.
He is interested, too. In the relationship between sound
and Image, and In his largest work, The Cybernetic Tower,
a piece of sculpture 52 metres (170 feet) In height, the
sound track (street noises, recorded and mingled with
electronic music) plays Its part In Farines et Lumières, a
programme presented annually, from June to September,
at the Palais des Congres at Liege, Belgium.
SchölTer's Tower Is controlled by an electronic computer
sensitive to atmospheric changes, and it is these which
regulate the movements of the sculpture. This skilful
mingling of aspects of the environment with the most
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
Marc Vaux
Malina has created a whole series of small lumidyne paintings of the various constellations In the heavens,
including those of the Zodiac. Painting at upper right represents Ursa Major (the Great Bear), the most
conspicuous of the northern constellations containing the stars which form the Plough. The other paintings
are variations in colour presentation of the constellation Cygnus (the Swan), with the bright star Dencb.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
Photos Vasarely
ART, MOVEMENT & LIGHT (Cont'd)
VIRTUAL MOVEMENT
Unlike the other works
shown on these pages,
this composition by Vic¬
tor Vasarely, " Transpa¬
rency " (below) does not
actually move. The illu¬
sion of movement, or
" virtual movement ", is
produced solely by the
change of position of the
viewer in relation to the
work. Vasarely sees a
place for these art forms
in the architecture of to¬
morrow's cities. Left, an
earlier work by Vasarely
showing how a form is
obtained by deviations in
pattern of straight lines.
Interpreting life's quickened pace
22
subtle creations of the mind is typical of Schöffer's victory
over traditional limitations.
In his earlier compositions sculpture was Schöffer's chief
interest; but at Liège his Cybernetic Tower is now flanked
by a giant screen on which moving forms and colours are
projected from a series of "light mixers."
Other experiments in filtering, projecting and polarizing
light have been made by the Italian artists Bruno Munarl
and G. Vardanega, by the Argentinians, Martha Boto and
Le Parc and the Israeli artist, P. Hoenich who uses the
sun as a source of light and natural wind for movement.
Some of their revolving structures are lit from within or
reflected in mirrors.
The introduction and synchronization of rhythm and
movement in the theatre brings us closer to the "com¬
plete" work of art. In Russia, V.E. Meyerhold and J. An-
nenkoff introduced the first mobile scenery. The German,
Oscar Schlemmer and Laszlo Moholy-Nagy sought to
establish a correlation between visual, spatial and musical
movement in drama and in dance that art of movement
par excellence brought back to life by Serge Diaghilev at
the beginning of the century. S.M. Eisenstein in Russia,
Jean Cocteau in France and Walter Gropius in Germany
even used films as part of the stage setting. Kandlnsky
in Russia achieved the first "complete" theatrical produc¬
tion by staging Mussorgsky's "Pictures from an Exhibi¬
tion."
The latest experiments again reveal a conscious effort
to bring the audience Into the performance so far as
possible. J. Belson and H. Jacobs at San Francisco,
have tried to create a new kind of drama by using
electronic apparatus, while in France, Jacques Polieri has
Ideas about a theatre completely In motion.
Similar methods are adopted in the Son et Lumière
performances, the purpose of which Is usually to bring
some famous building to life and to recount its history.
But the real impulse of kinetic art is towards a complete
rhythmic synthesis by using elements derived from
kinetic art Itself.
It thus seems that new modes of artistic expression
appeal to man's hitherto neglected kinetic "sense," the
connexion being established chiefly by light. It is an art
which strives to intensify the relation between this sense
and the others through an association of rhythms. From
the social standpoint, it may help to improve the stan¬
dard of aesthetic appreciation by disseminating and
multiplying original images conceived by the artist.
Kinetic art will not take the place of the other arts.
The poetic, intimate quality of traditional painting, the
three-dimensional message of sculpture and the stable,
monumental quality of architecture will continue to be
subjects for the aesthetic contemplation of mankind. But
man's additional need for an artistic link with the dyna¬
mism of life has always been of capital importance. In
fact, it dominates man's earliest writings and pictures.
As the Twentieth Century progresses, the pace of life
accelerates; distances shrink; man's contacts with his
fellow men become closer and closer. His ambitions lead
him to explore other real worlds, and even his imaginary
worlds are now formed from increasingly familiar ele¬
ments. Will man falter and fail to keep up the pace, will
our artists be unable to master the new techniques? Let
us hope that the artist was right in believing, as many
scientists do, that human resources like those of the earth
have hardly begun to be exploited.
Frank Popper has made an exhaustive study of the
development of new art trends and is now completing a
doctoral thesis at 'the University of Paris, to be entitled
"The Image of Movement in the Plastic Arts since 1860."
He is also engaged on research at the Institut d'Esthétique
et des Sciences de l'Art, at the University of Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Photos Groupe de Recherche d'Art Visuel, Paris
Two successive aspects of " Instability ", a work by the young Argentinian artist, Julio Le Parc,
whose research in kinetic art has produced many varied works. The play of shadows and light on
a painted plaque with a polished rim is governed by a mobile object before the source of light.
ARTIST ON FILM
By its very nature the
cinema offered an ideal
springboard for aesthe¬
tic research combining
the use of movement
and light. In this con¬
nexion the short films
of the Canadian artist,
Norman McLaren, are
now world famous. A
great experimentalist,
McLaren draws his films
directly on the celluloid.
Left, a cosmic move¬
ment from his stereo¬
scopic film, " Around is
Around ". He has also
found a way of adding
sound to his creations.
By designing with pen
and ink along the margin
of the film where the
soundtrack usually runs
he has now produced a
new kind of " music ".
National Film Board of Canada
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
TRACKING THE HURRI
Meteorologists now track hurricanes through a network of storm-warning radar stations, each able to scan several
hundred square miles of sky. On radar screen (below) is the horizontal plan of a storm. Light-coloured streaks in¬
dicate areas of heavy rain. Weather satellites also transmit vast amounts of meteorological data back to earth.
USIS
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
CANE
by E.R. Yarham
he hurricane Carla which struck the United
States in the early autumn of 1961, cost the
Insurance market about 100 million dollars. The sum
was made up of claims from nearly 250,000 Texan and
Loulslanan policy-holders. The claims related to damage
to property and contents of buildings caused by the wind,
and did not include marine, crop or livestock lasses cov¬
ered by Insurance. While these Carla losses were
substantial, they were not so great as those caused In
1960 by Donna, which, at 150 million dollars, proved the
costliest New World hurricane on record.
Such mighty tropical winds are not limited to the
Caribbean, but are found in similar latitudes around the
world. The chínese tal-fun (the "big wind,"), the Phi¬
lippine baquios, the Australian "willy-willy," and the Bay
of Bengal typhoon are all hurricanes under another
name. The name, however, comes from the New World,
where from the earliest days they were known to Euro¬
peans, to mariners, who learned to dread their terrors.
Columbus got this first knowledge of the "big wind" from
the Carlb Indians who called it Hunraken, after their
god of stormy weather. The Portugese explorers of the
same period imported a variation of the name, Huracán.
In the original scale of wind force devised for .sailing
ships by Admiral Beaufort in 1808, the word "hurricane"
was used for a wind "such that no canvas could
withstand." Later a hurricane was defined as a wind
whose mean speed exceeded 65 knots. Sir Graham Sutton,
the Director-General of the British Meteorological Office,
has given this description of the phenomenon: "In
modern meteorology the name Is reserved for a cyclonic
disturbance of relatively small area, characterized by in¬
tense low pressure around which winds blow at very high
speed. The more descriptive, but cumbersome phrase
revolving storm' is often used In British official
publications. The hurricane ranks with the tornado as a
major destructive force and is more to be feared because,
unlike, the tornado, it is relatively long-lived and capable
of causing widespread ruin should it move Inland."
|n an average the life of a hurricane covers
nine days of destruction, and in Jamaica there
is a jingle which warns the inhabitants when to expect
the big winds.
June too soon,
July stand by,
August look out you must,
September remember,
October, all over.
However, as Hobart E. Stocking, of the U.S. Atomic
Energy Commission, has commented: Just as June Is not
always too soon, neither do hurricanes always avoid
Jamaica in October. Spaniards of Colonial times were
aware of seasonal variations in hurricane paths. The
church decreed that Ad repellendat tempestates be
Included in all masses recited in Puerto Rico during
August and September but not in October, whereas the
same appeal was ordered In Cuban devotions during
September and October.
One of the most notorious of Caribbean hurricanes was
that of September 7, 1900. Whereas the diameter of a
hurricane is usually around 100 miles, this one eventually
gained a diameter of destruction 300 to 600 miles In
extent. The tempest reached its full maturity south of
the Mississippi delta. Shaped like a cosmic gramophone
record, hundreds of miles across but only thousands of
feet thick, the maelstrom of screaming winds whirled at
120 m.p.h.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
TRACKING THE HURRICANE (Cont'd;
Satellites sound the alert
Vicious air heaved the ocean into gigantic windrows
that moved with the speed of wind and then the city of
Galveston, Texas, was struck. First torrential rain
accompanied by shrieking winds flooded the streets to a
depth of four feet; then, striking with a force of 571b.
to each square foot, hurricane winds grasped waves
already mountainous and flung them against the, cowering
city. Like enormous battering rams the waves levelled
street after street. Three thousand six hundred houses
were, totally destroyed, not a structure in the city escaped
serious damage, and 6,000 people perished.
Even the greatest vessels are sometimes unable to stand
up against the ferocity of a full hurricane. One. of the
most historic escapes was that of the British warship
"Calliope" from the disastrous hurricane at Apia, Samoa,
in March, 1889. Three American and three German
warships were driven ashore with great loss of life- The
"Calliope" succeeded in steaming out through the narrow
entrance between the coral reefs in the teeth of the
furious wind and a raging, confused sea, in which at times
she was literally buried. It took her a full hour to cover
a distance of half a mile. The accomplishment was a
marvellous feat of seamanship.
More recently, during a western Pacific typhoon, the
U.S. Third Fleet cruiser, "Pittsburgh," only a year old,
had her bow ripped clean off by precipitous waves. Only
a short time before three destroyers had gone down with
the loss of 763 lives. The worst visitation in Hong Kong's
history was in September, 1906, when in addition to
heavy loss of life, in two hours there were sunk or
seriously damaged in or near the harbour 67 European
vessels, 652 Chinese junks, 54 lighters, 70 steam launches,
and innumerable, sampans.
Like all tropical hurricanes, typhoons bring winds of
tremendous strength, and during the Swatow typhoon of
August 1922, a sudden change, of wind direction as the
centre passed caused a huge wave to sweep over the town,
occasioning an estimated loss of 50,000 lives.
he willy-willy is a tropical cyclone experienced
_ over north-west Australia, mainly in late
summer. It originates in the hot Timor Sea, and first
moves south-westwards, often causing severe losses to
the pearl fishing industry. Then it recurves to the south¬
east, crosses the coast, where it causes more damage and
brings heavy rain, and moves inland to the Great
Australian Bight.
A typical willy-willy carved a path 50 to 70 miles in
width, wrecking townships and farms, and disrupting
communications. Roads were blocked for miles by fallen
trees, wheat silos, orchards, haystacks and fences were
wrecked, and stock killed by falling trees. So fierce was
the wind that a flock of seagulls was blown inland 75
miles from the coast.
South Africa is also of victim of similar visitations. To
mention one example a terrific hurricane, tearing
through darkness as black as night, struck parts of the
Orange Free State, one afternoon. The roofs of farm
houses were wrenched off and stock hurled to the ground
or blown along helplessly for long distances, and windmills
(used for pumping water) were bent and broken. The
hurricane, was followed by a destructive hailstorm lasting
a quarter-of-an-hour, destroying wheat crops and all
growing fruit. In the towns there was absolute darkness
for 30 minutes, and many children became hysterical and
terrified. The roof of an isolation hospital was jerked
off and hurled 700 yards, where it crashed to the ground
a shapeless mass. An enormous eucalyptus tree, 93ft. high
and five feet in diameter, was uprooted as if it had been
a reed and flung 100 yards away.
s has been pointed out. earlier, since the
Learliest days of its discovery by Europeans, the
Caribbean has been notorious among sailors for its
hazards during autumn. One of the worst tragedies,
occurred in 1780. A terrible storm resulted in the sinking
of an entire French fleet of 40 ships, with all their crews,
off the island of Martinique. An English fleet anchored
off St. Lucia met with the same fate. It was estimated
that 9,000 people perished in the former island and 6,000
in the latter. At Port Royal, Jamaica, fourteen hundred
houses were flattened out as if they had been made of
paper, and most of the inhabitants were killed.
One of the chief reasons for such heavy death-rolls
in the past has been that the hurricane struck its vic¬
tims before they were aware of its approach, and so they
were unable to make any preparations to shield themselves
from its fury.
To-day, happily, meteorologists are able to forewarn
territories lying in the path of an oncoming storm of its
imminence, and it is possible to predict with some
accuracy the path a hurricane is taking. This is made
possible thanks to arrangements made undex the auspices
of the World Meteorological Organization whereby weather
observations made simultaneously at thousands of stations
all over the world are exchanged by an international tele¬
communications system. These observations provide the
raw material for the synoptic charts which enable the
meteorologist to detect tropical storms in their early
stages of development, to forecast their movement and
to issue warnings to the populations of threatened regions.
Although such warnings cannot prevent gigantic damage,
they do help to keep down the loss of life.
This has been proved many time, as for example when
one powerful hurricane swept the Gulf Coast. As it was
a dozen people perished and several towns in Texas wexe
absolutely isolated. Had it not been for the precautions
usis
26
BULLDOZER
vs.
HURRICANE
If warning of a hurri¬
cane's approach Is given
sufficiently early, mea¬
sures can be taken to
protect property and
lives. Here, a bulldozer
raises a wall of sand to
protect structures on a
beach from seas which
will soon be lashed by
hurricane force winds.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
- - :ji
USIS
The American continent is particularly "hurricane prone". One of Its defence outposts Is this floating
station, Nomad I, anchored in the Gulf of Mexico, which is equipped to automatically transmit
hourly information on the changing conditions of air and sea when wlndspeeds exceed 33 knots.
taken when the alert was put out that the storm was
heading for land the, death roll would have been much
higher. It had proved possible to evacuate all the inha¬
bitants of the lowlands. The titanic power of the wind
was evident in the fact that everywhere the power lines
were snapped and towns thrown into darkness; trees
were torn up like saplings; houses fell like cards; and
families had to sleep in the open country for fear of
collapsing buildings.
As America suffers more than any other single country
from hurricanes, and as scientific research Is highly
organized there, one is not surprised to find the warning
system more advanced there than anywhere else. Since
the end of the last war the United States Weather Bu¬
reau has greatly intensified its watch on approaching
hurricanes. The difficulty is that although they can be
detected and tracked along their courses, nothing so far,
at any rate has been devised which can check their rav¬
ages. For instance, the Bureau was able to watch the
most destructive hurricane yet, Donna (it was named at
the outset), from a network of radar stations strung out
from Daytona Beach to Florida Keys, yet both scientist
and the man-in-the-street had to stand helplessly by as
it laid waste the countryside. The one advantage was
that as the outcome of earlier warnings people were able
too take shelter quickly.
Last year the radar screen was much extended
In both directions, and it now forms an
unbroken chain stretching from Portland In Maine, in
the north, to Brownsville, Texas, almost on the Mexican
border. In addition another recording device has now
been stationed In the Gulf of Mexico 300 miles south of
New Orleans. This is anchored to the ocean bed and is
known as Nomad I. Unmanned, it is equipped to
transmit a five-minute weather bulletin every six hours,
and if there are winds of more than 33 knots this Is
automatically switched to hourly transmission. In 19C0
a more primitive form of this apparatus was used, but Is
was able to pick up signs of hurricane Ethel and send
warnings to the mainland 48 hours before the storm
arrived.
Perhaps the most valuable, ally of the meteorologists Is
the satellite, the latest scientific development. This was
impressively shown in September 1961 during the career
of the hurricane, Esther, which fortunately missed the
mainland. Esther was spotted on September 10 by Tiros
III, America's third television-equipped weather satellite.
Reconnaissance planes were rushed to check on the In¬
formation from the satellite, and confirmed that a great
hurricane with winds of 130 m.p.h. was surging across the
Atlantic, but that the only land areas likely to be affected
were those, very close to the East Coast.
Tiros III, launched from Cape Canaveral In July 1961
is especially equipped to photograph the development and
movement of hurricanes and other tropical storms. Its
two wide-angled T.V. cameras are designed to locate them
when they are still no more than movements in tropical
cloud patterns. And It has certainly lived up to Its
reputation as a hurricane spotter.
During its first month of orbit it sent back more than
6,000 pictures. These included photographs of many
storms both In the Atlantic and the Pacific. These
photographs, combined with the findings of hurricane
hunter and research aircraft, have provided meteorologists
with vast amounts of fresh data on the behaviour of
severe storms. They hope the next move will be to attack
the hurricanes far out into the ocean, and get them to
dissipate their strength before they reach land. In the
1961 season experiments were made with this object,
consisting of "seeding" the storms with a chemical, silver
Iodide. The hope is that the action of the chemical,
converting super-cooled moisture to ice, will disturb the
storms' energy cycles.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
WHEN FLIGHT
WAS SILENT
by David Gunston
I
28
n the modern world where long-distance, jet-
I driven air travel is an everyday occurrence, it
is hard to believe that there was once another age of air
travel before aeroplanes were taken seriously. It was a
romantic, adventurous, now vanished era of flight the
age of the balloon.
Men first truly flew in balloons, and aviation really
began when these great cumbersome-looking aerial craft
were used as a means of transport. In fact, the world's
first air pilots controlled only a large bag full of gas with
a small wicker basket hanging beneath.
When the Frenchmen, brothers Joseph and Etienne
Montgolfler, profiting from the much earlier scientific
discovery that hot air rose, launched their first workable
balloon from the market-place at Annonay, France, on
June 5, 1783, it was to them merely an experiment. Yet
all unknowingly they committed mankind to mastery of
the air.
They could persuade no one that their simple balloon,
36 ft. in diameter, and filled only with hot air, would leave
the ground, let alone carry 400 lb. in weight aloft. But
at the appointed time, "their paper dome, filled with the
smoke of burnt wood, amid the shouts of congregated
men," rose to nearly 6,000 feet, to land ten minutes later
over a mile away.
The intrepid Montgolfiers were swift to follow up this
success, for in the month of August they sent up another
unmanned balloon, made this time of silk to an improved
pattern and filled with "Inflammable air," or hydrogen,
then newly discovered. This ascended to some 3,000 feet,
but drifted for 15 miles from its launching-place in a Paris
park, to be set upon with pitchforks by terrified peasants
when it landed in a field!
Before that momentous year of 1783 was out, several
other successful balloons were sent up, and on Novem¬
ber 21 came the world's first real human flight. Pilâtre de
Rozier and the Marquis d'Arlandes risked their necks by
going up in a large hot air balloon made of special paper.
They rose from the Bois de Boulogne in Paris, stayed in
the air for 25 minutes and travelled 5h miles over the
city.
To keep their balloon up they carried a fiery brazier
slung beneath its open mouth, to produce a continual
supply of hot air. This meant the fire had to be kept going
at a fair rate, with terrible risk of the paper envelope
igniting. In fact, de Rozier took up with him a large
sponge and some water, and coolly dealt with a small out¬
break of fire on the balloon casing.
Their feat was capped in December 1783 by Professor
J.A.C. Charles, who made the first voyage in a hydrogen
balloon, flying 27 miles from the Tuileries in Paris in a
rubberized envelope of his own design.
In fact, Charles was the real father of the balloon. He
quickly saw that the hot-air-and-brazier method was too
dangerous, and that the answer lay in a bag filled with
a lighter-than-air gas. Hydrogen, although inflammable,
seemed to him the best, and was in fact used for balloons
CONTD ON PAGE 30
Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Ai
The world's first aeronauts, the Marquis d'Arlandes and Pilatre de Rozier, rose above Paris on November
21, 1783. Their balloon, shown here in a modern re-enactment of the event, stayed in the air for 25 minutes 29
and travelled five and a half miles, over Paris opening the road to the conquest of the air. Ballooning
continued as a popular sport until about 1910 when heavier than air machines began to be developed.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
CHANNEL CROSSING. The first aerial cros¬
sing of the Channel on January 7, 1785, was
made by a Frenchman, Jean-Pierre Blanchard
and an American, Dr. John Jeffries, of Boston.
Unesco Photos
EQUESTRIAN ASCENT. Ballooning soon grew its own crop of eccentricsand showmen. Before
a Bastille Day holiday crowd on a Paris race course in 1850, a Frenchman named Poitevin made a bal loon
ascent (above right) mounted on his pony, Blanche. This kind of fairground stunt, whose cruelty
was rightly condemned, was started over half a century earlier by another Frenchman, Testu Brissy.
SCIENCE FICTION, 1863. An "Aerial Vessel
Designed for Exploration" was conceived and
drawn by an early balloonist, Etienne Gaspard
Robertson. Heavily loaded with equipment,
including a telescope, this early piece of
science fiction actually opened a window on
the future. Balloons have since been and are
still being used for astronomical observation.
WHEN FLIGHT WAS SILENT (Cont'd)
Fantasy & progress
30
until coal gas became readily available in 1821. He also
devised the strong rppe netting over the balloon that
safely supports the basket, or "car," the control valve at
the top, through which gas can be let out, and the cir¬
cular hoop below the rigging from which the car hangs.
On his second ascent he rose alone to nearly two miles,
and again landed safely.
Hearing of these epic flights, wise old Dr. Samuel John¬
son prophesied that the age of the "flying coach" was
near. In fact, ballooning became a reality before the
dawn of the nineteenth century.
In 1784, the first woman to fly, Madame. Thible, had
gone up as a passenger from Lyons, in France, and later
that year interest shifted to England, where a young Ita¬
lian diplomat, Vincent Lunardi, made the first English
flight. Over 20,000 highly sceptical and Impatient specta¬
tors watched his small red and blue hydrogen bag ascend
from the Artillery Ground in London.
The pilot took with him a cat, a dog and a pigeon.
The latter escaped soon after take-off, and the cat
suffered so much from the cold that Lunardi touched
down in Middlesex to release it. Taking off again, he
finally landed at Standon, in Hertfordshire, where a stone
monument commemorates his "traversing the regions of
the air" for 2i hours.
By 1784, in fact, basic ballooning principles had been
established. So long as the complete craft, filled with gas,
weighs less than the amount of air it displaces, it will
rise, leaving the ground after release of numerous sand¬
bag "anchors." When the volume of the surrounding air
equals the balloon's weight exactly, the gas-bag remains
suspended in space, "in equilibrium." Once gas is
released, however, air takes its place, making the weight
heavier than that of the surrounding air, and so the
balloon drops.
In practice, piloting a balloon was largely a matter of
extreme watchfulness in the use of the ballast carried on
board, usually sand in 20 lb. or 30 lb. bags. Even a handful
of sand dropped overboard would cause the envelope to
rise from equilibrium. The pilot kept a constant eye on
his simple altimeter, an ordinary aneroid barometer, and
so judged his height.
Among the hanging control ropes above the flyers'
heads, but kept in a separate sleeve and painted bright
red to prevent accidental use, was the rip-line. When
pulled, this tore out the long ripping-panel, about half
one of the vertical panels, or "gores" from which the
envelope was made. This instantly emptied the balloon
of gas, and was used only on landing.
As early as the second year of the balloon age, 1784,
these strange aerial craft were used for scientific experi¬
mentation and travel, as well as being a fascinating
novelty. Two hardy aeronauts, the Frenchman J. P. Blan¬
chard and Dr. John Jeffries, of Boston, U.S.A., made the
first scientific observations, from a free-flying balloon, and
in January, 1785, made the first pre-determlned journey
in one, across the English Channel, from England to
France.
They carried a compass with them, taking off when the
wind was blowing in the right direction, and finally landed
safely, but not before jettisoning their oars, food and sup¬
plies, and even some of their clothes to maintain height.
Pilâtre de Rozier and his friend Romain, trying to repeat
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
FLIGHT OF FANCY. This drawing wsa published
in Vienna in 1801 with the explanation, "The latest
invention : a balloon towed by eagles." According to the
artist's ingenious flight of fancy, these birds in harness
allowed themselves to be guided like a team of horses.
MID-AIR MARRIAGE. In 1865 an American bride.
showing that she was immune both to vertigo and the
limelight of publicity, agreed to be married in mid¬
air above New York. Already 80 years earlier the first
female balloon passenger had flown from Lyons, France.
this voyage in the reverse direction on June 15, 1785 in
a balloon that oddly combined both the hot-air and hydro¬
gen type, tragically became the world's first air casualties
when their gas ignited and they crashed near Boulogne.
Not long afterwards, on the express orders of Napoleon
himself, the balloon became an engine of war. In June
1794 the French army carried out military reconnaissance
from a tethered gas-bag at Maubeuge. Balloons of one
kind or another have been used for varying purposes in
every major war since.
Another use for balloons began in 1797 when the very
brave French aeronaut, Garnerln, successfully tested the
first real parachute from one. Parachuting from captive
balloons became a popular feature of nineteenth century
spectacles and outdoor entertainments, both men and
women dropping to delight the crowds. In the same year,
Testu Brissy went up mounted on a horse, ushering in a
long series of balloon ascents by all kinds of animals,
including stags and a bull.
All Europe went "balloonatic," as the saying was.
Hardy folk went up for the fun of It at fairs and the like,
where the gaily-coloured and patterned envelopes were
always sure to attract attention and money. Gradually,
however, men began to take this strange new form of
transport seriously, even though all balloon journeys were
at the mercy of the prevailing winds.
With cheap coal gas established as the lifting power,
scientists, inventors and explorers took to the air. Men
could fly at last, but passively, standing uncomfortably in
little wicker cars, at the mercy of the elements, yet In
control of the climbing and falling of their overhead craft.
What was it like to "enclose a cloud in a bag and sail
upon the bosom of the air?" All balloonists agree that
although it was exciting to risk danger and launch into
the unknown in such a new way, the greatest single
reaction was one of sheer elation. "Lingering in the deep
blue vault of space," though in fact seldom higher than
about 10,000 feet, regularly gave aeronauts "a sensation
of perfect quietude and restfulness, and a feeling of how
petty the earth and its concerns are," said one pioneer.
Ballooning was in fact like arriving at a mountain
summit without the fatigue of the climb. As the gas-bag
always travelled at the exact velocity of the prevailing
wind, there was no sensation of speed, rush or Indeed of
any movement at all. Early balloonists used to throw out
strips of paper to see whether they were rising or falling.
And the overall sense of tranquillity was further marked
by the complete and uncanny silence.
In these old days flight really was completely silent. To
travel in a balloon offered, as one man said, "a silence so
profound that no silence on earth can equal It." Apart
from the occasional slight friendly creak of basket or
rigging, the only sounds heard came up from the earth.
At low altitudes all were plainly audible: the concerted
roar of traffic over towns, the whistle and rumble of
trains, the noise of dogs, cockerels, cattle and children.
Above all, for the first time, men heard the full "Incessant
murmur of the commotion of the waters" when over the
sea. This was unlike the noise of the waves on the sea¬
shore, a strange, mighty rippling surge that In fact can
only be heard from a balloon.
Of course, there were hazards, though most aeronauts
declared their huge craft were easy to handle. There was
a decided chill when clouds or mist were entered, and
above 10,000 feet it could be distinctly uncomfortable. If
wet, ballast could freeze Into Immovable blocks. Owing to
the risk of fire from the coal gas, there was always a strict
"no smoking" rule, and tall hats were taboo. When the
rising envelope blew off surplus gas from its open neck
tube hanging directly above the flyers the effect could be
most unpleasant.
Sometimes when hot sunshine quickly dried out rain-
wetted rigging and caused a simultaneous slight loss of
gas, the car would drop suddenly, perhaps only a couple 31
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
TRIPS BY CINEORAMA. Visitors to the Paris Exhibition of 1 900 were offered the impressions of
a balloon flight without ever leaving the ground. This attraction was made possible by a multiple-
camera device, the "Cineorama", developed by a Frenchman, Raoul Grimoin Sanson. A platform
shaped like a balloon basket, over which hung a real balloon, was surrounded by a circular screen
over 300 feet in circumference. Beneath it was a room equipped with ten film projectors. Grouped
on the platform several hundred spectators could watch films, taken during real balloon flights over
Europe and Africa, projected on the circular screen. After only a few performances the Cineorama
was stopped by the authorities as a serious fire hazard. This spelt ruin for the inventor.
WHEN FLIGHT WAS SILENT (Cont'd)
No noise, no smell, no oil
32
of feet, but forcefully enough to terrify the crew through
the sensation of having broken loose. Lightning was
always a danger to be reckoned with, and it was tricky
trying to land on a chosen spot in a high wind.
From about 1852 onwards some aeronauts grew in¬
creasingly dissatisfied with their inability to steer their
craft or drive it forward. Attempts had long been made
to propel balloons with wooden oars, without success, but
yet another Frenchman, Henry Giffard, developed an
elliptical gas-bag powered by steam-driven propellers.
This was the true ancestor of the air-ship.
But other enthusiasts were content to float freely in
their "gallant and graceful aerial craft," and ballooning
did not begin to die out until about 1909-10, when the
aeroplane became feasible. In 1862 the eminence of the
static gas-bag was well demonstrated when the English
weather expert James Glaisher and the noted balloonist
Coxwell reached some 20,000 ft., a clear record for that
date. Both men went up to make meteorological obser¬
vations, and were seriously affected by the cold and lack
of oxygen. Incidentally, the balloon altitude record,
achieved in 1960 by Capt. J. W. Klittinger of the U.S. Air
Force, stands at 102,800 feet (19.13 miles).
Another aspect of the balloon's unattained powers was
illustrated as long ago as 1897, when the Swedish explorer,
Major S. A. Andrée, tried with two others to reach the
North Pole in a giant hydrogen balloon made of the finest
Chinese silk. With vaseline-soaked rigging to resist
moisture and a specially large car, this monster deserved
to succeed if ever a balloon did.
Unfortunately, Andrée failed to reckon with the Arctic
mist, and his balloon was forced down on the ice, heavy
with frozen mist on the envelope, 288 miles and 65Í hours
after leaving Danes Island. The three men trekked by
sledge over the drifting pack-ice for two and a half
months before perishing of cold on White Island, but by
an incredible chance their remains and last camp were
discovered in 1930. Although 33 years old, and damaged
by wet, some of Andrée's photographs of his crashed
balloon were later developed and printed.
In the early years of this century, ballooning became an
inexpensive sport followed by adventurous pioneers like
Charles Rolls (partner of Henry Royce), T.O.M. Sopwith
and J.T.C. Moore-Brabazón (now Lord Brabazón), Bri¬
tain's first pilot. They used to go up at weekends, and
take part in many events and races to see who could tra¬
vel the furthest before coming down. The 1914 record
of 1,890 miles still stands.
Since those days free-flying balloons have become
almost extinct, but balloons of other types, not least the
myriads* of small weather balloons regularly released all
over the globe, prove that the work of all those intrepid
pioneers was not wasted. Yet when the aeroplane took
over, something was lost, the strange attraction enjoyed
by those first flyers.
To quote Lord Brabazon, writing long afterwards:
"I still maintain that ballooning is the only gentle¬
man's way of going into the air no noise, no smell, no
wind, no oil just peace... and the delight of having to go
the way the wind willed, with the pleasant anticipation
of landing in some remote spot."
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
ROUSSEAU IN THE ROCKIES
Sir,
One of the enthusiastic publics for
your magazine is a little prep school
of very high academic standards that
nestles in the mountains of the Western
Slope of the Rockies, where for the
past few years I have been happily
teaching. At the moment we are
enjoying your special commemorative
issue devoted to Rousseau (Mar. 1963).
It happens that next year I shall be
teaching a college level course here, a
year's seminar on Voltaire and Rous¬
seau. I would like to order about
seven copies of your March issue, for
use as an introductory brochure for
the course.
J. Frank
Colorado, XJS.A.
THE FATE OF THE MAYAS
Sir,
In your March 1962 issue you
state "We know nothing about the
causes of the sudden disappearance
of this amazing pre-Columbian
civilization, whether it was by wars,
epidemics or natural disasters".
As doctors, we know that the
Mayas were wiped out in the middle
of the 15th century by a great
epidemic, which as we have now been
able to confirm, was yellow fever.
One of the characteristic symptoms
of this yellow fever was vomito negro
(haemorrhagic vomiting). The Aztecs,
who were the closest neighbours of
the Mayas, understood that bacteria
were in some way responsible for this
epidemic. They have left illustrations
of the Mayas in the throes of
haemorrhagic vomiting which show
small demons on the substance being
vomited.
The Mayas considered this epidemic
as a punishment inflicted by their
Gods for it was limited to their
territory. The reason for this is that
the fever vector was a mosquito
which never travels more than about
150 yards from the water where it
spends its larval stage. The outbreak
was so deadly that it left hardly any
survivors and even these were
scattered.
Prof. Erwin Gohrbandt
Berlin W. 15
WITH MALICE TO NONE
Dear Sir,
I heartily agree with M.J.M. Del-
larg (Better Investments than Arms
March 1963) that international pub¬
lications such as yours could be ins¬
trumental in uniting the people of the
world.
Our leaders must be made to un¬
derstand that we bear no malice
towards one another and the time has
come for them to settle their differen¬
ces other than by building up stocks
of weapons of unspeakable horror
with the constant threat of their use.
I find it impossible to believe that
the ordinary folk of any country want
to deliberately attack their fellow men.
W.M. Salmon
Kenton, England
DISCUSSION ON «THE ISLAND'
Sir,
From reading your magazine I have
often learned a great deal about the
world's peoples; but nothing has
taught me as much as did the
discussion on the film, "The Island"
between a Japanese girl student and
a man from Europe, published in
your April issue.
This is the road you should follow;
it will lead you to your goal which
is to bring the people in all countries
closer together. The voices of the
man and the young girl brought us
close to hearts and minds of millions
of people, outwardly so different, but
inwardly so alike. A door was opened,
a contact established and we began
to understand.
Keep on using this formula for
it is more alive and more fruitful
than scholarly speeches. I should like
to see a similar discussion published
in a future issue, but this time between
a Japanese man and a European girl
student. The subject? A representative
occidental film which many readers
are likely to have seen, such as
"Room at the Top", "Mourning
Becomes Electra", "La Strada",
"Executive Suite", "Justice est
faite", "Dieu a besoin des hommes"
or other even more appropriate
films those most likely to stimulate
ideas of a deep, sincere and revealing
kind.
It would obviously be a good idea
to present similar discussions between
people from other parts of the world
whose mutual lack of understanding
is one of the most regrettable features
of life today.
M. Pakerar
Saint-Maur, France
FLAG OF THE FUTURE
Sir,
The first Unesco Courier that I
have read is the January 1963
edition. I bought it because it was
in English and there are so few
papers or magazines in English that
we can buy in Budapest. But as I
turned the pages, I realized that it
will mean far more to me than just
an exercise for my English and to
have some interesting news from the
world.
Your articles are very interesting
and instructive. But more sympathetic
still is your purpose to help the
world, to give great help to all
nations undeveloped and others.
I would like to see The Unesco
Courier in our newspaper shops in
Hungarian. We hope one day it can
be done. And about mistrust among
nations... After my experience in
foreign countries and at home, I can
say that nations do not know each
other. We hear about countries
because of their policy. But that isn't
the best way to get to know other
nations. There are so many good
and wonderful things in every
country art, science, history, about
which we should read or should sec.
We send men up above the Earth,
but we should first look around our
world because there are so many
nations who live very badly. And
many people die because of diseases
and accidents who would not do so if
nations would trust and help each
other. We must save land and life
not only for today but for those
who follow. And the only way for
this is : peace. So when I read your
magazine, I read it as a flag of
culture, a flag of the future, a flag
of peace and life.
Miklos Malrai
Budapest, Hungary
UNESCO GIFT PROJECTS
Sir,
I am an adult education tutor with
the University of Otago, New Zealand.
My wife and I have interested a
small study group of lively-minded
people in the problems surrounding
the vast work of aiding under¬
developed areas of the world. We
arc especially interested in Uni.sco's
encouragement of cultural links to
further mutual understanding among
the peoples of Ihe world. In l)m
matter we are all under-developed,
and our informal study group firmly
believes that a great deal more could
be done practically in the struggle
against sickness, poverty and ignor¬
ance, if more people could be encour¬
aged to take part in such activities
as Unesco Gift Projects.
We have studied your pamphlet,
"You and Unesco", and have also
read with great interest the informa¬
tion about gift projects in Tup.
Unesco Courier (February 1963).
It is particularly the opportunity to
develop cultural links which the
projects offer, that interests my group.
Among ourselves we have developed
the habit of calling the group
"person to person"...
My wife and I are quite satisfied
that if such schemes as the Gift
Coupon Projects could be stimulated
in any way, the whole concept of
mutual understanding and the whole
approach to assistance in under¬
developed regions of our globe,
would take on a new vitality.
Can you help us? We have spent
more than a year discussing and
corresponding at all levels. We have
learnt a lot: now we wish to do
something useful.
Mervyn Palmer
Oamahu, New Zealand
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
T\fEW DITCHES FOR OLD: A drastic
programme of reconstruction is being
carried out on the Soviet Republic of
Uzbekistan's 100,000 kilometres of old irri¬
gation canals. Ditches will be straightened
and their beds surfaced with concrete, and
polymer films will be used to resist filtra¬
tion. By these measures it is expected that
enough water to irrigate one and a quarter
million acres will be saved yearly.
PROTECTING MECCA PILGRIMS:
Improved health facilities on the
Mecca Pilgrimage site have led to a sharp
drop in heat casualties, reports the World
Health Organization. Special facilities now
include hospitals with iced water tubs for
cases of heat stroke, mobile health units,
emergency drugstores and a modern ice
factory at the foot of Mount Arafat. Over
one million Moslem worshippers from 60
countries went to Mecca this year, and the
pilgrimage was free from quarantinable
diseases.
MULTILINGUAL LIBRARY GLOS¬
SARY: A multi-lingual glossary of
library terminology to aid international
exchanges in library materials has been
published by Unesco (x) Entitled "Voca-
bularium Bibliothecarii", the new and revis¬
ed edition lists over three thousand differ¬
ent library terms in English with equiva¬
lents in French, German, Spanish and Rus¬
sian. The first edition in 1953 listed only
terminology in English, French and Ger¬
man.
(x) "Vocabularium Bibliothecarii", 627
pages, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-T,
Price: $ 5.75 ; 28/9 (stg) ; 20 Frs.
If ARTHQUAKES TO ORDER: A major
series of experiments to test the resi¬
stance to earthquake shock of various types
of housing is being carried out near Tash¬
kent. Soviet researchers have built houses
complete with plumbing, sewage, gas
mains and heating systems and are stimul¬
ating earthquakes by using explosive
charges from 100 lbs. to 200 tons in
weight.
«»TNDERWATER FARM': At Tria-
*J bunne, on the eastern coast of Tas¬
mania, an "underwater farm" has been
established where various species of sea¬
weed growing along some 300 miles of shal¬
low coastline will be exploited for scienti¬
fic purpose. The harvesting of seaweed,
rich in a compound of alginic acid and
sodium, will be carried out by a boat fitted
with an underwater rotary reaper operat¬
ing three to four feet below the surface.
Chemicals derived from the sodium com¬
pound are used in pharmaceutical products,
cosmetics, foodstuffs and in dyeing and
printing.
tJPACE WATCH ON ANIMAL
v5 MIGRATIONS: Many problems of
animal migration may soon be solved by
information relayed from a satellite orbiting
the earth. A special instrument fitted in
a satellite 200 miles above the earth will
pick up signals from tiny radios strapped
to birds and beasts. Signals relayed by the
satellite to 24 ground stations will enable
scientists to track animals over an area
1,600 miles wide on each orbit, different
species being identified by their own radio
frequencies.
MORE ABOUT ASIA: A pioneer plan
to teach young American students
about Asia, including lessons in an Asian
language, has successfully completed its first
year. Called the Institute of Asian Studies,
its goal is to prepare students to enter col¬
lege with greater knowledge of a non-west¬
ern culture and a good groundwork in an
Asian language. So far the language taught
has been the literary language of China,
Mandarin, but next year's course will in¬
clude Japanese. The project was launched
by the head of a secondary school near
Boston who enlisted co-operation from six
other schools in the area. In New Zealand,
the Education Department has announced
that teaching about Asian countries is to
be introduced in primary and post-primary
schools.
wimii»immnrwi
34
GAY AND COLOURFUL CZECH FOLK ART
Left, a stamp dedicated to Unesco which
Czechoslovakia is issuing this month in six
denominations bearing gay and colourful designs
based on Czech Folk Art. As agent in France
of the U.N. Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all the U.N. stamps and
first-day covers currently on sale as well as many
stamps, like the one shown here, issued by
Unesco Member States to commemorate
important events in the history of Unesco and
the U.N. For prices and further details write:
The Unesco Philatelic Service, Place de Fonte¬
noy, Paris (7e).
h*iiita>
AT OCEAN CROSSROADS: A U.S.
mobile research station, the "Eltanin",
a converted cargo ship, carrying 30 scientists
and technicians, operates in Antarctic
waters for about ten months each year,
with rotating groups of scientists and
crewmen. Much of its work has been
carried out near the Antarctic Convergence,
where the cold waters of Antarctica sink
between the warmer waters of the Atlantic,
Pacific and Indian Oceans. The area is
of special interest to scientists because it
is exceptionally rich in marine life, and
may also play an important role in the
climate of the southern hemisphere.
|T NESCO AND YOUTH: A group of
*-" specialists met in Paris recently to
prepare UNESCO's first international con¬
ference on youth which will be held in
Grenoble, France, next year. This Paris
meeting also discussed a study on the aims
of out-of-school education which Unesco
will make prior to the conference. The
results of this survey, which will cover train¬
ing for professional life, for leisure activi¬
ties, for citizenship and social life and for
international life and understanding, should
provide a world-wide picture of out-of-
school education.
EiEDUCATIONAL TV IN LIBERIA:
The Government of Liberia has announced
that educational TV programmes will be
sent out from a transmitter due to be set
up in the capital, Monrovia, before the
end of 1963. Besides courses of study, the
programmes will include telecasts on educ¬
ational themes.
News Flashes. . .
A plan to develop a world-wide weather
forecasting system which will include the use
of artificial satellites has been approved by
the World Meteorological Organization.
Known as World Weather Watch it will
be run from three centres in Washington,
Moscow and a so far unchosen city in the
southern hemisphere.
As its 200th project to speed economic
development in low-income countries, the
U.N. Special Fund is to help set up a tele¬
communications centre in Baghdad, capital
of Iraq. Iraq's plan for development fore¬
sees expenditure of $94 million for moder¬
nization of telecommunications.
A Union of African News Agencies has
been set up following a Unesco meeting on
the development of national news agencies
in Africa. The Union will link existing
agencies and help to establish new ones
with the aim of increasing the flow of news
within the region and with the rest of the
world.
| Two highlights in the world campaign
against malaria: the population in areas
protected against malaria has reached 148
million; Europe has been freed from the
threat of this disease since the beginning of
1963.
Iceland's 6,000 fishermen are the world's
champions, catching on the average 115 tons
per year per man. This is four to five
times as much as their closest European
counterparts and 30 to 40 limes more than
the world average.
u
z
<
<
13
z
o
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Over 300,000 subscribers
Every month
ONE AND A HALF MILLION
PEOPLE READ
THE UNESCO COURIER
in English, Arabic, French, German,
Japanese, Russian, Spanish and Italian.
The aim of The Unesco Courier is to be neither
too "technical" nor too "popular". Its articles,
richly illustrated with striking photographs, offer
a vivid picture of the endless diversity of peoples
and countries, a world on the march, the great
adventures in science and the problems of our time.
Annual subscription only 10/-stg. ;
3.00 (Canada) ; 7 Fr. frs.
Recent issues included:
FREEDOM FROM HUNGER
JEAN-JACQUES ROUSSEAU
NEW HORIZONS IN MUSIC
SAFETY FIRST AT SEA
HISTORY OF MANKIND
Sp£¿m
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; rates quoted are
for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO COU¬
RIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry ol Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Melbourne University Press, 369 Lonsdale Street,
Melbourne, C. I., Victoria. (A. 15/-). AUSTRIA
Verlag Georg Fromme & C"., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 60.-). BELGIUM. Editions " Labor ",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgielei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (100 FB) and art slides only: Louis de Lannoy,
22, place de Brouckère, Brussels. CCP 3380.00.
BURMA. Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road,
Rangoon. (K. 5.50). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. ($ 3.00). CEYLON. The Associated
Newspapers of Ceylon Ltd., Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CUBA.
E.C.O.D.A.L.D., Neptuno 406, entre Manziquey San Nico¬
las Havana. (2.25 pesos). CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia
Ltd., 30 Ve Smeckich, Prague 2. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, A/S Tidsskriftafdelingen, Prags Boulevard 47
Copenhagen S (D.kr. 12). ETHIOPIA. International
Press Agency. P.O. Box 1 20. Addis Ababa. FINLAND.
Akateeminen Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
(Fmk. 540). FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, Place
de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. (7 F.).
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosens-
heimer Strasse 145, Munich. For the Unesco Kurier
(German ed. only) Bahren-felder-Chaussee 1 60,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP. 276650 (DM 8). GHANA
Methodist Book Depot Ltd. Atlantis House, Commercial
St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See
United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H. Kaufímann,
28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon
Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUNGARY.
Kultura, P.O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. INDIA. Orient
Longmans Ltd. Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13: Gun-
foundry Road, Hyderabad, 1 ; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf All Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxlord Book & Stationery Co.,
17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Sandía House, New Delhi.
Indian National Commission for Co-operation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3. (Rs. 7).
INDONESIA. P. N. Fad/ar Bhakti, Dialan
Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd., 3 5, Allenby
Road and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street. Tel-Aviv( 1 £ 5.50).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. Knox Educational Services, Spaldings.
(10/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Ton-Nichome,
Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo.
(Ten 670). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co.,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco,
P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole
and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Monrovia.
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue,
Luxemburg. MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications Ltd., Times House,
River Valley Rd.. Singapore (M. S 500) MALTA.
Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valetta. (10/-).
MAURITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon
Street, Port-Louis. British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF.). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague,
(fi. 6). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. C. T.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Curacao.
NEW ZEALAND Government Printing Office
Wellington, Government Printing Office, P.O. Box S344,
Auckland and Government Bookshops, Auckland,
Wellington, Christchurch. Dunedin (10/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshop, P.O. Box 174, Lagos. (10/-). NOR.
WAY. A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille Creme. 7, Oslo
For the Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narv«iens Liiteratur
Tjenesce, Stortingsgt. 4, Oslo, Poslboks 115 (kr 13.20
PAKISTAN. The Weit-Pak Publishing Cor
Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374, 56-N
Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PANAMA.
Cultural Panameña, Avenida 7a, No. TI-49, Apartado de
Correos 2018, Panama, D.F. (Balboas 3-). PHILIPPI¬
NES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenu« P. O. Box
632 Manila. POLAND. "RUCH" ul. Wiloza Nr. 46,
Warsaw 10 (Zl. 50). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada
Lda, Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon,
PUERTO RICO. Spanish English Publications Apartado
1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA & N YASALAND. The
Book Centre, First Street, Salisbury, Southern Rhodesia.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O, Box 1118. Khart¬
oum. SWEDEN, A/B CE. Frittes Kungl. Hovbok-
handel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm. For The Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15*17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7.50); SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag,
5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40, rut du Marché, Geneva.
CCP. 1-236. " Courier " only: Georges Losmaz, 1, rue
des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP. 1-4811. (Fr.S. 8).
TANGANYIKA. Dar-es-Salaam Bookshop, P.O.B.
9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND. Suksapan
Panit, Mansion 9, Ra|damnern Avenue, Bangkok. (35
ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda
Bookshop, P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Bookslore. Libri
Building, Church Street, Pretoria. For the Unesco Cou¬
rier (single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O.
Box 1033, Johannesburg. (10/-). UNITED ARAB
REPUBLIC (EGYPT). La Renaissance d'Egypte. 9 Sh.
Adly-Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H.M.
Stationery Office, P.O. Box 5 69, London, S.E.I. (10/-).
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications Center,
317 East 34th St, New York, 16. N.Y. ($5.00.)
and (except periodicals): Columbia University Press,
2960 Broadway, New York, 27 N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mez-
hdunarodnaja Kniga. Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA
Yugoslovenska Knjiga, Terazije 27/11, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
sy, Paris
A romantic, adventurous but now vanished era of air transport
the age of the balloonis recalled by this gaily-decorated craft
being prepared for a flight from the centre of Paris. The ascent
took place during a ceremony commemorating Jules Verne's novel,
" Around the World in 80 Days ", whose hero, Phileas Fogg,
accomplished one stage of his epic journey in a balloon. For the
story of man's first conquests of the air, see story page 28.
]]>
</page>
</document>
