<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078362eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
A window open on the world
W IT
year) U.K. : 1/6 stg. - Canada : 30 cents - France : 1 F
PERUVIAN
CHRONICLES IN CLAY
Wm\
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
* *v 'Vî
»
il tï e»V^' < 'i*#
If »A , * .
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART ©
The lonely world of Giacometti
These soaring, rough-pitted figures are the work of Alberto Giacometti, the great
Swiss sculptor, who died In January at the age of 64. Giacometti gained international
fame only in his later years. His sculpture has been called tree-like, and offers a
curious combination of togetherness and loneliness. He came to Paris in 1922 and
studied under Bourdelle, himself a pupil of Rodin, and produced many works, although
he destroyed a great, number which failed to satisfy him. Only about 200 of his sculpt¬
ures exist today, along with his ' paintings and drawings.
Maeght Foundation Collection, St Paul de Vence. Photo © Maeght Foundation-Claude Gasparl
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
MARCH 1966 - 19TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg. ; $3.00
(Canada) ; 10 French Francs or equivalent;
2years:27/-stg.; 18 F. Single copies 1/6-stg.;
30 cents ; 1 F.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in July and August when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed
by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied to editors on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly In The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*. France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief,
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition : Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Illustrations : Phyllis Feldkamp
Research : Olga Rodel
Layout & Design : Robert Jacquemin
Allcorrespondence shouldbe addressedto the Editor-in-Chief.
10
12
16
20
23
25
32
EUROPE'S EXPANDING NUCLEAR RESEARCH
By M. S. Wilde
PERU'S COASTAL DESERTS
Land of three great cultures
By Peveril Meigs
PERUVIAN CHRONICLES IN CLAY
LIBRARIES FOR CHILDREN ONLY
THE AMBER ROUTES OF ANTIQUITY
By Wladislaw Grzedzielski
THE TRANSMIGRATION OF SHOALS
A new Mediterranean fishing problem
By Daniel Behrman
ANCIENT SCRIPTS FROM AFRICA
By Dmitri A. Olderogge
GREAT MEN, GREAT EVENTS
FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Cover photo
The Indian fishermen of northern
Peru still use reeds to make
simple skiffs which they call
"little reed horses." They
inherited this tradition from
their distant ancestors, the Mo-
chicas, as is shown by this
Mochican pottery decoration: a
stylized drawing of a reed
vessel with bow and stern
fashioned into dragon heads.
The Mochicas were master cera¬
mists who revealed every de¬
tail of their lives in fine,
realistically moulded pottery,
(see page 12).
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
- 'V f i
i -: ^ '* ah ^
'fe; y n
^.m
' This tangled mass of wires I
problem for a telephone sw
reality it is part of a carefully-planned and complex
network of electronic equipment with which atomic
,., research teams monitor the results of experiments
at the European Organization for Nuclear Research.
Unesco-Paul Almasy, Paris
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
EUROPE'S
EXPANDING
NUCLEAR
RESEARCH
CENTRE
by M. S. Wilde
To probe deeper and deeper into the infin¬
itely tiny world of the atom, science has
paradoxically to design and build larger
and larger tools giant accelerators pro¬
ducing beams of high energy particles that
can "prise open" the close-knit structure
of atomic nuclei. CERN, the European
Organization for Nuclear Research, in
Geneva, which was created under the
auspices of Unesco in 1952, has decided
to build a new type of atom smashing
machine, 50 times more powerful than any
existing accelerator. What this will do
and why CERN foresees the need for a
still more colossal one within the next
decade are explained in this article.
peaceful penetration into France from Switzer¬
land has been made by CERN, the European
Organization for Nuclear Research, to find space to build
a new type of atom smashing machine which can reach
energies more than fifty times those produced by the
biggest conventional particle accelerator In the world today,
which is at Brookhaven, U.S.A.
On a 100-acre site In Switzerland, on the French border
just outside Geneva, CERN now has an accelerator called
a Proton Synchroton with an energy of 28 GeV (28,000
million electron Volts), the second most powerful in exis¬
tence.
This machine accelerates proton particles to speeds near¬
ly equivalent to that of light (186,000 miles per second),
which then smash against atomic nuclei in detectors.
However, these latter are stationary; and because of their
resistance or recoil, three-quarters of the original force is R
lost, so that the impact represents an energy of only 7 GeV.
The same, of course, holds true for all other accelerators
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
CERN CERN is a European co-operative enterprise in which the skills and resources of 13 European countries
are being applied to experimental and theoretical nuclear research of a non-military nature. The results
of its work are made available to all countries throughout the world. Over 350 fellows and visiting scien¬
tists come to stay at CERN for anything from two months to two years, so that It also plays an important
role in the education of the new generation of scientists. Many other scientists visit CERN to discuss and
describe the most recent discoveries in nuclear research. Above, an international group of physicists
carries on a discussion and (facing page) a visiting scientist lectures on atomic structures at CERN.
EXPANDING NUCLEAR RESEARCH (Cont'd)
Peaceful collisions beneath the frontier
6
of the same type, such as the one of 33 GeV at Brook-
haven, and the one of 10 GeV at Dubna, near Moscow,
U.S.S.R. It is also one of the reasons why nuclear physi¬
cists call for the construction of ever larger and more
costly conventional accelerators; one of 70 GeV is now
under construction at Serpukhov In the U.S.S.R., while
one of 200 GeV Is under contemplation in the United
States, and another of 300 GeV by CERN somewhere in
Europe, but not at Geneva where there is no suitable site
for it.
But some years ago, and practically simultaneously, a
team of physicists from Stanford and Princeton Univer¬
sities in the U.S.A., a group of Soviet physicists at Novosi¬
birsk, and another group, a mixed Italian and French team,
hit upon the same brilliant idea. Why not have two beams
of particles accelerated to about the equivalent of the
speed of light collide with each other In an intersecting
storage ring? In this way, energies could be produced far
exceeding those of smashing Into any stationary target.
However, at Stanford University it took six years of trial
and error to put the Idea into practice. The French and
Italians, working at Frascati, Italy and Orsay, France have
been experimenting with a small storage ring called "Ada"
since 1962. In the Soviet Union, physicists have built and
operated intersecting storage rings for electrons and posi¬
trons.
Once assured of its probable success, CERN decided to
put the collision principle into practice on a large scale.
Its Council has approved the construction of such a ring
in an underground circular tunnel, using protons, the acce¬
leration of the particles being provided by the existing
Synchrotron, which will feed beams at about the speed of
light Into the ring at two different points and In opposite
directions. There will be eight points of Intersection at
which collisions can be made to occur, and their results
observed, at a force for which a conventional accelerator of
1,700 GeV would be needed at present a practical Impossi¬
bility.
The ring, which will have a diameter of about 330 yards
(302 metres) will be equipped with powerful concentric
magnets to guide the beams. Its estimated cost is 64 mil¬
lion dollars (£22,500,000), which will be spent over the next
six years. The money will be provided by the thirteen
member states of CERN: Austria, Belgium, Denmark, France,
the Federal Republic of Germany, Greece, Italy, the Nether-
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
gw«^
l^t**'
Ä^M
Paul Almasy, Paris
lands, Norway, Spain, Sweden, Switzerland and the United
Kingdom (1).
Since there was not enough adjacent room on the Swiss
side of the border to construct It, CERN has leased another
100 acres (40 hectares) of land, belonging to the French
State, across the border in the foothill country of the Jura
mountains. The lease covers a period of 99 years and is
renewable. It Is at a "peppercorn" rent of ten francs (not
quite a pound sterling) per annum. However, In order
not to interfere with the provisions of the 1953 Convention
which established the European Organization for Nuclear
Research In Switzerland, the new area across the French
frontier will be completely fenced off, so that all entrances
and exits will be on the Swiss side. The agreement hand¬
ing over the French territory to CERN was signed at a
ceremony on September 13, 1965.
With this new project now virtually under way, with the
main object of achieving high energy collisions between
(1) Three other countries, Poland, Turkey and Yugoslavia, have
observer status with CERN.
particles, the question naturally arises why It should be
necessary to build bigger and more powerful accelerators
of the conventional static target type as well. The main rea¬
son Is that only collisions between protons and protons
can be investigated in the new storage ring, which Is cer¬
tainly not enough to explore properly the new world of sub-
nuclear particles and forces now opening up. It does not
allow the use of "probes" of mesons and other particles
which make up the large majority of today's experiments.
"This is why", says a recent CERN report, "everyone Is
agreed that a 300 GeV Proton Synchroton is essential for
Europe within the next decade, since it will generate the
whole range of different "probes" the high-energy beams
of many kinds of particles which will be needed. Never¬
theless, just as the first look into this new world was made
through the window of cosmic rays, so the Intersecting
Storage Rings which provide collisions similar to those
of cosmic rays, but with very much larger Intensity and
much better defined and controlled are to be seen as a
window into the possible world which lies behind the com¬
plexity of today's high-energy physics.
"The proton-proton interaction has always been a res-
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
7
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
EXPANDING NUCLEAR RESEARCH (Cont'd)
Nine countries
offer 19 sites
for future accelerator
pectable part of nuclear research, and the Intersecting
Storage Ring can provide for this part of the physics of
1,500 GeV (or even bigger) accelerators at a comparatively
small costabout 5 per cent of that of the equivalent
Proton Synchrotron."
Nevertheless, there are risks. The CERN report adds:
"Firm guarantees cannot be expected: any important step
Into the unknownwhether it be the CERN Proton Synchro¬
tron ten years ago or the Intersecting Storage Ring now
must ultimately be a scientific act of faith, since experience
shows that the questions that seem important now are
often resolved in other ways before a new machine starts
operating, and that its most valuable contributions to
knowledge are never foreseen at the start.
"It Is reasonable that CERN should carry for the whole
of Europe risks of this kind, which would not be acceptable
to countries individually, provided that they do not endanger
the running of CERN itself. The amount at stake can per¬
haps be judged from the fraction of the CERN budget
about 20 per cent which the operation of the Intersecting
Storage Ring will represent after 1970. The fraction of
the total European expenditure (on nuclear physics) will,
of course, be smaller still."
There is also the time factor to consider. If all goes
well, the new Intersecting Storage Ring should be in ope¬
ration within five to six years. The construction of the
colossal 300 GeV conventional accelerator, in a circular
tunnel with a diameter of one and one-half miles (2.4 kms)
on the other hand, has not even reached the planning stage.
When finally completed it would, of course, be the largest
of its kind in the world for many years to come; even the
U.S. is only contemplating construction of a similar machine
of only two-thirds this size and energy.
-'.''..'Jr-. -*"
PUZZLE
PHOTOS
These are playthings of grown men. With
them they learn a great deal about the
structure of the universe. You probably
can't guess what each contraption is for
except for one. Answers on page 32.
Photos CERN
8
BOUT a year ago, CERN asked member states
to offer sites for the new giant accelerator and
the response was gratifying; nineteen possible sites were
put forward by nine member states out of thirteen. All of
these had to be Investigated for suitability and, by the end
of 1965, there remained for consideration the following:
Goepfritz in Austria, Focant in Belgium, Le Luc in France,
Kongsvinger in Norway, El Escorial in Spain, Uppsala in
Sweden and Mundford in the United Kingdom. In addition
there are two sites still under review in the Republic of
Germany: Drensteinfurt and Sarrelouis; and another two
in Italy: Nardo and Doberdo.
Geological, geotechnlcal and hydrogeological studies are
continuing at all these places, as well as investigations
into local industrial potential, the availability of manpower,
housing, schooling, etc. It is expected that complete
reports on ten sites will be placed before the CERN Coun¬
cil when it meets next June, the other nine by then having
been eliminated.
Not until then will it be possible to make a final selection.
Thereupon the money for construction, estimated at about
150 million pounds sterling ($420 million), will have to be
found. Thereafter it will take at least ten years to build,
so that in no circumstances could the 300 GeV accelerator
be completed before 1976-77.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
© Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
4g
Paul Almasy, Paris Giant sand dunes in the coastal desert of the province of lea, southern Peru.
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
PERU'S COASTAL
nvrrQCrpTQ Land of three
ULOLlv I O great cultures
by Peveril Meigs Deserts reach down to the sea along some 18,500 miles of the world's
coastlines. They cover vast areas in Mauritania, South Africa, Australia and
California, form an unbroken chain from north-western India to the Red
Sea and follow the west coast of South America for well over 2,000 miles.
Coastal deserts have special characteristics whose study is of great impor¬
tance to arid zone research. The proximity of the sea and the possibilities
of desalting sea water on a large scale for domestic and industrial needs,
and perhaps eventually for irrigation, also give new importance to these
hitherto neglected areas,. This is made clear in a recently published report
on the inter-continental survey of coastal deserts (1) carried out for Unesco
by Dr. Peveril Meigs, chairman of the Arid Zone Commission of the Inter¬
national Geographical Union. In the article below, which is taken from
this study, Dr. Meigs describes Peru's coastal desert, historically and
economically one of the most interesting in the world. An international
conference on coastal deserts is to be held in Peru next year under the
auspices of Unesco and the International Geographical Union.
(/) "Geography of Coastal Deserts", Unesco, $.6.50; 33/-(stg.); 23 F.
B ordering the Pacific Ocean for 2,300 miles at
the base of the Andes stretches the longest
west-coast desert in the world. The southern part of the
desert, in Chile, is known as the Atacama. The northern
part, in Peru, has no accepted inclusive name, unless it be
simply La Costa (the coast).
Though the land offers little unity, the sea and its
associated climatic and biologic influences are strikingly
uniform along the entire coast. Directly off shore is a
belt of water abnormally cool for the latitude. Although
associated with the northward-flowing Peru Current or
Humboldt Current, the cold water belt consists actually of
upwelling water from the deep layer of the ocean.
Lowest temperatures of about 60° F. are found within a
mile of the coast, and westward they rise steadily for at
least 100 miles, to a level about 16° F higher. The tem¬
perature is remarkably uniform along the whole coast to
Punta Pariñas, where the continent reaches its western¬
most extent within less than 5° latitude of the equator.
As a result of the cool water off shore, and the pre¬
valence of south-westerly winds, the littoral has a strikingly
mild and uniform climate. The coolest month usually
August, averages above 59° F., while the warmest month,
January or February, is from 68 to 81° F. At such temper-
PEVERIL MEIGS ¡s a U.S. geographer who has specialized in
arid zone problems for many years. He is the author of "Distri¬
bution of Arid Homoclimates" , published by the United Nations
in 1952. The collection of maps specially compiled for this work
also appeared in the Unesco study "Hydrology of the Arid Zone"
(1953).
atures, practically all temperate and subtropical crops are
possible, provided water is available. As In other west-
coast deserts, the cool water off shore gives such stability
to the air that rainfall is slight or, in some years, non¬
existent.
But in winter, from June to October, there is a strong
development of low cloud, of a type locally famous under
the name garua. The garua, a fine mist, forms a layer
about 1,000 ft. thick, with its base between about 1,000 and
3,000 ft. above sea level. It furnishes enough water to
support a growth of vegetation on any hills or mountains
within its reach near the coast. In addition, the garua shuts
out the sunlight for most of the time, resulting in chilly,
gloomy conditions, and retarding evaporation in the land
below it.
The cool water off shore has other profound conse¬
quences for human activity. The upwelling water supports
a prolific growth of plankton, which in turn feed fish of
many species and tremendous numbers. From the earliest
times the fish have been an important source of food for
the Peruvians. In addition, they support many millions of
sea birds that crowd the desert islands up and down the
coast.
These birds, of which a type of cormorant, the guanay,
is by far the most numerous, nest on the islands, where
their droppings form the guano accumulations that consti¬
tute one of the most valuable resources of Peru. Such
accumulations are possible only in deserts, where there is
virtually no rainfall to erode the deposits.
Although the guano deposits were used by the ancient
Indian civilizations to maintain the fertility of the irrigated
lands of the coastal desert in Peru, their great value was
only "rediscovered" in the mid-nineteenth century, at which
CONT'D ON PAGE 14
H
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
Sea eagle from a Mochican
pottery design
is one of many birds,
plants and animals
of the Peruvian
coastal desert portrayed
by Mochican artists,
whose works reveal
an equal mastery
of painting and pottery.
Animal portraits were
also stylized
and sometimes grouped
in skilful geometrical
designs like the sea eagle
frieze shown
on facing page.
Below, painted vase
topped by figure
of owl god.
Hyokichi Sato-Yoshltaro Amano, Tokyo
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
PERUVIAN
CHRONICLES
IN CLAY
Over 15 centuries ago, long before
the rise of the Inca Empire, a remark¬
able civilization flourished on the
northern coast of Peru. Its people,
the Mochicas, excelled as ceramic
artists, and have left us a fascinating
record of the world they lived in.
These master potters modelled every¬
thing that captured their imagina¬
tion men and animals, birds, fruits,
vegetables and the humblest objects
of everyday life (see "On Looking
into a Mochican Urn" , Unesco Cour¬
ier, Feb. Î955). They were chroni¬
clers who painstakingly recorded in
clay the most intensely human
aspects of life as well as the cus¬
toms, beliefs and social structure of
their ancient civilization. Whether
modelling in clay or decorating
vases in red and brown colours on
a cream-yellow background, Mochi¬
can artists displayed an astonishing
degree of artistic perfection and
unbridled imagination. The Peruvian
archaeologist, Arturo Jimenez Borja,
has written a special study on the
significance of Mochican ceramics,
"Cuentos Peruanos" (Peruvian
Tales), from which the decorative
designs on these pages are taken.
Mochican hunter waving
a paddle, chases a seal
towards a suitable
killing ground,
where he will finish off
the animal with
a heavy club.
Sea shells and starfish
show that the hunt
is taking place
on the seashore.
Warriors' dance.
The tintinnabulation of the bells
attached to the ceremonial
costumes
helps the dancers
to keep the rhythm.
Dances of all kinds
are depicted on Mochican pottery;
paintings reveal use of
drums, reed pipes,
tambourines and bells.
Drawings © Arturo Jimenez Borja, Lima
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
PERU'S COASTAL DESERTS (Cont'd)
Less inhabited than in Inca times
14
time the guano had accumulated to depths of as much as
150 ft. on some islands. In the ensuing feverish "guano
rush", millions of tons were shipped to Europe, and the
deposits were mined out in a few years, with no thought
given to conservation of the sea fowl that made these riches
possible.
During the last fifty years, however, the Peruvian Govern¬
ment, through the Compañía Administradora del Guano, has
sponsored the necessary conservation measures to encour¬
age the multiplication of the guanayes, and the guano,
now treated as a perpetual annual crop, yields more than
300,000 tons per year. Not only are the fifty or more guano
islands set aside as bird sanctuaries, with guano harvesting
permitted only at certain seasons, but positive measures are
taken to encourage multiplication of the birds. Thus at
some localities low walls are built to prevent the young
birds from falling over the cliffs into the sea.
To expand the overcrowded nesting areas, starting in
1946 the Government has walled off peninsulas of the main¬
land so that birds can breed without molestation by animal
predators. In effect, this has already created ten or more
new guano "Islands", most of them on the southern coast
where true islands are lacking.
In recent years a new threat to the guano industry has
appeared. The vast schools of anchovies that make up
the chief food of the birds are now being harvested directly
by fishermen through mass methods, to be dried, ground
up, and sold as fresh meal for poultry and cattle feed. One
of the big questions is the extent to which direct harvesting
of the anchovies can be made without upsetting the écolo¬
gie balance that makes possible the production of guano.
Already the Government has placed restrictions on this type
of fishing.
A complicating factor In the écologie balance enters the
scene at irregular intervals: a warm countercurrent from the
north, known as the Niño (Christ Child) because it appears
about Christmas, when the solar heating system, along
with its intertropical air masses, has moved south of the
equator. The Niño annually flows southward 5° to 8° from
the equator, over-riding the northern part of the Peru
Current near the coast.
Occasionally, usually at intervals of seven or more years,
the Niño thrusts much farther south, sometimes even
reaching Pisco, 14° S., where it is finally deflected seaward
at the Paracas Peninsula.
BNORMALLY warm, this water causes the
plankton to remain far below the surface, in
cooler water, or to die at the surface where they form great
masses sometimes known locally as the "Callao Painter".
The fish, in turn, die by the millions, and the birds, weakened
by undernourishment and the effort of flying much farther
then accustomed in search of live fish, sicken and die in
such numbers that the guano crops drop disastrously,
building back to normal only after a period of some years.
The presence of the warm water off shore also gives
the air an instability that sometimes results in torrential rain
and floods in areas that may have had no rain for a year.
In 1925, one of the worst Niño years, Lima had a rainfall
of 60 in., as compared with an average annual rainfall of
1.8 in. Along the whole northern half of the coast there
was more rainfall In March than during the preceding ten-
year period.
The attractions of mild climate, abundant water from the
Andes, abundant fish everywhere off shore, vast deposits
of guano to maintain soil productivity and nearby mineral
deposits were taken advantage of to develop ancient cen¬
tres of advanced civilization in the coastal desert 2,000
years before the Spanish conquest.
Primitive agriculture may have started in this area as
early as 3,000 B.C., with cotton and later maize among the
chief crops, though sea food was the chief source of nutri¬
ment. From 1225 to 700 B.C., ceramics, textiles, architec¬
ture, irrigation and gold-working were developed. From
600 to 350 B.C., beans, llamas as beasts of burden, stone¬
walled terraces for irrigation, and copper-working entered
the picture.
HEN arose one of the greatest American civi¬
lizations, which lasted from the fourth century
B.C. to the tenth century A.D. Unlike the Egyptian, Medi¬
terranean, and ancient Greek civilizations, the ancient Peru¬
vian cultures were not ancestral to modern European-type
culture and consequently have received little attention from
Western writers, apart from the specialized academic
circles. Furthermore they had no written language. How¬
ever, they do provide valuable clues to the potentialities of
coastal deserts, and they passed on certain economic insti¬
tutions that still prevail in coastal Peru.
Many details of the material culture and chronology of
the great coastal civilization of Peru were obtained from
artefacts uncovered by the guano-quarrying between A.D.
1840 and 1880. The early Indians, in the course of their
guano-gathering, left behind articles of gold, copper, tex¬
tiles,, and other materials that soon became buried and pre¬
served under the constant accumulation of guano. We
know that arts and crafts reached peaks of excellence,
especially In pottery, textiles, and metallurgy in gold, silver,
copper and alloys (bronze was never hit upon). Agriculture
reached a level never subsequently regained in this region,
through the use of thoroughly planned Irrigation systems
and intensive use of guano.
Although the great civilization extended throughout most
of the Peruvian coastal desert, it involved numerous variants
in the different Irrigated valleys, most of which were sepa¬
rated from one another by sterile stretches of desert.
Three distinct subculture areas have been recognized: the
Mochica culture in the north, the Lima culture In the centre,
and the Nazca culture in the south.
The northern culture was the most extensive, reaching
from about Rio Jequetepeque to Rio Casma, and centring
in the great city of Chanchan, adjacent to the present-day
city of Trujilio. Chanchan, a city of 200,000 people, has
probably made more Intensive use of sun-dried "adobe"
bricks than any other locality in the world.
Great engineering works, Including one canal 73 miles
long, brought water from the Moche and Chlcama rivers to
irrigate the alluvial plain of Chanchan. Some of these
canals have been rebuilt and are In use today, though
large areas of formerly farmed land have not yet been
brought back Into Irrigation. In the Nepeña valley, near
the southern limit of Mochica culture, remains of a huge
dam have been found. Guano was systematically used to
extract maximum production from the Intensively cultivated
land.
Nazca culture In the south, In the basins of the Rio
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
O J. Hardouin
Monoliths engraved
with bas reliefs of
human figures stand
at the foot of Mount
Cerro Sechin, 250
miles from Lima, the
capital of Peru. An¬
cient stone sculpture
is rare in Peru, and
these standing sto¬
nes are one of the
mysteries of the old
coastal civilizations.
Nothing is known
about their origin
or their significance.
Grande and Rio lea, lacked the advanced metallurgy of
Mochica, but attained unsurpassed levels of excellence in
weaving. It had Its own distinctive pottery. The Lima cul¬
ture, in the valleys of the Rios Chancay, Chillón, Rlmac,
and Lurin, was the most primitive of the three.
In the eleventh and twelfth centuries A.D., the great
coastal cultures were overwhelmed by the Tiahuanacan
group from the Interior. ' In the thirteenth to fifteenth
centuries there was another blossoming of coastal civiliza¬
tion, known as the Chimú culture. Chanchan was a major
centre, but other small kingdoms flourished too. Then in
1470 the Inca conquest extended to the coastal desert,
and in 1533 Pizarro conquered all Peru and brought to an
end the whole highly organized civilization that he found.
The modern cultures, like those of the distant past, still
depend upon irrigation agriculture, fishing, guano, and llama
travel off the main roads. Cotton and maize remain major
crops, but two other chief crops, sugar cane and rice, are
post-Columbian In this region. Iron ore and petroleum,
unknown by the Mochlcas, have been added to the exploit¬
ed resources of the region. Hydro-electric power from the
bordering mountains is another new source of energy. Yet
the present-day population of Peru, about 11 million,
remains less than that of the Mochica and Inca periods.
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
FOR CHILDREN
ONLY
Children's libraries exist all over the world, but most of them are school librar¬
ies or simply sub-departments of public libraries designed to serve adults.
Libraries conceived and built to operate as independent units, catering exclu¬
sively for children are still rare exceptions. The latest of this kind and the
first in France opened recently among the red-brick apartment houses in the
Paris suburb of Clamart. Recent urban development in this, area had raised
its population of youngsters, aged four to fourteen, to over 6,000, but little
was being done to cater for their leisure time needs. So "La Joie par les
Livres," a nonprofit organization for promoting reading, decided to build a
comfortable and attractive cultural and recreational centre which would pro¬
vide books, illustrated lectures and classes in painting, pottery and clay mod¬
eling. The centre opened towards the end of last year and within two
months over 1,000 children were using it regularly. Our photo story shows
some features of the library, whose architecture, equipment and methods
combine to stimulate and satisfy the spontaneous interests of young people.
k
Children come down
the stairway from the reading
room to the lending section.
Youngsters really feel at home
in this library
with its attractive decor
of concrete and pinewood
lit by large lamps (left).
Below, young readers
take book choices
to the lending desk.
Library has space
for 10.000 books.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Bl BS
I JÍÍMÍi SfS h.
** «S S3 SB SB Ml SB «
- 's»» s--» ¡buk asa sc sai a«
-Jhivlt
The new children's library
at Clamart, near Paris,
mantled in snow.
Its design, based on a series
of intersecting curves,
makes maximum use of space.
Popular with the
youngest children is
the Story Room where
they listen to tales
and follow them with the aid
of picture books. Right
library viewed from garden.
Photos Unesco-Dominique Roger
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
$^;^m.>zx8®®m
Children find it great fun to walk
around the Clamart library
in their stockinged feet.
They were first asked to take off
their shoes because of the mud
they tracked in when the area
around was churned up
by building operations. The rule
has now been definitely adopted.
Shoes are stored in compartments
in the cloakroom (below).
Children run no risk of chills;
the heated floor warms their silent feet.
II 11!
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
m*
i*.
A PAINTING LENDING
LIBRARY FOR JUNIOR
How would that look in my room? A
young boy discovers some marvels of
world art (left), reproductions of which
are kept in a special collection at the
library. Children can take away these
framed pictures, just like library books,
and keep them for up to two weeks.
The collection is renewed regularly and
ranges from abstract art to Renais¬
sance paintings a youngster may
come across anything from a work by
Max Ernest to a drawing by Leonardo
da Vinci. Tasting art like this can
inspire children with a real taste for
art; aspiring artists can put their urges
to work in rooms set aside for paint¬
ing and modeling, and also get some
help from the art teacher if they wish.
The library has over 300 foreign language books English, Danish, Russian,
Italian, German, Japanese and so on which are equipped with tape-recorded
texts in French. Here a boy pores over some fascinating illustrations
in a Japanese book which he can also "read" on tape.
So far more boys than girls have been making use of the library.
Photos Unesco-Dominique Roger
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE AMBER ROUTES
OF ANTIQUITY
by Wladislaw Grzedzielski
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Trading in amber began
3,000 years ago when
the merchants
of Phoenicia
made long voyages
¡n search of it,
thus launching a commerce that
was to spread
throughout Europe.
The great amber routes
of the past which
ran from the Baltic
to the Mediterranean
and the Black Sea,
are shown on this map.
Sea routes,
probably those followed
by the Phoenicians,
are shown in white;
dotted lines indicate
where merchants
travelled across country
or by inland waterways.
I NE could hardly begin the story of amber
without recalling a Greek myth which Ovid
recounts in his Metamorphoses. No doubt most people
have already heard it, but its charm is such that one may
be forgiven for telling it again.
The adventure of Phaeton, who pursuaded his father
Helios, the Sun God, to let him drive the Sun Chariot across
the heavens, may serve as a warning to any young man
who should ever aspire to take the controls of a space ship
without a pilot's licence. The adventure ended disastrously
since Phaeton, unaccustomed to driving the Sun Chariot,
came too close to earth and nearly burnt up the universe. In
his anger, Jupiter struck Phaeton with a thunderbolt and
cast his body into the River Eridanus. Phaeton's sisters,
the Heliades, were changed into poplar trees because they
had yoked the horses to the Sun Chariot, and the tears
they wept hardened into drops of amber which the river
bore down to the sea.
What is really interesting about the legend is the idea
that amber has a vegetable origin ("tree tears"). This
was eventually confirmed at the end of the eighteenth
century and in the nineteeth century by the research of
such scientists as Lomonosov, Bock, Struve and others.
Aristotle had already been on the right track in asserting
that amber was a resin since it contained fossilized plants
and insects which could only have penetrated the amber if
it had originally been in a liquid state. Similar views were
put forward during the Roman epoch by Pliny and Tacitus.
What was it that aroused the interest in amber displayed
by Aristotle, Plato and the great Roman scholars? The
answer lies in the Greek name for amber, "elektron", a
word which provides the root for the universal term,
common to all languages, "electricity". When rubbed with
a piece of woollen cloth, amber attracts nearby vegetable
bodies and it was this which linked elektron with physical
phenomena observed subsequently. The Greeks and, no
doubt even earlier, the peoples of the Near East and Egypt,
regarded amber as a magical stone because of its electro¬
static properties, its splendid colour and the fact that it
was light and pleasant to the touch.
From remotest antiquity, therefore, it was used as an
amulet, a talisman which ensured happiness, fecundity and
WLADYSLAW GRZEDZIELSKI is a Polish journalist and is secre¬
tary-general of the Polish National Commission for Unesco.
protection against illness. In powdered form it was employed
as a medicine; it was an ornament worn by kings and
warriors; it was the favourite adornment of women. The
main decorative element in the renowned crown of
Tutankhamen in the Cairo Museum is a piece of sun-colour¬
ed Baltic amber surrounded with diamonds, emeralds and
rubies.
Amber was of considerable value and the merchants of
ancient Phoenicia, made long voyages in search of it, thus
tracing out the first great amber routes.
Various varieties of amber exist in every continent but
the widest range is to be found in the Baltic Sea region
where, according to the Greek legend, the Eridanus flowed
into the sea. The amber of the Baltic coast is distinguished
by its superb colouring in various shades of yellowish-
brown, so that from earliest times it was known as
"Northern Gold" a name further justified by the fact that
it was worth its weight in gold.
Before the Ice Age, in the tertiary period from the Upper
Eocene to the Lower Oligocène between 45 and 34 million
years ago the regions now occupied by Scandinavia,
the Baltic Sea and the northern parts of the U.S.S.R.
Poland and Germany were covered with vast forests. These
"amber forests" consisted mostly of resinous trees and
especially pines (Pinus succinifer) which must have had
great powers of secretion since blocks of amber weighing
several kilogrammes are still found today.
The largest quantities of amber, whether brought up from
the sea bed, washed ashore by storms or extracted from
the earth, are to be found in the Sambia peninsula in the
eastern part of the Gulf of Gdansk, which was known to
the Romans and the Arabs.
The word amber was borrowed from the Arabs and the
Roman "ambar" is the origin of the name used in all the
Romance and Anglo-Saxon languages. In Germany it was
baptized "Bernstein", a derivative of "Brennenstein" the
burning stone. This, of course, was because of the inflam¬
mability of amber, the splendid flame with which it burns
and the perfume which it exudes.
I have already mentioned the sea route which was prob¬
ably the first followed by the Phoenicians in the search
for amber. It passed through the Mediterranean and led
along the Atlantic coasts to the Jutland peninsula which
was the base for trade with the Baltic region. Another great
European amber route ran from Massilia, now Marseilles,
which was an important trade centre, followed the Rhone
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
AMBER ROUTES (Cont'd)
The North Pole in a tomb of resin
22
and the Rhine and then proceeded overland to the shores
of the Baltic.
In the final volume of his Historia Naturalis, the Roman
historian Pliny gives an account of one of the Roman
expeditions to the Baltic Sea region which brought back
vast quantities of the precious substance, including blocks
of amber weighing as much as thirteen poundsl Among
other things, this amber was used to sand the arena of the
circus where the games were held in Nero's time.
The most important trade route followed by the Roman
and Arab amber-seekers passed through what is today
Poland, and numerous traces have been found in the course
of excavations which have uncovered coins and other
objects of Roman or Arab origin together with "amber
hoards" which were in fact the caches where the wholesale
merchants or their agents stored the amber while awaiting
the arrival of the buyers.
At that time there were no roads in Central Europe, and
dense forests, mud, snow and wild beasts made all travel
difficult. As a result, people relied primarily on waterways
and the navigable network between the Vistula, the Dniester
and the Dnieper, like a great fan linking the Baltic and the
Black Sea, was ideally suited to the purpose. This route
comprised four "spokes": the first began on the Gulf of
Danzig and followed the Vistula, the Bug, the Pripet, the
Dnieper and the Don, crossing the Kuban and the Tigris
to end up on the Persian Gulf whence the amber was sent
on to the markets of the Near East and especially those of
Persia.
The second possibility was to follow the Vistula, the
San and the Dniester to the Black Sea where the amber
found ready buyers among merchants from Egypt, Greece
and Southern Italy.
The third path was along the Vistula to the Warta and
then by minor rivers to the Odra, ending at a point on the
site of what is now Wroclaw which, to judge from the
many "amber hoards" since found there, must have been
one of the most important centres of the amber trade.
From Wroclaw, the amber was carried overland across
Moravia to Northern Italy. On this route lay the ancient
Roman colony, of Vindobona, an important trading centre,
which became the city of Vienna.
The most north-easterly route linked the Baltic Sea and
Byzantium and ran along the Neva and the Dnieper. Amber
was not the only product imported from North-East Europe,
which also supplied livestock, furs and feathers, the largest
importing centres being in the areas where Venice and
Trieste now stand.
HE Roman and Arab traders mainly bartered
amber for objects in iron and bronze, ornamental
weapons and fine cloth. From the sixth century onwards
they paid in gold coins as proved by the vast quantities
of coin from whole Mediterranean basin which have been
found during excavations along the "amber routes" des¬
cribed above.
The town of Kalisz in North East Poland boasts of a
2,000-year-old tradition: it arose on the site of the ancient
colony dating from the days of the Roman merchants'
expeditions, a colony known as Calisia which, like Wroclaw,
was undoubtedly one of the centres of the amber trade.
The great popularity of amber in ancient times came to an
end with the fall of the Roman Empire. The last mention of
amber from the period immediately following the break up
of the empire is to be found in a letter from Casslodorus,
Chancellor of Theodorlc the Great, conveying his thanks
to the Baltic Estes tribe for a gift of amber from the Sambia
peninsula. "We greet you", wrote Casslodorus, "and we
inform you that we have received with pleasure your gifts
of splendid amber. The sea bestows on you these stones
which gleam with so marvellous a light and yet your envoy
tells us you are utterly unaware of their origin even though
you were the first to receive this gift from the sea".
In the Middle Ages, as in modern times, amber was
primarily used as an ornament and a jewel. European
museums often contain superb carvings, decorated cups
or small boxes which are masterpieces of the jeweller's
art, since amber lends itself admirably to carving and
decoration, a fact of which artists have taken the utmost
advantage. Nevertheless, people continued to ascribe to it
magical and curative properties. When, for example, Prince
Albrecht sent his wishes for a speedy return to health to
Luther, in the 16th century, his message was accompanied
by a magnificent piece of amber.
N OT only the Arabs but, until the begining of the
twentieth century, almost all the peoples of
Europe used amber for making pipe-stems and cigarette-
holders. This may well have been the outcome of a tra¬
ditional belief which endowed it with what we would now
term bactericidal or disinfectant properties.
Amber served yet another purpose in the sumptuous
palace of Catherine of Russia at Tsarkoie Selo near Saint-
Petersburg (today Pushkino near Leningrad). One of the
rooms was entirely lined with amber and all the furniture
and objects which decorated this room were encrusted
with it. This unique masterpiece was destroyed during
the Second World War.
In the second half of the nineteeth century and the
beginning of the twentieth new uses were found for amber;
in particular it was found to be a valuable source of know¬
ledge concerning the plant and insect life of various
geological epochs. The resin of the "amber trees" not
only enclosed plants but also innumerable arthropods,
insects and even lizards. Such fossils helped scientists
to identify 190 species of plants and some 1,200 species
of arthropods and Insects.
The knowledge so acquired has aided research in other
fields; the fact that almost all types of "amber forests"
are similar to plant species In East Asia and North America
today led to significant discoveries concerning the climate
of that epoch and confirmed the theory that there had
been a shifting of the North Pole and changes in our
planet's climatic zones. Feathers found in pieces of amber
likewise provide ornithologists with valuable leads.
While out walking during a recent vacation near Danzig
I found a scrap of transparent honey-coloured amber In
the sand. Holding it up to the sun, I observed a host of
small dark spots Inside a microcosm of an epoch as
far distant from ours in time as the celestial bodies of
galaxies discovered in the twentieth century are from us In
space.
The wonder of amberl And the astonishing story behind
the routes which led to ¡tl They are routes which seem
made for communication and contact between men rather
than for war and pillaging. Amber fascinated scholars
and fair women, merchants and poets, and the route which
led to it has become one of the great arteries of civil¬
ization.
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
Undersea aquarium. Members of a French océanographie expedition
in the Red Sea return to their sea-bed base with collections
of fish held captive in plastic bags.
A new Mediterranean fishing problem
© Les Requins Associés, Paris
THE
TRANSMIGRATION
OF SHOALS
by Daniel Behrman
WO gigantic and involun¬
tary human experiments
are affecting the biological environ¬
ment of the eastern Mediterranean
Sea.
The first in point of time, for it is
nearly one hundred years old, was
the digging of the Suez Canal which
opened an artificial waterway for ma¬
rine life as well as shipping between
the Red Sea and the Mediterranean.
The second, much newer, is the sud¬
den cut-off of a flow of silt loaded
with nutritive substances into the east¬
ern Mediterranean following the con¬
struction of the new Aswan High Dam
which has already reduced and will
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
MEDITERRANEAN SHOALS (Cont'd)
Goat-fish losing ground to lizard fish
shortly arrest the seasonal floods of
the Nile.
Océanographie research into the
effects of these man-made changes in
the sea may become a subsidiary as¬
pect of a co-operative study of the
South Mediterranean and the Levant.
The study, to be focussed on the
Atlantic Current entering the Mediter¬
ranean at the Straits of Gibraltar, was
recommended by a recent Unesco-
sponsored inter-regional meeting of
scientific experts from thirteen coun¬
tries at Split, Yugoslavia.
The problem' of the Nile flood direct¬
ly involves sardine fisheries in the
Levant. Traditionally, fishermen all
along the eastern coast of the Mediter¬
ranean enjoy a bonanza every year as
sardines teem in the muddy waters
of the flood, first off the Nile delta in
September, and then as late as the
following spring off Lebanon.
These waters form a grey surface
layer which can be seen from the air
as far north as the coast of Lebanon.
Plant life flourishes on this sudden
dose of fertilizing nitrates and phos¬
phates which produce green blooms of
phytoplankton. Quickly, the next link
in the food chain of the sea, Zooplank¬
ton, appears to provide the minute ani¬
mal life upon which the sardines feed.
I
24
T is not only through this
massive transport of mine¬
rals that the Nile flood creates more
favourable conditions for marine life.
The eastern Mediterranean is highly
saline 39 parts per thousand, compar¬
ed to an average of 35 through the
oceans but this solution is consid¬
erably diluted by the autumn onrush
of the waters of the Nile. A drop in
salinity can favour certain groups of
marine organisms.
Now, the Nile flood will vanish. Al¬
though insignificant economically com¬
pared to the benefits of the Aswan
High Dam, the consequent loss to fish¬
eries will have to be studied in all its
side effects.
Research on this and other effects
of the damming of the Nile, the experts
felt, should start at once when the
process is only beginning. This will
provide a base point against which
future findings can be compared.
Dr. El Sayed Mohamed Hassan, di¬
rector of the Suez Branch of the In¬
stitute of Oceanography and Fisheries
of the United Arab Republic, said that
the UAR is already making surveys
to determine these effects and will
continue them until the dam is com¬
pleted.
Unfortunately, such surveys do not
exist in the case of the other man-made
change in the ecology of the Mediter¬
ranean, the opening of the Suez Canal.
Most of the year about eight
months the current in the Suez Canal
flows from the Red Sea to the Medi¬
terranean. With it come both fish and
forms af plankton, anything from one-
celled plant life to larvae of fish and
invertebrates, that must depend upon
currents for transport
Once they have passed through the
canal, a process of colonization begins.
Not all forms of marine life survive the
change by any means, but some appear
to thrive on it.
This has been the case of the goat-
fish, an Indo-Pacific species from the
Red Sea. Up until the late 1940s,
red mullet was the main catch of fisher¬
men along the Levant coast. Then,
in the 1950s, the goat-fish appeared
in commercial quantities and, accord¬
ing to Dr. Heinz Steinitz of the zoology
department of the Hebrew University
of Jerusalem, it has replaced the red
mullet as a major catch as far north
as the Turkish coast off Iskanderun.
But the goatfish is now losing ground
in turn to the lizard fish, another new¬
comer from the Red Sea. This is a
voracious animal that appears to eat
anything, even its own young, and it
is a fearsome competitor. While
fishermen's hauls do not diminish in
weight as a result, the lizard fish
fetches a lower market price than its
victims did in the past.
Dr. Steinitz did not foresee any eco¬
logical changes in the Mediterranean
as drastic, for example, as the result
of the introduction of the rabbit into
Australia, but he commented, "as soon
as you transplant an animal or a plant
into new surroundings, you can expect
anything."
\ T the Split meeting, Prof.
Jean-Marie Pérès, who
heads the Endoume Océanographie
Centre in Marseilles, remarked that the
first large-scale appearance of Red
Sea species occured in the Mediter¬
ranean between 1940 and 1945.
"But certain countries had other
things to do at the time", he said
wryly, "and this phenomenon could not
be properly observed. At present,
nothing enables us to say whether
the change will be good or bad."
One question immediately comes to
mind: why did the change occur so
long after the opening of the Suez
Canal?
It does seem certain that marine life
was moving across the isthmus of Suez
long before the 1940s. The first Red
Sea fish was found about eighty years
ago in the Mediterranean by a zoolo¬
gist on the Suez Canal staff.
But there were no reports of Red
Sea fish in the commercial quantities
now being found. The explanation
seems to lie in the Bitter Lakes through
which the canal runs. When the sea
receded in past geological times from
the isthmus of Suez, it left behind great
beds of salt and the Bitter Lakes.
These salt beds raised the salinity of
the Bitter Lakes to a point so high that
it prevented the passage of marine life
in any significant amounts when the
canal was opened. But then a gradual
process of flushing began and the
salinity of the Bitter Lakes dwindled
until it reached a level where it no
longer constituted an almost impene¬
trable barrier against the migration of
Red Sea organisms.
WHEN these Red Sea fish,
invertebrates and plants
compete with indigenous species for
survival ¡n the eastern Mediterranean,
they have several factors on their side.
The salt content at the northern end
of the Red Sea is 41 parts per thou¬
sand, while that of the southeastern
Mediterranean is only 39. Ability to
adapt to high salinity may help explain
why Red Sea life has been able to
pass more easily through the Bitter
Lakes than Mediterranean species.
But once these animals are in the less
salty Mediterranean, they find more
favourable conditions under which they
flourish.
At the same time, the Levant ¡s an
outer fringe for West Mediterranean
and Atlantic species penetrating the
Straits of Gibraltar. They are dwarf¬
ed here in comparison to their size
further westward and less fitted to
wage a struggle for survival.
At present, thirty species of Red Sea
fish are believed to have migrated into
the eastern Mediterranean. Scien¬
tists at the Split meeting did not view
this as any sudden increase or cause
for alarm.
But, they agreed, research must be
carried out now if the process is to
be followed closely from its inception,
with the movement of individual spe¬
cimens or larvae, to its culmination with
the appearance of an unfamiliar haul
in the nets of commercial fishermen.
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The curved lead plate
which this printer
is carrying to a rotaiy
press in Lagos (Nigeria)
will print two pages
of a local newspaper.
Today the leading newspapers
in tropical Africa
are printed in English
or in French.
Standardized alphabets
are now planned
for some of
the most important
African languages
spoken in vast areas, from
Senegal to the Cameroons.
They will then
be able to play a major role
in education and
the circulation
of news and information.
Literacy textbooks,
grammars, dictionaries
and reading materials
will be prepared
and published with
the co-operation of the
Unesco Regional
Centre in Accra.
O Paul Almasy, Paris
Ancient scripts
from the heart of Africa
by Dimitri A. Olderogge
I T would be difficult to overestimate the import¬
ance of writing in human history; writing made
it possible for each generation to pass on to posterity the
knowledge it had accumulated.
In his Ancient Society, the American ethnographer Lewis
H. Morgan made the appearance of writing the starting
point of civilization. Karl Marx agreed with Morgan on the
significance of writing in the history of society and Marx's
colleague, Frederick Engels, said in his book, The Origin of
the Family, Private Property and the State, that civilization
began with the invention of writing and its utilization for
literary purposes.
The hieroglyphic writing evolved by the Egyptians in the
fourth millenium B.C. served as the basis from which the
alphabets of the Mediterranean and India were later deve¬
loped. The hieroglyphic writing of the peoples of the Far
EastChina, Korea and Japan appears to have developed
independently of the Mediterranean cultures. The same
DIMITRI OLDEROGGE is a leading Soviet specialist on African
questions. He is a corresponding member of the U.S.S.R. Academy
of Sciences.
may be said of the writing of the American people, the
Mayas in particular.
One of the most ancient systems of writing, the hierogly¬
phic script of Ancient Egypt was created in Africa (in the
Nile Valley), but it did not influence the development of
writing among other peoples of the African continent; the
one exception was the writing of the ancient Nubian kingdom
of Meroe (600 B.C. to 400 A.D.) which was obviously the
result of Egyptian influence.
Because of this it is usually assumed that the peoples
of the Sudan and tropical Africa never developed scripts
of their own; it is true that the Vai tribe in Liberia invented
a script in the early nineteenth century, and so did the
Bamum, of the Cameroons in the twentieth century, but
these were considered exceptions. It was also affirmed as
an indisputable fact that both scripts were invented under
the influence of either European or Arabic scripts. But Is
this true? Is it conceivable that the African peoples, with
their original self-created culture, never advanced to the
stage of Inventing some system of writing?
When Portuguese navigators first reached the west coast
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
ANCIENT SCRIPTS FROM AFRICA (Cont'd)
"Nlo tre' = to carve symbols on a calabash
26
of Africa, there were states in existence along the whole
length of the Upper Guinea coastline. The accounts of
European travellers mainly Portuguese, Dutch, and English,
but also German and French give descriptions of them.
In the sixteenth and seventeenth centuries trade was so
highly developed along the seaboard later known as the
Gold Coast, that Portuguese ships carried slaves from
Benin for sale to African merchants, instead of carrying
them to Europe. The African merchants used the slaves as
porters to take goods into the interior and bring back
gold and ivory.
The first European caravels were met by large fleets
of vessels sent out by local rulers, some of them capable of
carrying a hundred men. This fact alone shows that the
Portuguese navigators found the western seaboard of Africa
inhabited by peoples who had reached a high level of
culture. Any doubts there may be on this score are dispelled
immediately one calls to mind the ancient bronze reliefs
and sculptures in the round produced by the artists of the
Benin and Yoruba peoples.
These bronze castings have been preserved. They
include portraits of a king and his heir, an army commander
and many other high-ranking persons all indicative of
an elaborate court ceremonial. Each officer or courtier
wears some mark of rank headdresses, shoulder sashes,
masks worn hanging from the belt, which are the equivalent
of modern badges and insignia, and special types of
swords called ada or ebere.
Some reliefs show a nobleman of high rank setting out
on a journey accompanied by a numerous suite. The noble¬
man is mounted on a horse with young men supporting him
on either side; armour-bearers carry his sword and shield
and his servants hold their shields high above their heads
to protect him from the sun. The nobleman is taller than
the servants around him; the artist has done his best
to stress social inequality in the same way as those who
carved the reliefs of ancient Egypt.
It is easy to picture Benin from the descriptions of tra¬
vellers of that time. Houses in the town were built close
to each other in straight rows as in Dutch towns. The
king's palace, wrote a seventeenth century traveller, was
as big as the town of Haarlem. The streets were wide and
straight, as wide as the Herengracht or the Keyzersgracht
in Amsterdam; side streets almost as wide led away to left
and right.
WE know this from scraps of evidence that have
chanced to survive, and fortunately there are
enough to show the high level of culture in ancient Benin.
We now know that the Benin culture was only one branch of
the ancient and highly developed culture of Yoruba. Since
little of the Yoruba culture has been preserved we might
have regarded the tales and legends of the Yoruba about
their past as pure invention had it not been for the bronze
and terracotta sculptures real gems of African plastic
art that have been discovered recently. We have little
information on the states that lay to the west of Yoruba
only the tales of travellers and merchants who visited the
Gulf of Guinea between the sixteenth and nineteenth cen¬
turies. But these are sufficient to show that all along the
Guinea Coast there were states with developed cultures
and that to the west, north and east there were peoples
with considerable lower levels of culture.
All this gives us much to ponder on. One wonders
why, In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, peoples like
the Vai, Ekowi, Bamum and Toma who lived on the peri¬
phery of the West African states should have had their
own systems of writing, whereas nothing has been found to
suggest that any system of writing ever existed in the
coastal kingdoms. Why did the Vai script appear among
a people at a lower level of culture than that of Yoruba or
Dahomey? How did the Nsibidi inscriptions come to be
made by tribes living in the dense jungles around the Cross
River in the Cameroons?
One would naturally expect the peoples of Dahomey,
Yoruba and Benin, and other similar kingdoms to have
had their own systems of writing at some time. This seems
more than likely since the state must have needed records
of tributes received and taxes due, and reports on the state
of the army; it also had to issue orders and instructions.
Yet the question has never been investigated.
MONG the scripts of the Guinea Coast those of
the Vai and Bamun are the best known. The
Vai script was discovered in 1849 by S.W. Kölle who came
away with the impression that all adult men in Bandakoro
could, to some extent, read and write, and that in other
villages there were always a few people who could read
the native script. The American Africanist, Oric Bates,
noted in 1834 (thus even earlier than Kólle) "the Vai have
written volumes."
The rapid spread of writing shows that the appropriate
conditions for its invention must have existed long before.
Syllabic systems of writing derive from pictographic sym¬
bols, and the "invention" of the Vai script by Momolu Doalu
Bukele and some helpers consisted of selecting suitable
symbols and arranging them according to a precisely
defined system. Momolu Massakwa, the Liberian consul
in Britain, has told how the Vai transmitted news of a
sudden attack by their enemies, of the outcome of battles
and other events, by means of pictograms on strips of
bark. To say that the enemy had been defeated and had
fled they drew the figure of a man running with his hands
on his head and put a dot beside it to indicate the plural.
It was symbols of this kind that were used as a basis for
the syllabic alphabet.
The history of the Vai script is quite clear the symbols
gradually acquired a phonetic character and represented
the sounds of the syllables. Professor August Klingenhe¬
ben, an eminent linguist, discovered that the Vai script
depicts very exactly the phonetic structure of the language
(there are symbols which differentiate between syllables
containing two types of B and two of D, symbols for nasa¬
lized vowels and for labio-velar sounds). He concluded
that it could only have been invented by native speakers of
the language.
Influenced by the Vai writing, neighbouring tribes rapidly
assimilated its principles and invented their own systems.
We now know that similar systems of writing exist among
the Mende, Bassa, Gerze (Kpelle) and Toma (Loma).
The history of the Bamum script is now well known.
Njoya, the chief of the Bamum, evolved this system from
symbols that had been In use before him and which had
long been known in the savannahs of the Cameroons. In
his lifetime, Njoya four times reformed the Bamum script to
give it a more systematic form.
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Both the Vai and Bamum scripts, therefore, were created
by turning ancient systems of symbols into a standardized
system. The older symbols have not been preserved
because they were inscribed on perishable materials wood
and bark which did not survive long In the damp tropical
climate of West Africa.
The Nsibidi symbols, widely used among the Ibo people
(a tribe four million strong) in southern Nigeria, only became
known in Europe in 1904. The Nsibidi symbols are not
a real system of writing because one symbol may be used
for several different meanings and the same idea can be
expressed by several different symbols. The number of
symbols was unlimited and the way of drawing them was
not systematized.
The Leningrad Museum of Anthropology and Ethnography
(U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences) possesses a number of
calabashes from the Cameroons, many of which are covered
with Nsibidi symbols based on pictograms. These inscrip¬
tions are usually "records" of proverbs, "the sayings of
the old men". It Is no accident that In the Ewe language,
for Instance, the verb nlo means "to carve" (drawings)
and also "to write"; nlo tre means "to carve drawings on
a calabash" and nlo leta means "to write a letter" (from
the word "letter").
It seems that records of this type must have existed
throughout the Guinea Coast but they were never studied
and have now disappeared since they were written on
perishable materials like wood and calabashes.
The systems of recording numbers are better known.
Trade in gold has been conducted on the Gold Coast and
the Ivory Coast for centuries and gold dust was sent by
caravan routes to the trading centres of Western Sudan
Djenne, Bamako, Mopli, Timbuktu, and other towns. The
gold trade continued from the twelfth century until 1591
when the Songhai kingdom was crushed by Moroccan
troops. Weights were needed to weigh the gold dust, and
some made of bronze have been preserved. They are
covered with different symbols circles, spirals, volutes,
incisions, etc. Studies of these inscriptions show that they
are conventional signs for weights.
HERE is no doubt that the payment of tribute
had to be recorded, and that some system of
writing was needed apart from figures. Unfortunately
nobody has taken up this problem, but I believe that
something like a system of writing must have existed in
Upper Guinea for a long time. I base my theory on the
following facts.
Among the regalia of the kings of Dahomey was a cere¬
monial axe with a decorated biade. Ceremonial axes of this
kind could be "read", since each of them had its own
particular significance. King Takdonu or Dakodonu (1625-
1650) had an axe of very strange design. According to
A. Le Hérissé, a French scholar who studied the history of
Dahomey, the blade of the axe could be read in this way:
above there was a symbol depicting flint da, below a
depiction of the earth ko, with a hole In it donu; together
these make the name Dakodonu.
Le Herissé's Dahomey friends presented him with an axe
depicting his name. On the blade there was a local tree
hun with its leaves ama bound by a rope kan and with
spaces between the leaves biyo; this was read as nma-
kambiyo a word meaning "it doesn't matter, It is not neces¬
sary". This was also the name given to Le Hérissé by his
Dahomey friends because he repeated the word so often.
These examples show that the people of Dahomey long
ago developed the principles of hieroglyphic writing and
it has not been preserved simply because the materials
they used were not long lasting.
We also find less developed systems of writing on the
walls of Dahomey's palaces; they strongly resemble the
hieroglyphs of ancient Egypt, for instance those at Nar-
mer and other cities, where the early form of the cartouche
contained both pictograms and hieroglyphs. The Egyptian
Pharaoh was drawn as a hawk with a hoe in his talons des¬
troying city walls, or as a bull trampling a man underfoot
or tearing down a wall with his horns.
Of similar character are the reliefs on the Dahomey
palace walls that show the kings of Dahomey as ele¬
phants or mighty birds tearing their enemies to pieces.
In both ancient Egypt and in Dahomey we find the earliest
stages of the development of a system of writing.
From "L'Ecriture des Bamum". IFAN 1950
"King Njoya teaches the first characters
of his writing to the nobles"
says the inscription in Bamum
at the top of this drawing.
Njoya, King of the Bamum (Cameroons) Invented
a pictographic script
at the end of the 19th century,
and later transformed it into
a syllabic and phonetic alphabet
(see the Unesco Courier, Nov. 1950).
There is an anachronism in the drawing.
At the time their alphabet
was devised, the Bamum had not yet
adopted the Islamic dress
in which the artist, Ibrahim Njoya,
has depicted them.
The arrival of Portuguese merchants on the Guinea Coast
and the systematic hunt for slaves that followed interrupted
the independent development of the peoples of that area
and doomed them to suffer all the horrors of the slave
trade which prevented any further development of their
native culture.
Traces of earlier systems of writing are also to be found
among peoples Inhabiting the southern part of the conti¬
nent. An Italian missionary, Gazazzi da Monecuccolo, said
in his Historical Description of the Three Kingdoms of
Congo, Matamba and Angola (Bologna, 1687) that hiero¬
glyphic writing was widely used in Matamba.
The Portuguese historian Barroch tells of an Inscription
in an unknown language which he saw over the doorway at
the entrance to one of the stone buildings in the land of
Monomotapa. However, this statement Is not universally
accepted; some scholars believe he may possibly have seen
a carved ornament such as was frequently used to decorate
the walls of stone buildings.
It is difficult today to say whether a system of writing
actually existed in the sixteenth century on the territory now
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
í
m
Unesco-P.A. Pittet
ANCIENT SCRIPTS FROM AFRICA (Cont'd)
Scripts of the Tuaregs, Swahili and Nubians
28
known as Rhodesia. In the National Museum at Bulawayo
there is a manuscript report written by Blake Thomson, one
of the explorers of this area. This quotes a statement by
one of the local inhabitants, a man named Lino, who
declared that the Nyungwe people who lived on the banks
of the Zambesi once possessed manuscripts written on
skins. They were kept in the temple of Murenga and were
copied from time to time as the leather perished. The
copyists tried to imitate the symbols exactly although they
did not know their meaning. It ¡s a pity that Blake Thom¬
son's report and the copies of the symbols preserved in
the same museum have not been published
A hieroglyphic inscription discovered on the cliffs at
Cholemba near Tete (Mozambique) on the middle reaches
of the Zambesi was published in 1896. This inscription did
not seem to attract much attention, although to this day it
remains the only evidence of the existence of an ancient
system of writing in South Africa. It can scarcely be a
hoax since it was discovered at the end of the last century
when nobody was interested in the history of the African
peoples. However, it would be a mistake to draw any defin¬
ite conclusions until further discoveries have been made.
We may sure that many of the peoples of the Guinea
Coast, people who were free of all outside influences until
the fifteenth century, had the rudiments of systems of
writing and even developed systems.
The peoples of the Sudan and East Africa came under
the influence of Arab culture and Islam and created their
own scripts on the basis of Arabic. Just as adaptations of
the Arabic alphabet were made to suit the needs of the
Turkish and Persian languages, so systems of writing in
Arabic characters were devised by many African peoples.
Among the languages so written we may mention Swahili
with its rich literature and those of the Western Sudan
Hausa, Fulbe, Kanuri, Manding and others. Nor must we
forget the writing of Ethiopia whose original script was
devised early in the Christian era from the South Arabian
Sabaean script.
In Christian Nubia, the ancient Nubian system of writing
was devised in the tenth century under the Influence of the
Coptic script. Nobody even suspected the existence of
this Nubian script until 1906, when among Arabic and Coptic
manuscripts received by the Berlin Museum from Egypt
some in an unknown script were discovered. Studies
showed that they were written in the ancient Nubian lang¬
uage which makes them the oldest written records of
African languages proper.
Today, as in past centuries, the Tuaregs of the Sahara
use a special script known as tifinag which is a development
of the ancient Libyan and Punic scripts used in North Africa
at the time of Carthage, in the second century B.C.
Now that most of the African peoples have freed them¬
selves from colonial dependence, the problem of scripts
for the African languages has become more urgent. All
the newly-Independent states have naturally chosen as
their primary task the achievement of economic indepen¬
dence. This requires them to develop their own industry as
rapidly as possible, to build factories, construct ports with
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
languages
to grind
The people of Dahomey developed a form of hieroglyphic writing over three
centuries ago. They used it to give specific meanings to the designs of the
ceremonial axes known as "recades". Above, a decorated axe blade bearing
the emblem of King G I ele. which signifies "I am the lion cub which spreads
terror from the moment ¡t has teeth." Left, a Dahomean father explains
to his children the meaning of one of the reliefs sculpted a century ago on the
palace of one of Dahomey's monarch's, King Ghezo of Abomey. These alle¬
gorical figures, which recount the king's exploits, are actually a rudimentary
form of writing. Right, an ancient Dahomean calendar. Three calendars are
combined on this board into which marks have been burned and holes bored.
At the top, from left to right, are seven rows of circles: large ones represent the
days of the week; small ones indicate the propitious and the unfavourable
"moments" of the day and night. A local calendar (top right) is based on the
days for holding markets. The twelve rows of 30 holes each which cover most
of the board compose a yearly calendar based on lunar periods. Holes marked
with a sign announce tornadoes or rain. Dots tell when to plough and sow.
Photos O Musée de l'Homme, Pans
modern equipment, create highway and railway networks,
and to solve town-planning problems, all of which requires
skilled personnel engineers, technicians and an army of
proficient workers. Such skilled personnel can only be
trained if the people are literate.
There is no doubt that English and French, and perhaps
some other European languages, will remain the basic lan¬
guages for secondary and higher education in many count¬
ries of tropical Africa; primary education, however, must be
given in the local languages. Among the young people of
the African countries there is a great desire to learn; all
sections of the population are eager for knowledge.
I have seen how Africans are trying to devise alphabets
for their peoples. Different people have different ideas
about how the problem is to be solved; some propose to
devise symbols like the Vai or Bamum of which we have
already spoken, and to make up an alphabet from them;
others suggest using the Arabic alphabet as a base; the
third group, and its members form the majority, want to
take the Latin alphabet and adapt it to the phonetic system
of their own languages. In this field, too, there are many
difficulties.
The most widespread and best-established systems of
writing now in existence are those of the Swahili and
Hausa languages based on the Latin alphabet. The two
scripts are similar since they make use of the English
pronunciation of Latin letters and their combinations,
although there are some slight differences. Swahili, for
instance, uses the English combinations CH and SH while
Hausa uses C instead of CH, but uses SH like Swahili. The
vowels are not given their English value but follow "contin¬
ental pronunciation," as the British say.
In the former French colonies, where teaching in the
local languages in state schools was forbidden, the work of
creating scripts has to begin from scratch. A number of
African languages have spread from countries where the
official language is English to countries where it is French.
The Hausa language, for instance, is spoken in "English"
Nigeria, in Niger, Dahomey, Tchad, etc., where the French
language has been accepted. The question then arises
should the traditional English system of spelling be retained,
or should the French system be used, for instance, CH
instead of the English SH. Vowels create an even more
difficult problem.
In short, a number of specific problems exist. If they are
solved within the boundaries of a single state, many people
will remain divided the Fulbe, Hausa, Mosi and many
others are kept apart by the political boundaries of English-
speaking and French-speaking states. Unsolved problems
will have to be dealt with at special conferences attended
by linguists and representatives of the African governments.
For this purpose a number of conferences have been held
in recent years in the biggest university towns of West
Africa in Ibadan and Accra at which the problems were
discussed.
The most recent conference on linguistics was held
at Bamako under the. auspices of Unesco. It dealt with
the alphabets used for the chief languages of the Western
Sudan Hausa, Manding, Kanuri Fulani, Tamasheq and
Songhai. The aim of the conference was to bring concord
into the writing of these languages through the production
of a standardized alphabet.
In this short article we cannot deal with all the problems
that affect the African languages. The problems are many,
but we have to make the first advances by establishing
standard systems of writing for the most important lang¬
uages of the African continent.
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
MURASAKI SHIKIBU
The world's oldest novel, The Tale of
Genji, a Japanese work of the tenth century
was written by a woman, Murasaki Shiklbu.
Her exact date of birth is unknown, but she
is thought to have died about 1016. Lady
Murasaki, as she is sometimes called, was
the widow of a dignitary at the Imperial
Court of Japan. She was a woman of great
culture, like so many nobly-born women of
the Heian Period, which was marked by an
unprecedented flowering of art and litera¬
ture in Japan. In the tenth century a new
and simplified form of writing called Kana was
invented in Japan. Women in particular
adopted it in preference to the old-style Chi¬
nese characters. Kana made a vigorous Im¬
pact on Japanese literature; stories, narratives,
diaries and novels began to appear. Women
were revealed as outstanding novelists and
poets. The Tale of Genji was to make Lady
Murasaki the most famous of them all. Her
work is a long, 1,000-page novel which, while
recounting the amorous adventures of Prince
Genji, describes the exquisite refinement and
psychological complexity of Japanese court
life at that time. Murasaki Shikibu was a
perceptive and sensitive observer of life who
might well be said to have "invented" the
psychological novel six centuries before it
made its appearance In the West. Its In¬
fluence on Japanese literature was consider¬
able not only on the novel, but equally so
on Noh drama and the Kabukl theatre. This
classic of Japanese literature Is now part
of the universal cultural heritage. The most
famous translation into English is that by
Arthur Whaley, first published In the 1930s,
and ¡t is this version that has been accepted
in the Unesco Collection of Representative
Works, for which it has now been reprinted
by George Allen and Unwln, London.
FRANZ HALS
The name Frans Hals is one of the most
renowned in Dutch painting. Hals (someti¬
mes called "Hals the Elder"five of his
sons became reputed artists) was born In
1580. The dating of his first authentic work,
a portrait, as 1613 shows that he made a
late start on his career, and it is often said
that he had hitherto led a dissolute and
Improvident life. Nevertheless he quickly
made up for. lost time and established his
reputation with the now famous "Banquet
of the Archers of Saint George", painted
in 1616. This splendid group, In which the
influence of Rubens is clearly apparent, reveal¬
ed Hals as master of portraiture and of
colour harmonies. Hals continued to paint
the large portrait groups that were now in
fashion and replacing allegorical and religious
paintings in homes and public buildings. Most
of his later works were individual portraits
painted in sombre tones dominated by black,
grey and silvery shadows. Hals was gifted
with deep psychological insight. His por¬
traits reveal a searching analysis of character
whether the model Is a great man such as
Descartes or a simple gypsy girl, whether
a fisherman or a carefree youth. Hals died
In 1660 three years before Rembrandt.
Throughout his long career he continued to
develop his painting techniques, using ever
larger, bolder and more rapid brush strokes,
and overriding the confines of the sketches
on his canvas. Not without justification Is
he now called a precursor of Impressionism.
GREAT
GREAT
MIGUEL DE CERVANTES
The name of Miguel de Cervantes In¬
separable from that of his hero Don
Quixote is one that dominates world
literature. The life of Cervantes resembles
a picaresque novel. The son of a poor
surgeon, he was born in Alcalá de Henares
in 1547. From his earliest years he
displayed a passion for books. At 17 he
enlisted as a mercenary in the service
of the Colonna (an important Roman
family), a life which took him across all
of Italy. He lost the use of his left hand
at the battle of Lepanto in 1571. The
galley bearing him back to Spain was
seized by the Turks. He was sent to
Algiers as a prisoner where he suffered
hard privations and was finally ransomed.
Cervantes was in Madrid in 1580 trying
to live by his pen. He wrote plays, led
a poverty-stricken existence in Seville and
then in Grenada. On two occasions he
so badly managed his affairs that he was
put in prison. In 1604 he published the first
part of Don Quixote which was an instant
success. However, it was ten years before
Cervantes decided to finish his Quixote,
by now being read in all parts of the world.
The first part was translated into English
by 1612 and into French two years later.
Today translations of Don Quixote have
been made in almost every written
language including Chinese, Korean,
Tibetan, Japanese, Sanskrit, Arabic,
Hebrew, and all the languages of Europe.
In 1959, no fewer than 2,047 editions of
the work existed all over the world
in 53 languages (including Dog Latin).
A source of inspiration for other literatures,
Cervantes's masterpiece has been studied
for its bearing on politics, religion, science,
criminology, botany, medicine, in short,
in every one of its thousand aspects, both
comic and tragic. Sancho Panza in no
less celebrated than his master. The
donkey and the mare have entered the
world's lore of famous animals. Ever since
30
Romain Rolland's life (1866-1944) spanned
a period of social and political unrest, and
his works reflect the clashing forces of a
changing world: the nineteenth century
demands for justice and liberty, the twen¬
tieth century's search for communication
and human understanding. Rolland's path
led him from Tolstoy (with whom he kept
up a regular correspondence) to Gandhi,
to whom he dedicated a major work in
1923. For twenty years between 1920
and 1940 he strove to conciliate Occi¬
dental and Oriental thought, to reconcile
the rejection of tyranny and the doctrine
of non-violence. The theme of all his
writing is faith in man and in what he
ROMAIN ROLLAND
called the "grandeur of the world", and
nowhere does this resound more clearly
than In his vast correspondence. His out¬
put of works plays, essays, novels, pol¬
emical writings was one of the most
prolific of his day; all reflect an unswerving
belief in the unity of mankind. When he
was awarded the Novel Prize for Literature
just fifty years ago, Romain Rolland was
certainly the best known French writer in
Europe. His romantic cycle, Jean Christo¬
phe (the story of a German musician), was
immediately translated Into several lan
guages, and earned for him an International
reputation. His Au-dessus de la mêlée
(Above the Battle), written In the midst
of World War I, reflected his militant paci¬
fism and added to his prestige as an
idealist. Rolland, who was later to write
the lives of Ramakrishna
« and Vivenkananda, had
I already become a "guru",
I as a spiritual teacher is
called in India, in the eyes
I of the Western world. A
ttri| great lover of music and
_ art, Rolland wrote with
k N^ I intense feeling on Beetho-
Ä ven and Michelangelo.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
its appearance, Don Quixote has inspired
great writers. Samuel Butler's Hudibras,
Marivaux's Pharsamond, Wieland's Don
Silvio de Rosalia all are manifestations
of "Quixotism". Much of the philosophical
and spiritual writings of Miguel de Una-
muno are directly influenced by Cervantes
and Quixotism. The Melancholy Knight
also left a strong mark on music and the
other arts, from the seventeenth to the
twentieth centuries. Don Qu/xoie has
unspired a host of operatic composers,
from Purcell (1694) to Massenet (1910);
Richard Strauss used it as the theme for
one of his most beautiful symphonic
poems, as did Manuel de Falla in his
"Master Peter's Puppet Show". Painters,
sculptures and illustrators throughout the
world have added their interpretations
William Hogarth, Gustave Doré, Salvador
Dali to name only three. Don Quixote
has appeared as an American fiilm (1916)
and a Soviet film (1957). In 1935, the
celebrated Russian base, Chaliapin, sang
the role of Don Quixote in a film made
by the German producer, G.W. Pabst a
cinema opera with music by the French
composer, Jacques Ibert. Miguel de Cer¬
vantes died 300 years ago on April 23,
1616 on the same day as William
Shakespeare.
ISAAC NEWTON
Just three centuries ago, Isaac Newton,
a young scholar of Trinity College, Cambridge,
pondered a question that was to lead him
to one of the most important discoveries in
the history of natural science. Was the force
which caused objects to fall merely a ter-
restial phenomenon or was it one manifesta¬
tion of a great Universal Law ruling all motion
throughout space? It took Newton a number
of years to prove that there was indeed a
universal force, and to work out his full
statements on the laws of gravitation, which
he eventually published ¡n 1687. Newton first
tested his theory by calculating the orbit of
the moon, but when his results failed to
agree precisely with the moon's observed
course he laid aside his research until more
accurate figures were obtained for the dis¬
tance between the moon and the earth. With
these figures his calculation of the action of
gravitation on the moon corresponded exactly
with the moon's course; similar calculations
applied to other heavenly bodies completed
the chain of evidence.
Newton's discovery of the law of gravi¬
tation has tended to overshadow his many
other achievements. His contributions to the
theory of light were of almost equal import¬
ance. Through his experiments he was able
to break up white light into the colours of
the spectrum and to recomblne colours Into
white light. His studies on light also led
him to invent the reflecting telescope. His
discoveries in mathematics Included a new
method of calculus (or, as he called It,
"fluxions"). His contributions to science
include many of the fundamental laws of the
physical world upon which modern physics
and mechanics have been developed. Yet
this outstanding physicist and philosopher had
the modesty of true genius. "If I have
seen farther", he once wrote, "it is by stand¬
ing on the shoulders of giants." And on an¬
other occasion he declared: "I seem to have
been only a boy playing on the seashore
and diverting myself in now and then finding
a smoother pebble or a prettier shell than
ordinary, whilst the great Ocean of Truth
lay undiscovered before me."
GOTTFRIED LEIBNITZ
Mathematician, theologian, historian, dip¬
lomat the German philosopher, Gottfried
Wilhelm Leibnitz (1646-1716) was a man
of almost universal interests and attain¬
ments. At fifteen, already a practised scho¬
lar in Greek and Latin, he turned eagerly to
the works of modern thinkers Bacon,
Kepler, Galileo and Descartes. At twenty-
Five his theses on philosophy and law had
been accepted, he had studied chemistry,
higher mathematics and mechanics and
had written several works on theology and
politics two of his lifelong interests.
Leibnitz the mathematician invented diffe¬
rential calculus in 1676. As a theologian
he sought ways to bridge the schisms of
the Christian churches, and on this problem
he corresponded for many years with the
French prelate, Bossuet. As a diplomat
he sent to Louis XIV a memorandum on
French relations with Turkey, and drew
up for Peter the Great a plan for the
Westernization of Russia. As a historian
he founded the scientific method of histo¬
rical criticism. However, it was as a philo¬
sopher that he achieved his greatest fame.
In 1684 he rejected Cartesianism and ela¬
borated a new theory of knowledge in his
New Essays Concerning Human Under¬
standing. His Monadology (1714) was a
complete exposition of his philosophy the
doctrine of the supremacy of intelligence in
man and good in the world. Voltaire was
later to satirize this doctrine in Candide and
to ridicule its optimism with the famous
phrase, "everything is for the best in the
best of all possible worlds".
But optimism has always been a basis
of scientific thought and makes Leibnitz
more up to date than ever.
RUBEN DARIO
The works of Ruben Dario occupy as
honoured a place in modern poetry as they
do in the history of Spanish-language lite¬
rature. Yet despite their wealth of vigour
and elegance, they remain too little known
outside Spanish-speaking countries. Such
is their reputation within those countries
that it is often said there are two periods
in Spanish-American poetry "before Da¬
rio" and "after Dario."
Ruben Dario was born in Nicaragua in
1867. He lived in Chile, in Argentina and
In Paris, and travelled widely In Europe
as a diplomat and journalist. With his
knowledge of languages and his profound
culture, he recognized the importance of
the new literary movements in the Europe
of the late nineteenth and early twentieth
centuries. Among French poets like Bau¬
delaire, Mallarmé and Verlaine he redis¬
covered an economy of expression (of
which he was already a past master), and
their experiments inspired him to breathe
new life into Spanish-American poetry,
which had still not freed itself from a
rather grandiloquent romanticism. He be¬
came the leader of a movement, quickly
labied modernísimo, which gave new
accents to the great Spanish classic tra¬
dition represented by Cervantes, Lope de
Vega and Quevedo. The appearance of
each of his works Prosas profanas (Pro¬
fane prose) in 1896; Cantos de Vida y Espe¬
ranza (Songs of Life and Hope) in 1905;
El Canto Errante (The Wandering Song)
in 1907 and Poema de Otoño (Autumnal
Poem) in. 1910 was hailed as a major
event in Spanish-speaking countries. To¬
day, fifty years after his death, the repu¬
tation of the great Nicaraguan poet
continues to grow.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
BOOKSHELF
ARCHAEOLOGISTS AT WORK
The Desert Kingdoms of Coastal
Peru.
By Victor W. von Hagen.
Well documented and readable
description of the remarkable
Mochica-Chimu civilization (see
article page 10). Nearly 160 illustra¬
tions and drawings.
George Weidenfeld and Nicholson
Ltd., London. 1964 (63/-); New York
Graphic Society Publishers Ltd.,
Greenwich, Connecticut, U.S.A., 1965
($10.00).
Archaeology & the Microscope.
By Leo Biek, with a forward by
Sir Mortimer Wheeler.
The man in the trench and the
scientist at his bench working
together.
Lutterworth Press, London, 1963
(45/-).
Science in Archaeology:
Comprehensive survey of progress
and research.
Edited by Don Brothwell and
Eric Higgs.
595 pages. Basic Books, New York,
1963 ($17.50).
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Social Research and Rural Life
in Central America, Mexico and
the Caribbean Region.
(Technology and Society series),
1966 (18/-; $3.50).
Business Management.
By Roger Grégoire.
(The University Teaching of
Sciences series), 1966; (12/6;
Social
$2.50).
of
32
A Survey of the Teaching
Physics at Universities.
(The Teaching of Basic Sciences)
1966 (23/-; $4.50).
Asia in the Making of Europe.
Volume I: The Century of Dis¬
covery.
By Donald F. Lach.
The first in a series of volumes which
will trace, century by century, the
role of Asia in the development of
Europe.
Published in two books by the Uni¬
versity of Chicago Press, Chicago
and London, 1965 (144/-; $20.00).
World Understanding: A Selected
Bibliography.
Compiled and edited by Alice
H. Flynn.
Published for the United Nations
Association of the U.S.A. by Oceana
Publications Inc., Dobbs Ferry,
New York, 1965.
No Easy Walk to Freedom.
Articles, speeches and trial addres¬
ses by Nelson Mandela.
A first-hand report of the struggle
against Apartheid.
Basic Books, New York, 1965 ($4.95).
British Secondary Education:
Overview and Appraisal.
Twenty-three British educators tell
the story of their secondary schools.
Oxford University Press, London,
1965 (30/-).
From the Unesco New
Television lessons
for Africa
New adult education techniques are
being devised and tested in Senegal,
where a series of experimental television
programmes which could influence mass
education and literacy teaching throughout
Africa are being produced by a team
composed of 18 Senegalese, a New Zea-
lander and a Frenchman. This six-year
pilot project is financed by Senegal and
Unesco, and Canada is providing some
$63,000 in bilateral aid.
'Lost city' discovered
in Peruvian jungle
Ruins of a "lost city" dating from the
time of the Incas have been discovered
by the American explorer Gene Savoy,
near Pataz (Peru) in a jungle on the eastern
slopes of the Andes. Scattered over some
12 square miles, the city has well-built
roads, stairways and terraced temples
decorated with gargoyle heads and other
signs of a once flourishing civilization.
According to the explorer the city could
have been built by a tribe called the Cha¬
chapoyas who took refuge in the jungle
after their defeat by the Incas in the
15th century. Certain archaeologists believe
that this new find may be even more
important than the discovery of the famous
ruins of Machu Picchu in 1911.
Harvesting rain
in the desert
Technicians at the U.S. Water Conser¬
vation Laboratory believe they have found
how to harvest much of the rain that falls
in desert storms by spraying a water-
repellent silicone compound on the sand.
This holds the rainfall above ground where
it can be gravity-drained into reservoirs.
Yield from a half-inch rainfall on a "sili-
coned" plot of desert land proved to be
93%. The problem which still remains is
how to make the silicone crust permanent.
Confusing names
in medical terminology
Present confusion in medical terminology
can cause potentially dangerous misunder¬
standing. Some diseases have ten or
more names, even in the same language,
and at least one. myelofibrosis (a bone
marrow disorder) is known by at least 30.
PUZZLE PHOTOS IDENTIFIED
All photographs on pages 8 and 9 except one show equipment used in nuclear
research at CERN.
1. NOT A JET PLANE WHEEL This highly-polshed circular metal cap tops
an electrical condenser charged to 300,000 volts, and reduces the amount of
electricity discharged into the air.
2. NOT EQUIPMENT FOR AN ATOMIC SCIENTIST The spidery wheels of
a sophisticated garden rake. They would be of no use to a physicist, but gardeners
on large estates find them a big help in collecting leaves and grass cuttings.
3. NOT A TROMBONE OR A LASER A deflector of nuclear particles in a
giant accelerator. A pulse of electricity causes a beam of particles projected by
the accelerator to be diverted on to a target of atomic nuclei for an infinitesimal
second (200 microseconds).
4. NOT AN ARMY TANK Construction of a "bubble chamber", a device for
observing the behaviour of nuclear particles. No microscope Is powerful enough
to view nuclear particles. Scientists have therefore devised various methods of
"seeing" the tiny world within the atom. One of these is the bubble chamber
containing a liquid (often liquid hydrogen), which is suddenly decompressed and
made to "boil". Particles leave a trail of bubbles when projected into the chamber.
This bubble chamber is one of the two largest In the world. Last year
1,600,000 photographs of particle interactions were taken during six experiments
with bubble chambers at CERN.
5. NOT A HULA HOOP Physicist checks the starting point of a giant particle
accelerator. The rings he is inspecting are the source of electrically charged
atoms (called ions) which supply the infinitely tiny projectiles that are used to
bombard the nucleus of the atom.
6. NOT AN OUTSIZE GAS RANGE BURNER These objects are components
of an electromagnet used for testing conductive properties of different materials.
Twelve of these "pancakes", as they are called from the flat, spirally wound centre
section, are used in the electromagnet. The twelve arms are water circuits
for cooling.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
An international group of specialists
convened by the Council for International
Organizations of Medical Sciences (found¬
ed in 1949 under Unesco and WHO
auspices) has now suggested how this
chaotic situation could be cleared up. It
proposes the setting up of an international
clearing house for medical terminology and
lexicography which would study problems
of medical language, prune from it un¬
necessary words and adopt internation¬
ally acceptable terms and definitions.
Monument you can
listen to
An unusual type of monument is to be
built in Geneva to commemorate the cen¬
tenary of the International Telecommunica¬
tion Union. It will consist of two concrete
discs, 36 ft in diameter lined with titanium
screens, and a footbridge passing between
them. Persons crossing the bridge will
find themselves in an acoustic zone with
unexpected qualities. All sounds in this
area will set up prolonged reverberations
as they are reflected back and forth bet¬
ween the discs time and again. The Soviet
design was chosen by an international jury
which considered 21 1 entries presented in
the design competition for the centenary
monument. The jury also awarded prizes
to entries submitted by teams from Switz¬
erland, Poland and Yugoslavia.
World survey
of deep sea tides
A plan to turn the oceans into a labo¬
ratory for the study of deep sea tides and
their effect on such global phenomena as
the deforming of the earth by lunar and
solar attraction has been endorsed by the
54-nation Intergovernmental Océanographie
Commission. The idea was proposed by
the International Association of Physical
Geography. The survey would begin
with tidal observations at about 300 points
on the ocean floor, and the whole ope¬
ration would last from five to ten years.
Flashes...
San José, capital of Costa Rica, has
named one of its avenues "Avenida de la
Unesco".
The University of Papua, at Port Mores¬
by, South East New Guinea, will receive
its first students next year.
Jets of water under very high pressure
are being used in the mines of the Donbass
In the U.S.S.R. to cut anthracite, an extre¬
mely hard type of coal.
A museum dedicated to Paul Gauguin
(1848-1903) has been opened near Papeete
in Tahiti, where the painter spent the last
eight years of his life.
The Red Cross is setting up a centre
for study, research and training In Geneva.
It will be called the Henry Dunant Institute
after the founder of the Red Cross.
Over 8,000 newspapers in 44 languages
were published in India in 1964, reports
the India Press Registrar. Of 514 dailies
registered, the largest language group was
Hindi with 149 papers, followed by Urdu,
68 and English, 56.
WORLD PANORAMA
OF HIGHER EDUCATION
Did you know that:
Asia has the highest number of stu¬
dents in higher education in the world?
Europe has the largest number of
institutions of higher education in rela¬
tion to population?
North America is not expanding in
higher education as fast as other conti¬
nents, but has more students enrolled
than several of the other continents
combined?
Africa has had the highest percen¬
tage increase in higher education enrol¬
ment during the last decade?
These striking facts are revealed in
a new Unesco publication, Volume IV
of the World Survey of Education, which
gives a global picture of higher educa¬
tion based on reports and statistics
from 200 countries (1).
This monumental 1,433-page refe¬
rence work offers a country by country
survey with detailed facts and figures
and an analysis of the evolution and
present status of higher education toge¬
ther with its trends and problems. It
takes a broad, purposeful look at gen¬
eral trends ¡n higher education, analyz¬
ing Its progress since 1930, its changing
pattern, its intellectual and human as¬
pects and its plans and perspectives.
The speed of change in higher educ¬
ation, it reports, is higher than at any
other level of education. Taking a
sample of 39 countries it shows that
between 1930 and 1960, student enrol¬
ment rose from about 2.6 million to
9.2 million (an annual increase of 10%).
Some of the individual country in¬
creases during this period were specta¬
cular: Iraq, 212%; Thailand, 157%;
Puerto Rico, 39 %; United Arab Repub¬
lic 34 %; India 31 %; Argentina 22 %;
and Yugoslavia 18%. And the survey
makes it clear that we are in the early
stages of a process of growth that has
still far to go.
Other important developments report¬
ed by the world-wide survey show that:
Higher education enrolment in the
U.S.S.R. roughly trebled between 1930
and 1950 and then doubled by 1960.
India's university enrolment increased
by 250% between 1950 and 1960. and
under the new five-year plan is expected
to reach one million; in the Phillip-
pines one third of a million students are
now enrolled.
The proportion of science and tech¬
nology students increases yearly: while
(Í) World Survey of Education,
Vol. IV, Unesco; $33.00; £8.50; J 15 F.
world university enrolment rose by 50 %
between 1950 and 1960, enrolment in
colleges of technology outside the uni¬
versities increased by 200 %.
Today's "explosion of knowledge"
makes it difficult for scientists to keep
abreast of developments even in their
own specialities: the physical' and bio¬
logical sciences alone publish 70,000
scholarly journals annually.
Progress in specialization paradoxi¬
cally makes the specialist even more
dependent on matters that seem far
removed from his own field. For
instance a crystallographer is now asked
to apply his expertise to chemical, biolo¬
gical and historical problems.
By 1962 the proportion of post gra¬
duate students in science and technology
had risen to 20 % of the whole in United
Kingdom universities; in Soviet univer¬
sities and institutes of technology as
much as 10% of undergraduate students
do part-time research on projects being
carried out by their teachers.
Italy admitted women to its univer¬
sities as students and teachers as
early as the 13th century, but it was not
until the 19th century that universities
began to open their doors to women on
an appreciable scale. In most countries
today the proportion of women students
varies from one-third to one quarter.
Three-quarters of Soviet doctors and
30 % of engineers are women, and half
of all Soviet "executives and specialists"
are women.
The American college and university
has always welcomed the presence of
students from foreign countries. In
1961-62 roughly 57,000 students from
other countries were enrolled in insti¬
tutions of higher education in the United
States, and approximately 20,000 foreign
students received degrees from Ameri¬
can universities during this academic
year.
In France, 80,000 students out of a
total of 215,000 are concentrated ¡n the
University of Paris.
Sweden estimates that the demand
for civil engineers for industry alone
will rise from 89,000 in 1960 to
183,000 in 1970.
Volume IV of Unesco's World Survey of
Education completes a cycle of global
education surveys which began in 1955.
Earlier volumes were: Volume I, National
Educational Systems; Volume II, Pri¬
mary Education, and Volume III, Second¬
ary Education.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
34
TO VANQUISH HUNGER
Sir.
I have just begun to earn my living
and I would like to give Unesco part
of my first salary to help in the fight
against hunger now being waged in
the developing countries. I find each
issue of the Courier passionately in¬
teresting, particularly the articles on
social questions and on science and
the arts.
Hélène Levai
Paris, France
Fifteen Unesco Gift Coupon projects
offer readers a wide choice of ways in
which to help the world-wide FAO
Freedom from Hunger Campaign.
Details of projects and Gift Coupons
to the value of whatever sum readers
wish to donate can be obtained from:
Council for Education in World Citi¬
zenship, 25 Charles St., London W.I,
U.K.; Unesco Gift Coupon Office,
Room 2201, U.N. Building, New York
17. N.Y., U.S.A.; U.N.A. Committee
for Unesco, 329 Bloor St. West, To¬
ronto 5, Canada Editor.
THOSE MAGNIFICENT MEN
IN THEIR FLYING MACHINES
Sir,
The gallant epic of the men who
pioneered aviation is known to every¬
one. Don't you think that many
readers would be delighted to find
articles on the birth and the dynamic
progress of aviation in your magazine?
And what about the future of aeronau¬
tics? Surely this is a subject that
would interest every reader.
Christian Delannes
Brussels, Belgium
DEATH ON THE ROADS
Sir,
In your December 1965, issue, ap¬
pears an item which might be wrongly
interpreted. Under the title "Death on
the Roads", you quote the U.S. sta¬
tistic, 40,000 deaths in 1962, in a way
which would seem to indicate that
the U.S. death rate from highway ac¬
cidents has sharply increased in re¬
cent years.
The annual U.S. highway death toll
has remained more or less stationary
at about 40,000 until very recently
despite increasing population, increas¬
ing numbers of vehicles, and sharply
higher mileage travelled. I understand
that the experience of France in the
first nine months of 1965 has attained
the same level, proportionate to its
population, although the French vehicle
and mileage statistics are lower. Un¬
fortunately, I understand that the U.S.
figure has begun to climb again.
However, the sense of the para¬
graph, that the accident rate is climb¬
ing sharply in many countries, is cer¬
tainly true. This reflects growing af¬
fluence in Europe as well as the be¬
ginnings of road transport and in
creasing numbers of private vehicles
in the developing countries.
With the growth of experience and
discipline among the hordes of new
drivers, the construction of their
highways to safer standards, the acci¬
dent rate on a mileage basis will very
likely decline. However, the tragic
figure, the total number of deaths, will
undoubtedly continue to climb.
Drastic solutions a reduction in the
power and size of private automo¬
biles, long overdue in the U.S.; prohi¬
bition of automobiles within the hearts
of our cities; new transportation sys¬
tems allowing a reduction in mileage
and vehicles will ameliorate the prob¬
lem and bring it eventually within
tolerable limits.
Stanley I. Hart
Paris, France
MASTERPIECE FROM DAHOMEY
Sir,
When I received the December
issue (Arts of Africa, Oceania and
America) I was absolutely stunned
by the double-page photograph of
the Dahomey statue. I know
the Paris Musée de l'Homme
rather well, but I have never before
seen this particular statue, which is no
miracle at all as the museum is so
richly endowed that people should
spend months and even years to
discover all its treasures. I am full of
enthusiasm about the work of art itself
and the impeccable reproduction.
Rosemarie Kirschbaum
Basel, Switzerland
A PLACE BY ANY OTHER NAME
Sir,
Unesco's headquarters in Paris ¡9
situated in the Place de Fontenoy. I
learn from my encyclopedia that Fon¬
tenoy is "a Belgian commune, city
ward of Tournai. Scene of the battle
on March 11, 1745, in which the
French army of Marshal Saxe,
watched by King Louis XV, vanquished
the forces of England and Austria..."
That Unesco's address should evoke
a battle ¡n my view is inconsistent
with the basic task of the organization
to work for international harmony.
Would not the name of a great figure
a Nobel Peace Prize winner such as
Dr. Schweitzer, for example be just
as satisfying to our national pride and
surely a far more appropriate way of
identifying the "Unesco Place"?
Henri Boularrand
Carnoux-en-Provence
France
ART PLUNDER DOWN THE AGES
Sir,
Recalling your issue on Art Thieves
(November 1965), it may be worthwhile
to mention that already from the be¬
ginning of history kings and warlords
have taken away works of art by
force.
Prof. E. A. Speiser (who died re¬
cently) relates in Mesopotamia Evo¬
lution of an Integrated Civilization:
"The Elamite ruler Shutruk-
Nahunte invades Babylonia some time
before the middle of the 12th century
and despoils its major centres of such
priceless treasures as Naram-Sin's
Stele of Victory, and Hammurabi's
famous law code stele, among many
others. All were to be eventually
recaptured ¡n Susa by the far-reaching
arm of archaeology." They are now
in the Louvre. (Cited from The World
History of the Jewish People, Volume
I. "At the Dawn of Civilization";
Jewish History Publications Ltd W.H.
Allen. London 1964).
At the end of World War II in Paris
the Nazis tried to rob the most famous
paintings of French Art and to trans¬
fer them to Germany, as has been
presented in the extraordinary film
"The Train". And these are only
two examples of many.
Dr. Albert Baer
Kiryat Bialik
Israel
The article "Thief-Proofing our Art
Museums" did not deal in any way
with the problem of art plunder
through the ages which is a totally
different subject Editor.
CULTURES WITHIN CULTURES
Sir.
A reader from Barcelona (Feb.
1965) suggested that more attention
be paid to the cultures of the smal¬
ler national groups, especially those
which are minorities within a larger na¬
tion. May I support this plea by adding
that many of the smaller linguistic and
ethnic groups have cultures which are
both interesting and lively, but that
they often find it hard to maintain
their identity even where native ex¬
pression enjoys perfect freedom. Your
correspondent mentioned the Basque,
Catalan and Galician cultures of Spain
which exist in addition to the better
known Castilian.
The United Kingdom has several
languages apart from English. These
are Welsh, Scots Gaelic, Manx and
the French patois of Channel Islands.
Both the Isle of Man and the Chan¬
nel Islands have. their own ancient
parliaments. Wales has founded an
International eisteddford a competi¬
tive festival of folk song and dance,
and this colourful festival attracts
groups from many countries. The
eisteddfod is a Welsh literary and mu¬
sical institution which has its origins
in the Middle Ages, and the interna¬
tional eisteddfod is its modern exten¬
sion, open to the whole world. I feel
certain that many readers would wel¬
come accounts of activities of this
kind, and that the Courier is the ap¬
propriate vehicle for them.
G. Illtyd Lewis
Swansea, Wales
u
z
<
z
o
O
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
JUST PUBLISHED
This volume gives a global picture of higher education with
facts and figures from 200 countries. It is the fourth In
Unesco's World Survey of Education. Earlier volumes dealt
with National Educational Systems (1955), Primary Education
(1958) and Secondary Education (1961).
Introductory chapters
present a world survey of
education from 1957 to
1961, a general picture of
school-age and school-
going populations in ten
countries and a review
of progress in higher
education since 1930.
t\. Higher education
Global Picture
of Higher
Education
This monumental reference work also contains chapters
on the changing pattern, the intellectual arid human aspects
and the plans and perspectives of higher education by
Professor Basil Fletcher of the University of Leeds (United
Kingdom) which make a fascinating study in themselves.
For some of the striking facts given in this volume, see page 33.
1,433 pages
$33.00; £8.50 (stg.); 115 F
$38.00; £9.10.0 (stg.); 130 F (cloth bound)
A Look at Research
on Racial Problems
A new Unesco volume takes a far-ranging look
at research on racial relations, spanning Africa from
north to south, Europe, South-East Asia, North and
South America and Oceania.
Presents articles
by distinguished an¬
thropologists and
sociologists which
originally appeared
in Unesco's In¬
ternational Social
Science Journal (Vol.
XIII, 1961, N° 2)
and In its pre¬
decessor, the In¬
ternational Social
Science Bulletin
(Vol. X, 1958), plus
a specially-com
missioned study of
the Pacific area and
a 16-page biblio¬
graphy on race
relations.
research on
racial relations
unesco
265 pages
$5.00; 25/-stg. 17.50 F
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
ere for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER In any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzai, Prest Department, Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 1 09 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C, Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. All publications : Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-
Boek-handel, Belgièlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
112, rue du Troné, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road. Rangoon.
(	). CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
(S 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir
Chittampalan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B, 244, Colombo,
2. (Rs. 1 3/50). -CHINA. World Book CoLtd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1,Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. "MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3 rd Avenue, P.O.
Box 1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L..
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici lite¬
ratura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar Munks-
gaard, Prags Boulevard 47, Copenhagen S (D. Kr.M7).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120,
Addis Ababa (10/-). FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirja-
kauppa. 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie da I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7". C.C.P.
12598-48. (10 F.). GERMANY. All publications:
R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich.
8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only) Bahren-
felder-Chaussee 160. Hamburg-Bahrenfeld. C.C.P.
276650 (DM 10). GHANA Methodist Book Depot
td. Atlantis House Commercial St., POB 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens. HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64,
Nathan Road. Kowloon. HUNGARY. Kultura,
P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
lonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
(120 Kr.) INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol
Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 1; Kanson
House, 1/24 Asaf AM Road, P.O. Box 386, New
Delhi, 1 ; Sub-Depot : Oxford Book & Stationery
Co., 1 7 Park Street, Calcutta 1 6, Scindii
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco. Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs.7). IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop. Bagh¬
dad. IRELAND. The National Press. 2, Wellington
Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. 4. (1 5/5). ISRAEL Emanuel
Brown, formerly Blumstein's Bookstores 35, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8) .
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street,
Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.. 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O.Box 60 5 Tokyo Central. Tokyo
(1,200yen). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahousft Co., Darul-
Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi (10/-). KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64. Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops
Ltd.. P.O. Box 286. Monrovia (10/-). LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(F.L. 1 40). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd., Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3 rd
floor), 110, Jalan Pudu, Kuala Lumpur (M. $ 7.50).
MALTA. Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta,
(15/-). Nalanda Company Ltd., 30,
Bourbon Street, Port-Louis (1 5/-). MONACO. British
Library 30, Bid des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 10).
NETHERLANDS. N. V. Martinus Niihoff, Lange
Voorhout, 9. The Hague, (fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS
WEST INDIES. G. C. T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.)
N.V, Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. (NA fl 4,50). NEW
ZEALAND. Government Printing Office 20, Molesworth
Street (Private Bag) Wellingston, C. 1 Government Books
hops: Auckland (P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box
1721), Dunedin P.O. Box 1104) (15/-). NIGERIA.
C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O. Box 174. Lagos (10/-).
NORWAY. All publications : A.S. Bokhjornet, Lille
Grensen 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier also: A.S- Nar-
vesens Litteratur Tjeneste, Box 61 25. Oslo 6,
(17.50 kr.). PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Pu¬
blishing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box
374 56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILI¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23. Warsaw 10
(zl. 60). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal. Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA. The Book
Centre, and Educational Supply Co., Colonial Mutual
Building, Salisbury. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P.O. Box 1118, Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publi¬
cations : A/B C.E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 16. For the Unesco
Courier: Svenska Unescorädet. Vasagatan 1 5-1 7, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 211, Geneva 11, C.C.P. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue de¡ Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). TANZANIA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). Librairie Hachette. 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala (1 0/-). REPUBLIC OF
SOUTH AFRICA. All publications : Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O. Box 724 Pre¬
toria. For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only: Cen¬
tral News Agency P.O. Box 1033, Johannesbourg. (R1.-
50). UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librai¬
rie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent:
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 St. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 3 4th St, New York,
N.Y. 1001 6 ($ 5.00) U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Knlga,
Mocow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Kn-
jTg, Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
i
i lllll
1
m
!
GIANT
ACHINES PROB
THIN THE ATO
The laboratories of the European Orga¬
nization for Nuclear Research in Geneva
are a huge international centre for
intific studies where hundreds of
ientists probe the secrets of the
tructure of matter. Here, physic-
sts prepare to study atomic par¬
ies in an apparatus kno
s a "spark chamber"
(See page 5
Unesco-Paul Almasy, Paris
]]>
</page>
</document>
