<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078332eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
/
10*
rs
MAGIC ART
OF CZECH
GLASS
**
MARCH
1960
(/3th year)
Price : l/-stg. (U.K.)
30 cents (U. S.) !
0.70 NF. (France)
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
«Ei Unesco
NEW UNESCO ART SLIDES. As part of its campaign to bring the little known master-pieces of world art to the general
public, Unesco is now issuing collections of moderately priced colour slides. Here (in black and white) taken from the set
devoted to the Ajanta cave paintings in India is a celestial nymph with cymbalsa 5th century painting. (See story page 23.)
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Coiïri er
MARCH 1960
13TH YEAR
Contents
No. 3
COVER PHOTO
Whether shaped in the finest
crystal of Bohemia or In the
Innumerable forms It has
been given for use In scien¬
ce and Industry, Czech glass¬
ware has won world-wide
fame. Here, a shining bubble
of melted glass Is carried
from the furnace by Czech
glassmaker. See page 14.
Jan Lukas
Page
4 THE SOUND HUNTERS
A new international family,
By Jean Thévenot
6 A BABY CHICK IS BORN
1 1 NO SCHOOLS FOR ONE CHILD IN TWO
By Leo Fernig
14 THE MAGIC ART OF CZECH GLASS
By Indrich Santar
22 I WEEP, THEREFORE I AM
The purpuse of tears, yawns & laughter
By Ritchie Calder
23 'MUSEUMS' IN PLASTIC BOXES
Unesco Colour Slides bring art into the home
26 'MARK TWAIN' OF YIDDISH LITERATURE
The life and works of Sholem Aleichem,
By Joseph Leftwich
31 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
33 WORLD'S BIGGEST FARMING CENSUS BEGINS
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
Published monthly by
The United Nations Educational, Scientific and Cultural
Organization
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*, France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Alexandre Leventis
Spanish Edition : Jorge Carrera Andrade
Russian Edition : Veniamin Matchavariani
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly (12 issues a year) in English,
French, Spanish and Russian. In the United States of America it is distri¬
buted by the UNESCO Publications Center. U.S.A. 801 Third Avenue, New
York 22, N.Y., Plaza 1-3860. Second-class mail privileges authorized at New
York, N.Y. (M.C. 60.1.145 A).
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
Annual subscription rates: S 3.00; IO/-stg. ; 7.00 New
Francs or equivalent. Single copies I /-stg. 30 cents
(U.S.); 0.70 New Francs.
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
A New International Family:
THE SOUND HUNTERS
ÏT-
r
«^p*?*^
V»*«^
M
by Jean Thévenot
Honorary President, International Federation of Sound Hunters
TAPE-RECORDERS are nowadays becoming almost as common as cameras,
and recordings of children's voices made by their parents now provide a version
in sound of the "family album" with its record of events down the years.
Photo Unesco
OUND hunter... chasseur de son...
tonjäger. This new expression so
new that it would have drawn a blank look not so long
ago has now entered English, French, German and quite
a few other languages to describe a new species, the ama¬
teur sound recorder. Armed with a tape recorder instead
of a camera, he is the equivalent of the amateur photo¬
grapher in the World of sound. And yet, paradoxically,
sound recording by amateurs is as old as the phonograph.
At first, there were nothing but amateurs.
As early as 1878, the year when he had the first talking
machine constructed by his assistant, John Kruesi, Tho¬
mas Edison, foresaw a "'10-point programme" for the
phonograph. This is the way he jotted it down:
1. Letters and dictation of all sorts without a steno¬
grapher.
2. Talking books for the blind.
3. Teaching by oral methods.
4. Musical reproduction.
5. Family albums (various events and the last words
of dying persons).
6. Musical snuff-boxes and toys.
7. "Talking clocks" indicating in a clear voice the right
time to go home, to prepare meals, etc.
8. The preservation of correct accents in various
languages.
9. Educational uses.
10. Permanent recording of telephone conversations.
In short, Edison's fertile imagination had predicted
every possible use of his "talking-machine" except its
most important one. At that time, of course, not even
as prophetic a genius as Edison could imagine the mass
production of records and tapes (though envisaged by
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
Charles Cros in 1877) or the use of recordings in radio
and television broadcasting. The first phonograph
recorded sound on a cylinder covered with tinfoil or silver
paper (later, [with wax) and it was both a recorder and a
record-player. This was do-it-yourself sound recording at
home.
In 1880, Chancellor Bismarck recorded the student song
"Gaudeamus Igitur". In 1889, at the Paris Académie des
Beaux-Arts, composer Charles Gounod recorded a French
children's song, "'Il pleut, bergère..."
That same year, the builder of the Eiffel Tower, Gus¬
tave Eiffel, received a "new model" phonograph from
Edison as a gift. For many years it was to remain the
favourite parlour game of the great French engineer.
Every time he had friends in his home, he asked them to
speak a few words to be engraved on its wax cylinder for
posterity. As a result of this pastime, it is now possible
for modern Frenchmen to hear kiddies who later became
leading political figures talk of how they rolled then-
hoops in the Tuileries Gardens one day in 1891 or the
warning of learned members of
parliament in 1898 that a catas¬
trophe would result from the use
of balloons in the impending
Spanish-American War.
In 1896, a French pioneer of
sound recording, Horace Hurm,
decided to learn how to play the
oboe "phonographically" that is,
by recording himself and then
listening to the results on his
machine. By listening, he reason¬
ed, he would be able to correct
himself. At any rate, he won
first prize in 1901 at the National
Conservatory of Music in Paris...
for playing the oboe. He then
had the idea of teaching music
by sonic correspondence courses
in which recordings could be
used both for pupils' "home¬
work" and their teacher's cor¬
rections.
At the turn of the century, the
Pathé Brothers created the
"Pathêpost," an apparatus using
small disks instead of cylinders
and enabling its owner to record
and to "read" at home "phono¬
graphic letters." This created
a sensation: anyone could carry
on a correspondence without
bothering to learn to read and
write provided that he was
neither deaf nor dumb.
The ranks of these private
disk jockeys swelled considerably
until the day the mass-produced
disks appeared. That changed
everything. The old wax-cylin¬
der models (or the "Pathéposts")
were relegated to gathering no¬
thing more than dust in attics.
Professional sound recording took shape. Amateur
recording was eclipsed. Before it could reappear again,
a huge amount of ingenious and varied work had to be
done. The strangest part about this work Was that it
only began to achieve decisive results when it went back
to the old pioneer methods which had been abandoned.
Around 1930, the so-called "'flexible" record, which
permitted direct recording, was developed. Once again,
as in the days of the first cylinders, an individual
record could be engraved and heard immediately
afterward. The result was excellent, but this new process
was rather tricky to handle. In addition to near-pro¬
fessional skill, it required a minimum amount of technical
knowledge. "'Home recorders" were not very numerous.
Thomson-Houston
TRANSISTORS have helped to give sound hunters
complete freedom of movement. With battery-powered
tape-recorders run on transistors and therefore both
small and light, the amateur sound recorder no longer
has to keep his instrument within plugging-in distance
of mains electricity. He can record anywhere and at any
time. Above, a phase in the manufacture of germanium
crystal, the principal element in transistor production.
Amateur sound recording was really reborn only with
the appearance on the .market of magnetic recording,
first using wire, then tape, and this was relatively recent.
Yet a period slightly longer than a decade has seen
progress which cannot even be compared to what had
been achieved during seventy preceding years. Today,
private sound recording is taken for granted. While it
may be more widespread in some countries than in others,
the tape recorder can be seen everywhere and tends to be
as commonplace a sight as the camera. Nor is this progress
showing any signs of waning. Portable tape recorders
now run on transistors. This means that they are small
and light and it also means that the sound hunter has
been freed of his worst enemy, the restricting wire which
forced him to limit his prowling to the immediate vicinity
of electric points. Now he can record anything anywhere.
Stereophonic sound recording by amateurs has begun.
Soon, images on tape will begin to make their
appearance in the home.
Not all users of tape recorders are "amateurs". After
all, the man who relies upon a
dictating machine in his office
has not necessarily taken an in¬
terest in the art and technique of
sound reproduction any more
than the man who uses a type¬
writer or a mechanical pencil
sharpener shows a bent for litera¬
ture. Nor are all amateur re¬
corders "'sound hunters" in the
strict sense of the word that is,
they don't spend their time
roaming the landscape, tape rec¬
orders under their arms, like
the professional cameramen of
the newsreels or documentary
films. But, compared to profes¬
sional sound men, they deserve
the name of amateurs because
they don't have to go to the same
place every day to spend eight
hours manoeuvring microphones
and magnetic tapes. These
amateurs are under no obliga¬
tion. They make recordings only
in their leisure time for their
own pleasure and whenever they
feel like it or whenever an oppor¬
tunity comes up. If they are
really bitten by the bug, then
they patiently await the right
opportunity, just like the man
who hunts rabbits, tigers... or
butterflies. It is a state of mind
which makes them "sound hun¬
ters," even if they never take
their mikes outside their front
doors.
Exactly what do they do?
What does the amateur sound
hunter try to achieve? What
results has he obtained? What
can be expected of him (or her)
in the future?
These questions may seem simple, but their answeis are
quite complex. The answers vary from one country to
another, and also from one social group to anothei, for
there are sound hunters in all walks of life.
Let us take the case of France which I believe is typical.
Assuming that amateurs surveyed represent French sound
hunters as a group, we can say that nearly all of them
go through the same evolution, determined by three
distinct factors.
Aside from the fact that the laws governing passing
fads apply to tape recorders as well as to anything else,
the age of the sound hunter is of considerable importance.
For example, I have seen countless youngsters under
twenty become enthusiastic about recording. They team
CONT'D ON PAGE 8
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
LISTENING IN TO THE
BIRTH OF A BABY CHICK
A remarkable recording made by an amateur sound
hunter has captured on tape the birth process o'f a
baby chick both before and during the actual
hatching. It has been made by a Frenchman,
Joseph-Maurice Bourot, a scientist on the staff of
the National Centre for Scientific Research, in
Poitiers. First the heart of the still-unborn chick Is
heard beating inside the egg. The chick is still too
weak to do more than crack the shell. Soon it can
be heard breathing and, finally, it succeeds in
pecking its way out. With the tape-recorder tuned
up to full volume, the breaking open of the shell
sounds like a tremendous explosion. Photos
on these pagesa perfect pictorial version of
this unusual sound recordwere taken by R.H.
Noailles and appear in a children's book, "Un
oiseau est né " (A Bird is Born) published by
Atelier du Père Castor (Flammarion.) Paris".
» it- I
Top, a look inside the egg on 16th
and 18th day after incubation. Left,
on 21st day the chick has used its
tiny beak to break a series of hole
in the shell until, little by little,
one end of the egg is almost
ready to break away. Then, with all
the strength it can muster, the chick
puts its head against the broken end
and forces its way out into the world.
Photos © R.H. Noailles
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. Morch 1960
SljlStS ï2«ï3* «.?"-"
THE EGG IS OPEN AND THE CHICK FIGHTS ITS WAY OUT. THEN, COMPLETELY EXHAUSTED, IT FLOPS DOWN BESIDE THE SHELL.
AFTER 1 5 MINUTES THE CHICK" HAS RECOVERED SUFFICIENTLY TO BE ABLE TO RAISE ITS HEAD AND SURVEY THE WORLD.
WITHIN AN HOUR THE YELLOW BALL OF FLUFF WITH BRIGHT BEADY EYES IS UPRIGHT AND NOW QUITE FIRM ON ITS FEET.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
SOUND HUNTERS (Cont'd from page 5)
The three stages of the amateur
1° Baby's gurglings
2° A spree of Bach & choirs
3° Ambushing the unknown
up to buy equipment which they could not have afforded
alone... then they drop everything when they get married
and return to sound hunting only a few years later. On
the contrary, the person who takes up recording at a later
'age has less early enthusiasm but is usually less fickle.
In this respect, surveys are rather comforting. They
show that, in several countries and over the past few
years, the average age of the sound hunter is 35.
In addition, the state of technical progress at the time
the sound hunter starts his career is also important. It's
quite obvious that the delicate recording equipment of
twenty-five years ago or the temperamental wire recorder
of fifteen years ago was less tempting than today's simple,
easy-to-handle tape recorder with its high fidelity.
Finally, no matter what the influence of these first two
factors may have been, the use to which the amateur puts
his recorder follows a nearly constant curve down through
the years, aside from the specific case of correspondence
by sound (especiaUy International correspondence).
The first stage is the family album: baby's gurglings
and first words, the dog's barking, Mary's prize-winning
recitation, Jack's wedding. Since these recordings revive
common memories, members of the family listen to them
over and over again with delight and hilarity, to the
despair of nine out of ten of their friends who see in them
nothing but hopeless platitudes.
The second (and most dangerous) stage: now the ama¬
teur can handle his recorder, he knows how to balance
P. Guérin, St.-Savine, France
World Tape Pals. Inc., Dallas
Seven years ago a U.S. printer set up World Tape Pals for the
exchange of tape recordings between peoples. It now links
tape fans the world over. Here, Steve Veenker, director of the
junior section, "Teen Pals", displays some of his equipment.
Sound hunting ¡s a hobby into which young people plunge
with all the enthusiasm of their age. Above, youngsters in a
French village school question some of their classmates on
topical subjects and record the interview on a tape recorder.
sounds, he can create effects, he can edit tape. He feels
he is becoming a professional. He goes on a recording
spree of choirs, guitar players, and great organ music,
particularly Bach. He writes, acts and puts sound
effects Into theatrical, literary or musical works. He
dabbles in re-recording and concrete music. Then, he
suddenly realizes that he is not a professional after all
and that, unless he is an exceptional case, he does not
have the same equipment. It becomes clear to him that
this imitation of the professional can bring him nothing
but disappointments and that it is a blind alley for him.
Unless he decides to become a professional himself... in
which case, of course, he is no longer an amateur.
Third stage. Having learned through experience that
his true path leads in directions which professionals never
take because they cannot, the amateur begins to explore
his own territory: candid recordings, documentaries,
sound experiments. If you have to get up at three o'clock
in the morning to a certain nightingale, if you
have to lie in ambush two hours awaiting the joyous
homecoming of the neighbourhood souse, if you have to
wait a year for a "beautiful" thunderstorm, or if you
have to devote three or four years to research on an
unexplored problem, then only the amateur has a chance.
He's got time, he's in no hurry, he need not report to any
employer, his recordings do not have to be sold, he is a
free man.
O Sole Mio on a bicycle pump
FORTUNATELY, a large number of amateurs have al¬
ready reached this third stage, and we owe a lot to
them.
In the first place, many have shown a gift for the rare
or the picturesque in the choice of their subjects. This
takes imagination and a knack for being in the right place
at the right time.
Here, at random, are a few recordings which belong to
this category:
"Tiger Rag" played by a Swiss peasant band; a Nor¬
mandy blackbird whistling a French song; grackles, or
mandarin blackbirds, from Tonkin, speaking French with
a Nice accent; 1,200 trombone players all at once at a
trombone players' congress in Basle; the sound that a
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
Swiss lake makes when it freezes; a wedding party at the
Paris Ecole des Beaux Arts to the accompaniment of the
art students' band; the religious festivals of gypsies (as
joyous as a country fair); the old French song "Cadet
Rousselle" sung in flawless French by children at a
Moscow School; Molière's "L'Avare" (The Miser), played
in colourful French by the students of the Minneapolis
High School;
The constantly-astounding speeches recited by guides
at historical monuments; descriptions of the first flight
across the English Channel spoken by Madame Blériot,
the pilot's widow, and pioneer airmen; the tale of Eric de
Bisshop's shipwrecks by one of his companions; prison
guards' recollections of celebrated inmates; an argument
with a traffic policeman as he writes a summons; children
talking about artificial satellites; the initiation ceremonies
in French wine-drinking brotherhoods; the impressions of
a novice after his first flight in a glider; a wedding pro¬
posal (in cowboy style) sent by disk to the future bride's
father; all the different ways of saying "yes" recorded in
a church or at a city hall during marriages;
A profession of faith by a hermit bishop who had
re-established the Celtic rites of the 1st Century in a
forest in Britanny; all the interviews of centenarians
recorded during the "Tape Recorder Rally" organized in
France in 1958; "stolen phrases" and other hoaxes (in
which the amateur usually admits things to his victims
afterwards); counting-songs recorded by schoolteachers;
all kinds of strange or precious musical instruments
discovered in cellars, attics of obscure museums; a little
three-year-old Spanish girl bellowing a song in the midst
of a raving crowd in front of a Basque jai-lai court; a
joyous cooper singing the praises of wine and accom¬
panying himself by banging his wine barrels with a
mallet; "O sole mio" played on a bicycle pump; the music-
loving nightingales of Kent, recorded by a gardener who
is both a poet and a master sound recorder, and judged
"the recording of the year" in Great Britain in 1959.
To this varied list, too long and yet too short, should
be added a few recordings of unknown music discovered
by sound hunters with a penchant for cultural detective
work, and those countless recordings of folk music which
either capture traditions on the way out or else revive
them.
It might also toe noted that many of today's stage, fllm
Photos P. Guénn, St-Savine, France
Tape-recorders are becoming standard school equipment in
many countries, and are proving valuable aids in promoting
self-expression in children. Here, a class on Reunion island
in the Indian Ocean records a message for far-off friends.
Recording "director" in a French school classroom gives the
signal for a session to begin. This particular recording was
later included In one of the regular French radio program¬
mes which are devoted to sound hunters and their work.
and singing stars were recorded for the first time when
they were completely unknown, by amateurs. Many of
them have their own tape recorders and use them either
to test their work (Francis Lemarque, a leading French
songwriter, sketched his "Mon Copain de Pekin"My
Pal from Peking on his portable tape recorder in a train
back from Peking), to rehearse or else to relax among
friends by getting away from their own usual roles. At
last, you might say, a clown can play Hamlet. All this
adds up to a great deal of material for historians at all
levels.
Nor should we forget that the first recording of a
childbirth ever broadcast by radio (over the French na¬
tional radio network in 1951) was made by an amateur...
who happened to be the husband and the father of the
two "actors".
The pants of the ants at mealtime
THE great wealth of private sound recordings is
seldom appreciated at its true value because it has
never been assembled. But it can be safely said
that this value is quite high from ethnographical, socio¬
logical, political, artistic, scientific and cultural view¬
points, in addition to representing a considerable hoard
of anecdotes. This is only normal, after all, because the
great mass of amateurs have far more opportunities than
various professional organizations for recording anything
and everything.
The amateur's contribution Is also important when the
sound hunter turns to the laboratory. Several amateurs,
for example, have done some intensive research on ampli¬
fication with remarkable results. I will just mention
three of them.
After four months of preparation and 100 hours of
experimenting, Roger-Paul Besançon, a salesman of watch
gears and jewels (he's Swiss, of course), managed to isolate
the various elements of a watch and recorded the noise
of each of them amplified to machine shop volume!
A young girl from Brittany Miss Yann Evenou, whose
father also happens to be a tape-recorder fanatic, suc¬
ceeded in making an ant's mealtime audible.
Finally, a scientist, Joseph-Maurice Bourot, revealed the
noises inside an apparently soundless pile of dead Wood
and also the sounds of life within a hen's egg just before
hatching.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
SOUND HUNTERS (Continued)
THE FAMOUS RECORDING
OF THE 'SINGING DOGS'
This last recording is certainly one of the most amazing
ever made. First, you hear the beating of the chick's
heart inside the egg. Then the chick pecks at the shell
with Its beak, but it Is still too weak to break out. It only
manages to crack the shell; now we can hear its breath¬
ing. Finally, the chick starts drilling again. This time it
succeeds. And, with the recorder turned up to its top
amplification position, the breaking of that eggshell
sounds like the explosion at Bikini! (See page 6 and back
cover for photo story showing how a baby chick is born.)
In addition to '"sound documentaries", there are also
"sound experiments." Mr. Bourot has quite a few of
them to his credit. One of them consisted of running
the same loop of tape half a million times over the same
playback head thus proving that tape virtually never
wears out... at least not by playing it back.
This experiment also proves the amazing patience
displayed by amateurs. It is not rare, by any means. As
an example, there is that famous recording of the "singing
dogs" it was so perfect that many listeners believed, and
insist on believing despite what has been said, that a
skilled trainer managed to make dogs sing. Actually, it
is nothing less than a note-by-note editing of recordings
of various barks by several dogs.
Fake editing can make a man say sentences which he
never uttered. I know what I am talking about in this
case, because, as a professional radio and TV man, I've
been the victim on several occasions. But since I happen
to be an amateur as well, I should also like to mention an
example of a personal experiment Which could only be
done with a home recorder. Every year for the past six
years and at just about the same date, I have recorded
each of my two daughters reading successive pages from
a book. I plan to continue this for about ten years.
Then I'll put my sections of tape together and I shall
have a sound record, in a continuous story, of the evolution
of these two voices and of their personalities since child¬
hood.
A large part of our rich heritage of amateur recordings
is known because sound hunters have been able to appear
on radio programmes. It is this opportunity, no doubt,
which has certainly been the most important factor in
guiding them to that third stage of maturity which I
mentioned earlier. Going on the air is a form of glory
but it is also a severe and fruitful test. Once you have
heard yourself and the impression of others who have
heard you, then you know whether or not you are wasting
your time. Listening to others tells you what to avoid
and what you might attempt yourself.
In France, the starting gun for these programmes was
fired by the French national radio on February 9, 1948.
That day I thought I was just indulging in a harmless
form of amusement by playing for the public a few disks
made at home for internal consumption. I turned out
to be a sorcerer's apprentice. That one-day broadcast
snowballed into a series of programmes which has been
on the air for the past twelve years. Similar programmes
have gone out on other stations. In many countries ama¬
teurs have formed associations and the associations have
formed the International Sound Recording Federation.
They publish their own magazines, some of Which have
acquired considerable authority, such as the "Revue du
Son" in France and the "Tape-Recording and Hi-Fi
Magazine" in Britain. An International Amateur Recording
Contest has been organized and, at its last session in
London, a jury heard recordings from 18 different countries
and five continents. It awarded substantial prizes to
winners who no longer need envy the best of professionals.
One of them was a village priest in Burgundy whose
technical mastery in stereophonic recording Was dazzling.
Quite a few of the recordings which I've mentioned
earlier were awarded prizes by these international
contests. Some of them have even been issued as com¬
mercial recordings. Sound hunting is no longer just a
hobby. Certain associations help the Red Cross or other
welfare organizations, making recordings for the blind, for
example. The International Federation maintains rela¬
tions with Unesco as a recognized international non¬
governmental organization and it has started to carry out
a policy of co-operation which will probably aim first
at supplying the beginnings of a "recorded sound Bank."
One of the Federation's founding members, the Interna¬
tional Educational Centre for Sound Correspondence,
organizes regular exchanges among the schools and the
children of some twenty-five countries. Bringing the
world together is far less of an abstract idea when it is
expressed on such a plane.
Finally, just as soldiers are recruited from civilian life,
more and more professionals in the radio, recording,
radio-electric and electronic industries are rising from the
ranks of the amateurs. One of them was Stephan Kudel-
ski, the brilliant designer of one of the world's first (both
in quality and in date) self-contained tape recorders.
There is no need for me to add that this certainly does
not mean that amateurism is perishing under the Weight
of its own progress. Quite the contrary. It is continuing,
developing and prospering.
And, less than a century later, we have already gone
much further than anyone could have dared to predict
in the days when the phonograph was considered a scien¬
tific oddity or just a parlour toy.
SOUND HUNTERS AROUND THE WORLD
Amateur recording enthusiasts around the world have
formed associations which are grouped in the International
Federation of Sound Hunters (FICS) whose Secretariat
General is located in Antwerp, Belgium: Dr. Jan Mees,
Lange Leemstraat, 247.
International associations which are members of FICS
include: World Tape Pals Inc., P.O.Box 9211, Dallas,
Texas, U.S.A.; World Tape Pals-Europe, 38, Avenue
Pierre-ler-de-Serbie, Paris 8., France ; Centre International
Scolaire de Correspondance Sonore (CISCS) Mr. Pierre
Guérin, E.P.A. Chanteloup, Sainte-Savine, Aube, France ;
Tape Respondents International, P.O. Box 416, Saint-
Louis 66, Missouri, U.S.A.
Readers interested in amateur tape-recording may wish
to write to these organizations or to those in the following
contries : Denmark: Dansk Magnettone Klub, Mr. K.
Galle, Vesterbrogade 19, Kobenhavs V.; Great Britain:
Federation of British Tape Recording Clubs, Mr. A. Sta-
bleford 9 Normandy Terrace, London, E.C.4 ; Nether¬
lands: Nederlandse Vereniging van Geluidsjagers-
NVG, Alg. Secretariat, Slotlaan 154, Zeist; Sweden:
Svenska Magnetofón Klubben, Fack, Stockholm 26;
Union of South Africa: T.A.C., P.O. Box 386, Windhoek-
S.W.A. ; Australia : Australian Tape Recordists Associa¬
tion, P.O. Box 36, Noble Park, Victoria; Norway: Norsk
Magnetofón Klubb, formann, Ingwar Larsen, Moseid-
moen, Vikeland p.o. ; New Zealand: New Zealand Tape
Recording Club, H.C. Madigan, P.O. Box 255 A., Hawera,
Taranaki.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Q
The Unesco Courler. March 1960
here are about 550 million children aged 5-14
in the world today and 300 million boys and
girls are enrolled in school. For 250 million
no schooling is available. Very roughly, but
conservatively, it Would take $90,000 million
to accommodate these children, and another
$10,000 million a year to run the new schools.
The economic, social and individual effects of this
deprivation are well ¡knoWn. . The provision of education
is indispensable for economic and social progress.
Throughout the world, a satisfactory balance has not yet
been reached between the social programmes which help
to preserve life and the programmes that are aimed at
improving the condition of life.
Education is one major element of the latter group, and
there is a constant struggle to get ahead of increases in
population. Around 1950, about 56 per cent of the world
adult population was literate but only 48 per cent of the
children were going to school, meaning that the number
of future illiterates was likely to be greater than in the
past. By heavy sacrifices, countries raised the proportion
of school enrolments to 55 per cent five years later;
however, even this will not be enough to ensure a more
literate future generation than in the past.
In describing needs, however simply, it is better to take
by turn the main regions of the world. These differ so
much one from another that wider generalization risks
being too abstract. At the risk of over-simplifying
complex questions I shall try to pinpoint some of the
most urgent issues in education today and in the next
few years.
In Latin America, priority is attached by education
authorities to elementary schooling and to vocational
education. Despite some advanced countries, the region
has a high illiteracy rate, and elementary schooling is
not widely available. Rural areas are particularly under¬
privileged. Both the ICA and Unesco have Worked on
the rural school problem in recent years; Unesco in its
Latin American major project singling out for action the
training of better and more rural teachers.
But so far efforts aré not commensurate with the size
of the problem. Vocational and technical education have
No schools
today
for one
child in
two
by Leo R. Femig
of the Unesco Department of Education
Unesco-Pimol
Village school at Nong-Karn, Thailand.
made great strides in many countries, notably Argentina
and Brazil, and have been supported by industry. But
opportunities for adequate training for agriculture, home
economics and trades in general are still lacking in most
areas. Of the two million Latin American students who
pursue studies after elementary school, some 70 per cent
are enrolled in academic high schools, and a very small
percentage of the rest are studying courses of value to
rural occupations.
In the Near East region, educational problem No. 1 is
that presented by the Arab refugees from Palestine. Here
the United Nations Relief and Works Agency, with the
technical co-operation of Unesco, provides schooling for
120,000 refugee children, at an average cost of $50 per
child per year. All refugee children of elementary school
age are now in school. But the programme urgently needs
expansion, particularly in technical and vocational edu¬
cation: at present there are only two vocational training
centres, with a total combined capacity of less than 500
students. Within the countries themselves, technical and
vocational education opportunities are also regarded as
a priority problem. In some parts, where a formal school
system is just beginning to take shape, a considerable
expansion of elementary schooling is required.
For South-East Asia, where heavily populated States
with newly won independence predominate, attention is
being focused on much the same issues as in Latin Ame¬
rica, although for different reasons. One need is the
expansion of elementary schooling, particularly in rural
areas which still account for over 90 per cent of the
population. The second is a more varied secondary school
curriculum, training for practical life rather than for
white-collar jobs.
Much progress has been made in the high school field
by governments, and the Ford Foundation has centred
many education projects on the same point. Yet some
idea of the magnitude of the problem can be obtained
from the situation in India: despite ten years of effort
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
250 million children
without schools (Continued)
to convert the academic, bookish high schools into prac¬
tical multi-purpose schools, it is expected that by 1960
only 1,187 of the existing 20,000 schools will have been
affected and this programme does not even cover the
new schools to meet the needs of a rising population.
As to the other priority, universal elementary education,
the needs are correspondingly greater because of the vast
number involved. A third problem is also acutely felt
in this region of large populations and incipient indus¬
trialization: the absence of an industry serving the schools
with basic teaching equipment, paper, furniture and the
rest. Until such supplies become available, funds cannot
be diverted to the import of more advanced aids, such
as radios, moving picture projectors, etc., which are
regarded as standard classroom equipment in the West.
In identifying this need in Asia, I do not of course over¬
look the fact that it also occurs elsewhere, notably in
the Near East and Africa.
While the African region is perhaps one where all
aspects of education press equally heavily for attention,
some priorities may be hazarded. In the evolution of
new States, higher education in all forms is required
urgently to provide the necessary leadership. And secon¬
dary education, both general and vocational, will have
to be expanded for any significant steps forward in
productivity and welfare, as well as to feed institutions
of higher education; at present high schools enrol 2 per
cent of the numbers attending elementary schools, while
in the United States, Britain and France the figure is
between 30 and 40 per cent.
To say that higher education or universal elementary
schooling is an urgent need is not to explain much about
the need itself. This is best done by examining the
classic components of education the student, the class¬
room, the teacher, then the school system as a whole.
Lunch: an integral part
of going to school
First, the students. They are there, numerous enough;
but one cannot achieve an efficient education simply
by providing the buildings and the teachers these
students lack. It must be remembered that in under¬
developed areas, poverty and malnutrition accompany
illiteracy; a minimum welfare service is indispensable
to encourage school attendance and to enable children to
profit from tuition. Even in the United States the School
Lunch Programme is looked upon as an integral part of
the public school system. The experience of Unicef's
dried milk programme in many underdeveloped regions,
notably some Caribbean territories, has shown that a
basic nutrition service directly benefits school attendance
and relations between home and school.
Next, the plant, covering buildings, equipment and
teaching supplies. Provision of buildings is costly, as
everyone knows; from say $4 million for an institution
of higher education through $500,000-$750,000 for a secon¬
dary institution down to a modest $100,000 or less for an
elementary school. Of these figures, the greatest variation
in costs occurs at elementary level, where standards vary
greatly, and many underdeveloped areas create such
schools at as low a cost as $500-$l,000.
Outlay on building programme has to be progressive
and planned, the more so since each portion of capital
outlay brings in its wake fresh recurrent costs for runn¬
ing the school thus set up. The education development
schemes in Tropical Africa have revealed the risk of
overtaxing the local economy and the need for the pos¬
sibility of carry-over from one fiscal year to the next.
Moreover, too little in general is known about low-cost
school building construction and the use of local mate¬
rials. Research here might produce great savings.
Finally, it must be noted that teaching supplies are
indispensable for an efficient school system, and the
production of them is urgently needed in at least one
region. Costs of textbook plants or furniture factories
vary too much to allow one to fix norms; but Unesco
12
experience with textbooks in Korea, Ford Foundation help
to Burma, and the production of simple science equip¬
ment in India prove that these problems can be solved
at a national level only if sufficient capital is available.
Alongside students and buildings, there is a need for
teachers perhaps the greatest need of all. The education
of teachers is the investment part of the education budget,
and a fairly costly one, since the majority of teachers-
to-be have to be assisted during their course of training.
In rural elementary education as in general and voca¬
tional secondary schooling, the demand for teachers is
perhaps the point where development programmes can
do the most good: but action here requires not only the
setting up and staffing or the improvement of teacher
colleges, but also the provision of funds for maintaining
such schools at an efficient level of intake and output.
Last, the area of the school system as a whole, involv¬
ing educational administration, planning and research
aspects which lie close together is one of world-wide
concern. In much of the World, and notably in the
regions touched on above, research is the best method
for countries to cope in the long run with their own
problems. The difficulties are many: lack of research
personnel, of funds for faculties of education, and of
general public support for such activities.
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
Primary school in Basel, Switzerland Paul Merkle, Basel
Most of the preparation for administrators, planners
and research workers has been secured at high cost
through sending students to North America and Europe.
While such study abroad is important, it is likely that
regional, and progressively, national institutions will be
needed if an adequate supply of trained men and women
is to be produced. The institutional side of the fact¬
finding process bureaux for gathering, analysing and
diffusing educational data was "recognized when the
United States set up its Office of Education in 1867, but
is only now appearing as a felt need in the newly inde¬
pendent States.
The existing programme of Unesco reveals how resources
may be applied internationally to the solution of national
needs. Unesco at present provides some measure of edu¬
cational assistance to a large number of its Member
States in Asia, Africa and Latin America. This assistance
is aimed at improving education at all levels: university,
secondary education (vocational and general) and ele¬
mentary education. It is, for the most part, focused on
(a) help to governments in planning the development of
their national education systems and (b) the training of
teaching staff. Funds for the provision of equipment are
negligible. Each project aided by Unesco could be consi¬
derably expanded, were funds to become available.
Mr. Fernig's article is taken from
"Unesco Chronicle" (August-Sep¬
tember 1959, vol. V, No. 8-9) a
monthly publication which reviews
the activities of the Organization.
Each issue features three or four
basic articles on the programme
and achievements of Unesco, gives
news of the Secretariat and of
Unesco National Commissions in
different countries, reviews recent
Unesco publications (books and
periodicals;, reports news of international non-governmental
organizations which collaborate with Unesco and publishes a
time-table of conferences, meetings and seminars convened
or subsidized by Unesco. The "Unesco Chronicle " has been
published since 1955 in English, French and Spanish editions.
Annual subscription: $1.75; 10/6 (stg.); 5 NF. Per copy
price: $0.20; I/- (stg.); 0.50 NF.
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
THE MAGIC ART
OF CZECH GLASS
by Indrich Santar
Klement Gottwald State Prizewinner and author of the
scenario of the Czechoslovak Glass Exhibition in Moscow
" * tr»
ai.» \ <u .
M» P r- urn,
1'F'IIII
,/JlTTJUJiJ r^fu
-!1
¡
& JM££*L
m
~.+m
u i
Uy
7*:
.<r
kV
VI \1S&¿*< \\X
.~5 ;
'/ :r
*«*>>',. 4
It
m
GLASS FLOOR
is laid down by
artisans in Mos¬
cow prior to open¬
ing of a recent
exhibition in the
Soviet Union on
the history and
modern develop¬
ment of Czech
glass. Exhibition
was largest of its
kind ever held.
Sixteenth cen¬
tury wood en¬
graving (opposite
page) depicts a
pedlar heavily
laden with a mul-
lection of Czech
glass products.
.
.
J*r
9r
*&**&**
Jan Lukas
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
NO one knows exactly where or when men first
made glass. The Roman historian, Pliny the
Elder, attributed the discovery of glassmaking
to the Phoenicians but modern research has
traced glass far beyond the date set by Pliny.
In the case of Egypt, the oldest definitely dated piece
bears the cartouche of Amenhotep who reigned from
1551 to 1526 B.C. and glass beads found in excavations
at Ur (2450 B.C.) indicate that the manufacture may
have started in Mesopotamia or even further north.
Strangely enough most ordinary glass today is made
from the same materials used from the very beginning,
namely sand, lime and soda or potash and the pro¬
portions are usually about the same as those used
perhaps 4,000 years ago. The same is not true of the
techniques now employed, for today, glassmakers pro¬
duce different types of glass designed for a thousand
and one uses to which it is put in modern life.
Among the countries which have contributed their
skills and ingenuity to the development of the magic
art of the glassmaker, certainly one of the most out¬
standing is Czechoslovakia. In Moscow recently, a vast
exhibition of Czechoslovak glass gave eloquent proof
of the achievements of a centuries' old industry famed
alike for its expressively beautiful craftsmanship and
for the innumerable practical uses it has given to glass
in medicine, architecture, photography, cinematography,
broadcasting, television and many fields of research and
technology.
This was not only the largest exhibition in the history
of the Czechoslovak glass industry but also probably
the biggest thematic exhibition devoted exclusively to
glass that has ever been organized anywhere in the
world. It stressed the fascinating methods employed in
present-day glass production and at the same time
vividly recalled the history of Czech glass.
The history of the "'crystal masters"of Czechoslovakia
goes back many centuries. Archaeological and his¬
torical studies have shown that glass was made some
200 years B.C. on what is now the territory of Czecho¬
slovakia (it was then inhabited by Celtic tribes). It is
believed that glass manufacture diminished during the
first centuries of the Slav settlement of the country and
was not revived until the ninth or tenth century, the
formative period of the first Czech state. Ancient chro¬
nicles and artifacts of the period tell us that in the
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
WORLD-WIDE RENOWN OF
BOHEMIA'S CRYSTAL GLASS
THE MAGIC
ART
Continued
potteries (guty) in the forests of Southern Moravia,
especially at Gradiska and Mikulcic, a well-developed
glass industry existed. Such items as Slovak glass beads,
rings, amulets, etc., have been found during archaeolo¬
gical excavations.
Glass manufacture in the Czech lands attained a high
level of development during the reign of the Czech
King, Charles IV (fourteenth century) who was also
Emperor of the Holy Roman Empire. Some of the
glassware of the period that has been preserved is
unique sets of glassware, a considerable amount of
jewellery and ornaments and utensils used by apothe¬
caries and alchemists.
The art of combining coloured glass with painting
for stained glass church windows reached a very high
standard in Bohemia. In the year 1458, Enea Silvio de
Piccolomini wrote in his History of Bohemia: "I con¬
tend that in my time there are no such beautiful and
magnificent windows in the churches of any kingdom
in the whole of Europe as those in the Kingdom of
Bohemia. The light filters through . tall, wide windows
Reproduced from "Glati In Czechoslovakia"
published by S. N. T. L., Prague, 1958
made from clear, artistically decorated glass. And all
this is to be found not only in the towns and cities but
also in small villages."
The pretentiousness of feudal life, the thirst for luxury
and magnificence, brought about an extensive develop¬
ment of handicrafts and, in Bohemia, of glassmaking
in particular. The development was so great that by
the 16th century there were thirty-four glass manufac¬
tories on the territory of present-day Bohemia and
Moravia. They later began to specialize in the produc¬
tion of different types of glass and the old Czech crafts¬
men gave their glass an appearance of nobility that
made it famous throughout the world. They made many
varieties of glass, each embodying specific qualities,
especially that possessing the brilliance of a diamond
when elaborately cut and polished; this variety of glass
became widely known as "'Czech crystal glass." The
fine glassware of the Czech masters became an important
item in Czech export and even began to rival the work
of the famous Venetian craftsmen.
The diary of a certain Kreibich, a glass merchant of
that time, has been preserved and
from it we know that he made thirty
journeys to different countries,
supplied glass to the Russian Tsar
and the Turkish Sultan and carried
the produce of Czech craftsmen to
London, Stockholm and Rome ; he
also sold his wares in America and
Africa...
After the Thirty Years' War (1618-
48) Czech glass finally ousted Vene¬
tian glassware from the market.
The crisis created by the Napo¬
leonic wars and the continental
blockade, as well as the development
of glass production in a number of
European countries, checked the
development of the Czech glass
industry and its revival as an art only
became possible in the twenties of
the present century. The First
World War cut Czecb glass off from
the world market and brought about
a considerable stagnation in the
industry. It was only after the
foundation of the Czechoslovak
Republic, in 1918, that the period of
gradual expansion began.
CONT'D ON PAGE 20
RED-HOT GLASS blown by Czech glass-
makers and refined by the sensitive hands of
cutters and engravers has conquered the world
with its endless beauty. Left, crystal glass vase
engraved according to design of Czech artist,
J. Kotik. Right, glassmakers at work In
Czechoslovakia. Each craftsman has his
own "window" opening into the glowing
heart of the circular furnace (upper photo).
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE MAGIC ART (Continued)
CRYSTAL-PURE
CRAFTSMANSHIP
The development of glass production and the continuous
discovery of new possibilities in the use of glass are an integral
part of Czechoslovak history. Centuries ago Czechoslovaks
called glass "the most precious jewel of the land", and the
name "Bohemian glass" has become so universal in the history
of artistic production that it now stands for glass of a certain
composition processed into an object of art rather than to indi¬
cate the origin of the product. Down the years an ever-enriched
sense of artistry combined with skill of hand and eye has en¬
abled Czech artists and glass-makers, working in close colla¬
boration, to produce works of the quality shown here. Right,
engraved crystal jug (northern Bohemia, 1875) and Rococo
many-sided glass with cut monogram (Bohemia, around 1750).
Far right, 14th century drinking glass discovered in a house
in the old part of Prague. Below, several striking examples of
gracefully beautiful products of modern Czech glassmakers.
Reproduced from "Class In Czechoslovakia ", published by SNTL, Prague, 1958
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
THE MAGIC
ART
(Continued from page 16)
Tiny human and animal figures are
given graceful and amusing forms by
their creator, Professor Brychta, a
leading Czechoslovak glass designer.
CTK, Prague
The Czech producers made great efforts to gain pri¬
ority on the world market and increase the volume of
exports above the pre-war level, by adapting themselves
to foreign tastes and fashions. This was one of the
reasons for Czech glassware losing the typical originality
that had made it so famous in the past.
T
HE artistic merits of Czech glassware were
preserved by a few outstanding Czech artists
who were materially independent of glass production.
Among these latter were several artist enthusiasts (Pro¬
fessor Jaroslav Brychta, for example) who led a struggle
against the narrow commercial approach to glass pro¬
duction in Czechoslovakia and who laboured persistently
to find new, purely Czech forms for their art ware. Those
who worked without any support from the owners of
glassworks, however, were but few in number. Never¬
theless, these few enthusiasts, by their efforts, prevented
the further degradation of Czech art glassware.
Under the Nazi occupation during the second World
War, the Czechoslovak glass industry suffered heavy
losses. The majority of the foreign markets were lost
and many glassworks were reorganized for war produc¬
tion. This traditional branch of Czech economy was
saved only by the nationalization of the industry after
the liberation of Czechoslovakia and by the contribution
of all workers in the industry.
Glass, as is well-known, is one of the oldest of man-
made materials. Methods of treating glass have been
gradually perfected at various stages in the history of
its production; during the past few years new varieties
of glass have been invented and the prospects for further
improvement and more extensive use are tremendous.
Modern glass production in Czechoslovakia is
distinguished by its tremendous variety of wares (those
produced by its glassworks amount to some 300,000
items) . They include heavy and thin cut glass, coloured
and painted glass, the famous Czech glass bijouterie
(the glassworks at Jablonec turns out 7,000 new designs
every year), technical glass, building glass...
20
New items, the production of which is being rapidly
developed in Czechoslovakia, include glass pipes for
electric wiring, water and other purposes, foam glass
(a new insulating material), glass tiles for facing walls,
building mosaic and art mosaic.
Unbreakable glass is manufactured at two glassworks
in Karlovy Vary; glass with a great variety of chemical
additives is used for the manufacture of laboratory,
sanitary and dental ustensils and for a wide range of
items such as phials, microscope slides and electric bulbs.
The production of glass fittings for lamps of all kinds
is an important branch of the industry. In this field an
important place is held by the manufacture of chande¬
liers, both classical and modern, which, decorated with
glasswork, are exported to all parts of the world.
The Moscow exhibition demonstrated many varieties
of glass and the uses to which they are put. This is only
a fraction of the possible applications for glass, especially
in industry and building. Panels, staircases, facing tiles,
piping and sanitary equipment, furniture and drapings
for the home these can all be prepared from special
varieties of glass, from glass fibre or laminated fibre (the
latter glued together with plastics.) Many flour mills
and dairies in Czechoslovakia have received glass equip¬
ment that has proved more serviceable than articles made
from other materials.
lass is an inseparable part of our lives, espe¬
cially artistic and domestic glassware. It is
impossible to substitute plastic imitations for glass just
as it is impossible to substitute other materials for the
bronze, marble and stone without which a sculptor can¬
not work.
Czechoslovak glassware is famous today far beyond
the bounds of its homeland it is imported into 120
countries and the Czechoslovak people have every right
to be proud of the art of their compatriots, the artists
and craftsmen whose skill and fantasy create such works
of beauty from plain sand, potash and limestone.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
Taken from "Glass in Czechoslovakia", published by SNTL, Prague, I 9 58
ENGRAVER TO THE EMPEROR. Close-up of a piece of early engraved Bohemian glassthe
work of Caspar Lehman, engraver at the court of the Emperor Rudolph II (I 605). On an armorial
beaker, Lehman engraved the allegorical figures of Liberalitas, Potestas and Nobilitas together with
floral decorations. Shown here are details of the figure Nobilitas. Originally in the castle of Hluboka,
on the River Moldau, the beaker is now in the collection of the Industrial Art Museum, Prague.
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
I weep, therefore I am
by Ritchie Calder
A
T a British schools' conference recently some
students had an argument about how much
(or little) science knows about common¬
place things. Here are three questions for
which they wanted an answer.
QUESTION. David Crichton, of George Heriot's
School, Edinburgh, asks: "Is the fact that human
beings weep important physiologically speaking?"
9 ANSWER: Human beings exist because they can
weep. At least, that Is the suggestion made by
Professor Ashley Montagu of Princeton.
At a Columbia University Seminar on "Genetics
and the Evolution of Man" he argued that weeping
was an important factor in human survival, and
went so far as to say that the perpetuation of the
species was left to those who could weep.
His scientific arguments derive from the length
of the dependency period of the human child.
Human infants do not usually shed tears until
they are about six weeks old. Until they can speak
or have the ability to help themselves their only
means of attracting the attention of others when
they are in distress is by crying. In a tearless infant
crying is no more than the intake and expulsion of
air. It can be shown experimentally that such
crying will dry out the mucous membranes of the
nose. The dried mucous is a useful medium for
growing bacteria and the dried membrane becomes
permeable to germs and admits deadly diseases.
Tears do not only spurt from the eye. As we
know from the nose blowing at "weepy" films they
get into the breathing passages and keep the
mucous membrane moist.
But as Sir Alexander Fleming showed, long before
he discovered penicillin, tears are not just water.
They contain a powerful germ-killer which he called
"lysozyme". This is also found in the secretions
of the nose. This substance is capable of killing
bacteria in the eye or the nose in five to ten
minutes. It inactivates even the polio virus
Lysoyme explains |why the human eye, a delicate
organ, is so rarely Infected by the germs in
the atmosphere to which it is exposed. Similarly
the nose tries to cope with the germs we breathe.
So, the argument runs, natural selection favoured
those infants who were able to produce an abundant
flow of tears.
QUESTION: Carol Whyte of Parkstone Girls
Grammar School, Poole, Dorset, asks: "Was the
poet, Lord Byron, right when he wrote: 'And if I
laugh at any mortal thing, 'tis that I may not
weep'?"
ANSWER: Byron was as near the truth as anyone
in medical science is today. The psychologist,
William McDougall, called laughter "the antidote
to sympathy". Animals suffer the pains they feel
but human beings, with their powers of imagination,
suffer the pains of others as well. We weep for the
misfortunes of others, but we laugh at the mishaps
of the circus clown. As great comedians, like Charlie
Chaplin, have shown, laughter and tears are just
a sob's breath apart.
Indeed, a sob and a laugh are very much alike.
They are both, physiologically, the deep exhaling
and inhaling of air into the lungs, with the cackle
of laughter operating the vocal chords. Hearty
laughter sends a rush of blood to the brain and
to the face and we say: "He laughed until the tears
came."
Although we associate laughter with pleasure and
enjoyment, it is a harsh sound and, as the psycho¬
logists would point out, the harmless expression of
a cruel instinct.
That may sound an exaggeration but, when you
think of it, humour is our own or somebody else's
discomfiture. The universal cause of laughter is
the man who slips on a banana-skin. Even the
hoary old joke about the mother-in-law would lose
its point unless the listeners thought she might be
hearing it. We laugh at other peoples' em¬
barrassment, or at our own; we laugh at the
ludicrous, at people being silly or being made to
look silly. But, also, laughter is highly infectious.
We laugh because others laugh.
An interesting example is tickling. If we tickle
ourselves or are tickled by a stray hair or a fly the
effect is merely -disagreeable and we do not laugh.
Somebody else has to tickle us and both the tickled
and the tickler laugh, and, by laughing together,
they intensify and prolong their laughter, even to
the point of hysterics.
The laughter of young children at play is no more
than the yapping of puppy dogs, but the laughter of
children at Punch being hit by a truncheon, or
carried off to be hanged, is an elementary instance
of the quite primitive nature of laughter. The
situation has to be unreal. No normal child would
laugh at genuine cruelty.
None of this must detract from the value of
laughter. It is a release from tensions and a restor¬
ative. It is physically, mentally and emotionally
relaxing, but the psychologist would say it is not
just that we laugh because we are enjoying
ourselves; we are enjoying ourselves because we
laugh. We are the only creatures that do. And one
does not exclude the "laughing" hyena. He is not
enjoying himself.
QUESTION: John Hood (17), of Sheen Grammar
School, Surrey, asks: "What is the purpose of
yawning?"
ANSWER: The purpose is not, as is commonly
imagined, to get more oxygen into the lungs.
J.S. Haldane proved that many years ago. It is to
expel carbon dioxide, the gas drained from tired
blood cells. He showed that, although the body
needs oxygen, the mechanism of breathing is
governed by carbon dioxide rather than by oxygen.
It is the carbon dioxide in the blood which provokes
the brain to send messages down to the lung
muscles. And a yawn is a convulsive deep breath.
Yawning occurs at moments of lassitude what
a doctor friend of mine calls "waking sleep". It may
be in the open air, relaxing after a walk, and you
yawn and say "All this fresh air is making me
sleepy." Or it may be in the close, hot atmosphere
of a stuffy room. It may be when your body is
weary and you are read for bed. Or it may be when
a speech or conversation has become boring.
Whichever it is sluggishness of body or mind
yawning appears to be due to the carbon dioxide
drugging the blood. The yawn is the counteracting
muscle-response to restore equilibrium.
Yawning Is highly infectious. That is what makes
it social "rudeness"1 implying that you are bored.
But I hope you will yawn reading this because it
is suggestive. You will yawn when a cat or a dog
gapes or stretches. It need not be rude, just imit¬
ative, but you will politely smother it as you would
smother a sneeze, because it is infectious.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
UNESCO COLOUR ART SLIDE SERIES
BRINGS RARE ART INTO THE E
Unesco
"The Shepherds receiving the news". This detail from "The Nativity" is taken from
the Unesco Art Slides series on Yugoslav mediaeval frescoes. The painting, dating
from about 1265, is found in the richly-decorated church of the Trinity at Sopocani.
Little-known art treasures are
now being brought to the
general public at a price it can
reasonably afford thanks to a
new series of Unesco Art Slides.
These collections of slides veritable
miniature "museums" in plastic boxes
illustrate the latest use made by
Unesco of colour photography to
bring the Iworld's great Works of art
to a |wider public. Unesco believes
that, with the great number of pro¬
jectors now is use, high-quality, inex¬
pensive colour slides will bring within
the reach of many, particularly in
schools and study groups, a know¬
ledge of the great masterpieces of art
of different nations which are as yet
insufficiently known.
Since the first sets of slides have
been placed on sale, anyone possessing
a slide projector and screen can sit
back and admire scores of works of
art in the comfort of his own living
room. The first six sets offer a
choice of paintings from the tombs
and temples of ancient Egypt, Yugo¬
slav mediaeval frescoes, the Ajanta
cave paintings of India, the Persian
miniatures of the Imperial Library of
Teheran, Spanish Romanesque paint¬
ings and paintings from the Nor¬
wegian "stave churches". Three more
sets are due to be published later this
year; Masaccio the Frescoes of Flo¬
rence ; Australia Aboriginal Paint¬
ings from Arnhem Land; and Ceylon
Paintings from Temple Shrine and
Rock.
Of undoubted value to students,
teachers and lecturers, the Unesco
Art Slides collection has, however,
been specially designed for use by
non-specialists. Each set comprises
30 framed slides (5x5cms.) in a plas¬
tic box with an explanatory booklet
containing texts and captions in
English, French and Spanish. They
have been prepared by Publications
Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire, Paris.
Two further sets of slides have been
prepared by the French National Com¬
mission for Unesco to commemorate
the i two exhibitions held in Paris
during the tenth session of the
Unesco General Conference. These
are : "Orient-Occident-Encounters
and Influences in Fifty Centuries of
Art" and "The Art of Gandhara and
Central Asia". The set covering the
first exhibition is made up of 41 slides
in two boxes; the second comprises a
box of 21 slides.
The great periods of art which
come to life again in Unesco's colour
slides are also covered in the albums
of Unesco's World Art Series. These
albums of full page colour reproduc¬
tions have now been published over
several years by the New York Gra¬
phic Society by arrangement with
Unesco. They are devoted to the
great periods of art of all civilizations.
CONT'D ON PAGE 2 5
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
The miniatures in the "Iran" series of
Unesco colour slides are reproduced
from six manuscripts In the Imperial
Library in Teheran. Photo shows a
scene in the forecourt of a garden.
Work dates from end of XVth century.
© Unesco
Paintings in the "Spain" slide
series comprise frescoes and
panels from Romanesque sanc¬
tuaries in northern and eastern
Spain, particularly Catalonia
and Aragon. Above, detail of
a 12th-century church frontal
now in the Art Museum of Cata¬
lonia, Barcelona. It depicts
the Mass of St. Martin of Tours.
© Unesco
i*£&Êti£*:T*J
Opposite page, maid-servants
attending ladies at a banquet.
Fresco from an 18th Dynasty
Egyptian tomb. It is one of 30
reproductions in the new Unes¬
co colour slide series devoted
to "Egypt-PaintingsfromTombs
and Temples". The colours
are as fresh and vivid as when
the Egyptian artists applied
their paint 35 centuries ago.
© Unesco
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
COLOUR ART SLIDES (Continued) The Unesco Courier. March 1960
-4-J5
In each album, there are 32 colour
plates and texts written by scholars
of international standing. Selected
works are photographed by a Unesco
mission aided by the Unesco National
Commission in the country concerned.
While Unesco art albums have been
well received (some of them have
appeared in second or third editions)
their price is relatively high because
of their format and quality. This is
why Unesco is now issuing its art
slides so as to reach a larger audience,
especially i in schools and cultural
institutions. Unesco's catalogues of
colour reproductions and its travell¬
ing art exhibitions also aim at this.
The ideal situation of bringing peo¬
ple into direct contact with works of
art is hard to achieve because of
financial difficulties and material
obstacles which limit the movement
of such works. Leaving the organiza¬
tion of such exhibitions to the initia¬
tive of museums and public and pri¬
vate collections, Unesco has chosen
the solution of the "imaginary
museum".
The "imaginary museum" is based
on mass-produced colour reproduc¬
tions, which play the same role in
painting as do recordings in music.
Today, as can be seen in the catalo¬
gues of colour reproductions published
regularly by Unesco since 1949, hun¬
dreds of them are issued every year
in the world. Some two thousand have
already been selected by an interna¬
tional committee of experts for men¬
tion in Unesco's catalogues, where
they are shown in black and White
for identification purposes.
By taking this periodic inventory of
colour reproductions, Unesco tells the
public which worthy reproductions of
the inaccessible original works are
available and, at the same time, offers
publishers a panorama of world pro¬
duction, enabling them to see the
gaps which have to be filled.
One of the Unesco catalogues is
devoted to paintings prior to 1860;
the other to paintings from 1860 to
the present. In some countries they
have helped in the setting up of ar¬
chives of reproductions similar to
those maintained by Unesco and also
in the organization of museums of
reproductions.
By using its own archives, Unesco
has organized seven travelling exhibi¬
tions during the past ten years. Each
has been prepared in numerous copies
so that it can be circulated simul¬
taneously in many countries and for
long periods. Whatever the subject
"Paintings Prior to 1860", "From Im¬
pressionism Till Today", "Drawings
by Leonardo da Vinci", "Japanese
Woodcuts'", "Two Thousand Years of
Chinese Painting", "Persian Miniatu¬
res" and "Water Colours" each exhi¬
bition has been designed to appeal to
highly diversified audiences. .The or¬
ganization and aims of each exhibi
tion are explained in a catalogue by
an internationally-known specialist.
Seventy-seven countries have now
shown these exhibitions, either in
museums and art galleries or in
schools and cultural centres.
All orders for Unesco Art Slides should
be placed directly with the distributors,
Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire,
11, Rue Carvès, Montrouge (Seine) France.
The price varies according to transport and
other costs, but each series of 30 slides will
not exceed $10.00 U.S. or the equivalent
in national currencies. Educational and
cultural institutions are entitled to special
terms on application.
Orders for the two sets of slides prepared
by the French National Commission for
Unesco should also be sent directly to
Publications Filmées d'Art et d'Histoire.
Prices are as follows: For the two boxes
'" Orient-Occident", $13.00 U.S.; for the box
"The Art of Gandhara", $6.50 U.S. or the
equivalent in national currencies (trans¬
portation included). Educational and cul¬
tural institutions are entitled to special
terms on application.
For information on volumes in the
Unesco World Art Series apply to leading
booksellers or to the Division of Arts and
Letters, Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Pa¬
ris 7e.
For catalogues of reproductions write to
Unesco Sales Agents (see page 35).
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
THE 'MARK TWAIN'
UT I I U U I U M by Joseph Leftwich
LITERATURE
An exhibition marking the 100th anniversary of the birth of Sholem Aleichem and devoted
to his life and writings , was inaugurated recently at Unesco House, by Mr. René Maheu,
Deputy Director-General of Unesco. It was sponsored by the French National Commis¬
sion for Unesco. Gifted with a comic outlook, Sholem Aleichem wrote stories in which
he depicted the "little people with small hopes" whom he had known since childhood and
whom he had always loved. He wrote in Yiddish which had been scorned until then by
scholars and writers. Inaugurating the exhibition, Mr. Maheu said: "Sholem Aleichem, so
appropriately named, wanted to be a witness above all. It was in order to be as faith¬
ful as possible to his purpose that he chose to write in Yiddish, the living language of
the people. And yet, his work has universal value... It is because of this universality that
Unesco has included Sholem Aleichem among the eminent men whose anniversaries it
is commemorating: Schiller, Humboldt, Pierre Janet, Bergson, Haydn, Albeniz, Velasquez
and Chekhov. In the present circumstances, I hope that this commemoration in this setting
will be understood by all. Unesco, whose very reason for existence is the vigilance and
the awakening of man's conscience, also intends to bear witness." Below, The Unesco
Courier publishes an article by Joseph Leftwich, English author of Dutch origin, and
a leading authority on Yiddish literature.
Sholem Aleichem" is the Jewish form of greeting, like "How
d'you do?" or "'Glad to meet you," only the literal translation
is "Peace to you," and the words are Hebrew, which is one of
the two main components of the Yiddish language, as Anglo-Saxon
and Norman-French are of English. The Arabs whose language is
akin to Hebrew have the similar "'Salaam Aleikhem," with the same
meaning. Jerusalem derives from the same word, "'Sholem": "'City
of Peace." It is the age-old Jewish salutation after a pogrom, after
expulsion, after whatever tribulation, just as on a quiet, undisturbed
stroll or in visiting a friend, a Jew meeting another greets him,
"'Sholem Aleichem," and receives the answer "Aleichem Sholem":
"To you peace!"
Sholem Aleichem, the great writer, the centenary of whose birth
is being widely observed this year, explained that he adopted the
name out of respect for his father, a solid scholar and businessman,
so as not to embarrass him by his light-hearted stories. Instead of
writing as Sholem Rabinovitch he added Aleichem to his first name.
It was a stroke of genius. The name opened all doors to him;
in every Yiddish-speaking home he was a welcome guest ¡"Come in,
Sholem Aleichem!" He came in, he spoke to the people, and they
spoke to him. They told him about their life, and he wrote it down,
in their own folk-tongue, in their folk-idiom. He caught the folk-
spirit and the folk-humour of the Jewish masses, the millions of
Yiddish-speaking Jews who were living in the Pale of Jewish Settle¬
ment in Czarist Russia.
He pictures his characters speaking to him, telling him their
stories, "'Now I ask you, Panie (Mr.) Sholem Aleichem, isn't it a story
worth writing down?" "'Before Sholem Aleichem those Jews of the
folk hadn't spoken in literature," Dr. Bickel, the President of the
Yiddish PEN Centre, has written. "'They were spoken about. Not
CONT'D ON PAGE 28
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
The centenary of Sholem Alei¬
chem is being marked in many
countries. The whole of the
world's Yiddish press (there
are 168 Yiddish publications,
including 12 daily papers) is
publishing articles devoted to
Sholem Aleichem and stories
by him. In some countries new
editions of his works have
appeared. His plays are being
presented in all the Yiddish
language theatres and in parti¬
cular, during the present thea¬
trical season, by the Jewish
Theatres of the State in Poland
and Rumania. For the first
time, the celebration of a Jewish
literary anniversary is taking
place outside the Jewish com¬
munities. Innumerable meet¬
ings, recitals, concerts and thea¬
trical performances have been
arranged for the occasion.
Nationally organized celebra¬
tions have taken place in Israel,
Poland, Rumania and the Soviet
Union and in Belgium under
the sponsorship of the Ministry
of Education. Streets have been
named after him in the Argen¬
tine, Brazil, Bulgaria, Israel,
Poland and the Soviet Union.
Right, Sholem Aleichem a pho¬
tographic study taken shortly
before his death. Below left,
model reproduction of a scene
from "Tevya the Dairyman"
presented by the Yiddish State
theatre in Bucharest; right,
model of a scene from, " The
First Prize ", produced by the
Jewish Academic Theatre of Mos¬
cow. Opposite page, how one
artist has depicted two of his
best-known characters : top,
Menachem Mendel, the business¬
man ; below Tevya the Dairyman.
Unesco photos
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
On May 15, 1916, some 120,000 persons followed the hearse bearing Sholem Aleichem to his grave. This "was the greatest spon¬
taneous gathering of the people in the history of the City of New York" according to a United States Congressman of that time.
till Sholem Aleichem did they speak themselves, their
Own words, the endless flow of words that lay so heavy on
their hearts."
There have been and there are other great Yiddish
writers: Mendele, Peretz, Sholem Asch. Yiddish is not a
one-man literature, but no other Yiddish writer made the
Jewish people articulate as did Sholem Aleichem.
Sholem Aleichem lived and wrote in Russia before the
First World War, when Poland and the Baltic States were
part of the Czar's domains, and a mass of six million
Jews lived in compact settlements in a comparatively
small concentrated area, with an almost completely auto¬
nomous Jewish life. He died in 1916, before the Revolu¬
tion which changed the entire face of Jewish life in those
parts.
He could not have foreseen the Second World War in
which nearly six million Jews, almost the entire Jewish
population of Eastern Europe Was massacred in the death
camps and the gas ovens. It is understandable therefore
that many Jews in England and France and above all
in America and in Israel who are themselves immigrants
from Europe or the children of immigrants, look back
nostalgically on the world of Sholem Aleichem as the
world of their childhood or that of their parents and
grand-parents. And often in the tone of a valedictory,
as a world that has vanished from the earth.
But Sholem Aleichem is too great a writer to have
created people in his books who would so soon have
vanished from the earth. His figures are too full of Jewish
and universal humanity to die. They still live among the
survivors in Eastern Europe, and among the immigrants
and their children and grandchildren in America and
Israel and England and France and other places, not only
among those who still use Yiddish as one of their lan-
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courler. March 1960
I want to be buried among simple people
O
n Monday, May 15, 1916, a man whose very
name is unfamiliar, went to his grave. His
coffin was of plain pine boards, unadorned.
Yet, 120,000 people followed the hearse
through the city streets. There were only
a mere handful of police but no disorder, for those
who thronged the streets mourned. It was the
greatest spontaneous gathering of thé people in the
history of our city. Factories and workshops found
it difficult to proceed, and toilers, men and women
alike, who could ill afford the loss, sacrificed the
day's wage to join in the tribute.
"And the dead man was neither rich nor powerful.
Sholem Ben Menachem Rabinowitz was just a
writer...
"Of the home, of husbands, of wives, and of little
children he wrote, and the Jewish people, a home
and family loving people, thronged our streets to
honor his memory...
"When he died, they passed by the tens of thous¬
ands beside his dead body in his humble home in
the Bronx, and followed by scores of thousands his
plain coffln to its last resting place..."
This was the homage paid by Congressman
Bennett in a speech made to the United States
Congress, the day after Sholem Aleikhem's funeral
in New York.
The great Jewish author died at the age of 57,
leaving a will drafted six months earlier which in
itself is a masterpiece of humility and simplicity.
Here are a few paragraphs from this will:
'Wherever I die I want to be placed not among
aristocrats, or among the powerful, but among plain
Jewish labourers, among the people itself, so that
the gravestone that is to be placed upon my grave
should illumine the simple graves about me: and
these simple graves should adorn my gravestone,
even as the plain, good people during my lifetime
illumined their Folkeschrieber.
. "There should be no kind of debate or discussion
among my colleagues as to making my name eternal,
as to a monument to be erected in New York, etc.
I shall not be able to rest quietly in my grave if
my colleagues make themselves foolish.
"The best monument for me will be if my works
are read and if there be found among the better-
to-do classes of our people Maecenases Who will
publish and distribute my works in Yiddish or in
other languages, and thus give the people the possi¬
bility of reading and my family an honourable
existence.
"If I have not been worthy or have not earned
Maecenases during my lifetime, perhaps I shall be
worthy of them after my death. I go away from
the world in the full belief that the people will not
forsake my orphans."
guages, but even among those who no longer know the
Yiddish language in which Sholem Aleichem wrote, and
can read him only in translation. They communicate
themselves as characters in great literature do, to others
who do not themselves belong to that stock and derive
from that milieu.
His works exist in Russian translations, just as they do
in Hebrew, in English and even in Chinese. He has
millions of Russian and Ukrainian readers otherwise
there Would have been no point in the Soviet authorities
issuing a Sholem Aleichem postage stamp for his cente¬
nary. The Israeli Government also issued a centenary
stamp for a great Jewish writer, Who was an early Zionist,
and whose works exist in a complete and very popular
Hebrew translation by his son-in-law, I.D. Berkovitch.
A volume of Sholem Aleichem stories was issued for his
centenary in Yiddish by the State Publishing House in
Moscow, and the introduction emphasizes that "Russia
was his homeland. It was here that he wrote; his people
lived on this soil. There is no corner of this land where
his work is not known, translated in millions of copies in
many of the languages of the Soviet Union." His work
was known to the great Russian writers of his time;
Maxim Gorki, who had a great admiration for Sholem
Aleichem, said after reading one of his books: "A won¬
derful book. I laughed and wept. It sparkles with a good,
healthy and wise love for the people."
As a great humorist Sholem Aleichem compares in many
ways to Mark Twain, who is said to have introduced him¬
self once to Sholem Aleichem as the "American Sholem
Aleichem"; he recalls Mark Twain particularly in his
great book of the adventures of a young boy, Mottel the
orphan, who, in the different environment and with the
different speech, is a true brother to Huckleberry Finn.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
** <:^.: '
One of Sholem Aleichem's finest books, "Adventures of Mottel, the
Cantor's Son" is such an enjoyable book for children and grown-ups
that many persons have compared it with Mark Twain's "Tom Sawyer"
and "Huckieberry Finn". Here Mottel is seen filching an apple from a
neighbour's tree. "There's nothing as tasty as ripe apples plucked from
the tree in Menashe's garden," Mottel says. Woodcut by llya Schor.
Like Mark Twain too, he makes it difficult for some
readers to realize that the prolific joker who keeps them
chuckling and laughing is, under the cap and bells, a very
significant delineator of character and social conditions.
His humour has an immense social awareness, irony and
pity; he has fresh, bubbling humour, but also a bitter wit.
Sholem Aleichem wrote proliflcally. At home, on his
travels, ill in bed, he was always writing, and in his
57 years of life his output of short stories, novels, sketches
and plays Was enormous.
But the three figures around whom he wrote much of
his work are Mottel the orphan boy, Menachem Mendel,
the businessman, and Tevya, the dairy farmer. Menachem
Mendel is constantly chasing dreams of a financial success
that always eludes him; a restless, impatient seeker, he is
here, there and everywhere, full of madcap schemes, the
eternal optimist, a Micawber type. Tevya is a poor, hard
working village Jew, rooted to the soil, patient and plodd¬
ing, weighed down by poverty and troubles, yet steadfast
and unshakeable, with a deep faith in God and His ways,
that he is sure will in the end put everything right.
And Sholem Aleichem was all three himself. He was
Mottel the orphan boy. His mother died when he was 13,
and he was brought up by his grandfather. He spent-
several years in his teens and also, after a short interval,
in his twenties on a big landed estate owned by his father-
in-law, on whose death he became the administrator of
the estate; he observed the life of the Jewish and non-
Jewish farmers and village people, and felt much of their
attachment to the soil. He spoke of his years on the land
as the happiest years of his life. And he was in many
ways himself Menachem Mendel. He was on the Stock
Exchange in Kiev and in Odessa. He undertook all sorts
of business ventures, always unsuccessfully. "I tried all
trades, but failed in all", he said of himself. In all except
literature, where he became a great figure.
He projected something of himself into Menachem Men¬
del, into Tevya, into Mottel, and also into some of their
accompanying figures family and friends and acquain¬
tances. He observed and absorbed and recreated. Mena¬
chem Mendel and Tevya and Mottel are all drawn
bigger than life-size, more real than just one person.
They are a synthesis of the human boy, of the soil-
bound stolid farmer, of the restless dreamer-speculator.
Sholem Aleichem took his people as he saw them, as they
spake to him, and added himself as an ingredient; the
yeast which made them rise to the height of the univer¬
sal; he made them poetry.
And because he made more of them than the common
man, because he gave them universality, imagination,
poetry, immortality, the world of Sholem Aleichem has not
passed. People still recognize themselves in his characters.
So many orphan boys everywhere are Mottel. So many
Jewish farmers in Israel and America are Tevyas. So
many businessmen engaged in big speculations are Mena¬
chem Mendel. Dr. Emmanuel Pat in New York has
written an essay in Which he traces the development of
Mottel and his circle in American life to-day. He has
found them all still there, with Americanized names, with
different economic and social conditions, yet in character
unchanged.
Sholem Aleichem would have recognized them, as
others do. When he Was in London in 1906 he himself
recognized them in London streets and homes then. They
are still recognizably alive to-day, because they were
never only real people but are timeless and enduring.
And his voice and his writings are not only for Jews but
for all people.
Making the rounds, Methu-
saleh the ancient horse
wearily drags his master
Kastiel the Water-Carrier
from house to house. Illus¬
tration drawn by B.I. Inger.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
JtROTECTTNG THE AUTHOR:
Brazil and Czechoslovakia have now joined
the Universal Copyright Convention spon¬
sored by Unesco. The Convention was
drawn up to fill gaps in international copy¬
right legislation under which some countries
were bound by one convention, others by
a different one and still others by no agree¬
ments at all. It eliminates costly registra¬
tion formalities and calls on States to grant
foreign works the same protection as that
granted to works by their own nationals.
Thirty-four countries have now joined the
Convention.
y U.S.S.R. WEATHER MAP: Over
40 leading Soviet climatologists have
been working to compile the first volume
of the Climatic Atlas of the Soviet
Union. Climatic information about
various areas is needed for the construc¬
tion of water reservoirs, hydro-electric
stations and electric power lines and is
of particular importance for agriculture.
Information about the climatic peculia¬
rities of various areas enables economic
planners to give the most rational dis¬
position to different branches of pro¬
duction.
M INTERNATIONAL OUTLOOK :
In San Diego, California, a study of world
affairs by citizen groups is proving effective
in stimulating public interest in places and
peoples outside the borders of the United
States and in international problems
generally. The Citizen Consultations are
sponsored by the United States National
Commission for Unesco, and the San Diego
group is headed by Dr. Malcolm A. Love,
president of San Diego State College.
Five committees made formal studies of:
Americans as International Travellers and
Hosts; Asian-American Relations; Progress
of Less-Developed Countries; Our Moral
and Spiritual Resources for International
Co-operation; Foreign Languages and the
National Interest. The committees made
recommendations in their fields. One result
of the sessions was a stimulation of interest
in Unesco's work.
Reproduction authorized; Credit line
should read: (Unesco)
TV LESSONS IN AFRICA: In Wes¬
tern Nigeria, where free universal pri¬
mary education was introduced in 1955,
educational and commercial television
services are to be launched. It is pro¬
posed to devote not less than 50% of
daily telecasts to education programmes
for schools, adult literacy courses, advice
to farmers and other public welfare ser¬
vices. Since 1955 the number of chil¬
dren in Western Nigeria's schools has
more than doubled and has now reached
1,100,000.
4,000
NUBIAN MONUMENTS' CAMPAIGN: KING OF SWEDEN
ACCEPTS PRESIDENCY OF COMMITTEE OF PATRONS
KING Gustaf VI Adolf of Sweden, has consented to be President of the
Committee of Patrons of the International Campaign to Save the
Monuments of Nubia, which will be officially launched from UNESCO
Headquarters on March 8.
The campaign is being undertaken, on the proposal of Dr. Vittorino Veronese,
Director-General of UNESCO, in response to requests from the Governments of
the United Arab Republic and of the Sudan for large-scale international
assistance to save the sites and monuments of Nubia, threatened by submersion
as a result of the construction of the new Aswan High Dam.
The Committee of Patrons and an International Action Committee are being
formed by the Director-General of UNESCO to assist him in organizing the
campaign.
An international committee of experts is also being formed by the Government
of the U.A.R., in consultation with UNESCO, to advise on excavation and pre¬
servation plans, on the use of contributions and on allotment of counterpart grants
to Governments, institutions and persons participating in the international action.
The Government of the U.A.R. has offered to cede half the proceeds of the
excavations in the threatened area (with the exception of unique or essential
items needed by Egyptian museums), to authorize excavations of other sites in
Egypt, and to offer certain temples in Upper Nubia, with a view to their transfer
abroad, as well as a large collection of antiquities from other parts of Egypt,
which belong to the State. The Government of the Sudan has also offered,
with the same reservations, 50 per cent of the proceeds of excavations in the
threatened area of the Sudan.
_r9wv YEARS OF GAMES:
What games do the world's children play?
This question was posed by an exhibition
at Neufchatel, Switzerland. Exhibits showed
that children the world over play very
much the same games, and their play¬
things have not changed essentially over
thousands of years. On display were terra
cotta dolls and animals with which children
of Babylon and Egypt played over 4,000
years ago. Most games, according to the
exhibition, can be divided into four
groups competition, chance, mimicry, or
vertiginous and many are of magical
or religious origin. Devotees of football
or squash rackets, for example, are said
to be unconsciously perpetuating the rites of
sun-worshippers, long-since forgotten.
a JAPAN IN 1,000 PAGES: A wealth
of information on the history and cul¬
ture of Japan is found in "Japan, its
Land, People and Culture", issued by
the Japanese National Commission for
Unesco. In 1,000 pages, the book covers
the geographical historical, social, eco¬
nomic and cultural background and
aspects of modern life. Chapters on
drama, manners and customs, common
beliefs and superstitions and on recrea¬
tion and amusement, including expla¬
nations of tea ceremonies and flower
arrangement, provide a varied and
fascinating picture of Japan. Obtainable
from Japan Publications Trading Co.
Ltd, Central Post Office, Box 722,
Tokyo, Japan ($12.00).
Help for paralysis vic¬
tims: The Regional Office for Europe
of the World Health Organization has
appointed an international team to help
the Government of Morocco in treating and
rehabilitating paralyzed victims of the
recent poisoning at Meknes. This tragedy
has already claimed more than 10,000 vic¬
tims and probably represents the biggest
and the most serious case of poisoning by
adulterated oil in medical history. The
WHO teams, which include a specialist in
rehabilitation and two physiotherapists,
will advise the Moroccan Ministry of
Health on the organization of emergency
treatment, hospitalization, outpatient ser¬
vices and rehabilitation It will also train
personel assigned to it by the Moroccan
Government.
MUSEUM-GOING BY NIGHT:
Museum-going has now become another
way of spending the evening in Rich¬
mond, Virginia, in the United States,
where the Virginia Museum of Fine
Arts now opens its doors five nights a
week from eight to ten o'clock. By night
as well as by day, the Museum offers
visitors electronic guidance (tape-record¬
ed explanations) and film shows on art.
Among its other pioneering activities
have been the introduction of a state¬
wide visual arts service offering films,
film strips and exhibitions throughout
Virginia and the operation of an "art-
mobile" travelling to all parts of the
state.
EiiQUIVALENCE OF UNIVERSITY
DEGREES: A European convention on the
equivalence of university diplomas has
been signed in Paris by ten of the fifteen
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
foreign ministers of the Council of Europe,
or by their deputies. It will enable
holders of university degrees to pursue
their studies in any of the countries which
have signed the convention, or to use a
degree from a foreign university covered by
the agreement. The convention was signed
by Belgium, France, Federal Germany,
Greece, Iceland, Italy, Luxembourg, the
Netherlands, Norway, and the United
Kingdom.
The Unesco
Philatelic Service
Here is the first commemorative
stamp of the year issued by the
United Nations Postal Admi¬
nistration (in 4 cent and 8 cent
denominations). This stamp can be
obtained from The Unesco Phil¬
atelic Service which has stamps and
first day covers issued by many
Member States to commemorate
important events in the history of
Unesco and the U.N. (inauguration
of Unesco's New Headquarters,
Human Rights Day, World Refugee
Year). As the agent in France of
the U.N. Postal Administration,
Unesco's Philatelic Service stocks
all the United Nations stamps
currently on sale. Information on
items available, their price and the
methods of payment, will be sent
on request by Unesco's Philatelic
Service, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7e.
THAI TONY TRAP' LIBRARY:
A pony-cart travelling library regularly
leaves the Fundamental Education
Centre at Ubol, Thailand, on trips to
carry books to villagers in the surround¬
ing area. The library-cart is helping to
solve a problem that has been worrying
the librarian of the Centre, run by the
Thai Government and Unesco. Until
now, the Centre has been sending books
to the villages in boxes holding about
50 books as they could only be changed
every three months. A bookmobile
was out of the question, since it was
too expensive and roads are impassable
for motor traffic at certain seasons.
The idea of using a specially-designed
pony-cart was suggested by the Unesco
librarian at the Centre, and the students
themselves constructed the bodywork
while a skilled Thai craftsman made the
chassis.
JMaORI LITERARY REVIVAL:
Indications of a renaissance of Maori lite¬
rary effort (both in English and Maori)
have come recently from New Zealand
where a vigorous movement has grown up
in recent years round the educational
magazine '"Te Ao Hou" (The New Dawn).
When the magazine was started by the
Maori Purpose Fund in 1952, practically
nothing was being done by Maoris in lite¬
rary forms such as the short story and
poetry. Today most of the material for the
publication is written by them. Until the
last century the Maoris had no written lan¬
guage. There was a short creative period
at the end of the last century followed by
a decline, but the tradition never really
died as is seen in present movement.
MIDDLE EAST LABOUR INSTI¬
TUTE: The Labour Institute for the
Near and Middle East, created at Istan¬
bul five years ago by the International
Labour Organization was recently turn¬
ed over to the Government of Turkey
by the ILO. During the past five years,
the Institute has organized seminars or
courses on problems of industrial safety
and health, industrial medicine, social
security, and employment services, for
officials of the region. The Institute
comprises a museum of industrial safety,
a technical library and an industrial
hygiene laboratory.
French without tears:
Toronto schoolchildren are learning French
by "playing store", a method adopted in
experimental classes for English-speaking
Canadian pupils aged eleven and twelve.
Not a single textbook is used in the class
and teachers never translate a word of
French into English. Instead, drawings are
used to explain the meaning of words.
During a lesson, pupils take turns at being
customers, clerks, post-office employees or
bank cashiers... always in French.
H UJST. CHILDREN'S VILLAGE:
A '"United Nations Children's Village",
designed to bring together children from
all over the world, has been planned by
the People's Committee of Belgrade for
a new amusement park to be built in
the Yugoslav capital. The village is
foreseen- as a series of small houses,
each one typical of its own country,
which would serve as permanent exhi¬
bition halls. Countries wishing to par¬
ticipate in the village would be asked to
take charge of the building of these
houses as well as their operation that
is, the organization of games, sale of
books and toys, film shows on how chil¬
dren live, and programmes of dancing
and singing.
IMeasuring by
equipment for physics
EAR: Special
and chemistry
laboratories is to be manufactured in
Israel based on designs by an Austra¬
lian inventor. This equipment will
enable students at the lerusalem Educa¬
tion Home for the Blind to receive
scientific training and obtain employ¬
ment in fields which until now have
been closed to the sightless. The ins¬
truments, which were developed in
Australia by Mr. A. Wechsler, give
measurements that can be '"read" by ear
or by touch.
DECLARATION OF RIGHTS OF THE CHILD
The right of the child to *% happy childhood", to affection, security, education
and to protection against all forms of exploitation is proclaimed in the Declaration
of tbe Rights of the child Which has been adopted in New York by the United
Nations General Assembly.
The Declaration, which embodies 10 principles, stresses in its preamble, that
"the child, by reason of his physical and mental immaturity, needs special safe¬
guards and care, including legal protection, before as well as after birth." The
child's rights, the Declaration states, must be recognized without distinction of
race, colour, sex, language, religion, national or social origin, birth or other
status.
In all circumstances the child shall be among the first to receive protection
and relief. Every child has the right to free education, at least in the elemen¬
tary stages, and full opportunity for play and recreation. The physically and
mentally handicapped shall be given special treatment, education and care, and
all shall have the right to adequate nutrition, housing, medical services and social
security.
Stressing the responsibility of the parents, the Declaration states that the child
should grow up in their care "in an atmosphere of moral and material security."
"Society and the public authorities", it adds, "have the duty to extend particular
care to children without a family."
The Declaration seeks to protect the child against all forms of neglect, cruelty
and exploitation and against employment "before an appropriate minimum age."
He must be protected also from practices which may foster racial, religious, or
all other forms of discrimination, and be brought up in a spirit of tolerance and
understanding.
In the words of the preamble, "mankind owes to the child the best it has to
give", and the Declaration calls on men and women and national governments
"to recognize these rights and strive for their observance by legislative and other
measures."
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco Courier. March 1960
LARGEST CENSUS
OF WORLD'S FARMING
STARTS THIS YEAR
FAO photo by V. Bianchl
Special training for staff who are carrying out the World Census
of Agriculture in Latin America was given at a centre set up in
Lima, capital of Peru. Here, investigators prepared for the real
thing by making an experimental census of population, housing
and farming in mountain villages near to Lima. During practice
census trainee uses llama as a table while noting down facts.
A World Census of Agriculture the biggest inquiry of
its kind ever to be carried out is being taken this
year under the sponsorship of the Food and Agri¬
culture Organization of the United Nations (FAO)
. in Rome. In scores of countries, thousands 01
investigators are collecting the individual facts and figures
which, once assembled, should give a clear and accurate
statistical picture of farming the world's biggest industry.
On mountain-side farms in Peru, rice fields in the Far
East, coffee plantations in Brazil and orange groves in the
Near East, census takers are noting down facts about every
basic factor concerned with farming, from the land itself
down to the number of bees and silkworms and other forms
of life and possessions which appear in the farm inventory.
Investigators have hundreds of questions to put to farmers.
There are, for instance, 252 different crops to be dealt
with, ranging from corn to cabbages and from bamboos to
bananas, and the crop group forms only one of the ten
main sections into which agriculture has been divided for
the purposes of the Census. In addition it is hoped to
compile an accurate record of the number of farmers, the
size of farms, their tenure, acreage under crops, to note
whether they are watered by rain, canal or pumps and to
count heads of livestock of all kinds.
What is the point of this enormously complex undertaking?
Why should all these figures be required? And what use
can be made of this information when it has been gathered,
analyzed and published?
The answers, according to Dr. P.V. Sukhatme, Director
of Statistics Division, FAO, are these:
In the first place the Census will be of great benefit both
to countries and farmers as it will give them a proper idea
of where they stand regarding agricultural conditions.
Secondly it will give FAO a much-needed clear picture of
world agriculture, revealing the pattern of progress and
enabling it to see those sections of the industry to which
it should pay special attention, either on a world basis or by
regions and countries. Such a picture can only be gained
by collecting comparable statistics which can show each
nation's level of prosperity in relation to its neighbour's and
to the world generally.
Lack of reliable statistics is one of the main obstacles
facing FAO and its member countries in planning and
implementing the development of food and agricultural
resources by the use of more fertilizers, farm machinery
and irrigation, for example. Without the full basic facts
planning may go awry and result in wasteful expenditure as
well as the failure to improve food production.
'Tailor-made* for every region
This was why FAO took over the job of collecting, com¬
piling and publishing basic data on the food and agri¬
cultural situation of the world from the International
Institute of Agriculture when this organization merged with
the FAO.
The First World Agricultural Census to be sponsored by
FAO was in 1950, but at that time only five countries in
Asia and the Far East took part. Since then there has
been a growing recognition of the importance of the inquiry
and this year many more countries in that part of the
world plan to participate.
The programme for the 1960 World Census is the
outcome of many years of work, research and consultation
in all parts of the world. Regional programmes prepared
in collaboration with statisticians, agricultural organizations
and governments have ensured that the Census is adapted
to the needs of different areas.
Dr. Sukhatme points out that an agricultural Census is
a difficult operation even in economically developed nations
which possess established statistical and allied services.
Allocating areas to individual crops is complicated by the
cultivation of more than one crop in the same field. The
number of people working on farms varies from season to
season. Finally, uniform definitions must be agreed upon
if statistics are to be of value internationally.
To add to the complexity of carrying out this world
Census there exists a human element the farmer and the
Census taker. Farmers are often reluctant to give full and
frank answers because they do not understand the purpose
of the Census or because they fear that such information
may be used to their disadvantage, such as in assessing
taxes, although Census law guarantees that all replies to
questions will be treated as confidential.
There is also the problem of finding qualified staff. This,
FAO is helping to overcome by carrying through a training
programme for the Census planners and staff. It has
organized three regional training centres at Lima, for
Latin America, in Tokyo for Asia and the Far East and
at Damascus for the Near East countries. In these centres
emphasis has been placed on planning and conducting
experimental censuses in the field.
Seminars have also been held, at Accra for countries irj
Africa south of the Sahara and in Warsaw for European
countries. At both training centres and seminars, FAO has
dealt with such problems as adapting the Census to meel
national and regional needs and training personnel how tc
plan and conduct the Census in their country and region.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WE STILL DO AS ROME DID
Sir,
I was delighted to see the article,
illustrated with such beautiful photo¬
graphs, on Hadrian's villa at Tivoli in
your December issue. Anything ap¬
pertaining to the Romans is my
favourite subject, and I never dreamt
it would be featured in The Courier.
As you will guess, I would appreciate
more articles on this subject. Please
introduce us to the many other
examples of Roman civilization in
Europe, Asia and North Africa. I feel
that you will be helping to draw
together by a common interest peoples
of many tongues, even as the Roman
Empire did in its better days before
the decline. Moreover, you Will make
us ask ourselves why the Romans made
mistakes, and why we, with our greater
knowledge and experience, tend to do
the same.
I am curious to know if this subject
holds much interest for readers in the
Soviet Union and Eastern Europe.
B.S. Beezer
Eltham, London
CURING THE MENTALLY ILL
Sir,
In your most interesting issue
which has many valuable articles on
Mental Health, I find it regrettable
that you quote a statistic; namely, that
80% of mental patients can now look
forward to being cured and can take
their place once again in society.
Unfortunately, this is an over-
optimistic evaluation of the present
status of the therapy of psychiatric
illness. We gain nothing from over-
optimism and an unrealistic attitude.
As a psychoanalyst, I know that the
"cure" of a mental illness is only ac¬
complished by working out the emotion¬
al conflicts which underly it. The
effect of tranquillizing or energyzing
medications, attitude therapy, occup¬
ational therapy, change of environment
and other means is only to produce a
remission in the illness but it does not
unfortunately lead to a cure.
With the use of the above measures,
however, the patient may be able to
return to society and possibly take up
his former place and resume his
occupation. We must however view
this question of "'cure" in a scientific
manner and thus much, much more
research must be done before we can
speak of a "cure" of mental disease,
except through psychoanalysis.
There is much misunderstanding
concerning the role of tranquillizing
and energyzing drugs. These can never
cure psychiatric illness. At best they
can only make the patient more ac¬
cessible to other forms of therapy by
allaying anxiety to the degree that
therapy can now be utilized by the
patient. In this period of over-optimism
concerning the value of medications,
some of which promise increasing help
in the fntuxe but which as yet have
unfortunately proved somewhat dis¬
appointing, one must be careful to
avoid misleading statements and thus I
bring this matter to your attention.
Maurice N. Walsh, M.D.
Beverly Hills, California, U.S.A.
Ed. note: We have received the
following reply to Dr. Walsh's letter
from Dr. E.E. Krapf, Chief, Mental
Health, World Health Organisation:
Dear Dr. Walsh,
You consider it over-optimistic to say
that "'80% of mental patients can now
look forward to being cured and can
take their place once again in society."
I fully share your view if it were
claimed that 80% of mental patients
can now reach a state of complete
mental health. What is meant is
really "80% of mental patients can now
look forward to being cured in so far as
they can take their place once again
in society." Doubtless this could have
been expressed in a less debatable way.
On the other hand you will perhaps
agree that it is never very easy to speak
of the favourable outcome of a disease
in terms of a "cure" in the absolute
and ideal sense of the word and that
it is very general custom amongst
physicians to call a patient cured when
he has been improved to a point where
he can lead a more or less "'normal"
life.
As to your scepticism in respect of
the curative possibilities of drugs, I am
completely on your side. I quite agree
that "'there is much misunderstanding
concerning the role of tranquillizing and
energizing drugs" and that "'these can
never cure psychiatric illness." I am not
aware, however, that statements to the
contrary have been made in The
Unesco Courier or, for that matter,
in the WHO press release from which
The Courier took its information on
the achievements of modern psychiatry.
Lack of space prevents me from going
any deeper into the manifold problems
posed by the introduction of the new
"psychotropic" drugs.
There is one last topic upon which
you touch. If I understand you correct¬
ly, you are convinced that there is no
real cure for mental disease "except
through psychoanalysis."
May I say that I have some very
serious doubts in this respect. Being
a psychoanalyst myself I am, of
course, quite aware of the fact that the
"'working out of emotional conflicts"
sometimes leads to very spectacular
improvements, particularly where
neuroses and character disorders are
concerned; but as to the possibility of
reaching through psychoanalysis a state
of complete mental health, I am rather
inclined to adhere to Sigmund Freud's
own conclusion that strictly speaking
psychoanalysis is probably "intermin¬
able."
In his paper on the terminabi-
lity of psychoanalytic treatments Freud
in fact expresses the opinion that
only when in the genesis of a disorder
the traumatic factor predominates are
there good chances of obtaining a full
stabilization of the personality. A word
of caution is, however, added: "If the
patient who has made such a good
recovery never produces any more
symptoms calling for analysis, it still,
of course, remains an open question
how much of this immunity is due to a
benevolent fate which spares him too
searching a test." As far as I can see
this prudent reserve is still fully
justified.
E.E. Krapf,
Chief, Mental Health,
World Health Organization,
Geneva, Switzerland
ART INVERTED
Sir,
True sometimes it is difficult to tell,
but the photograph of the Miro Unicef
Greeting Card on page 24 of the
December issue of The Unesco
Courier is upside down. It looks
infinitely better the correct way.
Dr. M.F. Shore,
Brookline, Mass.,
U.S.A.
THE WORLD'S FOLKWAYS
Sir,
I think if from time to time you pub¬
lished articles on the folklore of dif¬
ferent countries and provinces, these
would interest many of your readers.
The subject is one' in which I am pas¬
sionately interested and I believe it helps
one to get to know and to like regions
and countries and, above, all, their peo¬
ples. Here is an excellent way to
stimulate understanding and friendship
between nations. An obvious proof of
this is the tremendous success which
foreign folklore groups have had when
they have performed in my own and
other countries.
Bernard Bascoul
Mazamet, France
o
z
<
o
z
<
o
13
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Where to obtain
Unesco
publications
Order from any bookseller, or write
direct to the National Distributor
in your country. (See list below ;
names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.)
Payment is made in the national
currency ; rates quoted are for an
annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaî, Press
Department, Royal Afghan Ministry of
Education, Kabul.
AUSTRALIA. Melbourne University
Press, 369 Lonsdale Street, Melbourne,
C. I. Victoria. (A. 13/-).
AUSTRIA. Verlag Georg Fromme
& C0., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V (Seh.
37.50)
BELGIUM. For The Unesco Courier.
Louis de Lannoy, 22, Place De Brouckère,
Brussels, CCP 338 000 (fr. b 100)
Other publications Office de Publicité,
I 6, rue Marcq, Bruxelles, CCP 285-98;
N V. Standaard-Boekhandel, Belgielei I 5 I,
Antwerp.
BURMA. S PC K. (Burma) 549, Merchant
Street, P O. Box 222, Rangoon.
CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa
Ont. (S 3 00).
CEYLON. The Associated Newspapers
of Ceylon Ltd, Lake House Bookshop,
100 Parsons Road, P O. Box 244, Co¬
lombo, 2. (Rs. 9).
CHINA. World Book Co, Ltd, 99
Chungking South Rd , Section I, Taipeh,
Taiwan (Formosa)
CUBA. Librería Económica, Pte Zayas
505-7 Apartado 113, Havana.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. Artia Ltd., 30
Ve Smeckách, Prague 2.
DENMARK. Ejnar Munksgaard Ltd,
6 Norregade, Copenhagen K. (D kr. 12).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agen¬
cy, P O. Box 120, Addis Ababa.
FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa,
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (F.mk. 540).
FRANCE. Unesco Bookshop, Place de
Fontenoy. Pans, 7<\ CCP. 12598-48
(7 NF)
GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg KG,
Unesco-Vertneb fur Deutschland, Rosen-
heimerstrasse 1 45, Munich 8. (DM 6).
GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28,
rue du Stade, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co , 25,
Nathan Road, Kowloon.
HUNGARY. Kultura, P O. Box 149.
Budapest, 62.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Private Ltd.
Indian Mercantile Chamber, Nicol Road,
Bombay I; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue,
Calcutta 1 3 ; Gunfoundry Road, Hyde¬
rabad, I; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2;
Kanson House, 24/1 Asaf Ah Road, P O.
Box 386, New Delhi, I, Sub-Depots.
Oxford Book & Stationery Co , Scindia
House, New Delhi; Rajkamal Prakashan
Private Ltd , Himalaya House, Hornby
Road, Bombay I. (Rs. 6.70).
INDONESIA. G C.T. Van Dorp & Co ,
Djalan Nusantara 22, Posttrommel 85,
Djakarta.
IRAN. Iranian National Commission for
Unesco. Avenue du Musée, Teheran.
IRAQ. Mackenzie's Bookshop, Baghdad.
IRELAND. The National Press, 2, Wel¬
lington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (10/-)
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores Ltd ,
35, Allenby Road and 48, Nahlat Benja¬
min Street, Tel-Aviv (1£ 4-)
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91
Harbour Street, Kingston.
Knox Educational Services, Spaldings ( I 0/-)
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd , 6 Tori-
Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605
Tokyo Central, Tokyo. (Yen 500).
JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous & Co ,
Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road, P.O B 66,
Amman.
KOREA. Korean National Commission
for Unesco, P O. Box Central 64, Seoul.
LUXEMBOURG. Librairie Paul Brück,
33, Grand-Rue, Luxembourg.
MALAYAN FEDERATION AND
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications
Ltd , Times House, River Valley Rd , I 35,
Singapore.
MALTA. Sapienza's Library, 26 Kings-
way, Valetta ( I 0/-)
MONACO. British Library, 30 Bid des
Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (7 NF)
NETHERLANDS. N V. Martinus Nij-
hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague (fl 6)
NEW ZEALAND. Unesco Publications
Centre, 100 Hackchorne Road, Christ-
church (10/-).
NIGERIA. CMS. Bookshop, P O Box
174, Lagos. (10/-)
NORWAY. A S. Bokhjornet, Stortings-
plass, 7, Oslo. (N. kr. 10)
PAKISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing
Co, Ltd , Unesco Publications House
P.O. Box 374, 56-N Gulberg Industrial
Colony Lahore
PANAMA. Cultural Panameña, Avenida
7a, No. Ti-49, Apartado de Correos 20 I 8,
Panama, D.F.
PHILIPPINES. Philippine Education Co.
Inc , 1104 Castillejos, Quiapo, P.O. Box
620. Manila
POLAND. Osrodek Rozpowszechniania
Wydawmctw Naukowych PAN, Palac
Kultury i Nauki, Warsaw. (Zl. 50)
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrada Lda,
Livrana Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70,
Lisbon.
SOUTH AFRICA. Van Schaik's Book¬
store, Libri Building, Church Street, P.O.
Box 724, Pretoria (10/-)
SWEDEN. For The Unesco Courier: Sven-
ska Unescoradet, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C (Kr. 7 50) other publications
A/B C E. Friezes, Kungl Hovbokhandel,
Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
SWITZERLAND. Europa Verlag, 5
Ramistrasse, Zurich
Payot, 40, rue du Marché, Geneva. CCP.
1-236. (fr. s. 7)
THAILAND. Suksapan Panit, Mansion
9, Rajdamnern Avenue, Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Isti-
klal Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
UNION OF SOUTH AFRICA. Van
Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church'
Street. Pretoria (10/-).
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT).
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha,
Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S E 1 (10/-)
UNITED STATES. Unesco Publications
Center, 801 Third Avenue, New York,
22, N Y. (S 3.00 ) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broad¬
way, New York, 27, N.Y.
U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200.
YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjïga,
Terazije 27/11. Belgrade.
Courses
Study Tours
Work Camps
Cours et
voyages d'études,
chantiers internationaux
Cursos y viajes de
estudio, campos
internacionafes de
trabajo voluntario
Vacations Abroad
Vacances à l'étranger
Vacaciones
en el extranjero
VACATIONS ABROAD
Vol. XII, I960
Courses, Study Tours, Work Camps
Do you want to plan your vacations to the best
advantage ? Do you want to make friends of your
own age in foreign countries ? Do you want to
know about all the opportunities that are open
to you ? If so, you will be interested in the latest
volume of VACATIONS ABROAD. It will give
you information on over 1,500 educational and
cultural vacation activities open to young people,
students, teachers and workers wishing to com¬
bine their holidays abroad with educational tra¬
vel. Over 770 institutions have contributed
information on vacation activities in I960 in
approximately 75 countries.
Order your copy of VACATIONS ABROAD
now from the Unesco national distributors (left).
US S 1.25 6/-(stg.) 4.50 NF
STUDY ABROAD
A companion volume to Vacations Abroad Vol. XI 1959/60
International Handbook of Fellowships, Scholarships and Educ¬
ational Exchange published for those interested in longer periods
of study abroad. 90 000 awards; I I I countries.
83.00; 15/- (stg.); 10.50 NF
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
BY CHICK
B OR
(See PjageJSl
Wî\±izï
r
Photos © R H. Noailles
»mm mm , WW~-
]]>
</page>
</document>
