<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078371eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
-. *'
.m* *2££J%>*
*/
-
*-» ' ^?¥>-
¿j- ' '
.
8SW' ','.»
'
The Ramayana and the Manainli^fô
TWO GREAT EPICS OF ASIA
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART©
Ravana shaking Mt. Kailasa
Numerous episodes from the Indian epic, the Ramayana, are carved ¡n relief on the
walls of the great 8th-century temple, cut from the solid rock at Ellorà, near Bombay.
This relief, one of the most dramatic and monumental, depicts the episode in which
Ravana, the demon-king, attempts to shake and uproot the sacred mountain Kailasa
(after which the temple is named) on which the god Shiva and the goddess Parvati
are seated. Here, imprisoned within Mt. Kailasa, Ravana strains his many arms in a
superhuman effort while Shiva with a single foot steadies the trembling mountain.
Í 1
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
DECEMBER 1967
20TH YEAR
NOW PUBLISHED IN
ELEVEN EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e.
Annual subscription rates: 15/-stg.; S3.00
(Canada); 10 French francs or equivalent;
2 years : 27/-stg. ; 1 8 F. Single copies 1/6-stg. ;
30 cents; 1 F.
.
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except
in August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German, Arabic,
Japanese, Italian, Hindi and Tamil. In the United Kingdom it
is distributed by H.M. Stationery Office, P.O. Box 569
London, S.E.I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot
be returned unless accompanied by an international
reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles express the
opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of the
UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in The Read¬
ers' Guide to Periodical Literature, published by
H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7e. France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant to the Editor-in-Chief
Lucio Attinelli
Managing Editors
English Edition: Ronald Fenton (Paris)
French Edition: Jane Albert Hesse (Paris)
Spanish Edition: Arturo Despouey (Paris)
Russian Edition: Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
German Edition: Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition: Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Hindi Edilion: Annapuzha Charidrahasan (Delhi)
Tamil Edition: Sri S. Govindarajulu (Madras)
Research and Illustrations: Olga Rodel
Layout and Design: Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressdto the Editor-in-Chief
Page
13
16
18
30
32
34
36
43
45
46
2
12 pages in full colour
THE MAHABHARATA - THE RAMAYANA
Two great epics of India and South Asia
By Arthur L. Basham
THE MARRIAGE OF DRAUPADI
An episode from the Mahabharata
THE COLLECTIVE DREAM OF A CONTINENT
By Anil de Si/va
HANUMAN, LEADER OF THE MONKEYS
THE EPICS IN THE ART OF SOUTH ASIA
Poems in stone, tales in miniature
By B.N. Goswamy
THE EXILE OF RAMA
A poem from the Ramayana as told by Kamban
MOVING TRAGEDIES IN STONE
Carved by Khmer artists of Cambodia
SHADOWS AND LIGHT ON THE RAMAYANA
Behind the screens in Cambodia's shadow theatre
KATHAKALI AND THE DANCE-DRAMA OF INDIA
By C. Kunchu Nah
INDIA'S ANCIENT HEROES ON CELLULOID
By Bhagwan D. Garga
FURTHER READING ON THE RAMAYANA
AND THE MAHABHARATA
LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
Ravana shaking Mt. Kailasa (India)
Photo © Rapho-Brihat. Paris Coyer photo
Dusserah is the name of the popular
Indian festival held in September-Oct¬
ober each year symbolizing the triumph
of good over evil. The culmination of
nine nights of celebrations, it is linked
with the story of the Ramanaya and in
northern India the festivities end with
the portrayal of Rama's victory over
Ravana the demon-king. Here a colos¬
sal paste-board effigy of ten-headed
Ravana bursts into flames after fiery
arrows shot by Rama set off crackers
packed inside (See also P. 15). In
southern India, Ravana is less a villain
than a tragic figure and a victim of his
ill-fated passion.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
Two great epics of India and South Asia
THE MAHABHARATA
AND THE RAMAYANA
by Arthur L. Basham
T
4
HE religious and cultural
life of the whole of the Indian sub¬
continent and much of the rest of Asia
has been deeply influenced by the two
great epic poems of Hinduism, the
Mahabharata (pronounced Ma-ha-bah-
ra-ta, accent on "bah") and the
Ramayana (pronounced Rah-my-ana,
accent on "my"). Putting aside all
question of their merits as literature,
which by any standard are very high,
they are among the most important
poems in the world.
Of the two the Mahabharata is in
essence the older, its nuclear story
having been transmitted from the
shadowy period following the compo¬
sition of the Rig Veda, the oldest liter¬
ature of India. A few of the names
of rulers, sages and priests mentioned
in the Mahabharata also occur in
sources of the later Vedic period, and
the story of the epic may have devel¬
oped around traditions of a great
battle which took place about 900 B.C.
But with the passing centuries the
account was so enlarged and develop¬
ed by the introduction of new charac¬
ters and incidents that its historical
kernel cannot now be established.
There is even some reason to believe
that the divine hero Krishna, who
plays such an important role in the
story as we now have it, was grafted
into the poem, and had no part in the
original martial tradition out of which
it developed. From references in other
Sanskrit texts, it seems that the story,
in a form not very different from that
which we now know, was current in
northern India a century or two before
our era and perhaps as early as
400 B.C.
ARTHUR L. BASHAM is professor of Asian
Civilization at the Australian National Uni¬
versity, Canberra. He formerly taught at
London University where he was lecturer in
History of India and later professor of
the History of South Asia. This year he
has been visiting professor at the South
Asia Regional Studies Graduate School,
University of Pennsylvania. Professor
Basham has written widely on Indian history
and civilization: "The Wonder that was
India" (Sidgwick and Jackson, London,
1954); "Studies in Indian History and
Culture" (Samboohi Publications, Calcutta,
1964) and "Aspects of Ancient Indian
Culture" (Asia Publishing House, Bombay,
1966).
The plot of the Mahabharata is a
complicated one. Like the Greek
stories of the Trojan war out of which
emerged the Iliad, and like the cycle
of Germanic myth and legend which
crystalized into the Nibelungenlied, the
Indian epic tells of a bitter quarrel
which developed into a war of exter¬
mination. The five sons of Pandu are
unjustly deprived of their ancestral
kingdom by their wicked cousins, the
Kauravas, and they regain it after a
tremendous battle in which all their
enemies and most of their friends are
slain. .
Echoes of a heroic age are heard
throughout the narrative portions of
the epic, and the martial values of
bravery, loyalty and truthfulness are
much encouraged. Heroes and villains
alike never refuse challenges, whether
to battle, to contests of skill, or to
games of chance, and few major char¬
acters are guilty of serious cowardice.
The atmosphere of the main narrative
is that of a society just emerging from
tribalism, in which personal loyalty to
one's chief and fellow clansmen is still
very strongly emphasized.
But the Mahabharata as we have it
contains more than the poetic account
of a legendary war. It is replete with
interpolations of all kinds, which were
obviously introduced long after the
main narrative was composed.
The longest of these Is the Santi
Parvan, the twelfth of the 18 sections
or books into which the epic is divided,
and by no means the shortest of them.
Here the slow death of the wounded
Bhishma, the elder statesman of the
Kauravas, is made the pretext for a
long series of didactic passages on
many aspects of polity, ethics and
religion.
Similarly Yudhishthira, the eldest of
the five heroes, is a passionate but
inexpert gambler, and it is as a result
of his vice that he and his brothers
are forced into exile. This gives the
cue for the introduction of the lengthy
tale of king Nala, another addicted
gambler of even older days who lost
his wife and kingdom through dicing,
but regained them at last after many
adventures.
This interpolation, in fluent easy
verse, often forms the student's first
introduction to Sanskrit literature in
the original. From its style and content
it appears to be at least as old as the
main narrative of the epic, and looks
back to the days of small semi-tribal
kingdoms before the time of the Buddha.
Undoubtedly the most important
. interpolation of the Mahabharata is the
Bhagavad-Gita, the long religious
poem which has become the most
influential text of modern Hinduism. Of
all works of Sanskrit literature it is
probably the most widely known out¬
side India, and ¡t has been translated
into many languages and read by
millions who know nothing else of the
epic poem which contains it.'
A pretext for its inclusion is provid¬
ed, just before the commencement of
the great battle, by the misgivings of
Arjuna, the second of the five heroes,
at the thought of fighting his own
kinsfolk and friends. His mentor
Krishna strengthens Arjuna's resolu¬
tion with this long religious poem,
itself possibly a conflation of verses
from more than one source, and
reveals himself as the great God
Vishnu incarnate.
Shorter interpolations are numerous,
and include the well known and beau¬
tiful legend of the faithful wife Savitri,
who saves her husband from the clut¬
ches of the god of death, the story of
Rama, a brief summary of the other
great Hindu epic, and that of Shakun-
tala, in a version significantly different
from the plot of Kalidasa's famous
drama.
These many episodes, both narrative
and didactic, seem to have been
incorporated into the text of the Maha¬
bharata by various editors in the
course of the five centuries between
the Maurya and Gupta empires, from
about 200 B.C. to A.D. 300. By about
A.D. 500 the full epic existed in some¬
thing like its present form.
A terminal date may be established
from the lists of tribes and peoples
which occur here and there in the text.
Such lists* include the Hunas (the
Hephthalites or White Huns), who
could hardly have been known to the
Indians until about A.D. 400, when
they had established themselves in
Bactria, but they do not include other
peoples such as the Gurjaras, who
first appear on the scene in the sixth
century.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
: P"
v- - ffí-ffilS' títo
iï%;&&^:tem^:*àm
Ä2VJ*Wr'-1?
Photo © Rapho, Louis-Frédéric, Paris
Sculptured on the great rock-hewn temple of Kailasanath, at Ellorà, near Bombay, this frieze
portrays episodes from one of the world's most ancient epic poems, the Mahabharata.
When this bas-relief with its innumerable figures of men and animals was carved
nearly 12 centuries ago, the stories and characters it depicted had already been well-known
to the peoples of northern India for a thousand years.
But, even ' after the closing of the
canon of the text, manuscripts were
subjected to many minor emendations
and interpolations, and three main
textual traditions of the Mahabharata
have been traced. Now the splendid
edition of the Bhandarkar Oriental
Research Institute of Poona, which has
just been completed after the labour
of many scholars for over forty years,
has provided an established text of
the epic, as it existed at the end of
the Gupta period.
Thanks to the great expansion which
it has undergone the Mahabharata is
something much more than a narrative
epic, though it is quite possible to
extract the narrative from the many
interpolations and present it as a
heroic poem.
The largest single poem in the
world, containing nearly 100,000 coup¬
lets or stanzas of two verses each,
or about seven times the size of the
Iliad and Odyssey combined, it has
aptly been described as an ency¬
clopaedia of early Hinduism. It treats
of almost every aspect of the religious,
political and social life of the India of
the time, viewed chiefly from the angle
of the orthodox brahmin. It contains
much didactic material out of which
developed the Dharmasastras, or legal
texts, and the Puranas, the long
poems on myth, legend and religious
practice which were compiled from the
Gupta period onwards. Thus, even
though no faith can be placed on the
historicity of its story, it is of the
utmost importance to the historian.
The plethora of didactic interpola¬
tions, which have expanded the poem
to so unwieldy a length, have some¬
what reduced its popularity. The main
story is widely known among ordinary
Hindus, however, and later authors
have written poems, dramas and prose
stories around many of its episodes,
in both Sanskrit and the modern lan-
guagos of India.
Abridged versions of the Mahabha¬
rata, omitting many of the interpola¬
tions, exist in most languages of India
CONTINUED ON PAGE S
5
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
6
MINIATURES
ON FILM
AND CANVAS
The Ramayana and the Mahabharata have been
subjects of Indian feature films for many years (see
article page 43). Left, a scene from "Sandesh," a new
Govt, of India cartoon film produced by J. Bhownagary
to help India's Save the Food campaign, using
traditional material from the Mahabharata for a
contemporary purpose. Draupadi, left, has no food
to offer except a grain on an empty plate.
Krishna replies that even one grain is important. The
images are the work of a young, gifted painter,
R.K. Malwankar. He is known for his lovely
miniatures using the thumb and fingerprint technique.
The artist has successfully caught the beauty and
atmosphere of 18th-century art in northern India, an
example of which is shown on right.
A miniature dating from 1765, it depicts
an episode from the Ramayana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
FAR INTO
THE NIGHT
WITH INDIA'S
TROUBADORS
In India, where oral and
visual tradition has
been a means of
transmitting knowledge for
centuries, the Ramayana
and the Mahabharata are
an enduring and inherent
part of popular culture.
They have found their
way into every language
and dialect of India and
South "Asia, where even
poor and isolated villages
have puppet shows,
dramas or plays based
on the epics (see pages
29 and 36). Everywhere
in Indian villages and
towns people love to sit in
a circle and listen far
into the night to the
recitations and songs of
these poems. Many
thousands of people
devote a set period
each day to reading the
Ramayana or Gita aloud,
starting again at the
beginning as soon as
the end is reached since
these works have almost
the sanctity of the Bible
among Christians.
Left and opposite,
wandering minstrels sing
the story of the
Ramayana to audiences in
Calcutta's open-air meeting
ground, the Maldan.
Popular paintings near
musician's hand depict
Rama and his wife Sita.
Photos © Georges Tcherkine, Paris
Photo © National Museum, New Delhi
r-»<- ^^ëBj^- / ;
JL" -» - Mf^^mi *- --"ul^y m, v<.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
TWO GREAT EPICS (Continued from page 5)
Mahabharata, world's longest poem verses
and Southeast Asia, and the story of
the five heroes, much adapted to local
taste and tradition, is still popular in
the wayang, the shadow theatre of
Indonesia.
Few but Hindu pandits and serious
students, however, have read the
whole Mahabharata from beginning to
end, even in translation, and in the
form in which we have it it can never
become a "popular classic." But in
India it has long served as a mine of
material for later authors, and it
remains so to this day.
The second of the great epics, the
Ramayana, differs from the Mahabha¬
rata both in theme and in character.
It tells of the righteous prince Rama,
who is unjustly exiled by his father,
Dasaratha, king of Ayodhya. Accom¬
panied by his beauh'ful wife Sita and
his loyal younger brother Lakshmana
he takes refuge in the wild forests of
central and southern India (see "The
Exile of Rama", page 30), where the
three have many adventures, the most
exciting of which is the capture of Sita
by Ravana, the demon king of Ceylon,
and her ultimate rescue by the bro¬
thers, helped by an army of monkeys.
At last Rama regains his ancestral
kingdom, but the end of the story is
not altogether happy, since in order
to satisfy public opinion Rama is com¬
pelled to put away Sita, who has lost
her ritual purity residing in the house
of another man, though in captivity
she was perfectly chaste and loyal
to her husband.
The Ramayana is an account of the
marvellous adventures of an almost
supernatural hero, embroidered with
wonders of every kind, and written in
formal courtly language. For a Euro¬
pean parallel we should look not to
the Iliad or even to the Aeneid, but to
such works as Wolfram's Parzifal or
perhaps Ariosto's Orlando Furioso.
The marvellous and supernatural
elements are intensified in the first
and last books, where Rama, the hero
of the poem, is revealed as an Incar¬
nation of the great God Vishnu, who
took human form in order to save the
world from the molestations of demons.
Hence, Rama is worshipped as a god
to this day, and the Ramayana is
looked on as a sacred text.
The epic has many passages of
drama and pathos, and shows consid¬
erable psychological insight. It incul¬
cates the virtues of courage, loyalty,
faith, forgiveness and fellowship.
The Ramayana does not contain
very lengthy interpolations, and in
style and content it gives a much
greater sense of unity than does the
Mahabharata. Moreover, its length is
less than a quarter of that of the other
epic. The composition is more literary
in character, and many similes and
metaphors suggest classical courtly
Sanskrit poetry of the kind written by
Kalidasa. Lengthy descriptive passa¬
ges punctuate the narrative, and these
include beautiful word-pictures of the
seasons of the Indian year, such as
became formal and regular features
of the later Sanskrit kavya or courtly
epic.
8
The marriage of Draupadi
The text below is taken from a children's book published in India in 1965 (1) which
retells a number of stories selected from the Indian classics. This tale, "Draupadi
Swayamwara", relates an episode from the Mahabharata: a contest of skill between
the Pandava and the Kaurava clans for the hand of the Princess Draupadi.
Text (c) copyright - Reproduction prohibited
T he Pandavas were living in Ekachakra when
they heard news about the Princess Draupadi. Draupadi
was the daughter of Drupada, the King of Panchala. She
was the most beautiful princess of the time and was
greatly talented. Kings and princes of many countries
desired to marry her.
King Drupada had hoped that Draupadi would marry
Arjuna, the cleverest and the most handsome among the
Pandavas. But he heard, with great sorrow, of the tragic
death of the Pandavas at Varanavata. Now he had to find
some other suitable husband for Draupadi. There were
many young princes of great name seeking her hand. But
King Drupada could not make a choice. He decided to
hold a swayamwara for his daughter.
Swayamwara was a kind of marriage where a princess
could choose her husband from among a crowd of suitors.
The suitors would be introduced to the princess one by
one and she would make her own choice. Sometimes the
suitors were asked to perform some difficult feat of strength
or skill and he who did it first would get the princess in
marriage.
A day was fixed for Draupadi's swayamwara and invita¬
tions were sent to all kings and princes. Everyone accepted
and they came to the Kingdom of Panchala.
The Pandavas, still in disguise, decided to attend Drau¬
padi's swayamwara. They went to the capital of Panchala
with Kunti. There they stayed in the house of a potter.
On the day of the swayamwara, the Pandavas left Kunti
(/) "Tales from Indian Classics". Book 1 retold by Savitri, illustrated
by Pulak Biswas. © Children's Book Trust, New Delhi. 1965.
in the potter's house and went to the palace. They went
there not as princes but as Brahmins and took their seats
among the visitors.
The kings and princes had arrived hoping to win the
hand of Draupadi. There were distinguished warriors
among them. The Kauravas, confident of winning the
princess, were also there.
The large marriage hall was beautifully decorated. The
guests took their seats. King Drupada and his son escorted
Draupadi to the hall. Everyone stood up and looked
eagerly at the most beautiful princess they had ever seen.
King Drupada then said that Draupadi would marry any
man of noble birth who could string a bow kept in the
hall and shoot at a target. The bow was huge and heavy.
The target was a little metal fish very high above the ground
inside a disc with holes that kept turning round and round.
A vessel of water was kept on the ground below the
target and the suitor had to shoot at the fish by looking
at its ¡mage in the water.
It was an almost impossible task. But the kings and
princes were eager to compete, for each wanted to win
Draupadi. One by one they got up and went to the mighty
bow to try their luck. Many could not lift it. Some could
lift it but were unable to string it. The most famous among
them were able to lift the bow and string it but failed
to shoot at the fish.
There was disappointment on the face of King Drupada.
People looked at each other in dismay muttering that it
was an impossible feat.
Then Arjuna stood up from among the crowd of Brah¬
mins, and walked towards the bow. Everybody looked at
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The account of Rama's exile, for
example, contains many fine passages
of natural description, as when Rama
describes the season of the rains:
"See how much lovelier now the
[forests are,
green from the constant rain, and gay
[with dancing peacocks.
The roaring clouds, weary with loads
[of water,
rest on the peaks, escorted by the
[cranes,
which, flying in line, rejoicing in the
[clouds,
seem like a chain of lotuses, wind¬
blown across the sky.
Green grass and flowers cover the
[warm earth,
like a lady wrapped in a many-coloured
[blanket." (1)
Successive editors introduced mat¬
erial from many sources into the narra¬
tive of the Mahabharata, which, despite
its ascription to a single author, the
sage Vyasa, and its generally correct
Sanskrit, has something of the anony¬
mity of folk-literature about it. The
(J) Translated by the author.
Ramayana is also ascribed to a single
author, the sage Valmlki, who is intro¬
duced in the first and last of the poem's
seven cantos as a contemporary of
the hero, and as the protector of the
pregnant Sita when she is cast out by
her husband.
But the Ramayana is also clearly the
work of more than one author, though
its structure is not so bewilderingly
complex as that of the longer epic.
The style of the first and last cantos
is significantly different from that of
the central five. These five cantos can
stand alone as a complete story and
have no real need of the other two.
Except for a few obvious interpolations,
they treat Rama as a mortal hero,
whereas in the first and last cantos
he is wholly divine, the full Incarnation
of the great God Vishnu.
There are many other arguments
which prove with virtual certainty that
at least two and probably three hands
have contributed to the poem in its
final form. But the most important part
of the story is the work of one man,
a conscious poet far more sophisti¬
cated and sensitive than the nameless
composers of the Mahabharata.
Since a synopsis of the Ramayana
story occurs in the Mahabharata it
seems that the former was in existence
before the process of adding interpo¬
lations to the latter came to an end.
Nevertheless the Ramayana . seems
more recent than the Mahabharata nar¬
rative, and its central portion may have
been composed no later than about
the beginning of our era. The capital
city of the Kurus, Hastinapura, on
which the story of the Mahabharata
centres, is in the western part of the
Ganga basin, some fifty miles to the
north of modern Delhi (1). Ayodhya, the
capital of Rama, is in eastern Uttar
Pradesh, and the western part of the
sub-continent plays little part in the
Ramayana story.
In the Mahabharata the Deccan and
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
(1) Editor's note. The site of Hastinapura
has recently bean excavated. Romila Thapar
writes in A History of India, "a part of it was
found to have been washed away in about
800 B.C. by the flooding of the river Ganges.
This incident is referred to in the Puranas
as having occurred in the reign of the
seventh successor to the king ruling at
Hastinapura immediately after the [Maha¬
bharata] war, which would suggest c. 900
B C. as the approximate date for the war."
This extraordinary scene is only a tiny portion of a gigantic 160-foot
bas-relief at Angkor Wat recounting episodes from the Mahabharata.
It depicts the combat between the Pandavas
and the Kauravas (see also photo p. 19). The Mahabharata,
Gandhi wrote, demonstrates the futility of war, and the field of battle
is our own body: "To one who reads the spirit of the Gita (a part of
the Mahabharata) it teaches the spirit of non-violence,
the secret of realizing the self through the physical body."
him and wondered how a Brahmin dare attempt a feat
which was beyond all the heroic kings and princes. But
Arjuna confidently picked up the bow, stringed it, and
shot five arrows one after the other at the target. The
fish fell to the ground.
There was jubilation among the crowd.. Draupadi looked
at the splendid youth and garlanded him. Some of the
kings and princes did not like the idea of a Brahmin
winning the hand of a princess. They wanted to start a
fight but others said that the princess was fairly won.
Arjuna and his brothers went back to the potter's house
to tell their mother of the happy event. It was night when
they reached the house. Arjuna knocked at the door and
shouted to Kunti : "Mother, I have won a wonderful prize."
Kunti replied from inside : "Share it with all your brothers."
And then she came out and saw what the prize was. "My
sons", said Kunti, "I cannot take back what I have said and
so Draupadi shall be the wife of all." Draupadi became the
common wife of all the brothers.
King Drupada was not happy at the Swayamwara. He did
not know who the young man was.. Was he really a
Brahmin? Or was he somebody who was disguised as
a Brahmin? He wanted to find out. He sent a spy to
the potter's house. The spy returned and informed the
king that the Pandavas were not dead and it was Arjuna
who had won the hand of Draupadi.
Drupada was filled with joy. He sent messengers to Invite
the Pandavas to the palace but he did not tell them that
he knew their secret. When the Pendavas arrived clad in
the clothes of simple sadhus, the king received them with
great honour. He. requested them to tell him who they
really were. Dharmaputra then told Drupada the whole
story.
The news that the Pandavas were alive reached the
Kauravas. On the advice of Vidura, Bhishma, Drona and
other respected elders, King Dhritarashtra asked the Pan¬
davas to return home. The Pandavas and the Kauravas
then made, peace between themselves. They divided the
country into two parts, one half to be ruled by the Pan¬
davas and the other by the Kauravas.
The Pandavas set up their capital at Indraprastha and the
Kauravas at Hastinapura.
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
TWO GREAT EPICS (Continued)
Ramayana, a living ideal down the ages
10
the Dravidian south of India are little
mentioned, except in lists of places
and peoples which have obviously
been worked over in the course of the
centuries in which the epic developed.
In the Ramayana these regions, as well
as Ceylon, play an essential part in
the story, though they are looked on as
shadowy and wild lands, chiefly the
abode of demons and of monkeys
which talk and act like men.
The court of Dasaratha ¡n the
Ramayana ¡s that of a typical Hindu
ruler of classical times, not that of a
chieftain such as we meet in the
Mahabharata story, who is merely the
first among his unruly peers. Though
the Hindu tradition places Rama many
thousands of years before the heroes
of the Mahabharata, the Ramayana
reflects a much more developed phase
of Hindu culture than does the Maha¬
bharata narrative.
A strange and very tame version of
the story preserved in the traditions
of Theravada Buddhism suggests that
there actually was, sometime in the
centuries before Buddha's birth, a
king named Dasaratha whose righteous
son Rama was wrongly exiled but in
the end regained his birthright.
But the exciting account of the
capture of Sita by Ravana and her
ultimate rescue finds no place in the
Buddhist version, and this suggests
that the Ramayana, like so many heroic
tales of ancient and medieval times, is
a conflation from more than one
source, and that some of the most
dramatic parts of the finished story
had no place in the original tale. "It
is, like the Mahabharata, a legend,
not a piece of sober history, or even
the reflection of the historical process
of the Aryanlzation of the Deccan."
Much work has now been done ¡n
unravelling the skeins of medieval
European stories such as those of
the Nibelungenlied and the Chanson
de Roland, both of which have been
shown to have no reliable historical
content; and there is no reason why
the Indian epics should be more his¬
torically trustworthy than their Euro¬
pean counterparts. They are far more
than mere historical narratives; rather
they are among the greatest poems in
the world's literature, and as such they
have inspired countless millions of
people for some two thousand years.
The Ramayana has impressed itself
even more deeply than the Mahabha¬
rata upon the soul of Hindu India. It
has been translated, or more often
freely paraphrased, in almost every
Indian language, and in most of the
languages of South-East Asia. These
versions have adapted the story of
Rama to the local cultures, and made
it part of the local traditions. It has
been heard repeatedly by many gen¬
erations of illiterate peasants, who not
only have been thrilled by its stirring
and often touching story, but also have
been taught the virtues of love, fore-
bearance, obedience, courage and
truthfulness from ¡t.
Rama has long formed the ideal of
Hindu manhood, as Sita has of Hindu
womanhood. Rama is invariably obe¬
dient and respectful to his parents,
loving and protective towards Sita,
loyal and affectionate to his relatives
and friends, humbly reverent to gods,
priests and sages, benevolent and
gentle towards his subjects, just and
forgiving to his enemies. The obe¬
dience and deference which Sita shows
to her husband and her husband's
family know no bounds, but she pos¬
sesses Intense courage, and is ready
to stake her life in defence of her
virtue.
I
HE story of Rama has long
been part of the cultural tradition of
Buddhist Burma, Thailand and Cambo¬
dia. The Muslim Indonesians and
Malays, who imported the Ramayana
from India long before their conversion
to Islam, still delight in the ancient
Hindu story, adapted slightly to meet
the theological requirements of their
religion and the different cultural milieu
of the Southeast Asian archipelago.
The Muslim tradition of India and Pakis¬
tan, however, seems to have rejected
the ancient legends in their entirety,
though in the days of the Mughals Per¬
sian paraphrases of both epics were
made.
There can be no doubt that the
enduring popularity of the two epics
has been largely due to the fact that
both were adapted at a very early
period to the needs of Vaishnava Hin¬
duism. According to the orthodox
formulation Vishnu, the High God from
whom all creation sprang, has fully
incarnated himself nine times In mor¬
tal form for the salvation of the world,
and will Incarnate himself a tenth time
at the end of this aeon, in order to
restore the age of gold. Of the ten
incarnations of Vishnu those most
widely revered are Rama and Krishna,
the former the hero of the Ramayana
and the latter one of the main char¬
acters of the Mahabharata.
Thus the epics of India have become
holy books, forming a sort of New
Testament to the older, less directly
appealing, Vedic literature. Unlike the
Vedas, which were intended only for
the menfolk of the higher classes,
especially the brahmins, the epics
might be heard, read and learnt by
anyone, even by women, children and
untouchables. Thus their influence on
the religious life of India has been in
the long run far greater than that of
the Vedas and Upanishads.
The devotees of Krishna have
several other classical texts, notably
the Harivamsa and the Bhagavata
Purana, with which to sustain their
faith. On the other hand, for those
who prefer to worship God in the form
of Rama the Ramayana in its many
translations and paraphrases has
become a sort of Bible.
The Hindi Ramayan of Tulsi Das was
the only religious text to impress
Mahatma Gandhi in his boyhood, and
with his last breath he called upon
God by the name of Rama. Another
great source of his inspiration was
the Bhagavad-Gita, which forms part
of the Mahabharata.
Some Indians of later generations
may feel that many of the moral pre¬
cepts of both epics are hardly appli¬
cable to present conditions, and may
have doubts about the theology which
they reflect, but, whatever their future
as sources of religious inspiration,
these texts have so deeply affected
the heart of Hindu culture and are of
such high merit as literature that they
can never be forgotten.
The non-Hindu who wishes to
understand the culture of Hindu India
and the basic values and attitudes of
Hinduism cannot do better than read
these poems. From the point of view
of modern "western" taste, their lite¬
rary value may be enhanced by judi¬
cious abridgement.
It ¡s unfortunate that so far little has
been done to introduce the Indian
epics to the contemporary non-Indian
reader, for, though full translations of
both exist in English and several other
European languages, none of these
has been made in a style which con¬
veys to the twentieth-century reader
the forceful narrative of the Mahabha¬
rata or the subtle dialogue and fine
descriptive writing of the Ramayana.
Good abridged translations of both
poems in modern idiom are needed to
bring something of their grandeur and
beauty io a wider circle of readers,
in the lands where their stories are
not traditionally known.
DAMAYANTI THE BEAUTIFUL
Narratives of romance and tragedy,
well-springs of philosophy and moral
precepts, the epics of ancient India
are also works of splendid descriptive
poetry which with lyric sparkle
often evoke the charms of nature:
the grace and mysteries of
the world of animals and an
infinite variety of living, growing things.
Painters and sculptors of many lands
have thus found in them an unceasing
source of inspiration. This painting,
the work of an 18th-century artist,
illustrates a Persian translation of
the Mahabharata. It shows the beautiful'
Damayanti, who won the heart of the
gracious Prince Nala, resting in her
garden on a summer day. The story
of the trials and tribulations of
Damayanti and her lover is told in
one of the finest and best known
poems of the Mahabharata.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
THE COLLECTIVE
DREAM
OF A CONTINENT
by Anil de Silva
I
Co/our page
Top: Bhishma, in the Mahabharata
(centre figure) expiring on the field of
battle while Krishna, holding a lotus
flower, listens to his dying words. When
Bhishma asks for water, Arjuna shoots an
arrow into the earth and brings forth a
sparkling spring to quench Bhishma's thirst.
This 19th-century painting decorates a
Vishnuite manuscript of episodes from
the Mahabharata compiled in Kashmir.
Photo Paul Almasy © Private collection, Paris
Left: A 17th-century Persian illustration
(Mughal school) for a translation of the
Mahabharata. It depicts the combat
between the powerful Bhima and the
wicked Duryodhana on a bare hillside.
Dominating the scene are the
Gods of the Indian Pantheon, among them
Indra, God of the sky and storms
and Yama, God of the underworld.
Photo © Victoria and Albert Museum, London
Right: The Ramayana is rich in
descriptive passages that bring vividly to
life the landscapes of India in all their
seasonal change. In one of them an Indian
artist of the 17th-century may have
found inspiration for this charming
miniature showing Rama and Sita travelling
in their chariot through a luxuriant land.
Photo © Bibliothèque Nationale, Paris
he Ramayana and the
Mahabharata, though born in India,
belong to the "collective dream" of
all of South East Asia. The epics are
reborn at every age, their message
renewed, their forms changing as the
course of history changes, fructifying
and revififying and filling the human
spirit. They have charmed and
enchanted, inspired and exalted the
people of India and South Asia, form¬
ing the very foundation of their rich
and living culture.
The epics are history, myth and
folklore, and the ageless quality of
their appeal, the influence of the moral,
ethical and religious values they
contain have shaped the daily lives of
millions of men and women for gener¬
ations.
It has often been said that "what is
not in the Mahabharata is nowhere."
Mahatma Gandhi, who wrote at length
on the meaning and import of the two
great epic poems and translated the
Bhagavad-Gita (which is a part of the
Mahabharata) into his native Gujarati,
once said: "The Gita has become for
us a spiritual reference book. . . the
deeper you dive into it the richer the
meanings you get."
Later he wrote: "Early In childhood
I had felt the need of a scripture that
would serve as an unfailing guide
through the temptations of life. . .
I learned Sanskrit to enable me to
read the Gita. Today the Gita is not
only my Bible or my Koran it is my
Mother. I lost my earthly mother who
gave me birth long ago, but this
eternal mother has completely filled
her place by my side ever since. She
has never changed, she has never
failed. When I am in difficulty or dis¬
tress, I seek refuge in her bosom."
("Gita the Mother" by M.K. Gandhi.)
The Ramayana Is an epic poem of
love and beauty and tells the story of
the princely hero, Rama, who fights a
battle to bring back his kidnapped
wife, Sita, from the demon king of
Lanka (Ceylon). The Mahabharata is
the story of the Great Civil War which
rent India about 1,000 B.C., a terrible
fratricidal war between the Kauravas
and the Pandavas, the sons of two
brothers, and fought on the northern
plains of Kurukshetra, in the region of
Delhi.
Both epics were transmitted orally
for centuries before being written
down, but even today wandering mins¬
trels and baliad singers travel regularly
from village to village throughout India
and other countries of South Asia
reciting and singing the epics far into
the night under the stars. Indian work¬
ing-men, wearied with the toil of the
day, are capable of spending a whole
night seated in a circle round the fire
listening attentively to a drama of three
thousand years ago.
To the central themes of the Maha¬
bharata and Ramayana have been
grafted a multitude of subsidiary stories
to illustrate the central themes. Their
heroes find prominent mention in the
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
ANIL DE SILVA of Ceylon has spent many
years of study on the art and literature of
India and Asia. She is the author of "The
Life of Buddha" (Phaidon Press, London,
1957) and "Chinese Landscape Paintings
in the Tun-Huang Caves" (Methuen and
Co., London; Crown Publishers, New York),
both of which have appeared in several
language editions. Her latest book, "India:
Conquest and Freedom" (New York Graphic
Society) will appear shortly. Anil de Silva
is co-editor with Prof. Otto von Simson "j Q
of "Man Through His Art", the series of | \J
art albums sponsored by the World Con¬
federation of Organizations of the Teaching
Profession with Unesco aid.
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
COLLECTIVE DREAM (Continued)
Endless variations on a theme
Indian and South Asian literature of all
ages from the fifth century onwards.
Both epics constitute a veritable
treasure-house of Indian and South
Asian lore, both secular and religious,
and give as do no other single works
an insight into the innermost depths of
the soul of the people. Both works
are great as a collection of stories,
great as epic poems describing in
magnificent language various emotions
and events, great as manuals of law
and morality, great as a record of
social' and political philosophy, and
great as sacred treatises pointing the
way to an understanding of the
supreme ends of life.
Hajime Nakamura, Professor of
Philosophy and Religion at Tokyo Uni¬
versity has written: "In the epics of
Mahabharata and Ramayana the typical
heroes of India are not national heroes
in the sense of any national and racial
consciousness, which they, as well as
their authors, lacked. Ancient Indians
preached as a virtue the offering of
one's property, even one's life if neces¬
sary, for the sake of others' happiness.
But they were never taught self-sacri¬
fice for a particular nation or race.
The concept of the national hero in
our sense did not appear in Indian
history." (1)
T
14
HE numerous variant tales
incorporated into the main story of the
Mahabharata are mainly related when
the Pandavas are exiled into the forest
after Yudhishthira loses his kingdom
in a game of dice. Many sages come
to visit them there and recount stories
and legends of the past. Over the
centuries, many of these tales have
been taken up again by hundreds upon
hundreds of writers,, rewritten and
modified, and used for plays and stor¬
ies and poems.
Among the most Important works
inspired by the Mahabharata was
that written in the 5th century by the
Sanskrit poet, Kalidasa, undoubtedly
the greatest poet dramatist of India's
Classical Age, and often referred to
as the "Indian Shakespeare." The
play, called Abhijnana-Shakuntalam,
relates a love intrigue in the king's
harem (first translation into English in
1789). The verses are simply enchant¬
ing. Goethe wrote about It, "flowers
and fruit, all that delights and all that
sustains, all heaven and all earth, are
expressed In the name of Shakuntala."
Another play inspired by the Maha¬
bharata was written by Rablndranath
Tagore for his famous Chitra. It takes
(1) "Ways of Thinking of Eastern Peoples"
by Hajime Nakamura, edited by Philip
P. Wiener (East-West Center Press, Honolulu,
Hawaii, 1964). Originally published by the
Japanese National Commission for Unesco
in 1960.
as its theme an episode about Arjuna,
the great hero of the Pandava brothers
clan. The play ¡s located in Assam
where Arjuna is said to have stayed
for some time.
There are uncounted versions of
the Ramayana. Every language of
India has its own Ramayana. The
three most famous Indian versions,
however, are the Sanskrit, attributed
to Valmiki and written about 300 B.C.;
the sixteenth century Hindi version by
Tulsi Das; and the ninth century
Tamil classic by Kamban.
Perhaps the most beautiful rendering
into English is the Ayodhya Canto of
the Kamban version, the most dramatic
part of the Ramayana, translated by
C. Rajagopalachari, and published in
1961 in the Unesco Collection of
Representative Works (a chapter of the
poem is given on page 30). Tulsi
Das's version has also been translated
into English by F.R. Allchin In the same
Unesco Collection under the title
Kavitavali (both books by George Allen
& Unwin Ltd, London). It contains
some of the poet's most highly
personal and profound expressions of
devotion to Rama.
- ~Valmiki's Sanskrit poem Is filled
with lyrical descriptions of Nature.
Rama and Lakshmana are tricked into
leaving Sita unprotected in the forest
and when they return they find her
vanished. She has been kidnapped
by Ravana. Rama, in his despair, runs
madly from thicket to thicket calling
Sita's name. In each ray of sunlight,
in each golden flower, he thinks he
recognizes her yellow robe.
Invoking the trees he cries: "Sweet
Kadambara, have you seen my fair
one? Speak, Basil, you must know,
for her limbs are like your graceful
branches	 Sweet Tila, fairest of
all, where is she who loved your
flowers? Gentle deer, has she played
with you? Is your moon-faced friend
hiding behind some tree? Have pity.
Speak to me	 Where are her soft
limbs, her moon bright face, her
shapely neck, her red lips..." (2) and
Rama throws himself upon the bare
earth in despair.
Later, wandering in the forest, Rama
and Lakshmana come to the grove by
the Pampa Lake. It ¡s Spring and
"Rama and Laskhmana bathe in the
crystal waters of the Pampa ablaze
with white and red lotus buds. The
trees are proudly crowned with flowers
along the banks and long creepers
fall from them laden with blossoms.
Screaming parrots make shrill music
and Rama feels his whole being filled
with langorous desire for Sita.
(2) This and the following quotations from
Valmiki's "Ramayana" come from an
unpublished adaptation of the "Ramayana" by
Anil de Silva and Lilian Lassen.
One of the dramatic episodes in the Ramayana is the abduction by Ravana, the
demon-king of Ceylon, of Sita, wife of Rama exiled in the forest. Rama is lured
into the forest in pursuit of a deer (a demon in disguise), and his brother Lakshmana,
guarding Sita, is tricked into leaving her. Ravana then appears, sweeps Sita
off in his aerial chariot, as seen in painting below. A great vulture, Jatayu, tries
to rescue her and though mortally wounded lives long enough to tell Rama of
Sita's abduction. Jatayu's combat with Ravana is depicted in this
miniature from the Punjab Hills school of painting, dating from about 1765.
Q
S
z
Ë
3
CD
CO
5
>-^"--^--' ¿\
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Photo Indian Tourist Office
THE FESTIVAL
OF DUSSERAH
Photo © Holmes-Lebel - R.J. Chlnwalla
The three colossal
figures dwarfing the
ordinary mortals at their
feet (above) are
pasteboard effigies of the
principal demons of the
Ramayana ten-headed
Ravana (centre) flanked
by Meghdana and
Khumbhakarna. They
figure in the celebration
of the Indian festival
of Dusserah. After
celebrations dedicated to
the Goddess Durga who
helped Rama against
Ravana, giant
effigies, like those above
erected in a northern
Indian city, meet a fiery
fate when flaming arrows
shot by Rama ignite
explosives packed inside
them. Right, putting last
touches to a figure's head.
"Look, brother, the Kakila birds
mock me with their joyful notes and
the yellow clusters of the cassias
awake my longing for Sita; the Mango
tree, breaking into flower, is like a
gaily dressed lover; the wild cock
calls to his mate near the waterfall,
my darling heard his shrill notes at
dawn one day in our cottage. From
tree to tree each bird seeks his mate,
filling the air with their triumph and the
call of the Spring is unbearable. My
eyes are tortured for a sight of Sita.
"Amid the bamboo thickets the pea¬
cock dances In frantic glee, his tail
glowing like a jewelled window in the
sun; the peahen answers her mate in
his amorous dance and he pursues her
through the tangled grass, no demon
has robbed him of his lovel Look,
Lakshmana, at this butterfly whose
wings are covered with the golden
pollen of the flowers he has kissed.
In this month the cup of my widowed
grief is full. I cannot bear the loss of
her, the long sleepless nights without
her.
"Somewhere under alien skies it
must be Spring too, and my imprisoned
love mourns for me. My spirit knows
she can never live without me. Every
gentle breeze that stirs the blossoms
on the trees fans the fury of my
desires	 Where are you, Sita,
my fawn-eyed love?" Rama wanders
through the wood calling desperately
for his lost love.
T
HE ardent zest for nature
seen in these extracts goes back to a
continuous tradition and is the supreme
expression of an essentially Indian
experience. All nature's exuberance,
the cries of the Kokila, the wind, the
sun, the moon, the heat, the ralnclouds,
the Mango trees, the bee, the vine,
the curve of a pitcher, the dark Indigo-
starred sky at night, all are caressed
by the poet and nature's vitality
expresses and symbolizes love, here
expressed by Rama for Sita. The
especial place the Ramayana holds In
the hearts of the people of India and
South Asia is due mainly to the purity
of the hero and heroine who incarnate
the ideals of conjugal love and fidelity.
How revealing is this description of
Sita as a prisoner: "Ravana woke to
a new day to the strains of music as
the solemn hymn of praise to the dawn
was sung. The thought of Sita came
to his heart, he could not control the
passion that absorbed his soul.
Laying aside his bow and arrow, he
put on a spotless white robe embroi¬
dered with flowers and gold and
entered the Asoka grove impatient to
see her. A sudden fear and trembling
took hold of Sita when she saw Ravana
in his pride; she folded her arms'over
her breasts trying to screen their
beauty from his bold and amorous
glances. She lay prone like a severed
branch on the earth, her thoughts flying
to Rama to give her courage."
Valmiki's Ramayana has Ravana as
the villain, but In South India and the
15
CONTINUED ON PAGE 17
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
HANUMAN,
LEADER OF THE MONKEYS
BELOVED BY MILLIONS
Animals occupy a leading place in the
Indian epics, notably in the Ramayana
in which they are treated as humans and
often deified. Monkeys are a symbol of
fidelity, and the loyalty shown to Rama
by Hanuman is proverbial. Right,
a painting of Hanuman with Rama
and Sita in his heart, an example of
the Kalighat "pop" art which bazaar
artists of Kalighat, Calcutta began
to produce early in the 19th-century
for mass sale to pilgrims who thronged
the Kalighat temple. It has been
claimed that Kalighat painting
"anticipated by a century or more
cubism and impressionism."
Photo courtesy Victoria
and Albert Museum, London
Hunaman is widely worshipped in South Asia. In memory of his
services to Rama, monkeys are held sacred. In Indian cities
they boldly roam about streets and public parks. Here a playful
monkey tests a bell at Temple of Monkeys in Calcutta,
as a stoic stone lion chews his tail.
Photo © Tony Saulnier, Paris
l'/ÍWw^V"- EMI
= p-J-i £ % i
k v^r \±i
H
ANUMAN was the most
powerful of the monkey chiefs. Hanu-
man's loyalty to Rama has become
proverbial, and he is held up as the
symbol of faithfulness and self-
surrender.
When Rama on his return to Ayo-
dhya asked Hanuman what boon he
desired as a reward for his great
service, the faithful monkey only asked
for permission to live so long as the
story of Rama would be told in this
world. The boon was granted and it
is believed that Hanuman still lives in
some inaccessible mountain.
In the "Mahabharata" is an interest¬
ing account of a meeting between
Hanuman and his half-brother Bhima
(Bhima was born of Kunti by the
power of Pavana, the wind-god).
After Rama's death, Hanuman was
living in a mountain fastness spending
his days in contemplation of his great
master. Bhima, in his search for a
mythical flower Draupadi wished to
possess, happened to pass this forest
and saw an old monkey sleeping
across his path. He haughtily asked
the monkey to get out of his way.
The monkey wished to know who
he was. Bhima gave a boastful
account of himself and the greatness
of the Pandava heroes; upon this, the
monkey asked him how such wonder¬
ful people happened to wander in the
forests without a kingdom and how the
beloved wife of such heroes was
suffered to be insulted by Duryodana.
Bhima disdained to make answer but
asked the monkey to clear the road.
The monkey said that he was ailing
and requested Bhima to step across
him. But Bhima would not do this
because, he said, of his respect for
his brother Hanuman who was a mon¬
key. Nor would he pass him by the
head side.
After some argument Bhima agreed
to pass by the tailside, but as he
started to pass the tail this appendage
of the monkey began to lengthen.
After walking along the tail for about
- .mi. "'iiiMimpiimn um
. L
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
COLLECTIVE DREAM (Continued)
Ramasymbol of love and chivalry
a league Bhima decided to lift it up
with his club, which weapon, however,
broke in the attempt.
Now the Pandava knew he was deal¬
ing with no ordinary ape and he came
back to Hanuman and asked him
respectfully who he was. Hanuman
smiled and disclosed his identity. He
entertained Bhima with many tales of
ancient days, and described to him the
feats performed by the monkeys in the
"Ramayana" battle.
Bhima requested Hanuman to show
him the form he had assumed for
jumping over to Lanka. Hanuman now
stood up and began to increase in
size; but before he reached his full
stature Bhima got frightened of the
enormity of the form, fainted and fell
down. Hanuman assumed a smaller
size, revived his brother, gave him
directions as to how to get the flower
he was seeking and sent him on his
adventurous task.
Hanuman was famous not only for
his physical strength but also for his
learning. "The chief of the monkeys,"
says the "Ramayana", "is perfect : no
one equals him in the Shastras, in
learning, and in ascertaining the sense
of scriptures. In all sciences, in the
rules of austerity, he rivals the pre¬
ceptor of the gods."
Hanuman is widely worshipped in
India. In memory of his services to
Rama, monkeys are held sacred. In
many Indian cities they boldly roam
about streets and public parks.
From: "Epics. Myths and Legends of India"
by P. Thomas. Copyright held by D.B. Tara-
porevala Sons & C°. Bombay, India.
Jain versions, Ravana is the great
tragic figure for his love for Sita
carries with it his own death; he
catches our imagination and the idea
that his passion bears its inevitable
disaster follows the spirit of Greek
tragedy.
The main school of Jain poetry
follows the poet Vimalasuri (whose
Sanskrit version was written round
the first or second century A.D.) and
probably contains one of the richest
Ramite literatures to be found in Sans¬
krit, Kanerese and in the dialects.
Vimalasuri makes Ravana beautiful:
"Shining, dark brown body, his face
like a full-blown lotus, large chested,
powerful long arms, waist slender and
hips like that of a lion, thighs like the
trunk .of an elephant. . . ."
The first non-Indian version of the
Ramayana was produced in Chinese
and dates from about the fifth century.
In Tibet, Nepal and Chinese Turkestan
local versions appear to be well known
from about 700 A.D. In Cambodia an
inscription dated 600 A.D. tells that a
sage presented the Ramayana to a
temple and made arrangements for its
recitation. We know that in the tenth
century a Sanskrit scholar expounded
both epics at the Cambodian court.
By the seventh century the epics
were known in Assam, Thailand and
Laos. Ayuthia the ancient capital of
Thailand was named after Ayodhya, the
capital of the kingdom of Rama. Indo¬
nesian versions, mainly based on very
early Indian variants, are depicted in
the shadow plays and in bas-reliefs of
the temples of Panataran and Pramba-
nan. In the Javanese versions of the
Ramayana only the bare bones of the
Indian version have been retained, the
rest being the incorporation of tradi¬
tional Javanese legends. The Mughal
Emperor Akbar had the Ramayana
translated Into Persian during the six¬
teenth century, produced with mag¬
nificent miniatures (see colour photos
of some Persian miniatures, pp. 11, 12).
There Is no part of India or Ceylon
unconcerned in some way with. either
one of the epics, and thousands go
on yearly pilgrimages to Ramesvaram,
the southernmost tip of the sub-conti¬
nent, where Rama and the army of
monkeys stopped before crossing over
to Lanka to rescue Sita. And in
Ceylon Itself, Sita Eliya is said to be
the Asbka Grove where Sita was kept
prisoner.
The great Indian festivals of Dus-
serah,' Divali and Navrati are linked
with the Ramayana, while others are
associated with Krishna, a god-hero of
the Mahabharata. Divali, the festival of
lights, is concerned with the return of
Rama to his kingdom. Every house,
cottage and hut burns its little oil
lamps in célébration; painted clay
images of all the characters are made,
and all homes are open to guests on
that day (see "Unesco Courier", April
1963).
The Ramayana has a special place
in India and South Asia because of
the purity of Rama and Sita and their
love symbolizing fidelity. The ideal
of chivalry in the epic corresponds to
that of Europe in the Middle Ages,
for Rama is the protector of the
oppressed, of widows and orphans; he
is the perfect knight valiant ¡n face
of danger, protective and tender to
all women while loving Sita alone.
Many scholars have frequently
found comparisons between Homer's
Iliad and the Ramayana for they share
the basic plot of a husband who goes
forth to battle to rescue a kidnapped
wife; and the story of Jatayu, the
vulture, whose brother burnt his wings
on going too near the sun recalls the
Greek myth of Icarus.
Many other characters in the, Greek
and Indian epics have points in
common: Agamemnon and the monkey
king Sugriva, Hector and Indrajit, the
son of Ravana who abducted Sita,
Nestor and Hanuman. Other details
recall the Bible: Hanuman and Joshua
both order the sun to stop in Its
course; and Hanuman, like Jonah,
enters the mouth of a sea monster.
ANY of the folk tales found
in the Mahabharata and translated dur¬
ing the Middle Ages have become part
of the legends and stories of many
European and African countries. In the
seventeenth century, the Bhagavad-
Gita and other Indian texts were trans¬
lated Into European languages and
influenced many European and Ameri¬
can thinkers and philosophers, writers
and artists: Beethoven, Schopenhauer,
Emerson, Freud, Thoreau, Whitman,
Rodin, and in more recent times, the
Irish poet Yeats and Aldous Huxley
among others. Goethe borrowed an
Indian stage convention from Kalida-
sa's drama Shakuntala (which had
been translated Into German) for his
own prologue to Faust.
The extraordinary richness of the
two epics accounts for the unbounded
popularity they have enjoyed for cen¬
turies in India and South Asia and the
joy and pleasure they continue to
afford to millions today. Although the
epics deal with mythical beings, ani¬
mals, demons, gods and men, all these
characters endear themselves to us;
they are never all bad or all good.
Whether these figures from the remote
past come from the epics of Vyasa
or Valmiki "they are the everlasting
oracles of life; they have to be ques¬
tioned anew with every age, each age ^
approaching them with Its own variety 1 7
of understanding. ... to learn, to evoke
fresh speech from them and under¬
stand that speech."
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
THE EPICS IN THE
ART OF SOUTH ASIA
by B.N. Coswamy
0
18
n the walls of countless
Indian homes today hang inexpensive
prints with illustrations of Rama sub¬
duing the ocean, or Krishna deliver¬
ing his celebrated sermon to Arjuna
on the battlefield of Kurukshetra, and
before them the householders offer
dally worship, much as they repair
with devotion to the crowded open
air grounds where the traditional
festivals and the ritual dance, the
Ramalila, are annually performed.
In the Himalayan hill district of
Chamba, young girls patiently embroi¬
der scenes from the Mahabharata on
muslin pieces which they will take
with them as dowry at the time of
their wedding. The heroic figures of
Arjuna and Bhima and Kunti move
about, with the same agility with which
they did several hundred years ago,
in the Indonesian shadow theatre, the
Wayang-Purwa. In Thailand the ancient
masked play, the Khon, still relies
principally on themes from the story
of Rama.
All this adds up to the marvellous
phenomenon of not merely the survi¬
val of the two great Indian epics, the
Ramayana and the Mahabharata, as
vital elements in living cultures, but
also of the arts, at least those among
them which are folk-based, continuing
to find inspiration in themes that come
from across several centuries.
The epics run like a thread through
time and space. In our time and day
the emotion may be wearing a little
thin, but the social and moral values
enshrined in these stories still sustain
vast multitudes.
B. N. GOSWAMY is a world authority on
Indian and Asian art. Professor of Art
History, department of Fine Arts, Panjab
University, Chandigarh, India, he is the
author of many studies on Indian art, includ¬
ing "Glimpses of Mughal Architecture"
(Bengal Govt., Calcutta, 1953); "Designs of
Orissa Temples" (Thacker and Co., Cal¬
cutta, 1950) and "Indian Temple Sculpture"
(Lalit Kala Akademy, Delhi, 1956).
It was quite natural for the sculp¬
tors and painters of South Asia to
have turned to works which were so
interwoven with life and affected so
profoundly the minds and the spirit of
generations of men and women. But
they turned to them also because it
was meritorious, conducive to dhar-
ma (1) and emancipation, to treat of
Gods and their deeds; and again
because in them they found a treasure
of heroic tales that could be told with
love and care.
The Ramayana has a wonderfully
rich narrative in itself, while the Maha¬
bharata is a veritable encyclopaedia.
The epics are everywhere in the
art of India and South-East Asia. So
enormous, in fact, is the body of works
of art devoted to themes from the
Ramayana and the Mahabharata, that
one can hope only to treat briefly of
the most significant among them.
It is difficult to speak with certainty
of the exact period the earliest repre¬
sentations of the Ramayana or the
Mahabharata in the arts belong to,
for -much has been claimed by time.
But they appear to come from the very
beginning of the time when Hindu
themes started finding consistent
expression at the hands of the Indian
sculptor.
The artist of the Gupta age (320-
600 A.D.), the classical period of
Indian history, turned his attention
alike to Buddhist and Hindu themes,
and an early, fifth-century relief from
the Garhwal region, a beautifully realiz¬
ed treatment of the battle between
Bhima and Jarasandha, ushers us
into a period of great achievement.
It is to this period that that chaste
monument, the Gupta temple of Deo-
garh in Central India, belongs. Of this
gem of Hindu architecture, popularly
called the Dasavatara temple with
(1) A word used in all the Indian languages
with a rich connotation of duty, right conduct,
justice, order, natural, and essential quality.
reference to the ten incarnations of
Vishnu to whom the shrine is dedi¬
cated, the entire basement was once
decorated » with a continuous frieze
representing events from the Ra¬
mayana.
Only a small fragment of this
sculptured frieze has survived, but
what exists is deeply moving. In these
reliefs is mirrored the classical Gupta
ideal of balance and harmony. The
voluptuous grace of the figures, the
quality of movement in the composi¬
tions, do not interfere in the slightest
with the tone of noble restraint which
characterizes the art of this period.
The sculptor appears to be In com¬
plete command both of his material
and his emotion, and whether he is
showing the deliverance of Ahalya
(turned to stone by her husband for
being unfaithful) when Rama's feet
touched her, or Rama, Lakshmana and
Sita leading a life of contented aus¬
terity in the forest, there is a quality
of quiet sweetness In his art. There
is no effusion, no overstatement.
The same grace and refinement
belong to the work of the Pallava
sculptors of the South, but to these
are added a new quality of dynamism.
Thirty-five miles south of Madras, at
Mahabalipuram, stand the remarkable
seventh-century rock-cut temples nam¬
ed after the Pandava heroes of the
Mahabharata; but what towers above
everything else here is the massive
granite boulder on the sea-shore that
presents a marvellous aspect of ener¬
gy and Imagination.
The entire face of this enormous
piece of living rock has been carved
to represent a scene of epic grandeur.
The theme ¡s a matter of some con¬
troversy among scholars, but whether
it ¡s the Descent of the Ganges
from Heaven, or the story of Arjuna's
penance, the source of the episode is
the Mahabharata.
The familiar figures of the heroes
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Carved into the stone of Angkor Wat,
this scene from the Mahabharata is
an outstanding example of the
monumental Khmer sculpture of
Cambodia which attained its apogee
in the first half of the 12th century. In
top centre of this carving lies Bhishma,
chief of the Kaurava clan, mortally
wounded by the arrows of Arjuna,
chief of the Pandavas.
do not appear here, for the story is
not an integral part of the narrative
of the epic, but a whole age is evok¬
ed while all the creatures of the world
range on either side of the Ganges
in gratitude for this miraculous gift to
the Indian world.
It is a little difficult to form an ade¬
quate Idea of the dimensions of this
great piece of sculpture and the
impression It makes, for no photograph
can easily convey this, but some idea
of the scale can be formed from the
fact that scores of figures of men
and animals, including a family of ele¬
phants, are represented here in life
size.
This vast, energetic composition,
suggestive of the magnificent quality
of the myth, is not confined by any
frame or line, but flows over the whole
surface of the boulder. Benjamin
Rawland has said: "Just as the space
of the relief Is untrammelled and,
indeed, seems to flow into the space
occupied by the spectator, so the
individual forms in ¡t are only partially
disengaged from the stone which
imprisons them. One has the
impression, indeed, that they are in
continual process of emergence from
the substance of the rock itself."
This seemingly is the age of great,
dynamic conceptions in the art of
India, one of the finest hours of crea¬
tive expression in human history. . And
the great rock-cut, eighth-century
Kailasanath temple at Ellora, near
Bombay, fits naturally into this age.
This enormous monolithic temple,
cut out of the rock, is dedicated to
Shiva after whose home, the sacred
mountain Kailasa, it Is named. But
this association with Shiva is no bar
in the mind of the Indian sculptor
against the representation of non-
Shivaite themes in the temple. There
are in fact numerous episodes from the
Ramayana that are carved in relief on
the walls of the temple and the smaller
sancturies that form a part of the
entire complex.
The mood here is dramatic and
scenes of remarkable liveliness unfold
themselves before the eye of the
spectator who becomes gradually a
Photo © Luc Ionesco, Paris
participant In the drama. Among the
most impressive scenes is one which
shows the abduction of Sita, the
heroine of the Ramayana, by the
demon-King, Ravana of Lanka. The
moment chosen by the sculptor is that
in which Ravana is fleeing with Sita
on a chariot towards his kingdom in
Lanka, and his way is barred by the
vulture-king, Jatayu.
The relief depicting this is an un¬
believably fine realization of dramatic
posture in sculpture. The figure of
Sita is mutilated, but the demon-king
powerfully breaks free from the simple
background of the composition, a
menacing figure, twisting around
angrily to deal with the bird that
vainly pecks at him.
The most dramatic and the most
monumental of reliefs at Ellora, how¬
ever, is Ravana shaking Mount Kailasa.
This is an illustration of the episode
in the Ramayana where Ravana
attempts to shake and uproot the
sacred mountain on which Shiva and
Parvati are seated, in order to use
it as a weapon in the great war
against Rama, and to destroy the
power of Shiva (see photo page 2).
The Ellora tableau it is difficult to
simply call ¡t a relief shows Ravana,
imprisoned in the foundations of the
19
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
20
ART OF SOUTH ASIA (Continued)
mountain, "in a cavern almost of Sty¬
gian gloom", straining his manifold
arms to shake the mountain with one
superhuman endeavour. The body of
the demon-king dissolves into the dark
recess, as his arms in the half light
seem actually to move and throb with
life.
In the upper part of the composi¬
tion, however, everything ¡s calm, for
Shiva with supreme effortlessness
simply stretches one of his toes to
press the mountain down with it. The
panic of the fleeing figures, the intui¬
tive fright of Parvati, as she leans to
seek support from her Lord as the
mountain trembles, are all ¡n mar¬
vellous contrast with the unruffled
serenity of the posture of Shiva.
The total effect ¡s indescribable for
this is one gigantic theatrical tableau
which sweeps the spectator off his
feet. Depth and darkness invest the
entire scene with a remarkable emo¬
tional and psychological suggestive-
ness. We here have one of the most
dramatic compositions in the entire
history of art.
With this monument, it is almost as
if the last great statement of an epic
theme, at least as far as sculpture in
India is concerned, has been made.
There is much that follows, but in
themes from the Ramayana and the
Mahabharata treated ¡n various periods
and schools of art, there is a certain
loss m intensity of feeling. The vision
falters a little. The interest in fact
shifts now to a distant region, the
lands of South-East Asia.
Indian settlements from a time going
back to the beginning of the Christian
era are known in these parts, but the
great periods of art date from the
seventh century onwards, when there
is evidence of Indian culture being
firmly rooted there. There is an enor¬
mous amount of artistic and construc¬
tion activity. The most impressive
monuments of Buddhism and Hinduism
alike are not in India, but in South-
East Asia.
With the institution of religious pil¬
grimages in the seventh and eighth
centuries, great complexes of temples
rose on the Dleng plateau in Middle
Java, the majority of them dedicated
to Vishnu. To this period also belongs
that supreme monument of mystic
Buddhism, the stupa of Borobudur,
rivalled by the great Hindu temple,
the ninth-century Chandi Loro Jong-
rang near Prambanam in Java.
This latter monument ¡s profusely
decorated with sculptures, the finest
of the carvings illustrating the earlier
part of the Ramayana. These run in
a continuous frieze on the exterior of
the balustrade of the upper terrace
of the temple of Shiva, and their
continuation was probably to be found
on the corresponding terrace of the
now ruined Brahma shrine on the right.
The style of these reliefs at Pram¬
banam, as indeed of the beautiful
reliefs of the great stupa at Boro¬
budur, which are perhaps even
CONTINUED ON PAGE 29
Colour pages
THE GRANDEUR OF MAHABALIPURAM (Page 21)
At Mahabalipuram, 35 miles south of Madras, near a group of
temples dedicated to Draupadi and the Pandava heroes of
the Mahabharata, a massive granite boulder dominates the
sea-shore. With its entire face carved to represent a scene
of .epic grandeur, filled with gods, winged figures, water-sprites
and animals of all kinds (like those in this photo), the mighty
rock (90 ft. by 20 ft.) is a monumental record of sculptural
art in 7th-century India. Its theme, the subject of some con¬
troversy, has been variously identified as "The Descent of the
Ganges" or "The Story of Arjuna's Penance".
THE SIEGE OF LANKA (Pages 22-23)
This striking painting (22 in. by 33) by an artist of the Punjab
Hills, northern India, dates from 1720. It portrays an
episode from the Ramayana: in the gardens of his palace on
the island of Lanka (Ceylon), Ravana tries in vain to seduce his
captive, the beautiful Sita. Aided by a huge army of monkeys,
Rama lays siege to Lanka and slays Ravana after a terrible hand-
to-hand combat. Two centuries ago the Punjab Hills, and notably
the small mountain kingdom of Guler, became a great centre of miniature painting
in India, many of whose works were inspired by themes from the Ramayana and
the Mahabharata. This painting is now in the Cleveland Museum of Art (gift of
George P. Bickford).
Photo © Cleveland Museum of Art,
courtesy Asia Society, New York
RAMA THE FAMOUS (pages 24-25)
For many centuries Cambodia's theatri¬
cal art has drawn much of its classical
repertory from the Ramayana, which is
known to the Cambodians as the Rama-
kerti, or "Rama the Famous". The ballet
composed of scenes from the epic mimed
by actor-dancers is a magnificent and
ever-popular spectacle. These photos were
taken during a recent performance by the
corps de ballet of the royal palace at
3 M Phnom Penh, capital of Cambodia. The
different characters are easily distinguishable by their ornate masks and glitter¬
ing costumes. (1) In a combat between monkeys, the valiant Hanuman, ally of
Rama, is masked and dressed in white. (3) Discovering Sita imprisoned in Rava-
na's palace, Hanuman tells her that she will soon be freed by Rama. (2) Garuda,
half-man half bird, the powerful charger of the God Vishnu. Garuda aided Rama in
the battle to deliver Sita.
TRIUMPH OF GOOD OVER EVIL (page 26)
Rama's combat with Ravana is the dramatic climax of this
scene from a ballet given in the royal palace at Phnom Penh
(Cambodia). Symbolizing the triumph of good over evil, Rama
brandishes his bow and with the aid of his ally, Hanuman
the monkey, subdues his adversary. Here, a woman dancer
takes the role of Rama. Formerly the entire corps de ballet
was composed of Khmer women dancers. Nowadays the
roles of the monkeys in the Ramayana are taken by men
while men and women alternate in the role of the masked
Ravana during the same performance.
THAILAND'S MASKED DANCE (page 27)
One of the most ancient forms of theatrical art in Thailand is
the masked pantomime performed by richly costumed dancers.
This scene re-enacts the struggle between Rama and Ravana.
In. the dance-dramas of Thailand, as in those of Cambodia and
Laos, Ravana wears a high pointed headdress and Hanuman
a white mask. The Thai title of this mask-play, Rama Kien,
signifies "Rama, the Famous".
^^m^mm* DANCE OF THE MONKEYS (page 27)
On the island of Bali (Indonesia) a unique dance-drama,
the "ketjak" or "dance of the monkeys", presents episodes
from the Ramayana. It is performed by 150 village men who
sit in circles around a great wooden torch, swaying in rhythm
as they chant. From time to time the figure of a narrator
rises above the swaying chorus and in tones alternately
plaintive and forceful recites the theme of the epic, recalling
the deeds of heroes at grips with demons Often the monotonous melodic chant is
broken by imitations of the jabbering, squeaking and chattering of the army of monkeys
in the Ramayana. The wandering voices, wailing cries and swaying gesticulating
figures all combine to enhance the exorcistic character of the dance. It was in fact
once used as an incantation to ward off evil forces from the village.
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
I
tftlifa
t -a' if a j ' «* > ^¿J2r i \ *W / C v s Z? \ *f
Sr-'Jh' '* /* I ¿ i - »i - ,,. ..- \ AS^a, '-«HVrtA
6ri/^
'ïlh
mmmm
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
W\¿
v>w4
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
*à
*%
¿v.
-" t-^ .
53feS
» r. .
.:;*Z«xr?-
.y, -.
* .r
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
if. tí'
<
; - í~ -< - j. .. vvi . . -
tri
1 1
i y AT'
F[*1 H
,
"^t'p?
üfe$ä3£8S&£
1
5Vîft»-\*i3^
.^N*inir§S^^(
M
afèfe^
¡
> *-*%
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
^
^flJ.
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
ART OF SOUTH ASIA (Continued from page 20)
One of the supreme arts of all time
superior, goes back clearly to the
Gupta reliefs at Deogarh. There is the
same quality of noble restraint in the
work. There is drama here, and much
movement.
Panel after panel Illustrates that
part of the Ramayana where Rama is
a witness to and a participant in the
fight between the monkey-kings, Su-
griva and Bali, and in these there is
an extraordinary animation, but the
emotion is again controlled. With
suavity and grace, the Javanese
sculptor makes his statements, always
employing economy but always suc¬
ceeding in evoking the feeling inherent
in the epic episodes.
We become witnesses to the divine
power of Rama as he bends his bow
with a movement of marvellous rhythm
to conquer the Ocean; we participate
in the struggle between good and
evil as the monkey-kings grapple in
their death struggle and Rama shoots
his arrow from behind seven trees.
Everything here is vitally alive.
The Indian models that so obviously
provided the inspiration for the work
in Java, lay also at the base of the
great periods of art from the first to
the seventh century in Cambodia. But
the styles change rapidly after the
upheaval of the eighth century and
the Khmer period of art In Cambodia
begins.
The relatively subordinate position
occupied by sculpture In the architec¬
tural monuments of the pre-Khmer
period also changes and we enter
upon a period of, increased sculptural
ornament that leads, step by step, to
the final explosive, Baroque style of
the last period.
The quiet note of early sculptures
like those at Sambor is left behind
INDONESIA'S WAYANG
SHADOW THEATRE
The name "shadow theatre" is inseparably
linked with Indonesia and its culture.
Here, the word "wayang" (literally,
"shadow"), identifies the flat, leather-carved
rod puppets whose shadows are projected
on to a screen. A form of entertainment
as popular as the cinema in Western
countries, the shadow theatre is a superb
medium for storytelling and has captivated
untold generations with its presentations
of ancient tales, bringing to life great
epics such as the Mahabharata and the
Ramayana. The Wayang theatre, which
is believed to have originated in India,
is also found in Malaysia, Thailand and
Cambodia (see page 34), and in parts of
southern India. The smallest of the
Indonesian puppets is about 9 inches high,
the tallest sometimes close to 40. A full
set of puppets may number 300 to 400
characters, each made according to strict
rules of iconography and all easily
recognizable. Left, episode from the
Mahabharata presented at Jogjakarta
(Indonesia).
Photo © Tony Saulnier, Paris
even by an early monument of the
First Style of Angkor, that jewel of
a shrine at Banteay Srei, -which an
inscription dates to the ninth century.
Several important lintels here illus¬
trate scenes from the Ramayana and
are set inside richly ornamented,
sinuously profiled arches. The scenes
are arranged in a formal manner, but
the symmetry does not jar. There is
an almost perfect balance in the
compositions, whether they be illus¬
trations of the battle between the
monkey-kings, or of Ravana shaking
Mount Kailasa again.
But in these there is an element
of ornamentation. The scenes lack
that dynamic character which belong¬
ed to the Indian reliefs of the eighth
century, and the representations are
suggestive of a playful air, "as though
the figures were moving to the mea¬
sures of an elaborate ballet."
The great Cambodian expressions
in sculpture came however from the
stupendous monument, the 12th-cen¬
tury temple complex of Angkor Wat.
It ¡s not only the architecture of this
monument of Khmer civilization at its
grandest that is difficult to describe,
but also the sculpture which covers
wall after massive wall.
Battle scenes are a favourite with
the Angkor Wat sculptors, and of these
the most Impressive and awe-inspir¬
ing are those that illustrate the Great
War from the Mahabharata. The
magnitude and the brilliance of the
epic scene are matched in this relief.
"The uproar and confusion, fierce
assault and valiant defence, of the
battlefield are rendered with Incredible
skill and inexhaustible Invention, the
whole surface of the wall being
decorated with forms in a brilliant
variety of dramatic postures," says the
great orientalist, Heinrich Zimmer, and
adds, "Once the eye has become
accustomed to this unemphatic style
there is an almost infinitely rich
variation to dwell upon and take in."
We have here one of the supreme
arts of all time at Its moment of
climax. The flatness of the surface of
these reliefs, a little disturbing to an
eye not used to it, is completely
intentional, for it is wholly appropriate
to the almost sunless galleries of the
temple.
The monotony of these anonymous
reliefs is only superficial, for in fact
there is in these scenes a dazzling
display of inventiveness, achieved
with an appearance of supreme ease.
Working on these scenes of a heroic
mould, the Khmer sculptors made
whole walls spring to life with the
great action which ¡s described with
such virtuosity and vividness in the
pages of the epic.
Only a century removed from Ang¬
kor Wat is the great mass of the
Bayon at the centre of Angkor Thorn.
Here again, there are whole friezes
representing scenes from the Ra¬
mayana and the Mahabharata, as at
Angkor Wat. This in spite of the fact
that the Bayon is a Buddhist monu¬
ment, but then it is only nominally so,
for ¡n fact ¡t reflects the true character
of the Cambodian ruler, Jayavarman,
who was neither a Buddhist nor a
Hindu but a Devaraja, or God-King.
Angkor Thorn once again displays the
Khmer virtuosity which is carried for¬
ward from the preceding century and
which ceases only with the disaster
that befell this civilization in the fif¬
teenth century.
What might be called the last of
the great periods of sculpture, at
least as far as the representation of
scenes from the Ramayana and the
Mahabharata in South-East Asia goes,
is to be seen at the fourteenth-
century shrine in Java, called the
Chandi Panataran. Here the epic is
the same, but the style has changed
appreciably. In a fantastic landscape
of forests and clouds that in itself is
reminiscent of an artificial stage-set,
characters from the epics take on the
aspect of puppets from the shadow
plays of subsequent centuries for
which they provided obvious inspira¬
tion. After this only stray voices are
to be heard.
In India at this time any sculptures
dealing with the themes from the epics
which we can call worthy of their
subject matter are now in bronze.
The growth of creativity from the
eleventh century onwards in southern
India is concentrated in the Chola
kingdom, and bronzes of breathtaking
beauty, including the famous Shiva
Nataraja, are produced.
Shaivism, however, does not claim
the entire attention of the Chola crafts¬
men; there is a great deal of sculp¬
ture of Rama and Krishna themes.
But the sculpture, in the nature of
things, is not monumental, nor is it
narrative in' any manner of speaking.
The concentration is on the produc¬
tion of icons which spring from the
needs of religion, not the narrative of
the epics. We do have deeply mov¬
ing sculptures like that of the great
monkey-God, Hanuman, who becomes
in the popular mind the archetypal
devotee of Rama, but the figures are
isolated. They do not become inte¬
grated with a narration in terms of
sculpture.
In stone, there are still numerous
representations of epic themes and
the Ramayana reliefs from Halebld in
the southern state of Mysore, or the
temple of the Thousand Ramas from
the Vijayanagar kingdom in South-
East India are cases in point, but
nothing as deeply moving as in the
earlier periods is seen. Great sculp¬
ture now treats of other themes, and
in the representation of epic themes yG
attention now positively shifts to ^**
painting.
From the great periods of early
CONTINUED ON PAGE 31
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
THE EXILE OF RAMA
Below we publish Chapter 11 of the Ayodhya Canto of the Ramayana by Kamban, one of the
greatest classic Tamil poets of the 9th century. Translated from the Tamil by Sri Chakravarti
Rajagopalachari, the work was published in 1961 by George Allen and Unwin Ltd., London, in the
Unesco Collection of Representative Works. The aged king Dasathara chooses one of his four
sons, Rama, to succeed him as ruler of Ayodhya, but is finally pursuaded by one of his wives to
name Rama's brother Bharata as his successor. Bowing to his father's decision, Rama prepares
to leave the capital and his wife. Sita refuses to accept this separation and insists on accompany¬
ing Rama and his brother Lakshmana into exile. Text copyright ©. Reproduction prohibited.
30
The city was distressed and citizens were dazed
And crowds unending followed as he went.
Rama arrived where Janaki was (1).
Startled, she rose, for she did not understand
Why the crowd did weep or why they came
Thus dazed and covered with dust.
Nor why her prince was strangely clad.
Her fright increased
As the women about embraced her;
They would not speak but smothered her in tears.
She turned her large eyes then to Rama:
"My prince, tell me now,
Is the king well
Or has some illness stricken him?"
And Rama quietly spoke:
"My peerless brother beloved will rule the realm
By the command of them that gave me being.
I go today to see the hills
From where the rains are sent.
And till I come again abstain from grief."
She sobbed but not for his dread exile
Or for the kingdom's sake:
She sobbed for the cruel words that scalded her ears:
"Grieve not the time I shall be away!"
For how could Sita bear the thought
Of separation? Were they not
An eternal pair together in the sea of milk
Together again on earth when he chose to be born
In Ayodhya to set the troubled world aright?
"This his resolve is surely good:
That which the king and our mother
Commanded him to do, so he must.
But why must I remain behind?"
She thought, heart near to breaking.
Then softly spoke she to Rama:
"How can you steel your heart
And cruelly leave me here and go?
Is it hot in the wilderness?
Can the sun scorch me so much there
As life here without you?"
He heard her words and his eyes saw
The sea of grief behind her tears.
He had no heart to leave her thus
And he pondered what to do;
Sita went in and soon came out
Clad in bark and stood by him
And quietly held him by the hand and laughed.
(1) As the adopted daughter of Janaka, king of Mithila, Sita ¡s also
called Janaki.
The women swooned and fell
At the sight of the princess
Thus suddenly prepared for exile.
"Those doomed to live must live,
They cannot die before their time,
In spite of every grief," they cried.
Rama saw that immense crowd
Of women plunged in burning grief.
"Oh, princess dear!" he said,
"Lovelier than lilies and the pearls of the sea
Are your teeth when you are moved to laughter
You know not what it means, beloved
To do as you propose
If you go with me
"Twill lead to sorrow without end."
At these words, Sita always soft in speech
Sweeter than the warbling of birds,
In angry tones did cry: "I understand indeed;
I am your only sorrow.
Cast me aside
And all will then be well!"
Rama spoke no more
And led her through the thronging crowds
Of men and women lamenting loud.
Brother beloved marched in front,
On his shoulder hanging his gut-bound bow;
Janaka's daughter smiling went behind
In hermit habit clad:
Between them walked the exiled prince
Majestic like a great rain-cloud.
O who can find the words
To tell their thoughts when the citizens saw this sight!
"Now that all is over," they cried,
"We no more shall weep and wail
But exiles all proceed with him,
To live where he abides who is ever our king."
The three received their royal mothers' leave
And Rama softly said to them: "I leave
My lord and father to your care,"
Then mounted he Sumantra's chariot
With beloved brother and divine spouse.
The city emptied with Rama's chariot;
The king remained and so his queens;
The paintings and the statues stayed behind too
For want of life.
As Sumantra drove the chariot
The cows flocked home and the stars began to appear.
The sun plunged among the hills
As though to shut his eye against the scene.
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
This Indian miniature by an artist of the Mughal school (late 16th century) depicts
the meeting between Rama and his brother Bharata in the forest. Bharata is outraged
by the intrigue that has deprived his beloved brother of the throne and telling
Rama, "I will not wear the crown that evil plotting has bestowed on me", implores
him to return as lawful ruler of Ayodhya. But Rama in obedience to his father's
command chooses to remain in exile. He gives his sandals to Bharata as a symbol
of authority and asks him to rule as regent in his place until his exile ends.
ART OF SOUTH ASIA
(Continued from page 29)
Indian painting from which we have
the frescoes of Ajanta, Bagh and
Badami, nothing has survived to indi¬
cate the existence of any great cycles
of paintings of Vaishnava themes
although literary references to Illus¬
trations of epic themes abound. But
soon after we move into the world
of miniature painting, we come upon
extensive sets devoted to illustrations
of the Ramayana and the Mahabha¬
rata, even if ¡n the style commonly
known as Western Indian, or Jaina,
not many representations of these
themes are found.
Among the first of the great sets
of miniature paintings dealing with the
theme of the epics ¡s an extensive and
brilliant series that was painted for
the Mughal Emperor, Akbar (1542-
1605). This is the famous illustrated
Razmnama a translation into Persian
of the Mahabharata, made under the
orders of the great Emperor himself,
and rendered in painting by the artists
of the Imperial atelier.
The set is believed to have been
completed by the year 1589, and an
estimated four' hundred thousand
rupees were paid to the artists who
drew and coloured the 169 full page
miniatures which are now in the col¬
lection of the Maharaja of Jaipur.
This is -one of the most sumptuous
of all Mughal manuscripts and we are
fortunate ¡n having the names of
several artists who collaborated to
produce this enormous work. This
is an exception to the great Indian
tradition of anonymity in the arts,
"one of the proudest distinctions of
Hindu culture."
We know little or nothing of the
nameless artists who created the
masterpieces of sculpture mentioned
above, but many of the Mughal paint¬
ings, in keeping with their own tradi¬
tion, are signed. Of the names of
several artists who are associated
with this great set, the most famous
are those of the gifted Daswanth and
his son, Basawan, two Hindu painters
working under the guidance and
supervision of Muslim master artists
of the Imperial atelier.
There is great richness and percep¬
tion in the work of these and other
artists. The colour and line are dazzl¬
ing. But there is something that seems
to be lacking in the series, perhaps
it is the feeling of devotion. One
senses that the epic has been reduc¬
ed in the transfer to the painted page.
The series tends to become the illus¬
tration of an engaging story, uninform¬
ed by the spiritual undercurrent which
runs through the epic as we know it.
Important series of Illustrations of
the Ramayana were also executed in
the Mughal period, and several sets,
some in the Imperial style others in
the provincial, have survived. There
is little doubt that the narrative of
the epics had conquered the imagina¬
tion of the Mughal artists of the
early period, and they illustrated it
with verve and imagination, but not
perhaps with the same intensity of
CONTINUED ON PAGE 44
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Photo © Yves Coffin, Paris
Photos © Luc Ionesco, Paris
32
jAïûr^i- i : t ^.«'-^a./ ', sr\: £';W.*à.-
MOVING
TRAGEDIES
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
.w r -r.-r r~\ xi :
Photo © Luc Ionesco, Paris
An ally of Rama in his campaign to free his wife is the monkey-king Sugriva, who has been dispossesed of his
throne and exiled by his half-brother Bali. The adventures and prowess of the monkey heroes . of the Ramayana figure
prominently in sculptures of all of South East Asia. Shown here are four of rare beauty by Khmer artists in Cambodia.
(1) Sugriva at grips with Bali, a 10th-century carving at Koh Ker, 60 miles east of Angkor. (2) Rama drives his
chariot to Lanka to deliver his wife Sita with the help of his monkey allies. (3) Sugriva weeps with anguish on being usurped
of his throne by Bali. These two 11th-century bas-reliefs are carved on the Baphuon temple at Angkor. (4) A masterpiece
of deep emotion in stone: pierced by Rama's arrow, Bali dies in the arms of his wife 12th-century bas-relief, Angkor Wat.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
In Cambodia
SHADOWS
AND LIGHT
ON THE RAMAYANA
uPSING its polished, allusive art to transport its
audience into the realms of ancient lore, the shadow theatre
has acquired a distinct technique and style of its own in
every Asian country where it exists (see page 28). In Cam¬
bodia, performances nowadays are limited to important
occasions the king's birthday, for example, or the cremation
of a famous person. Cambodia's puppets made of perforated
hide are not isolated silhouettes like those of Indonesia,
but are placed in a decorative frame in which the character
is surrounded by "scenery" motifs of various kinds that
relate to the scene being played. These elegant, often
leaf-shaped frames are seen as shadows on a translucid
screen lit from behind by candles. Above, "behind the
screens" as puppet manipulators at Siem-Reap, near Angkor,
present an episode from the Ramayana. Right, as the
audience sees the performance: holding up the puppets,
parts of which resemble exquisite filigree, the manipulators
sway from side to side like shadows dancing with shadows.
Music on traditional instruments accompanies the perfor¬
mance, and a narrator embellishes his account of the story
with subtle and comic allusions that delight his audience.
"v- i
Left, a performer holds up to
the shadow screen a frame
depicting an episode from the
Ramayana: Sita is found
in her place of captivity by
the vultures which Rama has
sent in search of her.
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Photos © Luc Ionesco, Paris
Shadow theatre puppets are
made with meticulous care and
skill by artists who respect a
traditional iconography yet imprint
their work with individual
artistic touches. Below, working
on a rectangle of buffalo hide,
a Cambodian artists at Siem-Reap
sketches two monkeys in
combat. Right, another artist
carves outlines of a figure and
motifs on a completed drawing.
' M
35
A
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
THE KATHAKALI
AND THE DANCE-DRAMA
OF INDIA
by C. Kunchu Nair
K
36
ATHAKALI is the principal
dance-drama form of Kerala, a narrow
strip of land lying on the coast of
south-west India. Though confined
thus to a small area, Kathakali is a
part of an all-India tradition of clas¬
sical theatre and shares with its sister
arts in other parts of India certain
broad features which sharply mark off
the Indian tradition from Its counter¬
part in the West.
It is neither possible nor necessary
to discuss here all these common
features relating to the growth of
unity in the Indian Theatre movement.
But, at the same time, one cannot
loose sight of certain striking factors
and circumstances which tended to
govern the content and form of this
traditional theatre.
One such factor was the most in¬
timate and enduring connexion the
theatre had maintained ever since its
C. KUNCHU NAIR began his studies and
training in the Kathakali dance-drama at
the age of 15. He has devoted the past
43 years of his life to the subject, studying
first under the late Pattikkamthodi Ravunni
Menon, the greatest Kathakali teacher of
modern times. He is now director of the
most important Kathakali dance academy
in Asiathe Keralakalamandalam, in Kerala,
south-west India, where he is also senior
professor. In 1959 he introduced the
Kathakali to Europe and this year his
troupe completed a smash hit visit to
Europe and Canada. Choreographer and
producer, he has studied every aspect of
the art of Kathakali.
birth with the religion of the land in
all its changing forms and with its
recorded and written literature. The
most important of this large body of
religious literature were and still are
the two very great and powerful epics,
the Ramayana and the Mahabharata
and the later Bhagavad-Gita.
Apart from their historical and liter¬
ary value, these bulky compilations
represented India's earliest memories,
collective wisdom ' and consciousness
and its religious and moral attitude.
Not only did they contain discussions
of various philosophical schools, codes
of morality and ethics and of abstract
qualities of virtue and vice, happiness
and sorrow and nobility and baseness;
but they also portrayed in bold types
and as the real embodiments of these
principles, noble heroes and heroines
and villains of all kinds.
They narrated stories of great bat¬
tles between good and evil and how
the former always triumphed over the
latter; they explained how the gods
often descended on the earth and
mingled and shared with human beings
their joys and sorrows; how the virtu¬
ous on the earth went to Heaven to
enjoy the fruits of their good deeds
and how the vicious were dragged
to Hell to answer and suffer for their
black deeds; if the gods sometimes
lapsed into human weaknesses, the
mortals often rose to the state of
godliness.
Always with ready answers to the
problems that troubled the suffering
human heart and with constant advice
through sweet persuasion and un¬
mistakable examples, these epics
seemed so near and dear that people
came to think of them as part of their
very selves.
No wonder, then, that these holy
books especially the Mahabharata,
Ramayana and Bhagavad-Gita exert¬
ed so powerful and lasting an influence
on the minds and dally lives of the
people and proved, over the ages, to
be inexhaustible sources supplying a
rich variety of themes for art and litera¬
ture in India. Rarely did any artist or
writer feel any compulsion to look
elsewhere for his subject matter.
Not that Indian Society remained
static. Changes there were in the
CONTINUED ON PAGE 39
KRISHNA AND ARJUNA
Two heroes of the Mahabharata, Krishna
(left) and Arjuna, as they appear in
a Kathakali dance-drama. In this
scene from the Bhagavad-Gita,
the God Krishna teaches Arjuna
the true virtues of the upright man.
The Kathakali theatre, which originated
in Kerala, south-west India, in the 17th
century, is part of an all-India tradition
of classical theatre in which poetry,
music and dance are closely intregrated.
The mythological characters are easily
identified by their highly stylized
costumes and make-up and their
characteristic miming and gestures.
Photo © Odile Montserrat, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
KATHAKALI (Continued)
Four-hour make-up for each dancer
Colour page
ARTIFICIAL JOWLS
OF PAPER AND PASTE
In the Kathakali theatre green make-up
and wide eyes (lotus eyes) accentuated
by thick black lines identify gods and
noble heroes (see page 36). Violent
characters such as the ruthless Duryodhana
of the Kaurava clan
(top left) wear green make-up variegated
with red and white, and grotesque
protuberances on their noses. Outright
scoundrels like Duryodhana's brother,
Dussasana (top, far left) have red beards
and are made up to look
repulsive and inhuman.
Kathakali dancers wear ornately
decorated crowns, those with the
largest circles being reserved for
the most evil and detestable characters.
The art of building up the elaborate
mask-like facial make-up of the Kathakali
dancers is a hereditary vocation and an
expert spends up to four hours on
each face. About 60 varieties of make-up
and costumes are used to portray the
different characters: god or demon,
woman or brahmin, and many others. A
facial border called "chutty" gives new
contours to the features. Made of paper
and rice paste mixed with lime, it is applied
to the cheeks, enlarging the face with
the aim of giving greater presence to
the character, just as thick-soled shoes
were once worn by Greek tragedians.
The form of the chutty depends on the
character being portrayed. Left, actor
completes the chutty he wears with
green colouring, to portray a hero of
the Mahabharata. Far left, top: an actor
Is given a "katti" (knife-shaped) make-up
for his role as Duryodhana. Far left, bottom:
putting the last touches to the basic
make-up. Designs on forehead also
serve to identify each character.
Photo © Odile Montserrat, Paris
social life, but not basic enough to
dislodge these great epics from their
supreme position. Any pressures from
the changing social and cultural values
were absorbed by a slight reworking
of the old materials.
This persistance of epic stories as
the recurring theme for the theatre had
tended to discourage realism. Leg¬
ends and myths, distortions and
exaggerations as they are from real
life, could hardly lend themselves to
realistic treatment without injuring
artistic unity and aesthetic propriety.
Besides, there was an important cir¬
cumstance that kept realism out of the
Indian Theatre. Never in the history
of its evolution could drama ¡n India
completely break loose from poetry,
music and dance as happened in the
West. Even as these three arts were
having their own indépendant courses
of development, they retained their
original connexion with drama. How¬
ever their development as separate
arts necessitated their reintegration
with drama at a higher level, the form
of integration depending on the pre¬
ponderance of one or other of the
three forms.
The heavy emphasis on poetry,
music and dance added to the almost
complete dependence on mythological
stories, ruled out realism. The only
logical and consistant direction the
development of Indian Theatre could
take from that position was evidently
towards an increasingly greater degree
of abstraction and stylization and
further refinement and rarefaction of
technique.
How did the art of acting stand in
relation to its three adjuncts poetry,
music and dance? To answer this,
we may introduce here the concept of
Abhinayam developed by Hindu theo¬
rists. This term has often been inade¬
quately translated as acting. In fact,
it is more than acting and if broadly
understood includes poetry, music and
dance.
Abhinayam is explained as the art
of conveying or communicating to the
spectator through suggestion the
thoughts and feelings of the charac¬
ters in relation to their causes and
effects. Feelings, emotions and moods
were analyzed and classified accord¬
ing to their intensity and permanence.
How these feelings are visually pro¬
jected all over the body through
changes in the colour, motion, position,
pose, gesture, etc., of the body, its
limbs and .features and changes in
the voice, was closely studied. The
movements and gestures and tonal
variation were abstracted, stylized,
condensed or enlarged and related to
definite feelings, moods and actions.
The Abhinayam consists primarily
in the actor's showing or "acting"
these elements thereby suggesting the
corresponding feelings, etc., which
become sublimated as aesthetic fla¬
vour or enjoyment in the spectator.
The Hindu theorists have recognized
four elements or aspects of Abhinayam
according to its means or media as
relating to (1) body (Angikam); (2)
speech (Vacikam); (3) mind (Satvi-
kam); and external means (Aharyam).
(1) Angikam - Proper use of artistic
gestures, actor's bearing, walk, move¬
ment of features and limbs.
(2) Vacikam - Use of proper pro-
nounciation, modulation of voice,
accent and rhythm, proper dramatic
delivery of the text (prose, poetry and
songs).
(3) Satvikam - Representation of
some of the basic psychic conditions
by such means as immobility, pers¬
piration, change of voice, etc.
(4) Aharyam - Make-up and cos¬
tumes and the stage decor and props.
In Its wider sense Angikam should
include dance, and Vacikam, music.
Considering these characteristic
features which are almost antithetical
to the Western concept of drama, it
will be more appropriate to call the
traditional Indian drama (including
dance-drama) a form of "lyrlco-drama-
tl.c spectacle." Incidently, it is inter¬
esting to note that this Is also true in
varying degrees of most of the
countries of the South-East Asia which
were once called "Greater India."
T
HE major forms of Indian
dance (of the interpretative type) and
dance-dramas like Bharatnatyam, Ka-
thak, Manipuri, Kathakali, Kuchlputi,
Bhagavatamela, Yakshaganam, etc.,
which were revived during the last fifty
years grew up in this all-India dance
tradition. However, in assimilating this
tradition each of these forms had its
own area of emphasis. Each is firmly
rooted in its local folk tradition which
Imparts and sustains its uniqueness
and justifies its independent existence.
Kathakali can be roughly translated
as danced play. A cycle of eight
plays based on the story of Rama,
the hero of the Ramayana, was written
between 1655 and 1661 A.D. (some
scholars say between 1484 and 1497
A.D.) by a ruler of a petty principality
called Kottarakara.
Many poets wrote Kathakali plays
during the last three hundred years,
but only some thirty of this large col¬
lection, numbering more than a
hundred, remained and still remain
popular on the stage. Of these nine
are based on the Ramayana, thirteen
on the Mahabharata and seven on the
Bhagavad-Gita.
In preparing the ground for the y\
emergence of this new form, the tra- ^^
dition of the older dance forms of
Kerala both folk and classical and
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
KATHAKALI (Continued)
Daily practice from 3 a.m. to 9 p.m.
religious and secular played a great
part. Many of the choreographic
patterns, the basic stance with the
feet planted wide apart and the out¬
stretched hands on either side, the
movements for fighting, dance sequen¬
ces and many of the elements of
the make-up and costuming all show
the strong influence of the Indigenous
folk arts.
Another art form on which Kathakali
has heavily drawn is Kutiyattam the
oldest classical form of drama for the
presentation of Sanskrit plays. This
form was developed during the ninth
and tenth centuries A.D. Kathakali is
heavily Indebted to Kutiyattam for its
technique of facial expression, hand
gestures and many of its stage
conventions. It was mainly through
it that the all-India tradition reached
Kathakali. Kathakali is thus a fine
synthesis between the indigenous Dra-
vidian tradition and the all-India tra¬
dition.
A
40
Kathakali performance
usually takes place in the open air and
occupies the whole night. Traditionally,
the acting area (12 feet square) was
not raised, but was on the same level
as the spectators who used to squat
on the ground, the stage being cover¬
ed with a pandal (a light roofed struc¬
ture on poles), which is at least 104
feet high.
Accompaniment: The musical accom¬
paniment consists of three drums, the
Chenda, Maddalam and Edakka, and
a gong, a pair of cymbals and a conch
shell. The Chenda is not played for
a female character and Edakka for
males. There are two vocalists, the
leading one holding the gong and the
other, the cymbals.
Preliminaries: On the day of the
performance, at about 6 p.m. a short
drumming announces the day's pro¬
gramme. This is called Keli.
At about 8.30 p.m. the programme
begins. A huge brass lamp with wicks
floating in oil placed at the front centre
of the stage is lit. Then follows
drumming on Maddalam called Aran-
gukeli.
Then two stage assistants hold a
curtain in front of the stage.
Behind the curtain one or two dan¬
cers perform a propitiary prelude call¬
ed Thotayam, ¡n praise of the gods
and accompanied on the Maddalam
alone. This is followed by a recital
of prayers by the two singers.
The next item is the conventional
introduction of the important character
or charactors of the play selected for
the night. In the full splendour of the
make-up and costumes and accom¬
panied by all the instrumentalists and
vocalists, they perform certain pure
dance sequences.
This is called Purappat.
Then the stage is given to the musi¬
cians alone and they give a recital
called Melappadam. Now they can
show their talents as soloists and more
freely explore the possibilities of their
arts without their playing being tailor¬
ed to the demands of the dance or
drama.
Story proper: The Melappadam conclu¬
des the preliminaries,- and the rest of
the night is taken up by either. one
full play or exerpts from several.
The Kathakali play, the literary
text composed by the playwright, is
the basis of Abhinayam. The text
is ¡n the form of verses and songs
written usually in highly poetic style.
The songs represent dramatic dialo¬
gues, the verses being generally the
words of the narrator and summariz¬
ing those sections of the theme which
are not represented on the stage. They
often act as the links between the
scenes.
Abhinayam (representation): One
peculiar feature of Kathakali which
differentiates it from most other Indian
dance dramas deserves special men¬
tion. In the other forms, all the four
elements of Abhinayam, mentioned
above, concern the actor-dancer alone.
In Kathakali, however, he does only
three, the Vacikam being entrusted to
the singers, except that the actor-
dancer in certain roles makes some
grunts. This suppression of Vacikam
has led to a remarkable development
and elaboration of the facial expres¬
sion of the actor-dancer to an extent
not often seen in any other school.
Vacikam (relating to speech or sing¬
ing): The singing of the verses and
songs forming the text of the play
constitutes the Vacikam. As the
singer sings the lines of the songs,
the actor-dancer interprets the ideas
and feelings contained in them. The
melody-moulds, the rhythms and the
tempi of the songs are of great sig¬
nificance. Their choice is so carefully
made as to create a variety of moods,
to retard or quicken the speed of the
action and to draw out or compress
the movement according to the need
of the particular plot situation or
feelings being projected. For instance
a song for a battle scene and one for
a love scene are entirely different In
their rendering, melody-moulds and
tempi.
Angikam (relating to the body): The
sole medium for Angikam is the body
of the actor. The silent artist suggests
the idea and related feelings contain¬
ed in the words and sentences of
the songs with the help of the move¬
ments of the body, its limbs and
features. They include hand-gestures,
mime, dance, etc.
In between the stanzas the actor
usually executes a sequence of dance.
This is not pure or abstract dance. It
reflects, by its tempo, quality and
nature the general purport of the
stanza which precedes or succeeds
the dance.
For hand gestures Kathakali mainly
depends on a short manual which
gives 470 gestures deriving them from
24 root gestures. They are classified
as single hand, double hand, mixed
hand (each hand forming different ges¬
tures from the other) and gestures
having more than one meaning. There
another division into eight types.
Each has its own different pose, direc¬
tion, movement of the body and way
of using space. Eyes normally follow
the gestures. The mode of showing
the gesture and the accompanying
movements of features and limbs are
determined by the context, the tempo
of the rhythm and the nature of the
character portrayed.
0
NE other feature is impro¬
visation and solo acting. There are
several occasions when there are no
textual lines to interpret and the actor
is required to fill in the gaps by Impro¬
visation. The character may be going
through a forest and describing the
wild life; or enjoying the sights of
Heaven. Here, without the help of
any scenic settings, the actor conjures
up a succession of visual ¡mages in
movement ¡n terms of which he tries
to explain and interpret the desired
theme.
The instrumental music provides a
powerful support. Its main function is
to simulate all kinds of movements of
m
C. Kunchu Nair (author of this article)
teaching at the Kathakali dance academy,
the Keralakalamandalam, in India,
of which he is director. Marks
in ash on his forehead and chest are
the signs of the Lord Shiva.
]]>
</page>
<page number="41">
<![CDATA[
BHÜ
V »'
3¿&->
sir5?-
Photo © Pic, Paris
Introductory dance to a Kathakali drama based on the Mahabharata, performed
at the 1967 Theatre of the Nations festival in Paris. A Kathakali troupe
from the Keralakalamandalam in Kerala, India, made a highly
successful tour of Europe and Canada this year, with the collaboration of the International
Music Council and the International Institute for Comparative Music Studies.
the actor-dancer including gestures,
dances, etc.
Aharyam: This primarily relates to
the make-up, costumes and jewellery
of the actors and secondly to the stage
props. Kathakali does not make use
of any stage settings. But the make¬
up and costumes have a most impor¬
tant function in this dance-drama
which ¡s primarily to indicate not the
birth, age, status, or nationality of the
characters but the essential nature of
their mental make-up. The distortion,
abstraction and exaggeration of the
make-up and costumes reflect the
same qualities of the mythological
characters.
There are now about 6lxty varieties
of make-up and costumes. Major types
are the nine given below:
Pacca (Green) - Generally for the
noble and virtuous. Gods and heroes
like Rama; Katti (Knife) - Characters
having vices such as greed, lust and
vanity. Ravana the demon king of
Lanka who was killed by Rama; Tatl
(Beard) - Destructive forces in the
form of terrifying demons; Minukku
(Polished) - Females, Brahmins,
Sages etc.; Karl (Black) - Aborigines,
hunter etc.; Pazhuppu (Mixture of
yellow and red) - Brahma, Shiva and
brother Krishna; Chuvappu (red) -
Sun, Fire etc.; Teppu (Painted) - Bird,
Snake etc.; Poymukham (Masks) -
Masks of monkey, pig, old hag etc.
are sometimes used.
The process of make-up and costum¬
ing ¡n Kathakali takes much time as
long as four hours to complete in
respect of characters having Chutty
the facial border made of rice paste
mixed with lime and sometimes paper
as well.
First the actor himself draws an
outline of the make-up on his face.
Then he lies down face upwards and
the make-up artist forms the Chutty
on his face little by little. This takes
most of the make-up time.
Next the actor himself completes
the remaining details and puts in his
eyes a granule-like particle which
grows Inside the flower of a plant
belonging to the Solanaceae family.
The particle ¡s retained ¡n the corner of
each eye and is removed only after
the performance. It makes the eye
red and imparts a special glow add¬
ing to the expressiveness of the eyes.
Then one by one he puts on the
costumes and ornaments with the help
of dressing room assistants. Before
he goes to the stage he pays respects
to his teachers.
The materials used for the make-up
are: Red arsenic, Indigo cake, Dammar
resin, Collyrium, red powder, rice
paste, lime, paper, cork, Miea, Glngilly
oil and Cocoanut oil.
The technique of Abhinayam as used
¡n Kathakali and the endless variety
of highly stylized and sharply defined
movements that goes with it presup¬
poses a long course of hard and
rigorous training of the body and mind
of the would-be actor-dancer. The
training begins at the age of 10 to 12
and lasts for about 12 years. By a
long series of repeated exercises and
other practices the body is trained to
become a proper medium of dance and
expression.
After the second year, the student
takes part in actual performances
as an understudy for minor roles.
June to December is the season
for training proper. For the rest of
the year he participates in as many
performances as possible under the
guidance of his teacher. As part of
the training, he undergoes for three
months every year a treatment of oil
CONTINUED ON NEXT PAGE
41
]]>
</page>
<page number="42">
<![CDATA[
KATHAKALI (Continued)
massage to make his body mellow
and supple.
Along with this goes the training
of mind. The student learns the text
of the plays and tries to understand
the problems of characterization, struc¬
ture of the play and a host of other
theories. By the time he leaves the
school he has studied at least 15 plays
which form the basic core of the
Kathakali repertoire.
The modern tendency ¡s to reduce
the period of training by extending
the classroom work to the whole year
instead of limiting ¡t to six months as
¡n former times. But the period cannot
be reduced to below eight years. The
maximum number of students a teacher
can handle at a time is four. Girls
never act in Kathakali, one reason
perhaps being the length and rigorous
nature of the training required.
A typical time table of training in
the past was:
3.00 a.m. to 4.00 a.m. Practice in
the movements, of eye, brow, lip*, neck
and other facial features.
4.00 a.m. to 6.00 a.m. Oil is
applied to the body; a course of exer¬
cises, foot-work, dance movements
etc., lead to the massage in which
the student lies on a mat and the
teacher works his body over with his
feet.
8.30 a.m. to 11.30 a.m. and 2.30 p.m.
to 5 p.m. Practice in the preliminary
dances, Thotayam and Purappatu;
rehearsal of the plays.
7.30 p.m. to 9.00 p.m. Practice in
expressing emotions, feelings and
sentiments with the help of eyes, brow,
cheek, lips, neck etc., and interpreta¬
tion of important sections of the play.
Modern schools of Kathakali have
had of course to make some conces¬
sions to this long and rigorous
schedule to allow time for the general
education of the students.
As part of India's cultural -renais¬
sance which began in the last century,
Interest in our traditional arts, music
dance and drama has been revived.
One of the best representatives of
this renaissance in Kerala was the late
national poet, Vallathol.' With the help
of his friends he founded in 1930 the
Keralakalamandalam the first and now
the most well-known Academy to teach
Kathakali and other arts of Kerala.
Vallathol travelled throughout India and
visited many countries, popularizing
this art form and seeking help for his
Academy, which is now owned and
run by the Government of Kerala. A
troupe from the Academy made a
highly successful tour of Europe and
Canada from May to September, 1967.
In 1939 a second school Kottak-
kal Natyasangham was started. To¬
day Kathakali is growing as an art
form and several other schools offer¬
ing training in Kathakali have opened
in India.
Drawings © Peter Schumann, Archives of
the International Institute for
Comparative Music Studies, Berlin
LANGUAGE OF HANDS. In the Kathakali dance-drama, the songs and verses of the text
are sung by soloists. The actor-dancer remains silent, but speaks in a language
of gestures, or "mudras". Mudras are the movements and positioning of the hands
to represent a word, a person, an idea or an action, and so on. The language is enriched
by movements and' miming with the body, limbs and features that express the ideas and
feelings of the characters in the play. One manual on mudras lists nearly 500 of these
hand gestures a few examples of which are shown below.
Brahma, the Creator
Rama, the hero
Truth
The Goddess Parvati Indra, King of lleavun
C\
Certainty
Obeisance (greeting) The five Pandava brothers
Reason King Duryodhana
To kill
Beautiful girl
Chariot
The heavens
Gentle ^v
Disc
Loved one
Brother Sin Cuckoo Marriage Wife
42
Poison To see Combat Husband Tortoise Lion
]]>
</page>
<page number="43">
<![CDATA[
INDIA'S ANCIENT HEROES ON CELLULOID
N,lot long ago someone asked
the distinguished Indian film maker
Satyjit Ray, if it was true that he
wished to make a screen version of
the Mahabharata. "Yes, I do," he
replied. "I have given it a lot of
thought. It is a theme that endures,
a theme of war and peace, tyranny
and struggle. Also, ¡t is worthwhile
to- look at one's roots."
From the classic age of Sanskrit
drama some sixteen centuries ago to
the present times, poets, playwrights,
sculptors and film makers have looked
at these roots with growing fascination
and drawn sustenance from them.
It is small wonder then that the very
first Indian film, "Raja Harishchandra,"
produced in 1913 by Dhundiraj Gobind
Phalke, should have been a mytho¬
logical tale sung and celebrated
throughout the country.
The story concerns Harishchandra,
a king known for his piety and
truthfulness. One day Vlswamltra,
the wise Brahmin in the epic literature,
demands of him the sacrificial gift due
to a Brahmin and the king offers him
whatever he might choose to ask,
"gold, his own son, wife, body, life,
kingdom and good fortune". Vis-
wamitra strips the king of all his
worldly possessions leaving him but a
garment of bark and his wife and son.
The king suffers untold miseries and
hardships, sacrifices his son, and is
about to offer up his wife, when the
gods arrive and entreat him to accom¬
pany them to heaven.
The film was a tremendous success.
Exciting as films from other countries
had hitherto seemed, it was an even
greater thrill for the audience to see
a familiar, traditional story set in India
and performed by Indian actors. It
lifted the audience out of day-to-day
frustrations into the world of legendary
India whose glorious past, familiar in
song and story, yet even so, half for¬
gotten, had thus been given living, mov¬
ing reality.
The impact, in fact, was overwhelm¬
ing. In one of Phalke's subsequent
films, when Krishna appeared on the
screen men and women in the audience
prostrated themselves. This sponta¬
neous action was not the naive gesture
BHAGWAN GARGA is an Indian cinema
historian and film critic. He has written on
many aspects of the Indian cinema and has
produced a number of documentary films on
Indian film-making and Indian art. On an
international level, hé has helped to arrange
the exchange of films between India and
France and was a member of the Unesco
committee of experts on Anthologies of the
History of the Cinema which met in Paris in
April 1967. Bhagwan Garga is to prepare the
Indian anthology.
by Bhagwan D. Carga
of people mistaking the screen incar¬
nation for the real god; the reverence
shown was for the symbol not for the
man portraying it.
The first decade of the Indian cinema
was given over almost entirely to
mythological stories from the Mahab¬
harata and the Ramayana. The Indian
film maker was quick to discover not
only the perennial popularity of the
two great epics, but also that they
were an inexhaustible mine of dramatic
material that could be adapted to suit
any audience.
In the heyday of the serials, when
"The Perils of Pauline" helped Holly¬
wood to make Its millions, the Indian
film maker, like many others, followed
the trend but on his own terms. In the
epics, particularly the Ramayana, he
discovered a wealth of action the
basic Ingredient of the serial film.
One of the earliest serials produced
and shown in several instalments ¡n
India was "The Exile of Rama" (1918).
Thrilling as it may have been to watch.
Miss Pearl White dangling from an
aeroplane or leaping from a burning
building, this heroine was still no match
for the monkey-god Hanuman, who
could suspend himself in mid-air or lift
a mountain on his little finger. Danger
lurked behind every bush in the forests
where Rama and his beautiful wife,
Sita, were exiled.. And what greater
thrill than to witness the combat bet¬
ween Rama and Ravana, the demon-
king, in which Rama struck off Ravana's
ten heads one after the other, only to
find that as one fell another grew in
its place.
T
HE Mahabharata is not
only the more ancient and the longer of
the two epics, but has a larger fund of
stories those of Nala and Damayanti,
of Shakuntala (immortalized by Kali-
dasa in his play of the same name),
of Savltri and, of course, the moving
poetic colloquies between Arjuna and
Krishna which form a separate book,
the Bhagavad-Gita.
All these stories lend themselves
readily to screen adaptations. The
most popular of all is perhaps that of
Nala and Damayanti, the story of a
beautiful girl for whose hand the gods
compete with her lover (a mere mor¬
tal) and lose. This ancient story illus¬
trates the humanized concepts of the
traditional culture, gods with a touch
of human frailty, women celebrated for
beauty and wit, men capable of win¬
ning when pitted against gods.
The cinematic potentialities of the
story are obvious enough, and the first
version was made as early as 1919 by
Madan Theatres of Calcutta, with an
Italian, Eugenio De Llguoro, directing
the film. "Nala and Damayanti" has
since been filmed at least twenty times,
but has lost none of its popularity.
The advent of sound films served, if
anything, to increase the popularity of
scenarios based on the epics. It is
significant that among the first sound
films by far the best was "Ayodhya Ka
Raja" (The King of Ayodhya), a mytho¬
logical film. A little later, in 1934, came
"Sita," directed by Devaki Bose, which
is perhaps the finest screen rendering
of the Ramayana to date.
Devaki Bose used a characteristic¬
ally Indian device in unfolding his
story. The ancient Sanscrit dramas
traditionally opened with a prologue
in which the chief actor or narrator
(the sutradhar) outlined the story or
commented on one or another aspect
of the play. Bose opened his film
with a commentary of this kind illustrat¬
ed with murals depicting Incidents from
the lives of Rama and Sita.
During the Second World War when
the demand for entertainment increas¬
ed tremendously and commercial com¬
panies in consequence took the line
of least resistance, Indian films too
showed obvious signs of decline and
"fatigue". Significantly, the two out¬
standing films of the period were "Ram
Rajya" (The Reign of Rama) and
"Shakuntala", the first based on the
Ramayana and the second on the Ma¬
habharata.
In "Ram Rajya" the crucial moment
comes when Rama, though convinced
of the chastity of his wife, Sita, while
she was the captive of Ravana,
nevertheless sends her into exile after
hearing a callous remark casting doubt
on her innocence. Vijay Bhatt, director
of the film, has recalled public
reactions to this part of the story
when he showed his film in New York.
"Many people asked me why the
kindly Rama yielded to the wishes of
the people in spite of his conviction
that Sita was innocent. I replied that
this was the difference between the
democratic kings of the West and of
the East. Edward VIII left the people
for the sake of his wife; Rama left
his wife for the sake of the people."
Superficially, Vijay Bhatt's reply
might appear chauvinistic and vain; in
reality it is nothing of the sort. It
shows how the Indian ¡s always
comparing and judging his own
conduct (and sometimes that of others)
by the standards set in the epics.
These standards are by no means
unattainable. In fact the popularity of A^i
the epics is mainly due to their deep *V
humanity, wherein gods behave like
ordinary men and men like gods.
]]>
</page>
<page number="44">
<![CDATA[
X^., y^r . *
¡M
. ..»">* * o
v t* jr í
In many temples on the
island of Java (Indonesia),
notably the famous temple
of Prambanan, stone reliefs
recount ancient stories
from the Mahabharata and
the Ramayana. Among
the finest are those
depicting the exploits and
adventures of Arjuna,
chief of the Pandava clan.
This masterly head of
Arjuna graces the ruins of
the 13th-century Djago
temple in eastern Java.
THE EPICS IIM THE ART OF SOUTH ASIA (Continued from page 31 )
44
feeling or psychological insight which
the Indian sculptor had brought to
his work.
In the seventeenth century, Mughal
painting takes a different turn, but
artists continue to paint the epics.
Now the scene shifts to Rajasthan
where several series of magnificent
paintings in long, extensive sets, are
produced. The favourite theme with
the Rajasthani painters is the Rama¬
yana and many sets now in impor¬
tant collections all over the world have
survived.
Although the technical level may not
be as high, the lines lacking the same
vibrancy, and the colour the same
sophistication or enamelled brilliance
of Mughal work, what has been gain
ed is an intensity of emotion. In
many of the Rajasthan paintings there
is a quality of naivete and wonder at
the beholding of divine form. These
are products of a wonderful spiritual
equilibrium. One feels that the artist
fully believed in what he was painting.
That other great centre of miniature
painting in India, the Punjab hills,
showed an equal interest in the epics.
One of the most famous sets of mini¬
atures of the Hill or Pahari schools
is the large Ramayana, many of whose
unusually large-sized leaves are now
in the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston,
and the Cleveland Museum of Art.
The date of this set is a matter of
controversy among scholars, but there
can be little doubt about the quality
of these paintings. In a scene like
the siege of Lanka, the imaginative
inventiveness of the Pahari painter,
as he arranges whole armies of
monkeys and bears covering the hill¬
side outside the golden walls of the
fortress of the demon-king, combines .
with his rich sense of colouring and
design.
What is seen in these paintings
above all is the feeling of wonder
and humility with which the painter
approached the subject. Here we
have the mature flower of an ancient
tradition. An even earlier set of paint¬
ings treating of the Ramayana theme,
and dating possibly back to A.D. 1720,
comes from the tiny principality of
Guler in the Punjab Hills.
]]>
</page>
<page number="45">
<![CDATA[
This is rendered in what is popu¬
larly referred to as the Basohli style,
and has all the vigour and intensity
associated with it. With the simplest
possible palette, consisting of hot
yellows and blues and reds, the artist
of the hills has created in these paint¬
ings a magnificent world of Gods and
heroes seen with eyes of devotion
(see colour plate, page 22-23).
There are still other sets of the Ra¬
mayana from the Hills, an important
and very extensive one coming from
the remote hill State of Kulu, and
popularly known among art historians
as the Shangri Ramayana.
But the set which has perhaps the
greatest amount of delicacy and
refinement of treatment illustrates the
moving episode of Nala and Da¬
mayanti from the Mahabharata. In
this series of exquisite drawings, some
partly coloured, the artist of the
eighteenth century has left behind a
masterpiece in terms of tenderness
of feeling. The number of paintings
in this set is not fully known although
it appears to have been very large,
but whatever has survived is of
magnificent quality.
The most extensive of the sets of
Pahari works is again a series of
drawings. This series illustrating the
entire story of the Ramayana has as
many as seven hundred leaves, these
being swiftly drawn In sanguine. upon
paper. The set is dated and signed:
it was executed in A.D. 1816 for Raja
Bhuplnder Pal of Basohli by the artist
Ranjha of the family of Pandit Seu.
The entire set is well preserved,
and is now in the collection of the
Bharat Kala Bhavan at Benares. This
makes it the most complete set of
paintings of any themes from the epics
anywhere in the world. And what is
amazing is that nowhere in these
hundreds of leaves is there any
weakening of intensity or emotion.
A significant passage from the Bal
Kanda of the Ramayana tells of the
legendary author of the epic, Valmiki,
realizing the story of Rama completely
in his mind before setting to work.
It was to gain this realization that
"seating himself with his face towards
the East and sipping water according
to rule, he applied himself to the yogic
contemplation of his theme.
"By virtue of his yoga power, he
then clearly saw before him Rama,
Lakshmana and Sita; as well as Da¬
saratha together with his wives, laugh¬
ing, talking, acting, and moving, in
his kingdom, as in real life. He be¬
held, by yoga power, all that had
come to pass and all that was to
come to pass In the future, like a
nelli fruit on the palm of his hand.
And having truly seen all by virtue
of his concentration, the generous
sage began the setting down of the
history of Rama."
The artist of the great works of art
of which we have spoken must also,
one feels, have proceeded in a some¬
what like manner.
FURTHER READING ON THE RAMAYANA
AND THE MAHABHARATA
RAMAYANA
The Ayodhya Canto of the
Ramayana as told by Kamban
Translated from the Tamil
by C. Rajagopalachari.
(Unesco Collection of Representative
Works.) George Allen and Unwin,
London, 1961 (16/-).
Kavitavali
by Tulsi Das.
Translated and with a Critical Intro¬
duction by Raymond Allchin.
(Unesco Collection of Representative
Works.) George Allen and Unwin,
London, 1964 (32/-); R.S. Barnes
and Co., Inc., New York. ($ 6.00).
Ramayana (in prose)
by C. Rajagopalachari.
Bhavan's Book Univ., Bombay, 1965
(paperback).
The Ramayana and the
Mahabharata
Condensed into English verse by
Romesh C. Dutt. Everymans's
Library. J. M. Dent and Sons, Lon¬
don; Dutton, New York, 1966.
The Holly Lake of the Acts of
Rama
by W. Douglas P. Hill.
New translation of Tulsi Das's
Ramacaritamanasa.
Oxford Univ. Press, London, Cal¬
cutta, 1952.
Thai Ramayana
Retold from the original version
written by King Rama I of Thailand.
Chalermit Bookshop, Bangkok, 1965.
MAHABHARATA
Mahabharata (in prose)
by C. Rajagopalachari.
Bhavan's Book Univ., Bombay.
Mahabharata of Krishna
Dwaipayana Vyasa
Translated into English prose from
the original Sanskrit by P. C. Roy,
Oriental Publishing Co., Calcutta,
1956 (12 vol.).
The Gospel of Selfless Action or
the Gita according to Gandhi
Translation of the original in Gujarati
with an addition, introduction and
commentary by Mahadev Desai,
Navajivan Publishing House, Ahme-
dabad, 1946.
The Bhagavad-Gita
Translated by S. Radhakrishnan.
George Allen and Unwin, London,
1948.
The Sita, the Song Supreme
Introduction by S. Radhakrishnan.
Taraporevala, Bombay, 1962.
The Bhagavad-Gita
Translated from the Sanskrit with an
introduction by Juan Mascaro, Pen¬
guin Books, Harmondsworth, London,
1962.
The Song of God Bhagavad-Gita
Translated by Swami Prabhavananda
and Christopher Isherwood with an
introduction by Aldous Huxley, Phoe¬
nix House, London, 1956.
ABOUT THE MAHABHARATA
Jnaneshvari
by Jnaneshvar, incorporating the text
of the Bhagavad-Gita (S. Radhakrish¬
nan translation). Translated from the
Marathi by V. G. Pradhan. Edited
and with an introduction by H. W.
Lambert (Vol. I). Unesco Collection
of Representative Works. George
Allen and Unwin, London, 1967
(52/6).
Gita, the Mother
by Gandhi.
Edited and published by A. T. Hin-
gorani, Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan,
Bombay, 1965.
The Teaching of the Gita
by Gandhi.
Edited and published by A. T. Hin-
gorani, Bharatiya Vidya Bhavan,
Bombay, 1962.
Ethnography of Ancient India
(Mahabharata)
by R. Shafert.
Harrassovitz, Wiesbaden, 1954.
On the meaning of the
Mahabharata
by V. S. Sukthankar.
Asiatic Society of Bombay, Bombay,
1957.
ABOUT BOTH EPICS
Ancient Indonesian Art
by A. J. Bernet Kempers.
Harvard University Press, Cambridge,
Mass., 1959.
Vyasa and Valmiki
by A. Ghose.
Sri Aurobindo Ashram, Pondicherry,
1956.
Art in Indonesia: Continuities and
Change
by. Claire Holt.
Cornell University Press, Ithaca,
New York, 1967.
Epics, Myths and Legends of
India
by Paul Thomas.
Taraporevala Sons and Co., Bombay,
1945.
The Loves of Krishna in Indian
Painting and Poetry
by W. G. Archer.
George Allen and Unwin, London,
1957.
A History of India (Vol. I)
by Romila Thapar. Penguin Books
Ltd., Harmondsworth, London 1966
(Pelican paperback, 7/6).
History of Indian and Indonesian
Art
by A. K. Coomaraswamy.
Goldston, London ; Hiersemann, Leip¬
zig ; Weyhe, New York, 1927.
1000 Mythological Characters
briefly described
by Edward Sylvester Ellis.
Noble and Noble, New York, 1927.
Indian Tales
by Romila Thapar.
G. Bell and Sons, London, 1961.
The Art of Indian Asia,
its Mythology and Transformation
by Heinrich Zimmer.
Edited by J. Campbell, Pantheon
Books, New York, 1953. 45
]]>
</page>
<page number="46">
<![CDATA[
Letters to the Editor
WAR OR PEACE ?
Sir,
Congratulations on the issue, "War
or Peace?" (August-September 1967).
It deserves the widest circulation par¬
ticularly among young people since it
makes us face up to our responsi¬
bilities and reveals the gravity of the
disarmament problem. A great deal
of nonsense has been written about
the problem and one often feels that
much of what is said about the critical
danger threatening us all has neither
rhyme nor reason. Your Issue, how¬
ever, was clear and concise, and I
particularly welcome the publication of
extracts from the Papal Encyclical. I
shall make sure that my family and
friends see the issue, not with the
idea of creating a "war psychosis", but
to encourage them to give deeper
thought to the problem.
Simone Aviron-Violet
Lyon, France
Sir,
Your August-September issue is a
wonderful presentation of facts that
affirm what is necessary for world
peace and international understanding.
I was so impressed with the articles
contributed by Philip Noel-Baker, His
Holiness Pope Paul VI and Unesco's
Director General, Mr René Maheu that
I ordered more copies which I shall
circulate among friends and members
of our local United Nations Associa¬
tion. I have subscribed to your maga¬
zine for four years and always find
it a mine of information (never a dull
copy).
A.E. Green
United Nations Association
Broadstone, U.K.
AFRICA'S SHORTAGE
OF DENTISTS
46
Sir,
The remarkable article by Nicholas
C. Otieno on training Africa's
scientists (June 1967) should also
have emphasized the serious shortage
of dentists in Africa.
If my information is correct, Africa
as a continent has only one dentist
for every 80,000 inhabitants. This
shortage is likely to increase unless
urgent steps are taken to expand
existing schools of dentistry in Dakar
and Lagos and unless new teaching
centres are established in the African
universities now being built.
Jacques Charon
Fédération Dentaire Internationale
Paris, France
NOISE POLLUTION
Sir,
The harmful effects of noise are
now invading the countryside. Two
reasons are the increasing use of
tractors and the opening of small
workshops which do not comply with
industrial health regulations, especially
for the prevention of damage to hear¬
ing. City dwellers seeking a few
weeks of rest and quiet In the coun¬
tryside are sometimes obliged to cut
short their vacations because certain
villages have become so noisy. Your
issue on Noise Pollution (July 1967)
will be of prime interest to country
people, particularly to school teachers,
since in small communities which have
neither doctor nor nurse, the teach¬
er ¡s the only person able to alert
people to the harmful effects of noise
on health.
Dr Pierre Rolland
Bourg-la-Reine, France
LINK BETWEEN FRIENDS
Sir,
I love the "Unesco Courier", as do
my friends who receive it when I
finish reading it. One, a teacher in
Kobe, Japan, says It is the best
magazine he reads, and it is always
in demand at his school library.
Sometimes there are several areas of
Interest so the magazine goes to
several friends in different countries.
Hugh Stewart Smith
Washington D.C., U.S.A.
THE NAMING OF MONTREAL
Sir,
The caption of a photo Illustrating
the article on Canada ("A Culture in
the Making") ¡n your April 1967 issue,
tells us that Jacques Cartier gave the
name "Montreal" to the city he
founded near Mount Royal.
Francis the First, of France, in
consenting to help Jacques Cartier to
search for new lands to the west of
the Island of Hierro (most westerly
Island of the Canaries), and in agree¬
ment with the Pope, instructed the
explorer to give the name "Montreal"
to the first town founded by him in
Canada. This was to honour the
youny Cardinal de Medicls, Bishop of
Avignon in France and of Montreale, a
small town near Palermo, Sicily.
Cardinal de Medicls had been
instrumental in obtaining the Pope's
agreement to Cartier's enterprise.
Eugene Guernier
Institute of Political Studies
University of Paris
A VAST INVENTORY
Sir,
The Corpus Vitrearum Med/7 Aevi,
the inventory of Europe's medieval
stained glass windows, is by no means
an "unprecedented undertaking", as
described in your April 1967 issue.
It is one facet of a colossal enterprise,
a vast and almost universal cultural
Inventory undertaken since 1924 by
the International Academic Union,
which comprises 27 of the world's
principal academies in the fields of
Letters and the Ethical and Political
Sciences. In addition to a score of
major undertakings, including the
Corpus Vitrearum Medii Aevi, the
Union sponsors many similar pub¬
lications.
Our Union, whose headquarters
are at the Académie Royale de Bel¬
gique (Brussels), benefits by sub¬
sidies from the International Council
for Philosophy and Humanistic Studies.
These subsidies are drawn from funds
which the International Council, as an
international non-governmental organi¬
zation, receives from Unesco.
Prof. Henri Lavachery
Honorary Perpetual Secretary
to the Académie Royale
de Belgique, Brussels, Belgium
NEW PRICE OF THE 'UNESCO COURIER'
Repeated rises in production and distribution costs have made
it necessary to adjust the annual subscription rates and single
copy price of the UNESCO COURIER.
On January 1, 1968 our new rates will go into effect as follows:
SINGLE
COPY PRICE
1/9 stg.
40 cents (Canada)
1.20 French francs
: 1 YEAR
SUBSCRIPTION
17/6 stg.
$4.00
12 F.
' 2 YEAR
SUBSCRIPTION
32/- stg.
Subscribers will be notified of the new rates in other currencies
by Unesco's National Distributors. Where available these rates
will be published in the list of National Distributors (opposite) of
our next issue.
Listed below are the new annual subscription, ratés in the follow¬
ing countries: Belgium: 170 FB - Denmark: 20 D.Kr. - Fed. Rep.
of Germany: 12 DM - Israel : £1 9.50 - Mexico : 30 pesos m/n -
Netherlands: 10 fl. - Spain: 160 pts - Switzerland: 12 Fr.S.
]]>
</page>
<page number="47">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER INDEX 1967
January
FLORENCE, VENICE. International campaign for Florence and Venice
(R. Maheu). Years to repair the damage (B. Molajoli). Plight of
Florentine artisans (R. Keating). Dimensions of a disaster. Hospital
for paintings (H.J. Plenderleith). Anatomy of the flood (D. Tonini).
Cimabue's "Crucifix". Ghiberti's "Gates of Paradise". eArt treasures
(12) Adam and Eve (Florence).
February
THE POPULATION CRUNCH. Three centuries of demography
(B. Urlanis). World population prospects (J. Fourastié). Hanging cities
ahead? International emergency technical aid service (E.D. Mills).
Landslides in Rio de Janeiro. Ethics in the mass media (R. Maheu).
New home for Rameses' Nubian temples. Unesco in the service of
peace (V. de Lipski). Art treasures (13) Spirit figure mask (Gabon).
March
APARTHEID. A country divided (Unesco report on Apartheid). Effects
of Apartheid on culture: Price of segregation (A. Paton); Forbidden
dialogue (L. Nkosi); Seeds of wrath (D. Brutus); The dying minds
(R. Segal); The fettered spirit (B. Breytenbach). South Africa's
wasted manpower (ILO report). Apartheid and the church. Art trea¬
sures (14) Hands (Auguste Rodin).
April
EXPO 67. Canada's culture in the making (F.C. James). Expo 67:
the world In a thousand acres. Canada's far north (I. Baird). Artists
of the tundra. Stained-glass of medieval Europe (colour pages).
Well-springs of Czech literature (A. Hoffmeister). Kenya's wild animal
orphanage (R. Greenough). Art treasures (15) Regal head (Hungary).
May
Birth of wheat and maize farming; early
(J. Hawkes). When Orpheus struck the
New mathematical horizons; dawn of the
Did the Japanese bring the art of pottery
to Ecuador 5,000 years ago? (B.J. Meggers). The sailing vessel
comes into its own (L. Gottschalk). The second scientific revolution
(J. Bronowski). Sinews of industrial society; era of synthetic mate¬
rials (CF. Ware, K.M. Panikkar, J. M. Romein). Study of animal
behaviour (J. Oppenheimer). Offspring of Icarus. Art treasures (16)
Wrought by master goldsmiths (Colombia).
June
AFRICA AND THE AFRICAN GENIUS. Birth of a new Africa
(G. d'Arboussier). Studying Africa's history (K.O. Dike). African arch¬
itecture. Protecting Africa's artistic heritage (E. Eyo). Map of Africa
HISTORY OF MANKIND,
domestication of animals
trembling lyre (L. Pareti).
geographic spirit (P. Wolff),
1967: 39 flags in full colour. African literature (E. Mphahlele). 21
writers of tropical Africa. Vernacular languages (P. Daigne). Train¬
ing Africa's scientists (N.C. Otieno). African bookshelf. Art trea¬
sures (17) From Africa's ancient past (Nigeria).
July
NOISE POLLUTION. Down with decibels (O. Schenker-Sprüngli).
Architects of silence (C. Stramentov). Reducing street and air traffic
noise (L.L. Beranek). Supersonic "boom carpet". Noise abatement
in Cordoba (G.L. Fuchs). Noise and health (G. Lehmann). Dange¬
rous sounds we cannot hear. Art treasures (18) Nostalgia for nature
(Henri Rousseau).
August-September
WAR OR PEACE? Image of a disarmed world (Unesco inquiry).
Science and disarmament (P. Noel-Baker). Challenge of peace
(V. Ardatovsky). Development new name for peace (Encyclical Letter
of Pope Paul VI). To build a new order in the world (R. Maheu).
Kuboyama and the saga of the 'Lucky Dragon' (R. Hudson). Man does
not live by politics alone (J. Nehru). Auroville, India's international
city of concord. Tistou of the green fingers (M. Druon). Unesco and
the search for peace. Art treasures (19) Hand of the Bogomils
(Yugoslavia).
October
MARIE CURIE. A life dedicated to science. The rarest, most precious
vital force (M. Curie). The dreamer in Warsaw (L. Infeld). The
woman we called "la patronne" (M. Perey). Menace of "extinct"
volcanoes (H. Tazieff). Ruben Dario (E.R. Monegal). World Food
Programme (C. Mackenzie). Great men, great events. Art treasures
(20) Altar boy (Korea).
November
U.S.S.R. TODAY. Metamorphosis of a continent (N. Mikhailov). From
illiteracy to astronautics (V. Elyutin). Complexities of modern education
(M. Prokofiev). Reflections on Soviet culture (S. Gerasimov). New
skyline in Moscow. 700,000 scientists in the U.S.S.R. (M. Lavrentiev).
TV programme girdling the world (P. de Latil). Journey to Ethiopia's
past (R.H. Howland).
December
TWO GREAT EPICS OF ASIA. Mahabharata, Ramayana
(A.L. Basham). Collective dream of a continent (A. de Silva). Hanu¬
man, leader of the monkeys. The epics in the art of South Asia
(B.N. Goswamy). Exile of Rama. Shadow theatres of Thailand and
Cambodia. Kathakali and the dance-drama of India (C. Kunchu Nair).
India's ancient heroes on celluloid (B.D. Garga). Art treasures (21)
Ravana shaking Mt.Kailasa (Inda).
WHERE TO RENEW YOUR SUBSCRIPTION
and order other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzat, Press Department, Royal
Afghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Longmans of Australia Pty Ltd., Railway Crescent,
Croydon, Victoria; sub-agent United Nations Associa¬
tion of Australia, Victorian Division, 4th Floor, Askew
House, 364 Lonsdale St., Melbourne C. I. (Victoria);
for the Unesco Courier only : Dominie Pty Ltd, 463 Pitt-
water Road, Brookvale (N. S.W.) AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C°., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
BELGIUM. All publications: Editions
"Labor", 342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-We-
tenschappelijke Uitgeverij Belgiëlei 1 47, Antwerp. I. For
TheUnesco Courier and art slides (488 FB) only :
Louis De Lannoy, 112, rue du Trône, Brussels S. CCP
3380.00. CANADA. Queen's Printer, Ottawa, Ont.
CEYLON. Lake House Bookshop, Sir Chittam-
palan Gardiner Mawata, P.O.B. 244, Colombo, 2
CHINA. World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chungking South
Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa). CYPRUS.
"MAM", Archbishop Makarios 3rd Avenue, P.O. Box
1722, Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahranicni
literatura Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. Ejnar
Munksgaard, Ltd., 6, Norregade, Copenhagen K.
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O.
Box 120, Addis Ababa FINLAND. Akateeminen
Kirjakauppa, 2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki.
FRANCE. Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7'. CCP. 12598-48. GERMANY. All
publications: R. Oldenbourg Verlag, Rosenheimerstrasse
145, Munich, 8. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed only)
Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160, Hamburg-Bahrenfeld, CCP.
276650 GHANA Methodist Book Depot
Ltd., Atlantis House, Commercial Street, P.O.B. 100, Cape
Coast. GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom.
GREECE. Librairie H. Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade,
Athens; Librairie Eleftheroudakis, Nikkis 4, Athens.
HONG-KONG. Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road'
Kowloon. HUNGARY. Akadémiai Konyvesbolt,
Vici u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Kónyvtárosok Bolt|a,
Nepkoztarsasag utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND.
Snaebiörn Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9, Reykjavik.
INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd., Nicol
Road, Ballard Estate, Bombay 1 ; 17 Chiccaranian Avenue,
Calcutta 13; 36a, Mount Road, Madras 2; Kanson
House, 1/24 Asaf AN Road, P.O. Box 386, New Delhi.
1; Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co., 17
Park Street, Calcutta 1 6 and Scindia House, New Delhi :
Indian National Commission for Cooperation with
Unesco, Ministry of Education, New Delhi 3.
INDONESIA. P.T.N. "Permata-Nusantara"
c/o Department of Commerce 22, Djalan Nusantara
Djakarta' IRAQ. McKenzie's Bookshop, Al-Rashid
Street, Baghdad; University Bookstore, University
of Baghdad, P.O. Box 75, Baghdad IRELAND. The
National Press, 2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin.
4. ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formerly Blum-
stein's Bookstores, 3 5 Allenby Road and 48 Nahlat
Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv JAMAICA. Sang-
ster's Book Room, 91 Harbour Street, Kingston.
JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd., 6 Tori-Nichome, Nihon¬
bashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo Central, Tokyo
JORDAN. Joseph I. Bahous & Co., Dar-ul-Kutub,
Salt Road. P.O B. 66, Amman. KENYA. E.S.A.
Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi KOREA.
Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O. Box Cen¬
tral 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The Kuwait Bookshop Co.,
Ltd., P. O. Box 2942, Kuwait LIBERIA. Cole and
Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286. Monrovia
LUXEMBURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-
Rue. Luxemburg MALAYSIA.Federal
Publications Ltd., Times House, River Valley Road,
Singapore, 9; Pudu Building (3rd floor), 110, Jalan
Pudu. Kuala Lumpur MALTA. Sapienza's
Library, 26 Kingsway, Valletta, MAURITIUS.
Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street, Port-
Louis MONACO. British Library, 30, Bid.
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Ni|hoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague.
NETHERLANDS ANTILLES. G. C.
T. Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V., Willemstad, Cura¬
çao. N.A. _ NEW ZEALAND. Govern¬
ment Printing Office, 20, Molesworth Street (Private
Bag), Wellington; Government Bookshops: Auckland
(P.O. Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721), Dune-
din (P.O.Box 1104) NIGERIA. C.M.S. Book-
shops, P.O. Box 174, Lagos NORWAY.
All publications: A.S. Bokhjornet, Akersgt 41-
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Norvesens Litte-
raturjeneste, Box 6175, Oslo 6, PA
KISTAN. The West-Pak Publishing Co. Ltd., Unesco
Publications House, P.O. Box 374 G.P.O., Lahore;
Showrooms : Urdu Bazar, Lahore, and 57-58 Murree
Highway, G/6-1, Islamabad. PHILIPPINES. The Modern
Book Co., Inc., 928 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila POLAND. All publications: ORWN PAN Palac
Kultury, Warsaw. For the Unecco Courier only:
"RUSH", ul. Wronia. 23, Warsaw 10
PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria Portu¬
gal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO.
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115.
Apartado 1 91 2, Hato Rey. SOUTHERN RHODESIA.
Textbook Sales (PVT) Ltd., 67, Union Avenue, Salisbury.
SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P. O. Box 1118,
Khartoum. SWEDEN. All publications : A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stock¬
holm 16. For the Unesco Courier: The United,
Nations Association of Sweden, Vasagatan 15-17, Stock¬
holm, C SWITZERLAND. All publications :
Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse, Zurich. Payot, rue Grenus 6,
1 21 1 , Geneva 1 1 , CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. TANZAN IA. Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O.B. 9030 Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit Mansion, 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu .Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop, P.O. Box 1 45, Kampala SOUTH AFRICA.
All publications : Van Schaik's Bookstore (Pty) Ltd.,
Libri Building. Church Street, P.O. Box 724, Pretoria.
For the Unesco Courier (single copies) only : Central
News Agency P.O. Box ** 033, Johannesburg.
UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC (EGYPT). Librairie
Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil, Cairo. Sub/agent :
La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-Pasha, Cairo.
UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops
in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester.
Birmingham and Bristol. UNITED STATES,
Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St, New York.
N.Y. 10016 U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaja Kniga,
Moscow. G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska
Knjiga Teraziie, 27, Belgrade; NAPRIJED, Trg. Republi¬
ke 17, Zagreb.
]]>
</page>
<page number="48">
<![CDATA[
The two ancient Indian epics, the Mahabharata and the Ramayana, have fired the
imagination of generations of poets and artists in India and much of Asia. Among
the countless works of art inspired by stories from these works are thousands of
bas-reliefs and sculptures carved in the stupendous 12th-century Khmer temple-
city complex of Angkor (Cambodia). In the largest of the temples, Angkor Wat,
scenes of epic grandeur from both epics cover over 13,000 square feet on the
walls of just the first floor gallery. This detail is from a panel depicting armies of
monkeys helping Rama, hero of the Ramayana, to vanquish his enemies.
]]>
</page>
</document>
