<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078438eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
I
A window
open on the world
1
<
&r
¿L
\0
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
2&*¡&Í2¡
WrW
m
mm
mBk
ran
jjMf
SslilBHslti!
HR
-
flWWJii
wttiïm
WÊmËÊÊÈfï
' '.Y'
EM»
HR
l3HH!t¥*~":
¡3ErÍo&Í
SB«
E !
:' "':
TREASURES
OF
WORLD ART
K(m) ' i
s
Thai/and ||
Walking Buddha
of Sukhothai
im
H
<» I H HI
Hrai few*
1 te g '-:--.'- y y'
This graceful bronze
statue (116 cms. high) is
one of the distinctive
"walking Buddhas"
sculpted in the round by
14th-century artists of
Sukhothai in northern
Thailand. One of
Thailand's earliest
settlements, Sukhothai
was the capital of an
independent Thai
kingdom founded in the
13th century. Impressive
remains of monasteries
and temples have
survived to show its
importance as a landmark
in Thailand's cultural
herkage. Unesco is to
launch an international
campaign for the
preservation of this
historic site.
mm
lililí.
ÜÜi
-
Photo Fine Arts Department,
Ministry of Education, Thailand
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco COUPICF
JANUARY 1978 31ST YEAR
PUBLISHED IN 17 LANGUAGES
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
Japanese
Italian
Hindi
Tamil
Hebrew
Persian
Dutch
Portuguese
Turkish
Urdu
Catalan
Published monthly by UNESCO
The United Nations
Educational, Scientific
and Cultural Organization
Sales and distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy,.75700 Paris
Subscription rates
1 year: 35 French Francs
2 years: 58 FF
Binder for a year's issues: 24 FF
The UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in
August and September when it is bi-monthly (11 issues a
year). For list of distributors see inside back cover.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may
be reprinted providing the credit line reads "Reprinted from
the UNESCO COURIER", plus date of issue, and three
voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed, must bear author's name. Non-copyright photos
will be supplied on request. Unsolicited manuscripts
cannot be returned unless accompanied by an interna¬
tional reply coupon covering postage. Signed articles
express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily
represent the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors
of the UNESCO COURIER. Photo captions and head¬
lines are written by the Unesco Courier staff.
The Unesco Courier is produced in microform (micro¬
film and/or microfiche) by: (1) University Microfilms
(Xerox), Ann Arbor. Michigan 48100, U.S.A. ; (2) N.C.R.
Microcard Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 111 West 40th
Street, New York, U.S.A. ; (3) Bell and Howell Co..
Old Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 44691, U.S.A.
The Unesco Courier is indexed monthly in the Readers'
Guide to Periodical Literature, published by H. W.
Wilson Co., New York, and in Current Contents -
Education, Philadelphia, U.S.A.
Editorial Office
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris -
Editor-in-Chief
René Caloz
Assistant Editor-in-Chief .
Olga Rodel
France
Managing Editors
English Edition
French Edition
Spanish Edition
Russian Edition
German Edition
Arabic Edition
Japanese Edition
Italian Edition
Hindi Edition
Tamil Edition
Hebrew Edition
Persian Edition
Dutch Edition
Portuguese Edition
Turkish Edition
Urdu . Edition
Francisco Fernandez-Santos (Paris)
Victor Goliachkov (Paris)
: Werner Merkli (Berne)
: Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Kazuo Akao (Tokyo)
Maria Remiddi (Rome)
H. L. Sharma (Delhi)
M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Alexander Broido (Tel Aviv)
Fereydoun Ardalan (Teheran)
Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Mefra Arkin (Istanbul)
Hakim Mohammed Said (Karachi) ,
Assistant Editors
English Edition : Roy Malkin
French Edition :
Spanish Edition : Jorge Enrique Adoum
Research : Christiane Boucher
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design : Robert Jacquemin
All correspondence should be addressed
to the Editor-in-Chief in Paris
page
4 LEARNING TO SHARE THE SAME GLOBE
by William J. Piatt
8 THE COLOURFUL WORLD OF 'THIRD THEATRE'
Testing new forms of communication at
a unique theatre 'laboratory'
by Ferdiñando Taviani
17 SPACE CO-OPERATION IN ORBIT
The benefits of international research programmes
by Aleksei A. Leonov
22 HOW RISKY IS GENETIC ENGINEERING?
Scientists from 24 countries review the latest findings
by Dan Behrman
27 BRUNELLESCHI
600th anniversary of the Florentine
who launched Renaissance architecture
by Francesco Gurrieri
30 VIEWPOINTS ON PERSPECTIVE
33 IN BRIEF
34 LETTERS TO THE EDITOR
TREASURES OF WORLD ART
THAILAND: Walking Buddha of Sukhothai
l-IV NEWS FROM UNESCO
Special supplement
Cover
Some 200 performers, many of them young
and little-known, recently took part in an
exciting 10-day international workshop on
group theatre held in Bergamo (Italy) under
the auspices of Unesco and the International
Theatre Institute. (See article page 8.) Cover
shows I Made Bandem, a master of Balinese
masked Topeng drama. During the workshop
he demonstrated with his wife and sons
how traditional Topeng acting techniques
are transmitted from generation to
generation.
Photo © Maurizio Buscarino, Bergamo, Italy
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
I
Above, a batch of globes from a Soviet
factory awaiting dispatch to schools.
Right, schoolgirls in Quito (Ecuador) pool
efforts during a geography lesson. Learning
to share
the same
globe
by William J. Piatt
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
THE schoolchildren of today, who will
come of age as the calendar turns to
the 21st century, will be confronted
as adults with an unprecedented challenge.
They will have to learn to cope with global
interdependence. Indeed, they must do so
if they are to survive.
Interdependence in the affairs of soci¬
eties and nations is by no means new.
Trade is as old as recorded history. Cultur¬
al exchange through travel, through the
diffusion of art, music, and literature and
through communication, are part of an
almost universal heritage. Science owes
much to international exchange. In
politics, interdependent relationships
through alliances, ententes and treaties,
and even intergovernmental organizations
of world-wide membership, existed before
WILLIAM J. PLATT of the U.S.A. was direc¬
tor of Unesco's Department of Planning and
Financing of Education and then Deputy Assis¬
tant Director-General for Education (1970-1975).
the present generation was born. In some
cases, they have existed for centuries.
What is new, as we move into the 21st
century, is that whereas earlier generations
throughout the world could practise a par¬
tial and largely selfish, "dilettante" inter¬
dependence, today's generations will have
to practise the real thing.
Dilettante interdependence meant that
societies and nations could choose the rela¬
tions which suited them best. One country
could, for example, buy raw materials from
another, while denying access to its own
markets for consumer goods. It could be
an active member of an international orga¬
nization and yet refuse that organization's
help or advice when sensitive domestic
issues were involved. It could appeal for
protection of the environment while per¬
mitting or even encouraging pollution.
When compromise or sacrifice of its own
interests were the price of further interde¬
pendence, or when justice demanded such
accommodations, it could retreat into its
shell, claiming that the matter at stake,
despite its side-effects on others, was of
domestic concern only, and immune from
outside interference.
Up to now, the issue of true interdepen¬
dence has been shelved. This is because
most complex relationships, when they are
not stretched to their limits, are quite able
to tolerate abuse. Let us take as an illustra¬
tion, a network of highways, with their
access streets and roads. Under light traf¬
fic conditions, drivers who commit offen¬
ces seldom tie up the whole system. On
the other hand, when the network is ope¬
rating at full capacity, during the rush hour,
a driving offence or accident usually brings
everything to a standstill and often starts a
chain-reaction of incidents. It may take
hours to set the traffic moving again.
Similarly, the earlier dilettante inter¬
dependence sometimes crueland
inequitable in its effects worked relatively
well in a world of seemingly endless hori¬
zons, where each nation was free to follow
its own course, where population was not
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
pressing on available land and resources
and where common definitions of justice
and human rights were not yet required.
But the modern world is a finite, limited
and crowded place, and is becoming more
so. Its population^ 4 billion today, will
increase to 7 billion at the beginning of the
21st century. Now there is less room for
manoeuvre and for the toleration of abuse.
Survival thus depends on a minimum of
global interdependence. If education is to
contribute to its creation, changes will be
required everywhere.
Minimal interdependence will have to
cover a number of related subjects on a
worldwide scale: security; economic rela¬
tions, including the supply and use of
energy, resources and food, together with
co-operation for development; and justice
and human rights.
Present arrangements for interdepen¬
dence in all these fields are both rudimen¬
tary and changing. But this is no excuse
for education to continue to neglect them
until they crystallize. The quest for a new
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
world order is an open one; it should be
brought into every classroom so that those
who will have to live with the consequen¬
ces of interdependence may understand its
mechanisms and the process of give and
take which it requires.
As fa r as peace and security a re concern¬
ed, the United Nations Organization was
created in 1945 primarily "to save succeed¬
ing generations from the scourge of war".
To do so, a considerable, though under¬
used and under-funded machinery for
peace-keeping and conciliation is available.
But in practice, international security
depends more on threats by sovereign
nations or blocs of nations to use military
force. Distrust breeds distrust, while a
nuclear sword of Damocles hangs over the
world, whose nations spend 163 times
more on armaments than they do on U.N.
activities for development and peace.
But if governments do, on occasion, turn
to U.N. peace-keeping arrangements,
usually when unilateral efforts have failed,
we must realize that an institution is like a
muscle of the human body. Without pro¬
per exercise, it will atrophy. The U.N.
peace-keeping apparatus should become
more of a first, rather than a last resort.
International economic interdependence
has become the subject of elaborate ar¬
rangements. But colonialism, imperialism,
and dilettante interdependence have left a
legacy of enormous and increasing inequa¬
lities in a world where poverty, malnutrition
and disease condemn hundreds of millions
Education for world understanding
The quest for a new world order based on interdependence between peoples
is one of the greatest challenges facing humanity today. If tomorrow's adults
are to understand the mechanisms of interdependence, teaching programmes
must be given a global perspective and develop a sense of commitment to the
world community. Unesco has for many years encouraged the development of
education for international understanding. Its Associated Schools Project, in
which over 1,000 schools and teacher training institutions from 66 countries
take part, seeks to promote wider knowledge of international problems and
co-operation and to foster the study of different peoples and cultures. Above
left and below, contrasting images of solitude and community at school.
Above, children dance a round in work by Turkish artist Ibrahim Balaban.
of people to a sub-human existence, if not
to a merciful early death. The food-hunger
balance is precarious: world grain reserves
declined from 105 days' supply in 1961 to
31 days' in 1976.
The U.N. Environment Programme
reports that much of the world's fertile soil
is being degraded, contaminated or lost,
and that in many cases the process is irre¬
versible. Until recently the world was obli¬
vious to inequalities of access to energy
and other non-renewable resources which
cut across generations and political boun¬
daries alike. The depletion of these resour¬
ces and the pollution of the environment
compromise the heritage of future genera¬
tions, as does the exploitation of the sea-
beds and space, whose resources might
have been obvious elements of the univer¬
sal patrimony.
There was a time when we could trust in
science and technology to make good any
deficiencies. But the former has its limits,
while a more modest and useful conception
of the latter's contribution is emerging from
the movement for "appropriate techno¬
logy".
Co-operation for development is crucial
to economic interdependence. The first
objective of Third World development-
political liberation from colonialism-
has been substantially achieved. But the
economic gap continues to widen,
although the slow but hopeful search for a
new international economic order promises
more equitable and mutually beneficial co¬
operation for development between deve¬
loping and industrialized countries.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
In the last analysis, we will only achieve
true interdependence by observing global
ethics and justice. Although the world has
only the flimsiest machinery for this pur¬
pose, we are, paradoxically, closer to
understanding the ethics and justice of
interdependence than we are to under¬
standing its other aspects. The improve¬
ment of justice depends in part on the new
international economic order which is
evolving. But a magnificent edifice for
interdependence with justice exists
already, with its foundations in the work of
those who drafted the U.N. Charter, the
Constitution of Unesco and the Universal
Declaration of Human Rights, which antici¬
pated the true interdependence to come.
The Universal Declaration of Human
Rights begins:
"Whereas recognition of the inherent
dignity and of the equal and inalienable
rights of all members of the human family
is the foundation of freedom, justice and
peace in the world..."
Its 30 articles spell out rights "without
distinction of any kind, such as race,
colour, sex, language, religion, political or
other opinion, national or social origin, pro¬
perty, birth or other status", which should
be the subject of lessons in every class¬
room.
Although these principles are binding on
members of the U.N., they are only par¬
tially realized. The lag between principle
and practice should come as no surprise
when we remember the time required for
even partial implementation of the Magna
Carta of 1215 or of the 200-year-old Bill of
Rights of the United States of America.
But now justice, like other aspects of 21st-
century interdependence, is becoming less
tolerant of abuse and neglect.
What does the shift from dilettante
interdependence to a true minimal inter¬
dependence signify in terms of educational
reform?
It does not mean reduced attention to
the identity of self, family, community,
province, nation or region. On the contrary,
civic training in these fields will fit a
student for world citizenship.
Nor does education for interdependence
imply a movement away from cultural
diversity. Interdependence itself depends
on specialization, and reflects the division
of labour in cultural as well as economic
terms. If anything, education for interde¬
pendence will be more complex and varied
than it was in the past. True interde¬
pendence will not be free of conflict and
confrontation. But mankind's common
destiny will be the theme for reconciling
differences and for resolving conflicts
without violence.
Thirdly, education for global interde¬
pendence does not imply the introduction
of special courses in international relations,
in inter-cultural studies or in interde¬
pendence itself. Instead, what is required
is the injection of a global perspective into
all parts of the curriculum.
What is the present state of education
for global citizenship and interdependence?
With some rare but encouraging excep¬
tions, teachers throughout the world
seem to have been listening to another set
of drums.
The colourful world
of Third Theatre"
Performers from five continents
test new forms of communication
at a unique theatre 'laboratory'
by Ferdinando Taviani
CONTINUED PAGE 32
8
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
FOR several days and nights at the end
of last summer, the old town of
Bergamo in northern Italy was
caught up in a swirl of fantastic and col¬
ourful events which left its inhabitants
agog.
A wave of exotic intruders invaded the
streets, turning the daily routine of work
and leisure topsy-turvy and driving away
the cares and anxieties of the towns¬
people. Fantastic birdlike creatures on
stilts strutted through town flapping their
FERDINANDO TAVIANI, professor of his¬
tory of theatre and the performing arts at the
university of Lecce (Italy), has published a
number of studies on the Commedià dell'Arte
and modern theatre. He is also the author of
II Libro dell'Odin (Feltrinel/i, Milan, 1975) and
Lo Straniero che Danza (Studio Forma, Turin,
1977), which, present the work of Denmark's
Odin Theatre, whose founder Eugenio Barba
is a leading figure in the "Third Theatre"
movement described in this article.
Versatile performers from many countries recently met in the beautiful
Italian town of Bergamo to take part in an international workshop on group
theatre. In a carnival atmosphere, actors, musicians, dancers, acrobats and
circus people from a diversity of cultural backgrounds worked together on
equal terms and shared their experience. Left, "albatross" with diaphanous
wings dance on stilts during a performance by Bergamo's Pocket Theatre.
Above, performer from Denmark's Odin Teatret troupe.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
One of the highlights of the
Bergamo workshop was an
onstage encounter between
distinguished exponents of
two forms of traditional
Eastern drama: the Japanese
IMoh theatre, in which the
actors are also singers and
dancers, and Kathakali, an
ancient form of danced
drama from southern India.
Photo below shows Noh
actor Hideo Kanze (at left) in
the midst of this unique
improvisation session with
Kathakali master Krishnan
Nambudiri. Right, masked
actor on stilts during a
performance by the Piccolo
Teatro of Pontedera (Italy).
, wings. Clowns, harlequins, buskers and
dancers mingled with the crowds, and
figures in outlandish masks and costumes
plied the streets. Actors, singers and
circus people had descended on Bergamo
from the four corners of the earth.
The unusual happenings in Bergamo
were part of an "International workshop
on group theatre", presented by the Inter¬
national Theatre Institute, under Unesco's
auspices and with Unesco's aid. The work¬
shop was a response to a crisis in the
theatre, which periodically gets stuck in
the rut of traditionah'sm and repetition,
and like any other art form which loses its
vitality, has to break out of the deadlock.
One of the boldest recent innovations in
Western theatre was the appearance in the
early 1960s of what (by analogy with the
Third World) has been dubbed "Third
Theatre". Outside the mainstream of tra¬
ditional theatre, it also stands apart from
avant-garde or experimental theatre, which
seeks to transcend tradition in the search
for new forms of expression.
In the last 15 years Third Theatre groups
have mushroomed all over the world in
Europe, North and South America, Aus¬
tralia and Japan. Few of the artists involv¬
ed have had traditional theatre training,
but they are not amateurs. They do not
consider a stage performance, however
original and polished it may be, as the
ultimate goal of their work. To them the¬
atre means involvement in the world and a
way of changing human relationships: it is
part of the living fabric of society.
10
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
They reject the age-old split between
actors and audience and look on the the¬
atre as a creative workshop, a laboratory
of human life. Instead of being merely a
formal means of expression, it is a way of
life and a means of communication.
In Third Theatre, the dividing walls that
used to separate the different arts of the
entertainment world have come tumbling
down. The idea of the performer as a
specialist is dead. Actors must also be
dancers, singers, jugglers and acrobats.
They discard the dull clothing and stereo¬
typed gestures of modern life, dress up in
Drama of
masks and
make-up
At Bergamo masters of O
traditional Eastern theatre
demonstrated their techniques
of make-up and masks, age-old
ways of helping spectators to
identify stock characters.
Krishnan Nambudiri created a
traditional character in
Kathakali theatre (1 and 3).
Rice-paste, overlaid with
painted designs, is the basic
ingredient in Kathakali make¬
up, which takes several hours
to apply. (4) A performer from
Greenland made up as a
sorceress. (2) Harlequin mask
from Commedià dell'Arte, a
form of improvised drama that
originated in 16th-century Italy.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
, shimmering materials, don masks, and
parade around on stilts. Instead of merely
acting a role, they express the creative
potential which all human beings possess
but rarely have a chance to display.
The expression "Third Theatre" was
coined by Eugenio Barba, the founder of
Denmark's Odin Teatret. It today describes
the activities of hundreds of groups, most
of which are unknown on the established
theatre circuit of the world's cultural
capitals.
In 1976, Eugenio Barba was asked by
Unesco and the International Theatre Ins¬
titute to organize an International work¬
shop of theatrical research on the theme
of Third Theatre. The workshop was held
in Belgrade that autumn, during the world
season of the Theatre of the Nations. (1)
"What interests me," says Barba, "is
that the theatre can form and sustain new
pueblos. I use the Spanish word inten¬
tionally, because some theatre groups to¬
day do resemble pueblos, or villages, in
both senses of the termon the one hand
as places where people live and have their
home, and on the other as communities
of persons with a common past".
Urban theatre, whether "institutionaliz¬
ed" or experimental, does not put down
roots in local soil. Its existence is based
on words, on paper, and on the opinions
of the critics. It needs an audience, and
an audience (however boisterously it ex-
At a working session in
Bergamo, participants
observe the movements of a
member of Japan's Buto Sho
group who was leading them
in rigorous training inspired
by Japanese martial arts.
One of the most popular
"happenings" at Bergamo
was a carnival improvised by
the 15-member Catalan Els
Comediants group. Below,
the crowds join in as a giant
masquerader leads the dance
in a Bergamo street.
presses its approval or disapproval) is
essentially passive. In the words of the
Brazilian Augusto Boal, one of the pro¬
phets of the new theatre in the Americas,
a spectator is "always somehow less than
a human being".
The world's major theatre companies
aim to attract the attention of an élite of
media people, critics, and in some cases
the general public. But their work does
not bite deep into life. Third Theatre, on
the other hand, creates a village atmos¬
phere, and Third Theatre groups them¬
selves constitute a kind of village, even
though they do not always originate in
rural communities. Third Theatre is a
place where human relationships are in¬
vestigated and human bonds are created.
Its function is ethical rather than aesthetic
and its purpose is to rescue people from
loneliness.
These guiding principles inspired the
work of the 30 groups which took part in
last summer's Bergamo worshop, which
ended with a mammoth series of non-stop
performances, transforming the town into
(DThe Theatre of the Nations was founded by the
International Theatre Institute in 1955. For 15 years,
many ot the world's most famous companies took
part in its season in Paris. Since 1975, it has moved
about, first to Warsaw (1975), and then to Belgrade
(1976), Paris (1977) and Caracas (1978).
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
a theatre. They came from many parts of
the world: the United Kingdom, Argentina,
France, Greenland, Japan, Italy, Peru,
Switzerland, Spain, Belgium, Poland,
Uruguay, the United States, Colombia,
Australia, Iceland, Denmark and Sweden.
None of them was so famous that it
arrived in Bergarno to a fanfare of recogni¬
tion. Some were even unknown in their
own countries. Others came surrounded
by a vague aura of scandal created by
conventionally-minded and blinkered critics
who saw only elements of fantasy and
absurdity in their work.
Some great masters of Eastern and
Western theatre took part in the workshop,
including Jerzy Grotowski of Poland;
Hideo Kanze, one of the greatest inter¬
preters of Japanese Noh theatre; Krishnan
Nambudiri, an actor in India's Kathakali
theatre; and I Made Bandem an his family,
who are continuing the tradition of Bali-
nese dancing and comic theatre.
The working sessions began each morn¬
ing at seven and sometimes went on until
late at night. Time was set aside for semi
nars, whose participants, in addition to the
performers listed above, included the KSEK
theatre group from Japan, the Roy Hart
theatre, the International Visual Theatre (a
group of deaf and dumb performers) and
the Cardiff Laboratory from the U.K.
For most of the day and in the evenings,
the public could join in the workshop acti¬
vities. These sessions attracted growing
audiences of up to 1,000, consisting of
young people from France, Switzerland
and elsewhere in Italy, as well as the
townsfolk of Bergamo.
The spectators did not see a "show"
in the usual sense of the term, but the
patient and dedicated process of theatrical
creation. One set of activities neatly
dovetailed into the next. A set piece would
lead to a spell of improvisation which
sometimes reached the point where per¬
formers broke the bounds of their own
skill and knowledge.
On 1 September; actors from the East
demonstrated their techniques of using
masks and make-up. Then Hideo Kanze
came on stage, having discarded his Noh
Two cultures with a single likeness:
there is a striking resemblance
between the Noh mask worn by the
Japanese actor Hideo Kanze (below)
and the expression of the drummer
from Greenland's Tukak group (lower
photo).
Photos © Maurizio Buscarino, Bergamo, Italy
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
mask for a Commedià dell'Arte mask
designed by Italian sculptor Donato Sar¬
tori. Kanze and Krishnan Nambudiri then
began an improvisation session with a
"sorceress" from Greenland and a Bali-
nese clown.
Other masked performers joined in: a
group of zannl (buffoons) from the Corn-
media dell'Arte; masqueraders from the
Catalan Els Comediants group; and pa-
pier-mâché puppets from the Piccolo Tea¬
tro of Pontedera, a little town in Tuscany.
An actress from Pontedera wore a grotes¬
que mask fashioned from an olive-tree
root, while another actress from the Pot-
lach theatre of Fara Sabina, a tiny village
near Rome, wore a mask that might have
been inspired by Goya's bestiary.
Improvisations and confrontations of this
kind reveal the principles on which Third
Theatre is based. The essential process
is not to teach, borrow or copy acting
techniques, but the patient development
of authentic group cultures.
At Bergamo, these groups formed a
unique cultural kaleidoscope. Virtuoso ac¬
tors from the Far East, the heirs of centu¬
ries-old traditions, who had trained for up
to ten hours a day since the age of eight
or nine, were perfectly at home working
with young Western actors who in some
cases had only made their stage débuts a
few months before and had no roots in
ancient cultural traditions.
A sense of affinity emerged from the
contact between those whose culture was
deeply rooted in the past, although in
some cases it might be stifled and embalm¬
ed within the supranational culture of the
modern world, and small "self-made"
group cultures which had sprung up from
nowhere.
Eugenio Barba, who directed the mask
performance from the wings, has had a
varied career. After attending secondary
school in Italy he went to Scandinavia,
working as a sailor on a Norwegian ship
for two years. He then entered Oslo Uni¬
versity, where among other subjects he
studied the history of religions. In 1960
he was awarded a Unesco scholarship and
went to Poland, where he spent four years,
working first at the Warsaw Conservatory
of Dramatic Art and then for three years
with Jerzy Grotowski at Opole.
Although in some respects he has parted
company from Grotowski, Barba remains a
self-confessed disciple of the Polish
master. When he returned to Norway, he
struck out on his own, and in 1964 found¬
ed the Odin Teatret, which two years later
made its home in Denmark.
Barba's knowledge of the history of reli¬
gions has influenced the development of
his ideas on ritual as a technique of dra
matic expression. "What some people call
'ritual' in our theatre is what I would
prefer to call a pattern of behaviour,"
he has said. "At moments of great
emotion extreme joy, fear and enthu¬
siasm react quite differently from the
way we do in everyday life. In our the¬
atre we try to bring out these behaviour
patterns and funnel them into disciplined
expression.
"Through our work we try to get
through to our living, original feelings,
which society has turned into conditioned
reflexes, and through discipline, to trans¬
late them into signs and situations. If
what we create sometimes smacks of
religious ritual, then it can't be helped.
"Perhaps what we regard as the natural
behaviour of the man in the street isn't as
natural as we think.. When the average
man is in the grip of real and violent
emotions, and his gestures instinctively
become strange or ritualistic, he may be
closer to nature than when he is relaxed
and puts his feet up on the table".
In September 1976, during the Theatre
of the Nations season, Barba directed
the Belgrade workshop on current trends
in the theatre, including Third Theatre, held
under the auspices of Unesco and the
International Theatre Institute. It was a
great success, but unlike the Bergamo
workshop in the following year it was only
attended by a limited public of theatre
people, journalists, writers and artists.
One of the most popular events at
Bergamo was a performance given by the
Els Comediants in a popular quarter of the
town. This was the first time that the
group had performed outside the Iberian
peninsula, and it attracted an audience
numbering between 3,000 and 5,000. The
15 members of the troupe paraded through
the streets, mingling with the crowds and
inviting bystanders to dance, enjoy them¬
selves, and let off steam.
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The next night, 15 performances were
given by clowns in "lower" Bergamo, the
modern part of the town. (Upper Bergamo
is the medieval town and the centre of
community life.) According to stories
that have grown up around the Commedià
dell'Arte masks, Brighella, the wise and
cautious valet, is said to have come from
the upper town of Bergamo, while Harle¬
quin, the foolish valet, came from the
lower town.
On the following day, 3 September, all
the groups descended on the lower town
from upper Bergamo by four different
routes. A medley of masked figures, fire-
eaters, jugglers, metal robots and white-
faced melancholy maidens wearing bowler
hats and brandishing umbrellas, burst into
the astonished crowds of shoppers.
That evening the Bergamo Pocket
Theatre presented an "Albatross" show
featuring great birdlike figures strutting
along on stilts with flapping wings. Six
masked and hunch-backed entertainers of
the "Theatre of Adventure" from Treviglio,
a small town near Milan, declaimed non¬
stop, filled the nearby streets with the
sounds of their accordions and perform¬
ed riotous antics for all and sundry.
At Bergamo, flights of fancy went hand
in hand with a solid sense of organiza¬
tion. The Italian groups Bergamo's
Pocket Theatre, the Piccolo Theatre from
Pontedera, Pisa's "theatre-laboratory", the
Potlach Theatre from Fara Sabina, Tre-
viglio's Adventure Theatre, Genoa's Drum
Theatre and the Arcoiris Theatre from
Rome are all small companies of up to a
dozen actors working in little towns or on
the outskirts of big cities. They all manag¬
ed to solve the organization problème
caused by the invasion of the town.
Though the streets of Bergamo sound¬
ed like the Tower of Babel, the language
barrier was forgotten in the creative
ferment of Third Theatre.
There is a world of difference, as Euge¬
nio Barba has remarked, "between a thea¬
tre which produces culture and a theatre
which is culture". The Bergamo Work¬
shop demonstrated that promoting culture
does not only mean working with cultural
"products" but also creating the condi¬
tions in which new cultures, new cells of
community life, can confront one another
and develop.
We theatre critics often spend our time
looking for new gems to distribute on the
market places of culture. We find it hard
to accept that events like the Bergamo
Workshop are also encounters between
those who are prospecting for precious
stones. It is true that many of them have
embarked on a vain and fruitless search
and will return home at the end of the day
with nothing but the memory of their
own anxieties. But we should never for¬
get that some of them may strike gold.
Ferdinando Taviani
Spectators rolled up in their hundreds to see the clowns, who delighted the
townspeople with simultaneous six-hour shows on two squares in different
parts of town. Left, clowns from Denmark's Odin Teatret. Above right,
balancing act by clowns from the Cardiff Laboratory (U. K.) amuses
passersby on a street corner. Above left, music and movement from
Sweden's Schahrazad troupe.
Photos © Maurizio Buscarino, Bergamo, Italy
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
The link-up of a U.S. Apollo
and a Soviet Soyuz 19
spacecraft on 17 July 1975
was a milestone in the
history of international co¬
operation in space. The
two-craft docked while
hurtling over Europe and
the crews met through a
special airlock which
allowed them to transfer
from one craft to the other.
Left, during a joint training
session near Moscow, the
commander of Soyuz 19,
Aleksei Leonov (right of
photo), acquaints his
American opposite number,
Tom Stafford, with the
systems of the Soviet
spacecraft. Above, during
the historic joint flight,
Leonov and Stafford display
Soviet and U.S. flags during
a news conference
televised from the Soyuz
spacecraft. Amateur artist
as well as pioneer
cosmonaut, Leonov drew
this sketch (right) of Vance
Brand, pilot of the Apollo
command module.
Photo © APN, Moscow
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Space co-operation in orbit
The first man to walk in space
tots up the benefits
of international research programmes
by Aleksei A. Leonov
TWENTY years ago, ground tracking
stations picked up the radio bleeps
of the world's first artificial satellite.
On that day, men and women everywhere
looked at the skies with different eyes.
Four years later, Yuri Gagarin took the first
steps on the path to the stars. As Neil
Armstrong, the first man to walk on the
Moon, would later say, "He called us all
into space."
Since then, 51 manned space flights
have been carried out, 32 of them from the
Soviet Union. In all, Soviet cosmonauts
have spent over 12,000 hours in space.
There is nothing surprising in the specta¬
cular development of space exploration.
What with the population explosion, the
energy crisis and the depletion of the
world's natural resources, I am convinced
that mankind will step up its efforts to mas¬
ter outer space, to build industrial com¬
bines there and gigantic thermo-electric
power stations run on unlimited "solar
fuel".
But I am equally certain that this will only
be possible if the conquest and use of outer
space are carried out exclusively for peace¬
ful purposes.
Today many countries are striving to
break into space research because their
industries need a stimulus of this kind in
order to increase their competitivity on the
world market. However, only scientifically
and technologically advanced states can
afford to engage in the systematic and
comprehensive study of space. Space
research has made tremendous progress in
recent years, costs have escalated, and
more and more people are asking what
benefits mankind has gained from it.
ALEKSEI ARKHIPOVICH LEONOV, Soviet
cosmonaut and twice Hero of the Soviet
Union, is the first man to leave a space vehicle
and walk in space. (For his account of his first
steps in space, see Unesco Courier, June 1965)
In July 1975 he was commander of the Soviet
Soyuz 19 spaceship which made the historic
linkup with a U. S. Apollo spacecraft as part of
the Soviet-American Apollo-Soyuz Test Project.
I shall begin my answer to this question
by pointing to the weather satellites which
today constitute an irreplaceable link in the
world meteorological system. The infor¬
mation collected by a meteorological satel¬
lite on a single circuit of the earth provides
a hundred times more information than
that provided by all the world's ground
meteorological stations in a whole day.
The Soviet Union's space meteorological
service, for example, has now been in op¬
eration for 10 years. Many countries, in¬
cluding the United States with which the
Soviet Union has concluded an agreement
on the exchange of meteorological infor¬
mation, today make use of this system.
With meteorological satellites, it is now
possible to obtain advance warnings about
the approach of such natural hazards as
typhoons and floods. Though figures are .
far from complete, it has been estimated
that such forecasts save as much as $60
billion a year in various countries around
the world.
Earth survey satellites used to examine
the anomaly in the Earth's magnetic field in
eastern Siberia revealed the presence and
precise depth of iron-ore deposits there, as
well as locating a hitherto unknown ano¬
maly in the southern Atlantic.
Satellites are also useful in detecting
forest fires all over the world, working 24
hours a day in all weathers, something
which no other fire prevention method can
do.
If automatic seismic recording stations,
which are relatively cheap to build, were
placed in key positions in the world's seis¬
mic zones and equipped for regularly trans¬
mitting data to special satellites, it would
be possible to obtain all the information we
need to draw up an overall map of the
seismic activity of the Earth's crust.
Satellites can also be used to chart the
movements of plankton and shoals of fish,
and to transmit this information to fishing
fleets.
A mere 15 years ago, TV programmes
were beamed over long distances through
a network of relay stations 40 or 50 kilo¬
metres apart. Each transmitter received
signals which it then amplified and relay¬
ed to the next station.
Today the Soviet network of Orbita
ground receiving stations, working with
Molniya satellites, provides television for
over 20 million Soviet citizens in the Far
North, Siberia, the Far East and Central L
Asia. The system also provides telephone, '
17
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
, , \
M
1
m
'u
i r
au
. .-.»
fi
vtysjft*??
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Chalking up
a space success
Peaceful space exploration is
bringing mankind many
direct benefits in
communications, weather
forecasting, and the global
management of natural
resources, as well as a host
of spin-off applications in
science, technology and
industry. (1) A Soviet
Soyuz 22 spacecraft in the
final stages of assembly,
and (2) being transported
to the launching platform.
(3) Mission completed:
Aleksei Leonov chalks
a grateful "thank-you" on
the landing capsule of his
Soyuz 19 which brought
him back to Earth at the
end of the joint
Apollo-Soyuz mission.
(4) Spectacular overhead
photo of the splashdown of
a U.S. Apollo 17 manned
spacecraft in the Pacific.
(See also back cover).
Photo © USIS, Paris
telegraph and teletype communications,
as well as facilities for the transmission of
photographs and newspaper columns.
The network took several years to cons¬
truct and the cost was a massive 100 mil¬
lion roubles. (One rouble = 1.34 U.S. dol¬
lars.) However, to provide the same facili¬
ties using traditional techniques,
15,000 km. of cable would have had to be
laid in rugged areas of the Soviet Union.
The work would have taken several de¬
cades, and the costs would have run to
thousands of millions of roubles.
A year(ago, a new TV transmission
system came into operation in the
U.S.S.R., using the Ekran satellite. The
main advantage of Ekran is that its signals
can be picked up by small, inexpensive
aerials on the ground, similar to ordinary
TV antennae, and thus does away with the
need for complex and costly aerials of the
Orbita type.
Ekran's signals can be picked up in any
village within its operating zone. It is an
extremely reliable system, and provides a
24-hour-a-day link in all weathers.
Thanks to communications satellite tech¬
nology, the oilmen of Samotlor (Western
Siberia), the diamond miners of Yakutin
(Central Siberia) the hunters of Tuva
(South-Eastern U.S.S.R.), and the builders
of the Baikal-Amur railway (north of Lake
Baikal) today enjoy television services.
In the last five years, scientists have
begun to make wide use of space techno¬
logy in studying the Earth's surface. A sin¬
gle photo taken from an orbiting laboratory
can provide as much information as 2,000
photographs taken from an aircraft. The
Soviet Salyut 4 orbital research station
took five minutes to do the photographic
work that would have taken a photolabora-
tory aircraft two years.
The analysis of photos taken from space
makes it possible to "see" hundreds of
metres beneath the Earth's surface and to
draw the contours of geological formations
that cannot be charted either on the
ground or by aerial photography.
Right from the start, satellite photo¬
graphy of the Earth led to discoveries of
world-wide importance. It was possible,
for example, to confirm the hypothesis that
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Europe's weather eye
Meteosat, the 11-member European Space
Agency's first weather satellite, is another
example of international co-operation in
space. As well as supplying Information
to European meteorological services, it is
also Europe's contribution to the World
Weather Watch system and the Global
Atmospheric Research Programme.
Right, one of the European satellite's first
pictures of the Earth, taken on 9
December 1977.
the geological structure of the Ural moun¬
tains stretches deep into the south as far as
central Asia. Photos taken from an orbiting
satellite were also used to improve the
plans for a tunnel on the Baikal-Amur rail¬
way, thus saving several million roubles.
In oil and gas prospecting, results were
equally gratifying. Geologists have been
studying the Fergan valley in Uzbekistan
for 60 years, and have discovered 102 oil
and gas deposits. The Salyut 3 orbiting
station found 85 new deposits within three
months.
Salyut 3 has also been used to draw up a
balanced land-use plan for the arid steppes
around the Caspian Sea. Space probes
over an area of 2,000 hectares located large
deposits of fresh or slightly mineralized
water fairly close to the surface, and as a
result plans are being made for the deve¬
lopment of irrigated farming there.
The economic value of the information
so far received from the Salyut 4 station,
launched in 1974, has been estimated by
specialists at between 50 and 70 million
roubles.
These are only a few of the results of
"space-earth studies". It should be noted
that any country could obtain similar
information by using these methods.
But I should like to draw attention to the
future potential of space-earth research,
for its applications open up vast possibili¬
ties. Particularly important today is its role
in surveying and drawing up an inventory
of the Earth's natural resources.
How can a region meet its food and
energy requirements without damaging
the environment. Where should tomor¬
row's big power stations be located? What
are the effects of swamp drainage on the
surrounding area? What are the most
rational ways of using land without upsett¬
ing the balance of nature? Space research
can help to provide the mass of infor¬
mation needed to answer such questions
and many others like them.
It is easier to pinpoint the direct contribu¬
tion of space research to the economy than
to assess its spin-off effects on industry in
general, through setting high_ standards of
precision, compactness, lightness, reliabi¬
lity and durability.
Recent experiments have shown that
perfectly pure crystals can be produced in
space, as well as certain alloys that are
practically impossible to obtain on Earth.
Grandfather of
the space rocket
The Russian scientist Konstantin
Eduardovich Tsiolkovsky (1857-1935)
pioneered the development of space
research. Before the end of the 19th
century he was already grappling with the
problems of using rockets In space,
including navigation, heating from air
friction, and fuel supply. A crater on the
moon today bears his name. Photo shows
Tsiolkovsky in his workshop in 1919.
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
One such metal, a 'lightweight but ex¬
tremely tough alloy of aluminium and
tungsten, may find a use in space research
or in aviation.
I believe that the time is not far off when
orbital dispatcher stations will be set up to
provide ships and aircraft with all the infor¬
mation they need to take the most econo¬
mical routes commensurate with complete
safety.
Data provided by navigation satellites
could lop some 45 minutes a day off the
time of ocean travel. Given the present size
of the world's merchant shipping fleet
(about 20,000 heavy-tonnage vessels),
orbiting navigational services could save
some $150 million a year. Satellites will
But however great its practical advan¬
tages may be, space exploration continues
above all to make a vast contribution to our
understanding of the solar system and the
rest of the universe, of the laws of outer
space and their effects on life on our
planet. We learn more about the history of
the Earth when we compare it with the
development of other planets. And sooner
or later this knowledge will be of tremen¬
dous practical use to mankind.
Space research is one of the most expen¬
sive activities in the modern world, and
international co-operation is absolutely
essential, if only from an economic point of
view. In 1967, when the Interkosmos pro¬
gramme of co-operation between the
socialist countries was set up, it was
French and American rockets have also
been launched from the Kerguelen Islands
in the southern Indian Ocean, while obser¬
vations were made in the northern hemis¬
phere, from Karpogory (Archangelsk,
U.S.S.R.).
The Soviet Union is also collaborating
with India in space research: the U.S.S.R.
helped to design India's Ariabata satellite,
which was put into orbit by a Soviet rocket.
Just over five years ago, the U.S.A. and
the Soviet Union signed an agreement on
space co-operation. Much has been
achieved since then.
The U.S.S.R. Academy of Sciences and
NASA (National Aeronautics and Space
Administration) have exchanged rock sam¬
ples brought back to Earth from various
Keeping tabs
on spacelabs
Antennae mushroom from
the deck of Kosmonaut
Yuri Gagarin, flagship of
the scientific research
fleet of the U.S.S.R.
Academy of Sciences.
They are used to maintain
round-the-clock
communications links
with orbiting Soviet
space laboratories.
also enable aircraft to take the shortest
possible routes, cutting flying time by 20
per cent and reducing the cost of air trans¬
port accordingly.
Another application of space research
technology will, I believe, be affecting our
lives in the near future. About a billion tele¬
phone calls are made in the world each
day, including some 10 million long¬
distance and 50,000 intercontinental calls.
By 1980, the number of transatlantic tele¬
phone calls and télégrammes will be so
high that at least ten new submarine cables
will have to be laid between Europe and
America.
Yet one or two communications satellites
could easily handle the soaring number of
calls, as well as reducing their costwhich
would be two or three times lessi A point
worth noting here is that even today calls
between many African countries still have
to be routed through the capitals of their
former ruling powers.
already clear that the conquest of outer
space would call for the combined efforts
of many states.
This nine-member programme was the
first move towards international co¬
operation in space involving such a large
number of states. So far the socialist coun¬
tries have jointly launched over a dozen
satellites, as well as several Vertikal
geophysical rockets and a large number of
meteorological rockets. A group of cosmo¬
nauts from the socialist countries is cur¬
rently being trained at the Soviet Cosmo¬
nauts' Training Centre in Zvyozdny near
Moscow.
In September 1976, Soviet cosmonauts
Valeri Bykovsky and Vladimir Aksyonov,
on board the. Soyuz 22 spaceship success¬
fully carried out a mission devised by the
socialist countries. During the flight they
tested and used a multispectral camera
designed by specialists from the U.S.S.R.
and the German Democratic Republic and
manufactured by Carl Zeiss, Jena (German
Dem. Rep.).
The years 1976-1978 have been declared
International Years for the Study of the
Magnetosphere. During this period some
50 space craft are undertaking global
research according to an internationally
agreed programme.
As part of the programme, the Franco-
Soviet Arax project has collected data
simultaneously from three widely distant
operating platforms.
parts ot the Moon's surface by the Soviet
automatic Luna craft and the manned
American Apollo spaceship.
Soviet and American scientists have also
exchanged a mass of valuable scientific
information about the phenomena re¬
corded by the Soviet Mars 2 and Mars 3
interplanetary craft and the American
Mariner 9 during their flights to Mars.
But the high point of this programme
was, of course, the Apollo-Soyuz link-up in
space in 1975. The American press esti¬
mated that the event was watched by a bil¬
lion televiewers around the world, while as
many again listened in to the radio reports.
Mankind had already witnessed dozens
of space launchings, but the Apollo-Soyuz
experiment captured the world's imagina¬
tion in an unprecedented way. Through
the link-up, the Soviet Union and the
U.S.A. gave a visible demonstration that
new and higher orbits of mutual under¬
standing, trust and co-operation were pos¬
sible.
The two countries recently signed a new
agreement on co-operation involving the
American Space Shuttle and a Soviet orbi¬
ting station of the Salyut type. Let us hope
that this new experiment will give a fresh
impetus to world détente. For if it does
not, it is hard to imagine what will
become of our Earth, the small, blue and
fragile looking planet which I have viewed
from space.
Aleksei A Leonov
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
How risky
is
genetic engineering?
by Dan Behrman
SO much is heard these days about
the possible dangerous conse¬
quences of biological research that
one tends to forget the real benefits that
can beand are being derived from it.
Some of these benefits were described
at a recent symposium on genetics and
ethics organized in Madrid by the Spanish
Higher Council for Scientific Research and
Unesco under its programme of science
in the contemporary world. Among the
34 participants from two dozen countries
was Professor J.R. Porter of the microbio¬
logy department of the University of Iowa
(USA). One of the microbe's firmest
advocates on the international scene, he
was particularly convincing at Madrid
when he described how it can contribute
to alleviating energy shortages.
"Should the price of oil go much
higher", he said, "ethyl alcohol production
by fermentation will become economically
feasible in many countries." This, of
course, is carried out in one of the oldest
production processes known to man, and
has been improved by the genetic selection
of yeasts to increase yields.
As a fuel, ethyl alcohol contains less
energy per litre than petrol but it works
beautifully as a supplement. Porter
reminded the symposium that Brazil is now
producing 800 million litres a year of
alcohol by fermenting cane sugar to reduce
its heavy dependence on oil imports.
It has been said that microbial processes
are so elegant and economic that they
make man's technology look like alchemy
in comparison. They certainly promise a
solution to that other and perhaps more
serious energy crisis created by the short¬
age of firewood for cooking purposes
among the poorest of the world's popu¬
lation.
DAN BEHRMAN, a Unesco science writer and
a frequent contributor to the Unesco Courier,
is the author of The New World of the Oceans
and Solar Energy, the Awakening Science, both
published by Little, Brown and Co., Boston,
U.S.A.
Microbial flora can produce methane-
known as biogas by fermenting manure,
plant residues or household wastes. So
far, little work in genetics has been done in
this field, but, said Porter, if biomass agri¬
culture and forestry were to become a
major source of energy, then certain select¬
ed microbes that attack cellulose and other
products would take on great importance.
Many years ago, Indian scientists began
to work on microbial digestion of cattle
dung both to produce methane for cook¬
ing and to keep the dung as fertilizer (it is
lost, of course, when it is burned for fuel
as at present). Such biogas plants are
now being promoted in India by the Kadhi
and Village Industries Commission in
Bombay. Thirty thousand units are already
in service and the target is 100,000.
These are community plants intended
to produce fertilizer as well as gas for
cooking and to run small engines. It is esti¬
mated that a small digester running on
manure from three to five cows will supply
a small family.
According to figures quoted by Porter,
Korea now has nearly as many plants as
India. But the leader by far is the People's
Republic of China where two million are
in operation.
When we hear of biogas, we tend to
think of the barefoot subsistence farmer
eking out a living. The symposium was all
the more impressed when Porter reported
on a mobile biogas plant developed in Colo¬
rado (USA) and mounted on a big semi¬
trailer so that it can be trundled around the
countryside for demonstration purposes.
This plant can take the daily manure pro¬
duction of 20 to 45 cattle and turn out
enough gas to heat one or two homes in
the chilly Colorado climate. Porter observ¬
ed that waste from a big feedlot operation
with 100,000 cattle could meet the needs of
a community of 5,000 people.
Microbes can also be used for quite
different purposes. Porter mentioned that
scientists are trying to extract uranium
from seawater. "Estimates are that the
oceans contain a few billion tons of ura¬
nium whereas land deposits are no more
than 1.0 to 2.9 million tons. Experiments
The characteristics of every living
organism depend on its genetic
material, whose key component is a
chemical substance called DNA
(desoxyribonucleic acid). Ribbon-like
strands of DNA, a highly complex
molecule, are here seen being released
from the head of a virus.
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
'.vy»:.
m
m
>:
iPV.
< X
,rft?v.
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
6ATTCAASTC«
CTAA^TTC^Cf
m p
The transmission of hereditary
characteristics is shown in
schematic representation (left).
The ladder-shaped double strand
that constitutes a DNA molecule
contains four substances
(represented here by four
letters). Each rung of the ladder
consists of a pair of the four
substances, which associate in a
specific way. When a DNA
molecule duplicates, it does so
by splitting lengthwise. In the
two new DNA "ladders", the
pairs form a different sequence,
with the help of an enzyme
depicted here as a little cartoon
figure with outstretched arms.
By manipulating this process,
scientists may one day learn
how to alter hereditary
characteristics.
Photo © Pr. Tavlitzki, Ciba-Geigy, Martin Boschet
are underway to" develop hybrid green
algae that will absorb and accumulate ura¬
nium from seawater. The marine algae
being developed by German scientists, for
example, will absorb uranium in concentra¬
tions several thousand times that of nor¬
mal seawater. Mesh vessels containing the
hybrid algae would be immersed in ocean
currents to harvest the uranium".
The symposium drew attention to certain
dangers in genetic research. Biologists
now know how to add a piece of DNA
(desoxyribonucleic acid, the gene's basic
component) from a given species to the
genes of another species, thus creating a
hybrid species. This technique was
recently used to insert into a bacterium the
insulin-producing gene of the rat. If it
proves possible to make this gene
functional, the implications could be
important. For example, insulin could be
produced by bacteria for the treatment of
diabetes.
Scientists were the first to fear that new
dangerous bacteria might be created. But,
with the passing years, the pendulum
seems to have swung in the opposite
direction. The feeling is that current DNA
experiments of the type described above
are less dangerous than much research on
pathogenic organisms now being perform¬
ed in medical laboratories with far fewer
precautions.
Nevertheless, great care must be taken
and scientists cannot afford to remain
above it all. Dr. Povl Riis from Denmark,
chairman of the European Science Founda¬
tion's committee on recombinant DNA
research, regarded the issue as a test case
in relations between science and society.
"If we do not fill the gap between scientists
and the mass of society," he said, "it will
Among these red corpuscles photographed under a microscope
are sickle shaped cells resulting from a mutation which may
cause sickle-cell anaemia, a potentially fatal disease.
be filled by wild fears and unrealistic hopes
which will lead to prohibitive legislation."
Too much "improvement" of genes may
not be a good thing.. Prof. Albert Jacquard
from the National Institute for Demographic
Studies in Paris, said: "The lesson of
population genetics is that at the level of
the gene it is impossible to say what is
good or bad." The gene that transmits
sickle cell anaemia can kill a child or, in
another form, help it resist malaria. Dia¬
betes is an illness, but it may also help an
individual to cope with less food in his or
her diet, perhaps a useful trait in the
future.
For the present, some serious social and
ethical issues have arisen as the result of
the findings of ecogenetics, which seeks
to determine how a person's genes
influence the way he responds to his
environment. Dr. H. Werner Goedde of
the University of Hamburg in the Federal
Republic of Germany, saw a genetic
explanation for the different ways that
individuals are affected by pesticides,
insecticides and herbicides as well as by
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
The form of mental deficiency known
as mongolism is due to a genetic
abnormality. This genetic "accident"
is visible in a mongoloid's hand: the
two lines running across the palm join
instead of remaining separate.
Above, milk droplets bouncing off a vibrating membrane. Many
people suffer from an inherited intolerance to lattose, the sugar in
milk. In the United States alone, this intolerance, due to to the lack
of the enzyme lactase, affects 90 per cent of Asian Americans, from
70 per cent to 90 per cent of American Indians and 75 per cent of blacks.
alcohol, cigarettes, drugs and industrial
pollution.
From one individual to another, the risk
of lung cancer in certain industries can go
up 33 times. Among heavy drinkers, some
end up with cirrhosis of the liver while
others do not. Significant differences in
response to alcohol are found between
Mongolian and Caucasian populations.
Similar variations are to be found in
reactions to pharmaceutical products,
which means, Goedde said, that care
should be taken in exporting them.
More examples were mentioned by. Dr.
Gilbert S. Omenn, assistant director for
human resources at the Office of Science
and Technology Policy in the Executive
Office of the President in Washington.
Inherited intolerance to lactose, the sugar
in milk, makes milk more a poison than a
food for 75 per cent of blacks in the United
States, 70 to 90 per cent of American
Indians, 90 per cent of Asians and 20 per
cent of Caucasians. "Given the symptoms
that may be induced," he has written, "it
is hardly surprising that many black children
'prefer Coke' or that Southwest Indians
have 'ungratefully' utilized powdered milk
to paint their adobes!"
Black and Mediterranean peoples are
often deficient in an enzyme known as
G6PD (glucose-6-phosphate-dehydrogenase)
which is essential to the integrity of red
blood cells. In its absence, an otherwise
healthy person may suffer acute anaemia
when treated with certain drugs (among
them sulfa derivatives and aspirin) or when
working in certain industries.
In some cases, individuals with this
deficiency are unable to eat fava beans.
Long before it was known to science,
Omenn remarked, the Pythagoreans were
said to have surrendered to their enemy
rather than flee through a field of fava
beans. And in Greek mythology, one sect
allowed women, but not men, to eat fava
beans. This is consistent with the way in
which the deficiency is transmitted from
one generation to the next.
One rare deficiency affects one in 2,500
Caucasians who will stop breathing for
hours if he receives suxamethonium, a
muscle relaxant frequently used during
surgery. Fortunately, a simple test exists
to screen such individuals.
Genetic screening, in fact, could protect
anyone suffering from these disorders but,
at the same time, it could bar them from
jobs or make it more difficult for them to
get insurance coverage. Is it right, Omenn
wondered, that they should be at a
disadvantage while others are not, simply
because their genetic predisposition to
other illnesses is not known?
Another question has been raised by a
proposal in the United States to introduce
iron supplements into bread to help a large
number of people suffering from mild iron
deficiency and anaemia. A smaller number
of people, however, are genetically suscep¬
tible to a disease brought on precisely by
too much iron. Such diseases tend to
increase as more and more new substances
are introduced into the environment,
inadvertently or not. Omenn is convinced
that cases now known represent only the
tip of the iceberg.
Genetic screening on a large scale is
now being undertaken in a number of
countries for a significant segment of the
population, the children yet to be born.
Prenatal examination can determine if the
child is suffering from mongolism, a risk
that increases with the age of its mother.
Other untreatable genetic diseases, but
not all, can be diagnosed in this manner.
Prospective parents can also receive
genetic counselling, particularly if they
already have an abnormal child and they
wish to know the risks they run in having
another.
Dr. Pertti Aula from the University of
Helsinki in Finland emphasized at the
symposium that even parents at risk have
a much higher chance than they might
think of having a healthy child. "In most
prenatal study projects, the number of
abnormal findings, which could lead to a
therapeutic abortion, has been about 5 per
cent. Thus in 19 out of 20 studies, the
results have been normal and the effect of
the study has been to relieve parents'
anxiety."
Aula insisted that individuals must be
given the freedom to choose whether or
not to undertake such prenatal diagnosis
and to decide themselves what steps to
take when the results are known.
The imperative need for such freedom
of choice was repeatedly stressed at the
symposium, whose participants agreed
that "the good of the species must yield
to the good of the individual". Professor
Jose Egoscue from the Autonomous
University of Barcelona in Spain expressed
the views of many when he said: "The
darkest hour of genetics is when it serves
political or economic interests."
Dan Behrman
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Brunelleschi
The
Florentine
who launched
Renaissance
architecture
by Francesco Gurrieri
The genius of the 15th-century architect Filippo Brunelleschi left an
enduring imprint on the city of Florence. Left, the cathedral of Santa
Maria del Fiore, whose mighty cupola, one of the biggest in the world,
was designed by Brunelleschi. It dominates the rooftops in panoramic
view of the city (below), along with another of Brunelleschl's
masterpieces, the domed basilica of San Lorenzo (left of photo). Above,
San Lorenzo in close-up.
Photos © Robert Descharnes, Paris
WITH the coming of the Renais¬
sance in the early 15th century,
Italian art underwent a funda¬
mental change. The development of a
new humanist outlook created a cultural
climate which favoured the blending of
the arts and the sciences and in the city of
Florence liberated the creative genius of
exceptional men such as the painter
Masaccio, the sculptor Donatello and the
architect Filippo Brunelleschi.
Brunelleschi was born in Florence in
1377, 600 years ago, an anniversary which
Italy has just commemorated with justifi¬
able pride. The son of a prosperous notary
who occupied an important position in the
Florentine Republic, he trained initially as
a goldsmith and sculptor, being admitted
to the Goldsmiths' Guild at the age of 21.
Small in stature, he was a witty and highly
cultivated man. We know how effective
he could be in answering back his critics k
from one of his poems in which he lashes J
FRANCESCO GURRIERI, Italian architect, art
critic and historian of architecture, is assistant
superintendent of Monuments in Florence. A
specialist on Tuscan architecture, he lectures
on architectural restoration techniques at Flo¬
rence university and has collaborated with the
International Council of Monuments and Sites
(ICOMOS).
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
, lO'ut at a denigrator of his greatest master¬
piece, the dome of Florence cathedral.
At this period of Italian history, the
communes towns and cities ruled by
free, self-governing institutionswere
yielding one after the other to the power
of new overlords, the signorie. Florence,
however, a city of powerful businessmen
and merchants, succeeded in preserving
its constitution and its right to self-
government, as well as freedom of expres¬
sion for its humanists and scholars. Its
rulers were men of letters whose influence
stemmed less from their rank than from
the esteem in which they were held by the
people. This was the age of Florence's
great "humanist chancellors", men such
as Coluccio Salutati, Leonardo Bruni and
Possio Bracciolini, whose names have
passed into the history of Italian literature.
Brunelleschi's first biographer, the
mathematician Antonio Manetti, reports
that his subject was deeply interested in
science, and particularly in optics (then
closely related to medicine and physics).
Thanks to his studies in this field, he
formulated revolutionary principles of
perspective and applied these laws to a
new concept of architectural space.
Another biographer, Giorgio Vasari, refers
to Brunelleschi's close relations with
mathematicians and physicists.
In 1401, at the age of 24, Brunelleschi
entered the famous competition for the
bronze relief decoration of the second door
of the Baptistery in Florence. His trial
piece won the competition jointly with that
For the Ospedale degli Innocenti, Florence's Foundling Hospital named after
the Innocents of Herod's massacre, Brunelleschi created a façade with wide
semi-circular arches and slender columns. Drawing below shows the façade
as it looked in 1445. Lower photo shows a detail of the interior of the church
of Santo Spirito, which Brunelleschi designed in 1436.
I Î f 1 I
Photos Paolo Monti © Electra Editrice, Milan
The Pazzi Chapel (below), which Brunelleschi built for Florence's powerful
Pazzi family, is one of the architect's most remarkable creations. The
columns, porches and many other details of the design show how carefully
Brunelleschi had studied the ancient ruins in Rome. Many of the terracotta
roundels inside the chapel are by the great sculptor Luca delta Robbia.
iWWWVWWW^^s^ii^iÉ
11
r rz\
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Detail of the wooden crucifix
carved by Brunelleschi for
the church of Santa Maria
Novella in Florence. The
crucifix (1 metre 70 cms.
high) is the only surviving
piece of monumental
sculpture in wood by
Brunelleschi.
In 1401, a competition was
held for the decoration of a
pair of bronze doors destined
for the Baptistery in
Florence, and sculptors were
invited to submit a trial piece
on the theme of "the
Sacrifice of Isaac".
Brunelleschi's entry (detail
below) won joint first prize
along with that of Lorenzo
Ghiberti, who later executed
the commission alone.
of Lorenzo Ghiberti. The two artists
were invited to share the commission, but
Brunelleschi refused to collaborate with
his rival and Ghiberti did the door. From
then on he turned increasingly to architec¬
ture, where far greater successes awaited
him.
In the early years of the 15th century,
Brunelleschi is thought to have visited
Rome to study the ancient monuments.
According to Vasari, he was accompanied
by his friend Donatello the sculptor, and
the two men spent so much time measur¬
ing the ruins of temples and palaces that
the Romans thought they were searching
for hidden treasure.
Brunelleschi's interest in the relics of
classical art reflected much more than a
mere concern with style. He was aiming to
create new modes of harmony and beauty,
as well as investigating building
techniques. The result was that he invent¬
ed an entirely new architectural language
which was far from being a slavish imita¬
tion of classical models. .
It was not until 1418, by which time he k
was 41, that Brunelleschi began to reveal f
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
, the full scope of his creative genius. In that
year he built a chapel (which has not sur¬
vived) for the church of San Jacopa
Soprarno in Florence. According to Manetti
he was trying to prove that the system of
vaulting by interlocking or "herringbone"
courses of masonry, which he had perfect¬
ed, could be used to construct a dome
without the use of a temporary wooden
supporting framework.
This ingenious new technique of alter¬
nating horizontal and vertical rows of
bricks in a herringbone pattern was to be a
characteristic feature of all Brunelleschi's
domes, both large and small. In his search
for perfection the architect closely super¬
vised the fitting together of the brickwork
and every other detail of the construction
work: each brick in the cathedral dome was
manufactured according to his precise
measurements and specifications.
In 1418, Brunelleschi also drew up a
project for the reconstruction of the an¬
cient Romanesque church of San Lorenzo.
Taking into account the ground-plan of
the ancient edifice, he devised a new
church with a nave and two side-aisles,
each flanked by small chapels. Even the
lateral views, from the nave towards each
chapel off the aisles, were conceived in
conformity with the rules of perspective.
Later in the same year, he began work
on the Old Sacristy of San Lorenzo,
intended to become the family chapel of
the Medicis. The building, a remarkable
example of purity of form, consists of a
cubic hall above which rises a circular
melon dome.
In the following year, 1419, Brunelleschi
began to produce projects for the Ospedale
degli Innocenti, Florence's foundling hos¬
pital, whose harmoniously proportioned
façade is still admired today. The Ospedale,
which would serve as a model for later
generations of hospital builders, marks the
birth of a new and authentically modern
type of building created along functional
lines by an architect who was also cons¬
cious of the imperatives and problems of
urban planning.
In August 1420, work began on the
dome of Santa Maria del Fiore, the cathe¬
dral of Florence, a mammoth undertaking
in which Brunelleschi was to be involved
throughout the second half of his life.
The dome, which rises over 80 metres
above ground level, is without parallel in
the history of architecture. Its construc¬
tion posed innumerable problems of design
and building technique, to which
Brunelleschi, as great an engineer as he
was an architect, devised some astonish¬
ing solutions.
The eight master-architects who had
preceded him in directing the work had
left the octagonal drum on which the dome
was to rest open to the sky. It stood there
like a vast crater, and no one knew how
to cover it. In 1417, the project was
thrown open to public competition, and
engineers and architects submitted a
number of designs incorporating a variety
of different approaches. Brunelleschi's
solution to the problem was novel and
attractive, but it alarmed the organizers of
the competition. He proposed to build the
dome without using the traditional wooden
supporting framework. The technique was
revolutionary but feasible.
When construction work began, it was
directed by Brunelleschi, Lorenzo Ghiberti
and Battista d'Antonio. By 1426, however,
Brunelleschi was virtually in complete
control. Among the many admirers of the
dome was the great architect and theore¬
tician Leon Battista Alberti (1404-1472),
who praised it as "a structure so great,
rising above the skies, large enough to
shelter all the people of Tuscany in its
shadow".
The dome, some 40 metres in diameter,
consists of an outer and an inner shell,
separated by a gap through which access is
given to the top. The thickness of the inner
shell is just over 2 metres and that of the
outer shell 0.75 metrest while the gap
between them is over 1 metre wide.
The red and green clay tiles which cover
the outer surface of the dome, together
with the white marble ribbing, create a
matchless interplay of colours against the
blue Florentine sky.
Brunelleschi's solution to the problem
of the dome expresses the humanist ideals
of the great architect and embodies a new
vision of the relationship between art and
mankind. The future development of
Florence was dominated by his monu¬
mental work, and through its association
with this new conception of art the city
became identified for all time with the rise
of humanism.
Many other designs have been attribut¬
ed to Brunelleschi, including work on the
Pitti Palace and fortifications in Pisa and
Vicopisano. The basilica of Santo Spirito,
planned in 1436 and begun in 1444, show
that his boldness in manipulating architec¬
tural forms in no way diminished as he
grew older.
The work of Filippo Brunelleschi marks
a turning point in the history of archi¬
tecture. In future plans would be drawn
accurately and methodically, and checked
against the laws of perspective. Buildings
would be carefully sited in their urban
surroundings.
Brunelleschi died in 1466. He is buried
in Florence cathedral, in the shadow of the
great dome which represents one of the
greatest triumphs of man's creative genius.
Francesco Gurrieri
Viewpoints
on
perspective
Around 1404, Brunelleschi
set forth the major laws of
linear perspective which
were to have a decisive
influence on the artists of
the Renaissance and would
dominate Western painting
until the 20th century. Linear
perspective is based on the
idea that an object appears
to grow smaller as the
distance between it and the
observer increases. It also
uses the principle that, as
parallel lines recede, they
seem to converge at a
"vanishing point" on the
horizon. However, other
civilizations have developed
different conceptions of
perspective (see opposite
page), which they use to
depict the real world
according to their own
spiritual and cultural values.
These conventions are all
linked to the position of the
viewer's eye in relation to
the horizon line. A full
treatment of this subject has
been given by Afif Bahnassi
in an article published in
Unesco's quarterly Cultures
(Vol. IV No. 3).
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
An artist represents linear perspective by moving all lines on his
canvas towards a vanishing point on the horizon. Linear
perspective, based on mathematical laws, creates an illusion of
depth. Above, "The Annunciation" by Neroccio di Landi, c. 1475.
According to ancient Chinese theories of perspective, the
horizon line is situated behind the viewer. The vanishing
points on this line are projected onto the painting as lines
that diverge as they move into the distance. The effect is
opposite to what the Western eye is used to: the painter
opens up his canvas to infinity. Above, "The Fifth Rakan
with Censer" by Lu Hsin-Chung, Sung Dynasty (960-1279).
Artists following traditional Islamic
theories of perspective transposed
volumes into flat surfaces. Above, a
late 13th-century Islamic painting.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
LEARNING TO SHARE THE SAME GLOBE (Continued from page 8)
Generally, these drums beat to ethno¬
centric and nationalistic rhythms only. At
worst the values implicit in what is taught
encourage the worship of parochial military
heroes, the glorification of self-righteous¬
ness, the reinforcement of patterns of
dominance and dependency, the distrust
of foreigners, the conquest of the environ¬
ment, the providence of an unfettered
science and technology, and, in some
cases, racism, aggression, and the oppres¬
sion of minorities. Too much teaching is
preoccupied with images of the past rather
than the future, fostering independence
rather than interdependence and national
rather than world citizenship.
Fortunately, however, the educational "
reforms which are required have been well
charted in international bodies and in
theory if not in practice in a number of
individual countries.
Unesco's General Conference in 1974
adopted a "Recommendation concerning
Education for International Understanding,
Co-operation and Peace and Education
relating to Human Rights and Fundamental
Freedoms". Article III, which applies to
"all stages and forms of education",
begins:
"Education should be infused with the
aims and purposes set forth in the Charter
of the United Nations, the Constitution of
Unesco and the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights...", and sets out the follow¬
ing objectives as guiding principles of
educational policy:
an international dimension and a
global perspective in education at all
levels and in all its forms;
understanding and respect for all
peoples, their cultures, civilizations,
and ways of life, including
domestic ethnic cultures of other
nations;
awareness of the increasing global
interdependence between peoples and
nations;
abilities to communicate with others;
awareness not only of the rights but
also of the duties incumbent upon
individuals, social groups and nations
towards each other;
understanding of the necessity for
international solidarity and co-opera¬
tion;
readiness on the part of the individual
to participate in solving the problems
of his community, his country and the
world at large.
The Recommendation then specifies the
kinds of behaviour and attitudes that
derive from the principles of interde¬
pendence. Member States are invited to
design the daily conduct of their educa¬
tional programmes in such a way that
these principles "become an integral part
of the developing personality of each
child, young person or adult..."
It indicates how international and inter-
cultural dimensions can be introduced into
education of all kinds and at all levels, and
how teachers may be prepared for this
task. It speaks of the needed reforms in
the production, dissemination and exchan¬
ge of equipment and materials, and urges
stimulation and support for research and
experimentation, the results of which can
make education more effective.
The Unesco Recommendation, which
incorporates the other ethical instruments
of the U.N., reflects a remarkable con¬
sensus by the world's governments on
what education should do to support basic
human rights and global interdependence.
A study entitled "International Human
Rights and International Education",
commissioned by the U.S. National Com¬
mission for Unesco, contains a critical
analysis of the Recommendation and its
antecedents, together with a review of
research concerning the international
knowledge and attitudes of young people.
This document should be of value to other
Member States of Unesco.
QHE conference of the World
Council for Curriculum and
I Instruction, held in the
U.K. in September 1974, whose proceed¬
ings have been published under the title
"Education for Peace", made an important
contribution to education for security and
peace-keeping. One chapter makes a
comprehensive diagnosis of the issues
facing mankind and draws implications for
education's role "in the challenging tasks
of building the mansions of peace". The
author insists that:
"The task of education is to develop a
global patriotism, to inspire commitment
to a larger world community; and to teach
behavioural skills that can imagine, analyze
and evaluate future possibilities and pro¬
babilities, or in short, the strategies of
survival."
The Unesco Recommendation and the
suggestions contained in "Education for
Peace" are only initial steps towards the
reforms that will prepare today's young
people for the interdependence of
tomorrow. The present time is one of
widespread and fruitful enquiry into a new
world order by the "North-South"
Conferences on international economic
co-operation, by the Club of Rome, and
by others. These investigations should be
adapted for classroom use.
The debates of the Sixth and Seventh
Special Sessions of the U.N. General
Assembly in 1974 and 1975 reflect the
struggle of the developing countries for
full partnership in international affairs.
Looking at the present, and delving into
the past, the quest for a new international
economic order is a fascinating adventure.
What better educational material could be
found?
Effective education for interdependence
must include attention to the methods,
processes, and structures of education as
well as to its content and curriculum.
Content affects form, and vice versa.
Authoritarian teaching would negate the
principle of participation at every level. A
class of pupils segregated by race or ethnic
background would have difficulty in learn¬
ing tolerance. Teaching which encourages
unquestioning, non-critical responses
would make students easy prey to dogma.
Similarly, an education seen primarily as
a "sorting" process (or the identification
of a few winners and many losers) would
encourage the competitive conception of
societies and nations, and thus run counter
to the notion of international and mutually
beneficial collaboration, while reinforcing
concepts of superiority and dominance.
This attitude should be contrasted with
the concept of "mastery learning" and the
emphasis on equality of educational output
as well as opportunities, an alternative
whose roots lie in the work of educational
reformers John Comenius in the 17th and
Johann Pestalozzi in the 18th centuries.
As Professor Benjamin S. Bloom has
shown, mastery learning begins "with the
notion that most students can attain a
high level of learning capability if instruc¬
tion is approached sensitively and system¬
atically, if students are helped when and
where they have learning difficulties, if they
are given sufficient time to achieve
mastery, and if there is some clear criterion
of what constitutes mastery." (1)
Even the concepts of development and
change can have a positive or negative
effect: the "trickle-down" concept would
not encourage participation because of its
reliance on elitism, while the "trickle-up"
notion would encourage initiative and
communication, and thus favour interde¬
pendence.
Students will only master a new educa¬
tion for interdependence if they assimilate
its principles and make them a part of
their own behaviour. This would suggest
that civic training, for example through the
encouragement of deliberation on children's
and students' rights, should form part of
their activities. When reality cannot be
brought into the classroom, simulated
situations should be used.
In asking education to adopt the reforms
which will help to prepare today's genera¬
tion for the challenge of tomorrow, we are
asking something which has always been
difficult to implement. Education more
easily follows than leads, more easily
mirrors the present and past than anti¬
cipates the future. But this time, world
survival is at stake. Isn't this the kind of
challenge implicitly assumed by all who
dare to take the sacred trust "to educate"?
William J. Piatt
1) Human Characteristics and School Learning, by
B.S. Bloom. McGraw-Hill, New York, 1976.
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
Planning for play
Although play is essential for children in build¬
ing responsibility, co-operation and the capacity
to integrate into their community, places to play
are increasingly rare. This problem will be exa¬
mined at the Seventh World Conference of the
International Playground Association, whose
theme will be "Play in Human Settlements an
integrated approach." For information about the
conference, to be held in Ottawa (Canada) in
August 1978, please write to Canadian Parks/
Recreation Association, 333 River Rd., Vanier
City, Ontario, Canada.
BOOKSHELF
RECENT UNESCO BOOKS
Thinking Ahead. Unesco and the
challenges of today and tomorrow.
A presentation of Unesco's Medium-
Term Plan for 1977-1982. 1977. 363 pp.
(36 F)
Unesco Statistical Yearbook 1976.
1074 pp. Trilingual: English/French/
Spanish. 1977 (200 F) See opposite
page.
Solar Electricity. An economic
approach to solar energy, by Wolfgang
Palz. Co-published with Butterworths,
London, who have exclusive sales rights
in U.K. 1977. 292 pp. (140 F)
The Challenge Presented to Cul¬
tures by Science and Technology, by
Jean Ladriere. 1977. 165 pp. (38 F)
International Directory of Scholarly
Publishers. 1977. 65 pp. (18 F)
Cultural Policy in Jamaica. A study
prepared by the Institute of Jamaica.
1977. 53 pp. (10 F); Cultural Policy
in Peru. A study prepared by Peru's
National Institute of Culture. 1977.
70 pp. (14 F). (Both published in
Unesco's "Studies and Documents on
Cultural Policies" series)
Communication Policies in Colom¬
bia, by Alberto Carrizosa Alajmo and
others. 1977. 49 pp. (18 F)
Access: Some Western models of
community media, edited by Frances
J. Berrigan. 1977. 229 pp. (40 F)
The Design of Engineering Cur¬
ricula, by Lawrence P. Grayson. 1977.
131 pp. (28 F)
Education and Employment: a
Critical Appraisal, by Martin Carnoy.
1977. 91 pp. (12 F)
Some Aspects of Professional
Freedom of Teachers. An interna¬
tional pilot inquiry, by Ben Morris. 1977.
213 pp. (28 F)
Trends in Environmental Education.
Contributions by experts from 13
1977. 244pp. (36 F)
Social Sciences in Asia III: Burma,
Mongolia, New Zealand, the Philippines,
Singapore. 1977. 111 pp. (16 F)
From Equivalence of Degrees to
Evaluation of Competence, by Jean
Guitón. A study designed to establish
standards of comparison for degrees
and diplomas at different levels of
education. 1977. 138 pp. (30 F)
To our readers
This issue of the UNESCO COURIER and the
previous issue have been published with consi¬
derable delay owing to a number of reasons
beyond our control. We ask our readers' indul¬
gence for the consequent late delivery of these
issues. Every effort is being made to ensure that
publication and distribution schedules will be
met for subsequent issues.
Hermann Hesse
and world literature
To mark the centenary of the birth of the noted
German-born writer Hermann Hesse (Nobel lite¬
rature prize, 1946), Unesco's international quar¬
terly Cultures presents in its latest issue the first
English translation of Hesse's essay "A Library
of World Literature". In the same issue, G.S.
Métraux discusses Hesse's most famous work,
Steppenwo/f, as an analysis of "modern man's
dilemma faced with the decline of a certain form
of civilization and the emergence of new rela¬
tionships between man and society." {Cultures,
Vol. IV, No. 4. 22 Fr. francs)
Heavyweight atlas
Geographers and cartographers from a number
of socialist countries have collaborated on a
newly-published world atlas weighing 33 kilos. If
all the 234 maps (scale 1 cm. = 25 km. ) were laid
out side by side they would cover 120 sq.
metres.
Record $569 million
for UNDP
The United Nations Development Programme
(UNDP) expects to raise a record $569 million in
1978 for technical assistance to developing
countries. However, this sum will still fall short
of the $600 million UNDP needs to raise this year
if it is to meet its target of paying out $2.5 billion
in technical aid during the 1977-1981 period.
Coconut power
Coconut may soon become a major energy
source in many Asian and other tropical coun-,
tries, reports the UNDP's bulletin Action UNDP.
Filipino scientists are examining the possibility of
burning coconut waste (some 6 million tonnes a
year) to generate power.
Living
together
in peace
On 27 January 1978 the U.N. Postal Administra¬
tion is issuing four new stamps in its
"definitive" series. The stamps, in Swiss franc
and U.S. dollar denominations, are on the gene¬
ral theme of "living together in peace". For fur¬
ther information please write to U.N. Postal
Administration, Palais des Nations, CH-1211
Geneva 10, Switzerland.
LAM ERICA LLATINA,
múltiple i una
Catalan edition
of the Unesco Courier
We are happy to announce the launching
of a Catalan language edition of the
Unesco Courier (see photo). Entitled Eh
Correu, the Catalan edition is published
by Editorial Teide S.A., Barcelona,
Spain. The publication of the Catalan
edition, which began in November 1977,
brings the total number of language edi¬
tions of the Unesco Courier to 17:
English, French, Spanish, Russian, Ger¬
man, Arabic, Japanese, Italian, Hindi,
Tamil, Hebrew, Persian, Dutch, Portu¬
guese, Turkish, Urdu and Catalan.
Professional training
for the developing world
Canada's International Development Research
Centre has established fellowships to allow
young professionals from developing countries
to study in Canada. Candidates must have been
working in public service for the past 3 years and
must return to their countries on completion of
their studies. For further details please write to
International Development Research Centre, 60
Queen St., Ottawa, Ontario, Canada.
Flashes...
A World Tourism conference is to be held in
1980.
90 % of the sewage flowing into the Medi¬
terranean each year is untreated, reports the
United Nations Environment Programme
(UNEP).
Switzerland has contributed $500,000 to the
U.N. Fund for Population Activities.
France has presented Egypt with 2, 150,000
Francs (some $444,000), the profits of a 1976
Ramses II exhibition in Paris, for the resto¬
ration of Queen Nefertari's tomb in Nubia.
77?e International Union against Cancer
ÍUICC) is ho/ding a Western European Work¬
shop on smoking control in London on 1-3
March 1978.
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Letters
to
the editor
IN THE HOOF-PRINTS
OF RLS
Sir,
Just 100 years ago, the famous Scottish
writer Robert Louis Stevenson set out on a
jaunt through the Cévennes mountains in
Central France which he later immortalized in
his delightful book Travels with a Donkey
through the Cévennes.
A committee headed by Prof. Philippe
Joutard of Marseilles university has been
created to mark the centenary of the event.
The 200-km-long route which RLS covered
in 12 days with his donkey Modestine is
being specially marked out and some ten
commemorative exhibitions are being orga¬
nized along the way. Hundreds of British
people are expected to turn up and repeat
Stevenson's feat.
Jean Groffier
Castellet, Vaucluse
France
CULTURAL PROFILE
OF LATIN AMERICA
Sir,
As President and Vice-President of the
Latin American and Caribbean group in
Unesco, we should like to transmit our mem¬
bers' congratulations on your issue devoted
to Latin America (Aug-Sept. 1977). We
were impressed by the level of the writing,
the range of topics discussed, and the
healthy variety of viewpoints expressed. We
did not always go along with certain state¬
ments made by some of the authors but
this is perfectly natural. The quality of the
contents was high and the visual presenta¬
tion was first-rate.
Victor Massuh
Permanent Delegate of Argentina
to Unesco
limar Penna Marinho
Permanent Delegate
of Brazil
Sir,
I should like to draw readers' attention to
an error of fact in your otherwise excellent
issue on Latin America. A photo caption on
page 56 describes the episcopal palace at
Lima as "one of the gems of colonial archi¬
tecture." It is true that there are many
magnificent examples of colonial architec¬
ture in Lima and elsewhere in Peru, but the
episcopal palace is not one of them. It was
built barely half a century ago, and the orna¬
mentation on the façade is a faithful repro¬
duction of the colonial style.
Julio Ramón Ribeyro
Cultural Counsellor with the
Peruvian Delegation to Unesco
Sir,
I read your issue on Latin America with
great interest. The selection of contributors
was most satisfactory, as well as the well-
balanced way in which you handled such a
complex subject. Leopoldo Zea's article on
Latin America's ""long journey to self-
discovery" would have presented a distorted
view of the subject had it not been counter¬
balanced by Gilberto Freyre's "Afro-Brazilian
experiment" to mention only two articles
written from completely different if not irre¬
concilable viewpoints.
Today no one would dream of disputing
Europe's imprint on early Latin American his¬
tory. Gilberto Freyre begins his article by
recognizing this as an "irrefutable historical
fact". But to deny, as Zea does, that racial
intermingling is at the root of Latin America's
present social and cultural realities is, in my
opinion, a mistake. Moreover, how far is
one justified in talking about the "juxtaposi¬
tion" of different cultures in a Latin Ameri¬
can culture which is an integrated whole?
Finally, can any culture be free from "ambi¬
guities and ambivalences," a situation which
Zea considers as unique to Latin America?
Gilberto Freyre's study is thus a well-
founded rebuttal of an erroneous view of
Latih American history.
Edilia Camargo
Professor of Philosophy and Aesthetics
University of Panama
Philosophy Division of Unesco
THE RIGHT PRIORITIES?
Sir,
In May 1976 you published a letter from
a group of French students protesting against
the slaughter of baby seals.
Their letter made me think. I admire their
humanitarian motives, but do they realize
that many people die of hunger every day?
When I look at photos taken in South Africa
and see that blacks are being killed there
because they want their freedom, how can I
think about seals? In our century some peo¬
ple are killed more unmercifully than seals.
A.M. Dalil
Teheran, Iran
THE BELEAGUERED ARTIST
Sir,
The monuments on the Acropolis of
Athens are threatened by air pollution and
mass tourism (Unesco Courier, October
1977). But what of today's artists? Surely
they too belong to a disappearing species.
Their work is either misunderstood, or else
systematically exploited to satisfy the
demands of the international art market.
Artists are the lumpen proletariat in
today's sharply defined social hierarchy.
Though they should be recognized as a pro¬
fessional group of major importance, they
lack the organization that would enable them
to play an active part in political, social, eco¬
nomic and even cultural life.
While artists were patiently going about
their business of creating works of art, uns¬
crupulous self-styled "specialists" exploited
snobbery and half-baked intellectualism and
created a system whereby art became a field
1 for investment and speculation. They suc¬
ceeded in diverting works of art from their
original purpose, which is not to become pie¬
ces of merchandise.
This process slowly contaminated the art
world. Weakened by the onslaught, many
artists gradually began to give in and finally
were starved into submission. Today, redu¬
ced to the status of slaves, they must com¬
promise their principles just to stay alive.
Most (but not all, I am glad to say) must
kowtow to blind and pretentious cultural
conformity because this is what is expected
of them by today's patrons of the arts (with a
few exceptions).
But perhaps even more appalling is the
way in which so-called art critics, art histo¬
rians and sociologists (once again, there are
some honourable exceptions! have capitaliz¬
ed on artists' work as a means of flaunting
their own intellectual expertise.
Artists are trapped. They have been depri¬
ved of their freedom to create, and all they
can do is to barter their remaining freedom of
action for money.
The fundamental freedom of artists to
create and to shape the environment must
be restored.
This can be done by formally recognizing
their right to live and work, by giving them
an opportunity to perform their basic func¬
tion in society and by releasing them from
economic and conceptual straightjackets.
Those who hold responsibilities in today's
cultural life and who take their role seriously
must proclaim loud and clear their determi¬
nation to be standard-bearers in mankind's
age-old struggle for true liberation.
Nicolas Schöffer
Sculptor
International Association of Art
Paris
DESERTS AND DEMOGRAPHY
Sir,
The articles in your July 1977 issue ("A
Halt to Desert Advance") show how unwise
it is always to rely on experts who claim that
the Earth has an inexhaustible supply of
natural resources. It would appear that the
only countries that are starting to make
headway in the struggle against encroaching
deserts are those such as China and the
U.S.S.R. which today have no demographic
problem.
Thus birth control is an essential factor in
advancing deserts, since "natural" regula¬
tory mechanisms (child mortality, epidemics,
and wars which in the past were often geno-
cidal) no longer operate
Roger Coulon
Vitrey, France
WANTED
MORE ON SOUTHEAST ASIA
Sir,
I have been an ardent reader of the Tamil
edition of the Unesco Courier ever since it
began publication.
However, I find it distressing that you only
devote scant space to India, China and other
Southeast Asian countries.
K. Subramian
, Vijayawada, India
Editor's note: Over the years the Unesco
Courier has devoted many articles _ and a_
number of? special issues to Southeast,
Asian cultures, including those of China and
the Indian sub-continent. Other issues devo¬
ted partly'or entirely to Southeast Asian cul¬
tures are currently being considered.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
Just published. .
statistical yearbook
annuaire statistique
anuario estadístico
Reference labia TaMcaiu de reference
Education Education
Science and lechnolofy Science et technologie
Libraría RiMiothcq ne»
Book production Edition de livra
Ncwlpapen and other Journaux et autrci
periodic»h pénodiqoci
Cultural paper Papier culturel
Film and cinema Film et cinema
Radio bi .jackalling Radiodtmuion
Tek* mon Télévision
Cuadros dt referencia
Educación
Ciencia y tecnología
' Bibliotecas
F die ¡i i n dc libros
Periódico* ? otra»
publicaciones periódica*
Papel cultural
Pc I leu lai y ciña
Radiodifusión
Televisión
The latest (1976) edition of Unesco's indispensable refe¬
rence book of statistics from over 200 countries on:
D Population
D Education
D Science and technology
D Libraries
D Book production
D Newspapers and periodicals
D Paper consumption
D Film and cinema
D TV and radio
Prepared by Unesco's Office of Statistics with the co¬
operation of National Commissions for Unesco and
national statistical services, and with the help of the
Statistical Office and the Population Division of the
United Nations.
Published for the first time in three languages:
English, French and Spanish.
1,074 pages Hardbound: 200 French francs
Where to renew your subscription
and place your order for other Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller or write direct to the
National Distributor in your country. (See list
below; names of distributors in countries not
listed, along with subscription rates in local
currency, will be supplied on request.)
AUSTRALIA. Publications: Educational Supplies Pty.
Ltd. P.O. Box 33 , Brookvale, 2100. NSW. Periodicals:
Dominie Pty. Subscriptions Dept., P.O. Box 33, Brookvale
2100, NSW. Sub-agent: United Nations Association of
Australia, Victorian Division, Campbell House, 100
Flinders St., Melbourne (Victoria), 3000. - AUSTRIA. Dr.
Franz Hain, Verlags-und Kommissionsbuchhandtung, Industrie¬
hof Stadiau, Dr. Otto Neurath-Gasse 5, 1220 Wien. - BEL¬
GIUM. "Unesco Courier" Dutch edition only: N.V. Handel-
maatschappij Keesing. Keesinglaan 2-18, 2100 Deurne-
Antwerpen. French edition and general Unesco publications
agent: Jean de Lannoy, 202, avenue du Roi, 1060 Brussels, CCP
000-0070823-13. - BURMA. Trade Corporation N° 9, 550-552
Merchant Street, Rangoon. CANADA. Renouf Publishing
Co. Ltd., 2182 St. Catherine Street West, Montreal, Qué H3H
1M7. CYPRUS. "MAM", Archishop Makarios 3rd Avenue,
P.O. Box 1722, Nicosia. - CZECHOSLOVAKIA. - S.N.T.L.,
Spalena 51, Prague 1 (Permanent display); Zahrancni literatura,
11 Soukenicka, Prague 1. For Slovakia only: Alfa Verlag
Publishers, Hurbanovo nam. 6,893 31 Bratislava CSSR.
DENMARK. Munksgaards Boghandel, 6, Norregade, DK
1165, Copenhagen K. - EGYPT (ARAB REPUBLIC OF).
National Centre for Unesco Publications, N° 1 Talaat Harb
Street, Tahrir Square, Cairo. ETHIOPIA. National Agency for
Unesco, P.O. Box 2996, Addis Ababa. - FINLAND. Akateemi-
nen Kirjakauppa, Keskukatu 1, SF-00100 Helsinki 10.
FRANCE. Librairie de l'Unesco, 7, place de Fontenoy, 75700
Paris. C.C.P. 12598-48. - GERMAN DEMOCRATIC REP.
Buchhaus Leipzig, Postfach 140, 710 Leipzig or from Internatio¬
nalen Buchhandlungen in the G.D.R. FED. REP. OF GER¬
MANY. For the Unesco Kurier (German ed. only): 53 Bonn 1,
Colmantstrasse 22, C.C.P. Hamburg 276650. For scientific maps
only: GEO CENTER D7 Stuttgart 80, Postfach 800830. Other
publications: S. Karger GmbH Karger Buchhandlung. Ange¬
rhofstrasse 9, Postfach 2, 8034 Germering/München.
GHANA. Presbyterian Bookshop Depot Ltd., P.O. Box 195,
Accra; Ghana Book Suppliers Ltd., P.O. Box 7869, Accra; The
University Bookshop of Ghana, Accra; The University Bookshop
of Cape Coast; The University Bookshop of Legon, P.O. Box 1,
Legon. - GREAT BRITAIN. See United Kingdom. - HONG
KONG. Federal Publications (HK) Ltd., 5A Evergreen Industrial
Mansion, 12 Yip Fat Street, Aberdeen. Swindon Book Co.,
13-15, Lock Road, Kowloon. - HUNGARY. Akadémiai Kôny-
vesbolt, Vâci u. 22, Budapest V; A.K.V. Konyvtürosok Boltja,
Népkoztársaság utja 16, Budapest VI. ICELAND. Snaebjörn
Jonsson & Co., H.F., Hafnarstraett 9, Reykjavik. INDIA.
Orient Longman Ltd., Kamani Marg, Ballard Estate, Bombay
400038; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Calcutta 13; 36a, Anna Salai,
Mount Road, Madras 2; B-3/7 Asaf Ali Road, New Delhi 1; 80/1
Mahatma Gandhi Road, Bangalore-560001; 3-5-820 Hyderguda,
Hyderabad-500001. Sub-Depots: Oxford Book & Stationery Co.
17 Park Street, Calcutta 70016; Scindia House, New Delhi; Publi¬
cations Section, Ministry of Education and Social Welfare, 511
C-Wing, Shastri Bhavan. New Delhi 110001. _ INDONESIA.
Bhratara Publishers and Booksellers, 29 Jl.Oto Iskandardinata III,
Jakarta; Gramedia Bookshop, Jl. Gadjah Mada 109, Jakarta;
Indira P.T., Jl. Dr Sam Ratulangie 47, Jakarta Pusat. IRAN.
Kharazmie Publishing and Distribution Co., 139 Shah Reza Ave:,
opposite to University of Teheran, P.O. Box 14/1480, Teheran;
Iranian Nat. Comm. for Unesco, Ave. Iranchahr Chomaii No.
300, B.P. 1533. Teheran. IRAQ.. McKenzie's Bookshop, AI-
Rashid Street, Baghdad. - IRELAND. The Educational Com¬
pany of Ireland Ltd., Ballymount Road, Walkinstown, Dublin 12.
ISRAEL. Emanuel Brown, formely Blumstein's Book-stores,
35 Allenby Road and 48 Nachlat Benjamin Street, Tel Aviv; 9,
Shlomzion Hamalka Street, Jerusalem. JAMAICA.
Sangster's Book Stores Ltd., P.O. Box 366, 101 Water Lane,
Kingston. JAPAN. Eastern Book Service Inc., C.P.O. Box
1728, Tokyo 100-92. - KENYA. East African Publishing House,
P.O. Box 30571, Nairobi. - KOREA. Korean National Commis¬
sion for Unesco, P.O. Box Central 64, Seoul. KUWAIT. The
Kuwait Bookshop Co., Ltd, 2942, Kuwait LESOTHO. Maze¬
nod Book Centre, P.O. Mazenod, Lesotho, Southern Africa.
LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy Bookshops Ltd., P.O. Box 286, Mon-
' rovia. LIBYA. Agency for Development of Publication £> Dis-
tribution. P.O. Box 34-35, Tripoli. - LUXEMBOURG. Librairie
Paul Brück, 22, Grande-Rue, Luxembourg. - MALAYSIA.
Federel Publications, Lot 8323, JI.222, Petaling Jaya, Selangor.
MALTA. Sapienzas, 26 Republic Street, Valletta. MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis. MONACO. British Library, 30 bd. des Moulins,
Monte-Carlo. - NETHERLANDS. For the "Unesco Koerier"
Dutch edition only: Systemen Keesing, Ruysdaelstraat 71-75,
Amsterdam-1007. Agent for all Unesco publications: N.V. Marti-
nus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout, 9, The Hague. NETHER¬
LANDS ANTILLES. G.C.T. Ven Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.), N.V.,
Willemstad, Curaçao. N.A. NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office, Government Bookshops at: Rutland Street, P.O.
Box 5344, Auckland; 130, Oxford Terrace, P.O. Box 1721 Christ-
church; Alma street, P.O. Box 857 Hamilton; Princes Street,
P.O. Box 1 104, Dunedin; Mulgrave Street, Private Bag, Welling¬
ton. NIGERIA. The University Bookshop of Ife; The Univer¬
sity Bookshop of Ibadan, P.O. 286; The University Bookshop of
Nsukka; The University Book-shop of Lagos; The Ahmadu Bello
University Bookshop of Zaria. NORWAY. All publications:
Johan Grundt Tanum (Booksellers), Karl Johansgate 41/43,
Oslo 1. For Unesco Courier only: A.S. Narvesens Literaturje-
neste, Box 6125, Oslo 6. PAKISTAN. Mirza Book Agency, 65
Sharah Quaid-e-azam, P.O. Box No. 729, Lahore 3. PHILIP¬
PINES. The Modern Book Co., 926 Rizal Avenue, P.O. Box 632,
Manila D-404. - POLAND. Orpan-lmport. Palac Kultury i
Nauki, Warsaw; Ars Polona-Ruch, Krakowskie Przedmiescie No.
7.00-901 WARSAW. - PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Ltda,
Livraria Portugal, rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. SEYCHELLES.
New Service Ltd., Kingsgate House, P.O. Box 131, Mahe.
SINGAPORE. Federal Publications (S) Pte Ltd., No. 1 New
Industrial Road, off Upper Paya Lebar Road, Singapore 19.
SOMALI DEMOCRATIC REPUBLIC. Modern Book Shop and
General, P.O. Box 951, Mogadiscio. - SOUTH AFRICA. All
publications: Van Schalk's Book-store (Pty.) Ltd., Libri Building,
Church Street, P.O. Box 924, Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency, P.O. Box 1033,
Johannesburg. - SOUTHERN RHODESIA. Textbook Sales
IPVT) Ltd., 67 Union Avenue, Salisbury. - SRI LANKA. Lake
House Bookshop, 100 Sir Chittampalam Gardiner Mawata
P.O.8. 244 Colombo 2. - SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop, P.O.
Box 1118. Khartoum. - SWEDEN. All publications: A/B CE.
Fritzes Kungl, Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Box 16356, 10327
Stockholm 16. For the Unesco Courier: Svenska FN-Förbundet,
Skolgränd 2, Box 150 50 S- 104 65, Stockholm. - SWIT¬
ZERLAND. All publications: Europa Verlag, 5 Rämistrasse.
Zurich. Librairie Payot, rue Grenus 6, 1211, Geneva 11, C.C.P.
12-236. TANZANIA. Dar-es Salaam Bookshop. P.O.B. 9030
Dar-es-Salaam. - THAILAND. Nibondh and Co. Ltd., 40-42
Charoen Krung Road, Siyaegi Phaya Sri, P.O. Box 402,
Bangkok:Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue,
Bangkok; Suksit Siam Company, 1715 Rama IV Road, Bangkok.
- TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal Caddesi, Beyoglu,
Istanbul. - UGANDA. Uganda Bookshop, P.O. Box 145,
Kampala. - UNITED KINGDOM. H.M. Stationery Office, P.O.
Box 569, London, S.E.I., and Government Bookshops in
London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Manchester, Birmingham,
Bristol. - UNITED STATES. Unipub, Box 433 Murray Hill Sta¬
tion, New York, N.Y. 10016. For "Unesco Courier" in Spanish:
Santillana Publishing Company, Inc., 575 Lexington Avenue,
New York, N.Y. 10022. - U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaya Kniga,
Moscow, G-200. - YUGOSLAVIA. Jugoslovenska Knjiga,
Terazije, 27, Belgrade; Drzavna Zalozba Slovenije, Titova C 25,
P.O.B. 50-1, Ljubliana.
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
January 1978
A bulletin published by
the Office
of Public Information
Unesco
7, Place de Fontenoy
75700 Paris, France
from
news
unesco
An ever increasing number of people are taking an interest in the
activities of Unesco. In order to keep this public informed about
Unesco's projects and accomplishments in the different regions of
the world, this special bulletin News from Unesco will be published
at regular intervals. In it you will find a brief summary of current
Unesco actions at Headquarters and, in the field.
A new world
information order
a key to peace
Inadequacy of communication is a
leading cause of misunderstanding and
tension in the world, according to Mr.
Sean MacBride, former foreign minister
of Ireland and winner of the Nobel and
the Lenin Peace Prizes.
Addressing the opening session of the
Unesco-sponsored International
Commission for the Study of
Communication Problems, of which he
is chairman, Mr. MacBride said "If we
can assist in improving communications,
we may also be able to assist in lessening
world tensions."
The 16-member commission held its
first meeting at Unesco Headquarters in
Paris from 14 to 16 December, 1977.
Its chief task, according to Unesco
Director-General Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, is to search for "general
agreement on the manner in which men
should organize free and balanced
exchanges of information and for ways
and means whereby the communication
media may contribute more effectively
to the progress of peoples and their
mutual understanding."
The commission, composed of leading
personalities both policy makers and
professionals from the communications
fieldhas been given the mandate of
studying the totality of communication
problems in contemporary society. It is
to make a preliminary report to the
Unesco General Conference in
November, 1978, and a final report, to
be published in book form, in mid-1979.
Mr. Sean MacBride,
winner of the Nobel and
the Lenin Peace Prizes.
Within this broad framework, however,
the Commission itself is establishing its
own work plan and research priorities.
As Mr. M'Bow emphasized in his
opening address, it is an independent
and autonomous body. While an
attempt has been made in the
composition of the group to see to it
that various cultures and ideological
points of view are reflected, the
members have been named in their
individual capacities and represent no
one but themselves.
A stricking characteristic of
communication problems, the Director-
General said, is their universality. They
arise not only at the international but
also at national and local levels and are
of concern to developing countries and
to industrialized countries alike. Iri
addition, he said, communication is not
merely a problem of material facilities
but also a socio-cultural problem in that
what is involved is a social phenomenon
governing the relations between persons
and between human groups. Finally,
communication is not simply a problem
of information, that is to say the
circulation of news, but must be posed
in more complex, more global and
indeed more "cosmic" terms, in respect
of its philosophical and spatial
dimensions.
In Mr. MacBride's view, four key
questions dominate the current
discussion of communication problems:
D What is meant by the free and
balanced flow of information?
I
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
D What does a "new world information
order" mean, and what is its inter¬
relationship with the new
international economic order?
D How may the "right to
communicate" with all its ethical and
legal implications be achieved
as a new line of thought and action
in the whole communication field?
D How can the objectivity and the
independence of the media be
assured and protected?
The Commission's search for answers
to these basic questions, Mr. MacBride
added, would be "as wide and as
broadminded as our collective will and
effort can make it." While not
minimizing the complexity and the
difficulties of the task, he was hopeful
and confident that the Commission
would be able to attract the cooperation
and good will of all those involved in
communication.'
Following its first meeting, the
Commission announced that a seminar
bringing together representatives of the
"Big Five" news agencies from the
industrialized countries and their
counterparts from Third World agencies
will be held from 24 to 28 April, 1978,
in Stockholm.
The seminar will also include smaller
news agencies from industrialized
countries as well as newspapers and
other media. The general theme of the
meeting will be the infrastructure of
news suppliers, and several working
groups will examine such problems as
the technological evolution of new
transmission, the content of
information, the objectivity and balance
of news now, and the relationships
between news agencies and newspapers
and other media.
Members of the Commission for the
Study of Communication Problems are:
Mr. Elie Abel (USA), dean of the
Graduate School of Journalism,
Columbia University
Dr. F.I. Agporuaro Omu (Nigeria),
Commissioner for Information, Social
Development and Sports, Bendel State
Mr. Hubert Beuve-Méry (France),
founder, Le Monde
Mr. Gabriel Garcia Marquez
(Colombia), novelist, author of "One
Hundred Years of Solitude"
Mr. Mochtar Lubis (Indonesia),
journalist, President, Press Foundation
of Asia
Mr. Elelbe Ma Ekonzo (Zaire), director
general, Zaire Press Agency
Mr. Mustapha Masmoudi (Tunisia),
Secretary of State for Information
Mr. Herbert Marshall McLuhan
(Canada), sociologist, communication
theorist
Mr. Michio Nagai (Japan), editorial
writer, Asahi Shimbun
Mr. Bogdan Osolnik (Yugoslavia),
journalist, Vice President, Federal
Council of the Socialist Federal
Republic of Yugoslavia
Mr. Gamal el Oteifi (Egypt), journalist,
Deputy Speaker, Parliament
Mr. J. P. Pronk (Netherlands),
economist, Minister for Development
Cooperation since 1973
Mr. Juan Somavia (Chile), executive
director, Latin American Institute for
Transnational Studies
Mr. Boobli George Verghese (India),
former editor, Hindustan Times
Mr. Leonard Zamiatin (USSR), director
general, TASS News Agency
"Aid African liberation movements"
European youth urge Waldheim
Some 400 young people from 14
European countries have sent a telegram
to U.N. Secretary-General Kurt
Waldheim urging the U.N. and its
member states to "step up their support
for liberation movements in their
struggle for freedom and national
independence."
The telegram was drafted by
participants in Unesco's annual Youth
Day devoted to the theme of human
rights in Southern Africa. Representing
Unesco Clubs, Associated Schools and
other institutions, they spent the day at
Unesco studying the right to education,
the right to work and the right to
expression and culture in South Africa,
Zimbabwe and Namibia. They also
heard addresses by Mgr Donal Lamont,
Bishop of Umtali, who was expelled by
the Rhodesian Government for allowing
medical assistance to be given to African
freedom fighters, and Mr. Perter
Katjavivi, a spokesman for the South
West Africa Peoples' Organization
(SWAPO).
Bishop Lamont said he was encouraged
by the young people's demonstration of
concern for human rights, pointing out
that lack of such concern was "a sure
sign of moral underdevelopment." He
had been removed by the Rhodesian
regime because he recognized that the
treatment it gave to the mass of the
population of Zimbabwe was a gross
violation of human rights.
Mr. Katjavivi told the young people that
all men of conscience in Southern Africa
who opposed the regimes there risked
fates similar to that of Bishop Lamont.
People in that part of the continent
were denied the most basic rights of
man: that was one of the main aspects
of the liberation struggle of his
organization.
World congress
of Unesco Clubs
Three decades after the founding of the
first Unesco Club in the world (in
Japan) the first world congress of the
Unesco Club movement will be held
next April at Unesco Headquarters in
Paris.
Two themes have been proposed for the
meeting which is expected to attract
Unesco Club representatives from 76
countries. The first is the new
international economic order and in
particular the contribution which
communication can make to such an
order. The second is human rights in
conjunction with the 30th anniversary of
the Universal Declaration of Human
Rights.
The congress has been made possible by
a very generous contribution from the
Japan Shipbuilding Industry
Foundation.
II
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
Asian news agencies
seek closer links
News agencies of 17 Asian countries are
taking the first steps toward establishing
a network for the exchange of news and
features following a Unesco-sponsored
meeting in Colombo, Sri Lanka, last
December.
Attended by observers from 16
international non-governmental
organizations as well as the news agency
experts, the meeting recommended a
feasibility study on the network as well
as identification of agencies willing to
serve as clearing houses or redistribution
centres. A five-member working group
(India, Indonesia, Iran, Mongolia and
Sri Lanka, plus representatives of
Unesco and the International
Telecommunications Union) was set up
to conduct the study.
In addition, the meeting invited Unesco
to organize a survey on the technical
needs of Asian news agencies; to study
the possibilityof setting up a special
fund for assisting national news
agencies; to prepare an inventory of
training facilities in Asia, and to
organize refresher courses and
workshops in some Asian
communication institutes or news
agencies.
Gondola builders
helped by
Unesco appeal
The sole remaining boatyard in the
world for building gondolas is being
aided thanks to Unesco's appeal for the
safeguard of Venice. It is one of the
beneficiaries of some $500,000 which
has been raised in five months by ten
private committees set up in response to
the appeal. Other restoration projects
being financed from the contributions
include several historic churches (San
Stae, San Pietro di Castello, La Pieta,
Santa Maria dei Miracoli, San
Bartolomeo and San Martino di
Castello) as well as schools and other
monuments.
Ill
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
Insurers ponder
earthquake risks
Could the insurance industry cover the
property losses if a major earthquake
were to strike a modern city such as San
Francisco or Tokyo? Damage in the first
case could total $50 billion, it has been
estimated, and in the second as much as
$100 billion.
Questions such as this will be on the
agenda of a Unesco international
seminar on earthquake hazards and
insurance to be held next summer. The
meeting will bring together seismologists
and earthquake engineers on the one
hand and economists and insurance
specialists on the other to discuss the
many problems involved.
Previous meetings on the subject have
found that there is a need for better co¬
ordination of knowledge beween science
and the insurance industry with respect
to risk assessment. They have also
noted a lack of readily available
statistical information on the location of
risks, the classes of buildings and their
susceptibility to loss.
Part of this information gap may be
covered by a related Unesco project
which envisages the setting up of a
worldwide earthquake data bank.
Towards an
international
passport for
university studies
In the future university students
wishing to study abroad may find their
transfers facilitated by an "International
Education Record Book."
This is one of the ideas put forward
by Jean Guiton in a recent Unesco
publication: "From Equivalence of
Degrees to Evaluation of Competence."
The record book, which Guitón
compares to the International
Vaccination Certificate issued by the
World Health Organization, would
enable host country university officials
to make a better evaluation of a
prospective candidate's chances of
success. It would include such
information as personal data, studies
completed, other achievements,
experiences and general ability to adjust
to new studies, linguistic knowledge and
ability, and an overall appraisal. The
section on studies would go into some
detail regarding methods, aims and
content of the studies pursued, the
system of assessment used, and
particular abilities and aptitudes.
Such a document, Guitón concedes,
would encounter many obstacles at first,
but its increasingly widespread use
would strengthen the movement away
from the present system of equivalences
of diplomas and degrees and toward
"personal appraisal" and "considered
judgment."
"No to violence,
Yes to peace":
the message of
Pope Paul VI
"Peace must be! Peace is possible"
wrote Pope Paul VI in his message for
World Peace Day (1st January, 1978), a
signed copy of which was presented to
the Director-General of Unesco by Mgr
Renso Frana, permanent.observer of the
Holy See to Unesco.
Far from being an idealistic dream or
an attractive utopia impossible to attain,
peace is "an idea that is gaining prestige
in the conscience of humanity," the
Holy Father continued. "Helsinki
teaches this. And these hopes are
confirmed by the forthcoming special
session of the United Nations General
Assembly, devoted to the problem of
disarmament."-
After proclaiming the absolute
necessity of peace which the great
international institutes strive to promote
and defend, the Pope denounced the
violence of today's world. "Violence is
not a true force," he said. "It is the
explosion of a blind energy which
degrades the person who gives in to it."
In a letter of thanks to the Pope, the
Director-General, Mr. Amadou-Mahtar
M'Bow, stressed the close relationship
between the spiritual ideals of the
message and Unesco's efforts to
establish a "just, lasting and
constructive peace." Citing the fact
that 1979 has been proclaimed
International Year of the Child and
noting that the Pope's message was
addressed particularly to children and
young people, Mr. M'Bow concluded
"Your Holiness's appeal will certainly
be heeded by all as it is henceforth
heeded by Unesco."
Back to school
programmes urged
for architects
Doctors, lawyers and other professional
groups spend a great deal of time
keeping up to date on latest
developments in their field, but
architects are behind in this respect, a
recent Unesco meeting was told.
Jointly organized by Unesco and the
International Union of Architects, the
meeting brought together specialists
from 30 countries to discuss the problem
of continuing education for architects.
Every country should formulate its own
specific operational objectives for this
training, the seminar recommended, and
should also consider whether continuing
education should be mandatory. The
participants also called for the
preparation of a programme which
would enable architects to intervene in
new fields normally outside professional
practice. This would include
participation in the decision-making
process in planning and programming at
the national level, as well as the
rehabilitation of historic quarters and
the conservation of buildings and rural
areas.
Making museums
thief-proof
People began stealing works of art
long before they began stealing money,
in fact long before money was invented.
Mankind's earliest records reveal that
cultural property has always been in
danger from thieves and vandals.
Today the protection of precious
collections is a major problem for
everyone from the directors of the
world's great museums to the humblest
parish priest, and practical help for
them is provided in a recent Unesco
handbook: "The Guarding of Cultural
Property". Written by William A.
Bostick, former administrator and
secretary of the Detroit Institute of
Arts, the pamphlet is the first in a new
series designed to give technical
guidance in various aspects of the care
and treatment of museum collections
and the preservation of monuments.
Chapters include various aspects of
security inside and outside museums, the
human element in security, the use of
mechanical and electronic devices,
enlisting the assistance of visitors and
volunteers, and achieving the maximum
security within the limits of manpower.
IV
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Down-to-earth
astronautics
The world community is today reaping a host of practical benefits from
international co-operation in peaceful space research through both
manned and unmanned flights. (See article page 16.) Below, Soviet
cosmonauts Valeri Bykovsky and Vladimir Aksyonov practise landing
techniques before a mission in a Soyuz 22 spacecraft.
-
mm
» "i
'
%l
tx
;
' ..
I m
-P'
3BS2
- t
Photo A.P.N., Moscow
]]>
</page>
</document>
