<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="078451eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
© A. CL. Brussels
Monuments of stone are often victims of diseases that cause them to corrode
and decay. Here the features of a statue of the Virgin, in the Abbey of St. Ghis-
lain, Belgium, are slowly being effaced by one of these maladies (see page 26).
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Courier
JANUARY 1965
18TH YEAR
PUBLISHED IN
NINE EDITIONS
English
French
Spanish
Russian
German
Arabic
U.S.A.
Japanese
Italian
COVER P H OTO
Tree roots spread like giant
tentacles over a sculptured
stone head as jungle vegetation
invades the temples of Angkor
in Cambodia. Today this mag¬
nificent ensemble of monu¬
ments is being restored and
also protected from many ills
that threatened to destroy it
completely (see page 28).
Unesco-Cart
Page
4 MONUMENTS IN PERIL
A world campaign to protect our cultural heritage
7 THE NEW SCIENCE OF ART CONSERVATION
By Harold J. Plenderleith
11 VENICE, A SINKING CITY
By Pietro Gazzola
14 THE CARE OF OLD PAINTINGS
18 APHRODITE'S CITY RESUSCITATED
Photo reportage in full colour
24 MAP OF UNESCO CONSERVATION MISSIONS
26 STONES ALSO DIE
By René Sneyers
28 ANGKOR - BEFORE AND AFTER
A complex of temples saved from the jungle
33 THE MENACE OF THE BULLDOZERS
By John 0. Brew
37 TO THE YOUNG PEOPLE OF THE WORLD
A message for the New Year
By René Maheu
38 FROM THE UNESCO NEWSROOM
THE UNITED NATIONS EDUCATIONAL, SCIENTIFIC AND CULTURAL ORGANIZATION
Published monthly by UNESCO
Editorial Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7", France
Editor-in-Chief
Sandy Koffler
Assistant Editor
René Caloz
Associate Editors
English Edition : Ronald Fenton
French Edition : Jane Albert Hesse
Spanish Edition : Arturo Despouey
Russian Edition : Victor Goliachkov
German Edition : Hans Rieben (Berne)
Arabic Edition : Abdel Moneim El Sawi (Cairo)
Japanese Edition: Shin-lchi Hasegawa (Tokyo)
Italian Edition : Maria Remiddi (Rome)
Layout & Design
Robert Jacquemin
THE UNESCO COURIER is published monthly, except in July ind August when
it is bi-monthly (1 1 issues a year) in English, French, Spanish, Russian, German,
Arabicjapanese, and Italian. In the United Kingdom it is distributed by H M.
Stationery Office, P. O. Box S69, London, S. E. I.
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted may be reprinted providing
the credit line reads "Reprinted from THE UNESCO COURIER", plus date
of issue, and two voucher copies are sent to the editor. Signed articles re¬
printed must bear author's name. Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned
unless accompanied by an international reply coupon covering postage. Signed
articles express the opinions of the authors and do not necessarily represent
the opinions of UNESCO or those of the editors of THE UNESCO COURIER.
The Unesco Courier Is indexed monthly In The Readers' Guide to
Periodical Literature published by H. W. Wilson Co., New York.
Annual subscription rates : 15/-stg. ; 8 3.00 (Canada);
10 French Francs or equivalent ; 2 years: 27/-stg. ; 18 F.
Single copies 1/6-stg ; 30 cents ; 1 F.
(M.C. 64.1.. 198 A)
N° 1, 196S
Sales & Distribution Offices
Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris 7*.
All correspondence should be addressed to the Editor-in-Chief.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
MONUMENTS
IN PERIL
A WORLD CAMPAIGN TO PROTECT
OUR CULTURAL HERITAGE
Our December 1964 issue reviewed the results of
the International Campaign to Save the Monu¬
ments of Nubia. The present number is devoted to
the International Campaign for Monuments which
Unesco launched last June. The campaign's purpose
is to foster greater public and official awareness of
the need to safeguard our monuments and cultural
treasures of the past from the neglect and ravages
of time which often endanger them. Where these
monuments are in peril, Unesco's member states
have been called upon to take direct action for their
protection. It is hoped that this issue will help to
focus attention and interest on this important
cultural problem facing many countries today.
Carcassonne in Southwest France
appears today exactly as it did in medie¬
val times, thanks to a remarkable feat of
restoration in the 19th century which has
saved it for posterity. The ramparts were
themselves built on the ruins of earlier
walls raised by the Romans and Visigoths.
© Paul Almasy, Paris
wmiii i
.' * i . X
*> v II *
^^/#|#>*X«;¿
¡P * . ¡j -y-3 x v ' i-. «
I NE of man's distinctive features ¡s his habit of
leaving behind on the soil from which he wrests
his livelihood all sorts of remains which provide a record
of his history. As the centuries go by, most of them are
reduced to ruins, to piles of stone or brick, sometimes
even to a mere succession of layers like the layers of
sediment at the bottom of the sea.
Digging into the earth, we come across these remnants
of ancient civilizations a blackened area with its reminder
of a fire, a layer of silt that means a flood has passed that
way, or the traces of far-reaching geological events alternat¬
ing with layers in which the vestiges of vanished cultures
appear.
But from age to age, man reconstructs in order to meet
new needs. He may again use the old stones, grind marble
to dust and make lime of it, demolishing what he regards
as useless and rebuilding on the same foundations. When
a city is no longer in keeping with the political structure of
a people or drops in status through a monarch's whim, or
war or pestilence have taken their toll, its fate is neglect
and, unless newcomers unwittingly camp in its ruins, no
one cares any more about its origins or its history. That
has happened for thousands of years.
Nevertheless, some special buildings and places such as
sacred precincts, temples and the tombs of the mighty,
were designed to last forever and were generally respec¬
ted by those who came after; and certain public construc¬
tions, such as fortifications, could endure for centuries
without losing their utility. In any case, man instinctively
built, if not for eternity, at least for his descendants.
Knowing how brief his own span of life was, he speculated
on the continuity of his institutions. With great labour and
expense, a community would erect the palace of a reigning
dynasty, a city hall, a market, a theatre or a place for
games. In the course of time, a new religion might appro¬
priate the temples of its predecessor, a republic might take
over the residence of a fallen prince. But when piety grew
faint, the heroes were forgotten or the prince took up
residence elsewhere, then the public buildings were
abandoned.
Then, again, wars were as fatal as revolutions to these
constructions that came to be associated with a hostile
authority. From time immemorial, the enemies of a religion
have sacked its holy places, rebels have turned their fury
on all that glorified the rulers, and invaders have wished to
wipe out all trace of the greatness of the people they have
conquered. A change of dynasty or of regime, even a
change of taste, was enough to condemn great buildings
to neglect and even to demolition. Repairs or additions
were nearly always made in the style of the new era.
The restoration of a building, often revered solely on
account of its age, was mostly in the nature of a recon¬
struction under new forms that revealed the new architects'
lack of interest in the work of their predecessors. Not
until comparatively recently have Europeans begun to
regard ancient works as relics that have survived from a
glorious past.
At first, their interest was simply one aspect of the
universal curiosity of the age of the Renaissance, which
devoted the same energy to exploring lands and seas as
it did to the study of remote history, discovering, beyond
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
ir* ,
|ÜX**
íS» ;' »Î üí %4É
%í ' \ V
¿b^V%
the immediate past, the more exciting record of Greek
genius and Roman grandeur, precious relics of which still
survived. These relics were greeted with enthusiastic
admiration by the humanists who styled them "monuments"
In the sense in which the word is used today.
While literary monuments parchments and papyruses
were copied and published at that time and antique statues
were cleared of debris and set up in palaces and in gardens,
it must be admitted that many an architectural monument
even some of the most admired, which artists sought to
imitate or equal continued to be used as a quarry.
Furthermore, as old values inevitably collapsed, Europe
seeking its ideal in classical antiquity, broke with the Middle
Ages; the works of that period met with less and less under¬
standing and were often ruthlessly destroyed.
Not until the 18th century did Europe at last rediscover
its medieval past and, following the teaching of certain
enlightened spirits, learn to take an interest in the works
of all civilizations, in the monuments of all countries, of all
peoples and of all ages.
This interest was matched during the* same period by the
beginnings of scientific archaeology, thanks to which the
study of ancient relics replaced the "treasure hunt" of the
preceding centuries. The miraculous excavations of Pompeii
and Herculaneum and, later, the exploration of towns
that had been swallowed up by the desert or the jungle,
made it possible to resurrect vanished civilizations. Ruins
acquired some meaning; and castles and old dwellings,
churches and convents likewise took on a new significance.
By now we have reached the point when we can read the
full record of man's mastery over the earth in those monu¬
ments which reflect the spiritual aspirations or social Ideas
of their times, as also in the buildings and engineering
works which served to meet the needs of everyday life.
Walls, gates, aqueducts and canals, bridges and old roads;
the traces of industries which have died out, illustrating how
the elements were tamed by human ingenuity; every vestige
bearing the imprint of human thought, everything denoting
the triumph of man over nature, seems worthy of our
interest.
Even in the case of buildings whose purpose was strictly
utilitarian, some concern for elegance can usually be
detected in the handling of practical problems, while there
is likewise an underlying harmony of proportions, a rhythm,
an interplay of line and colour, and dimensions which reflect
and harmonize with a given site and environment, all pro¬
ducing a lasting impression which will be a source of
pleasure and satisfaction to builder and spectator alike.
This pleasure is still felt, even after many generations, even
if we know nothing of the history or are ill prepared to
understand the artistic language of the time, for beauty
responds to a craving of our innermost being.
As we begin to appreciate these long-ignored treasures,
we become aware of their fragility and of the gravity of
the dangers which threaten them. An over-dry or humid
climate, sun or frost, sand or wind, vegetation or parasites
and, still worse, atmospheric pollution, will cause any
ancient building to crumble slowly unless it is constantly
cared for. Then, again, a monument may suffer from
excessive care or exaggerated renovations. Or it may
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
MONUMENTS IN PERIL (Cont'd)
deteriorate as the result of unfortunate changes in its
setting.
Man himself is still the most dangerous enemy of man's
creations not only man the warrior, the avenger, the van¬
dal, the iconoclast; the town planner, the engineer, the
builder, are just as much to be feared when, thinking only
in terms of practical efficiency, they confine their ambitions
to the task in hand" and take no care to check the harsh
dynamism of their age the economic pressures, the explo¬
sive growth of cities, the chaotic spread of suburbs and
industrialized areas. The example of dams and great
hydro-electric works submerging all cultural property, both
what is visible and what still lies hidden beneath the soil,
reflects in gravity and extent the whole problem of the
choice that has to be made between the heritage of the
past and the requirements of the future.
Between these two imperatives a compromise must at all
costs be found. The saving of the monuments of Nubia,
following an appeal made by Unesco, proves that it is
feasible, even on an international scale. And it is at the
international level that the protection of monuments against
the dangers of wholesale destruction must be sought, since
the maintenance of world peace is obviously a prerequisite
for their conservation, now that no building from the past
can withstand the effects of modern armaments.
NOTHER conclusion can be drawn from the
large-scale works of restoration which have
been carried out during recent decades, namely that we
now have the necessary technical means to protect,
repair, restore and, if necessary, even transfer any monu¬
ment. Moreover, in many countries monuments are
afforded special protection by legislation which regulates
and services which carry out all operations in this field.
This would appear to mean that we are equipped to
ensure the full conservation of the wealth of archaeolo¬
gical remains and other monuments in the world.
Would such conservation be likely to turn large parts
of the world into one gigantic museum? The cham¬
pions of the monuments, even the most stubborn, think so
extreme a solution unfeasible; they agree that the course
of technical progress cannot be reversed, and that in
certain cases it may require the sacrifice of buildings
associated with outmoded ways of working or of living. It is
also clear from experience that the dynamism of an era will
have the last word. Tremendous efforts are needed to save
even a limited number of monuments.
Even then, well-planned and conscientiously applied
legislation, good technical facilities and adequate financial
means are not enough. Monuments are certain to be pre¬
served only when ordinary citizens, realizing the value of
a given monument and knowing that with it something
irreparable will be lost, then combine of their own accord
to ensure that it will be preserved.
Monuments must be publicized and understood, and
friends be found for them, near and far. Thanks to the
extraordinary facilities for mass communication now avail¬
able, this can be done. The outline of a temple buried in the
depths of the desert becomes familiar to magazine readers,
cinema audiences and children at school. Tourists, once
they know about them, are only too eager to visit monuments
that lie along their route and offer an excuse for excursions,
even to out-of-the-way sites.
If the fate of a monument rests in the hands of an
6 effective administrative service, it will arouse interest far
beyond the circle of specialists and be a familiar image to
great numbers of people who will regard it with affection,
even if they are from other countries, some of them remote
indeed.
There is reason to hope, therefore, that this attitude will
become world-wide, fostering in all peoples an awareness
of their joint responsibility for monuments. In launching an
International Campaign for Monuments, Unesco seeks to
deepen this awareness and to facilitate the preservation of
the cultural heritage of mankind while at the same time
enhancing this heritage by making monuments an integral
part of the everyday life of peoples.
Admittedly, if we view the monuments of architecture in
relation to their restless environment, many obstacles to
that integration will become apparent. It often seems that
certain buildings especially those that no longer serve any
practical purpose are simply there in defiance of the
modernization in towns, as an obstacle to traffic and a
heavy financial burden. If, therefore, a monument is for¬
tunate enough still to serve its original purpose religious,
political or social it will be essential to see that it con¬
tinues to do so, even if some practical draw-backs are
involved; otherwise a use should be found for it, or it might
be adapted to some new purpose.
If it is to survive, it must, in one way or another, take
its place in ordinary life, help to mould the taste of the
younger generation, serve as a splendid illustration of an
historical period, remain or become a symbol, the emblem
of a town or a township, a familiar landmark in some rural
or urban area. It could serve as a starting point for town
planning, the justification for the maintenance or the crea¬
tion of a park, a place of rest in our feverish cities, bringing
to our distracted times a moment of quiet repose.
Most states, fortunately, are alive to the advantages of
doing this in the interests of tourists, and citizens as a whole
are not altogether indifferent to the resulting aesthetic,
cultural and practical benefits.
Nevertheless, it is impossible to make intelligent use of
a monument unless the responsible authorities, the town
planners and architects, and the owners of land and house
property come to agree that there is no common denomina¬
tor between the drawbacks entailed in the preservation of
a monument and the absolute gain derived from its beauty,
its human significance, and its spiritual aura.
I T is thus clear that, in the last analysis, the
question of the life or death of monuments
is one that closely concerns us and that the issue is
very clear-cut: either we assume in regard to the future
the responsibility for allowing a large part of these relics
of past civilizations to disappear, and thereby deprive
future generations of the opportunity of becoming acquaint¬
ed with the works handed down to us from the past,
by sacrificing them to the arrogant and intoxicating
adventure of a new world which will be the negation
of the old; or else we accept the principle of human
solidarity in time as in space and, adopting a new
approach, play our true historical role, knowing that we
live in an age in which it is no longer necessary to destroy
in order to create, which is perfectly capable of making
respect for what has been handed down from the past part
and parcel of its most daring plans for the future, and which
has the means of helping present-day man to commune
with the great works of his ancestors.
By adopting the second attitude, there can be no doubt
that we shall enhance the chances of seeing a more humane
civilization arise, in which the knowledge of the past will
find its place side by side with the discoveries by which
man hopes to better his future.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
THE OF KIZHY
An open-air museum of architectural monuments in wood has been
set up at Kizhy on an island of Lake Onega in northern U.S.S.R. As its
centrepiece it has the famous ensemble shown below: the 22 cupola
Church of the Transfiguration (right) built in 1714 (Peter the Great is said
to have drawn up its plans); the 10-cupola Church of the Intercession
built in 1764 (left) and between them a belfry built in 1874. The Church
of the Transfiguration is solid timberwork and does not contain a single
nail (detail in photo right). Restoration of this church, which was seriously
damaged during the Second World War, was completed last year.
Photos c A.P.N.
THE NEW SCIENCE
OF ART CONSERVATION
by Harold J. Plenderleith
I T is not easy to explain in simple terms what
is meant by the conservation of a monument.
Broadly, a monument may be made of any material and
it may be of any size, but a simple generally accepted
classification recognises two main types, the fixed object
and the portable object.
The temple, the statue and the totem pole are examples
that have to withstand the action of wind and rain, heat and
cold. Old ships such as the Vasa (raised from the sea bed
in Stockholm harbour; see "Unesco Courier," July-August
1960) or the Victory (preserved at Portsmouth, England),
provide special problems concerned with the control of
humidity, prevention from shrinkage and protection from
insect attack. Mural paintings, on the other hand, are
normally sheltered from extremes of temperature, but may
be invaded by capillary moisture and attacked by mould.
The portable objects within the category of monuments
are legion, comprising bygones as diverse as swords and
accoutrements, musical instruments, vestments and incuna-
bulae, the contents, in fact, of our museums, picture galler¬
ies, libraries and archives. A new science has developed
in the conservation of all these things. We are emerging
from the dark ages when medicine men applied secret
(1) For further reading, see "Archaeology and the Microscope", by L. Bieck;
London. Lutterworth Press. 1963.
nostrums and a gullible public was content to shirk its
responsibility and leave its priceless cultural heritage in
the hands of the soi-disant restorer.
The name "restorer" for the want of a better one, still
clings, but the connotation has changed beyond recogni¬
tion, for the modern practitioner is ideally a highly skilled
technician with basic training in physics and chemistry and
biology. He is organized, probably a member of the pro¬
fessional association, the International Institute for Conser¬
vation. He preserves a complete documentation of all
his work, publishes his results and discusses them in confe¬
rences held at regular intervals by the International Council
of Museums not only with his fellow restorers, but with
museum scientists and historians of art. Science in our
generation is at last working in the service of monuments
and of museums in no spirit of arrogance, but in full
co-operation with the art critic and the archaeologist (1).
It is tempting to digress and discuss the cause of this
awakening, but one need only consider the great improve¬
ments in the sensitivity of scientific equipment and the end¬
less variety of modern synthetic materials waiting to be
exploited in a knowlegeable way, in order to realize that
today, more than ever before, science, rightly applied, can
be the handmaid of the arts.
Synthetic materials have been developed to such an
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
ART CONSERVATION (Cont'd)
Art treasures on
the operating table
extent that they no longer need claim to be substitutes for
natural products, for they often provide improved pro¬
perties that are novel and of great utility. Modern synthetic
materials include the detergents and the wetting agents and
the waxes that are actually soluble in water, and very
useful as leather dressings, synthetic fibres, synthetic adhe-
sives and the very interesting compound called "soluble
nylon" that can be used as an impregnating medium on
tempera painting for consolidating a powdery surface
without imparting any residual shine. It can also be used
to consolidate pottery from salty deserts whilst the salts
are being washed from it and is readily removed afterwards
if desired.
It is now often possible by soft X-rays to record through
a painting the original crayon sketch made by the artist
on his canvas. Only a few years ago this would have been
regarded as miraculous. It is also possible to remove
a fresco from the wall and leave behind the mural painter's
original sinopia drawing, thus exposing for the art critic
a stimulating new world of interest.
In Moscow, certain painted icons have been found to be
built up in a series of strata on one and the same wooden
panel, and a special technique has been evolved whereby
it is possible to recover the lower and older ones without
losing those above. Pictures can be transferred from
worm-eaten panels and mounted on sound ones, and in
other cases rotting canvases are replaced by new ones.
In fact, the most delicate material and most complex struc¬
tures can be saved by the skill of the modern restorer.
I:N the field of archaeology, the mechanism of
I metallic corrosion, a universal cause of
deterioration, is now well understood and means have
been devised to remove it or, at option, to arrest its
advance without necessarily destroying the aesthetic
character of the piece. There is hope, therefore, that
many of the world's monumental treasures that are
threatened by exposure to atmospheres polluted by indus¬
trial fumes may be saved objects universally acclaimed
such as the splendid gilt bronze horses of St Marks,
Venice, or the lion and griffon of Perugia whereas,
in the absence of these recent advances in the service
of conservation, their years were numbered. The threat
will remain, however, as long as we are content to breathe
air that is polluted with sulphur compounds. The cumula¬
tion action on metals is as devastating as it is on the
human subjectl
. An altogether new field has been opened up by the phy¬
sicist in the application of his methods, of non-destructive
testing, and these have already made notable contributions
to the conservation of monuments. An example that Im¬
mediately comes to mind of modern science in action is
the discovery and excavation of an Etruscan tomb.
First the scientist applies his stethoscope to mother
earth. The detection equipment of the Lerici Foundation
in Italy, famous for its discoveries of Etruscan tombs (see
"Unesco Courier," Feb. 1957) can be compared with a ste¬
thoscope in sensitivity. When the scientist detects a discon¬
tinuity beneath the surface he can pin-point the centre
of a subterranean chamber and fix his instruments with
such care that on drilling vertically and inserting a special
tubular periscope with appropriate lighting, he has a
complete view of the interior. All that has been done to
make this possible is to drill a little hole in the ground
10 cm. in diameter.
That, however, is no more than the beginning. He has
located the tomb. He now proceeds to insert a small
CONT'D ON PAGE 10
An injection
for immortality
A wooden statue, its hands
clasped in prayer, is given
an injection against a sick¬
ness that would otherwise
have reduced it to powder.
Something like 80 % of
works of art in wood are
infested by insects which
thrive on a diet of dry, old
wood rich in starches and
sugar. They live and proli¬
ferate in the wood, boring
out innumerable tunnels in
the process. Today special
chemicals are injected
which seep throughout the
infested object, kill the
invader insects and prevent
reinf estation. Objects
which have been seriously
weakened by wood-boring
insects can be consolidated
by deep injections of plastic
solutions or emulsions.
Sarcophagi from Egypt and,
thousands of sculptures in
all parts of the world have
been cured by these tech¬
niques, as have celebrated
"invalids" such as the mag¬
nificent woodwork in
Westminster Abbey, Lon¬
don and the famed sculp¬
tures in the opera house of
the Château of Versailles.
© Solvay, Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
*!*âr
m ">*-* i
SI-
9
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
ART CONSERVATION (Cont'd)
Detecting the 'heartbeat' of a tomb
camera into the tube and he takes a series of six colour
photographs, rotating the camera through 60° between each.
When these photographs are laid out in orderly succession,
there is a complete record of the paintings that commonly
adorn the walls, of any bas-reliefs and of grave goods, etc.
Here is the monument disclosed for study yet without a
sod being turned. A decision has now to be taken and
an important deduction made. Is the tomb worthy of the
time, care and cost, necessary for its scientific excavation?
If not, it can be sealed and concealed and we are the
richer for the documentation that has already been obtained.
If, however, it is decided to excavate, the photographs
will show how to go about it for they will disclose the
position of the entrance door: the location of the entrance
passage can be deduced, and instead of breaking in
through walls or ceiling, as would have happened in pre¬
vious generations, the excavation can be so conducted as
to avoid all damage by entering the tomb from the side by
its own passage and doorway. But this is not the end. The
monument will be destroyed unless humidities are main¬
tained, at least until the mural paintings can be removed
and conditioned to the drier environment above ground.
We have learnt much from our wartime experience of fire
and pestilence and, not least, that the slow decay of sus¬
ceptible material by exposure to damp can be quite as
destructive as the damage from detonations of high
explosives.
A picture may disappear from a wall eaten up by mould
growths, leaving only a nondescript stain. But even here
science may have the last word. I know of paper bearing
invisible drawings having been nursed into shape and
successfully doctored by chemicals so that the drawings
were actually brought back to life again. Things that
are invisible to the naked eye can be photographically
recorded by using the methods of ultra-violet fluorescence,
and, as is known in every police laboratory, there are
several methods by which it may be possible to recover
and decipher on charred or burnt documents writings or
drawings when the ink seems to have been completely
burnt away.
The Italians are past masters at what might be called
preservation medicine and surgery. This is born of a na¬
tural facility in the studio and laboratory and the untold
wealth of their cultural heritage which demands incessant
attention. For it is not true that a monument having
survived from antiquity, will necessarily go on surviving.
Nature is always in a condition of change and the change
may be either sudden, as when an object is excavated,
or slow and relentless, as when a building is allowed to
fall into neglect.
FIRST come the rains, then growths appear of
moss, lichens or algae, and the mortar is loosen¬
ed. Ivy grows over the ruin, attacks the structure with its
penetrating suckers. Humus is formed, plants root them¬
selves, the level of the surrounding earth rises and capillary
moisture weakens the foundations so that the building
becomes derelict and in this condition it is liable to be used
as an all-too-convenient source of stone for adjacent build¬
ing or agricultural purposes.
How different is the picture when the aids of science are
involved. -The modern architect and chemist knows how
to exclude moisture, prevent or destroy damaging organic
growths without contaminating the stone, introduce a
hidden armature of ferro-concrete, grout the walls with
an approved cement, and, if the foundations are unsatis¬
factory or unstable hydrologically, there are simple means
10 by which consolidation is possible using the methods of
electro-osmosis as applied, for example, in Warsaw by
Cebertowicz to prevent the Church of St. Anna from des
truction due to the movement of the clay slope on which it
rested. The clay was consolidated, the movement was
arrested and a rock-like basis for the structure provided
by the electro-deposition of calcium silicate.
Great advances have been made in methods of condi¬
tioning the air of museums and galleries to give constant
figures of temperature and relative humidity and to remove
dust and noxious contaminents. At least one war-time
repository was constructed in an underground mine where,
beforehand, the dew-point had been continuously exceeded
and mushrooms were farmed commercially! Control meth¬
ods were put into operation with the result that this mine,
though far below the surface of the ground, became the
perfect store room for the most sensitive materials archi¬
ves, textiles, books and even salt-laden Egyptian stele and
other monuments: no single object suffered damage.
BUT major problems remain. How can one hope
to deal with a monument carved in crumbling
laterite exposed in a monsoon climate to alternatives of
fierce heat and torrential rains? We do not know, but we
can do some calculated guess-work which, in the scientific
field, is often the precursor of the pilot-experiment that leads
to an eventual solution. Not long ago waterlogged wood
was considered to be practically beyond redemption. Now,
the position is much brighter, thanks to a concerted attack
by museum scientists working in several countries, e.g. in
Poland, at the pre-Slav village of Biskopin which is gra¬
dually being recovered from its watery grave, on iron-age
settlements in Switzerland and on the frail but interesting
timbers from mines and from wells in the United Kingdom,
Each country has something to contribute. National mu¬
seums take pride in the quality of their conservation work
and friendly exchange of information in all such matters is
a feature of the present generation.
The conservation of monuments is of world importance,
so much so, that an intergovernmental organization exists
for the study of the preservation and restoration of cultural
property, the so-called "Rome Centre" and this serves all
nations with up-to-date information regarding methods and
equipment and materials and helps with the training of
young curators and museum technicians.
Its activities are known in many countries throughout the
world. It has worked in collaboration with Unesco for
the protection of the Buddhist temples of South Korea
from destruction and staining by water and lichen growths,
etc., and on Pakistan's Mohenjo Daro, being seriously
damaged by salt crystallizations. It has also worked on
Indian cave paintings darkened by shellac, on the painted
tholos of Kasanluk in Bulgaria, whose colours were flaking
off in layers, and on the Mayan site of Bonampak in
Mexico, where wonderful frescoes have miraculously sur¬
vived in the heart of the rain forests. Work has also been
done in Morocco, Tunisia, Libya, Egypt and on many Middle
East sites, and on medieval gold crosses in Vienna. Biblical
scrolls have been studied, dissected and made available
to scholars.
Patiently, continuously, this labour of conservation goes
on, a constructive service to preserve for posterity the
monuments of the past that have served through the ages
as a solace and an inspiration to mankind and will continue
to do so in generations to come.
HAROLD J. PLENDERLEITH is director of the International
Centre for the Study of the Preservation and Restoration of Cultural
Property set up by Unesco in Rome. Before becoming the first
director of the Rome Centre in 1959. he was professor of chemi¬
stry at the Royal Academy of Arts. London, and Keeper of the
Research Laboratory at the British Museum. His best known work
is "The Conservation of Antiquities and Works of Art" (Oxford
University Press. London, Toronto. New York, 1957).
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
This striking photo shows how the massive
walls of the fort of Sant'Andrea in Venice
have split open and begun to collapse into
the sea. The fort at the entrance to the
port of Venice, was built in the 16th
century by the famous architect, Michel
Sammicheli. In all parts of Venice great
monuments are gradually subsiding.
Soprintendenza ai Monumenti
VENICE
a sinking city
by Pietro Gazzola
State Inspector of Antiques and Fine Arts, Rome
^^W ITH its graceful buildings and the incomparable
magic of its light and colours, Venice is a spec¬
tacle that makes us forget the fragile foundations beneath
its architectural splendours. Venice, nevertheless, is a
sinking city.
Built on wooden piles driven into the mud of several
hundred tiny islands separated by a thousand canals that
are now its streets and avenues, Venice first used the sea
as a natural protective rampart against the hordes of bar¬
barians which swept over the mainland in the 5th century
A.D. Gradually it became one of the most beautiful and
unusual cities the world has ever known.
Washed by the clear waters of the Adriatic, Venice evol¬
ved, not in some haphazard fashion, but on the basis of
strict scientific principles. Its builders had precise know¬
ledge of the marine depths around it and were able to
calculate with accuracy the relationship between river
currents and the surge of the tides. The result was a
harmony so perfect that Venice seems to have arisen from
a single, almost miraculous act of creation.
But today this remarkable monument to science and
vision is in danger. Its deepest foundations are being
worn away and the city is slowly sinking, dragged down
by the subsidence of part of the lagoon bed.
Surveys show that Venice has sunk 111 millimetres (four
inches) in the past fifty years. Actually, according to the
Venetian Institute of Arts and Sciences, the subsidence
varies from place to place. Beneath the soaring Campanile,
or bell tower, of St. Mark's in the heart of the city, the.,,
ground has sunk 183 millimetres (seven inches).
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
ST. MARK'S IN THE WATER. The Campanile of St. Mark's has sunk
seven inches in the past 50 years. Above, high tides have flooded the
famous square in front of the Xlth-century cathedral. St. Mark's and
the Doge's Palace in the background seem to be standing directly in the
Venice lagoon. The Campanile can be made out in air view, below.
Archivío Artístico
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
VENICE, A SINKING CITY (Cont'd)
When industrial expansion created a need for swifter,
more direct communications, Venice deepened its existing
canals and made new ones. But the courses of the new
waterways were contrary to Nature's system of currents
and upset the natural balance of the lagoon waters.
The old canals were man-made but they kept logically
to the meandering of the currents; artificially straight, the
new ones were subjected to a greater impact of tidal ebb
and flow. Currents and eddies of unprecedented force
began to strike at the foundations and sub-foundations of
the city until surface subsidence showed that they were
eating into the deepest layers. The most spectacular and
alarming symptom was the partial collapse of the walls of
the fortress of Sant Andrea on the Lido.
The only way to avert these dangers is to restore the
harmony of the system on which Venice Is "anchored"
before it becomes irreparably compromised.
Another danger threatening Venice is erosion. This has
become worse in recent years because of the great fleet of
motor boats which have progressively replaced the gondola,
once the traditional means of transport in a city of 378
bridges where the use of motor-cars is ruled out. The
great surge of water raised by the passage of these power¬
ful motor boats through the canals gnaws away at the
city's foundations.
Erosion is also to blame for worsening decay in the
foundations of buildings attacked by salt water, whose
corrosive power is Increased by the deposits of oil ejected
from motor launches. Since the canals were deepened
they have been more affected by tides, and as tidal move¬
ments carry off sand from one part of the sea bed to
CITIES IN A CITY.
Each square or "campo"
of Venice is a miniature
replica of the piazza
San Marco with its bell
tower, its church, foun¬
tains and open market.
Campanile in photo
above right can just
barely be seen to left
of square. Venice boasts
not only its innumerable
canals and bridges,
large and small, but a
meandering network of
narrow streets and alleys
which no motor vehicle
could possibly enter.
AIR VIEW. Washed by
the waters of the Adri¬
atic, Venice was built on
370 tiny islands in the
lagoon. An automobile
and railway viaduct
(foreground) leads from
the mainland into the
city like an umbilical
cord. At the end of
the viaduct motorists
must leave their cars and
"take to the boats."
Venice's main water¬
way is the S-shaped
Grand Canal which cuts
the city in two. To the
seaward side of Venice
is the Lido beach.
Photos O Archivío Borlui
another, erosion increases. The famous Lido beach, for
example, has been reduced to a narrow ribbon of sand
whereas a few miles away, at Punta Sabbioni, a new beach
is being built up.
The exceptional structure of Venice poses singular prob¬
lems and demands constant watchfulness and super¬
vision by the city authorities. With its magnificent Byzan¬
tine, Gothic and Renaissance buildings and others of a
distinctively Venetian style it presents a unique architec¬
tural ensemble. But these buildings too are subject to
ills, old and new: saline erosion, the droppings of pigeons,
pollution from the air. All these take their toll, eating away
the ornamental facades of palaces and churches and
modest houses alike.
Decay has gradually reduced whole areas to a state of
picturesque semi-ruin, where the inhabitants seem to care
less and less about the state of the buildings and where
many edifices of great architectural beauty now serve as
storehouses or have become slum-dwellings. Yet even
these less important architectural elements still add
something to the character of the city and should be pre¬
served and revived.
Only a comprehensive plan of rehabilitation can save
Venice. In view of the vulnerability of its foundations the
whole. question of transportation will need to be reviewed.
Individual solutions will have to be found for each prob¬
lem, including possible revision of the paths of canals
and the rehabilitation of the poorer districts. This will not
only open the way to further social and economic progress,
but will safeguard the city's great wealth of monuments
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
r
TOOLS OF ART SUR¬
GERY. One of the most
delicate of all restoration
operations is the removal of
the paint used to retouch
a work during past restor¬
ations. When this old paint
is exceptionally hard and
resists the use of solvents,
the restorer has to scrape it
away gently with pencil-
shaped engraver's tools (left).
WARPED WITH AGE. Works executed on wood are often the
most fragile of all paintings. Right, detail of Van Eyck's masterpiece,
"Adoration of the Lamb," painted in 1453. This face was photograph¬
ed under a raking light while the work was being restored in Brussels.
The cracks in the paint have been caused by the warping of its
wooden panel support; the wood itself has split along the graining.
Left, restorer at work on a panel of the "Adoration of the Lamb".
PROBING RAYS. The first step in any restor¬
ation is a thorough examination of the painting
and its support (wooden frame, canvas,
nails etc.), X-rays are used to probe inside the
work and its backing. X-ray below clearly
shows the outline of a cradle used to strengthen
the frame about 70 years ago. From photographs
taken by infra-red, ultra-violet and fluorescent
light the state of each layer of paint is revealed.
Photos © A. C. 1_ Brussels
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
The
care
of
old
paintings
Few of the works of art that have come down to us from the past
are as fragile as paintings. To protect them from the ravages of time
and to preserve or restore their original beauty are problems that
have for long preoccupied the curators of museums. In the past
many masterpieces have suffered from well-meaning but clumsy
attempts at restoration and some of the work done by certain res¬
torers has been attacked as "sacrilegious" or destructive. Until
recently, the care of old paintings was the subject of violent contro¬
versy. Even today certain kinds of damage are still irreparable, but
at least we now know how to avoid causing harm to paintings. It
is now recognized that each painting needs individual study and
treatment and for this purpose there exist elaborately-equipped
laboratories "art hospitals" where with the help of ultra-modern
techniques, restoration attains the highest aesthetic standards. Since
1946 the sum of experience and skill in different countries has
been pooled increasingly through the efforts of the International Council
of Museums. Through this perfection of conservation techniques
the art restorer has become better equipped to deal with the complex
problems of his calling and is able to avoid the errors of the past.
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE CARE OF OLD PAINTINGS (Cont'd)
Five-year cleaning
for 'Last Supper'
Solano's copy of "The Last Supper" leaves
the Abbey of Tongerloo for treatment in the
Brussels "art hospital". Below, cloth-tipped
rod serves restorer as arm rest and also
protects painting from accidental damage.
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
Leonardo da Vinci's most famous mural, "The
Last Supper" (1494) was reproduced on canvas
by one of his pupils, Andreas Solario. This
giant work (see also back cover) went from Italy
to France and then to Belgium where it is
preserved in the Abbey of Tongerloo. It has not
come through its travels unscathed. It suffered
serious damage when it was hidden underground
during the troubled times of the French Revo¬
lution. And blundering attempts to restore it
in the past have not improved its condition.
In 1959 it was decided to hand it over to the
skilled restorers in the Institut Royal de Patri¬
moine Artistique in Brussels. Here a team has
been working over the painting inch by inch
for the past five years. Its restoration is not
yet finished, but already the work has regained
an original vigour and vitality that varnishing
and retouching had obscured and deformed.
Unesco - René Caloz
nsnssRfii'Nt']
r^^^^
S^ v «9
fit ; ' W+. - :J^Ê w_
Br] ' "*
9
UW . -±imM
i
m. fl w y .'M
*w . '^BÉk- A<4Í
Top, patiently and carefully a specialist removes varnish and overpainting
applied by earlier restorers until he reaches original paint. In the process any
traces of damage to the original work are also revealed. In infra-red photo
(centre) old repairs on this detail from "The Last Supper" are clearly visible.
Bottom, the same detail after cleaning. Damaged parts have been brought
to light, and at the same time original values are restored to the faces.
Photos ©ACL, Brussels
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
Aphrodite's city
resuscitated
Aphrodisias is a striking example of an historic city now saved by
government action. For centuries peasants had installed themselves
amid the ruins. Below, fragments of ancient columns used to
prop up village building. Turkish Government has built a whole
new town to remove the inhabitants and restore the ancient site.
THE traveller in modern southwest
Turkey who finds himself fol¬
lowing the fertile, winding course of the
old river, the Meander, now called the
Menderes, may take a rocky, dusty path
which rises among olive groves towards
the foothills of the encircling mountain
ranges where a snowy, jagged peak,
Baba Dag, towers against the calm and
open sky.
If he does so he will come, after some
time, suddenly upon a misty wilderness ¡
of poplar trees and through them he will
see, veiled at first and then startling in
their white and shining splendour, a row
of perfect Ionic colums rising from the
ground. He has arrived at the place
which was once the loveliest and most
famous of all the cities dedicated in
ancient times to Aphrodite, goddess of
beauty; to the city called Aphrodisias
built there in the 3rd century B.C. in
classic Caria, now the province of Aydin.
From its earliest times through the tur¬
bulent passage of Greek, Roman and
Byzantine history this city held a unique
distinction: it was the fountainhead of
art, the workshop of beauty which sup¬
plied an Empire. Generation after gene¬
ration of its carvers and sculptors sent
their work in the inimitable Carian marble
through the seaports of Asia Minor to
the rest of the world.
Alexander the Philosopher was born in
CONT'D ON PAGE 23
Colour page, opposite
Carved stone head peers from undergrowth
covering innumerable fragments of once-proud
buildings of Aphrodisias.
Centre colour pages
Top left: White Ionic columns standing among
young poplar trees are believed to be remains of
porticoes around the agora or public square
of Aphrodisias.
Bottom, left to right: Fallen glories of Aphrodisias,
where graceful Greek columns still rise above
tumbled masonry, form the backdrop to a
cabbage patch or serve to buttress bank of an
irrigation ditch.
Top right: One of many striking reliefs of gods,
goddesses, satyrs and other mythological figures
adorning the temple of Aphrodite.
Bottom right: Villager of Geyre stands amid
relics of halcyon period when Aphrodisias was
famed centre of art and religion.
All photos © Ara Güler. Istanbul
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
kV^
;
*»\
&
^J^' ^k
> >.
jwf*
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[

]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
APHRODITE'S CITY (Cont'd)
Stadium
for 30,000
Colour page, opposite
Top: The magnificent stadium
of Aphrodisias, one of the
most imposing- in the whole
Mediterranean area had places
for 30 000 spectators. Its
immensity can be judged from
comparison with cattle brows¬
ing in its grass-grown arena.
Bottom left: A mutilated but
still majestic marble head by
a sculptor of Aphrodisias. It
was found on the probable site
of a palace.
Bottom right: Housewife's
chores amid fragments of mar¬
ble carvings and columns for
which Aphrodisias was once
famous in the Roman world.
Below : In 1963 the Turkish
Government transferred the
villagers of Geyre from their
homes in the ruins of Aphro¬
disias to a new settlement of
modern houses. Excavation
and the eventual restoration of
the ancient city can now go on
unhampered.
Aphrodisias; medicine, rhetoric and phi¬
losophy flourished there; music and
drama had their festivals, Byzantine
Christianity made the city a Bishopric
with many churches. Somewhere between
the 11th and 14th centuries the city
declined and gradually sank back into
the quiet plain that had borne it, until
in the 17th or 18th century a small village
called Geyre came into being to straggle
uncertainly over its fallen glories.
Over the years the villagers of Geyre
unthinkingly made free with the artisti¬
cally priceless ruins scattered around
them, appropriating them casually into
the pattern of their daily life. Fragments
of fallen Ionic colums were used to prop
up the wooden houses and street posts
of the village; carved sarcophagi served
as wine presses or troughs to catch the
waters of mountain streams; a splendid
relief from the old city decorated a far¬
mer's barn and one of the world's most
perfect examples of Ionic columns which
probably had once been part of a great
temple to Aphrodite offered the spectacle
of their majestic, classic beauty from the
midst of a villager's cabbage patch.
In 1959 the Turkish Government
decided to save Aphrodisias the Beau¬
tiful. By 1963 it had built an entirely
new settlement for the people of Geyre
a mile away from the site of their original
village a modern community with
school, infirmary, barns and storehouses
and fertile pastures for the villagers'
livestock.
No longer hampered by the presence
of the villagers excavation and restora¬
tion work is now going on in Aphrodisias
under the aegis of the Turkish Ministry
of Education and the Direction of Anti¬
quities and Museums and with the help
of a team of archaeologists from the
University of New York.
The most grandiose relic of Aphrodisias
is the magnificent stadium, one of the
most imposing in the whole Medi¬
terranean area, which accomodated
30,000 spectators. Another gem is the
covered auditorium with rows of marble
seats and elaborate stage decoration of
handsome statuary. Elsewhere the dis¬
mantling of a wall revealed within the
foundations a nine-foot image of Aphro¬
dite buried there when the city became
a centre of Christianity.
Aphrodisias was a city of marble. When
it won fame and prosperity as a centre
of art and religion, an extensive building
programme used the nearby supplies of
Carian marble to raise the magnificent
monuments now being brought to light.
So many artistic treasures are being
discovered that it would seem the long
dead artists of Aphrodisias left their
greatest testament, not spread throughout
the world in museums, but in Aphrodisias
itself. Now the brilliance of this art is
being brought to light from the ruins
among the poplars and olive groves of
the tranquil Carian plain birthplace of a
city of grace and beauty.
All photos © Ara Güler. Istanbul
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
MEXICO. The sculp¬
tures and painted walls
(detail in photo) of
Bonampak, a temple in
the jungle, are an
illustrated encyclopae¬
dia of Maya life in
the 7th century A.D.
Bonampak Is being
seriously damaged by
damp. Three mission»
went there (1961-62-64)
to study ways of pro¬
tecting Its treasures.
CZECHOSLOVAKIA. A
wealth of Gothic 14th-
century frescoes is
preserved in Czecho¬
slovakian monasteries
of Strakonice and Sa-
zava, the church of Sla-
vetin, the fortress of
Karlstejn and the
Emails monastery in
Prague. In I960 a
Unesco mission studied
the conservation needs
of these works. Fres¬
coes at Prague were
damaged during the
Second World War;
others, like those at
Karlstejn (detail in pho¬
to) are victims of decay.
Institute for the Preser¬
vation of Monuments.
Prague
NUBIA. The res¬
ults of Unes¬
co's International
Campaign to Sa¬
feguard the Mon¬
uments of Nubia
are familiar to
readers. Each
year, from 1954
to 1964, a Unesco
mission was at
work in Nubia.
In photo a sphinx
from the sacred
avenue of Wadi-
es-Sebua temple
is being moved
to a new site.
PERU. In 1951 aid in restoration of
Cuzco, ancient Inca capital damaged
by 1950 earthquake. In 1964 collabo¬
ration in setting up central art labo¬
ratory at Lima. Studies made of
Peruvian monuments including ruins
of Chan Chan (photo) former capital
of Chimu Empire (1000-1600 A. D.).
SPAIN. To care for its rich heritage
of artistic and cultural treasures, Spain
has recently set up a central Ins¬
titute of Restoration equipped to
apply the latest techniques of the
modern "art clinic". Technical advice
on the creation of the institute and
the training of its staff was given by
a Unesco mission in 1963. The ins¬
titute will give priority conservation
to the Romanesque sculptures of the
monastery of Ripoll (photo) in
northern Spain and to 14th century
murals in the Cathedral of Toledo.
MOROCCO. Rich in ancient cities
dominated by graceful minarets :
Fez, Meknes, Marrakesh each a
monument in itself, whose balance
and character would be destroyed,
as a Unesco mission warned in
1962, if modern multi-storied build¬
ings were added to them. The
mission studied the setting up of
museums and libraries for the
conservation of ancient documents
and recommended special preser¬
vation treatment for mosaics in
Roman city of Volubilis (photo)
where excavations are proceeding.
Office Marocain du Tourisme
SYRIA & LEBANON. In 1953 Unesco sent to
Syria and Lebanon two missions of first-rate im¬
portance for the preservation and restoration of
many monuments. In Syria these sites included
the ruins of Palmyra (photo), an ancient city now
isolated in the desert; cruaders' castles, including
the famous Krak des Chevaliers; the mosques of
Aleppo amd Damascus; the ruins of Doma Eu¬
ropos, a Selucide city (4th century B.C.). Among
those of the Lebanon were many Phoenician,
Roman, Christian, Arab and Ottoman monuments
in city of Tripoli, and ruins of Baalbek, among
the richest remains of the Roman world. In
1960 another Unesco mission was sent to Syria.
'Ô Lucien Hervé. Paris
AFGH AN I STAN.
World's largest sta¬
tue of Buddha, 173
feet high (photo) at
Bamjyan threatened
by collapse of 3,000
tons of rock from
towering cliff above.
In 1963 mission stud¬
ied protective mea¬
sures for this world-
famed shrine and for
important monuments
in Herat, Ghazni, \ az¬
ar and other cities.
ALGERIA. Its monuments are a pageant
of history in stone: the theatre and
baths of the Roman city of Cherchel,
the Islamic monuments on the same
site, the Byzantine fortress of Setif
and the Roman city of Timgad whose
ruins (photo) are crumbling under the
invasion of wild fig trees. In 1963 a
mission examined Timgad and recom-
nended for priority restoration the
famous mosque of Qal's Beni Hammac'.
Unesco - P.A. Pittet
CAMEROUN. A 1964
mission examined palace
qf Sultan Njoya (inven¬
tor of Bamoun alphabet)
at Foumban with view
to restoration (photo
shows palace entrance
with sculptured balcony).
Inventories were made of
works of art sculptured
panels, furniture, masKs
preserved in palace
and houses of chieftains.
Jean Gabus. Neuchatel
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
'T y~ i-i i
M F--* ' "
Âm\ Ik *
EbNb -
'.^JK-I 1
BURMA. Studies for preservation
of murals made in 1961, principally
at Pagan, (photo) former capital,
with its forest of pagodas (once
4,000 existed). Many buildings
beyond repair but murals (covering
250,000 sq. ft. in 250 pagodas , most
of them dating from 11th to 13th
centuries) could still be saved.
0 ACL. Brussels
REPUBLIC OF KOREA. Monuments
needing protection inspected by
mission in 1961 included Buddhist
mountain cave temple of Sokkulam
(photo) on Mt. Toham where infil¬
trating water in damaging statues
and bas reliefs. Preservation mea¬
sures proposed for Sokkulam and
for other monuments including great
standing Buddha at Kwan Chok Sa.
Office of Public Information. Republic
of Korea
JORDAN. Missions in 1956 and
1960 studied preservation pro¬
blems of preclassical and
classical sites and monuments,
crusader and Islamic castles
and towns with medieval build¬
ings such as Bethlehem and
Jerusalem (photo shows walls
of Jerusalem with Moslem
cemetery in foreground).
Jordan's problems of town plann¬
ing and landscape protection
were given special attention.
Unesco - Hans Stekeweh
IRAK. Studies of ancient monu¬
ments, many of clay brick and fra¬
gile stone damaged by water infil¬
tration, made in 1954 and 1961.
Sites examined included Baghdad,
Nineveh, Ctesiphon and Hatra.
Photo shows Arch of Ctesiphon,
near Baghdad, the world's widest
single-span vault of un-reinfor-
ced brickwork (5th century A.D.).
Irak Ministry of Culture IRAN. Three important missions
(1960-62-63) studied one of world's
richest areas for historical monu¬
ments: Persepolis, Pasargadae, the
Ziggurat of Chuga Zambil, palace
and paintings of Ispahan (now being
restored). Among measures recom¬
mended: restoration of upper part
of Ziggurat (terraced tower temple)
and protection against erosion
of Persepolis (photo), an ancient
capital already partly restored.
B. Riazi-Harlaut
INDONESIA. Extensive studies of
important stone monuments made
in 1958. Mission reported to govern¬
ment on protective measures re¬
quired, particularly for giant temple
of Borobudur in lava. One of
world's great Buddhist monuments,
its stone carvings and effigies
(photo) are victims of tropical rains,
extremes of temperature and invad¬
ing vegetation. Borobudur has
1,400 bas reliefs and 500 statues.
Unesco - Marc Riboud
MAP OF
UNESCO
CONSERVATION
MISSIONS
We present on these pages
brief accounts of some of
the missions to safe¬
guard monuments carried
out by Unesco since 1951 at
the request of governments.
PAKISTAN. Three major mis¬
sions (1956, 61, 64) have asses¬
sed problems of Mohenjo Daro
the great capital of the Indus
River Valley civilization of 4,000
years ago. Immense ruins cover¬
ing some 250 acres are being
eroded by invading salt-impreg¬
nated waters from Indus River
and irrigation canals. Methods
of protecting ruins and of pump¬
ing away salty water now
being studied. Pakistan Govern¬
ment requested Unesco mis¬
sion to advise on measures for
saving site. Investigation and
report by the most recent
mission considered by special¬
ists as a model of its kind.
Photo shows a monkey god
statue found at Mohenjo Daro.
0 Paul Almasy. Paris
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
« *' * ' '
STONES
ALSO DIE
by René Sneyers
I N recent years every country has been made
increasingly aware of the grave deterioration
of the world's architectural legacy. There is frequent talk
of the "disease" of stone, a ruthless scourge which for
some time past has been attacking monuments and damag¬
ing them increasingly fast.
Everyone now knows that walls and statues which have
stood the test of time have been seriously damaged during
the last ten years, and among them are reported to be
famous works like the sculptures of Chartres cathedral
masterpieces of Gothic art.
What is this malady, the first appearance of which was
noted in London as long ago as 1620 when it was attributed
to the corrosive action of coal smoke? In 1646, Londoners
even presented a petition to Parliament asking for a ban
on the admission to London of coal from Newcastle, which
was considered particularly harmful.
One of the serious problems of towns and industrial
centres is the pollution of the air by smoke from the com¬
bustion of coal in homes and factories. This smoke con-
26 tains solid particles such as soot, and gaseous substances
such as sulphur dioxide and carbon dioxide. The sulphur
dioxide dissolved in water in fog, rain and snow turns
Into sulphurous acid and then into sulphuric acid, the corro¬
sive power of which is well known to everyone.
It has been estimated that the soot carried in smoke
represents as much as 6% of the weight of fuel consumed.
Soot also contains up to 5% of sulphuric acid, and polluted
air up to 5 mgr. of sulphur dioxide per cubic metre. As
each kilogramme of coal consumed releases about 20 gram¬
mes of sulphur dioxide, the million tons of coal burnt every
year in Greater Brussels, for example, discharges approxi¬
mately 20,000 tons of sulphur dioxide into the atmosphere
enough to transform 31,000 tons of limestone annually
into gypsum, the mineral from which plaster of Paris is
made.
Fortunately only a small part of these Impressively quan¬
tities of corrosive gas comes into contact with the lime¬
stone of our monuments, and most of it is washed away
by rain. In industrial areas, incidentally, rain distributes
from 13 to 27 tons of sulphuric acid on every square
mile each year.
The increasing consumption of heavy oil (diesel and fuel
oil) gradually aggravates the situation, because their yield
in sulphur dioxide is even greater than that of coal. In
the port of Los Angeles the 50,000 tons of petroleum pro¬
ducts consumed each day, a few years ago discharged
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Ift
^r
^
"HJ1
:-".'&£
'. .'
*y-
rr>
»
5S^
fc>
.'
LASCAUX
under treatment
One of the world's most remarkable collections of
prehistoric art. the cave paintings of Lascaux, has
been closed to the public since April 1 963. Following
the discovery of the cave in 1940 thousands of
people have visited Lascaux to marvel at images
of horses, cattle, stags and ibex whose colours
had been preserved exactly as Palaeolithic man
painted them 18.000 years ago. Had more been
known about bio-chemical corrosive action that
can occur in underground sites when Lascaux
became a celebrated tourist attraction, certain
precautions would have been taken. As it was
doors were fitted at the entrance and this innovation
together with the movement of thousands of
people through the cave altered the atmospheric
conditions that had preserved the paintings intact,
causing microscopic plants and bacteria to pro¬
liferate and spread over the walls. Examinations
were made by a committee of scientists and
measures were taken to safeguard the paintings.
Left, one of the Lascaux paintings under examina¬
tion. This strange beast with the heavy body of
a hippopotamus and a feline type of head, has
curious horns which have earned it the name of
". unicorn ". Each wand points to the centre of a
"swarm" of tiny plants. All the growths were
removed before they could damage the colours. The
cave is now "convalescent," but conditions there are
still being studied attentively and Lascaux must for
the time being remain out of bounds to the public.
Photo f Or. J. Bauer. Faculté de Médecine. Marseille
400 tons of sulphur dioxide into the air. Urban centres are
thus producing sulphuric acid on an industrial scale.
On the calcareous stones of buildings in Western Europe,
on surfaces sheltered from the rain generally those facing
north or east as well as in corners where the stone Is not
washed by rainwater, a hard, impermeable incrustation
forms, rich in gypsum, which collects soot and dust. The
formation of this black crust of gypsum is the first stage
of decomposition.
The attack continues beneath the incrustation, and the
second stage of decomposition begins with the infiltration
of mineral salt solutions (gypsum), which by crystallization
of their salts then cause the stone to disintegrate. The
gypsum eventually overcomes the resistance of the lime¬
stone and breaks up the surface layer.
When the stone does not resist smoke it is said to be
"sulphatable". The crust becomes detached from the stone,
forms blisters or cankers, cracks, then scales off, exposing
to the elements a powdery surface which is easily eroded
by rain and wind.
The pollution of the atmosphere of our city and Industrial
centres is thus the general cause of the weathering of
limestone. Even so only part of the limestone used for
building In the polluted areas is affected. The causes are
therefore likely to be more complex, and to the undoubted
action of smoke must be added the action of water in cir¬
culation, the characteristics and quality of the stone and its
position in the building. Some exports put the blame for
disintegration on temperature variations of the crust which
under heat expands much more than the healthy underly¬
ing mass and the repeated strains caused by alternating
expansion and contraction finally split off the crust from the
stone beneath. Other scientists explain the formation of
sulphates by bacterial action. It is observed however that
healthy stones are found to be infested with bacteria, while
damaged stones have none.
The resistance of stones to the formation of sulphates
has been determined in practice by observation of their
behaviour in monuments. No treatment now known is
capable of arresting the formation of sulphates in lime¬
stone. Because stones exposed to rainfull are usually
clean and healthy, while dirt and disintegration are found
in spots which receive no rain, it is generally thought that
the surest way of prolonging the life of monuments is to
clean the stone with water, used in a gentle stream or a
fine spray.
Research is now being carried out on various methods of
treatment proposed by specialists and the industrial sector,
to determine the conditions under which these treatments
are applicable and whether a protective treatment after
cleaning is likely to extend the useful life of the cleaning
operation.
The extent of damage due to sulphate formation has now
rendered a decision urgent. But there is still no absolute
proof of the value of using protective agents on natural
stone. The best policy is to take steps to reduce the
damage caused by soot-laden smoke (dust removal and
washing), and where possible, to transplant factories, and
especially large generating stations, so that they may dis¬
charge their smoke elsewhere than in urban centres.
Strangely enough, sulphate cankers also form on stone
other than limestone, such as porous standstone. In this
case careful investigation always shows a high calcium
sulphate content in the crust, and this is found whenever
limestone is placed above sandstone. This "contamination"
also occurs on soft bricks placed under calcareous rocks;
CONT'D ON PAGE 30
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
Above, stone steps
in the palace temple
of Angkor Wat after
reconstruction. Un¬
dermined by water
infiltrating from the
ornamental lake, they
had caved in (be¬
low). Restored to
regular alignment,
they are now pro¬
tected by reinforced
concrete foundations
and drainage system.
ANGKOR
before & after
' ' ( »' >
- L '' X \ -/ .
.,
,?**X*A.
These gigantic four-
headed towers of Bayon
Temple at Angkor Thorn
have been damaged by li¬
chen. In foreground, heads
before and after cleaning.
TODAY Angkor is rising from its ruins.
Magnificent pyramid-shaped tem¬
ples covered with finely worked
stucco reach towards the sky as they did
when Angkor was capital of the Khmer
Empire. To the world, the name Angkor,
in Cambodia, personifies the harmonious
art of the Khmer people which flowered
gloriously between the 9th and the 13th
centuries A.D. For five centuries, while
Angkor was abandoned, its temples fell
into ruin attacked by erosion, broken up
by infiltrating tropical rains, strangled by
invading vegetation. Today, reconstruc¬
tion is only one of the tasks of restora¬
tion. The stones must be protected from
constant attack by physical, chemical and
I*"-'"""'
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
Photo« E.F.E.O. - Angkot Contervstlon
Bases of these pillars in a gallery at
Angkor Wat have been attacked by an
invisible enemy bacteria which have
caused damage throughout the temple.
biological ills. Experts from the Museum
of Natural History in Paris, working with
art specialists from the French Far East
School and the Cambodian authorities,
have drawn up a "catalogue" of these ills.
Sandstone that appears healthy comes
away in layers exposing badly-decayed
stone. In one place stone is friable and
crumbles into dust. In another, bacteria,
fed on the droppings of bats, eat away
reliefs. In the temple of Bataneyi Srei
dark patches disfigure the rose-coloured
sandstone. What look like the traces of
a great fire are actually incrustations of
manganese oxide. But happily science
is now able to deal with ravages that
only yesterday were quite irreparable.
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
STONES ALSO DIE (Cont'd)
The destructive salt of the earth
such bricks too show signs of corrosion cankers. Often
the calcium sulphate originates in the lime mortar or cement
used in bricklaying.
Stones are frequently contaminated by salts other than
calcium sulphate. These soluble salts from the soil alka¬
line and alkaline earth nitrates, sulphates and chlorides
are crystallized at the surface of the stone and the develop¬
ing crystals create enough force to destroy the stone's
cohesion and disintegrate it.
Unesco recently published a report on the preservation
of the important historic site of Mohenjo Daro, in Pakistan.
The ruins of this great city in the Indus valley, 4,000 years
old, were excavated between 1921 and 1930. Since the
beginning of the excavation the water level on the site has
risen by five metres as the result of the construction of
irrigation canals. This water with a high saline content has
impregnated the bricks the basic material of the ruins
which have become saturated with mineral salts. The
crystallization of these salts on the surface of the building
materials causes the latter to disintegrate so rapidly that
it is certain that in a few decades the ruins will have lost
all their meaning.
Systematic studies were made at Mohenjo Daro by three
experts: Dr. H. Plenderleith, Director of the International
Centre for the Study of the Preservation and Restoration
of Cultural Property, in Rome, and two specialists from the
Netherlands, Mr. T. de Beaufort, an engineer specializing
In hydrology, and Dr. C. Voûte, a geologist specializing in
soil science. Their work is a model of the type of study
that can help to find satisfactory solutions to problems as
complex as the treatment of great archaeological sites.
Starting with the archaeological and human aspect the
experts dealt with the physical state of the city "in situ";
they analysed the building materials and identified the
harmful substances and structures and the rate of deterio¬
ration, and studied the movement of water and mineral
salts in the bricks and the effect of the salts on the bricks.
Analysis of the complex causes of deterioration, based
upon a mass of topographical, geological, meteorological
and hydrological data, made it possible to suggest possible
methods of treatment. The actual method will not be
decided upon until tests have been made for reducing the
underground water level and for extracting the saline
content by water sprinkling.
, ENERALLY speaking the movement of water in
' stones has a decisive influence upon their
survival, since it causes their weathering by sulphate forma¬
tion or saline inflorescence. Water, acts both as a solvent
and as a vehicle for the dissolved substances in the joints
and in the stones themselves.
For example, the softening of the shapes of Assyrian
sculptures in gypsum alabaster is due to the transformation
of limestones into water-soluble calcium bicarbonate.
Laterization is a typical alteration of inter-tropical regions;
the word is derived from "latérite," meaning "brick,"
designating the reddish soil of the damp tropical zone,
which in certain regions forms a sterile crust. Laterization
occurs in regions with heavy rainfall and a high mean
temperature. In time, most of the substances forming the
2Q stone disappear as solutions, leaving iron, silica and alu¬
mina and forming new iron and aluminium oxides.
Freezing in a humid environment is the chief factor in the
destruction of stone in cold countries and mountainous
areas. Everyone knows that a bottle full of water exposed
to frost will break because as the water freezes it expands
by 9%. Similarly, under certain conditions the water con¬
tained in the pores of building material can cause it to
split (by breaking or flaking). Hence the French expression,
"Il gèle à pierre fendre" (literally "It is freezing enough to
break stone") to describe a heavy frost.
It has been established that the pressure exerted by the
rapid freezing of water at -5° C is about 500 kilogrammes
per square centimetre. This pressure can break many types
of stone, because in this case the ice has not time to
extend into the empty pores or to the exterior. That is why
breaking due to frost is more often found in stone of aver¬
age porosity than in highly porous stone and in stone
saturated with water, that is, stone at the level of wet soil.
There may be considerable variations in temperature
between day and night, between sunny and shaded surfaces
and in material exposed to the sun and then cooled by rain¬
fall. As rock is a very bad heat conductor, tensions
capable of disrupting it may arise between the heart and
the skin of the building material. In marble, this pheno¬
menon sometimes produces curious deformations.
BUILDING materials can also be destroyed by
the transformation of some of the substances
in their composition. Thus marble and brick can be disinte¬
grated by changes in the iron pyrites they contain. On
coming into contact with moisture in the air, these pyrites
form ferrous sulphate and sulphuric acid, which decompose
the materials.
In humid tropical regions biological proliferation can
cause serious damage both through bacterial action and
through the solvent effect of acids produced by the lower
forms of vegetable life such as mosses and lichens.
The higher forms of vegetable life also destroy stone,
but their main action is mechanical, the swelling of roots
and trunks leading to the break up of buildings.
Animal excreta, particularly of birds and bats, often cause
considerable damage to monuments through the acids they
contain which have exactly the same effect as the sul-
phating produced by atmospheric pollution.
Dust-bearing winds blowing in arid zones cause serious
damage with very marked eroding characteristics. Protec¬
tion is provided by screens of vegetation or fences of plas¬
tic-covered metal similar to those used on airfields or to
the screen that protects the port of Marseilles against the
violent Mistral wind.
Thus weathering is caused by the combined action of the
elements (water, temperature, air) often associated with the
action of live organisms. Its extent depends not only on
the vulnerability of the mineralogical constituents of the
rock sandstone is more resistant to an industrial atmo¬
sphere than limestone but also on the actual structure of
the rock a coarse-grained rock weathers more quickly
than a fine-grained one. Where elements built up in layers,
such as mica, are present in the rock, water is able to
penetrate and liability to weathering increases.
Although the preservation of stonework has been studied
for more than a century the results of many experiments
have been so discouraging that it would be true to say no
progress has been made over the past hundred years. The
CONT'D ON PAGE 32
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
In Abomey (Daho¬
mey) an ancient
West African cultu¬
ral centre, the re¬
mains of the oldest
royal palaces are
now in the last
stages of ruin. Their
walls of dried mud
bricks (right) have
gradually crumbled
away under the
effects of erosion.
Two palaces those
of King Guézo and
King Glélé (19th
century) have been
preserved. Built in
simple architectural
style, theyareembel- Sr
lished with many j»
bas-reliefs of col- ?¡¿
oured terracotta.
Below, two mural
decorations : a cha¬
meleon and a lion.
Below right, restau¬
ration work at King
Guézo's palace.
Today the palace
buildings house
Abomey's museum.
«'. Pierre Verger, Paris
ROYAL MONUMENTS FROM AFRICA'S PAST
Photos Jean Gabus, Neuchâtel
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Photos © A.C.L Brussels Left, ravaged features of a 16th-century painted stone statue of the Virgin from
St. John's Hospital, Bruges, Belgium. Cracks and wrinkles have been caused by
each new coat of paint flaking off and also by progressive sulphating of stone.
Right, statue after it had undergone cleaning and restoration with paraffin wax.
STONES ALSO DIE (Cont'd)
only treatment which can be unreservedly recommended
for limestone affected by sulphating is to wash surfaces
that rain cannot reach with water.
As a general rule the best solution is to prevent or reduce
the causes of weathering. Since water is often at the root
of the trouble, efforts should be made to reduce its infil¬
tration by keeping roofs in good repair, by providing drain¬
age for the ground in proximity to the building, and apply¬
ing the appropriate traditional techniques for rendering
buildings waterproof or drying them out.
When restoration is being carried out, it is important,
despite a fashion which is becoming widespread, to bear
in mind the advantages of preserving the external and
internal coating on monuments, which have a considerable
protective effect. Moreover, these coatings, which are often
part of the original structures, should be respected merely
for historical reasons.
Increasingly rapid weathering and more frequent restora¬
tion of historical monuments are occurring at a time of
remarkable scientific and technical progress and Increas¬
ing public Interest in cultural property. People have come
to regard monuments and works of art as public property,
as something that concerns the man in the street no less
than the specialist. Hence it can be expected that the
32 authorities will plan to devote to preservation at least a
proportion of the funds they spend regularly on the res¬
toration of historical monuments.
Moreover in many parts of the world more and more
laboratories are being established for the preservation of
monuments. These institutions, collaborating with building
material specialists, will no doubt discover the proper
solutions for the grave problems which now confront us.
Unesco's Monuments Committee, the International
Council of Museums (ICOM) and the International Centre
for the Study of the Preservation and Restoration of Cultural
Property, in Rome, have recently taken the initiative in com¬
missioning the Laboratories Committee of ICOM and
in particular the Institut Royal du Patrimoine Artistique in
Brussels to carry out a large scale international investi¬
gation into the weathering and preservation of stonework.
The first contacts have produced a study on the loca¬
lization and action of salts in limestone and sandstone used
for building purposes, which will be published this year.
A working group made up of specialists in the preservation
of stone materials has also been set up. In this way it
is hoped to sum up the present state of knowledge in the
particularly delicate sphere of preservation of the mate¬
rials from which historical monuments are constructed and
to slow down the inexorable process of deterioration of
these monuments.
RENE SNEYERS, Head of Laboratory at the Institut Royal du
Patrimoine Artistique In Brussels, is a specialist in the conservation
of stonework in ancient monuments.
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
The menace
of the
bulldozers
by John O. Brew
President, International Committee
on Monuments
In the past 18 months Unesco has
carried out a broad inquiry into the
advisability of drawing up interna¬
tional regulations for the preservation
of cultural property endangered by
public and private works. The results
of this study based on replies from
some 40 member states were discussed
by the Unesco General Conference
which met in Paris last November,
and which felt that an international
instrument on this subject was needed.
It authorized Unesco's Director-Gene¬
ral to prepare a Draft Recommendation
to be submitted to the next General
Conference. The following article is
based on the preliminary Unesco study
prepared by Prof. J.O. Brew, Presi¬
dent of the International Committee
on Monuments and Director of the
Peabody Museum, Harvard University.
FOR centuries and even millennia, constructions
undertaken by man have destroyed vestiges of
his past. On the other hand, from that time In the remote
past when man evolved into a sentient being, some part of
his thoughts has ever been devoted to speculations about
his origin. The myths and folklore of our few remaining
primitive contemporaries bear witness to this pervading
tendency to speculate and seek evidence about the past.
All religions of which we have any evidence and all of our
various cultures are concerned with the history of how
they came into being, as well as with the present and the
future.
Formal attention to material remains as part of man's
search for knowledge of his past seems to have begun
with excavation in Italy and Greece of objects to provide
inspiration for the architects and sculptors of the Renais¬
sance. Later, in northern Europe, excavation produced
background for the romantic movement In literature and
art. In the New World, the first archaeological excavation
was an American Indian site dug by Thomas Jefferson in
Virginia in the latter part of the eighteenth century.
As the various peoples and civilizations of the world devel¬
oped and cities were built, as an increasing proportion of
the countryside was cleared for cultivation, destruction of
earlier sites or buildings was inevitable. Sporadic efforts
to counteract the results of such depredations appeared
during the closing decades of the nineteenth century. Tho
first archaeological salvage project in Poland was carried
out in 1883.
It was also during the mid-nineteenth century that Inte¬
rest developed In the preservation and restoration of monu¬
ments which had been erected earlier in history, at times
by peoples possessing cultural or religious traditions which
differed from the present populations. The famous Serpent
Mound in Ohio was saved from a housing development In
1887, excavated, and presented to the State of Ohio as a
State park by the Peabody Museum of Harvard University.
Perhaps the first attempts to modify or control modern
construction dated from this period, when groups of
buildings or even entire communities were protected in
order to preserve their character and historical aspect.
H OWEVER, it is the great technological develop-
'ment and expansion of population in the second
and third quarters of the twentieth century which produced
the crises with which we are now faced. National and local
governments have passed legislation which enables them,
or interested private bodies, to establish parks, and to
protect, preserve or restore national monuments and histo¬
ric and scenic areas for the enjoyment, recreation or educa¬
tion of the people.
Internationally, Unesco has not only sponsored instruments
dealing with some aspects of the problem of the safeguard¬
ing of sites and monuments, but has also aided many of
its member states, through the Programme of Participation
in the Activities of Member States, in the preservation of
their cultural heritage. The International Compaign to Safe¬
guard the Monuments of Nubia is an outstanding example.
There is no doubt, however, that extensive construction
projects will occur universally and will touch all countries,
great and small, in the next few years. No one with the
prosperity and well-being of mankind in mind could possibly
object to advantageous technological developments. The
benefits will be extraordinarily large to contemporary popu¬
lations. However, in attaining these indisputable gains, we
must also give full consideration to the other, more intan¬
gible, but none the less important, historical and cultural
values which play so great a part in the lives of all of us.
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
MENACE OF THE BULLDOZERS (Cont'd)
The big culprits: motorways,
airports, dams and pipelines
Among the modern technological developments threat¬
ening our cultural properties, the best known are the cons¬
truction of dams for irrigation, hydro-electric power and
flood control. Eventually, this movement will spread to
almost all countries. These dams create pool areas of
various sizes, from small to extensive bodies of water.
Hundreds of them have already been built and are planned
in many countries.
These operations are particularly destructive of cultural
values in arid, semi-arid or prairie regions. In the great
Missouri drainage in the U.S.A., it Is estimated that 80% of
the prehistoric population lived directly on the banks of the
main stream or of its major tributaries. Dam construction
during the last fifteen years has submerged all of the
known sites of five major prehistoric cultures. The new
High Dam near Aswan will produce a pool extending from
the first to the third cataract on the Nile over 500 kilo¬
metres. (See our last issue.)
In dam construction projects, there are a number of
additional threats to cultural properties and sites apart from
those which may be included in the pool area. The cons¬
truction of a dam, particularly of a major dam, presupposes
a considerable network of access roads which almost
always damage archaeological sites or affect the ambiance
of existing monuments.
Then there is always the camp to house the construction
workers, which, in the case of a large dam, can achieve the
proportions of a good sized city. In addition, many dams,
even large ones, are earthen dams, which means that great
quantities of materials must be excavated and brought to
the dam site. Very often and, in fact, almost inevitably,
archaeological sites occur in the borrow areas from which
the earthen materials are extracted. All of these site and
material areas must be surveyed, and important sites exca¬
vated, before the work begins.
s!ëis
&$3i
34
NOTHER major threat to our cultural heritage
Ns highway construction. This might, in the long
run, be even more devastating than the river basin projects.
Many people still do not comprehend the damage to the
countryside occasioned by modern motorway construction.
The great transcontinental super highways programmes in
the U.S.A. and in Europe constitute, because of the width
of the right of way and the methods of construction, one of
the most active threats there is to our historical and
archaeological record. Many people consider that these
projects are more destructive than the construction of dams.
In highway construction, as in the dam projects, con¬
sideration must be given to areas quite outside the actual
right of way. The extensive quarries and borrow pits from
which gravels and other road metals are obtained also
constitute a major threat to archaeological sites. In many
areas of the world where such monuments as prehistoric
mounds, barrows and tels are found, these structures are
considered by highway engineers to be the cheapest and
easiest sources for material for fills and other construction
needs.
Another important aspect of modern technology in which
provision must be made for the conservation of cultural
values Is the construction of pipelines for oil and natural
\ %*
'"'VI'
The Great Serpent Mound in
Adams County, Ohio, U.S.A., is
one of the most famous of the
earth monuments raised by the
prehistoric ancestors of the Red
Indians in North America, where
many mounds representing birds,
bears and other animals exist.
The Great Serpent Mound (1,350
feet long) is the largest in the
form of a snake. In 1887 it was
saved from destruction as a pro¬
posed site for a housing deve¬
lopment. The ground was pur¬
chased by the Peabody Museum
of Harvard University, excavated
and presented to the State of Ohio.
Development Department. Ohio
(j
gas. Such projects, because of the accidental fact that
the sources of oil and gas are usually in regions of the
world which contain important prehistoric sites or monu¬
ments, almost always cut through and destroy significant
cultural remains.
The construction of power transmission lines, of both
underground and pylon types, is another source of damage
to sites. In Sweden, where these are always built by the
State, provision for archaeological salvage is made; In
countries where such construction is done by private com¬
panies, it is more difficult to control. In the U.S.A., effec¬
tive co-operation has been worked out between power com¬
panies and State and local museums in Arizona and New
Mexico.
Farming operations have always been a major threat to
archaeological sites and historic monuments. Clearing of
land and ordinary cultivation has probably done more
damage to such sites in the past than any other single
agency of our technology. Modern farming techniques,
however, have increased this danger greatly.
Cities are expanding at an extraordinary rate all over the
world. With this expansion comes, inevitably, the destruc¬
tion of thousands of archaeological and historical sites, as
well as many buildings which in themselves may not be
worth conserving as national monuments, but which, as a
whole, constitute a witness to a previous stage of develop¬
ment.
Along with the expansion of the areas of cities, there has
also come into being In recent years extensive projects for
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
^W*
the redevelopment of the centre of the city well. In
many European countries this was precipitated by destruc¬
tion through bombing during the Second World War. Most
important cities are built upon sites where people have had
their cultural centres for many centuries and, in fact,
millennia.
In the present decade, similar situations have developed
in cities which did not suffer from war damage. Not only
are urban areas expanding rapidly into the surrounding
countryside, but also the older, obsolete buildings in the
centres of cities are being taken down and large areas have
become subject to "redevelopment". In many instances,
the threat of such development has required that some of
the old buildings be scheduled as monuments and preser¬
ved. It is certain that this process will continue and provi¬
sion must also be made for salvage of the underlying
archaeological remains before new construction takes place.
Examples can be cited of work already done by many
Unesco Member States. In Norway, more than twenty
excavations have been made in urban areas which have
produced over 150,000 early implements and the remains
of thirty medieval ships. The problem of urban develop¬
ment in Sweden is perhaps the most extreme of all the
states. Thirty years ago, 85% of the population lived in
agricultural communities. Now only 15% reside on farms.
Provision is made for open areas and historical and
archaeological monuments in the urban developments, but
again this protection applies only to the most outstanding
sites. Protection must still be sought for many important
sites and buildings which will be destroyed in this urban
expansion and which are not of the first magnitude, entitling
them to national monument status.
A similar situation exists in India. Monuments and pro¬
tected areas preserve the outstanding sites, but in the
major urban developments, such as New Delhi and Bombay,
hundreds of significant sites or monuments cannot receive
this protection.
Another important threat to cultural properties is the
extensive modern construction development which includes
new factories, research establishments, airfields and mili¬
tary installations. Some can be considered under the
heading of urban development discussed above. Many,
however, cannot since they are deliberately placed out in
the countryside because they need more land than is readily
available in an urban setting.
It is still not generally realized how much land has been
taken over recently for such enterprises. Particularly since
the advent of jet planes, an appreciable amount of the sur¬
face of the earth is now devoted to airfields and the pre¬
paration of such fields involves the same type of bulldozer
levelling as is used to prepare fields for irrigated agricul¬
ture, with the concomitant destruction of the archaeological
sites or removal or destruction of historic buildings.
Manufacturing plants have also moved out into the
countryside and occupy increasingly large tracts of land,
which also has to be levelled and cleared of all previous 35
CONT'D ON NEXT PAGE
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
MENACE OF THE BULLDOZERS (Cont'd)
The archaeologist alongside the engineer
36
encumbrances, including archaeological sites or ancient
buildings. In this category must also be placed military
and semi-military installations, research laboratories, atomic
energy plants, missile and space exploration establish¬
ments.
One of the older industrial operations which has been a
constant threat to archaeological sites is quarrying. Gravel
pits in particular have been destructive of palaeolithic sites
throughout Western Europe and especially in France, Ger¬
many and the United Kingdom. One of the more important
Early Man sites in North Africa was destroyed by gravel pit
operations in Casablanca In the early 1950's. Improved
modern techniques In this field and also in open pit and
strip mining have greatly Increased the potential damage.
So far we have only mentioned the more important of the
modern technological developments which are, with increas¬
ing rapidity, destroying our cultural heritage. There are
many others; new railroads, sewers, cable lines, canals,
levees, etc. Fifty and even only twenty-five years ago, this
was a matter of concern to only a few countries. Now,
however, it Is of world-wide importance. There is not a
single state whose national heritage is not endangered In
one way or another by these forces.
few countries have the type of strong central
control which might make It possible to bring
all of the various possible threats to cultural property by
new construction under a single regulation. These, how¬
ever, seem to be the exception rather than the rule. Major
governmental projects such as the construction of dams,
new land being opened for agriculture (e.g. the polders in
the old Zuyder Zee in the Netherlands or the Navaho
irrigation project in New Mexico (United States of America)
can be surveyed relatively easily, and monuments then
designated, objects preserved and archaeological excava¬
tions carried out.
In several countries, national services and organizations
have stimulated the interest of private firms and individuals.
In the western part of the U.S.A. and in the Arabian penin¬
sula, the private pipeline companies have, for the most
part, been very co-operative and have hired archaeologists
to excavate in advance of their construction crews; they
have even financed the production and publication of the
scientific archaeological reports. This has not always been
the case, however, and should be provided for by law.
The Archaeological Service in the Netherlands has over
200 correspondents throughout the country who help to
keep track of new finds. The service also has close liaison
In this matter with the Ministry of Agriculture.
In Norway, where an extensive inventory of prehistoric
sites exists, the Archaeological Service works closely with
the farm organizations. The question of budgeting is most
important here, as the farmer cannot be compelled to bear
the expenses of excavation.
In Sweden, the farmer is theoretically liable for the cost
of excavation, but in the case of extensive mound sites,
either the government or scientific foundations actually bear
the expense.
In Czechoslovakia, there are nine scientific organizations
which can excavate sites on farmland if these are brought
to their attention. In the U.S.S.R., the situation is some¬
what easier because there is no private farming and the
costs of excavation must be borne by the institution which
is working the site. In France, a classified site must be
preserved, with a protective perimeter around it, but no
satisfactory method has yet been devised to protect the
myriad sites which are not classified.
In Denmark, the advent of deep ploughing has caused
great difficulty in preserving sites. Although classified sites
have a protective perimeter, the farmer has a tendency to
plough closer and closer to the monument each year, and
controls must be instituted.
The problems involved in the safeguarding of monuments
and sites have become increasingly complex and urgent
owing to the scope and very rapid expansion of public and
private works of considerable magnitude contributing to the
welfare and economy of present-day peoples. It is impos¬
sible to provide an absolute safeguard for monuments and
sites, even if they are frequently the sole and, perhaps,
most important witnesses to the achievements of past
cultures.
On the other hand, various degrees of protection can be
considered, beginning with modifications to be made In the
plans of contemplated large-scale works in favour of im¬
portant monuments and sites; and with transfers of selec¬
ted monuments to areas outside of the zone directly affec¬
ted by construction. For those monuments which do not
possess sufficient importance or whose fabric does not per¬
mit transfer, careful records will have to suffice. Similarly,
a selected sample of an archaeological site can be excava¬
ted to provide scientific documentation of the past.
It Is necessary for the knowledge of our cultural history,
as well as for social and economic reasons, that such
measures be taken to safeguard monuments and sites en¬
dangered by public and private construction. This has
been recognized by many states which have taken steps
to ensure either the protection of sites and monuments or
their salvage.
Previous Unesco Courier articles
on the preservation of monuments
We publish here a short list of articles on the care and
restoration of monuments published in past issues of
"The Unesco Courier."
Italy's War-Damaged Art Treasures
Lose Their Scars	 November, 1949
Folk Arts in the Path of Civilization .. December, 1949
New Life for Ancient Paintings (spe¬
cial number) February, 1952
Restoring Quake-Hit Cuzco 	 February, 1953
SOS From the Past: Saving Our Heri¬
tage in Stone (special number) .. July, 1954
Rome's "Book Hospital": Saving An¬
cient Manuscripts	 February, 1957
Spina: Mystery City of the Etruscans. February, 1958
Guatemala's Picture Hospital 	 March, 1958
Cuzco Celebration: Old Inca Capital
Restores its Monuments 	 June, 1958
Save the Treasures of Nubia (special
52-page issue)	 February, 1958
Rebirth of a Shattered City: The Story
of Warsaw March, 1961
Abu Simbel, Now or Never (special
issue) October, 1961
Nemrud Dagh: Excavation of a Moun¬
tain Sanctuary	 February, 1962
Victory in Nubia (special issue) 	 December, 1964
]]>
</page>
<page number="37">
<![CDATA[
To the young people of the world
a message
from René Maheu
Director-General of Unesco
for the New Year 7965
HE New Year opens. The institutions of the United Nations have decided
to dedicate it to the cause of international co-operation, which they intend
not only to celebrate with words, but also to demonstrate with deeds. May this then
be the theme of my message, which carries with it my very best wishes to you,
my young friends throughout the world.
International co-operation is both a necessity and an ideal.
It is a necessity for modern civilization, because the opportunities for development
which this civilization offers can only be exploited, the problems of development
which it presents can only be resolved, by organizing the communication of know¬
ledge, the confrontation of ideas, the pooling of resources and the conjunction of
efforts within increasingly extensive and complex systems which transcend the
boundaries of nations, however vast and powerful these may be.
It is also an ideal and by that I do not mean a dream, but a moral impera¬
tive for men are coming to realize more and more that they are morally as well
as physically interdependent. Each of us is increasingly aware that he cannot be
completely happy if others are destitute or live under bondage, that he cannot be
really at peace with himself if others are waging war against one another in short,
that he cannot attain his full stature as a man if injustice and want are preventing
other men all of them from attaining that stature, like him and with him. I say
all of them, for, once we admit in our thoughts or in our deeds, that some shall be
excluded from humanity's family, we lose a part of our own individual humanity.
Such is the twofold justification for this international co-operation, which institu¬
tions like Unesco are designed to serve, and I call upon you to dedicate yourselves
to it from now onwards, with all the enthusiasm and generosity of your young years.
For, although international co-operation needs sound organization and technique
if it is to be effective, it cannot be achieved by those means alone. Even more,
it needs a certain openness of mind, a certain warmth of heart, in short a readiness
to serve, which itself implies a conversion to human brotherhood.
It is to this great cause that I call upon you to dedicate yourselves.
Please do not misunderstand me. I do not ask you to abandon those tasks which
you are to undertake within the context of your family, your career, your country.
I only ask you to remember, when carrying out these tasks, that you also belong
to a larger family, a broader life and a vaster community, which is mankind. I
ask you to realize that the meaning and value of your existence go beyond the
immediate confines of your own personal destiny and that you are taking part in
the same splendid adventure as the rest of mankind, an adventure which calls for
understanding and effort from all. Lastly I ask you to regard every man you meet
as a brother, that is, as your equal in dignity, with the same needs and the same
hopes, regardless of his race, country, language, social status or beliefs.
You are growing up in a period of technological miracles. Your generation will
reach the stars, but it is Man that I should like you, above all, to reach, to respect
and cherish, in yourselves and in others.
May 1965 allow you to progress towards this goal through co-operation and
concord, justice and peace!
Good luck to you, my friends! Be of good cheer and a Happy New Year to you!
]]>
</page>
<page number="38">
<![CDATA[
From the Unesco New
TO FIGHT ILLITERACY: The Shah of Iran
has proposed to Unesco the organiza¬
tion of an International congress to explore
the best ways of fighting illiteracy. In a
message to Unesco's General Conference,
the Shah congratulated Unesco on its
efforts for world literacy and declared "it
is the duty of every country and every
chief of 6tate to encourage and support
these activities."
SEABORNE COSMIC RAY RESEARCH:
Swedish freighters whose voyages
take them to South African, Australian
and Suez ports have been helping to
collect important data on the Influence
of terrestial magnetism on cosmic radiation.
Fitted with neutron monitors they have
been collecting information for the past
eight years to assist a programme of cos¬
mic radiation research set up by the U.S.
Bartol Research Foundation and the Cos¬
mic Ray Group of the Uppsala Physlcial
Institute, Sweden.
GUIDEBOOKS FOR EDUCATORS: Two
important publications designed as
basic aids for educational planning have
been published by the International Institute
for Educational Planning in Paris, which
was set up by Unesco In 1963. "Educa¬
tional Planning: a Bibliography", covering
several hundred documents, and "Educa¬
tional Planning: a Directory of Training and
Research Institutions" (covering 85 insti¬
tutions in 30 countries) have appeared in
English, and French versions will shortly
appear. Both publications can be obtained
from HEP Publications, 7, rue Eugène-
Delacroix, Parls-160.
OPEN-AIR POWER STATION: One of
the largest open-air power stations
in the Soviet Union Is now being built in
Tashkent, Uzbekistan. The warm, dry Cen¬
tral Asian climate has allowed the de¬
signers to dispense with a large building
to house the generating equipment, thus
effecting considerable economy in time and
money. The station, fueled by natural gas,
will have a capacity of 1,200,000 kws.
THE ANGLER'S FRIEND: In many Euro-
' pean countries otters have long been
considered as the angler's enemies and
have been hunted down to the point of
extermination. But as the otters disap¬
peared so did the fish. Scientists have
now found that the otters had been taking
mostly sick fish; when there were no otters
to do this, disease spread rapidly among
the fish population and numbers went
down. Forewarned by the experience of
other countries, Switzerland has now
removed the otter from the list of so-
called harmful animals and has given it
federal protection.
INVESTMENT IN EDUCATION: Two
' missions have been sent by Unesco in
co-operation with the World Bank to El
Salvador and the Dominican Republic to
study educational investment projects.
These missions mark the start of direct
co-operation between Unesco and the
World Bank in helping countries to finance
the costs of their educational development
programmes. The missions will give priori¬
ties to actual or potential projects that
are important for economic development
In the two Latin American countries.
CENSORSHIP OF ARTS & IDEAS: Two
new periodicals on censorship have
just begun publication under the auspices
of the Congress of Cultural Freedom. The
first, published in Great Britain and priced
2/6, is entitled "Censorship" (1-2 Langham
Place, London, W. 1). The second, publish¬
ed in France, is entitled "Censure contre
les arts et la pensée" and costs 2 F. 50
(104, Bd. Haussmann, Paris 8e).
HONOURING GALILEO: An exhibition
honouring Galileo and recalling the
major events of his scientific career was
held at Unesco's Paris H.Q. during the
Unesco General Conference. Organized
in collaboration with Unesco by the Italian
National Committiee for the celebration of
the 400th anniversary of Galileo's birth, it
included among its exhibits reproductions
38
INTERNATIONAL CONTROL OF NARCOTIC DRUGS
International efforts and achievements
in the control of narcotics are honoured
by a commemorative stamp (right)
issued by the U.N. Postal Adminis¬
tration. Since 1946, when it took
over responsibility for international
narcotics control, the United Nations
has worked to close gaps in existing
regulations and to prevent narcotics
needed for scientific and medical
purposes from seeping into illicit
traffic. It has also helped to improve
enforcement of narcotics controls, to
rehabilitate drug addicts and to develop
new crops to replace the growing of
narcotic-bearing plants. In 1961
provisions of existing treaties were
combined in a single U.N. convention
which also simplified international con-
».-»í.»T,3Ríí
UNITED NATIONS
trol machinery. As agent in France of
the U.N. Postal Administration, Unesco's
Philatelic Service stocks all U.N. stamps
and first day covers currently on sale.
For further details write to: Unesco
Philatelic Service, Place de Fontenoy,
Paris-7 V
of contemporary documents and replicas
of instruments spyglasses, a compass,
telescopes and an astrolabe whose origi¬
nals are in the Museum of the History of
Science at Florence.
AMERICAN READING HABITS: Is the
American reader solely a product of
"pop culture" (television, newspapers, and
"bestseller" list pressures) or does he
represent a real step forward toward uni¬
versal literacy and creative thinking? This
is one of the questions discussed in "The
American Reading Public", a new book
published by R. R. Bowker Co.. 1180 Ave.
of the Americas, New York (price, $7.95).
The book takes a fresh look at reading
methods taught in school, the quality of
textbooks, ihe role of the modern public
library and publishing and bookselling.
UNESCO SHAKESPEARE TRIBUTES:
Special programmes to mark the 4th
centenary of the birth of William Shakes¬
peare were presented in Unesco's H.Q.
in Paris during the Unesco General Confe¬
rence. A distinguished group of authors,
poets, critics, theatrical and film producers
and directors collaborated in programmes
relating Shakespeare to contemporary
literature, the cinema and the modern
theatre, including the presentation of scenes
from the Bard's works. Round table
discussions were held on different inter¬
pretations of Shakespeare's works and the
problems of presenting them in terms of
modern stage, screen and television pro¬
duction techniques.
ALL ABOUT THE U.N.: "Everyman's Uni¬
ted Nations" presents the complete
story of the U.N. family in a form that ans¬
wers the needs of both specialist and
casual reader. The latest edition (7th
Sales No. 64.1.9) constitutes a basic history
of the U.N. from 1945 to 1963, describing
its structure and purposes, the work it does
and the intergovernmental agencies related
to it. Published by the U.N. Office of
Information, it is available from U.N. sales
agents: Cloth edition, $5.00; paperback
edition, $1.95. (598 pages).
Flashes...
Two new countries Malawi and Zambia
Joined Unesco during the recent Unesco
General Conference, bringing the total
membership io 117 states.
Puerto Rico spends more of its nationa
income on education (6.9%) than any other
country reports Unesco's Statistical Year¬
book. Next to Puerto Rico come Finland
(6.6%) and Japan and Czechoslovakia
f6.5% each).
Two thousand schools are now taking
part In Sweden's educational television
programme. Some of the programmes are
also re-televised in the evening for the
benefit of parents.
Ultrasonic vibrations may become an
alternative to sprays and poisons for pest
control and may even be effective against
pests that are resistant to common insecti¬
cides, according to two scientists at the
University of Hawaii.
Deaths from cancer throughout the world
increased from 2,175,000 in 1950-52 to
2,623,000 in 1958-60an increase of about
20 % reports WHO. Cancer is the second
leading cause of death In the world after
cardiovascular diseases.
]]>
</page>
<page number="39">
<![CDATA[
catalog u«
de reproduction!
en couleurs de peintures
1860 i 1963
unesco paris
CATALOGUE OF COLOUR
REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS
1 860- 1 963
(Revised and enlarged edition)
An up-to-date listing of colour
reproductions of world-famous paint¬
ings compiled from the Unesco
collection of reproductions selected
by internationally-known art experts
on the basis of fidelity of reproduction,
the significance of the artist and the
importance of the original painting.
This Unesco catalogue contains
descriptions and illustrations of 1.440
reproductions available in full-colour
prints. 519 pages.
Price: 30/-; $6.00; 21 F.
Completely revised
and enlarged
CATALOGUE OF COLOUR REPRODUCTIONS
OF PAINTINGS PRIOR TO 1860
lists nearly 1,000 recommended colour repro¬
ductions
includes many examples from Asia, Africa,
Australia and Central Europe.
Catalogue dc reproductions
en couleurs
de peintures antérieures à i860
Catalogue of colour reproductions,
of paintings prior to i860
Catálogo de reproducciones
en color
de pinturas anteriores a i860
A beautifully
presented volume
of 379 pages.
Each painting is
reproduced in
black and white
together with full
details of the ori¬
ginal, name of
publisher and
price of colour re¬
production.
Price: 30 (stg);
$6.00; 21 F.
In the Federal Republic of
Germany, Switzerland and Aus¬
tria, a special Unesco-Olden¬
bourg Verlag edition (with
German text) also available.
Where to obtain Unesco publications
Order from any bookseller, or write direct to
the National Distributor in your country. (See list
below ; names of distributors in countries not
listed will be supplied on request.) Payment is
made in the national currency ; the rates quoted
are for an annual subscription to THE UNESCO
COURIER in any one language.
AFGHANISTAN. Panuzaï, Prest Department. Royal
Aghan Ministry of Education, Kabul. AUSTRALIA.
Tradco Agencies, 109 Swanston Street, G. P. O.
Box 2324 V, Melbourne C. I. (Victoria); United
Nations Association of Australia, Victorian Division,
8th Floor, McEwan House, 343 Little Collins St.,
Melbourne C. I. (Victoria). (22/6). AUSTRIA.
Verlag Georg Fromme & C*., Spengergasse 39, Vienna V
(Seh. 70.-). BELGIUM. Editions "Labor",
342, rue Royale, Brussels, 3. NV Standaard-Boek-
handel, Belgiëlei 151. Antwerp. For The Unesco
Courier (140 FB) and art slides only; Louis De Lannoy,
1 1 2, rue du Trône, Brussels 5. CCP 3380.00. BURMA.
Burma Translation Society, 361 Prome Road, Ran¬
goon. (	). CANADA. Queen's Printer,
Ottawa, Ont. (S 3.00). CEYLON. Lake House
Bookshop, 100 Parsons Road, P.O. Box 244, Colombo, 2.
(Rs. 13/50). World Book Co. Ltd., 99 Chung¬
king South Rd., Section 1, Taipeh, Taiwan (Formosa).
CYPRUS. Cyprus National Youth Council, P. O. Box 539,
Nicosia. CZECHOSLOVAKIA. S.N.T.L.. Spalena 51.
Prague 1 (permanent display); Zahrahnici literatura
Bilkova 4, Prague 1. DENMARK. E|nar Munksgaard,
Prags Boulevard 47 Copenhagen S (D. Kr. 17).
ETHIOPIA. International Press Agency. P.O. Box 120.
Addis Ababa. FINLAND. Akateeminen Kirjakauppa.
2 Keskuskatu, Helsinki. (Fmk. 9.40). FRANCE.
Librairie de I'Unesco, Place de Fontenoy, Paris-7'. CCP.
1 2598-48. (1 0 F.). GERMANY. R. Oldenbourg Verlag.
Rosenheimerstrasse 145, Munich. 8. For the Unesco
Kurier (German ed only) Bahrenfelder-Chaussee 160,
Hamburg-Bahrenfeld. CCP. 276650 (DM 10).
GHANA Methodist Book Depot Ltd . Atlantis Hous,
Commercial St., POB 100, Cape Coast. GREAT BRI
TAIN. See United Kingdom. GREECE. Librairie H.
Kauffmann, 28, rue du Stade, Athens. HONG-KONG.
Swindon Book Co., 64, Nathan Road, Kowloon. HUN¬
GARY. Kultura. P. O. Box 149. Budapest, 62. ICE¬
LAND. Snaebjórn Jonsson & Co. H.F., Hafnarstraeti 9,
Reykjavik. INDIA. Orient Longmans Ltd. Nicol Road,
Bellard Estate, Bombay 1; 17 Chittaranjan Avenue, Cal¬
cutta 1 3;Gunfoundry Road, Hyberabad, 1; 36a, Mount
Road, Madras 2; Kanson House, 1/24 Asaf Ah Road, P.O.
Box 386, New Delhi, 1; Sub-Depot: Oxford Book &
Stationery Co., 17 Park Street, Calcutta 16, Scindia
House, New Delhi, Indian National Commission Co-ope¬
ration with Unesco, Ministry of Education, for New
Delhi 3. (Rs. 7). INDONESIA. P. N. Fadjar Bhakti
Djalan, Nusantara 22, Djakarta. IRAQ. Mackenzie's
Bookshop, Baghdad. IRELAND. The National Press,
2, Wellington Road, Ballsbridge, Dublin. (15/5).
ISRAEL. Blumstein's Bookstores 3 5, Allenby Road
and 48, Nahlat Benjamin Street, Tel-Aviv (l£8).
JAMAICA. Sangster's Book Room, 91 Harbour
Street, Kingston. (15/-). JAPAN. Maruzen Co. Ltd.,
6 Tori-Nichome, Nihonbashi, P.O. Box 605 Tokyo
Central, Tokyo. (	). JORDAN. Joseph L. Bahous
& Co., Dar ul-Kutub, Salt Road. P.O.B. 66, Amman.
KENYA. E.S.A. Bookshop, P.O. Box 30167, Nairobi.
KOREA. Korean National Commission for Unesco, P.O.
Box Central 64, Seoul. LIBERIA. Cole and Yancy
Bookshops Ltd.. P.O. Box 286. Monrovia. LUXEM¬
BURG. Librairie Paul Brück, 22, Grand-Rue, Luxemburg
(FL 140). MALAYSIA. Federal Publications Ltd., Times
House, River Valley Rd., Singapore (M. S 7. 50). - MALTA.
Sapienza's Library 26 Kingsway, Valletta. (1 5/-). MAU¬
RITIUS. Nalanda Company Ltd., 30, Bourbon Street,
Port-Louis (1 07-) British Library, 30 Bid
des Moulins, Monte-Carlo. (F. 1 0). NETHERLANDS.
N. V. Martinus Ntjhoff, Lange Voorhout. 9, The Hague,
(fl. 8.50). NETHERLANDS WEST INDIES. G. CT.
Van Dorp & Co. (Ned Ant.) N.V.. Willemsiad. Curaçao.
N.A. (NA fl 4.50). NEW ZEALAND. Government
Printing Office 20, Molesworth Street (Private Bag) Wel-
lingston, C. 1 Government Bookshops: Auckland (P.O.
Box 5344), Christchurch (P.O. Box 1721), Dunedm P.O.
Box 1 1 04) (1 5/-). NIGERIA. C.M.S. Bookshops, P.O.
Box 174, Lagos (10/-). NORWAY. A.S. Bokhjorn.t.
Lille Grense 7, Oslo. For the Unesco Courier only: A.S.
Narvesens Litteratur T|eneste, Stortingsgt. 2 Otto, Post-
boks 1 1 5 (	). PAKISTAN. Th« Weit-Pak Publis¬
hing Co. Ltd., Unesco Publications House, P.O. Box 374
56-N Gulberg Industrial Colony, Lahore. PHILIPINES.
The Modern Book Co., 508 Rizal Avenue Manila.
POLAND. "RUCH", ul. Wronia, 23, Warsaw 10
(	). PORTUGAL. Dias & Andrade Lda, Livraria
Portugal, Rua do Carmo 70, Lisbon. PUERTO RICO,
Spanish English Publications, Eleanor Roosevelt 115,
Apartado 1912, Hato Rey. RHODESIA & NYA-
SALAND. The Book Centre, Gordon Avenue, Salisbury,
Southern Rhodesia. SUDAN. AI Bashir Bookshop,
P. O. Box 1118. Khartoum. SWEDEN. A/B CE.
Fntzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm 1 6.
For the Unesco Courier: Svenska Unescoradet, Vasa-
gatan 15-17, Stockholm. C (Kr. 12); SWITZERLAND.
Europa Verlag, 5 Rimistrasse Zurich. Payot, 40, rue du
Marché, Geneva CCP. 1-236. "Courier" only: Georges
Losmaz, 1, rue des Vieux-Grenadiers, Geneva. CCP.
1-4811. (Fr. S. 10). Dar-es-Salaam
Bookshop, P.O B. 9030, Dar-es-Salaam. THAILAND.
Suksapan Panit, Mansion 9, Rajdamnern Avenue. Bangkok.
(35 ticals). TURKEY. Librairie Hachette, 469 Istiklal
Caddesi, Beyoglu, Istanbul. UGANDA. Uganda Book¬
shop. P.O. Box 145, Kampala. UNION OF SOUTH
AFRICA Van Schaik's Bookstore, Libri Building, Church
Street, P.O. Box 724 Pretoria. For the Unesco Courier
(single copies) only: Central News Agency P.O.Box 1033,
|ohannesbourg.(RL.50). - UNITED ARAB REPUBLIC
(EGYPT). Librairie Kasr El Nil, 38, rue Kasr El Nil
Cairo. Sub/agent: La Renaissance d'Egypte, 9 Sh. Adly-
Pasha, Cairo. UNITED KINGDOM. H M. Stationery
Office, P.O. Box 569, London, S.E.I, and Government
Bookshops in London, Edinburgh, Cardiff, Belfast, Man¬
chester. Birmingham and Bristol. (15/-). UNITED
STATES. Unesco Publications Center, 317 East 34th St,
New York, N.Y. 1 001 6 (S 5.00) and (except periodicals):
Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York,
27. N.Y. U.S.S.R. Mezhdunarodnaia Kniga. Moscow.
G-200. YUGOSLAVIA. Yugoslovenska Knjig.
Tzrazije 27, Belgrade.
]]>
</page>
<page number="40">
<![CDATA[
Panax © Paris-Match
'Last Supper'
rejuvenated
One of the world's most celebrated works of art is Leonardo da Vinci's
"Last Supper", painted on the refectory wall in the convent of Santa
Maria delle Grazie, in Milan. Few people know about the existence
of a remarkable0copy of Leonardo's masterpiece made by one of his
pupils, Andreas Solario. This giant canvas has suffered from well-
meaning, but clumsy attempts at restoration in past centuries. It
is seen here in the hands of art specialists at the Institut Royal de
Patrimoine Artistique, in Brussels, who have already spent nearly
five years delicately and meticulously removing the patching
retouching and other traces of former "restorations" (see page 16).
]]>
</page>
</document>
