<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="079609eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
The Courier
JULY 1988 -9 French ir.nc»
From movable type
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
Inspiringfootwork
When sculptorfanus Kamban, who lives in
the Faeroe Islands, saw ourphoto ofa Sierra
Leonean boyplaying soccer (March 1987
issue, page 2) he was captivated by it. "I
thought it would befun to see the agile
movement from othersides too, " he wrote to
us, "so I made a statuette ofaplaying boy. "
Below, a photomontage showing the
statuette and thephoto that inspired it.
V***^
,.,!.>» , tat*«*1* , ,1. " ... '. '"
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
July 1988
Cover: Photomontage of a porcelain Chinese seal
(17th century) with carved jade printing surface;
¡mage of electronic circuitry produced by a com¬
puter; at right, print control strip used for check¬
ing the accuracy of colour proofs.
Photos (seal) © Réunion des Musées nationaux, Musée Guimet,
Paris; (circuitry) Betlavia © REA, Paris
Back cover: Detail of a page from the 42-line
Latin Bible printed by Johannes Gutenberg
(Mainz, c. 1455), the first book printed from
movable type in the West. The typestyle is known
as Textura, a Gothic script in which the design of
the characters produces an interwoven effect. The
decorative initial capital was added by hand.
Photo © Gutenberg Museum, Mainz, Fed. Rep. of Germany
The Courier
A uindou opt» on the u-orld 4 1st year
Published monthly in 35 languages English
French Spanish Russian German
Arabic Japanese Italian Hindi
Tamil Hebrew Persian Dutch
Portuguese Turkish Urdu Catalan
Malaysian Korean Swahili Croato-
Serb Macedonian Serbo-Croat
Slovene Chinese Bulgarian Greek
Sinhala Finnish Swedish Basque
Thai Vietnamese Pashto Hausa
«
From movable type to the microchip
Landmarks in printing
by Werner Merkli
4
10
14
16
19
20
22
25
28
32
34
35
2
'£
Calligraphy and typography in Europe
by Roger Druet at
Christophe Plantin
The master-printer ofAntwerp
by Francine de Nave
isThe desktop revolution
by Howard Brabyn
Unesco and the printed word cí
Computerized typesetting in China
by Xu Lian-Sheng §
The book situation in India
by Lokenath Bhattacharya
>4rf
First impressions
Arabic early printed texts
by Camille Aboussouan
L 'Encyclopédie
An eighteenth-century best-seller
by Robert Darnton
Printing and society in China
and the West
by Tsien Tsuen-Hsuin
Glossary
The Unesco Courier goes to press
Peoples and cultures
DENMARK: Inspiring footwork
Only a few years ago, it was widely contended that
one of the great transformations of modern society
was the decline of the written and printed word and
the rise to pre-eminence of the audiovisual media of
communication. Today, to paraphrase a remark
once made by the American humorist Mark Twain
when news of his own death had been prematurely
and inadvertently published, it may seem that
reports of the demise of the printed word have been
greatly exaggerated. While for centuries after the
invention of printing with movable metal type,
printing processes remained essentially unchanged,
today the production of books, periodicals and
other forms ofprinted matter is being
revolutionized by computerized type design and
photocomposition, satellite text transmission and
other new technologies. Paradoxically enough, the
development of microcomputers and "desktop
publishing" in theory at least may offer its
practitioners the extensive control over many stages
of the printing and publishing process that was
enjoyed by the European printers of 500 years ago.
This issue of the Unesco Courier presents some
landmarks in the history of printing and publishing
from the invention of paper in China 2,000 years
ago to modern electronic breakthroughs. It is
largely devoted to practical developments, ranging
from the evolution of calligraphy and typography
in late medieval Europe to methods of
computerized typesetting in modern China. Some
of the problems ofprinting and publishing in the
developing world are highlighted in an article on
the book situation in India by Lokenath
Bhattacharya, who reminds us that "the principal
factors governing publishing activities in a country
are its literacy rate, the size and nature of its
educated population, and its educational policies
and programmes".
Editor-în-chief: Edouard Glissant
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
FROM MOVABLE TYPE TO THE MICROCHIP
LANDMARKS IN PRINTING
BY WERNER MERKLI
WERNER MERKLI, of Switzerland, is editor of the German-language
edition of the Unesco Courier. A specialist in printing technology, he was for
many years a director ofa leading Swiss publishing andprinting company, and
served as president ofthe Association ofSwiss Printing Industriesfrom 1976 to
1981. He was for 25 years president of the friends of the Swiss Gutenberg
Museum, Berne. Among his published works are "Vademécum. An introduc¬
tion to the graphic arts", published by Hallwag, Berne (2nd ed. 1967).
FOR more than 400 years after Johannes Gutenberg's
invention of a process of printing from movable
metal type in the fifteenth century, all type was cast
in a hand mould, the text was composed by hand, and
printing was carried out on hand presses. It was not until
the nineteenth century that typesetting and printing pro¬
cesses were mechanized. Since the mid-twentieth century,
electronics and the microcomputer have revolutionized
text composition, reproduction of illustrations and print¬
ing techniques.
Papermaking
1 . The earliest picture of papermaking
in Europe is this woodcut made byjost
Amann for Hans Sach's "Book of
Trades", printed in Frankfurt in 1568.
Although almost all steps in
papermaking are now highly
mechanized, the basic process remains
unchanged. Plant fibres are separated
and wetted to produce pulp, which is
filtered on a screen, leaving a sheet
from which the water is pressed out.
The dry sheet is further compressed
and treated, depending on the use for
which it is intended.
2. Detail from a late 15th-century
woodcut from Nuremberg shows
Ulman Stromer's paper mill, the
first in Germany.
3. Side view and plan of
Nicolas-Louis Robert's
papermaking machine, 1798
The art of papermaking (1) was invented by the Chinese as
long ago as the second century BC (see article page 32), and
travelled westward when Chinese papermakers, taken prison¬
er by the Arabs near Samarkand in AD 751, were forced to
disclose their manufacturing secrets. In 1150 the art reached
Spain, and by the time of Gutenberg, paper mills had been
established in several European cities (2). Gutenberg thus had
at his disposal a perfect printing material that was much
cheaper than the parchment on which manuscripts were
produced in the monasteries.
Papermaking was not mechanized until around 1800, when
the first papermaking machine was invented by a Frenchman,
Nicolas-Louis Robert, in the Didot paper mills near Paris. It
used a moving belt, and paper was made one sheet at a time (3).
In 1805 the English engineer Joseph Bramah devised a paper-
moulding machine which used a rotating cylinder. This de¬
velopment later led to the production of continuous reels or
"webs" of paper (4). The manufacture of paper is now almost
entirely automated and quality control can be carried out by
computer.
4. Machine for producing reels of paper, c. 1 820
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
The art of printing
Letterpress
impression
cylinder
«y.
Letterpress is the oldest method ofprinting, and theonly
process which can use type directly. Printing is done from cast
metal type or from blocks on which the image or printing areas
are raised (in relief) above the non-printing areas. Ink rollers
touch only the top surface of the raised areas, and the inked
image is transferred directly to the paper. Above, operating
principles of a type of letterpress machine with a flat bed and an
impression cylinder.
Monastic libraries contain printed sheets dating from the
ninth and tenth centuries which were produced from relief
engraving on wooden blocks (5). Between 1041 and 1048, the
Chinese smith Bi Sheng used a technique of printing texts on
paper with movable characters made of earthenware, and
printing was also carried out with characters cast in copper in
a Korean printing works in 1403. Between 1436 and 1444,
Johannes Gensfleisch zum Gutenberg, of Mainz, Germany
(6), developed the type mould or matrix and originated a
method of printing from movable metal type that was used
without important change until the twentieth century.
Gutenberg cut a punch in hard metal for every letter, accent
and punctuation mark and struck it into a softer metal to make
the mould for casting identical pieces of type. The type was
made from an alloy of lead, antimony and tin. The finished
characters were kept in compartmentalized typecases (7) from
which the text was assembled. For printing, Gutenberg built a
wooden worm-screw hand press (8), similar to a wine press.
His printing ink consisted of a mixture of pinewood soot and
linseed oil, which was spread on the printing surface with
leather pads. To ensure better absorption of the ink, the paper
was dampened before printing.
It is not surprising that the first book Gutenberg chose to
print was the Bible, for at that time it was the work most in
demand. His "forty-two-line Bible" (see back cover), so
named because of the number of lines in each column, was
printed in Mainz between 1452 and 1455, in an edition of 200
copies. The coloured initial letters to chapters and the decora¬
tions were added afterwards by hand, because so far as the
design of the type (9) and the layout was concerned Guten¬
berg followed closely the model set by fine book manuscripts
in the monasteries.
The art of printing spread rapidly all over Europe. Many
efforts were made to improve the efficiency of the wooden
press, and Wilhelm Haas, a typefounder of Basel, Switzer¬
land, followed the basic design of the wooden press when in
1787 he developed the first all-metal hand press, which pro¬
duced a better quality impression.
6. The oldest known portrait of
Gutenberg. Copper engraving
from Vrais portraits et vies des
hommes illustres, Paris, 1584.
5. A modern woodblock-engraver
A
DIaar.mi3D aaacinaa
§1 1UL IUI JU DDDI iodo
SI iai iai IE3 anac lana
m im IDI JU DDEJt man
m IUI im 1U tiaac laajB
mtac IUI JU uaatia:*:u
ddqquuu EiDnaana 1
naaonHi aauauuuu 1
m inn nnn nrnaa
Ol IBU UUU JUaa
gl D BDO
.jlju;;
aale
BIIDD g DBBOB
- R G
V 1
7. Illustration of typecases from
Diderot's Encyclopédie
8. Gutenberg's press reconstituted
at Leipzig in the 1 9th century. The
press has a fixed, level lower
surface, the "bed", and a movable,
level upper surface, the "platen".
The composed type, after being
locked into a metal frame to make
the printing block or "forme", was
inked, covered with a sheet of
paper, and pressed between the two
surfaces.
9. Examples of letters Q /* % X r> r>
cut by Gutenberg
to to to to c c
te ta £ bi Ir tt
t C t f f f
10. Diagram of Koenig's press
(1 8 1 1), in which the platen is
replaced by an "impression
cylinder"
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
>
4
-1 4
|
^-«JlW^
1 1. The Walter rotary press, 1 866
The idea that a rolling cylinder might be used in printing to
overcome excessive manual strain was put forward in the early
seventeenth century, but it was not until 1811 that the first
steam-driven cylinder printing machine was patented by the
German compositor and inventor Friedrich Koenig (10).
Further progress was achieved in 1818 with the double rotary
press designed by Koenig and his associate Andreas Bauer, in
which paper printed on one side under one of the cylinders
passed to the other cylinder to be printed on the other side.
In 1844 Richard Hoe in the USA patented the first rotary
press in which the type was carried on a metal cylinder instead
of a flat plate. In 1866 the proprietor of the London Times,
John Walter, had the first rotary press fed by a continuous roll
of paper constructed according to the American model in¬
vented by Jeptha Wilkinson (11), making it possible to print
14,000 copies of the newspaper per hour.
Revolving at a rate of 35,000 revolutions
per hour, modern rotaries can print 500 m
ofpaper per minute.
Above, preparing to print a
newspaper on a rotary press.
impression
cylinder paper doctor
blade
12. A copperplate
engraver at work
Gravureprinting, like letterpress printing, is based on a height
differential between the ¡mage and non-image areas. In this
process the image areas are recessed (intaglio) below the level of
the non-printing areas. The surface of the printing plate is
broken up into small cells holding different ink volumes, which
constitute the image. The plate is flooded with ink and the
surplus removed by a "doctor blade", leaving ink only in the
recessed cells.
THE PRIZE
Gravure
This technique developed from the art of copperplate en¬
graving, in which the design is cut with a gouge, or chemically
etched, into a polished copper plate (12). The earliest known
etching was made by the Basel goldsmith, painter and graphic
artist, Urs Graf, in the fifteenth century. Printing from the
engraved plates was done by hand. Later an engraved cylinder
was used instead of a flat plate, and reels of the material to be
printed were fed between it and the pressing cylinder. This
idea proved attractive to printers of cloth in the eighteenth
century, and in 1783 a multi-colour gravure press for making
cotton prints was constructed in England by a copperplate
printer, Thomas Bell. In 1860 Auguste Godchaux, a Paris
publisher, obtained a patent for a gravure rotary press which
would print on each side of the sheet.
A key invention in modern gravure printing was a photo¬
graphic etching process using carbon tissue, developed by the
Czech painter and graphic artist, Karl Klic, or Klietsch, in
1878. Since then, millions of illustrated publications have been
produced by gravure printing (13).
In 1908, two Germans with experience in cotton printing,
Ernst Rolffs and Eduard Mertens, developed a flexible steel
"doctor blade" to wipe excess ink from the printing plate.
Later, the process of etching the printing cylinder was greatly
improved by the introduction of automated, electronic
engraving.
13. Early example of a children's
magazine illustration printed by
gravure
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Lithography and offset
The lithographic technique was discovered by chance in
1 796, when the Munich dramatist Aloys Senefelder, searching
for a economical method of printing his own work, tried
writing on a finely-ground stone surface and discovered the
water-repellent properties of his greasy, oil-based ink.
Initially, the images to be reproduced were hand-drawn on
a litho stone (14) and printed on a manual press (15). The
impression was taken by pressing the paper against the inked
stone with a scraper. Thanks to the mechanization of this
technique with Georg Sigl's flat-bed litho press, introduced in
Berlin in 1851, single and multi-colour lithographic printing
(16) became very important, especially for printing packaging
material.
As early as 1805 Senefelder had tried to find an alternative
to the heavy litho stone, but it was not until 1904 that Ira W.
Rubel and Caspar Hermann of New Jersey, USA, devised a
thin metal plate to carry the image to be printed. After this had
been inked, and the surplus ink repelled with moisture, the
image was transferred to a rubber-coated cylinder and then to
the paper (17). This form of indirect printing is known as
offset. The fact that the printing plate, the rubber blanket and
paper all ran on cylinders enabled higher printing speeds to be
achieved from the start.
In the early offset litho presses, the need for dampening
often caused serious problems and the impressions obtained
were dull and blurred. After the Second World War, technical
improvements combined with better inks and more thickly-
coated paper, resulted in sharper impressions and higher ink
saturation.
Today, large electronically-controlled offset rotary presses,
with several printing units in sequence, can print both sides of
the paper, in sheets or as a continuous web, at the rate of
30,000 impressions per hour (18).
impression^
Cylinder/ paper
1 7. Offset lithography. Basically the offset printing
press consists of 3 revolving cylinders. The first
cylinder carries the printing plate, the second carries a
rubber blanket, and the third (the impression cylinder)
presses the paper against the offset blanket. Other
rollers feed the paper through the press.
dampening
rollers
paper
inking
system dampening
, ^ system
kwater
In lithography, the printing and
non-printing areas are on the same
plane of the surface of a thin metal
plate, and the definition between
them is maintained chemically.
The printing parts of the surface
repel water when moistened but
absorb the ink with which they are
coated, whereas the non-printing
parts absorb the water and repel
the ink.
15. Wooden lithographic hand
press from the time of Senefelder
16. Colour illustration by the
Finnish lithographer Emilie
Topelius was reproduced in a
children's book, Sagor, published in
1847
. ¡ » i: i V
impression
cylinder
plate
cylinder
blanket
cylinder
printed
mage
1 8. An offset rotary press
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
Revolutions in typesetting
In the nineteenth century attempts were made to mechanize
text composition, which was still carried out line by line with
individual metal characters assembled in a composing stick
(19), following a process that had not changed greatly since
Gutenberg's time. The first patent for a typesetting machine
was taken out in 1822 by William Church of Boston; others
soon followed (20).
But the real breakthrough in the mechanical setting and
casting of type was achieved in 1884 by the German-born
watchmaker Ottmar Mergenthaler in Cincinnati, USA, when
he invented the Linotype machine, which could set 6,000
characters per hour as compared with 1,400 by hand. In the
Linotype system (21), the brass matrices in which the charac¬
ters are engraved in negative form are released from the
storage magazine by typing on a keyboard, assembled into a
line and moved into the casting mechanism. After casting, the
entire lead line or "slug" is ejected and the matrices carried
back to their position in the storage magazine where they
remain on call for another line.
In 1897, also in the USA, the English engineer Tolbert
Lanston separated the operations of setting and casting the
type in his Monotype machine. In the Monotype system (22),
again by typing on a keyboard, a paper tape on the setting-
machine was punched with a different combination of per¬
forations for each character. This punched tape mechanically
controlled the typecasting mechanism, which cast each char¬
acter individually. Because of the high quality of the type
produced by the Monotype system, it came to occupy a
predominant position in book printing.
Developments in photographic techniques led to many
attempts to replace metal type by photographing the images
of the characters (23). A successful early application of photo-
typesetting was the Lumitype system developed by two
Frenchmen, René Higonnet and Louis Moyroud, in the
1940s. Production speeds exceeded 28,000 characters per hour
on later models. In the Monophoto, introduced in England in
1950 as a development of the Monotype system, the charac¬
ters could also be enlarged and reduced in size when projected
onto film.
In 1955 sensational developments in electronics sounded
the deathknell of Gutenberg's lead type. Instead of being
controlled by perforated tapes, typesetting machines could
now be driven by a computer programmed to expose the
characters onto film, permitting an output of 30,000 to
100,000 characters per hour. A considerable acceleration in
output up to 600,000 characters per hour was achieved in
the 1960s with the development of faster computers and the
use of a cathode ray tube (CRT).
Another significant development at this time was the intro¬
duction of the Optical Character Recognition (OCR) reading
machine, which scans typewritten or printed text at the rate of
300,000 characters per hour to produce input to a computer-
driven typesetter.
Considerable improvements in text input speeds were
achieved with the introduction of integrated circuits and
microprocessors into computer systems, as well as by the
introduction of a visual display unit on which the selected
characters appear as they are typed. The text can be read and
corrected on the screen (24), before being stored in the
computer's memory. However, there is a limit to the typeset¬
ting speed of machines using CRT technology, as each charac¬
ter has to be picked out individually from the image matrix.
8
Another approach was adopted in 1 965 by Dr. Rudolf Hell,
of Kiel, Federal Republic of Germany. In his Digiset system, a
scanning device analyses each character electronically and
breaks it down into tiny squares, which are stored in the
computer's magnetic memory in digital form. When inputting
text, these squares are recombined on film, again using a
cathode ray tube, into characters of the required size and
typeface. With a initial production speed of over 1 million
characters per hour, this was another important breakthrough
in typesetting.
In 1976, the laser beam began to be used to replace the CRT
beam for digital recording of the characters (25). The intense
light beam from photons projects a sharper, clearer typeface.
Digital storage of text opens up revolutionary possibilities for
its high-speed transmission throughout the world, via satellite
or fibre-optic cable.
19. The composing stick holds
pieces of type. The compositor sets
the type upside down.
20. Hattersley's typesetting
machine, London, c.1870
21. Diagram of
Linotype machine
22. Early monotype
keyboard (left) and
caster (right)
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
The printed image
Throughout the Middle Ages, beautiful copperplate engra¬
vings, etchings, woodcuts (26) and lithographic prints were
produced by draughtsmen and painters by carving or drawing
on printing blocks of wood or stone, or by engraving on metal
plates. Discoveries regarding light and the theory of colour,
together with the invention of photography in the nineteenth
century, brought the potential of photographic processes to
the printing industry (27).
Although solid lines can be printed directly using the
letterpress and offset processes, the intermediate tones in
photographs cannot. In 1881, the Munich copperplate en¬
graver Georg Meisenbach succeeded, by photographing an
image through a screen of crossed lines, in breaking down the
image into tiny dots. In the resulting positive, the closely-
spaced dots combine to form the darker tones of the original
image, and the less dense dots yield the light tones. The
screened image can then be recorded on to a printing plate in a
process known as halftone etching. Screening is often carried
out by electronic scanning today (28).
For the reproduction of tonal images in colour, however,
three plates must be made one each to print red, blue and
yellow ink. Usually, a black plate is also made, because black
ink adds sharpness to the printed copy. The first step is to
separate the colours photographically in the original image.
The colour separations are made by taking four separate
photographs through different filters which block out all
colours except the desired colour, and also through a halftone
screen to produce the dot pattern required for printing. In
colour printing, some of the different coloured dots fall close
together and some are superimposed. The eye mixes the
colours of the dots on the printed page into all the tones of the
original. For example, what the eye sees as green is really an
area of tiny blue and yellow dots. Experiments carried out in
the USA between 1946 and 1950 led to the development of a
process for making colour separations by electronic scanning,
and by the late 1970s, following developments in electronics
technology, the impulses from the scanner beam were digi¬
tized. The tiny dots which produce the tonal values of the
reproduction are then reconstituted by laser beam, either on
film or directly onto the printing plate.
iVrnj&iua copoitdlj
nue DOOM
3lo.(WTfoncjncil-
Unue pmticnha
23. Diagram showing
operating principles of
a phototypesetting
machine
24. Composing text
on screen
26. In the early days of
European printing,
identical woodcuts
were sometimes used to
illustrate different
people.
27. Photo from William
Henry Fox Talbot's
Pencil of Nature (1844-
46), the first known
book illustrated
entirely with
photographs
28. Electronic scanners
(right) can be used to
process images for
printing. The image is
fitted onto a revolving
drum and reproduced
by the scanner as a
pattern of tiny dots.
Far right, halftone dots
enlarged
The electronic future
Developments in the printing industry during the coming
decades will be primarily determined by advances in electro¬
nics. Desktop publishing technology (see article page 16)
emerged in the 1980s for the processing of both text and
image. Using electronic pencils and brushes, computer
graphics can be created directly on the screen and integrated
into the stored text. Furthermore, magnetic discs are being
developed which can store over 1,000 million typographical
signs (500,000 typewritten pages) and integrated databases
will improve access to information.
Metal typesetting and letterpress printing processes have
virtually disappeared within a short period. Thanks to the
simplification of platemaking, however, the offset and photo¬
gravure processes have survived. Electrostatic printing,
whereby an electrostatically-charged plate transmits a dry
powder or liquid ink toner to plain paper, and inkjet printing,
in which computer-controlled jets are used to spray hundreds
of thousands of electrostatically-charged drops of colour per
second onto the paper to produce text and images, are just two
of the techniques which are leading to contactless printing,
instead of printing from an inked plate.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
Calligraphy and typography
in Europe BY ROGER DRUET
Hittite hieroglyphic
inscription from the
ancient city of
Carchemish.onthe
upper Euphrates (10th
to 8th century BC).
	,
V -
ABr
Above, inscription in Phoenician script
on the tomb ofAhiram, king of Byblos
(10th century BC). The ancestry of
Western alphabets can be traced back
to the alphabet developed by the
ancient Phoenicians.
Below, letters from modern typefaces
in Greek (left) and Cyrillic (right).
Cyrillic, the alphabet used for Russian
and other languages of the USSR, as
well as Bulgarian and Serbian, is
derived from the Greek. It was
probably developed in the 9th century
AD by 2 Greek brothers often called
the "apostles to the Slavs", St. Cyril,
for whom it was named, and St.
Methodius. Cyrillic was later
developed into printing characters
which were simplified in the early 18th
century on the instructions ofPeter
the Great.
ABB
q6b
ALL typefaces, even the most modern digitized char¬
acters designed with the help of a computer, are
based on forms of writing. This link between writ¬
ten and printed characters is particularly noteworthy in the
history of European typographical design.
The Phoenicians and the Greeks, who invented the early
alphabets from which Western scripts derived, were seafar¬
ing and colonizing peoples who needed to carry precise and
legible messages over very long distances. Consequently the
priorities of Western writing were speed of execution and
simplicity of design.
The creation of phonetic alphabets (instead of ideographic
systems) using only twenty to thirty signs for the transcrip¬
tion of language was a decisive step in a process of abstrac¬
tion in which the Greeks played a leading role by consid¬
erably developing the Phoenician alphabet. The alphabet
they created is the basis of the Latin characters used in many
parts of the world today.
By the fourth" century BC, the Golden Age of Hellenic
thought, Ionic script had already developed the rectangular
form of modern capital lettering. During the Greek and
Roman classical era, writing acquired the harmonious and
balanced form which is known as lapidary because of its
resemblance to the monumental script used for inscriptions
in stone. This script with its -firmly chiselled grooves and
broad strokes which stood out well in sunlight and were
enhanced by shadow, answered a need for beauty and
harmony but also expressed imperial power. Latin capital-
letter script may be regarded as the basis of subsequent
developments in Western scripts and, later, type designs.
Cyrillic script, which was adopted by Orthodox Chris¬
tians for the Slavonic languages, particularly in Russia, em¬
ulated these upright, monumental styles of writing. System¬
atically used as a phonetic form, it became a widely
employed substitute for Latin script in the Slav countries.
The invention of Cyrillic script, derived from a Greek book
hand, is attributed to the ninth-century Greek missionaries
Cyril and Methodius, and was standardized by the Byzan¬
tine Emperor Constantine VII.
After the heavy quadrata, or square capitals, the basis of
all Latin scripts, and the Roman rustic capitals, an early form
of cursive script, writing evolved towards the rounded uncial
script. In the ninth century, Charlemagne imposed on the
Holy Roman Empire the form of small lettering now known
as Carolingian miniscule, which included most of the fea¬
tures of the lower case Latin alphabet. The official adoption
of this cursive script did not bring about the disappearance of
capital letters, but it was the dominant hand of Western
Europe throughout the ninth century and served as a model
for later innovators until the dawn of European printing in
the fifteenth century.
With the foundation of universities in Europe in the
twelfth century, parchment became scarce. A new script,
known as black-letter or Gothic, as angular and narrow as
the Gothic pointed arch, answered the needs of the moment
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Printing was originally conceived as a process for
the mechanical reproduction of manuscript. Many
early printers came to typography through
calligraphy, and the work of some later
typographers has also been influenced by styles of
handwriting. Right, specimen Western scripts
from Roman times to the 18th century.
in that it took up a minimum of space. The expression of
thought seemed to be channelled through a kind of grid. This
design gave rise to two basic scripts: the rigid, vertical
Textura, used primarily for liturgical texts; and a more
flexible script, Rotunda.
In the fifteenth century, the angular Gothic script, having
been appropriated by the lettered classes in France, became
known as bâtarde or Bastarda. The invention and use of
spectacles also made it possible for writing to become small¬
er. It was not until the end of the sixteenth century that the
Germans introduced capital letters into the Gothic alphabet
for woodblock printing. Hitherto, the place of the "dropped
initials" initial letters at the beginning of a page or chapter,
which covered two or three lines of text had been left
blank, to be filled in by the illuminators.
For engraving, the Germans had adopted a spiky kind of
script, whose rather fussy, fractured style suggested its name,
Fraktur. The great painter and engraver Albrecht Dürer,
who thought that letters could be governed by mathematical
laws, undertook to impose a constructive discipline on
Gothic script. This admirable undertaking culminated in a
balanced appearance for each character.
Around 1440, the German printer Johannes Gensfleisch,
known as Gutenberg, of Mainz, took the remarkable step of
bringing together and organizing all the processes of print¬
ing: punch-cutting, making matrices, type-casting, compos¬
ing and the use of a hand press. Once the discovery had been
made, the art of printing spread rapidly. The Gutenberg
forty-two-line Bible (see back cover), the first great feat of
Western printing, was printed in Gothic lettering. Sub¬
sequently, Gutenberg increased his. range of typefaces to
almost 300 so that he could reproduce different scripts as
accurately as possible.
The humanist scholars of fifteenth-century Italy never
took to Gothic script. Petrarch considered that it looked
blurred from a distance and caused eyestrain close to, as if it
had been created not to be read, but for some other purpose.
The Italian Renaissance therefore turned for inspiration to
classical Antiquity, and calligraphers revived ancient monu¬
mental lettering, thus returning to a simplicity and clarity
that are still characteristic of printing today. The West,
influenced by its artists, pursued the chimera of "divine
proportion", the mathematical relationship believed to be
the key to beauty. Leonardo da Vinci sought it in the human
body, as did Dürer and the great French typographer Geo-
froy Tory, who studied the composition of letters according
to the proportions of the human body in the Champfleury
(1529), a treatise on type design.
An important event which encouraged a new approach to
printing was the sack of Mainz in 1462, which forced many
of Gutenberg's collaborators to leave the town. They took
the secrets of printing to several European countries.
Around 1470 one of them, the French engraver Nicolas
Jenson settled in Venice, where hé drew inspiration from
humanist scripts in designing a new type with wedge-shaped
Aa Lapidary (from 600 BC)
A Quadrata, Roman square capital
aA Rustic, Roman cursive capital
AAA Uncial, rounded capital (from 3rd century AD)
aA^ Carolingian miniscule (8th-9th century)
a
p3£
Goriic(12th-15th century)
Evolution from Textura (left) to Rotunda (right)
Capital revived for initials (15th-16th century)
a Bastarda vernacu'ar script (15th century)
Aa¿L Humanist classical revival (14th-16th century)
J%a Chancery cursive script (15th-16th century)
CL Roundedbook hand (17th-18th century)
Signature of Charlemagne, c. 800 AD.
The Emperor, who could not write,
merely added his own flourish to the
monogram painted for him by the
copyist.
Letter patterns from Champfleury,
the first theoretical treatise on the
designing of type (1529), by the
French printer Geofroy Tory, who
later became the royal printer of
King François I.
Ornamental capital letter, left,
from the Bible Historiale (c.
1380) attributed to a copyist
known as Pierre Comestor
("Peter the Eater"), is one of
the earliest European
depictions of a person wearing
spectacles. The invention of
spectacles made it possible for
writing styles to become
smaller.
11
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
is/ epíílolas mâdatc
asdeílinauíc. ita nt
ïmunitur.comeatu
Uuitionê accedunt.
as/ arbitratus omnia
rçcenri/ inftigat Bal
ratu dignamaggre
ir Demetrius.Quo '
ABC
abc
The type created by the French
printer Nicolas Jenson (c. 1420-
1480) and known as "roman" is
generally considered to be the first
consciously designed according to
typographical ideals rather than
manuscript models; Left, specimen
of text printed in Jenson's roman.
These drawings show a capital and
lowercase "a" in a typeface known as
Romain du Roi, which was
commissioned by Louis XIV in 1692 for
the exclusive use of the royal printing
works. The drawings, made by Nicolas
Jaugeon, a leading member of the
committee charged with the design of
the typeface, form part of a set
prepared for the guidance of the type-
cutter, Philippe Grandjean. The
committee turned away from the
principles of calligraphy and designed
each letter on a mathematical basis,
using a grid subdivided into tiny
squares.
Page from The Works of
Geoffrey Chaucer(\»%)
the crowning achievement
of William Morris'
Kelmscott Press. Critical of
the mediocrity of
contemporary machine-
produced books, Morris
reverted to the hand press,
handmade paper and
specially-made ink and
typefaces. His Chaucer was
printed in black and red,
and contained 87 woodcuts
by the leading English
painter and designer Sir
Edward Burne-Jones, plus
an abundance of borders,
initials and ornaments
designed by Morris
himself.
The first italic typeface was cut
around 1500 by Francesco Griffo
for the Venetian humanist and
publisher Aldus Manutius. The
design was based on the cursive
writing of the papal chancery
clerks. Left, modern Garamond
italic, named after its designer,
Claude Garamond (c. 1480-1561),
who was inspired by the
publications of Manutius. (This
issue of the Courier is set in
Garamond.)
serifs. This pure and beautiful style was known as roman, a
name which would in future be applied to typefaces with an
upright design. Among the heirs to his workshop in that
illustrious city was the learned Aldus Manutius, one of the
great figures in European publishing. His type designer,
Francesco Griffo of Bologna, cut the first example of a
sloping type which became known as Aldine and is today
called italic. It was based on the informal cursive writing
developed by chancery clerks to speed their work.
The sixteenth century was the Golden Age of calligraphy
in Europe, rich in great calligraphers such as Ludovico degli
Arrighi, Ugo da Carpi, Giovanniantonio Tagliente and Pala¬
tino in Italy, Jean Beauchenne in France and Roger Ascham
in England. As progress was made in copper engraving, so a
cursive script with slender finials (terminal hooks) emerged
and came to fruition in the work of Lucas Matherot and
Louis Barbedor.
In France, where the development of printing was influen¬
ced by the work of Geofroy Tory, the Estienne family was
prominent. One of its members, Robert Estienne, was print¬
er to King François I. He entrusted Claude Garamond with a
royal command to cut typefaces for editions of classical
Greek texts. The famous Grecs du Roi which resulted were
uncluttered and elegant. Garamond, the first commercial
typefounder, also designed the roman and italic typefaces
which bear his name and which played a leading role in
European typographical design until the end of the sixteenth
century.
In this great humanist movement, Christophe Plantin (see
page 14), a French bookbinder who became a citizen of
Antwerp and a printer, acted as a connecting link with the
Netherlands, where a great dynasty of printers, the El-
zeviers, had come to the fore and would be active until the
beginning of the eighteenth century. The Elzeviers gave their
name to an elegant wedge-serif typeface.
In 1692, during the reign of Louis XIV and classicism,
Abbé Nicolas Jaugeon of the French Academy of Sciences
was given the task of creating a new typeface. His design, cut
by Philippe Grandjean, was called Romain du Roi and was
reserved for the exclusive use of the Imprimerie Royale the
Royal Press. This cold, majestic script was first used in 1702.
The eighteenth century was an age of elegant typography
in Britain. The typefounder William Caslon cut a highly
legible typeface which is still in use today. Caslon was the
typeface in which a Baltimore printer issued the official
copies of the United States Declaration of Independence.
Another English printer, John Baskerville, who taught cal¬
ligraphy, designed a graceful, balanced typeface which revo¬
lutionized typography and is still popular.
In eighteenth-century France, Louis-René Luce, engraver
to King Louis XV, introduced the rational spirit of the
Enlightenment and the Encyclopedists into typographical
experimentation, while Pierre-Simon Fournier and François-
Ambroise Didot invented the point system of typographic
measurement. Both Didot's son Firmin and Giambattista
12
]]>
</page>
<page number="13">
<![CDATA[
ABC
abc
AB<C
ab
Bodoni of Parma were inspired by Baskerville's work to
create very similar forms of austere lettering with strongly
contrasting thick and thin strokes. Their work influenced
nineteenth-century type design in several countries.
The development of lithography, a process of printing
from a stone surface invented in 1796 by the dramatist
Aloys Senefelder (see page 7), encouraged printing from
types based on calligraphic script with fine, supple curves.
From 1830 onwards, as a result of scientific and technical
advances and the development of industry and trade, a
dynamic form of typography came into being through the
work of typefounders such as Alexandre de Berny and
Théophile Beaudoire. Egyptian, with its slab serifs, and Fat
Face, still widely used in the press and advertising, were
highly fashionable typefaces.
William Morris, the poet and writer who made a major
contribution to the revival of English decorative art in the
late nineteenth century, was the leader of the Arts and Crafts
Movement which took inspiration from the styles of medie¬
val times. The work produced by his Kelmscott Press had a
strongly individual graphic personality and exercised wide
influence. In France, George Auriol and the painter and
engraver Eugène Grasset were among the masters of Art
Nouveau. The latter received support from the typefounder
Georges Peignot, who later, with his son Charles, produced
a range of typefaces which would dominate printing until the
advent of phototypesetting in 1956. Peignot, designed by the
French poster artist Adolphe Mouron Cassandre in 1937,
and Bifur, a shaded script of great originality, are among the
finest typefaces cut by the Deberny and Peignot typefoundry.
Today, although computerization is widespread, there is a
welcome revival of interest among young people in the art of
calligraphy, which is encouraging the search for and creation
of new designs. Outstanding modern designers of digitized
letters include the great German calligrapher Hermann Zapf;
Adrian Frutiger of Switzerland; Ladislas Mandel, José
Mendoza, Albert Botón, all of France; as well as the young
French designer of Arin, Franck Jalleau.
We are at the dawn of a new age of typography. Lettering
is no longer created by lead objects but by strokes of light.
Photocomposition systems can now provide higher screen
resolution, allowing sharper definition of characters, as well
as an immense variety of typefaces, offering great scope for
creativity. Soon, these machines will achieve a degree of
sensitivity close to that of handwriting, and will give typo¬
graphers a degree of control over the design of lettering far
superior to that of early electronic typesetting systems. But to
safeguard an entire heritage of craftsmanship, metal type must
not be allowed to disappear.
ROGER DRUET, a leading French typographer and calligrapher, has been
professor ofgraphic design and the history ofwriting at the Ecole Supérieure
des Arts Appliqués, in Paris, since 1960. He is the author ofnumerous studies
on the art ofwriting in ancient and modern times, notably La Civilisation de
l'Ecriture (1977).
C
Specimen letters of 2 typefaces designed in
18th-century Europe, Baskerville roman (far
left) and Didot roman (left). With the creation
of the typeface that bears his name, John
Baskerville (1706-1775) made a major
contribution to the development of English
fine printing. Another important step towards
modern typography was made in France, by
Firmin Didot (1764-1836), whose typeface is a
far cry from the flowing lines of earlier designs
which were natural to pen or brush.
A typeface known as Bifur,
designed by the French artist
Adolphe Mouron Cassandre in
1937, and cut by the Deberny and
Peignot typefoundry.
Above, Labyrinth (1981), a
photographic print by Albertas
Gurskas (born 1935), a graduate of
the Lithuanian SSR Art Institute.
Enlargement of a letter "w",
digitized for generation by
computer. When the letter is
printed at normal size, the "steps"
become, or should become,
invisible.
Letters from Arin roman (below right), a new
computer typeface designed by Franck Jalleau,
of France. The design, which won an award in
an international typographical design
competition held in 1987, moves away from the
square outlines of early digitized type and
returns to calligraphic sources. Below, a stu
for the companion italic face. AB£
abc
13
]]>
</page>
<page number="14">
<![CDATA[
CHRISTOPHE
PLANTIN
The master-printer of Antwerp
BY FRANCINE DE NAVE
AaBbCcD
FRANCINE DE NAVE, Belgian historian and
palaeographer, is director of the Plantin-Moretus
Museum in Antwerp and of the Antwerp Print-
Room. She is the author ofmany books and articles
on the history ofAntwerp. A longer version of the
present text has appeared in Belgique, des Maisons
et des Hommes, published by Nouvelles Editions
Vokaer, Brussels.
CHRISTOPHE Plantin was born
some time around the year 1520 in
Saint-Avertin, near the French city
of Tours, and served his apprenticeship with
the bookbinder and bookseller Robert Macé
in Caen. In 1549, after a brief stay in Paris,
he moved to Antwerp, at that time the hub
of Western European trade, and set up a
bookbinding business.
Antwerp suited his purpose perfectly, as
it was ideally situated to provide the equip¬
ment and raw materials necessary to set up a
bindery. And since it was also a major
financial centre, the capital necessary to cre¬
ate a business was readily available. In addi¬
tion, it was a city which attracted wealthy
art-lovers of all kinds.
Plantin had been in Antwerp for only a
few years when, following a wound to his
arm, he abandoned bookbinding in favour
of printing. The publication in 1559 of a
description of the magnificent funeral cere¬
mony of the Holy Roman Emperor Charles
V, by his son Philip II of Spain, established
Plantin's reputation, and he quickly found
himself at the head of what would prove to
be the most important printing-house in
Western Europe during the second half of
the sixteenth century.
Between 1563 and 1567, Plantin printed
and published over 200 titles, ranging from
annotated pocket editions of the classics to
liturgical works, Hebrew Bibles, richly il¬
lustrated anatomical treatises and botanical
studies.
Now a man of substance, Plantin enjoyed
great celebrity and was surrounded by a
circle of influential friends and acquaint¬
ances, one of whom Gabriel de Cayas,
secretary" to Philip IIwas to play a decisive
role in the further development of his af¬
fairs. It was Plantin's ambition to produce
an authoritative edition of the Old and New
Testaments; de Cayas secured financial
backing for the project from the Spanish
king, who also sent to Antwerp, to serve as
its specialist editor, his chaplain the hu¬
manist Benedictus Arias Montanus.
The undertaking, which took five years to
complete (1568-1573), was an outstanding
success: a copiously annotated edition of the
Bible in four languages (Hebrew, Syriac,
Greek and Latin), running to eight massive
volumes in folio. This Biblia Regia or Biblia
Polyglotta, as it was known, not only con¬
stituted a personal triumph for Plantin; it
was also the most voluminous publication
ever produced in the Netherlands by a
single printer. Its appearance marked the
beginning of the most prosperous period of
Plantin's business.
Thanks to the success of the Polyglot
Bible, and through the influence of Arias
Montanus, Plantin, who had already ob¬
tained the office of prototypus regius (royal
printer) from the Spanish monarch, was
accorded a monopoly in the sale of missals
and breviaries in Spain and its colonies over¬
seas. The lands in question rapidly became
14
]]>
</page>
<page number="15">
<![CDATA[
Frontispiece of Plantin's masterpiece, the 8-
volume Biblia Sacra or Polyglot Bible, published
in 4 languages (Latin, Greek, Hebrew and
Syriac).
Photo © Rare Books and Special Collections Division, Library of
Congress, Washington, D.C.
Antwerp's Plantin-Moretus Museum is estab¬
lished on the premises of Christophe Plantin's
printing office and residence. The 16th- and
17th-century printing works has been recon¬
structed in the museum (above).
his most important clients, and carried his
fortunes to their zenith.
No fewer than sixteen presses were at
work in Plantin's printing-house an enor¬
mous figure when it is remembered that the
biggest printer in France at the time, Es¬
tienne, was operating only four. The num¬
ber of his employees confirmed Plantin's
ascendancy: there were 54 staff living and
working on the premises in 1574; with the
addition of those who lived or worked at
home the total must have been in the region
of 150. Work went ahead at a feverish pace;
12- or 13-hour days were the norm. Each
press had to meet a daily target of 1,250
printed sheets, or 2,500 pages. But the type¬
setters, printers and proof readers were by
no means dissatisfied with their lot: they
were pieceworkers, and a high output com¬
manded excellent rates. Plantin's workers
were among the best-paid in Antwerp.
Quantity was not, however, the sole con¬
cern. Plantin insisted on the highest quality
as well. The paper mills of the southern
Netherlands at the time produced only me¬
diocre material, so he imported the finest
paper from Germany, and more especially
from France. The type used for printing his
publications had to be perfect as well, and
he called on the best typecutters of the age:
Claude Garamond, Robert Grandjean,
Guillaume Le Bé and Hendrick van de
Keere, besides playing an important person¬
al role in the development of typestyles in
Western Europe by importing the roman
and italic typefaces currently in use in
France.
Concerned also with the quality of the
The modern typeface known as Plantin,
based on a design used by the Antwerp master-
printer.
illustrations, Plantin preferred to print them
from engraved copper plates, which pro¬
duced finer lines and more delicate tones
than the wood blocks generally utilized. If
the latter gradually fell out of favour for
book illustrations, it was because of the
success enjoyed by Plantin's publications.
Plantin was equally attentive to the con¬
tent of his books. Despite his monopoly of
the sale of liturgical works, his presses were
not exclusively engaged in turning out mis¬
sals, breviaries, antiphonaries,1 diurnals,
books of hours and psalters. He applied
himself to publishing the most outstanding
literary works of the post-humanist age:
collections of the classics or of laws, princi¬
ples and maxims; school books; the first
edition of Variarum lectionum libri III by
the Flemish humanist Justus Lipsius and
Origines Antwerpianae by the physician
Goropius Becanus in 1569; and, in 1574, the
first dictionary of the Netherlandic lan¬
guage, the Dictiunarium Teutónico-Lati¬
num, compiled at his request by his proof
reader Cornelius Kiliaan.
Tragedy came to Antwerp in 1576,
against the troubled background of the wars
of religion in which the Low Countries
were embroiled for much of the second half
of the century. In what came to be known as
the "Spanish Fury", mutinous bands of
Spanish mercenaries sacked the city, mas¬
sacring hundreds of its citizens, plundering
and destroying everything in their path.
Plantin's printing-house was spared, but its
output was seriously affected. After the
"Fury", Antwerp joined in the rebellion
against Spanish absolutism. Trade with
Spain, on which the prosperity of Plantin's
enterprise had depended, fell into a decline.
In 1578, only six presses were functioning;
after 1583 there would never again be more
than ten.
Under such circumstances, Plantin had
little choice but to work with the Repub¬
lican rebels. He was appointed official print¬
er to the city of Antwerp, governed at the
time by a Calvinist magistrate, and later
became printer to the Duke of Anjou,
French ally of William of Orange, the char¬
ismatic leader of the rebellion. The printing-
house thus took on a new lease of life, and
works of considerable importance were
soon emerging once again from the presses.
Towards the end of 1582, Plantin had to
face another turn in his fortunes. Spanish
troops were threatening Antwerp, so he
considered opening a branch office further
north, to which, if necessary, his activities
might be evacuated. He left Antwerp for
Leiden, where his old friend Justus Lipsius,
who was associated with the recently estab¬
lished Calvinist University, had obtained
for him the franchise of the university press,
then he worked for a time in Cologne, but
by 1585 he had returned to Antwerp.
Four years remained to the master print¬
er. The publication of the Martyrologium
Romanum of Cardinal Baronius in 1589 was
Christophe Plantin's last major undertak¬
ing. When he died, that same year, he left
behind a vast enterprise, the printing-house
he had created, which would survive him for
another three hundred years.
1. Books of chant melody and text in the Roman Catho¬
lic Church. Editor.
dEeFfGgHhliJjKkLl
15
]]>
</page>
<page number="16">
<![CDATA[
THE DESKTOP REVOLUTION
BY HOWARD BRABYN
One of the many possibilities offered by do-it-yourself electronic publishing systems using personal computers may be to
help developing countries meet their needs for textbooks and other printed materials.
IN 1473, explaining the somewhat slipshod appearance
of his latest publication, a printer of Parma in northern
Italy declared that because rivals were about to bring
out the same text, he had had to rush it through the printing
process "faster than you can cook asparagus".
This colourful hyperbole bears eloquent witness to the
astonishingly rapid spread of publishing in the second half of
the fifteenth century. Barely twenty-five years after Jo¬
hannes Gutenberg had originated his new method of print¬
ing (using movable metal type, a press and an oil-based
printing ink), printing had spread to nearly all the major
trading centres of Europe. In the first half of the fifteenth
century the number of manuscript books in Europe could be
counted in tens of thousands; by the year 1500, more than 9
million books had been printed.
The history of printing and publishing, like that of all
human progress, is a record of the interplay between techno¬
logical innovation and social change. Whilst each of these
two streams of human activity promotes the other, with each
in turn playing the leading role, the really crucial leaps ahead
have always been made when the two converge to become an
irresistible tide. Thus, whilst it was made technically possible
by Gutenberg's discoveries, the development of printing in
Europe, "The German Art" as it was at first called, was
equally a response to the spread of literacy and to the social
climate of the Early Renaissance.
The early printers were men of many talents. Not only did
they design and cast their own typefaces, they also fulfilled
the functions of publisher, editor, printer and bookseller.
Only bookbinding and the manufacture of paper were left to
others. William Caxton, for example, the first English print¬
er, was an accomplished linguist and himself translated from
the French the first book to be published in English, The
Recuyell of the Historyes of Troye (1475), which he printed
on the press he had established in Bruges.
One of the great early printer-publishers was the Venetian
Aldus Manutius (1449-1515). In 1490, Aldus began produc¬
ing the first printed editions of many of the Greek and Latin
classics. Later he pioneered the production of cheap pocket
editions, with what for those days were large print runs of
1,000 copies to keep down the cost, and commissioned the
first italic typeface (see page 12). In 1502, he published
Dante's La Divina Commedia on which his famous imprint,
the anchor and dolphin, appeared for the first time.
As the demand for books and publications of every sort
grew, the days of the great printer-publishers were num¬
bered. The only way the book-hungry market could be
supplied was by specialization and the division of labour. As
a consequence the world of publishing gradually took on a
new form, which has lasted until modern times, with the
functions of author, publisher, printer, bookbinder and
bookseller becoming separated.
Significantly, however, the name of Aldus Manutius has
become associated with the current revolution in the pub¬
lishing world, for Paul Brainerd, the man who in 1985 coined
the phrase "desktop publishing", is president of the Aldus
Corporation, the firm that produced one of the first pro¬
grams capable of composing and formatting text merged
16
]]>
</page>
<page number="17">
<![CDATA[
with graphics on a computer for subsequent output to the
new generation of printing and typesetting machines.
What exactly is desktop publishing? Basically it is the
application of personal computers to the entire range of the
publishing process, from the typing in of the author's origi¬
nal copy to the final printing of the publication. It is a means
of producing documents, complete with graphics, ranging
from one-page information or advertising leaflets, through
brochures and price lists, to newsletters, magazines and even
books, on equipment which can comfortably be housed on a
reasonably large desk.
. The basic equipment, or "hardware", required consists of
a computer, complete with a visual display unit (screen), a
keyboard and a movement sensing device known as a mouse,
an optical scanner and a laser printer. The programs, or
"software", needed to operate the equipment consist of a
"page description language" which translates the image on
the computer screen into a set of digital instructions that the
laser printer can follow, and a composition program to drive
the entire system.
The advent of desktop publishing was as sudden as its
social and economic implications were profound. As recent¬
ly as 1970, the text sent by a publisher to a professional
printer would be set in "hot metal" by methods not funda¬
mentally different from those used by Gutenberg and Cax-
ton some 500 years earlier. By 1985, typesetting to profes¬
sional standards could be achieved in the office and in the
home.
Five key technical advances made this possible:
the development of a new generation of very powerful
personal computers;
the development of page description languages to drive
laser printers and phototypesetters;
the development of small, comparatively cheap laser
printers with a printing resolution (300 dots per inch) capa¬
ble of producing output of "publishable" quality;
the development of composition languages to drive the
whole desktop system which can easily be operated by users
with very little knowledge of computers, typesetting or
graphics;
the development of scanning devices which can "read"
photographs, drawings and previously typed or printed texts
and feed them into a computer where they can be modified as
required and incorporated into the document to be pro¬
duced.
Coupled with the development of new manufacturing
methods which have brought the price of this equipment
tumbling down (it is now possible to buy a complete desktop
publishing system for US $10,000 or less, and prices are still
falling), these technical advances constitute a revolution of
worldwide scope and importance.
Anyone who uses such equipment is, like Aldus Manutius
and the early printer-publishers, in a position to control the
entire publishing process, from initial selection of what is to
be printed, through input of text and graphics, to final
output of the printed page. Only rather rudimentary meth¬
ods of bookbinding are available to the desktop publisher,
however, and, as in the days of Aldus Manutius, quality
bookbinding is likely, for the time being, to remain a
separate domain.
Desktop publishing has swept away most of the barriers
that for centuries have stood between those who want to
publish and their potential readers. Composition programs
and page description languages have replaced the craft skills
of the printing process and handed back the choice of what is
to be published to the author.
A good desktop publishing package will offer a wide
choice of typeface styles and sizes, number of columns per
page, justified or unjustified text, automatic hyphenation of
words at the end of lines, insertion of graphics and automatic
flow of text around them, as well as automatic page number¬
ing and spelling checking.
There is nothing now to prevent the author of a specialist
or minority interest book that no publisher will handle
*&:&.'&/&.&!&&<&<£>:
4a
Left to right: inventively designed devices or
marks of 4 early European printers. William
Caxton (1422-1491): the printer's initials and
trade-mark; Robert Estienne (d. 1559): the
philosopher under the tree of knowledge;
Christophe Plantin (1514-1589): compass on
book; Aldus Manutius (1449-1515): anchor and
dolphin.
]]>
</page>
<page number="18">
<![CDATA[
These pages from Man Belongs to the Earth, a
new report on Unesco's Man and the Biosphere
(MAB) Programme, were prepared for the press
using the techniques of desktop publishing. The
.175-page report, published in English, was
written and compiled by Howard Brabyn and
Malcolm Hadley.
The basic equipment of a desktop publishing
system: computer, visual display unit, key¬
board, movement sensing device ("mouse"), and
printer. ,
SATELLITE
SENSING
I d* *«tW
bird's-eye view
SATEUITE SCMSJMG AfRUi. PHOTOGRAPH V - THE CAKOPV RAFT
Ai _C
because it might not be profitable, or of a potential literary
masterpiece whose merit is not immediately recognized,
from publishing it himself.
Clearly, because of the problems of storing and handling
the huge quantities of paper involved, the ordinary member
of the public will not be in a position to print more than a
few hundred copies of a brochure, a newsletter, or even a
short book. Nor will he or she have the organization to
distribute a daily newspaper or to handle sales of a book that
turns out to be a best-seller. For the time being at least this
will still be the domain of the major newspaper proprietors
and the publishers with their well organized bookselling
outlets.
Nor should it be forgotten that, despite the impressive
functions that desktop publishing software has to offer, the
layout and appearance of the printed page will depend upon
the skill and taste of the operator. Many of the basic rules of
good page design can be quickly learned, but these need to be
complemented by flair and practical experience.
The wider social, political and economic implications of
desktop publishing are equally profound. Censorship,
whether by governments or by powerful interest groups,
will be much more difficult if not impossible to impose.
Minority groups will find it easier to make their voices beard
and, with the development of electronic transmission, fron¬
tiers will no longer be effective barriers to information.
For the developing world the possibilities would appear to
be enormous:
It will no longer be necessary to fund the huge capital
investment involved in setting up a traditional printing
works and distribution network (a complete desktop pub¬
lishing package can be bought for as little as a quarter of the
cost of a single professional typesetting machine).
A three-month training course in desktop publishing will
replace the long and costly apprenticeship of the traditional
print craftsmen.
Costly distribution of books, newspapers, etc., over large
areas, often with an inadequate or non-existent road and rail
infrastructure, will be replaced by electronic transmission of
the material to be published, in print-ready form for local
printing.
The cost of school textbooks will plummet as will the cost
of revising and up-dating them. No wasteful stocks of
unused books will be built up since it will be much easier to
match local print runs to local demand.
Each area will be able, where necessary, to modify text¬
books to meet specific local needs.
The advantages are not limited to the developing world.
The desktop publishing revolution may well lead to the
creation of tbe first personalized, electronic newspapers
which would be transmitted directly to the home or office
for printing on a laser printer. Subscribers with home or
office computers and printers could indicate those subjects
that interest them most and these would be included in the
personalized newspapers that would be transmitted to them
at any time they cared to specify.
Charles Geschke, who with John Warnock pioneered one
of the earliest and most widely used page description lan¬
guages, recently declared: "One of my fantasies is to wake up
in the morning and have my automated clippings service
deliver me a sheaf of papers on my printer at home with
exactly the kind of articles that I would be interested in."
Such fantasies may well soon become reality. Thanks to
the desktop publishing revolution, news of what is happen¬
ing anywhere in the world will soon be instantly available.
Perhaps more important still, we will all one day have direct
access to the accumulated sum of human knowledge and
culture very much "faster than you can cook asparagus".»
HOWARD BRABYN, of the United Kingdom, is a Paris-based writer and
journalist with a special interest in the popularization of science. He was
formerly editor of the English edition of the Unesco Courier.
18
]]>
</page>
<page number="19">
<![CDATA[
Unesco
and the printed word
Over 8,000 titles have been published by
Unesco or under its auspices in over 70 lan¬
guages, since the founding of the Organiza¬
tion in 1946. Right, the latest edition oilndex
translationum, Unesco's annual guide to
world translations.
*""
'¿«mu
I The rural press in Africa
In Africa today only 15 out of\every 1,000
people are reached by daily newspapers, and
the use of the press as a medium of mass
communication presents many problems,
especially in the rural areas where 80 per cent
of the population lives and where over 800
languages are spoken. And yet the printed
media can play an important role by bridging
the communications gap which prevents iso¬
lated farming communities from taking full
part in national development programmes
and by providing excellent follow-up mate¬
rials in literacy teaching. For many years
Unesco has co-operated with Member States
in this field by helping to create rural news¬
papers, by training journalists and by provid¬
ing other forms of technical support. One
current undertaking, the West and Central
Africa News Agencies Development Project
(WANAD) based in Cotonou, Benin, is serv¬
ing 13 national news agencies. As part of its
activities WANAD, which was launched in
1984 by Unesco with finance from the Feder¬
al Republic of Germany, provides training
for journalists in the fields of international
relations, health, rural development and the
environment. A sister project, SEANAD,
was set up in 1986 in Southern and Eastern
Africa. Above right, front pages of rural
newspapers from 2 WANAD Member States:
issue of Kpodoga, published in the Ewe lan¬
guage by the Institute of Adult Education of
the University of Ghana; special Interna¬
tional Literacy Day (8 September 1987) issue
of Tew Fema, published in the Kabyie lan¬
guage of Togo.
I Children's books in Asia and the Pacific
Launched in 1970 by the Tokyo-based Asian
Cultural Centre for Unesco, the Asian/
Pacific Copublication Programme (ACP) is a
venture designed to provide children in
countries of Asia and the Pacific with reason¬
ably priced illustrated books. Good stories
and illustrations by authors and artists from
different countries are selected and published
in an English version. Participating coun¬
tries use this master edition (as well as films of
the colour illustrations, which are also pro¬
vided free) to produce editions in their own
languages. ACP books have so far been
translated into some 27 Asian languages and
more than 2.5 million copies have been
printed. Right, illustration from Folk Tales
from Asia for Children Everywhere (Book 6).
lynamiini
n« Cui »kI ihc Watt
"neico
I Practical training for publishers
As part of its efforts to stimulate book pub¬
lishing in the developing world, Unesco has
organized a number of regional training
courses for publishing personnel in Asia and
the Pacific, Latin America, Africa and the
Caribbean. Over 200 people attended these
courses in 1986 and 1987. During a 6-week
course jointly undertaken by Unesco and the
University of the Philippines Institute of
Mass Communication in December 1987,
participants were divided into 3 teams, each
of which was given a manuscript about rice
and asked to prepare it for publication as an
illustrated booklet. Each team had to edit the
manuscript, prepare it for typesetting, cor¬
rect proofs, lay out the text, design the cover,
and write publicity material. Left, the book¬
lets produced by the 3 teams.
IBook development in Latin America
The Regional Centre for Book Development
in Latin America and the Caribbean (CER-
LALC) was founded in Bogotá in 1971 by an
agreement between Unesco and the Govern¬
ment of Colombia. Participating countries
today are Argentina, Bolivia, Brazil, Chile,
Colombia, Costa Rica, the Dominican Re¬
public, Ecuador, El Salvador, Nicaragua,
Panama, Paraguay, Spain and Venezuela.
The Centre aims to promote the production
and distribution of books and to encourage
the reading habit, taking account of develop¬
ment programmes as well as the public and
school library systems in each country. In
addition to the professional training courses
which CERLALC organizes for publishing
personnel, it has launched a copublication
programme of children's books for Latin
America. The aim is to publish good-quality
children's literature at low prices by sharing
the production costs between all the partici¬
pating countries. The first title to be pub¬
lished was "Tales, Myths and Legends for
Latin-American Children", in an edition of
20,000 copies (above left, cover of the Portu¬
guese version). Today publishers from 15
countries are taking part in the programme,
and 6 titles have been published, totalling
(with reprints) 332,000 copies.
19
]]>
</page>
<page number="20">
<![CDATA[
Computerized typesetting
in China
BY XU LIAN-SHENG
THE technique of printing using mov¬
able type was invented by Bi Sheng
in China between 1041 and 1048 and
not, as is widely believed, by Johannes
Gutenberg in fifteenth-century Europe. The
type used by Bi Sheng was made of earthen¬
ware, but in later times in China it became
common to use wood, enamelware or metal.
With the development of movable lead type,
"hot metal" came to be used all over the
world for the mass production of printed
works.
The low cost of setting lead type, which
could be melted down after printing so that
the same metal was used over and over again,
made this technique the mainstay of the
printing industry for centuries. With the
rapid progress of photocomposition,
XU LIAN-SHENG, of China, is deputy director
of the Photosetting Centre of the China Research
Institute of Printing Science and Technology. He
also played a leading part in the design of China's
KY Microcomputer Photosetting System.
however, and especially the computerization
of typesetting in recent years, movable lead
type has inevitably become obsolete.
In China, setting movable type has always
been a complex and exhausting job because
of the huge number of characters in the
Chinese language. A typesetter has to walk
between five or six cases of type and reach
high and low in order to find and retrieve the
required pieces.
A modern version of this problem arises
with computerized typesetting. A regular
keyboard will suffice for entering into the
computer all the letters of Western lan¬
guages, but has far too few keys to enter the
thousands of Chinese characters.
Two methods can be used to solve the
problem. One is to make a large keyboard
with each key representing a Chinese charac¬
ter, the finding and entering of which are
done by an operator. The advantage of this
method is that the operator can see the char¬
acter to be keyed in. The disadvantage is that
the keyboard has to be very large and the
arrangement of the keys is extremely com¬
plicated. The operator takes a long time to
learn by heart the position of each character,
and searching among the mass of keys is a
laborious task.
The other method is to use a keyboard the
same size as that of a Western-language com¬
puter and enter each Chinese character by
striking more than one key in a certain pat¬
tern which reflects the construction of that
character. A number of systems have been
developed in accordance with this principle;
they all make use of either the vocal or the
written features of a given character.
An operator using the vocal method has to
transliterate the characters into the Chinese
Phonetic Alphabet and then key in the let¬
ters. For instance, to enter the word China,
which has two characters, the operator
strikes the letters making up the words
"Zhong Guo" (the phonetic pronunciation
of the word). The advantage of this method
20
]]>
</page>
<page number="21">
<![CDATA[
Cases of metal type in the composing room of a
daily newspaper in China. The Chinese writing
system, which is ideographic rather than
alphabetic, uses several thousand characters.
©
Drawing of Wang Chen's movable wooden type
printing process, developed in the late 13th cen¬
tury, some 250 years after Bi Sheng's invention
of movable type. Right, a compositor typeset¬
ting with characters ingeniously arranged in
revolving typecases to enable rapid retrieval.
Left, brushing the back of a sheet of paper to
take an impression from the inked printing
block.
Illustration from Science and Civilisation in China, Vol 5, Part 1,
by Tslen Tsuen-Hsuln and Joseph Needham © Cambridge Uni¬
versity Press, 1985
An operator working on one of the first com¬
puterized typesetters for the Chinese language,
the KY Microcomputer Photosetting System
developed at the China Research Institute of
Printing Science and Technology.
Photo © Xu Lian-Sheng/Chinese edition of the Unesco Courier,
Beijing
A Chinese typewriter. The tray contains some
2,500 characters individually cast in lead and
arranged face up. Above is a sheet of paper on a
roller, and the typing mechanism, which is
moved into position above the required charac¬
ter. The operator then pushes a lever which lifts
the character out of the tray and forces it
against the inked ribbon.
is that anyone who knows the correct pro¬
nunciation of the character to be keyed in
can operate the machine without previous
training. The disadvantage lies in the high
rate of duplicated codes due to the fact that
there are so many homophones in Chinese.
Various methods of text input make use of
written features. All Chinese characters can
be broken down into basic structural com¬
ponents, which are few in number. If these
components are properly arranged on a
keyboard, any Chinese character can be
keyed in by grouping them. For example, the
word Jlj (country) is composed of 3£ and
\_\ . Both the number of key strokes needed
to enter a character and the rate of possible
duplicated codes can be reduced to a fairly
low level if the breakdown of the compo¬
nents is correct. Furthermore, the operator
does not need to know how to pronounce
the character. This method is clearly useful
since there are so many local dialects in
China that sometimes people who live fif¬
teen kilometres apart cannot understand
each other.
One practice commonly used to increase
operating speed is the word-group method,
whereby the operator strikes a single key to
enter a frequently used word or phrase.
Another problem is that Chinese text may
be set either vertically or horizontally (in
some magazines articles are set both ways),
and a good composing system must be cap¬
able of meeting these requirements. What is
more, a number of Chinese magazines pub¬
lish articles containing words or passages in
foreign languages, and so we also need a
system which can set Western language texts
as well as those in Chinese.
With regard to output the generation by
the computer of text in the required for¬
mat the biggest problem is how to cope
with the mass of data involved in processing
a huge number of characters each of which,
for the computer, has an information con¬
tent many times higher than that of an En¬
glish letter. Various methods have thus been
devised for compressing this information
into abridged form so as to take up less of the
computer's memory. This is an area in which
there is a need for further study and develop¬
ment.
Computerized typesetting in the Chinese
language has already made remarkable prog¬
ress and, as it comes to replace metal type¬
setting, will surely play an increasingly
important role in the Chinese printing
industry.
Below, Chinese ideograms printed using mod¬
ern metal type, in different typestyles and sizes.
Bottom, the basic elements of Chinese script,
from which all ideograms are constructed.
Illustration from Science and Civilisation in China, Vol 5, Part 1,
by Tsien Tsuen-Hsuin and Joseph Needham © Cambridge Uni¬
versity Press, 1985
ä $ t m pu si
S ft fi W rji m
* M « W nu si
* Jt # m 1$ «
tt * ti- äi m w
r. M 9 M rr »
) ~7
/ ¡
Tj V
21
]]>
</page>
<page number="22">
<![CDATA[
The book situation in India
BY LOKENATH BHATTACHARYA
INDIA, which publishes about 20,000 titles annually, is
the eighth largest book producing country in the world.
With a healthy climate for authorship, democratic pol¬
icies and institutions, increasingly well-equipped printing
plants, availability of locally produced paper, editorial ex¬
pertise, a functioning network of distribution and a growing
community of readers, the country also has the largest
publishing infrastructure in the developing world.
According to a survey of the Indian book industry carried
out by the National Council of Applied Economic Research,
there are some 3,000 active publishers in India, including
about 100 large firms bringing out a minimum of 50 titles per
year. Educational publishing occupies the most prominent
place. Although the great bulk of publishing is in private
hands, about 450 agencies in the public sector are also active
in this field. In fact, the central government has emerged as
India's largest single publishing agency, and now accounts
for about 20 per cent of the country's book production.
The problems of authorship and publishing in India
should be seen against a background of enormous linguistic
and ethnic diversity. Fifteen major languages are recognized
by the Constitution as national languages. They are, al¬
phabetically, Assamese, Bengali, Gujarati, Hindi, Kannada,
Kashmiri, Malayalam, Marathi, Oriya, Punjabi, Sanskrit,
Sindhi, Tamil, Telugu and Urdu. All these are independent
languages, not dialects or variations of another language, and
most of them have quite extensive literatures of their own.
Each is spoken by millions of people.
In addition to the major languages and a few others such as
Dogri, Konkani, Maithili, Manipuri, Nepali and Rajasthani
which, though not as important, are still spoken by large
numbers of people, there are nearly 400 tribal mother
tongues in India, most of them with no written literature at
all. The problem of scripts, too, is almost as complex. The
eleven major script systems, used in addition to the Perso-
Arabic and Roman, are Nagari, Bengali, Assamese, Manipu¬
ri, Oriya, Telugu, Kannada, Tamil, Malayalam, Gujarati and
Gurumukhi.
Then there is the oral tradition, the majestic presence of
the spoken word, which even today is far from being
superseded. "Talking" books, as opposed to written ones,
are still a familiar sight. Wandering minstrels board a train or
gather in village fairs, and keep an audience spellbound with
what they recount or chant. Even to this day, busy market¬
places in cities like Calcutta undergo a magical transforma¬
tion in the evening when groups of people assemble to listen
to an episode of the Ramayana or the Mahabharata.
The following figures give some idea of literary activities
in the major Indian languages, as well as works written in
English by Indian authors. In one recent year, India pro¬
duced a total of 21,265 titles 77 in Assamese, 1,302 in
Bengali, 10,438 in English, 972 in Gujarati, 2,633 in Hindi,
306 in Kannada, 595 in Malayalam, 1,514 in Marathi, 322 in
Oriya, 597 in Punjabi, 177 in Sanskrit, 910 in Tamil, 817 in
Telugu, 352 in Urdu and 253 in other languages. Around 33
per cent of the tptal were literary works (except in the case of
22
]]>
</page>
<page number="23">
<![CDATA[
LOKENATH BHATTACHARYA, Bengali poet and essayist, is a former
Director of the National Book Trust of India. He is the author of a Unesco
publication, Books and Reading in India, and of The Prose Poems of
Lokenath Bhattacharya (1972) and The Drum of the Guru (1979).
English, in which creative writing is negligible in India).
There is also the fact that less than 7 per cent of India's total
population know an Indian language other than their own
mother tongue although, since major language speakers are
not solely confined to specific areas or towns, all the States
and Union territories are multi-lingual.
Hindi, because of the numbers of people who speak it, has
been declared the official language of the country and every
effort is being made to promote its development and use at
the national level. The yearly output of publishing in Hindi
is second only to that in English.
Proficiency in English, instead of hindering the growth
and richness of expression in all the major Indian languages,
has significantly contributed to it. Today, India ranks as the
world's third largest producer of books in English, after the
United States of America and the United Kingdom.
The principal factors governing publishing activities in a
country are its literacy rate, the size and nature of its
educated population and since textbooks and other allied
supplementary reading material are the mainstay of the book
trade, especially in a developing country its educational
policies and programmes. While literacy and reading habits
are nowhere synonymous, literacy remains the first pre¬
requisite for the growth of a reading programme.
The last Indian census taken in 1981 shows the country's
literacy rate to be about 37 per cent, registering an increase of
nearly 7 per cent over the previous figures of 1971. This
4 Browsers at a New Delhi bookstall
Typesetting by hand at the Kerala Times in the
industrial town of Ernakulam in the State of
Kerala, southwest India. According to the latest
(1987) edition of Unesco's Statistical Yearbook,
there were 1,334 daily newspapers in India in
1984, with an estimated total circulation of
almost 15 million.
23
]]>
</page>
<page number="24">
<![CDATA[
Engrossed in a book, a traveller waits for his
train on Howrah station, Calcutta.
increase does not mean that there has been an appreciable fall
in the number of illiterates in the country. On the contrary,
due to a considerable expansion of population figures during
the decade, India's illiterate population has increased by as
many as 48 million.
This partly explains an apparent paradox. Despite the fact
that India is one of the leading book producing countries, its
per capita publishing figures remain far below the world
average. Similarly, the consumption of books per person per
year is as little as 32 pages in India, as against an average of
2,000 pages in the industrially advanced countries. As re¬
gards print-runs, the Indian average still lags far behind the
international average books in Indian languages rarely ex¬
ceed a print-run of 1,000 copies, while those in English do
rather better with print-runs of between 1,000 and 2,000
copies.
This notwithstanding, the progress achieved in recent
years, especially since Independence, gives grounds for opti¬
mism about the future of printing and publishing in India.
Today, India's printing industry is on the threshold of a
revolution as an increasing number of printers are switching
from hand composition to mechanical or photographic type¬
setting with high-grade equipment. However, the over¬
whelming majority of printing presses operative in India are
still letterpress, the rest being sheet-fed offset litho machines,
mostly single colour. While much of this equipment is
imported, India has now started to manufacture a wide
variety of presses, offset as well as letterpress.
Considering that Gutenberg's epoch-making invention,
introduced to India in 1557 by a Jesuit missionary, took only
a little over a hundred years to reach the country in an age
when communications were much slower than today, it
seems likely that new technologies will take a fraction of that
time to spread not only through the big towns, but to the
rural areas. Already, desktop publishing is making inroads,
with the introduction of personal computers and laser
printers.
Moreover, publishing has been introduced as a course of
study in several Indian universities, and there are in-service
training facilities for editorial and production personnel.
Various professional institutions, in the public as well as the
private sectors, offer annual awards and other material bene¬
fits to encourage good writing and excellence in printing.
Book fairs and exhibitions are now held all over the country,
and increasing numbers of books are being translated from
one Indian language to another.
Magazines pour from the press at a modern
printing plant at Faridabad, 40 km south of
Delhi. According to Unesco's Statistical Year¬
book, India consumed 388,000 tonnes of news¬
print, printing and writing paper in 1984, more
than twice as much as in 1970.
24
]]>
</page>
<page number="25">
<![CDATA[
1W<^
~
Os
a*
First impressions
Arabic early printed texts
BY CAMILLE ABOUSSOUAN
Above, early 17th-century punches for making
Arabic type, designed by Lebanese craftsmen at
the Maronite College of Rome. They were
brought to France in 1614 by the French diplo¬
mat and ambassador to Rome, François Savary
de Brèves, who intended to set up an "Oriental
Languages Printing House", and are today pre¬
served in the Imprimerie Nationale, Paris.
CAMILLE ABOUSSOUAN, Lebanese writer and diplomat, was formerly
his country's permanent delegate to Unesco and vice-chairman of Unesco's
Executive Board. A bibliophile specializing in works ofthe 16th, 17th and 18th
centuries, he is the author ofmany studies on the history of Lebanon and the
Near East. This article is an abridged version ofan essay which appeared in Le
livre et le Liban jusqu'à 1900, a work published under Mr. Aboussouan's
direction to accompany an exhibition, held at Unesco's Paris HQ in 1982, on
the history of the book in Lebanon.
ARABIC characters made their first appearance in a
printed book in 1486, when a Dominican monk
named Martin Roth printed at Erhard Reuwich's
workshop in Mainz the famous account of the "Voyage and
Pilgrimage Overseas to the Holy Sepulchre of the Holy City
of Jerusalem, written and recorded in Latin by Bernhard von
Breydenbach". In this original work, the narrative is in¬
terwoven with novel descriptions of scenes from urban life.
Erhard Reuwich is thought to have drawn and engraved the
plates in this book, which contains the first example of a
complete Arabic alphabet in a printed work, together with a
Latin transliteration, a map of Jerusalem and a charming
engraving showing Lebanese, dubbed Syrians, in a vineyard,
and wearing magnificent turbans.
This, however, was only the reproduction of an Arabic
alphabet. It was not until the reconquest of Granada several
years later that the need for a printed Arabic text arose in
Europe. In 1492, the last Muslim kingdom of Andalusia fell
to the Spanish Catholic sovereigns Ferdinand and Isabella,
25
]]>
</page>
<page number="26">
<![CDATA[
1.
Left, title page of the polyglot Psalter, in Latin,
Hebrew, Greek, Arabic and Chaldean (a form of
Syriac), published by the Genoese Oriental
scholar, Agostino Giustiniani, in 1516. Below,
this flowered "aleph" (the first letter in the
Arabic alphabet) from the Psalter is one of the
first ornamental letters in Arabic printing.
, l »_. r .. rt ï -! \>' a -«
The Arabic alphabet from "The art of learning
the rudiments of the Arabic language" (1505), a
textbook by the Spanish scholar Pedro de Alca¬
lá. Each Arabic character is transcribed into the
Latin alphabet, which is printed in a Gothic
typeface.
The printing works of the University of St.
Joseph has been Beirut's biggest since it was
established in the 19th century. Below, as de¬
picted in an old engraving.
"Of*"
Medal struck by the Paris Mint to commemo¬
rate an exhibition on the history of the book in
Lebanon, held at Unesco's Paris HQ in 1982.
The medal depicts the monastery of St.
Anthony at Qazhayya, in Lebanon, where the
first printing establishment in the Arab world
was founded around 1610. Photo © Paris Mint'
3
©
26
]]>
</page>
<page number="27">
<![CDATA[
Ifia. ôiU JE>il. Ha. k l&a. tea«
Gulf. ©utf. ©a. JE>a. £a. 2X jfe
.3 SIC l^U\f \J
IRim. tlföim. Xltbiin. flfcím. 3Lim. JLím. ©uifV
0|^Mj°|J|JJ^
»& #£. ©ad. JDad. jad. $ad. «un*
-£ he hHlctí
Ctf. íc ^e, Ä. 6S& Í5at. Ate
ß>e. Be. Am. *in. si». $m. £af.
ye. XcmflLf.Ä.emälif.Zemälif.0iicu. Ifóc, ¡be,
ye ye.
Ct(loeronloecaratcre0rnotib:c6DcUo j c
laraearaoígap.laaqualcotodao fe puede J l^-^
rnplirci5m'¿iolctraelatínaoocaftdlan9e.6 manera pliega
lücoinuiialSíiramanoíJtncccfTida^ oelaefabcnii conoce»
c ily
who had by their marriage united the two powerful king¬
doms of Aragon and Castile. Anxious to bring the Andalu-
sians back to Christianity, the Spanish rulers ordered mis¬
sionaries to evangelize the country again. It soon became
apparent that this goal could not be attained without using
the Arabic language. In 1505, Archbishop Fernando de
Talavera, the first prelate appointed to the new diocese, had
two Arabic textbooks printed for use by missionaries who
could not speak that language. The title of the first was: Arte
para ligeramente saber la lengua araviga ("The art of learn¬
ing the rudiments of the Arabic language"); that of the
second: Vocabulista aravigo en letra castellana ("Arab glos¬
sary in Castilian characters"). Their author, the scholar
Pedro de Alcalá, a native of the prestigious university city of
Alcalá de Henares near Madrid, wrote them in Latin script.
The typeface is Gothic.
The first twenty-one pages of the Arte are given over to
grammar, and the next twenty-seven consist of Catholic
prayers in Arabic, instructions for confession in Spanish and
in Arabic, the ordinary of the mass, and instructions for
votive masses, all in Arabic. By way of introduction to the
vocabulary, a short three-page note explains the author's
method of transcription: the vocabulary is in alphabetical
order, but under each letter three separate categories contain
first verbs, then nouns and lastly adverbs, conjunctions and
prepositions. The verbs are given in three forms: present,
perfect and imperative; nouns are given in both the singular
and the plural.
This work, which is a curiosity in the history of both
linguistics and typography, is also the first and perhaps the
most practical of all attempts to transcribe Arabic into Latin
characters. The alphabet on the twentieth page is in north
African script, and the language taught in both of Pedro de
Alcalá's works is the vernacular, which the Spanish mis¬
sionaries needed to communicate with the converted Moors.
In a few places, the author indicates differences between this
and the written language.
As in Breydenbach's book, the Arabic alphabet is thus
reproduced, together with its Latin pronunciation, but it is
transcribed from the Maghrebian calligraphy also found in
Agostino Giustiniani's magnificent Psalterium Hebraeum,
Graecum, Arabicum, et Chaldaicum, the first polyglot Psal¬
ter, which was published in 1516 at Genoa (then a major
printing and paper manufacturing centre) in five languages:
Hebrew, Greek, Arabic, Chaldean (Syriac) and Latin.
Agostino Giustiniahi (1479-1536) belonged to the Ge¬
noese branch of the Giustiniani, one of the great families of
northern Italy. A Dominican who became the bishop of
Nebbio in Corsica, he was a learned student of Oriental
languages and a friend of great humanists such as Pico della
Mirándola, Erasmus and Sir Thomas More.
Giustiniani was the author of an audacious project to
publish a polyglot edition of the Bible in Hebrew, Greek,
Arabic, Syriac and Latin, which would make known all
existing versions of the Bible and enable them to be com¬
pared, while also serving as an instrument for studying these
languages. He began with the Psalter, and when this was not
a commercial success, the project was abandoned. Even so, it
was a remarkable achievement for the time.
The preparation of this masterly work was an arduous
task, as Giustiniani noted in his dedication to Pope Leo X,
who had written the preface: "Our work has been long ...".
This can easily be imagined. At that time no matrices or fonts
of Arabic type existed; the alphabets in the books of Brey-
denbach and Pedro de Alcalá were printed from woodcuts,
and there were few Hebrew typefaces. Moreover, the work
had to be revised by several proof-readers with knowledge of
at least three non-European languages.
It seems that Giustiniani had already ordered and tran¬
scribed the texts to be published as early as 1506. It is more
than likely that the design and casting of the characters had
been done long before the publication of the Psalter, which
thus pushes back even further the creation of the first printed
text in movable Arabic type.
The Arabic text alone occupies a forty-one-line column
containing an average of 160 words per page for 246 pages.
The two examples of initial letters in Arabic which appear in
the book are very beautiful a flowered "aleph" in a frame
and a "tah" similarly adorned. These are certainly the first
ornamental letters in Arabic printing.
In 1529, Master Geofroy Tory, a French typographer,
engraver and author from Bourges, published his fine treatise
on typography, the Champfleury (see page 11), in which he
attacked the use of the Gothic typeface, and included an
Arabic alphabet with a key to its pronunciation. Meanwhile,
the German, Latin and Spanish editions of Breydenbach, and
its French translation by Nicolas le Huen, regularly repro¬
duced the Arabic alphabet of the 1486 edition, as did Sébas¬
tien Mamerot's work entitled "The journeys overseas of the
noble Godefroy de Bouillon who was King of Jerusalem. Of
the good King Saint Louis and of several virtuous princes",
which was published in the late fifteenth century.
In 1538, the French humanist Guillaume Postel, who had
accompanied the embassy sent by King François I to Con¬
stantinople, and who styled himself "The Cosmopolitan", or
"Citizen of the World" as we should say nowadays, publish¬
ed his "Arabic Grammar" in Paris, the first of its kind to be
printed.
27
]]>
</page>
<page number="28">
<![CDATA[
«L'ENCYCLOPEDIE »
An eighteenth-century best-seller
AS soon as the first volume of the first edition of the
supreme work of the Enlightenment, Diderot's En¬
cyclopédie, reached the subscribers, in 1751, it be¬
came apparent to the authorities in France that the book was
dangerous.
It did not merely provide information about everything
from A to Z; it recorded knowledge according to philoso¬
phic principles expounded by d'Alembert, the co-editor, in
his "Preliminary Discourse". Although he formally ac¬
knowledged the authority of the Church, d'Alembert made
it clear that knowledge came from the senses and not from
Rome or Revelation. The great ordering agent was reason,
which combined sense data, working with the sister faculties
of memory and imagination. Thus everything man knew
derived from the world around him and the operations of his
own mind.
The Encyclopédie made the point graphically, with an
engraving of a tree of knowledge showing how all the arts
and sciences grew out of the three mental faculties. Philoso¬
phy formed the trunk of the tree, while theology occupied a
remote branch, next to black magic. Thus Diderot and
d'Alembert presented their work as both a compilation of
information and a manifestation of philosophie. They meant
to merge those two aspects of the book, to make them seem
like two sides of the same coin: Encyclopedism; and the men
behind it became known not merely as collaborators but as
Encyclopedists. Traditional learning, they implied, amount¬
ed to nothing but prejudice and superstition.
So beneath the bulk of the Encyclopédie's twenty-eight
folio volumes and the enormous variety of its 71,818 articles
and 2,885 plates lay an epistemológica! shift that transformed
the topography of everything known to man.
The Encyclopédie was a product of its time, of mid-
eighteenth-century France, when writers could not discuss
social and political questions openly, in contrast to the
prerevolutionary era, when a tottering government permit¬
ted a good deal of frank discussion. The book's radical
element did not come from any prophetic vision of the
far-off French and industrial revolutions but from its at¬
tempt to map the world of knowledge according to new
boundaries, determined by reason and reason alone. As its
title page proclaimed, it claimed to be a "dictionnaire raison¬
né des sciences, des arts et des métiers" that is, to measure
all human activity by rational standards and so to provide a
basis for rethinking the world.
Contemporaries had no difficulty in detecting the purpose
of the book, which its authors acknowledged openly in key
articles. Diderot and d'Alembert had laid out such pleasant
paths through the arid expanses of knowledge that one could
merely follow their lead, stopping now and then to enjoy the
flowers along the way, and still have the satisfaction of
belonging to the intellectual vanguard. One did not even
have to read many other books, for the Encyclopédie was a
library unto itself. The editors did not list the works that it
rendered obsolete, but anyone who consulted its Discours
préliminaire would have no difficulty in distinguishing be¬
tween the heavy tomes of traditional learning and the stream¬
lined, modern model. From the appearance of the first
volume in 1751 until the great crisis of 1759,1 the Encyclopé¬
die was denounced by defenders of the old orthodoxies and
the Old Régime, by Jesuits, Jansenists, the General Assemb¬
ly of the Clergy, the Parlement of Paris, the king's council,
and the pope. The denunciations flew so thick and fast, in
articles, pamphlets, and books as well as official edicts, that
the Encyclopédie seemed doomed. But the publishers had
invested a fortune in it, and they had powerful protectors,
notably Chrétien-Guillaume de Lamoignon de Malesherbes,
the liberal Directeur de la librairie, who superintended the
book trade during the crucial years between 1750 and 1763.
The scandal continued to sizzle and spread as volumes 3 to
7 appeared and as skilful polemicists like Charles Palissot and
Jacob-Nicolas Moreau fanned the flames on the side of the
priests. On the other side, Voltaire loaned his pen and his
prestige to the cause; and Diderot and d'Alembert found the
ranks of their collaborators swelling with other illustrious
writers, including most of the men who were beginning to be
28
]]>
</page>
<page number="29">
<![CDATA[
BY ROBERT DARNTON
Copyright © 1979 by the President and
Fellows of Harvard College
ROBERT DARNTON, ofthe USA, is Davis Professor ofEuropean History
at Princeton University, New Jersey. He is the author of several books on
French cultural history, including The Literary Underground of the Old
Regime (1982), The Great Cat Massacre: And other Episodes in French
Cultural History (1986) and The Business of Enlightenment a Publishing
History of the Encyclopédie, 1775-1800 (Harvard University Press, 1979),
from which this article has been extracted.
Volumes from the 18th-century French Encyc¬
lopédie, ou dictionnaire raisonné des sciences, des
arts et des métiers ("Encyclopedia, or Classified
Dictionary of Sciences, Arts and Trades"),
edited and published by Denis Diderot and Jean
d'Alembert. The original large-format folio edi¬
tion (1751-1772) consisted of 17 volumes of text
and 11 volumes of plates.
identified as philosophes: Duelos, Toussaint, Rousseau, Tur-
got, Saint-Lambert, d'Holbach, Daubenton, Marmontel,
Boulanger, Morellet, Quesnay, Damilaville, Naigeon, Jau-
court, and Grimm. They also claimed Montesquieu and
Buffon, whose works they cited constantly, though it seems
that neither wrote anything expressly for the Encyclopédie.
Nothing could have been better for business than the
continued controversy and the volunteer corps of authors.
The publishers had envisaged a first edition of 1,625 copies,
but the subscriptions poured in so fast that they increased it
three times, until it reached 4,255 copies in 1754.
The Encyclopédie became smaller in size and cheaper in
price as it progressed from edition to edition.2 While the
format shrank from folio to quartp and octavo, the sub¬
scription price fell and the size of the print-runs increased.
Having satisfied the "quality market", the publishers tried to
reach a broader public by producing in quantity.
The "democratization" of the Encyclopédie had limits,
First page of the alphabetical entries in the first
edition of the Encyclopédie.
ENCYCLOPEDIE,
O U
DICTIONNAIRE RAISONNÉ
DES SCIENCES,
DES ARTS ET DES MÉTIERS-
A A
K \K
t& e.f.m. {trdft EmtyioftJ.
IwW. Stitact di f komme ,
Itftmwt , A't 4* (MiMwf«r,
Ci*mm. j cM*A*ft ou km
d* I» pteminc letite de l'Al¬
phabet , tu lâiin. en fiant,'1" .
ht tu prefqut to«« 1« Lan-
(¡«et i.- 1 \ ; -'.
Onptut c jrsfidetft ee »IK-
. eu tant que lent« , «A le ligne A* (on a ,
qui de tout Im Cm« de k **« cfl W pta fxile à
witaiir U M Um qu'ouvm I» bouche de pojíti
[ut -Li poumont.
On ¿* q»; '* ***** Tj't/4 .!« llcbreui: «wit
r j en not qne fou ne vient que de U ton lotir» tt^n
«kl otganctdc U parole i ic le tuiûcte on f*pnta
¿mm noue nout ferrant p«« itpreTenitt c« ion «
noutvitnt de IWaAa dti OtHB. 1 rt Luiat Ac let
MM pauptei de iTurnpc. ou imité le» Gre« dan«
I ; rotenc H'i'iU o« douait i celte lettic. Selon let
OntHBJÉni rlcraiiquet, te liC.iunnwic grnetitt
de P- R. p. 11. fuJr/u ne/fi ( lojOMttfnui ) ta'ffwr
t~t('n*'t f âr H4*n*ifem **/ feJaw aV U+tytllt mi M
tftf0t*ti\ i>li fail »oil «fie U rvcuemeii'ion dci let*
Irrt eft £u|«fí à vuiitk* dint d« Lenguct mrtitt ,
tontuaa elk fe* dam leí (.»çuet »"«« Cm il r*
eouftant , felón M UfAwf« 1< H. ILwcrgaftt ,qut
l'a/i/t fe piononçok tuitrf»* tMM mi*tr a , fe
OU"lL| TT im ene ftttIOtlT p» It [> »ll .'.,'( .1'F.rl ffh* , /*/.,-.
¿V. lív X. t. *j. ow ce l\ foultet, t ft« I« » Guía «m
ti Iciiret del HrKr-i; /,' cv tiu<¿ f*g*-
'rfptltM.-ent entfi imttíigii, (/»V
j'aun waananenr i'fvtF Qtud *mitm\t¡
' mmn (ÇmmmtUm} ew»,eiil>t
let mile» fp.it
!.
iuiciJirk f.fl J; ïj.qnitûûpii , ,ci ; Je
mi , & leí fillet le fon de \'t , premíete votelk de
ftm'i** : nuil t'tft une imagnWtflon fin* fontfeinent.
Quand let enf»m litMcnt tu monde ( ti que putW
It [ttniíit fait ill p <«iUn' Tait del ponmonij on
enten«! le fon de datfrrutret vorfiel , Mon qnMi
onvtcnt fUf on omÎm U bouvkt.
On du en f«wd À , ne ^ffrt e : mA * eft du ^( rt«
ip*&.i!ia , eunme Ut «wie« mjelU» de ckhic *l-
Le fo« defrf, «ttflî Wn^tte xiloide f«, et long
enectuim mwtl , eV bt.f en J'»u-rci; 4e(ltoof¿d«M
grJee , At bit fcUtn n|nM. Il U>. ij dit» idiAe qjunnd
ce mot fi^mne nn onv>*fje eju'on donne i like; Ai
il cil ber* dam Uth/ , mainU , foitillme. Il vA long
(Uni ».xi*, £iot chien; A: hrvfdtnt «Mflnt nremiti«
pHtic du r»u - ffw/narAM ImHI dtidPfjftJté
é»M.CAmU4*Ql
Ici Ronuiai, notu muquee Te lont* , Veíiinhent
JJi t.l dtxil>e , A.-U paw í/.'¿ ; i'iA nidi qu'on
tioa*e de«* nnt mcWm Antroii F.h.cuh **gi , fit-
Enfuit» lit iniéiettiM t» e emit kt dent n , .***/**
Enfin ili mtituum qtKlqncfou U figne ut U ftlitb«
lowrM, îj'j.
On met MJinufJlini un litem ùttoiulrft fur J"*
long , *a lien dc 1/qn'on èenroet »rrafott iruci ttt
« : m .it ta Htu iTécine mdßix , M*fmt , «/m » «V***
on i < r » mJifa , J/daw, due. Mut il ne faut pel croen
tree U plupart del Giunnument , OU« not ptitt
nVciivoM-iH (rtte /tpièt l'a , ou unce toute aulla
voyelle , qu*¿ pom mieqocí out rette voyant eeoie
longac: Ib ¿etiToMnt («le /. t*** q^'iU It pío-
nunfoiftv, et rent pranonciaiioM e* encoin an «¡Tift
dam not P.-ovintci ntcndkuvilcl, ou fön ptononet
tKif'n. tljlly í(/íti..
mtt point d'aoccnt fur la biff OU e nmmon
La fK,i tr* R w-iint rw« app- lU Umt f*Lunt ;
Jjutrj/. . |l t- fit; t chh Uilhpi'il
l igiáUt et'jlu jusIic «a dc cvfM*ow«t on »tfuie , let
©
29
]]>
</page>
<page number="30">
<![CDATA[
Sm
A/ '
od
©
Imprimerie ai Letíraí , t.;>,*
Plate from the Encyclopédie showing operations
in the composing room of a printing shop. Top
left, a compositor transfers metal type (such as
the letter "S" and the different-sized blank
spaces for separating words shown in 1) from
typecase to composing stick (2) to make a line.
Top centre, another compositor moves a line to
a tray or "galley" of type where, with other lines
(3) it forms part of a page. Top right, a third
compositor has locked two pages of type inside a
metal frame and is levelling the printing surface
ready for the press.
however, because even the cheapest edition would have
seemed expensive to the common people. The book re¬
mained beyond the purchasing power of peasants and arti¬
sans, even though some of them may have consulted it in
cabinets littéraires (reading clubs).
Diderot and his collaborators had done their share of the
work, but that was only the beginning of a long process
which culminated around 1780 with the reproduction and
distribution of their copy on a mass scale throughout Eu¬
rope. The text that reached the general reading public, if not
the masses, differed somewhat from theirs, however, because
it, too, suffered from the strains of the production process.
In his prospectus for the quarto edition (1777-1779),
Joseph Duplain, a Lyonnais bookseller who managed the
enterprise, had promised not only to reprint the original text
in its entirety but also to improve it in three ways: to correct
its numerous typographical and factual errors; to add a great
deal of new material; and to blend the four folio volumes of
the Supplément3 into it. He never intended to produce a
literal copy of the first folio edition but rather to create a
superior version of itor at least to persuade the public that
he had done so. The correcting, augmenting and blending
would require a great deal of editorial work, so the contracts
provided for a rédacteur. Duplain gave this job to the Abbé
Jean-Antoine de Laserre, an Qratorian priest and a minor
literary figure in Lyons-. Laserre therefore became the suc¬
cessor of Diderot and the intermediary through which Dide¬
rot's text reached most of its readers in the eighteenth
century.
For the most part he left the text alone, not because he
respected it but because he did not have time to make
changes. He worked at a furious pace, cutting out references
to the eight volumes of plates that were not to be included in
the quarto, attaching snippets from the Suppléments to the
main body of the book by bits of his own prose, and reading
over the final amalgam of printed and manuscript copy that '
was to be mailed out to the printers. As a half dozen printing
shops were working on different volumes at the same time,
he could hardly keep up with their demand for copy.
Having sent for copy, presses, type, ink, paper, ink-ball
leathers, candles, quills, imposing stones, galleys, chases, and
a hundred other articles, the printing shop needed men to put
Plate from the Encyclopédie showing machinery
used to wash out impurities from iron ore.
30
]]>
</page>
<page number="31">
<![CDATA[
©
Portraits of some of the "Encyclopedists" sur¬
round this scene in the Procope café in Paris, a
well-known meeting place for literary figures.
Anti-clockwise from top left: Buffon, Gilbert,
Diderot, d'Alembert, Marmontel, Le Kain,
Jean-Baptiste Rousseau, Voltaire, Piron and
d'Holbach.
the matter in motion. It ordered the workers pretty much as
it ordered the equipment and ran into the same problems of
supply and demand. But it also had to cope with the
peculiarities of printers as human beings. They had no notion
of joining a firm. Instead, they worked by the job, coming
and going according to the availability of tasks and their own
inclination. For printing was a tramping trade. Men went
where they could find work, even if they had to hike
hundreds of kilometres. When work abounded, they some¬
times changed jobs in order to collect travel money or simply
by "caprice", as they put it. They came and went at a furious
pace during the Encyclopédie boom, which sent repercus¬
sions throughout the migratory circuits of France, Swit¬
zerland, and parts of Germany, producing as much competi¬
tion for workers as for paper.
Psychologically, nonstandardized work must have differ¬
ed considerably from the kind of work that was then being
imposed on the labouring classes in England. The pace of
work in the factories was set by clocks and bells, by the
opening and closing of gates, by fines and beatings, and
ultimately by the production process itself; for later, in
assembly-line production, the men were reduced to "hands",
and work streamed past them in an endless, undifferentiated
flow. The compositors and pressmen worked at their own
pace. They exerted some control over their production.
Some mastery over the production process did not mean
that the workers developed any special affection for the real
masters of it. The bourgeois retained most of the power and
manipulated it brutally, by hiring and firing, while the
workers responded with the few devices at their disposal.
Although they may have felt some pride in their craft, they
took shortcuts and compromised on quality when it made
labour easier. The results can be seen in any copy of the
Encyclopédie todayclear, crisp typography for the most
part, but margins askew here, pages misnumbered there,
uneven register, unsightly spacing, typographical errors, and
smudges all of them testimony to the activity of anony¬
mous artisans two centuries ago.
In the era of the handmade book there existed a ty
pographical consciousness that disappeared sometime after
the advent of automatic typesetting and printing. Like their
forerunners of the Renaissance, the compositors of the
Encyclopédie made lines by transferring type from cases to
composing sticks; they made pages by moving lines from the
composing sticks to galleys; and they made formes by
imposing the pages in a chase. Gompositorial practices could
go no further in the direction of speed and efficiency until
the introduction of mechanization, in the form of cold-metal
typesetting machines during the 1820s, Linotype in the
1880s, and electronic composition today. Presswork, too,
did not advance by any great leaps forward in technology
before the adoption of the cylinder press from 1814 and
steam power in the 1830s. The Encyclopédie was printed on
the venerable common press, in essentially the same way that
books had been printed for the previous two or three
hundred years.
A whole world had to be set into motion to bring the book
into being. Ragpickers, financiers, and philosophers all
played a part in the making of a work whose corporeal
existence corresponded to its intellectual message. As a
physical object and as a vehicle of ideas, the Encyclopédie
synthesized a thousand arts and sciences; it represented the
Enlightenment, body and soul.
1 . In January 1 759, the procureur general of the Parlement of Paris warned that behind
the Encyclopédie hovered a conspiracy to destroy religion and undermine the State. The
Parlement promptly banned its sale and appointed a commission to investigate it. But
authority over the printed word in France belonged to the king. On 8 March 1759, the
Conseil d'Etat reaffirmed the king's authority by revoking the book's privilege and
forbidding the publishers to continue it. The Encyclopédie went onto the Index
librorum prohibitorum, the list of books banned by the Roman Catholic Church, on 5
March, 1759, and on 3 September Pope Clement XII warned all Catholics who owned
it to have it burned by a priest or to face excommunication.
2. In addition to the six versions of Diderot's basic text (three reprints of the original
folio edition, one quarto and one octavo edition), totalling almost 24,000 copies before
1789, there were two quite different works that used it as a point of departure: Felice.'s
Encyclopédie d'Yverdon, printed between 1770 and 1780 at 1,600 copies, and Panck-
oucke's Encyclopédie méthodique, begun in 1 782 at a print-run of approximately 5,000
copies.
3. The Supplément, in four folio volumes of text and one of plates, was published in
Paris and Amsterdam in 1776 and 1777, in a print-run of 5,250 copies. It had no formal
connection with the original Encyclopédie and involved a new group of contributors
and publishers.
31
]]>
</page>
<page number="32">
<![CDATA[
Printing and society
in China and the West
BY TSIEN TSUEN-HSUIN
Copyright © 1985,
Cambridge University Press
OFall the products from the ancient
world, few can compare in signif¬
icance with the Chinese inven¬
tions of paper and printing.
Paper was invented in China some time
before the Christian era. From early in the
second century AD its manufacture became
improved, using new materials and superior
techniques. By the third century it had be¬
come widely used in China itself and had
begun to migrate across the Chinese bor¬
ders; it reached the Western world only just
prior to the modern age. Printing from
wood blocks was first practised by the Chi¬
nese around 700 AD, and movable type was
used several centuries earlier than Guten¬
berg. Even the indelible ink of lampblack,
which has been manufactured in the West
under the misnomer "Indian Ink", can be
traced back to Antiquity in Chinese civi¬
lization. It was the introduction of these
ingenious elements that made possible mass
production of written records for wide
circulation.
Paper was not invented expressly for
writing, as has often been presumed. It was
extensively used in China in the fine and
decorative arts, at ceremonies and festivals,
for business transactions and records, mon¬
etary credit and exchange, personal attire,
household furnishings, sanitary and medical
purposes, recreations and entertainments. It
was not used for writing until perhaps early
in the first century AD, and even then did
not entirely replace the more cumbersome
bamboo and wood slips as the chief materi¬
als for making books until the third century.
But when it came, the use of paper enabled
books to be cheaper and more portable,
though their extensive production and wide
distribution was not possible until the in¬
vention of printing.
There is a long history of pre-printing
techniques in China, including the use of
seals for stamping on clays and later on silk
and paper, of stencils to duplicate designs on
textiles and paper, and of the inked impres¬
sions taken from stone inscriptions. All
these processes gradually led to more effi¬
cient methods of the mechanical multiplica¬
tion of copies and to printing. Movable type
was introduced by the middle of the elev-
The invention of papermaking is traditionally
attributed to Tshai Lun, a Chinese court official
who developed the idea of forming a sheet of
paper from the macerated bark of trees, hemp
waste, and rags.' In the 18th-century picture,
above, Tshai Lun is shown surrounded by 4
attendants and with brushes and writing tools
before him. In foreground are a pig and a chick¬
en. According to legend these animals were the
first to separate the wet paper sheets with snout
or beak.
Illustration from Science and Civilisation in China, Vol 5, Part 1,
by Tsien Tsucn-Hsuin and Joseph Needham © Cambridge Uni¬
versity Press, 1985
Setting wooden movable type at the Imperial
Printing Office of the Ch'ing court, around
1733.
Illustration from Science and Civilisation in China, Vol 5, Part 1,
by Tsicn Tsucn-Hsuin and Joseph Needham © Cambridge Uni¬
versity Press, 1985
enth century and multi-colour printing
some time in or before the twelfth century.
The movable type was first made of earthen¬
ware, but later various other materials, in¬
cluding wood, metal, and a variety of ce¬
ramics, were also adopted.
Because of the great number of characters
in written Chinese, woodblock printing was
used far more often than movable type for
book . production in China until recent
times. Wood blocks were simpler and more
economical, and could be stored easily and
were readily available when a reprint was
needed; movable type was preferred only
for large-scale production of voluminous
books. Nevertheless, both wood blocks and
movable type have gradually given way,
since the mid-nineteenth century, to the
modern printing press.
The prerequisites for a useful invention
included both the physical and the mental
readiness for the event; besides a creative
mind and a popular demand, proper materi¬
als and the essential basic techniques must
be available. Since all the material facilities
for the invention were present in Europe as
well as in China, why did the invention
occur in one civilization but not the other?
The early use of printing in China was
chiefly due to the early invention of paper,
the specialized use made of seals and rub¬
bings for duplication, the greater need for
mechanical aid in duplicating texts written
in a complex ideographic script, the standar¬
dization of Confucian texts used for civil
service examinations and, finally, the de¬
mand for great quantities of Buddhist scrip¬
tures which could not be met by hand-
copying. In the West, paper was not in¬
troduced until a rather late date, seals were
not used as duplication devices, rubbing was
not known until fairly recently, while print¬
ers were restricted by craft unions or guilds.
The relative simplicity of the alphabetic
script also lessened the need for a mechani¬
cal duplication aid.
Thus the materials and techniques neces¬
sary for the invention of printing were ei¬
ther not developed, or did not lead in the
direction of a printing process. Further¬
more, there was no such incentive or de¬
mand for huge quantities of copies as devel-
32
]]>
</page>
<page number="33">
<![CDATA[
oped in connection with Buddhism; the
needs that did exist could be met by hand-
copying. Until all these factors were
changed in the middle of the fifteenth cen¬
tury, the threshold for the invention of
printing was not reached in Western society.
Printing facilitated the economical mass
production and distribution of books and
had profound effects upon European
thought and society in the late fifteenth and
early sixteenth centuries. It stimulated the
spirit of the Renaissance and the Reforma¬
tion, which in its turn promoted further
development of papermaking and printing
until there was a flourishing publishing in¬
dustry. It also helped to establish national
languages and indigenous literature, and
even to encourage nationalism itself; it pop¬
ularized education, spread literacy, and in¬
creased the chances of social mobility. In
short, almost everything in the progress of
modern civilization can be linked in one
way or another to the introduction and
development of printing in the Western
world.
Mass production of texts increased their
chance of survival or preservation and re¬
duced the probability of their loss through
neglect or the destruction of single collec¬
tions. But it did more than this. Wider
distribution of texts and the enlargement of
the reading public meant that the clergy's
monopoly of learning was challenged by
laymen, including lawyers, merchants,
tradesmen, and artisans, who became im¬
portant consumers of books. At the same
time, the pride of place hitherto taken by
religious works was gradually superseded
by texts of humanist authors. With this
increased readership and a broader spec¬
trum of subjects, scholars became more
aware of inconsistencies and contradictions
in hallowed texts, weakening their faith in
the validity of old views, and setting the
stage for the advancement of new learning.
The standardization of texts resulting
from printing stood in contrast to the cor¬
ruption that was bound to be present in all
hand-copied texts. The printing press does
not guarantee freedom from textual errors,
but the requirement for multiple proof¬
reading before sending to the press and the
distribution of errata to correct mistakes
after printing, paved the way for the im¬
provement of future editions. The editorial
functions of the early printers also brought
about a degree of systematization of book
format not to be found in the age of scribes,
and this gradually created a habit of system¬
atic thinking by readers, as well as promot¬
ing the organization of knowledge in many
diverse fields.
For their part publishers naturally en¬
couraged the growing use of the vernacular
which brought an expanding market. As
books became easier to publish in national
languages, printing stabilized the vocabu¬
lary, grammar, structure, spelling, and
punctuation of each, and, furthermore, pro-
% i\. : i ' < %.
The first portrayal of a Chinese bookshop can be
seen in this detail from a 12th-century painting
entitled "The Spring Festival on the River
Bank".
moted its use. Once fiction was printed and
widely circulated, the common language be¬
came firmly established; this, in its turn,
facilitated the eventual growth of specific
national literatures and cultures.
The popularization of education and the
spread of literacy were also closely related
to the expansion of printing. As books be¬
came cheaper and easier to obtain, more
people were able to gain access to the print¬
ed texts which eventually affected their out¬
look on the world and their position in it.
And, naturally enough, easier access to
printed material promoted the rise of litera¬
cy, which stimulated a still greater demand
for more books.
In general, printing in Europe from the
sixteenth century onwards was vigorously
expanded, supporting many drastic and rad¬
ical changes in thought and society. On the
other hand, the progress of printing in Chi¬
na and other nations in East Asia was com¬
paratively constant with modest changes
occurring within a stable tradition. These
diversities reflect the distinctive characters
of Eastern and Western cultures, especially
their attitudes towards material life.
Chinese society has long been dominated
by the Confucian tradition, which concerns
itself primarily with proper human relation¬
ships and social order by way of moral
teachings and ethics, rather than with pursu¬
ance of material advance and extreme
changes in society. The high degree of social
and cultural stability over long periods in
Chinese history, especially from the thir¬
teenth to the nineteenth century, contrasts
greatly with the constant turmoil of life and
intellectual unrest during the same period in
the West.
Such different environments in China and
the West were certainly bound to affect the
role of printing, and in this sense printing
was not only shaped by the political and
social conditions of the time; it also exerted
an equal effect on those conditions. n
TSIEN TSUEN-HSUIN, Professor Emeritus of
Chinese Literature and Library Science and Cura¬
tor Emeritus of the Far Eastern Library at the
University ofChicago, is a leading worldauthority
on the history ofChinese printing. He is the author
ofPaper and Printing (1985), part 1 of Volume 5 of
Joseph Needham's monumental Science and Civi¬
lisation in China (Cambridge University Press),
from which this article has been extracted. Notable
among his other works is Written on Bamboo and
Silk: the Beginnings of Chinese Books and In¬
scriptions (University of Chicago Press).
33
]]>
</page>
<page number="34">
<![CDATA[
Glossary
blanket: the sheet of rubber or other flexible
material used to cover the impression cylinder of
an offset printing press.
block: an illustration, halftone or line art, as en¬
graved in metal for letterpress printing.
carbon tissue: paper coated with gelatin that can
be rendered photosensitive and exposed to light
before being applied to a metal surface of any'
shape.
chase: in letterpress printing, a steel frame in
which metal type and blocks are locked for prin¬
ting or platemaking.
composing stick: in hand composition, a tool in
which each line of type is assembled and justified.
composition: both the setting of type and the
arranging of the type on the page. Some typeset¬
ting systems can set whole pages at a time, while
on others each column of type must be set and the
result assembled as a page.
composition program: a set of instructions for a
computer-driven typesetter.
compositor: a person or company who sets type,
also referred to as the typesetter.
continuous tone: an image that has greys or
shades of colour, and which cannot be reproduced
in that form by most printing methods, because
the thickness of ink cannot be varied during
printing. (See halftone.)
cursive: applied to flowing typefaces that re¬
semble script handwriting, with connected strokes
and curved lines.
cylinder or flat-bed press: a printing machine on
which the type forme is carried on a flat bed under
a revolving paper-bearing cylinder. (See rotary
press.)
digital or digitized type : that which is drawn with
the aid of a computer as steps on a grid, and stored
as digital dot or line patterns, rather than as photo¬
graphic images. If the dot or line density is high
enough (see resolution), the result can look clean
and crisp.
dot matrix printer: forms characters by firing a
series of small needles at the printing ribbon, so
transferring dots to the paper.
face or typeface: a complete set of letters and
other characters in a particular design or style.
Typefaces come in families of different weights
(light, medium, bold), different point sizes, and
different slants (roman, italic, other oblique).
font or fount: a complete set of the characters in
one typeface and size.
forme or form: metal type and blocks for illustra¬
tions assembled in a chase and ready for printing
or platemaking.
galley: a copy of typeset material arranged in
columns instead of made up into pages. The term
comes from the galley or tray of type and the copy
of typeset material that was traditionally made by
hand for use in proofreading before the press ran.
Gothic or black-letter: a general term for a family
of typefaces with dark, angular characters made up
of contrasting thick and thin strokes; developed in
the late Middle Ages in Germany and the normal
text type in Northern Europe in the early years of
printing.
gravure or intaglio: any of various printing tech¬
niques using an etched or engraved plate.
halftone: an image that has been broken up into
tiny dots, which when viewed from normal dis¬
tances create the illusion of continuous tone.
hot metal: general term for typesetting machines
casting type from molten metal. "Hot type" tech¬
nologies are being increasingly replaced by "cold
type", using photographic or electronic processes
to create an image.
ink jet printer: forms characters by spraying a .
very fine stream of quick drying ink onto the
material to be printed. Drops of ink are either
electrostatically or thermally charged as they leave
a tiny nozzle.
input: data entered into a computer.
integrated circuit: minute electrical circuits
containing thousands of electronic components
on a chip of silicon.
justify: in text composition, to space out lines
uniformly to the desired length, so creating a
straight-sided column of text, as here. Unjustified
text has a ragged edge on one or both sides of the
column.
laser printer: forms characters by depositing dots
of carbon onto ordinary paper. A laser typesetter
deposits points of light onto photographic paper.
In each case, the characters which are output are
made up of tiny dots.
layout: the conceptual arrangement of the text
and illustrations on a page. (Makeup is the actual
physical or electronic page assembly.)
letterpress: the primary form of printing, taking
an impression on paper from an inked, raised
(relief) printing surface.
line art: illustrations containing only blacks or
whites, with no intermediate tones, which can be
reproduced without a screening process in the
same way as text.
lithography or litho: literally, "stonewriting"
printing from a dampened, flat surface using
greasy ink, the principle being the mutual repul¬
sion of oil and water. Originally the printing
surface was a porous stone but later a metal plate
was used.
lower case: the small (miniscule) letters in a font of
type, so named from the. lower compartments of
typecases used in letterpress hand composition,
where the most frequently used letters were kept.
The capitals, or upper case letters, were kept in the
upper compartments.
magazine: the case holding the matrices (moulds)
on a typesetting machine.
matrix : the individual brass character moulds on a
typesetting machine.
(micro)chip: a tiny slice of silicon with electronic
circuits etched into it.
offset: the development of lithography by which
the image is not printed direct from the plate but
"offset" first onto a rubber-covered cylinder,
which then performs the printing operation. (See
blanket.)
output: data generated by computer in the re¬
quired format.
photocomposition or phototypesetting: the
production of printing copy, on film or paper, by
photographic means.
plate: the metal, paper or plastic sheet containing
the image to be placed on the printing press.
platen: a flat plate in a letterpress printing ma¬
chine that presses the paper against the type forme.
platen press: a letterpress printing machine which
presses two flat surfaces together to make the
impression.
point: a measure of size used in layout and type¬
setting, most often used to indicate the size of
type.
print-run: the number of copies of a publication
to be printed.
program: a numbered list of instructions to make
a computer do a particular job.
register: the correct alignment of the separate
plates in colour printing.
resolution: in computers, the number of tiny
squares on the screen which a particular system
can control. The higher the resolution, the sharper
the image, thus giving better quality type and
graphics for printing purposes.
rotary press: a machine for printing from a revol¬
ving cylindrical forme, usually onto a continuous
reel of paper.
rotogravure: a system of intaglio printing where¬
by ink contained in the cells of a printing cylinder
are transferred to paper.
screening: to break up images that have conti¬
nuous tones into patterns of tiny dots, with the
darker tones represented by larger or denser dots.
This can be done photographically, or electroni¬
cally with a scanning machine. (See halftone.)
slug: a line of type or a blank line set on a
typesetting machine.
software: computer programs, as opposed to
hardware, or the machinery itself.
web: a continuous reel of paper, often used on
printing machines instead of single sheets.
Photo credits
Pages 4-9: letterpress, gravure and lithographic printing diagrams
© Werner Merkli, Berne, Switzerland. (1) photo © Gutenberg
Museum, Mainz, Fed. Rep. of Germany. (2), (26) woodcuts from
Hartmann Schedel's Liber chronicorum, Nuremberg, 1 493. (3), (4)
photos © Papierfabrik Biberist, Switzerland. (5), (12), (14) photos
© Werner Merkli, Berne. (6), (8) photos © Jean-Loup Charmet,
Paris. (7) photo © Roger-Viollet, Paris. (11) photo © Swiss
Gutenberg Museum, Berne; from Faulmann, Illustrierte Geschich¬
te der Buchdruckerkunst, 1 882. Newspaper press photos (left) ©
Béatrice Lagarde/REA, Paris (right) © Colin Rush/REA, Paris.
(15), (20) photos © Swiss Gucenberg Museum, Berne. (16) photo
©Finnish edition of the Unesco Courier. (17), (23) diagrams from
Pocket Pal, © International Paper Company, New York. (18)
photo © Maury/Jean-Claude Maillard, Pans. (21) diagram ©
Bantam Books, New York. (22) photo © Dunod, 6th ed., Paris,
1973 . (24) photo © Fleury/Ciric. (25) photo © Hallwag AG,
Berne. (27) photo © Nicephore-Niepce Museum, Chalon-sur-
Saône, France. (28) photo Gösset © Sygma, Paris.
Pages 10-13 (top to bottom): photo G. Dagli Orti © Hittite
Museum, Ankara, Turkey; photo © Archaeological Museum of
Beirut, Lebanon; (p. 11): calligraphy © Roger Druet, Paris; illus¬
tration from La civilisation de l'écriture, ùy Roger Druet and
Herman Grégoire © Librairie Arthème Fayard, Dessain et Tolra,
Paris; photo ©Jean-Loup Charmet, Paris; photo © Bibliothèque
Nationale, Paris; (p. 12): photo © Librairie Arthème Fayard,
Dessain et Tolra, Paris; photo © Roger Druet Archives, Paris;
photo © Newberry Library, Chicago, USA; (p. 13): Labyrinth
photo Unesco/Michel Claude; digitized letter © Librairie
Arthème Fayard, Dessain et Tolra, Paris; Arin © Franck Jalleau,
Paris.
34
]]>
</page>
<page number="35">
<![CDATA[
The Unesco
Courier goes to
press
At Unesco's Paris HQ
1. Editorial planning
2. Editing text on screen
3. Choosing illustrations
4. Page layout and cover design
At the printer's
5. Assembly of filmed pages for
platemaking and printing
6. & 7. Making printing plate
8. Removing imperfections from plate
9. Offset press
The Courier JUL
A window open on the world
Published monthly in 35 languages by
Unesco, The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
A selection in braille is published quarterly
in English, French, Spanish and Korean
Editorial, Sales and Distribution Office:
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris.
Editorial staff (Paris)
Managing Editor: Gillian Whitcomb
English edition: Roy Malkin, Caroline Lawrence
French edition : Alain Lévêque, Neda el Khazen
Spanish edition: Francisco Fernandez-Santos,
Miguel Labarca
Arabic edition: Abdelrashid Elsadek Mahmoudi
Braille edition:
Illustrations: Ariane Bailey
Layout and Design: Georges Servat
Research: Violette Ringelstein
Liaison with non-Headquarters editions:
Solange Belin
Sales and subscriptions: Henry Knobil
Special projects: Peggy Julien
Non-Headquarters editions
Russian: Georgi Zelenin (Moscow)
German: Werner Merkli (Berne)
Japanese: Seiichiro Kojima (Tokyo)
Italian : Mario Guidotti (Rome)
Hindi: Ram Babu Sharma (Delhi)
Tamil: M. Mohammed Mustafa (Madras)
Hebrew : Alexander Broîdo (Tel Aviv)
Persian: H. Sadough Vanini (Teheran)
Dutch: Paul Morren (Antwerp)
Portuguese: Benedicto Silva (Rio de Janeiro)
Turkish: Mefrallgazer (Istanbul)
Urdu: Hakim Monammed Said (Karachi)
Catalan: Joan Carreras i Marti (Barcelona)
Malaysian: Abdul ManafSaad (Kuala Lumpur)
Korean: Paik Syeung-Gil (Seoul)
Swahili: Domino Rutayebesibwah (Dar-es-Salaam)
Croato-Serb, Macedonian, Serbo-Croat, Slovene:
Bozidar Perkovic (Belgrade)
Chinese: Shen Guofen (Beijing;
Bulgarian: Goran Gotev (Sofia)
Greek: Nicolas Papageorgiou (Athens)
Sinhala: S.J. Sumanasekera Banda (Colombo)
Finnish: Marjatta Oksanen (Helsinki)
Swedish: Lina Svenzén (Stockholm)
Basque: Gurutz Larrañaga (San Sebastian)
Thai: Savitri Suwansathit (Bangkok)
Vietnamese: Dao Tung (Hanoi)
Pashto: Nasir Seham (Kabul)
Hausa: Habib Alhassan (Sokoto)
Subscription rates
1 year: 90 French francs.
Binder for a year's issues : 62 FF
Individual articles and photographs not copyrighted
may be reprinted providing the credit line reads
"Reprinted from the Unesco Courier", plus date of
issue, and three voucher copies are sent to the editor.
Signed articles reprinted must bear author's name.
Non-copyright photos will be supplied on request.
Unsolicited manuscripts cannot be returned unless
accompanied by an international reply coupon
covering postage. Signed articles express the opinions
of the authors and do not necessarily represent the
opinions of Unesco or those of the editors of the
Unesco Courier. Photo captions and headlines are
written by the Unesco Courier staff. The boundaries
on maps published in the magazine do not imply
official endorsement or acceptance by Unesco or the
United Nations. The Unesco Courier is produced in
microform (microfilm and/or microfiche) by : (1 )
Unesco, 7 Place de Fontenoy, 75700 Paris; (2)
University Microfilms (Xerox), Ann Arbor,
Michigan 48100, U.S.A.; (3) N.C.R. Microcard
Edition, Indian Head, Inc., 1 1 1 West 40th Street,
New York, U.S.A.; (4) Bell and Howell Co., Old
Mansfield Road, Wooster, Ohio 4469 1 , U.S.A.
All correspondence should he addressed
to the Editor-in-chiefin Paris
Imprimé en France (Printed in France) -Dépôt légal: CI -
Juillet 1988.
Photogravure-impression :Maury-Imprimeur S.A.
Z.I. route d'Etampcs, 45330 Malesherbes.
ISSN 004 1-5278
N°7-1988-CPD-88-l-458A
]]>
</page>
<page number="36">
<![CDATA[
^0
5novit tpiöola fonrh itoramraî ao
pauirmmt prtfonaura Dt omnibus
oirant iufiorâ mme-mptnilü jurat
&am aurorarais
tua nuctti mirrraf*
rula pfaaraïmiiît
&f tt ruautraraao
Óanrinrinto
amtriuâE«&îfJits
tetara füm i uttme atuniat noua:
¿j&rdjant <B tra au illa nonfliruDo £
3 ïpi njimrra muulata.çu non unU
tas m Earartiarie- rrâ prlna tantura
rrjrao>rrâ fômla 3 paiuâ*B aoularâ
Ira on ârara-a nimnaç unpturatû
fiuota rourüianr. ïtgira? ht nttmto
raflou)o»nuoûiâ luteaföjmmnaf.
nouoB aopt mfob-mana trâuûx-
utnra quoo oí IHmo turaftannimâ
a}motnt^nut nirantnaB ramipoj*
aras tatrs-ûr niaraajinrái îMiilir;
]]>
</page>
</document>
