<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="081564eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
VOLUME III-N 9 PRICE : 10 Cents (U. S.), 6 Pence (U. K.), or 20 Francs (FRANCE). OCTOBER 1950
8
UNESCO RESPONDS TO UNITED NATIONS
REQUEST FOR KOREAN ACTION
Resolutions. adopted by
the Exec. ulive Board
on August 28 1950
THE EXECUTIVE BOARD
PROFOUNDLY MOVED by the armed attack of which
the Republic of Korea has been the victim, and which led
the Security Council of the United Nations to adopt certain
measures with a view to re-establishing peace and security,
CONSIDERING that one of the essential aims of Unesco
is, as stated in Article I of its Constitution,"to contribute
to peace and security by promoting collaboration among
the nations through education, science and culture in
order to further universal respect for justice, for the rule
of law and for the human rights and fundamental
freedoms for the peoples of the world...",
CONSIDERING that the General Conference at its Fifth
Session, reaffirmed that"all the activities of Unesco must
be directed towards the peace and prosperity of mankind"
and that these"activities to be fully effective, imply a
truly and sincerely universal outlook excluding all thought
of aggression, and founded on recognition of the principles
of justice and freedom on which the Constitution of the
Organization is based",
CONSIDERING that, in the resolutions adopted by the
Security Council and the Economic and Social Council on
31 July 1950 and 14 August 1950, respectively, the Spe-
cialized Agencies were requested, in accordance with the
terms of their agreements with the United Nations to
give whatever help the Unified Command of the United
Nations in Korea might request, in order to assist and
bring aid to the civilian population in Korea,
CONSIDERING that the Economic and Social Council,
in its resolution of 14 August 1950, also stressed the neces-
s. ity for aid in securing the understanding and the support
of the peoples of the world for the action of the United
Nations in Korea, and requested the Secretary-General
to seek, in the name of the Council, whatever form of
co-operation was best adapted to this purpose,
TAKING NOTE of the communications of the Secretary-
General of the United Nations concerning the help which
Unesco could give, in accordance with the above-men-
tioned resolution,
ASSURES the population of Korea of its deep and
earnest sympathy,
RENDERS respectful homage to the soldiers of the
United Nations who are righting on the Korean front in
the name of international solidarity,
RECALLS that international peace-and security must
be based on the respect of the principles of law and the
decisions of the competent organs of the United Nations,
if force is not to triumph over law, and if justice is to be
maintained,
EXPRESSES its confidence in the programme and
methods of Unesco in serving the aims of peace of the
United Nations, through the perfecting of international
co-operation, through the amelioration of the living
conditions of man and through the development of inter-
national understanding by means of education, science
and culture.
CONSIDERS, that in order that Unesco may aid the
United Nations in eliminating the dangers of war more
effectively, it is particularly urgent, at this moment when
human solidarity is under trial and when human rights
are in peril, that still wider'and more active support
should be given to the execution of its mission, by Govern-
ments and National Commissions of Member States.
DECIDES that within the framework of its competence,
UNESCO will give all possible aid and assistance to the
action undertaken by the United Nations in Korea and
towards this end... (Continued on Page 3,)
UNDER THE FLAG OF THE UNITED NATIONS
In August, 1945, World War ß came to an end with the military victor ;
of the United Nations-and the way was clear for Korea to take its place
in the society of free nations, after 40 years of Japanese occupation.
Nearly five years after their liberation, the people of Korea still look to
the United Nations for the protection of their national independence.
In the photo above are shown some of the people of Taegu, provisional
capital of the Republic of Korea, on July 30, 1950, as they gathered
outside a meeting of the United Nations Commission on Korea, and
heard each member of the 7-nation commission reaffirm his country's
determination to support the fight of the United Nations to preserve
Korean independence.
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 2
A HUNDRED"
GROUPS WITH
A COMMON AIM
This is the fifth in a series of special articles describ-
ing the work of some of the 100 international
non-governmental organizations whose co-operation
with Unesco helps the accomplishment of its
programme.
GOETHE, whose bi-centenary was celebrated last year, has been
called a"universal man", for as it was said of him :"his
was the last of those universal minds which have 
able to compass all domains of human activity and know-
ledge... he stood on the brink of an era of rapidly expanding know-
ledge which has made forever impossible the universality of
interest and sympathy which distinguished him".
At the beginning of the nineteenth century, the genius of one
man could embrace extremities, for besides writing his great drama
Fault, Goethe made scientific studies lof colours, assembled one
of the most complete mineral collections of his day (there is even
a mineral, Goethite, named after him), and conducted extensive
experiments in chemistry and biology.
Today, the world of science has
expanded into a universe, and the
work in each sphere is so wide
that all scientists must be spe-
cialists. No one man, in fact, has
time to read all the publications
which appear in his own particular
field, let alone follow the full
advance of scientific accomplish-
ment.
Recently, for instance, aerodyna-
mics experts had been working
with wind-tunnels in studies of
turbulence, experiments of great
value to astronomers in observa-
tions they had made on the passing
of one dust cloud through another.
The astronomers, however, could
not understand the terms used by
the wind-tunnel experts. A sym-
posium Was held between two mem-
ber organizations of the Interna-
tional Council of Scientific Unions
(ICSU) to work out agreements in
terminology, making possible the
application of the results of the
laboratory studies to theories based
on astronomical observation.
"Human Chain Reaction"
THE International Council ofScientific Unions is a federa-
tion of selfgoverning groups
of scientists in particular fields,
such as astronomy, mechanics,
crystallography, radio-science, geo-
graphy, geodosy and geophysics.
The Council's main purpose is co-
ordinating the work of these
specialists, as it did in the sympo-
sium on terminology between mem-
bers of the International Astrono-
mical Union and the International
Union of Theoretical and Applied
Mechanics.
Unesco was extremely fortunate
in finding the ICSU already in
existence, with fifteen years'expe-
rience in its difficult work of admi-
nistration and correlating the
results of scientific research. The
two international organizations
entered into a formal agreement
of co-operation in 1946, and since
have rendered valuable services to
one another.
Since the exchange of theories
and ideas is the foundation of
scientific progress, Unesco's most
important contributions to ICSU
have been in the form of travel
grants to academic scientists, and
calling conferences and symposia
on specific problems.
One of the most important
aspects of scientific conferences is
the element of actual contact among
the participants. Such contact
The UNESCO COURIER is an international periodical devoted to the work
of UNESCO and *to activities and developments throughout the world in edu-
cation, science and culture.
A full year's subscription (12 issues) costs only $1. 00 US., or 5/-or 200
French Francs.
SUBSCRIBE NOW ! Tell your friends about the UNESCO COURIER and
get them to subscribe too.
Write to our agent in your country listed below, or directly to UNESCO
House, 19, avenue Kieber, Paris, 16<, France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamericana S. A., Alsina 500, Buenos-Aires.
Australia : H. A. Goddard Ltd, 255a, George St., Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, Graben 27, Wien I.
Barbados : SPCK Bookshop (Hegional Office) Caribbean area, Broad St., Bridgetown.
Belgium : Librairie encyclopédique, 7. rue du Luxembourg, Bruxelles IV.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editor. Rua Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio-de-Janeiro.
Canada : The Ryerson Press, 299, Queen Street West, Toronto.
Chile : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda 924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera 9a, 1791. Bogota.
Cuba : La Casa Belga, René de Smedt, O'Reilly, Havana.
Czechoslovakia : Orbis, Narodni, 37, Praha I.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6, Norregade, Copenhagen.
Egypt : Librairie James Cattan, 118, rue Emad el Dine, Cairo.
France : Maison du Livre Francis, 4, rue Félibien, Paris (6'). (Booksellers Only)..
Great Britain : H. M. Stationery Office : London : York House, Kingsway (Retail Counter
Service) : P. O. Box 569, London S. E. I. (Post orders).-Manchester 2 : 39-41 King
Street.-Edinburgh 2 : 13a Castle Street.-CardiH : 1 St Andrew's Crescent.-
Greece : Eleftheroudakis, Librairie Internationale, Athens.
Hungary : **Ibusz"Akademia-u. 10, Budapest V.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Israel : Leo Blumstein, Book Shop, 35 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Italy : Messaggerie Italiane, Via Lomazzo, 52, Milano.
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie Universelle, Avenue des Francis, Beirut.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo Sierra 16, Mexico DF.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff, Lange Voorhout 9. The Hague.
Norway : A/S Bokhjornet, Storr. ingsplass 7, Oslo.
Pakistan : Thomas 6. Thomas, Fort Mansions, Frere Road, Karachi 3.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru, S. A. Gir6n de la Uni6n, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co, Inc.. Corner Tanduay and Vergara Streets,
Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : Uniao Portuguesa de Imprensa, 198 Rue de S. Bento, 3"Esq., Lisbon.
Sweden : C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
Switzerland : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469, avenue de I'lndependance, Beyoglu, Is'anbul.
Union 0/South A/rica : Van Schaik's Bookstore, Pty. Ltd., P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United States of America : Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway, New York
27, N. Y.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperaci6n Cientifica, Avenida Agraciada 1875 Montevideo.*For France : Retail sales : Unesco Sales Service, 19, Avenue Kléber, Paris (l6').
Some of the groups of scientists whose work is co-ordinated by the Council of
Scientific Unions, have permanent stations of research and information centres
to assist specialists. The International Bureau of Physico Chemical Constants.
maintained by the International Union of Chemistry with Unesco aid, is a
stockroom of chemically pure substances which fills one of the most important'
scientific needs.. standards which are internationally recognized, and which are
invaluable to the work of these chemists (above).
fosters a"human chain reaction",
the development of an idea which
a scientist may pick up in discus-
sion with other specialists in his
own field, a nascent idea which
might never have appeared clear
to him in simply reading the
reports of those same men.
Most modern scientific advances
are made on the borderlines between
the formally-divided sciences. The
ICSU, with member unions repre-
senting nine special branches of
scientific work in forty nations,
has established international Joint
Commissions to study such"bor-
derline sciences".
Rheology, the study of viscous
substances, from the movement of
earth's crust to the flow of the
blood and the rise of sap in plants,
calls for research in physics, geo-
logy, chemistry, mechanics and
biology. Problems in terminology
so that the specialists concerned
could understand one another, were
dealt with in a special ICSU report.
Like many specialized sciences,
rheology may sound far removed
from our everyday life, but the
plasticS, fo7wiohich ivy have so many
uses are a product of this"border-
line science"which has contribute-
ed much to help a world short of
materials.
Standards For The World
SoME of the permanent servicesare joint commissions in them-
selves, ans exist for reasons
which make international co-opera-
tion a vital necessity. The boiling
point of water, the hour of the day,
the latitude of a certain point of
the earth cannot be determined by
a national law. The International
Time Bureau and the International
Latitude Service call for the work
of both the International Astrono-
mical Union and the International
Union of Geodosy and Geophysics.
This second Union also maintains
the International Seismological
Summary, the result of several
decades of research, which makes
possible the prediction of the paths
of earthquakes and the sending out
of early warnings.
Each of these Unions exists as
a permanent authority to assist
specialists, and the centres of
information and standards they
maintain are invaluable to scientific
work.
With the passing of the"uni-
versal man", we have entered a
world in which little progress can
be accomplished without the work
of specialists, a world whose future
depends upon their co-operation.
NEW PRICE FOR COURIER
IN U. S. AND CANADA
Due to increased costs, the
subscription price of the Courier
in the U. S. and Canada will be
increased from $1 to $1. 50, effec-
ttt ; e January 1st, 1951. The single
issue price will correspondingly be
increased from 10 cents to 15 cents.
ÍÙlalnl
jJlllJliadionA
PROFESSIONAL TRAINING
OF JOURNALISTS
(95 pages)
The professional training of
journalists is of direct concern
to Unesco because the press in
our time is one of the most
potent instruments for in-
fluencing the n1htds of men
toward peace or war. In
addition to a thorough dis-
cussion of the question, this
publication contains a selected
list of text-books and reference
books, as well as a bibliogra-
phy.
Price : $0. 40 2/-F. 100.
EDUCATION BY RADIO
(72 pages)
The use of radio as an ins-
trument of education can bring
to the teacher a knowledge of
new educational methods and a
wealth of information which
can enliven his class and
stimulate his own teaching.
A full analysis of the qualities
and limitations of radio as a
means of expression is here
presented.
Price : $0. 40 2/-F. 100.
THE PROBLEM
OF NEWSPRINT AND
OTHER PRINTING PAPER
(H) pages)
The object of this study is
to provide in as non-technical
fashion as possible the facts
relating to the problem of
production and distribution of
paper, especially newsprint.
Among the topics covered are
papermaking, pulpwood, and
wood pulp, production and
consumption of printing paper
and newsprint, and the de-
mand trends of all the regions
of the world. Approximately
25 tables giving pertinent data
supplement the text.
Price : $0. 65 4/-F. 200.
WAR-HAND) CAPPED
CHILDREN
Report on the European
Situation
(142 pages)
Survey of the educational
problems of war-handicapped
children.
Price : $0. 503/- F. 150.
Each month a newsletter-
"A Reader's Guide to Unesco
Publications"-is sent out
from Unesco House to all parts
of the world. Its purpose is to
keep people informed about
new Unesco publications, giv-
ing prices and languages in
which they appear, together
with advance news about
works in progress. Regular
copies of this newsletter can ! : Ie
obtained by writing to"A
Reader's Guide to Unesco Pu-
blications", Unesco House, 19.
Avenue K : eber, Paris 16".
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
UNESCO TO ASSIST UNITED NATIONS ACTION IN KOREA
The Members of the Executive Board and of Unesco's Secretariat seated round
the table in this photo are Count Stefano Jacini, Chairman (indicated by an arrow)
and reading clockwise : Mr. Jaime Torres Bodet. Director-General of Unesco ;
Mr. Benjamin Cohen-Assistant Secretary-General. United Nations Department of
Public Information ; Professor Louis Verniers ; Mr. Ahmet K. Tecer, Professor
AU Sommerfelt ; M. Roger Seydoux ; M. Guy de Lacharriere ; Mr K. V. Padmana-
bhan (alternate to Sir Sarvepalli Radhakrishnan) ; Professor Jean Piaget ; Pro-
fessor Alex Photiades ; Senator G. Pecson ; Mgr. J. Maroun ; Dr. H. El Diwany bey ;
M. A. Castro Leal ; M. Victor Doré ; Sir Ronald Adam ; Dr. Luther H. Evans ; Mr
Arthur Compton, Jnr, and Mr. R. Barnes (Secretary of Executive Board).
Unesco's Response to
United Nations Appeal
U m--rxESCO is responding resolutely to the United Nations
appeal for support following the act of aggression
in Korea. This action was decided on at a meeti g
of the Organization's Executive Board at the end of
August. It is significant that the 18 members of the Board,
who act as individuals and not as representatives of
governments, were unanimous in"deplormg tie violation
of international law"and in adopting a programme of
immediate and long-range action. This programme pro-
vides credits totalling $175, 000 for three major activities :-
1) relief assistance to the civilian population is Korea ;
2) plans to bring the Korean teaching system back to normal
once hostilities end ;
3) an expanded education programme to promote understanding
of the United Nations responsibilities In the present world
crisis.
Unesco has already formulated plans to send a mission
of enquiry to Korea if and when requested by the U. N., to
investigate the civilian needs of the population and to
determme how Unesco can best aid relief and recon-
struction.
But to achieve this unified action it is vital that inform-
ation and educational materials concerning the United
Nations action for collective security reach the peoples of
the world. The programme, approved by the Executive
Board, is designed to bring the message of the United
Nations to schools and universities in dynamic form.
Unesco will concentrate its efforts to make known the prin-
ciple of collective security and to show by concrete exam-
ples taken from world events and particularly the Korean
question, the world importance of the work of the United
Nations.
The decisions of the Executive Board have been made in
conformity with the Constitution of Unesco. Among its
main tasks the Basic Programme of the organization sets
forth the following :
"to bring about better understanding among the peoples of the
world and to convince them of the necessity of cooperating
loyally with one another in the framework of the United
Nations."
The Director-General of Unesco made Unesco's position
clear recently when he stated :"In condemning aggression
wAeret'er it appears, Unesco is not impelled by any party
spirit but adopts an attitude consonant with the notion of
peace within the law which its constitution proclaims. Far
from being an instrument of ideological war, our Institution
is first and foremost an organ of education for the peace
under the law.
"The activities we can undertake as a result of the events
in Korea fit into the framework of our normal programme.
They consist in sharing, to the full measure of our abilities
in the reconstruction of Korea, just as we are already con
tributing to that of many war-devastated countries, and
helping to show, by our teaching about the United Nations,
the value of collective security in the face of amI
ag'gresstOH."
EXECUTIVE. BOARDUNANLMOUSLY
VOTES 6-POINT PROGRAMME
THE Executive Board of
Unesco at its meeting
on Aug st 28th unani-
mously decided to give
all possible aid and assistance
to the action undertaken by the
United Nations in Korea. The
decision was contained in a
resolution adopted by the
Board, which instructed Di-
rector-General Jaime Torres
Bodet :
"To relieve the needs of the
civilian population in Korea
within the fields of education,
science and culture, by means
of emergency relief, and, at
the appropriate time by a re-
conslruction project" ; and
"To develop, within the re-
sources at his disposal, includ-
ing the periodical publications
of the Organization, the execu
tion of the programme resolu-
tions concerning teaching about
the United Nations and its
Specialized Agencies, putting
particular emphasis on the
necessity for collective security,
based on re, spect for law, with
the aid of concrete examples
and to this end to utilize
appropriate documentation pro-
vided by the Secretary General
of the United Nations."
The resolution moreover
appealed to the Governments
and National Commissions of
UNESCO's Member States to
participate to the extent of the
means at their disposal in this
action. It requested non-gov-
ernmental organizations, which
participate in the task of Unes-
co, men and women whose
activities are devoted to educa-
tion, science, culture and in-
formation, and all those who
wish to live in peace with their
fellow men, to contribute to the
work of Unesco, in that spirit of
liberty which characterizes all
of its actions with a view to
reinforcing in the minds of men
the intellectual and moral de-
fenses of peace through law
which the United Nations are
responsible for developing and
safe-guarding.
To Maintain Justice
THE Board also authorizedthe Director-General by
unanimous vote to carry
out six specific measures pro-
viding for emergency relief
and reconstruction in Korea
and for an educational cam-
paign in schools and univer-
sities and other institutions on
the United Nations. These
measures are set forth in the
text of the Executive Board
Resolution on this page.
The resolution of the Board
assured the population of
Korea of"its deep and eamest
sympatlly"and rendered"res-
pectful/wmllye to I he soldiers
of tile United Nations who are
ngMing on [lie !, orean front in
tile name of intemational soli-
daritl". It recalled that"In-
ternational peace and security
must be based on the reispect of
tile principles of law and the
decisions of tile competenl 01'-
gangs of tile united Nations, if
force is not to triumph areI'/'o !-ce !  ? t < fo <nM)7 !p/t ot'er
lali), and if justice is to be
maintained".
In connection with the con-
tribution of Unesco to the ac-
tion of the United Nations in
(Continued on page 8)
DIREtTOR. GENERAl OÐTlINES
BAtKGRODND FOR AM ! ON
ADDRESSING Unesco's Executive Board at the opening
of its meeting on August 26th, M. Jaime Torres Bodet,
irector General, stressed the important responsibilities
which fell on Unesco, as a Specialized Agency of the
United Nations, in the present situation in Korea. He said,
in part :
"May I, firs of all, say how glad I am that the Executive
Board has advanced the date of its summer session in order
to consider how Unesco can best assist the United Nations
in the Korean question. The grave events which led the
Security Council, on 25 June, to adopt measures for the provi-
sion of military assistance to South Korea in obedience to
the principle of collective security and in defence of in-
ternational law, confront Unesco with problems which demand
the immediate attention of its executive body. In the present
situation, Unesco, as a Specialized Agency of the United Na-
tions, has important responsibilities ; it will bring to their dis-
charge a clear appreciation of its resources and a firm
consciousness of its duties. Your meeting is, in itself, an
eloquent proof of that intention...
"... The problem raised by the armed attack of which the
Republic of Korea, one of our Member States, is the victim
does not concern Unesco alune : the whole system of the
United Nations and Specialized Agencies has taken cognizance
of it..."
(Continued on page 8)
RESOLUTIONS OF UNESCO'S
EXECUTIVE BOARD AUGUST 28 1950
. (Continued from page I)
THE EXECUTIVE BOARD...
... INSTRUCTS the Director-General :
(1) to relieve the needs of the civilian population in Korea within the
fields of education, science and culture, by means of emergency relief,
and, at the appropriate time by a reconstruction project ;
(2) to develop, within the resources at his disposal, including the periodical
publications of the Organization, the execution of the programme
resolutions concerning Teaching about the United Nations and its
Specialized Agencies, putting particular emphasis on the necessity for
collective security, based on respect for law, with the aid of concrete
examples and to this end to utilize appropriate documentation pro-
vided by the Secretary-General of the United Nations,
APPEALS to the Governments and National Commissions of Member States
to participate to the extent of the means at their disposal in this action,
REQUESTS non-governmental organizations, which participate in the task
of Unesco, men and women whose activities are devoted to education, science,
culture and information, and all those who wish to live in peace with their
fellow men, to contribute to the work of Unesco, in that spirit of liberty which
characterizes all of its actions with a view to reinforcing in the minds of men
the intellectual and moral defences of peace through law which the United
Nations are responsible for developing and safeguarding.
In implementation of the above resolution, the Executive Board :
AUTHORIZES THE DIRECTOR GENERAL,
1. With a view to providing assistance to the civilian population of Korea :
(a) to send a mission to Korea, upon the request of the Secretary-General
of the United Nations, to investigate the needs of the civilian
population of Korea, in liaison with the Unified Command and the
appropriate organs of the United Nations responsible for civilian relief ;
(b) to provide, upon request, educational supplies on an emergency basis ;
(c) to prepare in close liaison with the United Nations and other Spe-
cialized Agencies and launch a campaign in co-operation with Member
States, their National Commissions and with non-governmental
organizations, for assistance to the Republic of Korea in the field of
educational, scientific and cultural relief and reconstruction.
2. With a view to developing education about the United Nations and Specialized
Agencies,
(a) to prepare, in close and constant collaboration with the United
Nations, both written and audio-visual materials for use in schools,
and adult classes and universities ;
(b) to produce and distribute these to Member States in English, French
and Spanish, in sufficient quantities to enable Member States to adapt
them and diffuse them on a large scale for their own purposes ;
(c) to put at the disposal of the Secretary-General of the United Nations
two specialists with instructions to co-operate with the United Nations
Secretariat in order to assemble relevant documentation in connexion
with the United Nations'action in Korea.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 4
TWO UNESCO SEMINARS
GIJIDE EDUCATION TOWARDS
INTERNATIONAL UNDERSTANDING
To develop in children a < : onsciousness of the unity of mankind is one of the mainconcerns of responsible educators in all countries. Many teachers, however, are
only now beginning to discover suitable methods of making young people aware
that nations are inter-dependent. There is also a vast amount of work to be done in
"judging"textbooks : the revision of those"guilty"of bias or excessive nationaHsm,
and the preparation of new ones that stress the constructive work of mankind, teach
children about the international organizations of today, and the services they can render
to world peace and prosperity.
How to improve both teaching methods and textbooks to help this education for
international understanding were the subjects of two Unesco Seminars held recently.
The articles on this page describe the work done by the educators who met in Brussels,
at the Seminar on"The Improvement of Textbooks, Particularly History Books", and
those at Montreal where the Seminar subject was,"The Teaching of Geography as a Means
of Developing International Understanding".
Textbooks that speak
with a constructive accent
ONE of the most immediatelyimportant results of the Unesco
Seminar on"The Improvement
of Textbooks, Particularly History
Books", held recently in Brussels,
was a plan to put the history books
of nine countries"on trial".
The 45 specialists from 24 coun-
tries including, for the first time at a
Unesco Seminar, representatives of
Germany and Japan, laid down the
main lines of bi-lateral systems of
exchange and criticism of history
textbooks between groups of experts,
similar to those already being carried
out by the German Teachers Union
with associations of historians in
Britain and France.
These new plans will enable the
examination and mutual criticism of
history books to take place between
Belgium and Holland, France and the
United States and between Germany
and the following countries : Bel-
gium, the United States, Norway,
Holland, Sweden and Switzerland.
As a pattern for these exchange
systems, the members of the Seminar
used the successful work already
accomplished by the Norden Asso-
ciations, which were founded after
the first World War by Denmark,
Finland, Iceland, Norway and
Sweden to promote mutual under-
standing between the peoples of the
Nordic countries.
The system these countries deve-
loped to ensure that their school
history books were both factual and
fair was based on the three cardinal. principles of textbook improvement
- that it should be international,
mutual and positive. In other words,
that each country should examine the
books of another, and that not only
should offending passages be remov-
ed but each country should make
a complete and constructive study
of its neighbour's history with a
view to improving the coverage in
its textbooks.
Seminar's work was directed by
Professor Alfred Weiler, Director of
the Lycée Experimental Henri IV, at
Montgeron, France.
Technical problems of the impro-
vement of textbooks in all subjects
were dealt with by Group 1, directed
by Professor P. A. Lauwerys of the
University of London Institute of
Education. Its members studied
reports on such varied textbooks as
historical atlases, literary antholo-
gies, song-books and geography and
history texts, all of which showed
an undue degree of nationalist bias.
The group therefore recommended
that all types of textbooks should
be studied with the same critical
care usually reserved for history
books.
NO TEXTBOOK SLAVES
GROUP 11, directed by ProfessorHaakon Vigan er, of O l ,
author of the Unesco booklet
on Nordic textbook improvement,
concentrated on textbook problems
in the classroom. Among the con-
clusions they reached on this subject
was that the key to reform lay in
training teachers to evaluate text-
books and to develop initiative in
the use of varied materials. At all
costs, they said, teachers must not
be the slave of the textbook.
Problems both of writing scienti-
fically sound history textbooks and
their psychological effects on
children were dealt with by
Group III, conducted by M. Georges
Panchaud, Director of the Lycée Mu-
nicipal de Jeunes Filles, at Lau-
sanne.
To achieve objectivity in history
textbooks, the Group recommended
that texts should be submitted,
before printing, to historians of other
countries, as was done under the
"Nordic"system. Unesco was asked
to help provide authors with reliable
source material.
The last group, directed by Pro-
fessor F. W. Wood of Wellington
University, New Zealand, studied
such problems as the relationship of
national to world history.
Unesco's programme of textbook
improvement was outlined to the
Seminar by Mr. Richard M. Perdew
and Mr. Marcel Vanhamme, directors
of this programme in the Department
of Education. The final report of the
Seminar's work will be used as a
basis for two projected publications
and will also provide Unesco with
some useful suggestions for future
activities in the textbook field.
FROM EAST AND WEST
THE plans drawn up at the BrusselsSemi ar for mutual exchange
and criticism of history books
should give a new impetus and
guidance to the movements for
textbook improvement in all the
countries represented there.
In addition to most of the Euro-
pean Unesco Member States, educa-
tors came from Canada, Mexico and
the United States in the New World ;
Egypt, Iraq, Israel, Syria and Turkey
in the Near East ; and from Thailand
and Japan in the Far East. The
An exhibition 01 teaching aids and equipment was held at MacDonald College, near Montreal,
Canada, in connection with the Unesco Seminar on"The Teaching of Geography as an Aid
to International Understanding."Here. M. Jean Guiton, Deputy Head 01 Unesco's Education
Department, explains to a member 01 the Seminar the details 01 a planisphere constructed by
the young pupils 01 a Paris technical training school. The planisphere was designed to
illustrate the interdependence of all countries and its execution provided a series of lessons
on people 01 other lands for the youngsters who built it.
66 WORLD"
Geography lor all thW orld
No man today can escape being
a geographer. His whole
life, even to his most every-
day activities-the despatch of
the products of his work, the get-
ting in of supplies, keeping up-to-
date with the latest news-is
bound up so closely with what is
going on in countries that were
merely names to his forbears, that
he cannot help but acquire a great
deal of knowledge concerning all
parts of the world.
In former times, men may have
had a fair knowledge of their dis-
trict, their country and the neigh-
bouring states (particularly those
with which they had, all too often,
to go to war) but they knew little
about the rest of the world. Today,
when almost unknown places may
overnight become of world-wide
importance, the scope of geogra-
phICal knowledge has been greatly
extended and the stock of such
knowledge needed by the average
person has become much larger.
It is wrong, however, to tax the
memories of children with masses
of miscellaneous and ill-assorted
names and facts. What they
should know are those geographi-
cal facts which give a true picture
of life in other countries, for one
of the essential purposes of geogra-
phy and its teaching is to correct
wrong ideas about other lands and
peoples. In creatin good relations
among nations, this is an urgent
necessity.
Ways in which geography teach-
ing can best encourage world-mind-
edness and international under-
standing were studied by nearly
50 teachers and specialists who met
recently at a Unesco Seminar, held
at MacDonald College, near Mont-
real, Canada.
False Values-Few Maps
UNDER the direction of bir C.Delgado de Carvalho, the Bra-
zilian geographer and sociolo-
gist, these educators, from 22 coun-
tries, pooled their knowledge and
experience in discussions on the
improvement of teaching methods
and materials.
Making a comparaliye study of
geography teaching in the schools
of different countries, the Seminar
members came across many pro-
blems arising out of faulty empha-
sis in teaching or lack of suitable
equipment.
Many geography instructors have
to rely on their own initiative to
give their pupils a true picture of
the world, for wall maps and atla-
ses are lacking in many schools.
Even when maps do exist, the co-
lours and perspectives used often
give them a disproportionate value,
some countries receiving too much
prominence and others not enough.
Links Between Teachers
A ! \lONG the recommendations ma-de by the Se inar nd ai ed
at overcoming such difficulties
was for a textbook on geography
teaching to be widely circulated so
as to keep teachers, in countries
lacking such information, in touch
with activities in other parts of
the world. Another was that an
"international"atlas, printed in
colours, but without place names,
be produced and sold at cost price
to editors who would then complete
it for the schools in their countries.
Each member of the Seminar
worked with two groups, one
studying geography teaching in
relation to the mental development
of children in different age groups
and the other examining the main
aspects of geography teaching-
the training of teachers, teaching
aids, programmes and methods,
geography and international under-
standing etc.
Members of the Seminar are now
back in their home countries put-
ting into practice the individual
plan of action that each one pre-
pared before leaving MacDonald
College. These activities include
interviews with representatives of
educational authorities, parents'
associations, and programme pre-
paration committees, and the for-
mation of special groups to conti-
nne the work begun at the seminar,
including the publicizing of the
work and needs through newspa-
pers and the radio.
From the Seminar reports and
documents, a British expert, Mr Ne-
ville Scarfe, is to produce an
overall work on Geography and
International Understanding, which
will complete the handbook prepar-
ed as a working document for the
Seminar by a group of French geo-
graphers.
The most important feature of a Unesco Seminar is a small, informal study group in which information is exchanged, ideas and methods are
discussed and solutions to specific problems are suggested. This particular group at the recent Brussels Seminar studied the technical pro-blems of the improvement of textbooks.
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
How many 01 Korea's schools will be standing when the lighting is over ? Considerable
efforts had been made to improve and increase ducational facilities ince 1945# but much
01 this has almost certainly been wiped out in the first three months 01 the war.
FtVE YIEAIRS-ANID líJH[IRIEIE
MONTHS-IN KOREAN
EDUCAT ! ONl  1 f C A f lf  I.
by Robert LOMBARD
IN 1945, education in Korea was almost entirely the product of forty years
of Japanese rule. Japanese was the only language taught in primary schools
and in Universities. Administrative personnel, principals, head teachers
and inspectors were nearly all Japanese.
In both South and North Korea, radical changes have been made since 1945
to increase and improve education and restore its national character.
In South Korea, the proportion of national funds spent on education has risen
from 3. 6 per cent to about 10 per cent ; the primary school enrolment has
increased from 1, 500, 000 to 2, 500, 000 ; the number of Koreans attending middle
schools has risen from 62, 000 to 225, 000. The Imperial Japanese University
has been re-organized and combined with a number of other Colleges into the
new National University of Seoul, with an attendance, since 1945, of 8, 000
students. It possesses a library of half a million oriental books and about
150, 000 western volumes. Korea University, a private Foundation, which has
an enrolment of about 1, 000, received University status in 1946.
There are also a number of Christian and Buddhist Colleges and Seminaries
in Seoul ; higher education has always been concentrated in the Seoul region,
where, about 85 per cent of the country's educational facilities exist.
Similar progress is reported to have been made in North Korea where uni-
versal elementary education was introduced in 1947 and where, at the end of
1948, there were 720 secondary schools and 11 higher educational institutions
including a University established at Pyongyang. An extensive campaign
against illiteracy was begun in North Korea in 1946.
In five years, throughout the whole country, important progress had been
made. Instruction is now given everywhere in Korean, and illiteracy has been
reduced from 50 per cent to 20 per cent.
There are, however, very serious deficiencies, particularly a shortage of
teachers (the majority of whom in 1945 were Japanese) and a lack of text-
books in Korean. There is a shortage of school buildings and most of the
existing ones are poorly equipped. Technical and vocational training is
practically non-existent.
Considerable progress had been made to improve education in Korea during
the past five years-but most of it has almost certainly been destroyed by the
material losses, social chaos and economic dislocations caused by three short
months of the present conflict.
HOW UNESCO CAN HELP
THE KOREAN PEOPLE
To support United Nationsaction in Korea, Unesco's Exe-
cutive Board has approved the
opening of a credit fund of $175, 000
of which $50, 000 is to finance a
programme of education directed
towards a better understanding of
the ideals of the United Nations
and the principle of collective secu-
rity. The remaining 8125. 000 is to
be used for emergency aid and the
restoration of educational facilities
in Korea.
Unesco can help the Koreans in
the following ways :
A SPECIAL MISSION
Unesco must first investigate the
nature and extent of the educa-
tional needs of the Koreans. If the
United Nations consider it ne-
cessary, a special mission of experts
will be sent to Korea. These ex-
perts, working with the Unified
Command and with the Specializ-
ed Agencies'of the United Nations
will find out the most urgent needs.
Longer-term plans, concerning the
future educational needs of Korea,
when peace has been restored, will
also be considered.
URGENT EDUCATIONAL NEEDS
Because of the widespread de-
struction in Korea, it is likely that
schools will be in need of even the
most elementary. equipment. Unes-
co's emergency aid must include
help in the reconstruction of
schools or at least in the provision
of temporary educational facilities
in areas where the need is greatest.
To equip schools, supplies of all
kinds : blackboards, exercise books,
pencils will be needed. Supplies
required for the higher grades of
education are likely to include labo-
ratory and technical equipment and
books and periodicals for the Uni-
versity of Seoul and the colleges at
Seoul, Taegu and Pusan.
MATERIAL AID
Unesco is already considering
how it can bring material help to
the people of Korea. Such help
could include clothing for school
children and students and grants
to refugee students and teachers.
The provision of food, particu-
larly milk, to Korean schoolchildren
is likely to fall within the sphere of
operations of the United Nations
International Children Emergency
Fund.
PEDAGOGIC ENTRE.
If requested by the Republic of
Korea, Unesco could set up a tem-
porary pedagogic centre. there.
It is understood that the Spe-
cialized Agencies of the United Na-
tions will work together as a team,
each being responsible for urgent
measures in its own particular field.
The Secretary-General has appoint-
ed a Director of Civilian Relief for
Korea, Brigadier Parminter, form-
erly of U. N. R. R. A., who has al-
ready taken up his duties at Lake
Success. A Chief of Mission in the
field has also been appointed and
the nucleus of a United Nations
relief organization is being created
in South Korea.
The tragic plight of hundreds of thousands of refugees who have fled to the South
of Korea calls for the immediate provision of relief services and supplies. Before the
end of August incomplete reports gave the refugee population of South Korea as over
1. 500. 000, most of them living under pitiable conditions.
w
FIVE YEARS'WORK FOR VICTIMS OF WAR
UNESCO'S Relief Assistance Service which isto be responsible for some of the ork the
Organization will carry out in support of
As part of its relief work since 1946, Unesco has given
special assistance to the children's communities in which
war handicapped children are helped and re-educated.
At one of these communities. The Children's Republic,
at MouIin-Vieux, France, the boys, shown above in their
printing shop, prepare and publish their own newspaper.
United Nations action in Korea, has already five
years'experience of co-operation in the rehabi-
litation of education in devastated countries.
During this time, it has stimulated and co-ordi-
nated the reconstruction work of international
organizations, and in cases of particular urgency
has distributed immediate relief.
To raise funds for reconstruction, Unesco has
organized campaigns which have brought in large
sums of money. In 1948 and 1949 it published
the"Book of Needs", the first volume of which
deals with Europe and the second with Asia.
They give a full and authoritative account of the
losses suffered by the educational systems of each
country as the result of the war, and showed
more fortunate peoples how their generosity could
best be applied.
There were many other special publications,
calling attention to the specific needs of schools,
laboratories, universities, libraries and museums
which had suffered wartime destruction.
Two types of relief have been provided for emer-
gency relief drawn from the regular budget of
Unesco and funds raised through the Organiz-
ation's appeals or campaigns or from direct gifts
to Unesco. The following sums have been distri-
buted :
1947 1948 1949
From Unesco's regular budget $375, 381 310, 000 198, 000
Gifts forwarded to Unesco.. 22, 830 223, 433 217, 290
Gifts in kind.............. 60, 000--
$458, 211 533, 433 415, 290
EMERGENCY relief was provided for childrenin Greece and in the Middle East. In
Greece, grants were allocated to ten primary
schools, while in the Middle East thirty-nine
temporary schools were opened for children in
refugee camps immediately after the war in Pa-
lestine. Thirty-three thousand children are given
a primary education in these schools by six
hundred and thirty-eight teachers, themselves
refugees.
Unesco has strongly supported the International
Voluntary Work Camps whose work helps mate-
rial reconstruction and develops international
understanding.
Special help has been given to the International
Federation of Children's Communities whose
work and aims Unesco publicizes. Unesco has
also sponsored this Federation's activities, such
as the International Children's Camp organized
at Moulin-Vieux in the Isère Valley, France, in
1949.
Since the establishment of the Reconstruction
Department, now replaced by the Relief Assistance
Service, 17 pamphlets, designed to solicit help for
the cultural reconstruction of devastated coun-
tries, have been published. Unesco has produced
a film on the problem of neglected children, and
has made twenty-two radio recordings dealing
with the work of cultural reconstruction. Tra-
velling exhibitions have been prepared and
despatched to the United States of America, Ca-
nada, the Netherlands and Germany in support
of reconstruction campaigns. An exhibition deal-
ing with the International Voluntary Work Camps
was held in Belgium and several panels illustrat-
ing the work of the Service have been exhibited
in the Salon de I'Enfance in Paris.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 6
... DETERMINI
Succeeding
i
From The
Of \
A general view of the Security Council conference room on June 27. during the vote of the Sanction Resolution presented by the U. S. A., which
opened the way ior unreserved military operations by the 59 U. N. Members. With the U. S. S. R. absent, and Yugoslavia voting against, the
vote was seven to one in favour 01 the Resolution (Egypt and India reserving their vote until reception 01 instructions 01 their governments).
The seven hands shown raised in lavour 01 the resolution represent China. Cuba. Ecuador. France. Norway. United Kingdom and the U. S. A.
RESOLUTION ADOPTED BY SECURITY COUNCIL ON JUNE 25, 1950
THE SECURITY COUNCIL
Rccalling the finding of the General
Assembly in its resolution of October
21, 1949, that the Government of the
Republic of Korea is a lawfully esta-
blished government"having effective
control and jurisdiction over that part
of Korea where the United Nations
Temporary Commission on Korea was
able to observe and consult and in
which the great majority of the peo-
ple of Korea reside ; and that this
Government is based on elections
which were a valid expression of the
free will of the electorate of that part
of Korea and which were observed by
the Temporary Commission ; and that
this is the only such Government in
Korea" ;
Mindful of the concern expressed by
the General Assembly in its resolutions
of December 12, 1948 and October 21,
1949, of the consequences which might
follow unless Member states refrained
from acts derogatory to the results
sought to be achieved by the United
Nations in bringing about the complete
independence and unity of Korea ; and
the concern expressed that the situa-
tion described by the United Nations
Commission on Korea in its report
menaces the safety and well being of
the Republic of Korea and of the peo-
ple of Korea and might lead to open
military conflict there :
 Noting with grave concern thearmed attack upon the Republic of
Korea by forces from North Korea,
Dctcrmincs that this action consti-
tutes a breach of the peace,
.. 1. Calls for the immediate cessation
[of hostilities ; and
Calls upon the authorities of North
Korea to withdraw forthwith their
armed forces to the thirty-eighth
parallel ;
II. Requests the United Nations Com-
mission on Korea
(a) To communicate its fully consi-
dered recommendations on the situa-
tion with the least possible delay ;
ON JUNE 27 !) 1950
THE SECURITY COUNCIL
Having determined that the armed
attack upon the Republic of Korea by
forces from North Korea constitutes a
breach of the peace,
Having culled for an immediate ces-
sation of hostilities, and
Having called upon the authorities of
North Korea to withdraw forthwith
their armed forces to the thirty-eighth
parallel, and
flaving noted from the report of the
United Nations Commission for Korea
that the authorities in North Korea
have neither ceased hostilities nor
withdrawn their armed forces to the
thirty-eighth parallel and that urgent
military measures are required to
restore international peace and secu-
rity,
Having noted the appeal from the
Republic of Korea to the United Nations
for immediate and effective steps to se-
cure peace and security,
Recommends that the Members of the
United Nations furnish such assistance
to the Republic of Korea as may be ne-
cessary 10 repel the armed attack and
to restore internationalpea. ce and secu-
rity in the area.
(b) To observe the withdrawal of
the North Korean forces to the thirty-
eighth parallel ; and
(c) To keep the Security Council in-
formed on the execution of this reso-
lution ;
III. Calls upon all Members to ren-
der every assistance to the United
Nations in the execution of this reso-
lution and to refrain from giving
assistance to the North Korean autho-
rities.
RESOLUTION ADOPTED BY TilE SECURITY
COUNCIL ON JULY 7"1950
THE SECURITY COUNCIL
llaving determined that the armed attack
upon the Republic of Korea by forces from
North Korea constitutes a breach of the
peace,
llaving recommended that Members off,
the United Nations furnish such assistance
to the Republic of Korea as may be nieces-
sary to repel the armed attack nd to
restore international peace and security in
the area,
1. Welcomes the prompt and vigorous
support which governments and people of
the United Nations have given to its Reso-
lutions of 25 and 27 June 1950 to assist the
Republic of Korea in defending itself
against armed attack and thus to restore
international peace and security in the
area ;
2. Notes that Members of the United
Nations have transmitted to the United
Nations offers of assistance for the Repu-
blic of Korea ;
3. Recommends that all Members prov-
iding military forces and other assistance
pursuant to the aforesaid Security Council
resolutions make such forces and other
assistance available to a unified command
under the United States ;
4. Requests the United States to design-
ate the commander of such forces ;
5. Authorizes the unified command at its
discretion to use the United Nations flag
in the course of operations against North
Korean forces concurrently with the flags
of the various nations participating ;
6. Req'4ests the United States to provide
the Security Council with reports as appro-
priate on the course of action taken under
the unified command.
A major proportion of this issue of thethe work which is to be undertake :
of the Secretary-General of the Uni
the Unesco Executive Board, to provide :
1) emergency relief and eventual rece'
and culture for the people of Konc
2) information, through Unesco medi.
facilities about the United Nations
cular emphasis on the necessity J
Accordingly on ! pages I and 3 are
Unesco Executive Board, 28 August 1950.
of the meeting of the Executive Board,
Torres Bodet, and a story of the work
teaching, to children and adults, of the pI
On page 5 are stories about post. woe
summary of the educational relief and)
prepared to undertake in, Korea and a pc
by Unesco in other war-devastated countri
On page 12 is a story about the andc
than 2, 000 years so little known in other
On these centre pages are publishec
ments in man's history, the Charter of {t !
cisco, 26 June 1945. Like other historic affj
and human dignity, this document is too
It is like them, too. in the fact that it hasg
in days which seem darkest, for it begin !
the United Nations are"DETERMINED I
scourge of war."
We therefore publish Chapter I, Arpc
purposes of the United Nations, and Cïe
with action with respect to threats to the
of aggression. The Security Council of t !
resolutions dealing with the situation ir
these pages resolutions adopted by the 84
and 31 July.
CHAPTER I
PURPOSES AND PRINCIPLES
Article 1
The Purposes of the United Nations are :
1. To maintain internationa peace and
security, and to that end : to take effective
collective measures {or the prevention and
removal of threats to the peace, and for the
suppression o {acts of aggression or other
breach ! ! s o {the peace, and to bring about
by peaceful means, and in conformity with
the principles of justice and international
lau, adjustment or settlement of interna-
tional disputes or situations which might
lead to a breach of the peace ;
2. To develop friendly 1'elations among
nations based on respect {or the principle
o {equal rights and self-determination of
peoples, and to take other appropriate
measures to strengthen universa peace ;
3. To achieve internationa cooperation in
solving internaliona problems o {an econo-
mic, social, cultura, or humanitarian cha-
racter, and in promoting and encouraging
respect for human rights and {or {unda-
menta {reedoms {or all without distinction
as to race, sex, languages, or religion ; and
4. To be a center {or harmonizing the
actions o {nations in the attainment o {these
common ends.
CHAPTER VII
ACTION WITH RESPECT TO THREATS TO
THE PEACE, BREACHES OF THE
PEACE, AND ACTS OF AGGRESSION
Article 39
The Security Council shall determine the
existence of any threat to the peace, breach
of the peace, or act of aggression and shall
make recommendations, or decide what
measures shall be taken in accordance wüh
Articles 41 and 42, to maintain or restore
international peace and Security.
Article 40
In order to prevent an aggravation of the
situation the Security Council may, before
making the recommendatwns or deciding
upon the measures provided for in Arti-
cle 39, call upon the parties concerned to
comply with such provisional measures as
it deems necessary or desirable. Such
provisional measures shall be without pre-
jUdice to the rights, claims, or positiQn of
the parties concerned. The Security Coun-
cil shall duly take account of failure to
comply with such provisional measures.
Article 41
The Security Council may decide what
measures not involving the use of armed
force are to {) e emptoyed to give effect to
its decisions, and it may call upon the ltlem-
bers of the United Nations to apply such
measures. These may include complete or
partial interruption of economic relations
and of rail, sea, air, postal, telegraphic,
radto, and other means o {communication,
and the severanCe o {diplomatic relations.
Article 42
Should the Security Council consider that
measures provided for in Article 41 would
be inadequate or have proved to be invade-
quate, it may take such action by air, sea,
or land {forces as may be necessary to
maintain or restore international peace and
security. Such action may include de-
monstrations, blockade, and other opera-
tions by air, sea, or land {orces of} lfembers'
of the United Nations.
Article 43
1. All ! flembers of the United Nations, in
order to contribute to the maintenance of
international peace and security, undertake
Dr. Kamil Idil, Representative of Turkey to the
visiting a refugee centre at Pusan, with Dr. M.-M.
United Nations Commission on Korea, at teit.
Lee (right), Korean interpreter 01 the Commission.
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
IED To Save
Generations
.
; t Scourge
' ("
a r...
Page 7-UNESCO COURIER
I, Unesco Courier is devoted to accounts of
, by Unesco. in compliance with the request
nited Nations and upon the instructions of
onstruction in the field of education, science
ea :
Mar and through all Unesco's educational
I and its Specialized Agencies, with parti-
for collective security.
, published the resolutions passed by the
Also on page 3 and page 8 are accounts
. a declaration by Director-General Jaime
: already initiated by Unesco to improve
principles of the United Nations.
Far educational developments in Korea, a
reconstruction activities which Unesco is
partial record of similar work accomplished
tries.
íÏent culture of the Korean people, for more
r parts of the world.
ad excerpts from one of the noblest docu-
the United Nations adopted at San Fran-
lfirmations of human rights, human freedom
 little known by the peoples of the world.
igreatest meaning and importance precisely
i1s with the. declaration that the peoples of
tao save succeeding generations from the
Me I, of the Charter, which sets forth the
aPter VII, Articles 39 through 43, dealing
) e peace, breaches of the peace, and acts
the United Nations has passed a series of
in Korea. Accordingly, we reproduce on
Security Council on 25 June, 27 June, 7 July
to make available to the Security Council,
on its call and in accordance with a special
agreement or agreements, armed forces,
assistance, and facilities, including rights of
passage, necessary for the purpose of
maintaining international peace and secu-
rity.
2. Such agreement or agreements shall
govern the numbers and types of forces,
their degree of readiness and general
location, and the nature of the facilities and
assistance to be provided.
3. The agreement or agreements shall be
negotiated as soon as possible on the uni-
tiative of the Security Council. They shall
be concluded between the Security Council
and Members or between the Security
Council and groups of Members and shall
be subject to ratification by the signatory
states in accordance with their respective
constitutional processes.
On July 30, a public meeting of the U. N. Commission on Korea was held in Taegu, the provisional capital of the Republic of K : o= : >a.. A large
audience heard each member of the Commission reaffirm his country's determination to support the United Nations in Korea.
SECURITY COUNCIL RESOLUTION
OF JULY 31, 1950
THE SECURITY COUNCIL,
RECOGNIZING the hardships and
privations to which the people of
Korea are being subjected as a
result of the continual prosecution
by the North Korean forces of their
unlawful attack, and
APPRECIATING the spontaneous
offers of assistance to the Korean
people which have been made by
governments, specialized agencies,
and non-governmental organiza-
tions,
REQUESTS the Unified Command to
exercise responsibility for determi-
ning the requirements for the relief
and support of the civilian popula-
tion of Korea, and for establishing
in the : field the procedures for pro-
viding such relief and support ;
REQUESTS the Secretary-General to
transmit all offers of assistance for
relief and support to the Unified
Command ;
REQUESTS the Unified Command to
provide the Security Council with
reports, as appropriate, on its relief
activities ;
REQUESTS the Secretary-General,
the Economic and Social Council in
accordance with Article 65 of the
Charter, other appropriate United
Nations principal and subsidiary
organs, the specialized agencies in
accordance with the terms of their
respective agreements with the Uni-
ted Nations, and appropriate non-
governmental organizations to pro-
vide such assistance as the Unified
Command may request for the relief
and support of the civilian popula-
tion of Korea, and as appropriate in
connection with the responsibilities
being carried out by the Unified
Command on behalf of the Security
Council.
When the U. N. Commission on Korea held a public meeting in Taegu on July 30.. its first since the
outbreak of war.. some 6. 000 people for whom there was no room in the Cultural Half. waited
outside, listening to the proceedings over loud-speakers.
On May 10, ! 94S, elections toot place in Southern Korea under the supervision 01 the United Nations
Temporary COlllDÚ8sion on Korea. Here, Koreans are shown waiting to cast their votes.
Members of the secretariat of the U. N. Commission on Korean at work. From left to right : Mr. Cecil
Goyder, Telecommunications Officer ; Mr. John Gaillard. Acting Deptuy Principal Secretary ; and
Mr. Charles Coates, Political Officer.
Colonel Alfred G. Satin (left) Personal Representative of the U. N. Secretary-General during a
visit to the temporary headquarters of the Commission on Korea. With Colonel Katzin are Mr. A.-B.
Jamieson (centre). Australia, and Dr. Liu Yu-Wan, Commission Chairman during the outbreack of
fighting. In the background is Mr. George Movshon, U. N. Secretariat.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8
(Continued from page 3)
Korea, Mr. Torres Bodet pointed
out. that"the activities we can sunder-
take consist in sharing, to the full mea-
sure of our abilities, in the relConstruc-
tion of/f. orea, just as we are already
contributing to that of many war-devas-
tated countries."
Mr. Torres Bodet also defined Unes-
co's attitude toward aggression."In
condemning aggression wherever it
appears", he said,"Unesco adopts an
attitude consonant with the notion of
peace vithin the law which its Consti-
tution proclaims... Far from being an
instrument of ideological war, our
In. stitution is first and foremost an
organ of education for peace under the
lay".
Human Rights In Peril
IN order that Unesco may aid theUnited N tions in eli inating the
dangers of war more effectively,
the Board stressed the view that"it is
particularly urgent at this moment
when human solidarity is under trial
and when human rights are in peril,
that still wider and more active support
should be given to the execution of its
mission, by Governments and National
Commissions of Member States".
Ten members of the Board spoke in
connection with their support of the
help which Unesco proposes to provide
to the Korean civilian population in
answer to the United Nations'appeal.
M. Hassan el Dtwani, speaking on
behalf of Shafik Ghorbal bey, Under
Secretary of State of the Egyptian Mi-
nistry of Public Instruction, said that he
vigorously condemned aggression and
that"the vigour and the promptitude
with which the United Nations have
dealt with the conflict in Korea con-
trasts with their attitude vis-à-vis other
cases of aggression and of violation of
sovereignty of others memberrs of the
Organization".
Luther H. Evans, Library of Congress
of the United States, stressed the duties
of Unesco in relation to the United Na-
tions."The duty of Unesco is plain",
he said."It must fulfil its obligation
to the United Nations by explaining to
tlll'peoples of the u'orld, with the help
of teachers, scholars, writers and other
learters in the communication of knowl-
edge and ideas, that the issue in Korea
is clearly drawn between the defense of
peace and permitting brute aggression
to succeed... Unesco can have'no
greater task than to uphold the United
Nations as the defender of peace, and
must do its full part in rebuilding he
shattered life of the Kore, an nation."
A Great Revival Of Confidence
S AR. DAR MAUK, Ambassador of Indiain Paris, said the decision of the
Board was the answer of U''sec
to the appeal of the United Nations, and
that the contribution of Unesco would
be of inestimable value for the Korean
civilian population."All this is very
valuable", he declared."But, looking
at it from a wider angle, the work than
lies ahead of us in the fi. eld of education
is even more important. 1Vel can eli-
minate war only if the'whole world is
convinced thllt aggression cannot be
tole°ated, that the great principles of
human rights, of the rule of law, of
social and economic justice, and of
collective security, are vital principles
that each and everyone of us must be
prepared to accept and help to enforce."
M. Roger Seydoux, Director of
Cultural Exchanges at the French
Ministry of Foreign Affairs, contrasted
the speed with which the United Nations
took its stand and sent forces to Korea
with the hesitancies about plans for
sanctions at the time of the League of
Nations."The first soldier of the
United Nations who disembarked in
Korea", he said,"started a great revival
of confidence in the United Nations
throughout the wOl'ld, and. increased the
feeling that any breach of international
law might expect to be punished".
"In response to requests from the
United Nations and the Economic and
Social Council for help fl'om the Spe-
cialized Agencies", said M. Seydoux,
"tie are giving our help in complete
fidelity to our mission, by using the
only means at our disposal, and in strict
conformity with the te ! J'1Tls of our Cons-
titution-to promote peace, by educa-
tion, science and culture".
The Duty Of Philosophers
P nOFESSOR Paulo Carneiro, perma-nent delegate of Brazil to Unesco,
recalled a remark made by a
'wotan to a philosopher."The duty
of philosophers", she said,"is to stand
up against s1l ; ords without camjing
swords". This, according to Professor
Carneiro, is the mission of Unesco.
", 11 orality", he added,"must not be
subordinated to ; politics, and there can
be no morality : where the spirit which
inspires Unesco is absent. Ve< asso-
ciate ourselves with the crusack for
peace in order that'liJe may build a
peace based upon justice and the res'-
pect for sm".
The importance and meaning of the
Board's decision were also stressed by
a number of other members, including
Senora Geronima Pecson, member of the
Senate of the Philippines ; Professor
Alex Photiades of Greece ; Dr. Rafael
Jimenez of Colombia ; Monsignor Jean
Maroun of Lebanon ; and M. Kudsi
Tecer of Turkey.
In a statement to the Board, Benjamin
Cohen, Assistant Secretary-General of
the United Nations in charge of in-
formation, conveyed to the members the
thanks of Mr. Trygve Lie, Secretary-
General, for the speed with which they
had responded favourably to the re-
quest of the United Nations."Wlcile
men are dying in Korea", he said,"the
United Nations Organization does not
confine itsef to the task of repelling
aggression. It is also working to res-
tore the normalcy of the lives of the
peoples who are'suffering from the
effects of the aggression in order to
help them brid. qe this terrible period
until peace has been restored.
Mr. Benjamin Cohen, Assistant Secre-
tary-General of the United Nations in
charge of Public Information, thanked,
on behalf of Mr. Trygve Lie, U. N. Se-
cretary-General, the Unesco Executive
Board for its response to the call for
assistance in Korea. Mr. Cohen is
shown here (right), with M. Jaime
Torres Bodet. Director-General of
Unesco (centre) and Mr. Lionel El-
vin, Head of Unesco's Education
Department.
UNESCo is undertaking an intensive campaign to improve the teach-
ing of the principles of the United Nations in schools, adult
classes and universities of Member States throughout t  world.
Particular emphasis is being put on the necessity for collective
security, based on respect for law.
The campaign, while continuing Unesco's normal activities as an
organ of education about United Nations principles of peace through
collective security, is intended to encourage more effective and dynamic
methods of teaching these principles.
To assist members of teaching staffs, adult educators, university
professors and others concerned with teaching, Unesco is asking dis-
tinguished writers in a number of countries to prepare in close collabor-
ation with the United Nations, written and audio-visual teaching mate-
rials. These include pamphlets, books, maps, charts and bulletins
adapted to the various levels of instruction, ranging from those designed
to present the case for collective security in an elementary school manner
to scholarly studies on the concept of international law written. by leading
experts.
Teaching Aids For All Levels
THREE types of written material are being prepared in the French,English and Spanish languages for distribution to Unesco's Na-
tional Commissions. These will include a pamphlet designed for
use in high schools and adult classes ; a simplified version of this pam-
phlet supplemented by advice about practical class room methods for the
teaching of collective security and other UN principles ; third, a book
for a public on a more advanced educational level.
The visual teaching materials include wall charts and coloured maps
which can be reproduced in black and white to permit wide class-room
distribution. lIt is expected that National Commissions in. countries
where instruction is given in languages other than French, Spanish and
English willrrange for translations and adaptations., 
Unesco is arranging for an initial printing of 10, 000 copies each of
the two. kinds of pamphlets, and of 12, 000 for maps and wall charts.
But the programme is based on the assumption that National Commis-
sions will arrange for reprinting and distribution of many times these
totals.'
In carrying out the educational campaign Unesco will not only be
putting into effect the unanimous decision. of its Executive Board that
the Organization should, within its resources and province of activity,
develop teaching about the UN. It is also using the present international
situation as the point of departure for increased activity in an area
assigned to it by its Constitution r-help for teaching that tends to
lead toward the abolition of war, the replacement of violence by reason,
and the substitution of solidarity for international rivalry.
Unesco is also carrying out the instructions of its Executive Board
that it put at the disposal of the Secretary General of the United Nations
two specialists in the field of education with orders to co-operate with
the UN Secretariat in order to assemble relevant documentation in
connection with the United Nations action.
"A SSIST ANCE by Unesco to theSecurity Council, under the
arrangements for co-operation
between the Economic and Social
Council and ourselves, is covered by
Article VIII of the Agreement between
Unesco and the United Nations, which
reads as follows :
"'The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
agrees to co-operate with the Economic
and Social Council in furnishing such
information and rendering such assist-
ance to the Security Council as that
Council may request including assist-
ance in carrying out decisions of the
Security Council for the maintenance
or restoration of international peace
and security.'
"The procedure for giving effect to
recommendations of the United Na-
tions is laid down in Article V of the
same agreement, of which the first pa-
ragraph stipulates more particularly :
"'The United Nations Educational,
Scientific and Cultural Organization
having regard to the obligation of the
United Nations to promote the objec-
tives set forth in Article 55 of the
Charter and the function and power
of the Council, under Article 62 of the
Charter, to make or initiate studies
and reports with respect to interna-
tional economic, social, cultural, edu-
cational, health and related matters
and to make recommendations con-
cerning these matters to the Specializ-
ed Agencies concerned, and having
regard, also, to the responsibility of
the United Nations, under Articles 58
and 63 of the Charter, to make re-
commendations for the co-ordination
of the policies and activities of such
Specialized Agencies, agrees to arrange
for the submission, as soon as possible,
to the appropriate organ of the Orga-
nization of all formal recommendations
which the United Nations may take
to it.'"
(Continued from page 3)
A Vast Job To Be Done
"THE Secretary-General of theUnited Nations formally notified
me of the resolution of the Eco-
nomic and Social Council by letter
elated 22 August. Yesterday after-
noon, Mr. Benjamin Cohen, Assistant
Secretary-General for Information,
whom I am glad to welcome among
us, handed to me a letter from
Mr. Trygve Lie, the relevant passages
of which I should like to read to you :
"'I should be glad to make available
to Unesco information collected and
material already prepared by the Se-
cretariat so that Unesco could both
assist in distributing this material and
also use it to prepare its awn material
for distribution through its channels.
'"There is a vast job to be done in
educational circles-among the schools,
colleges, universities, and learned so-
cieties of the world-and Unesco will
be playing a very vital role if it can
effectively inform these circles.'
"Mr. Cohen will explain to you that
we have discovered a similar need
among the armed forces in Korea and
I have taken steps to make available
to the armed forces a highly competent
person thoroughly acquainted with the
United Nations to assist the Unified
Command in acquainting the armed
forces in Korea with the aims and
purposes of the United Nations and
especially with the nature of the
action being taken in Korea...
"... In a. world torn by anxiety, daily
threatened by new dangers, further
effort is daily required. I am persuad-
ed that the Executive Board will have
at heart the wish to show that, within
its proper sphere, Unesco is up to the
measure of its duties."
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
"lASCAUX :
Cradle of
Man's Art"
A unique colour
film opens a door
into the past
. CREDITS.
Title : Lascaux, Cradle of Man's
Art.
Written and directed by : William
Chapman.
Photographer : William Sumits.
Film Editors : Stefan Bodnariuk,
W : lliam Rudy.
Electrician : Pierre Guesseau.
Assistant : William Chapman, Jr.
Technical Aid : Meyer Rosenbloom.
The tHm is tar sale to. unh ; er-
silks, co. lieges, schaals, museums
and community graups far noun-
cammercial use any. It may be
obtained fram Gatham Films, 31
East 21st street, New Yark.
ONE day, in September 1940,
two French boys, Marsal
and Ravfdat, were walk-
ing along a wooded ridge
above the Vezere River, near the
village of Montignac in Southwest
France. Their dog Robot chased
a rabbit into a deep hole and in
attempting to rescue the dog, the
children worked their way down
into a cave which subsequently
proved to contain the. finest collec-
tion of pre-historic paintings yet
found.
Although similar paintings had
bun found in other caves and rock
shelters in this region, those at
Lascaux were unique in their excel-
lent state of preservation, many
being as vividly etched and co loured
as when they were painted at
various times between 12, 000 and
30, 000 years ago.
The lcrrgest mural in the Lascaux cave, where about 500 paintings
of animals were found. Close to many of the paintings are curious
eye-like signs, probably meant to represent the magical eye of the
hunter, and placed there to ensure success in the hunt.
Like all other female animals on the walls of the cave, this Chinese-
like horse is pregnant, expressing a wish by the men who made the
paintings that their food supply be assured. The darts behind the
animal are magic symbols of the wish for hunting success.
In a deep and almost inaccessible shaft. the archaeologists explo-
ring the cave found what was probably the record of some prehis-
toric drama. It showed a man with a bird's head, apparently dead
- the only human figure among the Lascaux paintings. Close by
were a totem-pike bird and a bison pierced through with a spear.
The original opening to the Lascaux cave through which the two boys
shown in this photograph Ravidat and Marsal, found their way to
the storehouse of prehistoric art. With the boys are (left) M. Léon
Lavat. a member of the <&lt; Société Prehistorique Française >&gt; and the
Abbé Breuil, an eminent French archaeologist.
It was only after the Liberation
of France that other countries
learned of this important disco-
very. Among the journalists who
visited the cave was an American,
William Chapman, who, having
already seen several art films based
on direct photography of the
paintings of great masters, concei-
ved the idea of bringing the pre-
historic paintings of Lascaux to
the screen.
It was not until 1948. that he
was able to carry out his project.
He had never before made a film
and he had to overcome many
technical difficulties. All his heavy
equipment, for example, had to be
hauled up the hillside by oxen.
Dr. Robert C. Angell, head of the
"tensions and International Un-
derstanding"project of Unesco's
Social Sciences Programme, since
September 1949, left Paris last
month to return to his former po-
sition as Chairman of the Sociology
Department of the University of
Michigan. Since the sudden death
of Dr. Arthur Ramos, last October,
Dr. Angell had served as acting
head of Unesco's Social Sciences
Department. Dr. Angell returned to
the United States on September 1st
to attend the annual meeting of
the American Sociological Society
of which he was recently elected
president. He is taking up his
presidential duties at the end of the
meeting.
Mrs. Alva Myrdal, Principal Di-
rector of the Department of Social
Affairs, of the United Nations since
February 1949, has now taken
charge of Unesco's Department of
Social Sciences.
Mrs. Myrdal, an outstanding so-
ciologist, has had a distinguished
career as an educationist and leader
in social affairs. From 1936 to
1948, she directed the Training
College for Pre-School Teachers, in
Stockholm, which she founded.
From 1944 to 1948, Mrs. Myrdal
served with many international
organizations including the Inter-
national Union for the Scientific
Study of Populations, the Inter-
national Federation of University
Women, the ! World Federation of
UN Associations, and the World
Council for Early Childhood Educa-
tion.
Chapman used colour film from
the United States, and took his
shots with a camera loaned from
London, with the. aid of lighting
provided by a French. electri-
cian. He was encouraged in his
work by Robert Flaherty, the well-
known producer of documentary
films and a grant from the"Viking
Fund"enabled him to finish his
work.
The result,"Lascaux : Cradle of
Man's Art", which has just been
shown for the first time in Europe
at the Antibes Film Festival, is a
remarkable colour film of the paint-
ings that cover the limestone
wall.
There are paintings of deer,
bison, wild horse, bulls, a totem-
like bird and many others. Some
animals are shown pursued by dots
and arrows, magic symbols for
hunting success, it is thought. All
the female animals are pregnant,
signifying a wish that the food
supply continue. There is one
remarkable picture of a horse, his
body shaded to indicate a third
dimension, his head turned and
fore-shortened, his ears shown in
a natural way. This may be
the first discovered painting
that attempts modern perspective.
Then, there are paintings on top of
paintings, done thousands of years
apart.
Only One Human Figure
ONE large section of the cave iscovered with huge black bulls,
some of them twenty feet long and
worked in among them are other
animals like galloping ponies. No-
where in the history of cave paint-
ing have animals as large as these
ever been found. There is only
one human figure in the cave ; it
is shown with bison and a totem-
like bird. There are also multitu-
dinous symbols and dots which may
be the beginnings of writing and
mathematics.
Everything has been success-
fully captured on film and the
commentary, spoken by Mr. Chap-
man himself, is intelligently help-
ful to an appreciation or. the
drawings.
Temple Of The Hunters
SCHOLARS think that the. cave
found by the boys in 1940 and
since caUed Lascaux, was a temple
devoted to securing, through magic,
an abunda. nce of food in those re-
mote times when man was so ! e a
hunter, before he had learned to
sow crops and before he had domes-
ticated animals. In addition to
showing the cave paintings, the
film also shows some of the sites in
the region, where many important
discoveries about pre-historic man
have been made. Lascaux opens a
door into the past and it empha-
sizes the rapidly growing belief
that the teaching of history must
soon begin with pre-history.
The study of pre-history is only
about a hundred years old. And
it was not until the paintings in
the Spanish caves at Altimira were
found in 1879 that anyone thought
of ancient man as an artist.
Through this and subsequent
discoveries, culminating in the
amazing find at Lascaux, scientists
are gradually taking a new view
of mankind's eariy history.
Chapman's 16 mm sound and
colour film which runs for 17 mi-
nutes was made especially for uni-
versities, colleges, schools, museums
and community groups.
Lascaux has been called :"The
capital of a lost continent in the
mind of prehistoric man". Cer-
tainly for those interested in art,
archaeology, anthropology, humani-
ties and kindred subjects, this film
offers insight, inspiration and
opportunity for countless hours of
study.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 10
INTERNATIONAL WORK CAMP VOLUNTEERS BRING
HELP-AND NEW HOPE-TO A FRENCH VILLAGE
EVERYONE looks forward to
his or her annual holiday
as a time of relaxation and
it is rare to hear or read of
people who voluntarily give up
this leisure time to work for
others.
This summer, 120 young people
from sixteen different countries,
met in two international work
camps in the French Landes, set
up by Jeunesse et Reconstruction
and Service Civil International
under the auspices of the French
National Commission for Unesco
which provided the funds. These
young people gave up their month's
vacation to help the people of
Saugnac, a village whose popula-
tion had dwindled from 1, 800 to
650 as the result of repeated forest
fires in the region.
Using scythes and spades, they
dug mile after mile of fire breaks
to check future forest fires. They
tilled the soil and made it ready
for crops. They cleared land
which was charred brush as a
result of past fires. They lived
in tents and primitive shacks
where they did their own cooking
and washing.
At the end of the day, they
gathered around wooden tables to
talk and to deepen friendships
begun while they worked side by
side in the fields. It was an
enlivening and stimulating expe-
rience for these young folk who
came from all walks of life-
students, workers, sailors, teachers,
dancers and journalists-and
whose homes lay as far apart as
Yugoslavia and Chile, Finland and
New Zealand.
In their leisure time they read
books from the Unesco Library set
up in the camp, or exchanged per-
sonal experiences. All the while,
they were gaining an insight into
the life of their new friends from
other lands and an affection for
the"Landais"whose soil they were
helping to bring back to fertility.
They left many friends behind
them in the village of Saugnac et
Muret. The work done by these
international work camps gave the
villagers fresh heart and confidence
for the future.
IEU[JO]PJE ? S OJRJPIHIANS ILIEAJN llO ILJIVIE
AGAJIN  AND TO LAUGH
Some child war victims Irom European
children's communities at the international
camp in the castle 01 Sanem at Esch-sur-
AIzette, Luxembourg. To repay the kind-
ness 01 Luxembourg school children who
contributed towards the cost 01 the camp,
these youngsters repaired and decorated a
room in the castle, now being turned into
a permanent community for the children out.
Luxembourg.
THIS summer one of the most
beautiful buildings in
Luxembourg, the castle of
Sane , at Esch-sur-Alzette,
became for one month, a
Europe in miniature. Forty children- all war victims-aged between
14 and 17, arrived there and set up
an international, self-governing camp.
Among them were Dutch, Germans,
Italians, Swiss, Belgians, French and
English.
Thev came from some of the child-
ren's communities which have sprung
up all over Europe in the past few
years. In these com mum ties live
boys and girls whose parents have
been killed or deported children who
have become delinquents for lack of
proper home life, and who have been
taken off the streets and out of
unhealthy slums to be given the
chance of becoming self-respecting
and respected members of a commu-
nity.
On the invitation of the Luxem-
bourg Teachers'Federation, the camp
was organized under the auspices of
Unesco and the FICE (Federation
Internationale de Communautés d'En-
fants). The castle of Sanem was
loaned to the FICE by the Commune
of Esch-sur-AIzette and contributions
from Luxembourg school-children
provided the up-kecp of their guests
from other countries.
As a token of thanks to their hosts,
the children attending the camp, re-
paired. and decorated a room in the
castle, which is now being turned
into a permanent community for the
children of Luxembourg.
Excursions were arranged so that
the children could learn about their
host country. Living and working
together, they wrote and produced
plays in five languages and composed
songs and verses.
One result of this mingling of dif-
ferent nationalities was an appeal
drafted by them and addressed to all
children's communities. It called
on the Communities to unite in efforts
to :
"present new wars from setting the
youth of the world against each
ocher" ; and,
"improve the spirit of responsibility
and constructive work in all commu-
nities and collaboration between
them"."
The Sanem camp also provided an
opportunity for educationists to
observe the psychological and physi-
cal development of the children, most
of whom have suffered mentally and
physically from their experiences
during and since the war.
Before they left the Sanem camp
last month, the children decided to
organize and finance a similar-camp
next year and formed an internatio-
nal secretariat, in which they invited
FICE to join. In the meantime, they
intend to publish their own periodi-
c&1 review. A member of the Re-
naissance Community in Rome will
assemble and edit the material and
send it to OdenwaLdschute in Germa-
ny for printing. From there it will
go out to children's communities-
each contribution being printed in its
original language.
UNESCO-CARE
PROGRAMME IS
H E LP) N G WAR-
HIT LIBRARIES
DURING THE past year, nearly$ 900, 000 worth of new books
have reached the shelves of
war-damaged and depleted libra-
ries in twenty-thee countries
under the programme operated by
CARE (Cooperative for American
Remittances to Europe and Asia)
at the instigation and with the
co-operation of Unesco.
These books, providing the
latest available information for
technical studies on such subjects
as applied science, medicine,
forestry, pedagogy and many
others, were the gift of profession-
al groups, colleges, research
councils, women's organizations
and private individuals in the
United States.
Purchases were made by CARE
on the basisi of lists supplied by
Unesco, reflecting the greatest
needs of libraries in all parts of
the world. Help was also given by
publishers who offered discounts
to cover the cost of packing and
export, and from customs authori-
ties who waived duties on the
cases of books.
In addition, arrangements were
made for 60, 000 volumes of new
and used books and periodicals not
on the established lists'to be dis-
tributed through Member Agencies,
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
P3le I I-UNESCO COURIER
ECUADOR'S
I KNOW NO SAFE DEPOSITORY OF THE ULTIMATE POWERS OF
SOCIETY BUT THE PEOPLE THEMSELVES ; AND IF WE THINK THEM
NOT ENLIGHTENED ENOUGH TO EXERCISE THEIR CONTROL WITH
A WHOLESOME DIRECTION. THE REMEDY IS NOT TO TAKE IT FROM
THEM, BUTTO INFORM THEIR DISCRETION THROUGH EDUCATION.
FROM A LETTER WRITTEN BY
THOMAS JEFFERSON IN 1820.
NEWSPAPERS LEAD A NATION-WIDE FIGHT
AGAINST ILLITERACY...
IN 1934, a newspaper in Guayaquil, Ecuador,"
Telegrafo", began to devote space in its columns
to weekly lessons suitable for teaching illite-
rates to read. From this small beginning has
grown a nation-wide campaign, started and backed
by the National Press Union (Union Nacional de
Periodistas) of Ecuador.
In this unique experiment-the only anti-illi-
teracy campaign Þrganized and directed by a group
of newspapers-the National Press Union has
used the organs of press and radio to give the
campaign wide publicity throughout the country.
"Co-operatn Committees"have been set up in
towns and villages, compo-
sed of representatives of
cultural associations, admi-
nistrative bodies, municipal
councils, workers'organiza-
tions and members of the
clergy. These have mobi-
lized teachers and private
individuals to help in the
campaign and have encou-
raged illiterates to join the
classes.
To support the scheme,
the Government of Ecuador
has issued two series of
stamps, each having a total
value of 500, 000 sucres
(about $30, 000).
The campaign organized
by the National Press
Union which began in 1942,
and another on a smaller
scale instituted by the Liga
de Ensenanza de Analfabe-
tes de Guayaquil the fol-
lowing year were originally
private enterprises.
Diploma
Of Citizenship
IN 1945, however, theGovernment passed a
law which aimed at making
every citizen of Ecuador
able to read and write. Just
how immense a task this
represents is indicated by
statistics published in 1944,
according to which 52 % of
Ecuador's population of
3, 400, 000 was illiterate at
that time.
The problem of illiteracy
is also complicated by the
fact that 27 % of the popu-
lation is Indian, most of
whom are illiterate and who
speak Quechua. A large
number have no knowledge
of Spanish.
For the Indians who have
a fair knowledge of Spanish,
the National Press Union
prepared"cartillas", or
elementary illustrated read-
ers, in this language. For
those knowing very little
Spanish, there is a"car-
tilla"with explanations in
Quechua, but the pupil is
taught to read and write in
Spanish.
Teachers are recruited
from among all sections of
the literate population, but
as it is impossible to pay
them any salary. a system
of bonuses is used, the
teacher in each campaign
area claiming the most
new-literates gaining a
prize of 1, 000 sucres ($ 60)
At the village of Chibuleo in the Province of Tungurahua, a
volunteer from one of the regional offices of the Ecuadorian
National Press Union explains to an Indian instructor how to
use the"cartilla", an elementary illustrated reader.
For the anti-illiteracy campaign
organized by the National Press
Union in Ecuador, teachers are re-
cruited from all sections of the po-
pulation. Here, Chief Gualavisi, of
the Indian village of Pingulmi, Pi-
chincha Province, teaches one 01
the village women to read.
times are arranged to meet
local conditions and work.
Factory workers, for exam-
ple, attend in the evenings
and waiters during the af-
ternoons. Each pupil is
given a pencil and a"car-
tilla"distributed by the
National Press Union.
Instruction is given on
two levels : pupils are first
taught reading, writing
and a little arithmetic, and
then after gaining their
"Citizen's Diploma", they
can join the second course
where they study texts on
history, geography, civics,
ethics, hygiene and feeding.
Unfortunately, this second
stage of the campaign has
been less successful than
the first. Many of the
pupils were not interested
in continuing the classes,
and there is also a lack of
teachers to give instruction
in the more specialised
subjects.
Despite the efforts al-
ready made, an enormous
task still awaits thy or-
ganization and individuals
carrying out the campaign.
One of the new and pro-
mising developments in the
work is the launching this
year by the Ecuador Go-
vernment of a mobile ser-
vice SARE (Service Ambu-
lante Rural Equatoriano).
This will carry the cam-
paign into those parts of
the country which are more
or less cut off from normal
means of communication.
and any teacher
with eight literate
pupils to his credit
qualifying for a
100 sucre bonus.
A"Diploma of
Patriotism"is also
awarded to tea-
chers and a"Citi-
zen's Diploma"to
every successful
candidate in the
examinations. This
"'Citizen's Diplo-
ma"is not merely
a certificate of
merit : it carries
with it the right of
the holder to fill a
public post, to vote
and to be elected
as a representative
of the people.
As the campaign
organisers declared
in a slogan publi-
cized all over the
country :"One less
illiterate means
one more citizen.
A U Cartilla"
For Everyone
,  VER a thous-and school-
centres have been
set up in the
different provinces
since 1944. These
centres organise
the classes which
are held in schools,
barns, factories
and in the open
air, sometimes
with as few as 5
or 6 pupils. Class
 CM/
in (Jd : iJlJJlJl...
.. It was just a year ago to-day... It was ten
years ago... This is our Golden Jubilee... This is
the centenary... Just about a thousand years
ago..."
The birthdays of a child, events in the lives
of individual men and women, commemoration
of the births and deaths of men and women
who have lit torches along the road of history,
red-letter days marking the advance of mankind
- these are dates traditionally noted in the arbi-
trary system of reckoning which we call the
calendar.
Not forgetting the unknown and unsung per-
sons and events, perhaps of equal greatness
making no claim at completeness, here are some
note-worthy dates in October, tenth month of
the Gregorian calendar.
"THE GREAT ENCYCLOPAEDIA"
Two hundred years ago a Paris bookseller
issued a prospectus announcing the early public-
ation of an extraordinary work-a record of all
human knowledge. Subscribers were not disap-
pointed. In a few years, in the face of censure
and legal disputes,"La Grande Encyclopedic"
was brought out as 22 folio volumes with eleven
volumes of plates. The main contributors were
d'Alembert, d'Holbach and Voltaire. But the
moving spirit was Diderot who threw himself
heart and soul into the work. He had become
the servant of". Reason", and his encyclopaedia
remains the boldest monument raised by the
eighteenth century to the glory of scientific
thought.
THE FIRST AEROPLANE
On 24th October 1890,
after 50 years'research, Cle-
ment Ader thought that his
aeroplane, christened"Eole",
was ready for trials. It was
a faithful reproduction of a
large Indian bat, had a
steam engine and retractable
wings and was 21 feet in
length and 45 feet in
breadth. It took off and"---.. 1"...-..
glided for about 55 yards at a speed of 17 yards
a second. For eight years, he made regular tests
and further improvements, but each attempted
flight was a dismal failure. Clement Ader lost
heart, but he watched without envy the work
of his more successful rivals, Santos-Dumont
and the Wright brothers.
GEOFFREY CHAUCER
On 25th October 1400,
Geoffrey Chaucer died under
the shadow of Westminster
Cathedral where he was
buried in the chapel known
to-day as"The Poets'Cor-
ner". Eustache Deschamps,
one of his French contem-
poraries said of him :"he is
the great translator whose
poetry illuminated the reign
of Aeneas". But Chaucer was far more than
a translator : his"Canterbury Tales"belong
not only to his people but to the literary
treasure-house of mankind. Dryden said of
the Tales :"they reflect the varied manners and
moods of the whole English people". In writ-
ing them, he made a selection unheard of in
his day ; his characters were men instead of
mere symbols.
THE SECOND OLYMPIAD
The second Olympic games, inaugurated a
few years previously by Baron Pierre de Cou-
bertin, ended in Paris on 28th October 1900. It
had not been easy to overcome public indiffer-
ence and national jealousies. Greece had been
determined to make Athens, the home of the
first games, the permanent centre of these sport-
ing contests. But Coubertin was adamant :"If
they are to be ultimately successful", he declar-
ed,"the Olympic games must be strictly demo-
cratic and international."But, he had to
persevere for years before sportsmen all over
the world had accepted the ideal he summed up
in the famous statement :"What matters in life
is not victory, but the struggle ; the essential is
not winning but fighting a good fight. In
spreading these principles we will teach mankind
to be more courageous, stronger, more scrupulous
and more generous."
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 12
The Cultural Heritage of Korea
"Land of the Morning Calm))
KOREA'S FLAB
w of the world's most beau-tiful flags, that of the Repu-
lic of Korea has in its centre
a circle of brilliant red and blue
on a white background. Both the
circle and the black bar designs
in the corners are rich in symbo-
lism.
The circle represents the Abso-
lute, or the essential unity of all
being. The Yang and the Yin
divisions within the circle repre-
sent eternal duality ; good and
evil, male and female, night and
day, life and death, being and not
being, etc. The presence of dua-
lity within the Absolute indicates
the paradox of life and the im-
possibility of ever comprehending
it completely.
The bar designs in the four cor-
ners have many meanings. They
represent the Father, the Mother,
the Sons, and the Daughters. The
bar combinations also represent
the four points of the compass,
and the four seas which bound
the universe. The fact that the
bars are of only two kinds (long
and short) yet may be arranged
into many combinations-of
which the four are but samples
- indicates the diversity which
can arise out of basic simplicity.
Actually, the symbolism of the
flag has an endless meaning. It
is sometimes used as an exer-
cise in reasoning, or in develop-
ment of the poetic imagination, as
students interpret the design in
manifold ways. For instance,
the Yang and the Yin, within the
circle, may be likened to the sun
and the moon, to heaven and
earth, to old age and youth, to
beauty and ugliness, to truth and
deception, to success and failure,
to happiness and misery, etc.
From the bar arrangements,
varied moral lessons may be
drawn. Thus the weaker (two
short) bars should be protected
by the stronger (two long ones) ;
but in the opposite corner, the
more precious (long bar) should
be protected by the less worth
(short bars). Like should cling to
like, as in the three long bars
together ; but also, tolerance
should sanction the grouping of
unalike, as in the other two bar
designs.
The significant fact about the
Korean flag is not to draw from
it any one specific meaning, but
rather to recognize that it is a
symbolic and philosophical repre-
sentation, encouraging the mind
to observe and interpret all the
varied meanings of the universe.
It ts this function of the Korean
flag that makes it unique amoag
all the banners of the world :
AND who are these Koreans ? Anonymous John Smith wants toknow-and finds himself repeating like a chant the question of
Walt Whitman :"Yellow man, yellow man, where have you been ?"
Where were the Koreans before the cannons, before the tanks, before the
bombers ? For, just three months ago, Korea became the centre of the
world ; it rose up suddenly, covered
with blood. Rose up from'what
historical past ?
Not so very long ago this past was
little more than a phantom to most
people around the world. A fine co-
lony, whose inhabitants were ordered
to forget their past, their national
soul, even their language which it was
forbidden, under penalty of the whip,
to use in schools, even in playtime.
At the end of the 14th Century,
there was the kingdom of Tyo-Ssyen,
Land of the Morning Calm, with its
capital at Seoul. The land was gov-
erned by a vassal of the Chinese Ming
Dynasty. The rare travellers who
tried to tell the rest of the world about
the treasures of this kingdom attri-
buted a Mongolian origin to this
homogeneous people. They remarked
THE TRADITIONAL DRESS OF THE
COUNTRY, worn by the elderly Korean
examining this ancient bell, was adopt-
ed from the Ming dynasty of China.
For the men it consists of loose white
robes and baggy trousers. Women
wear short, close-fitting jackets and
vividly coloured flowing skirts.
on the individuality of the language
and the simplicity of its alphabet of
25 letters. They recounted a formi-
dable list of discoveries and inven-
tions :
Long known as the"Hermit King-
dom", Korea is said to have evolved,
quite alone, many things which other
nations produced only by united effort :
the spinning wheel, the art of pottery,
movable metal type, paper monkey, the
barometer, even the armour-plated
ships used by Yi Soon-sin to defeat
Japanese invaders in 1592.
The Travellers'Tales
ANCIENT travellers told how educa-tion flourished. They actually
meant Chinese education, for the
Koreans, it seems, did not consider
themselves learned unless they could,
with the light strokes of a brush, show
themselves conversant with the langu-
age of Confucius and work their way
up in the administrative hierarchy,
relying only on the Chinese classics.
They judged their own fine alphabet
too simple, and good enough only for
children.
What high ramparts enclosed this
people ! Only the most poetically in-
clined historians were interested in
them. Records provide a description
of thatched cottages where the Ko-
rean peasant lived, the marriage cere-
monies and a few ritual dances and
traditions of native cooking. Most
travellers gave only a superficial pict-
ure of their own adventures in Korea.
THE SOUTH GATE OF SEOUL. The first king of the Yi dynasty conscripted
200. 000 workmen to construct a : great wall around Seoul, his new capital. Ii
was seven miles long, up to 20 feet wide, from 10 to 20 feet high, and contained
four great gates and four smaller ones. Today, the remains are well inside
the city, which has grown to over a million in inhabitants.
Only a few of them recounted Korean
proverbs.
Yet Korea has a rich collection or
folklore, fables and fairy-tales : Cinde-
rella is called Kongji ; little Red Riding
Hood will be eaten up by the tiger.
Both the tiger and the tortoise figure
as prominently in Korea as in China ;
the genii or jinns are as powerful as
those in Norway.
Well, in what niche at last can be
pigeon-holed this"culture"of the old
ancient lords, of peasants always in
white, always in mourning, of berib-
boned dancers and of the silent silk-
worm breeders crouched on the mud
floor unwinding the silk that they will
never wear ?
Old Beliefs Die Hard
RELIGION may give an answer.There are learned men who give
this explanation : about two
thousand years ago, Buddhism was
introduced into the kingdom of Silla,
accompanied by a now of Chinese
ideas. Buddhism spread its influence
through the princely courts in mar-
vellous works of architecture, piety and
philosophy ;. the temples, still rising
noble and serene above the fir trees
are favourite subjects of the modern
photographer.
Then, Confucianism replaced Bud-
dhism : and the official doctrines of
family and national loyalties were built
on the ruins of monasteries where the
monks eked out a miserable existence,
though still receiving the humble de-
votion of the womenfolk. The ancestor
cult was confined to the educated
class : the masses undoubtedly never
abandoned their old beliefs, their
sacrifices to Heaven, their rites in
honour of the Sun, the Moon and the
Stars. Holy places are still revered,
mountains shelter genii, and under the
sacred trees the passer-by still places
pebbles... In the 15th Century, Korean
learned men compiled an encyclo-
paedia in 112 volumes, but it is doubt-
ful whether they even wrote about
these daily practices of the common
people. In any case, the average Ko-
rean would not have access to these
works, for, like the Official Public
Records, they were not written in his
language.
Yet, for more than a thousand years,
many aspects of Korean art have been
truly great. Experts have spoken of
the pottery of the country as the finest
in the world. It is known that Japa-
nese sculpture developed in the 6th
Century from Korean art and that,
generally speaking, Korea was an
indispensable channel through which
civilization was introduced into Japan ;
for many centuries the Japanese called
Korea the Treasure Land of the West.
What System of Vo/ues ?
TODDY, the sparse accounts ofhistorians and adventurers are
being supplemented by the stories
of war correspondents with their
despatches which describe the extent
of the ruins, the weight of arms, the
thousands of fleeing refugees. The
sufferings of these refugees, some with
hope in their hearts others dulled with
misery, can easily be imagined.
But what system of values have they
now ? Beyond hunger and fear, what
A KOREAN STATUETTE depicting one
of Buddha's disciples.
fantasies fill their dreams ? What do
they think about in their waking mo-
ments ? For already they are begin-
ning to think of the future and their
thoughts will not be created out of
nothing ; the past is still with them
and whatever the future holds will be
influenced and coloured by that almost
forgotten heritage from their ancestors
- in short, by their culture.
It is the duty of every thinking
person to try to understand this people
that war has so brutally thrust into
world prominence, to study the records
of their philosophy and an art of the
highest kind which is still existent
today. He will gain far more than
just an historical background. He will
discover the character and manner of
life of present day Koreans living
under the symbolic nag, in which the
yang and the yin, fire and water, sun
and night, life and death are myster-
iously intertwined.
]]>
</page>
</document>
