<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document id="081543eng">
<page number="1">
<![CDATA[
VOLUME III-No 8 PRICE : 10 Cents (U. S.), 6 Pence (U. K.), or 20 Francs (FRANCE). SEPTEMBER 1950
"THE PRINT COLLECTOR JJ by Honoré Daumier (1808-1879)
)) honor6 Daumier was born during the First French Empire as a subject of Napoleon I. He sawthe fail of the Empire and the Restoration of the Bourbons. He saw the final fall of the Bourbons,
the coming and going of the House of Orteans, the birth and death of the Second Republic,
the beginning and end of the Second Empire and the 70 days of the Paris Commune. He died at
the age of 71 as a citizen of the Third Republic.
) n his lifetime, war, revolution and enemy occupation were more commonplace than peace.
In such a time, Daumier produced 3. 958 lithographs, 300 drawings and 200 paintings-and never
ceased to work and fight for human rights and human dignity. As a painter, he was one of the
founders of modern art. As a man of courage, he inspired other men-in his time and in later
times as well.
As Beethoven died deaf, Daumier died blind. The judgment of posterity was long delayed :
"Daumier's painting seems to stand above Time... It is accessible to every age...""Dau-
mier", by Jacques Lassaigne, Paris and New York, 1938.)
He is only one of the great artists of whom this may be said-and the solace and inspiration
of their work will be living realities in future centuries as in past centuries, in hard times and in
good times. The"print collectors"will survive.
To help bring great art closer to the people, in the troubled days of mid-195O-days which
still await the judgment of history-Unesco has completed and published a catalogue of the finest
reproductions available of paintings which cover the five-century span up to 1860.
For more details and a selection of works from the catalogue, turn to pages 6 and 7.
_- ··
,
r
]]>
</page>
<page number="2">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 2
A HUNDRED GROUPS
WITH
A COMMON AIM
This is the fourth in a series of special articles describing
the work of some of the 100 international non-governmen-
tal organizations whose co-operation with Unesco helps
the accomplishment of its programme.
LONG before modern psychologists
had stressed the importance of
pre-school education,"The
child is father to the man"Was an
old saying which renected the
importance of childhood experience.
The great seventeenth-century phi-
losopher Spinoza said that if he were
given a child to educate for its first
seven years, any education or lack
of it which followed would make
little difference.
In this formative period, children's
capacities for mutual understanding
grow by degrees-the first difficult
adjustments to the rights of others.
If directed toward the wrong ends,
as it was among the Nazis, it leads
to a corrupt view of mankind ; if
handled properly, it develops into
the tolerance and understanding
which the world requires of its
mature citizens to-day. ?
Many aspects of the fundamental
needs of young children including
education, health, school buildings
and children's gardens, were consid'-
ered at a conference called by the
World Organization for Early Child-
hood Education last month in
Vienna. This conference, held with
Unesco's aid, enabled psychologists,
pedagogues and anthropologists to
discuss children's needs and the
requirements of society. Delegates
from pre-schools in Mexico, Great
Britain, and Israel described what
each ; of their various systems
considers a well-spent day for a
small child.
The World Organization for Early
Childhood education is one of the
non-governmental groups ! working
under consultative arrangements
with Unesco, and its efforts are
extremely valuable since it is the
only international organization acting
in this field, with national commis-
sions in eleven countries.
The recognition of children's rights
is an essential foundation of any
civilized society. One of the orga-
nizations working to defend chil-
dren's rights and to help children in
distress is the International Union
for Child Welfare, which has already
helped over 4000 children, many of
them war victims. Recent conferen-
ces have been held by this group on
"Juvenile delinquency provoked by
war"and"Methods of protection of
children", and Unesco has contri-
buted to aid another conference of
experts on social aspects of the
educational problems of child war-
victims.
International
understanding
- the personal approach
THE picture which young peopleget of a 1'foreign country from
history and geography texts
becomes much more real once they
have been in direct contact with the
youth of these countries. To make
such contacts possible, the Inter-
national Federation for School Cor-
respondence and Exchange works
with other groups in twenty-five
countries, encouraging correspond-
ence among students which brings
opportunities for international under-
standing to a personal level. Work-
ing under consultative arrangements
with Unesco the Federation publishes
bulletins in which Unesco's activities,
especially the part its education
programme plays in better inter-
national understanding, are des-
cribed.
A typical international problem,
among the world's universities today
is the linequality of academic de-
grees. A student who graduates
from a universityjtn one country and
continues his studies in that-of
another may find that he receives
little or no academic credit for the
work he has already completed.
The International Association of
University Professors and Lecturers
contracted with Unesco to study this
problem. This group works to
The UNESCO COURIER is an international periodical devoted to the work
of UNESCO and to activities and developments throughout the world in edu-
cation, science and culture.
A full year's subscription (12 issues) costs only $1. 00 US., or 5/-or 200
French Francs.
SUBSCRIBE NOW ! Tell your friends about the UNESCO COURIER and
get them to subscribe too.
Write to our agent in your country listed below, or directly to UNESCO
House, 19, avenue Kléber, Paris, 16', France.
Argentina : Editorial Sudamerica S. A., Alsina 500, Buenos-Aires.
Australia : H. A. Goddard Ltd, 255a, George St., Sydney.
Austria : Wilhelm Frick Verlag, Graben 27, Wien I.
Belgium : Librairie encyelopedique, 7, rue du Luxembourg, Bruxelles IV.
Brazil : Livraria Agir Editora, Rua Mexico 98-B, Caixa postal 3291, Rio-de-Janeiro.
Canada : The Ryerson Press, 299, Queen Street West, Toronto.
ChXe- : Libreria Lope de Vega, Moneda 924, Santiago de Chile.
Colombia : Mr Emilio Royo Martin, Carrera 9a, 1791, Bogo : a.
Cuba : La Casa Belga, Sr. D. René de Smedt, O'Reilly, Havana.
Czechoslovakia : Orbis, Narodni, 37, Praha XII.
Denmark : Einar Munksgaard, 6, Norregade, Copenhagen.
Egypt : Librairie James Cation, 118, rue Emad el Dine, Cairo.
France : Maison du Livre Francis, 4, rue Félibien, Paris (6.). (Booksellers oily)..
Great Britain : H. M. Stationery Office : London : York House, Kingsway (Retail Counter
Service) : P. O. Box 569, London S. E. I. (Post orders).-Manchester 2 : 39-41 King
Street.-Edinburgh 2 : 13a Castle &treet.-Cardiff : 1 St Andrew's Crescent.-
Greece : Eleftheroudakis, Librairie Internationale, Athens.
Hungary :"Ibusz"Akademia-u. 10, Budapest V.
India : Oxford Book and Stationery Co, Scindia House, New Delhi.
Israel : Leo Blumstein, Book Shop, 35 Allenby Road, Tel Aviv.
Italy : Messaggerie Italiane, Via Lomazzo, 52, Milano.
Lebanon and Syria : Librairie Universelle, Avenue des Franglais, Beirut.
Mexico : Libreria Universitaria, Justo Sierra 16, Mexico DF.
Netherlands : N. V. Martinus Nijhoff. Lange Voorhout 9, The Hague.
Norway : AjS Bokhjornet, Stomingsplass 7, Oslo.
Pakistan : Thomas & Thomas, Fort Mansions, Frere Road, Karachi 3.
Peru : Libreria Internacional del Peru, S. A. Gir6n de la Uni6n, Lima.
Philippines : Philippine Education Co, Inc., Corner Tanduay and Vergara Streets,
Quiapo, Manila.
Portugal : Uniao Portuguesa de Imprensa, 198 Rue de S. Bento. 3"Esq., Lisbon
Sweden : C. E. Fritzes Kungl. Hovbokhandel, Fredsgatan 2, Stockholm.
Switzerland : Europa Verlag, 5 Ramistrasse, Zurich.
Turkey : Librairie Hachette, 469, avenue de 1'Independance, Beyoglu, Istanbul.
Union 01 South Africa : Van Schaik's Bookstore, Pty. Ltd., P. O. Box 724, Pretoria.
United States of America : Columbia University Press, 2960 Broadway,'New York
27, N. Y.
Uruguay : Centro de Cooperaci6n Cientifica. Avenida Agraciada 1875 Pontevideo.'For France : Retail sales : Unesco Sales Service, 19, Avenue Kleber, Paris (16').
In the formative period up to seven years of age, children's capacities for mutual under-
standing grow by degrees-the first difficult adjustments to the rights of others. Properly
handled this develops into the tolerance and understanding which the world requires 01 it*
mature citizens. Many international non-governmental organizations are today working with
Unesco to improve the techniques and to apply pre-school education towards this wend.
facilitate the exchange of professors
and students and to help students
from countries, whose educational
facilities are underdeveloped, to
study in other countries.
Students'problems are the concern
of the International Student Service,
which, with two other associations
has formed Ia European fund for
students in need. During and after
the war it distributed more than five
million dollars to universities and
students in Europe and Asia.
One special way in which the
Student Service helped Unesco was
by providing information which was
invaluable in setting up the Inter-
national Bureau of Universities.
This Bureau, created under Unesco
auspices at the conference at Utrecht
two years ago, assembles complete
documentation from universities, so
that professors and students the
world over can obtain information on
educational opportunities, scholar-
ships and conditions of admission in
other countries.
The right to education
- without distinction 01
sex
THE history of education shows usonly too clearly how women's
educational opportunities have
been much slighter than those of
men. Even today this situation still
exists in some countries. Unesco has
been greatly aided by, women's
organizations from many countries
in its effort to end this discrimination.
In a study of the situation at a
conference in Paris last winter,
reports showed that obstacles to the
educational equality of women were
sometimes legal or social, or based
simply on prejudice.
In a number of countries, the law
forbids the entry of women into
certain professions, and thus few or
none study in fields for which they
have great aptitude. Even in some
countries where women theoretically
hold equal rights, there are ten times
as many schools for boys as there
are for girls-a result of the ancient
custom of confining women jin
harems. In one country girls
are not permitted to attend secondary
schools ; in another, girls must go to
work at an early age ; in a third
women are legally allowed to
practice law but fear to do so
because of prejudice.
The International Federation of
University Women, with 130, 000
members in thirty-three countries,
has helped many university-educated
women who could not get the work
they : reserved because pf race,
religious or political beliefs. This is
one of the organizations represented
at the Paris conference, which passed
a number of resolutions aimed at
breaking down the barriers of
prejudice against women. Another
Conference resolution requested
Unesco to promote short-time resid-
ential courses for women, both on
their domestic problems and their
duties as citizens.
All of the women's organizations
which work under consultative
arrangements with Unesco have done
a great deal in making known to the
world the Universal Declaration of
the Rights of Man, as well as their
own campaigns for equality for
women in every field.
. Ilwm1
.
P. u6lk. a1WnA
WORLD COMMUNICATIONS :
PRESS, FILM, RADIO
(200 pages)
"WorM Communications". the
first single-volume survey yet pu-
blished on world facilities in press,
radio, films tlnd televIsion, has
been widely acclaimed by news-
papers and communications expel'ts
in many countries. Published last
May, the boor, was prepared in the
Free Flow of Infol'mation Division
of Unesco's Dcpartment of Mass
Communication.
Unesco sales agents report a
heavy demand fUI'copies, and Ame-
I'ican s"'lOols of journalism are
arranging to use the publication as
a te. l'tbook.
Press reports from Argentine,
Belgium, India, Morocco, Scandina-
visa, the United Kingdom and the
United States show that.. World
Communications"is not only being
widely I'ead but is providing much
information hitherto little known
in ? nany countries.
Points which have aroused par-
ticular comment inelude the follow-
ing : Brilons read the most news-
papers ; India is the second-largest
l'I'oduccl'of featlll'e films ; the So-
l'iet Fnion is the thil'd largest user
of television.
The book was compiled at the
reqllest of the United Nations Sub-
Commission on Freedom of Infor-
mation and of the Press.
""'ol'ld Communications"can be
obtained through Unesco sales
agents. It is priced at $ 1. 20 or 7S.
sterling-01'350 French francs,
TRAINING FOR RADIO
(105 pages)
Factual information on courses in
radio at present being offered by
radio organizations themselve. 0. 1'
by schools. Contains data suppli-
ed by Ii mdio organizations, 10
colleges and training schools in 16
countries. Price : $ 0. 40 2/-F. t00.
PUBLIC LIBRARY EXTENSION
(113 pages)
IJiscnssion of the methods of
ertel/ding public libmry activity to
meet the needs of scattered and
1'111'01 lJOplllations and special
[/rollps in the community. Price :
$ 65 4/-F. 200,
Last month, the first of a series
of newstetters-'A Reader'* Ou) de
to Unesco Publications"-wae sent
out from Unesco House to all parts
of the world.. The purpose of the
newsletters Is to keep people In-
formed about new Unesco publics-
tions, g) *) ng prices and languages
In which they appear, together
with advance news about works In
progress. Facts about three recent
Unesco publications referred to In
the first Newsletter are given below.
]]>
</page>
<page number="3">
<![CDATA[
Page 3-UNESCO COURIER
"It is in the hours 01 dillitulty..."
PRESENTING Unesco's Annual Report to the
Economic and Social Council of the United
Nations, on July 21st, M. Jaime Torres Bodet,
- concluded his. speech by referring to the Orga-
nization's contribution to the United Nations'
work for peace.
M. Torres Bodet said :
"Lastly, we come to a question which set the tone
for the whole of the proceedings in Florence, that of
Unesco's contribution to the United Nations'work for
peace.
'"The General Conference was unanimous in consi-
dering that this was Unesco's essential function.
"It also felt that our Organization's contribution
should not take the form of more or less spectacular
enterprises independent of the programme, for these
might cause confusion and deflect us from our proper
and important tasks. Rather was it thought that the
obligation could be fully met by effective execution
of the Programme.
"True. this Programme, by Unesco's very terms of
reference, is concerned with non-political problems.
It is, however, no less certain that directly or in-
directly, those problems have political repercussions,
relating as they do to nothing less than the social
and spiritual fabric of civilization, Only it must be
realized that in the complex action of the intellectual
on the political, there is little prospect of any im-
mediate effect on the world's fate. The deeper that
action goes, the longer will be the time needed for
its effects to be felt. We must have the courage to
recognize the fact and the patience to accept it.
"Courage and patience alike have never been harder
of attainment than in the anxious days through
which we are living, when peace is assailed by threats
so urgent. Yet for that very reason both have never
been more necessary. At a time when the political
problems of peace have reached their acutest stage
and when the balance of physical power is becoming
an increasingly important element in them. the
assertion of the primacy of the social and in parti-
cular of the spiritual factor-the postulate on which
all our work its based-is an example of the highest
value. Such an affirmation of faith in human pro-
gress is an affirmation of confidence in peace, and
that in itself makes for peace.
A World Will To Unity
"I T is regrettable that the fact of the material inter-dependence of states ha, g worn, acceptance more
swiftly than has the intellectual and moral soli-
darity of peoples. Nevertheless, international co-
operation requires, above all, an international spirit.
That was fully appreciated by the authors of the San
Francisco Charter. When they took up the work of
the League of Nations, they recognized the importance
of undertakings such as the International Labour
Office and provided for a series of Specialized Agencies
whose explicit purpose is to awaken and develop the
international spirit by giving to our interdependent
world the will to unity as a rock to build on and
- setting ua that unity's attainment as its labour's
crown.
"These Agencies are the principal novelty in the
United Nations system. The difficulties of the hour
must not make us forget the great promises which
accompanied their birth nor the constructive possi-
bilities inherent in them. On them largely depends
the establishment of that twentieth-century human
order which has still to be built and even to be
conceived.
"It is, of course, natural that the United Nations
and their Specialized Agencies in action should have
met with a thousand obstacles. They demand from
us all unceasing sacrifices which do not always nor
easily awaken enthusiasm. The need was to streng-
then the political security machinery of the United
Nations and at the same time to assemble resources
great enough so that the Specialized Agencies might
be able to carry out a fruitful work and one which
might not lose sight of the practical reality of daily
life. All this requires great and unceasing generosity.
"Peace-An Unending Creation"
or VEN among men of good will I know that thereare many who ask themselves rather doubtfully
whether the provision of education for the
ignorant, care for the sick and food for the hungry
will really serve to hold off war. Yet if there be one
truth that we should ever keep in mind, it is that
there is no real peace without economic justice and
social progress. To extend the political responsibi-
lities of the United Nations without increasing to a
corresponding or even greater degree the economic
and social activities of the Specialized Agencies would
be to throw the wliole system out of balance and to
repudiate the principles on which it is based. As
things are today, it would mean yielding, under the
guise of realism, to the most disastrous defeatism.
More than ever it is essential that international co-
operation should achieve acceptance by the scope and
effectiveness of what it does, and that the Specialized
Agencies set up to that end should show the people,
by practical achievements and no longer merely by
symbolic illustrations or exhortations, all the dignity
and happiness that peace brings with it.
"Peace has been defined as unending creation. It
is in the hours of difficulty that it is most important
to remember this. It is then above all that humanity
must be made to understand that agencies such as
the International Labour Organization, the World
Health Organization, the Food and Agriculture Orga-
nization and the United Nations Educational, Scien-
tific and Cultural Organization were not created to
knock together a jerry-built world of tomorrow during
an uneasy truce, but to pave the way, despite tensions
or even wars, for the dawn of the economic and
social justice without which there is no true peace."
UNITED NATIONS ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL COUNCIL
PRAISES UNESCO'S PRIORITY WORK PROGRAMME
A CTION taken t) y Unesco toconcentrate and co-ordinate i s
work through the adoption of a
system of priority tasks was strongly
approved by members of the Co-
ordination Committee of the U. N.
Economic and Social Council at
Geneva on July 21st, following presen-
tation of Unesco's annual report by
M. Jaime Torres Bodet.
M. Georges Boris (France) said that
Unesco's report and the decisions of
its General Conference at Florence
showed that it had explored the whole
of the province committed to it. It
had also gained an awareness of the
techniques and methods which it must
apply in order to achieve effective
results. The French delegation, he
said, wished particularly to congratu-
late Unesco on results it had obtained
in the field of specialist collaboration
and exchanges of technical informa-
tion.
Mr. Kotschnig (United States)
remarked that even as recently as this
year's Florence Conference as many as
200 new projects had been proposed.
Seen against such a background, the
most striking characteristic of the Or-
ganization's report was the great
progress made in concentrating pro-
grammes. Unesco was moving towards
the establishment, not only of prior-
ties, but of the classification of its
major programmes in terms of its
limited resources. Unesco, he said,
was the proper international organi-
zation to concentrate upon the promo-
tion of the effective methods of
educating the peoples of under-
developed countries... _
Threefold Technical
Assistance Work
Q EVERAL. speakers referred toUnesco's part in Unit d Nations'
technical assistance activities. Mr.
Entezam (Iran) declared that through
scientific research, the modernization
of education and the dissemination of
educational and cultural material
Unesco was already making a very
considerable, if indirect, contribution to
the welfare of under-developed coun-
tries. Pledging Belgium's support for
Unesco's technical assistance work,
M. Delhaye reiterated his country's
desire to see qualified refugee intellec-
tuals associated in the programme.
Unesco's initiative in undertaking
the creation of an International
Copyright Convention and its efforts to
publicize the Universal Declaration of
Human Rights were welcomed by Mr.
de Alba (Mexico) and Mr. Cabada
(Peru).
Contribution To Peace
and Security
-UNESCO'S work was the subject ofseveral resolutions adopted by the
Economic and Social Council on
August 9th.
The first of these commended
Unesco's efforts to establish priorities
in its work programme and invited its
members to concentrate in future pro-
grammes on projects designed to ad-
vance Unesco's contribution to peace
and security. The same resolution
expressed the hope that this concentra-
tion of effort would result in a reduc-
tion of the number of meetings and
conferences to allow adequate prepara-
M. Georges Boris (France) shown here with
M. Henri Laugier, Assistant Secretary Gene-
rod. United Nations Department of Social
Affairs (right), addressed the Co-ordination
Committee of the Economic and Social
Council during its consideration of the Unesco
annual report. In the face of the special
difficulties 01 the existing international
situation, he told the Committee. Unesco.
and especially its Director-General. were
trying to bring the work which Unesco must
carry out for the peace of the world, into
closer touch with present-day realities.
tion and proper implementation of
their findings. The resolution asked
Unesco to give special attention to the
programme of technical assistance for
under-developed countries.
Other Council resolutions were
aimed at co-ordinating activities relat-
ing to the freedom of information
carried out by the United Nations and
by Unesco and to drawing attention of
Member States to the practical value
of the Unesco Agreement designed to
abolish import duties on educational,
cultural and scientific materials.
ECOSOC RESOLUTION
ON KOREA ;
UNESCO EXECUTIVE
BOARD MEETS
The following is the text of a resolutionunanimously adopied by th  Econo-
mic and Social Council of the United
Nations, meeting in Geneva, on August
14th.
THE ECONOMIC AND SOCIAL
COUNCIL,
Profoundly concerned over the hardship
and suffering wrought upon the people of
Korea by the unlawfu I attack of the North
Korean forces.
Determined to do everything in its power
for the relief and support of the civil popu-
lation of Korea.
Having given due consideration to the
resolution adopted by the Security Councli
on 31 July 1950 and the request addressed
to it in that resolution, under the terms
of Article 65 of the Charter,
Bearing in mind the agreements between
the United Nations and specialized agencies
which provide for the co-operation of these
agencies with the Economic and Social
Council in rendering such assistance to
the Security Council as that Council may
request, and
Deeply conscious of its functions and
responsibilities under Chapters IX and X
of the Charter,
A.
1. Declares its readiness to provide for
such assistance as the Unified Command
may request in accordance with the
above-mentioned resolution.
B.
2. Requests the specialized agencies and
appropriate subsidiary bodies of the
United Nations to lend their utmost
support in providing such assistance as
may be requested by the Unified Com-
mand through the Secretary-General for
the relief and support of the civilian
population of Korea, and authorizes the
Secretary-General to transmit directly to
them such requests for assistance as
fall within their respective fields of
competence ;
3. Invites Governments Members of the
United Nations, the Secretary-General,
and appropriate non-governmental orga-
nizations, particularly those in consul-
tative status with the Economic and So-
cial Council, to assist in developing
among the peoples of the world the
fullest possible understanding of and
support for the action of the United
Nations in Korea and requests the
Secretary-General to seek on behalf of
the Council the co-operation of special-
ized agencies as appropriate for this
purpose ;
4. Authorizes the Secretary-General to
Invite appropriate non-governmental or-
ganizations to give such help as is
within their power for the relief of the
civilian population in Korea, and requests
him to make suitable administrative
arrangements in this connection ;
c.
5. Requests the Secretary-General to
render progress reports to the Economic
and Social Council on action taken under
this resolution and to include when
appropriate such other information and
observations as may be helpful for the
consideration of longer-term measures
for economic and social assistance to
the people of Korea ;
D.
Decides not to close the present ses-
sion when the Council has disposed of
the present agenda but to adjourn it
temporarily, and authorizes the Presi-
dent ; yin consultation with the Secretary-
General, to reconvene the Council at
United Nations Headquarters whenever
necessary in connection with matters
requiring action under this resolution.
As this editiQn of the Courier was
going to press, Unesco's Executive
Board began a special meeting called
by the chairman on the request of
eight members to discuss : <&lt; The
contribution of Unesco to the action
of the Unite'll Nations and Speciali : : ed
Agencies following the aggression
against Korea. >) The Board was also
due to consider the concentration of
Unesco's 1951 programme and the
extent of the Organization's actil'ities
in Germany.
]]>
</page>
<page number="4">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page : e 4
LIBRARIES-A NEGLECTED RESOURCE
Unesco Seminar proposes active
programme for adult education
"p l'BLIC lib1Ylries can,'be and indeed in some cases are among the
most effective agencies now existing for the continuing educa-
lion of great masses of people", according to a resolution of
the Unesco Seminar on libraries in adult education just held
in Malrno, Sweden.
The.'can be"is the justification Tor this four weeks'workshop for
professional librarians specially interested in adult education, arran-
ged by Unesco. The fact is that the potentialities of public libraries
are far from being realized or even recognized in many parts of the
world. It is also true that the public library movement is on the
move. This is clear from recent advanced made in many countries
and from the place public library development occupies in Unesco's
programme.
The progress is very uneven,
however ; indeed in some regions
it has not even sorted. The cen-
tral idea of this seminar was
to pool the best practices and
theories, to focus attention on the
role of libraries as educational
agencies and to reach agreement
on standards.
By the end of the seminar, the
48 participants from twenty
countries had produced a number
of clearly formulated recommend-
actions as to how libraries best
can aid popular education.
Some of these recommendations
are directly addressed to Unesco ;
others should ra. ther be regarded
as pointers to everyone engaged in
public library work and planning.
Library services in India, Ceyton. Egypt, the Argentine, France, Italy and Great
Britain are represented among these members of a study group at the Unesco
Seminar on Libraries in Adult Education, held at Malmo, Sweden. This group
was concerned with the ways in which libraries can help mass. education in
the large under-developed areas of the world.
library is a service organization
bringing educational and recrea-
tional aids to the people. These
aids are not only made out of
printed words. The spoken word
through radio, gramophone and
lecture, the image through film,
lantern-slide and poster and even
the combination of these two
modern techniques in tele\ vision
, UNESCO ACTIVITIES IN GERMANY
- N 1948, following the General
t Conference resolution passed atM xico City in 1947, Unesco,
acting in agreement and co--
operation with the appropriate
Allied Authorities, extended its acti-
vities to Western Germany and
opened its first office in Stuttgart.
A year later further offices were
opened at Mainz and Diisseldorf.
One of the first tasks of these
offices has been to make known
the aims and purposes of the
Organisation, both to the German
public generally by means of press,
radio, exhibitions and lectures, as
well as by the distribution of Unesco
literature and pamphlets translated
into German for this purpose, and
also to academic and other interested
circles by means of free distribution
or sale of Unesco's more specialised
publications and periodicals, as well
as by personal contacts. Requests
for material for distribution in
schools, for student libraries, for
exhibitions or for special broadcasts,
to mention but a few of the pur-
poses, are constantly increasing and
the needs are fulfilled as far as iSI
possible by these three offices.
Other important fields of activity
extended to Germany within the
framework of Unesco's programme
include the exchange of publications,
the exchange of persons, the study
of textbooks and the social sciences.
The exchange of publications bet-
ween German libraries and the li-
braries of Member States has been
greatly facilitated by the creation of
an Exchange Centre at Bad-Godes-
berg, financed by the Notgemein-
schaft des Deutschen Wissenschaft
(Emergency Council for German
Science). The extension of the
Unesco Book Coupon Scheme to Ger-
many, where it will shortly come
into operation, will provide a further
valuable means for German libraries
to acquire much needed foreign books
and periodicals without the compli-
cated procedure and long delays
which are at present inevitable.
Frequent enquiries are received at
the offices in Germany concerning
the possibilities of exchange and
study abroad by students, teachers
and many young people anxious to
come into contact with young people
of other nationalities. Information
is given on exchange agencies in
other countries and where possible
contacts are facilitated. The hand-
book"Study Abroad"has proved a
much sought after publication in
German universities, and the offer
of the first Unesco fellowship-in
the field of Youth Education-in
Germany has aroused a large res-
ponse.
IN co-operation with the appro-priate rogramme departments f
Unesco several studies have been
initiated in Germany. One of these
has been concerned with the post--
war preparation and production of
textbooks. Within the field of
Unesco's Tensions Project a sociolo-
gical study is at present in progress,
which is particularly concerned with
the attitudes of youth. In addition
studies are being carried out on the
problems and experiments in dealing
with war-handicapped children on
the problems with which youth is
faced with the purpose of enabling
those concerned with youth ques-
tions to gain a better understanding
of the problems of youth in Ger-
many and of their relationship to
other members of the international
community.
The Director-General, following
the recommendation of the General
Conference at its Third Session, esta-
blished a Committee of Experts to
One of the aims of Unesco's work in Germany is to encourage the activities 01 orga-
nizations carrying out adult education there. One of these organizations i  the
Federation'n of German Trade Unions for Western Germany under whose auspices the
Ruhr Theatre Festival was held this Summer. During the Festival. whose aim is to
bring to the workers an understanding of European culture in its widest sense. German
actors (above) presented Shakespeare's'King Lear".
advise him on matters affecting the
programme of Unesco's work in Ger-
many, and this Committee convened
for its first session in May 1949.
The Committee is composed of re-
presentatives from Belgium, Czecho-
slovakia, France, Netherlands, Nor-
way, Poland, Switzerland, United
States of America and the United
Kingdom, who meet periodically to
study the progress of Unesco's acti-
vities in Germany and to advise on
its future programme as well as on
any special projects which might be
carried out in that country.
The Commitee of Experts met
recently in Unesco House, Paris, to
consider the creation of an inter-
national centre for youth activities,
an international social sciences ins-
titute and an international pedago-
gical institute in Germany. The
Committee welcomed Unesco's pro-
posal to support special projects in
these fields, but felt convinced that
if these projects were to be carried
out full collaboration from German
circles anxious to work in the inte-
rests of international understanding
would be essential. The Committee
made a number of recommendations
designed to ensure the permanent
and international character of these
institutes.
FROM the time that Unescostarted its activities in Germany
keen interest has been shown by
Germans in the Organisation's work
in their country. In response to an
increasing desire to participate more
actively, a group of personalities re-
presenting all spheres of cultural life
in Germany met last January in
Bad-Soden near Frankfurt to consi-
der the means by which Unesco's
activities could be furthered through
German initiative, and to this end
decided that preparatory work for
the creation of a German Committee
for Unesco Activities should forth-
with be undertaken. An Interim
Committee was formed and has been
co-operating since that time with the
Secretariat Offlces in Germany in
various fields of their ·nrk, such as
in the selection of participants for
Unesco meetings and seminars, in
many cases also providing financial
aid to such participants for their
travel. Assistance has also been
given in obtaining German contri-
butions to recent Unesco publications,
such as the Index Translationem
and the Catalogue of Photographic
Archives of Works of Art.
It is expected that the permanent
Committee will be finally constituted
at a meeting to be held at the end
of September. In order to cover the
various activities of Unesco the Com-
mittee will comprise the following
groups : Arts and Literature ;
Science : Education : Press ; Radio
and Film. It will receive direct
financial support from the German
Federal Government.
It is hoped that the formation of
the Committee will lead to increased
active participation in Unesco's work
and afford to Germans greater
opportunities for partaking in and
contributing to international co--
operation in the fields of education,
science and culture.
now belong within the domain of
the librarian in the service of the
community.
This study-group formulated a
minimum, median and maximum
programme for the audio-visual
services of libraries. The mini-
mum programme which the Seminar
commends to all libraries requires
at least the establishment of an
effective community film inform-
ation service.
Unesco was asked to publish an
international list of selected films
of universal interest in the field
of adult education.
The work and recommendations
of this group huve meant a real
step forward towards the recogn-
ition of the film's rightful place
in public library services... An effective library service
forms an indispensable and integral
feature of any fundamental eduction
Programme", the third study-group
stated. This group was concerned
with libraries in the aid of mass
education in the large under-
developed areas of the world and
many of its recommandations were
addressed fo Unesco, an organisation
which since its start has devoted
much of its programme to funda-
mental education.
LlBRAIRIES-AND ILLITERACY
THIS group had to consider thelibrarian's problem in a
community that is mainly
illiterate but tun the process of
learning how to read and write.
The school system in such an area
is still inadequate, no libraries
exist. The educational experiment
to introduce reading materials is on
a'". pre-book" basis. The librarian
has to be a pioneer clearing new
paths, often in the face of op-
position and despondency and with
very scantv material means.
The forty-page report produced
by this group, in the work of which
professionals from all the conti-
nents participated, is itself a
valuable handbook jn librarv
planning and practice in the under
developed regions.
The group chairman was the li-
brarian of the Musée de 1'Homme in
Paris,. Mile Yvonne Oddon, whose
experience in the field, includes
Unesco's fundamental education
pilot project in the Marbial vallev,
Haiti.
The whole Seminar benefited
from the fact that the modern
town library of Malmo had been
chosen as the site. This model li-
brary is a fine example of the pro-
gressive Swedish public library
system and many of the participants
could not but feel envious when
they saw what excellent library
facilities are at the free and easy
use of the people of Malmo and
the province of Scania..
The results of a seminar cannot
be judged only from the reports
and recommendations produced.
The real results will come when
the words are translated into action,
when the new techniques have
been put into practice, new build-
ings erected, services expanded
and improved. This will happen
when the participants are back in
their communities and after their
colleagues and public opinion have
been given the opportunity to
benefit from their widened outlook
and improved skills.
Both kinds constitute impulses to
action on the local, national and
international plane.
Director of the seminar, which
used the discussion group techni-
que, was Dr. Cyril 0. Houle, Dean,
University college, University of
Chicago, who also led the work of
the group studying the organization
and administration of library adult
education programmes.
BOOKS-ONLY THE BEGINNING
THE modern conception i ?
much broader than the one
once commonly held of public
libraries as places where indi-
viduals caÌ1 borrow books and scan
newspapers. The modern public
]]>
</page>
<page number="5">
<![CDATA[
Page 5-UNESCO COURIER
To interrupt the cruel cycle ofsickness, hunger, weaS'-
ness, lassitude, ignorance
- and again the sickness
and hunger-Unesco during H) 49
organized an experiment in
collaboration with the Chinese
Mass Education Movement, which
was already carrying out practi-
cal fundamental education work
there.
The purpose of the project was
to prepare sample materials-
particularly audio-visual aids for
fundamental education-which
could be of use to educators in
other parts of the world. The
subject to be dealt with was given
the title of"The Healthy Village",
and the international team car-
rying out the project set out to
produce, with the help of local
artists, materials designed to en-
courage hygiene and defeat
disease.
By May, these artists, adapting
themselves to entirely new condi-
tions, had produced a first series
of posters, mobile posters, book-
lets and film strips dealing wit !)
the causes of and protection
against such diseases as small-
pox, trachoma and tetanus.
It was difIicult at first to per-
suade the Chinese artists to draw
anything as repulsive as a child's
face marked with smallpox or
eyes inflamed with trachoma.
But, once convinced that people
must be shocked into action by
seeing the terrible effects of these
diseases, they brought to their
work the patience and delicacy
which characterize the Chinese
artist.,-
Filmstrips Without
. A Camera
owE months later, Unesco sent
out to China Norman McLaren.
a young Canadian who had
been working for several years
with the Canadian National Film
Board. Under his guidance and
inspiration, the art centre at
Pehpei produced an impressive
total of static and mobile posters,
wall sheets, picture books and film
strips all teaching a simple but
vivid lesson in hygiene and the
prevention of disease.
When these materials were
"tested"in the local villages it was
found that the greatest effects
were achieved through the use of
film strips and mobile posters.
McLaren therefore began to ex-
periment with new methods of
filmstrip production. His efforts
led to some striking results by the
use of direct art work on the film.
Instead of using the normal film-
strip technique of drawing pictures
and then photographing them,
McLaren and his team did their
pictures directly on 35 mm motion
picture film.
Pictures were made on both
clear and black film by two basic
methods : (a) applying ink, paint or
colour to the film with pen or
brush and (b) removing the black
photographic emulsion (also ink,
paint or colour applied to the film)
by etching or scraping with a sharp
instrument. Cross combinations of
these methods produced a further
variety of mixed methods.
One advantage in using this di-
reet method was the speed of pro-
duction. This was found to varv
between one quarter to one tenth
the time required by the standard
method. In other words, the same
idea executed by painted drawings
CHINESE AR. T ! STS
And Unesco Experts
Find New Roads To
"THE HEALTHY VILLAGE"
One of the most successful audio-visual devices to teach health lessons
developed by the Unesco Project in China was the rotating wheel poster. This
photo, taken near Pehpei. shows a health worker demonstrating one of the
posters illustrating in eight stages how eyes inflamed by trachoma become
bright and healthy again with regular treatment. After a talk on trachoma.
the Unesco health worker would examine and treat people, leaving the poster
for the crowd to look at and operate themselves.
form when the village was visited
a second time.
Seeing themselves on the screen
was a novelty which attracted the
people in hundreds and created a
warmth of interest which helped
them, to understand why they
should get vaccinated against small-
pox and continue regular treatment
for trachoma. Above all, it made
them health conscious and more
ready to co-operate in the cam-
paign.
All Educators Will Benefit
THE work of the Pehpei project
has come to an end, but world-
wide use is to be made of the
reports which cover the adminis-
t. rative, art production, field work
and health activities carried out by
its members.
The reports, illustrated by pic-
tures taken during the work, are to
be published by Unesco in the
form of a monograph and made
available. to all educators in the
field of fundamental education.
Copies of the audio-visual mate-
rials prepared by Norman McLaren
and his team are being made and
Two-way posters were used by the Unesco team in Pehpei
to convey two alternative and contrasting health messages.
such as"Do"and"Don't"on a certain topic, or"The good
way"and"the bad way". In these photos, the two posi-
lions of the same poster show (left) a trachoma victim
who failed to take regular treatment and (right) the same
man when his trachoma was cured after a 21-day treatment.
These posters successfully brought home the lesson.
Instead of using the normal filmstrip method of drawing
pictures and then photographing them, Unesco Project artists
drew directly on 35 mm film. The Chinese artist (above)
is working on clear film on which ink, paint or colour can
be applied with paint or brush. h second method (above,
right) was to use black film. making pictures by the
removal of the black photographic emulsion (also ink, paint,
or colour applied to the film) with a stylus or kniff.
and later photographed which took
six weeks to carry out would take
about six days if translated directly
on film.
The fastest production at Pephei
was an 84-frame filmstrip made in
1 days and even the longest, a
6i frame filmstrip, only took six
days.
Put To The Test
arEa completed these filmstrips
were taken with other audio-
visual materials for testing
in local viHages. Members of the
Unesco team, including Dr. Clara
Nutting, the American head of the
Health Department, Mr. E. J. Fan,
Chinese head of the Field Depart-
ment and a Chinese commentator
and projectionist, travelled to the
villages, their ear piled high with
films, equipment and medical sup-
plies.
In the evenings they put on
shows in the village schools or
squares showing four or five film-
strips interspersed with records ofChinese music. These ended with
an announcement telling people to
come back for a medical examina-
tion the next day.
Sometimes as many as 600 people
turned up to have their eyes exam-
ined for trachoma and often one
third of them were found to be
suffering from this disease which,
if left unchecked, can cause total
blindness. In one : period of
23 days, Dr. Nutting examined 6. 389
persons-47 per cent of the po-
pulation,--and found that 251%
had trachoma.
The ueasants themselves became
"actors in several"actuality"
filmstrips. Pictures were taken of
the village folk attending a film
show or receiving treatment and
these were then projected in slide
will be loaned to governments, or-
ganizations and individuals carry-
ing out other projects where this
type of work has started or is about
to begin.
Unesco filmstrips showing de-
tails of the various techniques used
by McLaren will be made and the
young Canadian is himself prepar-
ing a special post-project report
outlining the methods he developed
at Pehpei and the equipment he
used.
In breaking new ground, espe-
cially by developing the use of di-
rect art work on filmstrips and
filmslides, and by providing ans-
wers to some of the problems in-
volved in reaching and driving
home health lessons to large num-
bers of people, Unesco's Project has
done valuable work. Its results
will be appreciated and used wher-
ever men and women are striving
to help their fellow c to live better
and fuller lives.
]]>
</page>
<page number="6">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 6
WIZ FINEST COLOUR P
To help bring wider understandingand enjoyment of outstanding
works of art to the largest
possible number of persons, Unesco
has published a 180-page catalogue of
fine colour reproductions of great
paintings done before 1860, which are
available at moderate prices. More
than 500 years of painting are
represented by 418 of the works of
170 masters, chosen from among more
than 2, 000 reproductions offered by
the principal publishers of the world.
The great majority of people in the
world can never hope, for geographical
reasons alone, to enter the museums
and galleries where most of the
famous art treasures are housed,
points out Dr. H. Gerson, Deputy-
Director of the National Bureau for
the Documentation of Art History,
The Hague. Dr. Gerson, one of the
experts who made the selection of
reproductions for Unesco, wrote in
his introduction to the catalogue :
"Unesco, an organization whose
scope is world-wide and which is
unhampered by prejudice or the
burden of any particular tradition, is
acting on behalf of the millions of
people who live far from museums and
galleries".
The standards of choice of the
reproductions contained in the catalo-r
gUe were the significance of the
artist, the importance of the painting,
and the fidelity of the reproduction.
But the element which makes the
work an especially useful instrument
in Unesco's programme of demo-
cratization of art is the revelation
that colour reproduction of some of
the world's finest paintings are
available at low prices. There are
Fra Angelicos, Bellinis and Goyas
which can be bought for 25 cents
each ; a dozen different Giottos at
$ 1 each ; and even the more costly
reproductions are priced no higher
than $ 15 to $ 20.
The working party of experts who
made the selections at meetings held.
at Unesco House in Paris, was nomin-
ated by the International Council of
Museums. It included, in addition to
Dr. Gerson, Charles Sterling and
Hélène Adhémar of the Louvre in
Paris, Sir Philip Hendy of the National
I 2 3
t The Birth of Venus" (detail), Sandro"BOTTtCELL (1444-1510), It ly.
2."Georges Washington", GilbertSTUART(1755-1828), U. S. A.
3"The Tribute Money", TITIAN (1477-. 1576), italy.
d'portrait of Moretto", Hans HOLBEIN. (1497-1543), Germany.
C Don ManuetdeZuniga", Francisco"'de GOYA (1746-1828). Spain.
A the Judgement of Paris", Anton Van"DYCK (1599-1641), Flemish.
7 A Man and a Tea House Maid", KIYO-. SAGA (1742-1815), Japan.
"man in Red", SHAH MUHAMMAD. (Tabr z SchoolXVlth century), Persia.
"man with Golden Helmet", REM-"BRANDT (1606-1669). N therlands.
"the Forest of Coubron", Jean-Baptiste'-'COROT (1796-1879), France.
7 8
171615
1281
]]>
</page>
<page number="7">
<![CDATA[
Gallery in London, Professor Mario
Salmi of Rome, and Professor J. Pijoan
of Chicago.
Each reproduction is printed in the
catalogue in black and white, accom-
panied by precise details in French,
English and Spanish about the
painting, the painter, and also the
reproduction. In each case, the
reader can learn exactly where he can
buy the reproduction and at what
price.
The catalogue brings to completion
a Unesco project of compiling a list of
good available colour reproductions
begun last year with the publication
of a similar volume, containing 423
separate items covering the period
from 1860 to 1949. It was pointed out
by Jean ICassou, Director of the
Museum of Modern Art of Paris, who
wrote the introduction to the earlier
volume, that"Colour reproduction
stands in the same relation to visual
art as does the radio or gramophone
record to music : it is an inter-
mediary".
Unesco aims to do more than to
help make more pictures available to
more people. For one thing, the
catalogues draw the attention of
publishers of colour reproduction to
the fact that many great paintings
have never been properly reproduced.
Publishers have already begun to fill
in existing gaps.
Another purpose is to encourage
publishers to improve the standards of
colour prints. Three-quarters of the
prints submitted for use in the second
volume of the catalogue had to be
rejected. It is hoped that publishers,
recognizing in the catalogues a
potential frame of reference of excel-
lence in the field, will seek to bring
their prints up to a standard meriting
inclusion in future editions.
MM CATAlOGUED BY UNESCO
Page 7-UNESCO COURIER
654
9 10
18 89 20
13 14
The Two Unesco Catalogues of Colour Repro-
ductions of Paintings may. be obtained from
Unesco Sales Agencies, listed on Page 2 of this
issue, or from the Division of Distribution and
Sates. Unesco, 19, Avenue K) eber. Paris (16-).
The price of the catalogue of paintings prior
to 1860 is 82. 10-, 600 francs ; the price of the
catalogue of paintings from 1860 to 1949
!'B 1. 50, 8/-, 400 francs.
]]>
</page>
<page number="8">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 8
AN INDIAN GIRL WITH A
LESSON FOR HUMANITY
ON July 18, Unesco issued a statement-the. work of twenty
scientists-designf'd to expose the hateful myth that one
.'race"is inherently superior to another.
On the basis of known facts about human race the anthro-
pologists and sociologists were unanimous in their opinion that racial
discrimination has no scientific foundation in biological facts.
To make known this important statement-the first step in a cam-
paign against racial prejudice and ignorance-Unesco mobilized all
its resources. The radio division sent out more than 400 releases, and
special recordings in ten languages reached 48 countries. Feature
articles went to more than 1500 newspapers around the world while
press releases were sent to newspapers, magazines and all United
Nations and Specialized Agency offices.
Thus, millions of men and women in all parts of the world read the
following assertion in one paragraph of the declaration :
"according to present knowledge, there is 110 pl'00t that the gl'OUpS
IN the Parana forests of Paraguaylive the Guayaki Indians, one of
the most primitive and least
known Indian tribes of South
America. M. J. Vellard, a French
ethnologist working for the Musée de
1'Homme in Paris, had spent many
months wandering through the
forest in search of these Indians
when, exactly eighteen years ago, he
unexpectedly found himself face to
face with them.
He went toward them, but the
answer to his gestures of friendship
was a flight of arrows ; his Para-
guayan guides opened fire and the
Indians fled in terror into the
undergrowth abandoning their stone
axes, their primitive huts and their
enormous arrows pointed with wood.
A few hours later Vellard's guides
returned with an unusual prize.
They were carrying, slung on a pole,
a small brown creature which Vel-
lard at first took for a monkey. To
his astonishment and indignation he
discovered that it was a little girl of
two whom his men had gagged with
leaves and whose arms and legs they
had bound so as to carry her more
easily. They were hoping to sell her
to some farmer in the district for a
hundred pesos or so.
The Guayaki Indians are the last
representatives of a very primitive
and rudimentary culture. Like their
neighbours they speak Guarani, but
unlike them are not sedentary. They
live almost exclusively by hunting
and gathering fruits, and wander at
large in the forest. Their hunting is
done with bows and arrows, the
latter being among the longest in the
world, while they use stone axes to
open up tree trunks and extract
honey, of which they are particularly
fond.
UNESCO NEEDS THE
SUPPORT OF WOMEN
A call to women throughout theworld to.. tolloc, suppor, t
and aid Unesco's tL'Ork"was
made bye. Jaime Torres Bodet,
Director General. before a ga-
thering of delegates from thirty
countries attending, a conference
of the International Federation of
University Women at Zurich.
The Conference marked the thir-
tieth anniwrsarv of the Fede-
ration's foundation.
The fields in which their assis-
tance was especially necessary,
: \1. Torres Bodet said, were
popular culture or, more accu-
rately, adult education, the pro-
blem of.-maladjusted children
and teaching for international
understanding. There are few
forms of injustice graver than
those which cut oil whole classes
or populations from civilization... But thl'oughout the'U'ortd, adult
educ/, Ition e. rperts are only a
handtul of men and IrOlllen over-
whelmed by the sheer vastness
of their lask. Who will help
them it not you. ?" till-'Oirector
General asked.
Of maladjusted children he
"aid, in part :.. If ow'genetalion
resi ! llI. s itself to a tCÎcked indifte-
reliCI'to" :/lrd Ihese child !'e/ !, it
must also abandon erery hope ot
peace Ilnd juslice ; fO/'these, the
wlfit, ignoranl, de : s1ífute and I. te. s-
pcf'Mte are lhe dli : : ells of tOIllO !'-
rot".
(JøcltøøfledWøy 01 Lile
THEIR worldly goods are very few
- baskets which they make
water-tight with wax, tools of
bone, a few necklets and lengths of
rope. Their dwellings are huts of
One ot the few photographs ever taken of a
member of the Guyaki tribe. Roaming the
dense forests of eastern Paraguay this man
and his fellows are limited by circumstances
to a primitive life. Yet, as a child he
possessed all the latent capacities for civil-
ised life in any part of the modern world.
boughs which they can erect in a few
minutes in the deep forests where
they live withdrawn from other
men. Probably their way of life is
very little different from that of the
first bands of men who colonized the
empty spaces of South America,
thousands of years ago.
As a result of being hunted by
other Indian tribes and Whites alike
the Guayaki have become timid and
suspicious. Today we know little
more about them than was known
to the Jesuits who tried to convert
them in the l7th century, and we
have only been able to secure a little
hazy information about their customs
from the few captives serving
farmers or settlers in Parana as
slaves.
Their primitive state might be
logically ascribed to racial inferiority,
but it is here that the story of the
captive ! child takes on its full
significance.
Out of pity, Vellard bought her for
a few pesos without thinking much
about what he, would do with her.
It was only later that he began to
wonder whether chance had not
given him an opportunity to show
that education and cultural back-
ground were more powerful than
the so-called laws of race alleged to
govern the development of the
individual.
Like A EuropelUl C'd'If
HE had grown fond of the childwith her gentle face and
friendly eyes. So, the little
Indian was christened Marie-Yvonne
of mankind differ in theiJ. innate mental charactel'istics. whether in
respect of intelligence 01'temperament. The scientific evidence indi-
cates that the l'ange of mental capacities in all ethnic groups, is much
the same".'
Reading these words, many people wanted to know if there are
actual case histories which can'''p1'Ove''to laymen the facts known
to the scientists. On this page the Courier presents the remarkable
story of Marie-Yvonne Vellard, a child of one of the most primitive
tribes on earth, found as a baby in the Parana forests of Paraguay 18
years ago. Today, aged 20, she works as an assistant to her adoptive
father, the French ethnologist who found her, and is regarded as
"superiOl"Ito most white girls of hel"age'in intelligence and agility"
The story of Marie-Yvonne Vellard is far from unique, for the
whole world is full of proof that :'''... given similar degrees of cul-
tural opportunity to l"ealize theil'potentialities, the average achieve-
ment of the members of'each'ethnic group is about the same"
and brought up by Vellard's* mother,
exactly like a French child. A few
months after her capture and
adoption she was already beginning
to speak a few words of French and
behave like a European child of the
same age. With her high cheek-
bones and black eyes she could have
passed for a Japanese or even a
child from the Northern provinces of
Argentina.
Less than a year after the start of
her new life her speech and manners
were better than those of a European
child of the same age. At the age
of seven she was already speaking
French and Portuguese and liked to
ask questions about Greek my-
, thology.
Art among the Guyaki people is
limited to the decoration of weapons,
calabashes and implements with dots,
dashes and strokes, yet, at an early
age, Marie-Yvonne was able to draw,
although she had never received in-
struction.
SLAVE OR SCHOLAR ? For this little Guyaki
girl, whose photograph was taken about
1899. the answer was probably slavery.
There was a happier answer for another
little Indian girl found eighteen years ago
in a Paraguay forest by the French scientist
Jehan Vellard. She is now his adopted
daughter and a member of a cultured socie-
ty. The only difference was... opportunity.
A European scientist who has
followed the case of iMarie-Yvonne
from the time she was brought back
to Lima, Peru, where she still lives,
has described her as"perhaps
superior to most white girls of her
age."She was, in fact, usually top
in every class at school and today,
as a biology student, she assists her
adoptive father in his laboratory.
Cultural Transformadoll
SHE was brought up exactly as awhite girl and though she is
completely aware of her* origin,
she takes no notice of the fact that
her skin is of a different colour to
that of her white friends.
Today, the Indian child, whose
kinsfolk are perhaps still hunting in
the Parana and felling trees with
stone axes, is an attractive, intelligent
girl of twenty and a typical product
of the cultural environment in which
she has lived for 18 years.
The story of Marie-Yvonne is not
unique. Hundreds of similar cases,
involving young native children born
among what are judged as extremely
primitive peoples, can be cited.
Providing a child is removed from
its cultural environment before it is
old enough to have been influence,
it can be completely assimilated into
"THE ONE STRAIT WHICH ABOVE
ALL OTHERS HAS BEEN AT A
PREMlUM IN THE EVOLUTION <JF
MEN'S MENTAL CHARACTERS HAS
BEEN EDUCABILITY, PLASTICI1T.
THIS IS A TRAIT WHICH ALL
HUMAN BEINGS POSSESS. IT JS,
INDEED, A SPECIES CHARACTER
OF HOMO SAPIENS,"
Extract from the Unesco Declaration
on Race, July l8th, 1950.
new surroundings. Like all human
beings it has innate aptitudes, but
none which can be considered as
belonging exclusively to the race of
which it is issue.
The lesson taught by the story of
Marie-Yvonne and hundreds like it
is that all human beings of normal
intelligence are capable of playing
their part in any form of civilization.
And it highlights one of the state-
ments made in the Unesco Race
Declaration-"The myth of race
still prevents the normal develop-
ment of millions of human beings
and deprives civilization of the
effective co-operation of productive
minds."
Study of Brazilian
ethnic groups will
help Unesco to
fight race prejudice
THE history of European coloniza-tion in South Americ  is full of
countless tales of bloodshed.
Brazil is no exception. It has been
the scene of bitter fighting between
different ethnical groups which some-
times ended in appalling massacres.
Yet this hostility never assumed any
permanent, collective form. Brazil is
one of the few countries which has
never known those systems of legal
oppression practised by ruling whites
over the slave masses and known as
the"Black Laws". The abolition of
slavery, which created such grave so-
cial problems in the United States,
was effected in Brazil without inci-
dent. Racial prejudice, cause of
bitter conflict in so many parts of the
earth, is so slight that it is frequently
confused with class prejudice.
What is the reason for this ? It is
difficult to find a satisfactory answer.
Unesco is making a study of ethnic
groups in Brazil as part of its general
campaign against race prejudice,
which is such a serious threat to world
peace. At the last General Conference
at Florence a resolution was passed
to make researches into Brazilian
anthropology, sociology and social
psychology for the purpose of discov-
ering the reasons for this historical
development.
There is much more than scientific
interest in this undertaking. The
results which can be anticipated from
such a wide enquiry will probably give
precise details of the origin of racial
prejudice. Then it will be possible to
attack this problem at its source and
endeavour to eradicate conditions
favourable to its development.
]]>
</page>
<page number="9">
<![CDATA[
Page 9-UNESCO COURIER
dW. w 
ajþm Sodldq
SCIENCE impinges on. society in
two main ways : techno-
logically. by changing the
material conditions of life.
work and production ; and intel-
lectually, by changing the way in
which men think. The former is
the more striking, since at least in
the more advanced countries every-
body is in minute-to-minute
contact with things that have
arisen from scientific research.
Clearly a high standard of living
is dependent on the use of devices
produced by scientific technology
or the use of more traditional
articles, now produced more chea-
ply and abundantly by science.
Many of the problems that face
the world today can be solved only
with the aid of science. The
problem of world food shortage-a
doubling of output is required to
BASED upon the beliefthat to-day there is more need than ever before to under-stand the full significance of the impact of science on society, Unesco has begun
publication of a bulletin of abstracts. Entitled"Impact", this bulletin collects
information on the various aspects of the international and social implications
of science and presents the material in the form of abstracts.
The first issue contains an introductory statement on the impact of science
on society (published on this page) and a bibliography of the main"historically
important"literature in English.
The second issue (Juty-September.) 1950) contains details of the papers pre-
sented at the important Fourth World Power Conference held in London in
July, 1950. Also a bibliography of films on world power and energy.
There are current abstracts in the form of reports of recent addresses given
by the world's leading scientists.
"impact", a quarterly bulletin, is obtainable from Unesco, t 9, Avenue Kieber,
Paris, France, or from the usual Unesco sales agents. Price 26 cents, Is. 6d.,
75 francs per issue.
give everybody a sufficiency-can
be greatly alleviated and eventually
solved by the proper application of
science.
The application of science does
not merely solve a few problems ;
its cumulative effect changes the
. shape of social life, as can be seen
by considering the consequence of
the development of electrical
StIENtE tIlfRS TEAtH tANADIAN
YOlfTH TO PROTEtT ITS
tOIJNTRY'S NATlfRAL 81tHES
The world-wide mo-
yement of science
clubs covers many
aspects of the study 01
science. In Canada
there is a great
emphasis, for example.
on the protection 01
nature (described in
the article below).
Finland has, in many
respects,'been a
pioneer country for
science clubs. It was
the first country to
give science club
members free admis-
sion to the laboratories
and other facilities
of the universities
and technical schools.
This photo shows
Science Club members
attending a course in
chemistry at a Finnish
university.
IN Canada today over 100, 000 boysand girls are learning to combine
a knowledge of science with an
interest and respect for the natural
riches with which nature has endowed
their country.
They are members of Canadian
Science Clubs, whose general aim is to
keep young country people from leav-
ing the soil and to create an outlook
favourable to the protection of Cana-
da's natural riches.
As might be expected in a country
abounding with natural resources,
where the use of the soil, forests,
mines and fisheries plays an impor-
tant part in the nation's economy, the
work of the clubs has so far been
devoted to natural science.
A report on the activities of the
clubs specially written for Unesco by
the"Association Canadienne-Fran-
çaise pour 1'Avancement des Sciences",
reveals the rapid progress they have
made in the last twenty years.
A good example of this growth is
offered by the"Cercles de Jeunes
Agriculteurs"formed about forty years
ago with the aims of introducing
young country people to agriculture
and communal life, giving them prac-
tical knowledge of agriculture and do-
mestic economy, encouraging the use
of improved methods on the farm and
in the home and training boys and
girls to be good citizens.
The movement spread slowly at first,
but after the first world war it increas-
ed its membership rapidly until, in
1931, there were 21, 000 members in
1, 215 groups. Following the second
world war new impetus was given to
the movement and at the end of 1948
it reached the record number of 3, 478
groups with 45, 337 members.
Another active movement is wiles
Cercles de Jeunes Naturalistes"which
now comprises over 20, 000 members in
1, 148 groups. This movement for
young naturalists formed in 1931, has
; tread beyond the Province of Quebec
In addition to groups in Canadian pro-
vinces there are others in the United
States, France, the West Tnãies and
India.
Similar aims are pursued by another
group of Canadian clubs,"Clubs Audu-
bon pour les Jeunes", organized, on
the same basis as the American
Audubon Junior Clubs, under the
patronage of the Audubon Society of
Canada. At present, there are 1, 250
clubs in Canada with a total mem-
bership of 25, 000 boys and girls.
To make young people realize the
importance of forests as a source of
national wealth and the urgent need
to protect them, especially against fire,
is the main purpose of the"Clubs de
Jeunes Gardes-Forestiers" (Junior
Forest Wardens), a movement which
covers all parts of British Columbia.
It is estimated that over 20, 000 young
people have been trained by the clubs
and the present number of trainees is
5, 000.
The effectiveness of the work done
by the clubs'is shown by the fact that
some years, the Junior Forest Wardens
have discovered or helped to fight over
200 forest fires in British Columbia.
In certain districts there has been a
marked decrease in the number of
fires since the clubs have been oper-
ating regularly.
Similar work to that done by the
junior wardens in British Columbia is
carried out in Quebec by the 4-H
clubs founded in 1942 by the"Asso-
ciation Forestiere Quebecoise".
science-the redistribution of in-
dustry, released by electric power
from its former compulsory proxi-
mity to coal mine or wharf ; the
levelling up of amenities between
town and country ; the changes in
world communications resulting
from telegraph, telephone and
radio (and the international poli-
tical consequences of this) ; and
many others. Some of the social
effects create serious new problems
- the threat of atomic war, tech-
nological unemployment, or the
dislocation of traditional family
life that has been produced by the
car, the cinema, and the like.
U The Idea Of Progress"
THE intellectual social effects ofscience are less obvious but no
less real. The"idea of pro-
gress"-the idea that the world
can be progressively improved if
men act appropriately-is taken
for granted today. Before the 17th
century, it was virtually unknown.
And Bury (1920) has shown that
the origin and growth of this idea
is largely attributable to the
impact of scientific discovery on
men's thoughts and the attitude of
mind adopted by scientists. In
many other ways the spread of the
spirit of science can change-
usually for the better-man's
outlook on life.
It may well be that ultimately
the intellectual impact of science
will be far more important to
humanity than its contribution to
material welfare. But"man must
eat before he can think", and in
the present state of the world it is
not practical politics to envisage
the spreading of the scientific
attitude to mankind as a whole. A
necessary prelude is to feed the
starving millions, and even in the
advanced countries to provide
those greatly improved conditions
of life and leisure which, as history
shows, are the necessary basis for
scientific thinking.
It is therefore natural-that
discussion about the social impact
and social function of science
concentrates mostly on the ma-
terial and technological aspects.
This need not damage the intellec-
tual progress of science, since even
from the most material point of
view fundamental research pays
the largest dividends.
Six Basic Questions
IN a conscious approach to theproblems raised by the social
impact of science, the basic
types of questions to be answered
are :
(1)-What are the more important
problems of material welfare
today ?
(2)-What lines of research are
most likely to contribute to their
solution ?
(3)-A discovery or invention
seldom has only the effects that
were intended. Hence the more
general question that must be
answered before taking decisions
based on (2) : What are the
probable total social effects of a
given scientific discovery or of a
proposed line of investigation ?
(4)-What changes in the organi-
zation of scientific effort are
required in order that the inves-
tigations suggested by (2) and
(3) may be efficiently pursued
and the results quickly applied ?
(5)-As a basis for answering (4),
what is the present organization
and how efficient is it ? And
more generally, what factors,
social or individual, ultimately
decide the course of scientific
advance ?
(6)-What changes in general
social organization are made
advisable by the advance of
science ?
The bibliography in Impact
gives a survey of the main attempts
to answer these questions in recent
times. It makes no attempt at
completeness. A number of his-
torical works are included because
it is clear that the answering of
questions (3) and (5), and to a
lesser extent the others, can be
greatly helped by historical studies.
FOOD AND PEOPLE
PAMPHLETS IN U. S.
In the last issue of the Courier,
the price of"Food, Soil and
People", by Charles E. Kellogg, was
incorrectly given as 50 cents.
The price of this pamphlet, one
of the six in the American series of
Food and People pamphlets pu-
blished by the Manlwtten Pu-
blishing Company, New York, is
60 cents.
ASSM) AI ! t) M t) f SC ! E)) CEOCIAT ON OF I N
WRITERS
FORMED IN FRANCE
THE formation in Paris of the"'association des Ecrivains
Scientifiques"makes France
the fifth country where science
'writers'associations now exist,
the others being the United States,
Great Britain, Denmark and Aus-
tria.
Set up with the assistance of
the Division for the Teaching and
Popularization of Science in
Unesco's Natural Sciences Depart-
ment, the new body has as its
"President d'Honneur", Prince
Louis de Broglie, Secrétaire Per-
pétuel de 1'Academie Franaise.
Its chairman is M. François Le
Lionnais and its Secretary, M.
André Fortin.
At the foundation meeting of
the Association letters of good
wishes were received from the
National Association of Science
Writers (U. S. A.) and from the
Association of British Science
Writers.
]]>
</page>
<page number="10">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 10
THE MOUNTAIN IS GREEN"
New French film
recounts life of
Victor Schoelcher
- fighter for
Human Rights
ON 20 May 1949 Paris witnesseda solemn procession which
brought the ashes of Victor
Schoelcher and Félix Eboué to the
Pantheon, the mausoleum reserved
for France's greatest servants.
Most Frenchmen remembered
Governor-General Eboué as the
man who was able to combine
championship of the people of
Africa with love and active loyalty
to France, but it is likely that the
name of Victor Schoelcher, libera-
tor of the slaves in the Antilles,
conveyed little to most of the
crowd that watched the cere-
mony.
Now, a little more than a century
after his greatest accomplishment,
worthy tribute is paid to
Schoelcher, one of the"'forgotten
men"in the struggle for human
rights, in a new French film,"'La
Montagne est Verte".
Slavery was finally abolished in
all French colonies in 1848. While
due honour must be paid to the fine
example of the Abbé Grégoire and to
resolute action of the Convention in
1794-the principal credit for
liberation must go to Victor Schoel-
cher.
Tittle : La Montagne est Verte.
Scenario and Direction : Jean Lehe-
rissey.
Production : J. ! (. Raymond-MiDet,
Paris.
Cast : Michel Vitoid, Jacques Hentey,
André Reybaz and the Folklore
Society of Martinique.
Length : 1, 000 metres36 mm.
Mission For Mankind
S CHOELCHER first visited Americaand the Antilles in 1829 as the
representative of an Alsatian
factory, and the condition of the
slaves in Martinique and Guadeloupe
filled him with horror. He deter-
mined to devote his life to their
emancipation, and launched a big
campaign to stir up French public
opinion. He had attended sales of
slaves by auction ; he had witnessed
floggings on the plantations ; he had
taken part in a man-hunt to recover
an escaped slave ; he had seen a
revolt of desperate slaves.
THE EMANCIPATOR AND THE SLAVE. Visiting the West Indian islands of Martinique and Guadaloupe in 1829. Victor Schoelcher was
horrified by the working and living conditions of the slaves there. Twenty years later slavery was finally abolished in all French colonies
largely as the result of his effort. In the film,"The Mountain is Green", the role of Schælcher is played by Michel Vitold (above, tell)
and the slaves he fought to free are portrayed by a Martinique folk-lore group.
The sight 01 slaves being examined and sold like cattle at public
Cluctions in the French West Indies and the harsh treatment
they underwent in the plantations stirred Victor Schoelcher to
work for their emancipation.
When it was learned in Martinique that the decree abolishing
slavery had been signed in. Paris, the beating 01 drums and
blowing 01 conch shells carried the news across the island.
Each year the people 01 the French West Indies honour the memory 01
Victor Schoelcher. Gathered around his statue they still sing the
simple, heat-Melt words 01"The Mountain is Green".
He saw slavery as an accursed
thing and understood that the only
remedy was outright abolition of a
shameful and degrading institution
which degraded masters as it did the
slaves.
Despite the mockery of a satirical
press, Schoelcher pursued his mission
without faltering and won to his
cause such men as Lamartine, Ledru-
Rollin, Edgar Quinet and Victor
Hugo. A month after the pro-
clamation of the Second Republic on
25. February 1848, Schoelcher, a
member of the provisional govern-
ment, was appointed chairman of a
commission to draft the decree of
emancipation. However, he still had
to fight temporizers and the adminis-
trative delays of even a libertarian
government.
Meanwhile the slaves in the
colonies were growing restive and in
May 1848 there was a revolt in Mar-
tinique of such dimensions that the
Governor proclaimed the abolition of
slavery at the request of the planters
themselves. In so doing, he did no
more than anticipate his orders, for
the decree of emancipation had
meanwhile, at long last, achieved
signature in France and very soon,
through Schoelcher's tenacity, there
were no more slaves on French soil.
Edward Dmytl'yk for Give us this
Day. (Great Britain).
DENMARK
* Cart Th. Dreye1"the Danish pro-
ducer'tvell-lmown {Ol'his mOl : Ìng
farm Joan of Arc and, more recentl,
Day of'Vrath, is planning to pl'oduce
a film on"The Life of Christ., in
Israel with the assistance o {Israe/'Ï
actors. The project'trill take about
two years, and'trill porttay Jesus'in
the social and political atmosphere of
his. ç times. To help recreate this
atmosphere, the Roman characters yin
the film'will speak in Latin, the
ordinary people of Ismet in Ilebrew
and the cultured classes in Gree/ ;.
FRANCE
* The French film critic Lo DUCil re-
cently produced a documentary film
on the work of the Fl'ench painter
Rousseau. Another joumalist and
CZECHOSLOVAKIA
* At the Film f'esNl'al'wid III,, (I/'-
looy-l'ary (Catlsbad), the Gmnd/'/'i. r
leas atl.'al'del. l to the Russian {ilm The
Fall of Bt'rlin. The Russians also
/'eceil'ed the Work Prize {o/'The
Cossacks of Kouban. About 40 films
o {di {fel'ent MI/its received mentions,
IImong them :"'orld YOUtll (lIungary
, lIId China), The Man'We like the Best
FI'ance). Things have changed in the
South (/talk), Horses (Germany). The
IJ1'Îze {or best photography'Went to
. lfe. rico {or The Countl''lWoman.
.'Ì1Jecial mention 1vas awarded to
film critic, Jean Vidal has used 19th
centuM) engravings in his film on
Balzac.
MEXICO
* During 1949 more than 100 full-
Iengtla falms were produced in Dleavico.
Production of shorter films mounted"
to about 75, not including the hundred
or so documentaries made up from
o ! < : ! MCK ; sree ! s.lel new r ls.
INTERNATIONAL
* The first film club of its kind has
been established in Paris, to provide
fOl-film exchanges which will help
to create understanding and collabo-
ration between peoples, and to support
freedom of artistic expression in all
its {orms. Similar {ilm clubs are
also being {ormed in Belgium, Eng-
lane ! and Italy. Among the commit-
tee members o the club in Paris are
Alexandre Arnoux, Marcel Carné,
ReM Clair and Jean Cocteau.
Song Of Gratitude
A CENTURY has passed since thenand human memories are short.
Yet the coloured folk of the
Antilles do not forget their liberator.
Today, as on the day when their
emancipation was proclaimed, their
gratitude finds expression in a folk
song moving in its simplicity,"La
Montagne est Verte".
The name of the song was chosen
by Jean Lehérissey as the title of his
film of the life of Victor Schoelcher.
It is an historical documentary made
in the Antilles with the assistance of
the Folklore Society of Martinique,
with the historical rôles played by
French actors. The part of Schoel-
cher is taken by Michel Vitold. The
restraint and historical accuracy of
the scenario and the pictorial quality
of the photography deserve the
highest praise. Many scenes, such as
the announcement of the great news,
with the initial doubt exploding into
joy, or the birth of the first freeborn
Negro child, cannot fail to stir the
spectator, and make this film a great
and moving work of art.
CREDITS
]]>
</page>
<page number="11">
<![CDATA[
Page II-UNESCO COURIER
THE SAUCEPAN
RADIO SHOWS
« A GOOD CHANCE
OF NEW LIFE"
by Gyril ERA Y
- w USAKA is a one-street Central-African town of
one-story buildings. One almost looks to see
the horsemen of a Western film gallop in
and hitch their horses to the rails outside the
store.
But overshadowing the one dusty street are the
towering radio masts that are the monument to an idea
- an idea that is already beginning to change the face
of the vast tropical territory of Northern Rhodesia and
to change the lives not only of its two million people
but of peoples in underdeveloped territories throughout
the world.
Northern Rhodesia is impoverished by soil erosion,
the present and future of its illiterate people threatened
and overshadowed by superstition, bad farming,
ignorance of the simplest principles of personal and
domestic hygiene.
How best to teach them the need for hard work and
for education, for water-conservation and better
hygiene, for the protection and care of pasture and
forests ?
Pamphlets and posters are useful-but not so useful
if only one African in every ten or so can read. More
and more African children are learning to read and
write, it is true, but how many years before a
completely literate generation has grown up ? And
what of the soil in the meantime ?
Chief Siamaundu of the Tonga tribe buys a"saucepan special"radio in a Rhodesian store.
Letters received by the Lusaka Broadcasting Station show that the average number of liste-
ners to each set is about ten. When it was suggested that"saucepan"owners should keep a
box for visitors to drop a penny in as a fund for battery renewal, the Africans replied :"This
is not according to our custom : it would shame us."
A semi-amateur radio
station had been set up at
Lusaka in 1941 to keep
Europeans and Africans
informed about the progress
of the war and to stimulate
their war effort. It was
found that the African,
unused to reading, was both
a readier talker and a better
listener than the European
- at home both at the
microphone ant at the
receiver. It was decided
that broadcasting to Africans
must not only survive the
wartime need but develop to
meet the post-war needs.
Hygiene, Husbandry
And Law
WHEN I toured Africaearly this year as one
of Unesco's field sur-
veyors to examine the needs
and the progress of the
various methods of mass
communication, I found the
Lusaka radio station broad-
casting in simple English
and in five African ver-
naculars, five hours a day,
to the native populations of
Northern Rhodesia, South-
ern Rhodesia and Nyasaland.
Lusaka was putting out
pr'51'ammes of European
and African music, news,
plays and talks and dra-
matized feature programmes
on hygiene, husbandry and
the rule of law. The station
had a potential listening
public of five million people,
perhaps eighty or ninety per
cent of them illiterate,
spread over an area as big
as Western Europe, or as
the states of Arkansas,
Louisiana, Oklahoma, and
Texas put together.
But the best broadcasting
in the world is of no use to
a population that cannot
afford the means to listen.
An answer to this need
is the"sauce {Jan special..
- a radio receIver that will
stand up to a tropical
climate and to clumsy hand-
ling, that can be used miles
from electric current, repair
shops, and battery chargers,
and be sold at a price within
reach of a considerable
number of Africans.
In the Unesco survey of
broadcasting in Africa is a
technical description of a
. ,
fJllutppJUlJlfi
in SRpl : RnWJlA...
"it. was just a year ago to-day... It was ten
years ago... This is our Golden Jubilee... This is
the centenary... Just about a thousand years
age..."
The birthdays of a child, events in the lives
of individual men and women, commemoration
of the births and deaths of men and women
who have lit torches along the road of history,
red-letter days marking the advance of mankind
- these are dates traditionally noted in the arbi-
trary system of reckoning which we call the
calendar.
Not forgetting he unknown and unsung per-
sons and events, perhaps of equal greatness
making no claim at completeness, here are some
note-worthy dates in September, ninth month
of the Gregorian calendar.
JANE ADDAMS
She was born on 6 September I860. In 1889 she
opened a social settlement in a poor district of Chicago,
which"respectable people"soon came to regard as
a hot-bed of revolution. Worse was to come when
Miss Addams obtained passage of a law regulating
the employment of women and children in factories.
She attempted, in the middle of the first world war,
to unite all the women of the world in the interests of
peace, and continued to preach peace until her death.
"People do not make war for honour or understanding 
she used to say,"but for destruction. We shall not
put an end to war by outlawing it, but only by foster-
ing an intelligent development of life's values."
ANDRÉ LENOTRE
One of the most pleasing features of the court of
Louis XIV, the"Sun King", was the fact that a peasant
like Lenotre, with his broad shoulders and mud-stained
coat, making his way with scant ceremony 1hrough
the crowd of courtiers, enjoyed such eminence. We
are constantly reminded of the age of Louis XIV by the
work this peasant did-the parks, terraces and orna-
mental water which we have been content, for three
centuries, to preserve unchanged. His work still gives
pleasure at Vaux-le-Vicomte, Versailles, Chantilly,
Saint Cloud and Saint Germain, and since he also
worked for King Charles 01 England, at Greenwich and
in St. James's Park. When he died, on 15 September
1700, he had brought tq life again in Europe some of
rthe forgotten splendours of Babylon, Egypt and China.
short-wave dry-battery set
which begins :.. The cabinet of the
receiver is in effect a large
aluminium saucepan (with-
out handle) of nine inches
diameter, with a back-plate
screwed and sealed, and a
gauze-covered opening at
the front of four inches
diameter". And it is in-
teresting to observe that
included in the notes on
such up-to-date and matter-
of-fact subjects as valves
and voltages is the sentence,
"It is painted MMC, since
resea1'lch in the various
colonies in Africa revealed
the fact tloot orte tribe or
another had some kind of
superstition about almost
every other colour".
H... Whole World
In My House"
saucepan special is
sold for five pounds
sterling, with a dry
battery for another twenty-
five shillings. The first two
thousand sets were
sold in a few weeks
and ten or more per-
sons glisten in to each
set. There are a !-
ready something
like twentv thousand
LAFCADIO HEARN
Lafcadio Hearn was the son of an Irishman and a
Greek woman, and later became a Japanese citizen.
As a correspondent of a New Orleans newspaper, he
spent two years in the West Indies, then proceeded
to Japan, where he found his natural home. He
became professor of English at Tokyo University,
married a Japanese wife, became a Buddhist and was
naturalized under the name of Yakumo Koizumi.. His
Irish name was still, however, to be seen on the
covers of the books he published between 1894 and the
date of his death on September 26, 1904. He had
become the best interpreter of Japanese culture to the
Western world. There was no one who had a more
sympathetic understanding of that culture, no one who
could express its essence with greater skill.
listeners of whom more
than three hundred have
already written to Lusaka
to express their delight-
a high proportion, when it
is remembered how few of
the listeners are literate.
A Chief from the most
primitive part of the ter-
ritory wrote a letter expres-
sing his joy that his people
were learning from the radio
"care of children, education
of girls, sanitation, house-
wifery, improved methods
of agriculture and many
other things", adding that
"particularly do the people
in this District desire to
hear more about care of
dams and how water can be
usefully reserved".
"1 feel proud", wrote
Mwitwa Amisi,.. when I
switch on my set and have
the whole world in my
house".
But it was perhaps John
Somati who best summed up
what the cheap radio set
can do for a simple and
primitive people when he
sat down in his wattle-and-
daub hut, under the palm-
trees, and laboriously wrote
down,"This wireless set
doing more than cost, thel'C-
fore I seen we African we
have a good chance or new
life".
SIX HUNDRED MJLLION
OF WORLD S CtHEDREN
LACK BAStC NEEDS
ONE of the features of the"Help for DistressedChildren Week"held in Cannes recently was an
exhibition organized by Unesco. In a message for the
opening of this exhibition, M. Jaime Torres Bodet,
Director-General of Unesco, said, in part :
"Charity derives from two ideas : love of that which,
should be dear to us, and love of that which
in the supreme scale of values, is of greatest price.
And I would ask you : is there anything more precious,
anything that we should hold more dear than children ?
"Ladies and gentlemen, the suffering of a child, with
his obscure sense of being ill-fitted for life, is an indict-
ment of us which we adults should find unbearably
painful. It is for the conscience of humanity to cry out
against the forfeiture of the child's indefeasible right
to happiness...
"Though, in our time, invaluable discoveries have
been made about the personality of children... though
new sciences have been developed under the names of
educational therapy and social pediatrics, children have,
in the same period, been the victims of crimes far worse
against humanity than almost any committed. The
number of children in the world who, as the aftermath
of the last war and the resulting upheavals lack the
basic necessaries of life, has been estimated at
600, 000, 000. Two hundred and thirty million of these
children are going hungry. In Europe alone there are
13, 000, 000 orphans, deprived of all the care they should
naturally enjoy...
"Concurrently with its own particular work of educa-
tion, our Organization, in close agreement with UNICEF
and the other Specialized Agencies of the United Nations,
has endeavoured to meet the other needs of children.
The resources of goodwill in every quarter must be
mobilized. Each one of us, in his own conscience,
must answer the child's despairing cry : Why have you
neglected me ?
During the last days of his life,
which ended on 21 September
1860, this Berlin philosopher was
still describing the miseries of
man's condition. With the Hindu
sages, he had said that the
desire for life was the great evil.
The wise man must free himself
by a continual effort of the intel-
iect to escape from the coils of
life and to attain"nirvana"I a
state of spiritual repose, in which
the philosopher will feel no more
than a mild pity for his fellows.
THE COMMONWEALTH OF AUSTRALIA IS
FIFTY YEARS OLD
It took fourteen years of conferences, planning, dis-
putes and referenda to bring about the political union
of the six self-governing states of this sparsely
populated continent. After repeated experiments, a
federal government modelled mainly on American and
British lines, with innovations adapted to the new
young Commonwealth was chosen. The British Par-
liament approved the coast ;, lotion of the new. Common-
wealth, with its administrative and commercial indepen-
dence, and, on 17 September, 1900, Queen Victoria
issued a proclamation announcing that, from 1 January,
the peoples of the six states, New South Wales, Victoria,
Queensland, South Australia, West Australia and Tas-
mania, were to be united in a single community under
the name of the Commonwealth of Australia.
ARTHUR SCHOPENHAUER
]]>
</page>
<page number="12">
<![CDATA[
UNESCO COURIER-Page 12
THE SIGN
THE most coveted possession inthe Brazilian town of Cachoei-
ro do Itapemirim is a simple
cardboard sign tacked on a front
door. It reads,"Nesta casa nao ha
analfabetos" ("In this house there
are no illiterates"). What it means
is that every man, woman and child
in that house has learned to read and
write.
That cardboard sign is just one of
the weapons which Dona Zilma
Coelho Pinto uses in an energetic
campaign to educate the people of
Cachoeiro. Her ambition is to pin it
on to every front door in the town
and ultimately to stimulate similar
action in every town in Brazil.
Her's is not the biggest town in the
State of Espirito Santo, but already
Dona Zilma's efforts have made it
one of the best known. While a
literacy campaign is being conducted
all over the country, Cachoeiro
presents perhaps the most spec-
tacular example of achievement-
and of individual accomplishment.
For it has been due chiefly to this
one woman's enterprise that 32 lite-
racy classes are now running for
grown-ups and for. children. It is
she who finances them by collecting
contributions and she who finds and
pays the teachers.
Dona Zilma has been called many
things :"A'Louco de Itapemirim"
("The Mad Woman of Itapemirim"),
and the town's No. 1 Beggar. The
harsh names come from some of
those whom she approaches for
financial help, but she finds adequate
compensation in the happiness and
gratitude of the hundreds of students
of all ages whom she has helped to
find the chance for a new life.
"Beggar"On Horseback
ON horseback and on foot, shemakes the round of homes and
offices, collecting 5 cruzeiros
here, 10 there, to finance her classes.
In 1949 she managed 32 full subs-
ON THE
FRONT
DOOR
criptions. That meant 32 classes,
each bearing the name of the donor
whose contribution paid the teacher's
modest fees. As for premises, rooms
are found in factories and schools for
night classes, and even in private
homes.
A Little"Pep"Talk
BUT Dona Zilma is not contentmerely to teach the towns-
people how to read and write.
She strives also to better their con-
ditions, for she knows only too well
that learning is no match for hunger
and sickness. That is why, when a
student is repeatedly absent from
class, a teacher is sent to visit his
home. If she finds that the cause is
simply laziness or lack of interest,
she administers advice and a little
"pep"talk. If it is sickness, she
advises the Organization's Health
Centre.
Hygiene is taught by the State
Health Department. Local doctors
and laboratories co-operate by pro-
viding each student *u) ith a. free
yearly X-Ray f ! xamination, vaccina-
tion and free medicine, while dentists
attend to their teeth.
Material aid to the poor depends
on the amount Dona Zilma is able to
collect-not only in cash, but in
garments food, and a variety of
immediately useful things. A tooth-
brush, a tin of condensed milk, a
broom to keep the floor clean, an
odd scrap of cloth, all are welcome.
And for those who learn to read and
write, there are prizes : old maga-
zines for the men and dressmaking
lessons for the women.
A new life is taking shape for the
people of Cachoeiro. To the grown-
ups who have known what it is to be
ignorant and ill-cared for, it is more
exciting than it is for their children,
who sit on the same school benches
and take their opportunities for
learning much for granted. But all
over the vast country of Brazil the
excitement is spreading. The hunger
for knowledge, aroused by the natio-
nal literacy campaign, is being fed.
This campaign, launched in 1947,
has already done a great deal towards
On horseback Dona Zilma Coelho Pinto (above) makes the rounds of homes and offices in
the Brazilian town of Cachoeiro do Itapemirim to raise money for the literacy classes he has
organized. Already. 32 classes for adults and children are running thanks to her energetic
campaign to educate the people of Cachoeiro.
decreasing the illiteracy rate in
Brazil which, according to the 1940
census, reached over 55 per cent.
But actually it is not so much
concerned with the figures of those
who read and write as with the state
of fundamental education as a whole
in Brazil, and with the insufficient
school attendance. Eighteen months
is the average school life of Brazilian
children.
Professor M. B. Lourenco Filho,
Director-General of the National
Education Department and Director
of the literacy campaign, made it
clear at the beginning that the
government was embarking, not
merely on a literacy drive, but on a
campaign for adult education. The
object to be kept in view was to
raise the living standards and cul-
tural levels of a large section of the
population by disseminating know-
ledge and popularizing techniques
which would help them make the
most of their environment and their
capacities. Reading and writing
were just a means to that end.
"Freedom"For A Million
THREE years of the literacycampaign have cost'the Bra-
zilian Government about 100
million cruzeiros, or the equivalentof  5, 000, 000. In that time, over a
million people have been taught to
read and write, 2, 000, 000 adolescents
and adults have enrolled for night
classes and there has been a marked
improvement in normal schools
attendance. Education, once consider-
ed in Brazil to be the prerogative
'of the privileged classes, has become
accessible to all. And what is more,
teaching is not confined to profes-
sionals : Individual volunteers are
constantly being sought to teach one
or more illiterates in their own
homes. They are supplied with the
necessary material by the national
and regional services (more than
200, 000 copies have already been
sent out in this way) and during the
three years of the campaign, more
than half a million letters and
circulars have been posted to induce
people to volunteer.
An important milestone in Brazil's
campaign against illiteracy was the
seminar organized at Quitandinha
near Rio de Janeiro in August 1949
by Unesco. Brazilian educators
were brought into contact with
colleagues from the other South
American countries, from England,
France and Egypt. They discussed
old methods and learned new ones,
and thanks to this experience, the
campaign has made even greater
strides in conquering ignorance and
the misery which accompanies it
like an evil twin.
Dona Zilma (shown above with two pupils in one of her
literacy classes) not only finds and pays the teachers, but
also tries to better the conditions 01 the townspeople, lor
learning is no maich for hunger and sickness.
"A new life is taking shape for the people of Cachoeiro.
I'o the grown-ups it is more exciting than for their children.
who sit on the same school benches and take their oppor-
tunities ior learning much more for granted."
For those who learn to read and write in the classes at
Cachoeiro there are prizes. The men receive maqazines
(being selected by teachers, above) and the women are
given dressmaking lessons.
]]>
</page>
</document>
